<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="014256eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
v
.«
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
<-
A. Tessore
TREASURES
OF WORLD ART o
Neolithic lady
(Dobruja, Rumania)
Each month on this page the Unesco Courier will publish an outstanding,
though little known work of art from a different country. Here we present a
6,000 year old figurine of a woman which despite its great age is extraordinarily
modern in appearance. The work of a Neolithic artist, it was found in 1956 in
a cemetary of 350 graves uncovered at Cernavoda in the Dobruja region of
eastern Rumania. Only 11.4 cm (4i In.) high, it was modelled in brown clay
and covered with a brownish-black substance. Extremely rich finds have
been made on Neolithic sites in the Balkans and in Anatolia in the course of
excavations carried out by Rumanian archaeologists in the past ten years.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier
JANUARY 1966 - 19TH YEAR
Page
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
Published monthly by UNESCO,
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7#.
Annual subscription rates: 15'-stg.; $3.00
(Canada) : 10 French Francs or equivalent;
2 years: 27 -stg,; 18 F. Single copies 1/6-stg.;
30 cents; 1 F.
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, excepr
in July and August when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year) in English. French, Spanish, Russian, German, Arabic,
Japanese and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed
by H.M. Stationery Office. P 0. Box 569, London, S E I
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from
the UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returned unless accompanied by an international reply
coupon covering postage Signed articles express the
opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
tne opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of the
UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in The Read¬
ers' Guide to Periodical Literature published by
H. W. Wilson Co.. New York.
8
11
16
22
27
32
33
34
MESSAGES TO THE STARS
Communicating with alien intelligent beings
By D.M.A. Mercer
GALAXIES CAUGHT IN A STEEL MESH
NEW PATTERNS OF TRANSPORT
FOR AFRICA
By W. H. Owens
DANTE : THE PRIMACY OF POETRY
By llya Ehrenburg
THE ROOTS OF PEACE
A pioneer effort in peace research
By Bert V.A. Röling
BEAUTY AND THE BEAST
The story of man through his art
By Pauline Bentley
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
THE INNER NATURE OF SCIENCE
By Warren Weaver
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7», France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant to the Editor-in-Chief
Lucio Attinelli
Managing Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton (Paris)
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse (Paris)
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey (Paris)
Russian Edition : Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Italian Edition : Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Illustrations : Phyllis Feldkamp
Research : Olga Rodel
Layout & Design : Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
H.W. Silvester, Lioux, France
Cover photo
In recent years a new expression
"peace research" has enter¬
ed the language. Peace re¬
search is a pioneer effort being
made in different countries to
analyse, scientifically, the vast
complex of factors which influen¬
ce the stability of world order
and the relationships between
nations. It deals with all types
of war: intentional, uninten¬
tional (war as a traffic accident)
and civil wars. (See page 22)
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
MESSAGES
TO THE STARS
by D. M. A. Mercer
FACE IN SPACE
A profile of the human face
seems to float among
the myriads of stars
in this enlarged photo
of the Milky Way.
The brightly luminous nebula
forming the outline is
visible in the constellation
of Cygnus (the Swan),
distant from the earth
by 1,000 light years.
© Observatoire de Paris
I F we woke up one morning to find, hovering
over our city, a space-ship from a distant galaxy,
we would no doubt view it with very mixed feelings. But
after the initial surprise had subsided, the very practical
question would arise how could we get in touch with its
crew? If we did not, at best the ship might simply consider
that there was nothing of interest in the vicinity and go
away and we would have lost an almost unique opportunity
of immense potentiality. But at worst, the ship might have
the means of destroying our whole planet. For a variety
of reasons, we would find it imperative to communicate
with the crew (or with the ship if, as may well be the case,
it is an unmanned robot).
But how should we start to communicate? Obviously there
is no point in flashing English messages in the Morse code.
What means should we use? Clearly this needs a good
deal of thinking through, and it is this subject which I want
to deal with the basis of communication with alien
intelligent beings (I use the word "alien" in the science-
fiction sense; the inhabitant of another part of the physical
universe who may have no necessary common physical
traits with us).
All we know about these people is that they are intelligent
they must be so, or they could never have built a space¬
ship. Any communication must be on the basis of our
. common intelligence. This puts the problem in the best
way what is the basis, the lowest common multiple, if
you like, of intelligence: something which is common no
matter how much its physical vehicle changes. If we can
understand this, we can understand how to communicate:
in fact the two problems are bound up with each other.
To start with our case of the space-ship which has
appeared in our vicinity, we assume that its builders are
(1) Intelligent; (2) At least as far advanced scientifically
as we are, and probably much more so; (3) Interested in
finding other intelligences. (This is probably a fair assump¬
tion, as they have apparently sent an exploring spaceship
although it is not impossible that races who are completely
withdrawn and introverted exist.) (4) Ready to communicate
4
D.M.A. MERCER, of the Physics Department of the University of
Southampton (United Kingdom) is a specialist in acoustics.
and to receive signals, and also to try to interpret them.
This last point is important, and it needs some discussing.
The probe will obviously not expect communication in
its own language. In fact, we must both seek a common
language. This is rather like the problem set up in certain
branches of game theory. You are to meet someone in
London on a particular day, but neither of you has any
knowledge of the time or place; you must choose not
what seems obvious to you, but what you think he thinks
you will choose in the situation in which you both are, etc.
(You might in this case choose Piccadilly Circus at 12 noon,
for instance.)
To follow this thought up, we should ask what signals
would show that we are intelligent, and would be so
understood by the probe. Any signals we send must look
artificial space is full of light and radio waves, and our
signals must clearly look as if they have not arisen from
a natural source.
I don't want to spend time discussing the mechanics of
signalling, except to say that we are limited, over long
distances, virtually to two means: short-wave radio, and
"laser" light beams. For most purposes it appears that
radio is preferable. I might also remind you that such waves
travel at the speed of light; so to communicate with a
planet 10 light-years away, the round-trip signal would
take 20 yearsl Clearly there is little scope for rapidly
changing one's mind while conversing.
In many cases, we are limited to sending a series of
identical signals in time i.e. a train of pulses of elec¬
tromagnetic energy, either radio beams or light beams.
One such series which has been suggested is a series
of prime numbers (numbers which have no factors, but
are divisible only by themselves and 1). If we send pulses
in groups of 1, 2, 3, 5, 7, 11, 13, 17... etc., they will
clearly come from intelligent beings. No radio storms
in the galaxy, or any other natural process, will produce
prime numbers.
o. .oo. .ooo. .ooooo. .ooooooo. . ooooooooooo. .ooooooooooooo. .
Fig. 1
They might be indicated as in Fig. 1, in which we choose
a fixed spacing in time for the pulses, indicated by the
space between symbols. A dot means the absence of a
pulse, and a circle means a pulse.
CONT'D ON PAGE 6
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
w
v
'
. *"
/V **
.
. -*
*. «i"H'
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
MESSAGES TO THE STARS (Cont'd)
How to devise an interplanetary signal
We might also try a series of squares, 1, 4, 9, 16..., or
the digits of jt, the ratio of the circumference of a circle
O..O00O..OOOOOOO0O..OOOOO0OOOOOO0OOO..OO0OOO00OO0OOO0OOO0OO00OO..
0OO..O..O0OO..O« .OOOOO..OOQOOOOOO. .OO..OOOOOO. .ooooo.ooo. .oooooo. .
.Fig. 2
to its diameter, 3.141.592... (Fig. 2). This, being a ratio,
is independent of the units of measurement. It does however
raise the sort of point which we will be considering again
can we assume that the circle is such a fundamental idea
that any intelligent being, however alien, will know it?
I think we can make this assumption; any being with any
knowledge of working materials, such as constructing
radio transmitters, must be familiar with the circle.
At this stage it might be pointed out that we could
make pictures. It has been suggested in the past that we
should build an enormous chain of beacons over a large
land-area, showing, for instance, Pythagoras' theorem
Fig. 3
(Fig. 3). If a space-ship were hovering overhead, this
would certainly be possible; although we might well want
to indicate that we had progressed further than the ancient
Greeks, and some more sophisticated diagram, of the sort
to be discussed later, might be more appropriate.
Such beacons however would be visible only to some¬
thing close at hand an alien space-ship orbiting the
earth, as I mentioned earlier. What if we tried to send
signals to a distant planet? Is there any way in which
we can send pictures to them?
»
Before discussing this, perhaps we should consider
two further fundamental points. One is that we assume
other alien races have eyes, or at any rate some corres¬
ponding sense organs. The other is that they can understand
pictures, which are two-dimensional representations of
three-dimensional objects.
Here again, we feel that a sense of vision must be
essential to anyone with an advanced technology. Secondly,
we feel that such an advanced technology must deal in
pictures and diagrams. We may be wrong over this; there
may be races dependent entirely on tactile senses dealing
directly with three-dimensional objects. All we can say
is that it seems unlikely: this is the sort of thinking we
must however attend to if we are to establish a basis for
a universal intelligence.
While on this point, we ought to consider a little further
the modes which intelligence can take. There may be
some intelligent races which are completely withdrawn
and introspective, wishing to have no contact with anyone
outside. There may be others who are uninterested: they
may have solved all their political and economic problems,
and spend their time watching television.
There are two other cases which may raise problems;
one is the case of beings whose processes are very slow
compared to ours. Although they may be intelligent, it
would be virtually impossible to communicate with them.
The other is the case of a civilization well versed in the
abstract virtues of goodness, truth and beauty, but without
any technology.
These would be difficult to communicate with as a
superior alien community would have found the classical
Greeks but I do not think there is an absolute bar.
I don't consider that any entirely abstract philosophy can
exist in isolation from the real world: even on this earth,
our most idealist philosophers slip in ideas of material
things counting, for example which they could not do
if in fact mind were the only thing which existed. (And
it is worth noting that the ancient civilizations have led,
in time, to our technological one.)
Returning to the problem of sending pictures, in fact it
is not too difficult to do so by a series of pulses. Suppose
we send a series as in Fig. 4. By itself it is not very
ooo	 .o.	boo. ....
	.o	...o....	ooo	.o
o	ooo o	
	o	ooo o	
	o	ooo o
..o	ooo o	W	o...
ooo .o. .o	ooo. .....
	o	o	ooo
o Fig. 4
meaningful. If however we cut off each series beginning
with three circles, and put them all one above the other,
we have a diagram of a circle, Fig. 5. This of course is
OOO o
OOO O o
OOO o o
ooo o o
ooo o o
ooo o o
ooo o o
ooo o o
ooo Fig. 5
a form of scanning in exactly the same way as that carried
out in a television receiver.
Alien races may not have the same sort of television
of course their sets may scan in a spiral but we would
think that they would be intelligent enough to try various
ways of superimposing traces until they hit on a "meaning¬
ful" one. (Here again I am assuming that "meaningful"
has the same connotation to any intelligent being i.e.
that the ideas of "random" and "ordered" are universal.)
o.o	oo	oooo . . . o . . . . o . . . o . . o	o ... o
....0......0.. .OOO. ..«.0....0. «OOOOO. .O. . .OOO. .00. »o. .
.o.... o	ooo.	o...o....o... o	...o-.,o... o	
..oooo	oo.o Fig. 6
There is in fact another way in which we can send
pictures in a rectangular array. Suppose we send a series
such as Fig. 6, starting and ending with one pulse, and
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
A.B.C.D.E.F.G.H.I.J.K.LM.IM.P.Q.R.S.T.U.V.W.Y.Z.
AA, B ; AAA, C ; AAAA, D ; AAAAA, E ; AAAAAA, F ; AAAAAAA, G ;
AAAAAAAA,H; AAAAAAAAA. I ; AAAAAAAAAA, J.
AKALB; AKAKALC; AKAKAKALD. AKALB; BKALC; CKALD;
DKALE. BKELG; GLEKB. FKDLJ ; JLFKD.
CMALB; DMALC; IMGLB.
CKNLC; HKNLH. DMDLN; EMELN.
JLAN; JKALAA; JKBLAB; AAKALAB. JKJLBN; JKJKJLCN.
FNKGLFG.
BPCLF; EPBLJ; FPJLFN.
FQBLC; JQBLE; FNQFLJ.
CRBLI; BRELCB.
JPJLJRBLSLANN; JPJPJLJRCLTLANNN. JPSLT; JPTLJRD.
AQJLU; UQJLAQSLV.
ULWA; UPBLWB; AWDMALWDLDPU. VLWNA; VPCLWNC.
VQJLWNNA; VQSLWNNNA. JPEWFGHLEFWGH ; SPEWFGHLEFGWH.
GIWIHYHN; TKCYT. ZYCWADAF.
14 DPZPWNNIBRCQC.
CAN YOU DECIPHER
THIS
INTERPLANETARY
MESSAGE ?
In 1960, Ivan Bell, an English language teacher
in Tokyo, heard about Project Ozma, a scien¬
tific plan for listening in for radio messages
from outer space. To amuse his friends he
devised a simple interplanetary message of
24 symbols. It was printed in The lapan
Times of January 22, 1960. and readers were
asked to decipher it. The newspaper received
four complete solutions, including one from
a U.S. reader who wrote her answer in the
same code, adding that she lived (by Jove !)
on Jupiter. Here we reproduce Ivan Bell's
lighthearted exercise in coding an interplane¬
tary message. The message is extremely
simple to decipher; far far simpler than it
looks. All readers are urged to try their hand
at it and if they fail, let them ask their
children to help. Three words of advice:
(1) Don't be afraid to use paper and pencil.
(2) When you've found the solution you won't
have to ask, "Is this it?" ; you'll know you have
the answer. (3) The key to the solution is to
be found in paragraphs 2 and 3. Paragraph 1
simply lists the alphabet (minus letters O and
X). Answers will be published next month.
Punctuation marks are not part of the
message but indicate time lapses.
repeating this series many times. If you count the total
number of symbols, (i.e. circles + dots) it comes to 203.
This is a number which can be decomposed in only one
way, 7 x 29. If we do split it up in this way, in a rectan¬
gular array 7 x 29 we arrive at Fig. 7.
oo oo oooo
oo o
° o oooo °
O OOOOO o oo
O O O ooo o
ooo o o
o oooo ooo
Fig. 7
Of course this expression 1+2 = 3 would mean
nothing as it stands, but I am simply indicating that it is
possible to send pictures using a train of pulses; and the
pictures could of course be much more complex than
this. What in fact should we send? I mentioned that we
wanted something more advanced than Pythagoras' theo¬
rem. One subject we do know about is the way in which
atomic nuclei can be split up in reactions taking place in
stars. One such reaction, believed to be correct, is when
lithium and hydrogen combine to form carbon and helium.
o o o
oo oo 00
o
o oo o ooo
o
oo oo oo
o o o
o 0
oo oo oo o
oooo o
o o 000 00
oooo o
oo oo 00 o
0 o
Fig. 8
If we indicate this as shown in Fig. 8, in which the
single and double circles represent two different types of
elementary particles in the nuclei, it is probable that it
will be recognised. (Of course we would use predeter
mined signs for the plus and equals.) The alien races
will then know that we understand stellar reactions. We
could send diagrams of the carbon cycle, indicating that
we live on the basis of carbohydrate chemistry. We
should perhaps send diagrams of our local constellation
and solar system.
Apart from all this, once one can send pictures the
problems become standard ones of education and logic.
It is however a fascinating idea to compile an educational
series on "All about us and our world for someone who
has never seen any of it." Think of putting together the
whole sum of human experience and existence in a series
of programmes. I would like to see some television series'
experts try it.
Quite apart from the problem of sending information,
however, there is the problem of listening. Suppose other
advanced galactic communities are trying to beam infor¬
mation at us? What should we be listening for?
Once again we are considering intelligent signals, differ¬
ing from the natural signals in the universe. There is one
way in which perhaps detection can be made easier,
Fig. 9
without examining every one in detail. Fig. 9 shows the
forms of two types of signal: (a) is noise, (b) is man-made.
The time spent by each near its zero line is quite different:
(a) spends a large proportion of its time near its zero-line,
the proportion becoming less the further away it gets;
(b) spends all of its time a fixed distance from its zero-
line. The test, in other words, to distinguish between
CONT'D ON PAGE 10
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Distant galaxies
caught in a steel mesh
Left, general view of the Arecibo
radio-radar telescope.
Its giant bowl-shaped
reflector, covering
over 18 acres (7 hectares),
Is made up of some
11,000 sections of i In.
(1.25 cm.) thick wire mesh.
Suspended above the centre
is the focusing device
weighing 500 tons
(close-up photo right)
which can be moved about
to allow the telescope
to scan a large area of sky.
The telescope's position,
18 degrees north of the equator,
enables it to reach
all the planets,
for at that latitude
they pass high overhead.
MONG the rugged green hills
Lnear Arecibo, Puerto Rico,
scientists and engineers have built the
world's largest radio-radar telescope. Its
bowl-shaped reflector, which lines a vast
natural hollow in the hills, is a taut ex¬
panse of steel mesh covering over 18
acres. Five hundred feet above it, sus¬
pended from cables supported by three
tall towers, is a 550-ton complex of gir¬
ders, wires and machinery. This is the
telescope's focusing device. A 96-ft (30
metre) metal finger points downwards to
send radio waves to the mesh which then
reflects them into outer space. When
these reflected waves strike something
they bounce back. Scientists analyze the
returning signals for information about
the object encountered in space. The
equipment operates as a radio telescope
when only the reflector (antenna) and
receiver are used; as a radar telescope
when short pulses of radio waves from
a transmitter are distributed over the
reflector. A beam of pulses is directed
to a target in space, and when they
bounce back the reflector is used a
second time to receive them. The tele
scope was originally designed for studies
of the ionosphere, the rarefied outer
atmosphere of the earth, but is now being
used also for radar exploration of the
solar system and for receiving radio sig¬
nals from some of the most distant
objects known to astronomers. The great
potentialities of radio astronomy for
revealing the large-scale structure of the
universe became fully appreciated in the
1950s, when it was discovered that some
of the most intense celestial radio
emitters, hitherto known as "radio stars"
were, in fact, galaxies so distant as to be
on the verge of detectability with the
largest optical telescopes. As Sir Ber¬
nard Lovell, director of the Jodrell Bank
Radio Astronomy Laboratories in Eng¬
land, points out in the December, 1965
issue of Science Journal, published in
England, for nearly 20 years the combined
work of the optical and radio astronomers
has. been revealing a cosmos of ever
increasing fantasy. The penetration into
space had increased so rapidly that
already in 1960 it became possible
to identify a radio galaxy (3C295) 4,500
million light years distant from the earth.
*-* - '
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Photos © Günther - I.L.N. - Holmès-Lebel
A
h
^L. -^"
^*^ w^-^i 	 '
**"'"
EN?
. *
Maintenance
worker skis
across the wire
mesh of the
reflector which
has a diameter
of 1,000 ft.
(350 metres).
Keeping the mesh
clear of paper
and leaves
Is a never-ending job.
9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
MESSAGES TO THE STARS (Continued from page 7)
40 years for an answer to come back
10
natural and artificial is a statistical one, and can readily
and quickly be applied, without studying each signal in
detail.
I might point out that we could learn a good deal about
the other planet just by the character of the radio signals,
quite apart from their information content. If the signals
appear at more or less fixed intervals, we might assume
that this represents the length of their day. The basic
frequency of their radio signal will slowly change, due to
the transmitter moving towards and away from us, due
to the rotations of the planet on its axis and about its star
(this is the well-known Doppler effect.) From a study of
this frequency, we could deduce these quantities, and
hence find something about their planet's behaviour. We
might even, from this, be able to identify their star.
It is necessary to digress to consider just how many
advanced communities there may be, as the type of signal
received (or the type we send) does depend on it.
S far as we know, a small fraction of stars have
^planets. For any planet to be able to support
life, it must be neither too hot nor too cold" because life
depends on chemical reactions, which will proceed too
slowly at low temperatures, and will not proceed at high
temperatures because substances decompose. (We know
that the whole universe is made of the same materials we
are familiar with, and the same general laws of chemistry
apply.)
Thus only a fraction of planets will be at the appropriate
distance from their stars. Further, only certain types of
star are suitable; they must give a constant energy output
over the biological time-scale.
When all this has been worked out, the next problem is
how long may technologically advanced communities exist,
compared with the whole time life has existed on their
planet? This is a matter for speculation: perhaps by
sociologists. In our own case, for instance, we have had
radio for only some 60 years, while life has existed over
the vastly longer biological life-time scale.
If we can imagine advanced communities existing for
much longer than our 60 years, we arrive at the quite
speculative figure that there may be some hundred million
advanced communities throughout our universe (taking the
number of stars in the universe to be denoted by a 1 fol¬
lowed by 21 zeros, i.e. one thousand million million million).
The general thinking in this section will be seen to stem
from one aspect of the "cosmological principle" namely,
that there is no reason to assume that we on this earth
are unique, or specially privileged in any way.
This is not a very useful figure, because many of those
communities will be immense distances away. But to come
nearer, within 15 light-years of us there are seven "suit¬
able" stars; within 50 light-years there are 100 "suitable"
stars. That is, there is a small probability that some
advanced communities are within hailing distance.
There is another conclusion to be drawn, however. The
lifetime of a technological community is probably so much
longer than the time we have had modern technology,
that nearly all the galactic communities are far more
advanced than we are. They may already be in a "galac¬
tic" club, busy communicating; and they may maintain a
small subdepartment who are beaming messages at other
likely stars in the hope that they may discover some novice
community, just on the threshold of interstellar communi¬
cation, to whom they can send .their kindergarten messages
and gradually educate to their standards. It is a humbling
thought.
What all this means in practice is that we might find
that any other community could pay very little attention
to us. They may have thousands of likely stars to send
signals to; as they would not have vast numbers of trans¬
mitters, we might receive signals only 1 day in 100 years
(and they might have been doing this for thousands of
years, of course without result).
This situation is perhaps rather pessimistic, because in
fact a much better way for any community to explore is
not to send signals, but to send unmanned space-ships,
or "probes". These would be loaded with computers and
recorded material, ready to give us information about them
and to record the information we send them. A superior
community might be able to spray thousands of such
probes into the galaxy with pre-programmed instructions
to listen for any radio waves, and "home" on any planet
sending them out.
What would such a probe do? It would circle a planet,
picking up radio waves. How would it make itself known?
This raises another basic problem; how you get people to
perceive the unexpected, and not to dismiss it just as
interference?
One suggestion which has been made is that the probe
would send back a replica of any message it received.
This is good technology, because the senders of the signal
would probably also be listening on this frequency. There
is in fact a case of some long-delayed echoes in a radio
transmission investigation about 30 years ago, which have
never been explained.
It is entertaining to speculate that they might have been
picked up by an exploring probe, which has relayed the
information back to its planet, many light-years distant;
a further message may be even now on its way to us.
(The delay is because, as pointed out earlier, no signal
can travel faster than light: so that if a planet is 20 light-
years away, it would be 40 years before a response to
the first signal was heard.)
I T is worth closing with the question, assuming
' that the sort of exploring probe I have discussed
may come to us one day, should we learn to listen or
learn to send? There is already a listening station in the
U.S.A. which has searched without result so far for
intelligible radio waves from some nearby stars.
Listening is exciting work: it has an appeal. Sending
information is not so appealing: you can do it for a long
time with nothing to show for it. But it seems to me that
it might be far more important. It is unlikely that a probe
will yield up its stored information unless we interrogate
it properly; and we should surely, besides giving informa¬
tion about ourselves, want to ask questions of the advanced
communities such as how to conquer cancer. (For it is
worth noting that the interchange of information in this
way is an entirely benign activity.)
I think we should spend time and energy on studying
how to send, and what to send to be ready for the
opportunity when it comes. For although the probability
of success in communicating with alien communities is
very small indeed, the probability of success if we do
nothing about it is precisely zero.
The above article Is the text of an address delivered by Dr. Mercer
at the meeting of the British Association for the Advancement of
Science, held in Southampton, England, last year.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
\
NEW PATTERNS
OF TRANSPORT
FOR AFRICA
Modern roads laid across
the sands of the Sahara
have made possible
the exploitation
of vast oil deposits.
This network of highways
will be incorporated into
a future Trans-Saharan highway.
Here, surveyors plot the line
of a new route
deep in the desert.
Esso
by W. H. Owens
I N recent years an entirely new pattern of trans¬
port has emerged in Africa and Asia where
the development of modern communications is a matter of
vital concern to the young independent nations. (See "The
Great Asian Highway", Unesco Courier, June 1965.)
Future progress and prosperity in these countries will
depend primarily on the exchange of materials, goods and
services both with their neighbours and with peoples over¬
seas. This means that they must be served by good inter¬
national road networks, linking the main cities, ports and
production areas, and by deep water harbours capable
of accommodating large ships and handling all types of
cargo with speed and economy.
In the past, the African and Asian transport systems
were based principally on the routing of export produce
and minerals as directly as possible from their source to
shipping points on the coasts. The railways and roads
constructed in the days of colonial rule were designed
first and foremost for this purpose. Consequently there
were no transport links across frontiers between the
main centres of neighbouring territories, except where they
happened to be provided by natural waterways.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
H
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
- 7
A big industrial complex ¡s now growing up around Accra, capital of Ghana,
thanks to the nearby new port of Tema with Its ultra-modern installations,
and also to the completion of a great dam across the Volta River.
The first two turbines of the Volta hydroelectric Installations,
which began to operate in August 1965, are now supplying electricity to a wide area.
Here, a surveyor signals to his partner on one of Ghana's
new construction sites near the Volta River.
G. Gerber-World Bank
NEW PATTERNS OF TRANSPORT (Cont'd)
Through jungles and desert wastes
12
Today the development of new means of transport is
strikingly evident in such a region as West Africa, where
a large number of former colonial territories have achieved
indépendance since World War II.
Modern industrial plants have been established to process
the crops and raw materials from farms, mines and forests,
and the various countries are eager to develop reciprocal
trade with their neighbours. Such trade can grow and
prosper only if there are modern inter-territorial communi¬
cations.
Over the past four years successive conferences have
been convened by the U.N. Economic Commission for
Africa (ECA) to discuss proposals for building international
highway systems to serve the main geographical regions
of the continent and provide easy access between them.
At the first meeting of West African Transport and Works
Ministers, held at Monrovia (Liberia) in 1961, agreement
was reached on the basic routes for a regional highway net¬
work of some 14,000 miles. This will link the capital cities and
major centres of all territories, reaching east to the Sudan
frontier and south to the Congo. Since then, ECA experts
have made detailed studies of West African transport
problems and the special transport needs of the land¬
locked countries of the region.
In 1962 ECA sponsored the first East African transport
conference at which an international road system for this
region, including all countries from Sudan in the north to
Mozambique in the south, was agreed to. Economic and
technical surveys of alternative routes, particularly over the
main existing gap between Khartoum and Nairobi, are now
under way.
Both East and West networks will link up at many points,
so that eventually it will be possible to drive the width of
the continent on continuous metalled roads. Construction
of some of the new inter-territorial routes are already
under way for example, the first all-weather highway
between the Ivory Coast and Ghana was started early in
1964 but the task is an immense one that will keep highway
engineers busy in Africa for a long time ahead.
With the major oil developments in the Sahara, the linking
of this vast and potentially rich region to the rest of Africa
has assumed growing importance. Desert highway cons¬
truction has so far been limited to the essential transport
needs of the oil and natural gas bases. But a considerable
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
*%-* *fc
T. Spencer-World Bank
'-%>£-'
Camels take a rest while a modern caravan rolls
by on a metalled highway which crosses an ancient trail
near the Awash River in Ethiopia.
mileage of these modern oil roads the first ever to be
built across the barren desert wastes will be incorporated
in the proposed trans-Saharan Highway which will link the
Mediterranean ports of Africa to the interior, and especially
the land-locked south Saharan states of Mali, Niger, Chad
and Upper Volta.
The trans-Saharan Highway project was discussed by
transport specialists from ten African countries at an ECA
conference held at Algiers in May, 1964. Agreement was
reached on a north-south route through the heart of the
desert to join up with the road network of West Africa.
This would take the form of an inverted letter Y on the
map, stretching south from the Mediterranean coast at
Algiers, via El Golea and In Salah, to Tamanrasset in the
Hoggar mountains.
From Tamanrasset there would be two branches; one
to Gao, in Mali, which could be extended through Upper
Volta to Ghana; the other to Agades, in Niger, which would
join up with the trunk road system of Nigeria. There
would also be two feeder roads at the Mediterranean end,
one from Morocco and one from Tunisia, both joining
the main trans-Saharan route at Tamanrasset.
A four-nation committee, consisting of Algeria, Tunisia,
Mali and Niger, is now studying the plans for this great
highway project which, at a conservative estimate, will
cost in the region of $126 million.
Delegates to all recent African transport conferences
have stressed the need for standardization, not only as
regards road and bridge design but in such matters as vehi¬
cle legislation, traffic signalling and safety devices, and the
classification of through highway routes.
Another problem being studied is the simplification of
existing frontier formalities or where possible, their aboli¬
tion. Without such reforms the immense value of the
international roads to future trade and tourism in Africa
could be seriously jeopardized.
Both African and Asian countries alike are too poor to
finance these urgently needed highways from their own
resources. So help is being provided on a generous scale
through agencies such as the U.N. Special Development
Fund and the World Bank. The World Bank has already
produced loans of well over a thousand million dollars for
highway development in nearly thirty countries, and most
of this vast sum has been invested over the past five
years. It has also sponsored transport surveys in India,
Burma, Nigeria and other countries.
Several important African highway projects are included
in the twelfth annual programme of the U.N. Special Fund,
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
NEW PATTERNS OF TRANSPORT (Cont'd)
Latest innovation:
the 'portless port'
which was approved by its governing council in January,
1965. Among these projects are a study of highway
development in Western Nigeria, the development of the
highway system in Somalia, and a transport survey of the
southern regions of the Central African Republic and
Cameroon. The Special Fund provides for the services
of consulting firms, experts, technicians and whatever
equipment is required.
Modern ports must also play a key role in the economic
development of the emergent countries. Significantly,
routes between ports and land-locked countries have
high priority in the international highway programmes both
of Africa and Southern Asia.
Until quite recently there were very few modern deep-
water harbours able to accommodate ocean-going ships
around the African coastline. Apart from the ports of South
Africa and the Mediterranean coast, most of the maritime
trade was handled at the numerous surf ports which had
served the African peoples for centuries.
Overseas vessels which called at these surf ports had
to anchor out in the roadstead while fleets of the traditional
paddle craft carried the goods in relays between ship and
shore. Quite obviously such an out-of date method has
proved increasingly uneconomic in modern times, and as
trade grew so did the delays to shipping.
I
14
N the years following World War II, queues of
ocean-going ships might be seen off the African
surf ports awaiting their turn to discharge or load cargoes.
Since then, however, the principal harbours on the east
and west coasts have been dredged and deepened. Con¬
crete wharves with modern cargo transit sheds have been
constructed to allow the direct berthing of deep-draft
vessels, and electric cranes and other mechanized handling
appliances have been progressively installed. As a result
of the greatly improved rate of ship turn-round, overseas
trade at these harbours has increased rapidly.
The most important single maritime development in Africa
during the past decade is Ghana's great new port of Tema,
which has replaced the surf port of Accra a few miles away.
Tema was officially opened in February, 1962, by President
Kwame Nkrumah, who described the 80 million-dollar pro¬
ject as "a signpost to the future" for his country.
Eastern Ghana now has a first-class modern seaport
for handling large ships and all types of cargo a facility
which will assist the country's development. Without it,
the famous Volta River Project Ghana's largest single
economic undertaking could never have been started at
all.
Tema Harbour is nearly one mile in circumference and,
with a water area of about 500 acres, is the largest man-
made harbour around the African coastline. Eventually
there will be twenty deep water berths for shipping and
the port can handle up to a million tons of dry cargoes
annually. There is a separate oil berth for ocean super¬
tankers of up to 35,000 tons.
The benefits of this new African port are not to be
confined to Ghana alone. Through the developing inter¬
national highways, other states in the region will be able
to share its advantages and thereby develop overseas
trade for the good of all. The extensive river systems of
A NEW CITY
has risen at Nuadibu
(formerly
Port-Etienne)
where the western
tip of the Sahara
desert meets
the Atlantic coast
of Mauritania.
The building
of port installations
and a railway
has led to
the exploitation of
one of the world's
largest iron-ore
deposits 400 miles
(600 km)
distant in the desert.
In 1960,
the World Bank lent
$66 million for
the development of
this vast mining
operation.
E H. Dean-World Bank
West Africa will play their part too. These are capable
of great development as low-cost transport routes to serve
the communities of the hinterland a long way from the
coast.
One of the real handicaps to maritime development in
the poorer countries of the world are the high costs both
of building and operating a modern deep-water harbour.
There is also an acute shortage of the various skills required
to run a complex enterprise of this kind.
These and other problems would suggest, perhaps, that
the conventional type of seaport may not after all be the
one best suited to the future needs of the emergent nations.
The new trend of carrying cargo in bulk, and the ocean
transport of goods in pre-packed containers, is already
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
making some of the long established operations at the
world's docksides obsolete. In other words, many activities
which are at present carried on in the vicinity of a ship's
berthing place could be done with much greater economy
in the areas to which most of the cargo is consigned or
where it originated.
One of the most interesting developments which could
perhaps help to solve port problems in many developing
countries is the offshore berthing platform, or loading
tower a conception which has been described, paradoxi¬
cally, as the "portless port". Linking a ship with the store,
and so to the connecting roads or railways, in the simplest
possible way gives such installations great flexibility.
For example, they can be set up as a shipping point as
close as possible to newly exploited sources of raw mate¬
rials, and so reduce the cost of building long stretches of
link roads or railways and of transport operations along
these. Offshore platforms can be adapted for handling all
types of ships and cargoes.
Although the emergent nations of Africa and the Far
East have many obstacles to overcome as they developed
their land and sea communications, they do also have the
advantages of an age of unprecedented technical and scien¬
tific progress and international co-operation. All the latest
technical advances in every field of transportation, together
with the means of financing them, are being made available
to these young and advancing countries through the various
specialist agencies of the United Nations.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
The seventh centenary of the birth of Dante in 1265 was marked last year by celebrations the
world over. In Paris, at the end of two sessions of round table discussions led by Profes¬
sor Vittore Branca of the University of Padua, Unesco organized a special commemorative
ceremony on the evening of October 28 to honour the great poet. In the presence of the Minis¬
ter of Education of Italy, Mr. Luigi Gui, leading personalities of the world of letters paid tribute to
the work of Dantei and his continuing influence across the ages: Marcel Brion of the Académie
Française spoke of four famous illustrators of Dante (Botticelli, Blake, Doré and Dali); the
Italian poet Eugenio Móntale spoke on "Dante, Yesterday and Today"; llya Ehrenburg on
"The Poet's Universality", and Mary McCarthy on "Dante's Paradise and the New World".
"If Dante seems so close to us today," Unesco's Director-General, René Maheu, said in
an introductory address, "it is partly perhaps because like our own generation, he lived in
a time of wars, fratricidal strife and persecution. What we particularly admire in Dante is
that amid the upheavals he lived through he maintained an unswerving faith in man, and suc¬
ceeded, misfortunes and calamities notwithstanding, in upholding the universal values
which all men at heart hold dear." And as Eugenio Móntale pointed out: "Dante is the only
great European poet of medieval times whose words have remained alive and meaningful even to
those without special literary training." It is precisely this universality of Dante's writings and
his relevance to our times that llya Ehrenburg stressed in his address, the most salient pass¬
ages of which are reproduced below.
FOUR FACES
OF DANTE
1. By Orcagna
(first half of the
14th century),
In the church of
Santa Maria Novella,
Florence.
2. By Giotto
(1266-1337).
Bargello Museum,
Florence.
3. By Raphael
(1483-1520).
Detail of
"The Dispute
of the Holy
Sacrament",
Vatican City.
4. By Luca
Signorelli
(1445-1523).
Kupferstich
Kabinett,
Berlin."
Photos Guidotti, Rome
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
DANTE
by llya Ehrenburg
the primacy
of poetry
he greatness of Dante is
evident, if only from the
enthusiasm his work arouses in
every part of our disunited world,
whether among the inhabitants of
inferno, real or imaginary, among those
who do not regard themselves as
living in purgatory, or among the illu¬
sory shades of paradise.
Reading is an act of creation: every
reader of the Divine Comedy brings
to Dante's text something of himself
a fragment, as it were, of his cen¬
tury. There are thousands of commen¬
taries lined up on the library shelves.
Dante is transformed into the hero of
his own Comedy and is written
about as freely as Hamlet is, or Don
Quixote. Some represent him as a
gloomy Scholastic, others as an im¬
passioned subversive figure bent on
the demolition of various dogmas,
others again as a visionary sage
whom the Popes, by some oversight,
failed to admit to the company of the
saints.
Dante Alighieri dreamed of posthu¬
mous fame, nor was he mistaken.
Never has he been forgotten, except
during a period which considered poe¬
try in bad taste; and in 1757, when the
Italian Bottinelli wrote slightingly of the
Divine Comedy, Voltaire declared
that he admired his daring in calling
Dante a madman, and his poem a
monstrosity.
With the advent of romanticism the
curtain rose anew on poetry, and
Dante's Comedy was "re-discovered".
Goethe, Novalis, Byron, Shelley and
Pushkin, found it an inspiration.
A torrent of commentaries poured
forth. One book in particular, publish¬
ed in the middle of the 19th century,
and dedicated to Pope Pius VII,
intrigues' me. The author, a devout
Catholic, was a certain Eugène Aroux,
and the very title "Dante, heretic,
revolutionary and socialist" bears
witness to the exuberance of his
imagination. But this is an exception.
Most commentators, while disputing
ILYA EHRENBURG is a world-famous
Soviet writer and poet whose works have
been translated in 60 languages. Among
his works in English are "The Fall of Paris"
(1942); "The Thaw" (1956) and "People
and Life" (1962).
amongst themselves, endeavoured to
claim Dante for their own faction;
Catholics, atheists, royalists and
republicans alike proclaimed him one
of themselves.
The controversy did not die. Those
engaged in it were not, for the most
part, lovers of poetry, but Scholastics
of all persuasions. The end of the
13th century and the beginning of the
14th was a period of transition, which
can be called either the late Middle
Ages or else the dawn of the Renais¬
sance; thus it is easy to represent
Dante looking to the past or to the
future.
The French historian, Jacques Le
Goff, in his recent book "La Civilisa¬
tion de l'Occident médiéval" (medieval
western civilization), calls the Divine
Comedy a sublime poetical summing
up of medieval learning and mentality,
but one turned wholly towards the
past; a magnificent monument of
"reaction". At the same time, dozens
of other literary historians and critics,
compatriots and contemporaries of Le
SOUL IN TORMENT. Drawing by
the French sculptor,
Auguste Rodin.
Guidotti. Rome
Goff, describe Dante as a "human¬
ist", a "philosopher of the Renais¬
sance" and "the father of individual¬
istic poetry".
In Soviet literature, we find similar
polemics going on. In the 1920s,
Vladimir Fritshe, one of the popular
exponents of Marxism, flatly called
Dante "an imperialist in the medieval
sense of the term" a judgement which
was contested by Anatole Lunacharsky,
who considered Dante "the greatest
poet of the early Renaissance." In
1965, a literary critic and poet wrote
that students of Dante in the Soviet
Union are interested in him mainly as
a "political thinker and a moralist";
yet a young Soviet political thinker and
moralist has written an essay on the
complexity, profundity and power of
Dante as a poet.
If I have noted all these disputes,
past and present, it is not because I
myself intend to stick a new label on
his portrait, or classify him in any par¬
ticular category. (Although Giotto, who
knew him, has left us a portrait of
Dante, I do not believe it is a true
likeness: Giotto doubtless protrayed
Dante in the same arbitrary terms as
Dante described Beatrice.. All that
remains is Raphael's conventional
profile of Dante, and the same des¬
cription of him occurs again and again
even in Alexander Blok's poem "the
shade of Dante, with the aquiline
profile." Not a word about his face,
only the nose resembling an eagle's
beak: a convention. Pushkin speaks of
"austere Dante"; Valéry Bryusov
calls him a "sombre hero of bygone
years".)
I have referred to the thousands of
commentaries, the controversies, past
and present, simply as a pretext for
speaking about Dante, not as a spe¬
cialist but merely as a reader and a
writer of the mid-20th century. Need
I say that I am drawn to Dante as a
poet, and as a poet alone? We look
at the paintings of Leonardo da Vinci
for the aesthetic experience and visual
pleasure, without reference to his work
on engineering or anatomy: as we read
Faust, we do not think of Goethe's
studies on colour.
What interests me in Dante is not
the feuds between Guelphs, Blacks
and Whites, not Pope Boniface VIII,
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18
DANTE (Cont'd)
not what Dante knew about
compasses or his ideas on geo¬
metry, Euclidean or non-Euclidean;
not his dream of a universal monarchy,
his conception of celestial perfection
nor any of the many other subjects
about which all the Dante experts in
the world, including some in my own
country, have written and are still writ¬
ing. I believe in the force and vitality
of poetry and, though Dante's learning
is out-dated, his sentiments, true to
the eternal laws of art, are still abun¬
dantly alive, and have the power to
kindle our imagination.
Croce the philosopher, the poets
Eliot and Saint John Perse, the
Soviet poets, Ossip Mandelshtam,
Anna Akhmatova and Zabolotsky, have
all praised the poetic intensity of the
Divine Comedy. Dante himself thought
it unlikely his work could be translated,
and he was no doubt right.
Each generation has its own
approach, and each reads Dante's
Comedy in its own way. I would like
to speak of what our generation finds
most remarkable in the work of the
great Florentine, as corresponding to
our own excursions into inferno, pur¬
gatory and paradise.
The first point I shall make is that
he was not impartial; for this
is something for which we Soviet
writers have all too often been criti¬
cized. The term "committed" is applied
to our poets with just a suggestion of
mockery, and it is alleged to account
for the failure of Soviet literature in
the past forty years or so to attain the
heights reached by the great Russian
writers of the last century. But this
explanation is not valid.
I have had occasion to quote many
writers who far from being hampered
by their lack of impartiality, on the
contrary found it an inspiration as in
the case of Stendhal, Dostoevsky and
many others.
But the best example of this is Dante
himself. Not only did he not eschew
politics: for long years of his life,
indeed, he lived for politics, and it was
on this account that he suffered exile:
"Thou shalt make trial of how
salt doth taste another's bread,
and how hard the path to
descend and mount upon
another's stair" (Paradise, XVII
58-61).
It was during the years of struggle
that the Divine Comedy was begun.
Alighieri still continued to negotiate
with other émigrés, the White Guelphs
but, disillusioned, he turned increas-
CONT'D ON PAGE 20
DANTE'S FLORENCE
Florence as it appeared
in the time of Dante.
Detail of a 14th century fresco,
"Our Lady of Mercy",
in the Loggia del Bigallo, Florence.
© Giraudon-Allnarl, Pans
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
FAMOUS ILLUSTRATORS
OF THE 'DIVINE COMEDY'
Below left, an angel of paradise,
drawn by the Spanish painter
Salvador Dali (1950).
Right, illustration by
the Italian painter,
Giorgio de Chirico,
for the first Canto
of the Inferno,
in which the poet relates
his encounter
with three wild beasts.
Bottom, "The Hypocrites
with Caiaphas",
a water colour by the
English poet and painter,
William Blake (1757-1827).
illustrating the 23rd Canto
of the Inferno.
Photos Guidottl, Rome
DANTE (Cont'd)
'Masterpieces
are born eternal'
ingly towards the Ghibellines, hoping
for the intervention of Henry VII. In
short, he never turned his back on
politics, and the Divine Comedy is
suffused with political passion.
And Dante's partiality not only
helped him to write the Comedy; it
infused many a canto with passion and
vitality. But who nowadays is really
interested in the struggle between the
Guelphs and the Ghibellines, except
perhaps the Dante specialists who,
though they have devoted their entire
lives to studies of the poet, neverthe¬
less miss the very essence of his
poetry?
What degrades art is not tenden-
tiousness, but the tendency to adulter¬
ate the essence of art. It is often
salutary to recall the old adage that
there is no point in using a violin for
knocking in nails with, if only because
it is better to use a hammer and
because violins may come in useful on
other occasions. Stendhal, who was
as committed as any man could be,
scribbled the following note in the
margin of his manuscript of Lucien
Leuwen: " I must be careful not to let
the man of politics eclipse the man of
passion. The man of politics will be
gone fifty years from now. All we
need of him is what history finally
judges interesting."
Dante succeeded in writing a poem
which still' stirs the hearts of its
readers not merely fifty, but six
hundred and fifty years afterwards.
What interests us are not the causes
of the feuds, but the passions involved.
I wanted to make this point because
there are many purists whose criti¬
cism, just or unjust, of modern writers
labelled "committed", is based on
these grounds alone. Yet the fact of
expounding a cause has not prevented
my contemporaries Mayakovsky,
Eluard, Brecht, Aragon and Pablo
Neruda from becoming great poets.
One of the questions of interest to
us today is that of the realism of
Dante, the poet. The word "realism"
may sometimes sound a trifle abstract,
like the use of numbers in the Divine
Comedy; it is disparaged or lauded,
anathematized or sanctified, by turn.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
As Beatrice leads
Dante towards Paradise,
he contemplates the souls
of the blessed a drawing by
the Italian painter,
Sandro Botticelli (1444-1510).
At Unesco's commemoration
of the seventh centenary
of Dante's birth,
Marcel Brion, the French author,
analyzed the different ways
in which great artists
have illustrated the "Divine Comedy."
Botticelli, in his view, was
Dante's most faithful interpreter,
and conceived his drawings
"like the schema for a moving picture,
five centuries before
that art form was invented."
Guldottl, Rome
3^ * J* -* »
f
V * ...
^ Mk «* < «. 3|
** * ' '*
JV'
V
%
*
*
* *
V V
Ï
» k ft * * ' ? *
» s-.v JE jg i
<^¿¡5s'-'í».¿¿K .
'4 3
-* A
V
//I 4! *
at-
*
&
*
*
tJb
-v
ä
I would like first of all to point out
the error of certain historians who
treat changes in artistic forms in the
same way as if they were dealing
with social progress or developments
in the exact sciences.
Stendhal, in his book on Italian
painting, describes Giotto as a clumsy
precursor of the great art of the
Renaissance. Such was the generally
accepted view during the first decades
of the 19th century. Then came the
time when the merits of the Quattro¬
cento were recognized. First, people
became enamoured of Botticelli ; then
later Masaccio was "discovered" and
it is now claimed that the work of
this artist, who died young, contains
all the seeds of modern painting. The
same cannot, I think, be said of
Raphael But does this make his
frescoes any the less perfect?
HE attitude to the painters
of the past varies accord¬
ing to the particular tastes and aspi¬
rations of every epoch. Is Giotto to
be labelled primitive because he lack¬
ed the eclectic academic skill of Guido
Reni? What Giotto had to express
was very different from the learning
and the canons of the 17th century.
Can the simplified forms of Picasso
and Braque be attributed to inability to
depict the universe in terms of a series
of colour photographs?
The Western world was evolving,
the knowledge of geography, physics
and astronomy expanding. In the
13th century, the sculptors working on
the Gothic cathedrals produced an
encyclopedia, in plastic form, of the
learning of their age, so that some
of the figures in their bas reliefs may
make us smile. For all that, these
sculptors were no less skilled, indeed
they were more so, than many of those
working in the second half of the
present century.
Victor Hugo once wrote that science
progresses constantly by a felicitous
process of self-cancellation. Science,
he said, is a ladder ; poetry a winged
flight... Masterpieces are born eternal.
Dante does not cancel out Homer.
Hugo knew that the Earth revolves.
Our contemporaries have learned that
infinity is not an abstract conception,
but a reality. This invalidates Dante's
cosmogony and cosmography, but
detracts nothing from his poetry.
Realism in art stems from the feeling
of real life, nature and man; and in
this sense Dante, like all true artists,
was certainly a realist. We read his
Divine Comedy with supreme interest
even though the symbolism of
numbers, the sanctity of the divers
dogmas and Dante's dreams of a
peaceful and just monarchy leave us
cold.
The picture Dante draws not only
of inferno and purgatory but of
paradise as well is based on the
image of the Earth, on all that he
himself has seen and lived through.
It is true that the scenes he describes
are drawn from fantasy, but is not
fantasy, after all, part and parcel of
the real world of man? Are not
Gogol's "The Overcoat" and Kafka's
"The Trial" in their way realistic?
Dante's vision, permeating both the
spiritual nature of the poet and the
purpose of the Divine Comedy, may
be described as realistic fantasy. Goya
was endowed with stupendous fantasy,
and his war scenes have nothing in
common with the battle pictures
painted by his contemporaries. But
Picasso, in his "Guernica" gave us
something different a foreboding of
Hiroshima. Dante, wandering through
the world beyond the grave, has
constantly before his eyes familiar
scenes from life on Earth. He is a
living person among the shades of
the dead-
Dante is a humanist and a realist;
but he is, first and foremost, a great
poet capable of transcending the
bounds of both Christian dogma and
naive realism. We have perforce to
forgive him the incident of the
discovery of a second, unknown world,
for which Ulysses was so cruelly
punished; and must accept the fact
that Dante spent his life straying not
only through the streets of Italy, but
also through the subterranean maze of
obscure emotions.
In purgatory, Dante meets the sing¬
er Casella, whom he knew and loved
on Earth; and begs him timidly:
"If a new law take not from
thee
memory or skill in that song of
love
which was wont to calm my
every desire,
may it please thee therewith
to solace awhile my soul...''
(Purgatory II, 106-109).
Whereupon Casella sings the love
song from Dante's Convivio and the
dwellers in purgatory, together with
Dante and even the wise Virgil, listen
enchanted until the guardian of the
lost souls, Cato of Utica, the Stoic,
who slew himself with his own sword
after the defeat of the republican
party, hustles up to chide the shades
entranced by the sweet strains...
"What is this, ye laggard spirits?...
Haste to the mount". And drives them
back to their task.
WHAT now remains of the
feud between Guelphs and
Ghibellines, the religious dogmas, and
the doctrines of Aristotle or Plato?
Dante's Divine Comedy itself, the
power and the music of his poetry
with all due deference to Cato of
Utica and his like.
Historians have indeed a difficult
task. We feast on the miraculous
apples, while they have to analyse the
soil from which the apple-trees sprang.
The Divine. Comedy ends with the
famous line :
"...The Love that moves the
Sun and the other stars".
Every child now knows that Dante
was wrong in thinking that the Sun and
the other heavenly bodies revolve
round the Earth; but every modern
man with a spark of humanity in him
knows in his heart that Dante was
right, and that love indeed moves the
Sun and the other heavenly bodies, «-j
including this planet, not very large ¿\
it is true, but important none the less,
the one which we call the Earth.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
THE ROOTS
OF PEACE
by Bert V. A. Roling
A new expression has entered the language ¡n recent years: "peace research".
Peace research deals not only with intentional war, but also with unintentional war
(war as a traffic accident) and civil war. The growing interest in this new activity
is conditioned by the nuclear arms situation which calls for a fundamental change
in the traditional organization of international relations Unesco is helping to pro¬
mote the peace research movement, and gave its support to the first international
conference of the International Peace Research Association, which took place in
Groningen (Netherlands) in July 1965. This year, Unesco is sponsoring a series
of studies on the economic and legal aspects of disarmament. Three inquiries
into the social and economic consequences of disarmament will later be carried
out under Unesco auspices in the Federal Republic of Germany, U.S.A. and U.S.S.R.
Readers' attention is drawn to a recent issue of Unesco's quarterly, International
Social Science Journal, devoted to Peace Research (Vol. XVII, No. 3, 1965)* The
complete text of the article below can be found in that issue.
(*) Single issue : 10/-(stg.), $2.00. Yearly subscription : 35/-(stg.), $7.00.
HE term "peace research" is comparatively
recent, as is the scientific interest in questions
of war and peace which is emerging all over the world.
This new interest is not surprising. It is linked up with
the changes in the nature and dangerousness of war.
Through these changes it has become possible, as is now
realized, for our technically highly developed culture to be
brought to ruin by its technology, through war.
There has always been war. An historian has calculated
that in 3,400 years of known history there have been 234
years without a known war. A French sociologist, Gaston
Bouthoul, has written a book entitled "8,000 Peace Treaties."
It is understandable enough that people should think that
war is unavoidable in view of what human nature is.
This idea of the inevitability of war has been expressed
through the ages in the "cycle of war," and is still alive
in wide circles of the population. In 1696 "The Beehive,"
by Francis Daniel Pastorious, described the cycle of war
in rhyme: "War begets Poverty, Poverty Peace, then
people will traffic and Riches increase. Riches produceth
Pride, Pride is War's ground. War begets Poverty, So we
go round." It is also understandable that people should have
made a virtue of necessity and have come to regard war
as a good thing, as the supreme manifestation of humanity,
as a cause of progress.
BERT V. A. ROLING Is secretary general of the International
f.,. Peace Research Association. From 1950 to 1957 he was a mem-
¿¿ ber of the Netherlands Delegation to the United Nations General
Assembly; he is now professor of international law and director
of the Polemological Institute at the University of Groningen
(Netherlands).
This may be surprising, in view of the misery caused
by war. But the dead are in their graves, and the cripples
are kept more or less in the background when the war is
over. The survivors usually regain their prosperity before
long. That mankind has been able to thrive and prosper,
despite our continual attempts on one another's lives, is
not due to the wisdom of our ancestors, but to their ignor¬
ance of the possibilities of destruction. We no longer live
in such ignorance. Technological evolution has now made
total destruction of the adversary possible.
War has changed its character primarily as a result
of social changes in the last few centuries. There were
times when it was waged with mercenary armies, later with
national professional armies. The Napoleonic period saw
the development of popular armies: the democratization of
war. This also had its effect upon the nature of war;
the limited war as waged by professionals had left open
the possibility of a certain chivalrousness and a military
code of honour. With the advent of the popular armies
all this was changed. Churchill rightly asserted: "From
the moment Democracy was admitted to, or rather forced
itself upon the battlefield, War ceased to be a gentleman's
game." It came to be the total war, in which people
stood facing each other.
The technical evolution in armaments made this total war
totally intolerable. There were revolutionary developments
in explosive power, in range and in speed. The destructive
power of weapons has become a million times intensified,
their range spans the earth, their speed makes defence,
effective protection against them, impossible.
From a means of pitting one's strength against another,
armaments have become a means of unrestricted mutual
CONT'D ON PAGE 24
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Mother and Child.
A sculpture
by Henry Moore.
© From "Mutter und Kind,"
Migros-Genossenschafts-
Bund, Zurich
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
THE ROOTS OF PEACE (Cont'd)
Military strength and foreign policy
destruction. This makes the total nuclear war an intolerable
catastrophe.
But will not this consequence tend to prevent war?
The power of the state is political power, and "political
power is not a power over nature, or material, or oneself,
but over the minds and actions of other men." Will not
the result of this enormous military strength be that the
adversary will no longer risk war? That is the doctrine of
the "deterrent," in which peace is sought through the threat
of intolerable destruction. Through the "balance of terror"
the intentional thermo-nuclear war certainly is excluded.
Von Clausewitz described war as the continuation of
foreign policy by other means: an attempt to achieve through
military power what had proved impossible without use of
force. Such views are no longer reasonably possible. The
thermo-nuclear war is no longer a reasonable means of
national policy. Possibly a smaller-scale war could still be
considered as such; the "limited war" of nuclear powers
or a war waged by ill-armed non-nuclear States. But in
both cases there is the danger of "escalation," of intensi¬
fication because the losing side resorts to ever bigger
weapons (military escalation), or because nuclear powers
become involved in the struggle for power between smaller
states (political escalation).
The thermo-nuclear war, in which the existence of peoples
and their cultures is at stake, is only conceivable as a
result of accident, miscalculation or escalation, as an unin¬
tentional war, as an accident in the hazards of interna¬
tional traffic.
Military strength by its very nature has a great in¬
fluence on a country's foreign policy. Military strength
opens up the possibility of a provocative, reckless foreign
policy, of brinkmanship, in the confidence that the opposing
side will not respond to the provocative policy with violence.
Only if interests that are considered really vital are affect¬
ed can the inflexibility be expected which makes a country
prepared to protect these interests by all means. But when
is inflexibility certain? On this point there is uncertainty.
N
24
ATIONAL nuclear armament is already a risky
foreign policy. Nuclear armament does prevent
an intentional nuclear war, and is as such a factor of peace.
But it also leads to reckless international policy, and in the
case of reliable "arms control" enables a country to
engage in "limited war." Because of this it increases the
risk of unintentional thermo-nuclear war, and does not
ensure the lasting peace which is the vital interest of
technically highly developed countries. National armaments
do not provide the required national security, since they
cannot prevent unintentional war, and cannot protect the
civilian population in case of war.
The increasing realization of the danger into which tech¬
nically highly developed cultures and possibly all mankind
are being led by their technology is the chief motive for
the present interest in peace research.
There is yet another motive. That is the moral aspect
of the present military situation. We have to do with
weapons of wholesale destruction, and today some -of
these weapons are aimed at the civilian population, at the
great cities. "Counter-city strategy" is an official compo¬
nent of this strategy.
The civilian population as a military target is a compa¬
ratively recent phenomenon. It seems that the practices
of actual warfare have changed the traditional law of
nations, and modern laws of war apparently sanction the
destruction of open cities. But such methods of warfare
are incompatible with what used to be regarded as the
military code of honour: war was fought against soldiers,
not against civilians.
HE "counter-city strategy" marks a lowering of
this level of warfare. It is clear proof that the
world wars did not only destroy material goods, but also
spiritual values. But this lowering of moral standards hardly
fits in with the great emphasis on human dignity in our
culture. This recognition of human dignity is the most
characteristic trait of our times, a recognition of dignity
"without distinction as to race, sex, language or religion"
(Article 1 of the Charter of the United Nations). Weapons
of wholesale destruction can hardly be reconciled with such
recognition. One may readily concede that they work
"without distinction as to race, sex, language or religion."
But they are hardly compatible with respect for man and
for human life.
In other respects, too, the "counter-city strategy" runs
counter to prevalent views and positive international law.
In 1949, the Red Cross conventions, which re-formulated
the laws of warfare, were concluded; under these conven¬
tions the taking of hostages was expressly forbidden
(Article 34, Geneva conventions relative to the protection
of civilian persons in time of war). But in the "counter-city
strategy" the civilian population as a whole is a hostage
for the good conduct of its government. "Hostageship"
has not disappeared: indeed it has been extended and
democratized!
This paradoxical situation is cited to demonstrate that
the arms situation has become morally intolerable, and
degrading for the culture in wHlch it appears. The "coun¬
ter-city strategy" undermines the cultural values which
it is supposed to defend.
Many writers have been most outspoken in their condemn¬
ation of the weapons of wholesale destruction. The ques¬
tion is, what consequences follow from this condemnation?
Unilateral disarmament? Some draw this conclusion. It
is the emotionally understandable answer to a situation
which is felt to be morally unjustifiable. But it is an
extremely unwise answer. It should be realized that the
arms situation has grown to what it is now through a
process lasting over many centuries.
We must take as our starting-point the situation in which
history has placed us: a world grown accustomed to think¬
ing in terms of the balance of power. A sudden disturb¬
ance of this pattern might have disastrous effects. The
non-disarmed adversary now unassailable in his power
would no longer be held in check in his foreign policy by
the power of his opponent, and would resort to a reckless
foreign policy which would be felt as intolerable by the
other side. This would very soon result in a tendency
towards rearmament. But this again might lead to pre¬
ventive action. Thus unilateral disarmament might pro¬
mote war, and encourage the use of nuclear weapons.
The realization that our armaments provide no security,
and that they morally undermine our culture, can only lead
us to strive for collective disarmament.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Unesco-Dominique Roger
PEACE IN JAPANESE
This Japanese character engraved
on the huge fountain-rock
in the garden at Unesco's H.Q.
signifies "peace".
It Is derived from an ancient
Chinese character depicting
a grain stalk (on right)
and a mouth (lower left).
General disarmament is no small problem. It can only
be achieved very gradually and with great caution. But
it is only through this approach that it will be possible to
attain lasting peace; and this will involve great changes
in the position of the national state and a great strength¬
ening of the world organization which must largely take
over its security function.
Complete disarmament under international control, with
appropriate provisions to take over the earlier function of
threat and violence, confronts the world with unprece¬
dented problems. It will strike at the root of a pattern of
life as old as humanity itself. This change cannot be
achieved by activity based on intuition. Up to the present
day existing peace movements and how popular they
were, especially between the two world warsl have
shown no practical results whatever.
Good intentions are not enough. The catch-phrases
of 19th-century peace movements disarmament and de¬
colonization as they were given expression in the resolu¬
tions of the conferences organized by the Bureau de la
Paix were correct. But the question of how such a result
could be attained was scarcely put. It would probably have
been unattainable then, too.
The Covenant of the League of Nations (Article 8) stated
that "the maintenance of peace required disarmament",
but this only implied a "reduction of national armaments
to the lowest point consistent with national safety". Consid¬
ering that the preservation of the colonial system was
impossible without arms this was an empty phrase, an
official truth which came distressingly near common
deception.
The nuclear weapons have opened our eyes to the neces¬
sity of disarmament. The Charter of the United Nations
hardly concerned itself with disarmament. It refers primar¬
ily to collective security. But then the Charter dates from
the pre-atomic age. Nuclear technology necessitates nation¬
al disarmament, makes it imperative to change the present
system, under which military power is the hard core of
relations between States.
This may be required by the actual situation, but how
can it be realized? The more one occupies oneself with
the problem of disarmament, the more strongly one is
impressed by its unprecedented complexity. One is driven
to the conclusion that today a good deal of "official
truth" is expressed in statements about general complete
disarmament, which is not always sincerely meant, and
which sometimes serves to mislead the masses.
HE effects of disarmament will be extremely far-
reaching. It follows that disarmament can only
be achieved very gradually. What are the appropriate first
steps? How is the process to proceed? What constructive
measures will have to accompany each stage of the
breaking-up of the national military machinery?
These are technical, military questions, economic and
social problems. But the greatest problems at this point
are political ones. They concern the attitudes of govern¬
ments and of the masses. For the solution of these
problems scientific research is indispensable.
The moral rejection of the arms situation, which is prima¬
rily based on the existing weapons of mass destruction
but which strikes at the root of the whole traditional military
organization is another motive for the present interest in
peace research.
A third motive may be mentioned. History shows us
that the size of the political unit in which man seeks pro¬
tection against enemies from outside has been more or
less dependent upon the range and penetration of the
existing weapons. The fortress, the town, the county, had
to disappear as distinct political units because they could
no longer be defended. The range and penetration of
modern rockets make the state a unit which can no
longer be defended. Even regional groups are no longer
capable of such defence. Modern weapons with their
world-wide capacity necessitate some form of world-wide
organization, which takes over the security function of
the states.
The age of nuclear weapons and rockets an age in
which the national state has a greater military potential
at its disposal than ever before, but can no longer guar-
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
THE ROOTS OF PEACE (Cont'd)
The science of waging peace
26
antee security is also an age in which far-reaching
changes must be effected in the current international organ¬
ization. This is a task which cannot possibly be achieved
by statesmen with a short-term policy based on conven¬
tional wisdom. The task requires extensive scientific
preparation, not only with regard to the system that would
eventually have to be established, but also with regard
to everything that would be needed to make populations
prepared to accept the ultimate goal.
In earlier times, many studies on war were published.
Indeed there exist a great many books about the causes
of war. They are worth while. But it should be borne in
mind that most of these earlier works deal with war as it
was understood by Von Clausewitz, that is to say inten¬
tional war, and pay little attention to unintentional war,
war as a traffic accident.
The old theories often lay the responsibility for war at
the door of small groups, such as ambitious kings, war¬
like generals or profit-seeking arms manufacturers. If
one asks after the cause of the unintentional war and
this implies asking after the cause of risky foreign policy
one is more likely to find it in very general factors,
current habits of thought and action. It then becomes
clear how fatal traditional habits and attitudes can be.
The cause of war is closely linked with the existing general
situation. All this indicates the democratization of the
cause of war.
If this is so, it makes the problem even more difficult.
So long as the fault lies with small élite groups, it is pos¬
sible to attempt to counteract their influence. But if we
have to do with attitudes and views which are deeply
embedded in the people as a whole, it is so much more
difficult to find ways of bringing about conditions for a
lasting peace.
It should also be recognized that as yet we know only
very little about the factors which lead to risky foreign
policies. Here too as in the problem of the cause of
the intentional war we have to do with a combination
of factors originating with the individual, with the state
and with the world. Is war unavoidable because man is
by nature aggressive? What gives rise to this aggressive¬
ness? Is it an essential component of human life, or a
reaction against frustration, or a cultural phenomenon,
acquired by imitation and adaptation to an existing pattern?
What is the effect of pornography intermingled with
violence, of films featuring violence?
And what about the factors in the state? What part is
played by public opinion here? How is public opinion
formed?
ND what factors govern the relations between
states? Are these primarily determined geo-
politically? Is overpopulation the all-important factor, as
Bouthoul thinks? What part is played by history here? What
are the origins of the stereotyped notions that peoples have
about one another? Is a disappearance of the general
distrust of foreign states possible? Is competition still more
profitable than co-operation? And if not, how can the
current pattern of competition be modified?
I mention only a few questions. They could be supple¬
mented with hundreds of others. They are mentioned
simply to show that many disciplines will have to co¬
operate to yield some insight: psychology, history, econo¬
mics, sociology, legal science, and even theology and art
history, for the Church and the arts play an important
part in attitudes and views held by individuals and groups.
These attitudes and views are of the greatest importance
with respect to war and peace. Here, too, it is essential
to emphasize, besides the concept of "intentional war",
the importance of the "unintentional war." Gradually,
there is developing a general feeling against war; there is
a growing aversion to war. But this is not yet the case
with "risky foreign policies." In the matter of foreign policy,
many things are still as they always were: security through
national or regional power, and occasional provocation if
the other party can be expected to give in out of fear.
It is an attitude which gives insufficient attention to the
concept of "unintentional war."
I N this context I would briefly note that as war
recedes into the background as a result of the
arms situation, world organization and war prohibition, civil
war acquires greater importance. A civil war is often a
limited "war by proxy," in which it is the outsiders who give
an originally purely domestic conflict its international
aspect, and contribute to its prolongation and intensification.
Civil war, too, falls within the scope of the science of war
and peace.
What system of world order would have to be set up
to prevent (total) war?
What are the requirements that would have to be met by
an effective peace policy? What is needed to ensure the
safety of international traffic? It stands to reason that
sacrifices will have to be made for peace, both in the
material and in the spiritual sphere. In the long run
war is inevitable if the gap between rich and poor countries
continues to widen, as it is now doing. Hence the need
for intensive activity to raise the standard of living in
the developing countries. It cannot be denied, however,
that economic changes in these countries will also entail
great social changes, with all the unrest and aggressiveness
that go with them.
It is important to arrive gradually at a clear idea of
the nature of a disarmed world. It goes without saying
that material sacrifices will be necessary. It is easily said
that of course peace has its price. But it is not only a
matter of material "sacrifices." Concessions will also have
to be made in spiritual matters. There will be opposition
to overcome for the very reason that the spiritual climate
in a disarmed world will necessarily differ from the present
climate. This will not tend to make things easier.
The traditional attitude is a facile one which is deter¬
mined only by the views current in one's own circle, which
takes a black-and-white view of' right and wrong accord¬
ing to the views prevalent there, and is prepared to
risk war for what is- felt to be right. A world-wide security
system involves entering into a larger whole, a recog¬
nition of the right of "foreign" views to exist, an atti¬
tude of tolerance towards others, of give-and-take, a willing¬
ness to act reasonably an'd to compromise.
To form an idea of what is needed for maintaining peace
is important also because by so doing we make it clear to
CONT'D ON PAGE 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
THE WHITE BIRD, an etching and aquatint
by the French painter, Georges Braque,
one of 12 works executed
by the artist when he was 80 (in 1962)
for a remarkable art book,
"The Order of Birds".
To accompany the engravings,
the French poet and Nobel
prizewinner, St John Perse,
wrote a poetical meditation on birds, which
he said, "preserve among
us like a very pure echo
something of the song of creation."
Man through his art
BEAUTY AND
THE BEAST
by Pauline Bentley HROUGHOUT every de¬
gree of civilization and
beyond the division of time and envir¬
onment, race or culture, man has al¬
ways known one perennial link of
common experience: his world has
been the dwelling place also of ani¬
mals.
Since his earliest* beginnings he has
used these sharers of his planet to
help him on the long haul of human
progress. They have provided him
with food and warmth and weapons.
He has domesticated them and put
them to work for him in peace and
war; he has used them in his quest
for knowledge and mastery; he has
formed societies to protect and hunt
them, to study and worship them;
there is no facet of his endeavours
whether for sport, magic, sustenance
or learning that has not been affected
by the existence of animals.
During this long and ancient part¬
nership man the artist has also fed
his imagination and sought inspiration
from the same source. He has taken
whatever implement lay to his hand to
depict the animals around him and in
so doing he has interpreted them not
only to himself and us, but left behind
a unique personal testimonial.
"It is the achievements in the visual
arts that have survived," writes Miss
Jacquetta Hawkes, the celebrated
archaeologist, "which brings us the
first insights into the imaginative lives
of our primitive forebears." Miss
Hawkes is writing here on the Palaeo¬
lithic cave paintings in the Dordogne,
France, in the opening chapters of
CONT'D ON PAGE 29
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
k- TK
% 1
,>*,"<
dseuc*
- *
*te
V.v
v
3*ry
&
5®
£v4V
/* #
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
BEAUTY AND THE BEAST (Cont'd)
© Anderson-Glraudon, Paris
METAMORPHOSIS OF THE HORSE
In the evolution from prehistory to civilization, man's relationship with animals has been
completely transformed. The change is easily distinguished In the way man the artist
has depicted his animal subjects, as witness these three horse's head sculptures.
Opposite page, top, The Horse of Commarque, in the Dordogne, France.
Some 13,000 years before the Christian era, a prehistoric artist used the natural indentation
of the rock in a narrow underground gallery to create this wild untamed horse
with sensitive nostrils a horse before Its enslavement to man.
Bottom, the Moon Horse of the Parthenon frieze In Athens, carved In marble
by the 5th century B.C. sculptor, Phidias. Found among the mutilated fragments
of the pediment, and now in the British Museum, it is the head of one of the horses
attached to the chariot of Selene, goddess of the moon. This is a modern,
domesticated animal, completely subjugated by man. Above, head of the bronze
equestrian statue of the Colleoni monument In Venice, carved by Andrea Verrocchio
in the late 15th century. The gentle, almost pensive head shows that this now docile
creature has become a companion to man.
The winged
master
of the airs
"Man and Animal", the third volume
of "Man Through His Art" published
under the sponsorship of the World
Confederation of Organizations of the
Teaching Profession with the financial
help of Unesco.
This book, with short texts by a
group of distinguished scholars from
different countries, and illustrated by
16 colour plates and numerous other
plates and drawings, gives an outline
of animal art throughout the world
from primitive to contemporary times.
"The subject of Man and Animal",
writes Miss Hawkes of the Lascaux
Man and Animal is the third in the
series of a contemplated 15 volume
collection of the Man Through His
Art albums. Already published: Vo¬
lume I, War and Peace; Volume II,
Music. Forthcoming volumes on
Education and Love and Marriage.
The volumes should provide teachers
with a valuable tool for furthering
appreciation of different cultural
values. Orders and inquiries from
the following addresses: U.K. edition:
Educational Productions Ltd., East
Ardsley, Wakefield, Yorkshire; school
ed. 25/-; general ed. 30/-. Cana¬
dian edition: The Queen's Printer,
Ottawa, Ont.; general ed. $8.00;
school ed. $5.00. U.S. edition: New
York Graphic Society, Greenwich,
Conn.; general ed. $7.95; school ed.
$5.75. For Scandinavia: International
Publishing Co., Box 404, Orebro,
Sweden; 45 Kr. PLEASE DO NOT
SEND ORDERS TO UNESCO.
cave paintings, "takes us at one leap
to the beginning of all art. The Paleo¬
lithic tribesman, like all hunters, were
in an ambiguous position in relation to
their animals. They felt a strong emo¬
tion towards them and accepted the
closest kinship with them, yet they had
to kill them. Indeed the marvellous
animal art might be said to be a kind
of propitiary gesture, a wordless state¬
ment of admiration."
This kinship was to be transformed
as man lost his "direct line" to Nature.
The animal dominates prehistoric art
but when man came to organize himself
into settled communities he first subju¬
gated, then domesticated his animals.
This changed relationship can easily
be distinguished in the course of man's
artistic treatment of his animal subject.
It is far cry from the mystical simplicity
of the Lascaux "Horse with Feathered
Darts" to the sophisticated deliberation
of the "wounded lioness" of an Assy¬
rian hunting stone relief of 1000-612
B.C.
The sculptural splendour of the
"Moon Horse" of the Parthenon frieze,
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30
BEAUTY AND THE BEAST (Cont'd)
Imagery
of beliefs
myths and ideals
as discussed by Professor François
Chamoux of the Sorbonne in Paris in
this book, is very distant in every
aspect except as subject matter, from
the Horse of Commarque, a seven foot
long relief made some 13,000 years be¬
fore the Christian era.
Here, an artist largely using the na¬
tural indentation of the rock, created
what Professor Giedion calls "a well-
nigh breathing ¡mage, yet one which
eludes our grasp. A horse which
blooms out of the rock in absolute
freedom, a horse before its enslave¬
ment to man."
Though Greek classicism saw the
apotheosis of man over animal, the
artist continued to draw from the ani¬
mal world his illustrations for his
beliefs and history, his myths and
ideals. Sixth century Chinese wall
paintings in the Tum Huang caves
depict the Buddha legend with ani¬
mals; Coptic weavers of the third to
fifth centuries A.D. used the birds and
fishes of their familiar river Nile as a
theme for decoration. The animal ima¬
gery of the middle ages was both
extraordinarily powerful and full of
humour; the animal in Mexican and
African art has a peculiarly potent
place.
In the 19th century the French paint¬
er, Eugène Delacroix, described in his
diary a visit to the Natural History Mu¬
seum and the Jardin des Plantes in
Paris. "What an immense variety of
animals and species of different shapes
and functions. And at every turn I saw
what we call deformity side by side with
what seems to us to be beauty and
grace of form. Why is it that these
things have stirred me so much? I had
a feeling of happiness as soon as I
entered the place. . . Can it be because
I have gone outside the everyday
thoughts that are my world; away from
the street that is my entire universe?
How necessary it is to stick one's head
out of doors and try to read from the
book of life that has nothing in common
with cities and the works of man. . ."
For now there has arisen what Pro¬
fessor Otto von Simson of Die Frei
Universität, Berlin, in his introduction
to this book calls "the second aliena¬
tion from nature the replacement of
the animal by science, by the machine."
The Importance of the animal to an
artist working in a world where animals
are becoming rarer needs no stressing,
but scientific progress is no indication
that this age-old communion between
man and animal need deteriorate. It
seems significant that the last creature
chosen in the book should be Braque's
"White Bird," that winged master of the
airs whose flight in man's imagination
can bring him within the reaches of
new worlds.
Washington D.C.
THE BEAR TAMER. Bronze statuette from China (5th-4th century B.C.) Since
ancient times the Chinese have been fond of acrobatic
performances by men and animals. Looking at this bear
and Its youthful tamer, we can easily Imagine the delight of an audience at the
dexterity of an animal which can be taught to juggle, walk a tight-rope, ride a rolling sphere
and also, as the statuette shows, balance itself on top of a pole.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
THE ROOTS OF PEACE (Continued from page 26)
ourselves how far we are still removed from what is
vitally necessary.
Yet even when we have ascertained what is necessary,
"necessary for survival," we have still not touched the
question whether the necessary will also be attainable.
Every community and every generation has only a narrow
range of action. Only gradual, small steps can be taken.
This leads to a fourth complex of questions: can the
necessary be made possible? The time available is not
unlimited. There is a certain urgency. The problem is
whether individuals and peoples can be induced by edu¬
cation and other means to make "the necessary" possible.
Is the "human way" of change through reason and common
sense possible? Man is also "irrational man," who in his
opinions and actions is primarily swayed by instinct,
emotion and tradition. Reason, especially in the human
group, has but little influence, and the influence of what
is emotionally felt, direct, and immediate, dominates. It
has been said that if one wishes to influence the masses,
one cannot afford to fly in the face of the "basic attitudes"
of nationalism, or freedom, or of security sought through
power.
The prevalent pattern of international relations is a
pattern of distrust and fear. Can this possibly be changed?
Certain fundamental human attitudes "have become so
much a part of the mind, and lie so far back, that (men)
are never really conscious of them at all. They do not see
them, but other things through them." The important ques¬
tion is how far ways can be found to make individuals and
peoples prepared to accept what the "long-term interest"
of ensuring peace demands.
This ends our brief survey of some questions which
determine peace research. To answer them thorough
scientific investigation is required in which almost all
scientific disciplines must be involved. Close co-operation
between these various disciplines will be indispensable.
The problem is a social one, one of individuals and
groups, and of contacts between individuals and groups.
In such an investigation the starting-point will have to be
the present situation, as a product of historical evolution,
hardened and intensified by the ideas and interests rooted
in it. The historical evolution of each group, which distin¬
guishes it from other groups through the deep-seated
memory of shared joys and sufferings, makes it desirable
that peace research should primarily be cultivated in each
individual political collectivity. Each collectivity has its
characteristic peculiarities and idiosyncrasies, each collec¬
tivity may have its own ways and possibilities of change.
EACE research in each state is important also
because there is a tendency towards spiritual
insulation on certain points, to protect the national pattern
of thought.
Peace research in each country will be able to help
counteract this nationalization of truth. Research in the
social sciences will recognize such nationalization as a
fact, but may through this very recognition be able to
prevent its worst excesses.
There is another important aspect. If it is true that our
world is not organized in such a way as to be equal to
the dangers that technological evolution has brought about,
then it is imperative that changes should take place.
That this is so is beyond doubt, although for the moment
we can leave aside the question of what these changes
would have to encompass. There is a predominant school
of thought which maintains that these changes will have
to run on lines of general and complete disarmament, and
the ensuring of security through world organization.
This means that the changes will have to be realized
everywhere. Security cannot be achieved by unilateral
measures, of whatever kind, but only through combined
efforts and concerted action. Changes at home will only
be possible as adequate steps are taken elsewhere,
prompted by a recognition of common long-term interests.
Now if it is true that for the realization of the changes
required for lasting peace scientific research is indispen¬
sable, then it is essential that such research should be
carried out everywhere. If peace research is to be effec¬
tive, the understanding it provides will have to become
public property everywhere. This will be promoted by the
existence of peace research institutes in every country.
v^h E have here a consequence of interdependence,
which is even more evident than that which led
to the establishment of the International Labour Office.
Improvements in the social conditions of the labouring class
could not be effected nationally without simultaneous
implementation elsewhere. Hence the attempt at inter¬
nationalization of labour legislation in 1919. International
security through disarmament can naturally only be attained
if the pattern of security through national armament is
universally abandoned, and appropriate measures are
universally accepted.
The first requirement, therefore, is that peace research
should be cultivated in all countries and nations: peace
research which can then start from the pecularities of
each, historically conditioned, national situation; peace
research which can express itself in the specific national
pattern of thought, enjoy national confidence, and thus
influence national patterns of thought.
The possibility cannot be ruled out, however, that the
nationalization of truth will also set its mark on nationally-
conducted peace research. Here is a first special reason
for the desirability of international contact and co-operation
in the science of war and peace.
Another special reason is that peace research deals
with matters which affect the whole world, so that it is
important to be informed of "the situation" everywhere..
It is only through the co-operation of scholars that an
understanding may grow of what is thought and felt in
various parts of the world, and of what in a concerted
effort to effect changes represents action possibilities.
In addition to these special reasons for international
scientific co-operation there are the general reasons of
mutual stimulation and supplementation favourable results
of which in different fields we can daily see before us.
The need for international contact and co-operation has
led to the establishment of the International Peace Research
Association. The Association aims to make a substantial
contribution to world and international peace research in
order to promote world order, peace and security. This will
be possible if many are prepared to lend their active
support.
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
LAKE BAIKAL POLLUTION
Sir,
Lake Baikal, as you are certainly
aware, is a body of water with unique
qualities. It contains one tenth of the
total volume of our planet's reserves
of fresh water, and its signifiance, for
science and for the future of man
alike, is immense. Two other unique
features of the lake are the physical
and chemical qualities of its water
and its fauna which comprises over
100 species. Thus it can be consi¬
dered as part of man's heritage from
nature. But a threat hangs over Lake
Baikal its possible pollution by in¬
dustrial waste waters from the pro¬
jected pulp and cardboard works at
Baikaisk and Selenga that are being
built despite protests from scientific
circles in the Soviet Union. Several
Soviet newspapers have campaigned
to warn against the danger of this
pollution which could happen within
30 years, thus destroying this pearl
of nature together with its fauna.
Means must be found to prevent this
senseless act.
Vladimir V. Eichwald
P. Lavachov
Tallinn, U.S.S.R
Ed note : According to recent Soviet
press reports the Lake Baikal area
is to become a huge national park
administered by a special body to
supervise the use of its immense na¬
tural resources while developing it
as a holiday and tourist centre. Spe¬
cial precautions would be taken
against possible pollution by indus¬
trial wastes. Two plans are being
discussed, one for a park with an
area of nearly 5,000 square miles
(13,000 sq. kms.) and another for a
park nearly three times as large.
YOUTH WITH A PURPOSE
Sir,
In the July-August 1965 Issue on
youth your staff has come up with
another unique journalistic success,
not so much dependent on the pic¬
tures or the prose or the lay-out,
but on the humanity of the whole.
Some particular gems of information
and understanding are the facts given
about Unesco clubs, the art essay,
with its colour pages, much of the
part on science, the fascinating essay
from the Soviet Union, and naturally
the concentration on the developing
countries. Something which the whole
panorama seems to have in common
is its rejection of any limitations on
man.
Kevin Henly
Clinton, Ontario, Canada
Sir,
I wish to say how glad I was to see
the issue on youth. I was interested
in the articles published in 1964 on
Juvenile Delinquency but could not
help wondering at the time why
doesn't someone write about the
normal youth ?
These are the people who will be
running the world for the next thirty
years or so and they will run it well I
Harry Torr
Canberra, Australia
INTERNATIONAL
CO-OPERATION IN UTRECHT
Sir,
The dual celebration of the 20th
anniversary of the United Nations and
U.N. International Co-operation Year
in 1965 was marked in Utrecht (Ne¬
therlands) by a huge illuminated sign
on the wall of the city's Industries
Fair Bulding (see photo below). The
sign (14 metres by 36; 46 ft. by 115)
was placed there on the initiative of
the Unesco Committee at Utrecht.
Fifteen thousand electric bulbs were
used to compose a scene showing the
clasped hands symbol of International
Co-operation Year surrounded by chil¬
dren of different lands. The bulbs
were arranged against a colourful
blackground so that passers-by were
also given a impression of the picture
in the daytime.
F.H. Tunnissen
Director
Unesco Centrum Nederland
Amsterdam
32
THE REVOLUTION IN BOOKS
Sir,
Congratulations on devoting your
September 1965 issue to today's
revolution in books. After reading
about Unesco's latest guide to world
translations (Index Translationum) I
wish to pass on some figures con¬
cerning Bible translations as given in
the September 1965 issue of Ecclesia.
According to this review: "In 1964,
sixteen new languages were added
to those in which at least one com¬
plete book of the scriptures has been
translated. Ten of these new lan¬
guages are spoken by South Ame¬
rican Indian tribes, four by African
peoples and two by Asian. The
complete Bible now exists in 235 lan¬
guages; the New Testament In 290
and a gospel or another complete
book of the scriptures in 707 lan¬
guages 1,232 languages.
In 1964, the world distribution of the
scriptures by bible societies (in millions
of copies) was as follows: Bibles 4;
New Testaments 4; Gospels 30; Se¬
lections 32 a total of 70 million
copies.
Abbé Jean-François Pinard
Charleville, France
KORZYBSKI & MARY EDDY
Sir.
As a professional linguist, I have
throughout the years noted many mis¬
translations, some of them rather
startling. But never have I come
across such a fantastic, unbelievable
whopper as in Prof. Zvegintsev's letter
in your issue of September 1965.
I have not seen your Russian edi¬
tion, but I presume that Prof. Zvegint-
sev wrote in Russian. Accordingly
the error must be attributed to your
translator.
To confuse "Science and Sanity"
by Alfred Korzybski (note the correct
spelling of his name) with "Science
and Health" by Mary B. Eddy Is a
monumental blunder. Both Korzybski
and Mrs. Eddy must be whirling in
their graves.
William A. Coates
University of Rochester
U.S.A.
NATURAL GESTURE
Sir,
I was very touched by the letter
In your December issue from a Viet
Nam reader who deprived himself of
breakfasts in order to subscribe to
a magazine which has so much to
offer him culturally. I am a school¬
girl, aged 17, and 1 realize what
knowledge costs. So I should like
to send him some reading material
on science of the kind he would find
useful.
I know what the position Is like In
Viet Nam today and how difficult
things are for students because of
the political Instability. I hope I shall
not be the only one to make this,
in my view, natural "gesture."
Catherine Collet
Geneva, Switzerland
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
Nobel Peace Prize
for Unicef
On December 10 Human Rights Day
the United Nations Children's Fund rec¬
eived the Nobel Peace Prize for 1965, an
award made in recognition of UniceFs work
for the world's children. Since it began
with emergency relief work for children in
war-stricken countries in 1946, Unicef has
extended its activities to include all depriv¬
ed children, especially in the developing
countries of Africa, Asia and Latin America.
Today, 571 assistance projects are operat¬
ing in 118 nations. Since 1961, when Unicef
decided to extend its aid to education, joint
Unicef-Unesco projects have been started
in 55 countries. They run from the educa¬
tion of handicapped children to community
development schemes, and from textbook
publishing to teacher training.
Unesco books reprinted
in 35 languages
Hundreds of books published by
Unesco have been reprinted by commercial
publishers throughout the world. In the
last quarter of 1965 alone, 90 Unesco books
were being reprinted in 35 languages.
Early publication of 70 more titles is fore¬
seen. Two main types of books are being
reproduced: Unesco publications dealing
with education, science, social sciences,
cultural activities and mass communica¬
tion; prose and poetry classics of different
nations, including folk tales and antholo¬
gies which Unesco translates and distribu¬
tes to make them better known in other
countries. Most translated book to date is
Unesco's "Source Book for Science Teach¬
ing", a "do-it yourself" science book which
explains how to do simple experiments with
"home-made" equipment; it has already
been published in some 30 languages.
Asia's educators look ahead
Educators from 15 Asian countries and
the Soviet Union reviewed problems of
Asia's future educational growth at the
recent conference convened in Bangkok by
Unesco and the United Nations Economic
Commission for Asia and the Far East.
Discussions brought out the need to work
for a balanced educational growth at all
levels, to expand technical education and
launch literacy campaigns, to keep in view
the varying levels of educational develop¬
ment In Asian countries and to bring edu¬
cational development into the economic and
social planning of each country. Delegates
recommended the introduction of an ex¬
panded programme of science teaching at
all levels.
Pollution problems
of Europe's rivers
The Rhine waters upstream from Lake
Constance contain only 30 to 100 microbes
per cubic centimetre, but the bacterial
count is between 100,000 and 200,000
where the Rhine reaches the sea. Above
Paris the Seine contains only 15 pathogenic
organisms per cubic centimetre; down¬
stream the figure is roughly 1,500,000.
These figures are taken from a report re¬
cently presented to the Council of Europe.
The Council plans to set up a convention
to fight water pollution and also to publish
a Water Charter to publicize the problem.
Economic effects
of disarmament
"The Economic Effects of Disarmament",
a detailed study of the effect of disarma¬
ment on the British economy, first published
in 1963, is now available in a special paper¬
back edition, price 12/6. Published by The
Economist Intelligence Unit, 27 St. James
Place, London S.W.1., the study shows
the types of industrial capacity and man¬
power which are now absorbed by defence,
the policies needed- for their conversion,
and the type of peaceful expenditure that
might replace military expenditure.
Versatile isotopes
Jobs now being done by radioisotope
instruments range from sorting the mail to
helping in the salvage of the Abu Simbel
temples in Nubia. A recent symposium of
the International Atomic Energy Agency
held in Warsaw was told that in France zinc
is added to the paper used for making
stamps so that X-rays can detect the
stamp's position on a letter. This enables
the first phase of mail sorting straighten¬
ing out envelopes and turning them face
up to be done at the rate of 400,000 let¬
ters an hour. At Abu Simbel, isotopes
trace the injection of resin as a reinforce¬
ment into the rock walls of the temples
before they are cut into blocks for remo¬
val. When the injected resin approaches
the surface of the rock to the point where
it might mar it, isotopes sound a warning.
Stop using the sea
as a junk yard and sewer
Man can no longer consider the sea as
a convenient and apparently limitless com¬
bination of junkyard and sewer. If this pro¬
cess continues, unplanned and uncontrolled,
man may pollute and destroy large areas
of the sea and its resources just as he has
polluted and destroyed (and. Domestic
sewage is rapidly broken down by micro¬
organisms in the sea, but crude oil, radio¬
active wastes, heavy metals and chlorinat¬
ed hydrocarbons used as insecticides are
not disposed of by biological processes.
DDT has been found in tunny fish caught
400 miles offshore and other pesticides
in penguins in the Antarctic. This warn¬
ing against pollution was given by the
Unesco-sponsored Intergovernmental Océa¬
nographie Commission at its recent meeting
in Paris. The Commission urged its 50 mem-
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
BOOKSHELF
UNESCO TRANSLATIONS OF THE
LITERATURE OF ASIA
Books Jisted below have been
accepted in the Asian Literature
Translations Series of Unesco. They
are recommended as highly readable
and representative of the literature
of the country of origin.
Poems of the Late T'ang.
An anthology of seven Chinese poets
of the 8th and 9th centuries A.D.
Penguin Books, U.K., U.S.A., Aus¬
tralia (4/-).
Letters of a Javanese Princess.
Writings of Raden Adjeng Kartini
who became an Indonesian national
heroine. W.W. Norton & Co., New
York ($1.95).
Su Tung-P'o.
Selections from the greatest poet
of China's Sung dynasty (960-1279).
Columbia University Press, London
& New York ($3.75).
Kavitavali.
A dramatic poem by the most famous
medieval Hindi poet, Tulsi Das.
George Allen and Unwin Ltd., Lon¬
don (32/-).
| The Woman in the Dunes.
The Japanese novel by Kobo Abé
which won the Yomiuri Prize for li¬
terature in 1960, and from which a
successful film was made. Alfred
A. Knopf, New York ($4.95); Seeker
and Warburg, London (21/-).
Flowers In the Mirror.
By Li Ju-Chen. A 19th century
Chinese classic a combination of
historical romance, fairy tale and
Chinese Gulliver's travels. Peter
Owen, London (35/-); University of
California Press, U.S.A. (in press).
The Manyoshu.
A remarkable anthology of 1 ,000
poems from 7th and 8th cent. Japan.
Columbia University Press, New
York and London ($12.50).
An Anthology of Sanskrit Court
Poetry.
An 11th century anthology of
Sanskrit verse in a superb transla¬
tion. Harvard University Press,
U.S.A. ($15.00); distributed in the
U.K. by Oxford Univ. Press, London.
All the above titles can be ordered
from your local bookseller or from
the publishers. In the U.S., the
Unesco Publications Center, 317,
East 34th Street, New York, can
supply all volumes.
THE U.N. STORY
The Quest for Peace.
A series of 24 Dag Hammarskjold
Memorial Lectures edited by Andrew
W. Cordier and Wilder Foote.
Columbia University Press, New
York and London ($7.95).
Toward World Peace.
Speeches and Public Statements
1957-1963 by U Thant.
Thomas Yoseloff, New York and
London ($7.50; 50/-).
Planning for the Needs of Chil¬
dren In the Developing Countries.
The United Nations Children's Fund.
(Hard-cover, $3.95; soft-cover, $1.95.)
Telling the U.N. Story.
By Leonard S. Kenworthy. New
approaches to teaching about the
United Nations and its agencies.
Unesco, Paris-Oceana Publications
Inc., Dobbs Ferry, New York ($2.00).
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
ber countries "to intensify their investi¬
gations of marine pollution in all its
"aspects", and set up a special group to
examine ways of furthering national and
international studies of océanographie pro¬
cesses affecting pollution.
Dynamic museum
The Neuchâtel Museum of Ethnography
in Switzerland often seems to be doing its
best to look as little like a museum as pos¬
sible. At its recent exhibition of "The
World's Children at Play", the visitor's eye
was greeted by 1,000 feet of wall space
where children had painted their own choice
of subjects on this theme, and his ear
by recordings of children playing street
games. The museum uses walls, furniture
and light to create an atmosphere that ena¬
bles visitors to see beyond the exhibits and
the bounds of this ultra-modern museum
building. Unesco's quarterly, "Museum",
devoted an entire issue (Vol.XVIII, No 1,
1965; $2.00, 10/-stg) to the Neuchâtel
Museum, which celebrated its tenth anni¬
versary in November 1965.
Balkan soil studies
A group of 15 soil scientists recently
made a study tour of five Balkan countries,
under the sponsorship of FAO, the United
Nations and Unesco, to exchange informa¬
tion on the classification and land use of
the major soil groups in Thrace (Turkey),
Bulgaria, southern Rumania, eastern Yugo¬
slavia and eastern Greece. Similar study
tours have been made in the U.S.S.R.,
Brazil, Rumania, Mexico, Japan and India to
collect information for the Soil Map of the
World Project being carried out by FAO
and Unesco.
34
Flashes...
A cheque for $250,000. the entry receipts
of an exhibition on "5,000 years of Egyptian
art", held in Tokyo, has been given to the
U.A.R. Government for the Unesco trust
fund financing the dismantling and transfer
of the Abu Simbel temples in Nubia.
Speedier and more accurate warnings
of the Pacific Ocean's devastating tsunamis
seismic sea waves, wrongly known as
"tidal waves" are the aim of an Interna¬
tional Tsunami Warning Centre at Honolulu
set up by the Intergovernmental Océano¬
graphie Commission.
To help meet the world's need for more
man-made forests, the developing countries
have already planted some 4.5 million hec¬
tares (1 1 million acres) of new forests,
reports FAO.
Today Latin America has only about
100,000 practicing physicians less than
half the number it actually needs, accord¬
ing to WHO. By J 980 the continent will
need 350,000 doctors.
Under an agreement between Jordan and
the World Food Programme, food aid worth
nearly $117,000 will be provided for
some of Jordan's schools and community
development centres this year.
THE INNER NATURE OF SCIENCE
by Warren Weaver
The Kalinga Prize for the Popularization of Science was awarded
by Unesco in 1965 to Dr. Warren Weaver of the United States.
Dr. Weaver, a distinguished science writer, science consultant and
a former president of the American Association for the Advance¬
ment of Science, was presented with his award by the Director-
General of Unesco at a ceremony in Unesco House on October 14.
In his address, Dr. Weaver discussed four aspects of the problem
of the interpretation and diffusion of science: the importance of
science, the difficulty of interpreting science, the special need
today for this interpretation, and why the interpretation by the
science writer, however difficult it may be, "must be carried for¬
ward continuously, interestingly but never trivially, accurately but
clearly, humbly yet enthusiastically, ardently yet patiently." In
his conclusion, Dr. Weaver declared:
I o live, in the modern world,
without some reasonable knowledge
of science Is to be critically handi¬
capped in any attempt to understand
many of the major forces which are
shaping our present society. It Is to
have all the senses dulled, and not
only dulled to what is going on In the
world but to be dulled to the beauty
and to the spiritual significance of
science, unaware of the incredible but
lovely way in which our universe Is
put together, unconscious of the Ins¬
piring unity which binds together all
life and all that Is at the moment
not alive, uninspired by the vision of
man's new capacities to control his
environment and to liberate himself for
new and more noble destinies.
"It ¡s a sad pity that so many per¬
sons think of science exclusively In
terms of the hardware the devices
that It makes possible. It Is unfortu¬
nate that those with a slightly clearer
vision see science chiefly as the heal¬
er and the feeder. In the long run
it will, however, be worst of all If
men cannot be made to understand
the essential inner nature of science.
"There are some so misled as to
view science as a sort of mechanical
monster, grinding ever forward, pro¬
ducing terrible engines of destruction,
forcing everything into dull conformity
with inexorable and soulless logic,
reducing everything to baffling but all-
powerful equations.
"To correct those false views I view
to be a major duty of those who in¬
terpret science to the public. For
those false views separate science
from the rest of life.
"From the time of Roger Bacon there
have been those who consider that
the business of science is simply to
collect a lot of "facts" (hard facts,
we often say, implying necessary per¬
manency, accuracy and objectivity)
and then construct a theory to explain
them. That theory then Is true ; and
all must bow before it.
"But we now fully recognize what
we should always have realized first
that we obtain so-called facts only
through observation, and that the
observer is himself an essential part
of the fact system, thus at one stroke
destroying both ultimate precision and
ultimate objectivity; and second, we
know that elements of choice, presup¬
positions which have neither a factual
nor a logical analytical basis but do
have both a personal and a cultural
basis, enter into the structure of all
theories and into the selection of the
group of facts to be dealt with.
"That our scientific knowledge pro¬
gresses by unjustified (and unjustifia¬
ble) anticipations, by guesses, by ten¬
tative solutions to our problems, by
conjectures and that these conjectures,
although they are controlled and refin¬
ed by criticism, can never be posi¬
tively justified is a viewpoint massively
and convincingly defended by the
great logician and philosopher Karl R.
Popper. Science proceeds, Popper
says, not by proving that certain
statements are correct, but rather by
showing that certain statements are
Incorrect. If this explodes the myth,
apparently comforting to some but
basically frightening, that science Is
the austere custodian of unassailable
truth, note that at the same time It
forces science to join hands with all
other human endeavours for we all
learn by our mistakes.
"You must not misunderstand why I
have made these comments about the
essential nature of science. I have
not done so to detract In any way
from the practical value of science,
nor to depreciate the magnificent
successes of science. But these very
successes, when viewed superficially
and when over-valued as they can so
easily be, tend to separate science
from the rest of men's lives. Where¬
as the great need, as science marches
forward, Is to assure that science
be merged Into a mutually advanta¬
geous companionship with all of the
humane arts, with philosophy and
with religion."
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
THE RACE QUESTION IN MODERN SCIENCE
Of all school subjects, geography is perhaps the
best suited to promote mutual understanding
between peoples. Geography can show not
only how peoples have lived and are living, but
also what they have contributed to the common
heritage of mankind. Unesco's aim in publish¬
ing this book is to aid and guide all who teach
or study in the world's schools. Practical
advice is given on how to improve teaching
methods and provide the proper materials for
effective geography teaching at primary and
secondary levels.
A Longmans-Unesco co-edition
Cloth : 21/- $4.50 15 F
254 pages Paper : 16/- $3.50 11.50 F
The race qmumn is
RACE
MIXTURE
by Hairy L. Shapiro
The m quest« la . f
nodsnt ttknee "Í
RACIAL
MYTHS
by Jva.Com«
i Unesco
The ne* quo! ion «
RACE
AND
PSYCHOLOGY
tj ÖtiJ Klmebtrj
Unesco
Reprints of six booklets in this best-selling series
Price per copy: 3/6; $0.60; 2.50 F
WHERE TO RENEW YOUR SUBSCRIPTION
and order other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment Is
made in the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzai, Prest Department, Royal'
Aghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Tradco Agencies, 1 09 Swanston Street, G. P. O.
Box 2324 V, Melbourne C. I. (Victoria); United
Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
8th Floor, McEwan House, 343 Little Collins St.,
Melbourne C. I. (Victoria). (22/6). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C*., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Seh. 70.-). BELGIUM. All publications : Editions
342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-
Boek-handel, Belgielei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (140 FB) and art slides only; Louis De Lannoy,
112, rue du Trône, Brussels S. CCP 3380.00. BURMA.
Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road, Rangoon.
(	). CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa, Ont.
(8 3.00). CEYLON. Lake House Bookshop, Sir
Chittampalan Gardiner Mawata, P.O.B. 244, Colombo,
2.(Rs. 13/50). CHINA. World Book CoLtd., 99 Chung¬
king South Rd., Section I.Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa).
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3 rd Avenue, P.O.
Box 1722, Nicosia. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L.,
Spalena 51 , Prague 1 (permanent display) ; Zahrahnici lite¬
ratura Bilkova 4, Prague 1. DENMARK. Ejnar Munks-
gaard, Prags Boulevard 47, Copenhagen S (D. Kr."17).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agency. P.O. Box 120,
Addis Ababa (10/-). FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirja-
kauppa. 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (Fmk. 9.40). FRANCE.
Librairie de I'Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7". C.C.P.
12598-48.. (10 F.). GERMANY. All publications:
R. Oldenbourg Verlag, Rosenheimerstrasse 145, Munich.
8. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed only) Bahren-
felder-Chaussee 160, Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, C.C.P.
2766S0 (DM 10). GHANA Methodist Book Depot
Ltd. Atlantis House Commercial St., POB 100, Cape
Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28, rue du Stade,
Athens. HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 64,
Nathan Road. Kowloon. HUNGARY. Kultura,
P. O. Box 149. Budapest, 62. ICELAND. Snaebjörn
Jonsson & Co. H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
(120 Kr.) INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd. Nicol
Road, Bellard Estate, Bombay 1 ; 1 7 Chittaranjan Avenue
Calcutta 1 3 ; Gunfoundry Road, Hyberabad, 1 ; 3 6a, Mount
Road, Madras 2; Kanson House, 1/24 Asaf Ali Road, P.O.
Box 386, New Delhi, 1 ; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book &
Stationery Co., 1 7 Park Street, Calcutta 1 6, Scindia
House, New Delhi, Indian National Commission Co-ope¬
ration with Unesco, Ministry of Education, for New Delhi 3.
(Rs.7). IN DONESIA. P.T.N. " Permuta-Nusantara " c/o
Dept.of Commerce, 22,DjalanNusantara,Diakarta. IRAQ.
Mackenzie'sBookshop.Baghdad.IRELAND.The National
Press. 2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. 4.(15/5).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores 35, Allenby Road
and 48, Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv (l£8).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour Street,
Kingston. (1 5/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O.Box 605 Tokyo Central, Tokyo
(1,200 yen). JORDAN. Joseph L. BahousS Co., Dar ut-
Kutub, Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman. KENYA. E.S.A.
Bookshop, P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi (1 0/-). KOREA.
Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Cen¬
tral 64, Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops
Ltd.. P.O. Box 286. Monrovia (10/-). LUXEM¬
BURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue, Luxemburg
(F.L. 1 40). MALAYSIA. Federal Publications Ltd.,Times
House, RiverValley Rd., Singapore, 9; Pudu Building (3 rd
floor). 110, Jalan Pudu, Kuala Lumpur (M. $ 7.50).
MALTA. Sapienza's Library 26 Kingsway, Valletta,
(15/-). Nalanda Company Ltd., 30,
Bourbon Street, Port-Louis (1 5/-). MONACO. British
Library 30, Bid des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (F. 10).
NETHERLANDS. N. V. Martinus Nühoff, Lange
Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl. 8.50). NETHERLANDS
WEST INDIES. G. C. T. Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.)
N.V, Willemstad. Curaçao. N.A. (NA fl 4,50). NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office 20, Molesworth
Street (Private Bag) Wellingston, C. 1 Government Books
hops: Auckland (P.O. Box 5344), Christchurch (P.O. Box
1721), Dunedin P.O. Box 1104)(15/-). NIGERIA.
C.M.S. Bookshops, P.O. Box 174, Lagos (10/-).
NORWAY. All publications : A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille
Grensen 7, Oslo. For the Unesco Courier also: A.S- Nar-
vesens Litteratur Tjeneste, Stortingsgt. 2 Oslo, Postboks
115 (17.50 kr.). - PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Pu¬
blishing Co. Ltd., Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box
374 56-N Gulberg Industrial Colony, Lahore. PHILI¬
PINES. The Modern Book Co., 508 Rizal Avenue Manila.
POLAND. "RUCH", ul. Wronia, 23, Warsaw 10
(zl. 60). PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Lda. Livraria
Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon	 PUERTO RICO,
Spanish English Publications, Eleanor Roosevelt 115,
Apartado 1912, Hato Rey. RHODESIA. The Book
Centre, and Educational Supply Co., Colonial* Mutual
Building, Salisbury. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop,
P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. SWEDEN. All publi¬
cations : A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel,
Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 16. For the Unesco
Courier: Svenska UnescorSdet, Vasagatan 15-'17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 12); SWITZERLAND. All publications :
Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse Zurich. Payot, rue Grenus 6,
121 I.Geneva 11, C.C.P. 1-236. "Courier" only: Georges
Losmaz, 1, rue des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. C.C.P.
1-4811. (Fr. S. 10). - TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND.
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue. Bangkok.
(35 ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul	 UGANDA. Uganda Book¬
shop, P.O. Box 1 45, Kampala (1 0/-). REPUBLIC OF
SOUTH AFRICA All publications : Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Libri Building, Church Street, P.O. Box 724 Pre¬
toria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Cen¬
tral News Agency P.O. Box 1033, Johannesbourg. (R1.-
50). UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT). Librai¬
rie Kasr El Nil, 38, rue Kasr El Nil, Cairo. Sub/agent:
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 St. Adly-Pasha. Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I, and Government Bookshops
in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester.
Birmingham and Bristol. (15/-). UNITED STATES,
Unesco Publications Center, 317 East 34th St, New York,
N.Y. 1 001 6 ($ 5.00) - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Mocow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Kn-
jig, Tzrazije 27, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
lVO
SKIING
il
A RADIO
TELESCOPE
Wearing water skis
to distribute
his weight evenly,
a worker crosses
the vast steel
"mesh reflector of
the world's largest
radio and radar
telescope near
Arecibo,
Puerto Rico.
Suspended 500 ft.
(150 metres)
above him is the
huge focusing
device which transmits
radio waves to
the mesh, which
then reflects them
as a beam
into outer space
(see page 8).
© Günther l.l.N.
Holmes-Lebel
]]>
</page>
</document>
