<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="040945eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
I
A window
open on the world
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
:'*p¿
(3
©
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
Syria
Ivory portrait
This finely carved head of a
prince or princess was
unearthed in the ruins of the
ancient city of Ugarit on the
Mediterranean coast of
northern Syria, where it was
produced in the 13th century
BC. Ugarit, whose
flourishing art included
steles, metal statuary and
repoussé work as well as
ivory carvings, owed its
prosperity to international
trade, notably with Egypt.
The Pharaohs exported
much ivory obtained from
the Sudan to the Syrian
coastal towns, whose
craftsmen were strongly
influenced by Egyptian
models. The head (15 cm
high) capped by a tiara is
preserved in Syria's National
Museum at Damascus.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco CY)UFÍCF
JANUARY 1980 33rd YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 20 LANGUAGES
English Italian Turkish
French Hindi Urdu
Spanish Tamil Catalan
Russian Hebrew Malaysian
German Persian Korean
Arabic Dutch Swahili
Japanese Portuguese
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 35 French Francs
2 years: 58 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 29 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in
August and September when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year). For list of distributors see inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R.
Microcard Edition, Indian Head. Inc., 111 West 40th
Street, New York. U.S.A.; (3) Bell and Howell Co., Old
Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in the Readers'
Guide to Periodical Literature, published by H.W. Wilson
Co., New York, and in Current Contents - Education,
Philadelphia. U.S.A.
Editorial Office
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris - France
Editor-in-chief: Jean Gaudin
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English Edition: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Russian Edition: Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
German Edition: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Arabic Edition: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Italian Edition: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Hindi Edition: H.L. Sharma (Delhi)
Tamil Edition: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew Edition: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian Edition: Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
Dutch Edition: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese Edition: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish Edition: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu Edition: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan Edition: Cristian Rahola (Barcelona),
Malaysian Edition: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean Edition: Lim Moun-young (Seoul)
Swahili Edition: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salaam)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy'Malkin
French Edition: Djamel Benstaali
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Philippe Gentil
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
page
4 THE GAMES PEOPLES PLAY
6 WHAT IS PLAY?
9 AUSTRALIAN BARK PAINTINGS
The aborigine artists of Arnhem Land
by Kare/ Kupka
15 PALLADIO
Master-builder of the Italian Renaissance
by Renato Cevese
25 TO THE NORTH POLE ON SKIS
by Dmitri I. Shparo
29 VALCAMONICA
In an Italian valley, the world's largest gallery
of prehistoric rock art
by Emmanuel Anati
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
SYRIA: Ivory portrait
l-IV NEWS FROM UNESCO
SPECIAL SUPPLEMENT
Cover
Tree bark forms the canvas on which
Australian aborigine artists paint scenes
from the real world of daily life and the
magical world of good and evil spirits. The
bark painting on our cover portrays a female
maam, or evil spirit. It was painted in 1963,
oh Croker Island, by the artist Namatbara
(see article page 9). Other themes in this
issue include: play as a form of social and
psychological expression; the work of the
great Italian architect Palladio.who died four
centuries ago this year; the first expedition
to the North Pole on skis; and, the amazing
rock art of the Camonica Valley Italy.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Carved from the trunk of a carefully selected and prepared red cedar tree, this totem-pole
is a typical example of the art of the coastal Indians of British Columbia, Canada. The
erection of a totem-pole was the occasion for a festive ceremony known as a potlatch. An
important potlatch could take years to organize. Guests were invited from far and wide
and gifts of all kinds were prepared for each of them. The festivities themselves
sometimes lasted several weeks. During the ceremony, the person erecting the totem-pole
would make a speech in which he would proclaim his right to the various emblems carved
on the pole. The guests would make speeches in reply. This would be followed by
dancing, the distribution of gifts, games and feasting.
This article and the box on pages 6 and 7 are
based on extracts from a recently published
L/nesco study on Children and Play, Theoretical
Approaches and Teaching Applications. Specia¬
lists from a number of countries collaborated in
the preparation of the study. The first part, from
which our extracts are taken, was written by
Juliette Raabe, of France, who also directed the
preparation of the study as a whole.
Photo © Chantai Lombard, Pans
The
ALTHOUGH the development of the
child and children's games and the
overall need for play can be seen as
a universal fact, play activities are none the
less profoundly rooted in each individual
people, whose cultural identity can be
discerned through the games and toys it has
invented.
In retracing the basic stages in the
psychological development of the child as
manifested through his games, one is aware
time and again of close dependence on the
environment; play is directly linked to the
social context.
The mother's presence or premature
absence, the family structure, the living and
housing conditions, the environment and
means of subsistence all have a direct bear¬
ing on play activities, which cannot develop
when children live in conditions that are too
unfavourable.
For play cannot occur just anywhere,
anytime, or anyhow. It comes about in an
environment which, without being
altogether committed, is prepared to pro¬
vide a dynamic setting that we may call a
play context. Such a context is made up of
the following components: (a) the actual
space, qualified by its dimensions and con¬
tent; (b) the individual with his experiences,
resources and aspirations; (c) pressure from
outside; and (d) adaptability to change.
Thus it may be said that for an infant up to
the age of one year, the play context is
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Left, two African girls play at pounding millet, using
makeshift utensils and make-believe millet. By
converting what for the adult is a daily chore into an
imitative game they are unconsciously preparing
themselves for a task that will be theirs later in life.
~ Disquieting if not macabre, the photo right is a reminder
of a phenomenon which, lamentably, is becoming more
and more evident: the proliferation of toys of a military,
warlike nature. From their earliest years many children
handle toys which, in one way or another, encourage
warlike attitudes and tendencies. In Sweden, the
praiseworthy principle has been adopted "not to produce,
import or sell toys, games or military dressing-up kits
relating to wars later than 1914".
games peoples play
defined spatially by his crib, rush mat, his
pram or his mother's back, the sides of his
cot, his mattress, sheets and blankets, his
mother's garment, as well as her body and
his own.
One can therefore speak in terms of a
specific play context shaped by society both
in the strictly spatial sense and in the tem¬
poral sense. According to whether the
society he lives in is rural or urban, industrial
or still developing, the child will either have
the run of a virtually limitless expanse of
fields, woodland or bush to roam about in,
or will be cooped up in an over-populated,
hyper-rationalized environment in which he
cannot come by the smallest portion of
"free" space to call his own.
In industrial-type countries, even when
people are adequately housed, it is not un¬
common to find parents labouring under the
delusion that they are giving their children a
better chance to play by cluttering up their
rooms with furniture and complicated,
stereotyped objects which mean nothing to
the child and result only in inhibiting more or
less completely their play capacity.
From the temporal standpoint, a wide
variety of conditions can lead to situations
objectively detrimental to play. Some
children left entirely to their own devices,
lose their ability to play, as is also the case
with those who are caught up in the
vicious circle of day-to-day chores-
helping adults in their tasks or under
pressure from schoolwork and do not have
even a few spare moments a day to them¬
selves.
The attitude of adults to children's play,
reflecting ideological patterns, is also
decisive. Hostile or indifferent, or again
possessive, adults can annihilate the child's
play opportunities as much by rejecting
them as by appropriating them or turning
them to their own advantage. The child is
well and truly turned into an object and
becomes no more than a toy in the hands of
the adults, who use him to act out their own
psychological problems or the system of
values to which they are attached.
As for toys, especially when they are
bought, they are part of a whole system of
implications inherent in the act of giving.
Certain ritualistic practices connected with
offering gifts, such as the potlatch, the
ceremonial distribution of gifts during the
winter festival, formerly practised by the In¬
dians of British Columbia, implicitly brought
an idea of challenge into the play structure.
Giving Christmas or New Year presents, a
common practice in the Western world, is a
chance for parents to lavish on their sons or
daughters an attention that does not always
find expression in day-to-day life. And one
could quote numerous examples of unloved
or ill-loved children constantly plied with
gifts.
In consumer societies, toys are produced
industrially and are the source of substantial
commercial profit. They are given wide
publicity of all kinds, put out on display in
trade fairs and glittering shop windows. For
the giver, they are a token of wealth and
social standing, and they are a source of
cruel social inequalities between children
in the same school or the same
neighbourhood, distorting neighbourly or
friendly relations by introducing a spirit of
competition based on the commercial value
of the toys owned.
More serious still is the fact that- an
industrially-made toy, stereotyped and
technically perfected, forfeits much of its
value as a plaything. It is a closed object,
setting up a barrier against creativity and im¬
agination. In almost all instances, an
elementary plaything is preferable, be it a
stick or a pebble, which the small player can
turn into a musical instrument, a tool, a
weapon, a car or a boat, a doll or an animal,
as his mood dictates.
Thus, on the one hand, millions of
children are expected to make do with the
same dolls or cars, mass-produced in a de¬
personalized universe, while elsewhere there
are toys made by the child himself, by an
elder brother or sister, a parent or the village
craftsman, which remain intrinsically
democratic and closely bound up with the
family and cultural environment.
Unlike what goes on in the modern, over-
stratified societies, in the so-called tradi- 1
tionalist ones of Africa and some countries I
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
of America and Asia all forms of play activity
are accessible to all social categories. This
democratic character can perhaps be ac¬
counted for by the fact that play activities
are primarily a field open to all, and especial¬
ly to the children, who imagine, design and
make their own toys.
Children in the Western world have
scarcely any opportunities left to make their
own toys: they live in an environment in
which the basic materials are difficult to ob¬
tain (and non-existent for town children;
even municipal dumps are gradually disap¬
pearing). As for tools, there is such an
obsession about safety that the children are
given only wooden hammers or plastic
saws, paltry substitutes for the real thing,
and although there are no physical risks in¬
volved, they have a disastrous effect on their
psychological development.
Such is not the case in Africa, for exam¬
ple, where parents let their children use their
tools, or make them scaled-down but usable
tools of their own. In these societies,
however, adults "see to it at all times that
any play behaviour out of line with the tradi¬
tional patterns is repressed. They have no
intention of letting the child spend too much
time on such 'futile occupations' which
might keep him back at an age which he
must grow out of as soon as possible, for in
terms of the unwritten but ever-present
socio-educational laws, the young African
must grow up as quickly as possible, in
order to assume his proper role both in the
family and as a full, productive member of
the community".
It should not, however, be inferred from
this that the Western child is better off as
regards play. On the contrary, the more a
child is showered with toys, the more firmly
he becomes entrenched in an "extra-social"
category, the more unimaginative his play¬
ing is and the more strained his relationship
with adults becomes.
Games and societies are so intricately
bound up that some theorists have sug¬
gested a close interdependence between the
principles and rules of games of strategy and
socio-economic patterns: for instance,
chess, bridge and monopoly are typical of
societies based on commerce, while games
such as awélé, played by Baoulé children in
Africa, correspond to trade by barter.
Play is thus directly connected to actual
social institutions and not only to housing or
subsistence conditions. One need only look
at the element of play in physical and in¬
tellectual contests and the role it assumes,
for example, in the choice of leaders (tour¬
naments, verbal "jousting" in election cam¬
paigns, etc.).
Do we not use expressions such as "the
political game"? The close connexion bet¬
ween play and police investigations is
brought out in the accounts of thousands of
true or fictitious criminal cases to be found
in novels, films or serials. Financial or stock
exchange speculations are also partly a
game, not to mention the great money-
winning games like bingo, lotteries,
sweepstakes, pools or other betting games
which have become veritable institutions.
Whereas this type of game seems to be a
typical feature of industrial societies, in
other parts of the world play has an essential
function at times of transition from one age
group to the next, in the shape of ordeals or
initiation rites, which are often painful or
dangerous but have an element of play in
them and are an occasion for festivities and
community celebrations.
Prepared for the ordeals over a period of
years by means of make-believe "games
about games", the child grows up in har¬
mony with his environment. Even in
societies of an industrial type, in which
rituals marking the transition to adolescence
or adulthood are obscured and discarded by
the body of society, boys and girls spon¬
taneously put themselves to the test in
various ways (motorcycle racing, drug-
taking...); but these formidable games have
lost any ties with the community as a whole,
which rejects them, refuses to set any value
upon them and does what it can to prevent
them without proposing any alternative.
If one accepts the psycho analytical inter- \
What is play?
THERE is no way of telling categorically that a particular form of
behaviour is in fact a game, or a particular object a toy. The same
object a hammer ora saw for instance will be a tool in the hands
of a carpenter and a toy for the child who borrows it from his father or the
handyman who uses it in his spare time.
Several specialists in animal behaviour have attempted to throw light on
the problem of play by observing animals. As.far back as the beginning of
the century, the American scientist Karl Groos advanced his theory of play
as "practice". In his opinion, for young human beings and young animals
alike, play was an instinctive process of acquiring forms of behaviour rele¬
vant to situations that the adult would have to face up to in later life.
More recently, the Austrian zoologist Konrad Lorenz, analysing the
behaviour of kittens, wrote: "How do these movements of play differ from
those of real earnest? In their form, even the most practised eye may fail to
detect a difference, but nevertheless there is one. In these games, com¬
posed as they are of the movements of catching a prey, fighting a fellow
cat and repelling a foe, serious injury is never done to the playmate acting
one of these parts. The social inhibition against real biting or deep scrat¬
ching is fully enforced during play, while, in a case of real earnest, it is
obliterated by the emotion evoking the particular series of movements. In
serious situations, the animal is in a particular psychological state which
brings with it the readiness for a particular way of behaving and for this
way only. It is typical of play, that, during it, highly specific behaviour is in¬
cited without the corresponding emotional state. The relationship of all
play to play-acting lies in the fact that the player 'pretends' to be obsessed
with an emotion which he does not really feel." Play may therefore be con¬
sidered as a sort of fictional practice for instinctive hunting and defence ac¬
tivities.
While these attempts were being made to grasp the specific nature of
play through the observation of particular types of behaviour, various other
authors, by contrast, 'sought to define the problem of play in terms of a
universally applicable theory. One of the most important is the French
author Roger Caillois. His work Les Jeux et les Hommes was published
twenty years ago and was an attempt to produce a universal definition and
classification of games.
Caillois proceeded from the definitions set forth by the Dutch historian
Johan Huizinga in Homo Ludens, his study of the play element in culture.
According to Huizinga, the game is a voluntary action or activity, perform¬
ed within certain fixed time and space limits according to rules freely ac¬
cepted but binding and an end in themselves; bound up with feelings of
tension and joy and the awareness of its being different from real life.
Caillois set forth the characteristics of games as distinct from other
human occupations; according to his definition, the game "is an activity
which is:
1) free: in which the player is under no compulsion to take part, failing
which the game instantly loses its appeal and pleasurable nature;
2) separate, taking place within precise, pre-determined space and time
limits;
3) uncertain, having no foreseeable progression or result, some latitude
for resourcefulness being necessarily left to the player;
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Kite by Jacqueline Monnier. Photo © Jean-Louis Bloch Laine, Paris.
4) unproductive, not giving rise to material gains or new elements of
any kind and, except for items of property which may change hands within
the group of players, leading to exactly the same situation at the end of the
game as existed at the beginning;
5) subject to certain rules or conventions superseding ordinary laws and
temporarily substituting for them a new code which alone counts;
6) fictional, the player being specifically aware that he is experiencing a
substitute reality or even a complete lack of reality distinct from everyday
life."
Apart from this attempt to describe games as objects, there are the
various psychological approaches seeking to apprehend the role of the
game in the development of the individual psyche.
For the Englishman Henry Bett, games are an involuntary resurgence of
vital instincts which have lost their significance today; for others, play is a
functional relaxation activity or, again, a way of using up excess energy
that cannot, or can no longer, be absorbed by survival activities.
In this field, two major theories prevail in current research.
Genetic psychology, founded by the Swiss psychologist Jean Piaget,
sees play both as the expression of and the prerequisite for a child's
development. A certain form of play is indissolubly linked with each stage
of development, and although the rate or age at which various games ap¬
pear may vary from one society to another or one individual to another, the
order in which they appear is always the same. Play is a yardstick of a
child's mental development.
' From the viewpoint of Freudian psychoanalytical theory, "play can be
correlated to the child's other fantasy activities, especially dreams". The
essential function of play can thus be seen as the reduction of tensions
arising from the inability to fulfil one's desires, but unlike dreams, play is
based on a permanent compromise between drives and rules, between
fantasy and real life.
The universal character of play in the mental development of an in¬
dividual is subject, as we have seen, to variations from one period of time,
culture or type of society to another. Thus in ancient societies the contrast
between work and leisure or play was not nearly as clear-cut as in industrial
societies, which from the eighteenth century onwards placed emphasis on
productive work to the detriment of any occupation that was thought to be
unproductive.
Huizinga goes so far as to consider play the very foundation of culture,
in so far as it is the only form of behaviour that cannot be traced back to
the basic survival instinct. He postulates that play underlies all social in¬
stitutions, political power, war or commerce, and points out the element of
play in all of them. In his view, play is also at the root of art, and it is true
that play has a strong element of creative activity and that similarities do
exist, although play, unlike art, is not intended to last.
In contrast to Huizinga, the Swede Yrjö Hirn sees games as the final
stage in a process of decaying social institutions. He sees proof of his
theory in the numerous rites that have disappeared, of which games are a
degenerate survival.
There can be no doubt, either, that while play is deeply ingrained in a
people's cultural traditions, it also evolves with society, and history has
shown that it is conditioned by economic and political systems. Thus the
simple toy made out of whatever happened to be at hand at the time, often
by the child himself, evidence of which can still be found in the recent past
of Western societies, has been supplanted in our industrial age by the toy
as a commercial product and a marketable item, a source of substantial
profit.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
pretation of play as a way of resolving libido
' tensions, one can account for the number of
play practices in which the player deliberate¬
ly tries to flirt with death or put himself in a
physical or psychological state at the ex¬
treme limit of his endurance, or to provoke
in himself a feeling of dread or horror.
Folklore the world over is full of masked
festivals, tales about death, imaginary
characters such as witches, ghosts,
bogeymen and ogres. In Mexico, they sell
candy skulls and cross-bones, which are
relished by children and old people alike.
There are countless word and drawing
games that provide an opportunity to
tamper with the laws of decorum, morality
or logic (nonsense rhymes or games).
Games of make-believe make it possible for
a child, with his teddy-bear or doll, to strike
a blow at the family hierarchy by parodying
parental or social authority, or even enacting
the death of his father or mother in dramatic
games. Play functions as a veritable "institu¬
tion of transgression", which cannot be
obstructed without serious psychological
consequences for both the child and the
adult and without profoundly affecting the
child's capacity to integrate.
It is not surprising that play, society's way
of providing an outlet for the pent-up forces
within it, is both a vital safety valve and an
actual educational institution operating
spontaneously.
Play assumed this role even before there
was such a thing as school, and continues
to do so today, before and during a child's
school-going years. Technological know-
how and knowledge in general are transmit¬
ted through play. A child deprived of the
first rudiments of knowledge that it brings
him would be incapable of learning anything
at school, and would be irreparably cut off
from his natural and his social environment.
When a child plays, it is his initiation into
adult behaviour, into the role he will be call¬
ed upon to play in subsequent life. He
develops his physical, verbal and intellectual
capacities and his ability to communicate. It
constitutes a far broader factor of com¬
munication than speech and it facilitates
communications between individuals from
different linguistic or cultural backgrounds.
Through its institutional aspect, the ar¬
bitrary nature of its rules and the virtually
compulsory ways in which they are
transmitted and through the hierarchical
structure of the group of players, play is a
micro-society in which children receive their'
initial training in social behaviour.
Watching children playing marbles in the
Geneva area, Jean Piaget noted the im¬
mutable way in which the "laws" were pass¬
ed on, each child spontaneously accepting
them as binding without being remotely
aware of how or by whom they had been
transmitted. The same applies to other
cultural models.
"In group games, the child learns to see
where he stands in relation to the others,
within a definite hierarchical framework. In
doing so, he learns to appreciate his own
position as a member of the group, thereby
determining his personal status, and
ultimately to perceive the group in terms of
himself and of other groups." It is in the
course of play that a newcomer will be
welcomed or turned away, and that children
assimilate the ethical values of the society to
which they belong. The children's group or
association therefore has an essential role.
The ethnologist Pierre Erny gives the
following description of the function of the
group among African children:
"Children from a whole village or from a
whole neighbourhood mix at a very early
age. Individual differences are brought face
to face; to begin with, children go about
their activities separately, then gradually
these activities interact and finally, with
rapidly acquired maturity, they are shared.
Thus a sort of mutual education process
takes root within the juvenile society, more
or less on the fringe of the adult world, and
it is perhaps not exaggerating to say that
there is in this education the element of
socialization that is a preponderant in tradi¬
tional societies.
"In the peer group organized to all intents
and purposes as an educational institution,
the child encounters an environment that is
different from his family, and is able to
undergo his training for life in society away
from over-restrictive bonds of affection,
belonging and dependency. There he will
find, in embryo, the atmosphere which will
later be characteristic of the public life of an
adult. He will perceive society in a new light
and step by step will prepare to make his en¬
try into that society and meet all of its re¬
quirements".
It goes without saying that the educa¬
tional institution of play is the carrier, along
with the cultural heritage, of certain social
norms that may become obsolete, such as
segregation between boys and girls. While
respecting play, the educator, in his capacity
as such, can endeavour to propose new
patterns.
Indeed, not least among the virtues of
play are its existence as a particularly effec¬
tive channel of transmission and its recep-
tiveness to innovation and creativity. It may
often happen that children's games are
technologically and ideologically ahead of
their social context and are a vital source of
invention and progress. Any would-be pro¬
gressive society therefore owes it to itself to
regard play as being of the utmost impor¬
tance and to keep a watchful eye out for any
premonitory signs foreshadowing its
decline.
Left, variants of the
game of "keeping a
straight face" are
played all over the
world by children in
the 8 to 11 years age
group.
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Australian bark paintings
The Aborigine artists
of Arnhem Land
by Karel Kupka
Text Copyright © Karel Kupka. Reproduction Prohibited
FOR the aborigines of Australia art and
life are permanently interlinked. As
well as the sacred objects used in
ancestral rites, they paint, etch and carve
their weapons, their tools and their everyday
domestic utensils. Their paintings decorate
their huts, which are made of bark, the sur¬
faces of rocks and even the ground itself.
They carve reliefs on trees and scratch out
ornamental designs in the sand.
Their majestic, finely sculpted mortuary
totem poles, the vessels in which are kept
the bones of the dead, even the skulls of the
dead are all richly painted. And despite the
fact that modern civilization is opening up
new horizons for the younger generation of
aborigines, these arts and rites have surviv¬
ed to this day in the purity of their traditional
forms, even if they are now less frequently
practised.
There is an overall unity of conception in
the aborigine plastic arts, but styles differ
from region to region. It may be that natural
conditions have encouraged the develop¬
ment of certain forms of art in Australia as
they have in other continents. The hot
climate of the north, with its stark sunlight
mirrored by the sea giving a light which
draws out the true value of colours and
seems to bring the horizon closer, seems to
encourage painting, just as do the natural
conditions of the Mediterranean area in
Europe and of Central America in the New
World. The cold grey mists of the south,
however, tend to inspire drawing rather than
painting.
Bark painting is the most characteristic of
the various aborigine arts and the form that
retains today the most vitality. It consists of
painting on panels of bark from the eucalyp¬
tus tree. The most common species of tree
in Australia, the eucalyptus provides a pain¬
ting surface which is easy to obtain and con¬
venient and simple to handle.
The tree must be healthy, straight and
have no cracks in its bark. A small section is
cut out with an axe, trimmed down to a thin
sheet and cleaned. The panel thus obtained
is then heated over a fire and pressed
against the knee or the foot until it is
CONTINUED PAGE 12
The Australian aboriginal painters who live
in the region of Milingimbi, on the northern
coast of Arnhem Land, use eucalyptus bark
as a "canvas" on which to portray the
complex myths of their people in an
otherwordly setting which they call "the
time of dreams". To conjure up this
universe of myth they use with great
freedom a wealth of figurative signs. Bark
painting, left, was produced in 1963 by an
artist named Djulwarak. It illustrates the
myth of the Wavilak sisters, which relates
the peopling of the Australian continent. At
bottom of painting is a waterhole beside
which grows a eucalyptus tree. One of the
sisters wakes the sacred snake Yurlunggur
which emerges from the waterhole (right of
painting). When the snake emerges a
second time (centre) it coils itself around
the two sisters and their children and
swallows them. In bottom right corner, the
two sisters reappear. The painting is
crowded with symbolic forms enabling the
viewer to "read" and memorize the story.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Klee Foundation, Kunstmuseum, Bern
Photo © Nationel Museum of Victoria, Australia
The art
of high spirits
The spirit world is a favourite theme of
Australian bark painters. The most popular
spirits are the mimi or rock-spirits, frail and
timorous ghosts who shun adults and are
only visible to children. Photo 1 shows two
slender, bony mimi; the male is carrying a
basket on his shoulder. Gesticulating with
their long, ribbonlike arms, the four mimi
in photo 3 are conducting an animated
conversation. An unusual feature of the
work is that the artist has not indicated the
sex of the figures. Although as a rule the
mimi are inoffensive creatures, they are
sometimes roused to ferocity. Bark
painting 5 shows mimi engaged in battle.
Two of the combatants, their broken bones
indicated by swellings, are lying flat out,
one on top of the other. The third, above
them, has had his legs broken in the fray.
By simplifying and reorganizing natural
shapes, the aborigine painters create a
sense of force and a figurative symbolism
which evoke the works of many modern
artists including Paul Klee (2) whose self-
proclaimed purpose was "to penetrate to
the interior and not reflect the surface".
Certain figures by Picasso (4) also recall
those created by the bark painters, while
the affinity is even more startling in the
case of the Cuban artist Wifredo Lam (6).
This puzzling figure in the form of a
question-mark, half-horse, half-woman,
displays the same fascination with linear
composition and the same preoccupation
with symbolism as those of the bark
painters.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Photo from Pablo Picasso, by Christian Zerros © Ed. Cahiers d'Art, Paris
Photos 1 Two spirits (bark painting from Geimbo
region, 1914).
Bust of a Child by Paul Klee (1963).
Four mimi by Namatbara (Croker Island,
1963).
Figures by Pablo Picasso (1929)
Battle of the mimi by Irvala (Croker Island,
1963).
Etching by Wifredo Lam (1966). .
Photo © Wifredo Lam, Paris
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Clouds are depicted in
this bark painting from
the region of Milingimbi
(1959-1960). In works
whose resemblance to
abstract art is only
superficial, the aboriginal
artist uses signs,
symbols and colours to
convey his message.
Thus when painting
clouds the colours he
chooses will indicate
whether his subject is
the morning mist,
looming storm clouds or
clouds at twilight.
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 9
straight. It is then kept flat under the weight
of some stones or sand. After a few days it
is dry enough to be painted and a first pro¬
tective coating of a sticky juice from the
stem of a wild orchid is applied to the
smoother inner side.
The colours used are yellow, red and
brown (natural ochres), white (from kaolin
or plaster) and black (chiefly from crushed
charcoal). The aborigines jealously protect
the sites from which they obtain their col¬
ours and the natural ochres that produce the
finest tints are valued highly enough to be
used in barter.
Aborigine artists handle their paint¬
brushes with extraordinary dexterity. The
brushes are made from thin stems of wood
chewed at one end or from the stalks of
plants to which hairs, plant fibres, shreds of
feathers or carefully cut leaves have been at¬
tached. After the first coating has been ap¬
plied, the colours are usually simply mixed
with water and this accounts for the fragility
of these paintings. But it should be
remembered that, for the aborigine artist,
the action of painting, the creative act itself,
is the important thing. Now that their works
have become popular with collectors, they
tend to take more trouble to preserve them
by the use of modern fixatives. But, clearly,
their fragility makes it absurd to judge these
works on the basis of their age; even in
museums there are very few bark paintings
more than fifty years old. The only valid
criterion of judgement is that of artistic
quality.
Nevertheless, this form of painting stems
from a long tradition. Modern scientific tests
have proved that the remains of rock pain¬
tings and petroglyphs found throughout
Australia are several thousand years old.
Since a large proportion of bark paintings
reproduce the same subjects as appear in
the rock paintings and use identical tech¬
niques, we may suppose that their origins
also date far back in time.
In spite of modern influences, the themes
of bark painting have hardly changed at all.
The aborigine painter is primarily a sym¬
bolist. He refines and simplifies his figures,
creating an almost abstract decoration to ex¬
press his ideas concisely. This pictorial art
form is still regularly employed in Arnhem
Land and its immediate surroundings in the
Northern Territory of Australia.
Bark paintings can be divided into three
main groups according to their
characteristics.
The painting of the west and south of
Arnhem Land and of Groóte Eylandt is
figurative painting; but it is extremely sub¬
jective, reflecting directly the inner feelings
of the painter. Although the natural shapes
reproduced, mainly animal or human, are
easily identifiable, it is not realistic painting,
at least not as realism is generally
understood. Reality as he sees it is less im¬
portant to the artist than reality as he knows
it and feels it. He expresses reality as he
knows it, imagines it or wishes it to be, not
as he sees it, accentuating the details which
help him to put across his ideas and
deliberately omitting details that do not in¬
terest him.
A "cubist" without knowing it, he
reconstructs his subject, bringing together
aspects which are normally seen from dif¬
ferent angles, and it does not bother him at
all that in fact they cannot all be seen at the
same time from the angle he has chosen.
The most striking proof of his subjectivity
is his habit of representing the bone struc-
Bark painting of a eucalyptus tree (left)
was created in 1960 by Dainganngang, an
artist living on the island of Milingimbi. The
form of the tree has been so radically
simplified that it is easy to see why such
works are sometimes thought to be
abstract compositions by those who do not
know what their creators are seeking to
depict.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
tures and internal organs of a creature that
are not normally visible, a form of "X-ray
painting" that has achieved a certain
measure of fame. His line of thought can be
more readily understood if we note that the
animals he paints in this way are the animals
which provide his favourite food. He does
not See them with his eyes alone, but with
his stomach also, an explanation which is
confirmed by the fact that he does not stress
these internal features when painting totem
animals which interest him for quite dif¬
ferent reasons. Since he is not attracted by
the meat of totem animals, he stresses their
outward appearance, as he does with
human figures, shaping them according to
his own conceptions and supplementing his
colour range by the use of cross-hatching
and dots.
The "people" in these paintings are main¬
ly "spirits" who are widespread in the area
known as the "Stone Country". The
mystery of the caves and the shadowy
darkness of the ravines exert their power as
they do in similar regions in other con¬
tinents. The aborigines interpret all natural
phenomena as manifestations of the spirits.
Storms, for example, are caused by the
Thunder-Spirit who appears in paintings
surrounded by an encircling line in the shape
of a cloud. At his elbows and knees, stone
axe-heads symbolize lightning and claps of
thunder.
The most popular spirits are the spirits of
the rocks, the Mimi. These are a whole race
of normally peace-loving, shy ghosts who
are seen only by children. They hide
themselves from adults not only because
they are shy, but also because of their
physical frailty. "They have to hide and live
in caves and underground; they are so weak
that the wind would break their necks at
once", say the aborigines.
There are also some dangerous ghosts,
the Maams or Mamandis. Deprived of
repose in the "land of the dead", they haunt
and disturb the living. The painters express
their supernatural power by depicting them
with several arms and legs.
The bark paintings of the eastern part of
the north coast and the adjacent islands are
quite different from those of the western
and southern parts of Arnhem Land.
Although they are not really non-figurative
paintings, they often give that impression.
Natural shapes get lost in the decorative
composition of the paintings, which the
painter divides into several different areas,
using colour right across the surface and
creating forms which are often so far from
reality that the resulting work seems to be
abstract. Here, painters show a preference
for totemic subjects for which they invent
representative symbols and signs.
These artists do not paint their totems and
symbols with the broad brush-strokes of
those accustomed to working on the vast
expanses of rock-face. Their technique is in¬
fluenced by totemic painting on the human
body. The artist creates graphic forms in
which each motif has a specific function.
These bark paintings sometimes resemble
body-painting so closely that they adopt not
only the same graphic forms and themes but
also its format. Thus the artist practises on
bark so that he will be better able to execute
ritual paintings on the face and torso for in¬
itiation ceremonies.
Bark painting is generally considered to
have an educative function, whether it be a
matter of teaching others or of perfecting
oneself. Each feature, each shape in a pain¬
ting has a precise meaning which the in¬
itiates must be able to distinguish. For
anyone else, the paintings remain in¬
decipherable.
By simplifying and recomposing natural
shapes, the aborigine painter therefore
achieves a kind of abstraction not unlike that
of many modern artists, the only difference
being that he does not set out to achieve
this effect deliberately. The motivation is
quite different.
It has often been said that "the chief
characteristic of modern painting is that it
does not tell a story"; aborigine art,
however, is constantly telling stories. In¬
deed, that is its main object and the essen¬
tial purpose of its symbols. The aborigine ar¬
tist wants to portray the inner nature rather
than the outward appearance of things. The
fine criss-cross lines he draws may represent
honey or fire, seaweed or water, air, sand,
rocks, bark, herbs, skin, fur or feathers.
For the aborigines, this pictorial sym¬
bolism is a way of writing down folk-tales,
the stories of the "Dream Time" (the sub¬
conscious life), or the recital of historical
events of importance. Line and colour rein¬
force the aural memory and their "spoken
literature" becomes a "painted literature".
This explains the astonishment of students
of aboriginal mythology when they find a
vast "literature" preserved without the i
benefit of the written word.
The dotted circles which intersperse the
leaves and branches in this bark painting
are the artist's way of representing, not
flowers, but flying foxes, large bats which
sleep hanging from the branches of a tree.
The aboriginal artists often depict animals
in this way, by means of a characteristic
sign or symbol which unmistakably
identifies the animal in question. In the
case of the flying fox, this distinctive sign
is the animal's droppings, which are
represented, as here, by coloured circles.
The circles not only heighten the decorative
effect but also indicate that the trees
featured in the painting are those favoured
by flying foxes as a refuge.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
The artists of Milingimbi Yirrkala and
other places in this region are past masters
in the creation of a real "literature in paint".
In this way they reconstruct on bark the
complicated action of a whole history. Their
abbreviations and particularly their signs and
symbols are wonderfully suitable for the pur¬
pose. The artists do not arrange them in a
preconceived order, but make a free com¬
position, a picture. So if we want to under¬
stand the story an artist is painting in all its
detail, as it unfolds in his personal version,
then we must be present when he is working
on it and watch him and listen to him as he
progresses step by step.
On the islands of Bathurst and Melville,
which lie north of Darwin, the aborigines
paint bark solely for the decoration of
special baskets. These are ritual objects
destined to crown the carved and painted
totem poles erected to the memory of the
dead. But they are not content to be mere
decorators; they know how to create true
paintings in which natural forms end up as
unintentioned abstracts. In these islands
too, bark painting is linked to the ritual pain¬
ting of the body. It reproduces totems which
here are chosen from plants or places rather
than from the animal world.
The artists give free rein to their fantasies
and their imagination, conceiving shapes to
represent a tree, a bush, a particular place,
an island, rocks, a pile of clay (especially the
clay or natural ochres they use in their
work), a stretch of sand, a water-hole, a
stream, a bay.
Ignoring visual reality, they create
abstractions to which they can attribute any
meaning they like. Either they remain
deliberately indifferent to the physical ap¬
pearance of natural phenomena, making no
attempt to describe that appearance
recognizably, or they have already gone so
far along the road of graphic representation
that we can no longer follow their line of
thought.
Other forms of ornamental painting, link¬
ed to rock painting and to its symbolism or
inspired by etchings on wood or mother of
pearl, are to be seen in the bark paintings of
the Port Keats area, on the northern shores
of western Australia. They reflect, as do all
the other forms of bark painting, the
mythology of the region. Natural forms like
the snake, for instance, are favoured by
these artists who find inspiration in the
curves of its body, in the circles and coils of
young snakes and the pale speckles of their
eggs. As they re-arrange and recompose
these forms, we can see the gradual transi¬
tion towards ornamentation.
With so-called "primitive" art enjoying in¬
creasing popularity, aborigine painting is
particularly sought after today. As a result,
bark paintings are proliferating throughout
Australia and this over-production is causing
their quality and educative value to suffer.
Nevertheless, among this excessive output it
is still possible to find works of value. H
KAREL KUPKA, French ethnologist of Czech
origin, is a research officer with France's National
Centre of Scientific Research, and is currently
studying the basis and purpose of art in the "pri¬
mitive" family. He began toJay the foundations of
his extensive first-hand knowledge of Australian
aboriginal art and customs on his first visit to the
continent in 1951 and laterplanned the Australian
Arts room at the Museum ofAfrican and Oceanic
Arts in Paris.
Bark painting of a "barramundi" fish is an
example of the remarkable "X-ray art" in
which some Australian aboriginal painters
depict not only the exterior outlines but
also the internal organs of their subjects.
The technique is often used by artists for
painting the animals which provide them
with meat. The work shown here was
painted in 1963 by an artist of Croker
Island, off the northern coast of Australia.
Bottom photo, a ritual body painting is
being executed on the skin of a participant
in the corroborée dances which mark
initiation ceremonies and other ritual
occasions. Eucalyptus bark is a readily
available material which aboriginal body
painters may use as a "sketchbook" in
which to practise their art.
Photo © K. Kupka. Museum of African and Oceanic Arts, Pans
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The master-builder
of the Italian Renaissance
by Renato Cevese
Andrea di Pietro, known to history as Palladio, was born in 1508
in Padua in northern Italy, where his father was a miller.
In 1524, when he was sixteen years old, he moved
to nearby Vicenza where, until about 1540,
he worked as a mason in the workshops of the town's two most famous sculptors:
Giovanni di Giacomo di Porlezza and Girolamo Pittoni di Lumignano.
It was in order to earn a living
that he undertook this sort of manual work
in which he was called
upon to execute bases,
capitals, architraves
and cornices for altars,
tombs and porticoes,
rather than statues
and figurative sculptures.
Palladio underwent a long period of
rigorous training to become an ar¬
chitect, a profession he was to practise
from 1540 to 1580 (the year of his death)
with unflagging and painstaking skill in
every corner of the Italian provinces of
the Véneto and the Friul. In his
eagerness to read De Architectura, the
celebrated treatise by the Roman ar¬
chitect Vitruvius (Ist century BC) who
was regarded as the incontestable
"legislator" of the laws of architecture,
Palladio learned Latin, which was to give
him access to the broadest horizons of
ancient scholarship. At the same time,
his frequent visits to Rome enabled him
to visit the ancient monuments still ex¬
isting in the regions he passed through
on his way.
Andrea also displayed keen interest in the contributions which
treatises by such Renaissance figures as Leon Battista Alberti and
Sebastian Serlio had recently made to the science of architecture.
Throughout his life he seized every opportunity to further his
studies and research. So we can be sure that he was in contact
with famous masters like Sansovino and Giulio Romano who, like
Serlio, travelled to Vicenza to advise on the consolidation and
restoration of the endangered fifteenth-century loggias surroun¬
ding the Gothic palace of Ragione.
For Palladio, who lived in a small town that had seceded from
RENATO CEVESE, of Italy, is secretary of the scientific council of the An¬
drea Palladio International Centre ofArchitectural Studies at Vicenza (Ita¬
ly) andprofessor of the history of architecture at the faculty of engineering
science of the University of Padua. He is the author or'Villas de la Provincia
de Vicenza lin collaboration with M. Barbieri and M. Magagnato) and Las
Villas de Andrea Palladio. He contributed a study on Palladio's work to the
Palladio exhibition held in Vicenza in 1973.
the Most Serene Venetian Republic,
personal contact with the great ar¬
chitects of the age was a highly
stimulating experience. He was also ex¬
cited by the new ideas brought to Vicen¬
za from Rome by Gian Giorgio Trissino
dal Vello d'Oro, a wealthy aristocrat,
humanist scholar, philologist and poet,
as well as an architecture enthusiast.
Trissino became Andrea's patron,
gave him the name Palladio [as an allu¬
sion to the Greek goddess Pallas Athena
and to a character in one of Trissino's
poems] and generally assisted him by in¬
troducing him to Vicenza's wealthy
aristocracy, often taking him along on
visits to Rome. Because of his social
position and his privileged place at the
Papal court, Trissino was able to in¬
troduce Palladio into the most influential cultural circles in Rome,
thereby enabling him to rub shoulders with the artists who were
then engaged in renovating the capital of Christianity: from
Michelangelo to Pirro Ligorio, from Antonio da Sangallo the
Younger to Giacomo Barozzi da Vignola.
Andrea Palladio was an interested and attentive observer of
works by these masters which were in an advanced state of con¬
struction, as well as of buildings by architects of the past. He was
also able to obtain from architects or their disciples first-hand in¬
formation about future projects. He was always ready to take from
contemporary architecture any innovations that might interest
him. At the same time he sought to achieve a thorough mastery of
the structure and form of ancient monuments. These he
measured, sketched and later incorporated into his own work, not
with the free-and-easy superficiality of the "antiquarian" dilet¬
tante, but with the keen intelligence and application of one who
had assimilated the logic of their form and construction through k
studying their surviving parts. f
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
**-#.
The church of San Giorgio Maggiore in Venice is one of the finest
achievements of Palladio, the great Italian architect who died four
hundred years ago. The airy cupola, vigorous pilasters with half-
16
columns, as well as the dynamic treatment of space, are typical of
Palladio's religious architecture. Above, view of the left arm of
the transept, as seen from the open gallery inside the cupola.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Palladio filled a vast number of folios with the plans and sket¬
ches of monuments of Antiquity which are today preserved in the
Civic Museum in Vicenza and at the Royal Institute of British Ar¬
chitects in London; some of these precious documents he used to
illustrate the fourth book of his Treatise on the "ancient Temples
found in Rome" and "others in Italy and outside Italy".
Palladio's art abounds in references to Roman architecture, not
only in his persistent use of the orders in the façades of palaces
and villas, in the loggias of the Basilica of Vicenza, in the pro¬
scenium of Vicenza's Olympic Theatre and in the church of //
Redentore in Venice but above all in his plans for certain urban
buildings and villas, and especially in the convent complex of the
Carita in Venice.
In the eighth decade of the sixteenth century, while Italian ar¬
chitects were embarking on the tormented path of Mannerism,
Palladio publicly proclaimed the Classicist creed which he would
never refute, by bringing the form of the Greco-Roman theatre to
Vicenza and evoking in his Villa Rotonda or round villa, the time-
honoured ¡mage of the Pantheon in Rome. In his last years, he
practised a more forceful and vigorous Classicism than ever. It
could well be that the excessive liberties taken by his contem¬
poraries in their interpretation of antiquity inspired in Palladio a
desire to proclaim the superiority of the ancients, the inimitable in¬
ventors of "exemplary" structures.
Any distinguished artist soon gains recognition through the
strength of character which marks him out from the rank and file.
The great artist always embodies something new, projecting
himself into the future with intuition far ahead of his time, or
achieving a remarkable synthesis of the forms and thought with
which he lives and works.
Where Palladio broke new ground in architecture was in his con¬
ception of the villa, the mansion or stately home which originated
not so much in the landed gentry's desire to flaunt their wealth and
power, still less in aesthetic requirements, as in a glaring economic
need. Before Palladio's time, most Italian country houses were
buildings with modest architectural pretensions, designed to
house the lord and master of the estate, when he left the town for
the country in order to direct in person the cultivation of his land
and the harvesting of his crops. Around such houses, which were
often set within a battlemented enclosure, were farm-workers'
quarters, stables and poultry-houses. Near the farmyard, or scat¬
tered over the estate, were other thatched cottages and more
stables.
Palladio combined into a single architectural entity the master's
house, which formed the central part of the building, and the out¬
buildings, on each flank. Viewed from the front, the outbuildings
appear as wide porticoes, lower than the central hall, as wide
wings, sometimes aligned with the central façade, sometimes pro¬
truding in front of ¡t. But Palladio was not a man to allow his
genius to be shackled by a fixed and immutable design, and he
continually introduced modifications, bending the wing porticoes
at right angles, or curving them into a semi-circle. Sometimes he
even shut off the court or farmyard into' an oblong perimeter of
continuous porticoes reminiscent of the ancient forum dominated
by the temple.
The master-builder from Vicenza also introduced important in¬
novations in palace construction. Palladio built a total of eight
palaces and three public buildings. And, had he been able to bring
to completion his projects for the Capra, Trissino, Angarano and
Garzadori palaces, Vicenza could lay even greater claim to its title,
"Città d'Autore"a city created by one man's genius.
In Palladio we have the interpreter and protagonist of a common
cultural consciousness and a man with a bent for the precise and
the practical: the genius who invents and the engineer who builds.
For Palladio was both poet and technician. Unlike Leonardo da
Vinci and Filarete in the Milan of the Sforzas, he was prevented by
historical circumstances from conceiving a model city. Palladio
was not a town planner in the modern sense of the word, but his
projects and constructions nevertheless convey an impression of
his extraordinary intelligence and a sensitive awareness of what a
town or city should be.
Palladio varies his conceptions with inexhaustible imagination. It
is above all in the palaces he designed that he shows himself an
heir to Venetian cultural traditions which gave priority to at-
CONTINUEO PAGE 21
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
The
triumphs
of
Palladio
II Redentore (upper photo at
left) on the Venetian Island of
Giudecca is a masterwork of
church architecture designed by
Palladio towards the end of his
life. It was built as a votive
temple to "our Redeemer" on
the occasion of a plague which
smote Venice and the Véneto in
1576 and 1577. The unflagging
inventiveness of Palladio's
treatment of space is admirably
displayed in the harmony
between the lengthwise thrust
of the nave and the soaring
ascension of the cupola. The
Tempietto Bárbaro, another late
work (lower photo, left), was
built at Maser near the famous
Villa Bárbaro (see photo page
24). The round cupola and the
columns and pediment of the
portico recall the Pantheon at
Rome, a monument of Antiquity
to which Palladio often looked
for inspiration. The architect,
near to death, broke with his
usual practice and had his name
carved on a frieze at the side of
the building.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Giraudon, París
Drawing of the Baths of Diocletian, above
right. Is one of many in which Palladio
reconstructed from surviving ruins the
appearance of ancient Roman monuments.
It bears a strong resemblance to the façade
of Palladio's Villa Foscari, right, on the
outskirts of Venice.
Palladio's art drew
sustenance from the
cultural heritage of
Greece and Rome
and in itself
contributed largely to
the revival of interest
in Antiquity. The
architect's strong
attachment to the
classical tradition is
even symbolized in
his name, which was
bestowed on him by
his patron Trissino as
an allusion to Pallas
Athena, the Greek
goddess of wisdom.
Left, the so-called
"melancholy
Athena", a sculpture
preserved in the
Acropolis Museum,
Athens.
Photo © Electa Editrice, Milan. Civic Museum, Vicenza
Although engraving
in neoclassical style
(left) is entitled The
Triumph of Palladio,
its ornate baroque
flourishes are in no
way Palladian. It
appeared as an
illustration in an
edition by James
Leoni, of Palladio's
treatise Quattro libri
del/'architettura,
published in 1716.
Right, an artist's
reconstitution of the
forum of ancient
Rome with the
Capitol in the
background. Ruins of
such monuments
provided Palladio
with models for his
works.
Photos © Centro Intemazionale di Studi di Architettura "Andrea Palladio", Vicenza,
Document from A History of Architecture by Sir Banister Fletcher. © Charles Scnbners Sons, New York
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Studio Coloz di Fornari e Ziveri. Galleria Nazionale, Parma Photo © Giraudon, París
Painting above left. The Basilica of Vicenza and the Rialto Bridge, is a fantasy on the
theme of Palladio and Venice by the Venetian artist Canaletto (1697-1768). In this view of
Venice with the famous Rialto bridge, Canaletto replaced the actual Rialto bridge with a
bridge project (presumed to be for the Rialto) which was produced by Palladio and
published in his architectural treatise Quattro Libri (below). On each side of the bridge are
two of Palladio's finest achievements, the Palazzo Chiericati (left of painting) and the
Loggias of the Palazzo della Ragione, or Basilica (right), both of which are in Vicenza not
Venice^ Photos on opposite page show these buildings as they are today. Above right,
view of modern Venice shows the real Rialto bridge, which was built a few years after
Palladio's death to plans by Antonio da Ponte.
Photo © Electa Editrice, Milan
DDD j D I
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 17
mospheric and pictorial value, and created perforated walls in
which the empty spaces predominated over the solid areas of
masonry. But, unlike the Venetian façades which are joined
together like so many multi-coloured tapestries exposed to the
sun, with their beautiful marble inlaid work, Palladio's palaces
display to all the world the vigour of their structures and stand out
because of his impressive three-dimensional use of the orders. This
is especially noteworthy in those palaces where Palladio used giant
half-columns (the Loggia del Capitaniato and the palace of Porto
.Breganze), orders which are not merely an ornament appended on
to the framework of the architectural fabric, but an integral part of
it, thereby fulfilling the dual function of composition and adorn¬
ment.
Here and there in Palladio's designs one comes across echoes of
Raphaël, Bramante, Giulio Romano, and Sebastian Serlio; but
these are mere reminders, simple allusions to the work of others.
So forceful is Palladio's creative instinct, which renews everything
within its purview, that such allusions lose any link they may have
had with the originals and take their place in an architectural
language which has no parallel.
It was not until the early 1560s that Palladio turned to ec¬
clesiastical architecture, to which he would devote much of the re¬
mainder of his life, especially in Venice. In 1561 he began to build
the magnificent convent complex of the Carita. In the following
year he undertook the building of the façade of San Francesco
del/a Vigna; and in 1566 he drew plans for the Church of San
Giorgio Maggiore, on the island in the Venp.tian Lagoon, opposite
St Mark's Square. In 1576 and 1577 he designed the temple of //
Redentore in the Giudecca. All these works enhanced the
magnificence of the already resplendent city of the Doges.
In work on the church of San Francesco delta Vigna, Palladio
was faced with a façade begun by Sansovino years before. The
plan he adopted was one which he would repeat time and again in
other churches: the superimposition of two façades which corres¬
pond to the division of space within the church. One, reinforced
with gigantic half-columns, was the same height as the central
aisle of which it formed the front, the other, which fronted the
two side aisles, was adorned with decorative fasciae (except in the
case of San Francesco della Vigna).
Palladio's genius is most evident in the force and impact of his
treatment of space; tripartite in the church of San Giorgio Mag¬
giore, a tribute to ancient Italic tradition and the more recent tradi¬
tion of Venice; unitary in the church of II Redentore, where the ar¬
tist appears to have reconstructed the atmosphere of the Roman
baths.
In the church of // Redentore there are three spatial "moments":
the first corresponds to the long processional hall, which opens
out into the chapels in the two apses; the second to the three-
aisled chancel; and the third to the quiet atmosphere of the choir.
The spatial thrust is lengthwise, in an area whose sides are
delimited by the powerful twin columns of the pilasters that
separate the six chapels; it rises upwards in the central mass of the
chancel and is transformed into a pure and resonant pattern of
light, in the monks' choir.
The overall effect of this sequence of spatial "episodes", each of
which fulfils a specific function, is to make II Redentore one of the
major architectural achievements of all time. At the sides of the
chancel and the choir, the two slender bell-towers rise sharply
against the lofty dome, built according to the traditions of Venice
and of the East.
Construction of the Teatro Olímpico (Olympic Theatre) in Vicen¬
za, begun in March 1580, was interrupted by Palladio's death in
August of that year. The theatre, which would be completed in
1584 by another great architect of Vicenza, Vincenzo Scamozzi,
was commissioned by the members of the Accademia Olímpica of
Vicenza, who were lovers of classical literature and wanted a
theatre in which Greek tragedies could be performed. As their
resources were limited, Palladio was compelled to use humble
materials for building the ancient-style theatre structure: the tiers
of seats and the orchestra were of wood; the podium was of
masonry and wood and the façade of the proscenium was of
masonry. A part of the perimeter walls was also built of wood.
The space available was rather narrow, and so Palladio set out
the tiers of seats in a narrow semi-ellipse, instead of the traditional
semicircle. As a result, he had to restrict the depth of the orchestra
but was able to erect a majestic, high, proscenium so vibrant in its
forms as to be a piece of theatre in itself. The statues he placed in
the niches of the simulated windows (see back cover) on the i
pediments and the columns, in front of the pilasters of the square |
Photos © Centro Internazionale di Studi di Architettura "Andrea Palladio", Y'cenza
The Palazzo Chiericati in Vicenza
(top photo) is one of Palladio's
most elegant constructions. Only a
small part of the Palazzo was built
during the architect's lifetime but
his original design was substantially
respected by those who followed
him. Lower photo, the loggias of
the Palazzo della Ragione or
"Basilica", at Vicenza were
designed by Palladio to cover the
fabric of a medieval Palazzo.
Planned in the late 1540s, they are
an outstanding example of the
growing richness and imagination
of Palladio's style.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
columns and on the crest of the central arch, seem to reflect and
echo the gesticulations of the participants in the drama being
acted out beneath them.
The impact of Palladio's work, like that of all great men, was
destined to be felt beyond his own time, especially during the eigh¬
teenth and the first half of the nineteenth century when there was
a revival of interest in Antiquity. Then Palladio's mansions and
villas rather than his churches and palaces were taken as models
for both town and country residences by architects in many coun¬
tries, in England and Ireland, France and Germany, Poland and
Russia, Italy, Scandinavia and the United States.
Renato Cevese
Palladio and world
architecture
Palladio is one of the most influential figures in the
development of Western architecture (photos
opposite page), above all in the Anglo-Saxon world
where a vogue for palladianism began in the 18th
century. One great admirer of Palladio's work was the
seventeenth-century French painter Poussin, who
took the neoclassical building in his Ashes of Phocias
(detail, left) directly from a Palladio drawing of the
Roman temple at Trevi. The façade has a striking
kinship with that of the famous Villa Rotonda, or Villa
Almerico near Vicenza (below) which is widely
considered to symbolize what Palladio sought to
achieve in secular architecture.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Palladian style can be seen in
Monticello, the famous mansion Thomas
Jefferson built for himself at
Charlottesville, Virginia (USA).
The Villa Krollkarnia, built in Warsaw
(Poland) by Demerlini (1786-1789).
Left, design entered by
Jefferson (under a
pseudonym) in a
competition for the
President's House in
Washington, D.C. was
directly inspired by
Palladio's Villa Rotonda. The
project was not adopted.
Pavilion at Castle Howard, Yorkshire (UK)
was designed by Sir John Vanbrugh and
built in 1724-26. The influence of Palladio's
neoclassical pavilions is again apparent.
The Villa Lopukhin at
Vvedenskoe (USSR)
designed by N. L'vov.
Above drawing of a project for a village of workmen's dwellings was
done in 1761 by Claude-Nicolas Ledoux, one of the most brilliant and
original adapters of the Palladian style in French architecture. The
project never came to fruition, but parts of another visionary scheme by
Ledoux, the Royal Saltworks at Arc-et-Senans in Franche-Comté, were
actually built (below). The treatment of volumes, soberness of
decorative features and harmony of buildings and landscape suggest
Ledoux's debt to Palladio.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Above left, central part of the proscenium
of the Olympic Theatre in Vicenza (see also
back cover). Although Palladio closely
followed a Greco-Roman model in this, his
last commission, the theatre nevertheless
bears the unmistakable imprint of his
creative imagination. Particularly
remarkable is the use of perspective in the
central corridor to conjure an impression of
depth from the limited space available.
Among those captivated by the Theatre is
the Spanish painter Salvador Dali, who
once wrote : "If I had to choose the places
which have made the strongest impression
of mystery on me, I should include
Palladio's theatre at Vicenza as being most
aesthetically mysterious and sublime".
Above right, Dali's 1937 painting Palladio's
Thalia Corridor. Right, another poetically
imaginative interior in a building by
Palladio. Paintings by Paolo Veronese
produce surprising illusions in a room of
the Villa Bárbaro at Maser.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
To the North Pole
on skis
by Dmitri Shparo
In May 1979 the members of a
Soviet expedition became the first
persons to reach the North Pole on
skis. Their long trek across drifting
ice was a both a sporting and a
scientific achievement. The article
below is based on notes jotted
down during the expedition by its
leader, Dimitri I. Shparo. Six other
men took part in the trek: Vladimir
Ledenev, a scientist, Yuri Khme-
levsky, who directed the group's
scientific work; Anatoly Melnikov,
an engineer; Vassili Chichkarev, a
manual worker; Vladimir Rakhma-
nov, a builder; and Vadim Davidov,
a doctor. The expedition was spon¬
sored by the Soviet youth news¬
paper Komsomolskaya Pravda.
ACCORDING to our calculations only
a three-hundred-metre stretch of
ice lay between us and the North
Pole. A vast and beautiful ice-field opened
out before our eyes, like a football stadium
but ten times bigger, with tiers of pack-ice
forming the stands.
We set off across the ice-field. After half
an hour I began to drop behind, only
catching up with the others near to an
enormous sheer-sided block of ice. The
crenellations of pack-ice all around us made
me think of the battlements of a castle.
Flat expanses of ice could be seen
through gaps in the frozen wall, and two
hundred metres further on we found
ourselves in a kind of field at the end of
which was a hummock shaped like a
haystack. I thought that this was where we
should put the Soviet flag, that' we should
pitch camp nearby and take photographs.
We formed a circle, each man with his
hand on his neighbour's shoulder. We had
DIMITRI I. SHPARO is a Soviet mathematician
and physicist who teaches at the Moscow Steel
and Alloys Institute. He has taken part in a num¬
ber ofpolar expeditions organized by Komsomol¬
skaya Pravda, the Soviet young people's daily.
been travelling for seventy-six days and had
covered 1,500 kilometres as the crow flies,
at least 2,000 if detours were taken into ac¬
count. It was ten years since we had first
talked of trying to reach the North Pole on
foot, and seven years since we had actually
started preparing our expedition.
At the turn of the century, the Americans
Frederic Cook and Robert Peary had reach¬
ed the Pole on sledges drawn by dogs. The
same feat was performed by the Englishman
Wally. Herbert in 1969 and the Japanese
Naomi Uemura in 1978. Eleven years ago, a
U.S. -Canadian expedition led by Ralph
Pleysted reached the Pole on motorized
sledges. Aircraft have landed at the Pole
several times and submarines have sailed to
it, and in 1977 the Soviet atom-powered ice¬
breaker Arktika became the first surface
vessel to reach the Pole through the ice. In
1937, the Soviet explorers I. Papanin, E.
Krenkel, P. Chirchov and E. Fedorov
established the first Soviet polar research
station and spent months on drifting ice.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
But no one had ever reached the Pole on
skis.
...Rudolf Island in the Franz Josef Land
Archipelago is the nearest piece of Soviet
territory to the Pole, which is 920 kilometres
away. Arctic Cape, the northernmost ex¬
tremity of Northern Land (Severnaya
Zemlya), is slightly further. Henrietta Island
in the Longa Archipelago, where we had
begun our journey on 16 March, is 1,450
kilometres from the Pole. Why did we
choose the longest route?
For one thing, the general drift of the ice
on meridian 164° East, just east of the
Longa Archipelago, is northerly and was
thus in our favour, whereas if we had started
from Franz Josef Land or Arctic Cape, we
should have encountered ice drifting from
west to east. The drift of the ice reduces the
difference in the distance between these
three points and the Pole. Even, if distance
and drift had been the only considerations it
would have made sense to start from Arctic
Cape or Rudolf Island.
But when we took into account the
ranges of ice-floes, stretches of open water
and other features of the relief, we decided
that the third route was the best. Besides,
Great Siberia, a vast stretch of open water
which does not freeze even in winter, lies
north of all the Soviet Arctic islands except
for Henrietta Island, which "bestrides" it.
This argument was decisive.
Our expedition was organized by the
newspaper Komsomolskaya Pravda and
financed by a students' sports club and a
number of other institutions, some of which
were interested in the scientific research we
would carry out during the journey. In addi¬
tion to us seven skiers, five other persons
were based on Kotelny Island (Novosobirsk
Islands) and at the Soviet "North Pole 24"
scientific research station. They were: dep¬
uty expedition leader and radio operator
Leonid Labutin; trainer and radio operator
Fedor Slokin; radio operator Georgi Ivanov;
and two reserves, radio operator Aleksandr
Chatokhin and navigator Mikhail Deev. Their
main task was to maintain daily contact bet¬
ween us skiers and the expedition's HQ in
Moscow.
Since we would be carrying everything
we needed on our backs, each item of
equipment and provisions had to meet
stringent weight and . size requirements.
Later, when we were asked what had been
the most arduous part of the experience,
five of us replied: "the rucksack". We also
carried reserves of petrol and provisions
(three meals a day for eighteen days, plus a
standing reserve for three days). Every fif¬
teen days an "llyushin 14" dropped five
parachute loads of provisions, petrol, batter¬
ies, skis, gloves, socks and other equip¬
ment.
A fully-loaded rucksack weighed between
45 and 48 kilos and got lighter by just over a
kilo a day. As we travelled, winter turned in¬
to summer, and the average temperature
rose by 24°, from -36° in March to -12° in
May. We had to leave many things behind,
but our rucksacks were none the lighter for
it because we filled them with new
notebooks dropped by parachute. When we
reached the end of the road our rucksacks
were as heavy as when we set out.
During our crossing of the Polar ice-cap
we did not see a soul, but we did often hear
the human voice. Using an "Orbit"
miniature receiver we checked the time each
morning from signals broadcast at pre¬
arranged moments. We tuned in to the
news, and listened to our friends and rela¬
tions. The radio was a godsend and brought
echoes of home and warmth.
The first stretcb of the journey was par¬
ticularly tough. We had to contend with a
torrent of water, shifting blocks of ice and
snow, some as high as two-storey houses,
immense frozen palaces collapsing before
our eyes. Everything around us was moving
at walking pace. Two skis fell into the water
and disappeared without trace. Chichkarev
and Khmelevsky tumbled into the water.
There was no time for them to change
clothes after this involuntary dip, for delay
could have spelled disaster. They had to
press on for another half hour at -30°, with
their clothes completely soaked.
We pitched our first camp on an ice-floe a
hundred metres in diameter. As the evening
wore on it became surrounded by black,
swirling water... The next morning we faced
the problem of how to continue without the
skis which had been lost. We decided to
empty twenty-four kilos out of one of the
sacks and to divide the load among the
other six. Each of us took turns to go for¬
ward on foot carrying the lighter rucksack. It
was much more exhausting than skiing with
a fifty-kilo load on your back.
In the next two weeks we found out what
the word cold really means. The sun hung
low on the horizon and in the evening it
disappeared completely. My tent was buf¬
feted by the north wind, and inside the
temperature was barely 8 degrees higher
than outside. We had trouble getting to
sleep; we felt strange and weak. The cold
dispelled any drowsiness. And so we pulled
our sleeping bags over our heads and as our
breath slowly warmed us up we gradually
dropped off to sleep. Sometimes the sleep¬
ing bags were so damp that they froze solid;
getting into them was like prising open a
clam. "Watch out, don't kill anyone with
your little eiderdown nest", was a barbed
joke that was heard time and again.
I knew that the Norwegian explorer
Nansen had had one of his fingers frostbit-
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
ten while he was asleep. In my case, when
my feet were so cold that I could stand it no
longer, I would crawl out of my sleeping bag
and bend and stretch each leg a hundred
times. It always worked.
Our faces and fingers were often frozen. It
was painful, but I always remembered
something Peary had written long before:
"We considered the freezing cold and
bleeding from the cheeks and the ears as
slight inconveniences which were part of the
great adventure. Pain and discomfort are in¬
evitable; when all's said and done it's not
bad". I shared Peary's sentiments.
During our laborious struggle across the
ice-floes we sometimes had to remove our
skis and take to our inflatable dinghies, a
small, 1.8 kilo model with a load capacity of
1 50 kilos, and a larger craft weighing 12 kilos
which could carry a load of 700 kilos.
Ice-floes, open water and thin ice were
our main obstacles. There was a risk of colli¬
sion with the ice-floes, while every gap in
the ice was a potential threat to our lives.
Gaps which open up suddenly and unex¬
pectedly in the ice are the great unknown
factor in the Polar region.
As we neared the Pole, we encountered
more water, more thin ice and broken blocks
of ice. During the first three weeks we ran
into southward drifting ice, something
which belied all the information we had been
given. We were equally astonished when an
ice-floe on which we camped on the 88th
parallel became surrounded with water, just
like our very first camp-site. Near to land this
phenomenon may happen when strong
winds whip up wide stretches of water; we
had probably hit on the very spot in mid-
ocean where the speed of the ocean cur¬
rents suddenly changes and breaks up the
ice. From 1 to 4 May we saw Nature's snow-
plough in action as the wind backed from
north to south, then north and back again to
south. This tempest transformed the ice into
lakes, rivers and torrents.
The characteristics of ice came to acquire
a special meaning for us: if it was thick we
felt safe; if it drifted it was either a blessing
or a curse, depending on the direction; salt
in the snow helped our skis to slide more
smoothly and added flavour to our food;
when there was no sun we used snow-
flurries,- ice-floes and water channels as
landmarks. We kept a detailed record of our
experiences, meticulously noting down
what we thought of our equipment and ra¬
tions. I hope that these notes will be useful
to scientists. We cooked three hot meals a
day: buckwheat porridge with milk, melted
butter and dehydrated meat in the evening;
porridge for breakfast; during the day we
prepared dehydrated cottage cheese. Ra
tions also included tea, coffee, chocolate,
sugar, biscuits, bacon, garlic sausage and
dry sausage.
We had to take great care not to overeat
on rest-days. Hungry though we were and
important though it was to restore our
strength, it was essential not to eat too
much. Sticking to a balanced diet was no
easy matter.
During the first stage of the expedition,
the food ration was a kilo per person per
day; later this was increased to 1,200 gram¬
mes. One of the dilemmas facing us was
whether to eat more and carry a heavier
load, or eat less and travel lighter. Eventually
we opted for the first approach. This was
the right decision: we had so far to go that
the more nourishment we could get the
better.
In collaboration with the members of the
expedition based on Kotelny Island and at
the Polar research station, we also had to
solve practical problems of physical
geography. We studied ice formations, drift
phenomena, the size and disposition of ice¬
floes, the dimensions of ice-fields and the
number of water-channels. Throughout the
trek we measured the magnetic variations
and carried out important experiments1 on
the movement of radio waves and the con- w
centration of ions in the atmosphere. f
GLACIAL
ENCOUNTER
with a denizen of the
frozen North
THE SKI'S THE LIMIT,
especially when you
need a framework for
your shelter in the midst
of the Arctic wastes. But
often during the 76-day
journey skis were
impracticable for scaling
mini mountain ranges of
Ice. Then they had to be
carried, adding to to the
burden of equipment and
supplies which the
trekkers remembered as
the toughest part of their
experience.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Ti
1
/ POLAR PERSPECTIVES
traced by ski tracks
across a stretch of thin
ice, one of the worst
hazards faced by the
skiers.
But the expedition's principal scientific
purpose was to study human behaviour in
Arctic conditions and the reactions of a
small group of persons to life on drifting ice.
Psychologists are now using our observa¬
tions to help them study the mechanisms of
psychological adaptation to stress, group
dynamics during a long-distance trek, emo¬
tional responses and physical and
psychological aptitudes for work in Arctic
conditions.
The inception of the Komsomolskaya
Pravda polar expedition goes back to 1970,
when five Muscovites trekked across the
Taimyr peninsula to Komsomolskaya Pravda
Island in the Laptev Sea and on towards
Cape Chelyuskin, the northernmost extremi¬
ty of our continent.
In 1971 the members of the expedition
crossed Northern Land. In the years that
followed our group worked in increasingly
close co-operation with the scientists of the
Institute of Medico-Biological Problems of
the USSR Ministry of Health. The depart¬
ments and laboratories of psychology, nutri¬
tion, hygiene and stomatology, as well as
specialists in protective optics, also took a
keen interest in the project.
In 1972 we embarked on our first expedi¬
tion on drifting ice when we set off from the
shores of Chukotka across Long Strait
towards Wrangel Island. That same year, at
the fourth national conference on cosmic
biology and aviation and space medicine at
Kaluga, we put forward the idea of a North
Pole ski expedition which would also carry
out a far-reaching medical and scientific
research programme. When Polar specialists
and well-known scientists pronounced that
such an expedition was not only feasible but
of uncontestable scientific value, prepara¬
tions began in earnest.
It was a historic moment when in 1976 we
set out on drifting ice from Wrangel Island
to station "North Pole 23". For this expedi¬
tion Vladimir Rachmanov and Vadim
Davidov joined the team which had crossed
Long Strait in 1972: Vladimir Ledenev, Yuri
Khmelevsky, Anatoli Melnikov and myself.
Thus the practicability of the Polar expedi¬
tion was put to the test several times.
If I were asked to name the fundamental
quality that enabled us to conquer the Polar
ice, I should say without hesitation: "the
people in the group and their team spirit".
Chatokhin and Davidov had already worked
in the Arctic, but not the others who were
mathematicians, engineers, hydroelectric
construction workers, physicists, and com¬
munications technicians. But during our
years of preparation we had learned to know
and love the Arctic wastes and we were cer¬
tain that in the high latitudes at "the top of
the world" we could reach the limits of
human capability.
B Dmitri I. Shparo
Photo V. Kuzmm © Tass, Moscow
ON TOP OF THE WORLD.
On 1 June 1979
journalists and sports
officials were flown in to
join the seven skiers as
they celebrated their
arrival at the Pole. Here
they pose with
mementoes of earlier
Russian North Pole
expeditions and
explorers. In foreground,
an unsinkable container
full of documents from
the annals of polar
exploration.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
&
Ji^ ^
ss*>
m . .,
Over 150,000 figures engraved in rock by prehistoric artists during
an 8,000-year period which lasted until the dawn of the Christian
era have been listed in Valcamonica, an Alpine valley north of
Brescia in Italy. The first figure was discovered at the end of the
last century but it is only since 1956 that a systematic study has
been made of the region. The carved rocks, are carefully cleaned
and photographed, and then reproduced in plaster casts or tracings
(above). Valcamonica constitutes the richest source of
documentation about the life and art, myths and symbols of
prehistoric man in Europe.
Valcamonica
An Italian valley is the world's largest gallery
of prehistoric rock art
PERCHED high up in the Italian" Alps,
the remote Valley of Camonica is the
site of the world's largest gallery of
prehistoric art. Its more than 150,000 pre¬
historic rock figures are authentic
documents created over a period of 8,000
years, which are helping historians to
retrace the evolution of European civilization
from prehistoric times.
The sixty-mile-long Valcamonica lies to
the north of the city of Brescia and stretches
from Lake Iseo on the edge of the Po valley
right up to the Tonale Pass in the heart of
by Emmanuel Anati
the Alps. The Romans built a road, the Via
Valeriana, which crossed the valley from
north to south. Before the Roman period the
valley was accessible from the south only by
boat across the lake, and from the north on¬
ly by two Alpine passes which are still
covered with snow for several months of the
year. High mountains make access from the
east or west very difficult.
Most of the figures engraved on the rock
are concentrated in the central part of the
valley, at the point most remote from all
means of access; 90 per cent of the figures
are located in an area measuring six by fou,r
kilometres.
Various archaeological discoveries have
been made at Valcamonica and in neigh¬
bouring areas: remains of villages, tombs,
ancient terraced farms, old mines and, more
recently, traces of roads and bridges. But
Valcamonica's main archaeological
characteristic is its rock art.
Some of the engravings were uncovered
in the course of excavations, while others
appear on rock surfaces some of which
measure as much as fifty square metres and L
contain more than a thousand figures. The *
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
-NEOLITHIC --3 800
uaumocicu
Humos
EPIPAIAEO-
LITHIC
lENUrifE
Wlti
BEFORE
6000
ac.
CHUCO-
LITHIC
BRONZE
ACE
TRANSITION
OF BRONZE
TO IRON
AGE
IRON
AGE
ANTHROPO-
MORPHS
" CERVIDAE WEAPONS
X
T
r
*
I
Î
Tí
¿
^
rl
Art
É
\(
fir
rfl
t*iW
Äfi
fill
o
90
I
:::))
f
^
figures are descriptive or symbolic, or both:
they are the work of generations of men
who lived in a specific territory and found a
way of expressing their own realities, their
own beliefs and their own feelings,
in an art form that has been preserved up
to the present time.
Research being carried out at
Valcamonica is aimed at evaluating a period
of eight thousand years during which hun¬
ting clans of the old Stone Age were
gradually transformed into tribes with in¬
creasingly complex activities and structures.
When, after four hundred generations, the
Camunians, as the Romans called them,
were incorporated into the Roman Empire,
they were already a nation with the
economic and social structure, the division
of labour and the class divisions which
characterize European civilization from that
moment onwards.
Study of the engraving techniques, the
styles, the various layers and super-
impositions, and the figurative elements that
every style possesses, indicates that Camu-
30
Wooded hill country
surrounds a Camonica
valley prehistoric rock art
site, the Luine hill near
Darfo (right). Rock rising
out of vegetation at
centre of photo is
inscribed with figures
which, like all the others
located in the district,
have been cleaned,
photographed and
recorded on special
tracing paper. Figure of a
deer wounded by arrows
(below) is a carving from
Luine. The artist used
natural cracks in the
rock to depict the
animal's legs. The
engraving, one of the
most ancient in the
Camonica valley, dates
from the Proto-Camunian
or Epipalaeolithic period.
The circular incisions
were added later.
Photo © Seminario e Centro Camuno di Studi Preistonci, Capo di Ponte, Brescia
nian art went through a process of stylistic
and conceptual evolution. These mutations
are of great importance because they open
up a new chapter in the history of art, and
throw light on primitive attempts at compo¬
sition and drawing in perspective. Through
them we can follow the evolution of a
symbolic art, and the birth of a figurative art
which is one of the oldest studied so far.
But this study also shows the ideological
and psychological evolution of a people, and
the relationships it maintained with other
peoples, as well as illustrating the historical
events that determined its destiny. It
attempts to reconstruct the epic story of the
Camunians, a people unknown until recent
times, and lift the veil that has lain over them
for the two thousand years since they
ceased to be an autonomous nation. Who
were they? Where did they originate? How
did they come to form themselves into a
nation? What vicissitudes had they experi¬
enced before the Roman Conquest?
Until about 10,000 years ago Valcamonica
was still covered with ice and neither ani¬
mals nor man could survive in such extreme
climatic conditions. But with the climatic
changes that marked the transition from the
Pleistocene to the Holocene epoch, life
came to the valley. Plant life was followed
by animal life, and after the animals came
the hunters. During the period of the thaw,
millions of cubic metres of ice melted and
the waters swept down on the great plains.
The plains of Padua, the Rhone, the Rhine
and the Danube were transformed into vast
swamps or enormous watercourses. Driven
out by the waters, some groups left the
plains and peopled the valley for the first
time.
Rock-art tells us the history of man from
the time when the clans of semi-nomadic
hunters came to the Alpine area after the ice
had receded, up to the moment when the
might of the Roman Empire drastically
altered their destiny.
The earliest traces date from 10,000 years
ago. In the beginning, during the Proto-
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Camunian period, Camunian rock-art resem¬
bled that of other European populations. Its
various forms show similar styles, concepts
and manifestations; so they probably had
common links and traditions. The sub-
naturalist style of rock-art in different parts
of Europe and the Middle East was created
by clans of huntsmen who were gradually
learning about cattle-raising; they were
semi-nomadic human groups who moved
about from valley to valley, and along the
plains, in search of animals to hunt.
The Palaeolithic art of the Franco-
Cantabrian caves (Altamira, Lascaux, etc.)
came to an end in central Europe with the
large-scale climatic changes that character¬
ized the transition from the Pleistocene to
the Holocene epoch, 10,000 to 12,000 years
ago. At that time there were still a few peri¬
pheral human groups outside the Franco-
Cantabrian area and during the early post¬
glacial era figurative rock-art flourished on
rock surfaces and in small caves in the Ibe¬
rian Peninsula, in the Arctic regions of Scan¬
dinavia, in central Anatolia and in southern
Italy.
Proto-Camunian art represents a link bet¬
ween this Palaeolithic rock-art and post-
Palaeolithic art ; but so far, no link elements
between the Proto-Camunian sub-
naturalistic style and the styles of the follow¬
ing periods have come to light in Valcamo¬
nica. From the fifth millennium BC, that is,
from the Neolithic period, however, there is
evidence of a stylistic evolution starting with
profoundly symbolic and hermetic composi¬
tions and moving on to highly complex des
criptive and anecdotal scenes in the later
periods.
Between the late Neolithic and the early
Bronze Age (3200-2500 BC), a wave of
ideological-religious influences served to
unify some of the main rock areas of the
Alps: Valcamonica, Valtellina and Upper
Adigio, the Swiss Valais and the Valley of
Aosta. Later, at the end of the Bronze Age,
around the year 1000 BC, a new wave of
external cultural influence joined the central
Alpine zone to the area under the general
sphere of influence of Urnfield culture (axul-
ture that existed in central Europe at the end
of the second millennium BC).
It is interesting to follow the general evo¬
lution in rock-art themes, from the Proto-
Camunian period when man exclusively
depicted large animals, sketching the con¬
tours with a typical hunter's eye. In the
course of the Neolithic period, animal
figures almost completely disappear, and
man becomes the principal theme of his
own figurative creativity.
At the beginning of the next period, the
Chalcolithic or Eneolithic (characterized by
the use of copper), around the year 3300
BC, among the many cultural acquisitions,
three new elements suddenly appear toge¬
ther: the cart and wheel, metal-work, and a
new type of monument, the menhir-statue.
These three elements reached the Alpine
area simultaneously, in the wake of Indo-
European influences from the Balkans.
The cart, that great discovery, opened up
vast new possibilities for transporting per
sons and objects. This led to an enormous
increase in trade, and greater freedom of
movement for families, clans and even entire
tribes.
One result of these new technological ac¬
quisitions was a change in social and
cultural standards. The man who possessed
metal tools had a physical advantage over
his neighbour who had not acquired them.
The use of metal also produced a new and
much wider trade, and led to far-reaching-
economic, social and political changes. The
man who owned a mine had to defend it;
and in order to defend it he needed men and
arms. The man who traded in metal ac¬
cumulated more wealth than he needed, and
soon had a great advantage over the others,
both in physical strength and economic
power. Society itself changed and became
more complex because the scope of the clan
was no longer sufficient for all the activities
that metal-working and the metal trade
involved.
Finally, the menhir-statues attest to
another type of acquisition: they show the
advent of a new religion, a universal religion,
which soon spread from the Caucasus to the
shores of the Atlantic, taking into orbit
many different populations scattered
throughout Europe.
These three factors, which appear in close
succession at the end of the fourth millen¬
nium BC, transformed the social and
economic structure and the mental attitudes
of the inhabitants of many regions of
Europe. The new religion illustrated by the
menhir-statues involved a new type of social
Ranks of praying human figures seem to march across the rock
in this monumental composition at Naquane near the village of
Capo di Ponte. The prehistoric art of Camonica underwent a
striking change in Neolithic times : animal figures disappeared
almost entirely and the schematized human form became the
dominant motif.
n late Neolithic times (4th millennium BC), the
use of symbols in Valcamonica art began to be
replaced by descriptive representations and the
naturalistic depiction of the human form. A
female divinity is surrounded by symbols, as
yet undeciphered, in this two-metre-long rock
engraving at Sellero in the Camonica valley.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Incisions on* the statue-
menhir, (left) may depict
a divinity, with the solar
disc at the top as the
"face" and two axes at
each side as the "arms".
In the centre are
triangular-bladed daggers
and, further below, three
parallel lines which could
represent a belt. The
composition, at Bagnolo
in the Camonica valley,
dates from the
Chalcolithic or Eneolithic
age (3rd millennium BC).
Archaeologists have
unearthed similar axes
and daggers belonging to
the Remedello culture
which flourished in
northern Italy during the
same period.
The "running priest" (right)
is one of the most enigmatic
figures at Naquane, where a
hundred incised rocks have
been discovered. The
Italian department of
antiquities has created a
national park to protect the
district and its sites.
structure and new human relationships. The
new physical and economic power, the
capacity for trade and accumulation of
wealth provided by the discovery of the cart
and metal-work, triggered off a. chain
reaction.
Trade and cultural movements of com¬
pletely new dimensions ensued: the trans¬
mission of information -went hand in hand
with the carts and merchants. With the ac¬
cumulation of wealth, man began to hanker
after more than the bare essentials of life.
The need to establish contact with other
populations in order to develop trade also
gave social relationships a new dimension.
The territory was prospected in the search
for metal, and the inhabitants acquired con¬
scious knowledge about some aspects of
nature, of the structure of soil and stone,
which led to new lines of thought. "Stone"
contained valuable materials and possessed
hidden powers of which man had been
hitherto unaware. This development was to
give rise to a new type of philosophy and
a new ideology.
At the end of the fourth and during the
third millennium BC, the formation of a new
type of stratified society continued, and this
is reflected in rock-art. The conception of
composition in Camunian art changed dur¬
ing this period. Formerly, rock-artists seem
to have attributed little importance to the
precise position of isolated figures within the
whole; but, henceforth, the series of arms,
symbols and animals in monumental com¬
positions are organized in a row, in
keeping with a new concept of order and
space, according to an arrangement
predetermined by a new type of discipline,
and an attempt at rational use of space. This
new way of representing things, of covering
rock surfaces with figures, shows a fun¬
damental change in human psychology, and
in man's way of seeing and thinking; the
mental order evident in the rock engravings
was necessarily a reflection of the new social
system that been established.
Later, in the second and fjrst millennia
BC, in the Bronze and Iron Ages, there was
a further upsurge of political entities, and
tribal societies continued to develop until
they achieved the status of real nations.
In rock-art this evolution is reflected in the
style and series of themes represented in the
various epochs. But what is more important,
each period manifests specific ideas on com¬
position and association, and reflects speci¬
fic ideologies and beliefs. This enables us to
trace the process of accumulation of an
increasingly extensive cultural equipment
and of constant technological and material
acquisitions over eight millennia.
The hunters of the Epipalaeolithic or
Mesolithic Age (the transition period from
the Palaeolithic to the Neolithic), between
the years 8000 and 5500 BC, used a concep¬
tual structure determined by hunting and
the animals hunted up to that time. No nar¬
rative scenes specific to that time, and con¬
sequently, no hunting scenes, have come to
light. There is only the animal, sometimes,
transfixed by the lance that has brought him
down. Man's idée fixe, the idée fixe of the
hunter, was the animal, the largest and the
"finest".
With the advent of farming, man replaced
animals as the fundamental theme. The
idealization of the human being follows an
interesting process between 5500 and 3200
BC. Early on in this itinerary we find man
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Elegantly stylized figure of
an animal assailed by arrows
(left) dates from the Late
Bronze Age (around 1000
BC). Near the animal is a
figure usually asociated with
the idea of death.
The figure of the god Cernunnos,
crowned with deer horns, a snake
around his waist, is incised in the
stone at a prehistoric site at Zurla
(right). At lower right of the scene,
created in the late Iron Age (around
400 BC), is the figure of a worship¬
per with arms upraised.
Hi
M 4 i '¡11*
TT r\"< « *^éb¿ \b
¥
The document above, a tracing of the central part of the Great Rock at Naquane, gives
some idea of the amazing profusion of figures (876 in all) which were carved into a
fifty-metre-long surface during five historical epochs. In some cases the artists incised
designs in patches of rock already used by their predecessors, creating what at first
sight seems to be an inextricable pictographic maze. Scholars are using the intricate
iconography of the Great Rock to help trace the historical and stylistic development of
rock art in the Camonica valley. One particularly puzzling feature is the square paddle¬
like motif, thought to have been a magic symbol with occult powers.
praying next to the sun's disc, next to the
axè or some other symbol. Later, there is an
extension of this tendency, and many
symbols and anthropomorphic characters
appear in a single scene. There are scenes of
sun-worship, scenes representing the cult of
the dead, scenes of groups of men dancing
or participating in other activities which
seem to represent various actions and
various ideas within a single context.
In the second part of the Neolithic Age,
from the year 4000 BC, we find the develop¬
ment of divinities as such, in anthropomor¬
phic form. At first, we have schematic faces
with large eyes; then, at the end of the Neo¬
lithic Age, around the year 3300 BC, we find
divinities two or three metres tall. These
rock-pictures attest to a mental develop¬
ment which is at the very root of our way of
seeing, thinking and conceiving things.
The Bible states that God created man in
his own image; in the Neolithic Age in the
Alps, we realize that the exact reverse
occurred: man created God in -his own
image. The exaltation of man created the
Superman, the Great Spirit, the Divinity
with the anthropomorphic traits. At the end
of the Neolithic Age, this ideological-
developmental process is interrupted and
there is a change in direction.
During the Neolithic Age, social and eco¬
nomic structures as well as intellectual inte¬
rests underwent a change. During the
Mesolithic Age man was essentially a gath-
rer of food, in the Neolithic he had become a
producer of food; but in the Eneolithic
period, and later in the Bronze and Iron
Ages, the production and gathering of food
played an increasingly minor role in remune¬
rative activities, while craftsmen and mer¬
chants gradually gained economic supre¬
macy. Economic interests underwent a
change; non-essential, luxury goods acqui¬
red more importance and became symbols
of success and social position. The exalta¬
tion of the product led to the worship of
objects, the glorification of what man had
created with his own hands.
Arms and other metal objects had super¬
natural power attributed to them and were
depicted with increasing frequency. Attri¬
butes of divinities or mythological ancestors
in the menhir-statues and monumental com¬
positions, daggers, axes, breastplates, pen¬
dants and belts, were not only transformed
into symbols of power and prestige, but also
acquired autonomy as supernatural powers
in the ideology of the times. Man changed
from being a creator to being a subject, and
became dependent on these luxury articles,
the products which he himself had created.
In the late Bronze Age, social patterns
became more complex; a society of specia¬
lists and a more diversified economy emer¬
ged. This was a polyvalent society; the chief
was a "Father Superior" to the nascent
nobility, to the warriors, to the tradesmen
and craftsmen; and it was thanks to their
economic and military power and their inter¬
national relations that he was able to steer
the destinies of the tribe and enhance his
own power.
Alongside the burgeoning aristocracy, a
polytheistic Olympus developed, where
gods and heroes imitated and exalted the
heroic deeds of mortals. The rock-pictures
of supermen engraved by the Camunian
artists at this time seem to have much in
common with Greek and Germanic mytho¬
logy. Once more Man seems to have created
God in his own image, concentrating his
aspirations and sublimating the reasons for
his frustrations in this ¡mage.
From man's vicissitudes which we find
reflected in the Valcamonica findings, the
history of the heartland of Europe can be
divided vertically into ten millennia. The his¬
torical evolution of the Camunians may well
be the prototype of a history embracing
much wider areas and which, in many
ways, reflects the vicissitudes encountered
during the formative period of European
civilization.
Valcamonica's rock engravings have pro¬
vided an exceptional mass of data and infor¬
mation about their authors. So far, there is
no other cycle of rock-art historical narrative
in Europe, and perhaps in the entire world,
which has endured for so long, offers such a
wide variety of cultural horizons, and whose
cultural stages can be followed with such
precision. H
EMMANUEL ANATI, Italian-born Israeli ar¬
chaeologist and anthropologist, is director of the
Camunian Centre of Prehistoric Studies at Capo
di Ponte (Italy) and general secretary of the Inter¬
national Association for the Study of Prehistoric
and Ethnologic Religion (IASPER). He has led
prehistórica! and ethnological research projects in
Europe, the Near East India and Australia.
Among his works in English are Camonica Valley
(1961) published by Knopf (New York), Rock Art
in Central Asia 14 vols, Louvain, 1972-75), and
Evolution in Style (Capo di Ponte, Italy 1976).
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
*4
[^5^7^Si ?
^û»
Eft»
*
11^ a r «m i a» i»
ni m \\
flr
mil
i
The Tree
of
Life
This "tree of life" was created at Unesco's Paris headquarters by a group of children
who took part in an "intercultural workshop" held by Unesco's International Fund
for the Promotion of Culture as part of the world children's drawing competition
organized by Unesco, Unicef and the United Nations High Commission for Refugees.
Successfully overcoming the language barrier, the ten prizewinners chosen trom
600,000 competitors from 89 countries worked together under the direction of two
adult artists, Amar Nath Sehgal of India and Nacer Khemir of Tunisia. The idea for
the project came from the story of the oldest baobab tree in the world, whose bran¬
ches are supposed to tell tales invented by children. The work was on show during
the international "peace Forum" held at Unesco House in November 1979.
Meiji Japan
The Editors wish to draw the attention of readers to a discrepancy which occurred in
the first paragraph of the article by Professors Keichi Oshima and Keiichi Furuya, entit¬
led Meiji Japan: a case study in industrialization and published in our November 1979
issue. This paragraph should have read as follows: "The development and industrializati¬
on ofJapan can only be properly understood if considered within the context of complex
historical, geographical and social elements; during the Meiji era (1868 to 1912), these
elements combined to create an environment which encouraged the rapid modernization
of a country that had previously been almost completely isolated from outside
influences. " The Editors regret this discrepancy.
Bookshelf
Recent Unesco books
Terminology of Adult Education,
prepared by Colin Titmus, Paz But-
tedahl, Diana Ironside and Paul
Lengrand for the International Bureau of
Education. 1979, 154 pp. (28 F)
Directory of Educational Docu¬
mentation and Information Services
(3rd edition). Prepared by the Inter¬
national Bureau of Education. 1979,
79 pp. (11 F)
Books received
Kiribati, Aspects of History, a book
written by a team of men and women of
the Gilbert Islands and published on the
occasion of the Islands' independence as
the nation of Kiribati. It is not an ex¬
haustive academic history but sets out to
present a Gilbertese perspective on
material which has hitherto only been
available through the eyes of others.
Published jointly by the Institute of
Pacific Studies and Extension Services,
University of the South Pacific, and the
Ministry of Education, Training and
Culture, Tarawa, Kiribati. 212 pp., 1979.
Nareau's Nation: A Portrait of the
Gilbert Islands, by Tony Whincup. A
photographic record of Kiribati life.
Stacey International Publishers, London,
1979.
Energy-Efficient Community Plan¬
ning: A Guide to Saving Energy and
Producing Power at the Local Level,
by James Ridgeway. A survey of conser¬
vation programmes and alternative
energy systems now being used in cities
and towns of the United States. The JG
Press, Inc., Box 351, Emmaus, Penn¬
sylvania 18049. 1979, 221 pp.
The Diminishing Returns of
Technology, An Essay on the Crisis
in Economic Growth, by Orio Giarini
and Henri Loubergé. Pergamon Interna¬
tional Library, Oxford, U.K., and New
York. 122 pp., 1978.
Child Workers Today, by James
Challis and David Elliman, in association
with The Anti-Slavery Society. Quater-
maine House Ltd., London, U.K. 1979.
170 pp.
Beyond Manila: Philippine Rural
Problems in Perspective, by Gelia T.
Castillo. International Development
Research Centre, Ottawa, Canada, 1979.
420 pp.
China, by Emil Schultess, Artemis
Publishing Co., Zurich. 1979.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
THE ARTS Ol THE BOOK
in Central Asia
«PINDIA PUBLICATION* HinSSCO
Just published...
A scholarly and beautiful volume on the arts and skills of
manuscript production during a classic period of Islamic
civilization, from the 14th to the early 16th century. An
international team of scholars surveys:
The Arts of Calligraphy
The Art of Illumination
The Art of Bookbinding
History of Miniature Painting
Compiled over a period of ten years, the book is a product of a
Unesco-sponsored study programme on the civilizations of the
peoples of Central Asia, in co-operation with the International
Association for the Study of Central Asia. Many of the
illustrations, notably those from collections in Istambul, have
never before been published.
General Editor: Basil Gray, Fellow of the British Academy,
formerly Keeper in the British Museum
328 pages 250 illustrations 350 French francs
Co-published with Serindia Publications, London, who have exclusive
sales rights in the UK, and share the market with Unesco in the rest of
Europe, in India and the Middle East; and with Shambhala Publications
of Boulder, Colorado, who have sales rights for North and South
America.
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Older from any bookseller or writs direct to the
National Distributor in your country. (See list
below; name* of distributor« In countries not lis¬
ted, along with subscription rates In local cur¬
rency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P.O.
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept, P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St , Melbourne (Victonal, 3000.
AUSTRIA. Dr. Franz Ham, Verlags-und Kommissionsbuch¬
handlung, Industriehof Stadlau, Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasse 5, 1220
Wien. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd , Ittefaq Building, 1, R K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only. N V. Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing Keesmglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Anrwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent. Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13 - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que H3H
1M7. CHINA. China National Publications Import Corpora¬
tion, West Europe Department, P.O. Box 88, Peking
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makanos 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box
1722, Nicosia - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S N T L , Spalena
51, Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura, 11 Sou-
kenicka, Prague 1 For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers,
Hurbanovonam 6,893 31 Bratislava - CSSR. - DENMARK.
Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Norregade, DK 1165, Copenha¬
gen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for
Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo.
ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P 0 Box 2996, Addis
Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1,
SF-00100 Helsinki 10. - FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7,
place de Fontenoy, 75700 Pans, CCP. 12598-48. - GERMAN
DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710
Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R.
FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier (German
ed. only): 53 Bonn 1, Colmantstrasse 22. For scientific maps
only: GEO CENTER D7 Stuttgart 80, Postfach 800830. Other
publications: S. Karger GmbH, Karger Buchhandlung, Ange¬
rhofstrasse 9, Postfach 2, 8034 Germenng/Munchen.
GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd , P.O. Box 195,
Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The
University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop
of Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legón, P.O. Box 1,
Legón. - GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. - HONG
KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial
Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen Swindon Book Co., 13-
15, Lock Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY. Akadémiai Konyves-
bolt, Vâci u. 22, Budapest V; A K.V. Konyvturosok Boltia,
Nèpkoztarsasâg utja 16, Budapest VI. ICELAND. Snaebiorn
JonsSon & Co., H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA.
Orient Longman Ltd , Kamam Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay
400038, 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai,
Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf Ali Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1
Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-Depots: Oxford Book Et Stationery Co
17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Sandra House, New Delhi;
Publications Section, Ministry of Education and Social Welfare,
511 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan, New Delhi 110001.
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah
Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr Sam Ratulangie 47,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution
Co , 28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Shahreza Avenue, P.O. Box
314/1486, Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco, Ave.
Iranchahr Chomall No. 300, B P. 1533, Teheran. IRAQ.
McKenzie's Bookshop, AI -Rashid Street, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd.,
Ballymount Road, Walkmstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL. ABC.
Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv 61000
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101
Water Lane, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc.,
Shuhwa Toranomon 3bldg, 23-6, Toranomon 3-Chome, Mmato-
ku, Tokyo 105, KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O.
Box 30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, P.O Box Central 64, Seoul. - KUWAIT. The
Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait - LESOTHO.
Mazenod Book Centre, P O Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern
Africa. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd , P.O. Box
286, Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency for Development of
Publication & Distribution, P 0. J3ox 34-35, Tripoli
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue,
Luxembourg, MALAYSIA. Federal Publications, Lot 8323,
JI.222, Petaling Jaya, Selangor. - MALTA. Sapienzas, 26
Republic Street. Valletta. MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company
Ltd , 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis. MONACO. British
Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. - NETHERLANDS.
For the "Unesco Koerier" Dutch edition only Systemen
Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75, Amsterdam-1007. Agent for all
Unesco publications. N.V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9,
The Hague. - NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine
N.V.. P.O. Box 200, Willemstad, Curaçao. NA.- NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, Government
Bookshops at: Rutland Street. P 0. Box 5344, Auckland, 130,
Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Chnstchurch; Alma Street, P 0
Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P O. Box 1104, Dunedm;
Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington. NIGERIA. The
University Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan,
P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of Nsukka; The University
Bookshop of Lagos.The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of
Zana. NORWAY. All publications. Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers). Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco
Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-e-azam,
P.O. Box No 729, Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404 -
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias 6 Andrade Ltda, Livraria
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. - SEYCHELLES. New
Service Ltd , Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé.
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19. SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951,
Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA. All publications. Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libn Building, Church Street,
P O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg
SOUTHERN RHODESIA. Textbook Sales (PVTI Ltd., 67 Union
Avenue, Salisbury. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop. 100
Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2.
SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. -
SWEDEN. All publications A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Regenngsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327
" Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Forbundet,
Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. -
SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag, 5
Ramistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva
11, C C P 12-236 - TANZANIA. Dar-es Salaam Bookshop,
P.O B 9030 Dar-es-Salaam. - THAILAND. Nibondh and Co.
Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box
402, Bangkok: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern
Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road,
Bangkok TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. National Commission
for Unesco, 18 Alexandra Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W I.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal Caddesi, Beyoglu,
Istambul. UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S E I., and Government Bookshops in
London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham,
Bristol. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue South,
New York, N.Y. 10010. - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga,
Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga, Trg
Republike 5/8, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba Slovenje, Titova C 25,
P.O.B 50-1, Ljubliana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
January 1980 from
A bulletin published by
the Office
of Public Information
Unesco
7, Place de Fontenoy
75700 Paris, France
news
unesco
Unesco Peace
Forum Calls for
Action to Correct
perilously insecure'
World Situation
A Peace Forum of fifty eminent
personalities which met at Unesco's Paris
headquarters from 12 to 16 November
expressed "pressing concern" with the
preservation of world peace and respect
for human rights and unanimously
condemned torture in all its forms.
The causes of the world's "perilously
insecure" situation were not only
armaments, the participants said, but
"prejudice, irresponsibility and
misinformation". It was generally agreed
that the situation was being aggravated by
arms spending, currently running at $ 1
million a minute, while armaments in
stock represented three tons of TNT for
every inhabitant of the globe.
For once, said the communiqué, every
participant was on the same side,
although the individuals taking part came
Jean d'Ormesson, of the French Academy,
opens the debate at the Peace Forum in the
presence of Unesco Director-General Amadou-
Mahtar M'Bow.
from many different countfies of
divergent political systems and viewpoints.
In fact, the participants who met at the
invitation of the International Council for
Philosophy and Humanistic Studies
represented every continent and a wide
variety of backgrounds and specialities.
There were four Nobel Prize winners,
three former Heads of State, a former
Prime Minister, jurists, economists,
educationalists, doctors, journalists,
artists, musicians, an actor and a poet.
Before the Forum began they heard a
message of encouragement from Pope
John-Paul II.
Stressing that action was now
necessary, the Forum decided to set upa
working group to continue its efforts;
there was a need to establish a new world
order which would correct the dangerous
imbalance in which 30 per cent of the
world's countries used 80 per cent of its
resources and rectify "a situation in
which the imbalance in trade combined
with the effects of inflation was hindering
the development of the Third World."
Communication
Commission
Completes Work
on Final Report
The Unesco-sponsored
International Commission for the
Study of Communication Problems
has completed two years of work
by adopting its final report and
recommendations.
Mr. Sean MacBride, Nobel and
Lenin Peace prizewinner and
chairman of the sixteen-member
commission, is expected to present
the report at the beginning of
January to Unesco Director-
General Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow.
Although the report has been
formally approved by the
commission, Mr. MacBride said,
individual members who might
wish to dissociate themselves from
one or another particular point
would have the opportunity to do
so up to January 5. The report
would then be translated and
reproduced in Unesco's official
languages and distributed to
member states. The report is
expected to be a major item on the
agenda of the Unesco General
Conference next autumn in
Belgrade, Yugoslavia.
The report consists of five parts:
Communication and
Society major dimensions and
issues; Communication Todaythe
institutional and professional
framework; and Communication
Tomorrow conclusions and
recommendations.
Continued page IV
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
East Meets West at Venice Music ¡Institute
Western European music is taught in
schools and conservatories around the
world, but until recently a Westerner who
wanted to study the musical traditions of
India or Indonesia or Vietnam had to go
to those countries to do so.
This has now changed. Thanks to a
grant from Unesco's International Fund
for the Promotion of Culture, an
Intercultural School of Music has been
established in Venice, where since last
September about sixty students from
Italy, France, Belgium, the Netherlands
and Switzerland have been introduced to
the music of India, south-east Asia and
central Africa. Italian folk music also
figures on the programme.
According to Alain Daniélou, director
of the Istituto Internazionale di Música
Comparata with which the school is
affiliated, the aim is to promote both a
theoretical and a practical knowledge of
the great musical traditions of the world,
traditions which have had a profound
influence on the development of Western
music. Thus the programme of the
Intercultural School of Music combines
university-level courses on the historical,
aesthetic and cultural aspects of these
traditions with practical teaching of vocal
and instrumental techniques.
"It would be impossible to study the
phenomenon of language having
knowledge of one language only," says
Daniélou, "and the same is true of music.
Different musical systems employ
different methods of organizing
sounds they might almost be called
grammars to construct sound structures
which enable sentiments to be expressed,
and to create different systems of
aesthetics.
"While it is not essential to reach a
professional level of playing ability to be
able to appreciate Indian, Arab or
Indonesian music, the student must be
able to recognize the value, the qualities,
the expressive capacity of these various
types of music without judging them in
relation to his own musical habits, just as
we can only fully appreciate poetry in a
foreign language when we no longer need
to translate it."
The original idea for the school came
from Ivan Vandor, an Italian composer
and musicologist of Hungarian origin who
has specialized in research on Tibetan
music. An outline for the project was
presented to the Unesco General
Conference in Nairobi in 1976, with the
backing of four countriesGhana, the
Philippines, India and Italyand was
approved in principle. It was only three
years later, nowever, that the necessary
financing was found. Support for the
school comes not only from the
International Fund for the Promotion of
Culture, but also from the Gulbenkian
Foundation, the Cini Foundation, and the
University of Venice, whose rector,
Professor Feliciano Benvenuti, serves as
president of the school.
Vandor, who is director of the school
as well as director of the International
Institute of Comparative Music Studies
and Documentation, Berlin, said that the
school's syllabus for 1980 will be widened
to include the Arab classical traditions
and those of China, Japan, Java and
Bali, while the courses on Indian and
African music and Italian folk music will
be maintained. In the future it is planned
to include courses on the music of the
world's major religions.
A sitar lesson by Indian musician Ustad Imrat Khan.
Photos Quasar Team, Venice
Dionigi Burranca demonstrates t
of playing a Sardinian wind insti
launeddas.
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Jean Loulendo, of the Congo, demonstrates an
African drum.
Trän Quang Hai accompanies singer Bach Yen
in a recital of Vietnamese music.
' technique
ment, the
Biosphere
Research
Programme
Expanded
Expansion of research on how man
affects the ecosystems of his environment
everywhere from the desert and the
oceanic island to the tropical forest and
the megalopolis was reported at the sixth
session of the International Co-ordinating
Council for Unesco's Man and the
Biosphere Programme (MAB) which met
in Paris from 19 to 28 November.
The Bureau of the Council approved
the addition of fifteen new biosphere
reserves in eight countries China,
Colombia, the German Democratic
Republic, Italy, Romania, Senegal, Sudan
and Ugandato the MAB network now
numbering 177 reserves in 46 countries.
These biosphere reserves are intended
to protect genetic material which might
otherwise disappear under human
onslaught. Unlike the national park,
which is usually an attempt to preserve
unique aspects of nature, the biosphere
reserve is a living laboratory intended to
represent the ecosystems in its
"biogeographic zone". Typically, it
consists of a small preserved core for
baseline measurements and a buffer zone
where the human population goes about
its normal daily life.
In MAB as a whole, there are now 906
field projects in 76 countries registered in
fourteen main subject areas. Their range
is almost infinite, as delegates to the 30-
nation co-ordinating council learned
during the session.
The umbrella of a MAB project can
cover the 200,000-hectare Changbai
Nature Reserve in northeast China as well
as the city of Rome. At the council
session, Dr. Piero della Seta, assistant for
technology to the mayor of Rome,
announced that Rome's municipal
government has decided to set up a Study
Centre on City Problems. It will do
research on urban ecology applied to the
city of Rome under MAB's general
project area devoted to "integrative ,
ecological studies of human settlements".
This work, which is being carried out
with the University of Rome and the
Italian National Research Council, will be
aimed at providing an ecological basis for
the future growth of what an Italian
architect calls "a chaotic, congested city
with an irrational urban structure".
Ill
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Communication
Fellowship Created
in Memory of
Tor Gjesdal
A ceremony in Oslo on 24 October,
United Nations Day, marked the
establishment of the Tor Gjesdal Fund
for meritorious work in mass
communication linked to the aims of the
United Nations.
Created in memory of the late assistant
director-general for communication by his
widow, Mrs. Anne Bollmann Gjesdal, the
fund is designed to carry forward Tor
Gjesdal's abiding concern throughout his
career as a journalist and U.N. and
Unesco official that communication
should serve the cause of international
understanding and co-operation. The
fund will be used to finance an annual
fellowship or travel grant to a prizewinner
from Norway where Tor Gjesdal began
his career as a journalist.
After heading the information section
of his country's government-in-exile in
London during World War II, Gjesdal
was invited by Trygve Lie, first secretary
general of the United Nations, to direct
the U.N. Department of Public
Information. He held this post until 1955
when he moved to Unesco in Paris to
head its communication activities. He
retired from Unesco in 1970, three years
before his death.
r
g-1
Tor Gjesdal
Continued from page I
Communication
Commission
Members of the Commission, in
addition to Mr. MacBride, were:
Mr. Elie Abel, professor of
communication, Stanford University,
USA; Mr. Hubert Beuve-Méry, founder
of the French newspaper Le Monde,
France; Mr. Elebe Ma Ekonzo, Director-
General, Zaire Press Agency; Mr. Gabriel
Garcia Marquez, novelist, Colombia; Mr.
Sergei Losev, Director-General, TASS
News Agency, USSR; Mr. Mochtar
Lubis, Indonesia, president, Press
Foundation of Asia; Mr. Mustapha
Masmoudi, ambassador, permanent
delegate of Tunisia to Unesco; Mr.
Michio Nagai, editorial writer, "Asahi
Shimbun", Japan; Mr. Fred I.
Akporuaro Omu, research professor,
University of Benin, Nigeria; Mr. Bogdan
Osolnik, member of the Federal Council
of the Assembly of the Socialist Federal
Republic of Yugoslavia; Mr. Gamal El-
Oteifi, Egypt, lawyer and legal adviser;
Mr. Johannes Pieter Pronk, Netherlands,
economist and politician; Mr. Juan
Somavia, Chile, executive director,
Instituto Latinoamericano de Estudios
Transnacionales; Mr. Boobli George
Verghese, journalist and head of the
Committee on Autonomy for
Broadcasting, India; and Mrs. Betty
Zimmerman, Canada, director, Radio
Canada International.
Scientists Describe
Search for Life
Outside our Planet
Have scientists any evidence that
intelligent life exists elsewhere in the
universe? What do they know about how
living organisms develop? Will rockets
and spaceships have a role to play in the
search for extra-terrestrial civilizations?
These were some of the questions
discussed at a public forum on the search
for extra-terrestrial civilizations held
recently at Unesco House, in Paris,
chaired by Mr. Albert Ducrocq, of the
French section of the Search for Extra-
Terrestrial Intelligence (SETI). The debate
ended a three-day conference organized
by the Council of Europe in co-operation
with Unesco at which specialists in such
disciplines as astronomy, biology, cosmic
chemistry, geology and astro-physics
discussed the present state of knowledge
and lines of future research in this field
of space exploration.
Professor A. Dolfuss, of the Paris
Observatory, began by tracing the origins
of the universe which, he said, came into
existence 15 thousand million years ago
by explosion or accident, not by an
evolutionary process. Galaxies were
created, then stars, some resembling our
sun. Later, planets were formed by a
natural process of physics. Astronomers
cannot at present say whether conditions
suitable for life exist elsewhere, though
this may be discovered within the next
decade or so.
For Professor R. Buvet, of the Energy
Laboratory at Paris University, and Dr.
Frank Drake, who conducted the first
radio search for extra-terrestrial
intelligence in the USA, there was a fair
chance of finding life on other planets.
The development of living creatures on
Earth had followed a regular pattern
which could be expected to occur widely
throughout the universe. As regards space
travel, Dr. Drake pointed to the
enormous distances, amounting to
thousands of light years, between the
planets the Venus probe took several
years to travel from Earth to a planet in
our own system which ruled out this
type of contact. This was just as well.
Space represented a sort of "quarantine",
he said, which would prevent the different
civilizations, if they existed, from harming
each other. Interstellar communication
would not be achieved by sending objects
into space but by radio signals and
electro-magnetic radiation.
o
<
o
i
IV
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
PALLADI
of the Italian Renaissance
]]>
</page>
</document>
