<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="042993eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
NOVEMBER 1980 3.50 French francs
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
@
Italy
St. Benedict,
patron saint of Europe
St. Benedict of Nursia (about 480-
547) as depicted by the Italian
Renaissance painter Piero della
Francesca. In this detail from the
altarpiece of the Virgin of the
Misericordia (about 1450-1460) at
Borgo San Sepolcro in Italy, the
founder of the Benedictine reli¬
gious Order is shown holding
rods and staff, the insignia of his
authority. The Rule, or set of
regulations governing monastic
life, which St. Benedict formu¬
lated, divides the day between
prayer, manual work and the
study of the scriptures. It was
adopted by monasteries through¬
out medieval Europe, exercising a
strong civilizing influence. In 1964
St. Benedict was proclaimed
"patron saint of all Europe" by
Pope Paul VI, and this year a
number of initiatives have
marked the 1500th anniversary of
his birth.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
NOVEMBER 1980 33rd YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 25 LANGUAGES
-English Italian Turkish Macedonian
French Hindi Urdu Serbo-Croat
Spanish Tamil Catalan Slovene
Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese
German Persian Korean
Arabic Dutch Swahili
Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly i n English, French and Spanish
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 35 French Francs - 2 years: 58 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 29 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (11 issues a
year including one double issue). Individual articles and photo¬
graphs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing the credit
line reads "Reprinted from the UNESCO COURIER", plus
date of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor.
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name. Non-
copyright photos will be supplied on request. Unsolicited
manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied by an
international reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of
the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced In microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New York. U.S.A.; (3) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mans¬
field Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Editor-in-chief: Jean Gaudin
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Malaysian
Korean
Swahili
Braille
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Howard Brabyn (Paris)
Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Werner Merkli (Berne)
Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Samad Nourinejad (Teheran)
Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Lim Moun-young (Seoul)
Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salaam)
Frederick Potter
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene Editions: Punisa Pavlovic (Belgrade)
Chinese Edition: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Philippe Gentil
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
page
YUGOSLAVIA
A KALEIDOSCOPE OF CULTURES
by Milan Pre/og
4 I. The tides of history
9 II. The language of styles
13 III. Birthright of a modern State
19 THE WORLD'S FORGOTTEN ARMY
OF CHILD WORKERS
25 STONE AGE MYTH-SCULPTORS OF SIBERIA
by Vitali E. Laritchev
29 THE PSYCHOLOGY OF MARBLES
by Jean Piaget
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 UNESCO NEWSROOM
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
ITALY: St. Benedict, patron saint of Europe
l-IV NEWS FROM UNESCO
Special supplement
Cover
The medieval frescoes in the church of
St. Andrew on the Traska river near Skopje
are among the many cultural treasures that
modern Yugoslavia has inherited from the
tumultuous past (see also article overleaf).
They were executed in the late 14th century
by Jovan Zograf, who was not only a famous
painter of his time but a metropolitan (arch¬
bishop) of the church. Magnificent portrait
head of St. Andrew on our cover is a detail
from the frescoes which, like the church
itself, is still in a good state of preservation.
Photo © Arsenije Jovanovic, Belgrade
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
YUGOSLAVIA : A KALEI
I . The tides of history
by Milan Prelog
This curious terra-cotta head was
unearthed at a neolithic site near Prístina in
Yugoslavia. It is one of many archaeological
finds which attest to the region's
cultural importance in prehistoric times.
THE visitor to Yugoslavia is immedi¬
ately overwhelmed by the extra¬
ordinary variety of the country's artis¬
tic heritage. In fact its territory has been
criss-crossed down the centuries by so
many political and cultural boundaries,
divided into so many States and shared bet¬
ween so many different languages and
religions that it would be more appropriate
to speak of several heritages.
Every work, even if its beauty is timeless,
manifestly belongs to a particular form of
society or a particular tradition among the
many which have flourished in the area.
Often a work ¡s evidence of a victory or a
defeat, symbolizing either an acceptance or
a rejection. Highly original variants of
culture and civilization have developed in
these lands, building on the ruins of the
past, and sometimes alternating with one
another.
In each case, the relationship between
native and foreign influence was not only
expressed in intellectual terms but reflected
the struggle waged by peoples to defend
and preserve their ways of life, sometimes
even their existence. Seen in this context
the phenomenon of "backwardness" in the
development of artistic and literary forms,
the debate between traditionalism and
modernism and the question of provin¬
cialism are basic to an understanding and
appraisal of historical evidence.
Art historians faced with the geographical
and cultural complexities of this area of
Europe have tended to oversimplify, dividing
it into two major spheres of influence: an
eastern zone where Byzantine Christianity
dominated, and a western one where the
main influence was the Church of Rome.
And because the boundaries drawn bet¬
ween the zones were generally based on
ideological assumptions rather than a
serious analysis of the monuments
themselves, scholars regarded them as
watertight compartments, refusing to
acknowledge the existence of mutual
influences between regions, in particular
between the Adriatic coastal area and the
hinterland.
Such divisions made it impossible to ap¬
praise the importance of many works which
did not conform to the simplistic definitions
of "eastern" or "western".
The architecture of many religious
buildings on the Adriatic coast erected bet
ween the tenth and twelfth centuries can
only be explained by Byzantine influence.
Similarly, the succession of churches from
Studenica to Decani built by the Serbian
kings between the twelfth and sixteenth .
centuries cannot be understood without
reference to Romanesque style. These
monuments and dozens like them are not
products of closed spheres of influence but
of crossroads of civilization where different
cultures met and mingled.
Again, the famous "stetchak" tomb¬
stones of Bosnia and Herzegovina were
carved or engraved in a specific historical
context: the struggle of a native community
against both "east" and "west". Moreover,
from the fifteenth century onwards, the
Turkish conquest and, consequently, the
presence of Islam in many of the lands that
make up present-day Yugoslavia added a
new dimension to the concept of the
"East", while highly specialized forms of
culture grew up in the so-called "western"
zone.
History does not mould geography, but it
does unfold in and adapt to a natural set¬
ting. From the earliest times centres of
cultural life formed around natural lines of
communication: the coast and inland water¬
ways. Soldiers and merchants travelled
these main routes and with them went their
myths, their gods and forms of worship.
Along them were to be found the first
human settlements, the first stone inscrip¬
tions and the earliest towns.
Life was harder on the bare plateaux and
in the forests of the mountain ranges that
rise between the Adriatic and the Danube
and Sava valleys to the north. Thus
geography and climate influenced the
development of habitats and life styles, in¬
cluding their variety and duration, as well as
the separateness of the different regions
whose originally natural frontiers later
hardened into political and religious ones.
If one were to begin the history of
Yugoslavia with the arrival of the Slavs, it
would go back no further than the seventh
century. However, the succession of civiliza¬
tions which flourished in these lands in both
historic and prehistoric times have left
countless remains not only those brought
to light by archaeologists, but monuments,
still standing, which today as in the past re- k
main permanent features of the landscape, f
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
DOSCOPE OF CULTURES
Portrait of a lady. A striking detail from a fresco in a 14th-century Serbian church.
Photo © Arsenije Jovanovic, Belgrade
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
The great funeral mounds containing
stone tombs, built by the lllyrians more than
three thousand years ago, are still a distinc¬
tive feature of Adriatic hillsides. The general
outline of prehistoric settlements survives in
the oval or circular shapes of many medieval
cities, especially in the highlands of Istria.
And roads built by long-forgotten peoples
continue to be used, while the names these
peoples gave to rivers, mountains and the
iarger islands have been retained in the
various languages spoken in present-day
Yugoslavia.
In Antiquity, the economic and cultural
growth of the Hellenistic and Roman periods
left its mark throughout Yugoslavia and
greatly influenced subsequent development.
In coastal towns such as Porec or Zadar, the
city plan still follows the basic lines laid
down by Roman surveyors. And when Split
was established in the Middle Ages, it
developed within the walls of the huge
palace built at the end of the third century
near Salona, capital of Roman Dalmatia, by
the emperor Diocletian.
In many other places the imposing ruins
of temples, triumphal arches, theatres, cir¬
cuses and necropolises are part of the land¬
scape and of people's daily life. And
churches built by the early Christians during
the last centuries of Antiquity are still used
as places of worship: a prime example is the
great cathedral of Porec, in Croatia, built by
bishop Euphrasius in the sixth century and
decorated with magnificent mosaics.
It is not surprising that this heritage
should have been an inexhaustible source of
inspiration for artists, particularly in areas
close to the Adriatic. In the eleventh cen¬
tury, anonymous sculptors used as models
statues found in Roman tombs. And in the
thirteenth century the master craftsman
Buvina, who carved the doors of Split
cathedral, borrowed ornamental designs
from a temple built during the reign of
Diocletian.
A few years later, disciples of another
master, Radovan, surrounded the statues of
saints on the portals of the cathedral of
St. Lawrence, at Trogir in Dalmatia, with
huntsmen, wild animals, satyrs, mermaids
and foliage reminiscent of ancient designs.
Depicted on the same doorway are two large
figures of Adam and Eve, the latter modestly
shielding her breast with one hand in a
gesture which irresistibly brings to mind the
figure of Venus.
Models from Antiquity recalling the
Roman history of the area were popular dur¬
ing the sixteenth century, and in literature
authors imitated the themes and forms of
Latin poetry.
For five hundred years, from the ninth to
the fifteenth century, the cultural life of
Yugoslavia developed within a variety of dif¬
ferent political systems. The earliest Slav
States were established in the hinterland
behind the Adriatic where, up to the end of
the eleventh century, the kingdom of
Croatia played a vital role linking the rural
communities of the interior to the ancient
urban civilization of the coast.
The towns which grew up during this
medieval period remained centres of Cro¬
atian culture for hundreds of years. But a
series of crises undermined the Croatian
State and it finally succumbed to Hungarian
intervention early in the twelfth century.
There followed a long period of Croat-
Magyar "association", which, after the six¬
teenth century, continued in the framework
of the Austrian empire, and, though marked
by constant friction and antagonism, lasted
until 1918.
Venetian interests dominated in the area
where sea-borne trade along the Adriatic
coast linked central Europe to the
Mediterranean. At first the Venetians were
content to occupv ports, but in the
thirteenth century they began to annex
territory on the west coast of Istria to
begin with and, later, along the Dalmatian
seaboard.
By the beginning of the fifteenth century
they had become masters of all Dalmatia,
with the exception of Dubrovnik (Ragusa)
which with its surrounding territory
developed into a city-state and maintained
its independence up to the Napoleonic wars.
Its end came shortly after the fall of the
Venetian republic.
Other states were formed in the interior.
First Serbia in the eleventh century, which
soon extended its influence to the south¬
east, establishing its hegemony over part of
Macedonia. Its rulers dreamt of conquering
Constantinople. But the Turkish invasion
put an end to these dreams and, in 1389, the
Serbian princes suffered final defeat at the
battle of Kossovo.
Bosnia's independence was even more k
short-lived. During the fourteenth and fif- f
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Eastern and Western traditions
meet at the monastery of
Studenica, in the church of the
Holy Virgin (far left). The
monastery, which was founded in
the late 12th century by the Serbian
ruler Stefan Nemanja, is widely
regarded as the finest example of
the "Raska" school of architecture
which flourished in medieval Serbia
and whose hallmark was a blend of
Romanesque and Byzantine
elements. At Studenica,
Romanesque influence is very
strong in the architectural
structure, whereas the frescoes
inside the church (left, detail from
the crucifixion) are Byzantine in
inspiration.
Photo Rune Hassner © G Bern, Pans
The skyline of Sarajevo,
below, is studded with
mosques and minarets many
of which date back to the
16th century when the town
became a stronghold of
Muslim culture. Sarajevo is
today the picturesque capital
of Yugoslavia's Socialist
Republic of Bosnia-
Herzegovina.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
, teenth centuries it extended its domination
over vast territories between the Adriatic
and the Sava river. But, here too, the
Turkish conquest cut short its expansion.
The north-west of present-day
Yugoslavia Slovenia and inner Istriawas
part of the Holy Roman Empire. In this area,
powerful vassals of the emperor both
secular lords and churchmen including
bishops, abbots and heads of religious
orders such as Cistercians and Templars,
custodians of temporal power ruled over
huge feudal estates and enjoyed relative in¬
dependence on a regional level.
In the medieval cities, harmonious and
lasting forms of social organization
developed independently, particularly on the
Adriatic coast where towns, while paying
allegiance to different powers, governed
themselves according to their own laws and
minted their own coins. But in the struggle
against Venice and the drive to gain free
access to sea-borne trade and establish
themselves as States, only Dubrovnik really
succeeded.
The evolution of cultural life in Yugoslavia
has not followed a simple course. It is like a
complex web of cross-currents which meet,
diverge and intersect. Some flow peacefully
in the same direction for centuries, others
gush forth like springs and then vanish.
Sometimes these currents run parallel to
one another, close yet separated by ac¬
cidents of history.
The centres of social, political and
religious life where these trends and
movements originated also had a chequered
history. Some faded out after a few dozen
years of intense activity, then revived, or
sank into oblivion ; while others developed
regularly without interruption.
Monasteries and bishoprics (both Or¬
thodox and Roman Catholic) as well as
princely courts played a part in this process.
But the most important centres were the
towns, for economic and social activity pro¬
moted the growth of culture and it was in
the cities that creative artists painters,
sculptors, miniaturists, goldsmiths and
silversmiths established their workshops.
Here, too, the towns of the Adriatic
seaboard took the lead. From the earliest
times, craftsmen in these centres of trade
and exchange produced works of high quali¬
ty. They were well aware of the importance
of the written word as a means of recording
both individual and collective achievements
for posterity, as can be seen in countless
manuscripts, archives and inscriptions in
crypts ; from the ninth century onwards
donors had their names carved in the
stonework in churches.
Very early on, too, artists began to sign
their works. Books were written in Latin but
also in Croatian in the Glagolithic alphabet.
Romance or Italian were spoken in addition
to Latin and Croatian. In fact, "multil-
ingualism" gave a specific stamp to the
region's cultural history. It was in these
coastal districts that the first literary works
in a "national language" were written, as
well as the first studies on the ethnic groups
of the region, the hinterland and the Slav
world in general.
In contrast, urban development in the in¬
terior was slow. A few boom towns grew up
near the mines in mountain areas during the
Middle Ages ; but they were short-lived.
Generally speaking towns developed
gradually round monasteries or castles. In
the north-west of the country (Slovenia and
northern Croatia), the first townships ap¬
peared only in the thirteenth century, and in
Bosnia and Herzegovina as late as the fif¬
teenth century when the Turkish occupation
became stabilized. But in most cases they
were no more than small country towns and
up till quite recently living standards there
were low. In certain border areas urban
development was arrested or slowed down
by the wars against the Turks.
Photo © Drag. Kazic, Belgrade
t*> "v^^m
These monumental stone tombs, known as "stetchaks", are examples of a
highly original funerary art created by the Bogomils, a Christian sect which
flourished in the Balkans from the 10th to the 15th century. About 30,000
stetchaks, some weighing over 30 tons, can still be seen scattered in the
mountains and forests of Bosnia and Herzegovina. They are decorated with a
wealth of carvings depicting heraldic signs and symbols, conventionalized
portraits and scenes of games, hunting and tournaments. The meaning of these
carvings is still not fully understood.
tSMCTK
~ _ £fc
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
YUGOSLAVIA
II. The language of styles
ART works are the best yardstick of
cultural evolution, and Yugoslavia
possesses a remarkable range of
historic buildings, paintings, frescoes and
sculpture. The greatest concentration of
monuments of all periods is to be found in
and around the coastal towns where secular
and religious architecture mingle, as do
private and public buildings.
Palaces and rich mansions, cathedrals,
churches and monasteries rise within the
cities' walls and ramparts and on all the
roads leading to them. And in the succes¬
sion of styles from Romanesque to Gothic
and Renaissance, all the major influences
common to European culture can be seen
interacting with one another.
Many works from this region are mention¬
ed in standard histories of art, but they are
generally listed under headings which take
no account of their origin or affinities. For
example, works from Istria and Dalmatia
have been classed arbitrarily as Italian art.
It is, of course, a historical fact that the
constant movement of people and goods
across the Adriatic and the links established
between communities on both sides of the
sea created a basic unity throughout the
region. But this does not mean that
everything can be reduced to a single ethnic
designation or a single political "amalgam".
Until a few years ago only a limited
number of important monuments
documented the evolution of art in this
region. But recent research has brought to
light a variety of works,- all bearing the mark
of the dominant style of their period. The
distinctive forms of Romanesque and Gothic
styles not only shaped palaces and
cathedrals, they are also to be found in
craftsmen's cottages and small churches in
poor neighbourhoods.
The "language" of these styles became a
lingua franca used by different social
classes. The semi-circular arch of Roman¬
esque windows and later the pointed arch of
Gothic façades indicated membership of the
urban community, while symbols carved
above doorways (ancestors of the coat of
arms) meant that their owners had risen in
the social scale to become leading citizens.
Style, particularly in architecture, was
thus a means of expressing social distinc¬
tions, much as Latin, the official language of
government and the courts, marked the
division between town and country. (In
Dalmatia this form of linguistic "separatism"
disappeared in the fifteenth century when
scholars in the towns began to write literary
works in the national language.)
Along with the evolution of style, a
deeper process was taking place: the
secularization of themes and traditions.
Already painters and sculptors of the
Romanesque period had abandoned the
Byzantine tradition. In its concern with ex¬
pressiveness and its narrative style linking
the religious universe to worldly reality, the
art of the region followed a trend common
to the whole of Europe.
In the fifteenth century the naturalistic
tendencies of late Gothic blended with the
new Renaissance style, producing in ar¬
chitecture, sculpture and painting forms
which it is difficult to attribute to a single
style. Romanesque art throughout the
coastal areas in the thirteenth century had
pervaded urban architecture; the ensuing
Gothic period broadened the scope of ar¬
tistic endeavour to include semi-urban and
even rural communities.
In the big cities artistic activity was condi¬
tioned by the classical training of the ruling
classes, whereas in smaller, less affluent
communities a dominant influence was ex¬
erted by the great mendicant and preaching
orders the Dominicans and Franciscans.
A similar evolution was taking place in the
north-east of the country. Mural painting
was an important feature in many village
churches built during this period in Istria,
Slovenia and northern Croatia. Bible history
was told in the form of racy picture-stories in
which traditional motifs mingled with a kind
of popular theology. A favourite theme in
these paintings is the Dance of Death
regarded by the faithful as an assertion of
the basic equality of all human beings in the
face of mortality.
Easel painting also flourished during the
fourteenth and fifteenth centuries. Rooted
in the traditions of Byzantine icon painting,
it was influenced to some extent by the Ven¬
etian school. But Gothic mannerism had not
yet given way to the brilliance of the
Renaissance, except in the work of a few
great painters such as Giorgio Schiavone,
Nicolaus Ragusinus and Mihailo Hamzió.
In the east and south-east of present-day
Yugoslavia, Byzantium was the dominant
influence in social, political, religious and
cultural evolution. The complex relations
which the Slav population of the Balkans
maintained with the centre of the empire at
Constantinople was marked by a succession
of offensive and defensive wars, com¬
promise and resistance. The Slav States
achieved independence and established
their power in battle, but that did not
preclude cultural and religious ties with
Byzantium.
The rise of the Bulgarian State, the
flowering of Tsar Samuel's short-lived em¬
pire and the establishment of the Serbian
State marked a rejection of Byzantine
domination. But though Serbia in the early
days showed certain "western" tendencies
CONTINUED PAGE 12
The west portal of the cathedral of St.
Lawrence, in the Dalmatian port of
Trogir, is a masterpiece executed by the
artist Radovan and his pupils in the
mid-13th century. The carvings around
it, on the theme of original sin and
redemption, include two large figures
of Adam (below) and Eve, as well as
scenes and motifs recalling the styles of
classical Antiquity.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
¿r
m
ri
... Sí H
^
% v
x\; > .
u
Photos © National Museum, Belgrade
Church walls in the great monasteries of medieval Serbia were covered with frescoes painted
by artists working within the Byzantine tradition of stylized religious iconography. Above
right, detail from the Descent from the Cross In the monastery church of Mileseva, founded
by King Vladislav in the middle of the 13th century. The fresco belongs to an important
ensemble of New Testament scenes. The Mileseva artists also left for posterity a unique
portrait gallery of medieval Serb rulers in accordance with a custom whereby the founder of a
monastery was portrayed as part of its decoration, surrounded by members of his family.
Medieval Serbia was also a major centre of ¡con painting. Above left, icon of the Virgin Mary
from the monastery church of Decani.
"The paths of glory lead but to
the grave." Photo right shows a
detail from a late 15th-century
fresco in a church at the little
Istrian village of Beram
(Croatia). The complete work
shows prince and peasant,
innkeeper and churchman, each
followed by a skeleton. In a
"Dance of Death" symbolizing
the equality of all men and women
in face of mortality.
Detail from a 16th-century
painting of The Last Judgement
in the monastery of Moraca in
Montenegro. The monastery
was built in 1251-1252 by the
grandson of Stefan Nemanja,
the founder of a great medieval
Serbian dynasty.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
A group of musicians is depicted in
this tiny detail from the 1,260
square metres of frescoes in the
church of the monastery of Piva.
Founded in 1573, Piva was for
almost four centuries little known
because of its remote location in
the mountain fastnesses of what is
today the Yugoslav Republic of
Montenegro. Its art treasures were
undocumented. Then the decision
to build a power station on the river
Piva jeopardized the monastery's
existence and aroused widespread
interest in its plight. In view of
Piva's importance and the fact that
its architecture and early 17th-
century frescoes make up an
indivisible entity, it was decided to
remove the monastery stone by
stone and reconstruct it high above
its original site. Work on the highly
delicate removal operation began in
1970 and since then the monastery
complex has been transported to
the new spot and the church has
been rebuilt. Work on restoring the
frescoes, which present a wealth of
iconographie themes influenced by
Cretan art, is still in progress.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Law and or(e)der
in Novo Brdo
Miniature above is part of a
recently discovered 16th-century
copy of a legal code drawn up to
regulate the mining industry at the
instigation of the Serbian ruler
Stefan Lazarevic (1389-1427). It
shows members of the council of
jurists during their deliberations.
The laws, known as the Code of
Novo Brdo after the town where
Serbia's biggest silver mine was
located, vividly evoke life in the
mining communities of medieval
Serbia. Miners' pay and working
conditions are rigorously defined
and provisions for security, such as
ventilation shafts, are laid down.
An annexe document highlights the
privileged status of miners:
merchants were forbidden to sell
food to anyone else as long as a
miner was waiting to buy it.
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 9
due to its access to the Adriatic, Constan¬
tinople continued to inspire the area's
cultural life.
In 1014, Samuel was defeated at T.he bat¬
tle of Belasica and his empire collapsed: the
conquerors put out the eyes of 14,000 of his
soldiers. A few years later, at Ohrid, Con¬
stantinople was to win a very different kind
of victory when the new cathedral of Saint
Sophia was consecrated: the magnificent
murals it contained were directly inspired by
Byzantine court painting, as were the
Richly embossed cover of a
Gospel-book (1557) from the
village of Besenovo in
Vojvodina.
frescoes in the small church of Saint Pan-
theleimon (1164) at Nerezi, near Skopje.
Painted by an exceptionally gifted artist,
these murals display several novel
features including a Pietà and deserve a
special place in art history.
Gradually the imperial art of Byzantium
spread to workshops in the smallest country
towns: the paintings at Kurbinovo, near
Lake Prespa, which date back to 1191, are
one example. This trend continued during
the next two centuries and, as the number
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
of donors increased, so did the activity of
artists.
The influence of the Byzantine-
Macedonian school of painting reached Ser¬
bia towards the end of the thirteenth cen¬
tury. Initially it met with resistance. For ex¬
ample, in the "royal church" of Studenica
monastery the architecture and even the
sculpture on the doorways reveal Roman¬
esque i.e. Western influence, whereas
the paintings inside belong to the Constan¬
tinople school.
This contrast reflects the political tension
rife at the time: Stefan II, son of Stefan
Nemanja whose dynasty was to last for two
centuries, was crowned king of Serbia in
Rome, but his brother, Sava, abbot of
Studenica monastery, threw in his lot with
Constantinople and became the first
patriarch of the Serbian Church. It is
therefore not surprising that he should have
called on Byzantine artists to decorate
Studenica. After his death, the decoration
of the funeral chapels of the Nemanja dynas¬
ty continued in the best tradition of Byzan¬
tine art: the frescoes in the monasteries of
Mileseva and Sopócani are just two
examples.
This trend received fresh impetus when
Serbia extended its rule to northern
Macedonia where artistic life was not
restricted to the court but also flourished in
centres established on the great secular and
church domains. At Ohrid, early in the four¬
teenth century, two masters Eustachius
and Michael painted magnificent works for
the church of Saint Clement, putting for¬
ward and developing the aesthetic ideas of
fhe Palaeologus Renaissance.
After the defeat of Kossovo at the end of
the fourteenth century, the Serbian rulers
moved their capital northwards to
Smederevo, in the Morava valley, and with
them went the artists. For more than a hun¬
dred years the "Morava School", heir to a
long tradition, was to produce remarkable
works both in painting and architecture (see
the Unesco Courier, August-September
1978).
This tradition continued, taking on a new
form after the fall of Smederevo in 1459.
Nothing now remained of the Serbian State,
but for Serbs living under Turkish domina¬
tion and those who had emigrated massively
to the north and west, the ¡cons, illuminated
manuscripts and fresco-decorated churches
were not mere relics of the past but symbols
of national identity.
These artistic traditions enabled the Serbs
in exile in Vojvodina to maintain themselves
as a national group resisting all pressures. In
fact, it was in this exile that modern Serbian
cultural life developed. Centres established
in exile remained active long after the rebirth
of Serbia in the nineteenth century. Recent
, research has shown that this latter-day
Byzantine art was not content with
repeating set formulas: it actually broke new
ground in Vojvodina during the eighteenth
century blending the Byzantine with the
new Baroque iconography.
YUGOSLAVIA
III. Birthright
of a modern State
BY the end of the fifteenth century the
Ottoman empire had occupied a large
part of present-day Yugoslavia and,
up to the end of the seventeenth century, it
continued to annex new provinces. Islam is
therefore an important factor in under¬
standing the cultural life of the country. But
the wars that devastated central Europe,
threatening even Vienna, and the bitter
struggle waged by the conquered peoples
left lasting memories which made it difficult
to speak of Islam's contribution to cultural
life.
Religion was the key to social position in
the empire, and the conditions under which
the conquered peoples maintained their
beliefs and coherence as national groups
were very hard. Conversion offered a means
of changing one's status, and in several
areas, especially Bosnia and Herzegovina,
part of the population adopted this solution.
Constraints and resistance notwith¬
standing, changes did take place in areas
where Turkish power had become stabiliz¬
ed. This evolution can be seen in the
characteristic plans of certain towns and the
architecture of religious and trade centres.
This architecture, however, was not entirely
foreign to the country, for Turkish culture in
the Balkans already embodied certain tradi¬
tions of the occupied areas: it had been In¬
fluenced in particular by the style of secular
and religious buildings in the Christian east.
Many fine dwellings recall this period, as
do bridges and several outstanding
mosques. In turn, the Christian population
assimilated elements of Islamic culture,
though in the literary field language proved
an Insuperable barrier.
Yet billnguallsm and even "pluri-
linguallsm" was common in some circles.
Yugoslavs served in the army and civil ser¬
vice and taught in the schools of the Turkish
empire as they did in those of Austria or
Venice. Political and ideological divisions
Imposed various forms of alienation, the
most severe being when men speaking the
same language found themselves fighting^
under different flags. f
These heads from the apse of
the cathedral of Sibenik in
Croatia are examples of the
Renaissance art which began to
flourish on the Dalmatian coast
in the middle of the 15th
century. In the opinion of some
specialists the finest works of
art in Croatia, if not the whole
of present-day Yugoslavia, date
from the Renaissance.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Baroque became the predominant style
of religious architecture and decoration
in Croatia where it was introduced by
the Jesuits in the 17th century and was
favoured by the Franciscans in the
18th. Photo shows part of a sculpture
from a church at Belec, Croatia, dating
from between 1743 and 1746.
Francesco da Laurana, one of the great
Renaissance sculptors, left Dalmatia to work
in Naples and Sicily before settling in Avi¬
gnon. Similarly the reformer Flacius II-
lyricus abandoned his native Istria never to
return, as did the historian Lucius of Trogir
who settled in Rome.
One of the greatest masters of Baroque
art, the painter Federico Bencovich, worked
in Italy and Germany, while the only links the
famous eighteenth century mathematician,
physicist and astronomer Ruggiero
Boskovic retained with his birthplace,
Dubrovnik, were memories of his youth.
For the provincial artist, passive imitation
of foreign models or static traditionalism
were the order of the day. The middle
classes were not powerful enough to In¬
fluence the evolution of art and as for the
aristocracy, they satisfied their aesthetic
needs by buying art works in the big cities.
Here and there some activity continued.
For example, during the Baroque period, in
teresting works were still being produced
outside the areas of Turkish occupation, and
several townships grew up or were rebuilt in
the north-west of the country. But from the
sixteenth to the end of the eighteenth cen¬
tury, one of architecture's main tasks-
judging by the size of the building projects
and the quality of the workwas to build
fortresses and ramparts.
The same period saw the rise of a growing
movement of revolt in all the provinces
under Austrian, Turkish and Venetian rule
and, as time went on, these movements
became increasingly national in character.
Linguistic imperialism and the refusal to
recognize national or regional differences
met with stronger and stronger resistance.
In the Ottoman empire these movements
developed into armed uprisings leading to
the liberation first of Montenegro, then of
Serbia. With Turkey now on the defensive,
the great powers sought to eliminate it from
the Balkans. Austria seized Bosnia and
Photo shows one of Slovenia's Kurenti dancers wearing a beaked and bewhiskered
mask surrounded by feathers. Kurenti dancers take part in an ancient Slav ritual
which, although pagan in origin, became part of the customs of the Catholic
population of Slovenia and is still practised today near Ptuj, a little town in the
north of the Republic of Slovenia. During the Austrian domination of Slovenia,
which lasted until 1918, the ritual was proscribed by Church and State and became
an expression of resistance to the authorities. This spirit of resistance to the
domination of another culture and language is also apparent in certain colloquial
forms of Slovene which, unlike other languages of the region, has conserved some
archaic Slav expressions.
From the fifteenth century onwards war
was a permanent feature in these parts. The
territory of present-day Yugoslavia was split
up between three powers Austria, Turkey
and Venice and there was fighting on all
their borders. It did not always take the form
of full-scale military campaigns, but there
were continual skirmishes and guerilla at¬
tacks as well as raids between rival factions
serving different powers. All this led to
widespread destruction and where fighting
was severe and continued for long periods
whole areas emptied of their population and
became nomanslands.
Worse still, the frontiers arbitrarily drawn
by the three great powers blocked natural
lines of communication between the interior
and the coast, curtailing the movement and
exchange of information, goods and people.
Thereafter each region developed in a kind
of vacuum, dependent on decisions taken in
far-off capitals. These territories were only
of marginal interest to the big States which
had fought so hard for their possession.
Differences between the provinces and
the main centres of power, and between
small and large towns grew more marked in
the seventeenth century when the develop¬
ment process was centered in the capitals
and major cities. Distant areas found it in¬
creasingly difficult to keep pace with impor¬
tant changes taking place in social, political,
economic and cultural life.
Signs of this "provincialism" can be
observed in art in the early sixteenth cen¬
tury. There were fewer and fewer building
projects, fewer and fewer commissions and
a decreasing demand for public work. In the
narrow, stifling atmosphere of provincial
towns emigration seemed the only solution
and the best artists sought fortune abroad.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Herzegovina, as she had seized the coastal
region after the fall of Venice and the end of
the Napoleonic wars. Up to 1918 Croatia and
Slovenia remained part of the Austro-
Hungarian empire.
Within this framework a new national
consciousness developed which found ex¬
pression not only in political struggles but
also in intense cultural activity. Among
major achievements of this nineteenth cen¬
tury revival were: the promotion of national
languages, new forms of historical research,
the attainment of higher education and the
creation of theatres and museums.
It is true that in areas formerly sealed off
from one another by historical circum¬
stances, revival sometimes coincided with
the awakening of several often conflicting
national movements a situation which was
to plague independent Yugoslavia between
the two World Wars: the centralization im¬
posed by the authorities clashed with the i
special interests and national feelings of the I
Striking contrast between
sober symbolism and
picturesque realism appears
in these examples of
Yugoslavia's remarkable
tradition of funerary art. Left,
symbolic carvings on a
tombstone from a Turkish
cemetery at Sarajevo. Below,
realistic human figures
sculpted on a group of
Serbian gravestones of the
kind which commemorate
men and women who died
far from home (while
travelling, at work, or on the
battlefield). Such
gravestones can still be seen,
notably in western Serbia,
standing singly or in groups
at the roadside. The figures
are posthumous portraits
featuring details of clothing
or articles associated with a
particular profession or
office, which indicate the
dead person's position in
society. Most of the stones
are painted, and many bear
epitaphs which are as
redolent of serenity,
melancholy or resignation as
the portraits themselves.
Photo © Drag. Kazlc, Belgrade
^*ú:
Ék#
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
A gigantic flower with immense petals
opening skywards. With this symbol of
hope, faith and dignity the sculptor
Bogdan Bogdanovic has
commemorated over 700,000 persons
who perished during the Nazi
occupation (1941-1945) in Yugoslavia's
biggest concentration camp. The
monument stands on the site of the
camp, in the Croatian village of
Jasenovac on the river Sava.
:::::::::::::::::::::::::^
:::::::
::::::: SLOVENIA^' \::: \\j¿¿
	::::L f" NjJ ^ ^^T
J »ZAGREB N-»^*lU--'^ x V]..
> \ VOJVODINA Y : : : : : : : :
¡i*	^ **0 CROATIA > Xi¿: :::::::::: :::::::
N~-# N0VI SAD ^J.	
vEESS ; \ / "'"'»«.»-.«n---^ r"' .. 4:::::::::::::::::
; *_' \ ! <
^k& ! \i-"x ' .. XlLi:::;-^:::::::
\ / V/ z*-3*
BOSNIA AND HERZEGOVINA * Belgrade V
^^^^T5^ * ' T^i;
¡Sk \ \ fi?:::
,--' SERBIA
\ SARAJEVO \ V-
s \ \	
=^===^^=^^=^=^=5=^=?^--«=^ \ _/ Vf 	
-"^^^111111111^ V\ v
p^ r \ y-
¡=^v MONTENEGRO"?--''
*	' JK^Á PRISTINA* . /
titogra# ^KOSOVO v--'X::
âTx::::::::\ ^'^/ \!i
Z^z^^z
ä>j :::::::: y-' skopje
:{ MACEDOISMAjr!
o
c
0)
c
3
O
n
o
o
0)
c
>
.
a>
u
c
(O
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
various peoples making up the community.
The resulting divisions were among the
major causes of the Yugoslav kingdom's
collapse in 1941.
Thus a form of provincialism continued
well into the twentieth century. The cultural
achievements of this period were often im¬
portant but, generally speaking, they took
place in isolation and could not keep pace
with the major trends of European cultural
development. Many of the best Yugoslav ar¬
tists suffered from this backwardness at the
turn of the century. Any attempt to compete
with the great masters of the day met with a
complete lack of understanding. What they
had learned in famous schools abroad had
to be forgotten directly they returned home,
and many lofty projects never saw the light
of day.
Under the guidance of the late Marshal
Tito, a new Yugoslavia emerged from the
resistance struggle against the Nazi invader
and the war of liberation which had created
the conditions necessary for resolving past
conflicts and fostering development.
The establishment of six federal republics
and two autonomous regions enabled the
country's diverse ethnic groups to give full
expression to their respective cultural iden¬
tities within the framework of a multi¬
national federal State.
The immediate post-war period was one
of great difficulty; during the war large areas
of the country had been devastated, towns
and villages had been destroyed and more
than a million and a half inhabitants had
perished. It was in this context that began
the twin processes of industrialization and
urbanization which, in a relatively short
period, were to transform the social and
economic structures of the country,
creating a new way of life and determining
the options open to coming generations.
The repercussions of this evolution made
themselves felt progressively in the cultural
life of the country. Traditional forms and an¬
cient customs intermingled with avant-
garde art and new cultural developments
under the impulsion of the increasingly in¬
fluential mass media.
Whatever separate judgments one makes
about the literary, artistic and scientific work
produced by Yugoslavia in the last thirty
years, there can be no doubt that the scope
of its creativity, give it a definite place in the,
mainstream of contemporary European
culture. H
MILAN PRELOG, of Yugoslavia, is an art histo¬
rian and a professor at the university ofZagreb in
Croatia (Yugoslavia). From 1976 until this year he
was a member of Unesco's intergovernmental
World Heritage Committee. He is the author of
several studies on art history, urbanism, and the
protection and renovation of ancient towns and
monuments.
Photos © Politika, Belgrade
UNESCO AND SCIENTIFIC RESEARCH IN YUGOSLAVIA
On July 26 1963, Skopje, capital of Macedonia and the third largest city of Yugoslavia, was hit by a
violent earthquake which left over a thousand people dead and 120,000 homeless. In an upsurge of inter¬
national solidarity, relief in money and in kind poured in from 78 countries. A Unesco earthquake recon¬
naissance mission was despatched to the stricken city to assess the situation created by the disaster and
to advise on long-term measures to be taken. Skopje has been completely rebuilt on the basis of a new
earthquake-proof town plan. Today Skopje is the home of the Institute of Earthquake Engineering and
Seismology, which was established through an international co-operative effort and with the assistance
of a number of international agencies, in particular Unesco. Below left, a computer-controlled shaking
table at the Institute tests the earthquake-resistance of a model of a steel structure. Below right, a
colony of blue algae (Ophiotrix quinquemaculatal photographed in the Bay of Piran by staff of
MARETRAC, the Marine Biology Centre at Piran, Slovenia, another institution which works in close co¬
operation with Unesco. An important recent development has been the establishment of the Interna¬
tional Unesco Centre for Chemical studies at the Edvard Kardelj University, Ljubljana. The Centre will
play a key role in Unesco's new International Organization for the Chemical Sciences for Development.
>»-V
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
teiiixAiss
«:¥35x m^^y^
mm
s^&w
:
,v"xV
^Ä3& s
É::>::::
!5?x^x^äI:
K il
»SX
"^ÍÍA^
¡tf^RS^S^K^X'ÄyX'X'X'X'lylylyX^yXyX;:;
BBRWííX^-'^X'ÍX-XvI-ljIyl^yXjXyXylyyX;
*-!röOOopqfr ^WOflnOnKv -'-*^^xVVSqo66p
^^^o^^^^^^M k:::::x:x'-::::::-.«:»
S^^^^^^^^OT fcx-x-x : ¿-'-2«
S I -v¿r^:£&&P8
^^^w.'X;.5aa hSffTi. 8 fcjftfeñigSXjwfcj
hwkXkvW'.'Tqookb^ '^5 iSääSSSSSSSSSSSi
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The world's
forgotten
army of
child
workers
&::
CHILD labour, often thought to be a
problem of the past, is still a
widespread and persistent evil in
the 1980s. The latest estimates made by the
International Labour Organisation (ILO)
show that in the world as a whole there are
no less than fifty-two million child workers
under the age of fifteen.
What is more, even this figure may under¬
estimate the real dimensions of this tragic
situation, since in some countries young
workers under fifteen are simply not includ¬
ed in the labour force statistics, while in
others young people who both work and at¬
tend school are rarely considered as part of
the labour force. In addition, the statistics
cover only those youngsters who have a
fixed job, and thus exclude the majority of
those who work only occasionally.
Children in every type of society have
always taken some part in those economic
activities which are necessary for the sur:
vival of the group to which they belong.
In earlier times children worked within
their family circle. Little by little, through
almost unconscious observation, associa¬
tion and imitation, they learnt the role they
would be called upon to play as adults. Dur¬
ing this process of socialization, of which his
"on the job" training formed a part, the
child grew to physical and intellectual
maturity and was simultaneously prepared
for adult life. Work of this kind can be liken¬
ed to those present day tasks which by
nature are light, sporadic, interesting,
educational and socially useful, and which
serve to integrate the child in the social life
of the group to which he belongs.
But against these pleasurable occupations
should be set other kinds of job: those that
are imposed upon the child, occasioned by
necessity, and carried out under conditions
of exploitation. They demand greater
physical and mental resources than the ex¬
ploited child possesses because they are
monotonous, strenuous, harmful or unduly
prolonged, because they are a source of
anxiety, and because they inevitably imply a
lack of schooling, relaxation and general
well-being. Jobs of this sort may be self-
employed or wage-earning, and are often
found in modern family businesses, albeit |
usually in a less extreme form. The very I
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
( many children who are engaged on work of
this kind grow up prematurely and sadly.
Custom and the law usually hold that the
work children do alongside their parents is
distinct from the exploitation to which they
may be subjected when they work for third
parties. In practice, this is generally the
case, since parents usually look after their
children's welfare. Nevertheless, however
much the physical effort, however the hours
of work and the boredom inflicted on the
child may be reduced, and however satisfac¬
tory his working environment may be, he
will inevitably be involved in the family busi¬
ness and will share with his parents the kind
of problems, preoccupations and uncertain¬
ties which are not usually the concern of
children of his age.
In those Western nations which are today
the most economically advanced countries
in the world, it was taken for granted in the
past that children would work alongside
their parents in the fields or in the home.
However, when the change-over to manu¬
facturing industry took place neither the
institutions nor the legislations of those
countries were adequate to meet the new
circumstances.
Thus in the nineteenth century it became
common for children to work in factories,
especially textile mills, from the age of six
years onwards, toiling some fourteen hours
a day in dreadful conditions, virtually unpro¬
tected from the risk of accidents. At the
beginning of the twentieth century, some
Western children were still being employed
in coal mines or at home on work sent out to
them by manufacturers.
It was therefore in the more developed
countries that people first became aware of
the harmfulness of this kind of child labour
and of the need to introduce compulsory
education and to give children the necessary
opportunities for recreation, and legal and
practical measures were gradually intro¬
duced to this end. It seems, however, that
these measures were not always inspired
purely by humanitarian motives. They were
also designed to protect the employment
and wages of adult workers.
Child workers do work that could very
well be done by adults; in other words,
hiring children deprives adults of jobs.
Moreover, children are paid much less than
adults. There is a vicious circle here: on the
one hand child labour increases unemploy¬
ment among adults and reduces their
income; and on the other, unemployment
and low wages induce families to put their
children to work. Thus child labour has both
a positive and a negative effect on family
income although it seems that the latter
outweighs the former.
If, on the one hand, child labour is pro¬
hibited by law in virtually all countries, on
the other hand the' numerous societies in
which it exists cannot provide all their chil¬
dren with means of subsistence, direct or
indirect, in any other way, nor provide them
with the educational and cultural facilities
and the means of recreation that they so
badly need.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Child labour in cities has greatly
increased following the rapid
urbanization of recent decades. In
developing countries, rural families
migrating to urban centres often
find themselves living in appalling
conditions in the shanty-towns that
have mushroomed on the fringes of
many large cities. Uprooted from
their homes and traditional way of
life and bewildered by a new and
unknown environment, the adults
often have great difficulty in finding
employment; the children are sent
out to work to enable the family to
survive. In many cases the children
become self-employed street
traders exposed to hazards of all
kinds inclement weather, dirt,
traffic risk, detention by the police
for vagrancy, excessive fatigue due
to long hours as well as the
temptation to drift into delinquency.
In many Asian and African
countries children have traditionally
been employed in textile
manufacture, from the spinning of
thread to the hand-weaving of
carpets. They can often work faster
and better than adults and form a
cheap and docile labour force.
In such circumstances there is every
reason to fear that families will continue to
send their children to work illegally and that
employers will continue to engage them
surreptitiously.
Thus large numbers of children are faced
with two alternatives: either to work in vio¬
lation of the law, or to resign themselves to
enforced idleness, with the resulting temp¬
tation to drift into vagrancy or delinquency.
Here is another vicious circle: destitution
compels the children to find an immediate
source of livelihood, and the fact that they
work during their childhood robs them of
the chance to attend school and obtain the
qualifications which might help them to
escape from poverty.
Because child labour is illegal, the law
makes no provision for safeguarding the
conditions in which children work. Children
thus do not enjoy the right to claim the
social benefits which the law provides, and
constitute a submissive and defenceless
labour force. They are unable to negotiate
their conditions of work (which are usually
imposed arbitrarily by the employer); they
have no trade unions to defend them and
virtually no access to sickness or employ¬
ment injury insurance or social security
schemes (where such exist). Many of these
problems also face children who work
legally is, those who work in countries
where the minimum age for admission to
employment is fixed by law at a very low
level (twelve or thirteen years). The great
social advances secured by adult workers do
not in fact apply to working children, who
are exploited as if those advances had never
been won.
The most recent ILO standards fix the
minimum age for admission to employment
at fifteen years and recommend, with
various provisos, that this be gradually
raised to sixteen years. However, at the
national. level the minimum age has been
fixed by law at anything from twelve to six¬
teen years, depending on the country. In
other words, in some countries children who
work from the age of twelve or thirteen
years are not breaking the law.
In the developing countries poverty is the
fundamental cause of child labour, but it is
usually combined with other factors, inclu¬
ding those that have just been mentioned. A
study recently undertaken in Bangkok
among several hundred working children
revealed that the principal reasons why they
were at work were as follows:
Reason given Percentage
Poverty 23.4
Need to assist parents in
household economic activity 32.9
Parents want them to work 26.3
Need to earn their own living 7.9
Better than doing nothing 6.9
Other reasons 2.6
In general, children take up a particular
job either because it is the only type of job
open at the time they are looking for work
(this may well involve a hasty choice which
can affect their whole future life); or
because one or more members of the family
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
LINKING
SCHOOL AND
WORK
The education that children
receive both at home and at
school should be a
preparation for life in the
society in which they live
and must not be too remote
from daily working needs.
In China, practical elements
are gradually introduced
into the school curriculum.
The youngest children are
given simple tasks to do
such as clearing away
dishes after meals (top
photo). Primary schools (7
to 12 age group) often have
small workshops attached
to them in which the
children undertake part-
time, practical, productive
work as part of the normal
school curriculum. Bottom
photo shows pupils at Kilin
primary school making wax
crayons. Secondary schools
are often closely linked with
full-scale industrial factories
where pupils learn
production techniques from
full-time employees (middle
photo).
> are already doing that kind of job; or
because the work in question does not call
for any special qualifications (which means
that the children will certainly remain at a
very low vocational level).
The age at which children usually begin
work depends on several factors tradition,
the size of the undertaking and whether or
not it is a family concern. An inquiry carried
out among a group of child workers in India
revealed the following points: 24.7 per cent
of the children had begun work between the
age of six and nine years; 48.4 per cent bet¬
ween ten and twelve years; and 26.9 per
cent between thirteen and fifteen years.
The results of another inquiry, carried out
a few years ago in Portugal by the Por¬
tuguese Industrial Association among
19,040 adult workers in 230 mechanical
engineering undertakings, showed that 3.6
per cent of the women had begun their
working life between the ages of five and
seven years, that 10.3 per cent of them had
done so between the ages of eight and ten
and that the proportion for those who had
begun to work between the ages of eleven
and thirteen was 41.1 per cent. In other
words, 55 per cent of the women in this
survey had started work before they had
reached the legal minimum age for ad¬
mission to employment.
In the developing countries children begin
their working life in various ways. Those
whose families have their own businesses
are introduced to work gradually by their
parents. In other cases, parents, together
with relatives or family friends, often get in
touch with possible future employers in
order to "place" a child in a job at a later
date. Usually the first employers to be ap¬
proached in this way are those for whom the
parents, relatives, friends or neighbours
work themselves.
In some countries employers recruit
village children as unqualified assistants (for
example, in a pastry shop or a dairy). Female
domestic servants also usually come from
rural areas: Often it is they who make con¬
tact with the families for whom they are go¬
ing to work but in other cases their parents
hand them over to their future employers so
that they can be "adopted" as subordinate
members of the household.
In parts of Africa, Latin America, Asia and
southern Europe it is not unknown for
parents, in return for a small loan or pay¬
ment in cash or in kind, to hand over their
children at the age of eight or nine years, to
an employer for whom they will work as
farm labourers or shepherd boys. (Needless
to say, this practice is a flagrant breach of
the law.) In this way many needy parents
forgo the custody of their children and the
exercise of parental authority. There have
been reports that in south and south-east
Asia some employers take possession of
children, against their will, and exploit them
ruthlessly.
When a child is dependent on the
employer in this way, it is usually the
employer himself who fixes the child's
general conditions of work, arbitrarily and
unilaterally. As a result the treatment meted
out to these young workers varies widely,
and reflects the employer's character and
mood, as well as local customs. Thus the
working child may be harshly treated, being
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
» *
Child workers are more liable than grown-ups to occupational accidents because they
lack experience in handling tools and machinery which are normally designed for use
by adults. Since in many cases they are working illegally, they benefit from no form of
social protection. Accidents often occur when the children are tired and their
concentration diminishes. Above, itinerant petrol-sellers being treated in hospital for
burns received during their work.
subject to corporal punishment, abuses of
all kinds, humiliation and frustration. The
possibilities for exploitation are, in practice,
unlimited. Other employers may be pater¬
nalistic, protective and generous. Between
these two extremes the general tendency is
for the child to be treated rather badly since,
as we have seen, he has no way of de¬
fending himself.
The apprenticeship system also gives rise
to abuses. Many children who are declared
by their employers to be apprentices receive
a negligible amount of training. More often
than not they are kept busy running errands
or doing hard, unpleasant jobs which often
have little connexion with the trade they are
supposed to be learning; or else they are
treated as servants and receive little or no
remuneration. The lucky ones, however, do
serve some sort of apprenticeship, despite
the poor conditions under which they work.
In spite of these bad working conditions,
many child workers seem to be satisfied
with the pay and benefits they receive, with
their hours of work, with their working en¬
vironment and with the attitude of the
employer and older fellow-workers, as well
as with the treatment they receive. The
reasons for their job satisfaction probably lie
in the low level of their expectations and in
the fact that they are earning a little money
and are not unemployed.
It is in urban areas, and especially in
manufacturing industry, that child workers
are treated the worst, exploited the most
and undergo the greatest privations. They
often have to work in very bad conditions,
exposed to the elements or, indoors, in a
restricted space in cramped premises which
are stiflingly hot, badly lit, badly ventilated,
noisy, unhealthy and damp. In these
unhygienic surroundings, in an atmosphere
contaminated with dust or gases, they are
crammed together with other workers,
without adequate means of security, and
without adequate toilet facilities. It is not
unusual for them to have to lift and carry
heavy loads, in violation of the principles
and norms laid down by the ILO.
The number of hours worked by children
each day varies considerably. They may for
example, work for part of every working
day, or they may work eight hours a day for
six days a week. Since, as we have seen, the
general conditions of work are usually fixed
arbitrarily by the employer, all kinds of
abuses occur: working days of ten, twelve
or fourteen hours for six or sometimes seven
days a week, that is to say far beyond what
the child can tolerate either physically or
mentally. Sometimes they do not have a fix¬
ed timetable they stay in the shop or café
where they work until the last customer has
left. '
For both self-employed and wage-earning
children the working week seems generally
to be extremely long. In many sectors the
children work six or seven days a week, and
it is common knowledge that girls in
domestic service usually work very long
hours, since they must be available when
their employers need them, almost on a per¬
manent basis.
In many cases young wage earners do not
enjoy the annual paid holidays that are laid
down by law for adult workers doing the
same job. Nor do young people working at
home enjoy annual paid holidays.
In the less developed regions especially,
children who work in the family business
usually receive no payment for their work,
since the family income is considered to be
one indivisible whole. This is equally true
when the family does farm work for a third w
party: the children take part in the,work and r
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
, the head of the family receives the total
earnings.
When the child is a wage-earner, his
wages are usually derisory in comparison to
the value of the work he does, and are in any
case much lower a half or a third or maybe
even less than those received by an adult
doing the same job. Some children, sup¬
posedly apprentices, get hardly any training
but work sometimes for years, without
receiving any pay.
Even in countries where the legal age for
admission to employment is twelve years,
young people of that age are often not paid
the legal minimum salary. When they work
overtime they are generally paid at the nor¬
mal rate (which is already unfairly reduced).
When the child does not work directly for
the employer but with an adult worker, the
latter usually pays the child only a fraction of
what he has earned.
In some kinds of commercial and in¬
dustrial undertakings it is customary for part
of the wages to be paid in cash and part in
kind. In commercial farming, children
sometimes merely receive board and lodg¬
ing; if paid, their wages are often extremely
low. For many parents the fact that a child is
housed and fed outside the home takes
some pressure off the family budget, even
though the child contributes nothing to it.
The self-employed child who has an acci¬
dent or contracts a disease of occupational
origin has nq.form of social protection. If the
child is a wage earner he is not usually pro¬
tected either, since in the vast majority of
cases he is working illegally, as we have
seen. If he is the victim of an occupational
accident or disease, he and his parents must
be prepared for terrible consequences. For
obvious reasons, official statistics reveal
only a very small proportion of the occu¬
pational accidents and diseases that affect
young people.
Agriculture is one of the most hazardous
sectors where the physical safety and health
of workers are concerned. There are a
number of reasons for this: the dangers in¬
volved in using modern machinery; prolong¬
ed exposure to heat, sunlight, dust, wind
and rain; the almost constant physical effort
that agricultural work demands; contact
with various chemical products, such as fer¬
tilisers and pesticides, whose long-term ef¬
fects on man may be completely unknown
and for the majority of which, in cases of
poisoning, no specific antidotes exist.
Children are particularly at risk from endemic
and parasitic diseases, diseases of the
respiratory tract, and dermatosis, and are
often the victims of fatal accidents.
In industry child workers face greater risks
than adults, because children lack ex¬
perience in handling tools, because their
powers of concentration are less than those
of adults, and because of shortages of
This article is based on Children at Work (edited
by Elias Mendelievich), a book prepared by the
International Labour Office as part of its contri¬
bution to the International Year of the Child.
Children at Work was compiled on the basis
of research carried out by the ILO in Geneva
and by independent investigators in some fifteen
countries.
security and prevention equipment such as
masks and special gloves. For example, in
glassworks children suffer greatly from the
suffocating heat and run the risk amongst
others, of sustaining cuts and burns.
Children employed in carpet manufacturing
breathe in wool dust throughout the work¬
ing day, and this penetrates deep into their
lungs.
It should also be borne in mind that, as
machinery, tools and workplaces in general
are designed for use by adults rather than by
children, they are a further potential source
of more or less serious accidents, and call
for increased effort by the child as well as
causing problems of adaptation.
Although children working in the building
industry are usually employed to do light
work, they are nonetheless exposed to a
wide variety of potential accidents and other
hazards such as falls, injuries, and the ef¬
fects of exposure to bad weather. Accidents
are common in this sector and are more like¬
ly to happen to children because of their im¬
maturity and lack of concentration.
In the less developed regions the provi¬
sion of schooling is meeting a number of
serious problems. There is a severe shortage
of facilities, particularly in rural areas, where
schools are few and far between. Because
of the shortage of capacity most schools are
used by two or more sets of pupils. Con¬
sequently, even if all children of school age
were allowed or able to attend school for the
full period of compulsory schooling, they
could not do so because there would be no
school for them to go to.
Thus, despite the tremendous efforts be¬
ing made by the Third World countries to
make schooling available to all, the idea of
universal compulsory education is still very
far from being a reality. There are still vast
numbers of persons who are either illiterate
or semi-literate not only children but adults
as well.
The exploitation of children is found for
the most part in those societies which are in
the throes of modernization or in modern
societies where marginal sectors continue to
exist. It is a consequence of several impor¬
tant social phenomena and is one of the fac¬
tors in a complex situation comprising the
economic system, the way in which society
is organized, and traditional ways of think¬
ing. The solution to the problem lies in the
orderly, progressive development of society
rather than in the adoption of ad hoc
measures; ultimately it lies in a modification
of the three factors mentioned above. This
modification cannot be imposed from out¬
side, and it cannot be achieved without a
wider awareness of the nature and extent of
the problem. The gradual elimination of
child labour is a large-scale and long-term
goal which will not be attained in isolation
from other social changes but as an integral
part of them.
Measuring 8.5 by 5.5 cm.,
this remarkable
neopalaeolithic carving found
at Malaia Syia recounts the
story of how night first came
upon the earth (see article
below). The outer outline, in
the form of a mammoth
facing left, represents the
world. Inside can be seen the
outline of a horse's head
(darker part of photo), also
facing left, within which a
wolf-like beast is depicted
about to spring upon and
devour a deer. Below, the site of
Malaia Syia.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Stone Age
myth-sculptors
of Siberia
by Vitali E. Laritchev
WITH its snow-covered plains,
its mountains and glaciers, its
impenetrable, bear-infested
taiga forests and bitterly cold winters,
Siberia is still widely regarded in some parts
of the world as an inhospitable region where
life is difficult for man, even when equipped
w'rth all the resources of modern civilization.
Yet, for over a century, geologists and an¬
thropologists have been examining the
intriguing possibility that an area of south
central Siberia was the site of the earliest
human settlements of northern Eurasia.
During the 1870s, Russian scientists
discovered in Siberia several sites of an an¬
cient culture. Following these discoveries
French anthropologists advanced the
hypothesis that during the palaeolithic era
Europe was peopled by migrants originating
from Siberia. But in view of the area's
reputedly impossible climate this hypothesis
was considered improbable and by the 1920s
opinion seemed to favour the diametrically
opposite view that during the Ice Age a
more advanced culture was introduced by
migrants moving northwards from the Euro¬
pean Mediterranean area to Siberia where
they encountered "backward savages".
During the 1930s, a site dating back
24,000 years was discovered at Malta, near
Lake Baikal, but it yielded no conclusive
proof of an ancient indigenous culture
and the "migrants from the south" theory
remained unshaken.
In 1975, however, archaeologists began
work on the site of a settlement at Malaia
Syia, on the banks of the river Bely louss in
central Siberia in a valley high up in the
Kuznecki Alatau mountains between
Novosibirsk and Abakan. Radiocarbon
dating of their finds indicated that the settle¬
ment dated back 34,500 ( +450) years.
The men who settled at Malaia Syia chose
their site well, for the valleys of the Kuznecki
Alatau mountains compare in beauty with
those of the Swiss Alps. Remains of bones
recovered from the site indicate that the
valley was the habitat of a surprisingly varied
and abundant animal life reindeer, wild
sheep, ibex, antelope, bison, deer, mam¬
moth, rhinoceros, wild horses, hares and
foxes.
Relieved by this abundance of game of
the necessity to travel in search of food, the
men of Malaia Syia built themselves per¬
manent dwellings, creating a veritable
township covering an area of several thou¬
sand square metres in which a comparative¬
ly developed and complex culture evolved.
The artistic gifts of the men of Malaia Syia
were revealed by the discovery of traces of
paints of many colours red, yellow, crim¬
son, black, green, violet made with
haematite and magnetite iron ores and
malachite copper ore powdered and mixed
with animal fat.
The archaeologists also discovered stone
sculptures including finely-carved pebbles
and rock reliefs of mammoths, rhinoceros,
horses, deer, bulls, wolves and lions, the
standard subjects of palaeolithic carvings.
But in addition to these there are carvings of
eagles and turtles which differ profoundly k
both in shape and composition from those f
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
> of the very oldest European art. Their
originality argues conclusively in favour of
an art with local roots, independent of all
borrowing or forms brought in by migrants
from outside.
Some of these carvings enable us to trace
back to earliest palaeolithic times stories still
remembered in the mythology of the
peoples of northern Asia. The Evenki people
of Siberia used to recount the story of how
Hêgelên the Deer-Sun was devoured by the
beast Main, illustrated in the photo on the
brevious page of a cosmogonie stone carv¬
ing from Malaia Syia.
The oldest version of this myth recounts
that Hêgelên the Deer (the sun) strayed one
day from the protection of the "heavenly
taiga" (forest) and climbed to the top of a
mountain. The beast Main immediately set
off in pursuit tracking Hêgelên all day across
the vault of the heavens from east to west
until, at evening, he caught and devoured
her. This, say the Evenkis, is how night
came to the world. But one of Hêgelên's
fawns escaped from Main and the next
morning climbed again to the top of a moun¬
tain and Main's eternal pursuit began again.
Reflected in the art of Malaia Syia are
cosmogonie or creation myths that are older
and more profound than the fable of the
rising and the setting of the sun. According
to ancient Siberian myth, the universe ori¬
ginally consisted of the primordial waters.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Drawings V. Jalkovsky Photos G. Kashin .© Institute of History, Philology and Philosophy of the Siberian branch of the USSR Academy of Sciences, Novosibirsk
The mammoth Shêli entered this ocean and
from its depths began to dig up the earth
with his tusks. But his enemy, the dragon
Diabdar, flattened out the earth dug up by
Shêli and the world he had created disap¬
peared beneath the waters. The illustrations
above of a carving found at Malaia Syia
depict the furious struggle that ensued bet¬
ween the mammoth Shêli and the turtle, the
aquatic equivalent of the dragon. The mam¬
moth's foreleg crushes down on the neck of
the turtle from whose gaping mouth issues a
roar of pain and terror.
The structure of the world and the
emergence of man and fire are depicted in
another carving from Malaia Syia (illustra¬
tions below). The mammoth, representing
the earth and the world father, is locked in a
sexual embrace with the bison, representing
the sky and the world mother. Emerging
between them is an anthropomorphic lion,
representing the sun, the atmosphere, fire
and man, who will eventually bring about a
rupture between the world parents, I.e. the
earth and the sky.
The discovery of these cultural relics of
the art of Malaia Syia, dating back as it does
some 34,000 years, shortly after the first
emergence of homo sapiens, suggests that
the intellectual capacity of our earliest
ancestors has long been seriously
underestimated by archaeologist and
palaeontologist alike.
VITALI LARITCHEV, of the USSR, is an ar¬
chaeologist and orientalist who specializes in the
Stone Age period of north, central and east Asia.
Since 1971 he has been head of the Oriental
History and Archaeology Section of the Institute
of History, Philology and Philosophy of the
Siberian branch of the USSR Academy of
Sciences. The author of a number of monographs
and scientific works, he has also published several
books for the layman on famous scientists and
great inventions.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
UBdíl PlSgQt, who died in Geneva on 16 September at the age of
eighty-four, was a pioneer investigator of the origin and development of
children's intellectual faculties and is widely regarded as one of the foremost
scientific thinkers of the century.
As co-director of the Institut Jean-Jacques Rousseau in Geneva and a pro¬
fessor ofpsychology at the universities of Geneva and Paris, he developedan
approach to logical and mathematical conceptualization in children which
has greatly influenced modern educators. At the heart of Piaget's complex
theories is the claim that everyone passes through four logically distinct
periods of development, with each period revealing a sequence from simpler
to more complex levels of organization. A famous example of this is the
"conservation problem" : a five-year-old who watches water poured from a
wide container to a long, thin container will say that there is more water in
the latter than there was in the former. He is convinced that because the
water level is higher in the thin container there is more of it than there was in
the wide container. Not until a later stage will the child grasp that changing
the shape of a quantity does not change the amount.
Dr. Piaget was actively associated with Unesco from its inception, serving
notably as head of the Swiss National Commission to Unesco, as a member
of the Organization 's Executive Board, as director of the International Bureau
of Education, and (for a short time) as Assistant Director-General for Educa¬
tion.
He gradually constructed his theories through a long series of brilliant
experiments which began in the 1920s and which continued until his last
years when he was working closely with specialists in various scientific
disciplines (mathematics, logic, etc.) at the Geneva Centre for the Study of
Genetic Epistemology which he had founded in 1955. Many witnesses have
described the remarkable empathy with children which helped Piaget to
enter their world and make the meticulous observations on which his
theories were based. On the following pages we publish a short extract from
a work he wroteasa young man, hoping that it will communicate something
of the zest and intellectual ingenuity with which Piaget examined the pro¬
blems of psychology and human knowledge. Here he uses the children's
game of marbles as a starting point for an enquiry into the way in which
children make moral judgments.
Photo University of Geneva © Journal de Genève
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
by Jean Piaget
Text © Copyright. Reproduction prohibited
CHILDREN'S games constitute
the most admirable social insti¬
tutions. The game of marbles, for
instance, contains an extremely complex
system of rules, that is to say, a code of
laws, a jurisprudence of its own. Only the
psychologist, whose profession obliges him
to become familiar with this instance of
common law, and to get at the implicit
morality underlying it, is in a position to
estimate the extraordinary wealth of these
rules by the difficulty he experiences in
mastering their details.
With regard to game rules there are two
phenomena which it is particularly easy to
study: first the practice of rules, i.e. the way
in which children of different ages effective¬
ly apply rules; second the consciousness of
rules, i.e. the idea which children of dif¬
ferent ages form of the character of these
game rules, whether of something
obligatory and sacred or of something sub¬
ject to their own choice.
The relations which exist between the
practice and the consciousness of rules are
those which will best enable us to define the
psychological nature of moral realities.
The rules [of the game of marbles as it is
played in Geneva and Neuchâtel, in the
districts where we conducted our work]
constitute a well-marked social reality, "in¬
dependent of individuals" and transmitted,
like a language, from one generation to
another. This set of customs is obviously
more or less plastic. But individual innova¬
tions, just as in the case of language, suc¬
ceed only when they meet a general need
and when they are collectively sanctioned as
being in conformity with the "spirit of the
game".
But while fully recognizing the interest at¬
taching to this sociological aspect of the
problem, it was from a different standpoint
that we raised the questions which we are
now going to study. We simply asked
ourselves (1) how the individuals adapt
themselves to these rules, i.e. how they I
observe rules at each age and level of mental I
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
development; (2) how far they become con¬
scious of rules, in other words, what types
of obligation result (always according to the
children's ages) from the increasing ascen¬
dancy exercised by rules.
The interrogatory is therefore easy to
carry out. During the first part, it is sufficient
to ask the children (we questioned about 20
boys ranging from 4 to 12-13) how one plays
marbles. The experimenter speaks more or
less as follows. "Here are some marbles."
(The marbles are placed on a large baize-
covered tablé beside a piece of chalk.) "You
must show me how to play. When I was
little I used to play a lot, but now I've
quite forgotten how to. I'd like to play again.
Let's play together. You'll teach me the rules
and I'll play with you."
The child then draws a square, takes half
the marbles, puts down his "pose", and the
game begins. It is important to bear in mind
all possible contingencies of the game and
to ask the child about each. This means that
you must avoid making any suggestions.
All you need do is to appear completely
ignorant, and even to make intentional
mistakes so that the child may each time
point out clearly what the rule is. Naturally,
you must take the whole thing very serious¬
ly, all through the game. Then you ask who
has won and why, and if everything is not
quite clear, you begin a new set.
It is of paramount importance during this
first half of the interrogatory to play your
part in a simple spirit and to let the child feel
a certain superiority at the game (while not
omitting to show by an occasional good
shot that you are not a complete duffer).
In this way the child is put at his ease, and
the information he gives as to how he plays
is all the more conclusive. Many of our
children became absorbed in the game to
the extent of treating me completely as one
of them. "You are dished!" cries Ben (10
years) when my marble stops inside the
square.
In the case of the little ones, who find dif¬
ficulty in formulating the rules which they
observe in practice, the best way is to make
them play in pairs. You begin by playing
with one of them in the manner described
above, and ask him to tell you all the rules he
knows.
Then you make the same request of the
second boy (the first being no longer pre¬
sent), and finally you bring the two together
and ask them to have a game. This control
experiment is not needed for older children,
except in doubtful cases.
Then comes the second part of the inter¬
rogatory, that, namely, which bears upon
the consciousness of rules. You begin by
asking the child if he could invent a new
rule. He generally does this easily enough,
but it is advisable to make sure that it really
is a new rule and not one of the many ex¬
isting variants of which this particular child
may already have knowledge.
"I want a rule that is only by you, a rule
that you've made up yourself and that no
one else knows the rule of N (the child's
name)."
Once the new rule has been formulated,
you ask the child whether it could give rise
to a new game: "Would it be all right to play
like that with your pals? Would they want to
play that way? etc."
The child either agrees to the suggestion
or disputes it. If he agrees, you immediately
ask him whether the new rule is a "fair" rule,
a "real" rule, one "like the others", and try
to get at the various motives that enter into
the answers.
If, on the other hand, the child disagrees
with all this, you ask him whether the new
rule could not by being generalized become
a real rule. "When you are a big boy, sup¬
pose you tell your new rule to a lot of
children, then perhaps they'll all play that
way and everyone will forget the old rules.
Then which rule will be fairest yours that
everyone knows, or the old one that
everyone has forgotten?"
The formula can naturally be altered in ac¬
cordance with the turn which the conversa¬
tion is taking, but the main point is to find
out whether one may legitimately alter rules
and whether a rule is fair or just because it
conforms to general usage (even newly in¬
troduced), or because it is endowed with an
intrinsic and eternal value.
Having cleared up this point it will be easy
enough to ask the two following questions.
( 1 ) Have people a Iways played as they do to¬
day: "Did your daddy play this way when he
was little, and your grand-dad, and children
in the time of William Tell, Noah, and Adam
and Eve, etc., did they all play the way you
showed me, or differently? (2) What is the
origin of rules: Are they invented by children
or laid down by parents and grown-ups in
general?
Sometimes it is best to begin by these last
two questions before asking whether rules
'I am an anxious man who can
only find solace in work'
"People have often asked me how I found the
time to write so much, in addition to my
university work and my international duties...
Fundamentally I am an anxious person who
can only find solace in work. It is true that I
am sociable and that I enjoy teaching and tak
ing part in meetings of all kinds, but I feel a
pressing need for solitude and contact with
nature. After a morning spent with other peo¬
ple, I start each afternoon with a walk during
which I calmly collect my ideas together and
coordinate them, before returning to my
work-table at home in the country. As soon as
the holidays arrive, I take refuge in the moun¬
tains in the wild parts of the Valais and I
write for weeks at a time on improvised
tables after pleasant walks. This dissociation
in me between the social creature and the
man of nature (in whom dionysiac excitement
achieves fulfilment in intellectual activity) has
enabled me to overcome a permanent under¬
current of anxiety and to transform it into a
need for work."
Extract from Jean Piagefs Autobiography,
Revue Européenne des Sciences Sociales,
1976 © Librairie Droz, Geneva
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Jte.
Photo © G Bern, Pans
can be changed; this avoids perseveration,
or rather reverses its direction, and so
facilitates the interpretation of the answers.
All this part of the interrogatory, moreover,
requires extremely delicate handling; sug¬
gestion is always ready to occur, and the
danger of romancing is ever present.
But it goes without saying that the main,
thing is simply to grasp the child's mental
orientation. Does he believe in the mystical
virtue of rules or in their finality? Does he
subscribe to a heteronomy of divine law, or
is he conscious of his own autonomy? This
is the only question that interests us. The
child has naturally got no ready-made beliefs
on the origin and endurance of the rules of
his games; the ideas which he invents then
and there are only indices of his funda¬
mental attitude, and this must be steadily
borne in mind throughout the whole of the
interrogatory.
The results which we obtained from this
double interrogatory are roughly as follows:
From the point of view of the practice or
application of rules four successive stages
can be distinguished.
A first stage of a purely motor and in¬
dividual character, during which the child
handles the marbles at the dictation of his
desires and motor habits. This leads to the
formation of more or less ritualized
schémas, but since play is still purely in¬
dividual, one can only talk of motor rules
and not of truly collective rules.
The second may be called egocentric for
the following reasons. This stage begins at
the moment when the child receives from
outside the example of codified rules, that is
to say, some time between the ages of two
and five.
But though the child imitates this exam¬
ple, he continues to play either by himself
without bothering to find play-fellows, or
with others, but without trying to win, and
therefore without attempting to unify the
different ways of playing.
In other words, children of this stage,
even when they are playing together, play
each one "on his own" (everyone can win at
once) and without regard for any codifica¬
tion of rules. This dual character, combining
imitation of others with a purely individual
use of the examples received, we have des¬
ignated by the term Egocentrism.
A third stage appears between 7 and 8, l
which we shall call the stage of incipient co- f
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
( operation. Each player now tries to win, and
all, therefore, begin to concern them¬
selves with the question of mutual control
and of unification of the rules. But while a
certain agreement may be reached in the
course of one game, ideas about the rules in
general are still rather vague.
In other words, children of 7-8, who
belong to the same class at school and are
therefore constantly playing with each
other, give, when they are questioned
separately, disparate and often entirely con¬
tradictory accounts of the rules observed in
playing marbles.
Finally, between the years of 11 and 12,
appears a fourth stage, which is that of the
codification of rules. Not only is every detail
of procedure in the game fixed, but the ac¬
tual code of rules to be observed is known to
the whole society. There is remarkable con¬
cordance in the information given by
children of 10-12 belonging to the same
class at school, when they are questioned
on the rules of the game and their possible
variations.
These stages must of course be taken on¬
ly for what they are worth. It is con¬
venient for the purposes of exposition to
divide the children up in age-classes or
stages, but the facts present themselves as a
continuum which cannot be cut up into
sections.
This continuum, moreover, is not linear in
character, and its general direction can only
be observed by schematizing the material
and ignoring the minor oscillations which
render it infinitely complicated in detail. So
that ten children chosen a*t random will
perhaps not give the impression of a steady
advance which gradually emerges from
the interrogatory put to the hundred odd
subjects examined by us at Geneva and
Neuchâtel.
If, now, we turn to the consciousness of
rules we shall find a progression that is even
more elusive in detail, but no less clearly
marked if taken on a big scale. We may ex¬
press this by saying that the progression
runs through three stages, of which the se¬
cond begins during the egocentric stage and
ends towards the middle of the stage of co¬
operation (9-10), and of which the third
covers the remainder of this co-operating
stage and the whole of the stage marked by
the codification of rules.
During the first stage rules are not yet
coercive in character, either because they
are purely motor, or else (at the beginning of
the egocentric stage) because they are
received, as it were, unconsciously, and
as interesting examples rather than as
obligatory realities.
During the second stage (apogee of
egocentric and first half of co-operating
stage) rules are regarded as sacred and un¬
touchable, emanating from adults and
lasting forever. Every suggested alteration
strikes the child as a transgression.
Finally, during the third stage, a rule is
looked upon as a law due to mutual con¬
sent, which you must respect if you want to
be loyal but which it is permissible to alter on
the condition of enlisting general opinion on
your side.
The correlation between the three stages
in the development of the consciousness of
rules and the four stages relating to their
practical observance is of course only a
statistical correlation and therefore very
crude. But broadly speaking the relation
seems to us indisputable.
The collective rule is at first something ex¬
ternal to the individual and consequently
sacred to him; then, as he gradually makes it
his own, it comes to that extent to be felt as
the free product of mutual agreement and
an autonomous conscience. And with
regard to practical use, it is only natural that
a mystical respect for laws should be accom¬
panied by a rudimentary knowledge and
application of their contents, while a
rational and well-founded respect is accom¬
panied by an effective application of each
rule in detail.
There would therefore seem to be two
types of respect for rules corresponding to
two types of social behaviour. This conclu¬
sion deserves to be closely examined, for if it
holds good, it should be of the greatest
value to the analysis of child morality. One
can see at once all that it suggests in regard
to the relation between child and adult.
Take the insubordination of the child
towards its parents and teachers, joined to
its sincere respect for the commands it
receives and its extraordinary mental docili¬
ty. Could not this be due to that complex of
attitudes which we can observe during the
egocentric stage and which combines so
paradoxically an unstable practice of the law
with a mystical attitude towards it?
And will not co-operation between adult
and child, in so far as it can be realized and
in so far as it is facilitated by co-operation
between children themselves, supply the
key to the interiorization of commands
and to the autonomy of the moral
consciousness?
Let us therefore not be afraid of devoting
a certain amount of time to the patient
analysis of the rules of a game.
Jean Piaget
Piaget maintained that numerical evaluation in the child's mind is for a long
time linked with the way in which objects are arranged spatially. In one
experiment a child at a certain stage of development is shown two rows of
beads each of the same length and each containing the same number of beads.
If the beads in one row are spaced out further, the child concludes that the
longer row contains more beads. Photo shows an experiment on numerical
correspondence with a seven-year-old child.
This article has been adapted from "The Rules of
the Game", a study carried out by Jean Piaget
(with the collaboration of Mme V.-J. Piaget and
Messrs M. Lambercier and L. Martinez) which
constitutes the first chapter of The Moral Judg¬
ment of the Child, published in 1932 by Kegan
Paul, Trench, Trubner and Co. Ltd, London.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the editor
MOBRAL:
THE ACHIEVEMENT BEHIND
THE STATISTICS
Sir,
I have recently read the June issue of the
Unesco Courier, and on pages 4 to 9 I came
across an interesting analysis of the illiteracy
problem in the world and some of the efforts
towards its eradication being made by several
countries, often with Unesco's support. The arti¬
cle's title is "Literacy a right denied to 800
million", and it paints a rather harsh, but truthful,
picture of the world problem. To illustrate these
remarks a graph on page 6-7 shows the distribu¬
tion of illiteracy in the world, and attributes to
Latin America the total of 44 million. Out of the
latter, 18 million are said to belong to Brazil and
this is precisely the reason for this letter. Brazil is
presented as still having 18 million adult illiterates
and these figures do not coincide with
MOBRAL's statistics.
As you are well aware, the MOBRAL Founda¬
tion has been dealing with this matter in Brazil
since 1970, when this country still had 18 million
illiterate adults. In ten years, however and this
can be proved by impartial documents, some of
which have been published or sponsored by
Unesco this figure has been reduced to 7.5
million which brings the adult illiteracy rate in
Brazil down to 11 per cent. According to
Unesco's standards this percentage is considered
almost satisfactory. To corroborate this assertion,
on the last page of the same issue, Mr Ralph C.
Staiger, from the International Reading Associa¬
tion, mentions MOBRAL's efforts, and quotes the
figure of 13 million as the number of .individuals
made literate in the period 1970-80. It seems clear
that the figure of 18 million shown in the graph is
incorrect unless there is a footnote explaining that
it corresponds to the year of 1970, when
MOBRAL was just initiating its operations.
Thanking you for having referred to MOBRAL
in your magazine.
Arlindo Lopes Correa
President of Mobral,
Brazil
The numbers of illiterates over the age of 15 given
in the diagram on pages 6 and 7 of the June issue
of the Unesco Courier are, as the caption in¬
dicated, estimates by the Unesco Office of
Statistics. The projections for Brazil are based on
returns from the census taken in 1970 and a new
census which has just been completed will enable
the situation to be clarified. Of course, projections
such as these can be considerably modified by
mass literacy campaigns. However, it should be
pointed out that if the Unesco estimate proves to
be correct, it nevertheless represents an enor¬
mous achievement on the part of MOBRAL (The
Brazilian Literacy Movement) and all those involv¬
ed in the fight against illiteracy in Brazil. For in the
ten years between 1970 and 1980 the Brazilian
population over the age of 15 increased by a stag¬
gering 35 per cent, from 54,585,200 to
73,988,900. During the same period Unesco
statistics show that the absolute number of adult
illiterates in Brazil fell by 292, 100 and the percen¬
tage of illiteracy fell from 33. 8 per cent to 24. 5 per
cent, a truly remarkable achievement by any
standard. Editor.
THE VICTIMS OF AUSCHWITZ
Sir,
Many of your readers must, like me, have been
concerned that the reference to Auschwitz-
Birkenau in George Fradier's article "Wonders of
the World", in the August 1980 issue of the
Unesco Courier, was incomplete.
The article failed to mention that of the four
million men, women and children assassinated at
Auschwitz, the great majority were Jewish. This
was surely a major omission.
Serge Cwajgenbaum
World Jewish Congress,
Paris
Millions of people, the majority of them Jews,
were deported to and died in the three concentra¬
tion camps established by the Nazis at Auschwitz-
Birkenau (the Polish localities of Oswiecim-
Brzenzinka). As the author of our article pointed
out, the name of Auschwitz will be forever
associated in the minds of men with the horror of
this outrageous crime against humanity. Editor.
MAINTAIN A WORTHY LEVEL
Sir,
With articles by specialists from all over the
world, clearly expressed ideas, subjects of univer¬
sal interest, and the variety of styles and high
moral tone of the authors from many different
countries who write in it, the Unesco Courier is a
magazine worthy of the Organization from which
it emanates.
I would not, however, have written to you in
this vein had it not been for the letter, published in
your September 1980 issue, from thirteen-year-
old Laurent Cavelier of Fecamp. He suggests that
you should lower the level of the vocabulary
employed and reduce the language of the articles
to a simpler, more basic form suited to his thirteen
years and, indeed, to older persons who have not
progressed beyond that stage. This, of course,
would mean either that you would no longer be
able to call upon the best writers, or that you
would have to ask them to write in the language
of their youth.
The letter does, of course, express an in¬
teresting point of view. What worries me,
however, is that in asking for readers' comments
on it you put in question the whole tone and
standing of the Unesco Courier, whereas other no
less interesting letters are published without
comment.
Emmanuel Mouchel
Saint-Denis,
France
KEEP IT SIMPLE
FOR THE YOUNG...
Sir,
I read Laurent Cavelier's letter in the September
1980 issue of the Unesco Courier with great in¬
terest, and in my opinion it deserves careful con¬
sideration.
Many young people would agree with
Cavelier's criticism that the Unesco Courier seems
to be addressed to an intellectual élite. In my own
case, I had some difficulty in understanding the
articles when I first began reading the magazine at
the age of sixteen.
I am convinced that a magazine like yours has
an important educative role to play and I consider
that young people should be its primary target.
The use of simpler wording, particularly in scien¬
tific texts, seems to me to be indispensable if you
are to hold the interest of this group of readers,
many of whom show great interest in the
magazine.
Béatrice Gretter
Mulhouse,
France
... AND FOR
THE OLDER READER...
Sir,
Although I am over sixty years old, I agree en¬
tirely with the point of view expressed by Mr.
Cavelier in your September 1980 issue, which is
just as valid for your older readers as for the
younger ones.
Since the aim of the Unesco Courier is to make
as many people as possible think about world
problems, it would be as well not to put off large
numbers of them by too academic a presentation.
Nevertheless, it is my hope that, whatever ap¬
proach you adopt, your action in favour of peace
will be successful.
M. Durand
Lamotte Beuvron,
France
IN THE NEXT ISSUE
The December issue of the Unesco Courier,
featuring eight pages in full colour, will mark
the hundredth anniversary of the birth of
Pablo Picasso (1881-1973) and will be entire¬
ly devoted to the life and work of the great
Spanish painter.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Unesco newsroom
UNICEF Greeting Cards
Over 350 million children around the globe
lack adequate food supplies, medical care,
clean water, and schools. One way of help¬
ing to improve this tragic situation is by sup¬
porting the work of the United Nations
Children's Fund (UNICEF). In 1978 UNICEF
raised $20,300,000 through the sale of
greeting cards, gifts and stationery, and
used these much-needed funds to bring
food, health services and education to
needy children and mothers in over a hun¬
dred countries of Asia, Africa and Latin
America! This year's UNICEF cards and sta¬
tionery are now available at UNICEF sales
points throughout the world. The cards, in
standard or mini format, feature over sixty
designs donated by artists and museums
from many countries. Also available is
UNICEF's trilingual (English, French,
Spanish) 1981 engagement calendar,
lavishly illustrated on the theme of "Festivals
and Celebrations". Proceeds from the sale
of just one box of cards mean that ten
children can be protected from measles, a
leading child killer in the developing world.
Above, card reproducing a batik design by
an anonymous Indonesian artist;
20th Anniversary of the U.N.
Declaration on Decolonization
December 14, 1980, marks the twentieth an¬
niversary of the adoption by the United Na¬
tions General Assembly of the Declaration
on the Granting of Independence to Colonial
Countries and Peoples. The Declaration pro¬
claimed the need to bring colonialism, in all
its forms and manifestations, to a speedy
and unconditional end. It declared that "the
subjection of peoples to alien subjugation,
domination and exploitation constitutes a
denial of fundamental human rights, is con¬
trary to the Charter of the United Nations
and is an impediment to the promotion of
34
world peace and co-operation". Since the
adoption of the Declaration more than
seventy million people have emerged from
dependent status. At present some three
million people still live in non-self-governing
territories which are politically dependent on
other countries.
Two new Member States
Zimbabwe and the Kingdom of Tonga
became members of Unesco on 22 and 29
September respectively. This brings the
number of Unesco's Member States to 153.
Photo © Italian Edition, Unesco Courier
Italian educators
honour Unesco Courier
Tribute was paid to the Unesco Courier by
Italy's National Centre of Socio-
Psychographic Studies at a convention on
the audio-visual media and education, held
in Venice on 10 and 11 October 1980. At the
opening of the convention, attended by
representatives of the mass media and
teachers in primary, secondary and higher
education, a gold plaque was presented to
Mme Maria Remiddi (above), who has been
Managing Editor of our Italian language edi¬
tion for the past 16 years. The plaque is in¬
scribed: "For the constant concern shown
by the Unesco Courier in handling educa¬
tional, scientific and cultural problems".
BOOKSHELF
RECENT UNESCO BOOKS
AND PERIODICALS
The International Yearbook of
Education Vol. XXXII 1980, prepared
for the International Bureau of Education
by Brian Holmes. 1980. 242 pp. (32 F).
Made to Measure: Children's
Books in Developing Countries, by
Anne Pellowski. 1980. 129 pp. (22 F).
The Teaching of Human Rights.
The proceedings of an international con¬
gress on the teaching of human rights
held in Vienna in September 1978, under
Unesco's auspices. 1980. 259 pp. (35 F).
Unesco Handbook for Science
Teachers. A companion volume to the
New Unesco Source Book for
Science Teaching published by Unesco
in 1973. 1980. 199 pp. (45 F) Co-
published with Heinemann, London.
Environmental Education in the
Light of the Tbilisi Conference. (No. 3
in Unesco's "Education on the Move"
series). 1980. 100 pp. (18 F).
New Trends and New Respon¬
sibilities for Universities in Latin
America. Published by Unesco and the
International Association of Universities.
1980. 96 pp. (22 F).
Communication Policies in
Kenya, by Peter Mwaura. 1980. 95 pp.
(20 F).
Science, Technology and Govern¬
mental Policy. A Ministerial Con¬
ference for Europe and North America
(Minespol II). (No. 44 in Unesco's
"Science Policy Studies and
Documents" series). 183 pp. (20 F).
OTHER BOOKS RECEIVED
Environmental Education: Prin¬
ciples, Methods and Applications,
edited by Trilochan S. Bakshi and Zen
Naveh. 1980. Plenum Press, New York.
285 pp. ($32.50).
Readings in Physical Anthro¬
pology and Archaeology, edited by
David E. Hunter and Philip Whitten.
Harper and Row publishers, New York.
346 pp. 1978.
Anawrahta of Burma, by Khin Myo
Chit. A historical novel woven around
the story of Anawrahta, king of Burma in
the 11th century. 2nd edition 1979. .
Published by Daw Khin Myo Chit,
Rangoon. 217 pp.
Gotama the Indian Prince. The
story of the young Buddha, 77 pp.;
Jeshua in an Occupied Country. An
imaginative reconstruction of the young
Jesus's life in Palestine at the time of the
Roman occupation, 79 pp.; Muham¬
mad the Arab Boy. A description of the
Prophet's childhood in 6th-century
Arabia, 64 pp. Nos 1, 2 and 3 in the
"Boyhood" series on the childhood of
the founders of the great world religions,
written by Byron Evans and illustrated by
Joan Gammans. Published by Stainer
and Bell Ltd., 82 High Road, London N2
9PW. (£1.50 each).
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Just published...
Many
Voices,
One
World
Smb MorBrti»
* EW Ah-i H.J-H i buw M+i -, Ebb* H« Ck
Oaktol Q**<- M».***» * Cmvm Uh* * HmM* UifcM
* *-r-* r*-1-'1- * " "^* * h-	-i i n _ii t
In 1977, in fulfilment of a mandate from the Organization's
General Conference, Unesco's Director-General appointed an
"International Committee for the Study of Communication
Problems", under the presidency of Sean'MacBride. The
Commission's members, from 16 different countries, were
asked to examine "the totality of communication problems in
modern societies". The publication of Many Voices, One
World now makes available the full text of their final report.
Among the questions addressed in this far-reaching study:
How to remedy imbalances and distortions in information,
especially at the international level?
What should be the guidelines for building a more just, more
efficient and better balanced communications system based
on democratic principles?
How to approach the problems of one-way flows of
information, the concentration of media ownership, freedom
and responsibility of the press, the power of transnational
corporations, the right to communicate?
A Unesco co-edition with Kogan Page, London and Unipub, New York
312 pages 50 francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscrip¬
tion rates in local currency, will be supplied
on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P.O.
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept , P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne {Victoria!, 3000.
AUSTRIA. Dr. Franz Ham, Verlags-und Kommissionsbuch¬
handlung, Industriehof Stadlau, Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasse 5, 1220
Wien. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent- Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7. CHINA. China National Publications Import Corpora¬
tion, West Europe Department, P.O. Box 88, Peking
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makanos 3rd Avenue, P 0. Box
1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena
51, Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura, 11 Sou-
kenicka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers,
Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava - CSSR. - DENMARK.
Munksgaard Export and Subscription Service, 35 Norre Sogade,
DK 1370, Copenhagen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF).
National Centre for Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb
Street, Cairo. ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O.
Box 2996, Addis Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirja-
kauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100 Helsinki 10. - FRANCE.
Librairie da I'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Pans, CCP.
12598-48. - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leip¬
zig, Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhand¬
lungen in the G D.R. - FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the
Unesco Kurier (German ed. only): Deutscher Unesco - Vertrieb,
Basaltstrasse 57, D-5300 Bonn 3. For scientific maps only: GEO
CENTER D7 Stuttgart 80, Postfach 800830. Other publications:
S. Karger GmbH, Karger Buchhandlung, Angerhofstrasse 9,
Postach 2, 8034 Germenng/Mùnchen. GHANA. Presby¬
terian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195, Accra; Ghana
Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University
Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape
Coast; The University Bookshop of Legón, P.O. Box 1, Legón.
GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. - HONG
KONG. Federal Publications IHK) Ltd , 5A Evergreen Industrial
Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-
15, Lock Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY. Akadémiai Konyves-
bolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V; A K.V. Konyvturosok Boltja,
Népkóztársaság utja 16, Budapest VI. ICELAND. Snaeb|6rn
Jonsson & Co., H F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA.
Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay
400038, 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13, 36a, Anna Salai,
Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf AM Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1
Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-Depots: Oxford Book Et Stationery Co.
17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House, New Delhi
Publications Section, Ministry of Education and Social Welfare,
511 C-Wmg, Shastn Bhavan, New Delhi 110001. -
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah
Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr Sam Ratulangie 47,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution
Co., 28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Enghélab Avenue, P.O. Box
314/1486, Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco, Ave.
Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B P. 1533, Teheran. IRAQ.
McKenzie's Bookshop, Al -Rashid Street, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd.,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL. A B.C.
Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv 61000
- JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101
Water Lane, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc.,
Shuhwa Toranomon 3bldg, 23-6, Toranomon 3-Chome, Minato-
ku, Tokyo 105, - KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O.
Box 30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. - KUWAIT. The
Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait - LESOTHO.
Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern
Africa. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd , P.O. Box
286, Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency for Development of
Publication Er Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue,
Luxembourg. MALAYSIA. Federal Publications, Lot 8323,
JI.222, Petaling Jaya, Selangor. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26
Republic Street, Valletta. MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company
Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis. - MONACO. British
Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. - NETHERLANDS.
For the "Unesco Koener" Dutch edition only: Systemen
Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75, Amsterdam-1007. Agent for all
Unesco publications: N.V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9,
The Hague. - NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddme
N V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. - NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, Government
Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 130,
Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Chnstchurch; Alma Street, P.O.
Box 857 Hamilton,- Princes Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin;
Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington. NIGERIA. The
University Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan,
P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of Nsukka; The University
Bookshop of Lagos;The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of
Zana. NORWAY. All publications: Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco
Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste. Box 6125, Oslo 6.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-e-azam,
P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404 -
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda, Livrana
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. - SEYCHELLES. New
Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé.
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications IS) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19. - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951,
Mogadiscio. SOUTH AFRICA. All publications: Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.
-SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam
Gardiner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2. SUDAN. Al Bashir
Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. - SWEDEN. All
publications A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel,
Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16. For the
Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Forbundet, Skolgrànd 2, Box 150
50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. - SWITZERLAND. All publications:
Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue
Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11, CC.P:i2-236. - TANZANIA. Dar¬
es Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam.
THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road,
Siyaeg Phaya Sn, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok: Suksapan Panit,
Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam
Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I. - TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi
A.S., Istiklâl Caddesi, No. 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu,
Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Govt. Bookshops in London,
Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmin¬
gham, Bristol. -UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue
South, New York, N.Y. 10010. - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya
Kniga, Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska
Knjiga, Trg Republike 5/8, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba
Slovénie, Titova C 25, P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubliana. - ZIMBABWE.
Textbook Sales (PVTI Ltd., 67 Union Avenue, Salisbury.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
November 1980 from
A bulletin published by
the Office
of Public Information
Unesco
7, place de Fontenoy
75700 Paris, France
news
unesco
i^HEL». \m
o
C
b.
i>
00
o
p¿
u
3
0a
"c
i
o
a
o
o
SI
0.
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow addressing the Conference after his unanimous
re-election as Director-General of Unesco
Unesco General Conference, in Belgrade,
approves three-year, $625,734,000 programme
"\ /TEETING in Belgrade, period into line with those of other Maldives, Zimbabwe and the Kingdom
1V1 Yugoslavia, a crossroads of United Nations agencies. Secondly, it of Tonga.
Eastern and Western cultures, the 21st was extraordinary in that the 1,869 The Conference heard addresses by
session of the Unesco General delegates from 150 of Unesco's 153 several eminent statesmen, beginning
Conference adoptedlargely by Member States included no fewer than witn the pres¡dent 0f tne presidium of
consensusa $625,734,000 programme 134 ministers and hundreds of tjje federal Socialist Republic of
for the Organization for the next three specialists of all sorts: archaeologists, Yugoslavia Mr Cvijetin Mijatovic
years. oceanographers, jurists, educational who paid ¿but"e t0 Unesco as a
The meeting, which lasted from 23 planners, poets, and even a "symbol of the broadest aspirations
September to 28 October, was unique cosmonaut. Eight countries were towards democracy and the
from several points of view. First of represented for the first time at the humanization of international
all, it planned Unesco's activities for a General Conference: Dominica, relations". President Sekou Touré of
three-year period instead of two. This Equatorial Guinea, Botswana, Sao the Revolutionary People's Republic
was done to bring Unesco's fiscal Tome and Principe, St. Lucia, the of Gumea caiieci on Member States to
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
support the Organization in full
measure "so that its action in favour
of each one of our countries will be
more effective". The Prime Minister
of Bangladesh, Shah Azizur Rahman,
appealed for progress in the North-
South dialogue, saying "We want
bridges not bombs".
The Secretary-General of the
Organization of African Unity, Mr.
Edem Kodjo, and Mr. Yasser Arafat,
President of the Palestine Liberation
Organization, who also
addressed plenary sessions, were among
a number of high officials of
intergovernmental, United Nations or
non-governmental organizations
attending.
The Conference also drew to Belgrade
outstanding artists from 15 countries
in widely separated regions of the
globe who gave performances and
concerts. The Sava Centar, where the
sessions took place, was the scene of
an outstanding event organized to
mark the 15th centenary of the
Hegira, a round table on "Islam
Today", in which eminent scholars
and scientists from all over the Muslim
world took part.
Working from dawn to dusk and often
far into the night, the delegates
participated in more than 200 plenary
sessions or commission meetings and
took decisions on more than 400 draft
resolutions. In addition to hammering
out the programme of Unesco
activities for the three years to come,
the Conference:
Unanimously re-elected
Mr. Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
of Senegal as Director-General
of Unesco for a seven-year
term.
Decided to increase the
membership of the Unesco
Executive Board from 45 to 51
in order to give additional
representation to Third World
nations, and elected 25
members to fill seats on the
Board which fell vacant at the
end of this term.
Adopted a recommendation on
the status of artists which
called on Member States to
take measures to "secure
greater freedom for artists,
without which they cannot
fulfil their mission, and
improve their status by
acknowledging their right to
enjoy the fruits of their work".
Endorsed the
Director-General's comments
and observations on the
findings of the International
Commission for the Study of
Communication Problems,
headed by Mr. Sean MacBride,
and particularly his view that
the Commission's
recommendations and analyses,
far from being definitive,
merely provided a basis for
broader and more intensive
discussions.
Adopted by consensus a
compromise resolution listing
some of the principles which
could underlie a new world
information and
communication order, called
for a study of principles which
might be included in a
declaration on this subject, and
decided to establish, within the
framework of Unesco, an
International Programme for
the Development of
Communication.
Decided to hold the next
regular session of the General
Conference in Paris in 1983,
with an extraordinary session to
be held (also in Paris) in 1982
to decide on Unesco's next six-
year Medium Term Plan of
Action.
While the widely shared desire for
consensus marked the entire
Conference, international events in a
rapidly changing and frequently tragic
world could not fail to affect the
deliberations.
At the inauguration, the Director-
General called on Iran and Iraq to end
their "fratricidal conflict". During the
course of the Conference, a
devastating earthquake ravaged the
region of Al Asnam in Algeria. Within
hours of the disaster, the Director-
General had offered Unesco's aid, and
when the plenary session met to call
for international solidarity on behalf
of the stricken population, he was able
to announce the despatch of a Unesco
mission to Al Asnam.
While the Conference was in
commission studying problems of
communication, appeals were launched
on behalf of a news agency
correspondent arrested in Africa. At
the end of the Conference, a
resolution was overwhelmingly
approved (82 votes in favour, 15
against and 4 abstentions with 49
absentees) supporting the Director-
General's efforts to secure the release
of a Unesco official, jailed by his
home country, in violation of its
commitments to respect his immunity
as an international civil servant.
The 372-page programme adopted by
the Conference spells out details of
Unesco's activities on behalf of a wide
variety of objectives ranging from
respect for human rights and
appreciation and respect for cultural
identity through the struggle against
illiteracy, status of women and
participation by women in
development, human rights and peace,
to the free flow of information and
the process and role of
communication.
Education: stress on action
THE focus in the education
programme, the largest of the
Organization's sectors, is on concrete,,
practical measures to broaden access
to education, especially for certain
disadvantaged groups. Unesco will
assist Member States to improve
educational administration and to
reduce construction costs of
educational facilities. Other steps are
planned to strengthen the links
between education and work and
between formal and non-formal
education.
For operational activities, the
education programme foresees a
budgetary increase of 20 per cent for
projects funded by the United Nations
system and of nearly 35 per cent for
those funded from other extra-
budgetary sources. It also places a
greater emphasis on technical co¬
operation among developing countries.
Of particular significance is a major
project in Latin America and the
Caribbean area. Inter-disciplinary in
character, it aims to reform education,
promote culture and advance
knowledge of science and technology
with a view to increasing productivity
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
and improving living conditions in the
region.
Unesco will also give support to a
major adult education programme in
the Arab Republic of Yemen and
launch an international appeal for
material and moral assistance to
Ethiopia's campaign to eradicate
illiteracy.
Science:
nine new regional
projects
THE main thrust of the science
programme, the fastest
growing area of Unesco's work, is to
promote the access of developing
countries to modern science and
technology, through consultant
services, training and technical
co-operation. While continuity of
action is provided by the strengthening
of the large-scale scientific
programmes (Man and the Biosphere,
the International Hydrological
Programme, the International
Geological Correlation Programme
and the Intergovernmental
Océanographie Commission),
innovation appears in the form of nine
major regional projects and the
reinforcement of activities in
informatics, in new and renewable
sources of energy and in integrated
rural development.
The nine major projects, which are
designed to make concrete
contributions to the establishment of
endogenous infrastructures in science
and technology, cover the integration
of technological research, training and
development in South-East Asia and
the Pacific; biotechnology and applied
microbiology in Africa and the Arab
States; geology for development in
Africa; integrated management of
tropical humid zones; integrated
management of arid and semi-arid
zones; rational utilization of water
resources in rural areas (Latin
America, Arab States and Africa
south of the Sahara); and research and
training leading to the integrated
management of coastal ecosystems.
The social sciences:
tools for understanding and action
AS in previous years, the social
science programme aims both
at the strengthening and development
of the social sciences and their
application to development problems.
It includes the encouragement of basic
and applied research, and creating or
supporting regional and national
institutions in order to promote the
endogenous development of the social
sciences.
Studies are also planned on the new
international economic order and the
influence of transnational corporations
in Unesco's fields.
Social science activities concerned with
the environment and human
settlements make up an important part
of the programme. They are designed
to train people responsible for land
management or town planning in the
complexities of environmental
problems.
In the field of population, projects
have been approved for the study of
internal and international migrations,
the effect of population factors on the
status of women, and the training of
personnel in communication on
population problems.
Education for disarmament occupies
an important place in the activities on
behalf of human rights and peace. In
addition, normative action is planned
to ensure the implementation of
existing international agreements on
human rights, as well as the study of
obstacles to the exercise of human
rights by certain disadvantaged groups.
Cultural identity
and the need for cultural exchange
ASSISTANCE to museums in
Aswan and Cairo, activities
to mark the anniversaries of Picasso,
Bêla Bartok, Andres Bello and Simon
Bolivar, preserving oral traditions in
Africa, supporting the Pacific Arts
Festival, protecting cultural and
natural sites the world over, organizing
a world conference on cultural
policies: all these examples illustrate
the wide variety of activities included
in Unesco's cultural programme.
The programme is centered around
two inter-related themes: the
recognition of the cultural identity of
all peoples and the need to promote
increasing exchanges between cultures.
Included in the programme are the
continuation or initiation of inter¬
cultural studies and studies of
Caribbean, Latin American, Asian,
Pacific and African cultures, as well as
the revision of Unesco's Scientific and
Cultural Historj of Mankind. The
programme also envisages the further
development of the International Fund
for the Promotion of Culture. The
Fund, established in 1974, has
provided assistance to date totalling
$1,300,000 for 90 projects.
Communication:
the drive for democratization
UNESCO, which has spearheaded
efforts to democratize
communication both within nations
and internationally, has emerged as
the lead agency in the United Nations
system with constitutional
responsibilities in the information and
communication fields.
In addition to the new International
Programme for the Development of
Communication referred to earlier, the
activities planned include such subjects
as studies on the influence of
advertising, the education of the
general public as regards the media,
the effects of industrialization on
communication and the protection of
journalists. (This last subject is to be
examined in co-operation with
professional organizations of
journalists.)
Among other major activities figure an
inter-governmental conference on
communication policies to be
convened for the Arab States, the
training of specialists and the
development and application of
methodologies for communication
policies.
Ill
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Thirteen-year-old Odina E. Batnag, winner of a world-wide song-writing contest organized
by Unesco, at a press conference in New York.
Filipino girl wins Unesco world-wide
song-writing contest
ODINA E. Batnag, a thirteen year
old high school student in
Manila, Philippines, has been awarded
the first prize in an international song-
writing contest sponsored by Unesco,
in collaboration with the Radio
Corporation of America (RCA), for
children under 14 years of age.
Almost a million children from fifty-
seven countries participated in the
competition and an international jury
of poets, musicians and writers
selected the best twenty from entries
submitted by national organizers of
the contest, the theme of which was
"Children Helping Children".
The final selection of Odina's lyrics,
entitled "I am but a small voice", was
made by Roger Whittaker, the
internationally-known singer, who was
one of the originators of the contest.
Mr. Whittaker recorded the song, for
which he wrote the music, and RCA
Records is releasing it as a commercial
single record and will donate the
proceeds from its sale to Unesco's
Education for Handicapped Children
Programme. RCA is presenting
Unesco with specially packaged copies
of the recording for sale throughout
the world. Whittaker is donating all
royalties from the song, which will be
included in his new album, to the
Unesco programme.
International
coin collection
to finance
cultural projects
UNESCO and the International
Fund for the Promotion of
Culture have decided to launch a
world campaign for the minting of
collectors' coins illustrating the theme
"Arts and Crafts". All profits from
the sale of these coins will be used by
the Fund to finance cultural
development projects in Unesco's
Member States, first of all in those
countries which have authorized the
minting of the coins.
The Greek government has just
communicated to Unesco Director-
General Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow its
decision to authorize the minting of a
series of three coins, one gold and two
silver. Thus Greece becomes the first
State to take part in this initiative.
The International Fund for the
Promotion of Culture was created by
the General Conference of Unesco to
aid in the promotion of cultural
values, and to assist artistic creation
and international and regional cultural
co-operation. It is governed by an
Administrative Council headed by Mr.
Felipe Herrera, former president of
the Inter-American Development
Bank.
The Fund, which began its operational
activities in April 1977, has approved
to date a total of $1,506,000 to aid 92
cultural development projects in 46
countries.
Apartheid doomed to disappear says Unesco Director-General
í 6 'T'HE system of apartheid
A represents the last relic
of a period in which systematic and
institutionalized racialism was rife",
declared Unesco Director-General
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, in a message
to the chairman of the U.N. Special
Committee Against Apartheid, on the
occasion of the Day of Solidarity with
the Political Prisoners of South Africa
which was celebrated on October 11.
"The epitome of all the flaws of that
period, it seems all the more
anachronistic and intolerable today. In
the face of world opinion which has
outlawed it and popular movements
which daily erode it, this system is
doomed to disappear, as the racialist
regime in Rhodesia has just
disappeared".
"But", the Director-General
remarked, "if the people of Zimbabwe
yesterday won their struggle for
liberation, and if the people of South
Africa are now beginning to take
responsibility for their own struggle, it
is because in both these countries
women, men and even children rose
up to put an end once and for all to
racialist oppression and to recover in
all its fullness their right to dignity,
freedom and justice, and because these
women, men and children were ready
to make the supreme sacrifice of their
lives."
IV
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
52 million child workers
>we5 down under the weight of newly-fired bricks, in a tragic
. parody^o^ the .game of "follow-my-leader", these young Latin-
Ámerfcáns are among the 52 million children under the age of 15
«tuteugftout the world who are obliged to work for their living. A
* recent study by the International Labour Organisation reveals the
plrgh.t of thisvás't army of youngsters who are being cheated of
their childhood. (See flrtTble).
]]>
</page>
</document>
