<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="046076eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco COMier A window
open on the world
-..J
uS| [JT fj -^. B>-
H
* -
Kl '
L '
v
/
1 ' '
f' V k&täa
J! >**Jf¡Sf IT
BS rT iil
-
áát^' ^* *
:
Li ^ 1 ér i
- . --
r.:..»i It Vi //*J 1
:
\
0&
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
^
Bulgaria
Photo © Archaeological Museum of Sofia, Bulgaria
Animal art of ancient Thrace
A lion crouches on its prey, a stag, in this detail from a silver plaque wrought by a Thracian
craftsman in the late 4th century B.C. The Thracian metalsmiths of Antiquity produced outstanding
miniature hunting scenes as well as depictions of ritual events and animal combat, conveying a
sense of flowing movement and drama through a masterly use of stylization. Today in the
Archaeological Museum of Sofia, this plaque (8.7 cm long) is one of many Thracian treasures
unearthed in Bulgaria.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco COUlíer
AUGUST-SEPTEMBER 1978 31st YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 19 LANGUAGES
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Malaysian
Korean
Japanese Portuguese
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific -
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 35 French Francs
2 years: 58 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 24 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in
August and September when it is bi-monthly (11 Issues a
year). For list of distributors see inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R.
Microcard Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th
Street, New York, U.S.A.; (3) Bell and Howell Co., Old
Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in the Readers'
Guide to Periodical Literature, published by H.W. Wilson
Co., New York, and in Current Contents - Education,
Philadelphia, U.S.A.
Editorial Office
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris - France
Editor-in-chief
René Caloz
Assistant Editor-in-chief
Olga Rodel
Managing Editor : Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
Edition: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
Edition:
Edition: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Edition: Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Edition: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Edition: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Edition: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Edition: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Edition: H.L. Sharma (Delhi)
Edition: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Edition: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Edition: Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
Edition: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese Edition: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish Edition: Mefra Arkin (Istambul)
Urdu Edition: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan Edition: Cristian Rahola (Barcelona)
Malaysian Edition: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean Edition: Lim Moon-young (Seoul)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
page
4 THE FLOWERING OF SLAV CULTURE
by Dmitri Markov
9 THE MAKING OF THE SLAV COMMUNITY
by Vladimir D. Korolyuk
13 MAGIC, MARRIAGE AND MERRY-MAKING
by Aleksandr A. Gura, Olga A. Ternovskaya and Nikita I. Tolstoy
18 HIDDEN SPLENDOURS OF RUSSIAN ART
Photo story
22 TH E SLAVS AN D BYZANTI U M
by Dimitr Angelov and Gennady Litavrin
26 AN ARAB TRAVELLER TO AN ANTIQUE LAND
28 TEA AND SYMPATHY
An intricate network of trade and cultural links with the Orient
by Olzhas O. Suleimenov
32 KIEV
The Mother of Russian Cities
by Yuri Asseyev
41 THE ART OF THE MORAVA SCHOOL
Sensitivity and grace in fifteenth-century Serbia
by Svetozar Radojcic
43 DUBROVNIK
Gateway to the Latin West
by Vuk Vuco
46 WORKMANSHIP IN WOOD
Photo story
54 THE COMMON HERITAGE
A cultural community stretching from the Baltic to the Black Sea
by Slavomir Vollman
59 DIALOGUE WITH THE WEST
A fruitful interplay of ideas and talent
by Igor F. Belza
64 From Copernicus to Korolev : ,
A 500-YEAR JOURNEY INTO SPACE
by Bogdan Suchodolsky
68 ARTS AND CRAFTS OF BYELORUSSIA
by Evgenl M. Sakhuta
70 A PHOENIX RISING FROM THE ASHES
Slav literature in the aftermath of war
by Aleksandar Flaker
73 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
74 IN BRIEF
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
BULGARIA : Animal art of ancient Thrace
Photo © Aurora Publishers, Leningrad
Cover
This double issue of the Unesco Courier is
entirely devoted to the history of the cultures
of the Slav world, whose study forms a major
part of Unesco's programme in the field of
culture. Cover shows a detail from a
fifteenth-century Russian icon of the Nativity
(Pskov School). Following the star with
outstretched, pointing hands, the Three Kings
serve as an introduction to our issue and also
herald other triumphs of Slav art.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
The flowering
of
Slav culture
Famed for the fanciful carvings of
warriors, fantastic beasts and masks
that cover its walls, the tiny cathedral
of St. George is the pride of the town
of Yuryev Polsky, 200 kilometres north¬
east of Moscow. Construction of the
cathedral, which was completed in
1234, is said to have been personally
supervised by Prince Svyatoslav
Vsevolodovich. Right, pointed mask
over the north portal is thought to be
the likeness of the Prince.
by Dmitri Markov
ALONG with the Latin and the Ger¬
manic peoples, the Slavs form one
of the major ethnic groups of Eu¬
rope. Slavonic languages echo from the
austere shores of the White Sea to the sun¬
bathed Adriatic coast, over the vast expan¬
ses that stretch from the Baltic to the Ural
mountains (Europe's frontier with Asia),
and further still, in Siberia and the Far East.
Jordanes, the sixth-century historian of
the Goths, tells us of the Antae (a group of
Eastern Slavs), who sacrificed oxen to their
Thunder God, Perun, who believed in
rusalki, or stream nymphs, and who wor¬
shipped rivers and woodlands.
Byzantine historians are unanimous in
recording the valour, integrity, hospitality
and, above all, the love of freedom of the
Slav tribes, to whom, in contrast with the
rest of Europe at the time, the institution of
slavery was virtually unknown.
This was a time when a page of history
was turning, when the Middle Ages were
replacing Antiquity and when the ancient
slave-owning societies were giving way to
new, feudal States. The Slavs played their
part in this process which affected the
whole of Europe. The kingdom of Great
Moravia, Kievan Russia and the Republic of
Dubrovnik, to name only three of the Slav
States, wielded considerable political
influence among their neighbours, not only
because of their economic and military
strength (in 911 A.D. Prince Oleg of Kiev
celebrated his victories by nailing his shield
to the gates of Constantinople), but also
because of their highly developed, diversi¬
fied and original culture.
The name of Great Moravia calls to mind
the unique achievement of two brothers
from Thessalonica, Cyril and Methodius.
The twenty-year adventure of the two
DMITRI MARKOV is a member of the
U.S.S.R. Academy of Sciences and director of
its Institute of Slav and Balkan Studies in Mos¬
cow. He is president of the Unesco-sponsored
International Association for the Study and Dis¬
semination of Slav Cultures.
"Apostles of the Slavs" began in 863 A.D.,
when the Moravian prince Rostislav sent to
Constantinople for missionaries who could
instruct his people in the Christian faith, in
their own Slavonic tongue. An ancient
"Lives of the Saints" tells us that when he
was taking leave of the Byzantine Emperor,
Cyril declared: "Teaching without an
alphabet and without books is like writing
upon water", and before they set off on
their hazardous journey he and his brother
Methodius devised a Slavonic alphabet,
thus laying the foundations of Slavonic
literature.
The cultural and educational activities of
Cyril and Methodius had far-reaching
effects in Moravia, Pannonia and the other
West Slav countries. And although their
great undertaking met with implacable
opposition on the part of the Catholic
Church, which cruelly persecuted the mis¬
sionaries, their disciples quickly took up the
struggle in neighbouring Bulgaria. Access
to writing was an epoch-making event for
all the Slav peoples, and consequently for
the history of the culture of the world.
The age of Kievan Russia (whose heyday
was at the turn of the eleventh and twelfth
centuries) saw unprecedented advances in
city-building, craftsmanship and com¬
merce, intense international political acti¬
vity, and a corresponding flowering of the
arts. Our appreciation of mankind's cultural
accomplishments is in no way complete if
we neglect the inimitable creations of the
Kievan age in architecture, literature, paint¬
ing and the applied arts, which have given
such profound aesthetic delight to succes¬
sive generations of Slavs and non-Slavs
alike.
The perfect moulding and the succinct
yet picturesque language of the Slovo o
Polku Igoreve, a contemporary epic poem,
place it on the same artistic and spiritual
level as the Nibelungenlied and the Chan¬
son de Roland. This "Lay of Igor's Cam¬
paign" carries in its lines the whispering
sound of the feather-grass of the steppe
across which, in the year 1185, Prince Igor
of Novgorod-Seversky rode out against the
Polovtsians; its language echoes the clash
of swords and the gasps and groans of
horsemen locked in mortal conflict. Indeed,
the Slovo constitutes an invaluable and elo¬
quent account of distant days, and of the
feelings and thoughts of the people of
medieval Russia.
Mention of Dubrovnik calls up memories
of its outstanding role in the development
of European humanism. Over a period of
several centuries, despite constant warfare
and the re-shaping of frontiers, the city-
republic conserved its independence. It
rivalled mighty Venice in terms of both
commerce and culture, to such an extent
that a special item was placed on the
agenda of the Venetian Senate: "Every
Fridaya discussion on ways and means
of crushing Dubrovnikl" (See article page
43).
Dubrovnik was a centre of study for
famous mathematicians and poets, histo¬
rians and philosophers. Between the fif-_
teenth and seventeenth centuries, the
combined labour and talents of architects
and engineers, of anonymous stone¬
cutters and masons, produced an ensem¬
ble of rare harmony which, in its magnifi¬
cent and lavish natural setting, made it
seem to be an eighth Wonder of the World
and a fitting destination, as Bernard Shaw
suggested, for those who are looking for
heaven on earth.
The fortress of Dubrovnik and its
princely palace are visible symbols of the
independence of Dalmatian humanism,
which evolved in keeping with the historical
development of the country of the South
Slavs, in intimate contact with the wealth
of their national culture and in
accordance with their original life-style.
The Slav peoples contributed in a variety
of ways to the intellectual and spiritual life
of medieval Europe, and provided much of
the ideological background to the Euro¬
pean anti-feudal and anti-clerical move¬
ments which resulted in numerous popular i
uprisings. Thus, for example, the Bulgarian I
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
y sect of the Bogomils laid the foundations
of the dualistic teachings adopted by the
Cathars, the Albigenses and the Templars.
It is worth mentioning here that in French
dialects of the Middle Ages, the word
bogre (Bulgar) was synonymous with
"heretic".
Protest was inherent, too, in the ser¬
mons preached by the religious reformer,
Jan Hus, who was burnt at the stake in
141 5 on the orders of the reactionary Coun¬
cil of Constance. From his martyr's pyre
blazed up the purifying flame of the Refor¬
mation which spread throughout Europe.
The great Martin Luther humbly called him¬
self a Hussite, while the teachings of the
Bohemian preacher became a foundation-
stone of the revolutionary ideology of burg¬
hers and peasants alike.
During the Middle Ages, the Slav peo¬
ples were to taste the gall of foreign
oppression. Poland and Russia, for exam¬
ple, found themselves under constant pres¬
sure from their east European neighbours,
and this obviously affected their own cul¬
tural development. Nevertheless, when
medieval European culture was refreshed
The
Kremlin
down
the
ages
and renewed by the irresistible tide of the
Renaissance, the Slavs were able, to the
extent that their historical circumstances
permitted, to play an active role in the great
spiritual movement of humanism.
In the space of a few generations, the
great figures of the Renaissance elaborated
a new vision of the world and a new con¬
ception of man himself. Their ideas were
reflected in the artistic masterpieces and
forward-looking scientific achievements of
the age. And among the great Renaissance
men were numbered many Slavs.
Pride of place must be acorded to Nikolaj
Kopernik, the Polish astronomer Coperni¬
cus (1473-1543), who overturned the image
of the world that the Church had sanctified
for more than fifteen hundred years (see
Unesco Courier, April 1973). His revolu¬
tionary theory that the planets, in¬
cluding the earth, revolve around the sun,
enabled the Italian philosopher Giordano
Bruno (1548-1600) to extend the frontiers
of the universe still further, and postulate
the existence of countless solar systems
similar to our own.
There is considerable evidence of the
importance which Copernicus's contempo¬
raries attached to his work. As a young
man, Jan Amos Komensky, better known
to us as Comenius, while visiting Heidel¬
berg in 1614, came across a copy of Coper¬
nicus's treatise De Revolutionibus Coeles-
tium Orbium; without hesitation, he emp¬
tied his pockets to pay for the manu¬
script, and was consequently obliged to
make the long journey home to Moravia on
foot.
Komensky himself (1592-1670) was an-
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
other Slav scholar who made a unique con¬
tribution to the culture of the new age. He
devised a complete educational system,
and was one of the first to understand that
the transformation of society and its
advance along the path of historical pro¬
gress depended in great measure on the all-
round development of man.
Komensky stood at the watershed of
two great European cultural epochs, the
Renaissance and the Enlightenment. It was
the latter movement which, in its confirma¬
tion of the unlimited power of human rea¬
son, finally dethroned the scholasticism of
the Church as the ultimate authority as far
as the perception and explanation of the
world was concerned. Built on the founda- 1
tions of outstanding scientific achieve-'
Photo © APN, Pans
The Kremlin, or citadel, formed the defensive core of the great medieval cities of
Russia. Pskov, Novgorod, Smolensk and Rostov were all built round Kremlins, which
generally contained cathedrals, the palaces of princes and bishops, government offices
and an arsenal. The Moscow Kremlin, the most imposing of all, was originally a wooden
fortress erected in 1156, but it was enlarged and rebuilt many times. Photos (1) View of
Moscow in the 16th century from a book by the German traveller Adam Olearius. (2) The
first known plan of Moscow, published in 1556 in a book by the Austrian ambassador
Sigismund Gerberstein. (3) The Palace Square in the heart of the Moscow Kremlin in the
17th century. (4) 16th century engraving of the stonemasons of Moscow. The inscription
reads: "That summer [1367] the Grand Duke Dmitri built Moscow in stone, and from
that time Moscow was built only in stone." (5) The Kremlin in the 18th century, as seen
from the River Moskva. Copper engraving by the Russian artist Michael Makhaev.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
> ments, the Enlightenment threw open the
doors to the further development of the
natural and human sciences.
The brightest star in the brilliant firma¬
ment of eighteenth-century Slav science
was undoubtedly Mikhail Lomonosov
(1711-1765), the great Russian scholar and
encyclopaedist, and a truly "universal
man". An urbane, yet poetic figure, Lomo¬
nosov combined the talents of physicist
and chemist, geologist and geographer,
historian and philologist. He was a versatile
and accomplished naturalist, and rightly
shared with the distinguished French
chemist Lavoisier the honour of discover¬
ing the law of conservation of matter
and energy.
The age of Enlightenment saw an affir¬
mation of the need to place scientific
knowledge at the disposal of the public as a
whole, and to create a non-clerical, secular
system of education, and it was not long
before this principle was put into practice.
The "Educational Commission" estab¬
lished in Poland in 1773 was the first
independent European "Ministry of Educa¬
tion".
The period between the mid-eighteenth
and mid-nineteenth centuries, rightly
known as "the age of national regenera¬
tion", was rich in consequence for the
development of Slav culture. In all spheres
of social life, the cultural element expanded
at an unprecedented rate. Literature, art
and science reflected a nation's greatness,
and served as its "visiting-card" as far as
other peoples and States were concerned.
The sudden flowering of Slav culture
was conditioned by (and inseparable from)
the national liberation movements of the
Slav peoples or, as in the case of Russia, by
the development of progressive social and
political ideas. Thus, the Russian poet of
freedom, Alexander Pushkin, echoed the
¡deals of the "Decembrist" revolutionaries
(1); the struggle of the Czechs for their
own National Theatre, which was conduc¬
ted under the slogan "By the people for the
people", was both a consequence and a
reflection of the upsurge of the national
movement; the Bulgarian writers Hristo
Botev and Ljuben Karavelov participated
directly in the armed struggle for the inde¬
pendence of their country.
Culture was a driving force in the politi¬
cal education of peoples, and in making
them aware of their identity as nations. In
March 1794, for example, the Poles reacted
to the first performance of Cracovians and
Mountaineers, a musical comedy by Woy-
zecfc Boguslavsky, the "father of the Polish
theatre", in much the same way as the
French Revolutionaries had reacted to
Beaumarchais' Le Manage de Figaro.
Each new decade of the nineteenth cen¬
tury saw an increased contribution by the
Slavs to the culture of Europe and of the
world. This was particularly evident in lit¬
erature, especially with the works of the
great Russian authors, Tolstoy, Dos-
toevsky and Turgenev, whose impact was
worldwide, while Poland was brilliantly
represented by Mickiewicz and Slovatsky,
and the Ukraine by Taras Shevchenko. At
the same time, outstanding Slav compo¬
sers like Glinka, Chopin, Tchaikovsky and
Smetana set new standards of excellence
in the music not only of their own coun¬
tries, but also of the world.
The theatre of the Slav countries under-
(1) The 'Decembrist rising' in Russia, so-called because
it occurred on 18 December 1825, was an ill-fated
palace revolution against the Tsarist autocracy.
went remarkable development, as may be
seen from a single example that of the
Moscow Arts Theatre, founded in 1898 by
the great actor-producers Konstantin Sta¬
nislavsky and Vladimir Nemirovich-
Danchenko.
In the twentieth century, the Great Oct¬
ober Socialist Revolution in Russia set in
motion a revolutionary process whose
impact on the development of modern cul¬
ture has been felt far beyond the borders of
the Slav countries. The vitality of the ideas
which provoked this development was put
to a severe test during the struggle of Slav
and non-Slav peoples alike against Fas¬
cism, a death-dealing movement which
also resulted in the mindless and pitiless
destruction of cultural monuments thou¬
sands of years old.
Today, Unesco's programme of cultural
studies is making cultural exchange even
more meaningful. A major component of
this programme is the study on Slav cul¬
tures, which reflects the increasing world¬
wide interest in the centuries-old cultures
of the Slavs, and in the economic and cul¬
tural achievements of the modern Slav
States.
Unesco has enlisted scholars and intel¬
lectuals and representatives of the mass
media and of educational institutions in
Europe, America and Asia in the implemen¬
tation of this project, a natural outcome of
which has been awareness of the need for
an international pooling and co-ordination
of efforts in the complex study of Slav cul¬
tures, and in the dissemination of know¬
ledge about the Slav peoples, the way they
live today and the contribution they have
made, and are making, to the civilization of
the world.
Dmitri Markov
The Slav cultural tradition, still very much alive today, now incorporates revolutionary
motifs. Known as "October Song", this porcelain dish is one of a series of decorative
objects produced by Maria Lebedeva in 1919-1920. The words of the "Internationale" are
reproduced on the inner rim.
8
Photo © Aurora Publishers. Leninarad
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Gold ornamental plaque
from a horse's trappings, found in a
Sarmatlan tomb in the Caucasus
region. It was probably made for a
Sarmatian noble by Greek craftsmen
who have deliberately adopted a
"barbarian" style. The two central figures are
representations of Dionysius and Athena.
Photo © Progress Publishers, Moscow
The making
of the Slav community
by Vladimir D. Korolyuk
VLADIMIR D. KOROLYUK, Sower historian,
is head of the department of ancient and medi¬
eval history at the Institute of Slav and Balkan
Studies attached to the U.S.S.R. Academy of
Sciences. He is the author of many studies on
the creation of the Slav states, the origins of the
peoples of Eastern Europe and the relations be¬
tween Eastern and Central European countries
between the 16th and 18th centuries. He con¬
tributed to the Unesco booklet The Slavs and
the East, published in 1965.
HISTORY portrays nomad peoples
such as the Sarmatians, the Huns
and the Avars as the main driving
force behind the great migrations of bar¬
barian peoples which crushed the Roman
Empire, leaving the ruins and ashes from
which feudal Europe was later to emerge.
Early written sources abound in graphic
descriptions of the nomads in action: stor¬
ming the ramparts of the Roman Empire,
besieging cities, subjugating the peoples of
the Roman provinces or putting them to
flight. Most of these accounts relate to
south-east Europe where nomad hordes
wrought havoc on Roman territory, turning
it into pastureland and enslaving part of the
local population.
Yet the Slav tribes, for the most part
farmers and herdsmen, played a role of
major importance in these great migra¬
tions, for the economic system of the
nomads could not survive without agricul¬
ture. When the Avars settled down in the
sixth century they turned to agriculture,:
and the toil of Slav farmers (as well as the
blood shed by Slav horsemen recruited into
the mounted hordes) was a decisive factor
in the emergence of the terrible and ruth¬
less force known as the Avar Khaganate.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
But such States of nomadic origin were
short-lived. In 622-623, Samo led the Slavs
in a large-scale rebellion against their Avar
masters, and two centuries later, in 803,
the Emperor Charlemagne destroyed the
Khaganate and the Avars ceased to exist as
a political force.
It was, therefore, pre-eminently as farm¬
ers and urbanized craftsmen and traders
that the Slavs first reached the level of eco¬
nomic development attained by the other
European peoples. In eastern Europe,
where they had long been established, and
in central and south-east Europe where
they settled after the great invasions, Slav
tribes took the road to feudalism. Distinc¬
tive Slav nations and governments began
to appear.
As for the nomadic tribes, some "per- ,
¡shed like the Avars" (to quote an ancient
Russian proverb), while others, such as the
Proto-Bulgars, a Turkic people which had
emerged from Asia with the invading
hordes, found their destinies linked with
that of the Slavs. The Proto-Bulgars inter¬
mingled with the sedentary Slav farmers,
while the Hungarian people also absorbed
an element of the Slav farming population,
adopted their practices, and entered Euro¬
pean history as a farming people.
The earliest written sources to give a
general idea of the areas occupied by the
Slavs in the vast expanses of eastern and
central Europe date from the first centuries
A.D. From then untiï the age of the great
migrations there is a virtually uninterrupted
flow of information, the most interesting of
which is found in the works of two sixth-
century historians: the Goth Jordanes and
the Byzantine writer Procopius of
Caesarea.
According to the historians of Antiquity,
central and eastern Europe were divided
into two geographical regions, Germania
and Sarmatia. Some ancient authors, fol¬
lowed by later Byzantine writers, held
that the Slavs were from Sarmatia (or
Scythia), but this was contested by their
better-informed contemporaries.
The Roman historian Tacitus, writing in
the 1st century A.D., made a sharp distinc¬
tion (based partly on economic criteria)
between the Slavs and the inhabitants of
Sarmatia. The Venedi, he wrote (using one
of the early names given to the Slavs) were
rather "to be classed as Germans, for they
build houses, carry shields and travel on
foot at great speed, in all these respects dif¬
fering from the Sarmatians, who spend
their lives in waggons or on horseback".
These differences of opinion are
seemingly due to the fact that the Slavs
occupied a region straddling Germania and
Sarmatia, where western and eastern cul¬
tural influences intermingled. The strong
resemblances between the Slavonic and
Baltic languages suggest that the Slavs
shared this area of forest and forest-
steppe, which stretched southwards
through eastern Europe as far as the nor¬
thern foothills of the Carpathians, with the
Baits (the ancestors of the modern Latvians
and Lithuanians).
The historians of the sixth century locat¬
ed the land of the Slavs with even greater
precision and maintained that it covered a
vast area stretching from the Baltic to the
Carpathians, eastwards to the Dnieper, and
even as far as the lower reaches of the Don
and the Sea of Azov.
Twenty years ago, the discovery of
traces of agricultural activity as well as ob¬
jects dating from between the seventh and
fifth centuries B.C. suggested that the
early Slav settlements were also centres of
craftsmanship. Since then, discoveries by
Ukrainian and Polish archaeologists have
provided a virtually continuous picture of
the development of the material culture of
the Slavs from the dawn of the first millen¬
nium A.D. up to the tenth and eleventh
centuries. The fact that the artefacts pro¬
duced in this vast territory over such a long
period bear a strong mutual affinity, over¬
riding local variations, points to the exis¬
tence of a Slav ethnic community.
Written testimony exists concerning the
unity of the Slavs, but refers to them by
different names. The most detailed
accounts date from the sixth century and
speak of two main groups, the Antae and
the Sclavini, which are described as mili¬
tary and political federations of Slavs
governed by an elite class and under the
overall leadership of a warrior chieftain or
prince.
The Antae, despite certain features
which distinguished them from the Sclavini
(notably their types of pottery and the
nature of their fortified settlements in the
sixth century) were undoubtedly kinsmen
of the latter in all other respects, and
shared the same life-style, appearance and
language.
The irruption of the Goths, the Huns and
the Avars into the territory of the Slavs
broke up their unity. But the invaders failed
to shatter a way of life based on a common
language and customs, economic activities
and marriage ties, and this ensured the sur¬
vival of the Slav community.
Early historians also show that the Slavs
were united by á common mythology. Pro¬
copius tells us, for example, that "both
these barbarian tribes [the Antae and the
Sclavini] lead identical lives and have the
same laws. They recognize one god, the
author of lightning, the only master of the
universe, and they bring him sacrifices of
cattle and perform other devotions in his
honour."
The literary sources do not contain,
unfortunately, sufficient material for a
reconstruction of Slav mythology in all its
details. But a description of the reforms
introduced by Vladimir, Grand Prince. of
Kiev in the tenth century, contains a list of
the old Slav gods. The supreme deity was
Perun, god of thunder and lightning, who
brought life-giving rain to the crops; he had
affinities with another deity, Stribog. Chors
and Dazhd-Bog (bog means "god" in the
Slavonic languages) were the gods of day¬
break and the sun. Volos (or Veles) was the
patron of flocks and herds, livestock-
raising and pastoral activities. Mokosh was
the goddess of fertility, weaving and spin¬
ning. Latin chronicles and archaeological
finds dating from the eleventh and twelfth
centuries indicate the existence of a similar
patheon of pagan gods on the western Bal-
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
tic coastline and among the group of Slavs
known as the Ljutici.
Traces of many ancient beliefs survive in
Slav folklore: vily and beregini, who haun¬
ted, woodlands and hills and above all rivers
and lakes and other watery places; Yarilo, a
god of fertility associated with springtime;
Kupala, apparently related to the sun; and
a host of household and family gods reflec¬
ting the patriarchal organization of the
Slavs.
Conversion to Christianity broke up this
mythological world, although a number of
pagan cults and rituals were incorporated
in the new religious practices, and the
medieval ideology of the Christian Slavs
still contained echoes of the beliefs of their
heathen ancestors.
Common beliefs, a common material cul¬
ture, linguistic continuity and a tradition of
intermarriage all point to the persistence of
a Slav community.
Pagan Pantheon
The Slavs decorated their pagan temples with beautifully carved images
of their many gods and goddesses. These were generally carved in
wood and as a result few of them remain, but some of the rare stone
idols still exist. Left, a typical four-sided, sacred stele (or Svietovit),
dating from the 10th century, which was found in the silt of the bed of
the river Zbruc, in the Ukraine. It is thought to represent "Mother
Earth", the protectress and symbol of fertility. Above, a stone statue
known as the "Idol of Shklov".
The map called Peuthger's Tabula (one
of the oldest maps of Europe) offers the
only indication that the Slavs (the Venedi)
moved south-westwards in the third
century.
Later, between the fifth and the seventh
centuries, they moved in a great wave into
central and south-east Europe, and settled
in the Balkans, the Dinaric, the Karawan¬
ken and Julian Alps, in the Danube basin,
and in the land east of the Elbe. Confronta¬
tion with the Slavs resulted in the transfor¬
mation of the slave-owning Eastern Roman
Empire into the medieval feudal State of
Byzantium.
But' let us now return to the Antae and
the Sclavini. Jordanes and Procopius tell
us that these two peoples played an equally
important role in the Slav migration into
the Danube basin and the Balkans. These
two federations of tribes, closely related by
language and customs, undoubtedly pos¬
sessed a highly developed sense of ethnic
identity. But when, during the concluding
stages of the great migration, the Slavs
settled in south-east Europe, the Greek
name Slaveni (which the Latins translitera¬
ted as Slavi) was extended to include the
whole of the Slav world, while the name
Antae disappeared.
This sudden upsurge of Slav conscious¬
ness, which occurred at the turn of the
sixth and seventh centuries and was reflec¬
ted in the adoption of a single name, was
largely due to the fact that the Slavs, after
centuries of confrontation with the Ger¬
mans, the Finns and all the nomadic tribes
that had come storming out of Asia, now
found themselves face-to-face with the
Eastern Roman Empire, and in doing so
became more keenly aware of their own
identity.
The consolidation of the Slav community
was followed by a complex process in
which the Slavs separated into three bran¬
ches, eastern, southern and western, each
of which evolved according to dif¬
ferent historical, geographical and econo¬
mic circumstances, absorbing in the pro¬
cess the indigenous population of the terri¬
tories it had occupied. At the same time,
Slav nation-states began to be created.
The Slavs were firmly set on the road to
feudalism.
There can be no doubt that the Slavs
who occupied the former Roman provinces
of south-east Europe and the lands which
bordered on Byzantium evolved more
rapidly than their kinsmen who had remain¬
ed closer to the original homeland. It was
here that they created the first central and i
south-east European States, Great Moravia I
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Detail showing the blind arcading and the faience tiles that embellish the tambour supporting the
single cupola of the late 15th century church of St. George-on-the-hill, at Pskov.
> and the first Bulgarian Kingdom. It was not
until the tenth and early eleventh centuries
that the rest of the Slav world
reached the same level of development.
The greatest medieval Slav State was
Kievan Russia which, like all the early feu¬
dal States, owed all its trappings of royalty
and aristocracy, and its secular and eccle¬
siastical "Establishment", to the back-
breaking labour of the peasantry.
The former forest regions were cleared
and put under the plough, and by the thir¬
teenth century, arable farming may be said
to have predominated everywhere. But
horticulture continued to be important: the
Slavs cultivated beans and peas, lentils,
poppy-seeds and turnips, as well as carrots
and gherkins, while in the words of an old
Russian folk-song"apple and pear-trees
flowered" in their orchards in the spring¬
time. The country people supplemented
their diets by bee-keeping and
fishing, by gathering wild berries, roots
and mushrooms.
The development of arable farming with
the use of draught animals implies that
livestock-raising was also an important
activity. The Slavs indeed bred oxen and
horses to pull their ploughs, as well as large
numbers of cows and pigs. Goats and
sheep were also reared, notably in the pas-
turelands of the Carpathians and the
Balkans.
But it was not "all work and no play" for
the Slav peasants, and their daily life was
enlivened by three cycles of festive
occasions one involving rituals and cere¬
monies related to cultivation, another con¬
nected with the raising of animals, and the
third with the mysteries of marriage and
fertility.
The development of Slav cities as cen¬
tres of craftsmanship and trade dates from
the eighth and ninth centuries, but subjec¬
tion to Byzantium a century later tempora¬
rily slowed down the expansion of South
Slav towns. Urbanization in ihe countries
of the East and West Slavs continued
throughout the tenth and especially the ele¬
venth centuries; their cities were fortified
with ramparts, moats and towers, special
attention being paid to the security of their
gateways.
These fortress-cities were built by the
Slavs themselves,' who became metal¬
workers, blacksmiths, locksmiths, armour¬
ers, potters, glass-makers, stonemasons,
cobblers and shoemakers. The craft of
wood-working was practised by turners,
coopers and wheelwrights. The Slavs also
proved to be accomplished jewellers, while
Russian craftsmanship, especially in the
form of steel blades and chain mail, ena¬
melled golden ware and objects carved out
of bone, was highly valued in the markets
of East and West alike.
The fortunes of all medieval cities de¬
pended essentially on the creation of local
markets capable of absorbing the produc¬
tion of their craftsmen. The foundation
and expansion of the Slav cities in partic¬
ular reflected the acceleration of a trend
which had begun at a considerably earlier
datenamely the separation of crafts¬
manship from agriculture. Cities with large
permanent populations of craftsmen and
traders, and with a transient population of
foreign merchants, rapidly became flouri¬
shing commercial and diplomatic centres.
In the streets of Prague and Wolyn, Kiev
and Novgorod, ambassadors and mission¬
aries rubbed shoulders with merchants
who had come to sell cloth and precious
stones, silverware, jewellery and exotic
spices, or to exchange them for slaves or
prisoners-of-war, furs or locally-produced
goods.
Busy trade routes ran from the Caspian
Sea along the Volga to Novgorod and the
Baltic, "from the Vikings to the Greeks",
and from Kiev to Cracow, Prague to
Regensburg. Arabic, Greek, German, Nor¬
dic as well as Slavonic languages were all
to be heard in the markets, princely pal¬
aces and aristocratic mansions of Kiev,
Novgorod and Smolensk. The picture was
much the same in the cities of the South
Slavs, while in Dalmatia, where the popula¬
tion combined Slav and Latin elements,
merchants from Italy were much in evi¬
dence.
A cultural tradition took root in the great
Slav cities where its basis existed already in
the form of sagas and songs recounting the
exploits of kings and princes, and where
story-tellers entertained the nobility with
byliny, or epic poems. It was in these cen¬
tres that architecture and painting develo¬
ped, and especially literature which,
throughout the early medieval Slav world,
lost no time in putting to use the alphabet
invented in the ninth century by Cyril and
Methodius for the transcription of the Sla-,
vonic language. The texts inscribed on
birch-bark discovered by Soviet archaeolo¬
gists (see page 25), which contain simple
accounts of everyday affairs, offer outstan¬
ding evidence of the cultural level attained
by the society of early Russia,
largely as a result of this leap forward in
Slavonic letters.
Vladimir D. Korolyuk
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Magic,
marriage
IM
merry-making
by
Aleksandr A. Gura,
Olga A. Ternovskaya,
and Nikita A. Tolstoy
iV~
"A
^
33 V
^
s
^1
A
FROM time immemorial, the life of the
Slavs has been bound up with agri¬
culture, and for this reason, ancient
rites and rituals connected with the seasons
of the farming year figure prominently in
their culture.
One such ceremony, commonly celebra¬
ted. until quite recently, was the dozhinka,
or harvest festival. This took varying forms
among the different Slav peoples, and may
thus serve as an indicator of their separate
yet similar development from a common
origin.
The rites which accompanied the end of
harvesting comprised a sequence of events,
carefully structured in space and time and
based on different combinations of three
distinct ceremonies, each centred on a spe¬
cific object. These objects, of which there
were a great number of variants, were
fashioned by the reapers out of ears of L
corn, straw, branches, flowers, thread and f
ribbon.
©
ALEKSANDR A. GURA, OLGA A. TER¬
NOVSKAYA and NIKITA I. TOLSTOY are
members of a research team attached to the
Institute of Slav and Balkan Studies of the
U.S.S.R. Academy of Sciences. Directed by
Nikita Tolstoy, they are carrying out ethno¬
graphic and linguistic research into ancient Slav
cultures including marriage customs and
other popular traditions.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
One of these objects, the dozhinochny
venok, or harvest garland, was a head-dress
woven from flowers, branches, ribbon and
other materials. The end of harvesting was
considered as a sort of marriage, and the
preparation of the garland was accompa¬
nied by rites reminiscent of the wedding
ceremony. The garland was worn by the
best and prettiest of the women reapers
who took the role of the bride in these
rituals whose magic, incantatory nature is
reflected in an old Byelorussian harvesting
song, with the refrain "The more you kiss
the mistress. Master, the more corn will
there be..."
Moreover, the other dramatis personae of
this rjtual adopted the names of the princi¬
pal participants at a wedding, so that the
terminology of the latter permeated the
harvest ceremony.
The ritual weaving of the garland was
common in the Ukraine, southern Byelorus¬
sia, Slovakia and Poland, but rare among
the Bulgarians and quite unknown in
Russia.
Another ceremonial object was the last
sheaf, or a, symbolic representation in the
form of a man of straw. This sheaf differed
from the harvest garland in that it was not
an adjunct of a leading human participant in
the ritual, but actually presided over the
events. For this reason, it was often given
anthropomorphic names such as baba
(granny), ded (grandpa), kumushka (the
merry wife) and nevesta (the bride). In
north-east Russia this sheaf was even con¬
sidered as the master (khozjain) of the
household ; and in Russia as a whole this
word is one of those most commonly used
to denote the guardian spirit of the family
home.
The ritual involved in the preparation of
the sheaf was widespread among the West
Slavs and the western group of the South
Slavs ; it existed also in northern and wes¬
tern Russia and was found in north-east
Byelorussia.
The most important ritual accompanying
the end of harvest-time among the Slavs
had as its focal point a patch of the crop
which was left uncut. The standing ears,
which the East and South Slavs called the
boroda (beard) were fashioned in a specific
manner plaited together, for example,
partly broken or knotted in some wayand
then served as the decor for various rites.
The womenfolk turned somersaults; the
young men wriggled under the bent stalks;
a girl danced in front of them; they were
sprinkled with vodka or water; little piles of
flax or stones, or of bread and salt were
placed beside them, and so on. After these
Seasonal
rites
Harvest-time in Poland,
left, was celebrated with
traditional ritual. Wearing
an elaborate crown of
wheat and escorted by
the village musicians and
the other villagers, the
prettiest of the village
maidens led the
procession to the village
church. After the priest
had blessed the crown,
the procession moved on
to the village hall. There
the mayor placed a cock
on top of the crown and
it began to peck at the
ears of corn. If the cock
crowed, this was taken as
a good omen signifying a
plentiful harvest. Finally,
the procession wound its
way to the house of the
local squire who
distributed gifts to those
considered to have
worked hardest during
the harvesting. The day
ended in feasting and
dancing. Right, in
Moravia, Czechoslovakia,
the arrival of spring is
marked by the making of
a "smartka", a figure
representing the death of
winter. In Bulgaria,
bottom left, this figure is
replaced by a villager
wearing an elaborate
mask.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
rites, the South Slavs cut or pulled up the
boroda; the East Slavs left it standing in the
field.
Traditional Slav weddings were compli¬
cated affairs, in which ritual and mythologi¬
cal play-acting were interwoven with the
recital of poems and with singing, music
and dancing. The relatives, friends and
acquaintances of the bride and groom all
participated in these activities; everyone
had a role to play, and was simultaneously
an actor and a spectator. The list of
wedding-guests often included professio¬
nal match-makers Isvaty), lamenters who
could be relied upon to produce a few tears
at the right moment, a master of ceremo¬
nies, sorcerers and soothsayers to protect
the newly-weds from witchcraft, and a jes¬
ter to amuse the assembly with his jokes
and witticisms.
The first stage in the process of getting
married involved the arrival of the match¬
makers at the bride's house, where they
engaged in a conversation full of symbols
and ambiguities with her parents. They
were travelling merchants, they said, or
hunters of martens and foxes; they were
looking for a lost heifer; were there any
stray ducks or geese in the vicinity; or did
the family have a young ewe-lamb or a little
wheat for sale? On rare occasions, when
the married couple was to set up home in
the bride's, rather than the bridegroom's
household, the match-makers addressed
themselves to the bridegroom's family;
sometimes the bride went to offer "her
hand in marriage. All these ceremonial
negotiations ended with an official
betrothal; the engaged couple began to
prepare for the wedding and drew up the
list of guests.
Once betrothed, the status of the fiancée
changed; no longer a spinster, she was not
yet a married woman; her former social and
family ties and relationships had been
loosened, but new ones had not yet taken
their place. In popular belief, she was ex¬
posed during this transitional period to the
dangerous influence of witchcraft and the
evil eye, and for this reason she was ex¬
cused from all her normal domestic duties.
Sometimes, for fear of harm, she did not
even leave the house.
In the Russian north, this was the period
when the professional weepers entered the
scene, some of them rubbing their eyes
with onions for increased effect. Ritual
weeping and wailing continued until the
end of the wedding ceremony.
The state of betrothal was also reflected
in details of the clothing, head-dresses and
hair styles of the nevesta the future bride.
The eve of the wedding was a special
occasion among all the Slav peoples. In
Russia, this was the moment when the
bride took leave of all her girlhood friends.
Ritual bathing was practised by the Rus¬
sians and the South Slavs, while in Russia
and sometimes in Byelorussia, Poland and
Bulgaria, the bride ceremonially let down
her hair. The East and West Slavs decorated
a "wedding sapling"; in the western
Ukraine, Poland, Czechoslovakia and Ser¬
bia, the girls plaited garlands; the South
Slavs and Slovaks prepared a wedding ban¬
ner. In Russia (particularly the south), Bye¬
lorussia, the Ukraine and Bulgaria, the eve
of the great day was the time for baking the
wedding bread.
The baking of this svadebny khleb was a
well-established tradition among the Slavs.
The bread, decorated in a variety of diffe¬
rent ways, was offered to the wedding-
guests with many ritual gestures and
songs, in which it was compared to the sun
and the moon. The bride and groom bowed
low before the round loaf and kissed it;
their parents blessed them with it and it
was used in the "bread and salt" ceremony
which greeted them after they were pro¬
nounced man and wife, as a symbol of Slav"
hospitality; and the newly-weds were bom¬
barded with handfuls of grain, to wish them
happiness and wealth.
The procession from the bride's house to
the wedding, and to the bridegroom's
house after the ceremony, was considered
to be a dangerous moment. The East Slavs
frightened each other, for example, with
tales of whole wedding parties being trans¬
formed by witchcraft into wolves. For this
reason, the guests took particular care to |
protect themselves from sorcery. |
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
One
hundred
kisses
"Luboks", or humorous
engravings of scenes from daily
life, became very popular in
Russia towards the end of the
18th century. Left, a village
wedding feast is in full swing.
The figure in the centre, a
relative of the bride, calls on the
bride and groom to "sweeten
the vodka", whereupon the
newlyweds are obliged to kiss
each other one hundred times,
while the guests in chorus count
each kiss. The children perched
on the bunk over the stove
seem more interested in stuffing
themselves with handfuls of
nuts. Right, from
Czechoslovakia, an elaborate
wedding cake representing
Adam and Eve before the tree of
knowledge.
y The wedding festivities included an
important act: the changing of the bride's
hair-style and head-dress to match her new
status as a married woman.
The newly-weds were seen off by the
guests, usually from the groom's house, to
the bridal bedchamber. Oddly enough, the
wedding night was generally spent in
unheated quarters in a store-room, a barn,
or even a cow-shed I
The next day was devoted to fun and
games. Tricks were played on the young
couple; the match-makers were "pun¬
ished"; men dressed up as women and vice
versa; the party wandered through the vil¬
lage disguised as mummers or gypsies, and
so on. Sometimes, as in the Byelorussian
region of Polesie, for example, the guests
re-enacted a parody of the previous day's
ceremony, with actors playing the parts of
bride and groom.
The last act of the wedding included a
ritual visit by the newly-weds to the village
bath-house, a symbolic "testing" of the
bride, and visits by the in-laws to each
others' homes.
To this day, the arrival of summer is cele¬
brated in Byelorussian Polesie on 7 July,
which corresponds in the new calendar to
the old Slavonic festival of Midsummer Day
and the Feast of St. John the Baptist. Des¬
pite centuries of religious persecution, the
occasion remains full of colourful relics '
from pagan times.
On the eve of Ivan Kupala, as the occa¬
sion is called, huge bonfires of brushwood,
straw, etc. collected by the boys and girts
are lit at twilight on the river banks or on
the little hills of this wooded and marshy
region. The fires are usually grouped in
threes, and are sometime topped by straw
"guys" which are either consumed in the
flames, or thrown into the river to "drown".
The fires burn until midnight or until
dawn. When the flames have died down,
the merry-makers jump over the embers.
beat the ground with fire-brands and gen¬
erally amuse themselves. Just before first
light, they gather piles of grass, and tell
each other the legend of the mysterious
flower of the fern which brings good
fortune to anyone who chances to see it.
What looks like just plain mischief by the
country boys and girls (they block up the
chimneys of cottages so that smoke from
the stoves cannot escape, take gates from
their hinges and throw them on to other
people's vegetable patches, or pull buckets
and chains out of the wells and drag them
noisily through the village) is, in fact, the
survival of ancient rites which, like jumping
over the fire or beating the ground with bur¬
ning sticks, were connected with exorcism,
purification, fertility and so on. Now, how¬
ever, they are merely the signs of uninhibit¬
ed gaiety, in which the whole population
stays up all night to join in the fun.
On Midsummer Eve in Poland, along the
lower reaches of the Bug river, the unmar¬
ried girls push little wooden cups with
lighted candles and posies of flowers out
across the water. A girl whose cup sinks
will be married during the year; but if the
cup floats on, she will remain a spinster. In
the Ukraine and in Byelorussia, the girls
also throw garlands of flowers into the
water and tell their fortunes with them.
On Midsummer Eve in Slovakia, the girls
dig holes in the ground with their bare heels
and fill them with sugar or bread. At dawn,
they come back to see what has happened:
if the sugar and bread are still there, they
are destined to remain old maids; if they
have disappeared, a death in the family may
be expected. A girl who finds ants in the
hole she has dug will marry a good lad; but
if it contains a starling, she will have to con¬
tent herself with a widower.
According to ancient superstition, wit¬
ches were abroad on Midsummer Night,
and the Slovaks and the people of Polesie
took pains to protect themselves from all
manner of sorcery. To sting the witches
(who among other devilments were liable
to steal milk from their cows) and drive
them away, they put nettles on their
window-sills and strewed them across their
thresholds.
The Slovaks set great store by the magi¬
cal properties of grass gathered on Mid¬
summer Night, a time when, so they be¬
lieved, every blade of grass was silently cry¬
ing out "Cut me! Cut me!" Among the
Cribs and nativity plays are important |
features of the Christmas festivities. Over j
the years, in Poland, a traditional
spectacle known as "The Herods" has
developed around the nativity story and in
particular the journey of the Three Wise
Men. This spectacle, in which the
principal characters are Herod, Death and
the Devil, is now a colourful feature of
carnivals as well as of the Christmas and
New Year festivities.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Serbs, the holiday was known as Sveti
Jovan Bil'ober (St. John the Grass-cutter).
Similarly, the Bulgarians, on the day they
called En'ov den (John's Day), gathered
grass, and protected their cattle and fields
from the evil spirits which threatened their
milk and harvest, while the young girls told
fortunes to find out who their future hus¬
bands would be. This was the day on
which, according to the Bulgarians, En'o
"threw a sheepskin coat over his shoulders,
since snow was on the way..."
The Croats and the Slovenes also greet
Midsummer Day with bonfires, thus joining
in the celebration which links the Slavs
with the other peoples of Europe. In medi¬
eval France, the king himself applied the
torch to "le feu de la Saint-Jean", and Mid¬
summer Night bonfires flickered over Den¬
mark, Italy, Scotland and England as well,
although they were banned in London in
1539.
Where these ancient rituals are still prac¬
tised, the participants are almost always
unaware of their initial magical signifi¬
cance. But as they make merry in the sun¬
light or in the glow of a blazing fire, as they
welcome the flowers and the harvest, and
the rippling fields of summer grass, they are
looking hopefully towards the future. Simi¬
larly, the distant forbears of the Slavs rejoi¬
ced in all these things, feeling that they
were a part of Nature's forces, as children
of the forests, the water and the sun.
Olga Ternovskaya,
Aleksandr Gura
and Nikita Tolstoy
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Colour page
Contrasted images of serenity and suffering in Slav religious art. Left, the
Saviour, an icon painted between the 11th and 13th centuries. It was
repainted several times and this is the first published photo of the icon
since it was restored in 1967-77 by M. Barutsin at the Andrey Rublyov
Museum, Moscow. Right, detail of a figure from the majestic high altar in
the Church of St. Mary, Cracow. Carved in limewood and painted, the altar
was executed by the great sculptor Wit Stwosz between 1477 and 1489.
Hidden splendours
of early Russian art
Many masterworks by early Russian painters were disfigured by later
artists seeking to "improve" or restore the original. Some were even
repainted entirely to suit changing tastes and fashions. Many of these
hidden treasures of Russian art have now been restored to their full glory
thanks to highly skilled and dedicated work by Soviet specialists.
Removing the layers of often crude overpainting as well as age-old
encrustations of grime requires immense patience and skill and, although
modern scientific methods are extensively used, the success or failure of
the operation still hinges on the talent and intuition of the restorer.
Restoration work in recent years has highlighted the importance of
regional schools of painting in such localities as Novgorod, Pskov,
Vladimir and Tver, and also shown how foreign influences were
assimilated to create a form of iconography that was distinctively
Russian. Photos 1, 2 and 3 show three stages in the restoration of a 16th-
century ¡con of the Apostle Paul. Restored between 1970 and 1973 by
I. Gromova, it is now in the Museum of Yaroslavl-Rostov.
iu A
® 1
f
f w
I1
Photos S. Zimnokh © Figurative Art Publishers, Moscow
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The astonishing metamorphosis
of a 13th-century icon, entitled
The Assembly of the Archangel Michael,
which was concealed beneath a mediocre
composition by a later artist.
The restoration work was carried out
by Soviet specialist A. Baranova and took
six years (1962-1969).
A great artist-monk
Andrey Rublyov (1370-1430) was one of the great masters of icon-
painting of the Moscow school. His ¡cons, in particular his Trinity
and his Saviour, rank among the masterpieces of world art. The
Saviour (below right) was discovered in a storeroom of the
Cathedral of the Dormition at Zvenigorod, near Moscow. Though
damaged and incomplete, it exudes the new spirit that Rublyov
introduced into Russian painting. The sensitive and profoundly
expressive image of the risen Christ, with its combination of
dignity, gentleness and compassion, contrasts strongly with the
stern severity that characterized the earlier Byzantine conception.
The icon is now preserved in the Tretyakov Gallery, Moscow.
Below left, 16th-century miniature portraying Rublyov at work on
a fresco at the Church of the Saviour at the St. Andronikov
monastery, Moscow.
Colour page
St. Boris and St. Gleb
Now in the Tretyakov Gallery, Moscow, this 14th-century
icon depicts two celebrated figures from early Russian
history. Boris and Gleb, two younger sons of Vladimir,
ruler of Kiev from 980 to 1015, were victims of fierce family
quarrels for the succession, being put to death by their
elder brother Prince Svyatopolk. Their cult was
widespread from the 11th to the 13th century and many
churches were dedicated to them. The icon is bordered
with scenes from their brief lives.
Photo © APN, Pans
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
The Slavs
and Byzantium
by Dimitr Angelov and Gennady Litavrin
STANDING astride Europe and Asia
and spanning a period of time
stretching from classical antiquity
to the Renaissance, the Byzantine Empire
linked different worlds and different ages.
This gave a special dimension to the cul¬
tural interactions of Byzantine civilizat¬
ion with those of neighbouring countries
and peoples interactions which were
vast both in range and scale.
Heir to antiquity and the culture of the
Hellenes and until the twelfth century the
leading power in Europe and the Near East,
the Byzantine Empire was the nucleus of a
vast area in which the Orthodox Church,
the eastern variant of Christianity, was,
throughout the medieval period, the domi¬
nant form of expression of spiritual life.
The frontiers of Eastern Christendom
were largely established by the early years
of the eleventh century. By this time they
encompassed huge tracts of south-eastern
and eastern Europe. In the Near East, in
north Africa and in the western Mediterra¬
nean region, however, Byzantium had lost
considerable ground, as a result of con¬
frontation with the Muslim world (first with
the Arabs and then with the Turks) and
with the Latin West and the Papacy.
Misunderstandings between Rome and
Constantinople came to a head with the
Schism of 1054, and the rupture became
final with the struggles and disputes arising
from the crusades. In the lost lands, the
once dominant Byzantine culture disappea¬
red with the passage of time and the
implantation of other civilizations.
In the northern regions of Eastern Chris¬
tendom matters evolved differently. Here,
the population, for the most part Slav, had
progressively been drawn into the orbit of
Byzantium throughout a thousand years of
stable and lasting cultural relations. Only
the West Slavs (including the Poles, the
Czechs, the Slovaks, the Baltic and Pola-
DIMITR ANGELOV is a distinguished Bulga¬
rian historian who has been professor of Byzan¬
tine history at the university of Sofia since 1949.
A corresponding member of the Bulgarian Aca¬
demy of Sciences, he is the author of many
works on Byzantine and Bulgarian history.
GENNADY LITAVRIN is a leading Soviet spe¬
cialist on Byzantine history and Russo-Byzantine
relations. He Is one of the authors of a basic
three-volume work "The History of Byzantium"
and assistant editor of the Soviet magazine
Byzantisky Vremennik (The Byzantine Period).
bian Slavs), the Croats and the Slovenes,
remained outside the pale of Eastern Chris¬
tendom, as the result of political events
during the ninth and tenth centuries,
coming instead within the sphere of
influence of Western Christian civilization.
Relations between the Slavs and Byzan¬
tium were complex. The initiative in es¬
tablishing contacts was generally taken by
the Slavs, and early links were strengthen¬
ed with the formation of the Slav States.
The first historically recorded contacts
date from the end of the fifth century A.D.
during the closing stages of the Great
Migration, which had seen the establish¬
ment of Slav peoples over vast areas of
eastern, central and south-eastern Europe.
In the seventh century, they arrived in the
north of the Balkan peninsula, and settled
in large numbers in Moesia, Macedonia,
lllyria and northern Thrace. Groups of
Slavs also moved into Thessaly, northern
Greece, the Péloponnèse and the Aegean
islands.
The aim of Byzantium, as it faced up to
its new neighbours, was not to dislodge
them, but to secure control over them, to
transform them into Christians and to
absorb them as vassals of the Empire.
These contacts and the occupation of
lands which had been intensively cultivated
for ages past and which contained centres
of sophisticated urban life had a catalytic
effect on the social development of the
Slavs. In a great many cases, they did not
oust the original inhabitants but merged
peaceably with them.
The arrival of the Slavs in the Balkans
was- also a matter of great importance for
the Byzantine Empire. They filled the
vacuum left by the devastating campaigns
of the Goths, Huns, proto-Bulgars, Avars
and earlier Slav tribes.
The Slavs who settled in the former
Roman province of Moesia found them¬
selves in a particularly favourable situation,
with all-round natural protection afforded
by the Danube, the Black Sea and the Bal¬
kan Mountains. It was here, during the last
quarter of the seventh century, that the
Slav settlers joined forces with and accep¬
ted the temporary leadership of a relatively
small but militarily well-organized group of
new arrivals, the proto-Bulgar horde of
Khan Asperuch, and created the first Slav
State on Byzantine soil Bulgaria.
Byzantium maintained close and lasting
contacts (at times peaceful and at times
hostile) with this new State and, towards
the middle of the ninth century when inde¬
pendent States were founded in the wes¬
tern and north-western parts of the Balkan
peninsula, the Empire entered into regular
political relations with the Serbs and the
Croats; similar relations with the Russians
began after the year 860.
Among the instruments of Byzantine
politics and diplomacy, conversion to
Christianity was a powerful and well-tried
tool. According to time, place and circum¬
stance, it was used as a first step towards
expansion of the Empire, as a method of
securing friendly neutrality, of
strengthening political influence or of
acquiring allies and vassals. Among those
Balkan Slavs who had not yet organized
themselves into States, for example, con¬
versions to Christianity served the Empire's
purposes of subjection and assimilation.
Missionaries either preceded, or followed
in the footsteps of the Byzantine armies.
The civil servants and ecclesiastics of
Byzantium had acquired great experience
in proselytizing and subduing alien neigh¬
bours. Unlike the Latin West, they allowed
newly converted peoples to worship in
their. own language, particularly when the
political possibilities of absorbing them ap¬
peared unrealistic.
In 863 A.D., just two years before Bulga¬
ria followed the same path, the kingdom of
Great Moravia became the first Slav State
to accept the Christianity of Byzantium as
its official religion. The same period saw
the invention by Constantine (better
known by his monastic name of Cyril) and
Methodius of a Slavonic alphabet. The two
brothers also translated into Slavonic all
the canonical and liturgical literature that
was required for the normal functioning of
the Church. They became the leaders of a
devoted group of Slav disciples and pupils
and their work launched a revolutionary
process in the cultural development of Bul¬
garia, Serbia and ancient Russia.
During the last third of the ninth century,
and the century that followed, Slavonic let¬
ters made triumphant progress in all the
Slav countries and became accessible to.
virtually every segment of society. The
principal role in spreading literacy among
the Slavs, and in disseminating the so-
called "Old Slavonic" literature belonged
to the kingdom of Bulgaria.
Although none of the independent
States which surrounded Byzantium, in¬
cluding those created by the Slavs, and
which accepted Christianity from Constan-
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
. v" iMñfltii
.
F5^
fa i
! B
,
I i
H w'-'^'ï
p.,;:J|
Hl* ** «1 ^"^* f>
f- ?S^
V" » *
iy
1
3 £ v
1
É
*
-, *
1
The murals of the church of Boyana, at the
foot of Mount Vitosha to the south of Sofia,
Bulgaria, are ranked among the masterpieces
of 13th century painting. Dating from 1259, the
Boyana frescoes herald the introduction of the
new realism that marked the "Palaeologian
style" of the late 13th and early 14th century.
Above, St. Ephraim by the unknown master
painter of Boyana.
tinople, was actually coerced into doing so,
Byzantium adopted a somewhat firmer
stand during the Christianization of Bulga¬
ria than it had during the conversion of
Great Moravia.
When, in 865 A.D., Bulgaria adopted the
Christian faith, the Byzantines, for political
reasons, deliberately refrained from pro¬
viding the new Church either with clerics
of Slav background or with church books
in the Slavonic language, and services had
to be conducted in Greek.
In 893, however, things changed.
Shortly after the accession to the Bulgarian
throne of Tsar Symeon (893-927), who was
to become the country's greatest medieval
ruler, Greek, which had remained the offi¬
cial State language, was proscribed. Wor¬
ship in the Slavonic language was introd¬
uced in the churches, and the Greek
clergy were expelled. Under the inspiring
influence of the seminaries created at Och-
rida and Preslav by Clement and Naum,
two disciples of Cyril and Methodius, the
number of educated people sharply increa¬
sed, and the foundations were laid of an
original and, for the period, highly sophisti¬
cated spiritual culture which made itself felt
in the neighbouring Slav countries, and in
Serbia and Russia in. particular.
This was the Golden Age of Bulgarian
literature, reflected in the works of talented
writers like John the Exarch, Chernorizets
"the Courageous", Bishop Constantine
and others, whose work was actively
encouraged by Tsar Symeon himself. The
close similarity between the written lan¬
guage and the popular speech of Bulgaria
was of no small significance in the develop¬
ment of national education, while the same
period also saw a flowering of architecture,
painting, mosaics, ceramics, glassware and
other applied arts.
The second great leap forward in the cul¬
tural development of Bulgaria occurred at
the turn of the twelfth and thirteenth cen¬
turies. During this period, the Bulgarian
Zograph monastery, founded on Mount
Athos in the twelfth century, played an
important role in strengthening cultural
contacts with Byzantium, Serbia and
Russia.
Outstanding developments in Serbian
culture, and in literature in particular, date
from the twelfth century onwards. Serbia's
first Golden Age was linked with the
coming to power of the Nemanja dynasty,
and in particular with the reign of Stephen
Nemanja ("the first-crowned") and the
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
activities of his brother. Saint Sava, who
' founded an important cultural centre, the
Serbian monastery of Hilendar on Mount
Athos, and was also Serbia's first Arch¬
bishop.
Relations between Byzantium and Rus¬
sia began to develop at a somewhat later
date. Early Russia, or Rus', as it was called,
was situated so far from the frontiers of the
Empire that there was no danger of direct
Byzantine aggression.
Through an alliance with the Pechenegs,
Byzantine diplomacy aimed to contain the
military forays of the Russians and to deny
them access to Byzantium's markets. The
attempt failed, and even before they were
united in a single State, the Russians had
established trading relations with Kherson
and Byzantium's Crimean colonies. Press¬
ing on still farther, the Russian merchant
adventurers, part-traders and part-soldiers,
reached the Byzantine commercial centres
on the southern shores of the Black Sea,
and in 860 A.D. their ships dropped anchor
beneath the walls of Constantinople itself.
Whilst gradually yielding ground to Rus¬
sia in the economic and political spheres,
Byzantium exercised on the young State an
increasingly far-reaching cultural influence.
During the decade which followed the ar¬
rival of the Russians off Constantinople, a
number of their leaders were converted to
Christianity. At the beginning of the tenth
century, a Christian church dedicated to
St. N'ya (Elias) existed in Kiev. In the
middle of the same century, Olga, the
widow of Prince Igor, who had become the
Russian ruler, was baptized during a visit to
Constantinople; and in 989, Prince Vladimir
accepted Christianity as the religion of his
country.
Bulgarian experience and the already rich
stock of Bulgarian literature were of con¬
siderable service in the enlightenment of
Russia. Immediately after his conversion,
Vladimir turned to Slavonic letters as the
basis for the organization of ecclesiastical
affairs and State business. It is probable
that the first officials to be entrusted with
this task were trained with the assistance of
"experts" from the South Slav Orthodox
States.
Less than half a century after conver¬
sion, Kievan Russia entered a period of cul¬
tural development that was to reach its
zenith in the twelfth century. That literacy
was widely disseminated is amply borne
out by the hundreds of birch-bark docu¬
ments discovered by Soviet archaeologists
since the 1950s, containing the accounts
kept by quite ordinary people of their every¬
day affairs. This period saw the construc¬
tion of magnificent palaces and churches.
Painting and the applied arts flourished,
and the splendours of eleventh-century
Kiev, including its Cathedral of St. Sophia
and the Golden Gate, made the city a
worthy rival of Constantinople itself.
The influence of Byzantine models was
particularly apparent in religious and mor¬
alistic didactic literature, architecture in
stone and mosaic work, stained glass,
icons, monumental painting and book illu¬
mination. In all these fields, however, the
Slavs began, a century and a half or so
after conversion to Christianity, to develop
their own artistic schools, language and
idiom, which reached back into their pre-
Christian traditions and pagan art and cul¬
ture. The result was a creative re-modelling
of Byzantine examples, and their adapta¬
tion to local tastes and requirements.
Byzantine influence was less marked as
far as secular literature was concerned.
This was especially true in the case of chro¬
nicles, poucheniya (written "admonitions"
or testaments generally left by rulers for
their successors) and accounts of journeys,
and of music and singing, the applied arts,
ornamentation, festive rituals, clothing and
interior decoration.
When it escaped from the constraints of
"official" religious ideology, spiritual life
was clearly influenced by local traditions
going back to farthest antiquity. And even
today, without knowledge of the living tra¬
ditions of the pagan culture of the Slavs it
is impossible to begin to understand Ser¬
bian heroic songs, the popular festivities of
the Bulgarians or the epic poems (byliny) of
ancient Russia.
Cultural interchange between Byzantium
and Slavdom was conditioned in great
measure by the selective approach which
the latter adopted as far as the Byzantine
legacy was concerned. Indeed, selectivity
on both sides reflected the single-minded
policies of the rulers of each: Byzantium
refrained from transmitting matters which
it considered dangerous for neophytes (the
latest acute theological controversies, for
example), while the rulers of the newly-
converted countries rejected importations
which seemed alien and potentially harmful
(such as the employment of eunuchs as
State officials, or organized horse racing
tournaments).
N even more important
reason for selectivity in
the adoption of Byzan¬
tine civilization was the incompatibility of
many of its aspects with the Slav environ¬
ment. The various collections of Byzantine
legal texts which circulated widely through¬
out south-east Europe during the thir¬
teenth and fourteenth centuries under¬
went, in their Slavonic versions, substan¬
tial amendment in the form of abbreviation,
addition and modification. Byzantine tem¬
poral law had virtually no impact in Russia,
whose legislation took the native form of
Russkaya Pravda, a collection of laws
whose origins could be traced back to
pagan times.
In the Latin West, the period from the
ninth to the twelfth century saw the forma¬
tion of original cultures in all the major
States, despite the levelling influence exer¬
cised by a single ideological and ecclesiasti¬
cal centre (the Papacy) and a single lan¬
guage (Latin) which, although incompre¬
hensible to the bulk of their populations,
dominated religious life, affairs of State,
science and culture.
In the Slav countries of Eastern Christen¬
dom, however, original cultures ripened
more rapidly for a number of reasons: their
Churches were less dependent on Cons¬
tantinople than their Western counterparts
were on Rome, and the language of litera¬
ture and of the church was not Greek, but
their own Slavonic language which was
comprehensible to the peoples of Bul¬
garia, Serbia and Russia alike.
Half a century to a century after their
conversion to Christianity, these countries
all had their own identifiable culture.
When, after a century and a half (1018 to
1185) Byzantium managed to acquire undi¬
vided control over the Balkans, to liquidate
the kingdom of Bulgaria and to annex the
Serbian principalities, the cultures of these
countries were sufficiently well-established
to resist not only assimilation but also any
substantial degree of transformation. The
historical memory of their early indepen¬
dence, the persistence of their own literacy
and literature, their own customs and life¬
styles, and their ethnic self-awareness
served as banners in the armed struggle
to reconquer their freedom, which they re¬
gained during the last quarter of the
twelfth century.
The sharpest confrontations in Eastern
Christendom occurred where Byzantium
was particularly stubborn in its attempts to
convert the cultural commonwealth it had
created into a hierarchical system of politi¬
cal and administrative units under overall
Byzantine direction.
Thus, from as early as the tenth and ele¬
venth centuries, the pronounced historical,
ethnic and cultural individuality of the Slavs
within the Orthodox sphere of influence
precluded their assimilation with Byzan¬
tium, though, paradoxically, the develop¬
ment of this individuality was accelerated
by the acceptance of Christianity from
Byzantium.
It is not surprising, therefore, that a deep
mutual sympathy grew up between the
South and East Slavs and the Greek people
that was to last for many centuries. Nor is it
surprising that when, with the fall of
Byzantium and the South Slav countries,
Russia remained the last bastion of Euro¬
pean Orthodox Christianity, the peoples
conquered by the Ottoman Turks should
look to Russia for deliverance. And finally,
it is not to be wondered at that their hopes
were finally to be fulfilled.
Dimitr Angelov
and Gennady Litavrin
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The making of an alphabet
The Cyrillic alphabet was invented in the 9th century by the
scholar-missionary brothers St. Cyril and St. Methodius so
that they could instruct the people of Moravia in the
Christian faith in their own Slavonic tongue. Use of the 43-
letter alphabet spread quickly throughout the West Slav
lands, finally reaching Russia in the 10th century. Over the
years the alphabet was gradually modified and during the
reign of Peter the Great a simpler version was elaborated
which today is used not only by the Slav nations but also by
many non-Slavs including the Aleuts and Eskimos. The
spread of literacy that the new alphabet made possible was
rapid and widespread. A number of letters and documents
written by ordinary citizens on birch-bark scrolls, found at
Novgorod in 1951, indicate that the new literacy was not
confined to an elite class. Photos : (1) A 14th-century
manuscript shows St. Cyril and St. Methodius, "the apostles
of the Slavs", transcribing the Scriptures and liturgical texts
into the Slavonic language. (2) Detail of a fresco on the
façade of a 13th-14th century church at the village of
Berenda, in Bulgaria, depicting St. Cyril the Philosopher.
Photo © The Bulgarian Artist, Publishers, Sofia
(3) An 18th-century wood sculpture of St. Clement of
Ochrida, a disciple and companion of Cyril and Methodius.
(4) This remarkable document shows two letters written on
birch-bark some 750 years ago by a seven-year-old boy from
Novgorod called Onphime. At top, the alphabet followed by
drawings of Onphime and his friends. Below, self-portrait of
Onphime astride a charger with an enemy dead at his feet.
HTiïfïo^p'oTA/ xZOS1 ¿TIT* p- A
-
Photo <£) Unesco Courier, Russian Edition Photo © Literature for Children, Publishers, Moscow
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
An Arab traveller
to an Antique land
The longest river in Europe, the Volga
rises in the Valdai Hills, north-west of
Moscow, and discharges its waters
into the Caspian Sea 3,690 km to the
south. Known in ancient times as the
Ra and during the Middle Ages as the
Itil, the Volga has always been of
immense importance as a cultural
and commercial highway. Today, the
Volga and its navigable tributaries
carry some two-thirds of all Soviet
inland freight. Opposite page, the
Volga at sunset. Right, carved
wooden prow of an 18th century
Volga rivercraft.
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Ibn-Fadlan was a member of the embassy sent by the
Arab Caliph Al-Muktadir to the rulers of the Bulgare of
the Kama and Volga rivers in 921 A.D. He visited Itil, the
capital of the Khazars, and travelled to the capital of the
Bulgare, Great Bolgar, which stood near the junction of
the Kama and the Volga. It was in Itil or in Great Bolgar
(ruins of which have survived to the present day) that he
came into contact with the Slavs. We present here an
extract from "Ibn-Fadlan's Journey to the Volga", an
account of his travels edited by I.Y. Krachkovsky and
published in Moscow- Leningrad in 1939.
I saw the Russians, when they came with their goods and est¬
ablished themselves on the banks of the river Itil (1). Never
have I seen men of more perfect stature; they are like palm
trees. They are red-haired, and wear neither jackets nor kaftans,
but the menfolk wear cloaks, throwing one side over the shoulder
so that an arm emerges from beneath. Each of them has a sword, a
knife and a pole-axe, and from these they are inseparable. Their
swords are broad and curved like waves; the blades are of Frankish
make. From head to toe they are painted with marks depicting
leafy trees, pictures and designs of all sorts. Each of their women
has pinned to her breast a little box made of iron or copper, or sil¬
ver or gold, according to the status and wealth of her husband.
Each little box has a ring, to which a knife is attached.
Around their necks they wear chains of gold and silver, for when
the husband has ten thousand dirhams, he gives his wife a chain;
when he has twenty thousand dirhams he gives her two chains; in
similar fashion, he gives her another chain for each ten thousand
dirhams, so that she often has many chains around her neck. Their
most beautiful ornaments are the green beads made out of clay,
which are sometimes to be seen on their ships; they try to get hold
of these beads at all costs, pay a dirham each for them and thread
them into necklaces for their women...
They come from their country and drop anchor in the Itil, which
is a mighty river, and set up large wooden houses on its banks; and
they gather together, ten or twenty, more or less in each house.
(1) The River Volga
Each of them has his own bench, on which he sits... to do his
bargaining...
When their ships come to the anchorage, everyone comes
ashore with bread, meat, milk, onions and some kind of fiery bev¬
erage. He goes up to a tall pillar which bears a face on it, resem¬
bling a human face; and around it there are smaller images set in a
circle; and behind these images there are tall pillars stuck into the
ground. He goes up to the biggest image, prostrates himself in
front of it, and says: "0 Lord! I have travelled a great distance...
and with me I have so many head of cattle, so many sable furs, so
many skins..." and so on, until he has enumerated all the goods
that he has brought for trade. Then he says: "And this gift, I have
brought for you", and places what he has brought before the pil¬
lar, saying: "I beg you to send me a buyer who has dinars and
dirhams, and who will buy from me all that I wish to sell him, and
who will not contradict me in what I say to him." And then he goes
away. And if the selling is difficult and lasts a long time, he comes
back again with a gift, and yet again. And if his wishes still remain
unfulfilled, then he brings a gift to one of the smaller images, and
seeks its intercession, saying: "This is for the wife of our God, and
his daughters", and from each of the ¡mages without exception he
solicits intercession... Often the selling is easy for him, and when
he sells his goods, he says: "My god has answered my prayer, and
I must thank him for that." So he takes a certain number of cattle
and sheep and slaughters them, and distributes part of the meat
among the poor ; the rest he takes and throws down before the
big image and the little ¡mages surrounding it, and hangs the heads
of the cattle and sheep on the pillars stuck into the ground. And
after nightfall, the dogs come and eat the meat, and he who made
the offering says, "My god has deigned to eat my offering".
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Tea
and
sympathy
An intricate network
of trade and cultural
links with the Orient
by Olzhas O. Suleimenov
Right, 17th-century drawing of a
Mongolian horseman. Slav
travellers brought back many
novelties from the Orient
including tea, the abacus and
ginseng. Photo from The Slavs and the East © Unesco
THE earliest contacts between the
Slavs and the peoples of the East are
shrouded in a mystery which we can
only attempt to pierce by fitting together a
jigsaw of fragmentary evidence: scattered
allusions by Latin writers, the testimony of
folklore, and linguistic and archaeological
data.
It is not until the sixth century A.D. that
the picture becomes clearer. From that
time and later, writings have survived
which, disjointed and incomplete though
they are, shed much light on the age when
the Slavs began to be known in Byzantium
and when, through the Greeks, the word
Slav began to be heard in the Orient.
Later chroniclers recorded the traditions
OLZHAS O. SULEIMENOV is a leading poet of
Soviet Kazakhstan who writes in both the Rus-'
sian and Kazakh languages. The author of ten
volumes of poetry and a number of studies on
Turkic and Slavic cultures, he is one ofa team of
Unesco consultants engaged in the preparation
of a History of Civilizations in Central Asia.
of this early period, along with information
culled from pre-lslamic annals. By the
eighth and ninth centuries Arab authors
were calling the Don "the river of the
Slavs" and the Black Sea "the Russian
Sea".
Some Arab geographers of the early
Middle Ages gave the word Slav so broad a
meaning that they applied it to peoples of
Germanic origin. This was no simple "mis¬
take" on their part; the confusion arose
because the Slavs and the eastern mer¬
chants followed such a vast and intricate
network of trade-routes and because the
Slavs played such a prominent role in the
relations between East and West.
Trade between the countries of the Arab
Caliphate and those of eastern Europe and
the Baltic seaboard began to expand in the
eighth century. Right from the start much
of this commerce flowed along the Volga
on the boats of eastern merchants who
plied northwards through the rich trading
centres of Itil (near present-day Astrakhan)
and Bolgar, which lay south of the con-
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Photo from Illustrated History ol the U.S.S.R. © APN, Moscow
A distant ancestor of the
rouble, this silver "grivna" or
ten-kopeck piece was used in
9th-century Kiev as both an
ornamental weight and a coin.
Photo © APN, Moscow
Overlooking Red Square,
Moscow, the 16th-century
Cathedral of St. Basil the
Blessed strikingly illustrates
how Eastern styles were
incorporated into Russian
architecture. Built under Tsar
Ivan the Terrible to
commemorate the conquest of
Kazan and Astrakhan, the
cathedral is actually a complex
of nine churches, the central
one being topped by a
traditional Russian "tent-
shaped" roof.
fluence of the Volga and the River Kama.
These merchants were attracted by the
legendary riches of the northern lands, and
chiefly by their furs: silver fox, sable, mar¬
ten, ermine, beaver and the pelts of other
animals. Such treasures were highly prized
in Baghdad, Bokhara, Khorezm and Cairo.
Poets sang their praises, and kings, emirs
and potentates strove to outdo each other
with magnificent gifts from the distant
northlands. They also imported wax, honey
and slaves from eastern Europe.
In return, the Slav countries received the
handiwork of eastern craftsmen, in particu¬
lar silver coins. Throughout the vast area in
which the East and West Slavs were set¬
tled, hoards of silver coins of the eighth to
the tenth centuries are still often dis¬
covered, evidence of intense commercial
activity. Torgovye gosti ("trading guests")
from Slav lands were familiar figures in
various towns of the Caliphate. Their boats
sailed down the Volga and the Don to the
Caspian and the Black Seas, and from
there they transported their wares by camel
to Baghdad.
The growth of trade between the Cali¬
phate and the Slav countries whetted the
appetite of Arab scholars for information
about their northern neighbours. Arab geo¬
graphers and historians writing between
the eighth and the tenth centuries discuss
the origin of the Slavs, their relations with
other peoples, their churches and their reli¬
gion, the life and customs of the different
tribes, and the first Slav States.
As for the Slavs, they obtained their
knowledge of the East both from eyewit¬
ness accounts and from written sources.
Russian, Polish and Czech annals (such as
the Polish chronicle of Gallus Anonymus
and the Czech chronicle of Cosmas of
Prague), compiled in the eleventh and
twelfth centuries, contained information
about the civilizations of the East: Egypt,
Assyria, Media and Iran. The early twelfth-
century Russian text known as the Russian
Primary Chronicle speaks of the trade route
along the Volga to the Caspian and thence
to Khorezm. Many references to the
ancient and medieval peoples of the East
are contained in the historical work of
the fifteenth-century Polish author Jan
Dlugosz.
The Pechenegs and later the Polovt-
sians, fierce Turkic nomad tribes who lived
to the north of Slav territory, often became
political enemies of the Slavs but did not
hinder the development of cultural con¬
tacts. They allowed Slav merchants to pass
through their territories, and sometimes
even served as middlemen.
Indeed, an important feature of modern
studies of the cultural relations between
the Slavs and the East is the current re¬
appraisal of the role of the Turkic peoples,
who served as intermediaries in the lasting
contacts which the Slavs established with
the vast and variegated cultural region
known as "the East".
These Turkic peoples, both nomadic and i
settled, were the closest eastern neigh- I
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Ivory head (above) recently unearthed at
Vergina (Greece) is thought to depict
Alexander the Great as a young man. In
the Middle Ages the story of his epic
expedition became part of Slav folklore.
, bours of the Slavs; and whereas relations
between the Slavs and the Arabs, Iran and
the Far East were largely confined to trade,
the Slav-Turkic relationship was closer and
more enduring. It is impossible to examine
the subject of Slav culture, economics and
political organization without taking into
account this "Turkic factor". (1)
Total harmony has never reigned during
the creation and development of civiliza¬
tions. It was often armour-clad and sword
in hand, rather than with caravans of
goods, that the people of one country set
off towards their neighbours. Contact
sometimes turned into tragic confronta¬
tion. And this was the case of the East
Slavs at the beginning of the thirteenth
century, when the nomad hordes led by the
Mongolian Khagan Batu (the grandson of
Genghis Khan) swept westwards out of the
steppes to invade their lands.
Kievan Russia and many other indepen¬
dent Russian principalities collapsed under
this onslaught. By their struggle against
the Tartar yoke, the East Slavs hindered
the nomads' westward drive, but their own
culture was thereby condemned to develop
for the next three hundred years or so
under foreign domination. Their struggle
for liberation contributed to the unification
of Russia, the establishment of a central¬
ized Russian State, and the appearance
and development of new forms of culture.
Throughout all this period, however, con¬
tacts between the Slavs and the East were-
maintained.
After their adoption of Christianity, Rus¬
sians began to travel to the East on pil¬
grimages to the Holy Land. Pilgrims' tales
of Constantinople, the Byzantine Empire
and Palestine appear in Russian chronicles
from the twelfth century onwards. As early
as the eleventh century, the Russians had a
special quarter in Constantinople where
their merchants lived. Colonies of Russian
monks were established in the monasteries
of Constantinople. Some of these monks
translated books by Greek authors and also
transcribed works by South Slav writers
and sent them to Moscow.
From ancient times, India had captured
the imagination of the Slavs. The fantasy-
embroidered story of Alexander the Great's
journey to the East, to a land known as
"Aleksandrija", was familiar to both East
and West Slavs. Information about this
strana chudes ("wonderland") first
reached the Slavs indirectly, through
Central Asia, Transcaucasia and Iran.
The first Russian traveller to see India
with his own eyes was Afanasi Nikitin, a
merchant of Tver, who visited it between
1466 and 1472. He described his journey in
a book entitled "Travels Beyond Three
Seas". In contrast with many travellers,
Nikitin was able to mingle with the Indians,
and to acquire a sound knowledge of the
country and its customs.
In the sixteenth century, when the age of
great geographical discoveries began, and
Men are transformed into fabulous beasts
in this illustration from a 16th-century
Byelorussian version of the Alexander
romance.
(1) The Turkic peoples: a number of tribes and peoples
who in the sixth century A.D. founded an empire
stretching from Mongolia and the northern frontier of
China to the Black Sea.
Europe was fascinated by news of the
incalculable riches of India and China, the
Slavs were a major link in the expanding
commercial and cultural relations between
western Europe and the East. At the begin¬
ning of the century, the Musco¬
vite ambassador in Rome, Gerasimov,
launched a project for the discovery of a
northern sea route to China. Tsar Ivan the
Terrible, who was interested in the East,
promised a substantial reward to anyone
who reached China by the northern seas;
and it was only in the second half of the
seventeenth century that efforts to do so
were abandoned, when it was found that
China could not be reached by sea, "be¬
cause of great ice, frost and darkness".
The widening and steadily strengthening
pattern of relations between the Slavs and
the eastern peoples, and the mutual in¬
terest which grew up between them, led to
the establishment and development of con¬
tacts between and an intermingling of their
different cultures. The eastern nomadic
tribes, for example, were strongly influenced
by their encounters with the settled Slavs,
whose sedentary way of life they gradually
began to adopt.
Not infrequently, however, cultural
influences arrived via intermediary peoples,
absorbing in the process elements of many
different cultures. It was by no means
always a matter of simply borrowing from
alien cultures; creative receptiveness and
modification were more often the rule.
Tillers of the soil from time immemorial,
the Slavs took a keen interest in the agricul¬
tural practices of the eastern peoples. It
was thanks to Byzantium and the Arabs
that rice came to Europe from the distant
countries of the East; in Russia it was
known as "Saracen millet". As early as the
seventeenth century. Tsar Aleksei Mikhai-
lovich had a special garden laid out close to
Moscow, where plants from the East were
grown on an experimental basis. Russian
ambassadors always endeavoured to bring
back new types of plants from eastern
lands, and more than one envoy to China
was instructed to procure "tea bushes".
Rare animals, including lions, tigers,
camels and elephants, were also brought
back from the East to the Slav countries.
Camels arrived in Poland as early as the
tenth century; Prince Mieszko I sent one as
a gift to the German Emperor. In the six¬
teenth century the Shah of Iran presented a
number of elephants to Ivan the Terrible,
and in 1741 fourteen of them arrived simul¬
taneously in Saint Petersburg. A special
"elephant court" was built for these exotic
animals, who were looked after by Indian
keepers. News of these fantastic creatures
from beyond the seas spread by word of
mouth through the towns and villages of
Russia, and, transformed in appearance by
popular imagination, they began to figure
in the wood carvings with which the pea¬
sants decorated their houses.
Articles made by Oriental craftsmen
were imported into the Slav countries,
while Slav craftsmanship was highly es¬
teemed in the East. It was no coincidence
that experienced master craftsmen of Slav
origin were to be found at the courts of
many eastern potentates. In the thirteenth
century there was a whole colony of Rus-
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
sians in Karakorum, the Mongol capital.
One of them, a skilled goldsmith named
Kosma, built a throne for Khan Koyuk, and
fashioned the great seal of state whose
imprint is preserved on a letter from the
Khan to the Pope.
Cultural relations with the countries of
the East also influenced the daily life of the
Slav peoples. It was in Mongolia that the
Russians first came across tea, at a recep¬
tion given by Altyn-Khan in 1616. The Rus¬
sian ambassadors were treated to milk with
melted butter, "with leaves of some kind in
it". They at first declined to accept tea as a
gift for the Russian Tsar, but finally agreed.
Tea thus came to Russia considerably ear¬
lier than to Holland and England, and for a
long time afterwards it remained the main
Russian import from China.
The habit of drinking tea, together with
its Chinese name, chai, became wide¬
spread during the eighteenth century in
Russia, Central Asia, Iran, Turkey, Syria
and Egypt. The vessel which, in its native
land, China, was used for mulling wine was
adapted for infusing tea, while water was
boiled in a Russian invention, the samovar.
Many eastern peoples became acquainted
with the samovar of Russia, which proved
extremely popular in Central Asia, Turkey,
.*.
p ' M
Kk'íS Ir
-^j^H ^BL
M
it .41 mr
iî>
l^Ê9m K*
r 1
7 * ^
> 4.
T
* 1 t ir J
f < f jm
4 "**" À j , \ *9 *
/^'
¡*1* J
U 1 |fij|
r « Ife^l
) ) wrk
**m 1 ir 1
1 B^^^^^
1
<*L I
^
1 w V
' 1 f w i
I
M m . '
Elephants
and envoys
Shown here are two of the
many lively and picturesque
works of art which record the
relations between the Slav
countries and the East. Left, a
Japanese artist's impression of
the famous Russian traveller and
diplomat Nikolai Rezanov, who
led a mission to Japan in 1804.
Every detail of his uniform is
carefully described. Rare
animals such as lions, tigers and
elephants were sometimes sent
as gifts to Slav rulers by eastern
potentates. When the first
elephant seen in Moscow
arrived from Persia in the early
18th century, the event was
commemorated by a popular
woodcut (above).
Iran and the Arab countries. In Kashmir, it
has even kept its Russian name.
The Europeans, the Slavs among them,
learned much about science, including
mathematics, from the eastern peoples.
The numerals still employed today are cal¬
led "Arabic" (although they really origin¬
ated in India). For their part, the Slavs took
a keen scientific interest in the East. Peter
the Great with his own hand corrected an
inaccurate map of the Caspian Sea and
Central Asia.
During the seventeenth century, Yuri
Krzanic, a Croatian living in Russia, com¬
piled descriptions of Serbia, Mongolia and
China. Returning in 1680 to his native land,
he presented his History of Siberia to the
Polish king, Jan Sobieski, thereby making
an important contribution to knowledge of
the Far East among the West Slavs.
The age-old lore of eastern folk-medicine
was highly regarded by the Slavs, who in
turn played a major role in the introduction
of western medical science in the East. In
the mid-nineteenth century, Russian doc¬
tors founded the first hospital in Japan.
The first doctor in Mongolia, Pavel Shas-
tin, was a Russian. His methods of treat¬
ment made such an impression on the^
Mongolians that for a long time the words F
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
vrach (doctor) and shastin were synony¬
mous.
These long-standing relations with the
East left their imprint on the Slavonic lan¬
guages. Historically and genetically the
Slavs belong to the Indo-European peo¬
ples, and for this reason their languages
preserve certain features which relate them
to the Indo-European languages. More¬
over, all Slav languages contain large num¬
bers of borrowed words and grammatical
features of eastern (and particularly Turkic)
origin, while a whole series of Slav words
have, as it were, "gone East".
Generations of descendants of ancient
eastern peoples have remained in the lands
of the West Slavs. At the beginning of this
century, a Polish Orientalist visited one
such group, the Karaims, and came across
an old glossary of Polovtsian words in the
house of a Karaim family. To his great as¬
tonishment, the seven-year-old daughter
of the house explained the text to him as he
read it aloud. From generation to genera¬
tion, this family had handed down a lan¬
guage which had ceased to be spoken
many centuries earlier.
Slavonic architecture came under a
strong eastern influence. In its early days,
the Byzantine tradition had a powerful
impact, while somewhat later Muslim
architecture, introduced by the Turks, left
its mark on the buildings of the South
Slavs. Eastern influences are less pro¬
nounced in the architecture of the West
Slav countries, in Poland and Czechoslova¬
kia, although here too monuments of eas¬
tern type may be found side by side with
old Gothic churches. Monuments built by
Armenian architects have survived in the
Ukraine and in Poland.
After the union of the Khanates of Kazan
and Astrakhan with Russia, eastern motifs
became more prominent in Russian archi¬
tecture. The famous Pokrovsky Church
(Cathedral of Saint Basil the Blessed),
situated on Red Square in Moscow, was
built in the national Russian Shater (or
tent) style of ecclesiastical architecture,
but also incorporates a number of eastern
elements.
Traces of eastern influences may also be
found in ancient Russian folklore: several
tales (bylinyj contain echoes of Turkic
epics. Many of them refer to heroes with
Turkic names, and the events they describe
reflect the history of the relations between
various branches of the Turkic peoples.
The intermingling of Slav and eastern
cultures was not only a source of mutual
enrichment, but also made a substantial
contribution to world civilization as a
whole. Today, the launching of an Indian
satellite by a Soviet rocket or the practice
of ancient Tibetan medicine on the shores
of the Baltic occasion no more surprise
than the appearance of a turbanned Indian
on the streets of Prague or of a fair-skinned
European amid the hubbub of an eastern
bazaar.
Any major culture is the product of con¬
tact and intermingling with many others,
great and small. History has shown that
creative borrowing is an essential factor in
cultural development and that attempts at
cultural isolationism lead inevitably to
impoverishment.
Olzhas O. Suleimenov
This 11th-century bas-relief
sculpture on slate depicts
Cybele, Mother of the
Gods, reclining on a chariot
drawn by lions. It was
discovered in Kiev's
Pecherskaya Lavra
Monastery, Russia's oldest
monastic establishment,
whose monks lived in cells
hollowed out of cliffs
overlooking the River
Dnieper. Mythological
motifs from Antiquity,
especially Hercules and
Cybele, often figure in
Kievan 11th-century art.
KIEV
The mother
of Russian cities
by Yuri Asseyev
YURI ASSEYEV, Sower architect and profes¬
sor of the history of architecture, is assistant to
the rector of the Kiev Institute of Art.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
THE heyday of the ancient Russian
State, whose territory stretched
from the White Sea to the Black Sea
and from the Carpathians to the steppeland
of the Volga, began in the tenth century
with the unification of the East Slav tribes
around Kiev. It lasted until the fourth
decade of the twelfth century, when the
development of feudalism led to a process
of fragmentation. During these centuries
the most outstanding masterpieces of
ancient Russian art and architecture were
created.
The roots of Kievan art were threefold.
The first ran backwards in time, towards
the rich cultural heritage of the East Slavs
themselves. The second grew out of the
living conditions and the demands of the
State in ancient Russia. The third stretched
beyond the frontiers of Russia itself
towards the accumulated experience of
other countries and above all of Byzantium,
the custodian of the great cultural tradi¬
tions of Antiquity.
The golden age of ancient Russian art
was eulogized in oral epics and in written
works alike, and nowhere more so than in
the cycle of poems (byliny) which com¬
memorate the exploits of the Kievan war¬
riors llya of Murom, Dobrynya Nikitich
and Alyosha Popovich. Conserved in the
popular memory over the centuries, these
poems transmit a message of pride and
admiration inspired by the grandeur and
power of the Kievan State.
The same sense of belonging to a great
and illustrious country permeates the Dis¬
course on Law and Grace composed in the
mid-eleventh century by Hilarión, the
Metropolitan of Kiev. Praising the princes
of Russia, he writes, "Not in some miser¬
able and unknown country did they rule,
but in the Russian land, whose name is
known and whose voice is heard in the
four corners of the universe".
The adoption of Christianity in 989 A.D.
brought Russia into closer contact with the
Christian world, and above all with the
world of Orthodox Christianity. By then the
Russians had a written language, and they
were able to practise the new religion in
their native tongue. This was a powerful
stimulus to the development of original
features in their art.
Patriotism was an important component
of the ancient Russian sense of beauty, and
had a strong influence on lyrical poetry.
Indeed, love for the homeland and the
natural environment is a leitmotif which
runs through ancient Russian art, particu¬
larly the epic poems. It echoes through the
Russian chronicles; it lies at the heart of the
famous Lay of Igor's Campaign; and it
finds expression in the Tale of the Ruin of
the Russian Land, whose author proclaims:
"0 Russian land, how radiantly bright and
beautifully adorned you are! Many and sur¬
prising are your charms: your lakes, your
rivers and your sacred springs, your steep
mountains and your lofty hills, your thick,
leafy forests and your lovely fields, your
monastery gardens and your churches..."
The building of cities, fortresses and
castles was an extremely important activity
which provided Russian architects with a
wealth of opportunities for developing and
perfecting their skills. The early cities,
whose buildings, naturally enough in a
country of forests, were for the most part
made of wood, usually consisted of a forti¬
fied nucleus (the detinets) whose precincts
contained the palaces of princes, nobles
and their retinues. Around this central area
lay the outer city, whose ramparts shelter¬
ed the bulk of the population. At the edge
of the city were the districts where the
craftsmen and tradesmen lived. During the
eleventh and twelfth centuries, the popula¬
tions of Kiev, Novgorod, Smolensk, Cher¬
nigov, Vladimir Volynsky and other major
Russian cities numbered tens of thou¬
sands, which made them among the most k
densely populated centres of Europe. t
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
m§gfo¡
f¡r,ti
With their ornately constructed and
high-towered wooden palaces, their many
wooden and stone-built churches and
monasteries, the Russian cities were an
impressive sight to the merchants from
Germany and Central Asia, from Italy and
the Arab Caliphate, from Scandinavia and
Byzantium, who made their way towards
their crowded market-places. These visi¬
tors, together with the Russian merchants
themselves, who travelled from their
homes in Kiev, Novgorod and Smolensk on
long journeys overseas, brought to Russia
a great variety of goods and articles of
foreign make, which served as models and
as inspiration for the local craftsmen.
The tenth century saw a sharp rise in
Russian standards of craftsmanship and in
the output of Russian craftsmen. In Kiev
alone sixty different crafts were practised.
Jewellery made in this city was particularly
prized, and won praise from the Byzantine
poet Tzetzes and from Theophilus of
Paderborn, a tenth-century German author
who wrote a voluminous treatise on the
jeweller's craft.
Foreign visitors to Kiev exclaimed that
nowhere else had they seen such beautiful
things, and this is not surprising if we take
as a single example the small piece of
jewellery, preserved to this day, consisting
of no less than 5,000 soldered ringlets 0.06
cm in diameter, in the centre of each of
which is a tiny precious stone measuring
0.04 cm. On a surface measuring eight
square centimetres, the jeweller fixed 120
golden flowers on thread-like gilded stems.
The first mention of the use of stone for
the construction of a palace dates from 945
A.D., but this material only began to be
widely used for building at the end of the
tenth century. Even at this early stage,
specifically Russian architectural tech¬
niques and forms appeared, as distinct
from those employed in Byzantium. One
original feature of Russian churches is the
onion-shaped cupola, which in the opinion
of many specialists was inspired by the hel¬
mets of the Russian warriors.
The most precious treasure of Kievan
Russia is the Cathedral of Saint Sophia.
According to the oldest surviving manus¬
cript, the Russian Primary Chronicle, it was
founded in 1037 on the site where, a year
earlier, Yaroslav the Wise had finally routed
the Pecheneg nomads. Beneath later addi¬
tions and the reconstruction carried out
during the seventeenth and eighteenth
centuries, the cathedral has to a remark¬
able extent conserved its original outline.
With its majestic and harmonious archi¬
tecture, Saint Sophia is a brilliant symbol
of Russia's new-found unity under the
authority of the Kievan prince, as well as a
memorial to victory over the nomads.
Particularly outstanding are the frescoes
decorating the staircases which lead to
upper galleries in two of the towers. They
depict scenes of princely entertainment:
wrestling matches, horse-races, hunting,
bird-snaring, dancing, music-making and
other activities. Beneath the galleries are
portraits of the family of Yaroslav the Wise,
including his daughters Anne, Elizabeth
and Anastasia, whom he married to the
kings of France, Norway and Hungary.
teî»!ïîvWri
NVlYlfîÇîL
pîJtïtÏYÎYiTiW'jfJi
IiJ/fïvrfît ! t it it itiL
c;I.'tiTjt»ti\>ititititl
fcfSN^WfîtîWr
Ü
l*&
¿*l»l
ILLUMINATED MINIATURE of St. Mark from a page of the Ostromir
Gospel, a masterpiece of Kievan art. Copied in 1056-1057, this Slavonic
manuscript was lost for centuries and accidentally rediscovered in the
18th century in the wardrobe of Catherine the Great. It is now preserved
in the Saltykov-Shchedrin Public Library, Leningrad.
LUXURIANT FRESCOES AND MOSAICS cover the columns, walls and
vaulted ceilings of the 11th-century cathedral of St. Sophia in Kiev.
Predominantly Byzantine in their symbolism, execution and
arrangement, they portray Apostles, Saints and martyrs and depict
episodes from the Old and New Testaments. Right, detail of fresco
illustrating the Visitation of the Virgin Mary to Elizabeth, the mother of
John the Baptist.
Some 2,000 square metres of eleventh-
century frescoes have been uncovered
from beneath later inscriptions and res¬
tored, and these constitute only a fraction
of the original decoration.
The mosaics covering the pillars, vaul¬
ting and walls of the luminous central area
of the cathedral are equally striking, and
the representation of the Eucharist and the
Church Fathers in the central apse is a
masterpiece of composition. Among the
portraits of the Church Fathers, those of
Saint Lawrence, Saint Gregory Palmyras
and Saint John Chrysostom are executed
with supreme artistry.
Approximately 650 square metres of
mosaic have been preserved in the cathe¬
dral. In the opinion of Soviet specialist Vic¬
tor N. Lazarev, they are the work of at least
eight master craftsmen. The artists
employed a wealth of colour, 177 different
tones in all, including 34 shades of green,
23 shades of yellow and nine shades of
grey.
Another celebrated architectural monu¬
ment of Kievan Russia is the Cathedral of
the Transfiguration in Chernigov, which
was founded, according to the chronicles,
around 1035-1036.
In the middle of the eleventh century, the
development of feudalism in Kievan Russia
strengthened the self-confidence of indivi
dual regions, and the establishment of new
centres opened a fresh chapter in the his¬
tory of Russian art and architecture. The
separatist tendencies of different princes
weakened the hold of Kiev, while the
influence of the Church grew stronger and
monasteries sprang up all over the land.
Kiev, however, was still the Russian
capital, and the main source of cultural and
artistic inspiration, much of which origina¬
ted in the Pecherskaya Lavra Monastery.
The Church of Saint Michael with the
Golden Roof, founded between 1107 and
1113, contained magnificent mosaics and
frescoes, its main apse being decorated
with a mosaic of the Eucharist, like those of
Saint Sophia and the Church of the
Assumption in the Pecherskaya Lavra. But
this large-scale composition is quite diffe¬
rent from the Saint Sophia Eucharist. The
figures are portrayed with far greater free¬
dom of expression,, more attention is paid
to the delineation of their psychology, the
colours are bright and intense. The indivi¬
dual heads are more diversified and their
expressions and gestures are more anima¬
ted. These features, together with the ins¬
criptions which accompany the portraits,
suggest that the mosaic was produced by
local masters. Some specialists believe that
one of them was the legendary Russian
icon-painter Alipi.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
The life and work of Alipi are described in
detail in the Pechersk Paterik, a collection
of writings on the religious and cultural
activities of the Pecherskaya Lavra. Accor¬
ding to the Paterik, Alipi "was not concer¬
ned with growing rich". He painstakingly
collected old icons by other masters and
restored them, while his own works were
so beautiful that the Kievans believed that
the angels had a hand in their production.
The power of healing was attributed to the
paints he used.
Many archaeological discoveries and lit¬
erary sources attest to the Russian attach¬
ment to pagan works of sculpture. This
attachment probably explains why Prince
Vladimir brought back ancient statues from
Khersonesus in the Crimea to decorate the
central square of Kiev.
Sculpture was associated with paganism
and the Byzantine Church disapproved of
this medium being used to depict religious
themes: the sculptures in Saint Sophia in
Kiev and in the Cathedral of the Transfig¬
uration in Chernigov are purely ornamental.
Another major centre of Kievan architec¬
ture was Novgorod. Three of its early
twelfth-century churches and monasteries
have survived in good order up to the pre¬
sent day: the Cathedral of Saint Nicholas
the Wonderworker (1113) and the Monas¬
teries of Saint Anthony (1117) and Saint
George (1119). Their cupolas, surmounted
by a cross and supported by six piers,
reflect the influence of the Church of the
Assumption at the Pecherskaya Lavra.
At the same time, Novgorod's own
Cathedral of Saint Sophia established a
new tradition of powerful forms and aus¬
tere stone and brick façades, in structures
with three or five cupola-topped towers. A
particularly splendid example of this style is
the Cathedral of the Monastery of Saint
George.
The surviving fragments of the frescoes
of the Monastery of Saint Anthony, dating
from 1125, are Romanesque in character,
but are executed in a particularly energetic
and free-handed manner that prefigures
some of the features of later Novgorod
painting.
Legend has it that Anthony of Rome, the
founder of the monastery, arrived in Nov¬
gorod after sailing across the Mediterra¬
nean and Baltic Seas on a millstone.
Meanwhile, some fishermen of Novgorod
hauled up a barrel full of precious objects,
which Anthony himself had thrown over¬
board at the beginning of his voyage. It
was on these riches that the monastery
was constructed.
Fantastic though it may be, this typically
medieval legend contains a grain of truth:
those of Anthony's possessions which
have survived are of authentically European
origin, and both literary and archaeological
evidence show that the city of Novgorod
enjoyed very close contacts with the West.
No trace has survived of Russian easel
paintings from the late tenth and the early
eleventh centuries, although the chronicles
mention the icons which decorated the
early churches. During the eleventh and
early twelfth centuries, a great number of
icons were imported into Russia from
Byzantium. One of the most famous of
them, "Our Lady of Vladimir", had a strong
influence on the development of Russian
icon painting.
Icons from Russia found their way to
neighbouring countries, where they were
held in high esteem; a notable example is
Poland's celebrated Virgin otCzestokhova.
The production of illuminated books
reached heights of perfection in Kievan
Russia. Books had long been prized, care¬
fully preserved and richly decorated in Rus¬
sia. In the words of an eleventh-century
chronicler, they were "rivers that quench
the thirst of the universe, sources of wis¬
dom whose depths are unfathomable".
The oldest surviving Russian book, the
Ostromir Gospel, was written in 1056-1057
by the deacon Grigori, for Ostromir the
posadnik (mayor) of Novgorod. It is dec- i
orated with a profusion of illuminated I
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
FOCAL POINT of Kiev's cultural, social
and religious life was the cathedral of St.
Sophia (dedicated in 1037), built by Prince
Yaroslav the Wise as part of plans to
emulate the splendours of Byzantium.
Little of the ancient edifice, whose 13
cupolas symbolized Christ and the
disciples, has survived, and the
extensively-restored exterior (above,
eastern façade) is largely baroque. A
unique feature of St. Sophia is its cycle of
secular frescoes depicting spectacles
similar to those presented at Christmas to
the Emperor at Constantinople. Over 130
merry-makers are shown juggling,
disguised as fantastic animals, dancing,
making music and hunting (below).
initials, head-pieces and miniature portraits
' of the evangelists.
Interesting portraits of members of the
family of Prince Yaropolk Izyaslavovich are
to be found in the so-called Codex of Ger¬
trude (also known as the "Psalter of Trier")
which was compiled between 1078 and
1087 and is today preserved in Italy (at Civi-
dale in Lombardy). Written in Latin at the
command of Egbert, Archibishop of Trier,
it came a century later into the hands of
Princess Gertrude of Poland, the wife of
Prince Izyaslav of Kiev, son of Yaroslav the
Wise. While in her possession, the manu¬
script was further decorated with a number
of miniatures, including portraits of Ger¬
trude's son Yaropolk and his wife Irina.
From about 1130 onwards, ancient Rus¬
sia entered a stage of "feudal disintegra¬
tion". If an all-Russian tradition persisted,
the different principalities created their own
cultural and artistic centres, where local
trends and tastes were intermingled with
more general features of artistic develop¬
ment at that time. In the words of Acade¬
mician Boris A. Rybakov, twelfth-century
Russia was a co-author of the many forms
of the Romanesque style.
By the fourth decade of the century, the
typically Kievan tradition of building with a
mixture of stbne and brick had been aban¬
doned, and Russian architects began to
turn to locally available materials. In the
Dnieper region and in Volynya, brick was
used. In Galicia and Vladimir-Suzdal,
limestone was at hand, and the façades of
buildings are decorated with carvings in
white stone. This feature finds masterful
expression in the Church of Saint Dimitri at
Vladimir (1194-1197) and in the Church of
the Intercession built in 1165 at the mouth
of the River Nerl.
The greatest masterpieces of Russian
icon painting in the twelfth and thirteenth
centuries are those of Saint Dmitri, from
the town of Dmitrov near Moscow, the Vir¬
gin of the Pecherskaya Lavra, and the Vir¬
gin of the Novgorod Dormition, all of
which are now in the Tretyakov Gallery in
Moscow.
If Russian art branched out in different
directions as each feudal principality asser¬
ted its independence, its tap-root conti¬
nued to draw strength from the original
source Kiev. And herein lies the signifi¬
cance of the art of Kievan Russia, as the art
of a united ancient Russian people from
which the art and architecture of the Rus¬
sians, the Ukrainians and the Byelorussians
would later develop.
Yuri Asseyev
Colour Pages
OPPOSITE PAGE
The Entry into Jerusalem, a late 15th or
early 16th-century icon of the
Novgorod school. Icons of this period
are often referred to as "mixed school"
icons because they combine the
vigorous naturalistic style of Novgorod
with the elegance and spirituality of
the Moscow school. Jerusalem is
depicted with the towers and walls of
Novgorod (top right). Christ looks back
at a group of his disciples, whilst the
people come out to welcome him,
carpeting his path with their cloaks
and with palm-tree branches.
Photo Bob Saler © Rapho, Paris
CENTRE DOUBLE PAGE
In the Moscow school of icon-painting,
three great names stand out:
Theophanes the Greek, Andrey
Rublyov (see page 21) and Dionysius
(1440-1508). Dionysius carried on the
Rublyov tradition but his art was
perhaps more luminous as well as
more decorative and ornamental. This
icon, attributed to Dionysius, came
from the Cathedral of the Dormition in'
the Moscow Kremlin and today is
preserved in the Tretyakov Gallery.
Dating from about 1483, it portrays the
Metropolitan Alexis holding the Bible
in his left hand. The ¡con is bordered
with scenes from Alexis' life.
Photo Bob Saler © Rapho, Paris
Photo ® U.S. S R. Academy of Art, Leningrad
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
!
UNI
.¡Y
»
-
Ñ
t V
.'v ^.y ^>c
,
\ -1
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
Photos © Miodrag Djordjevic, Saltykov-Shchedrin Public Library, Leningrad
The Morava school of painting marked the
golden age of Serbian art towards the close
of the Middle Ages. Frescoes, ¡cons and
miniatures all demonstrate how artists of the
Morava school succeeded in portraying vivid,
living personalities within the framework of
stylized forms. The four miniatures (across
both pages, above) by the master-painter
Radoslav come from a New Testament dating
from 1429, now in the Saltykov-Shchedrin
Public Library, Leningrad. The miniatures
depict the four evangelists listening to the
words of God as whispered to them by the
Spirit of Holy Wisdom. The symbols
attributed to each evangelist can be seen
in the top corner of each painting.
From left to right: St. Luke, with a bull; St.
Mark, with a lion; St. Matthew, with an
angel; and St. John, with an eagle.
The art
of the Morava School
Sensitivity and grace
in fifteenth-century Serbia
by Svetozar Radojcic
Left, detail from a 14th-century fresco known
as "The Saracens", from the Church of St.
Archangel, at Lesnovo, Macedonia,
Yugoslavia. The relationships between the
Saracens, the name by which the Muslims
were sometimes known in the West, and the
South Slavs were often turbulent.
Photo © Yugoslav Cultural Centre, Paris
A
NCIENT Serbian art began to flour¬
ish towards the end of the twelfth
century, but went into decline
SVETOZAR RADOJCIC is a noted Yugoslav
art historian who has carried out important
research into the art of medieval Serbia. He is
professor of the history of art at Be/grade
University.
after 1459, when Turkish invaders occupied
the fortress-town of Smederevo, the capi¬
tal of the Serbian Tsars. Nevertheless, this
national art survived, under the Ottoman
yoke, until the first decades of the eight¬
eenth century. When the Turks finally
retreated from the Danube basin, Serbian .
artists were ready to make their contribu-
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
tion to the late Baroque period of central
' and western Europe.
Against the background of the turbulent
history of the eastern Mediterranean
region, the Balkan peninsula and the
Danube basin, Serbian art, which had
formed an integral element of Byzantine
culture, followed its own path of deve¬
lopment.
When the great Serbian Empire crum¬
bled after the disastrous battle of the
Maritza, in 1371, and the extinction of the
Nemanja dynasty, the princely families of
the Lazareviói and the Brakovici struggled
to retain their hold in the narrow territory
that stretched from the belt of land bet¬
ween the Danube and the Sava in the north
to the two Moravas in the south (these two
tributaries, which flow northward from the
Macedonian border to meet in a single river
that joins the Danube east of Belgrade,
should not be confused with the Morava of
Czechoslovakia, from which the vast
region of Moravia takes its name).
It was here that the Serbian "despotate"
(a term borrowed from the Byzantine hi¬
erarchy of government, and in no sense
pejorative) had a short-lived existence bet¬
ween 1402 and 1459, as the last outpost of
free Christianity in the Islam-dominated
Balkans. In the struggle between the Chris¬
tians and the Ottomans, this little Serbia of
the south became the refuge of countless
emigrants from Byzantium, Mount Athos,
Macedonia, Bulgaria and Albania.
The roads leading to the despotate were
crowded with refugees: princes chased
from their principalities, bishops deprived
of their bishoprics, monks without monas¬
teries and seigneurs who had lost their fiefs
and castles. In their train followed a motley
retinue of writers, architects, painters,
musicians and singers the whole constel¬
lation of artists that surrounded the rich
and powerful figures of the day.
TEPHEN Lazarevió,
son of Prince Lazar
who fell in battle in
1389 at Kosovo- Polje,
where the Turks finally
established their supre¬
macy over the Serbs, was a typical repre¬
sentative of his age. Bearing the title of
"despot", conferred on him by the Byzan¬
tine Emperor, liegeman of the king of Hun¬
gary, vassal of the Sultan and commander-
in-chief of his own army, warrior and
patron of letters and himself a poet, he
attracted scores of writers to his court at
Belgrade. Sycophantic . contemp
oraries called him "the new Ptolemy". He
was the founder of the Resava school (so-
called after the monastery that stood close
to the river of that name). This was not
merely a school of copyists, as has some¬
times been slightingly suggested, but, as it
was referred to at the time, of
"translators".
Contemporaneous with the Resava
school, and created under the same aus¬
pices, was a still more significant school. It
has sometimes been said that art is the pro¬
duct of peaceful and happy times; the ,
Morava school, as it is called by historians
of Serbian art, which served as a nursery of
sensitivity and grace during a dark, doom-
laden period, provides ample evidence that
nothing could be further from the truth.
From the twelfth century onwards, the
quest for the aesthetic followed two paths
with artists seeking both outward and inner
beauty. These two contrasting and un¬
evenly balanced trends, the point and
counterpoint of which are most apparent in
architecture, reached their apogee during
the years of the despotate.
The churches of the Morava school,
whose inner volumes were perfectly plan¬
ned, and whose façades were covered with
sumptuous decoration, were suited both to
the routine of daily offices and to the occa¬
sional splendour of great ceremonies. Their
floor plan took the form of rectangles with
semi-circular ends, above which soared the
great conches of the apses and the crowns
of their domes. Their whole structure was
adapted to the requirements of a complex
liturgy involving numerous clergy, two
choirs, and the spectacular processions
depicted in contemporary frescoes. All the
different sections, passages and partitions
were functional and acoustically perfect.
The vocal music which completed the
beauty of these churches has only recently
been re-discovered. In fact it was not until
after the Second World War that Serbian
manuscripts dating from the turn of the
fourteenth-fifteenth centuries and contain¬
ing musical notations were deciphered and
their notes transcribed. Two of the proces¬
sions which appear frequently in ancient
paintings the "Grand entrance" and the
"Communion of the Apostles" can now
be accompanied not only by the words,
which were already known, but also by the
authentic musical background which gives
to the gestures of the depicted characters a
strange, unfathomable, almost unearthly
rhythm, a music which inspires in its list¬
eners the sentiment of unshaken and un-
shakeable belief.
The earliest frescoes, painted in the mid-
fourteenth century, portrayed the unusual
figures of the "chapel-masters" in their
richly decorated robes and strange, white,
three-cornered hats. Now we not only
know their names Stefan, Isaija and
Joakim but also the music they com¬
posed.
The beauty of these hallowed, music-
haunted places was enriched by a new
style of wall painting, in frescoes which
capture the same subtle and musical deli¬
cacy of tone and from which powerful and
severe brush-strokes are entirely absent.
The human portraits they contain are styl¬
ized, plastic, almost sculptural; like the
music, the figures seem unearthly.
From this point onwards, the painters of
the Morava school abandoned the tech¬
niques employed for earlier frescoes in
favour of the more subtle approach used
for painting on wood. Attitudes and move¬
ments are captured and, as it were, frozen
for all time; yet the gestures remain gentle
and harmonious. In the paintings of the
Serbian despotate, scenes from Christ's life
on earth are favourite themes: warrior-
saints, monks, bishops and preachers alike
are represented as "celestial men and ter¬
restrial angels", glowing with outward
beauty and inner perfection, inhabitants of
a universe whose only dimensions were
pictural, literary and musical.
This art is a faithful reflection of the
mysticism of Eastern Christianity. There is
something dramatic in the artistic expres¬
sion of the wonder provoked by revelation.
The sanctuary of the church, the "holy of
holies", is hidden behind a partition to
which icons are attached, the iconostasis
which, like the scenae irons of ancient
theatres, contains three doors draped with
rich fabrics. At certain specific moments in
the rituals, these curtains are raised. The
larger churches were decorated with rich
polychrome stone facings: broad ornamen-<
tal bands, arcades and large, rose-shaped
designs, and figures executed in low relief,
especially around the windows. There was
a great variety of decorative motifs: scroll¬
work, angels, mythical animals and enig¬
matic shapes, among which, at the Kalenió
monastery, for example, stood the centaur
Chiron, who taught music to the Greek
hero Achilles.
HE ancient dichotomy
of outer and inner
beauty is a recurrent
feature of works of the
Morava school, reveal¬
ed in its architecture, its frescoes, its
icons, its rich brocades, its jewellery and
above all its miniature paintings. Invariably
the ornamentation expressed an outer
beauty behind which transcendent, mys¬
terious, barely perceptible values lay con¬
cealed.
This grandiose vision of a perfect world,
evoked during an age of utmost peril, exer¬
cised a profound attraction on the survi¬
vors of Christian Byzantium; for the
mystics and intellectuals who, during the
fifteenth century, wandered between Italy
and the distant Russian steppes, it had the
value of a prophecy.
The merit of this fifteenth-century art,
which emerged from a Serbia whose fron¬
tiers had been so reduced, which was both
lordly and monastic and which was the
product of luxury and asceticism alike, was
that it reconciled the outer with the inner
beauty. European art was at a crossroads:
while the West turned its back on medieval
thought and art, the East continued to
cling to them tenaciously, adopting a scep¬
tical attitude both towards matter, nature
and the power of human reason, and
towards the spirituality of antiquity from
which, nevertheless, it derived its art an
art in which form alone resembled reality,
yet was itself a symbol and an allegory. The
figures of the writers embraced by the
Muses in the miniatures of the master
painter Radoslav are perhaps the finest
examples of this complex, traditionalist cul¬
ture, which found its most perfect expres¬
sion in the art of painting.
Svetozar Radojcic
42
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
DUBROVNIK
Gateway to the Latin West
by Vuk Vuco
Photos Nenad Gattin © University Press Liber, Zagreb
Ever since medieval times when Slav and Latin settlements merged to form a single city on a
promontory jutting out into the Adriatic, Dubrovnik, Yugoslavia (Croatia) has formed a link between East
and West. Although the port was almost totally destroyed by an earthquake in 1667, vestiges of the
ancient walls and bastions that once guarded its seaward approaches (above right) have survived to
frame the modern port (aerial view above left).
THE seventh decade of the seven¬
teenth century was an unhappy
one for Europe. Throughout the
1660s waves of disasters and afflictions of
all kinds swept the continent, from London
to the shores of Asia Minor, from Sicily to
Scandinavia. Wars and epidemics were
rampant, and claimed hundreds of thou¬
sands of victims.
At this time one proud European city on
the Adriatic enjoyed the blessings of peace
and prosperity in such abundance that its
VUK VUCO, Yugoslav poet and novelist, is also
a critic specializing in the dramatic arts. His
novel Les Voleurs de Feu (The Fire Robbers) has
been published in France by Seuil publishers,
Paris. He is currently editor-in-chief of Danas, a
magazine for Yugoslavs living in France.
citizens might have been forgiven for
thinking that the kindly waters of their sea
would protect them forever. This city, one
of the most beautiful in seventeenth-
century Europe, had a banner which bore
the inscription Libertas freedom. Its name
was Dubrovnik.
On 6 April 1667, the Wednesday of Holy
Week, a cloudless day dawned over
Dubrovnik. A calm, unruffled sea stretched
beneath an azure sky. By 8 o'clock that
morning the sky was still clear and the
waves lapped gently against the city fortifi¬
cations. A group of notables strolled out¬
side the palace, waiting for the bell to sum¬
mon them to the Great Council, which met
at Eastertide to pardon convicted criminals.
In the palace chapel a religious ceremony
attended by the ruler and by Dubrovnik's
highest dignitaries was drawing to a close, i
The bishop was intoning a prayer of grati- |
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
tude for the peace and plenty that prevailed
in the tiny republic and expressing his hope
that they would long continue.
At that moment the earth began to trem¬
ble. Within a matter of seconds, amid a
crescendo of noise, the entire city was
transformed by an earthquake into a mass
of rubble. Palaces, monuments, churches,
fortifications the pride of Dubrovnik
which had been lovingly and painstakingly
created over the centuries, all collapsed
like a house of cards.
The ruler of Dubrovnik, his retinue and
the highest servants of State perished in
the cataclysm along with three-quarters of
the city's population. On the nearby island
of Lopud, which was also hit by the earth¬
quake no more than 400 of the 14,000
¡slanders survived.
Misfortunes never come singly. The
earthquake was followed by a fire and a
tidal wave. Then came an army of looters
who for weeks on end pillaged the ruins
and robbed the dead. The enemies of
Dubrovnik, who until then had never dared
to attack the mighty fortress, flocked by
land and sea to the stricken and defence¬
less city.
Several times in its history Dubrovnik has
risen from the ashes of disaster. Barely two
centuries before the earthquake of 1667 the
city had experienced and survived another
terrible earthquake followed by an epi¬
demic of plague which decimated the
population. But neither natural catastro¬
phes nor the vicissitudes of history could
wipe this remarkable city from the map.
Many cities in the modern world pride
themselves on their cosmopolitanism and
boast that they provide a favourable setting
for the intermingling of different cultures.
Few can rival Dubrovnik as a cross-roads
where the cultural heritage of the East and
West' have met and been mutually en¬
riched. For Dubrovnik is remarkable not
only for its vitality and its resilience in the
face of ordeals, but as a gem which has
been polished for centuries in the ebb and
flow of East and West.
At the time of the great invasion of Dal-
matia by the Avaro-Slavs, around 614
A.D., the settlement of Epidaurus (present-
day Cavtat) was sacked and razed to the
ground. Tradition has it that the survivors
of this massacre went on to found a new
colony, Ragusium, two hours' march
northwards along the rocky coast.
Close by this settlement, whose name is
derived from a Latin word meaning escarp¬
ment, was the Slav forest colony of
Dubrovnik (dubrova in Serbo-Croat means
"woody"). The initial antagonism between
the two populations slowly disappeared,
and the two colonies merged into a single
city. By the beginning of the 13th century
"Ragusium-Dubrovnik" had become a
single community where different ethnic
groups, cultures and religions developed a
spirit of coexistence which still survives
today.
In the course of its long history, Dubrov¬
nik has transformed its handicaps into
advantages: it has turned poverty into
wealth, calmed the warlike, and reoonciled
different religions and opposing economic
forces. All this it has achieved by obeying
whenever possible an ancient local proverb
according to which "A bad quarrel is
always better than a good war".
Right from the start Dubrovnik's econo¬
mic life was based on seafaring and trade.
In the.ninth century sailors plied eastwards
as far as the Black Sea and northwards as
far as England, whence they set out on
even longer voyages in the Atlantic. By the
beginning of the thirteenth century its fleet
was so large that the tiny republic began to
challenge Venice for mastery of the seas.
Through a combination of diplomatic and
maritime skills, Dubrovnik had become a
great seaport by the 14th century.
Dubrovnik rapidly became the main
trading centre of the Balkan Peninsula, and
its operations extended as far as Italy and
other Mediterranean countries. Nor was
the shift of maritime trade from the Medi¬
terranean to the Atlantic a major drawback
to the city's economic fortunes ; indeed it
was in the sixteenth century and the first
half of the seventeenth century that
Dubrovnik achieved the very height of its
prosperity.
To preserve its freedom, the city always
had to pay a high price to the Venetians,
the Byzantines, the Turks and the Slav
kingdoms in the north. The Serb kingdoms
cast particularly covetous eyes on the tiny
independent state, attracted by the wealth
it had garnered from the four corners of the
earth but above all because it was an
incomparable outlet to the sea. And yet the
sea receded before them like a mirage as
they advanced, for all their efforts to wage
open war against Dubrovnik ended in
failure. Powerful protectors Slav Tsars
and Latin Kings alike rushed to aid the
republic whenever danger threatened.
After two perilous centuries, a ruler who
understood the true importance of Dubrov¬
nik came to the Serbian throne in the per¬
son of Tsar Dusan. An able statesman and
a prodigious expansionist, Dusan decided
to withdraw the sword of aggression and
extend the hand of friendship. Like the
other Slav rulers, indeed like all the Slavs,
he was mesmerized by Dubrovnik. But
paradoxically, for he was after all a Serb,
he felt that the city should be treated as a
precious relic. In 1346, shortly after his
coronation as Tsar, he set out for Dubrov¬
nik on a peace mission.
The meeting between Dusan and the
patricians of Dubrovnik beneath the gilded
beams of the Great Council Chamber
44
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
Customs house, mint and granary, the
16th-century Sponza Palace (above left)
played a central role in Dubrovnik's
economy. In niche beneath the roof is
statue of St. Vlaho (St. Blasius), the
city's patron saint. The early 16th-
century artist Nikola Bozidarevic
portrayed St. Vlaho holding a model of
Dubrovnik in painting (above) which
forms part of a triptych in the city's
Dominican church.
marked a turning point in the history of the
Serbian state and of the entire Slav world.
It opened up a new channel of communica¬
tion along which different traditions could
flow and be exchanged. This fruitful
alliance with Dubrovnik, a child of Western
civilization, would open for the Slavs a
gateway to European culture.
Medieval chronicles recount how certain
Serbian dignitaries persistently urged
Dusan to attack and conquer Dubrovnik
and how he categorically refused, prefer¬
ring instead to confirm the city's centuries-
old freedoms and to shower lavish gifts on
its churches and monasteries. Rather than
trample on the banner of St. Vlaho, protec¬
tor of the city, he would send young Slavs
to Dubrovnik for their education. Contem¬
porary writers report him as saying: "I res¬
pect the Senate of Dubrovnik for its signal
virtues. Through its Latin erudition, its
wealth and its trade, Dubrovnik is a fitting
model for the edification and the prosper¬
ity of my reign; this fine city will be the
trading centre of all the territories of my
realm."
In more recent centuries Dubrovnik also
had to pay a high price for its freedom.
When it came under Napoleon's domina¬
tion in 1806, and two years later ceased to
exist as a free republic, the city fathers
fomented a plot without parallel in history.
As a gesture of protest and as a means of
ensuring that no descendants of theirs
should ever bé subjected to foreign rule,
the families of Dubrovnik vowed not to
procreate until they were free once more.
From that moment until the liberation of
the city in 1815 no child was born to the
nobility of Dubrovnik.
In a long history stretching over twelve
centuries, Dubrovnik has never spared any
effort to preserve its freedom. This passion
for independence may be partly due to the
fact that the city's geographical position
makes it a point at which world cul¬
tural trends and influences converge. But
this is only part of the story. Dubrovnik has
succeeded in resisting threats and dangers
from East and West because of its links
with what is today Croatia, a hinterland
from which it has drawn linguistic and cul¬
tural sustenance. The Renaissance saw a
great flowering of Croatian literature in
Dubrovnik whose lasting achievements in
poetry and the dramatic arts are just as
important as the city's architectural master¬
pieces. By drawing life from the Croatian
artistic genius, Dubrovnik brought Croatia
into the great movement which was the
Renaissance in the West.
Travellers of the past penned ecstatic
descriptions of their first glimpse of
Dubrovnik from the sea. "An enchanting
picture opens out before your eyes", wrote
one of them. "The islands are deployed like
ships right as far as the port of Dubrovnik.
Your boat glides over the calm sea- and
rounds the lighthouse; it is as if you were
entering wonderland..."
Today the spell is still unbroken. The
modern traveller is transported into the
past as he approaches Dubrovnik's marble
and granite monuments eternally caressed
by the sun.
The city's long main street, the Stradun,
runs along a valley which was formely a
marshy channel dividing the Latin settle¬
ment from the Slav colony. Seven hundred
years ago the channel was filled in and
became a thoroughfare along which Latins
and Slavs would live together forever.
The people of Dubrovnik remain proud
of their city and its cosmopolitan traditions.
Walk along the Stradun today, especially in
the summer months, and you will hear
dozens of different languages being spo¬
ken. With its beautiful palaces, fountains
and churches, Dubrovnik has remained
faithful to its past. Each summer its music
and drama festivals attract great perfor¬
mers from all over the world, further
evidence that the cosmopolitan spirit still
lives on. The Slavs in our time the
Yugoslavs have preserved this gateway
to the Mediterranean. This city on the
shores of a sea which cradled more than
one civilization, continues to be a focus for
the exchange of traditions. Here where the
history of Europe began it continues to be
made and enriched.
Vuk Vuco
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
The Nikolo-Karelsky monastery, built in the 16th century on the
shores of the White Sea (where the town of Severodvinsk now
stands) was fortified in 1692 with the addition of a wooden
octagonal tower (right), a stockade and watchtowers. In 1932
part of this outstanding example of Russian fort architecture was
transported to the Kolomenskoye Museum in Moscow.
Eighteenth-century wooden carving of the sun (below) once
adorned the mast of a Russian river-boat. Opposite page, a sirin
or bird-woman. Her wings protectively unfolded, this guardian
spirit of the household kept watch over the window of an isba
(log hut) of ancient Russia. Unesco, in collaboration with the
International Association for the Study and Dissemination of Slav
Cultures, is currently preparing an illustrated book on the history
of Slav wooden architecture and sculpture. Specialists from
Byelorussia, Bulgaria, Poland, Russia, Czechoslovakia, the
Ukraine and Yugoslavia are participating in the project, headed
by Professor Andrej Ryszkiewicz of Poland.
Workmanship
in wood
AMONG the tools and instruments of daily life in the coun¬
tryside of old Russia, the distaff, not surprisingly, held a
prominent place; for many months of the year it was the
country woman's constant companion.
Bridegrooms gave distaffs and spinning-benches as wedding-
presents to their brides, and for this reason, their carved decora¬
tions frequently depicted scenes related to the marriage ceremony:
the journey of the groom to the bride's house, the couple's first
encounter, their rendezvous and walks together. A brand-new
spinning-bench distinguished the newly-married woman from her w
friends when they spent the long autumn and winter evenings f
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
L together, while particularly beautiful specimens were handed
down by the womenfolk from generation to generation.
In the Kalinin region of the U.S.S.R., archaeologists have disco¬
vered a perfectly preserved distaff dating from the second millen¬
nium B.C., which closely resembles nineteenth-century models in
shape.
Both the form and the decoration of the distaff enable us to
identify its place of origin. Thus, the craftsmen of the Vologod-
skaya region preferred ornamentation in the form of large-scale
geometrical figures circles, triangles or zigzag lines.
The painters of Mezen, using simple brush-strokes of black on a
brown background, sketched galloping horses and deer and
soaring flights of birds; those of the Lake Onega region preferred
to portray luxurious flowers and bouquets in a setting of brilliantly
contrasting colours. The distaffs painted by the descendants of the
ancient Novgorodians, the village painters of the basin of the
Severnaya Dvina, are highly distinctive; their decoration is a verita¬
ble pageant of colours, with a variety of themes depicting fantastic '
animals and birds, as well as exotic plants.
Wood was used not only for the construction of dwellings and
outbuildings, but also for sacred images, churches, boats and
domestic furniture. Master wood-carvers produced kitchen uten¬
sils and children's toys, together with decorations for their isbas
(cottages) and the mastheads of their boats.
One of the most curious and widely distributed examples of
domestic wood-carving in the Volga region is the bereginya,
whose name indicates that its purpose was to protect (oberegat)
the person or object with which it was connected. It would appear
that such images, in their earliest form, were in the shape of
rusa/ki, or water-nymphs, and were part of the carved decoration
of boats; indeed, objects of this type are still known as
korabel'naya rez'ba, or "boat-carvings". Their origins lie in the dis¬
tant ages when people invoked the protection of a benevolent
deity against evil spirits as they set off on journeys by water. Far¬
ther north protection was provided by the okh/upen', a huge larch
log which was fixed to the roof of the cottage. The roots were left
The wooden figurine (top) is a household spirit or
domovoi (from the Russian word dorn, meaning house).
Carved by a 14th-century craftsman, it was discovered
during excavations at Novgorod (U.S.S.R). Above,
"Original Sin", detail from a baroque iconostasis (the
icon-adorned screen which separates the sanctuary
from the nave in eastern Christian churches of
By7antine tradition) in the church of St. Marina in
Plovdiv (Bulgaria). Right, sculpture evoking fertility
is by a modern Bulgarian artist, Anton Doncev.
48
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
attached and shaped into a somewhat fanciful outline of a horse, a
duck or a deer.
Originally revered as sacred animals, these objects acquired over
the ages such perfect form that long after people had forgotten
their function as protective symbols, they continued to be incorpo¬
rated as essential decorative features of wooden buildings. In the
Russian North, villages containing huts decorated in this manner
may still be found today, whilst in some places the okhlupni from
old buildings are incorporated in new constructions.
The bird of paradise, or Sirin, was another decorative element of
peasant houses, and carried across the centuries the echoes of the
old pagan beliefs of the northern countryfolk. Another creature of
fairy-tale and myth'was the lion, which clasped in its jaws the end
of its own long tail. If its head was at times more like that of a dog
than a lion, we must remember that the old village wood-carvers
had never seen such exotic animals, and had to rely on their own
imagination in portraying them.
Door frames and window frames also reflected the
wood-carver's concern to decorate the ¡spa, and resembled the old
Russian napkins with lacy fringes which were traditionally used to
decorate icons or portraits.
Popular imagination also found quaint expression in the bee¬
hives carved out of tree-trunks, in the form, for example, of a bear
whose paw concealed the opening from which the honey was
drawn, or decorated in relief with the figure of a woman whose
eyes and mouth served as entrances for the bees.
Hollow vessels in the shape of ducks were carved from tree
roots to hold alcoholic beverages. In northern villages, carved
wooden "birds of goodness" were hung beneath the rafters of
huts, over the large table with benches along the wall which served
to receive guests in the "prettiest" corner of the hut. In the rising
cloud of warm steam from the samovar, the "bird of goodness"
rotated smoothly and solemnly as if surveying the cottage, in
which dead wood had sprung to new life under the village crafts¬
man's hand.
A dobraya (literally "she who is good") or
bird of goodness. Such small masterpieces of
the woodcarver's art were found in homes
throughout the Slav world. Suspended from
the rafters, they gyrated slowly in the heat
rising from the samovar.
A traditional wedding present from
bridegroom to bride, the distaff was
both a symbol of domestic life and an
indispensable piece of household
equipment. Slav craftsmen excelled at
fashioning highly elaborate distaffs and
spinning-benches adorned with carvings,
giltwork, polychrome decoration and
pokerwork depicting scenes related to
marriage and the home. The founding of
a home and a family is evoked in 19th-
century example (above): husband and
wife bring together trunk and branches
to form a fruitful family tree.
A bear serves as the handle of this wooden utensil
from Byelorussia, once used for "ironing" linen.
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
Photo © APN, Moscow
An open-air museum of religious
and secular architecture has been
established on Kiji, one of the many
islands that dot Lake Onega in
Karelia. Photo shows some of the
22 cupolas surmounting the Church
of the Transfiguration, the most
remarkable edifice on the island.
Not a single nail was used by the
anonymous carpenters who built
the church in 1714.
50
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
Fretwork patterns on the wall of an isba
(cottage) at Vologda, some 300 km from
Moscow, evoke the lace fringes of
napkins traditionally used to decorate
icons.
Some country churches, such as this
little 19th-century chapel in Poland,
were simple wooden structures topped
by a cupola and a bell-tower.
Below, the Church of St. Paraskeva
(who was the personification of Good
Friday) in the village of Alexandrovka
is a typical example of eighteenth
century religious architecture in
southern Ukraine.
Left, wooden windmill
constructed at the
beginning of the 20th
century in the Kharkov
region of the Ukraine has
been transported to the
Museum of Popular Art and
Traditions at Kiev
(U.S.S.R). Below, anatomy
of the interior of a windmill
near Mogilev in
Byelorussia.
î
51
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
Hives of good
humour
Examples of wooden bee-hives which Slav
craftsmen carved to represent animal and
human forms which were by turns
humorous, dramatic and caricatural. The
bees came and went through the holes
pierced in the chest of the Russian bear,
through the poignantly dilated eyes of the
Byelorussian woman and through the
navel of the bearded Polish hermit whose
skull cap could be lifted when it was time
to extract the honey. Other hives take the
form of a Slovak couple, a pipe-smoking
patriarch from Yugoslavia, and two
betrothed lovers from Poland.
Poland Poland
Russia
Byelorussia Czechoslovakia
Yugoslavia
52
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
Three expressive pieces of religious sculpture in wood from three
parts of the Slav world. Right, King David, prophet, poet and
musician, as depicted by an 18th-century sculptor of Smolensk in
Russia. Below, portrait of the Apostle Peter sculpted by a 19th-
century village craftsman from Gorodishche in the Brest-Litovsk
region of Byelorussia. Below right, St. John of Nepomuk, an
ecclesiastic of 14th-century Bohemia who died rather than betray
the secrets of the confessional. He is here depicted by a 19th-
century Polish wood-carver from the Limanova region.
53
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
The Bohemian religious reformer
Jan Hus (1369-1415) and Martin
Luther (1483-1546), the leader of
the Protestant Reformation in
Germany, pictured (symbolically
but anachronistically) serving
communion together in a 16th-
century woodcut by the great
German artist Lucas Cranach.
THE COMMON HERITAGE
A cultural community stretching from the Baltic to the Black Sea
by Slavomir Vollman
TIE non-Slav peoples became aware
of the existence of the Slavs as an
entity during the first eight centu¬
ries A.D., recognizing the relative unifor¬
mity of their spoken language and of their
cultural, social and ethnic characteristics.
Indeed, they painted colourful pictures of
SLAVOMIR VOLLMAN, Czech specialist in
comparative Slavic literature, is deputy director
of the Institute of Czech and World Literature of
the Czechoslovak Academy of Sciences and
head of the Institute's department of Slavic and
Comparative Literature. Vice-President of the
International Association for the Study and Dis¬
semination of Slav Cultures, he is deputy editor
of Slavia (Review of Slavic Philology) and a
member of the International Committee of
Slavists. He taught at the University of California
at Los Angeles in 1968-69 and is currently a
member of the department of Czech and Slovak
literature at Charles University, Prague.
this group of Indo-European tribes at a time
when the Slavs themselves, who had
spread out in a massive and powerful
movement of expansion over a vast area
stretching from the west bank of the Elbe
to the Volga, from Rügen on the Baltic to
the Péloponnèse and from northern Italy to
Syria, had neither a written language nor
any of the other means of communication
with each other to sustain their self-
awareness and their sense of unity.
The ancient Slavs undoubtedly referred
to themselves as Slovene, and this was the
name given to them by Latin, Greek and
German writers, from the sixth-century his¬
torians Pseudo-Caesarius, Procopius and
Jordanes onwards. The earliest Arab tra¬
vellers who came into contact with the
Slavs as they stepped on to the pages of
written history agreed with these authors
that they were tall, shapely and fair-haired.
The "national identity" of the Slavs
preoccupied all those who wrote about
them. The Byzantine historian Procopius
said that "they are not subjected to the
authority of a single leader, but have lived
from ancient times under a democracy;
consequently, everything involving their
welfare, whether for good or ill, is referred
to the people". Other sources mention
their warlike character and virile courage.
In the early Middle Ages, when the Slavs
began to behave in a manner that was
already common in the "civilized" (i.e.
Latin) West, their adversaries complained
that they were cruel and ferocious.
Thus, from a very early date, the non-
Slav world had its preconceived notions
about "Slav unity", "Slav character" and
even about the "Slav soul", notions that
were full of contradictions and frequent
flights of fantasy, that blended fact with
54
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
fiction and formed part of a complex "East-
West" mythology.
At times the Slavs adopted the charact¬
eristics attributed to them by foreigners,
when these coincided with their own feel¬
ings and experiences. Consciousness of
their common origin and linguistic affinity,
and awareness that they shared the same
historical destiny are reflected in their ear¬
liest written literature, and appear in diffe¬
rent forms throughout the whole of their
history. At the same time, however, there
began in the early Middle Ages the process
of formation, transformation and "crystalli¬
zation" of individual Slav peoples without
which their subsequent interrelationships
in the cultural, political and other fields
could not have developed. This contradic¬
tory process, of integration on the one
hand and differentiation on the other, was
to leave a profound imprint on the develop¬
ment of their cultural relations from the
"ninth to the nineteenth century, when it
became a subject of scientific study.
In 1826, in the Hungarian city of Buda,
Pavel Jozef Safarik published the first
serious attempt to present an overall view
of the development of Slav culture, under
the title Geschichte der Slawischen Spra¬
che und Literatur nach allen Mundarten
(History of Slav Literature and Language in
all its Dialects). The theme and conception
of this work, its language and its place and
date of publication, together with the per¬
sonality of the author himself, constitute a
striking example of relations between the
Slavs and the social and historical circum¬
stances in which these relations evolved.
Safarik has a rightful place in the history
both of Czech and of Slovak culture and
literature. A Slovak by birth, and in his
youth a poet in that language, he became a
teacher in the Serbian high school at Novi
Sad, capital of one of the provinces of the
Hapsburg Empire. He was also a Czech
scholar, and did not altogether favour the
movement for the creation of a specific
Slovak literary language, which reflected
the nationalist aspirations of Slovakia at the
time and which led to a rupture in the old
Czech-Slovak linguistic and cultural com¬
munity.
Safarik was neither an exception in his
age, nor in Slav cultural history as a whole.
Cultural relations between the Slavs have
always been influenced to an important
extent by the action of such bilingual fig¬
ures who wrote in two languages. The
Greek brothers Cyril and Methodius who,
according to their biographers, were fluent
speakers of the Slavonic tongue, used their
knowledge of the dialect spoken by the
Slav population of their native Thessalo-
nica to lay the foundations of the first Sla¬
vonic written language, created in Great
Moravia; they were also the authors of the
earliest Slav literature which their Moravian
disciples carried with them to the lands of
the South Slavs, who participated enthu¬
siastically in this further development. In
their turn, and right up to the sixteenth
century, hundreds of South Slavs settled in
Russia, and contributed to the literary and
cultural development of the East Slavs. The
late tenth-century Archbishop of Prague,
Voytech (Saint Adalbert), was a Czech
who became one of the patron saints of
Poland; the writer and humanist Bartolemy
Paprocky, born in Poland, earned a niche
for himself in the history of Czech culture.
These are only two among many examples
of the dual attachments which character¬
ized Czech-Polish cultural relations from
the early Middle Ages to the Renaissance
and beyond.
In the seventeenth century, this tradition
was continued by Jan Amos Komensky
(Comenius), leader of the old Protestant
church of the Moravian and Bohemian
Brethren, who were expelled from their
homeland by the agents of the Counter-
Reformation and who settled in the Polish
city of Leszno.
As an example of Ukrainian-Serbian
"biliteral" relations, we may mention Ema-
nuil Kozaóinski: graduate of a seminary in
Kiev, he became the founder of the Slav-
Serbian theatre during the first half of the
eighteenth century.
In addition to these and other well-
known figures whose names have come
down to us through history, there were, of
course, a great number of anonymous
intermediaries who took advantage of the
similarity of language and the relative ease
of assimilation in Slav countries other than
their own. These included an uninterrupted
flow of jesters, jugglers, singers and other
"Wandering players", humble people for
the most part, who, long before the Slav
nations emerged as modern States and
long before Safarik, contributed to what
the latter's friend the Czech-speaking Slo¬
vak poet Jan Kollar (another example of
Czech-Slovak dual attachment) called the
Vzaimnost or "togetherness" of the .Slavs.
It is also worth noting that Safarik's His¬
tory was published in the Hungarian capi¬
tal, which was at the time an important
centre not only of Hungarian nationalism,
but also of the movement for national
resurgence of the Slavs. Besides Buda,
other non-Slav cities where cultural reía- l
tions between the Slavs themselves deve- 1
The great Czech
educational reformer and
Protestant leader John
Comenius was born in
eastern Moravia in 1592.
Forced into exile by the
persecution of the Catholic
Emperor Ferdinand II, he
settled at Leszno, Poland, in
1628. His fame spread with
the publication of treatises
advocating full-time
schooling and new
teaching methods and he
was invited to England,
Sweden and Hungary to
advise on educational
matters. In 1652, Leszno
was occupied and
destroyed, but Comenius
escaped to Amsterdam
where he remained until his
death in 1670. Photos: (1)
Comenius, detail of an
engraving by David Loggan
which formed the title page
of a collection of his
writings on education
entitled "Didáctica Opera
Omnia". (2) Comenius
advocated separate schools
adapted to meet the
requirements of the
different stages of a child's
development. (3) Engraving
at the head of a chapter of
his "Orbis Sensualium
Pictus" (The Visible World
in Pictures), the forerunner
of the illustrated school
book, depicts the various
branches of man's
intellectual activity.
55
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
> loped included Vienna, Leipzig, Dresden,
Cluj in Romania, Venice and, later, Istam-
bul and Paris.
These relations, moreover, rapidly ac¬
quired a European dimension, and became
an integral component of cultural ex¬
change and development throughout the
world. Safarik, whose mastery of his native
language was outstanding, deliberately
wrote his History in German so that it
might be of greater service in Slav and non-
Slav cultural circles alike, and to the
younger generation in particular.
The fact that translations and adapta¬
tions of Safarik's work were published in
western Europe and America reflect its
great relevance to the issues of the time.
The concepts of a "world literature"
enounced a year later by Goethe had the
same objective: to set the creativity of his
people in a universal cultural context at a
time when, following the French Revolu¬
tion and the establishment of the modern
nations as fully-fledged actors on the stage
of human affairs, the world was entering a
new phase of development.
The movement which led to the emanci¬
pation of the Slavs, to their formation, self-
determination or resurgence as nations
freed from the feudalists "prison-houses"
of the Ottoman, Tsarist and Hapsburg
empires, and to their mutual collaboration,
found support in the ideas of the German
philosopher Johann Gottfried Herder, who
predicted a glorious future for the Slavs.
But the feeling of affinity of the Slav peo¬
ples, their conviction of the significance of
their own languages and cultures, in¬
cluding popular Slav culture, and aware-
Founded by St. John of
Rila in the early 10th
century, the Monastery of
Rila stands on the
southern slopes of the
Rila Mountain in south¬
western Bulgaria. The
imposing medieval tower
is all that is left of the
buildings erected in 1335
by the feudal overlord
Prince Hreljo. Over the
centuries the monastery
was destroyed and rebuilt
several times. Most of the
present buildings were
erected in the first half of
the 19th century,
following a disastrous fire
in 1833, and constitute a
fine example of the
architecture of the
"National Revival" period
in Bulgaria. Throughout
its chequered history, the
monastery has maintained
its high reputation as an
important centre of
European culture.
ness of the necessity to co-operate with
each other in the struggle for national and
social freedom, were founded on a thou¬
sand years of experience. Had not the
Saxon historian Widikund written of the
Slavs, as early as 967 A.D. that there was
no suffering they would not bear for the
sake of their beloved liberty (omnem mise-
riam carae libertatis postponendes)...
This steadfast attachment to freedom
was growing from strength to strength at
precisely the moment when Herder was
ascribing a "dove-like" nature to the Slavs.
And if Kollar, during the difficult period of
the Holy Alliance, spoke of the Slav cul¬
tural community as being as harmless as "a
gentle ewe-lamb in the life of the peoples",
he probably did not share Herder's point of
view. After all, the advocates of Vzaimnost
were also freedom-fighters, and the strug¬
gle for liberty which had begun with the
peasant risings of the eighteenth century
bore clear signs of mutual collaboration
between the Slavs.
Poles are known to have participated in
the storm of revolt that swept over east and
south-east Russia in 1773 under the lead¬
ership of the Cossack Emel'yan Pugachev.
Pushkin's reference to this fact after the
suppression of the Decembrist Revolt in
Russia in 1825 and the Polish Rising in
1830-1831 (two of the most important
rebellions against the same Tsarist tyranny)
was highly apposite; his words conceal
allusions to the clandestine democratic
movements which existed at the time in
Russia, the Ukraine and Poland, and which
were preparing programmes for the libera¬
tion of the Slavs. One of these movements
was even called the Obshchestvo soyedi-
nennykh slavyan (the Society of United
Slavs).
If the ideas and example of the French
Revolution conserved their significance
during the period of triumph of the Euro¬
pean anciens régimes, it should be pointed
out that in the Slav countries the seeds of
freedom fell on soil already prepared by
earlier generations. Already in 1775 seven
thousand Czech peasants in the eastern
part of the country had risen in armed
revolt, with a rallying-cry of "Freedom or
Death!" thus anticipating later events in
France.
In 1824, as punishment for having
belonged to a secret society of students in
Vilno, the young Polish poet Adam Mickie¬
wicz was exiled to Russia. The Tsarist
authorities hoped thus to neutralize this
militant member of the Polish national libe¬
ration movement and, if possible, to con¬
vert him to the imperial reason of the
Romanovs. In fact, this short-sighted act
on the part of the tyrants facilitated his
contacts with the Decembrist rebels and all
who shared their views, and created the
conditions for the friendly intimacy and
creative collaboration that characterized
the association between the two greatest
Slav poets of their ageAdam Mickiewicz
and Alexander Pushkin.
Pushkin and Mickiewicz undoubtedly
reinforced each other's views concerning
the importance of the poetry of the people
in the new and genuinely national literature
that they were creating. This is reflected in
the former's Songs of the South Slavs, and
in Mickiewicz's Forefather's Eve and Pan
Tadeusz.
Interest in folklore, its collection, and the
re-working of popular themes had begun
during the second half of the fifteenth cen¬
tury, when the Hungarian poet Janus Pan-
nonius creatively transposed into Latin
verse the picturesqueness of Croatian
CONTINUED PAGE 72
Colour page
Slav art has many facots, from portraits of
cossacks and courtiers to the churchman's
cap fashioned with masterly precision. The
cossack, a favourite theme in Ukrainian art,
is here depicted by an anonymous 19th
century painter. He is playing a bandore, a
stringed instrument still used in the Orient
and in some Slav countries. Top left, detail of
the coffer ceiling of the Deputies' Hall in the
Wawel Castle, Cracow (Poland). The Castle,
whose origins go back to the early Middle
Ages, was rebuilt between 1507 and 1536 by
Italian and Polish craftsmen whose
collaboration resulted in a highly original
blend of Polish and Italian art. Carved by
local Polish artists, the wooden heads in each
panel of the ceiling form a gallery of symbolic
studies and realistic portraits of court
personalities. Top right, a gilded mitre
produced by Muscovite jewellers in 1685. It
was given to the Metropolitan of Kiev,
Gedeon Sviatopolk, by Tsars Ivan V and Peter
I (then ruling jointly) and the Tsarina Sophia.
56
]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[
m otiraè miß untgaHumen nue um
]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[
Dialogue
with the West
A fruitful interplay of ideas and talent
by Igor F. Belza
IGOR F. BELZA, Soviet musicologist, com¬
poser and specialist on Slav cultures, teaches at
the Institute of Slav and Balkan Studies of the
U.S.S.R. Academy of Sciences. Editor-in-chief
of the Moscow review Readings in Dante, he is
the author of many articles on Slav cultures.
THE Curies, Polish scientist Maria
Sklodowska and her French
husband Pierre Curie, who played a
major role in the discovery of radioactivity
at the turn of the century, constitute
perhaps the most striking, and romantic,
example of the interplay of scientific and
cultural ideas between the Slavs and the
West. Yet this "marriage of minds" bet¬
ween Slav scientists and artists and their
Western counterparts had begun long
before. During the eighteenth century,
Mikhail Lomonosov (1711-1765) in Russia
and Antoine Lavoisier (1743-1794) in
France each discovered independently the I
law of conservation of mass. W
The Sorbs, or Wends, of Lusatia (Lausitz) are the descendants of a Slavic people who
settled in the 9th century in the Elbe valley between present day Dresden and Cottbus in
the German Democratic Republic. Some 100,000 Sorbs still live in this area, maintaining
their cultural and linguistic traditions. Below, Sorbian women in traditional costume.
Opposite page
One of the most important of the Slav
manuscripts that remain from the
Middle Bulgarian period (13th to 14th
century) is the Tsar Ivan Aleksandur
Gospel (or London Gospel), copied by
the monk Simeon, in 1356, for the
"Tsar of all the Bulgars and the
Greeks", and now preserved in the
British Museum. The miniature
reproduced here (top half of page)
portrays the Last Judgement. The
artist has included a portrait of Tsar
Ivan Aleksandur who is seen standing
beside the Virgin Mary at the bottom
left of the miniature. Bottom right of
page, a pastoral scene from the Liber
Viaticus, a 14th-century manuscript
now in the National Museum of
Prague. Bottom left, Satan dressed as
a monk; a miniature from the Codex of
Jena, a ferociously satirical illuminated
manuscript dating from the end of the
15th century in which Hussite
reformers attacked the hierarchy of the
Church.
© '
59
]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[
Voltaire by Pushkin
Pushkin wrote of Voltaire that his every
line was a precious gift to posterity. Like
the children of most aristocratic families
of the day, Pushkin learned to speak and
read French at an early age.
Pushkin by Pushkin
One of over sixty self-portraits by the
great Russian poet, this sketch shows
how Pushkin visualized himself in old age,
which, ironically, he was never to attain.
60
'He sang of love,
to love subjected'
(Eugene Onegin)
"He was the beginning of all beginnings",
wrote Dostoevsky of Alexander Pushkin,
the first in a line of towering figures in
Russian literature. His was a brief but
tumultuous life. "I have to spend much
time in society," he wrote. "My wife is a
woman of fashion, and it all requires
money; but I can only acquire money
through work, and work means solitude."
Below, a painting of his wife Natalya. It
was in defending her honour that, in 1837,
he was mortally wounded in a duel.
Mickiewicz by Pushkin
Generally considered the greatest poet of
Poland, Mickiewicz met Pushkin in
Moscow in 1826. Both these great
Romantic writers were strongly influenced
by the English poet Byron.
]]>
</page>
<page number="61">
<![CDATA[
h The same intermingling of Slav and Wes¬
tern names is found in the history of philo¬
sophy. Among the contemporaries of René
Descartes, the father of rationalist philo¬
sophy, were the "Polish Brethren", hun¬
dreds of whose works (especially those of
Simon Budny and Wolcogen) were pub¬
lished in Amsterdam in 1656 under the gen¬
eral title Bibliotheca Fratrum Polonorum.
The work of these writers was of great
importance to the seventeenth-century
Dutch philosopher Spinoza .(especially in
the elaboration of his Ethics) and also
influenced the English philosopher John
Locke, whose studies in their turn con¬
tributed to the development of French
materialist philosophy.
Mickiewicz by Delacroix
Mickiewicz settled in Paris in 1832 and
later taught Slavonic literature at the
Collège de France. His friendship with
Chopin drew him into the coterie that
formed around George Sand and which
included Delacroix.
Another contemporary of the Polish
Brethren was the great Czech educationist
and "teacher of the people", Jan Amos
Komensky (Comenius), whose Didactics
was well known in both Slav and Western
countries. He believed that the principles of
humanism should be assimilated at an early
age, and devised a harmonious, all-
embracing system of education. Echoes of
his teachings can be found in the ideas and
methods of the famous Swiss educational
reformer Pestalozzi.
Investigation of the cultural history of
the Slav peoples has drawn attention to a
number of remarkable figures who were
half-hidden in the shadows of the ages.
One example is the educationist Gyorgi-
Franciszek Skorina, Byelorussia's first prin¬
ter, who acquired wide learning during his
travels in the West. Another is the
eighteenth-century Ukrainian Grigori Sko¬
voroda, poet and self-styled "wandering
philosopher". The names of Skorina and
Skovoroda are today inscribed in the his¬
tory of European humanism.
Slav thinkers (including historians, wri-
line... played some pieces by Chopin.
Nothing banal, perfect composition! What
could be more complete? He resembles
Mozart more than anyone else. Like
Mozart's, his themes occur so sponta¬
neously, one might have thought of them
oneself."
Later he compared Chopin to Dante, and
portrayed him as "the greatest of poets"
("altissimo poeta"), both in his decoration
of the ceiling of the library of the Senate in
Paris, and in a drawing inscribed "Cher
Chopin" which was probably made shortly
after his friend's death.
There is an undeniable similarity between
the ideas and aspirations of the two mas¬
ters. Many of Delacroix's paintings, inclu¬
ding Dante and Virgil Crossing the Styx,
.The Massacre at Chios, Liberty Guiding the
People, and Greece Expiring on the Ruins
of Missolonghi, reflect a romantic percep¬
tion of nature and a violent denunciation of
evil and injustice.
In Chopin's sonatas, his ballades, his
fantasias and many of his preludes and stu¬
dies, Delacroix heard not only a Dantesque
Chopin
by Delacroix
Delacroix was a fervent
admirer as well as an
intimate friend of Chopin.
In this sketch, made
probably just after the
Polish composer's death,
he depicts Chopin in the
guise of Dante, the
"altissimo poeta". The
sketch bears Delacroix's
touching inscription
"Cher Chopin" (dear
Chopin).
V
ters and artists, as well as philosophers)
have always been profoundly attracted by
moral and ethical issues, and it is in this
field that the West has been most receptive
to the artistic and intellectual values cre¬
ated by the Slavs. Nowhere is this more
strikingly revealed than in the creative rela¬
tionship and warm friendship that united
the French painter Delacroix and the Polish
musician Chopin. Delacroix met many wri¬
ters, artists and musicians during his life
and was on close terms with a number of
them. None, however, impressed him more
than Chopin. During the composer's last
years, Delacroix frequently visited "this
great man who is dying". A few months
after Chopin's death, he wrote in his Jour-
naf for 13 February 1850: "Princess Marcel-
"outcry of anger", but also an incessant
call to combat.
Masterpieces of Western literature have
had a great influence on Slav writers. Wri¬
ting of the summits of literary achievement,
Pushkin set the works of Goethe on the
same high level as those of Dante, Shakes¬
peare and Milton. The Faustian theme of a
passionate search for the absolute on earth
has received highly original treatment in the
works of some Slav writers. In one curious
example, Mikhail Bulgakov's posthumously
published novel The Master and Margue¬
rite, the Faust theme is actually turned
upside down, thus prompting one critic to
dub it an "Anti-Faust".
The names of Gustave Flaubert and Ivan r
61
]]>
</page>
<page number="62">
<![CDATA[
FJr^í'q*
All
the world's
a stage
St. Petersburg became a
world centre of ballet in the
19th century and produced
some of the greatest ballet
dancers of all time,
including Anna Pavlova and
Vaslav Nijinsky. The
tradition is maintained
today by the world
renowned Kirov Ballet.
Left, extracts from the
score of Stravinsky's "The
Rite of Spring" with
notations of the
choreography created by
Nijinsky for Sergey
Diaghilev's Ballet Russes.
They were sketched in 1913
by the French painter and
stage designer Valentine
Hugo.
t mM *» '111
> Turgenev are in many ways symbolic of the
creative union and mutual enrichment of
Western and Slav literature. Turgenev's
translation of Flaubert's Légende de Saint
Julien l'Hospitalier is an outstanding exam¬
ple of the truth of Stendhal's dictum that
affection for a writer's work is a prerequi¬
site to successful translation.
Hundreds of characters from the
"human comedy" throng the pages of
Gogol, Turgenev, Dostoevsky and Chek¬
hov. Despite the specifically Russian
aspects of their experiences, feelings and
tragedies, they form part of the heritage of
all mankind, along with the angry protests
and satirical denunciations of social injus¬
tice, which reach the heights of intensity in
Gogol's Dead Souls and The Government
Inspector.
"I am sending you a morsel of contra¬
band", wrote the Austrian Ambassador to
Russia, Count Finkelmon, to Pushkin. The
contraband in question was a new novel by
Balzac, whose works had been banned by
Tsar Nicholas I. And in 1850, the Czech
educator Vaclav Bendl warmly observed in
the Journal of the Czech Museum that the
name of Pushkin had become a symbol of
all who refused subjection.
In a conversation with the author of this
article, a group of English specialists once
declared that Chekhov's dramatic works
marked the most significant development
in the history of world theatre since
Shakespeare. Their view was that the Rus¬
sian dramatist had invented the "non-star"
principle by breaking with the tradition
whereby one central figure overshadows all
the others. The judicious choice of a "star"
to play Hamlet was enough, they said, to
guarantee a successful performance of the
play. But neither in The Cherry Orchard,
nor in The Three Sisters, nor even in 77?e
Seagull is there such a central figure in the
generally accepted sense of the term; what
is developed is a system of interrelated
characters.
There is no need to dwell on the recogni¬
tion which the classics of Russian and
Polish literature have attained in the West,
nor on the reception accorded in the Slav
countries to Italian, French, English, Ger¬
man, Spanish and Scandinavian master-,
pieces. It is worth mentioning, however,
that it was not merely the artistic power of
Above, Olga Knipper Chekhova in the role
of Pernelle in Molière's "Tartuffe". She
was a member of the company of the
Academic Art Theatre of Moscow and
married the great Russian author Anton
Chekhov in 1901 after appearing in several
of his plays.
Left, Shakespeare as seen through the
eyes of the great Russian director Georgei
Tovstonogov. Actresses of the Gorky
Drama Theatre, Leningrad, in a scene
from "Henry IV, Part 1".
62
]]>
</page>
<page number="63">
<![CDATA[
the great Slav writers that attracted the
great masters of Western literature, but
also the languages in which they wrote. In
his eulogy of Pushkin, Prosper Mérimée
observed that no European language, with
the exception of Latin, could render the
beauty and laconic expressiveness of the
Russian writer's poem Anchar ("The Upas
Tree"). To make his point, he went on to
translate part of the poem into the lan¬
guage of Virgil.
, In music, the cultural links between the
Slavs and the West, which became particu¬
larly solid and varied, were established at
an early date.
The works of Glinka, Borodin, Mus¬
sorgsky, Tchaikovsky, Rimsky-Korsakov,
Skriabin, Chopin, Szymanowski, Smetana,
Dvorak and Janacek are all part of the
established repertory of world music.
Both Glinka and Rimsky-Korsakov treat¬
ed Spanish themes, while the latter turned
to Ancient Rome for a scene in his opera
Sevilla. Szymanowski portrayed medieval
Sicily, while Dvorak included themes inspi¬
red by Longfellow's Hiawatha in his Ninth
Symphony ("From the New World").
Rachmaninov and Moszkowski were both
inspired by the poetry of Edgar Allan Poe.
It should also be said that Bach, and to
an even greater extent the four great Vien¬
nese composers Haydn, Mozart, Beetho¬
ven and Schubert introduced "Slavisms"
into their works. Beethoven's three "Razu-
movsky Quartets", commissioned by and
named after the Russian Ambassador in
Vienna, contain the melodies of popular
Russian songs. Haydn, who was born in
the Croatian village of Trstnik (re-baptised
Rohrau by the Hapsburg authorities), and
who may well have spoken Croatian as his
mother tongue in childhood, thought
highly of the popular music of the Slav
peoples. Mozart and other Viennese com¬
posers followed his example, and their
works contain creative adaptations of the
beautiful and profoundly emotional songs
and dances of the Czech, Slovak, Polish,
Ukrainian and other Slav populations of the
"patchwork monarchy" of the Hapsburgs.
A picturesque example of this interplay
of influences is to be found in the "pastoral
intermezzo" which Tchaikovsky incorpora¬
ted in his opera The Queen of Spades. The
composer, who wished to give a Mozartian
flavour to this section, borrowed a theme
from one of Mozart's piano concertos. But
Mozart himself had taken this theme from
the gentle melody of a traditional Czech
folk-song, Mela jsem holoubka ("I had a
dove").
The attraction of Slav music in the West
has persisted up to modern times. The
world is familiar with the brilliant orchestra¬
tion of Mussorgsky's Pictures at an Exhibi¬
tion, created by Ravel who, like his older
contemporary Debussy, warmly admired
the five Russian composers (Balakirev,
Borodin, Cui, Mussorgsky and Rimsky-
Korsakov) who were known as "the mighty
handful". This admiration was, and
remains, mutual, as may be seen from the
recent publication in Moscow of a multi-
volume edition of the works of Debussy
and Ravel, and of studies of these great
composers by Russian musicologists.
Igor F. Belza
An amusing example of the
Russian popular engravings
known as "lubok", this late
17th-century woodcut is a
satirical attack on Peter the
Great (1672-1725) by the
Raskolnik! (Old Believers) who
were fiercely opposed to his far-
reaching reforms which affected
every field of national life. He is
depicted as "the Cat of Kazan".
The neatly groomed whiskers
are a jibe at the Tsar's own
moustachios
Peter the Great's
'Window on the West'
Leningrad, the U.S.S.R.'s second city, lies on the
Baltic at the eastern end of the Gulf of Finland.
Founded in 1703 by Peter the Great as a "window on
the west", it was named St. Petersburg and became
Russia's capital from 1712 to 1918. Famed for its
wide boulevards, its palaces and public buildings,
the city is threaded by many branches of the Neva
delta and has countless bridges, most of them
crossing canals such as the Winter Canal (above).
The State Hermitage Museum, one of
some 50 museums in Leningrad, is world
famous for its masterpieces. Founded in
1764 by the Empress Catherine II as a
private gallery for the art she had
amassed, it was first opened to the public
in 1852. The Hermitage has rich collections
of Oriental art, notably that of the Central
Asian steppes, as well as masterpieces of
west European painting since the Middle
Ages and fine collections of drawings,
coins and medals. Above, visitors throng
the entrance to the Hermitage.
As part of his aims to westernize Russian
institutions and customs, Peter decreed
that beards should be shorn. Old Believers
and merchants who insisted on keeping
their beards had to pay a special tax. This
lubok showing a barber cutting off the
beard of an Old-Believer merchant may
have been printed with the Tsar's
permission.
63
]]>
</page>
<page number="64">
<![CDATA[
These two spheres side by side evoke
steps in the conquest of space from the
Middle Ages to the present day. Copper
Arab astrolabe (right) dating from 1054
was still being used at the Jagiellonian
University (Poland) when Copernicus was
a student there in the late 15th century.
Opposite page: the historic link-up of a
Soviet Soyuz-19 and a U.S. Apollo
spacecraft on 17 July 1975 is depicted in
this mock-up on permanent display in
Moscow. (See Unesco Courier, Jan. 1978).
From Copernicus to Korolev
A 500-year journey
into space
by Bogdan Suchodolsky
A cosmonaut circles the Earth in a
spacecraft. At a given moment, he
steps out of his seemingly fragile
vessel and walks among the stars. Such
images come easily to the modern mind,
now that space travel has become a fact.
But before Man took his first "walk" in
space, another long and arduous journey
of discovery was necessary, during which
thinkers puzzled out the laws of the uni¬
verse and technologists created the means
whereby the age-old dream of space travel
could come true.
To conquer the force of gravity, Man had
first to understand the world around him
and to multiply his own strength. For cen¬
turies scientists in many countries grappled
with the problem, interweaving hopes and
aspirations, and philosophical and poetic
reveries, with mathematical calculations.
Poland set off on this road to understan-
BOGDAN SUCHODOLSKY, Polish philoso¬
pher and historian of science, is a member of the
Praesidium of the Polish Academy of Sciences.
He is the author of several works on trends
in philosophy and on educational matters. His
article incorporates material prepared by the
Polish scientist Prof. W. Voisé.
64
]]>
</page>
<page number="65">
<![CDATA[
Photo I. Gavrilov © APN, moscow
ding during the Middle Ages and the
Renaissance. In the thirteenth century, the
philosopher Witelo developed a theory on
the nature of material reality, the principles
of mathematical reasoning, the analysis of
natural phenomena (especially human
physiology and psychology) and astro¬
nomy. His treatise on perspective, which is
the only part of his great work to have sur¬
vived, was transcribed many times during
the Middle Ages, and often reprinted
during the sixteenth century. Witelo's stu¬
dies on the properties of light, used by the
' German astronomer Johannes Kepler in his
own research at the turn of the sixteenth
and seventeenth centuries, were a mixture
of metaphysical speculation and physical
science. What he called lumen divinum (or
"divine light") was, he believed, the
original form of existence of nature,
and of man as capable of perceiving it.
Another Pole, Nicolas Copernicus, took
a decisive step along the road to the stars.
His daring heliocentric theory set the Sun
at the centre of the universe and at the
source of life. This theory is sometimes
mistakenly reduced to the idea that the
Earth is spinning through the universe. But
if Copernicus "set the Earth in Motion", he
also and this was the most important
thing "stopped the Sun in its tracks." He
not only rejected the traditional belief that
the Earth was the centre of the universe,
but spoke out against the school of
thought according to which, and on the
basis of evidence produced by the senses,
it was the Sun, and not the Earth, that
moved.
Copernicus had many disciples, in his
own country as well as elsewhere. In his
well-equipped private observatory, Jan
Helvelius (1611-1687) carried out many
complicated astronomical . observations,
and his Selenography (1647), a description
of the Moon's surface, illustrated with
splendid maps, made him famous through¬
out Europe. This treatise broke new
ground, and combined the expression of
mankind's nostalgic affection for Earth's
silvery satellite with detailed descriptions
based on meticulous research.
While Helvelius was devoting his atten¬
tion to deciphering the Moon's secrets,
another man, the engineer Kazimezh
Semenovich, was examining the possibili¬
ties of actually getting there. His treatise on
ballistics (1650) was translated into many
languages, and astonishingly enough con¬
tains proposals for a multi-stage rocket.
Helvelius's astronomical calculations and
Semenovich's intuitive technical conject¬
ures were to be brought together in a single
field of research and aspiration.
One of the leading popularizers of Coper-
nicus's teaching was Bishop John Wilkins,
the author of Mathematical! Magick (1648)
and of a number of other works, and a
founding member of the Royal Society in
England. Drawing inspiration from the
Polish astronomer's ideas, Wilkins posed a
problem raised by the discovery of other
worlds: the problem of interplanetary
flight.
Although he wrote that a winged con¬
struction, of some kind appeared to offer
the best means of effecting such journeys,
he himself, on the basis of his study of Gali¬
leo's mechanics in particular, favoured the
solution of a "flying chariot".
Another self-confessed disciple off
65
]]>
</page>
<page number="66">
<![CDATA[
Lomonosov (1711-1765), the great Russian
scientist and encyclopaedist, a member of
the Saint Petersburg Academy of Sciences
and the founder of Moscow University. His
research in chemistry and physics opened
the way to the corpuscular theory of mat¬
ter, while his philosophy, which was in
direct opposition both to the rationalism of
Descartes and the empiricism of Locke,
was an attempt to unseat the mechanistic
conception of the world.
Substantial progress was made in this
direction during the century that followed.
The "Copernicus of geometry", as the dis¬
tinguished Russian mathematician Nikolai
Lobachevsky (1792-1856) was called, was
one of the creators of non-Euclidian geo¬
metry. His system played an important role
in the development of modern science.
Not long after this began the career of
Konstantin Tsiolkovsky (1857-1935), the
Polish-born Russian scientist who was the
founder of modern astronautics. His work
entitled "The exploration of cosmic space
with the aid of jet-propelled engines",
published in 1903, set out for the first time
a theory of controlled flight under both gra¬
vitational and non-gravitational conditions,
and paved the way for the use of rockets
for interplanetary travel. In 1929, Tsiol¬
kovsky published a second, equally innova¬
tory work, "Cosmic rocket ships", which
laid the foundations for the first interplane¬
tary flights.
Tsiolkovsky's activity brought to a close
The great Polish astronomer Nicholas Copernicus (1473-1543) "set the
earth in motion" and "stopped the sun in its tracks" by disproving the
accepted theory, formulated in Antiquity by Ptolemy, that the earth
was the motionless centre of the universe. His theory of a heliocentric
system in which the earth was a moving planet laid the foundations for
later developments in astronomy. Above, Copernicus as depicted in a
17th-century engraving by Edme de Boulonois of Brussels.
Reaching
for the stars
Copernicus was the French poet Cyrano de
Bergerac (1619-1655) among whose works
was a science fiction novel, published pos¬
thumously, entitled "The States and Em¬
pires of the Sun". In this fantastic tale, the
narrator describes how, after a scientific
discussion with his friends, he returned
home disillusioned with reading dry-as-
dust learned treatises and determined to
find out for himself whether the Earth was
actually spinning through space, and whe¬
ther life existed in distant worlds. Inspired
by an original idea, he tied around himself a
number of flasks filled with dew, believing
that the dew would be transformed into
steam by the sun's rays, and would carry
him into the upper layers of the atmos¬
phere.
This section of the novel, like many
others, contains hypotheses whose fallacy
has long since been demonstrated; but this
in no way detracts from the work's signifi¬
cance. We should forgive Cyrano for his
errorsafter all, he lived in an age when
the theory of gravity was still in its
infancy and by acknowledging the exis¬
tence of innumerable other worlds, he
struck a blow against conservatism of
thought.
In the Slav countries, another step on
the road to the stars took place during the
eighteenth century. In western Europe
during this period progress in the natural
sciences was developing through the appli¬
cation of empirical and rationalistic
methods in certain specific fields. Among
the Slavs, however, these methods were
utilized not only for piecemeal research,
but also in an endeavour to create an inter¬
disciplinary synthesis, through which the
universe might be explained as a dynamic
entity. This was a complex vision of things,
the accuracy of which could only be par¬
tially established at the time and which"
consisted for the most part of bold hypo¬
theses which would only be verified in sub¬
sequent centuries.
Two outstanding personalities should be
mentioned at this point. The first was
Roudjer Boskovich (1711-1787), a Croatian
philosopher and scientist, whose work
reflected the theories of both Newton and
Leibniz and contained the seeds of future
theories of relativity and non-Euclidian geo¬
metry. Boskovich attempted to construct a
mathematical model of matter based on
dynamic rather than mechanistic concepts,
and prepared a draft outline of a philo¬
sophy of the universe which differed con¬
siderably from that which was generally
accepted at the time.
The second great figure was Mikhail
66
]]>
</page>
<page number="67">
<![CDATA[
the long "pre-space" era and turned a new
page which would be inscribed with the
story of Man's final realization of his
ancient dreams. The real conquest of space
began in our century, as a result of further
advances in the natural sciences, in tech¬
nology and more especially in mathe¬
matics and astronautics.
A large group of Russian scientists wor¬
ked on these subjects during the early years
of the century. Nikolai Zhukovsky (1847-
1921), known as "the father of Russian
aviation", created in Moscow the first
European Institute of Aerodynamics, and
devoted much attention to the develop¬
ment of techniques of rocketry. The
younger generation of scientists, techni¬
cians and pilots followed in the steps of
their elders; S.P. Korolev (1906-1966) was
a particularly outstanding Soviet scientist,
whose work contributed to the creation of
the huge rockets used for launching the
first artificial satellites, the first flights
towards the Moon, Venus and Mars, and
the first journeys of the cosmonauts in
outer space.
The activities of Korolev, the construc¬
tion of the first sputniks, the first space
flight by Yuri Gagarin and Aleksei Leonov's
famous walk among the stars marked the
final stages of a journey that had lasted for
five centuries, and had led from an intuitive
and theoretical understanding of the struc¬
ture of the universe to the opening of its
very doors.
Bogdan Suchodolsky
Mankind has always dreamed of achieving mastery of space. Below left,
illustration from The States and Empires of the Sun (1662), a science fiction
novel by the French author Cyrano de Bergerac, a student of Copernican
astronomy. The gravity-defying hero is clad in a space suit equipped with
flasks containing dew which, he hopes, will be turned into steam by solar
heat and propel him to the upper atmosphere. The dream became reality in
1961 when Yuri Gagarin became the first man to travel in space. Medal
(below) was issued in the U.S.S.R. to commemorate his exploit.
"He was in himself our first
university," wrote Pushkin of
the Russian polymath Mikhail
Lomonosov (1711-1765). A poet
and linguistic reformer as well
as a scientist whose research
ranged from studies on metals
and gases to astronomy and
geology, in 1755 Lomonosov
helped to found Moscow
University, which is named
after him. Left, portrait of
Lomonosov by an unknown
artist.
"The Astral System of
Copernicus" is the theme of a
stained glass window designed
for Cracow's "House of
Physicians" by Stanislaw
Wyspianski (1869-1907), an
outstanding figure in modern
Polish art. Below, detail of the
cartoon design for this
composition, showing
Apollo, symbol of the sun.
Photo Stanislaw Lopatka © National Museum, Cracow
67
]]>
</page>
<page number="68">
<![CDATA[
HUH, C5-d£H. £ÍKE W£UP£H Hjí3U
MbTCM ibO«i>RTHhffi ZSilOALHE
tîhMOïfifcHM MPMKHH H3hIK5
¿OrîTOl'o ^HfilJIM^CKOPHHOfo
iiscadfiHáro riv/trf ikmoijw . sors kotth
Byelorussia's first printed book
The work of the scholar and printer Gyorgi-Franciszek Skorina is a milestone in
the history of Byelorussia's language and culture. Born at Polotsk in 1490, he
obtained the degree of "bachelor of the seven liberal arts" at Cracow and then
set off on a journey across Europe, staying in German towns, at Prague
University and in Padua where he was made a doctor of medicine. During his
years of wandering and study he conceived the great plan of publishing a Bible
in his mother tongue, Byelorussian. "God sent me this language," he wrote, "1
vow it shall become a language of books." Patiently and obstinately he raised
money for his venture and recruited illustrators and engravers. Between 1517
and 1519 he translated and published 22 parts of the Bible, followed a few years
later by the Acts of the Apostles. Exquisitely printed and illustrated, the Skorina
Bible is widely considered to be one of the world's most beautiful books.
Above, engraving showing Samson fighting a lion. Below, an episode from
Exodus when the Lord commanded Moses to make a tabernacle: "And thou
shalt make a mercy seat of pure gold... And thou shalt make two cherubims of
gold, of beaten gold shalt thou make them, in the two ends of the mercy seat."
Photos © Engravings ol Franciszek Skorina, Belarusi Publishers, Minsk
ARTS
AND
CRAFTS
OF
BYELO¬
RUSSIA
by Evgeni M. Sakhuta
68
]]>
</page>
<page number="69">
<![CDATA[
"Put me in the mud and I shall become
a prince," says the grain of rye in an
old Byelorussian proverb. According to
tradition, the first seeds sown when
the winter snows have melted are
taken from the last sheaf harvested the
previous autumn. The straw from the
sheaf is laid out on the ground in the
form of a cross, "so that Christ won't
get his feet wet when he comes to
bless the earth". Below, the first-fruits
of the harvest are ceremonially knotted
around the farmer's waist.
Byelorussian artists create
outstandingly beautiful works of art
out of plaited straw. Left, detail of the
remarkable "Tsars' Gate" in an 18th-
century country church in the Pinsk
region. Although made of straw it
glows with all the majesty of gold leaf.
POPULAR decorative art holds a pro¬
minent and colourful place in Byelo¬
russian culture. It is a highly original
art, for although the objects made by Bye¬
lorussian craftsmen have much in common
with those produced by their neighbours in
Russia, the Ukraine, Lithuania and Poland,
they have also been profoundly marked by
the special circumstances of Byelorussia's
social, political and cultural development as
well as by the natural environment.
Only rarely has this art been created by
organized groups of professional artists
and craftsmen. For the most part it has
been produced in a domestic setting. As a
consequence it remained rooted in tradition
until the early years of this century.
Working in wood, the most widely used
material, Byelorussian craftsmen produced
highly expressive forms of decoration,,
especially in the large objects such as mor-^
EVGENI M. SAKHUTA is a Byelorussian art
historian on the staff of the Institute for the
Study of Art, Ethnography and Folklore at¬
tached to the Byelorussian S.S.R. Academy
of Sciences. He is the author of many pub¬
lished works on the popular arts of Byelorussia.
69
]]>
</page>
<page number="70">
<![CDATA[
tars, canoes, beehives and tubs which they
hollowed out of tree trunks and boughs.
Smaller vessels were often embellished
with animal motifs, salt-cellars being car¬
ved in the form of ducks, and bucket hand¬
les being shaped to resemble the head of a
horse or bird, a rooster's tail'feathers or a
cock's-comb.
Geometric patterns were incised on
utensils used by women, such as distaffs
(in the Brest-Litovsk region) and tsurki
(sticks between 30 and 40 cm long to which
sheaves were attached) which are found in
central Polesie.
Pottery is one of the most ancient popu¬
lar crafts of Byelorussia, and a number of
old-established pottery-making centres are
situated near the cities of Pinsk, Vitebsk
and Minsk. Pots, basins, zbanki (pitchers)
sparishi (twin vases), sloiki (jars) and other
containers were all made out of clay. Some
pottery towns specialized in producing
black-glazed pottery which looked as if it
were made of cast iron. This is a curious
survival from prehistoric times, since Bye¬
lorussian pottery of this type has hardly
changed either in shape or decoration since
the Iron Age.
Other potters were renowned for their
skill in making earthenware in the form of
bears, lions and rams, also producing
highly distinctive figurines of cockerels,
ducklings, horsemen, ewes and dolls.
Along with wood-carving and pottery-
making, weaving was one of the most
widely practised crafts in Byelorussia,
where countrywomen had little choice but
to learn the art of the loom. Napkins,
towels and abrussy (table-cloths) were
woven in two or three colours arranged to
form checkwork, diamond-shaped, hexa¬
gonal and other patterns. The region
around Grodno specialized in rainbow-
striped drapery which is today found in
many parts of Poland. Geometrical pat¬
terns in white, black and red were the most
common features of dress design.
The plaiting of objects out of birch-bark,
willow wands, roots and straw is another
ancient Byelorussian craft. Articles fash¬
ioned out of straw are particularly distinc¬
tive, as well as large wickerwork household
utensils which derive their beauty from
their sculptural form and from the rhythmic
alternation of brown stripes of willow or
hazel on a background of golden straw.
But the aesthetic potential of straw, a
widely available material in Byelorussia, is
best seen in decorative objects, in toys and
in coffers decorated with raised wicker-
work ornamentation in the form of dia¬
monds. A masterpiece of Byelorussian
craftsmanship in straw is the eighteenth-
century "Tsar's Gate" in a little country
church at Vabulich-Lemeshevich in the
Pinsk region. Although made from the
humblest of materials it glows with all the
majesty of gold leaf.
The skills of Byelorussian village painters
found their widest expression in the de¬
corated coffers and chests which, from the
second half of the nineteenth century
onwards, were increasingly used in daily
life and figured prominently in the marriage
ceremony. Owing to the great demand for
such objects, it was inevitable that they
should eventually be produced in studios
by artists specializing in this form of
decoration.
Since popular art was primarily utilitarian
in character, it was bound to be affected by
social and economic changes. Thus many
domestic crafts declined in the second half
of the nineteenth century and some (such
as the hand-printing of textiles) died out
altogether.
The radical transformation of rural life
during the early Soviet period, and the
improved standards of living which the
workers began to enjoy, led to a temporary
depreciation of many traditional utilitarian
articles and reduced the people's reliance
on home-made utensils, furniture, clothing
and tools.
Concern for the preservation of popular
handicrafts and the quest for new ways
and means of promoting popular art led the
Soviet Government to adopt in 1919 a
decree "on assistance to domestic
industry". Exhibitions of works by crafts¬
men and artists were organized, the prob¬
lem was widely discussed in the press, and
regional museums began to assemble their
collections. Craft centres were open¬
ed to encourage the development and pre¬
servation of popular art.
In Byelorussia, and in the Soviet Union
as a vyhole, popular arts and crafts are
mainly produced by groups of craftsmen
and artists in craft centres. As a result of
their work, decorative objects of popular
art, especially those made of plaited straw,
are now becoming more widely familiar not
only in Byelorussia but also abroad.
There hqs been a revival of traditional
pottery-making, and weaving has taken on
a new lease of life. The traditional two- or
three-tone range of colours has been
extended, and modern weavers are pro¬
ducing complicated multi-coloured pat¬
terns based on plant motifs.
The majority of modern Byelorussian
wood-carvers today are creating small-
scale objects inspired by traditional themes
from history, folklore and everyday life, and
are trying to revive the manufacture of
traditional wooden utensils. Wood-carving
for purposes of architectural decoration
is enjoying widespread popularity.
Considerable attention is now being paid
to the revival, conservation and develop¬
ment of popular arts and crafts. Whereas in
the past national traditions and creative ori¬
ginality were handed down spontaneously
from generation to generation, often within
the same family, this task has now been
assumed by professional artists, art histo¬
rians and the staff of popular arts and
crafts centres. A museum of popular art
has recently been opened at Raubichi, near
Minsk, and a museum of ancient crafts and
domestic industries at Zaslavl. As well as
displaying the traditional heritage, these
institutions will help to train the Byelorus¬
sian craftsmen of tomorrow.
Evgenl M. Sakhuta
A
PHOENIX
RISING
FROM
THE
ASHES
by Aleksandar Fiaker
THE Second World War inflicted incal¬
culable losses on Slav cultures.
Monuments of rare magnificence,
such as the National Museum in Belgrade
with its priceless manuscripts and early
printed books, crumbled under the impact
of enemy bombs. The Nazis systematically
plundered museums, carrying off their
archives. Whole cities, Leningrad, Kiev,
Minsk, Warsaw and many others, were vir¬
tually erased from the map.
All Slav intellectuals, including writers,
were subjected to ruthless persecution.
Here are just a few names from the long list
of victims of this terror : Vladislav Vancura,
a leading figure in the avant-garde of Czech
literature, executed in 1942; a whole group
of Croatian writers and critics, including
August Cesarec, shot in 1941; Ivan Goran
Kovacic, the Croatian poet and essayist,
short-story writer and translator of Shelley,
Keats and Rimbaud, savagely murdered in
1943; the Bulgarian poet Nikola Jonkov
Vapcarov, shot in Sofia in 1942, who,
before his death, addressed a moving and
lyrical appeal to his wife and to the entire
Bulgarian people.
Among those who fell in the ranks of the
Yugoslav National Liberation Army were
the Slovenian poets Karel Destovnik-Kajuh
and Miran Jare, the Croatian prose-writer
Hasan Kikic, from Bosnia, the Serbian lit¬
erary critic Milos Savkovic, the famous
Macedonian poet Koco Racin, and many
others.
Yugoslavia alone lost at least 75 of her
most talented writers, not to mention
countless promising young poets who
perished at the front or among the Parti¬
sans, while their Polish contemporaries
were dying in concentration camps or in
the flames of the Warsaw Rising and
young Russians of the same generation
were giving their lives in the struggle
against the aggressor.
The war left indelible scars on the cul-
ALEKSANDAR FLAKER, prominent Croatian-
Yugoslav scholar in Slavic and comparative lit¬
erature, is Vice-President of the International
Association for the Study and Dissemination of
Slav Cultures.
70
]]>
</page>
<page number="71">
<![CDATA[
The Second World War left profound scars
on the Slav world. This image of
desolation, one of a series of Indian ink
drawings entitled "It must never happen
again", is by the Soviet artist Boris
Prorokov, who lost both legs during the
war. Many Slav writers and artists died in
the struggle against Nazi barbarity.
Detail of a fresco of the Virgin Mary in the
church of St. Nicholas, Novgorod. Used as
a target by occupying forces in the
Second World War, it evokes the fate of
many works of art destroyed during the
Nazi invasion.
71
]]>
</page>
<page number="72">
<![CDATA[
tures of all the European countries. But this
time of wholesale destruction, cultural
annihilation and massacre on an unprece¬
dented scale was also a period in which
fresh literary and artistic values made their
appeal anee, in which the foundations of a
more fitting human existence were re¬
modelled, and in which new horizons
were opened for future relations between
individuals, peoples and States. Thus,
from the ashes of this hour of destruction
arose, phoenix-like, a new literature and a
new art, dedicated to the struggle towards
the light and against the black forces
of modern barbarism.
If, as the Soviet novelist Leonid Leonov
puts it, culture is "mankind's memory", it
is easy to understand why the red stain of
their martyrdom remains imprinted on the
cultures of peoples who endured such suf¬
fering during the 1940s, a dark age in Euro¬
pean and world history, and yet who,
among the ruins, laid the foundations of a
new life.
Echoes from that wartime period are still
heard in modern Polish literature, from the
tragic evocation of the Warsaw ghetto in
Andrzejewski's "Holy Week" to the latest
prose works by the realist writer Miron Bia-
loszewski. Similar themes run through the
new Polish cinema, from Kavalerowicz to
Wajda, and the new cinema of Yugoslavia,
represented by Veljko Bulajic.
The War is still a major subject in the
Soviet novel, and permeates the works of
Konstantin Simonov and Yuri Bondarev.
Oles Goncar in the Ukraine, and Vasyl
Bykau in Byelorussia draw on the war years
for inspiration; the Croatian writer Miroslav
Krleza has turned his attention again to the
same period; and the novels of the Monte¬
negrin writer Mihailo Lalic set wartime
events in a new light.
The oppression of man, his resistance to
constraints and terror of all kinds, and his
liberation from the fear and threat of war,
are themes which find reflection in the
many sculptures and monuments which
are familiar landmarks in countless Rus¬
sian, Ukrainian and Byelorussian towns
and villages. Similar monuments are to be
found at the scene of battles and suffering
which already seem a part of distant his¬
tory, but which are not to be forgotten, for
they were the battles and sufferings of
whole peoples, indeed, of all mankind.
Aleksandar Flaker
THE COMMON HERITAGE
continued from page SB
songs and laments. During the nineteenth
century, this tendency was to be transfor¬
med into a powerful and enduring current.
The ancient Slav tradition inspired not only
Pushkin and Mickiewicz, but also Killar Lju-
dovit Stur, the founder of the Slovak lit¬
erary language; Vuk Karadzic, who estab¬
lished Serbo-Croatian on a similar lit¬
erary footing; the Ukrainian poet Taras
Shevchenko and many other prominent
figures of Slav culture.
The general tradition of Slav folklore also
gave rise to endeavours to create a new
"national music". These attempts were at
first reflected in the composition of "popu¬
lar songs" which were often the product of
cross-cultural collaboration. For example,
Czech musicians were actively involved in
the development of Russian music at the
turn of the eighteenth and nineteenth cen¬
turies. The works of Tchaikovsky and his
lively contacts with other Slav composers,
particularly Czechs, Dvorak's Slavonic
Dances and the long career of Josef Suk as
a composer and conductor in Russia are
just a few examples of collaboration of this
kind. Out of this current of "Slav music",
fed by the tributaries of individual popular
traditions, emerged the works of out¬
standing composers of worldwide
renown, from the operas of Smetana,
Glinka and Moniusko to Stravinsky's ballet
Petrushka.
The work of the Czech composer Leos
Janacek (1854-1928) is a brilliant example
of inter-Slav cultural exchange. His cantata
Taras Bulba is based on a poem by the
Ukrainian Shevchenko; the libretto of the
opera Katya Kabonova comes from a play
by the Russian dramatist Ostrovsky; ano¬
ther of his operas, From the House of the
Dead, is based on a novel by Dostoevsky;
and finally, his Glagolitic Mass draws its
inspiration from Slavonic literature and
ancient Russian music. All these creations
reflect at the same time the living tradition
of popular Slav music, which Janacek had
studied in great detail.
The continuation of the process of
crystallization of their national musical cul¬
ture may be observed today among diffe
rent Slav peoplesamong the Slovaks, for
example, where imaginative adaptations of
popular songs written by one of the foun¬
ders of "national" Slovak music, Stefan
Fajnor, are found alongside the operas of
composers like Suchon and Cikker.
Constant awareness of their affinity and
a feeling of belonging to a single family of
peoples was natural to the Slavs, who
could understand each other without inter¬
preters and who recognized the great simi¬
larity between the historical destinies of
their countries. And this awareness came
to the surface in different social, spiritual
and historical circumstances time and time
again between the ninth and the nineteenth
centuries. It formed the background to the
development of all the various themes and
forms of artistic creation, particularly
among the common people, who also ser¬
ved as intermediaries for its transmission. It
found an echo when the Slav peoples, one
by one, were converted to Christianity, and
lay at the foundations of their literacy. It
facilitated the dissemination of the "hereti¬
cal" ideas of the Bogomils, the Hussites,
the Arians and the Moravian and Bohemian
Brethren, and the circulation of the huma¬
nist ideals of the Renaissance and Baroque
periods. And it made itself felt even more
strongly during the age of Romanticism.
The founder of modern Czech poetry,
Karel Hynek Macha, who was a contemp¬
orary of Mickiewicz and Pushkin, appears
in the broad context of world literature and
culture as a confirmed "Byronist". Closer
examination, based on more detailed
knowledge of cross-cultural influences bet¬
ween peoples of different regions, reveals
him rather as a direct heir of the Polish pre-
Romantic and Romantic tradition. This is
merely one of many examples of the parti¬
cipation of the Slavs in the development of
world culture, either anticipating major
trends or joining in them. Throughout this
participation is marked by the reciprocity
and "togetherness" of the Slavs, men¬
tioned above. Thus, Czech actors, singers
and directors played an important part both
in the creation of a national South Slav
theatre, particularly among the Slovenes
and the Croatians, and in setting this the¬
atre in a broader European context.
The idea of a cultural "commonwealth"
of Slavs, which found reflection in the
works of so many Slav writers, was closely
related to the ideals of justice, universal
freedom and the common good. On the
eve of the revolution of 1848, Taras Shev¬
chenko praised, in a single line of verse,
both Safarik and Jan Hus, the spiritual
father of nationalist and anti-feudal revolt.
In the same stormy year, the Slovak poet
Karol Kusmany raised his voice in praise of
all "who were inflamed with the desire for
truth and were prepared to make the
supreme sacrifice for it, and those who
devoted their lives to the cause of human
rights". The words, "sweet freedom" that
appear in his verse echo the liberté chérie
of a French song of the same period. And
this should come as no surprise, since
there was no such thing as a completely
isolated and introverted "Slav world"; the
leading representatives of the culture of the
Slavs readily acknowledged that cultural
relations between themselves only made
sense when their purpose was to serve all
mankind, and to contribute to "the general
ordering of human affairs". This was the
message of freedom and universal equality
that Jan Amos Komensky had pronounced
two hundred years earlier.
Jan Komensky (Comenius) himself is
inscribed in history as an outstanding
educationist, the founder of pedagogical
science and the author of profoundly
humanistic teachings concerning the ach¬
ievement of universal peace and jus¬
tice through mutual understanding and cul¬
tural and scientific collaboration between
peoples, and through universal educa¬
tion, irrespective of religion, nationality,
sex or class.
The noble concepts of Comenius, the
"teacher of the people", might well serve
for all time as a sure guide and a standard
by which to measure the value and signifi¬
cance of cultural relations between peo¬
ples, and groups of peoples throughout the
world.
Slavomir Vollman
72
]]>
</page>
<page number="73">
<![CDATA[
Letters
to
the editor
RETURN TO THE HOMELAND
Sir,
I have read with interest, and a certain
amount of sympathy, the article by M.
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow appealing for the
return of art treasures to their country of ori¬
gin. (Unesco Courier, July 1978).
Surely a distinction should be made be¬
tween those objects acquired illegally and
those which were rescued, repaired, and
have been exhibited with loving care, and
which would otherwise have gone forever.
Some years ago I had the privilege of visi¬
ting New York's magnificent Cloisters at Fort
Tryon. Until then I had regarded the Ameri¬
cans as "snappers up of unconsidered
trifles", but after seeing tapestries collected
piece by piece, cleaned and mounted to
make a whole, I couldn't help remarking, "If
that's how they look after them they are wel¬
come to the rest."
D.M. Skippings
Yarmouth, Norfolk
U.K.
HARNESSING THE ATOM
Sir,
Congratulations on your June 1978 issue
on energy sources; every article dealt with
an extremely important aspect of the energy
problem. However, one potential source was
not discussed that of the enormous
energy, so far fortunately unused, stored in
and for nuclear weapons. According to the
Stockholm International Peace Research
Institute (SIPRI), this energy amounts to one
million times the force of the Hiroshima
bomb.
If the world is wise and successfully urges
the nuclear powers to dismantle their weap¬
ons and to place their plutonium gradually
under the custody and at the disposal of the
United Nations Atomic Energy Agency in
Vienna, humanity will have an invaluable and
ready source of energy for years to come.
A. Loeff
Rotterdam
The Netherlands
THE WORLD'S FIRST
WOMAN PH. D?
Sir,
In your July 1978 issue the young Vene¬
tian Elena Lucrezia Cornaro Plscopla, who
received her doctorate at the University of
Padua 300 years ago, is called the world's
first woman Ph.D.
But she was not the first female doctor!
That distinction belongs to Hypatla, who
taught in Alexandria in the 5th century A.D.
The daughter of a mathematician, Theon of
Alexandria, she was herself a prominent
mathematician, astronomer and philoso¬
pher. She wrote a number of astronomical
and mathematical commentaries, including
one on conic sections.
After a rigorous education she became a
professor, with the right to wear the philo¬
sopher's cape and to give lectures. A repre¬
sentative of pagan, Neoplatonist scholar¬
ship, she was murdered by fanatic Christians
in the year 415 after the Archbishop of
Alexandria had preached a sermon about
"sinful women", especially meant for Hypa-
tia, who had dared to give lessons to menl
Otto Ottesen
Sandefjord
Norway
RIDDLE OF
A ROYAL HUNT
Sir,
Reading once again an interesting article
in the October 1971 issue of the Unesco
Courier, entitled "A Sassanian Royal Hunt",
I noticed that the significance of the fifth-
century A.D. relief shown on page 38 (see
photo 2) has never been explained.
I was intrigued and curious to discover the
meaning of the scene, with its group of four
figures that appear to be lying down in front
of a line of advancing elephants. After a
careful study of all the illustrations of the
article, I believe that I have found the solu¬
tion.
The four figures are not marching, as they
might appear to be. They are actually open¬
ing a gate to allow the elephants and beat¬
ers to enter the king's hunting area which, as
one can see, was entirely enclosed. I also
noticed that in the lower left corner the
figure of a small dog is visible.
I came to this conclusion by comparing
the figures with those shown at left of ano¬
ther relief (see photo 1 ) pictured on page 35.
In closing, I should like to congratulate the
Unesco Courier on its excellent choice of
articles and suggest for future issues an
article on Alexander the Great, as well as
one on the recent discovery of the tomb of
his father , Philip of Macedón, at Verglna
in Greece.
Walter Marques
Rio de Janeiro
Brazil
An ivory head believed to portray Philip of
Macedón was shown on page 2 of our July
1978 issue, and on page 30 of the present
number we publish a photo of another ivory
head, presumed to depict Alexander the
Great. Both these important objects were
discovered in the tomb at Vergina which
may have been Philip's burial-place. They
were unearthed during excavations directed
by Professor Mano/is Andronicos, whose
article on the Athens Acropolis, Athenian
Democracy's Grand Design" appeared in our
October 1977 issue Editor.
MEASURING
THE WORLD'S WATER
Sir,
I agreed to cuts being made in my article
"Will Deserts Drink Icebergs?" (Unesco
Courier, February 1978) for reasons of
space. As a result of these cuts, which were
not submitted for my approval, certain facts
and figures which I consider important
disappeared from my text.
All published figures, even the most
recent, concerning the amount of water on
earth are highly approximate, but it is esti¬
mated that the total quantity is about 1,500
million cubic kilometres, 2.7 per cent of
which (some 40 million cubic kilometres) is
fresh water. It has also been estimated that
the total volume of fresh water stored in ice¬
caps and glaciers is of the order of 30 million
cubic kilometres (90 per cent in the Antarc¬
tic, 9 per cent in Greenland, 1 per cent in
glaciers).
Thus 70 per cent of the earth's fresh water
is stored in ice-caps and glaciers and 30 per
cent is in liquid form.
This 30 per cent consists of: surface water -
(streams, lakes, swamps, etc.); ground
water; moisture contained in soil, rocks,
sand, plants, etc.; and atmospheric water
(clouds, fog, etc.).
Estimates of these different "reserves" of
water vary widely from one publication to
another and are still extremely approximate
and tentative.
One of the most reliable figures at present
¡s that for the Greenland ice-cap (which was
accurately measured largely through the
work of French Polar Expeditions), followed
by that for the Antarctic ice-cap (measured
by a number of expeditions since Inter¬
national Geophysical Year in 1957).
Paul-Emile Victor
Paris
73
]]>
</page>
<page number="74">
<![CDATA[
Bookshelf
Recent Unesco books
and periodicals
Planning the Primary School Curri¬
culum in Developing Countries, by
H.W.R. Hawes. (No. 17 in Unesco's
"Fundamentals of Educational Planning"
series) 2nd impression 1978, 50 pp. (8 F)
The Education of Migrant Workers
and their Families. Case studies under¬
taken for the National Commissions for
Unesco of Finland, France, Sweden and
Yugoslavia. (No. 27 in Unesco's "Educa¬
tional Studies and Documents" series)
1978, 44 pp. (8 F)
Coral Reefs: Research Methods,
edited by D.R. Stoddart and R.E. Johan¬
nes. The most recent findings on the
functional ecology of coral reefs. (No. 5
in Unesco's "Monographs on Océano¬
graphie Methodology" series). 1978,
581 pp. (90 F)
Soil Map of the World 1: 5,000,000.
Volume VI Africa. Prepared by the
Food and Agriculture Organization of the
United Nations (FAO). This volume des¬
cribes the soils of Africa and accompa¬
nies the 3 map sheets already published
(price 50 F each). Co-published with the
FAO. 299 pp. (75 F)
Communication Policies in the
Republic of Korea by Hahn Bae-ho.
1978, 50 pp. (10 F)
Exploring Global Interdependence
is the theme of Unesco's International
Social Science Journal (\lo\. XXX, No. 2,
1978). Each issue 23 F; subscription 70 F
for one year or 116 F for two years.
Non-formal education ¡s the major
theme of Prospects, Unesco's quarterly
review of education (Vol. VIII, No. 2,
1978). Each Issue 12 F; subscription 42 F
for one year or 70 F for two years.
Unesco's literature
translations series
IRAN
The llahi-nama or Book of God of
Farid al-Din Attar, translated from the
Persian by John Andrew Boyle, with a
foreword by Annemarie Schimmel. Man¬
chester University Press, 392 pp. (£9.95)
ARABIC WORKS
Rusum Dar Al-Khilafah (The Rules
and Regulations of the Abbasid Court)
by Hllal Al-Sabi. Translated with an
introduction and notes by Elle A. Salem.
Lebanese Commission for the Trans¬
lation of Great Works, Beirut, 134 pp.
African technology
get-together
Nine African countries have established the
Association of African Industrial Technology
Organizations to co-ordinate their efforts in
industrial technological research and develop¬
ment. Member countries are: Ghana, Kenya,
Madagascar, Nigeria, Uganda, Senegal, Sudan,
United Republic of Cameroon, and Zaire.
Let the Village Hear
A workshop on information sharing, "Let the
Village Hear", is being planned for Calcutta,
India, in late November or early December 1978.
People involved in village development in the
Third World will take part in the workshop,
whose goal is to increase information exchange
in the developing world and to decrease reliance
on the traditional north-south flow of technolo¬
gical aid. The workshop has been initiated by
Rural Communications, a Third World service
agency based in South Petherton, Somerset,
U.K.
New guide
to U.N. information services
The first comprehensive directory of the infor¬
mation activities of the U.N. system has been
issued by the Interorganization Board for Infor¬
mation Systems (IOB) in Geneva. The 250-page
Directory of United Nations Information
Systems and Services contains particulars on
.over 100 information sources and covers sub¬
jects ranging from human rights to industry,
science, technology and sociology. Published in
English (French and Spanish editions will appear
later in 1978) the directory is available free of
charge to organizations, universities and libraries
from the Director, IOB Secretariat, Palais des
Nations, CH-1211, Geneva 10, Switzerland.
Unesco establishes
Simon Bolivar
International Prize
Unesco has set up an international prize,
financed by the Venezuelan Government, to be
awarded for noteworthy actions in line with the
¡deals of Simon Bolivar (1783-1830), El
Libertador (The Liberator) of Latin America. The
biennial prize of not less than $30,000 will
honour contributions to the freedom,
independence and dignity of peoples and to the
strengthening of solidarity between nations by
promoting their development and the advent of
a new international economic, social and
cultural order. It will be awarded for the first time
on 24 July 1983, bicentenary of Bolivar's birth,
on the basis of candidatures presented by
Unesco Member States or Associate Members,
and by intergovernmental and international non¬
governmental organizations with consultative
status or co-operative relations with Unesco.
The award will be made by an international jury
consisting of a representative of Unesco's
Director-General, a personality named by the
Venezuelan Government and five other
representatives of the different world regions
designated by the Director-General.
Saving the Mediterranean
Monk Seal
An Action Plan to save the Mediterranean Monk
' Seal, threatened by pollution, overfishing and
the destruction of its habitat, has been approved
at a meeting convened by the Greek Govern
ment and co-sponsored by Greece, the U.N.
Environment Programme (UNEP), the Interna¬
tional Union for Conservation of Nature and
Natural Resources (IUCN), and the University of
Guelph (Canada). The Plan will be co-ordinated
with Monk Seal projects in Turkey and the West
Mediterranean and with efforts to save other
species and habitats.
Radio manual
for population workers
Grassroots Radio, a radio manual by Rex Kea¬
ting, has been issued by the International Plan¬
ned Parenthood Federation, 18-20 Lower
Regent Street, London SWI. The manual is not
intended for professional broadcasters, but aims
to teach the basic elements of radio production
and writing and thus help family planning wor¬
kers explain to listeners the purpose and practice
of family planning.
U.N. Industrial Development
Fund reaches $9.5 million
A donation of $1 million from Saudi Arabia, a
pledge of over $1 million from the U.K., and
contributions from Burundi and Venezuela have
brought the money available to the United
Nations Industrial Development Fund to over
$9.5 million. Created by the U.N. General
Assembly in 1976, the Fund consists of volun¬
tary contributions to be used by the U.N. Indus¬
trial Development Organization ¡n support of
industry in the developing countries.
The Unesco Courier
in Korean
We are pleased to announce the launching of a
Korean language edition of the Unesco Courier
(see photo). Published by the Korean National
Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64,
Seoul, the first issue of the Korean edition
appeared in June. Publication of the Korean edi¬
tion brings the total number of language editions
of the Unesco Courier to 19: English, French,
Spanish, Russian, German, Arabic, Japanese,
Italian, Hindi, Tamil, Hebrew, Persian, Dutch,
Portuguese, Turkish, Urdu, Catalan, Malaysian
and Korean.
74
]]>
</page>
<page number="75">
<![CDATA[
The scientific enterprise,
today and tomorrow
Adriano Buzz»ti-Traverso
lyresoo
Just Published
A comprehensive study of the development of science and
technology today by a leader in the field of population genetics
and biophysics. Former Assistant Director-General for Sciences
at Unesco, Professor Buzzati-Traverso examines a number of
highly provocative and disturbing questions facing scientist and
layman alike:
Is science today the main hope for or the greatest threat
to the further advance of mankind?
What have been the true benefits of science to man and
his institutions?
Is it possible for developing lands to absorb the shock of
technology transfer on their ancient tradition-dominated
cultures?
Do we really need science and technology?
Dare we even continue to engage in laboratory research
and experiments?
439 pages 160 French Francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the
National Distributor in your country. (See list
below; names of distributors in countries not
listed, alona, with subscription rates in local
currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P.O.
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne (Victoria), 3000.
AUSTRIA. Dr. Franz Ham, Verlags-und Kommissionsbuch¬
handlung, Industriehof Stadlau, Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasse 5, 1220
Wien. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7. - CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makanos 3rd Avenue,
P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L.,
Spalena 51, Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura,
11 Soukemcka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag
Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava CSSR.
DENMARK. Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Norregade, DK
1165, Copenhagen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF).
National Centre for Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb
Street, Tahrir Square, Cairo. ETHIOPIA. National Agency for
Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa. - FINLAND. Akateemi-
nen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100 Helsinki 10.
FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700
Paris, C.C.P. 12598-48. - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP.
Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internatio¬
nalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R. - FED. REP. OF GER¬
MANY. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed. only): 53 Bonn 1,
Colmantstrasse 22. For scientific maps only: GEO CENTER D7
Stuttgart 80, Postfach 800830. Other publications: S. Karger
GmbH, Karger Buchhandlung, Angerhofstrasse 9, Postfach 2,
8034 Germering/Munchen. GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop
Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd.,
P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape Coast; The University
Bookshop of Legón, P.O. Box 1, Legón. - GREAT BRITAIN.
See United Kingdom. - HONG KONG. Fedora) Publications
(HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street,
Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Akadèmiai Kónyvesbolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V;
A.K.V. Konyvtürosok Boltja, Népkóztársaság utja 16, Budapest
VI. ICELAND. Snaebjörn Jonsson & Co., H. F., Hafnarstraeti
9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7
Asaf Ali Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road,
Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001. Sub-
Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta
70016; Scmdia House, New Delhi; Publications Section, Ministry
of Education and Social Welfare, 51 1 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan,
New Delhi 110001. - INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and
Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia
Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr
Sam Ratulangie 47, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publish¬
ing and Distribution Co., 28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Shahreza
Avenue, P.O. Box 314/1486, Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for
Unesco, Ave. Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B.P. 1533, Teheran.
IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, AI -Rashid Street, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd.,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL.
Emanuel Brown, formerly Blumstem's Book-stores, 35 Allenby
Road and 48 Nachlat Benjamin Street, Tel Aviv; 9, Shlomzion
Hamalka Street, Jerusalem. JAMAICA. SangsteKs Book
Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston.
JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., C.P.O. Box 1728, Tokyo
100-92. - KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O. Box
30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission for
Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. - KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co., Ltd, 2942, Kuwait LESOTHO. Mazenod Book
Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA.
Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication & Distribution,
P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul
Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg. MALAYSIA. Federal
Publications, Lot 8323, JI.222, Petaling Jaya, Selangor.
MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta.
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street,
Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins,
Monte-Carlo. NETHERLANDS. For the "Unesco Koerier"
Dutch edition only: Systemen Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75,
Amsterdam-1007. Agent for all Unesco publications^ N.V.
Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague.
NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O. Box
200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. - NEW ZEALAND.
Government Printing Office, Government Bookshops at:
Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace,
P.O. Box 1721 Christ-church; Alma Street, P.O. Box 857
Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin; Mulgrave
Street, Private Bag, Wellington. NIGERIA. The University
Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286;
The University Bookshop of Nsukka; The University Bookshop
of Lagos;The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of Zaria.
NORWAY. All publications: Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco
Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Sarah Quaid-e-azam,
P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. -
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-901
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda, Livraria
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES. New
Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé.
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications IS) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19. - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951,
Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA. All publications: Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.
SOUTHERN RHODESIA. Textbook Sales IPVT) Ltd., 67 Union
Avenue, Salisbury. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100
Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2.
SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum.
SWEDEN. All publications A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16.
For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Fbrbundet, Skolgränd 2,
Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. - SWITZERLAND. All
publications: Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse. Zurich. Librairie
Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11, C.C.P. 12-236. -
TANZANIA. Dar-es Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-
Salaam. - THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen
Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok:
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok;
Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok.
TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco,
18 Alexandra Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I. - TURKEY.
Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istambul.
UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145, Kampala. -
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569,
London, S.E.I., and Government Bookshops in London,
Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol.
- UNITED STATES. Unipub, Box 433 Murray Hill Station,
New York, N.Y. 10016. - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga,
Moscow, G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga, Trg
Republike 5/8, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba Slovenje, Titova C 25,
P.O.B. 50-1, Ljublana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="76">
<![CDATA[
Avantgarde
iconographer
Together with his compatriot Wassily Kandinsky, the Russian painter Kazimir Malevich (Kiev 1878-Leningrad'
1935) was one of the founders of abstract painting. Malevich developed an abstract style known as "Supre-
matism" which stressed the primacy of simple geometric elements and pure colours and culminated in his
famous White on White (1918). In this Head of a Peasant (1910), now in the Russian Museum, Leningrad, he
sought to achieve geometric harmony through the use of flat, tubular and conical forms. Like many of Male-
vich's other works on the same theme, it suggests an affinity with the ¡con painters of medieval Russia.
"* 'M&jjL-
f
Photo Russian Museum, Leningrad
]]>
</page>
</document>
