<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="050399eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
September 1974 (27th year)
2.40 French francs
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
^m
'
Photo G Koposnv r Ogonyok' magazine. APN. Moscow
Siberian deity
This mask-like face, reconstructed from fragments of a clay ritual vessel painted
with ochre, dates back some 4,500 years. It was unearthed in 1966, along with many
ancient tools, from a site near Voskresenskoye, on the Lower Amur River in Siberia,
by Academician Aleksei Okladnikov, a Soviet archaeologist well known for his
excavations in this region. The face is believed to personify a deity who in place of
hands has a bear's paws (seen alongside face). Present-day craftsmen of the Ulchi
and Nanai. two peoples established since prehistoric times along the Lower Amur,
decorate their products with the same spiral-like features and ornamentatiopis
gag
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier
SEPTEMBER 1974
27TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 15 LANGUAGES
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese
Turkish
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Annual subscription rate 24 French francs
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in
August and September when it is bi-monthly (1 1 issues a
year). For list of distributors see inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from
the UNESCO COURIER," plus date of Issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returned unless accompanied by an international reply
coupon covering postage. Signed articles express the
opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of the
UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (micro¬
film and/or microfiche) by : (1) University Microfilms
(Xerox). Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100. U.S.A. ; (2) N.CR.
Microcard Edition, Indian Head, Inc., Ill West 40th
Street, New Yoik, U.S.A.; (3) Bell and Howell C°.,
Old Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in the
Readers' Guide to Periodical Literature, published by
H. W. Wilson Co., New York, and in Current Con¬
tents - Education, Philadelphia. U.S.A.
France
Managing Editors
English Edition :
French Edition
Spanish Edition :
Russian Edition :
German Edition :
Arabic Edition :
Japanese Edition :
Italian Edition :
Hindi Edition
Tamil Edition
Hebrew Edition :
Persian Edition :
Dutch Edition :
Portuguese Edition :
Turkish Edition :
Page
4
8
12
17
20
26
30
Editorial Office
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant to the Editor-in-Chief
Olga Rodel
Ronald Fenton (Paris)
Jane Albert Hesse (Paris)
Francisco Fernández-Santos (Paris)
Georgi Stetsenko (Paris)
Werner Merkli (Berne)
Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Ramesh Bakshi (Delhi)
N.D. Sundaravadivelu (Madras)
Alexander Peli (Jerusalem)
Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Mefra Telci (Istanbul)
Assistant Editors
English Edition : Roy Malkin
French Edition : Philippe Ouannès
Spanish Edition : Jorge Enrique Adoum
Illustrations : Anne-Marie Maillard
Research : Christiane Boucher
Layout and Design : Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed to
the Editor-in-Chief In Paris
33
34
LOST TREASURES OF THE CINEMA
Thousands of films have perished
since the birth of the cinema industry
By Bhagwan D. Garga
SAVED IN THE NICK OF TIME
THE VIDEO REVOLUTION
The challenge of portable video to conventional television
By Henri Dieuzeide
SPIRALS
From the snail to the galaxy, Nature grows in spirals
By Gerald Oster
UNUSUAL TOMBSTONE ART OF YUGOSLAVIA
Folk images carved and painted
by 19th-century Serbian artists
By Dusan Stanimirovic
PARIS GETS A NEW HEART
A bold project to transform the city's cultural life
By Nino Frank
DISMEMBERED WORKS OF ART
By Selim Abdul Hak
EXILED PAINTINGS
OF FRANCISCO DE ZURBARAN
Photo report
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
UNESCO NEWSROOM
TREASURES OF WORLD ART
Siberian deity (U.S.S.R.)
3
o
5
Cover photo
The Indian actress Sharmila Tagore,
seen here in close-up in "The World of
Apu" (1959), a masterpiece of the Indian
cinema. The film is one of the great
trilogy by Satyajit Ray, the Indian
director who also writes the screen¬
plays and composes the music for his
films. The two other parts of the trilogy
are " Pather Panchali" (1954) and "Apa-
rajito" (1957). The spread of film ar¬
chives and cinémathèques throughout
the world is doing much to preserve the
treasures of the cinema, but many thous¬
ands of films of high artistic merit have
already been lost (see article page 5).
2 0 août m
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Lost treasures
of the cinema
Unesco Courier drswlno by Al«»»ndrlnl
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
A call to halt the negligence
(and even vandalism) through which
many thousands of films
have perished since the birth
of the cinema industry
by Bhagwan D. Garga
IIT is a fair assumption that
more movies (of the silent era, at least)
have disappeared than have survived.
How much of the work of Lumière,
Méliès, Feuillade, Ince, Griffith, Sjös-
tröm, Dupont, Pabst, Chaplin, Max
Linder, Clair and other great pioneers
of the cinema has been lost to pos¬
terity through wilful destruction or plain
neglect? How many millions of metres
of priceless documentary material, that
could bring alive a whole era, have
vanished?
Some years ago, I was engaged
in making a film anthology of the
Indian cinema. Enthusiastically, I
drew up a list of significant films and
proceeded to search for them. In
Calcutta, I went to see the proprietor
of a well-known film production com¬
pany and asked him to let me use
excerpts from them. These Included
both silent and sound films. He took
one look at the list and handed it back
to me, saying, "I don't have any of
them".
"What happened to them?"
"They were lying around for quite
a while, then we decided to send
them to Madras."
"Why Madras?"
"Because the junkmen there, for
some reason, paid a better price than
in Calcutta."
To my horror, I was to discover
later that of the total production of
BHAGWAN D. GARGA of India Is a well-
known film-maker, cinema historian and film
critic. He has written on many aspects of
the Indian cinema and has produced a num¬
ber of documentary films on Indian film-mak¬
ing and Indian art. He was a member of
the Unesco committee of experts on Anthol¬
ogies of the History of the Cinema, and in
1971 won the Grand Prix at the 4th Interna¬
tional Film Review, Colombo (Sri Lanka).
some 1,300 silent films, not even half
a dozen had survived. Of these, two
The Light of Asia and A Throw of
Dice were Indo-German co-produc¬
tions, copies of which had somehow
found their way to the Cinémathèque
Française and the National Film Ar¬
chive of Great Britain.
The lost films included such well-
known works as Balidan (Sacrifice)
based on a play by Rabindranath Ta-
gore; Mrichakatika (The Little Clay
Cart) an adaptation of Sudaraka's
Sanskrit classical play of that name
(3rd-4th century A.D.), and a film on
non-violence called The Wrath in which
the protagonist was a Gandhi-like char¬
acter. There were numerous mytho¬
logy films done in the style and on the
scale of the Italian super-production
Cabiria, and our own variations on
Pearl White's The Perils of Pauline.
Vandalism was not confined only to
the silent cinema. Hundreds of well-
known sound films had been made
over to junk dealers as a matter of
routine. There was no trace, for Ins¬
tance, of the first Indian sound film,
Alam Ara. Consequently, the history
of Indian cinema has yawning gaps
that no amount of academic research
can now close.
India Is not the only case. The
destruction of films has continued
unabated all over the world. The great
director Fritz Lang, in a foreword to
Herman G. Weinberg's nostalgic book,
Saint Cinema, recalls the lost films
of H. d'Abbadie d'Arrast, who died in
1968, the creator of "eight of the love¬
liest films ever made by anyone".
Lang says: "His films are lost for
ever, like many other films important
for the art of the cinema and for its
historians, because studio policies
aimed at the destruction of old films
printed on inflammable nitrate stock.
These same studios, as Erich von Stro-
heim has pointed out, "were not above
salvaging the few cents worth of silver
which formed part of the cellulose
base'."
In 1956, on the occasion of the
twentieth anniversary of the founding
of the Cinémathèque Française, its di¬
rector, Henri Langlois, gave an alarm
ing recital of films lost or destroyed
through neglect or wanton callousness.
The answers I received In response .
to a questionnaire I recently sent to
several film archives, are enlightening.
Eileen Bowser, Associate Curator of
the Department of Film in the Museum
of Modern Art, New York:
"There is no law against the des¬
truction of films in this country. I wish
there was, but it is unlikely we could
achieve such a law under our system.
There is a form of legal deposit In
that if you wish your film to be protect¬
ed by copyright, you must eventually
deposit a copy of it in the Library
of Congress."
Of the lost films in the United States,
she added, "There are hundreds of
significant American films that have
been lost over the years, not neces¬
sarily because of destruction, but be¬
cause nitrate films have been allowed
to deteriorate. A few years ago, we
did an exhibition of still photographs
and brought out a publication called
'Lost Films', to call attention to some
of the important films which had
disappeared, which had the result of
finding a few of them."
lb Monty, Director of the Danish
Film Museum:
"We could draw up an enormous
list of Danish silent films that have
been lost. Out of a production of
around 1,700 silent films only around
225 have been preserved."
Jörn Donner of the Svenska Film
Institute, Stockholm:
"Many of the significant films from
the silent period have disappeared;
according to our estimates about two-
thirds of all films and about half the
valuable films."
Kevin Gough-Yates, Deputy Curator
of the National Film Archive, London:
"There is no law in England against
the destruction of films... There are
many significant films that seem to
have been lost, not only British ones.
Merton of the Movies, for example, is *1
one that cannot be found, but there
are many others." He further added- w
"My own view is that unless the *
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Some of the world's great films are now no
more than names in the history of the cinema.
Fragile, an easy prey to neglect, indifference
and outright vandalism, they are lost forever,
except for a few stills which have survived in
archives. Here we show scenes from three of
these films: (1) Broken Blossoms, made in 1919
by the great American director D.W. Griffith
(1875-1948); (2) L'Atlantide, directed by the
French film-maker Jacques Feyder (1885-1948);
(3) The Wrath, an Indian film whose hero is a
Gandhi-like character. Others, which were once
thought to have disappeared, have in fact sur¬
vived, a single copy having narrowly escaped
destruction. An example is Jean Renoir's, The
River (4), made In India in 1951. Other films
have been preserved because they were bought
by their stars or their directors. Here are
scenes from two of them, starring famous
American comics: (5) Safety Last, made in
1923, with Harold Lloyd; and (6) Go West,
1926, starring Buster Keaton (1896-1966), who
was also its director.
6
^government Introduces legislation to
^enforce producers to deposit material
with the national archive much material
will be lost."
What about the socialist countries
where production is state-sponsored
and controlled? It came as a reve¬
lation to me when Jan Zbigniw Pas-
tuszko, Director of the Polish Film
Archive, wrote to say that there was
no law against the destruction of films
in his country. Poland, he said, aimed
at preserving films produced before
1945, but present-day films were left
to fend for themselves.
Dr. Sandor Papp, Director of the
Hungarian Institute of Film Science and
Archives, informed me that the Hun¬
garian Film Archive "has been func¬
tioning since 1948, and from 1957 as
an independent organization. Most of
the films before this period, including
about 50 per cent of those made
between 1930 and 1944, have been
lost."
In India, the largest producer of
films In the world, the situation is even
more dismal. The National Film Ar¬
chive of India was established in 1964,
although a recommendation that one
should be created was contained in
an Enquiry Committee report published
as far back as 1927-28. The proposal
was revived in 1951 with much greater
emphasis by another committee ap¬
pointed by the Indian government.
The National Film Archive finally came
into being 13 years later.
According to an official publication
(Reference Annual, 1974), the "Ar¬
chive's collection, as of December 31,
1972, totalled 835 films, consisting of
624 Indian and 211 foreign films" a
far from impressive figure considering
that in the same year, India produced
414 feature films, not counting the vast
number of documentary and reportage
films. Since the advent of sound (in
1931) India has produced well over
11,000 feature films and perhaps an
equal number of short films. It is
apparent that most of these have
either perished orare in various stages
of deterioration.
Indian laboratories in all the major
centres of film production Bombay,
Calcutta and Madras still hold hun¬
dreds of nitrate base films which no¬
body claims, yet in the absence of a
legal fiat to do so, the laboratories
are unable to make them over to an
archive. To the trade wing of the
industry, the moment a "property"
ceases to be "productive", it is best
forgotten.
The researcher and the historian
apart, the man who really feels con¬
cerned about it is the creator of the
film. But not having any commercial
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
SAVED IN THE
NICK OF TIME
I HREE dates stand out in the dramatic story of old
films and their preservation: 1895, when the cinematograph
was invented; 1914, when films first began to be hired out;
and the mid-1 930s, when the first film libraries were founded.
In all the arts, there are works which have been lost to
posterity. All trace of them has disappeared forever. This is
hardly surprising In the case of pre-medieval music and musical
notation for dancing. But it has taken only a few decades for
similar havoc to be wrought on works of the cinema, the
youngest of the arts, although films are relatively easy to
preserve.
One could draw up a long list of fine films which today
only exist in histories of the cinema, beginning with the often-
quoted examples of Broken Blossoms (1919), by D.W. Griffith,
the first great American director, and Jacques Feyder's L'Atlan¬
tide (1921), of which only stills remain.
The first well-known film library, the Cinémathèque Française,
was founded in Paris in 1936 by an ardent "cinema buff, Henri
Langlois. Langlois already had a small collection of old films,
which he had been buying for four or five years. It was then
relatively easy to get hold of "antique" films, dating from before
the introduction of the rental system, because the original
owners eventually got rid of them and they ended up in flea-
markets and junkshops. At that time, of course, people did
not realize all the precautions that were needed to preserve
old film stock.
Furthermore, a number of the major studios kept extensive
film archives; as a result, it has been possible to re-issue many
interesting films in recent years and to put together documen¬
taries and comedy films from old newsreels and shorts.
But at the time, no-one bothered to keep old films: once their
commercial career was over, producers lost interest in them.
Even before film libraries started to become more numerous,
however, private collectors were at work, and film stars and
directors in particular, had already begun to save copies of
their films. Mary Pickford, for instance, is said to own copies of
nearly all the films in which she and her husband, Douglas
Fairbanks Sr., appeared.
Perhaps the most interesting story, however, is that of the
three great stars of early American film comedy: Harold Lloyd,
Charlie Chaplin and Buster Keaton. Comedy films, whether
shorts or feature-length, date less and are often a better
reflection of the vitality of cinematic art than straight films.
The first comedies were made around 1905-1906, in France
and Italy, with Max Linder, André Deed, Charles Prince (Riga-
din), etc. It was not until 1910 that Mack Sennett in the
United States set out to emulate the French and Italians, Imme¬
diately achieving immense popularity. The next few years saw
the débuts of the great stars of comic films: Lloyd (the most
popular in the U.S.A.) and Chaplin in 1913, Keaton in 1917.
According to the histories of the cinema, Lloyd made 180
shorts, Chaplin 66 and Keaton 67. Between 1921 and 1923, a
turning-point in the history of the cinema, all three of them
began to make full-length films: Keaton made most63 films
of more than four reels (1,200 metres), Lloyd 18 and Chap¬
lin 14.
As they approached the height of their popularity, they tried
to collect copies of their own films. Apparently, Keaton was
the least successful; he was the least wealthy of the three, and
retrieving 63 feature films is no mean task. Harold Lloyd, who
left the cinema In 1947 and became a successful businessman
and President of the Beverley Hills Chamber of Commerce,
was more or less successful, and his collection is famous
throughout the United States. As for Chaplin, he owns and
markets all his feature-length films. It is to be hoped that
sooner or later all these treasures of the U.S. cinema will end
up in America's greatest film collection, that of the New York
Museum of Modern Art.
control over it, he is a helpless spec¬
tator of the destruction of what is
really part of himself.
A few years ago, Jean Renoir, the
famous French director, was desper¬
ately looking for a copy of his film
The River, which he had shot in India
and which he so dearly loved. The
negative of the film was fast deteriorat¬
ing but the producer (a Hollywood
florist) was in no hurry to do anything
about it. In the absence of an ade¬
quate authorization, the laboratory was
reluctant to take out a print. One can
imagine Renoir's agony. As it hap¬
pens, the film has since been revived
commercially, but a master's work
could have been lost forever.
Not every film-maker, however, has
the means and the foresight of a
Renoir or a Chaplin (see box above).
Nor are the archives over-anxious to
save all the films. Most curators
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
L select films for preservation according
^to their pet preferences.
Are these preferences and preju¬
dices justified? Do we know which
of the current films will interest scho¬
lars 30 or a hundred years from now?
Doesn't this indifference towards some
and preference for others constitute
a kind of vandalism? I had better
leave the answer to the man most
qualified to give it, and who, more
than anyone else, has put the world
cinema in his debt: Henri Langlois.
In an interview with Rudolph Chel-
minski of Life, Langlois said: "The most
important role of a cinémathèque, is
to preserve. There are many things
which seem to be without value, to
which time gives style invisible today.
Baudelaire and the Eiffel Tower are
examples. Other cinémathèques be¬
fore the war had plenty of money and
could have saved many films. Why
didn't they succeed? Because they
thought of choosing, while they really
ought to have been thinking of saving
everything.
"Judging, like criticism, is a game.
It is gambling with the future. So I
take all films I have no reason to
refuse any of them. I even have films
I detest.
"I never accepted that films couldn't
be saved. Once I got a bunch of the
old films and sent them out to a lab
to be cleaned and put on new reels.
They sent them right back. They're
all stuck together, they said. You
might as well chuck them In the gar¬
bage can.
"Well, I'm just a poor dope, not a
chemist. So I sat down and unstuck
them image by image, washed off the
sections and hung them out to dry on
clothespins.
"After that I got stubborn and read
up on how to recondition films it's
all there in the books, you know, but
no one had ever bothered to look.
Everyone told me that films would
. only last 20 or 30 years at the most,
so what was the use of trying to keep
them? Well, we have some of the
very earliest silent films In our collec¬
tion and we're still waiting for them
to deteriorate."
Perhaps, this is a film lover's ap¬
proach. Certainly there aren't many
around. What is of paramount impor¬
tance is the preservation of films, all
films, no matter where produced. They
should be treated on a par with the
rest of our artistic heritage a heritage
in which all of us have a stake.
Bhagwan D. Garga
Dominique Darr. Paris
8 The development of lightweight, portable v'deo equipment has decentralized
television, freeing it from the confines of the studio. Video camera crews,
like these young people in an Indian village, today film and record things on
the spot as they happen. Many video groups use the new technique to provide
a forum for discussion of " grassroot " problems in the community.
Bp«íb8pBmBmíIb
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Portable videotape equipment now permits
people all over the world
to master the art of television
instead of being passively exposed to it
pWUROPEAN Ministers of
Culture, meeting under Unesco's
auspices in Helsinki, in June 1972,
noted with concern that the mass
media, while helping to extend access
to culture, also "fragment society and
induce a sense of alienation." They
consequently invited "the anonymous,
solitary and helpless spectator" to do
all he could to "break out of the pas¬
sive role to which he may be led."
But at a time when radio and tele¬
vision systems were expanding every¬
where a development strongly sup¬
ported by Unesco by what means
and at what cost could the television-
viewer, alone or in a group, be ensured
of effective participation in the pro¬
duction of information whose output
had hitherto been a one-way process?
To these questions a group of
experts meeting Jn Vichy about this
time under the auspices of the French
National Commission for Unesco,
proposed this tentative answer: por¬
table video.
This was the period when electronic
videotape recorders of an easy-to-
handle type, such as the "Portapack",
were beginning to . appear. These
combine cameras and recorders,
weigh less than twenty pounds, are
battery-operated, give half an hour's
continuous shooting and record
extremely precise ¡mages of 300 to
400 lines on half-inch or 2/3 inch video¬
tape. Their price Is less than that of a
low-powered car.
Some might have thought that this
possibility of being recorded on tape
and viewing oneself immediately on a
screen was at most a technical
gimmick, a sort of electronic polaroid
camera.
Others saw portable video as a
useful instrument for making in-depth
analyses of individual performances,
suited, for Instance, to helping
Olympic champions perfect their
HENRI DIEUZEIDE is director of Unesco's
division of methods, materials and tech¬
niques in education and director of "Pros¬
pects", Unesco's quarterly review of education.
An expert in audio-visual teaching methods, he
created and directed the educational radio
and television department of France's Natio¬
nal Pedagogical Institute. He has made a
number of films on teaching and has written
several books on education, including "Les
Techniques Audio-Visuelles de l'Enseigne¬
ment" (Audio-Visual Techniques In Education)
which has been translated into five languages.
swimming-stroke or their sprint, or for
door-to-door salesmen to improve the
technique of "putting their foot in the
door."
But even at this early stage, in a
few industrialized countries this new
technique began to be used for social
action, and it has continued to be
developed along these lines ever
since.
In New York, the People's Video
Theater started up, along with the Rain-
dance Corporation, Global Village
(named for the expression coined by
Marshall McLuhan), Videofreex and
Urban Video; in California, the Mafundi
Institute, Videofree America and the
Media Access Center. In Canada
there was Matrix Video in Vancouver,
and in Great Britain, the VTX London
Video Co-op. In France, Collectif
Vidéo and Video Out were founded in
Paris and Vidéo Gazette in Grenoble.
The groups which survived this
period were those which were able
to obtain political and financial support.
Some became connected with uni¬
versities or television organizations.
In Canada, a "social action group"
called Société Nouvelle in Quebec and
Challenge for Change in the other
provinces has been financed since
1971 by the National Film Board.
Challenge for Change is designed "to
improve communication, create greater
understanding, promote new ideas
and provoke social change."
In France, since 1972, the Centre
National d'Animation Audio-Visuelle
(National Audio-Visual Centre) created
by the Fonds d'Intervention Culturelle
(Fund for Cultural Action) has been
supporting some video groups.
In the United States, despite their
precarious institutional footing, most
of these groups are going concerns:
some have contracts with foundations
or federal bodies and hire out video
equipment by the day, hold seminars
and even courses counting as credits
at university and provide training
sessions for adult organizations and
for industry. Some have opened up
"video theatres" to which admission
is charged, or produce documentaries
to order on local or family celebrations.
All in all, there are around a hundred
active "alternative video" groups
scattered through the United States
and Canada, Japan and Western
Europe, and Unesco is currently
studying their activities.
Most of these groups still show
signs of their origins in the under¬
ground and in protest movements.
Although they obviously take their
inspiration from the underground
press, which is written, distributed and
revamped by its readers, they are
more concerned with fulfilling an
"ecological" role: while opposed to
"visual pollution", they consider that
the biological equilibrium of the indi¬
vidual depends on his being fed
information. "An image-addict loses
the ability to evolve", they say. "To
survive in a communicational environ¬
ment, one needs to have and to master
the tools of communication."
For this reason they reject tele¬
vision, which they regard as an
industrial, prefabricated product, and
have come to spearhead the major
critical movement which sees mass
communication as an archaic instru¬
ment and a source of alienation.
u'NDOUBTEDLY more in¬
fluenced by cybernetics than its Euro¬
pean counterpart, the new American
generation is indeed particularly con¬
scious of the one-sided, non-reversible
character of television and of the
passive rôle of the viewer on whom an
image is imposed without his being
able to project anything back in return.
They are also aware of the social
tensions and psychological deviations
which may result from this. A case in
point is that of the demonstrators in
Great Britain who suddenly brought
their demonstration to an end so as
to be able to get home in time to see
themselves on the news. One of the
aims of the video revolution is to give
back to the passive viewer, who has
become an object, his essential
dignity as a subject.
With the "Portapack", which makes
it possible instantaneously to repro¬
duce from life any event as It occurs
(an "electronic ball-point pen" they
call it in Quebec), the video groups
see an opportunity of removing the
barrier which exists between the
producer and the consumer.
Unlike conventional television, what
is recorded can immediately be seen A
and discussed. Each individual viewer H
can participate in the process. What
counts is no longer mass response ^
but individual exchanges and inter- F
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
TELEVISION IN THE STREET
Portable video equipment is today being widely used as a tool for
community development. In the province of Emilia-Romagna, in
Italy, for example, the provincial authorities have provided various
groups (workers, teachers, lawyers, students, etc.) with video
sets to record TV films for broadcasting throughout the region.
Right, one of these groups interviews a passer-by on Piazza Verdi
In Bologna.
In Africa, video tape recording is being used in the countryside
of Tanzania experimentally to open a dialogue between village
groups and local and central government as part of the country's
creation of the Ujamaa community villages. Unesco is studying
the setting up in Tanzania of a video centre to train the villagers
to use this new type of communication for development.
10
actions, creating via the image a two-
way traffic. Video provides a com¬
munication process and not consumer
products: it is a tool for bringing
people together, not a means of
isolating them.
What these groups are trying to do,
for instance, is to arrange for every
recording to be seen and discussed
by people in a group, at the same time
recording the discussion so that the
viewers become participants in the
first recording, at one remove. In this
way, instead of there being one-way
communication, there is multi-direc¬
tional communication which, like
mirror-play, can go on indefinitely and
is both creative and liberating.
Despite the few attempts that have
been made by American groups to
create a "video art", most of these
groups deliberately seek not to create
finished works. Of course, sometimes
they do not have the means or the
technical skill, but on the whole what
they are out to obtain is a totally un-
contrived and even stark visual effect.
Their messages are "open-ended",
capable of being constantly modified
close-ups of faces in the street, people
casually % or vigorously exchanging
words, slices of life, visual fantasies.
The ¡mage recorded on the tape is
ephemeral by nature: it can be erased,
in time it fades. A work which is
unfinished bears the mark of authen¬
ticity: what is produced is an un-
embellished image and not the
finished result of an elaborate organ¬
izational process. Video is to tele¬
vision what the "happening" is to
traditional theatre.
Although politically, aesthetically
and morally opposed to traditional
television, these groups do not seem
to be really concerned about forming
pressure-groups aimed at influencing
the mass media. Their concept of
alternative television does not hinge
on a desire to programme the system
differently but rather on the desire
for a different system or even for a
complete absence of system in which
everyone would be both a spectator
and an actor.
Although they often take as their
slogan "guerrilla television", these
groups generally appear to be pro¬
foundly "non-violent". They want
neither to take over nor to destroy
existing television organizations, but to
deprofessionalize and de-institution
alize them. They are tired of "public ,
writers" holding a monopoly on
writing for a people of illiterates.
From this ferment of activity, which
is leading people to speak out, or
rather to attempt the difficult task of
mastering the still relatively undevelop¬
ed medium of visual communication,
a certain number of trends seem to
be emerging.
First of all, video Is used in social
therapy by bringing people into
contact with images of themselves
recorded in conditions of complete
freedom and spontaneity, .and in this
way, relations between them are
transformed: the camera does not lie
and one's own image becomes a
source of self revelation.
In America, psychiatrists have begun
treating problem-families using re¬
cordings made in their homes. At the
psychiatric hospital of La Chesnaye
in France, patients have been produc¬
ing their own programmes since 1971.
More generally, the image serves to
bring people into relationship with
each other, providing a way out of
situations of conflict by making them
talk about problems which directly
concern them. The free image spells
free communication.
It has become common practice in
America to establish "visual records"
for the authorities on the basis of
recordings of protests, grievances,
proposals and discussions within a
community. In France, a team travel¬
ling in a videobus through villages
in the Landes, carried out an exper¬
iment aimed at getting communities to
express their views on the develop¬
ment of the Aquitaine region.
The most significant advances have
been made in Quebec with "Vidéo-
graphe", a combined video work¬
shop, theatre, public forum and dis¬
tribution centre. As early as 1971 for
the first time a professional television
crew was placed, twenty-four hours a
day, at the service of all citizens
wishing to produce and present to a
public of their choice a programme
over which they had total control.
Today, after using video to pioneer
community TV and help revitalize the
economically failing rural areas of the
Saint-Jean Lake region and the poor
districts of Montreal, the Quebec
video-operators plan to take a video-
bus to the Indians of Abitibi and to
thirty or so deprived parishes in the
remote area of Gaspésie so as to give
the people there the chance to air
their views.
In the province of Emilia-Romagna
in Italy, efforts have been made to
"reverse the flow of information
between leadership and the grass
roots" by providing groups (factories,
schools, housing estates, hospitals)
with portable equipment to enable
them freely to express their points of
view.. Here, in contrast with the
"Vidéographe" project, it is the
organized group and not the indi¬
vidual citizen that is given the chance
to speak.
In New York, the black communities
of Harlem and the Puerto Ricans of
East Side have taken part in re¬
cordings in which group spokesmen
were invited to express their opinions
about "those on the other side" and
then to examine these opinions
together, the discussions being re¬
corded in their turn.
In the Bronx, a vast campaign
organized by Hunter College provided
a large number of the inhabitants
with the opportunity to speak about
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
m9
the various possible futures that they
wanted for their district. In various
instances in the United States the use
of video at key-moments in situations
of racial conflict in communities seems
to have acted as a safety-valve.
There is no escaping the fact,
however, that these attempts to stimu¬
late social communication have a
tendency to bring out latent conflicts
and that, here and there, they have
presented the authorities with a few
problems. After agreeing to give their
support to community relations activi¬
ties based on the use of video, some
mayors have been criticized by their
own electors, to the surprise of
everyone.
Education itself has been affected.
It has been observed that young
people born around 1960, those who
in the United States are called the "VT
generation" (videotape) in contrast
with the earlier, "TV generation",
display considerable expertise in the
use of portable videotape recorders
and that they readily make use of them
to express their views on society and
on the future. This generation is out
to master the image for itself instead
of being passively exposed to it.
In Washington, an experiment is
currently being carried out in which
a group of a hundred or so children
is being provided with video equip¬
ment and being given the task of
preparing a series of visual projects
aimed at bringing improvements to the
city.
In Philadelphia, the Clinton Project
represents a very enterprising effort to
get young school-children to use
mobile video so as to improve their
perceptive awareness and personal
interaction.
Video is also beginning to be used
by teachers for their own professional,
and especially in-service, training at
most training colleges in the United
States. This is true to an even greater
extent in Great Britain, where portable
equipment belonging to the Inner
London Education Authority is used to
record what is known as micro-
teaching, i.e. schoolwork performed in
small groups. The recording is sub¬
sequently subjected to detailed critical
analysis by the teacher concerned, by
other teachers and by the pupils, so
as gradually to define an ¡deal refer¬
ence model for improving interactions
between teachers and pupils and
between videotape-operators and
groups.
Recent studies carried out at the
University of Lausanne show that the
industrial applications of video should
help to establish new relations between
management and workers. Within the
factory or company, video makes it
possible to provide an overall view
of the organization and to simplify
descriptions of its activities, thanks
for instance to the visual analysis of
jobs. It enables viewpoints to be
compared and brings out the con¬
tradictions between real-life situations
and the formal reality of regulations.
Lastly, mention should be made of
the temptation to turn video into a
new political weapon. The American
groups that have moved on from a
very militant conception of the use
of video to more pragmatic views,
often express their surprise in face of
the tendency of most European video
groups to broadcast a traditional
political speech.«
CONTINUED PAGE 32
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
From the snail to the galaxy
Nature has evolved an infinity of
SPIRALS
by Gerald Oster
m ROM microscopic marine
shells to the celestial galaxies, spirals
abound in Nature. In geometric terms,
a spiral is a plane curve that winds
around a central point while moving
ever farther from or closer to it. The
figure is thus produced by the com-'
bined operations of rotation and ex¬
pansion or contraction.
The essential feature of a spiral is
that a straight line drawn from the
centre to the curve, known as the
radius vector, changes in length with
the rotation. A tight spiral has a small
change in its radius vector for a given
amount of turning, an open spiral has
a large change.
The extreme example of a tight
spiral is a circle, a figure produced
by pure rotation in which the radius
remains constant. The extreme case
of an open spiral is a straight line.
Here the figure is produced by pure
expansion without any rotation and
the radius is infinite.
The ancient Greeks were evidently
fascinated by the spiral. They in¬
corporated it in the capitals of their
Ionic . columns and based many of
their vases, such as the amphoras,
on whole or partial spirals. Typically
for the Greeks, all of these man-made
12
GERALD OSTER Is professor of biophysics
at Mount Sinai School of Medicine of the
City University of New York. A pioneer in
the study of moiré patterns, he has written
"The Science of Moiré Patterns', published
by Edmund Scientific, Barrington, New Jer¬
sey, 1969. (Moiré patterns are formed when
two regular patterns overlap, and have various
uses in scientific research, including the
examination of the atomic structure of crys¬
tals.) Professor Oster is currently research¬
ing into questions of human reproduction.
curves followed strict mathematical
rules.
There are many kinds of spirals;
their differences depend on the
manner In which the length of the
radius vector changes with angle of
turning. Perhaps the simplest spiral
to conceive of is the one discovered
by Archimedes in the 3rd century B.C.
and described in some detail In his
book On Spirals.
The Archimedes spiral is the figure
produced by a sailor when he coils
a rope. While each turn moves the
curve uniformly farther and farther
from its centre, the distance between
adjacent coils remains constant. In
other words, the length of the radius
vector is proportional to the angle of
rotation.
Some other examples of this type
of spiral can be illustrated by the
movements of an imaginary ant. If an
ant was to move outward from the
centre of a rotating turntable at a
constant velocity in what it presumed
to be a straight line, it would actually
be moving in an Archimedes spiral.
The functioning of the common
record player is the ant trick in
reverse. The pickup arm, guided by
the needle, is constrained to follow
the Archimedes spiral groove of the
record and hence moves from the
outside inward at a uniform velocity.
If an ant was trained to climb up
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
From the galaxy to the atom, spi¬
rals abound In Nature, appearing
whenever there is outward growth
combined with rotation. Here we
show four examples: (1) A nautilus
shell, the perfect example of an
equiangular spiral, its structure here
revealed by X-ray; (2) A spiral galaxy
seen in the heaveYis as a diffused
luminous mass and similar in form
to our own galaxy; (3) Nuclear part¬
icles visible as a spiral in a nuclear
research bubble chamber; (4) A
spiral formed by a drop of oil on a
glass plate turning at constant speed.
a cone at a constant slant, its course
a conical helix when viewed from
above, would be seen to be an Archi¬
medes spiral. Similarly, mountain
roads that ascend at a constant incli¬
nation appear in aerial views as such
spirals.
Crystals that grow around imperfec¬
tions, called screw dislocations, in the
orderly arrangement of their atoms
exhibit the Archimedes spiral.
Electron micrographs of a cross
section of developing nerve fibres in
prenatal human life and in infants up
to about a year old also show an
Archimedes spiral. This suggests that
the nerve covering, or the myelin
sheath, is laid down like the insulation
wrapped around an electrical wire.
Another wrapped spiral structure in
the body is the organ of hearing with¬
in the ear, the cochlea, which gets its
name from the Greek word for snail.
Let us return to the ant climbing
up the cone. If, as it nears the top,
it becomes progressively more tired
and takes a path of diminished slope,
the spiral it describes will become
tighter and tighter. If the ant's degree
of tiredness follows a geometric
progression, the spiral will be of the
type known as equiangular.
The equiangular spiral has been the
subject of considerable study since
the French philosopher and mathema¬
tician René Descartes first correctly
defined it In 1638, In this figure, as
the name implies, the spiral cuts all
Its radii at the same angle. The
smaller that angle, the more open the
spiral; conversely, the larger the angle, ^
the tighter the spiral. r
ma / k:
f¿ prjpp --I / / * S=
\
\
\
. . . « . vl
- " >
- ft"^ r;i, ^T,T_ 1 > 1 /
ri^ali~.-i L/All pppppi- ».
v' <C -XT' -1 -JL "^-« --Vj^ '-i
.~r . -^-jjpjpj
r^r-s?5H»
V \ ^
-:< -:¿£
Photo © Alvaraz Group, University of California
Photo 0 Jekabs Zvilna
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
If a sea captain should stubbornly
order his ship to follow a fixed com¬
pass course, the vessel would cut the
meridians at a constant angle and the
projected curve it would follow would
thus be an equiangular spiral. In
theory, such a course would cause
the ship to spiral into either the North
or South Pole.
Flying ants follow an equiangular
trajectory when moving toward a
source of light; a peculiarity of the
insect's eye causes it to maintain a
fixed angle of approach. A pilot will
also often follow an equiangular
trajectory when homing toward an
airport.
Strictly speaking, if the climbing and
flying ants, the sea captain, and the
pilot followed a true equiangular spiral,
they would never reach their destina¬
tions. Destinations sought by such a
course are called asymptotic poles;
they can be approached but never
reached.
Among the special properties of
the equiangular spiral is the fact that
the radii increase exponentially in
length as the curve moves away from
the centre. It was the Swiss mathema¬
tician Jacob Bernoulli who demon¬
strated in 1698 that the logarithm of
the radius is proportional to the angle
of rotation.
Because of its logarithmic character,
the equiangular spiral is also called
the logarithmic spiral. In his investiga¬
tion of this spiral Bernoulli noted
that if any part of the curve is en¬
larged, thereby tending to flatten it,
the segment will exactly match some
other part of the same spiral.
This invariant property so impressed
him that he ordered that his tomb¬
stone be inscribed with a logarithmic
spiral and the motto "although changed
I always come back the same". The
stonecutter got the motto right but
unfortunately chiselled an Archimedes
spiral by mistake.
The equiangular spiral expands
rapidly with the rotation of the figure.
With its swirling arm and exponentially
expanding radius, it seems a more
dynamic form than the plodding, slowly
changing Archimedes spiral.
There are many examples of equi¬
angular spirals in nature: the web of
the spider Epeira, the scales of the
pine cone, the florets of the daisy
and the giant sunflower, the shoots
of flowering cymose plants, the struc¬
ture of hurricanes.
Perhaps the most nearly perfect
equiangular spiral to be found is the ©
shell of the chambered nautilus. The |
chambers of this mollusc shell grow ¿
SPIRALLING FLOWERS
CITIES AND HERDS
From pine-cones to cauliflowers, from pineapples to
sunflowers, the seeds, petals and leaves of the plant
world are often arranged in spiral form. This was per¬
ceptively observed by the famous Japanese painter
Hokusai (1760-1849), as this flower painting shows
(below). The plan of Auroville in India (left) shows how
urban growth may take spiral form; its whorls are
similar to those of Hokusai's Japanese flower. Right,
a herd of reindeer takes fright, turning in on itself in
a tight spiral formation as it stampedes.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
in size in a geometric progression;
the curve cuts the radius vector at
an angle of 85 degrees. The shell
grows larger within a fixed form, that
is, it grows without a change in mor¬
phology. Given these conditions, the
only shape it can take is a spiral.
As with all true equiangular spirals,
a magnified view of a horizontal
section through the pole, or centre,
looks identical to the whole curve.
The nautilus shell grows at one end
only and in this respect it resembles
the horns of the rhinoceros or moun¬
tain goat, which also have some spiral
character.
Tiny marine organisms called for-
aminfera, which inhabit all marine
waters, also have shells shaped like
crude equiangular spirals. In fossil¬
ized form, these shells make up the
material of chalk cliffs and much of
the ooze on the ocean bottom.
Some foraminfera shells turn clock-
ART, LIKE NATURE, has adopted the
spiral as the form which lends itself most
readily to regular and simultaneous expan¬
sion in length and width and also height
in forms evolving around a central point.
One example is the helicoidal form of this
17th-century portrayal of the tower of
Babel (opposite page), rising upwards like
the shell of the fossilized gasteropod (left),
whose whorls coil around a hollow axis.
wise, others turn counterclockwise,
from the apex of the shell. The
direction of rotation depends on the
temperature of the water at the time
of the shell's growth.
By studying the ratio of clockwise
to counterclockwise shells in ocean
bottoms, it is possible to ascertain the
relative temperatures that probably
pertained during the Ice Age some
600,000 to 1,000,000 years ago, when
these shells originally grew.
Geologists have utilized the direc¬
tion of coiling of foraminfera shells in
petroleum exploration to make stratifi¬
cation correlations between various oil
wells and determine whether they are
part of the same bed.
How spiral growth commences is
something of a mystery. In all em¬
bryonic structures, cells are ordin¬
arily laid down radially In the first
few cleavages. The spiral character of
spiral organisms is visible after the
third cleavage, when 23 or eight cells
have been formed. The spiraling
characteristic is apparently a property
of the original starting cell.
In that connexion, it is of interest
that the majority of identical twins
have hair whorls that turn in opposite
directions and the same pairs of .
identical twins that have that form of r
Photo © Wideroes Flyveselskap, Norway
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
THE PAINTER
AND THE SPIDER
In his painting "Dialectic" (detail
shown here), the Italian Renaissance
artist Paolo Veronese depicts the
Greek myth of Arachne the weaver,
who enraged the goddess Athena
and was changed into a spider. In
spinning their webs, spiders follow
a spiral movement (see "Unesco
Courier", December 1969). This fact
escaped Veronese, who incorrectly
showed a web consisting of parallel
polygons.
16
mirror imagery also often exhibit
differences In right- and left-handed-
ness and reversed dental asymmetry.
The grandest of all spirals are the
spiral galaxies, which measure thou¬
sands of light years in diameter. They
are clusters of stars in the form of
multi-armed crude equiangular spirals
with centres at a common pole. About
50 per cent of all galaxies are spirals.
The form of the majority of these is
the same; they are double 73 degree,
equiangular spirals.
Our own galaxy, usually called the
Milky Way galaxy, is a spiral. The
earth is about 25,000 light years, or
approximately halfway, from the centre,
and, along with neighbouring stars,
rotates around it at the rate of about
150 miles per second.
It was once thought that a spiral
galaxy was like a rotating pinwheel
firecracker with stars being thrown out
from the centre. Recent observations
show this interpretation to be incorrect,
although at present astrophysicists
are generally at a loss to explain the
origin of spiral galaxies.
Such is not the case with the spiral
form of hurricanes, which can be clear¬
ly seen in aerial photographs. Warm
moist air rising in the storm system
and subject to the earth's rotation
produces a vortex motion, which cre¬
ates the spiral cloud formation. The
rotation of the vortex of a hurricane
is clockwise in the southern hemi¬
sphere and counterclockwise in the
northern hemisphere.
Counter spirals, those whose direc¬
tion has been reversed, appear in the
seed patterns of many plants. The
florets of the daisy and the sunflower
are arranged along sets of intersecting
equiangular spirals, one of which
rotates clockwise, the other counter¬
clockwise, from the plant's head.
The florets increase in age, and
hence in size, as the curves move
out from the centre. In the daisy
there are 21 clockwise spirals and 34
counterclockwise ones. In the giant
sunflower there are usually 34 clock¬
wise and 55 counterclockwise spirals,
but the largest of these flowers may
contain 89 clockwise and 144 counter¬
clockwise spirals.
The seeds of the pine cone and of
the pineapple are likewise laid down
as spirals; five clockwise and eight
counterclockwise in the pine cone;
eight clockwise and thirteen counter¬
clockwise in the pineapple.
The numbers of spirals in these
plants are successive terms of a
series called the Fibonacci sequence,
named for the twelfth-century Italian
mathematician credited with devising
it. The Fibonacci series is 1, 1, 2, 3, 5,
8, 13, 21, 34, 55, 89, 144 and so forth,
each number being the sum of the
two previous numbers.
So far, we have described spirals
.in terms of how the length of the
radius vector, or the distance from
the centre, changes with the angle of
turning. Spirals can be equally well
defined in terms of the manner in
which the amount of curvature changes
as one moves along the figure.
Thus, in an equiangular spiral, an
arc along the curve tends to flatten
out as one moves away from the
centre. In the circle, of course, an
arc taken anywhere along the figure
has the same amount of curvature as
any other arc.
There is yet another kind of spiral,
called a clothoid, from the Greek word
for spin, which has. two poles, or
centres, and two arms that curve in
reversed directions. In this figure, the
curvature becomes tighter the farther
one moves from a point midway bet¬
ween the poles. Each arm of the
clothoid, known also as Euler's spiral
for the Swiss mathematician who dis¬
covered it in 1744, resembles the
mainspring of a watch whose torque
on a shaft remains constant regardless
of how tightly the spring is wound.
Many individuals have hair that
curves in the form of one arm of a
clothoid. Hair like that Is flatter in
cross section than straight hair. Micro¬
scopic examination shows that one side
of such hair expands more with
moisture than the other side. The
expansion of the moisture-sensitive
side forces hair to curl over. Develop¬
ing ferns similarly often take on the
appearance of a clothoid arm due to
the unequal growth rate of the cells
at the tip of the plant.
In pondering on spirals, can we
find an underlying generality to
account for their existence from atoms
to galaxies? The most we can safely
say without blundering into anthropo¬
morphic or teleological philosophizing
is that wherever there is outward
growth, or a radial force, combined
with rotation, "a spiral is created.
Gerald Oster
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Carved and painted in 1867, this
tombstone at Bogojevic (Yugoslavia)
depicts a villager, Uros Simeunovic,
holding his son by the hand and his
horse by the reins. Everyday objects,
ornaments, animals and birds are
often portrayed alongside human
figures in this Serbian gravestone
art (see also back cover).
UNUSUAL TOMBSTONE ART
OF YUGOSLAVIA
'*: Si
Folk images carved
and painted
by 19th-century
Serbian artists
by
Dusan Stanimirovic
HE Southern Slavs are
known to have practised a funerary
art in the days when as nomads they
first came to the Balkans and began
peopling regions which bore the stamp
of a strong Hellenistic influence and
of Roman occupation. Traces of this
art have survived in the form of carved
and decorated wooden tombs, a few
of which can still be seen in the
Belgrade Ethnographical Museum.
Then, in the course of time, stone
was substituted for wood. Perhaps
the transformation of a nomadic civi¬
lization into a sedentary one imposed
the choice of stone because of its
permanent quality. Or perhaps it
followed naturally from contact with
builders and hewers of stone. Stone
was already dominant in the 14th and
15th centuries, especially in Bosnia,
with its funeral monuments of the
Bogomil religious sect, and to a lesser
extent in Serbia. These gravestones
were sculpted and in most cases in¬
cluded a representation of the human
figure.
Whatever the case may be, the
beginning of the 19th century saw a
sudden and remarkable development
of a specific tombstone art, which
flourished and reached its peak during
that century. It was still in evidence
at the beginning of the 20th century,
CONTINUED PAGE 20
DUSAN STANIMIROVIC, of Yugoslavia, is
an engineer whose career has taken him to
many countries and given him the opportunity
to take striking and original photographs,
which have earned him recognition as one
of the world's outstanding amateur photo¬
graphers.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
PORTRAITS
An unusual form of popular art the carving
and decoration of tombstones grew up
and flourished in central Serbia during the
19th century. The artists depicted human
figures with surprising realism and a sharp
eye for detail as these examples show.
(1) Soldier from the village of Mrcajevci,
carrying a pistol thrust through his belt.
(2) Young woman of Tresnjevica, wearing
earrings and a flowered headdress. (5) Old
lady of Pogled carrying her gloves and
umbrella. (3) Traces of paint that survive
show how it was used to accentuate such
details as the moustache and eyebrows of
this soldier. (4) Rain and wind have effac¬
ed all traces of paint from this head, giv¬
ing its features an expression of power
and serenity.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
TOMBSTONE ART (Continued trom page 17)
20
but apart from a few exceptions, it
has virtually disappeared today.
Originating in central Serbia, this
form of art is mainly concentrated in
the Sumadija region south of Belgrade,
where the towns of Kragujevac, Cacak,
Ivanica and Titovo Uzice are situated.
Its emergence was not an isolated
phenomenon, and it is not confined to
a few scattered places. The art was
practised in all the villages and small
towns of Sumadija and sometimes
beyond the bounds of that artistically
well-endowed region. It consisted
essentially of representing the dead
and perpetuating their memory by
detailing who and what they were and
what they did in carved and painted
stone.
Here we see everyday people, the
objects they used, the emblems of
their craft or profession, and very
often to one side of the slab, a tree
of life ending in a flourish of leaves
. pecked by a dove, representing the
. dead person's soul.
The mere depiction of a person's
life, however, sometimes takes second
place to portrayal of character. A
coquettish woman gives you a flirta¬
tious glance; a pessimist with down-
turned mouth evokes eternal dis¬
appointment; elsewhere the radiance
of contemplation and the inner life is
suggested by lowered eyes. And
everywhere there are soldiers, single
or in groups, frozen to eternal atten¬
tion, witnesses to lost battles and
vanquished illusions.
A whole motionless world of people
is represented, for whom the salvation
of the soul or the satisfaction of bodily
desires are cares of the past.
The originality of this art is beyond
question, and its variety amazing. It
is obviously related to an authentic
popular peasant art, and an attentive
and curious mind could today form an
Idea of the evolution of Serbian society
from peasant to urban life, using
only these gravestones as a guide.
What explains the extraordinary and
unexpected quality of what one would
a priori be tempted to consider a minor
art? The answer is that these artists
are true masters, and that their work
shows great originality and spontaneity.
It contains a real emotional element
which, though sometimes subtly
restrained, is invariably present, and is
often humorous.
This should really come as no sur¬
prise, for the Serbian people have
always felt an innate need both to
endure and to express their desire
for permanence. Even in a peasant
society with extremely limited possi¬
bilities the gifted found a natural outlet
for their creative talent in this humble
form of painted sculpture rooted in
the earth and the customs of daily life.
This is the explanation of its richness
and variety.
However, the development of urban
civilization changed the sources of
inspiration of these artists, whose
vocational talent was gradually super¬
seded by purely professional skill. The
very few craftsmen who still cut these
tombstones today possess neither the
technical mastery, nor the freshness
of inspiration, nor the spontaneity of
execution of the old masters.
Most of these tombstones were
worked in bas-relief and in some cases
there is no more than a simple outline
cut into the stone, with no relief at
all. Some were sculpted in the round,
but these are extremely rare.
It is highly probable that at first the
sculptors used white marble from the
quarries of Studenica, whose stone¬
cutters had been famous throughout
the country from time immemorial.
Although close examination reveals a
few traces of paint on these marble
tombstones, the very fine grain of the
marble prevented colour from holding
firmly.
Later on a highly porous stone was
used which was a conglomerate of
very fine particles; this had the advan¬
tage of being more easily worked than
marble and of absorbing the paint,
thus preserving the colours. In other
cases the porous stone has an overlay
of finer porosity which acted as a
support for the colour.
Some tombstones are engraved with
phrases and maxims describing how
the person died or his or her quirks of
character. Here are some examples:
"Alasl I am like a drooping flower
which has bloomed too soon and
withered fast, like a rose in the
burning sun."
"Far from home, the flowers of
Serbia will never bloom upon my1
grave. Tell my loved ones that I
shall never more return."
"He died against his will, struck
down by the hand of the guard in
the presence of the authorities."
(This is an elliptical way of saying
that he was executed.)
"Come closer, beloved brother and
traveller, I have nothing against you.
See where my youth is laid to rest."
"Here in calm repose lies Kruna,
first wife of Ljubomir Tadlc. She
was weary and wanted rest. May
she forgive us for having sinned.
Her bereaved husband Ljubomir and
his second wife Ljubovanka."
"Here I lie at rest while you look
at me. I wish you were in my place
and I could be looking at you."
These gravestones give no impres¬
sion of despair, but rather a certain
melancholy, great serenity, resigned
acceptance of a fate which was some¬
times unjust, a simple philosophy of
life and a sense of humour.
In their turn the works are slowly
dying under the assault of wind and
weather, time and neglect.
Dusan Stanimirovic
Plan of central Paris
shows the location of
two neighbouring sites
in one of the oldest parts
of the city, which are
today being redeveloped
in a bold programme of
urban planning. At right
of plan, the Beaubourg
Centre, already under
construction. It will be
rary <
brary, moi
lections, advanced au¬
diovisual equipment,
etc. At top of plan, the
former site of the
come a vast leisure and
commercial complex.
a»*4
Paris gets
a
new heart
by Nino Frank
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
A bold project
is changing
the appearance
and cultural life
of the
French capital
lI T goes without saying that
urbanism can have some influence on
the development of new and expanding
cities. It can reconcile the imperatives
of growth with the need to insert
buildings elegantly and rationally into
the environment.
In great old cities this is not the
case. They took shape slowly and
often capriciously in the course of
centuries, and In most of them
especially in their "historic centres"
only limited changes and sanitary
improvements are possible.
In these cities, everything flows
towards and converges on a densely
populated centre, where there is heavy
traffic, office buildings predominate,
NINO FRANK Is a Swiss writer and ¡ournalist
who specializes in cultural questions, parti¬
cularly literature and the cinema. He is the
author of several radio and television plays,
two volumes of memoirs, and books on
Paris literary and artistic life. He was for¬
merly a staff member in Unesco's Office of
Public Information.
Plan © Blondel la Rougery, ~ Paris
and the vestiges of the past have
accumulated. Here dwellings are
overcrowded and dilapidated. At the
heart of old cities there are often
vast Insalubrious areas where city
planners come up against a great
many largely insoluble problems.
We must renovate our surroundings
and adapt them to the future. But at
the same time there ¡s nothing we
can do with these city centres where
for centuries life has gone on in a
concentrated welter of activity, creat¬
ing a situation of virtually inextricable
complexity. Experts' dreams of re¬
creating these city centres or of
Infusing new life Into them can only
come true in the unlikely event of a
cataclysm.
In Paris this cataclysm has happened
and the urbanists' dreams have come
true. Of course, the va'st redevelop¬
ment operation now going on in the
heart of the city is exceptional. But
it is also instructive and fit to serve
as a model. Not surprisingly it is ^
attracting international interest. An r
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
22
additional and stronger reason for this
is that the French architects and
urbanists engaged on the project are,
in accordance with the wishes of the
authorities, working closely with
experts from other countries.
This bold . enterprise is underway
virtually at the geometric centre of
Paris, in the quarter which for cen¬
turies contained Paris's great central
markets Les Halles Centrales
among streets which formed part of
the great road, dating from the early
Middle Ages, which led from Flanders
to the Mediterranean and crossed
Paris from north to south. Later,
another great highway led from the
Marais quarter in the east, the centre
of Paris at the time of the Valois kings,
to the wooded suburbs in the west.
At the intersection of these two great
roads, Les Halles were built.
In the course of time the quarter
became cluttered and dilapidated
through the volume of traffic which
met there. This deterioration took
place in two separate areas which
circumstances have now combined to
join together.
To the west of the north-south axis
lay the Halles, with their bustling
nocturnal activity, their convoys of
lorries bringing loads of produce In
from the countryside, and their great
piles of refuse. The great French
novelist Emile Zola was inspired to
name one of his novels after this
teeming quarter, which he called "Le
ventre de Paris" the belly of Paris.
To the east is one of the oldest
quarters in the city, known as Beau¬
bourg because it was once a suburb
("faubourg") called beautiful ("beau")
because of the allure of the ladies who
lived ¡n it. From the end of the Middle
Ages, when the great Lombard finan¬
ciers did business there, until the time
of the Scottish financier John Law
and his spectacular bankruptcy in the
18th century, the neighbourhood was
a great banking district. Then It de¬
teriorated and in time became the most
decrepit and noisome part of Paris.
Photo Centre Beaubourg, Paris
About 40 years ago, the narrow
alleys of Beaubourg had become
sordid slums. Its tottering buildings
were condemned and razed to the
ground. The resulting big patch of
waste ground soon fell into the tenta¬
cular clutches of Les Halles, for which
it became a much-needed parking lot.
And this is how it would have stayed
had not the Halles themselves, too
sprawling and too inadequate for their
task, been condemned after the
Second World War.
On 4 and 5 March, 1969, there took
place what has been called Paris's
removal operation of the century. The
markets left the famous metal pavilions
built by the architect Baltard during
the Second Empire and moved out to
the suburbs. In this way, they returned
to their original extra-mural state, for
back in the 12th century their site lay
outside the city walls.
This colossal transfer freed 15 hec¬
tares of land, ten of them where the
Halles had been, five at Beaubourg.
This was the golden opportunity for
the urbanists; now they could, not so
much improve, as recreate entirely the
centre of a great city.
Of course, plans to fill these empty
spaces with massige buildings soon
began to appear in a steady stream.
It was proposed to install ministries on
them, or to make them the site of the
University of Paris. But this would
have meant that one problem would
have been replaced by another. In¬
stead of congestion at night there
would have been even worse con¬
gestion by day. It was at this point,
fortunately, that other Ideas prevailed.
Why, it was asked, not turn these
15 hectares into an oasis in the heart
of the city, a resting place from the
daily, turmoil? And why not restore
to each site its own autonomous
personality? Why not create a com-
. mercial centre thus respecting one
of the quarter's traditional activities
and a leisure centre on the site of
the Halles?
Why not turn the Beaubourg site
into a cultural meeting place, espe¬
cially by transferring to it Paris's
modern art museums?
A fundamental stipulation of this
project was that the ground level of
each area should be a pedestrian
precinct where people will be able to
stroll at their ease.
Work on this vast project has been
going on for some time, and immense
gaping craters have been excavated
on each site. So vast and deep are
they that scenes for a film were shot
in one of them during a halt in the
work.
The operation is instructive for
several reasons, and the way in which
the architects have solved the prob¬
lems facing them is particularly
admirable.
The redevelopment of the larger site,
the former Halles, will be a long job.
If everything goes according to plan,
work will be completed by 1982 or
1983. There will be several buildings
above the surface, and also an ex-
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
H ;-Ü:íWv P^P^P^P^P^HP^P^M
M
"'
*»«iPiíiiiy¡
,-*- r,
jL
Z2r<_
1
*I
/U -i
II.
FROM CAR PARK
TO PALACE
OF CULTURE
A great cultural centre is to rise
In the heart of Paris . on the Place
Beaubourg, for many years used as a
car park (1). In the words of its director,
Robert Bordaz, the Beaubourg Centre
"will bring to the public the living and
immediate image of art in process of
creation". Architect's model (3) re¬
veals the original features of the
metal-ribbed structure with Its immense
glass windows. Visitors will move
from floor to floor on escalators (2
and 4) set in transparent tubes and
attached to the facade so as to leave
the maximum of free space within
the building itself.
traordinary five-storey underground
structure, extending 25 metres below
ground level and covering 50,000
square metres in the form of a hol-
lowed-out inverted pyramid. This is
the "forum", which will be an area to
walk and relax in. It will have shops,
restaurants and cinemas, and the
whole area will be open to daylight
through a set of terraces.
Another feature of the project will
endow the commercial centre and the
forum with a unique and delightful
atmosphere. There will be almost five
hectares of park around them: a riot
of vegetation and trees.
The English landscape architect
Russell Page, who is preparing the
plans for this park, wants it to be
planted not only with traditional city
trees, such as chestnuts and limes, but
with exotic ones, such as cedars from
the Himalayas, maples from Canada,
tulip trees from Virginia, and rowans
from Tibet, so that passersby can
look at trees in bloom all the year
round. In addition wonder of won
ders in Paris there will also be lawns,
where In fine weather people will be
allowed to walk or lie down, a stream,
and ponds at ground level where they
will be free to take a paddle.
One of these tree-lined walks (as
well as underground corridors for
those who want to avoid the traffic
in the streets above) will lead to the
other area being developed, where
the visitor will be In a totally different
world. Here, If there is any commerce
at all, it will be a commerce In new
ideas and new inventions in art and
culture. Here, in 1976 the Beaubourg
Centre will open its doors, under the
direction of M. Robert Bordaz,
former director-general of the French
national radio and television network.
It will be a remarkable building: resem¬
bling a kind of light, transparent, lumi¬
nous ship a ship whose superstruc¬
ture is now rising from the earth.
In the area is the Fountain of the
Innocents, the work of the great 16th-
century French sculptor Jean Goujon.
It brings to mind the medieval charnel-
house where, In the previous century,
the great poet of France's highways
and by-ways, François Villon, would
go and dream in front of a Danse
Macabre painted on the walls.
Also nearby was a cabaret which
during the reign of Louis XIV was the
meeting place of a corporation of
dancing masters led by a man known
as the King of the Violins. In 1661
this corporation was awarded the pri¬
vilege of a title: the Royal Academy
of Dance. Later it merged with the
Royal Academy of Music. These were
the beginnings of the Paris Opéra,
which still has these titles today.
In short, culture is no stranger here.
(International culture too, since the
story goes that Giovanni Boccaccio,
the 13th-century Italian author of the
Decameron, was born not far away.)
President Georges Pompidou an¬
nounced the foundation of the Beau- aa
bourg Centre in 1969, and after his £A
death last April, it was decided that ¡t
should bear his name. In a speech .
made in 1972, President Pompidou r
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
, expressed his feelings as follows: "I
passionately want Paris to have a
cultural centre which will be both a
museum and a centre for creativity, a
place where the plastic arts may take
their place beside music, the cinema,
books, and audiovisual research. And
of course, creativity can only mean
modern art, in constant evolution."
And so the original idea of a
museum to which the state-owned
modern art collections should be
transferred and then enriched has
broadened to embrace a whole concept
of living culture. The building itself
will be as spacious as a cathedral,
but above all It will have the non-stop
animation of life on board ship, as
Renzo Piano, one of the architects in
charge of the project, has pointed out.
"The analogy with a ship is accurate
in several respects: concerning the
structure, concerning its scale, and
above all concerning its relationship
with a moving environment." One
cannot help thinking of the motto on
Paris's coat of arms: 'Fluctuât nee
mergitur' (It floats and does not sink.)
In 1970 a competition was held for
this great development project. In
order to stress the international charac¬
ter of the undertaking, it was thrown
open to architects all over the world.
This was unprecedented for such an
operation in France. 681 sets of plans
were submitted, 491 of them from
countries other than France.
An initial choice of 31 was made by
the International jury, which included
Oscar Niemeyer (Brazil) and Philip
Johnson (U.S.A.). The final choice
was a project submitted by architects
Renzo Piano and Gianfranco Franchini
(Italy), and Richard Rogers (U.K.)
assisted by engineering consultants of
Ove Arup and Partners (U.K.). The
project combined extreme technical
audacity with purity and simplicity of
line.
As revealed by the mock-ups, the
Beaubourg Centre will be an Immense
cage of light, 42 metres high, 60 metres
wide, and 166 metres long. There will
be five storeys, each with an area of
7,500 square metres "enough for two
football pitches on each floor", as the
architects point out. There will be no
partitions nor pillars, and all machinery
air conditioning, electricity, etc. will
be at the top of the building.
Thus each floor will be totally free.
People will move between storeys on
escalators covered by transparent
screens. These escalators will be at
the side of the building, and it will
be an impressive experience to make
this diagonal climb. On one side the
visitor will be able to see what Is
going on inside the building; on the
other, as he climbs, he will have
Paris stretched out at his feet from
the towers of Notre-Dame, the Seine,
and the dome of the Pantheon to the
green countryside beyond. The visi¬
tor's first impression as he approaches
the Beaubourg Centre will be this mov¬
ing tide of people, rising and falling.
Inside the building, forming a
counterpoint to this decor, there will
be, first of all, the vast department
of the plastic arts for which the Beau¬
bourg Centre was originally con¬
ceived. This will cover a considerable
area, since it will house two institu¬
tions which already exist elsewhere in
Paris: the Paris Museum of Modern
Art, whose collections will take up
three floors of the vast glass palace,
and the National Centre of Contem¬
porary Art, which was created to
promote avant-garde art. There will
also be rooms for temporary exhibi¬
tions and an extensive documentation
service.
For the first five years, the Swedish
museologist Pontus Hulten will be in
charge of this department. In 1956 he
created the Moderna Museet in
Stockholm, and has since won a
world-wide reputation for his depar¬
tures from the conventions of tradi¬
tional museum presentation i.e., sim¬
ply exhibiting famous works and letting
them speak for themselves and for
his conception of "art in movement".
For it is not enough simply to exhibit
a picture or the entire work of artists
such as Chirico, Picasso or Härtung.
To understand art forms with which
it is unfamiliar, the public needs to
appreciate the techniques, the thinking
and the feeling which go into their
creation. To understand an artist's
work, it is indispensable to have a
SURVIVAL
OF THE INNOCENTS
The Fountain of the Innocents, a 16th-cen¬
tury work by the great French sculptor
Jean Goujon, stands on the site now being
excavated as part of the Halles develop¬
ment project in central Paris. Above, the
fountain as it was before work began. Top
photo, to protect it during the excavations
it has been placed in a metal case sup¬
ported by steel props. (See also photo
opposite page.)
Photo J. Quldeau © Gamma, Paris
24
CANYON
IN THE CITY
Right, horsemen riding through
the rubble of the Halles develop¬
ment site are actors in a film made
by the Italian director Marco Ferrer!.
Opposite page, global view of the
gaping crater from which a com¬
mercial and recreational complex
will rise. The Fountain of the
Innocents (see photos above) In its
protective coffer set on stilts can
be seen In centre background.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
grasp, not only of the social and his¬
torical conditions In which he lived but
of the total artistic context in which he
worked music, literature, and films,
for example. Thus one might present
a Cubist painting by Picasso, for
example, by also showing an African
mask against the background of a
Spanish landscape, in an atmosphere
created by readings of Apollinaire's
poems and the performance of music
composed by Erik Satie for the Bal¬
lets Russes. "People must have the
chance to be surprised", says Pontus
Hulten. "We must give them an oppor¬
tunity to react, to accept or to reject."
Books, films, microfilms, recordings
and manuscripts will be available in
a Documentation Centre, where there
will also be exhibition rooms and ex¬
perimental galleries. Artists will be
able to work in studios forming part
of the Centre.
Another important section of the
Beaubourg Centre will be an industrial
design centre, concerned with every¬
thing from objects to urbanism on a
large scale which contributes to the
forming and transforming of the
environment. A computer-controlled
filing system, extending over 2,000
square metres, will answer questions
put by experts and the public. Tem¬
porary exhibitions will be held, and
there will be a retrospective gallery
devoted to the historical development
of industrial design, throughout the
world.
But culture also and primarily
means reading. Thus the Beaubourg
Centre will house a great and unique
library, where it is planned to store
no less than a million documents, to
which visitors will have free and imme¬
diate access. This new-style library
will specialize in current events and
will be a kind of university without
walls. It will also include a big chil¬
dren's section. It will be on three
floors, extending over a total surface
area of 15,000 square metres.
The various forms of audiovisual
activity will also have a prominent
place at the Beaubourg Centre. First
of all there will be a film museum, a
cinémathèque, an offshoot of the world-
famous Cinémathèque Française,
whose founder, Henri Langlois, will
direct It.
Up-to-date audiovisual equipment
will be installed throughout the build¬
ing. It will include a closed-circuit
television network capable of being
linked to outside television channels,
as well as recording studios, audition
rooms, seven cinemas (with a seating
capacity ranging from 40 to 800 per¬
sons), theatres, music rooms, and a
television network, broadcasting pro¬
grammes throughout the Centre. There
will also be film studios with editing
rooms, and television studios where
portable video equipment will be avail¬
able (see article on page 9).
Another feature of this vast complex
will be a "Médiathèque", containing all
the tools of modern mass communica¬
tions, from slides and printed matter
to video-cassettes and video-discs,
small format films and videotape
recorders.
A "Piazza" stretching over some
10,000 square metres the same area
as the building itself will be created
in front of the main facade of the
Beaubourg Centre. Here people will
be able to relax, stroll, and play games.
Improvised activities will take place
around inflatable domes in this leafy,
verdant setting.
Across the Piazza will stand an
important annex to/ the Centre, a five-
storey building which will house an
accoustical-musical research and co¬
ordination institute. This is sure to be
one of the Centre's most interesting
and attractive features.
The institute is an entirely new Idea.
Directed by the famous French con¬
ductor and composer Pierre Boulez,
it will be a laboratory for avant-garde
music. In it composers and research¬
ers, working closely with specialists
in accoustlcs and computer science,
will carry out research into music and
sound. Perhaps who knows? they
may one day launch a revolution in
music. The institute will not be for
professionals only. There will be con¬
certs for the public, and visitors will
also have the opportunity to come and
see on television screens musicians
and scientists at work in their studios.
All this vast complex is now about
to rise from the earth. But, on an
outlying part of the site, one feature
of the Beaubourg Centre can already
be seen. This is the Saint Merri
school, which takes its name from the
patron saint of the fine church nearby.
One of the first of its kind In a city,
this school is dedicated to the idea
of freedom of expression: there are
no partitions, neither in the teaching
areas nor in the teaching itself. During
the day about 1,000 children will attend
the school, and in the evening it will
be open to adults. Six studios, direct¬
ed by experts, will provide facilities for
modelling, cinema, photography, video,
and comic strips.
It is estimated that up to 10,000
people a day from all over the world
will visit this vast complex now being
built in the heart of Paris.
The architectural concept of this
"school without walls" reflects the
determination of the Beaubourg Centre
to break down the barriers within cul¬
ture itself. For the underlying con¬
ception of the Centre is that it shall
not simply be a place where separate,
autonomous activities go on. It is
to be a place where the spirit of
enquiry in its various forms can move
freely from one centre of interest to
another, a cross-roads where people
and ideas can meet and interact.
Nino Frank
Photo © Laurent Rousseau. Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
DISMEMBERED
WORKS OF ART
Reconstituting works of art which have been dismembered is a delicate
operation, especially when the fragments have been widely dispersed
and now belong to museums and collectors in different countries.
It calls for a combination of historical research, detective work,
diplomacy, goodwill, taste and cultural appreciation. This complex
international problem is examined in an outstanding book just pub¬
lished by Unesco: An Illustrated Inventory of Famous Dismembered
Works ofArt European Painting (223 pages, 340 illustrations, 54 F.).
Its publication marks an important step in Unesco's efforts to encourage
the reconstitution of dismantled works of art throughout the world,
the salient features of which are described in the following article.
by Selim Abdul Hak
26
M ROM time immemorial,
war, invasion and conquest have led
to the loss of countless works of art.
Because of the values they symbolize,
conquerors have set out to obliterate
them, since the destruction of a
nation's treasures or the relics of its
past was one way of eroding or
annihilating the personality of a
vanquished people.
Armed conflict is also responsible
for the deplorable practice of removing
works of art from the settings for
which they had been created, dismem¬
bering them and transporting the
fragments elsewhere for profit or
enjoyment or for reasons of prestige.
The ostentatiousness of famous
people, the passion of art-lovers and
the rich for collecting and the profit
motive of art dealers have also
contributed throughout the ages to the
dismemberment of works of art. Even
the owners of such works, unaware of
SELIM ABDUL HAK was head of Unesco's
Monuments and Museums Division from 1965
to 1970 and until recently was responsible
at Unesco for international conventions and
recommendations concerning the preservation
of the world's cultural heritage. Former di¬
rector-general of antiquities and museums in
Syria, he is the author of many studies on
art and archaeology.
their real value or tempted by the lure
of gain, have readily condoned this
practice.
Moreover, artists have turned their
hands to rectifying or transforming
works of art regarded as out of date
or immoral, and museum curators have
often succumbed to the temptation to
enrich their collections by acquiring
fragments of dismembered works.
It is, of course, some consolation
to reflect that the dispersion of these
fragments has helped to build up
great collections in famous art gal¬
leries and museums, thus helping to
CONTINUED PAGE 28
Photos © Bulloz, Paris
OUTRIGHT VANDALISM
ON A FAMOUS WORK
BY TOULOUSE-LAUTREC
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
La Goulue and Valentin le Désossé at the Moulin Rouge, painted ¡n
1895 by Henri de Toulouse-Lautrec (1864-1901), was acquired by a
collector who had no scruples about cutting it up and selling it In
pieces to increase his profit. It was one of a series of paintings
depicting two of the artist's favourite models, La Goulue (Louise
Weber) and Valentin le Désossé (Jacques Renaudin), dancers who
delighted revellers at the famous Moulin Rouge cabaret in Paris and
other Montmartre haunts at the turn of the century. The painting
was cut Into five pieces, and in the process Valentin le Désossé
(Valentin the India-rubberman) lost a foot, his right hand, and two O |
fingers of his left hand. In 1929 the painting was acquired by the ¿. f
French National Museums and painstakingly reassembled (opposite
page). Today it hangs in the Louvre. Above centre, La Goulue
dancing the can-can, facing Valentin le Désossé (right).
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
promote a deeper knowledge of the
arts and enriching the cultural life of
the world as a whole. So there would
be no point in re-examining the rights
and wrongs of the historical events
which led to such dismemberment nor
in condemning too harshly the methods
employed. Any attempt to do so could
only impair international under¬
standing.
Although research on these prob¬
lems has not hitherto enabled many
works of art to be reconstructed, It
has at least produced a great deal of
information about the nature, history
and original form of masterpieces
which have been fragmented and dis¬
persed. As a result, the value of
these fragments has increased, since
the fact that they form part of a well-
THE PRINCE
WHO LOST
HIS HEAD
In 1924 the Louvre Mu¬
seum in Paris acquired
a headless Sumerian
statuette. According to
Its inscription, it depict¬
ed Ur Ningirsu, a
prince of Lagash, who
had lived around 2100
B.C. The mutilated sta¬
tuette had been found
at Tello in Iraq, in a
region where archaeo¬
logical sites have long
been pillaged by loot¬
ers. In 1934 the head
was located in a pri¬
vate collection, and in
1947 It was bought by
the New York Metro¬
politan Museum of Art
It has now been agreed
that the Louvre and the
Metropolitan Museum
of Art will take three-
year turns to exhibit
the prince complete
with head.
Photo © Almasy. Paris
28
known original has given them a new
and hitherto unsuspected worth.
Co-operation between curators and
restorers has enabled several Europ¬
ean countries to. reconstitute dismem¬
bered works from fragments in their,
own museums and private collections.
Reconstitution is much more difficult
when fragments of world famous works
belong to two or more museums in
different countries, especially when
each fragment is a masterpiece in itself
and has over the years acquired a
value of its own. In these cases, the
problem can only be solved by co¬
operation between the countries con¬
cerned.
At a meeting held in Unesco's head¬
quarters in Paris, in 1966, specialists
studied such problems as the exchange
of works between museums, the re-
constitution of dismembered works on
a national and international basis, and
the role of international organizations
in this field.
The specialists considered that in
most cases it would be a mistake to
envisage the extremely costly oper¬
ation of attempting to reconstitute dis¬
membered architectural monuments
from dispersed ornamental fragments.
On the other hand, sculpture, painting
and other decorative features forming
part of these monuments should ob¬
viously be considered as having
acquired independent status and be
treated separately, an appropriate
solution being sought in each case.
As for the problem of reassembling
dismembered paintings, sculpture, en¬
gravings, etc., the specialists consider
that it should be dealt with through
exchanges between museums. In their
view, every effort at reconstitution
should take account of the same legal
and psychological issues as are posed
by exchanges.
In response to an international in¬
quiry carried out by Unesco in 1967
and 1968, 37 countries and three inter¬
governmental organizations stated
their views on the problems of ex¬
changing objects and reconstituting
dismembered works.
Several countries felt that fragments
of dispersed works should be as¬
sembled so that their reconstitution
benefits the country which is the real
owner, especially where such frag¬
ments either form part of an architec¬
tural monument or would complete a
collection.
This view was naturally opposed by
those who had come by such frag¬
ments legally. Several countries tried
to "cool down" the discussion by
pressing for a more cautious approach.
They proposed that exchanges should
be made only on the basis of free
consent, and that the problem should
be solved by the parties concerned,
and should never be considered as
a simple act of restitution.
The question of the counterpart to
be provided was considered to be of
vital importance. Since it raises legal
and psychological issues, it should be
settled by agreement between the
parties involved. It is essential that
objects to be exchanged should be of
equal value, especially when these are
unique objects of great worth. In this
connexion, a system of national, re¬
gional or international arbitration might
be of great assistance.
Despite these reservations, the
countries consulted were not opposed
DAVID EXCLUDED
FROM 'BATHSHEBA
AT HER BATH'
No one knows what motivated the muti¬
lation of this work (right) by the Flemish
painter Hans Memling (1433-1494) of
Bathsheba, wife of King David and mother
of Solomon, at her bath. The original
upper left-hand corner of the painting
(above), a half-length representation of
King David showing his ring to a youth
who may be a messenger, was removed,
possibly in the 17th century. It was
replaced by an architectural perspective
showing a man and a child standing on
the gallery of a palace. Today, Mem-
ling's painting, incorporating this curious
"improvement", hangs in the Staatsgale¬
rie, Stuttgart (Fed. Germ. Rep.), while
the fragment portraying King David,
since rediscovered, is in the Chicago Art
Institute, U.S.A.
to the idea that the problem of recons¬
titution might be considered within the
framework of new international regul¬
ations and solved by exchanges bet¬
ween museums, provided that the aim
was to restore the true value of dis¬
membered works, and that all the
necessary scientific, technical and
administrative measures were taken.
In 1968 Unesco organized a pilot
exhibition of dismembered works at
its Paris headquarters. Unesco's pur¬
pose was to set an example, which it
was hoped would stimulate thought on
the subject and lead to the reconsti¬
tution of other dismembered works of
art. The works displayed came from
several museums.
The Louvre Museum, in Paris, the
Rijksmuseum in Amsterdam, the Musée
des Arts Décoratifs in Paris and the
Museum of the Wawel Royal Castle
in Cracow (Poland) lent Unesco three
works, two of which had been perma¬
nently reconstituted, while the third
was reconstituted for the duration of
the exhibition only.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
This temporarily reconstituted work
was the Persian carpet, known as the
"Paris-Cracow" carpet, the two halves
of which belong to the Musée des
Arts Décoratifs in Paris and the Mu¬
seum of the Wawel Royal Castle in
Cracow respectively. Thanks to
Unesco, these two halves were put
together again after being separated
for a long period of time; and they were
displayed first at Cracow, from 27
April to 13 May 1968, and then at the
pilot exhibition in Paris the following
month.
This carpet, the only one of its kind
in the world, dates from the second
quarter of the 16th century and is the
work of the Tabriz school. It was
intended to cover the steps of the altar
of Cracow cathedral, but it was found
to be too large, and was therefore cut
in two.
The temporary reconstitution of this
carpet gave art historians an opport¬
unity to compare the two halves and
make scientific studies.
One of the two permanently recons
tituted works was the picture repre¬
senting "The Battle of Bergen (1665)",
painted by Willem Van de Velde the
Elder.
In 1877, the Nederlandse Museum
at The Hague purchased the right-
hand part, and the left-hand part was
acquired by the National Maritime
Museum at Greenwich (Great Britain).
After the exhibition, the Greenwich
Museum generously offered its half of
the picture to the Netherlands, thus
enabling the work to be reconstituted
in its original form.
The other reconstituted work on
display was a polyptych by Paolo Vene-
ziano. Dismembered after the disper¬
sion of the Campana collection, it has
been completely reassembled and
since 1956 has been in the collection
of the Louvre Museum, in Paris.
To provide material for systematic
exchanges of information and docu¬
mentation of dismembered works in the
various arts, Unesco decided In 1969
to prepare an inventory of major works
that have been fragmented or dis¬
persed. Since the dismemberment of
works of art is a prominent feature of
the history of European painting, it
was decided to begin with an inven¬
tory of European works of art, and par¬
ticularly of paintings from the Renais¬
sance to the present time. Inventories
covering other cultural regions of the
world will follow.
Unesco has just published this first
inventory, which is entitled An Illus¬
trated Inventory of Famous Dismemb¬
ered Works of Art European Painting.
It contains chapters on dismembered
works of Italian, Flemish, French,
Spanish, Russian and German painting.
One special chapter deals with Euro¬
pean illuminated manuscripts, another
with French dismembered tombs.
This illustrated inventory presents a
disconcerting picture of the disfigure¬
ments and dismemberment inflicted on
works of art by irresponsible hands.
Works by such great masters as Giotto,
Simone Martini, Masaccio, Paolo
Uccello, Andrea Mantegna, Roger Van
der Weyden, Hans Memling, Pieter
Bruegel, Hans Holbein the Elder, Al-
brecht Durer, Peter Paul Rubens,
Anthony Van Dyck, El Greco, Fran¬
cisco de Zurbaran, Juan de Valdes
Leal, Nicolas Poussin, Jean-François
Millet, Henri de Toulouse-Lautrec and
many others have paid a heavy price
for this deliberate vandalism.
One example is Paolo Uccello's
three great pictures of the Florentine
victory over the Sienese at the battle
of San Romano in 1433, which, with
three other pictures, once formed part
of the decoration of Lorenzo the Magni-
ficent's chamber in the Medici Palace,
Florence.
In the 16th century, the panels were
transferred to another part of the
palace, and were then lost without
trace until the 18th century. The
panel representing "The Unhorsing of
Bernardino délia Garda" was bought
sometime between 1769 and 1784 by
the Uffizi Gallery, Florence, where it
still hangs today, while the other two
were discovered in a private collec¬
tion In the 19th century. The one
showing "Micheletto da Cotignala
Counter-Attacking" was acquired by
the Campana Collection and today
hangs in the Louvre, while "Niccolo
da Tolentino Leading the Attack" has
belonged to the National Gallery, Lon¬
don, since 1857.
The fate of the triptych of the An¬
nunciation, painted by an unknown
fifteenth-century master for the cathe¬
dral of Saint-Sauveur, Aix-en-Provence
(France) has been equally tragic. After
the French Revolution, the central part
depicting "The Virgin and the Angel",
was transferred to the church of the
Madeleine in Aix.
The two side-panels passed through
several hands. The right-hand one,
showing "The Prophet Jeremiah in a
Niche", was acquired in 1923 by the
Royal Fine Arts Museum in Brussels,
while the left-hand panel was cut into .
two. One part of it, depicting "The
Prophet Isaiah in a Niche", is now
in the Van Beuningen museum in the
Netherlands. The other part, which
shows books and objects painted in
trompe-1' was acquired by the
Rijksmuseum, Amsterdam, and is at
present on loan to the Louvre.
A series of great paintings which
once formed a unity is "Christ and the
12 Apostles", by Van Dyck. No one
knows where these pictures were ori¬
ginally hung. However, in the early
18th century, the central painting of the
group a half-length representation of
Christ holding the Cross in his right
hand was in the Palazzo Rosso,
Genoa, where it still hangs.
The 12 apostles were detached no
one knows when and disappeared
until they were discovered around 1914
by a Munich art dealer, who sold them
separately. Today the whereabouts of
only six of them is known they are
in museums in the US.A. (Sarasota,
Florida), Hungary (Budapest), German
Fed. Rep. (one in Hanover and two in
Essen), and Austria (Vienna).
Among Spanish works of art which
have suffered dismemberments \ff an
altarpiece, painted by Francisco de
Zurbaran at the height of his powers,
which hung in the Monastery of St.
Joseph of the Order of Discalced Mer-
cedarians in Seville.
The paintings which formed part of
this magnificent group had a curious
fate. The group was broken up twice,
once in 1810 and once in 1835. Today
paintings from it hang in the Seville
Museum, the Louvre, Chartres Mu¬
seum (France) and others belong to
the heirs of Marshal Soult, the Valdes
collection (Bilbao), the Munt Gallery
(New York), the Hamilton Collection
(New York) and the heirs of the Mar¬
quis de Valdeterrazo (Madrid). OQ
The fate of the Très Belles Heures '
de Notre-Dame du Duc Jean de Berry, ^
was no less tragic. Written around*
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
SEVILLE (Spain)
The Eternal Father, from the main altarpiece
of the church of St. Joseph. Seville Museum.
TOLEDO
(Spain)
Martyr. Museum of the Casa del Greco.
Toledo.
CHARTRES (France)
St. Lucy, from the main altarpiece of the
Church of St. Joseph. Chartres Museum.
HARTFORD (U.S.A.)
St. Seraoion. The Wadsworth
Atheneum, Hartford, Connecticut.
LENINGRAD (U.S.S.R.)
St. Lawrence, from the altarpiece in the
transept of the Church of St. Joseph. Hermi¬
tage Museum, Leningrad.
EXILED
PAINTINGS
OF FRANCISCO
DE ZURBARAN
30
1380, some changes and embellish¬
ments being made in the early 15th
century, this manuscript was soon frag¬
mented. The first part, which was
illustrated by the Duke of Berry, passed
through many hands and was finally
acquired by the Bibliothèque Nationale,
in Paris.
The second part of the manuscript
was embellished by various masters,
including the Van Eyck brothers, Jan
and Hubert, and broken up into two
volumes. One part, which was in the
collections of the dukes of Savoy and
later In the Royal Library of Turin (now
the National Library) became known
as the Les Heures de Turin. This pre¬
cious manuscript was destroyed by
fire at the beginning of the 20th cent¬
ury. However, four leaves, which had
been detached from this part, event¬
ually found their way to the Louvre.
Finally, the second volume was ac¬
quired by the Museo Cívico, Turin, in
1935, after belonging to the Counts
of Aglie in Piedmont, and the Counts
Trivulzio of Milan, under the name of
Les Heures de Milan.
It is appalling to think that many
fragments of these and other works
of art have disappeared without trace
and are lost forever. However, the
situation is not entirely gloomy, and it
is encouraging to note that some spec¬
tacular reconstitutions have been
made.
The figures which formed part of
the altarpiece of the Last Judgment,
painted by the 15th-century artist Ste¬
phan Lochner for the parish church of
St. Lawrence in Cologne, were dis¬
persed in Frankfurt, Cologne and Mu¬
nich, and finally reconstituted in their
original form in 1936 for the Lochner
Exhibition, held at the Wallraf Richartz
Museum, in Cologne.
Under the Treaty of Versailles (1919),
the side-panels of the Holy Lamb
polyptych, painted by Van Eyck for
Ghent cathedral, were returned to
Belgium. They had belonged to the
collection of Frederic William III of
Prussia, who had presented them to
the Museum of Berlin. In 1923, the
Belgian government returned to the
cathedral the panels of the same po¬
lyptych, which depicted Adam and Eve
and which had been exhibited in the
Royal Fine Arts Museum in Brussels.
Thus this magnificent polyptych has
been reconstituted in the Vydt Chapel
of Ghent cathedral.
Two vast oil paintings by Toulouse-
Lautrec, La Goulue and Valentin le
Désossé at the Moulin Rouge and La
Goulue Dancing an Egyptian Dance in
her Shack were bought by a private
collector who in 1926 cut them into
ten pieces of various sizes.
Fortunately, the French National Mu¬
seums were able to trace the paintings
from photographs taken before they
were dismembered, and skilfully to
sew them together, again. Today the
two paintings hang in the Louvre
and one can see the marks of
the stitches, which serve as a reminder
of the perils to which they were expos-
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Of all the famous artists whose works have been dismembered down the centuries,
perhaps the Spanish painter Francisco de Zurbaran (1598-1664) has suffered most.
Between 1628 and 1640, when the great religious orders were commissioning
paintings to illustrate their history, Zurbaran executed a large number of works
of remarkable quality. Among them was the prodigious group of pictures he
painted for the Monastery of St. Joseph of the Order of Discalced Mercedarians,
in Seville. They were completely dispersed as a result of the secularization laws
promulgated by the government of Joseph Bonaparte in 1810. However, at least
one good thing has come out of this misfortune: in the 18th century Zurbaran
was virtually unknown outside Spain, and the dispersion of his works, today
displayed in museums from Aix-la-Chapelle to Boston, from Genoa to London, from
Barcelona to Leningrad and Paris, has brought him world-wide renown. On these
pages we show some of the works which Zurbaran painted for the Monastery
of St. Joseph in Seville and indicate where they hang today. The exact number
of pictures decorating the monastery is unknown, but Zurbaran's paintings of
the martyrs alone numbered about fifty, some of which have disappeared.
PARIS (France)
St. Apollinia, from
the main altarpiece
of the Church of St.
Joseph. Louvre
Museum, Paris.
MADRID (Spain)
Martyr. Adanero Collection, Madrid.
ed and the fashion in which they were
restored to their original condition.
Finally, recent work by the Museums
of Moscow, Leningrad and Kiev on
the reconstitution of Russian works of
art has shown that such operations are
always worthwhile and give good
results, even when the main elements
of the work are missing. The way in
which two 15th-century works the
royal doors of the school of Tver and
the iconostasis of the Novgorod school
have been reconstituted is truly
remarkable.
The adoption by the General Con¬
ference of Unesco, in November 1970,
of the Convention on the Means of
Prohibiting and Preventing the Illicit
Import, Export and Transfer of Owner¬
ship of Cultural Property marks a dis¬
tinct advance in the international com¬
munity's efforts to guarantee every
nation the possession of works that
are representative of its genius or that
have been created within its borders.
Contracting States, recognizing that
international co-operation is one of the
most effective means of protecting
such property against the dangers that
result from the illicit practices which
threaten it, undertake to oppose such
practices by removing their causes and
helping to make the necessary repar¬
ations.
The 1970 Unesco Convention states
that nothing shall prevent contracting
states from concluding special arrange¬
ments among themselves or from con¬
tinuing to implement agreements
already concluded regarding the resti¬
tution of cultural property removed,
whatever the reason, from its territory
of origin, before the entry into force of
the Convention. The party in whose
favour a work was reconstituted should
in principle give in return something
of scientific or artistic value equal to
that of the fragments which it receives.
The way is open to various arrange¬
ments which, while ensuring that the
interests of the parties concerned are
respected, may provide various valid
solutions for the reconstitution of
works of art exhibitions, long-term
loans, alternating possession for a
given period, or the permanent taking
over of a work of art.
Recently, the Metropolitan Museum
of New York and the Direction des
Musées de France jointly purchased a
12th-century comb, and decided to take
five-year turns in holding it. This is
an example of the way in which com¬
mon ownership can promote the inter¬
national enjoyment of a work of art.
Through this kind of arrangement, a
work of art may belong to two or more
institutions, each of which takes turns
to exhibit it.
Working along these lines, it may
be possible to reassemble certain dis¬
membered works of art or groups
which have been dispersed. If recons- _.
tituted they would recover their full jl
impact.
Sellm Abdul Hak
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
THE VIDEO REVOLUTION (Continued from page 11)
American groups see video as a
tool for direct political action in the
street or for the analysis of the way
people behave on the public highway,
for instance recording the attitude of
the police towards demonstrators film
can be erased by being exposed to
the light, but videotape can be wiped
clean only by means of electronic
equipment.
They may also use it for filming a
television crew making a report, thus
showing how it chooses and organizes
the elements of reality, or even to
reveal a teacher objecting to his
lesson being filmed by his students.
All these are typical cases of the
¡mage as action: the fact that those
watching are watched in their turn
leads them to modify their behaviour.
Far from considering these attempts
as games played by the pampered
children of the rich countries, some of
the developing countries are seeking
to explore the possibilities which might
be open to them.
The Canadian assistance pro¬
gramme, after its successful experi¬
ence in Quebec, is conducting video
campaigns in the south of Tunisia on
the development of simple visual forms
for the teaching of new farming
techniques.
In Bangladesh, a team from the
Global Village of New York attempted
in 1972-73, by showing in villages
videorecordings made in other vil¬
lages, to change the attitudes of
isolated and closed communities
towards all form of evolution, particul¬
arly birth control and new crop
techniques ("We can change if others
like us accept change too.").
I
32
N Tanzania, the programme
TY 16 (Tanzania Year 16), benefiting
from Canadian and Scandinavian sup¬
port, led to the launching between 1971
and 1973 of a programme of "perma¬
nent protest" via video aimed at spurr¬
ing on the building of Ujamaa com¬
munity villages.
Video makes it possible to pinpoint
conflicts with the authorities and to
locate bureaucratic bottlenecks. The
Tanzanian group, in the course of
successively recorded discussions,
thoroughly investigated the problems
of collectivization ("Is the land of the
ancestors to become everyone's
land?"). Video analyzes the pro¬
blems, records the remarks of the
villagers and then the comments of
the local and central authorities. All
of the recordings are then projected
before the villagers whose reactions
are recorded once again. At the
present time, Unesco is studying the
setting up in Tanzania of a video
communication centre which would
train the villagers in the systematic
use of this new type of communication
for development.
Projects are becoming more and
more numerous: Algeria is now pre¬
paring a campaign for the promotion
of rural activities known as the
"thousand villages campaign" which
will make wide use of video tech¬
niques, while in the Ivory Coast these
techniques are to be used In the
framework of rural development.
But it is probably in the most
deprived countries as the examples
of Tanzania and Bangladesh appear
to suggest that the uses of re¬
versible and simplified visual com¬
munications affording participation will
be most effective, inasmuch as they
will make it possible to break down
the resistance of archaic communities
without manipulating them, and pre¬
pare them collectively to face up to
the necessary innovations.
What then, over and above these
specific uses, is the future of portable
video?
For many, it represents a first
generation, a step towards other, more
institutional forms of group communi¬
cation. Undeniably there is a strong
possibility of its being taken over and
institutionalized by community tele¬
vision using cable-relay systems.
This development has moved on
apace over the last five years in some
countries: six million homes in the
United States, a million and a half in
Canada and two million in Great
Britain are now provided with local pro-«
grammes by cable-relay companies.
These programmes consist of weather
reports, sports results, etc.
Others have been in the project
stage in France (seven towns) and in
the Netherlands (six towns) since 1973.
These companies will have a great
need of ¡mages to broadcast and will
probably want to use the production
of the free video groups. In Canada,
the production workshop, "Vidéo-
graphe" of Montreal, has exper¬
imentally been connected by cable to
10,000 television receivers in three
neighbouring towns which have
been able on request to obtain
80 programmes recorded by non¬
professionals either at "Vidéographe"
itself, or outside (Sélectovision).
Pretty well everywhere in Europe,
experiments using portable video
within local communities are being
used to pave the way for cable tele¬
vision installations. But it is unlikely
that most of the video groups which
have been formed in recent years
will agree to become part of a one¬
way broadcasting system which, after
all, is fairly similar to what they hope
to replace.
If they do, it will be necessary, in
order to maintain the spirit of dialogue
which is their raison d'être, to install
two-way telecommunications making
it possible for images to be returned
to those transmitting them.
The projects which have been
developed in the United States, par¬
ticularly MINERVA (Multiple Input
Network for Evaluation, Reaction,
Votes and Attitudes) which should be
in operation in 1985 and which aims
at organizing citizens in uniform
groups of 30 correspondents linked
by telephone, these groups being
themselves connected to each other
by cable, show the absurdity, however,,
of wanting to "organize" participation
at any price through rigid networks
formed by complex technological
machinery.
more promising direction
would appear to be that pointed to by
the creation by Vidéographe of a tiny,
low-powered television station at Saint
Lambert in Quebec, installed In the
village church-tower to serve only the
village, or the Pic Saint-Loup project
in France which aims at combining
extremely mobile video equipment with
small local low-power transmitters for
transmission in rural areas. In both
cases the structures involved are
technically flexible, economically ac¬
ceptable and in keeping with the social
spirit of the video pioneers.
Indeed, one of the striking features
of these pathfinders is their wariness
as regards all that is institutional. They
also have a horror of advertising.
"Over-exposure brings under-develop-
ment in its wake", one of them said
recently.
In their attitudes these young
experimenters often display a certain
Puritanism and a moral outlook which,
in its tendency to strip things down
to the essential, seems sometimes to
borrow its metaphors from Maoism:
"One must be in the people like fish
in the water... The major' television
organizations remain on the bank and
see only the surface, never the depths
of the people", and so on. The
"Guerrilla television" handbook offers
the following advice: "Sell your car
and buy a Portapack." More than one
person seems to have done so in
the U.S.A. and Canada.
Could this belief in the liberating
potentialities of a technique perhaps
be naive and anachronistic? What is
striking about it, however, is its
serious-mindedness, and it is highly
possible that the intuition from which
it stems will turn out to be decisive
for the future.
It has often been observed that
the political and cultural criteria which
still govern the international community
seem to be borrowed from the period
of the Second World War, whereas
the basic technologies of our society
all came into existence after the war,
these technologies being information-
producing ones chiefly computers
and television.
In the last quarter of a century, so
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
OLDEST CHINESE
PAINTING ON SILK
Sir,
I wish to draw your attention to one
detail needing correction in Wen Pien's
"The World's Oldest Painting on Silk",
in your April 1974 issue. This is not
the oldest Chinese painting on silk. An
earlier one, dated 4th-3rd century B.C.,
was found a number of years ago, and
has been reproduced in several publi¬
cations.
L. Carrington Goodrich
Dean Lung Professor emeritus
of Chinese, Columbia University,
New York
The painting we reproduced is the
oldest complete Chinese painting on
silk (2nd century B.C.) found so far.
The work referred to by Professor Car¬
rington Goodrich is a fragment of an
earlier painting, discovered in 1949 at
In Hunan Province. The
fragment (drawing below) portrays a
woman praying in the presence of the
forces of life and death, symbolized
by the phoenix and the dragon.
Editor
PAPER AND FORESTS
Sir,
Congratulations on the presentation
and informative quality of your maga¬
zine.
I only hope that the "Courier" will
manage to keep us as well informed
for many years to come, in spite of the
Increasingly critical paper shortage.
And, talking of paper, why not publish
something on problems of soil and
forest conservation?
Michèle Moreau
Vaires-sur-Marne, France
SULEIMAN EL-BARUNI
Sir,
In your highly commendable number
on al-Birunl (June 1974) you included
among the commemorative stamps of
several countries (page 5) one from
the Libyan Arab Republic. I should
like to point out that the stamp in
question was issued on the Centenary
of a Suleiman El-Baruni, and not on
the Millennium of the great Abu AI-
Rayhan Mohammed Ibn Ahmad al-Biruni.
Suleiman Pasha El-Baruni was born
of Berber stock (1870) in the Libyan
province of Tripolitania, at that time a
part of the Ottoman Empire. He was
In his own right, a remarkable scholar
of Arabic literature, a poet, a leading
Tripolitanian statesman, and one of the
great national figures in Libya's long
struggle for independence.
When Italy invaded Libya In 1911,
and forced the Sultan to cede this ter¬
ritory (October 12, 1912), the Libyans
put pressure on the Ottoman Porte to
issue the Firman (Decree) of October
15, 1912 which granted them full auto¬
nomy. The Libyans regarded this action
as a declaration of independence, and
when many of the local leaders were
demoralized and reduced to inaction
after the recent strife, it was Suleiman
Pasha El-Baruni, who attempted to rally
the flagging resistance movement on
the assumption that only a show of
force would me&e Italy recogpjze his
country's sovereignty.
Though a daring leader, he was unable
to unite all the people behind him, and
the superior Italian forces soon overran
the country.
Baruni left for Istambul in 1913, to
return two years later in 1915 as his
country's new Governor and continued
the struggle against Italy to the end of
the First World War. In November
1918, he (as a member of a Quadrim-
vlrate: the Council of Four) proclaimed
the country's independence at a national
convention, and formally notified Italy
of the establishmep,t of the Republic.
Italy's willingness to negotiate on
this occasion was taken as a weakness
and tempted the Libyans to insist on
independence. As direct negotiations
with the Italian Government in Rome
ended in deadlock, war was declared
and once again Baruni carried on the
struggle until the resistance movement
was crushed in 1922. He went into
exile and died in Bombay (India) in.
1940, on the eve of his country's
liberation.
Mir Sarfaraz Husain
Paris, France
TOBACCO AND ENVIRONMENT
Sir,
In June of this year about 400 deleg¬
ates from 42 countries attended a
symposium at Unesco headquarters in
Paris on the health effects of environ¬
mental pollution. This symposium, I
believe, has helped to focus attention
on the dangers of tobacco.
It is usually said that factories are
responsible for approximately 50 per
cent of air pollution, cars for 25 per
cent, and homes for 25 per_cent. My
objection is that the maiiï culprit
tobacco is overlooked. Tobacco pol¬
lution affects not only smokers but non-
smokers as well, the latter of course
to a lesser extent. A recent declara¬
tion by the Health Protection Directory
of the European Communities in Brus¬
sels states that the level of carbon
monoxide passed into the blood by
tobacco is on average 16 times higher
than that caused by the atmospheric
pollution of a great city.
Paul Gönnet
chemical engineer
International Committee
for Protection against the Dangers
of the Use of Tobacco and other Drugs.
Montfavet, France
JIGSAW PUZZLE OF DRUGS
Sir,
Your issue on "The Jigsaw Puzzle of
Drugs" (May 1973) deserves special
praise. Your handling of the subject
was extraordinarily clear and objective.
With this delicate problem one has to
tread warily, especially when dealing
with young people stressing the phys¬
ical harm caused by drugs, but leaving
the young a free choice in the matter.
A clear and sensible explanation of the
problem is likely to produce better
results than campaigns which forbid,
threaten etc.
Anilo A. Krumenauer
Porto Alegre, Brazil
sociologists tell us, we have evolved
from a "métallurgie" society to a
"semiurgic" society (1), that is to say
from a system founded on the pro¬
duction, circulation and exchange of
products to another based on the
production, circulation and exchange
of signs and symbols, as is borne out,
for instance, by the increasing import¬
ance of labels and packaging for
consumer goods.
All the theories of material wealth
inherited from the 19th century were
incapable, and understandably so, of
taking into account this phenomenon
which is just beginning to be explored
by sociologists and economists. In the
event, one may well wonder whether,
(I) From the same root as "semiotics", the
study of signs.
with the advent of video, this new
economic science of signs is not itself
already being challenged.
For now visual communication is no
longer an object which is distributed
like a piece of merchandise; there are
no longer manufacturers and con¬
sumers, producers and receivers of
images, but persons communicating
with each other from all sides. A
utopia is taking shape: signs, messages
and symbols are being produced,
passed on and freely shared out
independently of the traditional cor¬
porate bodies and monopolies.
Whether it is a question of com¬
munities equipped with cable-relay
systems, of tiny low-power transmitters
or of "video ball-point pens", there is
evidence that, in a steadily Increasing
number of countries, the ¡mage is
being discreetly divested of its magical'
powers and is being used to revitalize
the social fabric. It is doing so by
providing minorities with the oppor¬
tunity for free expression, waking
people up to the environment and to
themselves, and serving as a basis
for the promotion of community ac¬
tivities and other forms of interaction
yet to see the light.
Everywhere "electronic literacy" is
gaining new ground, and not to the
detriment of conventional literacy. Do
not both forms constitute a contribution
to the task to which the international
community is summoned by Unesco:
the conquest of freedom and demo¬
cracy?
Henri Dleuzeide
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
BOOKSHELF
RECENT UNESCO BOOKS
Study Abroad and Educational
Development, by William D. Carter.
(Unesco: International Institute of
Educational Planning; Fundamentals
of educational planning, No. 19),
1973, 49 pp. (8 F).
Apartheid: its effects on educa¬
tion, science, culture and informa¬
tion. 2nd edition, 3rd impression,
1973, 256 pp. (24 F).
The Mass Media in a Violent
World, by Mary Burnet. (Reports and
papers on mass communication,
no. 63.) Re-run 1973, 44 p. (4 F).
Television Traffic a One-way
Street? A survey and analysis of the
international flow of television pro¬
gramme material, by Kaarle Norden¬
streng and Tapio Varis. (Reports and
papers on mass communication, No.
70), 1974, 62 pp. (6 F).
Realistic Educational Planning, by
K.R. McKinnon. (Unesco: HEP, Fun¬
damentals of Educational Planning,
No. 20), 1973, 45 pp. (8 F).
National Science Policies in Afri¬
ca: situation and future outlook.
(Science policy studies and docu¬
ments. No. 31), 1974, 387 pp. (48 F).
Mass Media in an African Context.
An evaluation of Senegal's pilot pro¬
ject. (Reports and papers on mass
communication, No. 69), 1974, 53 pp.
(6 F).
Two studies on Ethnic Group Re¬
lations in Africa: Senegal, the Unit¬
ed Republic of Tanzania, 1974, 156
pp. (18 F).
Symposium Leo Frobenius. (Ger¬
man Commission for Unesco, Col¬
ogne), 1974, 371 pp. (see "Unesco
Courier", October 1973).
UNESCO STUDIES <5 DOCUMENTS
ON CULTURAL POLICIES SERIES
Cultural Policy in Israel, by Jozeph
Michman, 1973, 79 pp. (8 F).
Cultural Policy in the Federal
Republic of Germany. Prepared under
the auspices of the German Com¬
mission for Unesco, 1973, 53 pp.
(6 F).
A Study of Cultural Policy in the
United States, by Charles C. Mark.
3rd impression 1973, 43 pp. (6 F).
Cultural Rights as Human Rights,
2nd impression 1973, 125 pp. (12 F).
Cultural Policy in Japan, by No-
buya Shikaumi. 2nd impression 1973,
55 pp. (8 F).
Cultural Policy in Great Britain,
by Michael Green and Michael Wild¬
ing in consultation with Richard
Hoggart, 2nd impression, 1973, 62 pp
(8 F).
wm B ks
Nixon-Brezhnev summit
supports Unesco
Unesco's international Man and Biosphere
programme of global research on inter¬
actions between man and ecological
systems received a boost at this year's
summit meeting in Moscow where President
Richard Nixon and General Secretary
Leonid Brezhnev agreed to designate
certain areas in their respective countries
as "biosphere reserves" protected areas
that will conserve valuable animal and
plant genetic strains.
The designation of the first biosphere
reserves will be examined by Unesco's
International Co-ordinating Council for Man
and the Biosphere when it meets in
Washington this month.
Revised Universal Copyright
Convention in force
The Revised Universal Copyright Con¬
vention, agreed in Paris in July 1971 under
the auspices of Unesco, came into force
on 10 July this year. Among other changes
in the text of the Universal Convention,
adopted in Geneva in 1952 under Unesco
sponsorship, the revised Convention pro¬
vides for the protection of exclusive rights
of reproduction, broadcasting and public
performance. It also sets up a preferential
system for developing countries as regards
translation and reproduction.
Cultural tourism
in Peru
A $29,300,000 loan from the Interamerican
Bank for Development will enable Peru to
launch a wide-ranging national plan for the
development of cultural tourism. The plan,
worked out by Unesco at the request of
the Peruvian Government, provides for the
restoration and protection of pre-Colombian
and Spanish monuments and sites in the
areas around Cuzco, Puno and Desagua¬
dero, once the heart of the Inca empire,
as centres of cultural tourism.
Towards universal
qualifications
The important aim of internationalizing
academic standards was brought a step
nearer with the submission recently to
Unesco Member States In Latin America
and the Caribbean of the Draft Convention
on the International Recognition of Studies,
Diplomas and Degrees in Higher Education.
Unesco is currently preparing similar con¬
ventions for the Arab States, for the States
of Africa and for Europe. The long-term
aim is a world agreement.
Asia's reading famine
Producers of periodicals and communi¬
cations media specialists from 17 de¬
veloping Asian countries recently met in
Tokyo under Unesco sponsorship to seek
ways of combating a region-wide "famine"
of reading matter. With a population of
nearly one billion (28 per cent of the world
total), the 17 countries produced only
6.5 per cent of the estimated world output
of 546,000 book titles in 1970. The aim is
to fill part of the reading gap with period¬
icals, with their greater potential audience
and possible faster and cheaper pro
duction. Other Unesco meetings on the
development of the periodical press are to
be held in Latin America, Africa and the
Arab States.
U.S.S.R. aid
for Philae temples
The U.S.S.R. is contributing 500,000
Egyptian pounds ($1,300,000) to save the
temples of Philae in Egypt. The pre¬
servation of the Philae temples is the final
stage in the international campaign launched
by Unesco in 1960 to save the monuments
of Nubia, threatened by the waters from
the Aswan High Dam. With the U.S.S.R.
gift, contributions of Unesco Member States
to the rescue operations total more than
$8.200,000.
Ethiopian drought
volunteers
Ninety student teachers from the Academy
of Pedagogy, Bahir Dar, Ethiopia, are
helping with drought relief work in their
country under a joint programme of Unesco,
Unicef, the United Nations Development
Programme and the Ethiopian government.
The students have volunteered for such
tasks as distribution of clothing, foodstuffs
and medicines, and supervision and ad¬
ministration of shelter camps. Where
possible, they also plan to set up literacy
classes for children and adults in the camps.
Educational science bureau
for Africa
The International Association for Ad¬
vancement of Education Research is to set
up an African Bureau of Educational Science
with headquarters in Kinshasa, at the
national university of Zaire. The Bureau
will promote African research into education
and publish information about current
studies.
Unesco medals
for monuments
Unesco is issuing a series of medals
to contribute to the raising of funds to
save some of the world's outstanding mon¬
uments and sites. The first medal in the
series is devoted to Moenjodaro (Paki¬
stan), one of the oldest urban sites in
the world, for whose preservation Unesco
has launched an international appeal (see
"Unesco Courier", December 1973). Below,
the obverse side of the medal showing
a King-Priest and the reverse depicting
a unicorn and pictographic inscription found
on a seal at Moenjodaro. The medal is
available In bronze, silver and gold. Other
medals will feature Borobudur (Indonesia),
Venice (Italy), Philae (Egypt), etc. Infor¬
mation on each medal issue may be obtain¬
ed from Public Liaison Division, Unesco,
Place Fontenoy, Paris 75700 (France).
o
z
<
5
Q_
I
<
I
CP
z
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Just published by Unesco
Tenth edition (revised) 343 pages 40 F
CATALOGUE OF
REPRODUCTIONS
OF PAINTINGS
1860 to 1973
with fifteen projects for exhibitions
Up-to-date listings of high-quality colour reproductions
of more than 1,500 important paintings produced between
1860 and 1973, chosen by an international panel of experts.
Each reproduction shown in black and white, along with
full details of original work (date, collection, museum, etc.)
and reproduction (size, price, publisher's address, etc.).
A new feature of the latest edition : fifteen projects for
exhibitions to help teachers and cultural organizers to mount
exhibitions on the basis of the reproductions in the catalogue.
MUSEUM
"Museums and the Theft of Works of Art" is the title of a recent issue
of Unesco's quarterly. Museum (No. 1, 1974), which is entirely devoted
to this growing international problem. Museum presents the results of
an Interpol enquiry into art thefts and examines the psychoanalytic
background to the theft and defacement of works of art, problems of
museum security, etc.
Each issue: 16 F. Annual subscription: 55 F.
Where to renew your subscription
and order other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See lilt
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed, along with subscription rates in local
currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications : Educational Supplies
Pty. Ltd., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale, 2100, NSW; Perio¬
dicals: Dominie Pty. Limited, Box 33, Post Office,
Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent: United Nations
Association of Australia, Victorian Division 5th floor,
134/136 Flinders St., Melbourne (Victoria), 3000.
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme & C, Arbelter¬
gasse 1-7, 1051, Vienna.BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier"
Dutch edition only: N.V. Handelmaatschappij Keesing,
Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-Antwerpen. French
edition and general Unesco publications agent: Jean de
Lannoy, 112, rue du Trône, Brussels 5. CCP 3380.00.
BURMA. Trade Corporation N' (9), 550-552 Mer¬
chant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Information
Canada, Ottawa, (Ont.). CYPRUS, MAM", Archbishop
Makarios 3rd Avenue, P. O. Box 1722, Nicosia.
CEZCHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L.. Spalena 51, Prague 1
(permnent display) ; Zahranicni literatura, 1 1 Soukenicka
Prague 1. For Slovakia only : Alfa Verlag - Publishers,
Hurbanovo nam. 6, 893 31 Bratislava - CSSR. DEN¬
MARK. Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Nörregade, DK-
1165, Copenhagen K. EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC
OF). National Centre for Unesco Publications, N* 1
Talaat Harb Street, Tahrir Square, Cairo; Librairie
Kasr El Nil, 38, rue Kasr El Nil, Cairo. ETHIOPIA.
National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis
Ababa. FINLAND, Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, 2 Kes-
kuskatu, Helsinki. FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco,
7-9, place de Fontenoy, 75700-Paris, CCP. 12598-48.
GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Deutscher Buch-
Export und Import Gmbh, Leninstrasse 1 6, 701 Leipzig.
FED. REP. OF GERMANY For the Unesco Kurier
(German ed. only): Bahrenfelder-Chaussee 1 60, Hamburg-
Bahrenfeld, CCP. 276650. For scientific maps only:
GEO CENTER D7 Stuttgart 80, Postfach 800830.
Other publications: Verlag Dokumentation, Postfach 148,
Jaiserstrasse 13, 8023 Munchen-Pullach. GHANA.
Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195,
Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra;
The University Bookshop of Cape Coast, The University
Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1, Legon. GREAT
BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. GREECE. Anglo-
Hellenic Agency. 5, Koumparl Street Athens 138;
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock
Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY. Akadémiai Könyvesbolt,
Váci u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V. Konyvtarosok Boltja,
Népkóztársasig utja 16, Budapest VI. ICELAND.
Snaebjórn Jonsson & Co., H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Nicol Road, Ballard
Estate, Bombay 1 ; 17 Chlttaranian Avenue, Calcutta
13; 36a. Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf
Ali Road. New Delhi 1; Sub-Depots: Oxford Book
& Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta 16: and
Scindia House, New Delhi; Publications Section, Ministry
of Education and Social Welfare, 72Theatre Communication
Building, Connaught Place, New Delhi 1. INDONESIA.
Indira P.T., Jl. Dr. Sam Ratulangie 37, Jakarta. IRAN.
Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution C*., 229 Danesh-
gahe Street, Shah Avenue, P.O. Box 1 4-1 486, Teheran.
Iranian National Commission for Unesco, Avenue Iran-
chahr Chomali No 300. B.P. 1533, Teheran. IRAQ.
McKenzie's Bookshop, Al-Rashid Street, Baghdad;
University Bookstore, University of Baghdad, P.O. Box
75. Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of
Ireland Ltd., Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12.
ISRAEL. Emanuel Brown, formerly Blumstein's Booksto¬
res, 35 Allenby Road and 48, Nachtat Benjamin Street,
Tel-Aviv; 9, Shlomzion Hamalka Street Jerusalem.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box
366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston. JAPAN. Maruzen
Co. Ltd., P.O. Box 5050, Tokyo International 100-31.
KENYA. The E.S.A. Ltd., P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co., Ltd., P.O. Box 2942. Kuwait. LIBERIA.
Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication
& Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. LUXEM¬
BOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue, Luxem¬
bourg. MALAYSIA. Federal Publications Sdn. Bhd.,
Balai Berita, 31, Jalan Riong, Kuala Lumpur. MALTA.
Sapienza's Library, 26 Kingsway, Valletta. MAURI¬
TIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street,
Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30, Bid
des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. NETHERLANDS. For
the " Unesco Koener " Dutch edition only : Systemen
Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75, Amscerdam-1 007. Agent
for all Unesco publications : N. V. Martinus Nijhoff,
Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague. NETHERLANDS
ANTILLES. G. C. T. Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.). N.V.,
Willemstad. Curacao. N. A. NEW ZEALAND.
Government Printing Office, Government Bookshops
at : Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 130,
Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721, Christchurch; Alma
Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O.
Box 1104, Dunedin; Mulgrave Street, Private Bag,
Wellington. NIGERIA The University Bookshop
of Ife, The University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. Box
286; The University Bookshop of Nsukka; The University
Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello University Book¬
shop of Zaria. NORWAY. All publications : Johan
Grundt Tanum (Booksellers) Karl Johans gate 41/43,
Oslo 1. For Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Littera-
turtjeneste. Box 6125. Oslo 6. PAKISTAN. The
West-Pak Publishing Co. Ltd.. Unesco Publications
House, P.O. Box 374 G.P.O., Lahore; Showrooms:
Urdu Bazaar, Lahore, and 57-58 Murree Highway,
G/6-1, Islamabad. Pakistan Publications Bookshop,
Sarwar Road, Rawalpindi. Mirza Book Agency 65 Shahrah
Quaid-e-azam, P.O. Box N- 729. Lahore- 3 PHILIP¬
PINES. The Modern Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue,
P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. POLAND. All publica¬
tions : ORWN PAN Palac Kultury i Nauki, Warsaw.
For the Unesco Courier only : RUCH, ul. Wronia, 23,
Warsaw 10. PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda,
Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SINGA¬
PORE. Federal Publications Sdn Bhd., Times House,
River Valley Road, Singapore 9. SOUTHERN RHO¬
DESIA. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union Avenue,
Salisbury. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop,
100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B. 244
Colombo 2. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O.
Box 1118. Khartoum. SWEDEN. All publications:
A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2,
Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16. For the Unesco
Courier: Svenska FN-Förbundet, Skolgränd 2, Box 150
50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. SWITZERLAND. All
publications : Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse, Zurich.
Librairie Payot. rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11, CCP.
12-236. TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop,
P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND. Suksapan
Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal Caddesi,
Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop,
P.O. Box 145, Kampala. SOUTH AFRICA. All
publications: Van Schaik*s Bookstore (Pty). Ltd., Libri
Building, Church Street, P.O. Box 724, Pretoria. For
the Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Central News
Agency P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg. UNITED KING¬
DOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569, London,
S.E.I., and Government Bookshops in London, Edinburgh,
Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol.
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications Center, P.O.
Box 433. New York, N.Y. 10016. U.S.S.R. Mezhdu-
narodnaja Kniga, Moscow, G-200. YUGOSLAVIA.
Jugoslovensita Knjiga, Terazije, 27, Belgrade; Drzavna
Zalozba Slovenije Mestni Trg. 26, Ljubliana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
*
w
*>**fyH
1
.'%*. .«*
r* +
NUSUAL
TOMBSTONE ART
OF YUGOSLAVIA
(see page 17)
m
]]>
</page>
</document>
