<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="053853eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Road to asceticism
TR EAS U R ES Buddhist artists have never tired of recounting in paint and stone the Jataka stories-talesof Buddha's previous lives before he attained E lightenment. This 19th century painting,
onze of a series of panels in the rock and cave temple of Mulgirigala, southern Ceylon, depictsa scene fram the Vessantara Jataka, the last birth of the Buddha-to-be as a king who gave
away a !  his worldly possessions and departed to the forests with his wife and children to
WORLD ART lead a life of asceticism. It is reproduced from"Ceylon : Paintings from Temple, Shrine and
Rock", one of 23 albums published in the former"Unesco World Art Series"that presented
 many little-known or inaccessible masterpieces of art. Other unfamiliar works from the
W treasury of world art are featured in 38 Unesco paperbacks comprising a"PocketCeylon Art Series", and are also available as colour transparencies in 48 sets of Unesco art siides.
0 j
: >
1
in :
e'
a
c
o.
d
1 : >
< :
'"
"
. ê
. <:;
(/)
. :
a
N
H
Ci
E
Q.
1-
E
. g
'"
Q.
. É
< :
ou
u)
< :.
E-
O
o
ù :
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
couriez
AUGUST-SEPTEMBER 1971
24TH YEAR
PUBLISHED ion 13 EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabie
U. S. A.
Japanese
! ta) ! anI lian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7e.
Annual subscription rates : 1 : 1 stg. ; $4. 00
(Canada) ; 12 French francs or equivalent ;
2 years : S 1. 80 stg. ; 22 F. Single copies : 10 p
stg. ; 40 cents : 1. 20 F.
*
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except
in August and September when ! t ! s bi-monthiy (11 issues a
year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German, Arabie,
Japanese, Italian, Hindi, Tamil, Hebrew and Persian. lu thé
United Kingdom it is distributed by H. M. Stationery Office,
P. O. Box 569, London, S. E. !.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads"Reprinted from
the UNESCO COURIER,"plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re-
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied on request : Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returned unless accompanied by an international reply
coupon covering postage. Signed articles express the
opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of the
UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in the Read-
ers'Guide to Periodical Literature, published by
H. W. Wilson Co., New York, and in Current Con-
tents-Education, Philadelphia, U. S. A.
*
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7e, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy KoHler
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant to the Editor-in-Chief
0) ga Rôde)
Managing Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton (Paris)
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse (Paris)
Spanish Edition Francisco Fernândez-Santos (F
Russian Edition : Georgi Stetsenko (Paris)
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabie Edition : Abdel Moneim E) Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Hitoshi Taniguchi (Tokyo)
Italian Edition : Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Hindi Edition : Kartar Singh Duggal (Delhi)
Tamil Edition : N. D. Sundaravadivelu (Madras)
Hebrew Edition : Alexander Peli (Jerusalem)
Persian Edition : Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
Assistant Editors
English Edition : Howard Brabyn
French Edition : Nino Frank
Spanish Edition : Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research : Zoé Allix
Layout and Design : Robert Jacquemin
Ali correspondence should/Je addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief
< (
'"
<D
N
est
; : : :
u
: 2
(J
S
'"
a :J
o
Z
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
YOUTH OF
YOUTH OF
by René Maheu
Director-General of Unesco
On November 4. 1971, uJsco'tili twenty-five years o) d.
To those who have served Unesco throughout this quarter of a century, giving
unstintingty of themselves and being rewarded a hundredfold by the exhilaration that
cornes from dedication to man in a !) his universality, this anniversary provides a wealth
of materia ! for reminiscence and reftection concerning thé pasto
But it is to the future that t took. The future is the true dimension of Unesco which
has as its mission to usher in a new spirit and which draws its whole strength from
the hope inhérent in its purpose. My thoughts turn to those who were not yet born
when Unesco was created, the young people who are the future of the world and who
make up more than half its population.
tt was fitting to ask a young person, who had played no direct part in the history of
Unesco, to tett thé story of our first twenty-five years, as he himself saw them with
the clear, fresh eye of youth. Those of us who have lived this history have lived it
chiefly for the young peopte of his generation, ever since that"great and terrible
war"when everything was so nearly lost, up until today when our efforts-with ail
their shortcomings-are under the sweeping scrutiny of tomorrow's générations. And
it is precise ! y on them that Unesco's tomorrow dépends. Even if they may misjudge
certain aspects of our activities or some of our intentions can we fait to ask youth
about their attitudes towards our work and whether or not it cornes up to their
expectation ?
! n thé past twenty-five years Unesco has had to face situations and tasks that its
founders had never foreseen such as the cold'war of the Fifties and aid for develop-
ment in the Sixties. Unesco thereby has demonstrated a capacity for adaptation and
invention which testifies to its vitatity, and at the same time it has shown a remarkabte
insight into present-day realities and their probable aftermath.
These qualities will be especially needed in the immediate years ahead which, 1 feel
sure, wit ! see the opening up of a new era. Here i am not referring to political
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
events, to m. difications in relations between States-although some very important
changes are already ernergin'g on the horizon ; 1 am thinking of those more profound
transformatians that are now taking place in the thinking and actions of men which
are bringing into questicn the very meaning of life and the order o# society.
LMOST everywhere, especially amongst thé younger age groups, it seems
to be increasingly felt that the quality of life of the individual is the only real justification
for the efforts made to promote growth and prosperity in a community. It is clear
that the quality of life sought by many persons-including those who choose with-
drawal from society or the path of revoit-ca ! ! s for a re-examination of currentty
accepted values. Development is coming less and less to be equated with growth
pure and simple. Growth for what ? is the often heard question.
We can therefore be quite sure that education, science, culture and communic-
ations, that. is, learning and training, research and the creativity of the mind which
enable man to exptain his existence and give purpose to life, will be matters of the
utmost concern for governments and citizens alike in the quarter of a century to
come. This is atready the case with education. What has been catted the crisis in
education, or more properly, the need for the total regeneration of education, is
clearly evident in different forms and to varying degrees ait over the world. For some,
this"crisis"is merely a symptom heralding the approach of a vast cultural revolution.
Faced with such great changes, the focus of which is still unclear, it is not unfitting that
Unesco in its youth should be entrusted to the youth of the world. Their destinies
are inséparable.
THE WORLD
UNESCO
5
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
25 years
of Unesco
viewed by
a student
of 25
by Ehsan Naraghi
On November 4, 1971, the United Nations Educa-
tional, Scientific and Cultural Qrganization
celebrates its twenty-fifth anniversary. To
mark this occasion we are publishing in this
special issue of the"Unesco Courier"a"youth's eye"
view'of Unesco, its achievements, its failings and its
problems.
The outcome of months of probing and delving in
and around Unesco's Paris headquarters by a young
Canadian student, Wayne McEwing, this lively survey
gives a new perspective to the work of the least spe-
cialized of the United Nations specialized agencies.
With a ! ! doors open to him, McEwing examined
Unesco from top to bottom, assessing it with the
objectivity of an outsider and putting his reactions
down with the critical candour of youth.
The story of how he came to write about Unesco
in itself speaks volumes for the keen interest of young
EHSAN NARAGHI is director of Unesco's Youth Division, and
was formerly professor of sociology and director of social studios
and research at the University of Teheran (Iran). As a sociologist
he has collaborated for many years in the work of international
scientific associations. yn 1965 he prepared for the United Nations
the first world-wide study on the"Brain Drain". He has written
p M/tde/y on sociological problems in the deve/oping countries, and
rince 1970 he has given courses on youth, education and society
in the Third World, at the University of Vincennes., Paris. His
latest book,"Université, Jeunesse et Société" (University, Youth
and Society) will appear shortly in Teheran.
people everywhere in the international scene and for
Unesco's own interest in the questions and points of
view of youth. Moreover, it demonstrates how
Unesco's approach to the world of youth has evolved
over twenty-five years.
Broadly speaking, before 1968 emphasis was plac-
ed on youth activities in the fields of leisure and sport
activities. n 1968 came the realization that the prob-
lems of youth were of deep concern to society as a
Whole. Now a further step forward has been taken
with the recognition that the problems of society as a
whole are of direct. concern to youth.
! n 1969, Unesco held the first of a series of three-
month, summer study courses for students from ail
over the wor ! d, and these have now become an annual
event. The aim of the courses is to involve young
people directly in the work of Unesco and at the same
time to benefit from the impact of fresh vision and a
new approach-in fact, to establish a two-way traffic
of ideas.
Each student works in a field of direct interest to
his outside activities. A student teacher, for example,
finds himself alongside members of the permanent
staff of the Education Sector working out a funcfional
literacy project for South America ; in the Science
Sector a would-be geologist studies new methods of
assessing earthquake hazards.
At the end of three months, the twenty or so stu-
dents attending a course evaluate what they have
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
learned and make their own observations and criti-
cisms of the way Unesco operates.
Wayne McEwing attended the first of these courses,
dividing his time between the Office of Public Infor-
mation and the Division of Higher Education. He com-
pleted his three months convinced of the value of the
work being done by Unesco. But he was equally con-
vinced of the need to explain what Unesco was doing
in a graphic way that would give young people a
greater sense of involvement. This was particularly
true for young people is developed countries who are
often less aware of Unesco and its achievements than
their counterparts in the developing nations.
After returning home he explained his viewpoint
in a letter to Unesco's Director-General, René
Maheu. McEwing was then invited back to Paris and
given a free hand to tell the Unesco story in his own
words.
He listened to the opinions of representatives of
the Member States, quizzed experts who had return-
ed from missions in the field, and watched the per-
sonnel of the Secretariat at work.
Whatever their philosophy of life, their conception
of the world and of modern society, young people
throughout the world, are eager to share in the
achievement of those ideals for which Unesco stands.
Unesco is equally eager to establish a permanent
dialogue with and provide a rostrum for the youth of
the world.
However, Unesco knows that young people consider
that international co-operation, whatever its apparent
dimensions, does not go far enough to eliminate the
disparities between rich and poor which exist within
each nation and between developed and developing
countries. The danger that this gap will continue to
grow makes youth critical of a society in which pro-
gress is too often measured in quantifiable terms
rather than those of renewal and social change.
Beyond this criticism of the instruments of inter-
national co-operation, many young people question
current political, economic, social and cultural options ;
they feel that one cannot hope to right the ills of the
world if one remains impotent and silent before the
arms race, the repression practised against groups
and individuals, the degradation and waste of natural
resources. For ail of these preoccupations, ail these
inspirations, can only find an outlet in action if the
members of the international community commit them-
selves to a new phase of co-operation among peoples.
The creative energy which youth brings to this will
for co-operation is a promise for the future.
We hope that the publication of this series of
articles on Unesco's twenty-five years will help to
provoke amongst our readers both young and old a
broad discussion of Unesco's contribution to the dev-7
elopment of Education, Science and Culture in the
world and of youth's preoccupation with international
co-operation and peace between nattions.
: :'". < : ;.-Q-
ëë
g
 L
o
'oc. < :;a.
t 0
Q
F
 O
OL
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
'Since wars begin in
the minds of men,
it is in the minds
of men that
the defences of peace
must be constructed.'
Constitution
of the United Nations
Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization
"Spring", an oit-painting
executed n 1938
by the French arUet-poet
Francis Picabia.
a
h
1 : >
. 
U.
0s
e
Q
o
a :
ci)
'' :
Q
o
.,
'-'
Y C
, !
Q.
O
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
SEASONS
OF THE MIND
1-Thoughts of peace
by Wayne McEwing
WAYNE McEWING is a young Canadian
who studied English language and literature
at the University of Western Ontario. He
has done post-gradftate work at Exeter
Col/ege, Oxford, and Harvard University
in Cambridge, Mass.
T HEAE ;, a, a, cieo<"ory
about two men ploughing a field. The
earth was stony and the season was
bad, but as they ploughed their fur-
rows one man's face was tight-lipped
and cold-eyed. He was thinking of the
hardness of his life, the aching of his
feet and legs. His horse did not go
fast enough to suit him and he was
convinced that his neighbour's wheat
would grow taller and fuller than his.
His neighbour, meanwhile, worked
with rhythm and grace, concentrating
on how straight he could direct his
plough, stopping now and then to rest
his mare.
As the sun beat down on them both
and the heat of the day increased, the
first farmer lashed out again and again
at his horse with the reins, sweat pour-
ed down into his eyes, the veins of his
hands stood out as he grasped the
handle of his plough. He could think
only that his neighbour was mocking
him by purposely going so slowly
about his work, and his rage built to
a violent crescendo. If he had his
neighbour's horse, he could plough
twice as easily, and twice as much.
He threw down his plough and, his
tongue thick, scooped up the largest
rock he could find. Then with a wild
cry he flung himself across the field
toward the other.
The next day, the neighbour was
back ploughing the field, but now he
was using both horses. He walked
more slowly than usual, however, sad-
dened by the strange memory of the
day before. He had looked up to see
his fellow farmer running wildly toward
him. Before he had time to react, the
man fell dead at his feet, his hand still
grasping a stone. Till the day he him-
self died, he was never able to under-
stand what had gone on in the other
man's mind or from where his savage
violence had sprung.
The moral of the story may be
obvious, but it is far from being sim-
ple. Both rage and a sense of peace
are very private qualities, both are
given birth in the fascinating, secret
places of the mind.
It is not enough to say simply that
the two men had a different state of
rnind and leave it as that. Clearly the
difference between them is a question
of value ; the man in harmony with his
world is better, more"human"than
the other.
By extension, the only really human
nation is a nation composed of people
with that same sense of inner peace-
fulness. There was a time when it
was considered possible to make peo-
ple and states get along by setting
down laws of conduct, but now when
the stakes have become so high, we
are beginning to realize that that kind
of uneasy, imposed peace is just too
unstable and dangerous.
Where would one begin to stimulate
that kind of ideal peace in individuals
and nations in a world only too ob-
viously full of discord and selfishness ?
That was exactly the problem facing
the people who were setting up the
United Nations system at the end of
the Second World War. It was ai ! very
we ! ! to bring governments together
to iron out differences, ai ! very
we ! ! to get food and medicine to the
millions of emaciated, disease-ridden
citizens of the world, but even at that,
it was not enough. To stop there
would be like giving an accident victim
painkiller and a hearty meal and not
trying to treat his wounds.
To really promote peace and gen-
erosity of spirit, they saw they had to
CONTINUED PAGE 12
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Photo &commat; Ins itut GéoraphiQue National, Paris
HELICOPTER VIES OUF
10 UNESCO lN PARIS
Unesco's headquarters with its distinctive 3-pointed, star-shaped Secretariat
building is clearly visible (Iower left) in this helicopter view of part of Paris's
Left Bank. The headquarters complex stands in the Place de Fontenoy, at the
end of an axis formed by a number of famous Parisian landmarks comprising
(from top right of photo) the lena Bridge, leading to the Eiffel Tower (not easy
to spot here as photo was taken almost at its vertical), the gardens of the
Champs de Mars and the Military Staff College. Fittingly, the Unesco H. Q.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
replaced old military barracks. With its striking modern architecture Unesco's
H. Q. has now become a familiar Paris landmark since its inauguration in 1958.
Corrugated pattern in left corner of Unesco site is the roof of the main
conference building. Six rectangles facing it contain blocks of underground
offices and conference rooms, ail looking on to six patios, each with a garden
and fountains. Another Unesco building (not shown in photo) has recently
been constructed a short distance from the main headquarters complex.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
THOUGHTS OF PEACE (Continued tram page 9)
deal with the minds of men. The
theory was that when you saw how
your neighbour's mind worked what
he ate, what he had accomplished,
what he had learned about the world
around him, how his family and cul-
tural background had shaped him and
how he looked at you, it would be
almost impossible to hate him. The
human mind cannot seem to reject
what it tries to understand.
Scientific knowledge, educational
background, cultural heritage... these
seemed the general areas that had to
be explored. And without too much
thouqht it becomes clear that in ait
these respects there are people in the
world who are light years apart.
Some men are literally living in the
stone age, and just because society
mi"ht feed them and take away their
hatchets (sometimes in exchange for
guns) it hasn't, begun to bring them
into the twentieth century.
50 he","the United
Nations Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization, Unesco, facing
the task of figuring out and developing
the mind of man, always toward peace
and mutual understanding, but very
often toward being able to write a
name, plant a field, or run a tractor.
To be honest, the United Nations
proved just how idealistic they were
by creating Unesco. The very thought
of heightening the consciousness of
the entire world is staggering, and it
stands to reason that any progress is
painfully slow. No one knows that
better than the people who work at
Unesco headquarters in Paris. Psy-
chologically, there can be few tasks
more frustrating than trying to put
an idealistic scheme into practical
operation.
When you are looking with a shrewd
eye at any organization, if you really
want to know how it ticks, it is wise
to find out who makes the decisions
and, even more bluntly, where the
money to support it comes from.
At Unesco the decisions are made
at a General Conference of the one
hundred and twenty-five member
states. Each delegation at these con-
ferences (they happen every two
years) has one vote in spite of the
fact that the contributions they make
vary a great deal, according to how
much they can afford to pay.
12 The people who work in variousdepartments of the headquarters in
Paris prepare detailed sets of pro-
posai for projects they think should
be attempted or pursued in the inter-
ests of the community of member
states. submit them to the conference
and then wait to find out if the majority
are willing to accept their ideas.
It is difficult enough to have one
boss, but when one has one hundred
and twenty-five of them, a with their
own views and interests, life can seem
incredibly complicated. To put it
mildly, the job of being Director-
General of Unesco (at headquarters
he is reverentially referred to as the
DG) requires boundless quantities of
tact. But one thing that comes across
more and more forcibly as time goes
on is that these 125 different states
actually can agree, and though the
odds against it seem enormous, they
can be brought into a working arrange-
ment together.
An interesting change has come
about in the membership of the or-
ganization. At the beginning there
were 20 countries involved, on the
who ! e, part of that cultural block called
"western civilization"and the atmos-
phere was more or less like a fashion-
able, post-war club for intellectuals.
However, life has speeded up con-
siderably since then and as new
nations have appeared literally by the
score (especially in Africa), the whole
tone of the place has changed.
When you take the lift in the
Secretariat, or especially when you
look into one of the conference rooms,
you get a very strong sense that this
is not just a building in a particular
city, in a particular country, it is a
building on the face of the earth. The
first thing you notice is the blend in
styles of clothing, then the mêlée of
languages, many not even identifiable
to the ear, and then the exciting
business of simultaneous translation
into the five officia) languages...
English, French, Russian, Spanish and
Arabic.
More important, as far as Unesco's
work is concerned, the emphasis is no
longer on the exchange of ideas
alone, but now the key work is
"deve ! opment". Unesco has taken
on an active role in education, science,
culture and communication, so for
every person working in the Secre-
tariat in Paris, there are two people
working on Unesco projects"in the
field". And that phrase has come to
cover a startlingly large range. It
can mean an expert giving advice on
how to set up a university in Iraq,
another shoring up the ruins of an
ancient temple in ! ndonesia, or yet
another working on a project in marine
biology at a centre in Mexico.
Again the question of money comes
up. If Unesco has taken on ah these
projects, who pays for them ? If
CONTINUED PAGE 14
HISTORY
! N A GLOBAL
PERSPECTIVE
One of the outstanding achievements
of Unesco's 25 years of effort is the
six-volume"History of Mankind", a
vast pioneering effort to bring an
international approach to the writing
of w o r i d history. Sponsored by
Unesco and produced by the Inter-
national Commission for a History of
the Scientific and Cultural Develop-
ment of Mankind, it spans the years
from prehistoric times to the 20th
century. Over 1, 000 historians, philo-
sophers and scholars from 62 coun-
tries laboured for eighteen years to
produce this 7, 000 page world history
with its many i)) ustrations and maps.
Editions have already been published in
seven languages (English, French,
Spanish, Greek, Dutch, Serbo-Croatian
and Siovenian) and further editions in
Hebrew and Catalan are in prepara-
tion. Unlike other world histories,
that have laid stress on war and
conflict between nations and peoples,
this history was the first attempt to
place man's scientific and cultural
development in a truly global perspec-
tive. Leaving aside the traditional
nationalistic approach to the writing
of history, the"History of Mankind"
presents a detailed study of the cross-.
fertilization of scientific ideas, of reli-
gions and cultural life, of economic
and social events and the forms of
artistic expression and the scientific
thinking of many peoples and cultures.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Above, a Chinese rabbin9 of the Han period, 206 B. C. to 220 A. D. Below,"Vou are free
in order to realize your dreams."reads an inscription which accompanies this mural on the
faculty of law building of the University City at Quito. The mosaic was designed by Guayasamin,
Ecuador's most famous living artist.
From"Estampages Han"by Zao Wou ki and Claude Roy, Club Français du Livre ; paris
Photo &commat; Holmes-Camera Press
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
THOUGHTS OP FEACE (Continued)
Unesco people just had their own
budget of about $90 million to go on,
they could make suggestions, do some
studies for governments and arrange
conferences, but as far as putting
projects into operation, their hands
would virtually be tied. So, Unesco
has become an administrator of other
people's money. For instance, from
the vast lump of money put aside by
the U. N. for world-wide development,
Unesco, under the watchful eye of the
people in New York, uses a sizeable
chunk for projects of the mind.
Also, individual organizations and
countries sometimes make specific
contributions to special projects in
other parts of the world, and here
Unesco plays the part of a generous
investment counsellor.
Often when you hear about aid
being given to a particular country,
it seems that they are merely being
given a hand-out by the so-called
richer nations. But in reahty thé nations
receiving aid have to put up the
money for as much of the project as
they can afford and do as much of
the work as they can. They may get
free advice and supplies, but as far
as possible, they are given the
dignity of paying their own bills and
helping themseives.
Another important question comes
to mind. How does Unesco decide
on doing a project in one country and
not another ? Do they send people
around telling different nations that
their educational systems are bad or
that they had better get busy and start
co-operating intellectually ? Hardly,
when it is up to the nations and up
to Unesco to wait until the member
state decides to ask for advice.
Let us invent the imaginary country
of Sutch. For our purposes Sutch is
a member of Unesco and every two
years three prominent Sutcherians
come to the conference in Paris.
(incidentatty. at the request of Unesco,
one of their delegates is a promising
young man beginning a career in his
native country and for him the con-
ference will be in itself a new kind
of educational experience.) The head
of the delegation, let us say, is a
charming, worldly-wise Sutcherian who
was educated abroad and then went
back to his native Sutch to make a
name for himself in educational circles.
He comes to Paris full of enthusiasm
for a project that he has been nursing
in the back of his mind ever since
he himself had to go half-way across
the world to school. If only Sutch
had its own university, he feels, its
14 educational system would really becomplete. Sutch might be small and
relatively poor, but since his student
days the quafity of its schools has
improved immensely, and he feels
that, with Unesco backing, now is the
time to found the University of Sutch.
Like most people, he feels that his
educational background is just what
everyone's should be, and when he
envisions the new campus, he pictures
a place very similar to his alma mater
transported to a pleasant hill just
outside the capital city of Sutch.
His proposa ! s are ail carefully set
out in detail, giving estimates of the
cost of the project, the need for
Unesco's advice and aid, the expected
enrolment and a ! ! thé other facts that
seem relevant. To a ! i of this, the
delegate adds his own enthusiasm
as he meets with many different
educational experts at headquarters.
They listen, ask questions, pause,
compare the Sutcherian project to
others they have worked on, check
the information that they have about
the Sutcherian school system, look at
the national economy, the political
situation.
A project of this size is going to
take several years of concentrated
work and a lot of capital, and no
matter how tempting the idea might
seem, it has to be questioned and
tested from every possible angle ; this
is not only to prevent Unesco from
wasting its time and other people's
money, but even more important, to
make sure the Sutcherians aren't
getting into something that they won't
be able to handle.
FOR, wh ; !., th.",." ; on,
that Unesco asks are random and
exploratory, but as the negotiations go
on some of them begin to fit into a
pattern. in the course of the dis-
cussions, one man asks how many
engineers Sutch is producing per year
and where they get their training.
They, too, have to go abroad to get
their instruction, do they not ?
The Sutcherian delegate is not too
sure of the precise number, but he
suspects that at most four or five
of them are produced per year.
Technological and scientific education
haven't caught on in his country, he
says, and most people want to study
humanities for a general education.
These statements strike the Unesco
expert as ah too familiar. Where are
a ! ! thèse arts graduates going to get
jobs, and what are the chances for
Sutch to develop its technology
without technicians ?
Someone else asks the Sutcherian
delegate what form he thinks the
university should take that would
really reflect the Sutcherian culture ?
That question stuns him ; he has never
thought about an educational system
as part of any particular culture, but
the more he thinks it over, the more
he begins to suspect that the ins-
titution he had in mind was more a
reflection of himself and of his own
experience than of the Sutcherian
culture as a whole.
Ideally, at this point the Sutcherian
delegate will begin to see that, eco-
nomically, a technical school will be
much more beneficial to the country
as a whole, that his idea of a uni-
versity will have to wait, and that
when it finally does become a reality
it will be very different from what he
had in mind. Ideally, Unesco and
Sutch will be able to raise the money
to set up the technical school, and
Sutch will be on its way to a techno-
logical renaissance and a new phase
in its history.
A ! ! thèse things will happen if the
de ! egate is willing to put off his
dream for a university, if the Unesco
experts have asked the right questions
about the project, if the Sutcherians
themselves are willing to study
science and engineering instead of the
humanities, if there isn't a more
pressing need for Unesco work and
money in another country. But in
actual fact, where human foibles and
limitations are concerned, things don't
always work out so smoothly.
"< :"
: >oaJ
ci
tQJ
0)< :
.. 
'"
o
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
While Unesco lends no support to one industria-
list's vie that"History ils buna", rit hais gong been
avare khat a grenat dal ouf buna still masquerades
ans history. Ans early ans 1950, Unesco sent in motion
a series of investigations of history textbooks
which revealed appalling distorsions ouf fac, souper-
filial treatment ouf major historical vents and
whole cultural areas of the world, out-of-date
accounts ouf the lifte stylets and custom ouf foreign
countries and aven hue lacune in the presentation
ouf certain major faces ouf history."ln lests than
once lifetime", rote Arnold Toynbee in 1956,"te
fasce ouf the world hais changea almost oust ouf recto-
ignition... Or vison ouf the history ouf mankind,
sine the risse ouf the earliest known civilizations
absout 5. 000 years agio, hais ben enormously enlarged
and hais alto ben brought inti mach harper focs.
Ad sine curiosity ils once ouf the characteristics of
humain mature, le fin ourselves moved, in our
trime. tao tale a now look ait the now fasce ouf history
ans a whole. Ans son ans once looks ait the now piano-
rampa ouf history, once sexes khat rit bursts the bounds
ouf the curent framework within which or western
historias havie ben doping their work for the fast
250 yea rs."
Unesco hais na poser noir the désire tao rye-frite
an country's history textbooks ; the only people
who cas duo tris are the peuple in mach country.
Brut, bey organizing spécial meeting with history
brook writers and publishers, Unesco has
encouraged the"de-bunking"of history
textbooks 50 khat pupifs ait nover the world
cas bye given a morse balance and morse objective
view of other countries.
For one thing, this example makes
Unesco look very wise and experi-
enced, but just as easily, the Sutch-
erian delegate might have come to
Paris bubbling over with exciting new
ideas and plans for educational reform,
only to find that Unesco wasn't ready
for them yet. No matter who is doing
the suggesting or who is lagging
behind, the important thing is for
governments and Unesco to work
together in spite of ai ! thé possible
obstacles.
! n that kind of relationship it is easy
to see why in Unesco there are so
many people concerned with liaison
between states, organizations and the
secretariat itse ! f. Proposa !, counter
proprosai, compromise, re-thinking,
changes of tactics, breakthroughs in
understanding... out of it a ! ! a project
gathers energy and support and gets
under way.
Then you have to add the new
dimension of the understanding, tact
and efficiency of a great number of
individuals putting it into operation in
the field and you begin to get an
idea of the full working of a project,
the research and planning involved,
thé diplomacy, and the solid hard
work.
Another factor of Unesco's job is
that most of the things it tries to do
have never been done before, so by
their very nature the projects are
elaborate experiments, experiments
often run on a limited budget and,
above ait, designed to be practical
when governments want to put them
into use throughout their country.
One expert offers his solution, another
expert insists that his is better. It
seems that there is a constant tugging
in two opposite directions, one toward
ultra-modern ideas and one toward
suggestions that are at least some-
what tried by experience.
0OF 00""0, it is up to the
government itself to make the final
decision ; their intuitions as to what
techniques will work and what will not
are bound to be more reliable than
those of even the most experienced
Unesco advisors. It might seem easier
for them to stay w ! th'the tried and
true remedies, but sometimes countries
which are developing at a breath-
taking rate do not have time to rely
on twentieth century answers and have
to caii on technology that really
belongs to the twenty-first century.
Just to complicate matters further,
in many cases there is no way of
knowing how a particular project is
working until it has been in operation
for a number of years. How do you
tell if a new educational system is
working until someone has had an
entire education in it ?
When you consider that several
thousands of individual young men and
women could have their entire educ-
ation wasted and their lives seriously
hurt if your system doesn't work out,
you use every bit of foresight and
draw on a ! ! thé wisdom you can muster.
Or as another example, after you
carefully draw up a treaty about copy-
rights or the preservation of monu-
ments, you can only find out if it is
going to work when it has been
tested by circumstance. ! n thé mean-
time, writers'life works may have
been pirated and irreplaceable
churches and museums destroyed.
You do your best. You can never
succeed completely, but hopefully you
never"fail completely, even if a ! ! you
have managed to gain is experience
for the next attempt.
But enough of the general nature of
Unesco. The categories"education,
science and culture"cover a huge
range. For instance, education in-
cludes teaching both young people
and adults to read and write, setting
up primary schools as we ! ! as uni-
versities, teaching sciences as weii as
humanities. So instead of dividing the
subject matter into big blocks, we shall
try to be as spécifie as possible absout
some Unesco projects and goals, and
from that you should be able to get
an idea of the whole..
HELPING TO RE-WRITE HISTORY
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
2-LITERACY
The mind
awakening
A 900d p'oo. ta,,, et d ;,-
cussing Unesco's work in education is
with the most basic kind of teaching...
leading people on their first steps from
illiteracy to the simplest kind of
reading, writing and calculating.
The very fact that you are reading
this page sets you apart from a lot of
the world's population. It is impossible
to say exactly how rriany people in the
world are illiterate ; naturally, govern-
ments who must supply the statistics
are eager to present as bright a picture
of their educational systems as pos-
sible, but conservative United Nations'
guesses put the present total at around
800 million people over the age of 15.
Eight hundred million people... one
of those figures that are a ! ways being
thrown at us. Look at it another way.
That means about one-third of the
world's adult population, over the age
of 15, or about four times the popula-
tion of the United States.
It may seem surprising, but there are
still people in the twentieth century who
think that"what folks don't know won't
hurt them"and that"a little learning
is a dangerous thing"."Why not leave
things as they are. If someone has the
talent and wants to learn, he will
somehow be able tao. n
At one time the educated élite might
have been able to justify that kind of
16 reasoning, but now when the illiterate
main is bombarded daily with signs and
important instructions, literacy has
become a matter of survival for every-
one. Just imagine yourself, no matter
where you live, trying to get through a
day if you couldn't read even the
simplest words and phrases, and you
will get some sense of the frustrations
that the modern-day illiterate has to
live with.
Ever since it was founded, Unesco
has been working in the field of literacy
and it is encouraging to see that,
finally, according to Unesco statistics,
the percentage of illiterates in the world
has begun to go down. What is most
frustrating, however, is that the world's
population is increasing so fast that,
in spite of the percentage figures, in
actuality, the total number of illiterates
is increasing at the rate of several
million a year.
On top of that, no one knows just
how many people have had literacy
training and are"officially"literate, but
have forgotten ah they knew because,
once their training was over, they had
no way to keep in practice. Unesco
insists that literacy has to be
"functional"or else it is just a point-
less exercise ; it may seem to be a
glorious and magnanimous gesture
to make as many people in a country
literate as quickly as you can, but
in effect, unless you make their new
abilities part of their lives, you are
being very unfair to them.
Put yourself in their place. What
could be more discouraging than to
learn the"magic"skills of reading and
writing only to find out that it hasn't
improved your life in any way ?
Naturally, you would forget it ah in no
time, and you would end up with a
terrible sense of being cheated and
made a fool of.
Literacy, Unesco has found, isn't
simply a matter of education ; it is a
matter of large-scale social change.
The newly literate individual should
have a chance to make the written word
part of his everyday life, whether in
his job or even in reading a special
"hteracy"newspaper that is geared to
his interests and his reading abilities
until he can read a regular paper.
THE new', n, tional nte,."
approach has to begin right from the
kind of knowledge that people use. A
man who makes his living at growing
cotton is vitally concerned with inform-
ation on new techniques of tilling the
soil and getting as rich a harvest from
his land as he can.
! n his case, Unesco experts have
developed a series of illustrated basic
primers beginning with the word"cotton"in his language and leading
him into more and more complicated
aspects of his job. By the time he has
mastered the information he needs to
know for his work he has begun to
learn td read. The same is just as true
for peuple of other cultures and other
languages who want to learn to run a
tractor or build a house.
Unesco primers to teach children to
learn to read and write are, naturally,
CONTINUED PAGE 18
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
) n 1956, 25 million
students were enroltad
in primary, secondary
and higher education
in Latin America.
By 1965 thé figure rose
to 42 miiiion and in 196S
it reached 51 mMtion.
This spectacular
achievement reflects
thé efforts made by
Latin American countr ! es,
particuiariy within the
framework of thé major
Project for primary
éducation in Latin America,
iaunched by
Unesco in 1957.
Right, Brazilian
schooichiidren from
thé Amazon région.
Photo . : Yves Billon. France
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
THE MIND AWAKENING (continues)
not so technical, but even they must
be carefully tailored to the world as
each child knows it."Dick and Jane
Build a 8nowman"or"The Adventures
of a 8quirrel"might be staple first
readers for children in temperate zones
where there are snowmen and squirrels,
and where the names Dick and Jane
are common, but they would be
strange and almost useless to a child
who grew up in tropica ! Asia or Africa.
It seems self-evident that any
person will learn to read and write
best in his native tongue ; it is hard
enough to master the reading and
writing without having to tackle a new
language at the same time. The diffi-
culties arise when, as in several areas
of Africa, the languages people speak
have no written form ; they have been
preserved completely by word of
mouth, as the languages of northern
Europe once were.
! n thèse cases, to teach the people
a different language for reading and
writing is to make their oral language
disappear completely in almost no
time. So that this won't happen,
Unesco experts are now busy record-
ing these precious traditions and
putting six groups of African languages
into a usable written form. One added
advantage of this project is that these
languages transcend mere political
barriers, and when they can be written
and understood, communication bet-
ween states will be made much easier.
UNFORTUNA TEL Y. the
people whose native tongues these
are have to wait on the average five
years before their languages can be
written down for them, and even longer
before basic literacy primers can be
developed. These language groups
are far from being"primitive"and eàsy
to reduce to an existing alphabet and
grammatical structure.
For example, in Yoruba, which is a
language of Nigeria, Ghana, Togo and
Dahomey, there may be as many as
57 different tense forms, as opposed
to a mere dozen or so in English and
French, and the language is tonal, so
that the same sounds pronounced with
different tones have different meanings.
Yet another local language, Hausa,
was already written down, but in two
different ways. ! n Nigeria, which was
administered by the British, it was done
according to English phonetics, and in
Niger, which was administered by the
French, according to French phonetics.
The result was one language that
looked like two foreign tongues. Now
Unesco experts are trying to devise a
way of writing Hausa that will be
. taught and understood in both Niger
and Nigeria.
18 tue search for new literacy tech-t Q niques, thé setting up of pilot projectes
to test them and thé work of putting
new concepts of literacy into long-
range plans for national development
and productivity are fascinating and
exciting in themselves, but at the
centre of ail this activity, the man who
is learning to read and write has
some definite demands and opinions
of his own.
He is moving through time at a fan-
tastic rate, from a social context be-
fore the written word to a highly liter-
ate modern realm ; he knows better
than anyone else just what a handicap
his illiteracy is, but at the same time,
he is an adult who got along in the
world long before any government
teacher or Unesco expert came to
give him an education and he refuses
to be patronized or talked down to.
For example, the illiterate who lives
in supposedly developed western
cities such as Chicago, Genoa or
Birmingham (to name a few) is parti-
cularly shy about admitting his limit-
ation. ! n his case, it takes carefully
developed television programmes and
advertising to give him the incentive
to begin classes or, in some cases, to
begin classes for the second or third
time ; here too, what some people
learned as children and never had a
chance to practice can become lost in
the grey chasms of lethargy and aim-
lessness.
Although the reaction may vary from
culture to culture, in many cases
adults attending literacy classes are
very sensitive to being treated like
children. The thought of meeting in
their own children's schoolrooms in the
evenings may strike them as vaguely
demeaning, and they are much more
relaxed in a church or a meeting
hall, in buildings that they have built
themselves as literacy centres, or
simply under the shade of a tree while
the daylight lasts.
The kind of person who is chosen
as the literacy teacher makes a very
important difference, as tell. Regu-
lar schoolteachers usually aren't as
effective with adults as people who
have been through a literacy pro-
gramme themselves and are fired
with enthusiasm to share their new-
found knowledge with their peers.
Usually, teachers who are not too
much younger than the students have
a better effect, but as soon as you
start making these distinctions, you
are bound to find a nineteen-year-old,
third-grade teacher who is more effec-
tive than ail the forty-year-old new
literates carefully chosen for a project.
You simply can't make neat, fixed
rules where literacy teaching is con-
cerned. Most often in the final analy-
sis it is the personal element that
makes the difference between success
and failure, and, often, you take who-
ever you can get for the job until
someone more effective or better
qualified can be found.
After Unesco experts and local
educators have studied what particular
methods of teaching will be most
effective for a particular country (most
likely by trial and error in experimental
projects), after they have devé ! oped
CONTINUED PAGE 20
BLIND TO THE
WRITTEN WORD
This young Sudanese woman (right) is
training to be a midwife, but since she
cannot read she is taught by repetition
and demonstration to identify certain drugs
by sight and, with eyes blindfolded, by
smell or taste. Soon, like many thousands
of other Sudanese, she may no longer be
blind to the written word thanks to an
intensive literacy campaign carried out by
the Sudan with Unesco aid. The campaign
is part of Unesco's experimental world
literacy programme launched in 1964, and
linking iiteracy with agricultural and
industrial deveiopment It now has projects
in operation in 13 countries of Africa, Asia
and Latin America, and 53 other countries
have asked to join the programme. f3elow,
literacy class for Peruvian women on an
island in Lake Titicaca, more than 12, 500
feet above sea level in the Andes, one of
the poorest regions in the world.
'"0oN
_
m
O
Y :
a : i
o.00
 1< :
=>1
o 1
 i0. 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
3
lU
. L ;
o
en
o
'' :
UJ
o
I
o
Õ
. c :
a.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
THE MI ND AWAKENING (Continued)
the materials necessary for teaching,
after they have trained the nucleus of
a teaching staff, and after a ! ! thé un-
expected snags have been ironed out
(such as adjusting to local harvesting
schedules in one place or compensat-
ing for long-standing social reactions
that hadn't been foreseen in another)
it is up to Unesco to slowly phase
itself out and up to the government to
take the project from there.
Where the government picks up
wholeheartedly as Unesco leaves, the
project should be firmly on its way.
Often the initial decision to invest in
adult literacy meant cutting back on
something like defence spending or on
more traditiona ! forma) éducation,
and as governments and individuals
change, so do their priorities.
Sad to say, where the government
has lost interest, or where it can't
afford to supply its share of the con-
tinuing costs, the project dies, and
within a short space of time ail thé
money and hours of work evaporate
as if they had never been invested.
Just to put Unesco's work in pers-
pective, however, many countries have
used striking methods of their own in
their blitz for literacy and, in these
instances, it is up to Unesco, through
its surveys, conferences and studies,
to pass on the information to others.
To supply the crucial need for liter-
acy teachers in Iran, for instance,
soldiers who had considerable educa-
tion were put into service as a peace-
time Literacy Corps. Now a simNar
idea has been used with the national
guard in Venezuela and the possibili-
ties the idea suggests seem endless.
Wouldn't it be a relief if a ! ! thé armies
of the world coula be turned into
educational forces full time ?
One of the most encouraging signs
both for Unesco and for the individual
governments concerned is how many
people want desperately to become
! iterate, so much so that, in some
cases, whatever projects might be
devised simply can't keep up with
them.
One Unesco expert assigned to
Ethiopia noticed a gentleman in a first
year literacy class writing busily and
at a level far ahead of the rest."D
you think this man has had some train-
ing a ! rèady ?" he asked the local
teacher."If he can read as we !) as
he can rite, 1 think we've put him in
the wrong class."
Sure enough, the man read back
what he had written perfectly, but he
insisted that he had never been to
school. Had he done it on his own ?
Oh, no. He was the proud father of
educated children, children who went
to school everyday. Every night when
they'came home he would sit down
with them and listen to their stories.
They would show him what their teach-
er had taught them and that is how
FÏÏ he knew about writing and numbers.If his children were goina to grow up
educated, wasn't it natural that he
should be educated too ? N
A RACE BETWEEN EDUCATION
AND CATASTROPHE
H. G. Wells wrote that the modern world is embarked on a race between education
and catastrophe. And it is true that if we want to ensure lasting peace in the world,
we have no ttme to lose to bring about a radical improvement in the standard of
living of the economically poor countries of the world. Most governments have
corne to a new awareness of the key role that education plays in a nation's develop-
ment. tn this respect, the efforts undertaken by Unesco in the past 25 years have
been of capital importance. The Director of the Institute of Education at the Univer-
sity of London, Dr Lionel Elvin, has aptly remarked that the most powerful single
idea that has spread through the world in relation to education in the last 25 years
is that it is a right. ln 1970. International Education Year, reports from Unesco's mem-
ber states revealed an unprecedented growth in the field of education. Between
1950 and 1965, the number of teachers in the world d incfeased from 8 to 16 million.
School enrolment increased by 80 per cent in India and 42 per cent in
Iran. tn the Arab countries enrolment increased from 8 1/2 million students in
1960 to 13 million in 1967. tn Latin America, between 1960 and 1967, thé number of
pupils entering primary education increased by 12 million.
a
djeQ.
a :
X,
. ! ! !
m j
0
Po
: ; ;
s 
po,
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
1  1 \
The
.
growlng
mind
whaut HAT.'Qumeot would
convince a bank to give a long-term
loan, without collateral, with no interest
and based completely on speculation ?
Investment bankers are a very shrewd
and practical lot and refuse to be
taken in by promises of vast capital
to be made or grand schemes for
future development. On the whole
they want their balance sheets to
prove that their money is actually
working and that it is working as
profitably as it possibly can.
Unesco has found that one area in
which they will give loans on exact-
! y thèse terms is in the field of
educational development. The real
resources of a country are not its
minera) deposits, nor ! ts agricuttura)
wealth, but rather, the people in it.
As gold must be refined, so these
people must be educated. Although
you cannot measure the profit immedi-
ately, sure enough, as the educational
level of a country increases, so does
its productivity... and that makes for
a good inve ; stment on anyone's terms.
Hence, the knowledgeable business-
men of the World Bank have decided
to make money available, through
Unesco, to finance educational projects
throughout the world. Again, the
individual governments have to contri-
bute as much as they can, and often
large parts of their budgets are spent
in the field of education, but it is
usually in the developing countries
which have least to spend that the
need is greatest.
For the sake of argument, let us
assume that a country has no formai
educational system, (and the problem
is never that straightforward in actual-
ity) ; where would you begin in setting
one up ? Naturally, you would start
with teachers, but where would you
get them ? The systems of education
in developed countries are self-
perpetuating in that teachers teach
young people who in turn can become
teachers.
in developing countries, you are
forced to create teachers almost over-
night out of people who really should
be students. The difficulties of per-
forming this conjuring trick are almost
insurmountable, and here is where a
great deal of planning and willingness
to learn from others becomes abso-
lutely crucial.
Not only does Unesco send experts
to individual countries, but it has set
up regional centres for educational
planning where countries with similar
cultures and interests can pool their
individual findings, work out ground
rules that will be useful to them a ! !,
and save each other a lot of valuable
time in planning their separate edu-
cational strategies.
And by planning is meant not just
starting high-powered teacher training
courses, building schools and planning
curricula and text-books ; it also means
taking into consideration such things
as what kinds of teaching won't set
up socio-cultural barriers that might
keep students from coming back day
after day, what techniques will make
the deepest, most economical impact
on them, and what training pro-
grammes will fit in best with the needs
of the country as a whole.
ONCLE again, this is an
uncharted field where you must begin
by setting up small, spécifie exper-
iments ; if they work, the government
can apply them to larger and larger
sections of the country depending on
the national plans for future expansion.
Often, in the area of education,
beside simply planning, experimenting
and rejecting a project if it doesn't
seem to work, you have to make the
brave decision to keep doing what you
are doing a limule longer in the hope 21
that it will finally catch zon.
When you are dealing with teacher-
training, for example, your first years
CONTINUED PAGE 24
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Photo S) C ! audeVénézia, Pans
22
...
õ
>-
mCl)
z
i
U
z
i
"
ï :
, : :>
E
. g
"
m
...
: !
CI)
: ;s
5
1-
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The two children in the photo below look as if they are having the time of their lives-and they
probably think they are. But you don't have to stand on your head to see what a topsy-turvy world
we live in. It is in the regions of the world where the needs are greatest that the means are most
! acking. m 1970 there were 1, 100 million children under the age of 15 in the developing countries
compared with only 312 million in the more developed countries (table, opposite). Children in the
prosperous countries (photo left) will then represent only one-fifth of the world's children.
They can expect to get an education while the vast majority of children (in the developing countries)
will still lack teachers, schools and books. A major Unesco effort to promote education in the
developing countries has been carried out in recent years in conjunction with the World Bank.
Up to now World Bank loans and credits for improving education have totalled $440 million.
Present plans foresee World Bank loans for education of a further $1, 000 million during the next
five years, between 1971-1976.
TOPSY
TURVY
WORLD
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
THE GROWING MIND (Continued Irom page 21)
of effort can seem very discouraging.
If a small country needs two or three
hundred teachers immediately, you set
up a training centre for as many
promising candidates as you can find,
let us say one hundred and fifty. You
hope to give them a fast education and
teacher-training at the same t ! me. but
you may find that at the end of five
years you have only been able to train
five or six people whom you could
really ça) ! compétent.
) n that case, a) ! you can do is keep
working with the group of people you
began with until they are trained,
trying every new and helpful method
you can come across. ln the mean-
time, there are yearly more and more
children of school age still with no
teachers and no schools.
ne of Unesco's most
venturesome and colourful projects
that was started as a small experiment
is now at the stage of being put into
practice nationally in the Ivory Coast.
The basic problem to be faced was
setting up primary schools in the
outlying areas of the country which for
part of the year were virtually inac-
cessible, but it went far beyond that.
Where would the teachers come from ?
How would they be trained ? There
weren't enough for the rapidly devel-
oping urban areas around Abidjan.
The idea of teaching by radio came
first to mind because Unesco and
many of its member states have used
it very effectively in the past and it is
one of the most popular current
methods for covering wide areas with
a minimum of teachers. It has the
disadvantage that it doesn't make the
same impact that visual teaching does
and it always has to be backed up by
a trained instructor in the classroom
and so for a long time the notion of
trying out television instead has been
gathering momentum.
The Ivory Coast seemed the perfect
situation to test it because with TV,
the classroom monitors need almost
no training in that they can take their
cues from the televised instructor and
the teacher-training element is largely
eliminated.
When that decision had been agreed
jupon, a few other problems began tocroup up. Numb r one : how do you
operate a TV set in a village that
doesn't have electricity ? ! n some
cases batteries seemed the best solu-
tion, but in others, in the desert lands
of the north, solar power seemed
better. So suddenly, some villages that
had never had any electrical power
were getting it, not by old-fashioned
twentieth-century methods, but by
technology which will not be used in
even the most advanced countries for
many years to corne.
While ail these strictly technical
angles were being seen to, a curricu-
lum of programmes and work materials
was being prepared with the help of
Unesco experts. Ultimately, one tele-
vision teacher would be doing the work
of many hundreds, and each lesson
could be prepared with far greater care
than any dozen regular teachers would
have time for.
If ail goes weil, ail first grade
students in the Ivory Coast will be
taught by television and each year a
curriculum will be prepared for the
next higher grade, so children starting
now will probably receive their entire
public schooling by television.
Again, since this is a Unesco project,
if it can be made to work successfully,
the techniques will be established for
other countries which want to follow
suit.
But Unesco's interests certainly do
not stop with public school. Where
traditional teaching methods are used,
the quality of secondary school grad-
uates directly influences the quality
of future teaching in public schools.
It is impossible to improve one part of
an educational system without con-
sidering and improving the whole.
One of Unesco's projects which has
now become history had to do with
teaching science after the Second
World War. The need for trained
scientists amounted to a serious crisis
in world development and the schools
and labs needed to train them lay in
ruins across Europe.
A group of brilliant and imaginative
Unesco experts devised a source book
for teaching science using the simplest
possible equipment... a lemon rolled
to squeeze out juice for conducting
electricity ; a fork, needle and glass of
water to test surface tension ; a cork,
a bulb and five nails to make a primi-
tive flashlight. There are even a ruler,
protractor and set-square printed on
the last page of the book which can be
traced and reproduced by students in
cardboard. Many of today's top-flight
scientists made a beginning with these
simple experiments.
Now, the book, reworked, brought
up-to-date and translated into more
than 20 languages, is more popular
than ever as a text in developing coun-
tries where sophisticated labs are yet
to be built. At least the aftermath of
war in one instance had a beneficial
effect on education, but it is the gla-
ring exception when any single good
thing cornes of war.
More characteristica ! ! y, war is the
destroyer of schools and a ! ! permanent
centres of learning and culture. It
leaves the children who survive it
starving, psychologically scarred and
almost totally cut off from any chance
to develop themselves into productive
members of their society.
Hundreds of thousands of Pales-
tinian refugees, spread across Jordan,
Lebanon, Syria and Gaza, were suffer-
ing these torments when, in 1950,
Unesco and the United Nations Relief
and Works Agency undertook to set
up some temporary kind of education
for them. At first the schools and
teaching methods were very makeshift,
but as the years passed, proper
schools were built and enrolment went
up to about a quarter of a million
students, in both primary school and
in three years of high school.
Neither Unesco nor UNRWA realized
what a gigantic project they were
undertaking, and even now, it survives
from year to year, depending on the
voluntary gifts of governments and
private organizations, and with the help
of the educational systems already
established where the refugees found
themselves.
A
As yo, oao'mag'o., 10'""
these schools involves some touehy
diplomatie manoeuvering. After the
Israeli-Arab war of 1967, many sehools
were again c ! osed because of war
damage, and refugees were again
moved. Wherever they went, schools
were pasted together again, some-
times in tents, sometimes in the open
air, and even in the midst of chaos, the
learning process was kept alive.
Also, some local texbooks were
considered in certain quarters to have
highly charged ideological content,
and so Unesco experts were called
upon to develop"neutral"Arabie
teaching materials.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
As another result of the war in
1967, students in Gaza could not take
their secondary school leaving exami-
nations. Not only was their path to
university effectively blocked, but they
had no way to finalize the years of
study they had a ! ready done.
! n a very courageous series of diplo-
matic manoeuvres, Unesco arranged
to have the exams, set in Cairo, flown
into the Gaza strip by way of Cyprus.
The exams were then administered by
Unesco people, flown back to Cyprus
and on to Cairo to be marked. Finally,
the grades were returned and the first
year that this tactic was used, a thous-
and students were allowed to cross
the Suez canal, under the supervision
of the International Committee of the
Red Cross, to continue their studies at
the universities of Egypt.
Had there been no international
organization such as Unesco in exis-
tence, there would have been no
channel for ail the complicated nego-
tiations and these students would, in
ail likelihood, still be stalled with no
diploma and no hope of getting one.
A NOTHER thomy pcoblem
that Unesco has been facing is figuring
out just what a diploma is worth. Does
a diploma earned at the University of
Moscow mean the same as a licence
earned at the Sorbonne, for example ?
The question seems purely academic
unless you happen to be a student
with a B. A. in one country trying to
get your credentials translated into
different terms before you can con-
tinue your studies abroad.
tn this area, Unesco is still at the
stage of collecting data and assem-
bling position papers, but as part of
its year-to-year programme, it pub-
lishes two very helpful books, called
"Study Abroad"and"Vacation Study
Abroad"to help make it easier for
young people to broaden the range of
their studies and move freely within
the international world of learning.
Not only do these books list courses
of study, but they also give all-
important information about scholar-
ships. It is thanks to one of these well-
thumbed volumes that many an enter-
prising young person has been able,
not on ! y to study abroad, but to have
most of his way paid for the experi-
ence as we ! !.
As a further step toward inter-
national education, Unesco is studying
the possibility of setting up an Inter-
national University, at the request of
the United Nations itself. Such a
futuristic undertaking is still a dream
which is yet to come true, but as a
concrete step toward transcending
political boundaries in the pursuit of
learning, Unesco arranges for co-op-
eration between established universi-
ties and technical schools and their
newborn counterparts thousands of
miles apart.
Sometimes, to create a flow of infor-
mation into a country which might
suddenly need a supply of trained
technicians or educational leaders, for
example, it gives its own scholarships
for qualified people to study abroad.
! n other cases, it gives money to artists
who have gained a certain reputation
at home to go abroad to learn new
techniques or, by osmosis, enrich the
fabric of life from which they create.
) n many cases, these scholarships
go beyond basic training and involve
renewing or enriching the knowledge
that people, some of them no longer
young, already have.
Aside from its interests in ai ! stages
of forma ! éducation, Unesco has come
to realize that when you finally have
your degree in your hand, no matter
what level it may be, you are not
necessarily.. educated"... period. The
fund of information about any subject
grows by leaps and bounds, some-
times in a matter of months, so how
can you say that even though you
earned a diploma five years ago, you
still know your subject ?
EDUCATION,"Uoe'co
has corne to use the term, no longer
refers to a period in one's youth spent
outside society absorbing facts, but a
continuous process which starts with
being born and ends, ideally, with
death. This new concept of"conti-
nuing education"sounds a ! i very weil
on paper and Unesco's work in educ-
ational planning is being done with it in
mind as an organizing principle ; but
when you ask specifically how far
anyone has gone in applying it, you
learn that only the barest beginnings
have been made.
And"continuing education"sirnply
can't be put off any longer. Every one
of us has known someone who man-
aged to achieve an education in this
wider sense and we have to respect
his brightness and modernity of think-
ing, but the way knowledge is explod-
ing, the chances that people will be
able to do the same thing for them-
selves in the future become slimmer
and slimmer.
One thing everyone agrees upon is
that present educational systems
everywhere will have to become much
more flexible and open-ended and that
each individual is going to have to
learn to admit when his education
has stopped working for him and
doesn't apply to the world as he finds
it ; in other words, the systems of
learning will have to keep up with the
exciting, fast-moving world they are
concerned with and the individual will
have to keep up with them.
1 T took"',"v. ca' geo. c-
ations before man's schools caught
up with Galileo's idea that the earth
rotated around the sun ; no one can
afford to move that slowly any more.
h a probability a thirty-year-old today
was never taught about the DNA
molecule, a crucial breakthrough in
twentieth century science, so unless a
whole generation is sent back to their
books or somehow re-informed, they
will find themselves at forty-five about
as far behind in understanding as if
they still believed the earth was the
centre of the solar system.
The very heart of education should
be change and regeneration both in
what man knows and how he thinks ;
too often in the past it has been an
instrument of stultification and dogma,
and will continue to be until govern-
ments and each one of us realizes
that, in spite of ah the educationai
statistics and diplomas in the world,
there can be no such th'ng as an"edu-
cated man", only a man"becoming
educated".
A full system of education based on
that understanding and taking in an
entire population has yet to be achiev-
ed by any nation, delleloping or"dev-
eloped", but that is the ultimate goal
which Unesco holds up for itself and
for ait its member states. As a goal
it is both an ideal and a necessity four 25
the near future-our lives must be
our education and our education must
be our lifte. 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
4-YOUTH
The mind
bright
and strong
ON the f ; fteenth of May.
1968, yet another conference to
plan the programme for the next
two years was going on at Unesco
headquarters, against the background
of the great wnite womanly Henry
Moore sculpture, the Miro tles and
the beautifully manicured lawns.
Perhaps the most unsettling thing
about the place was an enigmatic
Picasso, which gave the suggestion of
a wild and embarrassing private
laughter. Otherwise, a ! i went as usual,
but there was a new feeling in the air.
These were the days of the famous
"événements", the student strikes, in
France.
There were rumours that the
meetings would be picketed by youth-
fu ! demonstrators, the city was on the
verge of being paralysed by strikes
and, as it turned out, a whole new
segment of history was beginning-a
chain reaction of demonstrations, con-
frontations, conflicts and uneasy
ententes between angry young people
and"establishments"throughout the/Q worid.
This wave of action went beyond
individual countries and regimes, the
youth of the world were speaking
out-some against elements of their
society, some against the protesters.
And where violence could be avoided,
they proved to be articulate indeed.
As people who worked at Unesco
looked out from their offices while
the turbulence swept past them, as
they sat up ai ! night at the public
meetings or took part in street-corner
debates, a great deal of soul-searching
was going on. Unesco had had, right
from the beginning, a department of
youth, concerned with the rôle of
young people in redeveloping a
burned-out Europe.
On top of that, most of Unesco's
activities had to do with young people,
but with the exception of a few
isolated individuals within the org-
anization, the explosions came as a
complete surprise. At least, Unesco
people had the consolation that they
were no more shocked than anyone
else by the outbreaks throughout the
world, but somewhere there lurked
the suspicion that they should have
been able to predict such a phe-
nomenon.
Up to that point, Unesco's activities
had dealt with young people who
were, in the vernacu ! ar, very"straight".
These were the young men and
women who eagerly joined Unesco
clubs in developing countries, who
participated in its world-wide pro-
gramme for physical fitness, and who
promised to be the bright young
leaders of tomorrow. Their social
commitment was of a traditional sort
which could find expression through
conventional channels, but by the
early 1960s, even their participation
had become more and more per-
functory.
Because it was so closely tied in
with governments and because it was
part of a United Nations system
which was no longer looked upon as
a radical experiment in peace-keeping,
Unesco was getting the image of
being stuck with youth as part of its
job, but not really involved with their
prcNems and interests. It seemed the
last place for young people to go
with their opinions for change. With
the General Conference of 1968, an
a ! !-out effort was begun to change
that thinking.
There were some goverments which
deeply opposed the idea of young
people having a voice in an interna-
ma
e
d
û.- ; :
?.
É"oJ
cj
Cri ;"1 : >1 : >
a
'"
< ;"
( ;)
IQJ
o
Õ. < :;a.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
tional organization. They had been
willing to admit that young people
should be educated but were not so
happy when it became time for
students to start expressing what they
thought. Already, education was
having its effect on the world com-
munity, whether the men and women in
authority liked it or not.
Despite such opposition, Unesco
was in the moral position of a teacher
who with the highest motives stim-
ulates his students, encouraging and
rewardinp their ability to think for
themselves, and who suddenly finds
that he is more deeply involved in
their lives than he suspected. Tu eut
off dialogue and deny their right to
develop their opinions when things get
dangerous, is a denial of a ! ! that he
has done with them and of ah that
he stands for.
Unesco had always talked about
and relied upon the idealism of young
people and their capacity for change,
but slowly the realization was be-
ginning to dawn that young people
now grow up faster than those
of previous generations, and that there
is in them, not only a strong moral
sense, but also a scepticism and
Throughout the world Unesco Clubs have proved to be one
of the most effective means for promoting the ideas and
idéals of Unesco amongst young people. Unesco clubs now
number 1, 500 in 50 countries. Young people in Japan (above)
have formed over 400 such clubs, a total surpassed only by
France which has nearly 450. ! n Spain, Friends of Unesco
Clubs exist in several major cities. They arrange lectures,
plays, concerts and exhibitions and provide a forum for
discussions on local, national and international problems.
Through Unesco Gift Coupons, people in many countries have
participated directly in the work of Unesco, by providing
school or scientific equipment, books and supplies to projects
in Asia, Africa, the Middle East and Latin America. Donor
groups buy Gift Coupons and mail them directly to the
project of their choice, and in this way more than $2. 5 million
have gone to help literacy and adult education projects,
schools, libraries and muséums in developing countries.
practicality which refuses to be put
off or to be patronized.
To have any usefulness at ai !,
Unesco could no longer work"for"
youth like some cultivated, rich uncle.
Young people can speak and work for
themselves, and Unesco's new rôle is
to make sure that they have a chance
to do so ; in many cases, this means
acting as a mediator between society
and its youth.
At first. the panic that youth
managed to set up within established
governments when they accused them
of violence, corruption and a basis
in hate, amounted to near hysteria.
Youth was seen as a problem for
society and a threat to its very
existence. Now that the first waves
of shock have passed, these same
governments are in a position where
they can see, without being unneces-
sarily threatened, that young people
can tell them a lot and inject a ! ittie
life and efficiency into their more
shopworn institutions if they are given 27
haif a chancie.
Once again, Unesco is in the posi-
tion of suggesting to its one hundred
CONTINUED NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
THE MIND BRIGHT AND STRONG (continuel)
and twenty-five government masters
(with varying amounts of success) that
youth must be listened to, and more
important, that they must be able to
participate in a real way in making
policy and sharing genuine responsi-
bility within the social structure.
There is perhaps no more degrad-
ing and infuriating position for a young
person to find himself in than that of
being a"token"youth, going through
the motions of being on a commission
or having an impressive-sounding job,
when in reality he has no influence,
and is just filling a post to make his
society"look good".
Unesco and the entire United Nations
system found out the dangers of
putting young people in a"lets pre-
tend"mock-up of a real institution at
the World Youth Assembly, at United
Nations headquarters in New York.
As part of the twenty-fifth anniversary
celebration in the summer of 1970,
this was to be a United Nations Assem-
bly of young people (some of whom
turned out to be not so young) going
through the ritual of peaceful nego-
tiations.
Headlines about it splashed across
the newspapers of the world."World
Youth Assembly : Parroting of Eider'
Slogans in Familiar Disputes Obs-
cures Agreement on War"."Youth As-
sembly Clashes Over Move to Oust
Delegates"."UN Youth Drone on like
Statesmen"."UN Youth Assembly
Comes to Tumultuous Ending".
It finished in frustration and embarr-
assment for a ! !. Most people came
away with the disheartening suspicion
that the"new generation"was going
to keep making the same stupid mis-
takes as the last and that, from this
sample at least, they had less tolerance
and goodwill than their etders. What
good suggestions might have been
made by the delegates got lost in the
dramatic press coverage, but then,
since there were no plans for a con-
crete follow-up to the conference, they
would have been wasted anyway.
One striking fact of modern society
throughout the world is that there
is almost no way in which an estab-
lished government or institution can
find out what its young people are
really thinking. Any such attempt is
bound to be hit-and-miss at best.
Often, when confronted with officiai
surveys or questionings, young people,
like everybody else, are forced into
polemics. Or else, when a youth
organization gathers a sampling of
opinion, it is often one-sided and
refers almost solely to specific local
issues which are of little relevance
28 outside a limited areaThugs Unesco, with the somewhat
apprehensive but expectant approval
of its member governments, is under-
taking the job of finding out what young
people are thinking, not just in this
country or that, but beyond the arbi-
trary divisions of political units.
Maybe there is a world movement
in thought toward pacifism, toward un-
derstanding, toward honesty and open-
ness in young people, but until Unesco
can build a storehouse of data about
youth and get a valid flow of opinion
between young people and ail thé
world's establishments, nobody wi ! !
know for sure. And even then, the
pile of facts and attitudes will take
some very wise and clear-headed
interpretation.
M EANWHILE, Une"o', pco-
gramme involves a lot of talkil'lg and
listening but that is just what there
hasn't been enough of up to now-
young people hammering out their
positions at youth conferences, young
people in the Secretariat making them-
selves heard on matters of policy and
administration, youth organizations
working on studies for Unesco. Every
aspect of Unesco's programme is
somehow implicated, from education to
ecology research, to the phenomenon
of a self-sustaining"youth"culture.
The goal of the programme, however,
is to get some action, and Unesco has
made a modest beginning by having
young people come to work in the
Secretariat as summer interns, by re-
cruiting and training others for more
permanent jobs at headquarters and
in the field, by strongly suggesting that
each country include at least one young
person on its commission to Unesco's
General Conference. Naturally, the
number of individuals involved is quite
small, and some governments simply
don't buy the idea at ais, so there are
fewer people involved than there
should be.
On the other hand, some member
states have decided to go one step fur-
ther and take advantage of Unesco
experts in approaching their own
young people. Several countries, for
example, have asked for help in
arriving at national youth policies. If
such policies function as they are
meant to, they will involve youth di-
rectly with the government and give
them a chance to contribute to the
development of their society.
Only too often the talents of young
people are wasted to their countries
because what they studied has no rele-
vance to their society. At the outset of
their otherwise productive lives they
find themselves without jobs. That
bleak, soul-destroying reality is what
is behind a ! ! thé neat, precise statis-
tics concerning"trained, unemployed
youth"in many countries, both dev-
eloping and developed. They are the.. casualties"which come about from
the lack of national or regional educa-
tional planning.
Even if you get a job after your
training, often a lot of time has
been wasted by following outmo< : led or
irrelevant courses of study. Instead of
leaving the planning of curricula, and
university and school policy solely to
grey-haired administrators, it has for
many years been Unesco's contention
that young people should have a say
in what they study.
Again, in this instance, Unesco can
make suggestions, point out the advan-
tages to individual institutions and
share the knowledge of what other
young people have contributed toward
planning their studies, but ultimately
the decision rests with the particular
university or high-school, and with the
initiatives that students are wi !) ing to
take on their own.
Up to now we have been referring
to"youth"as being almost syn-
onymous with"student", as indeed il.
is in the minds of most people ; sup-
posedly. youth" are the young people
who are in a position to organize them-
selves and be viewed as the synthetic
entity that is talked about in the press
and in social analysis.
But what about the large number of
students who shun any form of org-
anized statement and keep their asso-
ciations as open and flexible as pos-
sible ? What about the young man with
almost no schooling wandering the
streets of a city, alone and without
any hope of work ? What about the
secretaries, the young office and
factory workers ? How do you reach
them and put them into your overall
picture of youth ?
Even more problematic, is reaching
the millions of rural youth, who while
they may be still in their early teens,
have never known anything but work
on one plot of land and are, for ail
intents and purposes, as aged as the
land itself. These people, too, are
"youth"a ! though they wouldn't recog-
nize themselves as part of their own
generations ; if Unesco could reach
them, especially, and could act as a
channel for them to express their needs
in education and in their work, they
might eventually come to share some
of the pleasures of being young.
There are a few youth organizations
concerned with young blue-collar wor-
kers and with whom Unesco can work,
but otherwise, except for a few per-
sonal contacts, aN these masses of
young people are virtually out of the
reach of Unesco's efforts.
There are, however, the radical
young who want to be heard in an
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
international forum, the ad hoc groups
who are straining to make their griev-
ances and their angers heard. They
are far beyond the governmental
channels through which Unesco op-
erates and, naturally, the prospect of
an international radical conference
makes member states very, very
uneasy. They expect the delegates
to rip the place apart, but probably
the officia) fears are too extreme.
! n reaiity. this could just be the
chance radical spokesmen were ail
looking for to say what they had to
say in perspective, and in the context
of other young people who had diffi-
culties of their own which might make
any personal gripes look unbelievably
smalt. Anyway, out of it ail would
come a very sharp-edged sense of
what was genuinely unjust and unfair,
and what, in the human state of
civilized compromise, was intolerable.
M
No matt., fo, whom, the
voiceless, disenfranchised youth of
the world or the articulate, well-
informed sceptics of society, Unesco
could offer a latitude of expression
they could get nowhere else in the
world. It is admittedly not an easy
task, nor a raine that Unesco is totally
relaxed in dealing with, but youth is
becoming constantly a larger percent-
age of the world's population and a
larger force to be reckoned with, so
Unesco maybe can become its spokes-
man and, if necessary, its officiai
support in a push for human and
spiritual rights.
Maybe. Unesco can never become
a fast-paced espouser of causes, but
its ability to be of use to the young
people of the world is yet to be
tested. Perhaps its governmental res-
ponsibilities will prove too confining,
perhaps they can be got round.
m the case of bringing exams to the
refugees of the Gaza strip, the per-
sonal considerations won out ; in this
extreme instance, diplomacy and per-
sonal goodwill broke through ah the
red-tape and ugliness of war in favour
of a handful of young people.
Hopefully, where youth in general
is concerned, Unesco will have the
same good results ; in effect, it is doing
a juggling act which up to now isn't
fully appreciated either by govern-
ments (some of whom accuse Unesco
of butting in) or by the young them-
selves.
A thankless task ? Perhaps, but as
one member of the Secretariat puts it,
"if we don't try to put a word in for
youth on an international scale, then
show me somebody else in this
messed-up world who wi ! !"t
INTERNATIONAL AWARD FOR FAIR PLAY
The Pierre Coubertin International Fair Play Trophy is awarded by Unesco's Director-
General each year to foster the spirit of fair play in sports. The trophy has been
won, since 1964 when the prize was inaugurated, byan Italian bobsleigh champion,
an American woman athlete (pictured above), a Yugoslav wrestler, a Spanish
footballer, a Spanish basketball player and a Polish cyclist. Football teams from
England, the Fed. Rep. of Germany, France and Japan, and the Swiss Juniors Golf
Team have a)) been honoured as have a French football trainer, a Hungarian referee,
a Swedish table tennis player, two American yachtsmen, a Polish skier and a Tuni-
sian basketball veteran. Other prizes awarded by Unesco or under Unesco auspices
include the Kalinga Prize for the popularization of science (awarded since 1952) ;
the Unesco Science Prize (awarded since 1968) for outstanding contributions to
technotogicai development ; Iran's Mohamed Reza Pahlavi Prize for the promotion 29
of adult literacy (first awarded in 1967) ; the Nadezhda K. Krupskaya Prize, testa-
blished by the U. S. S. R. in 1969 to help promote Unesco's literacy programme ;
and the Unesco Prize for Architecture (awarded since 1969 to the winner of an
international competition for architecture students).
Y-'"
(U ;
Zt
>-
o
Õ. s ;Q-
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Photo John Zimmerman @ Ufe Magazine, New York
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
5-SCIENCE
The
inquisitive mind
The happy faces of these youngsters
working on a home teletype terminal
connected to a central computer
suggest that science is child"s play
to modern youth. Hundreds of thou-
sands of youp9 people through-
out the world belong to leisure
time science clubs and Unesco has
encouraged the growth of these
clubs. Unesco has done pioneer
work in developin9 new approaches,
materials, methods and techniques
for teaching science through four
major pilot projects in Latin America,
Asia, Africa and the Arab States.
Under these projects groups of key
individuals were brought together
for periods of one year to re-think
the whole approach to teaching
various scientific subjects-Physics
in Sao Paulo (Brazil), Chemistry in
Bangkok (Thailand), Biology in Cape
Coast (Ghana), and Mathematics in
Cairo (UAR). Unesco's Source Book
for Science Teaching, first published
in 1957, which describes many scien-
tific experiments that can be carried
out with easily available materials,
has become a year in year out best
seller that has appeared in 28 lan-
guages. The explosion of scientific
knowledge has led Unesco to pro-
pose the establishment of a world
pool of scientific information that
will be instantly available to scien-
tists everywhere. Known as the
Unisist project, it involves working
out methods of standardizing com-
puter Systems, iinking existing infor-
mation networks and setting up
new information systems in coun-
tries now without them.
MODERN"'. nu. is a uni-
verse of its own,, xpanding at a rate
many times greater than population
size or economic growth. Research
and development has now become a
huge enterprise, consuming over 50, 000
million dollars world-wide annually and
employing over two million scientists
and engineers. These already astro-
nomical figures are likely to double in
the next five to ten years.
Countries rich in scientists and
technologists are"developed"and
their wealth grows as fast as these
men's imaginations can create new
ideas. Without scientists, no country
can properly be said even to be
"developing"in this twentieth century ;
so the world is divided, as some say,
into"have-science"and"have-not-
science"nations, the former getting
rucher and richer and the latter getting
farther and farther behind.
No wonder then that policy-making
has become so important in the effort
to bring some order to this situation.
The scientific establishment can no
longer ignore the fact that science has
been thrown into the arena of public
debate.
Unesco has undertaken to interest
developing countries in instituting poli-
cies for the organization of their own
scientific enterprise and for the devel-
opment of their own technological
capability. This means seeking ans-
wers to questions such as : should a
country rely on its own research and
development, such as it is, or should
it import technology ? Should it train
its researchers on the spot or should
it send them abroad, with the risk that
they may be destined to become part
of the brain drain ?
A country must first of ai ! ask the
most fundamental of questions : what
resources are available for carrying
out its own research and development ?
Ait these questions can be answered
provided the country has policy-
making organs to carry out the neces-
sary fact-finding surveys and analyses
and then take appropriate decisions.
By providing assistance in setting
up such organs and sending con-
sultants to advise them in critical
decision-making, Unesco has helped
countries of the Third World to
decide what science, and how much
of it, was good for them.
tn the basic matter of training scien-
tists, Unesco's work overlaps its
general work in education and in each
case the same ground-rules apply. As
a matter of survival, science teaching
must be as advanced and excellent as
possible. Where a country must start
from scratch, Unesco attempts to lay
the groundwork ; when science teach-
ing is already under way, Unesco can
supply the research and experts to im-
prove it and bring it up to date.
Although at first thought, it would
seem that you could graft a scien-
tific habit of mind onto an individual
from any culture, in actual fact, scien-
tific of technical education only
"takes"when it is treated as part of
the whole personality.
As an extreme case in point, in
many African countries, the only
high school bio ! ogy texts formerly
available were those which described
the flora and fauna of the European
country where it was originally pré-31
pared ; thus, many trained bioiogists Jt
might learn a great deal about English
hedgerows, for instance, instead of
CONTINUED NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
THE INQUISITIVE MIND (Continued)
about their own surroundings. The
absurdity of the situation is apparent,
but it took Unesco to finance the
costly, and time-consuming project of
creating a truly African course of
study in biology.
Similarly, in the training of engi-
neers, with the use of pilot projects
in different parts of the wor ! d, an
attempt has been made to train men
whose ski Ils will be precisely relevant
to the needs of their own industries
and their own societies ; machines,
buildings, modes of transportation
vary, and so should the educational
experiences that prepare men for
planning, building and maintaining
them.
Unesco is in the process of dis-
covering what countries have common
economic and physical conditions in
an attempt to share the information
that each one has arrived at by trial
and error, and save its corresponding
nation, which may be on the other
side of the world, from going through
the same slow process.
wW HEN you f ; n, Jly do become
a scientist or an engineer, the problem
of keeping up with new developments
is monumental. This is a field where
things are happening so fast, that
unless you do keep up, you not only
are out of date in your information, but
for a ! ! intente and purposes, you cease
to be a member of your profession. A
scientist in 1970 who is still using the
knowledge he had in 1965 and nothing
else might as weil be an alchemist
trying to change lead to gord by
muttering a magic chant over it.
Till the 1950s an individual could
stay abreast of his field if he read
every article as it came out and spent
aN his waking time on his"permanent
education". Today, however, in the
natural sciences alone, close to three
million articles are published in the
world per year, not to mention the
scientific books and pamphlets which
seem to appear by the library-full.
To take in even a tiny, specialized
area of ail this, the mind would simply
burst, and the world would be full of
"mad scientists"indeed.
Just as the computer has made pos-
32 sible ail this humanly-impossibleresearch and documentation, so only
the computer can manage to keep pace
with it. How much of this scientific
output is repetition of the same ex-
periments and what general trends
emerge from the great bulk, only a
computer can tell. Unesco can compile
bibliographies of some of the works
being published, but that is only an
organized list of titles. The content
of it ail is what really matters.
How much more straightforward the
problem would be if only ail the com-
puters of the world spoke the same
language, and the information could
be pooled and made available as soon
as it was arrived at. If only consistent
terms of reference, of measurement
could be agreed upon, if only com-
puter systems themselves could be
standardized.
To this end, Unesco has under-
taken to create Unisist, a World Scien-
ce Information System. It is still in
the planning stages, but it promises
to revolutionize past thinking about
the nature of scientific knowledge
itself. No country or group of scien-
tists will be obliged to become part
of it but, hopefully, as its fund of
information and analyses increases to
vast proportions, no individual interest-
ed in scientific enquiry will be able to
resist using it.
Of course, at first the new kind of
sharing that Unisist requires, both of
individual scientists and nations, will
take some getting used to. Private
discoveries will less and less be con-
sidered as private property for exploi-
tation and gain, but as part of the
world's storehouse for mutual benefit.
International co-operation of this
kind, Unesco has proved, actually can
work. Although the task of exploring
space has been carried out by indivi-
dual nations with their own budget and
programmes, man has begun to
explore his other great unfathomable
frontier, the ocean, in a concerted
international effort put together bY
Unesco.
For starters, they tackled the Indian
Ocean for six years. Ships and
scientists from 25 nations criss-
crossed its waters taking samples,
sounding the bottom in order to map
its cold, black reaches, exploring its
currents, recording its plant and ani-
ma life. The ships and equipment
varied from sophisticated gadgets on
floating labs, to bottles tossed over the
sides of fishing boats... and the infor-
mation poured in from a ! ! quarters.
It brought with it some interesting
surprises ; for one thing, scientists had
long believed that there was a strong
fast current racing northward along
the east coast of Africa, which they
named the Somali current, but it had
never been charted nor its speed mea-
sured before this expedition. And
indeed the current did exist, but what
came as a bit of a shock was dis-
covering that, unlike any other, it disap-
pears for ha ! f thé year ; when the
south-west monsoons are blowing, it
sweeps northward almost twice as fast
as the Gulf Stream, but when the
monsoon ends and the prevailing wind
direction reverses, it becomes a gentle
southerly drift.
! n effect, the scientists found that
with the monsoon winds they had
the use of a gigantic natural fan which
switched on and off. Instead of having
to theorize about what winds over
the ocean's surface did to the
current, for the first time they
could actually measure their effect, as
if the whole expanse of water were
one vast laboratory.
o NE othe, thiog they wanted
to figure out was why the Indian
Ocean doesn't seem to produce its
fair share of fish compared to other
oceans. The irony is that around it
are the world's most densely populated
countries where the need for fish
protein is most desperate. Yet, for
some reason not yet explained, the
explorers discovered that there are
layers of water in the Indian Ocean
which have very little oxygen content
and when they rise to the surface, the
plant and animal life is suffocated.
They did find one great upwelling
of water, however, which was teem-
ing with sea life, but it takes the most
modern trawling equipment to harvest
its wealth. Here is the food, tan-
talizingly close, but out of the reach
of those who need it and available
only to nations rich enough to scoop
it up for themselves.
To whom does the wealth of the
oceans really belong, the minerai de-
posits on its floor and its other untapp-
ed resources ? No satisfactory agree-
ment has yet been reached, but as
further exploration goes on in the
Mediterranean, the South Atlantic and
the Western Pacific, and as oceano-
graphic ships stumble upon great
stockpiles of minera wealth just out
CONTINUED PAGE 36
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
INTERNATIONAL
FLEETS
EXPLORING
THE OCEANS
A physiographic diagram of the Indian Ocean based on soundings made by
the fleet of 40 research vessels of the 25-nation Indian Ocean Expedition
(1959-1965), co-sponsored by Unesco and the International Council of
Scientific Unions. Working through an) ntergovernmenta) Océanographie
Commission which it set up in 1960, Unesco is co-ordinating oceanographic
research for which the participating nations contribute $15 million annu-
ally to explore one of the last unknown frontiers on our planet-the world's
oceans that cover three quarters of its surface. n 1963, 14 ships from 8
countries studied the effect of changes in ocean currents on fish yields in 33
the tropical zone of the Atlantic ; in 1964, 8 ships from 6 countries explo-
red the Gulf of Guinea ; in 1965, 36 ships from 6 countries began a study of
the Kuroshio Current, the western Pacific's equivalent of the Gulf Stream,
again to see how its variations affected weather and fisheries.
(þ 1964, Bruce Heezen and Marie Tharp (Reproduced by permission)
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
THE ARID LANDS
A CHALLENGE TO MAN
tn 1948, Unesco launched an international programme of research into the world's arid zones, which
cover a third of its land surface. Thousands of scientists from some 40 countries collaborated
in studies ranging from underground water research, climatology, solar and wind energy to plant,
human and animal ecology. The International Hydrological Decade. launched by Unesco in 1965, is an
extension to this programme. Photo above shows experiment carried out in Atgeria with Unesco
aid in 1954 on how camels can survive for long spells in the desert without water. Here camel's weight
is checked after beast was deprived of water for eight days. Left, research being ca'rried out on hydro-
ponics-growing crops without any soit. Hère an American pomologist (fruit-tree specialist) tends
rows of apple sprigs growing in sand fed with nutrient solutions. tn the past 25 years Unesco has
sponsored research projects on plant physiology and has also studied the special arid land
problem of saline soils and saline underground water in relation to irrigation, and in 1962 it organized j. J
a study symposium in Tashkent on this question in collaboration with the Academies of Science of
the USSR and Uzbekistan. Above left, section of a vast concrete irrigation canal under construction
in Soviet Central Asia.
Photo @ APN
CD
i 
E
0
. s
E
o
1 
1]
CD
o
c
CD
c>
<
in :
o
Õ
. <:;
"-
Photo &commat; Schmidt-Nielsen
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
THE INQUISITIVE MIND
(Continued (rom page 32)
of reach (as they accidentally did in
the Red Sea), the need to have soma
agreement worked out among the
United Nations becomes more and
more acute.
Though the bounty which nature
holds out sometimes tends to make
individuals greedy and self-seeking,
the violence of nature often brings
them together, whether they like it or
not, in a common effort to survive.
As the crust of the earth shudders and
jars in violent quakes, as wailing hur-
ricanes sweep the landscape clean, it
seems to be flaunting its prodigious
might in the face of man's puny efforts.
Like children we cling together in
helpless panic.
Although such natural disasters
cannot be avoided, with international
co-operation we may someday be able
to predict and prepare for them.
Seismology, a relatively new science,
has gone a long way toward record-
ing and describing the shock waves
of earthquakes after the fact, and
through Unesco, these findings have
been made generally available ; the
next step will be to put it a ! ! together
and try to discover the underlying
patterns of the eruptions in the earth's
crust. That done, man may someday
be able to predict precisely when and
where one is going to hit in time for
people to save themselves.
As an interim measure, the new
branch of seismic research called
earthquake engineering is given to
studying designs and methods of cons-
truction for buildings that will be earth-
quake proof. Hopefully, one day if
you live in an earthquake area you
will be warned to evacuate your home
for a few hours and when the shocks
are over you will come back to a build-
ing still intact, perhaps with a picture
or two off the wall and a few dishes
broken if you haven't had time to
pack them ; what is now certain disas-
ter may in future be just a routine
inconvenience.
Research in any branch of science
has become so complex that now no
single country can afford a ! ! thé pro-
jects that present themselves nor
supply the broad range of specialists
necessary. h nuclear research, for
example, the price of equipment and
QC trained peopie is astronomical, andUnesco long ago s w the need for
international co-operation. The Secre-
tariat thus became instrumental in form-
ing the European Organization for
Nuclear Research, better known as
CERN, whose scope, with Unesco
backing, has grown to the point that it
is now in the process of building
the world's largest particle accelerator
Although projects in the life scien-
ces may seem less monumental, in
effect they are also unbelievably expen-
sive. The task of studying the embryo-
logy of mammals by growing a mouse
in a test-tube takes a new blending of
biology, chemistry, fluid mechanics for
the artificial placenta, electronic
sophistication, etc.
Brain research, cell research-both
demand the wealth of a Croesus, liter-
ally hundreds of researchers and the
painstaking accumulation of minutiae-
identifying a chemical substance, per-
fecting a complicated technique, subt-
iy modifying someone else's theory.
These are indeed tasks for the world.
The goals of modern science may
seem earth-shattering, but if we are
to come close to understanding and
recreating the processes that gave us
our own life, we must act as one
life and one scientific mina..
1""
Ex
>&lt;,, ""
s.
0
o.
Õ. < :;a.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
BULWARKS
AGAINST
DISASTER
Over the years, Unesco's work in the field of science has
included a broad programme on the study and prevention of
natural disasters-earthquakes, tsunamis (seismic sea waves),
floods and volcanic eruptions. Unesco has an international
roster of natural disaster specialists who can be catied upon
to rush to a disaster-stricken area to study an earthquake
or other calamity. Photo left shows world famous volcanolo-
gist Haroun Tazieff studying the Irazu eruption in Costa Rica,
during a Unesco emergency mission in 1964. Up to 1970, over
20 Unesco missions had made on-the-spot studies of earth-
quake-hit areas, including Skoplje (Yugoslavia), Ancash (Peru)
and Dasht-e Bayaz (Iran). Japan is one of the world's most
experienced countries in earthquake engineering, and that is
why Unesco, in collaboration with the U. N. Special Fund, set
up the International Institute of Seismology and Earthquake
Engineering in Tokyo, to provide courses for non-Japanese
trainees from earthquake-prone countries. Photo, below
left, shows the unique"shaking table"or vibration-causing
machine located attheJapanese Government Building Research
Institute in Tokyo and which is regularly used by students from
the International Institute. Unesco also helped to set up the
International Seismological Centre in Edinburgh, Scotland,
which collects and processes data from a world-wide network
of more than 600 observatories. Flood prediction and preven-
tion are two other aspects of Unesco's efforts for protection
against disasters, and these are linked with the Unesco-
sponsored Hydrological Decade. ln this connexion, the mathe-
matical model set up by Unesco (with the aid of a com-
puter) for the development of the Mekong River delta has
been used incidentally for the prediction of floods in Cambodia.
Below, boatman on the Mekong.
: r.,
zonN<tI1
c :: J
! :<tI: r
&commat;
o
Õ. < :;"-
. c
". < :;": J'"
U
1 : >c :o0
E>-'"a :
&commat;
o
Õ. < :;Q-
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
6-ECOLOGY
The mind
extinct ?
u
Nit ! URTUNG through a death-
dealing and hostile environment, we
are ais clinging to the surface of a
great ba ! ! of rock which we calmi earth.
By a series of coincidences not yet
explained, about three thousand mihion
years ago a thin and fragile layer
began to develop around this bail ;
as energy poured into it from the sun,
the conditions necessary for life and
the elaborate processes for sustaining
it were set into motion. Oxygen and
water were created and they in turn
made it possible for plants to survive.
Then animal life first appeared, and as
the masterpiece of its evolution came
man. One system of life was trans-
muted to support the next and ail
worked in an exquisite balance.
This thin miraculously organized
layer, the biosphere, seemed cosy and
inexhaustible until man in ail hais
cleverness found that he had pushed
its resources. No one even now knows
just what happens to it when you set
off an atomic explosion in it, or when
you shoot a rocket vehicle through it
and out into space. No one knows
when its supplies of resources to
sustain life, its water and its oxygen,
will run out and the planet will slowly
die.
What became increasingly obvious
to scientists, long before the discussion
of ecology became popular, was that
man was pushing his luck, draining and
wasting precious resources in a mind-
! ess, suicida ! way. What is particu-
larly obvious to scientists, also, is that
no one country can save the biosphere
by itself. Some are worse polluters,
greater exploiters and disrupters of
nature than others, but ai ! suffer the
consequences.
38 From Unesco's work in oceano-graphe, it is clear that the ocean itself
is in danger of becoming a sewer.
Just to dump a bit of waste into its
depths seems literally like a drop in
a bucket, but who knows where that
bit of pollution may be carried by the
currents and what effect it may have
on the freshness of the sea.
Just drop ever so small an amount
of copper into a pond and see what
happens to the fish in it, or even
worse, add an infinitesimal bit of
organic mercury and, although the fish
and the algae they feed on may sur-
vive, they will concentrate it in their
bodies to such an extent that they will
poison anyone who eats them.
On land, to irrigate a large arid area
may seem like a great step forward
for one particular area, but what is it
going to do to the weather in a neigh-
bouring country ? It seems that for
any easy"progress"within the sys-
tems of the biosphere, somewhere else
a price must be paid.
DDT and other chlorinated hydro-
carbons have become part of the
twentieth century way of life, elimin-
ating the insects that carry malaria and
typhus, killing pests that ruin crops,
and even preserving manufactured tex-
tiles against moths. It is small wonder
then that traces of DDT have been
found as far afield as in the penguins
of Antarctica, to whom it was carried
in plants and fish. It takes no great
sleuth to suspect that the mysterious
disappearance of whole colonies of sea
birds fits into the same pattern of
evidence.
And the pesticides set up, with
man's help, a little eco-system of their
own. ! n one extraordinary case, farm
chickens that had never been allowed
out into the field showed traces of
DDT. Where could it possibly have
corne from ? What had happened was
like some ghoulish nursery rhyme :
the farmers sprayed the farmland
with chemicals ; wind and rain washed
it into the sea ; sea plants picked it
up ; fish ate the plants ; fishermen
caught the fish ; the fish was made
into meal ; the meal was sold to the
farmers, and the full cycle from farm
back to farm was complete, polluting
everything it touched along the way.
Perhaps the most frightening thing
about the whole story is that the pesti-
cide has become part of the cycle of
winds and condensed water, the hydro-
logical cycle. As part of water
droplets, pollution can literally range
anywhere over the globe, and deposit
its deadly self thousands of miles from
where it was taken up. So far the
hydrological cycle is a life-giving one,
but it must be carefully studied and
maintained or we will ail be in dire
trouble.
Unesco has set aside ten years for
the study of hydrology throughout the
world. Just how much available water
is there ? Where is it ? The way it
is being used, how long will the supply
last ? By melting some of the polar
ice caps how much could the supply
be increased without raising the
ocean level ?
Herse HERE"e, eve,,' u",'pped
reservoirs in the world, such as the
upper basin of the Rio Paraguay in
the Mato Grosso of South America ;
the area is called the I ? antanal, from
the Portugese word meaning"marsh-
land", and in ail it is almost the size
of France. ! n a joint project under-
taken by Unesco and the government
of Brazil, it is being explored and its
fresh water wealth measured and
opened for development, not only for
Brazil but ultimately for Bolivia and
Paraguay as tell.
Just one more way of telling a highly
industrialized, developed country from
a developing one is the amount of
water each person in it'consumes.
CONTINUED PAGE 41
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
'Tète Paysage" (Landscape Head) by the Flemish 17th century painter Joost de Momper.
CIl
'i
Il
: E
>. 0
!
. ! ! !
'S
!"
m
. 3c
ëii
no
Il...
Sm
J :
E
E !....
., ;
; :Il
no
"CD
0
"...
ri)c
ß
aUJ
w
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
THE WANTON ARROW
Wantonly used for target practice by an unknown vandal in Austria, this
stork had to forage for food for its young with an arrow through its breast
before it could be captured and the arrow removed by veterinary surgeons.
The conservation of the wortd's wild ! ife and natura) resources has always
been one of Unesco's major preoccupations. n this field it has collaborated
closely with the International Union for the Conservation of Nature and
Natural Resources and the Food and Agriculture Organization. n 1957 a
Unesco mission was sent to the Galapagos Islands to see how this unique
zoological site could be preserved. As a result the Charles Darwin Foun-
dation was established and a biotogicat research station, built with Unesco's
aid, was inaugurated in 1964. n Africa, a Unesco mission headed by Sir
40 Julian Huxley made an on-the-spot investigation in 1960, of the conserva-'U tio  of wild life nd natural resources in Central and East Africa. A Unesco
Regional Centre for Science and Technology, set up in Nairobi, Kenya, is
now helping several African governments solve their conservation problems.
......
j'"
0o
: 1
< (
&commat;
o
Õ'"iE.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
THE MIND EXTINCT"1 (Continued)
For the rich countries, the old phrase
"spending money like water"should
be changed to"spending water like
money."They have been using it as
if the supplies were never going to
run out.
With a ! i of thé earth's riches, men
have to learn to become students and
husbandmen of nature, not its heart-
less master. From satellites, we can
look down on the surface of the earth
and see areas of despoiled vegetation,
areas where the soit has become
salty and in which nothing can grow.
Also, great weather patterns become
clear to the cameras and, in short, the
biosphere is spread out to be examin-
ed. It is now Unesco's job to stimu-
late this examination, to act as a cen-
tre to help countries plan for preserv-
ing the resources with which they have
been blessed.
NOTER a ! m is to find out
what the"danger signs. are when man
has exceeded his limitations and
threatens to upset the balance for
everyone, just as miners used to take
canaries with them when they went
down the pits. Wh en the bird was over-
come by gas it was the man's signal
to save himself. Now when a partic-
ular species becomes threatened or
great natural changes take place, they
may be warnings of a similar kind if
only we knew how to interpret them.
Perhaps Unesco's greatest contribu-
tion to ecology is still many years off ;
it will be in establishing agreements
between nations to protect them from
polluting one another. Governments
will have to face the fact that some
system of international inspection and
contre ! of the environment wi !) be an
absolute necessity for us to survive.
But ait the agreements in the world
will be useless if the basic problem
is not faced squarely. The cause of
a) t thé earth's pollution is man, and
with the population of the world due
to double we) ! before the year 2000,
no matter how many c ! ever so) utions
science can come up with, pollution
will be a fact of life. We will be like
rabbits trapped in a cage with only a
limited supply of food, living in our
own filth, proliferating at a crazy rate
and frenzied in our fight for enough
water and food to keep alive.
The picture is not a pretty one, but
untess population growth is stopped, 41
it is inevitable. It is easy enough to
talk about industrial pollution, chem-
ical poisoning and the waste of
CONTINUED PAGE 43
Photos S) gamma
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
. >&lt;
o
>-
J :en
z
VÙ
N
N
L
V
"
'"
Q ;
. < :;
"
æ
CE'"'S
a :
o
Õ
. < :;
il.
. g
o
Õ
. < :;
d
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
THE MIND EXTINCT 1 (Continued)
resources a that we can blame
on someone else. but in the case of
the population"bomb"we have no
one to blame but ourselves And no
one car* solve the problem but indiv-
idua ! s who have enough concern for
their fellows to have a limited number
of children
m a !) of Unesco's work with ecology
the concept comes up again and
again that more must be supplied to
man by his environment than a ration
of food and a little runway of earth ;
he isn't just a rabbit. His life must
have quality as we ! t. He must have
room to move. a vista, colour, stimu-
lation and affection in his world, other-
wise he is alive only as an animal and
not as the being"man".
! n spite of the work of the world's
scientists, in spite of Unesco, if we
continue to pollute our planet and
overrun it as we are now doing, we
and our children will someday meet
grey morning after grey morning wish-
ing that we had never been bora.'.
Mighty forests of cedars once covered
about half a million hectares of the
Lebanon. The Phoenicians and succeed-
ing civilizations stripped the forests
to make galleys for their navies until
only four small groves of cedars remain-
ed. Under the Lebanese government's
"Green Plan", a vast programme of
reforestation has been undertaken.
Along the Lebanon range young cedar
and pine trees are hein9 planted in
terraces carved from the rocky hillsides,
like those (lest) above the limestone
cliffs of the valley of the Abou Ali river.
Unesco has played a key role in alertin9
world opinion to the importance of
conserving natural resources. n Sep-
tember 1968, Unesco, in co-operation
with the UN, FAO, WHO, the Interna-
tional Biological Programme and the
International Union for the Conser-
vation of Nature and Natural Resources,
convened the first world conference
on the rational use and conservation
of the natural resources of the bio-
sphere. As a result Unesco has been
lapping out a long-term international
programme I) n"Man and the Bio-
sphere"to deal with the scientific,
technisa), educational and instutitional
problems of the rational use of natural
resources and the improvement of the
environment.
N THE MINOIS OF MEN
ln the Minds of Men"is the title of a book commem-
orating the 25th anniversary of Unesco. The book
contains a study on Unesco by the Director-General,
René Maheu, as weil as 14 essays by distinguished figu-
res in the world of education, culture and science, who
have been closely associated with Unesco's work. We
present below brief extracts from some of these texts.
TOWARDS AN AGE OF DIALOGUE
Attempts at international communica-
tion often fail. People have been
known to come away from them frustrat-
ed, and even in a cynical mood. And
when these endeavours don't fail, they
still require, usually, more energy and
patience than communication within the
confines of a single country. Why,
then, does the ideal of international
intellectual communication, for ail thé
resistance and hostility it generates,
also exercise the extraordinary appeal
that it does ?
Obviously, it represents to many men
a hope for peace. Or course, success-
fu ! internationa ! communication is not
a guarantee of peace. The nations of
western Europe communicated freely
and openly with one another for many
years during which they also fought
suicidas wars. Nevertheless, if the
experience of the past is a guide,
among the contributing causes of war
are national stereotypes, the de-per-
sonalization of people on the other side
of the border, the misinterpretation of
their intentions and even their simplest
statements, and the incapacity to com-
prehend that reasonable men can see
the world very differently when they
look at it against the background of
an historical experience different from
one's own. Peace cannot be won by
better communication alone, but surely
such communication can reduce the
influence of factors which have made
the road to war an easier one for
people to take.
CHARLES FRANKEL
Professer of Philosophe,
Columbia University, New York
THE UNITY AND PLURALITY OF ASIA
Asia is big, embracing at the start
of Unesco over one billion people who
today have grown to two billion. Asia
is a plurality, containing peoples and
nations bound by socialist, market and
mixed economy ideologies, and adher-
ing to the great, historic religions of
Buddhism, Hinduism, Islam and Chris-
tianity. Asia is a unit y in its cultural
values and in its fight against poverty
and destitution. Unesco has had to
come to terms with these three basic
characteristics of Asia-its bigness, its
plurality and its unity.
MALCOLM S. ADISESHIAH
Former Deputy Director-General of Unesco
DIRECT PARTICIPATION
Unesco is not an academy of learn-
ing, nor a scientific laboratory, nor a
forum for theories and speculation. It
is an organization for action, for co-
operation and international aid in scien-
ce, education and culture, and it has
drawn up and launched a clearly-defined
global programme to which its member
countries have freely given their con-
sent. The member states did not create
Unesco merely to remain as onlookers,
but to participate directly in this action.
ATILIO DELL'ORO MAINI
Président of the Unesco
General Conférence (1970)
THE EDUCATION EXPLOSION
The"education explosion"of the last
25 years is now to be matched by the
requirements of quality, and educa-
tional systems everywhere need renewal
and transformation ; the new vistas
opened up by the emerging concept of
lifelong education point to radical chan-
ges in a ! ! societies, innovating fram
their own conditions and realities
toward the paths chosen by themselves.
! n this process of development in the
1970s, the catalytic role of Unesco in
bringing about innovations and its pro-
motional role for regional and interna-
tional co-operation could provide new
dimensions.
PREM KIRPAL
President of the Unesco Executive Board
EDUCATION, A RIGHT FOR ALL
Though not a world Ministry of Edu-
cation, Unesco has been able per-
sistently to emphasise the concept of
"Non-discrimination"in education, an
idea that has an unassailable moral
force behind it... It has ceaselessly
insisted that whatever rights are reali-
zable must be realized as much for
people with dark skins as with light,
as much for girls and women as for
boys and men, as much for persons
of one religion as for persons of
another.
LIONEL ELVIN
Director of the Instltute of Education,
University of London, and former head of the
Unesco Dept of Education
THE SEED OF INTERNATIONALISM
We are convinced that a world,
where literacy is becoming universal,
culture more internationalized and
science not a privilege of a number of
universities in a few countries, must
become a more peaceful world. Ob-
viously, the main instrument for creat-
ing those conditions is education. First,
educational facilities must be established
where there are none, and, second,
CONTINUED PAGE 59
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
7-CULTURE
The mind creatin
R EMEMBER the dey, wh"
"culture"was a luxury reserved for
the rich and leisured to dabble with ?
Remember when some cultures were
considered"primitive"and the stan-
dards of"real"culture were set in
the capitals of Europe for the
"natives"in the rest of the world to
imitate ? n many parts of the world
these days are still with us ; the old-
fashioned definitions die hard.
) n thé nineteenth century you could
consider yourself part of the cultural
scene if you knew nothing about Orien-
ta) or African history and literature,
but not any more. Whistler borrowed
techniques from Japanese wood-block
prints and Picasso was given a new
sense of mass and line by African
carvings, and through them western
man started to have his eyes opened
to what he was missing at first hand.
But not many of the original works
were available until Unesco under-
took to do its own kind of pioneering
and open something far more impor-
tant than the trade routes between
East and West, the routes of under-
standing in literature and the arts.
For literature, a platoon of trans-
lators were set to work putting repre-
sentative novels, poems and stories
into French and English from Arabic,
Burmese, Sinhalese, Chinese, Korean,
Indonesian, Iranian, Hebrew, Japanese,
Urdu, Thai, Viet-Namese, the non-Rus-
sian languages of the U. S. S. R., and
Indian languages including Sanskrit,
Hindi, Bengali and Tamil. Also, with
Unesco support, Buddhist texts writ-
ten in Pali have been transiated into
English, along with a rare collection
of"The Sacred Books of the East"
from Sanskrit, Pali and Chinese.
But the flow didn't go in just one
direction. Dickens was translated
into Burmese, Plutarch came out in
Chinese, Sophocles and Molière came
out in Indian languages, Nietzsche was
44 translate into Persian, Descartes,
trousseau and Voltaire into Arabic,
Shakespeare was translated into Thai
and Voltaire appeared in Viet-Namese,
to mention just a few.
Yet a classic novel about thirteenth
century Japan, or a Shakespearean his-
tory of sixteenth century England can
tell only so much about the Japanese
. or the English sensibility of the twen-
tieth century. The process, to be
complete, had to include works by
contemporary writers as we ! !.
Choosing classic works for transla-
tion is easy enough, but choosing a
handful out of the hundreds of living
writers to be translated, and investing
money in publications which would
probably not be a commercial success,
required much discussion and debate
by committees of some of the world's
most knowledgeable scholars.
in 1960, Unesco supported the pub-
lication of an anthology of poetry
which included many works by the
Greek poet George Seferis. He was
almost entirely unknown outside his
own country, and in 1963 he won the
Nobel Prize for Literature. Accidental
good luck on Unesco's part ? It was
more than that because in 1956 Unesco
had commissioned the first English
translation of the Japanese novel
"Snow Country"by Yasunari Kawa-
bata, the 1968 winner of the Nobel
Prize.
Whatever the translation, classic or
modern, Unesco will have it listed in a
tome the size of a large telephone
book with the formidable Latin title
Index Translationum. If you want to
read something from another country
or another culture, it will list current
works available in your own tongue.
Language differences may be the
most immédiate barriers when it
cornes to sharing a cultural heritage,
but there are other unexpected com-
plications in understanding. Music,
which you might assume would be as
universal a voice as a smile, has its
own vocabulary. h this case, no dic-
tionary will begin to explain the
differences in meaning.
The only way a western ear can
begin to"hear"oriental music is by
repeatedly being exposed to what may
at first seem like a jumble of ugly
squawks and wails. An"eastern"
ear has to sort through the undifferen-
tiated roaring of a Beethoven sym-
phony. It takes time, but eventually
one can recognize the beauty and
greatness of the other.
While western music is generally
available in the east, until Unesco pre-
pared an anthology of oriental music
(Japanese, Tibetan, Indian, Iranian, etc.)
westerners had little chance of ever
hearing it. When these records prov-
ed so successful Unesco did the same
thing for African music to popularize
its characteristic rhythms and sounds.
THE only art form that
needs limule or no translation is that of
painting. When one particularly great
artist sees the world in a new way,
the vision of the whole world changes.
h wealthy countries, brilliantly produc-
ed art books and richly-stocked
museums are accessible to everyone,
but in developing countries, access to
the world of paintings is very limited.
So Unesco established its"museum
without walls"which consists of sev-
eral travelling exhibits of reproduc-
tions and two huge compendiums of
the world's best colour prints. Even in
countries where a wide range of glossy
books is available, it would hardly be
profitable for a publisher to do whole
volumes on the Persian miniatures in
the Imperial Library, Ethiopian illus-
trated manuscripts and the Byzantine
mosaics and frescoes of Cyprus, so
once again Unesco seeks to make
them available by subsidizing their
publication.
A ! ! thèse projects have concerned
culture on the broadest possible scale,
but one of the things that makes world
culture so fascinating is its wonder-
fui variety and, in many cases, the
eccentricities of certain regions and
sensibilities.
A country without its own particular
cultural flavour is like a person without
a face. Like any expression of per-
sonality, it comes with a growing self-
possession, and without encourage-
CONTINUED PAGE 46
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
Appreciation of the arts and artistic creativity shouid begin in childhood. Unesco has
brought creative artists and educators together to see how this can be accomplished, and
has helped the creation of international societies and organizations which aim to foster
art education in schools and an appreciation of art in the community. During the past
25 years Unesco has published a large number of books on art : large-format art albums,
paperback*. catalogues of colour reproductions of paintings, specialized studies and
popular books on art. Unesco collections of records, produced in collaboration with the
International Music Council, have brought Western. Asian and African music to a wider
audience. tn co-operation with the International Theatre Institue. Unesco has promoted
theatre research and the use of new teaching methods in dramatic art. n co-operation
with the International Association of Art, Unesco is organizing, to commemorate its
25th anniversary in November 1971, an international poster contest for young artists on
the theme"A World Fit to Live in". n 1972 Unesco will hold a symposium for young people
to express their views on problems that face the artist of today and to discuss the future
of the arts throughout the world.
Photo 0 Thé Mem)-Pa) mer tnMitute-Donna J. Harris
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
GØQRGfl. SlNRIS
. tll ! lrll. 1tOØ)
. YMUtltAa,
tCA : WA1tA1'A
:.-t"t'".",.
- WMMiM.'
ttt
<= ,.," .
-
Literary
master-
pieces
across
frontiers
More than 400 translations of great
works of titerature already published
and a further 70 in préparation, this
is the present record of achievement
under Unesco's transition pro-
gramme which wus atarted in 1948.
Thé aim of the programme ils to
foster mutuat understaing bet-
ween nattions by maki translations
of cf888ica and cporat : Y wri-
tingsavaifable. rõugbout the
world.. Each year Unesco commit-
sions douns of n. w translations
from Ì'88 th. t ar.. un...
lit#a s yp #rr : y ia
: gMa' Ww<'<
warW''''tm'.'M''.'' :. 'K
ret 'wr,   a. 
rrâa  : ea r.
wri : s r < '
'..
ø
'. MMMA<'H". :. t
(M<9-<WM)
Lln8NtØ
(1tU-1N) *°°
ttt-'teM)
THE MIND CREATING (Continued)
ment, it is irretrievably lost. When
Unesco was first formed, one of its
major tasks was in convincing coun-
tries, shattered by war, not to neglect
their cultural heritage in rebuilding
themselves. Most governments want
to put off spending money on culture
until everything else is taken care of,
and of course, that never happens.
Why do particular countries have
tremendous explosions of creative
energy at particular times, when com-
munities of artists burn with a par-
ticular luminosity and intensity ? What
were the forces that created the works
of Renaissance Florence ? What fac-
tors produced the masterpieces of
the T'ang dynasty in China ? Where
did the glories of Aztec expression
sprint from ? To hope to recreate the'"thé conditions for such creativity one
must study culture, not as some fancy
pastime on a pedestal, but as an in-
tegral part of the life of a civilization.
Over the centuries, science has
itself been a part of culture. A beauti-
fully designed automobile is as much a
cultural expression as a Pharaoh's
chariot. As soon as you start talking
in these terms, ail the old snobbish-
ness connected with the arts begins to
disappear and a nation's culture starts
to become manageable.
It is no accident that, around Unesco,
culture is closely linked with the study
of the social sciences. Before you
can begin plotting a future cultural
policy for part of the world, you have
to study its past and its customs sys-
tematica ! ! y, in the largest possible
context. This was part of the aim in
writing a huge six-volume History of
the Scientific and Cultural Develop-
ment of Mankind.
The title itself gives some inkling of
just how mammoth an undertaking it
turned out to be. Most important, it
was meant to avoid any national and
personal prejudices, so international
teams of scholars pooled their talents
and tried to take in the whole human
picture, at the same time keeping in
mind their specifie theories and
opinions about their own fields.
At the moment, more spécifie works
are under way on spécifie cultural
units-Latin American, Oceanic, Malay-
sian, Arab and Indian. One of the
most ambitious of them is an eight-
volume General History of Africa. It
will take in Africa from its pre-history
before the seventh century B. C. to the
present.
Usually, doing a history involves
ploughing through stacks of dusty
documents and wading through a lot
of dry facts, but in this case, the only
way to get some of the necessary his-
torical and social mate rial is to listen
J. J tMMWMÀU
(tM2-i77a) (1t.)..
_ _ e e.  - m'
h    ,'. ; ra. ;e ;,.   n,  :
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Works have been translated'from
more thon sixty titeratures, corres-
ponding to some forty Aslan and
twenty European langages, as weil
as from the non-Slav literatures of
the Soviet Union and some African
literatures. Some of these transla-
tions are intended for a wide general
publie and have been pubtished in
paperback editions with targe prin-
tfJ\9S. ln addition. the programme
feresees the production of introduo-
torv handbooks to the iiteratures of
thé major Asian culturels written by
outstanding schofars. As our photos
show, thé writers seiected for
..... s. atioti oonstitute an interna-
! Ylr$ !.... al. 1 of ! ry fame. Works
J. thé first two, Geprge Seferis andVjtsanari Kawabata, were selected
for translation by Unesco before
etther of them had receivèd thé
eeveted Nobel prize for literature.
DANTE
(12M-1321)
TARASS
SHEVCHENKO
(iai4-18M)
RA8tNDRANATH
TA60RE
nSM-1941)
RUBAN Da"
(1817-1911)
"" :.-
..
SHAKESPEARE
(15t4-1618)
LAO. TU
(arcl cent... C. l)
DOMtMSO
SARMtlNTO
(181'-1888)
UNAMUNO
(''-''838>
 At.. GAHIZ
 ; {778-888)
TULsa DA.
(1632. 1'3J
MAOMt. OE'-
ÛSt-VÂM
ttSOC)
i'i ; : ;"x<&lt; MEfJK'<&lt;.; QeT<MOÀV : < :
<. (bom 1"') ; <   : ?
McjMMMtMS.'
° a-ts =
to and record the wealth of stories
and yarns that have been handed down
over the years by word of mouth. This
is history coming directly out of a liv-
ing tradition and even if the small
details may have been distorted by
time and vivid imaginations, the spirit
of the past is still immediately tangible.
The focus of a ! ! Unesco's activities
is still firmly in the present, in repeat-
ing the need for nations to keep their
heritage alive and, in practical terms,
to concern themselves with it seriously
enough to invest money in it, as an
essential part of a national future.
The means of expression, the new
media, new techniques, new stimuli at
the artist's disposai, in theatre, music
and the plaste arts has never been
broader nor the world around him
more challenging : his rôle as a life-
giver for society cannot be questioned ;
yet,"culture"as we know it may be in
for a great revolution which Unesco
is just now on the brink of exploring.
Already, it has become difficult to
tels from his works out of which
society a particular sculptor may have
corne or what background has shaped
an individual painter ; there is now a
so-called international style in archi-
tecture and in design. ! n some areas
mutual appreciation has created a kind
of uniformity of style and imagination
which is, ironically, just the other side
of what Unesco has been trying to
accomplish... and in many ways this
slavish sameness is worse than the
ignorance of other cultures that
Unesco has been trying to break
through.
With ail the plans for satellite com-
munications, to what extent will wé ail
be products of one world-wide tele-
vision culture ? Or, are these just the
perennial fears of those who are
stunned by the speed of man's dev-
elopment and who always raise a last
minute cry about losing their indivi-
duality ?
At this point no one can say for sure
what the new technology's effect both
on culture and society will be, but it
is clear, that now is the time to en-
courage national identities with ail
their wonderful variety and eccentri-
city while they still exist.
As up to now no one protected cer-
tain beautiful and rare species of
wild-life, so even now too few people
in positions of authority are concern-
ed with the culture of their regions.
Some of Unesco's studies may really
be about the last expressions of
national and regional customs as we.-
know them ; if not preserved by far/T/I-
sighted planning and support, they,
like the leopard for example, will
probably become extinct. N
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
8-MONUMENT
The mind
preserved
MACH of us owns some-
thing that we think is priceless and
irreplaceable. Maybe it is worth a lot
of money ; maybe it isn't worth
anything. It might be somebody's
picture, a collection of records, a ring...
but whatever it is, it is something that
has become a part of you. What if
someone, in a fit of anger or jealousy,
destroyed it right in front of your
eyes ? What would be your reaction ?
Fury ? Helplessness ? A feeling akin
to being smashed in the stomach ?
Bombs fall and destroy the city of
Dresden murdering thousands and
incidentally flattening a jewel among
cities. tn the name of progress,
ancient Egyptian temples which have
survived for aeons of time are to be
wiped off the face of the earth over-
night. What feeling does that arouse ?
The same awful sense of loss ?
Probably not. For most of us it
seems a pity that they should be
destroyed, but since it doesn't hit us
personally, we can't get a ! ! that excited
about it.
Unesco thinks differently. These
great glories of civilization belong to
everyone ; their destruction is a direct
loss for each of us and it is up to
us to adamantly defend them. It
seems ironic that the heights of man's
achievements should have to be pre-
served against his wars, his callous-
ness and his violence, but what we
have now of the past is merely the
leavings.
As early as 1954, Unesco prepared
a treaty on the preservation of monu-
ments during armed conflicts which
has been signed by less than hall of
its member states. Not a very good
showing-but some countries were
afraid that their enemies would use
sites protected by the treaty as
bunkers to operate from, and at which
nobody coula shoot back. The argu-
ment is as old as the history of war-
fare : if something is a strategic target,
no matter what it is or how valuable it
might be in itself, it must be destroyed.Often, the best that anyone can do
is to shore up a site against advancing
disaster, take pictures to record what
it looks like in case the sand-bagging
and other preparations don't work and,
if you have time, move the most
valuable parts of it somewhere else
for safe-keeping.
These are some of the precautions
that Unesco experts have taken with
the ruins of Angkor Wat, in Cambodia.
They are part of the remains of an
extremely rich civilization which flour-
ished in the twelfth century and then
was mysteriously deserted in the
fifteenth. The jungle took them over
and only in this century have archaeo-
logists discovered how vast the ruined
city must have been. By good for-
tune its fantastic carvings and eerie
pillared corridors of stone have been
preserved almost intact, and the story
of its unknown period lies waiting to
be explored both by tourists and the
experts who can piece together the
clues that Angkor holds.
It is now perilously close to the
Viet-Nam conflict... close enough to
be considered in it. The Secretary-
General of the United Nations and
the Director-General of Unesco have
made a public appeal to save it,
but, short of having it and miles
around it put off limits, the most that
can be expected is that, after the
fighting, it will somehow have been
protected enough to survive. Other-
wise, man will be left with only a
series of photos to remind him of its
beauties and fascinations.
Sometimes, it is man's practical
concerns rather than his ferocities that
menace great works of art ; it may
seem a pity, but there is no other way
of going about some building projects
than by destroying everything in your
wake.
When a new, higher Aswan Dam
was being planned to back up the
Nile and provide badly-needed hydro-
electric power, it was clear that the
great Egyptian temples at Abu Simbel
were going to be flooded in the
process ; but they were carved into the
stone face of a cliff, and there seemed
nothing that cou ! d be donc to save
them.
Then, in a dramatic move, it was
suggested that if enough countries
would co-operate with Unesco and help
to underwrite the enormous cost, the
temples could be literally sawn out
of the rock in huge chunks and moved
piece by piece to higher ground.
About fifty countries volunteered to
give support through Unesco and the
process was begun as the dam was
being built.
From the beginning, it was a race
against the rising waters ; but now
after five years of the actual work and
millions of dollars later, the temples
are we ! i above the newly-created lake,
and are more durable than ever. lu thé
moving, preservatives were added to
the stone itself and they were given
added strength by the most advanced
modern techniques of engineering.
A
BRU S ; mbel,"celved a
great deal of publicity as the glam-
orous centre of attraction in what
was in reality a much larger project ;
the full rescue operation took in the
whole area of Nubia where the mon-
uments were going to be submerged.
It took five years for 70 expe-
ditions from various countries to
catalogue and photograph ail thé
monuments, inscriptions and rock
carvings that were going to be
lost from sight beneath the waters ;
then, a) ! thé free-standing temples
were cut up and removed ; frescoes of
the Christian period were safely stored
and whatever was most precious was
saved wherever possible.
Throughout, experts kept a wary eye
on the island of Philae which was
located between the old and new
dams. Since the Nile had first been
dammed up at the beginning of this
century the temple to the goddess
Isis, its colonnade and a Roman temple
called Trajan's"Kiosk"on the island
had spent a large part of the year
underwater and had survived.
That is, they survived with the
exception of the many-coloured
Egyptian frescoes in the temple
which were stit ! intact in the nine-
teenth century, after 2, 000 years,
but were destroyed by the flood
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
The preservation of the world's cultural heritage has been one of the major tasks Unesco
set itself in the field of culture. The world campaign to save Abu Simbel and other monu-
ments of Nubia, launched in 1960, has now been brought to a successful conclusion except
for the rescue of the temples on the island of Philae (see page 63), but Unesco's action has
ranged a)) over the globe. The International Council of Museums which Unesco helped to
found in 1946, has become the recognized organization for museum authorities and techni-
cians throughout the world. n 1954, Unesco drew up an international treaty to protect
works of art and historical buitdingsduringarmed confiicts.) n 1959, it set up an international
centre in Rome for the study of the preservation and restoration of monuments and
works of art. Here a wooden statue is given an injection against a maladythat would have
reduced it to powder.
waters. With the decision to use the
basin between the dams as a reservoir
for generating electricity, the island is
permanently underwater ; the lake level
now changes up to nineteen feet daily
and the sandstone is being quickly
scrubbed away.
To save thís"pearl of Egypt"a dam
has to be built around the temples and,
using techniques similar to the ones
needed for Abu Simbel, they will be
carried away in about 20, 000 pieces
and reassembled on the firm, pinkish
granite of Agilkia, a deserted island
downstream.
What is frustrating about this project
is that, seventy years ago, when the
first dam was bui ! t, there was a
movement of historians to try to save
the temples but the government simply
couldn't afford the project. Had there
been an organization at that time such
as Unesco perhaps it could have mus-
tered the necessary international sup-
port and not only would we still have
the murais, now lost, but the whole
rescue could have been done for a
small fraction of what it is costing
today.
There are many treasures, like those
of Nubia, that are on the brink of
being destroyed and whose time for
rescue must come soon or never.
Fortunately, there is a new impetus
for present-day governments to keep
them from crumbling. If they will put
out the necessary capital for the work,
they aren't just wasting their money on
"art", they are investing in the highly
profitable venture of"cultural tour-
ism", attracting visitors, foreign
currency and a multi-billion dollar
industry of hotels and a ! ! thé services
of travel. Many of us can conceive of
getting on a plane and in a matter of
a few hours, actually visiting the tem-
ples of Isis and Abu Simbel. At least
it is a possibility.
tn that case, what about a visit to
the temples of Borobudur near Jogja-
karta, a moonlit stroll through the site
of ancient Carthage or an exploration
of the"Andean"and"Maya"routes
in Latin America ?
Borobudur is a massive Buddhist
shrine built twelve hundred years
ago in Java. It consists of four
square terraces which you walk around
to reach the summit ; ail along the way
there are hundreds of bas-reliefs
denoting various levels of spiritual
understanding. 49
You walk past these on a long
pilgrimage to the upper terrace,
getting farther and farther away
from concerns of the world so
CONTINUED PAGE 52
Photo Iþ Sotvay, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
Photo Unesco-Marc Riboud
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
Unesco has organized many hundreds of scientific missions to a ! ! parts of the world for the conser-
vation and preservation of sites and monuments and the cultural treasures of its member nations.
! n 1954 it launched an international campaign to alert the public and governments to the need to
safeguard monuments and works of art. n Africa, Asia and the Middle East, it has arranged special
training courses for technicians : at Jos. Nigeria, for African museum specialists, at the Latin Ame-
rican centre for the conservation of cultural property near Mexico City, and in Baghdad, for spe-
cialists from Arab member countries. Unesco has mobilized international ait for the restoration
of such famous monuments as Borobudur, in central Java (opposite, above, a statue of Buddha
on a terrace at Borobudur) and the ruins of Mohenjo Daro in Pakistan. tn 1966 it launched an
appeal for international aid to save Venice, and is now helpin9 to draw up and carry out a plan
for the preservation and restoration of the city. Above, angels surmounting the pediment of the
Santa Maria della Salute church in Venice. Opposite left, a"square of three cultures" (Aztec
remains, a 16th century church and modern apartment blocks) in Mexico City.
", c
í
"'"1 : >
,, :u
: ; 1"'"'
'"
êo
U
1
õ'
E"
: : >
<. : >
a :
G
o
õ. < :;a.
1
PRESERVING
OUR
HERIT AGE
OF
THE
PAST
51
-'"
Ci>-
Q)"
z
c. i"
U
Q ;. cmLU
mN
'"2'""a :
o
Õ. < :;©
g
o
Õ. < : ;Il.
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
Photo Unesco
) n 1953, Unesco sent conservation missions to Syria and the Lebanon which outlined plans
for the preservation of important monuments, includin9 the ruins of Palmyra, crusaders'
casttes. including the famous Krak des Chevaliers (above), and the ruins of Baalbek. A
major aspect of their studies was the problem faced by historical monuments in a modern
city, in the case of the Lebanon, the old quarters of Tyre, Sidon and Tripoli. Unesco's many
conservation missions to Asia have included several to Nepal to plan the preservation of
monuments in Katmandu and other cities. Brightly painted carvings (right) depict the
Hindu god Siva and his wife, Parvati, at a temple in Katmandu.
THE MIND PRESERVED (Continued tram page 49)
that you are prepared for the silent top
which looks out in every direction over
breathtaking mountain ranges.
Here in the centre, there are many
stupas or onion-shaped domes through
whose openings you catch glimpses of
hundreds of seated Buddhas ; the tall-
est one in the centre contains a sealed
globe which is the representation of
the highest spiritual truth of which man
is capable, the jmponderable Nirvana.
This spectacular edifice was built
entirely without mortar over a huge
mound of earth. Over the centuries,
water has seeped through the cracks
and eroded the foundations beneath.
As a result, the whole structure now
leans crazily every which way and if
the walls supporting the lowest terrace
crumble, it will ai crash down in a
massive landslide of statuary and wall
carvings.
The Indonesian government has res-
cued as many of the statues as pos-
52 rible, but with Unesco support it willbe able to save the temple itself. This
operation will involve dismantling it a ! !.
stone by stone, placing it firmly on
carefully concealed reinforced con-
crete foundations and putting in chan-
nels for the rain-water to escape.
! n thé process, the carvings will be
cleaned of the lichen and minerval de-
posits that are eating at them, and will
be covered with preservatives against
any further ravages of weather and
time.
The threat to the site of ancient Car-
thage is of another kind. It is threat-
ened by the growth of the modern city
that surrounds it, and unless it is ex-
plored and part of it restored with the
advice of experts from Unesco it will
no doubt be swallowed up by a sea of
asphalt and concrete. The kind of
project Unesco is undertaking with the
governments of Latin America is
essentially one of reclaiming their
Incan and Mayan heritage from the
jungle and making them available
as a resource for tourism.
The list of exotic names of places
throughout the world to which Unesco
is sending missions is very long in-
deed, but its involvement doesn't stop
by any means with what to a western
ear sounds rare and esoteric. ! n 1966,
when floods washed through the cities
of northern Italy, many of the famous
works of art that we think of as being
safe and well-preserved were damag-
ed and, in some cases, totally des-
troyed.
Florence was particu larly hard hit,
and Unesco launched an interna-
tional campaign of emergency help.
Money poured in from individuals and
governments the world over who
recognized the enormity of the loss.
The work of restoration, cleaning,
rebuilding and putting the city back
together took several years and is just
now being completed.
From it, Unesco experts have learn-
ed a lot about not only restoring and
preserving works of art, but about the
way museums and libraries should be
set up so that such a large scale disas-
ter won't occur again ; then it has
applied these new techniques to the
museums and libraries it is helping to
establish in its member states through-
out the world.
Precious documents were destroyed
in the archives of Florence which
could have been saved if the vaults
they were in had been waterproof ;
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
even if they had been catalogued and
microfilmed, at least their contents
wouldn't have been lost. With modern
preservative techniques, frescoes
buried in mud needn't have been totally
ruined. Of course it is easy to say
these things after the fact, but Flor-
ence has become a giant pilot project
for Unesco which will supply the infor-
mation needed to prevent the same
losses elswhere.
Another victim of the 1966 floods
was Venice, the jewel of the Adriatic,
but, it being a city built on a lagoon,
changes in water level there are not
such a catastrophe. However, its cul-
tural difficulties are more serious and
far-reaching than any others that
Unesco has worked with. There, not
only the cultural heritage of the city
must be preserved, but the life of the
city itself is at stake.
The salt waters are taking a heavy
troll of the magnificent palaces lining
the canais. The foundations are being
rotted away, and whole sections of
brick and plaster are col ! apsing into
the waters, often threatening to sink
passing gondolas as they do so.
The city is being more and more ex-
posed to the buffeting of the waves, so
people are simply not bothering to
repair the damage as it occurs. Many
of the buildings are being deserted and
residents are moving to the mainland
in droves. ! n effect, the city is being
left like a faded prima donna to memo-
ries and decay.
The task of saving Venice is more
than culturel, keeping its works of art
intact, protecting it from the sea, res-
toring the damage already done ;
although the entire city is an artistic
shrine, it must be considered socially,
economically and geographically as
we ! !.
in this case, a large part of the mo-
mentum for saving the city must be
generated from within. The glories that
were created by a wealthy sea-trading
empire have to be preserved by mak-
ing the modern Venice economically
sound. ! mproved transportation, per-
haps an undersea subway line connect-
ing with the main land, might open it
up as a more practical place t6 live.
And of course, tourism has to be
developed in such a way that people
will not just come over for the day to
look at St. Mark's, breathe in the at-
mosphere, and return to the mainland
at night. Once they are in Venice they
must be attracted enough to stay over
and spend their money there.
This project is a kind of culmination
of a ! ! that Unesco has been practising
and preaching through the years. Ail
these ornate, impractical palaces, the
expensive preoccupation with lavish
decor, the fascination with paintings
and sculptures worth kings'ransoms...
ais this"crazy"spending of money in
the past is the only reason that the
city is not being abandoned to thé
sweep of the sea today.
What Unesco has been dinning into
the ears of modern governments really
has the ring of truth ; aside from ail
the practical greatness of any society
now flourishing, probably the only
thing that will convince future genera-
tions to save its remains will be the
impractical, illogical, foolish outpour-53
ings of its artists and artisans. If any
of us are to be remembered, it is our
cultural life above ail that must flourish
and be preserved. *
Photo @ Photo Researchers Zinc., New York
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
9-COMMUNICATION
Sharing
the mind
ne of the gruesome. but
otherw ! se untested tacts to corne out
of brainwashing in prison camps is
that without any chance to commu-
nicate the mind collapses in rubble
and despair. n psychological experi-
ments, peuple whose hands, eyes and
ears are bound and who cannot move
are soon disoriented and desperate
for any kind of stimulation... a change
of temperature or even àn itch.
The mind simply cannot stand to be
in isolation ; it needs its place in the
real ! wor ! d of sights, sounds, feelings
and discomforts. m fact it is inconceiv-
able ! e to think of society today without
communications and, in a similar vein,
to think of communications without
realizing their potential impact on
society.
Since education ; science and culture
are ai ! différent ways of getting what
is going on inside one man's mind
into the minds of others. in the course
of its work, Unesco found itself deeply
concerned with theconcept of commu-
nication itsejf. A teacher has to sell
ideas to his students, to make them
live, or he is wasting his time ; there
are simply too many different stimuli
competing for their attention for him to
risk boring them. We hâve aN iearned
to tune out the colounul advertizing,
the noise and the high-pressure sales-
manship that bombards us every day ;
the trouble is that in the process, we
might miss thoughts and expériences
of real value.
! n high ! y mechanized societies, old-
fashioned means of communication,
such as books are taken for granted
and a iot of peop ! e just won't take the
time to sit down and read one when
they can do dozens of"more exciting"
things. Automated presses keep'turn-
ing them out by the millions and some
peuple do keep reading, but the idea
-' that a book might be an adventure
and that it takes real effort to produce
is almost entirely gone.
! n thé deveioping countries, how-
ever, there must be newspapers, a
book-publishing industry and a public
library system to make reading
materials available to everybody or
national literacy is impossible. So
Unesco has sought to strengthen
national publishing ventures through
aid in the form of equipment and
advisers to train the journalists,
printers and librarians who can put
the printed word in motion.
Yet can the deve ! op. ment of mass
media of communication stop even
there ? Just because a developing
country isn't wealthy, can it afford not
to have radio and television facilities ?
This is the last third of the. twentieth
century, the century of revolution in
communication, but perhaps aH the
advances are only for the rich. A lot
of the time, so-called"developed"
countries use television, in particular,
as if it were a toy to be fooled with,
a luxury that the poor of the world
couldn't possibly need. Unesco, how-
ever, sees it as an absolutely crucial
tool, which every developing country
is going to need if it hopes to catch up.
The educational possibilities for TV
are just now being explored with
"Sesame Street"for pre-schoolers in
the United States, Unesco's own
project in the Ivory Coast for primary
schoo ! s and Britain's"Open Univer-
sity."The real valus of the médium.
together with radio and films, is finally
coming through.
But it is coming through very, very
fast, and as a support for one of the
biggest challenges of the next
decades-mass media for lifelong
éducation. Either developing countries
hâve modern communications and the
trained film-makers and radio and
television technicians to operate them
in the near future or they will be so
far behind that they will never recover.
Unesco sees clearly the two sides
to the great boom in modern commu-
nications. On one hand, it can open
undreamt-of possibilités for mutual
understanding, or it can be a Pandora's
Box of tricks for setting up bad feel-
ings between countries.
For example, when an author writes
a book or a script he copyrights it for
his own country and for a few other'
countries who have worked out mutual
agreements, so that every time it is
printed or performed, he gets some
payment for the hours of work, the
training and thé investment of himself
and his talent that he has put into it ;
in effect, his ideas are his own and
he gets credit for them.
However, outside of the countries
that have agreements with his, his
work is fair game. It can be repro-
duced, changed unmercifully, and
exploited as if he had never written it,
and there is nothing he can do to
protect himself.
UNESCO h"dcaft. d'"
international copyright agreement
which could cut thrvugh ail the endless
political complications that now exist
and put an end to ail the mistrust and
skulduggery that is involved in selling
books from one country to another.
This"Universal Copyright Conven-
tion,"which covers not only literary
material, but scientific and artistic
works as we ! !, so far has only sixty
signatures, (not very impressive for an
organization of 125 states), but at least
among those who have signed, inter-
national feelings are considerably
smoother and maybe in the course of
time other nations will see the wisdom
of dealing fairly as we ! !.
But copyright is not the only
obstacle to making books available
in the developing world. There is also
the problem of converting currencies
CONTINUED PAGE 56
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
These Indian schoolboys are studying in the shade of one of
the massive masonry astronomical instruments at the Jantar
Mantar Observatory, New Delhi, built by the astronomer-
king MaharajahJai Singh)) in 1710. They may soon be learning
with the help of a Unesco-aided educational satellite broad-
casting system which India is planning to introduce on an
experimental basis in 1972. Unesco has a direct stake in the
use of space communications for education, science and
culture, and has promoted studies into the possibilities of
education via satellite relays. It has sent missions to the
Ivory Coast, Brazil and India to he) p ptan such communica-
tions systems. For Unesco, communication by every possible
means is the key to the achievement of its aims and ideas,
and from the outset it has sought to promote the free flow
of information and ideas. An agreement on the importation
of educational, scientific and cultural materials, adopted by
Unesco's General Conference in 1950, has been instrumentai
in reducing tariff and trade obstacles to the free flow of
information. Unesco sponsored the Universal Copyright
Convention, adopted in 1952, which helped to fill gaps in
existing copyright agreements. A recent conference at
Unesco's H. Q., studied how the copyright protection offered
by the Universal Convention could be extended to cover. JQ
the rights of reproduction, public performance and broad-
casting, in ways which would be of special benefit to the
developin9 countries.
N
a
e
Q."å : 1"'-0
c :
: ;0 : 1
è :o..
Õ
'"""".. J
Q
o
Õ. < :;a
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
SHARING THE MIND (Continued)
to enable"soft currency"countries
to purchase not only books, but also
films, school supplies or scientific
equipment from"hard currency"areas.
To get round this huge frustration,
Unesco has invented a system of
"international money orders,"known
as Unesco Coupons, which univer-
sities, schools, research institutions
and individuals in developing countries
can buy in their own currencies and
send to a publisher or supplier to pay
for the books or equipment they need.
To keep the slow of books, works
of art and scientific equipment going
throughout the world, Unesco has
written up agreements so that they
can a ! ! get through customs duty
free ; but the idea that you have to
move something across a border in
order to share it is quickly disappear-
ing now that satellite communications
can put you somewhere thousands of
miles away in a fraction of a second.
At the moment, when a television
programme, a tape-recording or a
record are concerned, you can be sure
of the range of the transmitter, and
you can corne to a fairly satisfactory
decision about the right to play it, but
in the near future a song sung once
or a drama acted once will potentially
have the whole world as a simul-
taneous audience, through satellite
transmission. ""
By the ear ! y 1970s, there will be
communal receivers working through-
out the world that will relay program-
mes into your home, and that will
leave some control as to what you
see, but by the early 1980s, indivi-
dual television sets will pick up
programmes direct from the satellites
themse) ves.
Just how much right do particular
governments have to say that they
don't want their citizens seeing partic-
ular programmes or hearing criticisms
of their work from the other side of
the world ? The whole system could
disintegrate to the level of a gigantic
and expensive propaganda mill, or it
could be a thrilling, mind-expanding
step toward putting the world back
together again. Unesco is faced with
negotiating an agreement that will
maintain the right to privacy for
specific cultures and ideologies and
at the same time preserve the right of
ail individuals to be fairly, impartially
informed.
It is a good thing that the satellites
won't be in commercial operation for
several years because a project so
loaded with political dynamite and
demanding such a complete change
56 of thinking on the part of everyone inthe world is going to take every minute
of negotiation that Unesco can
possibly afford to give its
The introduction of new educational techniques in the Ivory
Coast, the mobilization of world opinion to save the monu-
ments of Venice or Borobodur, the opening of an institute of
technology in Bombay-these are visible, concrete achieve-
ments of Unesco in recent years. But perhaps less evident
is the profound revolution in attitudes towards Education,
towards Science and towards Culture that Unesco has helped
to spark in its member states. It is this new awareness of the
right to education for a ! !, in the broadest sense of the term,
and its overriding place in economic and social development
that is one of the outstanding achievements of Unesco's
work over the past twenty-five years. Photo, above, in a sense
symbolizes the Unesco ideal-the chiid symbotizing a better
world of tomorrow through better education and modern
science without rejecting the great cultural values of the
past (symbolized by the statues) which enrich life and give
it a quality worth preserving.
]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[
The mind Reflects
s
SHELTERED between two
wings of the Unesco Secretariat is a
sma ! ! Japanese garden. Water flows
from a monolithic rock, glistening over
an ancient Japanese character for
"peace"cut deeply into it. Around step-
ping stones, it falls over a series of
waterfalls, each with a different sound,
now a miniature cataract growling,
now a gentle trickle. It finds peace in
a shallow pond, where copper-coloured
carp hide under overhanging bran-
ches, under a bridge, or beneath a
floating island of dark red lily pads.
Here, the seasons change from the
glories of pink and white spring blos-
soms, to summer irises among the
reeds, to the stark outlines of new-
fallen snow on black branches. Only
the miniature mountains of rock seem
unchanging and untouched.
Here in the silence and tranquillity
is the perfect setting for reflection.
The business of the Secretariat goes
on a ! i around just a few feet away, but
here details and appointments fade
and you can begin to put it ail into
perspective.
Just as this place apart refreshes
anyone who is willing to give it a few
minutes of his time, so in Unesco
itself, there is a place apart, a place
for theorizing, for self-evaluation, and,
most of a ! !, for contemplating the
world as it should be.
Thia ! s among the group of Unesco 57
philosophers whose job is to range the
spectrum of its activities and say
"Here we have a responsibility",
CONTINUED NEXT PAGE
u.w
5 : !
z
: ;)
,
cOB
õ
: I
"'"
: c"
"
o
Õ. < :;Li O_
10-PRINCIPLES
]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[
THE MIND REFLECTS (continuel)
"There an agreement must be reach-
ed among our member nations."Here
many of the ideas and concepts are
born which become an active part of
Unesco's work.
But often some of the most impor-
tant things that Unesco can contribute
to the world are the thoughts them-
selves. At the beginning of its life, the
United Nations drafted a Universal
Declaration of Human Rights which
talks about the right of any individual
to develop and fulfil himself, to ex-
press himself and to live with dignity
and pride of bearing.
OFFICIALL Y, Il'membe,
states accepted ail this optimistic
sentiment, but in reality in the last
twenty years since the declaration
was signed, its concepts have been
ignored, flaunted, violated and abused
in more ways than those who wrote
it could ever have believed. It makes
very painful reading indeed, in the
light of the oppression, the racial and
souciai discrimination, and the degrad-
ation of the human spirit that go on
every day.
It was signed as a gentleman's
agreement between nations, based on
national honour to be carried out-in
many cases not the most unshakeable
foundation when power politics and
social expediency are concerried. So,
in effect, the signatures are a ! ! that
the U. N. has.
The thoughts remain as sound as
when they were put down (at least,
where most of the world is concerned),
but the U. N. and its agencies have no
authority whatsoever to question, let
alone interfere in, the way that coun-
tries treat individuals or groups within
their own boundaries. The thoughts
of human rights have to speak totally
for themselves... where they be can
heard.
Recently, Unesco has been look-
ing at the Declaration again, in the
light of modern social science, to see
just how Universal it really is. How
could it be expanded and re-thought to
take in more of the world, without los-
ing its central force ?
You would think that no one would
have trouble accepting the concept of
human rights, at least in principle, but
in point of fact, political quibbles aside,
there are some fundamental philoso-
phical and emotional disagreements
with the whole idea.
) f you are a Buddhist, for example,
certain attitudes about the individual
may be at variance with the single
idea expressed in the Declaration ;
concern about self-worth and indivi-
duality is a form of pride ; the ideal
is to submerge an individual life into
tQ thé greater scheme of things with
humility and without complaint. One
! ife, even if it is your own, or many
! ives, don't merit so much fuss.
! n some Asian philosophies, the
concept that a ! ! persons are equal is
in itself strange, for according to such
thinking there is a hierarchy among
men, and you must accept whatever
those above you in rank (a ruler, a
father or an employer) might suggest
without question.
Where things get really complicated
is deciding what is universally a right
for women. Legally, in some countries,
the idea of woman as an inferior
and a chattel is a old as the civiliza-
tion itself, and the whole structure of
life has been based on that premise ;
the women themselves would perhaps
be more shocked than thé men by any
attempt to upset the traditional state
of affairs.
Still, even within the framework of
social male supremacy, every woman
has private, personal dominion over
what goes on in her mind and Unesco
stays firmly with the opinion stated in
the Declaration that every man, woman
and child has an equal right to be edu-
cated regardless of whatever other
inequalities might be imposed on him ;
the right to have a trained mind is
absolutely basic and upon that ail
other concepts of human rights can be
built.
! n one area of human rights Unesco
has been able to take a very forceful
stand, and that is in the realm of
racial prejudice. Racists have always
supported their arguments with bio-
logical, sociological and historical
pseudo-evidence. Unesco was in a
position to ça on world-famous
anthropologists, biologists and geneti-
cists to find out what is true in the
racist's case and what is a distortion
of the facts.
To their opinions were added those
of ethnographers, sociologists, his-
torians and lawyers and the whole
published in a Statement on Race
and Racial Prejudice, condemning
it as a threat to international peace
and a crime against humanity. One
country famous for its policy of Apart-
heid withdrew from Unesco but the
other members remained resolute and,
in principle, supported the scientists'
findings.
"lu principle"is a useful little diplo-
matic phrase that leaves the way open
for unlimited hedging. ln principle, ail
the member states of Unesco are com-
mitted to peace as we ! !. but since the
Second Wor ! d War there have been
100 armed conflicts which Unesco
took pains to list in the November
1970, issue of the"Unesco Courier".
Translated into a dozen languages,
the brutal facts were there for the
world to see, but the arms build-up
continues and countries continue to
spend over 200, 000 million dollars a
year (as much as the yearly income
of the poorer half of the world's popu-
lation put together) on ever more so-
phisticated murder-weapons.
ln principle, ail that money could
be spent for education, development
and a ! ! thé positive causes that man
could dream of, but in reality, it is
squandered on man's meaningless
war games, on threateninq his fellows
and paranoiacally protecting himself.
The thoughts of peace that Unesco
is aiming for seem far, far away,
bogged down in the old patterns of
narrowness of mind, selfishness and
hate. If you are Unesco or any part
of the United Nations system, by now
you have learned not to expect
miracles and you have learned how to
persevere.
But this is in no way to be mistaken
for pessimism or giving up. The suc-
cesses that Unesco has had, in what
it has attempted, speak for themselves,
but they are the first thing you forget
when progress is slow and new hosts
of problems and difficulties come up.
Within the Secretariat and out in the
field, there are people with the rare
and wonderful ability to work intensely
on a project and, through ail thé
details, the human mistakes, the paper
work and the unexpected setbacks, to
keep in view at a ! i times the ultimate
goals for which they and the organi-
zation are aiming. This kind of men-
tality, to work quietly without drawing
attention to yourself and without illu-
sions as to how much you can really
accomplish, is the backbone of
Unesco and of its staff. Not very
glamorous perhaps, but the best that
any experienced citizen of the world
can do.
Eo U CA TI 0 N. Scle, ce.
Culture. Thoughts of peace. A huge
experiment with the minds of men.
People of former centuries would have
scoffed at the idea of Unesco as
foolhardy and unreal... some still do.
Its progress is measured in the mo-
mentary flash of light and understand-
ing across a man's face as he reads
a page, a catch in the breath as a
young woman rounds a corner and
catches sight of a temple bathed in
sun, a smile after hours of poring over
a page when the equation works and
the whole solution spreads itself out
simple and clear... those moments of
clarity and relief when things finally
come right. You can't count smilles,
thoughts and breakthroughs, but to
see even one is to know that more are
happening and more will happen.
Unesco's work is just starting ;
twenty-five years isn't long in the
human scheme. Will we a ! ! one day
be educated ? Will our planet one day
be a beautifu !, fresh place for us a ! ! ?
Will we a ! ! be open to the beauties
and glories of the human imagination ?
That a ! ! sounds a bit too close to Eden,
highly impossible in the light of what
we know of man, but like schemes for
going to the moon, curing diseases,
and finding someone to love, it is a
beautiful, beautiful thought..
]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[
'un THE MINDS OF MEN' (Continued tram page 43)
education at ail levels must be permeat-
ed with the seed of internationalism.
For while education in itself is a sine
qua non, it must also bear the hallmark
of internationalism, spread the basic
idea of the necessity of internationalism.
There is but one world for ait of us.
To make us ail really understand what
that entails is the task of education.
And it is here that aN the activities
of Unesco must converge to become
action.
ALVA MYRDAL
Sweden's Minister of Disarmament and
former Director of Unesco's Dept.
of Soc ! a) Sciences
YESTERDAY'S ABSURD) TY
- TODAY'S REALITY
The achievement of political inde-
pendence by former colonies has not
solved the problems of their economic,
intellectual, scientific and technical
independence. The scientific and tech-
nical potential of a country depends on
the number of trained scientists it
possesses and the overall quality of its
scientific infrastructures and institutions
which enable it to define and resolve
problems of theoretical and applied
science. Twenty-five or thirty years
ago, the idea of a science policy and
the planning of science seemed absurd
to many politicians as we ! i as to scien-
tists themselves. Today, many young,
newly independent states. are trying to
create a network of scientific institutes,
to set up organizations responsible for
the overall control of scientific matters
and to allocate a regular share of their
budgets to the training of scientists and
to research.
VICTOR A. KOVDA
former Director of the Unesco
Department of Natura ! Sciences
ENCROACHMENTS ON PRIMATE LIFTE
Today, as never before, a code for
science and technology needs to be
drawn up, defining their ultimate ethical
aims and laying down the principles
governing their use exclusively in the
service of man, with the aim of promot-
ing, materially and spiritually, the har-
monious development of mankind.
International law should prote et the
individual against the effects of new
techniques or certain forms of advertis-
ing and propaganda which, if misused,
may encroach upon his private life or
threaten his intellectual and moral inde-
pendence. It should also protect him
against the increasingly serious threat
of total pollution of his environment
resulting from mass industrialization.
HANNA SABA
tonner Assistant D ! rector-Genera) of
Unesco for International Standards
and Legal AHalrs
IDEALS AND REALITIES
Ail Unesco's activities deriving from
its three inseparable functions (intellec-
tua !, ethicai and operational) are con-
tributing to Africa's development. They
are promoting a movement of moral
and intellectual solidarity which is the
wellspring of international co-operation
for development. Thus African deve-
lopment is benefitting equally from the
"Unesco ideal", the"Unesco reality",
the"Unesco thinking : and the"Unesco
action".
WILLIAM ETEKI-MBOUMOUA
President of the Unesco
General Conference (1968)
CULTURE, THE INDIVISIBLE
Culture today should aim for greater
depth and scope. Thé âge of the Ency-
clopaedists, as we wei ! know, is un-
happily long past, and the future of
science and culture lies with specialists
who are increasingly cramped and
confined within their own particular
spheres of interest. For years past the
disastrous effects of the divorce bet-
ween the"two cultures"-scientific and
literary-has been abundantly obvious.
Culture, which has been shrinking from
the cold, must once again venture into
the world outside or it may disappear.
Similarly, society, education and science
must become permeated by culture or
the results will be equally catastrophic.
Culture is an indivisible whole and the
cutting of those links that bound it not
only with science, but also with nature
is one of the great tragedies of today.
JEAN D'ORMESSON
Assistant Secretary-General
of the tntemattona) Councll
for Philosophy and Humantsttc Studles
.-5'1". : r'e, f *  p. ,'-$ Q ̀k , s^$¢  ', n * .. f &·  y S.
*
rai t 5
°z *s , _. r. r str`t, Gss,. .  » rR.. rru a, ^'2y-
59
Ny y. ` Pl : wll4
UN WMO , r IMF
I 0 W >4R"
 il United Nations World Meteorological International Monetary Fund
 Headquarters : New York Organization Headquarters :
Headquarters : Geneva Washington D. C.
UNRWA-==-mm--., M \"-"",United Nations Relief nd l ! ! L UNESCO  IAEA y iBRD
Works Agency for Palestine
Refugees in the Near East United Nations Educational, International Atomic Energy".,...",,'.
Scientific and Cultural Agence International Bank
gency R.
Organization H d rt V. for Reconstructiones quia ergs : lenna d D 1
UNICEF Headquarters : Paris an eve opment
Headquarters :United Nations Children's Fund 8'WHeadhuatrtersD : C
(8, ITU as mg on..
, "'U""
UNHCR'1R WHO International/rtig ! iiù
Office of United Nations High W : ; ; Health Organization Telecommunication
Commissionner for Refugees G anion
Headquarters : Geneva Headquarters : Geneva International Development
Association
UNDP, &commat;  Headuarters :
United Nations Deveiopment  FAO UPU Washington D. C.
Programme
Food and Agriculture Universel Postal Union : 1 
Organisation Headquarters : Berne v IFCUNCTAD of the United Nations."."....,.
United Nations Conference Headquarters : Rome-"Inte, rnational Financial
on Trade and Development"r", ICAO Corporation
"'0. 0"
A 1. 1 C.. 1 A. t. Headquarters :
Trade and Development Board''nterntloa IVI via Ion W h't D C
i ILO Organlzatlon. as mg on..Organization.
Headquarters : Montreal
UNIDO International Labour
United Nations Industrial Organization 'GATT
Development Organization Headquarters : Geneva tt'lSt. dl' IMCO G 1 A
....,..  enera greement
iA", Inter-Governmental Maritime on TariHs
B International Court Of Justice Consultative Organization and Trade
 Headquarters : The Hague Headquarters : London Headquarters : Geneva
]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[
NUBIA
Victory
of
international
solidarity
by Abdel Moneim El Sawi
ABDEL MONEIM EL SAWI held the post
of Under Secretary to the Egyptian Ministry
of Culture for 12 years, during which time
he was directly concerned with the inter-
national campaign to save the monuments
of Nubia. He was deputy chairman of the
joint venture to displace the temples of
Abu Simbel, and supervised the project
until the end of 1969. Mr. El Sawi is
editor of the Arabise edition of the"Unesco
Courier"and is chairman of the Unesco
National Publications Centre in Cairo, which
is responsible for the publication of Arabie
editions of a number of Unesco penod) ca/s.
An Arab man of letters, he has published
a number of books in Arabic.
]]>
</page>
<page number="61">
<![CDATA[
The rescue of the Abu Sim-
bel temples from the waters
of the Nile was not only one
of the greatest engineering
feats of the modern era. it
was also one of the finest
examples of selfless, disin-
terested, international co-
operation of ati time. Left,
one artist's conception of
the salvage operations be-
fore they were actually un-
dertaken. A temporary cof-
ferdam, in foreground, holds
back the rising waters as the
Great Temple of Rameses is
excavated and prepared for
dismantling. The smaller
Queen Nefertari Temple,
right of photo, awaits the
builders'attentions. A spe-
cially constructed road runs
along the cofferdam and up
to the new site where the
two temples were finally to
be installed in artificial
hillocks, 200 feet above
their original site. To exca-
vate the temples from the
hillside, 300, 000 tons of rock
had first to be removed.
The temples were then cut
up into blocks weighing up
to 30 tons each and with a
total weight for the two
temples of 15, 000 tons. Work
began in 1964 with the con-
struction of the cofferdam
and the two temples were
ceremonially inaugurated on
their new site on September
22, 1968.
Hue International cam-
paign to save the monuments and
explore the archaeological sites of
Nubia is one of the great achieve-
ments of Unesco in its quarter of a
century of existence. Eleven temples
once threatened by the rising waters
of the Aswan High Dam have been
removed and re-erected on new sites,
and four others dismantled and pres-
ented to the U. S. A., Spain, The
Netherlands and Italy in recompense
for the help they gave in the rescue
operation of the Abu Simbel temples.
Ah that remains is to dismantle the
temples of Philae and to reconstruct
them on the island of Agilkia, beyond
the reach of the Nile.
The tourist in Nubia today who
stands admiringly before the temples
now resurrected in the cultural"oases"
at Abu S ! mbe !, Amada, Wadi Es Sebua
and Kalabsha may little realize the
gigantic efforts that went into this
international achievement.
Nubia lies between the Aswan Dam
in Egypt and the Dual cataract in the
Sudan-over 500 kilometres of rugg-
ed country flan king the course of the
Nile, remote from urban civilization,
with an austere climate and acces-
sible only by boat.
As work started on the construction
of the High Dam, a vast exodus from
Nubian villages and hamlets began.
Soon the entire area was denuded of
life. Fruit and vegetable plantations
withered and then the waters rising
behind the dam wall slowly but inexo-
rably swallowed up roads, palm trees,
houses, te ! egraph and telephone lines.
Finally there were no communi-
cations, no crops, no food, no sec-
urity or guard posts, in fact virtually
nothing except the Nile waters and the
desert sands. It was in this austere
setting that an unprecedented cultural
rescue operation began.
During the Nubia monuments cam-
paign, from 1960 until 1968, perhaps 61
the most difficult years were those
when the lochai population was evac-
uated. When this emigration was
CONTINUED NEXT PAGE
ø'+,. < : ;"o
: I .Q)
1 : >'"a :
ë: >
C
3. <&gt;
'"F. 
èi
]]>
</page>
<page number="62">
<![CDATA[
NUBIA (Continued)
completed in. 1963, Nubia looked so
dead and empty that it seemed impos-
sible that men had ever lived there.
Nevertheless. the new.. inhabitants"
of Nubia-specialists, technicians and
workers from Egypt, Sudan and many
other countries-accepted the chal-
lenge of scorching sun and arduous
living conditions as they set about
the operation launched in response
to Unesco's international appeal of
March 8, 1960
T ODA Y,., l, ee. II the
achievements of this compaign, 1 would
like to pay tribute to the men and
women who embarked on this historie
endeavour : scientists, engineers,
artists, technicians and workers from
a ! ! parts of the world.
Nubia was transformed during the
excavation seasons into a unique in-
ternational arena. During the long
summer months when thé Ni ! e water-
level dropped beyond the Aswan Dam
as the sluices were opened to drain
away the flood water, excavation
teams searching for monuments and
other remains were scattered through-
out Nubia.
Living on Nile boats and in white
tents, they worked from dawn till
forenoon, then resumed work from
the afternoon till late in the evening.
Throughout each season, lights glowed
on both banks of the Ni ! e as thé scien-
tists busied themse ! ves with their
studies and, when they couid, org-
anized social life and entertainments.
tn these camps one coula hear
English, French, Czech, Spanish.
Polish, German and Russian spoken,
as oeil as Arabie and many other
languages.
An international spirit prevailed
everywhere in Nubia. This"Nubian
spirit", as it came to be known, over-
came ai ! différences and unified
everyone within a framework of co-op-
eration and friendship. The same
spirit prevailed among those at work
salvaging the temples.
The archaeological teams were
carrying out excavation work during
several months each year, before re-
turning home with their finds. During
these months the teams removing the
temples were also at work so that the
62 whole area bustled with activity.It should be recalled that the
operation of dismantling and re-siting
the two temples at Abu Simbel went
on without interruption for nearly five
years (from 1963 to 1968) despite
great material difficulties. For the
teams engaged on this project the
operation was a life and death race
against the rising waters of the Nile.
Yet the contract covering the joint
venture at Abu Simbel, signed in
November 1963, did not permit the
erection of any installations prior to
the start of the operation. We could
not have risked spending millions of
dollars on construction work until the
attitude of the International Nubian
Campaign towards this special project
had become quite clear.
Thus, we had to mobilize every
avallable means, however simple. Two
Nile boats were built and in these we
carried a the archaeologists, engin-
eers and technicians to their work
sites. At first we also carried food sup-
plies by boat. But refrigeration facil-
ities were so inadequate that we had
to send fresh vegetables, only to see
them spoiled by the scorching heat.
Finally we had to depend on canned
vegetables and make up any dietary
deficiencies with vitamins.
Another major problem was the
lack of pure water. This we over-
came by installing equipment for the
stringent filtration of water from the
Nile. Bread, too, was in short supply,
and at first we supplied Abu Simbel
with bread by air until another bakery
couid be built.
But gradually we completed the
construction of the village of Ram-
eses Sil at Abu Simbel, today the love-
liest community in the area of the lake
of the High Dam. It now comprises
hotels and rest-houses ; and it has elec-
tricity and pure water, a swimming
pool, tennis courts, a hospital, a mos-
que, a telegraph and post-office a
wireless station, paved roads and a
police post. Beautiful gardens have
been planted in which grow fruit trees
and vegetables, and now that an air-
port has been built, Abu Simbel has a
direct air link with Aswan.
Through the Nubian campaign,
Unesco has been able to achieve more
than one of its important goals. First-
! y, in undertaking to save the ancient
cultural heritage of Nubia, it has link-
ed the past to the present. Secondly,
it has linked the world with one idea,
bringing nations and peoples closer
and binding them together with this
strong and unique tie. Finally, Unesco
has proved that differences between
nations could be eliminated if only the
world as a whole were to co-operate
in constructive work, instead of squan-
dering its energies and resources on
disputes and wars based only on nar-
row se ! f-interest. «
5 MILLION
DOLLARS
NEEDED
TO SAVE
PHILAE
MONUMENTS
Qi. < :;()"oLL
aQ.
Xû.
0
a
Õ. < :;a
]]>
</page>
<page number="63">
<![CDATA[
Unesco has launched an international appeal to save the
great temples on the island of Philae in Egypt. $1 million is
needed by July 1, 1972, to start the rescue operation and
$5 million by 1976. The monuments of Philae-its temples,
colonnades and carvings-stand on an island submerged by
the Nile for most of the year. They will be irreparably lost
unless they are quickly dismantled and rebuilt on the nearby
island of Agilkia. The action to save Philae will crown a
remarkable achievement in cultural co-operation and will
be the last phase of the international campaign launched by
Unesco to save the monuments of Nubia from oblivion
beneath the waters of the Aswan High Dam. The cost of
"operation Philae", from dismantling to reconstruction, will
total $13. 700, 000, one-third of which will be provided by
the UAR. By June 1971, in response to Unesco's appeal,
nearly $1, 600, 000 had been pledged by 17 countries-Belgium,
Cambodia, Cuba, Cyprus, France, Fed. Rep. of Germany,
Ghana, India, Italy, Japan, Kuwait, Lebanon, Malta, Nether-
lands, Spain, Sudan and the United Kingdom-and about
one-third of these contributions had been received. So that
this international cultural rescue operation can be success-
futtycompteted, Unesco's Director-General, Mr. René Maheu,
has renewed his appeal of November 1968 to governments,
institutions, foundations and individuals to contribute to its
final stage. Above, part of the great temple of the goddess
Isis on the island of Philae. On left is the colonnade of the
"mammisi", or"birth house"of Horus, son of Isis. The
image of the goddess Hathor, sustainer of life and mother
of the world, is carved on the capital of each column. Pho-
tograph was taken when the Nile waters were at their
lowest level. But the temples and their remarkable sculpture,
over 2, 000 years old, are not likely to resist much longer
their immersion for nearly nine months of the year in the
waters of the Nile. There is no time to lose...
]]>
</page>
<page number="64">
<![CDATA[
SOME FACTS
AND FIGURES
ABOUT UNESCO
 n 1951, when Unesco launched its major project for primary
éducation ir Latin America, the continent had 216, 000 primary
schools. T en years later there were 300, 000 schools and the
proportion of insufficientty qua ! ified teachers had faiten from 53 to
31 per cent. Some 1, 500 teacher-tratning cotieges were set up
during this period.
 More than 40, : iteacher : d :  : : Onrolled, 1961
and 191 tacher t college y Unes ecelv-
'"'"""port"',"Uo."','M 0... 1. _01 Fund
(UNDP). Over 16, 000 engineers and technicians graduated from
50 colleges and technical institutes rece ! ving Unesco and UNDP
^ait. 1960 and 910, no n 161 mentpro proj ation, and sting ons,
were y U NDP over the
countriesconeerned.
 Unesco wery near ! y came into existence without an *S"in its
name. h as first conceed as Uneco-thé United Nattons Educ-
ationa) and Ctturat Organization. Thé person who acttwety and
successMty promoted thé *S* was tKe distinguished U, S. poet
Archibatd MacLetsh. Thé first Director-Generai, Jutian Huxtey, was
a scientfst.
 Nearty 900 primary scheois, seconda<y schoois and teacher train-
ing cotteges m over 60 countries now participate in Unesco's
Associated Schoots Protect for éducation in internationai under-
standing.) t seeks to devetop internatiSna) co-operation and to
promote tcnowtedge of wortd affatrs, of dMerent cuttures and ways
 e ned.
· v p l -into `
It was ; ivetf e üons 
l _Culturat E) rganiza#ion.-The san iv l
futty fre ° "was h l . , -
i flacLeish,'The l l l
r i '
·  o l  ; r l
ll in ù
Associated Schools Projeet for education in international undar-
, 1 l a'nai u '
knavledge l 'af airs, iff ent l '
of life, and of human rights.
 During the first United Nations Devetopment Decade, 1960-1910,
the number ef radio transmitters rosé by 25% in Latin America
and doubled in Asia and Europe. Thé number of receivers
increased even more. Newspaper ci c n almost doubled in
Asia, while thé number of countries with television transmitters
quadrupted in Africa, doublet in Asia and tripled in Latin America.
! During the t960s, Unesco's aid to Asian'development amounted
to around $80 million. The aid from a1f tJ. N, sources, including
IJnesco, to Asïan Education, Science and'Culture ; amounted to
$300 miltian : Assistance fram all sources, governmental artd non-
governmental ; public and püvate, multilateral and bitateral ; amaunt-
ed to $150 million per yeaf towards the end of the 196üs.-
Between 1948 and over 20, 000 people beneHted from
fellowships vel awards : about 11, 000 eceived
fellowships and study grants (11% went to women). Over 800 tra-
vel grants were awarded to individuals (553 to youth leaders,
150 to workers, 21 to worker education leaders, 99 to leaders of
women's organizations and 35 to teachers and students in adult
education). An additional 923 awards went to groups of workers.
About 11, 000 persons benefited from these group awards.
 Twenty per cent of Unesco fettowships and study grants were
awarded to Africa, 9% to Arab States, 27% to Asia and Oceania,
16% to Europe and Northern America and 28% to Latin America
and the Caribbean, in the fields of : education (43%), natural scien-
ces, engineering and technology (31 %), asocial sciences, human
sciences and culture (14%) and communication (12%).
 A major survey of the cultures of Latin America is now almost
complete after five years of research and international studies.
This Unesco survey, to be published this year, covers literature,
64 art, theatre, architecture, music and town-ptanning and their inter-
faction on today's rapidly changing soc ! ety.
 The Centre for Higher Studies in Journatism at the University
of Quito, Ecuador, set up with Unesco aid in 1959, now plays a
major rote in the training of journalists and other mass media
speciaUsts in Latin America.
 Unesco has compiled a catalogue of over 22, 000 works of art
and has made an inventory of about 600 palaces and churches
to be preserved and restored as part of the campaign for safe-
guarding Venice.
 : Unesco has been carrying out a monumental survey of educ-
ation throughout the world. To date, four volumes with an average
of 1, 500 pages each have been pubtished covering primary,
secondary and higher education in Unesco's member states.
 More than three oui of eyery five of 1, 072 milli ? eoPle
in 18 Unesco Member States in Asia are under 25 years age.
An estimated million wðre enrolled 1967 in schools au ail
levers, compared with 111 mM ! ion in 1960, and schools enrolment
is increasing at the rate of nearly seven million a year.
-Since 1985, Un®sco has given 24 cauntries technïcai aid in
school construction. These schools pravide ptac®s fa about
1, 000 students in primay schools, secondary schools, higher
education institutes and primary teacher-training calleges..
 A Latin American Faculty of Social Sciences was established
in Santiago, Chite, in 19. h unescoE :  The Fa 1 now
an importa ontinental c for research and the 9 of
socioiogists, and hais expanded to cover political s es and
public administration.
 Unesco has contributed to thé preservation of famous sites and
monuments throughout the wortd. Among them are : the Parthenon,
Greece ; the sites and monuments of Cappadocia and the Izmir
region, Turkey ; the A {anta caves,) ndia ; thé historié s tes of Perse-
polis and Pasargardae, tran ; the ruins of Patmyra nd thé Krak
des Chevaliers, Syria ; the sites of Ctesiphon and Nineveh,) Iraq ;
the ruins of Baafbek, Lebanon ; the colossal statues of Easter
) s) and, Chite ; the Maya temple at Bonampak, Mexico ; and the
Abomey Royal Palaces, Dahomey. The first Unesco conservation
mission sent to safeguard monuments in danger went to Peru,
after the earthquake of 1950 which ! arge) y destroyed the historic
city of Cuzco.
 A regional Mass Communication Institute for English-speaking
African countries has been set up with Unesco's aid in Nairobi,
Kenya. Its aim is to stimulante the growth of information media in
Africa. For French-speaking countries Unesco has helped to create
a Mass Communication Institute at Dakar, Senegal, for the train-
ing and education of mass communication staff. n West Africa,
too, an Information Institute has been set up at the University of
Lagos, Nigeria, to train specialists in audio-visual techniques.
 Sales of Unesco Coupons, first launched 21 years ago to help
institutions and persons in soft"currency countries to buy educ-
ational and scientific materials from hard"currency countries.
passed the $100 million mark at the end of 1970. Asia teads in
sales of coupons (60 per cent of total), followed by Africa (25 per
cent) and Latin America (15 per cent).
 Unesco has aided thé création of a number of institutes of
African studies such as the Federal Linguistic and Cutturat Centre
in the Cameroon, the institutes of human sciences in Chad, Gabon
and Ma) i, thé institutes of African studies in the University of
Ghana, the University of East Africa, the University of Ibadan and
the University of Addis Ababa.
 tn August 1970, an unprecedented Unesco conference brought
the representatives of 88 nations to Venice to debate the problems
of cultural policies in the modern world. Nearly half the delegations
were led by Ministers of Cutture.
]]>
</page>
<page number="65">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
THE'MAOC'
OF MODERN CHEMISTRY
Sir,
As a reader for five years, 1 have
generally enjoyed your articles, but
1 feel that the choice of those in the
June 1971 issue on the"Magic of
Modern Chemistry"was not up to your
usual standard.
Broadly speaking, we have to accept
the increasing use of synthetic mater-
ials. Combined with natural fibres they
create extremely useful"alloys". But
used alone, synthetic fibres are not
conducive to bodily comfort, or comfort
of any kind. The stretch or spandex
fibres you mention have met with little
success and are now of minor industrial
importance.
This also applies to polyurethane
foam. Plenty of worthwhile products
are made from it, but we should avoid
using such porous resin materials to
excess. One need hardly recall the
recent firé that ravaged a French dance
hall, killing over 100 young people
when synthetic foam furnishings flared
up with terrifying speed and gave off
cyanogen gas.
As to the wider picture of the global
population explosion, with 7, 000 million
inhabitants predicted for the year 2000,
i fear the world will experience sa me
catastrophic famines before that time.
T 0 calculate that the world (thanks to
the so-caiied"green revotution"), can
feed a population of 7, 000 million strikes
me as a cold and matter-of-fact ap-
proach to the problem, bearing in mind
that this figure is merely the take-off
point for a rise to a population of 15, 000
million.
We should remember that the miracles
of this same"green revolution"cannot
be wrought unless sufficient energy is
produced (even to provide no more than
water for irrigation), and neither atomic
nor any other form of energy will be
producing this amount of power by the
time it is needed.
N. E. Borlaug, Nobel prizewinner and
"father"of the"green revolution", is
by no means convinced about the"magie"of chemistry, and has warned
against the dangers of an exploding
population. With equal honesty, scien-
tists who created the petr'oleum-based
synthetic proteins affirmed that their
discovery, though useful, can have no
radical effect unless the population
explosion is checked. And ocean farm-
ing can provide only a useful (though
perhaps rital) new food resource that
will be needed ! ong before thé worid
has 7, 000 million inhabitants.
Worshippers of modern chemistry
would be wei ! advised to display more
wisdom and caution in regard to many
modern problems. Among chose 1
would list : the social consequences of
developments in medical science (will
longevity and good health become a
privilege of the rich ?) ; conservation
and production of fresh, pure water
(here water economy and energy costs
will be determining factors) ; the
recovery of arid lands (there are few
parts of the world where marginal lands
can be recovered-as has been done
in Israel, for instance) and in trying
to achieve such resuits ! n thé savannah
or tropical forest regions, we run the
risk of creating deserts rather than new
food resources ; finally, the formidable
problems created by DDT.
Jean Pilisi
Paris, France
CHEMtCAL'FALL PUT'
Sir,
Having witnessed how the forest
lining the Danish Lillebelt strait recently
turned black like charcoal and ail thé
leaves curled up-overnight-due to the
occasional airing of the ammonia tanks
of a passing ship, it is disquieting to
see an industrial consultant open up
your June issue using such a sentence
as,"And yet, there are many who decry
chemistry as the cause of undesirable
qualities of modern life.  This blind-
folded technocrat evidently has less
sense of ecology than any country
housewife.
With pollution increasing over 20 per
cent per year since 1960, mainly due
to the marvels of the high-energy-
demanding and highly-polluting petro-
chemical and plastic resin industries,
w ! th a//fish dying out in virtually
hundreds of lakes is southern Norway
due to acid rain, and the number of
reindeer on Hardangervidda suddenly
dropping from 14, 000 to 5, 000 (DDT and
dieldrin etc. drifting with winds con-
centrate unusually fast in reindeer moss
and lichens), we have indeed realized
that the marvels of nature mean more
to human survival than the prestige of
the chemical industry.
Chemists have made our present
precarious position possible. Unless
they are now mobilized, under the
strict supervision of ecologists, to save
the biosphere they shall be more curs-
ed than blessed.
Ulf Christensen
Gloria Newton
Oslo, Norway
PERILS OF SYNTHETIC SHOES
Sir,
h your June 1971 issue on the
revolution wrought by modern chem-
istry, on page 7 a photo shows sheets
of shoes being produced from a mat-
eria ! that"duplicatas ! eather's'breath-
ability', and has more than a million
pores per square inch."
It makes my blood boil that"experts'
should be so ignorant about hygiene
of the feet. As a shoemaker 1 am in
direct contact with my customers who
are coming more and more to realize
how unhealthy it is to wear such shoes,
that cause excessive perspiration, ath-
lete's foot, bad circulation of the blood
and fallen arches.
i am not against synthetic products
which have satisfied innumerable needs.
But where the feet are concerned, 1
say No ! Indeed i am surprised that the
World Health Organization, which is
we) i aware of these dangers for the
feet, has taken no action, particularly
with regard to children who need
healthy shoes while they are growing
up.
If these children are to be the future
"pedestrians of the moon"they will
still need their feet, so we should see
to it that they are shod in leather, a
noble material and healthy for the feet.
Michel Suignet
Saint-Mandé, France
TALKING POINT
Sir,
The facts in your excellent magazine
are used in my weekly sessions with
colleagues and students and become
often a starting point for lively
discussions and deductions. Here are
three recent deductions summarized :
Your issue on"Man and Violence"
(August-September 1970) :
Violence by men, caused through
overcrowding or isolation can be
instantly redressed by forming small
social and study groups where indiv-
idualized but mutual communication is
possible.
The article by Boris Nikitin"Latent
Ta/ent..." (February 1971) :
The experiments by the Swedish
neurobiologist Holger Hiden which prove
that"Neurons deprived of physical
nourishment and stimulation cannot
produce albumin... and finally cause
atrophy of the brain"must be extended
from childhood a ! ! thé way to senior
citizenhood, where senility could be
prevented. Social activities are not suf-
ficient. Challenging intellectual and
emotional stimulation plus the right
(not refined) food must be provided.
Your issue on"The Public and Modern
Art" (March 1971) :
The Toronto research revealed"what
is commonplace on TV in the way of
violence and other distortions of life, is
not... equally acceptable... for painting
(by the average public)."The reason
could be that TV violence is often
moving toward a redeeming finale,
while the static, permanent depiction of
violence in art becomes unbearable.
Dr Herbert Rona
Salt Lake City, U. S. A.
THE MODERNISED MUSEUM :
. STREAMLINED DINOSAUR'1
Sir,
As an"insider"in the Museum
World, 1 found Duncan Cameron's arti-
c) e"Muséums for Moderns" (your
October 1970 issue) euphoric reading.
Mr. Cameron's article deserves the
highest praise for its very detailed pic-
ture of present trends in the world of
museums. Its sole defect was that
since the author wrote of many facets
of museology in the imperfect tense,
he may have given the impression to
the uninitiated that the facts he related
belonged to the past.
But is there really a country in the
world where things are just as the
writer describes them ? 1 don't know
of a single one, certainly not in Europe.
A few spectacular achievements, weil
CONTINUED NEXT PAGE
65
]]>
</page>
<page number="66">
<![CDATA[
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR (Continued)
known to the public, because heralded
with a fanfare of trumpets, tend to
make us forget that a large number of
museums (including some of interna-
tional standing) continue to exist in
conditions unworthy of our time.
Through lack of funds and lack of
personnel they are unable to fulfil the
role the public has the right to expect
of them. The art treasures they dis-
play (though often they cannot do so,
since some rooms are closed owing to
lack of staff) hide the penury behind
the façade.
We can only hope that what Mr. Cam-
eron describes m the present tense
wn ! become a reality in a not too
distant future.
George van Deuren
Antwerp, Belgium
Duncan Cameron replies :
1 must admit that wh en 1 speak of
museum practices as they have been,
of new trends and deve/opments and
perhaps even a"new look"in museum
operations, 1 am being more than an
optimist. It is certainly true in Canada
and the United States that a great many
museums, including some of the most
important ones, continue to opera te in
the same mode as they have for at
least the past 100 years.
Further, 1 am aware from observation
in North America that"modernization"
of many museums means nothing more
than the addition of a little streamlining,
a few bits of chrome, The intrusion of
some audio-visual"toys"and a high
pressure public relations campaign-the
addition of these to the same tired old
museum philosophy.
Several commentators on our mus-
eums and art galleries have asked the
question in recent years"Are we really
dinosaurs ?"/n genera/thé react/on to
this question has been to cry'No/",
and produce (at great expense) stream-
lined dinosaurs.
It would not be fair of course to say
that the need for the reform of the
museum as an institution in society has
gone unrecognized in North America.
The streamlining as described above
has been one reaction but another has
been the tendency to employ, in senior
museum posts, non-museum personnel.. It is becoming rather popular to appoint
bright young corporation executives as
museum directors and to bring in publi-
city specialists as directors of museum
education and extension. The assump-
tion here is not jus that the museum
profession is incapable of reforming
itself but further, that within the museum
profession the necessary expertise and
progressive thinking cannot be found.
Neither streamlined dinosaurs nor eager
amateurs are an answer.
It was implicit in my article that 1 be-
lieve a fundamental re-organization of
museums is necessary ; that the invo/ve-
ment of the museum's publics in
decision-ma king must become a reality.
But the abandonment of traditional
museums'functions, as in some of our
newer science centres and exhibition
centres, is to bring an end to process
and to concentrate only on product.
Quite cIearly it is only a matter of time
until the absence of process will create
a shortage if not an absence of pro-
duct.
tn contrast, some reactionary institu-
tions have chosen to ignore the poten-
tial for a new role for the museum in
society and have limited their efforts
solely to traditional museum functions
and museum scholarship without regard
for public service. How long the public
will accept the redistribution of tax
dollars to institutions following this
course of action remains to be seen.
We must find the balance between
'democratization and public service on
the one hand, and the moral obligations
of preservation and research for future
generations on the other.
Recalling my error in applying the
imperfect tense, 1 can only suggest that
we live in a most imperfect world
wherein our museums and art galleries
have far more to contribute than most
of us have ever dreamed.
TEACHING AIDS FOR THE DEAF
Sir,
After publishing a most interesting
article about teaching aids for blind
school-children in your May 1971 issue,
1 hope you will also find space to tell
us something about the problems of
teaching deaf school-children.
During International Education Year,
1970, the Municipality of Barcelona
built one of the world's most modern
schools equipped with ail the latest
pedagogical and electro-acoustic aids
for the education of deaf children.
1 think that this achievement deserves
a mention.
J. Perello
Medical Director
Centro Municipal Fonoaudiologico
Barcelona, Spain
17TH CH) LD) N THE FAMILY
Sir,
1 read the"Unesco Courier"with
gréât interest, and was surprised to
find an obvious error in the February
1971 issue, in the article by Boris
Nikitin on latent talent in children, which
lists a number of famous men who
were 17th children in their families.
1 am sure that there is at least one
error : Heine, for example {lié Goethe),
was a first-born child and was certainly
not one of a family of 17 children,
and 1 doubt very much whether the
others mentioned were each the
17th child in the family.
Geneviève Bianquis
Dijon, France
Our reader is correct. Due to the
transposition of a full stop and a
comma. the passage in question stated :
"Out of 73 worM-ramous geniuses and
ta/ented persons, on/y four were first-
born chi/dren. Mi/ton, Leonardo da
Vinci, Heine, Anton Rubinstein, Ben-
jamin Franklin and Mende/eyev were
each the 77th chi/d in the family..."
/t shou/d hâve read :"... on/y four were
first-born chi/dren, Mi/ton, Leonardo da
Vinci, Heine, Anton Rubinstein. Ben-
jamin Frank/in and Mende/eyev were
each the 77th chi/d..."-Editor.
DISARMING SMILE...
Sir,
As outbreaks of violence become a
daily fact of life, the question arises :
how can we tame and contre ! man's
aggressiveness ? Thus, the survey of
scientific research on the problems of
aggressivity presented in your August-
September, 1970, issue gave this
number particular significance.
Clearly, man can be extremely
aggressive, perhaps even"a very dan-
gerous beast". But it is also true that
man is the only creature capable of
laughter. Laughter can be of great
service ; it can neutralize aggressive
impulses, and we should surely make
the most of this fact.
The noted Austrian zoologist Konrad
Lorenz has described, in"On Aggres-
s ! on", how an aggressive attitude can
be transformed into part of the ritual
of social politeness. He points out that,
in its original form, the human laugh
was a sign of appeasement and a form
of greeting."1 believe", writes Lorenz,
"that we should take humour more
seriously ; it can be a precious ally."
And therein lies a remedy that is
within reach of us ait, one that should
have a place in every family medicine
chest as an antidote to the fever of
aggressiveness.
Perhaps the"Unesco Courier"cou Id
one day devote an issue to the very
serious subject of humour.
Sonja Kipfer
Zollikofen, Switzerland
THE CH ! LD-ONLY
AN UNFINISHED ADULT ?
Sir,
The article"Latent talent-the ana-
gram that parents can solve", by Boris
Nikitin, in the February 1971 issue of
the"Unesco Courier", contained a
number of interesting and generally
undisputed findings of educational re-
search. But there were other points
1 would like to query.
"ln almost ail occupations", says
Mr. Nikitin,"mental and creative activ-
ity has a tendency to grow, and to grow
at an accelerated pace. Consequently,
development of creative faculties and
intellect is a paramount task in educ-
ation."
But is the basic concern of education
only to mould the child as early as
possible to the needs of his future
occupation ?
Again the author says," ! n our family
experiment... we wanted to fils thé
child's wor ! d with aH the things that
make up our'adult'world-real objects,
tools, materials, instruments and books."
Why are adults so anxious to project
their own world onto their children ?
Surely, children have their own inter-
ests (e. g. purposeless games) which
they should be allowed to enjoy. Why
do we grown-ups want to force on our
children our own world-the world of
utility, the world of co ! d, technica !
rationalism of the engineer ?
Ingo Knanp
engineer
Wettingen, Switzerland
u
,...
'"
.
E
"5
;.,
..
: ! !
"
<0
0.
..
Q
1
ui
u
z
< (
ft
z
UI
ouJ
I :
ä :
0.
2
z
< (
0.
a-
U
CI
Q
o
UI
CI
Ii
É
66
]]>
</page>
<page number="67">
<![CDATA[
N BIRTHRIGHT OF MAN
An anthology of texts from a ! ! penods and ail
continents showing how people have asserted
and claimed their human rights.
Cloth : £3. 00 $12. 00 35. 00 F
1 0 Unesco best-sellers
N STUDY ABROAD. INTERNATIONAL SCHOLARSHIPS AND COURSES
A students'guide to opportunities for study in over 120 countries.
50p. $1. 50 5. 50 F
M CATALOGUE OF REPRODUCTIONS OF PAINTINGS 1860-1969
A wide international selection of reproductions of world-famous works.
i2. 55 $8. 50 34. 00 F
N TEACHING AND LEARNING. AN INTRODUCTION TO NEW METHODS
AND RESOURCES l HIGHER EDUCATION
i1. 05 $3. 50 14. 00 F
N SOURCE BOOK FOR SCIENCE TEACHING
Revised and enlarged edition of a"do-it-yourself"science book
Cloth : i1. 65 $5. 50 22. 00 F Paperback : i1. 05 $3. 50 14. 00 F
N UNESCO STATISTICAL YEARBOOK 1970
Statistics on population, education, TV, cinema, radio, science and technology,
newspapers, libraries, books and museums in over 200 countries.
Cloth : i10. 50 $35. 00 140. 00 F Paperback : i8. 70 $29. 00 116. 00 F
N INDUSTRIALIZATION AND SOCIETY
Studies on the crucial effects of industrialization and technological
development on social change.
Cloth : i3. 30 $11. 00 44. 00 F
M THE ARTS AND MAN
A world view of the r8le and functions of the arts in society.
Cloth : i4. 10 $12. 95 48. 00 F
t USE AND CONSERVATION OF THE BIOSPHERE
An outstanding study of man's exploitation of nature and his environment.
i1. 80 $6. 00 24. 00 F
N STUDENTS AS LINKS BETWEEN CULTURES
A broad survey of cross-cultural links based on a special Unesco study.
f3. 00 $10. 00 40. 00 F
Where to renew your subscription
and order other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of dittributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one lan, ua, e.
*
- AUSTRALIA. Publications : Educational Supplies Pty.
Ltd., P. O. Box 33, Brookvale, 2100, NSW ; Periodicals :
Dominie Pty. Limited, Box 33, Post Office, Brookvale 21 00,
NSW. Sub-agenc. United Nations Association of Australia,
Victorian Division, 4th F ! oor, Askew House, 364
Lonsdale St., Melbourne (Victoria), 3000 ($ 2. 75).
- AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme & C'.,
Arbeitgasse 1-7, 1051, Vienna. (AS 82).-BELGIUM.
Jean de Lannoy, 112, rue du Trône, Brussels 5. CCP
3380. 00.-BURMA. Trade Corporation N' (9), 550-
552 Merchant Street, Rangoon.-CANADA. Information
Canada, Ottawa, Ont. ($ 4, 00).-CEYLON. Lake House
Bookshop, Sir Chittampahm Gardiner rlawata, P. O. B. 244
Colombo, 2. (Rs 12. 50).-CH) NA. Worid Book Co.
Ltd., 99 Chungking South Rd., Section 1, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).-CYPRUS."MAM", Archbishop
Makarios 3rd Avenue, P. O. Box 1722, Nicosia.-
CZECHOSLOVAK) A. S. N. T. L., Spalena 51, Prague 1
(permanent display) ; Zahranicni Hteratura 11 Soukenicka
Prague 1. For ! ovakiaoniy :Nakladatelstvo Alfa ; Hurba-
novo nam. 6 Bratislava.-DEN MARK. Ejnar Munksgaard
Ltd., 6, Norregade, 1165, Copenhagen K. (Dan. Kr. 19. 00).
- ETHIOPIA. National Commission for Unesco, P. O.
Box 2996, Addis Ababa.-FINLAND, Akateeminen
Kirjakauppa, 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki (Fmk. 11. 90).-
FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, place de Fontenoy,
Paris-7'. C. C. P. 12598-48 (12 F).-GERMANY. Ai !
pubiications : Verlan Dokumentation, Postfach 148.
faiserstrasse 13, 8023 Munchen-Pullach. For the
Unesco Kurier (German ed only) Bahrenfelder-
Chaussee 160, Hambourg-Bahrenfeld, C. C. P. 276650
(DM 12).-GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
- GREECE, Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28, rue du Stade,
Athens ; Librairie Eteftheroudakis. Nikkis 4, Athens.-
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 13-1 S, Lock Road,
Kowloon.-HUNGARY. Akadémiai. Könyvesbolt.
Voici u. 22, Budapest V ; A. K. V. Konyvtarosok Boltja,
Népkôzc5rsasfg utja 16, Budapest VI.-ICELAND.
Snaebjôrn Jonsson & Co., H. F., Hafnarstraeti 9,Reykjavik.
- INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Nicol Road, Ballard.
Estate, Bombay 1 ; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 1 3 ;
36a, Mount Road, Madras 2 ; 3/5 Asaf A ! i Road, New
Delhi 1 ; Sub-Depots : Oxford Book & Stacionery Co.
17 Park Street, Calcutta 16 and Scindia House, New
Delhi ; Publications Section, Ministry of Education and
Youth Services, 72 Theatre Communication Building,
Connaught Place New Delhi 1. (Rs. 1 3. 50).-) NDONE-
SIA. Indira P. T., Djl. Dr. Sam Ratulangie 37, Djakarta.
- ! RAN. franian Nationai Commission for Unesco, 1/154
avenue Roosevek, B. P. 1533, Teheran.-IRAQ. McKen-
niés Bookshop, AI-Rashid Street, Baghdad ; University
Bookstore, University of Baghdad, P. O. Box 75, Baghdad.
- IRELAND. The National Press, 2, Wellington Road,
Ballsbridge, Dublin, 4.-ISRAEL. Emmanuel Brown, for-
merly Blumstein's Bookscores, 35 Allenby Road and 48,
Nahlat Benjamin Street. Tel-Aviv (IL. 1 5).-JAWAtCA.
Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P. O. Box 366, 101 Water
Lane, Kingston.-J A PAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd.,
P. O. Box 5050. Tokyo International 100-31.-
KENYA. The E. S. A. Ltd., P. O. Box 30167, Nairobi.
- KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco
P. O. Box Central 64, Seoul.-KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co., Ltd., P. O. Box 2942, Kuwait.-LIBERIA.
Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P. O. Box 286.
Monrovia.-LIBYA. Agency for Development of
Publication & Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli.-
LUXEMBURG. Librairie Paul Bruck, 22, Grand-Rue,
Luxembourg (F. L. 170).-MALAYSIA. Federal Publica-
tions Sdn Bhd., Balai Berita, 31, Jalan Riong, Kuala Lum-
pur.-MAL TA. Sapien..'s Library, 26 Kingsway, Vallet-
ta.-MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon
Street, Port-Louis.-MONACO. British Library, 30,
Bld des Moulins, Monte-Carlo.-NETHERLANDS.
N. V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, the Hague.
(fil. 10).-NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. G. C. T.
Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.). N. V., Willemstad, Cura-
çao. N. A. (NA fi. 5. 25).-NEW ZEALAND. Govern-
menc Printing Office, Government Bookshops ac : Rutland
Street, P. O. Box 5344, Auckland ; 130, Oxford Terrace,
P. O. Box 1 721, Christehurch ; Aima Street, P. O. Box 857
Hamilton ; Princes Street. P. O. Box 1104, Dunedin ;
MulgraveStreet, Private Bag, Wellington (S 2. 15).-
NORWAY. A)) publications : Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers) Karl Johansgate 43, Oslo 1. For Unesco
Courier on) y : A. S. Narvesens Litteraturjeneste, Box
6125, Oslo 6 (K. 2. 75).-PAKISTAN. The West-
Pak Publishing Co. Ltd., Unesco Publication House, P. O.
Box 374 G. P. O. ; Lahore ; Showrooms : Urdu Bazar,
Lahore, and 57-58 Murree, Highway, G/6-1, Islamabad.
Pakistan Publications Bookshop, Sarwar Road, Rawalpindi ;
Paribagh, Dacca.-PHILIPPINES. The Modern Book
Co., 926. Rizal Avenue, P. O. Box 632, Manila D-404.-
POLAND. A publication : ORWN PAN Palac Kultury i
Nauki, Warsaw. For thé Unesco Courier ooly : RU CH, ul.
Wronia, 23, Warsaw 10.-PORTUGAL. Dias & Andra-
de Lda, Livraria Portuga). rua de Carmo 70, Lisbon.
- SINGAPORE. Federal Publications Sdn Bhd., Times
House, River Valley Road, Singapore 9.-SOUTHERN
RHODESIA. Textbook5ales (PVT} Ltd., 67 Union Avenue,
Salisbury.-SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P. O. Box 1118,
Khartoum.-SWEDEN. AN publications : A/B C. E.
Friczes Kung). Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan, 2, Box 16356,
1 03 27, Stock-hotm 1 6. For the Unesco Courier : Svenska
FN. För-bundet, Vasagatan 1 5.) V 1 01 23. Stockholm 1
Postgiro 184692 (Kr. 18).-SWITZERLAND. A !)
publications : Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse, Zurich.
Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11,
C. C. P. 12-236 (Fr. S. 12.-)-TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop, P. O. B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam.-THAILAND.
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9. Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
(37. 50 baht).-TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 4691stiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul.-UGANDA. Uganda Book-
shop, P. O. Box 145, Kampala.-SOUTH AFRICA.
A) ! pubtications : Van Schaik's Bookstore (Pcy). Ltd.,
Libri Building, Church Street, P. O. Box 724, Pretoria.
For the Unesco Courier (single copies) on) y : Central
News Agency P. O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.-UNI-
TED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT). Librairie Kasr
Et Nil, 38, rue Kasr Ei Nil, Cairo. Sub-agent : La Re-
naissance d'Egypte. 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha, Cairo.-UNITED
KINGDOM. H. M. Stationery Officie, P. O. Box 569,
London, S. E.)., and Government Bookshops in London,
Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham,
Bristol (E1)- UNtTED STATES. Unesco Publica-
tions, Center. P. O. Box 433. New York, N. Y. 10016
($ 5).-U. S. S. R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, Moscow,
G-200.-YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga, Te-
razije, 27. Belgrade ; Drzavna Zaluzba S) oveni)'e Mestni
Trg. 26, Ltubtjana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="68">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
</document>
