<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="060487eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
May 1965 (18th year) U.K.: 1/6 stg. - Canada: 30 cents- France: 1 F
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
á&
w
2 V
fx r
Man in noiselessness
Standing on a metal screen in a huge acoustical
chamber, but seeming to be suspended in mid-air, a
researcher listens to sounds " manipulated " by
delicate instruments, then reports what he hears.
Thick fibreglass wedges on walls make room sound¬
proof and eliminate echoes. In such specialized labo¬
ratories scientists are designing improved equipment
for the vast and still expanding network of world
communications. See page 4 for the story of the
International Telecommunications Union, now cele¬
brating its foundation one hundred years ago.
USIS
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
f A * WIWOOW OHM ON THI WO
Couriei
MAY 1965 - 18TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
Published monthly by UNESCO,
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7e.
Annual subscription rates: 15/-stg. ; $3.00
(Canada) ; 10 French Francs or equivalent;
2years:27/-stg.; 18 F. Single copies 1/6-stg.;
30 cents ; 1 F.
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except
in July and August when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German, Arabic,
Japanese and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed
by H.M. Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from
THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returned unless accompanied by an international reply
coupon covering postage. Signed articles express the
opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
tna opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE
UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in The Read¬
ers' Guide to Periodical Literature published by
H. W. Wilson Co.. New York.
37
38
TELECOMMUNICATIONS: 1865-1965
A century of international co-operation
FROM TELEPHONE TO TELLY-PHONE
Echoes from the astonishing world of telecommunications
THE BOMBAY INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY
(I) ENGINEERS IN THE NEW INDIA
by Vadim A. Javoronkov
(II) CONVERSATIONS ON A CAMPUS
by Daniel Behrman
CARAVAGGIO
The rehabilitation of a long-disdained genius
CARAVAGGIO IN FULL COLOUR
THE ANCIENT WORLD
Vol. 2 of the Unesco-sponsored History of Mankind
(I) ANCESTORS OF THE BALL-POINT PEN
by Luigi Pareti
(II) THE WOODEN OX (FIRST WHEELBARROW)
by Luciano Petech
(lll)THE BIRTH OF FUNCTIONAL ARCHITECTURE
by M.W. Frederiksen
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris T>, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant to the Editor-in-Chief
Lucio Attinelli
Managing Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton (Paris)
Jane Albert Hesse (Paris)
Arturo Despouey (Paris)
Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Hans Rieben. (Berne)
Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Maria Remiddi (Rome)
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Japanese Edition
Italian Edition :
Illustrations : Phyllis Feldkamp
Research : Olga Rodel
Layout & Design : Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence shouldbe addressedto the Editor-in-Chief.
Cover photo
To train the engineers needed by its
fast-developing industries, India has
set up a network of regional technolo¬
gical institutes. Here, at the Institute
of Technology in Bombay, created
with U.N. technical assistance through
Unesco, a student's experiment in the
physics laboratory is supervised by a
young woman assistant instructor
symbol of the new India of the
engineer (see article page 14).
© Paul Almasy, Paris
0NESc£>
<£CHIVE^,
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
With the launching of the communi¬
cations satellite "Early Bird " (right)
from Cape Kennedy, U.S.A., on
April 6, the world now has a " tele¬
phone exchange " in outer space.
The new satellite will also be used
for transmitting telegraph messages
and TV pictures above the Atlantic.
Capable of transmitting simultane¬
ously 240 two-way telephone conver¬
sations, " Early Bird " has now to be
tried out experimentally for two
months. " Early Bird " is on an equa¬
torial orbit at a height of 22,300
miles and keeps pace with the earth's
rotation, thus appearing to hover at
the same spot. The telecommunica¬
tions revolution began a little over a
century ago with the electric telegraph.
To the world of the 1840s, the tele¬
graph with its lines alongside the
railway track (left) also seemed an
astounding invention at the time.
1865-1965 TELE
COMMUNICATIONS
A century
of international co-operation
4
he International Telecommunications Union (ITU),
oldest of the United Nations specialized agencies, is
celebrating its 100th birthday in 1965, designated by the United
Nations as International Co-operation Year. The ITU was born
as the International Telegraph Union, on May 17, 1865, when
the growing network of electric telegraph lines linking country
to country had shown the need for international agreement
on communication procedures and regulations. Thirty-five years
later the first radio transmissions opened up another new era
in telecommunication. Radio, broadcasting, television and other
technological achievements during the past fifty years have
all brought increasing responsibilities to the ITU. Today, as
the ITU enters its second century, the contributions it is
making to the development of space communications show that
it is already planning for the needs of tomorrow's world.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
USIS
It might seem surprising that the ITU already has a cen¬
tury of achievements in peaceful international co-operation
to its credit. Nothing, surely, could be more modern than
telecommunications, with telex and television, with radio
helping us to reach out into space and the prospect of
our telephone calls travelling along beams of light. And
yet perhaps this juxtaposition of old and new is not so
strange. For what after all is "telecommunication" ?
Human societies, as they developed and began to
master the concept of distance, worked out a number of
ingenious ways for communicating over the vast areas
which separated them. Mostly, messengers of one kind or
another were used. But there were also methods involving
direct sight and sound drums in the jungle, beacons along
the coast, smoke signals on the horizon. These methods,
picturesque to-day, were strictly practical solutions
devised by man's imagination for overcoming the obstacles
that distance placed in the way of his basic need to
communicate. They were the first real telecommunications.
From the early dawn of civilization until a little over
100 years ago man did not get much further than the
written message, the drum, the beacon and the smoke
signal in his efforts to communicate at long distance. One
of the last devices was an "optical telegraph" or sema¬
phore invented by Claude Chappe, a Frenchman, at the end
of the 18th century. Signal towers with movable arms were
set on hilltops a few kilometres apart. Messages spelt out
by different positions of the arms were read by telescope
from one tower to another and passed on. The system
worked quite fast on clear days but was useless at night
or in fog.
With the development of electricity in the first half of _
the 19th century, man's capacity for practical achievement J
was suddenly enlarged a hundredfold. Nowhere was this
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Left, in 1791, a French
engineer, Claude
Chappe, first demons¬
trates his visual tele¬
graph system. Signal
towers with movable
arms were set on
hilltops a few kilo¬
metres apart. Mes¬
sages spelt out by dif¬
ferent positions of
the arms were read
by telescope from one
tower to another and
passed on. When, in
1 852, Chappe's system
was finally superseded
by the system of
electrical telegraphy,
France was covered
by a network of 556
semaphore stations
stretching over 3,000
miles (3,800 kms).
Laying the first trans-
Atlantic cable. In July
1858 a British vessel,
H.M.A. Agamemnon
(shown here) and an
American ship, the
U.S.N.S. Niagara, link¬
ed cables in mid-At¬
lantic and set out for
their respective home
ports. Eight days
later, on August 5,
1858, the first trans-
Atlantictelegraph mes¬
sage was transmitted.
ITU photos
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
TELECOMMUNICATIONS (Cont'd)
When telegraph networks halted at frontiers
seen more dramatically than in the invention of the electric
telegraph, of which the first known line was operated in
1837 and the first public line opened by Samuel Morse
in 1844. Its possibilities for commerce, for the new rail¬
ways, in diplomacy, in personal crises aroused an im¬
mediate tide of enthusiasm which, by 1849, had carried the
telegraph networks of European countries up to national
frontiers. And that was the start of the problems which,
sixteen years later, called into- existence the ITU.
At first, for example, international telegrams had to be
written down on a piece of paper and carried across the
border by a messenger at each frontier they passed. Then
there was the question of dividing the charges of the tele¬
grams between the countries which carried them. These
and other problems, for the most part totally new in inter¬
national relations, finally led the Emperor Napoleon III in
1864 to invite the major countries of Europe to a conference
to bring uniformity into the international telegraph system.
It was in May of 1865 that the delegates of twenty. nations
assembled in Paris. Among the states represented were
Baden, Saxony, Württemberg and a single Norway-Sweden.
The Turkish delegation had come part of the way on horse¬
back. Great Britain had not been invited because its tele¬
graph services, unlike those of other European nations,
were still in private hands. Paris at the time was discussing
Jules Verne's latest book, "De la Terre à la Lune" (From the
Earth to the Moon) a subject of some practical importance
to an ITU Conference 98 years later.
The Convention that was signed on May 17, 1865 created
the International Telegraph Union and brought common
rules to Europe's international telegraph system. Uniform
tariff rates were agreed on (except, understandably, for the
easternmost regions of the Russian and Turkish Empires)
and the French gold franc was made the currency for the
payment of International accounts.
HIS historic conference was followed in 1868
by one in Vienna which took a decision of
almost equal importance for the history of international
organizations. It set up a headquarters with a Secretariat.
The headquarters, established in Berne as the Bureau of
the Union, was under the control of the Swiss Government
until 1947 and started of with a staff of three Swiss citizens.
Modest though this beginning may have been, the principle
was made clear for the future that international government
organizations need a home and servants.
Throughout the rest of the 19th century the Union pushed
purposefully ahead, holding a succession of larger and
larger conferences in the romantically-tinted capitals of a
now-forgotten Europe. It revised and redrafted the Inter¬
national Telegraph Regulations, sternly forbade telegrams
against public order or decency, tirelessly wrestled with
legal and financial problems, wondered whether the wide¬
spread use of private codes might not be imposing too
great a strain-on ordinary telegraphists. In 1885 it also took
to legislating internationally for the telephone which had
been launched by Alexander Graham Bell in 1876. It grew.
In 1895 and 1896, the first successful wireless transmis¬
sions, crowning decades of research and experiment,
brought about what is still the greatest revolution in the
history of telecommunications. The invention of radio, one
of the proudest conquests that science can point to, will
always be associated with such names as James Maxwell,
Heinrich Hertz, Oliver Lodge, Alexander Popov, Guglielmo
Marconi and Lee De Forest.
T first regarded purely as a radically advanced
form of telegraphy, radio spread across the inter¬
national scene even more rapidly than the parent invention,
for the first time bringing ships at sea within the reach of
telecommunications. It became clear with equal rapidity
that international regulations were needed.
One major problem was highlighted as early as 1902,
when Prince Henry of Prussia, returning across the Atlantic
from a visit to the United States, attempted to send a
courtesy message to President Theodore Roosevelt, only
to have it refused because the radio equipment on the ship
was of different type and nationality from that at the shore
station.
Partly as a result of this incident, the German Govern¬
ment called a preliminary radio conference in Berlin in 1903
which prepared the way for the Berlin Radio Conference
of 1906. The 1906 Conference drew up the first Inter¬
national Radio Regulations, incorporating the principle that
ship and coastal radio stations must accept messages from
each other and adopting the SOS distress signal.
The problem of ensuring effective radio communications
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
The "heroic age" of radio broadcasting. In the early
1920's a radio service for the general public began to
develop. This raised the problem of sharing out radio
frequencies so as to avoid interference between
stations still one of the ITU's vital responsibilities.
CSF, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
A NEW ERA : SPACEVISION
New tools and new techniques have taken telecommuni¬
cations into the space age. Experimental communication
satellites placed in orbit around the earth have re-transmitted
television programmes across the Atlantic and have opened
a new era in long-distance communication. Left, artist's
impression of two communication satellites, "Syncom"
(top) and "Telstar". Below, first U.S. satellite commu¬
nications ship. Huge cupola on upper deck is the Radome
housing radar and other communications equipment. Right,
tracking a spacecraft orbiting the earth. Spacecraft is pin¬
pointed by bright light on map. It has just passed over
Zanzibar on its 16th orbit. Tracking stations are shown
on map and the circles around them indicate their range.
Photos usis
.1 .
"1^
jklS¿i§a!\TE
w
^#m.
k~*rs?
'****r
"¡A
TELECOMMUNICATIONS (Cont'd)
8
i CLEUummunibMi luno ii*umuy
15 per cent of radio spectrum for outer space
at sea were far from solved, as was shown dramatically
in 1912 when the desperate operator of the sinking "Titanic"
was unable to communicate with a ship within rescue
distance simply because its operator had gone off-duty
for the night. But a start had nevertheless been made
toward solving them.
The next decade saw great progress in the development
of radio and then, in the early 1920's, a new kind of radio
service began broadcasting. All -this gave rise to a new
problem how to share out the radio frequencies over
which transmissions travel so as to avoid the otherwise
inevitable interference between stations.
Since the use of radio constantly grows, it is a problem
which has to go on being solved all the time, and now
to-day, four decades and many conferences later, the inter¬
national responsibility for radio frequencies remains one of
the Union's heaviest and most vital jobs. The first move
was made at the Washington Radio Conference of 1927
which proceeded by allocating bands of frequencies to all
of the different radio services including maritime and
broadcasting.
In 1932, at Madrid, the organization took the formal
step of changing its name to the International Telecommu¬
nication Union, thereby embracing in its title the full range
of its new responsibilities. And indeed radio was bringing
in a new communication age. The 1930s saw the develop¬
ment of both television and radar. In the 1940s the speed
of the technological advance became more rapid. Wartime
broadcasting also made the world vividly aware that fre¬
quencies are free of frontiers. It was not hard to see that
much wider international agreement on radio would be
needed in the future.
Thus, two ITU Conferences met in Atlantic City in 1947
with the aims of magnifying and modernizing the Union.
Under an agreement with the United Nations, the ITU
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
'HIM
. »J '.%"!-
mm
;*-s?fe;'
M . :.-
k* .»»«Uf #
became a specialized agency and its headquarters were
transferred from Berne to- the traditionally international
atmosphere of Geneva.
As a result of decisions taken at Atlantic City, ITU head¬
quarters now harbour the staff of its four permanent organs
the General Secretariat, the International Frequency Re¬
gistration Board and two International Consultative Commit¬
tees (for radio and for telegraphy and telephony).
The advent of the Space Age has thrown the ITU a
new challenge, since man's exploration- of outer space
depends on radio. To meet the new demand, the Union
held a special world Space Radiocommunication Conference
in Geneva in 1963, at which more than 6,000 megacycles
were allocated for outer space (roughly speaking, 15 per
cent of the entire radio frequency spectrum).
Thus, this period of a hundred years, which began
with those who wanted to hear faster from abroad, has
been rounded off with those who want to listen closer
to the stars.
A hundred years of international co-operation. It can
be seen in the' regulations which govern the operation
of telegraphy, telephony and radio around the world. It
can be seen in the acceptance by ITU member countries of
the radio frequency allocations which determine the assign¬
ments they themselves make to their own radio stations.
It can be seen in the work of the ITU Plan Committee
which is drawing the blue-print for a future world network
in which telephone subscribers will' be able to dial each
other from anywhere to anywhere. It can be seen in the
Union's Technical Co-operation programme which is train¬
ing the engineers of new countries in the newest of tech¬
niques. It can be seen in the simple fact that it is pos¬
sible to telephone to another country or listen to a foreign
radio programme.
A hundred years of international co-operation which has
helped to make possible the amazing scientific and eco¬
nomic progress of this last century and which has, in
the quiet succession of its practical achievements, estab¬
lished the Union as a prototype of the sane collective
future that we seek.
In celebration of its centenary, the International Tele- Q
communication Union, in Geneva, is publishing a special **
book on the story of communications, "From Semaphore to
Satellite', by Dr. Anthony R. Michaelis.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
FROM TELEPHONE
TO TELLY-PHONE
Echoes from the
astonishing world of
telecommunications
ITU Chicago, 1893. At the scene of an accident a policeman calls
for assistance from one of the newly-installed phone booths.
10
Whose call
gets priority ?
The ITU Telephone Regula¬
tions lay down the following
priority for telephone calls:
1. Distress calls on land, sea
or in the air, and World
Health Organization calls
concerning epidemics.
2. Certain United Nations
calls.
3. Lightning Service Calls
(restoration of disrupted
telephone services).
4. Lightning Government
Calls.
5. Lightning Private Calls
(triple charge).
6. Urgent Calls (Government,
service and private, in that
order) charged at double
the normal rate.
7. Ordinary Calls.
SOS from
the cosmos
The first conference to allo¬
cate frequency bands for space
radiocommunication was organiz¬
ed by the ITU in Geneva in
1963. The conference recog¬
nized that flights by space vehi¬
cles" or manned satellites were
likely to increase and that the
search for and rescue of the
occupants and recovery of the
vehicles presented problems
similar to those of ships and air¬
craft in distress. It selected the
frequency of 20 007 kc/s for
Though they face each other across a table these two men could be sitting
thousands of miles apart to demonstrate the new Picturephone the tele¬
phone of tomorrow. Man sitting across the table uses a conventional
handset. Man in foreground uses speakerphone which picks up his voice
by microphone. and lets him hear by loudspeaker. Sending and receiving
equipment is in table control unit, used for calls and to control video screen.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
search and rescue to augment
those already designated for
distress. It also agreed that the
conventional international dis¬
tress signal of ships and aircraft
(SOS in radiotelegraphy and
MAYDAY in radiotelephony)
should also apply for' the time
being to space vehicles.
Our 170 million
telephones
In 1954 there were 90 million
telephones in the world. Today
there are over 170 million. By
the year 2000 there will probably
be 600 million. Thus the idea
of a global telecommunication
network is now becoming a real¬
ity. To deal with the immense
problems of numbering, switch¬
ing, signalling and transmis¬
sion and to estimate the likely
growth of international traffic
and to arrange its handling and
routing, the ITU has set up a
World Telecommunication Plan
Committee. The ITU is the
world forum for discussions on
telecommunication matters, but
the operation of international
links is the concern of nation¬
al administrations and private
companies.
300.000 km/sec
is still too slow
In communications with dis¬
tant satellites (or stars) the
propagation time of radio waves
(300,000 km/sec) is of major
importance. If a relay satellite
is used for voice transmissions,
a delay of almost three-tenths of
a second occurs between the
time of speaking and the recep¬
tion of the words. In an earth-
moon link the delay is approxi¬
mately 1.3 seconds. These de¬
lays in transmission are doubled
for two-way communication.
Fortunately there are now tech¬
niques to counteract and mini¬
mize these difficulties.
usis
Dialing anywhere
in the world
The cornerstone of the future
world-wide automatic and semi¬
automatic telephone service is a
numbering plan designed to take
care of estimated telephone
development beyond the year
2000.
The plan groups ITU member
countries into eight regional
zones and allots each country
a telephone number, the first
digit of which is the number of
its zone. These zone numbers
are: North America (1); Africa
(2); Europe (3-4); South Amer¬
ica (5). South Pacific (6); U.S.S.R.
(7); North Pacific (8); Far
East and Middle East (9). The
figure 0 is reserved as a spare
code.
To compose a complete world
number a subscriber would have
to dial between 13 and 15 digits.
For example, anyone wishing
to call ITU Headquarters in
Geneva from outside Switzer¬
land would have to dial the
following number: first the
world access code number that
connects him to his own coun¬
try's international exchange (two
or three digits); 41 (code of
country being called); 022 (Gene¬
va); 34.70.00 (ITU Headquarters
in Geneva).
Calls put through the world
network will pass through inter¬
national automatic exchanges
containing "memories" used to
store numbers being dialed.
Men to man
the networks
In many countries the effi¬
ciency of the telecommunication
network is not improving rapidly
enough to satisfy either national
or international needs. The ITU
has been working to remedy this
situation in co-operation with
the U.N. Expanded Programme
of Technical Assistance and the
Special Fund. Missions have
been sent to study special prob¬
lems and to advise govern¬
ments on communication deve¬
lopment. The ITU has organiz¬
ed training courses, sponsored
fellowships and seminars and
has supplied training and dem¬
onstration equipment. Thir¬
teen ITU-Special Fund telecom¬
munication training centres are
now operating; four more are in
the planning stage, including
one in Thailand.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
Singapore - Hong Kong
Middle East
îAMi
Argentina
-TWFi
Algeria
New Zealand
©®o
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
TELEPHONE TO TELLY-PHONE (Cont'd)
12
Chatterbox
satellites
Nothing can be done in the use
of outer space without the help of
radio at present the sole link be¬
tween earth and satellites. Good com¬
munications are actually more essential
for space use than for maritime or
aeronautical services. No signals mean
no information and no way of knowing
what is happening aboard a satellite.
Reduced to silence a satellite be¬
comes a mere pebble in the cosmos.
Conversely a satellite that cannot be
made to stop transmitting may take
up one or several frequencies and
interfere with other transmissions. A
garrulous satellite can be a danger as
well as a bore.
Place for space on
the radio waves
Transmissions from spacecraft can
cover wide areas because of the
altitude and orbital periods of the
space vehicle. A satellite placed in
low orbit, for example, passes regu¬
larly over the same areas, depending
on the tilt of its path. Placed in equa¬
torial orbit at an altitude of about
37,500 kilometres, it "sees" 40% of
the earth's surface throughout the 24
hours of the day. Thus in these
zones space services must be alloted
frequencies that wi.ll not interfere with
transmissions by other services.
Listening for
a feeble voice
Communication between spacecraft
and the earth is affected by distance.
Power sources on board a satellite are
relatively limited which in turn affects
the range of its transmitter. ' Because
transmissions from satellites often
reach the earth as weak signals,
ground receiving stations need special
protection against interference that
could make messages from space
inaudible.
New dimension
in communications
The. growing number of spacecraft
being launched into orbit and the
development of space programmes in
many countries create increasing
demands for new frequency allotment.
Only international agreement can save
communications with outer space from
becoming the next victims of radio
spectrum congestion and also protect
existing services from interference.
With the launching of the first satel¬
lites the ITU took up the problems of
space communications. Its vast new,
responsibilities have been formally
recognized by the United Nations
which has called the attention of all
member states "to the importance of
the action taken by the International
Telecommunications Union in the
peaceful uses of outer space."
y
'S-
TUNED IN TO OUTER SPACE. In this striking photograph of the
Paris Observatory's radio telescope at Nançay, France, stars
formed the myriads of white tracks as the earth turned during
the three-hour time exposure. At the centre of the circles is
the Pole Star. Radio telescopes are used by scientists to study
radio waves from outer space in the new science of radio as¬
tronomy. Since the first artificial satellites were launched in 1957
radio telescopes have also been used to track satellite flights,
because of the sensitivity and precision of their giant antenna.
CSF - René Bouillot, France
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
p>^flr;^r/^
' S
~^*%
\
/P*
^gf
>7' -.liv
\
fi» s
w^" à I "
.
* y
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
ENGINEERS IN THE
14
The Bombay
Institute
of
Technology
HE Republic of India needs thousands of
technicians for the many industries now deve¬
loping all over this huge sub-continent. To try to
meet part of these enormous needs the Indian Govern¬
ment has set up five regional technological institutes. One
of these top-level engineering schools is the Indian Institute
of Technology, Bombay (1).
As part of its technical assistance programme, Unesco
has given India large-scale aid in setting up the Bombay
institute. In 1955, an agreement was signed to enable
Unesco to use a contribution in roubles by the Union of
Soviet Socialist Republics to the United Nations Technical
Assistance Fund to aid the institute. It was foreseen that
(1) Editor's note: India's other technological Institutes have been
set up at Kharagpur (with aid from U.S.A. and U.K. and U.N.
technical assistance through Unesco); at Delhi (with aid from
U.K.); at Kanpur (with aid from a consortium of U.S. univer¬
sities) and at Madras (with aid from the Federal Republic of
Germany).
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
í
>
/
The administration building of the Bombay Institute of Technology (above) dominating
the campus of this engineering school was designed by the Indian architect, G.M. Bhuta.
The severe lines of reinforced concrete construction are softened by elements of traditio¬
nal Indian style. Only seven years ago the site was covered by jungle vegetation. Left,
one of the two vast reading rooms of the central library, which has over 60,000 books.
Photos Unesco - Boucas
NEW INDIA
by Vadim A. Javoronkov
aid amounting to $3.5 million would be provided over
five years, but assistance has actually amounted to over
$4.5 million. In addition, the Soviet Union has donated
equipment worth three million old roubles. On its side,
India has spent an estimated $10 million on the institute,
more than doubling the international aid received.
Soviet specialists have helped the Indian Ministry of
Education in working out a project for the institute, includ¬
ing workshops and laboratories. The Indian Government
undertook the full task of building the institute and Unesco
provided equipment for the main laboratories and workshops
and helped to organize academic and scientific activities.
From these combined efforts a university city has sprung
up on the shores of Lake Powai, in an area where signs
still warn swimmers of the danger of crocodiles. The
institute is located 18 miles from the heart of Bombay
on a site that only seven years ago was a jungle wil¬
derness.
Building operations were already in progress when India's
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
BOMBAY INSTITUTE (Cont'd)
Eight faculties, 2,000 students
Prime Minister, Jawharlal Nehru, laid the foundation stone
of the main administration building on March 10, 1959.
But as the need for engineers was so great the institute
had not waited for buildings to be completed. The first
students were enrolled in 1958 and in July of that year
the first classes were started in temporary premises in
Bombay.
The installations at Powai are now an impressive sight.
The dominating feature of the new campus is the admin¬
istration building which combines the clearcut lines of
modern architecture with elements of the traditional Indian
style. Reinforced concrete slabs jut out to give protection
from the sun and án efficient ventilating system keeps
the interior cool and fresh.
Behind the administrative centre, covered passages giv¬
ing protection against blazing sun and tropical monsoon
rains link a series of buildings with striking sawtoothed
roofs: mechanical workshops and the laboratories of the
mechanical and metallurgical departments.
The institute has other impressive-looking installations.
A water tower, rising like a lighthouse above the campus,
stands alongside the hydraulic laboratory. In the heavy
machinery shop is a giant travelling crane. There is
also a thermal station which services the turbine laboratory.
Few other technical institutes, even the most modern, can
boast such a harmonious blending of light and space
and the latest technological equipment.
EQUALLY striking are the architectural forms of
a conference hall, seating 2,000 people, which
faces the main entrance of the institute. Through the palm
and mango groves between the foothills and the shores of
the lake gleam the dazzlingly white walls of the student
hostels. These provide separate rooms for all undergra¬
duate and postgraduate students, and each building has its
own dining hall, games room and reading room. The
hostels are set around a great sports field with a gymna¬
sium and stands for spectators. Track and field athletic
events, volley ball and hockey are among the most popular
of the student's sporting activities.
The central library is housed in a three-storey building.
It has two large reading rooms, each seating 250 persons,
and over 60,000 volumes, including India's largest collection
Unesco - G. Mull
«WBWNM
IMS
If VJSVft
it,
(Wj
tMSfci
mf
»j». a"
^K<* *w, <*.amm¥,s i
a^llllftlk
? rmamnmcumz
&aaaaaaa«
»SI
"'
9 Hid L-2ftU¿I « £
-
*
LB**
¿«if
Waif II
îarjaa
'I
Bit* s
mmmwxt
".- 9 Utu.
««
n rupinev. 'u%«I:
"aftaMi-*'
*i«fc'£i
MISM*
«in
taai
«ai
W
É
Mht
Left, post-graduate students operating an electron-microscope in
the metallurgical department of the Bombay institute. Supplied by the
U.S.S.R., under the U.N. - Unesco technical assistance programme, it
magnifies specimens 100,000 times. Above, Professor Y.N. Loladze,
a Soviet specialist in machine-building technology, head of the
Unesco mission in Bombay in 1962 and 1963. "The purpose of
the expert here," he once said, "is to work himself out of a job."
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
of Russian technical literature (5,000 works) from which
books are loaned out to other Indian institutions.
Members of the faculty and technical staffs will live
in small houses and in buildings comprising two and
four-room flats now under construction.
The university city has now a population of 6,000 and
as its numbers increase more and more buildings rise on
the campus. The speed of this development owes much
to the organizational skill and energy of the director
of the institute, Brigadier S.K. Bose, ably supported by his
second in command, Professor Kamooth, and the institute's
registrar, Mr. Nera. Brigadier Bose pays special attention
to the living conditions of teachers and students, and the-
results of his efforts can be seen in the increasingly fine
academic record of the institute.
The project for technical assistance to the Bombay
Institute was financed by Unesco from the Soviet contri¬
bution to the U.N. Expanded Programme of Technical Assis¬
tance. Deliveries of Soviet equipment paid for by these
funds include an electron microscope with a magnifying
power of 100,000, highly sensitive instruments for use
in electricity and physics, precision metal-cutting tools and
100 and 200-ton hydraulic presses. The long list of
equipment includes such diverse items as an automated
rolling mill, an oxygen station and refrigeration units, and
Photos Unesco - Boucas
a continuous metal teeming machine, closed circuit tele¬
vision and high frequency heating apparatus.
These modern devices and machines are used to train
junior students in the fundamentals of the technology
of metals (cutting, welding, casting, forging, etc.) and
to help senior students familiarize themselves with the
basic processes and operations in their chosen specialities.
This specialized equipment is provided on a lavish scale
and enables the institute to cover a broad spectrum
of research.
HE institute has reached a planned enrolment of
2,000: 1,600 undergraduate and 400 post¬
graduate students. It has eight departments: chemical
engineering, civil engineering, electrical engineering, mech¬
anical engineering, metallurgical engineering, physics,
mathematics and humanities.
Students complete a five-year course to gain a bachelor
of technology degree, and then go on to take a two-year
course for their master of science degree.
The institute now trains students in twenty-six major
specialities some of which are quite new to India. Their
training is in the hands of 170 Indian teachers and eight
CONT'D ON PAGE 33
The Bombay Institute of Technology is well
equipped with heavy machinery to give
practical training to the future engineers of '
India's rapidly developing industries. Right,
Unesco specialists. A.A. Cosmin (far right)
and V.A. Javoronkov (author of our article)
discuss training with staff members.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
The rehabilitation of a long-disdained genius
CARAVAGGIO
Portrait
of Caravaggio,
by Ottavio
Leoni
Marucelliana
Library. Florence
ARAVAGGIO, the 16th-century Italian artist,
now occupies a special place in the history
of art. Long considered as a minor artist, accorded only
the status of a painter of works "for the curiosity shop",
Caravaggio has now been rehabilitated. During the past
thirty years he has increasingly been recognized as one of
the revolutionary geniuses of Italian art. Today, art histo¬
rians trace, within the vast perspectives of world painting,
his influence on such masters as Velasquez, Vermeer and
Georges de la Tour.
Caravaggio was a key figure in the development of baro¬
que painting but, with the decline of this art style as tastes
and fashion changed, his works fell from favour and finally
into disrepute. By the end of the 19th century "Caravag-
gism" was being attacked as strongly by the "naturalists"
as by those who preferred academic art, though for quite
different reasons. It was restored to a worthy place in
the Pantheon of the world's art thanks largely to the efforts
of two Italian art critics, Roberto Longhi and Lionello
Venturi, in the first quarter of the twentieth century. Six
major Caravaggio exhibitions have been held in the past
14 years.
The ups and downs of Caravaggio's posthumous career
were in a way postscripts to his stormy, turbulent life
which, when it ended in 1610, seemed to have been mar¬
ked during most of its brief course by shocks and scandal.
There was so much about Caravaggio that was scandalous:
his wealth of talent, the excesses of his Bohemian mode
of life and, apart from his revolt against the aesthetic
standards of his time, his new and disturbing view of the
world, which so antagonized many of his contemporaries.
For he suddenly revealed human beings as nature has
made them and not as the classical art style then decreed.
The son of a mason, Caravaggio was born in 1573 in the
village of Caravaggio near Bergamo in northern Italy.
His real name was Michelangelo Merisi, but as was common
in his day, he later took the name of his birthplace.
When he was eleven years old he was apprenticed to
a painter from Bergamo, Simon Peterzano, who worked
for many years in Milan. Caravaggio was sixteen or
seventeen when he finally set off for Rome, then the
dominant artistic centre of Europe.
With the Renaissance, classicism in art was again in
favour, a fact of which the young Caravaggio took no heed
whatever. This is reflected in his early works, particularly
in one he painted in 1590 when he was seventeen. Every
detail of "Rest on the Flight to Egypt" reveals a taste for
naturalism and a lyrical affection for nature.
In Rome, Caravaggio worked in the studio of Cesare
d'Arpino, a celebrated artist and teacher. For his master's
patrons he painted fruit and flower subjects, but also from
his brush came minor masterpieces: "Boy with a Basket of
Fruit" and "The Young Bacchus".
CONT'D ON PAGE 23
Left, The Supper at Em-
maus (detail). Caravaggio
made several paintings of
the meeting between Christ
and his disciples at Emmaus.
This version is now in the
National Gallery, London.
Unesco Catalogue of Colour Reproductions
Colour page, opposite:
Detail from the Martyrdom of
St. Matthew. French Church
of St. Louis, Rome.
Centre colour pages:
Christ Calling St. Matthew.
French Church of St. Louis,
Rome.
Photos © Arts graphiques de la Cité. Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
1BJK.
Éaf
^H '
Bfl
yjWM
BBJBBJBJBBJBSBBJSBBB
BBBBBBBBBBBBl BJBJBJBJBJBJBJBJBJBBBJbbbbbI
gn
Kl
BBBBB
TBHI
an
Bfl
#
.-
1- . .gpgaE^a»SaB
"
H^bbbbbbbibbbbbbki
BBBBWäS^SS^l!
îe
mi
IMS-
PJ««B«««1
P5BBBBT
¡mm: r
"Mbbbs_
SbbBB
«JBJ
BBBBB
BBBflSr
BBBBBT
«BBT
! '
Jas Wm
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
V
IbbI
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
?m
y¡m
BBl
BBJ
BJB
is*
I
.
"rtSfí :
Ö
BBl
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
CARAVAGGIO (Cont'd)
'Angry young man'
of the Renaissance
A Roman prelate, Cardinal del Monte, now became inter¬
ested in the talented young artist, and commissioned from
him three paintings depicting the life of St. Matthew, for
the Contarelli Chapel of the Church of St. Louis, in Rome.
In these works, executed between 1597 and 1600, the
full measure of Caravaggio's genius was at last revealed.
By his incomparable treatment of contrasts, by suddenly
infusing deep shadows with pools and shafts of piercing
light, he gave his paintings a startling effect of movement.
In this dramatic chiaroscuro, figures and objects acquired
a new wealth; his brush conjured up a new dimension.
Caravaggio's first religious paintings caused a scandal.
People called them vulgar and were shocked because the
models were no longer the idealized types used by Cara¬
vaggio's predecessors. He had simply taken them
from among the ordinary people he met in the streets:
old women with faces marked by hardship and adversity,
fresh-faced adolescents, young men looking astonishingly
like today's "mods" and "rockers", innkeepers, ragged
wastrels. In Caravaggio's hands, refined-looking, evanes¬
cent Madonnas were transformed into sturdy peasant
women suckling infants, and saints became ordinary men.
The abrupt gesture, the suggestion of violence so dis¬
pleasing to delicate and refined tastes, the return to a
world of physical reality shorn of every artifice, all, never¬
theless, tell of a love of humanity that still has the power
to move us three centuries later. Perhaps Caravaggio's
great secret, the very source of his inner power, was his
compassion, his ability to feel the emotions of others, to
suffer with them. He was indeed an "angry young man"
of the Renaissance whose "rage for life", paradoxically,
concealed a terror of death that only showed clearly in
his final works.
What displeased Caravaggio's contemporaries far more
than the "tricks" with light and shade was the presence in
his paintings of such convincingly life-like figures, the
sudden intrusion into the sacred of the everyday, as in
the "Crucifixion of St. Peter" and the "Conversion of
St. Paul." Yet the noblemen of Rome went on buying his
paintings. Caravaggio was now famous, but still a contro¬
versial and often disparaged figure. His fellow painters
observed him closely, recognizing a novator.
Caravaggio haunted the ill-famed quarters of Rome. He
became involved in brawls and was haled before the courts.
In one of these fights he killed a man. At that moment all
Rome was talking about his painting, "Death of the Vir¬
gin" (today in the Louvre Museum). Caravaggio had had
the audacity to depict Mary as a coarse, vulgar street
woman. Some even hinted that he had used as his model
the corpse of a courtesan taken from the River Tiber.
Caravaggio was forced to flee from Rome after his fatal
brawl. He went to Naples, then to Malta where, in 1608, he
found an enlightened patron in the Grand Master of the
Order of Malta. He went on paintingand brawling. Leav¬
ing Malta he returned to Naples from where he began to
make his way back to Rome. But on reaching Port 'Ercole
he fell ill. Desperate and alone, he died at the age of 37.
In these last years he painted "The Beheading of St. Jean
the Baptist" (Malta), "The Entombment" (Syracuse) -and
"Resurrection of Lazarus," (Messina) three masterpieces
immersed in the light of tragedy, their figures enveloped in
the silence of the vast empty space that hangs over them.
Above, The Flight to Egypt (detail). Caravaggio
painted this work when he was 17. (Doria
Pamphili Gallery, Rome). Below, Narcissus at
the Fountain. (National Art Gallery, Barberini
Palace, Rome.)
Colour page, opposite:
St. John the Baptist. National Art
Gallery, Corsini Palace, Rome.
© Arts graphiques de la Cité, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
I
MIî
An ancient Chinese char¬
acter meaning " different".
HE Unesco Courier is pleased to announce the publication
this month of The Ancient World, Volume II of the six-tome
History of Mankind, produced under the auspices of Unesco.
The Ancient World (published thus far in English) tells the story of
the momentous years between 1200 B.C. and 500 A.D. In this period
came the rise of the great civilizations of China and India and of
Greece and Rome, and the early years of Christianity.
To prepare this volume, the Unesco-sponsored International Commis¬
sion for a History of the Scientific and Cultural Development of
Mankind, called on Professor Luigi Pareti of the University of Naples.
Professor Pareti, who died shortly after completing the work, was
assisted by Professor Paolo Brezzi of the University of Naples, who
wrote on the origins of Christianity, and Professor Luciano Petech of
the University of Rome, who was responsible for the chapters on the
civilizations of India, the Far East and Central Asia.
Volume I of the History of Mankind, dealing with prehistory and the
beginnings of civilization, was the work of two archaeologists of
world-wide reputation: Jacquetta Hawkes and Sir Leonard Woolley
(see The Unesco Courier, June 1963). The Ancient World picks up
the threads of their story and follows mankind along the road of
progress and civilization. What it offers as it moves through the
centuries is a global view of man's positive achievements: the evolu¬
tion of language, art, transport, medicine, trade, architecture, science
and religion.
As Mr. René Maheu, Director-General of Unesco, writes in the fore-
ward to this volume: "The ambition to write a universal history is a
very old one indeed. Many have tried their hand at it . . . not without
merit, nor without success. However, this History of Mankind parts
company with its predecessors on several essential points. In the
first place it deliberately confines itself to shedding light on one of
mankind's many aspects, its cultural and scientific development In
doing so it departs from the traditional approaches to the study of
history which, as we know, attach decisive importance to the political,
economic and even military factors. It offers itself as a corrective
to the ordinary view of man's past."
The story of man which fills the 1,200 pages of this new three-part
volume of the History of Mankind thus presents history in a different
perspective. It takes the reader on a journey to the places of Antiquity,
including China, Persia, India, Eturia, Egypt and Carthage. It describes,
for example, what it was like to belong to one of the constantly
shifting populations of the Steppe civilization, how the alphabet was
first codified, how man began to compose music, write poetry and
create works of art, how trade and industries developed.
The Ancient World is a vast and colourful mosaic whose ensemble
reveals, most significantly of all, the contributions made by different
peoples and regions to the cultural rise of mankind during nearly
2,000 years of history:
Medicine as practised in Greece by Democedes, Diogenes and the
father of medicine, Hippocrates
The first production of pottery, glass and enamel
The houses and towns of the Romans, so well planned that many
still exist
Ingenious inventions like the device used by the Chinese to
measure earthquakes in the first century A.D.
The evolution of democratic ideas and institutions in Greece and
Rome
Indian, Chinese and Arabic contributions to mathematics and astro¬
nomy ... to name but a few.
To offer readers a preview of this latest volume in a series of histor¬
ical works that have been termed, "an international publishing ven¬
ture of unparalleled importance," The Unesco Courier presents on
the following pages passages selected from The Ancient World.
This work is published in the United Kingdom by George Allen and
Unwin Ltd., London (Price £6 6 0), and in the U.S.A. by Harper and
Row Inc., New York ($15.50).
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Love letter or household
accounts? With her stylus,
this young Roman woman
makes a gesture characte¬
ristic of reflection. The
stylus, a sharpened reed
or a pointed Instrument of
bone or Ivory, was used
to scratch letters on soft
wax tablets like those held
by this woman. Tied
together by cords, these
tablets formed a small
note-book called a "co¬
dex." The Romans also
wrote on parchment and
on paper made from
papyrus pulp (Mural at
Pompeii. 70 A.D.).
© Handke, Historisches Bild¬
archiv, Bad Berneck, Federal
Republic of Germany.
fa *i\"
. - i
*i"
ANCESTORS OF THE BALL-POINT PEN
o RIGINALLY the Chinese wrote with a bamboo
reed sharpened and cut like a pen: the matter
written with this had to be of uniform thickness. On the
bones employed in divination characters were incised with
a metal point. But the writing-brush, although its invention
is traditionally ascribed to Meng-T'ien under the Ch'in
dynasty (third century B.C.), already existed in the twelfth
century. It is not only represented on a pictogram of Anyang,
but at least three bones and a potsherd carry characters
traced with a brush. So Meng-T'ien did no more than
perfect the shape and composition of an instrument which
was already in being.
Writing materials in the Middle Eastern and classical
worlds were very varied. One reason was that after the
invention and spread of alphabetic methods the use of
writing proportionately increased, and consequently also
demanded lower priced material even if it was more
perishable. Naturally the increase in written documents
and the lower price of writing material went hand-in-hand
with the increase in the number of readers.
We start, then, with writings carved with chisels or simi¬
lar Instruments on rocks or plates or stone and marble
by Luigi Pareti
stelae. They might also be cut on the fronts of buildings,
or on tablets of bronze, copper, lead, or precious metal,
and later on coins and weights; or again they could be
scratched or tooled on tablets and seals of unbaked clay
or terracotta. To these were now added other writings
achieved in diverse ways.
Some were traced with the stilus on smooth wooden
tablets, or on tablets smeared with white paint {tabulae
dealbatae) or coloured. Others were written with the
small reed called a "calamus", and with ink {atramentum),
on light and plastic material. Leaves of papyrus pulp, or
some similar substance, are an example mentioned by Pliny,
and there was writing on olive leaves (the petalism at
Syracuse for instance), on linen bandages (especially those
used as coverings for mummified corpses in Egypt), on
earthenware sherds {ostraka) and so on. Later on Phoeni¬
cian influence was particularly responsible for the use of
calf-skin for expensive documents; and sheepskin (Perga-
mena) came in from Pergamum in Asia Minor. Skins were
used for inscribing the ancient treaty between Rome and OC
Gabil and also for a cypher employed at Sparta: for the "
latter strips of skin were wrapped in a spiral on to a cylinder
of given size and then inscribed, in such way that they
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
THE ANCIENT WORLD (Cont'd)
Assyrian royal library of 30,000 tablets
26
could only be read if they were wrapped once more round
an identical cylinder (scutate).
In ancient Egypt it was already the custom, when one
wanted to write a complete document or a definitive part of
a work, to paste one pressed papyrus leaf (byblos) on to
another and so to construct long strips; these were wrapped
together into a roll (volumen) and kept in a store (thece).
Herodotus (II, 92) speaks, of this device, though he does
not tell us when Greece acquired it: probably it penetrated
to Ionia in the days of Polycrates of Samos in the sixth
century, and to the rest of Greece about 500. Where tablets
or smoothed skins were used, they were joined together
into codices; and these, on account of their high price,
were often used more than once, the first set of writings
being cancelled and a further set being written over them.
A brief note must be made about the earliest methods
of writing in the American continents. Above all we must
mention certain mnemonic devices, like the notching of
sticks. There were the quipus or kipus, found especially
in Peru and Bolivia, which consist of a collection of strings
of different colours, with various types of knot either single
or in groups: these were genuine aides-mémoire for arith¬
metical data, for calculating the days or for matters of
statistical importance.
There were the wampum of the Iroquois in North America
which consist of figured and striped embroidery. In North
America too there were pictorial ideograms, carved mainly
on rocks, which were used to illustrate story-telling and to
keep records of arithmetical data: these often contain
representational figures with syllabic equivalents and look
like actual word-puzzles. Finally there are the illustrated
books of Panama, Colombia, etc., which helped in the
recitation of magical and religious texts.
But the Mayas and Aztecs of Mexico in early days
possessed real books made of folded bark: these were
covered with pictograms for ritual purposes, with calendars
for divination, with tribute registers and with annalistic
records. They also had stelae inscribed in bas-relief, on
which pictographic and syllabic elements are found side
by side.
But in all this the only objects likely to belong to late
antiquity are a bas relief on a stele at Vera Cruz and an
inscribed plaque now at Leyda7 These are assigned by
some scholars to the period around 320 A.D.
S written documents, both public and private,
'became more common, and as literary output
increased, it was necessary to consider better ways of
preserving and consulting writings, by bringing them toge¬
ther in suitable places. The classes of documents in question
were varied and important. The earliest which it was essen¬
tial to construct and preserve were state treaties, laws and
decrees, administrative acts, records of foreign relations,
chronicles both lay and sacerdotal, the acts of kings, and
the lists of priests and magistrates. All these were written
on relatively durable materials and were collected in royal
palaces, or in temple precincts and sacristies, or in the seats
of magistrates and of public assemblies.
Collections of official documents of these kinds are
known from finds. In Egypt the so-called Tell el Amarna
archives (14th century B.C.) contained the correspondence
with subject regions and neighbouring powers from the time
of Amenhotep III. In Crete we have the archives of the
Minoan palaces, and in the Hittite empire the archives of the
kings and leading cities.
In the ensuing period proper libraries came into being,
or at any rate departments for the preservation of literature
which adjoined the archives. One of the most characteristic
libraries known to us is that of Ashur-banipal (668-630), who
put on to its contents his stamp of ownership, his "ex
libris". Among these are 30,000 tablets of documents
contained in chests arranged on shelves. These include
receipts, levy lists, and his official and private correspon¬
dence. But in addition there are pieces of epic and mytho¬
logical poems; of liturgies and prayers; of magical writing,
psalms, oaths, and auguries; of annals, chronicles, and lists
of dates; of works on grammar and dictionaries; and of
astronomical calculations, tables of weights, and other
arithmetical writings. The king had sent scribes to many
places to copy ancient tablets. Another noteworthy library
is that of Nippur; and there were others owned by private
persons and by temples.
These Assyrian archives and libraries probably had their
precursors at Babylon and Bogazköy. They were followed
by similar institutions in the Persian capitals, among which
we know best the one instituted at Persepolis in the days
of Darius I.
HE first collections of literature, and therefore
the first libraries, in the Greek world must have
been made in the time of the sixth-century tyrants, Poly¬
crates of Samos and the Peisistratids of Athens. Later on
we are told of libraries belonging to individual literary men,
of whom the first is Euripides.
At the same time archives to preserve copies of important
private documents were on the increase. Examples of such
documents are conveyances, boundary plans, manu¬
missions, adoptions, and wills.
Education and the system of schools were also feeling the
effect of writing, and of written documents and work.
In early days the traditional ideas about religion and
techniques were learned in the family, or in priestly
colleges, or in unions of artisans, by means of mnemonic
methods. The teaching was oral, and the pupils com¬
mitted to memory what they learned. In our period this
was still the stage reached in education in India. The Indian
system of education was developing along clearly defined
lines. Writing was not used for religious purposes, and
oral tradition was therefore completely supreme: yet
instruction was confined to sacred matters. The study of
the Veda was given only to the first three castes, the Sudra
being excluded. From the beginning we see the sacred
texts being taught by a master and repeated by the pupils
in chorus "like the croaking of frogs" (Rigveda, VII, 103).
In Vedic times the religious students (ßrahmacarin) were
the educated class of India.
Their duties were to study the Veda, to serve their Brah¬
min masters (guru), and to maintain chastity. In very early
times the acceptance of a student into a school was con¬
ditioned by a complicated initiation ceremony, the upa-
nayana, through which the pupil received his second
(spiritual) birth and was therefore twice-born (dV/'/a). In the
Late Vedic period supplementary subjects, such as mathe¬
matics, grammar, and prosody, were added to the curri¬
culum. Education was originally confined to the Brahmins,
but was widened as time went on to include the Ksattriya
and Va/sya too: towards the end of our period a genuine
intellectual aristocracy came into being, with the Ksattriya
occupying a position at least equal to that of the Brahmins.
These are the circles in which Upanisadic thought took
shape. The sutra of Late Vedic times prescribe a detailed
curriculum, which already embraced all traditional Indian
knowledge, that is to say the six Vedanga (phonetics, ritual,
grammar, etymology, prosody, astronomy), together with
other ancillary sciences.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
GURU AND DISCIPLES.
A 1 3th century stele of pol¬
ished stone from Konarak,
Orissa, India depicting a
Brahmin teacher (guru) of
ancient India, explaining
the meaning of religious
texts to his pupils. These
oral lessons, at first restric¬
ted to religious matters,
were later expanded to
include mathematics, gram¬
mar and scientific subjects.
© Victoria and Albert Museum.
London
£Á^mr.^
With other peoples, however, the use of writing became
an aid to education at an earlier stage. With some the basis
of education remained theocratic, for instance in Egypt or
among the Hebrews especially after the Captivity, when
it was carried on in synagogues. On the other hand in the
Graeco-Roman world lay education predominated; it was
sometimes private and sometimes public, the many forms it
assumed being dictated by the varying bents and environ¬
ments of the different peoples.
Within the precocious culture of the Ionian Greeks we
find a form apparently already known in the Homeric poems,
which was intermediate between instruction at home and
instruction at school, and which was provided by a "peda¬
gogue" privately employed. Side by side with this there
existed the genuine school, where physical education (the
palestra) was originally the main feature but gradually
tended to get separated from instruction in music and
grammar.
A law of Charondas mentioned by Diodorus (XII, 12-13)
is often cited as evidence that masters were paid by the
state and experiments in compulsory education were already
known in the seventh century; but in all probability this is
not the original law made at Catana, but a revision of it
made in the middle of the fifth century at Thurii. Doubt has
also been cast on the passage of Aeschines purporting to
describe Solonian legislation on education.
The first certain case of a . state school, recorded by
Plutarch, relates to Troezen in 480. Meanwhile particular
importance was assumed by the schools of a domestic, or
professional, nature which were gradually created to pre¬
serve and advance the writings of various groups the Epic
poets (Homeridai), the doctors (in the Asclepieia), the
philosophers, and the mathematicians (cf. the Pythagoreans).
The Dorian world, Sparta or Crete for example, presents
a contrast. There, at any rate from the ninth or seventh
century onwards, the paramount feature was a militarist
education provided by the state; and letters were sacrificed
in favour of physical and athletic instruction.
A characteristic instance of individual arrangements is
provided by archaic Rome. After the end of the domination
exercised in the sixth, century by the more civilized Etrus¬
cans, the well-to-do families preserved the custom of
sending their sons to get instruction at Caere (Vol. II Pt. I).
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
THE ANCIENT WORLD (Cont'd)
'THE WOODEN OX'
The world's first wheelbarrow
by Luciano Petech
Engraving of a man push¬
ing a wheelbarrow, by a
Chinese artist of the Han
Period (202 B.C.-220 A.D.).
I
28
N China engineering always remained on a
practical level, without any connotation of
theory. Some bits of early information are found in the
K'ao-kung-chi (artificers' record) chapter of the Chou-li:
the original was lost and the present one was compiled by
the prince of Ho-chien (d. 130 B.C.). The larger works of
mechanical engineering were as a rule connected with
the imperial workshops (mostly called shangfang); for the
rest engineering was a family and hereditary craft.
Most of our information on mechanical appliances refers
to mechanical toys, which were always much appreciated
in China. A very famous example of such devices was the
south-pointing carriage (chih-nan ch'ê), in which a figure
was made, by the use of cog-wheels, always to point south¬
ward; it certainly had nothing to do with the compass.
The "//-recording drum carriage" (chi-li-ku-ch'ê), a sort
of hodometer, is mentioned in the fourth century A.D. and
described in the Sung-shu. As perfected later, it beat
a drum at every // and sounded a gong at every ten /;; it
was a simple problem of reducing cog-wheels.
Among these toys there was one destined for a great
future, if only the Chinese had guessed its practical use
cardamic suspension. Only known to Europe since the
sixteenth century, it seems to be described in the Hsi-
ching tsa-chi of the sixth century, which attributes it. to Ting
Huan (c. A.D. 180); "a perfume burner for use among
cushions. . ., a contrivance of rings which could revolve
in all the four directions (i.e., the three directions of space),
so that the body of the burner remained constantly level
and could be placed among bedclothes and cushions."
In this connexion we may mention a piece of charla¬
tanry which shows an odd element of prophetic divination:
about 320 A.D. Ko Hung speaks of a flying machine on the
principle of the helicopter: "Some have, made flying cars
(fei-ch'ê) with wood from the inner part of the jujube tree,
using ox leather straps fastened to returning blades, so as
to set the machine in motion." More solid than these
dreams was the fact that an old Chinese toy, the kite,
Perched on scaffolding, workers in a salt mine are
busy removing the brine. This impression of a Han
period engraving on brick depicts one of the many
forms of mining in ancient China, ranging from
minerals and precious stones to salt. In the 6th century
B.C. the state sought a complete monopoly over mining.
Illustrations on these pages from " Dictionnaire archéologique
des techniques". Editions de l'Accueil, Paris. 1963.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
¿g^f|jl
4L 'i MMN. jPP
JHpv&WI
FARMING 2000 YEARS AGO. Three
impressions made from stone engravings
depicting scenes from rural life and labour
during China's Han Period, when farming
techniques became finally established.
Above, ploughman at work with an ox.
Above right, kitchen chores. Beneath food
hung from the ceiling, housewives prépare
a fish and watch over the cooking pot. Right,
peasant farmers harvesting and threshing.
arrived in Europe at the end of the sixteenth century and
became the ancestor of modern aviation.
Of simple machines in everyday use, we find that some
of them were first manufactured in China. The folding
umbrella is one of them, and Wang Mang caused several to
be manufactured for magic purposes; some examples
have been found in the Lo-lang tombs in northern Korea.
The box-bellows (with double effect, like a double pump)
was a most efficient instrument, still widely used.
A humble but very useful contrivance was the wheel¬
barrow; the Chinese one, with the wheel in the centre of
the box, is much more practical than ours, because the
man merely pulls it and holds it in equilibrium, but carries
no part of its weight. It was first invented about 231 A.D.
by Chu-ko Liang, for logistic purposes; it was called wooden
ox (mu-niu).
Cog-wheels are first mentioned in the Han period, and we
possess a terracotta mould for a toothed bronze wheel of
that epoch. They are the necessary prerequisites for the
most typical Chinese hydraulic machine: the square-pallet
chain-pump (fan-ch'ê). It consists of an endless chain carry¬
ing a succession of pallets which, passing upward through
a trough, draw up water. It may lift water up to 16 feet
and can be worked by a treadmill, animal, or by a water-
mill. . ., the invention is attributed to the engineeer Pi Lan,
who died in 186 A.D. Water-mills, with both horizontal and
vertical axes, are found in China. They first appear in the
first century A.D., probably as an import from the West;
oddly, they were chiefly employed for driving bellows, and
seldom for grinding.
But engineering in China was fatally handicapped, in
comparison with the West, by the lack of knowledge of
some of the simple machines, such as the screw, and
also. of the crank (with the possible exception of the
winnowing fan) and so it could never go farther than
the so-called eotechnic stage.
Building enginerlng employed as its chief technique pisé
and raw bricks in wall building. Baked bricks took their
place during the Han period. The greatest and most
famous feat of Chinese engineering is, of course, the Great
Wall, which was formed in the years before 214 B.C. by
connecting already existing stretches of wall. Its main
purpose was administrative, fiscal, and, by making the
passage of masses of nomad cavalry difficult, also military.
The Chinese road network was started by the first empe¬
ror Shih-huang-ti, who in 220 B.C. caused two great postal
routes (ch'ih-tao) to be built, radiating from the capital
Ch'ang-an towards Ch'i and Yen to the east, and towards
the lower Huai to the south-east. They were planted with
trees and were paved with a sort of macadam; no traces of
them are left.
Several important roads were built under the Han dynasty.
We may mention the one from Ch'ang-an to Szechwan ;
it was built, or at least broadened, about 120 B.C., and
crossed a very rugged tract of country. About one-third of
its 430 miles consisted of wooden trestles over mountain
streams, or high up on the rocks. The general rule was
that road building was the concern of the central govern¬
ment; in practice the latter took care only of those roads
which were necessary for the transport of taxes in kind.
Suspension bridges are first mentioned in the famous
text of the Han-shu concerning the "Hanging Passages"
in the Hindu Kush. They are common in China, but it is
impossible to settle their chronology. The greatest rope-
bridge is that at An-lan in Szechwan: it has five spans,
the greatest of which is 200 feet, the total being over 700
feet. Perhaps it was originally built by Li Ping in the
third century B.C., but it is renewed every year.
The most notable innovation in Chinese agriculture of
this period was the "alternance field" (tai-t'len) technique,
introduced by Chao Kuo in the middle of the first century
A.D. It consisted in ploughing the furrow where in the
previous year the balk had been, coupled with a careful
weeding and lopping of the young plants. This procedure
was tried first in the imperial domains, where it resulted
in a double output per surface unit (mou); and then it was 00
officially introduced throughout the empire. It seems,
however, that its use did not last for more than a couple
of centuries (Vol. II Pt. 3).
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
J THE ANCIENT WORLD (Cont'd)
The birth
of functional
architecture
Town planning
and housing
in ancient Rome
by M. W. Frederiksen
Skilful architects and indefatigable buil¬
ders, the Romans raised cities in every
corner of their vast empire. Right, the
noble ruins of Timgad, in Algeria. It was
named Thamugadi when the legionaries
of the emperor Trajan founded it in the
Aures mountains in 1 00 A.D. Timgad con¬
forms to the typical Roman town plan
in which the forum or central square was
placed at the intersection of two main
streets (clearly visible in airphoto below).
As in Rome itself the cities of the outlying
provinces had their public baths, theatres,
arches of triumph and long arcades run¬
ning alongside the streets. At Timgad
many of the columns supporting these
arcades still stand, as this photo shows.
Compagnie aérienne de photographie
vO. w
HE skill and understanding of the Romans, both
in selecting sites and planning the towns, are
shown most 3trikingly by their survival into modern times:
in Italy, and the western provinces, where such policies
were especially applied, many towns were created whose
street-plans even today indicate their Roman origins. Like
Juilius Caesar before them, the emperors accepted that
municipalities were the basis of social life and administra¬
tion, and so wherever conditions permitted they founded
new colonies and towns.
The typical Roman town-plan was derived partly from
earlier Greek traditions and partly from their own ex¬
perience in laying out large military encampments. In Its
purest form, it was a strictly geometrical design, in which
«J¿ *4*t¿t \
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
two main streets intersected at right angles, and around
these was laid out a network of lesser .streets dividing
the city Into a series of uniform rectangular areas and build¬
ing-blocks. It Is seen most clearly where the builders were
able to create a completely new city.
The town of Aosta (in northwest Italy) founded in 24 B.C.
as the colony of Augusta Praetoria, was divided mathema¬
tically into sixteen rectangles, each of which was further
divided Into four; the surrounding town-walls took the form
of a larger but similarly-proportioned rectangle.
In the Trajanic colony of Timgad in North Africa, one of
-the best preserved Roman towns, the same precision can
be observed. But such perfection could not "always be
achieved; the plans are sometimes changed to meet the
© Ray-Delvert
difficulties of a site or to include an earlier settlement.
Roman architects sought to avoid any appearance of mo¬
notony by adding secondary features; colonnaded streets,
arches and gateways, or ornamental sculpture and fountains
could help to soften the sense of geometrical rigour. But
by such systematic planning they were able to provide the
building and amenities that were, for the Romans, of the
very essence of city life: the solemn central forum with its
temples and public buildings for local magistrates and
senate; an adequate drainage system and plentiful water-
supply; public baths and theatres; and shops and open mar¬
kets under official control.
Within a Roman town, private houses followed a variety
of patterns. In Italy, where our Information is fullest, the
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Wf*3¿:
German Museum. Munich OLD ROMAN AQUEDUCTS. A painting by Zeno Diemer showing the last
remains of a huge network of water supply channels which ran for several hundred
kilometres around Rome. The greatest of these aqueducts, which brought water from
the hills around the city, was the Acqua Marcia, 55miles (90kms) long. At the fall of
the Empire, Rome had nearly 1,000 public baths and 1,350 fountains, used one
million cubic metres of water daily and, in the words of the poet Properce, "every¬
where was heard the soft murmur of running water." Lead pipes and terracotta
tubes were used to bring water supplies right into the houses of Roman citizens.
THE ANCIENT WORLD (Cont'd)
Five-storey housing development schemes
32
earliest houses are of a low-built, spreading form of one
or two storeys, which were centred on an open hall
(atrium) and a colonnaded garden (peristylium). These
houses are best known from Pompeii, but they were
fashionable also in Rome, and were of a style well suited
to the aristocracy and municipal classes of the early
empire. In the provinces, housing seems to have kept to
local traditions, improved and embellished to suit the
prosperity of the times.
It was not long before the increasing wealth and social
changes in the empire were reflected in architecture. The
richest classes began to build luxurious villas with sur¬
rounding gardens, often in the countryside or by the
sea. But in the largest towns, where space was expen¬
sive and a large population of labourers and small craftsmen
needed housing, there begins to appear the new style of
building known as insulae, which were large apartment
houses divided into many shops and small flats. Some
areas of poor-class tenement housing in this style had
existed in Rome from early times; but the new technique
of brick-and-concrete architecture had made a revolution
ary change, and after the great fire in 64 A.D. Nero took
the opportunity to rebuild Rome systematically in the new
style.
Of the many cities where these insulae were built, our
best knowledge comes from the harbour town of Ostia.
It is vividly clear how with new building methods spacious
apartment houses of five storeys or more could be designed;
the insula, which had previously been a ramshackle tene¬
ment in a slum, was now converted into a safe, pleasant,
and almost fire-proof structure.
The historian Tacitus refers to the opponents of Nero's
scheme, who defended the unsafe and often insanitary city
quarters as they had been before and his comments
have a certain ironical flavour to modern readers. This
new utilitarian architecture reflected the changed social
conditions ; it supplied economical housing for a new
population who found that only the cities supplied them
with their employment and their amusements (Vol. II Pt. 3).
M.W. FREDERIKSEN, of Worcester College, Oxford, is one of
a number of scholars who contributed papers on specialized
subjects to Volume II of the "History of' Mankind."
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
(Cont'd from page 17) BOMBAY INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY
Unesco experts. Some of the Indian teachers were given
Unesco fellowships to complete a three-year course in
Soviet institutes and present their theses. They have
now returned to India and are working as departmental
and section chiefs at the institute. Other teachers have
received study fellowships in Australia, the U.K. and U.S.A.
Today the students they have trained are going out to
posts in India's developing industries. Many have already
joined the staffs of steel-making plants like those at Bhilai,
Durgapur and Rurkela, the machinery plant at Ranchi
and the heavy electrical installation at Bopal, to name
but a few.
There is also an urgent need to retrain men already
working in industry. The institute has therefore been
offering refresher courses to engineers and other techni¬
cians. In 1962-64 these courses included welding, metal
cutting, machine tools, rolling, electronics and automation.
new form of participation for the Unesco spe¬
cialists are the annual diploma courses attended
by engineers from different industries. These engineers
spend a year studying their speciality, design projects for
their diplomas and take examinations for a bachelor of
technology degree.
Unesco specialists also travel to other scientific and
research institutes to lecture and deliver reports which
all leads to shared experience between India's technical
institutes. The Bombay Institute also co-operates closely
with such major scientific centres as the Indian Institute
of Science at Bangalore and the National Physics and
Metallurgical laboratories at Delhi and Jamshedpur.
The Unesco and Indian specialists at the Bombay Techno¬
logical Institute are working in a spirit of true co-operation.
The daily discussions of curricula, lectures, teaching aids
and curricular guides have convinced every Unesco expert
completing his two or three-year stay at the Institute that
his work will be ably carried on by other members of
the faculty.
Now that the main laboratory equipment has been
thoroughly tried and tested, the Institute has begun to
concentrate on research facilities for its teachers. Young
staff members are working on their theses for master
of technology degree and many senior teachers are pre¬
paring their doctorates. Thanks to the Bombay institute
they can now do so without having to go abroad. In
1964 over thirty members of the faculty were doing research
and working for their doctor's theses. They received
valuable assistance from Unesco specialists who consider
this as one of their most rewarding duties. The series
of textbooks and manuals written by members of the
faculty and Unesco specialists now being published by
the institute is in great demand in other technical colleges
both in India and abroad.
The Bombay Technological Institute is becoming one of
the great technological research centres of India and,
in fact, of Asia as a whole. It plays host to All-India
conferences, seminars and symposiums concerned with
different branches of technology. The XVIIth Metallurgical
Congress, held there in 1964, heard reports from fifteen
teachers at the institute and from three Unesco specialists.
Recently an All-India seminar aimed at improving co¬
operation between technical education institutes and indus¬
try was held. The institute receives many visitors dele¬
gations and individual technicians from countries in Asia,
Africa and Europe.
VADIM A. JAVORONKOV is a Soviet specialist in metallurgical
technology. He was a member of Unesco's mission to the Bombay
Technological Institute and taught there from 1961 to 1964.
He is now a member of the staff of the Bauman Higher Technical
Institute, Moscow.
Specialized equipment is
available on a large scale
at the Bombay institute.
Using these modern ma¬
chines junior students learn
the basics of metal techno¬
logy and senior students
become familiar with their
chosen specialities. Right,
milling machine fitted with
a special device for studying
the stress at the toolpoint.
Unesco - Boucas
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
BOMBAY INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY
This text originally appeared in the chapter,
"The India of the Engineer" in the booklet
"Web of Progress: Unesco at Work in Science
and Technology" , recently published by Unesco.
CONVERSATIONS
Unesco - Paul Almasy
I
ALKING to some of the key men of the Bombay
Technological Institute at Powai offers a fasci¬
nating insight into the technological awakening of India.
They are all young in their thirties or early forties and
virtually none of them come from families of engineers.
They represent a startling change in the intellectual values
of an entire society. Each of them has his own reasons
for working at Powai.
Take Dr. Rudrapal Singh, the head of the institute's
physics department. In his family, his is the first generation
to go to a university. He worked through his master's
degree at the University of Allahabad and then took his
Ph.D. in theoretical physics at Washington State Univer¬
sity in the United States. After doing research on solid
state physics in Canada he returned to Allahabad but
came to Powai in 1958 because of a "better scientific
environment."
To a physicist, the presence of the Indian Atomic Energy
Commission and the Tata Institute of Fundamental Research
a few miles away is as important as the presence of Bom¬
bay's industries to the engineer. Dr. Singh was also
drawn to the institute because it enabled him to carry
A woman assistant in the physics laboratory of
the Bombay Institute of technology explains the
operation of electrical apparatus to students.
Below, practical workshop experience for MissTejas-
wini Saraf, training to be a researcher in electronics.
For two years she was the only woman student
Unesco « Jâïk Una
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
ON AN INDIAN CAMPUS
by
Daniel
Behrman
Student hostels (upper
right of photo) at the
Bombay Institute are set
around a vast sports field
with a gymnasium and
stands. Athletic events,
volley-ball and hockey are
among the most popular
sports. Here, students play
in a cricket match arranged
by the institute sports club.
Unesco - Paul Almasy
out one of his most cherished ideas: the creation of
"interaction between scientists and engineers." He had
received offers to do research work in the United States
but, he told me: "Here, you are building. You may be doing
less work yourself, but the future generations you train
will do it."
I heard the same remark in another context from Pro¬
fessor J. T. Panikar, a civil engineer from Quilon in South
India. "I am not building big dams myself," he told me,
"but some of my students will." Professor Panikar
earned his bachelor's degree in engineering from the Uni¬
versity of Trivandrum and then worked as a civil engineer
for the Kerala Electricity Commission. But he was looking
for a challenge and, In 1953, he won a French Government
fellowship to study construction techniques at the Ecole
Nationale Supérieure in Toulouse. There he turned to
fluid mechanics. He won his doctor's degree at Toulouse,
came to the Bombay institute In its earliest days and work¬
ed on the construction of its buildings.
Dr. Rangiah Bedford came from Madras State. After
earning his degree in electrical engineering from Guindy
College of Engineering in Madras, he taught at the Univer¬
sity of Illinois as a visiting assistant professor, but he
returned to India because of an opportunity to help set up
the electrical engineering department of the Bombay Insti¬
tute of Technology.
Another electrical engineer, Mr, Boddapatl Ravindranath,
did his undergraduate work at Hindu University in Benares
but camo to tho Powai Institute because he sought scope
for research and o possibility for study abroad. The possi
bility materialized in September 1960, when he was given
a Unesco fellowship to study electrical power systems at
the Moscow Power Institute, returning to Powai in early
1963. He adapted himself quickly to the Russian language
and also adapted himself to the Russian system of oral
examinations which has been carried over to some extent
in Powai.
France, the United States, the U.S.S.R., England ... all
the rivers of technology flow into Powai. Professor Ca-
dambi Balakrishnan teaches a course in electrical engin¬
eering materials using Russian and Indian equipment and
a textbook from the University of Minnesota.
One of the youngest of the top men at Powai is Dr. K. C.
Mukherji who, at thirty-three, is the professor in charge of
electrical engineering. After completing his undergraduate
work he joined the Damodar Valley Corporation the Indian
counterpart of America's Tennessee Valley Authority as
an assistant engineer, but he v/on a scholarship to England
where he worked first in industry and then earned his Ph.D.
in 1956 at the University of London. He, too, v/as a
research engineer for a large British firm but he returned
home in 1958 to join the Bombay Institute of Technology
because he felt it was a creative job.
Only ten years ago, Dr. Mukherji likes to remind you, a
graduate of an Indian engineering college could hope to go
into industry only as an unpaid apprentice engineer. Today,
the shoe is on the other foot Representatives of industry,
both public and private, interview likely candidates on cam¬
pus before graduation. The students at Powai are very
much in demand and they know it.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
^T
Li f m
Photos Unesco:W. Hubbell
BOMBAY
INSTITUTE (Cont'd)
Since 1951 India has created five regional institutes of technology. The first of these, covering eastern India,
was opened at Kharagpur near Calcutta with aid from the U.S.A. and U.K. and U.N.:Unesco technical aid.
Engineers sent by Unesco helped to set up a number of courses, including production technology. Left, learn¬
ing to use equipment in the geology laboratory. Right, the main entrance and institute buildings at Kharagpur.
The best form of foreign aid is education
36
Arvind Paranjpe, who is a fifth-year mechanical engin¬
eering student from Bombay, described his day. He gets up
at 7, has his breakfast at 7.30 and then goes to lectures
from 8.30 to 11.30. After a break for lunch until 1, he has
tutorials from 1 to 2 and then laboratory work from 2 to 5.
There is another break for tea and games until dinner at
7.30. He averages two hours of work at night. He would
like to try for a fellowship for study in the United States
and then come back to work in industry. "I must come
back," he said. "We must depend more on ourselves. We
can't go on having foreign help and experts all the time."
Mr. Paranjpe had studied science for two years at another
school where students always resorted to "guidebooks"
before taking an exam. He found that the competitive
entrance exam for the Indian Institute of Technology did not
fit any of the guidebooks. "They were more interested in
fundamentals rather than how much you had been able to
memorize," he said.
Research in electronics is the goal of Miss Tejaswini
Saraf, a third year student from Bombay, now one of a num¬
ber of women studying at Powai after having spent two
years there as the only one. She explained to me that
she had found an early vocation for engineering when she
started to tinker with the radio set in her home. Her first
week as the only girl in Powai was "awkward" but she
encountered no problems at all . . . not even in shop courses
where she did blacksmith work, welding and fitting along¬
side the boys.
Research also looms far above anything else in the life of
S. Ramani, a post-graduate student from Madras who came
to Powai because it was the only institute in India offering
a course in computer technology. He told me: "Research
appeals to me. I don't want to do work that is meaningless.
I don't want to be a slave to a machine. With an engin¬
eering degree here, I will have no financial problems. I've
never been used to much money; that doesn't bother me."
Every day, he travels to the Tata Institute of Fundamental
Research to work on the computer there, taking three buses
in a two hour trip each way. He spends his weekends in
the institute's library on the campus. "Three years ago," he
said, "I didn't imagine that I would get this opportunity.
There were 200 candidates for 20 seats in post-graduate
electrical engineering . . . and only four seats in computer
technology."
The director of the Bombay Institute of Technology, Bri¬
gadier S.K. Bose, has himself become, in a way, an end-
product of the institute, for he was sent to Nigeria on a one
month mission by Unesco to serve as consultant for the
establishment of an engineering college there with the aid
of the United Nations Special Fund.
Brigadier Bose is ubiquitous on the campus in his ancient
sedan. He teaches a class in highway engineering so as
not to lose touch with students. Under the institute's tuto¬
rial system, each staff member is responsible for five or six
students and these tutors meet regularly with the director
to discuss student problems. The creation of an espn't de
corps in this brand-new school is one of these problems
and Brigadier Bose has even found time to select the
institute's song based on a poem by Tagore.
He lives for the future. Eventually, he foresees a student
body of 6,000 at Powai, and its buildings have been care¬
fully sited to allow room for growth.
"The best form of foreign aid is education," he told me,
"but it is a long-term affair and you can see the results
only after a generation. Foreign aid should come from a
number of origins. Here, for example, you cannot simply
transplant the Ecole Polytechnique or the Massachusetts
Institute of Technology. We can expedite, but we cannot
squeeze in too much. An evolution of a hundred years
cannot be carried out in five ... but perhaps in twenty-five."
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
WORLD-WIDE
VOLUNTARY SERVICE
Sir,
International Voluntary Service is
part of a world-wide organization
which attempts to relieve poverty,
suffering and hostility among people
through the service of its volunteers.
Our work projects range from
spending a day painting rooms in a
centre for Chicago slum children to
working for years on community
development in India.
During the summer we hold many
work projects in the U.S. and Europe.
This year there will be over 100 camps
in Europe and about 10 here. We will
work with deprived children in
Chicago, rebuild a burned-out camp
in Tennessee, construct needed
facilities in a poverty-stricken town
in Florida, etc. Our volunteers will
come from all over the world and will
be of different backgrounds and ages
(though most tend to be in their 20's,
we are hoping to raise the average
age of our volunteers).
We strive to have represented in
our camps as many diverse points of
view as possible. We would welcome
inquiries from your readers.
Joyce Klein, US-IVS
American Group of
Service Civil International
1116 E. 54th Place, Chicago
Illinois 60615, U.S.A.
POMPEII IN PERIL
Sir,
Last October when I returned to
Pompeii, which I had visited two years
previously, I became aware of a
general deterioration and had difficulty
in gaining access to the houses:
watchmen were so few and when they
could be found, were unco-operative,
disinterested and occasionally surly;
sometimes too, when the gate to a
house was unlocked, access was
virtually Impossible on account of the
uncontrolled growth of weeds and
brambles in many cases, these were
breaking through mosaic designs and
disrupting mosaic floors. The sense
of neglect was appalling and, alas,
real.
An Intelligent and, to his credit,
greatly concerned watchman, pointed
out recent vandalism: visitors' (and
workmen's) graffiti and other damage
to wall-paintings; I learned that the
number of watchmen had been reduced
and the financial position had led to
increasing economies In maintenance.
But, Pompeii, like Herculaneum
which seems still well-cared for, ¡s a
unique, precious and priceless
archaeological treasure of the utmost
value to the whole world, whose
peoples indeed come to visit it, not
only In the persons of their most
eminent archaeologists, but In their
hundreds of thousands each year as
tourists. It is not just a tourist
attraction however, though indeed it
is that in every sense, but an un¬
paralleled glimpse into a pagan world,
stilled, in an instant of time and now
miraculously revealed before our eyes
by its painstaking recovery by the
most careful and diligent excavation
over many years. And, in this
connexion, it would be forever
regrettable if any present-day religious
prejudice were to endanger the
preservation, by apparent neglect, of
those pagan vestiges, now deemed
obscene, as seems to be In danger
of happening in the case of the
Lupanar and elsewhere in Pompeii.
The preservation and maintenance
of so internationally important an
archaeological treasure should not be
the burden of the Government of
Italy alone and, in view of the splendid
work you have initiated in saving
Abu Simbel, I hope that, through
Unesco, some steps may be taken
towards International concern In this
urgent matter, before it becomes too
late.
Dr. Norman Chlsholm
London, England
FOLK MUSIC ON RECORDS
Sir,
Some time ago "The Unesco Courier"
published an article by Alain Daniélou
(A New Language for Western Ears;
June 1962) announcing the release of
a series of folkmusic recordings.
Being very interested in other cultures,
especially the musical ones, I should
like to know which records of this
planned series are now on sale.
T. de Boer
Nijmegen, Netherlands
Ed. note: Long-playing 12-inch
records already published in the
Unesco Collectivn, "An Anthology of
the Music of the Orient", edited by
the International Music Council under
the direction of Alain Daniélou,
present the music of Laos (BM 30 L
2001); Cambodia (BM 30 L 2002);
Afghanistan (BM 30 L 2003); Iran I
(BM 30 L 2004); Iran II (BM 30 L
2005); India I (BM 30 L 2006); India II
(BM 30 L 2007) and Tunisia (BM 30 L
2008). Records of Tibetan and
Japanese music are due to appear
shortly. Records in this series may
be ordered through record dealers or
direct from the publisher: Bärenreiter
Musicaphon, Heinrich Schutz Allee 35,
Kassel, Federal Republic of Germany;
price per record: equivalent of DM 25
(about $6.00 or 30 F frs.). A series
of folk music recordings is being
prepared by the International Folk
Music Council under the auspices of
the International Music Council. The
first records, also published by
Bärenreiter Musicaphon, should be
available early next year. PLEASE DO
NOT SEND ORDERS TO UNESCO.
COURIER IN THE CLASSROOM
Sir,
In our higher English classes we
sometimes discuss your articles.
They are "eye-openers", besides being
extra good English exercises. I
personally like the readers' letter
corner, where all kinds of viewpoints
are expressed sometimes the most
unexpected. We are all very pleased
with your review.
Brother Nicolas
Institution Saint-Joseph
Thonon-les-Bains, France
INTERNATIONAL
CONSERVATION CORPS
Sir,
I am always pleased to see articles
on the conservation of wildlife and
natural resources published In "The
Unesco Courier" and I was certainly
Impressed by Professor Bourliere's
"Sanctuaries Astride Frontiers" (Feb.
1965).
The idea that national parks and
other conservation areas could become
meeting points for young people from
different nations has prompted me to
write to you about efforts being made
in this field by the International Youth
Federation for the Study and
Conservation of Nature.
For the past ten years this
organization, which is run entirely by
young people in Europe, has arranged
many international camps for the study
of nature, and courses for demon¬
strating the principles of nature
conservation and landscape man¬
agement. Many of these camps
have taken place in national parks
such as Gran Paradiso and Lüneburger
Heide, and their success has given
rise to the formation of an "Inter¬
national Register" of young people
who wish to take part in such
projects.
It is hoped that as the Register
develops it will prove possible to
form an International Conservation
Corps which will provide opportunities
for its members to understand,
through work and study projects, the
special values of nature conservation
for man's future wellbeing. A national
Conservation Corps has been working
successfully in Britain for some time
now and so an international extension
of the idea should prove its value.
It is a good thing that young people
from different nations should be able
to meet on a basis of common interest
and how much better it is that they
can meet in unspoiled areas set aside
by agreement between nations.
D.S. Davis
London, England
Ed. note: Several projects of the
International Youth Federation for the
Study and Conservation of Nature
have received Unesco aid. 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
NETHERLANDS UNESCO CENTRE: Nu¬
cleus of a network of over 100 local
Unesco committees in the Netherlands, the
Unesco Centre in Amsterdam has celebrat¬
ed Its 15th anniversary. Founded by stud¬
ent volunteers, it was the forerunner of
a wave of volunteer movements on behalf
of Unesco around the world which has led
to the formation of Unesco Clubs and simi¬
lar organizations in many member states.
ATOMIC POWER ON WHEELS: A mobile
atomic power station is now operating
In the Soviet Union. Weighing 350 tons
and mounted on four cross-country vehi¬
cles, It uses only 14 grammes of nuclear
fuel a day. Power plants of this type will be
used in the north and east of the Soviet
Union in areas where there are no sources
of power and fuel Is In short supply.
NATURE CONSERVATION IN ETHIOPIA:
A Unesco mission has recently been
helping Ethiopia to plan a campaign for
the conservation of nature and natural
resources. Two Unesco specialists have
been advising the government on setting
up a conservation board and bureau and
on emergency measures to protect threaten¬
ed species and sites. Another member of
the mission has been helping to Introduce
the subject of conservation Into school
programmes.
SOCIAL SCIENCES' DICTIONARY: In a
"Dictionary of the Social Sciences" (1)
recently published under Unesco auspices,
terms and concepts of basic Importance in
the social sciences are defined and de¬
scribed by 275 British and American spe¬
cialists. The 750-page English language
volume is part of a Unesco project for the
clarification of social science terminology
in some major languages (English, French,
Spanish and Arabic at present). Other
language editions will follow the English.
(1) Tavistock Publications, M New Fetter Lane,
London. Price in U.K. : 6 1/2 guineas.
M C HIGHER EDUCATION: College and
w»w. university enrolment in the United
States this year has soared to more than
five million, reports the U.S. Office of
Education. Total degree-credit enrolments
have broken all records for the 13th conse¬
cutive year and are more than double
compared with ten years ago.
FOR ELUSIVE AURORAS: Scientists
aboard the Australian National Antarctic
Research vessel, "Nella Dan" have been
using a special camera to make films of
auroras so faint that they can hardly be
seen by the human eye. The camera Is
fitted with an image intensifier which can
multiply 100,000 times the effect on film of
light given off by the aurora.
SPACE AGE DICTIONARY: An Astronau-
tical Multilingual Dictionary prepared by
the International Academy, of Astronautics
is due to be published later this year. It
will have a basic list in English of about
5,000 terms used In astronautics, with equ1-
valents In French, German, Italian, Russian,
Spanish and Czech, and separate alpha¬
betical lists of the translations In each lan¬
guage. Further information can be obtain¬
ed from the International Astronautical Fed¬
eration, 250. rue Saint-Jacques, Paris 5,
France.
PACKAGED GARDENS: Distributions of
gardens have been made
In 10 Indian states under a nutrition pro¬
gramme being carried out by the Govern¬
ment of India with the help of FAO and
UNICEF. These packages of certified seeds
provide a combination of vegetables for
school gardens, community gardens and
home-kitchen gardens.
INTERNATIONAL RESEARCH FLEET: Thlr-
' ty-three research vessels from seven
countries will embark on a new venture
In co-operative océanographie research in
July when they begin studying the Kuroshio
Current (its Japanese name means "black
current") In the northwest Pacific. The
Kuroshio Current, the Pacific's equivalent
of the Gulf Stream In the Atlantic. Is be¬
lieved to Influence both fishing and wea¬
ther In the Far East.
TEACHING TEACHERS BY POST: A
Unesco speclallst in organizing corres¬
pondence courses Is now helping to train
teachers in the Unesco-UNRWA schools
for 200,000 Palestine refugees children In
Jordan, Lebanon, Syria and the Gaza Strip
territory of the U.A.R. About 90% some
4,000 of these elementary and preparatory
school teachers need extra training, but
cannot be withdrawn from the schools.
The only solution is an In-service training
programme in which correspondence cour¬
ses play an Important part
INTERNATIONAL BIBLIOGRAPHIES
We are pleased to bring Maxwell's
International Subject Bibliographies
to the attention of readers to whom
they are available free of charge on
request. Each of these specialized
bibliographies gives a select inter¬
national listing of the most signifi¬
cant literature In a given field pub¬
lished throughout the world, and
thus covers many languages. Sub¬
jects dealt with which may be of
special Interest to readers include:
Series I, electronics; 2, oceanogra¬
phy; 3, archaeology; 4, design and
construction of scientific laborato¬
ries; 5, dermatology, venereology
and physiology of the skin; 6, ortho¬
paedics; 10, electrochemistry; 15,
graphic arts and Industries; 19. rein¬
forced plastics; 24, ultrasonics; 25.
cartography; 34, phytopathology. A
complete list of all bibliographies
currently available or In production
is available. Requests for bibliogra¬
phies should be sent to either of the
joint publishers: The Documentation
and Supply Centre of Robert Max¬
well & Co., Ltd.. Waynftete Building,
St. Clement's. Oxford. (U.K.); The
Documentation and Procurement
Centre, Division of Maxwell Scienti¬
fic International Inc.. 44-01, 21st St.,
Long Island City (U.S.A.). Readers
are asked to mention this announce¬
ment, when ordering.
38
PARTNERSHIP OF OVER 100 COONTRIES
The work of the United Nations Special Fund
has been honoured by a U.N. commemorative
stamp. Inaugurated In 1959, the Special
Fund is the U.N.'s largest programme of tech¬
nical co-operation for economic growth and
social advancement In the developing countries.
It is a partnership not only between more than
100 countries, but also between the U.N.
and nine of its specialized agencies. Another
recently issued U.N. stamp commemorates
the U.N. Peace-keeping Force in Cyprus. As
agent In France of the U.N. Postal Adminis-
' tration, Unesco's Philatelic Service stocks all
U.N. stamps and first day covers currently on
sale. For further details write to The Unesco
Philatelic Service, place de Fontenoy, Paris (7e).
SPECIAL FUND
UNITED NATIONS H
^3£s
Flashes...
Over 800 million people have now been
freed from the threat of malaria thanks to
the world malaria eradication campaign,-
reports WHO. This figure represents 52 %
of the population living In the originally
malarious areas.
Unesco now has 119 member states.
The latest countries to join are Malta
(118th member state) and Portugal (119th).
Under the World Food Programme, FAO
Is carrying out a $1.13 million emergency
relief programme for 700,000 drought-
stricken farmers In Somalia. Somalia's
crops have been near-failures for the past
two years.
The world fish catch In 1963 was
46.4 million metric tons, a 2.4% Increase
over 1962, reports FAO. Top fishing nation
was Peru with 6.9 million tons.
u
z
2
d.
<
O
z
o
o:
O
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO ART SLIDES
Unesco Art Slides are presented in a plastic case for ready projection, each series containing thirty
transparencies in mounts 5x5 cm, and an explanatory booklet with text and titles in French, English
and Spanish. The slides are produced for Unesco by Publications Filmées d'Art et d'Histoire, Paris.
Price for each box of slides varies but does not exceed $10.00 in local currency.
Series now available :
AUSTRALIA : Aboriginal Paintings
BULGARIA : Medieval Wall Paintings
CEYLON : Paintings from Temple. Shrine and Rock
CZECHOSLOVAKIA : Romanesque and Gothic
Illuminated Manuscripts
EGYPT: Paintings from Tombs and Temples
ETHIOPIA: Illuminated Manuscripts
GREECE : Byzantine Mosaics
INDIA : Paintings from the Ajanta Caves
IRAN : Persian Miniatures. Imperial Library
ISRAEL : Ancient Mosaics
JAPAN : Ancient Buddhist Paintings
MASACCI0 : Frescoes in Florence
MEXICO : Pre-Hispanic Paintings
NORWAY : Paintings from the Stave Churches
NUBIA: Masterpieces in Danger
SPAIN : Romanesque Paintings
TUNISIA : Ancient Mosaics
TURKEY: Ancient Miniatures
U.S.S.R. : Early Russian Icons
YUGOSLAVIA : Medieval Frescoes
To be published shortly :
AUSTRIA : Medieval Wall Paintings
CYPRUS : Byzantine Mosaics and Frescoes
POLAND : Painting of the 15th Century
RUMANIA: Painted Churches of Moldavia
ART EDUCATION
SLIDES :
Slides and text illustrate contemporary concepts of art education in
the world.
1. Play - Explore - Perceive - Create
2. Three dimensional art for the adolescent
3. Visual and plastic stimulae in art education
Special agents for art slides:
Belgium: Louis de Lannoy, 112, rue du Trône, Brussels. Denmark:
Kunstkredsen for Grafik og Skulptur, Gammel Strand 44, Copen¬
hagen V. Franco: Publications Filmées d'Art et d'Histoire, 44, rue du
Dragon, Paris (6e). Germany: Dr. Lucas Lichtbild, 1, Berlin-Lichter-
felde-West, Fontanestr. 9A. India: National Education and Information
Films Ltd., National House, Tulloch Road, Apollo Bunder, Bombay 1.
Italy: Casa Editrice Bemporad-Marzocco, Via Scipione Ammirato 35-37,
Florence. Netherlands: Stichting Centraal Projectieen Lichtbeeiden
Instituut, Weesperzijde 112, Amsterdam O. Norway: Johan Grundt
Tanum Bokhandel, Karl Johansgt. 41, Oslo. Switzerland: Filmes Fixes
Fribourg SA., 20, rue du Romont, Fribourg. Sweden: Pogo Produktion
AB, Fack 417, Solna 4. United Kingdom: Educational Productions Ltd.,
East Ardsley, Wakefield, Yorks.
In countries where there is no special agent, please apply to the
National Distributors for Unesco publications (see below).
WHERE TO RENEW YOUR SUBSCRIPTION
and order other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made In the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Pre« Department, Royal
Aghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Tradco Agencies, 1 09 Swanston Street, G. P. O.
Box 2324 V. Melbourne C. I. (Victoria); United
Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
8ch Floor, McEwan House, 343 Little Collins St..
Melbourne C. I. (Victoria). (22/6). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C".. Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Seh. 70.-). BELGIUM. Editions "Labor".
342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-Boek-
handet, Belgiëlei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (140 FB) and art slides only; Louis De Lannoy,
11 2, rue du TrAne, Brussels 5. CCP 3380.00. BURMA.
Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road, Ran¬
goon. (	). CANADA. Queen's Printer,
Ottawa, Ont. (S 3-00). CEYLON. Lake House
Bookshop, Sir Chittampalan Gardiner Mawata, P.O.B,
244. Colombo, 2. (Rs. 13/50). CHINA. World Book Co
Ltd., 99 Chungking South Rd., Section 1, Taipeh, Taiwan
(Formosa). CYPRUS. Cyprus National Youth Council,
P. O. Box 539, Nicosia.- CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L.,
Spalena 51, Prague 1 (permanent display) ; Zahrahnici lite¬
ratura Bilkova 4, Prague 1. DENMARK. Ejnar Munks-
gaard, Prags Boulevard 47 Copenhagen S (D. Kr. 17).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agency. P.O. Box 120,
Addis Ababa (10/-). FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirja-
kauppa. 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (Fmk. 9.40). FRANCE.
Librairie de I'Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7*. C.C.P.
1 2598-48. (1 0 F.). GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg Verlag,
Rosenheimerstrasse 145, Munich. 8. For the Unesco
Kurier (German ed only) Bahrenfelder-Chaussee 160,
Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, C.C.P. 276650 (DM 10).
GHANA Methodist Book Depot Ltd. Atlantis House
Commercial St., POB 100, Cape Coast. GREAT BRI¬
TAIN. See United Kingdom. GREECE. Librairie H.
Kauffmann, 28. rue du Stade, Athens. HONG-KONG.
Swindon Book Co., 64, Nathan Road, Kowloon. HUN¬
GARY. Kultura, P. O. Box 149. Budapest. 62. ICE¬
LAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co. H.F.. Hafnarstraeti 9,
Reykjavik. (1 20 Kr.) INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd. Ni-
col Road, Bellard Estate, Bombay 1 ; 1 7 Chittaranjan Avenue
Calcutta 1 3 ; Gunfoundry Road, Hyberabad, 1 ; 3 6a, Mount
Road, Madras 2; Kanson House, 1/24 Asaf Ali Road, P.O.
Box 386, New Delhi, 1; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book &
Stationery Co., 17 Park Street, Calcutta 16, Scindia
House, New Delhi, Indian National Commission Co-ope¬
ration with Unesco. Ministry of Education, for New
Delhi 3. (Rs. 7). INDONESIA. P. N. Fadjar Bhakti
Djalan, Nusantara 22, Djakarta. IRAQ. Mackenzie's
Bookshop, Baghdad. IRELAND. The National Press,
2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (15/5).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores 35, Allenby Road
and 48, Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv (l£8).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour Street,
Kingston. (15/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd.. 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 60 5 Tokyo Cent ral, Tokyo
(1,200 yen). JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous& Co., Dar ul-
Kutub. Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman. KENYA. E.S.A.
Bookshop. P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi (10/-). KOREA.
Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Cen¬
tral 64, Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops
Ltd.. P.O. Box 286, Monrovia (10/-). LUXEM¬
BURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue, Luxemburg
(F.L. 1 40). MALAYSIA. Federal Publications Ltd., Times
House, River Valley Rd., Singapore; Pudu Building (3 rd
floor), 110, Jalan Pudu, Kuala Lumpur (M. $ 7.50).
MALTA. Sapienza's Library 26 Kingsway, Valletta,
(15/-). Nalanda Company Ltd., 30,
Port-Louis (1 0/-). MONACO. British Bourbon Street,
Library 30 Bid des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (F. 10).
NETHERLANDS. N. V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange
Voorhout. 9. The Hague, (fl. 8.50). NETHERLANDS
WEST INDIES. G. C. T. Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.)
N.V, Willemstad, Curacao. N.A. (NA fl 4,50). NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office 20, Molesworth
Street (Private Bag) Wellingston, C. 1 Government Books
hops: Auckland (P.O. Box 5344), Christchurch (P.O. Box
1721). Dunedin P.O. Box 1104)(15/-). NIGERIA.
C.M.S. Bookshops, P.O. Box 174, Lagos (10/-). NOR-
WAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille Grense 7, Oslo. For the
Unesco Courier also: A.S- Narvesens Litteratur Tjeneste,
Stortingsgt. 2 Oslo, Postboks 115 (17.50 kr.).l PA¬
KISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing Co. Ltd., Unesco
Publications House, P.O. Box 374 56-N Gulberg Indus¬
trial Colony, Lahore. PHILIPINES. The Modern Book
Co., 508 Rizal Avenue Manila. POLAND. "RUCH",
ul. Wronia, 23, Warsaw 10 (zl. 60). PORTUGAL.
Dias & Andrade Lda, Livraria Portugal, Rua do Carmo
70, Lisbon. PUERTO RICO, Spanish English Publi¬
cations, Eleanor Roosevelt 115, Apartado 1912, Hato
Rey. RHODESIA. The Book Centre, Gordon
Avenue, Salisbury. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop,
P. O. Box 1118, Khartoum. SWEDEN. A/B CE.
Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 1 6.
For the Unesco Courier: Svenska UnescorSdet, Vasa-
gatan 15-17, Stockholm, C (Kr. 12); SWITZERLAND.
Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse Zurich. Payot, rue Grenus
6, 1211, Geneva C.C.P. 1-236. "Courier" only: Georges
Losmaz, 1, rue des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CCP.
1-4811. (Fr. S. 10). TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND.
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue. Bangkok.
(35 ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul	 UGANDA. Uganda Book¬
shop, P.O. Box 145, Kampala (10/-). REPUBLIC OF
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Bookstore, Libri
Building, Church Street, P.O. Box 724 Pretoria. For the
Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Central News
Agency P.O. Box 1033, Johannesbourg. (R1.50).
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT). Librairie
Kasr El Nil, 38. rue Kasr El Nil Cairo. Sub/agent: La
Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha, Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I, and Government Bookshops
in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester,
Birmingham and Bristol. (15/-). UNITED STATES.
Unesco Publications Center, 3 17- East 34th St, New York,
N.Y. 1001 6 ($ 5.00) U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Knig»,
Mocow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Yugoslovenska Kn-
jig, Tzrazije 27, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
© Giselle Freund
papermakers
Seated before a work bench, two women beat bark fibres for
papermaking. This terracotta work is a striking relic of the
Pacific Coast Civilization which flourished in Mexico from 300 to
900 A.D. Similar papermaking techniques were used by the Aztecs
and Mayas. The Pre-Columbian peoples assembled the sheets of
paper in the form of manuscript books, or codices (see page 25).
]]>
</page>
</document>
