<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="060619eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
WVt
abiï
, A *ti *»' ' .-.. - h "ÖL .Va-I
Î&ï»M$pS
Ganada : 30. cents - France : 1 F
;»%**
. j jt'.
'. --
;...- -
*#<*$$*?
?C
¡«c
O :u>»ai'.'*.t «
y».
ù **.
Sa
iSfeà»" O ?V*j
:t^
sííAri
*£*
.-arÄS
~* .í.-.vp'*'*
'- *ï 4 ^- ' S
ti
*f*lCT /
v ^ 2 fi '-t*
.-v»-. ¡»»
n
'&*r*4>ï
tteL m »&*ïs-nC-i
f..
ti i »!
Ü sp*¡ N
v*.1»
*«£**?
.->Vf
&3 r^wW "
N-¿y
í
rf' . J\ ^¡t.
>.A-
>
"a* ^:
ïbS
&3S? $;£*
í̂>^
í.^JF.1
Xí
í'í^SS
«i ufe»
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
HANDY FOR THE READER
In its search for mass-readership, the paper¬
back has spread far from the bookstore.
Today it is sold just about everywhere,
from chain stores to the village grocer's
shop, from the street-corner stall to the
petrol station. Paperbacks on this self-
service stand in a Paris store are displayed
between electrical goods and paintbrush
¿à
:^y
v
m* , VENTE
#H FUHlCMIff
_ feuTTT-p?	 ,	4
Livres service
i S
k
j \
;w
i
©
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier
SEPTEMBER 1965 - 18TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
Published monthly by UNESCO,
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7°.
Annual subscription rates: 15/-stg. ; $3.00
(Canada) ; 10 French Francs or equivalent;
2 years : 27/-stg. ; 1 8 F. Single copies 1 /6-stg. ;
30 cents ; 1 F.
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except
in July and August when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German, Arabic,
Japanese and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed
by H.M. Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from
THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returned unless accompanied by an international reply
coupon covering postage. Signed articles express the
opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
tne opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE
UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in The Read¬
ers' Guide to Periodical Literature published by
H. W. Wilson Co.. New York.
4
11
15
17
18
21
23
28
32
33
34
THE REVOLUTION IN BOOKS
By Robert Escarpit
A NEW DIALOGUE BETWEEN AUTHORS
AND READERS
By Robert Escarpit
TWO-THIRDS OF WORLD'S BOOKS
PRODUCED BY TWELVE COUNTRIES
THE GROWTH OF THE HISPANIC
BOOK MARKET
BOOKS PRINTED WITH A CAMERA
Photocomposition : a new era in printing
UNESCO AND THE WORLD OF BOOKS
By Julian Behrstock
DILEMMAS OF BOOK PUBLISHING
IN SOUTH-EAST ASIA
By Om Prakash
A CONTINENT IN SEARCH
OF A PUBLISHING INDUSTRY
A Unesco survey in Africa
By Clifford M. Fyle
BIBLIOGRAPHY
Unesco publications on books
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
FROM THE UNESCO BOOKROOM
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 78, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant to the Editor-in-Chief
Lucio Attinelli
Managing Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton (Paris)
Jane Albert Hesse (Paris)
Arturo Despouey (Paris)
Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Hans Rieben (Berne)
Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Shin-Ichi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Illustrations : Phyllis Feldkamp
Research : Olga Rodel
Layout & Design : Robert Jacquemin
Allcorrespondence shouldbe addressedto the'Editor-m-Chief.
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Edition
Edition :
Edition :
Edition
Edition :
Japanese Edition :
Italian Edition :
o
5
Cover photo
This issue is devoted to the revolution
in books which has been sweeping
both the developed and the develop¬
ing countries with increasing momen¬
tum in recent years. Cover shows an
Indian paperback of a classic entitled
"Umrao Jan Ada", originally written
in Urdu and translated into English
in the Unesco series of Representa¬
tive Works.
© Paul Almasy, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
THE REVOLUTION
IN BOOKS
by Robert Escarpit
The tremendous changes ¡n the world of books over the past few decades have
now attained the proportions of a revolution. As Professor Robert Escarpit, the
French author and critic, has pointed out: "During the past 2,000 years the
book has gone through a series of mutations, all of them associated with its
fundamental purpose of communicating ideas. Today we are experiencing
the latest of these mutations, a mutation which is adapting books to the
needs of mass readership." Professor Escarpit was speaking at a press
conference held on June 10 to mark the publication by Unesco, of his study,
"The Revolution in Books." In the following article, especially written
for this issue devoted to books, Professor Escarpit reviews some of
the outstanding questions he deals with in "The Revolution in Books."
We also present salient passages from this important work on pages 11 to 15.
4
THE appearance of the mass-circulation book is
probably the most important cultural develop¬
ment in the second half of the twentieth century. Although
people everywhere have at last begun to show an interest
in this event, no one has yet clearly grasped its significance
nor fully realized that it is taking place. English-speaking
countries, for instance, often misname this type of book
"the paperback," although some paperbound books are
high-priced articles with a very low circulation. Elsewhere,
as in most European countries, it is called, even less appro¬
priately, "the pocket book" or, quite absurdly, "the pocket-
size book." It would be as reasonable to talk of "cheap
books" or "bulk-printed books."
Mass-circulation books are not distinguished by their
specific appearance nor by the number of copies printed
nor by the retail price. It is easy to find examples of all.
these characteristics, sometimes more than a century back,
whereas the mass-circulation book is a global phenomenon
whose constituent elements cannot be separated, a new
type of publishing venture which first took shape in 1935
with the appearance of the Penguin series in England.
The obvious features of mass-circulation books (some¬
times wrongly regarded as fundamental characteristics) all
combine to enable them to play their role, a role which
consists of changing the scale on which publications are
distributed, by providing new processes which open up still
unsatisfied areas of readership, ethnic groups or social
strata.
What is involved is not the adaptation of books to new
conditions, but a genuine mutation. The mass-circulation
book is as different from the classical book as was the
printed book from the manuscript and the manuscript from
the clay tablet. This mutation, in fact, will eventually change
the content of books, just as it is already transforming
the dialogue between author and reader which constitutes
the reality of literature.
CONT'D ON PAGE 6
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
© Paul Almasy. Paris SOMETHING FOR EVERYONE. Once a year, Spain's National Book Fair draws crowds
of buyers to the open-air bookstalls set up, like this one in a Barcelona street, in all parts of r
the country. In recent years Spain's publishing industry has made spectacular progress: in **
1964 it published 10,129 titles, an increase of 1,435 over 1963. Spain is now one of the twelve
countries which together produce three-quarters of all the books published in the world.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
REVOLUTION IN BOOKS (Cont'd)
A million copies
quite normal
In other words, the whole of written culture as we have
known it for two or three centuries past is directly
challenged by mass-circulation books, and the cultivated
classes of our time are only wrong in feeling disturbed over
this development to the extent that such perturbation
reflects a niggardly attachment to values which have become
inadequate for the new dimensions of mankind.
To begin with, viewed as manufactured items, books have
at one bound caught up with other products of modern
industry; the book has been simultaneously adapted to the
demands of mass production and modern design. There
was virtually no technical difference between Gutenberg's
books and books produced at the end of the eighteenth
century; printers carried out identical operations and edi¬
tions remained about the same size, rarely exceeding a
few thousand copies.
Then, within ten to fifteen years, or roughly the length of
the Napoleonic era, everything changed. Printing was
mechanized and the book which had editions of from
between ten thousand and one hundred thousand copies
made its appearance. Editions of this order were still being
printed 130 years later between the two world wars, and
they are still produced in the traditional sector of publishing.
At the same time, however, mass consumer demands,
emerging from and affecting social advancement, penetrated
the cultural field. By the 1870s, these demands, which
exerted pressure on the whole complex of trade and
industry, were also affecting the media serving the field
of culture, and especially books.
As everyone knows, one of the first effects of mass
production in all fields was a decline in the aesthetic and
functional qualities of the product manufactured. Because
of their dual nature as physical objects and vehicles for
the communication of thought, books proved particularly
vulnerable to such debasement. "Mass produced" reading
matter became a by-product of the newspapers and
hawkers' books that were the only mass media of the time.
Such "poor man's books" often sacrificed either content
or appearance, and mostly both. At the beginning of the
century the working class reader in city or village could
only escape from the most stultifying type of reading by his
sheer determination to rise above the ugliness and unsuita-
bility of the reading material normally available to him.
I
6
T is not surprising, therefore, that such media
of mass communication as the radio and the
cinema, which from the outset had an aesthetic adapted to
their function, should have proved irresistible rivals to
books. Indeed when the 1930s came bringing restlessness
and more demanding standards, it might well have been
thought that books had lost the battle.
Such was far from being the case. Although no one
realized it at the time, a genuine revolution occurred in the
mid-1 930's in the thinking of our industrial civilization.
Raymond Loewy then wrote in the United States "The Loco¬
motive, Its Aesthetics," which anticipated his famous book
on industrial design, "Never Let Well Enough Alone."
A new type of functional beauty entered everyday life.
In Western Europe it was introduced by the "one-price".
stores, and in Moscow a similar function was fulfilled by
the newly-opened underground railway. Though this beauty
may not have been to everyone's taste, it nevertheless
suddenly lit up and humanized the dismal atmosphere of a
mass consumer world.
Industrial design, which thus became part of our
accustomed pattern a little before the Second World War,
has been defined as "a technique connected with the
creation of products, and aimed at studying the products
devised by a firm on the basis of such criteria as suitability
for use, beauty, ease of manufacture and reduction of cost
price."
Consciously or unconsciously, Allen Lane applied these
four criteria to book production when he founded Penguin
Books in England in 1935. Penguin books were the first in
the world to unite all the specific features of mass-circu¬
lation books. Pleasant to look at and convenient in form,
they enabled works of real quality to be distributed in
huge quantities and at a very low price. It should be
repeated that none of these various elements can be
considered separately; each depends on the others and the
whole secret of mass-circulation books lies in achieving
the right balance.
For the modest price of sixpence, the Penguin series
gave the public books that normally sold In a hardback
edition for ten shillings and sixpence more than twenty
times as much. Such sensationally low prices are now a
thing of the past, but one of the requirements of the mass-
circulation book is still that it should be sold at rock-bottom
price.
This price can be worked out very accurately. The price
at which a book is sold to the public is dependent on the
cost price of each volume in the original edition, and is
established on the basis of a simple formula. Some of the
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
USIS photos
costs of printing a book (type-setting, going to press, etc.)
remain the same no matter how many copies are printed;
others (such as paper and binding), are linked to each
individual volume and thus increase with the size of the
edition. In terms of cost price per volume these expenses
are incompressible. Fixed costs, however, decrease propor¬
tionately as the size of the edition increases, since they are
spread over a greater number of copies. The cost price
per volume thus diminishes accordingly.
There comes a moment, however, when the fixed costs
are spread over such a large number of copies that the
effect on the cost price is insignificant, and the latter, along
with the retail price then becomes stabilized at the lowest
level. The publisher's first concern must be to determine
this point, since only when it has been reached can he
benefit completely from the effects of mass production.
Everywhere books have their uses, from the kitchen
(how to prepare an Italian dish) to this cab rank
in Central Park, New York (how to kill time while
waiting for a passenger). Every day over one
million paperbacks are sold in the United States. In
1964 they totalled one third of all titles published.
serves only a small fraction of the population those social
strata or classes which produce the "cultivated" individuals.
In a highly developed country where the reading popu¬
lation (those capable of choosing and using reading matter)
represents 70 to 75% of the population, the real public
(those who make regular use of all types of reading matter)
represents at most 15 to 20 %, and the cultivated public
(those for whom the bookshops cater) barely 2 to 3%.
It is out of the question for the moment to reach the
whole of the reading population. But mass-circulation books
must spread far beyond the cultivated public and penetrate
the real public where they will have their most effective
social impact. This is what has happened, in the United
States, where before World War II best sellers rarely sold
100,000 copies, while editions of more than a million copies
are now commonplace.
BOOKS are not distributed solely through book¬
shops, but from an infinite number of sales
points, including drug-stores, self-services stores and book¬
stalls, with the backing of extensive advertising. Certain
countries, and especially the U.S.S.R., have developed
direct distribution methods through offices, factories and the
postal service. Finally, in the years ahead we will see an
extension of book vending machines which will increase
the bookshop's distribution power tenfold.
It is in this way that the boundaries of the "cultivated"
public are crossed. It should be noted, however, that
high sales figures do not necessarily mean that those boun¬
daries have been crossed. Many publishers, especially in
Europe, believe they are publishing mass-circulation books
because they have adopted the form and style of such
books and have increased their printing runs ten or twenty-
fold. All they have done in many cases is to saturate the
market offered by the cultivated public through the induce¬
ment of reduced prices.
The whole operation takes place within the old socio-
cultural frontiers, and this is especially true of countries
which have a large and active, though poorly-off, intelli¬
gentsia. There are countries where mass circulation starts
with sales of from five to ten thousand copies and others
where sales of between 50,000 and 100,000 still represent
limited distribution within the cultivated sector.
H OW far the publisher should go beyond this
point remains to be seen. For the purchaser
it makes no difference at all whether a book is published in
50,000 copies or in one million since the rock-bottom price
has already been reached. But the situation is altogether
different from the publisher's viewpoint. On the one hand
his financial investment is larger and the risk corresponding
greater; on the other hand, despite the reasonableness
and stability of the price, he cannot expect to distribute
a mass production book by the same methods he uses for
smaller editions.
This brings us to a third requirement of the mass-cir¬
culation book: new distribution outlets must be found. In
the most developed civilizations cultural patterns are still
more or less marked by the stamp of a civilization based
on a cultural elite. The bookshop network in particular
In short, the entry of books into the mass market can
affect them in other than material ways. Their content is
affected and, along with it, the use which readers make
of that content. The dialogue between author and reader
which constitutes the basic literary reality is being pro¬
foundly altered in its nature and in its machinery alike.
The. reading of the cultivated person is marked by an
active and conscious attitude. He reacts to what he is
reading by judgements, observations and reasoned conclu¬
sions, whether the work in question is "literary", in the true
sense, or functional. All these reactions combine to form
a "literary opinion" whose image returns to the author
through various channels: conversations, contacts between
publishers and booksellers, literary reviews and so on.
This feedback to the author is the specific and distinctive
feature of literary reality. It implies, incidentally, an
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
REVOLUTION IN BOOKS (Cont'd)
The paperback invades the university
extremely delicate balance. If the feedback signal is too
strong, in other words if the author is too conscious of
his public, his work may deteriorate.
If there is no feedback the author can only choose
between the sterile seclusion of the literary coteries and the
no less sterile use of mechanical techniques for capturing
and retaining the attention of the anonymous public like
any demagogue.
In mass circulation as we know it today, however, there
is no cultural feedback. The literary opinion of the
"masses" has no personal contacts, bookselling networks
or literary- criticism through which to express or transmit
itself and often has not even the opportunity to take
conscious form.
The publisher' of mass-circulation books in thus con¬
fronted with a difficult problem. On the one hand, in view
of the substantial capital involved, he must reduce the
risks of the operation by programming his production to the
maximum; on the other, he must offset the disadvantages
of having no feedback to guide him. The problem varies
according to the types of books he publishes. Here we
need only consider three types of books.
First of all, there are the functional books which represent
a known and recognized need. This to some extent guar¬
antees the sale of a considerable number of copies.
The typical example is the cookbook which continues to
rank among the best selling paperbacks in the United
States. Eating is a function which can always be relied on
and love of good food is one of the commonest of all
impulses.
The same applies to books needed by school and univer¬
sity students. In recent years the paperback has invaded
the American universities. This has revolutionized research
and teaching methods. Scientific textbooks, for example,
are no longer rare and expensive works to be placed on
library shelves where set timetables restrict their usefulness
and where they slowly grow out of date.
They are now cheap, attractively but unpretentiously pro¬
duced books which can be purchased for a modest sum
and which students are therefore ready to purchase. Even
if a student does not buy a book himself, the library can
offer him several copies without worrying unduly over the
possibility of their wearing out or being lost.
It is always possible, to reprint, bringing the book
. i
2*
I.1* él *^
ARISTOPHANE
VICTO»
IM «.O
US CHATIMENTS
0
f »»1AGE
imEllIlE HnaUMMUi
puMi-i'BiMoni jTrevrtT
riauAHDrcsrcTis
LI IUI M >
France France
Penguin
Reference
Books
Arthur Jacobs
a~ ;^s?;
United States
anptM JBI'I m-^i-wh««i
i ni,< i i m -s
United Kingdom
GIORDANO BRUNO
JOURNAL DE
//illIP. Wilt
fette mtfrt
Kasteel te huur
II H
59 Clare Lennart
Netherlands
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
up to date at the same time. In this way it benefits
from a genuine scientific feedback that expresses the views
of its users. In France this system has been employed for
many years in the Que Sais-Je? (What Do I Know?) series.
In their special field of scientific popularization and explan¬
ation, these little books had already discovered the formula
of the mass-circulation book in pre-war days, although
they were probably unaware of it at the time.
Another formula adopted in mass-circulation publishing
is to reprint a literary work which has already proved itself
in the cultivated sector. It may be one of the classics or
a book that has been outstandingly successful in an
ordinary edition. The formula of the classic is obviously
more convenient since the number of titles of works
retained in a country's historical consciousness is strictly
limited, .roughly about one per cent. Reprinting the classics,
therefore, presents few hazards and this explains why in
most countries paperbacks have produced an unhoped for
and reassuring flood of reprints of all kinds. Texts which
have disappeared from circulation now enter the public
domain and can be purchased at any bookstall.
At the same time, there is a limit to this wealth of material
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
The extraordinary deve¬
lopment of the paper¬
back has served to open
still wider the field of
research already well
explored by graphic ar¬
tists in producing illus¬
trated book covers. The
appearance of paper¬
backs, between one
country and another,
obviously reflects natio¬
nal tastes in illustration
and typography, but
their common denomi¬
nator is perfect legibi¬
lity combined with an
unconventionality that
touches the imagination
of the reader. All
covers, black and white
and colour alike, use
modern graphic forms
of publicity and imagery.
Federal Republic of Germany
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
REVOLUTION IN BOOKS (Cont'd)
Breakthrough to a vast public
and disadvantages in this practice. The number of classic
works which a literature can offer is not infinite, amounting
perhaps to a few thousand, and one can reasonably foresee
a point at which mass-circulation books in the more
developed countries will be offering scores of thousands of
different titles. A time must come then, which is not far off
in certain countries, when saturation of the market will
cause a slump in books of this type, and when the only
reliable outlet for these huge editions will consist of the
normal cultural consumption of schools, universities and
similar institutions.
But it is also possible to take up a best seller while it is
still enjoying a success, before it becomes a classic and
when the only process of selection it has undergone
one far less stringent than that of historical selection is
the. test of normal sales through bookshops.
This may be a very profitable practice, but unfortunately
many publishers have not yet understood the machinery
of this kind of sale. They wait too long after the book's
success in an ordinary edition before prolonging that
success in a mass-circulation edition.
z
o
A FAREWELL
TO ARMS
ERNEST
HEMINGWAY
On July 30, 1935 bookshops
and bookstalls in Great
Britain first displayed ten
new, paperbacked books in
bold orange, blue and green
covers decorated with a black
and white penguin. They
included novels, thrillers, and
biographies, of a standard
not often found at that time
among books sold for six¬
pence. Among the authors
of these first ten Penguin
Books were Ernest Heming¬
way (cover left), André
Maurois, Compton Mackenzie
and Agatha Christie. Penguins
broke new ground in pub¬
lishing and triggered off
developments which have
touched nearly every
book - producing country.
10
They imagine that the book's success in an ordinary
edition must be exhausted before launching it among what
they believe to be an extension of the same public. In
actual fact experience proves that the ideal moment for
switching a book from the ordinary to the mass-circulation
edition is at the height of its success in the former edition.
Far from interfering with its success in that form, the
mass edition provides a fresh impetus, exerting an infjuence
on the ordinary edition at the same time as it builds up its
own success through the interest the book arouses in the
cultivated sector.
In advanced twentieth century societies, the cultivated
public and the public at large come into contact daily,
often sharing the same media of communication and
expression. A book discussed in the literary columns of a
newspaper is not overlooked by readers of the paper who
are primarily interested in the sports pages or the crime
reports.
The solitary disadvantage of the system, therefore, is not
an economic one. It lies in the fact that the switching of a
book from the ordinary to the mass-circulation edition is a
unilateral operation. The book in question has been
lifted up and stimulated by a cultivated literary opinion.
Now it is imposed on the mass readership which unfortu¬
nately has no feedback circuit through which to bring its
opinion to bear on subsequent productions.
HIS brings us to the third type of mass cir¬
culation book the one produced directly for
the mass market and under pressure from that public.
These are, broadly speaking, the new literary books in the
usual sense of the expression. Unhappily, experience
demonstrates that such books are extremely rare. Publi¬
shers have not yet clearly understood the nature of the
instrument they possess. Still less do they know how to
use it. They are handicapped by obstacles of an institu¬
tional kind, unsatisfactory distribution channels, the
indifference or hostility of critics, representing the
opposition of the cultivated sector to the mass-circulation
book.
Even so, and this should be emphasized, the mass-cir¬
culation book will never destroy books in ordinary editions
or even the semi-de luxe book. On the contrary, by giving
unlimited scope to the bases for literary communication,
by transforming reading into a true, everyday activity, and
one which is an integral part of man's existence, it will
awaken a new interest in and a new enthusiasm for books.
Those who fear that the semi-de luxe book and the hand¬
some, top-quality book are doomed to be ousted by the
mass-circulation book are mistaken. The desire to own
books published in beautifully finished editions, solid and
lasting, pleasant to contemplate and to touch, represents
on the part of the reader, a final choice which can only be
the outcome of a long experience of reading. If so many
imitation de-luxe editions are now being distributed by
various clubs and if books are often regarded as decorative
elements or status symbols, this is because in such cases
the possession of a book is unrelated to the act of reading,
because there is a breach between the book and its
purpose.
As living standards rise throughout the world, the quality
book becomes accessible to more and more deeper and
deeper strata of the population; but reading, in the sense of
conscious reading, what we call literary reading, remains
the prerogative of a minority. Thanks to the mass-circulation
book, this situation is changing and we may fairly hope that
in the course of the next fifty years this type of book, the
"reading machine", will make its full contribution to the
life of the new societies which will inherit our world.
ROBERT ESCARPIT is professor of comparative litera¬
ture in the Faculty of Letters and Humanistic Sciences of
Bordeaux, France; professor at the Institute of Political
Studies, Bordeaux; and director of the Centre de Sociolo¬
gie des Faits Littéraires, Bordeaux. Professor Escarpit ¡s a
critic, novelist, literary historian and specialist in publishing.
He is also a regular contributor of humorous articles to the
Paris newspaper, Le Monde. His latest book La Révolu¬
tion du Livre (The Revolution in Books) has just been
published by Unesco, and will soon appear in English.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
In a supermarket (left) a housewife interrupts grocery shopping to buy books. Right, mobile
shop brings new books to factory workers. Forerunner of press, radio, films and tele¬
vision, the book has now taken its place alongside these media of mass communication.
WANTED: A NEW DIALOGUE
BETWEEN AUTHORS & READERS
The impact of the mass circulation book is not merely
one of quantity. What we are witnessing today is
a complete transformation in ideas about books and
about the relationship between the author and his new
public. The problem of opening a "dialogue" between
author and reader is examined by Robert Escarpit in,
"La Révolution du Livre" (The Revolution in Books)
from which the following text is adapted. Professor
Escarpit's book will appear in English later this year.
HE writer has not yet found his place in the
contemporary community. The reason for this
is perhaps that the modern community is an enormous
mutual security structure designed to protect its members
from the hazards of nature in the raw and man's estate.
But there is no way of protecting writers as such. True,
they can be given the same social security as all other
citizens, old-age pensions, free medical care, and legal aid,
but they cannot be insured against their literary hazards.
We are now sufficiently well acquainted with the
mechanics of literary life to appreciate that the writer pro¬
poses and the public disposes and so it must be. Liter¬
ature is born out of this intercommunication, derives its
sustenance therefrom and develops because of it. But it
¡s a murderous system in the sense that, for every 'thousand
works conceived, ten come to birth and one to maturity.
The proportion can, of course, be improved by various
technical devices, notably by broadening the social bases
of intercommunication, by improving distribution channels,
by giving the reader better and more frequent opportunities
of expressing his considered judgement, but the hazards
cannot be eliminated nor even reduced to any significant
extent.
... A writer's success is not quite the same as a publi¬
sher's. It is not enough for a book to sell well and provide
a certain return. . How indeed could we calculate the
interest on an investment reckoned in terms of life, thought
and action? Whatever' his financial gains, the writer never
recovers his capital; he works without security. We can,
none the less, accept an economic definition of a writer's
success: it is the point at which the .sales of one of his
books enable him to live by his writing. This point, more¬
over, represents another aspect of success the point at
which a writer saturates his possible public.
There is too much talk nowadays of how reading should
be "guided" and readers "directed." These are dangerous 11
terms which, in any case, have nothing to do with the true
role of criticism, which is to bear witness rather than
to teach.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
A NEW DIALOGUE (Cont'd)
The snares of success
Nowadays, the critic can speak to the general public
on behalf of literature and can reach that public. He need
do no more than become an adapter or commentator. A
sensitive and straightforward analysis of a text is tremen¬
dously effective on the television screen. The interpreta¬
tion of a literary masterpiece on television or radio may
perhaps be a misconstruction of the work, but it is certainly
of the type of those that have been called creative miscon¬
structions. Film producers have always encouraged people
to see the film after reading the book. To read the
book after seeing the film is no less to be recommended
and in all probability more fruitful.
Any literary criticism suited to mass circulation literature
should be based on a knowledge of the literary behaviour
of the public at large, acquired from inside, and personal
experience of it. In the extreme case, it may even be
considered that the critic is not absolutely needed as an
intermediary. In the socialist countries, contacts between
writers and workers in various sectors are systematically
organized, being based on living as a community and
working as a team.
These methods are undoubtedly effective but it is diffi¬
cult to do without an organizer to establish a common
language and prevent misunderstandings. Here, perhaps, is
the new figure needed in our present age the cultural
leader who does not restrict himself to the facile resources
of image and sound but uses them in order to undertake,
with all the intellectual humility and team spirit required,
the difficult task of organizing communication between the
people at large and the individual.
The success of mass-circulation literature depends on
the existence of such exchanges. The meeting ground
will necessarily be non-literary precisely because the
exchanges must go beyond the limits of the cultivated
public. Even if a writer and a reader are physically and
intellectually very distant from one another, the sharing
of trade union, political, religious or even just sports activi¬
ties may make it possible to create the conditions required
for communication between them.
It is here that the literary prize, so often and unfairly
denounced, may take on a fresh significance. Such
attempts at making a responsible selection from a necess¬
arily anarchic output are useful and even vital in them-
I.EOXAIll) HKIiXSTKIVS YOINU PKIII'I.K'S CnXCKKTS
I.ir n-rtillnr ,n>i i;.r-:ni..
12
INTERNATIONAL PUBLISHERS
CONGRESS
Four subjects of special interest to Unescoobs¬
tacles to the free flow of books, international copy¬
right, educational publishing and books for deve¬
loping countries were among the topics discussed
by the 17th Triennial Congress of the International Pub¬
lishers Association, which was held in Washington D.C.
(U.S.A.) from May 30 to June 5. The theme of the
Congress was "The World and the Book : Publishing in
an Age of Change."
In a message to the Congress, the Director-General
of Unesco, M. René Maheu, reminded delegates that
the historic role of books as a vehicle for the communi¬
cation of ideas has been revolutionized by social and
technological change. "The acute shortage of books
which exists In the vast and populous developing regions
of the world is a matter of common concern," said Mr.
Maheu. "This poverty of reading material . . . constitutes
a formidable barrier to education and to social and
economic advancement generally. The General Confe¬
rence of Unesco, at its last session, called for a co¬
ordinated programme designed to increase the availa¬
bility of books in the developing countries ... I believe
that the International Publishers Association and Unesco
are uniquely equipped, in partnership, to provide the
impetus for this great enterprise."
Illustration from
"Leonard Bern¬
stein's Young Peo¬
ple's Concerts," a
U.S. book record¬
ing T.V. program¬
mes on music
for young people.
(Simon and Shus-
ter. New York.)
Illustration from "If
Apples Had Teeth,"
an amusing collec¬
tion of illustrated
"ifs" by Milton
and Shirley Gla¬
ser, published by
Alfred A. Knopf,
New York.
selves. They essentially imply an academy, for through
them a representative selection of cultivated people belong¬
ing to a certain social group clearly and firmly express the
preferences of that group. .
In various forms, the system operated very satisfactorily
for centuries, in fact so long as the cultivated group
remained relatively small and homogeneous. The diffi¬
culties began in the nineteenth century, and have steadily
increased up to the present, as new social groups took
their place in forming literary opinion, set up their own
academic standards and developed their own judgements.
One of the results of this increase in the number of acade¬
mies, whether avowedly such or not, is the present plethora
of literary prizes which deprives the selection of all its
value.
But there is something still more serious to be consi¬
dered. In an élite culture, values remain stable whereas,
in a mass culture, they are fluid and constantly called in
question since what is involved is a way of life rather than
a way of being. The academic accolade of the literary
prize is, in the literal sense of the word, a consecration.
It marks out the author as one entitled to the enduring
respect of his peers for certain merit which can never
again be depreciated, but it also places him irremediably
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
out of reach of the people as a whole by transforming him
into a celebrity.
This phenomenon of celebrity, very clearly recognized
by Carlyle as early as 1840, dates from the earliest large-
scale printings at the beginning of the nineteenth century,
one of the most spectacular examples at that time was
the Byron cult. By no means all the winners of the Prix
Goncourt or the Nobel Prizes in our own day receive
the hero worship from which Byron suffered and which
was almost comparable with that now extended towards
film stars, but the mere prestige of their award turns
them, as it were, into institutions, legends, totems or, at
best, shining examples. This is one of the swiftest forms
of that literary death which accompanies success and,
unless he has an exceptional determination to recreate
himself and maintain his independence, no writer can hope
to escape it.
With or without mass-circulation books, societies pos¬
sessing a long-established literary tradition will find it
difficult to preserve themselves from the academic reaction
and will long continue to treat their writers as intellectual
heroes, but the younger nations where literature is currently
emerging must beware of the snare of institutiona¬
lization. .
If they set up literary prizes and they would be wrong
to disdain this method of selecting and encouraging writers
they will have to ensure that these reflect broad currents
of opinion deriving from the inmost feelings of the people,
even perhaps before the intellect comes into play at all.
With all due respect, it may be asked whether those
mysterious groundswells which lift up to the heights of
glory this or that singer or musician, or even this or that
poet who has chosen the record as his medium, may not
be more effective and more authentic than the pondered
judgements of the experts. The ideal would be for the
two forms of evaluation to be in agreement but this is still,
for the time being, a vain hope.
We must, after all, face up to the facts. The present mu¬
tation in the world of books may prove successful but will
be neither complete nor final. We may talk of mass circu¬
lation but by no means all the "masses" are involved. Even
in the most advanced countries, only a fraction of those
able to read will take to reading during the present stage
that fraction which succeeds in gaining control of the
social structures required for that end.
In the developing countries and we must bear in mind
that the reading public in Asia represents a quarter of the
total population and in Africa one-eighth many other sta¬
ges and many other mutations will be needed before what¬
ever is to replace books as they now are (perhaps at no
very distant date) can ensure that the messages of infor¬
mation and culture circulate freely among all men.
But even then there will still be active and passive
readers. There will always be people who, through idleness,
timidity or inclination, will decline communication with the
writer. There will always be those who love books as
objects and will not dissociate the message of the binder
and the printer from that of the writer.
This is of no great importance. The main thing is to
ensure that active readers should be more and more num-
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
Unesco - A. Tessore
THE FASCINATION OF STORY BOOKS. Children choose books from a mobile library
serving a Budapest suburb. -All over the world books for children and young people have
multiplied enormously in the past twenty years, and many are now illustrated by leading artists.
In the U.S.A. over 220,000 copies priced at less than S1.00 each were sold in 1964.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
A NEW DIALOGUE (Cont'd)
To vanquish hunger
of the mind
14
erous and more and more receptive. There is no reason
why plastic values should not be integrated with the values
of action, intelligence and sensitivity, in fact with all those
values which give reading its place in human life. The
revolution in publishing is the most liberal of all revolutions.
All it asks is that there be neither prejudice nor inflexibi¬
lity. Fetishism or fanaticism attached to books are incom¬
patible with the generosity of books. Books are like bread.
Throughout the world, the production of grain and the basic
foodstuff derived from it was primitive man's great victory
over hunger. The result was that bread became something
almost holy, the symbol of liberating labour, survival and
communion. The instinctive reactions of many peoples
especially the French still embody this sort of innate res¬
pect for bread, which is obscurely enshrined in their collec¬
tive memory as a saviour.
Books are the object of the same sort of unacknowledged
veneration since they were the bread of the mind, the great
victory achieved by somewhat less primitive men over
ignorance and the slavery it means. A book which does
not last, an ephemeral book, a book which is an act and
not necessarily a lasting reality, a treasure to be preserved,
a possession for all time, is something which profoundly
shocks our instinctive feelings and may even disgust us.
T the same time, we are very well aware that
^the poor man's bread in the present day world
has ceased to be a symbol and has become a mere
metaphor, and a bad one at that. We know that the world's
hunger will not be overcome this time by the individual
magic of the ear or the loaf, but by a vast collective effort
bringing into play all the scientific, technical, and mechanical
resources of the advanced civilizations, by a profound and
systematic reform of social structures, by a concerted
world policy which will affect many other sectors besides
those of agriculture and food.
Nor can the great hunger of the mind be overcome in any
other way. The individual demands of writers, the refined
tastes of cultivated book lovers, should be given neither
more nor less weight in our plans for the future than the
majestic gesture of the sower or the gastronomy of Brillât-
Savarin in the discussions of the Food and Agriculture
Organization.
We must deny nothing, but nor must we interpose anything
between books and life, and especially not myths. We are
living in an age when great things are being done by teams
assisted by machines. We readily accept this for the arts
which have developed along with mass civilization, such as
radio, television and films, not to mention the theatre, where
there is direct contact with the audience and where the
principle has always been more or less accepted. We must
now go on to accept it in respect of books.
It goes without saying that the very nature of reading will
always necessitate a greater measure of solitude than other
forms of communication or artistic expression, but the soli¬
tude of the writer, like the solitude of the reader, is not
anti-social. It is only the means whereby each may find the
other. A man reading alone in his room often has more
companions than if he were watching a film with a thousand
other spectators in a cinema.
It is this inherent virtue of books which must be main¬
tained and developed. Dissemination, limitless and cease¬
lessly renewed communication among all men that is the
true function of the book. Once it ceases to fulfil it,
however fine its appearance and however noble its content,
it is merely so much waste paper, a soulless treasure.
A "bibliocopter" lands a new stock of books for a library in an isolated
village in the mountains of Soviet Turkestan, Central Asia. Today the
U.S.S.R. has some 400,000 public libraries of all kinds, from the huge Lenin
Library in Moscow down to local lending libraries in factories and farms.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
TWO-THIRDS OF WORLD'S BOOKS
PRODUCED BY TWELVE COUNTRIES
\
APN
A book at least 49 pages
Until November 1964 there was no
uniform international definition of what
constitutes a book. The variety of criteria
used in different countries for defining a
book complicated the work of preparing
and interpreting publishing statistics. In
Italy, for example, a book was classed as
having at least 100 pages; India had no
stipulations on size. In November 1964,
the General Conference of Unesco unani¬
mously adopted a "Recommendation ' con¬
cerning the international standardization of
statistics relating to book production and
periodicals", which defines a book as "a
non-periodical printed publication of at least
49 pages, exclusive of the cover pages".
This recommendation classifies a pamphlet
as "a non-periodical publication of at least
five but not more than 48 pages, exclusive
of the cover pages", and also defines a
first edition, a re-edition, a reprint, a
translation and a title.
Publisher's windfall
A single best-seller, published in several
hundreds of thousands of copies and intelli¬
gently exploited, has often kept a publish¬
ing house going for several years, counter¬
balancing careless management, errors of
judgement and commercial blunders serious
enough to endanger the business.
Literature and languages
Twelve literary languages are each
commonly used by more than 50 million
people. In order of numerical importance
they are: Chinese, English, Russian, Hindi,
Spanish, German, Japanese, Bengali, Arabic,
French, Portuguese and Italian. The English
language area includes two great economic
powers, U.S.A. and U.K., and also takes
in the countries of the British Common¬
wealth. Like the English, the Spanish
group is widely dispersed, but the nations
comprising it are less economically deve¬
loped. The French group also has branches
extending overseas (Canada, Haiti, West
Indies and Africa), but its numerical impor¬
tance comes from France, Belgium and
Switzerland.
World book production
Total annual world production of titles
between 1960 and 1963 was as follows:
360,000; 375,000; 385,000 and 400,000. The
English, French, German and Spanish share
of this production totalled 34% In 1952
and about 36% in 1962. In the English-
language area, the U.S.A. is now replacing
the U.K. as the leading producer. The
sudden rise in U.S. production is largely
due to the mass publication of paperbacks.
Paperback sales in the U.S. had already
reached one million daily by 1960.
In 1962 production in the socialist countries
(not Including mainland China) almost exact¬
ly equalled the combined production of the
English, French, German and Spanish ling¬
uistic areas. It totalled some 125,000 titles
of world production.
Giants of publishing
Six countries produce more than
20,000 titles a year. By volume of produc¬
tion they are: U.S.S.R., mainland China,
Germany (figures for the Federal Republic
alone or including those of Eastern Ger¬
many), Japan and U.S.A. Six other coun¬
tries France, India, Spain, Italy, the
Netherlands and Czechoslovakia each
publish about 10,000 titles annually. Twelve
countries alone produce two-thirds of
the world's books. The 80,000 or so
volumes published in the U.S.S.R. are not
all books according to the 1964 Unesco
definition. Many Soviet titles are actually
counted several times, since the figure of
80,000 relates not only to books in the
Russian language, but to volumes in
93 languages (61 used by the peoples of
the U.S.S.R. and 32 foreign languages)
Yet even if only the works publish¬
ed in Russian and distributed through
normal commercial channels are counted,
Soviet production is still the highest of
any country in the world, with over
30.000 titles.
One man's book
India ranks as a leading book publisher
because it counts even short pamphlets
as books. It should actually be classed
much lower in world publishing. If Italy
had a less strict definition of books it
would be on the same footing as France in
terms of production, and the same is true
of Czechoslovakia. No details are available
on the classification of books in mainland
China.
Growing need for paper
In 1950, the English speaking countries
of America were consuming more than half
of the world's supply of printing paper. By
1960 this consumption had dropped to
43.2%. During the same period Europe
and Latin America remained at the same
level while the Pacific region basically
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Australia and New Zealand showed a
slight advance.
The most spectacular progress was made
by the Afro-Asian countries: an increase of
242.5% for Africa and 512.3% for Asia.
In Asia this advance was not limited to
economically developed countries such as
Japan and mainland China, but also extend¬
ed over the whole of this vast area where
such countries as Burma, Cambodia, Iraq
and Israel increased their consumption of
printing and writing paper tenfold. The
outstanding case was Syria whose
consumption per head rose from .01 kilo¬
grammes per year in 1950 to 0.3 kilogram¬
mes in 1960. The same development is
taking place in Africa where paper
consumption in the newly-independent
countries rose from 6,000 tons in 1950 to
90,000 tons in 1960.
A rare book: the best-seller
Best-sellers are extremely rare and repre¬
sent barely two to three per cent of
successful books. The best-seller is deter¬
mined not by the number of copies sold
but by the type of sales pattern. A book
may be a best-seller with a sale of 50,000
just as easily as with one of three million.
Very few books have a long life. Out of
a hundred published, scarcely ten sell a
year later and ten times fewer twenty years
later.
Translation test
Books are first tried out in a certain
literary market, language area, ideological
bloc or State. When a book fails this test,
there is no longer any question of translat¬
ing it even though, in other countries
there may be an unsuspected public eager
to welcome it.
Books and world trade
The book trade occupies a relatively
minor place in international trade. The
world's chief book exporters are U.K.,
Netherlands, U.S.A., France, Switzerland
and the Federal Republic of Germany. In
none of these countries, however, do book
exports account for as much as one per
cent of global national exports. Yet the
volume of trading in books is continually
increasing. In terms of tonnage rather than
price, book exports have doubled in most
countries over the past ten years.
Costly transport
16
In "Trade Barriers to Knowledge",
published in Paris in 1956, Unesco review¬
ed the diversity of laws existing in 92 coun¬
tries. The Universal Postal Union has
urged its member countries to system¬
atically reduce postal rates for books
and to simplify customs and administrative
formalities generally. Great progress has
been made in this direction since 1952 and
some fifty states have acted on the Univer¬
sal Postal Union recommendations. Since
1953 airline companies in the International
Air Transport Association have applied the
tariff for periodicals and catalogues to
books.
But the transport of books is still costly.
Even in countries where books are class¬
ed as printed matter, the cost of sending
a volume of average size is 3 U.S. cents.
This sum may seem trivial for a single,
expensive book, but when bulk distribution
is involved it affects the retail price con¬
siderably.
Major exporters
Nine-tenths of U.S.S.R. book exports are
taken by the socialist countries. Just under
half of U.S. exports go to other English-
speaking countries, where they meet compe¬
tition from Great Britain. Excluding books
sent to other socialist countries, Soviet
exports are as follows: Western Europe,
41%; English-speaking America, 21%; Far
East, 16%; Latin America, 6%; Near East,
4%; Africa, 3%; miscellaneous, 7%.
Excluding books sent to English-language
areas, American book exports are as
follows: Far East, 33%; Latin America,
27%; Europe, 25%; Near East, 8%; Africa,
4%; miscellaneous, 8%.
The importance of these enormous dis¬
tribution channels increases yearly. One
of their chief advantages is their suitability
for distributing the functional type of book
in the developing countries. In nearly every
case technical reasons prevent the importer
countries from producing these types of
books at present.
Decade of changes
World book production as a whole
increased by some 40% between 1952 and
1962, but dropped in several countries.
Among middle-range producers whose
publishing declined were Belgium
(25% drop) and Italy (16%). Some coun¬
tries made spectacular advances. Mainland
China's production, increased tenfold in
six years. U.S. production rose by 85%
to rival Japan's for 4th world place; ten
years earlier the U.S.A. was sixth. The
new publishing status of English-speaking
America is confirmed by the rise of
Canada's production from 684 titles to
3,600 in ten years.
A barrier to books
One obstacle to the circulation of books
is the diversity of the world's languages.
Twelve main languages are spoken by more
than three-quarters of the world's popula¬
tion in the following proportions: Chinese,
25%; English, 11%; Russian, 8.3%; Hindi,
6.25%; Spanish, 6.25%; German, 3.75%;
Japanese, 3.75%; Bengali, 3%; Arabic,
2.7%; French, 2.7%; Portuguese, 2.5% and
Italian, 2.1%. Written languages present
a different picture. Using only eight lan¬
guages it is possible to communicate with
three-quarters of the people in the world:
This time the breakdown is: English, 18.1%;
Chinese, 16.9%; Russian, 15.9%; Spanish,
5.2%; German, 5%; Japanese, 5%; French,
3.2% and Italian, 2.4%.
Channel for free thought
The Netherlands has a long tradition of
publishing and bookselling. When absolute
monarchies were interfering with the flow
of ideas in the 17th and 18th centuries,
Dutch books kept open a channel for the
expression of free thought. Today the
Netherlands receives much from abroad
(16% of its book production relates to
translations) and exports a great deal.
Between 1946 and 1960, its book exports
rose from $1.3 million to $33 million. Out
of 7,893 titles published in 1960, 1,140
were in foreign languages.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The growth
of the Hispanic
book market
SOME 145 million people live in
the Spanish-speaking cultural
area of the world, where pros¬
pects of an expanding book market
are today limited by problems of
economic development which vary
from country to country.
Spain was the chief book supplier
to Latin America until 1936, the year
of the Spanish Civil War. The
interruption of its book printing pro¬
duced an overnight growth of publish¬
ing houses in the New World, mainly
in Mexico and Argentina. After the
Second World War this became a
book production boom. More recently,
inflation has become widespread on
the Latin American continent and
foreign currency restrictions have
been introduced, thus limiting the pur¬
chase of paper, ink, machinery and
other supplies and restricting pay¬
ments for copyright in the case of
translations. With the situation thus
reversed, the sales of books produced
in Spain are regaining their former
importance in Latin America.
Book exports from Spain to this
vast region totalled five million, pese¬
tas in 1940; in 1963 they reached an
all-time high of 1,348 million pesetas.
Over the past three years, Spanish
book exports to Latin America have
doubled. Spain's book production has
increased 30% in the past five years
and Latin America has taken 40% of
these books.
In 1963, Spain's 743 publishing
houses put on sale 8,694 original
titles. These can be classed, with
approximate figures, as follows: Liter¬
ature, 2,800; social sciences, 1,800;
applied sciences, 1,100; theology and
religion, 1,000; history and geography,
700; fine arts, 500; pure sciences,
350; philology, 200; philosophy, 180;
general subjects, 160.
About 14% of all books printed
in Spain were translations of foreign
works. In 1963, 694 titles were trans¬
lated from English, 593 from French,
320 from German, 1 1 1 from Italian
and 180 from other languages.
In Argentina, the really striking
development in book publishing has
come during the past thirty years. In
1936 its entire production consisted
of 451 scientific and 372 literary
works; by 1963, production had risen
to 3,390 titles, and of these, 2,196
were chiefly made up of novels and
short stories, geography books, school
textbooks and dictionaries. In 1963
Argentina printed over 29 million
books.
Argentina's book production (in
terms of wholesale prices) has been
estimated at 4 000 million pesos a year
between 1960-1962. In 1963, Argentina
exported nearly seven million copies
of books and other publications. This
figure excludes orders despatched by
air.
Argentina and Mexico are Spain's
two chief competitors in the Latin
American market. In Mexico, book
production and sales have gone
through a similar kind of process to
that in Argentina. Mexico's annual
production was less than 1,000 books
between 1948 and 1955, but in 1962
it produced 3,760. Eustasio Garcia,
the Argentinian publisher, has estimat¬
ed that there are some 10,000 book¬
shops in Latin America, 900 of which
are located in Mexico.
The official production and free dis¬
tribution of primary school textbooks
in Mexico in recent years deserves
special mention. Since 1959, when
the national plan of Mexico's Educa¬
tion Minister, Jaime Torres Bodet (a
former Director-General of Unesco)
went into operation, over 100 million
textbooks have been distributed free
of charge to schoolchildren. This
year 21 million will be distributed.
Brazil occupies a unique place in
Latin America since, for linguistic
reasons, it does not export its books
to the rest of the continent, yet
appears to have top place among book
producers. Latest official statistics
relate to 1959 when a total of 5,337
titles was published. After Argentina
and Mexico in second and third pla¬
ces comes Chile which published 1,040
works in 1962. It is followed by Peru
and Cuba with 791 and 736 titles
respectively in 1963.
In Cuba, efforts to provide books
for all sections of the population are
made by different organizations. The
"Editorial Nacional de Cuba'', set up
by the government in May 1962 and
directed by the Cuban novelist, Alejo
Carpentier, prints national and foreign
works, on an average basis of 20,000
copies per title, but in some cases
reaching the 50,000 and 100,000 mark.
This national enterprise published
16,500,000 copies in 1963 and plans
to reach 22 million this year.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Top : at the keyboard of a photocomposing
machine, the operator selects a fresh type
by moving a control on the auxiliary panel.
Centre: the latest electronic equipment is
increasingly used to direct and speed up
photo-composition processes. Bottom: hun¬
dreds of characters cover this glass disc. As
it rotates the image of each character selected
is projected by a light and recorded on film.
BOOKS
PRINTED WITH
A CAMERA
NTIL recently the two great advan¬
ces in book printing were the use
of movable type composed by hand and the
introduction of metal type-casting machines
in the 19th century. Today, a new era in
printing has begun with the use of photo¬
composition, or filmsetting, which produces
texts directly on film that can be used for
engraving and printing, thus eliminating the
use of raised type.
Book publishers can expect to benefit in
terms of faster production and lower costs
from this new technique as it becomes com¬
bined with new discoveries In electronics.
Since the first photocomposing machine
was devised about 40 years ago a dozen or
more different types have been developed.
One ultra-modern one which Is largely elec¬
tronic in operation looks like an ordinary
metal office desk with a built-in typewriter.
The operator types texts on this central key¬
board and selects the kind and size of type
required on an auxiliary control board.
CONT'D ON PACE 20
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
tr
* : .
Book texts on tapes. Typed on the key¬
board of a photocomposing machine
texts are recorded in code on perfor¬
ated tape. Photographic unit decodes
tapes and produces film prints of the
pages ready for engraving and printing.
Photos © Paul Almasy, Paris
:
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
BOOKS PRINTED
WITH A CAMERA
(Cont'd)
In modern book
publishing, top-
quality illustra¬
tions are not only
found in works on
art and de luxe
editions but have
also become a fea¬
ture of low-priced
publications.
Every effort is
made to attain the
highest standards
of reproduction.
Left, colour illus¬
trations are given
an extra-close
scrutiny. Below, a
final check of
pages composed
directly on film.
A machine of this kind can compose texts
directly on film or can record them in code
on perforated tape. This can be stored and
later fed into an electronically-operated pho¬
tographic unit which, automatically sets type
on film in response to the information on the
tape, working faster than human hands.
At some future time book publishers may
deliver all their copy to the printer on tapes.
Electronically-controlled machines will then
decode the tapes and in a single operation
produce film prints of the book pages ready
for engraving and printing.
A big advantage of photocomposing ma¬
chines Is their compactness. An installation
covering 50 square metres can do the work
of present equipment needing ten times this
space. In one machine a rotating disc
bearing nearly 1 ,500 characters replaces over
one and a half tons of lead matrixes needed
in metal type casting.
Photosetting may also solve problems
created by the intricate forms, vowel accents
and, in some cases, the sheer volume of
characters in some of the world's complex
writing systems, for which metal type has
often been found inadequate. Research has
shown that photocomposing machines could
do the job. A machine for the Chinese lan¬
guage, for example, would need only twenty-
six signs on Its basic keyboard to select
any of the thousands of known characters.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO AND THE WORLD
OF BOOKS
by Julian Behrstock
0^ OOKS permeate the whole of Unesco's pro-
*^ gramme to such an extent that it is difficult
to isolate and define them as a separate factor. They are
basic to the achievement of almost all of the Organiza¬
tion's objectives universal primary education no less than
the mutual appreciation of cultural values or the advance¬
ment of science and technology.
Unesco's interest in books stems from its Constitution,
which assigns to it the promotion of "the free flow of
ideas by word and image" and of measures designed "to
give the people of all countries access to the printed
and published material produced by any of them." Twenty
years later this Constitutional point was reaffirmed by the
General Conference of Unesco in a resolution calling atten¬
tion to "the importance of publishing activities" and laying
the foundations for a new programme of action in the
book field.
As this new programme takes shape, a backward glance
at the work of the preceding two decades also shows a
wide-ranging record of achievement. For example:
A Universal Copyright Convention was established assur¬
ing a just recompense for authors and at the same time
encouraging the publication and distribution of their works
in countries other than their own. The Convention filled
a significant gap in international copyright legislation.
An international agreement was adopted removing tariff
and other trade obstacles to the free flow of books. The
agreement became widely accepted as an international
standard for the unimpeded circulation of books throughout
the world. Two other international agreements granted
facilities for the international exchange of educational and
government publications.
A coupon scheme was instituted overcoming foreign
currency difficulties. Some 27 million dollars in coupons
were issued for the purchase of books and other publi¬
cations.
Postal and transport charges for the dispatch of books
were lowered as a result of Unesco proposals to interna¬
tional rate-fixing organizations.
In order to help chart systematically the world pattern of
the book trade, a recommendation was adopted establish¬
ing international standards for the uniform classification
of book statistics.
A centre for the promotion of reading materials in South
Asia was established at Karachi in 1958. It conducted
workshops and seminars on all aspects of the book trade;
encouraged the development of professional associations;
awarded some 50 fellowships for training abroad; and was
responsible for the appearance of about 400 publications
in the languages of the region.
In Africa two centres were set up which helped to
promote educational publishing. One, at Accra (Ghana),
held seminars in West and East Africa on the preparation
of textbooks, including the training of authors and illustra
tors. The other, at Yaounde- (Cameroon), equipped with
a publishing unit, printed textbooks for various classroom
levels as well as reading materials for newly literate adults.
Through the intermediary of Unesco, textbooks for African
schools were also printed abroad without charge.
Writers in the developing countries were encouraged
and trained at literary workshops and were awarded travel
grants for the gathering of material. In the specialized
field of science writing, the first of a series of pilot
projects was launched at Sao Paulo (Brazil) where Latin
American professors acquired training to undertake local
authorship of science materials for the classroom.
To stimulate and develop public libraries, which in some
countries account for the purchase of half of all works
distributed, model libraries were created at New Delhi,
Medellin (Colombia) and Enegu (Nigeria). Training centres
for librarianship were established at Dakar (Senegal) and
Kampala (Uganda). National bibliographical centres were
similarly assisted and publications issued which provided
up-to-date information on the availability of books.
A Unesco Collection of Representative Works served to
make more widely known, in translation, outstanding lite¬
rary works drawn from diverse cultures. Almost 200 works
were translated from some 40 different languages and
published in English and French. Index Translationum
was published annually listing books published throughout
the world during the previous year which are translations
from the original version. The 16th edition in 1965 listed
some 35,000 translations published in 69 countries (see
p. 34).
Studies were published, such as "Books for All", by
R.E. Barker, which reviewed and focussed public attention
on obstacles to the flow of books. ("The Revolution in
Books", by Robert Escarpit, which has just been published
in French [see page 4] is a sequel to the Barker study
published ten years earlier). A brochure on "Books for the
Developing Countries" has been published in 1965.
Studies on books were but one aspect of Unesco's
concern with publishing during the past two decades.
Unesco initiated or itself published a total of some 4,000
titles, in which an array of subjects in all its fields of
interest were looked at from an international point of view.
An indirect contribution to book promotion was the
Unesco campaign to combat illiteracy and so to add to
the ranks of the reading public the many millions at present
unable to read or write, who number more than two-fifths
of the adult population of the globe.
The list could be lengthened but it suffices to show the
broad range and concrete character of book activities
throughout the whole of Unesco's programme.
These activities evolved during a period of swift change n-t
in the world pattern of book production and consumption. ¿'
It was during this period from the mid-1 940s to the
mid-1960's that advances in printing, publishing and distri-
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO AND BOOKS (Cont'd)
Textbooks make up 90 °/o of all books
in the developing nations
bution techniques made it feasible to produce low-priced
good-quality books on a vast scale. It was then, too, that
the paperback phenomenon achieved the proportions of a
"revolution", in which a million copies a day were sold
in one country alone.
T the same time, although the demand for
Lbooks in the developing countries surged
forward on the tide of indépendance, production remains
sharply below the requirements of their peoples. Asia
(Japan excepted), with more than half of the world's
population, accounts for only 17 per cent of the 400,000
or so book titles appearing annually throughout the world.
In Africa, fewer than ten countries regularly publish books
and the number of titles is less than two per cent of the
world total.
Hence the larger proportion by far of books being read
in most parts of Asia and especially of Africa continues to
be produced in technically advanced countries chiefly
those of Europe and North America. Yet, great as are
the present needs for books in the developing countries,
the spread of literacy and increases in population and
per capita income presage a more acute situation in the
years ahead.
Increasing the flow of books from present world centres
of production, however necessary, is recognized to be
only a stop-gap solution. National aspirations, expansion
of domestic industry and, above all, the production of
books closely attuned to the readers' culture and tastes
all these factors impel the developing countries to establish
their own capacity to write, publish and distribute books.
The creation of indigenous publishing industries in Asia
and Africa, however, encounters formidable deficiencies in
almost all the resources and skills required, ranging from
authorship to printing facilities, from paper supplies to
managerial personnel.
The first claim on meagre publishing facilities, moreover,
inevitably has been the production of books for the class¬
room. So pronounced has been the trend that textbooks
are now estimated to account for no less than 90 per cent
of all books read in the developing countries. The result
is an undiversified publishing pattern, offering relatively
limited fare for general readers, including new literates.
Thus, the "book gap", as it has come to be termed, widens
as the extension of education extends the demand for text¬
books to train new generations of readers whose book
appetites will, in turn, require a more variegated publishing
output.
I
22
T was against this background of striking tech¬
nological progress, on the one hand, and of vast
unfulfilled needs, on the other, that the General Conference
of Unesco, in November 1964, considered a proposal
submitted by the delegation of Czechoslovakia for Unesco
to embark on a new programme of book development. Two
months earlier a similar proposal had emerged from a
meeting convened at Washington, D.C. by the U.S. Agency
for International Development in which it was recommended
that Unesco should assume a role of leadership in the book
development field. The premise underlying both proposals
was that, in addition to its continuing book activities, the
time had now come for Unesco to make a concerned attack
on the central problem of helping to build indigenous
publishing capacity in the developing countries.
The General Conference resolution, adopted unani¬
mously, noted the importance of publications in "fostering
mutual understanding and economic and social develop¬
ment." It called for action "to stimulate and encourage the
publication of low-priced books, particularly for newly
literate adults and for young people in the developing
countries." Finally, it invited all concerned to study means
of strengthening international co-operation in the field of
publishing and dissemination of literature.
More specifically, the General Conference took three
decisions. The first was that the development programme
would be launched with a series of regional conferences,
the first for Asia in 1966; a second, for Africa, was envisaged
for 1967; and a third was to be held subsequently for Latin
America. Secondly, primary responsibility for the develop¬
ment programme was centred in one section of the Unesco
Secretariat, thus establishing for the first time a focal point
for the Organization's diverse book activities. Thirdly, the
General Conference invited the Director-General to con¬
sider presenting for 1967-1968 a co-ordinated programme
designed to promote the production and distribution of
books in the developing countries.
HE first of the regional conferences is scheduled
for Tokyo in the Spring of 1966. It will bring
together experts from all Asian Member States and in the
diverse fields involved ranging from authorship and copy¬
right to printing and publishing techniques. The purpose
will be to assess the long-term book needs of the Asian
countries and to draw up a programme of action.
It may be anticipated that the Asian countries will look
to the Conference above all for help in formulating
systematic policies for national book development in which
books are assured of adequate priority within the frame¬
work of economic and social planning. The Conference
may also assist the more advanced countries in shaping
and co-ordinating their bilateral aid programmes so as to
meet more effectively the needs of the Asian countries.
It ¡s hoped that the reports emerging from the Asian and
the subsequent African and Latin American meetings will
also serve as a basis for increased international assistance.
A parallel exists with the similar survey conducted by
Unesco in the three regions in the 1960-1962 period on
development of press, radio, film and television and which
resulted ¡n increased recognition of the mass media as a
sphere for technical assistance. The forthcoming cycle of
conferences should similarly establish the claim for books.
A hopeful sign for the future of the book development
programme is the confidence and interest it has already
elicited not only from governments but also from the
publishing profession. There is an evident feeling that
Unesco has a significant role to play in helping to harness
the forces of the revolution in books for the benefit of all.
JULIAN BEHRSTOCK is head of Unesco's Division of Free Flow of
Information, In the Department of Mass Communication, which deals
with Unesco's programme for book development.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
ignnaïïEïsr Vfe'v'v'^.vv;:-'v;.
THE DILEMMAS
A Hindi manual on anatomy,
published in New Delhi.
OF PUBLISHING IN
SOUTH-EAST ASIA
by Om Prakash
¿>*.Ji>LS-
"The Peaceful Uses of Atomic
Energy", Urdu booklet pre¬
pared with Unesco assistance
and published in Pakistan.
^úiJIrfláasr
"Africa" by Vidwan N. Subrah-
manian, an Indian author. This
book in Tamil was published
in India with Unesco's aid.
Jmtoli i Ch rpcn Jcpu i
,jL
I t
f1 1
*1 1
1
L^^^^H .^M
SHOJI
A collection of Japanese short
stories translated into the
Malay language and published
at Kuala Lumpur (Malaysia).
"Our Occupations", a collec¬
tion of articles on Thai careers
published in Bangkok (Thai¬
land) with Unesco's aid.
O VER 800 million people, or one quarter of the
world's inhabitants, live in South-East Asia (1).
Yet of 400,000 titles of books produced throughout the world in
1962, only 20,000 or one twentieth of the total were published in
this region.
It is evident that book publishing in South-East Asia
as a whole ¡s in an undeveloped stage. While twelve
countries together publish two-thirds of the world's books,
only one of them India is in South-East Asia. Book
production in other countries of the region is extremely
limited.
The production of translations is similarly limited. Of
a world total of 32,787 translations produced in 1962,
only 1,455, or 4.4 % of the total, were published in South-
East Asia.
South-East Asia's role in the international book trade
further illustrates the embryonic state of its publishing
industry. Although there is a substantial volume of exports
of books from Indonesia, India and the Philippines to the
Netherlands, the United Kingdom and the United States,
(1) Afghanistan, Burma, Cambodia, Ceylon, India, Indonesia, Iran,
Laos, Malaysia, Nepal, Pakistan, Philippines, Thailand, Viet-Nam.
respectively, book exports from the greater part of the
region are negligible. In contrast, imports of books, peri¬
odicals and other printed matter may represent almost
one per cent of a country's total imports.
Underdevelopment of book publishing in South-East Asia
results from a host of restrictive elements, ranging from
factors which directly limit the book market, such as
shortages of paper and equipment, to handicaps of a more
general nature, such as low purchasing power and poor
transport facilities.
The biggest single obstacle to a wider circulation of
reading materials is doubtless the high average level of
illiteracy in the region. However, illiteracy rates vary
widely betwen individual countries as the following figures
show:
Afghanistan and Nepal (95 to 99 %); Iran (85 to 89 %); ««
Indonesia, Laos, Pakistan and Rep. of Viet-Nam (80 to ¿u
84 %); India (70 to 74 %); Cambodia (65 to 69 %); Malaysia
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
SOUTH-EAST ASIA (Cont'd)
Dearth of scientific books for children
24
(50 to 54 %); Burma (40 to 44 %) ; Ceylon and Thailand
(30 to 34 %); Philippines (25 to 29 %).
Low income constitutes another major barrier to increas¬
ed reading. While low-cost paperbacks may offer a
means of extending book sales, per capita income is in
fact so limited as to affect the purchase of even the cheap¬
est books. Only Ceylon, Iran, Malaysia and the Philip¬
pines can claim an income of $101-300 per capita. All
the other countries In the area fall within the less than
$100 range.
A third major obstacle to increased production of reading
materials arises from the region's deteriorating terms of
trade. Suffering from a deficit in export over import earn¬
ings, nearly all South-East Asian countries are finding
it increasingly difficult to import the materials and equipment
they need for their national development efforts.
Printing paper looms large in these requirements.
Of the three newsprint producers in the region India,
Pakistan and Cambodia India's production covers only
20 per cent of its own demand, and only Pakistan has an
export surplus (some 15,000 tons in 1963). India is the
only substantial South-East Asian producer of printing
paper other than newsprint and writing paper but, here
again, consumption (234,400 tons in 1962) leaves no sur¬
plus for export. Nor does any other country in the region
export these grades of paper.
In contrast with the discouraging outlook for the develop¬
ment of paper-making in South-East Asia, a huge increase
in demand is foreseen. On the basis solely of population
growth and per capita income in the Far East, the demand
for newsprint in that region, excluding mainland China,
is expected to rise from 672,000 tons in 1955 to 2,920,000
tons in 1975.
The reduction of illiteracy acts as a powerful Incentive
to the demand for printed matter. In countries where
illiteracy is very prevalent, its reduction by one per cent is
estimated to have the same impact on the demand for
printing paper as a five per cent increase in purchasing
power.
However, it must be noted that the demand for books
at prices which the Asian peoples can afford has not
yet been adequately met. Low levels of literacy and of
purchasing power, coupled with the absence of wide read¬
ing habits, continue to limit the production and distribution
of reading materials. Publishers of general books and
books specially suited for children and new literates are
far fewer than those engaged in the publication of educa¬
tional or textbooks.
In the educational field, too, many countries continue
to rely on imports or on local branches of foreign publish¬
ing houses. In several Asian countries, European lan¬
guages introduced by the former European powers are
still used as media for advanced instruction.
There are general publishers of more than 50 years'
standing in Ceylon, Burma, Pakistan and India. In their
early years, they were almost exclusively engaged in
publishing religious books; some used to publish works
on mythology and astrology as well.
The number of regular book publishers in the region is
not available and would be difficult to estimate. Many
countries have no means of counting the publishers or
booksellers.
UBLISHING is a relatively small and unprofit¬
able business in most countries of South-East
Asia, and it has failed to attract capital. Scope for general
publishing is extremely limited. Recently, with progressively
wider use of national languages in instruction, there have
been increased activities and investments in educational
publishing. There are few large, well-organised publishing
firms in the region which can match their counterparts in
the West. The paucity of capital for publishing will persist
as long as the demand for general books continues to be
meagre.
Meanwhile, publishers need to depend upon their own
limited resources. In no South-East Asian country will
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Palm leaf books & 'tamarind seed' script
In past centuries many of the
books produced in South-East Asia
were devoted to religion. Tens
of thousands of religious works are
now preserved in the extensive
library of Adyar, near Madras
(India). Left, sixteenth-century
Buddhist texts written on palm
leaves. Linked by cords, these
manuscripts include 47 volumes of
the Pali Tipitaka (canonical works)
from Ceylon. Right, another manu¬
script from the Adyar library: a
17th-century Buddhist manuscript
from Burma embellished with red
lacquer and gold. The text, written
in "tamarind seed" script, sets
down rules for Buddhist monks.
Photos © Francis Brunei, Paris
Ft>
^""Stf
banks lend funds with printed material as collateral secu¬
rity. Loans from various other sources are not as easily
available to publishers as to other trades, with the result
that their activities remain cramped. In many countries
of the region, government loans are available to small
industries, including the printing industry. Such facilities
are, however, denied to publishers.
Publishing is generally conducted by small units which
are either owned individually or In partnership. The number
of nationally based joint-stock companies, with larger
capital resources, is very limited.
Only a small percentage of books have a chance of
being reprinted; most publications go through only the
first edition. There are few books, except religious and
traditional ones, which could be called "best-sellers" in the
modern sense.
The average first printing order for a general book in
Singapore is 5,000 copies; in Ceylon, 2,000; in Burma, 3,000;
In Indonesia, 5,000 to 10,000; in Iran, 1,000 to 10,000; in
Pakistan, 5,000; and in India, 1,000 to 3,000.
For books for children and new literates, the first printing
orders are for 5,000 copies in Singapore; 5,000 in Ceylon
and Burma; 5,000 to 20,000 in Indonesia; 2,000 in Iran;
2,500 in Pakistan; and 2,000 to 10,000 in India.
The largest first printing orders are given to educational
books. They amount to 20,000 in Singapore; 7,500 to
50,000 in Ceylon; 20,000 to 30.000 in Iran; and 5,000 to
100,000 and more in India.
University textbooks are printed in editions of 2,000 in
Burma, 3,000 to 5,000 in Indonesia and 2,500 to 5,000
in Pakistan.
The average price of books for children and new literates
varies, but considering the average capacity and inclination
to buy books in these countries, the prices must be
considered high. Until books are priced more cheaply
and printed in much larger numbers they will fail to be
widely used in South-East Asia.
Subjects for books for children and new literates are
folk tales, stories, religious and moral instruction and
biography and travel. The publication of books on develop¬
ments in science has been started recently.
There is a dearth In all the South-East Asian countries
of scientific books for children and new literates, parti
cularly in national languages. Owing to the lack of printing
facilities, few translations of such books are published
and attempts made in this field have not been very success¬
ful.
The production of reading materials for mass consump¬
tion suffers many handicaps in South-East Asia. Some
help, by way of subsidies or assured purchases, would
be required to effect a break-through. Unesco, through
its programme to stimulate the publication of reading
materials in the region, has subsidized the production in
certain Asian countries of selected titles in order to
promote international understanding (1).
Franklin Publications (U.S.A.) have also subsidized certain
publishers in Pakistan and several other countries to this
end, by meeting translation expenses and part of the
promotional costs. Franklin Publications charge a small
percentage of royalties on books thus assisted.
HERE has been little agreement among countries
of the region as to what constitutes a "book", a
"newspaper" or a "magazine". Ceylon defines a book as
"any number of pages permanently bound between two co¬
vers"; this includes pamphlets, booklets, magazines and
periodicals. A book is "a work of eight pages or more" in
Indonesia. Iran defines a book as "any printed material,
being bound or to be bound within the importing country."
The Philippine definition is "a volume, with or without covers
consisting of more than 100 pages." This ambiguity creates
continual complications, particularly for book importing and
exporting countries, but should now be resolved by the
latest Unesco definition of a book (see page 15).
The distribution of books in South-East Asia does not pre¬
sent a very happy picture either. Apart from bookshops,
other outlets are small bookstalls, pavement bookhawkers
and the newsagents. The latter are poorly organized and
are not dependable outlets financially. Few of them have
(1) A Unesco Regional Centre for Reading Materials was set up
in 1958 at Karachi, in collaboration with the Government of Pakistan,
to promote the publication and distribution to an increasingly wide
public of appropriate reading materials in their national languages.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
SOUTH-EAST ASIA (Cont'd)
26
Red-tape and
unfair competition
bank accounts, or the will or capacity to cater to intelligent
demands. Newsagents are little interested in books unless
they are low-priced, fast-selling items such as paperbacks.
Regular investment in stocks of books is practised by the
better type of bookshops and in most South-East Asia coun¬
tries these deal in imported books rather than in books
published locally in the national language. Booksellers who
stock books in national languages prefer to deal in fast-
selling educational books. The distribution of general books
faces great handicaps.
One factor hindering the growth of the booktrade in all
countries of South-East Asia is widespread price-cutting
and cutthroat competition. The published price of a book
does not mean much, since a buyer can haggle to obtain
a rebate on its face value. In the absence of a strong
demand for books, a publisher or bookseller has little
inclination to hold on to a book rather than sell it at the
cut price offered. The bookseller continually presses the
publisher to grant a higher discount so that after he has
allowed a discount to his retail buyer, he will still have
some margin left for himself. The result is that, even
though the bookseller may be getting a fairly high discount
on the published price of a book, he does not have enough
margin to meet the expenses or make a profit. Bookselling
remains a very unlucrative business which fails to give
the support expected of it by the publishing industry.
S earnings from the publication of translated
books in most South-East Asian countries are
meagre, many western authors and publishers are reluctant
to assign translation rights to publishers of this region.
Prices of translated books are much lower than the original
publications, though editions are small and must carry
the additional burden of translation. In addition, a foreign
publisher has no recourse when an Asian publisher defaults
in the payment of royalties. Western publishers conse-
quent'y tend to demand heavy advances on royalties
which South-East Asian publishers find it difficult to pay.
In most South-East Asian countries licences must be
obtained for the import of books. Iran and Singapore
are exceptions. In Pakistan books priced at Rs. 150.00
($30.00) can be imported for personal use without a licence.
In India even non-commercial institutions such as univer¬
sities and established libraries must apply to obtain a
licence for books which they may decide to import them¬
selves. In Burma, restriction on the import of books
from hard currency countries is comparatively stringent,
and in Indonesia an importer must obtain government
approval for each title if foreign exchange is to be officially
provided. In almost all parts of the region, systems for
obtaining import licences are cumbersome and complicated
by excessive red tape.
The developing countries of South-East Asia could benefit
greatly from the "paperback revolution". Prospects for
the publication of paperbacks in the region are not yet
encouraging, however. The number of publishers engaged
in publishing paperbacks is small, as are the number
of copies and titles they issue.
In Singapore, six publishers at present produce paper¬
backs, the initial printing order being 5,000 copies per
title. Ceylon has yet to begin publishing these books.
In Burma a number of publishers are now producing paper¬
backs, with the first printing order limited to 5,000 copies.
Two publishers in Indonesia and four in Iran are engaged
in this type of production with their first editions averaging
10,000 copies each. In Pakistan, publishers have not
yet taken to paperbacks seriously. One or two publishers
J. P. Charbonnier-Réalités
have tried to establish themselves in this field but their
first printing orders do not exceed 4,000 copies. In India
a number of publishers have successfully undertaken
paperback publishing in Hindi and various other languages,
though business now seems to be slowing down because
of a heavy percentage of unsold returns from newstands.
Publishers in Hindi, the official language, have had good
sales results, with first printing orders varying between
5,000 and 25,000 copies.
Most of the successful paperback publishers in the
West use newsprint. Because of the shortage of domestic
newsprint in South-East Asia, the authorities severely
restrict its use for paperbacks. Good quality newsprint
which could be used for books is mostly imported and
can be obtained only in limited quantities by special permit
and import licence. Import and excise duties on newsprint
increase the cost of paperbacks. Small printing orders
are another major cause of high prices. In comparison
to average purchasing power in the United States, for
example, which produces 25 and 35 cent "pocket books,"
the price of paperbacks in India, Pakistan and Indonesia
should be no more than a quarter of a rupee ($0.05),
whereas the actual cost is one rupee. Paperbacks in
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
21 -volume Japanese novel
sells 11 million copies
The Japanese publishing industry, the world's fifth largest,
enjoyed the best year in ten years in 1964: 342 million
books were produced, comprising 32,229 titles of which
14,000 were new an increase of 17% over the previous
year. Average price per book was 360 yen (about a
dollar) and the value of books published totalled 128,000
million yen ($356 million).
Books published in 1964 included 503 titles in general
works, 548 in philosophy, 1,112 in history and geography,
1,253 in economics, 1,765 in engineering, 4,586 in litera¬
ture, 5,433 in reference books, 3,078 in paperbacks, 2,918
in children's books and 219 in dictionaries.
The big increase in production during 1964 is due to
several factors and above all to a rising standard of living.
Nowadays Japan's bookshops are always crowded. Sales
of dictionaries and encyclopedias are greater than ever.
Book sales are also being boosted by an increased
interest in history as Japan approaches the 100th anni¬
versary of the Meiji Restoration which marked the
country's appearance as a modern state. Historical novels
are therefore enjoying great success. One novel, consist¬
ing of the 21-volume "Tokugawa leyasu" by Sohachi
Yamaoka, has sold 11 million copies. It depicts the adven¬
tures and love of the first Tokugawa Shogunate.
By April 1964, paperbacks represented 20% of Japan's
publishing activity and this proportion is still growing.
But the increasing demand for large-format volumes,
which represent the other end of the price range in publish¬
ing, shows the existence of a growing market for high-
quality works. Publishers earn greater profits from this
type of work even though fewer copies are printed. One of
Japan's 1964 best-sellers was "The Diary of Anne Frank",
translated from its Dutch language edition (700,000 copies).
Shin-lchi Hasegawa.
South-East Asia cannot, in fact, be considered as "low-
cost". They have appeared to be cheap to the buyer
only because in the usual hard-bound editions of 1,000 to
3,000 copies he has been purchasing similar titles at
about three rupees per copy.'
The variety of languages is another serious problem.
In Ceylon there are two languages, Singhala and Tamil,
in which books could be produced. Suitable languages
in Indonesia are Bhasa Indonesia and Malay. Both
use the same script and are very similar except for
differences in spellings. The governments of Indonesia and
Malaysia have made efforts to standardize spellings on a
state level. Other Indonesian languages include Javanese,
Madurese and Sundanese, but there is little demand for
books in them. In Pakistan, books in Urdu and Bengali
are required while in India books must be produced in
Hindi, Urdu, Kashmiri, Bengali, Marathi, Gujarati, Punjabi,
Oriya, Assamese, Tamil, Telugu, Malayalam and Kannada.
In Burma only one language (Burmese) is required for
books and in Iran only Farsi. In Cambodia, Philippines
and Laos books must be produced in Khmer, Tagalog and
Laotian, respectively.
Ceylon, Pakistan, Philippines, India and Malaysia also use
books in English to some extent. All scripts employed
in South-East Asia are non-ideographic and, with the
exception of Farsi, Pushto, Kashmiri and Urdu, are written
and printed from left to right.
The difficulties involved in producing well-designed books,
particularly scientific books, for children and new literates
in South-East Asia cannot be easily overcome if left to
individual effort. Most publishers of the region recognize
that wherever possible, co-operative effort should be under¬
taken to promote the mass production of reading materials
for children and new literates. Better quality will thus
be assured and costs reduced. Suitable subjects for
co-operatively produced books could include elementary
science, public health, and Asian folklore, philosophy,
flora and fauna. Such books could become an instrument
for better understanding among South-East Asian countries.
OM PRAKASH Indian specialist in publishing and book distribution, nn
is president of the All-India Hindi Publishers' Association, in Delhi. ¿ /
For a fuller account of this subject by Mr. Prakash, see the Unesco
booklet, just published, "Books for the Developing Countries:
Asia-Africa" (price 3/- stg; $0.50).
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
A continent
in quest of
a publishing
industry
A Unesco survey in Africa
by Clifford M. Fyle
I N many African countries the absence of a
sufficient number of readers is a major obstacle
to large-scale publishing, if not to publishing generally.
Total populations in general are small. Some ten coun¬
tries have between a quarter of a million and a million
inhabitants; seventeen countries have between one million
and five million and sixteen have populations of over five
million.
Thus while half of these countries might possibly sup¬
port a flourishing publishing industry on the strength of
their population, the rest will necessarily be limited to a
few publishers each. And in the six countries with no more
than 300,000 to 400,000 inhabitants even a single publisher
may be able to maintain only a struggling business.
But this visualizes a situation where everyone can read and
is therefore a potential user of books. This we know is far
from the case. The number of adult literates is small in
all African countries. The reading public consists largely
of the school population. In Sierra Leone less than 25%
of the potential school population between the ages of five
and twelve was attending school in 1962. And Sierra
Leone is not among the least advanced African countries
in education.
However, rapid strides are being made in educational
_- development, including the introduction of free or com-
¿Q pulsory primary education in some countries and the
expansion in others of the number of schools and univer¬
sities as well as improvement In the quality of education.
Such developments are bound to act as a stimulus to
publishing.
Mass literacy programmes, especially for adults, are
being launched and are making great headway. Ghana has a
programme for wiping out illiteracy within ten years and the
Sudan plans to make 200,000 people literate during the
next five years.
Many African countries therefore feel that lack of rea¬
dership is a temporary situation and that it has ceased
to be the chief obstacle to the development of publishing.
But high production costs and the shortage of proper
distribution outlets are still seen as serious problems.
The creation and growth of publishing industries in the
developing countries depend above all on national book
needs. A Unesco-sponsored inquiry into present obsta¬
cles to the production and flow of books in Africa revealed
a number of priority needs. Africa's greatest demand is
for children's books, books on all the basic and applied
sciences and on history and geography. More people are
studying languages, some interest is being shown in litera-
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Tfce Mb&n
CAtíMT (
Africa has a great tradition of oral literature. Today
the rich imagery of its poems and stories is finding a
new form of expression in the pages of books. These
illustrations are taken from a collection of Yoruba chil¬
dren's poems entitled "The Moon Cannot Fight",
published by Mbari Publications, Ibadan, Nigeria.
Drawings r Mbari Publications. Ibadan
ture, but little in the arts, in philosophy and psychology.
Top priority is given to books that contribute to economic
development. But this situation is gradually changing as
a middle class emerges and is creating a market for non¬
functional books.
African countries depend largely on imported books.
Reports from twenty-five countries revealed that eight had
no publishing at all, fourteen imported their primary school
books and nineteen all their secondary school books.
On the face of it there is no reason why African countries
should not continue to rely on book imports, providing
freight charges can be kept to a minimum and an effective
distribution system is established. But studies have shown
that in planning for the free flow of information and know¬
ledge within and between countries, it is better in the long
run for a national book industry, or as much of it as possi¬
ble, to be indigenous from the start.
A book-publishing industry can contribute to long-term
economic and social development and to industrial expan¬
sion and it is also a source of satisfaction to national
pride. There are also sound educational and psychological
reasons for developing national book publishing. Local
writers, artists and, above all, editors are more likely
-than those from another country to be responsive to the
ideas, feelings and general outlook in their own com¬
munities.
Should publishing in a developing country be state-
controlled or run by private entreprise? In some African
countries there is now a tendency for school books and
books for the general public to be state-controlled. One
example is Guinea where the national presses at Conakry
print political books under government auspices. Centra¬
lized state publishing has certain advantages, notably lower
production costs. The best solution for Africa appears to
be a combination of national centralized publishing and
private publishing.
Commercial publishing has established itself in Africa on
over the years, although mainly through foreign publishing ¿3
houses. Some countries have now set up companies to
which foreign publishers contribute capital and experience
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
IN QUEST OF A PUBLISHING INDUSTRY (Cont'd)
Opening 'book roads' to the village
30
and Africans provide the rest of the capital and the men
who will be trained to run the firms.
In countries with populations of three million or less
neither local nor foreign commercial publishers can produce
primers and readers for mass literacy at prices within
the reach of the average reader. The need to produce
books in several languages, perhaps with different scripts,
creates serious problems for the commercial publisher.
Today most primary school books are produced for a
wide area. It is true that publishers try to meet the needs
of smaller countries by publishing special editions, but
for financial reasons they can only make minor alterations
where, in fact, the books should be completely rewritten
to suit local conditions and school systems.
For small countries the best solution seems to be cen¬
tralized local publishing firms,- financed wholly or partly by
the government, but retaining freedom of action to plan
and handle operations to meet local needs.
The publication of books for mass literacy campaigns
is handicapped by the multiplicity of local languages in
African countries. Nigeria is said to have over 200 local
languages and dialects. Countries facing this problem sim¬
ply publish books in those of their languages which have
the widest currency. Sierra Leone, with a population of
only two million, has eighteen languages. It publishes
primers, readers and other literature in five languages and
primers in two others.
In most countries governments and educationists have
taken a firm line and have adopted the one or two languages
of widest circulation for teaching. This linguistic problem
may eventually be solved by adoption of a single national
language. Ghana, which has 56 languages and dialects,
is now working towards the use of Akan as its national
language.
I N some countries it might be better to combine
mass literacy publishing units and the school
publication centres into a single operation. A distinction
has to be made between the publishing and the printing of
books; to publish the books it needs for school and literacy
teaching a country does not need full book-printing facilities.
American publishers sometimes have their printing done
in Japan and British publishers have been known to print
as far away as Hong Kong.
There is, however, an obvious need for greater printing
facilities in Africa. While there are probably enough
presses to satisfy demands on a regional basis, a country-
by-country study reveals some critical situations. Cer¬
tain countries, Egypt, Nigeria, Kenya, Southern Rhodesia
and the Democratic Republic of the Congo, for example,
have a comparatively large concentration of presses. But
many African countries have only a few each (often a
single government-owned plant) and at least five have no
presses at all.
Neither large nor small countries appear to favour region¬
al co-operation as a solution to the problem of providing
printing facilities. The Unesco Textbook Production Centre
at Yaounde in the Cameroon is a type of organization that
it may be difficult to duplicate elsewhere in Africa. This
centre provides textbook printing facilities for the five
adjacent countries of Cameroon, Central African Republic,
Chad, Congo (Brazzaville) and Gabon.
The centre is already doing extremely useful work yet
in the near future it may become even more important
as a training ground for African printers than as a printing
centre for textbooks and manuals.
All over the African continent plans to install or expand
printing facilities are dependent on the availability of skilled
printers, proper machinery, paper and printing materials and
electric power.
Broadly speaking, once publishing houses begin to
function in African countries, the development of local
printers, proper machinery, paper and printing materials and
of a regular volume of books to be printed. An example
of how this process functions is offered by Jamaica in the
West Indies. There the creation of a schools publication
branch by the Ministry of Education has greatly stimulated
V / V / V J V 4
©mSOtaOSOSQfâSsteiaï
L-^
m^s^msmz
fl [^ fl t>fl ï^ fl P-fl *
]@[]@[i@[]@[]@d
\*WW J PwrV I JWAWJ [ ViV*V | j^V^ J [Wrtr^yj jW-Vw| |WVVV| [v*\rw| [v»W j
Í1S1ÍWWV VSrVWl^H *rVfc**V K-MhUW
HACHE
] IwwV^l |wsw|
"TTE=il
LTWWWWW
Many African countries still depend to a large
extent on imported school books. These de¬
signs are part of the cover of a French language
reader for African schools published in France.
the local printing industry. Jamaica, which previously had
no modern printing facilities, now has two large plants
capable of producing most kinds of primers and readers
for primary schools and adult literacy campaigns.
But in developing countries book publishing comes up
against a serious obstacle: printing costs. Many publishers
complain that prices in local African plants are much higher
than in countries on other continents.
In the new African plants printing costs are inevitably
high at the start. But publishers have to keep their prices
low to stay in business. Some compromise solution must
therefore be found.
The developing countries are not only short of printing
facilities but also of paper for printing books. African and
Asian needs in paper are steadily increasing. In 1960
countries on these continents (exclusive of Japan and
mainland China) required one and one eighth million tons
of newsprint and printing and writing paper. By 1975
these needs may well have increased five-fold to nearly
five million tons.
Even though these five million tons only represent
about one-tenth of the expected total world consumption
in 1975, it is doubtful whether' Africa and Asia will be
able to satisfy this demand from their own production
resources or even to purchase the paper they need.
Expensive freight charges, poorly developed distribution
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
systems and high tariffs, which vary from country to
country and which average between 20 % and 30 %, all
raise the cost of paper in Africa, sometimes to double
the international price level. Here, foreign aid would be
an invaluable asset. To supply Africa and Asia with paper
would be a sure way of helping their countries along the
road of educational and cultural progress.
Governments should be urged to reduce or abolish tariffs
and taxes on newsprint and paper for educational books.
They should also be encouraged to provide foreign currency
for the import of paper and printing supplies.
African countries wish to be free from their present
dependency on foreign supplies of paper and printing
materials. Many are now studying how to set up paper
mills and one in particular is watching with special interest
experiments in the production of paper from the eucalyptus
tree which grows plentifully within its borders.
Yet it is unlikely that on the basis of present plans
Africa will be able to produce more than a small proportion
of the paper it needs for some time to come. The pro¬
duction of newsprint and other printing paper depends not
only on availability of raw materials, but also on the
development of supporting structures: electric power, chem¬
icals, transport and so on.
In Africa, as in other developing areas, books must be
sold as cheaply as possible. This means that import
and export taxes, sales taxes and similar restrictions on
books must be reduced to a minimum or abolished. The
special claim of books for preferential treatment in compe¬
tition with other products is justified by the primary role
they play in national development, in the preservation of
culture and knowledge and in the free flow of ideas.
Although less than one quarter of the African countries
have so far signed the Unesco Agreement on the Impor¬
tation of Educational, Scientific and Cultural Materials, most
adhere to the spirit of this agreement by allowing books
to be imported free from customs duties and charges.
In Africa, bookshops are concentrated in large cities, and
attempts to establish them in rural areas have often been
difficult. Hence less conventional methods are used: retail
traders carry books as a line of stock, pavement hawkers
offer them to the passer-by and vans, mobile bookshops
and small bookshops attached to schools are all mobilized
as distribution points.
V"ÏT hVÜ^C
A geography text book
published in Addis Ababa
for Ethiopian schools.
DE TANAXAMYt
A work published by the
Institute of Higher Stu¬
dies at Tananarive, the
capital of Madagascar.
HE Unesco inquiry shows that in city areas the
most effective means of book distribution is the
bookshop, followed by the newsagent and the bookstall.
In rural areas the bookshop, even a small one attached to a
school, is found to be the most effective method of distri¬
bution; next come mobile bookshops and last of all the
book pedlars.
What measures will help to promote bookselling in Africa?
1) Prices of books must be kept low by both local and
foreign publishers; 2) controls on the importation of books
should be removed by governments; 3) shipping charges
should be cut, by international agreement if necessary since
shipping companies are seldom African-owned; 4) road and
rail charges should be reduced for book transport.
Every large town should have its bookshop and every
country its chain of bookshops. For this, government help
is needed. Such financial support is an investment in
education and therefore in the development of a nation's
potentialities.
In rural areas valuable work is being done by bookshops
attached to local schools and run by teachers and also
by small book vans and mobile bookshops. Furthermore,
in country districts the bookshop is not there merely to
stimulate the reading habit. If many bookshops in Africa's
rural centres have so far done only poor business, it is
because the booksellers are not properly trained. African
governments would be well advised to co-operate with
local booksellers in drawing up a comprehensive long term
plan for developing book distribution in their countries.
No matter how much is done to promote book sales,
some titles will always be beyond the reach of the average
pocket. This is especially true of the developing countries.
It is up to libraries to provide such books.
A good library service does more; it is itself an incen¬
tive to reading, and by stimulating people to buy their
own books and to gradually assemble home libraries it
helps to create a flourishing book trade. This, of course,
raises the problem of training competent librarians.
The same problem exists in book publishing. Africa
urgently needs properly trained personnel in this field, and
in setting up a training programme, the co-operation of
foreign publishing houses would be a major asset.
CLIFFORD. M. FYLE is a member of the Ministry of Education,
Freetown, Sierra Leone. He is the author of "The Flow and Pro¬
duction of Books in Africa" , published in "Books for the Developing
Countries" (No 47 in Unesco's Reports and Papers on Mass Com¬
munication) which is the result of a special inquiry carried out
under Unesco's auspices into the development of book production
and distribution in Africa and Asia.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Some Unesco publications on books
Access to Books, 1952*. $0.20. 1/-
Books for All, by RE. Barker. 1956 *. $3, 15/-
Books for the Developing Countries. Asia. Africa, by Om Prakash
and Clifford M. Fyle. Unesco 1965, $0.50, 3/-
Book Production 1937-1954 and Translations 1950-1954, Unesco
1957, $0.40, 2/-
The Delhi Public Library - An Evaluation Report, by Frank M.
Gardner, Unesco, 1957, $1 .50, 7/6
Development of Public Libraries in Africa - The Ibadan Seminar,
Unesco, 1954, $1.75, 9/6
Development of Public Libraries in Latin America - The Sao Paulo
Conference, Unesco, 1952*. $1, 6/-
Directory of Reference Works Published in Asia, by PK. Garde
(biling. Eng., Fr.), Unesco, 1956'. $2, 10/6
A Handbook for the Improvement of Textbooks and Teaching
Materials as Aids to International Understanding, Unesco. 1949*.
$0.45. 21-
Handbook on the International Exchange of Publications (quadri-
lingual Eng., Fr., Rus., Sp.). 1964, $7 50, 38/6. bound $8.50, 42/-
History Textbooks and International Understanding, by J. A. Lau-
werys, Unesco. 1958, $0.85, 4/-
Index Translationum (vol XVI) (latest issue), $25.00, 125/-, bound
$28 00. 140/-. .
Public Libraries and their Mission, by André Maurois, Unesco.
1963 \ free
The Revolution in Books, by Robert Escarpit, in preparation In Eng.
Unesco Copyright Bulletin, published annually from 1964 (triling.,
Eng., Fr.. Sp). $5 00. 25/-
Unesco Bulletin for Libraries, bimonthly, annual subscription $3.50,
18/-, per copy $0 75, 4/
* Out of print. Readers are referred to their local library.
Unesco Courier articles
JUNE 1948: Unesco Sets Programme for Classics Translation, by
H.M. Barnes, Jr.: Copyright Expert Views Conflicting National
Laws, by François Hepp: Low-priced Books A Neglected Medium
of Mass Communication.
OCTOBER 1948: Improvement of Textbooks Sought in Member
States, by L. James Quillen
JUNE 1949: The Librarians Join Hands.
AUGUST 1949: The Role of Cheap Books, by J.L. Crammer.
SEPTEMBER 1949: International Circulation of Publications;
Unesco's Contribution to Libraries' Reconstruction and Develop¬
ment.
JUNE 1950: Beirut Translation Commission Will Fill Gaps in Isla¬
mic-Western Literature.
SEPTEMBER 1950: Libraries, a Neglected Resource.
JANUARY 1951: Libraries and a Better Life.
MARCH 1951:. The Care-Unesco Book Fund Programme
JULY 1952: What People in New Delhi Like to Read, by Frank
M. Gardner
DECEMBER 1952; For Those Who Live by the Pen, by José de
Benito
JUNE 1953 (special issue on books); The Public Library A Force
for Popular Education; Books without Chains, by Francis L. Kent;
More Books for Africans, They Pushed Out the Walls, by Karl
Detzer, Biblioteca Infantil: A Paradise for Sao Paulo's Children,
by S.M Koffler; In Munich Pinocchio and Babar Are Language
Teachers; The Bookmobile Comes to Town, by Gladys Skelley;
Le Parisien Likes Travel Books La Parisienne Prefers Biogra¬
phies, by Georges Fradier; A Sikh Taxi Driver Discovers the Road
to the Library, by Frank M. Gardner.
APRIL-MAY 1954: A Forgotten Spanish Province Wakes Up, by
Tena Artigas
MARCH-APRIL 1955: MunichInternational Centre for Children's
Books, by Brigitte Gnauck.
FEBRUARY 1956: 5 Readers a Minute. 11 Hours Every Day in
Asia's Busiest Library, by Frank M. Gardner.
JANUARY 1957: The Treasures of Iran's Imperial Library.
FEBRUARY 1957 (Special Issue on Books): When Is a Book not
a Book?; On a Stroll with Immortal Friends, by- Gabrielle Cabrini
Agatha Christie Leads Dante and Homer, by Gabrielle Cabrini;
World's Most Translated Authors (1948-55); 1955's Most Translated
Authors in 15 Countries; Tidbits, Eccentrica and Other Morsels;
Saved from Fire and Water; 5,000 Million Books a Year; A Coin
in the Slot and out Pops Plato, by Bertha Gaster; Soviet Book
News for 1957; Men in Long Black Robes, by Jorge Carrera An-
drade; What Has TV Done to Book Reading? by Henry Cassirer;
The Publisher's Dilemma; Some Best Sellers in Science.
JUNE 1957: Great Literature of East and West, by M. Arrhe: Com¬
plete List of Unesco's Literature Series.
MARCH 1958: Books for the New Reading Public, by J.E. Morpurgo.
APRIL 1958: Translation in the Modern World, by E. Cary; Bridges
between East and West, an Analysis of "Index Translationum", by
Robert L. Collison.
JANUARY 1960: Books on Wheels A Library Comes to a Greek
Village.
APRIL 1961: Japan Misrepresented, a Look at Foreign Textbooks
MAY 1961: André Maurois Speaks of Books and of Libraries.
MAY 1962: Modern Japanese Fiction, a Break with Literary Tradi¬
tion, by Ivan Morris.
JANUARY 1963: The Library of the Future, by J.H. Shera.
FEBRUARY 1963: The Continuing Barrier, Translation and East-
West Communications, by Robert Collison.
All these issues are now out of print. We refer readers to their
local library.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
THE ' SEMANTICS'
OF SEMANTICS
Sir,
I read Seymour Fersh's article,
"Words Under a Mask" in your
February 1965 issue. I work in seman¬
tics, and should like to say a few
"Words Under a Mask," in your
publishing this article in your journal.
The term "semantics" has lately
been used In connexion with various
trends of thought, and has acquired a
multiplicity of meanings which some¬
times Inevitably results in grave
misunderstandings or is deliberately
made to serve certain ends. The
term was initially used by linguists
first by the German philologist Chris¬
tian Karl Reisig (1839), and later by
the French linguist, Michel Breal (1897)
and is at present widely current in
this sphere to designate the branch
dealing with the signification of words.
It subsequently served to denote
one of the three branches of semio¬
tics, the theory of signs and symbols
developed by Charles Pearce, Charles
Morris, and others. In semiotics,
semantics is assigned the study of the
connotations of signs. Semiotics is
akin to that trend in modern neoposi-
tivism, which in Soviet scientific writ¬
ing is designated by the name of
semantic philosophy (Logical seman¬
tics), and which analyzes the truth and
falsity of linguistic denotations.
GENERAL semantics was establish¬
ed in 1933 with the publication
of Alfred Korzibsky's book,
"Science and Health." It has nothing
to do with the semantics described
above although it does make an effort
to use their arguments, and tackles
some of their problems (in a highly
modified context) and in general tries
in even/ way to use "academic seman¬
tics" as a basis. On the other hand,
the latter In all its trends recoils from
general semantics, relations with
which it clearly finds embarrassing.
One of the leading lights of seman¬
tic neopositivism, Alfred Tarski, disso¬
ciating himself from the tasks and
purposes of general semantics, writes:
"... semantics... is a sober and modest
discipline which has no pretensions
of being a universal patent-medicine
for all the ills and diseases of
mankind, whether imaginary or real.
You will not find in semantics any
remedy for decayed teeth or illusions
of grandeur or class conflicts" (1).
The well-known American linguist,
Eugene Nlda, says that Korzibsky was
not Justified in using the terms "se¬
mantics" and adds that the latter's
pretensions have turned semantics
into a species of ethics... or almost
a religion (2).
These statements give an idea of
what general semantics actually is. Its
promises are many: it aims to debunk
Aristotelian (formal) logic, create a new
theory of cognition, establish peace
and social harmony on earth, release
man from the tyranny of language,
introduce a hygiene of thinking, etc.
It is therefore extremely difficult to
define its tasks and purposes. What
is more, they are variously formulated
by Korzibsky's followers: S. J. Haya-
kawa, Irving Lee, Stuart Chase,
Anatol Rapoport, and others.
STUART Chase appears to have
given the most widely accepted
definition of its purposes. They
are, one, to help make a more precise
evaluation of the environment, that is,
teach more precise thinking; two,
improve communication both on the
part of the speaker and the auditor,
and, on that basis, three, to develop
mental hygiene.
In spite of its international congres¬
ses general semantics is a patently
localized movement: it has not spread
beyond the borders of the United
States, although it has done every¬
thing to do so. The magazine Etc.
(which is one of the principles of
general semantics) is the propaganda
and theoretical organ of the movement,
which recruits its members from
among economists, lawyers, journa¬
lists, travelling salesmen, etc., who
try to practise the principles of
general semantics in their business.
General semantics is sometimes
defined as a distinct philosophical
trend, but there is no ground for
this. It is true that the works of its
most serious representative, Anatol
Rapoport, reveal an effort to confine
general semantics to a scientific
framework and to examine a number
of gnoseological problems. But, as
I have said, all its elements of scien¬
tific theory have been borrowed from
other spheres (through the multiplicity
of significations of the term "seman¬
tics"), and should be examined as
such. General semantics assesses
these problems from the standpoint of
their pragmatic signification. Conse¬
quently, general semantics is not a
philosophical trend but a definite
ideological movement.
The chief point of reference for
all the dissertations of general
semantics is human language and its
ambiguities which are revealed in the
process of communication. It takes
human experience and language to
be two distinct magnitudes and
ascribes all the flaws of communica¬
tion, which lead to incorrect conclu¬
sions and social misunderstandings,
to the inability of language to give
adequate expression to human expe¬
rience, and even to the inherent
property of language to distort reality
and impose on speakers the built-in
values of language.
Actually, however, language sums
up human experience.
It is always at the back of language
and people can understand each
other through speech for no other
reason than that both the speaker
and the auditor refer words to expe¬
rience. As for the abstract nature
of language, which is allegedly inca¬
pable of conveying the concrete
essence of each particular case, it is
only one of its aspects, for when
necessary language can be concrete
to the maximum. Of course, when we
take, say, the word "man" separately
it has an abstract meaning but then
we rarely use words without reference
to others. And when we link up words
with each other and say: "The man
before us", the meaning of the word
becomes adequately concrete to
convey the uniqueness of the situation.
ONE proposition of general seman¬
tics that can be accepted is that
language should be used with
the greatest possible care and preci¬
sion. But it is no easy task to erect
an original philosophic system on this
pretty tattered truth. General semantics
does teach another useful lesson: we
have clearly not made an adequate
study of human language, its properties
and specific features. Otherwise, there
would have been no room for the
kind of reasoning we find in general
semantics.
I'm afraid Mr. Fersh's article will
confuse readers by giving them an
incorrect idea of the authenticity of
our knowledge, the cognoscibility of
the real world, the causes of social
phenomena, and the science of
semantics in general. I think its publi¬
cation in such a journal as The Unesco
Courier is unjustified.
Profesor Vladimir Zvegintsev,
Moscow State University, U.S.S.R.
J. A. Tarski. The Semantic Concep¬
tion of Truth. Semantics and the
Philosophy of Language. Ed. by L.
Linsky, 1952.
2. E. Nida, A System for the
Description of Semantic Elements,
"Word", Vol. 7, 1951, N° 1.
Ed. note: Mr. Fersh comments:
"My major purpose in writing the
article was hopefully to stimulate an
Increased awareness to the ways in
which language misinforms as well as
informs. It was not my intention to
examine the 'semantics' of semantics
nor to appear in any way a special
proponent of a particular school of
linguistic analysis." 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Bookr
COR THE PARTIALLY-SIGHTED: Novels
printed in very large type for partially-
sighted people who cannot read normal
newspaper or book print even with the
help of glasses are being produced
in the United Kingdom. They weigh only
about a quarter of a pound heavier than
the average novel. The idea was launched
by a retired publisher. The first 24 titles
in the Ulverscroft series, as they are called,
will appear at the rate of four a month.
They will be available only through libraries,
welfare organizations and agencies for the
blind. For further information write to The
Library Association, Chaucer House, Malet
Place, London, W.C.1.
COUR CENTURIES OF PUBLISHING:
1 Last year the U.S.S.R., celebrated the
400th anniversary of Russian book printing
and honoured its founder, Ivan Federov.
The immense printing and publishing
industry in the U.S.S.R. now turns out
more than 2,000 books every minute (about
three million a day). Betwen 1918 and
1963, 27,500 million copies of books and
pamphlets (some two million titles) were
published in the Soviet Union.
C LECTRONIC BRAILLE: An electronic
computer is now being used to
translate English into Braille at the
American Printing House for the Blind at
Louisville, Ky. (U.S.A.) The computer con¬
verts English into the 246 characters of
Grade II Braille: combinations of six raised
dots representing the alphabet, punctuation
and numbers as well as 183 special contrac
tions and abbreviations. Working at electro¬
nic speeds, the computer can translate an
average of more than 1,000 words a
minute. Texts are first reproduced on
punched cards which are fed into the
computer. This produces a printed page
with Braille characters matched to the
English equivalent. After this has been
proof-read, the computer makes a new set
of punched cards which are used to
operate a sterograph (a machine producing
the embossed plates from which Braille
pages are prepared). The new process
has speeded up the publication of Braille
books.
MnESCO BEST-SELLER: One of
^ Unesco's best-sellers is a "do-it-
yourself" science book, "Source Book for
Science Teaching". First published by Unes¬
co in 1956, it has now been translated and
published in 27 languages, in editions
totalling 400,000 copies. It explains how to
make laboratory equipment and carry out
simple experiments and observations in
physics, astronomy, hydrology, electricity,
heat magnetism and many more scientific
fields. All this can be done with "home¬
made" equipment of the simplest kind,
such as tins, bottles, needles and clothes
pegs. Unesco's "Source Book for Science
Teaching" has especially helped schools
which have little or no science teaching
equipment.
A ID FOR THE PARALYZED: Cripples
^^ who are unable to read or write
because they cannot hold a pencil or turn
the pages of a book are being helped in
34
UNESCO'S LATEST GUIDE TO WORLD TRANSLATIONS
MORE books were translated in
1963 than in any previous year
according to the latest volume of
"Index Translationum", (1) Unesco's
international bibliography of transla¬
tions, which records a total of 34,143
titles translated in 69 countries. The
previous edition, covering 1962, listed
32,787 works translated in 70 coun¬
tries.
Compiled with the help of librarians
in many countries, "Index Transla¬
tionum" presents a detailed picture
of world translations, recording those
published in a single year; listings
include new editions of previously
published books. It has recorded over
376,000 titles of translated works in
the past sixteen years and this figure
will have passed the 400,000 mark by
the time the 17th volume is published.
In number of works translated in
1963 Shakespeare leads with 207,
reports the recently published 820-
page 16th edition. Printings of the
Bible and extracts from it total 181.
Translations of writings by Lenin
total 148, and the names of Marx and
Engels are listed 88 and 61 times
respectively.
Nobel Prize winners for literature
are well represented: John Steinbeck,
93 translations; Ernest Hemingway,
50; Jean-Paul Sartre, 45 (1963 was
his pre-prize year); William Faulkner,
37; Ivo Andric, 33; Albert Camus, 32.
Tolstoy, perennially the most trans¬
lated novelist, has 94 translations.
There are 84 listings for Jules Verne,
75 for Dostoievsky 65 for Balzac,
65 for Pearl Buck, 57 for Graham
Greene, 54 for Stendhal and 42 for
Somerset Maugham.
Among the established favourites in
other fields whose ratings remain
high are dramatists George Bernard
Shaw, Anton Chekov and Berthold
Brecht, the children's tales by Grimm
and Hans Christian Andersen and
the mystery stories of Agatha Christie,
Erle S. Gardner and Georges
Simenon.
(1) 16th edition. Unesco, Place de Fon¬
tenoy, Paris 7«. Price: $25; £6.5.0. (stg.);
87F.
the United Kingdom through special equip¬
ment devised by the Writing and Reading
Aids for the Paralyzed Committee, Polio
Research Fund, London. The committee
has developed a bedside microfilm
projector that reproduces the image of a
microfilmed book on a small screen. The
sick person can turn the pages either by
touching a switch, or with pressure from
the lips. A microfilm of any book requested
can usually be supplied within a few days.
DOOM IN BOOK CLUBS: Twenty per
cent of bookselling in the Federal
Republic of Germany was done through
book clubs in 1962, according to a recent
inquiry. Originally launched in Germany
in 1918, book clubs now operate in a
variety of forms all over the world. In
1962, 5.5% of the population of France
belonged to book clubs. Book clubs have
developed most of all in the United States.
XA/HO READS MOST? Frenchmen spend
more time reading than French¬
women, according to a study by French
publishers. A sample analysis of adult
reading habits in France showed that 45%
of men and 37.5% of women read books.
Most people (73%) do their reading in the
evening.
DOOKS ARE BIG BUSINESS: The
American reading public now buys
nearly $2,000 million worth of books every
year according to "The American Reading
Public: What it reads; why it reads"
(edited by Roger J. Smith and published by
R.R. Bowker Co., New York; $7.95). The
American public buys approximately
270 million copies of magazines every
issue and more than 60 million newspapers
every day (48 million on Sundays).
NEW ROLES FOR LIBRARIANS: The
spread of libraries across the U.S.S.R.
has put a librarian in every village and add¬
ed an important social and pedagogical role
to his work. In the United States, where
public libraries serve 70% of the popu¬
lation, the library is increasingly the cultural
centre of the community and a major aid
to adult education.
REPRESENTATIVE WORKS: Under its
Major Project on Mutual Appreciation
of Eastern and Western Cultural Values,
Unesco has arranged during the past eight
years for the publication of 60 titles in
English and 42 in French, translated from
the literature of Eastern countries. As
many as 100 additional titles are now In
preparation. Among works of major
significance published recently are trans¬
lations in English and French of the
famous collection of Indian stories, "The
Panchatanira" (Allen and Unwin, London,
28/-) and the important anthology of ancient
Japanese poetry, "The Manyoshu" (Colum¬
bia University Press, London and New
York, $12.50).
THRILLERS NOT POPULAR: In 1963-64,
1 India published 11,256 titles in English;
3,500 in Hindi; 1,763 in Marathi; and 1.666
in Bengali according to a report compiled
by the National Library, Calcutta. A
recent reading-habits survey in India show¬
ed that 61.2% of readers polled preferred
fiction and 62% were Interested In social
novels. Detective stories were only prefer¬
red by 21 % the lowest In the scale of pre¬
ferences.
o
z
<
z
O
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
DIOGENES
international review
of humanistic studies
A quarterly review, DIOGENES presents a panorama of the
theories and the discoveries that are forming and transforming
the life of modern man.
DIOGENES is the first review of its kind conceived on an
international scale (3 editions : English, French and Spanish).
It has been published since 1952 with Unesco's assistance by the
International Council for Philosophy and Humanistic Studies,
which groups leading specialists throughout the world in many
fields, including philosophy, history, anthropology and the
comparative study of civilizations.
Number 48 of DIOGENES publishes studies on art and seduc¬
tion, on African literature, on the experience of the holy and the
concept of man in Islam, on the narcotic complex of the New
World and on historiography and the disarmed world.
Contents of number 49 include : The politics and economics
of communist China, by the Australian economist , Colin Clark;
the pursuit of happiness, by the American historian, Henry Steel
Commager ; man between myths and technology, by the religious
historian, Charles Kerenyi; and a new conception of the state
between liberalism and socialism, by the Hungarian philosopher,
Laszlo Viraghati.
SUBSCRIPTION (4 numbers)
Canada and U.S.A. : 	 $6.00
Other countries :	 , . $7.00
Single copies : $2.00
ORDER FROM THE PUBLISHER :
Mario Casalini Ltd.,
1519 Pine Avenue West
MONTREAL 25, P.O.
CANADA
WHERE TO RENEW YOUR SUBSCRIPTION
and order other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Prest Department. Royal
Aghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Tradco Agencies, 109 Swanston Street, G. P. O.
Box 2324 V, Melbourne C. I. (Victoria); United
Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
8th Floor, McEwan House, 343 Little Collins St.,
Melbourne C. I. (Victoria). (22/6). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C" Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Sch. 70.-). BELGIUM. All publications : Editions
"Labor", 342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-
Boek-handel, Belgiëlei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (140 FB) and arc slides only; Louis De Lannoy,
1 1 2, rue du Troné, Brussels 5. CCP 3380.00. BURMA.
Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road, Rangoon.
(	). CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa, Ont.
(S 3.00). CEYLON. Lake House Bookshop, Sir
Chittampalan Gardiner Mawata, P.O.B, 244, Colombo,
2 (Rs. 1 3/50). CHINA. World Book CoLtd., 99 Chung¬
king South Rd., Section 1,Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa).
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3 rd Avenue, P.O.
Box 1722, Nicosia. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L,
Spalena 51 , Prague 1 (permanent display) ; Zahrahnici lite¬
ratura Bilkova 4, Prague 1. DENMARK. Ejnar Munks-
gaard, Prags Boulevard 47 Copenhagen S (D. Kr. 17).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agency. P.O. Box 120,
Addis Ababa (10/-). FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirja-
kauppa. 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (Fmk. 9.40). FRANCE.
Librairie de I'Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7". C.C.P.
12598-48. (10 F.). GERMANY. All publications:
R.Oldenbourg Verlag, Rosenheimerstrasse 145, Munich.
8. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed only) Bahren-
felder-Chaussee 160, Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, C.C.P.
276650 (DM 10). GHANA Methodist Book Depot
Ltd. Atlantis House Commercial St., POB 100, Cape
Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28, rue du Stade,
Athens. HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 64,
Nathan Road. Kowloon. HUNGARY. Kultura,
P. O. Box 149. Budapest, 62. ICELAND. Snaebjorn
Jonsson & Co. H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
(120 Kr.) INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd. Nicol
Road, Bellard Estate, Bombay 1:17 Chittaranian Avenue
Calcutta 1 3;Gunfoundry Road.Hyberabad, 1 ; 36a, Mount
Road, Madras 2; Kanson House, 1/24 Asaf Ali Road, P.O.
Box 386, New Delhi, 1; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book &
Stationery Co., 17 Park Street, Calcutta 16, Scindia
House, New Delhi, Indian National Commission Co-ope¬
ration with Unesco, Ministry of Education, for New
Delhi 3. (Rs. 7). INDONESIA. P. N. Fadjar Bhakti
Djalan, Nusantara 22, Djakarta. IRAQ. Mackenzie's
Bookshop, Baghdad. IRELAND. The National Press,
2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (15/5).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores 35, Allenby Road
and 48, Nahlac Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv (l£8).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour Street,
Kingston. (15/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O.Box 605 Tokyo Central, Tokyo
(1,200 yen). JORDAN. Joseph L. BahousS Co., Dar ul-
Kutub, Salt Road. P.O.B. 66. Amman. KENYA. E.S.A.
Bookshop, P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi (10/-). KOREA.
Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Cen¬
tral 64, Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops
Ltd., P.O. Box 286. Monrovia (10/-). LUXEM¬
BURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue, Luxemburg
(F.L. 1 40). -MALAYSIA. Federal Publications Ltd., Times
House, River Valley Rd., Singapore, 9; Pudu Building (3 rd
floor), 110, Jalan Pudu, Kuala Lumpur (M. $ 7.50).
MALTA. Sapienza's Library 26 Kingsway, Valletta,
(15/-). Nalanda Company Ltd., 30.
Bourbon Street, Port-Louis (10/-). British
Library 30 Bid des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (F. 10).
NETHERLANDS. N. V. Martinus Ni¡hoff, Lange
Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl. 8.50). NETHERLANDS
WEST INDIES. G. C. T. Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.)
N.V., Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. (NA fl 4,50). NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office 20, Molesworth
Street (Private Bag) Wellingston, C. 1 Government Books
hops: Auckland (P.O. Box 5344), Christchurch (P.O. Box
-1721), Dunedin P.O. Box 1104)(15/-). NIGERIA.
C.M.S. Bookshops. P.O. Box 174. Lagos (10/-).
NORWAY. All publications : A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille
Grensen 7, Oslo.' For the Unesco Courier also: A.S- Nar-
vesens Litteratur Tieneste, Stortingsgt. 2 Oslo, Postboks
115 (17.50 kr.).' PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Pu¬
blishing Co. Ltd., Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box
374 56-N Gulberg Industrial Colony, Lahore. PHILI¬
PINES. The Modern Book Co., 508 Rizal Avenue Manila.
POLAND. "RUCH", ul. Wronia, 23, Warsaw 10
(zl. 60). PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Lda, Livraria
Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. PUERTO RICO,
Spanish English Publications, Eleanor Roosevelt 115,
Apartado 1912, Hato Rey. RHODESIA. The Book
Centre, Gordon Avenue, Salisbury. SUDAN. AI
Bashir Bookshop, P. O. Box 1118. Khartoum. SWE¬
DEN. All publications : A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbo-
khandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 16. For the Unesco
Courier: Svenska Unescorädet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 12); SWITZERLAND. All publications :
Europa Verlag. 5 Rämistrasse Zurich. Payoc, rue Grenus 6,
1 21 1 , Geneva 11, C.C.P. 1-236. "Courier" only: Georges
Losmaz, 1, rue des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. C.C.P.
1-4811. (Fr. S. 10). TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND.
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue. Bangkok.
(35 ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette. 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Book¬
shop, P.O. Box 1 45, Kampala (1 0/-). REPUBLIC OF
SOUTH AFRICA. All publications : Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Libri Building, Church Street, P.O. Box 724 Pre¬
toria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Cen¬
tral News Agency P.O. Box 1033, Johannesbourg. (R1.-
S0). UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT). Librai¬
rie Kasr El Nil, 38, rue Kasr El Nil Cairo. Sub/agent:
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha, Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I, and Government Bookshops
in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester.
Birmingham and Bristol. (15/-). UNITED STATES,
Unesco Publications Center, 317 East 34th St, New York,
N.Y. 1001 6 ($ 5.00) U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Mocow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Yugoslovenska Kn-
jïg, Tzrazije 27, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
World book
publishing in 1963
totalled 400,000
titles (see page 15).
Here, copies of
a new book await
distribution by
a Paris publisher.
© Paul Almasy, Paris
]]>
</page>
</document>
