<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="061952eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
WLmWÊ
Thç^^
^^^mm\ A WINDOW OPEN ON THE W O R 'aW'B
- i x-w i -
19
lttmm
«Hil n L 7 iIC,
rW
m,
MAY 1964 (17TH YEAR) - PRICE 1 -STG. (U.K.) 30 CENTS (CANADA) 0.70F (FRANCE)
^itrmxti
D OD D
M]
GALILEO
A new vision
of the universe
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
*ÍSlr**
aa
ALILEO : " That universe that I
enlarged a hundred and a thousand
times from what the wise men of
all past ages had thought". Galileo's
investigations of natural laws brought
man a new vision and conception
of the universe (See page 24).
Photo shows vast nebular masses
amid the constellation of the Pleiades.
© Paris Observatory
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier
MAY 1964
17TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
COVER PHOTO
In celebrating the 400th
anniversary of Galileo's birth,
the world acclaims him as a
pioneer who helped to usher
in the era of modern experi¬
mental science (seepage 24).
This portrait of Galileo appears
on a commemorative stamp
issued recently in Italy.
Page
4 WORLD SIDE STORY
A special inquiry on teen-agers today
1) A Twentieth Century Dilemma
2) Why Should This Happen?
By William C. Kvaraceus
12 SHAKESPEARE, YEAR FOUR HUNDRED
14 THE LONDON THAT WAS SHAKESPEARE'S
By Marchette Chute
18 WORLD RENDEZVOUS IN STRATFORD
Preview of a striking Shakespeare exhibition
24 GALILEO: A NEW VISION OF THE UNIVERSE
By Carlo Maccagni
26 THE MAJESTY OF THE COSMOS
By Galileo Galilei
28 THE TRUTH BEHIND THE VEIL OF FACTS
By José Ortega y Gasset
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
THE UNITED NATIONS EDUCATIONAL, SCIENTIFIC AND CULTURAL ORGANIZATION
Published monthly by UNESCO
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7; France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
René Caloz
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey
Russian Edition : Victor Goliachkov
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Italian Edition : Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER ii publijhed monthly, except in July and August when
it is bi-monthly ( I I issues a year) in Fnglish. French, Spani-.h. Russian. German.
Arabic, Japanese, and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed by H.M.
Stationery Office, P. O. Box 569. London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering pottage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier it indexed monthly in The Readers' Guide to
Periodical Literature published by H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates : IO/-stg. ;S3.00 (Canada) ;7.00
French Francs or equivalent. Single copies I /-stg. 30
cents ; 0.70 F.
(M.C. 64.1.. 191 A)
N° 5. 1964
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
WORLD S
by William C. Kvaraceus
A 2 O T H
CENTURY
DILEMMA
O:jn the following
pages we commence
publication of a series ofarticles
presenting the findings of a
Unesco inquiry into juvenilede-
linquency. Two aspects of this
challenging social problem are
discussed in this issue : What
is a juvenile delinquent ? and
Why does delinquency exist?
Unesco's inquiry formed part
of a programme of studies into
problems of social inadapta¬
tion among young people. The
full report will be published
in a forthcoming Unesco study,
"Juvenile DelinquencyA Prob¬
lem for the Modern World".
Part One
of a
Special Inquiry
LMOST every language in the world now has a
i phrase to single out youngsters whose beha¬
viour or tastes are different enough to incite suspicion if
not alarm. They are the teddy boys in England, the
nozem in the Netherlands, the skinn knuttar in Sweden.
The French call them blousons noirs, the South Africans
tsotsis, and the Australians bodgies. In Austria and the
Federal Republic of Germany they are the Halbstarken, in
Taiwan the tai-pau, in Japan the mambo boys or taiyo-
zuku, in Yugoslavia the tapkaroschi, in Italy the giovani
teppisti, in Poland the hooligans and in the U.S.S.R. the
stiliagyi.
But we have no right to assume that every teddy boy
or every blouson noir is actively engaged in delinquency.
These names often mislead people. It is unjust to assume
automatically that a youngster who likes rock'n'roll music
or bizarre clothing is on his way to becoming a delinquent,
if he is not one already. Too often the adult world has
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
IDE STORY
From the French film "Terrain Vague" T) G.R.A.Y. Films-Manuel Litran
used the word "delinquent" to express anger or bewilder¬
ment at adolescent tastes. In fact many educators and
psychologists object to the expression "juvenile delin¬
quent," for the public has used it too often and too glibly
to describe young people who, in some way, offend them.
Not every minor who breaks a rule or who behaves
offensively should be considered a delinquent. After all
it is rare for the behaviour of young people to consistently
conform with the standards that adults set and expect
them to attain.
The differences from country to country with regard
to offences and penalties merely emphasize how divided
the world ls on who is a delinquent, who is not, and what
should be done about it. A widespread form of "delin¬
quency" in Cairo is the collection of cigarette butts from
the street, though this is not an offence in other parts
of the world. A recent survey in India showed that In two
urban areas, Lucknow and Kampur, the second most com¬
mon juvenile offence was vagrancy.
A few years ago in Hong Kong, juveniles brought before
the magistrate's court reached the startling figure of more
than 55,000 and yet over 90 per cent of them had com¬
mitted only technical breaches of the law such as hawking
without a licence. In these cases, one might well ask If
such examples of delinquency are not simply the acts of
the abandoned, the ill-fed or the desperate child.
In Lagos, Nigeria, a delinquent ls primarily an offender
against the unwritten laws of the home; here disrespect
and disobedience are regarded as serious offences.
Thus, statistics on the numbers of children prosecuted
for delinquent acts can sometimes be misleading unless
we know the nature of the offences and what particular
law they violate, and how the children were apprehended
and classified as delinquents by the authorities.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
WORLD SIDE STORY (Cont'd)
Teen-agers on a powder keg
What is there In common between the boy who collects
cigarette butts in a Cairo gutter, the Nigerian who defies
his family, the American who uses a switch-blade or the
European who commits larceny? The differences between
'them are striking yet all may be lumped together as
"delinquents."
In most countries, the upper age limit under the law
for Juvenile offenders varies from 16 to 19. In the United
States, It differs very much from State to State. In
Wyoming, for example, a boy ls legally an adult at 19 while
a girl ls considered a minor until 21. In Connecticut, the
upper limit ls 16.
The minimum age at which a child ls held responsible
for his acts and brought before any kind of court again
fluctuates from country to country. For example, it is
fixed at 7 in the United States, at 9 in Israel, 10 in Great
Britain, 12 In Greece, 13 in France and Poland, 14 In
Austria, Belgium, Czechoslovakia, the Federal Republic of
Germany, Italy, Norway, Switzerland and Yugoslavia.
And, finally, punishments laid down by the laws and
also penal methods vary greatly from country to country.
Corporal punishment was once legally accepted by a
large number of countries: today a judge can still order
it In Burma, Ceylon, India (with the exception of the
Bombay region), Iran, Iraq, Pakistan and Thailand.
Yet even when statistics on delinquency are judged with
the greatest reserve for no neat rows of figures can fully
express the extent of the problem their meaning ls clear:
delinquency Is increasing everywhere. The offences range
from stealing, vandalism and property offences, petty
extortion and gambling to violent behaviour, rowdlness,
truancy, Immoral or Indecent conduct, drinking and drug
addiction.
I n almost every city in the world where delin¬
quency exists, so does the juvenile gang
which has become a modern social institution. Despite
striking national differences, the teen-age gangs are
generally aimless groups of rootless, restless, unemployed
adolescents who most frequently meet on street corners.
Some gangs have committed murder while others do
nothing more offensive than mimic or insult passers-by in
the street.
But these gangs, Innocent or evil, are an important
element in the over-all pattern of juvenile delinquency.
Looking at delinquency In a world-wide context, one does
not often see individual youngsters becoming delinquent
each in his own fashion, but rather a number of boys
participating in joint activities that derive their meaning
and pleasure from a set of common sentiments, loyalties
and rules.
Many gangs are tightly organized; some have little
cohesion and drift apart quickly. The majority of these
gangs often do things which to the rest of the world seem
almost purposeless in their malice.
In Poland, teen-age gangs have damaged railroad trains
and molested passengers for no apparent reason. In
Saskatchewan, Canada, groups of boys have entered pri¬
vate homes (when the owners were away) and mutilated
expensive furnishings without attempting to steal a single
object. In Chiengmai, Thailand, a band of youths, with
a symbol of a white eagle tattooed on their arms, found
their greatest diversion In terrorizing or Injuring outsiders
at such times as they were not engaged in challenging a
rival gang to a war.
In Argentina, gangs of boys have gathered in cafés or
bars to insult or humiliate other customers or passers-by;
after this, they have sometimes wrecked a parked car. In
the Philippines, reports on teen-age gangs indicate the
6 same urge for vandalism. Several youngsters cruised
through the city of Manila in a car and went on a ram¬
page, breaking glass windows of fashionable stores and
residences. For several nights this particular gang kept
the police of three adjacent cities busy trying to track
them down and guess where they might strike next.
Some Juvenile delinquents, however, have clearer goals
in mind. Their satisfactions come from more profitable
acts. Racketeering or petty extortion are good examples.
A gang in Detroit, Michigan, which was composed of
fifteen boys from 13 to 16 years of age, organized a racket
in which all the smaller children of the neighbourhood
were forced to pay five cents for the Insurance of not
being molested on the way to and from the local cinema.
A report from India indicates that gangs of young boys
and girls have learned to be highly successful smugglers
of illicit liquor and drugs. In Israel, a juvenile court judge
has described the theft of cars by groups of young people
as a "striking new feature" because hitherto, gang
behaviour has been rare.
We should not assume, however, that these gangs
are always constantly active and that their
membership remains unchanged, year in and year out.
In each country, the patterns of their activities fluctuate
like the lines on a fever chart.
In the past, reports on the backgrounds of a cross-
section of juvenile delinquents always seemed to indicate
that these children were raised in poor living conditions.
A recent United Nations report points to a radical
change in this tendency. Today it can no longer be
said that juvenile delinquency is confined to a particular
social or economic group. There are numerous and
increasing indications that children from the higher-
income brackets are also becoming delinquents. In
France, the expression blousons dorés (jackets of gold) is
a somewhat ironic reference to delinquents from richer
families than those of the blousons noirs.
The problem of delinquency is by no means confined to
those children who are labelled as delinquents because
they were brought to the attention of law-enforcement
agencies. In every country there are also groups who for
a number of reasons, are not referred to the police or the
authorities. In some cases, their families or schools pro¬
tect them, or the complainant is reluctant to press
charges. It is this second group which complicates the
problem.
The first the known delinquents can be compared to
that part of a huge iceberg that juts above the water.
But the second group of unrecorded, or uncounted, delin¬
quents, is much like the submerged (and much larger)
part of the Iceberg, hidden beneath the water. In the
United States, a recent survey revealed that a relatively
large number of teen-age boys admitted that they had
committed serious acts of delinquency which had never
become a matter of court record. These were the' sons of
middle and upper Income families.
I ore and more studies from sources in many
parts of the world have pointed out that the
number of "hidden" or untabulated delinquents is more
substantial than previously guessed and these Include a
growing percentage of children from financially stable
homes. But "hidden" delinquency is a problem in econo¬
mically deprived groups, too.
One of the richest collections of twentieth-century
myths surrounds the subject of delinquency. Most of
these myths are harmful for they lull many people into
believing they know more about this question than ls the
case. Usually, these myths are over-simplified versions of
what causes delinquency.
In many people's minds, the cause of delinquency can
be clearly traced to the cinema. They cite films which
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Europress, Paris There is no reason to assume automatically that a youngster who
likes rock'n'roll music or bizarre clothing is on the way to becom¬
ing a juvenile delinquent. Too often adults use the word " de¬
linquent" to express anger or bewilderment at adolescent tastes.
seem to glorify or "glamourize" criminal or delinquent
behaviour.
The very broad generalization might be made that some
films can have a provocative effect; but they can rarely
be blamed directly for any type of deviant or criminal
behaviour.
No doubt there are numerous films and television pro¬
grammes that have had some harmful Influence on certain
children. This Influence might even affect the child
unconsciously. Many valid and sensible criticisms have
been made of cinema and television programmes and
comics, but it is an unscientific and somewhat over-sim¬
plified speculation to blame them entirely for delinquency.
Many children who are lonely, or unhappy in some way,
find solace by going to the cinema, watching television
and reading comics to an excessive degree. But delinquent
behaviour is due to much deeper and often more subtle
Influences than the films alone, or a constant diet of tele¬
vision programmes, or even a library of lurid comics.
Another widespread myth is that the absence from
home of mothers Is responsible for delinquent children.
The crucial Importance of a mother's relationship with
a child cannot be denied, but there ls again little scientific
proof that the effects produced by a mother's absence
Invariably include delinquent behaviour.
It is also widely believed that "broken" homes have
caused or Increased a good percentage of all Juvenile
delinquency but here again the available data on the
subject does not substantiate this as an over-all expla¬
nation.
A child ls not apt to benefit when his parents separate
for, after his infancy, he needs a father as much as a
mother. But the mere physical presence of parents ls
hardly enough. The so-called "broken" home is not
always more destructive to a child's growth than a home
where the parents live together in an emotional atmo¬
sphere of tension or unhappiness.
There are always people who point to slum areas as the
source of the problem. But research has shown that slum
clearance In Itself, while highly commendable, is not the
over-all answer to preventing or wiping out delinquency.
Some people have reached the harsh conclusion that all
Juvenile delinquents are stupid, if not retarded, and that 7
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
WORLD SIDE STORY (Cont'd)
The myth of juvenile delinquency
they behave as they do because they lack intelligence.
There ls hardly any reliable scientific information to
support the premise that delinquents are consistently less
Intelligent than other children or adolescents. On the
contrary, many delinquents have turned out to be
extremely bright when tested according to their own
backgrounds.
According to another myth delinquents "inherit"
certain tendencies that make anti-social behaviour in¬
evitable. Scientists have refuted the "bad seed" theory
for children cannot Inherit a "wicked" nature. Because
of many factors, they can and do grow up to become
unhappy and desperate people, but they are not born as
predestined delinquents or criminals.
»ne much publicized theory In Europe about the
cause of delinquency blames children affected
by the war conditions of 1939-1945 for the increase in
crime. But detailed studies in England show that these
children, who are now young adults, "contribute no more
and no less than their share of juvenile delinquency,
perhaps because the circumstances of the deprivation
called forth a very positive response in the general
community."
Once the myths and misunderstandings about delin¬
quency are exposed, the average person begins to perceive
that generalizations are useless. Such explanations as
slum living, broken homes, films and deprivation fall to
provide us with universal and realistic reasons. Some¬
times, each of these may be one among many factors that
shape a child's life, but no one factor can be accepted as
the single over-all reason for the thousands and thousands
of delinquent cases.
To begin to understand the problem of delinquency, we
must recognize that delinquents often do the same things
for vastly different reasons and to achieve very different
results.
To illustrate these differences as far as reasons and
results go here are examples of boys each of whom might
be considered a juvenile delinquent.
15-year-old American, John G., from Los
^Angeles, California, Is one of twelve members
of a street gang called the "Sharks." That gang has an
Inflexible code of values, standards and morals. All the
members have sworn allegiance to this peculiar code and,
for John G., it is the most serious and important
emotional commitment of his life.
Last summer, he and four other gang boys stole a car
that was parked in the neighbourhood. They abandoned
the car, a mile and a half away, the next morning around
4 a.m. When John G. was questioned by a juvenile court,
he made no attempt to explain why he had done It or to
express regret. He had previously been in trouble for
breaking windows and slashing the roofs of convertible
cars with a razor.
His background showed that both his parents worked
and their combined incomes were meagre. Their apart¬
ment was too small for the five members of the family.
John G.'s record in school was poor and his teachers
resented his pose of boredom and contempt. His attitude,
In school or outside of it, was spiteful and malicious, yet
a psychiatric examination revealed no pronounced emo¬
tional disturbances and a normal intelligence.
By conventional standards, John G. might be considered
as a disgrace by his law-abiding parents, as a failure by
his school and as a threat by his community. And yet
there is a telling logic in what he does. All of this delin¬
quent's most offensive acts won the approval and respect
of the people he most admires: gang members of the
"Sharks."
Perhaps every future project that John G. embarks on
will threaten or clearly violate some rule established by
the school, the community or the law, but he will con¬
tinue to be warmed by the admiration of the "Sharks."
His conduct is right by the standards of his own street-
corner subculture, although it happens to be wrong to the
outside world.
A 13-year-old English boy, Basil P., comes from a
prosperous family in London. Basil does not do well in
school, much to the disappointment of his father who
also studied there and had a fine record. Basil's most
conspicuous difficulty Is poor reading; in any subjects
requiring much effort in reading he is apt to become
distracted or lazy. He might have remained an anony¬
mous or sub-standard student, but for the fact that
several of his teachers and many of his classmates know
that Basil has "a habit of taking things."
The boy makes no attempt to deny it. For a long period
he has been pilfering objects from other boys, stealing
both valuable and trifling things. Basil does not hoard
them but often gives them away to classmates, consciously
increasing the risk that the original owner will see his
possession and claim it.
Once, Basil stole three gramophone records from a
music store. He says he ls "sorry" he steals, he does not
know why he does it and he wishes he could stop. His
parents are horrified, his teachers are annoyed and some
of his classmates despise him.
A psychiatric examination revealed that on a deep
symbolical level the objects Basil stole stand for, or
replace, something unconsciously desired but somehow
© Rapho. Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The many myths and misun¬
derstandings surrounding
juvenile delinquency are
usually over-simplified ver¬
sions of what causes it.
Some put the blame on
slums; others point to activi¬
ties of teen-age gangs in
new suburban housing deve¬
lopments. But such expla¬
nations as slum living, bro¬
ken homes, films and depri¬
vations fail to offer universal
and realistic explanations. No
one factor offers a single
over-all -reason for today's
increase in delinquency.
Dominique Roger, Paria
forbidden or unattainable. Basil is now to receive psy¬
chiatric help and treatment.
Do we consider this child as a "hidden" delinquent?
Basil was emotionally disturbed, whereas John G. was not.
Can every anti-social act be considered a neurotic
symptom?
A 17-year-old African, Pierre N.. travelled from his
home village on the Ivory Coast to try to find a Job In
the nearest city. He hoped to be employed in a hotel.
Pierre N. could read and write, speak two languages and
was a bright youngster. In the city, he was caught by a
clerk when trying to steal a shirt from a store. To the
judge, Pierre explained that his own clothes were shabby,
he had no money and he hoped a new shirt would make
a better Impression when he looked for a job.
Is Pierre a juvenile delinquent? If he had been success¬
ful the first time, would he have continued to steal ?
Does all stealing by young people clearly constitute an act
of delinquency?
The considerable differences between these three case
histories only begin to show the hazards of lumping all
adolescent misdeeds under the label of juvenile delin¬
quency.
It ls not always so easy to decide who ls a socialized
delinquent, who is an emotionally disturbed child and who
commits a single offence motivated by an overt and
obvious need. It is meaningless to talk diagnostlcally of
"the delinquent." It ls just not possible to declare that
a child ls a juvenile delinquent In the same way as the
clinical diagnosis affirms that a child ls an epileptic.
In most cases, a delinquent act may mean a fulfilment
of a personal need at the conscious or unconscious level,
and this act, usually a violation of what we consider law-
abiding behaviour, Is a symptomatic one.
Truancy, a violation of both school and legal precepts,
ls one example of symptomatic behaviour. In one case,
truancy may be regarded as a symptom of the healthy
rebellion of a normal adolescent who stays away for one
day. In another instance, truancy may be a sympton of
a child's genuine inability to face and cope with the fear¬
ful realities of dally life.
Perhaps our own realization of how very little we know
about the nature and cause of these symptoms can
encourage us to look at the problem of delinquency with 9
new curiosity and new compassion, and with an open
mind.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
0 WORLD SIDE STORY (Cont'd)
WHY SHOULD
THIS HAPPEN?
'smart alecky' youth who wore pegged trousers
^and a flattop haircut began six months on a
road gang today for talking back to the wrong judge.
M. J., 20, of M., was fined $25 and costs in Judge E. R.'s
Superior Court for reckless operation of an automobile.
But he Just didn't leave well enough alone.
'"I understand how It was, with your pegged trousers
and flattop haircut,' R. said in assessing the fine. 'You go
on like this and I predict In five years, you'll be in prison.'
"When J. walked over to pay his fine, he overheard
Probation Officer S. tell the judge how much trouble the
'smart alecky' young offender had been. 'I Just want you
to know I'm not a thief,' interrupted J. to the judge. The
Judge's voice boomed to the court clerk: 'Change that
Judgement to six months on the roads'. "
This anecdote taken from a press report headlined
"Judge Imposes Road Gang Term for Back Talk" clearly
points out the hostility that many adults even those in
responsible professional roles rather proudly display
towards those young people who Impress them as trouble¬
makers.
Not even the most sympathetic person can deny that
very often the actions of delinquents are harmful and
often revolting to other people and to community life.
Many law-abiding citizens thus feel justified in
condemning the behaviour of juvenile delinquents and
pressing loudly for stronger punishment.
Admittedly, the delinquent must learn to face the
natural consequences of what he does and realize that
he must accept a personal responsibility for his life. But
threats will not accomplish this and neither will bribes
or beatings. Sometimes punishment confirms delinquency.
It can have a compelling psychological effect on the child
who comes to believe that he deserves it and, so, must
also Justify it.
N
10
| OTHiNG Is more discouraging about the problem
of juvenile delinquency, aside from the tragic
results to the children involved, than the lack of clear and
immediate solutions. Understandably, most people whose
lives are affected by it (even slightly) want a sure-fire and
immediate plan of action. And they are all too often the
people who clutch at the belief that juvenile delinquency
has a single cause and, therefore, a single solution. This
Is never true.
We must accept the fact that delinquent behaviour,
which stems from so many combinations of factors,
cannot be treated or controlled until several scientifically-
evolved theories about the individual offender have been
checked. The child must be considered completely apart
from his fellow offenders. His life at home, his problems
at school, his relationship with his parents, his own self-
image and his personality must all be carefully revealed
and evaluated. Even this sort of meticulous and expensive
research does not provide the answers or solve the
question of how to help. It can always provide, however,
much more insight as to why a child chooses often un¬
consciously to be a juvenile delinquent.
But what are the theories? What are the views of the
world's specialists on human behaviour?
In the psychoanalytical field, there are many theories.
One says that delinquency, as with any other form of
defiant behaviour, results from severe frustrations suffered
by a growing child. Another, that juvenile delinquency
ls an expression of rebellionand clearly not a rebellion
for something but against something.
B'ewildered parents may ask, " A rebellion
'against what?" Here again, the answer
depends on the individual child who may be striking out
against what he unconsciously feels is an unwarranted
lack of love on the part of his parents. In other cases the
answer may be found in situations which seem threaten¬
ing or, simply, in the terrible doubts of the child about
himself.
Of course these are condensed explanations of very
complicated theories. It can never be assumed that every
anti-social child is trying to get revenge, or to be
compensated, for not being loved. If it were suggested
to a juvenile delinquent with a long record of offences
that he acts the way he does because of hidden feelings
that he cannot "identify" himself, the idea would seem
preposterous, or ridiculous, to him. For he does not really
know himself, or his own inner crises, or what has made
him the person he has become.
Another theory suggests that juvenile delinquency is
perhaps the failure of a young boy to be able to identify
himself with what psychologists call a "male authority
figure." This naturally means the child's father, the
dominating and consistent male influence in his life. If
there ls no father, if he is rarely at home or even if he
is a dim or withdrawn figure in the child's life, a small
boy may come to feel a very deep insecurity about his
own image of himself as a man. This may seem a pre¬
cocious worry to adults but it ls a valid one for the child.
And this worry will have a strong Influence on the child.
In the broadest sense any adolescent who ls unsure of
himself can appease his worries or will try to by being
aggressive. Here ls where one of the rare positive state¬
ments about all delinquent behaviour can be made: it is
remarkably aggressive. Aggression, however, ls not a
simple act and may show Itself In a variety of ways.
Aggression may be verbal, it may consist of destructive
acts, it may be sexual. Aggression may be directed
towards one's self, towards the world, or both.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Almost every professional person who has studied and
tried to analyse human behaviour agrees that children
who feel they are not loved or wanted can be very severely
damaged by such deprivationreal or Imaginary. This
also applies to children who sense that their parents' love
ls not really consistent and depends on too many things.
If a 6-year-old is constantly told that If he ls "good"
he will be loved, is It unreasonable of that child to feel
that this love ls a conditional thing? Feeling a lack of
love, or feeling that love ls a promised reward, not a
genuine and steady emotion, the child may develop an
overpowering fear. This fear may express itself In
aggressive behaviour based on anxietyand a long cycle
begins. The child whose parents do not love him as a
person feels betrayed or abandoned by them.
I aladjusted children and adolescents are
I usually those youngsters who have suffered
from these feelings. The courage to love and trust others
falls them. Dr. Lucien Bovet, a consultant In mental
health to WHO, has written: ". . . all the measures, advice,
detention, psychotherapy, or any other procedure applied
to a delinquent have a common aim; this primary aim is
to foster the growth in the delinquent of stable, secure,
emotional relationships with some person who gains his
confidence.
"By whatever paths, in fact, the delinquent arrives at
delinquency, we find in the factors leading to crime a
common denominator in the following vicious circle:
insecurity, anxiety, aggression, guilt, and insecurity. In
the same way, the common denominator of therapy is
security re-dlscovered."
Security re-dlscovered often means helping the child
to be able to enter Into trusting and affectionate relation¬
ships. It ls a long, fragile process and yet, without a
capacity for affection, no contentment or adjustment will
ever be possible.
I n analysing Juvenile delinquency In Poland, a
specialist has written: "The first command¬
ment of hooliganism enjoins the delinquent to force the
submission of others but never to submit himself. A
fellow who cannot hold his liquor, who gets thrashed In
a fight, who becomes sentimental over a girl, or shows any
emotion in any response, or who uses a "big word' in all
seriousness (I.e., speaks in the conventional language of
adult authority without the proper sarcasm), is said to
have 'chickened out.' He believes In physical fitness and
lives by brute force. He despises sentimentality; to him
life is ideally the Indulgence of Instinct." This descrip¬
tion can include many juvenile delinquents, not Just those
of one country.
Adolescence is a complex period. Few adults are very
sympathetic, considering that they, too, went through the
same process of growing up and often failed, in less
conspicuous ways, to achieve their own maturity. It ls
hard to remember, after so many years, the helplessness
a child often feels. An Australian specialist has wisely
written that adolescence ". . . is often a period of tur¬
bulent emotion and a time when love, tolerance and
imagination were never more in demand yet never harder
wholly to accept."
(To be continued)
By whatever strange and devious paths a young person
becomes a delinquent there exists in the factors leading
to crime the following vicious circle: insecurity, anxiety,
aggression, guilt and insecurity. The start of this cycle
may be rooted in feelings of not being loved or wanted.
William c. kvaraceus is a Unesco specialist on problems
of social inadaptation among youth. Dr. Kvaraceus, who
has taught at Boston University, is now Professor of Edu¬
cation and Director of Youth Studies at the Lincoln Filenc
Center for Citizenship and Public Affairs of Tufts Uni¬
versity, U.S.A. He is the author of Juvenile Delinquency
and the School and The Community and the Delinquent.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Susanne. London
MIDSUMMER NIGHT'S DREAMER. "Sleep that sometimes shuts up sorrow's eye. Steal me a while from mine
12 own company". A figure from" A Midsummer Night's Dream" slumbers in a London workshop where Gargantuan
models of Shakespearean characters have been made for an exhibition in Stratford-on-Avon on the life and work of
the Bard focal point of 1964's world-wide commemorations of Shakespeare's fourth centenary. (See page 18)
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
SIGNATURE OF WILLIAM SHAKESPEARE
i)
WILLIAM SHAKESPEARE
YEAR FOUR HUNDRED
Wfj&
THIS year the world is paying a 400th birthday tribute to William
Shakespeare. No one is certain on which day in April 1564 the
great English poet and dramatist was born. The register of the parish church
at Stratford-on-Avon, his birthplace, only records the date of his baptism
(April 26). Tradition and sentiment, however, have united to proclaim that he
was born on April 23. This was also the date on which he died in Stratford
52 years later in 1616.
What little is known of Shakespeare's life is based on official records,
contemporary allusions and various traditions. As far as we know no attempt
was made to record the facts of his life until 1662. And Shakespeare himself
paid so little attention to posterity that he did not even bother to get his own
plays into print (his collected plays published in a volume called the First
Folio did not appear until seven years after his death).
The son of a prosperous glove-maker, Shakespeare married when he was
18 and had three children. Between 1584, when his twin children were born in
Stratford, and 1592 when he was acting and writing plays in London, there is
no definite evidence of what happened to him. From 1594 to the end of his
London career he was a member of a dramatic company which was given the
title of The King's Men, under the patronage of James I. Most scholars attribute
38 plays to his authorship, and he left 154 sonnets, which were published
in 1609.
Thousands of books have been written about Shakespeare and his works
more than about any other world literary figureand he has probably also
inspired more controversy than any other man of letters.
To commemorate Shakespeare's 4th centenary. The Unesco Courier has
chosen to give its readers a look at some of the lesser-known aspects of the
Shakespearean periodthe London in which he lived and worked (the real
background to his activities as an actor-playwright) and the London theatre 13
audiences who came to watch him act and to applaud his plays.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
14
British Council
When Shakespeare arrived in London the first
public playhouse had only opened a few years
earlier, in 1576. Theatre and drama, however, were
already vigorous and expanding and before long a
"theatreland" had grown up in Bankside, seen in
the foreground of the panoramic view of London
Town shown at top of page. Engraved in 1616,
this shows two octogonal-shaped show places of
the day. Flags flying from the Globe Theatre (on
the right) for which most of Shakespeare's plays
were written and from its neighbour. The Bear
Garden, announce that a performance is sched¬
uled. Theatregoers arrived by boat or came
across London Bridge, which was then covered
with high buildings. Above, a model of a
typical Elizabethan theatre; Right, an artist's
impression of a play in progress at the Globe.
lO Reproduced by permission of the Trustees of the British
Museum
THE
by Marchette Chute
This article is copyright Reproduction prohibited
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
LONDON THAT WAS
SHAKESPEARE'S
When William Shakespeare came to London In
the 1580's, it was still in many ways the
mediaeval city that Geoffrey Chaucer had known. The
wall that surrounded the city was still intact, and the only
concession the authorities . had made to the increased
traffic was to open a new gate, called Moorgate, which
gave access to the fields to the north. The old monastic
foundations had been changed into residences and tennis
courts and even into factories, and the beautiful little
chapel on London Bridge had become a warehouse, but
London was still a city of churches and they dominated
the lives of its inhabitants.
The service at St. Paul's Cathedral was now given in
English, but the building was much as it had been except
that its wooden spire had vanished. It had caught fire
some twenty years earlier and so many citizens had
gathered to watch the blaze and hamper the fire fighters
that the famous steeple had burned down to its square
stone base . . .
In every way the tight little mediaeval city that Chaucer
had known was pushing against its confining walls under
the pressure of an expanding and increasingly excitable
population. The fall of Antwerp had made London a
substitute commercial centre and the religious war on the
Continent had doubled the foreign population of London
in thirteen years. Every few years the government
brought out another ordinance on the subject and the
penalties were strict, but in spite of the efforts of the
courts, the people went on packing themselves into the
overcrowded city, adding to what the citizen of a smaller
town bitterly called that "vast, unwieldy and disorderly
Babel of buildings which the world calls London."
Meanwhile the city government went on gallantly trying
to enforce a mediaeval code of behaviour that had been
nearly obsolete in Chaucer's day and was now little more
than a wistful idea. The mayor and the aldermen clung
to the conviction that If enough laws were passed it would
somehow be possible to turn their sprawling young giant
of a city into something small, neat, compact and
comfortable. They observed with horror the flaunting of
their authority in the suburbs, where men like James
Burbage put up buildings that had no place at all in a
Christian commonwealth (1), and they still struggled to
keep the city in a state of mind of which their great¬
grandfathers would have approved.
(1) The author is referring to the erection of London's first
theatres.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
SHAKESPEARE (Cont'd)
The
The mayor and aldermen were heavily handicapped in
this attempt by the fact they got no support at all from
Queen Elizabeth. When a bill to restrict Sunday pastimes
was passed by both houses of Parliament in 1585, it was
promptly vetoed by the Queen who herself went to
shooting-matches and plays on Sunday and saw no reason
why her subjects should not . do likewise. It was her
opinion that no amount of ordinances would keep a
Londoner from enjoying himself, and that the wisest
course to pursue was to make a government profit on the
money he spent.
She gave a patent for licensing gaming-houses to
Thomas Cornwallis in 1576, in spite of a strict law against
gaming in London, and justified it with the statement
that the Londoners "secretly or openly ... do commonly
play and ... no penalty of the laws or statutes aforesaid
hath heretofore restrained them." On the same basis
she gave licenses for bowling-alleys and the manufacture
of dice and playing cards; and the fencing clubs >and
theatre owners could always turn to the Queen for
protection when the attacks of the city fathers became
especially violent. Elizabeth was a true child of the
Renaissance, in this matter at least, and her attitude was
one that the mayor and aldermen were incapable of
understanding.
The truth was that the city authorities were trying to
maintain medieval standards in a city that was no longer
medieval in spirit. A new spirit of curiosity had
developed, an Intellectual ferment that made the old ideal
of blind obedience almost impossible to enforce. London
no longer lived In comparative Isolation but was
beginning to feel all the influences of Renaissance Europe.
Above all, it felt the stirring of new winds from Italy.
16
h or the average Londoner Italy was still the
place of strange poisons and passionate love
affairs, to be mistrusted as the home of the wicked
Machiavelll; but English architects travelled in Italy and
brought back new designs. English sportsmen did their
riding and fencing in the Italian manner, and when a
poet wrote love songs he imitated Petrarch. There was a
fury of translation from the Italian of novels and plays
and poems, and the brilliant Italian actors penetrated
England and flourished for at least a season in London.
The people of England and especially of London, still
took a rather provincial view of foreigners. Visitors from
the Continent spoke with some bitterness of the self-
satisfaction of the English, whose highest praise for any
foreigner was that it was a pity he was not an
Englishman . . .
An Englishman knew his own country was the centre of
the world, but he felt a deep interest in knowing how the
men of lesser nations lived. Nearly every young man of
birth took a tour abroad and this was also the era of the
great explorations, when boys from small English villages
came back from long voyages financed by London
merchants to tell of the outlandish wonders they had seen.
Occasionally these wonders could be seen in London
hustle and bustle
of a restless city
itself, like the gloomy Indians In brown taffeta, that
Walter Raleigh brought back with him. Londoners like
Richard Garth and William Cope started collections of
Instructive curios from other lands, and in Mr. Cope's
collection the respectful visitor could see costumes from
Java and Arabia, African charms, porcelain from China
and a long, narrow Indian canoe hung from the ceiling,
to say nothing of such special wonders as an embalmed
child, a unicorn's tail, and some little flies "which glow
at night in Virginia instead of lights, since there is often
no day there for over a month."
Some Londoners may have doubted this description of
Virginia, but no one would have doubted the unicorn,
except what one expert on natural history called a
"vulgar sort of infidel people" who believed only in cows
and sheep. Unicorns were mentioned even in the Bible
and it was well known that the horn of the animal,
pulverized and boiled in wine, made an excellent mouth¬
wash.
In any case, the greatest source of education to the
average Londoner was not museums, or language teachers
The bellman, or night
watchman, on his
rounds in the London
of Elizabethan days.
From " Shakespeare's
England ", Clarendon Press,
Oxford, 1 950
or college endowments. His greatest source of education
was books. It was the invention of printing that set the
one deep gulf between the Middle Ages and the Renais¬
sance, and the difference between Chaucer's audience and
Shakespeare's was the difference between a period when
a book was a rich man's toy and a period when it was
available to the whole of the middle class.
The average Londoner did not look upon a book pri¬
marily as entertainment for an idle hour. The purpose
of reading was to tell him something he wanted to know,
and books poured from the presses to tell him how to
keep accounts, how to survey land, how to play the cittern
without a teacher, how to take spots off velvet, or cook,
or ride, or write a good hand. There was information on
how to graft plants, how to compute interest, and what
to do "when the physician is not present," and there were
cook books and dream books and books on the art of
navigation for amateur mariners.
Elizabethan London was the home of the short-cut, with
each of its inhabitants wanting to know as much as
possible as quickly as he could. Nor for him was the slow,
laborious grounding in the classics and rhetoric on which
Oxford and Cambridge spent so much time. He could buy
a book of classical quotations, conveniently arranged
under subject matter, to be used whenever he needed
them, and to improve his vocabulary there were books
that offered lists of effectives similes and other aids to
rhetoric.
If an energetic and restless Londoner could not find
time to settle down and read a book, or if he lacked the
necessary sixpence or shilling, there was a still quicker
and cheaper way of getting Information. For a penny a
Londoner could buy an Illustrated ballad, a single sheet
of paper with an engaging woodcut and a vigorous rhyme
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
to be sung to some popular tune. These broadsides
occasionally reported bits of history or told stories of
Biblical and classical subjects, and a "proper ballad dia¬
logue-wise between Troilus and Cressida" was not un¬
usual. But. chiefly they kept the public informed on
interesting contemporary news events, especially murders,
fires and other public disasters, the death of prominent
people and monstrous births both at home and abroad.
A more sober observer of the current scene could pay a
little more money and buy news pamphlets that would
keep him informed on the state of the wars in Europe,
accounts of the exemplary courage of the English, or of
the atrocities committed by the wicked enemies of
England, or even a book with a special map of France
showing all the fortresses. There were more books on
news events than on any subject except religion, and the
government saw to it that the approach was just as well
controlled . . .
Any of these books and broadsides could be bought in
the book stalls that were chiefly clustered together in
St. Paul's churchyard. Building space was short In the
city and the booksellers had first erected sheds in the
area and then changed them into real shops. The book
stalls were open by seven in the morning and here the
cheap reprints of plays and the shilling novels jostled for
place with translations from the French and Italian and
handsome folios on law and medicine and theology.
From" Shakespeare's England " Clarendon Press. Oxford, 1950
Illustration from a popular ballad of Shakes¬
peare's time based on "The Spanish Tragedy"
a play by Thomas Kyd. These ballads could bo
bought for a penny. They bore an engaging
woodcut and a rhyme to be sung toa popular tuno.
any London shows cost the happy population
I nothing at all. No one had to pay to see the
Lord Mayor's show and cheer the wicker-work giants or
to see the water games on the Thames. Queen Elizabeth,
that great amateur showman, was given to making
sudden, spectacular appearances by torchlight, and when
she opened Parliament she was carried through the streets
in a red velvet cloak and a gold crown, while twenty-
four glittering maids of honour rode in single file behind
her. It was an age of the most determined dressing-up,
and a knight saw nothing undignified in appearing as
Eve in a tilt-yard show, with apples hanging on his
armour and long hair attached to his helmet . . .
If a Londoner liked to look at strange animals there
was the zoo In the Tower, where four lions, a tiger and a
porcupine could be peered at through the wooden lattices
after a judicious tip to the keeper; and for a time one
of the houses on London Bridge housed a melancholy
camel. A traveller from Kremzow reported that he saw
in London a cow with six legs and a porpoise. He also
saw a woman pigmy six thumbs high, a boy with a head
like a pig, and (by an association of ideas that would
seem normal to any Londoner) the Earl of Arundel being
led to his imprisonment in the Tower.
The Londoners especially liked their entertainment to
have an element of conflict and suspense in it, and they
went in large numbers to the Star Chamber hearings at
Westminster. The final stages of these trials were open
to the public and aroused such interest in the theatri¬
cally-minded Londoners that the audience would start
arriving at three o'clock in the morning to be sure of
getting a good seat and the usher of the chamber made a
small fortune in tips.
Betting members of the population spent much of their
"Afflicted with these strange
flies" (Romeo and Juliet).
Piles of garbage left in the
London streets bred flies
by the million in hot weather.
From " The Spider and the Flie "
by John Heywood, 1 556
time watching cock fights In an arena near Smithfleld,
where admission was a penny and the cocks who fought
on the round, straw-covered table were usually well for¬
tified with brandy. Even more popular were the bear-
baitings, which were patronized by everyone from the low¬
liest tinker to the loftiest of visiting noblemen, and a
visit to the Bear Garden was as much standard procedure
with the average London visitor as seeing the tombs at
Westminster Abbey . . .
Best of all, however, there were plays, and whatever a
Londoner's interests might be, there was sure to be a
play In town that would suit him. If he read the gory
penny broadsides and went to executions, he could go to
the theatre and see the best contemporary murders re-
enacted on the stage, with property limbs flapping about
and real blood flowing. If he liked processions, he could
see kings and councillors at coronations and in battle
order and at other noble events, for the plays never
omitted an opportunity for pageantry "where the drums
might walk and the play ruffle." If he were interested
in natural wonders he could see much of zoological Interest
on the stage, where pigmies warred with cranes, and
dragons were as realistic as hoops and painted canvas and
gunpowder could make them. If he were interested in
life in other lands, he could go to a play like "The Black¬
smith's Daughter" and shudder at a tale of treachery
in foreign parts, and if he were Interested in politics he
could go to "Pompey and Caesar" or "Catiline's
Conspiracies" and mark the danger of treason in
high places... Any popular story, from Samson to Henry V,
found its way to the stage to satisfy the greatest theatre-
going public in the world . . .
he nature of this Elizabethan audience has
been much misrepresented, chiefly by
nineteenth-century scholars, and among those that have
been unjustly treated are the London apprentices.
They have been pictured as a riotous, noisy group of
young clods who, as groundlings, would only appreciate
the broadest kind of ranting and horseplay, while their
elders and betters in the higher-priced seats were
smilingly able to appreciate the finer things that the
theatre had to offer.
This point of view can be well documented, but the
documentation comes from a rather prejudiced source.
It was the London Council that was always viewing the
youth of the city with disapproval that an older genera¬
tion usually feels for a younger one. It was the opinion
of the Council that every young man should spend his
time working very hard for an older one, and that any
CONT'D ON PAGE 20
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
L U íiii
mir i üi-
BIRTHPLACE OF THE BARD. Stratford-on-Avon (above left) some 90 miles
north of London is Shakespeare's birthplace and where he now lies buried
in the church by the River Avon. Above right, Falstaff, one of a group of
statues of Shakespearean characters near the Stratford Memorial Theatre.
18
WORLD RENDEZVOUS
IN STRATFORD
Photo reportage © Susanne, London. Text by M. Trajtenberg
Figures created
for the Shake¬
speare Exhibition
by Jean Hugo, a
great-grandson of
the famed French
poet and novelist,
Victor Hugo. Jean
Hugo is one of
the international
group of painters,
sculptors, design¬
ers and musicians
who shared in mak¬
ing the exhibition.
CHIEF attraction in Shakespeare's 400th anniversary celebra¬
tions in England this year is the exhibition that opens in
Stratford-on-Avon, on April 23. Conceived by writer and
art critic Richard Buckle and created by an international group
of 30 young artists and technicians, the exhibition employs
all the arts and a complex range of techniques to evoke the
life and work of William Shakespeare against a background of
Elizabethan and Jacobean England. Its 17 sections comprise
four main groups (winter, in Stratford ; spring, symbolizing the
Bard's progress to London ; summer in the English capital, with
its days of glory at the Globe Theatre ; and autumn, once again
in Stratford, to where Shakespeare retired and where he died
in 1616). Most of the scenes have been called "happenings"
because of the artifices of lighting, music, sounds and speech
which seem to give living movement to figures, paintings
and reconstituted scenes. Research (the monumental work of
Sir Edmund Chambers) and artistic fantasy (the analysis of
poetic images in every major Shakesperean work, that writer
Caroline Spurgeon calls "The Imagery of Shakespeare") have
also contributed. Some 10,000 visitors are expected daily.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Everything about Stratford, from its shops to
its Memorial Theatre recalls the story and evokes
the image of the town's most famous son.
Left, giant "beefeaters" (the famous guards of the Tower of London) in their
Tudor uniforms tower over a chaos of screens, drawings, wire and welding
equipment in a theatrical workshop improvised in a disused London ballroom.
Here, Stratford's exhibition took shape. Above, made of and garbed in fibre
glass and plastic (replacing stuffs, brocade and silks) this half-com¬
pleted Lady of Windsor symbolizes pomp and pride at the Elizabethan court.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
SHAKESPEARE (Cont'd)
Apprentices visit
'Satan's ChapeF
sign of Independence or lack of subservience to an
employer was a really serious offence.
The Ideal apprentice was not supposed to go to a music
or dancing school, and some of his employers would have
been equally pleased if he had not been allowed to go to
plays. "Whosoever shall visit the chapel of Satan, I
mean the Theatre, shall find there no want of young
ruffians", Innocent young lads who had become quite
corrupted through seeing plays. "Many of nature honest
and tractable have been altered by those shows and spec¬
tacles and become monstrous." and the Council united
with the Puritans In agreeing that nothing could be worse
for the morals of an apprentice than going to the theatre.
The apprentices themselves did not think so, and they
Hocked to the theatre. But a penny was a large sum of
money to a boy who was learning a trade and he expected
good value for it. Moreover, standing places could not
be reserved and he had to arrive at the theatre early to
be sure of a good location. From a complaint of the
mayor's on the subject, It seems clear that the theatre
began filling hours before the show started, and since the
groundlings had to stand both during this period and
through the whole action of the play, they demanded
much more in the way of entertainment than the com¬
fortable citizens in the seats overhead. If the groundlings
felt they were being cheated they were not slow to express
themselves, and most of the contemptuous remarks about
their mental incapacity came from the playwrights whose
plays had not had a popular success.
20
s a matter of fact, the apprentices belonged
Las a class to one of the most privileged and
intelligent groups in London. A landed gentleman did
not hesitate to send his son up to London to learn to be
a goldsmith or a draper, and in the ranks of the appren¬
tices were all the future aldermen and mayors of London.
Each of them was treated by his employer as a member
of the household and they belonged entirely outside the
ranks of the unprotected, exploited labourers with whom
London was unfortunately familiar. They were the future
businessmen of London and their only crime was their
youth and the fact that they loved the theatre.
Another section of the Elizabethan audience that has
sometimes been misrepresented is the women. It was
rather arbitrarily decided in the nineteenth century that
women seldom went to plays In Elizabethan times. Oc¬
casionally a coarse tinker's wife might get in among the
groundlings or a fine lady sheltered by a mask might be
escorted to one of the expensive seats, but the London
housewife stayed home and wove cloth and kept her house
clean as a good woman should. This may have been
the Victorian conception of womanhood, but it was cer¬
tainly not shared by the Elizabethans.
From the first the reformers had centered their special
attention on the women of London, since It was well
known that few "women come from plays... with safe and
chaste minds." One writer devoted a whole section "to
the gentlewomen citizens of London" and besought them
when they felt nervous and unhappy not to go to plays but
to visit a neighbour or read a good book. Another writer
tried to terrify them with tales of citizens' wives who
sinned and then confessed on their death beds that it
was the initial mistake of going to the theatre that had
turned their thoughts from a contemplation of virtue and
started them down the slippery path to perdition.
The citizens' wives paid no attention to all this advice,
for the women of London had always done what they
pleased and expected to go on doing it. England was
known as "a paradise for women" and nearly every
foreigner was startled by the amount of freedom they took
"they generally take up a wonderful laughter and shout
Susanne, London
together with one voice," and Gosson admits to having
done the same thing himself. "Many times we laugh
so extremely, that striving to bridle ourselves, we
cannot." Gosson happened to be writing after he had
given up making plays and abandoned the theatre, and
he added that this kind of enjoyment was very unsulted
as their right. "The womenfolk of England... have far
more liberty than in other lands, and know just how to
make good use of it."
The traveller from Kremzow noted that a throng of
spectators had a great many women In it "for the women¬
folk in England wish to be in at everything," and another
foreigner noted it as "particularly curious" that
women went into the taverns alone or accompanied by
other women . . .
The playwrights themselves were very well aware that
a large part of the success of a play depended on the
approval of the women. There was always an epilogue
spoken at the end of the show, with a request for applause,
and although very few of the epilogues of Shakespeare's
plays have survived, three of them are addressed to the
women in the audience. For
if they smile
And say 'twill do
the play would be a success . . .
Stephen Gosson, a playwright of the period, had
described the wholehearted enthusiasm with which a
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Detail of a model of Elizabethan London as it appears, beyond a reconstruction of a garden
of the period, from a window of the Long Gallery in the Shakespeare Exhibition at Stratford.
This Gallery opens the exhibition's "summer" section depicting the Bard's rise to
fame and prestige in London (see page 18). Showing some 40 contemporary portraits of
the great figures of the period, it has been called "an exhibition within an exhibition".
London audience settled down to enjoy Itself in the
theatre. If the play was a tragedy the susceptible
Londoners dissolved into sympathetic tears, "weeping
and mourning" with a rich vicarious satisfaction at the
woes portrayed on the stage. If the play was a comedy
to a Christian commonwealth. "When such excess of
laughter bursteth out that we cannot hold It, there is no
temperance. . . . Where no temperance is, there is no
wisdom ..."
here had always been a certain amount of
opposition to the acting profession in London,
and it crystallized when a whole building was put up
with no other purpose but to give plays. The plaster was
hardly dry on the walls of the theatre before the London
preachers began to wail about the temple of sin that had
been erected practically in their midst. Every current
disaster that struck Lpndon, Including the earthquake of
1580, could be traced to God's anger because this heathen
development, with its glittering walls and rich costumes,
had been allowed to flourish in the otherwise pure air of
the city.
These pulpit attacks had a certain promotion value to
a manager who was trying to fill a large theatre; for the
London preachers depicted the sinful delights of that
"gorgeous playing place," as they called it, with such
fascinated horror that they must have supplied an
excellent advertisement for the place. As the sober
journal of Sir Roger Wllbraham Indicates, the Elizabethan
business man was well aware of the value of this kind
of publicity. Wllbraham tells the case of a printer at
the turn of the century who found himself loaded with
unsold copies of a certain book. "He caused a preacher
in his sermon to inveigh against the vanity thereof; since
which it hath been six times under press, so much it was
in request ..."
An Elizabethan audience had become highly susceptible
to the use of words, trained and alert to catch their exact
meaning and full of joy if they were used well. But this
meant, as the basis of any successful stage production,
that all the words had to be heard clearly. The actors
used a fairly rapid delivery of their lines and this meant
that breath control, emphasis and enunciation had to be
perfect If the link that was being forged between the
emotions of the audience and the action on the stage
was not to be broken.
When Shakespeare first came to London, the problem
of effective stage delivery was made somewhat easier by
the use of a heavily endstopped line, where the actor
could draw his breath at regular intervals and proceed
at. a kind of jog-trot. But during the following decade
this kind of writing became increasingly old-fashioned,
giving way to an intricate and supple blank verse that
was much more difficult to handle intelligently; and no
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
SHAKESPEARE (Cont'd)
Above, Shakespeare's birthplace in Stratford. A centre of
pilgrimage for admirers of the great dramatist from all over
the world, it has been transformed into a museum. Right,
Shakespeare's memorial in the Holy Trinity Church, Strat¬
ford, where the poet is buried. The bust, which was placed
on the church wall a few years after Shakespeare's death, is
the work of a London tombmaker named Gheerart Janssen. Photos Unesco Courier Archives
His greatest monument :
the playgoers of the world
22
one was more instrumental In bringing the new way of
writing into general use than Shakespeare himself . . .
It was in London, for instance, that Shakespeare
learned French; and French was taught by Frenchmen
who worked in competition with each other and used oral,
conversational methods that were designed to get
colloquial French into the student's head as quickly as
possible.
When French was finally accepted Into the
grammar school curriculum it was subjected to
the heavy emphasis on rules and grammar with which
the Latin tongue was already burdened, and Shakespeare
was probably very fortunate that no one tried to teach
him English by the same system. All the rules, the ritual
and the reverent embalming were focussed on Latin, and
as a result the writers of the late sixteenth century had
a lighthearted sense of freedom where their native tongue
was concerned because it had never been laid out in the
schoolroom and expounded.
Much respect was given to the Latin language, but
all the affection, the excited experimentation and the
warm sense of personal ownership went into the English.
If a writer needed an effective word he could not go to a
dictionary for it. There were no English dictionaries,
although Richard Mulcaster remarked it would be a
praiseworthy deed to compile one. The writer could
either reach back into his memory, a practice that forced
every writer to be also an alert listener, or else he could
invent a new word entirely.
There was still some doubt among thoughtful men
whether it was quite respectful to the language to use It
in so light-hearted a fashion. George Puttenham
apologized for using such "strange and unaccustomed" new
words as idiom, method impression, numerous, penetrate,
savage and obscure. Gabriel Harvey was scolded for
using such abnormalities as theory and jovial and negotia¬
tion; and Ben Jonson, who could never forget his classical
education, was horrified by a fellow playwright who used
such outlandish words as damp, clumsy, strenuous and
puffy.
This use of new words could degenerate into complete
confusion in the hands in Incompetent writers but it
gave Shakespeare exactly the freedom he needed. He
felt at complete liberty to pick up effective new words
and combinations of words wherever he could find them,
and a play like Hamlet is so full of them that it would
have made a schoolmaster turn pale if he had had any
responsibility for teaching his charges the English lan¬
guage. Fortunately he had no such responsibility, and
young William Shakespeare was free to discover the great
reaches of the English language as a freeborn and
independent citizen . . .
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
It ls known that William Shakespeare Joined the Cham¬
berlain's company when it was formed in 1594 because he
is listed as one of the three actors who received payment
for that year's Christmas performances at Court. It is
not known whether he worked for the company earlier,
when It was under the patronage of Lord Strange, since
his name is on none of the scattered lists that have
survived; but he remained with this group of actors for
the rest of his professional life.
The men who made up this company were for all
practical purposes closer to Shakespeare than his own
brothers, for he worked with them summer and winter,
most of the day and often well into the night, for the
next sixteen years. They were his fellow craftsmen, his
close personal friends, and in one sense as much the tools
of his art as the words he used. They were the medium
through which he operated as a playwright to reach the
emotions of his audience, and it was one of the most
fortunate things In Shakespeare's fortunate life that he
worked with so able and intelligent a group of men.
An Elizabethan acting company was organized In such
a way that each member was heavily dependent on his
fellow members, and the economic Ufe of the troupe
depended on selfless and intelligent co-operation. There
was joint ownership of costumes and properties and
scripts, and In the case of Shakespeare's company a
hitherto unheard-of step was eventually taken and there
was joint ownership of a theatre building . . .
Shakespeare had never concerned himself with the
safety of his plays, and it may be that he thought they
were less valuable than the land. But his fellow actors
thought otherwise, and seven years after his death they
reared him their own kind of monument. It was the
complete edition of his plays and ls known as the First
Folio . . .
When Hemlnges and Condell gathered the plays of
Shakespeare together in the First Folio, they did it with
the same kind of love that made them willing to care for
the orphaned children of their fellow actors. "We have
but collected them, and done an office to the dead, to
procure his orphans guardians; without ambition either
of self-profit or fame; only to keep the memory of so
worthy a friend and fellow aUve as was our
Shakespeare ..."
Hemlnges and Condell grew old and died and were
buried near each other in the parish church of St. Mary
Aldermanbury. The Puritans came into power and
closed every playhouse in England. The last of Shakes¬
peare's descendants died and the direct line became
extinct. But Shakespeare's plays went on being read, and
in every generation there was an increasing number of
people who loved him. Hemlnges and Condell had wished
him "such readers" and given him the chance to get
them. Every year their number Increased, and they have
now built a monument to him that extends over the
whole of the world.
This text is made up of excerpts from "Shakespeare of
London" by Marchette Chute, copyright (c) 1949 by
E.P. Dutton & Co., Inc., New York, and is reproduced telth
the kind permission of the publishers. Marchette Chute,
author and biographer, is a specialist on the Elizabethan
period. She is a member of the National Institute of Arts
and Letters, New York, and a Fellow of the Royal Society
of Arts, London. Her inost recent work is a tico act play.
"The Worlds of Shakespeare", written in collaboration
with Ernestine Perrie and published last year by Dutton.
"Shakespeare of London" (U.S. edition $ 4.50) has also
been published by Smithcrs and Concilie, Toronto, Canada
($5) and by Seeker and Warburg, London (15/-). Paper¬
back editions of this work have appeared in the U.S.A.
(Dutton Everyman Paper-back, $1.55) and in Canada
U.M. Dent and Sons, $1.75). Other paper-backs of Mar¬
chette Chute's works are "Geoffrey Chaucer of England"
and "Ben Jonson of Westminster" (U.S., $1.55; Canada,
$1.75).
STAMP SALUTE
FOR THE BARD
For the first time in their history British stamps
recently bore a portrait head other than that of
Great Britain's monarch. The new head was that
of William Shakespeare and the break with tradi¬
tion was made in celebration of the 400th anni¬
versary of the poet's birthday. Selected from the
series of stamps issued on April 23, those below
depict Shakespearean characters Feste the Clown,
Romeo and Juliet and Henry Vflanked by the
heads of Shakespeare and Queen Elizabeth II ;
stamp on right shows graveyard scene from Hamlet.
» 2. S, ç .
23
s^chN*»^
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
24
'My dear Kepler, what would you say
of the learned who steadfastly refuse
to glance through the telescope ?'
GALILEO has related how, in 1609, he received a report from abroad on
the construction of a spyglass and applied himself to the invention of
a similar instrument. "First," he wrote, "I prepared a tube of lead, at
the ends of which I fitted two glass lenses, both plane on one side while on
the other side one was spherically convex and the other concave. Then
placing my eye near the concave lens, I perceived objects three times closer
and nine times larger than when seen with the naked eye. Next I constructed
another one... Finally, sparing neither labour or expense, I succeeded in
constructing for myself so excellent an instrument that objects appeared
nearly 1,000 times larger and over thirty times closer than when regarded
with our natural vision." Galileo eventually built hundreds of telescopes
(left, two of these now in the History of Science Museum in Florence).
His telescope was to bring a new vision to man, though not until intense
resistance had been overcome. "My dear Kepler," wrote Galileo to his
friend, the German astronomer, "what would you say of the learned here,
who, replete with the pertinacity of the asp, have steadfastly refused to
cast a glance through the telescope? Shall we laugh, or shall we cry?"
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
T;he pages of history are filled with coincidences
of persons and events which were we to notice
them would strike us as extremely Interesting and at times
highly significant. Two such coincidences mark the dates
of the birth and death of Galileo.
Galileo GaUlei was born in Pisa on February 15, 1564
and died In the village of Arcetri near Florence on January
8, 1642. Now, 1564 was the year of Michelangelo's death,
1642 the year of Isaac Newton's birth. With the death of
Michelangelo, the ItaUan Renaissance and its era of
artistic splendour comes to an end. With Newton, the
foundations of modern science, as we know and respect it
today and which Galileo's great pioneer work did so much
to create, are at last firmly established.
It is in this sense that it can truly be said of Galileo
that he marks the end not only of a period in history but
of a form of civilization. For thanks to his scientific
attitude and discoveries a wide breach was opened to
challenge the metaphysical and cosmological foundations
of his time.
The artistic and Uterary explosion of the Italian Re¬
naissance had not taken place within the pedantic circles
of the universities; instead it had burst forth and develop¬
ed in the highly refined atmosphere of the courts and
palaces of fifteenth and sixteenth century Italy. During
this time the universities had remained steeped in their
medieval traditions and trappings. Learning, both
phUosophical and theological, was purely speculative in
nature and reposed entirely on the doctrines of Aristotle
which had dominated Western thinking for two thousand
years. The science of the university scholars was reduced
to little more than abstract book-learning and, isolated
and divorced from reality, had lost all contact with the
exciting new techniques which were then being developed
by craftsmen and artisans across the face of Italy and
Europe.
The university scholars had taken over unchanged (and
Indeed were very proud of it) all of Aristotle's views of the
physical and cosmological laws governing the world, to
which had been added the system of astronomy devised
by Ptolemy of Alexandria In the second century of our era.
The Catholic Church had not only given Its support to
these views but had actually adopted them as the official
Church doctrine. The natural philosophy of Aristotle as
well as the astronomy of Ptolemy taught that the Earth
was the centre of things and that the heavens, with the
stars, the Sun, the Moon and the Planets, revolved around
It in twenty-four hours.
According to Aristotle the universe was divided Into two
separate and totally distinct realms the heavens and
earth.
In the heavens (the domain of astronomy) everything
was celestial or godly by nature and hence perfect, eternal
and incorruptible, the stars and their concentric spheres
all moved in perfect circles as did the Sun and the
Planets. Like everything else beyond the Earth these
were perfect, everlasting and immutable.
The Earth (governed by the laws of physics) was
imperfect, unstable, everchanglng and perishable. All __
natural and spontaneous motion could only be In a straight "
CONT'D ON PAGE 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Galileo presents his astronomical telescope to the Doge of Venice on August 24, 1610,
offering it as a gift to the Venetian Republic. The same year, Galileo left his post at Padua
University for Florence where he had been appointed as philosopher and mathematician to
Cosimo II de Medici, grand duke of Tuscany. Painting by Luigi Sabatelli (1772-1850).
Galilean Tribune, Florence
THE MAJESTY OF THE COSMOS
26
cannot without great wonder, nay more, disbelief, hear it being attributed
to natural bodies as a great honour and perfection that they are impassible,
immutable, inalterable, etc. : as, conversely, I hear it esteemed a great imperfection to be
alterable, generable, and mutable.
It is my opinion that the Earth is very noble and admirable by reason of the many and
different alterations, mutations, and generations which incessantly occur in it. And if,
without being subject to any alteration, it had been all one vast heap of sand, or a mass
of jade, or if, since the time of the deluge, the waters freezing which covered it, it had
continued an immense globe of crystal, wherein nothing had ever grown, altered or
changed, I should have esteemed it a wretched lump of no benefit to the Universe, a
mass of idleness, and in a word superfluous, exactly as if it had never been in Nature.
The difference for me would be the same as between a living and a dead creature. I
say the same concerning the Moon, Jupiter, and all the other globes of the Universe.
The more I delve into the consideration of the vanity of popular discourses, the more
empty and simple I find them. What greater folly can be imagined than to call gems,
silver, and gold noble, and earth and dirt base? For do not these persons consider
that, if there were as great a scarcity of earth as there is of jewels and precious metals,
there would be no king who would not gladly give a heap of diamonds and rubies and
many ingots of gold to purchase only so much earth as would suffice to plant a jessamine
in a little pot or to set a tangerine in it, that he might see it sprout, grow up, and bring
forth such goodly leaves, fragrant flowers, and delicate fruit?
GALILEO
Dialogue on the Great World Systems
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
GALILEO (Cont'd)
THE FIRST EXPLORER
OF THE MOON
The first celestial body on which Galileo trained his
telescope in 1609 was the moon. The sketches (below)
made by Galileo to illustrate his discoveries cannot
convey the sense of wonder and delight this new picture
of the moon awoke in him. The lunar landscape that he
saw through the telescope was not the smooth and
spherical surface that many philosophers had believed
it to be. What impressed Galileo was that it looked
like a ghostly "earthly" landscape. He described it thus:
"more and more peaks shoot up as if sprouting, now
here, now there, lighting up within the shadowed portion ;
these become larger, and finally they too are united with
that same luminous surface which extends further. And
on the earth, before the rising of the sun, are not the
highest peaks of the mountains illuminated by the sun's
rays while the plains remain in the shadow?... But on
the moon the variety of elevations and depressions
appears to surpass in every way the roughness of the
terrestial surface..." And Galileo calculated the height
of the mountains with an astonishing precision. Science
still agrees with his estimate that they are four miles high.
:&r
:
P *
«1 v. -.
m\ **>
»
'The best years
of my life7
line: heavy bodies fell downwards, toward the centre of
the earth (the Earth Itself being motionless in the centre
of the universe), while light bodies moved upwards. All
other forms of motion on earth, according to the Arlsto-
teUans, were "violent," that is, produced by some external
force acting upon a body. This movement ceased imme¬
diately the force was removed. Bodies fell at dliferent
speeds while certain elements, such as fire, moved
upwards. That the Sun, the stars, the Moon and Indeed
the whole universe rotated around the Earth appeared
obvious to anyone gazing up at the heavens while the
Earth seemed stable and solid beneath men's feet.
It was on this "commonsense" basis that physics and
astronomy were taught at the University of Pisa when
Galileo entered it as a student in 1581, seven years after
his family had moved back to Florence.
Galileo entered the "Faculty of Artists," as It was then
called, with the intention of taking a degree In medicine,
but he never completed the course, and after four years
left the university for good. But as a student he had
already made his first Important discovery in physics.
Watching a lamp swinging from side to side in the
Cathedral of Pisa he noticed that though the distance of
each swing was reduced sharply as the movement died
down the time taken for every full swing to and fro
remained practically the same. Thus was born the law
of the lsochronism (or equal time) of the pendulum which
was later applied in the invention of the pendulum clock
the first mechanism to make possible the constant and
accurate measurement of very tiny Intervals of time.
he importance of this discovery, however, was
far greater than this first practical appli¬
cation. It gave science an Instrument capable of making
the precise measurements required by astronomy and
experimental mechanics. Galileo himself made use of the
pendulum principle to demonstrate aspects of the law of
inertia.
Towards the end of his studies at Pisa, Galileo was
drawing more and more towards mathematics; he
concentrated In particular on the works of the great
Greek scholar Archimedes and developed a special Interest
in geometry and mechanics.
By 1589 he was so well versed In these subjects that the
University of Pisa appointed him as its Professor of
Mathematics, a post he held for three years. During this
period he carried out his experiments on falling bodies
and, as legend has it, dropped objects of dliferent weight
from the top of the Leaning Tower of Pisa to prove that
they would fall with equal velocity and with uniform
acceleration.
After writing treatises and dialogues "On Motion" (in
Latin, according to the tradition, under the title De Motu)
GaUleo then embarked on more original research in the
field of mechanics and constructed his Bilancetta, a
hydrostatic balance for weighing substances in water.
Galileo's fame as a scientist was now spreading in aca¬
demic circles. He passed on the results of his research
to other scholars, and established close personal contacts
with some of the most distinguished philosophers and
mathematicians of his time.
Galileo's reputation and scientific training as well as
the help of Influential friends now procured for him the
post of Professor of Mathematics at the University of
Paduaan appointment made by the Senate of the Vene¬
tian Republic.
Padua provided the ideal element for Galileo. He
remained there from 1592 to 1610 ,and in a letter to a
friend written many years later when he was old and
blind, he recalled this period as "the best 18 years of my
Ufe."
Padua, a neighbouring city to Venice, had preserved to
the full its ancient and vigorous university tradition. It 27
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
© Paris Observatory
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
GALILEO (Cont'd)
Dust turned to stars,
was the cultural capital of the Venetian Republic, whose
Senate took an Immense pride in the university and
allowed its Faculty and students the greatest freedom of
thought and opinion. The nobility of Venice was also
passionately drawn to the arts and sciences, and its
members were proud of have friends among the pro¬
fessors of Padua.
In the lively atmosphere of this university, with its
exuberant outlook and its opportunities for free, critical,
open-minded discussion, Galileo was quick to form new
contacts and friendships. He became a well-known figure
in Paduan and Venetian circles. Here he formed a close
and lasting friendship with a noblemen, Glanfrancesco
Sagredo, who later became one of the interlocutors of the
famous Galilean Dialogues. Watching the dockyard
workers of Venice at their tasks Galileo found new and
rewarding material for scientific reflexion.
Like most of the university professors of his day, Gali¬
leo had a number of students lodging at his home to whom
he gave private tuition. He also set up a small workshop
under the direction of a mechanic named Marcantonio
Mazzolani, where geometrical, astronomical and naviga¬
tional instruments were made. One of these was the
famous "geometrical and military compass" conceived by
Galileo in the first years of the seventeenth century. It
was a kind of sliderule with which certain operations
In arithmetic and geometry could be done mechanically;
it was also used to solve problems relating to fortified
works.
It was also from this workshop that the famous telescope
that Galileo constructed with his own hands in 1609 is
believed to have come. By introducing the telescope as
a scientific Instrument Galileo revolutionized astronomy
and cosmology and laid the foundations of modern science.
As Galileo himself relates, he set out to make the
telescope fired by his inborn desire for knowledge and his
urge to verify the findings of others in this case because
he had heard that a spectacle-maker in the Low Coun¬
tries had devised an optical instrument "by means of
which visible objects though very distant . . . were
distinctly seen as if nearby."
After many attempts he managed to produce a telescope
which though not very powerful was of sound design, and
then others, one of which he presented to the Venetian
Senate. Then, realizing the vast possibiUtles of the
instrument for astronomical research, he began to use
It himself for scanning the heavens.
The results were at once so encouraging that he was
spurred on to continue his research and extend his
investigations. So great was his enthusiasm that all his
discoveries in the realm of astronomy came in one tre¬
mendous explosion of new-found cosmic knowledge,
within the space of a single year.
It is nowadays difficult for us to imagine how Galileo
felt when, looking through his telescope for the first time,
he beheld the heavens spangled with stars that no man
had ever seen before. What he witnessed was the repudia¬
tion of all the traditional theories, in fact of everything
that philosophers and astronomers had ever taught the
ImmutabiUty of the heavens.
But was it not perhaps the fault of the instrument?
Was it deceiving his eyes? What was he to believe the
wisdom handed down over the centuries or the evidence
of his own eyes? He had, after all, tested his telescope
on nearby objects also visible to the naked eye and these
CONT'D ON PAGE 30
TRUTH BEHIND THE VEIL OF FACTS
28
FOR centuries and centuries
the sidereal facts of this
world were set clear before
the eyes of humans ; yet what
those facts meant, what they pre¬
sented to man, what they made
evident to him was by no means a
reality, but quite the opposite an
enigma, a profound secret, a prob¬
lem before which man trembled
in terror.
Facts then, come to be like the
figures in hieroglyphic writing.
Have you ever noted the para¬
doxical character of such figures?
There they are, holding up their
clean profiles to us so ostenta¬
tiously ; but that very appearance
of clarity is there for the purpose
of presenting us with an enigma,
of producing in us not clarity, but
confusion. The hieroglyphic figure
says to us. "You see me clearly?
Good now what you see of me is
not my true being. I am here to
warn you that I am not my own
essential reality. My reality, my
meaning, lies behind me and is
hidden by me. In order to arrive
at it, you must not fix your atten¬
tion on me, nor take me for reality;
on the contrary, you will have to
interpret me, and this means that
by José Ortega y Gasset
In order to arrive at the true and
inward meaning of this hieroglyph,
you must search for something
very different from the aspect
which its figures offer."
Science is the interpretation of
facts. By themselves, facts do not
give us reality; on the contrary,
they hide it, which is to say that
they present us with the problem
of reality. If there were no facts,
there would be no problem, there
would be no enigma, there would
be nothing hidden which it is ne¬
cessary to de-hide, to dis-cover.
The word which the Greeks used
for truth is "aletheia", which means
discovery, to take away the veil
that covers and hides a thing.
Facts cover up reality ; while we
are in the midst of their innumer¬
able swarmings we are in chaos
and confusion. In order to dis¬
cover reality we must for a mo¬
ment lay aside the facts that surge
about us, and remain alone with
our minds. Then, on our own risk
and account, we imagine a reality,
or to put it another way, we
construct an imaginary reality, a
pure invention of our own; then,
following ¡n solitude the guidance
of our own personal imagining, we
find what aspect, what visible
shapes, in short, what facts would
be produced by that imaginary
reality. It is then that we come out
of our imaginative solitude, out
from our pure and isolated mental
state, and compare those facts
which the imagined reality would
produce with the actual facts which
surround us. If they mate happily
one with another, this means that
we have deciphered the hiero¬
glyph, that we have discovered the
reality which the facts covered
and kept secret.
That labour is what science is.
As you see, it consists of two
different operations: one purely
imaginative and creative, which
man produces out of his own most
free substance; the other a con¬
fronting of that which is not man,
of that which surrounds him,
the facts, the data. Reality is not
a datum, not something given or
bestowed, but a construction
which man makes out of the given
material.
From "Man and Crisis". Copyright ©
1958 by W.W. Norton and Company, Inc.,
New York. Reproduction prohibited.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The spherical cosmos of the Greek astro¬
nomer, Eudoxus:(1) propelling sphere
invisible, immovable; (2) star sphere
(carries other spheres with it) period of
revolution: 1 day; (3) Saturn sphere 29
years; (4) Jupiter sphere 12 years; (5)
Mars sphere 2 years; (6) Sun sphere 1
year (7) Venus; sphere 6 years; (8). Mer¬
cury sphere 3 months; (9) Moon sphere
1 month; (10) Earth sphereimmovable.
From "Pictorial History of Philosophy",
Philosophical Library Inc. New York
OLD VISIONS
THE UNIVERSE
How the ancient Hindus saw the
world. An early conception of the
universe, in which the world was
supported on the backs of four
elephants, standing on a giant
turtle. (See In the Centre of the
Map ", Unesco Courier, March 1956).
Unesco Courier Archives
N their efforts to reform astronomy both
Copernicus and Galileo turned to writers of
the Ancient World to see what theories they had to offer,
and in particular to those of Pythagorean astronomy. In
the 5th cent. B.C., this school had pictured the universe as a
system with circular orbits whose pivot was a "central
fire", around which swung the earth itself an errant body
like the rest. Ptolemy, in the 2nd century A.D., conceived
a complex cosmic system in which, the earth stood immo¬
bile in the centre of the universe, with the stars and the
planets moving around it. Ptolemy's theories held sway for
15 centuries. About 1520, Copernicus returned to the
Pythagorean theory which placed the sun in the centre of
the system. Men scoffed at the theory of Copernicus until
the work of Galileo confirmed his reasoning. Illustrations
on this page illustrate some ancient views of the universe.
From left, Urania, muse of astronomy. Astronomy and Pto¬
lemy in this illustration from a work by Jean de Holiwood,
published in Paris in 1521. Above them is the Ptolemaic
conception of the cosmos with the earth at the centre.
The Globus Mag¬
nus of Tycho Brahe.
In the cosmic sys¬
tem invented by
this Danish as¬
tronomer just be¬
fore Galileo began
his observations of
the heavens, the
planets Mercury,
Venus, Mars, Jupi¬
ter and Saturn
moved in orbits
around the sun
while the sun mov¬
ed in an annual or¬
bit around theearth.
Unesco Courier Archives
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
GALILEO (Cont'd)
Bowed but unconquered
had not been altered In appearance, but merely magni¬
fied.
Perhaps indeed this was a sign that a new era was at
hand and that Copernicus had been right to attack the
Ptolemaic system after all? And if this new instrument
could be used to explore the uncharted expanses of the
heavens It would perhaps prove beyond doubt the validity
of the Copernican theory of astronomy, whose simplicity
had already convinced Galileo of its worth.
Such doubts as these must have assailed Galileo as he
continued his research; each night brought new elements
to add to the already formidable body of irrefutable
evidence against Ptolemaic astronomy and Aristotelian
cosmology.
One of the first discoveries which Galileo made, after
being struck by the amazing number of fixed stars, was
that both the Milky Way and the great Nebulae were
themselves composed of multitudes of stars and not of
particles of dust, vapour or clouds as traditional astronomy
had always maintained.
The first celestial body he studied was the Moon,
according to tradition a smooth, uniform and precisely
spherical body composed of absolutely pure matter. Gali¬
leo saw at once that it was "uneven, rough and full of
cavities and prominences"In other words, traversed by
valleys and mountains. He noted too that it was unevenly
Illuminated.
Thus the Moon, by its shape and its surface, appeared
to closely resemble the Earth. This disturbing resem¬
blance refuted the ancient dogma of Aristotle about the
heavens being both perfect and incorruptible: it also
challenged the worth of the entire traditional cosmolo¬
gical system, and threatened in consequence the accepted
metaphysical one and the theological system founded upon
this.
On the night of January 7, 1610, while Galileo was
observing the planet Venus, he noticed three more cel¬
estial bodies which, unlike the fixed stars, appeared to
move around the planet as if this was the centre of their
system. Continuing his observations on succeeding nights
and noting the regular periodicity of these stars, Galileo
deduced that they were Indeed satellites, and by January
14 he had discovered yet a fourth satellite of Jupiter.
Thus he reasoned, there exists in the Universe another
centre of rotation other than the Earth. Because of the
actual movement of the Moon and the apparent move¬
ment of the Sun, the fixed stars and the entire celestial
sphere, the Earth had hitherto been regarded as the uni¬
que axis of the cosmos. Now, more and more proofs were
found to support the Copernican ideas of cosmology.
Galileo decided to reveal his discoveries to other scien¬
tists. He did so in March 1610 in a sixty-page pamphlet
entitled Siderius Nuncius (The Starry Messenger) which
was published in Venice. The reactions it provoked rang¬
ed from enthusiasm to suspicion, curiosity and distrust.
Above all it gave rise to endless discussion.
To clarify his position Galileo left Florence, where he
had gone to live after leaving the University of Padua and
being appointed philosopher and mathematician to the
Court of the Medicis, and set out for Rome. Here, in the
spring of the year 1611 he was given a triumphal recep¬
tion. The fathers of the Collegio Romano, the supreme
authority in cultural affairs at that time, recognized his
discoveries. The select Accademla del Lincei (the lynx-
eyed), presided by Prince Federico Cesni, elected him a
member (the sixth), an honour he prized so highly that
thereafter he always signed himself "GaUleo Linceo."
PYTHAGORAS
While in Rome and on his return to Florence he pressed
on with his research, calculated the time taken by the
"Medicean Stars" to rotate around Jupiter and journeyed
ever further into the new world revealed to him by his
telescope.
The telescopes he made and others copied from them
were by now to be found in all parts of Europe. Scientists
and laymen fired with curiosity scanned the skies with
the aid of these new instruments and in no time at all
more had been added to the knowledge of astronomy
than in all the thousands of years gone by.
On July 25, 1611, Galileo observed that Saturn was
"triple-formed." His telescope was not powerful enough
to show him the rings around this planet. He saw it as
an oblong-shaped rather than a spherical body, and even
as having three parts a larger central body flanked by
two smaller ones. It was not until 1655 that Huygens, the
Dutch mathematician and physicist, using a much more
powerful instrument, perceived the ring around Saturn.
In the meantime, Galileo had also observed the spots,
on the sun. This was a revelation of major importance
for the supporters of the Copernican system for it dem¬
onstrated that the Sun itselfthis "noble" and "per¬
fect" body was also subject to changes not acceptable to
Aristotelian theory. Galileo was able to show that from
observations of these spots one could prove the rotation
of the sun, and even compute the speed with which it
rotates upon Its axis.
Already as early as December 1610, Galileo had observed
the phases of Venus which was another striking proof that
the centre of the orbit of that planet was not the Earth
but the Sun.
30
If he had been solely a mathematician and an experimenter our tribute today would be reserved
for his scientific genius. But he was also a philosopher who felt in duty bound to share his
discoveries and his ideas with the whole world. Though fully aware of the antagonisms that
this attitude would arouse, and of the difficulties and even dangers he might face, he persis¬
ted until the final trial; his seeming defeat, in fact, heralded the triumph of the new concepts.
RENÉ MAHEU
Director General of Unesco
In a message to the city of Pisa on the occasion of the 4th Centenary of Galileo's birth
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
THE BOOK
THAT SHOOK
A WORLD
More than 2,000 years ago Pythago¬
ras, the Greek (bust far left) and his
followers accepted the idea that earth
rotates on its axis and travels around
the sun which is placed at the centre
of the universe. But the ideas of Aris¬
totle, the Greek philosopher (4th
century B.C.) on the earth's immo¬
bility at the centre of the universe
continued to dominate the Western
world. Ptolemy's astronomy of the
2nd century AD, was also based on
this idea. In 1543, Nicolaus Coper¬
nicus, a Polish astronomer (right)
published his " De Revolutionibus ",
which claimed the earth revolved
around the sun. In 1 632, Galileo, wrote
his Copernican manifesto, the Dia¬
logue on the Great World Systems.
The frontispiece of the original edition
(left) shows Copernicus debating the
systems with Aristotle, whose follow¬
ers continued to oppose the new
Copernican view of the universe.
K ' J > %':U
05
4<ry . ÈÎLiÊfïMà
EsWsS'1 «LISI
COPERNICUS
In the books and letters by which he announced his
discoveries to the world of learning, Galileo consistently
affirmed his belief in the theories of Copernicus, which
had now been confirmed by so many convincing proofs.
But it was above all in one single work that he described
all the results of his years of research in astronomy and
mechanics. This was the Dialogo sopra i due massimi
Sistemi del Mondo (Dialogue on the Great World Systems)
whose pubUcation in 1632 was the signal for an onslaught
on Galileo by all the forces of reaction: all those who
refused either to understand or to concede the facts that
had been proved by experiment and reasoning.
Galileo had already received a sharp warning in 1616
and had been told not to uphold or teach the Copernican
doctrine which the Church had condemned as erroneous;
and he had, officially at least, bowed to this injunction.
When Maffeo Barberinl, who had often shown marked
favour to GaUleo, was elected Pope with the title of Urban
VIII, the scientist believed that he could now freely and
openly express his scientific views. Thus, after visiting
Rome in 1624 to pay homage to the new Pope, Galileo set
about completing his Dialogue, which, in reaUty, he had
been pondering on since his days in Padua.
For publishing this work Galileo was summoned before
the Tribunal of the Inquisition. He was charged with
violating the injunction of 1616 in that his new book,
while paying Up service to official views, was in fact
defending the Copernican doctrines.
The trial lasted from February 1633 Into the summer of
that year. Galileo was condemned to imprisonment and
ordered to recant. Subsequently the prison sentence was
commuted to confinement in the residence of the Grand
Duke of Tuscany in Rome; and he was later authorized
to move first to Siena, and finally to Florence.
Despite the condemnation, which was to have far-
reaching repercussions on scientific life In Italy, Galileo
did not capitulate. He worked on until he had completed
his greatest and most mature work, Discourses and
Demonstrations on Two New Sciences, which was pub¬
lished at Leyden in 1638.
The Dialogue on the Great World Systems and the
Discourses are Galileo's major works and together form
the basis of modern dynamics.
In the Dialogue, GaUleo embarked on his great defence
of the Copernican doctrine; in the Discourses he developed
the theme of his earlier work in far greater depth and
detail, confirming his conclusions by practical demonstra
tions. In this work Galileo set out the results of half a
century of scientific research, systematically expanding
and summarizing his discoveries and conclusions.
The measure of Galileo's greatness was that he saw
through the superficial and deceptive appearance of quite
ordinary, everyday things and grasped the reality behind
them that other men had never been able to perceive.
The key to Galileo's achievement was the completely new
method of scientific research that he himself had devised.
GaUleo made use of a powerful battery of arguments
in his assault on the theories of traditional science. He
advanced the universal principle of relativity, formulated
the law governing the free fall of bodies, defined the prin¬
ciple of inertia and studied the composition of motions.
And, perhaps most Important of all, he considered the
problem of the "truth" and the "validity" of I he science
of the universe from a viewpoint that still "modern."
Galileo used a revolutionary approach. His weapon was
the principle of relativity and with it he swept aside all
arguments advanced against the Idea that the earth
rotates. From the most commonplace experiments and
observations came principles that none of Galileo's pre¬
decessors had been able to grasp or expound.
The Galilean principle of relativity maintains that it ls
impossible to tell, from mechanical experiments carried
out within a given system, whether that system is in a
state of rest or in uniform linear motion. In this way
Galileo refuted arguments against the earth's rotation
based on facts observed on the earth Itself, that ls, from
within the same system.
To support his hypothesis Galileo used the example of a
ship. He pointed out that it is Impossible for anyone
Inside a vessel to tell whether it is in motion simply by
observing animals or objects In movement within, since
there are no observable relative changes between these
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
It is not true that after reciting (his) abjuration, he
muttered: "Eppur si muove. " It was the world
that said this not Galileo.
BERTRAND RUSSELL
The Scientific Outlook (1931) 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
'In questions of
science the authority
of a thousand is not
worth the humble
reasoning of a single
individual.'
Galileo Galilei
Galilean Tribune. Florence
GALILEO (Cont'd)
animals or objects due to any movement by the ship.
Moreover, he affirmed, there ls no absolute motion, either
celestial or terrestial, rotatory or Unear, upwards or
downwards; there is only motion in relation to a point
that is assumed to be fixed.
To determine whether celestial bodies are stationary or
in motion, astronomers still take as their point of refe¬
rence three axes traced within the solar system (and called
the Galilean axes In honour of the great scientist) by
which motion can to some extent be measured, though
subject always to relativity.
Some of the commonest arguments to support the view
that the earth is motionless had been based on observa¬
tion of moving bodies, and more particularly of projec¬
tiles, on Its surface. And these movements of course
showed none of the effects which it was wrongly believed
should be produced by the earth's rotation.
But although the principle of relativity had now
provided a satisfactory explanation on this point, there
still remained the problem of the "spontaneous" move¬
ment of bodies and the "violent" motion of projectiles.
By experiments, Galileo demonstrated the error of
Aristotle's theory that the velocity of a freely-falUng body
is directly proportional to its weight, and showed that all
bodies in free fall towards the earth have the same velo¬
city. These experiments led Galileo to his studies on
Inclined planes.
Objects dropped from towers or buildings could only be
observed in movement for a matter of seconds and thus
little Information of value was obtained from such experi¬
ments. With the Inclined plane, however, it was possible
to prolong the time of fall and to control and measure
the velocities produced.
By experiments of this kind and others carried out with
a pendulum. Galileo demonstrated that all velocities
reached in descending from the same height, but along
planes of different Inclination, are nevertheless always
equal. He was thus able to formulate a new basic princi¬
ple of dynamics: the principle of inertia. This states
that the velocity of a weight moving along an inclined
plane accelerates In proportion to the angle of slope of
the plane, and accumulates enough energy (allowance
32 being made for the effects of friction and air resistance)
to return, like the pendulum, to the same height from
which it started.
Galileo became blind a few years before his death in 1642,
but continued to work energetically. He maintained his scien¬
tific correspondence and, as shown in this painting by
Luigi Sabatelli, dictated his ideas to his disciples, Vincent Vivi-
ani, the mathematician, and Evangelista Torricelli, the physicist.
The formulation of the principle of inertia becomes
complete when it is shown that, unless outside forces
intervene, a body remains at rest (which even the Aristo¬
telian school admitted) or in uniform motion. This was
a postulate which ran counter. to all the ancient theories
on the contrast between natural and "violent" motions,
and it affirmed that these motions, which had hitherto
been regarded as entirely different in nature, could
actually be combined.
Applying the principle of inertia, the law of free-falling
bodies and the principle of the composition of motions,
Galileo was able to split up projectile motion into its
component parts: the motion of inertia operating in the
direction and at the velocity of the initial impulse, and
a downward motion due to gravity. The result is a para¬
bola. Galileo was now able to draw up the first firing
tables, which are reproduced in his Discourses.
This, in my view, was one of the greatest moments of
Galileo's scientific career. He was now possessed of
the facts that were required in order that the work begun
by him might be completed by the English scientist, Sir
Isaac Newton, nearly half a century later. Newton was
able to complete his elaboration of the scheme of the
Universe by applying to the motion of heavenly bodies
Galileo's analysis of the dual forces (inertia and gravity)
which govern the trajectory of projectiles. Thus were
laid the foundations of modern scientific development.
GaUleo had faced the humiliation of his condemnation
with firm courage, convinced beyond all doubt that his
was the path of truth. This was his "Credo," and he
never ceased to proclaim it to the world.
"We have found a strange footprint on the shores of
the unknown. We have devised profound theories, one
after another, to account for its origin. At last, we have
succeeded in reconstructing the creature that made the
footprint. And loi It is our own."
ARTHUR S. EDDINGTON
The Language of Science (1954)
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
STORY OF BRAILLE
Sir,
I would like you to publish an
issue on the life and work of Louis
Braille, as I work for the blind people
and do braille for them in Brisbane,
Australia.
Colin R. Brown
Coolangatta, Queensland, Australia
Ed. note: Our magazine lias published
material on this subject in past issues:
June 1960, March 1958, and March
1952. Interested readers are advised if
possible to consult these copies in a
library since they are now out of print.
THE WORLD OF ANIMALS
Sir,
Why not devote an issue to animal
life in general? It would be a great
success with young people in school
who, I gather, form an important
section of your readership. Your
issue on African flora and fauna
(Sept. 1961) was a promising foretaste
of what the issue I propose could
offer.
Francisco Olmos Garrido
Valencia, Spain
LASERS AND MASERS
Sir,
In your Feb. 1964 issue you pub¬
lished an article on The Fantastic La¬
ser. I wonder how many of your readers
knew the word "laser" or, for that
matter, the word "maser" associated
with it. I found "laser" described
in the dictionary as "a gum resin."
I should like to know the meaning of
these words and the difference bet¬
ween them.
Dr. E. Livneh
Jerusalem, Israel
Ed. note: A maser (Microwave Am¬
plication by Stimulated Emission of
Radiation) emits high frequency radio
waves. A laser (Light Amplification
by Stimulated Emission of Radiation)
also known as an "optical maser,"
emits light waves.
Two outstanding Armenians have
been ignored by Unesco in recent
years. First, the 1600th anniversary
of the birth of Mesrop Mashtots, the
creator of the Armenian alphabet on
a scientific basis. This was a truly
unique achievement...
Secondly, the 250th anniversary of
the birth of the Armenian Minstrel,
Sayat'Nova, who composed in the three
principal languages of the Caucasus,
Armenian, Georgian and Azerbaidja-
nian, the latter being understood at
that time by Turks and Persians also.
He was court minstrel to the king of
Georgia and his poems imply
friendship between nations.
Both these personalities are impor¬
tant illustrations of the principles of
Unesco Mesrop Mashtots in the field
of education and Sayat Nova in inter¬
national co-operation yet they have
been deserted in favour of a politician.
Yedvard Gulbekian
Mitcham, Surrey, England
SCIENCE FOR PROGRESS
Sir,
The issue on Science for Progress,
(July-Aug. 1963) was most impressive,
not only for its lessons, but also be¬
cause of the prospects for the future
it reveals. It was difficult to choose
between the marvelous article by
Semenov (Into the World of the Fu¬
ture) and the realistic reflexions of
Daniel Bovet (Homo Sapiens, that
Strange Paradox), to take only two
examples. But everything in it ins¬
tructs us and shows us new and unex¬
pected possibilities.
The article by René Maheu is a
lesson to those politicians and edu¬
cators who wish to cling to the
ancient methods. The provocative
subject matter of this article is
something that specially interests me.
Medicine poses a host of pedagogical
problems, and the mutual understand¬
ing of peoples and their eventual
reunion are unthinkable unless barriers
raised by universities of to-day against
recognition of foreign professionals'
degrees are removed.
Dr. M. Bustamanfe
Bilbao, Spain
and established beforehand, so that
artists can give full scope to their
creative talent.
Ramon Parada
Buenos Aires, Argentine
A GAP TO BE FILLED
Sir,
As an adult, 1 much enjoy Tut:
Unesco Courier, and I find many
children enjoy occasional articles and
the photographs. However, I feci
there is a void to be filled analagous
to that which the National Geographic
Society fills with its school bulletins,
written in less technical language,
briefer, and sent only during the
school year. I really hope something
will be made available to youngsters
which does for them what your
magazine docs for adults, with perhaps
some encouragement to children
around the world, perhaps 16 or
under, to communicate their thoughts
to each other. It seems to me a
format which would be less expensive
and more fruitful for this group could
be developed, which would reach them
in formative stages, and which would
lead to more adult interest in The
Unesco Courier.
Dorothea M. Dryer
Washlnßfon D. C, U.S.A.
SOMETHING TO LAUGH AT...
Sir,
I wish you could find a place in
your magazine for some cartoons or
other humorous illustrations from time
to time. I am sure they would be
appreciated by many readers. I should
like you to know how much I appre¬
ciated your special issue on Jean-
Jacques Rousseau (March 1963).
Thanks to your presentation the subject
became lively and vivid and took on
a virtually new and modern aspect.
Laurence Maire
Neuilly-sur-Scine, France
USE MORE MAPS
OUTSTANDING ARMENIANS
Sir,
I am wondering on what basis it
is decided at Unesco to celebrate in¬
ternationally the anniversaries of
outstanding personalities? I would have
thought that the important principles
would have been that the person must
have contributed to the furtherance of
world culture or to international co¬
operation.
On these grounds, I do not see what
justification there can be for the in¬
ternational celebration of the 25th
anniversary of the death of Kemal
Atatürk, Unesco Courier, Dec. 1963)
a controversial political figure...
SYMBOL AT SKOPLJE
Sir,
I wish to supplement the pro¬
posal of a Bulgarian reader (Oct. 1963)
that all U.N. member states should
share in the reconstruction of the
Yugoslav city of Skoplje. At the
crossing of the main avenues in the
centre of the new city a great monu¬
ment should be erected to symbolize
human solidarity and hope for the
final triumph of goodwill among men.
There should be a worldwide contest
with prizes contributed internationally
and awarded by an international jury.
The cost of building the monument
should also be paid for internationally
Sir,
I would like to suggest that articles
in your magazine which refer to par¬
ticular countries, or places in countries,
be accompanied by a small map of the
area, about 3 or 4 centimetres square.
With the establishment of new
independent governments throughout
the world, place names and boundaries
are often changed, and many of your
readers who value The Unesco
Courier will no doubt wish to re¬
read their copies in years to come and
these small maps would make easy
reference.
P. Förster
Black Rock, Victoria
Australia
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
SWEDEN'S OLDEST CITY: Excavations
by archxologists on the oldest urban
site so far discovered in Sweden Helgö, on
an island in Lake Malar, west of
Stockholm which dates back to 200 A.D.
arc now complete. Until the discoveries
made at Helgö, which include ceramics,
glassware and gold found in terrace, stilt
and pit homes, it was believed that
Sweden's oldest city was at Birka, on an
island further to the west.
ARAB STATES BACK LITERACY
CAMPAIGN: Delegates from Unesco
National Commissions in 12 Arab states
meeting in Algiers have agreed to support
a regional literacy campaign. The project
was adopted following a suggestion by
M. Rene Maheu, Director General of
Unesco, who pointed out that each country
might finance three-quarters of the cost
of teaching its illiterates, the remaining cost
being found from a fund created from
contributions based on a percentage of some
natural resources in Arab countries, parti¬
cularly income from oil.
niTY THE TORTOISE; While making a
*- census of the giant tortoises of the
Galapagos Islands, Dr. David Snow, the
Oxford zoologist who is director of the
station set up by the Charles Darwin
Research Foundation (established by agree¬
ment with Ecuador and under the auspices
of Unesco) reports that only one tortoise
was found on Hood Island. It was feeding
on a fallen prickly pear in company, and
in competition, with 15 goats. (For reports
on Galapagos research see The Unesco Cou¬
rier, Sept. 1961, Jan. 1958).
TTIIE U.N. AT WORK: The work of the
-*- U.N., including its role as a school for
the world, and the purpose and meaning
of its charter are discussed and described
in "The United Nations: Who Needs It?,"
No. 7 in the Unesco-U.N. Study Guide
Series published by Oceana Publications,
Inc., Dobbs Ferry, New York. This booklet
costs 50 cents and can be obtained through
Unesco Sales Agents (see page 35), from
the Unesco Publications Center, New York
and from the publishers.
ÏTNESCO MATHS TEST: Over 50,000
*-" Japanese junior and senior high school
students will participate in the first interna¬
tional mathematical achievement test which
will be held this year in at least 13 nations.
This new international examination has
been prepared by mathematicians from
different countries under the sponsorship
of the Unesco International Educational
Research Institute at Hamburg, Federal Re¬
public of Germany.
D1lEADLY DRINKING WATER: Disea¬
ses like typhoid, dysentery and cholera
in whose transmission drinking water plays
34 a part still attack some 500 million people
in the less developed countries. On a
world wide basis, diseases of this kind
account for about five million infant deaths
each year. Reporting these facts, WHO
adds that as many as 90% of the people
in certain areas have inadequate piped water
or use unsafe water.
I^LECTRIC FISH BARRIERS: A power
^ station at Buggenum on the River Maas
in the Netherlands has installed an electric
barrier to ward off fish. This electric
"fence" in the water is created by a series
of electrode plates. It protects the fish by
scaring them away from the power station's
water intake filters, and thus prevents these
from becoming blocked with dead fish.
O MILLIONS SEE STAMPS: More than
** three million people went to see U.N.
Postal Administration exhibits on display in
100 centres throughout the world during
1963. An even larger schedule of stamp
exhibits is planned for this year and the first
of these, a Human Rights stamp display, was
opened in Rabat, Morocco on January 30.
SCIENCE IN AFRICAN SCHOOLS: A
recent Unesco publication offers a
detailed analysis of the present position and
the future needs of science education in
Africa south of the Sahara. It also pro¬
poses replacement solutions to meet present-
day shortages in equipment. The sugges¬
tions made are of use to countries anywhere
in the world trying to build up or moder¬
nize secondary school science teaching.
Science Teaching in the Secondary Schools
of Tropical Africa, Unesco, Paris. (Price:
11/ (stg.); $2.25: 7.75 F.)
np OOTHSOME TRANSMITTER: A
radio transmitter small enough to fit
inside the molar of a false denture has
been perfected by Australian scientists at
the Melbourne Dental Hospital. Measuring
6x9 mm, and powered by a transistor
battery, it will be used to trace malforma¬
tions in the jawbone.
JP LOATING UNTVERSITY: A convert-
* ed ship named "University of the Seven
Seas" is now making a round-the-world
cruise before returning to its home port,
San Diego, California. Student-passengers
are taking courses in history, oceanography,
anthropology, business administration and
other subjects.
s» OXED' COUNTRIES: Mobile "book
" boxes" with films, colour slides, rec¬
ords, maps and pictures illustrating life in
India and Iran are touring schools in
Switzerland. The scheme has been intro¬
duced by the Swiss National Commission
for Unesco under the "Associated Schools"
project in education for international under¬
standing directed by Unesco. Nearly 300
schools in over 40 countries are associated
with this project.
17 AT MORE FISH: Though Mexico has
6,000 miles of coastline, its fishing
industry is underdeveloped and Mexicans
seldom eat fish. Today Mexico is moving
to put more fish on its dinner tables, reports
the FAO. It will do so by modernizing and
expanding its fishing fleet and studying the
fish resources around its coasts.
FT TV IN THE CLASSROOM: The
*J.l^. World Confederation of
Organizations of the Teaching Profession is
making an international inquiry into
teaching about the United Nations. This
will cover the place given to the subject in
school curricula and how teachers are
trained to present it. Reports from mem¬
ber associations in 84 countries will be
discussed at the Confederation's Assembly
to be held in Paris in August.
CjTOP SIGNALS FOR GAME: Every
^ year 1,200 elk and other game are
killed on Swedish roads despite the nu¬
merous game warning signs. The Swedish
National Road Board is now setting up
5,000 stainless steel mirrors which, by re¬
flecting the headlights of oncoming cars,
will act as a kind of stop signal for game,
mainly elk and deer. The same system
has already been tried in the Netherlands
with good results.
VICTORY OVER YAWS: Yaws, a
crippling skin disease which once
affected more than half the children in
some parts of Indonesia has been brought
under control in most of Java by a gov¬
ernment campaign based on a district-by-
district examination of the entire population.
The United Nations Children's Fund has
allocated more than $3 million to yaws
control in Indonesia. It has provided
vehicles, penicillin (one shot is usually suffi¬
cient to cure yaws) and field and laboratory
equipment.
F/ashes.
| Last year nearly 200 million people
were vaccinated during India's nation-wide
smallpox eradication programme reports
WHO. It is planned to cover the whole of
India's population by March 1966.
9 By drilling down three and a half miles
into the Earth near Stavropol, scientists
have now reached the planned depth of
the deepest borehole in the Soviet Union.
The drilling is a test run for future holes
to be drilled right through the Earth's crust
into the underlying mantle.
H Japan produces more than four metric
tons of rice per hectare compared with a
production of less than two tons in most
other Asian countries and, in some cases,
less than one ton, reports FAO.
% Cholera is still a major disease. Last
year there were 57,000 cases and 18,400
deaths, as compared with 39,396 cases and
just over 11,600 deaths in 1962, reports
WHO. The most important increases were
recorded in India and East Pakistan.
| Eight new projects in education and
technological training totalling nearly $12 i
million have been approved by the Gover¬
ning Council of the U.N. Special Fund,
with Unesco as their executing agency.
Unesco will furnish fellowships, experts and
equipment for the projects.
u
2
<
<
i3
Z
<
U
et
O
LU
O
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
STUDY
ABROAD
New
1964-1966
Edition
xv 1964-66 study abroadB
^*mjk\ Bétudes
l'étranger 1
Y kW M estudios ^Ê
^ÊwfmttW^Ê en
^^^^§ extranjero
rVirrJ
unesco
Just published
VACATIONS ABROAD
Vol XVI - 1964
This latest edition gives information from 1,050 institutions
and organizations in 68 countries on vacation courses,
summer schools and seminars, study tours, student and
youth hostels, summer camps and centres, international
voluntary work camps and other international educational
exchange schemes offering an opportunity for study and
travel, abroad, including details of financial aid available
176 pages. Price : S2.00 10/- (stg.) 7 F.
The fifteenth edition of "Study Abroad" brings you
the latest information on 130,000 fellowships offered
in 1964 and 1965 by governments, universities, foun¬
dations and other institutions in over 100 countries and
territories.
Fellowships and scholarships are available for work in virtually
all fields of learning and research, and can be held in almost
all parts of the world. The duration of studies varies from
several weeks to six or seven years.
An invaluable manual for anyone contemplating study in a
foreign country. An indispensable reference book for all
libraries, universities and information centres. A useful instru¬
ment in promoting educational contacts throughout the world.
N. B. "Study Abroad " will be published only once every two
years. The next edition will appear at the end of 1965.
$4.00 20/- 14 F.
ere to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Prest Department, Royal
Afghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Tradco Agencies, 109 Swanston Street, G. P. O.
Box 2324 V, Melbourne C. I. (Victoria); United
Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
8th Floor, McEwan House, 343 Little Collins St.,
Melbourne C. I. (Victoria). (A. 15/-). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C'., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Seh. 60.-). BELGIUM. Editions "Labor",
342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-Boek-
handel, Belgiëlei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (100 FB) and art slides only: Louis De Lannoy,
22, place de Brouckère, Brussels. CCP 3380.00.
BURMA. Burma Translation Society, 3 61 Prome Road,
Rangoon. (K. 5.50). CANADA. Queen's Printer,
Ottawa, Ont. ($ 3.00). CEYLON. Lake House
Bookshop, 100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Colombo,
2. (Rs. 9). CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99 Chung¬
king South Rd., Section 1, Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa).
CYPRUS. Cyprus National Youth Council. P. O. Box 539,
Nicosia. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia Ltd., 30 Ve
Smeckach, Prague 2. DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard,
Prags Boulevard 47 Copenhagen S (D.kr. 12).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agency. P.O. Box 120.
Addis Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (Fmk. 540). FRANCE.
Librairie de I'Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7". C.C.P.
12598-48. (7 F.). GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg Verlag,
Rosenheimerstrasse 145, Munich. 8, For the Unesco
Kurier (German ed only) Bahrenfelder-Chaussee 1 60,
Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, C.C.P. 276650(DM 8). GHANA
Methodist Book Depot Ltd. Atlantis House. Commercial
St., POB 100, Cape Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See
United Kingdom. GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann,
28, rue du Stade, Athens. HONG-KONG. Swindon
Book Co., 64, Nathan Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY.
Kultura. P. O. Box 149. Budapest, 62. ICELAND.
Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co. H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd. Nicol Road, Bellard
Estate, Bombay 1 ; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 1 3;
Gunfoundry Road, Hyberabad, 1; 36a, Mount Road,
Madras 2; Kanson House, 1/24 Asaf AM Road, P.O.
Box 386, New Delhi, 1; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book &
Stationery Co., 17 Park Street, Calcutta 16, Scindia
House, New Delhi, Indian National Commission Co-ope¬
ration with Unesco, Ministry of Education, for New
Delhi 3. (Rs. 7). INDONESIA. P. N. Fadjar Bhakti
Djalan, Nusantara 22, Djakarta. IRAQ. Mackenzie's
Bookshop, Baghdad. IRELAND. The National Press,
2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/3).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores 35, Allenby Road
and 48, Nahlat Benjamin Street. Tel-Aviv (1 £ 5.50).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour
Street, Kingston. (10/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd.,
6 Tori-Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605 Tokyo
Central, Tokyo. (Yen 670). JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous
& Co., Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road. P.O.B. 66. Amman.
KENYA. E.S.A. Bookshop. P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole and
Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LUXEMBURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22. Grand-Rue,
Luxemburg. MALAYSIA. Federal Publications Ltd.,
Times House, River Valley Rd., Singapore (M. $ 500).
MALTA. Sapienza's Library 26 Kingsway, Valletta. (1 0/-).
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon
Street. Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid
des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (7 NF.). NETHERLANDS.
N. V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague,
(fl. 6). NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES. G. C. T.
Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.) N.V., Willemstad, Curaçao.
N.A. NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Office
20. Molesworth Street (Private Bag) Wellingston, C. 1
Government Bookshops: Auckland (P.O. Box 5344),
Christchurch (P.O. Box 1721), Dunedin (P.O. Box 1104)
(10/-). NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshops, P.O. Box 174,
Lagos (1 0/-). NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornct, Lille Grense
7 Oslo For the Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narvesens
Litteratur Tjeneste, Stortingsgt. 2 Oslo, Postboks 115
(kr 1 3.20). PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing Co.
Ltd., Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box 374 S6-N
Gulberg Industrial Colony, Lahore. PHILIPINES.
The Modern Book Co., 508 Rizal Avenue Manila.
POLAND. "RUCH" ul. Wiloza Nr. 46x Warsaw 10
(Zl. 50). PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Lda. Livraria
Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. PUERTO RICO.
Spanish English Publications, Eleanor Roosevelt 115,
Apartado 1912. Hato Rey. RHODESIA * NYA¬
SALAND. The Book Centre. Gordon Avenue. Salisbury,
Southern Rhodesia. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop,
P. O. Box 1118. Khartoum. SWEDEN. A/B CE.
Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2. Stockholm 1 6.
For the Unesco Courier: Svcnska Unescorldet, Vasa-
gatan 15-17, Stockholm, C (Kr. 10): SWITZERLAND.
Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse Zurich. Payot, 40. rue du
Marché, Geneva C.C.P. 1-236. "Courier" only: Georges
Losmaz, 1, rue des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. C.C.P.
1-4811. (Fr. S. 8). TANGANYIKA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop. P.O.B. 9030. Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND.
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue. Bangkok.
(35 ticals). Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Book¬
shop. P.O. Box 145, Kampala. UNION OF SOUTH
AFRICA. Van Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Street, P.O. Box 724 Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier
(single copies) only: Central News Agency, P.O. Box 103 3,
Johannesburg. (10/-). UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC
(EGYPT). Librarie Kasr El Nil, 38, rue Kasr El Nil,
Cairo. Sub/agent: La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-
Pasha, Cairo. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office. P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I, and Government
Bookshops in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Man¬
chester, Birmingham and Bristol. (10/-). UNITED
STATES. Unesco Publications Center, 317 East 34th St,
New York, N.Y. 1 001 6 ($ 5.00) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broadway, New York,
27, N.Y. U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, Moscow.
G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Yugoslovenska Knjiga,
Terazije 27, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
7.*
-*., - >fc.
«K
BS
7
i&
'"f^
».
© Susann*. London
SHAKESPEARE. YEAR FOUR HUNDRED. The
spectacle of an Elizabethan courtier paying hom¬
age to his queen is one that Shakespeare could
have seen as he passed through Windsor on his
way to fame and fortune in London. As it waits
for the artist to mould its features, this personage
'-
flíSS^Wí*5*
seems to symbolize the mystery that still obscures
aspects of Shakespeare's life. The figure was des¬
igned and made by Nicholas Georgiadis for the
Shakespeare Exhibition, commemorating the 400th
anniversary of the Bard's birth, which opened
in Stratford, England, on April 23 (see page 18).
]]>
</page>
</document>
