<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="062313eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
m
WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
%1\ 1 1W
OCTOBER 1964 (17TH YEAR) - PRICE 1/6-STG. (U.K.) - 30 CENTS (CANADA) - 1 F (FRANCE)
CHALLENGE OF OUR CENTURY
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
i,
r r m
Folk Art
\J
Wf ,
1 '
BS
Ji j
i! f
f
A
I
IK
/ !
/
i
x i
ii »
f
Photos S R- Michaud, Paris
Jll
Ethiopia
Paintings by Ethio¬
pia's folk artists offer
a fascinating panor¬
ama of life in village
and countryside. An
everyday scene, like
women laden with
earthenware water
jars (right) has been
captured by one of
these artists in the
painting above. Ethi¬
opia's art has always
been an art of the
people (see page 18).
tV
¡V
f; y ,
*$tv',\ \ R II ii 1
\7* V
w>
i . sb ' » 1? V , »>
. wife:w
,iy,y 'W'- -v'
: >?ß
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier
OCTOBER 1964
1 7 T H YEAR
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
COVER PHOTO
Illiteracy affects some 700 mil¬
lion adults in the world. If it
is ever to be eradicated a two¬
fold effort is required : adequate
primary education for all child¬
ren; and well-planned literacy
programmes for adults. Unesco
has been concerned with both
problems for years and has
just drawn up a 5-year expe¬
rimental programme for mass
literacy (see p. 4). Cover photo
shows a fisherman and his son
learning to read and write.
Paolo Gasparini
Page
4 THE STRUGGLE AGAINST ILLITERACY
The most exalting venture of our generation
By René Maheu
9 INVESTMENT IN PEOPLE
A new approach to economic development
By H.M. Phillips
12 THE HIGHEST SCHOOL IN THE WORLD
Sir Edmund Hillary's latest conquest in the Himalayas
By R.J. Spector
18 ART OF ETHIOPIA
A folk tradition centuries old
By Otto A. Jäger
24 A SAFARI ARMED WITH MICROSCOPES
Hunting Africa's tiniest animals
By Janos Balogh
32 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
33 GREAT MEN, GREAT EVENTS
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
THE UNITED NATIONS EDUCATIONAL SCIENTIFIC AND CULTURAL ORGANIZATION
Published monthly by UNESCO
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7", France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
René Caloz
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey
Russian Edition : Victor Goliachkov
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Abdel Moneim El Sawl (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shln-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Italian Edition : Maria Remlddi (Rome)
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemln
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except In July and Aufust when
it is bi-monthly (I 1 issues a year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German,
Arabic, Japanese, and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed by H.H.
Stationery Office, P. O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted Irom THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors ol THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier Is Indexed monthly In The Readers' Cuide to
Periodical Literature published by H. W. Wilson Co.. New York.
Annual subscription rates : 15/-stg. ; $3.00 (Canada) ;
10 French Francs or equivalent. Single copies 1/6-stg ;
30 cents ; 1 F.
(M.C. 64.1., 195 A)
N« 10, 1964
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
AÍ/ correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
The struggle
against illiteracy
THE MOS
© Dan Sorin
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
T EXALTING VENTURE
OF OUR GENERATION
by René Maheu
Director-General of Unesco
T
here are more than 700 million men and
women in the world over 15 years of age
who cannot read or write. This figure, which
emerged from a study that Unesco carried out
in 1962 at the request of the United Nations
General Assembly, represents two-fifths of the
adult population of the globe.
In certain countries of Africa, Asia and Latin
America, the number of illiterates stands as high
as seventy, eighty or even ninety per cent
of the total population and in many countries
the female population is almost entirely illiterate.
Despite the spectacular expansion of education
for children, a by no means insignificant number
of youngsters attending primary school leave
before they have had an adequate schooling
and sooner or later end up as illiterates.
As a result, the number of illiterates is rising by
20 to 25 million persons each year according
to certain estimates.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
Gh. Serban
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
ILLITERACY (Cont'd)
The new strategy: a five-year selective
These figures speak for themselves and need little comment. They mean that
in our era of unprecedented advances in science and technology, millions of men and
women are condemned to live on the fringe of modern civilization. They mean that
a large portion of the intellectual potential of mankind is being lost forever. Such
a state of affairs is not only a disgrace and a scandal on the grounds of human con¬
science and justice but in terms of economics is the height of absurdity and a sheer
waste of manpower. Little wonder then that the map of the world's illiteracy is prac¬
tically identical with that of underdevelopment. Economists and specialists in ques¬
tions of planning have clearly shown the importance of human resources in imple¬
menting development programmes and have equally demonstrated that adult literacy
is an essential factor governing returns from other forms of investment. It is not
surprising, therefore, as I had occasion to point out recently in Geneva at the 1964
summer session of the U.N. Economic and Social Council, that the underdeveloped
countries consider illiteracy a top priority in their plans for development.
Countries where illiteracy is widespread have been making determined indeed
sometimes heroic efforts to combat this affliction, and in many instances the
results have been remarkable. But we must also face the fact that a number of
national literacy campaigns have had discouraging results even though they were
launched with much enthusiasm and were financed with more than adequate funds,
simply because in the initial planning stages certain conditions indispensable for
success were underestimated. It has now become clear too that isolated national
efforts varying considerably in size and nature cannot be the answer to a problem
which is worldwide in scope and that international action is needed.
II T was within this framework that the General Conference of Unesco at its
twelfth session held at the end of 1962, decided to submit a report to the
U.N. General Assembly on the eradication of illiteracy in the world, which included
a plan for international action to encourage and bolster national efforts. This report,
which I had the honour of presenting personally to the General Assembly in October
1963, was the subject of a long discussion that led to the unanimous adoption of a
resolution approving the principle of a World Literacy Campaign.
The resolution called on countries with a high proportion of adult illiterates to
intensify their efforts to reduce illiteracy, and asked countries which had solved the
problem to assist those that had not.
It Invited the Secretary-General of the United Nations "in collaboration with
the Director-General of the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization, the Managing Director of the Special Fund, the Executive Chairman
of the Technical Assistance Board and the President of the International Bank for
Reconstruction and Development and its affiliates, to explore ways and means of
supporting national efforts for the eradication of illiteracy through a world campaign
and any other measures, if appropriate, of international co-operation and assistance,
both non-financial and financial, and to submit a report thereon, together with appro¬
priate proposals, to the General Assembly at its 19th session,"
Since this important decision was adopted by the General Assembly a number
of significant events have occurred within the framework of the U.N. and Unesco
which reveal the interest the idea of a mass literacy campaign has aroused around
the world.
Thus, two U.N. regional bodiesthe Economic Commissions for Africa and for
Asia and the Far East met respectively at Addis Ababa in February and Teheran in
March 1964 and adopted resolutions recommending that the governments of those
regions include adult literacy programmes in their national education plans as a part
of overall development. Similarly, the regional conferences of the Asian and Arab
National Commissions for Unesco, the former held in Bangkok in February and the
latter in Algiers in March, used almost identical terms to stress the Importance of
literacy in those countries. At Algiers the idea was advanced for a regional sys¬
tem to co-ordinate activities in this field.
Africain trainee in the sheet
metal workshop of a vocational
training centre. One aim of
Unesco's proposed experi¬
mental programme for mass
literacy is to open the door
of vocational and technical
training to illiterate workers.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
programme
In March of this year, a regional technical conference on literacy, organized by
Unesco at Abidjan, drafted a series of recommendations which the conference of
African Ministers of Education, meeting in the same city a few days later, endorsed
unanimously. In particular, the Ministers agreed that since literacy was the starting-
point for any vocational training, even at the minimum level, and for the improvement
of workers'qualifications through continuing adult education, it was directly instru¬
mental in raising productivity. They therefore felt that literacy projects should pre¬
ferably be directed at the organized sections of production where the desire for
literacy is strongest.
© Paul Almasy
LAST April, an expert committee on literacy which had been specially conven¬
ed by Unesco in Paris urged that a "selective strategy" be adopted in the
literacy campaign and that it be started in those sectors of the national economy
which were already organized, such as factories and other public or private enter¬
prises, co-operatives, trade unions, village councils and community development
services. This committee also advocated a strategy of intensive projects, at the
beginning of the campaign, to be carried out on an experimental-demonstration
basis in a limited number of pilot countries.
Finally, a conference of non-governmental organizations having consultative
status with Unesco, which met in Paris in June, likewise emphasized the impor¬
tance of action to reduce illiteracy and promised the support of the many organi¬
zations and associations it groups together, including a number of highly influential
ones.
It was in the light of this consensus of opinion reached by all the responsible
authorities and competent experts in their conclusions and recommendations, that
I submitted to the 67th session of the Unesco Executive Board last May the broad
outlines of an experimental programme for mass literacy as a preparatory step in the
launching at a later stage of a world campaign, the principle of which, as I have
previously indicated, has been adopted by the General Assembly of the U.N.
This programme would apply the idea of "selective strategy" in two ways.
Firstly it would operate in a limited number of countries eight at the most chosen
on the basis of a number of factors such as the illiteracy rate of the given coun¬
try, the priority given to literacy programmes in its overall education plan, the
support its people could be expected to give such a programme, etc. Secondly, it
would be limited to those sectors of the national economy which were already
organized.
T!'HESE intensive projects at the national level in a few countries would be
supplemented by regional co-operation services for research, the training
of leaders and mutual assistance designed to strengthen existing institutions.
The idea is that the experimental programme will extend over a period of five
years, from 1966 to 1970, and as each project reaches the end of its operational
stage the results will be analyzed and evaluated immediately.
The experimental programme has been approved unanimously by the Executive
Board of Unesco and goes before the Unesco General Conference when it con¬
venes in Paris this month. It has won the wholehearted support of the Secretary-
General of the United Nations and was submitted to the Economic and Social Coun¬
cil which recently met In Geneva. The Council unanimously adopted a resolution
recognizing the importance of literacy programmes in national education plans and
approved the broad lines of the experimental programme, recommending that the
General Assembly should give it favourable consideration and entrust its execu¬
tion to Unesco.
This, then, is the progress which the idea of a mass literacy campaign has made
thus far within the family of the United Nations. Of course, we should realize that 7
CONTD ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
ILLITERACY (Cont'd)
Simultaneous attack on two fronts
other groups too have grappled with this problem, such as the World Congress
for the Combating of Illiteracy, to name only one, which met in Rome in September
1962.
In a little over two years, enormous strides have been made in focusing attention
on the problem of illiteracy and in the study of its possible solutions, but certainly
the most striking development of this period has been the recognition of the neces¬
sity for universal literacy, the necessity that every adult person on our planet know
how to read and write. This idea has struck a deep, responsive chord in world
public opinion, as Unesco has found in the understanding and support it has receiv¬
ed from men and women everywhere often expressed in the most deeply moving
terms irrespective of their religious or cultural backgrounds, their economic or
social status, or their country's political system.
Personally, I consider the struggle against illiteracy to be the most imperative
and the most inspiring task of our present generation. I believe that having recognized
the universal right to education it is our duty to make that right a living fact, at the
very least on this elementary level. If illiteracy is really to be wiped out, the battle
must be fought on two fronts simultaneously. First and foremost, we must see to
it that primary and compulsory education becomes a reality everywhere, for without
this, as I have already said, new multitudes of illiterates will continue to loom up
and cloud the world horizon. At the same time we must redouble our efforts to reduce
the present large number of adult illiterates. It is essential that the two types of
action should go hand in hand since obviously generalized primary education is
impossible in a society of illiterate adults, and adult literacy is pointless if no steps
are taken to ensure the adequate education of children.
BUT to bring literacy to adults on a mass scale will have no chance of success
without the understanding and active support of the general public, since it
calls for nothing less than a general mobilization of all mankind. This is so not only
because of the funds it would require but, more important, because the very unity
of mankind is at stake. At a time when science is opening the gateway to the
stars, it is unthinkable that two-fifths of mankind should still be prisoners of ances¬
tral darkness. Or are we to have two types of human beings one for the stars,
the other for the caves? There could be no hope of peace if we tolerated an
iniquity as flagrant as this unequal division of the benefits or progress.
It is most important that both governments and people be fully informed of
these things. They must know and understand the reasons which have prompted
the proposed programmes as well as its ultimate goals.
The countries with widespread illiteracy will of course have to provide the bulk
of the resources needed for carrying out the literacy programmes. It is expected
that national efforts will represent at least three-quarters of the total resources to
be mobilized. It will be the task of both the parliaments and the governments in
those countries to give the necessary priority to literacy and to continuing adult
education in relation to the nations' overall development needs.
As for the countries where illiteracy is no longer a problem it is hoped that
they will lend technical or financial aid as part of their bilaterial, regional or inter¬
national assistance to countries which need it for their adult literacy programmes.
Unesco invites all nations and all peoples to join in this great venture for the
unshackling of men's minds and the liberation of a .pew technological, civic and
moral potential everywhere.
The stake is a colossal one. Ultimately, it involves no less than opening up
the path of enlightenment and the portals of history to two-fifths of mankind now
stagnating in ignorance and resignation.
© Louis Normand
Bureau d'Études
Henri Chomette
8
An address to the Interparliamentary Union, meeting in Copenhagen, Denmark, on August 26, 1964.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
MARINE METROPOLIS. Strolling citizens dot the vastness of "Independence Square" at the port of
Cotonou, Dahomey, where a rising metropolis and fast-expanding port offer one of Africa's most striking
examples of urban planning and economic development. Building in background is Cotonou's Congress Hall.
INVESTMENT
I by H.M. Phillips
he economics of education and Investment in
human resources has been one of the
neglected subjects in the science of economics, though
the great founder of modern economics, Adam Smith
in his Inquiry into the Nature and Causes of the
Wealth of Nations, published in 1776, placed great
stress on education. In the middle and at the end of
the next century, other great economists notably Karl
Marx and Alfred Marshall also stressed the influence of
education on economic and social development. But for
much of the first part of our century the subject has
had little study. It is only in the last few years that
a growing number of economists have been making it
one of their principal pre-occupations, and that the
words "human capital" are coming into widespread use.
When an economist speaks of "investment in human
resources" or refers to the creation of "human capital,"
he covers all of the activities which increase the effective¬
ness of the human factor in production. These include
education, training in Industry, basic research; science,
applied technical research and development, and the
creation of all types of knowledge which increase pro¬
ductivity. He also covers the means for the better
distribution of such knowledge, communication media,
fellowships, libraries, travel abroad, as well, of course,
as all measures in the field of health, nutrition and
social organization which improve man's output. While
we are concerned here mostly with education, no aspect
of human resource development can be neglected with¬
out grave economic waste.
The sudden recognition by economists of the role of
education in economic development caught some edu¬
cators by surprise. Used to their high calling
as custodians and transmitters of human and social
values they had not sufficiently realized that they held
in their hands one of the most powerful means of 9
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
INVESTMENT IN PEOPLE (Cont'd)
Teamwork for educators and economists
wiping out the pathetically low living levels prevailing
over most of the globe. Finance ministers were also
caught by surprise. Used to regarding education as a
purely social expenditure, they suddenly found their
economists on the side of the education ministers, and
educational budgets as a whole are Increasing more than
proportionately to total budgets and population growth.
The words "human capital" can easily be misunder¬
stood and they are repugnant to some people because
they see In the use of them a materlallst view of human
personality, and perhaps they are best avoided. There
are two assurances needed. First what must be in mind
Is investment in people, and not the using of people as
if they were Investments. Secondly economics has
to be defined In the final analysis as the science of
how to Increase consumption rather than production,
i.e. the satisfaction of human needs, desires and expec¬
tations.
Economists have seldom disagreed on these points.
J. S. Mill stated: "the human being I do not classify as
wealth. He Is the purpose for which wealth exists."
Marx, in the same vein, wrote : "Modern industry,
indeed, compels society, under penalty of death, to re¬
place the detail-worker of today, crippled by lifelong
repetition of one and the same trivial operation, and
thus reduced to the mere fragment of a man, by the
fully developed Individual, fit for a variety of labours,
ready to face any change of production, and to whom
the different social functions he performs are but so
many modes of giving free scope to his own actual and
acquired powers." A century later, Keynes was writ¬
ing: "consumption to repeat the obvious is the sole
end and object of all economic activity."
While economics has to express itself in the form of
measurable human preferences, and Is therefore mainly
concerned with matters which can be measured, "psychic
Income" as well as "physical income" has long had re¬
cognition in economic analysis so long as It can be
expressed in terms of preferences. The economist draws
the demand curve; he does not make it. Moreover, even
in the narrow sense of economics, the desire to work
is a fundamental part of man's nature and a great
source of satisfaction to him. There Is nothing de¬
meaning in thinking of man in his economic aspects
so defined, even though he is also made for bigger
things.
Clearly what is required in an approach which Is
"convergent" to use the term Mr. René Maheu, the Di¬
rector General, has Introduced into Unesco's programme.
The problem Is not only to use the educational system
as an Instrument to raise living levels, but to use It
to enable man to protect and to develop his highest ac¬
complishments and aspirations. Of the world's popu¬
lation of 3,180 million, 40 % are under 15.
These young people will be the mature
population of the world in 1990 and
2000, when they will hold in their
hands man's vast technological power
and with it man's destiny.
But because of the poverty in so many parts of the
world today great numbers of these children are not at
school. Only half of the child population of five to
fourteen years of age is at school, and a large number of
these do not complete the full primary school cycle.
There is therefore an urgent task for educators and
economists working together on the economic aspects of
education.
«A Poets, as well as economists, have likened men to
money. Lorca in his volume Romancero Gitano says
of the death of the gipsy, Autonito el Camborio, Viva
moneda que nunca se volverá a repetir (living coin
which can never be minted again). Antonlto, the gipsy,
was illiterate and could not read Lorca's poem. There
are ' 700 million illiterates in the world today, and, as
Lorca saw, they have stamped on them the Irreplaceable
mintage of the human individual. No man must receive
less respect because he is illiterate. But every man
has the right to be literate.
Lorca himself, who wrote this famous line, was shot
while still in his thirties. With his death, the world lost
the full years of his genius, which can never be repeated.
It is a terrible thought that there is
an international convention for the
preservation of monuments and
works of art in times of war, but
none for the preservation of human
capital.
From the tragic death of a poet it is, I fear, piling
on the agony to take the reader to a further subject of
depression, the chamal houses of the Middle Ages. But
the first econometrician (economist-statistician) of
human resources, Sir William Petty, lived at the time of
the Black Death, the greatest single destroyer of human
capital in history the power of the plague microbe far
exceeding man's own destruction of man.
A witness of the plague in London, he estimated sta¬
tistically that it would have been worth while, in eco¬
nomic terms, for the bodies of the plague victims, since
they were the chief sources of infection, to have been
put in gold coffins and transported out of London. The
capital value of the lives saved would have far exceeded
that of all of the gold Involved. Sir William Petty
was an educational pioneer as well as an econometri¬
cian. He described the education of his day as a "rabble
of words."
In his book "Advice to Samuel Hartlib," he advocated
a more practical education, and said: "For we see
children do delight in drums, pipes, fiddles, guns made
of elder-sticks and bellows' noses, piped keys, etc., paint¬
ing flags and ensigns with elder-berries and corn-poppy,
making ships with paper and setting even nut-shells
a-swlmming, handling the tools of workmen as soon
as they turn their backs and trying to work them¬
selves, fishing, fowling, hunting, setting springs and
traps for birds and other animals, making pictures in
their writing-books, making tops, gigs and whirligigs,
quilting balls, practising divers tricks upon the cards, etc.,
with a million more besides." The controversy between
the "rabble of words" and the "gigs and whirligigs" and
"setting even nut-shells a-swimming" schools of thought
still persists today in the writings of educators and
economists.
Sir William would have been delighted to read in the
reports of the Community Education Centre at Djajagirl
that modern Indonesian children write their texts on
dried banana skins, on planks, and on the sand, when
their notebooks are used up, and new ones have not
arrived. Ingenuity is one of the most precious economic
assets.
For the next great econometrician of human capital
let us move to Soviet Russia in the early 1920's, when
a country which is now an industrial giant was going
through the first troubled years of its transition from
an underdeveloped country. In 1924, Professor S.G. Stru-
mllin, doyen of Soviet economists and still working today
In Moscow at a ripe old age, undertook a scientific
analysis of the value of years of schooling of different
length in raising the output of wealth.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
© Paul Almasy
For this Indian woman from an isolated valley in the Andes, the
streets of a large modern city are an entirely new world. Edu¬
cation could help to make this the everyday world of her children.
His studies showed the large superiority of producti¬
vity of workers who had had formal schooling, together
with vocational training, as compared with those who
had only training on the Job. Many people had. of
course, been aware of this before, but no-one had estab¬
lished clear-cut results based on statistical. measurement.
These and similar studies, since Strumllln himself was
one of the architects of the GOSPLAN, led to the
concentration of the Soviet Union on education over
the following years.
It was estimated In 1960 by the Oxford economist. John
Valzey, who has contributed so much to the study of
the economics of education, that the U.S.S.R. had, for a
period of over 30 years (starting, of course, at a lower
level than the Western European countries and with a
higher proportion of young age-groups), Invested bet¬
ween twice and three times as much of Its national
product in developing education than had the average
Western European countries.
In the lnter-war years, economists were mostly con¬
cerned with problems of stability, having seen the world
economy shaken periodically to the base by devastating
Industrial slumps. It was not until the solution to this
problem was found through the revolution in economic
thought brought about by Keynes, that attention was
concentrated on development.
The division of the world into the
developed and underdeveloped coun¬
tries with a growing gap between
them was seen as a danger equal to
or greater than that of the great
slumps.
The new thinking which took place on development
brought with It new light on the role of human resources.
In a study made for the United Nations in 1948, Professors
A Lewis, T. Schultz, A. Baltra and G. Hakim an expert
group from the U.K., the U.S.A., Chile and the Lebanon
stated : "In our opinion most underdeveloped countries
are In the situation that investment in people is likely to
prove as productive, In the purely material sense, as
any Investment In material resources, and In many
cases investment In people would lead to a greater flow
of goods and services than would follow upon any com¬
parable Investment In material capital."
Over the next few years pressure was high from the
governments of the economically less-developed countries
to have education treated among top priorities In their
request for assistance, the political demand for better
education being very intense In those countries; while
in the developed countries Interest was stimulated, not
only by the new economic thinking and the demands of
technical progress, but also by the power competition
between the western group of countries and the socialist
republics.
Professor Schultz, studying the economic progress of the
United States, has estimated that between 1919 and 1957,
with the addition of only one per cent of total inputs of
tangible capital and labour, real Income had Increased
at the rate of about three per cent per year, the rest being
attributable to a somewhat mysterious "residual factor"
in which education played a prominent part. Professor
Denlson, using a different approach, found the contribu¬
tion of education to economic growth In the U.S.A. in the
period 1929 to 1956 amounted to about 23 per cent of the
growth rate of national product.
Work was also done in Norway by Professor Aukrust,
who came to a similar conclusion In respect of the growth
of national production of his country between 1900 and
1955; while in the United Kingdom, Professors Reddaway
and Smith showed that capital and labour Inputs
accounted for only a quarter of the Increased output per
head in manufacturing industries between 1948 and 1954.
CONT'D ON PAGE 28
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Sir Edmund Hillary's latest
conquest in the Himalayas
THE HIGHEST SCHOOL
IN THE WORLD
by R. J. Spector
12
MEN OF EVEREST. The Sherpa,
Tenzing Norkay (left) photographed by
Sir Edmund Hillary (below) on the summit
of Mt. Everest at the moment of their
victory over the world's highest mountain,
on May 29, 1953. Tenzing carries the
flags of the United Nations, Nepal, India
and Gt. Britain. Above, a Buddhist shrine
in the Sherpa country silhouetted againsta
towering background of Himalayan peaks.
V
¿* IfcA^WA .
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
v
M. Peissel
Photos © The Mount
Everest Foundation
Some of the Sherpa villages on the flanks of the Himalayas
near the foot of Mt. Everest now have schools for the
first time thanks to the efforts of Sir Edmund Hillary, the
New Zealand mountaineer, who (with the Sherpa, Tenzing
Norkay) was the first to set foot on the summit of Everest
in 1953. Since 1961 Sir Edmund has been seeking new conquests
in the Himalayan mountain lands of northeastern Nepal. But
this time his assault is not so much on the grim forces of
nature as on ignorance.
L!
Inspired by his long experience and appre¬
ciation of the qualities of the engaging and
hardy Sherpa people of this Sola Khombu
region, without whom none of the Himalayan
expeditions from 1920 onwards could have
been conceived, let alone accomplished, Sir
Edmund's primary Interest has become focus¬
ed on the mountain folk themselves rather
than on the giant Himalayan peaks.
Soon after Sir Edmund had led a search
for the Yeti, the "Abominable Snowman"
(whom he judges, Incidentally, to be a com
posite figment of Imagination) he asked his
Sherpa helpers, "In order to show gratitude
In terms more meaningful than money",
what they would best like to have. Their
unanimous reply, "A school for our chil¬
dren," sparked off his new venture. A few
months later the village from which most of
his Sherpas came, Khumjung perched 13,000
feet up on the flank of the sacred mountain
Khomb'Ilathe "God of Khombu," which
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
HIGHEST SCHOOL (Cont'd)
A class for Sherpas, fathers & sons
man must never climb and only fifteen miles
from the foot of Everest, was able to boast of
having the region's first school.
The two-room prefabricated structure,
donated by The Indian Aluminium Company,
was flown In sections by the International
Committee of the Red Cross to the expedition's
Mlngbo airstrip, a hard day's Sherpa-march
from Khumjung, and assembled by Hillary
and his team-mates assisted by the Sherpas.
A teacher was recruited in Darjeellng, Just
beyond Nepal's eastern frontier with India,
and after an official blessing by the head lama
of the neighbouring Thyangboche monastery
the school was soon a flourishing concern.
In 1963, It was followed by two more schools
set up by Hillary In the villages of Pangboche
and ThamI with the approval of the Nepalese
Government and with money derived from
book rights, lecture tours and donations from
private sponsors.
Between them, the three schools, which
follow the official curriculum, now have about
170 pupils, with ages ranging from six to
twenty-six (for some of the parents also
attend). Many more children would be only
too happy to Join in, for enthusiasm for learn¬
ing runs high, but the parents cannot spare
them from farm work, and quite .often will
select a favourite son to receive these coveted
benefits, although the better-off families may
send a couple of sons, or even a daughter.
But a higher economic level would elimi¬
nate the need for child labour, and Sir
Edmund's basic aim is to raise that level, and
health standards also. However, he feels
that little can be done in that direction until
there Is a general ability to read and write.
At the moment, about one in ten of the
Sherpa men, through having worked In Dar¬
jeellng and elsewhere, can read and write a
little; but among their womenfolk, the Sher-
panis, illiteracy Is total. Sir Edmund there¬
fore plans this year (In conjunction with an
attempt to scale the 21,700 feet high Mount
Thamserku) to set up another three schools
In the regional "capital" Namche Bazar
and in the villages of Chaunrlkarka and
Junbesi.
In the meantime, Sir Edmund has already
helped to Install a plastic pipeline to provide
Khumjung village with water; and he intends
to build a new airstrip (at 9,500 feet) to faci¬
litate the administration of the schools as
well as the delivery of supplies. In the
absence of roads and railways supplies depend
on human porterage which may take weeks
or months along the rugged upland trails.
But the prime necessity, he feels, Is medical
and agricultural aid. One of the scourges is
smallpox, and Sir Edmund this year plans to
set up a temporary medical clinic with a view
to something more permanent in the future.
He is also anxious to find some means of
ensuring food supplies for the villages (the
potato crop, on which the Sherpa mainly
subsist, was gravely damaged this year by
frost).
One of the main problems is the training of
teachers for work in the Sherpa schools. Sir
Edmund has so far managed to recruit five
teachers from Darjeellng and has also
arranged to have some of the most gifted of
the pupils train for teaching at Nepali-type
schools in Darjeeling or Kalimpong. The task
of providing teacher training in Nepal has
been carefully studied by Unesco in a report
on "Primary Teacher Training In Asia," pre¬
pared by Dr. E.A. Pires for the Unesco Regio¬
nal Office for Education in Asia (Bangkok).
Dr. Pires noted that only 1,500 out of 4,600
teachers in Nepal had received training.
Teacher training is now being provided by
14
HIMALAYAN SCHOOLHOUSE. Above, Sir Edmund Hillary at work on a swing at the Pangboche school,
one of those opened for the Sherpa people by his "Himalayan Schoolhouse Expedition ". Above right, in another
of the schools, at Khumjung, children and parents watch a display of Tibetan acrobatic dancing. Below left,
young Sherpas in the Khumjung school. Below right, hardy Sherpa mountaineers from the Sola Khombu region.
I J
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Photos Himalayan Schoolhouse Expedition
© The Mount Everest
Foundation
training units (four more scheduled to be
added) travelling from one selected locality
to another.
Another study, by a joint mission sent to
Nepal by Unesco and the United Nations
Economic Commission for Asia and the Far
East (ECAFE) to assist the Government to
prepare an overall plan of educational de¬
velopment Integrated with national economic
development plans found that the people of
Nepal were among the most under-privileged
In the world in respect of social services.
They live on a marginal subsistence basis,
with an annual average income of about
370 rupees (less than $50) and are 94%
illiterate. And one of the decisive reasons for
Nepal's economic underdevelopment, the re¬
port concluded, is its under-educated people,
70% of whom live in tiny villages averaging
225 inhabitants.
Even after an intensive effort of educa¬
tional development between 1951 and 1961,
only 15.8% of all children of primary school
age were attending school (the proportion for
the Sherpa region being Infinitely smaller).
The 1964 target is 21.2%. For all these
children teachers have to be found; and the
report recommended a better distribution of
trained teachers throughout the country.
The problem is to train Nepalese teachers
who will be prepared to work in the least
privileged parts of the country, Including the
land of the Sherpas, and to provide children
with the sort of education that will not detach
them from their surroundings and send
them to the town to swell the ranks of the
semi-educated unemployed. The Unesco/
ECAFE report refers to "over-education" and
the danger of "desertion of the rural areas
and saturation of the large centres by primary
school graduates seeking jobs which do not
exist or demanding secondary and higher
education opportunities which the Nepalese
economy Is not at this time able to afford."
Sir Edmund is also strongly of the opinion
that Instead of "over-educating" the Sherpas
and thus Initiating a drift to the towns where
they will be non-productive, it would be more ^5
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
HIGHEST SCHOOL (Cont'd)
Aland
of gaiety
and courage
appropriate to fit them to cope more effecti¬
vely with their harsh environment and main¬
tain their links with their community a view
which is likewise upheld by another famous
traveller to Nepal, Ella Maillart.
In her "Land of the Sherpas" she wrote :
"It Is in their own homes that the Sherpas
must be Judged, and not as they exist on the
outskirts of Darjeellng, uprooted, living as
best as they can, often without work, badly
housed and In Ill-health, victims of the uni¬
versal vicious circle of over-population... In
their high valleys the Sherpas are at home
In their own world."
As to the outstanding qualities of the Sher¬
pas, "living In their own world" all are
agreed. Sir Edmund, like everyone who has
worked with them, has nothing but praise for
their gaiety, adaptability and Intelligence.
W.H. Murray, who was deputy-leader of the
1951 Everest reconnaissance in which Hillary
took part, describes the Sherpa, in his "Story
of Everest," as a "free and independent man,
full of resource in his own way of life . and
schooled from earliest youth in self-reliance."
While only a minority of Sherpas can read
and write, he adds, their way of Ufe "develops
In most of them a keen Intelligence". Above
all, they can laugh... they are, indeed, the
happiest people I have ever met."
Such are the people for whom Sir Edmund
Hillary has been so devotedly working.
Within five years, the Nepalese Government
Is due to take over the schools founded by
him. In the meantime, assisted by his sole
staff, Lady Hillary (who in 1963 Journeyed to
Khombu valley to present the first school
prizes ever awarded here), he is pursuing his
"Expedition Schoolhouse" and the related
schemes with the same slngleheartedness that
took him to the "roof of the world."
Recently passing through Bangkok In the
course of his promotion efforts. Sir Edmund
visited ECAFE and the Unesco Regional
Office, whose staff assembled to hear him give
an account of what he described as "the most
satisfactory project of our Himalayan adven¬
ture."
Unesco Is now studying the possibility of
supporting this educational venture through
its Gift Coupon Scheme. Anyone wishing to
give assistance to Sir Edmund's project may
wish to contact the Unesco Gift Coupon
Office, Place de Fontenoy, Paris.
R. J. Spector is publications officer at the
*g Unesco Regional Office for Education in Asia
(Bangkok, Thailand). He has been on the
staff of Unesco since 1957.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Seven centuries ago the Sherpa people crossed
the plateau of Tibet and settled on the slopes
of the Himalayas in what is now northeastern
Nepal. They hewed roads like giant stairways
from the solid rock, threw bridges across
rushing torrents, and built villages and mona¬
steries. Left, two monks sound their 15-foot
trumpets at the monastery of Thami. In
Buddhist monasteries and scattered over the
countryside, innumerable prayer-wheels turn
endlessly in the mountain wind (above right).
BUDDHIST BOOKS & PRAYER-WHEELS
Buddhist monks in the Himalayan monasteries are skilled printers and make
books with high quality paper produced by long-established Sherpa paper mills.
Below, books are wrapped in silk and protected by wooden covers. Left, Sherpa
children try vainly to turn a giant prayer mill containing hundreds of religious books. Photo* < M. Peissel
1
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
The most celebrated
of all Ethiopia's legen¬
dary stories is that of
the meeting between
King Solomon and the
Queen of Sheba, and
the birth of their son
Monelik, who founded
the Ethiopian ruling
dynasty some 3,000
years ago. It is also
the most popular of
all folk art themes in
Ethiopia where it has
been portrayed in the
same form (right) by
many generations of
painters. Below, an
Ethiopian artist works
on a series of paintings
recounting the story of
Solomon and Sheba.
i' Paul Almasy, Pans
18
A FOLK TRADITION
CENTURIES OLD
by Otto A. Jäger
HE history of Ethiopia goes back over 3,000 years to the
time of Solomon and the Queen of Sheba. According to
tradition the queen bore King Solomon a son, Menelik, who became Ethiopia's
first ruler and founded the royal dynasty. Modern Ethiopia ha9 developed in
an unbroken historical line from the ancient (Ist century A.D.) Axumite King¬
dom which took its name from its capital city at Axum.
Christianity has been Ethiopia's official religion since early in the 4th
century A.D. when the reigning monarch at Axum was converted to this faith.
Except during the five years of Italian occupation (1936-41) Ethiopia can look
back on 3,000 years of independence.
Ethiopian art, especially painting, has always been an art of the people.
This same tradition is found in every branch of artistic expression from
architecture, music and dancing to woodcarving, pottery, wickerwork and
the products of silversmiths' and goldsmiths' skills Ethiopia has produced
many specially talented artists, particularly architects and painters, whose
masterpieces now universally recognized as such mark periods when
Ethiopian emperors embarked on ambitious projects or when there was an
upsurge of religious fervour.
Ethiopia lies mid-way down the continent of Africa yet culturally it belongs
to the world of the orient. How has this come about ?
Lake Tana in northern Ethiopia is the source of the Blue Nile arid men
followed the banks of this river northwards to the Mediterranean and Ale/en-
dria; from Egypt others passed southwards to the highlands of Ethiopia.
Close ties were thus formed with the Mediterranean Cushite culture of Egypt
CONT'D ON PAGE 22
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
ART OF ETHIOPIA (Cont'd)
IMAGES
OF
DAILY
LIFE
DANCE OF THE PRIESTS. Liturgical dances are performed in Ethiopia on
the occasion of great religious festivals such as the " Timkat " (Epiphany) when
the populace is symbolically rebaptised and on Palm Sunday. Above, to
the sound of drums and sistrums lines of priests perform dances accord¬
ing to a time-honoured ritual. Below, artist's impression of the scene.
20
Photos © R. Michaud
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
*> *í
v
ON THE ROAD TO MARKET. All rural life in Ethiopia revolves around the weekly village market. When market
day arrives farmers and their wives (above), some carrying umbrellas of plaited reeds, set off from home laden
with produce. The group in the painting below includes a priest (second from left) wearing a white turban.
BOATS MADE
FROM
PAPYRUS
<¿XW¿ <r<r'% » :'\5R\
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
ART OF ETHIOPIA (Cont'd)
Meeting place
of two
continents
Other African territories south of the Sahara had no such natural lines of
communication.
To the east the narrow confines of the Red Sea were a bridge rather than
a gulf between Ethiopia and "Arabia Felix" ("Fortunate Arabia" as the Yemen
was named by early European geographers), in whose fertile territories there
was wealth and a high level of culture. The constant traffic between the
shores of the Red Sea took the influence of Arab culture far into Ethiopia.
Again, West and South Africa had no contacts of this kind.
Ethiopia's contacts with other more distant civilizations were made possible
by a natural phenomenon of the weather, the monsoon, which blew from
Africa to India from April to October and from India to Africa during the next
six months. Using these winds ships sailed safely and swiftly from Africa to
India and, with the turn of the monsoon, back to Africa again. We are told that
2,000 years ago as many as 70 ships laden with spices and fabrics from India
dropped anchor in a single day in the Ethiopian harbour of Adulis on the
Red Sea. At that time Ethiopia exported ivory, leopard skins, monkeys, gold,
slaves, myrrh and musk.
Ethiopia's unique geographical position is also shown in the racial compo¬
sition of its people. A high proportion of Egyptian Cushites and Semite
peoples from southern Arabia, a smaller percentage of indigenous African
peoples and small groups of oriental origin all mingled in the ethnic cons¬
titution of Ethiopia several thousand years ago.
Just as these different peoples merged in Ethiopia and became a homo¬
geneous new one, so Ethiopia took over cultural influences from outside its
borders and recast them in new forms of expression. This was chiefly made
possible by the country's geological character, a "mountain fastness" which
bred in its inhabitants a special appeciation of the hermit's life and an outlook
divorced from earthly concerns.
I N Ethiopian art the after-life and the irrational figure pro¬
minently and allusions to the other world, as perceived by
its people through myth and magic, determined the main lines of its deve¬
lopment. Painting is not realistic, but tends rather towards abstract forms.
This art is always of a religious kind. In the pre-Christian era its main
concerns were with life after death and the adoration of the moon, the earth
and water. In Christian times its contemplation has been devoted to God's
sphere, to heaven and hell and to angels, saints and devils.
One of the earliest characteristic elements of Ethiopian art is the braid
motif found on a wide variety of objects from parchment paintings to silver
crosses. These silver crosses were made by the "lost wax" process, being
first modelled in wax and then encased in clay. When the clay was heated
the wax ran out, after which the mould was filled with molten metal.
The braid motif with its endless intertwining lines is probably a symbol of
eternity. The same motif is also found in Coptic art generally, woven into
fabrics, carved in wood and stone, worked in silver and gold and painted on
parchment. The braid motif is also commonly found in early Irish miniature
religious paintings to which, strangely enough, Ethiopian miniatures often bear
a remarkable stylistic similarity. Among other characteristic motifs found in
Ethiopian bas-reliefs and illuminated manuscripts are the ornamental repre¬
sentations of people and animals.
The most important remains of Axumite culture dating from pre-Christian
times are the funerary monuments. They were cut from a single block of
stone and the tallest of them were over 100 feet high. The only one still
standing in Axum is 88 feet high. These monuments probably symbolize the
dwellings of the dead kings in the world beyond the grave.
Compared with these Ethiopian monuments, Greek or Roman temples of
about the same period have a far stronger "earthbound" quality, with heavy
roofs resting on columns that seem to anchor them still more firmly to the
ground. In contrast the remarkable Ethiopian works have practically no
foundation and their forms suggest celestial dwelling-places that have been
planted in the earth like an arrow fallen from the sky.
Ethiopia's other unique religious monuments are its rock churches which
probably date back to the 13th century. They have the appearance of carefully
planned structures built of squared stones and beams, but have in fact been
entirely hewn from the natural rock and so remain one with their foundations.
Here again inspiration seems to have come from above, leaving its imprint
on the surface of the ground, in contrast to European temples and cathedrals
which rise upwards from man-made foundations. The Ethiopian building is
like an engraving; it is as if God had impressed His seal upon the earth.
Along with architecture, painting is a widespread and vigorous form of
Ethiopian artistic expression. Early murals, executed in the old Ethiopian
style, are found at Deir Makaryus in the desert between Cairo and Alexandria.
At Farras in Nubia there, are 9th-century wall paintings which are to some
extent related to the Ethiopian style.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Pliulos iO H. Midland
THE MINSTREL. In former times the "azmari" or minstrel was
attached to the Ethiopian court or the houses of noblemen (above).
Today he is a wanderer (below) and travels from village to village
accompanying his songs on a "masenko", a kind of one-string fiddle.
From the 13th-century onwards the number of paintings from the Ethiopian
monastery schools in the region of Axum, Lake Tana and Lalibela and from
the Gunda Gunde monastery increased. The fullest and most varied expres¬
sions are on the pages of manuscripts. Decorative designs adorn the chapter
headings and pictures illustrate incidents from the life of Christ, the Virgin and
the saints. Some of these masterpieces were reproduced in "Ethiopia: Illu¬
minated Manuscripts" one of the albums of colour reproductions in the
Unesco World Art Series (See "The Unesco Courier", December 1961). The
style of the paintings is abstract and visionary in contrast to the lifelike
representations of the same period in Europe.
In early times there was probably no secular painting in Ethiopia. The
earliest paintings of this type, which are actually examples of Ethiopian folk
art, date from the 19th-century. Their subjects are legends, battles, judge¬
ment scenes and ¡mages of everyday life. By far the most common subject
for these folk art paintings is the 3,000 year-old legend of the meeting
between the Queen of Sheba and King Solomon.
Otto Jacer is the author of several works on Ethiopian painting including
"Aethiopische Miniaturen" {Ethiopian Miniatures) published by Mann,
Berlin, 1957. He was a contributor (with Jules Leroy and Stephen Wright)
to the album of colour reproduction, "Ethiopia, Illuminated Manuscripts" ,
in the Unesco World Art Series. A pediatrician, Dr. Jager has worked as
a specialist for the World Health Organization.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
i "
I
;
*. T
Mi .
"at'V
r, x.
i?--*
.^^
M
ar.l
I
£7
ÉË *&
rw
^
24
This fearsome looking monster from Chile is actually
only half a millimetre in length. A member of the col-
lembola family, it is one of the tiny animals which
inhabit the soils of temperate and tropical countries.
Drawing © Poivre, Ecological Laboratory, Brunoy, Francs
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
A SAFARI ARMED
WITH MICROSCOPES
by Janos Balogh
RAVAGED FOREST
In ever more extensive
areas of Africa forests
are being torn up to
make way for crops
(left). But deforestation
is not without its dan¬
gers Left without pro¬
tection topsoil is quick¬
ly washed away. Today
scientists are studying
problems of the "sick
soils" in tropical Africa.
© H. Zicsi
TINY GAME HUNT
Two members of the
expedition which made
a census of soil fauna
in the Congo (Brazza¬
ville) collect specimens
for examination from
their catch of well over
half a million. These tiny
animals help to main¬
tain the life of the soil
and thereby increase
the size of harvests.
Paul Almasy. Paris
Through their application to agriculture, recent discoveries in soil biology
have an important role to play in economic development. Unesco is es¬
pecially concerned with research into the soil problems of tropical
and sub tropical regions where each year soils become increasingly
impoverished. As part an its extensive programme in soil science, Unesco
sponsored the sending of a scientific mission to Africa from October 1963
to January 1964, to survey, collect and compare the animals found in
the soil of the Congo (Brazzaville). Similar missions are to be sent to
Australia, New Guinea and Central and South America. Below we publish
an article by the leader of the Unesco mission to the Congo (Brazzaville).
Iin school geography books of the
1 19th century the maps showed, many
blank spaces marked "unexplored." Since
then men have penetrated the densest jun¬
gles and crossed the most remote deserts, and
the last empty spaces have disappeared from
the world's maps. But this is true only in
a strictly geographical sense. A modern bio¬
logist still sees plenty of vast empty spaces
awaiting exploration by "Stanleys" and
"Brazzas" from among the world's scientists.
Today's expeditions of
however, are nothing like
set out a century ago. The
invited by the government
country. His equipment too
only arms he carries are
devices for capturing and
explorer-scientists,
the parties that
modern explorer is
of an independent
has changed. The
a microscope and
conserving Insects.
The discovery of a new species of mammal
or bird is now so rare that it earns news¬
paper headlines. It thus seems all the more
astounding to hear that during the past five
years scientists have discovered more than
400 hitherto unknown species of animals in
different parts of equatorial Africa. All these
creatures are minute: most measure less than
half a millimetre and even the largest never
exceed one millimetre.
Why should scientists take the trouble to
search for such tiny living creatures? Why
is so much money spent to send out missions
to jungles and savannahs on operations which
seem to have no immediate value? Certainly no
one would claim that this kind of research
brings any immediate improvement in the
food production of the regions concerned.
In this case, as in many others, science has
to look to the future. The research being done
here might be compared with a doctor's
examination of a patient. For in many ways
the soil of tropical regions is like a sick orga¬
nism. In their original, healthy state these
soils were covered with virgin forest. Down
the years great stretches have been cleared
with no regard to the consequences. Heavy
tropical rains falling on these deforested
areas wash away so much of the humus, or
vegetable mould, that the forests never grow
again.
Because unsuitable methods are often used
to cultivate the land in most areas of trop¬
ical Africa harvests are pitifully small and
each year the soil becomes more Impo¬
verished.
In the past twenty years scientific research
has shown that close links exist between the
minute fauna In the soil and the life of the
soil Itself and consequently with the quality
and size of the crops it produces.
It hardly seems believable that tiny crea¬
tures, not even one millimetre In length, should
determine whether harvests are lean or plenti¬
ful. Yet the results of scientific research are
irrefutable. In Central Europe It has been
shown that on every two and a half acres of
arable land the minute creatures living in the
soil produce substances equivalent to 25 tons
of organic fertilizer. This far exceeds the
amount of organic and synthetic fertilizers
which are used to feed the soil under the most
advanced methods of modern farming. The
tiny soil fauna thus Improve the soil at no
cost to man and on a scale which he is at
present unable to match. It Is not surprising
that science Is now taking a keen Interest in
the work of soil fauna, and that our expedi¬
tion should have been sent to the Republic
of the Congo (Brazzaville).
Our mission can be summed up as a
broad census and stock-taking of all
the animals living In the soil, from earthworms
to microscopic fauna. It took three of us
working as a team three months to make this
census In five different regions of the country
covered by tropical jungles and forests,
savannahs and crops.
Collecting specimens of soil fauna Is cer¬
tainly one of the most unusual forms of 25
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
SAFARI WITH MICROSCOPES (Cont'd)
Mysterious creatures
that fertilize the soil
A collembole from
New Zealand, one of
the innumerable spe¬
cies of a family of
soil animals whose
members are often
invisible to the naked
eye. Between 10.000
and 200.000 of these
creatures may live in
a square yard of soil.
An Andean collem¬
bole. These soil ani¬
mals have very poor
vision and thus rely
on their organs of
smell intheantennae.
26
Drawings (p Poivre,
Ecological Laboratory.
Brunoy, France
hunting. The ordinary hunter carries a rifle
and the entomologist a net, but the soil zoo¬
logist goes back to the most ancient hunting
techniques and sets traps for his quarry.
The simplest technique we used was to sink
plastic containers the size of flower-pots into
the soil of the virgin forest. Each one was
protected from the rain by a metal cover and
contained a liquid chemical product to pre-
serve the tiny creatures which
it trapped. Another of our
methods was to place some forest
soil on a sieve over a funnel
leading to a flask containing pres¬
erving fluid. As the earth grows
drier the little animals burrow
deeper and deeper until they fall
Into the funnel and are carried
to the flask.
We set hundreds of these
traps and collected an enormous
quantity of soil animals well
over 500,000 according to a pro¬
visional count. After we have
analyzed and catalogued this
huge collection we shall be able
to publish a report on the fauna living in the
soil of Africa's virgin forests and also
determine the role it plays in the formation
and loosening of productive soil.
One of our most interesting finds was that
forest humus Is formed not only at soil level
but also among tree foliage. We thus confirmed
the finding of Professor Delamare-Deboutte-
vllle of the Ecological Laboratory at Brunoy,
near Paris, who has already observed that
plants can take root in the dust which some¬
times accumulates in the axils of tree branches.
We ourselves noted that where virgin forest
vegetation is really dense, dead leaves can
accumulate among the branches and the
lianas which cling to the trees. Rain reduces
the leaves to a form in which soil animals
can make their habitat and the
excrement of these creatures
falls on the forest floor like an
unceasing rain of powdered
manure. Even worms are some¬
times found in this "suspended
detritus," of which we collected
many samples from the Congo
forests. Studies are now being
made of the fauna found in this
humus from high in the air.
In the Sibiti district in the
heart of the virgin forest country
we came across groups of pygmy
peoples. Had we been ethnologists we should
certainly have made good use of these en¬
counters, but in fact we were more concerned
in studying one of the most interesting
animal species in the forest, the giant nephila
spider.
The nephila is one of the most fascinating
creatures of the region. The females are
often between three and five centimetres in
size whereas the male barely exceeds eight
to twelve millmetres. The disproportion
between the weights of the two sexes is even
greater. It is as if a woman weighing 50
kilogrammes (110 lbs) were to have a husband
weighing two and a half kilogrammes.
An explanation for the existence of these
dwarf male spiders has been offered by the
evolutionist theory. The female is so vora¬
cious that it often devours the male. The
smaller males have escaped this fate more
often than those whose size offers a more
substantial meal. Thus by a process of natu¬
ral selection operating over millions of years
a race of tiny males has been evolved.
We have seen six or more of these dwarf
males gathered around the female's web and
waiting an opportunity to approach her.
Finally one of them will set off for an encoun¬
ter with the female. The Instant the female
attacks him, the little male releases a thread
and quick as a flash descends to safety.
The giant nephila's web is spun from
threads that are golden-yellow in colour and
often measure a yard in diameter. Mada¬
gascar's ancient kings were traditionally
buried in a shroud made from the giant
nephila's web and such shrouds are sometimes
still found in the old royal burial places on
that Island. About half a century ago an
effort was made to acclimatize the giant
nephila in Europe so as to use its thread for
producing textiles. But with the development
of synthetic fibres the experiment was
abandoned.
The tiny males are not
the only visitors to these
great golden webs. Spider
parasites make their
homes in them and
scavage the remains of
the female's banquets,
collecting tiny mosquitoes
which she disdains on
account of their size.
The two or three families
of guest spiders living
on each web pay for
their meals by keeping
the web clean.A collembole
found in the
Congo region. Altogether we spent
110 days in the Congo
(Brazzaville), a fascinat¬
ing country of great
beauty, especially the spectacle of the Stan¬
ley Pool betwen Leopoldville and Brazzaville
where the Congo resembles an immense lake.
Here masses of a lovely aquatic plant named
the water hyacinth from its handsome large
blue flowers, form great floating islands on the
surface of the waters. A native of America, it
was only recently imported into the Congo but
it has so quickly infested large stretches of
the river that it is now a threat to navigation.
During our mission we travelled over
3,000 miles through the Congo with no wea¬
pons more offensive than our entomologists'
tweezers. Less than 90 years ago the explo¬
rer Stanley had literally to fight his way
through the same regions. Africa has indeed
changed in the past century and is destined
to change even more in the near future.
Our expedition was only the first of many
scientific missions which in the years ahead
will study the soil fauna of equatorial
regions.
Prof. Janos Balogh, a soil biologist, is head of
the zoological research group of the Hun¬
garian Academy of Sciences and is president
of the Hungarian Zoological Association. Prof
Balogh, who has discovered over 300 hitherto
unknown species of animals living in tropical
soils, is the author of many scientific works.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
A. Zicsi
SCOURGE OF RIVERS
Early this century a tropical South American floating aquatic plant, named the
water hyacinth from its handsome large blue flowers, made its appearance in
Africa. It began to spread with terrifying speed, choking great rivers, blocking
irrigation canals and smothering dams. Efforts to halt its progress by spraying
weedkiller from helicopters have been unsuccessful and scientists are still seek¬
ing ways to check this invader plant. One possible solution might be to induce
the manatee or sea cow which feeds off the water hyacinth to take up residence
in African rivers (See The Unesco Courier, Feb. 1963, p. 23). Below, a carpet of
water hyacinth plants that now infest large stretches of the Congo River.
© Paul Almasy
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Cont'd from
page 1 1 INVESTMENT IN PEOPLE
These studies dealt mainly with education as a factor
In production, but attention was drawn to its role as an
item of consumption. By "consumption" is meant that
people want education for their children quite apart
from Its economic value, and are prepared to pay a
lot for it, because it contributes to the enjoyment of
life and Is a social and individual asset. It was also
noted that It is an Item of consumption which is
an economic and social end In itself that Is to say, it
is one of the components of living levels.
A few years ago the United Nations set up an Expert
Group on the definition and measurement of living
levels. This group selected twelve indicators which cov¬
ered the whole range of human needs, including both
those measurable in monetary terms and those which are
not. Among the twelve Indicators selected, the third
was education, and in the assessment made of the prio¬
rity of the different indicators, it was preceded only by
expectation of life and infant mortality rates (clearly
It is better to be uneducated and alive than educated
and dead), and national average food supplies (man can¬
not live by bread alone, but needs bread to live).
Further, education seems to be, as John Stuart Mill
maintained, the only item of consumption not subject
to the law of diminishing utility. One may, of course
say of a particular curriculum that as needs change its
utility diminishes, but it would be most unlikely for
anyone to claim he had all the education he could
usefully possess. Indeed, the evidence is, the more edu¬
cation people have, the more they want. A report by
the British adult educational societies showed that the
three quarters of the population who finished school at
14, and the four per cent who finished at 17 to 20, were
each represented by a quarter of society-members.
This does not, of course, mean that there is no limit
to the amount of education people should be given at
public expense. Indeed, the economics of education
Is concerned precisely with trying to determine what
proportion of national resources should be devoted to
education. Ideally, this would be done by measuring
the cost and benefits of education, and investment would
be made In education wherever the benefits exceed those
of alternative forms of Investment.
However, while it Is possible to measure the costs of
education. It is extremely difficult, to measure its future
benefits.
The mysterious residual factor already mentioned
consists not only of education, but also of research and
the whole range of man's skills which make physical
resources productive. Clearly, research is an indirect
return on education of very high value.
28
Estimates show that as of 1955 the
return on the average dollar invest¬
ed in hybrid corn research in the U.S.
was at least 700% per annum.
Results of this kind and it is unfortunate that all
research Is not as successful as this spring from high
levels of education. But the highest inventive skills of
this kind, whether scientific or organizational, have to
be supported by ranks of middle technicians, and by
entrepreneurs or educated farmers who will exploit
market possibilities, and complementary technical and
vocational education is required. Further, they need
to operate in a society with an Informed electorate, and
to operate in a society where there is a sense of indivi¬
dual opportunity based on a broad educational system.
In an American context we may note the findings by
Dr. G. Lewis and Professor C.A. Anderson from their study
of the social origin and social mobility of businessmen in
the city of Lexington. The enquiry covered all the
businessmen in a city of 100,000 persons and showed
that "the most Important single factor favouring busi¬
ness success was education." If we look at economically
underdeveloped areas, we find the same kind of data.
A survey in a backward rural area
in Jamaica showed that "for persons
in low status occupations, education
is the main channel of social mobi¬
lity. "
The whole question of the relation of education to
social mobility and social structure, is, however, a diffi¬
cult one. Education can also be a conserving force. And
even in societies with the best legislation and intentions,
people receive better education than others because of
original privileges of wealth and parenthood. Studies
in developed as well as developing countries illustrate the
danger of generalization as to the effect of education
on social structure without careful study of the particular
society and type of educational system involved.
Interesting studies have been made on this aspect by
Professor D. McClelland of the Massachusetts Institute of
Technology of the relation between economic progress
and what he calls "the need for achievement" or "n
achievement," a desire to do well, not so much for the
sake of social prestige, but for the sake of an inner feeling
of personal accomplishment. McClelland has applied
laboratory findings to workers in factories and has also
conducted a study of history relating degrees of "n achie¬
vement" and economic growth on the one hand, and
with education and "n achievement" on the other.
In modern times it is in the school that motivation for
"n achievement" is developed at an early age by school
examinations, the desire to emulate in competitions,
games, etc. All these, of course, presuppose that the
values transmitted by the society are progressive and
entrepreneurial; unless they are, the school can be the
custodian and transmitter of traditional forces opposed
to change. One must always remember that education
is what educators make of it.
The difficulty with the "n achievement" approach is
that it seems to make too easy assumptions as to what kind
of activities are worthwhile. Thus the young Buddhist
performing his year's service in the priesthood shows
high "n performance" in spiritual terms, but the begging
bowl which he carries reflects his performance in eco¬
nomic terms. Indeed, the more "n" he is, the more
aversion he will have to economic gain, while doing his
priestly service.
The question of what is of economic utility and what
is not is a difficult one. Some years ago a firm making
ball-point pens received an order from a developing
country for a large number of tops of pens. The firm
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
© Paul Almasy The world-wide expansion of education will call formulions of new teachers. Despite advances in teaching aids the
teacher remains the life core of education. Here, future science teachers are given practical laboratory experience.
queried the request. Had a mistake been made? Not
at all. The pens were wanted by people who could not
write, but put the tops of pens in their breast pockets
for prestige purposes. Sheer waste? A small and harm¬
less Imposture like high heels worn by short band
leaders? A good, advertisement for literacy.
Education tends to reduce excessive population growth.
An interesting speculation which I have heard made is to
suppose that developing countries experiencing the "popu¬
lation explosion" the average rate of population growth
of the poorer countries of the world is 70 per cent higher
than that of the wealthier countries Instituted as their
first priority compulsory education up to the age of
16 limited to females.
Whatever may be the political difficulties of such a
course, the effect would probably be to cause a direct and
immediate reduction of population expansion since many
births take place in that age group. This measure
would also create a better educated female population
which would be a source of recruitment for teachers
in primary educational systems, as well as increasing
the efficacity of teaching in the homea form of edu¬
cation not dealt with here, but of great importance.
The cost of education varies from country to country,
according to the demographic situation. Most developing
countries have a larger proportion of children to total
population than developed countries, and the relative
cost of teachers' salaries in relation to average income
is higher. The usual pattern seems to be that about two-
thirds of the annual cost of education consists of the
salaries of teachers. Education is therefore proportion¬
ately more expensive if the same standards are aimed at.
It is an unfortunate fact that normally the poorer
a country is, the more relatively dear is its unit cost
of education. It is not easy to make comparisons of
expenditure on education between countries, but It seems
that the percentage of national income spent on edu¬
cation varies between 2 per cent and 6 per cent, the
highest levels being attained in Japan and the U.S.S.R.
There Is another approach to measurement of the eco¬
nomic returns of education, which has attracted much
interest. A rough description of It is that it takes
the average earnings over a lifetime of people In occu¬
pations for which specific degrees of education are
required, and compares them with the earnings of people
without the same degree of education.
Professor G. Becker, in his studies for the United States
National Bureau of Economic Research, using a method
similar to this, estimated, that as of 1950 the U.S. male
population was earning 14.8 per cent annually on what
they had privately invested in obtaining their high-
school, college and university educations. If public costs
were added, the rate was about 11 per cent.
At the other end of the scale of economic develop¬
ment. Professor Oscar Lewis, in a survey of a slum area
on the outskirts of Mexico City (1) employing simpler me¬
thods, showed a close relationship between the Income
and the years of schooling of the Inhabitants even a
bare modicum of extra primary education enabling mem¬
bers of a poor community to outstrip the income of their
neighbours. This research gave results similar to that In
the Soviet Union which were described earlier, under¬
taken by Professor Strumllin.
(1) See "The Children of Sanchez," Random House, New
York, 1961 ($7.50); Seeker and Warburg, London, 1962 (36/-);
Penguin Modern Classics (paperback ed.), London, 1964 (8/6). «q
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
INVESTMENT IN PEOPLE (Cont'd)
A call for millions of new teachers
The foregoing material, while perhaps impressive as
Indicating the overall economic value of education, is not
usable as a practical guide to specific educational plans
and programmes. It indicates only a pre-disposltlon to
Invest in education unless it is clear that there Is some
other Investment which is of more vital Importance.
Governments, therefore, are still faced with an extreme¬
ly difficult problem In evaluating actual educational
plans and programmes in relation to other alternative
investments. On this Issue many of us lean to the more
specific method of finding out what are the educational
requirements of a given economic and social plan or
perspective of a given country.
In the same way the cultural demand from education
can be derived from the standards which the society
wishes to set.
Sometimes society's standards are
higher than the economy can bear,
and in these cases there has to be a
30
slowing up of educational expansion
until such time as the economist has
created the necessary resources.
But here again because of the long-term effects, direct
and Indirect, It Is unwise of finance ministers and planners
to be too rigid and to try to pin back education to narrow
economic limits, because of the impact of education on
the vitality of the whole economic and social system.
There Is much evidence that careful and long-range
planning of education builds up In society the "residual
factor" which acts as a stimulus to and a multiplier of
production, as well as meeting manpower needs.
What are likely to be the educational priorities of the
developing countries from an economic standpoint?
Clearly they should take action in the field of vocational
and technical education needed to fill existing gaps in
skilled manpower. In such cases the return is huge.
Then there is vocational and technical training for
known expansions of Industry, and in new States lacking
administrative cadres the quick training of administrators
and managers for Industry is also of the highest priority.
But "crash" action of this kind rapidly peters out unless
it is based on long-term extension of secondary, technical
and higher education, and this takes us at once to one
of the most vital needs of the daynamely educational
planning. Very close attention has to be paid to future
demand, which has to be met by planning now.
At the same time, the problem of the unemployed "white
collar" worker Is a serious one in many developing
countries, as is the surplus of lawyers and the shortage
of engineers, and the drift of young labour from the
land. It Is here that close co-ordination is required
between economic planning and educational planning.
The newly developing countries are advancing on new
ground. Better educational systems and Improved curri¬
cula are required. Aiming at quick growth with small
resources, they cannot afford the waste Involved of
leaving this to chance. Nor is it an answer to say that
In the older countries "laissez-faire" produced the
necessary results. Serious errors and dislocations In
educational development occurred in these countries at
various times. One of these has been over-specialization
on the part of students taking technical training.
Increased emphasis is now being placed on accom¬
panying technical training with a good general educa¬
tion In the developed countries because of the increased
rate of technical change, and In the developing countries
because of the need for flexibility in the use of their
limited resources.
While technical and secondary education have the
clearest economic returns, no country can obtain really
high or even medium-high leaving levels widely spread
over the population without a compulsory school system
of at least seven years, covering the primary grades and
extending into secondary a substantial proportion of
better pupils. Moreover, widespread literacy among the
adult as well as the pupil population is necessary not
only to Increase the productivity of labour, but. for social
and political purposes.
Importance must also be given to adult education in
subsistence areas to give people incentive to rise above
the poverty line and in rural areas to move from subsis¬
tence production into the market economy. This will
help to break the vicious circle of governments being
unable to raise taxes for education because of lack of
revenue, which in turn is due to a large proportion of
the population remaining outside the monetary economy.
Countries divided into literates and illiterates are dual
societies, where part of the population is not in the
position of being fully "legitimised" members of the
nation able to read, write and take effective part in
political and legal processes. What is true of individual
nations also applies to the world as a whole.
The world is today a dual society,
with hundreds of millions of people
who have had no effective education,
who cannot read and write.
Even for their children compulsory education of seven
years is still a future hope rather than a present fact.
Literacy programmes do not fall within the normal
planning of the formal educational system and call
for a special approach. There is, of course, a close inter¬
lock between the extent and effectiveness of primary
education in a country and its rate of literacy. Today,
the number of illiterates in the world is increasing, despite
adult literacy campaigns, because compulsory primary
education does not yet cover the large population of
children swelling every year the number of adult
illiterates. This is one of the results of "the population
expansion".
The approach of the economist to literacy is that
adult literacy campaigns should be related to the work
environment, and then spread out over the whole
country. Thus the first and most productive step is to
make literate all the country's factory workers. The
productivity of literates in factories as compared with
illiterates is so well established that the cost of the
literacy programme in factories is paid off in a short
time.
Further, the financial burden can be and should be
transferred from the State to the industries concerned
who will recover it later in the additional efficiency of
the labour force. Then the central government should
extend literacy campaigns to the public services, the
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
post offices, railways, etc., dealing not only with the
literacy of their employees, but utilizing the same facilities
to the families and relatives. This could be done by
passing the cost on to the consumer of public services,
with the State only paying the central charges for teacher
training, the production of materials, etc. Then rural
areas where there are large-scale projects of development
or modernization schemes or other forms of inter¬
vention in development through river valley projects,
etc. should be treated in the same way as factories.
The cost of the salaries of the teachers and of the
buildings should, as far as possible, be borne in the costs
of the projects themselves.
As resources become available, the central government
should extend over the whole country facilities for
creating literacy, training first the most productive age
groups and the most fast developing regions in order
to obtain the most rapid returns on the investment In
literacy. The development thus brought about and the
increase of the central budget should then be used as
early as possible to put the whole country on a uniform
basis of literacy as part of citizenship rights.
In addition to creating a well-planned educational
system and effective measures to eradicate illiteracy,
it is necessary for the developing countries to give
increased attention to science and technology. Here
again, the approach of the economists is a selective one.
Not all research leads to the huge returns we noted
earlier in the case of hybrid seed corn. Some research
is extremely costly and is on economic grounds best
carried as part of the costs of production of large scale
Industry.
A number of developed countries rely heavily on the
importation of research results rather than creating their
own research facilities. Japan is historically such a
case, although today it is planned to double the amount
of per capita income which is spent on research between
1960-1970 from just over one to two per cent. Germany,
currently, is spending very much less on research, even
allowing for its special military position, than either the
U.S. or the UK., and its importation of foreign patents
is very high.
Many developing countries spend less than a i% of
their gross national product on research and develop¬
ment activities whereas in the case or the U.S.A., U.S.S.R.
and U.K. the amount rises from 2.5 to 3 %, a good deal
of this, or course, being for military purposes, but at the
same time having substantial application to industrial
production as a whole. The importance of scientists in
economic growth, like the role of education, was greatly
neglected In the past.
In 1940 there were only 200 doctors
of philosophy in physics in the whole
of the U.S.A., and many less in the
European countries. In 1961 the
annual rate of production of Ph.D.s
in physics was 561.
Today the employment of scientists of all types Is
growing at a rate four times that of over-all employment.
The great expansion of science and development of
technology which is taking place calls for increased
effort in the social sciences. Man is not showing the
same mastery over himself and the problems of his
social and political environment as he is obtaining over
the physical world. The great advance which has taken
place in the last half century in man's power to create
material wealth, and in technology, could, with im
provements of social and political organization, solve In
a few decades the world's problems.
The danger is that technology will steer the ship instead
of providing the motors, and that opportunities for
leisure, culture and the full flowering of the human
genius will become the secondary instead of the pri¬
mary objective. Once again we come back to the concept
of convergence. A great effort is called for in the
social and the human sciences, and in our schools in
improving both the philosophy and the practice of educ¬
ation. In education the factor of quality as well as
quantity must never be overlooked.
The newness of the economic approach to education
calls for special understanding and collaboration between
educators and economists. Education is one of the most
sensitive aspects of national policy, and economists, when
moving into the field of educational planning In company
with educators, have to be closely Informed as to the
social and political as well as the economic aspects of
education.
Some countries regard education policy as too important
to be left to local authorities. Others regard it as too
important to be left to the central authorities.
It would be a strange world in which
we were all educated on a single
system under methods chosen only
for their economic efficiency.
At the same time the task of educational expansion is
so great that it can only be done by eliminating waste in
existing educational systems as well as expanding them.
All this calls for the close International co-operation
which it is Unesco's role to sponsor.
Unesco's has educational planning to the forefront
of its draft programmes and budget for 1965-6, which
includes over $5 million out of Its educational budget.
International aid for education, Including emergency
programmes In Africa and the Middle East, has been In
recent years probably of the order of $130 million
annually; while direct country to country aid has
amounted to about $500 million. The International Bank
for Reconstruction and Development and the International
Development Association have, in their new programme for
aid for education, already granted credits of about $20
million to countries.
But international aid will never be a solution in itself.
It can only be a stimulus and a supplement (though a
vital one) to national effort. The educational budgets of
the developing countries amount annually to about $14
thousand million, and in most countries education Is the
greatest single employer of trained manpower.
The great expansion of education which must take
place will call for millions of new teachers. For the years
1950 to 1970 the developing countries of the world will
probably need more than 700,000 additional secondary
and two-and-a-half million additional primary teachers.
Teachers, despite mechanical advances, remain the life
core of education. The teacher's profession is about
to meet a tremendous and unprecedented challenge.
H. M. Phillips is economic adviser and director of the
Economic Analysis Division of Unesco's Department of
Social Sciences. He is. the author of many studies on
economic and social research in education, on the human
factor in economic development and on demographic and
manpower problems.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
ROSETTA STONE RESEARCH
Sir,
I have recently read the article
"Cleopatra and Ptolemy gave Cham¬
pollion his missing clue" (The Art of
Writing, March 1964 issue) and would
like to mention that although Cham¬
pollion was the first person who
was actually able to read longer
passages and connected texts, credit
should also be given to the Swedish
diplomat, Jean David Akerblad, who
in 1802, in a letter to the French
philosopher Silvestre de Sacy, dis¬
cussed the demotic inscription on the
Rosetta Stones, and in the same year
published an alphabet of the cha¬
racters. If Champollion's alphabet,
published in his Lettre à M. Dacier,
Paris, 1822, be compaied with that
of Akerblad, sixteen of the charac¬
ters will be found to be identical.
The English scientist, Thomas Young
should also be given more credit as
he identified correctly the names of
six gods, and those of Ptolemy and
Berenice; he also made out the true
meanings of several ideographs, the
true values of six letters of the alpha¬
bet, and the correct consonantal
values of three more. As priority of
publication must be accepted as indi¬
cating priority of discovery, the work
of these two men and their contribu¬
tion towards the decipherment should
be more widely accepted.
F. S. Hindmarsh
Tawa, New Zealand
THE ART OF WRITING
Sir,
I have just finished reading your
issue on The Art of Writing. I am
completely captivated by the subject
as you present it and offer my congra¬
tulations on this issue. Every aspect
is clearly explained and the issue is
completely free from pedantry and
abstruseness. Thank you for helping
me to discover, at the age of 17, a
new and passionate interest: the pic-
tograms, ideograms and all the other
interesting and intriguing kinds of
writing.
Françoise Martin
Paris, France
INCA MEMORY AIDS
Sir,
Congratulations on the remarkable
qualities of your magazine and in
particular your issue on The Art of
Writing to which I should like to
add this small item. In the deci¬
pherment of systems of writing used
by different peoples one of the greatest
enigmas concerns the writing of the
Incas.
Did the Incas ever have a system
of writing? Some people have sought
an answer by investigating the mystery
of the Inca quipus (knotted cords)
which are perhaps the strangest and
most original form of written language.
The American historian, Hiram
Bingham, has affirmed that a relatively
simple form of writing was once used
by the scribes of the first Inca dynas¬
ties. When knowledge of this writing
spread among the people, the scribes
maintained that government would
become impossible if the people gained
access to state secrets through this
knowledge. They pursuaded the Inca
kings to abolish this simple script and
to replace it by the system of quipus
which had previously been used solely
for numerical calculations. This was
also the view of the Spanish chroni¬
cler, Montesinos. In "The Socialist
Empire of the Incas", published in
Paris in 1928, Professor Louis Bau-
din describes the quipus as a form
. of "writing" in the broadest sense of
the term.
François Schmitt
Strasbourg, France
Ed note: In the work mentioned
by our reader. Professor Baudin writes:
"The quipu is neither a method of cal¬
culation nor a system of writing; it is
a numerical memory aid." And he
questions the statement by Montesi¬
nos". In a study published in Paris
in 1948, James Février, of the Ecole
Pratique des Hautes Etudes, declares
that the quipus were simply a kind
of memory aid. Ten years later in
a work published in Stuttgart,
L.C. Gelb declares "all the interpre¬
tations of the ancient chroniclers on
the different uses made of the quipus
are completely fanciful."
CHINESE IDEOGRAMS
Sir,
Your issue on the Art of
Writing is a highly interesting one.
Both text and illustrations are valuable.
May I comment briefly on the part
involving Chinese writing. On page
30 the last sentence reads: "The cha¬
racter for Vords' is simply 'mouth'
with several additional strokes." This
is not correct. Professor Bernhard
Kalgren of Sweden describes § as
originally a drawing of a kind or flute.
On page 32, last paragraph, one
reads: "But even earlier, in 1403, the
Koreans had already invented print¬
ing with movable type." This too is
wide of the mark. The Chinese deve¬
loped movable type in the eleventh
century, and the art passed from them
to the Uighur Turks on the west and
the Koreans on the north-east.
L. Canington Goodrich
Dean Lung Professor Emeritus
of Chinese
Columbia University, U.S.A.
MAN THROUGH HIS ART
Sir,
We were very pleased to read about
volume 2 of "Man Through His Art"
in your June issue. This should give
great impetus and interest to this new
series, which we are happy to be dis¬
tributing in the United States.
We noticed in the box on page 24
listing the distributors that our price
for the school edition was omitted.
Could you make a note in The Unesco
Courier that the New York Graphic
Society distributes a- school edition at
$ 5.25 net, as well as the general edi¬
tion at $ 7.95. We would greatly
appreciate it as we know that there
will be great interest in Volume 2,
"Music", as there is in Volume 1,
"War and Peace".
Jean C. Tuton
New York Graphic Society
Greenwich, Connecticut, U.S.A.
CULTURALTHEMES NEGLECTED
Sir,
As a reader of your magazine for
several years I have noticed that more
and more space is being devoted to
science and education, in other words,
to didactic subjects: I know these are
urgent problems and cry out for solu¬
tion, but this has caused you to
neglect cultural and artistic themes.
I must admit that first rate articles
have been published on Tagore, Rous¬
seau, Art in the Life of Man, Stanis¬
lavsky and Shakespeare. But your
scientific articles are not sufficiently
popular in style for the tastes of many
readers, and though the didactic sub¬
jects offer revealing and interesting
facts, they by far outnumber the
occasional articles on art. Artistic
questions are just as important as
social ones, as I am sure you realize.
André Claubart
Paris, France
HELPING YOUTH IN ISRAEL
Sir,
I read with great interest your arti¬
cles about juvenile delinquency, (May,
June and Sept. 1964). Try to write
more about this serious problem of
adolescence and how countries deal
with it.
I am a teacher of a group of the
same sort of children (deprived, ne¬
glected, social cases) in Israel in a
Kibbutz (collective settlement) called
"Sdot Jam". Many of the Kibbut¬
zim try to educate such groups.
In Israel an institution called "Youth
Alija" provides funds for the work
being done with immigrant children
and social cases. Every group has
forty children. They come to us
when they are 13 years old and stay
until they go to the army. In the
beginning they have six hours of les¬
sons and two hours work, but after¬
wards four hours of lessons and four
hours work. They live in nice houses
two to four in a room, and are helped
and taught by a team of three or
four adults, all members of the Kib¬
butz.
I have been working for years with
such groups in the Kibbutzim and
have seen much progress and success
achieved.
Miriam Neeman
Kibbutz Sdot-Jam, Israel
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
' .
ABU BAKR
MUHAMMAD
(AL RAZI)
864-925
A UTHOR of one the greastest medi¬
cal encyclopaedias in the Arabic tongue,
AI Razl, a Persian physician, enjoyed an
uncontested authority in medical matters
until the 17th century. His treatises on
medicine won wide fame in medieval
times and were translated into Latin. A
mathematician and philosopher, he had
a bold and searching mind. In physics
he argued against the Aristotelian theo¬
ries held by certain Muslim scholars of
his day and in chemistry he rejected all
supernatural and symbolistic explanations
that were advanced at that time.
JAGIELLONIAN
UNIVERSITY
CRACOW
J Founded in 1364
HIS year one of Europe's oldest and
most distinguished centres of higher
education, the Jagiellonian University, at
Cracow, Poland, celebrates the 600th
anniversary of its foundation by King
Casimir the Great (above). The university
is named after the 14th century Jagiello¬
nian dynasty which enlarged and endowed
it. During the 15th and 16th centuries as
many as 40,000 students attended its
classes, including the future astronomer
Copernicus (from 1492 to 1494). Its
greatest expansion dates from the past
century and it now has five faculties.
GREAT MEN
=VA=i
On this page we present thumb-nail sketches of a
few of the great men and great events whose anni¬
versaries are celebrated around the world this year.
GEORGE
WASHINGTON
CARVER
1864-1943
« Negro plant chemist, George Wash¬
ington Carver, is one of the famous
names In American scientific agriculture.
In a simple laboratory and working
mostly with home-made equipment, he
discovered how to make hundreds of
new products from a few plant3. From
the peanut he made more than 300 pro¬
ducts, ranging from instant "coffee"
and salad oil to soap and Ink. He
conjured 100 more from the eweet po¬
tato, including flour and shoeblacklng.
He also succeeded in making marble
from wood shavings, dyes from clay
and gum from cotton stalks. The 6on of
slave parents, Carver gained a repu¬
tation as a "plant doctor" while still a
child. He earned his way through
school and college and eventually
headed the department of Agriculture ot
Tuskegee Institute, Alabama, where he
spent a total of 46 years. His research
and discoveries 8t Tuskegee brought
him international fame. Carver pur-
suaded the farmers of Alabama to grow
peanuts, pecans and sweet potatoes In
place of cotton. Since then a single
year's peanut crop from the southern
states of the U.S.A. has brought In as
much as $60 million. Carver was a
talented musician and also won Inter¬
national recognition as a painter. In
1940 he gave his life savings towards
setting up a foundation for research In
agricultural chemistry.
CARL OLUF
JENSEN
1864-1934
A precursor of modern cancer research,
this Danish bacteriologist and vete¬
rinary surgeon, born at Copenha¬
gen on March 18, 1864, was the
first scientist to prove that cancerous
tumours could be transferred from affect¬
ed mice to healthy ones by skin grafts.
His discovery gave an entirely new direc¬
tion to research on malignant tumours.
Dr. Jensen devoted much of his life to
the study of contagious diseases in ani¬
mals and did major work on the functions
of the thyroid gland.
RICHARD
STRAUSS
1864-1949
T HE early performances of the sympho¬
nic poems and even the operas which
Richard Strauss, the German composer,
produced between 1880 and 1895 shocked
many of his contemporaries. His striking
musical innovations were regarded as
exaggeratedly modernistic. But time and
growing familiarity with these works have
brought them well-deserved acclaim. Rich¬
ard Strauss who was born on Jjne 11,
1864, is now regarded as one of the
world's major composers and his songs
rank him as one of the great lyric masters.
MIKHAIL
LERMONTOV
1814-1841
BORN 150 years ago on October 3,
1814, Lermontov ranks second after Push¬
kin among the great poets of Russia. It
was Pushkin's death In a duel in 1837
that sparked the young army officer's lite¬
rary career and provoked his first angry
poem against Czar Nicolas I. Exiled twice
for his exposure of social injustice, he
died in a duel at the age of 27. His
novel, "A Hero of Our Times" is justly
considered a masterpiece of world litera¬
ture. Tolstoy, Turgenev, Dostoievsky and
others revered him as a teacher and model.
JOSE G.
ARTIGAS
1764-1850
BORN in Montevideo in June, 1764, José
G. Artigas can rightly be considered as
the father of Uruguayan democracy. In
1810 he joined in the struggle to free the
countries of South America from Spanish
domination. Foremost among his thoughts
was the education of his people. "After
bread," he said, "education Is the people's
first need." Artigas, who kept up a regu¬
lar correspondence with George Wash¬
ington, died in voluntary exile in Paraguay
at the ¡ige of 86.
MIGUEL
DE UNAMUNO
1864-1936
B ORN in Bilbao of Basque descent on
September 29, 1864, Miguel de Una-
muno is one of the great names of
Spanish letters He belonged to the
famous generation of 1898", a writers'
group of "angry young men" which in¬
cluded Azorin. Pío Baroja, Valle Inclán
and Blasco Ibañez. Philosopher, essayist
poet and novelist he wrote on an aston¬
ishingly broad range of subjects. His
philosophical essays "The Tragic Sense
of Life", "The Agony of Christianity", and
"The Life of Don Quixote and Sancho"
brought him international fame. /
Christian philosopher, he was a man of
extraordinary erudition (he was profes¬
sor of Greek at Spain's oldest and most
venerable university, the University of
Salamanca, and later its rector). All his
life he was an individualist and strugg¬
led against dogmatism and intellectual
fetters, fearlessly taking stand on all
public questions. One critic called him
"an oak tree with an owl's head." His
diatribes against the government cost
him his post and he spent two years in
exile. All of Unamuno's works are per¬
meated by an everrecurring themehis
anguish over life and death and man's
longing for immortality. It was this that
drew him to Kierkegaard, his favourite
author, and he learned Danish so as to
read him in the original. Like Kierke¬
gaard, much of modern existentialism
is foreshadowed in Unamuno's writings.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
UNESCO
1965-1966
A special priority
to science
for economic
development
Science as an aid to economic deve¬
lopment has a special priority in the
programme which will be submitted
to the Unesco General Conference when
it meets in Paris on October 20. In this
proposed programme for 1965-1966, Unesco
embarks on an expanded international poli¬
cy in science and plans to give, as a matter
of urgency, increased scientific aid to deve¬
loping countries.
The need for this aid was made clear at
last year's Unscat Conference in Geneva
on the application of science and techno
Unesco ' Unesco-Dominique Roger
Unesco's Executive Board has just assembled for the first time in a new meeting
room that has been built for it in Unesco's H.Q. in Paris. The Executive Board Room
( above right) andan adjoining committee room are the first sections to be completed
in the 4th building now being constructed on Unesco's Paris site. This building
will include 350 offices around six patios below ground level. Above left,
Mr. Rodolfo Baron Castro, Unesco Executive Board chairman (on right) and
Mr. René Maheu, Unesco Director-General, atan Executive Board meeting in May.
logy for the benefit of the world's less-deve- .
loped _ areas. (See The Unesco Courier,
July-Äugust 1963.) As part of its contri¬
bution to the Development Decade launch¬
ed by the United Nations General Assem¬
bly in December 1961, Unesco plans to
devote two-thirds of all funds available for
science from its own science budget
34
The first inte
conference on
THE idea of creating an Inter¬
national voluntary service of
young people to help in technical
assistance programmes was unani¬
mously endorsed by an International
Conference on Youth, in Grenoble,
France, recently. The first inter¬
governmental conference ever held on
youth problems, It was sponsored by
Unesco and the French Government.
If an international voluntary service
of this kind were set up it would
encourage young men and women
from all nations who had completed
their university education to spend
a year or two in developing countries
where their knowledge and skills
could be applied to projects for social
and economic advancement.
Noting that Unesco had already
proposed to study the problems and
possibilities of voluntary service of
this kind, the Conference urged
Unesco to consider carrying out a
pilot project, using volunteers recruited
on a broad international basis. The
Conference hoped this would even¬
tually lead to the regular use of
qualified long-term volunteers- in
Unesco technical assistance pro¬
grammes and particularly in campaigns
against illiteracy.
The Youth Conference, under the
rgovernmental
youth problems
chairmanship of Mr. Moussa Keita,
High Commissioner for Youth and
Sports In the Republic of Mali, dis¬
cussed ways in which all types of
out-of-school education could be
improved to prepare youth for work¬
ing life and leisure, for civic and
social responsibilities and for inter¬
national understanding and co-opera¬
tion.
Delegates, who came from 73
Unesco member states, stressed
the importance of youth's role in the
modern world, an importance under¬
lined by Mr. René Maheu, Director-
General of Unesco, at the opening
of the conference. "Never have young
people been so truly themselves," he
said. "Never have they given such
evidence of their virtues and defects.
Never have they exercised their gifts
to such an extent nor incurred so
many risks as nowadays."
Among other recommendations, the
Conference urged Unesco to set up
an International Committee on Youth
to advise on future programmes, to
send youth leaders and vocational
guidance counsellors to developing
countries to help Improve youth
organizations and services, to convene
regional youth conferences and to
study problems of out-of-school edu¬
cation.
(increased by 57 % compared with 1963-64)
and from extra-budgetary resources to
projects concerned with science and tech¬
nology for economic development. At
the same time it will continue to promote
international scientific co-operation.
While giving new emphasis to science in
its programme, Unesco will also maintain
the high priority it has always accorded to
education, especially since 1960. An out¬
standing feature of its educational plans
for 1965-66 is the proposal to launch an
intensive experimental programme in mass
literacy (see page 4). Other important pro¬
jects in Unesco's programme relate to edu¬
cational planning, teacher training and the
improvement of teaching methods.
In the fields of social and human sciences
Unesco proposes to study some fundamen¬
tal world problems concerned with the pro¬
motion of human rights and the consolida¬
tion of peace. These include racial preju¬
dice, the economic and social problems of
newly-independent and developing countries
and the economic consequences of disarma¬
ment.
In its programme of cultural activities
Unesco will survey problems of artistic
creation in literature and the fine arts and
will continue its efforts for the protection
of the world's cultural heritage. The Inter¬
national Monuments Campaign which it
launched in June 1964 will be continued
through measures to establish international
agreements for the protection of cultural
property. The Major Project on the Mu¬
tual Appreciation of Eastern and Western
Cultural Values will remain a focal point
of its efforts to spread knowledge of cul¬
tural values among different peoples.
In the field of mass communication
Unesco will continue to work for the
exchange and diffusion of ideas through
press, radio, films and television and to
develop the use of these media for educa¬
tion and the promotion of international
understanding.
A budget of $47,460,000 has been pro¬
posed for the programme to be submitted
to the Unesco General Conference. Unesco
should also be able to dispose of just
over $ 46 million from funds provided by
the U.N. Expanded Programme of Techni¬
cal Assistance and the U.N. Special Fund.
These substantial extra resources, will be
used to help developing countries to extend
and improve their educational systems.
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
HAVE YOU READ
these memorable works of world
literature translated into English
and published in the Unesco
Translations Series.
From Africa :
POEMS FROM BLACK AFRICA. Edited by Langston Hughes;
translated from various languages. Indiana University Press,
Bloomington, Indiana, $4.95.
From China:
STORIES FROM A MING COLLECTION, translated from the
Chinese by Cyril Birch. Indiana University Press, Bloomington,
Indiana $3.95; The Bodley Head, London, 18/-.
MENCIUS, translated from the Chinese by W.A.C.H.Dobson.
University of Toronto Press, Toronto, $5.00; Oxford University
Press, London, 25/-.
RECORDS OF THE GRAND HISTORIAN OF CHINA, by Ssu-Ma
Ch'ien, translated from the Chinese by Burton Watson. Colum¬
bia University Press, New York and London. Two volumes:
$20 or £8.
From Greece:
SIX POETS OF MODERN GREECE (Cavafy, Sikelianos, Seferis,
Antonlou, Elytis, Gatsos), translated from the Greek by Edmund
Keeley and Philip Sherrard. Thames and Hudson, London, 21/-;
Alfred A. Knopf, New York, $5.00.
From India :
KRISHNAKANTA'S WILL, a novel by B.C. Chatterjl; translated
from the Bengali by J.C. Ghosh. New Directions, New York.
$1.65.
LOVE SONGS OF VIDYAPATI, translated from the Malthlll by
Deben Bhattacharya. George Allen and Unwln, London, 30/-.
SACRED WRITINGS OF THE SIKHS (ADI GRANTH). translated
from the Pun|abl by Trilochan Singh, Bhal Jodh Singh, Kapur
Singh, Bawa Harkishen Singh, and Khushwant Singh; Intro¬
duction by Sarvepalll Radhakrlshnan ; foreword by Arnold Toyn-
bee. George Allen and Unwln, London, 22/-.
From Indonesia :
LETTERS OF A JAVANESE PRINCESS, by Raden Adjeng Kar-
tinl, translated from the Dutch by Agnes Louise Symmert; pre¬
face by Eleanor Roosevelt. W.W. Norton and Co., New York,
$1.95.
From Israel:
SIBERIA, a poem by Abraham Sutzkever, translated from the
Yiddish by Jacob Sonntag; preface and Illustrations by Chagall.
Abelard-Schuman, London (21/-), New York and Toronto ($5.00).
From Japan :
THE MAKIOKA SISTERS, a novel by Jun'lchlro Tanlzakl; trans¬
lated from the Japanese by Edward Seidensticker. Knopf, New
York, $4.95; Seeker and Warburg, London, 21/-; McCLellan and
Stewart, Toronto, $4.95; Charles E. Tuttle Co., Tokyo, 850 yen.
MODERN JAPANESE STORIES, an anthology; translated by Ivan
Morris, Geoffrey Sargent, Edward Seidensticker and George
Saito. Charles E. Tuttle Co., Tokyo and Rutland, Vermont,
$6.50; Eyre and Spottlswood, London, 30/-.
THE INK-SMEARED LADY AND OTHER KYOGEN, Comic skits
and folkplays, translated from the Japanese by Shlo Sakanlshl.
Charles E. Tuttle, Tokyo and Rutland, Vermont, $2.95.
These books may be obtained from the publishers or
through your local bookseller.
DO NOT ORDER FROM UNESCO
ere to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor In your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors In countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzai, Prest Department, Royal
Aghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Tradco Agencies, 109 Swanston Street, G. P. O.
Box 2324 V, Melbourne C. I. (Victoria); United
Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
8th Floor, McEwan House, 343 Little Collins St.,
Melbourne C. I. (Victoria). (	). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C"., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Seh. 70.-). BELGIUM. Editions "Labor",
342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-Boek-
handel, Belgiëlei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (140 FB) and art slides only; Louis De Lannoy,
112, rue du Troné, Brussels 5. CCP 3380.00. BURMA.
Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road, Ran¬
goon. (	). CANADA. Queen's Printer,
Ottawa, Ont. ($ 3.00). CEYLON. Lake House
Bookshop, 100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Colombo,
2. (	). CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99 Chung¬
king South Rd., Section 1, Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa).
CYPRUS. Cyprus National Youth Council, P. O. Box 539,
Nicosia. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L., Spalena 51 .
Prague 1 (permanent display); Zahrahnici literatura
Bilkova 4, Prague 1. DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard,
Prags Boulevard 47 Copenhagen S (	).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agency. P.O. Box 120,
Addis Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa.
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (	). FRANCE.
Librairie de I'Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7'. CCP.
1 2598-48. (1 0 F.). GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg Verlag,
Rosenheimerstrasse 145, Munich. 8. For the Unesco
Kurier (German ed only) Bahrenfelder-Chaussee 160,
Hamburg-Bahrenfeld. CCP. 276650 (DM 10).
GHANA Methodist Book Depot Ltd . Atlantis Hous,
Commercial St., POB 100, Cape Coast. GREAT BRI
TAIN. See United Kingdom. GREECE. Librairie H.
Kauffmann, 28, rue du Stade, Athens. HONG-KONG.
Swindon Book Co., 64, Nathan Road, Kowloon. HUN¬
GARY. Kultura, P. O. Box 149. Budapest, 62. ICE¬
LAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co. H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9,
Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd. Nicol Road,
Bellard Estate, Bombay 1; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Cal¬
cutta 1 3 ¡Gunfoundry Road, Hyberabad, 1; 36a, Mount
Road, Madras 2; Kanson House, 1/24 Asaf AM Road, P.O.
Box 386, New Delhi, 1; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book &
Stationery Co., 17 Park Street, Calcutta 16, Scindia
House, New Delhi, Indian National Commission Co-ope¬
ration with Unesco, Ministry of Education, for New
Delhi 3. (Rs. 7). INDONESIA. P. N. Fadjar Bhakti
Djalan, Nusantara 22, Djakarta. IRAQ. Mackenzie's
Bookshop, Baghdad. IRELAND. The National Press,
2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (15/).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores 3 5, Allenby Road
and 48, Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv (1 £ 5.50).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour
Street, Kingston. (15/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd.,
6 Tori-Nichome, Nihonbashi. P.O. Box 605 Tokyo
Central, Tokyo. (	). JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous
& Co., Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman.
KENYA. E.S.A. Bookshop, P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole and
Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LUXEMBURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue,
Luxemburg. MALAYSIA. Federal Publications Ltd.,
Times House, River Valley Rd., Singapore (	).
MALTA. Sapienza's Library 26 Kingsway. Valletta. (1 5/-).
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd.. 30, Bourbon
Street, Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid
des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (	). NETHERLANDS.
N. V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague,
(fl. 8). NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES. G. C. T.
Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.) N.V., Willemstad. Curacao.
N.A. (NA fl 4,50). NEW ZEALAND. Government
Printing Office 20, Mnlesworth Street (Private Bag) Wei.
lingston, C 1 Government Bookshops: Auckland (P.O.
Box 5344), Christchurch (P.O. Box 1721), Dunedin P.O
Box 1104) (15/-). NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshops, P.O'
Box 17 4, Lagos ( /-). NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet-
Lille Grense 7 Oslo For the Unesco Courier only: A.S,
Narvesens Litteratur Tjeneste, Stortingsgt. 2 Oslo, Post,
boks 1 1 5 (	). PAKISTAN. The Weit-Pak Publis¬
hing Co. Ltd., Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box 374
56-N Gulberg Industrial Colony, Lahore. PHILIPINES.
The Modern Book Co., 508 Rizal Avenue Manila.
POLAND. "RUCH", ul. Wronia, 23, Warsaw 10
(	). PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Lda. Livraria
Portugal, Ru» do Carmo 70, Lisbon. PUERTO RICO.
Spanish English Publications, Eleanor Roosevelt 115,
Apartado 1912, Hato Rey. RHODESIA & NYA-
SALAND. The Book Centre. Gordon Avenue, Salisbury,
Southern Rhodesia. SUDAN. AI Baihir Bookshop,
P. O. Box 1118, Khartoum. SWEDEN. A/B CE.
Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 1 6,
For the Unesco Courier: Svenska Unescorldet, Vaia-
gatan 1 5-1 7, Stockholm, C (Kr. 1 2) ; SWITZERLAND.
Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse Zurich, Payot, 40, rue du
Marche, Geneva CCP. 1-236. "Courier" only: Georges
Losmaz, 1, rue des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CCP.
1-4811. (Fr. S. 10). Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND.
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue. Bangkok.
(35 ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette. 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Book¬
shop, P.O. Box 145, Kampala. UNION OF SOUTH
AFRICA Van Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Street, P.O. Box 724 Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier
(single copies) only: Central News Agency P.O. Box 103 3,
|ohannesbourg.(RL.50). - UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC
(EGYPT). Librairie Kasr El Nil, 38. rue Kasr El Nil
Cairo. Sub/agent: La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-
Pasha, Cairo. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I, and Government
Bookshops in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Man¬
chester, Birmingham and Bristol. (15/-). UNITED
STATES. Unesco Publications Center, 317 East 34th St,
New York. N.Y. 1 001 6 (Î 5.00) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broadway, New York,
27, N.Y. U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, Moscow.
G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Yugoslovenska Knjlg,
Tzrazije 27, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
THE HIGHEST SCHOOL IN THE WORLD
Khumjung, a village perched at 13.000 feet in the
Himalayas close to the foot of Mt. Everest in the
Sola-Khombu region of Nepal was given its first
school in 1961. The school was set up by Sir
Edmund Hillary, the first victor of Everest (see
page 12). Sherpa children now enjoy the benefits
of primary schooling and even some parents have
joined the classes. Above, a young Sherpa lama
(Buddhist priest) from the Sola region where
the title of lama passes from father to son.
]]>
</page>
</document>
