<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="062393eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
M
JANUARY 1964 (17TH YEAR) - PRICE 1/-STG. ( U.K.) - 30 CENTS (CANADA) - 0.70 F (FRANCE)
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
I J
\
**
SHAPES & DREAMS
OF ASTRONAUTICS
Day-dreaming on the wonders of space explo¬
ration, a Russian boy studies the earth-girdling
patterns of artificial satellites (See page 24)
at a Moscow exhibition. He holds a photo of
Yuri Gagarin, the world's first astronaut.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier
JANUARY 1964
17TH YEAR
Contents
No. 1
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
APN
COVER PHOTO
Arm and leg movements per¬
fectly synchronized, three run¬
ners speed along a Moscow
stadium track in a 5,000-metre
race. Democratic and interna¬
tional by nature, sport has ex¬
panded enormously in the past
half century. But its develop¬
ment has created new condi¬
tions that today call for a
reappraisal of some traditional
ideas and practices (seepage4).
Page
4 SPORT IS EDUCATION
By René Maheu
10 WHAT MAKES THE ATHLETE RUN ?
The meaning of athletic performance
By Roger G. Bannister
20 ETCHCRAFT ON CELLULOID
The magic of Norman McLaren's films
By Anne MacDermot
24 COUNTDOWN FOR SPACE FLIGHT
By E. Aksenov, E. Grebenikov and V. Dyomin
28 NEW TOOLS TO MAP OUR MINERAL WEALTH
Scientific prospecting from land, sea and air
By J.M. Bruckshaw
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
(M.C 63.1.. 187 A)
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7; France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
René Caloz
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani (Moscow)
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Italian Edition : Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Scientific and Cultural
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in Jul/ and Au(ust when
it is bi-monthly ( I I issues a year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German.
Arabic, Japanese, and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed by H.M.
Stationer/ Office, P. O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providinf
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re*
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and 1S0 not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those ol the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier ii indexed monthly In The Readers' Guide to
Periodical Literature published by H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates : I 0/-stg. ; S3.00 (Canada) ; 7.00
French Francs or equivalent. Single copies l/-stg. 30
cents ; 0.70 F.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7'.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
SPORT IS ED
by René Maheu
We publish below extracts from an address given
by M. René Maheu, Director-General of Unesco,
on October 28, 1963 at the conference called in Paris
by the International Council of Sport and Physical
Education. M. Maheu deals with the threat to the
principles of competitive sports created by chau¬
vinism and what has been' called "shamateurism".
These questions were debated by the Council and
also were the subject of a long report by the former
French tennis champion, Jean Borotra. This interna¬
tional conference met on the occasion of the
centennial anniversary of the birth of Baron Pierre
de Coubertin (1863-1937) who was responsible for
the rebirth of the Olympic Games in modern times.
h or the revival of the Olympic Games we have
to thank Pierre de Coubertin who, in 1892
when he was barely 30 years of age, launched the idea
during the jubilee of the Union of French Athletic Clubs.
Two years later the revival was officially proclaimed at
the Sorbonne in Paris, and the first Olympic Games of
modern times took place in Athens in 1896.
"Why did I revive the Olympic Games?" said Coubertin.
"To dignify and invigorate sport, to make it independent
and durable and thus better fitted for its educational role
in the world today; to honour the individual athlete
because of his real value to the community as a stimulus
to physical exercise and to exalt feats that encourage a
healthy competitive spirit."
Coubertin reiterated these ideas, though in more deve¬
loped form, in "The Philosophical Bases of Modern Olym¬
pics," a message which he broadcast from Berlin in August
1935, a year before the 11th Olympic Games.
If, on this occasion, Coubertin was perhaps somewhat
too ambitious in claiming that modern Olympics should
be considered as first and foremost a religion, the reason
was his own fervour. But the other ideas in his Olympic
philosophy form a logical and compact whole of lasting
value which the most lucid minds should make a point
of studying.
Olympics, said Coubertin, postulate the existence and
assembly of an élite of athletes, an élite whose ranks are
open to anyone able to meet a single condition supe¬
riority in sport. The process of selecting this élite itself
implies a broad "democratization" of sport, and, conver¬
sely, the accomplishments of the élite help to popularize
sport among the mass of the people.
Indeed, in a now familiar axiom, Pierre de Coubertin
declared: "If 100 people are to take up physical culture,
50 must already be engaged in sport; if 50 are to practise
sport there must be 20 who specialize; if 20 are to specialize
there must be five capable of superlative feats."
Coubertin affirms too that we have nothing to fear from
these "superlative feats," but that, on the contrary, "it
would be Utopian to try to saddle athletics with a code of
compulsory moderation." Athletes must have absolute
freedom to overstep all bounds. That is why they were
given the vigorous motto, citius, altius, fortius ever
faster, higher and stronger, "the motto of those bold
enough to challenge existing records," in other words to
thrust back the bounds of the hitherto unattainable.
CONT'D ON PAGE 7 © Paul Almasy
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
s
> m
>***
ffr*£
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
A UNIVERSAL SPORT
Sports events have become the great popular spectacles of our time and of these
the most universally appreciated is football. An ancient game, it was played by
the Spartans as early as 500 B.C. In medieval Italy, teams of as many as 27 a side
lined up for matches between cities. A somewhat brawl-like kind of football became
so popular in medieval England that it was eventually banned by law, partly because
it diverted the yeomen from archery practice. It was only restored to legality by
Charles II in the 1 7th century. The skill and excitement of football and the enthusiasm
of its spectators are reflected in these photos. Above, Pelé, the "star" of the Bra¬
zilian team scores a goal. Below, Brazil's goalkeeper, Gylmar, dives across the
goalmouth (the ball rebounded from the post). Right, crowd scene in an African
stadium shows just how popular football has now become on this continent.
Associated Press
i Paul Almasy. Paris
6
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
SPORT IS EDUCATION (Cont'd)
© Keystone
Need for a careful
reappraisal
The moral conduct of athletes must be equal to the
standard of their performance In the field. Pierre de
Coubertin asks them to constitute an "order of chivalry"
which scrupulously observes a code of honour based on
fair play. He counts on the Olympic Games to bring this
home so strongly that not only will the example be
followed at all sports meetings international, national
and local but the spectators too will feel its impact.
For Coubertin the idea of a "truce" was also an impor¬
tant aspect of the Olympics. He saw it as a modern
evocation of the "sacred truce" of antiquity, established
by Iphitos, King of Ells, in agreement with Lycurgus,
which for nearly 12 centuries was respected at Olympia,
so that all quarrels, misunderstandings, factions and
hatreds cease during the Games. The alliance of
enthusiasm with the spirit of fair play found in compe¬
titive sports opens, in natural consequence, the way to
mutual respect and understanding and to friendship Itself.
"Hatred and violence," said Coubertin, "are attributes
of the faint-hearted."
Sport is Indeed an order of chivalry, combining honour
and a code of ethics and aesthetics, recruiting its members
from all classes and all peoples, mingling them In concord
and friendship throughout the length and breadth of the
entire world.
Sport is also a truce. In our technological way of life,
ruled by an inexorable law of toil, in which we arc only
what we 'have, and have only what we earn, sport is the
hallowed pastime, a princely gift to enrich our hours of
leisure. In an era of antagonisms and conflicts, domi¬
nated by the drive for power and by pride, it ls the
respite of the gods in which fair competition ends In
respect and friendship.
Sport, too, is education, the most concrete and the truest
kind of education that of character. Sport is knowledge
because it is only by patient study and self-rcvclatlon
that a sportsman can go from strength to strength.
Sport is culture because the transient movements it
traces in time and space for nothing but the sheer
pleasure of doing so, as Plato has it illuminate with
dramatic meaning the essential and therefore the deepest
and widest values of different peoples and of the human
race itself; it is culture, too, because it creates beauty, and
above all for those who usually have the least opportunity
to feast upon it.
I f there is one unchanging factor in Coubertin's
humanistic concept of sport, from the Paris
proclamation in 1894, his profession of faithright down
to the Berlin message of 1935 his testament it ls unde¬
niably the dual belief that sport is democratic and inter¬
national by nature and vocation. Half a century of extra¬
ordinary development in sport has shown how right he
was on both these points: his words have come true and
his spirit has triumphed.
But is it a betrayal of his memory to point out that this
confirmation and triumph have come about in conditions
which call for a careful reappraisal, and even a bold
revision of certain ideas or practices that he originated?
I personally do not think so; I feel that he, with his
remarkable open-mlndedness, would be the first to under¬
take the necessary reappraisals.
On the first point the democratization of sport does
anyone nowadays not see and realize that this democrati¬
zation, the conditions of urban life and, of course, the
raising of the level of athletic performance, have pro¬
foundly altered the conditions in which the athletic élite
is selected?
The famous axiom remains true: sport needs its cham- 7
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
SPORT IS EDUCATION (Cont'd)
'The champion is no longer an amateur'
pions. But, unless the circumstances are exceptional,
it ls no longer true, as It was in Coubertln's day,
that the champion can emerge, train, establish
himself and give the full measure of his potentialities
which ls properly not only his individual vocation but
also his rôle in society in that state of independence of,
and indifference to, the economic contingencies or rather
necessities of ordinary life which confers what is called
amateur status, and which at the time Pierre de Coubertin
no doubt considered essential to the spirit of the Olympic
Games.
hough amateurism is the right thing for the
general run of those who practise sports, to
try to make amateur status obligatory for the élite of the
sports world means with certain exceptions that prove
the rule imposing falsehood on that élite. In this res¬
pect, we must be honest enough to admit that the ethical
concepts of Pierre de Coubertin relate to a social situation
and a stage in the technical development of sport which
are now out of date.
Nor were they those of Ancient Greece, for apart from
the fact that the democracies of antiquity secured leisure
for their citizens at the price of slave labour, the Olympic
victors were what we today should call "State athletes."
The social conditions and sports technique which gave
Pierre de Coubertin his frame of reference were those of
his timeof Victorian England and, in general, of the
middle-class Europe of the early decades of this century.
Today it is practically impossible for the champion to
emerge from the rank and file of sportsmen unless special
arrangements are made for him to become a State athlete
or a university athlete or an athlete sponsored by some
commercial firm. Strictly speaking, he is no longer really
an amateur at all.
Why should we be so reluctant to admit that he is a
professional? Is an artista painter, musician or writer
disqualified because he receives a fee? Why should we
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
think that money (or some equivalent material gain)
dishonours athletic champions when it does not dishonour
poets?
In point of fact, it is falsehood that dishonours; and
it is high time, in my opinion, to admit what everyone
knows to be the truth; that most champions and budding
champions at best observe only the strict letter of the
outmoded standards of amateur status.
The problem of the champion and the future champion
is not whether or not they are professionals. The real
problem, in practical and social terms, is that while
practising sport for a few years as a virtual profession,
they must at the same time learn another for the not
far distant day when they will no longer be physically
able to keep up the championship standard. This
difficulty is a very real one and deserves the fullest
and most considerate study. Nor will it be easier to
reach a fair solution if we deny the obvious fact that
the champion is obliged to live the life of a professional
athlete.
This is what I wished to say about the first point,
namely the democratization of sport and the training
of its élites. As for the second point internationalism
no one will be surprised, I imagine, that for Unesco this
is a matter of vital importance. Here again we must
have the courage to look squarely at the facts and say
frankly what we see.
Sport has, of course, developed on an extraordinarily
wide scale. It is probably the aspect of modern life
which is most widely encountered throughout the world
the only one, perhaps, which ls common to both
industrialized communities and developing countries. It
is also, in a steadily increasing degree, one of the most
vigorous forces in international relations. There are few
international exchanges, encounters or contacts which
arouse so much mass feeling as sports events.
But though It ls becoming more and more international
in fact, is present-day sport truly international in spirit,
as Coubertin thought and wished it to be? There are,
unfortunately, plenty of reasons to doubt that it is.
In point of fact, nationalism, chauvinism and even racism
are more and more apt to win or should we say lose?
the day in international sports events. The passions
and emotions that these events arouse and that are
amplified and broadcast to the four corners of the
earth by the powerful modern mass media of the press,
radio, television and cinema, arc but rarely inspired,
it must be acknowledged, by the ancient moral law and
social virtues once presided over by Zeus Phlllos, god
of friendship. It is high time to act if we wish to prevent
the Altis of Olympia from degenerating Into the Roman
Circus or the Hippodrome of Byzantium.
LÖPNING KORTDISTANS
in the 19th century by the goalkeeper of an ice-
hockey team. Above, comparative images show
that in the world's oldest sport, running, move¬
ment and style are still the same as in Antiquity.
Photos £> Paul Almasy, Paris
Let my meaning be clear. I am not suggesting
that we should try to curb the emotional
appeal of the sport event, which has become the great
popular drama of our time. This would be absurd, and
for that matter, impossible. One of the functions of such
events, and certainly among the most salutary, ls the
same, though at a much higher degree of intensity, as
that assigned by Aristotle to all drama: the well-known
catharsis, the purging of passions and Instincts. Nor can
there be any question of trying to deprive the athlete of
the admiration he receives, especially from his fellow-
countrymen. Like any other form of excellence, athletic
feats deserve to be admired, and it ls natural for those
who have most in common with the victorious athlete to
feel this unquestionably fine sentiment more strongly
than others.
But just as no sports contest can fall to stimulate
the desire for victory, so none can be without rules and
ethics. It is these rules and the ethics which inspire
them that distinguish sport from the savage struggle for
life whose name is war. It is compliance with these norms
that transforms a feat into a virtue, and since these
norms are. by definition universal, it follows that although
the feat may be ascribed to a given country, the virtue
itself belongs to man.
What is more barbaric than this identification of
the public with the champion, this appropriation by
a nation of the victory won by an Individual or by
a team? These flags, these anthems, these banner
headlines In the newspapers, screaming "Wc won..."
or "National defeat," must surely seem to us a monstrous
exaggeration of the spontaneous reactions of the crowd,
even a shameful exploitation of its most generous
impulses. In any case, this is the opposite of catharsis:
it is nothing less than a return to a primitive outlook.
I think the time has come for an energetic reaction,
including the abandonment of certain practices which
have become part and parcel of the Olympic Games,
either with the consent of Coubertinsuch as the singing
of national anthems or in spite of him such as the
classifications by nations, which, as we know, is not
officially recognized. Only in this way can we hope
to restore sport, and by this I mean sport as a whole,
including athletes, organizers and spectators, to its
international vocation of promoting friendship among the
peoples.
Is this too much to ask? I am certain that Coubertin
would be the first to denounce the deviations from his
creation and the chauvinistic exploitations of it. In
1935 writing about International sports events, he
affirmed: "We must reach the stage where applause on
such occasions and with even greater reason at the
Olympic Games is given purely for the feats themselves,
to the exclusion of any national preference. There
should be a truce to all exclusively national feelings;
these should be, as it were, 'temporarily suspended'."
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
WHAT MAKES
THE
ATHLETE RUN?
by Roger G. Bannister
The following article is
abridged from the ad¬
dress entitled " The
meaning of Athletic Per¬
formance" given by Dr.
Roger G. Bannister at
the recent international
conference called in
Paris by the International
Council of Sport and
Physical Education. An
English track middle-
distance runner, Roger
Bannister was the first
athlete in the world to
run one mile in under
four minutes (in 1954).
A medical doctor, he
is the author of "First
Four Minutes" publish¬
ed in 1955. Right, an
action shot of Roger
Bannister on the track.
POLE VAU LTER Dave
Tork (above) set up a
new world record in
1962 when he cleared
a height of 4.92 metres.
This photo of Tork dur¬
ing a trial jump shows
him at the Instant he
swings over the bar.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Photos O Associated Piosj
HI ow ls it possible to describe the meaning of
what we enjoy, whether it be Mozart, Cézanne
or sport? One would need to be a sociologist and philoso¬
pher as well as a doctor to do justice to this subject. At
the centre is the problem of a mind-body relationship,
and considering our relative ignorance about the workings
both of the body and the mind, it ls hardly surprising
that the relationship between the two of them should
stretch us to our limits of comprehension.
I can still remember quite vividly a time when as a
child I ran barefoot along damp, firm sand by the sea¬
shore. The air there had a special quality, as if it had
a life of Its own. The sound of breakers on the shore
shut out all others, and I was startled and almost
frightened by the tremendous excitement a few steps
could create. It was an intense moment of discovery of
a source of power and beauty that one previously hardly
dreamt existed.
Now a scientist may attempt an objective explanation
of all this. The sense of exercise is an extra sense, or
perhaps a subtle combination of all the others. It is one
which many ignore; although the Englishman has always
had the reputation abroad for playing games with an
intensity he seldom devotes to real life.
When we exercise, small electrical impulses pass all the
time between our contracting muscles, our moving Joints
and our brains. The pattern of the electrical disturbance
in the brain ls presumably a source of pleasure, because,
like that caused by music. It has some interplay with
rhythms inherent in our own nervous systems. But no
explanation ls satisfying that does not take account of
subtler feelings. I think the scientific attempt ls just
about as successful as trying to describe a rose to someone
who has never seen one.
For an athlete the mystery of this simple situation
always remains. He cannot explain it further, or If he
could, he probably would not run well any more. He
would not need to. The paradox is as simple as that.
It ls now some years since I competed in any track race,
and so perhaps now I can make a little more sense out
of it all. Like life, the problems of sport and a sporting
career only make sense In retrospect. What significance
does sport have for the individual? I think, early on,
adolescence can often be a time of conflict and bewilder¬
ment, and these years can be weathered more successfully
if a boy develops some demanding activity that tests to
the limit his body as well as his mind.
Each adolescent has to And this demanding activity
for himself. It may be mountain-climbing, running or
sailing, or it may be something quite different. It may not
even be sport at all. But by absorption in this pursuit,
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
ATHLETE (Cont'd)
Where the losers
are also
the winners
12
he forgets himself and it Alls the void between the child
and the man. And later, when he finds a career or some
other loves, he will be surprised at the extent to which
he has grown. By then, he is no longer in a position to
make the sacrifices which he previously hardly noticed.
The meaning of games as opposed to simple physical
exertion is an even more difficult problem. Our satisfac¬
tion from games is a complex one. We enjoy struggling
to get the best out of ourselves, whether we play games of
skill requiring quickness of eye and deftness of touch, or
games of effort and endurance like athletics. There is a
desire to find in sport a companionship with kindred
people. Friendships which are formed under this
baptism of fire, if I can use that phrase, have a curious
permanence. I know that I have found all these things.
The sportsman can certainly enjoy his sport even if
he has no prospect of becoming a champion. In fact, It
may be thought of in the sense that an unsuccessful
sportsman Is perhaps the truest sportsman of all, because
his love of sport ls for Its own sake and untarnished by
any thought of success.
But the formative influence of sport on character does
not end there. Sooner or later in sport, the serious striver
after some sort of excellence will meet a situation that is
almost too big for him to master. Such situations occur
in ordinary life, and can often be dodged. We can play
hide-and-seek with reality, avoiding facing the truth
about ourselves; but In sport we cannot do this. It shakes
our roots with Its confusing pattern of success and failure.
As a result, sport leads to the most remarkable self-
discovery, of limitations as well as of abilities. This
discovery is partly physical one learns, for example, that
feeling tired does not mean that one ls reaching the limit
of exhaustion. But mainly the discovery is mental and
brought about by the stresses which sport imposes. The
self-discovery ls most rapid if we set out on the early
stages of this journey alone.
In time we learn how far from being self-sufficient we
are, we realize the value of co-operation and assistance
from others. But unless we start out alone, we never learn
the questions others can best answer and those which we
must answer for ourselves.
o many of us, action may not come easily.
We can allow ourselves to be blown along
like leaves in a wind, or on the other hand, we can try
to impose our own will on external events. For all of
us there comes sometime a moment when we are called
upon to face the metaphorical equivalent of a starting
pistol. Trying to bring the finishing tape nearer us, which
we sometimes may do in later life, is the alternative and
direct contrast to what the athlete is attempting to do,
attempting to reach a rather idealistic goal more swiftly.
These are my reasons for reiterating in a modern
context Baron de Coubertln's views of the educational
necessity of sport, as he conceived it, on a universal scale.
There ls no section of any community that cannot benefit,
except the most socially Impoverished one, and even under
these circumstances the prospect of international competi¬
tion may act as a spur to enlightenment and progress.
Physical deformity is not a barrier, as Dr. Guttmann has
shown by his Olympic Games for men and women who
have lost the power and use of their legs, so-called para¬
plegics, giving the Games the name "the Para-Olympics."
Sport is a vital part of maturity too. There may be
deeper reasons for its satisfaction that we hardly dare
y
.4. ' »"'I, ' ¡C
Svenska Turisttrafikforbundet
i'Pfl
ii
pppno
Í«. ,,.., Hi. m « ,i t '
SNAKE OF SKIERS. Last year a record number of 3,886
skiers took part in Sweden's Vasa Ski Race, an annual
commemoration of an Incident in the country's struggle
for Independence led by Gustav Vasa in 1521. Right, skiers
from seven nations set off on this 55-mile race while a
mass of others (top of photo) wait their turn. The record
time for the course (4 hours, 45 minutes, 10 seconds) was
set up in 1 961 . Above, the ramp of the ski jump at Ornskol-
dsvik in Sweden is so close to the town that this skier seems
to be gliding over the roofs. Skl-ing is said to have originated
In Scandinavia and from being simply a means of transport
has now become one of the most popular of winter sports.
admit to ourselves; some reasons that lie locked away In
the more primitive part of our minds. Thoreau once
commented "'the majority of men lead lives of quiet
desperation." We may strap-hang in the morning
travelling to work to reach our polished world of desk-top
size, or we may tighten endlessly nuts on a new motor¬
car, but we all of us must still seek instinctively some of
the freedom our far-off ancestors knew.
The meaning of physical exertion to the Individual ls
difficult to disentangle from its sociological meaning. The
need for adventure may at first have been satisfied by the
struggle for survival. But now that natural dangers have
been mainly conquered, we all of us seek further trials.
And unless men find them, is it not possible that they
may rebel with some form of shocking violence? Is It not
possible that a drift towards crime may be the result of
the thwarting of these impulses? Breathes there a man
with soul so dead that he has lost the urge to impress on
the world some indelible mark of his personality?
In sport man finds a trial for life which is more active
than a game of chess, more exciting than digging his
garden. We have used machines to conquer land, sea
and air. Athletes realize that if this quest for speed ls
worthwhile, it might as well take place too on the
running-track. There we can still feel our bodies have a
skill and energy of their own, apart from the man-made
CONT'D ON PAGE 14
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
13
© Associated Piess
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
ATHLETE (Cont'd)
For the favourite
the heat is always on
machines which they spend their time driving. There
we can fight a pitched battle against the claustrophobia
of our time. The new Don Quixote can tilt a vaulter's
fifteen-foot pole at the crazy windmill of modern life, or
defiantly hurl his fifteen-pound shot.
I believe that a collective restlessness, even violence can
safely extinguish Itself In the games we play. Sport
provides an alternative to the drag of passive leisure. It
provides an outlet for the craving for freedom, an outlet
which will become more Important, the more restricted,
artificial and mechanized our society becomes.
And of all sports, I think, athletics has great advantages.
You can do it in your own time, whether you work during
the day or night. You can choose your own event among
the many which suit dliferent physiques, the long and
thin, the broad and strong. While most ball games
demand great natural aptitude, this, I think, is less im¬
portant than industry and perseverance. Except in terms
of energy and effort, athletics costs no more than a pair
of running-shoes, and no one can say you may not run
faster than this or jump higher than that. The track is
yours and there is no limit.
io far I have talked about the meaning of
'physical exertion and of competition as a
form of self-trial. The excellence of the performance in
absolute standards ls hardly relevant to its value in
character building. It is a relative matter, the victory
being over self and previous performance or over fellow-
competitors of comparable standard rather than against
an arbitrary standard or a record. What is it like to
have the excitement of competitive struggle grafted on
the natural freedom found in movementto champion
the cause of club or country and to have their honour
as well as your own at stake?
What effect does the roar of a crowd of 50,000 people
in a stadium have, crying out for more effort and identify¬
ing themselves with each runner's success or failure?
What does it mean to wait weeks or months for a race
which may last only a few minutes or even seconds to
travel thousands of miles for a few seconds of supreme
exertion. For me, and I think for all athletes, the Olympic
Games have a special place on a plane apart from all
other races, all other competitions, national or inter¬
national. In past, this stems from the authenticity of the
games and from their roots in prehistory.
The ancient Olympic Games, historians have suggested,
emerged from a primitive anxiety lest with winter the
earth might never come to life again. With soil bare
HIGH JUMPER. Va¬
léry Brumel seems to be
floating effortlessly over
the bar as he Clears a
height of 2.27 metres in
the vast Lenin Stadium
at Loujinki, Moscow.
Brumel is world cham¬
pion with a record break¬
ing jump of 2.28 metres.
and food scarce, who could give an assurance that another
year would bring a fresh harvest? The saviour of the
harvest was the person with the magic of victory in him,
the athlete born of Zeus the Sky God. And, for a time,
the simple foot race was the way to choose this man.
Later the search broadened for the man who embodied the
Roman word "virtus," goodness or excellence.
The modern Olympic Games have still tended to pro¬
duce a champion of champions a Numi, a Zatopek, an
Elliot a modern hero, not altogether shorn of magic,
emerging as a symbol of the Games. Wé still need him
as a reminder that both body and mind can fuse in this
highest athletic achievement.
14
INFIRMITY NO HANDICAP
Physical infirmity is not necessarily an insuperable barrier to sporting activity.
Sportsmen and sportswomen, so incapacitated by accidents or serious illness that
any possibility of their entering competitions seemed out of the question, have
regained their physical powers and even improved on their previous performances.
An example of this was seen at the 1952 Olympic Games in Helsinki where a silver
medal for equitation was awarded to a woman rider, Lis Hartel, who eight years
before had suffered a serious attack of polio. It took her years to re-educate the
muscles of her paralyzed legs. Ignoring advice she had herself lifted on to her
horse to recommence her training. Her participation in the Olympics was in every
sense a challenge to adversity and her success was an example and an encourage¬
ment to all physically infirm people. Another example of courage in the face of
physical handicaps are the "Para-Olympics", the sporting events which have been
organized for paraplegics those who have lost the power and use of their legs.
R. Caloz
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
APN
For a moment I want to consider what Olympic competi¬
tion itself means to athletes who are taking part, and to
do this, I divide Olympic athletes, arbitrarily, but I hope
not unkindly, into three groups. The first, those who have
barely secured a place in their national team and are
certain to be outclassed; secondly, those who have a
sporting chance of a medal, and thirdly the favourites for
victory.
The first group with no chance of a medal are, strange
to say, in a way to be envied, for to him whom least, in
a relative sense, has been given, least is expected. Not
that they are indifferent athletes far from It, they have
fought hard to win a place in their team. Though they
are free to experience the Olympic competition, these
athletes perhaps do not savour the real quintessence of
the Olympics.
he athlete with a chance of a medal is happily
placed. He is in a position of strength; he has
nothing to lose and everything to gain. He can respect
and know close rivals. He has suspense, climax and
reactions and will never forget the experience. The public
at large hears about the risks, the international skirmishes
and silly nonsenses. It never hears of the unspoken
understanding that exists between such athletes whose
skill as craftsmen can compel a mutual respect no matter
what their eccentricities of character or disparity in
politics. This has been said often but it can be said again.
At the apex of the pyramid comes the favourite. His
public and press expect a gold medal through him. But it
ls a matter of simple arithmetic that most favourites will
return home without one. I think a favourite who does
not win knows as much as anyone about Olympic spirit.
A favourite for an Olympic title needs stoicism and self-
confidence to bear his burden lightly and shed humour and
good advice over a team that may look to him for
leadership. Perhaps it ls understandable If his joviality
on departure seems a little forced, his llght-heartcdness
a piece of play-acting as he waves from the aeroplane
steps.
In the short space of two weeks his experience is going
to be stretched to the limit of what is tolerable. He will
reveal to himself and perhaps to others unsuspected
weaknesses, but perhaps discover too a new secret
strength. For once in his life he ls utterly alone. This
situation is all Important, immediate and irrevocable. A
lifetime's intensity seems to be packed into a few
moments. The favourite, win or lose, can never be the
same again. And likely as not it may help him to do
something else better.
By the time he has reached this point, if he happens
to be a track middle-distance runner, he will already have
come tantallzlngly close to achieving a mastery over
himself which it Is the aim of every athlete to achieve.
He will have learnt to channel his whole energy, mental
and physical into a few moments. He will perhaps have
mastered the art of finding in himself more than he has
got.
This, like the knack of riding a bicycle, involves a mental
trick. The secret is to lose for a moment one's sense of
proportion. This process, in the greatest athlete, un¬
leashes a will to win that remains locked away in his
rivals. The presence, or absence, of this Is one factor
that sets the razor's edge between victory and defeat.
The other ls some mystical fortune that smiles on a victor
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
ATHLETE (Cont'd)
The athlete who is paid
is no less a sportsman
and which makes those who were defeated curiously
happy for the victor.
For a moment now I want to turn to another aspect of
sport which has I think changed considerably since de
Coubertin's day. This is the extent to which sportsmen
should be encouraged or permitted to risk their Uves.
Qualities of decision and boldness are necessary in all
sports, but boldness can easily become recklessness, even
ruthlessness, and this change spells disaster.
ODAY In some sports risk seems to me to have
overshadowed skill. Eighty-three people were
killed at Le Mans In 1955. A few days before his death
in the Mille Mlglia, the Marquis of Portago summed up his
racing philosophy: "Racing is a vice and as such extre¬
mely hard to give up. One can be at the top one second
but all it requires ls a very small error and one ls very
embrassingly dead the next."
I think such sportsmen are terrified by what they do,
but their fear, Instead of paralysing them, galvanizes them
to fresh action, as sometimes occurs on the battlefield.
Climbing accidents present another problem. A few years
ago, two French students were stranded near Chamonix.
Sixteen climbers risked their lives in rescue attempts
costing more than £150,000.
In searching for a definition of legitimate risk in sport,
certain distinctions must be made. In many sports there
is near criminal negligence by braggarts who underrate
the dangers of fast driving on unknown roads or swim¬
ming beyond warning flags. In Britain there are more
than 3,000 people a year killed In car accidents and 1,000
are drowned. People try to climb mountains equipped
with a bar of chocolate and an orange, or sail tiny craft
they cannot manage. This is folly not sport and should be
condemned.
There is an unhealthy element among spectators in
many of these sports too that is disturbing. In motor-
racing, how many spectators are attracted as much by
the morbid anticipation of disaster as by the skill of the
driver. On a different scale, a small boy once expressed
his profound disappointment after the finish of one of my
races. "He's no good today, he hasn't even fainted," he
said. Was it morbid interest or merely ignorance that led
a woman spectator at Melbourne to exclaim on seeing the
Olympic marathon runners stagger home "the final of this
should be worth watching?"
Having said all this about unnecessary risks, let me
confess that I have respect for sportsmen who, having
16
Although American colo¬
nists played a kind of
baseball as early as 1762,
it is only just over 1 20 years
since It became a popular
game with a standard set
of rules. Today It draws
enthusiastic crowds in
Cuba as well as Japan.
Though swimming is a
sport as old as the most
ancient records of history,
it was not one of the events
in the ancient Greek Olym¬
pic Games, though it was
included in the first Olym¬
pic Games of modern times
in 1896. It has been said
that all living creatures ex¬
cept men and monkeys can
swim by Instinct. Men,
however, have learned as
an art what they lacked by
instinct and have developed
many ways of swimming,
including the backstroke
(left). Olympic events
Include free style, back,
breast and butterfly strokes.
APN
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
J** -
USIS
excluded danger as much as possible, nevertheless risk
their lives in an attempt to extend the boundaries of
human achievement. No one but a fool risks his life
lightly, but thinking men with daring, even if they do not
always advance our practical knowledge of machines or
nature, raise the standard of individual vigour and enter¬
prise upon which the survival of mankind as a species
depends.
The factors which lead a man to stake his skill against .
his life must include factors which are far beyond his own
self-interest. Thoughtful courage cannot and should not
be eliminated from life, and those of us with children must
accept that they will be the better for having faced
danger, and we must if necessary be prepared to see them
do so.
The last decade has covered a strange period in the
history of sport. It has been the emergence of the new
professionalism, not only in the sense of direct and indi¬
rect payment for sports, but also in devoting unlimited
time and energy to sport, to the total exclusion of any
other career which Borotra has rightly deplored.
very country seeks to enhance national près-,
i tige by physical achievements. It may be in'
establishing new jet plane records of speed or altitude,
penetrating the depths of the sea, or scaling the world's
highest mountains. Too few questions seem to be asked
about the means and the motives, provided the end of
national glory is achieved.
Running, less than any other branch of track and field
athletics, perhaps less than any other sport refuses to be
distorted to fit into a pattern of this kind. Eighteen years
ago, when Zatopek first ran 60 quarter miles in 60 seconds
in a single training session, I wondered whether it was still
possible to be an international athlete any more and do
anything except training. But odd as it may seem, no one
has yet proved to my satisfaction that middle-distance
running cannot still be an activity upon which It ls neither
necessary nor desirable to spend unlimited time and
energy.
Fitting sport into the rest of life until one's work
becomes too demanding this is both the burden and Joy
of the old-fashioned amateur, a path which any athlete
is still free to choose, however difficult or rare it may be.
The athlete who chooses to be paid for sport ls no less
truly a sportsman. He too has a choice and often
exchanges some short-term advantages for many long-
term problems. I think it ls our duty to see that he
realizes this.
I think sport will survive the ethical and administrative
problems that now beset it. And the reason is this. Sport
has an individual basis and an Individual meaning, and
is not a national or moral affair. We run not because our
country needs fame, nor yet because we think it ls doing
us good, but because we enjoy it and cannot help our¬
selves. It gives each of us the chance to release a power
that might otherwise remain locked away Inside ourselves.
I am sure that this urge to struggle lies latent in
everyone, and the more restricted our lives become in
other ways, the more necessary it will be to find some
outlet for this craving for freedom. No one can say
"You must not run faster than this or jump higher than
that." The sportsman is consciously or unconsciously
seeking the deep satisfaction, the sense of personal
dignity which comes when body and mind are fully co¬
ordinated and they have achieved mastery over them¬
selves.
For a young man there are still few fields in which such
perfection can be approached and with such momentary 17
If transient finality. For the athlete the human spirit
Is indeed Indomitable.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
S59S
-
P¡3
\i
- »*-
. - % :*"* ~ . . -i- **r»
. , . -"C ^.-*"? r» «*
X . " *á"~..' - Jn'*- " -
v*" *- - - »
i«».*-... -.T «f - *s»
© Associated Press
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
C}-%
Photos © Paul Almasy. Paris
_ .
-
*-!^-¿%¿ tl*»ii« ?»y
*¿*:fl
'¿SsL *»
--?- ..- ti£i
?»i*3r.*.'T**"t*l1
, The ancient Greeks of Olympic times were passion-
" _. ately interested in athletic sport because they saw
*>; in it a means to develop the human body, men's
character and ideals of fair play. But above and
beyond this they loved sport for its grace and beauty.
Greek sculptors have left us countless memorials
, glorifying the movements of the javelin thrower, the
«. discus hurler and the marathon runner. On this
page the arrested motion of modern grace in sport.
h »Sh. Wilma Rud«>lf» known as the "dark gazelle" 1960
Olympic champion who- ran 100 metres in 11.3 sees.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
ON CELLULOID
by Anne MacDermot
With a shrinking world and a growing desire
on the part of all of us to "learn the other
man's language" so we can communicate with each
other, many people look at a shy film-maker who speaks
to people In 53 countries and wonder how he does it.
For more than 20 years Norman McLaren has been work¬
ing out of Canada's National Film Board. In this time he
has produced a stream of short films that have caught
the attention of film audiences all over the world. No-
one can ignore a McLaren film. You are either delighted,
startled, or enraged. And yet their impact is not in
words McLaren speaks without using words and not
in length the films are seldom more than five minutes
long. He does not preach. The purpose of his films?
"To give the Intellect a rest," McLaren says. And yet
these little films do have a message of beauty, of humour,
of peace. More than that, they betray their creator as
"one of the film world's gentlest people."
It all started when he was a young student. Born
in Scotland, in 1914, McLaren went to Glasgow for art
training. Like others at that time, he became fasci¬
nated with. the possibilities of a comparatively new toy
called film. He could not afford a camera so one day
he got hold of an old print, washed off the emulsion
and, taking a brush and coloured inks, painted his own
strip of films directly on the clear celluloid. The re¬
sult, "Colour Cocktail," was awarded a prize by the
acknowledged doyen of British documentaries, John
Grierson. McLaren went to London and with the General
Post Office Film Unit produced a series of short, vivid
films: "Hell Unltd," "Book Bargain," "Mony a Pickle,"
"Love on the Wing."
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
DIRECT ANIMATION
With their direct appeal to
eye and ear, the cartoons
of Norman McLaren have
cut clear across language
barriers in all parts of the
world. In his works,
McLaren speaks, but with¬
out using words, and
draws his cartoons directly
on to the film itself. Left,
the animator at work. His
technique is one of direct
animation for he uses no
camera but simply an ordi¬
nary pen and Indian ink.
Right, McLaren's apparatus
which holds the film while
he draws. It reflects the
image of the figure just
drawn on to the frame on
which he is now working.
The sheet in the background
with numbers indicates the
length of each sequence
of action in the film.
Photos : National film Doard of Canada
He moved to New York and there turned out "Allegro,"
"Sherzo," "Loops," "Rhumba," and "Boogie Doodle." In
1939, John Grierson once again stepped into his life. He
was asked to go to Ottawa where the dynamic Grierson
was building up what is today the Film Board. McLaren
accepted the job as head of the Animation Department,
on condition that he be given freedom to go on experi¬
menting with hand-painted films. In the decade that
followed he was to turn out some of his best-loved films.
What are they like? As the Film Board began to
distribute McLaren's films dozing theatre-goers in such
distant points as Rome, Johannesburg, Washington were
jolted out, of their seats by a small explosion on the
screen in front of them. Showers of sparks, stars and
whirling snowflakes rained down and the audience hardly
had time to catch its breath before the film stopped, as
abruptly as it began, like a giant Roman candle dropping
its last star into the night.
"Fiddle-de-Dee," for instance, is a cavalcade of riotous
colour. The images McLaren has painted on each film-
square, dance and streak across the screen to the wild
accompaniment of an old-time fiddler. "Begone Dull
Care" is a beautiful blues evocation set to the music of
jazz pianist Oscar Peterson. "Hen Hop" is a joyful little
film in which a hen motif leaps and bounds in a tricky
jive step.
McLaren made all of these by working on the film
base, frame by frame, etching, painting, counting squares
to synchronize them with the soundtrack. People inside
and outside the Film Board began coming to see how
he did it. He would show anyone who wanted to learn.
In fact his generous help, even during periods of frantic
production, have made him a legendary figure of thought-
fulness among colleagues (It was Grierson who called
him one of the film-world's gentlest people.) Few have
managed the concentration of hand and eye that go
into McLaren's intricate films. One thing, however, be¬
came apparent.
McLaren's films had a direct and Immediate appeal
to the eye and ear, regardless of language. Also this
one-man film producer had succeeded In turning out
films without the need of cameras, scripting, cutting and
all the other complicated processes that go Into most
cinema production.
In 1949, his abilities were called upon by Unesco. Mc¬
Laren joined a team to work on an experiment In visual
education in West China. Called "The Healthy Village,"
the project was designed to teach people who couldn't
read or write some of the rules of health.
From a cupboard in the Montreal offices of the Film
Board where I visited him, Norman McLaren pulled out
some of the work his pupils did at that time.
"The Chinese have a fine feeling for form," he said,
holding up a strip of film. "They are good draftsmen.
Here's a film strip, for instance, on 'Safe Water - Safe
Food.' "
He held it up to the light and showed the delicate 21
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
ETCHCRAFT ON CELLULOID (Cont'd)
One-man film unit
A SAD, MYSTERIOUS
scene taken from the film,
" A Little Fantasy on a 1 9th
Century Painting". The
film brings to life a well-
known work, "The Isle of
the Dead " by Arnold Bo-
ecklin (a 1 9th century Swiss
painter). It was made on
the basis of a single black
and white drawing which
evolved as different elenv
ents were added or removed
as shooting progressed.
etching against the black surface. In another film, there
were beautiful colours, rich plum and royal blue.
He dug into the box he was holding. "These are
animated drawings, done on rice paper. They show
how a log of wood is cut, carved and made into a plough,
step by step," he explained.
In China, McLaren had supervised 12 artists and
showed them the graphic teaching value of poster, pic¬
ture books, mobile devices, fllmstrips, slides and finally,
animated movies. While McLaren was in China the
big change In government occurred, but he did not leave
the project before a good number of Chinese who had
never seen a film before were given the key to make
their own productions.
Four years later, the government of India called upon
him to give the same kind of lessons. In co-operation
with Unesco, McLaren spent three months in Delhi and
three in Mysore. This time, the emphasis was on prac¬
tical problems and in his Montreal office McLaren
showed me some more samples: "The Rearing of Silk
Worms," "Compost Manure," "The Treachery of the
Money-Lender."
He remembers his students as serious and hard-working.
One of them, a lad named Obaid-al-Haque, later came
to Canada and spent a year with the Film Board.
It was after his trip to India that Norman McLaren pro¬
duced what many consider his most powerful film.
"Neighbours" is not the first film he had made using
a camera (a series of delightful French Canadian folk¬
songs, C'est l'Aviron, La-Haut sur les Montagnes and
Photos: National Film Board of Canada
22
FOLKSONG in the French-
Canadian tradition, " Là-
Haut sur les Montagnes "
was one of a number of
folklore cartoons produced
by McLaren. These were
made by photographing a
series of pastel drawings.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Poulette Grise had been made by photographing a suc¬
cession of pastel paintings) but it was a new technique
for McLaren in that he used live actors and photographed
them In puppet-like movements which give the elfcct of
very violent pantomime.
The film ls McLaren's longest. It runs nine minutes
and tells the story of two neighbours, sitting out in
their back yards, chatting and reading the newspapers
from their respective deckchalrs. The mood changes
when one glances down and notices a pretty little daisy
growing in the grass between them. The other follows
his glance. They both wonder to whom It belongs.
Suspicion, hatred and fear flare up. The men grapple,
attack each other's households, murder the wives and
children and finally kill each other. In the end the
daisy ls blooming in the grass between their graves.
The film ls undoubtedly the powerful comment on
war McLaren Intended it to be. It aroused a storm of
international controversy, taking prizes at international
film festivals but horrlying some audiences.
The next time McLaren used the "plxlllatlon" method
(live figures photographed as for an animated cartoon)
the film was "The Chalry Tale." Audiences once again
chuckled with glee. There was no fighting in this one.
'"Rhythmetlc" ls another favorite and here McLaren
uses cut-outs. Made to Introduce school children to the
business of learning numbers, and perhaps take some of
the bogey out of "Now it's time for our arithmetic lesson",
"Rhythmetlc" is a rollicking little film in which numbers
slide together, add, subtract, meet each other and
re-group to make sums, until suddenly all is upset by a
run-away zero which won't keep in line, sighs, deflates
like a flat tyre, tips like a dizzy egg in an egg-cup.
For La Merle McLaren once again uses a traditional
French folk tune (as in the popular "Fiddle-De-Dec")
and the elegant little film has taken Its share of prizes.
usic has always been as Important to McLaren
as the visual side. It is natural, perhaps, that
he should have found a way of bringing it too under the
supervision of the Individual making the movie. He began
experimenting with two little films, "Dots" and "Loops."
By drawing with pen and Indian Ink along the margin of
35 mm. film, where the soundtrack usually runs, he produc¬
ed his own "music".
"This was a primitive method", McLaren explained
some years ago. "After this we developed a system for
producing a more refined kind of animated sound."
What he had designed was called a "composertron"
and consisted of a complete set of cards representing the
chromatic scale. When the cards were photographed to the
left side of the film, where the soundtrack runs, they
added up to a new kind of "music". The technique had
been evolved to some extent by the Russians, Avzaamov
and Rimsky-Korsakoff, the German, Rudolf Phennlger
and two Englishmen, Jack Elliott and C. E. Buckle,
McLaren used it for several passages in the film, "Bllnklty
Blank", and another Film Board producer, Maurice Black¬
burn, used animated sound as the fourth instrument In
an ensemble for the McLaren film, "Phantasy."
By this time, McLaren's name had become known all
round to the world in film circles. However, he hates
personal publicity and found being famous a drawback.
Like every true artist he is happiest at his own drawing
board. There he continues to touch the imagination of
people all around the world by sending out dancing little
films that cross all boundaries.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
w^^ y eyes watched the clock. The hands pointed
I f I to seven minutes past nine... I heard a loud
whistle and then a steadily Increasing whine; the hull
of the huge ship shuddered as slowly, very, very slowly,
It rose from the launching pad. The struggle between
the rocket and terrestrial gravitation had begun. The
whine was actually no louder than the one you hear in
the cockpit of a jet fighter but in it were countless musical
notes and timbres that no composer has ever written
down and that no human voice and no musical instru¬
ment have yet produced. The giant rocket motors were
creating the music of the future..."
That is Yuri Gagarin's description of the take-off of
spaceship Vostok I as it was boosted into orbit in outer
space.
During the past five years dozens of artificial earth
satellites have been put into orbit, automatic interplane¬
tary stations have been launched in the direction of the
Moon, Venus and Mars, and the first flights have beeri
made In outer space by eleven men and one woman.
All these flights by manned and unmanned space
vehicles would never have been successfully accomplished
without complex and thorough planning and an astrono¬
mical number of calculations by thousands of engineers,
chemists, mathematicians and other specialists.
A spaceship ls boosted into an orbit around the earth
by a powerful multi-stage rocket, each of the stages
being Itself an Independent rocket. The multi-stage
system has many advantages over a single-stage rocket
which wastes some of Its energy since it has to boost not
only itself and the ship it carries but also continue to
carry fuel containers that once they have been emptied
become useless ballast. The most suitable type would
be a huge one-stage rocket that casts off the containers
as the fuel ls used up, but technical difficulties have so
far prevented the design of such a rocket. The one which
comes closest to it is the multi-stage rocket used by the
U.S.S.R. and the U.S.A. It consists of a series of rockets
placed one behind the other; each of them is discarded
when the fuel is exhausted, either automatically or by
a signal sent from the ground.
On the initial stage of its journey the rocket rises verti¬
cally from the pad; then its direction gradually changes
in accordance with a pre-set programme. After a flight
that may last from eight to fifteen minutes the rocket
attains a velocity of about eight kilometres a second; by
this time its flight position is practically horizontal and
thus parallel to the earth's surface.
Bousting a space vehicle into orbit involves loss
' of energy In overcoming the force of gravity.
Average velocity losses at this stage amount to two or
three kilometres a second. For a rocket-carried vehicle
to be put into orbit, therefore, it must develop a speed
which, in the absence of an atmosphere and of gravity,
would be ten or eleven kilometres a second. The power
the rocket must develop to reach this velocity naturally
depends on the weight of the vehicle it is to put into orbit.
For instance. Spaceship Vostok I weighed 4,725 kilogram¬
mes and was put into orbit by rocket motors that deve¬
loped 20,000,000 h.p. ten times the capacity of the Boulder
(Hoover) Power Station In the U.S.A. and three times
that of the Bratsk Power Station in Siberia.
Once the carrier rocket has reached the computed velo¬
city its last stage Is automatically detached from the
spaceship. The ship is now in free fall and from then
on becomes a celestial body whose motion is determined
by the laws of celestial mechanics. It is then said to be
"in orbit."
For a space vehicle to remain in orbit around the earth
it must travel at "orbital velocity" (or "first cosmic velo-
24 city" as Russian engineers term it) which is the minimum
speed at which a body may move without being pulled
back to earth by the force of gravity. Theoretically this
COUNTD
FOR SP
FLIGHT
by Evgeny P. Aksenov,
Evgeny Grebenikov
and
Vladimir Dyomin
THREE, TWO, ONE, ZERO... The Soviet
spaceship, Vostok 1, leaves the launching
pad in this shot which comes from the film,
"The First Voyage Towards the Stars."
APN
velocity is 7,909 metres per second, computed at the earth's
surface. If the programme requires a circular orbit, the
speed of the vehicle will be constant and will depend on
the altitude, as' orbital velocity varies inversely with
altitude.
We know from the laws of celestial mechanics that the
greater the radius of the orbit along which a body travels,
the lower its velocity will be. At the same distance from
the earth as the moon (an average of 384,000 kilometres)
a body in circular orbit would only need to travel at one
kilometre a second. Thus the time taken for each orbit
increases as the distance from the earth's centre increases.
At an altitude of 500 kilometres above the earth the
orbit takes 90 minutes but an orbit equal to that of the
distance of the moon would take roughly a month. If
the velocity of a body moving in space exceeds the orbital
velocity but does not reach the velocity of escape (which
Russians engineers call the "second cosmic velocity," and
which is approximately 11,200 metres a second at the
earth's surface), it will move in an elliptical orbit.
Spaceship Vostok I, launched by the U.S.S.R. on April 12,
1961, had an elliptical orbit with its lowest altitude (peri¬
gee) at 181 kilometres and its greatest (apogee) at 327 kilo¬
metres from the earth. One orbit was made in 89.1 min¬
utes. From these data the velocity of the spaceship is
found to be 7,837 metres per second at the perigee and
7,688 metres per second at the apogee. In other words,
engineers can now design rockets that travel at speeds
seven or eight times greater than the muzzle velocity of a
big gun.
Does the orbit of a space vehicle change as It encircles
the earth a number of times? Many factors do, in fact,
affect the variability of the flight paths, the chief among
them being the shape of the earth. Our planet is not a
true sphere but an oblate spheroid, the equatorial radius
being 18 kilometres longer than the polar radius; its mass
ls not homogeneous since densities are unevenly distri¬
buted and gravitational pull, therefore, is not uniform.
The atmosphere still offers a noticable resistance to
the motion of a body, even at altitudes of between 250 and
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
OWN
300 kilometres where the density of the atmosphere ls no
greater than that of the "vacuum" of a good radio valve.
The continued effect of even such a rarefied atmosphere
causes some changes in the dimensions of the orbit the
ship at such heights loses about two kilometres in altitude
on each orbit so that after circling the earth 80 to
100 times it is brought back into denser layers of the
atmosphere.
Probably the most important factor in the successful
boosting of a space vehicle into orbit (and still more so
for its landing in a pre-determined area) is the exact
observance of the planned flight programme. Mathema¬
tical accuracy must be nothing less than prodigious. The
slightest deviation of the vehicle in flight from the para¬
meters in the programme would lead to errors that cannot
be corrected in outer space a rocket aimed at the moon,
for instance, might shoot past it, or a spaceship re-entering
the atmosphere at too high a velocity might burn up.
LL automatic devices carried by the vehicle
Lmust function perfectly. The following exam¬
ple shows the degree of accuracy required. A satellite Is
to be boosted into an orbit elliptical in shape with a peri¬
gee at 6,640 kilometres and an apogee of 7,140 kilometres
from the earth. If the velocity differs only by 10 metres
per second due to the malfunctioning of the rocket
motors that is, by only twelve hundreths of one per cent
of the velocity there will be a difference of 39 kilometres
in altitude at the apogee.
If, at the time the last stage burns out, the vehicle
differs by one degree from the computed direction, the
perigee will be 25 kilometres less and the apogee 25 kilo¬
metres greater than programmed; this would bring about
vastly different flight conditions and might shift the orbit
from a perfectly safe region into a radioactive zone or
Into the denser layers of the atmosphere.
The many artificial earth satellites that have been
launched by the U.S.S.R. and the U.S.A. have enabled
engineers to design high precision systems of piloting
and delicate control devices that ensured the successful
flights of the first spacemen. These pioneers of space
flights are: Yuri Gagarin, Herman Tltov, Adrian Nlco-
layev, Pavel Popovlch, Valéry Bykovsky and Valentina
Tereshkova (the first space woman) in the U.S.S.R.; Alan
Shepard, Virgil Grlssom, John Glenn, Scott Carpenter,
Walter Schlrra and Gordon Cooper in the U.S.A.
When a spaceship returns to earth It has to be brought
out of orbit and to do this means that Its speed must be
reduced. The methods evolved for this purpose are a
combined application of the laws of celestial mechanics and
the aerodynamics of a body moving at supersonic speeds.
As the vehicle descends it enters the denser layers of the
atmosphere that act as an "air brake". The orbital velo¬
city is reduced by a system of braking rockets (retro-
rockets) whose action combines with the effective use of
atmospheric resistance.
The retrorockets have a thrust opposing the direction
In which the vehicle ls moving; the moment they arc
switched on, therefore, the spaceship must be oriented
so that the rocket nozzles point in the direction of flight.
Re-entry at an altitude of eighty to a hundred kilometres
and at a velocity many times greater than that of sound,
subjects the vehicle to tremendous stresses.
There are two possible types of landinghard and soft.
The rocket ship sent from the U.S.S.R. to the moon in
September 1959 made a "hard" landingIt made contact
with the lunar surface at such a high velocity that it
was destroyed by the impact. Even a hard landing
involves many intricate calculations and must be made
with steering, stabilizing and orienting devices of great
reliability. A matter of a few metres deviation at the
beginning of the vehicle's flight, or a slight variation in
its speed could be fatal and the vessel would never reach
the planet at which it was aimed.
The landings of spaceships with cosmonauts on board
launched since 1961 are examples of "soft" landings. ,_
Most difficult of all is the soft landing of a space vehicle Z5
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
SPACE FLIGHT (Cont'd)
A shower of meteorites
in a pre-determlned area which depends on the retro-
rockets being switched on at an exact moment with the
vehicle in exactly the right position.
The distance travelled by the vehicle during descent ls
very great. Yuri Gagarin's spaceship continued in flight
for half an hour after the "brakes" had been applied;
the U.S. vehicle. Friendshlp-7, landed in the Atlantic
Ocean after the "brakes" had been put on over the
Western seaboard of America. The actual position of the
vehicle and its exact velocity at the time the decelerating
process is put into operation must be determined with
absolute precision. An error of one metre per second
in computing the velocity or of one kilometre in computing
the altitude, would land the vehicle dozens of kilometres
from the appointed spot.
I
26
n the days before the first Sputniks were laun¬
ched, the possibility of encountering meteo¬
rites was considered one of the greatest potential obsta¬
cles to space flight. As ls well known, the earth (or rather
Its atmosphere) is under constant bombardment by a
"cosmic shower", consisting of various-sized particles of
matter coming from outer space.
American scientists have estimated that something like
30,000 meteorites with a diameter of one centimetre enter
the atmosphere daily. The shower of meteorites of one
millimetre in diameter is estimated at 75,000,000 a day
while the smallest particles of all, those less than
0,005 mm., arrive dally in such quantities that It would
require an elghteen-flgure number to express them.
Thus it seems not only probable but absolutely inevitable
for a spaceship to encounter meteorites on its journey.
These generalized figures, however, do not present a true
picture. Calculations have shown that a spaceship in
flight might meet a meteorite with a diameter of half a
millimetre once in fifteen years and one half a centimetre
in size about once in 25.000 years. Although It is theo¬
retically possible for a space vehicle to meet a dangerous
meteorite, this probability Is about as great as that of
someone on earth being struck on the head by one.
Despite the unlikelihood of the danger, spaceships are
nevertheless equipped with "shock absorbers" against
meteorites.
Before a manned flight could be attempted, the intensity
of cosmic, ultra-violet and corpuscular radiation had to
be studied so as to estimate the degree of danger from
them. Cosmic rays possess very great penetrative powers.
If the walls of the pilot's capsule were thin, cosmic rays
would penetrate and produce secondary radiation that
would be harmful to the man inside.
he nature of solar radiation in outer space is
also different from that experienced on earth;
a space flight is made outside the terrestrial atmosphere
that forms man's natural protective screen from the sun
by absorbing most of its ultra-violet rays. Studies of
different kinds of radiation made by artificial earth
satellites put into orbit by the U.S.S.R. and the U.S.A.
have given engineers enough data to design space vehi¬
cles with structural features best calculated to protect
them from harmful radiation effects.
It must be said, however, that the existing rockets are
unfit as yet to protect the spacemen from radiation of
high Intensity and thus the proper choice of space routes
Is still of vital importance.
Rocket flights into outer space enabled the American
scientist James A. Van Allen and the Soviet scientist
S. N. Vernov to study areas close to the earth in which
high-energy particles abound. These regions form several
radiation belts in circumterrestrial space at various dis¬
tances from the earth. Though deadly to man, these
belts, are not, however, continuous, but contain "holes"
over the earth's North and South Poles.
The particles In these radiation belts are of such high
energy that effective protection from them would add
tremendously to the weight of a space vehicle trying to
penetrate them. It has not yet been found practicable
to design such a ship and manned flights have been
confined to orbits between the nearest radiation belt and
the earth. Manned flights to other planets will have to
follow a trajectory that leaves the earth close to one of
the poles.
Another danger that existed has now been overcome by
space vehicle designers. We know that our atmosphere
ls a reliable shield that protects us from meteorites they
burn up or disintegrate when they crash into the atmo¬
sphere at high velocities. A space vehicle could also
become a "meteoric body" if its re-entry were made at
too high a speed; the vehicle's mass is relatively small
and the resistance of the atmosphere could easily
destroy it.
The mechanism of atmospheric resistance is this: any
body moving in the atmosphere pushes particles of air
before it. This "push" is transmitted by molecules of air
from particle to particle, thus providing a signal of the
moving body's approach a signal which travels uniformly
at the speed of sound.
If the body ls moving at a subsonic velocity, the signal
spreads more rapidly than the body moves. Waves like
those caused by throwing a stone in a pond spread
through the atmosphere ahead of the moving body ; they
consist of alternating condensed and rarefied layers
of air.
These rapidly spreading waves provide the air particles
with what might be described as a "warning signal"
about the moving body so that they open up a path for
It as it approaches and flow round it. The body moves
forward, meeting little resistance. Though this descrip¬
tion is somewhat simplified, it comes close to reality when
the body concerned is streamlined.
When a body moves at supersonic velocities an
entirely different situation is created. In this
case the signal announcing its approach is delayed
because the body moves faster than the waves can spread.
A region of densely compressed air forms a cushion in
front of the moving body. On a space vehicle's re-entry
an Impact wave forms ahead of it and the air cushion
builds up between the wave and the vehicle.
The compression of the air brings about a tremendous
increase in the pressure and temperature of the atmo¬
spheric gases. If the velocity of the vehicle is twice that
of sound the temperature reaches 250° C, and if it is six
times that of sound the temperature will rise to 1,800° C.
Describing his re-entry into the atmosphere, Her¬
man Titov spoke of "a mass of fire of the brightest
colours seething round the ship." The kinetic energy of
the rapidly moving body Is expended on the formation of
the impact wave and on heating the air cushion in other
words, it loses velocity. The heat generated in the air
cushion is only partly dispersed in the surrounding
atmosphere, most of it is used to heat up the vehicle.
A spaceship, therefore, must be provided with a protective
shell and the velocity of its entry into the denser layers
of the atmosphere must not exceed a certain limit.
Such is the overall picture, greatly simplified, of the
flight of our present spaceships, the first vehicles to open
up a path into outer space. Spaceships will not retain their
present form, they will be improved and developed as
science and technology progress. It may well be that
spaceships will soon be as different from those we know
today as modern motor cars differ from their prototypes
of the late nineteenth century.
The authors of this article Evgeny Grebenikov and
Vladimir Dyomin, of the Patrice Lumumba University,
Moscow, and Evgeny Aksenov of the Sternberg Astrono¬
mical Institute, Moscow are all specialists in physics and
mathematics.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
RETURN FROM SPACE. Soviet technicians recover capsules containing live animals parachuted
from research rockets after their re-entry into the earth's atmosphere. Thanks to tho giant parachutes
used for these operations the animals come down to a soft landing after their flight into outer spaco.
APN pholos
4 m
il
, i¿ -
.'.K'V
i
..-: «
*ffvfí*J^>?^ "ffT ''f «
27
>W<
.. ./<
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
NEW TOOLS
TO MAP
OUR HIDDEN
MINERAL WEALTH
by J. M. Bruckshaw
28
MAN-MADE GEYSER
A column of water
boiling shoots sky¬
wards from a newly-
drilled well in Reyk¬
javik, capital city
of Iceland. The
water will be con¬
trolled and fed into
the city's hot water
system for commer¬
cial and domestic
heating. From the
Poles to the Tropics,
geophysical and geo¬
logical knowledge
and techniques have
been mobilized to
aid the prospection
for minerals and
other valuable na¬
tural resources hid¬
den underground.
Their success in de¬
tecting underground
water resources has
led to many areas,
particularly those in
Africa, being opened
up for development.
Petur Thomson-World Bank
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
AIRBORNE SURVEYS
The Increasing de¬
velopment of in¬
struments enabling
magnetic, electro¬
magnetic and radio¬
active prospection to
be carried out from
the air has given
vast new scope to
the world-wide
search for hidden
mineral deposits. Air¬
borne geophysical
surveys have achiev¬
ed outstanding suc¬
cess in the search
for oil. The boom
trailing behind the
survey aircraft (right)
contains a magneto¬
meter which is used
to locate and map
the distribution of
rocks with magnetic
properties, such as
strongly magnetic
iron ores like magnet¬
ite, which is often
associated with other
mineral deposits.
Litton Industries. U.S.A.
he search for minerals of Importance to the
community has always confronted man with
major problems. The earlier discoveries, many of them
accidental, were generally of ore bodies outcropping at the
surface or those with a very thin superficial cover which
could be penetrated at little cost by trenching or by shaft
sinking. But once the shallower deposits had been located
and exploited, it became far more costly and difficult to
discover those at greater depths.
Thus it soon became evident that some guidance was
necessary to reduce this cost. Initially this guidance was
obtained from geological knowledge of the characteristics
of the deposit and its environment and from theories of
its genesis and mode of formation. This information and
the detailed study of the surface geology, which could be
extrapolated downwards, indicated the most likely sites
for the discovery of ore deposits, thus resulting in in¬
creased discoveries and reduced costs.
Unfortunately with increasing depth the projection
downwards of the surface geological picture became less
reliable. This is especially the case in the presence of
an unconformity a break In the geological sequence
which can result in there being little or no relationship
between the deeper rocks and those near the surface.
Following earlier sporadic investigations a real effort
was made about 1920 to discover if some of the geophysi¬
cal techniques, which had been found so successful In the
study of the structure and properties of the earth as a
whole could be used on a small scale to reveal similar
information about local geology.
The very promising results obtained, particularly In the
search for oil in the Texas-Louisiana Gulf Coast of the
United States, encouraged further field exploration and the
development of specialized instruments and led to yet
another application of science that has been of economic
benefit ever since.
The methods which were employed In the initial stages,
and which continue in more sophisticated guise up to the
present day, may be regarded as the classical techniques of
geophysics: the study of the earth's gravitational field, of
the earth's magnetic field and of earthquake waves. To
these must be added those methods which employ the How
of direct or alternating current through the earth anda
more recent development the study of the radioactive
properties of rocks.
The first of these methods has led to a knowledge of the
shape and size of the earth and also to modern Ideas of
the structure of continents and oceans. Its use In the
prospection for minerals ls based upon the fact that the
presence of rocks denser than their surroundings leads to
a locally high value of gravity. Thus the ability to
measure in detail very small variations in gravity from
place to place permits deductions concerning the distri¬
bution of densities In the upper few miles of the earth's
crust. In the early days the gravity field was investigated
by the Eötvös torsion balance, but this has now been
superseded by modern gravity meters capable of detecting
variations in gravity of two or three parts in 100,000,000.
The existence of local anomalies in the earth's magnetic
field had long been realized and attributed to the distor¬
tion of the regular field by the presence of rocks of marked
magnetic properties. Indeed, the magnetic method of
prospection was the first to be exploited for economic ends;
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
MINERAL WEALTH (Cont'd)
Underground exploration from the skies
30
shortly after It had been demonstrated that the earth
behaved as an enormous magnet, crude instruments, such
as the miner's dial and the miner's compass Were brought
into use In the search for strongly magnetic iron ores such
as magnetite.
The influence of large magnetic deposits on the magne¬
tic field may sometimes be spectacular, as at Kursk In
Russia where the strength of the field ls increased by a
factor of about five. Many rock formations are slightly
magnetic generally because they contain low concentra¬
tions of magnetite and they also can modify the local field.
Modern field magnetometers are sufficiently sensitive to
detect and measure these effects and to indicate the dis¬
tribution of magnetic material underground.
he study of earthquakes, particularly of the
time of different shock waves through the
earth, has given us a picture of the structure of the earth
as a whole and, in the case of near earthquakes, of the
structure of the continental and oceanic crusts. This has
been possible because, as the shock waves are transmitted
through the earth their paths are changed by reflection
and refraction at boundaries between rocks through which
the waves travel with different velocities.
In seismic prospecting, the earthquake is simulated by
the detonation of a buried explosive charge. The shock
waves travel through the various rocks, undergoing
refraction and reflection as they cross boundaries separat¬
ing rocks of different properties, and are detected at the
surface by carefully placed instruments which, amongst
other things measure the time of transit of the shock
waves from explosion to detector. A suitable analysis
of the data allows the position of the boundaries between
the rocks to be located, revealing the general geological
structure with its patterns of dipping beds, faults, anti¬
clines, synclines, unconformities and other characteristic
formations.
The electrical methods depend for their success upon the
wide range of the electrical conductivities found in rocks
and minerals. When a current is passed through the
ground it distributes itself in such a way that the resis¬
tance to its flow is minimum, I.e. there is a concentration
of current in rocks of high conductivity and a reduction
of current in those of low conductivity. Thus an examina¬
tion of the current distribution allows deductions
concerning the variation of electrical conductivity in the
ground.
The radioactive method was originally developed for the
search for radioactive deposits, but the varying content of
radioactive minerals in rocks enables us to differentiate
between rock types under certain conditions.
The methods already described may be applied In a
variety of ways to search for mineral deposits. Some
minerals have exceptional physical properties which pro¬
duce local distortions of the gravitational or magnetic
field. Examples are the high density of minerals such as
galena, chromite, barytes, etc., which modify locally the
gravity field. The case of magnetite which has large
magnetic properties has already been mentioned, while
many base metal sulphides have excellent electrical con¬
ductivity, which distorts the flow of current through the
ground.
More frequently the mineral sought may have no
exceptional physical property which permits direct loca
tion, but it may be associated with another suitable
mineral. Thus many mineral deposits have magnetite or
other magnetic mineral associated with them which can
be detected by magnetic prospection methods.
Again, gold often occurs in quartz reefs and the low
conductivity of quartz may be used to trace the reefs. In
such cases a geophysical indication is no guarantee that
ore is present but It at least narrows down the number
of sites to be examined.
Frequently ore deposits are genetically related to certain
geological formations, as for example, those resulting from
igneous activity. In this case, and depending on the pro¬
perties involved, one or other geophysical method may be
used to determine the position, size and inclination of the
formation and so limit the potential zone of min¬
eralization.
Finally the deposition of ore may be controlled by local
geological conditions. Ore may be confined to certain
formations, or be associated with rock contacts or with
faults. The local structure is often revealed by the geo¬
physical investigations and thus indicates the most
promising drilling sites. Indeed the search for oil is
reduced to a search for structures with which oil may
be associated, such as an anticlinal trap, a fault trap, etc.
Naturally in this Indirect approach more than one
method may be employed as, in the search for oil where
the magnetic, gravitational and seismic methods all play a
part. Similarly the magnetic and electrical methods are
frequently combined in the search for ore bodies.
Geophysical techniques were developed for use on land
under a variety of conditions ranging from those of the
Louisiana swamps to those in the Arctic. However, the
extension of geological studies to the offshore continental
shelves, and the vast mineral potential of these areas,
encouraged the development of methods for use at sea.
Thus gravity measurements can now be made by means
of underwater gravity meters lowered to the sea floor, and
today, experiments with ship-borne gravity meters giving
a continuous record of gravity along the ship's track are
in progress.
In spite of the great difficulties caused by the motion of
the ship, the sensitivities achieved already approach those
necessary for prospecting.
I| n marine seismic prospecting the situation is
even better since the mobility of ships allows
greater areas to be covered In a given time with a similar
accuracy to that obtained on land. In fact on land the
speed of operation may be severely restricted by rough
topography and by vegetation and the inaccessibility of
some areas.
Accordingly, instruments have been developed for
magnetic, electromagnetic (one of the many electrical
methods) and radioactive prospection from planes.
In addition to the greater speed with which an area
can be surveyed by air, these methods have the further
advantage that a continuous record of the variations in
the field is obtained, whereas on the ground the measuring
instruments are set up at a series of discrete stations
between which estimated values have to be used.
Airborne geophysical surveys have been made exten¬
sively In all parts of the world and will continue for very
many years. Their outstanding success has been achieved
CONT'D ON PAGE 32
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
OIL GUSHER
GOES WILD
A fiery column spouts from a blazing oil well in Venezuela. These spectacular oil fires may blaze
for many months and are often only extinguished by costly and hazardous operations led by 31
one or other of the handful of men in the world capable of mastering such flaming geysers
of oil and gas. In the meantime, millions of gallons of oil have gone up in smoke and flame.
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
*1
%i
».
«c . *i^
Litton Industries. U.S.A.
MINERAL WEALTH (Cont'd)
SEISMIC PROSPECTING. By studying the behaviour of shock waves set up by earthquakes
as they are changed by reflection and refraction at boundaries between different layers of rocks,
geophysicists have obtained a picture of the internal structure of the earth. In seismic prospecting
the earthquake is simulated by a series of explosive charges and the time of transit of the resulting
shock waves to detecting instruments is measured. From the data obtained, a record of the
contour of the earth below with its geological structural patterns is obtained. Here, columns
of earth spout upwards as a series of explosions are set off by seismic prospectors.
Fewer drill holes, more oil
in the search for oil, and the oil industry was responsible
for their development. A very high percentage of all oil
used has been found by the use of these techniques.
The mining industry has taken over the tools developed
for oil exploration but since the war methods especially
adapted to its own needs have been developed. Geo¬
physical prospecting methods find an important use in the
search for underground water resources, and many areas,
particularly In Africa, have been opened up for develop¬
ment as a result.
Recent composite surveys (frequently sponsored by the
United Nations) have included airborne, magnetic, electro¬
magnetic, and radioactive surveys and photogeology. All
available geological and geophysical data have been used
in the search for mineral wealth. The speed with which
these surveys can be carried out makes the system of
extreme value to new countries where an essential part
of establishing a sound economy is the discovery and
exploitation of natural resources. In the completely
different field of civil engineering geophysical methods
have been used for site investigation of dam emplace¬
ments, bridge foundations and tunnels and naturally have
32 added to the certainty of planning.
The main economic advantage of geophysical methods
stems from the fact that their use cuts down the number
of drill holes necessary to examine an area. Drilling gives
by far the most positive information, but it is without
doubt the most expensive method of exploration. By the
use of geophysics the most promising areas are delineated.
It is unfortunate that many formations of no economic
value can produce results Identical with those of an
economic area, and it is obvious that a suitable structure,
revealed by the methods already described, may be barren
of mineral. Some, but not all uncertainty may be
removed by geological and geochemical considerations and,
supplemented by these disciplines, the methods form a
very potent tool.
In the case of oil, wells based upon non-technical
considerations have a success rate of 1 in 30 compared to
1 in 5 or 6 when based on geological and geophysical
investigations. But, as even today the quantity, the qua¬
lity and frequently the nature itself of ore cannot be
determined, there are still some important problems of
exploration to be solved.
j. m. bruckshaw is head of the Geophysics Department
and professor of Applied Geophysics at the Imperial
College of Science and Technology, London.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
MEDICAL SCHOOLS OF
ANTIQUITY
Sir,
In your June 1963 issue, Sir
Leonard Woolley mentions the inter¬
nationalization of medicine in the
ancient Middle East, as well as the
free circulation of medical books
from one country to another. But
he does not mention where the medical
schools were located.
D. Chowry Muthu in his book
"The Antiquity of Hindu Medicine",
1931, writes that the Rig Veda (4000 to
2500 B.C.) gives the names of a
thousand and one medical plants,
as well as [details of] surgery, mid¬
wifery, therapeutics and sanitation.
Sir William Jones is quoted as
having found an "entire Upanishad
on the internal parts of the human
body, with an enumeration of the
nerves, veins and arteries," etc. The
Ayur Veda was said to have been
given from the god Indra to Atreya
who then began a college of physicians,
"whose work, the Atraya Samhita is
the oldest existing work on medicine,
containing 46,500 verses in all."
Susruta was the head of a school
of surgeons in his "Ayur Vedic
University in the city of Benares."
using "101 varieties of blunt instru¬
ments and twenty different kinds of
sharp (instruments)" that have only
been slightly modified in modern
times, also using anaesthetics, steriliz¬
ation etc.
The University of Taxilla was
famous for its medical school. And
the "University of Nalanda had 100
lecture rooms, where 10,000 students
received instruction ; it had six
immense blocks of residential
buildings, each being four stories
high..."
Arthur Johnson
Chicago, U.S.A.
SCORPION MAN OF SUMER
Sir,
The identification of the figure
shown on page 7 of your June 1963
as a scorpion man is in my view an
error. He is merely a priest or perhaps
a dancer wearing a garment with a
train. One of my reasons for saying
this is that Sumerian art only produced
anthropomorphic figures or combined
human-animal figures in the lions at
the Louvre Museum or in Nebuchad¬
nezzar's kudurru in the British
Museum, in which cases all the con¬
trasting features are clearly indicated.
It is clear that the artist responsible
for the lyre or harp ornaments you
reproduce had a good knowledge of
animal anatomy as your illustrations
show. Your "scorpion man" stands on
human legs and this, to me, is a most
telling detail. It is quite possible that
the woven material of his Sumerian
garment consists of a series of thick
braids which to the writer of the
caption suggested the likeness of a
scorpion.
Jos£ Gonzalez Gracia
San Carlos de Barilochc, Argentina
Ed. note : Representations of combined
human-animal figures are a charac¬
teristic feature of Sumerian art.
Purely animalistic art in Sumer was
in itself remarkable but animals
sometimes in a natural form and
sometimes in fantastic guise are
also combined in a variety of decor¬
ative arrangements. One of the
earliest known examples is the tress
pattern used to form the body of a
figure as in the case of the scorpion-
man from the tomb of the King of
Ur, described by Jurgis Baltrusaitis
in his work, "Art Sumérien et Art
Roman" published by Leroux, Paris.
INTERNATIONAL LANGUAGE
CONCLAVE
Sir,
Professor Pei's article, "One
Language for the World?", in the
Nov. 1963 Courier was excellent, but
I missed his usual urgency for
immediate action. Now, with the
United Nations' proposal for an
International Co-operation Year, what
better time for the universal accept¬
ance of an international language
which could be one of the major
efforts during this special year?
Perhaps we could emulate the Roman
Catholic Church. Instead of the
Cardinals, let's lock up representative
linguists from every nation until they
can agree upon an existing language,
whether natural or artificial, that the
world's peoples can start learning
immediately in order to get better
acquainted with one another while
there is still time !
W. W. Ruby Rapsey
Willowdale, Ont., Canada
FIRMER THAN IT SEEMED
Sir,
Well done again, Courier I I mean
the Oct. 1963 issue (Probing the Interior
of the Earth). It was terrifically
interesting to us in Japan, the most
"shaky" country in the world.
I would like to make one record
straight, though. The caption of the
picture on page 27: "photograph of
a swaying building only seconds
before it collapsed" in the 1948
Fukui earthquake is grossly incorrect.
Actually the building didn't collapse
at all. It managed to survive the
earthquake in the same state as
shown in the picture, though badly
scorched. It was later torn down for
reconstruction.
You ask for my qualification of
the statement? My father. Dr. Hideo
Tamama was responsible for the
reconstruction.
Tcluo Tamaina
Sompachl, Ikeda
Osakafu, Japan
AID TO LANGUAGE TEACHING
Sir,
As an English teacher I would be
very pleased to hear from you whether
the articles of the French and English
editions are alike, being in fact
translations from one language into
the other. I should like to use (hem
in my lop forms where learning how
(o (ranslate properly is of main
impor(ance. I have a very modern
classroom for language teaching so
could any articles be made available
on tape, in French, German and
English ?
Rev. J, I*. Mooljinan
Amsterdam, Netherlands
Ed. note : All our language editions
are indeed alike, being trans¬
lations from one language into
another. They therefore can be used
in language classes and are so used
in schools of many countries through¬
out the world, but we do not have
tapes of any of our language editions.
VISITING EDUCATORS IGNORED
Sir,
Sir Herbert Read, distinguished art
critic, writer, poet, aesthctician and
philosopher, visited Australia in June
last year. He arrived in Sydney
unheralded and departed in obscurity,
and apart from a few small adver¬
tisements in the newspapers giving
notice that two of his lectures would
be open to the public, he received
so little press publicity that only a
comparatively few people were aware
of his presence.
It is deplorable that public relations
failed to grasp this prcviouly
unequalled opportunity to culturally
alert the Australian public and give
them the opportunity of benefiting by
the visit of so distinguished a man.
I hope The Unesco Courier, with its
world coverage and its cultural
dedication, will publish this letter and
so alert administrators in other
countries to herald the presence in
their communities of visiting inter¬
national educators, so as to give
benefit to the broadest mass of in¬
habitants, rather than to the selected,
established few.
Oscar Edwards
Sydney, Australia
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
AUSTRALIAN SOLAR HOUSE. Scien-
tists from the University of Queens¬
land., Australia, have successfully experi¬
mented with a one-third normal size solar
house which provides hot water, refrigeration
and air-conditioning from its water-filled
copper-tubing roof and cooking facilities
from solar concentrators which focus rays
of light and heat on to a container of oil.
Further research will now be made with a
family living inside a similar, but full-size
house.
PROTECTING KENYA'S WILDLIFE:
* The Government of Kenya has pledged
itself to conserve the country's natural
resources. A declaration signed by the
Prime Minister, Mr. Kenyatta, states: "The
natural resources of this country its wild¬
life which offers such an attraction to
visitors from all over the world, the beauti¬
ful places in which these animals live, the
mighty forests which guard the water
catchment areas so vital to the survival of
man and beast are a priceless heritage for
the future."
CJ TAMPS GALORE: The world's largest
philatelic collection composed of over
100,000 mint postage stamps issued during
the past 90 years by some 500 countries,
states and postal administrations is being
presented on permanent loan by Britain's
Post Office to the British Museum in
London.
A LL STAR FESTIVAL: A unique pho-
"^^ nograph record brought out by the
Office of the U.N. High Commissioner for
Refugees offering music and songs by 13 of
the world's top recording stars is helping
refugees in many parts of the world. En¬
titled "All Star Festival" this long-playing
record is available through normal trade
channels and all net proceeds are used to
help U.N. refugee programmes including
those run by the U.N. Relief and Works
Agency for Palestine refugees. This 12"
record is priced at $3.98 (mono) and $4.98
(stereo).
«17NGLISH BY TRAIN': Swedish
commuters on the local morning
train from Uppsala to Stockholm can now
take English language lessons arranged by
Uppsala University on two days a week.
Riding in a special coach during their 40-mile
journey, the commuter students converse
in English and are taught useful phrases
for business correspondence.
17 UROPEAN SOCIAL SCIENCE
mj CENTRE: Austria and Unesco have
signed an agreement regarding their respec¬
tive contributions to the European Social
Science Centre set up in Vienna by a
decision of the Unesco General Conference.
The centre will carry out programmes of
comparative research into social and eco¬
nomic structures in European countries.
Themes to be dealt with include the social
consequences and legal aspects of indus¬
trialization and the underdeveloped areas
that exist in economically developed coun¬
tries.
\ SECOND 'BEAGLE' FOR THE
-" GALAPAGOS: A research vessel
fitted out in England for the Charles Darwin
Research Foundation set out in November
for the Galapagos Islands off the coast of
Ecuador. It was here that the Charles
Darwin Research Foundation was set up
by Unesco in 1959 (see The Unesco Cou-
34
ABU SIMBEL TO BE SAVED
PREPARATORY work will soon be under way on the Immense operation of
saving the Nubian temples of Abu Simbel from being engulfed by the
waters of the Nile when the new Aswan Dam Is completed. Through the
efforts of Unesco and Its member states the government of the United Arab
Republic has been able to sign a contract with an International group of firms
that will handle the operation of cutting up the temples and reconstructing
them 210 feet above their present hillside site.
Unesco's campaign to save the Nubian monuments of the Nile Valley (see
The Unesco Courier, Feb. 1960) has already made possible an extensive Inter¬
national programme of excavations, archaeological research and surveys and
the dismantling and removal to safety of smaller temples and monuments.
Various solutions to the outstanding problem of saving the Abu Simbel temples
had been proposed, including a plan to slice them from the hill into which they
were built 3,000 years ago, encase them in concrete boxes and raise these boxes
over 200 feet by giant Jacks (see The Unesco Courier, Oct. 1961). The project
finally adopted to cut up and then re-erect the temples will cost an estimated
$32 million plus a reserve of $4 million.
The United Arab Republic asked Unesco to obtain at least $20,500,000, and
the outstanding difference between this figure and contributions announced
by nearly 50 countries is expected to be covered by the campaign in the future.
The U. A. R. has pledged itself to make good the gap between the sum called
for by the international appeal and the total cost of the operation.
During the first six months of the operation a rivter port will be built 900
yards upstream from the temples, and roads and housing for workers constructed.
Only then will the actual cutting of the temples into sections begin.
RIER, Sept. 1961) to conserve and study
the unique flora and fauna of the islands
which started the train of Darwin's thought
leading to the famous Origin of Species.
The new research vessel has been named
"Beagle" after the ship in which Darwin
visited the Galapagos in 1835.
<EtONE AGE LIFE IN 1963: History
students from Moscow and Leningrad
universities have been finding out exactly
what it was like to live under stone age
conditions. Camping in the East Sayan
Mountains of the Soviet Union, they used
only stone implements, made fire by friction
and hunted animals with crude weapons.
They found it took three hours to light
a fire by rubbing two sticks together and
nine days to make a flint knife. But once
they had made a flint axe, they felled a
pine tree 40 cms thick in 30 minutes.
rp OO FEW NURSES: "It's a fine job but
there should be more of us." This
was the view of all the nurses interviewed
by "World Health," the monthly magazine
of The World Health Organization, which
devoted its December 1963 issue to Nursing
in the World Today. Out of 2,500,000 quali¬
fied nurses in the world today, 750,000
work in the Americas, 780,000 in Europe
and 600,000 in the Soviet Union. Thus
there are only 400,000 for the immense
populations of Africa, Asia and Oceania.
^VORLD BOOM IN TV: One of the
most spectacular developments in
mass media during the past decade has
been in TV. In 1953, North America had
90% of all operating transmitters. Europe,
including the U.S.S.R., had only 7% and
South America and Asia together had only
3%. By 1960, Europe had risen to 55%,
and North America had dropped to 32%.
Asia had 7% and South America 4%.
SWEDISH AID TO AFRICA: Sweden
^ has offered nearly $500,000 to Unesco
to finance projects for extending educational
opportunities for women and girls in Africa.
Projects envisaged include a secondary
school in Tanganyika, scholarships for 300
girls in Ghana, a teacher training college
and a mobile cinema unit in Sierra Leone
and mobile library services in Kenya, Tan¬
ganyika and Uganda.
Flashes...
Despite large-scale malaria eradication
schemes, the World Health Organization
estimates that close on 380 million people
are still exposed to the risk of infection by
this disease. WHO also estimates that
400 million people suffer from trachoma,
which can cause blindness, and that over
10 million are victims of leprosy. ^_
Gastronautics, the science of space
feeding, is becoming a real problem as
men are being launched into space for
longer periods of time. An astronaut's
menu now includes 23 different bite-size .
products and 37 different dehydrated
products.
Unesco will set up a centre in Mexico
for the planning and construction of school
buildings to aid Latin American countries
which are to spend $4,000 million in ten
years in this field.
During the past eight years the number
of the world's daily newspapers has
declined, although total circulation has
increased by 20%; in the same period
radio receivers have increased by 60%
and TV receivers by 200%.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Just published
xv 1964-66 study abroad]
études
'à l'étranger
estudios
en el
extranjero
xsrr
unesco
STUDY ABROAD
New 1964-1966 Edition
The fifteenth edition of "Study Abroad" brings you
the latest information on 130,000 fellowships
offered in 1964 and 1965 by governments, univer¬
sities, foundations and other institutions in over
100 countries and territories.
Fellowships and scholarships are available for
work in virtually all fields of learning and research,
and can be held in almost all parts of the world.
The duration of studies varies from several weeks
to six or seven years.
An invaluable manual for anyone contemplating
study in a foreign country. An indispensable refe¬
rence book for all libraries, universities and infor¬
mation centres. A useful instrument in promoting
educational contacts throughout the world.
N. B. "Study Abroad" will be published only once
every two years. The next edition will appear
at the end of 1 965.
S4, 20/-, 14 F
Where to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made In the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Press Department, Royal
Afghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Tradco Agencies, 109 Swanston Street, G. P. O.
Box 2324 V, Melbourne C. I. (Victoria) ; United
Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
8 th Floor, McEwan House, 343 Little Collins St.,
Melbourne C. I. (Victoria). (A. 15/-). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C*.. Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Seh. 60.-). BELGIUM. Editions " Labor ",
342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-Boek-
handel, Belgiëlei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (100 FB) and arc slides only: Louis De Lannoy,
22, place de Brouckère, Brussels. CCP 3380.00.
BURMA. Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road,
Rangoon. (K. 5.50). CANADA. Queen's Printer,
Ottawa, Ont. ($ 3.00). CEYLON. Lake House
Bookshop, 100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Colombo,
2. (Rs. 9). CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section 1, Taipeh, Taiwan (For¬
mosa). CUBA.Cubartimpex. Apartado 6540, La Ha¬
vana. (2.25 pesos). CYPRUS. Cyprus National
Youth Council, P.O. Box 539, Nicosia. CZE¬
CHOSLOVAKIA. ArtiaLtd., 30 Ve Smeckich. Prague
2. DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard. Prags Boulevard
47 Copenhagen S (D.kr. 12). ETHIOPIA. Interna¬
tional Press Agency. P.O. Box 120. Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa. 2 Keskuskatu.
Helsinki. (Fmk. 540). FRANCE. Librairie de I'Unesco,
Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7'. C.C.P. 12598-48. (7 F.).
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg Verlag, Rosenheimerstrasse
145, Munich. 8, For the Unesco Kurier (German ed
only) Bahrenfelder-Chaussee 1 60. Hamburg-Bahrenfeld,
C.C.P. 276650 (DM 8). GHANA Methodist Book
Depot Ltd. Atlantis House, Commercial St., POB 100,
Cape Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See United King¬
dom. GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28, rue du
Stade, Athens.- HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 64,
Nathan Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY. Kultura, P. O.
Box 1 49. Budapest, 62. ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson
& Co. H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik INDIA. Orient
Longmans Ltd. Nicol Road,, Bellard Estate, Bombay 1 ;
1 7 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 1 3 ; Gunfoundry Road,
Hyderabad, 1 ; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2; Kanson House,
1 /24 Asaf Ali Road, P.O.Box386, New Delhi, 1 : Sub-Depot:
Oxford Book & Stationery Co., 17 Park Street, Calcutta
1 6, Scindia House, New Delhi. Indian National Commission
Co-operation with Unesco, Ministry of Education, for
New Delhi 3. (Rs. 7). INDONESIA. P. N. Fadjar Bhakti
Djalan, Nusantara 22, Djakarta. IRAQ. Mackenzie's
Bookshop, Baghdad. IRELAND. The National Press,
2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores 35, Allenby Road
and 48, Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv (1£5.50).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour
Street, Kingston. Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
(10/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-Nichome,
Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605 Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
(Yen 670). JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub. Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman.
KENYA. E.S.A. Bookshop. P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64. Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole
and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286. Monrovia.
LUXEMBURG. Librairie Paul Brück. 22. Grand-Rue,
Luxemburg. MALAYSIA Federal Publications Ltd.,
Times House, River Valley Rd.. Singapore (M. S 500)
MALTA. Sapienza's Library 26 Kingsway, Valletta. (1 0/-).
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd.. 30. Bourbon
Street, Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid
des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (7 NF.). NETHERLANDS.
N. V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout. 9. The Hague,
(fl. 6). NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES. G.C.T. Van
Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.) N.V., Willemstad. Curacao. N.A.
NEW ZEALAND Government Printing Office 20,
Molesworth Street (Private Bag) Wellington, C. 1 Govern¬
ment Bookshops,: Auckland (P.O. Box 5344). Christ¬
church (P.O. Box 1 721). Dunedin (P.O.Box 1104(10/-).
NIGERIA. CMS. Bookshops, P.O. Box 174, Lagos,
(10/-). NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille Creme.
7 Oslo For the Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narveseni
Litteratur Tjeneste, Stortingsgt. 2 Oslo, Postboks 115
(kr 13.20) PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing Co.
Ltd., Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box 374 S6-N
Gulberg Industrial Colony, Lahore. PANAMA.
Cultural Panameña. Avenida 7a, No. TI-49, Apartado de
Correos 2018. Panama. (D.F. Balboas 3-). PHILLIPI¬
NES. The Modern Book Co.. 508 Rizal Avenue
Manila. POLAND. "RUCH" ul. Wiloza Nr. 46x
Warsaw 10 (Zl. 50). - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade
Lda, Livraria Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon.
PUERTO RICO. Spanish English Publications, Eleanor
Roosevelt 1 1 5, Apartado 1912, Hato Rey. RHODESIA
& NYASALAND. The Book Centre. Gordon Avenue, Sa¬
lisbury, Southern Rhodesia. SUDAN. AI Bashir Book¬
shop, P. O, Box 111 8. Khartoum. SWEDEN. A/B C.E.
Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 1 6.
For The Unesco Courier: Svenska Unescorldet, Vasaga-
tan 15-17, Stockholm, C (Kr. 7.50) ; SWITZERLAND.
Europa Verlag. 5 Ramistrasse Zurich. Payot, 40. rue du
Marché, Geneva C.C.P. 1-23 6. "Courier" only: Georges
Losmaz, 1, rue des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. C.C.P.
1-4811. (Fr. S. 8). TANGANYIKA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop. P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam.
Sukiapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue. Bangkok.
(35 ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette. 469 lit,kill
Caddesi, Beyoglu. Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda
Bookshop. P.O. Box 145, Kampala. UNION OF
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Bookstore. Libri Building,
Church Street, P.O. Box 724 Pretoria. Forthe Unesco
Courier (single copies) only : Central News Agency, P.O.
Box 1033. Johannesburg. (10/-). UNITED ARAB
REPUBLIC (EGYPT). La Renaissance d'Egypte. 9 Sh.
Adly-Pasha, Cairo. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M.
Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I. (10/-).
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications Center,
317 East 34th St, New York. N.Y. 10016. ($5.00.)
and (except periodicals): Columbia University Press,
2960 Broadway. New York, 27, N.Y. U.S.S.R. Mez-
hdunarodnaja Kniga. Moscow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA
Yugoslovenska Knjiga, Terazije 27, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
v* '-
000
yWWwuiiii'
	Ü
ASUR
FROM THE DEPTHS
aul Almasy, Paris
For many years only the upper layers of mineral wealth lying beneath the
ground were exploited by man. Today, geophysical techniques are
helping to reveal unsuspected mineral deposits in the depths of the earth.
(See article, page 28.) They have proved a potent tool in the search for oil to
enable refineries like the one shown here to satisfy growing world needs.
]]>
</page>
</document>
