<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="062352eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
^1 i
é
ice-ian
civilizations
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A time to live...
30 Argentina
Pride of the Pampa
Life on the pampa, the vast grassy plain of
central Argentina, inspired a rich literature
in the nineteenth and early twentieth cen¬
tury, and provided the theme for much of
Argentina's musical folklore. The nomadic
gauchos (cowboys) became legendary
figures, renowned for their horsemanship,
their spirit of independence, and their
physical endurance. Today, with the adop¬
tion of mechanization and modern tech¬
niques of animal husbandry, the way of life
mythified in gaucho literature has been
transformed. Photo shows cattle on the
pampa being vaccinated against foot and
mouth disease.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Courier
A window open on the woríd
Editorial
IN Asia, where Oryza sativa, the most widely cultivated of the
world's rice species, is generally believed to have originated,
many languages use the same expression, "eating rice", to
convey the idea of "a meal" or "eating" in general.
Rice is the staple food of more than a third of mankind. It con¬
stitutes half the diet of one thousand six hundred million people
and another four hundred million rely on it for between a quarter
and a half of their diet. Nine tenths of all rice grown comes from
Asia, and the civilizations of this part of the world have developed
profound links with rice. Despite the fact that, as the French
geographer Pierre Gourou points out in his recently published book
Riz et Civilisation (Rice and Civilization), rice was not a factor in
the emergence of these civilizations (the Chinese and Indian
civilizations existed long before rice acquired its later dominant
position) it is certainly true that rice has influenced, indeed fashion¬
ed, the rites and social structures of these civilizations by the
demands it imposes upon them, including the need for availability
of a large labour force and mastery of the growing environment.
As was stressed during the International Symposium on Civiliza¬
tions Related to Rice Cultivation in Asian Countries (organized by
The Centre for East Asian Cultural Studies in collaboration with
Unesco, which was held in Kyoto, Japan, from 6 to 10 June 1983),
by its physical and spiritual presence rice came to pervade the
vocabulary, the daily life, the literature, the arts and even the
beliefs of the peoples of Asia.
Owing to the constraints of time and space it was clearly impossi¬
ble in a single issue of the Unesco Courier to assess the influence
of rice on all the countries of Asia. We have therefore selected a few
particularly striking examples of the impact of rice on the lives and
minds of the peoples of the region. These include the deep-rooted
notion of the "rice soul", the Tamil festival of Pongal, the
kalapana system of ancient Thailand and the Azolla cult in Viet
Nam.
If a certain emphasis has been given to the impact of rice on myth
and custom, not forgetting its socio-economic implications, our
opening article by professor Monkombu Swaminathan, director of
the International Rice Research Institute, draws attention to the
progress achieved in genetic research on rice thanks to which crop
yields have increased rapidly over the past two decades. The Food
and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations has estimated
that it will be necessary to increase the production of rice by three
per cent annually until the year 2000 merely to keep pace with the
demands of a rising world population.
Cover: a rice-field in Bali (Indonesia).
Photo Amos Schliack © ANA, Paris
December 1984
37th year
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
4
9
14
16
18
20
23
24
27
31
32
34
36
38
The miracle of rice
by Monkombu S. Swaminathan
Rice in myth and legend
by Obayashi Taryo
Krushna the farmer
by Prafulla Mohanti
Pongal
by Guy Deleury
China's 7,000-year-old crop
by Hu Baoxin and Chang Shujia
The god who stole the rice
by Obayashi Taryo
Green winters on the Red River
by Dao The Tuan
A household god
by Lee Kwang-Gyu
A city built on rice
by Srisakra Vallibhotama
'Never eat rice in the dark...'
by Samuel K. Tan
The soul of a people
by Zainal Kling
A 'Plov' is as good as a feast
by Boris V. Andrianov
A touchstone of time and place
by Rafaralahy Bemananjara
Unesco Newsroom
2 A time to live...
ARGENTINA: Pride of the pampa
Published monthly in 28 languages
by Unesco,
The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Malaysian
Korean
Swahili
Croa to- Serb
Macedonian
Serbo-Croat
Slovene
Chinese
Bulgarian
Greek
Sinhala
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French, Spanish
and Korean
ISSN 0041-6278
N° 12 1984- OPI - 84 - 1 - 417 A
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
The miracle of rice
by Monkombu S. Swaminathan
KNOWN to have been cultivated in
parts of India and China for seven
thousand years, rice today is an
integral part of the lives of millions of peo¬
ple throughout the world. Used almost ex¬
clusively as human food, rice constitutes
half the diet of one thousand six hundred
million people; another four hundred
million rely on it for between twenty-five
and fifty per cent of their diet.
Rice is an annual grass of the Oryza genus
and grows in a wide range of environments,
from 50 degrees north latitude to 40 degrees
south latitude and from below sea level to
more than 2,500 metres above sea level.
Although it was originally cultivated in the
humid tropics as a semi-aquatic plant, it is
adapted to a wide spectrum of environmen¬
tal conditions ranging from arid to rather
cold situations.
There are two species of cultivated rice:
Oryza sativa, which is a common rice wide¬
ly grown in the tropical and temperate
zones, and Oryza glaberrima, which grows
in west Africa. Besides these cultivated
species, the genus Oryza comprises about
twenty wild species.
Over time, three sub-species of Oryza
sativa developed: Indica, Japónica and
Javanica. The designation Indica was used
to label the tropical rices and sub-tropical
varieties of India and China, while
Japónica covered the short- and round-
grained varieties of Japan, China and the
Korean peninsula. Javanica was used to
designate the bulu (awned or bearded) and
gundil (awnless or beardless) rices of In¬
donesia. The summer rices, the aus varieties
of eastern India and Bangladesh and the
Iong-panicled and bold-grained rices of In¬
donesia, which showed a high affinity with
both the Indica and Japónica rices, were
classified as an Intermediate Type.
East Asia
39.6 (27.5 %)
U.S
1.2 (0.8 %|
1.3 (0.9 %>
N. Africa W. Asia
0.4 (0.3 %l 0.6 (0.4 %)
Others
2.1 (1.4 %)
N. Africa and
W. Asia
1.1 (0.7 %)
Brazil
6.2 (4.3 %)
West
Pakistan
2 (1.4 %)
India
39.8 (27.6 %)
Bangladesh
10.2 (7.1 %)
Burma
Extremes of climate also led to the for¬
mation of specialized types such as upland
and deep-water rices. Varieties capable of
tolerating salinity, alkalinity or cool night
temperatures also evolved under the com¬
bined forces of human and natural selec¬
tion. There were probably more than one
hundred thousand varieties of Asian rice
before genetic erosion set in shortly after
the Second World War.
The African Oryza glaberrima rices have
a parallel evolutionary pathway to that of
Schematic map showing land devoted to
rice production throughout the world.
The space for each country is roughly
proportional to the area of land (express¬
ed in millions of hectares) planted with
rice. Also shown is each country's
percentage of the world total.
China
34.4 (23.9 %)
Rep, of Korea
1.2 (0.9
Lao People's Dem
0.7 (0.5 %)
%)
. Rep
Japan
2.5 (1.7 %)
4.8 (3.3 %|
Thailand
9.4 (6.6 %)
2.3(1.6%) Central
and East
1.8 (1.3 %)
Dem. Kampuchea
1.3 (0.9 %)
Malaysia
Southeast Asia
34.7 (24.1 %)
Philippines
3.5 (2.4 %)
Subsanaran
Africa	
4.2 (2.9 %)
Sri Lanka
0.8 (0.5 %)
0.7 (0.5 %)
South Asia
54.1 (37.5 %)
Soc. Rep, of Viet Nam
5.4 (3.7 %)
Indonesia
8.9 (6.2 %)
Chart (: Scientific American, New York
Oceania
0.1 (0.1 %)
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Rice-field songs in the Korean peninsula.
To the accompaniment of a drum, the
man standing leads the song and the
others respond in chorus. Folk songs ac¬
company every stage in rice cultivation,
from planting to harvest, andaré often ar¬
ranged into a kind of "show".
their Asian counterparts, although the
history of their cultivation in west Africa is
shorter and their diversity less than with the
Asian rices.
The many varieties of rice thus developed
constituted a valuable pool of germ plasm
which it was essential to collect, classify and
preserve for current and future breeding
programmes.
Shortly after the Second World War,
most Asian countries began to conserve
their cultivars (varieties developed under
cultivation). A number of foreign introduc¬
tions were also included in each national
collection. However, coverage was general¬
ly poor of varieties from the remote areas.
Few wild species were preserved.
Although rice is not indigenous to the
United States, the US Department of
Agriculture (USDA) made serious efforts to
assemble a world collection of rice. The
USDA also funded field collection projects
in India and Pakistan. The conservation ef¬
forts were materially aided by the construc¬
tion of a medium-term cold storage facility
at Beltsville, Maryland in 1957 and the
establishment of the National Seed Storage
Laboratory at Ft. Collins, Colorado in
1958-59. The US rice collection continued
to grow from about 6,000 in 1960 to about
13,000 in 1981.
During the early 1950s, the International
Rice Commission of the Food and
Agriculture Organization (FAO) of the
United Nations attempted to set up three
regional collections for the ecogeographic
races: Indicas in India, Javanicas in In¬
donesia, and Japónicas in Japan. Another
set of deep-water rices was maintained in
Bangladesh. The four collections totalled
1,344 varieties, but the three centres in the
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
The rice plant
Oryza sativa, the world's major cultivated
rice species, was domesticated in Asia
more than 7,000 years ago and over the
centuries differentiated into three
subspecies based on geographic condi¬
tions. These subspecies are indica,
japónica (or sinica) and javanica.
tropics could not adequately maintain the
seed viability without refrigerated storage.
Among the Asian countries, Japan is the
only nation to have had medium and long-
term storage facility since 1965.
When the International Rice Research In¬
stitute (IRRI) began its research operations
in 1961-62, it took on the role of a global
repository and exchange centre. The IRRI
was able to acquire a duplicate set of most
national collections. When the high-
yielding semi-dwarf rices began to spread
quickly in the Asian tropics and to replace
the traditional varieties, fourteen Asian
countries collaborated with the IRRI in
launching systematic field collection opera¬
tions in both the threatened areas and other
remote, hitherto unexplored areas. These
collaborative efforts have added 38,000
samples to national collections and the base
collection maintained at IRRI. The dwind¬
ling wild rices are also a target of conserva¬
tion. Similar efforts by regional centres and
national programmes in west Africa have
added 7,700 African samples to the world's
rice gene pools.
Since 1978 the International Board for
Plant Genetic Resources (IBPGR) has join¬
ed the campaigns by providing some of the
funds. During 1984 the IRRI collection of
cultivars and wild rices totalled 74,000 ac¬
cessions. Thus, the collective efforts of all
concerned have not only saved the rice crop
from genetic impoverishment but have
greatly enriched the gene pools available for
further crop improvement.
Shortly after the IRRI was established,
its seed distribution service and the promis¬
ing sources of desired characters identified
by its staff greatly stimulated the national
rice research programmes to expand their
systematic evaluation projects. Since 1962
the International Rice Germplasm Center at
IRRI has supplied nearly 100,000 seed
packets to rice researchers around the world
in response to more than 3,000 requests.
The number of requests indicates the
magnitude of research experiments being
conducted by rice scientists in different
countries.
The IRRI's systematic evaluation opera¬
tions for a large number of desired traits
were expanded and streamlined in 1974
under the Genetic Evaluation and Utiliza¬
tion (GEU) Programme. Multidisciplinary
teams were organized to seek rice improve¬
ment in eight research areas: agronomic
characteristics (especially grain yield),
disease resistance, insect resistance, grain
and nutritive quality, drought resistance,
adverse soil tolerance, deep water and flood
tolerance, and extreme temperature
tolerance. The magnitude of the IRRI's
GEU programme is indicated by the
30,000-50,000 seed samples drawn from the
Germplasm Center each year. A major
thrust of the GEU programme is to raise
yield levels and to stabilize crop production
in vast rainfed areas where the numerous
subsistence farmers have not benefited
from the semi-dwarf rices, which dominate *
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
§. 'Il
Wkr
BMà
t«
;
â ' *8 il
i .. ;
*
!^^**N.
^fi^î;,*
From land to mouth
1. Ploughing a rice-field in Sri
Lanka.
2. Mechanized planting on a co¬
operative farm in the Democratic
People's Republic of Korea.
3. Replanting rice in Democratic
Kampuchea.
4. Harvesting rice with the sickle in
the valley of Paro, in Bhutan.
5. Añer the rice harvest, villagers of
Java (Indonesia) get together to
make stacks.
6. Winnowing rice in Burma.
7. In Nepal a wooden beam called a
dekhi is used for husking rice.
8. Lunch break in Pakistan.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
The delta region of Bangladesh, con¬
sisting of the mouths of the Ganges and
the Brahmaputra, is an area where rice
farming is difficult because of abrupt
rises in the water level, especially since
embankments are still not widespread.
Farmers in the delta plant deep-water rice
which grows as fast as the water rises and
may reach a height of 6 metres. Current
research is aiming to improve varieties of
rice adapted to flooded land.
the irrigated areas. In recent years several
Asian countries have organized national
GEU programmes.
On an international scale, exchange and
evaluation were greatly expanded by the
establishment of the collaborative Interna¬
tional Rice Testing Programme in 1976.
From 1960 to 1980, average rice yields in
Asia rose by forty per cent and production
by more than sixty per cent, although it
must be remembered that Asia's population
rose fifty-five per cent over the same
period. These improvements in production
are due primarily to increases in yield per
hectare rather than to expansion of areas
cultivated. This has helped to lower the real
price of rice to consumers in several densely
populated countries.
How did the farmers of Bangladesh, Bur¬
ma, China, India, Indonesia, Japan, the
Philippines and other Asian countries
achieve the feat of raising rice production
more in this period of twenty years than in
the whole of the preceding 5,000 years?
Their success can be largely attributed to
five major advances:
1. The introduction of high yielding, semi-
dwarf, modern varieties.
Traditional, tall varieties of rice have a
tendency to "lodge", that is, to fall over
because of wind, rain or the weight of the
grain. The grain rots or is eaten by rats.
Modern semi-dwarf varieties can yield five
tons or more per hectare because their
strong stemsinherited from their Chinese
parents enable them to stand erect and
convert nutrients, water and sunshine into
grain more efficiently. About twenty-five
per cent of the world's rice acreage is now
planted to semi-dwarfs. Many of the new
varieties carry built-in genetic resistance to
a host of insects and diseases. For example,
a gene from a strain of Oryza nivara, from
north central India, has been instrumental
in limiting the ravages of the grassy stunt
virus.
2. The development of strains with short
growth duration which are insensitive to
day-length.
Teams of researchers selectively bred
these traits into the modern rice varieties to
make it possible for farmers to grow two or
three crops where they previously grew only
one crop, and to grow superior varieties at
different latitudes.
3. Cultivation of hybrid rice.
China is the world's pioneer in hybrid
rice production. China now grows more
than seven million hectares of hybrid rice.
Yields are about twenty per cent higher than
those of ordinary semi-dwarfs.
4. Improved irrigation and water
management.
Better availability of water gives farmers
the opportunity of growing two or more
crops per year in the same field.
5. Introduction of new farm-management
techniques.
Yields are higher and farm incomes more
secure because farmers now have improved
implements and mineral fertilizers and bet¬
ter methods of applying them, including in¬
tegrated procedures for pest control and
improved post-harvest technology.
There is a clear need for continued
genetic improvement in rice and advantage
must be taken of what the new technologies
such as tissue culture and genetic engineer¬
ing have to offer. The FAO has estimated
that merely to keep pace with population
rise an annual rate of increase of about
three per cent in rice production will be
needed to the end of this century.
Thanks to the development of early
maturing varieties we can now grow two to
three crops of rice every year provided there
is water and an adequate supply of
nutrients. In fact, in IRRI experimental
fields there is continuous cropping of rice
leading to yields of more than twenty tons
per hectare per year.
In this intensive rice production system a
hectare of land is divided into thirteen plots
because the variety used takes thirteen
weeks to mature from the date of planting.
By staggered planting one crop is harvested
every Monday. After harvesting the plot is
ploughed and planted again on the follow¬
ing Friday. Thus there are as many harvests
as there are weeks in the year.
This is a good demonstration of the
"green power" of the tropics where, thanks
to the abundance of sunshine throughout
the year, green plants can produce food
through the process of photosynthesis.
However, such continuous cropping of rice
can lead to serious problems of pest
epidemics and soil fertility depletion and
must be accompanied by integrated pest
management and balanced nutrient supply.
An old Chinese saying vividly portrays
the green power of tropical rice land. "A
field can look gold, black and green on the
same day". The gold represents the mature
rice crop, which the farmer and his family
harvest early in the morning. The same rice
field looks black around noon because the
family has already ploughed the field in
preparation for the next crop. Late that
afternoon the field looks green because the
family has transplanted a new rice crop.
No wonder that millions of people still
regard rice as a unique gift from God to
mankind.
MONKOMBU S. SWAMINATHAN is a
noted Indian scientist who played a leading
role in the "green revolution" in Asia and has
worked on a wide range of problems in plant
genetics and agricultural research and
development in the last 30 years. Since April
1982 he has been Director-General of the In¬
ternational Rice Research Institute, Los Baños,
The Philippines. He was formerly Director-
General of the Indian Council of Agricultural
Research (1972-1979), Vice-Chairman of the
Protein-Calorie Advisory Group of the United
Nations (1972-1977), and Secretary to the
Government of India in the Ministry of
Agriculture (1979-1980). He is the author of
some 200 scientific papers published in inter¬
national journals.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
RICE
IN MYTH AND LEGEND
by Obayashi Taryo
ALTHOUGH they have different
histories, cultures and societies,
all the countries of east and south¬
east Asia have rice as a common
denominator. It is not simply that these
peoples cultivate rice; they all have
customs, rituals and myths concerning rice
which serve as threads to bind them
together. Rice culture is extremely impor¬
tant as the common inheritance of these
regions.
Myths concerning the origin of rice take
many forms. Some have points in common
with myths related to other crops. One of
these, which is widely current in such parts
of the region as Indonesia and Malaysia,
tells how crops originated from the corpse
of a murdered god or human being. Myths
of this kind often relate that other crops
originated at the same time as rice. In Java,
according to some versions, fruit-bearing
plants originated from the corpse of a
young girl; dry land rice from the navel;
coconut palms from the head and genitals;
www --;:, j'j
Above and below, harvest folk dances
in the State of Gujarat, northwest India.
ripened fruit dangled from both hands, and
fruit originated from the legs and ripened in
the ground. Among the Manggarai people
of Flores Island, it is said that rice and
maize originated from the corpse of a
murdered child. According to the Japanese
classic Kojiki ("Record of ancient mat¬
ters"), compiled in 712 AD, Susanoo slew
the food goddess Ohogetsu-hime.
Silkworms came from her head, rice seeds
from both eyes, millet from both ears, red
beans from her nose, wheat from her
genitals, and soybeans from her buttocks.
Many mountain peoples of the southeast
Asian mainland and islands sacrifice
domestic animals such as water buffalo and
pigs as an agricultural ritual. Some plain-
dwelling peoples of the region, such as the
Lao of Laos, also sacrifice water buffalo.
The motives underlying this practice are
varied. It is believed that the flesh of the
animal is presented to the gods in exchange
for the gods' gift of an abundant rice
harvest. It is also thought that magical
power (mana) contained in animal blood
promotes the growth of plants.
Given the view that death is a premise of
life, animal sacrifice has points in common
with myths that relate the origin of crops
from corpses. In the southeast Asian
islands, myth and sacrifice frequently ac¬
company one another. Yet, on the
mainland, despite the fact that animal
sacrifice is widespread, myths which relate
the origin of rice from corpses hardly ap¬
pear at all.
\nother important form of rice cultiva¬
tion myth refers to the stealing of crop
seeds. These myths are found not only in
east and southeast Asia but are also
widespread among the agricultural peoples
of Africa and the Americas. Furthermore,
these myths are not exclusively tied to rice
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
In a Burmese village, a sheaf of rice is of¬
fered to the guardian spirit of the com¬
munity. The miniature horses are
vehicles in which the spirit is believed to
ride.
In a rice-field in Java (Indonesia) a woman
binds into a sheaf the first heads of rice to
be harvested. Next she will dress the
sheaf in cotton print cloth and carry it
home in her arms as if it were a baby.
cultivation but are also applied to the
cultivation of sorghum in Africa and to
maize in America. In Samoa, taro origin
myths also take this form. In parts of east
Asia, amongst the mountain people of
Taiwan, for example, this stealing motif is
found in myths concerning the origins of
millet.
It is said that the ancestors of the Miao
people of Sichuan, China, did not have the
necessary seed to sow their fields. They set
free a green bird which then flew up to the
rice granary of the heaven god and returned
with the heavenly rice seed and tare. A myth
of the Minahassa region of Sulawesi (In¬
donesia) recounts how a man went up to
heaven and returned to earth with unhulled
rice concealed in a wound in his leg.
A conspicuous feature of the rice cultiva¬
tion rituals of east and southeast Asia is the
frequent appearance of the concept of a rice
soul. The Lamet, slash-and-burn rice
cultivators of Laos, constitute a represen¬
tative example of ancient rice cultivation
rituals which are accompanied by this idea.
They perform rituals which include strict
taboos at each point in the cultivation pro¬
cess, and their concept of the rice soul is
similar to those of many of the peoples in¬
habiting the islands of southeast Asia.
The rice soul is especially important at
harvest-time. The cutting proceeds in such
a way that the rice soul does not escape but
is sent away to the corner of the field. It flies
from field to field, finally arriving at a
sacred field near the hut. This sacred field
is sown before the other fields and
harvested after them. In the other fields, the
kernel of rice is simply squeezed in one's
hand and the unhulled rice is removed. In
the sacred field, however, the rice stalk is
gently cut and bundled in sheaves which
contain the rice soul. From these sheaves
the unhulled rice is taken. It is then used to
sow the sacred field the following year. If
the rice soul escapes, then the rice will not
bear fruit.
Rice cultivation taboos and the concept
of a rice soul are widely found in the archaic
forms of southeast Asian rice cultivation
rituals. In Japan these features are found
notably in the Amami Islands. They are not
at all prevalent in northern Japan, however.
One special characteristic of the rice soul
concept of many peoples is the extreme sen¬
sitivity and susceptibility to injury of the
rice soul. It will quickly flee if injured. This
idea extends as far west as the Munda
people of central India.
In Japan, one example of the rice soul
concept is found in the eighth-century
Bungo fudoki ("Gazetteer of Bungo Pro¬
vince, Kyushu"). It tells the story of an area
called Tano, which in olden times was
broad and fertile. The farmers of this
district developed many rice paddies on this
land which bore an abundant crop. The
farmers made mochi (see article page 20)
and used them as targets for their arrows.
The injured mochi turned into a white bird
and flew to the south. During that year the
farmers died and their fields went to rack
and ruin.
The idea of the fleeing rice soul is also
found among the Khmer, a wet rice
cultivating people. They tell the following
myth: in ancient times, when rice ripened, it
fle\v through the sky and came to rest in a
granary. Thus it did not have to be
harvested. But on one occasion, a young
husband and wife living near the granary
made an unpleasant noise which startled the
god of rice. They then uttered indiscreet
words which offended the god. The god
fled into a narrow opening in a mountain.
Because of the absence of the god of rice,
the people throughout the land starved.
They tried various means of bringing the
god back, but in vain. Finally, someone was
chosen to serve as an envoy to persuade the
god to return, and after many difficulties he
accomplished his mission.
A variety of animals appear in rice
cultivation myths. A legend in which a
crane is the bearer of rice is extremely
widespread in Japan. Myths concerning
some kind of rice-bearing bird are also
prevalent on the mainland and islands of
southeast Asia, and tales citing dogs as the
bearers of rice are found from south China
to Assam. One such legend, from the Han
Chinese of Sichuan, speaks of the after¬
math of a great flood. The survivors of this
flood were without crops and in a state of
desperation. They noticed a dog crawling
out of the flooded fields, and from the rice
CONTINUED PAGE 13
Colour page
Above, a field of rice ripens under a stormy
Nepalese sky. Originally cultivated in the
humid tropics as a semi-aquatic plant, rice
can grow in a diversity of climates ranging
from the hot deserts of Pakistan,' Iran and
Egypt to the high mountains of India and
Nepal.
Photo Marc Riboud © Magnum, Paris
Below, Thai workers bagging rice in a river¬
side godown (warehouse) in Bangkok.
Photo Mike Yamashita © Rapho, Paris
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
On New Year's Day, the chief of a Lisu
village in northwest Thailandscatters rice
on the assembled villagers, thereby
bestowing on them the spiritual virtues
traditionally associated with rice.
Colour page
Above, two Harijan women, with their
children, outside their house which they
have decorated with rice paste to welcome
Lakshmi, the goddess of wealth. The
design represents sprays of rice with
flowers.
Photo © Prafulla Mohanti, Nanpur, India
Below left, legend has it that the first rice to
be brought to Japan was a red variety, and
even today a red variety of rice is still
cultivated in sacredpaddy fields belonging
to the Takuzu Shrine, in Tsushima, and the
Homan Shrine, in Tanegashima. Photo
shows a scene from a famous ritual con¬
nected with the red rice of Tsushima. In the
village of Tsutsu, in Tsushima, there are 15
old families who take it in turns to cultivate
the sacred red rice and to elect one of their
number as leader of the ritual. Each year, a
tanemomidawara, an elaborate rice bale, is
woven from the first red rice to be
harvested and is hung up in the house of
the leader of the ritual. In the middle of the
night of the 10th day of the first month of
the old calendar, the tanemomidawara is
taken down, covered with a ceremonial
robe, and carried in procession from the
house of the leader of the ritual for the
previous year to the house of the new
leader. The villagers line the route and
kneel to worship the sacred object as it
passes preceded by a torch-bearer.
Below right, rice cakes made from red and
white rice.
Photos © The Asian Cultural Centre for Unesco, Tokyo
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 10
seed that clung to the dog's tail they were
able to begin rice cultivation. Their feelings
of gratitude to this dog led them to give it
a portion of the first meal after the harvest.
In east and southeast Asia the connexion
between the rice soul and the gods varies
widely. In Java, for example, the female
deity of rice (sri) is contrasted with the male
deity wisnu or sedana. At harvest time these
two gods are thought of as bride and
groom. Consequently, when the rice buds
appear it is thought that the rice is pregnant.
When the rice is harvested, the rice goddess
and her husband are transported to the rice
granary. They enjoy their honeymoon night
without being disturbed. Thus a new fertile
crop is prepared for. In contrast to this, in
Thailand, the rice deity goes to a shed and
is requested to remain there until the
following year.
Among the Muong people of Viet Nam,
rice is given to the ancestors as well as to the
honoured spirits at the time of the New
Year festival (let). Afterwards the rice is not
only eaten but is also offered to the rice
itself. Thus the rice becomes doubly sacred.
All the gods such as the god of rice, the
rice soul, and the god of the fields figure
largely in these legends. In Japan the gods
connected with rice cultivation are usually
gods who do not always remain in the
fields. They come to the fields only when
the rice is growing. Gods of the mountain
become gods of the field in spring, when
they come down to the rice paddies. In
autumn, after the harvest, they once again
become mountain gods and return to the
mountains for the winter.
This conception of the seasonal comings
and goings of the field gods is important in
understanding Japanese rice cultivation
beliefs. Although I have not come across a
similar concept elsewhere in east and
southeast Asia, in Laos there is the idea that
the spirit of snakes dwells in the fields and
puddles during the rainy season and moves
to the rivers in the dry season.
But times are changing. In east and
southeast Asia rice cultivation rituals which
have been performed in many areas and the
widespread legends about the origin of rice
cultivation are gradually disappearing with
the advance of modernization and changes
in farming techniques. The death of an
elder means the loss of a legend and the
discontinuation of one more annual event.
It is the important task of anthropologists
and folklorists in these regions to record the
abundant content of these rice cultures and
transmit them to future generations.
OBAYASHI TARYO is professor of cultural
anthropology at the University of Tokyo. A
specialist in the cultural history of east and
southeast Asia, he is the author of several
books on mythology, ethnography, and an¬
cient Japanese cultural history. Professor
Obayashi was a participant in the research
project for Studies of Rice Cultivation gnd its
Cultural Aspects in Asia, organized between
1978 and 1983 by the Centre for East Asian
Cultural Studies, Tokyo, with the assistance
of Unesco.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
KRUSHNA
the farmer
by Prafulla Mohanti
KRUSHNA Jena is my childhood
friend. We went to school together
but he left his studies when he was
twelve to help his father with farming. He
belongs to the community of farmers in my
village of Nanpur in eastern India where the
main crop is paddy rice.
Krushna lives in a mud house with a
thatched roof. He is married with five
children, three sons and two daughters. His
father died five years ago and his seventy-
five-year-old mother lives with him.
Krushna is about fifty but looks older. I
remember he had a beautiful complexion.
But now his skin is dark and withered, the
result of working in the sun and the rain.
"Rice farming is a hard task. To work
with soil you have to become soil", he says.
Krushna learned to farm by watching his
father. He is considered a good farmer, and
some villagers ask him to cultivate their
land for them. Traditionally the Brahmins
and those belonging to high castes are not
expected to do manual work. Now the
educated feel that working in the fields is
degrading. So their land is cultivated by
tenant farmers who get fifty per cent of the
produce.
Krushna has almost one and a quarter
hectares of his own land but the plots are all
scattered. Some are three kilometres away
from his house. He also works as a tenant
farmer for several families. The govern¬
ment has a plan for land consolidation and
distribution to enable the farmers to have
their land in one area. But the task is dif¬
ficult as not all the land is irrigated. The
plots near the canal are the most valuable.
Krushna starts ploughing his fields from
the middle of April, which is the beginning
of summer and the new year. The date is
fixed by the village astrologer. The
ploughing is done by bullocks using a
wooden plough made by the village
carpenter. There are no tractors; even if
they were available it would be difficult to
use them because the plots are so small.
"For rice farming a bullock plough is the
best", Krushna says.
Ploughing is an art which his father
taught him when he was ten. But in the sum¬
mer it gets so hot that the land cracks and
ploughing becomes difficult. Some showers
are needed to moisten the land.
A regular supply of water is essential for
rice farming but too much rain can damage
the crop. There is a network of rivers but no
proper irrigation. During the monsoon,
which starts in July and continues till Oc-
Below left, rice paste wall designs in
the Indian village of Nanpur feature
elephants, peacocks and lotus motifs.
(See also colour photo page 12). Below
right, Mahlia Buddha, the village deity
ofNanpur, with his attendant. The deity
is decorated with vermilion paste and a
crown of flowers.
tober, the rivers overflow. If the floodwater
stays for a week it is good for the paddy,
because it leaves a fertile silt which kills the
weeds and stimulates the growth. But when
the floodwater stays longer the paddy is
totally destroyed.
"My old mother is constantly praying to
the gods for the right amount of rain to fall
at the right time."
By the middle of June the land has been
prepared for cultivation. The farmers sow
the seeds and pray for the rain to fall. They
rest for three days, observing the popular
festival of Raja. No work is done and the
villagers eat and play. Raja was originally a
peasant festival to celebrate the wetting of
Mother Earth by the first raindrops of the
monsoon. It symbolizes menstruation and
fertility. It is a particularly enjoyable time
for the unmarried girls. For three days they
live together in one room, singing folk
songs and playing on swings. They wear
new saris and decorate their faces with
sandalwood paste and their hair with
sweet-scented tropical flowers.
Every day Krushna gets up before dawn,
washes his face and feeds his cattle with
straw, husks and rice water, which his wife
regularly stores in an earthen pot. She
sweeps the yards and prepares breakfast for
him and the family. Krushna's breakfast
consists of a bowl of watered rice with chut-
nies and raw onions. He has a patch of land
at the back of his house where he grows
chillies and vegetables. Some days his
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
mother makes rice cakes for the whole
family.
"We eat rice at every meal. In my
childhood we did not eat any chapatis
(unleavened, pancake-shaped bread) made
of wheat flour. We only had puris (fried
wheat cake) for feasts or festivals. But now
wheat is cheaper than rice and many
villagers have started eating it for their
evening meals. At midday we eat boiled
rice, dal (lentils) and vegetables. After
feeding the family my wife puts whatever
rice is left over in water and stores it in an
earthen pot. It is left to ferment and is very
popular during the summer. It is called
pakhala bhata and is delicious when mixed
with yoghurt and lemon juice and eaten
with dried fish and fried spinach."
After breakfast Krushna goes to his
fields. Sidhia Malik the Harijan helps him.
Sidhia has no land of his own and works as
a tenant farmer. Until recently even the plot
on which his house stands belonged to a
high caste villager. Now the government
has passed laws relating to land reform
which gives the ownership of the land to
Sidhia. He worked hard, saved some money
and bought two bullocks. But one died sud¬
denly last year. He has not been able to buy
another and borrows Krushna's animals to
plough the fields. Krushna stops work at
noon. On the way back he bathes in the
Krushna the farmer sitting with his son
at the entrance to his house. Beside his
feet is a sack of rice.
river, washes his animals and gossips with
his friends about farming. He says his
prayers before eating his food and rests un¬
til the sun loses its strength, about three in
the afternoon. He returns to the fields to
work until it gets dark, around six in the
evening when his wife lights the oil lamp to
welcome the night.
He fetches water from the well, feeds the
animals and tethers them in their shed.
While drinking a glass of tea with roasted
rice sprinkled on it he tells his wife about
the day's work and listens to film music on
the radio. Some evenings his friends join
him and he discusses his daughter's wed¬
ding with them. She is seventeen and has
just left school.
"It is not good to keep an unmarried
daughter in the house", Krushna's mother
warns him again and again.
But it is not easy to find a suitable boy.
The parents demand dowries; wrist-
watches, cycles, radios and gold ornaments.
Now that television has come to the towns
it has been included in the dowry.
"If only my son could get a job my
problems would be over."
His eldest son is twenty-four and recently
graduated in arts from the local college. So
far he has not been successful in finding a
job and sits at home doing nothing.
"It's difficult for me to get ready cash,
we eat whatever we grow and very little is
left over to sell. I educated my son so that
he would be able to work in the town and
send me money."
If the rain does not fall at the right time
to germinate the paddy the farmers get
desperate. They have to buy more seeds,
which are expensive. After each harvest a
certain amount of paddy is kept aside to be
used as seeds but often most of it is either
eaten by rats and insects or cooked for
food.
Rice seedlings are cultivated specially for
transplantation and the process needs a lot
of care. First the seeds are sprayed with in¬
secticide and dried in the sun. Then they are
soaked in water for twenty-four hours,
taken out and kept in bamboo baskets.
They are covered with straw and sprinkled
with lukewarm water. Gunny bags are
spread over them. After three or four days .
the seeds begin to sprout. By then the
farmers have prepared special patches of
land with manures and the seeds are sown.
The seedlings take three weeks to grow to a
height of ten centimetres and are ready to be
transplanted. In the meantime the fields are
levelled, the soil must be like mud. The
seedlings are planted in rows, fifteen cen¬
timetres apart. The rice plants need a
constant supply of water, approximately
four centimetres. Two weeks before harvest
the fields are drained dry.
"It takes four months from the day I
plant the seeds until the day of the harvest.
There are lots of problems. If the wind
blows strongly at the time of flowering, the
rice is damaged. Insects eat the plants and
I have to spray them with insecticides,
which are expensive. But we don't use them
after the paddy has come out."
The intense green fields ripple in the
breeze like green waves. Gradually the col¬
our changes to deep green and when the
plants reach a height of a metre or so, they
turn golden yellow. If it is a good crop the
plants bend down under their own weight.
"It gives me a lot of pleasure to see the
fields full of crops. I'm glad that I'm a
farmer so that my family can eat pure food
grown by me. The food we buy is adul¬
terated. The traders mix sawdust with flour
and white oil with cooking oil. In the winter
months I grow lentils, potatoes and
vegetables and sell some of them in the
market. I like market days when I meet my
friends from the other villages. I also grow
a second crop of rice during the dry
season."
Krushna does not know what the green
revolution is. The farmers are encouraged
by the government to use high-yield rice,
fertilizers and pesticides to produce a
second crop. But it can only be achieved
from November until May. A few acres of
irrigated land are cultivated, the rest re¬
mains barren. Previously cow dung was the
only form of manure, but the village
women burned most of it as fuel. Fertilizers
and pesticides are sold in the market place
without any restriction. Most farmers are
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
not aware of the harmful effects they can
have on crops and health. The pesticides are
so poisonous that they have killed off much
wild life. The jackals have disappeared, the
frogs who used to fill the night air with their
croaking are gone.
"I spray pesticides, covering my face
with a cloth. I hire a pump from the govern¬
ment. It would be easier if I could have my
own pump, but it costs a lot of money. The
government has introduced new seeds pro¬
ducing more per hectare than the local
seeds. The rice is white and cooks well, but
there is no taste in it.
"I grow different kinds of rice; some
with long grains, some short, and all with
different flavours and typical of our area.
My mother insists on growing them. Other¬
wise we will lose them in a few years, she
says."
"When I harvest the rice in November
the sky is blue and the sun is golden. I cut
the paddy and leave it in the fields for a few
days to dry. I then tie it into bunches and
carry home the bundles on my head. I feel
very proud. When the harvest is good the
whole village smiles.
"On Thursdays during the harvest season
my wife cleans the house, gives the floors
and walls a mud plaster and decorates them
with rice paste to welcome Lakshmi, the
Goddess of Wealth. My daughters make
garlands with sprays of paddy and put them
around the house. I don't go out to work
and stay at home. My wife prepares an
image of the Goddess Lakshmi by putting a
bowl of rice in the middle of the room and
decorating it with coins and flowers. The
first rice from the field is offered to the
Goddess and shared among the family.
That night I can sleep well, but my prob¬
lems are not over. Whatever I get from the
land is just about enough to maintain my
family. With eight people to look after I
have to buy clothes, medicines and pay for
the education of my children. I can't afford
to buy a new shirt for myself. Floods and
droughts occur regularly and I don't get the
return for the labour I put in."
PRAFULLA MOHANTI is an Indian writer
and painter. His paintings have been shown in
many parts of the world, including Europe, the
US, and Japan, as well as India. His classic
book My Village, My Life (1973), an evocation
of the Indian village where he was born and
brought up, has been translated into
Japanese, Norwegian and Danish. His pen-
portrait of the English as seen through Indian
eyes will be published next year by the Oxford
University Press.
PONGAL
by Guy Deleury
WHAT could be more usual for a
farmer or villager of southern
India than to boil his rice? What
could be more common than the potbellied
vessel in which the women of his family
prepare the meals each day? Between the
Equator and the Tropics, what could be
more familiar than the Sun? And yet these
are the three commonplace ingredients
which, along with cows and oxen, form the
centre of the annual cosmic festival of
Pongal in the land of the Tamils.
Some civilizations have tried hard to
separate the sacred from the profane and to
confine religion to the sacristy. The Hindu
has a quite different approach. He creates
his liturgies from the humblest objects and
the activities of the daily round. For him the
cosmos is an organism in which the tremb¬
ling of a blade of grass on earth affects the
most distant stars. The castes gravitate
around the village like planets around a
sun, each in its own orbit. The caste system
is a solar system, like every atom of the
human body, the cycle of the seasons, and
the revolutions of the Moon.
Festivals are the nodal points at which all
the vibrations of the Universe concentrate
in a sound imbued with meaning. Pongal is
the most notable example of such a festival.
Every Hindu country has its own variant in
which it expresses its specific identity. The
festival of Ganpati in the land of the
Marathas, the festival of Durga in Bengal,
and the festival of Onam in Kerala are ex¬
amples of these manifestations.
Pongal is the festival of the winter
solstice, when the Sun returns to its nor¬
thern course; soon the days will begin to
lengthen again. Even if today the solstice
actually falls almost a month earlier,
around 21 December, the ritual solstice is
still observed on the same date as in the
sixth century, perhaps because the Sun's en¬
try into the constellation of Capricorn takes
place at the same time as the harvest of the
new rice. The date highlights the relation¬
ship between the Sun and rice, the ritual ex¬
tends the relationship to man and society.
The Sun causes the rice to emerge from
water and become food and life for man.
The instruments of this two-phase
transmutation are the oxen which work in
the rice-fields and the pot in which the rice
is cooked. The festival brings together these
four participants in the new life: the Sun,
rice, the cooking pot, and the oxas well as
a fifth, village society.
The festival may last two, three or four
days; its length varies in different parts of
Tamil Nadu. The first day is the vigil,
known as bhogi or "enjoyment", of the
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
During the Pongal festival celebrated in
Tamil Nadu, southern India, oxen and
cows become kings and queens fora day.
Opposite page below, in the village of Mel
Seval, Tirunelveli district, a woman cooks
rice for the household cattle. On the
ground can be seen the lines of the
kolam, a propitiatory design traditionally
traced in front of the house with white
lime powder (see Unesco Courier, March
1984). Right, newly washed and garland¬
ed, cows and oxen wander freely through
the village all day long.
kind that is celebrated at the summer
solstice, or diwali, the festival of lamps.
This is the day when people cleanse
themselves of the year gone by. The boys
pick up any scraps of wood or pieces of
basketwork that happen to be lying around;
the outer walls of houses and temples are
whitewashed. In the afternoon rice boiled
in water is eaten. Sometimes sacrifices are
made to Mariayamma, the goddess of
epidemics; more generally there are rituals
in honour of ancestor spirits. Old earthen¬
ware pots are smashed, and the potter gives
new pots to his customers. Just as they do
for the festivals of Durga in Bengal and of
Ganpati in Maharastra, the potters work
day and night for weeks beforehand to
make the pottery that will be used during
the festival.
Today it is increasingly common for this
pottery to be bought at the bazaar. In the
past there was a nexus of links, governed by
the jajmani system, between each family of
potters and a number of families of village
peasant-producers. Pongal was one of the
festivals at which the links between village
families of different castes were bolstered
and reaffirmed.
This was the purpose of the celebrations
on the second day, known as the day of the
great pongal or, in some cases, the pongal
of the gods. Each family boiled its pot of
rice and went, according to traditional rules
of precedence, to offer portions of it on
banana leaves to other families. Sometimes
the high castes cooked their pongal in the
morning and the other castes in the after¬
noon. The communal pongal was also boil¬
ed before the temples. On this day the
favourite form of pongal is sugar pongal;
its preparation is accompanied by a variety
of customs involving the use of brown cane
sugar, coconut, raisins, fried lentils, car¬
damom, saffron, and a hint of edible cam¬
phor. Each family was proud of .its own
recipe, and for the children this delicacy is
the very heart of the festival, along with the
sugar cane and the new clothes.
For the children are given fine stalks of
sugar-cane to chew. We know that the In¬
dians invented sugar, since the very word
can be traced back to Sanskrit. Pongal is
also pre-eminently a day for sugar. In
Maharastra, where the festival is called
Makara-Sankrant (entry into Capricorn),
tiny sesame pellets are given to elders and
friends to whom the giver says, "take this
sweet and tell me sweet things". By giving
and receiving these titbits the villagers vow
to put honey into all their relationships in
the coming year.
On that day or on the following day, red-
ochre stripes representing Shiva are painted
on the white walls of the temples of Vishnu.
But this third day is primarily the pongal of
the herds. Cows and oxen are the kings and
queens of this feast-day. They are washed
and beautified, their coats are decorated,
rice-straw garlands are hung around their
necks, their horns are trimmed, and a
sacred cord of munj grass fibre dipped in
yellow-red turmeric is hung between them.
Thus bedecked the animals are left to
wander at liberty through the village;
sometimes a solemn procession is organized
at which the rules of precedence of the
village castes are respected. Then the beasts
too are fed with perfumed and sugared
pongal.
Legend has it that cattle will only agree to
leave their paradise to help men work the
land on condition that once a year they will
be feted and given a holiday. By honouring
them, the village recognizes its debt towards
the milk cows and draft animals. The castes
of men and beasts must help each other out
so that the cosmos can turn.
Perhaps it is this cosmic aspect which
gives significance to the bull running which
takes place on the fourth day of pongal.
The animals are specially chosen for their
aggressiveness and strength; their horns are
sharpened to make them more dangerous;
gold or silver medals are attached to their
foreheads. They are released one by one on
a carefully marked out track winding
through the middle of the village. In the
midst of tumultuous shouting or anxious
silence, young people try to snatch the
medals from the bulls. The powerful vitali¬
ty of the bulls of the Sun is unleashed in the
land of the Tamils on the day of the winter
solstice, and they are dispatched on their
northern trajectory.
GUY DELEURY is a French author who has
spent much of his life in India and has written
widely about aspects of Indian thought and
civilization. Notable among his published
works are Renaître en Inde (1976) and Le
Modèle Indou (1978), an essay on the struc¬
tures of Indian civilization past and present.
His latest book, L'Inde en Fête, will appear in
1985 as part of an encyclopaedia of myths
and religions (Lidis publisher, Paris).
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
China's 7,000-year-old crop
by Hu Baoxin and Chang Shujia
PADDY rice cultivation has a long
history in China. A passage from
The Book of Songs, which
describes how "dates are gathered in
August and rice harvested in October to
make wines for the spring to celebrate
your enjoyment of longevity", testifies
that as early as 3,000 years ago under
the Western Zhou Dynasty, Chinese peo¬
ple in Shaanxi province harvested rice
and made rice wine. But the cultivation of
paddy rice can be traced much further
back. Excavations in 1973-1974 in
Hemudu village of Yuyao county, Zhe-
jiang province, revealed that indica rice
grown in the area of Hangzhou Bay has a
history of at least 7,000 years.
A high level of intensive paddy rice
cultivation was achieved under the Han
Dynasty (202 BC to 220 AD). Records of
the transplantation of paddy rice can be
found in the Simin Yueling (Farmer's
Almanac) written during this period, and
by the 6th century, a number of out¬
standing, comprehensive, theoretical
works on paddy rice cultivation had been
written.
According to Li Bozhong, "the tech¬
nique of rice-wheat multiple cropping
was introduced in a few of the most
developed districts approximately during
the reign of the Emperor Gaozong and
Empress Wu (650-704) during the Tang
Dynasty (61 8 to 906 AD). It was general¬
ly adopted during the early and middle
Tang Dynasty, mainly in the Changjiang
Delta, the Chengdu Plain and along both
banks of the Changjiang River".
From the middle of the Tang Dynasty
period, the Huanghe River Valley suf¬
fered from continuous wars and the
feudal rulers depended more and more on
revenues in kind from the south to defray
their huge State expenditures. The point
was reached when nine-tenths of the
revenues collected from the whole coun¬
try came from the area south of the
Changjiang River. Since, ¡n the area
south of the Changjiang, it costs twenty
to thirty per cent less to cultivate a paddy
field than an equivalent area of dry land
crop, the peasants tended to grow more
paddy rice so as to increase their income.
Under the feudal system, exploitation
of tenants by the landlords was extreme¬
ly severe. Su Shi, a great writer of the
Song Dynasty (960 to 1 279 AD) describ¬
ed how "income was divided into two
halves between the landlord and the
tenants". Rent was mainly collected in
18
kind, but by the end of the feudal period,
money rent was also being collected and
payment was being made in silver.
However, the basis of the rent was still in
kind as the sum of silver to be collected
would be the price of a fixed amount of
grain sold on the market.
Rice is thought of as having always
been the principal food of the Asian
people. Although this is basically true to¬
day, during the long period of feudal rule
in China, only the rich and middle-class
families could afford to eat rice daily. The
peasants who did the tilling were obliged
to eke out a bare existence on wheat,
barley, miscellaneous grains, potatoes
and taros.
Following the reclamation of the
Changjiang River valley, new farming
techniques including the use of ploughs,
harrows and earth-breakers, and new
cultivation techniques with emphasis
on the raising of healthy rice seedlings
were gradually introduced. Great im¬
provements were made in farming im¬
plements. Crooked shaft ploughs, earth-
breakers and earth-cutters were in¬
vented. Irrigation implements using
water-power to raise water automatical¬
ly, such as waterwheels, dragon-bone
water lifts and windmill water carriers,
came into widespread use.
Many large-scale irrigation projects
were undertaken, such as the famous
Dujiang Yan Weir in Sichuan Province,
the Ling Qu Canal in Guangxi Province,
the Zhengguo Qu Canal in Shaanxi pro¬
vince, and the Zhangshui Qu Canal in
Linzhang county, Hebei province. In
the south, many small-scale irrigation
systems were built. To increase the
sources of fertilizer, many methods of
collecting and making composts were
devised, involving the use of dung from
cattle-sheds, the rotting of various
organic substances, the fermentation of
cake manure, and the burning and baking
of dung.
Many varieties of improved strains of
paddy rice were bred and selected. The
method of selecting fine ears for
breeding was first used under the
Western Han Dynasty (202 BC to 9 AD)
and is still employed by peasants today.
For example in the 1940s Chen
Yongkang, a well-known rice-grower of
Songjiang county, Jiangsu province,
succeeded in breeding a species of
Japónica known as Lao Lai Qing which
produced record yields.
China also introduced advanced tech¬
niques and fine rice strains from foreign
countries. For instance, Zhan Cheng rice,
which was introduced from Viet Nam,
was widespread in Fujian province as
early as in the Northern Song Dynasty
(960 to 1126 AD), and eventually
established its superiority among the
broad masses of rice producers in South
China. Its outstanding resistance to
drought earned it the nickname of the
"drought-defeating" rice. Another
Han dynasty wooden rice seeder, dating
from the first century BC.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
A series of 18th-century Chinese engrav¬
ings illustrating the stages in the produc¬
tion of rice: (1) water is Introduced into
the paddy field which is then harrowed to
mix the water into the sun-baked topsoil;
(2) rice seedlings are transplanted from
the seed beds to the paddy field; (3) the
water level is raised as the plants grow;
(4) harvesting the crop; (5) sheaves are
stacked in ricks; (6) threshing is often car¬
ried out on flooring of bamboo slats; (7)
rice is ground to remove the hulls.
popular feature was its short growth
duration, which meant that it could be
harvested before the onset of the con¬
tinuous heavy rains of autumn.
Large-scale planting of paddy rice
brought continuous increases in food
production in southern China. In the
lower reaches of the Changjiang River
and the Taihu Lake Valley, two crops of
rice could be harvested a year. Rice pro¬
duction in Suzhou and Huzhou in the
Taihu Lake Valley was of national impor¬
tance. In the words of a popular saying.
"A good harvest in Suzhou and Huzhou
feeds the whole country."
Rice soon acquired a dominant position
among cereals, and it became a regular
practice to ship large quantities of grains,
principally rice, from the south to the
north, setting the pattern of food supply
which continued for hundreds of years.
The spread of the practice of growing
double or even triple crops of rice annual¬
ly further strengthened the leading posi¬
tion of rice among the grain crops. The
rice-producing region in south China
became increasingly important to the
national economy.
Rice was used in many ways. Besides
serving as the main staple food, it was
also used to make a great variety of pro¬
ducts such as wines, cakes, pastries,
and rice flour. According to the book
Anecdotes of Wulin (Hangzhou) written
by Sishui Qianfu during the Southern
Song Dynasty period (1127 to 1279
AD), a great many kinds of wines and
pastries were found in Hangzhou at that
time. About twenty kinds of pastries and
nine kinds of rice gruels were listed.
There were also special kitchens for mak¬
ing dumplings. In the Records of Grain
Dreams written by Wu Zimu, detailed
lists were made of the kinds of rice and
assortments of pastries and cakes and
dumplings on sale at the rice shops. The
varieties of wines and vinegars made
from glutinous rice numbered in the
hundreds.
Chinese medical scholars believed
paddy rice was capable of "replenishing
the body and nourishing energy" and "of
consolidating energy and producing
saliva". Indeed, the nutrient and medical
value of paddy rice is also very well-
known. Paddy rice contains the amino
acid lysine, which is very high in nutritive
value, and the protein content of rice
compares favourably with that of other
cereals. In administering medical treat
ment, our ancestors often added rice to
their prescriptions with a view to "pro¬
tecting the stomach, supporting the
good and removing the evil within the
body."
During the period of convalescence
after a serious illness, when stomach
energy is still impaired and is awaiting
rehabilitation, light soft foods like rice
soup or porridge should be taken.
For several thousand years, grain has
been the main element in the dietary
structure of the Chinese people. Today,
material civilization is being highly
developed. Western eating habits and
new conceptions of nutrition have been
introduced into China. The controversy
as to whether to take rice as a "major" or
"minor" item of diet has arisen in
Chinese academic circles. However,
looking at the issue from a historical
point of view, no matter what great
changes the development of science and
technology may bring to the dietetic
structure of the people in the next cen¬
tury, the prosperity of the Chinese peo¬
ple, the world's most populous nation, is
inseparable from the contribution made
by the agricultural produce which is their
principal food.
HU BAOXIN and CHANG SHUJIA are
agronomists with the Bureau of Agriculture of
China's Ministry of Agriculture, Animal
Husbandry and Fishery.
On a co-operative farm of the commune
of Mar Lu, near Shanghai, the rice crop is
harvested with a specially designed,
Chinese-built mechanical reaper.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
The god
who stole the rice
by Obayashi Taryo
ACCORDING to a legend of eastern
Japan, told in the Somegawa loca¬
lity of the Iwate Prefecture, there
was, in the beginning, no rice in Japan. One
day the god Inari-sama stole some rice
grains from Kara (China) which he hid in
the hollowed out stem of a large reed. Plug¬
ging the open end of the reed with paper, in¬
verting it and using it as a walking-staff, he
returned to Japan bringing with him the
country's first rice.
Because the god had used an inverted
reed to hide the rice grains, a reed is always
inverted and stood in the seedling bed. Once
the seedlings have been successfully
transplanted, it is then safe to stand the reed
with its root end down.
Linked to such rice-transplanting rituals
and the accompanying myth of Inari-sama
(literally, "the rice-carrying god") we find
a very old method of preserving rice by par¬
ching it. Making yakigome, or parched rice,
involves roasting the grains of rice and
pounding them to remove their outer husks.
Yakigome may be simply eaten as it is, re-
parched, or softened by mixing with hot
water and served as a hot cereal. In the last
few centuries yakigome has come to be used
primarily as a food-offering to the gods in
rituals that take place in the rice paddy.
In eastern Japan, when the rice seedling
beds are first sown, the minakuchi
ceremony is held to bless the water-control
inlet where water enters the field from the
communal irrigation system.
At Muraoka village, Fujisawa, in the
Kanagawa Prefecture, during the
minakuchi sowing ritual, yakigome is
presented to the gods and then divided up
among the children to be eaten. The
yakigome, which the happy children spill
on the ground around them as they eat it,
serves to feed the sparrows and the crows.
In this way, it is said, as the seedlings are
growing, they are protected from the
ravages of hungry birds. Many other
localities also used to believe in the efficacy
of the ritual involving the spilling or
spreading oí yakigome at the irrigation in¬
let, to be eaten there by the birds and so pre¬
vent them from harming the rice seedlings.
In western Japan, yakigome is presented
to the gods at the harvest festival, when the
first rice of the season is cut with a scythe
and presented in a rite of thanksgiving. It
was the custom in many areas of western
In the Aichi district of Japan, on the day
the rice seed is sown, flowers are offered
to the deity of the rice field at the irriga¬
tion water inlet.
After the harvest, in the Noto area,
Ishikawa district, Japan, farmers perform
the aenokoto rite in which the deity of the
rice field, symbolized by bales of rice
seeds, is venerated.
Japan that the first rice should be ritually
cut and parched even before the grains were
fully ripe. This yakigome was offered to the
gods and ancestors and also exchanged as a
ceremonial gift among the farm households
of the village.
Today, yakigome is almost exclusively
used for ritual purposes, but at one time,
along with hoshii'i, rice that is first steamed
and then dried, yakigome was an important
and convenient foodstuff for soldiers and
travellers.
While yakigome is no longer enjoyed as a
food, mochi remains popular and impor¬
tant in Japanese cuisine. Mochi is usually
translated into English as "rice cake",
which may be misleading because they are
made neither with regular boiled rice nor
with rice flour. Mochi is short-grain
glutinous rice steamed until soft and then
pounded while hot in a mortar until it
becomes a gluey dough with no discernible
grains. The dough in turn can be shaped
and seasoned in a myriad ways.
Mochi plays an especially important role
at the New Year festivities. Throughout
Japan it is the custom to arrange round-
shaped mochi in graduated sizes (osonae) in
In a field carpeted with snow, a Japanese
peasant family goes through the motions
of planting rice. This rite is performed
during the first month of the lunar calen¬
dar (February) to ensure a good harvest
for the following autumn.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
the central alcove of the main room. Mochi
are presented to the family gods and are
eaten in a special soup, o-zoni, partaken by
the family in the first ritual meal on the
morning of New Year's Day.
Mochi has also been widely used at
religious rituals other than those of the New
Year, and today it is a common food served
on many occasions. Combined with other
ingredients, especially sugar, it is a well-
loved sweet and a popular snack food.
Another type of rice-based food with
traditional and ritual significance in Japan
is sekihan (red bean rice) which is a short-
grain glutinous rice steamed with small red
beans (azuki) that impart a distinctive and
auspicious red hue. Today, rather than
steaming, many housewives simply add red
beans to their regular rice as they boil it in
order to make sekihan. Sekihan has tradi¬
tionally appeared at a variety of rituals,
while today it is often served on occasions
of celebration such as birthdays. Sekihan is
also dished up on less happy occasions; in
the northern Tohoku region it is served at
wakes and funerals.
Although some scholars are less than
satisfied with the explanation, it is said that
the red sekihan is an attempt to reproduce
on special occasions a reddish variety of rice
that was cultivated in ancient times. In the
sacred rice paddy of Homan Shrine,
On 24 June, in the sacred rice field of the
Izawa Shrine, near Ise, Japan, young
boys and girls, dressed in red and white
kimonos, celebrate the rice-transplanting
festival to the accompaniment of drums,
rattles and ritual chants. The songs re¬
count the Shinto myth according to which
rice was brought to Japan by a white
crane and offered to Amaterasu, the god¬
dess of the sun.
Tanegashima Island, in the Kagoshima
Prefecture, they grow a variety of red rice
for ceremonial presentation to the god. At
several other locations reddish rice is grown
for a ritual function. Red types of rice are
also found in China and southeast Asia.
Red bean rice porridge, azuki-gayu, is
similar to sekihan. Azuki-gayu is made by
simmering the small red beans with regular,
medium-grain rice in lots of liquid until it
attains a thick consistency. This is served on
the fifteenth day after the lunar New Year's
Day. In some regions it is customary for
men, not women, to prepare the porridge.
The fifteenth day after the lunar New
Year, called the "Little New Year", was
formerly a day on which many agricultural
rituals were performed. Indeed, it is a
characteristic Japanese custom to ensure
the success of the year's crops by means of
rituals and ceremonies held on this day,
long before actual planting time.
Two important customs of the Little New
Year are rituals that reproduce the actual
activities of farming dances that mimic
transplanting the rice seedlings, and the
decoration of homes and farm buildings by
placing branches of trees hung with such
things as mochi to represent prolific rice
with full heads of grain.
Traditionally, mochi and sekihan were
cooked in steamers; indeed, until the Mid¬
dle Ages, regular rice was not directly boil¬
ed but prepared in steamers of earthenware
or wood. Today, a few households still boil
their rice in large iron pots with heavy lids
(kama) over charcoal fires. Since the
Second World War, however, these have
been mostly replaced by electric or gas auto¬
matic rice cookers.
The work of agricultural households has
also been revolutionized by new techno¬
logy. Rice cultivation has been mechanized
and the number of Japanese families engag¬
ed full-time in agriculture has dropped
dramatically. Traditional agricultural
rituals have largely disappeared. Tradi¬
tional foods made from rice have lost their
ritual significance and religious meaning.
Families no longer grow their own rice or
make mochi or sekihan at home. Instead
they buy ready-made products.
OBAYASHI TARYO. See biographical note
page 13.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Nature's nitrogen factory
To the untrained eye the floating mass of
vegetation to be seen on the paddy fields
of Viet Nam looks as if it is choking the life
out of the young rice plants. In fact, it is
nature's way of providing the rice with a
supplement of all-important nitrogen that
promotes healthy growth and increases
rice yield. This natural, floating nitrogen
"factory" consists of two plants, the water
fern Azolla and the blue green alga Ana-
baena azollae, that live together in a sym¬
biotic association. Azolla, the host plant,
provides a safe home in cavities in its
leaves for the Anabaena alga which in
return collects sufficient nitrogen from the
atmosphere to meet its own and its host's
total nitrogen requirements. Some of the
nitrogen thus "fixed" finds its way into the
water of the paddy field where it is taken up
by the rice plants; but Azolla is most effec¬
tive as a rich nitrogen source when it is
ploughed into the soil of the paddy field
during the fallow season as a "green
manure". Photos: (1) The blue-green alga
Anabaena azollae. (2) Azolla is propagated
in ponds during the summer and autumn. It
spreads with astonishing speed, doubling
the surface of water it covers within a
week. (3) A much magnified image of the
Azolla plant as seen by an electron scann¬
ing microscope. (4) During the 17th century
this temple was erected in the village of La
Van, Thai Binh Province, Viet Nam, in
honour of the legendary monk Khong Minh
Khong who is credited with having Initiated
the Azolla fertilizer technique.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Green winters on the Red River
by Dao The Tuan
IN the northern regions of the Socialist
Republic of Viet Nam, the cultivation
of rice is closely linked with that of
Azolla, a water fern which, in association
with the blue-green alga Anabaena
azollae, has the ability to fix nitrogen
from the atmosphere. Nitrogen is a key
factor in increasing the yield of rice ob¬
tainable from a given area of cultivated
land.
For centuries Azolla has been used in
the paddy fields as a "green manure" for
winter rice. The term "winter rice"
designates a group of rice varieties that
are specific to the Red River delta which
were developed by our ancestors to grow
in the deep water paddy fields of the river
plain.
Being comparatively resistant to cold,
the Azolla of Viet Nam (Azolla Pinnata) is
well adapted to the winter climate of the
Republic. During summer and autumn,
Azolla is propagated in ponds in a few
villages in the Thai Binh Province in order
to produce spores, or inocula. These are
then sold to other villages to be scattered
in the winter rice fields after the
transplantation of the rice seedlings in
January. There the Azolla grows and
spreads until, by about the month of
March, when the rice is ripe for
harvesting, it covers the entire surface of
the water. After the rice has been
harvested, this mass of greenery is
ploughed into the ground where it
decomposes, releasing nitrogen into the
soil. A layer of Azolla covering a one-
hectare rice field produces about 10
tonnes of fresh vegetation, which is
equivalent to 25 kilograms of nitrogen.
The exact date when peasant-farmers
first began to use Azolla in the rice fields
of Viet Nam is not known. According to
popular legend, a giant Buddhist monk
named Khong Minh Khong, who lived in
the eleventh century during the period of
the Ly dynasty, was carrying on his
shoulders a yoke on which were hung
two large baskets of Azolla. As he was
passing near the Red River, he dropped
his load of Azolla on the rice fields of two
or three villages. As a result, only the
peasants of these villages knew the
secret of the propagation of Azolla.
During the seventeenth century a tem¬
ple was erected to the honour of Khong
Minh Khong in recognition of his role
as founder of the Azolla technique.
However, according to another legend,
the discovery of the properties of Azolla
is attributed to a woman, the goddess of
Azolla.
Towards the end of the seventeenth
century, the inhabitants of three villages
in northern Viet Nam, La Van, Bung and
Bich D.u, in. Thai Binh Province, are
known to have selected wild Azolla
plants which, during the summer
months, they raised in flower pots and
then in ponds sheltered from the heat of
the sun by hedges of bamboo. The in
ocula thus produced were then sold to
other farmers of the region. By about
1945, some 40,000 hectares of rice
fields were sown with nitrogen-fixing
Azolla.
During the 1 950s, this traditional tech¬
nique was studied by agronomists and
passed on to all rice farmers. By using
super-phosphates in place of the manure
and ashes previously employed to fer¬
tilize the Azolla, and by making greater
use of insecticides, the propagation of
Azolla was considerably improved. As a
result, during the 1960s and 1970s,
Azolla contributed to an important in¬
crease in the rice crop in Viet Nam. Since
then, with the introduction of new
varieties of rice, methods have changed.
Azolla is propagated in the paddy fields
before the transplantation of the spring
rice seedlings, which takes place ¡n
February.
Today, the use of Azolla is encounter¬
ing certain difficulties. It is labour-
intensive, and the shortage of super¬
phosphates and insecticides has imped¬
ed the development of the Azolla tech¬
nique. These problems are now the sub¬
ject of research in Viet Nam. Indeed, dur¬
ing the last few years research scientists
throughout the world have begun to
study this interesting plant with the aim
of developing its use in other countries. It
is to be hoped that current problems will
be overcome and that Azolla will con¬
tinue to make a contribution to the task
of increasing world rice production.
DAO THE TUAN is director of the Viet Nam
Agricultural Science Institute at the Ministry
of Agriculture, Hanoi. A specialist in plant
physiology, he has carried out extensive
research into the physiology of rice and the
Azolla plant described in his article.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
A HOUSEHOLD GOD
by Lee Kwang-Gyu
THE Korean peninsula is a moun¬
tainous area only one-fifth of which
is available for cultivation. Rice-
growing is possible, especially in the south,
thanks to the hot summer and abundant
rainfall amounting to 800-1 ,000 millimetres
a year. Sixty per cent of the precipitation
occurs in the summer months from June to
early September.
What are the origins of rice cultivation on
the Korean peninsula? When and how did it
begin? Of eleven archaeological sites that
have yielded evidence for rice cultivation,
the two earliest, Naju in the southwest and
Hunam-ri in the middle of the peninsula,
date back to sometime between the eleventh
and the thirteenth century BC, the early
Bronze Age in Korea.
Archaeologists have suggested that rice
may have reached Korea from south China
in two waysvia a land route through nor¬
thern China and via a sea route across the
Yellow Sea from central China, as an exten¬
sion of the Lungshan culture in China.
Another hypothesis has been put forward
by agriculturists, who contend that rice
came to Korea from north China because
the Japónica rice and the dry rice found in
Korea today are grown in north China.
The earliest type of rice cultivation was
by dry farming, with the land being
prepared using the slash-and-burn method.
Wet rice cultivation seems to have been
adopted in the first century AD, and the
construction of large-scale bank revetment
and irrigation systems in the second and
third centuries is reported in Sam-guk-sa-gi,
the History of the Three Kingdoms in
Korea.
During the Koryo dynasty (918-1392)
which followed the Three Kingdoms, rice
became the country's major crop. The
Choson dynasty (1392-1910) developed
agriculture and especially rice-growing,
even further. Rice even became a form of
currency, along with metal coin and cloth.
Officials were paid in rice, and paddy fields
were allotted to them according to their
rank.
Rice is still very important in Korean life
today. As in other parts of southeast Asia it
is the principal food of the people. It is serv¬
ed three times daily, and is the main dish
around which all other foods are disposed.
Even when a rich variety of food is served,
a meal is not considered a meal unless it in¬
cludes rice.
For purposes of the daily diet, rice is
thoroughly washed, then boiled vigorously
for five minutes, simmered for ten minutes,
and left unheated to steam for another five
minutes. Sometimes it is also boiled with
barley, soybeans, red beans, or millet.
Rice is also used for making gruel, cakes,
and wine. Rice gruel or porridge is made
with polished white rice for infants, the
sick, and the elderly, and is served with or
Threshing Floor and Farmers turning the
Soil, two stages in the cultivation of rice
painted by Kim Hong-do, a famous 18th-
century Korean artist. Left, watched by
their master, the peasants thresh the
sheaves of rice. Right, scenes such as
this, of peasants ploughing and prepar¬
ing the soil, can still sometimes be seen
in the Korean countryside today.
without side dishes. Over a hundred
varieties of rice cakes and confectionery are
made with rice flour derived from both
glutinous and non-glutinous rice. Different
rice cakes are prepared for different occa¬
sions such as seasonal holidays, ritual ser¬
vices for ancestors, birthdays, weddings
and festivals.
Wine is made from rice by mixing steam¬
ed rice with fermented leaven made from
wheat bran and water. There are three main
kinds of rice wine: the first is a turbid brew
called Makulli; the second is a clear
beverage called Yakju; and the third is a
distilled liquor called Soju.
Because of climatic limitations, only one
rice crop is grown each year, and in the
southern part of the peninsula the fields are
used for barley in winter and rice in sum¬
mer. In the central part of the peninsula,
rice cultivation begins with the washing of
the seeds in late March or early April by
solar calendar. The high-quality seeds,
preserved from the previous year's harvest,
are first washed in salty water to free them
from their husks and then washed again to
remove the salt.
In the sunniest part of the paddy, furrows
one metre wide are ploughed in preparation
for seedbeds which are then covered with
grass and ash and allowed to dry for two or
three days. Rice seeds are then sown and
watered generously so that they sink into
the soil. Fifteen days later, the water is
drained out of the seedbeds in order to
stabilize the roots; then the seedbeds are
watered again. This process is repeated
twice, and then the seedbeds are covered
with compost. After about a month, young
rice plants are transplanted from the seed¬
bed to the rice paddy field.
Prior to transplantation the paddy is
ploughed. Oxen were used for this purpose
in the past but today they are rapidly being
replaced by the power tiller. The field must
be levelled before it can be flooded to
receive the seedlings. The farmer must re¬
inforce the retaining banks of the field and
spread fertilizer, now using chemical fer¬
tilizers whereas in the past dung, muck, ash
and grass were used.
The young rice plants are planted a fixed
distance from each other, and are aligned
using a rope in which equidistant knots
have been tied. Men and women plant in
single file. Planting must be done in the
traditional way by hand as the complexities
involved in the development of the
mechanization of transplantation work
have yet to be solved.
In earlier times rice fields were weeded
three times a year; this was a long and
laborious task whether hoes were used or
whether the work was done by hand. Today
chemical herbicides have largely eliminated
the need for weeding by hand.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
v
W- %- !
MJJ^C
Tfte tug-of-war contests that traditionally
take place in January in villages in the
southern part of the Korean peninsula are
preceded by loop fightslively contests
between two teams equipped with
100-metre-long ropes to the end of which
are attached huge loops made of straw
and wood. The loop fight is a pushing
contest the aim of which is to force the
opposing team's loop to the ground.
Team leaders sit astride the rope or stand
on the loops which are held up on
wooden poles by the 50- to 80-strong
teams. The combination of men, ropes
and loops makes the entire scene look
curiously like a fight between two huge
dragons.
In early October the rice is harvested
. within a period lasting ten days or so.
Because of this time limitation, concen¬
trated effort is required of the farmer. After
being dried, the seeds are taken from the
plants by thresher a few weeks after the
harvest.
The typical farming village is located
near the rice field, at the foot of a moun¬
tain. Farmers say that they must be able to
look after the rice plants every day and that
if a plant is neglected it will fade away like
an abandoned child.
Most villages have a band in which the
farmers play at harvest time, on seasonal
holidays, or after the ritual service for a
village god on the day of the first full moon
by the lunar calendar, when many villages,
especially in the southern part of the penin¬
sula, engage in tug-of-war competitions.
This custom is also practiced elsewhere in
southeast Asia.
Above all rice is worshipped as the
housegod in farming villages. Rice in a
small jar is the main symbol of the
housegod. In the central regions of the
peninsula it is placed in the back yard, while
in other regions it is kept in the inner room.
The housewife offers rice cakes before
the god once a year, praying for good luck
for the family farm and for the good health
of the family.
Even today people feel uneasy if the rice
harvest has been poor, despite the
knowledge that imported rice will offset
any shortages. The opposite is also true.
People feel happy and fulfilled when the
harvest is bountiful, behaving generously
and forgiving past wrongs. In short, despite
modernization and industrialization, rice is
still the most important element in Korean
social, economic, and cultural life.
LEE KWANG-GYU, of the Republic of Korea,
is a professor at the College of Social
Sciences, Seoul National University, and a
former President (1976-1979) of his coun¬
try's Society for Cultural Anthropology. He is
the author of many studies on family structure
and kinship in his country and elsewhere in
east Asia.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
'*£" ^1
i®lR£iJäi
^^^^^^^^^^
Waf (temple) Mahathat is situated at the
heart of the ruined city of old Sukhothai,
the cradle of Thai civilization.
Í
Unearthed in central Thailand, this brick
contains rice husks, evidence that rice
was grown in the ancient kingdom of
Dvaravati which flourished in the region
from the 6th to the 13th century.
i
V --. \ v -, » J <» i
©
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
A CITY BUILT ON RICE
by Srisakra Vallibhotama
IN Thai history, the significance of rice
for the development of the State is
related to a cultural practice called
kalapana, the act of endowing sacred
monuments or objects with land, labour
and goods. This practice resulted in increas¬
ing the number of village communities pro¬
ducing rice for subsistence.
The rationale behind this practice was
that Thailand was a sparsely populated
country so that manpower was at a
premium in order to provide for the security
and prosperity of the State. Manpower
could be obtained in several ways. The
harsh solution was to wage war and
organize raids in the hope of capturing large
numbers of families. A gentler solution was
to offer protection to refugees or to per¬
suade merchants and travellers to come and
settle in the country. To assimilate these
people of different origins into society, it
was necessary to build a community to
which they could feel they belonged.
With this in mind the ruler would
establish a religious monument or a shrine
in a given place and for its upkeep he would
perform an act of kalapana, donating a
number of families, draft animals and ob¬
jects to the site in question. As a rule such
families were brought from outside. They
would clear the land, turn forest into pad¬
dy, make homes for themselves, and look
after the religious monument. In this way a
peasant community was created, to become
not only a unit of the wider society but a
supplier of labour to the State to which it
belonged. Accordingly, any assessment of
the strength and persistence of a Thai city or
State in the past must take into account not
only its size but also the number of religious
sites associated with rice-land in the sur¬
rounding area.
The State of Sukhothai, which emerged
in the thirteenth century and is generally ac¬
cepted as the earliest Thai kingdom in
Thailand, is a case in point. An inscription
records of its greatest ruler, Ram Kam
Haeng, that before he became king he had
honestly served his father and elder brother
in waging war against other States and had
taken many captives, whom he did not kill
or torture but made citizens of Sukhothai.
When he became king he persuaded mer¬
chants and travellers from outside his
kingdom to trade freely in Sukhothai and
settle there.
The city of Sukhothai was a large settle¬
ment surrounded with triple walls and pro¬
vided with large ponds for drinking water.
There were four main gates at the cardinal
points through which people thronged on
special religious occasions to pay homage to
the Buddha at the heart of the city. Around
Sukhothai there were orchards and temples
to the great Buddha; to the south and west
were the living quarters of monks, while to
the north and east were rice-lands and
villages.
During the lifetime of King Ram Kam
Haeng, the Sukhothai State was pros¬
perous: "there is fish in the water and rice
in the fields" runs a famous saying
associated with him. In order to integrate
outsiders into the Sukhothai State the King
built wat (Buddhist monasteries) donating
rice-land, labour and goods to form the
basis of village communities. We know that
this practice continued, for many later
Sukhothai inscriptions mention how
members of the royal family and
bureaucrats followed in his footsteps and
restored or built roads, bridges, weirs and
canals which were necessary for com¬
munication and rice cultivation.
The city of Sukhothai was, and still is,
situated near the slope of a mountain sur¬
rounded by low-lying land to the north and
east where rice is grown. These lowland
areas are dotted with ruins of temples and
stupas indicating the centres of peasant
villages. The main source of water for rice
cultivation was the Mae Lampan river
which passes by the city from north to east
before flowing into the Yom River about
eleven kilometres away.
Traces of ancient weirs and irrigation
channels can be seen on the northern and
eastern banks of the river, indicating
hydraulic facilities provided by the State for
the rice-growing communities formed as the
result of kalapana. In addition there is a
large rectangular area bounded by earthen
dykes near the northeastern corner of the
city which was reserved for rice cultivation.
These remains of ancient irrigation works
are a unique feature of the city which still
bear witness to the attempts of the rulers of
Sukhothai to grow sufficient rice to ensure
the survival of the city and its people in a
region prone to drought and where the
quality of the soil is poor.
SRISAKRA VALLIBHOTAMA, Thai
historian and social anthropologist, has been
associate professor of anthropology at
Silpakorn University, Bangkok, since 1980. In
1977 he was seconded as chief sociologist to
the Sukhothai Historical Park Development
Project, working in conjunction with Unesco,
and in 1980 he was a visiting professor at
Cornell University, USA.
Rice is Thailand's major crop, the basic
foodofthe Thaipeople, and the country's
most important export.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
>
©
Thousand-year-old roots of Java's rice
The rice-farmer patiently plodding
behind his buffalo-drawn plough was
already a familiar sight in the island of
Java (Indonesia) at least a thousand
years ago. This is one of the messages
of the hundreds of realistically carved
stone bas-reliefs (above), many depic¬
ting scenes from everyday life, that wind
around the walls of the great ninth-
century Buddhist sanctuary of
Borobudur (see Unesco Courier,
February 1983). Another relief (below)
shows a harvest scene with men and
women cutting rice in the field and carry¬
ing the bound rice-sheaves on their
shoulders. In the densely populated
plains of Java today, where the villages
are islands of vegetation rising out of the
flooded rice-fields, the buffalo may be
giving way to the motorized cultivator
and other machines but the old rice
myths and traditions die hard. In Java
rice is associated with fertility and was
considered as feminine, the incarnation
of the goddess Dewi Sri. Men were sub¬
ject to many prohibitions where rice was
concerned. They were forbidden to cook
it, and although they always prepared
the land it was the women who planted
and otherwise handled the rice. Every
stage in rice cultivation and processing
was an opportunity to pay respect to
Dewi Sri and an occasion for mutual aid.
Rice was held in higher esteem than
other crops such as maize or cassava.
Colour page
The Rice Harvest, by M. Runia (Bali).
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
£41**
Hfâ
fJíZ
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
'Never eat rice in the dark
s
Never eat rice in the dark or you will at¬
tract the evil spirit called momo (the ghost).
You might even swallow the evil spirit and
bring misfortune upon yourself.
If anyone wastes rice or throws it away,
his hand will become deformed and he will
never know abundance or prosperity.
If you give rice to a beggar, offer it to him
on a plate and not in the pangtakal (measur¬
ing cup), otherwise your supply of rice and
food will diminish.
Never place the measuring cup in the rice
bin upside down for this may result in a bad
harvest.
On the steep slopes of the mountains in
the north of Luzon, the largest island of
the Philippines, the ¡fugaos people, with
great skill and enormous effort, have
carved out an amazing complex of ir¬
rigated rice terraces. Creation of this
complex involved the construction of
20,000 kilometres of revetments, in¬
cluding 7,000 kilometres of stone walls.
Above, the Ifugao village ofBatud. Right,
an effigy of the rice goddess,
photographed in Batud.
Colour page
A cook prepares a meal of rice for
distribution to volunteers working on
the construction of a rice-field irriga¬
tion canal in the province of Da Nang,
Viet Nam.
Proverbs from the Philippines
selected by
	 Samuel K. Tan	
Professor of history, University of the
Philippines.
LI wM
-.-o
Rice should never be lent or given away at
night or early in the morning because this
brings bad luck. Rice may, however, be
bought at night.
Showering rice on newly-weds brings
prosperity both to the couple and to the per¬
son who throws the rice.
Rice must be washed three times for this
is in keeping with the ancient ways.
It is best to plant during a full moon and
on a clear and starry night for this will en¬
sure a good harvest.
Sundays, Mondays, the first day of
August and odd-dated days are in¬
auspicious for planting. Even-dated
Wednesdays and Fridays are the best days
for planting for they bring a plentiful
harvest and healthy grains, especially if the
planting is accompanied by prayers.
When planting, the planter should have a
full stomach for this brings good luck and
fruitful days and months ahead. When
planting is completed, the planter should let
out a great shout to signify that the day has
ended in triumph over adverse conditions
and unforeseen eventualities.
Harvest-time is the most keenly-awaited
period in the cycle of rice cultivation and
harvesting should be carried out before the
dew and morning mists have disappeared.
This will bring speedy good fortune to the
people.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
THE SOUL OF A PEOPLE
by Zainal Kling
IN Malaysia, it was traditionally believed
that rice, or paddy, was animated by
a soulthe rice soul (semangat padi).
The semangat (soul) is a generalized idea or
notion of a vital principle which enlivens
and animates objects and living things in
this world. It is the extra vitality or vigour
complementing the life principle (nyawa) in
living beings or the intrinsic power em¬
bodied in magical objects and is variously
conceived as "a diminutive but exact
counterpart of its own embodiment", or as
appearing in the form of an insect, a bird,
or an animal. Nevertheless, in the central
part of the Malaysian peninsula an an¬
thropomorphic conception of the rice soul
was often encountered in myth:
"In olden times, rice was not harvested
from the fields. Every morning a grain
would appear in the house of the farmer
and find its way into the rice cooking pot.
The housewife would normally cook the
rice grain without even opening the pot
cover, which was taboo (pantang). By the
afternoon the pot would be full of rice
ready for consumption.
"One morning, the housewife planned to
leave the house for her farm and therefore
she warned her children never to open the
rice pot during her absence. Once the
mother had gone, one of the younger
children grew curious and tried to open the
pot. Unbeknownst to her elder sister she
peeped into the pot and saw a little girl in¬
side. Suddenly the little girl disappeared
leaving only a small grain of rice. Her elder
sister was very angry and scolded her
severely.
"When their mother returned, she found
that there was no rice in the pot. She knew
that it had been opened and scolded her
younger daughter for disobeying her in¬
structions and breaking the taboo. But it
was no good crying over spilt milk, and
from that day onwards they had to work
very hard to plant the rice, harvest it, and
then carry home all the grains."
The anthropomorphic conception was
further elaborated by a series of endearing
names used to address the rice soul in in¬
vocations and incantations during various
rites, especially at first harvest (menuai
sulung). The soul was adored like a new¬
born baby and lovingly addressed as "the
nine-month baby" (anak sembilan bulan),
"sunray princess" (anak maharaja
cahaya), or "the crystal princess" (si dang
gemala). This human treatment of rice
reflects the inherent Malay attitude of
treating all humanity with the utmost
respect and kindness.
The rice soul was also regarded as a
manikin, or thumbling, with the most sen¬
sitive feelings which could be easily offend-
M jHhi
1 , i -
' * wmgm. A
	 / '
»
*
1 ^riM&M
"ai M
W i 	 -tmf
Each year in May, the Kadazan and Murut
villagers of Sabah (Malaysia), celebrate
the rice harvest with one of the most im¬
portant traditional ceremonies in their
cultural life. The festivities begin with the
celebration of magavau, a ritual in which
the "soul" of the rice is carried from the
rice-field to the home of its owner. Then,
to the beating of drums and gongs, the
bobohizan or Kadazan priestesses per¬
form the sumazau, the Kadazans' best-
loved dance, and the head priestess begs
fora good harvest the foliowing year. The
people join in the dance, the traditional
way of expressing everlasting gratitude
to their creator Kinoingan for sacrificing
his only daughter Huminodun so that the
different parts of her body could become
food for the starving people. Rice is the
embodiment of the spirit or soul of
Huminodun.
ed and hurt. It had to be handled with cau¬
tion, like a fragile, vulnerable baby or, as
the Malay saying puts it, as though "hand¬
ling a flat-bottomed tray brimful of cook¬
ing oil" (menatang minyak yang penu).
These human characteristics symbolically
project the personality traits generally
displayed by Malays themselves, for as a
people they are sensitive and unassuming,
easily offended and shamed by harsh words
and treatment.
The human attributes of the rice soul
became the focus of complex rituals and
elaborate ceremonies with a strong emo¬
tional content which built up to almost
cultic veneration and adoration in the
various rites throughout the cycle of rice
cultivation. From the first step of selecting
rice seeds, to the process of growing,
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
transplanting and weeding and up to the
time of the first harvest, the final storage
and the first tasting of the crop, a series of
rituals was carried out to express the
primordial need for a good harvest and the
survival of the community from hunger and
starvation.
The souls were entreated and invoked to
remain with the rice and not to abandon its
rice-seed embodiment or the community.
The ritual specialist, the Pawang, would
tenderly cradle a handful of seeds at the
beginning of the sowing ceremony or dur¬
ing the cutting of the first few stalks at the
first harvest. The Pawang's entire attitude
would be one of appeasement and tender
care of the soul against human violation or
destruction by malignant spirits. The first
few stalks were cut with a small palm-size
reaping knife to avoid hurting the tender
soul or inflicting violence on the ears of
rice.
Female Pawang, or housewives, would
normally invite the soul, believed to be em¬
bodied in a selection of the best of the
newly-reaped seeds, to return home with
them. The first seven ears of rice to be
reaped were swaddled and tenderly placed
in a specially-made basket, the cradle of the
rice soul. The basket would then be careful¬
ly kept in the rice store for next year's
cultivation. Whatever interpretation may
be placed on these various rituals, they
nevertheless clearly suggest a strong notion
of the rites of fertility, the concept of
"mother earth" and rebirth in the "mother
seeds" (ibu benith), the receptacle of the
child-like rice soul.
For generations these attitudes and rites
were part and parcel of the Malay cultural
system as reflected in rice cultivation, until
modern technologies reduced them to mere
memories, to sub-conscious skills to be
briefly recalled during a particularly bad
harvest or a period of unfavourable plant¬
ing conditions. In the modern technological
context of machinery, chemical fertilizers,
irrigation systems and hybrid seeds, the
idea of rice souls and ritual ceremonies
seem more and more irrational and
meaningless.
ZAINAL KLING, of Malaysia, is head of the
department of anthropology and sociology at
the University of Malaysia, Kuala Lumpur. He
is currently carrying out research into cultural
forms in Malaysia.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
r©
*»-
¡4fff '
* _, ***{ «
.- **
&Çf
<fé*
,<i,***.'i
r^
fc_»w
ÎTJiK
4**«?*
^4 'Plov' is as good as a feast
by Boris V. Andrianov
PLOV, the national dish of Uzbe¬
kistan, is relished not only by
the Uzbeks but by the peoples of
many other regions of the Soviet
Union. Fragrant, hot, ready to melt in
the mouth, the rice is cooked with car¬
rots, onions, and garlic, and served ¡n
white mountains on a huge platter with
morsels of mutton or beef. Among the
Uzbeks, the Kara-Kalpaks, the Tajiks
and other peoples of central Asia, it is
the favourite dish for high days and
holidays.
Rice cultivation came to central Asia
from more southerly Asian countries
where irrigation and cereal farming ap¬
peared in the sixth-fifth millennia of the
pre-Christian era. In the second half of
the third millennium and the beginning
of the second, the area under culti¬
vation grew considerably, and ar¬
chaeologists believe that an urban
civilization emerged in south-central
Asia during this period in an area where
two influences converged: the in¬
fluence of Sumer and Elam in the west,
and the influence of the ancient Indian
civilizations of the Indus plain in the
south.
Links with India undoubtedly
favoured the emergence of irrigated
rice cultivation in central Asia. As yet
there is not enough archaeological
evidence to give a precise date to this
development, but clearly it could only
have occurred when the peoples of
central Asia had learned how to build
vast- and complex irrigation networks,
a phenomenon connected with the
appearance in the cultivated oases of
major urban trading centres.
In central Asia as in many other
regions of Antiquity with an arid
climate the frontiers of the earliest
State structures largely corresponded
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
This head chef of a restaurant in
Samarkand, Uzbek SSR, in central Asia,
is renowned as a master in the art of
preparing Plov, a favourite rice dish of the
Uzbeks and peoples of many other
regions of the USSR.
to the limits of irrigated land. At the
end of the second and the beginning of
the last millennium of the pre-Christian
era, this accounted for the territorial
outline of many countries, including
Bactria which developed on the upper
course of the Amu Darya and its
tributaries, Dagestan on the Terek,
Margiana on the Murghab, Parthia in
the foothills of the Kopet-Dag moun¬
tains, Sogdiana in the valley of the
Zeravshan, and Khorezm in the ancient
delta of the Amu-Darya. The Greek
historian Herodotus (c. 484-420 BC)
mentions an irrigation installation on
the river Ak (Akes) which watered land
on the borders of Khorezm, Hyrcania
and Parthia.
Under the Persian Achaeminid
dynasty (sixth-fourth centuries BC)
which dominated a large part of central
Asia, the development of agriculture
was stimulated by the construction of
canals, and wheat, barley, millet and
many other crops were grown, in¬
cluding the vine, and possibly rice.
When Alexander the Great was
treading the path of conquest to India
around 327 BC, rice was fairly widely
grown in Bactria.
According to Chinese sources, rice-
growing was widespread in central
Asia in the second century of the pre-
Christian era. The traveller and
diplomat Zhang Qian tells how in
Fergana and Parthia "the way of life is
sedentary, agriculture is practiced, rice
and wheat are sown; wine is taken
from the vine". The results of ar¬
chaeological excavations, especially in
ancient Margia, confirm this
description.
In very early times, rice and the
dishes prepared with it became part of
the daily life of many peoples of central
Asia. But rice was primarily the food of
the rich who had the means to prepare
plov or boiled rice almost every day. At
the beginning of this century,
moderately well off families still only
made plov once a week at most. For
the poor it was a dish eaten at ban¬
quets given by the rich, and on
ceremonial occasions such as wed¬
dings, funerals, and the new year
festival (navruz).
Even today, among several peoples
of central Asia, plov and other rice-
based dishes are cooked at the home
of the bride and bridegroom and served
at weddings. Another custom which
has survived is for groups of young
men to club together and regale
themselves at plov picnics, with each
member of the group paying his share.
Rice has always been an important
ingredient in the ritual food served at
funerals. The meal begins with rice
cooked in milk, which is, according to
an old religious tradition, a sacred dish
fit only for the servants of the cult, the
khans (chiefs) and their entourage.
Rice cooked in milk was rarely eaten by
the mass of the people, who believed
nevertheless in its curative properties
and fed it to those suffering from
stomach ailments and nursing mothers
in need of energy and milk. All kinds of
popular beliefs are thus associated
with rice, considered to be sacred. It
was regarded as sinful to spill rice in a
dirty place.
In former times in central Asia rice
was only grown on land belonging to
the wealthy and powerful. From the
second half of the nineteenth century
on, however, when most of this region
became part of Russia, the poor
peasants began to grow rice for the
market, on rented land.
Today rice has entered every
household, thanks to common owner¬
ship of land and water, the use of fer¬
tilizer, machines for harvesting rice,
and the appearance of new varieties.
Plov prepared in giant saucepans is
sold in the streets, and it is widely
available in cafés, canteens and
restaurants.
There are over forty recipes for plov,
using meat, vegetables, salads,
raisins, etc. The art is proudly transmit¬
ted from generation to generation.
Cooking plov requires plenty of
strength and stamina! A saucepan may
contain anything from 50 to 300
kilograms of food... For each kilogram
of rice the cook must add an equal
quantity of meat, carrots and onions,
not forgetting condiments such as
barberry, chestnuts, and macerated
quinces which give plov its distinctive
taste. And woe betide the cook who
does not know how to boil rice so that
the grains don't stick together! Then,
when the dish is ready, hundreds of
trenchermen gather for the feast.
The area of rice-growing land has
greatly increased. It has risen from just
over 150,000 hectares in 1913, to
more than 800,000 hectares today.
The main rice-growing areas of the
Soviet Union are in central Asia, but
rice is today grown slightly further
north, thanks to the development of
new varieties obtained by selection. In
the European part of the Soviet Union
the most extensive and highly
mechanized rice-growing region is in
the Kuban basin north of the
Caucasus.
BORIS VASSILIEVICH ANDRIANOV, a
Soviet specialist on irrigated farming in Anti¬
quity, is attached to the Ethnographic Institute
of the USSR Academy of Sciences. He has
published a number of scientific studies and is
a co-author of a forthcoming collective
History of Irrigation in the USSR, commission¬
ed by the International Commission on Irriga¬
tion and Drainage (New Delhi) in collaboration
with Unesco.
A family get-together on a kolkhoz (col¬
lective farm) in Uzbekistan. The kolkhoz
produces both rice and cotton.
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
A touchstone
by Rafaralahy Bemananjara
THE island of Madagascar is a parti¬
cularly interesting example of a
"rice civilization". Known as vary
or vare, rice is the staple food of the island's
nine and a half million inhabitants and
holds pride of place in both their material
and spiritual life.
In the past, rice was one of the yardsticks
by reference to which the Malagasy situated
themselves in both time and space. The
basic unit employed in traditional systems
of measuring time was "the time it takes to
cook rice" (indray mahamasa-bary), a
period of between thirty minutes and one
hour, depending upon the fuel and the type
of cooking utensil used and the quantity of
rice cooked. The distance to a given place
would be described, for example, as being
"twice or three times the time it takes to
cook rice".
The growth cycle of rice was the
peasants' calendar. Sowing time, mamafy
ketsa, covered roughly the months of July
of time
and place
Winnowing rice near Antananarivo,
Madagascar. After the harvest the
sheaves ofrice are beaten against a stone
to separate the grain from the panicle, or
head. The grain Is then collected into
baskets. The winnowerplaces the basket
on his or her head and allows a stream of
grain to trickle through the outstretched
fingers of the hand; the husks and chaff
are blown away while the grains fall in a
heap on to a piece of matting.
and August, while the transplanting period,
manetsa vary, generally corresponded to
October and November. People commonly
spoke of events as occurring before, during
or after the mitera-bary (literally, "when
the rice gives birth"), that is, when the
grains of rice appeared, or mena vary, the
harvest period when the rice fields were
covered with a carpet of gold.
Rice also provided a standard for other
measurements, in particular large measures
of volume; the vary iray (literally, "a rice")
was roughly equivalent to 1.2 hectolitres,
and the most common measure, the
fahefabary or fahefany, was the equivalent
of half a dekalitre.
Composite names based on the word vary
(rice) were also used to designate units of
money. Shortly before the arrival of the
Europeans, and particularly during the first
tentative moves towards unification around
the end of the eighteenth century, markets
were established around the capital, An-
Wooden mortar from Majunga,
Madagascar, used for pounding rice.
Bamboo rice measure, 13.5 cm in height,
decorated with poker-work representa¬
tions of a horseman, a rowing-boat and a
palace. It comes from Fianarantsoa, a
large agricultural market-town on the
central plateau of Madagascar, to the
south of Antananarivo.
4 Towards the end of the 18th century in
Madagascar, foreign currency cut into
segments, like these pieces of silver
money found at Antananarivo, was used
as a means ofpayment. The value of each
segment depended upon its weight as
measured against the weight ofa grain of
rice. The smallest unit of currency was
the varifitoventy (the weight of seven
grains of rice).
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
tananarivo, and an attempt was made to
regularize exchange transactions. Foreign
currency cut into segments was used as a
means of payment, its value being deter¬
mined by weight. Here again the standard
adopted was a grain of rice. The variraiven-
ty ("a grain of rice") was the equivalent in
weight of the seven hundred and twentieth
part of a piastre and became the basis for
the denomination of monetary units. Thus
the smallest monetary unit used was the
varifitoventy (the weight of seven grains of
rice). The word variraiventy is still
employed but only in a particular negative
idiom tsy am-bariraiventy or tsy manam
bariraiventywhich mean, "without a
sou", or penniless.
The use of the word vary is not, however,
confined to quantifiable applications such
as measurements of time, place and weight,
and it often appears in idioms that express
value judgments on people or actions. To
express his appreciation of an act or gesture
a Malagasy would say: "That is truly rice
(vary) cooked in milk and topped with
honey", in other words, perfection itself,
the best the world has to offer.
One defect of ricethe fact that, when it
is fully grown, if it is blown over by the
wind it is unable to regain an upright
position was acknowledged by the
Malagasy of the past and is still embodied
in a popular expression. Someone who
gives rein to his vices is said to be "nivary
lavo" ("playing at fallen rice").
The single defect apart, the Malagasy see
many virtues in rice which they take as a
model on which to base their own conduct.
Rice itself is often personified. When the
stems swell, just before the heads form, the
rice is said to be "pregnant"; and when the
head breaks out, the rice is said to be "giv¬
ing birth". For the Malagasy, the growth
pattern of rice recalls that of man when
the heads first form, they stand erect with
the proud vigour of youth; they end by
bending under the weight of age and the
"fullness of years".
The symbiosis between rice and water has
always been taken as the symbol of undying
friendship or love: "May this friendship (or
love) be like that of rice and water; in the
fields they are always together and in the
house they are inseparable". Of marriage it
is said: "Love is like a young rice plant; if
it is not transplanted, it will never
blossom".
Many other popular sayings describe
human behaviour by reference to rice. Thus
to encourage each other to speak out at a
meeting, for example, people say: "Let us
be like rice, let everyone reveal what he has
in his heart".
During the long evenings around the fire,
rice is an inexhaustible source of discussion,
jokes and riddles such as this: "Of whom is
it true that you must take his life in order to
make him live the better?" Yes, you have
guessed it; the answer is the rice plant that
must be plucked from the seed bed to be
transplanted to the paddy field.
RAFARALAHY-BEMANANJARA, of
Madagascar, is head of his country's Institute
of Applied Linguistics. He has carried out
research into the problems of mother tongue
language teaching in Third World countries,
and has published a number of articles on the
development of African languages.
A versatile plant
Rice is one of the most adaptable
members of the plant kingdom. From its
original habitat in the hot, humid Tropics,
rice has spread throughout the world by
natural dispersal and human interven¬
tion. It is now cultivated in hot deserts
and in the cool climate ofhigh mountains.
In parts of Asia, Africa and Latin America
it is cultivated as a dry-land crop, while in
parts of Bangladesh, Burma, eastern In¬
dia, Thailand and Viet Nam floating rices
flourish in floodwaters that can be as
much as three metres deep. The two main
cultivated species are Oryza sativa, of
Asia, and Oryza glaberrima, of west
Africa. Archaeological data seem to show
that Oryza sativa ivas first domesticated
in Asia more than 7,000 years ago, and
that domestication of Oryza glaberrima in
Africa occurred somewhat later. It seems
probable that rice was cultivated in the
Niger basin around 1500 BC and in
Guinea about 400 years later; it is now
one of the principal crops cultivated in
the flood-plain areas of the Sokoto and
Niger basins. From top to bottom, trans¬
plantation of rice in Senegal, in France
and in Colombia.
'J
i
A
f
1
A
...A-'
..-":"*
âé\
"
1
««^.jifiiyMHiMÉMlÉtl
» -ter-** - Kj--- - > -, ''
1rs.
îndel©A.
l\ ^"TlV W VJ
HrrkpP*-
r \
'«S3 is>*|fiH
;
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO NEWSROOM
UNICEF
Greeting Cards
Artists and museums from many coun¬
tries have again contributed an attractive
and varied range of designs to this year's
UNICEF greeting cards, now on sale at
UNICEF sales points throughout the
world.
Proceeds from the sales of cards, gifts
and stationery help UNICEF, the United
Nations Children's Fund, to finance its
programmes for bringing improved
health care, education, nutrition and
sanitation to millions of deprived children
throughout the developing countries of
Africa, Asia and Latin America.
The sale of one card alone provides the
funds to vaccinate 4 children against
diphtheria, whooping cough and tetanus,
or to protect 10 children against blind¬
ness. In addition to standard-size and
mini-format cards and stationery, an Art
diary for 1 985, International Youth Year,
features photos of children and young
people from 57 countries. Card shown
here reproduces "Water Birds", a design
contributed by Indonesian artist Iwan
Tirta.
Unesco Peace Education Prize
awarded to international
physicians' group
The 1 984 Unesco Prize for Peace Educa¬
tion has been awarded to the Interna¬
tional Physicians for the Prevention of
Nuclear War. The US-based group is
headed jointly by a Soviet and a US car¬
diologist, Evgueni Chazov of the Soviet
Union and Bernard Lown of the United
States, who accepted the $60,000
award at a ceremony at Unesco's Paris
Headquarters on 30 October. The object
of the annual Prize, awarded for the first
time in 1981, is to promote action aimed
at constructing the defences of peace in
the minds of men, as laid down in
Unesco's Constitution. The Prize is
financed by a gift of $1 million from the
Japanese ship-building industry.
Unesco Medal
for Istanbul and Goreme
Unesco has issued a medal to enable
people to contribute to efforts to save
historic sites and monuments in Turkey.
The obverse side of the medal features
the great mosque of Suleymaniye in
Istanbul, where Unesco is concerned in
the preservation of ancient buildings and
quarters, and the reverse (below) shows
a Virgin and Child above the rugged land¬
scape of the Goreme valley in Cap-
padocia where Unesco is engaged on a
campaign to save the structures of chur¬
ches hewn out of the living rock. Design¬
ed by the Turkish artist Handan
Borutecene, the medal was struck at the
Paris mint and is available in gold, silver
and bronze. For further information
about this or other medals issued by
Unesco, please write to: Philatelic and
Numismatic Programme, Unesco, 7
Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices:
Unesco, 7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 58 French francs. 2 years (valid only in
France): 100 French francs. Binder for a year's issues:
46 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is publish ad monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, 8nd three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non -copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an inte mat ¡on ai reply coupon covering pos¬
tage. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors end
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions and
headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boun¬
daries on maps published in the magazine do not imply offi¬
cial endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the United
Nations.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform I microfilm endïor
microfiche) by: 11) University Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor.
Michigan 4SI 00. U.S.A.; (2) NCR. Microcard Edition. Indian
Head, Inc., 1 1 1 West 40th Street, New York, U.S.A.: 131 Hell
and Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road. Wooster, Ohio 44691.
U.S.A.
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Oiga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Howard Brabyn IParis)
French: Alain Lévéque {Paris}
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez- Santos {Paris)
Russian: Nikolai Ku2netsov (Paris)
Arabic: Sayed Osman (Paris)
German: Werner Merkli IBernel
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo!
Italian: Mario Guldotti (Rome)
Hindi: Rajmani Tiyyah (Delhil
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madrasl
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: Hossein Razmdjou (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeirol
Turkish: Mefra Mgazer (Istambul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Sinhala edition
of the Unesco Courier
We are pleased to announce the laun¬
ching of a quarterly Sinhala edition of the
Unesco Courier, published by the Sri
Lanka National Commission for Unesco,
Ministry of Justice, Hulftsdorp, Colombo
12. The publication of the first issue of
the Sinhala edition in August 1984
brought the total number of different
language editions of the Unesco Courier
up to 28, in addition to the quarterly
Braille selection.
New price of
the Unesco Courier
The continued rise in production and
distribution costs unfortunately obliges
us to increase the price of the Unesco
Courier. For 1 985, our new rates will be:
Annual subscription: 68 French francs
Two-year subscription (valid only in
France): 120 French francs
Single copy price: 7 French francs
Binder price: 52 French francs
Unesco's National Distributors (see list
opposite page) will inform subscribers of
equivalent rates in their countries.
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahiii: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es- Salami
Braille: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Vitomir Sudarski (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition: Neda el Khazen
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Serva t
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Special projects: Peggy Julien
Alt correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier Index 1984
January
1 984. George Orwell (J. Charpier). New trends in psychology (A. Oppenheimer).
Psychology in Black Africa (A.K. Tay). Anatomy of inequality (J. Sayinzoga). In
search of new economic structures (F. Perroux). Is crime a universal concept? (H.
Laborit). Culture shock and criminality (M. Rojas Mix).
February
LITERACY. 'A moral imperative' (A.-M. M'Bow). Cultural roots of literacy (M.
Guerra). Where there's a will (M. de Clerck). What next? (A. Ouane). The political
economy of literacy training (H. Gintis). World reports. Illiteracy in the 'Fourth
World' (A. Hamadache). Children in nomansland (S.A. Ramzi). Word within world
(P. Freiré). Unesco and the struggle against illiteracy. The 1983 literacy awards.
March
TAMIL CULTURE (S. Ramakrishnan). Scenes from everyday life (S.
Ramaswamy). Tamil cooking (T. Baskaran). Gateway to the gods (Ft.
Nagaswamy). Reflections on Siva Nataraja (A. Rodin). Bharata Natyam. Village
gods and heroes (photos). Sangam poetry (F. Gros). New writing in Tamil (S.
Ramakrishnan). Tamil women at the crossroads (CS. Lakshmi). Three great
scientists.
April
FOOD FOR A HUNGRY WORLD (K.A. Dakouré). Ill fares the land... (L. Brown).
Children in peril (V. Ramalingaswami). Malnutrition's tragic toll. Food first (P.
Lunven). Africa: the hunger belt. The promise of biotechnology (Y. Ovchinnikov).
Interdependence (P. Steidl-Meier). Unesco and nutrition education (S. Van Der
Vynckt). War, hunger, poverty (L. Echeverría).
May
REDISCOVERING THE AFRICAN PAST. (1) Africa from the 12th to the 16th
century: Four centuries of growth and splendour (D.T. Niane); Ife-Benin, two
kingdoms, one culture (A. Ryder). The secrets of Zimbabwe (B. Fagan). Trade
links from Europe to Cathay. West Africa's oldest metropolis. (2) Africa under
foreign domination, 1880-1935: The colonial challenge (A.A. Boahen); The
scramble for territory (G.N. Uzoigwe); An unequal combat (G.N. Uzoigwe); North
Africa, the long struggle (A. Laroui); West Africa, the fight for survival (M'Baye
Gueye, A.A. Boahen); East Africa, diplomacy and defiance (H. Mwanzi). The col¬
onial heritage (A.A. Boahen).
June
GREAT TRADE ROUTES. The adventure of world trade (A.J.B. Lima Sobrinho).
North Africa's great Roman road (E.E. Schneider). Europe's 'tin road' 2,500 years
ago (H. Schwab). Forever amber (W. Raunig). Fair city of Flanders (P. Morren).
The life of spice (Khoo Joo Ee). The silk road (Ma Yong). Sea, silk and sutras (R.
Tang, P. Colombel). The caravan routes of East Africa (J.F. Mbwiliza). The slave
trade (A. Kedros). A world athirst for oil (V. Labouret).
July
THE ARTISTIC GENIUS OF LATIN AMERICA. Two faces of Meso-American
art (J. Soustelle). Pre-Hispanic culture of Peru (J.F. Garcia Ruiz). The legacy of
colonial art (D. Bayón). Old Havana (M. Pereira). Brasilia (B.E. Panitz Bica). Four
artists (E. Glissant). Cándido Portinari (A.C. Calado). Armando Reverón (J.
Calzadilla). Bread art of Ecuador (J.-E. Adoum). Peruvian popular art (M. Checa
Solari). Master-craftsmen of Mexico (A. Lanz de Ríos). The dance of death (M.
Rojas-Mix). Castles in the air (R. Depestre). The artistic ferment of a continent (C
Rodriguez Saavedra).
August
ETERNAL CINEMA. The fragile art of film (R. Borde). African ¡mages (P.S
Vieyra). Egypt's film archive (K. Osman). The nitrate ultimatum (R. Edmondson,
H. Schou). The electronic alternative (K.H. Powers). Napoleon makes a come¬
back (R. Malkin). The world's missing films (S. Kula). The video grapevine (I. Man-
zi). India: it's never too late (P.K. Nair). Thailand: when the camera was king (D.
Sukvong). Cuba: a people in its pictures (M. Pereira). Cine qua non (F. Schmitt).
Birth of a notion (B. Matuszewski). Swiss film archive (F. Buache). The Gosfilmo¬
fond of Moscow (V.l. Dmitriev). Unesco and the preservation of moving images
(W. Klaue). The International Federation of Film Archives (R. Daudelin).
September
THE STORY OF THE UNIVERSE. The Big Bang (J. Gribbin). The infinitely big
and the infinitesimally small (D. Nanopoulos). Was there really a Big Bang? (J.
Narlikar). Red shift, the Doppler effect, Hubble's law. Galaxies and quasars; The
stellar menagerie (N. Henbest). The structure of the Universe (Y.B. Zeldovitch).
The canals of Mars. The origin of the elements. The mystery of life (C. Sagan).
A telescope in space (A. Duorocq).
October
THE GYPSIES. The Gypsy destiny (A.-M. M'Bow). The world their homeland (F.
de Vaux de Foletier). India's wandering blacksmiths (E. Cobas Puente). Bridging
the culture gap (J. Charlemagne). Europe's Gypsy craftsmen (M. Tomka). The
sharing, caring family (R.T. Janush). 'A wandering voice' (G. Soravia). Half a
million Gypsies victims of Nazi terror (M. Novitch). From campfire to footlights (N.
Slitchenko). Flamenco (F. Grande). The Gypsies of Brazil (A. Vilas-Boas da Mota).
November
SCIENCE AND SCIENCE FICTION. Co-explorers of reality (A. Goswami).
'Where I get my ideas' (I. Asimov). No science without fiction (A. Kazantsev).
Ariadne's thread (M. Pereira). Space settlements of tomorrow. Science fiction in
the classroom (C. Boutzev). 'Of what is past, or passing, or to come' (R. Brad¬
bury). Fantastic voyages in film. A Chinese utopia (Kang You Wei). Jules Verne
(A. Ducrocq).
December
RICE-LAND CIVILIZATIONS. The miracle of rice (M. Swaminathan). Rice in
myth and legend (Obayashi Taryo). Krushna the farmer (P. Mohanti). Pongal (G.
Deleury). China's 7,000-year-old crop (Hu Baoxin, Chang Shujia). The god who
stole the rice (Obayashi Taryo). Green winters on the Red River (Dao The Tuan).
A household god (Lee Kwang-Kyu). A city built on rice (Srisakra Vallibhotama).
'Never eat rice in the dark...' (S. Tan). The soul of a people (Z. Kling). Plov (B. An-
drianov). A touchstone of time and place (Rafaralahy-Bemananjara).
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Colling-
wood Victoria 3066; Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd.
P.O. Box 33, Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty.
Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-
agent: United Nations Association of Australia, P.O. Box 175,
5th floor. Ana House, 28 Elizabeth Street, Melbourne Victoria
3000. AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31,
A-101 1, Vienna. BAHAMAS. Nassau Stationers Ltd., P.O. Box
N-3138, Nassau. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books
International Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola,
Dacca 3. BARBADOS. University of the West Indies
Bookshop, Cave Hill Campus, P.O. Box 64, Bridgetown.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V.
Handelmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. BOTSWANA. Botswana Book Centre, P.O.
Box 91, Gaborone. BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co.
Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H 1M7.
CHINA. China National Publications Import and Export
Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Beijing. CYPRUS. "MAM",
Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena 51-1 13 02, Prague
1 ; Ve Smeckach 30, P.O.B. 790 - 1 1 1 - 27 Prague 1 (Permanent
display); Zahranicni literatura, 11 Soukenicka, Prague 1. For
Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893
31 Bratislava - CSSR. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export-OG
Tidsskriftservice 35 Norre Sogade, DK-1970 Kobenhavn K.
EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco
Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo. ETHIOPIA.
National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100
Helsinki 10; Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, Koivuvaarankuja 2,
01640 Vantaa 64. FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de
Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP. 12598-48. GERMAN
DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710
Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R.
FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier (German,
English, French and Spanish editions): Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher
Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57, D530O Bonn 3. For
other Unesco publications: Karger Verlag, Germering/München.
For scientific maps only: Geo Center, Postfach 800830,
Stuttgart 80. GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O.
Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University
Bookshop of Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legón,
P.O. Box 1 , Legón. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
HONG KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen
Industrial Mansion, 1 2 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book
Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon. Hong Kong Government
Information Services, Publication Centre, Baskerville House, 22
Ice Street. HUNGARY. Kultura-Bushimport - ABT, P.O.B. 149 -
H-1389, Budapest 62. ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co.,
H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd.,
Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 1 7 Chittaranjan
Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2;
5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh, Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahatma
Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001. Sub-Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.
1 7 Park Street, Calcutta 7001 6; Scindia House, New Delhi;
Publication Unit, Ministry of Education and Culture, Ex. AFO
Hutments, Dr. Rajendra Prasad Road, New Delhi 1 10001.
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl. Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl Dr Sam Ratulangie 37,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co.,
28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Enghélab Avenue. P.O. Box 314/1486,
Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco. 1188 Enghlab Av.,
Rostam Give Building, Zip Code 131 58, P.O. Box 1 1 365-4498,
Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, AI Rashid Street,
Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12; Tycooly International
Publ. Ltd 6 Crofton Terrace, Dun Laoghaire Co., Dublin. ISRAEL.
A.B.C. Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Alienby Road, Tel Aviv
61000. ITALY. Licosa (Librería Commissionaria Sansoni, S.p.A.)
Via Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552, 50121 Florence.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101
Water Lane, Kingston. University of the West Indies Bookshop,
Mona, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo
3-chome Bunkyo-ku Tokyo 1 13. KENYA. East African Publishing
House, P.O. Box 30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National
Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT.
The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait; for the
Unesco Courier; Farafalla Press Agency, P.O. Box SAFA 4541,
Kuwait. LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod.
Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA. Code and Yancy Bookshops
Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia. LIECHTENSTEIN : Eurocan
Trust Reg. P.O.B. 5 - 9494 Schaan. LIBYA. Agency for
Development of Publication & Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35,
Tripoli. LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue,
Luxembourg. MALAWI. Malawi Book Service, Head Office, P.O.
Box 30044 Chichiri, Blantyre 3. MALAYSIA. University of
Malaya Cooperative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur 22-1 1 . MALTA.
Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta.
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-
Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-
Carlo. NEPAL. Sajha Prakashan Polchowk, Kathmandu.
NETHERLANDS. KEESING BOEKEN B.V., Joan Muyskenweg,
22, Postbus 1118, 1000 BC Amsterdam. NETHERLANDS
ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad,
Curaçao. N.A. NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Office,
Government Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344,
Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace. P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch;
Alma Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box
1104, Dunedin, Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington.
NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The University
Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka; The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zaria. NORWAY. Johan Grundt Tanum,
P.O.B. 1 1 77 Sentrum - Oslo 1 , Narvesen A/S; Subscription and
Trade Book Service. P.O.B. 6125 Etterstad, Oslo 6; Universitets
Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, Postboks 307 Blindem, Oslo 3.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O.
Box No. 729, Lahore 3. PHILIPPINES. National Book Store, Inc.
701, Rizal Avenue, Manila D-404. POLAND. Orpan-lmport,
Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie
Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068 WARSAW. PORTUGAL. Dias &
Andrade Ltda. Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon.
SEYCHELLES. National Bookshop, P.O. Box 48, Mahé; New
Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé. SIERRA
LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone Diocesan
Bookshops, Freetown. SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (S)
Pte Ltd. Times Jurong, 2 Jurong Port Road, Singapore 2261 .
SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and
General, P.O. Box 951, Mogadiscio. SOUTH AFRICA. For the
Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Central News agency, P.O.
Box 1033, Johannesburg. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop,
100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2.
SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum.
SWEDEN. All publications A/B.CE. Fritzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356. 10327
Stockholm 1 6. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN Förbundet,
Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm; Wennergren-
Williams, Box 30004-S-104, 25 Stockholm; Esselte
Tidskriftscentralen, Gamla Brogatan 26, Box 62 - 101 20
Stockholm. SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag. 5
Rämistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 121 1, Geneva
11, CCP. 12-236. Librairies Payot also in Lausanne, Basle,
Berne, Vevey, Montreux, Neuchâtel and Zurich. TANZANIA.
Dares Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam.
THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road,
Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402; Bangkok: Suksapan Panit,
Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam
Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I. TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S.,
Istiklâl Caddesi, N° 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu, Istambul.
UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 7145, Kampala.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office. H.M.S.O., P.O.
Box 276, London, SW8 5DT, and Govt. Bookshops in London.
Edinburgh, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol; for
scientific maps only: McCarta Ltd., 122 King's Cross Road,
London WC 1X 9 DS. UNITED STATES. Unipub, 205 East
42nd Street, New York, N.Y. 10017. Orders for books &
Periodicals: P.O. Box 1222, Ann Arbor, Ml 48106. U.S.S.R.
Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Moscow, 121200. YUGOSLAVIA.
Mladost, llica 30/1 1, Zagreb; Cankarjeva Zalozba, Zopitarjeva 2,
Lubljana; Nolit, Terazije 27/1 1, Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd., P.O. Box 2664
Lusaka. ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union
Avenue, Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
Seeds of hope
Between 1960 and 1980. average rice
yields in Asia rose by 40 per cent and pro¬
duction by more than 60 per cent. This
dramatic increase was due largely to the in¬
troduction of modern rice varieties which
incorporate major technological innova¬
tions developed at the International Rice
Research Institute at Los Baños, in the
Philippines, these include: the development
of rice varieties that (a) make more effec
tive use of high rates of fertilizer application
and can grow at any season of the year
regardless of day length; (b) have the
genetic capacity to resist the attacks of cer¬
tain insects and diseases; and (c) have a
substantially shorter growth duration than
traditional rices. Above, a scientist tests a
newly developed variety for resistance to
insect pests.
Priori Georg Geister ' Rapho. Pans
]]>
</page>
</document>
