<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="062315eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
A window open on the world
m I
November 1964 (17th year)
Price: 1/6-stg. (U.K.)
Canada : 30 cents
France : 1 F
, *?2**
"*-..
n=
120 000
.¿y-v-
A er year
X J%%
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Signed in Moscow, August 5, 1963
(Preamble and Article I)
The Governments of the Union
of Soviet Socialist Republics, the
United Kingdom of Great Britain
and Northern Ireland, and the
United States of America, herein¬
after referred to as the "original
parties".
Proclaiming as their principal
aim the speediest possible ach¬
ievement of an agreement on
general and complete disarma¬
ment under strict international
control in accordance with the
objectives of the United Nations
ARTICLE I
which would put an end to the
armaments race and eliminate
the incentive to the production
and testing of all kinds of wea¬
pons, including nuclear weapons.
Seeking to achieve the discon¬
tinuance of all test explosions of
nuclear weapons for all time,
determined to continue negotia¬
tions to this end, and desiring to
put an end to the contamination
of man's environment by radio¬
active substances.
Have agreed as follows :
1. Each of the parties to this treaty undertakes to prohibit,
to prevent, and not to carry out any nuclear weapon test
explosion, or any other nuclear explosion, at any place under
its jurisdiction or control :
(a) In the atmosphere; beyond its limits, including outer
space; or under water, including territorial waters or
high seas; or
(b) In any other environment if such explosion causes
radioactive debris to be present outside the territorial
limits of the state under whose jurisdiction or control
such explosion is conducted. It is understood in this
connexion that the provisions of this sub-paragraph
are without prejudice to the conclusion of a treaty
resulting in the permanent banning of all nuclear test
explosions, including all such explosions underground,
the conclusion of which, as the parties have stated in
the preamble to this treaty, they seek to achieve.
2. Each of the parties to this treaty undertakes further¬
more to refrain from causing, encouraging, or in any way
participating in the carrying out of any nuclear weapon test
explosion, or any other nuclear explosion, anywhere which
would take place in any of the environments described, or
have the effect referred to, in paragraph 1 of this Article.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
NOVEMBER 1964
1 7TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
Page
2
4
6
11
14
TEXT OF MOSCOW TEST BAN TREATY
120 THOUSAND MILLION DOLLARS A YEAR
What the world spends on arms
NUCLEAR WEAPONS AND WORLD SANITY
by Linus Pauling
FALL-OUT HAZARDSNOW AND YESTERDAY
Radioactive dangers reduced by the test ban treaty
by Alexander M. Kuzin
THE SWORD AND THE PLOUGHSHARES
How the resources freed by disarmament might be used
18 TAPESTRIES BY JEAN LURÇAT
On man in the atomic age
20 THE PUGWASH MOVEMENT
Responsibilities of the scientist in world affairs
21 UNESCO AND DISARMAMENT
22 THE ECONOMIC IMPACT OF DISARMAMENT
26 DISARMAMENT AND THE DEVELOPING NATIONS
27 THE LAST FLOWER
A parable in pictures
by James Thurber
29 PEACEFUL USES FOR MILITARY ENERGY
by Ritchie Calder
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
THE UNITED NATIONS EDUCATIONAL, SCIENTIFIC AND CULTURAL ORGANIZATION
Published monthly by UNESCO
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7", France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
René Caloz
Associate Editors
English Edition :
French Edition
Spanish Edition :
Russian Edition :
German Edition :
Arabic Edition :
Japanese Edition:
kalian Edition :
Ronald Fenton
Jane Albert Hesse
Arturo Despouey
Victor Goliachkov
Hans Rieben (Berne)
Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in July and August when
it is bi-monthly (1 1 issues a year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German,
Arabic.Japanese, and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed by H.H.
Stationery Office, P. O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in The Readers' Guide to
Periodical Liternture published by H. W. Wilaon Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates : 15/-stg. ; S 3.00 (Canada);
10 French Francs or equivalent. Single copies 1/6-stg ;
30 cents ; 1 F.
(M.C. 64.1., 196 A)
N« 11, 1964
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chitf.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
THE United Nations General Assembly has
called disarmament "the most important
question facing the world today." Two aspects of
this vital question are dealt with in this issue of
The Unesco Courier.
The first of these is the significance of the Nuclear
Test Ban Treaty signed in Moscow just over one
year ago, which was a first step towards disarma¬
ment and which has already halted the rising threat
of radiation hazards for all mankind. The second
aspect is the significance of disarmament in terms
of housing, hospitals, schools, laboratories, farm
equipment, in short, in terms of everything that
could contribute to a better life for everyone.
In 1962 the United Nations completed its major
study on "Economic and Social Consequences of
Disarmament", and in the same year the General
Conference of Unesco voted a resolution which
emphasized the importance of "the diversion of
even a small proportion of the resources which
would be released by general and complete disar¬
mament to the long-term programmes of Unesco
for the planning and development of education,
scientific research and the development of mass
communication media." Unesco has therefore
undertaken studies on the impact which general
disarmament would have on education, science
and culture, and has urged its member states to
make similar studies.
Disarmament would open up vast prospects for all
mankind. But it will be achieved only through the
efforts of all men. This challenge will be faced
more readily if both its problems and its promise
are clearly understood. The editors of The Unesco
Courier hope that the present issue will contribute
in some small measure to that understanding.
World ex on arms
1 20,000 MILLION DOLLARS A YEAR
H t\ LL the problems of transition connected with disarmament could be met by appro-
^^Lpriate national and international measures. There should be no doubt that the diversion
to peaceful purposes of the resources now in military use could be accomplished to the benefit of all
countries and lead to the improvement of world economic and social conditions. The achievement-
of general and complete disarmament would be an unqualified blessing for mankind."
This view, expressed unanimously by an international panel of economists, is the final conclusion of
a major study entitled "Economic and Social Consequences of Disarmament" published by the United
Nations. "It is particularly encouraging to discover", writes U Thant, Secretary-General of the United
Nations, in its preface, "that it has proved possible for a group of experts drawn from countries with
different economic systems and at different stages of economic development to reach unanimous
agreement on a subject that until recently has been so beset by ideological differences."
The study reviews the resources devoted to military purposes; it shows the peaceful uses to which
these resources might be put when released; it examines the conversion problems that might arise,
and the impact of disarmament on international economic relations and on aid for economic develop-
4 ment; and it calls attention to some social consequences of disarmament.
This historic U.N. report deserves to be better known. Some of its major findings are summarized in
this issue (see opposite, and pages 14 to 17 and 22 to 26).
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
HE present level of military expenditure not only
represents a grave political danger but also
imposes a heavy economic and social burden on most
countries. It absorbs a large volume of human and ma¬
terial resources of all kinds which could be used to increase
economic and social welfare throughout the world both
in the highly industrialized countries, which at the present
time incur the bulk of the world's military expenditures,
and in the less developed areas.
On the basis of available data, the world appears to
be expending roughly $120,000 million annually on mili¬
tary expenditure (1). This is equivalent to about 8 to 9 per
cent of the world's annual output of goods and services
or to at least two-thirds of the entire national income
of all the developing countries, and is close to the value
of the world's annual exports of all commodities.
Nearly 20 million persons now serve in the world's
armed forces. When other persons occupied directly or
indirectly in servicing the needs of these armies are. added,
the total may well amount to over 50 million. The total
volume of manpower and of other resources devoted to
military use at the present times is thus very large indeed.
In many countries the estimates of military expenditure
range between 1 and 5 per cent of gross domestic product,
while in others, particularly in some of the larger countries,
(1) A 1962 estimate. Today's armaments' bill is believed to have
risen to between $130,000 million and $140,000 million.
the corresponding ratio ranges between 5 and 10 per cent.
The great bulk of the world's military expenditure Is highly
concentrated in a handful of countries and industrial sectors.
About 85 per cent of the world's military outlays is accoun¬
ted for by seven countries Canada, Federal Republic of
Germany, France, mainland China, U.S.S.R., United King¬
dom and United States.
Among the major military powers military production is
highly concentrated in a few industrial sectors, notably
munitions, electrical machinery, instruments and related
products, and transportation equipment, including airplanes
and missiles. In most other industries military outlays
account for a relatively small proportion of total demand.
Industries dependent on military expenditure also have a
high degree of concentration in certain regions and cities.
Total military expenditure in all the developing countries
amounts to about one-tenth of that of the industrial private
enterprise economies. This means that although many
developing countries devote significant proportions of their
resources to military purposes, the great bulk of the
resources released by disarmament would be concentrated
in a very few countries.
The situation is rather different in those countries that
rely upon imports for their supplies of military goods or
in which the major part of military expenditure is for the
pay and subsistence of the armed forces, rather than
for their equipment. In such cases, the resources devoted
to military purposes consist essentially of manpower and
foreign exchange. This is especially true of the developing
countries.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
ON August 5, 1963 the world learned with relief
that a Nuclear Test Ban treaty had been signed in
Moscow (see page 2). This treaty will go down in history
as the first important step on the road to complete disarmament.
Concluded between the United Kingdom, the United States
and the U.S.S.R., it has since been countersigned by over
100 countries. The banning of nuclear tests in the atmosphere,
in outer space and under water, brought not only a feeling of
relief, but also an immense hope. In May 1964, the Executive
Board of Unesco welcomed the Test Ban treaty as "a noteworthy
contribution towards the easing of international tensions, as
tangible proof of the possibility of a peaceful settlement of
international problems and as a step towards paving the way
for agreement on general and complete disarmament" and it
expressed the hope "that this treaty will gain universal support".
The first effects of the treaty have become apparent: there has
already been a significant reduction in the level of radioactive
contamination whose threat for all mankind would have become
steadily greater if nuclear weapons tests had continued. This
was announced recently by the U.N. Scientific Committee on
the Effects of Atomic Radiation. On page 11 one of the mem¬
bers of this committee. Prof. Alexander M. Kuzin, a prominent
Soviet bio-chemist, reveals how the health hazards from
radioactive fall-out are being reduced. Below, Professor Linus
Pauling evokes some vital world problems of the nuclear age.
On June 19 of this year the noted U.S. scientist, Linus
Pauling, spoke at Unesco House in Paris on Science Education
and its Responsibilities. Professor Pauling has the rare dis¬
tinction of being a double Nobel Prize Winner. For his efforts
over the past two decades on behalf of world peace and to
outlaw war he received the 1962 Nobel Peace Prize (awarded
in 1963); his discoveries in molecular chemistry won him the
Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1954. Professor Pauling was invi¬
ted to speak under the Unesco programme to promote a series
of university lectures by distinguished visiting scientists. The
Unesco programme has been organized to show how impor¬
tant is the role of science in the world we live in today. Below
we present a few salient passages from Prof. Pauling's address
dealing with the Test Ban Treaty, modern nuclear weapons
and the need for disarmament.
NUCLEAR WEAPONS
AND WORLD SANITY
by Linus Pauling
Nobel Peace Prize 1962
Nobel Prize for Chemistry 1954
The world's stockpiles of atomic weapons are now believed to
total the equivalent of 16,000 twenty-megaton bombs. The power
of a single twenty-megaton bomb is equal to the effect of a 1,000
bomber raid of World War II, repeated day after day for 14 years.
Above, a European city destroyed in the battles of World War II.
©APN
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
M'-*'
--%>
f*
l T is the duty of society as a whole to make the
important decisions regarding social, political
and economic matters but it is the special duty of the
scientist to contribute with his special knowledge and
understanding to a greater extent than other people and to
help his fellow citizens to reach the right decisions.
When the Bomb Test Treaty was being discussed last
year there was one point that was very difficult to com¬
prehend and yet which it was vital that everyone be made
to understand. That was the nature and amount of the
damage done to the people of the world and to the pool
of human germ plasm (that is, to our unborn children) by
the radioactive materials liberated in the testing of nuclear
weapons. Never before had it been dangerous to people
the world over for military establishments to carry out tests
of their future weapons; but now damage has already been
done to members of the human race by the nuclear wea¬
pons tests.
One of the great discoveries of the last few years has
been the unravelling of the mechanism of heredity. Scien¬
tists have found that the genes are molecules of deoxyri
bonucleic acid (DNA) which constitute the units of heredity.
These genes, as they are passed on from parents to chil¬
dren, determine the nature of the new organismsour
offspring.
There are about 100,000 genes in the fertilized ovum,
50,000 coming from the father, 50,000 from the mother. If
the embryo has a poor collection of genes it will die before
reaching term. Whether a child is healthy or not after
birth is largely determined by the genes. Seven per cent
of the children born have gross congenital physical or
mental defects, and it is estimated that about half of these
defects are due to mutated genes. For example, about
one child in twelve hundred is born with a newly mutated
gene for achondroplasia, which affects the cartilage so
that the long bones of the body do not grow. Most of
these children die in infancy but some survive. They are
achondroplastic dwarfs with large hands, large heads but
with short "long bones". This is just one of the thousands
of ways in which gene mutation can increase human
suffering.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
NUCLEAR WEAPONS (Cont'd)
The threat to unborn millions
High energy radiation, it Is known, causes gene mutation,
and it is possible to estimate the amount of gene mutation
resulting from radiation from caesium 137, carbon 14 and
other radioactive nuclei produced in the testing of nuclear
weapons and liberated into the atmosphere. These radio¬
active substances, and particularly carbon 14, will continue
to produce defective children for thousands of years.
If the human race survives and world population conti¬
nues at a reasonable level, then I have calculated (and the
U.N. Scientific Committee on the Effects of Atomic Radia¬
tion reached essentially the same conclusion, as did also
the Federal Radiation Council set up three years ago by
the U.S. government to study the damage done by high
energy radiation) that the bomb tests carried out thus far,
and amounting to 600 megatons, will in the course of time
affect sixteen million children so severely that they will
suffer gross physical or mental defects or embryonic, neo¬
natal, or childhood deaths.
BOUT one per cent of this total, or 160,000 In¬
fants, will be stricken in the first generation, but
the damage will continue with only slight decrease genera¬
tion after generation, year after year, for thousands of years.
The figure of 160,000 may seem like a small number when
compared to the four million or so children who are born
each year with gross physical or mental defects caused by
natural radioactivity and cosmic radiation which cannot be
prevented and other causes of gene defects hard to control.
Nevertheless we should not say that a few thousand
additional defective children born each year are not a
matter of any concern to us. As President John F. Kennedy
said In a broadcast to the American people on the Test
Ban Treaty in 1963, "the loss of even one human life or
the malformation of even one baby, who may be born long
after we are gone, should be of concern to us all. Our
children and grandchildren are not merely statistics towards
which we can be indifferent."
I should point out that estimates on this subject are very
difficult to make. The figures I have just given are uncer¬
tain, and everyone should learn to understand the meaning
of probability and uncertainty, that is, probable error. The
figure of 16 million that I have indicated is usually described
as being uncertain by a factor of five either way. So
perhaps the sacrifice we are making is only three million
persons one-fifth of 16 million, or perhaps it is 80 million
five times the 16 million, and of course the uncertainties
may be really greater than this.
Now, one 20-megaton bomb detonated in the atmosphere
or at the surface of the earth liberates radioactive materials
into the atmosphere which will, according to the best
estimates that we can make, cause gross damage or death
to 550,000 unborn children. This is the probable sacrifice
of the testing of a single H-bomb by any one nation.
Everyone must understand this.
We know that large amounts of high energy radiation
produce cancer. If we accept the principle that high
energy radiation even in small amounts is also cancerogenic
as I believe it is then it is possible to calculate the
sacrifice of human beings now living to the bomb tests.
The estimated figure is that two million human beings now
living will die five, ten, fifteen or twenty years earlier than
otherwise because of cancer or other diseases produced
by the high energy radiation liberated in the bomb tests
carried out so far. This is about one person in fifteen
8 hundred in the world, and it gives us some idea of the
nature of atomic weapons in so far as the tests go.
Of course there would be a tremendously greater amount
of contamination with radioactive materials all over the
earth if there were to be a nuclear war. In addition to the
destructive and lethal effects of blast, fire, and immediate
high energy radiation, there would be the effects of local
fall-out, so that survivors within hundreds of miles of where
the bombs exploded would generally be exposed to about
half of the lethal dose that causes acute radiation sickness
and death within a few days, and these survivors would
have their portion of the pool of human germ-plasm
seriously affected. Their lives would be shortened consi¬
derably on the average by some ten or fifteen years by
exposure to this high energy radiation.
Let us now turn to another question the stock-piling of
nuclear weapons. The amount of explosives existing in
the world is enormous, but there has been very little
discussion of how great the world's nuclear stock piles are.
The standard nuclear bomb today is the 20-megaton
bomb. (One megaton equals a million tons.) The Soviet
Union has detonated a 60-megaton bomb, which was appa¬
rently only the first two stages of a 100-megaton bomb. A
100-megaton bomb involves only about three and a half
tons of explosive material and probably can be carried in
a single large rocket from one continent to another. But
100-megaton bombs don't make very much sense because
a 20-megaton bomb is big enough to destroy any city on
earth. '
A 20-megaton bomb exploded over any city on earth
would destroy it completely and kill most of the people in
it. It would produce a crater of twenty kilometres in
diameter; it would set off fires 50 to 100 kilometres away,
producing a tremendous fire storm and would damage
people by the immediate high energy radiation and by the
radioactive fallout. Even people 300 kilometres away would
be killed.
During the second World War there were some great
bombing raids on German cities. In one such raid, on one
night, one thousand aeroplanes each carrying four tremen¬
dous one-ton blockbusters destroyed much of the city of
Hamburg and killed an estimated 75,000 people. If there
were to be such a raid on, say, Paris today and another
such 1,000 plane raid tomorrow, and then another the next
day and so on day after day for fourteen years, the explo¬
sives delivered would have the power of one 20-megaton
bomb.
Y estimate is that the stock piles of the world
comprise about 16,000 of these 20-megaton
bombs or the equivalent of them. Now, there aren't 16,000
large cities in the world and one might well ask why this
irrationally great amount of explosive material has been
produced. I shall answer this by saying that it is because
the system of science education has been faulty in the past
so that the people who were making the decisions could
not have had a clear understanding of what they were doing
if indeed anyone did make the decisions, for there has
been some doubt as to whether the development of these
tremendously great stock piles was the result of decision¬
making rather than some sort of accident and shifting of
responsibility primarily in the United States and the Soviet
Union and perhaps too in Great Britain to some extent.
And yet in the Franck Report written by scientists work¬
ing on the atomic bomb project in the U.S. in 1945, a
prediction was made of the future nuclear situation in
the world which has turned out to be correct up to the pre¬
sent time.
CONT'D ON PAGE 10
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
WRITINGONTHE
WALL. Of what
was once a man
there is left only a
shadow on a wall.
For a single instant,
on August 6, 1945
at Hiroshima, the
man's body absorbed
the radiation and
heat from the atomic
blast and traced the
the outline on the
building behind. The
man vanished. The
ladder remained.
© Asahi
i^V. ^**k-
- &&* - jSfc$wiM
$&
N^è*^îS
"n.
V-i-
» . -
»"' '. ' f..i Ï
&
^
<'*mmi#*' *
" 'iw !
* -.
c?-*' .*.-. ¿; ^
¿.
ipm
&f*
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
NUCLEAR WEAPONS (Cont'd)
The goal of disarmament no longer a dream'
320,000 megatons is my estimate of the size of the
world's present nuclear stockpiles. If ten per cent of
the stockpile (32,000 megatons) were to be used in a
nuclear war with the bombs exploded on the average
within a hundred and fifty kilometres of the targets (you
don't have to hit the target in order to get the result) then
60 days after the day on which the war was fought and
we assume that It would cover Europe as a whole, all the
Soviet Union and the United States of the 800 million
people living in these regions, 720 million would be dead,
60 million severely injured, and there would be 20 million sur¬
vivors with only minor injuries, but having to cope with the
problems of complete destruction of all cities, metropolitan
districts, and means of communication and transportation,
complete disruption of society, death of all livestock, and
gross radioactive contamination of all growing foods. This
would be the end of this part of the world, and how great
the damage would be to the rest of the world no one has
been able to estimate in a reliable way.
One can understand why it has been said over and over
again that no dispute between nations can justify nuclear
war. U Thant, Secretary-General of the United Nations,
recently said: "Anybody who proposes the use of atomic
weapons for destructive purposes is, in my view, out of
his mind." We are forced now, in the way that Alfred
Nobel foresaw, to abolish war from the world. But it is
a difficult and complex problem. And yet I feel that
everyone must accept this conclusion. It is the duty of
everyone to work in whatever way he can to achieve the
world from which war has been abolished. This the only
rational course for the world to follow.
The partial test ban treaty signed at Moscow last year
was a great step forward. I regret very much that this
treaty was not made three years earlier, during the long
period when no bomb tests were carried out by any nation
except France, which only made very small bomb tests.
Of the total of 600 megatons tested, 450 megatons or
three-quarters of the total were tested in the last three
years. Millions of unborn children were sacrificed because
of the inability to see that the test ban solution could have
been accepted three years earlier. I hope that further
mistakes of this sort are not made. I am grateful for the
bomb test treaty, but of course we must move forward.
The test ban treaty is just the beginning.
The further steps that need to be taken were clearly
outlined, I think, in the great speech that President Kennedy
gave in the United Nations in September 1961, when he
said: "The goal of disarmament is no longer a dream. It
Is a practical matter of life or death. The risks inherent in
disarmament pale in comparison to the risks inherent in a
continuing, unlimited arms race."
F the proposals he made, one, the banning of
nuclear weapons in outer space, has been ac¬
complished by resolution in the United Nations. (For text,
see page 13.) As for stopping the production of fis¬
sionable material, some steps are being taken in this
direction by agreement between the U.S.A. and the U.S.S.R.
The steps toward general and complete disarmament
will, 1 think, be taken only with great difficulty. I should
like to see some action taken in the meantime that would
decrease the chance of outbreak of a devastating nuclear
war, perhaps through some psychological or technological
accident or through some combination of circumstances
such that even the wisest of national leaders could not
prevent the descent to catastrophe.
In my Nobel lecture in Oslo last December [delivered on
the occasion of the award to Prof. Pauling of the Nobel
Prize for Peace] I proposed that the American stock pile
of nuclear weapons and the Soviet stock pile of nuclear
weapons should, separately, be put under joint national and
international control, so that the Soviet nuclear weapons
could not be used except with the permission both of the
Soviet Premier and of the Secretary-General of the United
Nations, and that the American nuclear weapons could not
be used except by permission both of the President of the
United States and of the Secretary-General of the U.N.
I also proposed that there should be in authority in the
control stations in both countries, United Nations personnel
as well as Soviet personnel in the U.S.S.R. on the one hand
and U.N. personnel as well as American personnel in the
U.S.A. on the other. I believe that even a first step in this
direction, the step of having United Nations observers in
these control stations, would be of much value in increasing
our security and decreasing the chance that these weapons
would be used.
I LOOK forward to the time when there is in
existence in the world a satisfactory system of
international law taking the place of war. In working to
abolish war from the world we are working also for human
freedom, for the rights of individual human beings. It is
war, militarism, and extreme nationalism that are the great
enemies of the individual human being in every country. I
believe that as we achieve the goal of peace in the world
and disarmament, we shall see great improvement in the
social, political and economic systems of all nations and
in the rights of individual human beings all over the world.
The idea of replacing war by world law is an old one and
it has continued to be advanced up to the present time.
Only now has the time come when it will be accepted. As
Nobel said, "When it becomes possible for two army corps
to annihilate one another in a second then war will be
abandoned." It is now possible not only for two army
corps but for two great nations to destroy one another
essentially and completely in a period of time little longer
than a second in a few hours.
Seventy-five years ago the Norwegian legislature, the
Storting, took the lead in proposing that there be a requir¬
ed system of arbitration for disputes between nations.
The Storting at that time said: "The Storting is convinced
that this idea has the support of an overwhelming propor¬
tion of our people. Just as law and justice have long ago
replaced the role of the fist in settling disputes between
man and man, so the idea of settling disputes among
peoples and nations by arbitration is making its way with
irresistible strength. More and more, war appears to the
general consciousness as a vestige of prehistoric barbarism
and a curse to the human race."
We have now come to the time in the history of the world
when we shall eliminate this vestige of prehistoric harbar-
ism, this curse to the human race. And I believe that
we are fortunate to be able to contribute to the achieve¬
ment of this great goal, when not only shall we have
abolished war with its suffering from the world but also
have made it possible to utilize the resources of the world
and the discoveries of scientists and the results of man's
labour for the benefit of human beings all over the world.
I believe that we shall in the course of time build a world
that is characterized by social, political and economic jus¬
tice for all human beings, and a culture worthy of man's
intelligence.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
FALL-OUT HAZARDS
NOW & YESTERDAY
tIN 1954, following a long series of atomic and
hydrogen weapons' tests, scientists first drew
public attention to the fact that the atmosphere, the oceans
and the land surfaces of the globe were being contaminated
by radioactive fall-out.
They revealed that great quantities of radioactive
substances ejected into the atmosphere by each explosion
were being caught up by air currents, carried across the
globe and slowly deposited on land and sea; these radio¬
active elements were then being rapidly absorbed by
plants, and were entering the bodies of men and animals
through vegetable foods.
Many scientists of the world warned of the great dangers
presented to humanity by the rise in the radioactivity of the
environment, and called for an end to the testing of atomic
and hydrogen weapons.
In 1955, the United Nations set up a special committee,
consisting of leading scientists from 15 countries, to make
an objective assessment of the health hazards of radiation
from nuclear explosions. In 1958 this committee reported
to the U.N. General Assembly that if the tests went on at
no greater rate than that of 1954, hundreds of thousands
of people would succumb to hereditary disease, and to
by Alexander M. Kuzin
Member of the U.N. Scientific Committee
on the Effects of Atomic Radiation
leukemia and cancer caused by the increased radiation
background.
Meanwhile, the logic of the arms race caused each new
series of nuclear text explosions to be considerably more
powerful than its predecessor. There was a consequent
increase in the radioactive contamination of the atmosphere,
of the earth's surface and of the human body.
When an atomic, and especially a hydrogen bomb, is set
off in the atmosphere, it produces huge quantities of neu¬
trons which transform the nitrogen of the atmosphere into
radioactive carbon (C-14). Small quantities of C-14 are
always present in the atmosphere where they are formed
through the action of cosmic rays. But the nuclear tests
produced a rapid increase in the level of C-14. The 1958
tests alone raised the content of C-14 in 1959 to almost 30
per cent above its natural level, and the 1961-1962 tests
increased this concentration by nearly 90 per cent over
and above the normal quantity.
Atomic explosions also produce large amounts of two
other radioactive substances strontium-90 and caesium-
137. The 1961-1962 explosions nearly doubled the content
of strontium-90, as compared with the earlier tests and 11
there was a similar increase in caesium-137. Both these
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
IRRADIATED
MOUSE
NORMAL
MOUSE
HOW
RADIATION
DEFORMS
AN EMBRYO
The extreme vulnerability
of an embryo to the effects
of atomic radiation is illus¬
trated strikingly in these
X-ray photos. In compar¬
ison with the normal new¬
born mouse (right) the sec¬
ond (left) is stunted and
shows marked bone mal¬
formation. It had been
exposed to radiation eleven
days after its conception
the equivalent of four
weeks of development in the
case of a human embryo.
© from "Radiology" n° 3, 1952
J^fc W ...
1*4
"4 «a £
12
FALL-OUT HAZARDS (Cont'd)
are long-lived isotopes, with a half-life (1) of about 30
years, which easily penetrate the human system through
food and then cause protracted irradiation of the internal
body tissues.
When nuclear explosions take place, the level of radio¬
activity is also increased by short-lived isotopes (like
iodine-131) which easily find their way into milk and thus
into the bodies of children, thereby increasing the possibi¬
lity of subsequent disease. The average levels of radio¬
active iodine content in milk rose sharply in the years of
the most intensive nuclear tests.
The danger of which the scientists had warned was
mounting from year to year. Reporting to the U.N. General
Assembly in 1962, the U.N. Scientific Committee unanim¬
ously emphasized that the immediate prohibition of nuclear
blasts would be of the greatest benefit to mankind.
Many organizations called for the cessation of nuclear
tests and an end to the contamination of the environment
with radioactive substances as a first step towards the
relaxation of international tensions and to general disarm¬
ament.
Thus the nations of the world hailed with satisfaction the
signing on August 5, 1963, of the Moscow Treaty Banning
Nuclear Weapons Tests in the Atmosphere, Under Water
and in Outer Space. Thanks to the Treaty, no products of
(I) The time needed tot halt of the origina/ atoms of a radioactive substance
to disintegrate.
radioactive explosions have been poisoning the world
around us for the past year or more.
Has there, in fact, been any change in the amount of
radiation to which people have been exposed during that
period? Information reaching the U.N. Scientific Commit¬
tee on the Effects of Atomic Radiation indicates that there
has already been a reduction in the amount of radioactive
substances being absorbed into the human body, especially
in the case of children. There has been a sharp drop, for
instance, in the amount of short-lived isotopes in the
surrounding environment. In 1963-1964, their average
absorption by the human body was down to less than one
per cent of the amount absorbed during 1961-1962, when
the tests were on. As 1964 runs out, it will be virtually
impossible to detect any pollution of the earth by short¬
lived radioactive substances.
But long-lived radioactive elements such as strontium-90
and caesium-137 pose greater problems. Intensive
research over the last ten years suggests that their rate
of fallout n-ns its course in twelve to eighteen months
from the lower strata of the atmosphere, but takes much
longer to complete up to three years or more when
coming from the upper atmosphere layers.
The bulk of the radioactive debris from the 1961-1962
explosions, actually produced fallout in 1963. Thanks to
the halt of testing in the sea, on land and in the air, new
fallout in 1964 can be expected to drop by 30 per cent, as
compared with 1963.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
On the basis that radioactive debris remains in the
atmosphere for an average of two years, it is safe to say
that as from 1965 there will be a sharp cumulative drop
in the fallout of strontium-90 and caesium-137. The overall
amount of strontium-90 and caesium-137 in the soil is still
rising and will contine to rise for another two or three years,
when it too will decline due to radioactive decay.
But in spite of the increase of strontium-90 and caesium-
137 in the soil, far less of these substances will be absorb¬
ed by human beings in 1965 than was the case in 1962-
1963. The reason is that these elements penetrate plants
in two ways. Through its roots a plant takes in calcium
from the soil and also radioactive strontium, which has
similar chemical properties. Its roots also absorb caesium-
137 along with potassium. This process will continue for
some time to come. But fresh radioactive substances
which are deposited directly on the leaves of growing
plants are absorbed at a much greater rate. In the years
of peak fallout, the bulk of the radioactive contamination
of vegetable foods took place through new fallout.
Thanks to the Test Ban Treaty new fallout began to
decrease as early as 1964, and a considerable reduction is
expected in 1965. This will lessen the radioactive pollution
of foods and reduce the entry of radioactive substances
into human beings and animals through the food they eat.
Over the years the reduction will be even more marked.
With the cessation of tests, our environment will be grad¬
ually cleared of artificial radioactive carbon (C-14).
Although it has a long half-life (nearly 5,000 years), it will
be disappearing as it dissolves in the waters of the oceans.
This year the U.N. Committee on the Effects of Atomic
Radiation estimated that if the Test Ban Treaty is observed,
the artificial radioactive carbon content is bound to fall
from 85 per cent over and above the natural level in 1964,
to 60 per cent in 1969, and that it will be down to three per
cent by the end of the century.
Children are the most sensitive to the effects of radia¬
tion. That is why there has always been so much concern
over the fact that during the tests large amounts of radio¬
active iodine, radioactive strontium and radioactive caesium
were being absorbed by children via milk, and that the
strontium-90 content in children's bones was increasing
from year to year. However, their food is now being freed
of these noxious elements. It is entirely free of radioactive
\ \
A scientist at a nuclear research centre uses a
a special atmospheric dust sampler to test for
radioactivity in the air. Particles drawn in by
this device are tested with a Geiger counter.
CEA
iodine, and the amount of other radioactive substances is
dropping.
Many thousands of children would inevitably have fallen
victim to disease if the tests had been continued; many
other potential victims will be spared over the next few
years by the strict observance of the Moscow Treaty.
Banning Nuclear Tests in the Atmosphere, Under Water
and in Outer Space.
The Moscow Test-Ban Treaty marks a first stage in the
easing of international tension ; it also demonstrates tho
possibility that the threat of thermo-nuclear war can bo
averted, that the use of nuclear weapons can be banned
and that agreement can be reached on general and com¬
plete disarmament the present hope and goal of all whose
concern is for the future of mankind.
NUCLEAR WEAPONS BANNED IN SPACE
Resolution of the U. N. General Assembly, 17 October, 1963 :
The General Assembly... determined to take steps to
prevent the spread of the arms race to outer space,
Welcomes the expressions by the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics and the United States
of America of their intention not to station in outer space any objects carrying nuclear
weapons or other kinds of weapons of mass destruction;
Solemnly calls upon all States:
a) To refrain from placing in orbit around the earth any objects carrying nuclear
weapons or any other kinds of weapons of mass destruction, installing such weapons
on celestial bodies, or stationing such weapons in outer space in any other manner;
b) To refrain from causing, encouraging or in any way participating in the conduct
of the foregoing activities. 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
THE SWORD AND THE PL
14
"HERE are so many competing claims for
usefully employing the resources released by
disarmament that the real problem is to establish a scale
of priorities. The most urgent of these claims would
undoubtedly already have been largely satisfied were it
not for the armaments race.
The resources liberated by disarmament within any
country could be employed in part to promote economic
and social progress at home and in part to expand foreign
aid. The main civilian purposes for which the freed re¬
sources whether domestic or foreign in origin, could be
applied, may be classified as follows:
Raising standards of personal consumption of goods
and services;
Expanding or modernizing productive capacity through
Investment In new plant and equipment;
Promoting housing construction, urban renewal,
Including slum clearance, and rural development;
Improving and expanding facilities for education,
health, welfare, social security, cultural development, scien¬
tific research, etc.
The resources freed by disarmament could ultimately be
used for any one or more of these purposes and in any
combination. Labour can be retrained and, where ne¬
cessary, can move to other areas. As old equipment
becomes obsolete it can be replaced by new equipment
oriented to new patterns of demand. In the long run,
there should be little difficulty in adapting resources to
needs.
BY contrast, in the very short run the range of
choice may be somewhat more limited. It takes
time to turn swords into ploughshares or to make an office
clerk or factory worker out of a soldier. Studies in some
Industrial countries have shown that the productive
capacities released from military use would be much more
immediately adaptable to the increased output of consumer
durables and industrial equipment than to the production
of houses, food clothing or educational facilities.
Thus, in the transition period, countries may wish to
take into account not merely the unsatisfied needs for
higher consumption, investment and foreign aid, but also
the extent to which alternative patterns of new expenditure
would take full advantage of the particular resources that
disarmament would make available. Some major military
powers now have fairly confortable margins of productive
capacity. In these cases it is unikely that disarmament would
generate many new demands that could not fairly readily
be satisfied from available resources.
In the centrally planned economies, even though they
have generally been operating approximately at capacity,
the transfer of industrial capacity and labour force to the
production of goods for peaceful uses could be achieved
in a relatively short time. This transfer could be readily
achieved by measures formulated within the framework of
the general economic plans which can ensure a desirable
balance between demand and resources.
In the developing countries the principal resource
released, apart from the purely financial, would be man¬
power, both skilled and unskilled. In some cases a signi¬
ficant proportion of Industrial and transport capacity would
also become available for other uses. In many there would
also be considerable savings in foreign exchange. The
effective utilization of released resources would depend
upon the soundness and vigour of development program¬
mes and the volume and character of aid received.
Personal consumption and productive investment. Among
the alternative uses of resources released by disarma¬
ment, increased personal consumption might well absorb
a large share. It is fair to suppose that even in the
developed countries there would be strong pressure
on governments to raise the level of living. Disarmament
would, in particular, offer an important opportunity to
raise incomes of low income sections of the population
and to facilitate equalizing the rates of pay for men and
women.
Part of the gain from disarmament could also take the
form of an increase in leisure as, for example, through a
reduction in average working hours without a correspond¬
ing reduction in real income, or through an increase in paid
vacations.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
OUGHSHARES
A NEW
PROTOTYPE
BOMBER
WITH FULL
EQUIPMENT
One year's
salary for
250,000
teachers
30 science
faculties
each with
1,000 students
75 fully
equipped
100- bed
hospitals
50,000
tractors
or 15,000
harvesters
mm
In most countries, however, not all the resources freed
by disarmament would be allocated directly to consumption,
no matter what the level of income might be. In the first
place, a substantial portion of the released resources would
be used for expansion of productive capacities because
only such expansion can provide a firm basis for further
increases in consumption.
Social investment. Social investment is an impor¬
tant alternative both to private consumption and to indus¬
trial and agricultural investment. Its claims rest partly
upon the clear urgency of the direct need for improved
social amenities, and partly upon the fact that growth of
industrial and agricultural productivity is dependent upon
developments in education, housing, health, and other
fields. Since social investment has had to compete with
military claims for state funds, it (like aid to developing
countries) has probably been particularly affected by the
armaments race.
I N the United States the National Planning Asso¬
ciation estimated at the end of 1959 the cumu¬
lative expenditure requirements for selected governmant pro¬
grammes over the next five years. These estimates were not
intended to be precise but simply represented a summary of
the existing programmes of development and improvement in
various fields over the next five years. The significance
of these estimates, which imply annual average expenditures
of $66 thousand million, may be judged from the fact that
the present spending of the Federal, State and local gov
ernments on all these programmes amounts to about $30
thousand million per year. It is therefore apparent that
these programmes could absorb much or most of any
resources released by disarmament.
In the Soviet Union the task has been set of achieving
a sharp improvement in living standards within the next
twenty years by raising the Income of the population and
also by expanding social benefits (education, health pro¬
tection, social insurance, housing construction, etc.). As
stated in an official document, "general and complete dis¬
armament on the basis or an appropriate agreement be¬
tween States would make it considerably easier to overfulfil,
the planned improvement in the living standards of the
working people".
The problem of urban renewal is world-wide. In 1950
about 80 per cent of the world's population was still living
in rural areas. Between 50 and 60 million people are being
added to the world's total population every year, mainly to
its urban areas. In Asia as many as 500 million persons
may be added between 1950 and 1975 to the population of
cities with over 20,000 inhabitants. In Latin America,
sixty-two cities with over 100,000 people accounted in
1960 for some 40 per cent of the region's total. In Africa
a considerably higher rate of growth is taking place in
urban areas than in rural areas. Rapid urbanization is
characteristic of Europe and North America.
The rural and urban environments in many countries are
both deteriorating, mainly under the impact of this rapid ,.,.
growth. The social and physical symptoms are bad hous-
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
THE SWORD AND THE PLOUGHSHARES (Cont'd)
A new approach to world-wide
prosperity through disarmament
ing, poor community services and delinquency, the para¬
lysis of city traffic, and in many of the less developed
countries an absence of sanitation and a high incidence
of communicable disease. In many metropolitan cities of
such less developed countries "squatters' settlements"
already contain a considerable part of the population.
In India alone approximately $1 thousand million a year
will be required to house the new inhabitants of cities with
over 100,000 people. The provision of city-wide services,
utilities and transportation would at least double the needed
investment.
In Latin America it was estimated by the Organization of
American States in 1954 that an annual investment of $1.4
thousand million was required over a period of thirty years
to wipe out the housing backlog, to replace obsolescent
dwellings and to provide new homes. According to rough
THE FIRST STEPS
"We have taken the first steps along the pathway
to disarmament. Last year saw the test ban treaty,
the direct communication link, and the U.N. reso¬
lution against nuclear weapons in space. This
year both the Soviet Union and the United States
have announced reductions in the production of
fissionable material for nuclear weapons.
"Each of these steps point in the direction of
effective control of arms. Each moves us a small
way along this long and difficult road.
"We must not hesitate now that the journey has
been begun. We must redouble our efforts until
it is completed."
Lyndon B. Johnson
estimates by the United Nations Bureau of Social Affairs,
as many as 150 million families in the less developed coun¬
tries are in need of adequate homes. These immense
requirements are contributing in many developing countries
to the maintenance of a level of spending on housing and
urban development such that the pressing claims of directly
productive sectors have to be curtailed.
In the Soviet Union a housing shortage still exists despite
the building of dwellings for nearly 50 million people in
a five year period. In order to overcome the shortage and
house every family in "a separate, comfortable apartment",
an increase in twenty years of about 200 per cent would
be required in the existing housing facilities. To reach
this goal the average annual housing construction needs
to be raised from the target of 135 million square metres
in 1961-65 to 400 million square metres in 1976-80.
Another field in which the supply of social capital is
16 deficient in many countries is road and air transportation.
The rapid increase in the stock of automobiles and the lag
in road facilities in these countries during the post-war
years have been accompanied by extraordinary congestion
and a rising accident rate. Airports and other air facilities
are also deficient in many developing countries as well as
in some more advanced economies, and investment in civil
aviation will claim a share of the resources freed by dis¬
armament.
The development and conservation of natural resources
provides another important field for increased outlays in
the event of disarmament. In the United States it has been
estimated that Federal expenditure requirements up to
1980 in the field of water resource development alone total
almost $55 thousand million, while $173 thousand million
will be needed for non-Federal programmes. The Soviet
Union could advance the preparation and implementation
of a number of important nature-transforming projects in
various parts of the country in order to improve living and
working conditions for the people. There is, for example,
a plan to divert part of the waters of the Pechora, Vychegda
and Ob Rivers (now flowing into the Arctic Ocean) into
the basins of the Volga and the Caspian and Aral Seas.
This would bring about a considerable change in the climate
and in living conditions in Central Asia and in the southern
European part of the Soviet Union. In the developing
countries there are also many important multipurpose
schemes for the conservation and the utilization of water
resources. (See "The Unesco Courier", July/August 1964.)
HE world's demand for water is growing much
more raoidly than the supply. Increasing sup¬
plies are needed not merely in order to keep pace with
the rapid rise in population, but also in order to meet the
still faster growing needs for irrigation and industry. Further
expansion necessitates increasingly heavy investment in
obtaining access to other sources, including the purification
of sea water.
Other urgent requirements for natural resources develop¬
ment and conservation exist in the fields of forestry, soil
and watershed conservation, rangeland conservation, park
and recreational development and fish and wildlife con¬
servation.
Investment in health, education and social services.
There is an urgent need for improvement in health ser¬
vices throughout the world. In many countries
the ratio of doctors, dentists and other medical personnel
to the population is inadequate and even falling, and there
are also great deficiencies in the supply of hospitals and
hospital beds as well as of other basic health facilities.
In some of the poorer countries of Europe, for example,
the medical facilities available to each doctor have been
estimated to be as little as one-fiftieth of those in the better
equipped countries. Yet even in the richest countries
there is great need to improve standards of medical ser¬
vices. In Canada and the United States, for instance, the
deficit in hospital beds has been estimated at from a quarter
to a half of the existing number. In the developing coun¬
tries the need for improved medical care is obviously
greater. Infant mortality rates are in excess of 100 per
1,000 in many of these countries as opposed to rates of
20 to 30 per 1,000 in economically advanced countries.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
"Complete disarmament cannot be effected in
a single step, although each step should be in
that direction."
Jawaharlal Nehru
An indication of the magnitude of investment require¬
ments for medical care may be gained from projections for
the United States. The present rate of construction, plus
a limited programme of renovation, modernization and
increase in rehabilitation facilities, would require at least
$15 thousand million over the next decade instead of the
$9 thousand million that would be needed if such changes
were not carried out. In the Soviet Union it has been
officially suggested that hospital accommodation might be
increased by 40 per cent (that is, by several hundred
thousand beds) at low cost by converting into hospitals
part of the buildings now in military use.
In most developed countries educational needs are rising
and are bound to expand even more rapidly; withthe ever
wider spread of technical progress there will be a rising
premium on a higher educational background, on better
scientific and technological skills and on a broader range
of knowledge. At the same time greater efforts will be
directed towards reducing the drop-out rate of the less
talented and towards ensuring that an increasing proportion
of the highly talented reach upper levels. The realization
of all these purposes would imply the devising of new
kinds of education and provision of adequate means so
that people keep abreast of the latest developments in
knowledge.
OST of the developing countries still have illi¬
teracy rates of well over 50 per cent of the
population aged fifteen years and over. The cost of edu¬
cational requirements in developing countries is exemplified
by a recently adopted African programme (1). The total cost
of this programme is expected to increase from $590 million
in the first year to $1,150 million in 1965, $1,880 million
in 1970 and $2,600 million in 1980. It ¡s assumed that
the share of national income devoted to education will
rise from three to four per cent between 1961 and 1965, and
thereafter will increase further, reaching 6 per cent of
national income by 1980. This means that the difference,
amounting in the same years to $140 million, $450 million,
$1,010 million and $400 million, respectively, would need
to be covered by foreign aid.
There are also urgent requirements for expansion in
social services. Even the most advanced countries have
too few child welfare services, vocational rehabilitation
agencies, community centres and other special services.
The recent acceleration of population growth and of
technical change make it certain that the need, and the
demand, will grow. Social investment therefore is likely
to claim increasing resources, to which disarmament
would make a welcome contribution.
Scientific research for peaceful purposes. Amongst
the major powers a significant part of the national
research and development effort currently serves military
purposes. With disarmament it would thus become
possible to encourage programmes of basic scientific
research in fields which have hitherto been neglected, and
to mobilize great scientific potential for the solution of
some of the world's greatest problems in medicine, urban
development and reorganization and the technical prob¬
lems associated with the economic development of the
developing countries. If human ingenuity, in the space
of a very few years, has so vastly increased man's powers
for destruction, it should be able to make an equally
massive contribution to peaceful and constructivo achieve¬
ment.
I:IN some instances satisfaction of the needs al¬
ready described will require international co¬
operation. Serious gaps exist in the permanent world-wide
network of meteorological observing stations and in the
corresponding telecommunication facilities, and far more
funds are needed for basic research on improving meteoro¬
logical services. There is also considerable scope for in¬
ternational co-operation in developing world air transport
facilities.
THE CRUCIAL PROBLEM
"We are all faced with many outstanding interna¬
tional problems. Not all of them are equally impor¬
tant or urgent. Some of them concern the relations
between individual countries, others affect the
interests of the peoples of a number of countries
and continents. But there is one problem whose
solution is awaited with hope by the people of
all countries, big and small, whatever their social
system and way of life the problem of disarma¬
ment. Whether mankind will head towards war
with its disastrous consequences or whether the
cause of peace will prevail depends largely on
whether or not the correct solution is found to
that problem."
Nikita S. Khrushchev
(1) United Nations Economic Commission for' Africa and Unesco: "Outline of
a Plan for African Educational Development"; the plan covers thirty-five States
and territories of Africa.
Disarmament would also open up possibilities for joint
international ventures of an even more ambitious kind,
including the utilization of atomic energy for peaceful
purposes, space research, the exploration of the Arctic
and Antarctic for the benefit of mankind and projects to
change the climates of large areas of the world. Joint
research into the earth's interior may lead to discoveries
that would be of real value to the whole world. In
addition, joint projects to assist the development of the
developing countries as well as programmes of co-opera¬
tion in the social and economic fields could be undertaken.
These international projects could have a major impact
on world living standards and civilization.
It is evident that the resources freed by disarmament
would not be large enough for the many claims upon them.
Though it would take active decisions by governments in
the light of national and international needs to set in motion
programmes for employing the released resources, it
seems abundantly clear that no country need fear a lack \~¡
of useful employment opportunities for the resources that
would become available to it through disarmament.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
The Huge Charnel-House (440 * 770 cm.) Detail.
"A macabre dance around an atomic explosion."
Nine tapestries on man
in the atomic age
Mankind after Hiroshima. (437 x 292 cm.)
W;far and peace have frequently inspired
the painter and artist down the ages.
But the theme of war and peace in the atomic age is
now the subject of an arresting series of nine tapestries
just completed by the world -renowned French artist,
Jean Lurçat, whose modern works during the past
40 years have been instrumental in reviving the
ancient art of tapestry. Lurçat has named his latest
efforts Le Chant du Monde (Song of the World). The
nine works woven in glowing colours have a total
length of 230 feet and cover a surface of 3,230 square
feet. We present here some details of these tapestries
which were recently exhibited at the Louvre in Paris.
As a contrast to four images depicting the horrors of a
nuclear holocaust in which all man's works and
mankind itself would be destroyed, Lurçat presents
five others evoking the triumph of peace. Lurçat
has commented on his works in these words : "Our
generation has lived through two wars and now over
our heads and over all those who are to follow us
there hangs a terrible threat: the atomic horror. That
is why I have called my first panel The Great Threat;
it also explains why I have shown a sinister-eyed
eagle hovering above the world and a buffalo spraying
poison over all things living or as yet unconceived."
But Lurçat believes that human reason will prevail :
his nightmare images of mankind annihilated and art
and civilization reduced to dust give place to Man in
the Glory of Peace. He is now working on a sequel
to Song of the World; its themes will be love,
friendship and everyday joys.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Great Threat (440 x 900 cm.) "The atomic mushroom cloud convulses the world and man seeks refuge
from the pursuing monster in a Noah's Ark."
19
Man in the Glory of Peace (437 * 1316 cm.) Detail,
on his head and carrying the laurels of peace."
"Man with an owl, the symbol of wisdom.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
MÊÊMi
fl c ^Rr "*
iMüíHf|Ti|W|6í p>
.« i r* ""**r *W
20
Unesco-Rosten
NEW NAMES IN THE TABLE OF ELEMENTS. When
all the known chemical elements were classified
according to their atomic weights in 1869 the last
on the list, N° 92, was uranium at that time the
heaviest known element. Since the fission of uranium
the production of new elements (by irradiation of
existing substances) has raised the total in the Periodic
Table of Elements to over 100. Among the new names
are neptunium, einsteinium and mendelevium (named
after Dimitri Mendeleyev, who arranged the first
table of elements according to the periodic law).
PUGWASH
kINCE they were inaugurated in 1957 the
Pugwash international meetings have come to
occupy an important place in the world forum of thought
and discussion on the implications of modern science for
the future of mankind. In September of this year the
13th Pugwash Conference on Science and World Affairs
brought together an international group of prominent
scientists and scholars in Karlovy Vary, Czechoslovakia.
The meeting held far-ranging discussions on a host of
questions with political implications such as measures for
reducing tensions and dangers of war, the current status
of proposals for arms limitation, progress in achieving
comprehensive disarmament, problems of collective
security, and two questions of particular interest to
Unesco, the role and the responsibility of the scientist
in the cause of peace and economic development of the
emerging countries.
On the role and responsibility of the scientist in advanc¬
ing the cause of peace the Pugwash Conference presented
its conclusions in clear and unequivocal terms. "In our
time," it said, "two challenges have been placed before
mankind: to abolish war and to create a world advancing
toward greater and more universal wellbeing."
The Pugwash Conference declared that the first
challenge called for universal disarmament and peaceful
co-operation among countries having different economic
and political systems and that the second implied that this
co-operation must be not merely passive but active and
constructive. The Pugwash Conference pointed out that
both challenges are the result of the scientific revolution
and hence that scientists have a personal and professional
responsibility in both areas.
"The increasing role and importance of science in a
contemporary society," the Pugwash statement declared,
"inevitably results in an increasing influence and respon¬
sibility of scientists in the economic, cultural and political
development of nations. They should use their influence
to promote further reduction of international tensions, and
increases in international contacts and co-operation. They
should help their governments in the development of poli¬
cies contributing to permanent peace and in the well-being
of all people."
HE Pugwash conferences owe their name to
the little Canadian town of Pugwash in Nova
Scotia where the first meeting was opened on July 6, 1957.
The idea for Pugwash was born as a spontaneous
movement among scientists seeking an international
exchange of ideas on the impact of science on human
affairs. The first meeting was sparked by a bold statement
on the dangers of war signed by a roster of internationally
famous scientists headed by Albert Einstein and Bertrand
Russell. On the agenda of the first meeting were three
challenging topios : (1) the problem of radiological dangers
(2) problems of atomic disarmament (3) responsibilities
of the scientists in the atomic age.
Pugwash conferences have maintained their original
informal character. Those participating attend as indivi¬
duals and not as representatives of their respective coun¬
tries. They are present as scientists, often of Nobel Prize
winning stature, who have given much thought to the
implications of science on modern society. An increasing
interest is being shown by governments in the Pugwash
conferences. At the September 1964 conference messages
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
A world movement on the responsibility
of the scientist in world affairs
were received from the heads of several governments as
well as from the Secretary-General of the United Nations.
The Pugwash Conferences have come to be known as
one of the great scientific meeting grounds of scientists
from countries with different economic and political systems,
national Pugwash committees have been set up on all
continents and the Pugwash conferences are increasingly
being referred to throughout the world as "The Pugwash
Movement."
HE Unesco draft programme and budget for
1965-66, in referring to the continued co¬
operation between the Unesco Secretariat and associations
of scientists who are concerned with the problem of
economic and social development as affected by
disarmament, singles out for particular mention the
Pugwash Conferences on Science and World Affairs.
Important Pugwash conferences have been held in recent
years in Great Britain, the U.S.S.R., the U.S.A., India,
Austria and other countries with the focus of attention
broadening to include the consideration of international
scientific co-operation and the role of scientists in aid to
developing nations.
From the Pugwash deliberations in Vienna in September
1958 came a seven-point declaration reflecting the unani¬
mity of opinion of 70 leading scientists from all parts of
the world. This declaration stressed the necessity of
ending war, of ending the arms race, what war would mean,
the hazards of nuclear tests, the need for scientific
co-operation, the development of technology in the service
of peace and the responsibility of scientists.
As the Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists wrote: "Future
historians may look on September 20, 1958 as a significant
date, and on the Vienna Declaration as an important docu
ment in the history of man's transition io living in tho
scientific age." (1)
The seventh and eighth Pugwash conferences held in
Stowe, Vermont (U.S.A.) three years later, in 1961, wore
perhaps even more significant and produced a virtual
"Charter for International Co-operation." They demons¬
trated strikingly the belief of scientists everywhere in
international co-operation in all areas of science. All
participants agreed on the urgent need for large scale
expansion of present international co-operation, not only
in pure science, where such co-operation has been tradi¬
tional, but also in large technological undertakings such as
space rocketry, drilling through the earth's crust, global
weather prediction, and technical assistance to newly
developing countries.
As participants permitted their imaginations to roam
freely over all areas of scientific endeavour in which inter¬
national co-operation and sponsorship could lead to vastly
accelerated progress, the atmosphere became charged
with enthusiasm and the dark clouds of political conflict
seemed to recede. As one participant observed "it was
an exhilarating experience."
Among the questions taken up at the September 1964
Pugwash conference were some of the long term conse¬
quences of disarmament on the development of science
and technology. Unesco, which has a special interest
in this problem, sent two top-ranking officials (the director
of its Department of Application of Science to Develop¬
ment, and the deputy-director of its Department of Social
Sciences) as observers to the meeting. It is hoped to
establish continuing working relations between the Unesco
CONT'D ON PAGE 33
(1) "The Third Pugwash Conference" by Eugene Rabinowitch. Quoted in "The
Atomic Age (Scientists in National and World Affairs)" an antholoay of articles
taken from "The Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists" Z945-/962. Edited by
M. Grodzins and E. Rabinowitch. Basic Books Inc.. 1963. S10.
UNESCO'S PROGRAMME ON PEACE AND DISARMAMENT
WHAT are the ideas of the man
in the street on disarmament and
its long term consequences ?
What image does the general public
have of a world without arms ? What
use should be made of the resources
freed by disarmament? A public
opinion survey on these questions is
being made in France, Norway and
Poland by the European Centre of Co¬
ordination of Research and Documen¬
tation, located in Vienna (Austria)
with help from Unesco. Results of
the survey will be available next year.
This is one example of the peace
research and studies on the effects of
disarmament which Unesco is carrying
out or sponsoring, following the publi¬
cation of the historic United Nations
report on the Economic and Social
Consequences of Disarmament in 1962.
Further development of these activities
is foreseen in Unesco's proposed pro¬
gramme for 1965-1966.
One of the long-term consequences
of general disarmament is the opening
up of vast possibilities for the
development of science and the appli¬
cation of science and technology,
especially in the developing nations.
Unesco is setting up a scientific study
group to consider how resources even¬
tually released by disarmament could
be used for basic research and also
applied to new, creative programmes
of international co-operation in science
and technology.
In several countries in which disarm¬
ament would have far-reaching
effects, Unesco is carrying out a study
of how to increase the transfer from
developed to developing countries of
some of the potentially huge resources
for education which would become
available through disarmament. Re¬
sults of this research will be published
next year.
Unesco will maintain close contacts
with national, institutes and centres
concerned with peace research. Many
of these organizations are now group¬
ed in an international peace and
disarmament research association.
Facts and figures about well over
100 institutions working on problems
of peace will be given in an Interna¬
tional Repertory being prepared for
Unesco by the Peace Research Insti¬
tute in Oslo, (Norway). Unesco will
pursue its collaboration with the
Pugwash Conferences on Science and
World Affairs whose aims are closely
related to Unesco's activities in this
area.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
THE ECONOMIC IMPACT
OF DISARMAMENT
EALIZATION that the disarmament issue is as
important as the survival of humanity itself is
now world-wide. In this age of rapid change we may
indeed one day see the negotiation of a multilateral disar¬
mament agreement. Nations will then have to make
economic adjustments of considerable size. Thousands of
millions of dollars are involved. Giant industries and
millions of job-holders have a stake in the outcome.
Millions of men in arms will have major accommodations
to make.
In its report on the long-term consequences of disar¬
mament, the U.N. has concluded that "all the problems and
difficulties of transition connected with disarmament could
be met by appropriate national and international measures".
Disarmament would raise both general problems of
maintaining the over-all level of economic activity and
employment and specific problems in so far as manpower
or productive capacity might require adaptation to non-
military needs.
In the economic life of all countries, shifts in the pattern
of demand and in the allocation of productive resources are
continually occurring. The reallocation of productive
resources which would accompany disarmament is in many
respects merely a special case of the phenomenon of
economic growth.
The post-war conversion was a much larger one and
involved a more rapid transfer of resources than total
disarmament would require at present. During the last
years of the war, the world devoted about one half of its
resources to destruction. The real military expenditure and
the number of people in uniform were about four times as
high as today. Nevertheless, huge armies were quickly
demobilized without a significant rise in unemployment in
most countries, and the pace of recovery, particularly of
industrial output, was impressively rapid.
URING the post-war conversion, the major
concern of economic policy was to restrain,
rather than to 'maintain, over-all demand. In adopting a
programme of general and complete disarmament, however,
it would be important to maintain a high general level of
domestic demand for goods and services and thereby to
support satisfactory levels of output and employment.
Much attention has already been given in the industria¬
lized private enterprise economies to the methods by which
total effective demand can be maintained.
Monetary and fiscal policy could be used to offset the
effect of a shortfall in total demand that might result from
22 a decline in government expenditure. Bearing in mind,
however, that a substantial part of military expenditure
would probably be replaced by other government expen
diture in most countries, it may be concluded that the
maintenance of effective demand in the face of disarma¬
ment should not prove difficult.
For many developing countries, the effect of disarmament
upon the industrial countries' demands for primary pro¬
ducts, and thus on the export earnings of the primary
producing countries, would be of great importance. So
would the methods of dealing with the liquidation of stra¬
tegic stockpiles.
In the centrally planned economies, the maintenance of
effective demand while reducing military expenditure would
be simply a matter of efficiency of planning techniques.
Since decisions concerning the production of military out¬
put as well as of investment and consumer goods are co¬
ordinated through the national economic plan, the substitu¬
tion of one type of expenditure for another does not raise
any basic problems, and in consequence, effective demand
could be readily maintained. The principal problems of con¬
version would then concern the physical adaptation of
plants producing armaments to the production of goods for
civilian use.
ET even with the successful maintenance of
total effective demand during a period of
disarmament, significant problems of adjustment would
remain in specific sectors and areas of the economy.
Part of the personnel released by the armed forces and the
armaments industry would have to be trained or retrained
so as to permit absorption into peacetime occupations.
Some plant and equipment would have to be converted.
Productive capacity might contract in some industries, and
might have to be expanded in others. Where the manu¬
facture of armaments has been concentrated in particular
regions, it would be necessary either to shift resources out
of those regions to other areas of growing demand, or
alternatively to undertake schemes of redevelopment.
Steps would have to be taken to modify the direction of
research and of technological development.
The resources now supplying military requirements could
be adapted to peacetime needs partly by shifts within
industries and plants. For instance, there might be a shift
from tanks to tractors, from military to civilian aircraft,
from naval vessels to merchant ships, or from electronic
equipment for military purposes to television sets. This
might be a relatively easy procedure, in many cases
involving little more than changes in designs, retooling,
and minor adaptations of skills, particularly in plants and
enterprises which already produce both military and civi¬
lian goods.
Shifts between industries might call for a more complex
form of conversion requiring the output of some industries
to be completely stopped or sharply curtailed and that of
others to be correspondingly expanded. In some countries,
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
*
:'^l
fö
ÏÏ
km
Và\ -
"iS^-T,
I «SB
I i-J*»
rllikJL
IS«
w
/
1.4i
1
fils
"Hi
M
HL «
i - '
Til
J 4 'til
41 .1 ^
J «
M
-, ii' j
»' i '.
-*i* '
.ittft
"il
' Kit
S»*'«»
_lil
Ml
ill
'¿??Z~'
»V-
1 liftaffTLîL'a;
:-3:v =ra i .
r-¿,»
i*:.
E^
M
*rjî? ;
<%H
^ y
I
M . '
Paul Almasy
A
the total output of aircraft, ships and boats would have to
be reduced since civilian demand for such products would
not fully offset the fall in military demand. On the other
hand, a considerable expansion of output in the cement,
brick, glass and building industries might be required should
there be a shift in expenditure in favour of civilian cons¬
truction. Shifts between industries would necessitate acqui¬
sition of different types of skill by the working force as
well as new investment in plant and equipment.
Disarmament would allow each country to raise the rate
of investment and to adapt productive capacity more ade¬
quately to the needs of the population and to the require
ments of economic growth, both in the private enterprise
and the centrally planned economies.
Hypothetical studies on the assumption that military
expenditure is replaced wholly by increases in expenditure
on other kinds of goods and services suggest that in the
event of very rapid disarmament some 6 or 7 per cent
(including the armed forces) of the total labour force in the
United States (about 4.5 million persons) in employment
in 1958 would have to change their employment from one
industry group to another or find civilian instead of military 23
employment.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
DISARMAMENT (Cont'd)
Refrigerators, cycles
& washing machines
in place of arms
Developing countries generally have been meeting their
requirements for military goods and services by imports,
so that their disarmament would release foreign exchange
rather than industrial workers. It would also free members
of the forces with many useful skills and training. Some of
these would be absorbed by the growing labour market;
others could be usefully employed in the development of
social capital by construction of minor irrigation works,
feeder-roads and other community development projects,
which would help to mitigate the already acute problem of
underdevelopment.
In some of the semi-industrialized countries, however,
the newly started basic industries which manufacture
chemical fertilizers, heavy machine tools, heavy vehicles,
aircraft and electronic equipment, have been serving both
military and civilian needs. In the event of disarmament
these industries could concentrate, without any transitional
difficulty, on the manufacture of capital goods so urgently
needed for both consumer goods industries and capital
goods Industries. Transport capacity, particularly vehicles,
released from military uses, would supplement the inade¬
quate transport facilities available In the present, stage of
their development.
I N the centrally planned economies, productive
I capacity is usually fully utilized. Thus it
would be necessary to convert plants producing military
equipment to production of durable consumer goods and
of such investment goods as can be produced in them
with only minor retooling. Such conversion could be
achieved rapidly. Many plants producing military equip¬
ment produce also certain goods for civilian purposes.
In Poland, for instance, plants which manufacture military
equipment also account for about 50 per cent of the
national output of motor cycles and scooters, 80 per cent
of the sewing machines, 70 per cent of the washing ma¬
chines and 30 per cent of the refrigerators produced in
the country.
Some special problems would arise with regard to re¬
employment and training of manpower and reorientation of
scientific research. While most members of the armed
forces have received training that would fit them easily for
civilian life, a special effort would have to be made to find
suitable employment for the rest. Some of them might be
called on to serve in various capacities in the international
. organs to be set up for control of disarmament.
The demobilization of the non-professional members of
the armed forces would involve a much larger number of
persons. But most of these men have been drawn from
civilian life where they were previously engaged in non-
military occupations. In many cases, however, they have
acquired new technical skills while in military service. In
24 most of the underdeveloped countries, the regular armed
forces possess a much higher level of industrial and tech¬
nical skills than the civilian population; this would tend to
ILO
DEMOBILIZING MEN
AND INDUSTRIES
After the Second World War
huge munitions plants were
converted to peacetime uses
and many millions of men
were demobilized with a
minimum of friction and dis-
give them a relatively greater chance of being absorbed
into civilian employment, particularly in an expanding
economy.
In some countries, which are faced with shortages of
manpower, the availability of a larger labour force could
indeed contribute to an acceleration of the rate of economic
growth. Moreover, the financial resources released by
disarmament should make it possible to arrange for termi¬
nation pay and special allowances for various types of
training. The Government of the United States carried
out, after the Second World War, a large programme for
education, training and job placement for demobilized army
personnel. Nearly eight million veterans took advantage of
the training programme.
In industries depending heavily on military orders, many
of the employees possess a level of skill that should find
gainful employment in other branches of production, so
long as over-all effective demand is rising. Moreover,
where some form of retraining or additional training would
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
location in terms of outputand
re-employment The conver¬
sion problems of 1945 were
far larger and more complex
than those which disarma¬
ment would present today.
be needed for employment, it could be acquired through
the facilities for apprenticeship and on-the-job training
often provided by individual firms or plants for their new
labour force. Even so, there might be some cases which
would require special assistance to encourage the adapta¬
tion of skills to new jobs.
Owing to the concentration of military output in a few
Industries, termination of military contracts would bear
specially upon the activities of particular enterprises. To
facilitate readjustment, attempts should be made to diver¬
sify the structure of employment by developing new
industries where possible; adequate relocation allowances
should be provided to facilitate the movement of those who
are mobile to areas where the labour market is expanding;
and adequate relief should be granted to those whose
attachment to the locality is too deep or whose age is too
advanced to contemplate moving to other areas. The costs
of such measures would be very small in relation to the
resources that disarmament would release.
The magnitude of the task of shifting scientific and tech¬
nical personnel to non-military fields of research would
differ from country to country, but no reduction in the
actual employment of scientific and technical personnel
need be feared, because the demand for civilian research
would increase rapidly. Indeed, one of the main reasons
why scientific research is still far from adequately applied
in many civilian fields is the fact that highly qualified per¬
sonnel have been scarce, and have been pre-empted by
military demands.
A more adequate supply of specialists would make it
possible to open up new fields of inquiry, hitherto virtually
neglected, as well as to devote larger resources to existing
lines of scientific investigation in both the developed and
developing countries. The scope for peaceful research in
the physical, chemical, biological and human sciences is 25
unlimited, and the potential benefits to the whole of huma¬
nity incalculable.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
DISARMAMENT AND
THE DEVELOPING
COUNTRIES
IISARMAMENT would be bound to have favou¬
rable effects on the development of interna¬
tional economic relations. The political detente that would
accompany an International disarmament programme would
in Itself Imply that nations were willing to reconsider their
economic relations with one another. The consequent
relaxation of international tensions would provide a sound
basis for reduction of trade barriers and for modification
of existing trade agreements and trading practices.
In the long run this would encourage an expansion of
international trade, a more rational international division
of labour and a more effective use of the world's resources.
In the short term it might help conversion by generating
new demand for exports from existing sources of supply
that could be satisfied fairly easily from existing capacities.
The promotion of economic and social development in
developing countries is one of the most important ways
in which the resources released by disarmament could be
put to use.
The world's military expenditures appear to far exceed
the combined gross investment expenditures of the less
developed areas; they are probably at least five times as
large and may be much greater. A much larger volume
of resources could thus be allocated to investment for
productive development in these countries even if only a
fraction of the resources currently devoted to military
purposes were used in this way.
Assuming that the necessary national development pro¬
grammes and social and Institutional reforms were effec¬
tively realized, developing countries would be able to
absorb a considerably larger flow of productive investment.
The total amount of foreign capital required by the
developing countries, over and above their domestic
resources devoted to investment, is estimated to range
from $6 thousand million to $10 thousand million annually.
Would disarmament release in sufficient quantity the parti-
The latest atomic submarines cost some
$160,000,000 each. With this money over
50 cities could each be provided with a
modern $ 3 million hospital.
The total cost of developing one of the
latest supersonic fighter planes has been
estimated at over $6,500 million. This
would build 600,000 new $10,000 homes
to house more than three million people.
26
cular resources required for economic development? Is
the present institutional framework of aid tc developing
countries likely to be affected by disarmament?
In the longer run, productive capacities can be adapted
to any changed patterns of demand, and provided that the
needs of the developing countries are known in sufficient
detail, no serious problems should arise in matching
resources to uses. Even in the short run, however, it
seems probable that a significantly large proportion of the
resources absorbed for military use would indeed prove
to be of a type useful for investment in developing coun¬
tries. An important proportion of military expenditure
absorbs the output of heavy industry and of the engineering
and construction industries. The output of these industrial
sectors could undoubtedly make a valuable contribution
to the industrialization of the less developed areas and
to their accumulation of social capital. Transportation and
communication equipment, an important component of
military expenditure, is urgently required by developing
countries.
I ISARMAMENT would also release scientific
research workers and engineers, who could
be utilized for other purposes. In the event of disarma¬
ment, it should prove possible for the industrialized
countries to provide greater technical assistance and
thereby help remove one of the serious limitations to
development efforts in these countries. Furthermore,
disarmament would free from military service in both the
more advanced and the less developed countries large
groups of young people. Past experience in utilizing
their good will and enthusiasm in a number of countries
indicates that when completely freed from military preoc¬
cupations, many of them could make an important contri¬
bution to economic and social development in developing
areas.
Discussions in the Economic and Social Council and
the U.N. General Assembly have frequently emphasized
the importance of the savings to be derived from general
disarmament. The basic position of the General Assembly
on this matter in 1953 was defined in an unanimous reso¬
lution which declared:
"We, the Governments of the States Members of the
United Nations, in order to promote higher standards
of living and conditions of economic and social progress
and development, stand ready to ask our peoples, when
sufficient progress has been made in internationally
supervised world-wide disarmament, to devote a portion
of the savings achieved through such disarmament to an
international fund, within the framework of the United
Nations, to assist development and reconstruction in
underdeveloped countries."
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
World War XII, as everybody knows, brought
about the collapse of civilization
Towns, cities and villages disappeared from
the earth
Men, women, and children became lower
than the lower animals
Years and years went by
She told other humans that the last flower
was dying but only one young man paid
any attention
THE LAST FLOWER
by James Thurber
In 1939 just before the world was plunged into World War II the American
humorist, James Thurber, published "The Last Flower", a parable in pictures on
the theme of war and peace. With the advent of the Atom Bomb and in the light
of man's present capacity to devastate the world, Thurber's work today three
years after his death takes on even greater depth and meaning and points as
never before to the need for disarmament. The book first published by Harper
& Brothers, New York, was dedicated to "Rosemary, in the wistful hope that her
world will be better than mine."
© by James Thurber. Reproduced with kind permission.
All the groves and forests were destroyed.. ...And all the works of art
Discouraged and disillusioned, dogs deserted
their fallen masters
Emboldened by the pitiful condition of the
former lords of the earth, rabbits descended
upon them
Boys and girls grew up to stare at each other
blankly, for love had passed from the earth
One day a young girl who had never seen a
flower chanced to come upon the last one
in the world
Together the young man and the girl nurtured
the flower and it began to live again
Before long there were two flowers, and then
four, and then a great many
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
THE LAST FLOWER (Cont'd)
Groves and forests flourished again Love was reborn into the world Dogs came out of their exile
Towns, cities and villages sprang up Troubadours and jugglers came back into
the world
And painters and poets
And soldiers And still more soldiers The liberators set fire to the discontent
So presently the world was at war again This time the destruction was so complete.,
Except one man And one woman
..That nothing was left in the world
And one flower
© Reproduction prohibited
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
PEACEFUL USES
FOR
MILITARY ENERGY
by Ritchie Calder
Professor of International Relations,
University of Edinburgh
HE nations of the world are spending over
£43,000 million ($120,000 million) on armaments
per year.
As the United Nations survey on "The Economic and
Social Consequences of Disarmament" pointed out this is
equivalent to about 8% to 9% of the world's annual output
of all goods and services and according to some estimates
is equal to the entire national incomes of all the devel¬
oping countries put together.
More significant however, is the fact that about 85% of
the world's military expenditure is accounted for by seven
countries: Canada, the Federal Republic of Germany,
France, mainland China, the U.S.S.R., the United Kingdom,
and the United States. On the other hand, the remaining
15% represents a disproportionate burden on the econo¬
mies of poorer countries.
The U.K. Defence Budget has now, with the recent sup¬
plementary expenditure, passed the £ 2,000 million ($ 5,600
million) mark. That represents over 7% of the gross
national product. In terms of direct employment in Britain
the armed forces, the supply departments, industrial
contracts and research this represents about 1,118,000
persons or 4,5% of the total working population. That is
the number of people whose livelihoods would be affected
by disarmament, "affected", because it can be shown
that it does not mean unemployment but, rather, a labour
force made available for constructive, not destructive
purposes.
Nevertheless the threat to their livelihoods, not unreas¬
onably, colours the attitude of workers towards disarma¬
ment. If you put it crudely "Do you want armaments and
employment, or disarmament and unemployment?" even
the least militaristic would at least hesitate. This is the
more true in these days when contract-work on defence
expenditure is not always obvious as visible weapons.
The worker who builds a Polaris submarine or bores
the barrel of a gun may be aware of the arms he is making,
but the man who is making parts for a computer may never
think of it as the instrument which will launch a nuclear
ballistic missile. He is not a conscious trigger-man, but
he is probably aware that his firm has defence contracts,
the cancelling of which might lose him his job. You cannot
reproach these people as "war-mongers" because in the
complexity, and the sinister ingenuity, of modern weapons
few of us can remain entirely innocent.
If I write an article on some new development in nuclear
physics, 1 may put an idea into somebody's head as
to how it might be adapted to missiles. The scientists
involved in that highly admirable enterprise, the International
Geophysical Year, in which a hundred nations took part
for purely scientific reasons, did not foresee that artificial
satellites, which to them were merely observation instru¬
ments, might be exploited as nuclear space-mines.
The making of armaments which are obsolete as soon
as, or even before, they are in production is, in the econo¬
mics of wastage, the equivalent of digging a hole and
filling it up with this difference, that the hole we dig is
either our own grave or a refuse dump in which we bury
the elaborate artifacts which consume our scarce natural
resources and squander our human resourcefulness.
"The Economic Effects of Disarmament" produced by the
Economist Intelligence Unit, sponsored by the United
World Trust, (1) is a survey of the effects of disarmament
in terms of one country, Britain, and it confirms the findings
of the United Nations experts that there need be no econo¬
mic or labour-force convulsions if the disengagement from
arms is planned with an awareness of the industrial and
man-power adjustments which have to be made.
I N general disarmament, the re-deployment of
I men and industrial plants is no more complex,
indeed less so, than the running down of the fighting
services and the munition industries at the end of the
Second World War.
In June, 1945, after the collapse of Germany, there were
5,100,000 persons in the British armed forces and approxi¬
mately 3,900,000 persons producing equipment and supplies,
giving a total of nine million persons directly engaged in
military effort. In October 1945, a target was set for the
demobilization of one and a half million men and women
from the forces by December 31 plus a simultaneous
reduction of 1,400,000 in munitions and related industries.
In the event, despite transport difficulties, the reduction
of the armed forces was successfully carried out and so,
for all practical purposes, was the reduction in the indus¬
trial field. The run-down was almost complete by the end
of 1946. Both in terms of output and re-employment the
disarmament programme was carried out with the minimum
of friction and dislocation.
Behind this remarkable piece of redeployment was the
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
29
(1) Published in January 1963 by the Economist Intelligence Unit.
London, and University of Toronto Press, Toronto.
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
PEACEFUL USES (Cont'd)
The case of one countryBritain
meeting of the International Labour Office at Philadelphia
in April/May 1944. The liberation of Europe and the end
of Hitler's war was still a year off. The I.L.O., when the
League of Nations collapsed, had moved to Montreal. It
was still at that time an organ of the League of Nations
and this war-time Conference re-dedicated the I.L.O. to
the constructive purposes of peace. Delegates, on the
regular pattern of government, employer and worker, came
from the allied nations then fighting the war.
The Office had prepared careful studies on demobiliza¬
tion and the re-employment and the re-deployment of
industry. Delegates, beset by the urgencies of war and,
most of them, anxiously concerned about the sufferings of
their people under enemy occupation were asked to give
thought to the transfer from war to peace.
The mood might have been "Let's win the war firstl" but
it was not. All of them could remember the disarray of
the labour force after the First World War and the hardships
of the years which followed.
The I.L.O.'s staff-studies dealt with the demobilization of
the armed forces and the machinery necessary for direction
and re-training; with the needs of young people, evacuated
from their homes, even exiled from their countries, their
schooling interrupted and, often, drafted into factories;
with the women "doing their bit" in industry but likely to
be displaced by ex-service men; with the disabled, civilian
as well as military, and their rehabilitation; with the
technological changes, already taking place in industry,
to which the returning workers would have to be adapted,
and with the complications which would follow the switch
of plants from war to peace.
HE recommendations approved by the Phila¬
delphia Conference, provided the basis for
subsequent, and salutary, actions by governments, em¬
ployers and trade unions. The measures agreed eased
the processes of re-adjustment and contributed to the
remarkably swift recovery of war-ravaged countries.
One of the factors in Britain of the easy transition was
the back-log of demand built up during the war years due
to both the devastation and the lack of supplies. In fact
Britain even now has not fully caught up with that back-log.
Her machine tool industry for example has still not reco¬
vered from the effects of the war which prevented re-
equipping. Forty-five per cent of the hospitals taken over
by the National Health Service in 1948 were in poor condi¬
tion, and no new hospital was started until 1954, and
between 1954 and 1958 the proportion of the national
income alloted to hospital building was still only half of
what was spent before the war.
In the United States, the transition was equally easy
because there was an enormous unsatisfied demand for
consumer goods, and for everything the American economy
could produce from food and fuel to automobiles and refrig¬
erators as well as every kind of machine tool and machi¬
nery. So the wartime U.S. boom continued, and reached
new heights during the Korean War. Then in the words of
a U.S. journal "Peace Broke Out" and there was a definite
recession because by then the American home markets
were saturated in terms of affluent requirements.
The American economist, James P. Warburg, has said
in his book. "Disarmament: The Challenge of the 1960's"
that no unsatisfied demand for consumer goods like that
of the post-war transition period now exists. Instead, he
adds, the extension of automation has meant five and a
half million workers displaced by the machines so that the
reconversion of the nine per cent of the gross national
product which is represented by U.S. military expenditure
is going to produce difficulties unless, and he terms it
a self-evident "unless", the United States goes out for
public works and social services to provide for the under¬
privileged ten per cent of its population. More than that,
as J.P. Warburg adds, it must go out into the wider world
where the unsatisfied demand exists but the purchasing
power is lacking. "The provision of that purchasing
power" he writes, "and the gearing of the American eco¬
nomy to the world's needs can be readjusted to meet it."
BUT the U.S. has a problem apart from the
conversion of industry. The military installa¬
tions themselves account for a government military and
civilian payroll of $11,000,000,000 a year. This is equal
to one-and-a-half times the combined payrolls of the iron
steel industry and all the other basic metal industries. It
is more than double the payroll of the automobile industry.
By comparison, the position in Britain is relatively sim¬
ple. Britain has a smaller military force and the number
of workers engaged on defence work is 750,000 in 138
companies. Of the defence contracts, 27.6% are in the
London and South-Eastern region and 7.7% in Scotland.
Northern region accounts for 5%, East and West Ridings
5%, North Midland 4.5%, Eastern 6.8%; Southern 7.7%
South Western 6.3%; Wales 3.2%, Midlands 15%, North
Western 10% and Northern Ireland 2.3%.
The British industries directly affected are the aircraft
industry, the electronics industry, shipbuilding and marine
engineering, the motor industry, the electrical industry and
of course, ordnance and small arms. The aircraft industry
is the most exposed; 45% of its 300,000 workers are
directly employed on defence contracts and it gets
£ 100,000,000 ($ 280,000,000) from the Services for research.
Some 40,000 men in the electronics industry (about 20%
of the total labour forces) are "on defence work. The motor
industry is barely affected a mere 2% of its 420,000
workers. Shipbuilding and marine engineering with a
labour force of 244,000 has about 81,000 workers on Service
contracts. Mechanical engineering with 1,265,000 has only
3% involved and the electrical industry with 500,000 workers
has only 4%. Ordnance and small arms would have a
redundancy of about 23,000 assuming that general disarm¬
ament abolished everything including rifles.
But these figures are deceptive to the extent that in
practically every instance with a major exception of the
CONT'D ON PAGE 32
Technicians wear protective helmets and
gowns when handling certain equipment
in a nuclear research laboratory. Atomic
energy for peaceful uses is now being deve¬
loped on such a large scale that in the event
of disarmament it could quite easily also use
the services of nuclear scientists and engine¬
ers at present engaged on military projects.
© APN
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
i
s
,v 1
1 JkV
1 KV sJiV
BEI ÉJ
*** W
¡M
1 K -jiA ^^^k V m Ig wj
tafe ^» -7 kàww 1 J
f- 1
r * V
^^ IWä
N
jj0ty%*i -
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
PEACEFUL USES (Cont'd)
What we need is the courage
aircraft industry, largely involved in military type aircraft
and in missiles the work is interchangeable, civil and
military. A worker in the electronic industry is not like an
armourer. He has not spent all his life perfecting his skills
for one particular weapon; his products are components
capable of unlimited diversity. What the electronics indus¬
try needs is not massive reconversion but a continuation
of orders for civil electronics machines to bring British
industries up-to-date.
And the same would apply throughout the "demobilized"
sectors of industry. Instead of making weapons which if
they are ever used are catastrophic and, if they are never
used, are sheer waste, industries would be making things
which would multiply the components of prosperity.
The word to emphasize is "components" because we
have become hidebound in our thinking about the finished
article. The liner Queen Elizabeth is not just a ship; it is
a city wrapped up in a hull but the components of that
city do not have to be encased in steel and slid down a
slipway. In a country badly needing homes and hospital
wards and classrooms, there is no reason why shipyards
dependent on armed forces contracts should not turn over to
the pre-fabrication of "living units" for assembly ashore.
Then the reduction of naval construction would not be a
threat to workers' livelihoods.
ND when the contracts are committed and
Lwhen it would cause great hardship to cancel
them, then we should think of more imaginative uses for
military or naval or air force surpluses. For instance,
Britain is committed by contract to a fleet of Polaris
nuclear-powered submarines each costing £70,000,000
($200,000,000). A lot of money already appropriated and
a lot of work already started. But they could be converted
Into a fleet of submarine tankers, or freighters, which could
go under the polar ice and open up the frozen north of
Canada.
This is not a fanciful idea. Consider Hudson Bay. Look
at that great bight on the map bulging into the heart of
Canada the shortest sea-route to the grain lands of the
middle provinces and to the still undeveloped wealth of
Atom Age minerals in Keewatin, the sub-arctic region of
Eastern Canada, and to the iron deposits of Labrador.
But Hudson Bay is inaccessible to ocean-going ships for
nine months of the year. It would not be very difficult to
maintain an ice-free port (like a seal's breathing-hole
through the ice) where submarine freighters, or submarine
tugs could surface any time. The Canadian authorities
seriously considered having such a port but abandoned it
because of the cost of providing a nuclear submarine fleet.
But if Britain had such a fleet going abegging, it could do
for the north of Canada what the transcontinental railways
did for the Middle West in the 19th Century. Go North,
young manl
In the wider world we need components unlimited.
Unesco has stated that in the struggle to help the illiterates
of the world, we need a minimum of 400 million radio-
receivers, cheap, foolproof, battery transistor-sets are
needed. The hundreds of millions already invested in
electronics for guided missiles could pay-off by provid-
32 ing the components. We need hundreds of millions
of tractors, which if they were made simple and durable
enough (and not the sophisticated mobile power-units
which advanced farming uses) could transform the agri¬
culture of the underdeveloped world. We need hundreds
of millions of small motors the sort of things that operate
the flaps of bombers which, as components, could be
used in a thousand different ways, from winnowing machi¬
nes to village industries. We need hovercraft, pipelines,
telecommunications, machine-tools, teaching machines and
packaged nuclear power reactors.
If nuclear materials were not locked up in military stock
piles and if brains and skills were released from the com¬
pounds of military establishments, we might keep some of
those promises of footloose energy which were made at
the first Atoms for Peace Conference.
As important as the money and resources which could
be released are the imagination and skills which have
been diverted to military purposes and could be redirected
to all those opportunities which were arrayed in February
1963 at the U.N. Conference on Science and Technology
for the Benefit of the Less Developed Areas held in Geneva.
What we need is the courage to accept general disar¬
mament.
"Fear knocked at the door. Hope answered. There
was nothing there."
MUSEUM
OF THE
FUTURE
Guide:
"The monster
appeared in the
middle of the
twentieth cent¬
ury and threat¬
ened the whole
world. It be¬
came extinct
with the great
disarmament."
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
HOW TO HELP THE U.N.
Sir,
The Unesco Courier deserves the
highest praise for the illuminating and
challenging article, "The Flags Are
Not Enough," (June 1964). I hope
that this article and others like it
will awaken all nations and peoples
to the necessity of making the United
Nations Development Decade a
success.
The magnitude of the task before
us staggers the Imagination. Ten
thousand people die every day in the
world from hunger or malnutrition.
Yet the problem of hunger, poverty,
disease, illiteracy, and other forms of
human misery can be solved. We
have the technical ability and the
resources to build what Paul G. Hoff¬
man called a "World Without Want".
Let us, therefore, bend our shoulders
to the effort. If there is nothing else
we can do, we can at least contribute
to the United Nations Children's
Fund. However, there is much more
that we can do especially if we hold
positions of leadership in the de¬
veloped nations. People must be
awakened, inertia must be overcome,
minds and bodies must be put to
work. Your article was magnificent.
Now let us have more articles telling
what the U.N. is doing to solve the
problem and what individual citizens
in all nations may do to help.
Palmer Van Gundy
California, U.S.A.
Ed. Note: One way is through the
Unesco Gift Coupon programme which
has a/ready raised well over §7 mi/lion
for literacy, technical training and health
projects in developing countries. By
supporting Unesco Gift Coupon projects
/inked with the FAO "Freedom from
Hunger Campaign" and the UNRWA
schools for Palestine refugees, for
example, readers would be effectively
helping the work of the U.N, family.
For further information on this pro¬
gramme write to Unesco's Public Liaison
Division, Place de Fontenoy, Paris.
Another way to help is by buying the
Greeting Cards sold each year by the
United Nations Children's Fund. The
proceeds help to save millions of chil¬
dren from hunger and disease.
A NEW ALPHABET
Sir,
A useful addition to your Issue
dealing with the Art of Writing (March
1964) would have been something
about the future and in particular the
new developments in adjusting scripts
to the spoken word. The best example
of this is the Initial Teaching Alphabet
now being used in Britain by some ten
thousand children learning to read.
The principle on which it is based
could be applied to any language and
if widely adopted would make Unesco's
literacy campaigns much easier. How
much easier it is hard to say because
for some reason Unesco has estab¬
lished no measure to show how hard
it is to learn to read in one language
as compared with another. This
should be an essential preliminary
inquiry before a world campaign
begins.
A second virtue in the new alphabet
is that it makes easier the learning of
foreign languages. English is an exas¬
perating language to learn because
often letters are pronounced in diffe¬
rent ways whereas in the new alpha¬
bet they are always pronounced In the
same way, and yet the two alphabets
are so alike that it is easy to change
from one to the other.
A number of countries have already
realized the significance of the new
invention and the new alphabet is
being used in a number of countries
such as in the U.S.S.R. at Irkutsk, In
Israel, In Canada and elsewhere. It
seems a great pity that Unesco
appears to ignore It even In the tra¬
velling exhibition "The Art of Writing".
Nicholas Gillett
Adviser on Teacher Training
Unesco Mission to Iran
DETERGENTS &
WATER POLLUTION
Sir,
I read the issue, "Water and Life",
(July-August 1964) with great Interest
and particularly the article, "Can We
Stop the Cancer of River Pollution?",
by Reno Colas.
The problem of water pollution has
long been a concern of the Interna¬
tional Union for Conservation of Na¬
ture and Natural Resources. Its Com¬
mission on Legislation has studied the
juridical aspects of water pollution and
has followed the evolution of legisla¬
tion relating to this problem. You
may be Interested to know that a law
on the use of detergents the first
of its kind in the worldcomes into
force In the Federal Republic of Ger¬
many on October 1. This forbids the
sale of detergents unless 80 % of
their content dissolves on contact with
water, and this percentage may be
still further increased In the future. A
similar plan Is now being studied In
the United States.
It is to be hoped that measures of
this kind will become general.
Unesco is particularly well placed to
bring this new law to the attention of
its member states.
W. Burhenne
Commission on Legislation, IUCN
Bonn, Federal Republic of
Germany
PUGWASH (Cont'd from page 21 )
secretariat and Pugwash in the study of this important
question.
One of the highlights of the Pugwash meeting was the
official announcement that the Swedish government had
decided to establish an international peace research
institute to mark Sweden's 150 years of unbroken peace.
Three research projects have thus far been mentioned for
possible study (a) the establishment of a modern seismo¬
graph system (the so-called seismic cross) in Swedish
territory as an aid in detecting underground explosions of
nuclear weapons; (b) studies of economic and social
problems of disarmament (c) development of needed
resources for a growing population. Other projects will
certainly follow.
Over a hundred persons from 19 countries attended the
1964 Pugwash meetings including two Under-Secretaries
of the United Nations, 1950 Nobel Peace Prize Winner
Ralph Bunche and Vladimir P. Suslov As 1965 has
been named United Nations International Co-operation
Year it is expected that a large part of the
Pugwash Conference which opens in Venice next April
will be devoted to international co-operation in science and
international co-operation to help the developing countries.
As the Vienna Pugwash conference declared:
"The extremely low level of living in the industrially
underdeveloped countries of the world is and will remain
a source of international tension. We see an urgent need
to forward studies and programmes for the effective
industrialization of these countries. This would not only
improve the level of living of the majority of the population
of the world; it would also help reduce the sources of
conflict between the highly-industrialized powers. Such 33
studies would offer fruitful scope for co-operative efforts
between scientists of all nations."
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
KALINGA FILM PRIZE. "Shopje 63," a
film based on the earthquake that
destroyed the capital of Macedonia last
year, has won for the Yugoslav film direc¬
tor, Veljko Bulajic, the Kalinga Film Prize
for 1964. The award Is made to the film
Judged to have done most to bring home a
major achievement In the realm of Interna¬
tional co-operation. It Is awarded by the
Director-General of Unesco with the help
of an International jury and is financed by
an Indian Industrialist, Mr. Bijoyanand Pat-
nalk, director of the Kalinga Foundation.
Two other films were singled out for honour¬
able mention: "L'Art Nègre" (France) and
"A New Reality" (Denmark).
SOLAR POWER STATION: Some of the
sunlight in the Mediterranean basin is
now now being transformed Into electricity
34
Ban on nuclear testing
A padlock enclosing the mushroom
cloud of a nuclear explosion appears
on the most recent U.N. commemo¬
rative stamp marking the first
anniversary of the entry into force
of the Nuclear Test Ban treaty on
October 10. 1963, The U.N. Postal
Administration Is distributing this
stamp accompanied by the following
text : "The use of nuclear and
thermonuclear weapons Is contrary to
the spirit, letter and aims of the
United Nations and would cause
Indiscriminate suffering and destruction
to mankind and civilization. It is a
war directed not only against an
enemy or enemies, but also against
mankind In general. Any State using
nuclear or thermo-nuclear weapons is
to be considered as violating the
Charter of the United Nations, as
acting contrary to the laws of
humanity, and as committing a crime
against mankind and civilization". As
agent In France of the U.N. Postal
Administration, Unesco's Philatelic
Service stocks all U.N. stamps and
first day covers currently on sale. For
prices and further details write to
the Unesco Philatelic Service, Place
de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
for industrial use at a solar power station
overlooking the port of Marseilles. This is
done by a furnace composed of numerous
"cells" made of refractory materials which
transform light reflected from a 600 sq. ft.
surface of mirrors into heat.
STONE AGE QUEST: An archaeologist
from the Lebanon, Dr Dimitri Haramkl,
has been sent to Libya by Unesco to help
organize exploration of sites which may
ultimately prove to be one of the world's
richest and so far largely untapped sources
of knowledge about the stone age and
prehistoric times. Dr. Haramki will advise
the Department of Antiquity In Tripoli on
planning survey and excavation programmes
in the hinterland of Libya.
FOR THIRSTY DESERTS: The first section
of one of Central Asia's largest irriga¬
tion systems, the Kafirnlgan Project, is now
In operation. When completed at the end
of the year ¡t will bring water from the
Kafirnigan River to almost 250,000 acres of
arid pastures in Southern Tajikistan. A
pumping station will raise river waters over
one third of a mile to reach the irrigation
canals. The U.S.S.R. has now over 23 mil¬
lion acres of Irrigated land.
HIGHWAY HOLIDAY: Twenty thousand
young Yugoslavs have spent part of
their holiday this year working alongside
several hundred young people from abroad
on the construction of the Adriatic highway.
The road, started several years ago, will
eventually link the two seaports of Rijeka
and Bar. The highway Is due to open to
traffic on May 1, 1965.
GOING DOWN: Work has now started
on the hole which the Soviet Union
is hoping to drill to a depth of six miles
through the earth's crust as part of the
Upper Mantle Project (See The Unesco
Courier, October 1963). The Soviet drilling
site is in the Caspian Depression about
180 miles from the oil town of Guriev.
As a complementary project in the interna¬
tional plan to probe for new knowledge
about the earth's crust and upper mantle,
U.S. scientists plan to drill a hole Into the
ocean bed. Test drillings have already
been made off the Californian coast.
FIGHT AGAINST ILLITERACY: The sec¬
ond Unesco regional conference on
the planning and organization of literacy pro¬
grammes recently brought together heads
of adult education and literacy services of
all Arab member states, associate members
and territories, in Alexandria, U.A.R. The
conference discussed how to step up the
fight against illiteracy throughout the Arab
world, and in particular the integration of
literacy programmes in national economic
and social development plans. The first
Unesco regional conference on literacy
took place at Abidjan, Ivory Coast, in
February, to consider problems of African
countries.
PROSPECTION FROM THE AIR: Scien¬
tist and specialists In aerial photo¬
graphy met recently in Toulouse, France, to
discuss how their respective knowledge and
techniques can best be combined ¡n aerial
surveys that would specially help develop¬
ing countries in locating and evaluating
their natural resources. Among the bran¬
ches of science represented at the confe¬
rence, which was organized jointly by
Unesco and the French National Centre
for Scientific Research, were geology, geo-
morphology, soil science, botany and hydro¬
logy.
BEST TEXTBOOK PRIZES: Annual prizes
are to be awarded by Unesco to
authors of outstanding textbooks, in accor¬
dance with the provisions of a bequest
made to Unesco by the late Mr. Nessim
Habif in 1960. The aim of the awards is
"to encourage the production in developing
countries of good textbooks which are
objective, balanced, up-to-date and peda-
gogically sound." The first award will be
made next year for textbooks published
in Asian countries, and in successive years
will cover Unesco member states in Africa,
the Arab world and Latin America.
ROCK PAINTING FIND: Rock paintings
i and engravings described as the most
spectacular single example of aboriginal
art of this kind in Australia have been
found in a cave on Cape York peninsula.
They completely cover a vertical rock face
twelve feet high and seventy-five feet long
and depict vegetation, animals and human
figures.
F/ashes...
A plan to increase nearly fifteenfold the
number of scientists in Africa (from around
5,000 to between 50,000 and 70,000)
during the next 15 years has been approved
by a conference of 29 African nations
convened in Lagos, Nigeria, by Unesco and
U.N. Economic Commission for Africa.
Weather bureau warnings of storms,
floods and bushfires save Australia about
£A250 mi/lion a year. The annual cost of
running the bureau is less than £A4 1/4 mil¬
lion.
Nine agreements recently signed between
the World Health Organization and its
member states in the Eastern Mediterranean
aim to eradicate ma/aria by expanding the
mass campaign that has a/ready given
protection to over 45 million people in this
region.
During the past three years some small
farmers in the north of Latin America have
increased their incomes as much as 20 times
through the use of fertilizers combined with
other better farming practices, reports the
Food and Agriculture Organization.
Seventeen member states or associate
members of Unesco in Africa have set up
television services or plan to do so before
the year's end, it was reported at a recent
Unesco meeting on television development
in Africa, held at Lagos, Nigeria.
Diseases of the heart and blood vessels
cause nearly one half of all deaths in
22 countries, most of them highly industrializ¬
ed, covered by a World Health Organization
survey.
Professor A.N. Matveyev, formerly pro¬
fessor or theoretical physics at Moscow
State University, fast month took up his
duties as Assistant Director-General in
charge of Unesco's science programme.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
HAVE YOU READ*)
these memorable works m
of world literature trans- |
lated into English and
published in the Unesco
Translations Series
FOR THE NEW YEAR
offer a subscription to
THE UNESCO COURIER
Extra pages
in full colour
In our next issues:
December 1 964
EXCLUSIVE: Art treasures unearthed in Nubia.
| January 1965
Monuments of the world in peril.
A full year's subscription
From Rumania:
THE UPRISING. A novel by Livin Rebreanu,
translated by P. Grandjean and S. Hartauer.
Peter Owen, London, 35/-.
From China:
CHUANG TZU: Basic Writings, (13/6; $1.65)
HAN FEI TZU; Basic Writings, (13/6; $1.65)
HSUN TZU;. Basic Writings, (14/-: $1.75).
MO TZU; Basic Writings, (13/6: $1.65).
All four translated by Burton Watson. Colum¬
bia University Press, New York and London
From Korea:
ANTHOLOGY OF KOREAN POETRY
Translated by Peter H. Lee. John Day Co.
New York, $5.00.
From India:
CHEMEEN. A novel by Thakazhi Sivasankare
Pillai, translated by Narayana Menon, intro¬
duction by Santha Rama Rau. Gollancz, Lon¬
don, 18/-; Harper, New York, $5.00.
May be obtained from the publishers
or through your local bookseller.
DO NOT ORDER FROM UNESCO.
only 15/ - (stg.)
S 3.00 (Canada)
10 French Frs
Order through the Unesco sales agents listed below
ere to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ¡ the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Prest Department, Royal
Aghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Tradco Agencies, 109 Swanston Street, G. P. O.
Box 2324 V, Melbourne C. I. (Victoria); United
Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
8th Floor, McEwan House, 343 Little Collins St.,
Melbourne C. I. (Victoria). (	). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Frommes C\, Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Sen. 70.-). BELGIUM. Editions "Labor",
342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-Boek-
handel, Belgiëlei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (140 FB) and art slides only; Louis De Lannoy,
11 2, rue du Trône, Brussels 5. CCP 3 380.00. BURMA.
Burma Translation Society. 361 Prome Road, Ran¬
goon. (	). CANADA. Queen's Printer,
Ottawa, Ont. (S 3.00). CEYLON. Lake House
Bookshop, 100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Colombo.
2. (	). CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99 Chung¬
king South Rd., Section 1, Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa).
CYPRUS. Cyprus National Youth Council. P. O. Box 539,
Nicosia. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L., Spalena 51,
Prague 1 (permanent display); Zahrahnici literatura
Bilkova 4, Prague 1. DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard,
Prags Boulevard 47 Copenhagen S (	).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agency. P.O. Box 120,
Addis Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa.
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (	). FRANCE.
Librairie de I'Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7*. C.C.P.
12598-48. (1 OF.). GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg Verlag,
Rosenheimerstrasse 145, Munich. 8. For the Unesco
Kurier (German ed only) Bahrenfelder-Chaussee 160,
Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, C.C.P. 276650 (DM 10).
GHANA Methodist Book Depot Ltd . Atlantis Hous,
Commercial St., POB 100, Cape Coast. GREAT BRI
TAIN. See United Kingdom. GREECE. Librairie H.
Kauffmann, 28, rue du Stade, Athens. HONG-KONG.
Swindon Book Co., 64, Nathan Road, Kowloon. HUN¬
GARY. Kultura, P. O. Box 149. Budapest, 62. ICE¬
LAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co. H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9,
Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd. Nicol Road,
Bellard Estate, Bombay 1; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Cal¬
cutta 1 3 ¡Gunfoundry Road, Hyberabad, 1; 36a, Mount
Road, Madras 2; Kanson House, 1/24 Asa! Ali Road, P.O.
Box 386, New Delhi, 1; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book &
Stationery Co., 17 Park Street, Calcutta 16, Scindia
House, New Delhi, Indian National Commission Co-ope¬
ration with Unesco, Ministry of Education, for New
Delhi 3. (Rs. 7). INDONESIA. P. N. Fadjar Bhakti
Djalan, Nusantara 22, Djakarta. IRAQ. Mackenzie's
Bookshop, Baghdad. IRELAND. The National Press,
2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (15/5).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores 3 5, Allenby Road
and 48, Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv (1 £ 5.50).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour
Street, Kingston. (15/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd.,
6 Tori-Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605 Tokyo
Central, Tokyo. (	). JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous
& Co., Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman.
KENYA. E.S.A. Bookshop. P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole and
Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LUXEMBURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue,
Luxemburg. MALAYSIA. Federal Publications Ltd.,
Times House, River Valley Rd., Singapore (	).
MALTA. Sapienza's Library 26 Kingsway, Valletta. (1 5/-).
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon
Street, Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid
des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (	). NETHERLANDS.
N. V. Martinus Nijhoff. Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague,
(fl. 8.50). NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES. G. C. T.
Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.) N.V, Willemstad. Curaçao.
N.A. (NA fl 4,50). NEW ZEALAND. Government
Printing Office 20, Molesworth Street (Private Bag) Wel-
lingston, C. 1 Government Bookshops: Auckland (P.O.
Box 5344), Christchurch (P.O. Box 1721), Dunedin P.O.
Box 1104) (15/-). NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshops, P.O.
Box 174, Lagos ( /-). NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet-
Lille Grense 7. Oslo. For the Unesco Courier only: A.S.
Narvesens Litteratur Tjeneste, Stortingsgt. 2 Oslo, Post¬
boks 1 1 5 (	). PAKISTAN. The Weit-Pak Publis¬
hing Co. Ltd., Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box 374
56-N Gulberg Industrial Colony, Lahore. PHILIPINES.
The Modern Book Co., 508 Rizal Avenue Manila.
POLAND. "RUCH", ul. Wronia, 23. Warsaw 10
(	). PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Lda. Livraria
Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. PUERTO RICO.
Spanish English Publications, Eleanor Roosevelt 115,
Apartado 1912. Hato Rey. RHODESIA & NYA-
SALAND. The Book Centre, Gordon Avenue, Salisbury,
Southern Rhodesia. SUDAN. AI Baihir Bo"l<.hop,
P. O. Box 1118, Khartoum. SWEDEN. A/B C.E.
Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredigatan 2, Stockholm 1 6,
For the Unesco Courier: Svenska Unescorldet, Van.
gatan 15-17, Stockholm, C (Kr. 12); SWITZERLAND.
Europa Verlag. 5 Rämistrasse Zurich. Payot. 40, rue du
Marche, Geneva C.C.P. 1-236. "Courier" only: Georges
Losmaz, 1, rue des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. C.C.P.
1-4811. (Fr. S. 10). TANGANYIKA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND.
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue. Bangkok.
(3S ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette. 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Book-
shop, P.O. Box 145. Kampala. UNION OF SOUTH
AFRICA Van Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Street, P.O. Box 724 Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier
(single copies) only: Central News Agency P.O.Box 1033,
Johannesbourg. (RL.S8). - UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC
(EGYPT). Librairie Kasr El Nil, 38. rue Kasr El Nil
Cairo. Sub/agent: La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-
Pasha, Cairo. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M.. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I, and Government
Bookshops in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Man¬
chester. Birmingham and Bristol. (15/-). UNITED
STATES. Unesco Publications Center, 317 East 34th St,
New York, N.Y. 1 001 6 (S 5.00) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broadway, New York,
27, N.Y. U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga, Moscow.
G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Yugoslovenska Knjig,
Tzrazije 27, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
&$&
]]>
</page>
</document>
