<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="062603eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A message
to world youth
IN 1979 the General Assembly of the United Nations designated 1985
as International Youth Year.
The main purpose of this Year, dedicated to participation, develop¬
ment and peace, is to inform world opinion about the situation, needs and
aspirations of young people. It also aims to strengthen co-operation in the
search for solutions to questions concerning young people and in the laun¬
ching of joint youth action programmes, and to associate young people in
studying and solving problems of social, economic and cultural develop¬
ment and of world peace.
In 1983 Unesco's General Conference decided that the Organization
should play as full a part as possible in the celebration of International
Youth Year. Young people form a considerable and ever-increasing propor¬
tion of the world population. Inevitably they are concerned by all the
problems arising from the present and future of humanity. None of the
major questions of our time can be answered without the active involvement
of young people.
Young people constitute 45 per cent of the world's population today and
their numbers are continuing to grow. There were 730 million fifteen- to
twenty-four-year-olds in 1975, and this figure should rise to 1,180 million
by the year 2000 an increase of 60 per cent in twenty-five years.
If the role and impact of youth in national life vary from country to coun¬
try, young people in many cases share a number of common preoccupa¬
tions, fears and aspirations.
In many countries young people are particularly exposed to such
problems as unemployment, hunger, delinquency, drugs, violence and
racism, all of which are rooted in the tensions and uncertainties of today.
But young people are also endowed with imagination, enthusiasm, and
courage, qualities which may contribute to the changes which prove
necessary; they stand at the meeting-point of continuity and change, tradi¬
tion and progress.
The different groups of young people must have the opportunity to par¬
ticipate fully in all aspects of the economic, political, educational, cultural,
and scientific life of the society in which they live, and to exercise freely in
it the qualities which are theirs.
Unesco, which places action in favour of young people at the heart of its
programmes, notably those concerned with education and training, is
making its contribution to the achievement of this goal.
Unesco's efforts in this field are focussed on three main objectives:
stimulating research on young people in the different world regions; pro¬
moting the diffusion and exchange of information about and for young
people; contributing to the formulation of policies and the application of
programmes which will encourage the participation of young people in all
aspects of the life of societies.
The Unesco Courier will publish in the coming months a number devoted
to young people in which these themes will be covered and an opportunity
will be given to many young people to tell us in their own words about their
successes of today and their hopes for tomorrow.
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
Director-General of Unesco
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Editorial
COVERING more than seventy per cent of the surface
of the globe, water is the most common substance
on earth. It is in the air we breathe and in the
ground we walk on. It fills the oceans, rivers and lakes. It is
the source and sustainer of life without which neither plant
nor animal nor man could live.
Every living thing consists mostly of water. A human be¬
ing is about 65 per cent water, an elephant about 70 per cent,
a potato about 80 per cent and a tomato an amazing 95 per
cent.
The wonder of water does not end there. It is both our
slave and our master. It helps to regulate the global climate,
and with its tremendous force it shapes the earth, at times
destroying man's puny constructions. We use it for bathing,
cooking and recreation. It carries away our wastes and ir¬
rigates our fields and, when taken from certain sources, has
unequalled therapeutic properties. It is an inexhaustible,
self-renewing resource.
The benison of water is not evenly distributed. Although
clean fresh water is vital for life and for health, over half the
people in the Third World do not have clean water to drink
and three-quarters of them have no sanitation, yet more than
three-quarters of human illness is related to lack of clean
drinking water and sanitation.
This is why, in November 1980, the GeneralAssembly of
the United Nations declared the International Drinking
Water Supply and Sanitation Decade (1981-1990), whose
target is "Clean Water and Adequate Sanitation for All by
1990".
Unesco's involvement in water problems goes back to
1950 when it launched a programme of research on the
world's arid zones. The purpose of its current International
Hydrological Programme (IHP) is to develop a scientific
basis for the rational management of water resources and to
help' find solutions to specific water problems in countries
with varying geographical conditions and levels of
technological and economic development.
Badly managed, water, or the lack of it, can be a
destroyer. Ill-conceived irrigation schemes can ruin
agricultural land as effectively as drought and desertifica¬
tion, the two great scourges now affecting huge areas of
Africa. Bad land-use practices, such as overgrazing and
deforestation, can make water a prime agent of erosion. Bad
industrial practices can turn rivers into sewers and "the gen¬
tle rain from heaven" into an acid-bearing blight that can kill
a lake and destroy a forest. .
There is as much water on earth today as there has ever
been or ever will be. We must look after it.
Cover: Photo Unesco Courier
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
January 1985
38th year
Emblem of the International Drinking Water Supply
and Sanitation Decade, 1981 to 1990.
4 Water and man
by Grigori Voropayev
7 Nature's water wheel
8 Erosion, drought and deserts
When man is careless, water can be a destroyer
10 Drought over Africa
The eleven worst-stricken countries
12 The menace of desert advance
by Mohamed Skouri
14 Mining fossil water
by Jean Margat and Kamal Saad
17 Managing the world's most precious resource
Unesco's International Hydrological Programme
21 Acid Rain
1. An unwelcome export
2. Can we save our lakes and forests?
25 Cities athirst
27 Washing our dirty water
29 The waterlords of ancient Sri Lanka
by Ananda Gurugé
31 The deadly snails of Dongfeng
How a Chinese community vanquished schistosomiasis
by Zhang Bihua
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
TER
-J
W^BMMI mmhmk
One or f/ie natural wonders ofSouth Ame¬
rica, the Iguacu Falls are situated on a
stretch of the Rio Iguacu forming the
boundary between Brazil and Argentina.
The horseshoe-shaped falls are over
4 km wide (4 times wider than Niagara in
North America). During the rainy season
from November to March the flow rate
may reach 12,740 cubic metres per
second. The Falls derive their name from
a Guarani Indian word meaning "great
water".
THE Earth is a sphere covered with a
humid envelope, the hydrosphere,
which comprises the oceans, the
seas, and all other water resources. It was in
the oceans that life appeared and took
shape. But the extremely complex
mechanism of life on our planet today can¬
not function without fresh water or, more
precisely, without the very small proportion
of water that is renewed each year in the
water cycle through evaporation, precipita¬
tion, infiltration and runoff (that part of
precipitation that flows toward streams on
the ground surface or within the soil).
As part of this great natural movement
(see drawing page 7), some 120,000 km1 of
water reaches the continents as rainfall; this
is only 1 per cent of total surface runoff
water and 0.001 per cent of underground
water. This water is today the essential
source of life on our planet: it humidifies
the plant layer of the soil, which is indispen¬
sable for agriculture; it conserves the
forests and promotes their expansion; it
completes the underground reserves whicl
provide drinking water for almost one fiftl
of the world's population.
' A large proportion of precipitation, som<
40 per cent, constitutes the hydrographica
network which controls the biológica
equilibrium of lakes, seas and oceans, anc
influences world economic activity. Rive:
water provides the habitat of edible fish anc
is an important link in the biological chaii
of certain sea and river fish such a
sturgeon, salmon and eel.
Deltas and estuaries formed by rive
mouths, river systems, lakes, marshes anc
fresh water reservoirs all provide importan
habitats for a large number of anima
species necessary for human needs.
River water runoff constitutes annuall;
some 50,000 kmJ, or a little more than 0.:
per cent of the total fresh water of thi
planet. But its geographical distribution i
unequal: it is mainly concentrated in thi
northern hemisphere, and in one-third o
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
AND
by Grigori Voropayev
'-*
	 &
the hottest continental zones there are few
or no rivers.
The birth of civilizations, population
growth, increased production in all fields,
from agriculture to advanced electronics,
would be impossible without fresh water.
While many countries have been notably
successful in developing techniques for the
desalinization, purification and re-
utilization of used water, world consump¬
tion of river water continues to increase
each year. Since the beginning of the twen¬
tieth century consumption of fresh water
has risen more than sevenfold and now
stands at almost 3,000 km' per year. In the
next twenty or thirty years the figure is ex¬
pected to rise by at least 50 per cent.
Where the river network is insignificant,
notably in the world's arid zones, the main
existing watercourses are already or soon
will be fully exploited in order to satisfy
economic needs. This is the case of such
rivers as the Nile, the Tigris, the Colorado,
the Syrdarya, the Chu, the Amu Darya, and
many other rivers in Australia, India, Mex¬
ico, Africa and elsewhere. In these regions
the provision of drinking water and the
development of irrigation are major
problems.
The unequal distribution of river runoff
on the different continents has a con¬
siderable impact on the water supply. Its
annual volume per head of population is
some tens of thousands of cubic metres for
Oceania, South America and North
America, but only a few thousand cubic
metres in the case of Europe and Asia. The
gap is even bigger in countries and regions
where the annual volume per head is no
more than several hundred cubic metres,
which in practice makes it impossible to
supply the population with drinking water
or to establish modern hygiene facilities.
For people living in these regions, water
supply is a vital question which mobilizes all
their efforts.
However, in spite of these major dif¬
ficulties, the problem would be easier to
solve if the natural mechanism of the water
cycle remained constant. Unfortunately
this is not the case. Man's economic ac¬
tivities modify the water cycle by influenc¬
ing the hydrological regime, as well as water
reserves and quality. The release of sulphur
compounds into the atmosphere leads to
the formation of "acid rain" which
modifies the acidity of the aquatic environ¬
ment, has a harmful effect on all forms
of life and restrains the development of
vegetation.
Intensive urbanization has an impact on
evaporation and infiltration, modifies the
runoff regime and the chemical composi¬
tion of the water, and loads it with
pollutants that are in many cases toxic. In
some regions the catchment basins of rivers
have already been and continue to be
transformed by human activity.
The consequence is a drop in Spring
flooding and flooding caused by rainfall.
The area of naturally irrigated land is
reduced, while the salinity of the water in- 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Below, a mangrove swamp in El Salvador.
The mangrove is a tropical tree that flou¬
rishes in estuaries and swamps where
fresh water mixes with the salty ocean
and no other tree can grow. As it grows it
sends down roots from its branches.
Mangrove swamps were once considered
wastelands, but their environmental
Importance and their economic potential
are now recognized. Their leafy canopies
and maze of roots constitute unique
ecosystems sheltering an astonishing
array of bird, insect and marine life. They
are also an important source of timber,
fuel, fisheries, fertilizer and other pro¬
ducts. In collaboration with the Interna¬
tional Council ofScientific Unions (ICSU),
Unesco is conducting a research and
training programme to promote the ratio¬
nal utilization and conservation of man¬
grove ecosystems in different parts of the
world.
Lake Baikal, in the southern part of east¬
ern Siberia, is the world's deepest lake
and a unique living museum of aquatic
plant and animal life. Some 25 million
years old, it contains about one fifth of
the fresh water on the Earth's surface,
and is 636 km long with an average width
of 48 km. Its area is 31,500 sq km. More
than 300 rivers flow Into the lake. Most of
the outflow is through the Angara river
which flows out from the southwest coast
of the lake, shown in photo.
creases in the river mouths.' Many streams
and rivers disappear forever. As a conse¬
quence of the construction of reservoirs,
sluices and tapping facilities, river flow is
diminished, water quality is radically
changed, and the exchange of water bet¬
ween land and sea is accordingly slowed
down. Effects on the environment are
negative, especially as regards humidity and
air temperature.
If, as certain scientific data now suggest,
the climate of the globe is changing, the
heat and water balance of the continents
and their water resources will undergo
major changes.
In recent years there have been major ef¬
forts to improve domestic and industrial
fresh water supplies. In addition to progress
in techniques for desalting sea water,
several projects have been mooted for off¬
setting the water penury of certain regions:
the transport of icebergs, a more extensive
use of glaciers, long-distance transfer of
water by tankers and by aqueducts.
Successes achieved so far provide
grounds for a certain degree of optimism.
But massive efforts will be required to solve
these regional water supply problems, and
ultimately these are bound to affect the
geographical distribution of population
and industries.
We live at a time when progress in the
Earth sciences is such that environmental
change can be foreseen and this knowledge
can provide the scientific basis for a
strategy for the utilization of natural
resources and notably for the wise manage¬
ment of the hydrological regime and water
resources as the most important and effec¬
tive lever for modifying natural processes.
It is for the world scientific community to
unite in the search for a solution to this
urgent problem.
GRIGORI VOROPAYEV, of the Soviet
Union, is a corresponding member of the
USSR Academy of Sciences and director of its
Institute ofHydrology. A member of the USSR
National Committee for Unesco's Interna¬
tional Hydrological Programme, he is the
author of some 170 books and studies on
problems of water including a monograph on
the Physical and Geographical Principles of
Water Supply in Agriculture.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Nature's water wheel
Precipitation on land
Moisture over land
Evaporation
from water
turface
Evaporation from land
Interception and transpiration
from vagstation from soil
Evaporation
from ocean ' Precipitation
OUR earth has been called the Water Planet, and with good
reason. If it were not for the pervading presence of water
on earth, the life forms that we know simply would not
be here. Some very simple organisms can exist without air, but
none can do so without water.
If this globe on which we all reside were not 150 million
kilometres from our sun, the earth would not have its present
mixture of gaseous, liquid, and solid moisture. Calculations
show that if the earth were located closer than 134 million
kilometres from the sun, our water would be boiled away. On the
other hand, should the orbit of the earth have turned out to be
more than 166 million kilometres out from the sun, the Ice Age
of the earth would have been without end.
So things happen as they do because our solar system's ther¬
monuclear fireball is located where it is. The sun is just the right
distance to keep the earth's "water wheel" (the "hydrological
cycle" as scientists call it) in constant motion.
The sun lifts water from the surface of the oceanas well as
from fresh water lakes, reservoirs, and streams. Additional
significant amounts of moisture are obtained from the surfaces
of plant leaves through a process called transpiration.
These masses of moisture, invisible unless temperature condi¬
tions are such that clouds form, move over the oceans and land.
When lifted by mountain rangesor when they come in contact
with cooler air massesthe water molecules coalesce, and can
no longer be supported aloft. Rain, hail, or snow then takes
place.
If the precipitation falls upon relatively impermeable soil, the
water may flow over the land as a small rivulet. But if the surface
of the soil is quite porous, or with thick vegetation which softens
the blows of the falling drops, there will be more infiltration and
less direct runoff.
Once water begins to infiltrate the soil surface, its rate of move¬
ment drastically decreases. If the soil is tightly compacted or con¬
tains much clay, the water may move hardly at all. In such an in¬
stance, the water may be hundreds of years in reaching what is
called the groundwater tablethat area of the ground which is
saturated with water.
It should be noted that the area between the surface of the soil
and the top of the groundwatercalled the unsaturated zone-
is of major importance to vegetation. If it were not for this region
which contains some water, along with oxygen, most plants
could not exist.
The moisture which reaches the groundwater is not per¬
manently removed from the water which is circulating in the
world-wide hydrological cycle. The groundwater will move,
however slowly, back towards the ocean. It may reach a lake
where it may be lifted skyward. It may come to the surface in a
spring where it joins the overland movement of a stream. When
the stream does reach the river/ocean interface, the hydrological
cycle may be said to have been completed.
In fact, of course, the cycle continues. The earth is still
operating with its original supply of water which is still essentially
undiminished. The molecules of water in Archimedes' bath are
still floating around in some ocean, lake, stream, or aquifer.
It is estimated that approximately 505,000 km3 of ocean water
is evaporated annually. However, about 458,000 km3, is of no
use to us as it precipitates back into the oceans. Only about
47,000 km3 is carried far enough to precipitate over the land. It
is only this water that is available to us for our multiple domestic,
agricultural and industrial uses. In reality, the total annual
precipitation over the land is much more than that; it is of the
order of 119,000 km3, the balance of 72,000 km3, comes from
water permanently retained as moisture by the atmosphere, soil
and vegetation in a never-ending cycle of evaporation from
ground and water surfaces, transpiration from vegetation, and
precipitation from the atmosphere. The excess of about 47,000
km3 of water carried over from the evaporation of the oceans
returns to the oceans as rivers and groundwater runoff.
This text and those on pages 25 to 28 are .
adapted from the booklet Water and the City,
published by Unesco within the framework of
the International Hydrological Programme and
written by Gunnar Lindh, professor of water
resource engineering at the Lund Institute of
Technology, University of Lund, Sweden. .
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Erosion,
drought and deserts
When man is careless, water can be a destroyer
SOIL is a country's most precious
natural resource, aptly described
as "the bridge between the in¬
animate and the living". It consists of
weathered and decomposed bedrock,
water, air, organic material formed from
plant and animal decay, and thousands of
different life forms, mainly micro¬
organisms and insects. All play their part
in maintaining the complex ecology of a
healthy soil.
Although soil erosion does occur
naturally, the process is slow. Man has in¬
creased the rate of natural erosion by at
least 2.5 times and, over the centuries,
has destroyed an estimated 2,000 million
hectares of land. There is good evidence
that past civilizations, in the Mediterra¬
nean and in Central America, collapsed
as a result of soil erosion following the cut¬
ting of forests on steep slopes and other
destructive practices.
Soil erosion occurs primarily when land
is exposed to the action of wind and rain.
Unprotected by a cover of vegetation, and
the binding action of roots, each raindrop
hits the naked soil with the impact of a
bullet. Soil particles are loosened, wash¬
ed down the slope of the land, and either
end up in the valley below or are washed
out to sea by streams and rivers.
Water erosion is the commonest form of
erosion. It is causing massive damage in
nearly all developing countries. It is found
where steep land is being unwisely farm¬
ed and where gently sloping land is left ex¬
posed to the effects of heavy rain for any
length of time.
Worldwide, about 25,000 million tonnes
of soil are being washed away each year,
ending up in the rivers and finally the
oceans. According to a study carried out
by the Food and Agriculture Organization
of the United Nations (FAO) and the
United Nations Environment Programme
(UNEP) an estimated 11.6 per cent of
Africa north of the equator and 17.1 per
cent of the Near East are subject to water
erosion. So are 90 million of India's 297
million hectares.
Water erosion causes two sets of prob¬
lems: an "on-site" loss of agricultural pro¬
ductivity; and a downstream movement of
sediment, causing flooding, a loss of river
navigability and the silting up of
reservoirs.
While heavy rainfall, prolonged drought
or high winds may be the direct cause of
soil erosion, they are not the real problem.
A landscape can remain stable under all
these conditions, whether it is in a natural
state or being sensibly farmed. Erosion
occurs when farming practices are used
which fail to take account of the ease with
which soils can be washed or blown away.
For example, over-stocking and over¬
grazing have caused untold damage in
much of Africa and Asia in the past few
decades. In arid areas, soil is compacted
around water holes, the vegetation is
stripped and dies, and erosion sets in.
Too often the land ends up as desert, the
intimate result of soil erosion and
degradation. If erosion is the sickness of a
land, desertification is its death.
Today, desertification is threatening
about 3,200 million hectares of land; the
livelihoods of the 700 million people who
depend on that land are at stake.
About 30 per cent of the world's ex¬
ploitable soils are still under shifting
cultivation in Africa, Asia and Latin
America. The technique is practised by
more than 30 million people in Africa
alone. Formerly, this use of land served to
conserve fertility, as it allowed a long
fallow period during which soil fertility
would build up to its previous level. Today,
population pressure and the struggle for
improved yields are cutting the fallow
period back to virtually nothing. Under
such conditions, the forest soils soon lose
their fertility and begin to erode. Essential¬
ly, this is because the land is being farmed
beyond its capability.
Nearly always, it is exposed land which
erodes while land covered in vegetation is
stable. The process often starts high in a
watershed, on the steep slopes which are
traditionally forested. But over the past
few decades, there has been mounting
pressure on fuelwood resources. Rural
people have been forced to travel further
and further to find their energy supplies,
and to cut wood from higher and steeper
ground. Many tropical forests have also
been cleared for agricultural develop¬
ment. Between 1975 and 1980, 37 million
hectares of forest were destroyed in
Africa, 1 2.2 million in Asia and 1 8.4 million
in Central and South America.
In some countries, an increasingly
critical balance of payments situation has
forced governments to plant more and
more cash crops. If no more arable land is
available, the new crops have to be
planted in marginal land, previously
pasture, which is brought under the
plough for the first time. Much of the thin
soil may be lost in the first heavy rain
which occurs when the field surface is still
bare. During a short storm in the United
Republic of Tanzania a few years ago,
scientists found that a field they were
studying lost 5 centimetres of topsoil over
its whole surface in just a few hours; rills
had cut down to a depth of 1 5 centimetres.
The problems of soil conservation are
closely connected to those of rural
development and rural poverty. A farmer
who has to struggle to grow even enough
food to feed his family cannot devote
weeks or months to terracing his land or
learning new farming techniques. It
follows that successful rural development
is an essential precursor to eliminating
soil erosion.
Text, drawings and photos adapted from Pro¬
tect and Produce: soil conservation for
development, published by the Food and
Agriculture Organization of the United
Nations.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Sheet erosion...
... is the more or less uniform
erosion of the whole surface of a
field. The roots ofplants, tree
roots and fence posts are
increasingly exposed
Rill erosion...
... is the accentuation of
natural depressions caused by
surface run-off. While normal
cultivation often hides the
damage, much fertile soil is still
lost
Gully erosion...
... causes deep fissures in
otherwise cultivable land. If left
unchecked, gullies cal their way
progressively back into the hill
Streambank erosion.
... converts deep, fast-flowing
streams into wide and sluggish
meandering watercourses with
extensive mud banks. It can
cause serious loss of cultivable
land
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Drought over Africa
The eleven
worst-stricken countries
Ghana
Most affected provinces: upper and
northern regions.
Ghana, almost self-sufficient in cereal
production ten years ago, is today facing a
severe economic and financial crisis ag¬
gravated by the recent prolonged drought.
The marked deterioration of agricultural
production compounded by the non¬
availability of transport and fuel, the poor
road network, the lack of storage facilities,
and reduced purchasing power has had im¬
mediate impacts on the nutritional status of
mothers and children.
The infant mortality rate, which was
steadily diminishing, is now on the increase
throughout the country and especially in
the north.
Food shortage is especially dramatic in
the northern part, since a serious logistic
problem has to be overcome to facilitate
food distribution in this region.
Burkina Faso
Most affected regions: the northern
part of the country (Sahel region).
Burkina Faso, formerly Upper Volta, the
fifth poorest country in the world with one
of the highest infant mortality rates, has
been seriously affected by drought and
desertification ever since 1 968. The lowest
recorded rainfall for 30 years was
registered in 1 98 1 when about one-third of
the country's livestock was lost due to
drought. 1983 was another peak drought
year, especially in the northern part of the
country where the harvest failed
completely.'
In a country where the health and nutri¬
tion status of children and mothers is nor¬
mally already very poor, the present
drought renders them even more vulnerable
to communicable and parasitical diseases
as malnutrition increases.
Large-scale imports of basic foodstuffs,
which have become an annual feature of
the country's battle for survival, were again
needed in 1984 to meet the food shor¬
tages. Seeds for the next planting season
will also be required.
Mauritania
Most affected provinces: nine regions
(out of a total of 1 2).
The drought situation, which has existed
for over ten years, became particularly
serious in the course of 1983. In certain
localities, rainfall levels were the lowest in
70 years. The Senegal River rose only to
10% of its normal rainy-season level, thus
preventing water-recession agriculture,
and the losses of animals and grazing land
have been massive.
Difficulties in the supply of milk and meat
are foreseen due to the present large-scale
sale of livestock at low prices. Current
cereal production is estimated at 15,000
tons (against 61,000 tons in 1981/1982),
which represents only 6% of consumption.
Severe cases of malnutrition are already
recorded in some areas (numerous cases of
vitamin deficiency, especially scurvy and
anaemia).
Zimbabwe
Most affected regions: all eight pro¬
vinces (the outskirts of the country
more than the centre).
According to government estimates,
malnourished children total 464,200,
and only 244,400 are currently
assisted.
Zimbabwe is suffering the third year of a
drought which is the worst in living
memory. No surplus food is currently
available and the situation is not expected
to improve with the next harvest. The
maize shortfall over the next 15 months,
entirely due to the drought, is estimated at
838,000 tons.
Amongst the vulnerable groups, the
health condition is often very serious.
Drought relief programmes are being co¬
ordinated by the Zimbabwe government
and include the distribution of basic food
rations and supplementary feeding
programmes.
Ethiopia
Most affected regions: Wollo, Gon-
dar, Eritrea, and Tigre.
Number of affected persons:
5,200,000 out of a total population of
32,395,000
The percentage of those under the age of
15 affected varies from 37 to 68% in dif¬
ferent regions. In addition, about 2.2 million
displaced people need assistance. Several
administrative regions have not had rain for
three consecutive crop seasons. The most
affected regions are all in northern Ethiopia.
Serious food shortages are also occurring
in other administrative regions of Ethiopia.
Some 52,950 people in the region of Bale,
278,830 in the region of Hararghe, and
35,250 in the region of Gojjam require im¬
mediate assistance; 122,000 in the Soha
region, 2,530 in Arussi, 79,880 in Gemu-
Goffa are likely to require assistance.
165,040 nomads in the Sidamo ad¬
ministrative region are also in dire need of
assistance. In addition, some 221,610
displaced persons in the Gondar, Hararghe,
Bale and Sidamo regions require immediate
assistance.
Mozambique
Most affected regions: Gaza, Inham-
bane, Maputo, Tete, Zambezia, Sofala,
Manica.
Number of affected persons:
4,700,000.
Mozambique has been experiencing
severe drought for the past four years, with
an aggravation of the situation in 1 982 and
1983. Gaza, Inhambane, and Maputo are
considered to be the most seriously af¬
fected. FAO estimates that 4.7 million peo¬
ple, especially in rural areas, are affected,
including 1 .8 million in the southern pro¬
vinces alone. Moreover, the Maputo pro¬
vince was struck by a cyclone at the end of
January 1984 and more than half of the
population was affected by the complete
loss of summer crops.
The cereal imports required by the coun¬
try at large are estimated at 600,000 tons
as opposed to 300,000 tons in normal
years.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Chad Mali
Most affected provinces: Kanem,
Biltine, Batha.
Number of displaced and affected
persons needing emergency assistance:
Kanem, 200,000; Biltine, 50,000;
Batha, 50,000; the majority are women
and children.
The. situation is catastrophic due to 17
years of internal conflict, a decade of
drought, lack of adequate administrative
structure, and a very poor internal com¬
munication network.
Chad is presently totally dependent on in¬
ternational food aid for its survival. The
Comité Inter-Etats de Lutte contre la
Sécheresse au Sahel (CILSS) estimates that
the structural food deficit in Chad is 1 5,000
metric tons a year. The Ministry of Natural
Calamities estimated the net food deficit
for 1983/1984 at 107,557 tons.
The most severely affected groups are
women and children. They are facing
serious malnutrition and illnesses caused
by nutritional deficiencies and lack of drink¬
ing water (scabies, malaria, measles, in¬
testinal infections, tuberculosis).
Niger
Most affected provinces: Zinder and
Diffa.
Number of affected children: 23,800.
Niger, which has a large external debt, is
like other Sahelian nations facing the con¬
sequences of uncertain rainfall. In 1983
and 1984 persistent drought severely af¬
fected certain pockets of the population,
especially in the areas of Zinder and Diffa in
the south-east.
On the other hand, in some other parts of
the country, harvests were more or less
satisfactory. Although some food stocks
are available, many households in both rural
and peri-urban areas do not have the pur¬
chasing power to buy them.
Most affected provinces: all the
Sahelian zone of the country (Gao and
Timbuktu regions).
Number of affected persons:
2,500,000 of whom 1,100,000 are
children under the age of 15 and
500,000 under the age of five. These
figures exclude migrants from
neighbouring countries, as their present
number is difficult to evaluate.
Chronic drought has affected the
Sahelian region of Mali (two-thirds of the
country) since 1 969. The severe drought of
1968-1974, with the peak year of 1973,
drastically reduced livestock levels. There
was some improvement between 1 976 and
1978,' but since 1980 the recurrence of
serious drought conditions has again
resulted in a drop in food production and the
herd level.
The situation worsened in 1 983; the rain¬
fall throughout the country has never been
so poor and the level of the rivers is the
lowest recorded this century. Most of the
lakes are now dried up.
Many of the water points where seden¬
tary and nomadic people are now concen¬
trated are not equipped to cope with the in¬
creased numbers. This creates a spreading
ground for diseases and epidemics and puts
the children in particular at high risk, all the
more because the areas severely affected
by the drought are also seriously under-
equipped in the social and health fields.
It is feared that the catastrophic death
toll of 1973-when 90% of the children
under the age of five died in the camps that
had been set upwill recur if no urgent ac¬
tion is taken to rehabilitate the health and
nutrition conditions.
Texts adapted from Ideas Forum, UNICEF.
As we go to press, new and higher figures for
the numbers of people affected are being
quoted. Some authorities now estimate the
figure for Ethiopia, for example, to be as high
as 7,000,000.
Senegal
Most affected provinces: the river
region, the north, and the Louga and
Linguere regions.
Number of affected persons:
1,100,000 among whom 500,000 in
the most vulnerable group (children,
pregnant and nursing mothers).
Senegal has been suffering over the last
1 5 years, and especially for the last seven
years, from a severe drought that has
seriously affected the population and the
local economy. Drought conditions drive
cultivators and nomads towards the towns,
which are totally unable to support them.
The 1 983 rainy season was particularly
poor and the harvest available for consump¬
tion in 1983/1984 was estimated at half
the normal annual production. The cereal
deficit itself was estimated at 370,000
tons.
Angola
Most affected provinces: central and
southern provinces.
Number of affected and displaced
persons: 1,000,000.
The drought began in 1980/1982 in the
central and southern provinces. More than
260,000 people are affected and among
these almost 80% are women and children.
A succession of dry seasons has con¬
siderably reduced food production, and the
decline in the price of oil, coffee, and
diamonds on the world market has also
considerably reduced export earnings at a
time when large-scale importation of food
is necessary.
In addition to the deteriorating economic
situation, the political and military conflict
has displaced and affected many more
people.
Heavy rains during February and March
1984 had disastrous effects on the road
conditions, housing, sanitation, and crops
as floods washed away seeds and young
plants.
Today in Angola, one-third of the children
die before their fifth birthday.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
The menace
of desert advance
by Mohamed Skouri
FOR the past twenty years, areas on
the fringe of the Sahara have suf¬
fered from profound disturbances
which have drastically changed the facts
of desertification. In addition to the per¬
sistence of the drought, these areas have
undergone substantial socio-economic
and ecological changes which have even
increased the severity of the problem.
Although scientific knowledge about
near-desert environments has made enor¬
mous progress, a great deal still has to be
done on the practical level to arrive at
solutions which are adapted to the
ecological and socio-economic conditions
prevailing there.
Research must therefore aim not only
at broadening knowledge and at improv¬
ing the methods of exploiting natural
resources but also at taking greater ac¬
count of the characteristics of these
resources in relation to technological
development and to changes in socio¬
economic conditions.
It was with just such things in mind that
Unesco launched its major international
programme on Man and the Biosphere
(MAB). The goal of this programme, which
started operations early in the 1 970s, is to
promote a new approach to research on
natural environments, studying the im¬
pact of human activities on natural
resources in order to identify the best
ways of using those resources. As well as
leading to an improvement of methods,
this programme has contributed to the
launching of pilot projects embracing
research, training and demonstration ac¬
tivities and closely involving the people
concerned, researchers, extension
workers and decision-makers.
In preparation for a special meeting
held In Nairobi in April/May 1984 to make
a general assessment of progress in the
Implementation of the Plan of Action to
combat desertification, Unesco was re¬
quested to update three case-studies con¬
cerning Chile, Niger and Tunisia which
were initially prepared for the 1977 United
Nations Conference on Desertification.
The study on Niger provides a typical
example of the way MAB works.
Updating the case-study shows that of
the two main causes of desertification,
that is, the prolonged drought and in¬
creasing human and animal pressure,
either could have been the main one.
However, the fact that there are instances
of serious deterioration in sparsely in¬
habited regions means that the initial
cause of the process was the inadequate
rainfall. There is reason to believe that if,
in 1970, human and animal pressure on
the natural environment had been less
Each year21 million hectares ofonce pro¬
ductive land are rendered useless for far¬
ming and a further 6 million hectares are
reduced to desert. Left, the abandoned
village ofDouz, Tunisia, has been almost
completely swallowed up by encroaching
sand dunes.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
©
severe, the effects of the drought would
have been neither as swift nor as
dramatic, but they would have existed in a
more localized fashion.
By 1983, despite a rise in rainfall since
1977, the vegetation had not yet returned
to its pre-drought level, either in quantity
or in quality. This was certainly due to the
fact that the rains during these "good
years" were neither abundant enough nor
sufficiently well distributed to make up for
the heavy toll of the long years of previous
deficits, and also because human and
animal pressure on pastoral areas had
outpaced regeneration. When the crisis
began during the 1970s, the pastoral load
was eased as the people fled and was
eased even more towards the end as
animals died after depleting all the fodder.
After the exceptional drought, the return
of Peul cattle herds, the livestock
replenishment policy and the rapid in¬
crease of small livestock has led to a rapid
reconstitution of herds, though previous
numbers have not yet been attained.
The responsibility of man, whose action
is coupled with the effects of the climate,
is beyond doubt. However, the impact of
man is localized since the destruction of
the vegetation through direct felling,
through grazing or trampling by herds,
and even through bush fires, never af¬
fected the entire environment as climatic
change did. In the absence of man, his
herds and/or his crops, the shortage of
rainfall would have had nearly identical ef¬
fects, outside areas of heavy concentra-
With the smell of water in their nostrils, a
flock ofgoats races towards a water hole
across rangeland badly eroded by over¬
grazing in Kenya.
tion. Overgrazing is not responsible for
the alarming regression of the Com¬
miphora africana, a shrub whose leaves
are eaten by goats and camels, but the
prolonged drought and the wind. On the
other hand, overfelling of forest for
firewood is quite independent of climatic
variability.
The greatest source of concern for the
future is now the effects of the regression
of the plant cover. When inadequately
covered, the land is exposed to the
ravages of the sun, water and wind. The
lack of plant matter reduces the formation
of humus so that a chain reaction is likely
to be triggered off which would make the
possibility of any true "recovery" of the
biological environment very unlikely.
The reduction of plant biomass and the
concomitant dwindling of plant formations
leave the soil bare and reduce obstacles
to the winds. Denuded surfaces have in¬
creased significantly and, in addition,
wind abrasion is affecting larger areas,
which in turn are increasingly difficult for
vegetation to reconquer. The now-
frequent, violent, sand-laden winds are
surely a sign of a worsening of en¬
vironmental disintegration.
In the final analysis, it is very hard to
provide a categorical countrywide
response to the question: "Has deser
tification increased or diminished in north¬
west Niger since 1977?" In fact, accor¬
ding to the sector or factor under con¬
sideration, one can give opposite replies.
Plant cover in the Sahel is constantly
undergoing change and quite frequently,
to complicate observation, the her¬
baceous layer does not develop at the
same rate as the tree layer, or growth on
sandy soils is not the same as growth on
clay soils. Faced with these non-
synchronous changes, it is rather difficult
to express an overall opinion on trends in
1984. On the other hand, views are
unanimous about the causes described
above and this makes it possible to build
a strategy on solid bases.
The study on Niger clearly underlines
the fact that despite adverse climatic con¬
ditions, the natural plant formations have
a good regenerative potential which can
be enhanced if human and animal
pressure is maintained at a level compati¬
ble with those formations' regenerative
capacity. The area covered by the study,
about 70,000 km2, is sufficiently large to
be quite representative of much of the
Sahelian environment.
MOHAMED SKOURI is a programme
specialist in Unesco's Division of Ecological
Sciences. An agronomist, he specializes in
problems of arid zones.
This article is based on a longer study publish¬
ed in Unesco's environmental magazine
Nature and Resources, Volume XX, No. 1,
January-March 1984.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Mining fossil water
by Jean Margat and Kamal Saad
Semi-arid
Sub-humid to humid
Maps based on Map of the World Distribution ofArid Regions.
Unesco, 1977.
Maps show, top, zones of aridity In north
Africa and, lower map, the location of the
main sedimentarybasins containing deep
aquifers.
FAR below the surface of the earth,
vast quantities of life-giving water
have lain concealed for thousands
of years in huge aquifers (layers of water¬
bearing porous rock) formed in the exten¬
sive sedimentary basins that exist in every
continent.
Most of these aquifers were first
discovered and exploited during the nine¬
teenth century, but, in some countries, it
is only in the last few decades that inten¬
sive use has been made of them.
In arid areas such reservoirs have, of
course, become of outstanding impor¬
tance and often represent the sole perma¬
nent source of water. Fortunately reser¬
voirs of this kind are to be found in the
subsoil of several countries in arid areas,
including, in particular, the huge desert
area which stretches from the Atlantic
Ocean to the Gulf, covering the north of
the African continent (the Sahara) and the
Arabian peninsula (see map).
Naturally enough, the primary concern
in these countries was to improve pros¬
pection and exploitation techniques. More
and more wells were drilled and water pro¬
duction was often substantially increased
in each basin.
This increased exploitation had the
predictable effect of reducing water levels
and in some cases the quality of the water
drawn deteriorated. It soon became evi¬
dent that what was needed was to
establish a strategy for the long-term ex¬
ploitation of each basin as a whole.
Research carried out in a number of
countries soon showed that the water con¬
fined in these deep aquifers represents a
non-renewable resource. There was
clearly a need for a special conception of
water resources and special procedures
for evaluating them. A model example of
this type of approach is Unesco's Study
Project on Water Resources in the Nor¬
thern Sahara.
In absolute terms hardly any ground¬
water exists completely independently of
the natural water cycle. However, water
moves at very different speeds in different
aquifer layers, and in addition the
distances travelled may vary greatly.
Where water has to cover hundreds or
even thousands of kilometres at speeds of
the order of several metres a year, it may ^
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Above, as this dramatic aerial view of a
rotary irrigation system in northern Africa
demonstrates, the mining of water from
deep aquifers allows desert areas to be
reclaimed for agriculture. In the Sarir
region of the Libyan Arab Jamahlriya 500
productive wells have been drilled and
50,000 hectares of desert reclaimed for
cultivation. Right, well and pivot mecha¬
nism round which the sprinkler rotates at
the centre of an irrigated area. The huge
sprinkler arm can be moved round as
required and can irrigate an area of some
80 hectares.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
stay in the subsoil for periods of up to tens
of thousands of years.
This does not mean that this "fossil"
water, as hydrologists call it, is stagnant
or that there is no renewal of water in
these very extensive deep aquifers. It is
simply that the renewal is very very slow.
It is also, strictly, incorrect to call this
water a non-renewable resource; it is only
non-renewable in relation to its use on the
human time-scale. On the larger scale of
the natural water cycle, water drawn is
never lost, but is merely transferred and
modified.
However, the local structure that pro¬
vides the resource may, through intensive
exploitation, undergo irreversible
changes such as the compaction of the
soil or an intrusion of salt water. Thus
harnessing the water resources of one of
these aquifers amounts to drawing on the
water reserve capital and, by analogy with
the extraction of mineral ores, it can right¬
ly be described as the "mining" of
groundwater.
"Water mines", productive drilling
fields exploiting deep aquifers on the
basis of withdrawal from storage, are ¡n
operation in various countries in the arid
zone where they account for the bulk of
water production.
In the developing countries in the arid
zones of Africa and the Middle East such
projects have been increasing rapidly and
plans exist to intensify them, for example,
in the northern Sahara (Algeria and
Tunisia), in Egypt and in the Libyan Arab
Jamahiriya.
Deciding whether or not to exploit
groundwater reserves, whose use means
their depletion, ¡snot an academic ques¬
tion since this is already current practice.
The deliberate mining of groundwater
raises first, as in any mining operation, the
problem of evaluating the formationin
this case the reservoir and its exploitable
resourcesand forecasting the effects of
withdrawals on usability. The exploitation
of a dynamic reserve which reacts to ex¬
ploitation is more complex than that of a
passive ore deposit.
Furthermore, mining costs rise as water
levels fall, with a marked increase when
the change takes place from artesian ex¬
ploitation to pumping or where the pro¬
ductivity of wells declines as a result of
compaction of the aquifer.
Questions also arise in a wider perspec¬
tive as to the long-term disadvantages of
such exploitation. The gains for one or two
generations are achieved to the detriment
of future generations. The choice is bet¬
ween maximizing production for the
benefit of the present generation in order
to speed up socio-economic development
or spreading production out over a
Desert aquifers are to be found at depths
ranging from 50 to 1,500 metres. Below,
"fossil" water gushes forth after a suc¬
cessful drilling operation in Saudi Arabia.
relatively long period in order, for exam¬
ple, to make it easier to adapt to the even¬
tual requirements of a different water
economy.
Replacement solutions for water supply
might involve, for example, the recharg¬
ing of depleted aquifers with water pro¬
duced by the desalinization of sea water
(as in the current Qatar project for the
recharge of deep aquifers) or, rather
analogous to the closing down of a mine,
moving the population or at least limiting
it to activities involving low water con¬
sumption (as in the project to end irriga¬
tion in various counties in the State of
Arizona, in the United States).
Should the mining of groundwater be
encouraged or discouraged? In practice
action has often preceded analysis and a
commitment made to the mining option.
Thus the question that now arises for
those responsible for water resource
management is primarily one of choosing
between maintaining the present trend
and even intensifying it, or modifying it
with a view to prolonging production at a
reduced level.
JEAN MARGAT is a French hydrogeologist
at the Bureau de Recherches Géologiques et
Minières, Orleans.
KAMAL F. SAAD is a water specialist at
Unesco's Regional Office for Science and
Technology for the Arab States.
This article is taken from a longer study
published in Unesco's environmental
magazine Nature and Resources, Volume XX,
No. 2, April-June 1984.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO'S INTERNATIONAL HYDROLOGICAL
PROGRAMME
Managing the world's
most precious resource
HALF the population of the world, two billion men, women
and children, lack easy access to an adequate supply of
pure fresh water. In rural areas, where the situation is
worst, only 29 per cent have access to safe water supplies and still
fewer, 13 per cent, have sanitary facilities.
Yet drinkable water is necessary for life, for health, and for a
productive existence. Without it, both men and animals sicken and
die. Fresh water provides sustenance to plants, constitutes the
habitat of fish and aquatic organisms, and makes agriculture possi¬
ble. It is essential to some industries, and in rivers and lakes pro¬
vides a medium of transportation and recreation. The United Na¬
tions has recognized the importance of fresh water and adequate
sanitary facilities by naming the period 1981 to 1990 the Interna¬
tional Drinking Water Supply and Sanitation Decade.
Water, or the lack of it, poses enormous problems for mankind.
The World Health Organization estimates that 80 per cent of the ill¬
ness affecting the population of the earth is directly associated with
water: for example, 400 million people suffer from gastro-enteritis,
200 million from schistosomiasis, and 30 million from onchocer¬
cosis, and water is involved in the transmission of all of these. It has
been estimated that if potable water were universally available, the
world rate of infant mortality could be halved, primarily through
eradication of diarrhoeal diseases.
Those who are ill cannot work productively. But even among
those who are well, tremendous amounts of time and energy are
wasted by the daily search for water. Women and children in
developing countries often walk long distances each day in search
of water. In one village in Burkina Faso, (formerly Upper Volta),
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
for example, mothers walk for two to three hours a day to find a
river or stagnant pond, and return to their homes carrying 25
kilograms of the precious stuff in earthenware jars on their heads.
In some slums surrounding the cities of developing countries,
families often have to spend 10 per cent of their income to buy
water for household needs.
While water scarcity is the major problem for the majority of the
world's people, a surplus is sometimes just as serious, as when
floods occur, wiping out whole villages and sweeping food crops
away. Tidal waves can be a deadly hazard for villagers living along
coastlines.
Many such problems are the result of man's incomplete
understanding of the ways in which water moves through and over
the earth, is replenished by rainfall and disappears into the at¬
mosphere through evaporation. Others are caused by man's
mismanagement of the earth's waters, or by a lack of management.
Pollution and over-enrichment (eutrophication) of inland water
bodies are major problems worldwide, while coastal areas of the
oceans, where two-thirds of the world's population live, have suf¬
fered extreme pressures as these people have advanced
economically.
Man's fresh water problems are likely to increase in future unless
steps are taken to improve the management of this valuable
resource throughout the globe. Unesco's programmes are designed
to contribute to this more rational management. The objectives are
to improve scientific and technical knowledge, train the necessary
personnel, build up research and training institutions and stimulate
participation by the populations concerned in the conservation and
development of water resources.
Unesco's programmes deal with both fresh water and the oceans,
but in view of the immense scope of these subjects, this issue of the
Unesco Courier focuses attention on some of the major problems
involved in the rational development and management of fresh
water resources.
Unesco's involvement in water problems goes back to 1950, when
it launched a programme of research on the world's arid zones, in
which hydrology played a major part. By 1965, despite Unesco's ef¬
forts, world water problems had increased. The rapid growth of
population, together with the extension of irrigated agriculture and
industrial development, had led to such environmental stress that
nations realized they could no longer use the earth's water resources
as carelessly and wastefully as they had in the past. The need for
a consistent policy of rational water resource management had
become evident.
Thus it was that Unesco began the first worldwide programme of
studies of the hydrological cycle the International Hydrological
Decade (IHD). This remarkable example of international co¬
operation, which involved more than 100 countries, made a signifi¬
cant contribution to an understanding of the processes occurring in
the water cycle, assessment of surface and groundwater resources,
and adoption of a rational attitude towards water use.
The International Hydrological Programme
After reviewing these results and assessing the continuing need
for co-operation in this field, Unesco's General Conference in 1974
decided to launch the long-term International Hydrological Pro¬
gramme (IHP). The IHP's purpose is to develop a scientific basis
for the rational management of water resources, taking into ac¬
count both quantity and quality. It is designed to help find solu¬
tions to specific water problems in countries with different
geographical conditions and levels of technological and economic
development, and constitutes the main components of Unesco's
fresh water programme.
The IHP works through governmental representation on Na¬
tional Committees and National Focal Points (through which the
work is carried out). By the end of 1983, 101 Member States of
Unesco had established National Committees, and National Focal
Points had been established in another 31. Thus a total of 132
Member States were involved in the programme. It is an open-
ended programme: IHP's Intergovernmental Council, in Paris in
March 1984, approved the third phase of its work, designated
IHP-III.
IHP-III involves worldwide projects under 18 major themes.
These range from assessment of the role of snow and ice on the
water cycle to the compilation of information on the impact of
climate change on droughts and catastrophic floods, to the applica¬
tion to water resources studies of new technologies like remote sens¬
ing from satellites.
Beginning with IHP-I, great emphasis has been placed on educa¬
tion and training activities. Nearly 1,500 specialists were trained in
Unesco-sponsored or organized courses during the period
(1975-1980). During 1981-1983, more than 600 specialists in the
water sciences from developing countries obtained advanced train¬
ing under Unesco sponsorship.
Because of a change in Unesco's budgetary period to coincide
with other United Nations bodies, the second phase of the IHP
(IHP-II) extended only over the period 1981-1983. The IHP has
now returned to six-year phases, coinciding with Unesco's
Medium-Term Plans, with IHP-III running from 1984-1989.
Practical Applications
IHP-III is placing much greater emphasis on practical applica¬
tions of scientific knowledge and rational water management,
although the programme will continue to deal with the traditional
hydrological sciences. The current programme phase is also at¬
tempting to devote greater efforts to reaching audiences that
formerly would not have been thought to be within the scope of
such a scientific endeavour, such as planners, policy-makers and
the concerned public. Demonstration projects are also emphasized,
Desalinization, the process of removing
salt and other minerals from sea water to
provide pure water for drinking or for
industrial use has been practised on a
small scale for many years. As water
needs grow and the techniques involved
become more efficient, more and larger
desalinization plants are coming Into op¬
eration, although the initial capital outlay
required is still very high. Left, a desalini¬
zation plant at Jeddah, Saudi Arabia.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
A typical family with five children needs
about 40 litres of water a day just to sur¬
vive and about 200 litres a day to keep
clean and healthy. In many parts of rural
Africa and Asia women and children
spend up to eight hours a day on the soul-
destroying task of fetching the water.
Right, In Niger, a woman and her daugh¬
ter at a water hole.
to reinforce learning. And the immediate practicality of results is
being stressed. All these aspects are illustrated in the Major
Regional Projects described below. Another characteristic of the
programme is the attempt to use new techniques, such as remote
sensing from satellites, for the study of water resources.
One notable aspect of the IHP as a whole is its participatory
nature: the IHP works because a great number of experts and pro¬
fessional organizations around the world recognize the need for it
and want to take part in it. Most of this participation is on a volun¬
tary basis, through the IHP National Committees.
At the IHP Council meeting in Paris in March 1984, Unesco's
Regional Hydrologist for Africa made an eloquent plea to the inter¬
national community to assist in "making more heads free from car¬
rying pots, pans and buckets in search of water several kilometres
away".
Such is the purpose of Unesco's major regional project on the ra¬
tional use and conservation of water resources in rural areas in
Africa. (There are similar programmes for Latin America and the
Caribbean and for the Arab States.) Some parts of Africa south of
the Sahara are among those in which, as noted earlier, village
women have to spend several hours a day walking to and from
water sources during the dry season to meet their families' needs.
Traditionally, such people have lived a nomadic life, wandering
from place to place to make best use of available water, so they
never developed methods of water storage. But as population has
grown, water supplies have become exhausted.
In the Far East, where traditions are different, villagers in areas
where groundwater is saline have taken easily to the idea of building
ferrocement tanks for rooftop rainwater storage. The tanks are
built inexpensively from concrete reinforced by metal mesh, or
sometimes by bamboo poles. In north-east Thailand, for example,
1,500 such tanks have been built by villagers in a self-help project
to store rainwater collected from rooftops.
During 1983, the Asian Institute of Technology, with Unesco
support, organized a seminar and study tour of the Thai villages for
African officials from Benin, Ghana, Liberia, Senegal, Sierra
Leone, Zambia and Burkina Faso, to familiarize them with the use
of ferrocement for rainwater harvesting from rooftops. The group
attended lectures at the A.I.T. laboratory and visited the material-
testing laboratory. They also travelled to Java, Indonesia, to
observe the use there of tanks for rainwater storage as an alter¬
native to water from heavily polluted irrigation canals, which are
the traditional source of drinking water.
After the tour, participants recommended introduction of fer¬
rocement to Africa, and the establishment of training centres and
pilot projects. Since then, Unesco has proposed that the Govern¬
ment of the Republic of Congo provide funds for some 20 ferroce¬
ment rainwater storage tanks to demonstrate the suitability of this
technology for rural Africa.
Subsurface dams are another possible way of providing water to
drought-prone areas. These dams are simply sheets of metal or
other impervious material placed perpendicular to the direction of
water flow and introduced into dry sandy river beds. The dams
force a build-up of water under ground which can then be tapped
by bore-holes, and sometimes create sand reservoirs by retaining
the bed load that moves in the stream during floods. In a Botswana
project, two concrete weirs raised the level of the sand bed by about
one metre. Other similar projects are going on in Kenya and
Burkina Faso.
Major Regional Projects
The Major Regional Projects, begun in 1981, are intended to
contribute to the growth of scientific and technical potential in the
area involved, to the development of information networks, and to
a rational use of water resources based on the choice of the most
appropriate technologies for local conditions. The African project
will include publication of an inventory of existing rural water
systems and technologies, with the idea of identifying the most pro¬
mising low-cost examples.
. The purpose of the Major Regional Project in the Arab States is
to promote the conservation and improvement of traditional water
systems for use in rural areas. Here, too, an inventory of traditional
methods is being compiled, this time in co-operation with the Arab
Centre for Arid and Dry Lands. For each type of traditional
system, the project determines the conditions under which it will
best function. Studies are being undertaken to determine the ap¬
plicability of the systems under present circumstances and the way
in which they complement modern water management systems.
Guidance material is prepared for teaching engineers and techni¬
cians; other material is designed for decision-makers and some for
the general public. Local traditional skills are being revived to
assure the survival of the traditional systems.
The Latin American and Caribbean Major Regional Project has
similar aims: bringing back life to rural areas by combining prin¬
ciples of both traditional and modern technologies in low-cost, ap¬
propriate systems. National education and training programmes
will be promoted through mass media informational campaigns,
using radio, video, films, posters and training manuals.
Among the projects in this area are those that attempt to obtain
water in arid areas from non-conventional sources such as fog and
dew. Other projects will be aimed at obtaining energy for transpor¬
ting, desalinating and pumping water from sources such as extreme
daily temperature fluctuations, water currents and solar radiation.
Attention is being given also to water resource management and
erosion control through such techniques as terracing, construction
of farm ponds, and water-saving practices, such as irrigation
through porous pots. ^
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Rising from the skyline in the Pacific
coastal regions ofLatin America, in areas
where there is very little rainfall, these
curious, diamond-shaped structures are
helping to solve the problem of a chronic
lack of water. They are fog traps which
have been installed at experimental sites
in Chile, Ecuador and Peru as part of
Unesco's Major Regional Project on the
Use and Conservation of Water Resour¬
ces in the Rural Areas of Latin America
and the Caribbean. Fog, which is frequent
in these coastal areas due to an effect
known as "thermal inversion", is often
the only local source of fresh water. The
octahedral structures, which are made of
ordinary mosquito netting, intercept the
moisture which condenses into water.
Each octahedron can produce up to 200
litres of water a day.
The Secretariat for the International Hydrological Programme
(IHP) is provided at Unesco headquarters in Paris by the Divi¬
sion of Water Sciences under its Director Sorin Dumitrescu.
Under the supervision of the Intergovernmental Council of
the IHP, the Secretariat co-operates closely with the IHP Na¬
tional Committees and Focal Points for the IHP established in
over 130 Member States. An expert in water resources is sta¬
tioned at each of Unesco's five Regional Offices for Science
and Technology to provide on-the-spot advice and
assistance.
Close contacts are maintained with other United Nations
organizations with an interest in water resource problems
such as the United Nations Environment Programme (UNEP),
the World Meteorological Organization (WMO), the Food and
Agriculture Organization (FAO), the World Health Organiza¬
tion (WHO) and the International Atomic Energy Agency
(IAEA).
Field Projects
In addition to those included in its own annual budget, Unesco
also administers a number of field projects financed by funds from
outside the Organization. These deal with applied research, educa¬
tion and training, assessment of water resources and institution
building. For example: In Algeria and Tunisia, a study of ground¬
water resources in the northern Sahara, completed in 1972,
established the limits of exploitation of both shallow and deep
aquifers underlying the area. The results were presented in a form
useful for planning ministries. The International Atomic Energy
Agency and the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United
Nations co-operated in this project.
In Portugal, an environmental study of the Tejo estuary
(1977-1982), dealing with quality aspects of water management, is
to form the scientific basis on which the government will base its
pollution and environmental regulations and its decisions for in¬
vestment in waste water purification works. Other water resource
assessment projects have been carried out in the Canary Islands,
Spain, Brazil, Zambia and Mozambique.
In the Sudan, Unesco, with funds from the United Nations
Development Programme (UNDP), has assisted the Ministry of Ir¬
rigation since 1974 in establishing a hydraulic research station in
Wad Medani. This station is gradually becoming the water
resources engineering study branch of the Ministry. It will be
capable of carrying out hydrological surveys, hydraulic model
studies and hydraulic computations. Similar projects have been
carried out in Brazil, India, and Argentina.
In Nigeria, another Unesco/UNDP project has since 1978
assisted the Federal Ministry of Water Resources in establishing a
Federal Institute of Water Resources, which gives top priority to
training middle-level water resource technicians. Similar projects
have been carried out in Brazil, Tanzania and India, some with
financial support from Unesco's Funds-in-Trust projects.
In Sweden and Sicily (1977), India (1979) and Tanzania (1981),
Unesco has organized short-duration training courses on ground¬
water development from hard rock with the support of the Swedish
aid agency SIDA. With the assistance of the Norwegian Govern¬
ment, two to three-month courses for hydrology technicians were
organized in Kenya (1977) and Zambia (1982 and 1984).
The unique characteristic of all Unesco's activities in science and
technology is their international nature: no other organization is
able to call on the entire scientific resources of the world. Further¬
more, Unesco has in large part been responsible for creating some
of the most important international scientific bodies and networks,
such as those mentioned above, and for supporting them and en¬
couraging their activities. Because the world's waters are in large
part transnational resources, only an organization that works
through governments, as Unesco does, can fulfill this role.
This text is taken from a booklet now being prepared by Unesco science
writer David Spurgeon and which is to be published shortly by
Unesco's Science Sector under the title Managing the World's Waters.
The booklet will also cover problems connected with the world's
oceans.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Acid rain
1. An unwelcome export
MANKIND has always reverenced
what Tennyson called "the use¬
ful trouble of the rain". With¬
out the 120,000 cubic kilometres of it that
fall each year the continents would be
barren.
Yet now the rain in parts of the earth has
taken on a new and threatening complexity.
It mixes in the air with pollution from burn¬
ing fossil fuelsparticularly in power sta¬
tions, factories and motor vehiclesand
brings down dilute sulphuric and nitric
acid. This is killing fish and other water life,
and corroding buildings, including some of
the world's most important ancient
monuments. It may also damage forests
and croplands, and possibly pose a substan¬
tial threat to health.
Acid rain is not a new phenomenon the
term was first coined by a chemist, Robert
Angus Smith, who described pollution in
Manchester, England, over a century ago.
What is new is the realization that it is an in¬
ternational problem. The air of towns like
Manchester has been largely cleaned, partly
by building tall chimneys at power stations
and factories, which push pollution high in¬
to the air. These chimneys have made things
better locally, by dispersing the pollutants,
but have aggravated the international dif¬
ficulties. For the sulphur and nitrogen com¬
pounds emitted by burning fossil fuels can
be blown thousands of kilometres by the
winds, to cause acid rain in countries far
from their points of origin.
Acid rain was first raised as an interna¬
tional issue by Sweden at the United Na¬
tions Conference on the Human Environ¬
ment in Stockholm in 1972, and it has now
developed into a major international en¬
vironmental issue. At first the Swedish
views were treated with some disbelief, par¬
ticularly by some of the emitting countries.
Over the last decade, however, there has
been a great deal of international research
into the issue. Ample information was
available by the end of 1982 through the ac¬
tivities of the Co-operative Programme for
Monitoring and Evaluation of Long-range
Transmission of Air Pollutants in Europe
(EMEP), under the Convention on Long-
range Transboundary Air Pollution 1979,
and activities conducted in accordance with
the Memorandum of Intent Between the
Government of Canada and the Govern¬
ment of the United States of America con¬
cerning Transboundary Air Pollution. Fur¬
thermore, there was a special conference in
Stockholm in 1982 on acidification of the
environment, and this reviewed and assess¬
ed a large amount of scientific information
not previously available.
So far, acid rain has been seen as an
essentially regional problem, confined to
the industrial areas of the northern
hemisphere. But, though the problem was
first perceived there, it may become much
more widespreadfor acid rain is likely to
occur wherever fossil fuels are intensively
used.
Acidification is an environmental prob¬
lem, or becoming one, in parts of Europe
and North America. Around five to ten
million square kilometres of these con¬
tinents are affected. Similarly polluted
areas are likely to exist elsewhere in the
world, especially around large urban and
industrial conglomerations. We do not yet
know where they are, because so far no
evidence on them is available.
Industrial regions of the world suffer
much more acidic fall-out than they did
before the industrial revolution. This is
because power plants, some industrial pro¬
cesses, vehicles and homes emit sulphur and
nitrogen compounds, mainly from the bur¬
ning of fossil fuels, and have greatly in¬
creased the amount of them in the
environment.
Natural processes also put sulphur and
nitrogen compounds into the air, besides
man-made sources. Nobody knows precise¬
ly how much they contribute around the
globe. Estimates vary between 78 and 284
million tons of sulphur a year in the form of
sulphur oxides, and between 20 and 90
million tons of nitrogen a year in nitrogen
oxides.
In comparison, man emits between 75
and 100 million tonnes of sulphur a year.
So, despite the differences in estimates of
natural sources, it can be concluded that
man-made and natural emissions of sulphur
are, globally, of the same order of
magnitude.
Burning coal provides about 60 per cent
of the man-made emissions, burning
petroleum products gives rise to another 30
per cent, and various industrial processes
account for the remaining 10 per cent. Ap¬
proximate estimates indicate that burning
fuel in electric power stations and industry
provides almost three quarters of sulphur
emissions in the European Economic Com¬
mission countries.
There are indications that sulphur diox¬
ide emissions (the main pollutant in Europe
and North America) have not increased
during recent years, as they were predicted
to do, and are not likely to rise over the
coming decades either. This is the result of
two factors: better pollution control, and
less burning of fossil fuel as a result of
energy conservation and, possibly, slower
economic growth in the west than had been
expected.
Like sulphur oxide pollution, pollution
from nitrogen oxides is also of the same
order compared to natural sources. Fossil
fuel combustion yields about 20 million
tons of nitrogen a year, which have already
caused environmental problems on a
regional and local basis in industrialized
countries.
Not all the pollution is acid rain, i.e.,
sulphuric and nitric acid dissolved in
precipitation. Some of it happens when the
sulphur and nitrogen oxides themselves fall
out on the land, in what is known as "dry
deposition". In general this tends to be the
main form of the pollution near its source,
and the longer the gases stay in the air, the
more likely they are to go through the com¬
plex changes that will turn them into acid
rain (or wet deposition), to fall perhaps
thousands of kilometres from where they
began their journey. Wet deposition rates
are fairly well known, but dry deposition is
harder to calculate and rates remain more
uncertain. Both types of deposition can be
intercepted by vegetation canopies. The
canopies of evergreen forests, in particular,
can be subjected to high deposition rates.
Lakes and rivers were the first victims of
acid rain to become evident. Hundreds of
lakes in parts of Scandinavia, the north-east
United States, south-east Canada and
south-west Scotland have turned acid. Parts
of these areas are particularly vulnerable
because their soil and bedrock offer little
protection against acidic rain. They are
made up of minerals like granite, gneiss and
quartz-rich rocks which contain little lime
and do not weather easily, and therefore
can do little to neutralize the acid when it
falls.
As the water becomes more acid, the
amount of aluminium in it starts to increase
rapidly. Concentrations as low as 0.2
milligrams per litre of the metal in acid
water kill fish. Large scale fish kills have
been recorded in some Swedish lakes, and
these have been attributed to aluminium
poisoning rather than to high acidity alone.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
©
At the same time, phosphates, which
nourish phytoplankton and other aquatic
plants, attach themselves to the aluminium
and become less available as a nutrient. So
increasing aluminium levels may reduce
primary production on which all other
water life depends. As the water gets more
acid still, other metals, like cadmium, zinc,
lead and mercury also become increasingly
soluble. Several of them are highly toxic,
and some may be taken up by water life
through food chains, though little evidence
of this is available so far.
Soils are normally much better able to
resist acidification than lakes, rivers and
streams, and so can take much more acid
without noticeable ecological drawbacks.
Their vulnerability differs depending on
their type, the kind of bedrock they cover,
and the use to which man puts them. The
most vulnerable lands are those that have
bedrocks poor in lime, covered with
shallow layers of soil containing low con¬
centrations of protective substances. Large
parts of Scandinavia are like this.
Intensive experimental research into the
effects of acidification on forest, land and
wood production was carried out in the
1970s. It is still going on, but so far the
results are inconclusive. Acid fall-out does
seem to have a distinct effect on soil
microbiology, chemistry and fauna but
the effects on the growth of plants, in¬
cluding trees, are far less clear. Indeed,
depositions of nitrogen may even have a
fertilizing effect and increase productivity
significantly, at least in the short term.
Studies on the trends of tree growth in
southern Sweden between 1950 and 1974,
for example, failed to reveal any statistical¬
ly significant pattern.
In the Federal Republic of Germany, on
the other hand, 7.7 per cent of the forest
area was reported in 1982 to be damaged by
wasting disease due to the consequences of
deposition and accumulation of air
pollutants. In addition, trees have suffered
more storm damage and experienced
regeneration difficulties. These forests
receive much more fall-out than Scandina¬
vian ones because they are close to cities and
big industrial areas, such as the Ruhr, with
many polluting sources.
One reason postulated to explain this
damage is the combined effects of surges of
naturally produced acid, extreme climatic
situations (very high or low rainfall,
temperature extremes) and atmospheric
acidic deposition. These release aluminium
into the soil and make it easier for bacteria
to damage the fine roots of the trees. This
reduces their vitality, leads eventually to a
rotting disease, and may make them more
vulnerable to storms. High concentrations
of sulphur dioxide in the air may damage
leaves, and so cut the trees' productivity.
Acid fogs, persisting for several days, may
also damage trees in mountain areas.
As well as the health of important
ecosystems, human health may also be put
at risk by pollution. High concentrations of
sulphur dioxide, nitrogen, oxides and dust
have long been known to be harmful. This
issue is only marginally related to the
problem of acid rain, since such concentra¬
tions are usually only found close to the
sources of pollution, and sulphur oxide
levels in many European and North
American cities have been decreasing
recently. The minimum concentrations of
sulphur dioxide and nitrogen dioxide con¬
sidered to cause health damage are: sulphur
dioxide, 250 micrograms per cubic metre as
a 24-hour average or 100 micrograms per
cubic metre as a long-term average;
nitrogen dioxide, 190-320 micrograms per
cubic metre, as a maximum one hour ex¬
posure not to be exceeded more than once
a month.
Other, indirect, health hazards are
suspected. These would be caused by the
metals like lead, copper, zinc, cadmium and
mercury released from soils and sediments
by increased acidification. They can get in¬
to groundwater, rivers, lakes and streams
used for drinking water, and be taken up in
food chains leading ultimately to man. The
releases of cadmium in particular may give
rise to a growing problem as acidity in¬
creases, as normal levels in human food are
already close to the acceptable daily intake.
Acid water may also cause galvanized steel
and copper water pipes to release metals,
and it seems that the risk arises as soon as
the acidity of the water rises above normal.
Most drinking water in industrialized coun¬
tries, however, is supplied by public water
works which eliminate this problem with
proper treatment techniques; but much re¬
mains to be done in developing countries.
Meanwhile, acid accelerates corrosion in
most materials used in the construction of
buildings, bridges, dams, industrial equip¬
ment, water supply networks, underground
storage tanks, hydroelectric turbines, and
power and telecommunications cables. It
can also severely damage ancient
monuments, historic buildings, sculptures,
ornaments and other important cultural ob¬
jects. Some of the world's greatest cultural
treasures, including the Parthenon in
Athens and Trajan's column in Rome, are
being eaten away by acid fall-out.
Tests have shown that materials corrode
between twice and 10 times as fast' in
polluted urban and industrial atmospheres
as they do in the countryside. Carbon steel
(both coated and uncoated), zinc and
galvanized steel, copper, nickel and nickle-
plated steel, sandstone and limestone all
corroded faster as the amount of sulphur
dioxide in the air increased. On the other
hand, materials such as aluminium and
stainless steel were only negligibly affected. >
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The damaging effects of acid rain first
became apparent in lakes and rivers. In
Sweden, damage to fisheries attributed
to acidification has been observed in
2,500 lakes and evidence of acidification
has been found in another 6,500. Of the
5,000 lakes In southern Norway, 1,750
have lost all their fish and another 900 are
seriously affected. In Canada, nearly 20
percent ofall the lakes so far examined in
Ontario have become acidified or are
extremely sensitive to acidification. Bet¬
ween 30 and 60 per cent of the lakes of
southwest Quebec are sensitive or highly
sensitive to acidification. In Canada's
Atlantic provinces many lakes have
become 10 to 30 times more acid during
the past two decades. Above, Lake Mali¬
gne, Alberta Province, Canada, is seen
against the backdrop of the Henry
MacLeod Mountains.
The sensitivity ofaquatic organisms
to a lowered pH in fresh water
pH 7.5 7.0 6.5 6.0 5 5 5.0 4.5 4.0 3.5
HEM&
Crustaceans, snails, molluscs, etc
Salmon, char
ß ^^sé^.
Sens
and
itive
animal
trout, roach die
insects and plant
plankton die
Whitefish, "siklöja", grayling die
Perch arid pike die
die
Eel and brook trout die
'11112! Insensitive insects, certain plant and animal
plankton can survive
Damage starts at
pH less than 6.5
All "norimal" life
pH less ithan 5.
gone at
White moss increases
Source : Acidification today and Tomorrow, Report by the
Swedish Ministry of Agriculture to the 1982 Stockholm
Conference on Acidification of the Environment, i
O
©
t
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Acid rain
2. Can we save our lakes and forests?
THE damage caused by acid rain can
be alleviated by adding lime to
lakes, rivers and streams and/or
their catchment areas. Many chemicals such
as caustic soda, sodium carbonate, slaked
lime, limestone, or dolomite can be used to
counteract the acidity. Slaked lime and
limestone are the most popular. Sweden
began a liming programme in the autumn of
1976, and by the summer of 1982 about
1,500 Swedish lakes had been limed at a
total cost of about $15 million.
Liming alleviates some of the symptoms
of acidification, but it is no real cure, is not
practicable for many lakes and running
waters, and does not attack the causes of
the problem. It should, however, be con¬
sidered as an interim measure which offers
some defence until the emissions of
pollutants can be reduced to a satisfactorily
low level.
The only lasting solution is to reduce the
emissions of the pollutants in the first place.
Apart from the effect that strict controls
would have in protecting water and forests,
they could save millions of dollars by
avoiding corrosion. The Organization for
Economic Co-operation and Development
(OECD) made a first attempt in 1981 to find
a way of quantifying corrosion costs. This
came up with the estimate that strict emis¬
sion control measures in 13 European coun¬
tries could save about $1.2 billion in corro¬
sion costs every year.
The easiest way to control the pollution is
to use fuels that are low in sulphur; but this
will not be feasible for long because the
world supply of these fuels is believed to be
limited. A more permanent solution is to
use other sources of energy instead of fossil
fuels, and to improve energy conservation.
According to some recent estimates, in¬
cluding those submitted to the 1982
Stockholm Acidification Conference, tak¬
ing sulphur out of fuel oils would cost about
$20 to $40 for every ton of oil, depending
mainly on the type of the oil and the size of
the plant, among other factors. This would
add about $5-10 to the cost of every
megawatt/hour of energy produced (in
1980 prices), adding about 10 to 20 per cent
to the cost of electricity production. In¬
dustry, on the other hand, puts the costs at
$40 to $85 for every ton of oil.
Coal contains two kinds of sulphur
pyrite (iron sulphide) and organic sulphur.
Washing coal, after first crushing and
grinding it, will remove pyrite sulphur. The
cost of this mechanical process is estimated
to be $1 to $6 per ton of coal. On average
it will remove about half of the pyrite,
though at best the process can be made to
remove up to 90 per cent of it from some
coals. The chemical methods are more ef¬
fective, but also more expensive and have
not yet been fully developed. They can
remove organic sulphur as well as pyrite.
The cost of getting rid of 90 to 95 per cent
of the pyrite and half the organic sulphur
would be around $20 to $30 per ton of coal.
The extra costs for coal washing range from
less than $1 to about $3 per
megawatt/hour, adding between one and
six per cent to electricity costs. Chemical
desulphurization would cost much more,
about $8 to $12 per megawatt/hour, and
this would add between 15 and 25 per cent
to electricity costs.
Nitrogen oxide emissions can be reduced
by changing the ways of burning fuel, par¬
ticularly in heat and power stations. One of
the methods proposed for doing this is to
reduce the combustion temperature to
below about 1500°C and/or to allow only
low intakes of air. Such changes could cut
in half the amount of nitrogen oxides
emitted.
Removing sulphur from fuel and gases
creates waste products solids and
slurrieswhich have to be disposed of pro¬
perly to avoid water, groundwater, or soil
pollution. Naturally, this problem grows as
emission controls are increased.
According to preliminary calculations by
OECD, it costs a total of some $800, on
average, to stop a ton of sulphur from get¬
ting into the air. More recent estimates sug¬
gest that the costs may be somewhat higher.
If northwestern and southern European
countries were to cut their annual sulphur
emissions by about half (around 5.9 million
tons) within the next 10 to 25 years by con¬
trolling the emissions of conventional
power stations, it would cost them about 10
per cent of the total cost of producing their
electricity.
There are, moreover, other factors that
complicate such analyses. Onecommon
to many other instances of damage to
shared natural resourcesis that the coun¬
tries which would benefit from the reduced
pollution would often be different from
those that would have to bear the cost of
cutting it back. Another is that all the
estimates of benefits assume that the
damage caused by acid rain can readily be
reversed if enough pollution control is
implemented and in reality this may not
be so. It might be a long time before the
ecological damage, in particular, began to
be reversed. Unfortunately, scientific infor¬
mation on the recovery process is extremely
scanty.
This is only one of the problem areas in
the whole field which, despite considerable
progress in research on the subject, still re¬
main unknown or only superficially
understood. Research is needed on dry
deposition of polluting gases and particles,
and their effects on water, soil, young and
old foliage, and other recipients of their
pollution; on how the pollutants undergo
changes in the atmosphere, and how they
are transported and deposited; on how
bedrocks weather under different acid in¬
puts and release nutrients; on how acid af¬
fects the soil, particularly in the long term;
and on the possible adverse effects of acid
fall-out on forest growth.
In addition to these meteorologically and
ecologically orientated research topics, in¬
formation is needed on the effects on health
of the increasing spread of cadmium and
other toxic metals as a result of acidifica¬
tion. Among other things, the levels of the
metals in food, human tissues and body
fluids must continue to be monitored.
Some areas in the tropics may be highly
or moderately susceptible to acidification,
and this could cause special problems. We
need to work out the nature of these
problems. In dry tropical areas, acid rain
itself cannot play a major role owing to
scarce precipitation, but the role of dry
deposition is unknown. In humid areas the
ecosystems, temperature and moisture
levels are different from those in the
temperate areas where acidification has
been studied so far, and quite different
problems may arise.
Besides, some soils have too little sulphur
in them or are highly alkaline. These could
benefit, to a certain extent, from extra
sulphur and nitrogen fall-out or merely
from more acidic rain. This could add a
significant new factor to calculations of
costs and benefits from the pollution, but
the issue has not yet been explored.
This article is based on a longer study publish¬
ed in the UN CHRONICLE, Volume XX, No. 5,
and entitled State of the World Environment
1 983, A Report from UNEP.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Cities
athirst
TODAY'S metropolitan giants sprawl
across wide areas and have an
impact on the environment far
from their city cores. London, Paris, Mex¬
ico City, Amsterdam, Los Angeles, and
many others have pushed out into fertile
farmland and, in so doing, have
transformed it into endless blocks of
masonry. They have stretched their ten¬
tacles of iron and concrete pipe many
kilometres out into the countryside to cap¬
ture the contents of remote streams and
lakes. They have denuded much of the
vegetation within their own city boun¬
daries, replacing the verdure of grass,
shrubs, and trees with asphalt, concrete,
and impervious rooftops.
All these actions have affected the ur¬
ban environment and the water supplies
upon which the city dwellers depend.
Numerous events take place during the
transformation of an uninhabited piece of
ground into a city complete with streets,
squares, subway tunnels, monuments,
and the rest of the paraphernalia of
civilization. Three overlapping stages in a
city's growth have an impact on the water
supply.
The first stage involves the removal of
trees and other vegetation to make room
for the initial homes, stores, and streets.
This removal affects the local area's water
budget by reducing the transpiration once
"lost" from the vegetation.
The digging of wells to supply the city-
dwellers also usually takes place during
the first stage. This also affects the local
water budget as the wells will usually
lower the water table.
Watercourses in the budding metro¬
polis will also be affected by sedimenta¬
tion. The construction of homes and com¬
mercial buildings as well as excavations
for water pipes can loosen the soil to a
point where it can be easily eroded into
the streams.
Construction of septic tanks is yet
another activity which usually takes place
in the early stages of a city's growth. If not
properly constructed and located, they
ê Water supply is one of the most urgent
| and intractable problems facing Mexico
5 C/fy (population 17 million), which is
® among the world's fastestgrowing conur-
§ bâtions. Local water sources are Inade-
^ quale and the city is being obliged to
% reach out further and further (between
a 150 and 200 km) and lower and lower
w (1,000 metres below the level of the city)
| for its water. Left, aerial view of Netza-
é hualcoyotl, a district of Mexico City.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
may pollute areas of the aquifer. Without
a sewage collection system, cesspools
and other effluent sources generally drain
into groundwater horizons, and this has
caused outbreaks of cholera and typhoid.
During the next stage of urbanization,
excavations are made for bigger houses
and buildings, more topsoil is removed,
and small pools of water are filled up. Ac¬
celerated soil erosion and sedimentation
in the watercourses result.
As the city expands there will be an in¬
crease in impermeable surfaces. Reduc¬
ed infiltration into the groundwater will be
a consequence. Because of the increased
impermeability, peak flows will be increas¬
ed in the remaining watercourses. Some
flooding may occur.
The most dangerous situation for
human healthwhich usually occurs dur¬
ing this second stageis the discharge of
chemicals or insufficiently treated waste
water into the area's streams. This
pollutes the receiving streams and often
also leads to the killing of aquatic life.
Waterbased recreation will be affected.
The degradation of the streams' quality
will also affect those human communities
located downstream.
The final stage of urbanization is mark¬
ed by nearly all of the original open soil be¬
ing covered with buildings, streets and
other near-impermeable surfaces. Infiltra¬
tion to the groundwater is markedly reduc¬
ed, and storm runoff is increased and
accelerated.
With less water reaching the aquifer,
wells may have to be deepened to meet
the needs of a larger population. Or the
municipality may have to reach beyond its
own area to tap regional water sources. It
has been observed that certain basic
elements of water-supply technology-
capture in distant catchment areas, con¬
duction along aqueducts and distribution
within citiesare as characteristic of re¬
cent works as they are of late nineteenth-
century projects and indeed of Roman
systems. In this respect modern engineer¬
ing seems to have changed no basic prin¬
ciple, although it has come to have a bet¬
ter grasp of the problems involved.
And yet the U.S. Environmental Protec¬
tion Agency has identified a number of
major sources of pollution to the ground¬
water in the United States. Most are
related to urbanization. They include
underground injection wells used to
"dispose" of hazardous wastes; acciden¬
tal spills of these materials on city streets,
industrial sites, railroad rights-of-way, and
airports; leaks from pipelines and storage
tanks; abandoned domestic water wells;
overuse of agricultural chemicals; unlined
slurry ponds, and salt water encroach¬
ment into aquifers.
Roman engineers ofAntiquitybuilt highly
developed water supply systems. The
Pont du Gard (c. 19 BC) In southern
France, below, Is only a small section of
a 40-kllometre-long conduit, mostly
underground, which carried water to the
city of Nimes. Its 3 tiers of arches rise to
over47 metres. The highest tier, carrying
the conduit, consists of 35 4.6-metre
arches.
Pumping deeper and deeper for more
and more water can also lead to land sub¬
sidence. In the United States, the boom
metropolis of Houston, on the Texas
coast, has an acute subsidence problem.
So much water has been withdrawn that
the land within a 64-kilometre radius of the
city centre has dropped almost three
metres below its original elevation. It has
been pointed out, somewhat tongue-in-
cheek, that should this subsidence con¬
tinue at the existing rate, the top of a
downtown landmark, a 45-storey building,
will be below sea level by the year 2180!
Mexico City, situated at more than
2,134 metres above the sea, is obviously
not going to suffer a similar fate. But this
major metropolis has sunk some 10.7
metres during the past 70 years into the
filled-in lake bed on which it has been
built. The cause? Withdrawal of water
from the aquifer below.
Mexican authorities have been at¬
tempting to meet the ballooning demand
for water by planning to tap rivers more
than 1 60 kilometres away from the capital.
It has been suggested that by the year
2000, Mexico City's population may sur¬
pass 30 million, and therefore have the
world's greatest urban concentration. It is
interesting to note in that respect that
from 1 960 to 1 976, the water supply to the
city was more than doubled, but the
amount available per person declined. In
1982, only 15 per cent of the residents in
urban areas around Mexico City had
piped water for their homes. '
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Washing our dirty water
TODAY there is world-wide agree¬
ment, at least in principle, about
the need to reduce pollution so
that mankind can survive. It is now con¬
sidered necessary to treat all effluents
before they are discharged into water
bodies.
The following are the principal
substances and types of pollution which
the treatment processes are designed to
remove:
Suspended solids, such as silt (which
produce turbidity and form sludge
deposits).
Material that consumes oxygen.
Nutrients necessary for the creation of
new organisms.
Extremely important nutrients are the
phosphates and nitrates. In waste water,
phosphorus and nitrogen are mainly the
result of the domestic use of water. They
are also becoming a major problem as a
result of the excessive fertilization of
farmlands.
The role of phosphorus in waste water
pollution has been debated since it was
first recognized that synthetic washing
detergents (when first introduced) con¬
tained large amounts of this substance
which soon found its way into nearby sur¬
face waters.
Manufacturers have drastically reduc¬
ed the phosphorus content. But treatment
plants are still faced with large amounts of
phosphorus and nitrogen contained in the
waste water arriving at the plants.
The waste water from municipalities
also contains pathogenic bacteria,
viruses, and chemicals. Mercury, lead,
copper, zinc, and chromium (the so-called
"heavy metals") are waste products of
some industries.
Such substances can dramatically af¬
fect the health of many organisms which
inhabit streams and lakes. Certain ef¬
fluents also can change the pH (acidity) of
the water. The pH is an indication of the
acidic/basic nature of the liquid, running
from 0 to 14. Seven is neutral; the lower
the value the more acidic the liquid. Fish
regarded as desirable game species
(such as trout) need a pH of more than five
in order to survive. Too high a pH on the ,
other hand may be dangerous for fish.
The paper and pulp industry is mainly
responsible for effluents that cause low
pH values. Tanneries and textile mills
At this purification plant in Louisiana,
USA, industrial waste water is literally
being "washed". Highly oxygenated
water is pumped into the waste water
through hundreds of jets. The oxygen in
this water (it shows up white in the photo)
breaks down the organic matter In the
waste water which is then returned to the
Mississippi River.
discharge waste water with high pH
values.
Two other groups of pollutants which
can have major biological impacts are the
pesticides and the hydrocarbons which
escape from refineries, automobile ser¬
vice stations, garages, and streets.
The following four steps are used in
waste water treatment processes:
sludge separation
biological treatment
chemical treatment
complementary treatment,
filtering.
such as
The handling of waste water at a
sewage plant always begins with a pre-
treatment process that removes those
materials that float, are large in size, or
heavy. Sand and gravel also are removed
during this initial stage.
Following this initial screening process
the remaining materials move to a basin
where the velocity of the waste water flow
míimm*ñ4t
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
is purposely kept low. As a result, solid
material will then sink to the bottom where
it is removed by scrapers. This stage of
the process may take up to three hours.
This phase of the process can be per¬
formed in two ways. In the first method,
the aerated sludge process, the water
enters a basin where it is aerated,
together with a biological floe. The
bacteria in the floe metabolize the waste
solids. The air is introduced by air diffu¬
sion or a turbine aeration system, causing
the water to be set in motion. Floes of
sludge are formed and grow in size. After
one to three hours in the aeration basin
the suspension moves on to a sedimenta¬
tion basin where the sludge is allowed to
settle, and is recycled or removed.
The second method uses a biologically
active bed made up of layers of material,
often of coarse stones. Microorganisms in
a gel adhering to the stones remove and
decompose the organic material and
periodically slough off. As with the
previous process, the partially treated
sewage is then passed on to a sedimenta¬
tion basin where settling of the sludge
occurs.
The next step, when used, is chemical
in nature. Aluminium sulphate and iron
compounds are added to facilitate the
creation of floe. The phosphorus in the
sewage water is removed at this stage. As
a final step, filtering may be carried out to
remove the floes still present.
A troublesome by-product from waste
water treatment is the sludge. In earlier
days, the sludge would be dumped into
the sea in those countries located along
an ocean coast. That option now is not ac¬
ceptable because of the known harmful
effects on marine life.
Sludge can be treated in digestion
chambers where an oxygen-free condi¬
tion transforms the organic material to
more stable non-organic compounds.
This procedure takes about three weeks.
However, the digested sludge still must
be processed, because it contains con¬
siderable water, which may be removed
by the use of drying beds or by heating.
The latter method requires considerable
energy.
After the sludge has been dewatered.
There are several options for the final
disposal of the material:
It can be removed to a sanitary landfill.
There a new problem can be
encounteredleakage from the landfill. If
not properly constructed, precipitation
may percolate through the sludge to the
groundwater.
The sludge can be composted with
domestic solid waste products.
The sludge can be incinerated. Unfor¬
tunately, this process may transform
water pollution into air pollution. The ash,
which remains after the incineration, also
may contain hazardous heavy metals
which could be taken up by living
organisms.
The sludge can be used as a soil im¬
provement substance similar to cattle
manure. Still remaining, however, is the
problem of the heavy metals. In many
This sewage treatment plant at Lubbock,
Texas, uses a 1 ,200-hectare-farm as its
tertiary disposal facility. The nutrients
that are normally absorbed during this
stage of the treatment process are
applied to the land as fertilizer.
countries rotted sludge cannot legally be
used in vegetable gardens for fear that the
heavy metals will find their way into food
products.
It should be apparent that there are
serious difficulties in getting rid of the
harmful substances that man introduces
into the hydrological cycle. We are often
left withif not exactly those pollutants
which we originally added to the
systemsome degenerated pollutants
which can still be biologically hazardous.
The crucial point is that man continuously
adds pollutants to the hydrological cycle.
In the treatment plants these pollutants
are mostly transformed into solid wastes.
Something must then be done with the
solids. If contaminants in these materials
are allowed to reach the surface or
groundwater the pollution cycle is closed.
What happens then? Do we have any
alternatives? Unfortunately, not many.
We need new industrial processes that do
not cause water pollution, and we also
need improved recycling processes to
prevent polluted water from being
discharged into streams and lakes. It
needs stressing that all components of an
urban area's water environment must be
satisfactorily handled as a total system.
An adequate and potable supply must be
secured, the waste water must be effec¬
tively treated, and the leftover products
such as sludge must be safely disposed
of. A breakdown in any of these com¬
ponents of the system will place the entire
process and the city in a hazardous
position.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The waterlords
of ancient Sri Lanka
<L
ET not a single drop of rain that
falls on this island flow into the
ocean without first serving
humanity." This was the governing prin¬
ciple of a massive water resources develop¬
ment programme undertaken by one of the
greatest kings of ancient Sri Lanka,
Parakramabahu I (1153-1186). The king's
record was impressive. The Sri Lankan
Chronicle, the Culavamsa which was writ¬
ten in the Buddhist canonical language Pali,
enumerates his works both as a provincial
ruler in western Sri Lanka and later as the
monarch of the whole country: he either
built or restored 163 major reservoirs (call¬
ed "tanks" in Sri Lankan usage), 2,617
minor tanks, 3,910 irrigation channels, 328
stone sluices and 168 sluice blocks, besides
repairing 1,969 breaches in embankments.
Among the reservoirs he built was the tank
at Polonnaruwa, called on account of its
size the Sea of Parakrama. With an area of
3,000' hectares and an enclosing embank¬
ment fourteen kilometres long, it irrigated
nearly 10,000 hectares.
The resulting improvement in the conser¬
vation and distribution of water brought
about an expansion of cultivated land.
Consequently, during his reign the produc¬
tion of rice increased to the point that Sri
Lanka exported so much of it to neighbour¬
ing countries that the country is said to have
become known as the granary of the east.
. In executing this vast programe,
Parakramabahu I was fulfilling one of the
most important royal duties laid down by
tradition. The obligations of kings were
conceived as serving the two-fold interests
of the nation: the material and the spiritual,
expressed in Pali as loka-sasana-
abhivuddhi. Under the first category came
the two fundamental duties of defending
The great artificial lake of Anuradhapura
in the north of Sri Lanka, with a monu¬
mental stupa, Ruvanvalisaya, in the back¬
ground. The kingdom of Anuradhapura
(2nd century BC-10th century AD) cre¬
ated a remarkable Irrigation system
which was the basis of its prosperity.
the nation against external and internal
threats to its security, and the conservation
and management of water resources to pro¬
mote rice cultivation. Included in the se¬
cond category of duties was the sustenance
of Buddhism through the promotion of
monastic institutions and the construction
of impressive edifices. Every Sinhala
monarch who is rated great in history has
excelled in all or at least two of these three
functions.
King Mahasena, who constructed the
Minneriya tank in the fourth century, was
actually deified by the people, and in a tem¬
ple on the lake bund he still receives homage
from local cultivators who seek his help in
growing successful crops. When the fifth-
century king Dhatusena was asked by his
rebellious son Kahsyapa to reveal where the
royal treasures were hidden, he led his cap¬
tors to Kalaweva, a lake with a circum¬
ference of ninety kilometres which he had
constructed. Taking a handful of water, he
said, "This, my friends, is the whole of my
wealth."
These constructions involved a very high
level of technological knowledge and skill.
Perennial rivers were dammed with stone
barrages and diverted kilometres away
from their courses. Seasonal streams were
dammed in stages to form a series of reser¬
voirs along the valleys. The earthen em¬
bankments of these reservoirs extended
from a few hundred metres to fifteen
kilometres and in some places were eighteen
metres high. The Jaya-Ganga, an irrigation
channel aptly called the Victory River, was
a masterpiece of engineering ingenuity. Still
functioning today, it is over eight
kilometres long with a uniform width of
twelve metres. To minimize silting and ero¬
sion of banks, its gradient for the first thirty
kilometres is an imperceptible 1 in 10,000.
It connects two river systems and maintains
adequate water supplies in a series of inter¬
linked tanks which irrigated over 46,000
hectares of rice-fields.
Though little is known of either their
techniques or the tools they used, the skills
of the ancient Sinhala engineers in
hydrodynamics as well as surveying and
levelling were of a very high order. The
stone sluice gate with its control well, called
in Sinhala the Biso-kotuva, was a
remarkably effective apparatus which
displays a full understanding of water
under pressure. It regulated the speed and
the quantity of water issued to the fields and
thus protected both the channel and the
fields from erosion and flooding. It also
prevented a reservoir from being tapped to
its last drop by eager cultivators in times of
drought, to the detriment of the survival of
man and beast. Similarly, a stone spill or
flood escape was constructed to a required
height, often some kilometres away from
the sluice gate, to safeguard the em¬
bankments from the heavy pressure of sud-
dent rain or flood water.
Many a modern engineer has been baffl¬
ed by the sophisticated designs on which
these reservoirs and channel systems were
constructed. It is known that the Dutch
engineers of the eighteenth century and
their British counterparts in the nineteenth
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
failed to understand the design of the giant
tank near Mannar on the northwestern
coast. Only in recent years, when the tank
was restored in conformity with the original
design, was it found that levelling by the
unknown engineer of the past was vastly
superior to that attempted by modern
engineers.
The origin and early development of a Sri
Lankan science of water resources are not
easy to trace. The earliest recorded instance
of the construction of a reservoir dates to
the founding of the Sinhala kingdom in the
sixth century BC. But whatever the source
of their technological knowledge, the
Sinhalas won wide recognition for their
skills in irrigation. Pliny's account of the
Sri Lankan embassy to Rome in 45 AD to
the court of the Emperor Claudius refers to
the artificial lake near the capital,
Anuradhapura. Though couched in
mythological terms, the reference in the
Kashmirian history Rajatarangani to
Lankan experts who helped Jayapida to
drain a lake sometime around the eighth
century records a possible case of technical
assistance.
A complex system of rules and regula¬
tions on the management of water has been
operating in Sri Lanka since ancient times.
Not only did it prescribe how water was to
be distributed and used, it also assigned
responsibilities for the upkeep of tanks and
channels. Until driven to obsolescence by
the advent of the monetary economy in re¬
cent times, these regulations were upheld
through a process of co-operative self-help,
and the tradition persists in remote villages.
The royal duty to develop water
resources and thus provide life blood to
rural Sri Lanka and its multi-faceted
culture has been carried on by the Govern¬
ment of the country ever since political
power was vested in national leaders in the
1930s. In a massive effort to regenerate the
rural settlements of the Dry Zone in the
north central and southeastern regions of
the island, over 3,000 reservoirs of varying
sizes together with their channel systems
have been commissioned into service and
vast stretches of new rice-fields have been
brought under cultivation.
The Senanayaka-Samudraya (the Sea of
Senanayake, so named in commemoration
of the first Prime Minister of independent
Sri Lanka, who was an indomitable pioneer
in restoring ancient water resources and
establishing new villages) vies with the Sea
of Parakramabahu of 800 years ago. The
most impressive effort in this direction is
the current programme to divert Mahaveli-
ganga, the island's longest river. This multi¬
purpose project which, besides producing
electricity and controlling floods, will bring
thousands of hectares under cultivation,
symbolizes the persistent belief of Sri
Lankans that the glory of their nation lies in
the village with its lake, rice-fields and
temple.
Irrigation
ANANDA GURUGE is chief of Unesco's unit
for co-operation with UNICEF and the World
Food Programme. He is a specialist in Asian
and Buddhist cultures on which he has written
several books.
NEARLY one eighth (230 million
hectares) of all the world's agri¬
cultural land is under irrigation.
An additional 50 million hectares are ex¬
pected to be added to this total by 1990.
The Benefits
Increased food production. Over the
past twenty years the productivity of
agricultural land has been increasing on
average by two per cent a year. Some six¬
ty per cent of this increased agricultural
output has come from newly irrigated
areas.
Increased income for the small farmer
Irrigation can double or treble the number
of crops that can be grown in a single
year. This means that, with irrigation, a
once inadequate plot of land can provide
a reasonable living for a peasant farmer
and his family.
More land can be brought under cultiva¬
tion. Thanks to irrigation, wheat and
maize now grow in parts of northern Mex¬
ico and rice grows in the Kuban Valley in
the USSR on land that was previously
uncultivated.
The Dangers
Water-borne diseases. Badly planned ir¬
rigation schemes can increase the in¬
cidence of water-borne diseases such as
schistosomiasis, malaria and river blind¬
ness (see box page 32).
Salinization and waterlogging. When
poorly drained land is irrigated in hot
climates, the sun evaporates the surface
water leaving behind an accumulation of
alkaline salts near the surface in which
crops cannot grow. In addition, inade¬
quate drainage eventually causes the
water table to rise and the land becomes
waterlogged. In the mid-1970s the Food
and Agriculture Organization of the
United Nations estimated that 952 million
hectares of land were affected by
salinization.
Effects ofsalinization (salt buitd-up in the
soil) due to poor drainage and water¬
logging, in India (above) and the United
States (below).
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Villagers search for snails along a drain¬
age ditch at Dongfeng, near Shanghai.
Since the early 1970s, such ditches have
been dug deeper to prevent the fields
from becoming waterlogged, a situation
in which the disease-bearing snails
flourish.
The deadly snails ofDongfeng
How a Chinese community vanquished
schistosomiasis
DURING the last decade living condi¬
tions have changed dramatically
for the 400 families of Dongfeng,
near Wuxi city in South China.
In Dongfeng (literally, East Wind), as in
all the rural areas of Wuxi county, the
village roads have been paved and the old,
single-storey brick houses are being replac¬
ed by two and three-storey houses with tiled
roofs. As family incomes rise, the villagers
are acquiring a range of consumer goods:
hi-fis, television, washing machines and
cameras.
The other significant change is not so
easily apparent to a visitor. There are no
snails in Dongfeng now. And since 1972
there has not been a single new case of snail
fever, a debilitating disease which has af¬
flicted China since the time of the Hans,
2,000 years ago.
Medically called schistosomiasis (or
bilharzia), its symptoms include fever, liver
pains, blisters on the skin, and blood in the
by Zhang Bihua
faeces and urine. It is caused by the
schistosome, a parasitic worm, which
spendspart of its complex life cycle in fresh
water, part inside a particular species of
snail and part in the human body (see
diagram). People pick up the disease by
wading or bathing in an infected canal, lake
or pond.
The Wuxi area is criss-crossed by rivers
and canals, and it is bordered on the south
by Lake Tai, one of China's biggest lakes.
The city gets its water from the Grand
Canal which carries water from the Yangtze
River to Lake Tai, branching on its way into
the villages built on its banks. The fertile
soil, moderate climate, and the abundance
of water has made this a very productive
and prosperous area: a "Land of Fish and
Rice".
However, the water is a mixed blessing,
for it has also brought the schistosome,
snails and disease. Early post-Liberation
(1949) statistics show that snail fever af¬
fected 100 million people in 11 provinces
(including Jiangsu where Dongfeng is)
south of, and along, the Yangtze River.
The Dongfeng brigade is part of the
Luyuan commune in the suburbs north of
Wuxi city. Here the Grand Canal flows
through five branches of the Liangqi River
into a spider's web of waterwaysthe very
best environment for the schistosome and
its host, the snail.
Though Dongfeng was not as badly af¬
fected as many other areas, its people were
exposed to the "swollen belly disease"
every time they collected water from the
Liangqi the only source for drinking and
all other domestic purposes. The brigade
had two old community wells, but there
were no household wells.
Children sometimes used to defecate in
the fields, and the adults used bucket
latrines which were also emptied out in the
fields. The buckets were washed in the same
river from which they got their water, and
this helped spread the schistosome eggs.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
But the peasants of Dongfeng had no
idea why their stomachs swelled or how
they caught "the disease of laziness", as
they called it. They knew it made them
feeble and unable to work. If the pain were
too great they would pierce their abdomens
to release the accumulated fluid.
It took Dongfeng more than 20 years to
get the better of the scourge that its waters
brought. How was it done? First came the
national programme to eradicate snail
fever, emphasizing preventive measures
such as destroying the snails and their
habitat, and strictly controlling water usage
and nightsoil disposal. A special group was
set up at every level, from the central Health
Ministry at Beijing, down through county
and province to the brigade.
The campaign to rid Dongfeng brigade of
snails began, as part of this national pro¬
gramme, in the 1950s, but it took many
years to get fully organized.
The brigade collectively owns all the land
and all the otherresources, and also con¬
trols all the finances. A percentage of its
total annual income is accumulated in a
community welfare fund, which supports
co-operative medical care. Money for the
anti-snail campaign came from this fund.
It was only in 1972 that the Dongfeng
campaign gathered momentum when a
four-member anti-schistosome group was
formed to lead the work. All four were
recognized local leaders the Communist
Party secretary, two heads of the brigade
production teams, and a "barefoot" doc¬
tor. (The barefoot doctor, crucial to
China's rural medical system, is not a
medical graduate but a middle school-
educated peasant).
In 1972, 27-year-old Su Guiying was the
brigade's barefoot doctor working on the
campaign. As a child Su had seen people in
her village suffer from schistosomiasis. "I
vowed that one day I would become a doc¬
tor and relieve their pain", she says. In the
1960s she trained as a barefoot doctor and
devoted herself completely to helping snail
fever patients.
To qualify as a barefoot doctor Su had to
take a four-month training course in Wuxi
city, which included elementary phar¬
macology, the diagnosis and treatment of
common illnesses such as influenza and
diarrhoea, and midwifery. For the anti-
snail campaign she had to take a brief addi¬
tional course on the disease, learn about the
ecology of the snail and the basics of testing
stools.
The Party secretary and the two brigade
heads in the anti-snail group were also
trained on the non-medical aspects. The en¬
tire group watched films about the disease,
examined the larvae and the eggs of the
worm, and even dissected an infected rabbit
to see how the victims suffered. All this
knowledge had to be disseminated to the
people of Dongfeng.
Lu Guomin, a doctor at the Wuxi city
centre, says they soon found it was more ef¬
ficient for peasants to spread the informa¬
tion among themselves than for profes¬
sionals to carry the message from village to
village.
But this required a tremendous publicity
effort. Posters and slogans were hung on
walls, blackboards were used to carry
cartoons and short articles on snail fever.
And during work breaks in the fields,
loudspeakers constantly broadcast basic in¬
formation about the disease. In the even¬
ings, amateur actors performed skits and
sang ballads to get the message home.
Mass participation was vital to the cam¬
paign. Su says propaganda is essential to
pave the way for such mass participation,
but believes that patience is the key.
All the hard work paid off. In the early
1970s at least one person in each of the
brigade's then 300 households was affected.
But in 1975, three years after the campaign
got properly organized, there were only 18
remaining cases.
The improved health conditions were the
result of three major activities of the cam¬
paign. These were:
the elimination of snails;
building new channels for irrigation,
drainage and transport;
Waterborne Diseases
THE World Health Organization has estimated that 80 per
cent of all sickness and disease in the world is attributable
to inadequate water or sanitation. This includes the effects
of drinking contaminated water, water acting as a breeding
ground for carriers of disease, and disease caused by lack of
washing.
Five types of disease are related to water and sanitation:
Waterborne diseases spread by drinking (or washing food,
utensils, hands or face in) contaminated water. They include
typhoid, cholera, dysentery, gastro-enteritis (diarrhoea) and,
where pollution is exceptionally severe, infective hepatitis.
Water-washed infections of the skin and eyes spread by inade¬
quate water for personal washing. They include trachoma,
scabies, yaws, leprosy, conjunctivitis, skin sepsis and ulcers.
Water-based diseases, so called because the vector (carrier) is
an invertebrate aquatic organism. The most important are
schistosomiasis and the guinea worm.
Diseases with water-related insect vectors. Mosquitoes (car¬
riers of malaria, filariasis, yellow fever) and blackflies (carriers of
river blindness) need water for breeding. Certain tse-tse fly vec¬
tors of sleeping sickness usually bite near water.
Infections primarily caused because of defective sanitation,
such as hookworm.
DIARRHOEA directly kills 6 million children in developing
countries each year, and contributes to the death of up to 18
million people. Victims often die of dehydration. Survivors are
weakened and easy prey to other diseases. In unsanitary condi¬
tions the disease easily passes from child to child. The cure is
rehydration, the replacement of lost fluid and salts by weak sugar
and salt solution taken either orally or by intravenous drip.
TRACHOMA is a virus infection of the outer parts of the eye,
eventually causing build-up of scar tissue over the eye and blind¬
ness if untreated. Spread by flies and touch. 500 million people
infected world-wide.
SCHISTOSOMIASIS (bilharzia, or snail fever) is caused by a
parasite spread by freshwater snails (see article). It is today a
cause of misery and debility for 200 million people in Africa, the
Middle East, parts of Latin America and southeast Asia. Infec¬
tious schistosome larvae penetrate the skin when a person
swims or wades in water. The larvae migrate to the blood stream
where they become adult worms. Eggs leave the body via faeces
or urine. Symptoms include fever, painful liver, blisters on skin
and blood in faeces and urine. Ironically schistosomiasis has
spread dramatically because of the spread of irrigation canals
and dams which provide a suitable habitat for the snails and their
parasite.
RIVER BLINDNESS (onchocerciasis) is caused by minute
worms carried from person to person when bitten by small black
flies that breed in fast flowing water. Worms spread inside body
often to eyes where damage and scarring eventually cause blind¬
ness. An estimated 30 million people are affected.
MALARIA, common in many of the hot, tropical parts of the
world, is carried from person to person by carrier mosquitoes.
Almost any amount of water is sufficient for the mosquitoes to lay
their eggs. Each year it is estimated that 800 million people suffer
from the fevers of malaria.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Above, photo taken with an electron
scanning microscope of the parasitic
worm that causes schistosomiasis or bil¬
harzia. Right, the anopheline mosquito
which transmits malaria.
The life cycle of the schistosome, the
parasitic worm which causes schistoso¬
miasis, also known as "swollen belly
disease" or snail fever.
s".
So
Q>
1. Fluke escapes from snail
2. Enters water
3. Fluke penetrates human skin
4. Young flukes mature in blood vessels
of lungs
5. Adults reach the small intestine
6. Eggs are laid and move through tissue
to intestinethey are passed out with
waste
7. Mature egg when passed reaches
water and hatches almost Immediately
8. Larva seeks out an appropriate snail
o
X :
5
©
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
changing methods of water supply and
nightsoil disposal.
In each of the three activities, there was
a combination of government support,
community action and motivation from
local leaders.
Some work had been done to destroy
snails in Dongfeng during the early years of
China's anti-snail campaign during the
1950s and the 1960s. Like many other local
leaders, Yang Zoji, an agricultural tech¬
nician, had also suffered from snail fever.
He says that in the early days of the cam¬
paign they used boats to search the river
banks for snails. The snails were Caught and
killed by immersing them in boiling water
on a stove on the boat. This was a slow and
laborious process because of the number of
small rivers.
The snails could have been poisoned with
chemicals but these were too expensive.
Yang calculates that a tonne of imported
chemicals cost the equivalent of four tonnes
of rice.
By the early 1970s, the methods changed.
An "army" of sharp-eyed village children,
armed only with a pamphlet picturing dif¬
ferent kinds of snails, searched the irriga¬
tion channels and the drainage ditches for
the particular snail species which causes
schistosomiasis.
Within two months, the people of
Dongfeng dug new ditches and used the
fresh earth to fill the old ones (totalling 18
kilometres), effectively killing the snails by
burying them. "No sophisticated technique
was required and it didn't cost us anything
except for our muscle-power, as we fought
with our own spades and rakes", Yang
remarks.
The new channels and ditches, which
were straighter and deeper than the old
ones, were necessary to prevent the fields
from getting waterlogged (a favourable en¬
vironment for the snail). But this involved
changing the contours of the fields. Many
in the brigade were initially opposed to this:
they thought it would just be a waste of
labour.
Yang recalls that an old man complained
that a new ditch, which ran alongside the
graves of his ancestors, affected the direc¬
tion of the wind and altered the flow of the
water. He believed this had brought bad
luck to the family and made his grandson
Two Thai villagers slake their thirst with
water from a tap Installed by UNICEF (the
United Nations Children's Fund).
ill. Su treated and cured the child and that
helped people accept the changes.
Dongfeng also used the east-west branch
of the river to transport goods to Wuxi city.
Wang suggested constructing a new north-
south channel which would halve the travel
time of three and a half hours, and help
clear the river of snails. The residents of
Dongfeng contributed their labour, work¬
ing often by gaslight at night.
The campaign's third area of activity,
water supply and sanitation, was perhaps
the most difficult. The peasants had always
used the contaminated river water for
drinking. A strict ban was imposed on
washing the latrine buckets in the river and
on collecting drinking water from it. The
brigade dug several public wells, and each
household was also asked to dig its own
shallow well.
It took a couple two days to dig a well
three metres deep and line it with bricks.
They needed 300 bricks and 50 kilograms of
cement and sand, and the brigade supplied
half of this.
Lu Wenying, the health worker,
distributes chemicals to each household to
purify the water. A plastic tube with two
holes is filled with solid bleach (sodium
hypochlorite), and is lowered into the
water. This lets in the water slowly and
releases chlorine, a much safer method of
purification than immersing the chemical
powder directly in the water as used to be
done.
A special three-chambered pit was in¬
troduced for disposing of nightsoil. The
faeces are fermented in the first chamber
for 15 days, during which time 90 per cent
of the schistosome eggs settle at the bottom
of the chamber. The fermented mixture
then flows into the second chamber, and the
process is repeated. When this chamber too
is filled the mixture flows into the last
chamber, from which it is removed. The
final product is good quality fertilizer, high
in nitrogen content and without any
schistosome eggs. .
Snail fever has now been eliminated in
Dongfeng. But preventive measures con¬
tinue. Snail searches are made in the spring
and autumn, when snails are active. A
reward of 20 yuan (US$40) has now been in¬
troduced for reporting a snail. (When the
work was at its peak, however, no monetary
incentives were given).
Better water supply and nightsoil
disposal have also helped to improve the
health of the people. Better irrigation has
increased the production of vegetables and
other crops. Individual incomes have risen.
Joint community effort and government
support has helped Dongfeng eradicate the
bloodsucking worm. Lu Wenying sums up
the success of the Dongfeng campaign with
an old Chinese saying: "Two chopsticks are
easily broken but not a bundle".
ZHANG BIHUA, of China, is a journalist
working at China Features, Beijing.
This article is based on a longer study first
published in Who Puts the Water in the Taps,
a paperback book published by Earthscan,
London.
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices:
Unesco, 7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 68 French francs. 2 years (valid only in
France): 1 20 French francs. Binder for a year's issues:
52 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering pos¬
tage. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions and
headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boun¬
daries on maps published in the magazine do not imply offi¬
cial endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the United
Nations.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm and/or
microfiche) by: (1) Unesco. 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris ;
I2) University Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100,
U.S.A.: (3) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian Head, Inc.. 1 1 1
West 40th Street, New York, U.S.A.; (4) Bell and Howell Co.,
Old Mansfield Road. Wooster, Ohio 44691 , U.S.A.
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
French: Alain Lévêque (Paris)
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov (Paris)
Arabic: Sayed Osman (Paris)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Rajmani Tiwari (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: Hossein Razmdjou (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salam)
Braille: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Vitomir Sudarski (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition: Neda el Khazen
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Servat
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Special projects: Peggy Julien
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
JUST PUBLISHED
Earthquake Prediction
Proceedings of the International Sym¬
posium on Earthquake Prediction.
Contains the texts of all 83 papers read
at the Symposium, held in Paris in
April 1979. A comprehensive assess¬
ment of the state-of-the-art of earth¬
quake prediction, with suggestions for
further action to foster international
co-operation in the field. Themes cov¬
ered include: earthquake precursors,
physical processes, methods of predic¬
tion, the role of institutions, and
communication of predictions and
warnings.
1984. 995 pages 750 French francs (approx.)
Co-published with Terra Scientific Publishing
Co., Tokyo (Terrapub)
Terrapub has sales rights in the United States
and Japan.
EARTHQUAKE
PREDICTION
PROCEEDINGS OF THE INTERNATIONAL SYMPOSIUM ON
EARTHQUAKE PREDICTION
Terra Scientific Publishing Company (TERRAPUB), Tokyo
Unesco, Paris
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Colling-
wood Victoria 3066; Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd.
P.O. Box 33, Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty.
Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-
agent: United Nations Association of Australia, P.O. Box 175,
5th floor. Ana House, 28 Elizabeth Street, Melbourne Victoria
3000. AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31,
A-1011, Vienna. BAHAMAS. Nassau Stationers Ltd., P.O. Box
N-3138, Nassau. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books
International Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola,
Dacca 3. BARBADOS. University of the West Indies
Bookshop, Cave Hill Campus, P.O. Box 64, Bridgetown.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V.
Handelmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean da Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. BOTSWANA. Botswana Book Centre, P.O.
Box 91, Gaborone. BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co.
Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H 1M7.
CHINA. China National Publications Import and Export
Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Beijing. CYPRUS. "MAM",
Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena 51-113 02, Prague
1 ; Ve Smeckach 30, P.O.B. 790 - 1 1 1 - 27 Prague 1 (Permanent
display); Zahranicni literatura, 1 1 Soukenicka, Prague 1 . For
Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893
31 Bratislava - CSSR. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export-OG
Tidsskriftservice 35 Norre Sogade, DK-1970 Kobenhavn K.
EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco
Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo. ETHIOPIA.
National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100
Helsinki 10; Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, Koivuvaarankuja 2,
01 640 Vantaa 64. FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de
Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP. 12598-48. GERMAN
DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710
Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R.
FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier (German,
English, French and Spanish editions): Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher
Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57, D5300 Bonn 3. For
other Unesco publications: Karger Verlag, Germering/München.
For scientific maps only: Geo Center, Postfach 800830,
Stuttgart 80. GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O.
Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University
Bookshop of Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legón,
P.O. Box 1, Legón. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
HONG KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd.. 5A Evergreen
Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book
Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon. Hong Kong Government
Information Services, Publication Centre, Baskerville House, 22
Ice Street. HUNGARY. Kultura-Bushimport - ABT, P.O.B. 149 -
H-1389, Budapest 62. ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co.,
H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd.,
Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan
Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2;
5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh, Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahatma
Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.
17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House, New Delhi;
Publication Unit, Ministry of Education and Culture, Ex. AFO
Hutments, Dr. Rajendra Prasad Road, New Delhi 110001.
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl. Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl Dr Sam Ratulangie 37,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co.,
28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Enghélab Avenue. P.O. Box 314/1486,
Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco. 1 1 88 Enghlab Av.,
Rostam Give Building, Zip Code 1 31 58, P.O. Box 1 1 365-4498,
Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, AI Rashid Street,
Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12; Tycooly International
Publ. Ltd 6 Crofton Terrace, Dun Laoghaire Co., Dublin. ISRAEL.
A.B.C Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv
61000. ITALY. Licosa (Librería Commissionaria Sansoni, S.p.A.)
Via Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552, 50121 Florence.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101
Water Lane, Kingston. University of the West Indies Bookshop,
Mona, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo
3-chome Bunkyo-ku Tokyo 113. KENYA. East African Publishing
House, P.O. Box 30571. Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National
Commissk>nafor Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT.
The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait; for the
Unesco Courier; Parafalla Press Agency, P.O. Box SAFA 4541,
Kuwait. LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod.
Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA. Code and Yancy Bookshops
Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia. LIECHTENSTEIN : Eurocan
Trust Reg. P.O.B. 5 - 9494 Schaan. LIBYA. Agency for
Development of Publication & Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35,
Tripoli. LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue,
Luxembourg. MALAWI. Malawi Book Service, Head Office, P.O.
Box 30044 Chichi ri, Blantyre 3. MALAYSIA. University of
Malaya Cooperativa Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur 22-1 1 . MALTA.
Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta.
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-
Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-
Carlo. NEPAL. Sajha Prakashan Polchowk, Kathmandu.
NETHERLANDS. KEESING BOEKEN B.V., Joan Muyskenweg,
22, Postbus 1118, 1000 BC Amsterdam. NETHERLANDS
ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad,
Curaçao. N.A. NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Office,
Government Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344,
Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace. P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch;
Alma Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box
1 104, Dunedin, Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington.
NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The University
Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka; The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zaria. NORWAY. Johan Grundt Tanum,
P.O.B. 1177 Sentrum - Oslo 1, Narvesen A/S; Subscription and
Trade Book Service. P.O.B. 6125 Etterstad, Oslo 6; Universitets
Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, Postboks 307 Blindem, Oslo 3.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency. 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O.
Box No. 729, Lahore 3. PHILIPPINES. National Book Store, Inc.
' 701 , Rizal Avenue, Manila D-404. POLAND. Orpan-lmport,
Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie
Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068 WARSAW. PORTUGAL. Dias &
Andrade Ltda. Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon.
SEYCHELLES. National Bookshop, P.O. Box 48, Mahé; New
Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé. SIERRA
LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone Diocesan
Bookshops, Freetown. SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (S)
Pte Ltd. Times Jurong, 2 Jurong Port Road, Singapore 2261.
SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and
General, P.O. Box 951, Mogadiscio. SOUTH AFRICA. For the
Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Central News agency, P.O.
Box 1033, Johannesburg. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop,
100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mewata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2.
SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1 1 1 8, Khartoum.
SWEDEN. All publications A/B.C.E. Fritzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356. 10327
Stockholm 1 6. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN Forbundet,
Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm; Wennergren-
Williams, Box 30004-S-104, 25 Stockholm; Esselte
Tidskriftscentralen, Gamla Brogatan 26, Box 62 - 101 20
Stockholm. SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag. 5
Rämistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva
1 1 , CCP. 1 2-236. Librairies Payot also in Lausanne, Basle,
Berne, Vevey, Montreux, Neuchôtel and Zurich. TANZANIA.
Dares Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam.
THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road,
Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402; Bangkok: Suksapan Panit,
Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam
Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I. TURKEY. Haset Kitapevl A.S.,
Istiklâl Caddesi, N° 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu, Istambul.
UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 7145, Kampala.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, H.M.S.O., P.O.
Box 276, London, SW8 5DT, and Govt. Bookshops in London.
Edinburgh, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol; for
scientific maps only: McCarta Ltd., 122 King's Cross Road,
London WC 1X 9 DS. UNITED STATES. Unipub, 205 East
42nd Street, New York, N.Y. 10017. Orders for books &
Periodicals: P.O. Box 1222, Ann Arbor, Ml 48106. U.S.S.R.
Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Moscow, 121200. YUGOSLAVIA.
Mladost, llica 30/1 1, Zagreb; Cankarjeva Zalozba, Zopitarjeva 2,
Lubtjana; Nolit, Terazije 27/1 1, Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd.. P.O. Box 2664
Lusaka. ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union
Avenue, Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
HM -
m
^BrfIH
HB
i&H
ijjb¿j.
Am1
*to9^V
fpE
~
í
-**
' y*1 ida
ÉH 31
_3<s3ö.r) ^ -\v
*fi
^4c/í/ rain
The deposition of acid in rain and other forms of precipitation
is today causing extensive environmental damage in parts of
Europe and North America. These two photos of Hanskuhnen-
burg in Lower Saxony (Federal Republic of Germany) were
taken eleven years apart, in 1972 (above) and 1983 (below). See
article page 21.
]]>
</page>
</document>
