<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="062672eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
-4 WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
rier
APRIL 1963 (16TH YEAR) - PRICE 1/-STG. (U. K.) - 30 CENTS (U. S.) - 0.70 F (FRANCE)
'
RIENT-OCCIDEI
STUDY
I IGNORANCE
i
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
ART FIND IN RUMANIA. A re¬
markable discovery of sculptures
dating from the Roman era (2nd
century A. D.) was made in Ru¬
mania last year during excavations
for the construction of a new rail¬
way line. In all eight statues were
found, one of the most striking
being this sea deity in reptilian
form and carved in marble. It is
now preserved in the museum of
the Black Sea port of Constanza.
© A. Tessore, Turin
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
ON THE WOHLS^i*«^ 4 WINDOW OMN <
Courier
Contents
No. 4
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
COVER PHOTO
One of the noblest monu¬
ments of Buddhist art is the
gigantic sanctuary of Bo-
robudur on the island
of Java. Dating from 750
A.D., this man-made
mountain of stone carvings
and terraces has 504 statues
and 1,400 bas reliefs. From
its summit, this statue
of the Buddha in medita¬
tion gazes over Java's
central plain and its
towering volcanic peaks.
Unesco - Marc Riboud.
APRIL 1963
16TH YEAR
Page
4 ORIENT-OCCIDENT: A STUDY IN IGNORANCE
By Georges Fradier
(1) PROGRESS... AND PREJUDICE
(2) DIALOGUE ON THE FILM 'THE ISLAND'
14 A PORTUGUESE SANCHO PANZA IN THE FAR EAST
The voyages and adventures of Ferdinand Mendes Pinto
By Antonio Jose Saraiva
20 DOES LIFE END AT SIXTY?
By Alfred Métraux
24 HOLIDAY CURE FOR BORED TEEN-AGERS
Two million volunteers for world workcamp projects
By Arthur Gillette
28 CENSORSHIP: A DOUBLE-EDGED WEAPON
The Hidden Face of the Cinema Pt.4
By Paul Léglise
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
(U.C. 63. 1. 1 79 A)
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
René Caloz
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey
Russian Edition : Veniamln Matchavarianl (Moscow) -
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Abdel Monelm El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shln-lchl Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Italian Edition : Maria Remiddl (Rome)
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER, is published monthly, except in July and August when
it is bi-monthly (I I issues a year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German.
Arabic, Japanese, and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed by H.M.
Stationery Office, P. O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in The Readers' Guide to
Periodical Literature published by H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates : U
French Francs or equivalent,
cents (U.S.) ; 0.70 French Francs
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris T
S. $3.00; IO/-stg. ; 7.00
Single copies l/-stg. 30
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
ORIENT-OCCIDENT
A STUDY IN IGNORANCE
by Georges Fradier Flames from myriads of tiny oil lamps twinkle in the November
night, lighting up a ghatone of the flights of stairs which lead
down to the River Gangesin Benares, the sacred city of the
Hindus. The time is Diwali, the Festival of Light, a day of cele¬
bration throughout India, marking the triumph of light over
darkness. Right, a group of Greek children, each carrying a
lighted candle, takes part in a traditional Easter Eve procession.
Richard Lannoy From " La Joie de vivre " (Joy of Living ) published by the Federation des Cooperatives Migros, Zurich.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
...AND PREJUDICE
The article below is taken from " Encounters and Celebrations ", a study on the
mutual appreciation of cultural values in Orient and Occident by Georges Fradier,
which is shortly to be published by Unesco. The article on page 8 " Dialogue
Between Orient and Occident on the Film 'The Island' " which comes
from the same work was written in collaboration with Miss Tomiko Takeda.
re you more intelligent than your parents?
kMore tolerant? Do you have a more developed
awareness of things? Is your outlook more forthright
and independent? Do you think that nations or people
in general are more friendly today and that the world
is a less incomprehensible place than your elders found
it?
All these are questions which one would like to put to
young people who talk in an abstract way about progress.
For the images and ideas which the word Progress seems
to evoke nowadays are increasingly vague and obscure.
Most of the younger generation recognize, of course, the
existence of progress in technology, science and medi¬
cine. Only a minority believes in ethical progress or if
others do believe in it they are afraid to say so.
As for progress in art, philosophy and literature, this
is an even more difficult theme. For we have got into
the habit of describing progress in statistical terms, of
illustrating development by charts and some subjects
simply do not lend themselves to such interpretation. It is
easy to point to the steadily increasing output of litera¬
ture, music and painting and to the hundreds of millions
of readers. But it is impossibe for us to say whether
the books are better, the pictures finer and the readers
more perceptive; indeed, the very question lacks meaning.
One day an attempt may be m|ade to assess the results
of the Major Project launched by Unesco in 1957 to
promote the mutual appreciation of Eastern and Western
cultural values. It will be asked, for instance, whether
the English or more particularly the younger generation
in England now know more about the cultural values of
the Chinese, and appraise them with more perceptiveness
and friendly understanding, and vice versa. Ingenious
methods and infinite patience will need to be applied here.
Meanwhile we may perhaps begin to draw a general, and
let us hope, credible picture of the progress achieved.
One might, indeed, begin by applauding the substantial 5
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
STUDY IN IGNORANCE (Cont'd)
Beware of the superficial
increase of information now everywhere available about
the history, development, social and political problems,
way of life, scenery, religion and art of almost all
countries. Efforts have been made, for example, in the
field of education. In several countries studies of the
history and culture of wide areas which were hitherto
ignored have recently found their places in official school
curricula.
It would be even easier to show the growing influence
again in the field of cultural values of films, broad¬
casting, television, newspapers and magazines, records
and publications (journalistic reports, surveys, transla¬
tions of classical works and contemporary novels, etc.).
Then there is the part played by travel, now becoming
easier and easier for young people, and by meetings,
youth festivals and international work camps not to
SMILE FROM EUROPE...
Alongside the saints, angels and demons with which
they embellished the cathedrals of Europe, Gothic
sculptors carved remarkable and distinctively human
portraits in stone. One of these a young woman
carrying one of her glovesadds a note of youth and
gaiety to the figures on Basle Cathedral, Switzerland.
From "La Joie de vivre" (Joy of Living) published
by the Federation des Coopératives Migros, Zurich
mention the wonderful introduction to international life
afforded to fellowship-holders studying abroad.
In other words, the amount of information that young
people from Western countries, for instance, can pick
up nowadays about the habits, problems and amusements
of Eastern countries is out of all proportion to the know¬
ledge that was available on the same subjects twenty
years ago.
The casual listener to a radio programme may hear
a sarode concert or a Balinese orchestra. The cinema
will already have introduced him to the daily life of
peasants in the Nile Valley and to the most varied
episodes of Japanese mediaeval or contemporary history,
and he may have been lucky enough to come across
documentary films revealing the beauties of Borobudur,
Angkor Vat, Isfahan and the Taj Mahal. In daily and
weekly papers he will have seen a wealth of pictures,
generally beautiful and always picturesque, of the differ¬
ent "developing countries" whose glories, contrasts and
mysteries never fail to interest and intrigue.
Thus, most young people in the West have now a
broad access to facts about the Eastern countries, and
the same applies to youth in the East (most of whom
have become enthusiastically fond of dance music and
films imported from America and even from Europe).
Does this mean that the Major Project has achieved its
aims? That is less certain. A mass of superficial Infor¬
mation, unrelated Ideas and images arbitrarily removed
from their contexts as well as isolated statistics may
well be the raw material for lively conversation, but do
not necessarily add up to genuine understanding.
O|n the contrary, there is some danger that all
this information, most of it haphazard and
passively absorbed, may build up a sense of blase com¬
placency. After seeing a little of everything and hearing
epochs and countries brought up in conversation in any
and every connexion, people quickly come to believe that
they are well informed and have understood all there is
to know.
Information which is too rapidly acquired does not
always even have the advantage of overcoming prejudice.
The other day an article on Japan, describing a "typi¬
cal" Japanese family, appeared in a glossy magazine with
an international circulation. Many such articles are
published, and this one was better than most; it conveyed
a good deal of accurate and Interesting information
about the economic and social life of the "professional
middle class".
At the same time, to lend a picturesque flavour to
his article, the writer stressed those well-known conflicts
between tradition and modernism which observers are
always noticing In the East. These conflicts, or tensions,
take various formsin terms of language (foreign words
brought into the vocabulary), in terms of psychiatry
(people living half in the atomic age and half in a tradi¬
tional environment become schizophrenic), or in terms
of history (the Middle Ages lingering on into the 20th
century) .
This last approach is the most popular with the caption
writers; a pair of trousers symbolizes the 20th century,
a kimono is mediaeval; the naval shipyard belongs to
the 20th century and the Shinto temple to the Middle
Ages. There is a grain of truth in all this. But to dwell
on these alleged contrasts is unwittingly to perpetuate
prejudice. We are told that "the East derives its scien¬
tific cultureeven its 'rationalism'its comforts, its
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
politics and its amusements from the West ; it is painfully
or ludicrously torn between the traditional, Oriental mind
and the modern mentality; the result of adaptation to
technologies which its culture is unable to absorb can
only be fatal", etc.
In order to come nearer to the truth, I would suggest
an article written in the same style, with the same skilled
photography about, let us say, a "typical" family in Würt¬
temberg. Nothing would be easier than to underline the
contrasts, or even the irreconcilabilities between the
modern life of a German engineer and the mediaeval
traditions that linger in his home.
HI is old mother, his wife and perhaps even he
himself still read an ancient work called Die
Bibel, which was translated by a monk revered even
today long, before the Industrial Revolution. The man
works all day in an ultra-modern office. In the evening
he meets his friends in a building which looks, and may
even be, Gothic and joins them in drinking a beverage
made from fermented barleythe formula for which goes
back to the Teutons and Celts to the accompaniment of
ancient ritual choruses.
A young Chinese spending a few weeks in Stuttgart
would notice these contrasts without seeing any reason
to deplore them; he would meet people ready to supply
a good-natured explanation of them. Knowledge picked
up during travel is not so piecemeal as that acquired from
the newspapers; it is more concentrated, and its appeal
is not solely to the memory.
Through individual or group travel, and even more
by international meetings, young people are enabled
in greater numbers every yearto discover their distant
contemporaries in the East or West. Their contacts
will probably be confined to young people like themselves,
however, for it is not easy to discover a whole country,
let alone a whole culture.
Nothing is better, of course, than to learn to express
ourselves and be understood on the level of friendship;
to work together, to play together and to join in reso¬
lutions about peace and harmony all these are to be
encouraged. But even the rrçost cordial meetings some¬
times fade to dim memoriesand also tend to over¬
simplify the problem of different cultural values.
IIn such cases, the preconception about insur¬
mountable barriers makes way for an as¬
sumption of uniformity, which affirms "We are all alike.
The world is the same everywhere. We all have the same
needs and the same ambitions." This can lead to the
conclusion that intellectual effort of any kind is super¬
fluous.
On the other hand, a different danger seems to lie
in wait for those with more exacting minds, who have
a taste for history and for currently fashionable his¬
torical theories. The tendency to generalize, while
excellent as an antidote to narrow-minded specialization,
sometimes leads people to dip too hastily into the past and
into human geography and, for the sake of convenience,
to classify whole nations in one civilization or cultural
group.
Whatever may be the advantage of these vast, all-
embracing explanations as a means of conveying ideas,
we must not overlook the drawback that they aré
frequently no more than optical illusions. Even the
most cultivated people may be taken In by them.
For a long time, for instance, we have heard criticism
I Sunil Janah, Calcutta
...SMILE FROM ASIA
This graceful Yak. sini or nymph was carved over ten
centuries ago on the Temple of Siva at Bhubaweshar
In the Indian State of Orissa. A holy place, Bhuba¬
weshar was once known as "The City of Temples".
But of 7,000 temples only a few hundred now remain.
of the sweeping judgments pronounced on Orient and
Occident; but it is astonishing how they persist. We are
still told that the East has a monopoly of spiritual
enlightenment and that all Western nations are mat¬
erialistic. Other concepts, less far-reaching but equally
unsubstantiated, also survive; authoritative writers still
publish reflections on happiness "conceived in the West
as the plenitude of life and in India as release from life,
as absorption into the Infinite"; in the East one still
meets distinguished professors leaving for Europe, looking
forward confidently to unrestricted and profitable meet¬
ings with their opposite numbers in the West, "because
In Europe all cultivated people speak English, just as
they do here".
In reality problems relating to the mutual appreciation
of cultural values are by no means simple ones. They
are still neither outdated nor solved. And even in the
case of collective problems it is still up to the individual
to solve them on a personal level by facing up to situa¬
tions in which disputes or misunderstandings are likely
to occur but in which, providing the necessary effort is 7
made, understanding and cultural enrichment can also
be found.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
STUDY IN IGNORANCE (Part 2)
»
DIALOGUE BET
ON THE FILM
ONE small islet, only five acres in area, was chosen by the film director
Kaneto Shindo, from among the countless islands that compose the stately
yet delicate landscape of the Inland Sea of Japan, as the setting for an extraor¬
dinary film which some people consider to be worthy of comparison with the
work of Robert Flaherty, and in particular with " Man of Aran ".
It is a film in which nothing happens. Or, more precisely, in which a host of
episodes, trivial and yet intense, take place without forming a story. This island
is an arid waste of stones and poor soil ; but it is inhabited and cultivated (meti¬
culously, inch by inch) by a couple, who are still young and who labour unceas¬
ingly from dawn to nightfall, with the frenzied obstinacy associated with certain
insects such as bees, ants and termites.
They have two little boys, the elder of whom is at school all day on the big
island, where his parents go almost hourly to fetch water. For their own islet
has no well, no springit is completely dry. For the greater part of the year
the couple spend their lives rowing to and fro in a boat and bringing back water
in buckets which they carry, slung from a yoke, carefully and slowly to the
top of their hill, where they meticulously water their beans and their sweet pota¬
toes plant by plant. They also grow maize and wheat.
Planting, hoeing, watering, rowing, carrying, digging, day after day such
is the round of their existence. They hardly pause to eat] or sleep. They
know nobody in the outer world, on the big island. This is simply the place
where they go for water, the place where the school is situated, and the shop¬
keepers to whom they pay rare, respectful visits, and also the doctor who arrives
too late one day, to find the elder boy dead.
The film is as simple as that; it shows us people living, working and dying
without uttering a word. It is not a silent film ; it is a film in which people do not
speak. The photography is admirable, but the spectators do not always notice
the beauty of the scene, they are so gripped by the two chief characters, or rather,
by the concentrated performances of two great actors, Yasuji Tonoyama and
Miss Nobuko Otowa.
Oriental and Occidental impressions of "The Island" are reflected in the
following dialogue between a Japanese girl student (J) and a European man (E)
both of whom have seen the film several times.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
WEEN ORIENT & OCCIDENT
THE ISLAND
On an arid island in
Japan's Inland Sea a peas¬
ant couple toils around
the clock tending crops
and fetching water from
the mainland. From these
simple facts Kaneto
Shindo has made a re¬
markable film in which
the roles of wife and the
husband are played by
Nobuko Otowa (left) and
Yasuji Tonoyama (right).
Photos Kmdai Eiga Kyokai
E. When I was in Japan a few months ago, it struck
me that "The Island" was very little known or appreciat¬
ed. I asked several people about it but they only said
vaguely. "Yes... a documentary film?"
3. No one in Japan took much notice of it until
people in the West became interested. A documentary?
Yes, Shindo Kaneto has a reputation for making shorts
and feature films in a proletarian spirit, films taken from
real life, perhaps to show up its Injustice: a kind of
socialist realism. And people admired Nobuko Otowa, who
usually plays glamorous parts, for agreeing to depict an
earthy character, whose face is often covered with
sweat and dirt. Then the film attracted attention abroad
and won a prize at the Moscow festival; so finally, in
Japan it came to be classed as a "melodrama."
E. Thafs a strange description. But let us assume
for a moment that the film really is a documentary. If
that is so, what does it teach us about Japan apart from
the beauty of the scenery? We see the fields of corn or
rice looking like gardens, sown in perfectly straight rows;
scrubbed and polished. There is the impression that the
sea carries an unceasing traffic of small boats, tugs and
steamers. We are taken to visit the town, which is of
course noisy, crowded and industrious.
3. That's Onomichi. It is worthwhile, in any case,
to have a glimpse of a town that is so old and at the same
time so modern a medium-sized town and the scenery,
both are quite typical. As for the houses, a foreigner who
has never seen our Japanese houses, except in films, finds
it very difficult to imagine what they look like. For
instance, French people think of houses as buildings
made of stone a material never used for this purpose
in Japan or brick, with a roof of slates or red tiles. The
first thing we Japanese think of is wooden posts and
exposed beams, and whitewashed earthen walls which are
hollow, built upon a framework of woven bamboo stems.
The roof is thatched, or, in more modern houses, made
of grey tiles. The building gives straight onto the outer
world, through big French windows another term which
is likely to give the wrong idea. The paper door (shoji),
the paper partition (fusuma) and the traditional tatami,
which carpets the whole of the interior, are things one
has to know about before one can imagine a Japanese
house.
E. The film does, I agree, give us a glimpse of all that.
But the hut on the island where the couple live seems too
squalid, quite to correspond to this idea of a house. Does
this mean that all Japanese peasants are as poor as that?
3. Certainly not. On the whole they are by no means
well off, although they create so much wealth for the
country. But the people in The Island are not really
destitute. They are in no danger of starvation; they are
quite respectably dressed. Yet people who live so
wretchedly and work so hard are a very small minority.
E. So this may, after all, be a "propaganda film,"
intended to expose the injustice from which that minority
suffers?
3. Yes... It looks as if the director tried to give it that
meaning at first. But he was too much of an artist, too
much of a poet, to be satisfied with that alone. In the
end it turned into a poetic work.
E. I think so too. Even a tragedy. After setting out
to describe the living conditions of a peasant family in
a remote part of Japan, the film goes much further. Or
rather it is not quite a tragedy; just one thing is lacking.
3. What do you feel is missing?
E. Speech. These people live together and suffer
together without exchanging a word. The chief quality
that distinguishes man from the other animals is speech, q
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
STUDY IN IGNORANCE (Confd)
Silence that speaks
from the heart
or so we are usually told. But these people never, abso¬
lutely never, say anything; one wonders whether they
are really together, or merely side by side, one person and
then another, each quite alone.
3. Oh yes, the absence of communication! That
Is what always strikes foreigners. Several times already,
people have asked me, "Have they nothing to say to each
other?" But believe it or not, I myself did not notice
the silence at all. In Japan, in moments of the most
intense emotion, the deepest grief, people say nothing.
E. I remember that terrible scene when the young
wife, after once again climbing the hill with her infinitely
precious supply of water, stumbles and upsets one of the
buckets. Her husband looks at her, comes closer, and
knocks her down with a single blow. That blow is the
only way he can express himself.
10
J. And yet he loves his
wife, there is no doubt of
that. He does not strike
her out of cruelty. She
has unintentionally done
wrong. He is putting
things to rights. I think
she understands that.
Later on, in the evening,
she is looking across at
the big island. She is all alone, watching the fireworks
(it is probably August 16, the Feast of the Dead, associat¬
ed with fire ; after the fireworks, we see illuminated boats ;
in the old days this was the season of epidemics, and
people are still afraid of typhoid fever); she watches.
Her husband comes up behind her. He says nothing.
Can he find no word to comfort her? No. He does
not know how to tell her that he, too, is unhappy, and
that he understands her. And she does not even know
that her husband has paused for a moment to watch
her, with an aching heart. And without a word they
both go up the hill, spade in hand, to bury their son's
ashes.
E. Do you mean they know instinctively that words
cannot relieve a deep sorrow?
3. It's not that; the Japanese, like other people,
know very well that when one is unhappy it is a comfort
not to feel alone, and that two people together are better
able to bear a great grief.
E. You mean it is a kind of awkwardness?
3. I suppose so. But awkwardness of that kind is
so common that it does not upset us. That's why I
found the silence of this film perfectly normal and na¬
tural, apart from the fact that the director wanted it to
be like that. The members of that family don't talk to
one another; and that inevitably reminds me of my own
family, I wonder how it is that where I come from
people express themselves so little and so badly brothers
and sisters, husbands and wives, even lovers. Perhaps
we talk more freely to friends or school companions...
When I first came to Europe I was struck by the way in
which the children of the family I knew (two teenage
boys and one younger one) used to argue with their
parents at meals. They had no hesitation about
contradicting their father's opinions. And sometimes he
would say calmly "Yes, you're right." In my own home
it would never have occurred to me to argue with my
father! Even if I thought he Was mistaken, I would
never say "Father, I don't agree. I think so-and-so,
because...!" I don't know whether he would be angry
or pleased ; I have never tried. I have never talked, really
talked, to my mother, either.
Every precious drop of
water for cultivation has
to be rowed over to the
island and then carried in
buckets slung from a yoke
to the top of the hill
where the crops are grown.
J. No, let's make no mistake about it; it is simply
the absence of argument. I don't mean chatter...
E. But Japanese life is changing, and so is the rela¬
tionship between parents and children...
3. Japan has recently experienced social changes
perhaps more abrupt and violent than those In any other
country. How can I explain? Two hundred years ago
our most successful dramatists were writing popular plays
in which the hero killed his own son in order to save the
son of his feudal lord, as loyalty required of him. That
kind of hero was applauded without hesitation. And even
when those plays are given nowadays, the audience sheds
floods of tears without pausing to ask itself whether a
father is entitled to kill his own child. One such play
was forbidden during the American occupation, because
its feudal code of morality was contrary to democracy and
human rights. But a few years later it was revived, and
received as enthusiastically as ever. Reason and law have
proclaimed that the individual, starting in childhood, has
certain rights. And nowadays nobody would sacrifice his
own son to save the son of his superior. But for all that,
a present-day audience sees nothing criminal or immoral
in such plays.
E. And what does that show?
3. In my opinion, family life is not yet up to date
in its spirit. We have not entirely shaken off the vestiges
of the fine Confucianist ethical code.
E. You consider it a fine code?
E. Perhaps that is a sign of good behaviour?
dience?
Obe-
3. It really was very
fine. As for married
couples, they are on a more
equal footing than fifteen
years ago. The wife's
situation has changed.
There is a scene in the
film which I find signi¬
ficant. It comes towards
the end. In a sudden fit
of rage, the woman deliberately knocks over the precious
bucket of water; she deliberately repeats the action
for which her husband had not hesitated to strike her.
And then she throws herself on the ground and begins
frantically uprooting the plants... But this time the man
does not move. With deep compassion, he watches his
wife, who has lost her self-control because of her child's
death. He says nothing. If he were to let himself go,
perhaps, he, too, would throw himself on the ground.
But as usual he says nothing. He turns back to his work.
He quite understands his wife's grief and her revolt against
the poverty which caused them to leave their little boy to
die. She has no other way of expressing herself. Neither
has he. They are not in the habit of speaking, of
expressing their thoughts or feelings.
E. Sometimes it's better that way. In Tokyo a woman
friend took me one day to the Asakusa temple. As we went
though that districtwhich might be called the religious
birthplace of the city with its cinemas, its places of
entertainment, and its stalls of souvenirs and religious
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
objects, I was expecting to be given all kinds of explana¬
tions about the temple, which was destroyed during the
war and rebuilt recently, with modern materials, though,*
exactly as it had been standing for centuries, down to the
smallest details. Nothing of the kind; my friends merely
suggested that I should go up the steps and take my shoes
off. Then we knelt (or rather, sat down in the Japanese
fashion) among the congregation. We stayed there for
quite a time, naturally without uttering a word. And
words would have been superfluous. In similar circums¬
tances, one of my own countrymen would have shown
me the statues and ornaments, pointed out the beauties
of the architecture, and remarked on amusing or
touching things concerning the behaviour of the monks
and pilgrims. He would have tired me out. There,
instead, there was this long, silent contemplation. And
it left an impression I shall never forget.
3. So you do appreciate silence. Yet In the life of a
family, or of a married couple, it baffles you. A man
and a woman may be aware that they love each other
deeply and yet find no words in which to say so.
E. Is it true, as I have been told, that the Japanese
language has no words to express affection?
3: It is rather that people don't know how to use
them. A young Japanese friend of mine once admitted
to me that he would find it easier to tell a girl he loved
her in a foreign language than in his own. I was not
surprised. A Japanese boy who will say "I love you," in
English will not be so ready with the corresponding words
in Japanese. That is because he has probably never
heard them spoken. He has often read them in romantic
stories, but they are never used in daily life, and hardly
ever even between Intimates. Even a couple who are
madly in love will not speak them aloud.
E. Then how do they make themselves understood?
J. ^Wlth their eyes. There is a proverb that says
"The eyes speak more clearly than the lips." So Japanese
loversN remain silent. It is not necessarily a falling, but
it is certainly characteristic.
E. 7s it also characteristic to remain completely
silent at a funeral when you have come, as we should
say, to offer your sympathy? In "The Island," I found
the funeral sequence unbearable. The schoolchildren
come with their teacher to attend the cremation of their
little school-fellow. The bonze (priest) is with them,
young and well-fed, in his beautiful robes; his manner is
cold and indifferent...
3. I have never known a bonze to show emotion. But
did you notice how serious, hcrargrave the little boys and
girls were?
E. The parents and the small brother go down to the
shore to receive all these visitors, they greet one another
politely, one almost expects them to smile.
3. They might smile. It would be proper. And you
would be even more puzzled, wouldn't you?
E. Yes, the smile of Asia... Ortega y Gasset explain¬
ed it as a result of dense population, saying that the more
people you expect to meet, the more polite you are likely
be.
3. We have heard a lot about the "Oriental smile..."
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
Photos Kindai Eiga Kyoka'
Planting, hoeing, watering, rowing, carrying, digging, the life of the family on the Island Is an endless,
unvarying round of toll. Sometimes interpreted as a cry of protest against the lot of the Impoverished,
Sindo's film Is also seen as a poetic work showing man's ability to triumph over grief and adversity.
'--ci'
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
STUDY IN IGNORANCE (Cont'd)
A merciless picture of the human condition
A Frenchman who has lived for a long time in the Far
East told me how his Chinese secretary came to him one
day to announce the death of his mother. With a smile.
Anyone would have thought that the secretary was
either mad or pleased at his mother's death. Not at all.
It is simply politeness; the smile sets up a barrier both
against you and in your own interest. You must not
express opinions or feelings to your superior before being
invited to do so. In the event of misfortune, one is
still less entitled to thrust one's own unhappiness upon
people to whom one owes respect, such as neighbours.
This is a hard-and-fast rule, the same in Japan as in
China or in Viet-Nam. During the funeral on The Island,
no one sheds tears; but the impression is heart-rending.
E. The funeral pyre is still burning. The visitors
take their leave. The boat sails round the island; the
little brother runs from field to field, watching till it is
out of sight. Later, the parents bury the ashes and put
up a little board on the grave.
j. They have written the dead boy's name on it.
From the top downwards; his name under the Law, which
the bonze has just given him for his future life, and his
own name, Taro.
E. As you say, the impression is heart-rending. Our
own feelings can easily be explained, because we are eye¬
witnesses of the unbearable scene; we see the people's
faces; and besides, we hear the music. Music plays a
tremendous part in a film, and this is often overlooked.
J. Yes, Hayashi Hikaru's music is perfect for this
film. A very simple tune, repeated at various moments,
with slight variations.
E. Was Hayashi trying to compose a traditional air,
the kind of thing one might call "typically Japanese?"
j. 	 No, not at all. But the instruments sound very
Japanese. One has the impression of hearing the
shakuhachi, flute, and the Koto rather than the guitar.
E. The musical score is extremely effective. But I
would like to point out that what we hear is incidental
music, intended to work upon the feelings of the audience;
not music within the film, such as the actors would hear.
There is hardly any of that. To introduce the Spring
sequence, a woman's voice sings the beginning of the
traditional cherry-tree song, Sakura... The characters,
one may suppose, have it running through their heads.
And later we hear the schoolchildren singing a little song
in class. And then a few really ancient folk-songs, in
two very short scenesthe games and dances of the
harvest, and the New Year festivities. The two little boys
are present on these occasions, but do not take part in
them. Much less their parents, who have no time. They
do not belong to the world in which people sing, dance,
play and say their prayers...
j. They are very poor. They live apart from the
community. And it is true that the community, the
village, the big Island, despises and rejects them for that
reason. They draw their water from a brook, where it
runs out of the riceflelds. Water that has already been
used. And the Island does not belong to them. When
they go to deliver their wheat to that horrible man who
does not even come out to greet them, they are paying
their rent. I think they sell one sack out of four for
their own benefit, that brings them enough to buy a
few groceries and a bottle of saké.
E. That's right, they are outsiders, outsiders and
alone. That must be why I can't help seeing this film as
a tragedy, a merciless picture of the human condition,
or, if you prefer it, of a certain human condition. For
the people we see in it, life is essentially a matter of toil,
grief, production, reproduction and death. Once in a
while there is a digression towards something loftier and
out of reach; a thought is given to "culture," to more
exalted values national and religious traditions, as re¬
mote from real life as are the great liners that glide along
the horizon. These values have not been forgotten; they
are added ironically, dangled just beyond people's reach.
Then there is another thing: these people are poor and
12 exploited. Could they improve their lot?
j. How? By fixing up a winch to hoist their buckets?
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Family rejoicing (left) when
one of the sons catches a
large fish which will pay
for a rare visit to the nearby
city. A poignant moment
(below) after the death of a
son, when boys and girls
from his school arrive by
boat to attend his funeral.
The wife (right) is an image
of grace and serenity even
as she lifts her heavy buckets.
Photos Kindai Eiga Kyokai
By digging a cistern? Perhaps. But I think they are
too poor, too deeply Involved in their work... As for
leaving the land and becoming a labourer in the town, the
husband would never dream of it. He would be just as
poor and have even less freedom.
E. Yes, they are prisoners in their existence. Shindo
has succeeded in expressing alienation not only among
the proletariat, but in ourselves. His view of the world,
is completely pessimistic though the pessimism has a
dignified restraint.
3. I don't agree. I do not feel the irony you speak
of. "The Island" is simply a very beautiful film in which
the director shows a family that is happy, in spite of
great material difficulties and in spite of the death of a
child, which would not have happened in wealthier
surroundings. We are shown the contentment of these
peasants, who have complete confidence in the soil. One
sees the ecstasy which they regard the thirsty earth and
the young shoots.
E. You really call that happiness?
J. Yes, enviable happiness. There are moments of
real delight. When the little boy catches a big fish, they
are all delighted. The next day they put on their best
clothes and take the steamer to the town, intending to
sell the fish to some gourmet for a good price. Finally
they sell It to a fishmonger, rather too cheaply, perhaps,
but making the best of it, for fear of disappointing the
children. And it fetches enough money for them to have
dinner at a restaurant (a great event), and buy some
shirts, and go for a ride in the funicular, high above the
rooftops. All that is gay. But more important, there are
many other moments of even simpler happiness: those
that come while working quietly at home during the rainy
season, and those that follow the hard day's work in the
evening. Picking up a handful of leaf-mould. Rowing
slowly in the morning, at earliest cock-crow. Watching
the sun as it sinks into the sea. Taking the evening
bath. You remember that? They heat lots of water.
The children jump into it first. Then the father. And
lastly, the mother. Did you notice her smile then? It is
the smile of a happy woman.
E. I feel that in discussing "The Island" you have
taught me an enormous number of things about Japan.
J. You have taught me a great deal about your own
outlook. And I must admit that it is always my foreign j 3
friends who reveal to me more about my country through
the interest they take in it.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
A PORTUGUESE
SANCHO PANZA
IN THE FAR EAST
by Antonio Jose
Saraiva
Europe's pioneers of oceanic
navigation to the Far East
were the Portuguese. In 1497,
Vasco de Gama, sailed to India
and opened a maritime trade
route to the Orient. By 1519 a
Portuguese cartographer was
able to depict with commendable
realism (in this picturesquely
illustrated map) countries from
the Red Sea to South East Asia.
¿JBÜSfeS
h &¿f
> y^y~y ,
£." -»*t "i
I N the 15th and 16th centuries, the Portuguese
_ and Spaniards reached America, the Indies,
the Pacific Islands, the Malay Archipelago, China and
Japan, and in 1522 the world was first circumnavigated
by Ferdinand Magellan, a Portuguese. Next it was the
turn of the Dutch, the English and the French to voyage
and to establish settlements in many parts of the globe.
However, it cannot be claimed that Europeans imme¬
diately penetrated to the spiritual treasures of the civiliza¬
tions they were discovering. The conquerors and traders
were less interested in souls than in gold, silver and
spices and also in slaves who were themselves trade goods
like the rest. Even Christian missionaries saw only
human error or the wiles of the devil in beliefs that
differed from their own.
The crushing of the Aztecs and the Incas and the obli¬
vion in which their remarkable art was doomed to remain
for several centuries are outstanding examples of this
failure in understanding which led to the impoverishment
of the cultural tradition of mankind as a whole. Only
in our own day has the pre-Columbian art of America
regained its rightful place in the world's cultural heritage
and has made a rich contribution to the originality of
modern Mexican painting.
History, however, is not completely void of cases where
the world's diversity was accepted and voyagers showed
a sympathetic understanding of non-European civiliza¬
tions. One of the oldest examples is offered by a Portu¬
guese book of the 16th century, Peregrinacao, by Ferdi¬
nand Mendes Pinto, a Portuguese trader in the Far East,
who died in 1582.
Though almost forgotten today, Peregrinacao was at
one time known throughout Europe. First published in
14 1614, it was translated into a number of languages, in¬
cluding French, English, German and Dutch, during the
17th and 18th centuries.
The Portuguese navigator, Vasco de Gama arrived at
Calicut, the present seaport of Kozhikode, on the
Malabar coast of India, in 1498. In 1511, the Portuguese
annexed Malacca which gave them a firm control over
trade in the Far East for some time. In 1517, they sent
an Embassy to the Emperor of China, but at that time
the Ming Dynasty had turned its back on the sea and
closed its frontiers to foreigners; and so the ambassador
of the King of Portugal failed in his mission.
Nevertheless, a few venturesome Portuguese merchants
and adventurers managed to trade between China, the
Malay Archipelago and the Pacific Islands, by accepting
the risks which this involved. Private Individuals,
unconnected in any way with the Portuguese State, they
operated in a more or less clandestine way, building
small stores and depots on the Chinese coast which
eventually grew into self-governing mercantile commu¬
nities and trading stations. If the opportunity came
their way, they were not above acts of piracy. On
occasion their voyages took them to places hitherto
unknown to Europeans.
Thus, about 1542 a ship with Portuguese merchants
aboard, including Ferdinand Mendes Pinto, who by then
belonged to this strange world of adventurers, arrived at
the island of Tanegashima in Japan. Mendes Pinto has
left us an account of this first meeting between Euro¬
peans and Japanese.
He was charmed by the chivalrous spirit and noble
nature of the Islanders and impressed by attention paid
to questions of honour which was the cause of endless
feuds between the nobles. He also tells us how one of
his companions, Diego Zeimoto, introduced firearms to
Japan. The first time they saw Diego killing game with
his gun, the local people took him for a magician, but
they quickly learned to make guns themselves since
as Mendes Pinto tells us their craftsmen were extremely
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
JXDÍV I INTRIGA
f Y-M / -'T^yi iu:vil'-> i¡ff^ l v i:
2 %I"r^M^ ^''Z^^^fd
)J¡£ljJ¿S:'\, s F "	.niJg'iv XJLj^ ;
í&
AAR.EIM)LCVM
<s
PIALEÖVS
^¿- y a&frg§
SÉ
tSSáSsIe.
Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
skilful. Pinto also remarks on the graciousness of the
women and the exquisite politeness of the courtiers.
This delightful picture of the Japanese is only part
of the book. Its author boasts of having covered the
whole Asian coast from the Persian Gulf to Siberia, with
detours through the Indonesian Islands and the Island
of Taiwan, and of having travelled in China by river and
canal between Pekin and Nanking, where he was as¬
tounded at the huge "towns" of boat-dwellers.
He claims to have worked as a convict on repairing the
Great Wall of China and to have been able to measure
its height and thickness with his own hands. He asserts
that he was enlisted into the Mongol army which
invaded China about 1544, that he was taken before the
famous king who burnt the suburbs of Pekin (probably
Dayan, King of the Ordos), and that he visited the Holy
City in Tibet.
These travels, some of them undoubtedly true, and the
others imaginary, serve him as a framework for a vi¬
vidly romanticized autobiography. It is packed with
incident, with land and sea fights, shipwrecks, wander¬
ings, dreadful crimes, glorious exploits and popular
risings, with anecdotes, with descriptions of customs,
rites, beliefs, ceremonies, towns, palaces and temples of
the most wonderful kinds. From its pages speak a mul¬
titude of characters into whose mouths the author puts
eloquent discourses studded with Eastern imagery. The
whole is a blend of narrative and description almost
Homeric in Its variety and power.
The main character, the author himself, is successively
agent of the Governor of Malacca, merchant, pirate,
slave, vagabond, beggar, soldier, and finally, simul¬
taneously ambassador of the Viceroy of Goa to a
Japanese baron and Jesuit missionary.
He never depicts himself as a hero but rather as a
poor booby muddling his way as best he can out of
innumerable misfortunes. Most of the time he is at
grips with hunger and fear. In a word, he is the com¬
plete "picaro," the "anti-hero" of the Spanish picares¬
que novels. If we prefer, we can look on him as a
Portuguese Sancho Panza of the East. He has no notion
whatever of knightly honour and he is the absolute
reverse of a "hidalgo" or "conquistador."
At most, he is a trader and that is why, even when he
is acting as an ambassador, he always appears to be of
a, lower order than his Eastern interlocutors, be they
Malay Sultans, Chinese mandarins, Japanese Samurai,
priests anywhere and everywhere, or even the impo¬
verished fishermen whose slave he was for- a while.
From all these people he receives lessons of every kind
to which he is obliged to hearken submissively.
The women too, for whom Mendes Pinto has the
utmost affection, have something to teach the plun¬
derers. A storm hurls them on the shores of the Island
of Léquia (Taiwan). They are borne off to prison on
suspicion of being sea-rovers disguised as merchants, but
the wretched state in which they arrive, naked and
covered with cuts and bruises, stirs the. women to pity.
When the travellers are on the point of being executed
the women flock to the main square of the city with a
moving petition to the King, signed by hundreds, begging
him to spare the prisoners. The King is moved and
releases the condemned men, but says that he will not
receive them "because it ill becomes a king to look on
men who, though knowing God, do not obey His laws
and are wont to steal their neighbour's goods."
To Mendes Pinto's Orientals, the Europeans are little
better than savages: they eat with their fingers, quarrel
loudly and sometimes come to blows for futile reasons.
To the East, they are objects of amazement or derision. 15
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
PORTUGUESE SANCHO PANZA (Cont'd)
The first European to reach Japan
Above all, however, Peregrinacao gives us a whole¬
heartedly admiring picture of the civilizations of the
Far East. As for China, Mendes Pinto depicts it as an
absolute Utopia: justice is swift, humane and completely
fair to the accused; the structure of the State prevents
the corruption of its magistrates and the oppression of
its subjects; there is no unemployment or famine; manu¬
facturing and trade supply all the needs of man ;
there is a complete system of communications; manners
are perfect; and "Rome, Constantinople, Venice, Paris,
London, Seville, Lisbon or any other famed city of Europe"
do not begin to compare with the capital, Pekin. Men¬
des Pinto even goes so far as to wish that the laws of
China could be copied in Portugal.
This description of China is of course rather idealized and
the indications are that our author did not know China as
well as he knew Japan. What counts, however, is his
admiration and lack of prejudice, and his admiration is
not purely intellectual, but comes also from the heart.
At every turn we find him moved to wonder by the
works of art, the towns, the crowds, the colour and
music, the manner of speech the ceremonies, the beauty
of the women and the delightful ways of the children.
He even gives us descriptions of Chinese and Japanese
plays, translates forms of greeting and courtesy, and
provides transcriptions (though how faithful, it is hard
to say) of occasional words of the tongues of the East.
Naturally, the picture he paints is not without its blem¬
ishes. It Includes accounts of unbelievable atrocities.
Yet the fact remains that Mendes Pinto was, I am sure,
the first person to attempt a synoptic sketch of the
civilizations of the Far East and that he produced one
that is lively and artistic, and that seeks to penetrate
to the heart and essence of those civilizations and to
understand them from within.
Leaving aside some undeniable mistakes and errors of
fact, we have in Perigrinacao, which was written in
Lisbon in the second half of the 16th century, a book
which does not treat men with beliefs differing from the
author's own as mere objects, whose sole interest lies
in the profits and advantages that can be gained from
them. In other words, for Mendes Pinto the European
viewpoint is not the only valid one.
That is why, in any history of European feelings and
attitudes towards non-European civilizations, Mendes
Pinto has earned an honoured place.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Japanese and Europeans
met for the first time
when a ship with Portu¬
guese merchants aboard,
Including Ferdinand Men¬
des Pinto, reached the
Island of Tanegashima in
Japan, about 1 542. Soon
other trading vessels
followed them and the
arrival of one of these is
shown here in a Japanese
screen painting which
dates from about 1600.
Kobe City Museum, Japan
THE VOYAGES AND ADVENTURES
OF FERDINAND MÉNDEZ PINTO'
Extracts from the book with the above title, done into
English by Henry Cogan and printed in London in 1663.
FOR the better satisfaction of the reader, I dare boldly say, if my
testimony may be worthy of credit, that in one and twenty years
space (during which time, with a world of misfortune, labour and pain,
I traversed the greatest part of Asia, as may appear by this my discourse)
I had seen in some countries a wonderfull abundance of several sorts of
victuals, and provisions which we have not in our Europe ; yet, without
speaking what each of them might have in particular, I do not think there
is in all Europe so much as there is in China alone.
And the same may be said of all the rest, wherewith Heaven hath
favoured this climate, as well for the temperature of the air, as for that
which concerns the policy, and riches, the magnificence and greatness
of their estate. Now that which gives the greatest lustre unto it, is their
exact observation of justice ; for there is so well ruled a government in
this country, as it may justly be envied of all others in the world...
I think it not amiss to make a brief relation here of the city of Pequin,
which may truly be termed the capital of the monarchy of the world ; as
also of some particular I observed there, as well for its arches and policy,
as for that which concerns its extent, its government, the laws of the
countrey, and the admirable manner of providing for the good of the whole
state.
THIS city of Pequin (Peking) is scituated in the height of forty and one
degrees of northerly latitude ; the walls of it are in circuit (by the report
of the Chineses themselves, and as I have read in a little book, treating
of the greatness thereof, and intituled Aquisendan, which I brought since
along with me into Portugal) thirty large leagues, namely ten long, and five
broad... it is environed with two rows of strong walls, where there are a
number, of towers and bulwarks after our fashion.
Without this great inclosure, which (as I have said) is not comprehended
in the city, there is in a distance of three leagues broad, and seven long,
fourscore thousand tombs of the Mandarins, which are little chappels all
gilded within, and compassed about with balusters of iron and lattin, the
entries whereinto are through very rich and sumptuous arches...
It hath also five hundred very great palaces, which are called the houses
of the son of the sun, whither all those retire that have been hurt in the
wars for the service of the King, as also many other soldiers, who in
regard of age or sickness are no longer able to bear arms, and to the end
that during the rest of their days they be exempted from incommodity, each
of them receives monethly a certain pay to find himself withal, and to live
upon.
LIKEWISE there are along this river Batampina, whereon we went from
Nanquin to Pequin, which is distant one from the other one hundred
and fourscore leagues, such a number of engines for sugar, and presses
for wine and oyl, made of divers sorts of pulse and fruit, as one could hardly
see any other thing on either side of the water.
In many other places also there were an infinite company of houses and
magazines full of all kinds of provision, that one could imagine, where all
sorts of flesh are salted, dried, smoked, and piled up in great high heaps,
as gammons of bacon, pork, lard, geese, ducks, cranes, bustards, ostriches,
stags, cows, buffles, wild goats, rhinocerotes, horses, tygers, dogs, foxes,
and almost all other creatures that one can name, so that we said many
times amongst ourselves, that it was not possible for all the people of the
world to eat up all those provisions.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
m- '.,-
j
in m
X
%, rJh
»C
V
aa/^**
From "Science and Civilisation in
China" by Joseph Needham, r Cam¬
bridge University Press, I9S9.
A CHINESE VIEW OÉ THE EARTH in the mid-17th century is offered by this
page from the Ko Chih Tshao, a rare treatise on astronomy and geography,
by Hsiung-Ming-Yu, which includes a diagram explaining the sphericity of our
planet. Some 16 centuries earlier, a great Chinese astronomer of the Han
Era, Chang Heng, described the heavens as "like a hen's egg and as round as a
crossbow bullet ; the earth is like the yoke of the egg, and lies alone in the
centre". Hsiung Ming-Yu also used the phrase "as round as a crossbow bullet"
to describe the earth, but graduated his sphere into 360 degrees instead of the
365 1 4 degrees used by the Han astronomers. The sphere shows ships ofChinese
rig, pagodas and, at the antipodes, a large European building like a cathedral.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
NEW TRADERS
THE EAST
Left, merchant adven¬
turers dressed in Euro¬
pean costumes of late
16th century disembark
on the coast of Japan
from a Portuguese trad¬
ing vessel. This Japan¬
ese screen painting dates
from the same period.
Below, Portuguese mer¬
chants ride on an ele¬
phant and are carried by
bearers in this detail from
a Japanese screen paint¬
ing. The complete work
shows a ship lying in the
harbour of Goa, the Por¬
tuguese trading settle¬
ment etablished on the
west coast of India, before
setting sail for Japan.
Kobe City Museum, Japan
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
DOES LIFE END
AT SIXTY? I
by Alfred Métraux
MONG the many problems facing our modern
^civilization, the fate of the aged is certainly
one of those foremost in the public mind, judging by the
number of articles on this subject carried by magazines
and newspapers. Over the past century, in fact, the
average life span in industrialized countries has increased
by leaps and bounds until it has now reached 73 years.
This growing percentage of old people in our population
Is a new phenomenon demanding new solutions. After all,
how can we reconcile the very understandable Impatience
of new generations with the enforced retirement of men
and women who still have many years of life ahead of
them and who still feel energetic enough to remain active
far beyond the time limits imposed on them by society.
How can we find occupations for these people whose
physiological age does not correspond to their real age?
Here I do not intend, like so many others before me, to
seek answers to the problems, but rather to describe
briefly some of the attitudes observed in primitive socle-
ties towards elderly persons who can no longer share the
normal activities of their group.
A stubbornly persistent legend still maintains that
many "savage" societies put people with failing strength
to tests in which failure is tantamount to a sentence of
death. It is said, for example, that in the South Seas, old
men of some tribes are forced to climb coconut trees which
are then shaken. Those unable to hang on would thus
inevitably be eliminated. These particular tales are quite
untrue. '
I T is true, however, that among certain peoples
I living under very hard conditions as In the
past among the Eskimos or the inhabitants of Tierra del
Fuego those no longer able to join in the struggle for life
were condemned to death. In such cases it was usually
the individual himself who felt that he had become a
burden. When he realized, through the veiled remarks of
his relatives and friends, that his presence had begun to
20 weigh upon them, he asked to be put to death. With that
extreme discretion so characteristic of the Eskimoes, the
men who decided to die merely stepped off their sledges
WHO photo by Pierre Pittet
without saying a word and stretched out In the snow to
await their end. Or else a member of the family was
asked to put an end to their life. The American anthro¬
pologist, C. Weyer, once met an Eskimo who told him
frankly how he had killed his own father in these cir¬
cumstances. His father had even pointed out the exact
spot where the son was to plunge his knife blade.
Often, too, the aged were imprisoned in an igloo where
they died of cold. Even though these executions were not
condemned by the Eskimoes, they nevertheless gave rise
to signs of remorse. This feeling of guilt is expressed in
Eskimo myths that often tell of the miraculous rescue of
an old person and the punishment of those who had left
him to die.
It would be unjust to consider these peoples, whose
slender resources forced them to get rid of their old people,
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
A PATRIARCHAL SOCIETY. For the Dogons, a tribe which settled on the banks of the Niger
River some 800 years ago, the word of the elders Is law. As in other societies whose traditional
ways of life still hold sway, they revere the head of the family whose authority Is unquestioned.
as cruel or barbarous. One must not forget, that the
question here was a matter of life and death for the entire
group. In most cases, the nomads who applied this harsh
law did so upon the very request of those who could no
longer keep up with the group and who knew that they
were harming it by slowing Its progress. Usually, nomads
would abandon an invalid only after vainly trying to carry
him and not without leaving him a food supply in the
hope of finding him still alive when they returned.
In a comparative study devoted to The Role of Age in
Primitive Societies, Dr. Lee Simmons reached the con¬
clusion that most societies that live by hunting and food
gathering do not neglect their aged who receive their fair
shares of game or fruit.
It is true that "primitives" at this economic level are
more willing to share their wealth than peoples living
from agriculture or grazing. Here, solidarity is the rule
and no exceptions are made for those no longer capable
of participating in the group's activities.
When a Crow Indian hunter on the Great Plains of the
United States killed a large number of buffalo, he would
cry out: "I shall take neither my arrows nor my skins."
Then the meat of the carcasses belonged to the elderly
people who were the "poor" of the tribe. In the same
manner, Creek hunters always set aside a share for the
old people who also knew that no hut in their clan would
be closed to them.
In the past, the Samoans found it difficult to understand
what it meant for a white man to be poor. To them, It
was inconceivable that a person burdened by age could go
hungry and without shelter. In the rural communities
of the Inca Empire, farmers organized working parties to 21
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
DOES LIFE END AT SIXTY (Cont'd)
Living
of the tribes
cultivate land whose produce was reserved for widows,
orphans and old people. Even today, among the descen¬
dants of these same Indians, village solidarity to the
needy is an invariable rule.
It might often be wondered if the lot of the aged in
archaic civilizations is not preferable to what they
experience in our own society. First of all, they do not
feel quite so useless. Even when their declining strength
prevents them from doing their share of the work required
for their community's subsistence, it is easy for them to
find a new role in the group in occupations which, by
common consent, are reserved for them. They become
counselors or helpers. While they may no longer take
the Initiative, they at least co-operate in the work of
others and these new activities, far from being considered
In any way inferior, reward them with the respect and
esteem of their community.
The situation of men considered as tribal elders among
the Cayopos whom I visited a few years ago could not be
described by any stretch of imagination as pitiful. Part
of the "men's house" was set aside for them and there
they manufactured arrows or wove baskets. They kept a
watchful eye on the village and Intervened each time a
quarrel broke out. In addition, they lectured the younger
generations and their speeches, which often went on for
hours, enabled them to evoke epic incidents in their past
lives as hunters or warriors.
In a great many tribes, the most useful artisanal activi¬
ties are the prerogative of the veteran craftsmen. Their
skill, acquired through long experience, assures them
ample customers among the younger men, eager to acquire
tools or weapons.
The National Film
Board of Canada
À
THE PRESTIGE OF AGE. Persistent legends
that aged people in some societies are treated
harshly, even to the point of being put to
death when weakness and infirmity make them
a burden on their community, are discounted
by studies of anthropologists. They have
concluded that most old people are helped
by village or tribal solidarity and In fact are
held In respect and esteem. As custodians of
'ommunities also turn to the aged when they
'need someone to supervise a difficult opera¬
tion, such as the building of a house or a boat. Medicine,
too, is a field in which old people excel. They are reputed
to know the right herbs to treat any sickness and, above
all, the appropriate magic formulae which are no less
indispensable. One has only to recall the extent to
which magic enters into the life of these peoples, to realize
the importance of the elder's knowledge for a tribe or a
village. Hunters, fishermen and even farmers must all
turn to them if they want to be sure of good luck and of
protection against evil influences.
Furthermore, who better than the elders, knows the
tribal rites and the details of ceremonies? They have
witnessed them all their lives and make sure that they
are now carried out in accordance with tradition. The
importance attached by "primitives" to ritualistic details
is well known, and the custodians of these traditions are
the men and women of age and experience.
These people are also the tribe's living archives. It is
their duty to transmit their group's historical myths and
legends to Its young generations. They can also be con¬
sulted not merely on a point of knowledge but to settle
questions of tribal law.
Among the Akambas, an African tribe, anyone in doubt
as to how custom required him to act in any situation
consulted an elder whom he paid. During disputes the
elders were expected to produce legal precedents for
settling these quarrels.
This knowledge and wisdom not only bestows prestige
and status on many elders, but Is also a source of wealth.
For the magic formulae that they chant or the advice they
give, they are paid on the basis of agreed rates.
22 In the case of the Akambas, for example, anyone
wishing to seek an elder's advice does not go to him
empty-handed. He brings with him an ox or, at least, a
goat in payment. The chants, charms and prayers that
the Navaho Indians stored in their memories was literally
a goldmine of knowledge which was a rich source of profit.
Old men shared their knowledge only upon payment of
large sums and it has been said that the sum total of
medical formulae, sacred names, secrets and songs were
worth more than a herd of three thousand animals
sheep, cattle and horses. Any man could thus accumulate,
during his life, the scientific, religious or historical
elements of this oral literature and in his old age use it
for the benefit of others and for his own profit.
The prestige and influence of the aged are so great in
these societies that it would be no exaggeration to describe
them as gerontocracies. The classical example of this
ascendancy of age is offered by the aboriginals of Austra¬
lia. The elders among the bushmen wield almost tyranni¬
cal authority over almost every aspect of tribal life. Often,
they form secret societies whose mysteries are divulged
to young men seeking initiation only at the price of
absolute obedience. Initiation rites so widespread In
primitive societies are usually conducted by elders who
have made them an Instrument of domination.
This gives them control over young men who are made
to pay dearly for the religious privileges bestowed upon
them. In Australia, the elders terrorized the women and
youths by using ritual instruments that made noises like
the roaring of bulls.
According to the British anthropologists, B. Spencer and
S. J. Guillen, the main purpose of certain ceremonies was
to engrave into the minds of youth their obligation to
obey the laws of the tribe and to convince them of the
superiority of the old men who alone knew the ritual of
these ceremonies.
Knud Rasmussen, the Danish explorer, and a perceptive
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
tribal lore, ranging from remedies for sickness
to tribal rites and details of ceremonies, the
elders wield great influence. They are much in
demand for tasks like house and boat-build¬
ing which call for skill and long experience.
With age women too enjoy an enhanced status
and are allowed many privileges normally
reserved for men. Above, eskimo Igloo builder
carves out his Icy bricks in Canada's northern
territories. Right, an aged African woman.
Unesco, Gerda Böhm
interpreter of the life of the Eskimo people, recorded the
following remarks made by the Eskimoes about their
medicine men: "We do not understand hidden things,
but we have faith in those who say that they know them.
We believe in our angakuts, in our magicians... for we
wish to Uve a long time and we do not want to expose
ourselves to the dangers of hunger and poverty. If we
did not follow their advice, we would perish."
North American ethnography brings us countless
examples of respect for the aged. A man, even a young
man, would be called an "elder" as a sign of respect. In
point of fact, this respect was often based on fear. The
elders, after all, were close to those ancestors whom they
would soon join. If they were slighted in any way, they
might well complain to these ancestors who would then
withdraw their protective powers leaving the descendants
exposed to all kinds of dangers.
This, too, was the way the Dahomeians reasoned when
they explained the consideration they showed for old
people. To them, a long life is evidence of divine favour
and proof that a person has been able to gain the good¬
will both of the gods and the spirits. Among the Palungs
in Burma, prestige increases with age so much so that
women even try to pass themselves off as older than
they are.
Not the least of the advantages enjoyed by the aged is
their freedom from numerous taboos. It is widely believed
that those who have reached a ripe old age are immunized
against dangers which taboos are supposed to ward off.
Furthermore, when death draws near, a man has less need
to guard against the perils that threaten youth.
When women reach a certain age, their status tends to
rise to that of men. They are allowed to smoke, to drink
and to use strong language. In New Guinea, they are even
permitted to enter the meeting house of the men. The
myths and legends that make up oral literature also
favour the aged who are readily represented as sages and
as the benefactors of the tribe. The authority of which
they dispose in daily life is reflected in the supernatural
powers attributed to them in the fabulous adventures of
which they are the heroes.
Family ties have always been the safest guarantee of
well-being for the aged. Many societies give elders the
privilege of marrying young women who will take care of
them. Often it is the first wife who feels the burden of
her years and she urges her husband to take a young wife
who will make her work easier. In Australia, the elders
had acquired a monopoly of young women so much so
that young men had trouble finding wives and had to
settle for partners who were much older than themselves.
Within a family, particularly affectionate relations
nearly always exist between grandparents and grandchil¬
dren. For the youngsters the old people appear in a
protective role. Their relations are closer than those
between the children and their parents. Grandparents
are protectors, friends and also playmates. They often
talk to each other as if they belonged to the same genera¬
tion and they do not hesitate to jest and to play jokes on
each other. And this is why the elders prefer to confide
their secrets to their grandchildren rather than to their
sons or daughters.
When we look once more at our own society after this
brief glimpse of the way of Ufe of the aged in primitive
societies, we see more clearly what our technological pro¬
gress has cost us. We certainly live longer than "savages,"
but we have paid a high price for this privilege.
To be respected, to feel one's self a useful and active
member of society, to enjoy the friendship of one's grand¬
children... are not these advantages worth far more than
the comfort offered by our communal homes for the aged
or our "towns for old people?"
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
HOLIDAY CURE
FOR BORED
TEEN-AGERS
by Arthur Gillette
24
THE youth of today is bored. This
is a foregone conclusion of the
Study of the Objectives and Content of
Out-of-School Education that UNESCO
is undertaking in 1963-1964. Young
people in the industrialized countries
are faced with increasing amounts of
ready money and free time and often
find themselves at a loss to put these
to creative use. Growing minds and
muscles seem to lack stimulation in the
atmosphere of material ease prevalent
in Europe and North America, and
untapped energies of young people
from all social backgrounds express
themselves increasingly in acts of
hooliganism and gratuitous violence.
In the developing countries, young
people frequently those who have
attained a relatively high level of edu¬
cation are pouring out of the country¬
side into the cities in search of paying
jobs and the stimulation of urban life.
Many find neither employment nor ex¬
citement and more often than not
spend months, if not years, perfecting
the art of wasting time.
Meanwhile, in all countries, newly
independent and technically advanced
alike, there is no lack of social prob¬
lems which youthful energies could
help solve. In even the wealthiest of
societies the material and, above all,
the psychological needs of certain
groups old people, slum dwellers, the
mentally ill, immigrant labourers, racial
minorities, juvenile delinquents, etc.
go largely unanswered. The needs of
the newly developing countries are
even greater: roads and railways,
schools and community centres,
teachers and technicians the list of
necessities in a modern society.
Here then is the paradoxical situa¬
tion today. On one hand, young people
the world over are at loose ends,
bored, marking time before they gain
the rights and accept the responsibi¬
lities of adulthood. On the other hand,
some of the world's most crying needs
are unheeded. One answer to this
paradox though by no means a pana¬
cea for all today's ills is to yoke rest¬
less youthful energy to these pressing
needs, to give young people the oppor¬
tunity for exciting and creative service.
This is the function of the international
voluntary workcamp movement.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Unesco - Louis van Paridon
Cheerful workcampers prepare for the day's activity on a housing construction project in Waldkappel,
German Federal Republic. This exceptionally large voluntary summer workcamp project was attended
by some 2,500 volunteers who put In a total of over 240,000 working hours on the building sites.
he first "modern" workcamp was held near
Verdun, France, in 1920 when young people
from France, Germany and other nations helped rebuild
war-rravaged farms. The movement has grown, especially
since the second world war, until now each year some two
million volunteers from all continents and most countries
gather for from three to six weeks in camps of five to 200
(the average is 25) to make a personal contribution to
the welfare of their less fortunate neighbours.
During the day there are long hours of hard physical
work: slums are painted in the U.S.A., France and Great
Britain, schools built in Bolivia, Ghana and the Ukraine,
roads laid in Yugoslavia, India and Togo, flood and earth¬
quake damage repaired in Morocco, Chile and the Ger¬
man Federal Republic...
In the evening, guitars, recorders and mouth-organs are
brought out to accompany folk-singing and dancing. Or
else, lively, sometimes heated (and always earnest)
discussions spring up. In some camps, those devoted
specifically to improving Orient-Occident understanding
for instance, lectures and discussions are carefully pre¬
pared in advance, but volunteers everywhere join in with
youthful verve usually tempered by the experience of
trying to do something concrete about the problems they
are discussing.
Whether many nations or different regions of one coun¬
try are represented in a given camp or not there is
never a dearth of topics: the rôle of the developing
countries in the United Nations, abstract art. Eastern
religions, "are workcampers do-gooders with a guilt
complex?", racism, etc.
On weekends there are excursions to points of local
interest, hikes and a chance for the weary to catch up
on 6leep.
A good example of the kind of project undertaken is
the camp that was held a few summers ago at Blitzingen,
a small picturesque village perched high in the Swiss Alps.
Every summer for decades, perhaps centuries, the people
of Blitzingen have carried their cows' milk down miles of
twisting road once or twice a day from their summer
pastures perched 1,200 feet above the village.
As mechanization became widespread in Swiss dairies,
Blitzingers could no longer compete; the young people of
the village began to move away arid Blitzingen seemed
doomed to wither and die. Then 20 young workcampers
representing several nations and races came to help. For
about a month they worked side by side with the villagers
who had remained and laid a plastic pipe down the moun¬
tainside. Now the milk comes down from the summer
pasture in six minutes (instead of three hours) and Blit-
zingen, encouraged, is beginning to revive.
As well as short-term service there also exist oppor¬
tunities for experienced volunteers to do long-term
(6 months to two years) workcamping, primarily in Asia,
Africa and Latin America. Long-term volunteers are
putting their knowledge and experience to work trans¬
forming the slums of New Delhi, preparing a student-run
literacy campaign in Bolivia, helping refugees in Morocco
and Austria.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
CURE FOR BOREDOM (Cont'd)
Vacation time, gay but useful
In one typical long-term project, Nicole Leymann, a
young French social worker, and Max Hildesheim, a Bel¬
gian architect, spent a year in Togo, helping to strength¬
en the activities of the Togolese workcamp organiza¬
tion "Les Volontaires au Travail." Nicole had the special
task of Interesting Togolese women in literacy, home-
making and other educational activities of the workcamp
group, while Max worked together with local development
officers to encourage young village men to build schools,
dig wells, surface roads and accomplish other projects.
The main aim of the work done by Nicole and Max,
was to make young Togolese aware of their own
constructive potential and to teach them the techniques
which will enable them to put their potential to
work. Now back in Europe, Nicole and Max agree
that they learned as much as they taught. Their
year of service was not a one-way flow of information
from the "developed" to the "developing" countries but
rather a truly human exchange.
At present, long and short-term workcamp projects
are run by some 250 organizations located in more than
50 countries throughout the world; there are small, large,
regional, national, international, Buddhist, Catholic,
Jewish, Muslim, Protestant, non-religious, governmental,
non-governmental, political and apolitical organizations
involved.
The most active of these (80 at the time of writing)
are grouped in the Co-ordination Committee for Inter¬
national Voluntary Workcamps, a supra-national, non¬
governmental organization located in Paris, to which
Unesco has granted Consultative Status. The work
of the Committee (whose Secretariat is staffed by long-
term volunteers) includes publicity and co-ordination
of workcamp activities as well as several Major Projects.
(For news of the latest project, see page 34.)
Hard physical effort of the kind furnished by these
volunteers in England is combined with lectures,
discussions and other educational activities in work¬
camp projects now run by over 250 organizations in
more than 50countrlesforover 2,000,OOOvolunteers.
Unesco
26
Weht ' > "y
One of these, provides young people from Eastern
Europe and Western Europe with an opportunity to
labour, play and live together in voluntary work camps,
to get acquainted with one another as individuals in an
atmosphere of common effort. To date, they have worked
together in camps in France, the German Democratic
Republic, Poland, Sweden, the U.S.S.R. and Yugoslavia.
Another Major Project of the Co-ordination Committee
is the organization of regional training courses for
prospective workcamp leaders in the developing countries.
In many of these countries workcamp movements
already exist; but expansion of their activities demands
leaders and there are simply not enough experienced
qualified leaders to go around. Without solid leadership,
the energy and purpose of these new movements would
be wasted.
he Co-ordination Committee tries to remedy
this situation by organizing, in collaboration
with local workcamp groups, regional leader training pro¬
jects. So far, four projects have been organized in South
East Asia (three in India and one in Pakistan), three in
Africa (Ghana, Togo and the U.A.R.) and one in Latin
America (Paraguay). In each project between 30 and
50 trainees, sponsored by local workamp and other youth
organizations, divide their time between theoretical
sessions (talks and discussions led by workcamp and
community development specialists) and practical phy¬
sical labour (building schools, digging wells, etc.).
As a result of this combination, future leaders come
to feel the exicitement of workcamping and, at the same
time, learn how to put their newly acquired techniques
into practice. Through these regional training projects,
which are generously supported by individuals and
groups who contribute through the Unesco Gift Coupon
System, voluntary workcamping has been strengthened
in countries where it existed and spread to new areas.
At the First Latin American Training Project, for
example, 29 young people from eight countries came
together in the village of Primavera, Alta Paraguay, in
early 1961 for a month's intensive instruction by several
experts from the Americas and Europe. As a practical
project, they added a wing to a rural hospital.
Typical of the trainees was Jaime Reyes Mérida, Gen¬
eral Secretary of the Bolivian University Confederation.
Soon after his return to La Paz from Paraguay, Jaime
and other student leaders began making careful plans
for a literacy campaign, in which student volunteers
would serve as teachers of reading and writing and
builders of schools and literacy centres. With the help
of Unesco, interested workcamp organizations in Europe
and international student groups, this campaign was put
into action.
This activity and growing interest in voluntary service
projects is now being "boosted" by the second Latin
American Training Project which takes place in Sucre,
Bolivia, from March 15 to April 13. This project combines
the hard practical work of building a university literacy
training centre with a period of intensive study of the
techniques of organizing workcamps. Some 30 volun¬
teers from 9 countries in Latin America now working and
studying together will return after the training project
to use their new-found knowledge in their own countries.
It would, of course, be unrealistic to expect all young
people everywhere to be interested in giving their free
time to physically strenuous voluntary service activities.
Yet, each year, more and more discover that work¬
camping is a means of doing something practical about
the world's problems, of bridging the political, social,
racial and other chasms that divide men, in short, of
building peace. This is certainly one answer to the
boredom of today's youth.
A
Arthur Gillette, of the United States, is General Secretary of the
Co-ordination Committee for International Voluntary Workcamps,
in Paris. A specialist in the organization of volunteer training pro¬
grammes in developing countries, he is at present in Bolivia helping
to organize the Second Latin American Training Project.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
DRUMBEATS CALL
TOGO
VOLUNTEERS
TO WORK
"
In the newly-developing nations of Africa,
the International Voluntary Workcamp Move¬
ment has done much to guide and encourage
work on community development projects.
In the Republic of Togo, for example, a young
French social worker spent a year assisting
the local workcamp organization, Les Volon¬
taires au travail, her special task being to inte¬
rest Togolese women in literacy, home-making
and other educational activities. A Belgian
architect worked with local development
officers to encourage young village men to
build schools, dig wells and surface roads. Left,
volunteer builders working to the sound of
drumbeats are constructing a pre-natal clinic
In the Togo Republic. Below, another Togo
volunteer group thatches a newly-built home.
Photos© Paul Almasy, Paris
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
THE HIDDEN FACE OF THE CINEMA (4)
CENSORSHIP
A double-edged weapon
by Paul Léglise
In a series of articles based on a world survey of the cinema, (See
The Unesco Courier, Dec. 1962 and Jan. and Feb. 1963) Paul Léglise
dealt with some of the lesser-known aspects of what might be termed
the "private life" of the cinema industry, from production to distribu¬
tion and presentation. But films have also a collective life, control¬
led by institutions and laws. Here, M. Léglise discusses censorship
problems and the growing importance of films for young people.
Doll actors fight a duel
for love of a lady in a
puppet film version of
Shakespeare's "A Mid¬
summer Night's Dream",
produced by the Czech
puppeteer Jiri Trnka.
Filmexport, Prague
film is a collective work subect to precise
i economic imperatives and made to satisfy
cultural needs. Because of these characteristics it
demands the creation in every country of an institution
to co-ordinate, promote, control, guide and arbitrate the
affairs of the national cinema industry.
The actual forms taken- by such institutions can vary
greatly. In one country the nationalization of industries
puts authority into the hands of the State. In another,
professional organizations join forces to create an organ¬
ization which handles the general problems of the cinema
industry. Under other arrangements some affairs remain
in the hands of the State while others are dealt with by
the film-makers themselves.
Already in the early days of the cinema, film makers
formed associations not only to look after their pro¬
fessional Interests, but also to co-ordinate and syste¬
matize techniques and working methods. Soon they were
joined by other groups whose prime interest was in the
cultural problems of the cinema.
Today all these organizations have an important func¬
tion in every country, representing the interests of the
cinema industry in its relations with the public authori¬
ties. Sometimes a professional organization takes over the
affairs of the industry in its own country and becomes
responsible for negotiations with those of other countries.
The United States is a typical example of this "self
government in business."
Other groups concerned with the cultural problems of
the cinema in turn affiliate themselves with international
bodies having similar aims, such as the International
Federation of Film Societies, the International Scientific
Film Association, the International Centre of Films for
28 Children, the International Committee for Film Education
and Culture, the International Experimental and Art Film
Theatres Confederation, the International Council for
Educational Films, the International Art Film Federation,
the International Catholic Film Office, the International
Amateur Film Union, the International Animated Film
Association and so on.
Among the laws that affect the, cinema industry cer¬
tainly the most controversial are those relating to cen¬
sorship. A subject which constantly preoccupies film
makers, censorship is the cinema problem that comes
up for discussion most often of all. It is one that can be
argued about endlessly. Sometimes it Is simply referred
to as "control," either to distinguish it from official
censorship in which direct power is held and exercised
by a government, or simply for euphemistic reasons which,
In any case, deceive no one.
Every country provides for the maintenance of law,
order and public decency in the general body of its laws
and it thus seems somewhat pointless to introduce special
legislation applying only to films. Justification for censor¬
ship, however, has been based on the immense influence
which films have on the public and this has led to abusive
or haphazard application to films of laws relating to public
order and morality.
The cinema industry needs protection against the con¬
fused and incoherent use of such laws on a local level,
and a national censorship of films thus offers a safeguard
against such excesses.
It thus comes as no surprise to find the cinema industry
itself demanding that a system of censorship be set up or
even deciding to establish one under its own responsibility.
The purpose here is to prevent the blocking of commercial
distribution through contradictory censorship decisions
that may easily vary between different areas of the same
country and even between one city and another. A central
censorship authority is, in fact, an economic necessity.
"The kind of censorship does not matter," wrote a French
film-maker in 1919, "as long as it is a centralized one."
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
This need for a centralized control is amply illustrated
by the case of the United States. Although the Tariff Act
forbids the importation of any film that incites people to
subversion or acts against the government of the United
States and proscribes the entry of anything immoral or
obscene, there is no federal censorship.
Some local authorities, however, possess wide dis¬
cretionary powers. Five States Kansas, Maryland, New
York, Pennsylvania and Virginia have established censor¬
ship systems, and in several others censorship even
operates on the municipal level.
Faced by such a lack of legislative uniformity, it is
hardly surprising that the Motion Picture Producers and
Distributors of America decided to set up a Production
Code intended for general application and seeking to
establish some measure of uniformity in an otherwise
confused mass of criteria. The Code, in fact, represents
the unifying force in the organization of the American
film industry. Its creation only serves to emphasise its
necessity, for economic reasons alone, to the film industry.
All the American producers and the importers of pro¬
ductions from abroad can submit their films to the Pro¬
duction Code Administration (PCA) for approval.
Scenarios of U.S. films submitted for PCA approval are
examined carefully and in controversial cases PCA mem¬
bers may decide to watch the shooting of certain scenes.
In any case, PCA approval is given only to completed
films. Where films have not been submitted for approval,
is nothing to prevent their being shown in
specialized cinemas, but the normal channels of distribu¬
tion for the commercial circuits are to all intents barred
to them. Though the PCA mark of approval has no actual
legal value it is a significant fact that films bearing it are
exempted from municipal censorship in many cities. This
alone would seem to justify its existence.
Similar kinds of- systems are found in some other
countries: The British Board of Film Censors (United
Kingdom), the Freiwillige Selbskontrolle der Filmwirt¬
schaft (German Federal Republic) and the Administra¬
tion Commission of Motion Picture Code of Ethics (Japan),
to name but three.
In Great Britain the British Board of Film Censors
delivers three types of certificates to approved films: "U,"
meaning suitable for general release; "A," more suitable
for adult than juvenile audiences, and "X," for adult
audiences only.
In the German Federal Republic there is close collabo¬
ration between the authorities and the FSK (the organ¬
ization named above). There is actually no censorship in
the Republic although a 1957 law requires authorization
for the screening of films to audiences of young people in
three age categories: less than 12, 16 and 18 years of age.
All the States of the Republic have agreed to abide by the
decisions of the self-created voluntary censorship service
of the country's cinema industry.
All these self-censorship institutions operate on the basis
of a production code which defines the kinds of scenes
regarded as improper: certain aspects of crime and bru¬
tality, vulgarity in dialogue, indecent or obscene passages
and things likely to give offence to national sentiments or
religious beliefs.
In the United Kingdom there is no written code. The
British Board of Film Censors prefers to judge each film
on its individual merits and to take all aspects of the
work Into account.
In cases where institutions of this kind do not exist or
where film censorship authority is not vested exclusively
in the municipal authorities as it is in the case of Bolivia
and Ecuador, for example what other systems do we find
in operation: full freedom or rigorous control? The
answer: widely varying degrees of censorship extending
between two extremes.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
1 1 Zy u..
A Unesco-
Hungarian
co-production
on the history
of numbers
In prehistoric times, the extent of the
cave man's conception of numbers was
"one", "two" and "many". One day he
began to realize that "two" is always
"two" no matter what it describes...
... and he then made the second basic
discovery: the representation of ideas
by symbols. Now he has started to
keep a record of his hunting bag by
means of notches he cuts in his club.
3 1 S ( *
0
9 -lo
ïïîï
fiMM i*» »O -J
In Egypt, arithmetic was used for land
measuring, construction and book-keep¬
ing. Here ancient Egyptians show how
to calculate proportions of a right-
angled triangle with a knotted cord.
By the position of the numerical symbols
they used, the Babylonians develop
their number system. The same symbol,
by a use of repetition, can be employed
to signify 1 or 60 or 60 x 60, and so on.
Wise men of India meet to decide on
numerological symbols. They agree on
numbers running from 1 to 9 (basis of
our present numbers). But something
is missing. At last they find it: the zero.
i\>\
^RABl^
AL6ORIÏM0Ï
ALGfJEA
From India, Arab men of learning bor¬
rowed the numerical symbols (now
completed by the zero). One of them
was soon to give a striking new im¬
petus to the science of mathematics.
This man was AI Khowarizmi. One of
his works entitled "Al-jebr w'al muqa-
balah" has given us the word "algebra".
The term "Logarithm" is said to be a
distortion of this Arab author's name.
Moving across North Africa, algebra
eventually reached Spain. Soon it be
came ah intrinsic part of mathematics
that were taught in Spain's universities
whose fame spread throughout Europe.
CINEMA (Cont'd;
Freedom but not licence
30
The first of these extremes Is In the Kingdom of Saudi
Arabia, where not only film production but also any com¬
merce in films is strictly prohibited. Only diplomatic
missions and a few foreign organizations are allowed to
screen films ' and these performances must be strictly
private.
The other extreme Is the Republic of Argentina. Article
22 of an Argentine law passed in 1957 declares that anyone
interfering with the freedom of expression of the cinema
in any way whatsoever, applying censorship or preventing
the free movement and screening of films is liable to a
prison sentence of from one to six months.
Does this prohibition of censorship by law mean that
no control whatever exists in Argentina? No! For
freedom does not mean licence to do anything one
pleases.
An Argentine decree of 1961 has somewhat reduced the
scope of the earlier law. The new text specifies a number
of things whose presentation on the screen can give rise
to legal action: offences against decency, things offensive
to religious beliefs or to other races or foreign countries;
vindications of crime, dishonesty, immorality or violence.
Despite these far-reaching modifications, Article 22 of the
original Argentine law is still in force. Control of films is
now therefore guaranteed and carried out under the
powers of judicial authority.
One aspect of the censorship problem the admission of
children to certain film shows still preoccupies many
authorities and even the Argentine Republic has decided
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
ur cave man has learned his first lesson
arithmetic: "two" and "two" make
ur. He has already started down the
>ad of abstract ideas. Then one day
i slips and falls flat in a muddy pool.
Furious and dripping with water he
goes to wipe his muddy hands on a rock.
His misfortune is really a blessing in
disguise for it gives him the means to
make a new and important discovery.
Gazing at his finger marks on the rock
he counts: "One handfive fingers ;
two handsten fingers". Man's ten fing¬
ers thus became the basis for the foun¬
dation of the decimal system of today.
These drawings are reproduced
from a Hungarofilm-Unesco co-
production entitled "1, 2, 3..." in
which animated cartoon techniques
give charm and humour to thé
history of mathematics (in capsule
form) and show the contributions
of Orient and Occident to Its
evolution. This colour film was
made by a team of Hungarian ani¬
mators, Gyula Macskassy and Gyorgy
Varnai. Films by Gyula Macskassy
received the best cartoon awards
at the Karlovy Vary Festival in
1960 and the 1961 Cannes Festival.
Unesco photos
2 J-£~c
The Greeks showed genius in analyzing
many fundamental ideas of mathema¬
tics. Here Pythagorus demonstrates his
now famous theorem on the squares
of the sides of a right-angled triangle.
Roman numerals were hardly designed
for simple and rapid calculations and
the Romans were obliged to make use
of the abacus, a simple calculating mach¬
ine, consisting of beads sliding on wires.
t/NIVE
1-0
&)
I=1-Z.
W®'
Students, monks, and scholars came
to be initiated in this new branch of
science "from the Orient." AI Khowa-
rizmi's "Algebra" was widely translated
by medieval scholars and won renown.
The science of numbers spread like wild¬
fire across Europe where each succeed¬
ing generation of scholars and scientists
carried it one step further towards its
present-day breadth and complexity.
A universal legacy, mathematics is a
science in itself and the to.ol of all other
sciences. It is also a vast and interna¬
tional language in which scientists of
all lands can speak and be understood.
not to leave Its solution to an application of general laws,
even when these have been specially amended. The 1957
law in Argentina was modified in this connexion later the
same year. The new text stipulates that the National
Institute of Cinematography must issue a prior certificate
of approval to Argentine and foreign productions, and
empowers It to classify films as being unsuitable for young
people under the age of 18. Local authorities have the
right to prohibit the admission of minors to the perfor¬
mances of such films.
The moral protection of youth is, in fact, another reason
offered for the maintenance of censorship. Conjointly
with the threat of repressive action by local authorities,
this new principle, today written into the laws of most
countries, often raises a barrier to another long-estab¬
lished principle: freedom of expression.
Belgium has found a way out of this dilemma with a
solution that is both original and ingenious. It has no
general censorship to block the free movement of films,
but admission to cinemas is forbidden to young people
under the age of 16. A control commission has been set
up with a mandate that is clear and precise: it gives
approval for certain films to be shown to children and
thus attenuates the stringency of general censorship.
Another system long in use is a governmental author¬
ization given on the advice and judgment of a special
commission composed of educationalists, psychologists,
doctors, magistrates and other competent authorities.
The universal and controversial problem of censorship
is one with which countries with socialist economies have
also to come to grips. In Poland, for example, a decree
of 1945 (modified in 1952 and 1953) created a central office
for the control of the press, publications and entertain¬
ments. Its purpose is to prevent the diffusion of any
written, auditory or visual matter considered to be
against the interests of the State or infringing law or
morality. A Ministry of Education committee views each
film and decides at what age children may see it.
As the production and the distribution of films in a
Socialist country are both nationalized activities, it is a
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
CINEMA (Cont'd )
A growing industry: films for the young
normal and general rule for a control to be effected
through the choice of subject matter for films or of films
themselves in cases where they are imported.
It is all too easy to criticise and poke fun at film cen¬
sorship. But its roots are deeply and tenaciously
engrained and it would be idle to hope for their eli¬
mination in the near future. Far better to admit, even
unwillingly, that there is still some justification for
censorship.
The acceptance of this fact in no way prevents us
from denouncing and exposing the abuses of censorship
or its hypocritical use, so as to prevent its extension
beyond admissible bounds. Nor is this attitude likely to
prejudice in any way a progressive advance to the day
when everyone will regard films in the same way as all
other major forms of expression, subject solely to the
general laws of a country and answerable, if need should
arise, to a court of justice.
In bridging the gap that still separates us from such
a happy state of affairs, an important role will fall to
the educational and cultural aspects of the cinema. This
movement has, in fact, already begun and most govern¬
ments have shown that they are ready to take positive
action by using the cinema for educational and cultural
goals.
There exists, no doubt, a certain long-standing mistrust
on the part of some authorities and a disparity between
needs and resources, but it is certain that national
authorities everywhere are giving increasing attention to
the possibilities of educational films. In many cases a
special service attached to the ministry of education
takes charge of film production and distribution and
supplies equipment. Two examples are the Cinemato¬
graphic Service of the Belgian Ministry of Education
and the National Pedagogical Institute in France. Not
all such 'institutions are governmental in origin.
Frequently an autonomous institution produces films and
other audio-visual materials for educational use and
trains special staff in their uses .
In this field valuable international co-ordination is ef¬
fected by the International Council for Educational Films
founded in 1952 and now grouping 23 countries which
encourages exchanges, and acts as a catalyzing agency
by stimulating co-productions between different countries.
Other specialized organizations encourage action on a
regional basis. One of these is the Latin American Ins¬
titute for Educational Films, set up by the Mexican
Government in collaboration with Unesco. It arranges
reciprocal exchanges, the training of staff and the pro¬
duction and distribution of films in Latin America.
Apart from its role in the educational film field, govern¬
ment action often extends into the production and dis¬
tribution of cultural and scientific films, especially short
length ones. Sometimes a special body is set up to act
as co-ordlnator for the film activities of all its country's
ministeries and to negotiate with private film companies
on behalf of the State. Examples of this kind include
France's National Cinematographic Centre, Britain's
Central Office of Information and the Information Film
Section in the Republic of South Africa.
IIn France the funds allocated by the State for
the production and distribution of short-length
cultural films an activity co-ordinated by the National
Cinematographic Centre annually amount to 10 million
francs. In the United Kingdom, the Central Office of
Information is each year responsible for the production
of some 50 films destined for both commercial and non¬
commercial channels, a further 100 for overseas TV
transmission and also short films for TV and newsreel use.
Another Increasing trend today is the setting up of
official agencies responsible for film production on behalf
of the State. These include the National Film Board of
Canada, the Dansk Kulturfilm and Ministeruerhes Film-
ydvag in Denmark, the Aengencia Nacional in Brazil
oo Spain's No-Do, Morocco's Cinematographic Centre and
National Film Units in Australia, India, New Zealand
and Malaya.
These organizations do not necessarily hold the exclu¬
sive monopoly of film orders for the state. They are
generally concerned with news-film production and,
depending on which country they are in, have a more or
less indirect share in the production of other kinds of
films, either using their own technical staffs or calling
on private film companies to do the work.
India's Films Division, for instance, produces a news-
film and several documentaries each week. The Canadian
National Film Board each year distributes its productions
(1960-1961 figures) in over 70 countries.
Similar organizations equipped to prepare and produce
educational, scientific and cultural films exist in the
countries with socialist economies. In the Soviet Union,
popular science films are produced in studios at Moscow,
Leningrad, Sverdlovsk, Kiev, Tbilissi, Minsk and Tash¬
kent. In Czechoslovakia, documentary films are produced
in Prague, popular science and educational films in Brno
and Prague, and children's films in Gottwaldow.
Annual production of short films, documentaries and
popular science films in the Soviet Union is about 750.
In 1959, 377 similar films were produced in Czechoslo¬
vakia, whose Gottwaldow studios produce between 80 and
100 films for children each year.
This global production of cultural films finds some
outlet through normal cinema channels, but it is chiefly
distributed through specialized "non-commercial" cir¬
cuits.
B:.EFORE leaving the subject of cultural films
'mention should be made of developments in
the production of films for young people. In an earlier
reference to censorship, we emphasized how a growing
concern for the moral protection of youth was being
written into the laws of many countries to an extent
where it threatened to nullify the long-standing principle
of freedom of expression.
However, negative action with regard to films is today
being offset by positive measures which encourage the
development of films especially designed for juvenile
audiences. These include subsidies, special reduced prices,
bonuses, the waiving of taxes and the creation of
specialized production studios and distribution channels.
Under the impulse of the International Centre of Films
for Children in Brussels, measures are now being worked
out to encourage international co-productions and film
exchanges. Though, this is a long-term project some of
its positive results can already be seen.
The International Centre of Films for Children was
created under the sponsorship of Unesco and its members
include international organizations and national groups
which are working to develop the movement for chil¬
dren's films in their respective countries. Priority is
given to international film exchanges, but the Centre is
also working to bring about a greater freedom of circula¬
tion for films intended for juvenile spectators.
Mention is made of these activities in this context to
show how some groups and organizations are demonstrat¬
ing convincingly that outdated and negative forms of
censorship can be counteracted, and are recognizing the
positive role that the cinema can fill for teen-agers.
Delegates to a conference on the development of infor¬
mation media in Latin America, held in Santiago de
Chile in 1961, noted that in the field of films for youth
there existed "a regrettable apathy, often resulting from
a shortage of funds but chiefly due to an absence of
organizations working to highlight the need for this kind
of film and to encourage its production."
If these facts are evident in Latin America, they are
also reflected in the situation existing in most other parts
of the world. Thus we must look to the International
Centre in Brussels for a lead In stimulating the creation
in all parts of the world of national centres whose aim is
to work for this worthwhile cause.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
LOST HYMNS OF GEORGIA
Sir,
I have read the letters by Alberto
Hemsi and Bathja Bayer (Octo¬
ber 1962 issue) dealing with my article
on the "Lost Hymns of Georgia".
(May issue). ,
The composer, Mr. Hemsi, while
welcoming the solving of the mystery
of ancient Georgian music, would like
me to explain "the problems of the
rhythm and duration of sound with
the same precision that the details of
the pitch arid subsequent pattern of
tones have been outlined."
Obviously, it was impossible for me,
within the scope of a brief article, to
treat in detail all the aspects of the
decipherment of the old Georgian mu¬
sical notation. In a somewhat enlarg¬
ed Georgian version of the article
these detailed aspects have been dis¬
cussed.
Replying to the two questions rais¬
ed by Mr. Hemsi:
1. The rhythm of old Georgian
chants corresponds exactly to the me-
trorhythmical structure of the ver¬
sified texts of the hymns.
2. The problem of duration of
sound. Ancient Georgian religious
singing, as ancient Christian music
in general, is the so-called cantus pla¬
nus ("plain chant", or to use the old
Georgian term "corresponsive" sing¬
ing).
Religious vocal music was aimed
at conveying the texts of the hymns
to the listeners without obscuring the
meaning, and so the syllabes of the
text of the hymns were for the most
part of even duration (musical "chro-
nos protos" a half note in slow time,
a quarter note in quick time.)
Augmentation and diminution of
duration were indicated by signs (repe¬
tition of notes, signs of jubilation.)
Instructions as to the manner of
performance, tempo and dynamic col¬
ouring of separate chants and groups
of hymns are given in Ancient Geor¬
gian synaxaries, indicating the calen¬
dar regulations as to their perfor¬
mance.
My synthesizing work on "The De¬
ciphering of Ancient and Mediaeval
Georgian Musical Notation (with spe¬
cimens of deciphered texts)" in Geor¬
gian, Russian and English, is schedul¬
ed to come off the press in 1963-64.
Those interested will find in it a cir¬
cumstantial account of Ancient Geor¬
gian music, as well as the detailed nar¬
ration of all the aspects of its decipher¬
ment.
I now pass to the questions raised
by Mr. Bayer, who, while agreeing
with the fundamental thesis of my
deciphering, considers it necessary to
touch upon a few details which do
not, as he himself observes, affect the
main points of- the problem. He be¬
lieves that the names of some musi¬
cal instruments, a photograph of which
appears with my article, are not given
quite correctly. "Mostly the transla¬
tor and not the author, seems to have
been at fault" adds Mr. Bayer. In
this he is right. A comparison with
the Georgian original of my article
(published Aug. 23 and 24 in the Geor¬
gian press) will show at once that not
one of the terms in question figures
in the Georgian original.
Though for the most part
Mr. Bayer's remarks are correct some
of . them are not. The thirteenth-
century Georgian miniature under
discussion (Page 24 of The Unesco
Courier) represents an orchestra of
four instruments. Mr. Bayer is
inclined to think that the third instru¬
ment of this orchestra "'is more
probably a trumpet of sorts." This is
not so. The two Georgian terms for
it are "stviri" and "nai". These terms
(especially the latter), as well as
references as to the composition of
such orchestras preserved in Georgian
sources, show that the instrument in
question is a variety of flute. Thus
the name in the text in The Unesco
Courier is correct.
Mr. Bayer also points out that the
practice of writing down polyphonic
chants in Western music dates from
the 9th contury, and not from the
13th. As is well known, only the
first relatively crude attempts at sim¬
ple polyphony (or rather diaphony)
date from the 9th century. And even
afterwards in the following centuries
when polyphony was undergoing fur¬
ther development in the West, the
chief melody, cantus firmus, was
usually written down while the accom¬
panying voices were written down
only sporadically in exceptional cases
(they were sung according to worked
out norms). The practice of writing
down the accompanying voices along
with the cantus firmus became general
comparatively late, from the 13 th cen¬
tury.
With this I conclude my brief notes,
especially since Mr. Bayer's remarks
refer only to the details, and accord¬
ing to his own summing up "the great
value of Dr. Ingorokva's communica¬
tion of course remains unaffected in
principle."
In conclusion allow me to express
my sincere gratitude to The Unesco
Courier and to the authors of the
letters, for the interest they have
shown in the cultural heritage of my
native land Georgia, a country of an¬
cient culture.
Pavle Ingorokva
Tbilisi, Georgia, U.S.S.R.
DEVELOPMENT IN ISRAEL
Sir,
You have published admirable arti¬
cles on ethnological and artistic sub¬
jects and interesting studies which have
brought readers into touch with Asian
and African peoples. But there is
also a small nation, Israel, which, in
the face of many difficulties, has cul¬
tivated and developed its lands. I am
not well acquainted with this country,
but I know that in place of rocks and
stones, there is now wheat, where
there were once tracks there are now
spacious highways and where tumble¬
down huts once stood, modern build
ings have risen. In the place of mules,
primitive presses, shepherd boys and
darkness, there are now automobiles,
.factories, doctors and light. This
little country is not well known. Why
not devote some pages in your maga¬
zine to this courageous, hardworking
and intelligent people?
Paul Jaume
Coursan, France
WHAT TEACHERS
SHOULD READ
Sir,
In reply to Dr. Sten Rodhe (Too
Heavy for Teacher, October 1962), I
too am a "busy" teacher of primary
children, but I find time to read the
articles in The Unesco Courier be¬
cause I find them stimulating and inte¬
resting; also the illustrations are excel¬
lent; some of these I can make use of
in my class work. I don't think that
teachers should only read "what can
be used directly in their teaching",
surely some time can be found to go
beyond that.
Judith Myrtle
Kelowna, B.C. Canada
TEMPLE AT JOCJACARTA
Sir,
The text of the cover photo of the
December issue of The Unesco Cou¬
rier comments on details of a bas
relief of a gallery of the Temple of
Shiva, near Djakarta, Indonesia.
Actually this Temple of Shiva is the
Loro Jonggrang-temple of the Pram-
banan-complex near Jocjakarta (Cen¬
tral-Java). Djakarta is the capital of
Indonesia whereas Jocjacarta is the
centre of the old Javanese culture.
The Prambanan-complex is situated
to the southeast of the famous Bud¬
dhist Borobudur-temple. Since 1961
the epic of the Ramayana is enacted
in the Prambanan-compounds with
each full moon. Thousands of foreign
tourists have watched these Ramaya-
na-ballet-performances with the Loro-
Jonggrang as the background of the
play.
Licm Tiong Gie
Singaradja (Bali)
MORE PLACE TO SCIENCE
Sir,
Would it be possible to increase the
scientific features, both in number and
in contents? I am fully aware of the
fact that The Unesco Courier is read
by all sorts of persons, and that there¬
fore it cannot become a science peri¬
odical, apart from the fact that there
are already many other periodicals of
that sort. Still, I believe that more
emphasis on new discoveries and new
horizons opened by contemporary
science would be of interest. This,
however, should absolutely never go
to detriment of the extremely good
artistic features which appear. The
ones on archaeology, in particular, are
of the highest level.
Andrea Larsen
Rome, Italy
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
"¡\TEWS AGENCIES FOR AFRICA:
Upper Volta is shortly to have its
own national news agency, for whose staff
a training seminar was recently organized
by a Unesco specialist at Ouagadougou, the
capital. Other newly-independent French-
speaking African States which have set up
their own news agencies (some with help
from Unesco experts) include Cameroun,
Dahomey, Guinea, Ivory Coast, Mada¬
gascar, Mali and Senegal...
ANY CLIMATE YOU WISH. A
£A600,000 installation for plant
research, now operating in Canberra, is
capable of producing almost every known
type of climatic condition. Many hundreds
of plant growth experiments can be car¬
ried out simultaneously in this phytotron
which is an important Australian contri¬
bution to world efforts aimed at increas¬
ing food production.
UNESCO CLUBS HELP IRAN'S
BLIND: Unesco Gift Coupons total¬
ling $4,000 which can be used to buy
books and educational materials were
recently presented to the Nur-Ayin school
for the blind at Isfahan in Iran. The
gift is part of a sum collected through a
campaign organized by the French National
Commission for Unesco and the French
Federation of Unesco Clubs to help blind
children in many parts of the world.
ALL THE WORLD'S MUSIC: All
musical works, in printed or manu¬
script form, written before 1800 are to be
listed in a 50-volume inventory now being
prepared by libraries in 20 countries. Five
volumes are already published or are being
printed. The International Musicological
Society and the International Association
of Music Libraries are working on this
project with aid from Unesco and from
American foundations.
SWEDISH TECHNICAL AID: Three
new Swedish schools for vocational
training in East Pakistan, Liberia and
Lebanon are to start operating this year,
reports the Swedish Agency for Interna¬
tional Assistance (NIB) in a survey of its
1963 activities. One of them, an institute
in Siblin, Lebanon, for training instruc¬
tors, foremen and technicians, is Sweden's
contribution to the work of UNRWA, the
United Nations organization helping Arab
refugees.
||OM£WORK FOR TEACHERS: Bri-
" tish teachers make use of TV pro¬
grammes in school but usually only have
time to follow those dealing with their
own field. To give teachers a complete
view of the possibilities of educational TV,
British networks put out special pro¬
grammes for teachers during the Christmas
holidays. Teachers in schools not yet
34 equipped with TV were able to make
their own estimates of the value of such
services.
AFRICAN TEXTBOOK CENTRE: A
centre for the production of school
textbooks has been set up at Yaounde in
Cameroun with Unesco assistance. It is
to produce reading primers, textbooks for
citizenship education, geography and his¬
tory, reading texts for adults, literacy
booklets, leaflets and posters. It will serve
the Cameroun and also four neighbouring
countries: the Central African Republic,
Congo (Brazzaville), Gabon and Chad.
WARSAW'S POLYGLOT SCHOOLS:
Since the start of the present school
year foreign language teaching in two
secondary schools has been applied to other
subjects in the school curriculum and spe¬
cial daily conversation classes have been
started. This is the first step towards the
creation of four schools in Warsaw where
teaching will be conducted in French and
German and, later, in English and Russian.
]^TUCLEAR MEDICAL CENTRE: Five
-^ hundred research workers are to staff
the new Institute of Nuclear Medi¬
cine, set up by the Soviet Academy of
Medical Sciences to develop all aspects
of the application of isotopes ' and radio¬
active methods in the treatment and pre¬
vention of disease.
TALK ABOUT STORMS. Building
research engineers from eight coun¬
tries will attend the first international
conference on the effects of wind on build¬
ings and other structures, to be held at
the British National Physical Laboratory
at Teddington, near London, in June.
Subjects to be discussed include the effect
of sudden gusts of wind on various kinds
of structures and also wind tunnel techni¬
ques developed for their investigation.
GAS UNDER THE CHANNEL: The
possibility of carrying supplies of
natural gas from recently discovered fields
in the Netherlands by undersea pipe to
Great Britain is now being studied. Ano¬
ther possible future use of pipelines dealt
with in a paper on this subject presented
to the Royal Society of Arts, in London,
was for the movement of pulverised coal
by pipeline.
OPPORTUNITIES FOR SERVICE: A
special bulletin listing opportunities
open for skilled long term volunteers
who wish to work in the world's developing
countries is now being published by the
Co-ordination Committee for International
Voluntary Workcamps, 6, rue Franklin,
Paris 16". Produced in co-operation with
the Mass Communication Department of
Unesco, this three-weekly bulletin (available
to volunteer organizations) is the most
recent major project of the workcamp
movement, which has also . recently
published a survey of the real heeds for
volunteer workers in 20 countries.
FILMS & SOCIAL SCIENCE: An
international study of the social reality
of our time as seen in the images presented
by films has been published by Unesco (*).
Its author, Luc de Heusch, professor at the
Free University of Brussels, has analyzed
documentary films from many countries
from the viewpoint of their use for
sociological research and training, the term
sociology being taken to include social
psychology and cultural anthropology.
(*) "The Cinema and Social Science", by Luc
de Heusch (Reports and Papers in the Social
Sciences'), Unesco, Paris. Price : S 1.00 ; 5/ - ;
3,50 F.
F/ashes .
UNICEFthe United Nations Chil¬
dren's Fund allocated $38.7 million to
helping children and mothers in develop¬
ing countries last year its largest contri¬
bution since 1950. For every $1.00 from
UNICEF, receiving countries committed
more than $2.50.
Soviet geologists report following last
year's cruise of the research vessel "Vityaz"
that in a vast volcanic plateau on the Paci¬
fic Ocean bed there are iron and manganese
deposits far richer than any revealed on
the world's continents.
International training facilities for jour¬
nalists and broadcasters will be provided
by the Thomson Foundation, a newly-
created £5,000,000 trust. It will provide
a residential training centre for young
journalists in England and a training centre
in Scotland for men who will run new
TV services in developing countries.
The world's lowest death rate is in the
Canal Zone of Panama which, according
to a World Health Organization survey
covering 1950-1960, had only 3.6 deaths
per 1,000 population. Lowest mortality
rates in Europe were in the Faroe Islands
7.1, Iceland, 7.2 and the Netherlands, 7.6
deaths per 1,000 inhabitants.
UNESCO PHILATELIC SERVICE
The second 1963 U.N. commemorative stamp, issued
last month, salutes the World Freedom from Hunger
-"; «AClOMfiS UNIDAS _ , , , , i i i k l l- I I A It
Campaign launched by the U.N. Food and Agriculture
Organization. (During World-Freedom-from Hunger
Week the last week in March over 140 countries
issued special commemorative stamps). The U.N.
stamp is issued in 5 cent and 11 cent denominations.
As agent in France of the U.N. Postal Administration,
Unesco's. Philatelic Service stocks all the U.N.
stamps and first-day covers currently on sale, and
those issued by Unesco member states to comme¬
morate important events in the history of Unesco
and the U.N. For prices and further details write to The Unesco Philatelic Service,
Place de Fontenoy, Paris (7e).
FREEDOM FROM HUXiHt
«»HttïHM
U
z
<
o
z
<
u
a
O
LU
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
No. 4 1962 UNESCO PERIODICALS
Economics
of education
Published quarterly io/-(stg.) 6NF
Impact deals with the social aspects
of science and technology, with
subjects concerning relations bet¬
ween science and governments and
problems of scientific organization.
It ¡s a quarterly for all thoughtful
persons in all walks of life who are
interested in scientific progress and
the advancement of society. Annual
subscription: 9/6; $1.75.
International Social Science Jour¬
nal. The most comprehensive inter¬
national journal of its kind because
of its interdisciplinary approach:
sociology, political science, law,
demography, anthropology, etc. In
each number it brings a series of
original studies on a subject selected
on account of its international impact
or its bearing on current research,
accompanied with news on research
institutes, international meetings.
(Quarterly).
Annual subscription: 32/6; $6.50.
international
journal
of adult
and youth
education
u n c 1 c o vol. xiv (1962) no. 4
International Journal of Adult
and Youth Education. A quar¬
terly technical journal intended mainly
for specialists in fundamental and
adult education, which contains ar¬
ticles describing important activi¬
ties in this field and information
concerning programmes and general
lines of policy.
Annual subscription: 7/6; $1.50.
Where to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; rates quoted are
for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO COU¬
RIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuza?, Press Department, Royal
Afghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Melbourne University Press, 369 Lonsdale Street,
Melbourne, C. I., Victoria. (A. 15/-). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C°., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Sch. 60.-). BELGIUM. Editions " Labor ",
342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-Boek-
handel, Belgiëlei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (100 FB) and art slides only: Louis de Lannoy,
22, place de Brouckère, Brussels. CCP 3380.00.
BURMA. Burma Translation Society, 3 61 Prome Road,
Rangoon. (K. 5.50). CANADA. Queen's Printer,
Ottawa, Ont. ($ 3.00). CEYLON. The Associated
Newspapers of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Colombo, 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99 Chungking South
Rd., Section 1, Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa). CUBA.
Librería Económica, Pte Zayas 505-7, Apartado 113,
Havana. (2.25 pesos). CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia
Ltd., 30 Ve Smeckich, Prague 2. DENMARK. Ejnar
Munksgaard, A/S Tidsskriftafdelingen, Prags Boulevard 47
Copenhagen S (D.kr. 12). ETHIOPIA. International
Press Agency. P.O. Box 1 20. Addis Ababa. FINLAND.
Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
(Fmk. 540). FRANCE. Librairie de I'Unesco, Place
de Fontenoy, Paris-7'. CCP. 12598-48. (7 F.).
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg Verlag, Rosens-
heimer Strasse 145, Munich. For the Unesco Kurier
(German ed. only) Bahren-felder-Chaussee 160,
Hamburg-Bahrenfeld.C.CP. 276650 (DM 8). GHANA
Methodist Book Depot Ltd. Atlantis House, Commercial
St., POB 100, Cape Coast. BRITAIN. See
United Kingdom. GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann,
28, rue du Stade, Athens. HONG-KONG. Swindon
Book Co.. 64, Nathan Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY.
Kultura, P.O. Box 149. Budapest, 62. INDIA. Orient
Longmans Ltd. Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay 1; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; Gun-
foundry Road, Hyderabad, 1 ; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/1 Asaf Ali Road, P.O. Box 386, New
Delhi, 1 ; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.,
17 Park Street, Calcutta 16, Scindia House, New Delhi.
Indian National Commission for Co-operation with
Unesco, Ministry of Education, New Delhi 3. (Rs. 7).
INDONESIA. P. N. Fadjar Bhakti, Djalan
Nusantara 22, Djakarta. IRAQ. Mackenzie's
Bookshop, Baghdad. IRELAND. The National Press,
2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd., 35, Allenby
Road and 48, Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv( 1 £ 5.50).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour
Street, Kingston. Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
(10/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-Nichome,
Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605 Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
(Yen 670). JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman.
KENYA. E.S.A. Bookshop, P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole
and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LUXEMBURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue,
Luxemburg. MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications Ltd., Times House,
River Valley Rd., Singapore (M. S 500) MALTA.
Sapienza's Library 26 Kingsway, Valetta. (10/-).
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon
Street, Port-Louis. British Library, 30 Bid
des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (7 NF.). NETHERLANDS.
N. V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague,
(fl. 6). NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES. G. C. T.
Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.) N.V., Willemstad, Curacao
NEW ZEALAND Government Printing Office
Wellington, and Government Bookshops, Auckland,
Wellington, Christchurch. Dunedin (10/-). NIGERIA.
C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box 174, Lagos. (10/-). NOR
WAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille Grense. 7, Oslo
For the Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Litteratur
Tjeneste, Stortingsgt. 4, Oslo, Postboks 1 1 5 (kr 13.20
PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing Cor
Ltd., Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box 374, 56-N
Gulberg Industrial Colony, Lahore. PANAMA.
Cultural Panameña, Avenida 7a, No. TI-49, Apartado
de Correos 2018, Panama, D.F. (Balboas 3-). PHI¬
LIPPINES. The Modern Book Co., 508 Rizal Avenue
Manila. POLAND. " RUCH " ul. Wiloza Nr. 46,
Warsaw 10 (Zl. 50). PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada
Lda, Livraria Portugal, Rua do C&rmo 70, Lisbon.
RHODESIA & NYASALAND. The Book Centre, First
Street, Salisbury, Southern Rhodesia. SUDAN. AI
Bashir Bookshop, P. O, Box 1118, Khartoum. SWEDEN.
A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2,
Stockholm. For The Unesco Courier: Svenska Unes-
coràdet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stockholm, C (Kr. 7.50);
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse
Zurich. Payot. 40, rue du Marché, Geneva. CCP.
1-236, " Courier " only: Georges Losmaz, 1, rue des
Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CCP. 1-4811. (Fr. S. 8).
TANGANYIKA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B.
9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND. Suksapan
Panit, Mansion 9, Ra|damnern Avenue, Bangkok. (3 5
ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda
Bookshop. P.O. Box 145, Kampala. UNION OF
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Bookstore, Libri
Building, Church Street, Pretoria. For the Unesco Cou¬
rier (single copies) only: Central News Agency, P.O.
Box 1033, Johannesburg. (10/-). UNITED ARAB
REPUBLIC (EGYPT). La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh.
Adly-Pasha, Cairo. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M.
Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I. (10/-).
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications Center,
801 Third Avenue, New York, 22, N.Y. (S 5.00.)
and (except periodicals): Columbia University Press,
2960 Broadway, New York, 27 .N.Y. U.S.S.R. Mez-
hdunarodnaja Kniga, Moscow. G-200.YUGOSLAVIA.
Yugoslovenska Knjïga, Teraziie 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
SUMMER
HOLIDAY
WITH A
PURPOSE
© Paul Almasy, Paris
Since its inception in 1920, the International Voli
tary Workcamp Movement has grown into a world¬
wide operation of building for peace. Each year
over 2,000,000 volunteers step forward to work
e by side in workcamp projects from India to
Bolivia and from the Ukraine to Morocco (see
story page 24). Above, international workcamp¬
ers on a summer construction site in France.
]]>
</page>
</document>
