<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="062706eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
^^^^ A WINDOW OPEN ON THE W
Courie
I YEAR) - PRICE 1/-STG. (U. K.). - 30 CENTS (CANADA.) - 0.70 F (FRANCI
*
«~	 -
/ X
-
.:
i Vi
SAFETY"
FIRST
AT SEA /" v-
* ' " **M,
m
\
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
**
***** ^^w*¿4-J ******* ********
*** v*»*******«**: < ******* '****
?**/******** «*r*****V *******
- **** * :- uk- *v** ***iî*5** **?
»-**-.V;*v*
¡t£** *********
,-
t***W*V*V*f <
*****"* SKI
a*********';^^
U*****»/**** MÜMIták' '
»"MP»" » * \ ¡4&
******,) ******
V*******<4*V fe \ *y*V*í*
^* . - v**.
«
V*VV*V^V****
**w#v>"'*n**» *********** ********
***' ._. ****-******* ******* **
******
******* ********** ******** ********* ******* *
****** ******** ******** ******** ***********
********* ******* ********* x******** *****
>^
********* ; ******* --¿mm**
***** **********]
# *******
1*******
******'
******!
*****
******* ******* <0
****************
**%**** ***
*****'$, *5 f i *****
^*v***r
*V*'.*#******** ' -"</fJ
Ut\ ^»\% *******
^^***v *v***r ;/v**w***** ***V*****
I*******,**» ***^r**>V*^>.- < -*r***r**>
i *
/******** ******** *********** ^******v** ******
*^**** *<5******^*í' W*** *ÍÍt* ***** ********* ********* **********
MOSAICS
OF ANCIENT
TUNISIA
© Unesco
The art of mosaic work which flourished at the time of the Roman Empire is a mirror
of life and beliefs in the Ancient World, from hunting scenes to mythology and from
religious rites to secular games. In Tunisia numerous pavement mosaics have
been uncovered. A collection of some of the most striking is now offered in "Tuni¬
sia: Ancient Mosaics", the 18th volume in the Unesco World Art Series. This de¬
tail of a fishing scene (3rd cent. A.D.) is in the Susa Museum, Tunisia. Published by
the New York Graphic Society by arrangement with Unesco, this album, printed
in Italy, has 32 full-page colour reproductions and is priced at $18.00 or equivalent.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
ê ariNeOW Orl« ON INI aOlll
ner
MAY 1963
16TH YEAR
Contents
No. 5
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
COVER PHOTO
Fires aboard ship have always
been one of the greatest
hazards faced by the seafarer.
Research Into ways of impro¬
ving safety equipment carried
by ships has produced these
awesome-looking fireproof
asbestos suits for fire
fighters. (Story on Safety
First at Sea, page 4)
U.S. Navy
Page
4 FOR THOSE IN PERIL ON THE SEA
A world-wide network for maritime safety
By David Woodward
10 A LOOK AT WORLD CO-OPERATION IN SCIENCE
By N.M. Sissakian
17 STAINED GLASS-400 YEARS IN ONE FAMILY
A great artistic craft in the shadow of Reims cathedral
Photo-story by Paul Almasy
21 THE USELESS BARRIERS
The Hidden Face of the Cinema (5)
By Paul Léglise
25 OPERATION 'NORDESTE*
Brazil's bold programme in the hunger campaign
By Josué de Castro
30 STAMPS AGAINST HUNGER
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
(MC. «1.1.180 A)
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7', France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
René Caloz
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani (Moscow)
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Italian Edition : Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemln
Scientific and Cultural
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except In July and August when
it is bi-monthly (1 I issues l year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German.
Arabic, Japanese, and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed by H.M.
Stationary Office, P. O. Box 549, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re*
printed must bear author's. name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Uneaco Courier la Indexed monthly In The Readera' Guide to
Periodical Literature published by H. W. Wilaon Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates: IO/-stg. ; $3.00 (Canada) ; 7.00
French Francs or equivalent. Single copies I /-stg. 30
cents ; 0.70 F.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7\
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
FOR THOSE IN PERIL
ON THE SEA
by David Woodward
a
i üRiNc the years 1960 and 1961 nearly 200 ships,
totalling more than three quarters of a million
gross tons, were lost at sea. The exact figures were
114 ships of 418,195 tons in 1960 and 78 ships of 355,362
tons In 1961. But while details are available for ships of
a certain size only vessels over 500 tons are Included In
the figures given above it ls quite impossible to obtain
precise figures for small craft or the loss of life by
drowning.
The most nearly authoritative guesses speak of about
200,000 lives lost annually In every kind of drowning acci¬
dent from a collision between passenger liners in the
North Atlantic to the destruction of scores of tiny fishing
vessels and their crews by a typhoon in the Far East.
Accidents at sea are thus so numerous that the dead go
unnumbered. The sea is still cruel and there are times
when even the best-found, best-handled ship is at its
mercy.
To prevent folly or greed from jeopardizing ships and
the lives of seafarers, regulations have existed since Noah
limited the passenger capacity of the Ark. The Greeks
and Romans established regular laws. Emerging from the
Middle Ages, 600 years ago, the English and the French
made laws to regulate the traffic by sea; already in the
Twelfth Century, the Crusaders, using mostly Italian ships,
had marked on the sides of their craft a cross, the arms
of which Indicated the maximum depth to which the ship
might be loaded. The mark of the Crusaders made its
way with the flow of trade to the Baltic and within a
hundred years it had been adopted by the merchants of
Vlsby on the Swedish island of Gotland.
This use of a load line was of course on the same prin¬
ciple as the famous Plimsoll line adopted by British
shipping in 1876 after a tremendous battle in Parliament.
Plimsoll himself was by no means careful of the accuracy
of the charges which he flung about the House of Com¬
mons. But fundamentally, he was right. Many men were
being sent to sea in overloaded or inadequate ships for
the sake of gain; such ships were too often disaster-prone
in bad weather. When Britain stipulated that her ships
should not be overloaded, the British Government also
laid down that foreign ships using British ports should
conform to the same regulations.
The problem of safety at sea had become especially
grave by the nineteenth century because of the great
development in world trade and because Iron steamships
could sustain greater hazards than wooden sailing ships.
However, for centuries before the Industrial Revolution,
the training of sea captains, pilots and seamen had been
an object of concern to the principal maritime powers.
Henry the Navigator of Portugal had, perhaps, first of all,
This is how a German
artist, Willy Stcewer,
visualized the nightmare
of April 15, 1912, as
panic-stricken survivors
struggled to get away
from the rapidly-sink¬
ing "Titanic" after it
crashed head-on into an
iceberg. Only 711 people
were saved. The death
toll was 1,517. This
tragedy eventually
brought about measures
to promote safety at sea,
including the setting up
of iceberg patrols and
stringent regulations
about the proper num¬
ber and proper equip¬
ment of lifeboats to be
carried by all vessels.
© UPI
tried to systematize these matters ; the Emperor Charles V
had followed his example, and Henry VIII of England
founded the establishment known as the Brethren of Tri¬
nity House which, to this day, controls lights and pilotage
matters in British waters. In France and the Low Coun¬
tries, similar arrangements date from the sixteenth
century.
Nevertheless, much more than that was needed for the
training of seafarers in the first half of the nineteenth
century. The Foreign Office in London, through its
consuls abroad, began a long agitation to raise the
standards of conduct and technical proficiency In the
British merchant service not only for humanitarian
reasons but for economic ones as well. The consul at Riga
reported in 1843:
"Foreign shipmasters are generally a more respectable
and sober class of men than the British. I have always
been convinced... that British shipowners... are great
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
losers írom the serious delays occasioned while on the
voyage and discharging and taking in cargoes, growing out
of the incapacity of their shipmasters and their intem¬
perate habits. I have had occasion to remark... that
American vessels, in particular, will make three voyages to
two of a British vessel, in this way having an Immense
advantage over their competitor" (1).
Developments in the field of trade and in naval con¬
struction had brought increased problems to the seafarer,
but at the end of the nineteenth century developments In
telecommunications more than redressed the balance.
Nevertheless, when radio telegraphy was first Introduced,
it began in a state of confusion. Ships and shore stations
were often fitted with different types of equipment
operated by different companies. Competition became so
keen that the employees of one radio company would not
handle the traffic of another; sometimes they would even
jam rival signals or broadcast abuse of each other. It
took two big International conferences held at Berlin In
1903 and 1906 to bring some order to the situation and to
secure an acceptable agreement between the various
countries.
A little later, in 1909, came the first use of wireless tele¬
graphy to summon aid to a vessel in distress, when the
White Star liner Republic was sunk in collision off
Nantucket. A young man who was the ship's radio opera¬
tor made history and a name for himself by sticking to
his post and summoning aid which was brought by ships
of five different nationalities. These immediate replies to
the Republic's distress signals were an extension of the
unwritten law of the sea whereby a response must be
given to appeals for help. There is also a material side,
since the first ship to answer effectively an appeal for
help may be able to earn her owners and crew very con¬
siderable sums for salvage.
(1) Seafarers and Their Ships, London, H.M.S.O., 1955, p. 22. 5
CONT'D ON NEXT PACE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
PERIL ON THE SEA (Cont'd)
Lessons of the Titanic'
The original radio distress call had been the letters
CQDCome Quick Dangerbut by 1912, this had been
changed by international agreement to SOS not because
those letters stand for anything, but because the com¬
bination of three dots, three dashes, three dots in Morse
code was judged to be especially ear-catching. The signal
is sent "SOSOSOS..." while a lesser degree of emergency
is signified by the letters "TTT." Much later, with the
over advent of radio telephony, the phrase "May Day"
(from the French m'aidez) was used for a spoken, as
opposed to a Morse appeal for help.
Three years after the loss of the Republic came the
sinking of the Titanic, perhaps the greatest peacetime sea
disaster in history.
Even after fifty years crowded with terrible events, the
story of this disaster still has power to horrify. In 1912,
when the nations had experienced no world war for
almost a hundred years, it came as a blow so shocking
that it made men doubt the whole order in which they
lived.
Briefly, four vital factors had caused the disaster and
the enormous loss of life which accompanied it. They
were :
The failure of the iceberg warning measures.
Insufficient life boats to hold all the passengers and
crew.
Poor water-tight compartmentation, so that the ship
flooded easily, and
Confusion over radio traffic, which hampered recep¬
tion of the Titanic's SOS.
A conference of the principal sea-faring powers was
convened in London during the winter of 1913-14 to deal
with these points on an international basis. Although the
agreements were never officially ratified, because of the
outbreak of World War I, they did bit by bit come off the
conference table and begin to shape the lives of those
who worked or travelled by sea.
First and foremost of these agreements was the for¬
mation of the North Atlantic Ice Patrol. This was set up
by the United States Coast Guard with international
financial support and functions to this day, using ships
and aircraft to spot dangerous icebergs.
The Titanic's boats held only 1,178 people, and the ship
had on board at the time over 2,200 people. In fact owing
to the difficulty of loading and handling the boats, not
more than 700 actually found places in the boats, and
1,517 people lost their lives, hundreds of them not
drowned, but found next morning floating in their life
jackets, frozen to death in the icy waters.
Accordingly, "boats for all" became a popular slogan,
and the 1913-14 conference laid great stress on these
being provided in the future perhaps too much stress,
because there are many occasions upon which a ship sinks
so fast that there is no time to complete the launching
of boats, and extra life rafts would be more valuable than
boats.
Regulations were also proposed by the Conference to
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
o upi
Improve the standard of water-tight compartmentation,
and also to diminish confusion over radio messages
warnings of Icebergs had failed to reach the Titanic's cap¬
tain, and his SOS went unheeded by a ship within sight
of the lights of the stricken liner, because her radio
operator had gone to bed.
At the conclusion of World War I and with the creation
of the International Labour Organisation (ILO) In Gen¬
eva, another approach was made to the question of safety
of life at sea. The ILO's principal preoccupation was
with working conditions and hours, but their immediate
relevance to safety may be seen when efficiency ls con¬
sidered in terms of a well-fed, well-rested and healthy
crew compared with one which ls not.
Crowded forecastles, where men sleep In damp straw,
eat badly-cooked mixtures of food from a single dish,
after it has been carried from the galley across an open
half-deck, where there ls a struggle to dry soaked clothing
and as hard a struggle to get sufficient fresh water, are
not quite a thing of the past. But the picture is certainly
brighter than It was thirty years ago and International
action can take much credit for the Improvements that
have been made.
While the conference room has thus been productive
of reform at its own tempo over the past four decades, the
laboratory and the electrical workshop have within the
past 15 years or so provided a series of revolutions of their
own in the field of maritime safety. At the end of both
world wars, international co-operation at sea on a large
scale was necessary to sweep the hundreds of thousands
of mines laid by both sides.
In between 1914 and 1918 some 240.000 mines were laid,
while that figure was nearly doubled in the Second World
War. The mines were most thickly strewn In European
waters and in the three years after V-E-day, 1,900 mine¬
sweepers took three years to sweep safe channels of some
125,000 miles. In theory, these mines become useless after
a period of years, but no chances can be taken. After all,
live mines from the Russo-Japanese war of 1904-5 were
still being reported in the 1930's.
Some wartime developments for detecting ships and air¬
craft have resulted in entirely new devices which have
revolutionized navigation, especially in dangerous waters.
Nor is there any sign of this process of change being com¬
plete future developments. It would seem, will be just
as far-reaching as those which have occurred since 1945.
Radar and Its refinements have combined to offer solu¬
tions to a great many of the mariner's safety problems,
although they have In turn set problems of their own.
Briefly, radar's supersonic electrical impulses, reflected
off objects which they strike above the surface of the sea,
reveal the presence In fog or darkness of rocks, other
ships or other obstacles. At the same time, the electric
Impulses of asdic or sonar can reveal the depth of the
sea and the presence of submerged obstacles.
These new sciences are still in their Infancy. Refine¬
ments of radar are now being developed whereby stations 7
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
PERIL ON THE SEA (Cont'd)
World network for
safety at sea
ashore and on board a ship, working together in coastal
waters, can indicate a ship's position as a tiny disc of
light on her own chart. Experts point out, however, that
these and other devices are only aids to navigation, and
that the first line of defence against disaster is the mari¬
ner himself, his eyes and his brain.
The precision of such developments is such that the
suggestion has now been put forward that In crowded
waters and fog the seaman's worst enemy the move¬
ments of ships should be controlled from the shore in the
same manner that the landings and take-offs of aircraft
are controlled from the ground. The traditional indepen¬
dence of ship-masters is likely to give this proposal a
discouraging reception but as traffic grows, it may be
necessary to Impose it, nevertheless. It Is at any rate
a far cry from the fog-horn hitherto the only aid to
safety and navigation in thick weather.
A similar measure of control which has been proposed
is the introduction of a kind of one-way traffic system
In the Straits of Dover, whereby west-bound ships use
one channel and east-bound ships another. The Straits
are still the busiest sea lane in the world, with 750 ships
passing every day.
usis
Tiny white specks in the sea
are actually massive icebergs
those in the centre are excep¬
tionally large onesthat have
"calved" from 'the glacier seen
in this aerial photograph taken
off the east coast of Green¬
land. These ice-islands become
deadly serious maritime hazards
when they drift southwards into
the Atlantic shipping lanes. But
ships and aircraft of the North
Atlantic Ice Patrol are on the
watch and warn shipping of
the presence of the icebergs.
Somewhere at sea a ship is in
distress. Out goes an SOS and
other ships change course to
bring help. Here a U.S. Coast¬
guard patrol boat picks up sur¬
vivors of a vessel lost in a hur¬
ricane. To reach the ship¬
wreck it braved waves 60 feet
high and winds of 90 m.p.h.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
© French Polar Expeditions Paul-EmMe Victor
IMCO, to which this proposal has been referred, Is the
Inter-Governmental Maritime Consultative Organization
which was set up in London in 1959 as the maritime
agency of the United Nations. In Its first four years of
existence, more than 50 nations with most of the world's
shipping, have become members. One of its main tasks
ls to place the international work on safety of life at
sea on a permanent basis, which was hitherto the task
of international conferences summoned from time to
time at sporadic intervals. The first such conference was
that already mentioned after the Titanic disaster in
1914-15; two more followed In 1929 and 1948.
However, IMCO's concern is not only with the safety
of life at sea; the agency also deals with discriminatory
actions and restrictive practices in the field of shipping,
organizes the exchange of information between govern¬
ments and considers any maritime question that may be
referred to it by the United Nations or by any of the
other specialized agencies.
In May and June 1960, IMCO held a conference in
London on the safety of life at sea, at which fifty-four
nations were represented. This meeting thrashed out the
technical aspects and drew up a new Convention which
included up-to-date provisions on the use of radar and
modern types of life-saving equipment. The safety of
nuclear-powered ships, signalling, fire-fighting, electrical
equipment and collision regulations were all included in
the final Convention. The measures adopted represented
another step forward to reduce the risks run by sea¬
farers.
But in the struggle with the sea there can be no final
victory. Vigilance, courage and ingenuity are always
required. International regulation and electronic inven¬
tion can strengthen these qualities, but are no substi¬
tutes for them. A note of the grim reality which lies
behind IMCO's work was provided recently by that
organization's request to the World Health Organization
to set up an expert committee to investigate the contro¬
versial problem of whether shipwrecked mariners should,
in an emergency, drink sea water. The experts unani¬
mously decided against such a remedy, despite recent
claims that this is one way in which the castaway can
prolong his life.
David Woodward is a documentary writer-producer
the British Broadcasting Corporation, London.
for
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
A BIOLOGIST
LOOKS AT
WORLD CO-OPERATION
SCIENCE
by Norair^ Martirosovich Sissakian
V,
' "I llll "j|j '
~^
10
usis
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
THE FISHERMAN'S
FRIEND: The chemist,
the biologist, the geolo¬
gist and the physicist
are all keenly Interested
in the sea today and
international co-opera¬
tive research In these
fields ls growing. Efforts
to Increase our food
supply from the oceans
depend not only on the
fisherman but the marine
biologist. Here scien¬
tists on the deck of an
océanographie research
vessel are seen gathering
microscopic specimens
from the sea in the course
of a research cruise.
National Institute of Oceanosraphy, Great Britain
J TjST as life itself depends on biological exchange
for its normal development, so science needs
the exchange of ideas, methods and principles for its own
enrichment and to strengthen the control of man over
nature. Perhaps nowhere does the need for scientific co¬
operation on an international basis emerge with such
clarity as in the field of biology, or, putting it more
broadly, in the field of life sciences.
This co-operation is all the more Indispensable as,
within present-day natural sciences, the biological
sciences are progressively assuming an ever-larger place ;
the part they play in the promotion of welfare for all
mankind is becoming more and more influential. If we
consider the matter in its broadest perspective, mankind
is faced with a number of vitally Important problems,
which we cannot afford to ignore.
With steadily widening economic, scientific and cultural
contacts between peoples, I believe the foremost obliga¬
tion of scientists is the unification of creative efforts for
the successful elaboration of the following scientific
problems:
Assurance of unlimited resources of energy for the use
of mankind;
Enlargement of food resources to meet the needs of
all peoples of the globe in foods of full nutritive value ;
Elimination of all infectious diseases and the creation
of material and hygienic conditions for longevity, along
with conservation of vigour, capacity for work, and
physiological activity at a sufficiently high level;
Exploration of other worlds of the universe, the un¬
derstanding of their laws and the utilization of these
for the welfare of all mankind.
These problems of science, which concern all
humanity, Inspire the scientists of the whole worldthose
true scientists for whom the great power of science must
serve exclusively the Interests of peace, friendship and
happiness of all people. These Ideas and problems must
and should, I believe, serve as a basis for the organization
of international scientific co-operation.
In this respect, we have positive experience to work on.
The co-operation of scientists In the programme of the
International Geophysical Year, the creative work of
scientists from several countries In the Antarctic, the
beginning of large-scale research on marine life within
the framework of Unesco, the experience gained as a
result of mutual agreements on scientific co-operation
among many countries of the world all this represents
an important contribution to mutual understanding and
co-operation between peoples.
International scientific co-operation may be realized in
various ways and at various levels. In particular, the
organization of International symposiums and widely rep¬
resentative scientific meetings can do much In this res¬
pect. For example, the International Biochemical
Congress held In Moscow in August 1961 proved to be a
magnificent forum for the biochemists of the world.
If the problems of securing permanently available
energy resources for all of mankind must be solved by the
efforts of physicists and power specialists, the other prob¬
lems which I have listed will have to be dealt with by
representatives of an intricate complex of biological
sciences.
A number of important problems may be cited which, in ^
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
SCIENTIFIC CO-OPERATION (Cont'd)
my view, may serve as a basis for international co-opera¬
tion:
The study of forms of life, of laws of reproduction and
the increase in biological productivity of the world's
oceans;
Elucidation of the nature of photosynthesis so as to be
able to reproduce this truly cosmic process otherwise
than in chlorophyllous plant life;
The multi-disciplinary study of the brain.
The study and the utilization of the world's oceans,
like meteorological and geophysical research, is the most
appropriate and the most necessary form of international
scientific co-operation.
The ocean Is the largest integral natural object on our
planet, in which all processes and phenomena are Inter¬
dependent and lnterdetermined. The study of the ocean
calls for co-ordinated research In several disciplines such
as physics, chemistry, biology and geology.
he scientific study of the ocean and of the
problems of its practical utilization must be
treated as a single coherent entity. There must be
no schism whatsoever between theoretical Investigation
and practical problems.
Studies of the physical processes in the watery mass of
the ocean and the interaction between it and the
atmosphere will bring solutions to many problems concern¬
ing navigation, climatic forecasting and the utilization
of the power resources of ocean waters. Chemical and
geological studies of the ocean will lead to the
utilization of its mineral resources; the geological
findings will also result in important progress in
navigation and port-building. Bio-oceanological re¬
search ls necessary for the full and rational utilization
of the vital resources of oceans and for the solution of
navigation problems. A fuller knowledge of the ocean will
help us to develop rational means of protecting the ocean
from pollution, from the deterioration of its biological
resources, and from dangers to the health of mankind.
The present rapid development of such studies is
explained by the fact that this branch of science and its
practical aspects lagged behind others in the past, as well
as by the application of many new methods of research
and the realization of the tremendous scope and signifi¬
cance, from both theoretical and practical viewpoints, of
the perspectives of scientific and economic mastery of the
global ocean.
In working out an International programme for bio¬
logical Investigation of the ocean, the international study
of the Indian Ocean which was started in 1959 and which
should continue for the next 3 to 5 years under the joint
supervision of SCOR (Scientific Committee for Oceanic
Research) and Unesco must be taken Into account because
of its great importance. Yet these investigations should
in no way impede the development of general interna¬
tional research in oceanography within the programme of
the Intergovernmental Océanographie Commission, one of
whose tasks ls to determine the character and intensity
of biological processes which take place in various parts
of the global ocean In other words, to elucidate all aspects
of the biological structure of the ocean.
CONT'D ON PAGE 14
© E. Aubert de la Rue
GIANT
MARINE PLANTS
& PYGMY
The tiniest of seaplants
are mostly invisible to
the naked eye. Their
hidden beauty, however,
is revealed by micro-
photography, through
whose penetrating eye
the cluster of common
algae (right) is seen to
resemble a delicate fan
richly studded with gems.
Fronds of giant seaweed
(left) line the banks of
a fjord on the Kerguelen
Islands in the Antarctic.
Seaweeds have long been
used as a source of
iodine and vegetable gela¬
tin and many kinds are
eaten directly because
they are a rich source of
vitamins and minerals.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
13
USIS
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
direction of wind
-*
SCIENTIFIC CO-OPERATION (Cont'd;
Mysteries of photosynthesis
The basic task of marine research must be the study
of the character and tempo of biological productivity at
various latitudes and In various parts of the global ocean,
the qualitative and quantitative structure of its plant and
animal life and their biological peculiarities. The process
of production undergoes regular changes according to the
physical and chemical conditions experienced in the
various geographical zones; from pole to pole, from the
shores to the central parts of the ocean, and from its
surface to its depths, the quantitative changes may vary
a hundred-, a thousand-, and a hundred-thousand-fold.
The International programme of biological reseach must
Include the study of plant and animal organisms as
possible carriers and concentrators of radioactive waste
matter, and the phenomena of biocirculation as one way
by which such matter may be dispersed in the ocean.
he biological data thus obtained must form
the oceanological basis for the recognition and
evaluation of fish and other kinds of resources in regions
whose resources have so far been barely used or left
completely untouched. Nevertheless, the tremendous
amount of information collected by international océano¬
graphie programmes should not be kept separate from
practical considerations, such as those which affect the
fishing industry. In no case should incomplete utilization
be permitted of the data obtained In the investigation of
the ocean, for such data can be of use to various branches
of economy, including the fishing industry.
Today the photosynthesis of plants (in which the plants
perform the primary synthesis of organic substances and
store the energy from solar radiation) ls practically the
only primary source of food for all living organisms on
earth, including man.
There ls no doubt that in the future, too, the decisive
role in this area will be played by the natural photo¬
synthesis of plants, for only the cultivation of highly
j 4 productive plants over tremendous territories can guar¬
antee the abundance of food needed for the world's
population no matter what its size, and can satisfy the
needs and tastes of man in respect of the composition
and variety of such food supplies.
At present, the green plants of the globe create through
photosynthesis hundreds of times more organic substances
than are needed as food by the population of the Earth.
Even so, the problem of food resources Is one of the most
acute problems of contemporary mankind. This problem
has social and biological-technical aspects.
For example more than 90 per cent of photosynthetic
production occurs in the plants of seas and oceans and of
forests and prairies, yet the percentage of this production
used for food is extremely low (about 0.02). Cultivated
plants produce only 10 per cent of the total photosynthetic
production, but the proportion of utilization of this pro¬
duction for food is high: the cultivated food and fodder
plants yield not less than 80 percent of the food used by
human beings.
Nevertheless, this production does not fully satisfy the
food requirements of mankind. Furthermore, to the prob¬
lem of assuring food supplies of the requisite nutritive
value for present generations must be added that of
providing for the constant growth of the population. For,
after all, It is the potential products of photosynthesis and
the extent to which mankind can utilize these products
for food that will determine the population potential of
the globe and its standard of living.
For this reason, the photosynthesis of plants, the in¬
crease of photosynthetic production and the control of
plant photosynthesis as a source of food are among the
most important problems of mankind.
The adequate, rapid and most advantageous solution of
the problem of photosynthesis in the above context
depends to a large degree on the co-ordination of research
on an international scale. Let us consider the following
examples:
# According to contemporary calculations which,
however, are neither precise nor final about 80 per cent
of the total photosynthetic production of plants of the
globe is carried out by the photosynthesizlng organisms
of seas and oceans (mainly unicellular seaweeds).
CONT'D ON PAGE 16
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
___ WËÊÊÊk
Painting by David Pratt repro¬
duced from the book "Oceans",
produced and © by Geographi¬
cal Productions Ltd., and pub¬
lished by Paul Hamlyn, London
(50/-); U. S. edition entitled
"Seas. Maps and Men", pub¬
lished by Doubleday (S9.95).
LIFE LINES IN THE SEA
Present knowledge of large parts of the oceans is still pitifully small.
Only within the past few decades have we begun to understand some
of the processes taking place in their depths. The most important of
these from man's viewpoint, since it affects the food harvests from the
sea, is the cycle of food chains shown here in coastal and oceanic waters.
(1) As marine animals die and decompose, their remains sink to the
deeps and are reduced into salts by bacteria. (Creatures shown at the
bottom are "garbage eaters" only found in the depths of the ocean.)
Upwelling of deep waters returns the salts to the surface where (2)
floating masses of microscopic green plants (phytoplankton) turn them
into food by photosynthesis through the light of the sun. This "grass"
of the sea is then eaten (3) by the smallest floating animals and these in
turn become food for "carnivorous" Zooplankton (4). The final food
chain (5) runs from tiny fishes through progressively larger creatures
to sea mammoths like the sperm whale. Here the cycle begins again.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
SCIENTIFIC CO-OPERATION (Cont'd;
Exploring the workings of the brain
16
But this production ls used by man as food almost
exclusively through Industrial fish and other animals, by
way of complicated and often circuitous food chains.
As a result the coefficient of utilization of the photo¬
synthetic production of seas and oceans for food for man
is so small as to be almost negligible. This situation is
made worse by the total absence of attempts to regulate
the photosynthetic activity of phytoplankton of seas and
oceans, the lack of serious attempts to reconstruct and
Improve the food chains, and also above all by the pri¬
mitive methods used to bring In the harvest of fish and
animals, which are both insufficient and often predatory
In character.
Finally, it is important to determine the extent and
possibilities of regulating and utilizing the photosynthetic
production of oceanic vegetation. This potentially tre¬
mendous source of food and of other valuable material for
man must no longer remain neglected as It has done in
the past.
> As to plants on the earth's surface, especially culti¬
vated food and fodder plants which in the future, too,
will constitute the main supplies of food for men, the
basic factor determining their possible and final produc¬
tion is solar radiation energy, the principal force of the
process of photosynthesis. In fact, all agriculture
constitutes a system of processes the object of which is
the utilization of solar radiation energy to form organic
substances with the help of photosynthesis.
ur knowledge concerning the solar radiation
energy which can be used for photosynthesis
in various zones of the globe and on the globe as a whole
ls far from complete and certainly Insufficient.
To change this present unsatisfactory situation calls
for broad unified efforts in blo-actinometrics over as large
areas of the globe as possible.
In the final analysis wide-ranging and well co-ordinated
studies in photosynthesis and in the optimum use of solar
radiation energy for this purpose, will open up for man¬
kind unlimited possibilities for the solution, on any scale
desired, of the most important biological and technical
problems. Complete, rapid and radical solutions to these
problems will only come through unified efforts of scien¬
tists within a broad framework of international co-opera¬
tion.
The exceptional significance of cerebral activity in the
history of man, in his productive efforts, his cultural life,
his education and in so many other fields, is drawing more
and more scientists to study of the workings of the
human brain.
No matter how successfully we try to "relieve" the
human brain by such means as the automation of
industrial processes and the use of computing machines,
no matter how much we improve conditions of life, the
growth of science and technology makes more and greater
demands on the activity of the human brain.
In this respect, special recognition is now being given
to the new field of neuropharmacology or psychophar-
macology as It is called which has developed as a result
of successful studies concerning the functions of separate
brain centres, their interrelationship, their reaction to
drugs, as well as of specific metabolic processes in various
parts of the brain.
Drugs have been discovered which, by changing the
metabolism of specific regions of the brain, raise or lower
the tonus of the cortex, bring about changes in behaviour
and affect the activity of Internal organs. Medicine has
acquired potent means for the treatment of a number of
psychic diseases and epilepsy. And there is no doubt that
if they continue on this path scientists in the near future
will acquire even more effective means and methods for
the directional regulation of brain activity.
H| ere we refer not only to the treatment of brain
diseases and their prevention in hereditarily
tainted persons, but also to the re-establishment of the
complete and efficient working of the brain in persons
with neurotic tendencies and insomnia and the treatment
of narcomanias (alcoholism, caffeinism, etc.).
Furthermore the development of contemporary science
and technology stimulates the need to find ways of
increasing the working efficiency of the brain and of
boosting intellectual activity. In other words, we must
find ways of raising the speed of memorizing and the
extent of memory, of fighting against premature brain
fatigue and of maintaining a normal tonus of nervous
activity.
It is obvious that apart from other general measures
this will be achieved through action on the metabolism in
the central nervous system and the ability to regulate it.
Particularly difficult conditions, usually referred to as
extreme conditions, are occurring more and more
frequently during the working activity of man. Here, too,
methods affecting the nervous system, based on neuro-
physlological and neuroblochemical studies, should play
an important role along with general measures to safe¬
guard the normal activity of the brain.
All these problems are extremely complex; not only are
those sciences which must work directly for their solution
challenged but other forces must also be brought to bear
if we are to reach successful solutions rapidly. Scientists
of different countries who work in this field must co¬
ordinate efforts in the further study of the mechanisms
which regulate the activity of the brain and In the search
for new directional means which would have no side
effects on the basic nervous processes in the brain of man.
While scientists of the Soviet Union are ready to share
the results of their investigations, they are also eager to
learn what is happening in the institutions of other
countries. Thus every encouragement should be given to
the work of international scientific conferences, congresses
and symposia for each one is a step towards international
scientific co-operation and towards the development of
friendship and mutual respect among the representatives
of science from all countries of the world.
Norair Martirosovich Sissakian is Vice-President of the
U.S.S.R. Academy of Sciences and Chief of its Biology
Branch. A leading Soviet biochemist, he has carried out
research on enzymes in the metabolism of organisms and
in the cell structure of plants. He is a member of the
Executive Board of Unesco.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
I n the ancient French cathedral city of Reims
I lives a family which can look back over four
centuries of unbroken dedication to a great artistic
craft the design and execution of stained glass windows.
The history of the Simon family as makers of stained
glass began In the 16th century when Paul Simon settled
in Reims and opened a workshop in the shadow of the
soaring Gothic cathedral. Here he began to work in
stained glass an artistic craft that originated In anti¬
quity and gradually spread throughout Europe.
Paul Simon could hardly have foreseen that his humble
little workshop would survive him by many centuries and
that in time it would become one of the most highly es¬
teemed of all places where stained glass is made. In
founding it, he also created a dynasty of artist craftsmen
who handed on the tradition from father to son unin¬
terruptedly down the years.
A few years ago it looked as though the famous
workshop in Reims would pass into other hands. The
head of this oldest established firm of stained glass makers
in France, Jacques-Paul Simon, was thinking of retiring
and he hoped his son would succeed him. But Luc Simon,
a young painter, told his father that he had decided not
to follow the family tradition. Instead he wished to
devote himself exclusively to painting.
This was a hard blow for his father. It now seemed
almost certain that the dynasty would come to an end.
Then Jacques Paul's daughter, Brigitte, an art student
in Paris, stepped forward. "Ill try to carry on the work,"
she told her father.
Jacques-Paul Simon accepted immediately, and Brigitte
left the art school In Paris and came to the workshop
in Reims. She began her apprenticeship with enthusiasm
and from the energy and talent she displayed. It was soon
clear that she had the makings of a first-class artist In
stained glass, one worthy of the family name.
These expectations have since been confirmed and
today Brigitte is in complete charge of the workshop.
Nowadays her father only pays occasional visits to the
workshop to inspect with pride and satisfaction the work
Brigitte ls doing. Brigitte shares this work with her
husband, Charles Marq, a former student of philosophy
who, when he married, also decided on a change of career,
and who has since become a fine stained glass artist.
Examples of the skill and artistic talent of the members
of the Simon family who ran the workshop in the 16th,
17th and 18th centuries are recorded in the family archives
and preserved In the windows of many French churches.
However, perhaps the most striking achievements were
CONT'D ON PAGE 20
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
STAINED GLASS (Cont'd)
CARRYING ON THE
FAMILY TRADITION
Photos © Paul Almasy, Paris
18
In the workshops where the
ancient art of stained glass
is still maintained today,
over 1,400 different colour
tones are used. Above left,
Jacques-Paul Simon, who used
600,000 fragments of shatter¬
ed glass as a basis for restor¬
ing the war-damaged windows
of Reims Cathedral, examines
some glass samples. Left, his
daughter, Brigitte, works on
a window that will be placed
in the French church of Vitry-
le-Francois. Above, Brigitte
preparing a project for a
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
new window. She has execut¬
ed windows based on designs
of such well-known artists as
Chagall, Joseph Sima, Braque
Bissière and Villon. Below,
the Simon family team in the
workshop founded by their
ancestor, Paul, in the 16th
century. Right, the great
south Rose Window in Reims
Cathedral. An entirely new
window, it was executed after
the First World War by
Jacques-Paul Simon, to replace
a 16th-century window des¬
troyed in a bombardment.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Paul Almasy, Paris
Marc Chagall, at work on
a series of windows for
Metz Cathedral, is watched
by Brigitte Simon and her
husband, Charles Marq.
This husband-and-wife team
executed all the windows
for the Synagogue in Jeru¬
salem which were also
designed by Marc Chagall.
STAINED GLASS (Cont'd)
Save the old & create the new
those of Pierre Simon in the 19th century and of Jacques-
Paul, the present head of the family, in the 20th.
About 1830, Pierre Simon, who was then responsible for
the upkeep of the stained glass in Reims Cathedral,
decided to make records of every panel in these windows.
He did so on paper applied directly to the panels which
he had previously coated with a light oil painteasily
removable afterwards in the appropriate tint. He thus
obtained a complete record of the leads, the outlines of
the figures and designs in the windows and even the half
tones. The method also enabled him to work unhindered
by opacities due to dirt or poor transparency.
All these records were carefully stored in the family
archives and later, Pierre's son, Paul, completed his
father's work by making a precise colour catalogue of
every individual piece of glass.
A few years later all these records were an invaluable
aid to the Simon family. In 1866 a great storm damaged
the cathedral, shattering the great Rose Window above
the central portal and leaving it full of gaping holes.
From the detailed Information collected by his father and
himself, Paul Simon was able to make a perfect restora¬
tion of the damaged window.
Half a century later, a similar work of restoration,
though on a much larger scale, was carried out by Jac¬
ques-Paul Simon, then at the start of his career. The
First World War was raging and Reims was close to the
front line. In April 1917 a violent bombardment shattered
all the windows in the cathedral. When the war ended,
the French Ministry of Fine Arts asked Jacques-Paul
Simon If he thought it was possible to restore the windows.
20 After a long examination of the records collected by
his father and grandfather the young man decided to
accept the task which he knew would be delicate and
arduous. He assembled a team of six craftsmen and set
to work.
About 600,000 fragments of stained glass were collected
from around the cathedral and within the building itself.
Each window was slowly and painstakingly rebuilt with
these fragments and areas of missing glass were replaced
with new pieces painted in exactly the original tints.
Altogether these artist-craftsmen reconstructed over
16,000 square feet of stained glass: eight windows in the
nave, eight more in the transepts and a further eleven
in the chancel. The results were greater than had ever
been hoped, but the work took 20 years to complete.
During the same operation the team completely restored
the rose window on the south side of the cathedral. This
was the only window at Reims which did not date from
the 13th century. The original 13th-century rose window
was destroyed in a fire and was replaced in the 16th
century by a craftsman named Nicholas Derodé. Jacques-
Paul Simon created a completely new rose window based
on the subject of the earlier work.
Remarkable new works have come from the Simon
workshop since Brigitte and her husband have taken over
its management. Brigitte herself has executed a modern-
style stained glass window for the baptismal font chapel
in the cathedral which offers new proof of her talents.
In the church of St. Remy at Reims, Jacques-Paul Simon
has executed a rose window in the north transept and
Charles Marq has been responsible for a flamboyant
window on the south facade of the same church.
Working from designs by the famous artist, Marc Cha¬
gall, this husband and wife team executed all the
windows for the Synagogue in Jerusalem. Today they are
engaged on a new series of Chagall-designed windows for
Metz Cathedral.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
THE HIDDEN FACE OF THE CINEMA (END)
THE USELESS
BARRIERS
by Paul Léglise
In this, the fifth and final article condensed from a special world study
describing lesser-known aspects of the cinema industry, Paul Léglise
discusses some of the problems created by the international exchange
of films and shows how Unesco and other organizations are helping
to overcome various barriers to the free flow of films. The author is
now working on a final chapter to be devoted to the future of the cinema.
The Editors hope to publish portions of this text in a future issue.
THE movement of films across frontiers
can do much to advance mutual under¬
standing between peoples. Specifically,
the cinema gives a direct stimulus to trade
through its industrial, technical and agricultural
films. A well-proved asset in the field of
mass communication, it is able to bring home
to vast audiences, through newsreels, docu¬
mentary and information films of every kind,
the significance and purpose of national and
international projects for economic develop¬
ment. And, thanks to scientific, art and
educational films, it plays an all-the-more
decisive role in cultural exchanges.
The whole economy of the cinema, however,
is dominated by the concept of the film as
a form of entertainment. Films become
consumer goods whose profitability depends
largely on box-office returns in countries
where they are imported.
National laws and regulations which affect
international trade in films seek, in reality, to
protect home-produced films and at the same
time to encourage their export. These regu¬
lations, however, are applied indiscrimi¬
nately to all classes of films. Today, efforts
are being made to change this situation.
Firstly there is an increasing trend towards
economic, technical and artistic co-operation
of the kind mentioned in an earlier article
in this series on international co-productions.
Secondly, efforts are being made to place
cultural, educational and scientific films in a
special category to free them from obstacles
that hinder their development and free
movement across frontiers.
Just over half the income of film companies In
the U.S.A. comes from the export earnings of
their productions. Roughly the same figure can be
applied to most of the other major film-producing coun¬
tries: 60% in Italy and 50% In the United Kingdom, for
example.
These are significant figures and they have an equally
Important counterpart: the export of films leads to a
corresponding increase In the circulation of foreign films
within the exporting countries and a resulting decrease
in the screening of national films on the home market.
From these facts alone we can recognize the Impor¬
tance of the problem and understand the two-fold
reactions of governments anxious to facilitate world¬
wide export of their countries' films and to protect these
films within their own frontiers. Some have enacted
laws under which exported films receive financial help
and others give subsidies to the organizations responsible
for the distribution of their countries' films abroad.
The second kind of official reaction Is the traditional
protectionist kind that can take many forms. Of these
the most long-standing arc customs duties which protect
home markets and contribute to national revenues.
Through exchange control the State can keep an eye on
all payments involving foreign currency as well as on
the transfer of national capital abroad.
The most common form of control ls the import licence
which must be presented by any Importer wishing to
obtain foreign currency. This licence ls not always deli¬
vered automatically, for restrictions can be Imposed on
the importation of certain articles according to their
nature (films are a case In point) or to their origin. A
ceiling is sometimes imposed on the amount of foreign
currency that can be spent on certain Imports. Finally,
export licences enable a country to retain its essential
resources, or to plan and control the flow of Its foreign
trade, encouraging exports towards hard-currency coun¬
tries and placing restrictions on those with soft-currency
countries.
Unesco has carried out a systematic survey, country
by country, of these methods in so far as they apply to 21
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
CINEMA (Cont'd)
Dubbed films or sub-titles?
educational, scientific, and cultural materials. The result¬
ing report, "Trade Barriers to Knowledge" is of first-
rate Importance for everyone concerned with problems
of international trade.
Protectionist action also takes the form of quotas.
One type limits the number of import licences granted
for foreign films; another requires cinema proprietors
to show a certain number of nationally produced films
during a specified period.
The import-quota system is simple to enforce: a sti¬
pulated number of foreign films ls authorized for entry
during a given period.
The Internal-quota system was introduced for the first
time in the United Kingdom in 1927, and gave a remark¬
able boost to the British film Industry, whose annual
production rose from 26 films to 128 within two years
and reached 225 by 1937. The general principle of the
internal-quota system is the one applied in France
today: all cinemas must show French films for five weeks
In every quarter. In the United Kingdom, 30% of the
feature films shown in a cinema must be British (25 %
In the case of short films). In Italy, 100 days in every
year are reserved for the screening of nationally-pro¬
duced films chosen by a jury.
These restrictions on the free movement of films are
thus Justified by the desire of governments to make sure
that film companies in their own countries are not
deprived of the substantial revenue offered by the home
market. But the walls of cinematographic protectionism
are undermined to a certain extent by bilateral, and
sometimes even by regional agreements for co-production
and exchange which are stimulated by the obvious
advantages to be gained from entering foreign markets.
Although International action aimed at bringing about
the free circulation of educational, scientific, and cultural
films is a real possibility, action of this sort becomes a
much more complicated affair when it concerns the
kind of commercial films usually shown in ordinary
cinemas.
These regional centres would also house the technical
equipment needed for making film copies; or, failing this,
would see that this work was done by existing services
in different countries of the region on a co-operative
basis. Lack of technical equipment Is, in fact, another
major barrier to the movement of films.
Therefore in order to facilitate exchanges of educa¬
tional, scientific, and cultural films within these regions,
Unesco has been asked to encourage countries with
developed cinematographic services to place their labo¬
ratories at the disposal of others which have none.
One new difficulty has appeared in all countries during
the last few years, as a result of the most recent dev¬
elopment in film technology. This is the wide screen, or
the "panoramic format." This has become very popu¬
lar; moreover the use of 70mm film has made it possible
to project onto very wide screens. The width of the
S
)ne of the greatest difficulties is language. An
imported film must undergo transformation
before it can be shown to audiences speaking a different
language. Sub-titles are still the cheapest solution to
this problem. But generally speaking audiences have been
found to prefer to hear the dialogue or the commentary
In their own language without having to read sub-titles
at the moment when their attention should be focused
on the picture. Nevertheless the true cinema lover by
far prefers undubbed films which preserve the original
voices and sounds of the film without distortion.
Dubbing, on the other hand, gives a film a greater
commercial value, but costs far more. A mere translation
Is not enough. The dialogue must come as close as
possible to the original text so as to avoid major discre¬
pancies between the lip movements seen on the screen
and the syllables that are actually spoken.
The complexity of this problem is soon brought home
to us when we consider the number of languages spoken
in the world. In India, films are dubbed in 13 different
languages. Recording studios and laboratories carry out
this work of post-synchronization in many countries. In
some countries the dubbing of all imported films has
been made compulsory in order to keep the teams of
actors and technicians who do this work in .full employ¬
ment.
But what happens in countries In which technical
facilities are lacking? Conferences held at Bangkok,
Santiago, Paris, and in Chile were all obliged to go into
this question. While the problem is less serious in Latin
America than elsewhere thanks to common linguistic
links there, It is very much more difficult to resolve in
Africa or in South-East Asia. It has therefore been
22 proposed that regional centres should be established and
equipped to produce local versions of educational and
documentary films.
A scene from the
Argentine film
"Shun ko", evoking
problems of primary
education in the rural
areas of northern Ar¬
gentina. Chilian di¬
rector-actor, Lautaro
Murua, is here seen
as a schoolmaster,
teaching Angel Greco
(Shunko - the boy's
name in Quechua)
to count with the
help of an impro-
vized abacus. The
film won first prize
for the best Spanish-
speaking film at the
International Film Fes¬
tival of Mar del Plata,
Argentina in 1961.
From the film " Shunko "
i
4P
I
fJ
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
projected Image is twice, and sometimes even more than
twite that of its height.
As a result, the old format now seems quite outdated.
That is why many cinema proprietors use a wide screen
at all times, even when they are showing standard-sized
films which have not been expanded horizontally. In
such cases, the projected image is considerably distorted.
There is, in fact, little co-ordination in the development
of new cinematographic techniques, and there is no
doubt that the introduction of new sound and picture
processes, all demanding widely differing filming and
screening techniques has led to a disquieting situation.
The image undergoes wide and indiscriminate modifi¬
cations. As a result, the audience often sees on the screen
something which bears little relationship with what the
producer of the film wanted them to see: actors are
shown with their feet or the tops of their heads cut off
(and sometimes the subtitles are cut off, too) ; propor¬
tions are faulty, there is distortion at the sides of the
picture; as for the so-called sterephonic effect, it often
turns out to be mere cacophony.
René Clair has said: "The cinema is on the decline
when the universal character given to it fifty years ago
is threatened by the existence of too many different
systems. In these conditions, all progress ls mere Illu¬
sion. What ls a landscape without the tops of trees,
without sky and clouds? What ls a palace without Its
ceilings?"
Unesco realizes the cultural Importance of this tech¬
nical problem and at the 1958 General Conference, it
referred to the International Cinema and Television
Council the Idea of studying the possibility of "an Inter¬
national Instrument to secure standardization of prints
of 35mm. cinematographic film."
The principles are virtually Identical In the case of
commercial shorts. The chief obstacle to the free cir¬
culation of such films ls the way In which they are dis¬
tributed and screened. They are chlelly used as pro¬
gramme Allers and they are usually obtained very
cheaply, sometimes even without charge. Their prospects
are thus closely linked with those of feature films and
their production should be lower, or at any rate, not
exceed that of feature films. In fact, more are pro¬
duced than can be absorbed by the International market.
In France, the producer of a feature film Is granted
additional financial help when his film has been awarded
a special mention, provided that a short film of similar
CONT'D ON PAGE 32
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Drought and resulting famine periodi¬
cally strike the Sertao, the backlands
of northeastern Brazil, and are fol¬
lowed by a mass exodus from out of
this parched land. Carrying only a
few belongings, men, women and chil¬
dren set off down the roads leading
to Brazil's more prosperous areas.
© P. Verger
OPERA
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Brazils bold programme
in the hunger campaignm n i
TION NORDESTE
-V. "- K, " ' ' ~~
by Josué de Castro
There is more talk of hunger today than
at any time in the past. Hunger, in fact,
has become one of the great issues of
our time. It almost seems as if it had novor
existed beforea calamity that only appoarod
in the 20th century.
This, of course, is a completely false im¬
pression. Hunger has always oxistod side
by side with wealth and abundance. Neithor
hunger nor poverty are new facts in tho world
of today. What is new, as India's Primo
Minister, Pandit Nehru, has told us, is that tho
hungry peoples have come to realize as novor
before the true facts of their condition and
are showing a mounting impatienco to bo
freed from tho yoke of hunger and povorty.
It is the new awareness of tho social and
economic inequalities in the world now
shown by these hungry millionstho so-
called underdeveloped peoplosthat has
brought the problem to the foreon the radio
and in the press, in speeches by statesmen
and on the agendas of world congresses
and international meetings.
| ne of the chief and persistent causes of
present-day social tensions ls the world's
economic disequilibrium and Its resulting social
Inequalities. The deep economic gulf which separates
economically-developed from underdeveloped countries ls
one of the greatest threats to world peace. Growing
wider all the time It thus causes discord and fear and
gives rise to political and Ideological conflicts.
Economic inequality is the basic cause of Innumer¬
able other types of Inequality which are often
blamed on racial or climatic factors. It is responsible
for a life expectancy in most underdeveloped regions
of 30 years (in India, 27) whereas In countries of Europe
and North America, life expectancy ls 65 or more than
twice as high. It has a decisive Influence on the infan¬
tile mortality rate in the rich and the poor areas of
the world. In some places this mortality rate rises to
around 200 per thousand and yet in others it ls only 30
per thousand seven times lower.
The United Nations' "World Social Survey" highlights 25
CONTD ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
OPERATION 'NORDESTE' (Cont'd)
A scheme to revitalize 1/7th of Brazil
clearly and In great detail the stark contrasts prevailing
between prosperous and poverty-stricken countries.
Facts and figures in every field from production to
health, and from education to levels of consumption,
reveal the precarious state of the underdeveloped
regions.
But the most striking feature, the darkest and
most constant blot on the economic and social
condition of the underdeveloped regions, ls the chronic,
widespread hunger from which the mass of the people
sufferthe "vast disinherited masses," as Tibor Mende
has called them, whose only inheritance from generation
to generation has been their unchanging share of hunger
and wretchedness.
The very fact that huge concentration camps exist in
time of peacewhich is what the underdeveloped areas
really are underlines the sombre realities of our 20th
I
4
I
The north east
?
k Bl^
ern area of Brazil \ "typ
(shaded) covers N J
460,000 square \ -J
miles (14% of the 4^
country) but the 1 y
23 million who \ ~f
live there repre 1 ,j
sent one-third of I f SOUTH
the population. y AMERICA
century as gathered In the statistics of the U.N. Special¬
ized Agencies namely, that at least two-thirds of
mankind live on a inadequate diet or In a state of chronic
hunger. Out of the 2 1/2 thousand million individuals
who Uve on our planet, almost 1,700 million have still
not succeeded in escaping from the iron grip of hunger.
Lamennais spoke the truth when he said that hunger
was both the whip and chains for the slaves of our
civilization.
26
his present world situation, expressed in the
precise and unemotional language of stati¬
stics, was revealed to the 10th Conference of the Food and
Agriculture Organization held in Rome in 1959. It led
the Conference to approve a resolution, submitted by
Dr. B. Sen, Director-General of FAO, for the launching of
a World Freedom from Hunger Campaign, and calling on
governments of FAO member states and national and
International bodies concerned with social welfare to take
part.
Approval of this FAO resolution is a victory for the
ideas of a small group of pioneers who for years have
fought to make the whole world recognize that here was
a problem basic to mankind's future that must be faced.
This resolution made it possible to break the silence of
dominating majorities who had sought to stifle the cry
of the hungry masses, to conceal the true facts of their
everyday existence and to avoid even the mere mention
of hunger.
¡Thanks to this resolution, the taboo surrounding hunger
has been removed and a new era in international policy
has begun: the struggle against the scourge of hunger is
no longer a question of benevolent aid designed only to
make the effects of hunger less intolerable and to prevent
the explosive revolt of the hungry; it is a struggle which
goes to the very root of the problem. This new philo¬
sophy of action is based on the premise that hunger is
merely the biological expression of the whole complex
of economic underdevelopment and that, in the final
analysis, the struggle against hunger is part of the
struggle against underdevelopment.
The first meeting in May 1960 of the campaign's
advisory committee in Rome, at which the writer had the
honour of presiding, approved a report in which there
was the following passage: "The Campaign must attack
the roots or basic causes of hunger in the world and not
restrict Itself to the adoption of palliatives." Thus, in
1960, began the ten-year period of the World Freedom
From Hunger Campaign which was subsequently
broadened by the United Nations resolution establishing
the Development Decade, one of the basic aims of which
Is the struggle against hunger.
II t is an immense task to eliminate a world-
'wide scourge with roots deeply embedded in
the soil of the socio-economic structures prevailing
throughout most of the globe. With the limited
resources available to the United Nations, it is obvious
that the problem cannot be attacked simultaneously in
its full range and in every region where it exists.
It therefore seemed preferable to establish the
campaign's precise philosophy of action and to launch a
limited number of regional plans or pilot projects.
During the 1961 FAO general conference we suggested
the use of northeastern Brazil as a pilot area for the
campaign and the reasons we gave led the FAO to accept
this proposal made by the Brazilian Government. The
result has been closer co-operation between FAO and
Brazil aimed at eliminating the scourge of hunger from
northeastern Brazil through a realistic development of
the region.
To understand why we considered the Nordeste as
an appropriate pilot zone for the campaign against
hunger and proposed its choice to FAO, one needs to
take a look at the geo-economic characteristics of the
region.
Northeastern Brazil comprises an area of 1,200,000
square kilometres (460,000 sq. miles, or 14% of the whole
country) stretching from the State of Bahía to the State
of Maranhao. The region is neither geographically
homogeneous nor has it a clearcut geo-economic unity.
It comprises two typical and complementary regions: the
eastern Northeast and the western or central Northeast.
The eastern Northeast consists of a narrow stretch of
land near the coast with an average width of 50 miles;
the soil is dense and fertile and the climate is
distinguished by regular and abundant rainfalls. Sugar¬
cane monoculture has developed on this strip of land,
wiping out the forests which once covered it and
occupying every Inch of arable land with terrifying
thoroughness.
It is in this area that the sugar industry has been
established on the basis of monoculture and large estates,
an industry which, via a feudal land system and slavery,
CONT'D ON PAGE 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
DROUGHT &
OVERPOPULATION
irtf&Q
- . '- ;^£"*ss-»..x- - -.--."" v- .
'' .-3 v :<¿r¿ .* 'Y~v¿-» >.'.,» * -'. ,r .
Antonio Ronek © O Cruzeiro, Rio de Janeiro
José Pinto © O Cruzeiro, Rio de Janeiro
m Much of northeastern Brazil is an unsmiling land, a '.piney wilder mv, ul twr.ted
dwarf shrubs surrounded by cactuses (left). Over population p. anoihei sn iuu-,
problem in this "Polygon of Drought". Young men on a railway '.talion platfurm
(below) are migrating "Retirantes" waiting foi a tr am to take them to mon- (ultimate
regions where they may find |obs. Farming here is always at the hick y ul ihe
weather. One long-established activity is cultivation of small ihr ubs (being liar vested,
above) the fibre of whose stem is dried and turned into sacking, ropes and nets
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28
FAO
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
OPERATION 'NORDESTE' (Cont'd;
A 10-point guide for development
now forms the basis of the region's economy while at the
same time completely upsetting the regional economy
as a whole and preventing any possibility of other types
of cultivation.
The other Northeast^-the central or westernconsists
of semi-arid land known as the Sertao. This is the
"polygon of drought," periodically subject to a complete
absence of rain or to inadequate rainfalls which disor¬
ganize the region's entire economy and thus bring epi¬
demics of hunger during the drought seasons. The
economy of this sector is based on cattle-raising and
cotton-growing together with food polyculture which, in
rainy years, makes it possible to provide a well-balanced
diet.
he 23 million people who live In the Northeast
one-third of Brazil's total populationhave
a very low standard of living. The average gross per
capita income in Brazil ls 320 dollars; In the Northeast
it is only 100 dollars. This is the largest population group
in Latin America to have such low productivity and so
small an income. Thus, while Brazil can point to some
remarkable advances, this northeastern region continues
to be widely regarded as a problem area, since there
hunger remains a pitiless scourge.
In. fact, the Northeast suffers from two types of hunger.
The sugar-growing region is plagued by chronic
hunger caused by a lack or Insufficiency of various
elements in the everyday diet which ls based on
manioc and beans. The affliction of the Sertao
region is acute hunger, epidemics of hunger provoked
periodically by periods of drought.
This dismal picture of the northeastern economy has
given many people the impression that the Northeast,
with its complex and unfavourable geo-economic
situation, can never be reclaimed. Nothing could be
further from the truth, and more void of scientific reason
than this hasty and pessimistic interpretation of the
Northeast's economy. The hunger and poverty of the
Unesco- E. Aubert de la Rue
PHOTO LEFT is not the bombardment of some lunar
landscape but heavy rain falling on soil, loosening and
lifting it, and thus making it more vulnerable to erosion.
Northeastern Brazil's real plague is irregularity of
rainfall rather than a dearth. When the rains come
they fall in torrents and bring a quick harvest... but
they also wash away huge quantities of topsoil, leaving
a parched eroded surface like the one shown above.
Northeast are not attributable to natural conditions to
basically poor physical characteristicsbut rather to the
deformations and errors that accompanied Its economic
exploitation.
This Is proved by the surveys and research In economic
semiology which have been carried out with scrupulous
scientific care. The Ills of the Northeast are structural
ills whose origin lies in the colonial-type exploitation,
in the monoculture and large estates. Some of the
original social characteristics of these large land
holdings which the Portuguese colonists established
there four centuries ago still survive today.
Surveys carried out by SUDENE. an organization set
up specifically to assist the development of the North¬
east by integrating its economically marginal population
In the national economic system, leave no room for doubt
on this point. The great difficulty in the Northeast is
not, as has so long been claimed, the intermittent pheno¬
menon of drought but the archaic feudal structure of the
system of agrarian ownership which results in both the
failure to use the region's natural resources and to the
non-employment of the working capacity of the north¬
eastern population.
It would be difficult to find any other regions in the
world so well-suited to a pilot experiment In the struggle
against hunger as northeastern Brazil. It ls a thickly
populated area, in which different types of hunger are
rife and the situation there is socially explosive because
the population has become aware of the reasons for its
sufferings. It ls also suitable because it has poten¬
tialities for recovery and possesses technical organizations
like SUDENE which are equipped to carry out properly
planned large-scale projects. To this array of factors
favouring the experiment we may add the fact that
several years ago, at our Instigation, a plan for the
struggle against hunger was initiated In this region
through the World Association for the Campaign Against
Hunger (ASCOFAM).
Within the framework of the present experi¬
ment, here, broadly, is what has already been
done and what is planned for the years ahead. In Brazil,
ASCOFAM has concentrated its work on the Northeast,
dividing Its efforts between a broad educational pro¬
gramme as well as the shaping of a practical philosophy
of action, and the execution of projects designed to
stimulate the public response vital to any attempt to
transform the economy of the region.
Let us examine some of these activities in both sectors.
ASCOFAM initiated surveys and research on the agrarian
structure of the Northeast and Its elfect on the economic
and food situation of the region. On the basis of these
surveys, it even drew up an economic plan for agrarian
reform In the region, Including the total investments
this would require. It organized seminars on regional
problems. Including one on endemic diseases in rural
areas and undernourishment. The basic conclusions
of this seminar which took place in 1958 with the
participation of outstanding scientists, deserve to be
widely publicized. They present an analysis of the corre¬
lation between the problem of endemic diseases and the
problem of hunger in underdeveloped regions with an
objectivity which makes them valid for any under¬
developed region In the world.
These are the 10-point conclusions reached at the
seminar:
"1. The current socio-economic situation of the North¬
east, resulting from the serious mistakes made over many 29
CONTD ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
OPERATION ' NORDESTE ' (Cont'd)
Peaceful upheaval
in the backlands
years, is primarily responsible for the deficient diet of the
population and has thereby helped to aggravate the ende¬
mic diseases prevailing there.
2. The bulk of endemic diseases cannot be eliminated
without changing the socio-economic structure and diet¬
ary habits.
3. Aid programmes and public health programmes,
while essential, do not generally provide results any
more lasting than long-term social objectives unless
parallel action ls taken to change the socio-economic
infrastructure and the dietary conditions of the people.
4. The Northeast must be incorporated in the national
economy and has need of public and private action
capable of raising the economic level and improving
the distribution of wealth.
5. The regional phenomenon of drought, although
serious, cannot in the light of the present level of techno¬
logy and science be claimed as the main factor in the
Northeast's economic stagnation.
6. The productivity levels for the Northeast must be
raised as a matter of urgency In order to improve health
standards and overcome the incidence of regional en¬
demic diseases.
7. Under-capitallzatlon and under-employment are
major obstacles to the rational exploitation of the North¬
east's wealth and potentialities and, coupled with the
bad distribution of agricultural property, are serious
handicaps to production, acting as a brake on the
region's agricultural economy.
8. Sugar-cane monoculture, because of the form it
takes and despite the wealth It produces, is a serious
negative element in the social and dietary imbalance
of the peoples In the Northeast.
9. Emergency projects and action can only relieve
specific situations of a temporary or catastrophic kind
but will not lead to permanent results.
10. Industry and agriculture In the Northeast should
not be regarded as conflicting activities but both require
technical organization and financial assistance to reduce
production costs, to create and expand markets and to
ensure that useful individual man-power is fully occupied
and thus ensure the firm establishment of the north¬
eastern peoples."
s part of its programme to turn Brazilian and
^world attention to the problem of the North¬
east, ASCOFAM has produced a film entitled "The
Tragedy of Drought." This presents an eloquent picture
of the social reality of the semi-arid Northeast and points
to the possibility of solving this regional problem through
the struggle against drought and hunger.
ASCOFAM's main achievement, however, has been the
artificial enrichment of the region's basic foodstuff-
manioc flourby the addition of proteins and mineral
salts. Three small pilot factories set up in northeastern
Brazil turn the flour the sole source of hydrocarbons
and caloriesInto a foodstuff rich in acids, mineral salts
and certain vitamins. The process is economical and
practical and thus helps to combat habitual diet defi¬
ciencies of the region.
3Q A year-long experiment carried out in the town of
Surubim, one among the main centres of endemic pella¬
gra, revealed that the general use of this enriched flour
virtually banished this deficiency disease from the region.
Enrichment of manioc flour has so far been effected
on the basis of fat-free soya flour and a mixture of salts
and vitamins but ASCOFAM is currently studying a still
more practical and rational process which consists of the
addition to the usual manioc flour, made from the plant's
roots, of a flour made from the actual leaves of the
manioc which contain some 20% of proteins and
which have a high content of betacarotine (prqvita-
mine A).
Efforts are now being turned to a total utilization of
manioc through a project to be carried out in the town
of Nazareth, a semi-urban, semi-rural community which
is typical of the sugar monoculture region.
In this selected pilot area, techniques, relatively simple
but capable of greatly increasing the region's well-being,
will be used to develop production of certain Items, mainly
foodstuffs, to Increase and improve basic services in the
fields of health and education and to develop available
social capital.
In short, the Nazareth project consists of mobilizing
within this experimental area all the unused or Inade¬
quately used local production resources, primarily labour,
land, building materials and a certain physical capital
such as tools, working animals, etc.
Once the results of this experiment have been collected
and collated, they will be passed to other national and
international groups which are looking for co-operation
techniques capable of promoting community ' develop-
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
STAMPS AGAINST HUNGER
On this page we present a selection of the special stamps marking
Freedom from Hunger Week, mid-point in the five-year, world-wide
crusade of the U. N. Food and Agriculture Organization to improve
production and distribution of food supplies. Commemorative stamps
were issued by over 140 postal administrations on or around March 21 .
The double purpose of the international stamp plan was to publicize
the gravity of the world hunger situation and to enable people
everywhere to identify themselves with the Campaign. Stamps shown
here and others issued in support of the Campaign can be obtained
from the Unesco Philatelic Service, Place de Fontenoy, Paris (7 ).
ce POUR UN MONDE AFFRANCHI Dt LA FAIM
Mali's efforts to raise food production
through improved farming methods
are recalled in design of this stamp.
SUOMI
ISTA.LIE -A.
FOIS
Nutritional needs of children are also
emphasized in this stamp from Finland.
It bears Campaign slogan in Finnish and
Swedish, Finland's official languages.
Stamp above depicting a child,
eagerly drinking his milk, has
been issued by Argentina. The
drawing was inspired by photo
(right) taken by Paul Almasy
and published on the back
cover ot the special Freedom
from Hunger (July-August
1962) issue of The Unesco
Courier. Argentina has litho¬
graphed over two million.
Special French stamp incorporates, at
do most other issues, heads of wheat,
symbolizing FAO's concern with raising
nutritional standards the world.
ment in other areas afflicted by similar problems.
In addition, FAO, in co-operation with Unicef (the
United Nations Children's Fund) is carrying out a pro¬
gramme of dietary education in the Northeast. This
aims to introduce Improved dietary habits and to encour¬
age the production, preservation and better use of
foodstuffs possessing a high nutritive value. Several
other projects are now being examined by the World
Food Programme which might contribute, as a form of
investment capital, some of the food for workers engaged
in these development projects.
SUDENE has now laid down as one of its objectives the
improvement of food resources in the region, thus contri¬
buting to the direct struggle against hunger and under¬
nourishment. SUDENE'S activity Includes the following
projects: redistribution of the population so as to make
better use of surplus manpower in certain areas, encour¬
agement of stock-breeding by increasing the quantity of
fodder plants adapted to the ecological conditions of the
region, a programme of agricultural expansion and im¬
provement of production by gradual changeover to new
products.
In co-operation with the programmes of the Alliance
for Progress and other international bodies. SUDENE
cb-ordinates many activities designed to combat
hunger in the region.
FAO has already sent a technical commission to the
Northeast to survey this experiment. Many of the reso
lutions adopted by the last FAO regional conference for
Latin America, In Rio de Janeiro, related to problems of
agricultural structure, and the Brazilian Government has
taken account of these In Its recovery plan for the eco¬
nomic and food resources In the Northeast.
Northeastern Brazil ls today being watched by the world
whose interest has been drawn to this geographical area
by the obvious complexity of Its problems, the surprising
vitality of its people and the social tensions which
threaten it Internally. It may render the world an ines¬
timable service since it ls the scene of a peaceful revo¬
lution in which the application of science, technology and
planning will make it possible to uproot the scourge of
hunger, the most characteristic feature of economic and
social underdevelopment.
JOSUÉ DE CASTRO, the distinguished Brazilian nutri¬
tionist, is President of the Association for the World
Campaign Against Hunger, and a former President of the
Council of the U.N. Food and Agriculture Organization.
He is the author of many works on 'the problems of food
production and nutrition, of which the best known is
"The Geography of Hunger." He is now chief of the
Brazilian permanent delegation to the international
organizations in Geneva with the rank of ambassador.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
CINEMA (Cont'd from page 23)
Top priority freedom for films
category is always shown on the same programme during
the first three years of the feature film's Ufe. This boils
down to saying that only those short films which have
received an award stand a chance of being chosen to
accompany a French feature film. In Italy and in Argen¬
tina, short films In the top category have a certain num¬
ber of days set aside every year for them alone. In
Italy, the minimum number of days is 180.
In Argentina, category "A" films which are not taken
up by any cinema proprietor within one month are allo¬
cated by lot to certain cinemas which are obliged to
show them. The aim is to keep down the number of
home-produced films to reasonable proportions, thus
ensuring an improvement in their quality.
What are the general characteristics of International
trade In newsreels? Most of such trade is subject-matter
(i.e. sequences dealing with a particular event or subject
included in a newsreel). There is rarely a market for a
complete newsreel, for not all the items even in a special
national edition would appeal to local tastes. Most news-
reel firms have trade agreements by subject with their
colleagues in other countries.
Unesco keeps a watchful eye on all problems to do
with educational, scientific, and cultural films. When all
the Immense and varied difficulties that must be overcome
before International agreements applicable all over the
world can be reached are taken into account, there are
Indeed grounds for satisfaction with results achieved.
In 1961, when it received the report on international
relations and exchanges in the fields of education, science,
and culture prepared for the U.N. Economic and Social
Council, Unesco's Executive Board pointed out that these
international contacts, apart from their general aim of
developing peaceful relationships between nations, had
two no less Important objectives:
1. The organization between nations of exchanges of
persons, information, knowledge, ideas and equipment;
and
2. To enable the more fortunate and better equipped
nations to aid the less privileged ones.
This general aim and this double objective are an
intrinsic part of Unesco's action in the field of educational,
scientific, and cultural films. Permanent contacts have
also now been established between Unesco and interna¬
tional organizations concerned with the cinema, thanks
to the creation of the International Film and Television
Council.
uI nesco has already achieved some impressive
results in the field of international agreements
for the circulation of objects of educational, scientific, or
cultural interest. Films benefit from the many facilities
which have been obtained in this way.
Unesco has adopted an international instrument, known
as the Florence Agreement, which facilitates the free
circulation of books, publications and educational, scien¬
tific and cultural materials.
Films which meet these conditions are covered by the
agreement, which provides for exemption from customs
duties and from certain Import dues; it also makes provi¬
sion, as far as possible, for the granting of foreign
exchange and Import licences.
Certain limitations, however, are imposed on the scope
of the convention where films are concerned. Films must
be Imported only by organizations approved by the com¬
petent authorities of the importing country for the
purpose of duty free admission of such material and may
only be exhibited by the approved organizations; in
practice, this means that the films in question can be
used only for non-commercial purposes.
The other Important international agreement adopted
by Unesco, the Beirut Agreement, facilitates the inter-
32 national circulation of visual and auditory material of
an educational, scientific and cultural character. This
instrument differs from the preceding one in that 1) It
applies only to visual and auditory materials, 2) it grants
exemption not only from customs duties but from
quantitive restrictions on imports and the need to apply
for Import licences, and 3) in general, it does much to
reduce difficulties arising from the international circula¬
tion of educational, scientific, and cultural films, even
when these are shown commercially.
Three drafts which were drawn up by the Customs
Co-operation Council in conjunction with Unesco were
adopted by this Council in 1961. These new provisions
supplement the measures already adopted concerning
temporary importation. Temporary importation is an
arrangement by which states allow educational, cultural,
and scientific films to enter a country and suspend the
application of customs duties for a limited period.
What are these new agreements? First of all,
there is one which makes use of international
carnets to exempt importers from a large number of
formalities to which they were previously subject. Second¬
ly, all professional and cinematographic equipment needed
for film-making in a foreign country has been brought
within the scope of temporary importation regulations.
The third agreement concerns the temporary importation
of material for International exhibitions.
International trade ls controlled by agreements of a
worldwide, regional, or bilateral nature. There are other
agreements which deal specifically with cultural
exchanges. Rather than describe these in detail, or make
an analysis of their application to the international cine¬
matographic trade, let us simply take a brief look at the
general way in which they work.
The General Agreement on Trade and Tariffs (G.A.T.T.),
which came into operation in 1948, has turned out to be
one of the most decisive steps in freeing international
trade from hampering restrictions.
Through it, the quota system has been considerably
reduced in many countries, and many categories of
articles, particularly those of an educational, scientific,
or cultural nature, have been freed from various forms
of control. For example, during a conference held at
Geneva in 1956, Unesco asked that tariff reductions
should be granted on a series of articles and many
countries agreed, and on films In particular.
There are also regional agreements affecting film
exchanges. The European Economic Community, better
known as the Common Market, was established by the
Treaty of Rome. This treaty is concerned particularly
with the economic aspects of European trade, and for Its
purposes films are treated as trade commodities.
In our field, therefore, the aim of the treaty is the
integration of the film industry on Common Market lines,
the implication being that national help and fiscal charges
will be brought into line and trade made easier.
In other parts of the world, there are regional
agreements which make a similar attempt to create
economic communities or to establish the foundations
of cultural co-operation. One example, is the Council for
Mutual Economic Aid which brings together countries
having a socialist economy, although films do not seem
to play an important role here. Amongst regional agree¬
ments with a more pronounced cultural nature, is the
convention signed by the members of the Organization
of American States with a view to encouraging inter-
American cultural relationships, and also the activities
of the Cultural Committee of the Nordic Council (Nordisk
Kulturkommission ) .
This brief survey of the different agreements covering
cinematographic exchanges highlights the importance of
the problems involved and the extent of the interest
shown in them by national authorities as well as by
regional and International bodies.
Films, as consumer goods, follow the general trends
of trade liberalization. But as intellectual and culture
products, they deserve an even more rapid liberation on
a world-wide scale a top-priority freedom.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
PROS AND CONS OF ESPERANTO
Ed. note: We have received a volu¬
minous correspondence following the
publication of Robert H. J. van Kuyk's
letter on the drawbacks of Esperanto
(March issue). Space permits us to
publish only excerpts from a few:
Sir,
Mr. van Kuyk's conception of the
role of Esperanto is much too limited,
and it is not clear whether he thinks
we must learn all the great languages
(virtually an impossibility) or only one
or another of them (which would still
leave vast numbers of people without
a common language.) It would be
unwise to give much weight to opi¬
nions expressed by one who reasons
that because Esperanto removes the
need to learn other languages, there¬
fore it prevents one learning them !
CM. Cather
Torquay, England
Sir,
Offering an excuse for Mr. van Kuyk
I would say that he has never had the
occasion to work in the field of expe¬
rience available daily to a teacher.
He was lucky enough to be born in
the Netherlands it is a well-known
fact that the Dutch people are tradi¬
tionally more or less polyglot and
he is also blessed with rather rare
and special natural gifts qualities
with which he seems to believe his
fellows are equally well endowed.
If he was in daily contact, as we
teachers are, with hundreds of chil¬
dren and adolescents he would soon
realize what an effort the average
pupil has to make even to be able,
at the moment of his "Baccalauréat",
to stammer out a few phrases of a
language learned during seven years
in a secondary school... If he had
this experience he would not say with
such assurance "it is far better to
learn languages like English, Russian
and Chinese..." And what about the
millions of adults in the world who
have never set foot inside a secondary
school?
P. Dennis
Bar-Ie-Duc, France
Sir,
Mr. van Kuyk's objections have
long been refuted. I need only quote
the famous Danish linguist Otto Jes-
persen who as early as 1928 wrote:
"An objection which is often raised
against constructed languages is that
they can never be as good as natural
languages. It is true that our Inter-
language is not as rich as English,
not as elegant as French, not as vigo¬
rous as German, not as beautiful as
Italian, not as full of nuances as Rus¬
sian,, not as 'homelike' as our mother-
tongue. But note this well, that all
these good qualities, which one appre¬
ciates and praises in the national lan¬
guages, are found only when they are
spoken or written by natives. And
the Interlanguage may very easily be
richer than the English spoken by a
Frenchman, more elegant than French
as spoken by a Dane, more vigorous
than the German of some Italians,
more beautiful than the Italian of the
English, more full of nuances than the
Russian of the Germans, and more
homelike than my own tongue spoken
by Russians. And as our language is
an auxiliary language, it can only be
compared fairly with natural langua¬
ges as usually spoken by foreigners."
An International Language, London,
Allen and Unwin.
Dr. S.M. Auerbach
London, England
Sir,
Esperanto is drawn from the same
roots as the world's living languages
and is an outgrowth of them. Nothing
could be more false than to describe
it as an "artificial" language. It is
in fact a living link between other
languages. Congresses of young
Esperantists coming from many coun¬
tries are an undeniable proof of this.
René Llech-Walter
Perpignan, France
Sir,
How can such people as a farm
worker in the Massif Central (or Lower
Saxony) a postman in the Pyrenees (or
Croatia), a housewife in Britanny (or
one in Sicily or Norway) learn lan¬
guages "like English, Russian, Chi¬
nese, Arabic" even supposing they
wanted to?
F. Lenz
Paris, France
Sir,
I support Mr. R.H.J, van Kuyk.
Learning a real language is an excit¬
ing adventure into another culture; one
learns of the climate, scenery, history,
arts, institutions, philosophies, reli¬
gions, and daily problems and customs
of the people. Surely, these are the
very things we want to understand!
If I may exaggerate a little, Esperanto
is rather like a catalogue compared
with real languages. It is better to
learn mere smatterings of several than
to waste time on it. Arriving in a
foreign country for work; or for plea¬
sure, how much more enjoyable and
more friendly to try to share a little
in the normal social life and culture
than to confine oneself to Esperanto!
Most languages seem to have some
unnecessary difficulties which are only
perpetuated by the tireless and misguid¬
ed efforts of teachers. They seem to
serve only as a barrier, showing up
the so-called "well-educated" from
others who may, in fact, be better
educated in more worth-while aspects
of language and life. Dropping this
pedantry, perhaps in twenty years
three-quarters of school-leavers could
have some knowledge of about five
other languages, about one-quarter
speaking them fairly fluently, with
many skilled linguists becoming avail¬
able for exacting work.
B.M. Johns
Cambridge, England
CO-AUTHORSHIP IN FILMS
Sir,
My article describing the machin¬
ery for distributing films in the world
(The Hidden Face of the Cinema Pt.2
- January 1963 issue) included a brief
explanation of how copyright is
applied to films. From this simpli¬
fied definition readers may have gain¬
ed the impression that this was a uni¬
versally accepted idea synthesizing
various current practices in the world
today. However, on the question of
"authorship" the long-standing dis¬
agreement, which I briefly evoked, bet¬
ween the notion of the producer as
an "author" of a film and as an
"intellectual creator" is still not settled
today and still involves multiple shades
of meaning. The correct balance
between these two conceptions seems
to have been adopted in a French law
of 1947 which considers a producer
as co-author of the film only when
he can be said to have made an intel¬
lectually creative contribution towards
it. But the problem is too complex
to be explained in the few lines I was
able to devote to it and which simply
touched on the subject. The ¡deal
international solution has not yet come
forth. Let us hope that one will
soon be produced.
Paul I^ßllse
Paris, Frunce
RUDOLF STEINER'S
NATIONALITY
Sir,
In your February 1963 issue you
refer to Rudolf Steiner as "the Ger¬
man philosopher and educator". Stei¬
ner was, in fact, born at Kraljevic, on
the Austro-Hungarian frontier, on
February 27, 1861. The tremendous
scope of the work he accomplished
in so many fields during his short life
is presented in "Rudolf Steiner", a
booklet published for his centenary
exhibition in 1961 and edited by the
Goethcanum, in Dornach, Switzerland.
Marguerite Bourdicr
Rome, Italy
Ed. note: Our reader is correct.
Rudolf Steiner was, in fact, Austrian.
GREAT ILLS IGNORED
Sir,
My only complaint regarding your
magazine is that you give too much
space to information on the Arab
countries and tend to neglect such
great ills of our time as alcoholism,
prostitution and juvenile delinquency.
I would suggest that you visit the in¬
stitution at Lannemezan in the Hautes-
Pyrénées department. You will find
enough material there to fill a very
interesting issue.
E. Haro
Pau, France
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
JlOWER LINE AIR SPIES: Airborne
inspection of Sweden's 20,000 miles
of overhead power lines has reduced costs
by 50% compared with conventional
ground patrol inspection. Flying at tree-
top height in helicopters or light planes,
the inspectors dictate their observations to
portable tape-recorders.
l?OR AFRICA'S NEW TEACHERS:
Nearly 300 fellowships providing train¬
ing for teaching staff in African universities
will be granted under Unesco's 1963-64
fellowhip programme. They will be avail¬
able in 22 Unesco Member States, offering
theoretical and practical study at the uni¬
versity level in science, social science, the
humanities and mass communications.
MÏIDDLE EAST QUESTS: The search
for the early origins of civilization
will this year take archaeologists from the
Oriental Institute of the University of
Chicago to four ancient sites in the Near
and Middle East. They will be investi¬
gating how man the hunter lived in cen¬
tral and southern Turkey 11,000 years ago
and how Christianity moved from Pales¬
tine to Mesopotamia in the 6th century.
Two other sites to be studied are an
ancient town in Iran, Jundi Shapur, and
Khirbat al Kerak in Israel, where remains
dating from the third millenium B.C. have
been found beneath a 5th century A.D.
Byzantine church.
CASTLE ART TROVE: Fifty lost paint-
ings including masterpieces by Tinto¬
retto, Rubens and Veronese have been
found in a dusty attic of Prague CasUe.
They are part of the collection of Rudolf
II, which was dispersed in the 17th and
18th centuries. The works remaining in
Prague were hitherto assumed to be only
minor ones.
Y) ESERT LABORATORY: Scientists
~^ from the University of California are
using a stretch of desert 15 miles square
as a research laboratory to study the
evolution of plants and animals in arid
regions. In this "living laboratory", with
no buildings or complicated scientific equip¬
ment, scientists are seeking the answers to
such questions as how desert animals live
and adapt themselves to the conditions of
heat and drought.
¥ IBRARY SERVING THE BLIND:
"^ Delhi Public Library, established by
Unesco and the Indian Government as a
model for South Asia in 1951, has now
opened a Braille section for blind readers.
Another activity it has greatly developed
is the publication of booklets for new liter¬
ates. Stocks of the first 36 titles of these
booklets were soon sold out.
17\ST-WEST MIMES ON FILM: A
documentary film, "The Language of
34 Movement-Mimes of East and West", made
by Unesco as part of its East-West major
project to encourage mutual appreciation
of cultural values, is available to TV sta¬
tions all over the world. Mimes and
dances from eight countries Italy, France,
Turkey, India, Japan, Poland, USA, Nether¬
lands offer a convincing display of the
universality of this art.
J» ACT AGAINST DISCRIMINATION:
The Convention designed to combat
discrimination in education adopted in
1960 by the Unesco General Conference
has now been ratified by Kuwait, New
Zealand and Czechoslovakia. This brings
to 15 the number of countries that have
ratified the Convention which entered into
force in May 1962.
ffiOLAR BATTERY POWER: A silicon
solar battery designed by a Soviet
scientist at the Uzbekistan Institute of Phy¬
sical Technology has developed a power
of 150 watts although it has a surface of
only four square feet. This remarkable
achievement in solar engineering has been .
obtained by increasing ten-fold the con¬
centration of the sun's rays falling on the
battery surface through mirror focusing.
This solar power station powers a pump
which in one hour can raise over 1,300
gallons of water to a height of 20 feet.
]VEW FARMING FOR NIGERIA: Today
nearly 60,000 young men are being
trained in modern farming methods under
a scheme launched by the Government of
West Nigeria in co-operation with the U.N.
Food and Agriculture Organization. Farm
institutes and settlements are being created
where newly-trained young men become
tenants of a "farm unit" growing such
crops as cassava, yams, sorghum, maize,
peas, beans, cocoa, rubber, oil palm and
coconuts. Each settlement or village
consists of about 200 families and is orga¬
nized on a co-operative basis.
OUR UNCHARTED PLANET: Sixty
scientists from forty countries the
Commission for the Geological Map of the
World who met in Unesco House recenüy
approved plans to go ahead with the prepa¬
ration of a world geological atlas which
is to be published with Unesco's aid.
Their meeting was a reminder that while
we are looking into outer space, we still
do not possess a unified map of the
world's sub-soil.
VACATIONS ABROAD: Hundreds of
choices for unusual holidays offered
by over 1,000 organizations and institutions
in 81 countries are listed in the 15th edition
of Unesco's "Vacations Abroad" (*).
They range from opportunities to learn a
new language (open to almost everyone)
to conducting orchestras, for which a
conservatory education is required.
Vacations Abroad XV, 1963, Unesco, Place
de Fontenoy, Paris fl'). Price : 6/ - (stg), J1.75 ;
4.50 F.
¥f EAPPEARING AMERICANS: The
Indian population in the United States
reached its lowest point at the end of the
19th century but since then has made a
steady comeback. During the past 30
years it has increased about sixty per cent
to well over half a million.
/ÍÍÍÍÍ ^nLLlON RADIOS: Nearly 70
^4"" per cent of the world's people,
most of them in Africa, Asia and Latin
America, lack receivers to pick up even
local radio broadcasts. Over 400 million
additional sets, according to a Unesco
estimate, would be needed to provide a
receiver for each family in these regions.
To meet this need the International Tele¬
communication Union and Unesco have
jointly studied the designing of transistor¬
ized receivers which could be mass produc¬
ed for the developing countries for as little
as $5.00.
STOCKTAKING AT SEA: Two French
& trawlers equipped as floating laborato¬
ries will set out this year on a fishing expe¬
dition to take stock of the marine resour¬
ces of the' Gulf of Guinea as potential
food supplies for Africa. Carrying inter¬
national teams of scientists, they will co¬
ver 5,600 miles over the African conti¬
nental shelf during two cruises this year
and next. In addition to taking meteoro¬
logical and hydrological observations, the
ships will sweep the sea bottom at inter¬
vals of thirty or forty miles to take a
census of its population.
MUSIC IN EDUCATION: Music-
ogists, musicians, composers and
music educators from all o'ver the world
will be meeting in Tokyo in July to discuss
contemporary trends and developments in
music and music education in both Orient
and Occident. They will be attending the
Fifth International Congress on Music
Education.
F/ashes...
; Mexico has launched an eleven-year
plan to expand education at all levels and
is now devoting 22% of the federal budget
to education.
H Fatal road accidents are on the increase
all over the -world with the exception of
the United States where the trend has been
reversed, reports the World Health Orga¬
nization.
; Unesco Coupons an international me¬
dium of exchange, enabling, "soft" cur¬
rency countries to buy educational, scientific
and cultural equipment in "hard" currency
areas have now made possible 550 million
worth of transactions.
: The world's population increase has
brought the proportion of the "under-
twenties" to over 50% in some countries.
Tlie total of young people in school in¬
creased 62% from 257 million to 417
million between 1950 and 1960.
Meteorological information from around
the world is now supplied by 8,000 fixed
weather stations as -well as by 3,000 mer¬
chant ships and 3,000 aircraft. Weather
satellites now supplement this network.
u
z
<
<
z
o
o
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Jfcfflft
¡2; -e *^
K9 if.
catalogue
de reproduction» en
couleurs d« peinture*
I860 à 1961
' colour reproductions
of paintings
-, I860 to 1961
catalogo de
reproducciones
en color de pinturas
I860 a 1961
CATALOGUE OF COLOUR
REPRODUCTIONS OF PAINTINGS
1 86 0- 1 96 1 (Revised and enlarged edition)
An up-to-date listing of colour reproductions
of world-famous paintings compiled from
the Unesco collection of reproductions sel¬
ected by internationally-known art experts.
The highest standards guide their choice:
fidelity of reproduction, the significance of
the artist and the importance of the original
painting. Only the most worthy paintings
are chosen for Unesco's catalogue, which
contains descriptions and illustrations of
1,347 reproductions available in full-colours
prints. 485 pages.
Price : 28/6; $6.00; 20 F.
CATALOGUE OF COLOUR REPRODUCTIONS
OF PAINTINGS PRIOR TO 1860
Revised and enlarged edition
lists nearly 900 recommended colour reproductions
gives more examples from Asia, Africa, Australia and Central
European countries.
Offers detailed information
A beautifully presented volume of 323 pages. Each painting
is reproduced in black
and white accompanied
by full details of the ori¬
ginal, name of publisher
and price of colour re¬
production.
Price : 30/- (stg) ;
$6.00; 21 F.
-^ In the Federal Republic of
Germany, Switzerland and
Austria, a special Unesco-OI-
denbourg Verlag edition (with
German text) also available.
Where to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; rates quoted are
for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO COU¬
RIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuiai, Press Department. Royal
Afghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Melbourne University Press, 3 69 Lonsdale Street,
Melbourne, C. I., Victoria. (A. 15/-). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C"., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Seh. 60.-). BELGIUM. Editions " Labor ",
342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-Boek-
handel, Belgiëlei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (100 FB) and art slides only: Louis de Lannoy,
22, place de Brouckère, Brussels. CCP 3380.00.
BURMA. Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road,
Rangoon. (K. 5.50). CANADA. Queen's Printer,
Ottawa. Ont. ($ 3.00). CEYLON. The Associated
Newspapers of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244. Colombo, 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd.. 99 Chungking South
Rd., Section 1, Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa). CUBA.
Librería Económica, Pte Zayas 505-7, Apartado 113,
Havana. (2.25 pesos). CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia
Ltd., 30 Ve Smeckich. Prague 2. DENMARK. Ejnar
Munksgaard, A/S Tidsskriftafdelingen, Prags Boulevard 47
Copenhagen S (D.kr. 12). ETHIOPIA. International
Press Agency. P.O. Box 1 20. Addis Ababa. FINLAND.
Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, 2 Keskuskatu. Helsinki.
(Fmk. 540). FRANCE. Librairie de I'Unesco. Place
de Fontenoy. Paris-7«. C.C.P. 12598-48. (7 F.).
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg Verlag, Rosens-
heimer Strasse 145, Munich. For the Unesco Kurier
(German ed. only) Bahren-felder-Chaussee 160,
Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, C.C.P. 276650 (DM 8). GHANA
Methodist Book Depot Ltd. Atlantis House. Commercial
St., POB 100, Cape Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See
United Kingdom. GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann,
28. rue du Stade, Athens. HONG-KONG. Swindon
Book Co., 64. Nathan Road. Kowloon. HUNGARY.
Kultura, P.O. Box 149. Budapest, 62. INDIA. Orient
Longmans Ltd. Indian Mercantile Chamber. Nicol Road.
Bombay 1; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; Gun-
foundry Road, Hyderabad, 1 ; 3 6a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House. 24/1 Ataf AM Road. P.O. Box 3 86, New
Delhi, 1 ; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.,
17 Park Street, Calcutta 16, Scindia House, New Delhi.
Indian National Commission for Co-operation with
Unesco, Ministry of Education, New Delhi 3. (Rs. 7).
INDONESIA. P. N. Fadjar Bhakti, Djalan
Nusantara 22, Djakarta. IRAQ. Mackenzie's
Bookshop, Baghdad. IRELAND. The National Press,
2. Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.. 3 5, Allenby
Road and 48, Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv( 1 £ 5.50).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room. 91 Harbour
Street, Kingston. Knox Educational Services. Spaldings.
(10/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-Nichome,
Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605 Tokyo Central. Tokyo.
(Yen 670). JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub. Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman.
KENYA. E.S.A. Bookshop, P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64. Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole
and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LUXEMBURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22. Grand-Rue,
Luxemburg. MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications Ltd., Times House.
River Valley Rd., Singapore (M. $ 500) MALTA.
Sapienia's Library 26 Kingsway, Valetta. (10/-).
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30. Bourbon
Street, Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library. 30 Bid
des Moulins. Monte-Carlo. (7 NF.). NETHERLANDS.
N. V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout. 9, The Hague,
(fl. 6). NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES. G. C. T.
Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.) N.V., Willemstad. Curacao
NEW ZEALAND Government Printing Office
Wellington, and Government Bookshops, Auckland,
Wellington. Christchurch, Dunedin (10/-). NIGERIA.
C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box 174, Lagos. (10/-). NOR
WAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Lilla Grente. 7, Olio
For the Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Litteratur
Tjineitc. Stortingsgt. 4. Oslo. Postboks 115 (kr 13.20
PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing Cor
Ltd., Unesco Publications House. P.O. Box 374, 56-N
Gulberg Industrial Colony, Lahore. PANAMA.
Cultural Panamtna, Avenida 7a, No. TI-49, Apartado
de Correos 2018. Panama, D.F. (Balboas 3-). PHI¬
LIPPINES. The Modern Book Co., 508 Rizal Avenue
Manila. POLAND. RUCH " ul. Wiloza Nr. 46.
Warsaw 10 (Zl. 50). PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada
Lda. Livraria Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon.
PUERTO RICO. Spanish English Publications Apartado
1912. Hato Rey. RHODESIA A NYASALAND. The
Book Centre, First Street, Salisbury. Southern Rhodtsia.
SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop. P.O, Box 1118. Khart-
oum. SWEDEN. A/B C.E. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbok.
handel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm. For The Unesco
Courier: Svenska Unescoridct, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm. C (Kr. 7.50); SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag,
5 Ramistrasse Zurich. Payot, 40, rue du Marché, Ganeva.
C.C.P. 1-236. " Courier " only: Georges Losmaz. 1, rue
des Vieux-Grenadiers, Gineva. C.C.P. 1-4811. (Fr. S. 8).
TANGANYIKA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop. P.O.B.
9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND. Suksapan
Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok. (35
ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette. 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda
Bookshop. P.O. Box 145. Kampala. UNION OF
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Bookstore, Libri
Building, Church Street, Pretoria. For the Unesco Cou¬
rier (single copies) only: Central News Agency, P.O.
Box 1033. Johannesburg. (10/-). UNITED ARAB
REPUBLIC (EGYPT). La Renaissance d'Egypte. 9 Sh.
Adly-Pasha, Cairo. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M.
Stationery Office. P.O. Box 569, London. S.E.I. (10/-).
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications Center,
801 Third Avenue. New York. 22. N.Y. (J 5.00.)
and (except periodicals): Columbia University Press,
2960 Broadway, New York, 27 N.Y. U.S.S.R. Mez-
hdunarodnaja Kniga. Moscow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA.
Yugoslovenska Knjiga, Tcrazije 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
STAINED GLASS ARTISTS
OF TODAY
The makers of stained glass in Europe achieved their greatest master¬
pieces in the 12th, 13th and 16th centuries. In the 16th century one
young French stained-glass craftsman opened a workshop in the shadow
of the great Gothic cathedral at Reims. Since then the family tradition has
been handed down uninterruptedly from father to son. Now, for the first
time, it has passed to a daughter (shown here working on a window) who
is adding new lustre to the renown won by her ancestors. (Story page 17)
© Almasy
f
70m»
****
]]>
</page>
</document>
