<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="062882eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
CO
Uj
^r^ ^^B ^É^P^^^^B FEBRUARY 1985 -7 French francs ^B
TheCouner
The memory of mankind
LIBRARIES AND ARCHIVES
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A time to live...
31 Venezuela
The magic harp
The legends of different countries and
peoples have recently been recreated for a
world television audience in a series of 26
half-hour films made by the Canadian film
company Via le Monde inc. The series, en¬
titled "Légendes du Monde", is the fruit of
an ambitious coproduction venture, the
participants in which include the second
channel of French TV, the Canadian
Broadcasting Corporation, and Unesco's
International Fund for the Promotion of
Culture. Each film dramatizes a legend
using actors from the country in which it
is set. Photo is a still from "The Magic
Harp", a Venezuelan story which tells how
young Felipe's musicianship saves his
father from financial ruin.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Courier
A window open on the world
Editorial
OVER the past twenty years a quiet but profound revo¬
lution has taken place in the world of libraries and
archives. The first eddies of the wind of change were
felt among the bookshelves with the irruption of the computer
on the world scene. Its seemingly unlimited powers encouraged
a flurry of wild speculation. Its arrival, it was said, heralded the
era of the "paperless office", and there were those who did not
hesitate to announce the imminent demise of the book.
Today the computer has come of age. The menacing mystery
has turned out to be a friendly servant whose ministrations af¬
fect every aspect of our daily lives. Far from killing off the
book, it offers the possibility of easy access for all to the world's
libraries and archives and has itself become the subject matter
of thousands of new books and periodicals.
Other audio-visual technologies are playing their part too. In
particular, the simple cassette recorder is at this moment filling
a key role in saving for posterity that other source of distilled
wisdom, the oral tradition of many cultures of the Third World.
In our enthusiasm for these new technologies and the im¬
mense possibilities they open up, we should not forget that
behind the sleek machines lies the dedicated intellectual and
planning effort both of brilliant individual men and women and
of many non-governmental, national and international
organizations.
Among the latter Unesco can claim to play an irreplaceable
role. Under its Major Programme VII, Information Systems
and Access to Knowledge, it has been steadfastly pursuing four
objectives which merit being quoted here extensively:
(I) to develop standards, rules, methods, guiding principles and
other normative tools for the processing and transfer of
specialized information and the creation of compatible infor- ,
motion systems;
(II) to enable developing countries, individually or on a regional
basis, to set up their own data bases and to have access to those
now in existence throughout the world;
(III) to promote the development ofspecialized regional infor¬
mation networks in co-operation with the appropriate interna¬
tional regional organizations;
(IV) to contribute to the harmonious development ofcompati¬
ble international information services and systems among the
organizations of the United Nations system.
This issue of the Unesco Courier presents a far from ex¬
haustive account of some of the problems facing archives and
libraries today. These problems are summed up in the words of
American educator Ernest L. Boyer: "Television extends
human sight, computers extend memory and ability for calcula¬
tion. Books extend wisdom. It is now our task to fit together
these tools, the new ones with the old." This is a task to which
Unesco is firmly committed.
Front cover: Decorated spines of Bohemian Land Registers dating from the
16th to the 18th centuries. These Tabulae Terrae, some of which date back
to before the Battle of the White Mountain (1620), are among the most
precious possessions of the Czechoslovak archives and are the rarest ar¬
chival documents of their kind in the whole of central Europe.
Photo © Archivnl Správa Praha
February 1985
. 38th year
The memory of mankind
by Jorge Luis Borges
Libraries and archives for tomorrow
by J. Stephen Parker
Contested records
The legal status of national archives
by Charles Kecskemeti
1 3 African archives and the oral tradition
by AH A. Mazrui	
17 The 'Archives Agreement'
A modern approach to literary conservation and research
by Leopold Sedar Senghor
1 8 Unesco's library and archives
23 The riches of the Vatican library
by Alfonso Marie Stickler
24 A letter of credit drawn on the past
by Fiero Barucci
25 Grassroots of the pampas
by Cesar A. Garcia Belsunce
26 The computer revolution in research libraries
by Richard M. Dougherty
28 History off the record
The archives of a teaching age
by Eckhardt Franz
31 Sense and censorship
Behind the censor's blue pencil
by Peter Hanak
33 The Lenin Library
33 The new science of bibliology
by Anne-Marie Bianchi
34 A 'What's What' of libraries and archives
38 Unesco Newsroom
2 A time to live...
VENEZUELA: The magic harp
Back cover: The library of the 15th-century Lingshed monastery, Zaskar,
northern India. Stored in the huge, pigeon-hole bookshelves are many an¬
cient sacred Buddhist scriptures, including several volumes of the Kagyur
(the collected sayings of the Buddha) and the Tangyur (a book of commen¬
taries). The books consist of fine but strong sheets of rice-paper, with wood¬
cut printing on both sides. There is no binding, the sheets being simply
stacked together, wrapped in yellow or orange silk or brocade and clamped
between two planks of engraved wood. The volumes are identified by silk
labels.
Photo © Monique Pietri, Paris
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
Published monthly in 29 languages
by Unesco,
The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Malaysian
Korean
Swahili
Croato-Serb
Macedonian
Serbo-Croat
Slovene
Chinese
Bulgarian
Greek
Sinhala
Finnish
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French,
Spanish and Korean
ISSN 0041-5278
N° 2 - 1985 -OPI -85- 1 - 419 A
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
The memory of mankind
by Jorge Luis Borges
MY father's library was the crowning
event of my life. There, through my
father's voice, that mysterious thing
poetry was revealed to me, as were maps, and
illustrations, then more precious to me than the
printed word. There I discovered Grimm, Lewis
Carroll and the virtually infinite Thousand and One
Nights. Later I wrote in a poem:
and I imagined paradise
in the form of a library.
Seneca, in one of his letters to Lucilius, made fun
of a man who had a library of a hundred volumes.
In my long life I do not think I have read a hundred
volumes but I have dipped into rather more.
Above all, encyclopaedias: from Pliny to
Brockhaus, via Isidore of Seville, Diderot, and the
eleventh edition of the Britannica, the golden spines
of which I imagine in the motionless penumbra of
blindness, they are, for an idle and curious man the
most delightful of literary forms.
Libraries are the memory of mankind. An
infamous memory, said Shaw, but with it we shall
build a future which will resemble, however
slightly, our hopes.
The Argentine writer Jorge Luis Borges (born 1899) was director of his
country's National Library, in Buenos Aires, from 1955 to 1973.
-\*o
Domesday Book
The two volumes of which Domesday
Book consists are the outcome of a
general survey of England ordered by
William the Conqueror in 1085. Originally
known as the Book of Winchester, by the
mid-12th century it had acquired the
name of Domesday (the Day of Judge¬
ment) because there was no appeal from
It. The first volume, right, known as Great
Domesday, contains the final summariz¬
ed record ofall the counties surveyed ex¬
cept Essex, Norfolk and Suffolk. Accor¬
ding to a note at the end of the smaller
volume, the survey was made in 1086.
' ¿».Ute it-J . - - ar'. ftfe -".Win. ."« ,1*.
V.;- tUf.4iC1t|) " úi.vXVf It Siltul lirjalhul
Îtjj- - ,.L- JJt Lar. ^i' u4ui VIII Lit. m.A.-.TJ. lit-
ut ^hvt imuir 1*haWU¿Jit< lkq-.iflr.i-,. k.jf
. -i 1 itf I" UT " Ti.uiUi-^-ljniiU..*. ¿-if' '
[I, ¿ natu* it i*f.i i*ti.rïL"*-i- Loaual« W
-'-mïAn iV-w.Jfi (¿.^-ù^ni-wrui.
..*,.. If.-ff/íi -rfai. "
»IW* wiiiijrt ]k tf*rw\ nit -il aar*
taw. '-tai jlIL -m hJH««A' -,m liftTwiipi s».
ti-n n«Fa JÜuiL.TLt VJtïL^im .TL.L.t^jrtA'
iTïlfr^a ïih. 5^ ft^ul" li ¿l«w.ffïjW \jiVujr
ira-i«. ^«TV .r.triajtä'ii-.ir (HÚUfk,!*:
ftttajUta lr.ti:.f(-^i.i''.iHmi !l"i.|[.T
.«"half 7,i. türnnln'iíK^'"!, t**! -ii.k*4~»tt
... MT 1*1 tint fvt nL . Tí ujjt. Li. MIk w. u: i. (jj
- títua* iVarfi .LTnk-WVlfitti ï*4K>0t>OjàVl.
Utiv*. 'ÍÍÜ -itt-kViLT in-ïnV -*id^in.£|A.
Prt.-ïrnM^.f coAí.ílt*. mljwxptrtf.-infly.
lnEw^-i»' nffr-nna. AitK. -W'.i . Htfm inu
VJ&t .tt-W m.-Ji..l- fatal |«tuHlH|tV
*». fWfk üLUu' whufc- laVuj " tu«. «nt^T
-srtuA ¿Í. JUu3UlH4anr .«nil by !^lwplpJ^
|||: ^ty" "itf ni ,ifii -,-uA.Wnl ^f.,vA . dr' Ih U
*n ít^.-it. ^.»«líiíWiíi^-iMt.i*,'
jLtlat-áV Jfcatar iswi.«U*.lVi(uiif
-u. uJd ol.*ha»f"mjWJ¿,.*l.i#*Si«*«HF.
i t ¿T IL t. fbi (ùr-f 1 1- i*r i"Jr¿-J -tf W
te *
V ^ 1 fc.. £ . 1JW*. .«I"11* 1k*«rf«lt T«M a>£m.
'Ii*AtíL-rm'.-Hít ¡MP L*TKrrJfjT* ¿ttuntar
*»-* »*»(»»- wtnV««- B. .-.»jll»
U. ii» ai."« " ->"
fi twa i- hT'« tttV..U-«* . U-wktn
-- I».
lw Wut* ^H^tl^.^^-. .J
Í4J..II -trltniv. t*-1 - Vh.£ _ .^^¿¿U 3
A^»r^*^-t»iir»ÜMtl.hlíÍit.,,BlH
TrtUW*lUi-7^ L, V,,,ii^-W*¡3
-ii V -if \ti . fnfii. i"Jw Jí lili ít il + j^_ '
, V ujJU-iT.i: W fn*ij*rii Lft. -HiUIMIUH
^' lbwTFl* 3^. ïiTJfJ É-frft lu'
ri jt-iM.oiriitc^H.i^bi.-^j
... l^j^
MlW fui« l-HlV-UJlipt« LIH*^*J
i'.«Fi 4H-"-tlí..Mií W -ur^ltadlU.
J>lra.Vt Jfw" ^ mi»'»*" L^i"JtS"
bun Uut famr.-etut iAw7dl»uH|
v^4i;.xiM..c^.ltj..v íbpl-h-íH^V"
¿^mf*!**»-* .- J
m wctLrurt i-i* CllT-rltilf I^Pl I^N- M
diH^oa«"-« UJ'l.lao«! lrK-irt»>*
-. -.-w-i.^iaa
trfini.Tmini UUiw .nia roi,T« i_ SWl«tJ>->--->-^
ii^.t .«.air.f«i
Üt m'<\uflt- tivl
V i-»»(-r-il «T-
..« ik » ir--- * r-:Hi^'
VAiitjir-.W rfliii'jafrl
[L^ij.L^t-kpT.LvU Jr-7.-" .
_ Vil. "i SJlaW^'--~Z3
- à- hic.....h<i - --m '
.í *i.íirt, if wit fcW1 "'*r d
r^Mt^itai^ |n>¿^í-irt ir- «3f P"
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Libraries and archives
for tomorrow
by /. Stephen Parker
THE ability to communicate, not only
across great distances but also by
means of written and graphic
records, is a distinctively human
characteristic; and the creation, dissemina¬
tion, preservation and use of such records
are uniquely human activities which have
played a vital role in the development of
human civilization.
From earliest times organized collections
of records have been made for different
purposes. Libraries, as a rule, have brought
together records from many different
sources, for use particularly in research and
study. Archives, on the other hand, have
usually comprised collections of records
associated with a particular institution a
commercial firm, a government depart¬
ment, an academic institution or an entire
community brought together as a record
of its activities for administrative, legal or
historical reasons.
Broadly speaking, in many archives the
emphasis has been on preservation,
whereas, in libraries, greater emphasis has
usually been placed on use. Although it is
usually clear enough whether a particular
institution is a library or an archive (in fact,
many libraries contain collections of ar¬
chives and many archives maintain their
own libraries), the theoretical distinction
between them is by no means precise and
both may equally well be defined as "collec¬
tions of documentary or other records
organized for use".
The present century has seen an increas¬
ing emphasis on the final word of this
definition ("use") and the development of
ever more sophisticated and effective ways
of organizing such collections, of providing
guidance as to what they contain and of
providing a variety of services to their users
to help ensure that they are used to their
maximum advantage.
Documentation services, designed to pro¬
vide access to the contents of documents
through indexes, abstracts and the like, and
information services, intended to extract
flj.rHtft^.V.at * l'ff WMOtKl,
v'ai Li Htai t ¿Ufa >l-l. i Utaiai^
'V
_.iï**iUai
'-* .
,4'ájaVa.w.lWiH >--*d.,fcaJtM
M.«at-t-t *f*«ar. L4V..I. t,at
IvU^uMf.llaa
._«U""Lf.
jt au-' m J"** .-\ r- tnW". " Va-tajd"*
t^;l^,..*r'"^ 'S11"" **«
' l¿t>akr^fVrrü ,a.(Ja£
J ¿Hi t ¡-I*"- " IBi|tCal .
.{ J¡tat <*"< tf- lUK**' ' --i*. -'-¿.
R.iaJt-MtM «u ,-iwL tatr' t^ ij.ri.j^,,.
!*rlrrM n*Hr ' ¡ni' * ,* pwy^
r'Vbli-J pblfWtfÜ- ,
_Ä ;»*:'** Bai* |_1Tfrfta" vi 1tJ'i^.
» ki + jjf . lar,. ,. , J -,.
kWi t*""' -^*« "T.H" »Il «»1
*tait *-^' n'
P-Í* 'W «a* Tfr-HW.' ilTThlli! n jj^, |y
M«M-|buAk.|r.1.alfjr fwLaaWT V<-ft-
L : -4* .A t*. ifiÄ L* VH -LaW***
UttiftMlfciT HJ-htUpJf.^^Uf
7ftt(Ör "Tjrt lu-u*. L
V,lW , Ka^.WÜ* ^
| íi iprW un AUntfiL j^-iVhV T^wlWiqÎ'jlç»
«InltWC wiUW^iiaWult
7 -j« *i+.i. or;' Lin- «< kvi -"vü Jb.
^Wtr^.t^ftvi.^^U^^au,^^^
-If *i. KaU- " t,. 4( ^ ^A^ïa,^!-
^1-1.1 tk..Ua.altV-.,Iir»LS_ _,.l^|
-.' ¿aar' ^itT-aalau »L^^tatLiajltf &
P< MM»WÍvlatíii..¿jf_
ltH-L.l-4eJA,.-.|.íi,'ta.a.lW»- 	 [_.
t a\ "taJt L^f-^atLà..'
^¡, ^r^**lUl» t» ht- Mut U1UUH1.Ë,
m-TU«utal jh¿ -rit. ^rfaWli, .i.
*lV.i-i.tl^^,,tiJkl-.L,'l«*iî7t^'1l,
ViaT-uta.,-. 6k*. -H--.1T--
Í-P.dt'-a WtoiaúW -4-»w
L;Muir,tlUattlá;.-if«Jijr; ^-- ^
I »., »atHjiUl^.^.
Jííú XJifc-'IbiniiLi.k
IfV**'WJt ut. ltd'
itWr-j^- IV.N.lJí.aUaJl
,.., te í. «».Bt.
l-aaa*! |>» PtrtHJTitteU.
1 . LLtaU jí
Jiffwifsfcl^w^ii»««»!;,, y,
napfi. atóla, f -*j^i [n *-u taw. ^r'
-* v, tara j»,
ffcvalt -fot^ttal Ja,t*W*L^-tJíiüt
tv*^ a. . LtT. \yO jr.ii A -i' Il T' lirUtf fíj
	 la:J. i aJ¿J7_ a. j=- r^V, .JV.Vjif^
¡(LutlBieni liiMmimil'm
It-W* * -ttwMtí-ali -i~»W
«al«. .¿ It d. ._t . U
1S*i ataáat ttmJ,^LM|it" l,|jl ' fea,* l^
-..i3 ~ - . ^ a. ,;.(. .aj,- ¿ _
Val.. LvUJ ni .ÖT "^
from documentary and other sources
precisely those items of information re¬
quired by the user, have become increasing¬
ly important in recent years as the volume
of documents being produced throughout
the world has itself increased at an exponen¬
tial rate, as the needs of users have become
ever more sophisticated and as
developments in information technology
have made it possible to manipulate the vast
amounts of information now being
generated.
To meet potential users' vast range of
needs, a wide variety of institutions and ser¬
vices have been developed. In recent years
national, university, public, school and
special libraries, mobile libraries and
library services to the housebound and the
hospital patient, specialized documentation
and information services and archives in all
fields have been established with increasing
frequency.
The traditional demand for the complete
document is still being met, in many cases,
by allowing it to be studied in a reference
library or reading room, or by making it
available for loan; it may now also be met
by delivering a copy of the document, either
full size or in microform, and either by post
or by telefacsimile. The complete texts of
many documents are now being stored in
computer systems and made available for
consultation, possibly thousandsf of
kilometres away from the computer, either
on the screen of a visual display unit or in
paper copy produced on another com¬
puter's printer.
Computers also make it possible to
search the entire texts of such documents
for key words or phrases and thus to supply
users with specific items of information
without having to reproduce the document
in full. The identification of specific
documents, whatever their format, is now
made infinitely easier and quicker through
the creation of computerized bibliographic
databases containing millions of references
to documents of all kinds published in
almost all parts of the world. Computerized
databanks containing statistical and scien¬
tific data may also now be consulted
directly.
There have been suggestions that such
systems will one day render libraries and ar¬
chives obsolete, but it seems more likely
that, as with other modern communications
technologies such as television, they will
supplement existing methods rather than
supplant them, becoming generally ac¬
cepted particularly in those areas, such as
the provision of specific items of factual or
bibliographic information, where they are
clearly superior to traditional methods.
It must be recognized also that many of
the new mediafloppy discs, magnetic
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
tapes, laser discs, etc. are themselves
documentary records and thus are suscep¬
tible to the techniques of organization and
management which have been developed
and employed in libraries and archives for
many years.
The new media also bring new problems
for librarians and archivists. A record
which is created and permanently stored in
a computer may never have a hard copy
capable of being preserved in a conven¬
tional archive. Indeed, some documents are
specifically intended to be modified at will
by certain groups of users and thus may
never have, even in electronic format, an
identifiable "master" or archival text
which can be recognized as such for record
purposes. Even those which do have such a
master text, particularly if they are in
magnetic format, may create serious prob¬
lems of preservation and storage for
archivists.
Reference was made earlier to
bibliographic databases which may contain
references to documents published in
almost any part of the world. One difficult
and sensitive problem associated with the
new information technology is the great
and growing disparity between rich and
poor countries, not only in terms of gaining
access to such systems, but also in the extent
to which information which they
themselves have generated is made available
through such systems.
^SAs*.
Not only are the vast majority of the
computerized databases and databanks
located in the richer countries of the in¬
dustrialized world, chiefly in Europe and
North America, but an overwhelming pro¬
portion of the information they contain is
generated in and relates to the interests of
these same countries.
Access to such databases from almost
any part of the world where suitable
telecommunications facilities exist is cer- .
tainly possible, but it is often prohibitively
expensive, not only in terms of the charges
imposed by the information providers for
the use of the databases, but also in
telecommunications costs. Furthermore,
the information obtained at such expense is
often of only marginal relevance to the
needs and problems of the developing
world.
This is not a new problem. Librarians in
the developing countries have for many
years been faced with a lack of adequate
supplies of books and periodicals in local
languages that are relevant to local needs.
This raises the further problem of obtaining
foreign exchange to buy the only available
alternatives: expensive foreign books of
little relevance to their users' needs.
The need for programmes of book
development to help redress this imbalance
has long been recognized and, in some
countries significant progress has been
made. The growing dominance of the new
information technologies, exhibiting a
similar bias towards the interests of the in¬
dustrialized countries, suggests that the
time has come to devise and implement
similar programmes of information
development which will help the developing
countries to become more self-sufficient in
this respect.
Unesco has been concerned with these
problems ever since its inception. Its ac¬
tivities in the fields of library and book
development, often undertaken in col¬
laboration with other inter-governmental
and non-governmental bodies, have played
a major part, not only in drawing attention
to these problems, but also, in some cases at
least, in helping to solve them.
Unesco supports, for example, the ef¬
forts of the International Federation of
Library Associations and Institutions
(IFLA) to develop worldwide programmes
for Universal Bibliographic Control (UBC)
and Universal Availability of Publications
(UAP), whilst its own Records and Ar¬
chives Management Programme (RAMP),
which operates within the framework of the
Unesco General Information Programme,
is implemented in close collaboration with
the International Council on Archives
(ICA).
Within the framework of its UNISIST
programme (also part of the General In]or-
mation Programme), Unesco has, since
1971, been collaborating with the Interna¬
tional Council of Scientific Unions (ICSU)
and with other international bodies in at¬
tempting to lay the foundations for a world
This 9th-century Chinese painting
depicts a Buddhist pilgrim heavily laden
with manuscripts. At his feet Is a serpent
anda tiger walks at his side. In the top left
hand corner a Buddha Is to be seen
seated on a lotus flower.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
scientific information system which would,
among other things, help to ensure a more
equitable distribution of scientific and
technological information throughout the
world.
These efforts are now also being applied
in support of the establishment of a global
information network under the auspices of
the United Nations itself, in accordance
with the recommendations ' of the United
Nations Conference on Science and
Technology for Development (UNCSTD),
held in Vienna in 1979.
Despite the changes being brought about
by the introduction of new information
technology, there seems little doubt that
libraries and archives will continue to be
needed throughout the world in the
foreseeable future. A well organized library
is much more than just a source of informa¬
tion, and a well organized archive is not
merely a repository of facts. The impor¬
tance of both types of institution lies in the
fact that, in their different ways, they bring
documents into physical juxtaposition, in
an environment conducive to their study;
this provides an opportunity not merely for
the retrieval of known facts but also for
seeking knowledge, inspiration and wisdom,
as well as recreation and enlightenment.
J. STEPHEN PARKER, of the United
Kingdom, is editor of the new international
journal Information Development and chair¬
man and managing director of Library
Development Consultants International Ltd.,
Bath, England. He was the first director of the
National Library Service of Botswana and has
undertaken assignments for many national
and international bodies. From 1981 to 1982
he was editor of the Unesco Journal of Infor¬
mation Science, Librarlanshlp and Archives.
In 1983, the Library of Congress of the
United States began experiments with
analog vldeodisks for storage and
retrieval of graphic and photographic
materials In colour. Already researchers
are using this system for speedy, non¬
destructive access to precious and fragile
visual materials. Experiments are also be¬
ing conducted with optical digital disks
that store Incredible quantities of print
material with high resolution. A one-sided
12-Inch digital disk can store between
10,000 and 20,000 pages of text depen¬
ding on the resolution required. One side
of an analog disk can store up to 54,000
Images. Above, the "Juke-box", a
machine that stores and retrieves Library
of Congress optical disks. This new
technology offers Improved storage
retrieval and preservation combined with
greater flexibility of access.
One of theJewels of the State Archives of
Luxembourg Is a series ofdrawings taken
from the list of quit-rents due to the
Benedictine Abbey of Saint Wlllibrord.
The list was drawn up around the year
1600 by the Abbot Jean Bertels
(1544-1607) and the drawings with which
he Illustrated It constitute a rich source of
Information about the people, the towns
and the countryside of the region at the
turn of the 16th century. The caption to
the drawing right reads: This place Is call¬
ed "Der Roost". It pays us à tithe for the
crops. This makes twelve maldres (Middle
English "melder", a measure of grain).
yLK KOOgT
*Mli 	 i-tt.	 if i a .
\.
'
. . 'w.>-.-.|gjp¡
-JA-J
-JL....L ^fi , ^ïil Äoi>t«r r,'
O C li/^ «jOaÀA. 7,,, .fW ^^^
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Riicur (A- "Robinson i¿r//s son Tflc
Universal
bibliographic
control
With the increasing growth of interna¬
tional exchange of information, it has
become indispensable to harmonize na¬
tional bibliographic systems and to
make them compatible. This is the
main purpose of the Universal
Bibliographic Control (UBC) pro¬
gramme, launched by the International
Federation of Library Associations and
Institutions (IFLA) and with which
Unesco became associated in 1974. In
the words of Günther Pflug, Director-
General of the Deutsche Bibliothek,
Frankfurt (Fed. Rep. of Germany), the
UBC "is intended to guarantee univer¬
sal information about literary produc¬
tion on a country-by-country basis.
One of the most important tasks of this
programme is undoubtedly to promote
the creation of national bibliographies
in those countries where they have not
yet been introduced". The aim
therefore is to strengthen national
bibliographic control and to develop
and bring into use international stan¬
dards and other normative tools. The
programme's essential practical aim is
to prevent duplication of efforts in
cataloguing and bibliographic
recording.
Founded in Munich in 1948 by Jella Lep-
man, the International Youth Library Is
the only central library In the world
specializing In literature for children and
young people. Since 1953 It has been an
Associated Project of Unesco, and In
1969 Unesco donated to It 28,000 books
from the International Bureau of Educa¬
tion in Geneva. In 1982 its holdings totall¬
ed some 380,000 volumes In over 120
languages, and new acquisitions
amounted to 15,000 each year. The
Library has a historic collection of 50,000
books for children and young people
published before 1945. Left, an illustra¬
tion from the Library's edition of The Life
and Surprising Adventures of Robinson
Crusoe, published In Amsterdam In 1721.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Contested records
The legal status of national archives
by Charles Kecskemeti
ARCHIVES are tools of government,
indispensable for the management
.of a country's affairs. In Europe
this circumstance led as early as the seven¬
teenth century to the widespread adoption
of a juridico-diplomatie practice whereby
agreements made when there was a change
of sovereignty over a given piece of territory
(and such changes were frequent after wars
or settlements between ruling houses)
regularly made provision for the exchange
or remittance of archives. Research in 1977
produced a list, not claimed to be ex¬
haustive, of 157 agreements of this kind
concluded since 1601. But this practice,
however deeply entrenched it may have
been, did not lead to the establishment of
international standards for the cession and
sharing of archives, and as a result the pro¬
visions of different agreements vary to a
startling extent. The only generally observ¬
ed practice was that the originals or copies
of documents necessary for the conduct of
routine affairs were handed over to the suc¬
cessor State.
The absence of established doctrine had
very serious consequences when the col¬
onial system was wound up. With few ex¬
ceptions, the achievement of independence
by the former colonies did not give rise to
agreements regarding the devolution of ar¬
chives. The measures taken by the colonial
powers did not obey any single logic and
ranged from the return of all documents to
return on a selective, albeit massive, basis.
Apart from certain countries such as
Algeria or India which made known their
claims immediately after independence, this
de facto situation seemed to be implicitly
accepted everywhere. Clearly this was an il¬
lusion, and it was inevitable that the ques¬
tion would be raised sooner or later at the
international level since an essential part of
the historical evidence relating to over a
hundred countries was (and still is) outside
their national frontiers.
The matter was put before Unesco's
General Conference in 1974, and since at¬
titudes were firmly entrenched a prolonged
controversy might have been feared. This
was avoided thanks to. Unesco's insistence
on drawing up, as rapidly as the complexity
of the problem allowed, a document accep¬
table to all its Member States. Work carried
out over a four-year period in collaboration
with the International Council on Archives
The first page of the law of 7 messidor
year II (25 June 1 794) promulgated by the
National Convention, the revolutionary
assembly which founded the first French
Republic In 1792. The law broke new
ground in placing all the archives of a
country under the control of a "central
depository" and established free access
to public archives for all citizens.
led to the development of an entirely new
intellectual approach.
A general typology was proposed, for ap¬
plication to the vast range of situations in
which disputes involving archives could
arise :
A change in sovereignty over a ter¬
ritory without the creation of a new State
(territorial claims, although increasingly
rare, still exist);
The transfer of archives during wars
or as a consequence of military occupation;
The creation of new States as a result
of the disintegration of existing political en¬
tities (Bangladesh is a recent example);
Situations created by decolonization,
each calling for a specific approach: the
return of archives to the metropolitan coun¬
try; the existence of archives of regional col¬
onial administrative services relating to
/l*M¿, ¿la ÍT.l^MLilM^av« ST
Ukc/i-MM"
DÉCRE
DÉ LA CONVENTION NATL
)u g^/^^a? - jour ie ¿f/hdJ/tkyi l'an deuxiê!
République frahçaife une et indivisible- ¡
Ap /titit .
t- sSti
" I !
ï; ¡s ,
k <^ î=
f-C' tt*&/nJi'ej^->^átuir/¿£.
i §N ~íuíOO ^ziffyj HffW**fta^9a**t¿tt£jr
Jj "" at^(if¿íi¿/j¿t( c).t.¿i-Á&a&- &Vin<-^?iMltí- ou-j&âiiù sitz, &&ç_ï
J ¡5AÄ*i«L_a,
fé
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
-/	 -'/-- ,-íf «- ¿\,
¡9.* W: . W ¿¿3 ...'^-- L- »-'Mg* &J fit
' t*,*,~t 7*-* ^ ^- *V .\.
tajá *J* *-**?[
' .-
tfV l "* P*?¿. fl-
*£ >~- H: ¿t,".^a-t
>
'*** r ./its fjfi*i -rr* *t *>'
'*Mrrt* i fur* Çt-t*** * --Am1 Cjllpf
iV>if fr+fmj 4ta/ jÍí"* í^ar ^frn.Ä+4-f* , * .^tertr
1/ f1* 'H' B+rnf i>* iAfrimf^ iiti.vrr/r rrjr r
I fTT-f f-^H t ri ¡ Fr r- . iCfliafJ eÄ J /i r > i r i r- r* j-ij</f '
f' (me* Jr' mtThrvrvr tA' inirñj»Vw>i^
>V;IIIPrV*.
>«r flo ^ \ y Va*
The last page of the will of William Shakespeare,
dated 25 March 1616 (the poet died on 23 April).
The signatures at the foot of each of the docu¬
ment's three pages are the only specimens of
Shakespeare's own hand. This one, tremulously
written, reads: "By me William Shakpeare".
Text of the oath sworn by Pedro I,
emperor of Brazil from 1822 to 1831, after
promulgation of the country 's first
constitution.
T-^ai alCraO- a^t4WOJ
*V _ C^^44T *¿n ****** r*ir/"
^\. «jJEafy-ffuftt-. f-H
^ta+aaEj^i^t-
tVi'fh fh/s autograph document dated 25 June
1924 Albert Einstein accepted his re-election as
a member of the international committee for in¬
tellectual co-operation created by the League of
Nations.
£, ^
p. ^ . out so. ^
aULlLI	 g Ji -S.A-S-I
PBOFPSED D e C_L -V J / ^J-&.J8
fta a^oHlilMat of th^Unltad Síhtau or J*-M rios rt&4 tha
OÖTftaTLLaBnt Id tho Limitad, Kuigaoci, o-oinn; ;n*t tcaathttt-.. floe^ It
right to mía« knoim oertftUa caa.iün prliMilpL.il in th» nú t lana1
iclislaa of their ro^pectlts countr-loa on which thay btoi*
thalr hnva» far * líítttf futLir* íor th* íarld.
Pint, ttnïlp countrl« aa*K na nrü.ranai«manta.
Ht i-r-i ",'jri f: I út -jta-.or -.
SMund, thay deeiPiT to- Aq tOrrltoriAt aluiTijai
tJiíit 4p nit Atiuna. ylth tí» fr*o]j *iDTfl*aci irlniiee ar ttio
7-CT..lflfj fiorttnrïKJtla.
Thlri, thor r*íi>att t-tvB Tlfiht üf nil ícojaloB to {¡hmnu
«La rom uí flrTvomnon'; intiltr ntLicíi tlwy »ijl li-foj and thiiy
to («a eoverolan rieht* alad ae lT-p;v¿ «unarj t raatorod to
thú*c Hila tia*í.- Doan rorallil? dorr itcd. of ttn^:.
Psurth* ta-iíjy lili ûnionvoiir, tíüi 4tk ra»iioot ta tr.eli*
aviating all Llj&ti on b * te fUptlaap tha nn] oycioJit tj nil >»w4*.
nf ciaauBflF l^i nnjunl tor^ttf tn the tpailt: anil ta tï.o Mr»
^iterlal* tf tho Torld líiiah nj-c noatlcd r*p t^ulr ocohonlc
ppDaporltía.
Pirthj. tiLCry .lflftirc to bring a'tj^J* t.iiv rmlBot »llrib-
oration botitqap mu tittiena In the vctfi riml ç Tlvld v.'IUi tho
object of ooouritifi for ri]tl p*a»hi^j^cjvr:.. 1-bc::- u tfji¿f .^a :
oconomla ^4r ^jta.iA t onl dcoIqI httcwlvr-1~"^^^*r^m4^p
Bl rti-i t aatfury rtíp* ta aút ont^bl lg ted. -^nj)/r afttr the
final acBtaruetl«! or the tfaEL Tr^rSiray'Tlînc it «ill nflord
?ill natlcitia tho j.icna.n cf ¿wlj 11 lnrj iii fcvaiTJf:-1 '.il thin thoi
ort hounidíLPlaa, r:r.(l which »111 orf-Wd Uinratu **3rrt'
fm itli.ft-ei.Ft thtj,' nay 11t0 «* thut« Lives in fraodnn tí
fcinr rjid nrjat.
Ilshth» thay oolioïi: thr-t all af tjio n-^tJ-Mis of ttii. \ LnnA
'ltÚinu»t lniiLrjiJLli[il Iw ullft to the ^íúrLurtrieiJat of (¡ha Mac'
fare*. niXttftih TrlitLííl .e^o^ jjini be rKilht?,lti(*fl tr "XaxA,
/WaJ-r; aoa ap nLr r. coritlpiic ta bo «¡cloyed by naîlcmo *hlah
thrcBt or mry thront cftj. a£Eraaal£Hi ontaldo of tholr
ffontl upbi^ thoy bol i cr^i taTL-it tha ilataarrmrticji t of »nah nAtlín*
1« oiflçTitiAl jciiiIanTB^h^ofltAlljj^itÊnt sf r. wlilcr i:n¿^or¿^
^crmËiÛBÎ* -A-Mitmi &J aanriphl aeC
¡flaunt fluí «f all äthDr jaW etica^blëpo^pi; r- a irtilah Till, llilita
TOT - r. CC- lovU i ¿ IjCOÜÜB thii [jt f fiH B I Tr b^ídOD úf ftPIBaftBatl.
jijiaüAt ia- l*4J
(n August 1941, Winston Churchill and
Franklin D. Roosevelt met at sea and pro¬
claimed the Atlantic Charter, the prin¬
ciples of which foreshadowed those of
the United Nations Charter of 1945.
Above, draft of the Atlantic Charter dated
12 August 1941. Corrections and amend¬
ments are in Churchill's own hand.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
During the Second World War, Warsaw,
the capital of Poland, was 90 per cent
destroyed by the Nazi occupation forces.
When the city was rebuilt, archive
documents provided essential informa¬
tion, especially for the reconstruction of
the old quarter. Right, 16th-century
engraving of the city is taken from The
Capitals of Europe, a guide to the sources
for the history of their architecture and
construction (1980), an international
publication (bilingual: French and
English) produced on the initiative of the
International Council on Archives with
the financial assistance of Unesco.
I» several independent States; the existence of
archives created and preserved in the
metropolitan countries, etc.
With the same purpose of obtaining a
consensus, certain concepts were for¬
mulated to enable the parties concerned in
bilateral negotiations to "speak the same
language". Principles which were invalid
because of their imprecision also had to be
brushed aside. One of these was the notion
of "territorial relevance" which lent itself
. to widely divergent interpretations and in
the past gave rise to veritable "massacres"
of archives. The classic case of this was the
dismemberment of documents, with dif¬
ferent pages going to different places
depending on the information in them, car¬
ried out in accordance wjth the Treaty of
Turin concluded in 1 8 1 6 between Savoy and
Geneva.
It was also necessary to define a special
status for holdings of archives which are of
equal interest to countries with a shared
history and which if dismembered would
lose all value as sources of information. The
formula adopted here was that of common
heritage, with the physical conservation of
archives being entrusted to one of the part¬
ners and the same rights of access and copy¬
ing being recognized for the others.
Finally, Unesco rallied the international
community in support of a key idea, of
the need to undertake a task of historic im¬
portance: the reconstitution of archive
heritages through the transfer of
microfilms.
This is a formidable challenge. Counting
only the most fully stocked archives in eight
former metropolitan countries (Belgium,
The National Archives building of
Malaysia, Kuala Lumpur. It was built In
1982 with Unesco aid, In accordance with
the latest standards. In order to provide
the best possible conditions for the
preservation of documents, a system of
air conditioning maintains a constant
temperature and humidity level, and the
emission of ultra-violet rays by the
lighting system has been reduced to a
minimum.
Spain, the United States, France, Italy, the
Netherlands, Portugal and the United
Kingdom), the total number of photos to be
taken probably amounts to somewhere in
the region of 250 million, representing
almost a century of uninterrupted work for
twenty-five technicians. This does not of
course include preliminary filing and inven¬
tory work which it would be pointless to try
to calculate in terms of time and money.
Without special resources, the systematic
microfilming of archives for countries
wishing to reconstitute their heritage is out
of the question. At the rate at which routine
operations are currently taking place, and
the production capacities of archive
laboratories rule out any acceleration, this
task would take a thousand or two thou¬
sand years, perhaps more. This is not to be
wondered at, for after all these documents
are the result of work done by thousands of
officials, officers, magistrates, lawyers and
sailors during one, two or three centuries.
Nevertheless, these figures and specula¬
tions about cost should neither cause alarm
nor obscure the practical aspects of the
problem. A vast microfilming programme
à A
for the developing countries can be under¬
taken on three conditions:
that financial resources should be
available over a long period to enable the
archives involved to increase the productive
capacity of their studios and workshops;
that action should be planned at the
international level in order to use such pro¬
ductive capacity to the full;
that conditions for the reception of
the microfilms should be the responsibility
of the public record offices of the countries
wishing to reconstitute their heritage by this
means.
The third millennium is at hand. It would
be neither reasonable nor fitting to
postpone to the twenty-first century a task
which is perfectly feasible today.
CHARLES KECSKEMETI, of France, has
been executive secretary of the International
Council on Archives since 1969. He is the
author ofmany articles, including two studies,
published by Unesco, on the settlement of
disputes involving archives.
ï jr1 '""-i
h
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
African archives
and the oral tradition
by Ali A. Mazrui
HOW important are archives for
Africa? Do we not have more
serious problems of malnutri¬
tion, ignorance, disease, political instabili¬
ty, and general underdevelopment?
Let me answer the question indirectly. In
one of the Sherlock Holmes stories by Sir
Arthur Conan Doyle there is a reference to
the dog that did not bark. The importance
of the evidence was negative. If the dog on
guard had not barked, the intruder must
have been someone familiar to the dog. The
dog's silence was the devastating piece of
evidence, the telling clue.
My concern in this essay is with the
historical importance of something equally
negative the comparative weakness of the
archival tradition in Africa and its
devastating consequences for the history of
our people. Africa was silent about its
history; the African archival dog did not
bark at crucial moments. This had serious
consequences for Africa's place in interna¬
tional stratification.
The archival tradition may be defined,
quite simply, as a cultural preoccupation
with keeping records, a tradition of captur¬
ing the past through preserved documenta¬
tion. This means much more than
establishing national archives; it means a
particular propensity for recording the
dates of births and marriages, collecting
maps, preserving love letters, and keeping
household accounts, as well as documen¬
ting treaties, contracts and the like. Because
the archival tradition was weak in Africa,
the scientific tradition became weak, our
languages atrophied and so did philosoph¬
ical tradition with ghastly consequences
for our peoples across the centuries.
Why was the archival tradition weak in
Africa? Firstly because most indigenous
African cultures refuse to regard the past as
a bygone or the present as transient. The
ancestors are still with us and we ourselves
In Africa the cultural heritage Is largely
sustained by the oral tradition, which
Unesco has systematically studied and
encouraged In many ways. In Mall, In
1983, the Organization launched a pilot
rural "audiotheque" experiment with
several original features. The com¬
munities concerned are given copies of
the recordings they make as well as
equipment enabling them to listen In and
make other recordings whenever they
wish. Left, villagers of Mana listen to a
recording.
will be ancestors. If the present is not tran¬
sient why bother to record it?
A related reason for the weakness of the
archival tradition in African cultures is the
weakness of the calendar tradition (in¬
cluding the tradition of the clock). Many of
my fellow students in Mombasa, Kenya, in
the 1940s did not know when they were
born. The first president of my country,
President Jomo Kenyatta, did not know
when he was born.
There is a Gregorian calendar, an Islamic
calendar, an Indian calendar, a Chinese
calendar but no African calendar apart
from the revised Orthodox Christian calen¬
dar of Ethiopia.
The third reason for the weakness of the
archival tradition in Africa is the weakness
of the written word. Many African societies
have only come to know the written word
during the last century.
This is not to say that Africa is uniform.
Quite apart from other differences the con¬
tinent as a whole operates within a triple
heritage of culture. This triple heritage con¬
sists of indigenous, Islamic and Western
traditions.
Modern archives are mainly Western in
conception, and they are also Islamic to
some extent. But can they be indigenized?
Or are they inevitably part of the imported
sections of Africa's triple heritage?
To the extent that archives until recently
have been viewed almost entirely as collec¬
tions of written records, the indigenous
aspects of ,the triple heritage have not been
viewed as archival material. Muslim Africa
has been better endowed with written
records than non-Muslim indigenous
Africa. These records in Islamic societies
have sometimes been in the Arabic
language, but they have also sometimes
been in African languages using the Arabic
script.
But what is a document? Here we are
mainly concerned with the written word.
But there are five categories of documenta¬
tion in all:
Material documentation such as ar¬
chaeological evidence, from pottery to
Great Zimbabwe, from skeletons to coins.
Written documentation: a mystical
reverence for the symbols of literacy has
conditioned our view of what constitutes ar¬
chival relevance itself.
Pictorial documentation, including
painting or carving on rocks.
Sound documentation, which is in some
ways the newest form of archival record.
But the oldest form of documentation is
the raw memory of man, a capacity to
"recollect in tranquillity".
Two concepts are useful in approaching
the question of archives in Africa, the con¬
cept of documentary deficit and the concept
of primordial surplus. Documentary deficit
concerns an -apparent excess of silence in
African historiography, a shortage of
recognized documentation in the written
and material fields.
Primordial surplus can take a variety of
forms. Here I am particularly concerned
with a surplus of allegiance to primordial
identities, a commitment to ethnicity or
religious sectarianism.
The problem of documentation has af¬
fected Africa in two very complex ways.
One is the crisis of documentary deficit in
the material and written remains; the other
is the crisis of primordial surplus in the area
of raw human memory. The past is strongly
with us. Materially, Africa has had relative¬
ly few stone monuments, few hard
documents of the past. Great Zimbabwe is
striking partly because of its very
uniqueness.
But the crisis of the documentary deficit
also extends to the area of written remains.
Among the great cultures of the world,
African civilizations have had less written
records than average. For a long time this
literary deficit resulted in the assumption
that Africa was a continent without history.
Did this negative cultural image condemn
Africans to centuries of marginality and
servitude? Was the slave trade partly a case
of cross-cultural images? Was colonialism
partly a product of cultural perceptions of
racial hierarchy? Did Africa's documentary
deficit sentence the continent to the lowest
stratum in the ranking order of global
privilege?
Why did Europeans pick on Africans to
enslave? Why did they not enslave Arabs or
south Asians? Partly because the cultural
distance between Europeans and Africans
was deemed to be particularly wide. It was
partly the absence of castles, cathedrals and
written contracts in Africa which made the
civilizational gap appear so wide.
Africa's crisis of documentary deficit had
a good deal to do with the origins of racism.
Civilizations were often evaluated in terms
of either concrete remains or written»»
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Mansa Musa (prob. d. 1332), one of the
most prestigious rulers of the Mall Em¬
pire, is depicted In this detail from a map
of Africa by Johanes Viladestes (1428).
The map Is one of a number of Important
early modern maps produced at Majorca
in the 14th and 15th centuries.
records. Most of Black Africa seemed to
have neither.
The crisis of documentary deficit had
related implications for science and
philosophy. The absence of the written
word deprived much of Africa of the boun¬
ty of cumulative heresy. Africa's oral tradi¬
tion was a tradition which tended to
transmit consensus rather than dissent,
what was agreed upon rather than what was
rejected by the establishment.
Where were Africa's Platos and Lockes,
Rousseaus and Lenins? Most of them lie in
the graveyard of consensus, in the cemetery
of the oral tradition. Brilliant Africans fail¬
ed to surface above village life, genius was
too steeped in the oral non-literate legacy of
rural Africa.
Who would ever have heard of Karl Marx
in the twentieth century if he had operated
in a completely oral tradition in nineteenth-
century Europe? The written word was
needed to preserve Karl Marx's heresies in
his own formulation.
But while the oral tradition is an illustra¬
tion of documentary deficit in material and
written remains, it may also illustrate the
dynamism of raw human memory in
Africa.
The question which arises in the twentieth
century is whether that raw human memory
is a case of surplus primordial documenta¬
tion! Is there too much raw documenta¬
tion? Are ordinary Africans remembering
too much of their origins and their past? Is
the past too present among us? Is the pre¬
sent refusing to be transient and
temporary?
In the second half of the twentieth cen¬
tury the most obstinate aspect of primordial
surplus is the resilience of ethnic identity.
The great majority of Africans refuse to
forget their primordial origins, be they
Baganda or Acholi, Luo or Kikuyu, Shona
or Ndebele, Hausa, Yoruba or Ibo. The
resilience of ethnic identity is a resilience of
documentation at the level of raw human
memory, for better or for worse. Ethnicity
is an archive, stacked with documents of the
annals of the "tribe", the records of com¬
munity, the memory of collective identity.
This situation has had repercussions in
the post-colonial period. Surplus ethnic
identity has outweighed deficit class con¬
sciousness in Africa. A Hausa peasant is a
Hausa first and a peasant second when the
political chips are down.
Deficit class consciousness in Africa was
compounded by deficit literary documenta¬
tion. Why is it that it is a socio-linguistic im¬
possibility for an African to be a
sophisticated Marxist without being at the
same time highly Westernized? One cannot
be a sophisticated Marxist without exposure
to the works of Marx, Engels, Lenin, and
other ideological founding fathers. But
these works are not available in African in¬
digenous languages ("vernaculars"). Ac¬
cess to sophisticated Marxism must
therefore be through a sophisticated com¬
mand of a European language. A non-
Westernized African Marxist is for the time
being a contradiction in terms.
In the origins of European socialism,
history was used as evidence against the
past. That is what Marx and Engels meant
by viewing all events as an agony of class
struggle. In contrast, some African
socialists have tended to view history as
evidence in favour of the past. Tradition
has been seen as primordial collectivism,
concern for the disadvantaged and univer¬
sal hospitality.
European use of written archives resulted
in a view of socialism as an interruption,
sometimes as a drastic revolution, designed
as a fundamental departure from the past.
On the other hand, African socialism in
some countries has emerged as a doctrine of
continuity, a link with ancient life-styles.
While European socialism has proclaim¬
ed a negation of the European past, African
socialism has often proclaimed a reaffirma¬
tion of African ancestors. While Karl Marx
at the British Museum was using archives as
allies in social revolution, African socialists
later looked for archives to vindicate
cultural revivalism.
Zimbabwe: history on tape
IN rural Zimbabwe as in other African countries where the oral
tradition is strong, when meetings are held to settle
succession disputes and the affairs of the community, the
successful claimants are often those who support their case with
the fullest genealogical and historical details. In recent years
such gatherings have attracted, in addition to those directly con¬
cerned with their outcome, observer-historians from the National
Archives of Zimbabwe, which since 1977 has been carrying out
a wide-ranging project for recording and preserving the coun¬
try's oral history and traditions. The meetings not only often pro¬
vide a gold mine of information in themselves; they also put the
historians who attend them on the track of prospective infor¬
mants who can be interviewed later on.
The reasoning behind the Oral History Programme is that the
oral traditions of pre-literate people serve the same purposes as
archives and museums in literate societies. The task of preserv¬
ing this material is all the more urgent since accelerating moder¬
nization is sweeping away traditional history and lore and many
valuable reminiscences will be lost forever if they are not record¬
ed by the present generation. The Zimbabwe programme is be¬
ing carried out in the country's three major languages, Shona,
Ndebele and English. Historians tape free-ranging interviews in
these languages with informants located in a variety of ways, in¬
cluding publicity given to the programme by the radio and the
local press. The interviews are then transcribed, translated and
edited by the historians before being catalogued and indexed by
the librarian who makes the information available to the public.
In this way a data bank of material has been assembled, ranging
from genealogies, narratives, parables, stories, myths and
legends, to songs, poems and ritual dialogue.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
But it is not just ideology and philosophy
which pose questions about continuity and
change. Science also needs a built-in prin¬
ciple of instabilitya readiness to be
challenged by heresy.
African science and technology were too
stable. Major paradigm shifts were too
rare. When it is too stable, science becomes
stagnant. But was not African science
unstable in another sense? Since it was
taught through the oral tradition, was it not
subject to variation from mouth to mouth?
The answer is yes. Science passed through
word of mouth is vulnerable; but this is the
instability of imprecision rather than the in¬
stability of careful revision.
Those African languages which were not
written were also unstable. They changed
too fast. It is harder to understand a
nineteenth-century African poem even in
Kiswahili than to understand a nineteenth-
century English poem. Many Africans are
more eager to learn the imperial European
languages than to protect indigenous
languages. Linguistic patriotism is weak
partly because of the weakness of the ar¬
chival tradition.
What then is the new archival order for
Africa? In his Ode on Intimations of
Immortality the English poet William
Wordsworth talked about the child being
father to the man. In the West the national
archive was the child of the archival tradi¬
tion. The national archive was a conse¬
quence of a pre-existent cultural preoccupa¬
tion with record-keeping. In Africa the na¬
tional archive may have to father the ar¬
chival tradition or at least help that tradi¬
tion become strong.
More than dusty documents are at stake.
We must stop believing that the present is
not temporary, that the past is still with us
even if we do nothing to preserve its
records. We must learn to keep accounts,
record births, marriages and deaths, keep
picture albums, and protect contracts.
Perhaps above all, we need not only to
respect intellectual heresies, but also to
create a climate where they do not perish in¬
to unrecorded oblivion. A new archival
order in Africa could help change the conti¬
nent fundamentally. And a world with a
fundamentally different Africa cannot but
be a fundamentally different world.
ALI MAZRUI, of Kenya, is Research Pro¬
fessor at the University of Jos in Nigeria and
Professor of Political Science and of Afro-
American and African Studies at the Univer¬
sity of Michigan, Ann Arbor. He is the author
of A World Federation of Cultures: An African
Perspective (1976), Africa's International
Relations 11977) and Political Values and the
Educated Class in Africa (1978). The present
text has been extracted from a paper
presented by Prof. Mazrui at the Seventh Bien¬
nial Conference and Seminar of the East and
Central African Regional Branch of the Inter¬
national Council on Archives, held in Harare,
Zimbabwe, in 1982.
In 1981 the Jamaican Government took
steps to create a Cultural Heritage
"Memory Bank" dedicated to the
documentation and preservation of tradi¬
tional forms of culture such as dances
and rituals, and the experiences and
knowledge possessed by many elderly
persons. In 1982 the project received the
support of Unesco's International Fund
for the Promotion of Culture. Above, a
farmer (right) explains how cassava Is
cultivated. Beside him sits the Memory
Bank interviewer with three other farmers
listening Intently.
The episcopal conference of Chile, with
the aid of Unesco 's International Fund for
the Promotion of Culture, Is engaged on a
programme designed to collect, record
andpublish traditionalpeasant songs and
to hold festivals at which these songs are
performed, thereby preserving one of the
oldest forms ofpopular literature In Latin
America. Below, the Chilean singer
Manuel Gallardo.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
, (ti (wlTL^at Cptia,
tí |fc«.S
^"^tr^La^
cauta
l*U. U «J_¿ t^i^ , Ç« JU* ,tjÄata~.
¿ta ^^a^^. ^ Jt-^tHL.
it*íiw: j
. «t -^ÍHLaL.A**-^ tVÍ. fu
Far left, an anonymous caricature of the
Guatemalan novelist and poet Miguel
Angel Asturias, who was awarded the
Nobel Prize for Literature In 1967. Left, a
manuscript page of El Árbol de la Cruz
("The Tree of the Cross"), an unfinished
and unpublished text by Asturias who
donated it with his other manuscripts to
the Bibliothèque Nationale in Paris, to be
used In establishing an International
critical edition of his complete works. So
far five titles have been published In the
Asturias collection which Is supported by
Unesco's International Fund for the Pro¬
motion of Culture.
^f OME twelve years ago, the Guate-
^k malan writer Miguel Angel Asturias
U (1899 to 1974) donated his manu¬
scripts and archives to the French Biblio¬
thèque Nationale with the twofoldpurpose
ofensuring thephysicalpreservation ofhis
writings and making possible the establish¬
ment of an international critical edition of
his complete works. Under the aegis of the
Association of the Friends of Miguel Angel
Asturias, whose secretary-general is the
Italian literary specialist Amos Segala and
whose international scientific council is
headed by Leopold Sédar Senghor, several
volumes of this critical edition have already
appeared.
With this experience behind them, the
Association and its French and interna¬
tional partners have enlarged the scope of
this initiative by establishing a new project,
the Archives de la Littérature Latino-
Américaine, des Caraïbes et Africaine du
XX« Siècle.
The objective of this international pro¬
ject is to ensure the preservation and
dissemination of manuscripts of contem¬
porary authors of Latin America, the
Caribbean and Africa. A number ofscien¬
tific institutions are collaborating in the
project, including the French Centre Na
tional de la Recherche Scientifique, the
Italian Consiglio Nazionale delle Ricerce,
the Spanish Consejo Superior de Investiga¬
ciones Scientificas, the Portuguese Instituto
Nacional de Investigacäo Científica and the
National Libraries of Latin America and
the Caribbean.
Just as with the manuscripts donated by
Asturias to the French Bibliothèque Na¬
tionale, the manuscripts of Latin
American, Caribbean and African authors
will be systematically catalogued before be¬
ing preserved and microfilmed. Students
and researchers will have access to these
document collections which will be as ex¬
haustive as possible. In addition, a team of
specialists drawn from both the regional
and international scientific communities
will be entrusted with the task of
establishing a new international collection
ofcritical editions ofmajor works from all
the countries ofeach ofthe regions concern¬
ed. The collection will thus contribute to an
adjustment ofthe balance ofcritical assess¬
ment of the literary history of these regions
during the twentieth century and to a wider
and more accurate understanding of their
literature.
From the start, this unprecedented,
multilateral co-operative undertaking, en
compassing three continents, received sup¬
port from Unesco and, in particular, from
the International Fund for the Promotion
ofCulture. Itformspart of the wider move¬
ment for the safeguarding of the cultural
heritage of mankind, laying emphasis on
that vital but none the less vulnerable part
ofit, the manuscripts ofmodern authors, as
defined at the World Conference on
Cultural Policies (MONDIACULT) which
was held In Mexico in 1982 and which is one
of the major preoccupations of Unesco.
Furthermore, the Archives de la Littérature
Latino-Américaine, des Caraïbes et Afri¬
caine, together with the Association of the
Friends of Miguel Angel Asturias, con¬
stitute a Non-Governmental Organization
with official consultative status vis-à-vis
Unesco.
The signing in Buenos Aires, in
September 1984, of the Archives Agree¬
ment byfour Latin American countries and
four Latin countries ofEurope marked the
birth of the collection Archives de la Lit¬
térature Latino-Américaine du XXe Siècle.
We publish below extracts from a speech
made on the occasion of the signing by
LeopoldSédar Senghor, one ofthe most ac¬
tive promoters of this new "dialogue bet¬
ween cultures".
The Alejo Carpentler Cultural Promotion
Centre, Inaugurated In Havana In 1982,
has Its headquarters In the house, left,
which provided the famous writer with In¬
spiration for the setting of his novel El
Siglo de las Luces (published In English
under the title Explosion In a Cathedral).
The Centre, which promotes Carpentler's
work and contemporary Cuban literature
and music In general, seeks to carry out
cultural exchanges with similar Institu¬
tions In other countries.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The 'Archives Agreement'
A modern approach
to literary conservation and research
by Leopold Sédar Senghor
IT must be confessed that to bring together eight
countries Argentina, Brazil, Colombia, Mexico,
France, Italy, Portugal and Spain in a long-term
programme such as the Archives Agreement is a very con¬
siderable achievement.
Yet this alliance in a common cause was no chance occur¬
rence. At the Mondiacult Conference of 1982, judging by the
welcome received by the proposals I made there on this sub¬
ject, a movement was born, a unanimous will to save from
perdition, from the flames of a second Alexandria, the word
that tells us and future generations the meaning and purpose
of our existence.
AH at once, in this world of sound and fury, the word of
the poet seemed alone and defenceless against the ravages of
time and human malevolence.
The purpose of the Archives programme is, first, to
safeguard a hitherto neglected part of our cultural
heritage the manuscripts of contemporary authors and
then to research them and to publish critical editions. It in¬
augurates new forms of scientific co-operation and cultural
solidarity which, I am sure, will create a precedent that other
regions of the world will take as an example and adapt to
meet their own specific requirements. The Archives Agree¬
ment comes at a critical moment, at a time when it is the
general opinion that the revival of letters in our region is be¬
ing spearheaded by the poetry and narrative prose of Latin
America and the Caribbean, which has its roots deep in the
collective imagination of our peoples.
Today is born a great literary collection, since it consists
of over a hundred titles, from twenty-two countries of the
region and in the four main languages spoken there. The key
aspect, however, is that these texts will be treated with the
consideration until now reserved for the great Latin and
Greek classics. You will allow me, as a man of letters myself,
to say how much I rejoice in this new respect accorded to our
own writings, a respect which will be ensured by both the
geographic and the disciplinary diversity of the groups of
researchers (over five hundred specialists will be involved)
associated with this initiative.
Unaccustomed as they have always been to working
together, and consequently to knowing and appreciating one
another, despite a language, a history and a Weltanschauung
which ought to bring them closer together rather than
separate them, the Latin American countries are now em¬
barking, for a significant span of time, upon a series of ex¬
changes, a sharing of literary experiences and of cultural
messages which will be so many factors of integration, of real
rapprochement, less spectacular perhaps than the declara¬
tions of politicians, but far more significant and effective.
Another aspect of the Archives Agreement which seems to
me to be of capital importance is the participation of the four
Latin countries of Europe which, for reasons of con¬
sanguinity or history, are deeply and irreversibly bound to
Latin America. Just as the Latin American countries involv¬
ed have, as it were/rejected their traditional nationalism in
favour of a global, unifying vision of history and culture, so
the Latin countries of Europe are collaborating in an act of
solidarity towards a region with regard to which each of them
had formulated individual policies and jealously maintained
agreements, both covert and overt, often obtained at the ex¬
pense of their neighbours.
Under the Agreement, the Latin countries of Europe are
pledged to help each country of the region, by its own ef¬
forts, to rise above that level of communication, both inter¬
nal and external, below which it would be severely handicap¬
ped and prevented from taking its rightful place as a full
member of the cultural community to which it belongs.
The Archives Agreement means profound and practical
innovation both in Latin America and in the Latin countries
of Europe as well as in the interrelationships between them.
As proof of this may I cite Portugal's proposal to adopt the
methodology and structures of the Archives collection in
launching a collection of authors from the four Latin coun¬
tries of Europe concerned. This proposal brings a new
equilibrium and a new and important dimension to the scope
of the cultural dialogue envisaged. Since the proposal in¬
volves Fernando Pessoa, the greatest Portuguese poet of the
twentieth century, it confirms the will and the opportunity of
making the Archives Agreement the favoured instrument of
a real cultural exchange across the Atlantic.
Going further still, the delegates of the eight countries par¬
ty to the Archives Agreement, at my suggestion, are appeal¬
ing for a suitable technical and juridical instrument to be
placed before the twenty-third General Conference of
Unesco in which all aspects of the safeguard of and access to
authors' manuscripts as well as of their reproduction on
microfilm and the publication of critical editions would be
covered at national, regional and international levels. The
fact that a document similar to that which we propose, but
which was concerned with moving images, was adopted at
the General Conference of Unesco held in Belgrade, in 1981,
gives grounds for hope that a satisfactory solution will be
found for the written word, as yet unprotected or assured of
free communication by any convention.
It is high time, before the bulk of these riches is lost to us,
for an international debate to be engaged which would lay
down the broad outlines of an objective policy of preserva¬
tion and exchange.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Unesco's library
and archives
ORGANIZATIONS like Unesco
need a library "to give access
to knowledge" and to furnish the
printed information necessary for the per¬
sonnel in their work. In fact, the Unesco
central Library is the focal point of a
house-wide network of sectoral documen¬
tation centres which together serve the
programme specialists . and the
secretariat units.
With 100,000 volumes kept up to date
and 2,200 serials, including periodicals,
the Library is in a position to answer any
questions that may arise in the course of
the work of Unesco. Under certain condi¬
tions the Library is also open to outside
researchers.
The Library, however, is not merely a
collection of books; it is also a cataloguing
and indexing unit for Unesco's own
documents and publications. The best
and most detailed source of information
on what Unesco issues is to be found in
the Unesco List of Documents and
Publications, a printed and computerized
reference tool available in main libraries
and documentation centres throughout
the world and accessible on-line at
Unesco headquarters. The data base now
contains about 60,000 document
references available for consultation in
paper form and also on microfiches pro¬
duced by the Unesco Microfiche Service.
A Systems Development Section main¬
tains and develops the computer software
necessary for indexing. This programme,
called Isis, is also available to Member
States free of charge.
The Library is an organized collection of
books, while the Archives incorporate all
the records created or received by the
Organization in the course of its activities.
Unesco's archival documents are the
natural and unavoidable result of its work.
They comprise files, letters, memos,
speeches, working and meeting
documents, budgets, plans, programmes,
agreements, photographs, tapes, etc., all
reflecting faithfully the action taken in the
execution of the Organization's pro¬
gramme. Unesco's archival documents
are open, according to the established
rules, to researchers and students and all
other interested persons can consult
Unesco's published documents in the Ar¬
chives reading room.
The services described above are the respon¬
sibility of the Unesco Library, Archives and
Documentation Services, Programme Support
Sector.
Colour pages
Opposite page
The first Surah (section) from a two-
volume Qur'an preserved In the Egyptian
National Library, Cairo, whose current
holdings total 1.5 million volumes and in¬
clude one of the world 's finest collections
of Arabic manuscripts.
Photo © Martin Lings/World of Islam Festival Trust
Centre pages
Left: An illuminated page from the 12th-
century Latin "Bible of the Pantheon",
one of the treasures of the Vatican
Library. It depicts four Old Testament
scenes: (from top to bottom) the journey
of Jacob and his family to Egypt; Moses
and the Hebrews constructing the Taber¬
nacle; the Lévites carrying the Ark of the
Covenant; Moses consecrates his brother
Aaron as high priest. The Bible of the Pan¬
theon Is exhibited In the Library's Sistine
Hall, with a number of other ancient edi¬
tions of the Bible.
Photo © Vatican Library, Rome
Right: The world-famous library of the
former abbey of St. Gallen (Switzerland)
contains 100,000 printed books, 2,000
manuscripts and 1,700 Incunabula, which
provide an almost unrivalled source of In¬
formation for historians of the Middle
Ages. Many of the manuscripts show
Celtic Influence and are elaborately Il¬
luminated. Photo shows a detail from one
of the library's treasures, the Irish
Evangelary (750 AD). The apostle Luke Is
depicted standing before a throne and
holding the Gospels. Above the halo Is an
ox, St. Luke's symbol.
Photo © Stiftsbibliothek St. Gallen, Switzerland
Three Non-Governmental Organizations
working
in partnership with Unesco
The International Federation
of Library Associations
and Institutions (IFLA).
Founded in 1927, the Federation is a non¬
profit organization whose aim is to pro¬
mote international discussion, co-operation
and research on all aspects of library ac¬
tivities. It collects, collates and publishes in¬
formation concerning libraries,
bibliography and documentation services as
well as on professional training.
International Council
on Archives (ICA).
The Council is the world professional
organization for archives and archivists.
Founded in 1948, its main objectives are to
promote and encourage the preservation
and use of the world's rich archival
heritage.
International Federation
for Documentation (FID)
Founded in 1895 as the International In¬
stitute of Bibliography, the Federation
adopted its present name in 1938. Its aims
are to promote, through international co¬
operation, studies and research on and the
organization and practice of information
science in all fields, including science,
technology, the social sciences and the
humanities.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
-S k TB a* V.TJ --.J ^»*. "-^ L
%^VrA>ráYi'ii<"""""i.
Qn°nQnQ o n o no
lift
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
»^^ >^
«£>=?* ö
' 1 X. itiVrl
1 >~íii' .T
1
ÉBS&
jagg
lssS5
1
SS J
M
5^,1 ¿^¿^¿^¡^Ê^M 1
*VH^^%V j&Sr^^* ajfaaafl
irm i v HCjS**?^,»,^k
^Jt1""' S Bull B
» _ __ t
.a» J J
Above, the Sistlne Hall of the Vatican Library In Rome.
The riches of the Vatican library
THE Vatican Library was officially founded by Pope Sixtus
IV on 15 June 1475 by the Bull Ad decorem militantis Ec-
clesiae. By that date however the papal library already had
a long history. It contained collections of ancient manuscripts
assembled by earlier Popes following a tradition which began with
Damasus in the fourth century and was continued by Boniface VIII
(during whose pontificate the first catalogue was produced) and by
its first real promoter, the humanist Pope Nicolas V who opened the
Library to the public and left at his death over 1,500 manuscripts.
In 1481 the Library possessed 3,500 manuscripts acquired by
papal envoys throughout Europe. The contents of other works were
recorded for posterity by a throng of copyists. The humanist preoc¬
cupations of this period, which were welcomed and encouraged by
the Popes, not only included the holy scriptures, patrological and
theological works, but also extended to secular texts: philosophy,
literature (Greek, Latin, Hebrew, Syriac, Copt and Arabic), law,
history, art, architecture and music. The Vatican Library still
perpetuates this humanist tradition today.
The heritage constituted by successive Popes has been enriched
by the donation, acquisition or deposit of entire libraries. Some of
the most important libraries in Europe thus came into the hands of
the Vatican Library. Notable among them are the Palatine Library
of Heidelberg (1622), the libraries of the dukes of Urbino (1657),
Colour page opposite
Detail from a rare 15th-century Ethiopian
Illuminated manuscript on parchment
preserved In the Bibliothèque Nationale,
Paris, shows David playing the lyre. One
of the world's oldest libraries, the
Bibliothèque Nationale was originally the
Royal Library. First opened to the public
In 1692, It became State property during
the Revolution and was renamed the
Bibliothèque Nationale In 1795.
Photo © Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
of Queen Christina (1690), and of many patrician families, as well
as holdings from churches and other Vatican institutions such as the
basilica of St. Peter and the Sistine Chapel. The Library also houses
a store of archives whose riches are still unexplored.
The holdings of the Vatican Library today total some 70,000
manuscripts, 8,000 early printed books (incunabula), and a million
printed works. They also include major collections of prints (over
100,000), maps, handwritten documents (some 200,000), tens of
thousands of archive documents, coins and medals, and even art
objects of all kinds housed in the oldest part of the Vatican
museums, which is under the supervision of the Library.
The Vatican Library has. a restoration laboratory and a
photographic laboratory. It publishes works and distributes them
through its own bookshop. The Library is managed by a prefect
(the scientific and administrative director) under the supervision of
the Cardinal librarian.
The Library is dedicated exclusively to research and access to it
is limited to scholars and specialists. Each day it is used by an
average of 120 readers, sometimes as many as 180.
Alfonso Marie Stickler
pro-Librarian
of the Holy See
Left, ornamental letter from a 15th-
century "Life of Alexander the Great"
produced at Naples for king Alfonso of
Aragon and now preserved In the Vatican
Library. The profile of the young Alex¬
ander Is depicted In the medallion.
(Another masterpiece In the Library Is
shown on colour page 20).
Photo © BICE/Vatican Library, Rome
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
A letter of credit drawn
on the past
by Piero Baruca
POLITICAL and cultural institu¬
tions, as well as industrial enter¬
prises and banks often feel the need
to look back to their origins, perhaps in
order to find in their past history the
dynamism they need to overcome the dif¬
ficulties of the present. This may account
for the current widespread interest in
business archives, which contain documen¬
tary evidence of the activities of a business
enterprise since its foundation. Such ar¬
chives can help a business to become aware
of roots which although ancient are still im¬
portant to it.
The Monte dei Paschi bank of Siena is an
example of this phenomenon. One of Italy's
leading credit establishments and the head
of a major financial group of five banks,
the Monte dei Paschi has had an eventful
history that stretches back for five cen¬
turies, and is scrupulously recorded in its ar¬
chives which cover the period from 1568 to
1872.
Today preserved in the Palazzo della
Roca Salimbeni in Siena, right next door to
the headquarters of the bank, this major
deposit occupies over 330 metres of shelf
space. Also exhibited in the great salon of
the Palazzo are precious objects connected
with the life of the bank, ranging from seals
(the oldest dating back to the 16th century),
letters of credit some of which were drawn
up in the 17th century, and old letters of ex¬
change. Most of the post-1872 documents
are preserved in other premises of the bank.
Strangely enough, any account of the
Monte dei Paschi archives must begin with
documents which are preserved elsewhere,
not because they have been scattered or
destroyed, but because of the special cir¬
cumstances attending the bank's creation.
Founded in 1472 on the initiative of the Free
Republic of Siena, it was considered initial¬
ly as an institution of the State, and its ac¬
tivities were strictly regulated. Consequent¬
ly bank documents dating from the period
of Siena's political autonomy until 1555
were treated on a par with official
municipal documents and later deposited
with them in the local public record office.
The public nature of the bank when it was
founded and during the early years of its ac¬
tivity was confirmed when Siena lost its in¬
dependence, and the Medicis of Florence
recognized the bank's special status. Since
then the bank has been closely involved in
the country's social and economic life.
The activities of the period following the
reform in status of 1568, whereby the bank
obtained administrative autonomy, are ful¬
ly recorded in the documents preserved in
its archives which run without a break from
1568 to the present and were enriched with
the addition to the bank of a savings bank,
founded in 1833, and a building finance
house.
With the unification of Italy, one result
of which was to extend the bank's field of
activity, a process of internal and external
reorganization began. After the deposit of
its statutes in 1872, its structure was
modified and it was divided into several
autonomous enterprises.
Today the historic archives of the Monte
dei Paschi have become an important in¬
stitution devoted to organizing a mass of
documentary material which is of in¬
estimable value as a source of information
for scholarly research into Italian economic
history and whose quantity and diversity
are constantly growing.
PIERO BARUCCI, of Italy, has been presi¬
dent of the Monte dei Paschi bank and finance
house, Siena, since 1983. He formerly taught
economics at the universities of Siena and
Florence. A member of the American
Economic Association and the Royal
Economic Association of the UK, he is the
author of many published works on economic
questions.
Two ancient documents conserved In the
historical archives of Monte del Paschi,
Siena, Italy. Left, a typical bank credit
note, Issued In 1624. Right, the first
known example (1646) of a printed letter
of credit.
3N VACAB.LE DE' PASjCHl
A. S.
T/r U Ctmfr* cht hs/mtím :* J*' .*:< feJ*J-< tJ 'l i¡ .. j .
tuo$i di dm* Montr per fffi^jt di ftjMt trHfi frr t**f? dt foe fttf< fvma . nur i ftmítjfi
W"^**' > f Ctfitoh ¿KÍfscjft Htü ' JJMftrißim ¿Utrera dt Bait* /tá} j.¿ .Vohi-nirr tfl*.
Im V¡rfmdiJÍ4 frt/i/ilr erdi/iUfiJ JÍfC-fm*r/t^ ixiiro, rit for* périt itmfi . du/r*\_J dds-
tjvu ¿lernt p.tfii stfkJdttti ,f ftndf tio^tu Ftxxv
ftragai rWfö da íjj¡j . *¿m fit m-'fíUmauaitittt porZioxe , E di deluCûMpr* fr deifttj-
Z,*iitfitf>4£*r<ir Affmnfif *¡L'EtSr*i*Gcnrr*¡t & ^fh Àisntt , faun* ±4 ix fi. , c
ÖWr ra fiit hMiitA^,ßtUfi^*Upre/nttM^m^tf*r4fw^:r^I*J*iPri9yedi!m*nT»
A(-jfc ** » *fil**** <** noftr+fîtii* figiß ,
rj¿fa&tt ¡y zht¿ (pwAttsyt*
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Grassroots of the pampas
by Cesar A. Garcia Belsunce
T
"T was the first time a dentist had
come to the village, and I was his
first patient. There were no fa¬
cilities for anaesthetics in the village then. I.
was ten years old and they put me in a chair
opposite a hanging skeleton. The skull
seemed to be smiling, and I smiled back at
it. Then the lady who was helping the den¬
tist said to me, 'So that you won't be
frightened, I'll play the guitar for you while
the doctor is working.'" Seventy-five years
later the heroine of this adventure was
reminiscing into a tape-recorder and
describing what may have been the first ap¬
pearance of dentistry and music therapy in
Castelli, a village in the wet pampa of
Argentina, where a regional museum and
archive have recently been created.
This region, which bordered on Indian
territory until 1820, was inhabited by
native-born Argentinians and immigrants,
mostly Italians and Basques, who have
always had a strong sense of their past and
have withstood the impact of the modern
world with greater firmness than other
peoples in the region. As a consequence, the
area was chosen by the Latin-American Ar¬
chives Association for a pilot project on the
collection of data relating to its social
history. The idea was to collect
systematically all existing documentation in
private hands, such as letters, account-
books, school exercise books, photos, and
films, as well as the kind of eyewitness ac¬
count quoted above.
The National University of La Plata has
also launched an archaeological research
project in the same district and taken steps
to create a museum there, based on the cer¬
tainty that many traces of more or less
sedentary indigenous populations must sur¬
vive in this region rich in lagoons. In addi-
Photographs, post-cards, letters, oral
testimony, all these are grist to the mill of
the Museum and Regional Archive of
Castelli, Argentina, In its effort to create a
documentary record of the life of the
region. In these two photos, now In the ar¬
chives, can be seen (above left) a local
family, photographed In 1905, and (above
right) a viewof the village ofCastelliat the
beginning of the century.
tion to archaeological specimens, the
museum will collect and display objects
relating to the farming and stock-breeding
civilization which developed in the area
following its occupation by populations of
European origin, as well as examples of
animal and plant life in the local
environment.
The execution of these projects, which
were launched simultaneously in the middle
of 1983, was immediately co-ordinated,
although each retains its distinctive nature.
This co-ordination led to the creation on 8
August 1984 of the Castelli Regional
Museum and Archive. It is not yet open to
the public, but an inaugural exhibition has
already been held there with marked
success.
The written documents that have been
assembled provide interesting evidence
about the organization of social life at the
beginning of the century, and about such
matters as the cost of living and the way in
which contracts were drawn up. A mass of
photos vividly illustrate changing customs
and ways of living, notably the change from
traditional to modern dress, the evolution
of housing from humble cottages to opulent
estancias inspired by the manors and villas
of Europe, the floods which periodically hit
the region, and rural activities as they were
before the mechanization of agriculture.
Even more interesting are the eyewitness
oral histories. Old villagers have been inter¬
viewed and have told racy anecdotes about
the paternalistic relationship between the
land-owners and their "peons", and about
the political rivalry between radicals and
conservatives: "A long time ago, in the
1920s," said one, "the different parties
were always accusing each other of electoral
fraud. And so one day it was decided that
elections would be strictly supervised and
from then on the irregularities stopped. But
the ballot-boxes had to be taken by train to
the town of Dolores for the votes to be
counted and once, when the train was
winding its way along the banks of the
lagoon of Sevigné those who thought! they
had lost the election threw the boxes into
the water."
Both projects have been organized to en¬
courage the active participation of the
villagers. Volunteers are given instruction
by professional archivists, museologists and
archaeologists and when they have been
trained they are sent out to do fieldwork. In
Castelli today young people can be seen go¬
ing from house to house in search of
documents and museum objects, while
other volunteers excavate on the banks of
the Rio Salado.
CESAR A. GARCIA BELSUNCE, of Argen¬
tina, is a member of the Executive Committee
of the International Council on Archives and
chairman of the Latin-American Archives
Association. A former director ofhis country's
General Archives, he is the author of many
published works on archival and historical
themes. He is in charge of the project to col¬
lect social history documents which has given
rise to the museum and archives centre
described in this article.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The computer revolution
in research libraries
by Richard Dougherty
THE research library in the United
States today is more than simply a
vast reservoir of traditional books,
journals and microforms; its role has ex¬
panded and been enhanced to support
faculty and students in obtaining and utiliz¬
ing information resources. Furthermore, in
order to cope with the physical growth of
collections due to the vast increase in the
number of publications, libraries on many
college campuses have been dispersed and a
network of library outlets created. Staff of
the premier research libraries often number
several hundred and the functions they per¬
form are vastly different from those carried
out by their predecessors.
The impact of computer technology on
United States research libraries over the
past decade has been little short of spec¬
tacular. In the past ten to fifteen years there
has been a gradual evolution of the con¬
figuration, power and functions of these
systems. Ushered in by the appearance of
the Ohio College Library Center (OCLC)
computer network, the new technical
capabilities enabled libraries to share a
common data base in support of catalogu¬
ing operations. Without question the
OCLC system revolutionized the work of
technical services divisions of large
libraries. OCLC grew rapidly throughout
the 1970s until it now serves over 2,000
public, academic and special libraries and
the computer support system supports in
excess of 6,000 terminals.
A similar system developed by the
Research Libraries Group, called the
Research Libraries Information Network
(RLIN), was designed specifically to sup¬
port the programmes of research libraries.
Although the technology underlying OCLC
and RLIN are fundamentally different,
both systems are nationwide in scope and
are configured in a manner network experts
frequently refer to as "star networks", that
Right, the opening bars of one of thirty-
three hitherto unknown organ chorales
byJohann Sebastian Bach found last year
In the Yale University Library. The works,
which were contained In a volume of
manuscripts donated to Yale In 1873,
were Identified by Bach scholar and Pro¬
fessor of Music Christoph J. Wolff, while
he was working with the Yale Library on
the preparation of a new Bach
compendium.
is, with a centralized computer system
which is linked to distant libraries via
telecommunications .
In addition to such networks as OCLC
and RLIN, individual libraries such as those
of Northwestern University, Stanford
University and the University of Chicago,
have developed local on-line technical sup¬
port systems (for example, systems to han¬
dle book purchasing, accounting, serials
check-in, on-line cataloguing, etc). In the
late 1970s, commercial vendors also began
to make available "turn-key" systems
designed to support single operations such
as circulation and acquisitions.
Currently the provision of on-line
catalogues to replace the venerable card
catalogue is receiving the highest priority in
most university libraries. Studies that have
already been conducted by the Council on
Library Resources, Inc. reflect how much
more powerful the new catalogues are and
every indication is that they will be en¬
thusiastically accepted by the next genera¬
tion of library users.
In the next few years it will become com¬
mon for libraries to operate integrated
library systems which will tie together all the
traditional library support activities into a
single computer system. An integrated
library system will support the basic func¬
tions of circulation, acquisitions, accoun¬
ting, cataloguing of all materials, all aspects
of serials work, binding and inter-library
lending.
Perhaps more importantly these library
systems will be tied into campus networks
so that users will be able to access the
catalogues of neighbouring libraries.
At present there is a nationally-funded ef¬
fort to link together the computers of the
Library of Congress, the Research Libraries
Group, OCLC and the Washington Library
Network (a regional network which serves
the libraries of the north Pacific in the same
manner as the systems of OCLC and the
Research Libraries Group support their
members). When this Linked Systems Pro¬
ject is completed, it will become possible for
the major bibliographic utilities on the
North American continent to share records
among themselves and with the Library of
Congress.
Another major preoccupation of United
States librarians today is the physical
preservation of their collections. As P.N.
Banks, a noted expert on paper preserva¬
tion, warned in 1978, "it is safe to say that
the library environment is essentially hostile
to all forms of recorded materials". But the
severity of the problem did not gain general
recognition among research librarians until
the late 1970s. Even though preservation ex¬
perts had been issuing warnings for many
years, most library administrators were
under such extreme pressure to find ways to
increase inter-library lending and to
automate library operations that they had
little time to attend to the longer-term
danger of collection deterioration.
During the early 1980s the situation
changed rapidly and library staffs began to
look carefully at the condition of their col¬
lections. A survey conducted at the Univer-
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
sity of Michigan determined that, based on
1978 costs, expenditure in excess of forty
million dollars would be required to
preserve and to conserve all the volumes
that would require attention between 1978
and the end of the century. The results
reported by the University of Michigan
were typical of reports issued by other large
research libraries.
The financial dimensions of the preserva¬
tion problem are so staggering that most
universities will not be able to raise the
funds necessary to solve local problems.
Co-operative programmes, such as the
Research Library Group's microfilming
project, offer one of the few viable solu¬
tions, allowing libraries to work together
and to avoid unnecessary duplication of
microfilming activity. In the final analysis,
if the content of American libraries is to
survive for the use of future generations, it
will probably require the assistance of
private foundations and the intervention of
Federal programmes to augment the
resources made available by individual
universities.
The rapid growth in size and programmes
of research libraries has also brought about
great changes in the duties and respon¬
sibilities of professional librarians. Faculty
staff have played a less active role in the
development of library collections and this
work has been turned over to library
bibliographers and collection development
experts.
While the appearance of new technology
has created new opportunities for libraries,
the rapid changes caused by technology
have also caused a great deal of organiza¬
tional stress. Librarians are caught between
the opportunities afforded by technology
and the considerable strain of acquiring
new skills and developing new programmes.
Technology has enabled librarians to
play a more central role in providing faculty
and students with publications, informa¬
tion and data derived from bibliographic
and non-bibliographic data bases. In large
part librarians have been successful because
in recent years the profession has placed a
strong emphasis on preparing them to work
in an increasingly technological environ¬
ment. The major question facing academic
librarianship is what roles the librarian will
play in the years ahead.
American research libraries will embrace
new technology as it becomes available. For
example, libraries are already considering
how best to use the new video and optical
disc technologies. These new storage
systems linked to microcomputers will pro¬
vide opportunities to store vast amounts of
printed matter in the form of analog images
or as digitized data. The work at the Library
of Congress utilizing optical disc
technology suggests that this storage media
might very well solve the current preserva¬
tion crisis.
Librarians have been eminently suc¬
cessful in assisting students and researchers
in the use of data bases to obtain informa-
, UVtóWc
|' f^-.y "jfc-y+S,****^aíínnjrra^a-^-a+L-,
y
fj rtiff '/¿SSSrfef 'jfáSjfU. ra* at-aa-öV -*a" S*V -/*«y^^
... 	 U ,^a _.. ,aj£*ScXm\.rwS~< *** -'¿be**- -
JSSdCu
7¿.
f r . .*_...
*twtrt» aTi>i ., i,ar^-.a- 1 ¿r, ..nr, \ jmtt 	 T'
"' » J-aTWaatail-^rtfcff--* lùff M^F,*,?^ r -VÎf*-
\'uM tt "*" *"-*>-'
'ftp .mfri^ij-a*'. Vi- . r)£f . jt-«Jv.,^''Jaral" a>r*¿r.
,VllBlÍÍ|J J *-*£* Xtfjtrt«****^'»***'**?'-'"*
^-WA,,, itr^^a^*1<L^«.>ii^-*V^^^ , , J,
. r^ .; 	 ÜZtZ. m*¿¿mZ^¿p,^j:>~s^ joJü	 i*£- *«^"/J''" '%"* ^
rt'ÍÉC-VLVai.HtVl
fmlfUSt^.nJ ïu*.
HtV^^^íi^a^'lí^K'^i-^ad HnM^lTi
PV I ^ r ^. á ar-vr-a'aaí», J*' il-V^f.f ¿t£*jf **f H*^
. jt.-^-ií:i^ , . .-.arf^í^^-íi*
a^fe.aW^y»''' TT jifa aT. a,	 ,, , *>»tW7^- í^''/ iM^*.
jfrr^S'S*?-rp**tr Jft»mf/r
.^^ ,- J ^ . ^ ^^>^ 1
-.r.-p+^-tía-r.a-.arn^-ía-a-a-r . . at" . j-.af.. . _rí 	 f rf" J I iff 1>^I -afa.-~^-J -J -.J^ agLd^a, ,
¿^J ^rt) ^ . a V //Jia^tatt^-»;*/^-*^* ^ 'a^Ufi^>a^aWa^i^la-fw L
*f "V*1 W|H* 	 	 a!^ '
^-^W,aít*4^.^^a>^,^-^.t-^--:f*-a*~'^V-*<*!>-*
¿¿,.*<+ »* , a^L-.aij^r-^r-»-'«-^"^V"~
-ty.i^aá-^á^ . ...a- .. . aa 	 ?>jat¿
^ . /v^^.*/>1Çt^a»^^-í-*-^^^^^í^-^-'J'" : ~T ^_,Ä_t
.a-* a^ai^- * .aífT^^+^^-
Above, the first of the four parchment
pages of the Constitution of the United
States, signed on September 17, 1787. It
came Into force as part of the "supreme
law of the land" on June 21, 1788 when
NewHampshire became the ninth State to
ratify it. The first three words were highly
significant, since under the Constitution
the source of power became "We the
People". It Is the oldest written document
of Its kind In the world.
tion about the location of books and jour¬
nals. But our ability to deliver documents
has not kept pace with the improvements in
providing bibliographic access. Thus future
emphasis on improvements in document
delivery systems seems quite important.
One of the most important developments
will be the growing interdependence bet¬
ween libraries and campus computer cen¬
tres. These two campus support systems
have operated as independent organiza¬
tions, but as libraries become increasingly
dependent upon technology and computer
centres become more involved with the
delivery of information the need for these
two organizations to work more closely
together becomes more evident. Although it
is too early to say what changes are likely to
take place, it is possible that this growing
relationship will require changes in the way
libraries and computer centres are organiz¬
ed within the university governance system.
Writers such as Patricia Battin have
described a possible integration of these two
campus organizations. She foresees that
such an integration of library and com¬
puting agency, "each with its specific
strengths and expertise, will provide one-
stop shopping for the university community
as well as stabilizing planning mechanisms
for effective and flexible response to rapidly
changing technologies". Other writers
foresee a greater involvement in public
policy as the scope of problems such as
budgets, the need to capitalize expensive in¬
formation services and the problem of
preservation require institutional response
in the context of public policy.
In the longer term, those who formulate
public policy may come to realize that the
research libraries of universities comprise a
cohesive national resource rather than a
series of individual collections. The
technology necessary to link together the
libraries of the nation is rapidly becoming
available and affordable so that the chang¬
ing attitudes of legislators and government
officials toward the role of research
libraries could become a major develop¬
ment during the next generation.
RICHARD M. DOUGHERTY, of the USA, is
director of the university library and professor
of library science at the University of
Michigan. He is a member of the board of
governors of the Research Libraries Group. He
has edited a number of journals and is the
author of several books, notably Scientific
Management of Library Operations.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
History off the record
The archives of a teaching age
by Eckhardt Franz
	 Ll
WJ
Emblem of
International Youth Year
Photo © United Nations
KILLINGWORTH Middle School, in
the English county of Northumber¬
land. Twelve-year-olds are studying
history not the broad sweep of history as
found in the traditional textbook, but
history as it happened where they actually
live.
In a farmhouse on the Middleton Hall
estate they find the date 1811 carved over
the door. By consulting old land maps they
learn what the countryside looked like when
the house was built and that it took its name
from another house, now in ruins, that
stood farther up the hill.
The name of the first occupant of the
house is recorded in the county archives.
Here also is to be found the contract of
employment of shepherd Robert Burn,
which lists his duties and specifies that he is
to be paid in oats, barley and wheat and the
yield of a row of potatoes and grass for two
cows and sixty sheep.
The children's teacher discovered other
things too the building plans for the
manor house, showing the dining and living
rooms, bedrooms and a study, the farm ac¬
counts in which the life style and farming
methods of the past come to life far more
vividly than in the readymade textbook
presentation which makes the eighteenth
century seem as remote and impersonal as
the sagas of classical antiquity.
In the Federal Republic of Germany, at
the suggestion of former President Gustav
Heinemann, an annual competition has
been held for the past ten years for
schoolchildren who, in their own
neighbourhood, in the local library, the
local archives, among their friends and ac¬
quaintances, search for traces of the history
Children at work making paving-stones in
a quarry near Paris. This illustration, from
the Journal Illustré, dated October 15,
1871, was displayed In a mobile exhibi¬
tion on "Working Children of the 19th
Century", organized In 1984 by the
Departmental Archives of the Val de
Marne.
of, for example, the 1848-49 revolution, life
under the oppressive National Socialist
régime and the new start after 1945.
Three seventeen-year-olds in Darmstadt
have researched a national democratic
festival held in the summer of 1848 and
have made a comparative study of leaflets
and posters, newspaper reports and police
records. A detective-like reconstruction of
past events from frequently contradictory
sources also provoked critical reflections on
contemporary journalism. Pupils in
Kelsterbach-am-Main are investigating the
employment of prisoners of war and forced
labour in local factories. They are discover¬
ing tombstones, old photographs,
newspaper reports, lists of names and court
records. These speak more eloquently than
all the figures of anonymous millions in
history textbooks.
Schoolboy or schoolgirl in the archive,
archivist in the schoolthis does not quite
tally with the conventional image of the ar¬
chive as the silent, cloister-like haunt of
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
r
éí^cjjSSc^TSbctói^íSs^q ^)@jtsiSocx>¿ áoq.|jeá£gTJ&>r^
,*q8osî (¿öospiaSLXÖÄ) 6íSD6c-a«3t&j£>í¿)x^o^^
._ ^jOTi¡iwBr--fffi ,
»»iBtÍAAEÍl-a^ . ¿tta^tfkéjBËèt^^iftlt^aÂlI) - ^oí«Sgg^!S»î)jt.O** KJ&aî.
. {t^3wt^a^l^'¿'&-aBW¿->'t^ (¿JSL>f^*«BWlSB^«iai ..r1 .
l^lJla-a» . «ílJi^T^áAaííoriíteciaA»,
ÖisAefti^jLaiJati^Sriä^lwL, *»- »*
í«Üñ*»sí6if0eía
.flT-t.,. ^fljví
.»r-i»
Sfi*¿-. ,,**.»-
*V * aa*L-ÍA»i
:
:-*©
z
©
During the period of their occupation of
Ceylon (now Sri Lanka), the Dutch Issued
many Instructions to local officials. The
one reproduced here Is written In Sinhala
and Is dated 1738. The National Archive
ofSri Lanka has a considerable collection
of these documents, dating from 1641 to
1795, which throw much light on ad¬
ministrative, economic and social condi¬
tions of the period.
The first Issue of The Gleaner, a replica of
which we reproduce, right, waspublished
In September 1834 a few weeks after the
abolition of slavery. The replica of this
first Issue was publishedas a supplement
to the December 8, 1890 Issue of The
Gleaner, now a dally, and Jamaica's
oldest newspaper.
WrrLKWKSTf:l>'...SKl¡ ' I.Ki-. I"*"'
1 IMC (.laKANl-R,,
äuit ¡UÏUeh.ij \
COMPENDIUM OF NEWS.
.iJHtrrkn-.ijrUiriBH. .laTl
AaJ . #m **kr#X h SI
Wütt.ií UD i-rh.r.r..iHJiu f.-jy-
Vol, L Sut HT day Aft mimm. Sepl ¡¡¡¡¡W 13th, 1 SU, >.i. 1.
TO BE PUBLISHED \¿i£&r*
44-jhl* MÉfJW ** -
; btHln-fkiM, 'ib^i -<t^i i . Ç,|_ m Ji.i »Lia ITTmi. ** IlLE^^l w
fat unsw uuau, 3^-áSw^^"^
-111 p-L.ra.1«- auch 1- í»*r
l"* *^¡jTÍ 'bm nHYt* fe1 *
Tt mj í.*-. IWj|h SîJîïr,!"*
n^r-laiT* -Vi
	
1 r... ...i..*-
"l.Etí^ÍAnií-'" i Tar : ttTÉiÉf« ]>«ri»- ; ÍMk«, ¡ d w
V)
I t
o
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
T/i/s study o/ í/ie proportions of the
human body Is the work of the German ar¬
tist Albert Dürer (1471-1528). The draw¬
ing, which was made In 1513, Is from a
collection of Dürer sketches now con¬
served at Dresden.
scholars in which elderly researchers,
waited upon by dusty, attentive archivists,
turn over the pages of ancient folio
volumes, only occasionally disturbed by
some cheeky student preparing a doctorate
in history. The changed professional image
of today's archivist, who not only takes
good care of the documentary heritage en¬
trusted to him but tries to use it actively for
the political and historical education of a
wider public and of the younger generation,
coincides with a new trend in historical
research and the teaching of history.
Like other school subjects, history must
no longer be taught in classroom lectures
dealing in broad contexts and supported by
recitals of large1 quantities of facts and
figures. It must be learned by independent
personal effort. The sources thus consulted
gain in clarity and vividness if they originate
in familiar surroundings and relate to the
student's own region or even his or her
place of residence. This is facilitated by the
increased attention now being paid to
economic and social history.
Exhibitions of documents from archives
and school visits to archives were, of
course, organized in the past. But the tradi¬
tional school visit, with a short introduction
to the life, duties and working methods of
the archivist, a tour of the archives and a
presentation of selected documents, was
merely a last optional item, coming after
visits to the local newspaper office or sugar
factory.
Nowadays, classes or study groups of
schoolchildren come to the archives to
work, under the direction of teachers and
archivists, with documents relating to the
historical theme they are studying in class,
so that through their personal fréquenta¬
tion of the archives they can acquire a con¬
crete perception of the past and its
documentary sediments, a glimpse into the
world of historical research and an
awareness of the need for a critical ap¬
proach to historical sources.
A display of a limited number of
documents centred on a particular subject
of study in class, in whose selection atten¬
tion is paid to their informative value, meets
educational purposes much better than a
magnificent exhibition of the precious,
original and visually attractive documents
from an archive, or a large-scale represen¬
tative display which impresses and over¬
whelms by its richness and variety.
Experience in recent years has shown that
not only senior secondary school students
but also younger children, especially those
in the twelve-to-fifteen-year group, acquire
an added interest in history while working
on source documents. In England even
eight- to ten-year-old children in domestic
science classes in primary schools have been
known to work with archive documents.
Not all schoolchildren can visit an ar¬
chive. Not every town possesses an archive
that is under expert supervision and many
of the smaller ones lack adequate space to
work in. But archives now go out to the
public. For more than ten years the Hesse
State Archives have been holding travelling
exhibitions devoted to various aspects of
the region's history. Exhibitions on, for ex¬
ample, "Industrialization in Hesse" and
"Emigration from Hesse" have made two-
year tours visiting between twenty and thir¬
ty towns in the State and exhibiting not only
in public records offices and museums but
also in town halls, savings banks and
schools. Many teachers are already enquir¬
ing about the exhibition planned for next
year so that they can structure their courses
around it.
Transcending the topical value of an ex¬
hibition, so-called "archival teaching
units", comprising a limited number
The preamble to the
Constitution of India
which was adopted
by the Constituent
Assembly on
November 26 1949.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
(generally six to twelve) of facsimile
documents have been produced with the co¬
operation of public records offices. They
are accompanied where necessary by
transcriptions, translations and ex¬
planatory notes. Sets of transparencies with
accompanying explanatory texts serve a
similar purpose but they need to be sup¬
plemented by facsimile documents with
which the pupils themselves can work.
Archival teaching aids of this kind are
available in many States of the Federal
Republic. They cover a large number of
themes, especially economic and social
history, crafts and craftsmen of the past,
manufacturing and factories, road and
railway construction. More general
historical themes, such as the Reformation,
the Thirty Years War, the impact of the
French Revolution and the political strug¬
gles of the labour movement, also lend
themselves to illustration with documents
from the neighbourhood.
The archivist cannot cope unaided with
this new, additional task in the educational
field. Not all archivists have received
pedagogical training or have previous
teaching experience. If this work is to suc¬
ceed, there must be co-operation between
public records offices, school authorities,
teachers and archivists.
In France an organized Service éducatif
in the State and Departmental public ar¬
chives and the attachment of qualified
teachers to public archives, where they co¬
operate with archivists in organizing visits
and preparing exhibitions and archival
teaching units, goes back to the 1950s. In
the United Kingdom too, the functions of
the "Archive Education Officer" are
becoming more and more widely recogniz¬
ed. An essential condition for the develop¬
ment of this type of co-operation is that the
assistance of the public archives be made
use of in the training of teachers and the
running of guidance seminars for history
teachers and future teachers. Arrangements
of this kind are reported from many
countries.
"Archive and School" is a new and un¬
familiar concept for many archivists and
for most teachers. Several decades of prac¬
tice in France, and more recent experiments
and expert discussions in the United
Kingdom, the Netherlands and the Socialist
countries, show that this is an important
task and that the archivist can help the
teacher to instil new life into the historical
legacy of the past. It is also a task to which
particular weight should be attached in
Third World countries concerned for their
historical identity. A study planned for
1985 by Unesco's Records and Archives
Management Programme, on the theme
"Archives and Education", will develop
guidelines for future action from a com¬
parison of recent experiences in this
domain.
ECKHARDT G. FRANZ, of the Federal
Republic of Germany, is lecturer in archive
science at the Marburg school of archives, and
honorary professor of modern history at the
technical university of Darmstadt. He has car¬
ried out several missions for Unesco as a
specialist, notably to Beirut, Khartoum and
Tunis. He is the author of Einfuhrung in die Ar¬
chivkunde ("Introduction to Archive
Science", 1974) and many articles and
studies on history and archives.
Sense and censorship
Behind the censor's blue pencil by Peter Hanak
LARGE quantities of documents from
the censorship services of the old
Austro-Hungarian monarchy are
today preserved in the Kriegsarchiv in Vien¬
na and in the military history archives in
Budapest. Between 1916 and 1918 a thou¬
sand censors, grouped according to
language, examined from eight to ten
million letters a month, devoting particular
attention to correspondence with foreign
countries, soldiers and prisoners-of-war.
Letters considered to be harmless were sent
on untouched to their recipients; passages
in others were obliterated and some letters
were even confiscated. The obliterated
passages were scrupulously copied out by
the censors, and, with the confiscated let¬
ters, provided the basis for reports written
by the Censorship Office on the morale of
the troops and the civilian population. Half
a century later these documents have
become historical sources.
These letters and fragments of letters pro¬
vide the scholar with little reliable informa¬
tion about troop movements, casualties, the
output of factories or harvest yields. On the
other hand they do contain precious infor¬
mation about everyday life and about the
prevailing spirit in the army and the coun¬
try. Of course, the opinions expressed are
far too moderate and loyal to be totally
sincere, for their authors were quite aware
that their letters would pass through the
hands of the censor. But this in no way
detracts from the informativeness of the
materia], for reading between the lines it is
possible to discern grievances and news
which the writers ingeniously but vainly
sought to conceal from the censors.
Towards the end of the war, self-
censorship became notably more relaxed.
From Spring 1917 on, the letters reflect to a
fair extent what the population was think¬
ing and feeling. Some reports and extracts,
like those concerning the desertion of the
Serbs (1,300 extracts) or the repercussions
of the October Revolution in Russia are of
considerable interest to scholars. The
overall impression of revolutionary ferment
and of the radicalization of public opinion
which emerges from these letters written by
simple people is far more accurate than the
contents of a biassed press subject to
pressure from the authorities.
This material was highly suitable for
quantitative studies through the statistical
treatment of representative samples. But
the first step was to establish a grid of the
basic themes of popular thinking. To
analyse the state of mind of the population
between November 1917 and March 1918,
the author of this article took a sample of
1,500 letters, two-thirds of which had been
written by workers and peasants, and one-
third by intellectuals and middle class peo¬
ple. In view of the ethnic structure of the
monarchy, 46 per cent of the letters chosen
were written by Austrians and Hungarians,
and 54 per cent by members of other
nationalities.
The most common theme is that of social
discontent (inequalities between rich and
poor, boss and workman), which was ex¬
acerbated during the war and is evoked in
37 per cent of the letters, in which the lives
of the privileged, profiteers, and people in
easy jobs are contrasted with the sacrifices
of soldiers at the front and the poverty of
the workers. Then comes the question of'
work which is raised in 36 per cent of the let¬
ters, most of the complaints expressed at the
beginning of the war being motivated by the
disruption of normal activities. Thirdly,
patriotism, referred to in 27 per cent of the
letters, covers the conflict between loyalty
to the State (represented by the emperor)
and the nationalism of the different peoples
of the monarchy.
Social discontent, expressed in com¬
plaints against dire poverty, oppression and
flagrant inequalities, and in sympathy for
socialist movements and the Russian
Revolution, intensifies in all the national
groups as the months go by. The same
tendencies emerge from letters in which the
second theme appears, with nostalgia for
peace being transformed into positive
demands. The majority (60 per cent) of the
letters in the third group reveal the discon¬
tent caused by the oppression of the na¬
tionalities and a more or less explicit desire
for autonomy, although loyalty towards the
State remains firmly rooted.
Quantitative analysis of the letters con¬
firms the existence of a close correlation
between social discontent and a desire for
peace, and an inverse correlation between a
desire for social justice and peace on the one
hand, and aspirations for national
autonomy on the other. It seems that after
the Russian socialist revolution, the masses
were ready to accept the maintenance of the
system in exchange for an immediate peace,
a point of view not shared by the intellec¬
tuals of the oppressed nationalities. "Vic¬
tory is unnecessary, Russia is bringing
peace", the Austrian censor remarked.
"The people will soon put an end to all
that", noted the Czech censor. "We need
peace even at the price of a revolution," is
the message of the letters read by the
Hungarian censor. Strike movements at
that time illustrate the same state of mind.
As well as making a direct contribution to
our knowledge of the history of the First
World War, the systematic analysis of the
censorship archives in Vienna and Budapest
can help us, in a broader context, to under¬
stand the mechanisms which formed public
opinion and moulded public attitudes.
PETER HANAK, of Hungary, is professor of
the history of cultures at the Eotvos Lorant
university and director of research at the In¬
stitute of Historical Sciences of his country's
Academy of Sciences. His research is mainly
concerned with the history of the Austro-
Hungarian monarchy and with problems of
social and cultural history.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
£&fe
t htri Ib-atatot» <t*. "
ai.a.t,« a I- ha«» Ju«ac*
[| |f |ruu*'V *
rJ¡Sí*7^a--taw«. "fHiTÄÄSr S* T'tIkM-
, ,. ,pl,,i*i^JI'''"''',"!7i Jp* F-VA. ttil 3» Lai
__ p.. ""^ ** frJi t ^ an^nL^iÉ^É^ Émáxttini *r «h roui i f*** ^
- T" /'* rj* kM b*-* . * d« M * 1* l*>n*ï t« r"
Î!TÈ*ASiiA^S^tia=rï?r
i^ta,^" "> " "«1 v« J^l-u. L^n7:".'^y*«y'
p»i**
-IT »T. 1*1 n , | IK LI^U r-
tlute G ru mit &
r,i | |
--i val****'
r' \
/
<->
I ÛC
lu
I©
Enemies
of the written word
All materials of vegetable or animal origin that are
used as a surface on which to write are extremely
fragile. A host of enemies lie in wait ready to attack.
Depending on whether they are chemical, at¬
mospheric or biological foes, they will assail either
the outer surface or the very structure of the material.
Inks fade and disappear, parchment and leather curl
and craze. Insects and rodents devour organic
materials; humidity, acid and light attack vegetable
fibre; and fire can destroy anything combustible.
Throughout the world, research institutes are study¬
ing ways and means of protecting books and
documents. As part of its action for the safeguard of
the world's cultural heritage, Unesco is publishing a
series of technical notes on the preservation and
restoration of cultural property. The sixth of this
series of publications, from which our photos are
taken, is entitled Livres et Documents: Sauvegarde et
Conservation (Books and Documents: safeguard and
preservation), by Françoise Flieder and Michel
Duchein (1983, in French only). Photos show ex¬
amples of deterioration due to three different agents.
Right, a Syriac document transformed into "lace" by
the action of ink. Some inks, when subject to humidi¬
ty have the effect of releasing sulphuric acid which
eats away paper and parchment to give this lacework
effect. Water too can cause considerable damage.
Above, a book deteriorated by humidity. A wide
variety of insects can cause havoc in libraries and ar¬
chives. Top photo shows a book ravaged by the atten¬
tions of an insect of the Anobidae family (which in¬
cludes the drugstore and death-watch beetles).
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Lenin Library
THE Lenin State Library is the most important library
in the Soviet Union. It is the keystone of the coun¬
try's unified library system, in which it acts as a
depository for all publications, a co-ordination centre for
library science and bibliographical work, a scientific and
methodological centre, and a centre for inter-library loans.
The library was founded in 1862j Its nucleus was the
library of Count N.P. Rumantsev, an early nineteenth-
century Russian politician and scholar for whom it was
named. In 1918, when the Soviet Government was transfer¬
red from Petrograd to Moscow, the Rumantsev public
library became the National Library. In 1921 it was function¬
ing as a State depository for all books published in the coun¬
try, and in the same year began to extend its holdings
through the acquisition of works of foreign literature, a pro¬
cess which has continued regularly ever since. An interna¬
tional exchange service was inaugurated. On 6 February
1925, by a decree of the Soviet Government, it was named
the Lenin State Library.
On 1 January 1984 the holdings of the Lenin Library
amounted to 331,243,000 titles. Each year a million new
works are acquired, 600,000 non-periodical publications and
400,000 periodicals. The Library has almost 300,000 readers.
Each year 2,215,000 entries are recorded, including
1,202,000 to the scientific reading rooms.
The Library publishes 500 titles each year. Its lending
facilities serve 3,500 libraries in 110 countries. As part of
inter-library exchange facilities, it receives approximately
125,000 books and supplies 210,000.
In 1987 the Lenin Library will be celebrating its 125th
anniversary.
"The Apostle", the first dated Russian book, was printed at
Moscow In 1564 by the first Russian printer, Ivan Fedorov. It
forms part of the rich collection of rare books and manuscripts
In the Lenin State Library of the USSR.
The new science of bibliology
BIBLIOLOGY is a comparatively new
science, dating from around the end
of the eighteenth or the beginning of
the nineteenth century. The word first ap¬
peared in France in 1812 in Traité de
Bibliologie a "Treatise on Bibliology" by
G. Peignot which he described as "a univer¬
sal repertory containing critical and
descriptive notes (...) on a large number of
works (...) and covering every aspect of
bibliography".
Bibliology as a science is arousing con¬
siderable interest today as two recent sym¬
posia bear witness. In 1981, a joint
French/Bulgarian symposium on
Bibliology, Documentation and Informa¬
tion Sciences, organized by the Central
Library of the Bulgarian Academy of
Sciences in collaboration with the French
by Anne-Marie Bianchi
Centre National de la Recherche Scientifi¬
que, was held in Sofia; and, in February
1984, a congress on Research and the
Teaching ofBibliology and Trades Relating
to the Book was held at the Georges Pom¬
pidou Centre, Paris.
The Paris symposium drew up a balance
sheet of the state of the art and proposed the
broad outlines of a policy for research on
the book, for the teaching of bibliology and
for the development of the teaching of pro¬
fessions connected with the written word,
excluding newspapers and periodicals, for
the period 1980 to 1990.
Bibliology can be said to be an extension
of bibliography. Whereas bibliography is
concerned primarily with the classification
of books and articles, bibliology aims to ex¬
amine and explain the various manifesta
tions of the book and the written word in
general with regard to its production and
distribution as well as to its reading.
Bibliology is the study of the written
word as a tool of communication within
society, with all its sociological, cultural
and economic implications. It therefore
encompasses all the disciplines that are
concerned with the world of books
bibliography, library management, book
collecting, and the psychology and psycho-
sociology of reading.
ANNE-MARIE BIANCHI, of Italy, is director
of the University of Grenoble bibliographical
documentation and research -centre, which
she founded in 1963.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
A What's What' of libraries
and archives
5,000 years of archives
3000-2800 BC. In the temple of Eanna, in
the Mesopotamian city of Uruk (now
Varka), not far from what was then the
mouth of the Euphrates, accounts and in¬
ventories were written in Akkadian
cuneiform script on clay tablets. It is from
these, the oldest surviving, written
documents, that the first economic archives
developed. At about the same period the
hieroglyphic system of writing was being
developed in Egypt. It was used initially for
inscriptions on monuments.
1400-1200 BC. Diplomatic correspondence
on clay tablets was documented in well
organized chancery archives, remnants of
which have survived in various capitals of
the Eastern Mediterranean region such as
Tell-el-Amarna in Egypt, Ugarit in Syria
and the Hittite capital, Boghazköy, in
present-day Turkey. Documents in clay
tablet form dating from the same period
have been found in the so-called Palace of
Nestor, north of Pilos, in the
Peloponnesus. .
78-79 BC. The Tabularium of the central
State archive of the Roman Empire was
constructed at the foot of the Capitol,
above the Roman Forum. Its ruins can still
be seen. At first the Romans wrote on
whitened wooden tablets (album). Later
they adopted papyrus rolls from the Egyp¬
tians and Greeks. Fundamental laws were
publicly displayed on bronze tablets.
98 AD. A document written in the Chinese
province of Gansu testified to the invention
of paper, which legend attributes to the
minister Ts'ai Lun. From China paper ar¬
rived in Japan and Korea. It reached the
Arabs about 750 via the trading centre of
Samarkand and afterwards spread to the
whole of the Arab cultural area.
538 AD. The Emperor Justinian decreed
that the treaties and acts entered in the city
registers or gesta municipalia, and per¬
manently preserved in a special public
building called the archeion or archivum,
should be regarded as authentic. He thus in¬
tegrated the archives into the corpus juris
on which the development of European law
is based.
753-755 AD. Deeds or charters on parch¬
ment with wax seals stamped on or hanging
from them became the most important
form of document during the European
Middle Ages. The earliest ones which have
come down to us, now in the National Ar¬
chives in Paris, are the original charters
issued by King Pippin to the Abbey of St
Denis. The first archives of deeds and
charters originated in monasteries. It, was
only later that city and State archives came
into existence.
1198. The present register of the Vatican ar¬
chives was begun when the Papal Chancery
was transferred to the Vatican. The older
register, in which the ancient tradition of
the Roman public records or commentant
survived, was destroyed in the Lateran fire.
Soon after 1200 a register of cor¬
respondence, which was important for the
organization of archives, began to be kept
in the royal chanceries of Paris, Barcelona
and London. In the last-named capital they
were kept in the form of rolls.
C. 1450. In addition to the older charter or
treasury archives, there now appeared ar¬
chives of administrative records, for which
paper imported into Western Europe via
Spain was already being used in rapidly in¬
creasing quantities from the 14th century
onwards.
1794. The French National Convention
adopted the Archives Law of 7th Messidor
of the year II, under which the nation's ar¬
chives, previously largely kept secret, were
opened to the public. The system of
organizing archives on national and
regional or departmental lines, which was
introduced under the revolutionary regime
in France, became the model for modern ar¬
chives organization in Western Europe.
1821. The Ecole des Chartes, the first
school to specialize in training archivists
and librarians, whose formation is concen¬
trated on the study of historical sources,
was established in Paris.
1841. A decree made work in French ar¬
chives subject to respect des fonds. The
principle of provenance, already partly
observed elsewhere, under which archives
are classified according to the authorities
and institutions where they originated,
became the fundamental modern system of
archive organization.
1910. The first international congress of ar¬
chivists and librarians was held in Brussels.
The subjects discussed ranged from the
repair of archive volumes and restoration
problems to the economic archives then be¬
ing set up and the handling of film archives.
1918. The revolutionary government in
Russia led by Lenin issued the decree of
1.6.1918 on the "reorganization and cen¬
tralization of archives". Its concept of a
centralized State archive became the model
for archives in the Socialist countries.
1948. Influenced by the damage caused to
archives during the Second World War, a
group of archive experts invited to Paris by
Unesco decided upon the creation of the In¬
ternational Council on Archives (ICA). Ar¬
chivists from 33 countries participated in
the founding congress two years later.
1950. The passing of the Federal Records
Act in the USA provided a legal basis for
the system of rational records administra¬
tion already in operation and for the
establishment of record centres. The British
Public Records Act of 1958 created another
model for records administration.
1968. The creation of a regional archives
association for Southeast Asia (SARBICA)
confirmed the spread of modern archive
concepts in the Third World. In the same
year it was decided at a congress in Niamey
to set up a regional training centre in Dakar.
The resultEDADis a model for closer
co-operation between archive, library and
documentation centre. Meanwhile the In¬
ternational Council on Archives embraces
nine regions in every part of the world. At
the International Archives Congress in
Washington in 1976 there was talk of a
"geoarchival revolution".
1984. About 1300 archivists from over 100
countries took part in the 10th Interna¬
tional Archives Congress in Bonn (FRG).
Under the general theme of "the challenge
to archives", the participants discussed the
effects of computerization and the new
media, and new tasks in the public sphere.
Built In 1534, during the Ming dynasty,
the Imperial History Archive, located In
the eastern part of Beijing, Is the oldest
and best preserved Imperial archive In
China. Right, the main hall of the Archive,
built entirely In brick to reduce fire risk.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
©
Frontispiece from the Diamond Sutra, the
world's earliest dated printed book. This
Chinese version of a Sanskrit Buddhist
text was discovered In a cave library at
Dun-huang, Gansu province, In 1907. It
depicts the Buddha preaching to his aged
disciple Subhutl.
'<%
The ancient Chinese used to Inscribe I
their writings, mainly divlnatory or
oracular, on bones or tortoise shells
which they preserved with great care.
This Inscribed fragment of bone, 3,000
years old and little more than two cen¬
timetres long, was unearthed recently at
Zhouyuan, In Shanxl province.
' X '
3'T \
Archives
by the kilometre
THE importance of the world's ar¬
chival institutions, from large
National Archives to local record
offices, may be gauged from the number
of people who use them or by the volume
of their holdings, usually measured in
metres of shelvingalthough such quan¬
titative yardsticks provide only a limited in¬
dication of the value of their contents for
research.
One of the world's oldest archival in¬
stitutions is the General Archives in
Simancas (Spain), with 9,500 metres of
records some dating as far back as 834.
The largest archival institution outside
Europe is the National Archives in
Washington, D.C., which today has 470
kilometres of shelving. The Public Ar¬
chives of Canada preserve 38 km of con¬
ventional archives, and 350 km of semi-
current records administered in federal
records centres throughout the country.
Europe's biggest archives are the Ar¬
chives Nationales in France (350 km not
including 36 km at the Archives d'Outre-
Mer, 27 km at the Foreign Affairs archives
and 65 km at the Armed Forces archives)
and the Public Record Office in London,
which holds 379 km (the India Office
records occupy 11 km of shelving
whereas the National Archives of India
preserve 25 km).
The State Archives of Venice hold 68
km, surpassing archives which are
historically as important such as the Na¬
tional Archives of Belgium (55 km) and
Hungary (33 km).
The Haus-, Hof- und Staatsarchiv in
Vienna preserves 25 km of data, but there
are five other central archives in Austria,
which together preserve 100 km.
In Czechoslovakia, federal, regional
and local archives together preserve 563
km. In the Netherlands, a small, densely
populated country with a long history in
which cities played an important role,
there are 383 km of historical archives, 63
km of which are in the National Archives at
The Hague.
Major archives exist not only in Europe
and North America. The National Ar¬
chives of Zimbabwe preserve 49 km, not
counting 33 km of semi-current records in
other centres. In Nigeria the National Ar¬
chives store 28 km.
All these institutions, as well as hun¬
dreds of smaller archives, are listed in the
International Directory of Archives
published by the International Council on
Archives (a new edition is currently being
prepared for publication this year.
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Documentation centres
EUROPE
France. CDST Centre de Documentation
Scientifique et Technique du Centre Natio¬
nal de la Recherche Scientifique, Paris.
Science and technology, medicine and
life sciences. Periodicals: 20,000 titles
(including 13,000 current), plus theses,
reports, congress documents. PASCAL
bibliographic data base (5,000,000
references).
Federal Republic of Germany. FIZ
Fachinformationszentrum Energie, Physik,
Mathematik GmbH, Karlsruhe.
Energy, physics, mathematics. Periodi¬
cals, studies, patents. Data bases on INKA
host.
United Kingdom. BLLD British Library
Lending Division, Boston Spa.
Provision ofbasic documents in all dis¬
ciplines, 172,000 periodicals (including
56,000 current titles), 2,498,000 mono¬
graphs, 2,515,000 reports, 390,500 theses
and 184,500 congress documents.
USSR. VINITI Vsesoyuznyi Institut
Nauchno Tekhnicheskoi Informatsii,
Moscow (Ail-Union Institute of Scientific
and Technical Information).
Science and technology. Periodicals:
more than 25,000 titles. 20,000 books. Data
base, growing by 500,000 references yearly.
Hungary. OMIKK Orszagos Miiszaki
Informados Központ es Könyvtar, Buda¬
pest (National Technical Information Cen¬
tre and Library).
Technical library with 400,000 books,
5,700 periodicals, 635,000 translations.
Information dissemination system (conver¬
sational access to major European hosts).
ASIA
China. ISTIC Institute of Scientific and
Technical Information of China, Beijing.
Science and technology. 18,000 current
periodical titles, plus lectures, reports, the¬
ses, reference works. 2,000 scientific and
technicalfilms. 1,000,000 microform units.
Japan. JICST Japan Information Center
of Science and Technology (Nihon Kagaku
Gijutsu Zyoho Senta), Tokyo.
Science and technology. 8,000 periodi¬
cal titles; 10,000 books; 90,000 microform
units; JICST-FILES data bases (2,250,000
references, growing at a rate of400, 000 per
annum).
India. INSDOC Indian National Scienti¬
fic Documentation Centre, New Delhi.
National depositoryfor scientificperio¬
dicals and reports. 4,500 current periodical
titles (110,000 volumes).
THE AMERICAS
Brazil. BIREME Biblioteca Regional de
Médecine, Säo Paulo.
Indexes Latin-American medical litera¬
ture for the Index Medicos (2,200 referen¬
ces); organizes a national network of 280
medical libraries and 305 information units;
2,313 periodical titlesplus 1,033 acquired by
partners in the network. Obtains NTIS
microfiches through the IBICT (Brazilian
Institute for Information in Science and
Technology).
United States. NTIS National Technical
Information Services, Springfield Va.
Physical, biological and social sciences;
technology; information science. Over
730,000 titles. Data bases: EPA Report
System; NTIS Bibliographic Data File
(850,000 items, growing by 70,000 yearly).
Canada. CISTI Canada Institute for
Scientific ' and Technical Information,
Ottawa (ICIST Institut Canadien de l'In¬
formation Scientifique et Technique).
Themost important Canadian collection
ofscientific, technical and medical publica¬
tions. 34,000 periodical titles;
300,000 books; 1,550,000 microfiches plus
congress documents and reports. Numeri¬
cal data bases (CAN/SND); on-line access
to major international data banks
(CAN/OLE).
AFRICA
Senegal. Centre National de Documenta¬
tion Scientifique et Technique, Dakar.
Economy, sciences and technology.
Data base (75,000 references).
Egypt. NIDOC National Information
and Documentation Centre, Cairo.
Sciences and technology. Almost 5,000
periodical titles and 30,000 books.
OCEANIA
Australia. CSIRO Commonwealth
Scientific and Industrial Research Organi¬
zation; CLIS Central Library and Infor¬
mation Service, Melbourne.
Central library and 70 network libraries,
17,000 periodical titles, 115,000 books.
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
A Canadian man and woman In winter
dress, Quebec, Canada, November 21,
1805. Ink drawing and watercolour by
Sempronlus Stretton.
The Manuscript Department of the Na¬
tional Library of Thailand has a fine col¬
lection of writings on palm leaves. Left,
Buddhist palm-leaf manuscript, Inlaid
with mother-of-pearl, dating from the
reign of Rama III (1824-1851). Above left,
this palm-leaf manuscript has a gilt lac¬
quer coverand Is wrapped In a cloth bear¬
ing the emblem of King Mongkut (Rama
IV) who reigned from 1851 to 1868.
Some major
world libraries
National libraries
EUROPE
France. Bibliothèque Nationale,
Paris
Germany (Fed. Rep.). Bayerische
Staatsbibliothek, Munich
United Kingdom. British
Library, Reference Division,
London
USSR. Gosudorstvennaya
Ordena Lenina Biblioteka,
Moscow
Volumes
10,000,000
4,700,000
8,750,000
28,745,000
ASIA
China. National Library of
China, Beijing
India. National Library,
Calcutta
Japan. Kokuritsu Kokkai,
Toshkokan (National Diet
Library), Tokyo
10,000,000
1,512,000
3,790,000
THE AMERICAS
Brazil. Biblioteca Nacional,
Rio de Janeiro
Argentina. Biblioteca Nacional,
Buenos .Aires
United States. Library of
Congress, Washington, D.C.
AFRICA
Algeria. Bibliothèque Nationale,
Algiers ,
Egypt National Library, Cairo
Zaire. Bibliothèque Nationale,
Kinshasa
OCEANIA
Australia. National Library of
Australia, Canberra
3,500,000
1,600,000
19,578,000
1
920,000
1,500,000
1,200,000
2,120,000
University libraries
EUROPE
France. Bibliothèque de
la Sorbonne, Paris
United Kingdom. Bodleian
Library, Oxford
Cambridge University Library
USSR. A.M. Gorki Library of
the Moscow Lomonosov State
University
ASIA
China. Quing Hua University
Library, Beijing
3,000,000
4,502,000
3,549,000
6,630,000
2,000,000
THE AMERICAS
Argentina. University of
Buenos .Aires
United States. Harvard
University library, Cambridge,
Mass
Yale Univeraty Library,
New Haven, Conn
1,150,000
10,260,570
7,402,000
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO NEWSROOM
Unesco Prize
for Peace Education
Nominations are being invited for the
Unesco Prize for Peace Education, which
will be awarded for the fifth time this
year. The purpose of the Prize is "to pro¬
mote all forms of action designed to 'con¬
struct the defences of peace in the minds
of men' by rewarding a particularly
outstanding example of activity designed
to alert public opinion and mobilize the
conscience of mankind in the cause of
peace." The Prize, which is worth
$US 60,000, is awarded annually. Ac¬
cording to the rules governing the award
of the Prize candidates may be "an in¬
dividual, a group of individuals, or an
organization" and may be nominated by
"Member States of Unesco, intergovern¬
mental organizations, non-governmental
organizations granted consultative
status with Unesco and persons whom
the Director-General deems qualified in
the field of peace." Laureates are
designated by the Director-General on
the basis of proposals submitted by an in¬
ternational jury, the International Com¬
mission for Peace in the Minds of Men.
Nominations should reach the Unesco
Secretariat not later than 31 March
1985.
Kalinga Prize Awards
The 1984 Kalinga Prize for the
Popularization of Science has been
awarded to professor Yves Coppens of
France and Academician Igor Petryanov-
Sokolov of the Soviet Union. Prof. Cop-
pens, who is the director of the Musée de
l'Homme in Paris, is a distinguished
palaeontologist who has written and lec¬
tured widely, given many radio and TV
broadcasts, and organized numerous ex¬
hibitions including one on the origins of
man which drew 300,000 visitors to the
Musée de l'Homme in 17 months.
Academician Petryanov-Sokolov, who is
a professor at the Moscow Institute of
Chemistry and Technology, has col¬
laborated with a number of popular
science magazines and took part in the
production of the scientific section of the
12-volume Soviet Children's Encyclo¬
paedia.
Finnish edition
of the Unesco Courier
We are happy to announce the launching
of a Finnish edition of the Unesco
Courier, published by the Finnish Na¬
tional Commission for Unesco, Ministry
of Education, Rauhankatu 4, SF - 001 70
Helsinki 17. The publication of the first
issue of the Finnish edition, in October
1 984, brought the total number of dif¬
ferent language editions of the Unesco
Courier to 29, in addition to the quarterly
Braille selection.
International
Simon Bolivar Prize
The International Simon Bolivar Prize will
be awarded for the second time in 1 985.
The biennial Prize, established by the
Government of Venezuela and awarded
under the auspices of Unesco, rewards
activity of outstanding merit which has
contributed to the freedom, in¬
dependence and dignity of peoples and
to the strengthening of solidarity among
nations, or facilitated the quest for a new
international economic, social and
cultural order. The first recipients of the
Prize, in 1 983, were King Juan Carlos of
Spain and Nelson Mandela, the African
National Congress leader imprisoned in
South Africa. The final date for the sub¬
mission of nominations is 15 March
1985.
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices:
Unesco, 7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 68 French francs. 2 years (valid only in
France): 1 20 French francs. Binder for a year's issues:
52 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering pos¬
tage. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions and
headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boun-
deries on maps published in the magazine do not imply offi¬
cial endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the United
Nations.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm and/or
microfiche) by: 1 1 1 Unesco. 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris :
(21 University Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100,
U.S.A.: (31 N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111
West 40th Street, New York, U.S.A.: (41 Bell and Howell Co..
Old Mansfield Road. Wooster, Ohio 44691 .U.S.A.
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
French: Alain Lévêque (Paris)
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov (Paris)
Arabic: Sayed Osman (Paris)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Rajmani Tiwari (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: Hossein Razmdjou (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salam)
Braille: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Vitomir Sudarski (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition: Neda el Khazen
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Servat
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Special projects: Peggy Julien
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
General introduction
to the techniques
of information and
documentation work.
Clajire Guirtcllal
and Micfiel MefK)Li
In developing countries, the organization of efficient
library and documentation structures is being held
back largely by the absence or shortage of trained
staff. General Introduction to the Techniques of In¬
formation and Documentation Work is a comprehen¬
sive, simply written, and easy-to-consult manual for
all those who, in developing countries, begin their
careers in information units without any basic train¬
ing in information science. It aims to enable them to
grasp the essential purpose of the activities they are
asked to perform and to understand how these ac¬
tivities are related to the full range of means used to
ensure the flow of information. It also provides a
description, sufficiently detailed to serve as a guide, of
the various operations, instruments and concepts
related to information systems. Designed primarily as
an instrument of self-training, to be used by the in¬
dividual on his own, it could also be employed in in¬
formation units or in colleges of information science
as a reference work for training courses, as a guide for
the preparation of courses or as a means of checking
background knowledge prior to a course of specializ¬
ed training.
Unesco
1983 340 pages 90 French francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors In countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Colling-
wood Victoria 3066; Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd.
P.O. Box 33, Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty.
Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvele 2100,'nSW. Sub-
agent: United Nations Association of Australia, P.O. Box 175,
5th floor. Ana House, 28 Elizabeth Street, Melbourne Victoria
3000. AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31,
A-101 1, Vienna. BAHAMAS. Nassau Stationers Ltd., P.O. Box
N-3138, Nassau. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books
International Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola,
Dacca 3. - BARBADOS. University of the West Indies
Bookshop, Cave Hill Campus, P.O. Box 64, Bridgetown.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V.
Handelmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. BOTSWANA. Botswana Book Centre, P.O.
Box 91, Gaborone. BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co.
Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H 1M7.
CHINA. China National Publications Import and Export
Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Beijing. CYPRUS. "MAM",
Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena 51-11302, Prague
1 ; Ve Smeckach 30, P.O.B. 790 - 1 1 1 - 27 Prague 1 (Permanent
display); Zahranicni literatura, 11 Soukenicka, Prague 1. For
Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893
31 Bratislava CSSR. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export-OG
Tidsskriftservice 35 Noire Sogade, DK-1970 Kobenhavn K.
EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco
Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo. ETHIOPIA.
National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100
Helsinki 10; Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, Koivuvaarankuja 2,
01 640 Vantaa 64. FRANCE. Librairie da I'Unesco, 7, place de
Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, C.C.P. 12598-48. GERMAN
DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710
Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R.
FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier (German,
English, French and Spanish editions): Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher
Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basartstrasse 57, D5300 Bonn 3. For
other Unesco publications: Karger Verlag, Germering/München.
For scientific maps only: Geo Center, Postfach 800830,
Stuttgart 80. GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O.
Box 195, Accra; Ghana Bdbk Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869,
«cera; The University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University
Bookshop of Cape Coast;- The University Bookshop of Legón,
P.O. Box 1, Legón. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
HONG KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen
Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book
Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon. Hong Kong Government
Information Services, Publication Centre, Baskerville House, 22
Ice Street. HUNGARY. Kultura-Bush import - ABT, P.O.B. 149 -
H-1389, Budapest 62. ICELAND. Snaebjörn Jonsson & Co.,
H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd.,
Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan
Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2;
5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh, Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahatma
Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.
17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House, New Delhi;
Publication Unit, Ministry of Education and Culture, Ex. AFO
Hutments, Dr. Rajendra Prasad Road, New Delhi 110001.
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl. Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl Dr Sam Ratulangie 37,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co.,
28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Enghélab Avenue. P.O. Box 314/1486,
Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco. 1 1 88 Enghlab Av.,
Rostam Give Building, Zip Code 1 31 58, P.O. Box 1 1 365-4498,
Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, AI Rashid Street,
Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12; Tycooly International
Publ. Ltd 6 Crofton Terrace, Dun Laoghaire Co., Dublin. ISRAEL.
A.B.C. Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv
61000. ITALY. Licosa {Librería Commissionaria Sansoni, S.p.A.)
Via Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552, 50121 Florence.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101
Water Lane, Kingston. University of the West Indies Bookshop,
Mona, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo
3-chome Bunkyo-ku Tokyo 1 1 3. KENYA. East African Publishing
House, P.O. Box 30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National
Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT.
The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait; for the
Unesco Courier; Farafalla Press Agency, P.O. Box SAFA 4541,
Kuwait. LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod.
Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA. Code and Yancy Bookshops
Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia. LIECHTENSTEIN : Eurocan
Trust Reg. P.O.B. 5 - 9494 Schaan. LIBYA. Agency for
Development of Publication & Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35,
Tripoli. LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue,
Luxembourg. MALAWI. Malawi Book Service, Head Office, P.O.
Box 30044 Chichi ri, Blantyre 3. MALAYSIA. University of
Malaya Cooperative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur 22-1 1 . MALTA.
Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta.
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-
Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-
Carlo. NEPAL. Sajha Prakashan Polchowk, Kathmandu.
NETHERLANDS. KEESING BOEKEN B.V., Joan Muyskenweg,
22, Postbus 1118, 1000 BC Amsterdam. NETHERLANDS
ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad,
Curaçao. N.A. NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Office,
Government Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344,
Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace. P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch;
Alma Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box
1104, Dunedin, Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington.
NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The University
Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka; The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zaria. NORWAY. Johan Grundt Tanum,
P.O.B. 1177 Sentrum - Oslo 1 , Narvesen A/S; Subscription and
Trade Book Service. P.O.8. 6125 Etterstad, Oslo 6; Universitets
Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, Postboks 307 Blindem, Oslo 3.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O.
Box No. 729, Lahore 3. PHILIPPINES. National Book Store, Inc.
701, Rizal Avenue, Manila D-404. POLAND. Orpan-lmport,
Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie
Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068 WARSAW. PORTUGAL. Dias &
Andrade Ltda. Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon.
SEYCHELLES. National Bookshop, P.O. Box 48, Mahé; New
Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé. SIERRA
LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone Diocesan
Bookshops, Freetown. SINGAPORE. Federal Publicetions (S)
Pte Ltd. Times Jurong, 2 Jurong Port Road, Singapore 2261.
SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and
General, P.O. Box 951, Mogadiscio. SOUTH AFRICA. For the
Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Central News agency, P.O.
Box 1033, Johannesburg. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop,
100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2.
SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum.
SWEDEN. All publications A/B.C.E. Fritzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356. 10327
Stockholm 1 6. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN Förbundet,
Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm; Wennergren-
Williams, Box 30004-S-104, 25 Stockholm; Esselte
Tidskriftscentralen, Gamla Brogatan 26, Box 62 - 101 20
Stockholm. SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag. 5
Rämistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 121 1, Geneva
1 1 , C.C.P. 1 2-236. Librairies Payot also in Lausanne, Basle,
Berne, Vevey, Montreux, Neuchâtel and Zurich. TANZANIA.
Dares Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam.
THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road,
Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402; Bangkok: Suksapan Panit,
Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam
Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I. TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S.,
Istiklâl Caddesi, N° 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu, Istambul.
UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 7145, Kampala.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, H.M.S.O., P.O.
Box 276. London, SW8 5DT, end Govt. Bookshops in London.
Edinburgh, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol; for
scientific maps only: McCarta Ltd., 122 King's Cross Road,
London WC 1X 9 DS. UNITED STATES. Unipub, 205 East
42nd Street, New York, N.Y. 10017. Orders for books &
Periodicals: P.O. Box 1222, Ann Arbor, Ml 48106. U.S.S.R.
Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Moscow, 121200. YUGOSLAVIA.
Mladost, llica 30/11, Zagreb; Cankarjeva Zalozba, Zopitarjeva 2,
Lubljana; Nolit, Terazije 27/11, Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd., P.O. Box 2664
Lusaka. ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union
Avenue, Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
</document>
