<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="062935eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
m
MARCH 1963 (16TH YEAR) - PRICE 1/-STG. (U. K.) - 30 CENTS (U. S.) - 0,70 F (FRANCE)
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
© Almasy, París
WORLD CAMPAIGN AGAINST ILLITERACY
Five hundred million adults in the world cannot read
or write. In vast areas the whole question of raising
living standards is blocked by illiteracy. This is. why
Unesco's recent General Conference gave top priority
to education in the programme of action it approved
for 1963 and 1964. (See page 31). While continuing its efforts
to help the development of primary education, Unesco
will during the next two years survey problems of illi¬
teracy on a world scale and will prepare a campaign whose
initial phase will aim to bring literacy to 350 million people.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Contents
No. 3
BOW OMN ON TNI W O * 1 0
ner
MARCH
16TH
1963
YEAR
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
This portrait of Jean-Jacques
Rousseau, a detail of which
appears on our cover, is a
crayon drawing by the famous
French pastelllst, Maurice
Quentin de la Tour. " Mon¬
sieur de la Tour, " declared
Rousseau, " is the only
artist who has ever produced
a good likeness of me. "
Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
Page
4 THE APOSTLE OF AFFLICTION
A portrait of Jean-Jacques Rousseau
By Barbara Bray
10 ROUSSEAU, THE FATHER OF ANTHROPOLOGY
By Claude Lévi-Strauss
16 THE SOLITARY WANDERER
With Rousseau along the paths of reverie
By Anne-Marje Pfister
18 ST. PIERRE: ISLE OF BLISSFUL SOLITUDE
21 ROUSSEAU'S MESSAGE FOR OUR WORLD TODAY
The enduring validity of Rousseau's ideas
By Lourival Gomes Machado
23 THE ROAD FROM PERSECUTION TO APOTHEOSIS
The victory of ideals over despotism
24 ORIENTAL ECHOES OF THE «SOCIAL CONTRACT'
By Takeo Kuwabara
27 THE INDIVISIBILITY OF WORLD PROSPERITY
The anatomy of underdevelopment Pt. 4
31 A WORLD PROGRAMME FOR EDUCATION
SCIENCE & CULTURE
A look at Unesco's tasks in 1963-64
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
(M. C. 63.1 , 178 A)
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7; France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
René Caloz
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse
Spanish Edition í Arturo Despouey
Russian Edition : Veniamln Matchavariani (Moscow)
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese- Edition : Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Italian- Edition : Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in July and August when
it is bi-monthly ( I I issues a year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German.
Arabic, Japanese, and Italian. Jn the United Kingdom it is distributed by H.M.
Stationery Office, P. O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Un-esco Courier is indexed monthly in The Readers' Guide to
Periodical Literature published by H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates : U. S. S3.00 ; IO/-stg. ; 7.00
French Francs or equivalent. Single copies I /-stg. 30
cents (U.S.) ; 0.70 French Francs.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7\
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
<&2¿¿s
THE APOSTLE
OF AFFLICTION
by Barbara Bray
From July 1962 to July 1963 the world is celebrating the
250th anniversary of the birth of Jean-Jacques Rousseau.
During this Rousseau Anniversary Year innumerable tributes
are being paid in all parts of the world : lectures, exhibitions,
ceremonies, films and radio broadcasts. The event has been
accorded a place of honour In Unesco's calendar of an¬
niversaries of great men and events. The Unesco Courier
now offers its tribute to Jean-Jacques Rousseau, and devotes
a large part of this issue to the 18th-century philosopher,
social reformer and educationalist, whose doctrines and
ideas are as modern today as when they were first expressed.
Blibiothèque Nationale, Paris
lean-Jacques Rousseau was born in Geneva of
French stock on June- 28, 1712. His mother
died nine days afterwards. "My birth," he said, "was the
first of my misfortunes."
The apostle of affliction, Byron called him...
"The apostle of affliction, he who threw
Enchantment over passion, and from woe
Wrung overwhelming eloquence..."
Dr. Johnson, speaking to Boswell, was more severe.
"Rousseau, Sir, is a very bad man. I would sooner sign a
sentence for his transportation, than that of any felon
who has gone from the Old Bailey these many years.
Yes, I should like to have him work in the plantations."
Was Rousseau "a very bad man"? A lot of people
thought so, many still do, and certainly, considered as an
individual he was not a conspicuously good one, with such
peccadilloes as lying, stealing, and untiring if unsuccessful
amorousness.
He sent all his five children to the Foundling Hospital
almost as soon as they were born, and thought up what
seemed to him good reasons for it; he was always difficult
and vain, and ended up such a prey to persecution mania
that when he died he had hardly a friend left in the
world. Yet his real crime in the eyes of his contem¬
poraries was not personal: it consisted rather in being one
of those great rare originals who have the effrontery and
bad taste to change the course of history.
Rousseau furnished a blue-print for the French Revolu¬
tion, his ideas were written into the American Constitu¬
tion, his teachings on education are still heard indirectly
in almost every classroom in the world, and his influence
on literature is not yet spent.
Europe in the middle of the eighteenth century was
ripe for change. France in particular was a powder-barrel
That spark was Jean-Jacqueswaiting for a spark.
Rousseau.
One day in the summer of 1749, When he was still
unsuccessful and unknown, he set out from Paris, where
he had settled, to visit his friend Diderot, the editor of
the great Encyclopedia, who had been imprisoned in the
Chateau of Vincennes for reasons not unconnected with
the atheistic and materialistic tendencies of his writings.
"The state of my finances not permitting me to pay for
hackney coaches," relates Rousseau, "I went on foot.
I thought a book in my hand might make me moderate
my pace. I took the Mercure de France, and as I walked
and read, I came to the following question proposed by
the academy of Dijon, for the premium of the ensuing
year: Has the progress of sciences and arts helped to
corrupt or to purify morals?
"The moment I read this, I seemed to behold another
world, and became a different man... On my arrival at
Vincennes, I was in an agitation which approached deli¬
rium. Diderot perceived it; I told him the cause, and read
him what I had written with a pencil under a tree. He
encouraged me to pursue my ideas, and to become a com¬
petitor for the premium. I did so, and from that moment
I was ruined.
"All the rest of my misfortunes during my life were the
inevitable result of this moment of error... All my little
passions were stifled with the enthusiasm of truth, liberty,
and virtue; and this effervescence continued In my mind
upwards of five years..."
Rousseau, maintaining the then paradoxical view that
the cultivation of the arts and sciences always generates
moral corruption, won the prize. He immediately became
CONT'D ON PAGE 6
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
R.M. Clermont-Ciné Club du Val de Bièvre
ibliothèque Nationale, Paris
A PLACE OF PILGRIMAGE
Tall poplar trees which give their name to this tiny island in a lake at Ermenonville,
near Paris, surround the tomb where Jean-Jacques Rousseau was buried on July 4,
1778. The island soon became a place of pilgrimage and people flocked there in
such numbers that for a time permission for visits had to be curtailed. The visitors
vented their enthusiasm on the trees in the park which were soon covered with ins¬
criptions carved in many languages. The Swiss artist Geissler evoked this wave of
enthusiasm in "Resurrection of Jean-Jacques Rousseau" (left) in 1794, when
Rousseau's remains were transferred with great ceremony to the Panthéon in Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Turning point in a vagrant life
At the age of 1 6 Rousseau
ran away from Geneva.
Then began an extraor¬
dinary series of wander¬
ings and adventures,
At Annecy came one
of the turning points
of his life; his meeting
with Madame de Warens
(far left) who took him
into her home. Later,
she gave him affection,
good advice and a stu¬
dious atmosphere in
which to work. It was
in her house at Char-
mettes (left) from 1738
to 1 740 that he expe¬
rienced " the short-lived
happiness in my life ".
ROUSSEAU (Cont'd;
The boy who learned
to hate oppression
involved in a series of controversies which brought him
more and more into the public arena, and led him to deve¬
lop his political ideas over the years that followed in a
number of works that culminated in 1762, two hundred
years ago, in his treatise concerning "The Social
Contract."
"Man is born free, yet everywhere he is found in
chains." These, the opening words of Chapter One,
echoed round the world. Basic to The. Social Contract as
to all Rousseau's writings is the belief than man is natu¬
rally good, and that society is something artificial and
necessarily corrupting. At the origin of civilized society,
he imagines, was some act of political association, unde¬
sirable but necessary for survival, which has led to the
present discontents. What would be the best form of
social contract?
For Rousseau individual sovereignty should be surren¬
dered voluntarily in favour of the State a political entity
which acts through laws. These laws must express the
collective sovereign will of the people, by means of a
representational system free from influence or corruption.
The object of all legislation must be liberty and equality.
In his Social Contract the implied criticism of the actual
state of France was of course devastating, and was one of
the most powerful elements that, working in the mind of
the revolutionaries, led ultimately to the destruction of
the old order.
How did Rousseau come by the passions which animate
The Social Contract? He gives us some clues in the
Confessions, his autobiography. After telling of a childish
injustice suffered at the age of about twelve, he goes on:
"Even while I write this I feel my pulse quicken, and
should I live a hundred thousand years, the agitation of
that moment would still be fresh in my memory. The
first instance of violence and oppression is so deeply
engraven on my soul, that every relative idea renews my
emotion. When I read the history of a merciless tyrant,
or the dark and subtle machination of a knavish designing
priest, I could on the instant set off to stab the miscreants,
though I was certain to perish in' the attempt."
He also gives us a picture of one of the origins of his
horror of oppression. Wandering as a young man in
France, he approached a peasant's hut in a particularly
pleasant and prosperous-looking part of the country, and
asked if he could have a meal, which he would pay for.
One day In 1749 Rousseau went to visit the
philosopher, Denis Diderot, imprisoned in the
Chateau of Vincennes. On the way (below) he
decided to compete for the Dijon Academy prize
offered for an essay on the effect of the progress
of civilization on morals. " All the rest of my
misfortunes during my life were the inevitable
result of this moment of error... " he wrote.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Photos Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris Music meant much to Rousseau. He taught and composed it and actually invented a new system of
musical notation. For long periods he lived by copying musical scores. This engraving shows him singing
verses which he composed to show his thanks to the family with whom he lived on the island of Saint-Pierre.
At first the most meagre fare was provided, and then, as
the countryman's suspicions were lulled, he brought some
ham and some wine and some eggs out of hiding.
Refusing payment, he pronounced tremblingly the terri¬
ble words "Commissioners" and "Cellar-Rats."
"He explained," wrote Rousseau, "by giving me to under¬
stand that he concealed his wine because of the excise,
and his bread on account of the tax imposed on it; and
he would be undone if it were suspected he was not
almost perishing with want.
"What he said to me made an impression that can
never be effaced, sowing seeds of that inextinguishable
hatred which has since grown up in my heart against the
vexations these unhappy people suffer, and against their
oppressors... I left his cottage deploring the fate of those
beautiful countries where nature has been prodigal of her
gifts only that they may become the prey of barbarous
exactors."
A point that Rousseau Insists on in The Social Contract,
and one that is perhaps his most important contribution
to the safeguarding of all the principles he cared for, is
that the government that executes the laws is composed
merely of officials paid to carry out the general will, but
all governments will tend to usurp power if not carefully
watched and held in check. The precious and enduring
truth of his great work is that sovereignty belongs to the
people, and must never under any pretext be transferred
to any individual or group of individuals.
Some details of The Social Contract have been distorted
or exaggerated to justify totalitarian practices, but this
is in direct contradiction of the author's spirit.
As Viscount Morley, Rousseau's greatest biographer,
said: "It was in Rousseau that polite Europe first
hearkened to the strange voices and faint reverberations
from out of the vague and cavernous shadows in which
the common people move." And polite Europe hearkened
not because Rousseau was a model of correct thought or
a brillant exponent of practical organization, but because
his Ideas were what they had been waiting for, and
because they were proclaimed with depth and fervour.
Needless to say it was not in Rousseau's lifetime that
he was acclaimed. While he lived he was persecuted, and
hounded out of France and Switzerland. In an age which
still bowed to the divine right of kings Rousseau was a
republican and believed in the divine right of the people.
When the faculty of reason was held- to be man's highest
attribute, Rousseau abandoned its cool systems in favour
of the flushed and unpredictable promptings of the heart.
And when the churches were shoring themselves up with
dogma against the storms to come, Rousseau was the
advocate of "natural religion," which required no inter¬
mediary between man and God.
But in spite of the unpopularity and even personal dan¬
ger to which his writings exposed him, Rousseau scorned
to take the usual course of seeking refuge in anonymity,
nor would he obliterate a word of what he had written.
It was Emile, his treatise on education, published like
The Social Contract in 1762, that really got Rousseau into
hot water. For in Emile, occurs the digression on religion
known as the Profession of Faith of the Savoyard Vicar.
This a composite portrait of two priests whom Rousseau
had known and revered. He Is a man who seeks God not
by reason, as every previous philosopher from Plato
onwards had done, but by introspection.
Rousseau's Vicar interests himself not at all in dogmas,
does not, it goes without saying, believe in original sin, and
in discussing the after-life never once mentions the Christ¬
ian doctrine of Redemption. If interpretations and forms
of worship vary, no matter. The book of nature is open
for all to read: "The essential worship, Is of the heart."
Rousseau thus brought about a simplification of belief
a simplification that seems cautious rather than con¬
troversial nowadays, when his views have become part of
the general atmosphere. But in 1762 his was a highly
dangerous doctrine. To his Dutch publisher, who seeing
the book seized in France, begged him to cut the offending
passage, he wrote: "There is no reproach or danger or
violence or power on earth that will make me ever retract
a syllable."
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
ROUSSEAU (Cont'd)
Tamile' a bold new concept of education
Emile has been called a sentimental manifesto where
we must not look for too much intellectual cohesion. Yet
the idea that there is a kind of instinct in human beings
that provides the deepest sanction of right and wrong is
one of the many flashes of Insight in Rousseau which to
this day have not been made to yield their full signifi¬
cance.
Besides being an advocate of natural religion Rousseau
was the prophet of a revolution in education no less cata¬
clysmic and far-reaching than the revolution in politics.
His qualifications as an authority on education were
strange indeed.
His father had introduced him to literature at an early
age by reading inflammatory French romances with him,
afterwards progressing at random to a few more solid
works that happened to be lying about. Later Rousseau
was sent with his cousin to board in the country with a
tutor for a couple of years "to learn Latin, with all the
insignificant trash that has obtained the .name of
education."
Up till now, according to Rousseau himself, he had
always been surrounded with the tenderest and most
healthful care although some of the details he mentions
in passing may seem to us to bode no good at all to the
infant that was exposed to them. At the age of thirteen
he was apprenticed first to a notary, then to an engraver,
but he hated all restraint and after three years ran away.
The next few years were spent in a vagabond sort of
existence, wandering about the country and from time to
time taking jobs of a more or less menial kind.
The main formative influence during these years
was Madame de Warens, an attractive Catholic
proselytiser older than himself, whom he long loved in his
own peculiar way and who did a great deal to civilise him.
It was not until he was about twenty-six, when he was
installed with Madame de Warens in the beloved rural
retreat of Les Charmettes, near Chambéry, that Rousseau
set about educating himself systematically. He was han¬
dicapped by a very poor memory: "I must have learned
and relearned the Eclogues of Virgil twenty times over,
and I cannot recollect a single line of them."
Although by this time he was convinced that his talent
lay in music, he took a job for a time as a tutor, with
farcical results. In Book VI of his Confessions he tells us :
"The natural gentleness of my disposition seemed calcu¬
lated for the employment, if hastiness had not been
mingled with it. While things went favorably, and I saw
the pains (which I did not spare) succeed, I was an angel;
but a devil when they went contrary.
"If my pupils did not understand me, I was hasty, and
when they showed any symptoms of untoward disposition,
I was so provoked that I could have killed them... I could
only make use of three means, which are very weak, and
often pernicious with children; namely, sentiment, reason¬
ing, passion... Everything I undertook failed, because
all I did to effect my designs was precisely what I ought
not to have done."
What Rousseau ought to have done we find in Emile.
Here again we are offered not so much a practical plan as
a sort of ideal embodying the principles to be observed.
Emile, the pupil, is to be given a "natural education"; that
is to say, one that preserves as long as possible against
the corruption of the world that original goodness, happi¬
ness and innocence Rousseau believed to be born in every
human being.
The method Rousseau prescribes means interfering as
little as possible with the free development of the child's
mind and body, and making the unavoidable adaptation
to society so careful and so gradual that the pupil suffers
the least possible harm in the process.
Emile is to be brought up alone by a tutor, away from
his parents, in an environment scientifically calculated to
produce the best conditions for free development. He is
to be treated not as a miniature adult, but as a natural
being whose virtues as such must be preserved and culti
vated. The influence of Emile was electric and is still
reflected today in almost every modern school.
A point that is not sufficiently remembered is that Rous¬
seau founded his educational method on the cultivation of
the sensibilities above all things. Right feeling is an indis¬
pensable preliminary to right thinking and acting, and
any educational system that neglects or blunts the sensi¬
bilities of children in order to concentrate on intellectual
or technical achievement has left out the whole essence
of the matter. Here is another idea of Rousseau's that
has not yet been made full use of.
It was also as a man of feeling that Rousseau made his
great contribution to literature. Everything he did was
original in some way. His Confessions, which were not
published until after his death, are the first example of
what is now one of the most characteristic elements in
Western literature the completely unashamed exposure
of all an author's most intimate thoughts, experiences and
desires. And the Confessions, like his work Reveries of a
Solitary Wanderer, introduce a new attitude to nature,
though it is the pleasurable and more mildly sympathetic
aspects of the landscape that please him and not the full
romantic diapason.
From his sensibility, then, all Rousseau's virtues, like
all his vices, sprang. The Scottish philosopher Hume, who
was his friend until Rousseau quarrelled with him as he
did with everyone else, and with as little reason, described
him thus: "He only felt during the whole course of his
life, and in this respect his sensibility rises to a pitch
beyond what I have seen any example of; but it still
gives him a more acute feeling of pain than of pleasure.
He is like a man who is stripped not only of his clothes,
but of his skin, and turned out in this situation to combat
with the rude and boisterous elements."
On July 2, 1778, at Ermenonville, after years of wander¬
ing and quarrelling and of illness that does much to
explain some of his behaviour, Rousseau died of uraemia.
His main source of income for many years had been music
copying: he had scorned to set up as a professional writer.
His companion was a coarse illiterate servant-woman who
had been with him for more than thirty years. This
relationship has been very roughly handled by many
critics, but in fact, as Morley with great magnanimity
points out, it shows that Rousseau for all his faults was
capable of almost heroic loyalty and forbearance. Some
have called his life deplorable, but the man whose name
stands for liberty and equality, for the beginning of
reasonableness and sympathy in education, and for a new
kind of poetic beauty, is one who deserves to have his sins
remembered kindly. Many of his ideas were golden, and if
they are still as powerful now as they were in his own day,
it is because he had also the gift of a golden tongue.
Barbara Bray is a regular participant on the BBC programme,
"The Critics", and literary contributor to British newspapers and
periodicals. She has translated various works of I8//1 century
French authors. This article is adapted from the radio programme
she wrote for Unesco in honour of Rousseau.
Publications Filmées d'Art et d'Histoire.
Portrait of
Madame
d'Epinay
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
BROKEN FRIENDSHIPS & A LITERARY TRIUMPH
By nature Rousseau was sensitive and quick to take offence and
eventually quarrelled with many of his friends. He fell out with Madame
d'Epinay (portrait on opposite page, by the Swiss painter Jean-Etienne
Llotard) who for long had been his protectress and confidante. She
gave him the use of her house, "L'Hermitage", in the valley of
Montmorency, near Paris, and he lived there from April 1756 to
December 1757. After their friendship ended, Rousseau moved to
"Mont-Louis" (above), another house in the same valley. There he
finished The New Eloísa, whose success was great and immediate. In 1778,
he returned to the valley of Montmorency shortly before his death.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
ROUSSEAU, FATHER
by Claude Lévi-Strauss
The Invitation you have extended to an anthro¬
pologist to take part in this commemorative
occasion offers an opportunity to a young science to pay
homage to the genius of a man who, it might well seem,
had been fully honoured in every possible facet of his
life work which included such fields as literature, poetry,
philosophy, history, ethics, political science, education,
linguistics, music and botany to mention only a few.
In addition to this, though, Rousseau was more than
just a keen and subtle observer of peasant life, an im¬
passioned reader of books on foreign travel, a skilfull and
accomplished investigator of exotic customs and beliefs.
Without fear of contradiction it can be stated that a full
century before anthropology was actually born he con¬
ceived, desired and foretold it, placing it directly in the
ranks of the natural and human sciences then in
existence. He even guessed correctly the practical way
in which it would later begin to function, namely, by
individual or collective patronage.
This prophetic conception, which he formulated both
as a plea and as a programme of action, appears in a
long footnote to the Discourse on the Origin of Inequa¬
lity. "I have difficulty in comprehending," Rousseau
wrote, "why in an age that prides itself on learning, two
men cannot be found, one of whom would sacrifice
twenty thousand crowns of his wealth and the other ten
years of his life, to make a historic journey round the
world, studying not only the inevitable stones and plants,
but for once men and customs."
And a little further on he exclaims: "The whole of the
world is a weave of nations of which we know only the
names. And we presume to judge mankind! Imagine
a Montesquieu, a Buffon, a Diderot, a d'Alembert, a
Condillac, or men of that stamp, travelling to instruct
their fellow-countrymen, observing and describing as
only they know how, Turkey, Egypt, Barbary, the empire
of Morocco, Guinea, the land of the Kaffirs, the interior
of Africa and its eastern coast, the Malabars, the Mogul,
the banks of the Ganges, the kingdoms of Siam, Pegu
and Ava, China, Tartary, and above all Japan; and in
the other hemisphere, Mexico, Peru, Chile, the Magellan
lands, not forgetting the Patagonias real or imaginary,
Tucuman, Paraguay, and if possible Brazil, the Caribbean,
Florida and all the savage lands. Such a journey would
be of more importance than all others and would have
to be made with the greatest of care. Imagine that
these new Hercules, on their return from those unfor¬
gettable travels, -were to write at their leisure a natural,
moral and political history of what they had seen, then
we would see for ourselves a new world arise from their
pens, and we would learn to know our own..." (Discourse
on the Origin of Inequality, note 10.)
Is this not the very subject matter as well as the work¬
ing method of modern anthropology? And are not the
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
OF ANTHROPOLOGY
illustrious names cited by Rousseau the same ones that
present-day anthropologists still revere and seek to emu¬
late in the firm conviction that only by following their
example will their science continue to deserve the
respect so long denied it?
But Rousseau did not just foresee anthropology, he
actually founded it. Firstly, he did so in practice by
writing the Discourse on the Origin and Foundations of
Inequality Among Men which posed the question of the
relationship between nature and culture, and is perhaps
the first treatise produced on general anthropology.
Secondly, he founded the science in theory by setting
down with remarkable clarity and precision the aims of
the anthropologist as distinguished from those of the
moralist and the historian:
"When one wishes to study men, one must look close
at hand; but to study man, one must learn to look into
the distance; one must first observe the differences in
order to discern the properties." (Essay on the Origin of
Languages, Chapter VIII.)
This method of approach which Rousseau assigned to
anthropology marks the birth of the new science and
helps to clarify what at first may appear to be a double
paradox: that Rousseau could at one and the same time
advocate the study of men living in the most remote
corners of the earth, but in effect, devoted most of his
attention to the one man nearest to him, namely himself;
and that in all his writings his systematic desire for iden¬
tification with others went hand in hand with his total
refusal of identification with himself.
Now every anthropologist at some time or other during
his life work must resolve these same two seeming contra¬
dictions which in reality are no more than the two inter¬
changeable sides of one coin.
All anthropologists owe a special debt to Rousseau: for
he not only traced the precise course of their new science
in the scheme of man's knowledge, but by his work and
the character and temperament it displayed, by the in¬
tensity of his feeling, his nature and personality, he
provided anthropologists with the fraternal solace of an
image in which they recognize their own image and are
thus led to a deeper understanding of themselves not
in the abstract sense of pure intellectual thought but as
the Involuntary agents of the profound transformation he
has wrought within them and which all mankind has
come to find in the person of Jean-Jacques Rousseau.
Each time that the anthropologist goes out into the field
he plunges into a world where everything around him is
strange and often hostile. He finds himself alone with
nothing but his own person, his subjective self, to help
him survive and carry on his work. Physically and
mentally wracked as he is by fatigue, hunger and
hardship, by the "disruption of his normal habits, and by
the sudden revelation of prejudices which he had
never suspected to exist, his self reveals itself in these
unfamiliar surroundings as it really is battered and
buffeted by all the shocks and impacts of his personal life,
which not only affected his choice of a career but would
thereafter deeply mark its entire course.
I
'NOBLE
SAVAGES' OF
THE FRIENDLY
ISLES
Rousseau's idea of the "noble
savage" uncorrupted by civilization
caught the imagination of 1 8th-
century Europe and was often
distorted Into a fairy-tale image,
both in people's minds and in the
paintings and engravings of the
period. Left, the artist shows
Captain Cook landing at Middel-
burgh in 1778, one of the Friendly
Islands east of Australia, and depicts
the islanders dressed in the flowing
robes of ancient Greece or Rome.
Bibliothèque Nationale
N the work of anthropology, therefore, the
» observer uses himself as his own instrument of
observation. As a result, he must learn to know himself,
to look at himself objectively and at a distance as if he
were another person. And so the anthropologist turns to
this other person within him, which is different from his
self, in order to arrive at an evaluation. And this -then
becomes an integral part of all the observations he carries
out in the field on groups and individuals and the other
within them. The principle of "confessions," written or
unacknowledged, is thus basic to the work of every
anthropologist.
But if Rousseau's experience helps us to see that of
anthropology in a clearer light, it is because
Rousseau's temperament, his personal history and cir¬
cumstances spontaneously placed him in a situation
which is precisely that of the anthropologist. And like
the anthropologist, Rousseau did not fail to note at once
the consequences that this situation had on him per¬
sonally:
"So there they are," -he wrote of his contemporaries,
"foreign, unknown, nothing to me, since they wished it
so! But I, detached as I am from them and from all else,
what am I? That is what it remains for me to discover."
(First Promenade)
And the anthropologist contemplating for the first time
the savages he has chosen to study might indeed almost
echo Rousseau's words and exclaim: "So there they are,
foreign, unknown, nothing to me, since I myself wished
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
FATHER OF ANTHROPOLOGY (Cont'd)
The key question: 'what am I?'
it so! But I, detached as I am from them and from all
else, what am I? That is what / must first discover."
For in order to rediscover one's own image as reflected
in others, which is anthropology's single purpose in study¬
ing man, one should first reject one's image of oneself.
It is to Rousseau that we owe the discovery of this pro¬
found principle and the only one on which the sciences
of man could be founded. But it remained out of reach
and grasp and incomprehensible so long as the accepted
philosophy was based on Descarte's doctrine of the Cogito
(Cogito ergo sum) and was fettered to the alleged logical
proof of the ego upon which the edifice of physics was
constructed though only by renouncing that of sociology
and even biology.
Descartes believed that he could pass directly from the
interiority of man to the external world, overlooking that
between these two extremes there existed societies and
civilizations, that Is, worlds made up of men.
Rousseau speaks eloquently of himself in the third
person as "he" (sometimes even splitting this "he" into
two distinct parts as in the Dialogues) heralding the
famous formula "The me is another" (the anthro¬
pologist does the same thing before proceeding
to show that other people are men like him
self, or in other words, the other is me.
Rousseau thus emerges as the great
Innovator of the concept of unconditional
objectivity. In his first Promenade, he
defines his aim as "to study the modi¬
fications of my soul and their sequels,"
and then adds: "In a sense, I shall
perform upon myself the same experi¬
ments that the physicist carries out
on the atmosphere in order to dis¬
cover its daily condition."
What Rousseau reveals to us (and
though modern psychology and anthro¬
pology have now made it more familiar,
it is nevertheless a most astonishing revel¬
ation) is that there is a third person "he"
that thinks within me, and at first leads me to
doubt that It is I who am thinking.
To Montaigne's question "What do I know?" (which
started the whole discussion) Descartes thought he could
provide the reply with his "I think, therefore I am."
To this Rousseau retorted with the query "What
am I?" which cannot be answered until another, more
fundamental, question has been resolved: "Am I?" And
the answer that personal experience has given is the "he"
concept that Rousseau discovered and which he proceeded
at once to explore with consummate lucidity...
Now if we are to believe that when first human societies
appeared on earth man achieved a triple transformation,
passing from a state of nature to culture, from sentiment
to knowledge, and from an animal-like state to that of
humanity (which is precisely what Rousseau set out to
prove in his Discourse on Inequality) we can do so only
by attributing to man in his very earliest primitive condi¬
tion some vital faculty or quality which impelled him to
make this threefold transition.
And we must consequently assume that from the very
start this quality latently possessed both contradictory
elements at least as attributes if not as intrinsic parts,
so that it was at one and the same time both natural
and cultural, emotional and rational, animal and human.
We must also assume that the transition could be made
from one to the other providing this quality became
conscious in man's mind.
j- This quality, as Rousseau repeatedly stated, is pity
which issues from man's identification with another not
just a relative or a companion or a compatriot, but with
any man because he is a man; and indeed with any living
creature because it is alive.
Early man thus began by intuitively feeling himself
identical with all his fellow beings. And he never wholly
forgot this feeling even when the rise of population forced
him to migrate to new lands and to adapt himself to new
modes of living, and led him to the awakening of his own
personal identity.
But this awakening came only after he had slowly
learned to recognize the identity of others and to dis¬
tinguish the various animals according to their species,
the human state from the animal state, and his own
individuality from the individuality of other men.
The recognition that all men and animals are feeling
beings (which is what identification signifies) long ante¬
dated man's awareness of their differences: first with
regard to the characteristics common to all living
creatures, and only later to the human as opposed to non-
human attributes. It is with this bold conclusion that
Rousseau put an end to Descarte's doctrine of the Cogito.
If this interpretation is correct, if by the use of anthro¬
pology Rousseau did indeed shatter the traditions of
philosophy as radically as I believe, then it
becomes simpler to grasp the fundamental
unity which marks Rousseau's varied and
heterogeneous works, and to understand
why subjects like linguistics, music and
botany held so preponderant a sway on
his thoughts even though they at first
appear to be somewhat remote from
his main work as a writer and philo¬
sopher.
The evolution of language, as Rous¬
seau described it in his Essay on the
Origin of Languages, can be seen to
follow almost an Identical path
(though on a different plane) with that
of the evolution of man.
In the first stage no distinction was made
between the strict and figurative meaning of
things, and only progressively did the strict
meaning detach itself from the original metaphor
(in which one object is contained in several others.)
With regard to music no form of expression seems to me
better suited for refuting Descarte's theory of the oppo¬
sition between the material and the spiritual, mind and
matter. For music is an abstract system of both contrasts
as well as relationships, and when performed elicits a dual
effect: First a transfer occurs in the relationship between
the self and the "he" in us, since when I listen to music
I hear myself through it; and second, a transfer occurs in
the relationship between mind and matter since the music
actually lives within me. "A chain of relationships and
combinations," Rousseau termed this in his Confessions
(Book Twelve) but one which nature presents to us incar¬
nate in "perceptible objects" (Reveries, Seventh Prome¬
nade).
It is in these terms too that Rousseau defined his
approach to botany, thus proving that here again he
hoped to find both sensitivity and intellect united as one
because this constituted man's original estate and existed
at the moment of the first awakening of the rational
mind, only to vanish thereafter except in rare and precious
instances.
Rousseau's thought thus evolved from two principles:
identification with another, even the most removed
"other" of all others including creatures of the animal
world; and the rejection of identification with oneself,
that is to say the rejection of everything which might
make the self seem "worthy". These two attitudes are
complementary, the second actually being the springboard
I	'"
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Photos Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
EQUAL RIGHTS FOR ALL
"When one gazes on human society with detachment, it appears at first to reveal nothing but the
violence of the powerful and the oppression of the weak", wrote Rousseau in his Discourse on Ine¬
quality. Rousseau's ideas helped to form The Declaration of the Rights of Man and of the Citizen,
in 1789, at the outset of the French Revolution. In this allegorical engraving of the period, a mother
shows the Declaration to her son while nearby lightning strikes and shatters special privileges.
for the first: I am not "me" but the weakest and humblest
of "others". Herein lies the true originality of the
Confessions.
As for the anthropologist, are his writings anything
else but confessions? Confessions first about himself, for
as I have pointed out, the discovery of himself is the
driving force of the anthropologist's calling as well as
of his work. And then in his work, confessions about his
own society which, through the medium of the anthro¬
pologist, has chosen other civilizations and societies
deliberately among those that appear to be the weakest
and the most humble of all, so as to ascertain to what
extent it itself is "unworthy". By unworthy, I mean that
it is in no way a privileged form of society but only one
of countless "others" that have succeeded each other in
the course of millenia, and which because of their diversity
and brief moment of duration offer added proof that as
a collective entity too man must first come to know
himself as "another" before he can hope to think in
terms of himself.
The Rousseauist revolution, as precursor and genesis of
the anthropological revolution, lies in the repudiation of
compulsory identifications either of a culture with its
own culture, or of an individual member of a culture with
a public figure or rôle which that culture seeks to impose
upon him.
In both cases the culture and the individual assert
their right to free identification, and this can only
be achieved beyond man, i.e. with all living and therefore
suffering creatures; and also before the public figure or
role, i.e. with a being as such and not one already shaped
and classified.
In this way the "I" and the "he", freed from the dis¬
tinction that only philosophy has sought to encourage, are
once again united and merged. With their original unity
thus restored at last, they can forge together the us
against the them, that is, against society antagonistic and
inimical to man, and which man is the more easily pre¬
pared to reject since Rousseau, by his own example, has
taught him how to escape the intolerable contradictions of
civilized life.
For though it is true that man has been expelled by
nature and that society continues to oppress him, he can
at least reverse the extremes of the dilemma to his own
advantage by seeking the society of nature in order to
meditate on the nature of society. This, it seems to me,
is the lasting message of the Social Contract, the Letters
on Botany and the Reveries...
But it is today, for all of us who have come to experience
Rousseau's prediction to his readers of "the terror of those
unfortunates who will live after you," that his thoughts
tower to their full height and reveal the broad sweep of
their horizons..
In this world more cruel to man perhaps than it has
ever been, charged with extermination in every form,
massacre and torture not always disavowed no doubt but
comfortably dismissed by us as no longer important since
they were confined to far-off people who we were told -.o
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
FATHER OF ANTHROPOLOGY (Cont'd)
The deadly effects of an illusion
suffered for our good or at any rate in our name In this
universe of ours become smaller, more drawn together as
our members steadily augment and with no fragment of
humanity left safe from insidious attack the anguish of
living in society weighs on us all.
It' is today, I repeat, because he put civilization on trial,
pointing a finger at its iniquities and abuses and denied
that these could possibly lead to the exercise of virtue in
man, that Rousseau can help us to shatter an illusion the
deadly effects of which we are now able alas to observe in
ourselves and on ourselves. For is it not because of the
myth of the exclusive dignity of human nature that
nature Itself suffered its first mutilation, to be followed
inevitably by other mutilations?
We began by severing man from nature and setting him
up as a sovereign kingdom apart. With this we thought
we had done away with the one characteristic that can
never be denied, namely that man is first of all a being
that is alive. And by closing our eyes to this common
feature the door was opened wide to every outrage and
abuse.
Never in the course of the past four centuries
has western man been in a better position to
realize that by arrogating to himself the right to raise a
wall dividing mankind from the beast in nature, and
appropriating to himself all the qualities he denied the
latter, he was setting in motion an infernal cycle. For
this same wall was to be pulled steadily tighter, serving to
set some men apart from other men and to justify in the
minds of an ever-shrinking minority their claim to being
the only civilization of men. Such a civilization, based
as it was on the principle and notion of self-conceit, was
corrupt from the very start.
Only Rousseau raised his voice against this type of
egotism. In the footnote to the Discourse previously
quoted Rousseau recounts that, from the clumsy descrip¬
tions made by travellers, he preferred to recognize the
great apes of Africa and Asia as men of an unknown race
rather than run the risk of denying human nature to
creatures who might possess it.
And the first error would indeed have been less serious
than the second since respect for others springs spon¬
taneously and naturally in man, long before reasoning and
its sophistries come into play. Rousseau saw the proof
of this native response in man's "innate abhorrence to
witness the suffering of his fellows." From this we are
Inescapably led to look upon every creature that suffers
as a fellow being and hence entitled to the inalienable
right to pity.
For the only hope that each of us can have that we
shall not be treated one day as beasts by our fellow men
is for all our fellow men, we first amongst them, to look
upon ourselves at once as suffering beings, nurturing
within us that faculty for pity which in nature replaces
"laws, morals and virtue," and without which, as we are
now coming to realize, there can be no law, no morals and
no virtue in society.
Thus, far from presenting itself to us as a nostalgic
return to the past, identification with all forms of life,
beginning with the most humble, proposes to humanity
today through the voice of Rousseau the principle of all
collective wisdom and all collective action. This principle,
in a world where overcrowding makes mutual respect more
difficult and therefore that much more necessary, Is the
only one which can permit men to live together and build
a harmonious future.
14 It may well be that this teaching was already contained
in the great religions of the Far East. But in the tra
ditions of the west where, ever since antiquity, it was
thought that one could play a double game and tamper
with the evidence that man was a living and a suffering
being, no different from all other beings before secondary
factors distinguished him from them, who else but Jean-
Jacques Rousseau has made this message available to us?
"I have a violent aversion," Rousseau wrote in his
fourth letter to Monsieur de Malesherbes, "to social
orders that dominate others. I hate the Great, I hate
their condition." Does not this assertion apply first to
man who has sought to dominate other living creatures
and maintain a separate state, thereby giving the least
honourable of men freedom to do the same to other men
and to take advantage of a notion as disgraceful in this
latter instance as it was in the earlier broad context.
In a cultivated society there can be no excuse for the
only really inexpiable crime of man, that of considering
himself abidingly or momentarily superior, or treating
men as objects, be it for reasons of race, culture, conquest,
service, or merely expediency.
We know that in the life of Rousseau there was one
minute perhaps one second which, tenuous though it
was, he prized above any other. That is why towards the
end of his life it was this moment which obsessed him
most and which he took pains to describe at length in his
last work, returning constantly to it in the course of his
country walks. Yet. it was no more than his simply
regaining consciousness after a fall which caused him to
faint. But the feeling of being alive is of all others a
"priceless feeling" no doubt because it is so rare and so
uncertain:
"It seemed to me that I filled with my own slender
existence all the objects I perceived... I had no distinct
notion of my individuality... in all my being I felt a
delightful calm to which, whenever I recall it, I can find
nothing comparable in the full range of known pleasures."
This famous passage in the second Promenade was
echoed in the seventh with an added explanation of what
it meant to him: "I feel ecstasies, ineffable delights in
losing myself as it were, in the system of beings, in identi¬
fying myself with the whole of nature."
TJL r
his primeval identification which is denied
man in the state of society and which, having
forgotten its essential virtue, man can no longer feel
except by chance or by haphazard circumstance, takes us
to the heart of Rousseau's work. And if we accord it a
place apart among the great creations of man's genius it
is because Rousseau not only discovered in identification
the true principle of the sciences of man and the only
possible foundation for morality, but because he also
rekindled in us Its ardent flame. For two centuries it has
burned and will continue to burn, firing the crucible in
which the union of beings is taking place notwithstanding
those sociologists and philosophers who in their pride are
everywhere intent on rendering Incompatible the self and
the other, my society and other societies, nature and
culture, the emotional and the rational, humanity and life.
Claude Lévi-Strauss is professor of social anthropology at the
College de France in Paris. The above article is an abridged
version of his address last year to a commemorative gathering
organized by the Workers' University and the Faculty of Letters of
the University of Geneva in homage to Rousseau. The complete
text has now appeared in "Jean-Jacques Rousseau" (Collection
Langages) published by Editions de la Baconnière, Neuchâtel,
Switzerland.
All reproduction rights reserved.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
TEACHING
BASED ON RESPECT
Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
Rousseau's ideas on the education of children made a vivid impression on his contemporaries.
Instead of the harsh, rigid education of the time which treated children like adults, Rousseau
proposed a method of teaching based on respect for the child and an appreciation of his sensi¬
tivities. In 1 779, one year after Rousseau's death, a monument to the author of Ém//e was erected 15
in Geneva. It showed the new type of teacher guiding a child, and his former chains decked in
a garland of roses. The evils of the old educational system are shown on a broken medallion.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
THE
Rousseau chases his hat
blown off by a gust of
wind. This engraving based
on a painting by Jean-Michel
Moreau dates from the
period when Rousseau was
a butt for ridicule and
hotly attacked by the philo¬
sophers of his time. Right,
Rousseau gathering flowers
near the house in which
he lived at Ermenonville.
R
16
ousseau's work and personality are so rich and
varied that it is not always easy to grasp their
deep-reaching unity and to see them as a whole. While
we should keep in mind the connexions between the diffe¬
rent aspects of the man and the multiple facets of his
talent, it is also rewarding to concentrate on one of these
and to try to walk with Rousseau along one of the paths
he followed, in this case, the path of reverie which, in his
own words, became for him "an intense passion."
Reverie for him effaces the misery of existence and
leads to true happiness, such as he enjoyed during his
enchanted stay in the island of St. Pierre, in the autumn
of 1765. To his experience there, he devoted some of the
finest pages of Book XII of his Confessions and, above all,
the famous fifth walk in the Reveries of a Solitary Wan¬
derer. This, his last work, left unfinished and published
four years after his death, had a considerable influence on
so many of the greatest poets and prose-writers of the
19th century, from Senancour to Baudelaire and Rimbaud,
and, among many others, Novalis,." Nerval and Hölderlin.
To reach the heart of Rousseau's experience, we must
cast a glance at the part played in his life by solitude and
the contact with nature he found when walking alone.
We shall then see how, to use Rousseau's own words (The
Second Dialogue) "an active heart and a lazy tempera¬
ment," aided by a lively imagination, found in day-dream¬
ing the supreme form of bliss.
Although Rousseau was often alone, enjoyed solitude
and at certain periods lived very introspectively, he was
far from being the sour recluse his enemies tried to make
him out. He was no egoist pent in an ivory tower, but
an expansive and sensitive being who had, since youth,
obviously had great difficulty in adapting himself to
society, partly because of certain traits of character and
partly because of the circumstances of his life. In the
first book of the Confessions, he speaks of the lasting
influence of the novels he had read in his childhood.
They had given him "extravagent, romantic notions of
human life, which experience and reflection have never
been able to eradicate."
Self-adaptation means taking the rough with the
smooth; not accepting everything, but compromising to
a certain extent; admitting the transition from the
absolute to the relative. Rousseau was not always able
or willing to make this effort. Disappointed in his human
loves and friendships, he sought refuge in a world of
reverie, peopled with beings after his own heart. He had
an innate tendency to prefer the immediate and readily
accessible joys of the imagination to the struggles and
suffering involved in facing up to reality.
It was natural, then, that the persecution his bold ideas
brought upon him and the hatred he felt growing round
him, magnified by his morbid and pessimistic imagination,
should aggravate his love of solitude and his deep convic¬
tion that he was different from other men. This persecu¬
tion created an ever-widening gulf between him and his
contemporaries, aggravating the differences between him
and them at the expense of what they had in common.
Although he believes himself alone of his kind "I am
not made like anyone I have been acquainted with," he
writes in his preamble to the Confessions he does not
yet, at the time of writing his great autobiographical
works, the Confessions and the Dialogues, feel himself cut
off from the rest of humanity. By justifying himself to
his contemporaries, by leaving to posterity a portrait
which he believes faithful and absolutely sincere, he is
trying to establish contact with his reader.
t is only in the Reveries that he claims to be
writing for himself alone, so that in old age
he may recapture both the memory of the walks and
thoughts that would otherwise vanish so swiftly from
his failing memory, and the joy he feels at the moment
of penning them. In his first walk, he describes his
situation as he sees it two years before his death.
"All that is external to me, is now strange henceforward.
I have in this world, neither neighbour, nor kinsmen, nor
brothers. I am upon this earth as upon a strange planet,
whence I have fallen from that which I inhabited... Alone
for the rest of my life, because I cannot find except in
myself consolation, hope and peace, I ought not, and do
not wish to occupy myself any longer save with myself...
The leisures of my daily walks have often been filled with
delightful contemplations of which I regret having lost the
memory. I shall set down in writing those which may
still come to me; each time that I reread them will give
me new pleasure.. I shall forget my sufferings, my perse¬
cutors, my opprobrium, in dreaming of the reward which
my heart has merited."
Rousseau had no expectation of the astonishing success
the book was to have or of the ever-growing public it has
attracted since its publication. We come closer to him
in the Reveries than we have ever been, for he takes us
with him into the heart of his spiritual life. The title of
his last meditations is revealing. Far from breaking
with his past, the Reveries of a Solitary Wanderer throw
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
SOLITARY
WANDERER
by Anne-Marie Pfister
Photos Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
light on his whole life, for the enchantment of solitude,
the love of walking and day-dreaming have been familiar
to Rousseau since his youth. On one of the playing cards
which he carried around in his pockets so that he could
jot down the ideas that flashed across his mind as he
walked, he wrote these revealing words:
"In order to justify the title of this collection, I should
have begun it sixty years ago, for my whole life has
scarcely been anything other than a long reverie divided
into chapters by my daily walks."
Solitary life and social life are the two poles between
which Rousseau's life oscillates, ¡as does that of each of
us. He knows, and he reminds us in the Dialogues, that
"absolute- solitude is a lonely state and in contra¬
diction with nature: affectionate feelings nourish the
soul, the communication of ideas quickens the mind.
Life at its sweetest is relative and collective and our real
self is not entirely contained within us. Finally, man is so
constituted in this life that he can never really be his
happiest self without the aid of someone else."
But this aid, as Rousseau conceives it, pre-supposes
the establishment of a friendly relationship between
people, a relationship entirely free of superficiality and
based on reciprocal confidence and equality. Because of
the disappointment of his profound longing for a society
in which heart would speak Intimately to heart and men,
instead of hiding behind the mask of conventional words,
would spontaneously express their innermost thoughts;
because this absolute transparency cannot be realized in
practice, Rousseau has gradually, "as he got to know men
better," thrown himself back upon solitude.
He wrote this as early as January, 1762 in the
first of his four great autobiographical letters to Monsieur
de Malesherbes. The originality and the vigour of his
thought, combined with extreme sensitivity, could not fail
to isolate Rousseau. Moreover, the ups and downs of a
stormy life prevented him from ever quite fitting into
a social group or community. Throughout his life, he was
never in harmony with those about him and long before
his exile and his years of wandering, this "citizen of
Geneva" who lived outside his own country, was already
a person without roots.
Even among the Encyclopedists, the liveliest of
intellectual circles, where he met people of his own level,
he did not feel entirely at his ease: their basic convictions
differed too widely. Everything conspired, then, to
strengthen his taste for solitude which set him free from
the, to him, unbearable constraint of community and
social life and enabled him to indulge his inclination for
sweet reverie, the source of certain and immediate joy.
The love of nature, dating from his childhood years
at Bossey, at the foot of Mount Salève, was another,
unchanging characteristic of Rousseau's life. The passion
for rustic scenery is not necessarily a concomitant of the
love of solitude, but they are often linked. Going for long,
lonely walks through beautiful countryside filled
Rousseau's heart with bliss and gave him an exalting
sensation of freedom.
Recalling his departure from Geneva at the age of
sixteen, he describes the elation and the illuslonary joy
that filled him: "Having attained my liberty, I thought
everything attainable; I entered with confidence on the
vast theatre of the world."
he wandering life he led in the prime of his
youth was an essential experience which
should be kept in mind when one reads the following
admirable page from the Confessions: "What I most
regret is not having kept a journal of my travels, being
conscious that a number of interesting details have slipped
my memory; for never did I exist so completely, never live
so thoroughly, never was so much myself, if I dare use
the expression, as in those journeys made on foot.
Walking animates and enlivens my spirits; I can scarcely
think when in a state of Inactivity; my body must be
exercised to make my judgement active.
"The view of a fine country, a succession of agréable
prospects, a free air, a good appetite, and the health I
gain by walking; the freedom of inns, and the distance
from everything that can make me recollect the depen¬
dence of my situation, conspire to free my soul, and give
boldness to my thoughts, throwing me, in a manner, into
the immensity of beings, where I combine, choose and
appropriate them to my fancy, without constraint or fear.
"I dispose of all nature as I please ; my heart wandering
from object to object, approximates and unites with those
that please it, is surrounded by charming Images, and
becomes intoxicated with delicious sensations... In stop¬
ping, I thought of nothing but a hearty dinner; on part¬
ing, of nothing but a charming walk: I felt a new
paradise waiting for me at the door: my one object was
to go and find it."
The paradise opened to him by his imagination gives 17
CONT'D ON PAGE 20
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Learning that a warrant had been issued for his arrest following the
publication of The Social Contract, and Emile, Rousseau fled to Swit¬
zerland in June 1 762. After spending three often unhappy years at
Motiers, he found a new refuge on the tiny island of Saint-Pierre in
the Lake of Bienne (above and below). Never before had he found'
such complete and blissful solitude as during the six weeks he spent
there. He strolled about the island, examined herbs and plants and
meditated. He lived in its only house and the walls of the room he
occupied (right) are today covered with Inscriptions left by visitors.
Far right, a pavilion where the solitary wanderer came to meditate.
18
**«£*!
Saint-Pierre : Isle of
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Y
' ; m
-:
Blissful Solitude
;£, '-
i. . 1". * -.
É
""« -,
During his wanderings in exile, "The Citizen of Geneva" was harassed by the
lack of understanding and hostility of his contemporaries. In 1962, two cen¬
turies after Rousseau passed through their village, the people of Neuveville
(above), opposite the island of Saint-Pierre, line their streets to acclaim
the memory of a great man during a re-enactment of Rousseau's visit.
Photos © A. Acquadro. La Neuveville
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
SOLITARY WANDERER (Cont'd)
A longing for closeness with Nature
him more real satisfaction than do worldly goods which,
at any moment, may "escape in a thousand ways from
whomsoever thinks he holds them." Rousseau gives
pride of place to the imagination which he describes as
"the consoling faculty." It compensates him for his
disappointments and agrees with his temperament. He
describes himself as being "lazy to act because of too much
eagerness to desire." In his second Dialogue, he stresses
his tendency to withhold: "contemplative life makes one
loth to act."
Occasionally, Rousseau succeeds in "soaring into ethe¬
real regions and hovering there, sustained by sublime
contemplation." He then defies the "blows of fate and
the Insane opinions of men," but what efforts are required
to reach such detachment! Often, he feels so overwhelm¬
ed by his sorrows that his terrified imagination foresha¬
dows only a dark and despairing future. At such times,
nature, and plants in particular, help him to exorcise the
gloomy aspect of his Imagination.
"In this state an instinct which is natural to me, making
me fly every saddening idea, imposed silence on my imagi¬
nation, and, fixing my attention upon those objects which
surrounded me, made me, for the first time, absorb in
detail the spectacle of Nature, which I had scarcely con¬
templated except in mass and in its whole."
Aj BANDONiNG himself to reverie, he "loses himself
with a delicious intoxication in the immensity
of the splendid scheme with which he feels himself
identified." But the moment comes when fusion with all
creation gives way to attentive and detailed observation,
which likewise brings Rousseau release and calm. "It
costs me nothing, nor need I take trouble in wandering
carelessly from herb to herb, from plant to plant, in order
to examine them, to compare their divers characters, to
mark their similarities and their differences... There is
in this leisurely occupation," says Rousseau, speaking of
botany, in the 7th Reverie, "a charm which is only felt
when the passions are calmed, but which alone suffices to
render life happy and sweet."
Rousseau's imagination needs the support of perceptible
things; when too abstract, meditation tires and wearies
him. The type of reverie, therefore, which recurs most
frequently in his life is that which replaces disappointing
and painful reality by an ideal company, consisting of
good, enlightened men, charming and virtuous women,
reliable and faithful friends.
In such reverie, life is enacted against a perfectly har¬
monious natural background and the day dreaming is
fruitful. It gives birth to The New Eloisa. Nevertheless,
it Is only a first stage in Rousseau's experience. Not only
does the "nothingness of his chimera" sometimes cloud
and obliterate the prestige of this enchanted world; he
sometimes realizes that even if his dreams became reality,
they could not satisfy him.
I felt in myself", he said, "an inexplicable void
which nothing could fill, a certain longing of
the heart for some other kind of happiness which I could
not imagine, yet felt the need of." The thirst for the
absolute and for eternity that lies at the centre of our
being makes us crave for such happiness as can only
rarely be enjoyed on earth, that "sufficing happiness,
perfect and full" which the soul, free of all particular
affection, enjoys in the pure feeling of existence, when
time itself stands still and an unlimited present com¬
prehends, without distinction, both past and future.
This purified reverie, lulled by the coming and going of
20 the waves on the shore, when the imagination is silent
and thought inexistent, is the final achievement of Rous¬
seau's inner experience. In this natural mystic ecstasy,
world and self lose themselves in one identity; all separa¬
tion disappears; all desire fades; man suffices unto him¬
self, as does God. Such was the happiness Rousseau
enjoyed in the privileged moments of his stay in the island
of St. Pierre. The experience is described in the fifth
Reverie.
"The flux and reflux of this water, its continuous sound,
swelling at intervals, struck ceaselessly my ears and eyes,
responding to the internal movements which reverie
extinguished in me, and sufficed to make me feel my exis¬
tence with pleasure, without taking the trouble to think.
"From time to time was born some weak and brief
reflection on the instability of earthly things, of which the
surface of the water offered me the image; but soon these
light impressions effaced themselves in the uniformity of
continuous movement which rocked me, and which,
without any active help from my soul, did not fail to
attach me to such an extent that when summoned by the
hour and the signal agreed upon, I could not tear away
without an effort."
Anne-Marie Pfister is curator of manuscripts at the library
of the University of Geneva. The article above is taken from the
text of the address she delivered at a commemorative ceremony
honouring Jean-Jacques Rousseau, held in Unesco House, Paris, on
November 29, 1962.
SOUVENIRS OF REVERIES &
REVOLUTIONARY CHANGES
<&*íi¿¿3 ¡í''y IA '«Vf« /a n«-
§£> ^i^^j bûj en. t t lnyJ ¿C
b "'On
poj ci ty-ti fi'- ' * > 0-e-Y/ortft.
Itxt' n' cyx. (&¿t ' >-££-«_
* * 4
During his long promenades, Rousseau noted down ideas for his
Reveries on the playing cards he carried in his pocket. Later, his
own features appeared on cards of the French Revolutionary period.
Rousseau, depicted as a sage (below), replaces the King of Clubs.
i ¡t ctfíi vr» /gn f,
- l/Xi U Ii
A f H i*. I -
la. ¡Jeninij;,
A ;h<j<zi, A"«y»nr-/
*>V,ii/W f/i fi'n.f'- ^ii,t,t I
'V /<U- ./ \lC fir- f***Vrt':>i.\ " /"Y icu
¡it? jti (f/tff n - i AtItem
flu. ¡U (,li- ttt' f.luiUitvL*J- urjAni
/-«f 9au *, .o ifi^j* 'tit .c'TT/j
u* /W-'-wi,« ¡u>,ii U#.wn*. /, Ju/,
«iViVtèiï* >ií tau 7m: ¿m**v «a
Photos Bibiotheque
Nationale, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
m. s -J
ROUSSEAU'S
MESSAGE
J^kJ FOR OUR
mSk wt WORLD TODAY
Vj \ by Lourival Gomes Machado
1) y Director of Unesco's Dept. of Cultural Activities
:
A bust of Jean-Jacques Rousseau
by the 18th-century French
sculptor, Jean-Antoine Houdon.
© A. Acquadro, La Neuveville
T:he commemoration of the 250th anniversary
of Jean-Jacques Rousseau's birth coincides
with the bicentenary of two of his major works, Emile
and The Social Contract. It also has a special character¬
istic rarely encountered in anniversary celebrations of
this kind actuality.
Mr. René Maheu, Director-General of Unesco, had this
fact in mind when, addressing the world Round Table
organized at Royaumont near Paris by the French Natio¬
nal Commission for Unesco, he declared last year, "to
reread Rousseau is to go directly to the heart of today's
problems." By associating itself, both directly and in¬
directly with this celebration and with several similar
events, Unesco has affirmed clearly and unequivocally its
belief in the validity for our own time of the great themes
dealt with by Rousseau.
These themes are strikingly up-to-date and are cer¬
tainly destined to remain so until such time as man every¬
where has fulfilled his multiple possibilities. This can only
be accomplished by man through a better knowledge of
himself.
However, we today should not be intimidated by such
a wealth of ideas. For Rousseau's works have a perfect
unity, as surprising as this statement may seem regarding
an author whose "lack of method" was so often evoked
by his contemporaries and by succeeding generations.
Modern critics, though, have come to see the unity of
Rousseau's work only after long, patient study carried out
with sympathy and understanding, and unmindful of the
consequences which Rousseau's ideas at once carry with
them. These consequences are inescapable and compel us
to abandon the misty, innocuous realms of pure
speculation.
Fortunately, the reading of Rousseau can begin with any
one of his works without in any way interfering with an
understanding of his philosophy. The reader can start
with Emile or the first Discourse or a Letter to Christophe
de Beaumont, The Social Contract, The New Eloisa or the
Essay on the Origin of Languages. Each of these texts
introduces the reader to one of the main themes of Rous¬
seau's philosophical point of view. And all these works in
their sweep form part of one complete whole, for as
Rousseau said in defining the purpose of his meditations:
"It is man that interests me." That is why most readers
of Rousseau who want to find that aspect of his work
most significant to us today are inclined to choose first
his treatment of the theme of equality.
For perhaps no one has given to the idea of equality
between men a greater world impetus than did Rousseau
and the power to instil in every individual respect for all
men wherever they may live and whatever their status.
In Rousseau we find the first modern definition of man
in terms of his intrinsic worth, and henceforth the mere
fact of being a human being gave one the right to have
an education and knowledge of others, human rights and
the esteem of one's fellow men, regardless of origin, race
or creed.
It is this message which explains why Rousseau's ideas
swept across frontiers and why everywhere they kindled
the torch of new freedoms which though ever latent,
nevertheless remained ignored and unfulfilled.
T:his great theme of the equality between the
peoples of one nation is still in many ways
more a hope than an accomplished fact; and it has found
its contemporary response in the deep preoccupation of
our day to put an end to the inequalities between nations
and people, as Unesco for example, is trying to do.
How many persons and even whole communities are still
deprived today of certain fundamental human rights,
have no opportunity for schooling and are constantly
exposed to disease and hunger. All those whom history
has neglected in their chance for economic security and
development; all those who, more than others, have
remained outside the pale of man's greatest scientific and
intellectual conquests because of circumstances beyond
their control or hapless chance.
Rousseau's revolutionary ideas will continue to live for
so long as such inequalities have not been vanquished.
And for those who finally achieve this position of equality,
Rousseau's words will sound a note of caution to warn
them how fragile their victory can be.
Only the joint efforts of all nations can guarantee that
all men will be equal as they originally were as members
of the same species Homo Sapiens.
From here, the unity which binds the writings of Rous-
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
MESSAGE FOR TODAY (Cont'd)
Jean-Jacques and
Unesco's ideals
seau leads us to a new theme on the problems of civiliza¬
tions. This subject is as modern today as the previous
one and its significance to man was also dealt with by
Rousseau with admirable depth.
Rousseau stressed the fundamental unity of all men
despite the different civilizations which society has
developed on our planet down the ages. Above individual
societies of men he saw a single, universal humanity that
is, simply humanity itself.
At a period in history when the foreigner from a far-off
land was considered at best as a "noble savage", Rousseau
rejected the idea that man could ever be foreign to his
fellow men and proclaimed that universal fraternity was
their one common denominator.
This idea of fraternity which Rousseau inspired was to
have deep repercussions, not only in the emotional
upheavals of the Romantic Period, but in the struggle for
democratic ideals which is still going on.
Perhaps the finest homage to Jean-Jacques Rousseau
in the past year's commemorations was paid by Claude
Lévi-Strauss when he saluted Rousseau as the first to
realize that "in order to rediscover one's own image as
reflected in others, one should first reject the image of
oneself".
For the only satisfactory foundation on which frater¬
nity can rest is the world-wide recognition of the principle
of equality. This is the ultimate purpose and goal of all
today's efforts for greater international understanding,
and to which Unesco has been unceasingly committed.
In celebrating the 250th anniversary of Rousseau's birth,
we are also marking the 200th anniversary of both The
Social Contract and Emile. It is difficult in this connexion
not to mention, even if only in passing, the important
place (indeed now the first place) accorded to education
by Unesco as part ot its great cultural objective. For the
principle of education as Rousseau conceived it has today
found acceptance everywhere in our modern world.
R;
22
ousseau insisted that heart and mind, the
irrational and rational, all played their part in
man's great urge to learn about himself and the world.
He considered this urge ever-present, eternally reborn and
revitalized, and strengthened by man's unending search
for the origin of things.
From the moment he won the essay prize offered by the
Dijon Academy, Rousseau was opposed to jurists and
philosophers, as Indeed he was to the wave of rationalist
thinking in the 18th century. He attacked the jurists and
philosophers for making no distinction between man's
fundamental nature and the accidental existence he is
forced to lead twisted and contorted by a thousand and
one forms of inequality.
Nor did Rousseau flinch from later attacking even the
Encyclopedists, including those who sincerely liked and
admired him. For he felt they were little more than the
stewards of an enlightened elite which regarded itself as
the sole guardian of the struggle against the injustice
maintained by the authorities in power.
And Rousseau realized that liberty and equality as well
as the enormous task of education could no more be left
in the hands of those who held power and denied justice
than in the hands of those who held the privileges of
rank or the monopoly of knowledge.
Today, once again, the peoples who have recently
acceded to independence have awakened to the need for
educating their young as the very condition for their
social stability and their social progress. Thus, far from
being outmoded, the tasks laid down by Rousseau still
loom large before us. The dream of the solitary dreamer
has become the fabric of our political and social structures
as it has that of our everyday action. For years to come
Rousseau's ideas will continue to inspire all those whose
task it is, as he himself said, "to help men to establish
their rights."
Writing of his exile in Motiers, Switzerland, Rousseau related
in his Confessions : "I continued to walk quietly through the
country wearing' my fur bonnet and long coat, surrounded by
the clamours of this scum of the earth and sometimes by their
stones." Engraving (right) shows Rousseau in the situation he
described. But history was to offer him a striking posthumous
victory over those who tried to stifle his words. From the time
of the French Revolution his influence was felt unceasingly and
his popularity became immense. Above, portraits of Rousseau
and Voltaire used here to illustrate an 18th-century calendar.
* ,
M HIM
1 I -.1 ."! 1 ;I-i I I I I
1 M 111
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
THE ROAD FROM
PERSECUTION
TO APOTHEOSIS
Below, Rousseau's portrait flanked by those of Voltaire and Benjamin
Franklin. Grouped under the title, "The Torch of the Universe", they
were used as a medallion decoration on a box made during the revolu¬
tionary epoch. Left, The Apotheosis of Jean-Jacques Rousseau. Sixteen
years after his death his remains are transferred in state to the Panthéon.
Photos Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
ORIENTAL ECHOES
OF THE
SOCIAL CONTRACT
There have been three thinkers
in the Far East whose ideas reveal
singular analogies with those of
Jean-Jacques Rousseau. Chronologic¬
ally they were Houang Tsong-Hi
of China, who lived in the XVIIth
century ; Shoeki Ando, a Japanese
country doctor who was a contem¬
porary of Rousseau ; and another
Japanese, Chomin Nakae, a writer
in the latter part of the XlXth
century who translated the Social
Contract, who was the first to ac¬
quaint the Far East with Rousseau's
by Takeo Kuwabara
5 Werner Bischof-Magnum
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
theories and who was known as
the «Rousseau of the Orient".
Houang Tsong-Hi's period is a
century earlier than that of Rous¬
seau ; but, two hundred years after
his death, Houang's democratic ideal
was to inspire the Chinese people
during the 1911 revolution, and he
was known to the revolutionaries
as the "Chinese Rousseau".
Shoeki did not even know the
name of Jean-Jacques Rousseau but,
for many reasons, he well deserved to
be called the "Japanese Rousseau".
A portrait of Houang Tsong-
hi (1610-1695) known as
"The Chinese Rousseau".
Iwanami Publishing Co
H| ouANG Tsong-Hi was born in 1610 in a repu¬
table family of central China during the Ming
dynasty. His father, a learned and scholarly man, was
involved in plots against the Court eunuchs and was even¬
tually sent to prison where he died. Houang too took up
the political struggle, often at the risk of his life, and only
devoted himself finally to philosophy when he saw that
the collapse of the Ming regime was complete.
In 1663 he published a work entitled Ming y tai fan
lou. Though only fifty pages in length, it was nonethe¬
less a work of prime importance which set out the basic
principles of his political theory. The title literally means
"Political Advice to an Ideal Future Head of State" and
the main chapters of the 13 which make up the preface
are entitled "What is the Prince?" "What is the Subject?"
"What is the Law?" "The Prime Minister's Establish¬
ment" and "Academy."
In the chapter entitled "What is the Prince?" Houang
explains that man has always looked after his own
interests and that though this may be a natural state of
affairs, it also means that no one has the public interest
at heart or tries to eradicate things which harm the com¬
munity as a whole. As a result, it is hard to maintain the
"T'ien hia" (a Chinese term meaning human society as
compared with "Kuo" which means the State or the
Kingdom).
Men thereupon step forward who are prepared to
sacrifice their own interests on behalf of the T'len hia
men such as Yao and Chun, kings from a legendary past
whom the Chinese regard as paragons of princes or
saints. But the kings of later times considered that the
T'ien hia belonged to them and lived in luxury and
idleness to the detriment of the people: they became
thieves preying on the T'ien hia.
Accordingly, the people regarded the reigning princes
as enemies. "The people constitute the most precious
thing in the world," said Mencius, "then comes the State
and the least precious is the Prince." The Chinese philo¬
sopher recognized the .right to revolt, asserting that it
was proper to overthrow a government which harmed the
interests of the people.
The learned men who criticise Mencius, said Houang,
are corrupt; and he adds that when an official has a
position in the government it is in order to, serve the
T'ien hia (human society), and not the reigning Prince.
The law existed in the Golden Age under upright princes
because laws were established for the benefit of T'ien hia
whereas later on they were promulgated in the interest
of the kings so that power, which the kings looked on as
their own property, was transmitted from father to son.
They therefore do not deserve to be called Law.
As regards the academy, Houang's thought is entirely
original. The academy was an institution which at one
time grouped the thinkers and scholars. Its principal and
its professors were not solely concerned with teaching;
they also undertook to raise, in the loftiest sense of that
term, the political ideal of students. The revered kings
of antiquity invariably accepted the views of the academy.
It was not for them to decide on their own account what
was sound policy; they had to refer the question to the
academy.
Houang called for the revival of this system. The
"assembly of Intellectuals" should meet once each month
with the head of the academy in the place of honour and
the Prince listening among the students. The principal's
task would be to appraise the Prince's policy without fear
or favour.
Certain Japanese scholars emphasise the fact that
Houang did not reject the monarchy (in which he differs
from Rousseau whose ideals were republican and egalita¬
rian) and remained a devotee of primitive Confucianism
headed by Mencius. However this may be, the revolution¬
ary movement of the T'sing period called on Houang's
theories and when Rousseau's ideas began to be known in
China, via Japan, Houang became known as the Chinese
Rousseau. It was because of this kinship between their
ideals that Rousseau's ideas, through those of Houang,
came to play an important role in the modernization of
China.
S. HOEKi Ando, on the other hand, exercised no
' Influence whatsoever in his own country. Very
little is known of his life, not even the exact date of his
birth and death. It is known that the was a doctor in
Northeastern Japan and that he travelled widely through¬
out the country. His masterpiece is the Shizen Shi-
neido (The True State of Nature) which was published
in Kyoto in 1753 in an abridged form.
In the XVIIIth century, Japanese society which had
remained in a state of stability since 1639, when the coun¬
try had been virtually prohibited to foreigners, began to
suffer from a disequilibrium which was to lead to revolu¬
tion a century later. Capitalism did not yet exist but the
merchant middle class was growing stronger. The big
landowners grew increasingly wealthy and the peasants
increasingly poor. As from 1750, peasant revolts became
more and more frequent. Such was the period in which
Shoeki wrote.
His ideal was the "Chokko no Shinzin" ("The pure man
who cultivates the land with his own hands".) To work
the land with his own hands represents man's true con¬
dition. As a result, all men should be free and equal.
It is because the true state of nature has been lost and
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
ORIENTAL ECHOES (Cont'd)
Revelations of the son of a Samurai
26
replaced by an artificial state that classes have come into
being with the rich exploiting the poor.
This brings us close to Rousseau. But Rousseau was a
great artist whereas Shoeki was little concerned with
beauty of expression. He Is sometimes held to be an
atheist because he rejected Buddhist and Confucian doc¬
trine, but although he criticized corruption among the
Shinto priests of his time, he remained in favour of
ancient Shintoism.
Shoeki hoped to transform society by gradually return¬
ing the Samurai to the land, since they produced nothing,
and by turning the great lords into small land-holders or
local magistrates. But he had no other clear plan for the
future. He did not even envisage the concept of a "social
contract" and, while his criticisms were harsh, he did
nothing to overthrow the established order since he
loathed violence. His philosophy was based on nature
and he believed in a necessary co-operation between all
the component parts of society. Good and evil were not
absolute opposites; nature required their co-existence.
A century after Shoeki's death, the feudal system of the
Tokugawas was abolished, but Shoeki's theories played no
more part in this revolution than those of Rousseau, for
the very good reason that nothing was known of Rousseau
in 1868 while Shoeki had been utterly forgotten. Japan's
major need at that time was modernization, without which
the country would have been entirely dependent on the
Western countries which had already achieved their
Industrial revolution. And it was to bring about modern¬
ization that the people overthrew the feudal government.
Ten years later, a great anti-government movement
demanded liberty and equality, the "Jiyu-Minken-Undo"
based on Rousseau's theories and with Chomin Nakae as
its ideologist.
okusuke Nakae, the son of a Samurai of
Shikoku Island, is better known by his pseu¬
donym of Chomin which means "people numbering a
thousand million." This name which he chose for himself
is indicative of the way his thoughts ran. Chomin learnt
Dutch and French and spent two years in France. On
his return, he founded a school where he lectured on
French civilization (language, philosophy and politics).
In 1882, he completed his translation of The Social Con¬
tract but as early as 1877 manuscript excerpts were cir¬
culating in liberal circles. It is certain that this trans¬
lation stimulated the spirit of resistance and the rebellion
against the despotic government. In 1883, the translation
of the Discourse on the Sciences and the Arts followed
that of The Social Contract.
Chomin subsequently contributed to various newspapers
and periodicals and disseminated Rousseau's democratic
ideas so thoroughly that the government expelled him
from the capital. When the first National Assembly was
convened in 1890, he stood as a candidate and was elected
but resigned in order to protest against bribery which
occurred when the government paid certain deputies, even
including liberal deputies, to ensure that the budget was
voted.
Opposed by the government, the "Jiyu-Minken-Undo"
the Democratic Liberal Movement had failed, but there
can be no doubt that it contributed to the formation of
the constitutional government. The 1889 Constitution did
not recognise the supremacy of the people but it would
have been even more dictatorial in essence had the demo¬
cratic movement never existed.
The ideologist Chomin felt responsible for the fate of
the people. He did not become a statesman but remained
a thinker whose influence was considerable in China as
well as Japan. His main work, the San Suijn Keirin
mondo (Political Discussion among Three Drinkers) pre¬
sents the pro-Western "Yogaku-Shinshi" who urges the
immediate creation of a democratic republic; the nation¬
alistic "Goketsu-Kun" who holds imperialist views
regarding the continent of Asia and, finally, the moderate
"Nakai-sensei" who seeks to reconcile the demands of his
companions by proposing gradual modernization.
This discussion among the three drinkers clearly sums
up the political problems of the period. Chomin himself
used the arguments of the "Yogaku-Shinshi" but with the
reasoned qualifications of the "Nankai-sensel." He classi¬
fied democratic systems in two categories: the first, those
which the people had obtained through force and the
second, those consented by the Prince. The latter he con¬
sidered the more estimable.
Like Rousseau in The Social Contract (Book 11, Chap¬
ter 6), he believed that it was possible and necessary to
establish a republic in Japan while retaining the monarch
in his position.
Chomin, however, believed more in evolution than in
progress and, in this sense, he divides with Rousseau. In
his view, both nature and mankind evolve and men should
assist that evolution. Again, his ideas were based on
materialism and atheism reached via Buddhistic natura¬
lism. Confucianism had strongly Influenced him, too, and,
while he may have rejected the Chinese philosopher's doc¬
trine on the political level, he was nonetheless deeply
affected by his thinking.
Thus we discover three Asians whose ideas were linked
with those of Rousseau. This strange homogeneity gives
us much on which to ponder. Is it because the separa-
teness of urban existence and its associated wealth raises
a social problem in all societies based on peasant life and
agriculture and because luxury engenders inequality? In
that case, no matter what the country, liberal and sen¬
sitive thinkers preoccupied with this contradiction follow
a revolutionary line of thought which precedes industrial
revolution. Since science and techniques have not yet
succeeded In radically transforming human society, such
thinkers evoke an ideal society which is supposed to have
existed in the past. If they cannot unveil the structures
of the future, they infuse their analysis of reality with
certain idealistic elements which are to contribute to the
building of new social structures and thus play their part
in the society of the future.
takeo kuwabara is director of the Institute of Cultural Sciences
and professor of French literature at the University of Kyoto,
Japan. The article above is adapted from an address given by
Professor Kuwabara to the World Round Table on "Jean-Jacques
Rousseau and Modern Man" , held in Royaumont, near Paris, from
June 28 to July 3, 1962.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
'(
I 'r:'. '
" ü«*!2«
Mexican farmers learn some new agricultural methods that
improve yield and quality of Indian corn crops. Combined
efforts of the Mexican government and international organi¬
zations have been giving a large boost to Mexico's agricultural
output. Wheat harvests alone have doubled in the past decade.
:; *%£?& ¿«PR %^^^7i 5rm
wwm^^
i Paul Almasy, Paris
THE INDIVISIBILITY
OF WORLD PROSPERITY
THE ANATOMY
OF UNDERDEVELOPMENT
(Pt 4) *
In many of today's underdeveloped
countries, economic development
involves the rapid and simulta¬
neous carrying out of so many
nation-wide activities that often
only governments are competent
to provide the necessary initial
impulse and over-all supervision.
Even governments, however, lack
some of the means required for
this immense task. Technical assis¬
tance on a vast international scale
¡sthe subject of this, the concluding
article in a series based on a new
study produced by the United Na¬
tions under the title "Aspects of
Economic Development: The Back¬
ground to Freedom from Hunger."
(*) See The Unesco Courier, July-August, Sep¬
tember and November 1962.
fOR the first time in history, men, wherever they
live, are learning to think of the resources and
welfare of the human race as something of concern to
all. For the first time, the peoples of the world are
beginning to share their vast experience and accumulated
knowledge. The existence of the international secretariats
is itself evidence of a new outlook.
Here, a body of specialists in many fields, recruited
from the most diverse backgrounds and working under
an oath of objectivity, is available to assist and advise
governments in the formulation and execution of their
economic and social policies. This change in human
attitudes is still no more than tentative, but the English
historian, Sir Arnold Toynbee, has described it as perhaps
the most significant mark of our times.
Just as individual firms, industrialists and others in the
underdeveloped countries are turning to their governments
for help, so governments are turning to the world
community of nations. There are many ways, direct and
indirect, in which the international organizations can
make such help available to them. Certain forms
of direct assistance, namely technical and pre-investment
assistance and the financing of economic development may
first be briefly examined.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
WORLD PROSPERITY (Cont'd)
Man's greatest common enterprise
The governments of countries undergoing economic
development can seek technical assistance from a variety
of sources, such as the United States International Co¬
operation Administration, the British Commonwealth
Colombo Plan, the U.S.S.R. foreign aid programme or the
bilateral aid programmes of France, the Federal Republic
of Germany, the Netherlands, Norway and other countries.
The larger foreign aid programmes operate on an
impressive scale. Thus, the United States allocates for
economic, as distinct from military, assistance over $2,000
million per year. The British Commonwealth Colombo
Plan disbursed approximately $3,500 million in the period
1950-1957.
The equivalent of over $8,000 million is aid to be devoted
each year by the industrialized countries as a whole to
various forms of economic assistance. This figure Includes
about US $1,600 million from private investment, of which
over $1,000 million comes from Western Europe.
Substantial assistance Is given in various forms by such
countries as the United Kingdom, France and the
Netherlands to colonies or former colonies. The French
outlay on such assistance, not counting Algeria, is said
to amount to 1,2 percent of the national income, which
is claimed as a record.
The governments of underdeveloped countries also turn
for help to the United Nations and the related inter¬
governmental agencies, for all of which technical assis¬
tance has become an extremely important activity. It is
with technical assistance provided by the United Nations
and those agencies that we are concerned here, although
its annual volume so far represents only a fraction of that
supplied bilaterally.
he U.N. Expanded Programme of Technical
Assistance was launched in 1950, since the
assistance given by the United Nations and the Specialized
Agencies out of their regular budgets was proving much
too modest for the needs. This Expanded Programme is
paid for by voluntary contributions made annually by
governments, members of the United Nations or Spe¬
cialized Agencies. It is co-ordinated by the Technical
Assistance Board (T.A.B.), which consists of representa¬
tives of the United Nations and of the eight intergovern¬
mental agencies which also participate in the programme.
The organizations participating in the Expanded Pro¬
gramme are the United Nations, the International Atomic
Energy Agency, the International Labour Organization,
the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Na¬
tions, the United Nations Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization, the International Civil Aviation
Organization, the World Health Organization, the Inter¬
national' Telecommunications, Union and the World
Meteorological Organization.
Each of these participating organizations works within
a specific field. Economic development as such is one of
the responsibilities of the United Nations, although the
term is so broad that all the activities of the participating
agencies are in some degree associated with economic
development programmes. United Nations technical
assistance is closely integrated with the work of the
Department of Economic and Social Affairs.
Early each year, T.A.B. notifies governments of the
approximate sum which is expected to be available to each
under the Expanded Programme of Technical Assistance
in all fields during the next year, and asks for an official
28 list of requests for experts and fellowships to be drawn
up in order of priority. Technical assistance is given on
the basis of such requests. Each year, the report of T.A.B.
to the Technical Assistance Committee of the Economic
and Social Council reviews the work of the previous twelve
months and critically appraises progress and trends.
Under the Expanded Programme, experts in a great
variety of fields are made available to governments re¬
questing their services, and fellowships are awarded for
nationals of the economically underdeveloped countries to
study the most recent techniques which have been
developed abroad. In certain cases, limited amounts of
equipment may be made available, primarily for demons¬
tration purposes.
t any moment, there are over a thousand
k experts . serving on foreign missions for the
T.A.B. and other technical assistance programmes organ¬
ized by the U.N. family. Since 1950, about 10,000 of them
have been sent out from 83 countries and territories and,
in the same period, some 20,000 fellows from 149 countries
and territories, have studied abroad a multilateral
pooling of skills such as has never before been attempted.
Every problem of economic development has at some
time been the subject of a request for expert advice or
for fellowship study. Technical assistance given under
the T.A.B. programme ranges from advice given directly
to a Prime Minister on long-range economic planning in
all fields to technical guidance on some defect revealed in
the manufacture of a spare part. The advice of the
"older" countries is continually being placed at the
disposal of those with less experience.
Even countries which are comparatively new to indus¬
trialization are often asked, under the United Nations
programme, to make some of their few experts available
to help others which are about to grapple with the
obstacles we have been studying. It has been found that
their special knowledge of the obstacles and difficulties
renders their advice particularly valuable and makes them
quickly able to assess needs.
At the 1958 General Assembly session, a United Nations
Special Fund was established "as a constructive advance
in United Nations assistance to the less developed
countries." Special Fund assistance differs from tradi¬
tional U.N. technical assistance in several important
respects. For one thing, it concentrates on relatively more
expensive projects. The average gross cost of the first
205 projects approved was somewhat more than $2 million,
with the Special Fund contributing $850,000 to each, and
the recipient Government the remainder.
hURTHER, the projects not only involve bigger
teams of experts but also a much higher
equipment component. This ranges from the provision
of an airplane for forestry inventories to supplying rigs
and diamond drills to find ground-water.
Finally, the projects are designed to have the widest
possible impact on the economic and social development
of the countries, particularly by facilitating new capital
investment. Thus the Special Fund provides a kind of
technical assistance in depth, assistance specially geared
to make substantial investment feasible and more effec¬
tive.
This "pre-investment" assistance falls into four
principal categories: .
surveys of needs for skilled manpower and of natural
resources, for instance mineral and geological sur¬
veys, water power, hydraulic and meteorological
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Unesco-Almasy
In those tropical countries which are "sun-rich" but poor
in conventional fuels like oil and coal, solar energy
may one day become a widely-used source of power to
run pumps, refrigerating plants and to purify brackish
water, for example. Research is now being stepped up.
Above, a solarimeter at the Solar Energy Laboratory,
University of Dakar, in the Senegal Republic, is used
to measure solar radiation that is diffused by the sky.
surveys, other land and water use surveys, and fishing
surveys ;
applied research, such as agricultural, fishery,
veterinary, forestry and industrial research;
training, especially of teachers and extension
workers, in such fields as agriculture, forestry, ani¬
mal health and fishing, in industry, engineering,
transport and communications and for secondary
school teachers; and
training and advisory services in economic planning
and public administration.
Mr. Paul G. Hoffman, formerly head of the United States
"Marshall Plan" for European post-war recovery, is
Managing Director of the Special Fund. He is responsible
to a Governing Council of eighteen States elected by the
Economic and Social Council. Half of the members are
industrially advanced nations, and half low-income
countries. Requests for Special Fund assistance are
submitted by governments to the Managing Director, who
recommends to the Governing Council for its approval
only those considered to meet the criteria of the Special
Fund and to offer promise of early results.
The objective is always to speed up the integrated
technical, economic and social development of the less
developed countries. The implementation of each project
thus far approved has been entrusted to the services of the
United Nations or one of its specialized agencies.
Today's underdeveloped countries face formidable
obstacles in the struggle to increase the earning power of
their people. Often there is no mercantile class ready to
become the entrepreneurs of a new historical phase, and
in many lands the educated classes show active distaste
for the industrial or commercial life. Inadequate know¬
ledge of the prospects before a new industry is an added
deterrent to those who have capital. The mass of the
people is far too poor to have money for investment or
for the purchase of manufactured goods.
Land reform and other social changes may be an essen¬
tial preliminaty to any substantial increase In the
earnings of the people. New attitudes of mind which
machinery and industrialization require on the part of
masses of men are also a conspicuous need. At the same
time, care must be taken to preserve, as far as possible,
those social and other values of the non-industrialized
culture which might otherwise be needlessly sacrificed in
the helter-skelter of change.
In these circumstances, governments have come to play
an important role in economic development, for In all the
countries concerned, development involves tasksecono¬
mic, educational and social of a magnitude which calls
for some degree of central planning and co-ordination.
But, while the role of national governments may be vital,
governments themselves require international help in
carrying out these huge tasks.
H ELP is given by the United Nations, the spe-
l cialized agencies and the International Bank
through technical and pre-investment assistance, through
international loans and through the machinery for regular
consultation and for specialized publications provided by
the international organizations. These publications have
established themselves as a unique source of information
on economic and social development.
Side by side with numerous bilateral programmes of
technical aid, the United Nations and the specialized
agencies are assisting governments on request by providing
them with internationally recruited experts and with
fellowships for their own nationals to study abroad.
Not the least important aspect of economic development
is the remarkable opportunity it is giving for International
discussion and exchange of knowledge. For the first time,
technical assistance and related activities are making it
possible to bring the entire world's experience and skills
to bear upon each individual country's problems. While
the international organizations are using economic deve¬
lopment, as the Charter requires, to help raise living
standards, they are also finding In it a means to further
world co-operation and to promote the friendship of
nations.
N evertheless, despite all that has been done to
publicize economic development programmes,
there is not yet sufficient understanding of the vast issues
which they involve for man's future. The urgency of the
need for increased assistance is not yet grasped by the
mass of the people, and even by many public figures, in
the industrialized countries from which that assistance
must chiefly come.
Nor are the nature and duration of the effort which
will be called for in the less developed countries them¬
selves always fully understood by their citizens, any more
than the profound changes of attitude that will sometimes
be required before living standards can be made to rise.
The economic state of any society is the result still more
of the psychological state of its members than of its
geographical situation or natural resources.
We are engaged upon perhaps the greatest enterprise
which man has yet undertaken in common. We cannot
yet be sure of success, and we know that the effort will be
exacting and very long. But the energy and persistency
with which we pursue this effort must be the measure of
our high ambition. (End.)
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
This year and In 1964 Unesco's programme gives top priority to education. In addition to pre-
30 paring a world adult illiteracy campaign, Unesco will step up its aid to newly-independent and
developing countries which need to expand and improve their school systems. Above, time
out from the classroom for children from a temple school in the heart of Benares, India.
© Richard Lannoy.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO 1963-1964
A WORLD PROGRAMME
FOR EDUCATION
SCIENCE AND CULTURE
he Unesco General Conference held its 12th
session In Paris from November 9 to December
12, 1962, under the presidency of Professor Paulo de Ber-
redo Carneiro of Brazil. Among the important decisions
taken three stand out: the election of a new Director-
General for Unesco, an increase in membership of the
Unesco Executive Board and the approval of Unesco's
programme and budget for 1963-1964.
Three heads of statethe President of the Council of
Ministers of the U.S.S.R., the President of the United
States and the President of the French Republicsent
messages of good wishes to the Conference. Mr. Krush¬
chev's message was received on November 9, that of Presi¬
dent Kennedy on November 13 and that of General de
Gaulle on December 12. The French President had
previously received the members of the General Committee
of the Conference at the Elysée Palace, on November 16.
One of the first tasks of the Conference was to elect a
Director-General of Unesco. On November 14, by an
overwhelming majority, it elected for six years Mr. René
Maheu of France who had served as Acting Director-
General since the resignation of Mr. Vittorino Veronese
of .Italy in 1961.
Responsible for the execution of Unesco's programme
and its general policy between sessions of the General
Conference, the Unesco Executive Board Is composed of
persons of special competence in the arts, humanities,
the sciences, education and the diffusion of Ideas who
are elected as Individuals, but represent the governments
of their respective countries. In view of the great increase
in the number of Unesco's Member statesfrom 44 to 113
in the past 16 years the Conference decided to raise the
Board's membership from 24 to 30.
The chief task of the Conference was to examine and
approve Unesco's programme. After taking stock of the
work carried out since its previous session, the Conference
outlined Unesco's tasks for 1963-1964. To finance them,
it voted a budget of $39 million as compared to a previous
two-year budget of just over $32,500,000. Unesco will also
dispose of extra-budgetary resources from the United
Nations Technical Assistance Programme, estimated at
about $12 million for the next two years. In addition
Unesco will serve as executing agent for a number of
United Nations Special Fund Projects.
^IVE special priority projects stand out in
Unesco's programme for 1963-1964:
A world literacy campaign;
A programme of international co-operation in scientific
hydrology ;
A major study of main trends in social science
research ;
A programme for the study and development of school
building plans;
A study on the use of satellites for telecommunication
purposes.
Top priority was given to education. The Conference
voted a total of $9.9 million for education out of the
regular budget and In addition an estimated $17.3 million
will be available for educational activities from United
Nations Technical Assistance and the U.N. Special Fund.
The General Conference discussed at length the prob¬
lems raised by the need to eradicate illiteracy through¬
out the world. Each year the number of adult illiterates
in the world increases by between 20 and 25 millions.
Today there are an estimated 500 million of illiterate
people aged between 15 and 50 years of age. "Shameful
figures," declared Mr. Maheu at the opening of the Confe¬
rence, "shameful for moral reasons because of the
injustice to which they bear witness, shameful, too, for
strictly economic reasons because of the fantastic waste
of intellectual resources that they represent."
Unesco will work out concrete and effective measures
for the launching of a world campaign which, In its
initial phase, will aim to bring literacy to 350 million
people. This action will be a major Unesco contribution
to the United Nations Development Decade (See The
Unesco Courier, June, 1962). Declaring that Unesco was
ready "to promote and support such a campaign," the
Conference added that it should be carried out in
conjunction with programmes for the extension of primary
education.
he Conference decided to establish in Paris an
International Institute of Educational Plan¬
ning which will provide special courses for government
officials and administrators, educational planners and
economists or other specialists from institutions concerned
with encouraging economic and social development. At
the same time the Conference stressed the importance
of research and assistance concerning school building
construction, and decided to increase assistance given in
this field in 1963-1964.
Regional aid in education a large part of Unesco's grow¬
ing operational activitieswill be concentrated on Africa
where the most urgent needs are the recruiting and
training of teachers, the building of schools and the
production of textbooks. Large-scale aid, however, is also
forseen for activities benefiting the Arab States, Asia and
Latin America.
By its decision to include in the natural sciences pro¬
gramme preparatory work for an International Hydrologie
Decade, the Conference recognized the extreme gravity
of problems concerned with various aspects of water
management in many parts of the world. Hydrology, the
science which treats of water and its distribution over the
earth's surface, its properties and laws and its use by
human beings, needs to be rapidly developed so that acute
problems due either to lack of water or to the misuse of
present water resources can be met.
In vast areas of the world basic facts and figures relat¬
ing to water are insufficient or even Inexistant; there are
nowhere near enough specialists in this field. Even in
economically-developed countries few universities offer
training courses for hydrologists, as such, and countries in
the throes of development need scientific help and advice
in order to create laboratories and research institutes.
In preparation for the International Hydrologie Decade
in 1965, the Unesco Conference decided to call a special
meeting in 1964 to discuss and adopt an international pro¬
gramme in scientific hydrology. In the meantime Unesco
will offer fellowships and organize training courses so that
many countries will be able to participate In this pro¬
gramme once it is adopted.
The social science programme as outlined by the
Conference reveals a clear trend towards concrete applica¬
tions. The role of the social sciences as a "hinge" had
been recognized, declared Mohammed El Fasi, President of
the Programme Commission, "not only because they are
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
WORLD PROGRAMME (Cont'd)
Prospects of communication satellites
essential to a clear-sighted planning of education itself,
but because they provide young nations with the means
to proceed with their development clearly and rationally,
and the international community in general with ways to
grapple with some of the major problems of the modern
world."
The Conference decided to support the establishment in
Vienna of a co-ordination centre for social science research
and documentation, where specialists from countries of
different social and economic systems will collaborate. At
the regional level, Unesco will aid the Latin American
Social Science Faculty at Santiago, Chile, the Latin
American Research Centre at Rio de 'Janeiro and the
Research Centre on Social and Economic Development in
Southern Asia at New Delhi.
u nesco will also carry out a major study of main
	 trends in social science research similar to
the remarkable survey that was made of world scientific
trends and technological research (*) which could
provide a new basis for and give fresh impulse to the
branches of the social sciences in question.
Unesco's programme in the field of mass communication
for 1963-1964 will have three main objectives: (1) to pro¬
mote the free flow in information and the development of
the means and techniques of mass communication; (2)
to develop the use of these media and techniques in the
service of education at all levels; (3) to stimulate their
use in furthering international understanding.
A Unesco World Enquiry carried out during the past
four years at the request of the United Nations has shown
that about 70% of the world's populationsome 2,000
million peoplestill lack adequate Information facilities.
In various ways Unesco is to help developing countries
to set up or to expand their newspapers, news agencies,
radio broadcasting services and, where applicable, educa¬
tional television services. Unesco's Department of Mass
Communication in addition will assist countries to make
wider use of modern information techniques at all levels of
education, as well as already established methods such as
filmstrips, slides and tape recordings.
After discussions on the free flow of information, the
Conference noted "the lightning progress made during the
past two years in the launching and peaceful utilization
of artificial earth satellites" and- considered that "these
marvellous achievements of science and technology, and
those which may be expected in the near future, open ur»
boundless prospects for the free flow of information with
peaceful aims, the education of young people and adults,
the universal dissemination of knowledge... and cultural
exchanges between countries." It authorized Unesco's
Director-General "to study the consequences which the
use of new techniques of communication on a world
scale... are likely to have."
One of the consequences in question will be the
_ need to re-allocate the radio frequency spec¬
trum to make provision for the use of appropriate fre¬
quencies in the communication satellite service. A special
conference of the InternationalTelecommunications Union
(ITU) will open in Geneva next October to allocate fre¬
quency bands for space radio communication purposes. A
subsequent meeting of specialists, to be held at Unesco's
H.Q. in Paris, will make further studies aimed at achieving
a common programme concerning Unesco member states
and international organizations, and will also put forward
new recommendations for Unesco's programme in 1965-
1966.
Unesco's programme of international exchanges will
also be devoted to international communications but in a
different form. Unesco's exchange service will, in addition
to publishing "Study Abroad" and "Vacations Abroad,"
32
(*) "Current Trends in Scientific Research" by Pierre Auger
(See The Unesco Courier, April 1962).
also bring out a new volume, "Handbook for International
Exchanges" which is designed as a standard work of
reference in the field of exchange. The Exchange Service
will also administer some 1,500 Unesco fellowships in
1963-1964.
Finally, the Conference underlined the role of cultural
activities, alone capable of preparing the way for a
humanism in which universality and diversity are reconcil¬
ed. Philosophy and the humanistic sciences are called
upon to advance knowledge of different cultures and
civilizations and to go thoroughly tato the cultural aspects
of present-day world problems. Unesco offers a frame¬
work for and a bridge between the studies and research
of thinkers and scholars. The constructive exchanges
thus encouraged open the way to broad new perspectives.
A share for everyone in cultural life one of the rights
laid down in the Universal Declaration of Human Rights
is a condition of social progress. The man in the street
will have increased opportunities to appreciate the results
of Unesco's work, whether through the popularization of
treasures of art (world art albums and pocket art books),
of the cinema (aid to art and cultural films), of literature
(series of translations of classical and modern works from
East and West), or of music (records in a Musical Antho¬
logy of the Orient).
During the next two years, the major project on the
mutual appreciation of Eastern and Western cultural
values will aim mainly at the establishment or strengthen¬
ing of research and teaching institutes capable of ensuring
permanent future exchanges between large cultural
regions.
'roblems relating to the protection of the
world's cultural heritage remain principally
centered on the specific case of the Nubian monuments.
Thanks to Unesco's intervention, major arch
excavations of vital historical significance have been
carried out and a large number of monuments have been
taken to places of safety or protected where they stand.
But there is still a question mark over the fate of the
temples of Abu Simbel. The Conference refused to
guarantee a loan of $30,500,000 to finance the lifting of
these rock temples and instead, issued a new appeal for
voluntary contributions to governments and to public or
private institutions. An executive committee of represen¬
tatives from 15 countries is to meet before March 31 to
study the results of this appeal.
In the words of Professor de Berredo Carneiro, "Unesco
has given itself the task of promoting mutual understand¬
ing among the peoples, of giving a powerful stimulus to
education and the dissemination of culture and of assist¬
ing in the maintenance and advancement of knowledge."
Yet all these actions must be indissociably linked With an
ideal which is written in its Constitution: the maintenance
of peace. Thus another of Unesco's permanent functions
is to encourage the adoption by governments of laws and
practices essential to peace and intellectual progress.
Two recommendations of this kind were adopted. The
first, concerned with technical and vocational education,
stresses the need to develop this form of education accord¬
ing to common principles covering the organization,
orientation, staffs and methods of schools for training,
engineers, technicians and skilled workers. The second
aims at guaranteeing the protection of rural and urban
landscapes which, despite their esthetic value, "are in
danger of being disfigured by building development and
land speculation."
These, in brief, are the main achievements of the 12th
session of the General Conference in preparation for the
two years ahead. The whole forms the programme of
Unesco which has set out to establish a system of co¬
operation and social harmony on rational foundations for,
as Professor de Berredo Carneiro reminded the General
Conference, "Without a far-reaching reform of opinions
and moral codes through education, the social sciences
and the development of culture, it will be impossible to
control the disturbances which increasingly affect Inter¬
national life."
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
BETTER INVESTMENTS
THAN ARMS
Sir,
Unesco cannot concern itself exclu¬
sively with problems of education,
science and culture, standing aside
from the struggle to maintain world
peace. Today, Unesco should do all
in its power towards reducing present
world tensions. The most effective
way to safeguard world peace is for
all nations to agree to total disarma¬
ment.
You could explain what mankind is
losing by investing gigantic resources
in armaments. What wonderful pro¬
jects for the transformation of our
planet could be carried out with this
money, with a benefit to everyone
and an improvement of living stan¬
dards in all lands.
M.J.M. Dellarg
Léopoldville, Republic of the Congo
SOCIETY CALLS THE TUNE
Sir,
In the November 1962 issue of your
superb magazine (of which I am
regrettably a rather late subscriber) is
the most interesting article "Society
calls the Tune" by Peter Lengyel. To
fellow-readers interested in this subject,
I strongly recommend "Music, its
Secret Influence Throughout the Ages"
by Cyril Scott (John F. Rider Inc.,
New York), In the Chapter "The
Future of Music", Mr. Scott prophe¬
sied the invention of new musical
instruments to be used in the music
of the future. "Perhaps the instru¬
ment invented by MM. Baschet and
Lasry, is one of the those prophe¬
sied many years ago.
Harry Scheid
Cleveland, Ohio, U.S.A.
Sir,
I am a student of the Bartok Con¬
servatory of Budapest. In your Nov¬
ember 1962 issue I read with great
interest an article by Mr. Peter Len¬
gyel, "Society Calls the Tune". I
should like to express my thanks to
Mr. Lengyel for his writing. I think
his article has done much in the for¬
mation of my opinion about music.
Csaba Erdelyi
Budapest, Hungary
GERHART HAUPTMANN
AND ALFRED KERR
Sir,
In his article on Gerhart Haupt¬
mann (Sept. 1962) Karl Ruhrberg
wrote: "Alfred Kerr, the dramatic cri¬
tic, who devoted a lifetime to com¬
menting on Hauptmann's development
and explaining his intentions, declared
that the basic sentiment in his writing
was longing longing for a better
world, where all men would be bro¬
thers, all class and racial prejudices
forgotten."
A reader unfamiliar with events that
took place around 1930 would be led
to believe that throughout his life
Alfred Kerr had been a supporter of
Gerhart Hauptmann. But such is
not the case, and in the interests of
historical fact it should be made clear
that what Karl Ruhrberg calls "a life¬
time" ended brusquely in 1933 when
Kerr cut himself off from Hauptmann
for ever. He did this not through bitter¬
ness over the destiny which forced
him, as it did so many other figures on
the German cultural scene, to eat the
bitter bread of exile, but because he
could not forgive Hauptmann for
taking sides with the persecutors and
executioners of those he had defended
in his social drama "The Weavers".
In November 1933, Kerr wrote in
the "'Volkstimme" of Sarrebrucken:
"The author of these lines has always
been a friend of Hauptmann... we have
followed together the road of life un¬
til today. No, rather until yesterday...
Since yesterday we have nothing in
common."
Kerr certainly did not expect Haupt¬
mann "to man the barricades". But
he did believe that although the au¬
thor of "The Weavers", could not find
the strength to protest, even in silence,
against the masters of the Third Reich,
he would never go so far as base flat¬
tery. "This man", »wrote Kerr, "who
throughout his life was regarded as a
poet of altruism, bows and scrapes be¬
fore the mortal enemy of altruism.
He cannot utter a single word of pro¬
test against the most barbarian of the
barbarians. He witnessed an act of
inhumanity. His closest friends were
the victims... he kept silent and linked
himself in unequivocal friendship with
the gaolers of Germany.
We wish in no way to besmirch the
memory of Gerhart Hauptmann. Our
purpose is simply to prevent the crea¬
tion of a legend which would show
Alfred Kerr at the side of the author
of "The Weavers" to the very end.
Emil Locher
Neuhausen am Rheinfall
Switzerland
THREAT TO MAN & BEAST
Sir,
Pierre Guillon's letter (In Defence
of Fertilisers, December 1962 issue)
was in reply to one from Michel Lam¬
bert (Are We Poisoning Ourselves?
July-August 1962 issue.)
The answer seems to be yes! It is
not fertilizers which contain toxic
chemicals but some sprays for weed
and insect control. In Great Britain
much wild life is threatened by
residual poisons. Some farmers and
many private gardeners are in
innocent bliss of the damage they are
causing to both wild life and man.
Certain doctors believe very many
cases of deformed children being born
are due to these toxic chemicals.
They remain in the body or plant
and cannot be excreted. When fatal
quantities have been built up death
results. The red-backed shrike, or
butcher bird, is much rarer in
England than it used to be. So are
other birds of prey, especially the
kestrel. Their prey die from
poisoning and are eaten by their
natural enemies. In their turn they
are killed by the accumulation of toxic
chemicals in the bone marrow.
Sometimes humans eat plants and
animals so affected. Are we poisoning
ourselves?
K. H. Lavender
Herne Bay, England
DRAWBACKS OF
ARTIFICIAL LANGUAGES
Sir,
E.D. Allen of Dunedin, New Zea¬
land asks (in the December 1962 issue)
"Could not Esperanto be a second lan¬
guage common to all the people of the
world?". I am a former Esperantist
and my reply is simple and direct:
"No!".
Esperanto is an artificial language
itself a. contradiction in terminis and
is not viable because it lacks the cul¬
tural and spiritual foundations that
give to a language its quality of lan¬
guage. Furthermore once Esperanto
has been learned there is no need to
learn other languages, which represent
the world's different cultural areas.
Thus one is deprived of the keys to
their literary and other intellectual
treasures, treasures which help one to
a better understanding of special
differences between peoples, and
thereby to better mutual understand¬
ing.
Against Esperanto as a vehicular
language my objection is that it is not
feasible to create a language and intro¬
duce it into an international commu¬
nity whose existing languages are the
logical outcome of historical develop¬
ment.
It is often necessary to learn a sec¬
ond language in addition to one's
own, as for example, in my country
Dutch is a difficult language and not
widely known elsewhere but in such
cases the second language must be
learned as thoroughly as possible.
My study of Esperanto has convinc¬
ed me that this language is not suitable
for general use and thus can do little
to build practicable roads between the
nations. By its admirable efforts
Unesco seeks to draw within the
community of the world's intellectual
life, all those at present illiterate. In
order to enter this community it is far
better to learn languages like English,
Russian, Chinese, Arabic, French and
Spanish rather than Esperanto.
Robert H. J. van Kuyk
Bussum, The Netherlands
EUROPEAN COMMUNITY
Sir,
I should like to see more articles
on Europe particularly in view of the
tremendous importance that the Eur¬
opean Economic Community will
have upon Europe generally and on
the resulting relations through trade
with the African and Asian coun¬
tries.
H. C. Sallnow
Cardiff, Wales
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
IN THE STEPS OF ROUSSEAU: A special 110-page booklet, "In the Footsteps of Jean-
Jacques Rousseau", illustrated by 22 colour slides has been prepared under the auspices
of the French and Swiss National Commissions for Unesco to mark the 250th anniversary
of Rousseau's birth. It contains a text by Anne-Marie Pfister, Curator of Manuscripts at
the University of Geneva Library and a preface by Jean Guehenno of the Académie
Française. Booklet and slides (in 5 x 5 cm. mounts), produced by Publications Filmées
d'Art et d'Histoire in Paris, are available in parchment or plastic cases from: Great
Britain: Miniature Gallery, 60 Rushett Close, Long Ditton, Surrey; 59/6 (parchment), 54/6
(plastic); U.S.A.: Prothman, 2787 Milburn Avenue, Baldwin, Long Island, N.Y.; $15.00
(parchment), $12.00 (plastic), $9.00 (for teachers); Canada: Queen's Printer, Ottawa,
Ont. $8.00 (parchment). $7.00 (plastic).
POLAND'S OLDEST UNIVERSITY:
The Jagellon University at Cracow
Poland's oldest will celebrate the 600th
anniversary of its foundation next year.
The university is being modernized and en¬
larged for this event and among the new
buildings are 14 scientific institutes. Over
130 universities in all parts of the world
have been invited to attend the commemo¬
ration ceremonies.
AU.S. WATER ATLAS: The story of
U.S. water resources has been told for
the first time in a single reference book.
"Water Atlas of the United States" is a
comprehensive visual guide in which 40
maps and descriptive texts offer a wealth
of water facts: sources, quality, availability
and uses. Available from Water Informa¬
tion Center Inc., 60 East 42nd St., New
York 17, N.Y.
DUCKS, SUN AND STARS: Navigation¬
al experiments with young ducks
carried out at California University, U.S.A.,
have proved that as long as the sun is
shining or stars are visible these birds can
find their way through unknown territory
to their favourite pond. A zoologist trained
the ducklings to find water to the east of
their cage and each time they were able to
see the sun or stars, they found the right
direction.
SWEDEN'S NEW SKY-EYE: A tele¬
scope with a range of "several thousand
million light-years" is to be built on the
Swedish west coast near Gothenburg. De¬
signed for radio astronomy, space research
and tele-satellite communications, it will
enable Swedish scientists to share more fully
in international space research.
DAY MOTHERS NEEDED: Millions of
children need day mothers because
more and more young women are taking
work outside the home, reports the World
Health Organization, reviewing needs of
day-care centres around the world. In the
U.S.A. alone, over three million of the
84 million working women have children
below school age.
COAL DUST DISSOLVES GLACIERS:
Soviet scientists seeking. ways to speed
up the melting of glaciers and thus increase
water supplies for irrigation have found an
effective method: coal dust sprinkled on the
ice. Five tons of dust on each square kilo¬
metre doubles or even trebles the flow of
water. Glaciers in the Soviet Union cover
about 77,000 square kilometres and contain
about 15,000 cubic kilometres of ice.
BOMBAY'S TECHNOLOGY INSTI¬
TUTE: Starting in a temporary build¬
ing in a newly-reclaimed jungle area six
years ago, the Indian Institute of Techno¬
logy at Bombay has grown into a fully
fledged engineering institution with 1,600
students. It recently held its first gradua¬
tion ceremony. The Institute has benefited
from Unesco aid since 1956 and many
Unesco specialists are working there today.
UNESCO PHILATELIC SERVICE
NATIONS UNIES KêB
i á
s sí
-Vv' "ÀiW^j
34
OBMflHHEHHblE HAUHH
Development through
Science and Technology
The first 1963 U.N. commemorative stamp (left,
was issued on February 4 to mark the opening of
the U.N. Conference on the application of Science
and Technology for the benefit of the world's less
developed areas in Geneva. Issued in 5 cent and
11 cent denominations, it calls attention . to the
objectives of the present U.N. Development
Decade. As agent in France of the U.N. Postal
Administration, Unesco's Philatelic Service stocks
all U.N. stamps and first-day covers currently on
sale, and those issued by Unesco member states
to commemorate important events in the history
of Unesco and the U.N. For prices and further
details write to The Unesco Philatelic Service,
Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7e.
WORLD THEATRE IN WARSAW:
The tenth World Theatre Congress,
organized by the Polish Centre of the In¬
ternational Theatre Institute is to be held
in Warsaw in June. Over 200 dramatists,
producers, actors, scene designers, critics
and theatre historians from 50 countries are
expected to attend.
ISRAEL AIDS IRAN: Israeli agricultural
experts, irrigation specialists and rural
planning advisers have arrived in Iran to
help build a model village in the area which
was devasted by earthquakes last year.
The new village will be a pilot project for
the reconstruction of other agricultural
communities in the region.
SAWING THROUGH ICE: Soviet engi¬
neers have designed a new icebreaker
that saws her way through ice packs. The
vessel's long inclined prow is fitted with
saws which slice through the ice. As the
ship moves forward the ice slides up an
incline and on to conveyors which dump it
over the sides.
T^TUCLEAR POWER AHEAD: Sweden's
-L' power resources will become 26% nu¬
clear by 1980 according to present plans.
By that time, water power at present 94%
of the country's power supply will have
dropped to 65%.
FREEDOM-FROM-HUNGER WEEK:
Well over 100 member states of the Uni¬
ted Nations or its Specialized agencies will
issue special stamps during World-Freedom-
from-Hunger Week (the last week of
March). The stamps are being issued in
support of the World Freedom from Hun¬
ger Campaign launched by the U.N. Food
and Agriculture Organization. As they
appear they will be put on sale by the
Unesco Philatelic Service (see box on this
page).
Flashes.. i
B An international océanographie research
operation to determine potential fishery
resources in the tropical Atlantic has now
begun. Vessels from Argentina, Brazil,
the Congo (Brazzaville), Ivory Coast, Nige¬
ria, the U.S.S.R. and the U.S.A. are due to
take part.
In the past ten years the population of
Hong Kong has shot up from one million to
three and a half. To help feed this booming
population, Hong Kong's acreage of fish
ponds has been doubled. Value of fish
produced annually is now over H.K. $5
million.
B The problem of paying for education was
recently defined in these terms: "To give
each child, eight years of primary education
in the following countries, would cost, at
current prices, about 0.80% of the national
income in the U.S.A., 1.7% in Jamaica,
2.8% in Ghana and 4% in Nigeria.
B Forty-five countries have now joined or
ratified the Unesco-sponsored Universal
Copyright Convention under which states
grant foreign works the same protection as
those of their own nationals. Norway and
Finland are the latest countries to ratify
the Convention.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
JUST PUBLISHED
VACATIONS ABROAD
unesco
STUDY
ABROAD
VOLUME XIV 1963
Its 740 pages give full details on
130,000 opportunities for study
and travel abroad in 1963 and
1964, offered in 116 countries
Price : 1 5/- (stg) ;
$3.00; 10.50 F. F.
Gives full informa¬
tion to help you to
make stimulating
use of your vaca¬
tions
SUMMER
COURSES
STUDY TOURS
WORK CAMPS
186 pages
6/-(stg.)
U.S.S1.75
4.50 F.F.
Vol. XV 7963
VacationsAbroad
Vacances à l'étranger
Vacaciones enel
extranjero
XV 1863
UlieSCO Work Camp*
Cour* etvtA'Wjct1* dï-tuci-f*
chftntiera iiiu'rnírtioninrx
Cursof-^viaje* de iftudio,
efunpo-j inttTnlfcinnal«-» d.
t rnlw-.i" valtm-Uü-io
Where to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; rates quoted are
for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO COU¬
RIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Press Department, Royal
Afghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Melbourne University Press, 369 Lonsdale Street,
Melbourne, C. I., Victoria. (A. 1 5/-). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C°., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Sch. 60.-). BELGIUM. Editions " Labor ",
342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-Boek-
handel, Belgiëlei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (100 FB) and art slides only: Louis de Lannoy,
22, place de Brouckère, Brussels. CCP 3 3 80.00.
BURMA. Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road,
Rangoon. (K. 5.50). CANADA. Queen's Printer,
Ottawa, Ont. ($ 3.00). CEYLON. The Associated
Newspapers of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Colombo, 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99 Chungking South
Rd., Section 1, Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa). CUBA.
Librería Económica, Pee Zayas 505-7, Apartado 113,
Havana. (2.25 pesos). CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia
Ltd., 30 Ve Smeckách, Prague 2. DENMARK. Ejnar
Munksgaard, A/S Tidsskriftafdelingen, Prags Boulevard 47
Copenhagen S (D.kr. 12). ETHIOPIA. International
Press Agency. P.O. Box 120. Addis Ababa. FINLAND.
Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
(Fmk. 540). FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, Place
de Fontenoy, Paris-7'. CCP. 12598-48. (7 F.).
. GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg Verlag, Rosen-
sheimer Strasse 145, Munich. For the Unesco Kurier
(German ed. only) Bahren-felder-Chaussee 160,
Hamburg-Bahrenleld.CCP. 276650 (DM 8). -GHANA
Methodist Book Depot Ltd. Atlantis House, Commercial
St., POB 100, Cape Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See
United Kingdom. GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann,
28, rue du Stade, Athens. HONG-KONG. Swindon
Book Co., 64, Nathan Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY.
Kultura, P.O. Box 149. Budapest, 62. INDIA. Orient
Longmans Ltd. Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay 1; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; Gun-
foundry Road, Hyderabad, 1 ; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/1 Asaf Ali Road, P.O. Box 3 86, New
Delhi,- 1 ; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.,
17 Park Street, Calcutta 16, Scindia House, New Delhi.
Indian National Commission for Co-operation with
Unesco, Ministry of Education, New Delhi 3. (Rs. 7).
INDONESIA. P. N. Fadjar Bhakti, D|alan
Nusantara 22, Djakarta. IRAQ. Mackenzie's
Bookshop, Baghdad. IRELAND. The National Press,
2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd., 3 5, Allenby
Road and 48, Nahlat Beniamin Street, Tel-Aviv( 1 £ 5. SO).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour
Street, Kingston. Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
(10/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-Nichome,
Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605 Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
(Yen 670). JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman.
KENYA. E.S.A. Bookshop, P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole
and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LUXEMBURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue,
Luxemburg. MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications Ltd., Times House,
River Valley Rd., Singapore (M. S 500) MALTA.
Sapienza's Library 26 Kingsway, Valetta. (10/-).
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon
Street, Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid
des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (7 NF.). NETHERLANDS.
N. V. Martinus Niihoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague,
(fl. 6). NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES. G. C. T.
Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.) N.V., Willemstad, Curacao
NEW ZEALAND Government Printing Office
Wellington, and Government Bookshops, Auckland,
Wellington, Christchurch Dunedin (10/-). NIGERIA.'
C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box 174, Lagos. (10/-). NOR-
WAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille Grense. 7, Oslo
For the Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Litteratur
Tjeneste, Stortingsgt. 4, Oslo, Postboks 115 (kr 13.20
PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing Cor
Ltd., Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box 374, 56-N
Gulberg Industrial Colony, Lahore. PANAMA.
Cultural Panameña, Avenida 7a, No. TI-49, Apartado
de Correos 2018, Panama, D.F. (Balboas 3-). PHI-
LIPPINES. The Modern Book Co., 508 Rizal Avenue
Manila. POLAND. " RUCH " ul. Wiloza Nr. 46,
Warsaw 10 (Zl. 50). PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada
Lda, Livraria Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon.
RHODESIA & NYASALAND. The Book Centre, First
Street, Salisbury, Southern Rhodesia. SUDAN. Ai
Bashir Bookshop, P. O, Box 1 1 1 8, Khartoum. SWEDEN.
A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2,
Stockholm. For The Unesco Courier: Svenska Unes¬
coradet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stockholm, C (Kr. 7.50);
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse
Zurich. Payot, 40, rue du Marché, Geneva. CCP.
1-236. " Courier " only: Georges Losmaz, 1, rue des
Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CCP. 1-4811. (Fr. S. 8).
TANGANYIKA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B.
9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND. Suksapan
Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok. (35
ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda
Bookshop, P.O. Box 145, Kampala. UNION OF
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Bookstore, Libri
Building, Church Street, Pretoria. For the Unesco Cou¬
rier (single copies) only: Central News Agency, P.O.
Box 1033, Johannesburg. (10/-). UNITED ARAB
REPUBLIC (EGYPT). La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh.
Adly-Pasha, Cairo. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M.
Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I. (10/-).
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications Center,
801 Third Avenue, New York, 22, N.Y. ($ 5.00.)
and (except periodicals): Columbia University Press,
2960 Broadway, New York, 27 N.Y. U.S.S.R. Mez-
hdunarodnaja Kniga, Moscow. G-200.
Yugoslovenska Knjiga, Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
'At ^w
*v m-ii
il
77* - -: - ~S3Éf I, Ä *
Äfr^
OR SPERITY IS INDIVIS
^fe
3s*
A giant intake pipe is installed on the site of the Furnas
Hydro-Electric Development Projectthe largest of its
kind ever undertaken in Latin America. Sited on the
banks of the Rio Grande in the Brazilian state of Minas
Gerais it is being built with aid from the International
Bank for Reconstruction and Development (The World
Bank). When completed in 1965 the installation will add
a further 1,200,000 k. w. to Brazil's electrical power
resources. Forthe first time in history the peoples of the
world are beginning to share out their skills and resour¬
ces among the less fortunate nations. This is one of the
most significant developments of ourtime. (See page 27).
]]>
</page>
</document>
