<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="062906eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
s^tÉSC©
WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
MillM
APRIL 1964 (17TH YEAR) - PRICE 1/-STG. ( U.K.) - 30 CENTS (CANADA) - 0.70 F (FRANCE)
WORLD HEALTH DAY
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
î
^r* '*»--"»" w*«. :»A~
5R5fc
.< A» .
UPSIDE-DOWN WORLD
These two children are probably having the time of their lives but
many grown-ups would probably look askance at such behaviour. For an
article on a famous woman who certainly did not, see article page 16.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier APRIL 1964
17TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
Page
COVER PHOTO
Eskimo children in particular
have benefited from the health
services set up in recent years
in the Far North of Canada
(see page 12). In other Arctic
territories Alaska, Greenland,
Scandinavia and Siberia
health services are also being
expanded, and research into
health problems in these areas
is being co-ordinated by
the World Health Organization.
© Paul Almasy, Paris
11
12
14
16
21
24
26
32
33
34
TUBERCULOSIS: STILL 3 MILLION DEATHS A YEAR
World Health Day 1964
THE BATTLE OF TUNISIA
A nation declares war on tuberculosis
A MOMENTOUS LOOK INTO THE MICROSCOPE
Robert Koch's discovery of the tuberculosis bacillus
BIRTH OF A NEW VACCINE
The success story of BCG
RESURRECTION OF THE ESKIMOES
Health patrols and flying doctors in the Far North
SUPER-BACILLI : A NEW CHALLENGE TO MEDICINE
The T. B. bacillus counterattacks
VISION OF MANKIND TRANSFORMED
Maria Montessori and education for peace
By Maria Remiddi
THE SILENT MUSIC OF THE EARTH
By May Hall Thompson
PANTHEON OF GREEK GODS
THE DAY THE RIVER SPOKE
A short story from India
By Kamala Nair
STORIES IN STAMPS
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
THE UNITED NATIONS EDUCATIONAL, SCIENTIFIC AND CULTURAL ORGANIZATION
Published monthly by UNESCO
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*. France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
René Caloz
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition
Spanish Edition
' Russian Edition
German Edition
Arabic Edition :
Japanese Edition
Jane Albert Hesse
: Arturo Despouey
Victor Goliachkov
: Hans Rieben (Berne)
Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Italian Edition : Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except In |uly and August when
it is bi-monthly ( I I issues a year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German.
Arabic, Japanese, and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed hy H.M.
Stationery Office, P. O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors ol THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly In The Readers' Guide to
Periodical Literature published by H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates : I 0/-stg. ; $3.00 (Canada) ; 7.00
French Francs or equivalent. Single copies l/-stg. 30
cents ; 0.70 F.
(M.C. 64.1.. 190 A)
N- 4. 1964
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
TUBERCULOSIS
Still 3 million
deaths a year
"At least 15 million people suffer from infectious
tuberculosis today. The disease still claims more
than three million lives each year... in nearly all
economically-developed countries, the number of
sufferers has not declined as nearly as rapidly as
the number of deaths, and tuberculosis remains a
grave problem. In the world as a whole, between
two and three million new cases occur each year..."
These warning words by Dr. M.G. Candau, Director-
General of the World Health Organization, explain
why the theme chosen for World Health Day 1964
(April 7) is "No Truce for Tuberculosis". On the
following pages The Unesco Courier retraces
the long history of tuberculosis and the efforts
to find curative and preventative medicines. Also
described are the powerful new drugs and infection
control methods which can be used to defeat tuber¬
culosis and eliminate it as a public health problem.
Because, as Dr. Candau has also pointed out, "for
the first time in man's history we now possess
effective weapons with which to fight tuberculosis."
Five years ago Tunisian doctors met in the
Public Health Office, one of the government
ministries in the Kasbah at Tunis (right) to plan
a war on tuberculosis. As a prologue to this
national campaign, a pilot experiment into
the use of drugs for preventative treatment
was carried out jointly by the Tunisian Govern¬
ment and WHO. The test zone was the Djebel
Lahmar (below) a community of 25,000
people whose homes are one-storey mud
dwellings grouped on the outskirts of Tunis.
>
M )H " 1
1 1 HI '
- * "I
Mil
Photos © Paul Almasy. Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
THE BATTLE OF TUNISIA
I n Tunis, one morning In January 1959 an all-
I out war was declared on tuberculosis. It all
started when the authorities of the small town of Ksar
Ellal, near Sousse, found that the number of sick was
increasing daily among the 10,000 inhabitants of the com¬
mune, most of whom were weavers.
An SOS went out by letter and telegram to the Govern¬
ment Public Health Office. A health team was sent
to investigate.
When the X-ray vans arrived in Ksar Ellal they were
besieged. In record time 5,000 people were examined.
The results were alarming: a tuberculosis prevalence of
8%, or more than ten times present-day figures in Europe.
In some of the weavers' families at Ksar Ellal, tubercu¬
losis had existed for generations. Not through heredity,
of course, but simply because it was inevitable in such
overcrowded living conditions and dusty working en¬
vironment that sick parents should pass the disease on
to healthy children in their daily contacts. And if tuber
culosis prevalence was 8% at Ksar Ellal, what, the Health
Office wondered, would it be elsewhere?
With the aid of technical advisers from WHO, it was
decided to launch a nation-wide campaign against tuber¬
culosis. The Government offered completely free treat¬
ment to all tuberculosis sufferers, and earmarked a special
budget of 95,000 dinars (£80,000) for the campaign. The
Governorate of Sousse (460,000 people) was chosen as the
starting place because it had the next largest population
to Tunis itself.
Wherever they went, the teams worked according to
three basic principles: case-finding, supervised treatment,
and protection through BCG vaccination. Lorries laden
with X-ray equipment set out along the dusty roads,
while the organizers scoured the countryside in small cars.
The teams were warmly welcomed everywhere. In the
Governorate of Sousse alone, almost 95% of the popula-
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
TUBERCULOSIS (Cont'd)
Tunisia's health authorities began their anti-tuberculosis campaign in the province of Sousse
most heavily populated area after Tunis itself. The campaign will move south to^ cover
areas around Kairoun and Gafsa, near where this photo was taken during the annual "sheep
festival " in April. Here, villagers watch local rider performing a traditional mounted "fantasia".
Passport to health
tlon turned out. There was no need for posters. But to
ensure full coverage, it was decided to carry out a census
by family. This took up precious time, but only when it
was completed could the real work begin. Once the
administrative controls had been carried out, the pace
quickened.
Here, as throughout this hard-fought campaign, vacci¬
nators and caseflnders worked side by side. Radiological
examinations for everyone over five years of age. Next,
please! A tuberculin test was administered to all the
under- twenties. Next, please! Those who had been
given the test came back three days later BCG vaccina¬
tion for the negative reactors. For all suspects there were
medical examinations followed by INH (isoniazid)
treatment for the mild cases, and hospital for the more
serious ones. When everyone had been examined in the
village or district, the diagnostic teams packed up and
went off to start the same work elsewhere, returning
three months later to check up on the sick.
The work went on without a break; the teams relayed
each other from sunrise to sunset. All sorts of problems
arose. Some were relatively simple like the transport of
equipment . and its maintenance. Hermetically sealed
thermos containers of wood, cork, and zinc were rigged
up on the spot to protect tuberculin and BCG which
quickly deteriorate under the blazing sun. Trained
technicians were needed to maintain and repair the 11 X-
ray microphotography machines and the generators.
A radiological engineer sent by WHO to co-ordinate this
work has already trained 13 Tunisian operators. Others
now being trained will shortly form the nucleus of a
central technical service being set up by the Tunisian
Government.
To carry out their ambitious programme, the Tunisian
teams have had to adapt themselves to the most unexpected
situations. In Moknine and Kalas Kebira towns deeply
attached to religious traditions radiophotography had to
be carried out at night, sometimes until two in the morn¬
ing, because women were not permitted out of doors
before sunset. During Ramadan, worried heads of
families were afraid that the tuberculin-test injection
might break the fast, and the religious authorities had to
be brought in to convince them that it is permissible.
Elsewhere, the census ran up against other unforeseen
difficulties. At Gabes, with its 400,000 palm trees, the
oasis encircles the town in a vast pincer-movement. There
it was found that four sheikdoms overlapped. After end¬
less working sessions the exact boundaries were defined,
thus permitting a census of the inhabitants, which was
carried out street by street in the town, and hut by hut in
the oasis. The absence of surnames did not make matters
any easier when making sure that everyone, without
exception, was called for examination, but that no one
was called twice.
But problems of case-finding were nothing compared to
those of treatment. One difficulty has been the distances
to be covered. The assistants sanitaires ("health assis¬
tants") travel by car from sheikdom to sheikdom,
distributing INH tablets, checking the progress of treat¬
ment, encouraging those who seem to be faltering.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Health workers measure mothers and
children (right) and take identity
photos (below) for records and the
eventual issue of a family health card.
The operation was carried out jointly
by the Tunisian Health Ministry and
UNICEF. Since 1959, BCG vacci¬
nation against tuberculosis has been
compulsory for all Tunisians under 20,
and children are not allowed in school
unless they have been vaccinated.
Photos © Paul Almasy. Paris
At regular intervals the population Is asked to gather at
control centres. The crowd thronging round the doors is
sometimes too large to handle easily. At first there may
be about 400 people waiting, but soon these may increase
to 600, 700, or even 1,000. Then the health team has to
organize and process them as best it can.
To conquer tuberculosis in Tunisia also means to build
new houses. Parents, children, uncles, aunts, and grand¬
parents are frequently crowded into a living-space of 15
square metres. Even then the palm-covered huts of the
farm labourers at the Gabes oasis are certainly preferable
to thé caves of Old Matmatta, 15 km to the south. Here
the steppe country is broken up into fantastic canyons;
the soil grows progressively stonier and the water scarcer.
But the people who are living In holes in the mountain
will soon be evacuated. They will be resettled some
15,000 or 20,000 of themIn the town of New Matmatta,
which has been specially built for them near a dam In the
plain, 10 km away. New Matmatta has something even
better than new houses a fountain with running water all
day long. Here water is vital. When you turn your back
on Gabes, the desert is quite near, just at the end of the
road, its presence indicated by the spectacular sunsets.
The campaign organizers are constantly haunted by
this problem: how can someone who earns a bare living
be ' expected to go to hospital when it means leaving his
family in even more tragic poverty ? If he Is a farm
labourer he may earn 6 dinars a month, plus 2 kilos of
semolina 6 dinars a month when a loaf costs 50 mllllmes,
a kilo of fish 400 mllllmes, and meat is 600 or 700 mllllmes
a kilo (about one-tenth of his monthly Income).
An effort Is being made to solve this problem. Special
committees have been formed to co-ordinate the work and
share out the resources. All the needy are aided, all
patients with active tuberculosis who earn less than 180
dinars (£150) a year receive a monthly ration of flour,
corn, maize, millet, powdered mille, beans, and cheese a
total of 16 kilos per patient per month, plus 8 kilos for
each dependent child.
Thus, between July and September 1963, 336 tons of food
were distributed to tuberculosis patients and their chil¬
dren. Today these food supplies serve as an Incentive for
the patients, for if it Is found that they are not following
the prescribed treatment regularly, the extra rations are
cut off.
Short-term hospitalization can have a dual effect. The
patient Is encouraged in healthy habits and he gains In
self-respect. He undergoes a sort of transformation. He
will also have become accustomed to taking his INH
tablets at a set time. For these patients the hospital Is
a kind of school. The normal period of hospitalization
is two months, but with difficult cases It is extended, the
date of discharge being postponed as long as possible.
Tunisia is the only North African country without a
sanatorium. As for the hospitals, the Tunisians have
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
TUBERCULOSIS (Cont'd)
Door-to-door
medical check-up
made an enormous effort, providing 1,500 new beds at
1,000 dinars a bed over the last 15 years. As a result, the
country's hospitals now have some 2,300 beds reserved for
these patients.
The first Tunisian medical faculty has just opened its
doors. It Is anticipated that it will be able to admit 70
students a year, most of them on State scholarships. That
there is an urgent need for trained personnel is confirmed
by the results of the anti-tuberculosis campaign in the
Sousse Governorate.
At the time of the census, there was a population of
460,395. Of these, 419,661 were examined, and 341,630 X-
rayed. The number of cases detected was 22,812, includ¬
ing 10,700 active cases (this means a tuberculosis preva¬
lence of 2.6 per cent.). Of these cases 8,800 have now
been "stabilized" or cured. But how many new cases
have occurred since? How many will occur In future and
need treatment?
A pilot experiment directed by a joint WHO Tunisian
Government commission preceded the antituberculosis
campaign. Its object was to study the use of drugs to
protect currently healthy persons from tuberculosis. The
test zone was the Djebel Lahmar, a community on the
outskirts of Tunis. Here some 25,000 people live in one-
storey mud dwellings, usually with five or six rooms group¬
ed round a courtyard, and one family to each room. The
windows are small, ventilation is poor, and sanitary
facilities are rudimentary.
he Inhabitants are nevertheless concerned
about their health, and responded willingly
when the Sheik asked all of them, except the under-twos
and those already vaccinated with BCG, to take part In
this study of the prophylactic value of INH.
The procedure was the same as in the antituberculosis
campaign. A house-to-house census was carried out. As
there was no civil registration, serial numbers were paint¬
ed on the walls.. Then the population (24,505 persons,
according to the census) was divided into two groups.
Those in the first group were given INH tablets, while
those in the second group served as controls. (Naturally
actual tuberculosis sufferers in both groups were given
curative treatment.)
The people were required to take the INH tablets
regularly for one year. All were supervised at regular
Intervals by health assistants. However, in a surprise
check-up, it was found that four-fifths of those examined
had not taken their medicine on that particular day.
To improve the supervision of non-hospitalized patients,
the medical assistants are now carrying out more of
these surprise check-ups, visiting a number of houses each
day. It may thus be possible to prevent patients from
stopping the treatment because they cannot be bothered
to make the effort. Both Tunisian experts and WHO
advisers consider that the main hope lies in continuity
of action. After the campaign in Sousse, it will be the
turn of Kairouan, and Gabes. But a campaign is a
transitory thing and some provision must be made for
the years to come.
There is another way the protection of the young.
This has Government support: a law passed in 1959 made
BCG vaccination compulsory for everyone under 20 with
a negative tuberculin test, and its application in progress¬
ing with the development of the campaign. Mothers now
know that they cannot send their children to school unless
their Family Health Card shows that they have been
vaccinated. Soon, throughout Tunisia, this little docu¬
ment will be a veritable "passport to health."
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Radio Times. Hufton Picture
ROBERT KOCH'S
GREAT DISCOVERY
In 1882, the German scientist, Robert Koch,
succeeded in identifying for the first time
the agent of tuberculosis : a slender rod be¬
tween three and four thousandths of a milli¬
metre in length. Then Koch succeeded in
producing cultures of the bacillus and in
transmitting tuberculosis to animals. He
demonstrated conclusively that the bacillus
was the specific organism of tuberculosis,
Koch later identified the comma bacillus
that is responsible for cholera. In 1905 he
was awarded the Nobel prize for medicine.
Left, a London slum, as the well-
known artist, Gustav Doré, de¬
picted it in 1874. Tuberculosis
raged everywhere in 19th-cen¬
tury Europe. Towns became
overcrowded and slums prolife¬
rated as people poured into the
first industrial cities. At the
beginning of the 19th century
one death in four was due to
tuberculosis. Tuberculosis was not
a new disease; it had been well
known in the ancient world, but
probably reached its worst period
in Europe during the 18th century.
March 24, 1882
A MOMENTOUS LOOK
INTO THE MICROSCOPE
uberculosis was known and studied by the physicians of
the ancient world. Four thousand years ago the famous
Code of Hammurabbl, King of Babylonia, mentions "the wasting
disease." An Egyptian papyrus written in 1,600 B.C. gives the first
description of chest diseases. Excavations in one area of Egypt have
unearthed so many bodies with tuberculous lesions that some special¬
ists believe it was the site of a large sanatorium.
The disease, In fact, goes back much further still, as we may Judge
by the skeleton of a young man found In a neolithic burial ground
near Heidelberg: Its fourth and fifth dorsal vertebrae were fused
together showing that tuberculosis of the spine was already afflicting
prehistoric man some 6,000 years ago.
Tuberculosis was described clinically by Hippocrates, "the father
of medicine" (about 460-370 B.C.), who called It "phthisis" (from a
Greek verb meaning "to dry up"), and it was known either by this
name or as "consumption," until the 19th century.
Remedies for the disease were described by Galen (about 130-200
A.D.), another famous name in ancient medicine. Avlcenna (930-
1034), "prince of physicians" and author of "The Canon of Medi¬
cine," considered that the disease evolved in three stages, and
another doctor, Ferrari of Pavla, wrote a "Treatise on Phthisis."
The painter Botticelli lost his favourite model, Slmonetta Catarina
Vespucci, a beautiful Florentine, carried off by phthisis at the age of
16. He made a tender portrayal of her hollow cheeks, frail neck and
sloping shoulders.
The typical Romantic of the 19th century was emaciated, had
flushed cheeks, and died spitting blood at the age of 30. This was
the period when George Sand and the consumptive Chopin fled from
Majorca, and a Barcelona hotel-keeper demanded compensation for
the musician's bed after the police had ordered it to be burnt. The
disease inspired Byron, who declared that he would like to be carried
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
TUBERCULOSIS (Cont'd)
Two allies:
poverty and war
10
off by a consumption so that all the ladles would say how interesting
he looked while dying.
Edgar Allan Poe was haunted by the memory of his wife, Virginia,
who died of consumption at the age of 24. Dumas wrote in his
memoirs that "everyone was consumptive and especially the poets
it was good form to spit blood from sheer emotion." Marie Bashkirt-
seff, the famous nineteenth century painter, noted: "... I never stop
coughing, but miraculously it does not make me ugly on the
contrary, It gives me a languid air that is most becoming."
Tuberculosis as the disease was beginning to be called raged
everywhere In 19th century Europe. Towns became overcrowded and
slums proliferated as people poured Into the first industrial cities.
Children of 13 did the work of adults. Towards the middle of the
century, the death-rate from the disease was as high as 500 per
100,000 in some places. Tuberculosis had become a social disease.
It was to remain one as long as there was no improvement in econo¬
mic and social conditions, declining only when the social benefits of
industrialization and technical progress ultimately began to be felt.
In times of war, however, tuberculosis found allies in stress, mal¬
nutrition, and poor housing conditions and at once renewed its
attacks.
FTER 270 unsuccessful attempts, a German scientist called
i Robert Koch succeeded In identifying the agent of tuber¬
culosis: a slender rod between three-and four-thousandths of a milli¬
metre in length.
When he discovered the bacillus that bears his name, Robert Koch
was 39 years old.
Koch began to be interested in bacteria when a country doctor in
Silesia, but did not remain in the provinces for long once his brilliant
researches on the anthrax bacillus had brought him to the notice of
his contemporaries, the scientists Cohn and Cohnheim.
"Koch will again astonish us with his discoveries," one of them
predicted. And both his sponsors used their influence to secure him
a post with the Imperial Health Office in Berlin. Koch brought with
him the microscope his wife had given him for his 28th birthday.
Day after day he sought the best medium for the culture of
microbes, and perfected the techniques for studying them. He showed
the same persistence in his attempts to isolate the bacillus of tuber¬
culosis, which was then the most widespread disease in the western
world.
He spent most of his time shut up in his laboratory at the Charity
Hospital, Berlin. The door was closed to everybody except his co¬
workers and his wife. His only other companions were the. guinea-
pigs, rabbits, and mice needed for his experiments.
He finally succeeded in isolating the bacillus, a micro-organism
that was not only hard to cultivate, but hard to see. It was particu¬
larly difficult to stain, since the colouring matter had to be left to
act for a period of 12-24 hours. He therefore borrowed a technique
from the dyers, that of using alkali with the dye. Added to methy¬
lene blue, the alkali acted as a mordant enabling the dye to penetrate
the bacillus.
At last the great day came. On March 24 1882, in a crowded room
at the headquarters of the Berlin Phthisiological Society, the young
man with the pointed beard addressed some 80 fellow-scientists.
Robert Koch explained his discovery in a matter-of-fact way, as if
he were presenting some routine paper. He told them all about the
culture technique, the bacillus, and the characteristics of the lesions.
Microscopes stood waiting on the desk in front of him. One by one
the audience came up, peered into them, and saw the slender rods
for themselves. There was a dead silence. Not a single voice was
raised in opposition to Koch's findings. From that moment everyone
knew that the origin and propagation of tuberculosis were no longer
a mystery. It was not a hereditary, but a communicable, disease.
Soon after the First
World War, two French
scientists, Albert Cal-
mette and Camille Gué-
rin, gave the world the
first effective weapon
against tuberculosis :
BCG vaccine (Bacillus
Calmette-Guérin). To¬
day, hundreds of mil¬
lions of doses of BCG
have been administered
throughout the world.
Right, Camille Guérin
at the Institut Pasteur,
Paris in 1960, a year
before his death. Photo
in the background is of
Calmette (1863-1933).
WHO. René Caloz
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
wo French scientists, Albert Calmette and
Camille Guérin, gave the world the first
effective weapon against tuberculosis.
Léon-Charles-Albert Calmette, was a former naval
doctor who took up research on bacteriology, first becoming
Director of the Pasteur Institute at Lille, then Sub-
Director of the main Pasteur Institute at Paris. With his
closest collaborator, the veterinarian Camille Guérin, he
had published a "Contribution to the study of the
vaccination of bovids against tuberculosis" shortly before
the First World War.
In it the two scientists described how they had cultivat¬
ed the tubercle bacillus on potato boiled in glycerlnated
beef bile, using a virulent strain of bovine origin. After
about three weeks the bacillus was found to have lost
some of its virulence. But it was not until years later,
after the operation had been repeated more than 200
times, that Calmette and Guerin succeeded in evolving
a new kind of bacillus, harmless, yet capable of conferring
a state of immunity when administered by vaccination.
Animals inoculated with this bile-cultivated vaccine
proved resistant- to tuberculous infection.
Shortly after the end of the Second World War, Cal¬
mette felt that the time had come to test the effects of
this vaccine in man.
On July 1 1921, in a Parisian apartment, a baby received
three 6-milligram doses of Bacillus Calmette-Guérin
(BCG), administered orally. Since both the child's
mother and the grandmother who was bringing him up
were suffering from tuberculosis, there was a good chance
that he would become Infected. Yet six months later he
was developing normally and healthily.
Then the vaccine was tried out on a larger scale: 664
babies in the crèche run Dr Weill Hallé, paediatrician at
the Paris Hospital of Charity, were vaccinated without
any ill effects.
Henceforth Calmette was considered as the leading
authority on tuberculosis. He published a paper In the
Journal de l'Académie de Médecine, entitled "Trial of a
vaccine against tuberculosis Infection" in which he
summed up 20 years' work in a few pages. The vaccine
began to be widely used. The Pasteur Institute was
authorized to send ampoules of BCG abroad, and vaccina¬
tion were carried out In Barcelona, Montevideo and Rio
de Janeiro; in Argentina, Cuba, and Poland; in Dakar,
Saigon and Sao Paulo; and in the Balkans.
Nevertheless, there were some dissenting voices. At the
Trudeau Sanatorium, Saranac, N. Y., Dr Petrolf asserted
that the vaccine had retained pathogenic qualities. In
Switzerland, some authorities pronounced it dangerous.
In Vienna, Dr Kraus, Director of the Institute of Sero¬
therapy, forbade the use of BCG In Austria. Even in
France, Calmette was attacked.
Nevertheless he went on organizing demonstrations and
controlled experiments, and succeeded in turning the tide
of opposition. He submitted his case to an International
jury of experts, convened by the League of Nations, which
concluded that BCG was indeed effective. \\
CONT'D ON PAGE 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
RESURRECTION OF THE ESKIMOES
\A/HEN the Eskimoes lived alone in the Far North they
** hardly knew what illness was. But from their first
contact with civilization they harvested tuberculosis, then
syphilis and later poliomyelitis. Sixty years ago, the Eskimoes
were a disappearing race. Today, the trend has been re¬
versed. The Eskimoes seen in these photos, who live in
the Far North of Canada, have increased from 7,000 to over
12,000 in the past 15 years. .One reason is the health net¬
work dispensaries, airborne doctors and air ambulances,
andpreventative services, including tuberculosis case-finding
now woven over great reaches of the Eskimo country.
CHILDREN OF THE ESKIMOES (above
and below) were the first to benefit
from new health services in the Cana¬
dian Far North. To maintain these
services for a widely scattered popu¬
lation of about 12,000 Eskimoes costs
an average of $2,000 per head annually.
National Film Board of Canada
12 ONLY ONE CHILD IN TWO used to survive the first
year of life. Now, thanks to better health practices
and emergency aid, four children out of five survive.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
TUBERCULOSIS (Cont'd)
FLYING AMBULANCE lands near a lonely
dwelling in Canada's north to pick up an
emergency case requiring surgical treat¬
ment. Emergency calls arising from
accidents and illnesses are answered
all the year round and in all weathers.
Photos WHO- Paul Almasy
Victory over calumny
and suspicion
Suddenly there was a tragic development. Out of 252
children in Lübeck, Germany, who had been vaccinated
with BCG between December 1929 and April 1930, 71 died
and 27 fell ill, five of them dangerously so, the cause being
a serious tuberculosis infection.
Protests flowed Into the Pasteur Institute from all sides.
An Inquiry was held, and revealed that Calmettc's work
was not at fault. The Institute Issued a statement:
"Either the BCG culture was accidentally Infected by a
virulent tuberculosis germ from other cultures In the lab¬
oratory at Lübeck, or else, through carelessness, llasks
or tubes containing virulent tubercle bacilli were unfor¬
tunately placed In the same drying-cupboard as the BCG
cultures and substituted for them In the preparation of
the first vaccine emulsions in January 1930.
" The idea that BCG could suddenly have become
virulent after being administered to the children Is unten¬
able. There Is therefore no doubt that the children In
Lübeck received a virulent tuberculosis culture Instead of,
or mixed with, BCG."
A lawsuit was started. Then German bacteriologists
revealed that the conditions In which the BCG strain
had been kept in the laboratory were unsatisfactory.
A serious mistake had been made. In a culture that had
been used In the preparation of the vaccine, BCG was
found mixed with virulent bacilli from a strain forwarded
to Lübeck by a laboratory In Kiel. It was proved that
the tragedy had been caused by a blunder at the Lübeck
laboratory. The doctor responsible was sentenced to two
years' imprisonment, and Calmette and his Institute were
exonerated.
A million small children In all parts of the world
had already been vaccinated with BCG. But,
as if to exemplify the old saying "If you Hing enough mud,
some of it is bound to stick," BCG was to be viewed with
suspicion for a long time to come.
Today its value Is no longer In question. Full recogni¬
tion finally came In 1948, when 300 delegates from all
parts of the world took part In the First International
BCG Congress. BCG vaccination Is now compulsory in
several countries, including France and the U.S.S.R. The
vaccine Is manufactured by more than 50 laboratories In
different parts of the world, from strains supplied by the
Pasteur Institute.
By June 1924, Calmette and Guérin had vaccinated 217
children. Today several hundred million doses of BCG
have been administered, 150 million of them in campaigns
undertaken by WHO and UNICEF In more than 60
countries.
Further Indisputable proof of the value of BCG was
obtained in a recent intensive trial of the vaccine among
35,000 young people living In highly industrialized
communities in Great Britain. There were 80 per cent
less cases In those who had received BCG than in those
who had not, and this reduction has by now been main¬
tained for more than eight years after vaccination. It
has often been argued that the unfavourable sociological
and economic conditions and the high exposure to Infec¬
tion found in developing countries would lower the value
of BCG. A controlled study in India, supported by WHO,
has however recently revealed the same degree of protec¬
tion as that found in the British trial.
Being economical and easy to apply, BCG vaccination
couldIf used systematically and continuously over the
next few decades bring about the elimination of tuber¬
culosis as a public health problem in any developing
country.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
TUBERCULOSIS (Cont'd)
'SUPER-BACILLI'
A NEW CHALLENGE TO MEDICINE
|ne difficulty in large-scale campaigns against
tuberculosis using modern drugs in the
appearance of tubercle bacilli that are "resistant" to their
action. But, as the International Union against Tuber¬
culosis declared recently: "We hear a great deal about
the resistance of the bacillus. But not enough is said
about another form of resistance: that coming from Igno¬
rance, apathy, and lack of interestin a phrase: the
resistance of Man." Immunization, diagnosis and treat¬
ment offered on a community-wide scale are nothing but
empty gestures if the public is not willing to make full
use of these services. There is need for active and
continuing co-operation of both the individual and the
community.
Doctor and patient have often different points of view.
The doctor wants to "follow up" his patient, while the
patient tries to keep away from his doctor. Both in the
sanatorium and at home, the patient is far from being
always co-operative. Despite the serious nature of his
illness, there all too often comes a time when he revolts
against the tiresome routine of taking his daily quota of
drugs.
Even sanatorium patients have been known to throw
their pills out of the window. They want to believe that
there is no need for further treatment, to think that they
are already cured; the truth is that the course of the
disease Is merely interrupted. They have only one idea
in mind: to leave the sanatorium and get home as soon
as possible, regain their freedom and resume their normal
activities.
When this human weakness is a real problem even
under strict hospital routine, then It Is not surprising that
the discipline of the home-patient, who has to take the
drugs dally on his own initiative, easily breaks down.
H uman resistance to the discipline of taking
potent drugs regularly for a long period means
that the tubercle bacillus is subjected to only a half¬
hearted attack and this gives it the time to mobilize a
drug-resistant population. Once this has happened there
is no reprieve: the bacillus that has been "immunized"
through the patient's negligence produces other bacilli
just as impervious to the effect of the drugs to which
it is resistant.
Doctors have the greatest difficulty in dealing with
these "super-bacilli," which respond only to a few costly
drugs that may be dangerous and must therefore be
administered under close hospital supervision. To provide
such special treatment on a large scale would place an
Intolerable burden on the strained economies of most
of the developing countries.
The consequences of defaulting from treatment are
extremely serious: not only does the patient get worse,
but he may succeed in spreading drug-resistant bacilli to
healthy Individuals who, in turn, become untreatable by
the normal methods.
Perhaps the only way of dealing with the "resistant"
patient is, after all, to supervise him and make sure that
he takes the medicine at his home or at the health centre.
If drug treatment could be given Intermittently, say once
a week, instead of daily, medication could be supervised
even in developing countries. The Madras Chemotherapy
Centre has been investigating this possibility: twice-
weekly ambulatory treatment with isoniazid and strepto¬
mycin gave the same spectacular results as daily
administration of isoniazid and PAS: more than 90 per
14 cent, of advanced cases cured. Stimulated by these
unexpected and encouraging findings, the Centre has
begun to study the feasibility of a once-weekly regimen.
Applicability on a mass scale, economy, convenience,
and reduced toxicity: these are the truly impressive array
of advantages offered by the latest possibilities in the
treatment of a disease that has plagued mankind since
the beginning of history.
Tuberculosis is an international health problem and
must be solved on a world-wide basis. Although varying
enormously from the large underprivileged areas of the
world to the highly industrialized countries, the tubercu¬
losis situation is of serious concern to all.
tvEN those few countries which are gradually
eliminating the problem within their own
frontiers cannot hope to be safe as long as tuberculosis
is rampant elsewhere. The increasing rapidity and
volume of international transport, the migration of
workers across national boundaries tend to intensify the
risk of infection. Another cause for worry is that as
tuberculosis becomes less frequent in a country the
natural resistance of the population may be expected
gradually to diminish, and this at a time when the anti¬
tuberculosis services are likely to relax their vigilance.
Tuberculosis must be conquered everywhere.
Since it came into being in 1948 the World Health
Organization (WHO) has assisted national governments
in bringing tuberculosis under control by providing expert
advice and teams of specialized personnel.
Under its guidance, mass vaccination with BCG, the
first weapon against tuberculosis, has been extended to
most parts of the world. However, the very first large-
scale vaccination campaigns were launched by the "Inter¬
national Tuberculosis Campaign" which was set up after
World War II by the Scandinavian countries to aid
nations which had been most seriously ravaged by the
disease.
More recently, when effective antituberculosis drugs
became available, the rational use of this powerful weapon
in the many countries where hospital facilities are limited
or non-existent was investigated through special projects.
It is clear that none of the weapons against tuberculosis
can be used in exactly the same way in every country.
Conditions and resources differ and different strategies
have therefore to be developed. To meet this need
WHO has co-operated in pilot projects for tuberculosis
control in numerous countries.
I n all of these activities the United Nations
Children's Fund (UNICEF) has been a partner
of WHO. With the joint assistance of WHO and UNICEF
more than 150 million people have been vaccinated in
campaigns in 61 countries, tuberculosis control training
centres have been set up in many parts of the world and
more recently pilot projects in tuberculosis control for
about a third of the world's population have been started.
Another important partner in the world-wide fight
against tuberculosis is the International Union against
Tuberculosis (IUT). A frequent obstacle to the efforts
made by governments to control tuberculosis is a lack
of sustained co-operation by individuals and by commu¬
nities. It is here that the IUT and its constituent
voluntary tuberculosis associations can play a decisive
part: what governments cannot do national, regional and
local associations often can. The Mutual Assistance
Programme of the IUT has been designed specifically to
supplement the governments' efforts by mobilizing and
maintaining nation-wide support.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
WHO. Spooner
MASKED & GOWNED
AGAINST INFECTION
Stringent precautions against infection are taken in this tuberculosis section of a research
laboratory. Staff work in gowns and masks and all items of equipment are coloured
red to avoid possible confusion with material from other research sections. Research
leading to discovery of drugs with direct action against the tuberculosis bacillus strep¬
tomycin, p-aminosalicylic acid and isoniazid has sharply reduced mortality rates.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
María Montessori
A VISION OF MANKIND
TRANSFORMED
by Maria Remiddi
II n 1947, two years after the end of the Second
World War, great interest was awakened in
Rome by the announcement that Maria Montessori was
to give a talk there on "Education and Peace." For
although Maria Montessori had studied in Rome (she held
degrees In medicine, biology, philosophy and education)
and her first research into the psychological development
of small children had been carried out there, she had
pursued the rest of her career in foreign countries, open¬
ing schools in England, the United States of America,
Spain, Denmark, India and the Netherlands. At last she
was coming back to Rome, a dignified old lady dressed in
black, with a halo of white hair. She had a very quiet
voice and spoke so simply that no one could fail to follow
her arguments.
She said there was no need to unite the world, for it
was united already. In order to develop a peaceable
disposition in young children, we must give them their
place in this new united, unified world where everyone
works for the benefit of his neighbour. For in the world
of today nothing comes to us direct from nature in the
old, simple way; men must work to bring it to us.
She pointed out that this applied not only to houses,
tables, chairs, books, but that even a fruit, which seems
the most direct and genuine of nature's gifts, comes to us
only because men have tended the tree it grew upon,
plucked it and brought it to market.
She went on to say that nothing was easier than to
make little children aware of the human kindness which
is constantly being expressed in work, for every child
meets with such kindness in everyday life. Unconscious
kindness, perhaps, but kindness all the same. It helps
people a great deal if they realize they have this kindness
within them.
Maria Montessori never wrote out her lectures or lessons,
16
Maria Montessori gave
her entire life to education.
She worked tirelessly to
develop teaching methods
and materials that have
since been incorporated
into many current educa¬
tional systems. Left,
towards the end of her
life, the distinguished Ita¬
lian educator greets an
Indian teacher at a Mon¬
tessori Congress. Right,
freedom of expression, as
displayed here by a young
classroom artist from
Czechoslovakia, is one
of the main principles
of the Montessori method.
Publifoto, Rome
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
(Q Jan Lukas. Pragus
and spoke without notes. When I went to ask her if
I might have a copy of what she had said, she looked
surprised and told me she had not got one. So I hurried
home and wrote down everything I could remember. She
read my notes afterwards and agreed that they were her
words.
Even so, they gave only a pale reflection of her ideas.
She had begun to take an interest in young children in
the early years of this century, when she was working at
the psychiatric clinic of the University of Rome and had
been instructed to study the behaviour of a group of
feeble-minded children.
S¡-he had already received a thorough scientific
'training for this type of research from Giu¬
seppe Sergi, the anthropologist, who had founded the first
Institute of Experimental Psychology at the University of
Rome; and she was also familiar with the work of Pro¬
fessor Cesare Lombroso, the celebrated authority on
criminal psychology. On completing her studies she
turned to research, gradually deepening her insight into
the physical and psychical substratum underlying abnor¬
mality and her understanding of the educational methods
by which behaviour could be improved.
To acquaint herself with what was being done elsewhere
In the field of remedial education, she went abroad,
spending some time in England and then in France. In
the latter country the investigations carried out by Itard
and Séguin interested her particularly. J.E. Marie Gaspard
Itard (1774-1838) was a physician who had devoted him¬
self to the education of deaf children.
After her return to Rome, Maria Montessori continued
her study of mentally defective children, improved her
methods of training, and invented the teaching materials
that bear her name a set of objects (Interlocking puzzles,
cubes, cylinders, laces, coloured Implements, figures,
letters) designed to stimulate dormant sensory perception.
Finally she opened a school to train teachers for the diffi¬
cult task of preparing feeble-minded children to play
their part in normal life.
Meanwhile, however, she had become Increasingly
absorbed by another question. "If," she asked herself,
"after all this scientific research and study of educational
methods, we can now Improve the lot of the mentally defi¬
cient child, what results should we obtain if we gave
equally close attention to normal children, on whom the
future of the human race depends?" She decided that the
methods of scientific research must now be applied to the
psychology of normal children, and that in order to obtain
reliable data the children must be in surroundings where
they could behave spontaneously and naturally.
An opportunity to put this plan Into practice occurred
when the city of Rome began to build large blocks of
low-rent flats In slum dLstricts, each provided with a Casa
dei bambini (a kind of crèche), and Maria Montessori was
asked to organize and manage these. This was in 1906.
In these nursery schools the children were given the Mon¬
tessori teaching materials to stimulate their sense of
touch, hearing and observation; and most important of
all, they had teachers who, though always on the watch,
left them free to behave just as they wished.
And to the amazement of these teachers and of Mon¬
tessori herself this led to the gradual emergence of a
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
MARIA MONTESSORI (Cont'd)
A search for
peace and
a better world
18
new type of child, who could concentrate on one occupa¬
tion for a long time, who was thoughtful, pursuing its
psychological development and building up its own per¬
sonality in this quiet and peacefully experimental atmo¬
sphere; who was placid and naturally polite a completely
unaggressive child.
Was it her discovery of the unaggressive child that led
Montessori to the conclusion that man was really Intended
for work and peace, not for battle and destruction? Or
was it her wish to guide mankind along the paths of peace
that prompted her search for the methods and surround¬
ings which would produce peaceful men? We shall never
know; but from this time on she devoted herself mainly
to the search for "the better man" who is to be found in
every child that comes Into the world.
She noted at this period that "The child's unsatisfied
demands leave their mark on the grown man in the form
of a conflict, a perpetual struggle that awaits man at birth
and continues throughout his development the conflict
between the adult and the child, between the strong and
the weak, and one might even add, between the blind and
the sighted. The adult gets the better of the child, with
the result that the grown man always carries the scars of
these battles; something has been destroyed In him, and
the price of his victory has been a painful adjustment."
And it grieved her deeply to realize that during the process
"the finest psychic qualities of the individual are lost for¬
ever."
When Maria Montessori gave her first public
lecture on the theme of education for peace
in 1932, at Nice, at a Congress of the International Bureau
of Education she was almost dismayed by her realization
of the novelty of this idea. Rather than make a frontal
attack on the subject, she therefore chose an imaginative,
persuasive approach.
She went back through history some twenty centuries
and spoke at some length on the mysteriously recurring
plague which took, over the years, a toll of millions and
millions of lives. This had continued until men of learn¬
ing, scrutinizing the invisible universe, discovered the
microbe that was responsible for the scourge, and halted
its reproductive process by drawing up certain vital rules
of hygiene and Inducing society to adopt them. As a
result, modern man is physically healthier than his
ancestors.
Having thus built up a proper basis for comparisons,
Maria Montessori carried her argument further: "War Is
like plague," she said, "and it leaves us bewildered. But
just as a new physical constitution was needed to defeat
plague, so we need a new spiritual constitution to help
us put an end to war.
"A child is required to be obedient, both at home and
at school; as this demand for obedience Is not based on
any Inner conviction, and makes no appeal to reason or
justice, it merely produces men who are submissive to
blind forces. The form of punishment, so frequent in
schools, which consists in holding up the offender to
public obloquy putting him, as it were, in the pillory
gives children a senseless, irrational fear of public opinion,
even when that opinion is manifestly unjust and mistaken.
"%r ifm
. ° --¡3 1
GEOGRAPHY IS FUN for
the younger children in this
school in Pueblos, Colorado,
U.S.A., when it can be learn¬
ed while playing games
on a giant map painted on
the school playground. Les¬
son-games on this 35-foot-
wide map of the U.S.A. are a
feature of the programme.
Unesco - Sholomovitch
USIS
CONT'D ON PAGE 20
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
NURSERY SCHOOL
HOUSEKEEPERS
Children in this Paris
nursery school learn
how to wash the baby,
a 6-lb. doll that "eats"
and sleeps. The 300
three - to - six - year - olds
in this school receive
housekeeping and child-
care lessons as part of
training for adult life.
One of the principles on
which Maria Montes¬
sori based her system of
teaching was that chil¬
dren should be shown
how to do such practical
things as sweeping,
cleaning and washing.
YOUNG SCULP¬
TORS, pondering over
their figures of men and
animals, belong to the
children's art school in
Komsomolsk on the Ri¬
ver Amur, a city founded
32 years ago and now
one of the most impor¬
tant industrial centres
of the Soviet Far East.
19
Unesco - Giselle Freund
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
MARIA MONTESSORI (Cont'd)
In the steps of Jean-Jacques Rousseau
"Adjustment to these circumstances, and to many
others of a similar nature, which help to create a per¬
manent inferiority complex, breeds and encourages a
spirit of devotion, almost of Idolatry, directed towards the
'leaders', the authorities who, for such repressed per¬
sonalities, are a reincarnation of parents and teachers
the figures the child was taught to regard as perfect and
Infallible. In this Way, discipline becomes almost a form
of slavery."
But, declared Maria Montessori, there was another way
In which schools could be regarded as the breeding-ground
of war, inasmuch as Instead of developing the child's
sociability, they discouraged it. Five years later she
stressed this point again: "Education in its present form
encourages the child's sense of isolation and his pursuit
of his own interests," she said. "Children are taught not to
help one another, not to prompt those who do not know
something, to think of nothing but their own advancement,
to aim solely at winning prizes in competition with their
companions. And these pathetic egotists, mentally wearied
as experimental psychology reveals them to be, then go
out Into the world, where they live side by side like grains
of sand In the desert every one cut off from his neigh¬
bour, and all sterile. If a gale arises, this human dust,
with no spiritual essence to give it life, will be swept away
In a death-dealing whirlwind."
The death-dealing whirlwind was just appearing on the
horizon; for this was in 1937.
At the Vlth International Montessori Congress, at
Copenhagen, the founder declared that the words
"Educate for Peace" should henceforth ring out like a
command. As she spoke there was a new note of distress
in her voice. At the opening meeting she praised Den¬
mark, "great and generous in offering hospitality to world
peace," and expressed her satisfaction that Belgium,
Catalonia, Chile, Czechoslovakia, Egypt, France, Greece,
Haiti, Latvia, Mexico, Rumania, the U.S.S.R., the Swiss
Canton of Ticino and the United States had responded
to her invitation by sending official representatives to the
Congress. She spoke of education for peace, of peaceful
children, of peace as the true destiny of mankind,
throughout that week in August, from the first meeting of
the Congress to the last.
The Second World War confirmed her belief that her
methods should be applied as widely as possible. As soon
as it was over she began again to address teachers in her
assured way, putting her ideas to them clearly and con¬
vincingly.
And so she worked on, tirelessly, to the age of 81.
It might well be asked: "What was so original about
Maria Montessorl's ideas?" She undoubtedly follows in
the great tradition of Rousseau, who declared that the
child is basically good, but is spoilt by society. But
whereas in Rousseau this belief sprang from poetical
intuition, in her it was the outcome of a precise, scientific
study of the hundreds of young children she had the
opportunity to observe.
It is true that while she was engaged in research and
experiment other investigators in different parts of the
world were working on the same lines and reaching simi¬
lar conclusions. But she alone was guided by this ardent
vision of mankind transformed ; and she alone pointed out
that nothing but an educational system which, instead of
crushing the child, fostered his psychical energies, could
produce men with the moral qualities required to control
the tremendous scientific advances they themselves had
brought about.
Unesco-Tamagawa Gakuen, Tokyo
20
AS A TEAM. Smil¬
ing group of young¬
sters from a Tokyo
school set off for a
day of outdoor acti¬
vities of the kind
advocated by Maria
Montessori as a po¬
sitive means of de¬
veloping the child's
sociability. "Edu¬
cation", she said,
"too often encou¬
rages the child's
sense of isolation
and also his pursuit
of his own interests. "
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
by May Hall Thompson
HE classical definition of sound relates the phenome¬
non exclusively to the response of a "hearing" mecha¬
nism such as the ear. As such, sound is the sensation received
through the organs of hearing from vibrations transmitted by any
vibrating area in contact with the air.
But in physics sound is generally taken to relate to alternations
in air pressure (or that of water or of other fluids) over a wide
band of the spectrum. Thus, there are waves of such low fre¬
quency that we do not ordinarily think of them as sound at all but
only as cyclic pressure waves of air of such long wave lengths
that they can be detected only by sensitive instruments operating
somewhat in the manner of a barometer.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Unesco-Mercier
THE EARTH'S
BRITTLE CRUST
Movements of the earth's
crust under the ocean are
shown in this plate from
the Unesco colour film-
strip, "The Sea". From the
waters emerge atolls and
the Islands formed by vol¬
canic activity. Beneath lie
huge undersea mountain
ranges and between them
is a vast rift in the earth's
crust. It was the opening
up of a "fault" of this
kind that caused the des¬
tructive earthquake in
Chile in 1960. Scientists
were able to map the fault
action from recordings of
terrestial vibrations the
strange music of the earth
hidden from man's ear.
VIBRATING
PATTERNS
Intricate circular wave
systems flow out through
water into which two
probes have been set
vibrating on the same fre¬
quency. As the effect of
the vibrations diminishes
the patterns become less
complex. The same effect
is produced by the
fundamental free oscilla¬
tions of the earth.
MUSIC OF THE EARTH (Cont'd)
Sixteen octaves below mans perception
22
Such knowledge is not new, and "ultra-sound," or sound
frequencies five or six octaves above the human
sound perception threshold, has been made use of in
industry, as is well known. By producing the right
number of vibrations to accomplish a particular job,
sound, or rather ultra-sound, can be used in various
industrial processes. Supersonic waves can sterilize food,
pasteurize milk, emulsify paint, clean castings, and so on.
But the use of sound that is not sound has recently
brought to light another possibilitythat of exploring the
earth's interior structure. From the new methods now
used precise and detailed information can be obtained on
the details of the earth's Inner density and elasticity, on
the length of major earthquake faults, and the degree of
the "ringing" of the earth. So while most of our attention
recently has been turned to Outer Space, scientists have
actually been learning more about the earth's interior (1).
Scientists, especially geophysists, have discussed and
studied the vibrations of the earth for more than three-
quarters of a century, but until recently little was known
about these phenomena. Nevertheless science was able to
evolve some theories and to define the related problems.
Scientists believed there were free oscillations of the earth,
unrelated to normal earthquake waves about which much
had already been learned.
By studies of the passage of earthquake waves through
the earth, some knowledge of the density and elasticity of
the earth's crust, mantle, and core had been gained. But
scientists believed the earth had vibrations of its own.
They believed the earth played music that might be
"heard" if only the means of detecting it could be devised.
And if it could be heard, they wondered what would be
the pitch, or the musical term for frequency, of the result-
inc oscillations?
Some scientists began working on new instruments,
electronic digital computers called extensometers and
gravimeters. The extensometer records oscillations in the
horizontal direction and the gravimeter in the vertical.
The extensometer, an extremely sensitive seismograph
capable of recording very slow oscillations, was designed
by Dr. Hugo Benioff, seismology professor at the Cali¬
fornia Institute of Technology Seismologlcal Laboratory.
Seismographs pick up normal earthquake waves that go
around the earth but disappear quickly. The new
computers were sensitive enough to detect a squeeze or
stretch of one-sixteenth of an inch in the earth between
Pasadena, California and New York.
One of Benloff's extensometers was located near
Isabella Dam in California's Kern County and two of
them at Nana, Peru. It was already known that certain
shock waves, when passing through molten matter, act
differently from when moving through solids. But among
the things scientists also want to learn about the earth's
interior is how much of it is molten and how much of
it Is solid; how deep the roots of mountains go into the
TWO MINUTES TO NOON
The worst natural disaster in recorded history
occurred on September 1, 1923 when a great
earthquake, followed by fires and landslides,
devastated Tokyo, nearby Yokohama and the
surrounding countryside. A dramatic new
account of this great seismic catastrophe is
presented in "Two Minutes to Noon", by
Noel F. Busch, published by Simon and Schuster,
630 Fifth Avenue, New York 20, U.S.A. ($ 4,95)
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
USIS
earth; and how the course and severity of earthquakes
can be accurately predicted.
If earth's music could be recorded and studied, more
and more answers to these problems could be obtained.
And then in 1960 the tremendous Chilean earthquake
struck, and its massive jolt served as the striking hammer
on the bell of the earth and set the earth ringing loudly
enough for its vibrations to be picked up on the instru¬
ments. Sound that is not sound was "heard" at last! And
through it more was learned about our ringing earth.
It was learned that the earth has two fundamental
frequencies of vibration, one with a period of 53.1 minutes
and the other with a period of 54.7 minutes. This double
pitch is due to the fact that the earth Is spinning on its
axis. If it were not spinning it would have only one
fundamental pitch whose frequency would be somewhere
between the two.
The earth's overtones, or the secondary tones produced
by the Independent vibrations of a part of the vibrating
body itself, go to frequencies as high as one vibration
every 3.7 minutes. The torsional vibrations, or the twist¬
ing and turning vibrations caused by internal stress, are
42.3 minutes In length. The overtones die down a little
faster than the fundamental vibrations. After about one
hundred oscillations, the overtones were down to one-
third of their original strength. The fundamental oscilla¬
tions lasted even longer in the earth's core than near the
surface because the core is a better bell.
Yes, there is a music of the earth that can never be
heard by the normal ear unless a recording of it Is arti¬
ficially speeded up and played back, for the frequency of
the vibrations is little less than one per hour. Sound
that man can hear travels about 344 metres (1130 feet)
a second in air under normal conditions. The lowest
audible tone man hears naturally is four octaves below
Middle C, while the Globe's music Is about 20 octaves
below. But the music Is there sound that Is not sound, as
we normally speak of It, yet now known and heard by
certain scientists.
This discovery led to further progress. Analysis of the
oscillations enabled the scientists to map the fault action
that resulted In the Chilean earthquake, a fault of about
600 miles beginning near the town of Concepción and
extending southward, mostly under the sea.
More facts about the elasticity and the density of the
earth through the crust, mantle and core were also learned
and no doubt the future will bring us still greater
knowledge. At present It takes great earthquakes, such
as the Chilean one, to set the earth ringing loudly enough
for its vibrations, to be detected. Smaller earth tremors
may produce similar effects but so far scientists have not
been able to "hear" them. Who knows, however, what
the future will tell us about the inside of our planet?
Perhaps it will prove almost as interesting as Outer
Space.
(1) See "Probing the Interior of the Earth," The Unesco
Courier, Oct. 1963.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Above, head and neck of bridled horse decorates
both sides of this black-figured Attic vase (560-
550 B.C.). Below, another vase painting showing
Theseus killing the Minotaur, the famed mythological
monster of the Cretan Labyrinth (about 540 B.C.).
PANTHEON OF GREEK
GODS AND HEROES
The scenes from Greek mythology shown here
were painted over 2,500 years ago on Attic
black-figured vases now in the collection of
the Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York.
Photographs and descriptions of 56 of these
vases and vase fragments recently appeared in
a special fascicule (1) prepared by Dietrich
von Bothmer. It was published under the
auspices of the International Council for Philo¬
sophy and Humanistic Studies with financial
help from the Metropolitan Museum and from
Unesco. The fascicule has now been added
to the Corpus Vasorum Antiquorum, a vast
"catalogue" of the world's antique vases which
the International Academic Union has been
assembling since 1922. Many countries have
contributed to the Corpus whose 118 fascicules
now constitute a planned and detailed record
of some of man's finest antique art treasures.
(1) "Attic Black-figured Amphorae", published by Har¬
vard University Press, 79, Garden Street, Cambridge,
Mass. U.S.A., from whom this and other U.S. fascicules
in the " Corpus Vasorum Antiquorum " may be ordered.
Do not order from Unesco.
24
Four men and a youth competing in a foot race. They
appear on a prize amphor, one of the Panathenaic vases
linked with the festival of Athens, held to celebrate the
union of Attica under Theseus (about 520 B.C.).
All photos
New York.
1963, The Metropolitan Museum of Art,
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
A scene believed to depict the apo¬
theosis of Herakles. The woman in
the chariot, holding the reins and the
goad, is probably Athena, goddess of
wisdom. On far side of horses are
Apollo and Hermes (about 530 B.C.).
Dionysos, in the centre, turns his head
towards a flute-playing satyr. To
the right of Dionysos stands Hermes
holding wine pitcher (530-520 B.C.).
Dionysos, god of wine, of fertility
and of the theatre, shown between
two dancing satyrs. In his left hand
the god holds a drinking horn. Vase
painting dating from about 520 B.C.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
26
^¿¡¡Fm».
i
Jrf¡,
7Kjâ^\
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
THE DAY
THE RIVER SPOKE
This is a story about Janu, the little girl from India who
lived in a village way down in the southwest, in a place
called Kerala between the mountains and the sea. It is a
green land where the hibiscus and the frangipani bloom,
and coconut palms grow tall and beautiful. In the fields
men and women work together before the monsoons and
after, in the seasons of harvest and sowing, if the big
rains fail there is not enough rice to go round, and many
homes go hungry. But the children are bright-eyed and
eager, wanting to know what lies over their mountains
and their sea in their own land which is india, and the
other lands beyond.
A Short Story
by Kamala Nair
J
Study of a girl by
Purnendu Mukher-
jee, a IZ-year-old
Indian boy. This
drawi ng was
awarded first prize
(13-14 age group)
in the international
children's art
contest held by
Shankar's Weekly,
New Delhi, in 1954.
ANU wriggled through the gap in the bamboo fence and walked down the path between tho
paddy fields. The paddy lay green and soft as far as the eye could see to the east where
blue grey hills were tall against the morning sky, to the west till it met the railway track,
and before her, southwards, right up to where the green river slipped and slid through shale
and boulder to the sea.
She could not see the sea, of course. But Chandu, the fisherman, had long stories to tell of
the river's journey to the sea and how skilfully he had to row his boat at the river's mouth.
It was wonderful to listen to the stories Chandu had to tell and to see the fish he brought,
rowing up river from the sea the clams and mussels and the silvery sardines that all her
village loved, and the dogfish that was cured and salted and hung from the kitchen rafter
in a plaited basket made of palm leaves.
All along the river by the edge of the fields were the coconut palms, their leaves feathery
in the sunlight, and when the big, round moon rose above the hills, the leaves were wet with
moonlight and they rustled. Sometimes when the breeze swept through the bamboo clumps
by the river one could hear a delicate "rat-tat-tat" the reed song that the bamboos liked to
sing.
Janu walked a little slowly now, sniffing the salt air which blew landwards from the sea. Some¬
times, she stopped to pick up the small flat stones which she saved for skimming on the still
water of the tank in Meena's house. The red silk cotton tree was a glory of colour and the
gnarled, twisted branches of the frangipani were laden with blossom. She plucked two, fold¬
ing the petals back so that they looked like ear-rings. Their scent was lovely and warm and
she put some in her hair as well.
She noticed a tiny yellow spider in the golden heart of a flower, and shrank from it at first,
then she shook the flower, and the spider spun a long thread and fell to the ground. A tiny,
golden spider. "I hardly saw it at first,", thought Janu, "it was so yellow, just like the flower."
She had seen brown spiders and large black ones which always scared her, but never one
this colour.
She had reached the river bank now and sat on her favourite rock, her hands cupping her
chin. She had long, bright eyes which her mother had darkened with lamp-black and anti¬
mony and her hair was bunched up in a knot.
A green lizard slid from under the rock and disappeared into the bamboo. A copper-smith
sounded Its "Honk honk, honky tonk" in the distance. The river went past, its murmur soft in
the stillness, and Janu said to herself she loved talking to herself "I've never seen a yellow 27
one before. Why do yellow spiders hide in yellow flowers? I must ask Ettan."
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
The day the river spoke (OmtV)
Ettan went to school where the teacher had taught him to read and write, and he used to sit
in their verandah loudly reading his lessons over and over again. All the boys in their village
went to school, she noticed. But not all the girls.
Meena went, of course, but that was different. Meena had no brothers or sisters and her
father was the village headman. Why, her mother even wore gold "zari" on her blouse when
she went to the big town in the railway train, and she had a fine black umbrella, and Meena had
one too, a small black one with a red tassel.
Most of the others in their village used palm-leaf umbrellas which they wore on their heads
like a hat with a wide brim. It was so much easier to work in the fields in rainy weather when
one wore a palm-leaf umbrella, because it left both one's hands free, but a black umbrella was
so much nicer to have.
"Mother, why can't I go to school like Ettan and Meena?" Janu had asked. Janu called her
brother "Ettan" because Ettan means "Elder brother," but his real name was Gopi. And Mother
had replied: "You are too small, baby. Maybe later." But when she was five, Little Ramu was
born and Mother said: "Maybe next year. Janu girl, mind your little brother while I go to the
fields now."
T
HEN Little Ramu was two, and then three and Mother said: "Hush your crying
now. Ettan goes to school because he is a boy and boys must learn early. You be just my little
girl and help me to clean the rice and fetch the wood. And you keep Little Ramu out of mischief."
"But Meena is a girl and she goes to school I"
"Meena's father has a lot of money," said Father who had come in from the fields. "Sending
girls to school, indeed! Learning to cook is what they need. And sweeping and pounding rice
and helping in the harvest."
And Big Uncle who lay on his straw mat in the corner sat up and said: "What's that? What's
that? Getting lazy, is she? A bamboo switch is what she needs," and then he choked because
his wad of betel leaf nearly went down the wrong way and Mother rushed to pat his back to
stop the coughing and Janu nearly wept because no-one was listening to her.
"But I can do all that when I come back from school. I promise. Please, Fatherl"
"And who's to mind Little Ramu, I'd like to know? And your mother in her condition!"
Janu looked at her mother and sighed. She looked very much as she did just before Little
Ramu was born.
"Would you like to go down to Chandu and buy some sardines for the pot?" asked Mother
kindly, changing the subject, and Janu took the coin Mother gave her and went down the fields
to Chandu.
DRAWINGS BY
A.B. SCHWARZ
These illustrations
are taken from "A
Journey Through
Toyland," by Ka-
28 mala S. Dongerkery;
Popular Book Depot,
Bombay, 1954.
B,
'UT Chandu only laughed when she said she wanted to go to school like Ettan.
"And what would you be doing in a school?" asked Chandu. "Bawling your lessons all together.
Waste of time, I call it. Now if you said: "Let me learn to make a net, let me learn to catch fish,"
there'd be some sense. Schools!" Chandu spat with unerring aim into the water. He wrapped the
sardines in a piece of paper and said: "There, now. You run along home and learn to make
some man a good wife one day. And tell your Mother sardines are coming scarce now. Next
time it'll be dogfishl"
Ettan was twelve and growing bigger and Ramu was five and going to school and she was
nearly ten and minding Little Appu who was the smallest. She came sometimes to the river
when Mother wasn't looking, slipping through the gap in the fence. Down by the river every¬
thing was quiet and peaceful and she was happy. Mostly. But today wasn't one of those days.
A big bright tear splashed down her nose. And another. And another. A kingfisher swept
down, its wings an arrow of blue in the sunlight. And the green lizard slithered down to the
river's edge to bask in the sun, "Dear, dear!" said a sleepy, murmuring voice, "what's the
matter?"
Janu started, because she was sure she had been quite alone. It couldn't have been the lizard.
And the kingfisher was up in the bamboos eating the fish it had caught. It couldn't be the par¬
rots, because parrots shrieked and this was such a sleepy voice. She looked around her. There
wasn't a soul in sight. She was rather scared and wanted to run away.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
"You shouldn't cry, you know," the voice went on. "And you really shouldn't be scared,
when you have been coming here to see me every day well, almost every day."
She started uncertainly. It was such a murmurous sleepy voice, like the river. It couldn't bo
the riverl
"Well, tell me all about it," said the River, for it was the River. "I've got to hurry to reach
the sea, you know."
"They won't let me go to school," said Janu. "They don't want girls. They only" sho stop¬
ped a sob "only want boys. And I'm so old now, they'll never let me go. And I want to go.
I want to learn to read like Ettan and Meena. I want to know why spiders are yellow In yellow
flowers, why the bamboos rustle, why the moon always comes from behind the hills, never tho
other way, why the baby fish in the field water become frogs, why. . ."
"Stop!" said the River. "You make me breathless. So many 'why's'l I can tell you where
the moon goes," he said conspiratorially. "She goes down towards the sea. I've seen her; she
always takes the same way over the mountains and down to the sea, like me!"
"Even Little Ramu goes to school," said Janu bitterly. "Pity the school Isn't by tho sea,"
said the River. "Then I could take you along, you know. But I suppose I couldn't really. You'd
get your feet wet. And that would never do! No, there's only one thing you can do, I'm afraidl"
"I can do something?" asked Janu. "Well, it's up to you," said the River. "Seems to me httlo
girls can do as much as little boys they swim as well as little boys. You Just slip along ono
morning and sit there in the school and listen to what's going on, and maybe the teacher will let
you stay."
"I couldn't," gasped Janu. "I couldn'tl They'd scare me. They'd chase me out." Tho River
laughed. "You? Scared?" he said, "when you're not afraid of the green lizard, or of the snake
in the bamboo clump," (Janu started) "or the big trains rattling past that bridge. Trains aro
noisy. I prefer ships," said the River.
I
ANU forgot to be scared of the snake she'd never known was in the bamboo
clump. "What are ships?" she asked. "Big boats," said the River, "so big that they can tako
hundreds of people, and they sail along the sea with lights that shine all night."
Janu held her breath. "Will they come here?" she asked. "I'm afraid not," said the River.
"Too large, you know. Chandu's catamaran is good enough for me. Chandu can take you to
see a ship, some day."
"They'd never let me!" wailed Janu. "Oh, why am I a girl?" "Try going to school first," said
the River. "Remember it's up to youl"
He sounded sleepier than ever and Janu could hardly hear him now. She rubbed her eyes and
sat up. It must have been a dream. But when she scrambled down the boulder, carefully
skirting the bamboo clump before she got to the path through the fields, she thought she heard
the river chuckle. A slow, sleepy chuckle.
She'd done it at last, but it hadn't been easy. First of all she'd had to wait till Father went
to the fields and Mother began the cooking.. Then she combed her hair and put on the red
ribbon Meena's mother had once given her. Big Uncle had finished his early meal of cold rice
and salted mangoes and was asleep. Little Appu was sucking a contented thumb and Ettan
and Ramu had already left for school.
Ramu was using the slate Ettan used when he first went to school and which, when no-one
was looking, Janu used to borrow just to draw pictures. Very quietly she would draw Chandu's
boat and the bamboo clump and the school. On the slate you could draw things and rub them
out and draw again.
She put Little Appu down on the mat and went towards the fence. Little Appu let out a
howl. She went back hastily and picked him up. Little Appu gurgled happily and pushed a
chubby fist into her face. She said under her breath: "I suppose I'll have to take you now. Only
if you start crying when we get there, I'll I'll throw you into the trees and the parrots will come
and take you away."
She reached the school panting and out of breath and stood by the door listening while the
teacher read out the lesson. It was a story about a prince called Asoka who became a great
king. Little Appu had fallen asleep on her shoulder. She crept nearer and nearer till she
was in the back row squatting with the others on the earthen floor. Little Appu made no noise
and she listened.
The teacher was asking questions. Everyone was busy turning over the pages and holding
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The day the river spoke (Confd)
up a hand to answer and when the questions were finished, the teacher said: "Now, I have a
surprise for you. Next week we shall take the train and go down to Kozhlkode and there
we can see the big bazaars and the tile factory and I shall show you the sea and the lighthouse."
There were delighted shouts from the class. "Please, Sir, what is a lighthouse?" asked Kutty,
the weaver's son.
"It is a big building shaped like a pencil a huge pencil with a bright light at the top that
shines very far, so that the ships at sea can sail safely."
"Is a ship like a catamaran, Sir?" asked Nanu whose mother lived all by herself at the edge
of the clearing by the forest. He walked two miles to school and back every day.
"Now who can answer Nanu's question?" said the teacher and Janu forgot Little Appu and
her fear and her shyness and said clearly: "It is much, much bigger than a catamaran, big
enough for hundreds of people to live inside and. . ." She stopped.
All eyes were on her and Little Appu who had been jerked out of sleep when she got up to
answer, let out a wail. Janu panicked. "Where did you spring from, little girl?" asked the
teacher. "And what is your name? You're new in my class. And haven't I told you, all of you,
not to bring your little brothers and sisters here? Whose little boy is he? Who brought him here?
Hey? Answer mel"
The teacher's spectacles nearly fell off and the class was a forest of shiny black heads all
nodding, all whispering. Janu's lower lip trembled. «J-Janu, Sir. He. . . He's my little brother.
I didn't mean to make him cry. I didn't mean. . ."
"She's Gopi's sister Gopi is in the next class, "said one of the boys.
"It's Janu," said another.
"She's Uncle Gopalan's little girl," said a third.
And the teacher said: "Come here, Janu. All right, all right, pick him up and bring him along,
too. Come here to my desk. Now, all the others can go."
S.
30
HE went in fear and trembling and Little Appu sobbed with fright at the strange
faces round him. The boys trooped out into the sunshine, leaving her along with this stranger.
She held Little Appu close for comfort. She no longer wanted to go to school. School without
the children inside was terrifying.
"So you're Gopi's little sister? Nice lad, Gopi," said the teacher, peering at her over his spec¬
tacles. "I suppose he doesn't know you're here.
"I suppose your mother thinks you're lost. And your little brother, too. Now tell me, why
didn't you come to school before?" He held out a pencil to Little Appu who looked shyly at him
and finally grasped it in his chubby fingers.
By the time the teacher had heard from Janu herself all about how she couldn't go to school
it was past midday, and when she went home her mother was so worried that she scolded Janu
from sheer relief, and her father said he'd take a stick to her back one of these days, roaming
about when there was work to do, and much more, in the way her father always spoke when he
came home tired.
But her secret was her own, like the bright shiny copper coin she polished with tamarind juice
and put away carefully under her mat each night. Of course, when Gopi came back from
school, everyone would know about her escapade. But no-one knew what the teacher had told
her her bright shiny promise which she held tight to her heart like her copper coin which glint¬
ed in the sunlight. "If you really, really want to come to my school, Janu," the teacher had said,
"we'll talk your father into it. Don't you worry. We'll find a way."
Meena had laughed at her story. Meena always laughed a lot and when she did, the dimples
came and went. Meena said it was all over the village, the way Janu had just walked into
school, and Meena's father thought it a pity that some boys didn't have so much spirit and
Meena's mother said: "Wait till she grows up, she'll shake up this place, I've no doubt." Then
Meena had said: "Let's swim a bit, shall we? Race you to the tank." And she had pulled Janu
into the water and they raced each other swimming to the other side and back.
"School Is fun," Meena said, shaking her damp curls. "You'll like it. I hope your father will
let you come. My father says that if you really study hard, you can go on and on and on,
maybe even to High School."
"And after High School?" asked Janu, though she didn't know what High School was. But
Meena didn't know the answer to that. Not yet.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Janu saw the teacher walking up the steps to their gate the next evening when she was
lighting the lamp. She lit the lamp and brought it to the front verandah and set it down on
the step, a tiny winking light to bless their home. Big Uncle had a sprig of tulsl leaf behind his
ear, and was chanting his prayers and Ettan and Ramu joined In, little Ramu stumbling over
the big words. She was too excited to pray. To chant them with Big Uncle, that Is. But, she
did say a prayer all by herself. Not loud, but a small prayer which she hoped God would hear.
She could see her father scratching his cheek the way he did when he was worried and
the teacher was nodding and saying something she couldn't make out. Then he offered her
father some betel leaf and tobacco to chew and they chewed It in a friendly way by the bam¬
boo fence.
And Mother said: "Little Janu, I shall miss you when you go to school. They do say nowa¬
days that girls should learn like boys when I was your age I wanted to go to school, but your
grandmother said 'No', but now, I am glad the teacher came to talk to Father."
H
.E came yesterday too when you were at Meena's house. He thinks you can
study just like Gopi, and I want Gopi to grow up and pass his examinations and work In a big
building as they say Meena's uncle does, far away in a place called Delhi so far It takes threo
days to reach there by train.
"But what will you do, Janu girl, if you go to school now? You'll learn to write your name
and maybe to sew with that big machine,, like Meena's mother, but we won't have any money
to buy a machine, so it's no use thinking of that. Well. . .if you'vo set your heart on It, I
suppose there's no stopping you."
And she sang to Little Appu:
O little koel, little black bird,
Don't you know the season's changed?
Comes the wind and comes the rain
Won't you build your nest again?
And Janu said: "Motherl" and went and threw her arms round her mother's neck and hugged
her tight. "When I grow up," she said, "I'll be a teacher and I'll go from house to house in our
village and ask all the little girls to come to my school. And I'll teach them all I'm going to
learn. You'll seel"
And she went down the path between the fields the next morning before school began, with
a hop, skip and jump and sat on her favourite rock, the red ribbon in her hair and a yellow
flower.
I
did ¡tl" she told the river. "I was scared, but I dit itl And they're letting me
go. I'm going to learn to write my name and do sums and find out why our little fishes in the
ricefields turn into frogs and see the lighthouse. One day I'll see a ship," she nodded to the river.
And the river slipped and slid between shale and boulder and held its green course among
the bamboos, and the coconut palms. Janu took the frangipani blossom from her hair. "Take
this to the sea for me, dear River," she said, "and hurry, hurry, or you'll never reach there." She
turned back to look as she went past and there was the white and yellow blossom floating down
the current. She was sure it was a dream the day the river spoke, but here she was actually going
to school with a red ribbon in her hair and that wasn't a dream.
She ran between the tall green fields. And way behind her she thought she heard the river's
sleepy chuckle: "Come again, little girl, and I'll tell you all about the ships that sail the sea,"
he seemed to be saying, but of course, it could have been just the breeze sighing through the
ricefields in the morning.
KAMALA NAIR is a member of the Indian Ministry of Education, New Delhi. Her story is set
in Kerala which has the highest percentage in India of literacy amongst women, and where
almost all girls of the age group 6-11 are now in school. "The theme, however," she writes,
"is of topical interest in view of the very real need of stepping up the enrolment of girls in
schools in South and South-East Asia."
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
7 Camuâ 1
z
^ >w. m
° V V A -
OB"bE AÜ±LE_H_
A~^V v' z
>
O r.liK ?1 M H F H H tí I H All H H
©[H2ÍSÍSÍSH.
3nT ^Bftv 'ç;
' ÍMS iHSfl M
fg^äffpl
The Unesco philatelic service
As agent in France of the U.N. Postal Administration, Unesco's
Philatelic Service stocks all U.N. stamps and first day covers
currently on sale as well as stamps issued by Unesco member
states to commemorate important events in the history of
Unesco and the U.N. Some recent issues are shown here.
Above, from left, a newly-designed U.N. 50 cent stamp which
has now replaced the 50 cent issue in use since 1951, a U.N.
stamp honouring the United Nations Conference of Trade
and Development which opened in Geneva on March 23, and
a stamp commemorating the 10th anniversary of the Korean
National Commission for Unesco. On left are stamps from
Nepal (with the slogan "Education for All", recalling Unesco's
efforts to promote literacy and extend education) and from
the Mongolian People's Republic (marking its entry into
the United Nations). For prices and further details write to
The Unesco Philatelic Service, Place de Fontenoy, Paris (7e).
STORIES IN STAMPS
Some years ago an enterprising teacher in Monaco decid¬
ed to organize a philatelic contest among his pupils. His
idea has now grown into a large scale international
stamp competition and exhibition which, as Scolatex II,
recently attracted 2,000 entries from 18 countries.
Organized by the Unesco National Commission for
Monaco and the Monaco Philatelic Union, the contest
seeks to show the educational value of postage stamps
and their role in promoting international understanding.
After being judged and displayed in Monaco, a selection
of the exhibits was shown at Unesco's H.Q. in
Paris, where prizes, including Unesco Art Albums and
subscriptions to The Unesco Courier, were awarded by
Unesco. Winners of the inter-school section awards
were : (1 ) École Schlpflin, Strasbourg, France (History of
Postal Services in Alsace-Lorraine); (2) École Catholique
de Garçons, Wissembourg, France (Hunger in the World) ;
(3) Young Philatelists' Club, Kochitse, Czechoslovakia
(The History of Dress). Winners of individual prizes
were : (1 ) Claude Bosse, Monaco (Hydro-electric power) ;
(2) Zbynek Pop, Breznice, Czechoslovakia (A Child Grows,
Plays and Learns); (3) Alta Lanos Iscola. Budapest,
Hungary (The Concentration Camps). Right, four stamps
from the prizewinning exhibit. The History of Dress.
CESKOSMNSKO
coc_ »«1
c7 *'j it
i
ITS Kj L fi n < 1 r totltM
CESKOSLOVENSKO
ÜEPÜKUUPtíloSíAlsE
GOETHE
... 174» - l«3l 	
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
A CLASSROOM HELPER
Sir,
We live in a time of "universalism"
and nothing concerning mankind
should be alien to any of us. Through
your magazine Unesco helps to
achieve the great task of making
nations approach each other on the
basis of a broader mutual knowledge.
In the French lessons which I give
at the University and the Polytechnic
School of Guayaquil, I make good
use of the French edition of The
Unesco Courier, both for translations
and exercises. By using it in this
way I find that the interest created
in the subjects you present is sustained
and increased for my students.
Luis Felipe Torres
Guayaquil, Ecuador
WHEN FLIGHT WAS SILENT
Sir,
In his article on the history of
balloons (Sept. 1963) David Gunston
relates how the French used a tethered
gas-bag for observation purposes at
Maubeuge. This captive balloon was
actually used at Fleurus in the Belgian
province of Hainaut during the famous
battle in which the army of the French
Republic defeated the Austrians, on
June 26, 1794. This was the first time
a balloon was used for military recon¬
naissance.
I was surprised that the article did
not mention Auguste Piccard, the
Swiss scientist and professor at the
University of Brussels, who in 1931
became the first person to reach the
stratosphere (16,000 metres) using a
balloon carrying a sealed nacelle.
Eliane Jacquemyns
Brussels, Belgium
VULCANOLOGISTS OF RABAUL
Sir,
In your excellent issue about the
interior of the Earth (Oct. 1963) vul-
canological observatories are discussed
but no mention is made of the well-
equipped observatories in the Melane-
sian region of the Pacific: facilities
for. the prediction of volcanic eruptions
exist at Rabaul, in New Guinea;
Honiara in the Solomons; and Vila in
the New Hebrides.
In particular, at Rabaul, the Aus¬
tralian Government has maintained a
Vulcanological Observatory since
1937 to watch over the 30 dormant
and active volcanoes in the Territory
of Papua and New Guinea. The
Observatory is under the auspices of
the Administration of Papua and
New Guinea and is partly staffed
from the Bureau of Mineral Resources,
Canberra, Australia.
The Rabaul Vulcanological Obser¬
vatory is equipped with a most up-to-
date telemetered seismic network to
safeguard the large population living
in and around the Rabaul Caldera.
In addition, a comprehensive report
ing network utilizing government
patrol posts, missions, private plan¬
tations and air companies ensures an
adequate warning of any premonitory
volcanic phenomena. These reports
are immediately checked by competent
vulcanologists from Rabaul. Three
more seismic outstations nearing
completion at outlying volcanoes, to
be manned by Papuan and New Gui¬
ñean Vulcanological Assistants, will
increase the protection offered by the
present organization.
C. D. Branch
Vulcanologlst
Rabaul, New Guinea
BELGIUM'S CONGO RECORD
Sir,
In your November 1963 issue you
publish a long article on the Congo
(Leopoldville). I can understand that
Unesco wishes to tell readers what it
is doing in the world, but I would
have hoped for a more accurate ac¬
count and for a little justice to be
rendered to the former colonizers.
Though it may be true that in 1960
the Congo had produced few university
students, it was also a fact that of all
countries in Tropical" Africa, it was
the one with the lowest illiteracy
rate.
You also speak of Lwiro. From
the captions with the photographs
anyone unfamiliar with the subject
would certainly believe that this scien¬
tific centre had been created by
Unesco, when, in fact, it was a Belgian
foundation and always welcomed
foreign research workers who wished
to study there.
I have been sorry to see that in the
organizations connected with the Uni¬
ted Nations, Belgian achievements in
the Congo are easily forgotten whereas
there is no lack of criticism of a kind
that is not necessarly valid.
Dr. R. Mouchet
Brussels, Belgium
HIDDEN HUMUS RICHES
Sir,
In the forests and jungles covering
great stretches of the earth, a con¬
tinuous process of life and death goes
on, especially in the tropical and sub¬
tropical zones. Rotting bark and
leaves, transformed into humus, even¬
tually feed new plants and trees that
replace the dead ones. Humus can
also be obtained by draining lakes
and swamps whose bottoms are full
of decomposed plants and other
vegetal organisms. Could not the
humus from both sources be used as
a fertilizer in those parts of the world
whose dry, sterile soil needs it so
badly? This might literally mean sal¬
vation for millions facing hunger. Is
my idea too Utopian? Let us have some
expert opinions on this point.
Augustin Rubio Delclos
Barcelona, Spain
OPEN THE WINDOW WIDER
Sir,
Your motto is "A Window Open on
the World." Unfortunately that win¬
dow is not a very big one! Ours is
a changing world and in my opinion
Tue Unesco Courier does not keep
pace with the changes.
In place of former colonies, new,
independent states are taking sh.ipe
with their own, original, even though
young, cultures. A glance at the map
of Africa is sufficient; in the last five
years the continent has become un¬
recognisable.
What is life like in these new states,
how arc the people building their
economy despite all their difficulties,
how do they work, how do they spend
their leisure time? F.vcry one of these
peoples has its own customs, each has
its own dances and songs. I should
like to sec all these interesting things
through your "window."
It is true you have published some
material on these subjects, but very
little, and your authors have more to
say about the past of the peoples of
Africa and Asia than about the pre¬
sent.
The theme is certainly a broad one.
Tell us how the people of countries
like Mali or Ghana, Western Samoa
or Yemen or Gambia arc living today.
Interesting changes arc taking place
in the U.A.R. and Algeria. In short,
open your window wide, so that
through it we shall see that part of
the world to which spring is only
just coming.
The year 1963 was marked by a
very encouraging event the conclu¬
sion of the Moscow Test Ban Treaty.
The world is growing warmer, but the
warmth is only faintly reflected in
the columns of your journal.
I should like to read how the people
of different countries arc fighting for
peace, I should like to know some¬
thing about our contemporaries who
grudge no effort in the struggle for
this great cause.
Anatoly Chclvcrikov
Gorky, U.S.S.R.
PORTRAITS OF GREAT
ARTISTS
Sir,
I realize that you cannot always
satisfy the requests of all readers. I
would like to hope, however, that you
will one day publish an issue similar
to the one on Velasquez (December
1960) which encouraged me to sub¬
scribe to your magazine. Could you
not devote an issue to another great
artist?
René G. Kyckebuscli
Dallas Texas, U.S.A.
Ed note: We are studying the possi¬
bility of introducing colour and thus
hope to present great works of art in
colour more often.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
TpESTS FOR TEXTBOOKS: Five Eu-
ropean countries are taking part in a
Unesco experiment to compare geography
books published in different countries and
assess their contribution to international
understanding. Books from Denmark,
France, the Federal Republic of Germany,
Poland and Spain are to be evaluated for
accuracy, adequacy, objectivity and balanc¬
ed presentation by experts from Argentina,
Brazil, Chile and Mexico. Geography
books from these Latin American countries
will also be reviewed on a similar basis
by European specialists.
JIJeW UNESCO ART SLIDES: Mosaics
from Israel, illuminated manuscripts,
from Ethiopia and Byzantine mosaics from
Greece are illustrated in three new series
of art slides issued by Unesco. The Unesco
Collection brings within reach of a wide
public masterpieces that are not adequately
known. Each series consists of about 30
mounted slides (5x5 cms) with an explan¬
atory booklet and captions in English.
French and Spanish.
LONGEST LABORATORY: Across
the Central Asian deserts, the Kazakh
steppes, the Altai mountain chain and the
Siberian tsiga stretches a chain of seis-
mological stations of the Soviet Institute
of Earth Physics, ranged in a line over
2,300 miles long. In the past three years
it has made studies into what is happening
inside the earth to a depth of 600 miles
and more. It has also made a special
study of tidal movements in the earth's
crust oscillations which can amount to
over one foot per day.
^lENNA COURSE FOR GEOLOGISTS:
An International Post-Graduate Train¬
ing Centre, sponsored by Unesco and
organized by the Geological Survey of
Austria, will hold its first course in Vienna
for eight months, from September 21,
1964. Application forms to attend this
course are obtainable from Geological
Survey of Austria, Wien III, Rasumof-
skygasse 23, Austria, and should be
returned before April 15.
j^JlLKY WAY TELESCOPE : Sweden's
largest radio telescope is now being
built near Gothenburg on the country's
west coast. Intended for research in the
Milky Way and for tracing space signals,
the telescope is equipped with a reflector
whose diameter is over 100 feet.
Yii WINDLING REDWOODS : The
M^ World Wildlife Fund reports that the
Giant Redwoods of California are still
being felled for lumber in their hundreds.
In one area six miles of redwoods will
soon fall unless conservationists can acquire
the property. It is hoped that one grove,
the Pepperwood Grove, may be bought
as a memorial to Dag Hammarskjold, late
Secretary-General of the United Nations.
I
H. /^-
- t___j__i j 1 yf
*MM* \ __L--V^\1 Ut^"
i	\ \ \A^l | V^
rrnAJi^
1
E THIOPIA'S NATIONAL MUSEUM:
A museum is to be built in Addis
34 Ababa to house the cultural and artistic
heritage of Ethiopia. It will have three
main departments : archeology, painting
and sculpture, and folk arts, and an
auditorium for theatrical and cinema
performances.
* ¥ IBRARY/USA' : A unique com¬
puter-equipped reference library,
"Library/U.S.A.", is one of the outstanding
features of the New York World's Fair.
It makes use of a combination of books,
electronic equipment and professional
personnel not only to provide information
to Fair visitors, but also to demonstrate
the dynamic nature and significance of the
modern library.
]l#ONUMENTS ON THE MAP : Swit¬
zerland has arranged for the publica¬
tion by its Topographical Institute of a
map on which there are shown the sites
of its artistic and historical monuments, as
well as those of Liechtenstein, its neigh¬
bour. Switzerland was the 49th country
to ratify the International Convention for
the Protection of Historical Monuments in
the Event of Armed Conflict, sponsored
by Unesco.
KTaBUKI SHOWS FOR EUROPE:
Kabuki, the centuries-old traditional
drama of Japan is to be presented to Eu¬
ropean audiences later this year according
to the Japanese Foreign Office. It is
hoped that a troupe composed of 60 to 70
leading actors, will perform in Berlin,
Rome, Paris and London.
^|7aR ON ILLITERACY: Senior
officials from some 40 African
countries met in Abidjan, Ivory Coast, at
a Unesco regional conference last month,
to explore ways of stepping up the fight
against illiteracy throughout Africa. Their
conclusions were later submitted to a meet¬
ing, also held in Abidjan, of African Mi¬
nisters of Education.
f^ ALLING DOCTOR X : An Australian
doctor has developed an emergency
radio call service gadget called "Telmar".
Connected to the horn of a motor-car it
can be used to contact the doctor while
he is on his rounds or, as it weighs only
two and a half pounds, it can be worn
in a case over the doctor's shoulder. Tests
have shown that Telmar can receive signals
from 50 miles away.
¥|OCTORS FOR THE CONGO. Fifty-
nine Congolese (Leopoldville) medical
assistants who were accepted in French
medical schools in 1960 have now
gratuated and have returned to their
country as full-fledged doctors. Their train¬
ing was made possible by fellowships
from the World Health Organization,
financed from U.N. allocations to the Fund
for the Congo.
YI^MTING ABOUT THE U.N. : A
prize competition for the best
magazine articles on the economic and
social activities of the United Nations
published in 1964 is being organized by
the International Federation of the Period¬
ical Press, which is offering awards of
§500, $250, $100. Articles entered should
be sent to the IFPP, 45, rue de Lisbonne,
Paris-8*, France, before January, 1965.
¡KCIENCE BOOKS FROM SWEDEN:
A gift of 50,000 volumes of scientific
literature, worth about $80,000, is being
made by Sweden to a dozen developing
countries in Asia, Africa and South Ame¬
rica. The scheme is sponsored and
financed by NIB, the Swedish Agency for
International Assistance.
TTV EYES FOR GEOLOGISTS: In
the U.S.A., geologists are using a set
of two TV cameras to scan holes in the
earth's crust drilled to depths of up to
5,000 feet. The set, designed by the
Lawrence Radiation Laboratory of the
University of California, has one camera
which looks down the hole while the other
views the sidewalls, enabling geologists to
determine rock formations and mineral
deposits.
¥JRUGUAY'S SCIENCE FAIR: About
*^ 750 boys and girls from secondary
schools in Uruguay entered models and
projects in the country's first National
Science Fair held in Montevideo and timed
to coincide with an "Atoms at Work"
exhibit organized in the capital. Entries
covered all aspects of the natural sciences
from astronomy to zoology, and included
projects relating to space science, industry,
cattle-raising and agriculture.
CARIBOU IN DANGER: Only 15 years
ago men were taking as many as a
million caribou a year in the Canadian
arctic, to feed themselves and their dog
teams. By 1955 the total number of
caribou was estimated to have been reduced
to a mere 278,000 as the numbers killed
by far exceeded the number of calves
born to the herds. Many Canadian con¬
servationists regard the ultimate survival
of the caribou as still in doubt, according
to an article in "Canadian Audubon".
Flashes. . .
Three million students in 7,500 ele¬
mentary or secondary schools and many
thousands in colleges in the United States
are receiving part of their education through
television, according to the Institute for
Communications Research of Stanford Uni¬
versity.
| More than eight million square kilo¬
metres of Africa is a danger zone for
sleeping sickness reports WHO. This area
is infested with 23 species and 13 subspecies
of tsetse fly, the insect that transmits the
diseases to animal and man.
| More than one quarter of Mexico's
budget about 400 million dollars will
be devoted to education in 1964, when it
is planned to build 12,500 literacy centres
and to increase primary school enrolment
by 260,000.
g The floor of the Pacific Ocean is a vast
dumping ground for chemicals and miner¬
als, including nickel, copper, cobalt, phos¬
phates and manganese produced by rivers,
submarine volcanoes, disintegrating rocks
etc., reports a University of California
scientist, who estimates that there are
1,500,000 million tons of metal nodules
waiting to be "mined".
The Government of West Pakistan plans
to open 5,500 new primary schools by the
end of the present school year. At least
one thousand of these schools are destined
for isolated areas. .
u
z
<
2
o
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Volume I : Paintings Prior to 1860
Lists nearly 900 recommended colour reproduc¬
tions and includes many examples from Asia,
Africa, Australia and Central Europe.
Price: 30/-(stg); $6.00; 21 F. 323 pages.
In the Federal Republic of Germany, Switzerland
and Austria, a special Unesco-Oldenbourg Verlag
edition (with German text) is also available.
UNESCO CATALOGUES OF
COLOUR REPRODUCTIONS
OF PAINTINGS
Two volumes presenting an up-to-date listing of
colour reproductions of world-famous paintings com¬
piled from the Unesco collection of reproductions selec¬
ted by internationally-known experts on the basis of
fidelity of reproduction, the significance of the artist
and the importance of the original painting.
Each painting in these beautifully presented volumes
is reproduced in black and white together with full
details of the original, name of publisher and price of
colour reproduction.
catalogue
de reproductions
en couleurs de peintures
1860 i 1963
Unesco paris
Volume II
Paintings
from 1860
to 1963
A new and completely
up-to-date edition of 519
pages.
Contains descriptions
and illustrations of 1440
reproductions available in
full colour prints including
28 artists represented, for
the first time.
Price:
30/-(stg); $6.00; 21 F.
Where to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Press Department, Royal
Afghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Tradco Agencies, 109 Swanston Street, G. P. O.
Box 2324 V, Melbourne C. I. (Victoria) ; United
Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
8 th Floor, McEwan House, 343 Little Collins St.,
Melbourne C. I. (Victoria). (A. 15/-). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C.. Spengergasse 3 9, Vienna V
(Sch. 60.-). BELGIUM. Editions " Labor ",
342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-Boek-
handel, Belgielei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (100 FB) and art slides only: Louis De Lannoy,
22, place de Brouckère, Brussels. CCP 3 3 80.00.
BURMA. Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road,
Rangoon. (K. 5.50). CANADA. Queen's Printer.
Ottawa, Ont. ($ 3.00). CEYLON. Lake House
Bookshop, 100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Colombo,
2. (Rs. 9). CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section 1, Taipeh, Taiwan (For¬
mosa). CUBA.Cubartimpex, Apartado 6540, La Ha¬
vana. (2.25 pesos). CYPRUS. Cyprus National
Youth Council, P. O. Box 539, Nicosia. CZE¬
CHOSLOVAKIA. ArtiaLtd., 30 Ve Smeckách. Prague
2. DENMARK. Einar Munksgaard, Prags Boulevard
47 Copenhagen S (D.kr. 12). ETHIOPIA. Interna¬
tional Press Agency. P.O. Box 120. Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, 2 Keskuskatu,
Helsinki. (Fmk. 540). FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco,
Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7'. CCP. 12598-48. (7 F.).
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg Verlag, Rosenheimerstrasse
145, Munich. 8, For the Unesco Kurier (German ed
only) Bahrenfelder-Chaussee 1 60, Hamburg-Bahrenfeld,
CCP. 276650 (DM 8). GHANA Methodist Book
Depot Ltd. Atlantis House, Commercial St., POB 100,
Cape Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See United King¬
dom. GREECE. Librairie H. Kaufímann, 28, rue du
Stade, Athens. HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 64,
Nathan Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY. Kultura, P. O.
Box 149. Budapest, 62. ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson
& Co. H. F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik INDIA. Orient
Longmans Ltd. Nicol Road,, Bellard Estate, Bombay 1 :
1 7 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 1 3 ; Gunfoundry Road,
Hyderabad, 1 : 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2; Kanson House,
1 /24 Asaf Ah Road, P.O.Box386, New Delhi.1 ; Sub-Depot:
Oxford Book & Stationery Co., 1 7 Park Street, Calcutta
1 6, Scindia House, New Delhi. Indian National Commission
Co-operation with Unesco, Ministry of Education, for
New Delhi 3. (Rs. 7). INDONESIA. P. N. Fadiar Bhakti
Djalan, Nusantara 22, Djakarta. IRAQ. Mackenzie's
Bookshop, Baghdad. IRELAND. The National Press,
2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/3).
ISRAEL. Blumstem's Bookstores 3 5, Allenby Road
and 48, Nahlat Beniamin Street, Tel-Aviv ( 1 £ 5.50).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour
Street, Kingston. Knox Educational Services, Spaldingt.
(10/-). JAPAN. Maruien Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-Nichome,
Nihonbashi, P.C. Box 605 Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
(Yen 670). JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub. Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman.
KENYA. E.S.A. Bookshop, P.O. Box 30167. Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole
and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LUXEMBURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue,
Luxemburg. MALAYSIA Federal Publications Ltd.,
Times House, River Valley Rd., Singapore (M. $500)
MALTA. Sapienza's Library 26 Kingsway. Valletta. (10/-).
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon
Street, Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid
des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (7 NF.). NETHERLANDS.
N. V. Martinus Ni|hoff, Lange Voorhout. 9, The Hague,
(fl. 6). NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES. G. CT. Van
Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.) N.V., Willemstad, Curacao. N.A.
NEW ZEALAND Government Printing Office 20.
Molesworth Street (Private Bag) Wellington, C. 1 Govern¬
ment Bookshops,: Auckland (P.O. Box 5344), Christ-
church (P.O.Box 1721), Dunedin (P.O. Box 1 1 04 (1 0/-).
NIGERIA. CM. S. Bookshops, P.O. Box 174. Lagos
(10/-). NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille Grenu.
7 Oslo For the Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narvesens
Litteratur Tjeneste, Stortingsgt, 2 Oslo, Postboks 115
(kr 13.20) PAKISTAN. The Weit-Pak Publishing Co.
Ltd., Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box 374 S6-N
Gulberg Industrial Colony, Lahore. PANAMA.
Cultural Panameña, Avenida 7a, No. Tl-49, Apartado de
Correos 2018, Panama (D.F. Balboas 3-). PHILLIPI¬
NES. The Modern Book Co., 508 Rizal Avenue
Manila. POLAND. "RUCH" ul. Wiloza Nr. 46x
Warsaw 10 (Zl. 50). PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade
Lda, Livraria Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon.
PUERTO RICO. Spanish English Publications. Eleanor
Roosevelt 1 1 5, Apartado 1912, Hato Rey. RHODESIA
& NYASALAND. The Book Centre, Gordon Avenue, Sa¬
lisbury, Southern Rhodesia. SUDAN. AI Bsshir Book¬
shop, P.O.Box 1118. Khartoum. SWEDEN A/B CE.
Fntxes Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 1 6.
For The Unesco Courier: Svemka Unescorldet. Vasaga-
tan 15-17, Stockholm, C (Kr. 10); SWITZERLAND.
Europa Verlag. 5 Rímistrasie Zurich. Payot, 40. rut du
Marché, Geneva CCP. 1-236. "Courier" only: Georges
Losmaz, 1, rue des Vieux-Grenadiers. Geneva. CCP.
1-4811. (Fr. S. 8). TANGANYIKA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop, PO.B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam.
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue. Bangkok.
(35 ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda
Bookshop, P.O. Box 145, Kampala. UNION OF
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Bookstore. Libri Building,
Church Street, P.O. Box 724 Pretoria. For the Unesco
Courier (single copies) only : Central News Agency. P.O.
Box 1033. Johannesburg. (10/-). UNITED ARAB
REPUBLIC (EGYPT). La Renaissance d'Egypte. 9 Sh.
Adly-Pasha, Cairo. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M.
Stationery Office. P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I. (10/-).
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications Center,
317 East 34th St, New York. N.Y. 10016 (15.00.)
and (except periodicals): Columbia University Press,
2960 Broadway, New York, 27, N.Y. U.S.S.R. Mez-
hdunarodnaia Kniga, Moscow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA
Yugoslovenska Knjiga, Terazi|e 27, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
© 1963, The Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York
CERAMIC ART
FROM ANCIENT GREECE
Four steeds poised as though awaiting the charioteer's command decorate this
6th-century B.C. Greek amphor from the collection of Attic black-figured vases
in the Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York. The design on the reverse side of
this 16-inch high vessel shows Theseus killing the Minotaur. For other exam¬
ples of these graceful ceramic masterpieces from ancient Greece see page 24.
]]>
</page>
</document>
