<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="063381eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The
A WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD^~^^ A IND OPEN ON
Lour i er
NOVEMBER 1963 (16TH YEAR) - PRICE 1/-STG. ( U.K.) - 30 CENTS (CANADA) - 0.70 F (FRANCE)
Constantin Stanislavsky
THE MAN
WHO REVOLUTIONIZED
THE THEATRE
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
RUMANIA'S
PAINTED
CHURCHES
Photo © Unesco
The painted exterior walls of the Moldavian churches of northeastern Rumania with their figures
and scenes are like the open pages of giant illustrated books. This majestic 16th century fresco,
depicting The Last Judgment covers the western façade of the monastery church of Voronet
which was completed and decorated In 1547. Some of the finest examples of this art have now
been collected in " Rumania : Painted Churches of Moldavia ", a new album in the Unesco World
Art Series. Published by the New York Graphic Society by arrangement with Unesco, this album,
printed in Italy, has 32 full-page colour illustrations and is priced at SI 8.00 or equivalent.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
NOVEMBER 1963
16TH YEAR
Contents
No. 11
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
COVER PHOTO
This year marks the one-
hundredth anniversary of
the birth of the Russian
actor and stage producer,
Constantin Stanislavsky. An
inspired and meticulous
artist for whom no effort
was too great, he gave a
completely new form to
dramatic art. A quarter of
a century after his death the
impact of his work conti¬
nues to be felt in all parts
of the world. (See page 12)
Official Soviet photo
Page
4 UNESCO IN THE CONGO
By Garry Fullerton
12 CONSTANTIN STANISLAVSKY
Revolutionary of the modern theatre
By Grigori Kristi
15 MY LIFE IN ART
Last pages of Stanislavsky's spiritual testament
20 LEAVES FROM STANISLAVSKY'S NOTEBOOKS
23 ONE LANGUAGE FOR THE WORLD?
By Mario Pei
24 ALLO! - HALLO!...
A Unesco film puts communications in a nutshell
28 UNICEF GREETING CARDS
30 THE UNSOLVED MYSTERY OF MARAJO
What caused the decline and death of an island people?
By Alfred Métraux
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
(M.C. 63.1., 185 A)
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7', France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
René Caloz
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey
Russian Edition : Venlamin Matchavariani (Moscow)
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shln-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Italian Edition : Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except In July and August when
it is bi-monthly ( I I issues a year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian. German.
Arabic, Japanese, and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed hy H.M.
Stationery Office, P. O. Box S69, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re>
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier le indexed monthly in The Readers' Guide to
Periodical Literature published by H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates : IO/-stg. ;$3.00 (Canada) ;7.00
French Francs or equivalent. Single copies l/-stg. 30
cents ; 0.70 F.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO
IN THE CONGO
by Garry Fullerton
N o one In Leopoldville or anywhere else in the
I Congo knew whether the secondary schools
would open In the fall of 1960. And if they did open, no
one knew how many teachers would be on hand to greet
the returning students.
Education, like all other public services, was a victim
of the political and military instability of the new
republic's first few months of independence. Thousands
of European technical and professional personnel
teachers, doctors, lawyers, civil servants, journalists,
engineers, business people had left the country and few
Congolese specialists had beeen trained to replace them.
Answering the appeal of the Congolese Government,
the United Nations and the specialized agencies tried to
All the breach. A vast co-ordinated programme of civilian
assistance, covering nearly every field of activity, was
launched in July and August, 1960, and grew rapidly until
it became one of the most extensive international efforts
of its kind ever undertaken.
In Unesco's part of the programme, secondary schools
were by far the most urgent problem. First of all, there
were virtually no Congolese teachers and it was not
known how many Belgian teachers would return after
their summer holidays in Europe. Secondly, although
secondary school graduates were desperately needed in
every sector of government and industry, enrolments
were extremely low and only 152 Congolese graduated in
1960.
The picture was equally grim in primary education, but
there the problem was one of quality rather than quantity.
By the official statistics, nearly 1,500,000 children were in
primary schools throughout the Congo in 1960. They
constituted 71.5 per cent of the age group 5 to 14, one of
the highest enrolment ratios in Africa. But only 3,500 of
the 16,000 schools provided teaching beyond the second
grade, and nearly 70 per cent of the pupils left school
before completing four years, the minimum necessary to
maintain literacy. Only nine percent finished the full six
years.
Similar situations prevailed in the fields of science and
of mass communication with which Unesco was also
Unations
concerned. Many European journalists had left, and the
Congolese who had received journalistic training fre¬
quently rose to positions of prominence in the new
government. Thus newspapers and radio were left with
staffs who lacked both professional training and a good
cultural background.
To solve the secondary school problem, Unesco helped
the Congolese authorities recruit teachers from other
countries and establish a National Institute of Education
to train Congolese teachers.
Although initial recruitment was slow, Unesco managed
to send 66 teachers to the Congo during the winter of
1960-1961. Together with a number of Belgian teachers
who volunteered to remain at their posts under a bilateral
technical assistance programme, these teachers made it
possible to re-open or keep open a number of schools
which otherwise would have had to close their doors or
reduce the number of classes.
By the 1962-1963 school year, some 556 teachers had
been recruited with Unesco's help for Congo schools, about
one third of the entire teaching force. These teachers are
actually employed by the Congolese government, but
Unesco pays one third of their basic salaries in foreign
currency, as well as a bonus of $1,200 a year.
Among the 25 nationalities represented by this corps of
teachers, Haitians are the most numerous, followed by
Belgians, French and Lebanese in that order. But there
are also teachers from Spain, Italy, United Arab Republic,
Syria, Greece, Afghanistan, Poland, Canada, Honduras,
Vietnam, United States, Norway, Switzerland, Netherlands,
China, Luxemburg, Mexico, Rwanda, United Kingdom,
Colombia and Sweden. Several school faculties have as
many as a dozen different nationalities, and one the
athénée at Goma has 15.
Despite difficult living conditions (especially food and
housing) and teaching conditions, most of these teachers
have done a job of which they can be proud. A few have
been outstanding.
CONT'D ON PAGE 6
READING BY STREET
LIGHT. Thirst for educa¬
tion impels young men and
women to buy books when
they have little money for
food and to spend long
hours at night studying
under the streetlamps of
Leopoldville (right) when
their homes are too noisy
or too crowded or have no
light. In 4 years secondary
school enrolment has more
than doubled in the Congo.
Left, one of hundreds of
secondary school teachers
recruited with Unesco's help
is seen in a history class.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Unesco - Unations - Basil Zarov
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Unations photos
NEWSPAPERS have a larger circulation in the Congo
than in any other French-speaking African country
according to a Unesco report. Its six dailies now total
34,000 compared with 24,000 before independence,
and there are about a dozen weeklies besides. During the
past year Congolese newspapermen have been attending
courses combining journalism and general education
run by Unesco specialists. Below, Unesco expert Antoine
DesRoches explains some aspects of front-page layout.
LOVANIUM UNIVERSITY, above, traces its origins to
1925 when the University of Louvain, Belgium, established
a medical foundation and agricultural centre near Leopoldville.
Given university status in 1956, Lovanium now includes
faculties of law, medicine, philosophy and arts, theology,
science, political and social sciences, and polytechnical
studies. Its research facilities include Africa's first nuclear
reactor. In 1961-62, 1,100 students were enrolled in Congo
institutions of higher education, eight of which now exist.
CONGO (Cont'd)
Decolonizing of the
"Unesco's aid has been extremely precious to us in the
difficult years following independence," Michel Colin, the
Congo's minister of education, told me last May. Other
Congolese authorities acknowledge too that without the
foreign teachers there would be no secondary education In
the Congo.
The ministry of education has estimated that the need
for foreign teachers will continue to grow until 1967,
reaching a peak of 7,000, before leveling off as Congolese
are trained to take their places. Whether this many can
be supplied either through international or bilateral tech¬
nical assistance remains an open question. Perhaps
Congolese secondary schools will remain short-staffed for
some years to come.
Meanwhile, however, the National Institute for Educa¬
tion will begin in 1964 to graduate about 100 teachers a
year. The institute, better known by its French initials,
IPN (Institut Pédagogique National), opened its doors in
1961 and is a prime example of international co-operation.
Headed by a Congolese director, its staff includes Unesco
experts from 12 nations. It receives financial assistance
from the Congolese government and the United Nations,
as well as from the United States AID programme and the
British Council.
IPN's student body includes young people from all
£_L&
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
mind
MOBILE UNESCO TEAMS are now touring the Congo giving refresher courses
in education to many of the country's 42,000 primary school teachers. Each team is
made up of three Unesco educators as well as a UNICEF nutrition-hygiene specialist.
Above, a group of young Congolese teachers get a "live" demonstration in child caro.
provinces of the Congo, selected without regard to ethnic
origin or religious belief. In addition and this Is
something of a novelty in a country where women have
traditionally received very little education and teaching
has been mostly a male monopoly it is open to women as
well as men.
The institute's programme of studies lays heavy stress
on African linguistics, African and Congolese history,
cultural anthropology and sociology. By emphasizing the
Congo's own heritage, it hopes to become what Joseph
Ngalula, former minister of education, called "an instru¬
ment of mental decolonization."
Antonio Chiappano, the Unesco expert responsible for
the school's curriculum, feels very strongly that it must
combine the best experience of all nations and yet be
adapted specifically to the needs of the Congo.
"We know that the experience of one country is not
directly transferable to another country," he said, "but
we don't know yet what can be saved and what must be
discarded. We are in a process of constant revision and
self-correction. The institute is above all experimental.
What we learn here will be applied when additional
teacher training Institutions are set up."
This same pragmatic philosophy also guided the work
of the reform commission established by the Congolese
government with the help of Unesco to overhaul and
streamline the entire structure of secondary education in
the Congo. The reform involves both modernization of
the system to take advantage of the latest educational
research (similar to efforts being made in most other
nations) and emphasis on Africa, particularly in such
subjects as history and geography.
The commission, appointed In February, 1961, was
headed by Henri Taklzala, secretary-general of the Congo¬
lese ministry of education. It included representatives of
the administration, the Catholic Office of Education, the
Protestant Office of Education, the University of Lovanium,
primary education and technical education, as well as
Unesco advisers.
The group proposed that- secondary education be
divided into two cycles: a first "orientation" cycle of two
years, during which all students would take the same
courses; and a second cycle of four years with specialized
sections for science, the humanities, commerce and
administration, agriculture, teaching and technology
(mechanics, electricity, construction and industrial
chemistry).
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
CONGO (Cont'd)
On the long road to school
The principal difference between the new system and
the old Is that the new one is "promotional," seeking to
advance as many students as possible without sacrificing
quality, rather than limiting itself, through rigid selection,
to the education of a tiny elite. Whereas the old system
produced a large number of academic failures, ill-adapted
for any sort of occupation, the new one is so designed that
students can Interrupt their schooling at any one of
several points and begin useful careers with the informa¬
tion already acquired.
The orientation cycle has already been put into effect
in most Congo schools, and the first year of the four-year
cycle is beginning this year. Formidable obstacles stand
between the plan on paper and Its application in reality,
however, including the shortage of teachers, the shortage
of textbooks and the shortage of funds. An ideal system
of education, and this plan comes close to that, cannot
be bought cheaply and it may be many years before the
transition from old to new is complete.
iNALLY, although the reform has received over-
m whelming approval from most Congolese edu¬
cators, a small but vocal minority has remained opposed
to it. In part this opposition stems from the natural
conservatism of educational traditionalists; in part it
reflects a suspicion, quite unfounded incidentally, that
the reform is an attempt to "water down" the old curri¬
culum for Congolese consumption.
These psychological obstacles are gradually being over¬
come, however, and if the tough problems of teachers,
books and money can be solved, the reform can become a
reality. Should this happen, this might well constitute
Unesco's most significant contribution to the Congo.
With Unesco's help, the Congolese government is
tackling all aspects of education simultaneously and at
all levels. One Unesco expert traveled 24,000 miles in a
five-month period early this year as a school architect,
designing and supervising the construction of classroom
and laboratory buildings and student and faculty resi¬
dences, both for secondary schools and higher education.
Another acts as purchasing agent for all books and school
supplies used throughout the system and supervises the
sale of Unesco Coupons for this purpose. To date more
than $7,000,000 worth of these Coupons have been used
in the Congo. Still other experts are helping the central
and provincial governments reorganize and strengthen
the administrative and financial services of their
ministries of education.
Some of the most exciting work, however, has been that
of Unesco's four mobile teams which travel across the
Congo giving four-week refresher courses to primary school
teachers. These teachers, In contrast to the secondary
school teachers, are almost exclusively Congolese, but the
level of their professional qualifications and general
education is often extremely low.
I met one of these mobile teams, two Frenchmen, a
Frenchwoman and a Haitian, in the steamy river port of
Kindu one day last April. A few days earlier they had
set out from Bukavu, 700 kilometres away, to cross the
parallel ranges of mountains which separate the East
African lakes from the Congo River basin. It took them
three days to make the journey. Their heavily-loaded
Jeep station-wagon had averaged 20 km an hour over
roads that were little more than jungle paths, across
slippery pontoon bridges rocked by churning flood waters,
through swamps where mud choked the axles and water
reached the floorboards.
CONT'D ON PAGE 10
FOCAL POINT for science in the
Congo is the Institute of Scientific
Research in Central Africa. Its
principal installation (below) at
Lwiro on Lake Kivu includes the
best equipment in Africa for
seismological and geomagnetic
measurements as well as extensive
botany and zoology laboratories.
The Institute also serves as a
meeting place for regional and
international scientific congresses.
One such meeting, a seminar on
seismology and geophysics spon¬
sored by Unesco in April 1963,
supplemented its work with visits
to the nearby Niragongo volcano
and the Goma lava fields (right).
Mmm
Photos: Unesco- Unations - Basil Zarov
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
RESEARCH STATION at Uvira
on the shores of Lake Tanganyika
concentrates on hydrobiological
studies. Scientists aboard its
research vessel, the President Paul
Ermens (right) have identified and
classified more than 400 species of
fish in its waters, a fact of major
importance for the diet of Congo¬
lese and Tanganyikans. Other
scientific facilities in the Congo
include a network of more than
100 meteorological observation
stations, linked with the central
bureau at Binza, near Leopoldville
where student forecasters (below),
learn the use of meteorological
equipment. The World Meteorolo¬
gical Organization is organizing this
training of Congolese weathermen.
A. Gille
Unations
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Unesco - Unations - Basil Zarov
LAND OF VAST NA
With 15 million inhabitants scat¬
tered over an area the size of
Western Europe, the Congo (Leo¬
poldville) is one of the largest
and potentially one of the richest
of all African countries. It pos¬
sesses vast untapped sources of
hydro-electric power and some
of the world's greatest mineral
deposits. The mines of Katanga
(right) supply seven per cent of
the world's copper and two-
thirds of its cobalt. The develop¬
ment of a future tourist industry
is possible in the lake district of
CONGO (Cont'd)
One quarter the size of Europe
10
While such journeys are not everyday events for the
mobile teams, they Illustrate the kind of difficulty these
modern day pioneers can expect to meet. They also face
formidable odds in their efforts to improve primary
education in the Congo. As indicated previously, the
quality of both the Instructors and the teaching in many
primary schools is quite low.
Thus, theoretically, French is now the official language
of instruction for all schools in the Congo. In practice,
however, much of primary teaching is still done in the
four major African languages which the Congo uses Lin-
gala, Kikongo, Tshiluba and Swahili.
Then, too, there is the matter of school equipment.
Although some schools in the larger cities are well-
equipped, the average school in the "bush" consists of
four poles and a thatched roof. Very often there are
no tables, chairs, desks or benches, no blackboards, chalk,
notebooks or pencils, few textbooks and no visual aids of
any kind.
In the face of this situation, Unesco's four mobile teams
(plus a fifth which supplies them with audio-visual
materials) can only scratch the surface of what needs to
be done. However, the project which began in October,
1962 on an experimental basis has already proved its
worth.
In Kindu, for example, I talked with Benoit Kayombo,
a primary school inspector, who told me how he had put
into practice a number of ideas he had picked up in an
earlier refresher course in Bukavu. All his teachers now
instruct their pupils in hygiene (one of the points the
team stresses), and he has begun shifting his better
teachers to . the first and second years of school, where
they can do the most good, instead of reserving them for
the upper grades.
As of April, 1963, some 1,702 Congolese teachers had
taken part in courses given by the mobile teams at 14
different places, and at least that many more had to be
turned away and persuaded to wait for later sessions.
Present plans call for the creation eventually of more
teams and more courses, but for longer periods of time and
with fewer participants. It is also hoped that Congolese
experts may soon be associated with the teams and
eventually form teams of their own to continue the
activity.
In addition to improving primary education and expand¬
ing secondary education, Unesco has helped the Congo
create two new Institutes for technical training at the
post-secondary level. These are the Institute of Building
and Public Works in the Leopoldville suburb of Ozone,
and an Institute of Mines all the way across the Congo
in Bukavu.
Both institutes, staffed entirely by Unesco experts, give
intensive practical and theoretical training to a limited
number of students who will become engineering tech¬
nicians, field supervisors or works supervisors in the
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
TURAL RESOURCES
the Congo's eastern border, around
Lake Kivu (left) for example.
Among this region's attractions
are a relatively cool, pleasant, cli¬
mate, volcano-surrounded lakes
and the immense (1,926,600 acres)
Albert National Park (below).
No part of the tropical world has
been the subject of such long,
careful and exhaustive study,
carried out by specialists of fifteen
different nationalities, according
to Unesco's recently published
"Review of the Natural Resources
of the African Continent".
A. Gille Unations
mining and construction industries. Some of them may
also continue their studies at the university level to obtain
degrees as architects or engineers. Many, at least for the
next few years, will be drafted for administrative positions
in the central and provincial governments.
From the relatively modest beginnings in the autumn
of 1960, Unesco's work in the Congo has grown until it
now embraces virtually every problem in the field of
education. Much of these activities would have very
little lasting result, however, if there were not at the same
time efforts to train Congolese experts to assume the
tasks now being performed by foreign specialists in the
central and provincial ministries of education. This has
been done in two ways: first, by In-service training In the
Congo Itself, and secondly by sending Congolese personnel
abroad for special study. Two groups of senior educa¬
tional officials, for Instance, have been sent to Geneva
for nine months of intensive training in a programme
sponsored jointly by Unesco and by the International
Bureau of Education. Their studies at the University of
Geneva and in special seminars were supplemented by
study visits to Swiss, French, Italian and Austrian school
systems.
Unesco's aid to the Congo in the field of education has
been accompanied by assistance In mass communications
and science, as well. During 1963, four experts in radio
and the written press have helped the Congolese govern¬
ment reorganize its ministry of information, drafted sta¬
tutes to govern the operation of the Congo radio and a
national news agency, provided in-service training for
reporters, editors and newscasters, and improved the scope
and effectiveness of educational radio programmes.
In science, the major effort has been the safeguarding
of the Congo's principal scientific research institutions.
One of these in particular, the Institute for Scientific
Research In Central Africa (IRSAC), boasts some of the
finest laboratory equipment In Africa for study of the
earth sciences. Another, the Institute of National Parks
in the Congo (IPNC), Is extremely Important for the
conservation of African wildlife. Unesco has been
Instrumental In securing interim financing for these
institutions from the Congolese and Belgian governments
and from private foundations. At the same time, a
Unesco expert has helped draft a charter for the co¬
ordination of all scientific research in the new nation, and
another to provide for the transition of the institutes from
being Belgian organizations to becoming Congolese ones.
In the autumn of 1963, Unesco's activities in the Congo
probably reached their peak. Nearly 800 foreign teachers,
recruited with Unesco's help, were teaching in Congolese
schools this year. More than 80 experts In education,
science and mass communication are helping the central
and provincial governments of the republic move toward
a better future.
Within the next year or so, It is expected that there
will be a gradual lessening of this type of emergency aid
and a "normalization" of relations between the Congo and
the various specialized agencies of the United Nations
family.
Readers may be interested in a forthcoming booklet, "Unesco
in the Congo", by Garry Fullerton, which tells the story of 11
Unesco's share in the vast United Nations programme of
assistance to the Republic of the Congo.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
STANISLAVSKY
Revolutionary of
the modern theatre
by Grigori Kristi
This year is the centenary of the birth of
Constantin Stanislavsky, Russian actor,
director and theatrical producer, whose
ideas on the teaching and practice of
dramatic art have revolutionized the dev¬
elopment of world theatre. On the follow¬
ing pages " The Unesco Courier "
presents some aspects of the life and
work of this great man of the theatre.
Official Soviet photos
FROM HIS SEARCH for a way to
help actors master their art, Stanis¬
lavsky (left) evolved a system whose
influence has spread from the theatre
to the world of the cinema. One
of Stanislavsky's innovations was the
theatre studio where students and
professional actors too could experi¬
ment, improvise and work out their
art together. America, in particular,
adopted his studio idea and from
the American theatre studios a
whole modern tradition has sprung,
known in America as "The Method."
The now well-known Actors' Studio
in New York is associated with the
names of many talented actors and
actresses of stage and screen, and
these include Géraldine Page, Paul
Newman, Joanne Woodward and
Marlon Brando. Marlon Brando is seen
above in the film "On the Waterfront,"
produced by Elia Kazan, a former
co-director of the Actors' Studio.
Nearly half a century ago, Stanis¬
lavsky wrote : "Modern cinemato¬
graphy actors will teach real actors
how to live. Everything is exposed on
the screen and anything stereotyped
is recorded forever. Here you are
able to see more clearly the difference
between the old and the new art."
!
|
*
-;
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
cONSTANTIN Stanislavsky Is one of the great
_>names In world theatre. The 75 years of his
life were marked by events which brought great changes in
world history. Stanislavsky was born in Moscow in 1863,
soon after the abolition of serfdom in Russia; he lived
through the First World War and the Russian revolution,
and he died in 1938, on the eve of another world war.
Enormous changes took place during these 75 years.
Stanislavsky's art, which echoed the needs of the times,
also underwent constant changes. Its development is
marked by continuous research, fresh attempts and new
achievements.
Constantin Alexeyev (he later adopted the pseudonym of
Stanislavsky), came from a well-to-do family of the
Moscow bourgeoisie, which from the second half of the
19th century played an increasingly important part in the
cultural and social life of Russia. Among members of this
cultivated middle-class, close to his family, were Pavel
Tretiakov, founder of the Museum of Art, Savva Mamon-
tov, patron of the arts and creator of a private opera,
Sabachnikov, the publisher, and Morozov, an industrialist
who gave considerable help towards the building of the
Art Theatre in Moscow.
From the age of 14, young Stanislavsky played on a
family stage. The theatre was a tradition in his large
family and the education he received stimulated his inte¬
rest in the stage. His mother was the daughter of a
French actress, Marie Varley, and his two sisters and
two brothers all later became actors or producers.
In 1888, Stanislavsky became director of a troupe in
Moscow, the "Society of Patrons of Art and Literature."
He played many roles, from vaudeville characters to parts
in the tragedies of Shakespeare and Schiller.
It was at this time that he first tried his hand as a
stage producer and at once attracted the interest of artis¬
tic circles in Moscow. Stanislavsky's productions were
Columbia Pictures - Cahiers du Cinóma
startling for their realism and the new ideas he expressed.
He used novel production methods and had an entirely
new concept of the role of the actor. From the start, he
declared war on old theatrical conventions and outmoded
aesthetic Judgements. To a French critic who accused
him of violating tradition In his production of "Othello,"
Stanislavsky wrote: "Believe me, the work of our gene¬
ration consists in doing away with outdated traditions and
routine. To save art, we must give free rein to imagina¬
tion and creativeness."
In 1898, Stanislavsky, together with the critic and play¬
wright Vladimir Nemirovich-Danchenko, founded the
since famous Moscow Art Theatre. The first play produced
by the Theatre was Alexis Tolstoy's historical tragedy
"Czar Fedor Yoannovlch," but Its real première was the
production of the "Seagull" by Chekhov. In Chekhov, and
later in Gorky, Stanislavsky and Nemirovich-Danchenko
found authors whose work reflected the problems of the
time. Their plays contributed to the rapid growth of the
Art Theatre and determined the course of its development.
To-day, the "Seagull" has become the emblem of the
theatre, which was later named after Gorky.
Stanislavsky was bound to Chekhov by literary and
artistic interests which later developed Into a warm per¬
sonal friendship. Chekhov's plays were fresh and original;
they called for a new treatment. With them was born the
art of stage-craft in Its modern sense, the idea of the play
seen as a whole.
Stanislavsky's Interpretations of Chekhov's and Gorky's
characters have become classics. But the Art Theatre was
also famous for its production of works by contemporary
playwrights from other countries: Hauptmann, Ibsen,
Maeterlinck and others. Almost every new production,
every new role, was in the nature of a discovery. In his 13
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
STANISLAVSKY (Cont'd)
youth, Stanislavsky tried to create a stage impression
close to naturalism, and later he was drawn to symbolism.
But with time he turned to simpler and more expressive
forms, which, he maintained, were best fitted to render on
the stage all the complexities of the human spirit.
After the setting up of the Soviet regime, Stanislavsky
continued his efforts on behalf of realism. The Revo¬
lution had opened the doors of the theatre to a new pro¬
letarian spectator who, as Stanislawsky said, needed
plays "with real human feelings expressed in a simple
and understandable, yet strong and convincing form."...
"In art, as in his food," said Stanislavsky, "he is not
accustomed to piquant delicacies that stimulate appetite."
He did not confine himself to modern plays, but
extended his repertoire to include Russian and foreign
classics, producing works by Ostrovsky, Gogol, Pushkin,
Shakespeare, Moliere, and Beaumarchais.
Nor did his reforms affect only the dramatic stage. In
1922, in his apartment on Leontievsky street, he produced
Tchaikovsky's opera "Eugene Onegin" in an entirely new
setting which broke with all traditional ideas regarding
the lyric theatre. From then on he spent his time between
opera and drama.
On the basis of his own experience on the stage, Stan¬
islavsky tried to define the principles of acting. For
young actors, to whom everything seemed simple and
easy, he listed the qualities necessary for a stage career.
An actor, he said, must be able to observe; he must be
sensitive; have a good memory, fantasy and Imagination
so as to bring his part to life; he must have taste, intelli¬
gence, a sense of rhythm and timing; he must be musical,
sincere, spontaneous, ingenious and know how to control
his emotions; he must be prepared "to follow a hard and
painful path, covered with brambles and thorns, spurning
fame and devoting himself entirely to his craft."
I any years of research, trial and error, led to
the formulation of Stanislavsky's "system"
which subsequently became famous. This "system" is a
collection of methods designed to set the actor on the
right path by encouraging him to make a more or less
"systematic" study of the dual instrument he possesses,
his mind and his body, and of the psycho-physical tech¬
niques of dramatic art which spring from them.
Stanislavsky continually repeated that no technique,
however perfect, could bestow genius. "The theatre," he
wrote, "is the most important of all the chairs of learning,
more Important even, through its influence, than books
and the press... The task I have set myself, to the limit
of my ability, consists in showing to the rising generation
that the actor Is the apostle of beauty and of truth."
But this task was no simple one. He was obliged to
make a stand against dilettantism and stale custom,
against a naturalism that was barren and a formalism
without spirit.
Stanislavsky trained several generations of producers,
of whom two of the best known in Russia are Meyerhold
and Vakhtangov. Many actors and opera singers were
also his pupils or his disciples. A few, like Mikhail Chek¬
hov, Sanin and Boleslavsky continued his teaching In
other European countries and In the United States. Stan¬
islavsky had bonds of friendship with many leading
figures of the Western theatre Gordon Craig, Max Rein¬
hardt, André Antoine, Jacques Copeau who visited Russia
or whom he met while on tour with the Art Theatre com¬
pany abroad.
Today the Influence of this Russian stage producer
continues to make a profound and ever-widening impact
on the development of the theatre in all parts of the
world. Well-known actor-producers like Jean Vilar, of
France, and Eduardo de Filippo, of Italy, have acknow¬
ledged the debt they owe to Stanislavsky and so have
other leading men of the theatre in Great Britain, the
United States, Japan, China, Czechoslovakia, Poland and
many newly- independent countries.
Official Soviet photos
GRIGORI vladimirovich KRISTI is a Soviet producer who teaches
in the school of the Moscow Art Theatre Studio. He was a friend
4 and pupil of Stanislavsky, under whose direction he made his
debuts as an opera producer and as a teacher in the studio of
dramatic art created by Stanislavsky in 1935.
FAMILY TRADITION. Stanislavsky made his
first stage appearance at the age of three in the miniature
theatre at his family's country house in Lioubimovka,
near Moscow (right). By the time he was 14 he was
appearing regularly in plays and entertainments produc¬
ed by his family who had a deep and traditional
interest in the theatre. Stanislavsky's mother was the
daughter of a French actress, Marie Varley, and his
two sisters and two brothers all eventually became
actors or producers. Above, in 1881 at the age of 18,
Stanislavsky plays the part of Megrio in an amateur
dramatic group production of "A Woman's Secret."
The following year he produced his first play.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Y LIFE IN ART
Last pages
of Stanislavsky's
spiritual testament
I am no longer young and my life in art is approaching Its last
act. The time has come to sum up the results and to draw
up a plan of my last endeavour in art. As a stage director and actor I
have worked, on the one hand. In the field of production, and, on the other,
In the actor's sphere of Inward creatlveness.
Having tried In the theatre all the means and methods of creative work;
having paid homage to the enthusiasm for all types of productions along
all the lines of creatlveness costume drama, symbolic, Ideological and
others having learned the production forms of various artistic movements
realistic, naturalistic, futuristic, schematized, exaggeratedly simple
(with statuary, drapes, screens, tulle and all sorts of lighting effects)
I have come to the conclusion that all these things are unable to oiler
the background which the actor needs to display his creatlveness to the
full. And while my studies of scenery and stage design convinced me In
the past of its limitations, I can now say that its possibilities arc indeed
exhausted.
The sole ruler on the stage is the talented actor. But I have never
succeeded In finding for him the scenic background which would not
interfere with, but help his complex artistic work. What is needed Is
a simple background, a simplicity created by a wealth of imagination, not
a lack of It. Unfortunately I have not yet learned how to keep the
simplicity engendered by a rich imagination from being even more
conspicuous than very luxurious theatricality. It attracts more attention
than ordinary scenery, to which our eye Is accustomed. We can only
hope that a great painter will one day solve this, the most difficult of all
scenic problems, by creating a simple yet artistic background for the actor.
The situation in the sphere of inner creatlveness is entirely different.
Here everything Is dependent on talent and intuition, and In the
overwhelming majority of cases pure dilettantism reigns supreme. The
laws of acting have not been established, and many think that they would
be unnecessary and even harmful.
A passionate search for truth
urn m
H B IV
í:.S»w_
There Is a very old belief that the actor needs only talent and Inspiration.
There is another opinion, very widespread In our profession, that the
thing most needed Is technique, though, of course, talent Is also acceptable.
Is it not because such people are afraid of genuine emotion and of living
their part on the stage that they are unable to do so?
Nine-tenths of an actor's work lies in feeling the role spiritually, In living
it. When this is done, the role Is almost ready. It Is senseless to leave
these nine-tenths to mere chance. Let exceptional talents feel and create
their roles at once. Laws are not written for them; It is they who write
them. But astonishingly enough I have never heard them say that
technique is unnecessary and that talent Is the only requirement, or that
technique comes first and talent second. On the contrary, the greater the
actor, the more he is interested In the technique of his art.
This need to acquire experience and skill is particularly apparent in
theatrical art. The tradition of painting is preserved in museums and art
galleries; the tradition of literary art In books; the wealth of musical forms
In scores. But the tradition of stage art lives only in the talent and
ability of the actor. This is the sphere of living tradition. This is a torch
which can be passed only from hand to hand; and not on the stage, but
through instruction, through the revelation of mysteries, on the one hand,
and exercises and stubborn and inspired effort to grasp these mysteries, on
the other.
The main difference between the art of the actor and all other arts Is
that other artists may create whenever they are inspired. The actor,
however, must be the master of his own Inspiration and must know how
to call it forth at the time announced on the theatre's posters. This is
the chief secret of our art. Without this the most perfect technique, the
greatest gifts, are powerless. And this secret, unfortunately, Is most
jealously guarded.
With but few exceptions, the great masters of the stage not only do not
try to disclose this secret to their younger comrades, but keep it behind
an impenetrable curtain. The absence of any tradition in this sense
doomed our art to dilettantism.
Among the thoughts and ideas that have reached us are those of
Shakespeare, Molière, the Rlccobonls (father and son), Lesslng, the great
Schröder, Goethe, Talma, Coquelln, Irving, Salvlnl and other law-makers
in our art. But all these valuable thoughts and counsels have not been
systematized and classified. That is why we still lack the sound principles
which could guide instructors in our art. All that has been written about
CONT'D ON PAGE 17
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
"I am a character actor" said Stahislavsky. His capacity for character¬
ization was, indeed, phenomenal. It was due to his clear and precise
understanding of the character he was playing and because beneath
his mask of make-up he was able, without reserve, to express the feel¬
ings of the person he was portraying handsome or ugly, good or
wicked, ridiculous or exalted. These photographs of Stanislavsky
in six contrasting roles illustrate the wide range of his repertoire.
Below, he appears as Argan in Moliere's 'The Imaginary Invalid".
ACTOR WITH
A HUNDRED FACES
Official Soviet photos
16
"A Month in
the Country"
by Turgenev.
"The Living
Corpse" by
Tolstoy.
"Uncle Vanya"
by Chekov.
"Wit Works
Woe" by Gri-
boyedov.
"Lili," an oper¬
etta by Hervé.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
)
STANISLAVSKY (Cont'd)
the theatre Is either pure philosophy sometimes very Interesting, aptly
describing the desirable goals In art or criticism which applies to the
value or uselessness of what has been achieved.
These works are valuable and necessary, but not for practical uses, for
they say nothing of how final results are to be achieved, or what we should
do with the beginner or with the over-experienced and spoiled actor.
What kind of "solfeggio" exercises does he need? What scale and arpeggio
does an actor require to develop his creative mood and to live his part?
The exercises he needs should be numbered, as problems are numbered
In an arithmetic book and systematically practised in school and at home.
But books and treatises on the theatre say nothing of this. There Is, in
fact, no method handbook. There are only attempts to create one. but
it is either too early to speak of them, or they are not worth speaking about.
It is obvious that there can be no system for producing inspiration,
just as there cannot be a system for playing the violin like a genius or
singing like Challapin. Both have been endowed with the most important
thing a gift from the gods. But there is something, small yet Important,
equally indispensable both to Challapin and the ordinary chorister, since
they both have lungs, a respiratory system, nerves and physical organism
however better developed in one case than In the other which must
produce sound according to laws of nature. The same applies to the
sphere of psychic, creative life, since all actors, without exception, absorb
food for creation according to these laws of nature, retain what they
receive In their intellectual, emotional or muscular memory, digest these
materials in their artistic Imagination, give birth to the Image and life
of the human spirit, and incarnate It according to known, natural laws
that are Incumbent upon all.
Like a prospector in the wilderness
The creative laws that can yield to our consciousness are few. They do
not play a purely honorary role; they have well-defined professional uses.
These laws should be studied by every actor, for it is only with their aid
that he can set In motion his superconsclous whose essence, It seems, will
forever remain a mystery to us. The more talented the actor, the greater
and more enigmatic the mystery and the more he needs the technical
methods accessible to consciousness; It is by these that he penetrates the
Innermost recesses of the superconsclous to call forth Inspiration.
We must try to understand the perspectives, the goal the younger
generation is seeking to attain. It Is very interesting to live and watch
what is going on in the minds and hearts of youth.
But in this new situation I would like to avoid playing two roles. I am
afraid of becoming a young old man who flatters the young, tries to look
their age and share their tastes and convictions, or fawn upon them. Nor
do I want to play the role of the too experienced old man, who has seen
everything, who Is impatient, Irascible, opposed to everything that Is new,
forgetful of the experiments and mistakes of his own youth.
In the last years of my life I would like to continue being what I am
in reality, what I must be according to the laws that have ruled my life
and my work in art. What am I? What do I represent in the new theatre
of today? Can I, as in the past, fully understand all that goes on around
me, all that enthuses youth?
Organically I feel I can no longer understand much In the aspirations
of present-day youth. One must have courage to admit this. You know
from what I have told you how we were educated. Compare our life with
the life of the present generation of youth brought up amidst the dangers
and trials of the Revolution.
We know from our own experience the meaning of a permanent art and
the path outlined for it by nature, and from our own experience we also
know the meaning of fashions in art and their transitory nature. We had a
chance to see how useful It is for a young man temporarily to turn from the
highway leading to a well-defined future on to a side road and to roam
freely along it. It would be dangerous, however, to leave completely the
highway art has followed from time immemorial.
How can I share with the younger generation the results of my
experience and warn them against mistakes that are bred by inexperience?
When I look back on the road of my life in art, I feel like comparing myself
to a gold prospector who first has to roam the wilderness to find a vein of
gold, then wash tons and tons of sand and rock to get a few grains of the
precious metal. And like a prospector, it is not my labours, my quest and
privations, my joys and disappointments that I can bequeath, but only
the few grains of gold that I found . . .
The above text is extracted from the final chapter of Stanislavsky's "My Life in
Art", written in 1925 and translated into English by G. Ivanov-Mumjiev (.Foreign
Languages Publishing House, Moscow). Stanislavsky wrote an earlier and shorter
version while in the U.S.A. in 1924 and that edition, published by Little, Brown
and Co., is the one known to most English-speaking readers. The Moscow trans¬
lation was published over a quarter of a century later. Another important work
by Stanislavsky, "An Actor Prepares", has been published in the U.S.A. by Theatre
Arts Inc. The publication of the "Works of Stanislavsky" in eight volumes is now 17
¿n progress in the U.S.SJI. under the supervision of the Soviet Academy of
Science Press.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
STANISLAVSKY (Cont'd)
Official Soviet photos
" All the work of the Russian actors at the Moscow Art Theatre is admirable," wrote Gordon
Craig, the English actor, stage designer and producer, in 1 908. Whether they are dealing with
an episode of modern life or a fairy story, they display a sure, discriminating and masterly skill."
Above, members of the Moscow Art Theatre listening to Chekov reading from his work, " The
Seagull" in 1898. This was the new theatre's first important success and to this day it carries
a seagull painted on its curtain in memory of its debt to Chekov. Stanislavsky and his actress
wife, Lilina, are seated on either side of Chekov. Standing, far left, is Vladimir Nemirovich
Danchenko, playwright and joint founder, with Stanislavsky, of the Moscow Art Theatre. Far
right, seated, is Vsevolod- Meyerhold, theatrical producer and one of Stanislavsky's disciples.
Right, a page from Stanislavsky's Notebooks, with a sketch and working notes for "The Seagull. "
ACTOR-
PRODUCER
AT
WORK
A<U 'lA zto
I }Tl4lA4 lO^^L+lJ) 1AJ.IA x. t.
U.OU4 xfi.Mj^t'L-tA^
Mm it 3,ij w,tu yifvo
dé
\ lui.j. < <y>..x'j-<¿
HjUL.jí.iyO í^tAl.
¡ " *i e*""t *'
OfCjZ-r.t.jPpC.^.Ç/
Àce tJ-A~4Al*-*.M
. '< :> it /tiC-t.L , t /-itfv_ (S/,..
' ! LL.L'.Lû-i3AiAjûi	iA/.
</uA
\ :
	, J
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
I » ilifl
«K ¡3h
í^V^rs
Vh4 -
" Si - M *
^^^¿ * yj ^A^H
Stanislavsky did not believe
that acting, the kind worthy
of being called an art,
could be left to chance.
The perfection he sought
in acting and in theatrical
production was attained
at the price of repeated
effort, careful reflection and
a scrupulous attention to
details. "There are no
small parts," he once said,
"only small actors." Above,
a scene from Molière's
"Tartuffe," a production
undertaken by Stanislavsky
shortly before his death
on August 7, 1938, but
only presented the follow¬
ing year. Right, in "The
Lower Depths" by Maxim
Gorky (1912), Stanislavsky
(centre) plays the part of
a tramp. While preparing
this play, he and other
members of the cast visited
the place in Moscow where
tramps congregated, to see
exactly how they lived.
The doss-house scenes in
this play created a new
standard in realism for the
theatre of that time. Left,
a scene from "The Govern¬
ment Inspector" by Gogol.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
LEAVES FROM STANISLAVSKY'S NOTE
Throughout his life, Stanislavsky jotted down in his note¬
books comments on everyday occurrences as well as his
professional observations and reflections. There are over
100 of these notebooks in the literary archives of Stanis¬
lavsky, now kept in the museum of the Moscow Art
Theatre. Many of the notes, a short selection of which is
published here, appear in more developed form in the
eight-volume collection of his works.
1899-1911
When you play an evil man look for his
good points.
Intuition Is not an ideal guide for every
actor. For instance, when I forget myself
I act badly: I talk too much, I make mean¬
ingless gestures, my voice squeaks, I grim¬
ace and make a hash of everything.
People go to the theatre to be enter¬
tained, but leave it either enriched with
knowledge or with their problems solved;
with questions put into their minds which
they will try to elucidate, or with their eyes
opened to something that happens every
day, but that only a genius has noticed
(In Gogol's The Inspector General, for
example).
So long as an actor is striving towards
an ideal he is an artist; but when that ideal
has been reached' he becomes an artisan.
In order to express silence there has to
be some sort of noise. In order to express
the idea of the emptiness of a street a few
extras have to walk along it. In order
to express gaiety you must show .dullness.
All these moods depend on their relations
to their opposites.
If the producer lacks the sensitivity and
imagination to add even an insignificant
detail that is not shown or that has been
omitted by the author, but which follows
the author's intentions, then he is unworthy
of his calling. Even when working on the
great Shakespeare the producer must invent
details to interpret the author's idea and
convey it more successfully or to help an
insufficiently gifted actor to communicate
the author's thought... for it is impossible
for the author to foresee every chance
element in the complex life of the stage.
I am reproached with underestimating the
importance of the actor and enhancing too
much the role of the author. That is not
so. On the contrary, I extol the importance
of the actor, making him a collaborator with
the author. That is a far more honourable
role than the one actors choose for
themselves when they try to use other
people's creations in order to display
themselves. It is far more honourable, for
example, to collaborate with Shakespeare
than to exploit him.
Critics and public of narrow views who
fail to understand the breadth of a work
of art are frightened by novelty of any
sort; they are afraid of being confused.
They surround art with a mass of rules
and conventions without which they them¬
selves cannot exist.
1912-1918
This morning, December 16, 1912, ex¬
hausted after the performance of "Uncle
Vanya" I felt so reluctant to give last night.
At first it was agony. But the audience
listened so- attentively that it forced me to
act and by the middle of Act One I found
myself under the influence of the excellent
atmosphere reigning in the hall, and played
with pleasure as if in a new and well-master¬
ed part. One has to admit that the audi¬
ence is the third creator of a performance!
Theoreticians butt their heads against
theory and see nothing on the other side
of that wall.
Academicism has no failings, only virtues,
and for that reason it is dead, dry and
lifeless.
An actor's playing is the fulfilment of a
number of creative ends corresponding
to' the author's intentions, and these ends
are only achieved by truly living the part.
Find tasks,
acting.
not by reasoning but by
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
BOOKS
Sentimentality is bearable up to the point
when it rouses your feeling for creative
work and warms your heart; but the moment
it begins to crowd out feeling, substituting,
sloppy lyricism for real transports of love,
it is bad.
When I am in the auditorium I understand
everything, just what I have to do and
how. I go on stage and at once I become
an idiot who doesn't understand the sim¬
plest thing about feelings and inter-relations.
.To understand, to remember and to feel
these are different domains.
Don't analyse intonation but the emotion
that gave birth to it.
Now it is clear that the crisis of the
theatre of representation and entertainment,
the theatre of spectacle, has already begun
and is inevitable. In terms of outward
effects, in a purely professional sense,
cinematography has defeated the theatre.
Decoration, in the sense of naturalness
(and stylization too), crowd lighting, pro¬
cessions, scenes of everyday life, thun¬
derstorms, wind these are incomparable
in cinematography. In a matter of a few
years there will be sound cinematography
too. Besides, in cinematography those
emotions which are felt by the actor at an
early stage, when the role is fresh, before
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE In 1918 Stanislavsky undertook to improve the dramatic sido
of the Moscow Bolshoi Theatre's operatic productions, rio
set up an Opera Studio which functioned at his homo for
the next seven years. Above, Stanislavsky (seated) with tho
Russian bass, Chaliapin (on left). The portrait is of Anna Pavlova.
During his tours in Europe and the
U.S.A., Stanislavsky was given a
warm welcome and hailed as the
great renovator of dramatic art.
Right, in New York in 1921, he
visits the Paramount Studios during
the filming of "Monsieur Beau-
caire" and meets a star of the
silent screen, Rudolph Valentino
(standing beside Stanislavsky).
The actresses seated on the right
are Bebe Daniels and Lois Wilson.
Far left, Stanislavsky meets Marion
Anderson, the singer, and, left,
dines with George Bernard Shaw.
Official Soviet photos
1
* i ^i
III Vm
¥ ' - Av-*Jni
f i^HH"
à À
UT.>.'
r V
r H¿i
f *
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
TNP-Agnès Varda
A WORLD-WIDE INFLUENCE. Stanislavsky lived to see his ideas adopted in theatres far
from those of his own country. "And his influence is far from spent," writes Jean Vilar, the
French theatrical producer. "The many thousands who flock to theatres each evening in
New York or Moscow, Rome or Paris, London or Berlin, are unaware that much they find to
admire, from the individual play of the actor to the composition and disposition of groups on
the stage, comes from the teaching of Stanislavsky." Above, Jean Vilar (foreground) in a
production of Balzac's "Le Faiseur" presented at the "Theatre National Populaire" in Paris.
Stanislavsky's notebooks <c°f<D
22
his feelings have grown stale and stereo¬
typed, can be repeated again and again.
The actors are constantly seeing themselves
and their work and this gives them a chance
of perfecting themselves...
Shakespeare is so boundless that each
of his works requires its special form of
production.
1. The Tempest stage it as a mystery-
play (god, people, monkey forebears). In
front a chorus (orchestra unnecessary,
chorus of voices without words, with closed
lips).
2. Julius Caesar, Corialanus should be
read as speeches in parliament.
3. The Merchant of Venice Find a fairy¬
tale form. Against a gold background and
a dirty wall.
4. King Lear Against black drapes
where Lear's sufferings are terrible, against
rich tapestry where he is in his glory,
against white where Cornelia is pure,
against red where the evil daughters express
their true selves.
Actors are superstitious because they
place themselves in direct dependence on
chance inspiration.
...Picture of a new theatre, with a mu¬
seum back stage, music, lectures, etc. In
the new theatre the orchestra ought not to
be in the house as now, but in the wings.
Words should become a means, not an
end.
You can imagine, see or hear in your
mind how you or some imaginary person
would act or speak at a given moment in
studying a certain role. These pictures
evoked within himself allow an actor to
copy the thing imagined. In other words,
this way leads to an imitation, a portrayal
of a role. But you can approach a role
in a different way, by putting yourself in
the place and situation of a character. You
can feel your fellow actor at your side, like
the very soul of the character he portrays;
you can then set out to influence, to a greater
or lesser degree, this living soul of the
character your partner is playing. Only
then do you begin to fulfil your task, when
you begin to act instinctively, according
to your experience of life. That is the
path to living one's role, to creative acting.
Actors are always concerned about "how"
they should play, not "what".
Producers make a grave mistake when
they impose their feelings and their own
conception of a role on the actor. That is
to use force. The function of a producer
is something else. He ought above all to
understand the inclinations of the actor,
the designer and all those -who take part
in the performance. He must take from
them all the spiritual creative material they
can offer and then consider what use can
be made of it and how this is to be done.
If he imposes his own feelings he will not
obtain a vital, living substance from his
actors, and out of dead material will come
a dead work.
If a critic has talent he can be a friend
to the actor and help him in his work and
also as an intermediary who explains to
the audience what is good in the actor.
A critic who lacks talent does great harm
even when he praises an actor.
Nothing repeats itself in life. There are
no two persons, thoughts or feelings alike.
The feelings an actor experiences on the
stage to-day are not repeatable to-morrow.
That is why emotion itself can never be
fixed; it has to come afresh.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
ONE LANGUAGE
FOR THE WORLD?
by Mario Pei
u niversality was implicit in the ancient world
of the Romans and in the mediaeval world
that followed it. The language of Rome, which had
served the universal Roman Empire and the universal
Christian Church, continued to be the common language
of western scholarship until the dawn of the Renaissance.
But modern progress, the invention of printing, and the
spreading of literacy to upper and middle classes that had
been largely illiterate in the past, coupled with the
beginnings of the modern national states, brought the
spoken vernaculars of the masses to the fore. The fif¬
teenth century witnessed the final triumph of the national
languages over the Latin that had dominated the
thousand-year period since the fall of Roman Empire
natural, national languages be used, singly or in combi¬
nation, in straight or modified form, for international
purposes.
But the proposal advanced in 1629 by the French philo¬
sopher Descartes was of a radically different nature.
Answering a letter written him by a Father Merscnne,
who had enclosed in his missive an anonymous Latin
prospectus concerning the desirability of an International
language, the great philosopher presented his own views
on the subject.
Beginning with an attack on the difficulties of national
grammars, which prevent people from seizing the meaning
of a passage by referring to the dictionary alone, Des¬
cartes goes on to advocate the creation of a tongue whose
LEBTOREONFO PEETOFOSENSEN
PIFTOFOSENSEN =
Honour thy father and thy mother
of the West, and Europe assumed its modern linguistic
aspect, With an array of national tongues, both literary
and official.
It is therefore not to be wondered at that many minds
began to turn to the problem of a single language that
would serve for the new and numerous cultural exchanges
that were being established. Latin no longer sufficed.
In the thirteenth century, the traveling scholar would
care to communicate only with his peers, and they all
knew Latin. In the seventeenth, his desire was for oral
communication with all sorts people: merchants and
sailors and soldiers and nobles and perhaps even peasants,
and they knew no Latin. The vernaculars were not
merely too numerous ; they were too much broken up into
local dialects.
Yet Comenius, a seventeenth-century educator with an
international background, came out with the startling
proposal that the leading languages of eastern and
western Europe be used in international fashion, with
Russian serving the east and French and English the
west.
These proposals have been repeated, in one fashion or
another, from that day to the present. The Monde Bilin¬
gue movement, the zonal languages of Stalin, the advo¬
cacy of English in normal, Basic, or revised-spelling form,
are only three of the many suggestions that existing,
grammar will be so simple that it can be learned without
effort by anyone, by reason of Its absolute regularity and
logic.
Along with this, he proposes a word-coining system
whereby there will be, among the ideas of the human
mind, the same order that prevails among numbers in
mathematics, so that Just as there is In mathematics a
logical progression from the known to the unknown, the
same process may be possible with words. If thLs Is done,
he concludes, peasants will be able to determine truth in
better fashion than do philosophers at present.
What Descartes advocates, though he gives no example
of it, is a constructed language of the a priori or philoso¬
phical type, whose grammar will depart from known
grammars to the extent that it will be regular and
without exceptions, and whose word-stock will not be
haphazard, but logically connected. Such a language,
based on the analogy of mathematical operations, is per¬
fectly possible, but does not coincide with the structure
of any known tongue.
Descartes supplied no sample of his ideal international
language, but such samples were immediately forthcoming
from several of his contemporaries, Dalgarno, "Urquhart,
Wilklns, Leibniz. Cave Beck, in 1657, offered an ingenious
system based on combinations of letters and numbers to
CONT'D ON PAGE 28
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Alio! Hallo!... Communicati
The drawings on these pages, made especially for The Unesco
Courier by Ion Popesco-Gopo, a leading Rumanian artist-
producer of animated cartoons, offer readers a brief preview of
Gopo's humorous little film, "Allol-Hallo! : Communications in a
Nutshell." "Allol-Hallo!" is a history in miniature of man learning
to communicate with man. Homo sapiens, the little character
shown in these drawings, progresses sometimes by accident,
but always by using his brain from smoke signals, graffiti and
hieroglyphics to telephones, radio and international TV by satellite
relay. Gopo ends his story with a forward-looking peep at the
interplanetary communication of tomorrow. "Allol-Hallo!" was
made for Unesco by Bucarest Studios and was produced in col¬
laboration with the Rumanian National Commission for Unesco.
Unesco photos
24
ION POPESCO-GOPO.seen
here at work on "Allol-
Hallol" in the film studios
at Buftea, near Bucarest,
is a former newspaper car¬
toonist who found his real
vocation in animated car¬
toons. Since 1950 his
films have won numerous
Festival awards (Edinburgh,
Cannes, Tours, Karlovy-
Vary, San Francisco). Last
year he decided to try his
hand at a feature-length
cartoon and took as his
theme the need to use
atomic energy exclusively
for peaceful purposes. He
is now working on another
full-length cartoon, enti¬
tled "Steps on the Moon."
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
ns in a Nutshell
/V
221
§8
&>
«|
©
fll »
'
p
a oo o
ft 1
ft
s\. u T
BJL1 "ViB 1
/ tcSE^»jP^
(^p¿i****
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
(Cont'd from page 23)
ONE LANGUAGE
FOR THE WORLD?
be used in writing, while the numbers would be replaced
by sounds In actual speech.
"Honour thy father and thy mother" would appear in
Beck's written system as "leb2314 p2477 pf2477," which
would be read lebtoreonfo peetofosensen piftofosensen
(each numeral stands for a spoken syllable) It is perhaps
obvious why this system did not take hold. The strain
imposed on the memory is tremendous.
Since the days of Descartes, Leibniz and Beck, it Is
estimated that at least six hundred different proposals
have been advanced for the solution of the world's lin¬
guistic troubles. Their chronological sequence has inte¬
resting features. Once we are past the seventeenth cen¬
tury, popular interest seems to flag. Between 1800 and
1850, only four important projects appear, but one of
them is Sudre's famous Solresol, based on the notes of
the scale. This attracted enormous attention, was later
sponsored by such people as Victor Hugo, Lamartine,
Humboldt and Napoleon III, and had at one point a
considerable body of speakers, with die-hard followers as
late as 1900.
Statistically, combinations of the syllables do, re, ml
fa, sol, la, si yield seven words of one syllable, 49 of two,
336 of three, 2,268 of four, 9,072 of five. Shifts of accent
from one syllable to another then yield the possibility of
changing the function of a word from noun to verb or
adjective or adverb. The language could be sung or
played or hummed instead of spoken; it could be written
as music; knocks, or even colors, could be substituted foj
the syllables for distant communication. A phrase like
"I don't love" is dore do milasi.
That the constructed language of the a priori type,
having no connexion with existing languages, has not
fully died out is proved by two interesting twentieth-
century samples, both of American origin. One is Foster's
Ro of 1912, in which the first part of the Lord's Prayer
runs: Abze radap av el in suda, ace rokab eco sugem; ace
to leave the vocabulary alone and change the gramma¬
tical structure. In 1903, Peano presented a system called
Latino Sine Flexione (Flexionless Latin), in which the
endings of Latin are dropped or merged: Studio theorico
proba que es necessario nulla regula de grammatica, nullo
suffixo de derivatione (A theoretical study proves that no
grammatical rule, no derivational suffix, is necessary).
Language blends run all the way from barely disguised
modifications of Latin and Romance to systems that pro¬
pose to give what amounts to proportional representation
to all of the world's great language families. The original
idea, that arose in the middle of the eighteenth century
and replaced the earlier striving for "logic" in language,
was that of "the greatest ease for the greatest number."
But since, at the time when this principle was enunciated,
"the greatest number" referred only to speakers of
western-type languages, many of these blends, even today,
resolve themselves into combinations of Latin, Greek,
Romance, occasionally Germanic, still more seldom Slavic,
with little or no attention paid to the vast numbers of
speakers of other types of tongues.
The first a posteriori language to meet with favour was
Schleyer's Volapuk of 1885, a tongue which blends Latin-
Romance, English and German elements. "I don't want
the book, but a book" is in Volapuk No vilob eli buki, sod
uni buki.'
By 1890, the vogue of Volapuk had come to a standstill,
and Zamenhof's Esperanto assumed international im¬
portance. Here, too, we have a predominance of Classical,
Romance and Germanic elements, with other languages,
including the Slavic, largely left out of the running (this
is surprising, since Zamenhof was a Pole)*.
The popularity of Esperanto continues to the present
day, and it is estimated that eight million people through¬
out the world speak it in one fashion or another. But
the popularity of Esperanto seems to have had the effect
of encouraging rather than discouraging further attempts.
NO VILOB ELI BUKI,
SOD UNI BUKI =
/ don't want the book, but a book
26
rajda ec hep: ace va .eco uz in suda asi in buba. The
other Is Russell's Suma of 1957, in which the beginning of
the First Book of Genesis runs: talo moti sima baki boto
e beto e beto te peka e ena gide e ena doba.
Far more numerous and varied are the languages of
the a posteriori type, based on one or more existing natu¬
ral languages. Here a distinction must be made between
modifications of single existing tongues and language
blends of various kinds.
Typical of the modified natural language is Basic
English, which is ordinary English restricted as to voca¬
bulary, so that "participate" has to be rendered as "take
part", and "selfish" paraphrased into "without thought
of others." The claim (not altogether substantiated) is
that with 850 English words at our disposal we can cover
the entire vast range of human language needs.
Basic English does not interfere with normal English
sounds or grammar; but other modified languages prefer
In the course of the present century, well over 400 cons¬
tructed languages have been offered to the world.
Most of them are of the same basic type as Esperanto,
with a grammar that is more or less arbitrary and a
vocabulary drawn from the western languages. This is
true even of languages constructed by some of the world's
great linguists (de Saussure and Jespersen, to cite only
two names).
On the other hand, some very ingenious schemes have
been advanced to give some measure of representation to
other major language groups. Cheshikhin's Nepo of 1910,
for instance, adds Slavic to the Latin-Romance-Germanic
combination (Vatero nia, kotoryja estas in la njeboo,
heiliga estu nomo via is the beginning of the Lord's Prayer
* For an article on Zamenhof, the Father of Esperanto,
see The Unesco Courier, December, 1959.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
in Nepo). Hogben's Interglossa of 1943 presents a Graeco-
Latin vocabulary, but with a Chinese word-order (.Na
Parenta in Urani; Na dicte voló; tu Nomino gene revero).
Steiner's Pasilingua oí 1885 makes provision for syno¬
nyms from Latin-Romance and Germanic: "good" may
be either bono or guto; "God" Is Deo or Gotto; "often" is
saepe or oftis. Fred Mill's Anti-Volapük of 1893 goes even
further, combining international connecting words, taken
largely from Latin-Romance, with nouns and verbs of the
speaker's own language, with the proviso, presumably,
that each speaker will learn enough of the other speaker's
nouns and verbs to be at least able to understand them.
Thus, the sentence "I think he is in the street" would
come out in the following English, French, Italian, Spanish
and Russian versions:
a western European blend to the exclusion of other lan¬
guage groups, which In the modern world are acquiring
an ever-growing Importance.
The corresponding disadvantage, to which many lin¬
guists object, Is that the constructed language, not having
grown from the soil, is not the bearer of cultural values.
For a language that is meant to be, at the outset, a
vehicle of material communication rather than an instru¬
ment of cultural Imperialism, this is not a disadvantage,
but the opposite.
History teaches us that cultures grow around languages
which were originally rough, crude, material tools of
communication. If a world culture grows In similar
manner around a world language, that will be all to the
good. At any rate, Esperanto, with Its numerous original
WO-TI ÑAMA MATA-HARI;
WO MIRU PER NI-TI FENESTRA ==
/ am called the sun; I look into your window
"Io think ke le es in le street."
"Io croire ke le es in le rue."
"Io credere ke le es in le strada."
"lo creer ke le es in le calle."
"Io dumat' ke le es in le ulitsa."
Most comprehensive among proposals designed to give
representation to all major language groups is the recent
one of Leidenfrost that a Universal Grammar and Voca¬
bulary be constructed by a commission of language specia¬
lists on the basis of a blend of ten representative lan¬
guages: Iraqi Arabic, Mandarin Chinese, English, Hin¬
dustani, Hungarian, Indonesian, the Kpelle of Liberia,
Russian, Spanish and Swahili. This still leaves out two
major language groups, the Japanese-Korean and the
Dravidian of southern India, both of which have well over
100 million speakers.
The dangers of these too extensive blends are pointed
out by Dr. Gode of Interlingua, a language constructed by
a team of language experts on the customary basis of a
combination of Western tongues. In Interlingua as it is,
he offers the following passage: "Le sol dice: 'Io me
appella sol. Io es multo brillante. Io me leva al est, e
quando io me leva, il es die. Io reguarda per tu fenestra
con mi oculo brillante como le auro, e io te dice quando
il es tempore a lever te'."
Now he shifts to an intercontinental version that
includes Chinese, Japanese, Indonesian and other Orien¬
tal tongues: "Mata-hari yu: 'Wo-ti noma mata-hari. Wo
taihen brillante. Wo leva wo a est, dan toki wo leva wo,
ada hari. Wo miru per ni-ti fenestra sama wo-ti mata
brillante como kin, dan wo yu ni toli ada tempo a levar
ni'." His points are that no westerner will even begin to
understand the second version without very special study,
and (perhaps even more important), that the Indonesian
speaker, who supplied mata-hari, will not understand the
Chinese wo-ti, ni and yu, or the Japanese taihen.
One final word may be added, in connexion with the
desirability (or lack thereof) of a constructed tongue vis-
à-vis a national language adopted for international use.
One of the great advantages postulated by the proponents
of constructed languages is their internationality or neu¬
trality, the fact that no nation need object to them on
the ground that they are vehicles and standard-bearers
of alien cultures.
This is quite true of the a priori languages, which are
based on no known tongue. It is far from true of the
majority of a posteriori languages, which definitely reflect
works, both in prose and in verse, shows us that a con¬
structed language, once It is In use, is perfectly capable of
creating its own cultural values.
Two considerations of a highly practical nature offer
themselves. National languages, big or small, seldom have
a system of perfect phonetic notation. This Is particularly
true of languages of century-old civilizations, such as
French and English, where the time-lag between the nor¬
mal evolution of speech and the bringing up to- date of
the spelling has worked to deepen the separation between
speech and writing.
Constructed languages, on the other hand, are normally
completely phonetized, with absolute sound-ior-symbol
correspondence (Esperanto Is a good example). This
means that any national language selected for Interna¬
tional use would have to go through a process of spelling
reform, at least for international purposes, before it could
be properly put into operation, while a constructed lan¬
guage could go Into operation at once, without further
study or change.
Even more important Is the fact that national langua¬
ges normally show deep dialectal divisions, with frequent
uncertainly as to a standard form. This is particularly
true of English and Spanish, somewhat less true of
French and Russian, where a "correct" standard exists,
whether or not it is followed by all the speakers. But the
constructed language Is normally fully standardized, and
the only problem is to keep it that way once it goes into
operation.
These two characteristics of constructed languages, pho-
netizatlon and standardization, are perhaps of greater
importance than a "neutrality" which seldom appears,
and which can in no case be made altogether perfect.
They are, in the opinion of this writer, of sufficient Impor¬
tance to warrant serious consideration of a constructed
language for international use along with the numerous
national tongues, old and new, that are offered for
candidacy.
Mario peí, an American linguist, is Professor of Romance
Philology at Columbia University, New York. He is the
author of "The Story of English", recently published by
Fawcett World Library in the United States. Readers will
find a more ample development of the ideas contained in
the above article in Mario Pei's book, "One Language for 27
the World", published by Devin-Adair Co., 23 East 26
Street, New York 10, N.Y. U.S.A.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Homework, by the French
artist, Jean Commère, de¬
picts children at home busy
with their work and games.
UNICEF
GREETING
CARDS
LAST year the United Nations Children's Fund (UNICEF)
sold 26 million greeting cards the proceeds of
which were used to pay for milk, vaccines and other
disease-preventing measures for millions of children
Each box of UNICEF cards sold can provide a daily
glass of milk for one week for 45 children or enough
vaccine to protect 60 children from tuberculosis. Each
year artists from different lands donate drawings and
paintings to help the Fund. The 18 cards on sale this
year were designed by 11 artists. Some of the designs
they contributed are reproduced here. Others have
been made by Gordon McCoun, a "Sunday painter"
of U.S. nationality, now living in Peru; by Otto Nielsen,
a Danish artist; and by Jeanyee Wong, a U.S. artist of
Chinese ancestry. UNICEF cards come in boxes of ten,
priced at 7/6 (U.K.); $1.25 (U.S.) and 6F. (France)
per box. Write to addresses listed below for a
free, illustrated, full-colour brochure giving full details.
Starlight, by Adolf Oehlen
of the German Federal Re¬
public. This card is printed
on airmail paper.
The Family, a painting
by British sculptor Henry
Moore. Chosen as the
official United Nations card,
it has been issued in a
special large-format series.
28
For further information, orders
etc., write: UNICEF G.C.F., 13,
Heddon St., London W.I., G.B.:
National UNICEF Committee,
280 Bloor St. West, Toronto 5,
Ont., Canada (Attention Mrs.
G. Richards) ; U.S. Committee
for UNICEF, P.O. Box 22, Church
Street Station, New York 8,
N.Y. (Att. Miss Olga Gechas) or
UNICEF, Fonds des Cartes de
V24, rue Borghèse, Neuilly-
sur-Seine, France.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Marketplace, one of two
designs by Lena Stöckli of
Switzerland, illustrating her
impressions of Peru.
Reindeer Fantasy, a de¬
sign by Ruben Freidwall,
who was born in the
"reindeer country" of north¬
ern Sweden.
Magic Carpet is one of
five designs by British artist
Edward Ardizzone on the
theme of children's dreams
around the world.
Candy Floss, one of two
gay designs by Aida Marini,
of Lebanon.
Clown, one of two paint¬
ings donated by Karel Svo-
linsky of Czechoslovakia.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
MONG the many civilizations whose remains are
^scattered through the New World few have so
Intrigued archaeologists as that which once flourished on
the island of Marajo at the mouth of the Amazon. We do
not know who were its artisans; it was the work of men
who had vanished before Europeans landed on the coast
of Brazil.
The existence of this centre of civilization in so unex¬
pected a place had already inspired the most venturesome
theories In the 19th century. What, indeed, has not
been written on the subject? Egyptians, Phoenicians and
even Vikings were all named in turn to explain the con¬
trast between these remains of a people which had
reached a relatively advanced level of civilization and the
wretchedness of the local physical and human environ¬
ment. There was something paradoxical in the fact that
an art which was both original and refined should be
found in a part of the continent which one might imagine
had always been the stronghold of barbaric tribes.
Moreover, there was nothing about this alluvial land
below the Equator to favour its development as an artistic
centre. Depending on the season, the large island is
turned into lakes and swamps or into dusty plains. When
the streams are in spate, natural or artificial hills emerge
here and there from the water and provide a refuge for
men and animals. These are conditions barely suited to
primitive groups engaged in rudimentary farming com¬
bined 'with fishing and hunting. Such, indeed, was the
way of life of the tribes which the Portuguese found there
in the 17th century and which they promptly set about
exterminating.
Yet part of the island was once occupied by a seden¬
tary people who knew how to make the best use of their
land. Their villages were built on slopes which today are
littered with shards of pottery. Their burial-grounds are
also filled with pottery fragments and objects made of
clay, and from these we have able to reconstruct in part
the culture of a people whose very name Is unknown.
The "Marajoaras," as we may call them for con
venience, certainly possessed relatively complex social and
political structures : the works they carried out mark them
as a disciplined people governed by chiefs or by an aristo¬
cracy. It would be difficult to explain how they built arti¬
ficial hills 25 feet high, some 400 feet long and 130 feet
wide unless there were some common determination and
leadership. Isolated communities like those of the pres¬
ent-day Indians could never have achieved such a feat.
That the ancient Marajo society had a hierarchic char¬
acter may be inferred from the lavishness of certain
tombs which archaeologists have uncovered in the burial-
grounds side-by-side with more modest graves.
The island of Marajo contains only a small quantity of
An island as large as
Denmark, Marajo stands
between the Amazon and
Para rivers, almost touch¬
ing the Equator. One of
the most important regions
for cattle raising in all
northern Brazil, its herds
number well over 600,000
head. Its ranchers are
skilled riders, using horses
and also the saddle oxen
(left) which offer greater
security as mounts in
periods of heavy rains that
transform the flat coun¬
tryside into lakes and
swamps. The Marajo cow¬
boy rides barefoot and,
only placing his big toe
in the stirrup can dismount
with speed and agility.
© Marcel Gautherot,
Rio de Janeiro
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
THE UNSOLVED
MYSTERY
OF MARAJO
by Alfred Metraux
rock. Thus, ceramics are almost the sole relics left by this
mysterious people. Like the Sumenans and the Babylo¬
nians, they delighted in making clay versions of many
objects whose prototypes were normally fashioned of some
other material. For example, terra cotta cylinders seem
to have been used as ornaments for the lips and ears.
Terra cotta seats have been found which are identical in
form with those which the Indians carve from wooden
logs. Finally, excavations have turned up great numbers
of triangular plates, slightly convex and perforated at the
ends. Their shape, the signs of wear they show and their
proximity to female skeletons have led to their being
identified as a tanga, or slip. They bear some resemblance
to those triangular pieces of bark which are the sole
garment worn by the women of certain tribes of the
Amazon.
All we know of the religious beliefs of this people are
their funeral rites. They either cremated the dead or
preserved their bones in urns. Statuettes of crouching
women have been found in the tombs and may have some
ritual significance. The style of Marajo pottery is essen¬
tially geometric and is also distinguished by the use of
various decorative techniques modelling, Champlevé ena¬
mel and painting. Certain vases are decorated with
reliefs showing men and animals. There are burial urns
on which paintings and reliefs embody the rough image
of human beings whose eyes are often marked with an
oblique stroke which gives a sad expression to the face
as though the artist had sought to suggest mourning and
ATLANTIC OCEAN
Island of Marajo
grief. Only actual Illustrations give a proper Idea of the
richness and varied arrangements of the motifs they used.
What is known of the origins of this civilization?
Scholars have sought in vain for any reference to this
mysterious people in the old chronicles and documents
dealing with the exploration and conquest of the Amazon.
None of them has anything to say on the subject. The
mystery would therefore have remained absolute had It
not been for the work of two American ethnographers,
Clifford Evans and Betty Meggers.
Despite all the obstacles with which the bush and the
swamps confronted them, they carried out a scries of
excavations in the island of Marajo. They were able to
establish that the civilization of the "Marajoaras" had
been preceded by three other archaeological phases of
a much more primitive kind, the first comprising a people
of hunters and fishermen. There is no link whatever
between these ancient phases (which In many respects are
little different from those of today's Amazon Indians)
and the most culturally advanced one.
I ne day, which the two archaeologists place In
the Xllth century, a mysterious people
emerged at the mouth of the Amazon, bringing with
them an artistic tradition which was already fully formed.
The Invaders established themselves In the plains of the
large island and lived in villages built on the heights of
artificial hills.
Far from prospering In their new home, they gradually
declined. The pottery on the mast recent sites is less
finished and less beautiful than in the older deposits. The
objects connected with burials grow poorer and more uni¬
form, which suggests that with the general decadence
there came a levelling out of the social classes.
Finally, at a period which was probably not long before
the discovery of America, the Marajo civilization came to
an end as if those who had created it were no longer capa¬
ble of preserving it. The people seem to have succumbed
to forces the nature of which is still wrapped in mystery,
since excavations have revealed no trace whatever of wars
or invasions.
The Marajo civilization Is therefore a late one. It was
Introduced already formed by emigrants who, cut off from
their original home, were unable to develop or even to
preserve it. Once these facts were established It then
remained to discover the birthplace of the unknown ~.
people who settled on the edge of the Atlantic.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
MARAJO (Cont'd)
3000-mile migration
along the Amazon
Comparative studies which it would take too long to
describe here convinced Evans and Meggers that their
research should be directed towards the Andean region
and more especially in Colombia. Scattered finds along
the Amazon seemed to mark the route followed by the
"Marajoaras" and it was in the hope of finding fresh
traces of this migration that they recently carried out
excavations on the banks of the Rio Napo, one of the tri¬
butaries of the Amazon, which has always been a means
of access from the Andes to the Amazonas.
he eleven archaeological sites which they
explored fully confirmed the theory which
had led them there. The ancestors of the "Marajo peo¬
ple" had travelled down the Napo and had stayed there
for sometime. The pottery which was discovered there
was frequently identical with that of the Marajo. The
Napo had therefore been one of the stages in the
migration which started in Colombia and ended at the
mouth of the Amazon, some 3,000 miles further on.
The unknown tribe which crossed the continent did so
relatively quickly for the layer of archaeological deposits
of the Napo is not particularly thick and corresponds to
a relatively short occupation. It is probable that the
bearers of the new civilization also stopped during their
journey on the Middle Amazon since pottery was
discovered in the Manaos area which in shape and orna¬
mentation resembled both Napo and Marajo pottery.
But the actual birthplace of Marajo civilization which
must lie somewhere in Colombia has not yet been dis¬
covered. Similarities between various Colombian cultures
and those of the Amazon have been recognized but the
Ceramics, like the pottery vessels shown here (above
and below), are almost the only relics left by a mys¬
terious people who once lived on the island of Marajo.
Their pottery bears geometric designs and is richly
decorated with modelling, enamel work and painting.
Musée de l'Homme. Paris
32
archaeologists have not so far been able to identify the
area where those elements typical of the Marajo civiliza¬
tion might have originated. In archaeological terms,
Colombia still happens to be a little-known country.
According to Evans and Meggers, the decline and then
the disappearance of the Marajo civilization was solely
due to economic causes. Like all the tropical tribes, the
Marajoaras practised shifting cultivation on burnt-out
land with the result that the soil was exhausted within a
few centuries. The time eventually came when the
Marajo people were no longer able to produce enough
food for their fairly dense population. With the decline in
numbers, the specialized craftsmanship which had encou¬
raged the development of pottery and other industries
could no longer survive. The fate of the Marajo people is
somewhat similar to that of the Maya empire which
likewise came to a sudden end. Today, the economic
explanation of the death of tropical civilizations is
contested. Hence the problem is far from resolved and
we are forced to admit that without that explanation
the mystery remains intact.
This ¡s one of the last articles that Dr. Alfred Métrauxsentto
The Unesco Courier. A regular contributor to this maga¬
zine since its foundation in 1948, Dr. Métraux died in
April of this year. Anthro¬
pologist and writer, he won
international repute for his
expedition to Easter Island
and others amongst the
South American Indians, and
for his work on behalf of
racial equality. Three of his
most noted books are "Eas¬
ter Island " (1 941 ); "Haitian
Voodoo" (1959) and "The
Incas" (1962). The series
of books on race which
Unesco published over the
past twelve years were pre¬
pared under his editorship.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
FAR NORTH CULTIVATION
Sir,
In the July-August 1962 issue
accompanying an excellently reproduc¬
ed photograph of a reindeer team, is
a paragraph that cannot be called
anything but idle fantasy. It says:
"Alaska's lands now under cultivation
cover 100,000 square miles, or about
half the area of France." According
to official American figures, the area
under crops in the state of Alaska in
1959 was 6,900 hectares (about 17,000
acres) and total ploughlands, includ¬
ing those abandoned amounted to
9,700 hectares (about 25,000 acres)...
This strange error is followed by an¬
other: "On the Taimyr Peninsula,
within the Arctic Circle, Soviet far¬
mers are growing maize and potatoes."
If the author of this text had been
better acquainted with the state of agri¬
culture on the Taimyr Peninsula, he
would have known that maize does
not grow there. The northernmost
point at which maize is produced is on
the Yenissei on the 57th parallel, about
1,500 kilometres south of the southern
frontier of Taimyr.
Potatoes are planted in the Taimyr
National Area on a few hundred square
metres of land; even this small patch
is in the south of the Taimyr National
Area and on the Peninsula there is
no farming of any kind.
Such distortions arouse the indigna¬
tion of a reader who is acquainted
with the real state of affairs, and
make him wary in respect of other,
truly magnificent, achievements in
conquering the Soviet Far North.
V. Andreyev, Professor,
Director, Far Northern Agricultural
Research Institute U.S.S.R-
LANGUAGE IS THE KEY TO
THE HEART OF A NATION
(Johann Gottfried von Herder)
Sir,
In your December 1962 issue,
E. D. Allen, of Dunedin, New Zea¬
land, suggests that Esperanto should
be adopted as a second language
throughout the world, now that
modern transport has brought nations
so close together.
The very fact that nations have
now become near neighbours offers
many facilities for the general public
to gain a knowledge of foreign
cultures which in the past was reserved
for privileged individuals or specia¬
lists. Languages are the key to this
knowledge, for the ideas and cultural
values of a nation find their liveliest
expression in its language. The semi¬
nar on the Teaching of Modern Lan¬
guages, organized by Unesco in
Ceylon in 1953, demonstrated beyond
a doubt that the student of foreign
languages is taking the surest and
most direct probably, indeed, the
only way towards a knowledge and
understanding of other cultures and
peoples. There is no better method
of gaining an insight into the spirit
of a foreign culture.
At a time when unprecedented
opportunities for cultural exchanges
are beginning to present themselves,
ought we to restrict them by limiting
ourselves to the study of an artificial
language as an adjunct to our own?
Recognizing that considerations of
technical utility should not be allow¬
ed to narrow down the spiritual
horizon of mankind, the International
Federation of University Women, at
its Conference, at Mexico City in
July 1962, adopted the following
resolution on the subject of language
study:
"The International' Federation of
University Women affirms the impor¬
tance of studying the language and
culture of people of all parts of the
world as one of the most essential
means of promoting international
understanding and friendship; and
urges national federations and asso¬
ciations to encourage the study of at
least one foreign language and culture,
under qualified teachers, not only in
secondary schools and universities but
also, as far as possible, by children
in primary schools and by adults in
various out-of-school programmes."
I feel convinced that this would
make a useful contribution to the
solution of many current problems.
Magda Staudinger
Freiburg-im-Breisgau
Federal Republic of Germany
BOTTICELLI WORKS
RECOVERED
Sir,
Your June issue referred to the
disappearance of 88 original Botti¬
celli drawings (illustrations for Dante's
"Divine Comedy") which prior to
the war were kept in. the Print Room
of the Berlin Museum. Though these
drawings were indeed thought to have
been lost during the war I am glad
to be able to tell you that they came
to. light again a few years ago.
Twenty-seven have now returned from
Wiesbaden to West Berlin and 61
have come back to East Berlin from
Moscow.
Paolo Peterlongo
Milan, Italy
NO BALLOON
FOR PHILEAS FOGG
Sir,
I should like to point out an error
in the back cover caption of your
September issue:
"A ceremony commemorating Jules
Verne's novel, Around the World in
80 Days, whose hero, Phileas Fogg,
accomplished one stage of his journey
in a balloon."
Phileas Fogg never used a balloon.
(Is there some confusion here with
Verne's Five Weeks in a Balloon or the
opening of The Mysterious Island?)
There is balloon episode in the film
version of Around the World..., but
not in the novel...
Aldo Danil
Genera, Switzerland
Ed note : Our reader is correct.
The balloon In our illustration was
used at a ceremony marking the Paris
release of the film version of "Around
the World in 80 Days" in which
several new episodes were added to
the Jules Verne story.
FROM 'THE LIONS' REFUGE'
Sir,
For the past 20 years I have lived
alone with wild animals in Central
Africa and have worked with other
defenders of African wildlife to try
to halt or at least reduce the mas¬
sacre that has become general despite
so-called measures, good intentions
and parodies of protection for wild
animals. In the Chad, in particular,
our work will never be effective
unless there is a reduction in the
large-scale importation of arms for
hunting and as long as there are
too few people conscientiously work¬
ing to ensure that hunting regulations
are properly respected which, as it
happens, is practically never the case.
There is also the fact that veterinary
services are authorized to use poison
to destroy carnivorous animals.
The "Lions' Refuge," which I
continue to run without any govern¬
ment help, is of immense value to
me in my campaign among both
Africans and Europeans. My ama¬
zingly friendly adult lions are now
known in Europe and in America.
To show them to people is perhaps
the most convincing way to pursuadc
the hunters to stop their massacres.
Our campaign slogan is "Don't kill
animals, photograph them. Take a
camera instead of a rifle." But the
work is difficult and the upkeep of
my animals is a heavy burden, for
all I have to live on is my salary as
secretary to the Chamber of Com¬
merce in Abéché.
Johanna Ludanl
Aheché, Republic of Chad
Mme Luclanl shows her lioness,
Tanlt, to an African visitor.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
"T*HE Soviet cosmonaut, Yuri Gagarin,
« who made the first earth-girdling
space flight on April 12, 1961, addres¬
sed the 14th International Astronauti¬
cal Congress held at Unesco's H. Q.
In Paris from September 25 to Octo
ber 1. On this occasion he was receiv¬
ed by Unesco's Executive Board, whose
chairman, Dr. C.E. Beeby, hailed him
as "the living symbol of the capacity
of the spirit of man to transcend
the limits of his physical environment."
Unesco-Dominique Roger
Colonel Gagarin during his visit to Unesco. With him, (from left to right) are
Professor A.P.Pavlov, permanent delegate of the U.S.S.R. to Unesco; H.E.
Serge Vinogradov, U.S.S.R. Ambassador to France; M. Georges Fleury
president of the French Astronautical Society; Professor Edmond Brun,
President of the International Astronautical Federation.
AFRICAN PROBLEMS: "Assignment
Children" a new review published by
the European Office of Unicef (The
United Nations Children's Fund, 24 Rue
Pauline-Borghese, Neuilly-sur-Seine, Fran¬
ce) has devoted its first issue to some major
African problems. Articles by leading
educators, doctors and writers point out
the dangers springing from poverty, hunger,
illiteracy and disease that now threaten
the children of Africa's developing coun¬
tries, and describe what needs to be done to
eliminate these evils. "Assignment Chil¬
dren" is to be published twice yearly in
English, French and German language
editions.
«EARTH OF DENTISTS: There should
"be at least one dentist for every 1,000
people, but figures issued by the World
Health Organization reveal a serious world
shortage: one dentist for every 283,700 peo¬
ple in Indonesia, one for 108,000 in India,
for 5,100 in the U.S.S.R., for 3,900 in the
United Kingdom, for 2,700 in France and
for 1,700 in the U.S.A.
LOOKING INSIDE ROCKS: The
internal structure or rock formations
is now being studied at the University of
Georgia Geology Department by the use of
X-rays. Through this technique, the geo¬
logist can determine details of internal
structures and fabrics which greatly in¬
fluence the localization of ore minerals and
the movement of fluids like petroleum and
ground water.
34 -jr EARNING AT THE WHEEL: Phy-
-B-' sicians in the United States have now
an ingenious means for keeping abreast "of
the latest developments in medicine. Medi¬
cal societies in several states issue weekly
tape-recorded lectures on current research
and discoveries in such special fields as
pediatrics, obstetrics, surgery, or cardio¬
vascular diseases. Doctors subscribe to the
series which interests them and play the
tapes on portable machines while driving
between home and hospital or patients'
homes.
REGINAS 'ARMCHAIR LOUVRE':
The city of Regina in Canada offers
its people an "Armchair Louvre" where
they can go and enjoy masterpieces of art
from all parts of the world. This minia¬
ture gallery comprises over 500 books and
folios of high-quality reproductions repre¬
senting all the great art movements. It is
visited regularly by students, art apprecia¬
tion and adult education groups, artists
doing research and people who simply go
there for their own pleasure.
METEOROLOGY INSTITUTE FOR
POONA: The United Nations in
collaboration with the World Meteorolo¬
gical Organization is helping India to set
up an Institute of Tropical Meteorology at
Poona. Its work will include research into
monsoons and their forecasting, warnings of
tropical cyclones, medium range weather
forecasting for the benefit of agriculture
and flood forecasting.
TEACHERS FOR AFRICA: At the
request of African educational autho¬
rities Unesco has set up an information
service to help African countries obtain
foreign teachers who are needed to help
staff universities, teachers' colleges and
high schools until enough African teachers
can be trained to replace them. The first
bulletin published by this "Teaching
Abroad" service lists 400 teaching jobs
offered in 17 African countries.
News Flashes. . .
H Two figures reflect the growing role of
Africa in Unesco's work: African member
states now number 32 as compared with 8
before I960; over 27% of the total current
budget for Unesco activities, including extra-
budgetary resources, is devoted to program¬
mes in Africa.
IP Enrolment has doubled this autumn at
Moscow University with 6,240 young
people beginning their first year studies.
Most of them have worked for two or
more years in industry or agriculture.
pj 44 countries have now joined the Unesco
Agreement on the Importation of Educa¬
tional, Scientific and Cultural Materials
which exempts books, newspapers, maga¬
zines and works of art from import duties.
Latest country to join this "Free Flow"
treaty is Somalia.
| Miniature nuclear power packages are
being developed to generate electricity for
satellites and spacecraft, with many poten¬
tial applications down on earth. Already
such packages are being used in robot
weather stations and in ship navigation
devices.
HONOURING THE U.N. GENERAL ASSEMBLY
The fourth U.N. commemorative
stamp for 1963 honours the U.N.
General Assembly. Bearing a design
depicting the U.N. Headquarters in
New York, the stamp is being issued
this month in 5c and 11c denomi¬
nations. -As agent in France of the
U.N. Postal Administration,. Unesco's
Philatelic Service stocks all U.N.
stamps and first day covers currently
on sale, and those issued by Unesco
member states to commemorate impor¬
tant events In the history of Unesco
and the U.N. For prices and further
details write to The Unesco Philatelic
Service, Place de Fontenoy, Paris (7e).
u
z
<
O
z
<
u
O
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
¿rm
%^
catalogue
	4«^productions
en couleurs de peintures
antérieures à 1860
* * '
catalogue
of colour reproductions
of paintings
prior to 1860
catálogo de
reproducciones en color
de pinturas
anteriores a I860
unesco paris
Volume I: Paintings Prior to 1860
Lists nearly 900 recommended colour reproduc¬
tions and includes many examples from Asia,
Africa, Australia and Central Europe.
Price: 30/-(stg); $6.00; 21 F. 323 pages.
In the Federal Republic of Germany, Switzerland
and Austria, a special Unesco-Oldenbourg Verlag
edition (with German text) is also available.
UNESCO CATALOGUES OF
COLOUR REPRODUCTIONS
OF PAINTINGS
Two volumes presenting an up-to-date listing of
colour reproductions of world-famous paintings com¬
piled from the Unesco collection of reproductions selec¬
ted by internationally-known experts on the basis of
fidelity of reproduction, the significance of the artist
and the importance of the original painting.
Each painting in these beautifully presented volumes
is reproduced in black and white together with full
details of the original, name of publisher and price of
colour reproduction.
catalogue
de reproductions
en couleurs de peintura
1860 à 19Í3
%
JUST PUBLISHED
Volume II : Paintings
from 1860 to 1963
A new and completely
up-to-date edition of 519
pages.
Contains descriptions
and illustrations of 1440
reproductions availablo in
full colour prints including
28 artists represented for
the first time.
Price:
30/-(stg); S6.00; 21 F.
ere to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; rates quoted are
for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO COU¬
RIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Press Department, Royal
Afghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Tradco Agencies, 109 Swanston Street, G. P. O.
Box 2324 V, Melbourne C. I. (Victoria) ; United
Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
8,'th Floor, McEwan House, 343 Little Collins St.,
Melbourne C. I. (Victoria). (A. 15/-). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C-., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Sch. 60.-). BELGIUM. Editions " Labor ",
342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-Boek-
handel, Belgielei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (100 FB) and art slides only: Louis de Lannoy,
22, place de Brouckère, Brussels. CCP 3380.00.
BURMA. Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road,
Rangoon. (K. 5.50). CANADA. Queen's Printer,
Ottawa, Ont. ($ 3.00). CEYLON. The Associated
Newspapers of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Colombo, 2 (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99 Chungking South
Rd., Section 1, Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa). CUBA.
Cubartimpex, Apartado 6540, La Havana.
(2.25 pesos). CYPRUS. Cyprus National
Youth Council, P. O. Box 539, Nicosia, CZE¬
CHOSLOVAKIA. ArtiaLtd., 30 Ve Smeckách. Prague
2. DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard, A/S Tidsskriftafde-
lingen, Prags Boulevard 47 Copenhagen S (D.kr. 12).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agency. P.O.Box 120.
Addis Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kiriakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu. Helsinki. (Fmk. 540). FRANCE. Librai¬
rie de l'Unesco, Place de Fontenoy. Paris-7". CCP. 12598-
48. (7 F.). GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg Verlag, Rosen-
heimer Strasse 145, Munich. For the Unesco Kurier
(German ed. only) Bahren-felder-Chaussee 160,
Hamburg-Bahrenfeld.C.C.P. 276650(DM 8). GHANA
Methodist Book Depot Ltd. Atlantis House, Commercial
St., POB 100, Cape Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See
United Kingdom. GREECE. Librairie H. Kaufímann,
28, rue du Stade, Athens. HONG-KONG. Swindon
Book Co., 64, Nathan Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY.
Kultura, P.O. Box 149. Budapest, 62.
Snaebjorn jonsson & Co. H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik
INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd. Indian Mercan¬
tile Chamber, Nicol Road, Bombay 1 ; 1 7 Chittaranjan Ave¬
nue, Calcutta 1 3 ; Gunfoundry Road, Hyderabad, 1; 36a,
Mount Road, Madras 2; Kanson House, 24/1 Asaf All Road,
P.O. Box 386, New Delhi, 1 ; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book &
Stationery Co., 1 7 Park Street, Calcutta 1 6, Scindia House,
New Delhi. Indian National Commission for Co-operation
with Unesco, Ministry of Education, New Delhi 3. (Rs. 7).
INDONESIA. P. N. Fadiar Bhakti, Djalan
Nusantara 22, Djakarta. IRAQ. Mackenzie's
Bookshop, Baghdad. IRELAND. The National Press,
2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores 35, Allenby Road
and 48, Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv (1£5.S0).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour
Street, Kingston. Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
(10/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-Nichome,
Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605 Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
(Yen 670). JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co..
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman. .
KENYA. E.S.A. Bookshop, P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64. Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole
and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LUXEMBURG. Librairie Paul Brück. 22, Grand-Rue,
Luxemburg. MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications Ltd., Times House,
River Valley Rd., Singapore (M. $ 500) MALTA.
Sapienza's Library 26 Kingsway, Valetta. (10/-).
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon
Street, Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid
des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (7 NF.). NETHERLANDS.
N. V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague,
(fl. 6). NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES. G. C. T.
Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.) N.V., Willemstad. Curacao.
NEW ZEALAND Government Printing Office 20.
Molesworth Street (Private Bag) Wellington, Government
Bookshops,: Auckland (P.O. Box 5344), Christchurch,
(P. O. Box 1721), Dunedin) P.O. Box 1104 (10/-).
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box 174, Lszos,
(10/-). NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille Grense.
7 Oslo For the Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narvesens
Litteratur Tjeneste, Stortingtgt. 4 Oslo, Poitboks 115
(kr 1.320 PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing Cor
Ltd., Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box 374 S6-N
Gulberg Industrial Colony, Lahore. PANAMA.
Cultural Panameña, Avenida 7a, No. TI-49, Apartado de
Correos 2018, Panama, (D. F. Balboas 3-). PHILLIPI¬
NES. The Modern Book C o., 508 Rizal Avenue P.O. Box
632 Manila. POLAND. " RUCH " ul. Wiloza Nr. 46x
Warsaw 10 (ZI. 50). PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada
Lda, Livrana Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon.
PUERTO RICO. Spanish English Publications Apartado
1912, Hato Re/. RHODESIA«, N YASALAND. The
Book Centre, Gordon Avenue. Salisbury, Southern Rhode
sia. SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop, P. O, Box 1118,
Khartoum. SWEDEN. A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbok-
handel, Fredsgatan 2. Stockholm. For The Unesco
Courier: Svenska Unescoradet. Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 7.50); SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag,
5 Ramistrasse Zurich. Payot, 40. rue du Marche, Geneva
CCP. 1-236. " Courier " only: Georges Losmaz, 1 ,rue.
des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CCP. 1-4811. (Fr. S. 8).
TANGANYIKA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop. P.O.B.
9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND. Suksapan
Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok. (35
ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette. 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu. Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda
Bookshop, P.O. Box 145, Kampala. UNION OF
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Bookstore, Libri
Building, Church Street, Pretoria. For the Unesco Cou¬
rier (single copies) only: Central News Agency, P.O.
Box 1033. Johannesburg. (10/-). UNITED ARAB
REPUBLIC (EGYPT). La Renaissance d'Egypte. 9*Sh.
Adly-Pasha, Cairo. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M.
Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I. (10/-).
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications Center,
317 East 34th St, New York. 16, N.Y. ($5.00.)
and (except periodicals): Columbia University Press,
2960 Broadway. New York. 27 .N.Y. U.S.S.R. Mez-
hdunarodnaja Kmga. Moscow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA
Yugoslovenska Knjiga, Terazije 27/11. Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
i
i* f* > ! '. .' X '
YEARS
OF CHANGE
IN THE CONGO
Paul Almasy, Paris
Since 1960 when it became an independent African nation, the Republic of the Congo
has been rebuilding and expanding its educational system on all levels with help from
Unesco. (See story page 4). During the same period the population of its capital,
Leopoldville, has more than doubled and now numbers over one million. This statue
is one of the figures in the memorial to Henry M. Stanley, a pioneer of African explo¬
ration, which stands on a hillside near Leopoldville, overlooking the broad Congo River.
]]>
</page>
</document>
