<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="063436eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
m
WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
H 1 1M
JULY-AUGUST 1963 (16TH YEAR) - PRICE 2/-STG. ( U.K.) 60 CENTS (CANADA) - 1 .40 F (FRANCE)
SCIENCE
FOR
PROGRESS
<£
'^^iî
S
r m
iiBJ
I 9Bj!
<afl TWJBTT "VSnafT-.
( UMBju. .'¡grgt
11"!
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
m
w
CSF - Georges Bru
ELECTRONIC INFRASTRUCTURE
Suggesting an ultra-modern artistic composition,
this "tableau" is nothing more than tiny wires
and metal plates which are components of that
versatile electronic device, the transistor. Re¬
placing to a large extent radio valves, transistors
are smaller, use less power and have no filaments
to burn out. Their use has brought a great many
revolutionary changes in the control and opera¬
tion of innumerable branches of modern industry
and technology. (See other photos, page 62)
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
JULY-AUGUST 1963
16TH YEAR
Contents
No. 7-8
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
COVER PHOTO
Meeting on a street in Dakar,
Republic of Senegal, these
young men, one a university
science student, the other a
peasant youth who has never
been to school, symbolize two
sharply-contrasting aspects
of life today in developing
lands.
© Paul Almasy. Paris
SPECIAL DOUBLE ISSUE
Science for Progress
4 WORLD OF OPPORTUNITY
By Ritchie Calder
10 FREEDOM WITH KNOWLEDGE
By Abba Eban
14 THE PROMISE OF NUCLEAR POWER
By Homi Jehangir Bhabha
18 S.T.P.INDEX OF PROSPERITY
By Victor A. Kovda
22 UNESCO EXPANDS ITS SCIENCE PROGRAMME
24 330 MILLION BRAINS FOR A NEW ERA
By René Maheu
30 SHOPPING IN THE SUPERMARKET OF SCIENCE
By P.M.S. Blackett
32 A FACE-LIFT FOR THE SCIENCE CURRICULUM
By Jerome B. Wiesner
37 A UNIVERSITY TOWN BUI LT BY A COUNTRY DOCTOR
Photo-story by Paul Almàsy
41 ASSIUT, EGYPT'S MOST MODERN UNIVERSITY
By S.A. Huzayyin
44 AFRICAN METAMORPHOSIS
By E.A.K. Kalitsi
50 URBAN EXPLOSION IN DEVELOPING NATIONS
By Paul Mercier
56 HOMO SAPIENS, THAT STRANGE PARADOX
By Daniel Bovet
58 INTO THE WORLD OF THE FUTURE
By Nicolai Semenov
65 SCIENTISTS ABROAD
By Alan Elliott
(M. C. 63.1., 182 A)
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational,
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
René Caloz
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : jane Albert Hesse
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani (Moscow)
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shin-lchl Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Italian Edition : Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Scientific and Cultural
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except In July ind August when
it is bi-monthly (I I issues s yeir) in English, French, Spanish, Russian. German.
Arabic, Japanese, and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed by H.M.
Stationery Office, P. O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly 1rs The Readers' Guide to
Periodical Literature published by H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates : 10/-stg. ;$3.00 (Canada) ;7.00
French Francs or equivalent. Single copies l/-stg. 30
cents ; 0.70 F.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
WORLD
by Ritchie Calder
Last February the United Nations brought together at
Geneva probably the world's greatest assembly of scientists
to discuss the application of science and technology for
the benefit of the less developed areas. This double issue
is based in major part on material from these discussions.
In the special article below Ritchie Calder, winner of
Unesco's Kalinga Science Prize (1961) highlights the
work of the UNCSAT conference and its implications for
the new nations tomorrow. He is now completing a
full-length analysis of the meetings, shortly to appear
under the title "World of Opportunity" as Volume I of an
8-vo/ume condensation of the UNCSAT conference to be
published later this year by the United Nations.
HERE are plenty of new flags fluttering at the
mast-heads. When the United Nations was
created in 1945, there were fifty-one members. Now there are one hundred
and eleven and of those forty-six are countries which have won their indepen¬
dence in the meatime.
But flags are not enough. Political freedom is an exhilarating experience,
but there is the morning after the celebrations when peoples are likely to wake
up and find that freedom has been robbed of much of its meaning; they are
just as hungry, just as sick, just as impoverished. They have the pride of
nationhood but are deprived, by squalor and hardship, of human dignity.
They have an equal vote in the assembly of the nations but they suffer the
inequality of unshared abundance.
This is the contradiction of the modern world. At one and the same time,
there has been the "revolution of rising expectations," of which political
freedom is only part-fulfilment, and the scientific and technical revolution which
has increased the prosperity of the advanced countries and has widened the
gap between them and the less-developed countries.
From the peasant in the paddy-field to the astronaut
As Professor M. S. Thacker, in his presidential address to the United Nations
Conference on the Application of Science and Technology for the Benefit of
the Less Developed Areas, reminded the world: "One tenth of the peoples of
the world enjoy 60% of the world's income, while 57% of them have
less than 10% of that wealth at their disposal. If present trends are to
continue, the gulf between the poor and the rich countries will widen still
further and this at a time when great continents have awoken to freedom
and their populations are clamouring for certain minimum standards of life...
Prosperity, like peace, is indivisible."
The gap is as wide as the vertical 200 miles which separate the peasant,
wading in the wet paddy-field transplanting rice stem by stem, from the
astronaut, circling the planet Earth which 3,000,000,000 human beings have
to share; between the muscle-efforts of the poor and the supreme achievements
of modern science; and between those who lack science and technology and
those who have them.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
OF OPPORTUNITY
The closing of this gap was the "categorical imperative" of the injunction
of U Thant, United Nations Secretary General, to the 1,655 participants at the
qcience and technology conference at Geneva. Ironically, the roll-call of that
conference displayed the gap; the numbers of delegates from the advanced
countries were four to one of those from less-developed countries, representing
two-thirds of the world's population; their governments just could not afford
to send more than one or two delegates; fourteen could not send any.
A meeting of minds without precedent
Unesco. - Pierre A. Pittet
The Bosscha Astronomical Observatory,
close to Bandung in Indonesia, has been
equipped, partly through a Unesco con¬
tribution, with twin telescopes, one
intended for visual and the other for
photographic work. Because they are
situated seven degrees south of the
equator, the observatory's telescopes
are well-placed for studying certain
constellations such as the Milky Way.
Apart from its size and the 10,000,000 words which "went into the record,"
this conference was exceptional. It was not one more of those 1,500 scientific
conferences which are held every year and at which scientific specialists discuss
the details of their specializations. It was a public "stock-taking" not only
of the goods which science has to offer in what Professor P. M. S. Ulacketl
called "the supermarket of science," but of the cupboards, meagre in the
essentials of human existence, of the less-developed countries. It was u
venture in a new dimension of discussion not just the laying out of facts but
a consensus of human aspirations.
No one had to be reminded of what science is capable of doing the release
of atomic energy and the circling satellites (57 when the conference opened)
were proof of what Thinking Man can do when he sets his mind to it. There
were no bitter recriminations; political considerations, while not entirely
absent, were muted. There was a certain amount of finger-wagging, of
professorial cautioning about not attempting too much but also salutary
reminders about the dangers of doing too little.
There was, to begin with (because it was a conference without precedent), a
tendency to over-formalize the discussions but that quickly broke down under
protest and perhaps more mental business was transacted outside the sessions
than in them, in the lobbies, and in the bars of the Palais des Nations. Anil in
a real sense the delegates fullfilled their function of being, in Professor
Thacker's phrase, '"the ambassadors of the needy and the spokesmen of the
tongue-tied."
As Academian E. K. Fedorov said, the range of items was '"encyclopa:dic."
Governments had been asked to submit papers as well as to send delegations
and, in advance of the conference, over 4,000 papers were sent in, from which,
with political as well as scientific tact, the scientific secretariat had to reject
2,000; the number of papers eventually presented to the conference was 1,849.
If all the transactions, totalling 10,000,000 words, were to be published, they
would fill 80 volumes. Instead, one of the post-conference tasks was to distill
from all this material eight "'working" volumes (1), eacli self-sufficient as a
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
(1) 8-volume series, "Science and Technology for Development" : I. A World of
Opportunity; II. Natural Resources; III. Agriculture; IV. Industry; V. People 5
and Living; VI. Education; VII. Science and Planning; VIII. Plenary papers
and Index.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
This "forest" of multi-coloured cork balls is a research laboratory scale model (100 million to 1)
of an atom compound showing its crystal structure. To obtain the information they needed to
build this model, research chemists first studied the direction and intensity of X-ray beams diffracted
by a crystal. From research like this much has been learned about the internal structure of matter.
WORLD OF OPPORTUNITY (Cont'd)
subject, so that men of affairs could comprehend and, more important, act
upon the useful suggestions.
There were 96 sessions in sixteen days three plenary sessions in which out¬
standing and understanding personalities could survey the problems and set
up the signposts for The World Development Decade, as the U.N. General
Assembly designated the 1960s; 12 general sessions, covering cognate subjects;
and 81 specialized sessions.
A host of unexpected answers from the computer
At the instigation of the President, three other special sessions were arranged
so that the representatives of the less-developed countries could canvass their
general problems. Even that was not enough; the chairmen of the various
sessions organized twenty-three extra meetings so that they could go into more
detail. And just to show how desperately in earnest the participants were
an extra-curricular service that no one had planned sprang into existence.
Experienced conference-goers became the "hosts" for the hesitant and made
it their job to introduce them to those who had the answers for which they were
looking.
The result was a friendly "clubbin0" little groups getting together in alcoves
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
or private rooms. And it was not a one-way traffic; the "teachers" became
the " taught," because they learned from the representatives of less-developed
countries a great deal that is not in the text-books. In winding-up, Professor
Thacker compared the conference to a computer into which a great amount of
information had been fed and a lot of unexpected answers had come out.
It was, in truth, a conference without precedent but, then, the circumstances
were unprecedented. Historically one might think of The Age of Reason at
the end of the Eighteenth Century when there was a similar ferment of
freedom, with the coming into existence of the United States, with the French
Revolution, with Voltaire, Rousseau and Tom Payne and with the "encyclo¬
paedists" trying to encompass and disseminate the knowledge of their times.
And all of it coinciding with the invention of the steam-engine which gave a
new power to the Industrial Revolution. If, as in the case of the Geneva
Conference of 1963, there had been a coming together of those two forces, of
aspirations and of material change, how different would history have read
today.
There was, in the Geneva Conference, this sense that it was changing human
destiny. It could not be otherwise. Science and technology lias become the
social dynamic of our times. While reminding the leaders of the emergent
nations that they were inadequately informed of the scientific advances which
would give the maximum content to political freedom, U Tliant, in his message,
had this challenge to offer:
"Science today is on trial because of the vastly increased power it has given
to the forces of war and destruction to the point that, for the first time,
humanity may be threatened with instant and total annihilation hut equally
because, in its boldest and most far-reaching experiments science seems to have
lost contact with society. Its processes have at times become so involved in
mathematical abstraction and its preoccupations centred on areas so remote
from daily life, that to the common man the scientists may appear today to live
in a secluded world of their own. In some way, science must lie made to
remain aware of its human origin and human destination."
No more foundling on the doorstep of society
The scientists accepted that challenge. By their very presence in such
numbers, they had accepted the fact they had social obligations and must no
longer be prepared to leave their discoveries like foundlings on the doorstep
of society with no responsibility for their upbringing. Rut speaker after
speaker made this explicit in such phrases as:
"No one can deny that the scientist has become a man of power and influence
in the twentieth century. Whether he likes it or not, he has obtained a high
place in decision-making." (Thacker, India.)
"Science is a supra-national activity, for its truths recognize no political
boundaries." (Bernardo Houssay, Argentine.)
"For far too long has the scientist lived in an ivory tower of his own creation.
For far too long he lived the captive life of the djinn of Aladdin's Lamp.
He must change his own attitudes before he can ever see the goal of world
development fully realized." (Abdus Salam, Pakistan.)
"We, scientists who have each of us embarked on vessels over which we have
no control, have at least the right and the duty of saying publicly that in aiding
the under-developed countries, the industrialized countries should not only give
away their superfluity or their surpluses but should be ready to deprive them¬
selves and give until it hurts." (Henri Laugier, France.)
"Today, when science is exerting enormous influences on life, scientists
appreciate their responsibility for the way their knowledge is being applied."
(Fedorov, U.S.S.R.)
This, however, was not just a conference of soul-searching but of life-giving.
In the twelve sections of the Conference, problems were examined on the most
prosaic as well as the most profound levels. In purely material terms, -¡
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
WORLD OF OPPORTUNITY (Cont'd;
countries are underdeveloped because full use has not been made of their
natural resources. More often than not, they do not know what natural
resources they possess and a great deal of practical consideration (and advice)
was given about how those resources should, by modern techniques, be found,
charted and made use of.
One of the most critical discussions in this section was on river basin develop¬
ment. Agriculture, rightly in a hungry world, had more papers than any
other subject. Industry in all its aspects was examined, with the recognition,
continually emphasized that, however preoccupied with increasing its farm
yields, no country can enjoy complete independence unless it has a developed
industry.
Charting and using a nation's natural resources
Transport and communications are indispensable to "getting a country on
the move." Health, nutrition, housings rural and urban development, were
examined and exemplified, with the recurring warnings to avoid the mistakes
of the older industrialized countries and reminders that development is not an
end in itself but a social purpose.
Planning, it transpired, is no longer a suspect word with ideological inflec¬
tions. This was one of the most important of all the sections, not only in
terms of economic planning but especially of the planning of science and its
direction to the needs of countries. Permeating and to some extent domin¬
ating all sections was the need for education and the sharing of knowledge and
skills and how this is to be done, in terms of international collaboration and
new techniques, as the most urgent follow-up of the conference. In this,
Unesco's role, as in the promotion of science for development, was obvious and
accepted.
Perhaps the most significant, indeed revolutionary change in thinking was
the recognition of the need for "investment in human resources." This is basic
to all U.N. thinking and has been embodied in all the work of all the
specialized agencies. But here was the recognition that the true "in¬
frastructure" is not that of conventional economics the building of ports,
railways, roads, etc. as a precondition of industrial development, "the gravit¬
ational flow of capital." Instead, it is not only "human resources," but "human
resourcefulness" which matters. A healthy, better fed, better educated popu¬
lation can hasten everything else. In addition to being the "social beneficia¬
ries," human beings become the economics factors in their own prosperity.
J
The rising expectations that cannot wait
"Hasten" is the operative word. People are now impatient to give material
meaning to their freedom. Delay, as the Geneva Conference insisted, means
a worsening of the disparity between the rich and poor "a slum at the bottom
of the rich man's garden," as the President put it.
We are trying to telescope time. Britain, first off the mark in the Industrial
Revolution, has the benefits of 200 years of industrialization; Western Europe,
of 150 years; the U.S.A., of 100 years; Japan, of 80 years; Russia, since the
Soviet Revolution, of 40. If the less-developed countries have to wait 40, those
"rising expectations" will be deferred until the twenty-first century. Science
and technology, shared and with means to make their possibilities real, can
8 compress the calendar. The World Development Decade, with the Geneva
Conference to give it its head-force, is under way.
The University of
Ibadan in Nigeria is
one of the most mod¬
ern in Africa. Some
2,000 students at¬
tend its faculties:
Science, Agronomy
and Veterinary Sci¬
ence, Economic and
Social Sciences, Let¬
ters and Medicine.
© Paul Almasy. Pans
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
wo movements dominate the life of our age.
One of these Is the growth of knowledge.
Vast conceptual changes, new terms for the understanding
and definition of nature, have gone hand in hand with
spectacular technological results. Man is now clothed
with a power which he never previously held to generate
and control energy; to fructify land; to conserve and
utilize water; to combat disease; and to draw mankind
together in close and constant accessibility.
Together with the growth of knowledge we have
celebrated the growth of freedom. The movement
of scientific progress has been accompanied by an intense
movement of national liberation. More than fifty states,
most of them in Africa, have added their flags to the
international family within the past two decades.
Fifteen years ago a quarter of the world's population
lived in colonies and dependent territories under the rule
of Imperial powers. Today the emancipation of Asia is
almost complete. In Africa the family of Independent
states has grown from three to thirty-three. All but a
few of the 230 million Africans have achieved their sover¬
eignty or are negotiating for Its early attainment.
Multitudes are newly embarked on the adventure of
freedom with its pitfalls and hazards but also with its
deep, enduring satisfactions.
jQ If constitutional freedom could itself guarantee welfare
and equality we should now be celebrating mankind's
golden age. But in the awakening continents political
freedom has not been attended by a parallel liberation
of peoples from their social and economic Ills. Behind the
new emblems of sovereignty millions continue to languish
in squalor, illiteracy and disease. Men awaken to learn
that they may be free in every constitutional sense and
yet lose the essence of their freedom in the throes of
famine and want. As the political inequality between
nations passes away, a new inequality comes to the fore.
It is the inequality between those who inherit the new
abundance and those who can only look in upon it from
outside.
N ow the United Nations conference on the
of science and technology for the
benefit of the less developed countries has sharply
revealed the extent of the gulf separating those two
worlds. In the advanced countries the average per capita
income varies between $900 In Europe and $2,500 in North
America. In most countries of Asia and Africa it is $50
to $100. In advanced western countries the average life
expectancy has reached 68 to 71. In the undeveloped
areas it stands between 29 and 39.
In the west industrialization goes forward with swift
momentum. In most of the new states it is Impeded by
the lack of basic technical skills, of power and transport,
and of the social and economic Infra-structure necessary
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
for a technological society. Natural resources are abun¬
dant but not developed. The lack of momentum In the
educational movement prevents a wider acquisition of
technical skills. Debilitating diseases continue to enfeeble
the people and set a limit to production. At the same
time the expansion of welfare in the advanced countries
is swift and headlong. And the gap is becoming wider,
with the science and technology of the advanced coun¬
tries increasing it dynamically year by year. Meanwhile
the pressure of population on resources grows more
intense.
The disparities in achievement between the advanced
and the developing states do not arise from any inherent
inequalities in moral and intellectual capacity. Nothing
has been achieved by Europe and America of which Africa
and Asia are intrinsically incapable. Indeed, If a con¬
ference similar to this had been convened some centuries
ago, the east would have been defined as the advanced
world, the west as the backward region. The truth is
that since the scientific revolution began, one part of
humanity has been cut off from contact with processes
of thought and action which have endowed another part
of humanity with the elements of its power.
It might seem that all we need to do is to "export"
science and technology from countries in which it is
abundant to countries in which it is scarce. Such an
easy formulation would distort the truth. Science is a
plant which can only grow in certain conditions of social
climate and economic soil. It cannot be transferred fully
grown. Science is not a monopoly of any social system.
It has flourished both in capitalist and In socialist socie¬
ties. It has prospered In big states, but some of Its most
eminent representatives and institutions have arisen in
small communities. Nevertheless, it is a tree that will
only grow In a society which possesses a vision of dev¬
elopment, which allows freedom for the creative Imagina¬
tion, and In which education, the pursuit of scientific truth
and the penetration of the spectacle of nature are held
In profound respect.
Every state, however poor and small, can train
enough of its citizens to ensure its own entry
Into the domain of scientific thought and action. Indeed,
the prolonged exclusion of any state from that world Is
compatible neither with Its national dignity nor with Its
economic and social progress. But the narrowing of the
gap between advanced and developing states requires
international action going far beyond scientific advice
and technical training.
There must be a vast Increase in the flow of capital
available for developing states. Some of us have Joined
in calling attention to the improbability of such an
Increase so long as 150 billion dollars and untold eilorts
by scientists and technicians are spent annually on the
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
FREEDOM WITH KNOWLEDGE (Cont'd)
Standing on a new threshold
arms race. Even If our hopes in this direction are not
fulfilled, something can be achieved by a more logical
system of human priorities In the world's scientific effort.
How is It possible to Justify the expenditure of tens of
billions of dollars In prestige projects in outer space, when
there is hunger, disease and illiteracy on this planet
where the human condition stands to be determined for
good or ill? Is it our business to invade the moon or to
save the earth for our common humanity?
The advanced states and the international agencies
should regard this problem as having a higher priority
than it has hitherto enjoyed. If we cannot change the
relationship between advanced and backward regions
within two decades, the chances of a peaceful and ordered
human society may be forever lost. By 2000 a world
populated by 6,280 million people will not be able to endure
the Inequalities which now exist between states. The
problem which has engaged the attention of the UNCSAT
Conference should be solemnly considered by the heads of
all governments interested in international development.
The problem is not less urgent than those on which other
"summit conferences" have been held.
Nothing of value can be achieved without the Initiative
of the governments of developing states. These govern¬
ments must be given a deepened confidence in the modern
scientific movement as one of their sources of their pro¬
gress. The course open to them is clear: Draw up a
survey of resources; formulate a ten-year development
plan; give the most urgent priority to human resources;
establish an indigenous science through the training of a
scientific elite: make maximal use of the U.N. Specialized
Agencies, of bilateral agreements, and of the specialized
assistance which is so patently available to governments
seeking accelerated development.
WHO
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Largest advanced training centre for Israel's scientists is the Weizmann Institute at Rehovoth
founded nearly 30 years ago. Two hundred scientists work here in nuclear physics, experimental
biology, electronics, plant genetics and other subjects. Above, in the special cold room (up to
-15 degrees C.) of the bio-chemical department research workers wear arctic clothes.
Opposite, woman scientist uses an induction heater for research on iron magnetism.
Í5 Poul AlmdSy, P.iMS
Let us hope and believe that the leaders of new nations
will approach the problems of development and technical
progress with the same ardour and perseverance which
they have hitherto devoted to the struggle for national
liberation.
While I advocate a full use of international machinery,
I do not believe that the United Nations should claim a
monopoly of initiative and responsibility. The communion
between the world of science and the world of national
liberation should be sustained at every level. Individual
states and scientific institutions should do what they can
to stimulate the reciprocal flow of experience and know¬
ledge. Bilateral programmes sometimes have an intimacy
and speed which large international agencies cannot
always achieve.
Many of the new states have territories and populations
too small to constitute viable units of development.
Irrigation projects, universities and research institutes
except in such unusual conditions as those which affect
my own country, Israel require a broad demographic and
territorial basis. There is a strong case for regional
organization of planning and research, especially in Africa.
It is not impossible to combine individual sovereignty with
collective development.
FUTURE conferences held by the United Nations
or in member states should be of more limited
scope and should address themselves to clearly defined
fields. Believing that soil and water are still the main
source of life for millions in the awakening continents,
Israel proposes to hold a conference 'In 1963, bringing
experts on agricultural planning and agrarian education
together with ministers and officials of developing states
concerned with these problems. I believe that similar
specialized conferences could usefully consider problems
of disease control, technical and scientific education, the
use of new energies, Initial Industrialization and planning
and survey techniques. The dialogue held here must be
maintained and even intensified, but on an Increasingly
functional basis.
IIf we understand the U.N. Conference In its
special context of history, we have no reason
to be disappointed. There has never been such a
concentration of scientific knowledge and responsibility
in the service of humanity's submerged millions those
who have secured the outward form of liberty and now
seek its inner content. There is evidence that the world's
scientific conscience Is being galvanized by the pathos
and opportunity of the less developed regions. This is
the first generation of mankind In which the elimination
of poverty and disease has become objectively possible.
Science Is the father of this possibility. Scientists do not
wish to retreat into their laboratories in an cifort to
escape the challenge of human anguish and human hope.
They have the will and the capacity to transform the
human situation.
If we can only fertilize their will and organize their
capacity we may yet inaugurate one of the Great Ages
of History.
Abba Eban has been president of the Weizmann Institute
of Science since 1958. He was Israel's representative to
the United Nations between 1948 and 1959.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
THE PROMISE OF
by Homi Jehangir Bbabha
n adequate supply of energy is the primary
»requisite for all modern industrialization and
for supporting a high standard of living. For the under¬
developed countries of the world, It is therefore of prime
Importance to ensure that adequate amounts of energy
and power are harnessed at all stages of their develop¬
ment. A sound policy with regard to energy development
can be formulated properly only by taking a long view of
the broad energy requirements for quite some time into
the future.
In planning for the supply of electricity, it is important
to remember that the capital investment in plants and
industries required to consume a unit of electricity is on
the average roughly seven times the capital investment
in plant required to produce a unit of electricity. Thus,
in any industrial complex the investment in power pro¬
ducing industries is generally only about 10 to 15% of
the total investment.
A conclusion to be drawn from this important fact is
that when making large investments in power production
it must be assured that several times this amount, say
five to seven times, is available for investment in new
industries to utilise this power. Otherwise, some of the
investment made in producing new power will lie unuti¬
lized. A second and equally important conclusion to be
drawn is that while the investment in power has to be
roughly one-seventh of the total industrial investment,
one should always ensure that the investment in power-
producing industries is somewhat more rather than less
than the optimum figure of about one-seventh. Under-
supply of power has a much more adverse effect than
an over-supply.
14
When discussing the economics of utilizing alter¬
native energy resources, the present levels of
energy consumption the growth in demands for energy and
the availability of the different energy resources have to
be taken into account. For an examination of these fac¬
tors, it is convenient to divide the world into nine groups
of countries as follows: North America, comprising essen¬
tially the United States and Canada; Oceania, consisting
of Australia and the Pacific Ocean islands; U.S.S.R.; West¬
ern and Eastern Europe; Africa excluding Egypt; Latin
America including Mexico and countries south of it;
South Asia and the Far East, including all countries of
Asia excluding the Middle East and China; The Middle
East, including Iran, Turkey, Egypt and other Arab
countries, and China.
A tabulation of the per capita consumption of com¬
mercial energy, electricity production and installed elec¬
trical capacity for these regions shows that the per
capita energy consumption for North America is about
7.8 tons of coal equivalent per annum, and that for Europe,
Oceania, and the U.S.S.R. is about 3 tons. These areas
comprise the industrially advanced countries of the
world today.
On the other hand, Latin America, Africa, South Asia
and the Far East, the Middle East and China, which
comprises areas that may be termed as "underdeveloped",
have a per capita consumption of less than 0.7 tons coal
equivalent. The disparity in these figures points to the
CONT'D ON PAGE 16
..^ - V~ '
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
NUCLEAR ENERGY
India Is basing plans for its future industrial development on tho uso of nucloar
energy. It began surveys of its nuclear fuel resources uranium and thor¬
ium as far back as 1 949 and, as part of its programme of nuclear research,
began to operate its first reactor, the "Apsara", or water nymph, at Trombay,
near Bombay in 1 957. It now has three research reactors at Trombay, Includ¬
ing the Canada-India Reactor whoso huge steel protective domo is shown
here, and in addition it is planning to build two nuclear power stations.
Canadian National film Board
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
NUCLEAR ENERGY (Cont'd)
Coal and oil exhausted in 75 years
enormous Increases in energy production that will be
required as the underdeveloped regions industrialize
themselves. Moreover, the underdeveloped regions con¬
tain the bulk of the world's populationsome 2,139 mil¬
lion out of a total of roughly 3,000 million.
According to a recent survey by the World Power Con¬
ference, it is estimated that the total reserves of fossil
fuel In the world that could be economically recovered
are about 3 i million million tons. On the other hand,
the total consumption of commercial sources of energy
in the world in 1960 was about 4,200 million tons of coal
equivalent. The world consumption of energy increased
at a rate of about 5% per annum in the 1955-1960 period,
and the rate has increased above this figure in 1959 and
1960. On this basis the estimated reserves of economi¬
cally recoverable fossil fuel would be exhausted in about
75 years.
So far as water power is concerned, it is estimated that
if all the sites in the world that have been surveyed are
utilized, it should be possible to generate about 5 million
million Kw hours of electricity per annum. This forms
a small portion of even the present total world energy
consumption and would be less than 3% of the likely
consumption 30 years hence. It therefore appears that
within the foreseeable future, the world will have to go
in for a massive utilization of nuclear energy or other
non-conventional resources.
A tabulation of the total reserves of conventional re¬
sources, both measured and inferred, for different re¬
gions of the world, reveals the striking fact that the
underdeveloped areas of the world are also those with
the least per capita resources of conventional energy.
The reserves are under 400 tons of coal equivalent per
capita for the underdeveloped areas, 1,400 tons for Eu¬
rope, over 8,000 tons for North America and over 25,000
tons for the U.S.S.R.
We may assume that the underdeveloped areas will
aim at achieving as rapidly as possible a stage of dev¬
elopment corresponding to that prevailing in Europe today,
which would mean a per capita annual energy consump¬
tion of about 3 tons of coal equivalent. With a consump¬
tion of 3 tons per capita for these regions annually the
entire reserves would be exhausted in less than 40 years
in Latin America, less than 65 years in the Middle East,
less than 30 years in the South Asia and Far East region
and less than 133 years in Africa. This does not, of
course, take into account the steadily rising population.
It is clear therefore that in the underdeveloped areas,
POWER FROM THE
SUN. Energy captured
from sunshine may one
day be used to run entire
factories. For the moment
there is an immediate need
for small solar power units
that can be used to pump
water from wells and un¬
derground streams in the
world's arid areas. Re¬
search on such batteries
of mirrors is going for¬
ward in many countries.
This photo shows recent
installation at the Uni-
16 versity of Dakar, Senegal.
© Paul Almasy. Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
the conventional reserves will not be sufficient to support
a developed economy for any significant length of time
and that recourse will have to be made either to nuclear
energy or to imports of fuel on a massive scale in the
near future.
The area which is worst endowed with conventional
resources is the South Asia and Far East region which
with a present population of 925 million will therefore
require the use of nuclear energy at the earliest date of
all.
The cost of commercial energy depends on two factors;
first, the intrinsic cost of the energy in the fuel used,
and secondly the cost of the plant necessary for extract¬
ing this energy from the fuel and converting it into a
commercially useful form, such aá electricity.
If the cost of coal is $4 a ton, the cost of energy in it
comes to 20 US cents per million British Thermal Units.
Transport may more than double the cost of energy. For
furnace oil at $16 per ton, the cost of energy contained
in it is 40 US cents per million BTU. The cost of nuclear
fuel is higher, for we have to include the cost of bringing
the ore to the surface of extracting the uranium content
in it and then fabricating this uranium into fuel ele¬
ments of the desired type. This may result in fuel
elements costing anything from $30,000 to $60,000 per ton.
On the other hand, the amount of energy that can
be extracted from each ton, even with today's technology,
is so enormous that the cost of energy from uranium may
vary between 8 and 20 cents per million BTU. In other
words, the intrinsic cost of energy from nuclear fuel is
almost invariably lower than the cost of energy from
conventional fuel, and may in many cases be less than
half the cost of energy from coal even at the pit heads.
This general situation could have an important bearing
on fuel policy. If fuel has to be imported in any case,
then it is much cheaper in terms of the energy obtained
to Import nuclear fuel rather than conventional fuel.
The known reserves of conventional fuels In most of the
underdeveloped areas are relatively so small that the full
industrialization of these areas will have to depend either
on a large scale import of fuel or on using nuclear energy.
In view of the markedly low cost of energy In nuclear
fuel the necessity to import fuel in very big amounts
will itself tip the balance In favour of going In for nuclear
energy. Thus, we come to the conclusion that the full
industrialization of the underdeveloped areas will in the
long run take place only on the basis of atomic energy,
whether the fuel is Imported or obtained indlgeneously.
If the generation of electricity from nuclear energy is
not already much cheaper than from conventional fuels
it is entirely because the technology is still In its Infancy
and the cost of plant required to utilize nuclear fuel Is
greater than the cost of plant required to use conventional
fuel. However, the cost of nuclear power stations has
been coming down rapidly, so much so that In many
areas of the world electricity from atomic energy has
already become competitive with electricity from conven¬
tional fuels. A major portion of India, which is remote
from the coal fields, falls within this category, and cer¬
tain high fuel cost regions of the United States are prob¬
ably also In the same class.
I n conclusion It Is necessary to make a few
general observations. Should a study oí the
economics of the situation In a particular underdeveloped
area show that it would be expedient to go In for nuclear
production, this could be done Initially on the basis of
imported equipment. It is neither necessary nor desirable
for every such country to go In Immediately for the design
and manufacture of nuclear equipment, as the necessary
technical effort may well take away scarce personnel from
more urgent problems.
On the other hand, every new Industrial project,
whether in the nuclear field or otherwise, should b"e made
the starting point for the training of personnel, not only
for operating such plants but for wider purposes. Each
industry should be used to make its contribution directly
and indirectly towards the development of technical
personnel in a wider context than merely required for its
operation.
It is not necessary for every country, especially a small
one, to produce everything, but it must be able to produce
some things containing a high technological content
which can be sold in return for other things which may
be needed. A balance cannot be maintained only by
trading raw materials for industrial equipment. In the
last analysis, the most important asset of the highly
industrialized countries is their educated and trained
manpower in all fields, in particular their large number
of scientists, technologists and skilled labour. It Is this
resource which the underdeveloped countries must build
for themselves as quickly as possible, if they are to cease
lagging behind, and to pull their own weight In the
forward march of humanity.
Homi Jehangir Bhabha is one of India's most distinguished men
of science. Chairman of the Indian Atomic Energy Commission
since 1961, he is also a member of the U.N. Scientific Advisory
Committee and was president of the first International Conference
on the Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy in 1955. He gained
distinction through his original research in theoretical nuclear
physics and in particular on the quantum theory and on cosmic
radiation.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
-«#
v>.
./
T~*
T
r i » i i i i "i1" » m
18
World Bank Mauritania, a largely desert country in northwest Africa, is twice the size of France, but has a population
of less than one million. Today, new opportunities for economic growth in Mauritinia have been created
by the discovery of one of the world's richest deposits of high-quality iron ore near Fort Gouraud in the
Sahara. A $66 million loan from the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development is helping
Mauritania to build a township in the mining area, port installations at Port Etienne on the Atlantic
Coastanda railwayfedfromstockpilesofrailslike thesewhichwill link Port Etienne with Fort Gouraud.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
INDEX OF PROSPERITY
(Scientific & Technical Potential)
by Victor A. Kovda
Ocience is the most dynamic cultural force in the modern world. The
^impact of science has revolutionized habits of dress, speech, travel and
communication, cities and villages. At a deeper level it has affected philo¬
sophy through its new concepts of causality. And by making human want
technologically obsolete it has brought into relief the moral responsibility
of its use for constructive rather than destructive ends. A country without
scientists and engineers cannot be in the main stream of modern life.
A developing country can begin to meet its most imme¬
diate economical needs by importing scientists from
abroad, but it will never be really independent until It
has created its own national pool of highly trained scien¬
tists and engineers, and its own scientific institutions.
The economic progress out of which the cultural well-
being of a country will grow depends to a great extent
upon natural resources : climate and topography, flora and
fauna, soil and water, and mineral riches. Therefore the
very first requirement is scientific knowledge of a country's
natural environment and its resources. A detailed know¬
ledge of geographical conditions and energy sources, for
example, must precede economic and industrial planning.
This scientific knowledge can be obtained only through
a series of systematic studies and surveys of natural
resources. This is a task of paramount Importance be¬
cause it can provide both the basis for the elaboration, of
economically profitable schemes of exploitation and for
rational plans of conservation.
The number and type of resources having economic
importance are very variable, depending on the natural
history of the territory and of the continent where the
country is located. It is characteristic for natural re¬
sources to be distributed very irregularly. Thus we find
a concentration of important mineral deposits in one
country and a total absence of the same type of deposits
in a neighbouring country.
The experience of the scientifically advanced countries
shows that no country is really "poor In natural resour¬
ces" In the absolute sense. The absence of one resource
can be compensated for by the presence of another no
less valuable, but this obviously requires the development
of human resources, of the Individuals within the country
who are capable of directing both studies and development
because they have the scientific knowledge to do so.
One of the most Important of the new concepts which
Unesco Is now using Is that of a country's scientific and
technical potential or S.T.P. S.T.P. Is the totality of a
country's resources for formulating and solving problems
of national, regional and International importance in the
field of science and the application of science.
In determining a nation's S.T.P. six factors have to be
considered:
The number of scientists and engineers. We have
suggested that an index should be established showing the
number of scientists per million population. The more
developed countries have from 500 to 4,000 scientists per
million population. If we take as a target for the scien¬
tifically less developed an average of 1,000 scientists per
million population, then a country with a population of
5 million should have 5,000 scientists; one with a popula¬
tion of 30 million should have 30,000 scientists; a continent
with a population of 200 million should have 200,000
scientists.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
ENGINEERS
FOR IRAN'S
NEW INDUSTRIES
Future engineers for Iran's new industries are seen
here on the grounds of the Teheran Polytechnic during
a break in classes. Left, a brunette Iranian teacher
explains the operation of textile machinery to students.
Far right, a Unesco expert in a practical course on
textile engineering. The Polytechnic was set up with
Unesco and U.N. Special Fund aid. Unesco has
provided specialists in building construction and in
textile, electrical and mechanical engineering. It has
awarded fellowships to Iranians in these fields and has
supplied large quantities of equipment. The Poly¬
technic has four Institutes where special emphasis is
placed on practical skills not only in workshop and
laboratory work, but in actual training within industry.
S.T.P. (Cont'd)
inimum target : 1,000 scientists
per million population
20
Judging from the experience of the most developed
industrial countries, the number of engineers should be
from five to ten times as great. The United States, with
a population of 185 million, has 1,000 scientists per million
population and 4,000 engineers per million population.
The Soviet Union, with a population of 200 million, has
1,800 scientists and 20,000 engineers and agronomists per
million population. France, with a population of 46,000,000
had (in 1955) 360 scientists and 2,608 engineers per million
population.
These figures can be used by any country to estimate its
ultimate needs for scientists and engineers. But to
achieve this proportion will take one or two generations.
The number and equipment of national research insti¬
tutes. The next index of a country's S.T.P. is the number,
equipment and system of organization of national research
institutes, universities and laboratories. We are studying
this question and propose to publish monographs on the
organization of science in a number of typical countries,
such as Belgium, Czechoslovakia and Norway. Talks are
also taking place with India and the Ukraine. The more
numerous and the better equipped a country's scientific
institutes are the greater is that country's S.T.P.
It is also important to know whether a country has
research centres in mathematics, physics, chemistry,
mining and geology, chemical technology, economics and
statistics.
National production of scientific apparatus, measuring
instruments and special equipment. This index illustrates
a country's capacity constantly to renew and improve the
scientific apparatus and equipment needed for research.
Scientific equipment becomes obsolete approximately every
ten to fifteen years, and has to be replaced by new, more
improved types. Today, production of scientific apparatus
and precision instruments is mainly concentrated in
twelve to fifteen of the most developed countries.
At the present stage of scientific development, it is very
important that a country should be able, if not to produce,
at least to repair and service the technical equipment it
requires, for example, isotopes, electronic computers, tele¬
vision, and so on.
Network of scientific documentation centres. Scientific
libraries, microfilm libraries, map collections, scientific
museums, translation and bibliographical services are a
revealing index of a country's S.T.P.
The range and number of national scientific publica¬
tions. Periodicals, textbooks and works of scientific
popularization are another important element of a coun¬
try's scientific planning and research programmes.
Scientific vocabulary. The existence or lack of a
national scientific vocabulary, of a scientific terminology,
and of appropriate concepts in the national language are
another important index of a country's S.T.P.
A nation's level of literacy, the general level of educa¬
tion, and the extent to which education is compulsory
should also be taken into account. This does not mean
that all these factors are necessarily of equal importance
or incontrovertible, especially since it is not quantity so
much as quality which is the decisive factor. Unesco
will intensify research in this field, and in particular will
attempt to determine the absolute and relative importance
of all these factors, which constitute a nation's S.T.P.
A national scientific policy may be defined as a system
of measures taken by a government to carry out a long-
term (fifteen to twenty-five years) programme for science
and its applications aimed at achieving the maximum
socio-economic and cultural effects for the benefit of its
people. In this sense a national scientific policy becomes
an integral part of the government's economic policy.
Many of the countries which have recently attained
independence are endeavouring to establish a network of
scientific establishments, to set up a guiding scientific
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Photos Unesco-Paul Almasy
body in the government, and to assign a regular part of
the budget to training scientists and to scientific research.
Unesco's Department of Natural Sciences is conducting
extensive studies of the existing situation with regard to
national scientific policies. Of Unesco's 113 Member
States, twenty-five do not now have any central bodies to
guide or co-ordinate the activities of scientific establish¬
ments. About thirty have relatively ineffective national
centres or councils responsible for the planning and
development of science.
n increasing number of requests are being re¬
ceived from the governments of Unesco
Member States for assistance in preparing legislation for
the establishment of national scientific councils, centres
or academies. For instance, at the time of the opening
of the Geneva Conference, the Parliament and President
of the Republic of Lebanon approved a law (prepared
with the help of Unesco) establishing a national council
for the direction of science in that country.
We feel that assistance to governments in working out
national scientific policy and scientific organization will
be one of Unesco's most Important tasks during the next
few years. We are already helping several governments
to prepare appropriate legislation and programmes, as in
the case of Lebanon.
The size of State expenditure on national scientific Ins¬
titutions is an equally important element of State policy
in the field of science. Every government should deter¬
mine the total financial outlay on science and Its
apportionment among basic, technical and social sciences.
The size of expenditure and its allocation depend, of
course, on the historical, social and natural conditions in
each particular country.
Economically and scientifically advanced countries
allocate from 1 to 5 percent of their annual national
income to development of science. European Industrializ¬
ed countries allocate on an average 2.5 per cent of the
national income. Some large countries which have
recently achieved Independence spend about 0.25 per cent
of the national income on science, but most of the Inde¬
pendent countries of Asia, Africa and Latin America
spend less.
Available statistics obviously do not show the full
picture. Further research and improved methods of
collection, processing and also evaluation of the available
figures are necessary. But even now It is safe to say that
the less developed countries do not spend enough on
science. Much greater eilorts are required of the
countries themselves and of the International organiza¬
tions of the United Nations family.
The third basic element of national policy In the field
of science is the laying down of the main lines of scientific
research, the planned creation of scientific Institutions on
a long-term basis, the establishment of priorities and time
limits, having regard to the economic and natural condi¬
tions of the country and Its Individual regions. This is
particularly Important in the case of large multinational
States with vast territories and a heterogeneous popula¬
tion.
The assessment of immediate and long-term require¬
ments as regards the training of scientific staff and
teachers is the further Important element of State pol¬
icy In the field of science. The growth and development
of science are inseparable from the creative activity of
the scientist. The talents and working capacity of the
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO EXPANDS ITS
HE United Nations Dev¬
elopment Decade has set
out to mobilize the world's technologi¬
cal and economic resources in a vast,
peaceful offensive in support of dev¬
eloping countries in all parts of the
world. Following the United Nations
Conference on the Application of
Science and Technology for the Bene¬
fit of the Less-Developed Areas, held
in Geneva last February, Unesco is
now reshaping its activities and its
thinking in order to play its part in this
offensive.
The UNCSAT Conference in Geneva
clearly brought out the fact that the
"application of science and technolo¬
gy" is not keeping pace with the pre¬
sent growth of the world's new nations.
It is the urgency of this problem creat¬
ed by the ever-increasing immediate
and long-term needs of the developing
countries that has led Unesco to plan
a reinforcement of its activities in
science and technology for the bene¬
fit of these nations.
As presently proposed by Unesco's
Director-General, Mr. René Maheu, the
new Unesco programme (for 1965-66)
will give to science an importance simi¬
lar to that now accorded to education.
Unesco's budget for science, techno¬
logy and their applications will amount
to about $7.3 million for two years as
compared with $4.3 million for the cur¬
rent programme. About 60% of the
budget will be concentrated on acti¬
vities of direct importance to dev¬
eloping countries, helping them to set
up national scientific and technolo¬
gical institutions and universities, to
make studies of natural resources and
to train engineers, research workers and
university professors. '
To carry out this vastly expanded
work new units will be created within
Unesco to direct a multi-sided pro
gramme in science teaching at all levels,
in research and training in the en¬
gineering sciences and in studies and
training related to natural resources.
Unesco's reinforced Department of
Natural Sciences will then have broadly
two main responsibilities: the interna¬
tional promotion of science and the ap¬
plication of science to problems of eco¬
nomic development. In addition, a post
of Assistant Unesco Director-General
for Science and Technology will be set
up.
Moreover, Unesco will be able to
count on financial and organizational
help from the United Nations Technical
Assistance Programme and the United
Nations Special Fund which are expect¬
ed to provide, through Unesco, bet¬
ween 20 and 25 million dollars during
1965-66. This will make possible the
creation of new faculties and institu¬
tions, the recruitment of specialists and
the purchase of equipment.
The new programme was considered
in broad outline by Unesco's Executive
Board in May and will be given further
study by the Board in October. In its
final form the expanded plan will be
submitted for approval to the Unesco
General Conference in 1964.
Its adoption, however, will in no way
diminish Unesco's continually evolving
programme in the field of international
scientific co-operation. About 40%
of the expanded regular budget for
science will be devoted to the basic
and earth sciences.
The new programme proposes a
considerable expansion of international
activities in astronomy, atmospheric
sciences, geology, ecology and pedo¬
logy. A reinforced and expanded pro¬
gramme in the life sciences in bio¬
logy and brain research, for example
will be carried out. Research in outer
space sciences and oceanography will
be maintained and expanded. An im¬
portant new project in scientific hydro¬
logy The International Hydrological
Decade, which will be of long-term
value to all countries will be started.
In drawing up its plans for 1965-66,
Unesco has taken into consideration
many of the facts and the recommen¬
dations received from national, regional
and international scientific organizations
as well as from special advisory groups.
Many valuable suggestion were offered
by an advisory committee which met
in Paris in April to discuss specifically
Unesco's role and functions in the use
of science for economic development.
This committee brought together top-
level scientists and technologists from
seven countries under the chairman¬
ship of Prof. M. S. Thacker, of the
Indian Government's Planning Com¬
mission, who presided over the UNCSAT
Conference in Geneva (1).
Noting that Unesco is the only U.N.
Agency with a general mandate in the
field of science and that as such it
has an extremely important role to play,
this committee declared that increased
emphasis should be placed upon
science and technology not only in
view of economic development, but also
as a component of education and of
culture.
The committee urged Unesco to em¬
phasize technological and scientific edu¬
cation at all levels and in all branches,
from the secondary to the post-univer¬
sity level. It asked Unesco to continue
its aid to countries establishing national
research councils and other similar poli¬
cy-making bodies. Unesco should fur¬
ther encourage local scientists to share
in the work of international scientific and
technological associations and foster
increased interest by these associations
of problems facing developing areas.
S.T.P. (Cont'd^
The head and eyes of science
22
scientist are precious qualities which must first be recog¬
nized and brought out in a young man or woman and
then developed and trained.
Plans for the training of scientists and university
professors must always be prepared and carried out well
ahead of current needs and in anticipation of future
needs. It is necessary, for example, to allow for the
inevitable elimination of some students and scientific
workers in the initial stages. The Increasing need for
scientific staff follows a geometrical progression, and this
too must be met.
Of 100 boys and girls in schools, only ten to fifteen will
attend a university. Of 100 university students only ten
to fifteen are likely to become scientists if they are given
the opportunity. But of 100 scientists perhaps only two
or three will be innovators of outstanding merit and
significance in science.
If a student is to grow into a true and creative scientist,
he will need fifteen to twenty and sometimes twenty-five
years for education and training and also to learn how to
work as an individual researcher.
As part of its national policy in science and technology,
each country must decide what proportion of theoretical
scientists and technical experts it wishes to have in
various branches and special subjects. Each country,
however, will always require good mathematicians, phy¬
sicists, chemists, geologists, geographers, biologists and
technical experts.
The Department of Natural Sciences of Unesco, together
with international associations of scientists is preparing
optimum types of scientific curricula, and suggestions for
laboratory equipment and educational experiments to
assist less-developed countries in establishing faculties
of science and in training scientists in the basic branches
of learning.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE PROGRAMME
United Nations
The Central African Institute of
Scientific Research at Liviro, Repub¬
lic of the Congo (Leopoldville)
boasts one of the best equipped
seismologicai and geophysical labor¬
atories in all Africa. Here a team
of Unesco specialists inspects the
observatory installations there dur¬
ing a recent tour which they made
of scientific research and training
facilities in ten African countries.
Today Unesco is making a large re¬
appraisal of its resources in science so
as to give maximum support to the
vast United Nations effort that is
implied by the Geneva Conference.
However, the urgency of the problems
evoked by that Conference were recog¬
nized by Unesco's General Conference
three years ago, when it approved a
ten-year programme for science,
stressing the special importance of all
forms of assistance, through science
and technology, for the accelerated
industrialization of developing coun¬
tries.
The Conference named three priori¬
ties in this ten-year (1960-70) pro¬
gramme.
Co-ordination of scientific activities
on both national and international
levels ;
Exploration of the earth, methods for
drawing up an inventory of natural
resources, and the study of scien¬
tific problems related to the exploi¬
tation of these resources.
Application of science and techno¬
logy for industrialization.
In Unesco's current (1963-64) pro¬
gramme for science, all forms of assis¬
tance to Member States for the creation
of national scientific institutions, univer¬
sities, industrial research laboratories
and polytechnic institutes, have been
greatly increased in comparison with
past years. About 250 specialists are
now working in research and training
institutes that are being established
with the aid of Unesco and the United
Nations. Between 30 and 35 new scien¬
tific institutions, faculties of engineering
and applied research centres are being
created with Unesco's help and the use
of U.N. special funds.
While looking to the future and plan¬
ning its action on a new scale and with
greater scope, Unesco can now draw
on a decade of working experience in
this field.
Institutions like the Indian Institute of
Technology in Bombay or the Middle
East Technical University at Ankara
show what can be achieved by large-
scale national effort (in this case by
India and Turkey) with a backing of
international technological aid supplied
by Unesco.
Unesco specialists have trained geo¬
logists who are working to solve the
water problems of Brazil's Polygon of
Drought, they have taught physics In
Indonesia, they have gone to earth¬
quake-prone areas to advise on sound
construction methods for building and
public works and they have set up a
world network of centres to make avail¬
able the documentation which is the
lifeblood of science.
In these and many other ways,
Unesco is working to accomplish aid
programmes in scientific research and
training and in the applications of scien¬
tific and technological knowledge. It Is
thus responding to requests for aid
from many newly-independent countries
who realize that real political and eco¬
nomic independence can only be achie¬
ved by the parallel creation of scien¬
tific institutions and universities carrying
out research and studies on vital prob¬
lems related to economic and cultural
welfare.
(11 Other member» of the committee were:
Prot. Harrison Brown, of the California Insti¬
tute of Technology, In the U.S.A. : Mr. Ray¬
mond Cheradame, director of studies at the
Ecole Polytechnique In Paris : Professor
V.C. Emlllanov. head of the U.S.S.R. Agency
for the Utilization of Atomic Ensrgy : Dr. Ro¬
lando Victor Garcia, dean of the Faculty of
Sciences, University of Buenos Aires: Prof.
James Grelg. of the University of London:
Dr. Eni Nloku. vice-chancellor of the Nigerian
Federal University at Lagos; and Lord Todd
of Cambridge University.
Is the most ultra-modern equipment (automation, elec¬
tronics, radio-isotopes, television, etc.) really needed for
industrializing the less-developed countries and for
developing their economy and science? Unesco has
studied this question and has concluded that these things
really are essential. The economic reconstruction of the
newly-independent countries will have to be completed
rapidly in the life-time of one or at the most two genera¬
tions. They must now bridge the gap separating them
from economically developed nations. Thus, Unesco
believes that the development of industry, transport, agri¬
culture and forestry should be based on economically
viable foundations which are scientifically and technically
the most advanced and also adapted to local conditions.
This view is shared by many Unesco Member States ; for
example India, whose Government has co-operated with
Unesco in establishing a first-class polytechnic institute
in Bombay; or Turkey, where a Middle East Technical
University is being established by Unesco and the Turkish
Government with the assistance of the United Nations
Special Fund. Institutes of the same kind and highly
developed scientific centres are being established co¬
operatively by national governments and Unesco. True,
this process is only just beginning. We shall have to
establish these centres not only by ones and twos but by
dozens, and in the future perhaps by hundreds.
The next question is whether or not there should be
any functional division between scientific research and
the application of scientific discoveries. What I have in
mind here is not economic Investment, nor the practical
aspects of Industrializationplanning for industrialization
and executing these plans. Obviously these are not
matters for Unesco. What I am thinking about is the
indivisibility of research, the training of a scientist or
an engineer, and the practical application of science In
the national economy.
It often happens that the application of science leads
to new theoretical discoveries or to new general theories.
It is the role of the scientist himself to suggest the best
possible ways of applying scientific discoveries in practice.
If we separate theory from practical application, science
will have lost its brain and eyes. If we separate reasoned
application from scientific theory, then the theory will
lose all meaning.
Victor A. Kovda is director of the Unesco Department of
Natural Sciences. A soil scientist, he is a corresponding
member of the U.S.S.R. Academy of Sciences.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
330 MILLION BR
A fully-equipped language-teaching laboratory complete with separate booths, tape-
recorders and playback machines is now used at the University of Dakar in Senegal.
Paul Almasy. Paus
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
AINS FOR A NEW ERA
by René Maheu
Director-General of Unesco
When looked at from the standpoint of educa¬
tion the major factor underlying underdeve¬
lopment is the absence, for much of a given population,
of the minimum of schooling required to learn those
basic signs and characters which are the key to the Intel¬
lectual and technical creations of our civilization. This
major factor, in short, is illiteracy.
There are today an estimated 700 million adults or
more than two-fifths of the world's total populationwho
are illiterate (the word adult here being taken to mean
persons 15 years of age or older). And it is in the less
developed regions that most of these adult illiterates
live.
As for children of primary school age (5 to 15 years),
47 per cent did not attend school during 1960 in the
countries of Latin America, Africa, the Middle East and
Asia. If we add to this figure those children who are
going to school now but who will drop out before they
master reading and writing and hence will grow up
Illiterate, we can say that there are today 150 million
future illiterates in these countries and that there will
be an additional 20 to 25 million illiterates added to the
world's adult population in the next 6 or 7 years.
It is in the light of this general context of educational
under-development that the special problem of training
scientific and technical personnel in the less developed
regions must be viewed.
First of all let me emphasize what a frightful loss of
mindpower these hundreds of millions of illiterates repre¬
sent for technological progress. Who can say how many
scientists, engineers and technicians potentially existed
among all these forsaken adults as well as the children
consigned from birth to the shadows of ignorance.
There is certainly no need for me to make the point
that an illiterate person never ceases to be a human
being endowed with his own natural dignity and ability.
I have personally known individuals who, despite the
fact that they were illiterate, possessed unusual intelli¬
gence, keen judgement and a high standard of culture.
The realm of signs and characters does not encompass
the whole gamut of human experience. Nevertheless,
illiteracy by the very fact that it makes science and
technology a closed book makes active participation in
modern civilization impossible. The millions of illiterates
I have referred to submit to history, they do not make it.
The question then Is raisedwhy isn't a big
International campaign started to help these
countries to get rid of this blight, since to allow it to
continue is an absurdity in terms of economic efficiency
as much as it is a disgrace on the moral conscience of the
world. Unesco considers that the political, economic and
technical conditions are at the present time such as to
make a campaign of this kind possible, if we so desire it.
At the end of last year, after a series of consultations
with many experts on the question, I submitted a plan
to the Unesco General Conference for making some
300 million adults between the ages of 15 and 50 literate
within 10 years. The plan applied to illiterates living In
Africa, Asia and Latin America.
The real question is, are we willing to undertake such
a job? We cannot blink the fact that it will be a very
expensive operation. Unesco has calculated that It will
cost about 1,900 million dollars for the ten years, four-
fifths of which will have to come from national budgets.
But Is it not much more expensive to allow 330 million
brains to go to waste? And are there not other types
of expenditure which are also very costly but which our
planet could well afford to do without?
A country with a high percentage of Illiterates does
not only suffer an Intrinsic loss in terms of wasted man
and mindpower; the progress of the educated segment
of the population is equally slowed down and made more
difficult. It Is a well-established fact that the degree
of education of the adult population as a whole has
a direct bearing on the lasting effects of the education
given to children In school.
We can no longer afford to have, as we unfortnately
do in many of the developing countries, an enormous
gulf separating one group or generation from another,
that is, those who have had a full, modern education
from those who are illiterate. Such an unhealthy state
of affairs disrupts the equilibrium and unity of a country
and completely defeats any effort to create a nation-wide
positive attitude toward scientific thinking and technology
without which there can be no real development.
n educational system Is or purports to be an
^organic whole, both intellectually and admi¬
nistratively, the different parts of which at their various
levels are mutually dependent and Intrinsically related.
Hence It is neither desirable nor possible to plan the
Improvement or expansion of one particular stage
of education in Isolation from all the others. Obviously
this does not mean that emphasis and resources must be
equally divided throughout the entire school system.
Priorities do exist, depending on the circumstances and
situation of a country, and these of course make for
differences. But It does mean that no serious reform
should be contemplated or carried out even in a priority
area of the school programme except within the frame¬
work of an overall reform of the educational system as
a whole.
In my oplntion there is one principle which Is basic
to the organic unity of education and Its administration,
namely, that the general always conditions and prepares
the specialized. In the context of our discussion this
means that specialized technical training always presup¬
poses a general technical education Just as this in turn
implies a grounding in general science. And general
science too must itself be viewed as an integral part of
general education.
To turn now to the -question of educational planning
as a national policy, I am convinced that such planning
is not only justified but absolutely Indispensable. Three
considerations lead me to make this statement.
In the first place educational planning follows logically
from the idea I have just referred to, namely, the organic
unity of education. For obviously If students are to
advance rationally from one stage of education to another
within a total framework there must be some kind of
plan.
Secondly, planning carries with it the very great advan-
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
BRAINS FOR A NEW ERA (Cont'd)
Education's new role in a modern society
tage of not neglecting the importance of time as a factor
in education, first determining the time available and then
putting it to the best advantage. Educational planning,
therefore, has a special added function for the developing
countries, that of providing a much-needed standard or
yardstick to gauge the future.
In these countries, where the past offered little oppor¬
tunity for advancement, where the present is fraught
with impatience and the future charged with emotion,
educational planning serves as a measure of caution
since the practical necessity of making the best use of
available resources Is usually out of all proportion to
actual needs. But it also commends itself, perhaps even
to a greater extent, as an invaluable mental exercise to
prepare the way for the building of a sound future. It
serves as a reminder to the developing countries that
anything at all cannot happen at any time whatever
and that even acceleration must obey the rule of rhythm
and order.
Thirdly, educational planning Is now being increasingly
recognized as an Integral part of the planning of eco¬
nomic and social development as a whole; an essential
part since it is basic to all the others and so broad in
scope, but nonetheless only a part, which should be
perceived as such. When it is so integrated, educational
planning is of the greatest value in helping a country
speed up its development since it becomes possible to
gear the educational system to the specific needs and
potentialities of the nation. This is especially true for
the training of scientific and technical personnel for
they are the ones who will be most directly involved in
the actual development process.
One of the most striking and encouraging aspects of
the change taking place in the world's educational
thinking in recent years has been the growing recog¬
nition of precisely this threefold need for educational
planning.
Unesco Is proud of the part it has played here and
will intensify its activities in this priority area of Its
programme. This year, for Instance, Unesco is setting
up an international institute with the specific purpose
of training top-level specialists and promoting research
in educational planning; and its regional centres now in
operation" or about to start functioning, mostly in con¬
junction with the planning institutes of the U.N. Regional
Economic Commissions, have the same purpose. I am
certain that these institutions will all play a tremendous
role in advancing the theory and practice of educational
planning which is still in its infancy, and will be able
to help the member countries of Unesco' in setting up
their own national centres and in training their own
leaders in this field.
. knowledge of what the organic unity of the
»education system implies together with metho¬
dical planning these then are the frames of reference
and the basic requisites for any realistic approach to the
special problems facing the less developed countries in
the training of scientific and technical personnel.
Broadly speaking, there are three areas of major diffi¬
culty education, university training and
methods of science teaching.
Probably the greatest need for expansion and impro¬
vement lies in the field of technical and vocational
education, particularly at the secondary school level
since this is certainly the part of the school system of
the most immediate importance for the growth of the
26 developing countries.
Here Unesco has devoted considerable effort in recent
years to helping the developing countries in two different
ways : by working on international standards for technical
education, and by direct aid in the field. For three
full years a Unesco team of experts studied the question
of standards, and in 1962 the Unesco General Conference
approved the terms of an international Recommendation
one section of which specifically deals with standards of
scientific and technical education. The drafting of this
Recommendation was carried out in consultation with the
International Labour Office concurrently with the revision
of a similar Recommendation on vocational education by
the International Labour Organization.
I n its operation activities in the field, Unesco
has been giving its member states direct aid
in setting up or developing national schools for post-
secondary or higher technical education, thanks to large
financial contributions made by the U.N. Special Fund.
At present Unesco is the Special Fund's executive agency
for 22 projects (totalling about $24,500,000) for the estab¬
lishment of trade schools and higher institutes of tech¬
nology. This work, on what I would call the general
technology level supports and serves as a basic foundation
for that of the other bodies of the U.N. family who are
engaged in specialized technological training in specific
fields.
As for the role of universities in training senior scien¬
tific and technical personnel, the importance of which
cannot be stressed too strongly, it varies considerably
since conditions in the less developed countries are by
no means uniform.
In certain countries the problem is chiefly one of
quantity. Here the key word is shortage: a shortage of
universities, a shortage of instructors and professors, a
shortage of equipment, mainly laboratory equipment,
even a shortage at times of adequately prepared students
arising from the inadequacies of secondary education.
In other countries the problem is chiefly one of quality,
that is, lack of organization and guidance services with
the result that higher education is poorly adapted to the
needs of a modern economy and technology. Thus most
of the university students in these countries are advised
to prepare for degrees in traditional subjects; and those
who do major in science and technology often do so by
chance or for personal reasons that have little to do with
the real top-priority problems of economic and social
development in their country.
As a result, though these countries can boast eminent
scientists in no way inferior to those of the more deve¬
loped countries, such men are few in number and lack
sufficient fellow scientists and technicians to work with
them or under them and on whom they can count or who
can follow in their footsteps. In other words what is
missing is the rank and file for the teams of scientists
which are now becoming a standard feature of scientific
work and a prerequisite for optimum results.
And so, though we find a need for new universities in
one place,, for expansion in another and reform elsewhere,
everywhere the development of universities remains an
urgent, vital problem. Foreign study grants or scholarships
no matter how generously endowed or wisely planned can
never really compensate for the basic deficiencies I have
just outlined. The evil of underdevelopment must be
attacked at its very root by creating national structures
for training qualified personnel where they do not exist
and strengthening and improving them where they do.
In the present state of things in the world there is no
question but that study abroad is absolutely essential.
But if practised indiscriminately it has a serious drawback
in that it separates the fellowship holder from his native
land and environment and may eventually detach him
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
from his own country and its needs. In point of fact it
often happens that the student who goes abroad finds it
difficult to fit into the pattern of his home country for
psychological, social or economic reasons. He rarely uses
more than a fraction of the knowledge and techniques
acquired abroad after his return. Sometimes he simply
never returns, and so an erosion or drainlng-off process
begins with the most talented minds migrating from the
underdeveloped nations to the developed ones.
In reality training abroad is required chiefly to enable
technicians and other specialists of an advanced or even
professional level to acquire additional technological skills,
and as such serves its full purpose only as an adjunct of
the studies carried out at home within the pattern of the
nation's cultural, economic and social requirements.
If a country Is to build a sound foundation for its tech¬
nological development it is of paramount Importance that
science be taught in the schools at every level. For the
point cannot be too often made that only meagre, super¬
ficial and short-lived progress can be achieved by the
acquisition of technical skills or knowledge when the
people of a nation are almost untutored in science. The
real basis for development is a scientific civilization.
Merely importing techniques without the science which
This wide-eyed Philippines schoolgirl is one of the world's
lucky children. In countries of Latin America, Africa, the
Middle East and Asia, 47% of the children of school age
have no schools to attend. This is the measure of under¬
development in education which each year condemns
millions of children to adult ¡lliteray. How many potential
scientists, engineers and technicians are thereby lost?
Unesco - Pierre A. Pittet
r
produces and serves them will not in Itself equip the
underdeveloped countries for the full utilization of their
natural and human resources whereby they hope to
achieve their great transformation. And though the
Importing of techniques results in a number of immediate
improvements in certain domains It prolongs and rein¬
forces the state of dependency of the general economy
of these countries.
Now It can hardly be denied that, as a general rule,
there are many things wrong with science teaching In
the underdeveloped countries and that something must
be done about it as quickly as possible.
Too often there is a tendency In science classes to
overstress the Importance of knowledge as such, especially
practical knowledge, to the detriment of scientific thinking
and the scientific attitude of mind. As a result very little
of the real scientific attitude Is more than superficially
apparent In the thinking of the technical and other super¬
visory personnel who occupy subordinate and Intermediate
positions in society. In most cases the only thing learned
from science is a series of formulas and prescriptions
applied mechanically and unthinkingly.
Teaching of this sort, which puts exercise of memory
before the cultivation of the mind seems closer to tralned-
seal-learning than to genuine education. It is the very
antithesis of science which seeks In essence to achieve
the liberation of the mind as well as the mastery of
nature... In the same manner It Is the antithesis of
everything that the less-developed countries require
most in order to regain control of their own destinies.
here is much talk of the disequilibrium and
tensions brought about In these countries by
the conflict between the Imported scientific and techno¬
logical civilization and the traditional national cultures.
This certainly constitutes a problem such as arises when¬
ever a society is subjected to a process of swift change
under the impact of outside factors. But the resultant
conflict and tensions are chiefly due to the fact that
science does not appear to these countries In Its true guise,
that Is, as a civilizationIndeed the only civilization of
potential universalitybut as a kind of alien magic
imparting sudden power. And if the civilization aspect of
science is not apparent to those whose eyes are chiefly
fixed on its more practical technological consequences, it Ls
fundamentally because the heart of the matterthe .scien¬
tific spirit and its methodsis neglected In the teaching of
science.
This teaching ls particularly defective as regards the
practice of the experimental method and the understand¬
ing of its significance as a general mental discipline.
Training In the experimental method, which ls the most
effective initiation to modern civilization for both young
minds and young societies ardently desirous of progress,
must contend with many obstacles In these countries.
Some are due to local circumstances In that there is
often a distressing shortage of even the most essential
laboratory equipment for schools and universities, and
purchases and gifts are not always wisely made.
But the educational system ls responsible for other
obstacles which are no less serious for being less directly
apparent and can be overcome only by sustained effort.
In many cases, curricula are ill-conceived, textbooks and
teachers' handbooks are not suited to local conditions,
either material or psychological, and the training of
teachers leaves a very great deal to be desired, turning
to little account the substantial progress made over the
past few years In both the psychology and technology
of education. In all these spheres, Unesco Is at pains to
promote and back up the efforts of Its member states.
Everywhere the results are heartening, but like the funds
available, they are limited. Far greater resources must
be marshalled by international aid for this vital contri¬
bution to progress.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
TV LESSONS
FOR 1,500
COLOMBIAN
SCHOOLS
n^Tziiii'
Colombia boasts the largest TV network in all Latin America.
This year a special transmitter. Televisora Educativa, will begin
to televise a series of educational programmes to classrooms of
1,500 schools, many of them in isolated villages high up in the
Andes. More than half Colombia's population lives in rugged
mountain terrain, but TV engineers have overcome communica¬
tions problems this presents by siting transmission stations
high up on the mountain sides. Today TV programmes cover
90 % of the country. New experimental and teacher-training
telecasts are due to begin this autumn and the regular school
programmes next February. Above, announcer introduces an
educational programme which is followed (left) on studio control
panel. Right, studio teacher in "What do we know?" programme.
BRAINS FOR A NEW ERA (Cont'd)
Catching up with science's dizzy pace
28
However, it is questionable whether, even If national
efforts and foreign aid, both bilateral and international,
are stepped up considerably, the educational system, as
it ls run at present and with its existing teaching methods,
ls capable of meeting the tremendous quantitative and
qualitative needs of technological development In
our modern era of population explosion and quickened
scientific progress.
To this question, which it is the duty of educational
leaders to ponder most seriously, I for one must resolutely
answer no. I do not believe that the educational system,
with its present organization and methods, can meet the
demands of the growth of our civilization in the developed
countries, let alone those in the underdeveloped areas. It
is far too costly In terms of money and still more so in
terms of qualified personnel, and the returns are not high
enough.
Education cannot make its full and decisive contribu¬
tion to the technological revolution which must take place
in the less developed countries unless it Itself drastically
overhauls its own technology, which in many respects
is out of date.
Changes are needed both in the utilization of staff and
in the use of teaching aids.
So far as staff is concerned, we all know what a long
and costly process the training of teachers is at no matter
what level. There can be no question of economizing in
this vital field; far from it. But it is rational to keep
such qualified personnel for the most vital tasks in educa¬
tion. Experience has shown that for the performance
of other duties, assistants, with a far less advanced train¬
ing, are quite adequate. The savings made in this way
may be quite considerable.
Even the machines now being tried out for programmed
instruction, by increasing the contribution made by the
pupil's or student's own efforts, reduce proportionately the
need for personal coaching by the teacher and thus enable
him to concentrate on the truly decisive steps in educa¬
tion.
As for teaching aids, the audio-visual media for the
recording and dissemination of information that have
been created by modern technology over the past fifty
years and ' are constantly being perfected open up for
school and university education as well as for the out-
of-school education of young people and adults tremen¬
dous possibilities as yet insufficiently explored and only
half-heartedly exploited. It Is undoubtedly at this point
that the all too belated technological revolution of modern
education should be carried through, particularly in those
fields relating to scientific and technical training.
Nowhere is the wholesale, systematic use of audio¬
visual media more natural and surer of having a strong
psychological impact than in those countries where,
owing to the high proportion of illiterates, the image and
the spoken word are the traditional media for the acquisi¬
tion, preservation and appreciation of knowledge. The
cinema, radio and television not to overlook such Valu¬
able teaching aids as filmstrips and the gramophone
have demonstrated over and over, again how potent they
are as means of conveying ideas, imparting knowledge, and
expressing emotions and passions, too. Educators must
lose no further time in discovering what the professional
entertainers and political propagandists have already
found out in other fields, the vital part these media can
play in the progress of education in the developing
countries.
After considering the question of the training of scienti¬
fic and technical personnel against the general back¬
ground of educational underdevelopment, on the one hand,
and of the educational system on the other, one must also
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
view it in the light of the demands of science Itself and
of its offshoot technology.
The inexorable consequence of the quickened pace of
progress in knowledge, is the speedwhich increases with
each higher* degree of specialization with which the
content of scientific education and technical training
becomes' unusable. I mean that the knowledge and prac¬
tices acquired through this education and training are
being ever more rapidly outstripped by the constant
advance of science and technology and must accordingly
be revised and renewed. We have taken quite a long time
to realize this, but in one generation the phenomenon has
assumed such proportions that by now it has revolution¬
ized the position of scientific and technical education.
The obligation to keep scientific and technical know¬
ledge constantly up to date affects teachers and taught
alike. Teachers, particularly those at the university level
or those concerned with specialized technology, must
increasingly be prepared to attend intensive training and
refresher courses. The same applies, with even greater
force to those actually engaged in technical work. As
for the general educated public which merely aspires to
understanding the scientific factors underlying modern
civilization, and accordingly to keeping in a position to
play an active part in the life of this civilization, a veri¬
table permanent education must now be planned and
organized for it. In neither case can scientific and tech¬
nical education stop short at the end of their formal
studies.
Does this mean that these studies should be extended
and diversified so as to cover all the ever-growing expanse
of science itself? Not at all. This would be an utterly
exhausting and fruitless endeavour for schools and uni¬
versities, which are already showing all too many
symptoms of hypertrophy and take up too much time and
energy. No, they must deliberately confine themselves to
providing a relatively general training, leaving more spe¬
cialized knowledge to be acquired later in direct contact
with practical- life.
In my opinion it is not in schools or universities (though
both can continue to promote educational activities
beyond their scope) that this renewal or extension of
scientific education and technical training must be
effected. It must take place wherever the main part of
an adult's life and energies are spent at a place of work
and during leisure hours.
Places of work are ideal centres for specialized scientific
and technical education on a continuing basis. The major
undertakings are becoming increasingly aware of this
educational responsibility which they bear and which has
Incomparably wider implications than the immediate
concern of improving production and fostering harmonious
relations between employers and workers. This Ls a task
on a scale commensurate with modern society as a whole.
The fact Is that the major industrial and commercial
concerns are bound to assume more and more the cha¬
racter of specialized training establishments supplement¬
ing the work of schools and universities. The university,
far from ignoring or vying with them, is In duty bound
to keep In very close touch with them in order to stimulate
and guide them, for they are its natural extension.
As for the considerable amount of leisure made available
by industrialization. It ls being increasingly taken over or
at least controlled by the mass communication media.
It ls already clear that it ls from these media that the
vast majority of adults and even a proportion of those at
school and university derive the bulk of what I would
term their scientific and technical culture.
While the diversity of situations which distinguish the
less-developed countries from the industrialized ones call
for different approaches to the problems of development,
there are, however, no ways and means too novel or
modern for the less developed countries in applying the
solutions adopted for those problems. Quite the contrary.
And this is why the training of scientific and technical
personnel is so urgent a necessity for them. For on this
personnel depends whether or not they are to play a real
part on the contemporary scene.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
SENSIBLE SHOPPING IN THE
SUPERMARKET OF SCIENCE
by Patrick M.S. Blackett
Nobel Prize for Physics
'ROBLEMs of formulating practical and
realistic plans for the application of science
and technology today face the government of many a
newly emerging country. I specifically have in mind the
new African nations, since, for various historic reasons,
they are very short of trained manpower.
The first thing which must strike, say, the Prime
Minister or Minister of Finance of such a young nation,
ls that science and scientists are expensive and that their
financial demands clash with the innumerable other
demands on a country's very limited financial resources,
and still more limited foreign currency. Even in the field
of scientific and technical education alone, there will be
the choice to be made of the proper allocation of finance
between primary, secondary and higher education;
or between training science teachers, scientifically trained
administrators, research workers in pure and applied
science, and engineers and technologists. Then there are,
of course, the essential problems as to what the scientist
and technologist should be used for.
It is important to note that these main decisions have
to be made by the Government. For the Government
alone, in general, has the financial resources to carry out
any worthwhile programme. Even when financial aid
from other countries is available for specific educational
and scientific projects, government assessment and
approval will generally be necessary.
So today a great deal of very detailed decision-making
in the scientific and technical field will fall on the govern¬
ment of these newly-emerging countries, and just at a
time when vital political, economic, and social problems
have to be solved. It is evident that a high priority for
the educational system of an emerging country is the
training of an adequate number of scientifically and
technologically minded executives, able to make these
complex and difficult decisions.
Any minister or other high official from an emerging
country attending the U.N. conference on science and
technology will, no doubt, be in two minds about the vast
display of scientific and technological developments which
are dealt with in the hundreds of communications. On
the one hand, the conference will make clear the great
possibilities, inherent in modern scientific industrialization
and agriculture, for the raising of the material standards
of life of the emerging countries. On the other hand, it
will confront such a statesman or official with a frighten¬
ing number of decisions which must be taken. For, even
leaving new research and development out of account, the
sheer bulk of advanced technology which is available to
be bought in the world today, by a nation with the cash,
is staggering.
Even rich countries like the United Kingdom do not
buy every process, plant, machine tool or vehicle on sale.
How much more must this be true of the newly-emerging
countries, with their very limited resources both of finance
and of trained manpower! Their representatives may feel
like window-shoppers, admiring the riches of modern
technology through the plate glass window of their limited
resources in money and men. Moreover, when they have
some money in their pockets they must clearly be very
discriminating purchasers.
In considering the formulation of national policy in
30 relation to the application of science and technology to
the increase of material wealth, it is useful here to
distinguish three main aspects.
The first is that of known and available technology.
Most of the most urgent needs of the emerging countries
in the early stages of development come into this category.
To set up a motor bus service, it is necessary to have the
foreign exchange to buy the vehicles and fuel, and the
technical schools to train the drivers and repair personnel,
but no research or development at all is needed. Nor is
new research and development required to set up an
airline, or a television system, or an electricity supply, or
a sewage system and piped water supply, or the majority
of normal manufacturing plants.
Though such projects do not involve any appreciable
research and development, they do require a large supply
of technically and scientifically-trained personnel to run
them. A big increase of indigenous-trained scientific,
technological and administrative personnel will be needed
before a country can make full use of the known techno¬
logies without undue and expensive reliance on foreign
personnel. A major task of a new nation's educational
system must be to provide as soon as possible the necessary
technological intelligentsia to make use of all the known
and available technology which the country can afford to
buy.
Prominent among the vital tasks which such trained
people will have to tackle is the formulation of a sensible
"shopping list" I mean by this homely phrase the deci¬
sion as to what to buy and what not to buy in the world's
well-stocked supermarket for production goods and pro¬
cesses. In one sense the UNCSAT conference is a cata¬
logue of what is available, and so should be of great value
to the citizens of the emerging countries who have the
responsibility for making these decisions. One cannot
over-emphasize the importance of recognising the necessity
for wise choice of what to buy. Incidentally, the mere
reading and digesting of the mountainous mass of the
conference documents will provide a major task for the
scientists and engineers of the emerging countries.
The second most important aspect of the
application of science and technology to a
less developed country is that concerned with problems
which are related to the special conditions of the country,
and the solution of Which must be done on the spot.
Prominent among these, of course, are those special
aspects of agriculture and medicine which have specific
local significance and so cannot be studied elsewhere.
Then there are many problems in meteorology, geology,
geophysical surveying, road building and housing, where
original research and development related to local condi¬
tions Is required. In addition, many new technological
problems arise in the setting up of local industries, due
to the special properties of the local fuels, raw materials,
textiles, foodstuffs, etc.
In relation to these problems, the importance of a first
rate Information service is vital. It must be made as easy
as possible for the research and development personnel
to be kept continuously aware of the state of general
world knowledge on a particular subject, so as not to be
led by ignorance into expensive researches to find out
what is already well known. The opposite danger is to
assume too easily that some process, technique or method,
which has long been in successful use in some other
country, can be transferred without modification to new
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
AN OLD
TWIST
This African leather
craftsman possoses no
machino of any kind
for processing tho ani¬
mal skins ho usos in
his trade. To soften
the skins ho uses an
age-old method of his
people which consists
of stringing up tho
undressed hides to a
tree, attaching a heavy
weight to them and
then twisting and turn¬
ing them until they
are in a workable state.
© Paul Almasy. Pans
surroundings. Some of the most valuable research pro¬
jects in the early stages of a country's development will
surely lie in the imaginative adaption of known methods
to local conditions.
There is one ever imminent danger in such fields as
medicine and agriculture. This is, that the policy¬
makers may become so impressed by the latest triumphs
of science that the more humdrum requirements of public
health and good husbandry may get too little emphasis.
The danger of relying on wonder drugs and neglecting
the plumbing is very real. Historians of the future may
be amazed that our present epoch had the genius to
discover penicillin, but had not the wit to give the ma¬
jority of mankind a sewage system up to the technological
level of River Valley civilization 5,000 years ago.
The third aspect is the group of new technologies which
are not yet in general use but are still under development,
mainly in the technologically advanced countries. I refer,
for instance, to such things as solar heat, fuel cells,
desalination of Water, and hosts of improved processes
and manufactured goods. Though a close watch must
be kept on these developments, I am convinced that the
national economic and technological planning of a new
country's development, over the next decade or so, should
be based on what is now known.
Useful technological innovation, when it arises, should
be welcomed as a windfall profit: it should not be relied
on for planning purposes. In fact, most of the now
emerging new technologies are likely to be of only mar¬
ginal economic Importance to those countries, which are
in the early stages of development, compared with the
possible gains from fully utilizing existing technologies.
For often, but not always, new developments like nuclear
power, desalination of water, etc., are expensive In capital
cost and It is capital, particularly In the form of foreign
exchange, that emerging countries tend to be most short
of.
It is essential that the applied scientists and technolo¬
gists of the emerging countries develop a sound sense of
the economic realities of the related phases of research,
development and production. The first two stages are
expensive. Only when the last stage of production ls
reached ls there any Increase in material wealth. Though
no one would admit to believing that modern science is
a magic wand to be waved over a poor country to convert
it into a rich one, not a few seem to act as if It were
true! In fact the advance of scientific technology can
only be a part of a concerted national programme of
educational, economic, industrial and social change. Only
when integrated into such a plan will the full fruits of
scientific technology be reaped.
Patrick M.S. Blackett of Great Britain was awarded the
Nobel Prize for Physics in 1948. Since 1953 he has been 3^
professor of physics at the Imperial College for Science
and Technology, University of London.
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
A FACE-LIFT FOR THE SCI
Among the new mass media techniques
(such as films, recordings, TV, radio) which
are revolutionizing modern teaching, specia¬
lized photography is also proving itself a
precious auxiliary in many subjects, parti¬
cularly science. The photos on these and
the following pages were made to illustrate
a new secondary school course on the
fundamental laws of physics, recently dev¬
eloped by the Physical Science Study Group,
a group of American physicists and teachers
under the auspices of the Massachusetts
Institute of Technology. The course is taught
in some 1,000 U.S. high schools and has
been adapted for use in schools of develop¬
ing countries. It also uses slow motion
films and gives not only future scientists
but all students an appreciation of the me¬
thods, beauty and development of science.
This time exposure shows the student that motion is
described differently on the frame of reference of the
observer. Lights were fixed to the axis and the rim of a
moving wheel. To the camera or to an observer standing
alongside the point of light on the rim describes a
complicated curve called a cycloid. Similarly, in respect
to the axis of the wheel, the same point describes a circle.
Photos Berenice Abbott - USIS
32
This photograph of a
bouncing ball ¡s a por¬
trait of various natural'
laws of physics the
action of force on a
body, the principles of
momentum, impulse,
kinetic and potential
energy, the conservation
of energy. These prin¬
ciples govern the mo¬
tion of bodies as large
as the sun and as small
as an atomic particle.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
ENCE CURRICULUM by Jerome B. Wiesner
S ociETY today is in an evolutionary state, in
which each advance of our knowledge of the
natural world has a series of consequences, frequently
unforeseen and probably unforeseeable In detail.
For example, one consequence of the automobile not
written in the original specifications is the congested city.
Improved health measures may mean a greatly reduced
mortality rate, but without accompanying improvements
in agricultural methods or the Industrial base, they may
result in greater impoverishment. Widespread use of
nuclear energy for industrial purposes may provide an
answer to some problems of development, but as we can
already see, it may also pose the serious problem of con¬
tamination of our environment.
Each of these advances therefore poses new problems
and new challenges, forcing man through science and
technology to make hard choices as to how he will use his
technical advances. The wiser and better informed these
decisions, the more chance we have of moving towards
better social conditions and of avoiding the fate of the
dinosaur.
I do not want to minimize the problems of transfer and
adaptation of technology from one culture to another.
Indeed, the variety of cultures offers opportunity for
experimentation in the application of science and techno¬
logy to development. With the increasing number of inde¬
pendent countries we can have a variety of experiments
with new approaches to old and new problems.
The problem of transfer may indeed work both ways. I
have not attempted to differentiate between the more and
less developed countries for, in fact, all countries are
faced with the same need for wise application of science
and technology to solution of their problems.
Many of the presently less developed countries have an
opportunity to leap-frog the problems and patterns en¬
countered in the economically advanced countries. This
age is newer than many of us realize; we should not
commit the error of copying old ways that are being
replaced by new ones. Many new countries have the
opportunity to experiment and produce something
better; in the older countries we should like to be in the
position of being able to copy their Innovations. For
example, the communications satellite will soon be avail¬
able and in many situations will be superior to present
techniques for Internal communications.
It Is obvious that an adequate level of education is an
absolute prerequisite to enable any society to incorporate
new ideas and attitudes into its development process.
But a more subtle and exciting observation ls that educa¬
tion Itself can benefit from the application of research.
Here the needs are monumental in all countries and
the field ripe for the kind of systematic research and
development on the educational process itself that has
only recently begun.
I have become convinced that if we pool our best efforts
dramatic Improvements In teaching and learning are
possible. I can speak on this subject with some feeling.
We in the United States have come to realize that our
educational system has not kept pace In the way we feel
necessary with the world created by scientific and techno¬
logical advance. Accordingly a number of the scientists
and technologists in our universities, who heretofore have
limited their efforts to traditional fields of research, arc
now applying the methods of organized research and
development to education, not only In the universities,
but also at primary and secondary levels.
As a result of their initiative over the past few years
it has been demonstrated, repeatedly and on a grand
scale, that educational quality in our schools can be
vastly improved. I am firmly convinced that the same
methods can be applied, taking account of given varia¬
tions, to greatly Improve and speed the development of
new educational systems.
OI ne aspect of the effort to improve educational
quality ls the development of new aids for
teaching. The blackboard and the textbook have done
good service for half a millennium, but that does not mean
that the presentation of Information cannot profit from
a little re-design. In these experimental programmes, we
are beginning to make new use of media that until
recently have been the province principally of the enter¬
tainment industry film, tape, records, radio and tele¬
vision. And we are also experimenting with teaching
devices of an entirely novel character new methods of
instruction and new types of apparatus, not to replace,
but to enrich the work of the teacher, the indispensable
human factor in education.
Our scientists and technologists also are working on
curriculum structure and content. They are seeking to
insure that fundamentals are taught; that the informa-
CONT'D ON PAGE 36
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
FACE-LIFT (Cont'd)
Bending light. Six beams of light plus a plastic box filled
with water demonstrate the behaviour of light passing
through a prism. The beams, coming from a source at the
bottom, are bent or refracted as they pass from air to
water and then from water to air. The fourth beam from
the left is partly refracted and partly reflected toward the
right. Beams five and six are wholly reflected from the face
of the prism and then they are refracted as they leave.
A precise view of physics
34
Like light, water waves pro¬
duce shadows. Above straight
waves are incident on a round
obstacle placed in a ripple
tank. The shadow above the
dark disc is readily seen. The
shorter the wave length with
respect to the size of the
object the sharper is the sha¬
dow. Experiment (left) shows
that reflected water waves,
like light, leave the reflecting
surface at the same angle at
which they approach it. The
angle of incidence equals the
angle of reflection. Here
the straight waves are reflec¬
ted from a diagonal barrier.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Photos Gerenico Abbott - USIS
Iron filings spread on a piece of paper
assume this pattern when an electric
current is passed through the loop of
wire. This pattern indicates the
direction and magnitude of the magnetic 35
field. Note that lines are heavier near
the wire, indicating a stronger field.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
FACE-LIFT (Cont'd)
A lesson from the entertainment industry
tlon presented ls up to date, accurate and in perspective;
and that the method of teaching and the content impart
the excitement and challenge of the subject to the student
he ls a potential scientist or mathematician
or technologist, or one who will pursue other occupa¬
tions.
Although our experience has so far concentrated on
science and mathematics and foreign languages, we are
beginning to extend this approachto the teaching of
social studies, history, writing, literature, and also the
practical arts, In order to develop the skills necessary for
work in the new industries and in the new agricultural
enterprises.
The preparation of first-rate curriculum materials in
a subject is a complex operation in research and develop¬
ment. It requires the use of teams of workers from a wide
variety of backgrounds. The teams comprise not only the
outstanding masters of the field, but also outstanding
teachers at the appropriate levels, specialists who have
conducted significant research on the learning process,
and technicians such as artists, photographers, laboratory
and shop workers, who can help in devising new methods
of presentation.
Like research and development in other fields, the
creation of new educational techniques also requires a
large and genuine testing component. New curriculum
materials are not made generally available until they are
demonstrated to work In the classroom, in an experimental
process that can involve many schools over several
years.
What are the implications for the less developed
lands for this growing experience in improving
educational quality? The spirit of innovation, the team
approach, the development of new media and techniques,
and classroom experimentation would appear applicable
to new and old countries alike with the added advantage
for some countries that they are starting relatively fresh
in facing their educational problems.
This new approach to education could make possible a
massive attack on the problem of illiteracy, from which
so many of our countries suffer. To attain basic literacy,
as well as scientific literacy, true co-operation is in order.
There is no rule saying that the citizens of one country
experts in subject matter and experts in new teaching
devices cannot work with the citizens of another country
in developing new materials. People with distinct kinds
of special experience may also be necessary on the teams.
There may be problems of special frames of reference,
for example, exploiting local flora and fauna in a biology
course orto cite a more subtle problemteaching expe¬
rimental science in a culture that traditionally depreciates
manual labour.
In some cases, especially in mathematics, some of the
curriculum materials already developed might be useful
directly in other lands. In 'fact, some efforts for such
transfer are already under way, as are some efforts to
use teams made up of people from many countries to
develop new curriculum materials.
There is one aspect to improving educational quality
which dwarfs all others: the preparation of teachers to
teach the new courses both the retraining of teachers
now teaching traditional courses, and the education of
new teachers. A large number of teachers is needed and
so is a large number of teachers of teachers. But if we
are willing to experiment a little in finding more efficient
ways to prepare people for both tasks, it may not ne¬
cessarily take generations to build up a large supply of
skilled professionals.
I any of our colleges and universities have set
up special institutes to retrain teachers, both
in short summer programmes and academic year pro¬
grammes. In some schools we have tried establishing a
kind of interneship in education, an arrangement under
which the new teacher works for a period of time under
the supervision of a master teacher. We are also making
use of local broadcasting facilities, using both taped and
live programmes, to help teachers on a week-by-week
basis in using new instructional materials.
To conclude, I believe that educational development
must go hand in hand with scientific and technical de¬
velopments. Isolated technical projects, however worthy
by themselves, do not add up to development unless they
fit into an integrated national effort. There is a role in
the development process for all branches of science and
technology, for all the academic disciplines. We need a
better sense of priorities a closer identification of those
problems most in need of technological attention.
In this way the United Nations Specialized Agencies
will gain better guidelines for orienting their own pro¬
grammes of technical assistance in support of the deve¬
lopment process.
Jerome B. Wiesner is Director of the U.S. Office of Science
and Technology. A communications engineer on the staff
of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, he is a
member of the U.S. Presidential Science Advisory
Committee.
A multi-flash photograph shows the path of a wrench when thrown horizontally. Although it
seems to be wildly tumbling, the cross on the handle, marking the centre of mass, belies this.
A ruler laid along the line of crosses shows that the centre of mass follows a straight line. The
spaces between the crosses are equal, showing that the wrench travels with constant velocity. Berenice Abbott - USIS
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
A UNIVERSITY TOWN
BUILT BY A COUNTRY DOCTOR
Unesco photographer Paul
Almasy made special Jour¬
neys to Asia, Africa and Latin
America to take many of the
photos in this issue, inclu¬
ding the photo-story on the
following pages.
I N 1942, Manipal was a village with a few hundred
Inhabitants on the outskirts of the town of Udipl in
the State of Mysore, southern India, hardly distinguishable from scores
of similar hamlets In the region. Today, Manipal is a town of nearly
10,000 Inhabitants. It has a medical school, an engineering college, a
college of arts, letters and science, a college of commerce, a school of
music, three elementary schools and a secondary school. How did this
obscure village become a thriving town and a vigorous educational and
cultural centre?
The transformation of Manipal has come about through the vision and
determination of a country doctor named T. M. A. Pal who sparked a
remarkable community enterprise in education and science. Dr. Pai,
who was born in a village not far from Manipal 67 years ago, studied at
the University of Madras and after obtaining his medical degree returned
to practise in his native village.
As he went his rounds, Dr. Pal mused on many problems, but the one
that preoccupied him most of all was India's lack of schools, not only
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
COUNTRY DOCTOR (Cont'd)
THE UNBELIEVABLE
BREAM COME TRUE
schools to train other doctors like himself, but schools for engineers,
technicians and teachers of all kinds. "Knowledge Is power" was his
guiding maxim.
In his own area there were no facilities for higher education and he
knew that many promising young men and women were without the
means to continue their education at Mangalore or Madras. How could
he help them?
The answer came in 1940 when, after discussing the problem with
leading citizens of Udipi, he decided to create an educational co¬
operative to give the area the schools it needed. Two years later, In
1942, his courageous project came into being with the foundation of the
Academy of General Education at Manipal. The first aims of the Aca¬
demy were to make available technical and commercial education by
A street in Manipal. With
the gradual expansion of
schools and faculties this
tiny village has become a
town whose inhabitants
38 now number nearly ten
thousand, of whom seve¬
ral thousand are students.
- . '' . -
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
On the building site (left) Doctor Pai and members of his staff study
the layout for the foundations of a new library which is the latest
addition to the university complex that has been created in the village
of Manipal. Right, the entrance to the Kasturba Medical College,
established in 1953. In this modern faculty of medicine, lessons are
given by some of India's most eminent doctors and scientists.
supporting or building schools and colleges. A vigorous drive was
undertaken to enlist support and donations from all sections of the
community.
The project started modestly enough with a few vocational courses but
soon expanded to include two primary, a higher elementary and a secon¬
dary school. By 1949 Dr. Pal was able to enter the field of higher
education with the establishment of an Arts and Science College later
named the Mahatma Gandhi Memorial College to honour the memory of
the great Indian leader.
Four years later, in 1953, he astounded educationalists by setting up
India's first privately-sponsored medical college, the Kasturba Medical
College, named after the wife of Mahatma Gandhi. This was one of
Dr. Pai's most significant achievements. He and his friends had been
moved by the plight of the many young men for whom there were no
places in existing medical colleges in India, so they launched the
Kasturba Medical College on a co-operative basis, asking the parents
of the students who would benefit from its tuition to contribute equal
amounts to the project. Sixty-seven per cent of the first class graduated
as doctors in 1959.
In 1960 a large teaching hospital was added to the College. This has
provided clinical facilities for the students and has helped to relieve
some of the region's urgent medical problems.
Today the Academy has 800 medical students, 700 at the Polytechnic
School, 1,200 at the College of Arts, Letters and Science, 200 at the
School of Commerce. The primary schools founded by Dr. Pal have
900 boys and girls, the secondary school 550 and the School of Music,
350.
Dr. Pai's achievement Is a triumph of educational planning and educa¬
tional financing from co-operative sources, for today the Academy's
resources amount to £250,00 ($700,000).
Most men would be satisfied to see their hopes and dreams realized
on such a lavish scale. But Doctor Pai is still looking far ahead. Today
he Is giving Manipal a large modern library of which the Academy's
present library will be the nucleus.
"I believe", he said recently, "that It Is the duty of everyone to give
everything he can to help the development of education."
A nurse gives her report to Dr. Pai as he
does the rounds of the hospital at Manipal
which has been operating since 1960. It
has 600 beds and besides providing clinical
facilities for the students, it helps to relieve
some of the region's urgent medical problems.
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
COUNTRY DOCTOR (Cont'd)
A PEASANT BECOMES AN ENGINEER
Jayakar Shetty, the son of
a poor farmer in the Indian
state of Mysore, seen here
(photo on left) helping his
parents, would never have
had the chance of a school
education if Dr. Pai had
not launched his educa¬
tional project at Manipal.
Right, Jayakar now cycles
daily from h¡s home to
Manipal, ten miles away, to
attend courses (below) at
the Engineering College.
4P
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
At Assiut the ancient
capital ot Upper
A NEW UNIVERSITY
IS BORN
Assiut University,
the first to be built
in Upper Egypt and
inaugurated in
1957, will be the
most modern in the
United Arab Re¬
public when finally
completed. Shown
here is a model of
the teaching hos¬
pital complex that
will have 1,200
beds and complete
facilities for the
students and staff.
by S.A. Huzayyin
University of AsmuI
I n 1957 the United Arab Republic established
a new university at Assiut in Upper Egypt.
One of the main problems of a modern university is
how to maintain balance between three functions:
educating the youth and preparing them to assume
their role as leading citizens of their country,
providing the country with a centre of higher thought
and culture, and
making the country's contribution to the develop¬
ment of human knowledge and science through the
pursuit of research.
In highly developed countries the last function may
tend to outgrow the other two, while in developing
countries stress may often have to be laid upon the first.
In some cases too, the second function may also either
be overlooked or overstressed in a way that diminishes
the possibility of national contribution to peaceful human
development through the work of the university.
Prior to 1952, the United Arab Republic had three
modern universities together with Al-Azhar, the tradi¬
tional theological university of the Muslim World. These,
however, were not enough to meet the needs of the
developing country. They were also all concentrated in
the north in the two single large cities of the country,
Cairo and Alexandria.
This meant that in the provinces of the south the young
people were deprived of an equal opportunity to attend
university. Only the well-to-do could afford the long
journey and the costly life of the far cities. Some
800 kilometres extending along the narrow strip of the
Nile valley south of Cairo had no higher educational
services. Not a single institute of higher education was
established south of the capital. Over six millions of the
population had to send their children to Cairo or further
north if they were to get any form of higher education.
Once in Cairo or Alexandria for university education
lasting from four to seven years, students from the
southern provinces tended to look for Jobs in the north
Instead of going back to their home areas. This meant
a regular depletion of human resources. Indeed the
southern part of the country, which was once the seat
of power in ancient Egypt, became badly neglected in
many respects.
The Idea of establishing a university in Assiut, the
capital city of the region of Upper Egypt, goes back to
1949. But the effective step to bring the project into
existence was taken in 1955. After two years of planning
and preparation, two faculties for science and engineering
were Inaugurated in 1957. In Upper Egypt, the High
Dam of Aswan was to be built and schemes for industrial
as well as agricultural development had to follow. We
had to think of the need for technicians to carry out the
vast programmes which were to change the face of this
ancient land. This meant the need for faculties of
science, engineering, agriculture, medicine, veterinary
medicine, business administration, etc.
But the potentialities of the country for the establish¬
ment of such a modern university had to be carefully
surveyed. A new modern university would need, above
all, qualified staff in large numbers for teaching and
research work. It was realized that the university would
have to be built up In stages, and that priorities in setting
up one faculty after another would have to be governed
by needs and availability of staff. It was also decided
to start with the first year enrolment of students in each
faculty and to let it grow year by year.
In 1958 a third faculty, agriculture, was added. In
1960 the faculty of medicine was Inaugurated and in
1961 new departments of pharmacy were added. In the
same year a new faculty of veterinary medicine was
established. This year the faculty of commerce and
business administration will be added. In following years
new faculties for dentistry and for arts (humanities),
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
A UNIVERSITY IS BORN (Cont'd)
Campus for 16,000 students
will complete the picture of the university. It ls a plan
which has been carefully prepared and which will take
some 10 to 12 years to Implement in full.
At Assiut there were no buildings available as a per¬
manent campus for the new university. A good secondary
school building was taken as temporary headquarters.
New land was purchased for the campus within easy
reach of different parts of the city, totalling some 370
acres, to comprise the whole campus with its scientific
departments, its recreation and sports grounds and a
university city to .house students and staff. It comprises
also the site for university hospitals as well as an
experimental farm.
Of course for an agricultural country as densely popu¬
lated as ours, it was a pity that the university should
take such space from the arable land. But it was plan¬
ned that once the faculty of agriculture was established, it
should undertake a project of reclamation covering at
least four times as much of desert land in the vicinity.
The reclaimed land would then be handed over to
landless peasants in the area according to agrarian
reform laws. This will not only afford good training
opportunities for our students; it will also show the
local community that the university did not deprive
them of good arable land. It will also help integrate
more Intimately the work of the university with the
efforts being made In the area to raise the standard of
living of the people.
A plan was then drawn up for the
building of a campus. A careful study
was made of present and future
requirements with possibility for expan¬
sion. It was found that the university
would need some 30 buildings for its scientific departments,
apart from the public buildings for library, hospitals,
recreation, etc. The programme was spread over some 10
years for the principal buildings, with an additional two or
three years for the completion of auxiliary Buildings.
A professor of architecture was appointed as head of
the architecture department of the faculty of engineering
and put in charge of the planning of the site and prepara¬
tion of the draft designs for building. Some of the
buildings, such as the hostels for students and the blocks
of flats for the staff, were also designed by members of the
staff.
It is estimated that the total cost of the campus will be
in the neighbourhood of eight million Egyptian pounds.
The programme started late in 1958 with the building of
large workships for engineering (and where most of our
furniture and some of our scientific apparatus is now being
manufactured) and part of our recreation grounds. It
is hoped that . by 1968-1969 the whole campus will be
completed. It will accommodate some 12,000 students
(attending 8 or 9 faculties), and eventually 16,000 students.
The question of style of buildings was also carefully
considered. The idea of a classical style was discarded.
We are building a university in the second half of the
20th century, and feel that it should reflect Its time and
age.
So we adopted a modern style, adapted it to the local
conditions of a warm climate (such as double external
walls, double roof, good orientation to provide insulation,
etc.). The buildings are of a concrete frame, with red¬
brick outside walls and large glass windows, especially on
the shady side.
The purchase of up-to-date scientific equipment ls
necessary for the proper functioning of any university.
As our university at Assiut is composed principally of
"science" (rather than humanistic) faculties,' more
apparatus is needed for this work. That was why we
had to start in our building programme with the work¬
shops, which have so far been able to provide 'us with
some of the simpler apparatus for teaching, as well as
some of the apparatus especially designed for research.
Equipping a scientific department with apparatus needs
very careful planning to avoid waste and make one's
funds go as far as possible. It also Implies other
difficulties connected with obtaining hard currency.
Another problem we faced was that we had to get our
equipment from different countries, East and West. This
entailed special training of technicians and, in some
instances, the sending of technicians abroad, or receiving
the help of foreign technicians for short terms at Assiut.
One other problem which we had to tackle was the repair
of instruments. But the workshops of the university
were of invaluable help in this respect.
It is difficult to estimate the total cost of 'apparatus
for a new university, for this depends on the number of
scientific departments to be equipped and the total of
student enrolment. We have so far invested over
1,500,000 Egyptian pounds. But we are still less than half
equipped in some of our newer faculties.
As for books, we began collecting some during the two
years of planning before we went to Assiut in 1957. We
started with a nucleus of more than 50,000 volumes for our
library. But we found real difficulty in getting back-
numbers of scientific periodicals. The university is
setting up its own press to publish a "Bulletin of Science
and Technology," as well as text books prepared by the
staff and sold to students at cost price.
Staffing of the scientific departments was probably the
most difficult of all our problems. Fortunately, when the
idea of the university was first conceived in 1949, some 50
graduates from the other universities were sent abroad for
Ph. D. work in the various disciplines. They represented
the nucleus of our first faculties. The staff of the
university was then regularly added to year by year from
returning members of missions or by other recruitment
for leading posts. Gradually we also received a small
number of visiting professors from other countries, mostly
through cultural exchange agreements.
In 1955 a vigorous programme for research at universi¬
ties in Europe and America was started. By the summer
of 1962 we already had some 130 men and women doing
research abroad, together with another 40 to follow. Some
of these have already finished their preparation abroad
and are returning to assume teaching posts. Nearly 1,500
At its foundation, the University of Assiut gave priority
to science and 'engineering faculties. Already 500
science and engineering students have graduated to
join those now carrying out development programmes
in Upper Egypt. Below, buildings of science faculty.
42 Cuts show the ancient symbol of the union of two lands. The reed
of Upper Egypt and the papyrus of the Delta are entwined around
a hieroglyph meaning "to unite".
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
Photos : University of Assiut Bird's-eye view of future campus of the University of Assiut to be completed in 1969-70. Covering
about 250 acres, it will have 30 buildings for science and allied subjects alono and a total student
body of 16,000. Dormitories are at lower right below stadium. Humanities faculty is just above tip
of minaret. Faculties of science and agriculture line the northern edge alongside irrigation canal and
those of engineering and medicine the southern side. At left is the university teaching hospital.
members are now abroad and will occupy teaching or other
posts upon their return. Thus the acute problem of
staffing the University of Assiut is being gradually solved.
Ours was to be essentially a provincial university. It
was decided that our places should be allocated primarily
to students taking their secondary school certificate from
schools in the five southern provinces of the country.
This meant that the new university would alleviate
pressure on the universities in Cairo and Alexandria.
Entry into all universities in the United Arab Republic
Is based upon open competition between students finishing
their secondary education. In addition to the numbers
accepted from the country, 10% of the total is allocated
to students from different Arab and other countries. At
present girls make up 8 to 10% of our enrolment, but the
percentage is steadily rising.
The establishing of our university in Upper Egypt has
provided a new opportunity for girls in this part of the
country to obtain a university education. At present
nearly 80% of our students are from the five southern
provinces of the country. The University of Assiut started
with 500 undergraduate students and some 10 research
students. The total number (including research students)
was nearly 6,000 during the academic year 1962-1963.
As in most other countries, our youth justly feel that
we are becoming an engineering society. So most of our
boys (and many of our girls) prefer to join the engineering
faculty. Next in preference are the faculties of medicine
(and pharmacy) and science.
As already mentioned, Assiut is a small provincial city
of some 120,000 inhabitants. Before the university was
established, the town had limited accomodation for
visitors from outside. It was never really a tourist city.
It was also not in the tradition of its families to accept
strangers as paying guests. So there were difficulties for
the university to establish itself in the city. Living
conditions were not easy for staff or for students.
Eight blocks of new apartment buildings were rented
by the university and converted into hostels for students.
The building plan Included the construction of the
university city already mentioned, to house, when complet¬
ed, some 3,000 students..
An appeal for funds was made and the sum of 65,000
Egyptian pounds was collected from private donations.
This was sufficient to build the first block of buildings
for students. Ten more blocks will follow. Also three
blocks of flats have already been built for 24 families of
the staff. Other blocks will follow. A new housing
scheme was also started by the local authorities two years
ago. So the face of our little town is quickly being
changed. It is estimated that within 10 years or so, the
university will have added (directly or indirectly) to this
provincial city about 20% of Its population. This will give
a new pattern to the social life in Assiut.
Life in the campus ls gradually taking shape. Ours
will be one of the rather rare examples of a complete
campus, comprising both academic buildings and living
accomodation for a section of the staff and student
population. At the same time, recreational amenities are
gradually being added. The recreation grounds were
actually amongst the earliest facilities to be provided. A
stadium ls already being used by students and other youth
of the city. It is in our plan to have all our facilities
open to the public. This includes the stadium, the club,
the halls, the theatre, as well as the public library.
The university has Its own department
of public relations to organize contact
with the local community. Extramural
activities and extension services include
Assiut and the whole region north and
south of it. The faculty of agriculture gives advice and
guidance to peasants and farm groups. The hospital Ls
designed to serve the whole region and to be a centre for
health services and research. Even the workshops of the
faculty of engineering are in the service of any citizen
who wishes to avail himself to their services at cost price.
The university of Assiut ls gradually building up its status
as a provincial institution In the service of the commun¬
ity and the whole neigbourhood.
Yet even this new university is not limited in its ser¬
vices to the area in which it is located. It is in our
tradition in this land to consider ourselves as an Integral
part of the Arab people as a whole. In addition to the
percentage of seats reserved for students from Arab and
other neighbouring countries, these students are accorded
every care to facilitate their stay with us. Already
students from more than 10 countries, coming from as
far as Malaya, are studying in this small university. The
numbers of students and the countries from which they
come are gradually Increasing. This ls a welcome feature
of our university education.
Our university is thus playing an ever-increasing part
in our national life and development, as an Institution
for men and women citizens of a growing nation.
S.A. Huzayyin is Rector of the University of Assiut, United
Arab Republic.
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
AFRICAN
METAMORPHOSIS
by E.A.K. Kalitsi
Like other newly-independent
nations of West Africa, Ghana is
living through a time of construc¬
tion and fundamental change. Its
people are building new paths in
technology and industrialization,
opening schools, hospitals and
technical institutes. But in creat¬
ing this new fabric of life, they do-
not forget their ancient past
with its culture, crafts and tradi¬
tional values. Left, stairway of a
Ghanian home; right, nurses go
on duty at the Sekondi hospital.
All photos with this article, taken
by Willis E. Bell, are from " The
Roadmakers ", by Efua Sutherland,
© Newman Neame Ltd., and Ghana
Information Services
44
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
kix years ago, Liberia was the only independent
"country in West Africa (1). The rest of the
area was divided between the British, French, Spanish and
Portuguese. Today, only Gambia (a British crown colony)
and Portuguese and Spanish Guinea with less than 2%
of the population are dependent countries. The rest of
the population, totalling more than 80 million inhabitants,
is divided among 15 Independent states (2) of which
Nigeria alone has 40 million people and Ghana six and a
half million people.
In spite of ample land, minerals and forest wealth.
West Africa remains a poor region. None of the countries
has an annual income per head of 200 dollars. Many in
fact have only about 100 dollars a head per year.
The main problem of development in West Africa there¬
fore is how to raise the levels of production so that the
people can come somewhere near the 800 dollars per head
which is earned in Western Europe, not to speak of the
2,000 dollars per head which is earned in the United
States. It will require a phenomenal rise in productivity
for the real incomes in West Africa to approach those of
the developed world.
While the West African leaders and their professional
advisers are puzzled about how to tackle this problem,
the higher consumption standards of the developed
countries are being communicated to West African
(1) West Africa is here understood as the area stretching 1,700
miles from Cape Verde near Dakar on the west coast to the
Cameroons mountains in the east and from the Gulf of Guinea
in the south to the northern boundaries lying in the Sahara
Desert which starts roughly some 600 to 700 miles from the
coast. It covers an area of about 2,400,000 square miles and
has a population of about 80 million.
(2) Cameroun, Dahomey, Gabon, Ghana, Guinea, Ivory Coast,
Liberia, Mali, Mauritania, Niger, Nigeria, Senegal, Sierra Leone,
Togo and Upper Volta.
villagers, who in turn are no longer content to remain
without the amenities of good food, good housing, good
health and good education for their children. Most of
the goods and services which go to satisfy these higher
levels of living are still imported goods. The need arises
therefore to find the foreign exchange to pay for develop¬
ment as well as current Imports if standards of living
are not to fall.
West Africa is a producer of primary commo¬
dities. Industries are almost non-existent. In
each of the countries, the economies have been geared to
the needs of European powers with which they were
associated. Thus, each country ls heavily oriented to
the production of one or two commodities only at the
expense of a more balanced development in the economy.
Ghana ls heavily dependent on cocoa, Nigeria on cocoa,
oil-palm and ground-nuts, Liberia on rubber, and the
former French West African countries on cotton.
The heavy dependence on primary production for export
makes these countries victims of the whims of foreign
trade, producing In them large fluctuations of income.
The bitter experience of cocoa farmers in the 1930's
caused a stagnation In the cocoa production of Ghana
for some twenty years. One aspect of this pattern of
trade is that each European power held a monopoly of
the trade of each dependent territory. That is why even
today exports and imports of the French-speaking coun¬
tries of Africa are still almost exclusively with France
and those of Nigeria and Ghana with Britain.
These countries have therefore been unable to establish
among themselves an Internal West African market which
could widen their areas of exchange and gain for them
the economies of large Interdependent production.
French West Africa's trade with other West African
CONT'D ON PACE 47
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
SYMBOLS & WISDOM
"The wisdom and achievement of the past are our guide", say the
people of Ghana. Above, the family elder, to whom the household
looks for counsel and guidance. Below, from a blackboard on the
outside wall of a Ghana village school a young man pursues his
studies. Symbol of the age of new development for Ghana is the
country's first steel suspension bridge (right) which was. com¬
pleted in 1956, and which now spans the Volta River at Adomi.
K"\
.: 3 1 10'
a. a '» '-- * n Z',
Ho pu a Si la á-T»^
46
. ..-_;«S*
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
AFRICAN METAMORPHOSIS (Cont'd)
Challenge to science :
a revolutionary plough
countries ls 10% of her total trade, Ghana's ls 4% and
Nigeria's 1%.
This In itself should not have made any difference
were It in fact practicable for the surplus or under¬
employed population of West Africa to migrate to France
and Britain and capital to flow In large volume from
Europe to West Africa. If this were possible, the present
large disparity in Income would not have developed
between the European countries and their complementary
dependent economies in West Africa.
The United States has the same relation with Puerto
Rican trade. But within the last twenty years, Puerto
Rico's yearly imports have been exceeding their exports
by some 50%. The difference has no doubt been going
into the rapid capital formation going on In the country.
At the same time, Puerto Rico has transferred during this
twenty-year period some 30 to 60,000 of her surplus or
under-employed population per year to the United States.
I t is not surprising therefore that the same
pattern of trade should produce in a little,
resource-poor Island of 2-1/2 millions a per capita income
of 565 dollars while producing In the large relatively rich
region of West Africa with 80 million people under 100
dollars per head per year. As West Africa has not the
advantages of Puerto Rico therefore, the problem arises
how best to develop an internal West African market
large enough to stimulate all-round production while
retaining the present expert products upon which the
countries depend at the moment.
What of the resource situation in West Africa ? Unlike
Asia, fortunately, West Africa's population ls not alarm¬
ingly large. But, with the rapid improvements going on
in the health of the people, It can be expected that the
population will rise, thus creating greater pressure upon
the land. At the present over 70% of the people are
farmers, mainly peasant subsistence farmers with pro¬
ductivity only about a fifth that of United States farmers.
This low productivity of West African agriculture can be
explained by the very low level of capital Input into
agriculture, poor techniques and deficiencies in the land.
he failure of the British attempt to mechanize
agriculture In East Africa illustrates In a dra¬
matic way some of the problems of Increasing agricultural
productivity in West Africa. It has been found, for
example that the rock fragments of West African soli are
such that a caterpillar tractor only consolidates the sur¬
face into a hard macadam layer. Thus ls ruled out the
majority of mechanical cultivators at present used in
temperate countries. Disc ploughs have also been found
unsuitable and frequent ploughing only ploughs out all
the goodness from the land.
Until agricultural scientists devise suitable equipment
and techniques for the soil, therefore, It appears there
will be no alternative to the small hoe and shifting culti¬
vation. In spite of those disadvantages, agriculture
remains the most important source from which surplus
can be generated for other development. Effort is
therefore needed to raise this surplus.
In addition to agriculture, there ls some evidence of
substantial mineral resources in West Africa. Gold and
diamonds are at present exploited In Ghana, bauxite In
Guinea and Ghana, tin, coal and petroleum in Nigeria,
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
AFRICAN METAMORPHOSIS (Cont'd)
Nation-builders in transition
iron in Liberia and Sierra Leone, phosphates In Togoland,
manganese In Ghana, and saline salts in Mauritania.
Further geological work ls required to determine the
extent of these deposits.
Although West Africa has ample land and a not
ungenerous supply of mineral resources, the countries are
still very poorly supplied with capital, whether as fixtures
like houses, roads, railways, or as equipment like ma¬
chines, transport vehicles and agricultural tools. In fact,
capital accumulation has been going on at the rate of
about 5% a year, but at that rate capital formation can
barely keep pace with the rate of population growth, let
alone cover any increase in the standard of living.
I t is considered by some people that the rate
I of capital formation should be upped to 10%
or 15% if development is to accelerate. But with Income
so low, it is not the easiest thing to save such a large
percentage for capital formation. Like other poor coun¬
tries of the world therefore, West Africa is caught in the
proverbial vicious circle of poverty. But how can this
circle of low investment and low productivity be broken?
The answer produced by the West African governments
was to create the social overhead capital so that directly
productive activities can be established or expanded.
During Ghana's first five-year development plan, for
example, a first class trunk-road system was established
running from north to south and from east to west and
also linking the major urban areas of the country.
Several hundred miles of secondary roads, untarred but
quite adequate, radiated to most of the small villages and
hamlets in the country.
A new harbour and its 40,000 service township was
planned and substantially completed. A university was
built, the school system expanded and health centres built
throughout the country. Telephone and electric lights
more than doubled. This development was carried out
during a period when the country was a net exporter of
capital. This was due mainly to the good price of cocoa
which financed some 90% of the 130 million pound pro¬
gramme.
In the Second Development Plan, the emphasis shifted
from the infra-structure to concentration on agricultural
improvement, development of industry and expansion of
the secondary school system to provide necessary tech¬
nicians for the new activities. As the country has been
dependent upon cocoa production so far, a start was made
to diversify agriculture by introducing or encouraging
crops such as coffee, bananas, and rubber. At the same
time, attention was given to improvement of cocoa. A
public corporation was given funds and the authority to
develop industries in the country. Tax concessions were
provided to investors, factory buildings provided on rental
basis for those who needed them, and financial and other
assistance offered. Trade agreements were signed with
countries like the United States.
The foregoing gives an example of some of the attempts
being made to create the conditions for industrialization
48
Pottery (right) the pro¬
duct of an ancient, indi¬
vidual craft, and newly
skilled hands in indus¬
try (far right)- sum up
West Africa's evolution.
Now its dominant need
is higher production
in industry and in the
rural economy. Today
many people in West
African countries earn
no more than $100 per
year. Over 70% are
farmers. In spite of
ample lands, mineral
riches and forest wealth
West Africa will remain
a poor region until it
exploits these resources
and has acquired its
own skilled personnel.
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
in West Africa. As a practical matter, local capital can
be gathered only slowly, mainly out of present agriculture
and it will take a little while for the local entrepreneurs
to acquire the necessary industrial know-how. Foreign
capital can help tide over this period of transition in the
economy. But the flow has been slow. Most of the
foreign investment is locked up in quick-yielding enter¬
prises like import and export trade. What is wanted
really is the means to exploit local resources and train
adequate personnel. The governments are therefore out
of necessity forced to undertake some of the directly
productive activities considered necessary for the growth
of the economies.
here is no doubt that increased capital for¬
mation is urgently necessary for West African
countries. But we do not want to lay too much stress
on that factor alone. The existing capital could be put
to a better use and even increased if the illiteracy rate
were not so high. It is significant that the new state of
Israel, located on a desert, should within a very short
time have developed faster than the oil-rich Middle East
countries. Not a small part of the explanation ls that
Israel had a high degree of literacy which enabled the
country to train her work force and organize them
quickly, free from the crippling inhibitions of tradition-
oriented social structure and illiterate communities.
In any case, in West Africa, with some 85% of the
people illiterate, any scheme of major development ls
bound to press hard upon the already limited supply of
educated people who are required as legislators, business¬
men, engineers and technicians. Fortunately, there have
been enough of these people to assume the responsibilities
of self-government without a breakdown occuring as has
happened elsewhere. However, what constitutes an
immediate bottleneck for many of these countries'
developments ls secondary school graduates for training
in the technical and skilled operative level In agriculture
and industry. The problem can be tackled as has been
done in Ghana by the allocation of more resources to
secondary education than before. But it will take time
for the teachers, especially in the scientific fields, to
emerge.
Of even greater importance is the problem of political
stability and the establishment of law and order. Now
that most of the countries have become independent, they
are faced with the problems of transition. The new
institutions have not yet established their full authority.
The energies of the leaders are therefore concentrated on
political problems of natlon-bulldlng, leaving them little
opportunity to give full attention to problems of economic
and technical development.
The bureaucracies trained in the old colonial school
to regard their main function as maintenance of law
and order are converting even more slowly to their
new function of speeding up the economic develop¬
ment of their countries. However, it is noteworthy
that the leaders as well as the people of West Africa arc
all anxious to transform their countries into modern
nations. I believe that this enthusiasm for development
which can be seen In the brisk and lively cities of the
western coast, is perhaps the most important factor which
will help clear away some of the problems of developments
in West Africa.
E.A.K. Kalitsi is senior assistant secretary of the Deve¬
lopment Commission, Volta River Authority, Government
of Ghana.
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
URBAN EXPLOSION
IN DEVELOPING NATIONS
by Paul Mercier
I
50
n the majority of developing countries, the
I town (especially the large town) is an entirely
new phenomenon which forced itself ruthlessly upon
essentially peasant communities. These were village
communities In which economic and social relations
developed between horizons that were often extremely
narrow. In these villages blood relationships were
broadly the basis of much of the social life, attachment
to the soil was of religious or quasl-rellgious significance
and respect for tradition slowed down the effects of
forces of social and cultural change.
The city thus offered an environment radically opposed
to the traditional way of life. It is significant that in
various regions of Africa south of the Sahara, for instance,
visits to the city and a temporary stay have replaced to
some extent the reputedly hazardous rites of initia¬
tion to which young men formerly had to submit before
being admitted to a fully adult status in society. Contact
with the city came to be considered as an experience par
excellence of a foreign, difficult and hostile world, though
one that none the less held many attractions.
For nearly all the developing countries entry into the
modern world has meant the creation of towns: adminis¬
trative centres in colonial territories, commercial centres
everywhere and an at first limited number of industrial
centres.
Economists were the first to emphasize the importance
of these links with the economically-developed nations,
links established by these countries for their own needs
as centres of political and economic domination in
directly colonized countries or simply for economic control
in others.
The limited integration of these towns with the regions
they were intended to exploit rather than to serve was
also noted. Even today this Integration is only proceed¬
ing at a slow place. A similar lack of harmony is also
found on the social and cultural level, though it is also
true that migration to the city has done much to spread
Its influence widely within a short time.
At first the new towns were rather primitive, and they
have still not outgrown this stage in many cases. Build¬
ing over the urban as whole Was sparse and somewhat
haphazard. Residential sections looked more like over¬
grown villages or "encampments." (Today many towns
are still unable to provide sufficient housing for their
inhabitants.) The creation of municipal administrative
services was in its formative stages as also was the labour
market.
However, within the last few decades, and especially
since the Second World War. many of these towns have
diversified their activities and have reached a stage of
partial consolidation. This process of diversification is
extending today, especially in former colonial territories.
The development of trade, industry and administration
Ibadan, capital of
the Western region
of Nigeria, is the
largest purely Afri¬
can town south of
the Sahara, with a
population of nearly
three-quarters of a
million. Negro Af¬
rica's first TV station
and Nigeria's first
university are in this
bustling, rapidly
growing city where
gleaming apartment
and office buildings
rise amid a sea of
tin-roofed houses.
Yet many of Iba-
dan's people still
work as farmers.
© Paul Almasy. Paris
and of political and educational activities is increasingly
combined in many towns.
The influence of the town as a centre for spreading
standards, prototypes and new ways is now penetrating
the rural areas more systematically. The development
of transport and news and Information media of all kinds
helps appreciably to reduce the gap between town and
country. Some plans for modernization and equipment
show clearly the intention of making the towns and their
resources the effective servants of the rural areas.
Nevertheless, the stabilization of urban populations
essential for the creation of sound economic and social
conditions still creates difficult problems.
Most new towns have heterogeneous populations, hete¬
rogeneous from regional, ethnic, linguistic and religious
points of view. Thus they facilitate contacts and the
mixing of different elements which is especially Important
to countries striving to achieve unity. However, they are
also the scene, for varying periods, of social tensions
which sometimes turn Into bitter conflicts between indi-
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
viduals, regional or ethnic groups or even between
different castes.
This situation arises all the more frequently because
of the lack of arrangements to assimilate these people
in urban areas. The individual or group has therefore been
driven to congregate with others of similar origin so as to
enjoy familiar social relationships. These could to some
extent be continued in town and help to lessen the
shock of starting an entirely new kind of life. At the
same time, the formation of associations of this kind,
all aiming basically at mutual aid, partly compensated for
the loss of the traditional kinship groupings which had
been the very basis for existence in the past, but which
could only subsist with difficulty in urban surroundings.
One of the main reasons for the intense migration to
towns is rural over-population. However, this is not the
only cause, and countries with a very low density of
population offer equally spectacular examples of migra¬
tion. The factors which come into play here Include
various kinds of social imbalance found in rural areas,
economic regression due to special historical circumstances
and direct and Indirect constraints imposed in colonized
countries to make sure of an abundant labour force, and
even a manpower surplus which helped to support a low
wages policy.
Although migration concerns a large part (often the
majority) of the adult male population, most migrants
do not settle permanently in towns or have no Intention
of doing so. Industrial labour studies show that in the
majority of developing countries the numbers of men
actually employed are small, but that the labour force ls
continually being renewed.
Industrial workers and town populations are basically of
a shifting kind. Recruitment of workers for industry and
urban Jobs has a "partial" character. The village re¬
mains their real "home" and even those who settle more 51
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
URBAN EXPLOSION (Cont'd)
Replacing the shanty towns
or less permanently in towns return to the village
periodically to visit their relatives, to help with the
harvest, to take part In ceremonies and so on. They do
not evade the social and religious obligations imposed by
the village. Studies in India and Africa revealed many
facts of this kind. While there is thus no complete rup¬
ture between the town and rural populations the tem¬
porary town dwellers or those who remain largely alien
to their new environment are nevertheless inadequately
equipped to meet the social and economic demands of
the town
Migration to the town means a search for work an
often hopeless search, as many migrants discover. Most
studies reveal a large proportion of unemployed and even
more often, of non-employed persons. If the migrant
does not immediately find employment, he stays in town
knowing that he will always be able to subsist with the
help of "relatives" he will find there.
The man who finds a job is a privileged person; relatives
often come to live at his expense and he usually complies
with the ancient, still surviving rules of family solidarity.
This phenomenon of "family parasitism," found almost
everywhere, is an obstacle to the raising of the standard
of living of the worker and to any show of initiative by
him. Yet , at the same time it offers a spontaneous
compensation for the effects of urban under-employment.
Some economists have referred to the transfer of under¬
employment from country to town. We shall return later
to the question of the lag that can be observed between
the rate of growth or urban populations and the rate of
increase in the number of jobs. Not all town dwellers
without regular employment are entirely inactive, but the
work they do is of an unproductive kind everywhere
there is an abundance of servants, petty traders, middle¬
men and people who live by doing odd jobs. The enormous
increase in the section of the population which does not
earn regular salaries reveals the extent of under-employ¬
ment in towns.
In urban areas which are still poor in resources and
where productive activity lags well behind the increase in
population, the housing shortage is always acute. Every¬
where there are shapeless shanty towns. Even the man
with a job often has no more than "a corner to sleep in,"
and overcrowding is a general rule.
tvEN where vigorous efforts are made to meet
this situation there is only a very gradual
Improvement. Intensive speculation in land, housing and
rents has been reported in many towns. Anything (even
the "corner to sleep in") is let at an exhorbitant price.
Rent eats up far too large a proportion of the budgets
of the lowest income groups. This explains why seasonal
migrants especially, but sometimes other categories of
workers too, are ready to accept overcrowding and poor
sanitary conditions or even to share accomodation with
others on an "in rotation" basis. This situation, the
result of rapid urban expansion, again reveals the limited
degree of integration of the townsmen in their new
environment.
Having developed too quickly the town communities
lack administrative structures and show signs of serious
disequilibrium. Reports have referred to "formless masses
of people." This is an exaggeration, although the fact
remains that the individual does lack the social structures
which he needs to support and guide him. The groups
to which he belongs are unable to give him all the help
he needs in the difficult choices confronting him and in
his efforts towards adjustment.
52 Efforts are often made to establish traditional types of
groups but these can never be more than fragmentary and
relatively ineffective. The basis of a new social structure
is still far from firmly established. The small family
unit tends to replace the large family group, but this
transition creates many problems because people are
unprepared for the new kind of relationships which it
involves between men and women, children and parents.
The fragility of this social structure ls only partially offset
by the relations that are maintained with the large family
groups In the villages from which the migrants came.
We must also remember that many towns had and
sometimes still do have very unbalanced demographic
structures because of the surplus of men, particularly
young men. This is explained by the nature of the mi¬
grations and has often lead to a widespread growth of
prostitution, along with other social disorders. A Society
in which traditional standards no longer apply or are
misapplied, in which new rules have not yet taken shape
or are not yet properly understood, is a favourable breed¬
ing ground for many kinds of disease. In some cases
there has been an alarming increase in crime and delin¬
quency.
It has been said that the incorporation of rural peoples
into the industrial work force demands a real effort of
"conversion" on their part. This is also true of every
kind of non-traditional work offered by the town. The
migrant who gets a job finds himself facing an entirely
new situation which includes a salary system, payment in
cash and the breaking down of work into individual tasks.
The new conception of economic and social relations in
work is instilled only with great difficulty.
Along with the instability of the labour force one finds
a lack of skill and low productivity due to a number of
Paul Almasy, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
physical, psychological and social factors. While the new
townsman learns his job fairly easily, either by following
a properly organized training course or "on the job"
(which is usually the case), he has more difficulty in
adapting himself to its context. His new work lacks the
social and religious meaning of traditional occupations;
it is specialized and he finds it hard to grasp the process
as a whole. This, therefore, mitigates against the intro¬
duction of incentives to production.
The worker, moreover, is not properly at home in an
undertaking which is made up of heterogeneous working
groups, sometimes managed by foreigners, and in which
he often stays only a comparatively short time. The
vocational training which many countries endeavour to
develop must not only be vocational but must also com¬
prise an element of "cultural adaptation." The efficacy
of such measures depends largely upon the control of
migration and by this fact is closely bound up with the
whole process of development.
Towns are favourable breeding grounds for new forms
of social stratification. Soon it is possible to distinguish
several more or less contrasting types of townsmen. Even
where a class structure has not fully developed in
present or former colonial territories, for example the
main social groups emerge by reason of their length of
residence in town, level of education, professional qualifica¬
tions, political activities, by their style of living (housing,
food and recreational activities becoming status symbols)
or by the ties maintained with traditional social forms
and values.
This stratification, combined with the creation of new
notions of prestige, produces a social breakdown very
different from that prevailing in the old communities.
The nucleus of townspeople who are firmly established,
who have permanent employment and the highest incomes
and who have adopted to a large extent the non-
STRAW IN THE WIND. Dilapidated shacks and straw huts contrast
sharply with nearby neatness of new homes built at Katutu in the
Republic of the Congo (Leopoldville). Housing is an urgent problem
in Africa's burgeoning towns. Most have shapeless shanty towns and
"encampments", the homes of hordes of migrants from rural areas.
traditional ways of life, fills the top ranks of this social
structure. These are the people who play a decisive role
in political life, not only In town, but in the country as
a whole. The town, then, ls the chief formative centre
of these modern elites and this ls an important clement
of its prestige and of its attraction for the rural popula¬
tions.
The control of migration to towns (the prerequisite of
equilibrium and general development) implies both an
expansion of the industrial economy and a rapid improve¬
ment in the situation of the rural areas. Irrespective of
whether or not they suffer from overpopulation.
he difficulties Inherent in agrarian reform
have already been mentioned. It is signifi¬
cant that those who draw up development plans often
include only modest provisions for increasing agricultural
production, as, for instance, in the case of India's first
two national plans. Many targets, desirable but too
costly, have In fact eventually to be abandoned. Except
in very limited spheres, educational measures can only be
expected to produce long term results. Even some tech¬
nological enterprises which seemed not ovcrambitious
ended in failure because social changes which are part
and parcel of such development were not taken suffi¬
ciently Into account; this has happened in many regions
of Africa south of the Sahara.
One good example of the difficulties Inherent In
the development of the rural economy Ls the mechaniza¬
tion, at least to a certain extent, of agriculture one of
the methods envisaged In many countries, as a way to
increase agricultural production and In particular the
production of foodstuffs In short supply.
Mechanization, of course, calls for considerable Invest¬
ment. But foreign or international aid ls mostly directed
to other sections of the economy, state subsidies are
usually small and the ability of the local farmers to
save money or to invest ls very limited or even non¬
existent.
In the case of regions where highly profitable crops for
export have been Introduced, for example, when the
revenue earned from agriculture exceeds the amount
required for immediate needs, the surplus is used primarily
to buy luxury consumer goods or goes on traditional items
of expenditure. This is true of many African regions
and the money amassed there ls (economically speaking)
more or less frozen.
Even If mechanization was financially feasible, It would
still raise many other problems. It often demands
structural changes in the community; people must be
trained to look after the new equipment, and peasant
habits must be changed. In addition, mechanization in
tropical countries may cause still greater deterioration to
already fragile soils.
Theoretically, the simplest solution ls to Increase the
area of cultivated land and to put to use virgin lands.
It has been said that in the case of Africa south of the
Sahara this kind of expansion would be possible and would
demand only slight technological changes.
In many regions of Africa, areas which had hitherto
been uninhabited or only sparsely populated were turned
to cultivation during the colonial period, though not with
the aim of increasing the average agricultural production
per inhabitant. This was done because the already
cultivated lands were becoming exhausted and because
new land was needed for bumper export crops which
quickly impoverish the soil. Such use of virgin territories
without the use of improved land care techniques and
proper precautions resulted all too often in a squandering
of frail soil.
But the case of Africa is by no means the most serious.
In some parts of the world either it ls Impossible to
Increase the land under cultivation or such possibilities co
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
URBAN EXPLOSION (Cont'd)
Finding new jobs for migrants
54
are very limited. Egypt's territories outside the Nile
Valley cannot be used for agriculture and this is also true
of most of the Amazon Basin in Brazil. Even in regions
where there are virgin lands their exploitation in the
near future will only be possible where cultivation would
not entail prior (and too costly) development of com¬
munications, irrigation and so on.
It will not be enough simply to throw these lands open
for exploitation. The farmers who settle there will need
to be led and educated technically, economically and
socially and migration will have to be carefully con¬
trolled, otherwise the immediate benefits gained may well
prove illusory.
While it is often difficult to increase the area of land
under cultivation, it is possible everywhere to improve
methods of exploitation within limits which vary accord¬
ing to each individual case. The dangers of overambi-
tlous plans have already been stressed. It is the small-
scale agricultural projects, costing comparatively little,
which have proved effective in many cases and which have
quickly produced an Increased yield by better use of land
in terms of its particular qualities, by Improved farming
methods and by changes in the system of crop rotation.
Larger scale measures which bring long term benefits
are irrigation, soil preservation and the rehabilitation of
worked-out land. These must be part of an overall plan.
The Importance of "a broad programme of small under¬
takings" has been stressed particularly in relation to
irrigation. These individual efforts can be accomplished
without recourse to large-scale investment and in the
familiar setting of a village or group of villages.
This, of course, does not exclude enterprises on a
grander scale such as dam building when funds and labour
are available. But such projects often involve major
changes in social and agrarian structures and also in the
way people are housed. And this in turn calls for a
concerted programme affecting the entire rural com¬
munity.
Soil conservation measures may include the use of
"green manure" (although this modern technique often
meets with opposition from traditionalist farmers) or of
chemical fertilizers, though these are expensive and their
use in tropical countries needs further study. In the
immediate future it looks as though in many cases action
will have to be restricted to teaching farmers how to care
for their soil.
As regards long term measures, the restoration of
exhausted lands for later use can often be achieved at
low cost and with existing labour resources, by planting
protective rows of trees and building low walls along
slopes and so on. But efforts of this kind must be part
of a future plan for the complete modernization of agri¬
culture and an intensive educational programme.
Reference has already been made to the existence of
a surplus population in areas now in the throes of ur¬
banization and industrial development. This recent in¬
dustrial growth has been unable to absorb the enormous
mass of migrants who have come to the towns in recent
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
decades. The increase in the number of jobs is never
more than a feeble percentage as compared to the rise
in the urban population: about 3% in India, 5% in
Africa and 6% in Latin America.
As the proportion of men of working age among the
new town dwellers is very high, under-employment In the
towns has actually increased. This problem is reflected
in national development plans whose target figures for
creating new fields of employment are enormous. The
second Five Year Plan in India, for example, aimed at
creating 15 million new jobs.
But targets of this importance are hard to attain even
when priority is given to the development of industries
which need large labour forces. Industrialization moves
at a slower pace than should be the case, not only because
of the general shortage of investment capital, but for
other reasons as well. The absorption of individuals and
family groups into an industrialized economy does not
necessarily give them a higher standard of living.
Actually it is often difficult to make statistical com¬
parisons between the living standards of the wage-
earning population and those of the rural peoples engaged
in a subsistence economy.
A worker with a regular job is regarded as a privileged
individual and his commitments increase accordingly.
Below a certain level of industrialization the income of
the vast majority of wage earners provides only for a
precarious existence and does very little to reduce the
poverty of the rural populations. The level at which the
situation would be reversed is seldom reached.
Industrial development may be carried out in various
ways depending on the particular conditions found in
each country and upon the choices made by each govern¬
ment for economic and political reasons.
In countries where population pressure is not an imme¬
diately urgent problem the only kind of industrialization
that can be envisaged (except In a limited number of
fields) is a long-term one, priority being given instead to
the technological and social transformation of the rural
economy. In the majority of cases, however, both poli¬
cies will have to be pursued simultaneously.
Industrial development aiming at the production of
consumer goods ls effective only In so far as the rural
areas are capable of absorbing a substantial part of these
goods. This in turn assumes that a number of conditions
will be met. Agricultural production must rise above the
ordinary level of subsistence in an ever-increasing number
of regiqns. An adequate network of roads must be
constructed. Distribution channels between producer and
of Industrially-produced goods on rural crafts must be
borne in mind.
Finally, efforts must be made to bring about changes
in the needs and demands of consumers (often very differ¬
ent from those of people in highly Industrialized coun¬
tries). This ls a fundamental need, economically,
socially and culturally. Consumer demand ls only partially
linked with the circulation of money and ls only partially
aimed at the satisfaction of individual needs.
But any educational effort In this direction will be
meaningless" unless It becomes part of a global attempt to
Introduce changes in the traditional ways of life of these
peoples. Thus we see once again how necessary it is to
consider both Industrial development and rural develop¬
ment as an inseparable whole and also to avoid approach¬
ing either the one or the other from a too strictly econo¬
mic point of view.
Paul Mercier, a leading French specialist in African questions, is
director of economic and social studies at the Ecole Pratique des 55
Hautes Etudes, University of Paris. He is also a Unesco consultant
in social studies.
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
HOMO SAPIENS-
THAT STRANGE PARAI III
by Daniel Bovet
Nobel Prize for Physiology and Médecine
X
56
What Is science? What are we scientists trying
to accomplish in the work we do in our
laboratories and research? When we try to answer this
question we come up against the two complementary
aspects of the problem. On the one hand, science seen
only as part of the development of rational thought and
knowledge; on the other the contribution of science to
economic and social advancement through the applica¬
tion of new techniques in industry, agriculture and
communication.
Even though the classical opposition between pure and
applied science is today out of date, the purposes and
consequences of science cannot be totally divorced from
these two aspects.
If the purpose of scientific knowledge is considered by
some to be the enunciation of universal laws, to others it
is nothing more than an instrument of practical action.
Whereas Henri Poincaré affirmed that "thought is no
more than a flash of light in the darkness of a long night
but it is this flash that is everything," Henri Bouasse, not
without humour, supported the pragmatic attitude when
he wrote "the scientist seeks a pattern into which the
facts may be moulded, and science has but one justifica¬
tion for Its extreme monotony: to serve an end."
When looked at in terms of economic development
(where its results are most apparent) the answer to our
question is relatively easy: the growth of new sources of
energy, the advances made in telecommunications and
methods of transport, automation in industry and fac¬
tories, the rise in the expectation of life and the almost
total disappearance of infectious diseases are but a few
of the hundreds of obvious examples of the progress
achieved by the second industrial revolution.
But this is not the most important consideration, and
if we are not to overlook what is perhaps the crux of
the problem we must recognize that the moral, social
and even political revolution brought about by the recent
development of science is as important as, if not more
important than, the technological changes themselves.
Today scientific research has become such an impor¬
tant element of modern society conducted and exploited
almost on a par with mineral or land resources, that a
real effort must now be made not to forget that this
capital asset is really no more than the ideas, the culture,
the creative genius I am tempted to add the flight of
fancy of a few men.
Thus if the stereotyped image of the scientist as a man
in an ivory tower lost in incomprehensible experiments,
little understood and the butt of many jokes, has not
entirely disappeared, it is slowly dying and giving way
to the modern notion of the "team of scientists" working
in richly endowed institutes, forming a growing army of
skilled investigators at the service of important industrial
and governmental bodies.
One of the major results of the new policy of planning
scientific research is the influence it will have, either
consciously or not, on the ultimate equilibrium between
the various branches of scientific research.
In the nineteenth century the most audacious theories
of science came from the field of biology and it was here
that the greatest battles raged between old and new ideas.
In our present century the most spectacular and most
revolutionary discoveries have been made in the physical
sciences micrpphysics and our knowledge of the uni¬
verse. The scope of present-day discussions on both
questions of theory and practice lead one to believe that
the balance will continue to weigh heavily in favour of
the physical sciences for some time to come.
But when we consider the enormous problems facing
the biologist and the crucial importance for all mankind
of the ultimate solution to these problems it would seem
preferable to have the scales of the balance tip once
again in favour of the life sciences.
I should like to recall at this point a hypothesis which
I formulated some years ago concerning the history of
the major trends in human thought. I called it "the
hypothesis of the constant or invariability of grey
matter". This hypothesis is based exclusively on the
experimental method. Thus, of 100 rats raised in my
laboratory only ten (or fifteen at the most) are capable
of being taught even a slightly complex operation. If I
train them to climb on to a perch at a given signal it
Is unlikely that they will learn to open a door. If I teach
them to push a lever in order to get a drop of sugared
water they often forget their other skills.
I have sometimes asked myself if this does not also
apply to our own human society.
We know that certain colleges and universities have
found themselves depleted of staff because of the serious
inroads made upon them by industrial laboratories. Can
we imagine what would härmen if an excessive demand
for physicists suddenly deprived us of good biologists and
doctors? Do we not have examples in history where cities
have suffered from a lack of good statesmen because
everyone wanted to be an artist, or where the over-
popularity of philosophy deprived a nation of leaders for
its defence. This is a subject the reader might carefully
ponder.
I t is no longer enough to proclaim that no
I sphere of knowledge can henceforth remain
unexplored; we must also recognize our degree of igno¬
rance regarding the many problems deeply affecting man
himself. These embrace a broad field of subjects parti¬
cularly the vast domain of the basic sciences, molecular
biology and biophysics, research into intermediary meta¬
bolism and the science of nutrition, neurophysiology, the
study of the information processes in the central nervous
system, psychology and animal sociology in relation to the
study of behaviour.
Man's noblest intellectual and cultural achievements
have sprung from the human brain, the organ which
controls our behaviour and thought and largely regulates
our physical and mental well being. , The study of the
brain should, therefore, it seems to me, occupy a promi¬
nent place In research programmes and be carried out
as a co-operative scientific enterprise both on an inter¬
national and inter-disciplinary scale.
As for the field of pharmacology, particularly familiar
to me, I feel that the time is now ripe for a concerted
]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[
WHO-Spooner FROM MICE TO MEN. The behaviour of animals, of mice and rats in particular, has been
widely studied by scientists. Biologists have gained valuable knowledgo for tho lifo sciences.
attack on the problems of therapeutics and mental and
social hygiene just as the research drives of recent years
have led to important breakthroughs that have van¬
quished disease and prolonged human life.
We must work for the prevention and treatment of the
degenerative diseases of the brain, mental deficiency and
the physical disorders of old age. Certainly after
conquering a horde of disease-bearing microbes, chemo¬
therapy is hardly less capable of attacking those more
subtle spectres, our hallucinations and obsessions.
Not long ago a biologist formuiated the hope that
science would produce à "formula to make' men good."
I for my part believe that since man can never halt on
the road of evolution he will be obliged in the future to
resolve his own dilemma by choosing between the "Soma"
of Huxley's Brave New World which will plunge him into
a state of stupid beatitude, and the pill which will make
him more intelligent by developing his learning capacity
and power of retention.
Since I have espoused the cause of biology I dare
say I gladly support the seeming paradox which main¬
tains that it is through the study of animal behaviour
that we should embark on the study of the human
sciences. And I am convinced that biological research
offers us the clearest road for understanding how the
development of his own knowledge can in fact modify
and enrich man's vision of his own destiny.
In human terms then what can we foresee as the result
of -this new "Operation Scientific Research"?
In contrast to Jean-Jacques Rousseau who denounced
the corruption of morals engendered by science, the
Encyclopaedists saw in scientific progress the one great
hope for mankind and the raison d'être of all our endea¬
vours. In the centuries that followed, Rousseau won
numerous new supporters as the world witnessed the
extraordinary development of science and technology.
And even today there are still those who point an accusing
finger at science. The narrow intellectual sphere in
which the scientist works is roundly denounced and cer¬
tain groups have even gone so far as to see in the machine
and automation a "world conspiracy against all inner
life," accusing the scientist of depriving man of hLs
"soul."
And yet the value of science in forming and developing
the Individual is evident to us every day as teachers. We
see it In the drive, the enthusiasm, the perserverance as
well as the will and spirit of abnegation of our students
and colleagues; we see it in action among our fellow
scientists in universities and research institutes; we sec it
in the determination of so many of them to be an active
part of the society they live in, convinced that their deep
faith in a supreme truth will help to achieve a much
broader ideal of human justice. As scientists wc arc filled
with the feeling that we have received a parcel of the
wonderful heritage bequeathed to us by our masters, and
which, transcending those now living, continues to enrich
us after four centuries of a long, prodigious tradition.
Why is our age, which is barely over the threshold of
Immense new sources of energy, gripped by a sensation
of helplessness bordering on despair? Wc are so dLsillu-
sloned by the experience of two world wars and their long
aftermaths; so obsessed once again by the feeling of
insecurity and so deeply troubled as members of society,
that It would seem our generation has lost the courage
and the will to believe and work for peace.
As men of science we must proclaim loudly not only
that science is not solely responsible for all the evils of
our day but that some of the greatest accomplishments
of the post-war period have been brought about by
science.
Confident as I am in a new humanism, I believe that
we can have no sober constructive vision of the future if
it is not based on a rational approach to reality, recourse
to science to solve the problems facing us, and the search
for an ideology and technology worthy of man.
Daniel Bovet, of Italy, won the Nobel Prize for Physiology
and Medicine in 1957. He is director and founder of the 57
Therapeutical Chemistry Laboratory at the Institute of
Health in Rome.
]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[
INTO THE W
58
CSF, René Bouillot
Two symbols of today's vast scientific revolution. Above, telemetering
equipment for tracking the orbits of satellites in space. Opposite
page, completion of a huge parabolic mirror used in helio-technology
to capture the rays of the sun and turn them into useful energy.
]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[
ORLD OF THE FUTURE
by Nicolai Semenov
Nobel Prize for Chemistry
Soviet photo. SCR photo library. London
What will the world be like 20 or 40 years hence,
at the close of the century? What levels, so
far unimaginable, will science and technology attain by
that time? And what fundamental changes will this
have wrought in the world economy? In this age, when
science is moving ahead with such amazing speed, it is
impossible to predict new scientific discoveries. But we
can foresee, with a certain degree of probability, the very
considerable practical consequences of scientific trends
that are already apparent.
The 19th century is often described as the age of steam
and electricity. How are we to describe the 20th cen¬
tury? As the age of nuclear energy, of the conquest of
the air and of outer space, of plastics, of radio, television
and electronics, or of cybernetics and electronic computers,
of chemicalized and mechanized agriculture, of new
medical compounds and longevity?
Modern science is ceaselessly producing new and varied
types of technique and new kinds of production. The 20th
century is characterized not only by the great increase in
the volume of scientific knowledge but by the qualitative
change In the character of science itself.
Comprehension of the inner structure of matter, the
attack on the inner regions of the atom, began In the first
20 years of the 20th century and It was that which started
this revolution in natural science. This understanding
of the internal structure of matter has made it possible
for us consciously to determine some of the characteristics
of some materials.
In chemistry this has led to a new method of synthesis,
by which we can create new compounds and improve the
technology of producing previously known substances.
In physics it has led to a great number of new dis¬
coveries in the field of solid bodies, of which we shall men¬
tion only a few. They are the emission of electrons
under the Influence of heat and irradiation by light; the
discovery of semiconductors with their astonishing
electrical properties; the discovery of the phenomena of
the transmission of energy in a solid body and, connected
with it, the possibility of coherent radiation of a narrow
59
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[
WORLD OF THE FUTURE (Cont'd)
Brief encounter with an 'anti-man'
60
beams of light and short radio-waves in the so-called
lasers and masers.
All this led to the creation of new techniques in very
different forms. For example, the discovery of radio-
waves, predicted by Maxwell and made by Herz in the
19th century, has acquired very great technical signifi¬
cance only as the result of the application of the dis¬
coveries of physics in the 20th century. New fields of
science and technology have appeared, such as radiotech-
nology and electronics.
Many wonderful discoveries were made as a result of the
study of the atomic nucleus. When nuclei are being
formed a tremendous amount of energy is liberated from
the protons and neutrons as a result of the nuclear forces
between them. According to the well-known equation
formulated by Einstein on the equivalence between mass
and energy, the energy liberated corresponds to the loss
of mass. Depending on the content and the structure of
a nucleus the concentration in the nucleus varies, as a
result of which different nuclei have different losses of
mass which can be measured. This loss of mass is called
the mass defect.
In nuclear reactions the less the mass defect of the
initial elements, the greater the energy released. I feel
confident that the day is not far off when we shall be
able to achieve a controlled thermonuclear reaction which
promises quite unprecedented prospects for the develop¬
ment of world energy.
Our galaxy consists of substances built of protons and
neutrons In the nucleus, and electrons in the shell of an
atom. However, there is a possibility that some other
galaxies are made of anti-substances, of anti-protons and
anti-neutrons in the nucleus and positrons in the shell
of the atom. In these worlds anti-particles will be stable
and our particles will be unstable.
It is noteworthy that all physical and chemical quali¬
ties of the atom will be identical in both worlds. In these
other worlds we might find the same chemical combina¬
tions with the same structure and qualities and it is quite
probable that living matter and even human beings simi¬
lar to those in this world may exist there.
Imagine the meeting of a man and an anti-man some¬
where in space. They will be able to study each other
and even become bosom friends, but they will not be able
to touch each other. If they should try to do so, they
would both explode with a power considerably greater
than that of a thermonuclear bomb...
here need be no doubt that coming decades
will see a powerful upsurge in physics which,
as is always the case, will have as its "end" result very
Important technical achievements. In fact, I believe that
two fundamental problems stand out in modern natural
science. The first concerns the theory of elementary
particles in physics, or, in other words, the problem of
the primary particles of matter. The second, in contrast,
concerns the structure and behaviour of highly organized
matter in biology and chemistry.
Animate matter is the most highly organized matter.
The revolution which began in physics, and partly in
chemistry, in the early years of the century, reached
biology about half a century later, some 10 or 15 years
ago. Working in concert with physicists and chemists,
biologists began to penetrate the inner physical and
chemical foundations of the amazing phenomena of life.
In these fifteen years we have obtained highly interesting
scientific results, and the pace of research is constantly
being increased.
Just as in the case of the study of atomic structure,
these major scientific discoveries have not had, and prob-
The very real dangers of air
pollution resulting from indus¬
trialization are now being stud¬
ied intensively by scientists
in all parts of the world. Here,
samples of air are analyzed in
a laboratory in Mexico. Uni¬
versal application of electric
power in the future would
drastically reduce even per¬
haps eliminate altogether
the emission of harmful gases
and dust into the atmosphere.
© Paul Almasy. Paris
ably will not for some time have, serious practical results.
But it Is beyond doubt that sooner or later they will lead .
to revolutionary changes in medicine and agriculture. For
instance, I feel sure that the problem of cancer can be
solved only by developing this trend in biology. And I am
equally certain that research in the mechanism of physical
and chemical processes in vital activity will likewise lead
to a veritable revolution in chemistry.
By applying the same principles to inanimate matter we
should be able to create catalysts of unprecedented power
and specific properties, notably for photochemical pro¬
cesses. We should also be able to design fundamentally
new types of machines which, working like muscles, will
directly and efficiently convert chemical energy into
mechanical energy, etc. That is why I believe that the
problem of highly organized matter is the second main
problem in the decade ahead.
It is very characteristic of modern science to make a
profound investigation of the internal structure of matter
and to produce on this basis new unprecedented techniques
and new types of production. Research which now seems
very abstract and of no practical application, such as the
Investigation of the properties of matter, sooner or later
leads to revolutionary changes in industry. The more
purely scientific the research appears, the greater the
changes that result. The research that seemed most
abstract of all turned out to be that which produced the
greatest practical results the discovery of atomic and
thermonuclear energy.
Here, I can only give a brief outline of the gigantic
prospects opening up before mankind as a result of the
further development of science and its practical applica¬
tion.
Available sources of power, notably electric power and
deposits of coal, oil, uranium, thorium, and water power
resources will not last forever. They are gradually being
exhausted, and though the reserves are great, they are
nevertheless limited. In addition, the mining of coal,
uranium and thorium, even with maximum automation,
will always involve strenuous working conditions. The
question therefore arises of the new, more powerful and
practically inexhaustible sources which could be developed
with relative ease.
At present there are three ways of solving this crucial
scientific and technical problem: (1) by controlled thermo¬
nuclear reaction: (2) by the utilization of solar energy;
and (3) by the utilization of the underground heat of
the magmatic stratum below the earth's crust.
]]>
</page>
<page number="61">
<![CDATA[
achieve this in practice. However, the progress in photo¬
electric and thermoelectric research should, within a few
decades, enable us to devise new photo- and thermo¬
elements and find special catalysts of photochemical
processes. This. In turn, should make it possible to
convert solar energy Into electricity with an efficiency
rate of 30 to 40 per cent. I am convinced that the
problem of utilizing solar energy for power purposes can
and will be solved before the end of the century.
The third potential and practically inexhaustible source
of energy is the underground heat of the magmatlc strata
of the earth, located about 30 kilometres below the surface
and much nearer under the ocean bottom. The chief
problem here is effective and economical technological
methods of deep boring. Recent years have seen revolu¬
tionary changes in boring techniques, but many formida¬
ble technical problems have still to be solved before wc
can tap these underground heat depositories.
Several countries are working on new methods of deep
boring, and In some cases they are actually being applied.
Given an abundant supply of low-cost electricity and
Improved transmission techniques, we should be In a posi¬
tion to replace boring by the melting of rock and extrac¬
tion of the melted substance.
Controlled thermonuclear reaction would open up
altogether new and incomparable vistas for the human
race. However, it seems that a continuously controlled
thermonuclear reaction is practically impossible because
it releases such tremendous heat and such high tempera¬
tures to sustain itself that the walls of the "thermo¬
nuclear furnace" would be immediately vaporized.
But physicists have suggested the principle of magnetic
isolation, which reduces heat radiation through the walls
and makes the process feasible in principle. By using
a powerful current impulse they have succeeded in
obtaining temperatures close to those required to start a
thermonuclear reaction and test the principle of magnetic
isolation.
However, to start a self-sustained thermonuclear reac¬
tion we shall have to obtain considerably higher tempera¬
tures. There are also many other major difficulties, for
instance, the problem of effective magnetic isolation in a
continuous thermonuclear reaction.
Controlled thermonuclear reaction has not yet been
achieved. Undoubtedly its achievement calls for new
ideas, new departures. It is hard to say when this
cardinal problem will be solved, tomorrow or many years
hence. But I believe that solved it will be, and within
this century. For all the experience of modern science
shows that what is possible in principle soon becomes
possible in practice.
Ery great prospects would be opened to
mankind If we learned to transform solar
energy Into electric energy with a high efficiency
standard. The sun sends to earth 4x10" calories per
second. Most of this solar energy is diffused or absorbed
by the atmosphere, particularly by clouds. An average of
only 30 per cent reaches the earth's surface in any given
year a little more in southern latitudes, a little less in
northern latitudes. Yet even one-tenth of what reaches
the land surface would suffice to generate thousands of
times more power than we have today. This is the second
major potential power purveyor, and one that will always
be there and will never require mining or expenditure of
fuel.
In principle, 100 per cent of solar energy can be
converted into electricity, but we are not likely ever to
ND so, In addition to coal, oil, uranium and
i thorium, we have other, much more potent
suppliers -of energy. If we put them to efficient use, all
the power requirements of the world's growing population
will be fully met, for these new sources are practically
limitless. But they can be utilized only If there ls a vigo¬
rous and concerted effort by scientists and technicians,
and, needless to say, by all the peoples of the world.
Thus, I feel sure that by the close of the century all
three new sources of energy will have been put to work
and the first thermonuclear, solar and underground
generating plants will have been built. The 21st century
will see the mass construction of such plants. That will
bring electricity to every Inhabitant of the world, in
virtually limitless quantities.
With a superabundance of electric power at its dLsposal,
mankind could tackle and accomplLsh other, even more
ambitious tasks. One example Ls the regulation of the
earth's climate. Temperature and rain control could
turn our planet into, a flourishing garden.
The auspicious beginning of space travel poses another
problem, one which today seems rather far-fetched. I
refer to the possible role of thermonuclear energy In the
exploration of Mars and other planets of the solar system.
We know, of course, that Mars has an atmosphere but, In
the first place, it ls much more rarefied than the Earth's,
and secondly and more important it contains a very
small proportion of oxygen. Apparently there Ls water on
Mars, but in relatively small quantities. The climate ls
colder than the Earth's, and that would be an additional
drawback.
Let us consider whether or not it ls realLstlc to create
on Mars, within a relatively short period (say, a few
decades) conditions that would support life. The first
requirement for this Is to obtain several hundred trillion
tons of oxygen, to bring Mars's oxygen content near to
that of our own atmosphere. Oxygen can be produced
from the water we shall find on Mars. Calculations show
that if we build thermonuclear power plants on Mars
capable of generating ten thousand times more electricity
than ls now produced on Earth, and if this energy is
used for the electrolysis of water, then we should be able
to accumulate the needed oxygen in a few decades.
I do not know whether mankind will ever need to do
that. It may well be that it will find better employment
for its superabundance of power. But I cite this example
to indicate the majestic alms mankind can set itself once
it has inexhaustible sources of energy. g4
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="62">
<![CDATA[
WORLD OF THE FUTURE (Cont'd)
Transistor network on the moon
In discussing the practical problems involved in explor¬
ing the solar system, I should like to go a step further in
my fantasy and examine opportunities for utilizing the
moon to supply power to our planet. The moon Is 16
times smaller than the earth, but since It has no
atmosphere It gets three times more solar radiation, per
unit of territory, than the earth. Consequently, in terms
of solar energy absorption, the moon ls equivalent to one-
fifth of the earth's surface or, what amounts to the same
thing, gets nearly as much energy as all our continents.
Thus, if we were able to cover the moon with a network
of high-efficiency transistor photo-elements, and if, in
addition, we devised ways and means of transmitting this
energy (say, via directed radio beams), then the moon
would become a huge generating plant serving the earth.
It might also become a suitable location for nuclear and
thermonuclear power plants that could rid our earth of
all radioactive contamination.
Utilization of thermonuclear and solar energy and of
underground heat would naturally involve fundamental
changes in industry, agriculture and what we sometimes
describe as household service. Inorganic chemistry,
metallurgy and the building materials Industry would, in
the main, use high-temperature reactions and arc dis¬
charges. There would also be a sharp increase in the use
of electrolysis techniques. Super-high temperatures
would be obtained either through arc electric furnaces
or from thermonuclear reactor waste gas, heated to several
thousand degrees.
For example: nitrogenous fertilizers would be obtained
chiefly from the air, through a synthesis of nitrogen
oxides. All the elements of the Mendeleyev Table could
be produced either by electrolysis or by decomposition of
ores, effected by high-temperature thermonuclear reactor
waste gases. In fact, the very concept "ores" would
change, for any combinations, notably those that have
not been used hitherto because of their chemical inertia,
could be employed as "ores."
On the other hand, utilization and enrichment of poor
ores would be greatly simplified. Essentially, any soil
treated by high-temperature techniques could become a
building material. Universal application of electric power
would lead to maximum automation in all lines of pro¬
duction and would drastically reduce even perhaps
eliminate altogether the emission of harmful gases and
dust into the atmosphere.
There would, of course, be a great demand for polymers,
and their production would be on a scale comparable to
the production of metals. All deposits of natural gas, oil
and some of coal would be used for this purpose and for
obtaining a wide variety of organic substances. All that
will be possible when electricity replaces gas, oil and coal.
However, despite total electrification, there would still
be automobiles, aircraft and rockets; they would still be
using liquid and gaseous fuels; there would still be a need
to produce substantial quantities of oil and gas.
The problem can be solved by (1) producing synthetic
fuel from inorganic raw materials. This can be done, for
instance, by employing electric techniques to obtain
hydrazine from nitrogen and hydrogen; (2) by using
carbon dioxide and hydrogen for an artificial synthesis
of conventional fuels.
Agriculture and the food industry would be electrified
arid automated throughout. When we have a supera¬
bundance of cheap electricity, the production of fertilizers,
as I have already pointed out, will be greatly simplified
and enlarged. Irrigation, too, would be expanded, by
using plastic sheets to retain moisture, both under and
over plants.
Another development would be soil heating in northern
areas and a vast expansion in hot-house cultivation.
Combined, these methods would produce high harvests
and. in many areas, two harvests annually. Lastly,
electricity would be used on a very large scale to augment
our fresh-water supply from seas and salt lakes.
^ * *
#* *
*»»
/
\
4 & *
444 &
44 4
44£
\
52
/
)
]]>
</page>
<page number="63">
<![CDATA[
ELECTRONIC
MARVELS
Today's gigantic technological
achievements often have as
their basis the tiny electronic
components in these photos.
Transistors, opposite page, and
diodes, right, are the miniature
amplifiers and detectors for
which almost limitless useshave
been found wherever electro¬
nics is needed, be it in TV,
radar,atomic energy equipment,
electronic computers, aeronau¬
tics, space research and auto¬
mation processes in industry.
Diodes shown here are sealed
glass tubes only six millimetres
long, containing a single wire
solded to a germanium plate.
Photos CSF. René Bouillot
There is no need to dwell on the fact that electricity
adds to our comfort. I will, however, mention two
beneficial developments: electric heating and air
conditioning in every home in every part of the world.
Universal automation would reduce the working day to
three or four hours, leaving many hours for sports,
gardening, amateur theatricals, art, literature, civic duties,
and for research in excellently equipped public labora¬
tories, which would become centres for bringing science
to the people and ensuring its continuous development.
That is how I visualize life in the 21st century: an
age of total electrification. That ls my vision of the
heritage we can and should bequeath to our children,
grandchildren and their children.
The ideal of social progress can be approximately denned
in the following way: the maximum happiness for the
maximum number of people, for almost everybody. The
first precondition for this is naturally the full satisfaction
of the material and cultural needs of every man on earth.
However, the satisfaction of material needs alone is not
enough for a happy Ufe, though it is, of course, the main
and necessary precondition for the full spiritual activity
of man. But by his nature man is also a creator of
material and spiritual values. The need of creative
activity Is not only one of the noblest but also one of the
most Important fundamental and Ineradicable needs of
homo sapiens. So our greatest task ls to bring varied
creative activities within the reach of the mass of the
people.
Some people may not agree with my understanding of
happiness; they regard happiness not as a creative but
as a passive thing. Others regard happiness as a turbu¬
lent thing arising out of work or leisure. But I personally
believe that such views of happiness are due to spiritual
poverty or to the lack of the social conditions necessary
for the discovery and development of the creative talents
which exist potentially in every normal man.
In a word, to demonstrate his creative ability and to get
pleasure from doing so, every man must have a certain
level of knowledge, of mental and emotional development,
of aesthetic taste, and a moral attitude towards society
and himself. This can be achieved if such economic and
social conditions are created as to ensure an all-round
development of people and their creative labour.
Nicolai Semenov, Soviet physicist and physical chemist,
was the winner of the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1956. 53
A member of the U.S.S.R. Academy of Sciences, he is pro¬
fessor of physics at Moscow State University.
]]>
</page>
<page number="64">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New:
DEPUTY DIRECTOR-GENERAL FOR
UNESCO: Dr. Malcolm Adiseshiah,
who has been an Assistant Director-
General of Unesco since 1954, has now
been appointed as Unesco's Deputy
Director-General. Dr. Adiseshiah, of India,
joined Unesco in 1948. He has been
especially concerned with the development
of technical assistance activities and has
played an important role" in the etablish-
ment of educational plans for Asia and
Africa.
DIAL 'BOOKS': Thanks to new auto¬
mation techniques, homes in the
U.S.A. will in the next ten years be tied
in through equipment no more complicated
than the average telephone with local
libraries, through them to regional centres
and finally to a national centre. All
information in these libraries will then
become directly available to the house¬
holder or businessman. This future prospect
is described in a report, "The Library and
Information Networks of the Future",
prepared by the American Library
Association.
UNESCO-SPONSORED COURSES :
i An international course on soil science
and plant .biology sponsored by Unesco
will be held at the Universities of Seville
and Granada between October 21, 1963,'
and May 7, 1964. Another Unesco-
sponsored international post-graduate
course, in Probability Theory and Mathe¬
matical Statistics will open at the Hungarian
Academy of Sciences in Budapest on
October 15 and will continue until May 15,
next year.
WORLD CLASSICS TRANSLATED:
Thirty-six classics of world litera¬
ture are being translated into the principal
Indian languages by the Sahitya Akademi
(Indian National Academy of Letters). The
works include plays by Moliere and
Shakespeare, Machiavelli's "The Prince"
and works by Thucydides and Confucius.
In appreciation of this contribution towards
its projects for the mutual appreciation
of cultural values in the Occident and the
Orient, Unesco has donated $5,000 worth
of printing paper to the Academy for. the
publication of the works.
ART FILM FESTIVAL: A festival of
films on art sponsored by . the Cana¬
dian National Commission for Unesco was
held in Ottowa recently. At a seminar
which accompanied the festival, inter¬
national specialists led discussions on the
use of the film in the study of art, the
challenge of TV, and problems of preview,
distribution and programming.
DISAPPEARING GRIZZLIES : If
Americans were to choose a national
animal, says the National Audubon
Society, in the United States, the grizzly
bear might well win the honour. Yet
today grizzlies are being killed off so fast
that no more than 600 are left, all but a
few in the state of Montana.
RADIOISOTOPES FOR ARAB LANDS:
A regional radioisotope centre recently
set up in Cairo under the. auspices of the
International Atomic Energy Agency will
be responsible for promoting the use of
radioisotopes in Arab countries in the fields
of medicine, agriculture, hydrology and
industry.
AFRICAN UNIVERSITY EX
CHANGES: Six African universities
have agreed to join a programme of
student exchanges suggested by the Uni¬
versity of Ghana. They are higher educ¬
ational institutions in Tanganyika, Sierra
Leone, Morocco, Uganda, Ivory Coast and
Ethiopia.
MjESSONS BY POST: Correspondence
education in the United States has under¬
gone a phenomenal growth in the past few
years. There are now 59 accredited private
home study or correspondence schools
enrolling some 800,000 students from the
U.S. itself and many countries around the
world. Subjects range from agriculture
and accounting to zoology. There are
courses for practically all ages and those
with special needs, including the blind and
handicapped.
International school for
IBADAN: An international secondary
school which aims to prepare African
students for higher education will be
opened in October in Ibadan, Nigeria, by
the University College. The school will
be co-educational and its curriculum will
include additional specialized courses such
as Nigerian languages, home economics and
religious studies. Pupils will also be
encouraged to join "hobby" classes. Special
efforts will be made to link the school
with those in other countries.
IT OMAGE TO FIRST SPACEWOMAN:
" In a statement congratulating the
Soviet Union on the success of the twin
space flight of the cosmonauts Valéry
Bykovsky and Valentina Tereshkova,
Unesco's Director-General, Mr René
Maheu declared: "It is the human aspect
of this exploit the presence aboard one of
the vessels of the young Valentina Teresh¬
kovathat grips one's imagination. Above
all, it is a magnificent example of intelli¬
gence, endurance and courage, demons¬
trating that woman is fully man's equal."
CYPRUS CENTRE FOR WORK-
CAMPERS: On a site close to Nicosia,
in Cyprus, members of the International
Student Movement for the United Nations,
working with Cypriots, are laying the
foundations of a training centre for work-
campers from countries in the Eastern
Mediterranean region. The centre will offer
courses in the theory and practice of inter¬
national voluntory service, particularly in
community development
POLIO CASES DOWN: The number
of known cases of poliomyelitis in the
world was reduced by about 65 per cent
between 1954-56 and 1960. In Asia,
however, the drop has only been 25 per
cent and in Africa the number of cases
has actually risen by 10 per cent.
TWO MILLION COMPUTER
EXPERTS: Within the next 20 years
the Soviet Union will need at least two
million computer programmers. Work is
already beginning on the training of this
army of specialists and many secondary
schools now include the use of calculating
machines in their studies.
News F/ashes. . ,
THE UNESCO PHILATELIC SERVICE
64
A slender figure of a bird formed from
palm leaves has been used as the
design for this 13 cent airmail stamp
issued, along with two other airmail
stamps In 6 cent and 8 cent denomina¬
tions, by the United Nations Postal
Administration on lune 17. As agent
In France of the U.N. Postal Adminis¬
tration. UNESCO's Philatelic Service
stocks all the U.N. stamps and first day
covers currently on sale, and those
issued by UNESCO member states to
commemorate important events in the
history of UNESCO and the U.N. For
prices and further details write to The
UNESCO Philatelic Service. Place de
Fontenoy. Paris (7e).
An estimated 150 million people suffer
from bilharziasis, a serious disease of the
tropics caused by snail-borne parasites and
passed on to man through rivers and canals
in which the snails live, reports the World
Health Organization.
East Africa, which scientists used to
consider an earthquake-free area, probably
has between 2,000, and 3,000 local tremors
a year, according to a team of Unesco
experts who toured the region recently.
Forty-six countries have now joined the
UNESCO-sponsored Universal Copyright
Convention designed to fill gaps in existing
international copyright laws.
The Unesco Kalinga Prize for the
popularization of Sciences has been awarded
to Mr Gerard Piel, American science
writer and publisher of the "Scientific
American", who is the ll//i winner of the
prize.
]]>
</page>
<page number="65">
<![CDATA[
SCIENTISTS ABROAD
by Alan J. A. Elliott
bout one third of all fellowships and scholar¬
ships offered for study abroad are awarded In
the fields of science and technology. This has been
revealed by successive analyses of the offers listed in
Study Abroad, Unesco's international handbook on
fellowships, scholarships and educational exchange.
The thirteenth edition of Study Abroad, which gave
information on awards available in 1962 and 1963, listed
over 130,000 individual opportunities. Of these about
10% were for the study of mathematics and natural
science. And about 20% were for the study of applied
sciences and technology, Including engineering, medicine
and agriculture. For the sake of comparison, about 14%
of awards were offered in the social sciences, and nearly
16% in humanities, liberal arts, linguistics, literature and
history.
This means that at least 40,000 scientists and techno¬
logists received awards for study abroad during the aca¬
demic year 1962 alone. In practice the figure may be
considerably higher, because 25-30% of the offers made In
Study Abroad do not specify a field of study. Although
the actual allocation of awards is not known with any
great accuracy it would be safe to say that at least a
quarter of these awards, amounting to about 10,000 were
also made to scientists.
Actual examples of fellowship programmes listed
in Study Abroad are extremely varied. They include
the programmes of the Food and Agriculture Organiza¬
tion, Unesco, the World Health Organization, and other
organizations of the United Nations system. There are
also the programmes of other intergovernmental organiza¬
tions such as the European Organization for Nuclear
Research and the International Computation Centre.
Non-governmental organizations such as the Inter¬
national Union against Cancer and the International
Astronomical Union contribute their share. Among the
national chapters some very important programmes are
listed, for example those of the French Centre National
de la Recherche Scientifique (CNRS), the United Kingdom
Department of Scientific and Industrial Research (DSIR),
the United States National Research Council and the
U.S.S.R. Academy of Sciences.
O|n the other end of the scale there are many
programmes of limited size and more
specialized aims. For instance, Rutgers University, New
Jersey (USA), gives one fellowship a year to a young
Italian microbiologist. The A.F. Regnell Botanical Dona¬
tion permits the Swedish Royal Academy of Science to
award, at Irregular intervals, fellowships to Swedes for
study of botany in Brazil or other "intertropical
countries."
In between these two extremes are a large number of
programmes involving many thousands of individual
awards directed in general towards the promotion of
economic development. Most of these programmes are
government-sponsored, accounting for about 50% of all
fellowships offered.
It is not always easy, though, to identify the proportion
devoted to science and technology. The Government of
India offers four "Union Territories Overseas Scholar¬
ships" for "any branch of science, engineering, technology
or medicine." But the Government of Libya offers 258
State Scholarships for study of "teacher training, agri¬
culture, engineering and other fields" In Europe, the U.S.A.
and the United Arab Republic. And among countries
offering technical assistance, the U.S. Government, In one
of Its many programmes, makes approximately 1,900
awards for which the subject of study Ls "generally
unrestricted" to "nationals of most countries having
United States diplomatic or consular posts." It is
reasonably certain, however, that a high proportion of
such awards ls made In science or technology.
The fellowship programmes of the U.SS.R. on the other
hand, although fewer in number, make more .specific
mention of "science, agriculture and medicine" as fields
of study.
When attention Ls turned to the number
of scientists studying abroad, regardless of
whether or not they are receiving fellowships. It Ls found
once again that they represent a large proportion of all
foreign students. Unesco's tenth annual survey of foreign
students enrolled in higher education showed a total, In
all fields, of over 250,000 In the academic year 1900-1001.
In a very general way, the overall situation can be viewed
from two main viewpoints. One Ls the tradition that
science, and for that matter all academic learning and
research, cannot be restricted to any one nation, and that
as long as there have been universities, students and
teachers have gone abroad to follow their vocations.
The other of much more recent origin concerns the
great need for training scientists and technologists from
countries undergoing rapid economic development. This
second part of the problem Is by far the more urgent
for practical, present-day purposes; but as It cannot be
seen In entire Isolation a word needs to be said about the
more general problem of scientific exchanges.
In a sense, the phenomenon of scientists studying abroad
Is only part of the broader problem of the international
exchange of scientific Information. While It would be
wrong to Infer that all scientists who go abroad do so for
purely professional purposesthere ls probably as high a
proportion of "educational tourists" among scientists as
in any other discipline it can be assumed that most of
them are prompted by the need to acquire knowledge and
experience that they cannot obtain at home.
It may be that Institutions for scientific study do not
even exist In their own countries; or perhaps they have
been unable to obtain places in suitable institutions. With
respect to the more specialized branches of post-graduate
study or research, a student may feel the need to work
with a particular teacher abroad. Very few countries
are entirely self-sufficient in facilities for scientific re¬
search. And even those that are. or nearly so, have a
strong tradition of exchanging knowledge with workers in
the same fields abroad.
But study abroad ls not the only way of exchanging
scientific Information. From some points of view It is a
very Ineffective way. For the problem nowadays ls not
so much one of encouraging scientists to meet each other,
but of providing them with a means of access to the very
large quantities of articles and papers on a enormous
range of subjects appearing In the scientific journals of cc
the world. bi
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="66">
<![CDATA[
SCIENTISTS ABROAD (Cont'd)
50,000 science fellowships a year
Fellowships for study abroad are by no means
the only way of promoting personal contacts. An
Increasingly important phenomenon is the large number
of congresses, conferences and meetings that take place
every year. The facilities of air travel, and the financial
support of governments and industrial concerns, has made
It possible for larger numbers of scientists than ever
before to meet each other. At least half a million go
abroad every year for such purposes.
This, then, is the general background of international
scientific relations against which the problems of study
abroad must be seen. But when one turns to the particu¬
lar problems which face countries in the process of rapid
enonomlc development a completely new set of factors
has to be taken into account. In the past and even
today some of the greatest scientific developments have
been achieved without a very clear definition of goals. In
fact, the research scientist often produces his best results
through being allowed a maximum freedom of action.
Nowadays the drive towards economic and social
development demands a very careful statement of
objectives. This tendency affects the whole world, but
It Is particularly drastic in countries which can least afford
the luxury of wasted effort.
In two-thirds of the countries of the world, in which
many millions Uve on the borderlines of undernourish¬
ment, there is the greatest need for economy of effort
and the careful development of human resources. Offers
of outside assistance are not lacking, but programmes of
technical co-operation cannot achieve the results expected
of them unless they are carefully planned and co¬
ordinated. The development of science and technology
is obviously one of the first and foremost needs.
But inevitably projects in the fields must find themselves
In competition with other types of projects. Moreover,
scientific personnel must be of high intelligence and
ability. So there is competition for human resources just
when the most desirable prizes may seem to lie in politics
or diplomacy rather than In further academic study.
Further than that, there is competition between basic
sciences on one hand and technology on the other. If
there are not enough scientists it simply means that not
much research will be done. If there are not enough
technologists there will be no factories or railways. And
beyond that there is competition between the different
sciences and different technologies. And so on.
Where does study abroad fit into this picture?
The answer to this is complicated by the fact
that whatever its role may have been in the past there
must now be a careful assessment of plans for the future.
Two major considerations must be taken into account.
The first is derived from the well-known situation in
which exceptionally large numbers of science students
who go abroad never return home. And of those that
do there is much dissatisfaction owing to Inability to find
employment suitable to the experience acquired abroad.
The second consideration depends on an assessment of
where the most serious obstacles to scientific development
lie. For the present and immediate future some of the
most serious problems He in general education at the
primary and secondary levels, rather than in the specific
training of scientists. But in many countries the heart
of the problem can be pinpointed as lying in science
teaching in secondary schools. And this is not a problem
which can be solved by massive programmes for study
abroad by scientists.
It is clear that In future there must be a careful selec¬
tion in fact, rather more careful than has hitherto been
the case of objectives to which funds will be devoted for
study abroad. This must begin with an assessment of
the number of qualified scientists who can be produced
eg by domestic training institutions, and decisions as to how
these institutions will be developed or supplemented in
the future.
To a great extent plans for study abroad must be
designed to fill the gaps. Some countries may still have
to send relatively large numbers of science students abroad
for university degrees, simply because of a present lack
of university places. Others may be able to pinpoint their
needs to a few specialized post-graduate subjects in which
they do not possess and in which they may probably not
find it worthwhile to possess fully developed research
facilities. But above all, the scientist must be assured
of worthwhile and remunerative work on his return.
Wherever possible, fellowships for study abroad In
scientific or technological fields should be planned so as
to achieve very much more effective results than at
present. It is worth noting that in Unesco's fellowship
programmes, in which science is given a very high priority,
only about one-quarter of the thousand or so awards made
each year are In scientific subjects per se. A high propor¬
tion of Unesco fellowships as a whole are for thé develop¬
ment of general education.
MONG the science fellowships awarded by
Unesco there are many examples of the ways
in which study programmes are carefully elaborated in
relation to clearly-defined needs. One of its programmes,
which is operated in collaboration with the International
Brain Research Organization, provides for about 30
fellowships through which interdisciplinary studies
concerning the brain can be promoted. Fellows may
specialize in neuroanatomy, neurochemistry, neurophar¬
macology or other relevant fields. Plans are being made
for a fellow from Japan, for example, who has already
been studying at the University of California, to do re¬
search on the topic of "Brain Mapping in Birds" at the
University of Tübingen.
Another type of fellowship can be found in connexion
with projects under the United Nations Special Fund.
Whereas the brain research fellowships are intended to
promote research at a very advanced level, Special Fund
fellowships are designed to give the necessary qualifica¬
tions to scientists or technologists who will be employed
on clearly-defined projects after their return home. Five
fellowships of this type, for mathematical study and
hydraulic engineering, are being awarded, for example, to
candidates from Vietnam and Cambodia in connexion
with preliminary studies for the gigantic project of
controlling the Mekong River, which flows through.
Vietnam, Laos, Cambodia and Vietnam, by a series of dams
and barrages.
A different example of a Special Fund project can be
found in the Japanese International Institute of Seismo¬
logy and Earthquake Engineering. Fellowships for atten¬
dance at the Institute by candidates from seismic zones
elsewhere in the world are awarded by both the Govern¬
ment of Japan and by Unesco.
But an important part of this broader picture is the
increasing realization that the application of science and
technology for the purposes of economic development is
not a one-way process in which the more highly indus¬
trialized nations transmit their knowledge and experience
to those less advanced. The real key to the problem lies
in the creation of institutions in less developed countries
which can absorb and utilize experience gained elsewhere.
Once these institutions have begun to take root they
are often in a position to contribute to development
outside their own frontiers. In scientific matters, as
much as any others, much of the success of this process
must depend on the sympathetic relationships which can
be established between institutions in different countries.
As often as not these relationships are of a non-govern¬
mental or private nature.
There are many examples of fruitful results from the
"pairing" or twinning of universities. The personal
contacts established through study abroad on this basis
can have far more meaning than when such a system
does not exist. In this and similar ways there lie the
greatest possibilities of not only assisting developing
countries in their more urgent needs, but also of bringing
them, to the advantage of all, to the status of full
participants in the worldwide scientific community.
u
z
<
Z
a:
<
]]>
</page>
<page number="67">
<![CDATA[
source book
for science
teaching
A UNIQUE SURVEY OF WORLD SCIENTIFIC TRENDS
UNESCO SOURCE BOOK
FOR SCIENCE TEACHING
A new revised
and enlarged edition
of this indispensable aid for
science teachers and students
previously translated Into 20
languages and reprinted 1 1 times
250 PAGES, CLOTH BOUND
Price: 20/-(stg) ; $4.00 ; I4F.
Published in the United Kingdom
in ' co-edition with Educational
Productions Ltd.
by Pierre Auger
A book which Is not only the first of its kind,
but likely to be one of the most Important basic
scientific works of the coming decade. It will
be of exceptional Interest to science research
Institutions, universities, government science
officers, science teachers and Industryin fact,
to all who are interested In the history and deve¬
lopment of scientific research.
Twenty-nine intergovernmental organizations,
66 international non-governmental organizations,
the national research organizations of 42 coun¬
tries and 255 scientific experts have collaborated
to produce this book under the direction of Pro¬
fessor Pierre Auger, a leading physicist and the
former head of Unesco's Department of Natural
Sciences.
Cloth bound : 33/(stg) ; $6.75; 23 F.
current
trends
in scientific
research
DO YOU READ IMPACT' ?
Everyone interested In scientific progress
and the advancement of society should read
this Unesco quarterly. Each Issue presents
articles on social aspects of science and
technology written by specialists from different
countries.
Annual subscription: 9/6 (stg); $1.75; 4.50 F.
Where to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; rates quoted are
for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO COU¬
RIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. PanuzaT, Press Department, Royal
Afghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Melbourne University Press, 369 Lonsdale Street,
Melbourne, C. I., Victoria. (A. 15/-). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C-., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Sch. 60.-). BELGIUM. Editions " Labor ",
342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-Boek-
handet, Belgielei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (100 FB) and art slides only: Louis de Lannoy,
22, place de Brouckère, Brussels. CCP 3380.00.
BURMA. Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road,
Rangoon. (K. 5.50). CANADA. Queen's Printer,
Ottawa, Ont. ($ 3.00). CEYLON. The Associated
Newspapers of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Colombo, 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99 Chungking South
Rd., Section 1, Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa). CUBA.
E.C.O.D.A.L.D., Neptuno 406, entreManziquey San Nico¬
las Havana. (2.25 pesos). CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia
Ltd., 30 Ve Smeckàch, Prague 2. DENMARK. Ejnar
Munksgaard, A/S Tidsskriftafdelingen, Prags Boulevard 47
Copenhagen S (D.kr. 12). ETHIOPIA. International
Press Agency. P.O. Box 1 20. Addis Ababa. ICELAND.
Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co. Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, 2, Keskuskatu.
Helsinki. (Fmk. 540). FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco.
Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7'. CCP. 12598-48. (7 F.).
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg Verlag, Rosens-
heimer Strasse 1 45, Munich. For the Unesco Kurier
(German ed. only) Bahren-felder-Chaussee 160,
Hamburg-Bahrenfeld.CCP. 276650 (DM 8). GHANA
Methodist Book Depot Ltd. Atlantis House. Commercial
St., POB 100, Cape Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See
United Kingdom. GREECE. Librairie H. Kaufímann,
28, rue du Stade, Athens. HONG-KONG. Swmdon
Book Co., 64, Nathan Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY.
Kultura, P.O. Box 149. Budapest, 62. INDIA. Orient
Longmans Ltd. Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay 1; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; Gun-
foundry Road, Hyderabad, 1 ; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/1 Asal Ali Road, P.O. Box 3 86, New
Delhi, 1 ; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.,
17 Park Street, Calcutta 16, Sandia House, New Delhi.
Indian National Commission for Co-operation with
Unesco, Ministry oí Education, New Delhi 3. (Rs. 7).
INDONESIA. P. N. Fadjar Bhakti, Dialan
Nusantara 22, Djakarta. IRAQ. Mackenzie's
Bookshop, Baghdad. IRELAND. The National Press,
2. Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd., 35, Allenby
Road and 48, Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv( 1 £ 5.50).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour
Street, Kingston. Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
(10/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Ton-Nichome,
Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605 Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
(Yen 670). JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman.
KENYA. E.S.A. Bookshop, P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission (or Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64. Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole
and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LUXEMBURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue,
Luxemburg. MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications Ltd., Times House,
River Valley Rd., Singapore (M. $ 500) MALTA.
Sapienza's Library 26 Kingsway, Valetta. (10/-).
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon
Street, Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid
des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (7 NF.). NETHERLANDS.
N. V. Martinus Ni|hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague,
(fl. 6). NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES. G. C. T.
Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.) N.V., Willemstad, Curacao.
NEW ZEALAND Government Printing Office
Wellington, Government Printing Office, P.O. Box 5344,
Auckland and Government Bookshops, Auckland,
Wellington, Christchurch Dunedin (10/-). NIGERIA.
C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box 174, Lagos. (10/-). NOR.
WAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille Grense. 7, Oslo
For the Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Litteratur
Tjeneste, Stortingsgt. 4, Oslo, Postboks 115 (kr 13.20
PAKISTAN. The Weit-Pak Publishing Cor
Ltd., Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box 374, 56-N
Gulberg Industrial Colony, Lahore. PANAMA.
Cultural Panameña, Avenida 7a, No. TI-49, Apartado de
Correos 2018, Panama, D.F. (Balboas3-). PHILIPPI-
NES. The Modern Book Co.. 508 Rizal Avenue P.O. Box
632 Manila. POLAND. " RUCH " ul. Wiloza Nr. 46,
Warsaw 10 (Zl. 50). Dias & Andrada
Lda, Livraria Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon.
PUERTO RICO. Spanish English Publications Apartado
1 91 2, Hato Rey. RHODESIA & NYASALAND. The
Book Centre, First Street, Salisbury, Southern Rhodesia.
SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O.Box 1118, Khart¬
oum. SWEDEN. A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbok-
handel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm. For The Unesco
Courier: Svenska Uneicoridet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 7.50); SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag,
5 Rlmistrasse Zurich. Payot, 40, rue du Marché, Geneva.
CCP. 1-236. " Courier " only: Georges Losmaz, 1, rue
des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CCP. 1-4811. (Fr. S. 8).
TANGANYIKA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop. P O.B.
9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND. Suksapan
Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok. (35
ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda
Bookshop, P.O. Box 145, Kampala. UNION OF
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Bookstore. Libri
Building, Church Street, Pretoria. For the Unesco Cou¬
rier (single copies) only: Central News Agency, P.O.
Box 1033, Johannesburg. (10/-). UNITED ARAB
REPUBLIC (EGYPT). La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh.
Adly-Pasha, Cairo. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M.
Stationery Office. P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I. (10/-).
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications Center,
317 East 34th St, New York, 16. N.Y. ($5.00.)
and (except periodicals): Columbia University Press,
2960 Broadway, New York, 27 N.Y. U.S.S.R. Mez-
hdunarodnaia Kniga. Moscow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA
Yugoslovenska Knjiga, Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="68">
<![CDATA[
I
! v.
T
Students at the Institute of Physics and Chemistry
in Asuncion, Paraguay, are shown the uses of
miniature o kits of experimental apparatus for
science teaching, by a Unesco science expert. Pro¬
fessor Alvarez-Querol. Unesco helped to set up the
Li INIA à
Asuncion Institute and has continued to provide it
with expert advisers and equipment for its work
of training science teachers for secondary educa¬
tion and future university professors and also
for the provision of modern research facilities.
]]>
</page>
</document>
