<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="063446eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
DECEMBER 1963 (16TH YEAR) PRICE 1/-STG. (U.K.) - 30 CENTS (CANADA) - 0.70 F (FRANC
:*»»
^>-.*>
"*»jt"
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A UNESCO ALBUM
OF TURKISH ART
© Unesco
These two examples of Turkish art are taken from a Unesco World Art Series
Album, "Turkey: Ancient Miniatures " (See page 18). Top of page: "Scene of
Nomad Life" by Siyah Kalem (15th century), from The Album of the Conqueror.
Above : "Music in the House of a Notable", from the Album of Ahmed I (1603-1617).
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier
DECEMBER 1963
16TH YEAR
Contents
No. 12
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
COVER PHOTO
This issue is devoted to the
Universal Declaration of Human
Rights, on the occasion of the
15th anniversary of its adop¬
tion by the United Nations
General Assembly, on Decem¬
ber 1 0, 1 948. For the fi rst ti me
an international document pro¬
claimed the rights of the indi¬
vidual and laid down the
conditions required to assure
the liberty and dignity of the
human person. But today,
hundreds of millions of human
beings are still waiting for
their rights to become realities.
© Verger - ADEP
Page
4 FIFTEEN YEARS AGO...
Man and his rights
By Jaime Torres Bodet
6 UNESCO AND HUMAN RIGHTS FOR ALL
12 THE OUTLAWING OF INDIA'S CASTE SYSTEM
By Humayun Kabir
15 ELEANOR ROOSEVELT
A lifetime of dedication to Human Rights
By U Thant
16 THE TEXT OF THE UNIVERSAL DECLARATION
18 ANCIENT TURKISH ART
Images of court and everyday life
20 ATATURK AND THE EMANCIPATION OF WOMEN
By Afet Afetinan
26 FREEDOM AND CULTURE
By German Arciniegas
32 UNESCO PUBLICATIONS ON HUMAN RIGHTS
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
(M.C. 63.1., 186 A)
Scientific and Cultural
France
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational,
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
René Caloz
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani (Moscow)
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Italian Edition : Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER ii published monthly, except in July and August when
it is bi-monthly ( I I issues a year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, Ctrmtn.
Arabic, Japanese, and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed hy H.M.
Stationery Office. P. O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier Is Indexed monthly In The Readers' Guide to
Periodical Literature published by H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates : IO/-stg. ;$3.00 (Canada) ;7.00
French Francs or equivalent. Single copies l/-stg. 30
cents ; 0.70 F.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
15 YEARS AGO..
On December 10, 1948, the
Universal Declaration of Human
Rights was adopted by the
General Assembly of the United
Nations meeting in Paris. At
that time, Unesco's Director-
General, Jaime Torres Bodet
hailed this great event in these
words:
THE declaration of io December
1948 is more than an historical
summary, it is a programme.
Every paragraph is a call to action,
every line a condemnation of apathy,
every sentence a repudiation of some
moment of our individual or national
history; every word forces us to scru¬
tinize more closely the situation in
the world today.
The destiny of mankind is an
indivisible responsibility which we
all must share. So long as it remains
possible to flout with impunity even
one of the rights of one single human
being, the United Nations Declara¬
tion will continue to accuse us all of
cowardice, sluggishness, laziness, and
to remind us that we are lacking in
human charity. So long as the greater
part of the human race continues to
live face to face with hunger and
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
injustice and to die in squalor and
ignorance, the Declaration adopted in
Paris will represent nothing more
than a remote ideal.
To make the Declaration known
everywhere is to wage a world¬
wide campaign for a life
worthy of man, to whom the
governments have dedicated this
Declaration, not in mere lip service,
but in solemn recognition of their
duties to civilization and to humanity.
To help States carry out these
duties in the field of education,
science and culture is the proud
mission of Unesco. What nobler
task could be assigned to culture,
education and science, than to make
all men the guardians, and hence
the fervent exponents, of the Uni¬
versal Declaration of Human Rights ?
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
£) Paul Almasy. Paris
SCHOOLS FOR ALL. Education must be free and compulsory, at least in the elementary
and fundamental stages, to make the right to education a reality for all. Above, an elementary
school class in Tunisia where a 10-year nation-wide programme to establish free and compul¬
sory education has been in operation since 1958. School enrollment has already increased by
nearly 65%. Unesco has sent educational specialists to Tunisia to help with this programme.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO
AND HUMAN RIGHTS
FOR ALL
Unesco helped to prepare the Universal Declaration of Human Rights
and has since assumed two responsibilities: to spread knowledge
and understanding of the principles on which the Declaration is
based and to work for the attainment and universal respect of rights
relating to education, science and culture. The rights on which
Unesco has concentrated special efforts are those defined in Articles
26, 2, 27 and 19. (The complete text of the United Nations
Universal Declaration of Human Rights is reproduced on page 16).
Everyone has the right to education . . .
(Article 26)
LL Unesco's work for education from the
i extension of free and compulsory primary
education to educational planning and development, from
education for international understanding to the im¬
provement of general secondary and technical vocational
education and from adult and youth education to the
international exchange of educational information and
documentation aims to help member states achieve the
standards proclaimed in Article 26 of the Universal
Declaration.
As part of its efforts to extend free and compulsory
primary education Unesco launched in 1957 a 10-year
major project for the extension of primary education in
Latin America. This is designed to help co-operating
states of the region to provide education for all children
of primary school age as speedily as possible.
Since then, other large-scale programmes for the
development of education at the primary and other levels
have been undertaken in Africa, Asia and the Arab states.
For example, with resources provided from the United
Nations Special Fund, Unesco has recently started several
broad development programmes in these regions for
technical and vocational education and the training of
secondary school teachers.
The educational goals of the Universal Declaration
will only be attained if the advancement of education in
schools is accompanied by action to provide out-of-school
education for both young people and adults. Unesco has
therefore set up regional training centres for education in
community development in the Arab states and Latin
America; it has aided national projects of youth and
adult education; it has organized international con¬
ferences and expert meetings, and has carried out a wide
variety of educational activities In collaboration with non¬
governmental organizations.
A further step of major importance was taken in 1962
when the General Conference of Unesco authorized the
Organization to help prepare a massive world literacy
campaign. The first phase of the campaign, which would
be completed within the limits of the United Nations
Development Decade, aims to bring literacy to some
300 million of the 500 million illiterate young people and
adults In Unesco member states in Asia, Africa and Latin
America.
Unesco has joined in the struggle against discrimina¬
tion in education. A Convention and Recommendation
against Discrimination in Education was adopted by the
General Conferences in 1960, "not only to proscribe any
form of discrimination... but also to promote equality of
opportunity and treatment for all in education." The
Convention came into force in 1962.
In combating discrimination in education, Unesco has
singled out for special attention the problem of providing
full access to education for girls and women. It co¬
operates closely with non-governmental organizations
working to extend education opportunities for women.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO AND HUMAN RIGHTS (Contd)
Without distinction of race, colour, sex,
language...
(Article 2)
u nesco's action to combat discrimination ranges
over many different aspects of the problem,
from Its effects in impairing the right to education
to the harm caused by racial discrimination.
In recent years Unesco has been diagnosing the causes
of racial prejudice among young people and finding out
how to prevent such prejudice from developing. Its
Inquiry on this subject among young secondary students
In France, the German Federal Republic and the United
Kingdom can be considered as the first comparative
study of its kind.
During the past 12 years, Unesco has published or has
sponsored the publication of some thirty works on race
questions. To these publications it will shortly be adding
a study by S. Zavala (Mexico) on "The Defence of Human
Rights in Latin America" (16th to 20th centuries) in
the series Race and Society, and also a collective work,
"Industrialization and Race Relations," prepared under
the direction of the Institute of Race Relations (London)
in the series, The Race Question in Modern Science.
The nine booklets previously published in this series
have been re-Issued in one major volume which presents
the points of view of sociologists, anthropologists, biolo¬
gists and ethnologists on the origins and development of
race prejudice, and demonstrates that there is no scien¬
tific justification for racial discrimination.
Unesco plans to carry out and to publish the results
of two further studies. "The Development of Race Rela¬
tions in Africa," a collective work, will include contribu¬
tions by African and non-African specialists. The results
of the second study will be published as a booklet, "The
Economy and Race Relations." (See also The Unesco
CourierOct. 1960on "Racism").
Unesco has also made studies of the ways of life of
certain marginal social groups. One of these "Nomads
and Nomadism in the Sahara," prepared by C. Bataillon,
of the Ecole Pratique des Hautes Etudes in Paris, has
made an important contribution to knowledge of noma¬
dism, of the conditions in which it develops and of its
social and cultural consequences. Another example is
the study by J. Ben Davis, of the University of Jerusalem,
on the agricultural communities established in Israel by
the immigrants who arrived there in great numbers after
the second world war.
Thirteen years ago, Unesco published a declaration
in which some of the world's leading specialists in the
fields of biology, genetics, psychology, sociology and
anthropology set down the conclusions of scientific think¬
ing on the question of race. Judging that the time is
now opportune for a fresh evaluation of scientific thought
on this question, Unesco is to convene another internation¬
al meeting of specialists to reconsider the previous
declaration.
Everyone has the right to the protection
of the moral and material interests
resulting from any scientific, literary or
artistic production of which he is
the author.
(Article 27)
Unesco is making a broad
study of new possibilities for
attaining the right to share In cultu¬
ral life. By showing some of the
factors which already give the popu¬
lation as a whole access to cultural
life, Unesco will try to establish a
better and more precise definition of
measures that can assure a broader
and more effective application of this
right.
This study is being made in already
technically advanced countries and in
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
<0 Rapho-Bornhard Moosbiucgoi
others at present embarking on
programmes of technical development.
Basically it seeks to assess the
potential results that can be attained
through a rapid expansion of mass
communication media (radio, the
press, T.V., the cinema, libraries and
museums), always keeping in mind
the need to maintain the cultural
values of works that will become
increasingly accessible through these
means.
In the field of copyright, where
multilateral Conventions already in
existence have failed to obtain gene¬
ral accession, Unesco has drafted a
Universal Copyright Convention
which lays down that in all states
adhering to it, works and authors of
foreign origin shall enjoy the same
protection as is given to works and
authors of national origin. This
Convention, which came into opera¬
tion on September 16, 1955, estab¬
lished an Intergovernmental Copy¬
right Committee which continues to
watch over the operation and appli
cation of the Convention and over
questions of copyright in general.
Unesco Is currently convening an
African regional study meeting on
copyright at which the newly-inde¬
pendent nations on this continent
will examine together problems of
authors' rights.
Unesco has also recently sponsored
an International Convention for the
Protection of Performers, Producers
of Phonograms and Broadcasting
Organizations.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO AND HUMAN RIGHTS (Cont'd)
BOUNDLESS
PROSPECTS
OF SPACE
COMMUNICATION
Last year, the General Conference of
Unesco declared its conviction that
space communication offers "boundless
prospects" for advancing Unesco's aims.
The retransmission of radio and TV pro¬
grammes carried out experimentally with
the U.S. satellite, Telstar, (left) has
already revealed the feasability of inter¬
continental communications by this
means. For economic reasons, space
satellites are likely to be first used regu¬
larly in the field of information and later,
depending upon the extent of interna¬
tional co-operation, for educational and
cultural exchanges on a global scale.
Right, a transistor radio brings the
latest news to villagers in Mauritania.
USIS
The right to receive and
impart information and
ideas through any media
and regardless of fron
tiers...
(Article 19)
10
Fifteen years ago, the United Nations Con¬
ference on Freedom of Information declared
that freedom of information "is the touchstone of all the
freedoms to which the United Nations is dedicated."
The United Nations and Unesco have recognized this fact
by their constant efforts to help the people of developing
countries to obtain adequate means of information.
Four years ago, the United Nations Commission on
Human Rights asked Unesco to make a special study of
information facilities press, radio broadcasting, films
and TV in developing countries and to suggest how they
might be improved.
Covering Asia, Latin America and Africa, Unesco's
survey took, as a basic standard that any group of people
should be considered to enjoy the "vital minimum" of
information facilities if, for every 100 persons, it had the
following: ten copies of daily newspapers; five radio
receivers, two cinema seats and two TV receivers.
The inquiry revealed that for some 2,000 million people
in over 100 countries available information media falls
short of this "minimum standard"; in other words, two-
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
te
UNCSCO - Pioiro hllot
thirds of the world's population is deprived of this basic
right to information.
Unesco then prepared a programme to help the devel¬
oping countries to reach the minimum standard by 1975.
The programme was endorsed in December 1962 by the
U.N. General Assembly which asked nations to consider
it as an element in the United Nations Development
Decade. The General Assembly also asked Unesco to
keep its survey up to date and to continue to further the
development programme by using such means as new
communication techniques to speed up progress in edu¬
cation.
u nesco is carrying out this task In a variety
of ways. News agency development has been
spurred by the setting up under Unesco's auspices of
regional associations of news agencies in Asia and Africa.
Unesco is helping to promote the training of journalists
by granting fellowships and holding regional seminars.
It sends experts to help countries build up their radio,
film and TV services and to train staff in the use of these
media for education. It is now studying how space
communication through man-made satellites may be
used to promote the free flow of information and aid tbe
development of education.
As defined in the Universal Declaration of Human
Rights, freedom of information comprises freedom to
seek, receive and Impart Information and ideas "through
any media." The agreement which Unesco prepared
abolishing customs duties on books, publications and
other educational, scientific or cultural materials has now
been adhered to by 44 countries.
To appropriate International conferences Unesco has
submitted proposals designed to promote free flow of
Information through a reduction of postal and telegra¬
phic charges and of transportation costs for persons
engaged In educational, scientific and cultural work.
Unesco has also introduced a coupon scheme as a
means of reducing currency barriers to the free move¬
ment of educational, scientific and cultural materials and
to the exchange of students, teachers and research
workers. Unesco is helping to Improve and extend tech¬
niques in information media. The reports and studies
which it publishes are alerting public opinion to the ..
obstacles which Impede the free flow of information
between countries.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
THE OUTLAWING OF
INDIA'S CASTE SYSTEM
by Humayun Kabir
NÍEVER before in history has there been such
recognition of the rights and duties of the
ordinary citizen as there is in this century.
In spite of the teaching of religions to the contrary, all
societies in the past have been hierarchic in which a
minority enjoyed privileges at the cost of the majority.
Race, colour and sex have In the past been the basis of
discrimination within and among communities. Different
conceptions of human rights could and sometimes did
subsist side by side and because of lack of communica¬
tions failed to coalesce or influence each other.
Today such a state of affairs is unimaginable. Whatever
happens in one corner of the globe has immediate reper¬
cussions on all other parts. There can therefore no longer
© Richard Lannoy
be divergent conceptions of human rights. Any charter of
human rights today must be a charter on a global scale.
Such a charter is the Universal Declaration of Human
Rights.
The great religions of the world have perceived the
identity of human rights and duties from the earliest
times. Though quite early in the history of India caste
became an essential feature of the Hindu community,
Hindu religious insight has always recognized the dignity
of the individual by Identifying the human soul with the
Absolute. Buddhism with its doctrine of flux and the
conception of Nirvana, Christianity With its enunciation
of the Fatherland of God and Islam with its emphasis
on the brotherhood of man have all proclaimed the same
doctrine with equal and sometimes even greater force.
12
Women pilgrims
from Maharashtran
in Western India ar¬
rive in Benares, the
sacred city of the
Hindus. These coun¬
try-women wear tra¬
ditional heavy silver
anklets and they have
tied up their saris like
trousers to give them
greater ease when
walking. In India
today, the Constitu¬
tion affirms complete
equality of rights for
all citizens what¬
ever their religion,
race, caste or sex.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Today, in schools the world
over, new generations learn
the lessons of human rights.
By instilling the recognition
and respect of these rights in
the classroom, the teacher
can do much towards dispel¬
ling deep-rooted social and
racial prejudices. In India,
"untouchability" on the basis
of caste has now been abo¬
lished and its practice in any
form is forbidden. Right, a
teacher in a village on the
Upper Ganges reads to his
class from a book written in
Hindi, a language used by
over 100 mjllion people in
India. The painted mark seen
on his forehead shows that he
belongs to the Hindu religion.
Raphe- <0 Louis-ri6d6tic
All religions have declared that injustice against one
man Is an offence against all men. The Indian religions
carried this doctrine still further and held that an offence
even against an animal or a plant is a sin. One may add
that apart from religious considerations, self-interest, if
not ethics, has from the earliest times taught man that he
should refrain from doing unto others what he would not
like being done unto himself. Without this recognition of
the rights of others, there would have been no civil society.
In spite of the fact that mutuality of rights and duties
is the basis of human relations, man has often sought to
claim rights for himself and deny his duties to others.
Till the modern age, consent of the ruled was assumed
rather than sought for. With the spread of the democratic
principle, this has changed and today all progressive
countries have written into their Constitutions certain
fundamental rights and safeguards to preserve the dignity
of the individual and secure social justice to all. The
preamble of the Indian Constitution affirms its determi¬
nation to secure for all citizens: "Justice social, economic
and political; Liberty of thought, expression, belief, faith
and worship; And to promote among them all fraternity;
Assuring the dignity of the individual and the unity of
the Nation."
This reaffirmation was the more necessary in India, as
our practice has often deviated tragically from the ideal.
I need refer only to the disabilities which arose out of the
institution of caste. In origin and intention, though not
In actual operation, caste was a device for enabling
different races and individuals to live together in har¬
mony. Individuals as well as families could in the earlier
phases pass from one caste to another. Caste in its earlier
phases also helped to mitigate the economic conflicts
which so sharply divided nineteenth-century Europe.
Whatever may once have been the justification of caste,
it had already become an Institution of oppression by the
time the Buddha appeared. His was one of the first nota¬
ble revolts against caste. Ever since, Indian religious
teachers and reformers have fought it. The South Indian
Nayannars denied It In the first mlllenlum after Christ.
Sankaracharyya, often regarded as the champion of
orthodox Hinduism against Buddhism and all other here¬
tical creeds, ls believed to have honoured an untouchable,
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
OUTLAWING CASTE (Cont'd)
Prejudices die hard
14
a man of the lowest caste in the Hindu social hierarchy.
The impact of Islam In the middle ages gave an Impetus
to the movement against caste and fostered a religious
renaissance based on the dignity of man. Great reformers
like Ramanand and Kablr, Nanak and Chaitanya sought
to break down the barrier of caste and judge individuals
for their intrinsic worth.
The advent of Europe on the Indian scene also helped
to undermine the rigors of caste. Starting from Raja Ram-
mohan Roy, a succession of social, political and religious
leaders fought to diminish the rigors of caste, if not alto¬
gether to abolish it. Names like those of Vidyasagar and
Ranada, Shraddhanand and Vivekanand readily come to
one's mind.
ne of the most powerful poems of Tagore
Gitanjali attributes the misfortunes of India
to the evils of caste. Gandhi threw the whole weight of
his personality against untouchability and caste and
staked his Ufe to restore freedom and equality among
all members of the Indian community. It is therefore
not surprising that the Indian National Congress has
accepted the eradication of caste as one of its major
goals.
The declaration of the equality of rights and duties for
all citizens in the Indian Constitution ls therefore a direct
outcome of the teaching of Indian seers from the days
of the Buddha. In the modern period, voluntary agencies
in all parts of the country have worked to create a new
social consciousness based on the equality of man.
One may add that modern developments in technology
had in any case created a situation where caste and
untouchability had become obsolete. Modern modes of
transport compelled close contact among people of diffe¬
rent castes, communities, races and creeds. Industrializa¬
tion forced men and women to Uve together regardless of
caste. The growth of towns led to increasing anonymity
and offered the individual an opportunity of shedding
disabilities of caste.
OME ideological as well as technological consi¬
derations have combined to enshrine the con¬
cept of natural justice and respect for the individual in
the Indian Constitution. Of the many article dealing
with human rights, the following are of special interest:
"The state shall not discriminate against any citizen on
grounds only of religion, race, caste, sex, place of birth or
any of them."
"No citizen shall, on grounds only of religion, race,
caste, sex, place of birth or any of them, be subject to any
disability, liability, restriction or condition with regard to
access to shops, public restaurants, hotels and places of
public entertainment ; or the use of wells, tanks, bathing
ghats, roads and places of public resort maintained wholly
or partly out of state funds or dedicated to the use of the
general public."
"There shall be equality of opportunity for all citizens
in matters relating to employment or appointment to any
office under the State."
"No citizen shall, on grounds only of religion, race, caste,
sex, descent, place of birth, residence or any of them, be
ineligible for, or discriminated against in respect of any
employment or office under the State."
"'Untouchability' is abolished and its practice in any
form is forbidden. The enforcement of any disability
arising out of 'Untouchability' shall be an offence
punishable in accordance with law."
"No citizen shall be denied admission into any educa¬
tional institution maintained by the state or receiving
aid out of State funds on grounds only of religion, race,
caste, language or any of them."
"The State shall promote with special care the educa¬
tional and economic Interests of the weaker sections of the
people, and, in particular, of the Scheduled Castes and the
Scheduled Tribes, and shall protect them from social
injustice and all forms of exploitation."
As a further step towards the eradication of the social
disability of the so-called lower castes, the Untouchability
(Offenses) Act, 1955 (22 of 1955) became law on June 1,
1955. This Act provides for the punishment for the prac¬
tice of "Untouchability," for the enforcement of any
disability arising therefrom and for matters connected
therewith. Offenses under the Act, on the grounds of
"Untouchability," are punishable with imprisonment.
I n a democracy, the outcome even of legisla¬
tion depends ultimately on the will of the
people and on the determination and effort of the back¬
ward sections themselves. Prejudices die hard and quick
results cannot be expected. The surest, though not the
quickest, way is therefore to make education broadbased
and extend to all neglected classes the benefits of gene¬
ral, technical and professional education. A programme
for the purpose was taken up even before the Consti¬
tution was adopted and it has been intensified since then.
With the development of educational facilities all round
and the growth of industries and cities, it can be con¬
fidently expected that "untouchability" will vanish before
long. The major burden for bringing about a change in
outlook depends on the teachers. They will have to deve¬
lop a feeling for Human Rights in the minds of the rising
generations through precept and, even more important,
practice. The U.N. Charter will prove a most valuable
tool for teachers in this work, for here we have a for¬
mulation of rights and duties which apply to all men in
all countries of the world. Although not enough has been
done In schools in India and particularly in teacher train¬
ing establishments for spreading the lessons of the Char¬
ter of Human Rights, it is my earnest hope that the
15th Anniversary celebrations of the signing of the Decla¬
ration will give a fillip to this programme.
In the words of our President, Sarvepalli Radhakrish-
nan, "The Commonwealth of humanity has no written
Constitution; it is based on community of ideals, freedom
and dignity of the individual, rule of law, economic
opportunity for all citizens and love of peace."
Humayun Kabir is Minister for Scientific Research and
Cultural Affairs of the Government of India. A distin¬
guished writer and educator, Professor Kabir is the au¬
thor of many works on philosophy, poems and shaft
stories. His article and the review of Unesco's work for
Human Rights (pages 6-11) are taken from a neio United
Nations publication, "Teaching Human Rights" (2nd
edition, 1963), a handbook for teachers in elementary and
secondary scliools. (Price: $0.35.)
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
ELEANOR ROOSEVELT, who died last
year, once wrote that in all her years at
the United Nations she considered that
the most important task had been her
work on the Human Rights Commission.
Chairman of the Commission from its
inception in 1946 until 1951, she was
present in Paris on December 10, 1948
when the Universal Declaration, elabo¬
rated by the Commission under her chair¬
manship, was unanimously adopted by
the United Nations General Assembly.
USIS
ELEANOR
ROOSEVELT
A lifetime
of dedication
to Human Rights
by U Thant
s
*
¡Et;
F \
m
L > i
^fl ^lC*' ^1lÉIÉÉ^H-^^^^ *L^a\
f AM IHj^*
Secretary-General
of the United Nations
rs. Eleanor Roosevelt was a dominant figure
lin the early days of the United Nations, for
she came nearer than anyone else ever has to being an
actual embodiment of the commonly held ideals and aims
of the people of the world. Her personality, courage,
generosity and dedication placed her In a class by herself
and gave her a unique position of universal confidence
and respect.
It is perhaps misleading to try to single out her specific
work in the United Nations from the mainstream of her
amazing range of activity, for the whole of it was based
on broad and affectionate humanitarlanism. But this
humanitarianism and her deep concern for the underpri¬
vileged found an historic focus in the United Nations
especially in the work of the Human Rights Commission,
and in the proclamation of the Universal Declaration of
Human Rights. She could not only communicate with
the oppressed and the exploited the world over, she could
identify with them. When she spoke of rights and
liberties, she evoked no mere theory, but a practice and
a way of life.
Mrs. Roosevelt's patient and untiring work as Chairman
of the Commission on Human Rights and its Drafting
Committee was a major factor in giving shape and
substance to the Universal Declaration of Human Rights.
It was she who, as chairman of Its first session in
April 1946, proposed that the bill of rights should be
drafted in the form of a declaration or manifesto to be
followed by conventions that would be legally binding
on states.
It was her persistance and tact which guided the
immensely complicated work of drafting the Declaration
In 1947 and 1948, and her energy and enthusiasm which
sustained others In this great labour.
Though the impact of this historic document may well
take generations to achieve Its full force, its Importance
in the development of human Institutions and in the place
of the individual in history is already great and is
increasing.
Mrs. Roosevelt was one of those rare individuals whose
courage, vision and good-will and Indeed outright good¬
ness can light up a whole period of history and give
comfort and hope to humanity even in times of the
greatest anxiety and despair.
In a world in which human rights are still delayed and
denied, it is well for us to recall that Eleanor Roosevelt
nourished the dream and the hope that the Declaration
of Human Rights might one day become the Magna Carta
of all mankind.
This text is taken from an address by the Secretary-
General of the United Nations, delivered at an Interna
tional Tribute to
October 21, 1963.
Eleanor Roosevelt, in New York, on
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
TEXT OF THE UNIVERSAL DEC
Preamble
Whereas recognition of the inherent dignity and of the
equal and inalienable rights of all members of the human
family is the foundation of freedom, justice and peace
In the world.
Whereas disregard and contempt for human rights have
resulted in barbarous acts which have outraged the
conscience of mankind, and the advent of a world in
which human beings shall enjoy freedom of speech and
belief and freedom from fear and want has been pro¬
claimed as the highest aspiration of the common people.
Whereas it is essential, if man is not to be compelled
to have recourse, as a last resort, to rebellion against
tyranny and oppression, that human rights should be
protected by the rule of law.
Whereas it is essential to promote the development of
friendly relations between nations.
Whereas the peoples of the United Nations have in the
Charter reaffirmed their faith in fundamental human
rights, in the dignity and worth of the human person
and in the equal rights of men and women and have
determined to promote social progress and better stan¬
dards of life in larger freedom.
Whereas Member States have pledged themselves to
achieve, in co-operation with the United Nations, the
promotion of universal respect for and observance of
human rights and fundamental freedoms.
Whereas a common understanding of these rights and
freedoms is of the greatest importance for the full reali¬
zation of this pledge.
Now Therefore
The General Assembly proclaims
THIS UNIVERSAL, DECLARATION OP HUMAN RIGHTS
as a common standard of achievement for all peoples and
all nations, to the end that every individual and every
organ of society, keeping the Declaration constantly in
mind, shall strive by teaching and education to promote
respect for these rights and freedoms and by progressive
measures, national and international, to secure their uni¬
versal and effective recognition and observance, both among
the peoples of Member States themselves and among the
peoples of territories under their jurisdiction.
Article 1
AU human beings are born free and equal in dignity and
rights. They are endowed with reason and conscience and
should act towards one another in a spirit of brotherhood.
Article 2
Everyone is entitled to all the rights and freedoms set forth in
this Declaration, without distinction of any kind, such as
race, colour, sex, language, religion, political or other opinion,
national or social origin, property, birth or other status.
Furthermore, no distinction shall be made on the basis of
the political, jurisdictional or international status of the
country or territory to which a person belongs, whether it
be independent, trust, non-self-governing or under any other
limitation of sovereignty.
Article 3
Everyone has the right to life, liberty and security of person.
Article 4
No one shall be held in slavery or servitude ; slavery and the
slave trade shall be prohibited in all their forms.
Article 5
No one shall be sujected to torture or to cruel, inhuman
or degrading treatment or punishment.
Article 6
Everyone has the right to recognition everywhere as a person
before the law.
Article 7
All are equal before the law and are entitled without any
discrimination to equal protection of the law. All are
entitled to equal protection against any discrimination in
violation of this Declaration and against any incitement to
such discrimination.
Article 8
Everyone has the right to an effective remedy by the compe¬
tent national tribunals for acts violating the fundamental
rights granted him by the constitution or by law.
Article 9
No one shall be subjected to arbitrary arrest, detention or
exile.
Article 10
Everyone is entitled in full equality to a fair and public
hearing by an independent and impartial tribunal, in the
determination of his rights and obligations and of any
criminal charge against him.
Article 11
(1) Everyone charged with a penal offence has the right to
be presumed innocent until proved guilty according to law in
a public trial at which he has had all the guarantees
necessary for his defence.
(2) No one shall be held guilty of any penal offence on
account of any act or omission which did not constitute a
penal offence, under national or international law, at the
time when it was committed. Nor shall a heavier penalty
be imposed than the one that was applicable at the time the
penal offence was committed.
Article 12
No one shall be subjected to arbitrary interference with his
privacy, family, home or correspondence, nor to attacks upon
his honour and reputation. Everyone has the right to the
protection of the law against such interference or attacks.
Article 13
(1) Everyone has the right to freedom of movement and resi¬
dence within the borders of each state.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
LARATION OF HUMAN RIGHTS
(2) Everyone has the right to leave any country, including
his own, and to return to his country.
Article 14
(1) Everyone has the right to seek and to enjoy in other
countries asylum from persecution.
(2) This right may not be invoked in the case of prosecutions
genuinely arising from non-political crimes or from acts
contrary to the purposes and principles of the United Nations.
Article 15
(1) Everyone has the right to a nationality.
(2) No one shall be arbitrarily deprived of his nationality
nor denied the right to change his nationality.
Article 16
(1) Men and women of full age, without any limitation due to
race, nationality or religion, have the right to marry and to
found a family. They are entitled to equal rights as to
marriage, during marriage and at its dissolution.
(2) Marriage shall be entered into only with the free and
full consent of the intending spouses.
(3) The family is the natural and fundamental group unit of
society and is entitled to protection by society and the State.
Article 17
(1) Everyone has the right to own property alone as well as
in association with others.
(2) No one shall be arbitrarily deprived of his property.
Article 18
Everyone has the right to freedom of thought, conscience
and religion ; this right includes freedom to change his
religion or belief, and freedom, either alone or in community
with others and in public or private, to manifest his religion
or belief in teaching, practice, worship and observance.
Article 19
Everyone has the right to freedom of opinion and expression ;
this right includes freedom to hold opinions without inter¬
ference and to seek, receive and impart information and
ideas through any media and regardless of frontiers.
Article 20
(1) Everyone has the right to freedom of peaceful assembly
and association.
(2) No one may be compelled to belong to an association.
Article 21
(1) Everyone has the right to take part in the government of
his country, directly or through freely chosen representatives.
(2) Everyone has the right of equal access to public service
in his country.
(3) The will of the people shall be the basis of the authority
of government ; this will shall be expressed in periodic and
genuine elections which shall be by universal and equal
suffrage and shall be held by secret vote or by equivalent free
voting procedures.
Article 22
Everyone, as a member of society, has the right to social
security and is entitled to realization, through national effort
and international co-operation and in accordance with the
organization and resources of each State, of the economic,
social and cultural rights indispensable for his dignity and
the free development of his personality.
Article 23
(1) Everyone has the l-ight to work, to free choice of
employment, to just and favourable conditions of work and
to protection against unemployment.
(2) Everyone, without any discrimination, has the right to
equal pay for equal work.
(3) Everyone who works has the right to Just and favourable
remuneration ensuring for himself and his family an
existence worthy of human dignity, and supplemented. If
necessary, by other means of social protection.
(4) Everyone has the right to form and to join trade unions
for the protection of his interests.
Article 24
Everyone has the right to rest and leisure, including reason¬
able limitation of working hours and periodic holidays with
pay.
Article 25
(1) Everyone has the right to a standard of living adequate
for the health and well-being of himself and of his family,
including food, clothing, housing and medical care and
necessary social services, and the right to security In the
event of unemployment, sickness, disability, widowhood, old
age or other lack of livelihood in circumstances beyond his
control.
(2) Motherhood and childhood are entitled to special care
and assistance. All children, whether bom in or out of
wedlock, shall enjoy the same social protection.
Article 26
(1) Everyone has the right to education. Education shall be
free, at least In the elementary and fundamental stages.
Elementary education shall be compulsory. Technical and
professional education shall be made generally available and
higher education shall be equally accessible to all on the
basis of merit.
(2) Education shall be directed to the full development of
the human personality and to the strengthening of respect
for human rights and fundamental freedoms. It shall
promote understanding, tolerance and friendship among all
nations, racial or religious groups, and shall further the
activities of the United Nations for the maintenance of
peace.
(3) Parents have a prior right to choose the kind of education
that shall be given to their children.
Article 27
(1) Everyone has the right freely to participate in the
cultural life of the community, to enjoy the arts and to share
in scientific advancement and its benefits.
(2) Everyone has the right to the protection of the moral and
material interests resulting from any scientific, literary or
artistic production of which he ls the author.
Article 28
Everyone is entitled to a social and international order in
which the rights and freedoms set forth in this Declaration
can be fully realized.
Article 29
(1) Everyone has duties to the community in which alone the
free and full development of his personality is possible.
(2) In the exercise of his rights and freedoms, everyone shall
be subject only to such limitations as are determined by law
solely for the purpose of securing due recognition and respect
for the rights and freedoms of others and of meeting the
just requirements of morality, public order and the general
welfare in a democratic society.
(3) These rights and freedoms may in no case be exercised
contrary to the purposes and principles of the United
Nations.
Article 30
Nothing in this Declaration may be interpreted as implying
for any State, group or person any right to engage in any
activity or to perform any act aimed at the destruction of
any of the rights and freedoms set forth herein.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Detail of "A strolling theatre and various
acts on a raft during a night festival."
Early in the 18th century, Vebhi, a well-known poet
compiled a Surname, or festival book, for the Sultan
Ahmed III. Many copies were made of the Surname-i
Vehbi, the best known being that illustrated by the
Istanbul painter, Levni. These three reproductions are
taken from this copy which has 1 37 miniatures. Below,
"The march past of the mehter (military bandV
LIFE OF COURT & PEOPLE
IN ANCIENT TURKISH ART
Detail of "Dances and
before the Sultan."
^Phe splendid achievements of Turkey in the fields
of architecture, carpet weaving, pottery and
tile-making have been universally recognized. Yet
of all the schools of painting which existed in the
Near and Middle East during the Islamic period that
of Turkey is least known. Orîe of the reasons is that
very little of this art ever left Turkey and even in
Turkey itself it remained almost inaccessible, being
housed in the palace libraries of the sultans. Only
since the establishment of the Republic under Ataturk
have manuscripts and paintings become more readily
available. Some remarkable examples of this little-
known art have now been published in colour in a
Unesco World Art Series Album: "Turkey, Ancient
Miniatures." As these show, the Turkish miniaturist
can be distinguished from his better-known counter¬
part of the Iranian school by his choice of subject
matter. He prefers the market place swarming with
people rather than a fairy-like garden of some Prince
Charming. Though a "courtly style" of painting existed
and was used to depict incidents in the lives of the
great sultans, even this was latterly combined, in the
same painting with the "popular style" which showed
episodes in everyday life and crowds with their noise
and gossip, and which even went as far as the gro¬
tesque. This documentary approach makes many
a Turkish painting a valuable historical record. A
great number of such records are found in the "Festival
Books," "Books of Travel," "Itineraries" and "Books
of Diplomatic Missions" so profusely illustrated by
Turkish artists. On this page we present a few of the
32 full-page colour illustrations of works dating
from the 13th to the 18th centuries presented in the
album of Turkish art published by the New York
Graphic Society by arrangement with Unesco. Printed
in Italy, this volume is priced at SI 8.00 or equivalent.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
*'rf
The three drawings on this
page are by Mehmed Siyah
Kalem, a remarkable 15th cen¬
tury artist whose works figure
in The Album of the Conqueror
three volumes of drawings,
miniatures and specimens
of handwriting by Chinese,
Uighur, Seljuk and Ottoman
masters of the 14th and
15th centuries. Siyah Kalem
never depicts the settled life of
the towns. His subjects tra¬
vellers and animals chiefly
come from the highways, and he
may well have been the painter
of a nomad people. Above,
"Strolling medicine-men."
Right, detail of "Huntingscene."
Below, "Horse training."
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
ATATURK & THE EMAN
by Afet Afetinan
& Ara Guler, Istanbul
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
CIPATION OF WOMEN
Forty years ago a sweeping social revolution under the leadership and impelling
drive of Kemal Ataturk gave birth to modern Turkey. The spectacular changos
in the status of Turkish women which it brought have since becomo a symbol
and a goal to inspire those working for the emancipation of women in many
other countries. Below we publish extracts from the text of a booklet. "Tho
Emancipation of the Turkish Woman," published by Unesco last year. Its author,
Dr. Afet Afetinan, a Turkish historian, played a leading role in Turkoy's social
evolution and worked in close collaboration with President Ataturk, whoso
memory is being celebrated this year, a quarter of a century after his death.
URKisH women of the Ottoman era (14th to
20th centuries), especially those in the cities,
spent their lives In the complete seclusion of the harem.
Their occupations consisted mainly of doing or supervising
the housework, looking after the children or embroidering.
Their social life was restricted to family gatherings.
In one of her letters, Lady Montagu, wife of an English
ambassador, wrote (1717-18): "The main things women
do is go visiting neighbours, go to Turkish baths, spend
lavishly and create new costume designs." She also told
her friends in England that she liked the costumes worn
by Turkish women and that she herself possessed some.
Lady Montagu, of course, meant the costumes worn
by city women Indoors. The clothes worn outdoors
reflected the kind of secluded life led by Moslem Turkish
women. Their faces were veiled and they wore a loose
wrap known as a charshaf. A variation of this costume
was the combination of the feradje (something like a
loose-fitting overcoat) and the yashmak (a veil which left
the eyes uncovered and which was worn especially by the
CONT'D ON NEXT PAO.E
Unosco-W. Mubbell
IMAGES OF YESTERDAY
AND TODAY. Kneeling in
front of a mosque wall which
bears the name of Allah (left),
these Turkish women have
veiled their faces with their
loose wrap, or charshaf. Until
the start of the 19th century it
was forbidden for Turkish
women to appear in public
places and they had no part
in the social and cultural life
of the country. It was only
in 1923 when a democratic
regime was created in Turkey
that they attained the rights
enjoyed by women in other
modern states. Right, in this
secondary school at Ankara,
girls nowadays sit alongside
boys in a geometry class.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
ATATURK (Cont'd)
From harem to university
women of the palace). At a later date the wives of high
officials and other women who from time to time visited
the palace, either as private guests or on State occasions,
were compelled to wear the feradje and yashmak.
This type of costume was generally worn throughout the
Moslem world but only at a later date and there is nothing
to suggest that women were compelled to adopt It in the
early stages of Islam.
The Levant Herald (England) of August 15, 1881 report¬
ed: "The officers of police are instructed to keep a strict
look-out, and to make a report whenever they observe a
woman daring to wear the thin veil under circumstances
In which it ls not sanctioned by the regulations. The
report will state the name of the offending lady and the
particulars of the breach of rule and will be submitted to
the Minister of Police. Moslem ladies are also forbidden
to drive or walk round the places of Beyazlt, Shahzade-
Bashl and Aksarai and to walk In the Great Bazaar and
to sit down in shops.
"Moslem ladies are also strictly forbidden to gather
together in groups in any public places and if the police
observe any group, it will be their duty to invite them to
EQUAL RIGHTS. In Turkey the past 40 years have
been marked by rapid and far-reaching improvements
in the status accorded to women. Today they are
found in virtually every profession. Below, a young
nurse helps a doctor to vaccinate school-children.
WHO
22
disperse. This invitation will be addressed to the oldest
lady in the group, or to the servants in attendance, at the
discretion of the officer. The latter part of the regula¬
tions Is devoted to prescribing the manner in which men
shall behave to ladies in public. Any man who permits
himself to speak to a woman or to make signs to her will
be punished under Article 202 of the criminal code."
These rules, however, were not strictly applied at all
times. There were even times when women enjoyed a
measure of freedom. During the "Tulip Period," which
coincides with the second half of the eighteenth century,
women wearing light coloured feradjes attended open-air
festivities and entertainments, as is shown by paintings
and writings of that period.
From the fourteenth century until early in the twentieth
century (1918), Turkish women were subjects of a
Moslem Empire which spread over three continents
Asia, Europe and Africaand covered about six million
square kilometres.
But while the theocratic Ottoman State was extending
its boundaries, the social position of women deteriorated.
The expansion of the Ottoman Empire brought it In
contact with the influence of Persia and Byzantium, and
the old Turkish customs were slowly forgotten. During
this period new differences of status between the sexes
increased. The harem life of Persia and Byzantium was
introduced into the Turkish palace. In the fifteenth
century, on orders from the Sultan, the palace was divided
into the harem (women's section) and selamlik (men's
section).
The viziers and beys were not slow In Introducing this
system into their homes, and soon harem life and poly¬
gamy spread among a certain class of people and became
an accepted custom.
'olygamy was practised in Arabia long before
Islam and led to such a deterioration of family
life that the limitation of the number of wives to four
was considered to be an important reform. The Islamic
stipulation that men and women are equally responsible
for the honour of the family was also regarded as an
advance in Arabia, the birthplace of Islam.
Thus men and women alike were expected to abide by
the rules of morality and to be faithful to their spouses;
but all the rules and teachings of Islam could not bring
about the desired equality between the sexes even though
the laws of Islam, in general, honoured women more and
conceded them more rights than did the old Arabic, and
perhaps even the Roman laws.
The Islamic family laws adopted by the Ottomans were
concerned with marriage, inheritance and minorities. As
regards marriage, women had no say In choosing their
husbands who were selected by the parents of the girl or
an older member of her family. Engagement was not
recognized in law and, if it took place at all, It was by
private arrangement between the two families. The
husband had the right to divorce his wife whenever he
wished merely by announcing to her, orally or in writing,
"I divorce thee."
What was the situation of the slave woman of the
Ottoman period who filled the harem of the palace? They
were brought from the Caucasus and other parts of the
empire. The leading figure in the palace harem was the
sultan's mother; next came the mothers of the sultan's
children ; in addition to their wives the sultans could keep
as many odalisques and slaves as they wished.
Occasionally the sultan would give some of these women
their freedom.
Although female slaves in the Ottoman period were
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
SYMBOL OF WOMEN'S
SECLUSION. The Turkish
woman in this 19th century
photo wears a yashmak or
veil, which hides the face,
but leaves the eyes uncov¬
ered, and which women
were always obliged to
wear in public. In 1922
the first women students
who enrolled at the Faculty
of Medicine in Istanbul
wore their veils when
attending lectures with
men. They continued to
do so until 1925 when
Kemal Ataturk urged adop¬
tion of European dress.
Ata Guler collodion
treated like chattels, they were also given rights whereby
they could acquire their freedom and become members
of free society, and children of parents who had won their
freedom were also regarded as free citizens. Slavery and
the slave trade were abolished by a decree of 1854.
The role of country-woman in all the parts of the
empire was that of the producer. In farming women
supplied a great proportion of the labour and they also
played their part in the economy of the home. Though
polygamy was also practised in the country and men
sometimes married as many as four wives it was generally
for economic reasons. Country women did not dress like
the city women When outdoors. Open-air Ufe set them
working alongside men and therefore they did not hide
their faces behind veils or yashmaks. They only avoided
a man and covered their faces if he was a stranger.
In the 19th century there was a movement towards
western ways of life which led to considerable changes in
education, art and science, as well as an evolution In
social life. As a result, some progressive ideas had
already been implanted in women's minds by the end of
the century.
Already before 1869 the Government decided to open
primary and secondary schools for girls, but because the
teachers In such schools would necessarily be male and
because girls of 11-13 years of age were considered as
having reached an age when they should be segregated
from men, public opinion would not tolerate the idea. In
1870 a school was opened in Istanbul to train women
teachers for the primary and secondary girls' schools.
Although initially most of the teachers In this school
were men, by 1900 women were in the majority and hence
the number of women with a modern education likewise
increased.
The years 1908-18 were marked by two developments:
enrolment In girls' schools progressively Increased, and
certain men even ventured to go out in the company of
their wives. The fact that Sadrasam (Prime Minister)
Fuat Pasha consented to sit with his wife In the lounge
of an hotel caused much comment.
A new social situation was created in Turkey when the
Ottoman Empire entered the First World War. As men
were called up for the army women had to be appointed
to fill vacancies in the offices. During the war the
first faculty for girls attached to ttie University of
Istanbul was opened (1914). In 1921 the Arts Faculty
agreed to co-educatlonal attendance at lectures.
The passive resistance with which women, from the
CONTD ON NEXT PAGE
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Sabah
Revolutionary changes
in language & writing
When the fabric of the theocratic and feudal Ottoman Empire with its out¬
dated structures and institutions collapsed after the First World War, Kemal
Ataturk transformed Turkey into a secular state. The greatest obstacle to
development was illiteracy (over 90%) so he decided to reorganize the
educational system and to make use of Latin script (in 1928) because it
lent itself more readily than Arabic characters to a rendering of the Turkish
language in writing. Innumerable borrowings from Arabic and Persian
had produced a literary language which was almost unintelligible to the
majority of the population. Before launching a nationwide educational
programme, Ataturk decided to rid the Turkish language of these foreign
words. Today the spoken and written forms of the language are identical.
Ataturk established a number of cultural institutions, including The Turkish
Historical Society and the Turkish Language Society. He stimulated and
actively supported the historical and archaeological research in Anatolia
which has revealed to the world the existence of hitherto unknown civiliza¬
tions. Left, a portrait of Ataturk (1881-1938). Right, Ataturk visiting a
Turkish school at the time of the country's change over to the Latin script.
ATATURK (Cont'd)
Educate women to educate a nation
beginning of the twentieth century, opposed veiling and
the witholdlng of the right to go out freely, to ride in
the same carriage as their husbands and to sit next to
them, eventually triumphed over the fanaticism of
public opinion.
Until the end of the First World War, men and women
were separated from each other on public transport by
partitions. On boats sailing the Bosphorus and crossing
from Istanbul to the islands, women were obliged to stay
in closed cabins below decks. When women were finally
permitted to remain on deck, a woman author described
her feelings at being able to watch the sea in the open
air during that one-hour trip with such zest that anyone
would have imagined that she was crossing the ocean for
the first time.
There were many changes in the status of women
between 1918-23, largely brought about by the historical
events of the time.
In 1918, the Ottoman Empire signed the Treaty of
Mondros as one of the defeated powers, losing all rights
over her Asian territories (Arabia, Syria, Palestine, Leba¬
non, Iraq). In 1920, the last government of the Ottoman
Empire signed the Treaty of Sèvres, agreeing to the
dismemberment of Turkey, and every part of the country
now faced the possibility of occupation.
While the Sultan and his government accepted these
terms the nation itself did not and turned its mind to the
Idea of liberation. To preserve the unity of the country
it was necessary to bring together all the local forces.
With this in mind, Mustafa Kemal (Ataturk) assumed
the leadership of the nation and his first actions as leader
were to refuse to recognize the International treaties
entered into by the Sultan and his government and to
launch resistance against the occupying powers. In the
beginning this resistance took the form of guerilla fighting,
24 but on April 23, 1920, Kemal formed a government and
a regular army and attacked the forces of the occupying
powers.
In 1922 Anatolia was cleared of occuping troops and
with the Treaty of Lausanne in 1923 the boundaries of the
new Turkey were established. The same year, on October
29, a democracy was instituted with Ankara as the new
capital. Thus monarchy in Turkey came to an end.
In the democratic State which was created in 1923,
Turkish woman had at last attained the rights enjoyed
by women in other modern states.
The constitution of democratic Turkey made elementary
education for boys and girls compulsory, but because of
the shortage of teachers and school buildings its applica¬
tion remains largely theoretical. Turkey's high percentage
of illiteracy Is thus likely to remain so for some time.
All faculties of the Istanbul University started opening
their doors to girl students from 1921 and many teacher-
training schools, lycées, and other institutes were opened
for the benefit of girls. In addition, many of the existing
schools introduced co-education. In 1928, the adoption of
the Latin alphabet made learning much easier and as a
result there was an immediate increase in the number of
persons able to read and write.
O|nce women began to study in colleges and
,^.' universities many of them entered a variety
of professions and trades. But this was not always an
easy matter, as was seen in the case of the medical pro¬
fession. When young women wished to study law or
the arts no obstacles were placed in their way. But
when they showed interest in becoming doctors of medi¬
cine, public opinion was aroused and even educated
parents were reluctant to accept the idea. Articles were
published in the newspapers, claiming that women were
not likely to succed as doctors.
However, a small minority approved and supported
women in their struggle. Encouraged by this support,
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Educational Film Centre
seven girl students enrolled at the faculty of medicine of
Istanbul University in September 1922. Because, in terms
of dress, women were still bound by the old customs these
first women medical students wore their veils while
attending lectures with men and continued to do so until
1925, when Kemal Ataturk urged the adoption of European
dress.
The first women medical students completed their stu¬
dies in 1927 and, after a year's interneship, received their
diplomas as fully qualified doctors. These and other
women doctors who had studied in Europe or America
worked only as general practitioners. When some of them
wanted to become specialists, however, most of their male
colleagues declared that despite their attainments as
students, women would not be successful as practising
doctors. In time, the difficulties were overcome and
women who have specialized in different branches of
medicine have once again proved their capabilities.
Today, women are found in virtually every profession.
The engineer who supervised the building of the Ataturk
Memorial Mausoleum in Ankara, for instance, was a
woman, Sabiha Guneyman. The chief architect of the
Evkaf (religious trusts) in Istanbul is also a woman,
Cahide Tamar. The famous Rumell Fort In Istanbul was
restored by three women architects.
Teaching was the first profession open to women in
Turkey and the number of women who have taken up
teaching in primary and secondary schools, lycées and
universities is still much higher than in other professions.
So far, there is only a small number of women professors,
although there are a good many lecturers and assistant
lecturers. Those holding top positions in government
departments are still far from numerous.
On the stage, women have likewise distinguished them¬
selves, especially when it is remembered that until a
quarter of a century or so ago they were kept strictly
within the confines of their homes. It had always been
considered against the principles of Islam for women to
act. Aflfe Hanlm was nearly Imprisoned in 1921 for
contravening this principle. Women had to struggle for
their rights in this field just as in so many others.
The first woman Joined the Turkish bar In Ankara Jn
1928. Since then the number has Increased considerably
and today, in addition, there are many women Judges,
commissioners of oaths, legal advisers and lecturers at
the law schools.
Today, in Turkey, men and women are equal in the eyes
of the law. The many social reforms Introduced during
the presidency of Kemal Ataturk (1923-38) always took
account of women's position; many legal rights and duties
were freely conceded to them.
In 1926 the Turkish Government introduced a new set
of civil laws along the lines of the Swiss Civil Code. Tills
gave Turkish women all the rights customary In modern
communities.
The Turkish Civil Code, in terms of civil rights, did
away with all the legal differences between men and
women. It made women the equals of men, except that
women were subject to certain restrictions aimed at
securing permanency in marriage.
The prohibition of polygamy was one of the fundamental
features of this code, which also raised the marriageable
age for girls to 18, laid down certain pre-marrlage forma¬
lities, and required that marriage ceremonies should take
place before the municipal authorities in the presence of
witnesses, and also that a marriage should be recorded
both In the register and on the Identity cards of both
parties.
In April 1930, parliament passed the Municipal Laws Bill
giving women the right to vote and to stand in municipal
elections. The next step was to give women the right to
stand for parliament. President Ataturk was in favour
of this and often tried to induce members of the govern¬
ment to accept his views. In the constitution then In
force, mention of franchise was always accompanied by
the words "every Turkish male." On December 11, 1934
the words "and female" were added to this phrase.
Thus, Turkish women managed within a quarter of a
century to overcome a fanatical opposition and thereby
set an example to other women of the Moslem world.
ince they were given the right to vote both as
1 a result of the action of political parties and
their own desire to carry out their duties as citizens, a
high percentage of women have participated in elections.
For example, in 1954 out of 5,366,024 women voters (the
total number of voters was 10,287,733), 4,741,304 used their
right to vote.
In spite of all the legislation enacted for their benefit,
however, Turkish women In general have not yet achieved
the social and intellectual standing that could be desired.
In the country as in the town, they must be educated so
that they realize the meaning of all the rights conceded
to them by law.
On this subject, Professor Sadl Irmak wrote in 1962:
"There are four factors that undermine our efforts to
bring about equality for women: Ignorance, bad traditions,
wrong interpretation of religious rules, male selfish¬
ness ..." Professor Irmak analyses all these elements
and emphasizes the effect of illiteracy, declaring: "we
must educate women so that they, in turn, can educate
our nation." It ls essential that women of Turkey should
realize the meaning of their rights and duties before
exercising them.
The man responsible for the reforms in Turkey was
Kemal Ataturk, who believed in preparing both the
people around him and also public opinion before
introducing anything new. Ataturk wanted his people
to progress and to prosper according to the most 25
enlightened ideas and the principles of modern civilization.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
CULT
CULTURE EXPRESSES ITSELF IN CUSTOMS. It is seen in gestures,
manners, the expressions which appear on the lips; in the hands, in the
looks of the countryman, artisan or student ; it passes from one lip to another,
one hand to another, one eye to another... until it covers with a mesh of
behaviour every human group. In Japan, people remove their shoes before
entering a temple (below), just as they do when going inside their own homes. Oliver G. Wackernagel, Basle
A
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
URE AND FREEDOM
by German Arciniegas
; ;
Fifteen years ago the Colombian author, Gorman
Arciniegas, wrote a remarkable study on tho right
to culture which was later published in English in
the volume "Freedom and Culture"(1).Tho follow¬
ing article is abridged from this text which is as
timely and meaningful today as when it was writton.
Like many other cities in America, Lima has Its
own archaeological museum. Learned Peru¬
vians, French and German archaeologists, poor peasants
from the mountains all show nowadays a keen interest
In recreating the history of civilizations which existed in
the Western Hemisphere before the arrival of Christopher
Columbus.
The centre of interest has shifted. Discoveries now
made in America have aroused the same public curiosity
as did, in their day, the Assyrian excavations and the
finding of Tutankhamen's tomb. Diggings undertaken In
sandy stretches of the Peruvian desert have revealed
mummies between five and ten centuries old, wrapped in
cloaks of the most exquisite texture and colouring. The
dry particles composing these arid dunes have preserved
the cloth, which looks as glossy as if It had only Just left
the unknown hands and primitive loom of Its native
weaver.
But neither mummies nor cloth can compare with the
museum's eighty thousand pieces of pottery. Until the
Europeans arrived, the Indians made clay figures of ani¬
mals, birds, flowers and men. They achieved technical
perfection. The thin layer of terracotta, covered with
enamel, has withstood the action of time. The work ls
the living expression of an age-old spirit.
Clay represented for those earlier peoples poetry, the
theatre, and books. It was the natural vehicle for the
expression of their genius. In clay the artist depicted
with one bold stroke the proud heads of warriors, or the
loving, submissive brow of the Indian woman. In his
representation of old people, the irony and malice of the
ceramist have the same corrosive effect as has the hand
of time, when it wrinkles and shrivels up the skin. It is
unlikely that sculptors of our own day will be able to put
greater meaning Into their work.
These old artists of Peru had some magic quality In
their fingertips. They combined poetry with realism
superbly. In a design showing two doves or the head of
a llama they could convey the rhythm of a subtle grace¬
fulness with a delicacy which has never been surpassed
in the decorative arts. When representing scenes of daily
life, they showed man engaged in all his crudest activities
with a frankness ingenuousness of expression which no
present-day artists have ever ventured to use.
Four centuries ago, this culture came to a standstill.
Then began the colonial epoch, Introduced by the Spanish
sovereigns in the name of Christianity. Little by little, the
fruits of a new culture began to take shape. They have
not yet reached maturity. For Instance, it is Impossible
to find in Peruvian ceramic art of today works as perfect
as the old ones, or which reflect so faithfully the life of
a people.
Nevertheless, those forgotten nations which entrusted
their Innermost poetic dreams to the care of so fragile a
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
27
(1) All reproduction rights reserved
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
FREEDOM AND
CULTURECCo/7f'c/> THE SE
Around the pow¬
erful and pres¬
tigious court of
the kings of Abo-
mey in Dahomey,
West Africa, there
has long existed
a rich tradition of
arts and crafts
which still flou¬
rishes today. The
exploits, emblems
and animal mas¬
cots of the royal
family are em¬
bodied in works
by Abomey's ar¬
tists and crafts¬
men. Left, grace¬
ful giraffes fash¬
ioned in copper.
K. and R. Corpel. taken
from the album Terre
Dahoméenne ". Infor¬
mation Dept.. Republic
of Dahomey (1961)
III
ill III.
I i I I I I I
i i l n i I i
i i i I I I
il it'
.» .' .». ». I. '
III III
, V I n ', V .
. ». .« ,' '. «. } .
V." .'¿'.V.'
I.I Jill II
frf&v;
© Georges Patrix
The ups-and-downs of a word
material as clay continue to live. The humble, unknown
potter can never have imagined that the frail vessel on
which he stamped a woman's fugitive smile would remain
floating above the current of the centuries and be turned
into a message from his then isolated and remote native
land a message of wonder to our modern world which he
must have been quite unable to envisage.
This provides an excellent lesson. It shows us that
there Is something about culture which is immortal.
Today we can get to know a lost world, simply by looking
at pieces of pottery in a Lima museum, just as we can
make contact with other worlds in the gilded halls of the
Cairo museum, or among the ancient stones of Yucatan,
China or Rome. Learned men labour to determine the
number of dead civilizations. But are they really dead?
Is it not rather we who are deaf to the voices of the
remote past?
The word "culture" is one of those that has
suffered the most ups-and-downs in all languages, in a
2g universal masquerade of misunderstanding. Those respon¬
sible thought that by taking the word away from its
obvious and natural meaning (stemming directly from the
root word "cultivate") and trying to turn it into a grand
lady dressed in her Sunday best, they were going to create
the most important character in the "drama of enlight¬
enment."
We are now coming to the moment when it is necessary
to consider whether such a disguise must, be considered
definitive, or whether the time has not arrived for a
radical change which should place culture in the simple
context of human rights not in that of a privilege
pertaining to an intellectual class. For culture is a for¬
ward movement whose object is to cultivate the mind, to
form the personality. "Culture is something which has
to grow. You cannot build a tree; all you can do is to
plant it, arid look after it; and wait for it to mature in
its own due time." These are the words of T.S. Eliot true
words and words that should be elevated into a symbol.
In the history of languages, the first thing to appear
as culture is the cultivation of plants, the labour of the
soil, agriculture. Let us recall the line of Pope's:
We ought to blame the culture, not the soil.
It would seem as though, before appertaining to the
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
VENTH ANCESTOR
Weavers in Africa have a legend to explain
the origin of their craft. In a handsome
volume published in connexion with the
exhibition, "The Hand of Man", held this
year (June 23 to December 31 ) at the Ethno¬
logical Museum of IMeuchâtel, Switzerland,
Jean Gabus, director of the museum, says
that in the case of the Dogon people of
Mali, the basic technique of weaving is
linked with a mythical origin, forming part
of an African conception of the creation
of the universe. In the words of Ogotem-
meli, a Dogon hunter: "The seventh ances¬
tor was the creator of weaving. Between
his upper teeth, used like the reed of a
loom, he distributed 80 strands of cotton.
He did the same with his lower teeth, thus
forming the warp of the loom. By opening
and closing his jaws he moved the warp
through heddles separating the threads.
As the threads crossed and recrossed, the
ancestor's tongue pushed the thread of
the weft, and the strip of cloth was for¬
med outside his mouth. And from the
breath which he thus exhaled came the
second word: the words were woven into
the threads and became one with the strip.
They were the cloth itself and the cloth
was the Word: a blending of word and
method; of physical movements and spi¬
ritual forces." Right, this weaver of the
Bouaké, in the Republic of the Ivory Coast,
cannot draw the designs he weaves. But
when asked to depict a man he improvised
on his loom the figure shown on the left.
^te~ *
¿Ü
,VV
>*
S
history of literary development, culture were by natu¬
ral right a word belonging to natural history.
If, in referring to a "tree," Eliot were not speaking sym¬
bolically, he would be leaving something unfinished. For,
so far as culture is concerned, there is something more
than just a tree, subject to decay. What gives culture its
particular quality is its power to transmit a heritage, a
treasure, from generation to generation what is called a
tradition.
When we dehumanize culture and cut it off from its
branch in order to stick it in a flower-vase, we hasten the
day of its death. Culture is rooted In the depths of human
existence. It begins on the very day man discovers the
means of raising himself above the level of the beast
when he controls fire, invents the arrow and begins to
speak.
Between these first discoveries and those of the wheel,
the metal wing, the waves which carry the voice and even
the light and shade of photographs across the oceans. He
centuries of research, generations which have sweated
blood, rejoiced and suffered under the chancy pendulum
of life. All is part and parcel of this development of
human culture.
But when we say "culture" in the singular, we are using
an abstraction; as such it is unsatisfying, giving the term
a generic, amorphous sound. We must look at the
species in its plural aspect, for the "cultures" In the
plural evoke wonderful facts: Egypt and Mexico, Greece
and Japan, France and China, the Amazon, Polynesia.
In naming them thus, the vital slgnificace of the term
becomes apparent. Representatives of every nation take
on colour, voice and shape as they move across their own
magic screen. I would almost suggest that "culture" ls
not a noun but a verb, indicating the action carried out
by the peoples as they move forward under the urge to
rise, take shape and mould their characters.
The right to culture is therefore an individual one. It ls
the human right of every people to reveal its soul, to
express itself freely. And It is a permanent right. It
took many centuries for the Egyptians to acquire an
architecture of their own and a hieroglyphic style of
writing and to evolve methods of preserving their dead,
portraying their great national leaders In stone, and
bringing the Nile valley under control in order to turn
it into the nation's granary.
The archaeology of the great cathedrals of Europe ls
the best witness to the slow development of cultures. We
see In these cathedrals how the ages overlap one another.
We begin with the Romanesque crypts with their dog¬
tooth arches, and end with the Gothic spires, which had
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
CULTURE AND FREEDOM (Cont'd)
The humblest artifact tells a story
to wait centuries before the stone sprouted forth in floral
decorations, strange and fabulous creatures, and all that
the Middle Ages produced from their miracles and magic,
their patience and their dreams.
Finally, we may say that the right to culture Is, as it
were, the ultimate right of all peoples. It must be upheld
until they are able to loosen their tongues and untie the
knot in which their hidden longings are held bound. It is the
most important factor in the development of their internal
freedom. It has made possible the creation of languages,
symphonies, mural paintings, ornamental capitals, figures
in marble and bronze, and books.
Culture expresses Itself In customs. It is seen in ges¬
tures, manners, the expressions which appear on the Ups,
in the hands, in the looks of the countryman, artisan, or
student; It passes from one lip to another, one hand to
another, one eye to another, right up to refined circles,
until it covers with a mesh of behaviour every human
group, which thus reaches Its own style of expression.
It would be interesting to follow, in painting for
example, the history of the different attitudes of the
hand; from the hand which grasps, clutches and closes
over convulsively, to the two hands that unite in prayer,
or are covered with rings, or seem about to bestow a caress.
We may recall the oriental hands of Fujlta; those of the
Dutch peasants painted by Van Gogh In his Supper of
Potatoes; those of El Greco's noblemen in the Burial of
the Count of Orgaz; those of the Gioconda, and those
of the women in Botticelli's Spring. Every expressive
gesture disseminates itself by sympathetic contagion.
Thus are the customs of each society formed.
t every new stage, with minute variations,
^ attitudes take on greater refinement, polish
and meaning and words more colour; while new concep¬
tions, issuing in felicitous gesture, can be attained even
among the lowest ranks of society. Whoever has lived
among countryfolk knows how, under their rough exterior,
there is a native civility some would say even courtesy.
This is expressed in such ways as, for instance, hastening
at a meal to pass the first and best helping to the woman
guest, wife or mother. May not this part of our culture
have had its origin among such as these, and subsequently
have passed into urban usage?
The same thing happens in the case of words. It is a
pity that in the rush of modern Ufe there is not time to
"prepare" Words, to await the moment when they
suddenly become so charged with meaning that they seem
to have some miraculous effect on the development of the
language.
Formerly, in all languages each of the smallest parts of
a house, a ship, or a coat-of-arms was given a name which
was a poetic Image. In our mechanical age, words to do
with the motor-car and the aeroplane sprout up In the
catalogues with the same speed at which steel sheets are
pressed into shape in the moulds. There still remains,
however, a wide margin in the matter of adjectives and
of names that spring up in popular intercourse. If the
greatest writers in all ages, those who have later become
the pride and ornament of literary cultures, made them¬
selves masters In one thing, it was in this: picking up,
as they went along, gems of popular speech.
From hands and words we may pass to countless
different aspects of life. There is no piece of crockery
we use daily, no household utensil, that does not contain a
history of novel shapes developed, transformations brought
about by taste which has been free to function creatively.
30 In their handwriting and in the peculiarities of their
capital letters the characters of the different peoples
show up plainly. In clothes, in hats, in cosmetics, in
polite social intercourse and in cooking in everything we
see the cultivating hand of man, leaving an impression of
his passage, proclaiming his active, personal presence.
Are there superior cultures; or are there only different
cultures? Upon the answer which we give to this double
question depends the whole problem of respect for
culture, for the individual spirit of different peoples, for
the freedom of expression which is of the essence of such
matters. If so much Uterature had not accumulated on
the subject of superior culture, It would be puerile to
present the question in its double form. It can only be
answered by referring back to the obvious and natural
meaning of the word "culture." For then we eUminate
the deformations imposed by nationalist imperialism, the
vanity of certain peoples, or the momentary triumph of
certain political tendencies, and arrive at the original and
permanent conception that culture consists in the cultiva¬
tion of Man; which acts as a refining influence on the
personality of every people, shaping its individual style
in the course of generations.
Every people is bound to have its own parti¬
cular mode of expressing itself, a variety of
images, rhythms and gestures, in which Eastern art can
be as rich as Western. The painting of the Japanese
Sesshu is of one style; that of Rembrandt is of another
style. The glory of the world consists in there being
both a Sesshu and a Rembrandt.
Culture has what we might call provincial depth. It
is essential to observe that culture is a measurement of
depth, not of surface. And It is in the provinces where
the spirit of a people is concentrated and where greater
emphasis is given to the personaUty. It is this provincial
consciousness that gives Europe its highest value. To be
able to talk of a Flemish, Provençal, Scottish or Basque
tonality to be found in language, painting, dancing or
dress ls to express vital facts about the culture of a
continent.
This intercourse between Nature and the arts and
customs which Goethe saw realized in Italian culture,
occurring as it does in every part, in every single province
of the world, produces the wealth of expression character¬
istic of mankind. Freedom of expression, freedom of
study and research, freedom to penetrate into the life of
the people and to present the fruits arising out of one's
meditations, these open to man the only road by which
his passage through this world can be made other than
sterile. _
The superiority implied by democracy over aristocratic,
oligarchic or absolutist systems lies in offering people of
every colour, social origin or race, opportunities of access
to Institutions working for the advancement of culture
through the medium of the sciences, the arts and letters.
These opportunities are nowadays a human right on which
all intellectual progress depends. It is the human enter¬
prise par excellence. Humanising culture simply means
returning to authentic culture.
he fundamental thing about culture is its
_ intimate association with historical develop¬
ment. There is no superior culture; there are only inci¬
pient, adolescent or mature cultures. It is all a question
of time.
Nowadays there are means that can be used to accelerate
the development of culture; but there is a Umit to such
acceleration: it has to conform to natural laws.
CONT'D ON PAGE 32
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Vi.»
--*. í
7/y
: :
M
/
" Gisèle Freund
It was not until 1952 that archaeological research in Mexico revealed that pyramids built
by the ancient Mayas not only served as substructures for their temples, but also as tombs.
Among the objects found in the tomb of a monarch-priest beneath the Temple of Inscriptions
at Petanque was this warrior's head modelled with a headdress of plumes and flowers.
The artist has given the nose a form corresponding to the Maya concept of the ideal human
profileclosely resembling that of the Quetzal bird which the Mayas and Aztecs revered.
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
CULTURE AND FREEDOM (Cont'd)
Man has not spoken his final word
The same thing does not happen in the case of civiliza¬
tion, for which reason a distinction must be drawn between
the two words, although not necessarily in the Spenglerlan
sense. "Civilization" is an expression of the citizen, of
civil life, which springs up in the city. When there Is a
civil authority, a civil law, a civil code, life has become
civilized. It makes no difference that the people should
still remain uncultured. It might happen, as has been
affirmed, looking at the problem from a European stand¬
point, that civilization represented the final stage of a
culture. But this Is not essential.
But what ls happening today? Civilization can be
fabricated. There is no need to plant It like a tree.
Everyone is agreed that the progress of civilization has
been rapid, and not always favourable to culture. CiviUza-
tion Itself has been shown to have a marked propensity
to suicide. It can devour Itself for lack of culture.
It is obvious that in order for culture to prosper civiliza¬
tion is necessary; that is to say a system of civil life in
which the dignity of man is respected and the free
working of the means for study and self-expression
assured; where there is civil justice and work is not
carried on under barbarous laws, so that the intelligence
is able to retain its spontaneity and freshness which are
the mainspring of its activity. The problems of man and
of the spirit, which today confront one another in Asia,
Europe and America, are thus situated between the two
terms "culture" and "civilization."
In the present development of civilization a new factor
Intervenes: communications. All inventions are diffused
nowadays with a rapidity undreamt of before. Continents
are brought together and, in this sense, the
world appears to be uniting. It represents far more one
civilization than many civilizations, in contrast with the
position in the field of culture, where diversity is the rule.
The attainment of a civil existence enabling man to
cultivate his "spirit" that is what the common sense of
the ordinary human being demands at the present time.
solemn declaration of man's ancient faith
Un his liberties has now become a matter of
the greatest urgency. Our struggle and the great ques¬
tion of our time are comprised in those precedents whose
study Unesco has agreed upon. In the preamble to the
Constitution of this new international organization it
is already stated: "Peace must be founded upon the intel¬
lectual and moral solidarity of mankind."
From the depths of the collective soul rises a demand
for justice, for balance. For hope also is one of the
rights of man an alleviation of his toil and fatigue.
"The Universal Declaration of Human Rights," says the
[former] Director-General of Unesco, M. Torres Bodet,
"ls the most promising international document to which
governments have set their names since 1945 ... It is the
first international manifesto enumerating the rights of the
Individual and setting forth the conditions to be fulfilled
by those States that desire to respect the liberty and
dignity of the human person. It is the extension of
honour in man. It is an urgent call to governments to
remind them that man exists . . ."
Yes, indeed: man exists. His is the lasting value.
Dictators are here today and tomorrow are gone with the
wind. Man is the result of generations of struggle, ideals,
work accomplished, hopes which form the basis of his
rights to life, liberty and a place in the sun. Every step
forward in the conquest of civilization, every advance in
culture, have been marked by. nameless sacrifices, by
vigils in which ardour overcame all misfortunes.
32 Centuries of history have given man his strength. He
has been a slave in innumerable dark periods in his life
that are well known. But every time he has hoped for
the dawn. And the dawn always comes in the end. Man
does not so much live as outlive himself. He Is the work
we Inherit, the work we continue, and the work we leave
behind unfinished when our hands fall, to be carried on
by the nimble hands of our youthful descendants.
For man the hour for the complete realization of know¬
ledge, justice and liberty has not yet arrived. Open before
us lie ever new vistas to feed our dreams, new incitements
to struggle, new reasons for not allowing life to become
a profitless existence. Every bit of knowledge we possess is
still a subject for free discussion. The explanation of man
and the argument in favour of liberty are based on the
evident fact that man has not spoken his final word.
German Arciniegas is one of Latin America's leading historians
and thinkers. Through his many books in English translation, he
has introduced Latin American history and present-day social
conditions to the English-speaking world. Among his works in
English are: The State of Latin America, Caribbean: Sea of the
New World and Green Continent, an anthology of works by leading
Latin American writers which he edited. Freedom and Culture
was compiled by Unesco with an introduction by Julian Huxley and
published by Columbia University Press, New York and Wingate,
London (out of print.)
SOME UNESCO PUBLICATIONS
UN HUMAN RIGHTS
Buddhism and the Race Question, by G.P. Malalasekera and
K.N. Jayatilleke, 1958 ($0.50; 2/6)
The Catholic Church and the Race Question, by Yves M.-J.
Congar, 2nd impr. 1961 ($0.50; 2/6)
The Changing Social Position of Women in Japan, by Takashi
Koyama, 1961 ($2.00; 10/-)
The Emancipation of the Turkish Woman, by A. Afetinan, 1962
($1.00; 5/-)
For All Children (photo display set), 1960 ($1.00; 5/-)
The Jewish People: A Biological History, by Harry L. Shapiro,
1960 ($0.70; 3/6)
Jewish Thought as a Factor in Civilization, by Leon Roth, 2nd
impr. 1961 ($0.50; 2/6)
Race and Class in Rural Brazil, by C. Wagley, 2nd impr. 1963
($2.00; 10/-)
The Race Concept. Results of an Inquiry, 2nd impr. 1958
($0.85; 4/-)
Race and Biology, by L.C. Dunn, 6th impr. 1961 ($0.30; 1/6)
Race and Culture, by Michel Leiris, 5th impr. 1961 ($0.30; 1/6)
Race and History, by Claude Lévi-Strauss, 3rd impr. 1958
1960 ($0.70; 3/6)
Race and Psychology, by Otto Klineberg, 2nd impr. 1958
($0.30; 1/6)
Race and Society, by Kenneth L. Little, 4th impr. 1961 ($0.30;
1/6)
Race Mixture, by Harry L. Shapiro, 2nd impr. 1960 ($0.50; 2/6)
Racial Myths, by Juan Comas, 4th impr. 1958 ($0.30; 1/6) .
The Roots of Prejudice, by Arnold M. Rose, 6th impr. 1960
($0.30; 1/6)
The Significance of Racial Differences, by G.M. Morant, 3rd
impr. 1958 ($0.30; 1/6)
The Race Question in Modern Science. A collective volume
of the 9 booklets listed immediately above, 2nd impr. 1959
(Bound $5.00; 20/-)
Race Relations and Mental Health, by Marie Jahoda, 1960
($0.50; 2/6)
The Universal Declaration of Human Rights: A Guide for
Teachers. 1951 ($0.50; 3/-)
Women in the New Asia, by Barbara Ward, 1963 ($8.00; 40/-.
Bound $11.00; 55/-)
*
**
Race Prejudice and Education, by Cyril Bibby (7/6 stg.)
Published under the auspices of Unesco by Heinemann, London
1959
Order this title from your local bookseller or direct from
the publishers, but NOT from Unesco.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
WITH LOVE FROM CELESTE
Dear Sir,
I am 7 years old. I am in grade 2.
I do not want the monument of Ram¬
ses II at Abu Simbel to be drowned,
because I want to see them. I am
sending $3.00 I saved.
Love,
Celeste-Marie Sullivan
Worcester, Mass., U.S.A.
UNESCO COURIER ON TAPE
Sir,
Answering your question why we
did not renew our subscription the
reason is a purely personal one and
has nothing to do wtih a lack of
appreciation of your highly interesting
and informative magazine.
I ordered it for my" mother,
Mrs. Else Danelius, after her immigra¬
tion from the U.S.A. last year, for a
trial period. My mother belongs to
that rather substantial group of old
people who have to pay for an other¬
wise blessed old age with failing eye¬
sight. In the U.S.A., she was granted
a talking book machine by the U.S.
Government and was thus able to
enjoy books and journals read to her
on disks. In this country, we have a
Central Library for the blind whose
stock in non-Hebrew books on tapes is
rather limited and which is dependent
on the goodwill of European countries
for its reading material. As my
mother's eyesight permits her to enjoy
pictures, I took out a Unesco Courier
subscription for her.
My mother enjoys your magazine
very much but, unfortunately, there is
nobody who has enough time to read
to her the rather substantial and very
informative articles for which the
pictures are only an illustration. If it
were possible to have these articles
read on tapes in a similar way as
some magazines are read on disks in
the U.S.A. and distributed to blind
people, you might open the contents
of your magazine to an entirely new
group of readers : those whose eyesight
is too weak to permit them to read
by themselves. I am sure that these
handicapped people would enjoy the
paper as much as their seeing contem¬
poraries and appreciate your work even
more than we do.
I have no idea whether your means
permit you to embark on such a
project, at least in one or two of the
most popular languages. I feel quite
sure that the Braille institutes all over
the world would be only too glad to
help you. Some of the people working
there are blind themselves and I have
come to admire their activity on behalf
of their equally handicapped brethren.
Dr. Eva Danelius
Herzliya/Nof Yam. Israel
Editors's Note. Our corres¬
pondent's suggestion is most interest¬
ing. Unfortunately, our magazine lacks
the means to launch such a project.
TEMPTER TRANSFORMED
Sir,
In your April issue a photo
published under the heading. "A Smile
from Europe" depicts a 13th-century
statue on Basle Cathedral. From the
caption we learn that it represents a
girl. The statue is part of a religious
composition quite common in the
Middle Ages, taken from a Biblical
story about the Tempter and the
Foolish Virgin. The statue in the
photo is that of the Tempter. In the
Pushkin Museum of Fine Arts there
is a plaster cast of the statue in the
mediaeval gallery.
Vera Ycrmonskaya
Moscow, U.S.S.U.
Sir,
The statue on Basle Cathedral is
not that of a young woman. It depicts
a Tempter who stands opposite the
figure of a woman symbolizing Sin.
This couple in stone are placed (photo
below) to the right of the main door
of the Cathedral.
Brigitte Senn
Basle, Switzerland
EAST-WEST TRANSLATIONS
Sir,
I read with special interest in your
February issue the article by Robert
Collison : "The Continuing Barrier :
Translations and East-West Communi¬
cations." The accompanying tables
listing translations from Asian to
Western languages in 1960 showed the
following results for Belgium : 2 books
from Chinese, 1 from Ethiopian, 1
from Hindi, 2 from Japanese, 1 from
Syriac. I should like you to know that
in one series of publications alone
the Corpus Scriptorum Christiano-
rum Orientalium my firm printed in
the original language the following
volumes : 1 Arabic, 2 Coptic, 2 Syriac,
2 Georgian and 1 Ethiopian, as well
as the corresponding translations of
these eight volumes.
K. I'cctcrs
Louvaln, Belgium
THE SOUND AND THE FURY
Sir,
Unesco estimates (May issue) that
400 million more radios would be
needed to provide a receiver for each
family in Africa, Asia and Latin Ame¬
rica. I just cannot regard a radio
receiver as an instrument for cultural
betterment. I live in a middle-class
district of Paris. My neighbours, who
one would expect to be relatively cul¬
tured people, force me to listen to
their favourite radio programmes. Hut
what I hear from open windows on
every floor is of the very poorest
quality : hackneyed tunes, stupid jokes,
ear-splitting jazz. It is clear to me
that instead of trying to improve public
tastes and standards, the radio merely
aims to satisfy the demands of the
run-of-the-mill listener.
The people for whom it is proposed
to provide the millions of transistor
sets are in many cases those who have
created, and continue to create, folk
music which is far finer and more
inspired than the "international" airs
they will hear through their radios.
Just like tobacco and alcohol, the
radio has already poisoned too many
people. And as a first-class instrument
for filling people's heads with propa¬
ganda it has already been widely used
in the "war on the wavelengths."
M. MuIIcr
Paris, France
HOUSEWIFE LINGUISTS
Sir,
A letter in your May 1963 number
asks: "How can such people as a
farm worker in the Massif Central (or
Lower Saxony), a postman in the
Pyrenees (or Croatia), a housewife in
Brittany (or in Sicily or Norway)
learn languages like English, Russian,
Chinese, Arabic even supposing they
wanted to?"
The great majority of Norwegian
children get lessons in English in the
elementary school and more than
90% of them get further schooling
with education in English and other
languages.
We would also like to point out
that the housewives of Norway form
a substantial number of the scholars
in the special adult courses throughout
the country. These courses especially
teach foreign languages.
Mrs. A. J. Loe Whist
General Secretary, The Norwegian
Housewives' Association
Oslo, Norway
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
TRAINING AFRICA'S LIBRARIANS:
The first regional centre for training
librarians from French-speaking African
countries began operations recently at the
University of Dakar, Senegal. Established
co-operatively by the Government of Sene¬
gal and Unesco, it will train students from
18 African countries in modern techniques
of librarianship.
34
TWO BOOKS ON UNICEF: "Toward a
Better World for Children", describes
the work done by the United Nations
Children's Fund (Unicef) around the
globe. Excerpted from "Towards Man¬
kind's Better Health" (Vol. 3 of a Study
Guide Series on the U.N. Family) this
booklet can be obtained from the United
Nations, or Oceana Publications, Inc.,
Dobbs Ferry, New York, price 50 cents,
with special discounts for 500 copies
or more. "Children of the Developing
Countries", is a special report in which
Unicef describes what it is doing to
help many of the 500 million children in
the developing countries. Published by the
World Publishing Company, 2231 West
110th Street, Cleveland 2., Ohio, it is
priced at $1.45.
PROTECTING THE WHALES: The
International Whaling Commission
recently decided that humpback whales are
to be completely protected in waters south
of the equator and blue whales protected
in most of the Antarctic south of 40 degrees
S. In view of decreasing catches of whales
generally, the international quota for whal¬
ing has been reduced by one-third. In
future international observers will travel
on all factory ships.
TV SCHOOL FOR GHANA: Ghana,
which is planning to introduce nation¬
wide TV by 1965, has opened up a TV
school to train the staff for three projected
transmitting stations and a production and
administration centre. In Southern Rho¬
desia, TV studios at the Ministry of Edu¬
cation in Salisbury have inaugurated their
first series of educational programmes.
About 140 schools have so far been equip¬
ped with TV receivers.
«W HOTS WHO IN GRAPHIC ART':
This work, the first illustrated bio¬
graphical work of reference on the world's
leading graphic designers, typographers,
illustrators and cartoonists, is published by
Amstutz and Herdeg Graphis Press, Zurich.
With texts in English, French and German,
it presents the work of 414 artists from
37 countries with 4283 examples of their
best work. A full page is allotted to each
artist and the biographies are arranged by
countries, each country being introduced by
an essay on its graphic art. "Who's Who
in Graphic Art" is not only a rich source
of information for specialists but also an
entertaining and useful work for the general
reader. It costs £ 9.9.0. or $ 36.00, and its
distributor for the United Kingdom is
A. and C. Black Ltd., London.
m» ODERN ART MEETING : For three
! days last September the 12th Inter¬
national Congress of Artists, Art Critics
and Scholars met in Rimini and Verucchio
(Italy) and San Marino to discuss inter¬
national problems of contemporary art. The
September 1963 issue of The Unesco Cou¬
rier on movement and light in art was
one of the subjects under discussion.
rNESCO YOUTH CONFERENCE :
Unesco's Executive Board has invited
41 international youth organizations to take
,part in Unesco's first International Youth
Conference which will be held in Grenoble,
France, next August. The Conference will
discuss out-of-school education for youth
and Unesco's future programme for young
people.
WJ|7 BLDLIFE MISSION TO ETHIOPIA :
"" A Unesco scientific mission headed
by Sir Julian Huxley, British biologist and
a former Director-General of Unesco,
recently completed a survey of wildlife
conservation problems in Ethiopia, at the
request of the Ethiopian government. The
mission covered most of the country either
by car or by air in order to seek sites
that could be turned into national parks or
preserves where animal and plant life would
be adequately protected.
KUWAIT HELPS UNRWA: Kuwait
recently became the highest per
capita contributor to the United Nations
Relief and Works Agency (UNRWA) when
it gave $220,000 to the agency to cele¬
brate its admission to the United Nations.
The donation is equivalent to $.68 per
inhabitant. $100,000 of this sum will pro¬
vide training scholarships for 200 young
refugees at UNRWA teacher training cen¬
tres in lordan and Syria.
]\TEW ARABIC PERIODICAL: A new
-^ review entitled "Al-Lissan Al Arabi"
(The Arabic Language) is to appear early
next year. It will be published by the
Coordinating Committee of Arab National
Commissions at Rabat (Morocco). It will
be chiefly devoted to questions on the Arab
language, its terminology and problems of
translation.
SHOCKS FOR BETTER CROPS : Soviet
biologists have discovered that process¬
ing crop seeds with high-voltage alternating
current greatly improves their quality.
Maize seed processed for 30 seconds pro¬
duced 27% more ears than on the control
plot. Exposure to an electric field for 10
to 20 seconds increases the rate of growth
of wheat, rice and other crops by between
15 and 30 per cent and germination by 8
to 15 per cent.
T NDIAN-UNESCO TV PROJECT :
* Unesco has now published a re¬
port (1) on a joint pilot project which it
undertook with All India Radio (AIR). The
project set out "to assess the value of
different kinds of TV programmes suitable
for group viewing in rural and urban
communities which may be useful not only
for India but for other Asian countries
too." A similar experiment was conducted
under Unesco's auspices in Japan in 1957.
News Flashes,
Antarctica is the world's biggest land
mass after Eurasia, according to Soviet
cartographers. The main ice-cap and
adjacent islands cover 5,409,000 square
miles.
The U.S.A. has more radio receivers
than any other country : 948 for every
1,000 habitants. It is followed by Canada
(452), Sweden (367) and Denmark (332).
! Denmark has become the 18//? country
to adhere to the Unesco Convention against
discrimination in education, and Peru the
41th country to join the Unesco-sponsored
Universal Copyright Convention under
which states grant foreign -works the same
protection accorded to works by thair own
nationals.
H Thirty-one African nations, whose repre¬
sentatives attended a Unesco Conference
on Higher Education in Africa at Tanana¬
rive, aim to raise the number of students
receiving higher education ninefold (from
31,000 to 274,000), by 1980.
(1) Social Education through Television, No. 38
in the series "Reports and Papers on Mass
Communications." Price : $0.50; 2/6 stg); 1.75 F.
STAMPS FROM 40 NATIONS
MARK HUMAN RIGHTS
UNITED NATIONS 58
*|	'	 *
NATIONS UNIES
Forty member states of Unesco
have announced plans to issue spe¬
cial commemorative stamps to mark
the 15th anniversary of the Universal
Declaration of Human Rights on
December 10. The United Nations
will also issue a set of stamps on
this occasion. Above, the 5c stamp
of this set. The Unesco Philatelic
Service is publishing first day covers
for the event. As agent in France
of the U. N. Postal Administration,
Unesco^ Philatelic Service stocks
all U. N. stamps and first day covers
currently on sale, and those issued
by Unesco member states to com¬
memorate important events in the
history of Unesco and the U. N.
For prices and further details write
to The Unesco Philatelic Service,
Place de Fontenoy, Paris (7e).
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
TABLE OF CONTENTS THE UNESCO COURIER 1963
January
AFRICAN EXODUS. A dramatic problem of 1 50.000 refugees
A museum of the Alphabet The library of the future A sputnik's-
eye view of the earth Unesco art pocket books Unesco in retro¬
spect and perspective The vast machinery of film distribution.
February
THE 'MODERN' ART OF THE HITTITES. A lost civilization
emerges from the past Uncharted lands Translations and East-
West communications Unesco's annual translations guide
Ishi, the last of the Yanas Gastronomy for the bold Cinema : an
audience of 12,000,000,000.
March
JEAN-JACQUES ROUSSEAU. The apostle of affliction
Rousseau, the father of anthropology The solitary wanderer
Rousseau's message for our world today From persecution to
apotheosis Oriental echoes of the "Social Contract" The indivi¬
sibility of world prosperity Unesco 1963-64: A world programme
for education, science and culture.
April
ORIENT-OCCIDENT: A STUDY IN IGNORANCE. Progress
and prejudice Dialogue on the film, "The Island" A Portuguese
Sancho Panza in the Far East Does life end at sixty? Holiday
cure for bored teen-agers Cinema: Censorship, a double-edged
weapon.
May
SAFETY FIRST AT SEA. A world-wide network for maritime safety
A look at world co-operation in science Stained glass: 400
years in one family Cinema : The Useless Barriers Brazil's
programme to grow more food Stamps against hunger.
June
HISTORY OF MANKIND. A global view of scientific and cultural
development The awakening of the mind The dawn of art A
schoolboy in Sumer First astronomers of China and Babylon
The commonwealth of medicine The birth of glass The Red
Cross The mental strains of Antarctic solitude
Comedy" in Esperanto.
Dante's "Divino
July-August
SCIENCE FOR PROGRESS. World of opportunity Freedom
with knowledge The promise of nuclear power S.T.P.: Index
of prosperity Unesco expands its science programme 330
million brains for a new era Shopping in tho supermarket of
science Face-lift for the science curriculum A university town
built by a country doctor Assiut, Egypt's most modern university
African metamorphosis Urban explosion in developing nations
Homo Sapiens, that strange paradox Into tho world of tho futuro
Scientists abroad.
September
MOVEMENT & LIGHT IN TODAY'S ART . New dimensions
in painting and sculpture Malina : artist-scientist of tho spaco ago
Blindfolded traveller in New Delhi Tracking tho hurricane When
flight was silent.
October
PROBING THE INTERIOR OF THE EARTH. Aro tho continonts
drifting? The Upper Mantle Project Project Moholo Tho
hidden world of volcanoes 300,000 earthquakes a year Wanted :
More quake-proof buildings.
November
THE MAN WHO REVOLUTIONIZED THE THEATRE. Cons¬
tantin Stanislavsky, the actor and producer who gave a now form to
dramatic art My Life in Art Leaves from Stanislavsky's note¬
books Unesco in the Congo One language for tho world?
Allô-Hallo: communications in a nutshell Unicef greeting cards
The unsolved mystery of Marajo.
December
HUMAN RIGHTS FOR ALL. Unesco and Human Rights
Outlawing of India's caste system Eleanor Roosevelt : a lifetime
of dedication to Human Rights Text of U. N. Declaration
Turkish Art Album Ataturk and Women's Emancipation Tho
Right to Culture.
Where to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Press Department, Royal
Afghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Tradco Agencies, 1 09 Swanston Street, G. P. O.
Box 2324 V, Melbourne C. I. (Victoria) ; United
Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
8th Floor, McEwan House, 343 Little Collins St.,
Melbourne C. I. (Victoria). (A. 15/-). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C"., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Sch. 60.-). BELGIUM. Editions " Labor ",
342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-Boek-
handel, Belgielei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (100 FB) and art slides only: Louis de Lannoy,
22, place de Brouckère, Brussels. CCP 3380.00.
BURMA. Burma Translation Society, 3 61 Prome Road,
Rangoon. (K. 5.50). CANADA. Queen's Primer,
Ottawa, Ont. ($ 3.00). CEYLON. Lake House
Bookshop, 100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Colombo,
2. (Rs. 9). CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd.. 99
Chungking South Rd., Section 1, Taipeh, Taiwan (For¬
mosa). CUBA.Cubartimpex, Apartado 6540, La Ha¬
vana. (2.25 pesos). CYPRUS. Cyprus National
Youth Council. P. O. Box 539, Nicosia, CZE¬
CHOSLOVAKIA. ArtiaLtd., 30 Ve Smeckich. Prague
2. DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard, A/S Tidsskriftafde-
lingen, Prags Boulevard 47 Copenhagen S (D.kr. 12).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agency. P.O.Box 120.
Addis Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kiriakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu. Helsinki. (Fmk. 540). FRANCE. Librai¬
rie de l'Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7'. C.C.P. 12598-
48. (7 F.). GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg Verlag, Rosen-
heimer Strasse 145, Munich. For the Unesco Kurier
(German ed. only) Bahren-felder-Chaussee 160,
Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, C.C.P. 276650 (DM 8). GHANA
Methodist Book Depot Ltd. Atlantis House, Commercial
St., POB 1Ô0, Cape Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See
United Kingdom. GREECE. Librairie H. Kaufímann,
28, rue du Stade, Athens. HONG-KONG. Swindon
Book Co., 64, Nathan Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY.
Kultura, P.O. Box 149. Budapest, 62.
Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co. H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik
INDIA. Orienc Longmans Ltd. Nicof Road, Bombay 1 ;
17 Chictaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; Gunfoundry'Road,
Hyderabad, 1 ; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2; Kanson House,
1 /24Asaf Ah Road, P.O.Box 386, New Delhi, 1 ¡Sub-Depot:
Oxford Book & Stationery Co., 17 Park Street, Calcutta
1 6, Scindia House, New Delhi. Indian National Commission
Co-operation with Unesco, Ministry of Education, for
New Delhi 3. (Rs. 7). INDONESIA. P. N. Fadjar Bhakti
Djalan, Nusantara 22, Djakarta. IRAQ. Mackenzie's
Bookshop, Baghdad. IRELAND. The National Press,
2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores 35, Allenby Road
and 48, Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv (1£5.50).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour
Street, Kingston. Knox Educacional Services, Spaldings.
(10/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-Nichome,
Nihonbashi, P.C. Box 605 Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
(Yen 670). JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman.
KENYA. E.S.A. Bookshop, P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole
and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LUXEMBURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue,
Luxemburg. MALAYSIA Federal Publications Ltd.,
Times House, River Valley Rd., Singapore (M. $ 500)
MALTA. Sapienza's Library 26 Kingsway, Valetta. (1 0/-).
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon
Street, Port-Louis. British Library, 30 Bid
des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (7 NF.). NETHERLANDS.
N. V. Martinus Ni|hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague,
(fl. 6). NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES. G. C. T.
Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.) N.V., Willemscad, Curacao.
NEW ZEALAND Government Printing Office 20,
Molesworth Street (Privace Bag) Welhngcon, Government
Bookshops,: Auckland (P.O. Box 5344), Christchurch,
(P. O. Box 1721), Dunedin) P.O. Box 1104 (10/-).
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box 174, Lagos,
(10/-). NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Lilla Grenie.
7 Oslo For tho Unesco Courier only: A.S. Nirvcicns
Litteratur Tjeneste. Storcingigc. 2 Oslo, Pottboks 115
(kr 13.20) PAKISTAN. The Weic-Pik Publishing Co.
Ltd., Unesco Pubhcacions Houie, P.O. Box 374 56-N
Culberg Induscrial Colony, Lahore. PANAMA.
Cultural Panameña, Avenida 7a, No. TI-49, Apartado de
Correos 2018. Panama, (D. F. Balboas 3-). PHILLIPI¬
NES. The Modern Book C o., 508 Rizal Avenue P.O. Box
632 Manila. POLAND. " RUCH " ul. Wiloza Nr. 46x
Warsaw 10 (ZI. 50). Dias & Andrada
Lda, Livrana Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon.
PUERTO RICO. Spanish English Publications. Eleanor
Roosevelt 1 1 5, Apartado 1912, Hato Rey. RHODESIA
& NYASALAND. The Book Cencre, Gordon Avenue, Sa¬
lisbury, Souchern Rhodesia. SUDAN, AI Bashir Book-
shop, P. O, Box 111 8. Khartoum. SWEDEN. A/B CE.
Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel Fredigatan 2. Stockholm 1 6.
For The Unesco Courier: Svenska Unescorldec, Vasaga-
tan 15-17, Stockholm, C (Kr. 7.50) ; SWITZERLAND.
Europa Verlag, 5 Ramiicrasse Zurich. Payoc, 40. ru« du
Marché, Geneva C.C.P. 1-236. "Courier" only: Georges
Losmaz, 1, rue des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. C.C.P.
1-4811. (Fr. S. 8).TANGANYIKA. Dar-es-Salaam Bo¬
okshop, P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND.
Suksapan Panic, Mansion 9. Raidamnern Avenue. Bangkok.
(35 ticals). Librairie Hachette. 469 litiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda
Bookshop, P.O. Box 14b, Kampala. UNION OF
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik'i Bookstore, Libri
Building, Church Streec. Precona. For the Unesco Cou¬
rier (single copies) only: Cencral News Agency, P.O.
Box 1033, Johannesburg. (10/-). UNITED ARAB
REPUBLIC (EGYPT). La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh.
Adly-Pasha, Cairo. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M.
Stationery Office, P.O. Box 5 69, London, S.E.I. (10/-).
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications Cencer,
317 East 34ch St, New York, 16. N.Y. ($5.00.)
and (excepc periodicals): Columbia University Press,
2960 Broadway. New York, 27 .N.Y. U.S.S.R. Mez-
hdunarodnaja Kniga. Moscow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA
Yugoslovenska Knilga, Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
If «OUf
m
\*£[ £>^f LE JEÜNEARÍ-
n ideal
New Year's
gift
. « ">* q '«', 4 »Ml
a subscription
to
The Unesco Courier
>*»>r»
?) ti
(»iLvnhe urll>
ll< ¡¡li lililí
I V
AN ENTIRE YEAR'S READING
for only 10/- (stg.)
$3.00 (Canada)
7 Fr. Frs
Write to the agent in your
country listed overleaf
A,^t-H wir. <>,
~¿je/--* i
Í.,:U:
íí \JIC|L \ l 1 -
IEL.ARTE
WO Of
LOS HHEOS eight languages k
]]>
</page>
</document>
