<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="063659eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
wà
2 (15TH YEAR) - PRICE 1/-STG. (U.K.) - 30 CENTS (U.S.) -0.70 NF (FRAN
w
a
;t*
K J»
M
J-^H
Karl von Frisch:
NATURE'S HIDDEN LANGUAGES OF SMELL
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
te the
walls of the Angkor Vat temple in northern Cambodia. The first city
of Angkor and its great temple were built by a Khmer king, Suryavar-
man II (1112-52). A successor, Jayavarman VII, In 1181 founded a new capital, Angkor Thorn, close by and adorned the great
temple of the former capital (previously dedicated to the Hindu god Vishnu) with Buddhist decorations. He gave the great
temple-fortress the title it still bears Angkor Vat (the palace monastery). Archaeologists and engineers of several countries
are working to restore and save Angkor's monuments, now threatened by diseases in the stones and ravages of time and weather.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier
Contents
No. 10
OCTOBER 1962
15TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN
EIGHT EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
COVER PHOTO
The life of the bee has fas¬
cinated men since early an¬
tiquity. Yet only In recent
years have we come to un¬
derstand the amazlno mech¬
anism of the bee's sensory
organs. In the article on
page 4, Karl von Frisch
reveals the Important role
of the bee's sense of smell.
Photo shows a worker from
a wild-bee colony returning
to a hollow-tree nest, its legs
heavily loaded with pollen.
From the film "Secrets of Life".
(©) Walt Disney.
16 NIKO PIROSMANI
A new find in primitive painting
By Jean Keim
25 BUILDING A FUTURE FOR YOUNG ARAB REFUGEES
By Richard Greenough
29 WILL THE INDIAN OCEAN YIELD ITS SECRETS ?
History's most ambitious venture in oceanography
By Daniel Behrman
32 THE FIRST U. N. MEMORIAL STAMP
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
(MC. 62.1.173 A)
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cutturaf
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7; France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
René Caloz
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition
Spanish Edition
Russian Edition :
German Edition
Arabic Edition :
Japanese Edition
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Jane Albert Hesse
: Arturo Despouey
Venlamln Matchavariani (Moscow)
: Hans Rieben (Berne)
Abdel Moneim EI Sawi (Cairo)
: Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except In July and August when
itis bi-monthly ( I \ issues a year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, Germsn
Arabic and Japanese. In the United Kingdom it is distributed by H. hi
Stationery Office, P. O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted (rom THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re*
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier It Indexed monthly In The Readers' Guide to
Periodical Literature, published by H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates: U. S. $ 3.00; IO/-stg. ; 7.00
New Francs or equivalent. Single copies l/-stg. 30
cents (U.S.) ; 0.70 New Francs.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
M correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
NATURE'S HIDDEN
LANGUAGES OF SMELL
by Karl von Frisch
Professor Karl von Frisch,
famous for his discovery of the
"language" of bees, recounts
here some surprising facts
about the sense of smell among
insects and fish. Even in the
"language" of bees, smell plays
a vital role. Bee (left) extract¬
ing nectar from a flowering
shrub, can direct other bees in
its hive to this food supply by
"dancing". The others identify
the tree or flower by smelling
the odour on the scout's body.
J. M. Baufle, Pans
S:,ome odours please us; others we dislike. To
' most people the perfume of a bunch of roses
In a room is an agreeable odour but nobody would dream
of putting an arum lily there in a vase, for it gives off
a pungent smell of decay.
Nevertheless, men and animals do not find the same
smells pleasant or disagreable. Moreover, many animals
have a much keener sense of smell than human beings.
For example, dogs, sniffing close to the ground, can follow
a trail whose existence no man would ever have suspected.
It has actually been shown that the fatty acids which
make up a large part of the secretion of the human
skin can be smelt by a dog in a solution a million times
more diluted than that which the human sense of smell
can detect.
There is nothing surprising in this if we compare
human and canine anatomical characteristics. The
nasal cavity, in which the olfactory cells are located, is
particularly developed in dogs; the olfactory mucous
membrane covers a far bigger area than it does in the
human nose, and the nerve centres in the dog's brain
which record and assimilate smell messages are much
more developed. This is also true of many other ani¬
mals. For nearly all mammals smell is more important
than sight just as it is for many fish and for certain
insects. Smell is the determining factor in their exis
tence, guiding them just as we ourselves are guided
by sight.
We must bear this in mind if we are to understand
the behaviour of certain animals.
One particular case which has long intrigued biologists,
giving rise to some strange hypotheses, is that of the
bombyx butterfly. Entomologists have found how to
catch large numbers of the extremely rare male bombyx
butterflies with the help of a fertile female of this species
placed under a wire-mesh cover.
The abdomen of the female bombyx contains a gland
which gives off a smell quite imperceptible to us. When
the female wants to attract a male, she turns this gland
round and it diffuses an attractive scent. Now an
insect's sense of smell is located in the antennae and any
butterfly collector can distinguish at a glance a male
bombyx from a female by the male's antennae, which
are large and contain innumerable olfactory cells. The
big penniform antennae of the bombyx show its highly
specialized olfactory powers and correspond, anato¬
mically, to the well-developed "smell receptors" in a dog's
nasal cavity.
The male bombyx butterflies are attracted by the smell
of the females. They are not at all interested in their
CONT'D ON PAGE 6
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Mantids generally have thin
filamentous antenna, but this
species has unusual feather¬
like ones. The increase of an¬
tenna! surface allows for a far
larger number of sense organs.
A Bandsma and R. Brandt, Wellington, New Zealand
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
LANGUAGES OF SMELL (Cont'd)
Perfumes for
a bumble-b
wedding
ANTENNAE CLEANING TIME.
Long-horned grasshoppers have long
sensitive antennae which are conti¬
nually waving about, "feeling" the
path of these insects. Because of
their Important function they are
kept meticulously clean. Here a
grasshopper cleans its antennae.
© A. Bandsma and R. Brandt
appearance. For them, smell alone is the quintessence
of feminine charm. This was proved by removing the
scent gland from a female, a small operation which in
no way altered her appearance, and then placing the
scent gland beside her. The males which had been
attracted to the spot turned their attention from the
female to the gland, and tried to mate with it.
Another species of nocturnal butterfly whose males
are attracted by the smell of the females is the mulberry-
eating bombyx. The caterpillar of this moth is the
silkworm, which has been bred by the Chinese for
thousands of years. Silkworm breeders supply the worms
with food (mulberry leaves) and the male moths with
females. Sheltered from their natural enemies, the
bombyx multiply freely, but as with other domesticated
creatures, their natural instincts tend to deteriorate.
The males no longer need to fly off in search of a mate.
In fact they have one put under their very noses, or
more precisely under their antennae. As soon as they
smell the attractive odour, their wings begin to flutter
and they rush towards the female.
Scientists have studied the chemical composition of
this scent. After twenty years' investigation, a team
g of research workers led by Professor Adolf Butenandt,
Nobel Prize Winner in 1939, succeeded in Isolating the
substance from the scent glands, and in analyzing its
chemical composition. This difficult task was made all
the harder because of the extremely small amount of
odoriferous substance produced by the gland. No less
than 500,000 females were needed to make 12 milligram¬
mes of a pure extract of the substance which attracts the
males. Its chemical composition is simple, being what
is known as a non-saturated alcohol.
Once the formula was known, the research workers
succeeded in making a synthetic substance which has
turned out to be just as effective as the natural product.
A minute quantity of it on the end of a glass rod brings
the males hurrying along just a effectively as the pre¬
sence of a female, which shows quite clearly that it is
the smell which attracts the male towards the female.
With other species, the males produce the odoriferous
substance which is love's messenger. One of these, the
bumble-bee, for a long time managed to keep the secret
of its amorous rendezvous, and the mystery was explained
only a few years ago.
In a forest on a sunny spring morning, a male bumble¬
bee can sometimes be seen flying towards the base of a
tree-trunk; he touches the bark here and there, and then
flies off again. A few dozen yards or so further on, he
lands oh the lower branch of another tree and goes
through the same performance. He touches the edges of
the leaves with his jaws, flies off again, makes another
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
puzzling halt, and eventually returns to his starting
point, after having flown round a wide circle in which
he has made a number of mysterious landmarks.
The fact ls that there ls a scent gland at the base of
the bumble-bee's jaws and the strange smell these glands
give off is perceptible even to us. The bumble-bee has
left traces of this smell on the bark and on the leaves
during his morning flight. He will go round the circuit
for hours on end, often from morning until night,
stopping for a moment at each point and adding a drop
more scent if need be. Elsewhere in the forest other
males are blazing the same kind of trail.
Bumble-bees which were captured and marked, resumed
their endless round as soon as they were set free.
Hunger eventually drove them to feed off the flowers In
the nearby fields but they quickly rushed back to their
rounds. The bumble-bee's secret is that the females
pick up the smell given off by the landmarks and wait
for their ardent suitor at one of them.
As there are several species of bumble-bee in the same
area, how can a female be sure that the "invitation card"
she finds has been left by a male of her own species?
Nature has provided for every contingency. The scent
in the jaw glands of the male varies according to the
species. As a further safeguard the various species follow
different itineraries on their sentimental journeys. Some
leave their scent on the lower branches of trees or on
roots just showing above the ground. Some go to the
leaves at the top of a tree. Others prefer gramineous
stalks or grass in the fields. Instinct tells the females
where to look for a male proposal.
The purpose of these alluring smells is the perpetuation
of the species. But the part played by odours in the hunt
for food is no less important. The attractive smell given
off by flowers helps scores of insects to find food, and
at the same time ensures the perpetuation of the plants.
Two birds are killed with one stone, as it were, for the
scent of the flower attracts the insects, which find nectar
and pollen in the calyx. Flying from flower to flower,
they carry the pollen which sticks to their bodies on to
the stigmata of other flowers of the same species, thus
ensuring the fertilization and the development of the
seed.
As honey seekers, bees play an essential role in this
fertilization. They gather the nectar not only for imme¬
diate food needs but also to build up stocks for the
winter. That ls why they fly unceasingly from flower to
flower. Bees have another peculiarity: they are
"faithful", each one adopting a particular species of
flower. This ls essential if pollenlzatlon ls to be effective,
but they can be faithful only If they are able to distin¬
guish the chosen species with absolute certainty. The
scent of the flowers, which varies with the species, plays
a decisive role In their recognition. In addition, the
scent has a special significance for the bees.
When one of the scouts finds a new supply of fooda
lime-tree in flower for exampleit returns to the hive
and announces the discovery by dancing on the cells
of honeycomb. This lively dance tells the other bees
how far away the new supply of food is and in which
direction it lies. Some of the bees gather round the
dancer, and touching the messenger's body with their
antennae, they pick up the smell of the lime-tree with
which it ls impregnated, and then fly off in the direction
indicated. The scent of the flower thus plays an impor¬
tant role in the "language of bees."
At the time when lime-trees are In flower and
full of nectar, other flowers are in bloom too.
And so the hive ls divided up into several teams of honey
gatherers, one of which deals with lime-trees, another
with robinia, and a third with yet other llowers. The
members of each team recognize immediately from the
smell of the dancers if the message ls meant for them or
for another team. The members of each team identify
one another in the hive through the scent of the llowcr
which each bee gives oif, and these specialized honey
gatherers form tightly-knit communities. They stick
together when resting, Just as they do when at work.
Not all flowers have a pleasant scent. Some give ofT
an utterly repugnant odour and thus attract files who.se
habits is to lay their eggs on rotting flesh. Scenting a
familiar odour of decay, the Hies arc lured to these
flowers and taken in in more senses than one. Here,
nature's ingenious arrangement of the flower's structure
keeps the files prisoner and does not set them free until
they are well powdered with pollen.
Yet the flies are not clever enough to learn a lesson
from this unpleasant experience. Attracted by the same
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
SEDUCTION AND WARNING. The
female of the mulberry-eating bombyx (the
caterpillar of this moth Is the silkworm) has
a scent gland which secretes a substance attrac¬
tive to the male of the species (right). Con¬
versely, a substance In the skin of minnows if
released by the slightest scratch is immediately
"scented" by other minnows and causes them
to flee for their livesa timely warning if It is
a pike that has begun to attack the shoal.
R.H. Noaillcs. Pan's.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
LANGUAGES OF SMELL (Cont'd)
Mr. Wasp taken in by an orchid
smell of putrefaction coming from another flower of the
same species, they are taken in again and in this way
the pollinizatlon of the stigmata is assured.
Some orchids amongst them the ophrys are even
more perfidious in their use of insects as pollenizing
agents. The females of burrowing wasps those of the
gorytes species, for example produce a special smell to
attract the males, just as the females of the mulberry
bombyx do. The flowers of the ophrys orchid have
succeeded in imitating the smell of the female wasps.
The males are attracted, they land on the flower and,
completely deceived, they try to mate with it.
The illusion does not last for very long, but the contact
has been enough to ensure the fertilization of the flower.
The fact that these orchids produce no nectar is itself
significant. They have, indeed, no need of this bait;
their scent alone is enough to ensure the co-operation of
the Insect.
It is well-known that in the case of mammals, smell
plays a vital role in the quest for food. The exceptional
sense of smell in dogs and in other mammals has already
been mentioned. It is far less well-known that fish,
too, have a highly developed sense of smell. Their
olfactory organs are not part of their breathing apparatus
but are concerned only with the detection of smells.
Experiments have shown that certain fish can find
their food and recognize members of their own species
entirely by sense of smell, after being deprived of their
sight. It is the eel which has the most highly developed
olfactory organs, its sense of smell being on a par with
that of the dog.
Some fish migrate over great distances and during
their journeys make special use of their sense of smell.
Salmon are often born in the fresh water of small streams
and creeks flowing into rivers. The young salmon follow
the river down to the sea where they spend several years,
often far from the mouth of the river. Once fully
grown, they return to the river and we still do not know
how they manage to find their way back. Nevertheless,
it has been proved by marking young salmon that not
only do they reach the river they came from, but they
also get back to the very tributary in which they were
born.
The riddle has been partly solved today, for samples
taken from different parts of rivers show that the smell
of the water varies. This is no doubt due to differences
in the geological formation of the river bed as well as
to the diversity of water plants. It has also been proved
that salmon which have .been deprived of their sense of
smell cannot find their way back to the stream where
they were born. It is the "smell memories," then, of its
earliest youth that urge the salmon to make its way back
to its birthplace.
We have seen that smells can be used as a bait. They
can also be used as a means of scaring other animals
away.
In North America and in South America there are
several varieties of skunk, a relative of the badger.
When attacked, they squirt out a jet of foul-smelling oily
liquid, which is secreted by the anal glands. A man who
has been unlucky enough to be sprayed by this liquid is
not fit company for some time afterwards, even though
he may take a bath and change his clothes.
Many insects too have adopted this method of defence
amongst them, the stink bugs. Some brightly-coloured
species are spared by insect-eating birds, for they have
glands which secrete an unpleasant-smelling liquid. It
has recently been discovered that they very successfully
protect themselves, in much the same way as the skunk,
against such enemies as ants.
I could go on giving examples but I would
rather mention a case in which a protective
smell of this kind sowed panic amongst the members of a
same species.
I was carrying out some experiments on the sense of
hearing in fish, and had trained a shoal of minnows to
pick up sounds made below the water near the shore of
the Wolfgangsee. I had to check whether all the mem¬
bers of the shoal used the same feeding ground, so I
caught one of the minnows and, with a needle, severed
a small muscle, the destruction of which makes the tail
turn a very dark colour. I then put the fish into the
water again.
No sooner had it joined up with the other fish than
something quite unexpected occurred. The minnows
panicked, sought refuge on the bottom, grouped together
again, and then fled into deeper water in the centre of
the lake. For several days they were very timid and
wary and it was only after repeated distribution of food
that they again became as familiar as they had been
before.
\
/ im
f ^^^^^ . ^*J
v IE'i- Y ; . -
flfl
BSLJkwiff
W 41 Bb^^^^aÄ w Hi
WH
1 V
\
\
5t*
ANT DAIRY-MAIDS. Many ants
keep "cows" sap-sucking insects such
as aphids and feed on their excess
juices. They take out their "livestock"
to graze on plant stems and roots and
later bring them back to the nest in
the same way as this ant dairymaid
herding closely a tiny scarabaeid beetle.
From the film "Secrets of Life". © Walt Disney
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
<
IN HIVE OR FIELD the bee is an industrious worker who has many surprising lessons to teach man. The male
bees or drones are born from unfertilized eggs laid by the queen bee. Inside the hive the female worker bees keep
a strict control over the proportion of the sexes in the colony and decide when to get rid of the drones. Left,
worker bees dispose of the larva of a drone. Right, a worker bee sucks nectar from a (lower with Its long tongue.
Could the wounded minnow have told the others about
his unpleasant experience? Obviously not. A beheaded
minnow caused just the same panic, and so did one that
had been minced into small pieces. In fact, the filtered
juice from these small pieces was enough to scare the
shoal away.
I tried to find out from which part of the body this
warning came, and finally decided that it lay in the skin.
So far it has not been possible to Isolate the substance
contained in the skin. All that is known is that It must
be soluble in water and that fish can smell it. Normal
minnows are very sensitive to it whereas minnows which
have been deprived of their sense of smell are quite
unaffected. An extract taken from a tiny piece of skin
is enough to put a whole shoal of tamed fish to flight.
Even the minute quantity diffused in the water following
a needle prick as had been the case when I noticed the
phenomenon for the first time has this effect.
We can hazard a fairly close guess at the biological
significance of the phenomen. Minnows are preyed upon
by many types of fish and their greatest enemy is
undoubtedly the pike. When a pike catches and devours
a minnow, its numerous sharp teeth are bound to scratch
and tear the minnow's delicate skin, and the panic-
creating substance spreads Into the surrounding water.
Thus, any minnows which happen to be near are warned
of the danger; they flee and remain on the alert for
some time. It is for this reason that a pike does not get
a chance to destroy an entire shoal.
I was interested to find out if the phenomen is peculiar
to minnows, or if this strange form of "life insurance" is
practised amongst other fish. Exhaustive experiments
have since shown that it is unknown amongst sea fish,
but that it is very common amongst fresh-water fish,
being limited, however, to the group which zoologists
call "ostariophysl." All fish related to the carpi.e. the
cyprinides and the slluridans, many kinds of which arc to
be found in America, Asia and Africabelong to this
group. The skin of the fish of all these species contains a
warning substance which ls released by a scratch, and
which produces the same effect as the one noticed in the
case of the minnows.
It has also been shown that the warning substance
from minnows acts upon other members of the cyprinides
family, but its power decreases with the remoteness of
relationship. The same experiments have made it possi¬
ble to verify suggestions based on anatomical data
concerning the race history relationship of the ostarlo-
physi group of fish.
Whereabouts in the fish is the warning substance pro¬
duced? Recent microscope research has shown that
there is a particular type of unicellular gland in the skin
cells only of those fish which produce the warning
substance. The secretion from these glands is not
released unless the skin is scratched. We may presume
from this that the glandular cells make up the warning
substance itself, and that it is their function to send a
rapid farewell message of warning to the rest of the
shoal when one of its members is seized by some
marauding fish.
Dr. Karl von Frisch, world famous zoologist, was awarded
the Kalinga Prize for the Popularization of Science in
1959. Former director of the zoological institutes of Ros¬
tock, Breslau, Graz and Munich, he is the author of
"The Dancing Bees" and "Bees, Their Vision, Chemical
Senses and Language."
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
At the Great Temple
of Abu Simbel
F ORGOTTEN for many centuries, engulfed by
desert sands and finally rediscovered in 1813,
Abu Simbel ls still a storehouse of secrets. What myste¬
rious purpose determined the activities of the engineers
who executed the orders of Rameses II? Why does it
embody such curious lighting effects which can hardly
result from mere chance? With what intent was the
interplay of rock and sunlight so expertly combined?
At a time when Unesco is leading a world campaign to
save these unique temples from being swallowed up for¬
ever by the swiftly-rising waters of the Nile (See The
Unesco Courier, Feb. 1960 and Oct. 1961) one special
aspect of the Great Temple deserves closer study: the
relationship between its structure and the rising sun.
The facade of the great temple faces east, but not due
east; it runs slightly north-east/ south-west. Throughout
the year it receives the first rays of the sun practically
full on as soon as the sun rises from the hills lying on
the opposite bank of the river.
The sun first lights up the frieze of baboons, over six
feet high (there were once 22 of them) topping the temple
facade. The Egyptians had observed that baboons are in
the habit of uttering loud cries just before sunrise. In
Egyptian mythology they became the helpers at the birth
of the god Re every sunrise after his dangerous journey
through the darkness of the underworld.
At dawn the Sun god leaves his nocturnal bark for the
ship of day and resumes his triumphal journey through
an eternally blue sky. The cohort of baboons dances
with joy to celebrate his victory over the lethargy of
night:
A few moments later, the rising sun is greeted by what
seems to be his own image: the god Re Horakhti (the
sun rising on the horizon) standing in an oblong niche
beneath the cohort of baboons above the high doorway
leading into the underground temple. His falcon head is
surmounted with the sun disc from which a cobra spits
fire. On his left hand and on his right, the pharaoh
offers up the supreme gift of an absolute sovereign: the
image of Maat, goddess of balance, of justice and of
truth.
But is the statue really that of Re Horakhti? Under
his right hand is a dog-headed sceptre (in Egyptian
"user") and, under his left hand, the traces of a small
statue of Maat, which is difficult to recognize today but
which appeared clearly in the drawings made at the
beginning of the 19th century when the temple was
rediscovered.
These elements, with the name of the god himself;
complete a rebus of the name Rameses chose for himself
when he acceded to the throne: User-Maat-Re. Thus,
here is an identification of the pharaoh with the god just
as, thousands of years later at Versailles, another "sun-
10 god", Louis XIV, identified himself with Apollo.
CONT'D ON PAGE 13
DANCING BABOONS
As the sun rises over the mountains
it lights up a frieze of baboons atop
the façade of the temple. Thus
begins the first act in the myste¬
rious relationship between the
sun and the temple that has long
intrigued egyptologists. In Egyptian
mythology the baboons salute the
sun god, dancing with joy to cele¬
brate his new victory over night.
THE SUN GOD
Moments later a new phase begins
in an ingenious reconciliation of
religious symbolism and architec¬
tural creation. Sunlight bathes the
statue of Re Horakhti, the sun god,
standing in a niche above the en¬
trance to the underground temple,
his falcon's head surmounted with
the sun disc decorated with a
cobra. The Pharoah, Rameses II,
identified himself with this god.
Photos Unesco-Almasy
INTO THE MOUNTAIN
Still rising, the sun shines full upon
the four giant statues of Rameses
that form the façade. The next
phase, as the rising sun penetrates,
at certain times of the year, within
the temple, eventually reaching the
sanctuary 200 feet from the thres¬
hold, evokes the enigma of Abu
Simbel. Why did the Pharoah's
priests and astronomers choose
this site in Upper Nubia to carve
out the great temple ? Was the
construction of the galleries and
chambers deep within the moun¬
tain "married" purposefully to the
yearly course of the sun in such a
way that its first rays reach the
gods in the sanctuary at fixed dates ?
And why are these dates significant ?
Unesco - van der Haagen
DEZ VOUS
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
RAMESES' MYSTERIOUS
ENCOUNTER AT DAWN
by Jan K. van der Haagen
T^
' t 	 «- _
WITH THE SUN IN THREE ACTS 11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Ideal horizon: equivalent to height of altar inside
the temple Seen from interior of the temple:
RISING SUN APPEARING
OVER THE HILLS
NEW LIGHT ON
AN ANCIENT RIDDLE
j. van der Haagen
Position of sun above horizon; _^^^^M
Up to 4 degrees inner sanctuary (B)is fully illuminated. ^^^^^^^
Above 54 degrees no rays of sun enter the temple. ^^^^r
\ M CROSS SECTION OF TEMPLE AXIS
/y. / m A. Entrance hall with colossi
/ y/ /ni m ^' lnncr sanctuary
/' /mi
1 7 /^KT~T^~^^
Inside entrance hall (A in drawing on right). Inner
sanctuary is in far background (B in drawing).
The sudden illumination of the statues of the
sun gods in the sanctuary deep in the heart of
the rock at Abu Simbel is a breathtaking spect¬
acle. Its religious meaning is clear: divine light
seeks out from within the bowels of the earth
"he who holds divinity within him". But what
is the deeper significance of the dates, in February
and October, when this phenomenon occurs ?
Perhaps the whole vast undertaking of construct¬
ing the temple was linked with the important
ceremony that took place on the Jubilee of
Rameses II in the 30th year of his long reign.
Other evidence suggests a link between the
temple and a brilliant star in the constellation
ofOrion which, about1260B.C, rosein the vicin¬
ity of the axis of the temple. Photos on these
pages show how astronomers, builders and engi¬
neers enticed the rising sun to illuminate the
colossi inside the entrance hall (left) and finally
reach the gods seated in the sanctuary (right).
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
National Geographie Institute, Paris
Below, left to right, seated behind the sanctuary altar:
the gods Ptah, associated with the underworld (never
lit by the sun), Amon, Rameses and Re Horakhti.
ENCOUNTER AT DAWN (Cont'd)
A faint glimmer
on the wall
A few moments later, still rising, the sun lights up the
colossal statue of King Rameses (more than C5 feet high)
who has now discarded his divine metamorphosis. While
It was customary to place the statue of a sovereign close
to the entrance of a temple built on his command, here,
at Abu Simbel, the entire facade actually consists of the
four statues of the king.
Between the moment when it lights up Re Horakhti
and the moment when it shines full upon the statues of
Rameses, the rising sun reaches the entrance of the tem¬
ple. Its first rays faintly illuminate the upper part of the
wall at the back of the famous chamber of statues. This
chamber or entrance hall corresponds to the "first court"
in classic Egyptian open-air temples. It is divided into
three aisles by a double row of four pillars against each of
which stands a statue of the pharaoh.
Although these pillars arc generally called "Oslrian",
they represent Rameses and not Osiris. It is true that
the pharaoh holds in his hands the crook and the scourge
which are the attributes of Osiris, sovereign of the
Empire of the Dead, but these objects had already long
become the insignia of royalty.
In conformity with the classic Egyptian plan, the corri¬
dors become narrower and narrower, and the successive
chambers smaller and smaller, the ground sloping upwards
as the roof slopes downwards.
Viewed from any spot on the globe, the sun ls seen to
rise at the same point only twice a year. Consequently,
in the underground temple of Abu Simbel the play of light
deep within the earth varies constantly. When the sum¬
mer solstice comes round and the sun rises to the north
of the axis of the temple, the seat and legs of the statue
of Rameses on the facade to the north of the entrance
prevent the first rays of the sun from penetrating the
temple, and a little later In the morning it ls the lintel of
the doorway that serves as a screen.
Not until September 10 do the sun's rays reach
the face of the first colossus on the left In the
big chamber. On the following days they reach further
In, and a photograph which I took on October 0, 1959,
shows that the last colossi on the southern side were the
first to receive the light.
The culminating point of the cycle lies between October
10 and 30, during which period the first rays of the sun
reach the last chamber, the holy of holies, situated in the
heart of the mountain 200 feet from the threshold. It is
at this time that the sun-gods seated against the back
wall are illuminated, either separately or in pairs, and
each totally or partially according to the date.
These gods are Amon, the sun-god of Thebes (the capi¬
tal at the time), Re Horakhti and, seated between them,
a god among gods. Rameses himself. The god Ptah, one
of those who preside over funeral ceremonies, is not en¬
titled to the divine light and, except for his left arm, he
remains in perpetual darkness.
Henri Bonneval, leader of the Geographical Institute
of Paris expeditions, who made the photogrammetrlc
recordings of all the temples in Egyptian Nubia, has estab¬
lished that the sun appears on the horizon exactly in
the axis of the temple on October 19 and on that day its
first rays largely illuminate Amon and Rameses.
As autumn draws to a close the sun's first rays reach
the colossi on the north side and finally those seated
nearest the entrance. After November 30, the sun is once
more banished from the sanctuary. But less than a
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
13
Unesco-Almasy
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
ENCOUNTER AT DAWN (Cont'd)
Search for a forgotten star
month after the winter solstice, on January 20, it shines
inside once again, and in January, February and March,
the phenomena just described take place in the opposite
order. Amon and Rameses are reached by the first rays
on February 21.
The sudden illumination of these statues deep under¬
ground is breathtaking. Its religious Implication seems
clear: divine light seeks out from the very bowels of the
earth the man who holds divinity within him. As the
temple seems deliberatly to have been constructed on an
axis not exactly at right angles to the facade which
had to run according to the cleavage plane of the rock
the question arises as to whether the dates of February
21 and October 19 have a particular significance.
The spring equinox (March 21 or 22) and that of
autumn (September 22 or 23) immediately jump to mind.
Searching for an explanation of the difference of one
month. I wondered whether the phenomenon called the
precession of the equinoxes might not be involved. In
the Platonic year, which lasts nearly 26,000 ordinary years,
the celestial poles describe wide circles, finally returning to
their point of departure. Thus the entrance of the Pyra¬
mid of Cheops was orientated according to the French
astronomer Camille Flammarion towards a star which
then played the part of the pole star. Similarly, might
not the axis of the great temple at Abu Simbel be orien¬
tated towards a point which today has no particular
significance, but which, when the temple was built, was
that of the rising sun at the time of the equinox?
Astronomy soon brought me the proof that the
precession of the equinoxes played no part
here; so I had to look for another explanation. Could the
dates of October 19 and February 21 have been of special
importance in Egypt in the time of Rameses II?
The French Egyptologist, Louis Christophe, who retraced
the history of the construction of the underground temple,
after detailed studies of the figures carved on the facade
and the bas-reliefs inside, concluded that the decoration
of the oldest parts must have been completed before the
26th year of Rameses II's reign, and that of the principal
chambers before the 34th. The temple would thus have
been built towards the time of the sovereign's Jubilee,
in the thirtieth year of his reign, the famous Heb-Sed.
The Heb-Sed was one of the important ceremonies in
Egypt at the time of the Pharaohs and probably the
survival of a prehistoric custom which consisted in putting
the head of the tribe to death with great pomp lest he
become senile and harmful to the community. On the
occasion of his Jubilee, the Pharaoh had to prove that he
was still in full possession of his faculties, after which he
was enthroned as his own successor.
According to Louis Christophe, the first sculptures at
Abu Simbel are, as It were, a tentative move to identify
Rameses with the sun-god. The identification grew
closer as his reign proceeded, to become complete in the
30th year. But what was the exact date of Rameses
first Jubilee? It seems to be unknown. Nevertheless, the
Jubilee was followed by others at much shorter intervals
and we know that the fifth and sixth Jubilees of Rameses,
who reigned for nearly 70 years, were celebrated during
the first days of the fifth month of the civil year. In 1260
B.C. that day corresponded to our own October 22.
From this fact, Louis Christophe concluded that the
building of the temple was begun with the Heb-Sed in
mind, and that it was on that solemn day that the
Pharaoh had been deified.
It will be noticed that there is a difference of two or
three days between the date of the royal Jubilee estab-
J4 lished by Louis Christophe and the date at which the
sun Tises in the axis of the temple. Perhaps it is possible
to reduce this difference to one or two days.
Here is how I think this may be done. It seems
probable that the astronomer in Thebes or Memphis
who was asked to determine the exact point where the
sun rises on October 22 at Abu Simbel did not know
details of the site Memphis, for example', is nearly 800
miles from Abu Simbel. The astronomer may in conse¬
quence have based his calculations on an "ideal" horizon
situated on the same level as the temple. In reality the
sun rises at Abu Simbel about five minutes after it crosses
the "ideal" horizon since on the right bank of the Nile,
about 3,600 yards from the temple, there runs a chain
of hills sufficiently high to delay the sun's appearance.
Moreover, since, in the month of October and at that
place, the orbit of the sun makes an angle of about 66
degrees with the horizon, the first segment of the sun's
disc appears at a slightly more southern point than that
where the sun clears the "ideal" horizon. The problem
ls further complicated by the fact that the crest of hills
is far from level and at one point dips steeply.
But does the "astronomical error" really provide a full
explanation? Even taking into account the phenomenon
which led to the introduction of the bissextile year, it is
evident that a discrepancy of at least 24 hours exists
between the day the sun rises in the axis of the temple
and the date of the Jubilee. Now, if Louis Christophe's
theory is correct and the temple offers proof of the deifi¬
cation of Rameses II on the day of the Heb-Sed, the date
on which the first rays fully illuminate the statue of the
king is much more important than that on which the
sun rises in the axis of the temple.
The rays of sunlight do so a little after October 19, and
a photograph taken on October 21, 1961, shows the sunlit
statue of the king. Taking into account the difference
of one day which we have just mentioned as a possible
"astronomical error", this brings us to the day of the
Jubilee. At the same time, the fact that the depression
in the crest of the hills is not in the axis of the temple,
but slightly to the south of it, takes on particular signi¬
ficance. On October 21 and 22, the sun seems to keep its
point of rising as long as possible in the neighbourhood
of the depression as if to give its first rays the longest
possible opportunity of lighting up the sun-god.
This explanation, of course, is based on the assumption
that the ancient Egyptians had great ability in the fields
of theory and practical skills. We know this was already
the case one thousand years before Rameses. Moreover,
once the main lines of the undertaking had been estab¬
lished by calculation, it was still possible for the builders
to make rectifications. The size of the statues, for
example, enabled them to regulate the play of light
precisely as it happens the statues are not all the same
size. For this reason it would perhaps be wiser to believe
that around the year 1260 B.C., the Heb-Sed fell, not on
October 22, but on the day we now call October 21.
T here remains another hypothesis the possi¬
bility of there being a link between the temple
and the fixed stars. Although the precession of the
equinoxes does not change down the centuries the
direction in which the sun rises, it is equally true that the
appearance of the night sky was very different 3,000 years
ago from what it is today. One may reasonably wonder
whether the axis of the temple was not related to the
appearance of a star which was important to the
Egyptians.
At my request, Henri Bonneval carried out research on
this question and his findings are astonishing: for a
number of years around 1260 B.C., an exceptionally
brilliant star in the constellation of Orion did in fact rise
in the immediate vicinity of the axis of the temple.
Orion was one of the rare constellations in ancient
Egypt that modern astronomers have been able to iden-
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
PRIESTLY VIGIL IN THE CHAPEL OF RE HORAKHTI. At the northern end of the temple terrace at Abu Simbel stands a
little building known as the Chapel of Re Horakhti. What was its original purpose and why was Its axis pointed nearly 30 degrees
south instead of at right angles to the terrace ? One of the hypotheses outlined by Jan van der Haagen following his Intensive his¬
torical and astronomical research throws new light on this question. The chapel appears to be orientated In such a way that a priest
posted in the centre of the chapel would, at the moment of the winter solstice, see the rising sun exactly In Its axis. Until now
there has been no direct evidence that the Egyptians determined the solstices. Photo, Documentation Centre on Ancient r£yl,t
tlfy with certainty. Everyone Is familiar with the three
brilliant stars of Orion's belt, known for centuries as the
Three Wise Men. The middle star, the one we are concer¬
ned with, bears the Arabic name of Alnltam.
Today, thanks to the famous "astronomical ceiling"
on the tomb of Senenmut in the necropolis of Thebes,
we know that Orion, or rather, the three stars in Orion's
belt, were of great significance to the Egyptians. Various
texts also make It clear that Orion (Sah for the Egyptians)
was identified with Osiris, the god of resurrection.
"Osiris has reappeared in Orion" says one of the texts
of the pyramids.
It seems that the Egyptian calendar was based on the
heliacal rising of Sah and Sothis (our Sirius). The
200-feet-long tunnel formed by the temple was obviously
an invaluable aid in determining the moment when the
rising star first appeared in the faint light of dawn. The
tunnel formed an ideal screen against the rays of the sun
when it rose immediately after the star.
There is yet another hitherto unsuspected relationship
between the great temple at Abu Simbel and the yearly
course of the sun. At the northern extremity of the
terrace which runs along the great temple, a terrace
bordered with statues which represent Rameses and
Horus the Falcon alternatively, there is a curious small
edifice without a roof. The eastern facade has something
of the form a pylon and the building is known as the
Chapel of Re Horakhti.
" A small staircase and door lead up to it. In the centre
of the building stands what is generally called an altar.
However, this altar is not intended for offerings. A stone
staircase leads up to it and the priest In office, surrounded
by four stone baboons, one in each corner, could watch a
particular point on the horizon from between the crennels.
The baboons and the small obelisks standing to the north
and to the south of what is conventionally called the
altar (now preserved in the Cairo museum) prove that it
"/as indeed a sanctuary consecrated to the sun.
But there ls something unusual about this building.
Its orientation Is very different from that of the terrace
and consequently from that of the great temple. The
little temple is orientated further to the south.
What ls the reason for this? I wondered whether the
axis might not have been orientated in such a way that
the priest looked straight at the point where the sun
appears In the winter solstice a point which makes an
angle of 116 degrees with the north. Vital Information
on this point came from the Geographical Institute of
Paris. The axis of the small temple makes an angle of
about 118 degrees with the north. The difference of two
degrees is negligable considering that the axis of the
small temple ls only a few metres long.
Finally, we may recall that the eastern wall of the
little chapel has the form of a pylon. According to the
theory advanced by Mrs. C. Desroches-Noblccourt (Chair
of Egyptian Antiquities. Ecole du Louvre, Parts) the pylon
embodies an ancient Egyptian myth about the creation
of the world and does so to celebrate the winter solstice
and the rebirth of the young sun-god who succeeds
Osiris.
What will remain of the play of light between the sun
and the temple when Abu Simbel has been raised over
200 ieet a height about equal to the towers of Notre
Dame Cathedral? The line of the horizon to the east
will be a little lower, and In consequence the baboons
will greet the sun five minutes earlier than they have
been doing for centuries. But, as three thousand two
hundred years ago, with a difference of barely one or two
days, the rays of the sun will light up Rameses and the
sun-gods at fixed times, leaving Ptah in eternal darkness.
Jan K. van der Haagen, former chief of the Museums and
Monuments Division in Unesco's Department of Cultural
Activities, is now director of Unesco's Nubian Monuments
Service. He is the author of works on loth century 15
landscape painting in the Netherlands and on icono¬
graphy.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Feast during the grape harvest (1 0 ft X 3 % ft).
NIKO PIROSMANI
Still life (small painting: 27 X 8 in. ).
UNKNOWN MASTER
OF PRIMITIVE ART
A beauty from Ortastchal (46 in. X 20 in.).
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
In every age and land there have been painters
who in all simplicity and without special
study have sought to express their picture of the world
In paint. They were little interested In being classed as
artists and In fact they were not recoginized as such since
their works clashed with the artistic canons of their time
and were not considered "beautiful."
But the present half century, for the first time since
the Renaissance, has witnessed the disintegration of the
more or less official rules of academic art as the existence
and importance of hitherto neglected forms of art came
to be appreciated, such as the Romanesque, Pre-
Hellenic, Oceanian, and African art, the art of ancient
civilizations unearthed by archaeologist as well as that
of prehistoric man.
by Jean A. Keim
Subsequently, art historians also began to turn their
attention to a style of painting termed "simple-hearted
painting" in Germany, "primitive painting" in the United
States and Yugoslavia and "naive painting" in many
countries.
This variety of labels shows how difficult It is to find a
suitable classification for those unsophisticated artists for
whom the world was a great canvas to be reproduced
as simply as possible. Perhaps a better name might be
the one used as the title of a Paris exhibition In 1935:
"Popular Masters of Reality."
The most famous of these artists was a Frenchman, the
Douanier Rousseau, whose paintings are now eagerly
prized by museums the world over. But when Rousseau
held his first major exhibition' in Paris in 1912 his
canvases were greeted with sniggers of scorn by the
fashionable critics of the day.
Siiince then countless other such painters have
been discovered, some good, some bad for
simplicity alone does not make a great artist. A fairly
representative selection of their works was shown at the
New York Museum of Modern Art in 1938.
Today many pages would be needed to list all the
painters who can be grouped in this same category yet
whose works are as markedly different one from another
as Dietrich of Switzerland, Generallc of Yugoslavia,
Greffe of Belgium, Guillen of Nicaragua, Hyppolite of
Haiti, Metelli of Italy, Grandma Moses of the United
States of America, Ociepka of Poland, Paps of Germany,
Pasada of Mexico, Shalom of Israel, Theophllos of
Greece, Urtiaga of Peru, Vivancos of Spain, and Wallis
of Great Britain.
Each day brings us the name of a new artist, of greater
or lesser talent, as well as many unsigned works the
authors of which are now being sought by art collectors.
A number of these painters are of exceptional merit yet
their names still await the world recognition they fully
deserve. Foremost among these is the Georgian popular
painter Niko Pirosmanashvili, or Pirosmani as he is known
for short.
THE COOK (42 in. x 18 in.). Niko Pirosmani often
chose his models from the simple folk he knew best.
17
CONT'D ON PACE 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
AUTUMN DAYS
AND
HARVESTS
In Niko Pirosmani's works the same themes
appear time and againscenes from rural life
or of craftsmen at work, sometimes arranged in
anecdotal groups. Above, "Harvesting": from
the grape and fruit harvest to the wine press.
The painter was fond of poetic touches like
the autumn pumpkins (foreground) and the
flight of migrating birds (left rear). Painting at
right is entitled 'The Childless Millionaire with
Poor Woman and Her Children" (52 in. x
45 in.). As canvases for his paintings, Pirosmani
employed a wide range of materials including
wood, tinplate, black oilcloth and shop walls.
Strikingly rich colour characterizes his work.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
PIROSMANI (Cont'd)
20
MARGARET THE ACTRESS. (3 ft. 1 0 in. x 3 ft.)
This striking primitive painting is aglow wih colour.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
AL FRESCO FEAST. Though he
himself often went hungry, Niko
Pirosmani was fond of painting
others at table, thus combining
portraiture with studies of still life.
Above, a vintager, detail from
" Feast During the grape Harvest "
a painting reproduced on page 1 6.
In a dark cellar, a lonely man
Plrosmanashvili was born in 1860 In a small village In
the Kakhetli district of Georgia. When he was still a
boy his parents died and he found himself alone In the
world. He made his way to Tiflis, the capital of Georgia,
where he found work with some small traders and taught
himself to read and write. But all the time he was
doing sketches and drawings.
In 1882, at the age of 22, he joined up with a painter
and opened a small paint business but his commercial
sense was very poor and he was soon forced to close shop.
He then found a job as a labourer on the railways, and
later opened a small dairy and finally a butcher's shop,
but all these ventures ended in failure.
Alone In the world, without either friends or
relatives, Pirosmani lived a miserable, hand-
to-mouth existence. He wandered about Tiflis trying to
scrape a bit of money together by decorating restaurants
and cellars, and painting signboards. It was not long
before his health failed and he sought refuge from his
frustration and bitterness in alcohol. In the words of
one authority, Professor Dudchava, "he drank to paint
and painted to drink." More often than not he received
no money for the work he did; instead the tradespeople
paid him with food and drink, estimating that it was
cheaper to allow Pirosmani to decorate their walls with
frescoes than to hire an ordinary house painter to redo
their walls.
In 1912 he was discovered by a French artist named Le
Dentre, then by the Zdanevlch brothers of Tiflis, painter
and poet respectively, and Pirosmani's name began to be
mentioned in art circles. In 1916 the Union of Georgian
Painters expressed concern about him and sent the
painter Gudiashvili to try to help him. Gudlashvlll has
left us a description of him as "a very tall, grey-haired
man with a small beard and drooping moustache; pale
and exhausted by his life, but gentle and serene; his
jacket and trousers covered with paint stains; living in
extreme poverty In a dark cellar."
One day, when a meeting was In session at the head¬
quarters of the Painters' Union at Tiflis, the door opened
and Plrosmanashvili walked In. He sat down, folded his
arms and stared dreamy-eyed In front of him. Only once
did he open his mouth during the discussion. "Well,
brothers" he said, "Do you know what we need? We've
got to build a big house In the centre of town where we
can all meet, buy a big table and a samovar to keep us
going, and talk about painting." He later left, never to
return. A Tlllls newspaper published a photograph and
then a caricature of him. This apparently Infuriated him
and he decided to break with his fellow painters.
Some time afterwards the Union again sought to come
to his aid, but Pirosmani had left Tlllls and disappeared.
The search for him went on In vain. When he did
return he was a dying man. Three days later a friend
found him lying In a cellar and had him transported to
a hospital. There he died on May 5, 1917. His place of
burial is unknown.
Plrosmanashvili was a noble-hearted, proud man who
never complained of his sad fate. His works are simple
and unsophisticated; he painted what he saw, as It stood,
with a purity of feeling and lyricism which reveal his
true love of mankind. In all his painting one senses his
deep attachment to ordinary folk, and the vitality of his
decorative art is vividly expressed In a combination of
brilliant colours, sharp greens, bright yellows and intense
blues often set against a background of deep black.
Again and again he painted the same themes, on re¬
quest, depicting scenes of abundance and plenty which
he himself had rarely known: Harvest Festival; Gay
Feasts; Banquet Under the Trees. But In the apparent
gaiety of these scenes his own Inherent melancholy can
always be felt.
His models were the simple people he knew: the Inn¬
keeper, the Cook, the House Porter. Today, their por¬
traits strikingly Illuminate a gallery of the Tiflis Museum.
He painted the Noble Lord, the Wealthy Peasant Holding
CONT'D ON PAGE 24
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
PIROSMANI (Cont'd)
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
THE HOUSE PORTER (portrait, 42 in. X 18 in.).
a Riding-Crop, the Millionaire with a Poor Woman and
Her Children, and later a Protest Meeting... perhaps an
unconscious gesture of revolt against the social conditions
of his time.
He had a great love for animals and portrayed them
in many works. He painted bucks and does, like The
Wounded Hind; bears and cubs as In the magnificent
She-Bear Under the Moon; eagles, as in Eagle and Hares;
and even a Lion and a Giraffe.
For Pirosmani also painted subjects he had never
actually seen. Though his whole life was spent in and
near Tiflis he has left us some remarkable scenes like the
Port of Batum, a Hunting-Party in India, and views of
the Russo-Japanese War.
Steeped In the history and legends of his country, he
painted portraits of Tsarina Tamara, and the Georgian
national poet Rustaveli, and illustrated salient passages
from the Man in the Tiger-Skin. He also painted innume¬
rable still lifes showing shashlik on a skewer, Georgian
vegetables and fish, and the traditional glass of red wine.
Although he was Georgian to the core, Pirosmani's
works stand apart from those of his contemporaries
which were completely dominated by European influen¬
ces; nor can they be placed In the tradition of the-ancient
frescoes which adorn Georgian churches. A born genius,
his style was all his own, and without affectation he
painted what his heart led him to paint.
After the Revolution, the Soviet Union began to give
prominence to his work. In 1930 his pictures were
exhibited in Tiflis, Moscow, Leningrad, Kiev and Kharkov,
and in 1938 and in 1960 important exhibitions of his
works were held in Tiflis. Many poems have been
written about him, and his life is the subject of a play
now being performed at the Rustaveli Theatre in Tiflis.
Years after his death a renown has come to this "ill-
starred" painter which he did not seek and certainly
never expected. Special tribute to Pirosmani was paid
to the artist In 1960 with a retrospective exhibition of his
paintings In Tiflis Museum. In the catalogue published
on that occasion, the director of the Tiflis Museum,
Academician Amiranashvili wrote: "In the history of
modern Georgian art prior to the Revolution, the work
of Plrosmanashvili stands out as a great milestone. And
it is to Soviet art criticism that we owe the present
understanding and appreciation of his painting."
But far beyond Georgia, by virture of his genius and
humanity, Niko Plrosmanashvili belongs to world art.
24 Jean A. Keim, former Cultural Attache at the French
Embassy in Moscow, is a member of the International
Association of Art Critics.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
BUILDING A FUTURE
FOR YOUNG ARAB REFUGEES
by Richard Greenough
H owever it Is examined, In human, political or
simply numerical terms, the problem of
the 1,180,000 Arab refugees living In Jordan, Leba¬
non, Syria and the Gaza Strip seems as far away as
ever from solution. In fact, those closely associated with
the problem admit that It has, year by year, taken on a
more stubborn and a more chronic nature In terms of any
ultimate solution. The situation remains explosive,
charged with highly inflammable emotion.
But having said this, It is agreeable to be able to report
that a determined and constructive start has now been
successfully made by means of vocational training, towards
equipping some of the young men and women with skills
which will enable them to lead useful and productive lives.
An encouraging aspect of this work ls that it ls being
greeted with Interest and enthusiasm, especially among
the younger refugees, and that the Arab host governments
are also, in general, supporting the projects with facilities
for land, local services and funds from the more than
$5 million a year they are allocating for overall assistance
including UNRWA.
Since 1950 UNRWAthe United Nations Relief and
Works Agency has been providing food, shelter, health,
welfare and educational services for the Palestine refu¬
gees. Education which now reaches a total of more than
200,000 children in 398 of UNRWA's elementary, prepara¬
tory and secondary schools, situated mostly in the 57
camps where 40% of the refugees live, or in government
schools subsidized by UNRWA, and taught by some 4,000
teachers, is being carried out with Unesco providing tech¬
nical responsibility.
UNRWA
HOMEWARD BOUND from school, these Arab girls
are some of the 3,000 children being educated In
UNRWA-Unesco schools now operating within the
Aqabat Jaber Camp outside Jericho in the Jordan Valley.
E'xisting education services are being Improved
land expanded wherever possible by more and
better trained teachers, by more classrooms to avoid
double-shift schools, and by new streamlined teaching
methods. Refugee children are, in principle, guaranteed
nine years at elementary and preparatory schools with
opportunities for three more years at secondary school.
But over and above this, great new emphasis has now
been placed on long-range plans for vocational and
teacher training centres. These plans, to produce any
real impact and to achieve the expected snowballing
effect, are predicated on and must continue far beyond
the present UNRWA mandate due to end In June 1963.
UNRWA also regards this vocational training as more than
just training for an occupation but as an alternative form
of secondary education much more suited to the great
majority of young refugees than the normal academic
secondary course.
Specifically and thanks largely to $4.5 million subscribed
during World Refugee Year (1959-1960), a three-year, $8
million programme ls well under way which will:
(a) Expand vocational and teacher training among the
Arab refugees to a point where UNRWA can turn out
2,000, possibly 2,500, graduates a year compared with 300
in 1960.
(b) Increase the number of scholarships awarded
annually to students In Middle East universities from 90
to 180.
(c) Improve the agency's basic elementary and
secondary education programmes partly as a means of
supporting the two previous steps and of properly relating
this to the educational trends of the host countries.
(d) Continue a modest loan-grant programme of
helping qualified refugees put their acquired skills to
productive uses In enterprises of their own.
This $8 million ls part of a S16 million Increase over the
regular annual UNRWA income of some $34 million
voluntarily subscribed by 41 countries. 05
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
ARAB REFUGEES (Cont'd)
MANY SKILLS & TRADES are taught to young
Arab refugees in the string of vocational training
centres set up in four Middle East countries by
UNRWA in co-operation with Unesco. Above,
a trainee reaches for an electric arc-welder in the
Kalandia Centre where more than 20 trades
are taught. Left, typing practice for some of
the students attending the commercial course.
for 22 trades & professions
26
However, all this should be considered against the grey
background of the fact that the refugee population
Increases by about 30,000 a year 30,000 more children
become adult, their places being taken by 30,000 to 35,000
new babies each year.
The whole Arab refugee problem has thus, with time,
shifted to the younger adults as more children grow to
maturity each year. Today of the 1,180,000 refugees,
approximately half are children under 18, half adults. Of
the nearly 600,000 adults depending on UNRWA, three out
of five have reached adulthood as refugees. The problem
is also compounded by the fact that maturing refugees
have hitherto been given so little chance adequately to
develop their latent productive talents that this deficiency
Is, in itself, a major contributing cause to the continuous
Increase in the number dependent on UNRWA. The
tragedy of this situation is not accurately reflected in
this rate of increase, but must be evaluated in terms of
Idle hours, vanished hopes, wasted talents, thwarted lives.
But UNRWA feels the picture is not hopeless. The
talents of these maturing young men and women can be
salvaged and put to constructive use.
In the words of Dr. John H. Davis, of the U.S.,
Commissioner General of UNRWA: "The three-year pro¬
gramme of UNRWA is not intended to be a solution of the
Palestine refugee problem. Rather it is based on the
humanitarian premise that young refugees should be, and
must be, given an opportunity to put to useful purpose
the basic talents with which they have been richly
endowed... It is important to bear in mind that specializ¬
ed training, In and of Itself, in no way prejudices the
ultimate solution of the refugee problem, in that young
persons reaching maturity will need specialized skills
regardless of where they may ultimately live." In other
words, try to ease a situation where the bottleneck of
refugees anxious to go out and make their way in the
world is forever growing tighter while the bottle of refu¬
gees grows bigger.
So UNRWA, with co-operation from Unesco in the form
of 24 international education experts drawn from 12
countries to help and train the Arab instructors at the
centres, has now established a string of vocational and
teacher training centres through the four Middle East
countries. UNRWA has its own team also of 28' interna¬
tional education experts at these centres.
Nine centres are now working. A training capacity of
nearly 4,000 young men and women 633 of them girls
is aimed at by next academic year, with an annual
graduation from then on of 2,000 to 2,500 students. Of
these some 1,700 will be for special vocations, the rest will
become teachers. All trainees are selected from among
those refugees entitled to draw rations on the form of
food supplies of a basic subsistence rate of 1,500 calories
a day in summer, 1,600 in winter. Of the 1,180,000
registered refugees, about 870,000 are entitled to these
rations, and of the balance who are not so entitled
because they earn a self-supporting wage, all but a very
few are nevertheless entitled to medical, welfare and
other UNRWA services.
In this part of the world where the Bible is
the ordinary man's Baedeker, the sites of
these nine centres are almost as rich in historical asso¬
ciation as some of the refugee camps, which can be found
in Jerusalem itself, Bethlehem, Hebron, Nablus, Jericho,
Damascus, Aleppo, Baalbek, Tyre, Sidon and Gaza.
The nine centres are situated: one in Lebanon, at Siblin
near Sidon; two in Syria, at Homs towards the north and
on the outskirts of Damascus; two in the Gaza Strip, at
Gaza itself and at Beit Hanoun; four in Jordan, one in
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
UNRWA Photos
NURSING STUDENT studies microscope slides at a refugee training centre. A prc-nurslng
course has also been introduced for 1 6-year-old girls who, If they do not choose to take up
regular nursing, may instead specialize in child care, midwifery or public health services.
Wadi Seer on the high ground above the capital, Amman,
one at Kalandia and two at Ramallah, both places a little
way out of Jerusalem on the old Roman road to Nazareth.
At Ramallah are the men's teacher training college and
also, opened September 1962, a combined teacher training
and vocational centre for girls, the latter a pioneer of
Its kind in the Middle East. It will ultimately have a
capacity of 633 and is housed in fine, hewn stone buildings
In 20 acres of hillside given by the Ramallah municipality
for a nominal rent of I Dinar ($2,80) a year, complete
with 1,050-old olive trees.
Twenty-two trade and professional courses, mostly two
years, some one, are offered the men. They include
carpentry, building, surveying, radio/TV, auto, electrical
and general engineering, sheet metal work, welding,
telecommunications, accountancy and commercial courses.
The favourite courses, nearly always oversubscribed by
three requests for every vacancy, are radio/TV and auto
mechanics.
The selection of courses is based on the best informa¬
tion presently available to the agency with respect to
employment prospects in the area. They are planned on
a flexible basis so they may be modified as more adequate
information becomes available. A word on this matter
of job placement later.
Six types of courses are offered to the women. Typing,
shorthand, secretarial work, known as "office arts" to
avoid any suggestion of direct competition with the men's
commercial courses; home and Institutional management;
infant leader courses for day nurseries and the like;
various types of dress design and dressmaking, known
rather unglamorously as clothing construction; pre¬
mising; and hafrdressing, manicure and pedicure.
The last presents special problems In the Arab world
according to Miss Marie Geldens, of Holland, chief Unesco
expert in vocational training for girls. Ilalrdresslng
training must be aimed at first chiefly for home atten¬
dance as the western Idea of women going to hairdrcsslng
salons has only been adopted In very few places In the
Arab world. "But the habit ls slowly growing and more
salons will open up," said Miss Geldens.
Nursing as a career for women ls still rather looked
down upon In the Arab world and women who have
regularly tended men patients In hospitals find their stock
quoted low in the marriage market. As a result this prc-
nurslng course has been Introduced to Interest girls
while they arc still young, 16 or so, as the top age limit
for entry Into the centre ls 19, In the hope that If they
don't choose to take up regular nursing, they may specia¬
lize In children's nursing, midwifery, public health or
become doctors' secretaries.
As with the men's courses, there has been no lack of
applicants for the girls' centres at Ramallah. For the
300 vacancies this current year In both teacher and voca¬
tional training, there were over 600 applications.
One heartening factor In the UNRWA-Unesco
education and training programmes is the
growing number of Arab girls In school at all levels, and,
more Important, those who remain In school now Instead
of dropping out as so often In the past for work at home,
in the fields or an early marriage. The attraction of
vocational training that this UNRWA-Unesco centre at
Ramallah has pioneered In the Middle East ls gaining
ground especially now that the entry of women into
teaching has become an accepted fact In the Arab world.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
ARAB REFUGEES (Cont'd)
For a more prosperous Middle East
As to the finances of this three-year programme and for
the future of the vocational and teacher training pro¬
grammes, most of the new centres and the expansion of
existing ones were financed through the $4.5 million
gathered during World Refugee Year, over 80% of It sub¬
scribed by three countries, the USA, Canada and the
United Kingdom, plus extra donations from the govern¬
ments of Kuwait and Morocco. Cost per trainee is
$500 per 11 months academic year.
To train the 2,000 students will cost $2 million during
1962 and 1963. Encouraged by the results of World
Refugee Year, UNRWA's chief, Dr. Davis decided to appeal
to voluntary organizations, private persons and in some
cases to governments, to "adopt" these refugees by
buying scholarships for them to attend the centres at the
rate of $500 per head per year.
The result has been encouraging. Funds have come
from such divergent sources as the United Steelworkers
of America and the Finnish Girl Guides ; from a commu¬
nity of North American Indians living in Canada and a
group of voluntary organizations in- New Zealand; from
the Arabian American Oil Company (ARAMCO) and U.N.
staff associations; from Swiss cheesemakers and the
Oxford Committee for Famine Relief.
Obtaining a job after finishing the courses is a crux of
the whole training programme. Placing teachers presents
few problems. Besides going Into the Agency's refugee
schools where there is always a need for more and better
equipped teachers, there is now a steady demand for
trained teachers throughout the Arab world and recently,
the total output of nearly 500 teachers trained over a
period In UNRWA-Unesco colleges, was absorbed not only
in the refugee schools but In Kuwait, Saudi Arabia, Qatar
and Libya.
With regards to the graduates from the voca¬
tional centres, where hitherto only a maxi¬
mum of 300 a year have so far had to find, and have found
jobs, UNRWA believes that the Increased output can be
absorbed Into a Middle East which is now undergoing
rapid technological development. The real test of this
will come, of course, when the first 2,000 or so come on
the labour market next year.
From surveys made by UNRWA placement services,
there seems reason to be optimistic. In the various host
countries, those in charge of national development pro¬
jects as well as private industry have apparently expressed
readiness to take on trained refugees In addition to their
own native citizens.
In Syria, for example, Mahmoud Hamad, director of the
Damascus centre which will have a capacity of 392
trainees, said that Syria's own new oil industry would
need a growing number of trained people. Electrical
foundations, telephone and water companies were busy
extending services to rural areas and also needed skilled
people. One company, he said, was ready to take on
80 plumbers for building projects as soon as they could
be provided.
In Jordan, Wadi G. DIdes, principal of Wadi Seer (capa¬
city 404 trainees), said that the Jordanian government
was ready to take all his graduates in the telecommuni¬
cations field and that civil aviation companies expanding
activities through the Middle East, were also asking for
more telecommunications experts as well as skilled radio
men and electricians.
28 At the Gaza centre (capacity 369 trainees), the director,
Abdel Kaher Nagl, said that last year all his 126 graduates
were taken on by the United Arab Republic, and he hoped
for the same result, in all branches of trades taught, this
year. In Lebanon, in the Gaza Strip and the UAR with
which Gaza is associated, the situation is a little more
complicated. Refugees, from Gaza are allowed to work
In the UAR provided they have definite jobs offered; they
cannot enter the country looking for work. However,
recently the UAR has started opening up large numbers
of places for the graduates from the training centre, for
further industrial training. In Lebanon, though refugees
do not have the rights of Lebanese citizenship, work is
available.
It is likely that a good proportion of the graduates will
have to cross international boundaries to obtain work, as
has been the case in the past with the smaller number
of graduates turned out by centres. The obvious spots
are other Arab countries with a developing economy, or
with oil wells.
R¡ecently, Mr. Ahmad Tuqan, of Jordan, a
«.seasoned Unesco expert in general education,
toured a number of the Arab countries, particularly
those in the Persian Gulf, and returned with enthusiastic
reports that there was still a thirsty labour market for
nearly all trades, and one which looked like continuing
for a while. He cited specially, the Sheikhdom of Abou
Dhabi, one of the Trucial States, until recently a small
community of some 15,000 people, but where oil has been
lately discovered in such abundance that output may
eventually rival that of Kuwait, and annual income
should reach something like $150 million in a year or so.
Moreover, the Sheikh Shakhbout plans to use much of
his new income in social and economic development for
his people. There will be room for many teachers and
builders, home economic experts and hairdressers, as well
as for pipe-line welders, accountants and auto mechanics.
By making the learning of English compulsory at the
vocational centres, trainees are also being better equipped
for work both inside and outside the Arab world.
It would be idle, and wrong, to assume that by launch¬
ing this ambitious vocational and teacher training pro¬
gramme, which can in any case only cater for a small
percentage of refugees at the present time, though there
is always hope and provision for expansion, UNRWA
seeks to find a solution to the problem of the Palestine
refugees. That is not UNRWA's job anyway. The refugees,
many of them, still cry out after 14 years, to be allowed
to return to their homes, a step which, though many
today feel to be no longer very practical, is nevertheless
acknowledged in U.N. resolutions within the fiamework
of a general settlement. Alternatively, they demand
compensation.
The U.N. Conciliation Commission for Pales¬
tine is still actively at work, and early last
summer combined renewed energy with muted hopes for
a possible compromise plan, though political tension has
perhaps run too high for anything much to be achieved.
All that can be said in the meantime, however, is that
UNRWA and Unesco are seeking every means to restore
to the refugees some economic independence, while at the
same time educating their children and training theñ-
youth so that, whatever the future may bring, the new
generation will not grow up in conditions of stagnation,
and will have a chance to play its part in the develop¬
ment of the Middle East.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
f.,
THE INDIAN OCEAN which
represents 14 per. cent of the
earth's surface is the least
known of the earth's oceans.
Since 1 959 science has explored
its mysteries on three levelsat¬
mospheric, surface and under¬
water. Right, trainees from
South-east Asia at work on
the research vessel "Stranger".
Unesco - Mattson
20-nation
scientific
expedition
ILL THE INDIAN OCEAN YIELD
ITS SECRETS? by Daniel Behrman
Apeaceful international fleet of forty vessels
will be setting out over the next two years
on a voyage of discovery in which the factor of the un¬
known looms almost as large as it did to the first naviga¬
tors to venture over the horizon in the past.
This fleet is the International Indian Ocean Expedition,
history's most ambitious co-operative venture in oceano¬
graphy, a science as old in its origins as seafaring and
yet as new and as challenging as the exploration of outer
space. Twenty countries in all are participating. Since
1959 several exploratory vessels have already been cruising
the Indian Ocean as part of the Expedition.
These research vessels are to cover the Indian Ocean
which represents 14 per cent of the earth's surface and
28 million square miles, of which so little is known that
they have been only semi-facetlously termed as "inner
space." The mysteries which this expedition is seeking
to crack, sound at times as if they had come from the
pen of a Jules Verne or an H. G. Wells.
For example, in the northwestern corner of the Indian
Ocean alone, running from the Arabian Sea to a line ten
degrees south of the Equator, vessels next year will be
trying to learn if the actual geological boundary of the
African continent extends almost to the middle of the
Arabian Sea Instead of running along an offshore contin¬
ental shelf.
Others will be investigating the physical processses of
this ocean to find out why it suddenly appears to become
deadly to Its fish population. In 1957, a Soviet vessel
bound from Ceylon to the Gulf of Aden encountered a
mass of dead fish floating over 60,000 square miles, a
tonnage estimated as equal to the world's commercial
fish catch for an entire year.
At one point the expedition will become a combined alr-
and-sea operation; the atmosphere will be converted into
an open "prism," miles In height, by weather planes flying
triangles or pentagons with surface observers at the end
of each 100 mile leg. The difference in readings at both
ends of the "prism" is expected to provide clues to the
flow of heat and water vapour over the ocean. This ls
another step in the process of attempting to learn how 29
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
INDIAN OCEAN (Cont'd)
Hunting the elusive coelacanth
the earth's atmosphere actually works in order to put
weather forecasting on a more scientific basis.
Generally speaking, the Indian Ocean itself is a gigantic
laboratory for studying the effect of wind on currents.
It is the world's sole ocean in which the direction of
prevailing winds and, consequently, that of prevailing
currents changes twice a year with the onset of the
northeast and southwest monsoon seasons. Oceanogra-
phers are extremely eager to investigate these reversals
because they are directly linked to the ocean's fish pro¬
ductivity.
What do currents have to do with fish? Very much,
In the case of the Indian Ocean and other tropical seas
where a warm layer of surface water blankets cold food-
laden deeper layers ' and prevents normal mixing.
Currents produce upwelllng of these deeper layers, bring¬
ing up "fertilizer" in the form of phosphates and nitrates
needed to sustain life.
The Importance of these studies in the Indian Ocean
ls obvious. Around Its shores live some of the world's
most heavily-populated countries. The possibility of
"farming" the Indian Ocean for fish protein cannot be
overlooked.
Another biological aspect of the International Indian
Ocean Expedition is even more appealing to the imagi¬
nation. In 1964, one vessel is to go out on a latimeria
hunt. The latimeria, a species of coelacanth, was believed
extinct until scientists learned, almost by accident, that
one had been caught in African waters in 1938. Physiolo¬
gists are anxious to study its waste-elimination processes
which are an intermediate stage on the path of evolu¬
tion leading to present-day fish.
These are some of the highlights of the International
Indian Ocean Expedition brought out at a recent meeting
held in the United Kingdom. Oceanographers from the
Federal Republic of Germany, France, India, Pakistan,
the United States and the United Kingdom met at the
British National Institute of Oceanography at Wormley
to co-ordinate future operations in the northwest Indian
Ocean. The meeting was called by the Intergovernmental
Océanographie Commission which, together with the
Scientific Committee on Oceanic Research of the Inter¬
national Council of Scientific Unions (the body which
organized a similar joint venture, the International Geo¬
physical Year) and Unesco, is sponsoring the expedition.
It was an appropriate meeting-place, even
though the British National Institute of Ocea¬
nography is high and dry in the green hills of Surrey.
It stands on a knoll as a plain redbrick structure, but it
is surrounded by seabattered buoys, tidal gauges and rows
of barrels containing whale ovaries (one of the Institute's
tasks ls to keep track of the world's declining whale popu¬
lation.)
Chart by U.S. Navy Hydrographie Office, Washington
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
\ 1
Unesco - BiU Simmons
.<'.
OCEAN PROFILE IN PLASTIC. A clear picture of the ocean bottom Is shown In
relief by the plastic profile (right) used by scientists in their studies of the world under
the waters. Beside it is a classic profile chart of the ocean depth. One of the new tools
which has transformed oceanography Is the precision echo-sounder capable of measur¬
ing the outline of the ocean bed to one fathom (six feet) at a depth of 3,000 fathoms.
A closer inspection of the institute in these bucolic
surroundings reveals even more startling wonders. One
entire corridor is lined like a champagne wine-cellar with
hundreds of samples af sea-water from all over the world
in glass ampules. A room no larger than an ordinary
office is occupied by the North Sea that is, by a mathe¬
matical 'model where the effects of tides and storm surges
on the flooding of coastal regions in Northern Europe are
studied.
Some of the equipment being used by oceanographers
in the Indian Ocean Expedition has been developed or
tested here. Two of these devices serve as excellent
Illustrations of the new tools which have transformed
the science of oceanography within the past decade or so.
One is a precision echo sounder, accurate to one fathom
at a depth of 3,000 fathoms. This instrument has enabled
geophysicists to study the great abyssal plains of the
ocean floor sloping almost imperceptibly (with gradients
less than one in one thousand.) Previous sounders had
a margin of error as wide as fifty fathoms which meant
they could "see" a plain as rolling hills and valleys.
The second is a deep-water current-measuring Instru¬
ment which can be set to float at a predetermined depth
where it drifts and emits a radio signal (hence its
nickname of "pinger") enabling it to be tracked. This
instrument, which has also been called an "underwater
sputnik," has helped revise many long-standing ideas
concerning the stillness of the ocean depths. For
example, it has detected a current moving twenty miles
a day at a depth of 4,000 metres.
The activities of the British National Institute of
Oceanography are under the efficient and good-natured
command of Dr. G.E.R. Deacon, who also served as chair¬
man of the meeting to dicuss operations In the northwest
ocean. Dr. Deacon, at fifty-six, is one of Britain's leading
oceanographers and he is typical of the scientist who has
had long months of patient observation at sea. He seldom
speaks and, when he does, it is in a low tone calculated
not to distract his fellow scientists working under condi
tions reminiscent In many ways of the long voyages In the
days of sail.
As a matter of fact, Dr. Deacon Is the first to remind
a landsman that the study of winds and currents was a
flourishing science during the heyday of the sailing vessel
until it fell into a state of wrongful neglect with the
advent of steam. Present-day oceanography has revived
this study with modern techniques, particularly the ana¬
lysis of waves. Precise Information on wave conditions
has enabled certain vessels to cut their time across the
North Atlantic by 10 per cent In recent years.
Oceanographers, In general, have a more than
sentimental Interest In sailing vessels. Right
now, for example, the three-masted schooner "Vema," an
American research ship operated by the Lamont Geological
Observatory of Columbia University, Ls cruising the Indian
Ocean. At low speeds or while heavlng-to for observa¬
tions, such a ship can be more comfortable than a more
modern vessel.
It ls Interesting to note that the "Atlantis II." the
new research ship now being built by the Woods
Hole Océanographie Institution in the United States,
is powered by steam reciprocating engines rather
than by turbines or diesels. This "antiquated" technique
offers less noise interference In certain studies, particu¬
larly the propagation of sound. The "Discovery," Bri¬
tain's new research vessel launched last July and sche¬
duled to cruise the Indian Ocean next year, has adopted
dlesel-electrlc drive as an economic solution to problems
of low-speed operation. Both new vessels will be equipped
with "wells" amidships allowing Instruments to be
lowered directly into the sea.
In addition to "Atlantis II" and "Discovery," a new
2,200-ton research ship now being constructed In the 31
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
INDIAN OCEAN (Cont'd;
The oceans are one of the world's last
unexplored frontiers whose topography
and living things, plant and animal, are now
being revealed by patient research. Speci¬
mens like those shown here at the Nathrang
Institute of Oceanography, Vietnam, will be
studied for years before scientists find all
the solutions to their many mysteries.
Unesco - Pierre Pittet
40,000 miles
of sea-bed mountains
Federal Republic of Germany will take part in the Indian
Ocean Expedition. This means that some of the world's
most modern océanographie vessels and techniques are
to be tested there.
These new vessels offer the advantage of being able to
carry teams of scientists from different disciplines on the
same cruise which is actually the equivalent of two or
three cruises aboard smaller vessels previously used. The
largest ship to work in the Indian Ocean so far has been
the Soviet Union's "Vltyaz" listed at 5,700 tons.
The "Vltyaz" made an important contribution to the
Expedition in 1959 and 1960 by investigating layers of
hydrogen sulphide in the northeastern Arabian Sea and
in the Bay of Bengal, from depths of 125 to 1,000 mètres.
This was also found to be the most oxygen-starved layer
of the ocean and it will be the subject of further study in
the next two years to examine its influence on marine life.
In geophysics as well, the Indian Ocean Expedition has
already produced interesting findings. This was the case
of the nine months' cruise of the "Owen," a British- vessel,
which Investigated the Western Somali basin of the
Arabian Sea. Gravity and magnetic surveys of this area
seem to indicate that the African continental structure
continues more than 200 miles out to sea towards the
Seychelles Islands.
To explain the results of these surveys, a theory has
been advanced that the thick sedimentary layers of the
continent continue under the ocean. Next year, the new
"Discovery" and the "Owen" will use underwater seismic
explosions to determine the nature of the ocean floor in
this region. These two vessels, using underwater photo¬
graphy apparatus as well, will also seek to chart the
Carlsberg Ridge, part of a continuous mid-oceanic ridge
system comparable to a mountain range 40,000 miles long
linking the world's oceans.
In all, a total of nineteen océanographie research vessels
will be at work in the northwestern Indian Ocean next
year. Among them will be ships from two of the coun¬
tries directly concerned with the results of the expedition,
India and Pakistan. Both are also offering special faci¬
lities such as exemptions from harbour fees or storage
space for explosives used in seismic tesis to vessels in
the expedition.
On land, Pakistan is adding to her existing system of
tidal gauges while India has completed the building for
an International Biological Centre at Cochin to be oper¬
ated with Unesco assistance. Specimens taken by ships
will be sent to Cochin for preservation and study.
The expedition has also succeeded in enlisting the aid
of merchant and naval vessels crossing its territory for
supplementary observations. "Air support" will come in
May, June and July of 1963 in the form of meteorological
planes from the United States Weather Bureau and the
Woods Hole Océanographie Institution.
It fell to the men who met at the British National In¬
stitute of Oceanography to co-ordinate these efforts by
individual nations in order to avoid duplication of cruise
tracks and to establish agreement on such matters as the
choice of common reference stations for benchmark
observations or the maintenance by one ship of recording
buoys set out by another. Agreement was reached in a
manner as simple and as straightforward as the oceano¬
graphers themselves who are accustomed to working on
the high seas, a world without political boundaries.
And this will not be the least of the achievements of
the International Indian Ocean Expedition.
32
THE UNESCO PHILATELIC SERVICE
The thousands of persons who have given their
lives serving under the U.N. Flag, including
staff members, truce observers and military
personnel of member states, are honoured by
the first U.N. memorial stamp (far right). Stamp
from Panama (centre) is one of many issued by
U.N. members honouring Dag Hammarskjold.
Other stamps, Issued by the United Arab Rep¬
ublic, Afghanistan and Argentina, mark Unesco's
15th anniversary last year. The UAR stamp
also publicizes Unesco's efforts to save Nubia's
ancient monuments. All these stamps can be
obtained from Unesco Philatelic Service, Place
de Fontenoy, Paris (7*), which, as agent in France
of the U.N. Postal Administration, stocks all
U.N. stamps and first day covers now on sale.
^
NUION- UNIES
&\
POSIES AF6HÄSES
» . XHSOUSMBBUttlMRnSWII
75 -,i.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
WHY ANTARCTICA IS COLDER
Sir,
As our earth is orbiting around the
sun on approximately the equator
line west to east and approxim-
r.tively that position all the year
round, why is it that the North Pole is
warmer than the the Antarctic and why
are the Eskimoes able to live in the
North?
Colin R. Brown
Coolangatta, Queensland, Australia
Ed. Note:
Dr. G. Laclavère, President of
SCAR, The Special Committee - on
Antarctic Research, has been kind
enough to furnish us with the following
information: "To produce a complete
answer for your Australian corres¬
pondent would really call for a lengthy
paper. However, here are a few
salient facts on the subject. What he
says is more or less true; a more
precise astronomical calculation would
show that, taken over the entire year,
the South Pole enjoys more sun-hours
than the North Pole.
The reasons why the South Pole is
colder than the North are manifold,
but basically there is the fact that the
South Polar area is a vast, raised
continent, entirely covered by an ice-
sheet, whereas the North Pole benefits
from the moderating influence of the
ocean on which the ice-pack rests.
Antarctica is screened from the heat
of the equatorial and tropical areas of
the world by the circulation of the
peripheral winds. Here are several
basic reasons which should satisfy
your correspondent. But you might
also tell him that the reasons why so
much ice has accumulated in the
Antartic rather than in another
region of the world are still something
of a mystery."
IN NAIROBI
Sh,
I note that mention was made in your
March 1962 issue (The Awakening
African Cinema) of the African film
"Liberté I". This film has now been
shown around the world and, dubbed
in Swahili under the title of "Uhuru",
it has had a tremendous success in
Nairobi, Kenya where 30,000 people
witnessed its première. Hundreds
poured in from the outlying districts
pnd those who could not get in stood
on the tops of buses, lorries and cars
as far away as six hundred yards from
the massive, specially erected screen.
The tremendous crowd surged forward
chanting "Uhuru", to grasp the hands
of the stars, Manasseh Moerane of
South Africa and John Amata of
Nigeria, who came specially to
Nairobi. Mr. Amata said, "This film
will make Kenya the land of
expectation and hope for Africa. It
is the right answer, the right place,
the right time and you are the right
people to take it to all Africa."
Nahashon Ngare and Stanley Kinga,
who dubbed the film into Swahili, said,
"We are doing this as our part in the
struggle to answer tribalism and create
fundamental and lasting unity and
make leaders and led incorruptible and
unselfish as the only guarantee for a
free, full life for all in an independent
Kenya."
J. l'oncy
Cologny, Geneva, Switzerland
A SUNKEN OASIS
In the special issue (May 1962) of
The Unesco Courier on "Thirsty
Lands", you published photographs of
a sunken oasis: "A few years ago an
oasis cast its green shade near Fort
Flatters in the Sahara. Today it has
been swallowed up by the creeping
sands and only the tops of three palm
trees mark its grave." As a postscript
to this I am sending you a photograph
I took of this oasis in 1923 when I
often had occasion to visit it. At
that time the little pool there provided
enough water for growing a few
vegetables and several patches of
millet, and there were also several fig
trees and vines. I was one of five
Fienchmen who lived on the edge of
the oasis which was then the home
of about a dozen Touareg families.
The reason for the poor quality of the
photo is that it was developed at Fort
Flatters, where the water is heavily
impregnated with magnesium.
V. Mazzonl
Oran, Algeria
LOST HYMNS OF GEORGIA
Sir,
As a composer and specialist in folk
music, I was greatly interested by
"Lost Hymns of Georgia" (May 1962)
in which a Soviet linguist, Dr. Pavle
Ingorokva, explained how an ancient
musical mystery was solved. I have
often had to face similar problems
during research in the Middle East
into Biblical music written according
to the Sephardic Jewish oral tradition.
In Alexandria, in 1929, I published
a short brochure in French, in which,
under the title of "Music of the
Torah", I grouped all the material
I had collected. While admiring,
without reserve, the results already
obtained with regard to the Georgian
music, I should have liked Dr. Ingo¬
rokva to explain to us the problems
cf the rhythm or duration of sound
with the same precision that he has
outlined details of the pitch and
subsequent pattern of tones.
Alberto Hemsi
Aubervilliers, France
Sir,
Permit me to suggest some amend¬
ments to Dr. P. Ingorokva's "Lost
Hymns of Georgia". They concern
only those points which obligate any
musicological communication, even
when addressed to the general pub¬
lic. Mostly the translator and not
the author, seems to have been at
fault.
1. Hoth the nine-stringed square
instrument in the miniature and the
triangular one photographed (p. 27),
were designated as "lute", which
neither one actually is. In the minia¬
ture wc probably have a kind of
psaltery (musicologically: zither
strings over a .soundboard, with no
neck or yoke). This is cither held ver¬
tically, or only represented thus in or¬
der to evade a problem in perspective.
The instrument on p. 27 is an angular
harp (strings stretching from a sepa¬
rate neck and meeting the plane of
the soundbox vertically). As a "lute"
we would define the combination of
body and handle-like neck, with strings
parallel to the soundboard, as exem¬
plified by the various kinds of fiddles,
or the Caucasian "Tar".
2. In the same miniature, the wind
instrument is more probably a trumpet
of sorts, and not a "flute", even
though the painter made its player
hold it obliquely. At most it could
be a kind of shawm; if however, the
miniature is supposed to illustrate
Psalm 150, a trumpet-like instrument
is indicated. The "tabor", in the
same miniature, might better be called
a barrel-drum.
3. The bronze faun playing a wind
instrument designated as "auloi"
(flute) with bulging checks and a
wrinkled forehead l>oth indicate even
though the actual instrument is mis¬
sing the typical effect of blowing a
doublc-rccd instrument, which the an¬
cient aulos in most cases indeed was.
Therefore "aulos" (oboe).
4. Two points on page 27: for
"voice" substitute "mode" or, more
appropriately, the Byzantine term
"echos" melodic class. (The au¬
thor's statement raises a musicological
point which cannot be discussed
here); the accompanying voices in
Western art music for church use (not
"Roman Catholic church music",
which is non-polyphonic to this day)
began to be written out from the 9th
century onwards (not the I3th).
The great value of Dr. Ingorokva's
communication of course remains
unaffected in principle.
Bathja Bayer
Haifa, Israel
TOO 'HEAVY' FOR TEACHER
Sir,
I am continually receiving The
Unesco Courier and the Orient/Occi¬
dent Bulletin. I should appreciate if
they were a little more popular. The
articles are so "heavy" that it is diffi¬
cult to find time to read and use them
when the days are filled with teaching.
We teachers can seldom find time to
read more than what we can directly
use in our teaching, and The Unesco
Courier does not give us much of
that.
Dr. Sten Rodhe
Malmo, Sweden
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New;
TRIUMPHS OF SPACE RESEARCH:
Two major scientific achievements in
connexion with space research the launch¬
ing of the Telstar communications satellite
on July 10 and the successful completion
of the longest-yet manned space flights on
August 15 have been hailed by Unesco.
Making possible the first transatlantic TV
transmission, Telstar marked a new era of
long-distance communication. Congratulat¬
ing the United States, Unesco's Director-
General described the event as "a sign¬
ificant advance for the free flow of
information, one that opened up new
possibilities in international understanding."
The Director-General congratulated the
Soviet Union on the feats of cosmonauts
Adrian Nikolayev (1,663,000 miles in 94 J
hours during 64 orbits) and Pavel Popovich
(1,247,000 miles in 71 hours during
48 orbits). These latest achievements of
Soviet science, he said, "marked an
important further advance toward the
scientific exploration of outer space."
HOW SALTY IS THE SEA? Scientists
now find the answer by testing the
electrical conductivity of sea-water samples
which gives a more precise indication of
the salt content than the chemical method
hitherto employed. Scientists met at
Unesco's H.Q. in Paris, recently to discuss
this question whose importance is related
to design and construction of ships and
harbours, the prevention of coastal erosion
and the behaviour and migration of fish.
E
LECTRONIC AID FOR NURSE:
British scientists have now a device
which can register changes in a patient's
pulse, breathing, blood pressure or tempe¬
rature and flash them to a central control
panel. Its purpose is not to provide an
electronic substitute for nurses but to free
trained personnel from routine tasks.
KINDERGARTEN LINGUISTS: Chil¬
dren can begin to learn a second lan¬
guage even before they can read and write
their own with no detriment to the deve¬
lopment of the first language, to intellec¬
tual growth or general school attainment,
according to specialists from 11 countries
who met recently in Hamburg. The
meeting convened jointly, by the Unesco
Institute of Education and the Unesco
Dept. of Education, recommended that a
second language should be taught in
kindergarten.
GIANT GAS PIPE: The world's biggest
gas pipeline is being built in the
U.S.S.R. from Ghazli in Uzbekistan
(source of the gas supply) to the Urals a
distance of over 2,500 miles. Cheap gas
will replace coal which has to be trans¬
ported to the Urals. This is the first time
that pipes of over three feet in diameter
have been used to transport gas.
GUIDE TO MUSIC FILMS: Designed
... to serve as a teaching aid in music
education throughout the world, the first
international catalogue of music films has
been published by Unesco with the aid
of the International Music Council and the
International Society for Music Education.
CLASSROOM NEWSROOMS: One
school out of three in the Federal
Republic of Germany has its own magazine
and two out of three schoolchildren buy
it regularly. Journals edited and published
by schoolchildren now number 570.
U-]^- IN PICTURES: A pictorial
*ly* m record of the men, women,
events and places that have shaped the
story of the United Nations during the past
16 years; has now been presented in
"Pictorial History of the United Nations"
by Jacob A. Rubin (Published by Thom¬
as Yoseloff, New York, London and To¬
ronto; $7.50 and 42/-stg.) .
WESTERN ART FOR THE EAST:
More people in India will be able
to study the art of the West thanks to a
special gallery which the Government has
decided to set up in the recently opened
National Museum in New Delhi. The
Museum will organize guided tours, tem¬
porary exhibitions and lectures and, as its
collections of western art increase, will
become a centre for exchanges with
museums in other Asian countries.
G ERHART HAUPTMANN CENTEN¬
ARY: The Schiller National Mu¬
seum in Marbach (near Stuttgart) has
opened a memorial exhibition to mark the
centenary of the birth of Gerhart Haupt¬
mann, the German playwright and Nobel
prizewinner (See Sept. issue of The
Unesco Courier). The exhibition, com¬
prising some 750 documents photographs,
manuscripts and first editions will remain
open until October 31.
MOVIES IN MUSEUMS: In collabo¬
ration with the International Coun¬
cil of Museums, Unesco is making a world
survey of film projection rooms and of
libraries of art and cultural films attached
to museums with the aim of encouraging
the wider showing of cultural documentary
films. Similar surveys will cover libraries
and universities.
ANEW MINERAL'GAGARENITE':
Scientists from the U.S.S.R. Aca¬
demy of Sciences Institute of Geology and
Mineralogy have discovered a new mineral
which they have named "gagarinite" in
honour of the world's first cosmonaut.
The rare earths which compose more than
50% of gagarinite are elements widely
used in electronics and hard-alloy metal¬
lurgy and they may therefore be used in
the construction of future spaceships.
MrEW EUROPEAN SCHOOL: In
i-^ addition to the "European" schools
already existing in Belgium, Italy and
Luxembourg, one is to be built at
Karlsruhe in the Federal Republic of Ger¬
many. It is primarily intended for chil¬
dren of atomic scientists who work at the
European Institute for Transuranic Ele
ments, now being constructed near
Karlsruhe by EURATOM and the Society
for Nuclear Research.
AID FROM ALPS TO ANDES:
Mountaineers of Valais in Switzer¬
land have generously answered an appeal
to help poverty-stricken Indian mountain-
dwellers in the Ayaviri region of southern
Peru. After hearing, through films and
lectures, about the plight of the Indians,
the Swiss villages have generously contri¬
buted towards a fund which will be used
to open a hospital, maternity clinic and
schools. Nurses and technicians from
Valais will also travel to Peru to help the
Indians.
TfcTEW TAGORE ANTHOLOGY: A 400-
page anthology of writings by Rabin-
dranath Tagore (See The Unesco Courier,
Dec. 1961) has just been published by The
Hyperion-Verlag in Freiburg, Federal Rep¬
ublic of Germany. Arranged by Pro¬
fessor Amiya Chakravarty, who was Ta-
gore's secretary for many years, it includes
travel-journals, poems, plays, essays on
education, art and literary criticism, short
stories and conversations with Einstein,
Romain Rolland, H. G. Wells and other
famous figures.
ASTRONOMICAL TASK: An arithme¬
tic teacher at an elementary school in
Osaka, lapan, recently gave his class the
following task. "Count from one to
100 million by tomorrow." The pupils
began counting aloud, but three hours
after starting the children had only reached
4,000. The children's parents protested to
the school authorities and the teacher
apologised for having imposed such a mam¬
moth task: it would have taken the chil¬
dren four to five years, counting 24 hours
a day to finish this item of homework.
F/ashes...
Each year 3,000,000 people die of tuber¬
culosis and 3,000,000 new cases appear.
Some 15 million people are estimated to
suffer from this disease.
| Forty-three countries have now joined
the UNESCO-sponsored Universal Copyright
Convention under which states grant foreign
works the same protection accorded works
by their own nationals. Panama was the
latest country to join.
| A world plan designed to reduce adult
illiteracy by 50% within ten years has
been drawn up by experts meeting at
UNESCO's H.Q. in Paris. Today an esti¬
mated 700 million people (half of the
world's adult population) cannot read or
write.
| Soviet engineers have drilled a hole
nearly 16,000 feet deep in Azerbaijan for
special studies of the earth's crust. Work
has begun on two more bore-holes which
should reach 23,000 feet, and still deeper
ones are planned.
| Floating robot laboratories are to be used
by the International Ice Patrol in the North
Atlantic to record information on the pres¬
ence of icebergs in the shipping lanes.
Replicas of the Gutenberg Bible, the
masterpiece printed from movable type in
1455, have been printed in the United States
in two-volume sets priced at $750. The
last sale of an original Gutenberg of which
only 47 known copies survive brought over
$500,000.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Current
trends
in scientific
research
RECENT UNESCO PUBLICATIONS
by Piètre AupcT ipcnal nmnilliiii
CURRENT TRENDS IN
SCIENTIFIC
RESEARCH
245 P.; 33/-, 23 NF, $6.75
(CLOTH)
mt
. , ': j catalogue
.¿ " de reproductions en
.', .£ I860 a 1961
.... .1 ,f ..-
:> >' r.- ¡J catalogue of
*j .colour reproductions
: > '^ of paintings
" Vi'l I860 to 1961
¡j !-5"f catalogo de
' reproducciones:'.'
;' en color de pinturas
ra&L
TELEVISION
TEACHING TODAY
247 P. s 20/-, 14 HF, 14.8S
(CLOTH); 15/., 10.51 NF,
{3.00 (PAPER)
laching '" """
^.about the
Wi ^
THE NEWSPAPER.
MAN'S UNITED
NATIONS
21» P. | 11/.. « NF,
S2.25 (CLOTH) j
8/4, 4.25 NF,
51.75 (PAPER)
CATALOGUE OF COLOUR
REPRODUCTIONS
OF PAINTINGS
1860 to 1961
485 P.; 28/6, 20 NF, $6.00
TEACHING ABOUT
THE FILM
120 P.; 20/-. 14 NF
54.00 (CLOTH) |
15/. 10.10 NF,
53.00 (PAPER)
ere to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; rates quoted are
for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO COU¬
RIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. PanuzaT, Press Department, Royal
Afghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Melbourne University Press, 369 Lonsdale Street,
Melbourne, C. I., Victoria. (A 15/-). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C-., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Seh. 60.-). BELGIUM. Office de Publicité S.A.,
16, rte Marq, Brussels. CCP 285.98. NV Standaard-
Boekhandel, Belgielei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (100 FB) and art slides only : Louis de Lannoy,
22, place de Brouckère, Brussels. CCP 3380.00
BURMA. Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road,
Rangoon. (K. 5.50). CANADA. Queen's Printer,
Ottawa, Ont. (S 3.00). CEYLON. The Associated
Newspapers of Ceylon Ltd.. Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Colombo, 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99 Chungking South
Rd., Section I, Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa). CUBA.
Librería Economics, Pia Zsyss 505-7, Apartado 113,
Havana. (2.25 pesos). CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia
Ltd., 30 Va Smeckich, Prague 2. DENMARK. Ejnar
Munksgaard, A/S Tidsskriftafdelingen, 6 Nbrregade,
Köbenhavn K. (D.kr. 12). ETHIOPIA. International
Press Agency. P.O. Box I 20. Addis Ababa. FINLAND.
Akateeminen Kirfsksupps, 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
(Fmk. 540). FRANCE. Librairie de ''Unesco. Place
de Fontenoy. Psrls, 7«. C.C.P. 12598-48. (7 NF.).
GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier, Vertrieb Bahren-
felder-Chaussea 160, Hamburg-Bahrenfeld. CCP.
276650 (DM 8). Other Publications: R. Oldenbourg
Verlag, Rosenheimerstrasse 14 5, Munich. GHANA.
Methodist Book Depot Ltd. Atlantis House. Commercial
St., POB 100, Cape Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. Sea
United Kingdom. GREECE. Librairie H. Kaufímann.
28, rua du Stade, Athens. HONG-KONG. S-ind;.-.
Book Co.. 64. Nathan Road. Ke**1oon. HUNGARY.
Kultura, P.O. Box 149. Budapest, 62. INDIA Orient
Longmans Ltd. Indian Mercantile Chamber, NjcoI P.o»4,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Arenwe, Calcutta 13; Gun.
foundry Road, Hyderabad, I; 36a.Koumt Roa.d. Madras 2 ;
Kanson House. 2411 Aaa! Aii P_oa.d, P.O. Box 386. fie«
Delhi, I ; Sub-Depot: Oxlord Eock & Statíorery Co,
17 Park Street. Calcutta 16. Sciimda Hvji*. fíe« D*i'ha.
Indian National Qc*?*rr rs».cffi for Co-c^eraci-ont wnt-S
Unesco, Ministry of Edjcaccn. fie« C-tr,;» 3. fía- 7)-
INDONESIA. P. 14. Faijw E*j>u. D^ix
Nusantara 22, Djakarta- IRAQ- f-aiciren z.e*s
Bookshop. Baghdad. IRELAND- Tie fítec^j: Press.
2. Wellington Read. Ea. Incur .igt. OaWhi. (1--L
ISRAEL. B!un-3 tenia's r.cc*j»cre!S Ltd. 35. A.leni-f
Road and 48. Na-Vat &**uim,m StreecTei-^*"» flD£ S.5">
JAMAICA. S.UTgK*r"s ï.co« ïjott. il mtrbinr
Street, Kirgscofi- »Ctc« E i wctimrnsil Sb-*-ic*». ícíiiiíLirrgx-
( 10 -). JAPAN. !"«a« Ci. Lit. Í T:i-^iidtotn
Nihonhas*,. P.O. £.=,« 41S Tw-"3 Cenc-siL T;*-*^
(Yen 67C). JOR3AH. Jauejit. S_ í¿ 1 <Za^
Dar 1.1-JC.nitj.ï. Jit *~Ti£. if .Ci 4 1. /t.-nmiuTL.
KENYA. EJ5..A. iconic», ffO. ízx JHi7. I>w> -to..
KOREA- Scream Ilnicimiul Ccmrnirizjiiin 1:ir Oi«uts.
P.O. Ecx Cercill * ï*.-.ul. LC SITUA. Cil«
arid Yai-tf £.zizk3ÏHzn7L \lzjL ? Clisr ZIÍ., y,inr~?*>xb
LUXEMBURG. ILitmi-ii i*Tuil Si-utÀ.. Z2.. Cnn.i-T.ut..
Luxerrtiirr- KJLUt.YA.'m F£SE,T.ATtG»« AJO
SINGAPOP-E. if*t»enil F'-ujiiirsniuiii tlit.. Tm.ei itn^une.
RjveirVilîiry rLü.SiTij-iuirrx IK.AI.TA. îaamn^a slLßru-j
26 VLfTjT«<F'. '* uitca. 1(IIIj-*> Irr.X^'tjm^S. P*iuuniî*
Cccrcarr? Hrrr'i.. IL. ïou-ïiijn Sr-wc, F*:r-:-ll^iins_
MOKHCO. îr-nnrt. ILi}/-u-f. il ïlit «si Ifaitlna.
M.^ca-Cu-ii. </7 M1 A. IK,r»:£]».lA-NOS. I>«..V_
Mjft,iTiiia INiiitcjfi, ILsnij't * .'izr-tirnc., Ir. TTte IHij-tie.
t=TTL t*. *rrVI£KLA.VZS V.-EST HNZIES. CCI
Vtlî Crirx 1 Cr.. I"1««; /*.tcj) I*». A' *'*'¡I«rnn=fc£., Cu-scac
NEVs7 XEJkLA.H3u drwsnrnmrr: JrVnCir g CMce.
V*«,'iii;p3iT^ »rit Ci.-^ir-imimil î^oi3.-tircn. ajcii.a.Td.
V*tlí.7.rt^íT4. Ctra-TTtiir-rt., CunmairtiUIi-'i. NICEPJA
CjTILS. î^CHa-trrit., ? .C. ïis* Il 7 A, Llfíst. (| Il 1 -JV NOR
WAY. For the Unesco Courier only: A.*, ffirvesens Lit
teratur-Tjeneste. Stortingsgt. 4. Oslo, Postboks 115 (kn
I 3.20) Other publications. A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille Grer.se.
7, Oslo. PAKISTAN. The V/est-Pak Publishing Cor.
Ltd.. Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box 374, St-M
Gulberg Industrial CoJony, Lahore. PANAMA.
Cultural Panameña, Arenida 7a. ffo. TU47, Apartado
de Correos 2018, Panama, D.F. (Balboas 3-).
UPP1NES. Philippine Education Co. Inc., 1 104 Castill*.
>os. Q-apo. P.O. Box 620. Manila. POLAND.
" FUCH " vl-V/iksza ffr. 46, Wars»« 10 (Zl. 50).
PORTUGAL. f>as & Andrada Lda. Lirrana Portugal,
Pva do Carr-.o 70. Lisbon. RHODESIA i. NYASA.
LAND. The E^ok Centre. First Street. Salisbury,
So..»-em tr^inix. SWEDEN. For The Urtnto
Co.^r»er: Srer-ska Unescoradet, Vassgaun 15.17, Stock.
*rj.-r, C (Kr. 7.50): oth.er publications A B C £. Fritzes
Kjurj". Ho-rbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
SwmERLAND. Europa Verlag. 5 Plmistrisse
21»^^.-«. Payot, 40, rue du Marchí, Genera. C.C.P.
1-236. « Co-jr,er » only: Georges Losmaz, I, rue des
V,e.»Gre-a.í.ers. Genera- C.C.P. 1-481 I. (Fr. S. 8).
TANGANYIKA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B.
9C3I. Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND. Suks span
Panne. Maison 9. Rajdamnern Avenue. Bangkok. (35
to.«]!. TURKEY. Librairie Hachette. 469 Istiklal
Ct¿:«¡. Eeyoflu. Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda
£«o«.-^p. P.O.. Box 145. Kampala. UNION OF
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Bookstore. Libri
£.-iL'ri.-g. Church Street. Pretoria. For the Unesco
Corf-^r: Central Ne«s Agency. P.O. Box 1033, ]ohan-
irest-vrg. ( 1 0 -). UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC
(EGYPT). La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha,
Cars. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Cf.ce. P.O. Bo>x 569, London, S.E.I. (10/-). UNITED
STATES. Unesco Publications Center, 801 Third
A.er.e. rie« York, 22. N.Y. (5 5.00.) and (except
per-.od.cals): Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad-
*tf. tir- Yot'i. 27, N.Y. U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnija
Kx ga. Mosco«. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslo-
»rs<j Kr^Tga, Terazije 27/11, Belgrade,
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
"i v
Jtttffl
S»
rv
S*>1,
^BW*-*R'
2f% \
i :"
W
1 * -aa-is« '-^s-«BBBBB|
Br ni, b^TB ^ ! .
F'iSbÀï ^Bk
ttW ^B ,jAV r -
^4 ^^^P
f '
i p
NEW FIND IN PRIMITIVE PAINTING
Niko Pirosmanashvili, called Pirosmani, was a Georgian
painter who died 45 years ago in utter obscurity, and his
very place of burial is unknown. Though his name is now
a little known in the Soviet Union, he is totally unfamiliar
to art lovers in other countries. Yet he deserves to
rank among the great masters of modern primitive
painting. Above, "The Prince", detail from "Three Princes
Feasting in a Meadow", which is reproduced on page 23.
]]>
</page>
</document>
