<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="063738eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
'
.
The
_^-"^ A WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
Courier
JULY-AUGUST 1962 (15TH YEAR) - PRICE 2/-STG. (U.K.) - 60 CENTS (U.S.) - 2 NF (FRANCE)
«
FREEDOM FROM
HUNGER
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
LEAN YEARS of famine in Ancient Egypt are recalled
by this emaciated figure carved in stone, from the pyra¬
mid of Ounas, near Gizeh. It symbolizes the hunger
which gripped the land when no flood waters descended
the Nile and harvests failed. (See article on page 15)
Louvre Museum © M. Chuzeville, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Of l H ON TNI WON ID
Contents
No. 7-8
PUBLISHED IN
EIGHT EDITIONS
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
COVER PHOTO
This old man from Ceylon
has been marked by a lifetime
of hard toil, by a struggle to
win from the soil, with only
the most primitive of means,
food for himself and his fel¬
lows. But his dignity and
resolute gaze speak for all
simple men of the land,
expressing the undefeated
spirit of those for whom
poverty has never become a
valid cause for resignation
United Nations
JULY -AUGUST 1962
15TH YEAR
SPECIAL DOUBLE ISSUE
Freedom from Hunger
5 EDITORIAL
7 THE CHALLENGE OF HUNGER
By Dr. B.R. Sen
15 FAMINE, THE GREATEST SCOURGE OF HISTORY
By Georges Zottola
20 HIDDEN HUNGER
The world-wide effects of malnutrition
By Prof. Michel Cépède
24 MAPS OF HUNGER
The daily food ration of every nation
26 FOOD TABOOS AND PREJUDICES
By Dr. Marcel Autret
32 THE FOOD DESTROYERS
Ravages of insects and other pests
By Dr J. Val lega
38 FOOD AND PEOPLE
The global balance sheet of a critical problem
47 THE FIRST VICTORIES
Positive achievements in the fight against hunger
By Dr. Frank W. Parker
54 A WORLD STRATEGY FOR SURPLUS STOCKS
55 THE ANATOMY OF UNDERDEVELOPMENT
The first of a series of articles on problems of economic growth
57 WAKING THE SLEEPING LANDS
A story of U.N. Technical Assistance
By Kathleen McLaughlin
64 FOR FURTHER READING
65 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
66 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
(M.C 62. 1. 17 I A)
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7; France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
René Caloz
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse
Spanish' Edition : Arturo Despouey
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani (Moscow)
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in July and August when
it is bi-monthly (I I issues a year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German
Arabic and Japanese. In the United Kingdom it is distributed by H. M
Stationery Office, P. O. Box 569, London,- S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of Issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier Is indexed monthly in The Readers' Guide to
Periodical Literature published by H. W. Wilton Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates: U. S. $ 3.00; IO/-stg. ; 7.00
New Francs or equivalent. Single copies l/-stg. 30
cents (U.S.) ; 0.70 New Francs.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
WORLD CAMPAIGN
AGAINST
HUNGER
s'a
^F
When hail or rain threatens to ruin a crop, har¬
vester crews in the United States work around
the clock. Combines like those shown here
can do the work of 40 farm hands. Right,
wheat harvesting near Lahore, Pakistan.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The first half of the 20th century has witnessed three major revolutions.
The political revolution has brought self-government to nearly a third
of the world's population and has brought their aspirations for a better life to the
forefront of world attention.
The revolution in communications has broken down the barriers of distance
and language, and the dynamisms of ideas can no longer be contained within the
limits dictated by social privilege or political considerations.
The demographic revolution has imparted to the challenge of poverty and want
a new dimension.
It is against this background that the Freedom from Hunger Campaign was
launched in 1960 by the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations
(FAO). Its main objectives are twofold: first, to create a world-wide awareness
of the problems of hunger and malnutrition which afflict more than half of the
world's population and which, apart from the human suffering and human degra¬
dation that they involve, pose a serious threat to peace and orderly progress ;
and second, to promote a climate of opinion in which solutions to these problems
can be organized both on a national and on an international basis.
In the short time since its launching, the Campaign has already provided a focus
for co-operative endeavour for international organizations, national govern¬
ments, non-governmental organizations and various citizens' groups all over the
world. The 104 member nations attending the biennial FAO conference in Novem¬
ber 1961 paid unanimous tribute to the significance of this Campaign for the future
well-being of the world.
The Freedom from Hunger Campaign attempts to attack the problem of hunger
on a broad front and at all levels of economic and social thought and action ; but
for practical purposes it defines three sectors of operation: (a) information and
education, (b) research, and (c) action.
The information and education programmes will help bring to citizens every¬
where a living awareness of the concrete facts and issues, and provide bases for
deciding what new national and international policies and action programmes
are needed. This effort to create informed and active awareness will rise to a
climax with the World Food Congress to be held under FAO auspices in 1963.
Many international, professional and citizens' groups will hold forums on Cam¬
paign issues this year and in 1963. Many national Campaign committees will also
organize similar discussions. Representatives from all these bodies are expected
to participate in the World Food Congress and help bring into focus policies and
action for plans for the future.
This special issue of The Unesco Courier has been prepared to help people
throughout the world to understand the great issues involved. An attempt has been
made to summarize in popular form the major facts known and the agreed conclu¬
sions of experts up to now. The Editors hope that this special number will provide
study groups in schools and public discussion groups with useful and reliable
material on a critical world problem that is of vital concern to us all.
m
'&**%.
o
<
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
© Sunil Janah, Calcutta
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
THE CHALLENGE OF HUNGER
by Dr. Binay Ranjan Sen
Director-General, FAO
T
J
4 » «tf JbX '
Innumerable weak and hungry
people were driven by the
famine which gripped southern
India in 1945 to wander the
countryside in search of food.
he greatest challenge that faces mankind
today and in the coming decades is the
problem of feeding the growing population of the
world. While the world population is increasing
at an unprecedented rate, food production in the
areas of the world where most people do not have
enough to eat is lagging. Thus, today, mankind
as a whole is not being adequately fed and there
is a population increase of such dimensions that
by the end of this centurypossibly earlier
the number of mouths to be fed will be more
than double.
The implications of this situation are grave in the
extreme; yet, except for a few prophetic voices crying in
the wilderness, it is only in recent years that the leaders
of nations, the philosophers, the thinkers, the scientists
and, later still, the governments have awakened to the
perils of the food and population problem.
Indeed, FAO has tried to bring this dual problem into
focus, through the McDougall Memorial Lectures given
by Professor Arnold Toynbee (1959) and Mr. John D.
Rockefeller (1961), and through the Freedom from Hunger
Campaign, launched by FAO on July 1, 1960.
For several years FAO has pointed out the dangers
inherent in the situation. It has stressed that food
production as a whole, but especially in the underdevelop¬
ed and developing countries, is not increasing fast enough.
The rate of population growth in the developing countries
is well over 2 per cent, while the volume of agricultural
production is increasing at slightly less than 3 per cent
per annum a margin which is clearly precarious. Any
major set-back in agriculture in any part of the world
owing to climatic or other natural factors could quickly
wipe out the gains which have been so painfully won. The
latest statistics reveal the realism of this warning.
Estimates of world agricultural production in 1960-1961
(excluding Mainland China) show an increase of no more
than one per cent over production in the previous season
which is less than the estimated rate of population
growth of 1.6 per cent. Further, if Mainland China Is
included in the world agricultural production figures, the
total production for 1960-1961 would probably be less than
that of 1959-1960 instead of a one per cent increase. And
set-backs due to bad weather in several regions of the
world indicate that the 1961-1962 production may again
be small.
But let us look a little more closely at food production
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
CHALLENGE OF HUNGER (Cont'd)
Millions still go hungry
as seen in recent years. Since the Second World War
there has been a great expansion in the production of
food and agricultural goods but, unfortunately, by far the
largest part of this has taken place in Europe, in North
America and in Oceania.
All these are countries where standards of living are
high and the people generally are well fed and adequately
nourished. In the food deficient regions of Africa, Asia
and Latin America the Increases have so far barely kept
pace with the population increase.
Thus, although the Far East Region, which is the worst
nourished and most populous area in the world, has had
a good harvest for three successive years (excluding
Mainland China), the 1960-1961 food production per head
has only brought consumption levels up to those of pre-
1939.
In other words, improvements in diets which could have
been expected as a result of increases in food production
have, in fact, been largely nullified by population increase.
In Latin America, for example, per capita food production
continues to lag behind pre-war levels. In the Near East,
however, per capita production is now about 10 per cent
above the low levels prevailing in the pre-war period. In
Africa, a rather stationary situation has prevailed with
some ups and downs. These regional figures, of course,
conceal wide differences among individual countries.
A statistical study of the incidence of hunger and
malnutrition was recently made by Dr. P. V. Sukhatme,
director of the Statistics Division, FAO, based on the
international reference scale for calorie requirements and
on the variation in energy expenditure among men of the
reference age group.
Applying the FAO calorie standards as a basis of
comparison for the quantitative aspects of the diet, the
study showed that calorie supplies in Europe, North
America and Oceania are of the order of more than 3,100
calories per capita per day and exceed the requirements
by about 20 per cent.
In the Near East, Africa and Latin America they are
about equal to requirements, amounting to some 2,400.
In the Far East, the supplies are of the order of only
2,050 compared with a calorie requirement of some 2,300.
The supply thus falls short of the requirement by 11
per cent.
This gap is particularly striking when compared with
the total calorie supplies of other regions. Thus, the
shortage in the Far East is of a quantity large enough
to feed the entire population of the Near East and still
have some to spare.
Even for other regions where the overall picture looks
balanced there are wide variations within the region. In
the Near East, for instance, there is apparently enough
food in a group of countries where one-half of the popula¬
tion lives. But the other half lives in a relatively poorer
area. The calorie supplies in this area are only 2,100 to .
2,200 per capita per day. It is therefore justifiable to
conclude that many millions of people in the world still
go hungry at least for a part of their lives.
Thus, a recent study conducted in FAO has shown that
the gap of 11 per cent between the calorie supplies and
the calorie requirements in the Far East is shared by one
fifth to one fourth of the population of the region. Since
this region comprises one half of the total world popula¬
tion it is clear that a conservative estimate of the propor¬
tion of undernourished in the world is between 10 and
15 per cent. In actual numbers this means that between
300 and 500 million go hungry for part of their lives even
in normal times.
i
THE
WORLD'S LANDS
TOTAL
NEGATIVE AREAS
-cold, mountainous,
arid- n
(After Professor Dudley Stan
ACTUALLY CULTIVATED
'/.{ 2 1
AJA4
A./
2V
Á
ACRES PER HEAD
OF POPULATION
Y
POTENTIALLY INADEQUATE
USABLE SOIL
TOO ARID TOO MOUNTAINOUS TOO COLD
.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
EDUCATION
NOT A LUXURY
It has been said that it is too much to expect
countries fully engaged in building their econo¬
mies to make sacrifices for education. " Sacri¬
fice " is a word I cannot accept. There is no
such thing as making "sacrifices" for education,
and the funds set aside for this purpose are
never sacrificed. On the contrary, they are an
enrichment and investment for a nation. Perhaps
the greatest intellectual task of Unesco today
is precisely this to prove that money used for
education is not just money spent, but money
invested. For education cannot be considered
a luxury. It forms part and parcel of the
equipment of every country. And all the mate¬
rial and technological equipment to develop
industry or agriculture would be wasted to a
great extent without prior investment in the
human resources needed to exploit a nation's
material resources.
René MAHEU
Acting Director-General of Unesco
in an interview on the French radio, May, 1962
Differences in protein supplies between countries are
very striking. For example, for the USA the average daily
per capital figures in grammes for total protein and
animal protein for. 1959 were 93 and 65 respectively,
while the corresponding figures for Peru were 52 and 13,
for India 51 and 6 and for Ceylon 46 and 9. There is
very concrete evidence that much ill-health and disease
due to lack of protein are prevalent in many parts of
the world. Protein malnutriton affects mainly young
children aged 1-4 years and in many underdeveloped
countries a high proportion of children suffer from it. It
can safely be concluded that existing supplies of protein,
particularly protein of good quality, are seriously
inadequate in many of the developing countries.
Taking into account the evidence of numerous small-
scale experiments on social feeding with better diets,
reported from different parts of the world, showing
increased working officiency and vigour, and also the
numerous reports on malnutrition, particularly in chil¬
dren, with effects ranging from retardation in growth to
serious diseases and death prevailing in these countries,
the incidence of malnutrition in the less-developed coun¬
tries, relative to the United Kingdom and France, may
be placed at well over 50 per cent. In other words well
over 1,000 million people in the world today suffer from
various degrees of malnutrition.
I have mentioned these figures to show the magnitude
of the food problem as it exists today and to indicate the
even greater problem which will face the world in the
coming years. It is clear that only the most heroic
efforts to increase food production and raise standards of
living in the underdeveloped countries will enable us to
feed tomorrow's six thousand million people.
The possibilities exist to bring about an increase in
food production at a much greater rate than that being
achieved at the present time. What has been done in
Europe, North America and some other parts of the world
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
Un. ted Nations
Refugees receive food and medical care at a dispensary
in South Kasai, Congo, in 1960, when emergency food g
supplies were rushed in under a relief programme to
fight famine caused by political and social upheavals.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
CHALLENGE OF HUNGER (Cont'd)
Wheat yield doubled in Mexico
can also be done in the rP7ions where food deficiencies
now exist.
It is not so long ago, in terms of history, when the
standard of living and levels of nutrition in Europe were
low and famines were recurrent. But through techno¬
logical progress in agriculture and as the result of the
general economic and social development of Europe,
famine conditions are non-existent in these parts of the
world.
This freedom from hunger has been achieved even
though there has been a tenfold or more increase in
population since the times when famines and food short¬
ages were a common occurrence.
On the basis of existing scientific and technical
knowledge, food and agricultural production can be
increased substantially in all the underdeveloped coun¬
tries, a fact that needs hardly to be argued. For instance,
tests have proved that the use of improved varieties of
seed alone could ensure increases in crop yields up to 50
per cent. If such seeds are used along with improved
agricultural practices, more fertilizers, better irrigation,
mechanization, double cropping to mention a few of the
more obvious steps the increase in production of the
great range of food crops could reach several times its
present level in the underdeveloped countries.
This point was made recently by Professor D. L. Linton
of the University of Birmingham in an article in the
journal of the British Association for the Advancement
of Science. In writing on population and food in the
tropical world, he stated: "... what has been done in
Europe can be done in the tropics. It is not desirable,
as some agriculturists thought a generation ago, to
substitute European type crop rotations and cultivation
practices for those of the tropics, but it is very necessary
to find ways of bringing to tropical husbandry the
benefits of scientific knowledge and especially of appro¬
priate fertilizers.
"The average yield of wheat per acre in Pakistan today
is no more than that of England in the fifteenth century
and only a quarter of the modern yield. That it can
certainly be raised is dramatically shown by the way in
which the average wheat yield of Mexico the most
advanced of all the tropical countries has been doubled
in the last ten years. The staple food grain of Mexico,
Primitive farming techni¬
ques are one of the chief
reasons why people in
some countries are un¬
able to win from the soil
all the food it is capable
of producing. Viet-Nam
farmer (right) returning
after the day's work, car¬
ries a rudimentary plough
and harrowall he has
for working the land.
© Pierre Pittet, Geneva
however, is maize not wheat, and here the National Maize
Commission created in 1947 is undertaking an agricultural
revolution. Regional centres supply hybrid maize for
seed, specify cultivation techniques and necessary
fertilizers, and already the national harvest is three times
what it was twenty years ago.
"Even in the lands of intensive rice cultivation the
possibilities of deriving more food from the soil are far
from exhausted. The average yield of rice per acre in
It happened to me too, but I could' not see myself,
only what happened to others: saw their flesh melt
away and their skin sag and sink between their jutting
bones, saw their eyes retreat into their skulls, saw
their ribs curve out from under the skin; and what
withered the young bore doubly hard on the old and
they were emaciated twice over.
But of us all Kuti suffered the most. He had never
been a healthy child; now he was constantly ailing.
At first he asked for rice water and cried because
there was none, but later he gave up asking and
merely cried. Even in his sleep he whimpered, twist-
THE FACE OF FAMINE
ing and turning endlessly, permitting no one to rest.
Ira was gentlest with him, and tirelessly patient, nurs¬
ing him in her skinny arms and giving him most of
what came to her. But more often than not he turned
away, unable to take the rough food we offered, and
then she would hold him against her and give him her
breast, and he would pull at the parched teat and be
soothed, and for a while his thin wailing would die
away.
KAMALA MARKANDAYA
© from "Nectar In a Sieve"
Published by: Putnam and C°, London.; TheJohn Day Co. lnc.,New York,
10
AN EVIL FOR ALL MEN
The hunger which ravages immense areas of the world is an affliction for all men every¬
where; and all peoples, whether famished or well-fed, must fight this evil, for In this
struggle there is no place for neutrality.
ILYA EHRENBURG
Speaking at the "Rencontres Internationales de Geneve", 1960
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
India today is no more than the yield in Japan nine or
ten centuries ago, and only a quarter of the current
Japanese yield. Small wonder that the suggestion has
recently been made that the best form that western aid
to India could take might be the building of 40 or more
regionally-distributed fertilizer plants."
While the application of existing scientific and technical
knowledge to agriculture in the underdeveloped and
developing regions could, as the case of Mexico shows,
transform the food situation, there is a continuing need
of course to carry on fundamental, long-term research.
The key to progress is the enquiring mind, the search
after knowledge, the achievement of new triumphs in
science and technology. It is the thrust of new ideas
and new techniques that is the force of progress. This
is as true of agriculture as of industry, of food growing
as of food processing.
For example the development of the technique of dry
land farming in Canada, the U.S.A., and Australia which
called for the design and manufacture of specialized
machinery, has opened up the possibilities of productive
farming in a wide range of countries throughout the
world. It has given realism to hopes and plans for
producing more food in such semi-arid countries as
Tunisia, Libya, Arabia, Jordan, Saudi. Arabia and many
others elsewhere.
If the underdeveloped countries are to play their full
part in their own development and such self-help is
essential they too will ultimately have to contribute to
research on a scale comparable to that of the technically
advanced countries. Of course, research is already being
carried out in many of the underdeveloped countries but
it is restricted by the limited resources of trained
personnel facilities and equipment.
Successful economic and social development of these
countries will make it possible for them to join in the
costly, complex and highly skilled research programmes
which are characteristic of technically advanced countries.
The main problem at the moment, however, is how to
apply on as broad a scale as possible existing knowledge
and techniques so that food production can be
substantially increased season by season and year by year.
First and foremost, we must realize that agriculture
cannot be dealt with in isolation from the rest of the
economy. It cannot be pulled up by its own boot strings
from the bog of tradition, inefficient practices, prejudices,
illiteracy and poverty. It is so basic and so linked with
all aspects of life in the underdeveloped countries that
any plan or programme to increase productivity must be
an integral part of an overall development scheme if it
is to succeed.
This fact is stark enough when it is realized that 80
per cent or more of the people in these countries live by
some sort of farming mostly subsistence farming, result¬
ing in a life always threatened by serious food shortage,
if not famine. It is among these masses of illiterate
people, numbered in their millions, that hunger or mal¬
nutrition is a life-long affliction.
The prerequisite to any progress is, as I have said, an
overall economic and social development plan and in this
plan agriculture must be the cornerstone. Such a plan
calls for increased investment of capital, materials,
services and manpower. While a large part of the capital
needed must come from within the country, the various
international agencies or countries in a position to offer
bilateral assistance or private commercial enterprise must
assist to the extent possible and in a growing measure.
Any long-term plan to increase agricultural production
involves many sectors of national life and at various
levels. For instance, adequate government administrative
and extension services must be organized; training and
instruction in improved techniques must be provided if
the introduction of improved tools and equipment is to be
effective; facilities must be made available for the
development of improved varieties of seed, the use of
more and better fertilizers and for the development of
' irrigation schemes and so on.
To take action along any of these lines calls for capital
investment of one kind or another and for personnel
training schemes. This latter requirement is of front rank 11
CONT'D ON PAGE 14
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
POLYGON OF THIRST & HUNGER
In northeastern Brazil are some 300,000 square
miles of parched land where 23 million people
live in constant fear of the periodical droughts
and resulting famines which have given the area
the name of "'polygon of thirst and hunger." Some
dates have been burned into the memory of these
people: 1877, 1899, 1915, 1957. Worse than the
dearth of rainfall is its irregularity. When, as
sometimes happens, rains fail to materialize for
two orthree years running, disaster strikes. Water
has to be brought from afar and measured out
parsimoniously (left). Herds are wiped out and
entire towns go hungry. Below, a farmer contem¬
plates the sun-bleached bones of his cattle.
Droughts set off a mass exodus of peopie from
the Polygon (right), seeking work on the plan¬
tations and in the factories in southern Brazil.
*-
*^*ij -^.
*¿ -'- **»
...1 ' Pr-
->'.'. ". 'y-.. ©***. >.-' ir
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
*<tJtí>
" ' . > . ». - Ri» - .
. * r v.- -T
~ ... * ...»'* . . -. -..' ."<
-"* £- f.- ' ' .*
. * .
. T't -
13
Photos © O Cruzeiro and Mánchete, Rio de Janeiro
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
CHALLENGE OF HUNGER (Cont'd)
A literate farmer is a better farmer
14
importance. Even with capital, equipment and facilities
available, little effective progress will be made without
trained personnel. It is the lack of such personnel that
characterizes underdeveloped countries; therefore, any
development plan must take into account the need for
training at all levels, particularly, in the first instance,
at practical workaday levels.
One of the most valuable of the services provided by
FAO and other international organizations has been, and
remains, technical training programmes. We have carried
out such training in many ways, especially through
working parties, seminars and training centres. In most
cases these have been essentially practical in instruction.
For instance, some years ago FAO was concerned with
the Government of India in setting up training centres to
teach illiterate fishermen how to operate and maintain
outboard engines, to handle Improved types of fishing gear
and equipment, and to navigate by compass and chart.
In a six months course, 80 per cent of which was practical
demonstration, these fishermen were taught to sail to
and from fishing grounds far out of sight of land and
far beyond the near shore grounds which they had always
fished in catamarans and other local craft. The first two
of these training centres were so successful that a number
of others have been opened up in India.
Instruction in improved techniques, imparting the
practical "know how," is the key to all our technical
assistance work. Every expert we send into the field has
local assistants to work with him. In this way, personnel
are trained while the job is being done, with the object of
their being able to carry on the work when the expert
leaves the country.
Any plan for the economic development of a country
must take into account sociological factors, and this is
particularly true in the agricultural sector. Farmers and
rural dwellers are proverbially conservative people, having
very little margin of income to undertake application of
new ideas and new techniques, deeply rooted in traditional
ways life and embedded in a social structure which resists
change and experiment.
WE ARE ALL
EQUALLY
RESPONSIBLE
...We should like to express Our sincere appre¬
ciation for the highly beneficial work which the
United Nations Food and Agriculture Organi¬
zation is undertaking to establish fruitful
accord among nations, to promote the moderni¬
zation of agriculture especially in countries in
the process of development, to alleviate the
sufferings of hunger-stricken peoples.
...Mindful of Our role of universal Father, We
feel obliged solemnly to stress what We have
in another connexion stated: "We are all equally
responsible for the undernourished peoples...
Therefore, it is necessary to educate one's
conscience to the sense of responsibility which
weighs upon each and everyone, especially
upon those who are more blessed with this
world's goods."
POPE JOHN XXIII
Encyclical Letter "Mater et Magistra", May 15, 1961
As I said earlier, a great majority of them in the
underdeveloped and developing countries are subsistence
farmers who do not own the patches of land they till and
are often in debt. As a result, the poor harvests they
reap have to be divided, one part to pay off their debts
or the interest on them and the other part to live on.
Furthermore, even where such farmers are owners of the
land, inheritance has resulted in fragmentation of
holdings to a point where the area worked is so small
that the fanner cannot produce enough food to feed
himself and his family throughout the year.
It is obvious that in the circumstances, an essential
condition for the development of agriculture is land
reform. This is a very complex, intricate and politically
difficult question, and one which can only be tackled
effectively by the government of the country concerned.
We, in FAO, have been closely concerned with these
problems of agrarian reform for many years. Many
governments have asked for our advice, and have acted
upon it. Even so, the problem remains acute and is of
such a nature as to hold back progress. The mere passage
of land reform bills is not enough. These must be made
effective operationally at all levels, from the government
department down to the farmer. Such reform measures
are but a start towards tackling the problem.
PROBABLY the only way to overcome the obstacles
presented by traditions and prejudices, and
the established patterns of life in rural communities, is
through education in its broadest sense. Obviously, any
effort to introduce new ideas, even in the shape of a
useful tool, must be done with sympathy and under¬
standing, if it is to be accepted. And communicating new
ideas and techniques is very difficult if only the spoken
word can be used, and that just to a limited extent.
Even the most elementary education, that of learning
to read and write, smooths the path for people who are
trying to introduce new techniques and equipment. It is
axiomatic that a literate farmer has a much better
chance of understanding a reform and development
programme and grasping the opportunities offered than
does one who can only rely on his memory to understand
and make use of what he has been told.
Thus, the progress of any development plan for
agriculture depends to a large extent on overcoming the
obstacle of illiteracy. And while practical demonstrations
will enable the adults to understand and adopt new
techniques, children and the younger generation need to
be educated. They learn quickly and it is on them that
the pace of future progress depends.
From what I have said it is quite clear that no national
or international programme of assistance on the present-
day scale is big enough to encompass all that should be
done. The problem is too vast to be left entirely to
governmental action.
For many years I have lived with this problem and when
I became Director-General of FAO in 1956 I became more
and more conscious of the fact that all we had done so
far through international and bilateral aid was insuffi¬
cient. I felt that the problem could only be tackled
effectively if people everywhere in the world became fully
conscious of its nature and magnitude. It was with these
ideas in mind that I proposed the "Freedom from Hunger
Campaign" so that all men and women and children in
all countries could join in the struggle to eliminate
hunger.
Clearly we cannot hope to achieve victory in a few
years, so this is a struggle which must go on for a genera¬
tion, even several generations. In order to make that
possible it is necessary that people in all countries should
be fully informed as to the nature of the task and of its
significance to the future well-being of people everywhere.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Their limbs and bodies wasted by starvation, these men
were found prostrate in the streets of Calcutta. Here
they are being cared for by a charitable organization
which has already saved the lives of thousands of people.
FAMINE
THE
GREATEST
SCOURGE
OF HISTORY
T
by Georges Zottola
he world's earliest record of hunger is a stone.
On a stele discovered in a tomb near the First
Cataract of the Nile, a Pharoah of Egypt inscribed in
granite his cry of despair about the "Lean Years" of
famine ravaging his kingdom. Like a warning to
posterity, the stele of famine reads:
"From my throne I grieve over this calamity. During
my reign the Nile has not been in flood for seven years.
Corn is scarce and food is lacking. Men have become
thieves and pillage their neighbours. Those who would
run cannot even walk. Children cry and the young falter
and stagger like old people. Their legs drag or give way
under them. Their spirits are broken. The council
chamber of the nobles is deserted. The food bins are
broken open and empty. It is the end of everything."
Ancient art has bequeathed to us images of hunting and
agriculture, music and dance, but it has rarely given a
face to hunger. No effort was needed to evoke its
features. Down through the ages at the height of terrible 15
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
FAMINE (Cont'd)
A haunting picture of death and desolation
epidemics, murderous wars and major disasters it has
always been a close companion to man.
Hunger also haunts the pages of the Bible. Like a
slow-moving, distant wraith it glides implacably across
the pages of Genesis, Exodus and the Book of Kings. The
prophet Joel bewailed its appearance in the wake of
hordes of locusts in these words:
"Lament like a virgin girded with sackcloth for the
husband of her youth... Alas for the day... The seed is
rotten under their clods, the garners are laid desolate
and the barns are broken down... How do the beasts
groan!... Oh Lord, to thee will I cry."
The "daughter of the night," as the Greek poet, Hesiod,
called it, figures in all the great events of Antiquity. In
the year 440 B.C. the Plebians of Rome, crazed by hunger,
threw themselves in multitudes into the Tiber. Ancient
Rome had its Lactaria Columna. At the foot of this
monument, women, recalling the legend ' of the female
wolf which succoured Romulus and Remus, abandoned the
newly-born children they could no longer feed.
The spectral shape of hunger dominates the entire
Middle Ages. It drove Attila and his hordes towards the
south. It went its furtive way throughout the Hundred
Years War. Sometimes, as in 879, 1016 and 1162 A.D. it
held the whole of Europe in its grip. People were driven
to eating earth mixed with a little flour and baked as
a loaf. Animals were bled and men, like vampires,
sucked their blood.
In 1190 during the Crusades, beans were sold one by
one. The story is told of some crusaders at the siege ot
St. Jean d'Acre who paid a denier (a French coin,
originally of silver) for 13 beans. On their return to
camp they discovered that one of the beans had a weevil
in it and rushed back to the food merchant to change it
for a good one.
Thirteen times in the 16th century and eleven times in
the following century, famine gripped France. Writing
to Louis XIV, the great French philosopher, François de
Fenelon, declared: "From one end to the other, France
resembles a huge hospital, desolate and without food."
Hunger was one of the causes of the French Revolution.
In 1788, its baleful countenance was seen in the heart of
Paris itself, a grim omen of the bloodshed to follow.
Recording the ebb and flow and analyzing the ravages
of hunger in France during the second half of the 18th
century, Hippolyte Taine, the 19th-century essayist and
philosopher, notes: "The Bishop of Chartres found that
people were eating grass like sheep, and dying like flies."
Towards the end of the same century, a strange
comparison was drawn between famine and plague by a
pastor of Zurich, J.H. Waser. He concluded that plague
was infinitely preferable to famine.
"The loss of life through plague," he declared, "can be
made good in a matter of ten years or so, but the devasta¬
tions of famine have far more serious consequences...
Those who survive it do not fully recover until years later.
Those who come safely through an epidemic, however, are
INVOCATIONS
TO THE GODS
Since the Neolithic Age. when man turned from
being a nomadic hunter to become a farmer,
wheat, rice and corn have become the basic
foods of the majority of the world's peoples.
Thus, from time immemorial the cycle of winning
these foods from the soil has had religious and
ritualistic associations, reflecting man's hope for
good harvests and his fear of famine. One belief
of ancient Egypt visualized an afterlife in a place
where harvests were always plentiful. One of the
16
© Musis Guimet, Paris
RICE : The Japanese god of rice and of happiness.
Bulloi
WHEAT : Fragment of Egyptian tomb painting.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
carefree and in good fettle.. Those who have succumbed
have left them a new place to occupy, as well as inheritan¬
ces, and thus all those who have a mind to get married
can now do so."
The historian, Cornelius Walford, agreed when he
wrote: "The losses in human life caused by hunger are
far greater than all the wars and epidemics put together."
The first deadly blow against hunger was struck by
Western Europe at the start of the 19th century the
century of hope. The discovery and development of
machinery uprooted agriculture from its age-long
lethargy. On the oceans, the majestic but archaic sailing
vessels were displaced by aggressive and bustling
steamships which were to supply the Old Continent with
more foodstuffs than it had ever before possessed.
Floored, but not yet beaten, hunger struck once more,
this time in Ireland in 1846 where it killed one million
people and drove another million to emigrate. Then it
retreated to Eastern Europe and the Far East where, as
if seeking its revenge, it produced its greatest ravages of
all times.
One hundred million Chinese died of hunger in the 19th
century. "No social factor anywhere in the world," noted
Josué de Castro, "has ever made its impact on human
conduct with a more despotic power than the collective
hunger of the lands of the Far East. When a Chinese met
a friend, he no longer said "Good-day to you." His first
words of greeting were: "Have you eaten?"
The 19th century was also the era of India's most
terrible famines. In 1876 alone, hunger wiped out five
million people and in the last years of the century twenty
million Indians fell victim to famine.
Nineteenth-century Russia traversed 40 years of famine.
In 1891, the newspaper, Russkie Viedomosti, reported:
"From morning till evening, hungry people wander from
ancient Japanese gods of happiness was also the
god of cereals, pictured astride sacks of rice.
In pre-Columbian America, the Zapotee Indians
made funerary urns in the form of gods associated
with agriculture and in particular the maize god.
house to house begging for something to eat. But they
return home empty-handed for no one gives anything
away at all."
"Traders went the rounds of villages," reported Hin,
"and taking advantage of the famished people, bought
up anything they could lay their hands on for next to
nothing. Even the bonnets and shawls of old women were
pulled out of the family chests and sold. Women sold
their hair. A good tress was worth two roubles."
The moujiks survived this hecatomb through a form of
"hibernation."
"The peasants practise a kind of artificial winter sleep
which they call Ijoschka. There is no mistaking its
resemblance to the ways of hibernating animals. This
collective sleep can go on for as much as four or five
months and arrangements are made to ensure its dura¬
tion, not just in the case of a few people, but for entire
villages. People simply stay in bed, move as little as
possible, and only do what is absolutely essential. They
only get up to refuel the fire warming the house."
H unger, the issue of natural disasters, did not
disappear with the arrival of the 20th century.
As an offspring of war, it struck in another guise with
even greater fury. Between 1940-1945, from France to
Greece and from Holland to Poland and Russia, it crush¬
ed Europe beneath its heel.
Only the resources of the black market in food saved
millions of French people from conditions like those found
in the "death camps." In Belgium, the marks of hunger
were written in faces and bodies swollen by the oedema of
malnutrition. In the Netherlands, during the terrible"
winter of 1944-1945, so many people died that there was
finally no wood left to make coffins and the bodies had
to be stacked in long rows in the churches. The system
of exterminating Jewish people by starvation during the
last war, as de Castro has emphasized, "caused dozens of
times more deaths than the gas chambers and execution
squads."
The writer, Boris Shub, has drawn up a striking table of
"famine statistics": "In 1941, nearly 50,000 Jews one-
tenth of the population died in the Warsaw Ghetto. By
1942 the death rate of Jews in Vienna was ten times that
of before the War."
But history's most recent great holocaust was not
confined to Europe. In 1942-1943 famine gripped Calcutta
with such intensity that people died by the thousands
and the number of corpses strewn in the streets was so
great that their disposal became a critical problem.
In 1945, the physiological processes of acute malnutri¬
tion were largely unknown. The "daughter of the night"
had always been a subject as taboo as, say, sexual prob¬
lems. The living-corpses of Bergen-Belsen were free, but
still went on dying "because," in the words of a leading
British specialist, the late Sir Jack Drummond, "we had
no idea how to revive these dying victims of hunger."
Gorged with food, and given injection after injection,
the moribund victims simply died twice as quickly. The
most effective antidote against malnutrition, it was
quickly found, is skim milk given in small quantities.
One of the first scientists to study the question of food
in times of famine was Parmentier.
"I know that those who live amid plenty," he wrote
in 1781, "cannot imagine that their fellow citizens are
deprived of the most basic necessities, nor could they
believe that most of the plants which I shall name are
often eaten uncooked."
The "Father of the Potato," as Parmentier has been
called, then listed thirty-four foodstuffs for times of
famine, all of them the roots of wild plants: Aristolochia
rotunda, Astragalus scandens, Cuoumis sylvestris, Arum
dracunculis, etc.
For lack of anything better, people have eaten the roots
named by Parmentier and also clover, ferns, acorns, nettle
leaves, and the sweepings of grinding mills. Clover, in
17
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
© Musée de l'Homme, Paris
MAIZE : A Zapotee funerary urn from Mexico.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
FAMINE (Cont'd)
Driven to eating
straw and wood
particular, has saved many millions of starving people.
A Polish botanist, Doctor A. Maurizio, has published a
learned work on famine foods of the past. He tells us
that roots and wild plants were not the only "hunger-
breakers" used. People have eaten tree-bark or, more
precisely, a bread made with the bark of pine, elm, birch
and beech.
But eating "bark bread" can be dangerous. A Russian
traveller, J. Beckmann, describing a famine that occurred
in 1769, reported that children became weaker more
quickly than adults on this diet. Yet even adults, after
eating the bread for several days, developed such badly
swollen feet that they could no longer walk. Bark bread
is by no means the most extreme remedy for hunger.
Famine-stricken people have used especially in northern
Europe flour wood and shavings.
Doctor Maurizio explains how it was made. "First wood
was dried in the sun or in an oven. Repeated heating
makes the wood easier to grind and more digestible.
Cooked with yeast added, it produces bread which, it is
said, tastes better than that made with clover." The
trees used for making such wood bread were the maple,
the poplar, the lime, the birch and the elm.
Chopped up and ground straw was also resorted to in
the past. During a famine which occurred in Sweden in
1813 people actually ate the straw from their mattresses.
Dr. Maurizio tells us that "straw flour was mixed with
rye flour and bonemeal." In western Gotland, even dried
cow-dung was reportedly used.
Grim facts like these not only belong to eras long past;
they are also close to our own times. Famine still cleaves
its deadly way amid the great political and social
upheavals of our day, as in India and Pakistan between
1946 and 1948, when the partition of the two countries
caused the biggest migration in history, and nearly 12
million refugees flowed between the two countries. It
struck again during the recent events in the Congo.
Catastrophes of nature, like the great drought from 1951
to 1953 in Brazil's "Polygon of Drought," also continue to
claim innumerable victims.
A History of Hunger would be the greatest book on world
history ever written.
Based on a chapter from "La Faim, La Soif et Les
Hommes" (Hunger, Thirst & Men) by Georges Zottola,
published by Hachette, Paris, 1960.
Ou Maij/rr-os Le par mottuf, eft itf
Tbutrr, a Große- ruifttte mj/, timt f
© Bulloz.
THIN AS RAKES
& FAT AS HOGS
In the 1 6th cent. Pieter Breughel
the Elder pictured with mordant
skill an age-old human injustice
in these engravings of the lean and
hungry and the fat and overfed.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
..' : .
HUMILIATIO
"The one thing to which a man can never become
inured is humiliation. Hunger becomes unbearable
when it is linked in men's minds with humiliation. If,
in recent years, hunger has become a dangerously
explosive problem, it is because men who look on it
as a form of humiliation have become ever more
numerous. Thus, the basic question we must ask
ourselves is not why, in the mid-twentieth century,
hunger is now the central problem of our planet, but,
more exactly, why at this time hundreds of millions
of people have come to think of their hunger as an
intolerable humiliation.
TIBOR MENDE
Speaking at the " Rencontres Internationales de Genève ", 1960.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
HIDDEN HUNGER
The term malnutrition can be defined as the result of a diet which does
not provide the right kind of food for good health, for the normal deve¬
lopment of children and adolescents, nor for normal activity at allages of
life, The chief form of malnutrition is under-nutrition which is a defi¬
ciency of the vital nutrients in the food one eats. Malnutrition resulting
from eating too much of these nutrients is also known to exist but it is
extremely rare and does not even remotely have the social significance
of hunger, that is, under-nutrition.
by Prof. Michel Cépède
National Agronomy Institute, Paris
Tío maintain that two persons out of three in
the world still suffer from hunger, as was once
done in the past and is still done by a number of people,
including myself, it is necessary to abandon the simple
notion that the level of food consumption is measured
merely by the number of calories present in the daily
food eaten by each person.
When at the end of the 18th century Lavoisier showed
the analogy that existed between living matter and
combustion, he pioneered the idea that food was the
body's combustion agent or fuel and introduced quanti¬
tative analysis into the study of what happens to the
food we eat. His successors were thus able to calculate
the number of calories required by the human body to
sustain ' life.
Man's minimum calorie needs are very strictly defined.
Specialists of the subject agree (with variations of some
100 calories) that 2,200 calories are the minimum require¬
ment for the average adult at rest, depending on height,
weight, etc. With this as a basis, even the most optimistic
authorities admit that 10 to 15 per cent of the world's
population (excluding mainland China) is undernourished.
The first survey of the world food situation undertaken
between the years 1934 and 1938, the results of which
were published by FAO in 1946, revealed that average
daily calorie consumption was less than 2,250 in countries
totalling more than half the world's population, between
2,250 and 2,750 calories for one-sixth of the earth's
inhabitants, and over 2,750 calories for only a little less
than one-third of the population of our planet.
The more optimistic figures of 10 to 15 per cent cited
above were arrived at long after the first world food
survey, but can be accounted for by the fact that first,
mainland China is no longer included in United
Nations statistics, and second, food needs calculated on
the amount eaten (intake) are often confused with the
food actually available (bought at the retail level). At
the indispensable minimum level of calorie needs, the
difference is in the order of 100 calories, a figure which
can hardly be disregarded.
In some cases economists have even based their
calculations on gross food production figures, thereby
ignoring food losses as well as those food products not
consumed but used for other purposes. Statements of the
kind made in The World's Food, published in 1954 by
M.K. Bennett who determined dietary needs in terms of
20 "calorific equivalents in cereals" must be judged in the
light of these remarks if we are to avoid the same hasty
conclusions that led the English economist Colin Clark
to deny the very existence of undernourishment and hence
hunger itself.
Moreover, calculations based on the average availability
of food actually conceal an extremely important aspect
of the problem, since even in countries where enough food
is available there are those who have more and
consequently others (usually more numerous) who do not
have enough. The late John D. Black of Harvard
University once estimated that even in the United States
25 per cent of the population was overfed, 42 per cent well
fed, and 33 per cent underfed.
With these observations in mind, I do not hesitate to
state that for the total population of the earth more
than one-third and no doubt nearly one-half of mankind
suffers from under-nutrition due to lack of calories, that
is, hunger in the strictest sense of the word.
Unfortunately, calorie deficiency is not the only form
of undernourishment. In cases where attempts were
made in the past to feed populations cheaply on a diet
limited to low-priced calories, chiefly in the form of cereals
and especially roots and tubers i.e. foods with a high
starch content (such as manioc, taro, plantains, yams and
potatoes) it was soon discovered that serious illnesses
inevitably resulted. Josué de Castro has coined the
appropriate phrase "specific hunger" for such ailments.
To operate the human machine, fuels (in other words
calories) are not enough. Many chemical nutrients used
up by the body have to be replaced, and these must come
from the food we eat. Such nutrients have to be supplied
the body in particular forms, for as the great French
nutritionist André Mayer put it some time before his
death, "man is an imperfect chemist."
Certain plants are able to convert minerals into food,
and there are animals which can derive essential vitamins
and certain proteins from other forms of food. Man's
chemistry, however, is even more imperfect than that of
many animals. Consequently our bodies require more
than just a certain number of calories to save us from
malnutrition or "specific hunger."
The first specific hungers man came to know about were
the protein deficiencies (or at least a number of them),
mineral deficiencies such as calcium and phosphorous,
and above all the vitamin deficiencies. Extreme cases of
such deficiencies have been studied in spectacular diseases
like scurvy, pellagra, beri-beri and rickets and have been
found to vanish almost miraculously when diets were
modified. And it is well-known how vitamin-conscious
people were in the first quarter of the present century.
Only in more recent years has it been discovered that
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
There is no unanimity even among experts as to the propor¬
tion of the world's people who suffer from hunger since there
is no internationally accepted yardstick for measuring
"hunger". A number of years ago FAO advanced the figure
of two-thirds of humanity but has since lowered this as
Dr. Sen's article on page 7 indicates. Professeur Cépède, of the
FAO Council and a world authority on nutrition, here explains
why, in his opinion, the first FAO figure still holds true.
Pierre Plttet, Geneva The history of China is a history of hunger. Over a period of 2,000 years it has experienced no
less than 1,829 greatfamines. Today most of Asia's people are still undernourished and their health
and working ability impaired by malnutritionthe "hidden hunger" caused by diet déficiences.
long before these diseases actually appear specific under¬
nutrition saps health and working capacity to such an
extent that the whole life of the individual suffering from
specific hunger is seriously impaired.
What is true for the average adult applies with even
greater force to those who must not only feed their bodies
but need extra nourishment to promote growth. Expectant
and nursing mothers, children and adolescents are
particularly vulnerable to the various forms of specific
hunger.
As early as 1936, Lord Boyd Orr in his book Food, Health
and Income, which still stands as the first authoritative
work on the economics of food, used the example of Great
Britain to show that only the expensive foods made it
possible to avoid the specific hungers and their conse¬
quences.
We may well ask therefore if specific hunger is merely
a qualitative problem, or to put it slightly differently, if
all one has to do to ensure that mankind is well fed is
to inform people what types of food should go into every
person's daily diet of say 2,500 calories. As Lord Boyd Orr
has pointed out, such a diet is more expensive and it is
precisely the poor sections of society and the impoverish¬
ed nations more than the others who are the real victims
of specific hunger.
Agronomists have added a new factor whereby the
specific hungers can be re-appraised globally just as
caloric under-nutrition was re-calculated. For if the food
products which are essential to a proper diet are sold at
a higher price than those which simply provide energy
(calories) then it is obvious that the former mean far
more in terms of "agricultural production" than the
latter.
One of the most serious of the specific hungers, affecting
chiefly the more vulnerable sections of the world's popula¬
tion, can be overcome only by certain protein products
such as milk, eggs, meat and fish. Most of these are not
obtained directly from agriculture since each acre of land
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
HIDDEN HUNGER (Cont'd)
THE SAME CHILD
AFTER 10 MONTHS
When Molok, a little Iranian girl
four months old, was brought
into a foundling home in Teheran,
she weighed less than seven
pounds (left). A pitiful sight,
with her skinny limbs and swollen
belly, she was in an advanced
stage of malnutrition. Ten months
later (right) thanks to proper food,
careful nursing and hygienic condi¬
tions she had fully recovered and
was nine pounds heavier. The
home where Molok was cared for
was started by a British woman
specialist sent to Iran by FAO to
advise on school feeding pro¬
grammes. Over a period of 18
months it took in 132 children and
managed to save the lives of 100.
But for every child as lucky as
Molok, there are also countless
thousands who do not survive.
Public Health Dept., Iran
The earth is not overpopulated-it can feed 1 0 times the present number
must first furnish the required vegetation which in turn
is consumed by the animals that provide us with the
protein food. The fact is, however, that the yield of such
a process is extremely low, so that one calorie of grass
or grain does not produce one calorie of milk or meat.
The first world survey proposed as a conservative co¬
efficient the consumption of seven initial (or vegetable)
calories for the production of one calorie of animal prod¬
uct. Since then we have used this ratio which offers a
satisfactory scale, far superior at any rate to the ones
which calculate food level in terms of final calories
consumed, or of calorific equivalents in cereals which
amounts to the same thing (1).
On this basis we can indicate that if the daily diet of
an undernourished person is made up for instance of
1,700 calories of plant foods and 100 calories of animal
products, this represents 1,700 + (100 x 7) 2,400 "initial
calories." Similarly, If a properly nourished person con¬
sumes 2,000 calories of plant foods and 1,200 of animal
products daily, this represents 2,000 + (1,200 X 7) = 10,400
"initial calories". In terms of agricultural production
the second diet is 4.5 times greater than the first although
in "calorific equivalents" it is only 1.75 times greater.
Thus while we have pointed out that it is incorrect
to assume that a diet composed of an adequate number
of calories is a guarantee of proper nourishment, we can
now state that a diet composed of an adequate number
of "vegetable or initial calories" does meet man's
"specific" needs as a general rule. But of course the
figure of 2,200 "intake" calories is no longer applicable as
the minimum requirement when speaking of initial cal¬
ories; the true figure ls more like 6,000 initial calories for
22
(1) M Cépède and M. Lengelle, "Economie alimentaire du
globe" (1953).
an average person, allowing for the special needs of chil¬
dren, adolescents and expectant and nursing mothers.
In fact as early as 1953 we estimated that the per capita
daily diet for Egypt and France ought to be 5,850 and
5,804 "initial" calories respectively.
The first world food survey showed that the average
level of food consumption in Egypt was 2,100 "final" cal¬
ories and 3,000 "initial" calories. The figures given for
France for both types of calorie calculations were 3,012
and 6,160. A diet of 5,800 vegetable calories would corres¬
pond to a diet of 2,200 calories of which 600 came from
animal protein products.
On the basis of these calculations we easily arrive once
again at the figure that the nutritionists of FAO and
particularly Lord Boyd Orr advanced In 1946 to the effect
that two persons out of three suffer from hunger, that is,
from malnutrition through caloric under-nutrition and/or
specific under-nutrition. This figure was reached by a
series of estimations based on an analysis of the first
world food survey and not as a result of a simple mathe¬
matical error as M. K. Bennett believed in 1954 and Colin
Clark and many others still maintain.
A diet made up almost exclusively of plant foods, despite
the statement that it satisfies human needs expressed in
terms of "calorific equivalents in cereals" not only is
"monotonous and uniform" but cannot possibly meet "the
physiological requirements of the human body." And
those persons whose diet consists only of such food "truly
suffer from hunger." Both Lord Boyd Orr and Josué
de Castro are nutritionists and food physiologists, and
their affirmations were based not merely on statistics but
on factors visible to anyone who observes how man lives.
No doubt tomorrow may see new "advances" made by
science so that some of the nutrients now found only in
animal products may one day be available, perhaps even
more cheaply, in cereal or synthetic foods. A number of
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
results have already been achieved with food preparations
for certain animals such as pigs whose nutritional phy¬
siology does not differ markedly from man's, and the
experiments being carried out look promising.
But the many catastrophic attempts to feed people
cheaply which have marked the development of the
science of nutrition since the time of Lavoisier should
incline us to caution. Yet despite these failures there is
room for hope.
It is one thing, however, to have faith in the progress
of science and technology and quite another to claim that
mankind already has enough to eat.
And it is quite another thing too to pretend that the
earth is now overpopulated or that it will become so when
our planet contains six to ten thousand million people.
The fact that our present world population of 3,000 mil¬
lion does not get enough to eat, that two persons out of
three live face to face with hunger, does not mean that
we are incapable of feeding twice this number properly
and adequately. Colin Clark has written : "If we con¬
sider a diet based on cereals we could have a total popu¬
lation of 90,000 million."
Let us assume that his calculations are correct (2) and
merely rectify the basic error taken from M. K. Bennett
by adding animal products to the requisite diet. This
reduces his figure of 90,000 million people to about
35,000 million who could be properly fed on the basis of
our present level of scientific knowledge. And this figure
is by no means a maximum, especially if we look ahead
to the future.
But this is precisely the scandalous situation of our
time and one which it is useless to seek to disguise: that
in a world capable of properly feeding 35,000 million
human beings and containing only 3,000 million, at least
2,000 million suffer from hunger.
Particularly since one of the consequences of mal¬
nutrition is malnutrition itself. For malnutrition ruins
man's health and Impairs his ability to work. Proper food
is not simply a goal of, but a factor in, economic develop¬
ment (3). As Albert Sarraut has rightly pointed out, in
too many countries the inhabitants "are undernourished
because they do not work and they do not work because
they are undernourished."
It is not possible here to refer to the many lengthy
studies which show the relationship which exists between
food, health and working productivity. Let me simply
recall one experiment carried out in Costa Rica during
the construction of the first Pan American Highway.
The men working on the highway had a very low output
when their diet consisted chiefly of sugar cane which
gave them the requisite calories intake. When this diet
was changed and they were properly fed, it was found
that their output improved to such an extent that it
equalled the standards of workmen in the temperate cli¬
mates of Western countries (4).
This experiment was so spectacular in its results that
the Costa Rlcan section of the Pan American Highway
has come to be known as "The Road That Food Built."
But the food needs of adults or even workmen are not
our most urgent problem today. The malnutrition of
expectant and nursing mothers, of children and adoles¬
cents, has far more serious consequences on a nation's
health and the capacity to feed its inhabitants and
achieve economic development.
Much has been said and written about the rise
in the expectancy of life in modern times, but
the individual who has already reached adulthood does
not have a much higher life expectancy whether he is
well fed or poorly fed. For although diet does condition
the adult's working productivity it is no longer the over¬
riding factor of adult health, provided of course that the
body has the strict caloric minimum required of living.
The situation is totally different, however, as regards
the body of a growing child or an expectant mother.
The eminent French pediatrician, Professor Robert Debré,
has pointed out that the sudden deficiency of animal pro¬
tein which strikes children in the undernourished coun¬
tries when they cease to be breast fed and are deprived of
their mother's milk, is without a doubt the most serious
of all the diseases which afflict mankind.
This disease of malnutrition, the acutest forms of which
have all been given the common name "kwashiorkor",
often attacks eight children out of ten and is responsible
for the higher death rate observed in these countries.
But above all it cripples the children who manage to
survive, and for the rest of their lives (which may be
quite long) they remain physically impaired and unable
to provide the necessary food either for themselves or
their family.
To feed the adults of today and especially the men and
women of tomorrow, means putting mankind in condition
to feed itself better, it means breaking the vicious cycle
referred to by A. Sarraut; it means launching a process
of development so that tomorrow, if we so will it, we
shall no longer have two persons out of three suffering
from hunger as we do today even if in the meantime the
population of the earth does double or even multiplies
ten times.
It is not by denying the tragic realities of today that
mankind will be deprived of its oldest enemy, hunger, but
by facing up to these realities squarely and honestly and
recognizing that they are the scandal of our time for
which ignorance is responsible and not the ungenerosity
of nature or the number of people on earth ignorance
and problems of economics... For if two people out of
three suffer from hunger, perhaps the economist should
tell us why.
(2) These are based on a harvest of just over 1-2 tons of
grain equivalents for each of the 17,300 million acres of the
world's recognized arable lands.
(3) M. Cépède "Food as a Production Factor": Indian Journal
of Agricultural Economics. 1959.
(4) Between 1943, when 70 per cent, and January 1946, when 23
88 per cent of the workmen were Costa Ricans, daily output
per man rose from 313 cubic yards to 1,440 cubic yards.
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
0
.
Ill
(9ZDZIL0
tno>
_
(A
^
Q
.
<E
oj¿n
i
ZO
o
co
«
.
»
-
H
O
)
«
ao
U
T
3i
-
Q
.
3
OU
O
a
.
urrj
Co
o
T
J
o
C
L
O
ao
5
a
Q
0
)
i:
Z
"O
*
<
O
1
_
3OU
a
o
o
o
íp
N
o
3
W
u
.
aoaa
>Co^
p3-
a
Û
2
4
oO
DS
Cnu
g^2
¡
E
S
n
<l>
U
U
o
o
*
o
o
u
3
53a
.
O
J
co«
C
O
o -Brazzavi -Leopold
a
a-Urundi
:
:
r
-
:
:
109.Congo 110.Congo111.Ugand112.Kenya 113.Ruand
¿
S
O
<
C
>
"w
1«
«
"C
-0
S
?
0)
h
c
¿T*
-
3
fc
e
°
-
b
o
H
j
D
I
O
w
I
D
Z
m
\
D
N
C
O
C
N
O
-
-
f
N
r
o
c
o
c
o
c
o
c
o
c
o
o
^
c
^
o
^
c
*
O
J
o
E
t
í
ooO
J
o
íso
I
"
G
o
3En
Z
a
¿
ñ
«
f
í
"r
-o
S"
a.
IE
3
jl
°
.Si
^
^
57
«
i
5
£
£
U
Z
U
¿
T
O
°
-
3
-
c
tí
"
^
-
u
l>
O
t
-
^
C
O
C
r
*
O
x
-
iN
OOo
-
OOO
J
o
í
1
.S
o
_o
n
Ü
c
_
O
£
e
-g
.2
t;
S
jS
js
ü
c
E
~>j?
=
>
3
ü
i1
5
N
ü
3
3
:5
<
>
lj
o
.
U
1
o
:
m
<
m
"
i
-
u
>
v
û
N
©
^
O
T
"
ooh
.
o
î
O
O
tí
C
O
D
-
Eo
-
o
3
'«
:=
x
i
x
i
«
«
u
w
ttj
CJ
c
o
j
O
3
<
I
J
:
D
û
Z
f
^
M
^
"
iO
\
O
S
C
O
O
>
0
¡
c¿
"5
"H
0>
-^
rt
v»
v
U
D
S
U
J
*,X
û
o
-
O
-
.'(
S
m
'i-
in
v
flN
c
o
o
»
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
pa
û)
.
"2
ri
.iz
(d
X
r
i
C
o
c
rd
°
o
E
S
,<
ra
o
-2
a
ô
£
5
S
«
S?
-J
|
Ñ
-5
S
"
oo
^
«
S
t
i>
u
5
«
a
tí
c
.
>-
O
Ï
S
ï
o
|
<
.^
.L
O
z
_
2
_
i_
to
û
0
c
û
c
o
u
n
Ca
>
-
!
-
o>
_
a_
_
dEM
tu
*-"
C
C
rd
O
O
>
-
d
hadudan thiopiaomalia uinea erraLeLiberia IvoryCGhanaTogo DahomeNigeria
»
t
-
O0
)
U
m
lu
m
k
j
t/i
.
.
O
T
-
r
i
m
t
m
-
n
*
L
O
.
Í
>
O
.
C
O
O
O
O
O
O
O
O
dd
co
o
rd
td
.£
i
r
«
n
i
:
o
a
.
a
Z
.2
S
08
-
Q
.
S
rd
N
¡d
a
.
C
=
O
u
5
E
-
trdt»
0
oc
3aoa
_
o
r
d
"
H
c
j;^
X
>
3
0
l0
O
.0
U
iÍ.w
U
ü
.£
<
Z
¡Z
«
,Z
<.
m
V
tJ
l^
o
is
c
o
r
js
ö
r
^
fN
r
n
-
d
r
t
s
N
r
s
N
r
s
N
N
C
O
C
O
C
O
C
O
C
O
0
)
O
C
>
.
u
a
>
01
1/3
_¡¿
-
rd
lord
cr
i
S
i
-
-
*
.
-
r
t
<
u
-
^
;-
d
c
	
_
^
to
i-
û
-
o
t*
y
3
t
c
r
c
(J
D
h
l^
"
j:
o.J?
>
-
ii
n
i
(»J
d
;
u
i
o
n
a
i
r>
d
r^
r
i
r
i
L
n
i
n
m
i
n
i
r
t
i
n
i
r
i
L
o
s
O
O
^
o
^
}
.
-
C
;
60
:
<
CO'oaoac3OuN
1=
I
8
rd
-S
(Jû
.
rd
I
0
)
~
:
o
c
:
c
j
¡
>
.>
=
6
ri
J-
-
'¡J
'
L
"D
>
.
-
r
j*r
u
a
.
o
._
rt
m
lo
u
.
Z
c
û
u
.
io
Q
.
i
:
(/)
o
o
u
.
i
>
C
O
~
rd
r
i
n
n
r
*
i
r
o
fï>
w
i
i
ouudo0
)
c.2
w
JÖ3aoaa
>co^
p3J
3
»<
/)
Û
rd
i
j
OO
od
_
>
3
rd
rt
id
2
I
lS
i
O
¡ï
rd
n
i
z
u
£
u
>
o
lu
à
:
«s
u
o
t-'
rJ
w
d
/
in
^
.o
cô
o»
d
t-
'-
T
-
<
r
-
i
-
T
-
r
-
T
-
T
-
T
-
T
-
l
N
r
-
M
X
I
Cre
I
c'a
i
2Q
-
HEO
0
1
X
I
c3
X
I
Cr
e0
)
>O
I
re
"3M
O
o>o
O<
2
5
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
FOOD TABOOS
ALLY
OF
HUNGER
by Dr. Marcel Autret
Director, Nutrition Division, FAO
A FISH FARMER'S HARVEST
Encouraged by their state government and
with help from FAO and UNICEF, the
villagers of Orissa, India, have become
fish farmers. This extensive programme of
pisciculture was decided on when nutrition
surveys revealed a high incidence of pro¬
tein malnutrition among the people of
Orissa. Harvests from the village fish
ponds will help to compensate for the
lack of animal protein in present diets.
26
Photo Jacques Linf. - UNICEF
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
w
hove and hunger lead the world," observed
Gorki, echoing Anatole France not
long before and Hesiod some twenty-seven centuries
earlier. "Hunger and sex are the two biological finalities
which govern Man's social life," wrote Audrey Richards
in her study of the Bantus in 1932. Among African
peasants or Bolivian workers with extremely low incomes,
food accounts for 80 per cent of the family budget. This,
moreover, only provides a bare subsistence allowance.
Among the North Americans or Western Europeans, from
25 to 40 per cent of the family budget is still devoted to
food.
As Professor A. Mayer has noted, three-quarters of the
world's population works to produce its food and the
remainder works in order to purchase it. Thus, all the
progress made in science and technique has been unable
to free man from this harsh necessity and has merely
succeeded in reducing the effort involved in seeking his
"daily bread" and ensuring a diversity of food production
to meet the increasingly varied tastes of an increasingly
large number of increasingly demanding consumers.
Food habits are an integral part of any culture.
Initially, no doubt, they were imposed by the environment
and limited to whatever could be gathered in that environ¬
ment; from huntsmen, the nomads, having tamed wild
animals, became first of all pastoralists and then, having
learnt to plant and look after cropbearing seeds, develop¬
ed into settled agriculturalists.
Through habit and physiological adaptation, men
acquired a taste for the basic foodstuffs produced in this
way. Depending on the regions and the ecological condi¬
tions, man's diet was to be almost solely composed of
meat (Eskimos), or milk products (the Masai) or of items
almost wholly vegetable in origin (Indians, Mayas, Bantus
and Asian peoples) while other groups, more favoured by
nature or more ingenious, were to be omnivorous.
From the outset, therefore, diet was subject to the
limitations of production. This latter was subsequently
improved by a technique which was acquired and
ceaselessly perfected and, depending on the regions
concerned, created the restrictive framework within which
emerged the various dietary types.
But economic determinism stops there. Before long,
through an uninterrupted process, man a biological being
endowed with the sense of observation and with a memory
in the course of an empirical operation covering thou¬
sands of years and often at the cost of experiences for
which he paid dearly, selected from the animal and
vegetable species those which proved . good for him, for
his health, his taste, his strength or his well-being.
All of this was accompanied by the intrusion of innu¬
merable spiritual, social and cultural obligations, created
by man himself and, unfortunately, always restrictive in
nature and by the development of certain acquired and
possibly transmittable preferences. In the long run,
this choice whether freely made or imposed created
the dietary habits which are now part of a way of life
and one of the aspects of each culture. To parody a
famous remark, we might almost say, "Tell me what you
eat and I will tell you who you are."
IODAY, of course, preservation and transport
methods encourage economic exchanges; the
French get bananas from the Ivory Coast and peanuts
from Senegal with oil which can be used in place of
butter or olive oil; the Senegalese receive rice from Viet-
Nam, the Ghanaians wheat from Canada, the Europeans
cocoa from Africa and coffee from Brazil; these are
important innovations but they are none the less minor
in the sense that they do not change the dietary type.
Dietary habits range from the most extreme simplicity
to the most infinite variety. From the nomadic herdsman
of Mauritania devoted to his camel milk to the Mexican;
with his taste for "tortillas" made of corn, beans and
fiery peppers, from the Batéké of the Congo who eats
manioc with palm oil and the Ouolof of Senegal who eats
millet with peanut oil sauce to the Asian with his
preference for rice with fish sauce, three-quarters of
mankind in essence only know one dish: the basic food
rice, wheat, corn, millet, sorghum, manioc, taro, yams or
plantains and a sauce ranging from clear broth with a
little pepper and salt to a mixture of everything which
the housewife has been able to lay hands on- oils, fats
vegetables, meat or fish.
It is in the remaining quarter of the world that we
mostly find the sequence of varied dishes, the elaborate
sauces, the heavy foods ranging from the Roman banquets
to the gargantuan repasts dear to Bruegel the Elder, from
the solid, down-to-earth meals provided at country
weddings to the subtle blendings which skilled master
cooks once set before selected initiates.
"Those who go on eating when their stomachs are full"
will one day have to learn not to "dig their graves with
their teeth," as the Turkish proverb puts it. But it is
not with them that we are concerned today. It is not
over-eating but under-nourishment and deficiency mal¬
nutrition, hunger in short, that we must combat first and
foremost.
As a cause of under-nourishment and, still
more, malnutrition, that responsibility ls a
heavy one. However limited food resources may be, man
is far from making the best use of them. All sorts of
prohibitions and taboos, innumerable beliefs or mere trad¬
ition govern the use or non-use of foodstuffs; dietary
prohibitions vary according to the clan, the family and
the individual; age, the physiological condition and the
season of the year; days, associations with the products
concerned and methods of killing, transport, harvesting,
storing, cooking; the types of cooking implements, etc.
This complexity of taboos undoubtedly derives from
many factors: empirical observation, protection of the
individual or more generally of the community, equal or
preferential sharing of resources, a concern with the
preservation of natural resources of the perpetuation of
species, abstention because of ignorance, health considera¬
tions or caution, purifying fasts, propitiatory abstinence,
hoarding (or wasting) for reasons of prestige.
All of them are causes which may be readily perceived.
Some are readily accepted by our reason, and others, for
which no scientific explanation has yet been found, we
accordingly classify as "magical," forgetting that the
difference between the magic which replaces science
among primitive peoples and our own "science" is only
one of time and degree.
Certain dietary practices whose reasons are lost in the
mists of time, however, are no longer justified today. If
they are harmless from the viewpoint of health or
economics, let us respect them by which I mean, let us
leave them alone. If they are harmful from a nutritional
or economic viewpoint, let us study them in co-operation
with the ethnologist or the sociologist and try either to
change them or to make better use of them. Bernard
Shaw's remark is to the point: "Facing the past, hats
off; facing the future, sleeves up." Faced with the
diversity of dietary habits, rites and taboos, we have all
too many illustrations for our purpose.
Dietary prohibitions apply particularly to meat, eggs,
fish and milk. They extend to absolute or temporary
prohibition among pregnant women, nursing mothers,
young children and adolescents, precisely those whose
need of such protein foods is increased. Thus, in many
regions, a pregnant woman may not eat meat of any
kind, wart-hog, antelope, rat, snake, chicken or turkey;
elsewhere, she may not eat fish. A young child must
only consume its mother's milk or light gruels made with
the predominant food which, depending on the region,
may be corn, millet, wheat, rice or manioc. Neither eggs
nor fish; no meat or "hot" foods, no fruits guava, paw¬
paw "cold" foods.
The reasons given for this today are as unconvincing
for us as they are essential for many different peoples:
milk causes sterility in women, eggs lead to the disappear¬
ance of the libido; certain meats have a harmful effect
on children; fish can cause leprosy, mottled beans or
speckled bananas cause smallpox; a number of foods
provoke digestive disturbances, eye trouble, Intestinal
worms or other more mysterious dangers!
It is not surprising, therefore, that mothers very quickly
suffer from serious anaemia and vitamin deficiency (beri¬
beri) and that children are often born with latent defi¬
ciencies which, in conjunction with the deficient weaning
diet, lead to Kwashiorkor, a protein deficiency illness 27
CONT'D ON PAGE 30
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
AFRICAN RECIPES
FOR
HEALTHIER MEALS
Like many other countries Ghana suffers from malnutrition despite its rich
harvests. Though a land of plenty, certain areas, have near-starvation condi¬
tions. Much of the nation lives on a basic diet of grains or starchy roots. The
biggest deficiencies are meat, milk, fish and eggs. The Ghana Government
recently launched a nationwide campaign to teach healthier eating habits and
combat food taboos with the help of FAO and Unesco. Results of village-to-
village enquiries (right) to survey the situation and discover appropriate
recipes already used, were then gathered together into nutrition-recipe book,
"Good Food for Good Health", (1959) followed by a children's book, "The
Story of the Six Food Families", both edited by Miss Ella Griffin of Unesco.
Below, a nutrition course in a Ghana village; and recipe class (below right).
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Photos © P. Almasy
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
FOOD TABOOS (Cont'd)
for eating an egg
which haunts children in underdeveloped countries and
which has a name in virtually every language. Nor is it
surprising that there should be deficiencies of vitamin A
which often lead to blindness and numerous vitamin B
deficiencies (Infantile beri-beri, pellagra, ariboflavinosis)
which, when they do not themselves kill, prepare the way
for infections which frequently prove mortal.
' Whereas the infant death rate in Western countries is
between 10 and 30 per 1,000*, it is between 100 and 300
in under-developed countries. Still more striking is the
comparison between death rates among children from 1
to 4 years of age where it is recognized that the nutri¬
tional factor is a primordial cause, directly or indirectly,
of death. In this age group, for each child that dies in
Sweden or France, 4 die in Portugalbut 24 in India and
50 in Africa.
This is partly due to poor conditions of hygiene, to
poverty; to a much greater extent it is due to ignorance,
to traditions, to taboos which prevent the best use from
being made of necessary and often available foods. The
surveys carried out in Guatemala, Mexico, Nigeria and
India reveal that, even in families with a satisfactory food
consumption, young children only rarely receive the share
which they require. Mothers, thinking they are doing the
right thing or from fear of doing the wrong thing,
systematically exclude all protein foods from the child's
diet up to the age of two years with the exception of
mother's milk which is notoriously inadequate.
It should, moreover, be noted that it is in this delicate
and dangerous field of weaning that dietary habits are
most conservative. Thus mothers in Haiti, where the
essence of African cooking has been submerged under the
Caribbean, Spanish or French influence, still use akassan
and kenke to feed young children. These corn gruels,
although carefully prepared, have remained identical
with the formula brought two or three centuries earlier
from Dahomey or Ghana where they are still used today.
It is essential that this should change, that there should
be a better distribution of food within the family, that
better use should be made of local products. And this
necessitates educating the mother of families.
An example of another kind is provided by the pastoral
peoples of Africa. The Masáis of Kenya, the Moors of the
western Sahara and the Bororos of Central Africa are
proud of their herds, the value of which is calculated by
the number of head in a given herd. The larger the
herd, the greater the prestige and the higher the social
standing of the owner. Among primitive and developed
peoples alike, pride is another of the motives underlying
man's actions, to be added to hunger, love or hatred. So
these herds are not exploited and at most a few animals
may be taken from them to form a dowry, to acquire a
wife or to pay taxes.
One day, none the less, cattle must be com¬
mercialized and this will involve establishing
the deep- reasons which link the man to his herd: survival
of the worship of the cow, affection for preferred comp¬
anions, an ultimate form of saving or sheer pride of
possession. In the latter case, the time is not far off
when the herds will be weighed against other forms of
prestige since, as the anthropologist Lowrie has observed,
"man is more a peacock than a biological or economic
animal."
In any case, education of the stock-breeders will consist
of showing him that there are other pleasures besides
contemplating a herd, that there are other forms of
exploitation which are more enriching andwhy not, if
it is in the interest of the community to have the hitherto
meat or milk commercialized? that there are
other forms of prestige to be offered to the peacock.
Or let us take another example of poor food utilization.
In a region of West Africa, the. butter sold by the Peuhls
is made into soap with the result that Mobas and Gour-
mas women suffering from vitamin A deficiency wash
30 their clothes with soap containing vitamins.
Deaths in the course of the first year per 1,000 live births.
Other dietary habits are of relatively recent origin and
are no less regrettable. An example ls provided by the
consumption of tea and loaf sugar among certain
Mediterranean peoples. Today, Morocco consumes more
than 40 kilogrammes of sugar per inhabitant per year,
i.e. more than 110 grammes per day, to sugar mint tea.
This is a level of consumption comparable to that of
countries with ten times as high an income. To give an
idea of the cost of this practice, it is enough to mention
that tea and sugar absorb two months salary in the
average Moroccan family! Such expenditure, even
allowing for the social significance and the stimulant
effect of this national drink, could be considerably
reduced.
Will we one day be able to change these
unsound dietary practices? Combat the taboos,
the false beliefs, make rational use of available resources?
Make it possible for the Indonesian baby to be given fish
and the African peanut flour, for the young girls of
Uganda to be given milk and pregnant women various
meats and eggs? Undoubtedly, yes. With few exceptions,
dietary habits only seem static when observed over a
short period.
There are abundant examples of evolutions which, in
some places, even resemble revolutions. Is it necessary
to recall the history of the potato? Do not we Europeans
owe to the Crusaders many of the fruits of the Near
East, does not Africa owe to the Portuguese corn, manioc,
tomatoes, sweet potatoes, to mention only the main items
which originally came from South America?
When we measure the place which these products today
occupy in African agriculture, it is astonishing to note
the changes which have occurred in three or four cen¬
turies. And today, before our very eyes, the advance
continues: the area given over to the growing of manioc,
for example, Ls increasing dangerously at the expense of
cereals, even in regions where the treatment required by
the bitter manioc obliges the housewife to cover long
distances in order to get to streams where it can be
steeped. Similarly, bread consumption in Africa is rising
very rapidly. This is simultaneously the result of
urbanization and new habits acquired during the war by
African soldiers. Some form of spaghetti, with or without
tomatoes, constitutes the evening meal in almost every
Libyan familya practice which certainly did not exist
before the Italian occupation.
If you ask the girls of Gazaya College, near Kampala
in Uganda, who drink milk every day and eat fish, whether
they are not afraid of becoming sterile, they will tell you
that those are old wives' tales which they have not
believed for a long time past, even if, in fact, some of
them still have to make a certain effort "to do as the
others do" and even if their fears have only recently
disappeared. In the centre of the Congo, near Kikwitt,
a milk distribution programme was organized in 1952. In
less than a year, mothers who had only taken milk for
their young children and the boys, began to take it for
themselves and their little girls.
And where, a mere fifty years ago, a husband could
repudiate his wife and claim the cattle given as a dowry
if he discovered that his wife had eaten eggs, chicken
raising is now rapidly developing. (But it is not so long
ago in certain farms which I know in France, that the
boys could only have chicken, at the price of a good
hiding when they "sacrificed" a bird and the only eggs
they had were those they "pinched" from the nest.)
In both cases, if the penalties were different, the motives
were surely the sameto prevent valuable foods from
being kept from the master's table or the market. Thus,
many dietary customs described 50 or 100 years ago by
ethnologists and travellers among peoples which had
hitherto had no contact with western civilization have
today vanished.
The progress of diversified agriculture, the introduction
of new vegetable or animal species, the increased produc¬
tion of fisheries, the improvement of preservation methods
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
ONLY ONE DISH
ON THE MENU
Food habits, were initially imposed by the environment and the limitations
of production. Thus, an Eskimo's diet (left) is almost solely composed
of meatcaribou, seal, fishwhile that of India's people (right) is almost
wholly vegetable in origin. Three-quarters of mankind in essence
know only one dish, a basic food flavoured by a sauce of some kind.
and distribution systems, the pressure of commercial
propaganda and the emergence of a purchasing power
help to change the dietary type by modifying the economic
sub-stratum which determines it. But, above all, it is
education which, by changing the cultural sub-stratum
that shaped dietary habits, is responsible for the great
changes which have taken place. This education is
carried out:
First of all, by schools where teaching relegates to the
subordinate ranks the sorcerers and witch-doctors whose
gifts are at last being questioned; where instruction in
simple notions of agriculture, diet and hygiene is each day
occupying a larger place, linked with school meals,
gardening and even the raising of poultry and flshbreed-
ing; where the girls learn housework, cooking, care of the
family and child-care; where, in short, is trained not only
an élite which will migrate to the towns but also a rural
population better prepared than its ancestors to raise com¬
munity living standards material and intellectual.
By maternity or child centres where an increasingly
well-informed staff teaches mothers to feed their young
children in a rational way, thereby attacking and already
with success the difficult problem of harmful practices
at the moment of weaning;
By community development movements adult groups,
youth clubs, women's clubs and social centres where talks
are given by lecturers in popular agriculture and rural
domestic economy, by social assistants, health educators,
public nurses, school-teachers, in a word by all those
with access to peoples prepared by the spirit of co¬
operation and mutual assistance which community devel¬
opment implies to learn from better informed teachers
the methods needed to ensure the raising of their con¬
dition in general and their food standards in particular.
The rôle of international organizations in co-operation
with the national authorities is to train such teachers,
from the highest level to the village level.
In the nutritional field, this pre-supposes a knowledge
of dietary types and habits and of their economic and
socio-cultural sub-stratum, the determination of resistance
points and weak points with a view to attacking vulnera¬
ble practices or by-passing obstacles which are too deep-
rooted, the choice of priority targets in accordance with
the urgency of the nutritional problems and with due
regard to existing or potential resources. It calls, too,
for the orientation of production or the provision of trade
channels so that the demand to be created can be met
without an untoward effect on prices; in short, a national
food policy, an operational plan at the local level, work
methods and, finally, the training of the staff needed to
carry the programme to a successful conclusion.
Hundreds of such programmes are being conducted by
one or another of these methods while, over the last three
years, an effort has been made to strike on all fronts
simultaneously: schools, maternity and child centres,
community development programmes, public education
campaigns. Some 50 programmes of education in food
and diet are under way in more than 40 countries.
These programmes are conducted under the auspices
of FAO, UNICEF, WHO and sometimes Unesco. The
importance of the programmes has not so far exceeded
the pilot stage: thus the programme under way in Costa
Rica affects 60,000 out of a total population of 700,000.
The four programmes in India concern between 2 and
3 per cent of the population. But already governments
are convinced of the success of these programmes and are
anxious to increase them very rapidly.
Thus, India not only wishes to extend these programmes
to 16 States within three years but also intends to
increase the area of application within each State. Brazil,
whose poverty has been so well described by Josué de
Castro, wishes to set up such programmes in all the
north-east States where two programmes are now being
carried out. From throughout the world, requests for
financial and technical aid reach FAO.
The programmes are limited by the lack of credits to
carry out basic surveys, to salve certain problems of
applied research, to train directing staff or cadres, to
supply certain equipment or merely transport means
which increase the effectiveness of "know-how," and
finally to pay those who set the programmes going and run
them until such time as the national staff is competent
enough to be left to itself.
The aim of the "Campaign Against Hunger" is precisely
to come to the assistance of those countries where hunger
reigns, not only by giving them food surpluses, sent
urgently as a partial and temporary solution, but by
putting at the disposal of those countries specialists for
the training of men with whom, through additional
material aid, they will set up programmes designed to
bring about important and lasting results in the field
of the production and utilization of foodstuffs.
International aid would make it possible to reach within
twenty-five years objectives which, at the present rate,
could only be attained in a century. But time presses
and terribly so, for, as José Americo has said: o«
"Worse than dying of hunger in the desert
Is to have nothing to eat in the Land of Canaan."
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
THE FOOD DESTROYERS
INSECTS AND OTHER PESTS RAVAGE CROPS
THAT COULD FEED UNTOLD MILLIONS OF PEOPLE
by Dr. J. Vallega
Director, Plant Production
and Protection Division, FAO
32
AGE-OLD ENEMY of
the desert locust, still
tests over 60 countries and
territories. A single swarm
of these hungry marauders
may number as many as
1,000 million and can weigh
anything from 50,000 to
100,000 tons. It eats the
equivalent of its weight in
green plants every day,
leaving desolation behind
it. Areas in the path of
advancing swarms are now
given warning by a special
service jn which the FAO
rid Meteorological
on join forces.
echiney-Progi!, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
J. P.. Geigy S.A.. Basel, Switzerland STOREROOM RAIDERS like Insects and rodents each year cause losses
equivalent to the produce of scores of millions of acres. Modern methods of
grain storage could greatly reduce damage by such pests as weevils and rats.
J;IuxiAN Huxley in his essay on "Living in a
Revolution" said, "human evolution has been
getting faster and faster its tempo during recorded
history is at least 100,000 times faster than that of pre-
evolution."
Fascinating changes which characterized the last decade
of the nineteenth and the first decade of the twentieth
century support Huxley's view. Human knowledge, from
physics to sociology, vastly expanded during this time and
an impressive number of discoveries brought men to the
dawn of a new age of wealth and achievement. Then,
in less than 25 years, two world wars threatened to destroy
this modern civilization and lay waste the efforts of
thousands of brilliant scientists and technicians who had
paved the way to a better life. But, despite the havoc
wrought, the wars acted as "a hot house" in forcing the
pace of scientific and technological progress. Even the
terrifying, development of the atomic bomb has made
possible man's peaceful uses of atomic energy.
. While this progress in the technically advanced
countries is apparent for all to see, in some emerging
countries it has slowed down, in others it has come to a
standstill and in some the situation has grown worse than
it was before the Second World War.
Today, although more food is produced than at any
previous time in history, we are still a long way from
being able to provide enough food -for everybody. Indeed,
the world food situation is perhaps more serious than
ever. Pests and parasites continue to take a very heavy
toll of the food produced, although scientific means exist
to keep them under control.
More than one-fifth of the food that should be harvested
from the crops planted by mankind never reaches the
dinner-table. For example, It has been estimated that
about 20 per. cent of the annual world food crop plantings
is destroyed, or seriously damaged, by insects, disease and
other pests, and that in some countries as much as 10
per cent of grain production food on which money and
labour have been spent in cultivation, processing and
transportation is destroyed in store by Insects, rodents
and fungi.
Other factors which take their one per cent toll here
and their two per cent toll there, make up an annual loss
of food, which, if saved, would feed several tens of
millions of people. The world production of cereal grains
in 1959, excluding the U.S.S.R., was 856,000,000 metric tons,
of which at least 10 per cent was destroyed in store,- a
loss of 85,600,000 tons which, at an average ration of about
800 grammes daily per person, would have fed almost
300,000,000 people for a year.
From hiblical times, locusts have provided the most
striking example of an insect plague:
"A nation is come upon my land, strong and without
number, whose teeth are of a lion. Like the noise of
chariots on the tops of mountains shall they leap, like
the noise of flames, of fire that devoureth the stubble.
The appearance of them is as the appearance of horses
and as horses 'so shall they run. The land is a garden
of Eden before them and behind them a desolated
wilderness. Joy is withered away from the sons of
man."
So spoke the prophet Joel of the locusts three thousand
years ago, and -they still plague humanity, bringing with
them the threat of famine to many lands. Throughout
the centuries, they have been the scourge of farmers in
the Near and Middle East and the northern half of Africa,
CONT'D ON PAGE 36
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
INSECTS WHO CAME TO DINNER
COCKROACH is a serious pest with
house-invading habits. Found in all
parts of the world, it feeds on all sorts
of things in a house, contaminates
food and has an unpleasant odour.
34
All photos © Pechiney-Progil, Paris
/'"/'
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
THE FOOD DESTROYERS (Cont'd)
SCOURGE OF TROPICAL
AFRICA. More than 750,000 dif¬
ferent species have been counted
among the world's insects. Some
are man's friends and others are
his foes, among the most deadly of
which is the tse-tse fly (left) which
infests over four million square miles
of tropical Africa. The tse-tse's
bite infects man with deadly sleeping
sickness and transmits other orga¬
nisms fatal to cattle and domestic
animals. As a result vast areas
suitable for farming are uninhabi¬
table either by man or his livestock.
-Victory over the tse-tse would
restore these lands to man's use.
© J. P.. Geigy S.A., Basel, Switzerland
MAN-MADE INSECT. A helicop¬
ter fitted with agricultural spraying
gear flies over a forest in the Uni¬
ted States projecting a cloud of
pesticides over the trees. Heli¬
copters and other aircraft have pro¬
ved their worth in the war against
insect pests that ravage man's
food crops. They have actually carr¬
ied the battle against locusts into the
air, spraying the swarms in flight.
USIS
Sirens, bombs and flamethrowers of no avail
a persistent plague which has hampered agricultural
development. Swarms of locusts, each swarm weighing
anything from 50,000 to 100,000 tons, are carried by the
winds over thousands of miles. They eat the equivalent
of their weight of green plants every day, leaving desola¬
tion behind them.
More than 20 countries, members of the FAO Desert
Locust Control Committee, are co-ordinating their efforts
against the plague. A field force composed of locust
specialists, air-spraying experts, meteorologists, biologists,
etc., is working in teams over vast areas of Africa, the
Near East and the Far East, to destroy the locusts in their
breeding areas on the ground or the swarms in the air.
But still the locusts are eating our food, although it is
hoped that the present campaign will go far towards
bringing this pest finally under control.
Monoculture, a practice which consists in cultivating the
same crop over vast areas, has also considerably increased
the spread of destruction caused toy insect pests and
parasites because it disturbs the biological balance of
nature. Examples of this practice are to be found over
large areas of the Americas, Africa and Europe, where
thousands of square miles are now cultivated uninterrup¬
tedly with the same crops: wheat in the TJ.S.A. and
Canada, sugar cane in the U.S.A. and Cuba, rice in a
number of Far Eastern countries, rubber, cocoa, palm
trees, groundnuts in many parts of Africa and the Far
East.
The natural enemies of the pests and parasites that prey
on the crops have disappeared, allowing an extraordinary
proliferation of the enemies of the crops. Pesticides and
insecticides when available and properly used permit
control of most invasions of crop predators.
It appears now, however, that many of the predators
3g have developed a resistance, and even an immunity, to
the chemicals which only a few years ago destroyed them
in masses. New methods of control and new chemical
compounds have to be continuously developed to keep on
top in the struggle against man's enemies.
But insects are not the only enemies man has to cope
with. A pretty little bird with a red beak, black collar
and beige body feathers, which is often kept as a pet, is,
next to the locust, perhaps the most damaging winged
pest to be found in Africa. Weaver birds in swarms of
millions' devour crops over hundreds of thousands of
square miles from Senegal to Somalia and Transvaal,
sometimes driving villagers from their homes by com¬
pletely destroying their crops.
Here, again, man has struggled to control this pest but,
so far, without conspicuous success. The African farmer
tries to protect his crops by frightening the birds, beating
drums, boxes, tins and anything to make a loud noise.
Sirens, detonators, smoke producers and low-flying air¬
craft have been tried in recent years, but with equal lack
of success. Air bombing, flame-throwers to burn the
nests and biological control have also been tried but have
failed to establish full control of the pest.
Unknown plant diseases continuously appear. About
Í928, a new disease appeared in a coconut plantation on
San Miguel Island in the Philippines. At that time
nobody suspected that this disease would, in about 25
years, destroy all coconut trees on the island 250,000.
Then in 1951 it spread to Luzon where 1,788,000 trees
were affected. Destruction soon became widespread, with
44 million being infected in 1952, 5i million in 1953,
6 million in 1954, 8 million in 1956, and 9i million in 1958.
The total loss in coconuts for 1958 was estimated at 164
million dollars. If the disease continues to spread at the
same rate, 17 million trees in Luzon will have succumbed
by 1964. The probable cause of "Cadang-Cadang," the
local name for the disease which means "death," is a
virus but this has not yet been identified.
It took several centuries to establish control over
epidemics of human diseases, such as smallpox, plague,
yellow-fever, etc. This was achieved mainly through
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
mass-vaccination, constant medical checking, enforced
quarantine regulations and permanent medical vigilance.
Man has not yet established similar control over animal
diseases, nor is he fully aware of the need to do so.
Economic losses resulting from animal diseases are
tremendous. For example, in Burma, nearly a million
cattle were lost from rinderpest during the Second World
War. Most of these were plough and draught animals, and
so the farmers were deprived of the power they needed
to cultivate their land, as well as milk for their children
and dung fuel for heating and cooking. As a result,
Burma lost the whole of her annual export surplus of
3,000,000 tons of rice. This not only ruined her economy
but threatened famine to neighbouring Bengal.
The 1951-1953 outbreak of foot-and-mouth disease in
Europe cost $420,000,000. Mastitis, another serious cattle
disease, costs the British dairy industry some $28,000,000
a year, and the U.S.A. about $200,000,000 a year, although
the incidence of the disease is only 10 per cent today
compared with 30 per cent 25 years ago. In a report
published by O.E.E.C. in 1952, it was estimated that the
total of animal losses to Western Europe for that year
amounted in value to about $16,800,000,000, or 15 per cent
of the total output of livestock products and this in one
of the most advanced agricultural regions of the world.
Norris E. Dodd, a former Director-General of FAO, once
said that, "if the blood-sucking intestinal parasites of
domestic animals could be removed the resulting increase
in food would more than satisfy the needs of all the
deficient areas of the world."
Technical means exist but the lack of knowledge and
purchasing power, particularly in the less-developed
countries, have made it impossible up to now to control
the enemies. Besides, new dangers have appeared. Air
travel, for instance, has considerably complicated man's
struggle against animal disease. Long sea journeys, often
occupying several weeks, allowed time for symptoms of
infectious diseases to develop. .But with air travel the
time taken seldom permits the development of recog¬
nizable symptoms.
Staff, funds and equipment for research work in plant
and animal disease control are insufficient in relation to
the magnitude of the problem. Much has been done in
the past, more is being done today, but very much more
still remains to be done. For this present world is still
a rival world where man is struggling against Innumerable
enemies. There is no turning aside from this fact, no
escape and no shortcut. More food must be produced
and less food eaten or destroyed by insects, pests and
parasites. Only through satisfying the basic needs of
man and food is certainly the first of these requirements
can we "hope to build a peaceful world for the coming
generation.
CORROSIVE HUNGER
If mankind fails to put into effect, urgently and
on a world scale, measures capable of halting
the corrosive inroads of hunger, then all that
human genius has created will crumble and be
swept away like dust, long before a natural
erosion could destroy the untold riches hidden
in the ground. And mankind, already haunted by
the distant threat of a world transformed into
desert by the using up of its natural resources,
will witness the paradoxal arrival of a world
become barren and depopulated even though it
still overflows with hidden fertility and riches.
Josué de Castro
in "Géopolitique de la Faim", Editions ouvrières, Paris, 1956 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
As part of the Freedom from Hunger
Campaign, the Food and Agriculture Orga¬
nization and other U.N. bodies have been
preparing a series of 16 "Basic Studies"
to help citizens in discussing the great
issues involved (see bibliography, page 64).
In a general foreword to the series, the
FAO chief, Dr. B.R. Sen, notes: "These
volumes... cover broad subjects such as
the adequacy of food levels in the world,
the possibilities of producing more food
and the ways in which economic develop¬
ment and training in the newly-develop¬
ing countries can raise buying power and
thus help hungry people to buy more food
for themselves." "These studies," writes
Dr. Sen, "attempt to summarize the known
facts... and thus provide useful and reliable
background material for study groups and
public discussions." The Basic Studies aim
not only at stimulating thought and action
on the problem of hunger, but also to bring
about "an ever-expanding understanding of
the related social, economic and technical
issues." The agencies co-operating with
FAO in producing this series are ILO,
WHO, Unesco, WMO, and the U.N. itself.
The article below is taken from the U.N.
Basic Study, "Population and Food Supply"
which is to be published this summer.
Prepared for the U.N. by the Population
Reference Bureau it seeks to present an
objective picture of world population in
relation to the food problem.
GREATEST INCREASES . in
population growth are taking place
today in regions where tempo of
economic development is slowest
and food deficiencies most pro¬
nounced. Africa's present popula¬
tion of well over 200 million, for
example, is expected to more than
double in the next 40 years. Today
more than half of Africa's people
are under twenty years of age.
F
38
rom a relatively rare creature over half a
million years ago, man (or proto-man) moved
upward from tens or hundreds of thousands to tens and
hundreds of millions by the beginning of the Christian
era. For the time of Christ's birth, scholars very tenta¬
tively set the total world population in the neighbourhood
of 200-300 million.
This guess is probably as good as the assumption gene¬
rally accepted that this number approximately doubled
by the middle of the 17th century to 500 million. The
thousand million mark was reached about two centuries
later by 1850; and in the succeeding 110 years the
3,000 million mark has been reached.
Today world population is increasing at a rate which
would double the number in about 50 years, and certain
FOOD
populations numbered in the millions are growing so fast
they would double in 25 years. This sudden increase is
explained not only by the rise in the birth rate but by
the sharp decline almost everywhere in "the adult and
especially the child death rate.
Moderate population growth now extends over all
Europe (including the U.S.S.R.), northern America, tem¬
perate South America, Japan and Australia, containing
about a quarter of the human race. Yet even in these
areas the low death rate is resulting in a rapid increase.
In the U.S.A. for instance the present rate of three chil¬
dren per family is increasing the population by almost
50 per cent per generation.
Asia with now more than 1,600 million people (excluding
Asian U.S.S.R.) may have 2,000 million by 1975 and
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Aîmasy, Paris
AND PEOPLE
3,900 million by 2000, according to a U.N. analysis. A
recent report of the U.N. Economic Commission for Asia
and the Far East (ECAFE) indicates that if present trends
continue, the population of the region will nearly double
in the next 30 years and will then almost equal the entire
world population today.
The ECAFE report points out that the Western world
witnessed a slow, gradual transition from high death rates
and birth rates, to low death and birth rates, in step
with a similarly slow and gradual improvement in econo¬
mic and social conditions. "Per capita income, nutrition,
housing and sanitation improved, the death rate gra¬
dually fell, and after a time lag the birth rate also fell.
But in Asia and the Far East... mortality has fallen before
any major improvement in social and economic conditions
has occurred. (For example Denmark took 50 years to
reduce the death rate from 20 to 14 per thousand; in
Ceylon it occured in one year 1947-1948 but with no drop
in birth rate).
The ECAFE report contends that the rapid population
growth may well act as a brake on economic develop¬
ment of most of the countries of Asia. "This is all the
more true," it says, "since the " emigration outlet, which
provided substantial relief to population pressure in
Europe during its demographic transition, is not avail¬
able to Asian countries to any significant extent."
The combined population of Africa (240 million in 1960)
and Latin America (206 million in 1960) is less than a
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
FOOD & PEOPLE (Cont'd)
Four general
world trends
third that of Asia. Population density is lower and land-
resource possibilities are more favourable. The U.N.
"Basic Study" on Population and Food Supply points out,
however, that actual living conditions over large areas of
Latin America are marginal, and cites the case of north¬
eastern Brazil where famine conditions are reported
"despite the fact that Brazil's agricultural resources are
quite adequate to feed a much larger population than the
current 66 millions. With a per capita annual income of
less than $250, 42 per cent of the population under 15 years
of age and with half the adult population illiterate, the
difficulties of utilizing available resources to meet the
needs of the people of Brazil effectively are enormous."
From this the U.N. report draws a general conclusion:
"The persistence of poverty and hunger in the face of the
very real potential for food production and economic
development... demonstrates a tragic truth: little advan¬
tage is gained from such a potential if the ability and
capacity to exploit the natural resources and to build
up social and economic capital do not proceed hand-in-
hand with population growth."
T-
pi
he Population and Food Supply study then
oints out that despite many attempts to
define and measure "over-population" and "under-pop-
ulation", no generally accepted indicators have been
devised. Population density, while it is sometimes a useful
indicator of population pressure on agricultural resources,
does not take into account the relative abundance or
availability through commerce of other natural resources,
the extent of industrial development, or the degree of
technological progress and other factors which are
important in determining the welfare of the population.
"In recent years," the report states, "attention has
turned increasingly toward analysis of the relation be¬
tween rates of population growth and factors influencing
economic development, particularly for the under¬
developed countries where the need for economic progress
has taken on such importance."
The U.N. study summarizes the four world trends which
influence the social and economic situation: the first
is a decline in the percentage of agricultural population,
rapid in the developed regions, slower in the less-
developed regions. The second is an increase in urban
population proportionately slower in the developed
countries than in the under-developed ones. Third is the
decline in intercontinental migration since the early part
of the 20th century, as contrasted with its great importance
in the 19th. Fourth is the relatively rapid decline of death
rates in the developing regions in recent years compared
with the slower previous decline in the industrialized
countries, without comparable declines in birth rates.
The effects of rapid population growth, the report con¬
tinues, compared with slow or moderate growth are sev¬
eral: 1. It tends to increase the pressure of the farm popu¬
lation on land which may already be densely settled,
further complicating the effects of excessive fragmenta¬
tion and land holdings so small as to be ineffecient;
2. It increases the urgent need for capital investment to
equip the growing labour force productively;
3. It tends to reduce the amount of capital that can be
40 invested in productive equipment. The capacity to pro¬
duce does not rise proportionately with the rise in popu¬
lation in countries with a labour-surplus, though the
The rise in world popu¬
lation since the Augus¬
tan Age of the Roman
Empire is illustrated in
this drawing recently
published by the"Gior-
nale d'ltalia" of Rome.
$*=«
v.v.-.-.
fflp
£X!X:X
...
-v.v.v.v
vXvXv
t
In the time of Augustus *Mi*5«
*
NVV
Nit
300 millions
In 1500
600 millions
In 1850
1,200 millions
In 1960
2,900 millions
In 2210
200,000 millions!
V. V
4v>
i »
%v
vX
» * »
^ *
"
v.v.v.v
"
need to consume does, and this puts heavy demands on
limited capital to meet social needs that are not imme¬
diately productive in economic terms but are nevertheless
essential (such as schools and hospitals) ;
4. It results in a population with a relatively low per¬
centage of people In the effectively productive age groups,
so that on the average each person of working age will
have to support a large number of dependents.
"In terms of simple arithmetic,* it seems evident that
the problem of achieving the needed increases in food
production during the next decades would be made easier,
and the risk of failures would be diminished, if the popu¬
lation were to increase less than present trends indicate
for the economically less developed regions of the world.
Actually, the mathematics of the problem are not so
simple; it is not just a question of addition of a larger or
smaller number of consumers to share a certain quantity
From here on this article ls composed oí verbatim passages from
"Population and Food Supply."
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
FUTURE PROSPECTS
" | N the world picture of food needs and
population growth, these four features
deserve to be highlighted:
1. Demographic changes take place slow¬
ly. There is no prospect that there will be a
sudden decline in the world birth rate. Bar¬
ring catastrophes, there is a good prospect
that the world death rate will decline still
further. Hence, during the immediate future
extending over the next few decades, there
is every prospect that population growth will
continue at a rapid rate.
2. A vast increase in the production of
food to meet the inevitable population in¬
creases over the next decades is imperative
if appalling disasters are to be averted and
the possibility of an orderly and constructive
transition to a satisfactory, stable balance
between food and population is to be
assured.
3. If such a transition is to be achieved, the
magnitude of the operation must be re¬
cognized. It is all very well to say that
"much more food can be produced." To
create the technology and the education and
the storage and transportation facilities and
everything else required to bring this transi¬
tion to pass is an operation on a scale far
vaster than anything contemplated in the
plans either of individual governments or of
the co-operative undertakings now contem¬
plated by United Nations agencies.
4. Indefinite multiplication of people on a
finite planet is impossible. If the rate of pop¬
ulation growth which is occuring in some
areas of the world today were to be applied
to the total human population of the planet,
within only two or three centuries the entire
land surface of the earth would be covered
with human beings."
from the U.N. Basic Study. " Population and food Supply "
of food, for people are producers as well as consumers.
While population growth adds to requirements, it also
contributes through increasing manpower to the possi¬
bilities of producing food and other goods.
With few exceptions, the experts who have studied this
question agree that the outlook would be far more favour¬
able if the present rates of population increase in the
under-developed countries could be slowed down by mode¬
ration of birth" rates. In fact, some experts hold that
unless the growth of population becomes slower in the
near future, there is little hope of improving the condi¬
tions of life in many of these countries, or even to hold
the present low levels of living may prove to be difficult.
In the case of India, for example, it is clear that the
present rate of population growth is a very serious im¬
pediment to the country's economic development and the
solution of its food problem. A.J. Coale and E.M. Hoover
have worked out a series of three models to show how the
conditions appear in 1986. In each model it is assumed
that the death rate will fall. by more than 40 per cent
by 1986.
Model I assumes that fertility begins to decline imme¬
diately and continues down to half its present level by
1981.
Model II assumes no change in fertility until 1966,
and then a decline so sharp that fertility is cut in half
by 1981.
Model III assumes that fertility will remain at the pre¬
sent level until 1986.
Under Model I, with an immediate decline in the birth
rate, the population will grow to 589 million by 1986. Since
there is no immediate prospect of an effective lowering
of the Indian birth rate, this model is mainly of theore¬
tical interest. But if India's birth rate had miraculously
started to decline in 1959, her economy and the welfare
of her people would be far more advanced in 1986 than
under either of the other alternatives.
Under existing conditions, there is a definite possibility
that Model II might be achieved. If the birth rate should
begin to drop sharply after 1966, the population would
grow to 634 million by 1986.
Under Model III, with the birth rate remaining at its
present level, a population of 775 million is the prospect
for 1986. That is nearly double the present population.
C;OALE and Hoover find that continuing high
i fertility would present a major barrier to an
economic break-through. The proportion of children
under 15 in 1986 would be so high (42 per cent, compared
with 30 per cent for the low projection) as to constitute
a decisive handicap to economic development.
By that time, only 10.1 per cent of India's national
income would be available for productive investment.
With almost twice as many people, each year a larger
proportion of capital would be diverted for essential social
services, such as health and education and for non¬
productive investment, such as housing. In contrast,
under the low-fertility pattern of Model I, 14.7 per cent
of the national income would be available for productive
investment.
The difference between 10.1 per cent and 14.7 per cent
of the national income may not seem impressive. But for
a nation struggling to emerge from a marginal agrarian
culture, it might well mean the difference between victory
and defeat in the battle for economic self-sufficiency. The
higher percentage would be adequate to provide a gra¬
dual improvement of living levels.
The problem is not the same where the density of popu¬
lation is lower and there are large reserves of unused or
little used land suitable for agriculture, as in many coun¬
tries of Latin America and Africa. But it has been pointed
out that even in such circumstances, excessively rapid
growth of population is a major hindrance to economic
development. The report of a recent United Nations semi¬
nar on population problems in Latin America makes the
following observations on this score:
'Of course for each new mouth there is also a pair of
hands. But the mouth has to be fed now; the hands
become useful only some years later. In several Latin
American countries as much as 40 per cent of the popu¬
lation is under the age of fifteen. At the same time,
Governments must find productive jobs for a rapidly
growing and sometimes poorly trained labour force, a
task which entails demands on scarce capital resources
which would not be made by a population growing less
rapidly. From each of these points of view, present rates
of population growth are a real handicap to economic
development.'
The issue of population policy and birth regulation is
not purely one of economics. It also involves questions
of cultural ideals, moral principles, and social and political
philosophy which are seen in different lights by the people ^1
CONT'D ON PAGE 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
;WrfJ
FOOD
AND
PEOPLE ».i 1
(Cont'd) ^
i <ll "'»1
Almasy, Pans
BIG CITIES
GETTING
STILL
BIGGER
The concentration of urban populations in
swiftly expanding cities is a world-wide pheno¬
menon of modern times. To these growing
towns and cities flock the workers who found
they could no longer gain a livelihood in agri¬
culture. In Japan, whose 90 million population
has doubled since the start of the century,
Tokyo alone (left) has over 11,000,000 in¬
habitants and is now the world's largest city.
Buenos Aires (above) was one of the last of
the world's great cities to experience a popu¬
lation "boom" through the influx of emigrants.
Inclusive of its suburbs it now has six and a half
million inhabitants, which Is equivalent toalmost
the total population of Argentina ¡n 1914.
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
» Mam
Official Argentine photo
and the governments of different countries. Some groups
object in principle to birth regulation in general or to
certain forms of it; others hold that the decision to prac¬
tice it or not should be left strictly to the people without
any governmental interference or pressure.
The councils of the United Nations, confronted with
the sharp differences in view on this question, have taken
the position that it must be left to each national govern¬
ment to decide its own policy.
The United Nations Population Commission declared in
the report to the Economic and Social Council on its
eleventh session (1961): 'It is the responsibility of each
Government to decide its own policies and devise its own
programmes of action for dealing with the problems of
population and economic and social development. In par¬
ticular, each Government must decide for itself whether
or not any measures should be taken for the purpose of
modifying the trends of population as an aid to the solu¬
tion of these problems, taking into account the work of
the Population Commission.
'On the other hand, it is in the interest of the United
Nations that decisions on national policies should be
taken, and national action programmes should be
planned, in the light of knowledge of the relevant facts,
and that the programmes should be adequate to assure
satisfactory economic and social progress. Among the
circumstances which must be considered are the relevant
features of national culture and ideals as well as the
trend of population, the physical resources and other
economic circumstances of each country.
'It is appropriate that the United Nations should
encourage and assist the Governments, especially of the
less developed countries, in obtaining basic data and
carrying out essential studies of the demographic aspects,
as well as other aspects, of their economic and social
development problems. It is also considered appropriate
for the United Nations to give technical assistance, as
requested by Governments, for national projects of
research, experimentation and action for dealing with
problems of population.'
It would appear from the above that the United Nations
neither encourages nor discourages adoption by Govern¬
ments of any particular population policy, but stands
ready upon request to give technical assistance to Govern¬
ments for the purpose of making effective whatever poli¬
cies they may adopt.
In four of the most populous Asian countries India,
Pakistan, China (mainland) and Japan the Governments
have sponsored various kinds of measures aimed at
encouraging limitation of births and moderating the rate
of population growth, as an aid to economic and social
advancement.
In India, a programme introduced with the first five-
year plan in 1951 provided advice and assistance on family
planning as part of the services in hospitals and health
centres. In the second five-year plan, this programme
was intensified. The third five-year plan provides for
further expansion in the programme. However, neither
this programme nor a similar one in Pakistan appears
as yet to have brought about any great reduction in
births.
In mainland China, the programme of family planning
was launched in 1955. The results of the 1953 population 43
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
FOOD & PEOPLE (Cont'd)
Know-how exists to feed a bigger world
44
census had just been published, and the effect of the
rapid population increase on the problem of industria¬
lization and economic development was realized. But there
is no reliable information regarding the effects of this
programme on the birth rate.
In Japan, the Government, before and during the
Second World War, enforced a pro-natalist policy. But
public interest in family planning rose sharply soon after
the close of the War, probably owing to economic pressure
upon the families. The birth rate dropped from 30.1 per
1,000 population in 1945-1949 to only 17.2 per 1,000 in
1957. As the death rate dropped during this period from
17 to 8 per 1,000, the net result was to bring the annual
rate of natural increase of the population down from
1.3 per cent to 0.9 per cent.
Japan's birth rate at present is as low as or lower than
the rates of most European countries and considerably
below the present birth rates in the U.S.S.R., the United
States and Canada.
In Japan's case, the movement to limit births was
greatly facilitated by the comparatively high degree of
industrialization and economic development of the coun¬
try, and the high level of education of the people, in
comparison with other countries in Asia and the Far
East.
In a number of other areas, including Ceylon,
China (Taiwan), Hong Kong, and Singapore,
family planning activities are supported by the Govern¬
ment although the Government itself does not take a lead
in promoting such measures. In countries such as the
Federation of Malaya and Thailand, family planning
activities are supported by private organizations only,
with no direct assistance from the Government.
In those parts of the world where there is strong oppo¬
sition to birth-control programmes on moral, religious,
or other grounds, the solution of the population problems
is all the more difficult. The report of the United Nations
seminar on population problems in Latin America, men¬
tioned earlier contains the following remark on this
subject:
'Most Governments in Latin America would be very
hesitant to adopt a policy aimed at encouraging family
planning. For them, if they feel any need to slow down
population growth, the appropriate measures of policy
will be less direct they might be concerned, for instance,
with possible means of instilling into the minds of the
poorer and less educated classes of the people a keener
sense of responsibility and prudence in regard to marriage
and the birth of children, which would be consistent with
their religious ideals and the highest values of their
culture.'
In spite of all the difficulties, it may prove possible
within a decade or two to achieve with determined efforts,
appreciable reductions of birth rates in the countries
where national policies having this aim have been
adopted, or where they may be adopted in the near future.
But it scarcely seems realistic in view of all the circum¬
stances to expect a radical reduction of births in the
under-developed countries generally during the next ten
or twenty years.
Meanwhile, the population of most of these countries
can be expected to go on growing rapidlyquite possibly
even more rapidly than it is growing at present. Thus
it is absolutely imperative to find adequate solutions for
the problems of increasing food production sufficiently
during the decades ahead, especially in those countries
where the present standards of food consumption are
lowest and where the largest increases of population are
in store.
Experts are convinced that technical knowledge exists
to meet the world's present food shortages and to take
care of the needs that will result from population growth
for some time to come. Similarly there is enough tech¬
nical knowledge of the means of controlling births to
bring about a decided moderation of the rate of population
growth whenever the Governments and more important,
the people have the will to do so.
If everything possible were done to bring the existing
technical knowledge of food production methods to bear
fully throughout the world including, among other
things, large-scale programmes for training key person-
Unesco - Almasy
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
nel, vigorous and imaginative attacks on ignorance and
traditional inertia, and massive mobilization of capital
on a world-wide scale for investments in agricultural and
industrial development of the underdeveloped regions
the Freedom from Hunger Campaign might achieve its
great objective over the course of some decades. But
neither the present programmes nor the efforts to imple¬
ment them are adequate.
In India, for instance, the current large expenditure on
agricultural research and development has served to
increase food production by about 3 per cent a year, but
an 8.2 per cent annual increase is necessary to meet the
1965-1966 targets for adequate production.
With reference to the countries of Asia and the Far
East, the ECAFE report previously quoted puts the prob¬
lem in these terms:
'...If Asian agriculture adopted the modernized techni¬
ques used in some parts of the world, food production in
PLOUGHING A WET FURROW. Despite its relatively small area of
arable land, Japan's agricultural production will soon exceed its needs. This
is due to a greater use of chemical fertilizers, the mechanization of fishing
fleets, the elimination of illiteracy and improved ways of cultivation (below).
FOREWARNED
IS FOREARMED
a part from the direct help which the Freedom
from Hunger Campaign could provide, it
was Important, above all else, in teaching by
example the younger generation who, in twenty
years, would be sharing the world with
4,000,000,000 people. Everyone, everywhere,
must be brought to recognize that this, together
with the menace of nuclear destruction, is one of
the two most pressing problems of our times,
overriding patriotism, national aspirations or
ideologies.
RITCHIE CALDER
from " Common Sense About a Starving World "
Gollancz, London, 1962.
most of the countries could probably be made to keep
pace with this upsurge in demand for food. In addition,
research and technological advance may make it possible
to cultivate land which has been hitherto considered
uncultivable... On the assumption that average land pro¬
ductivity in Asia could be raised to Japanese levels, that
calorie supplies were increased to 2,500 per person per
day and the present low-protein type of diet maintained,
many countries could still support a population two or
three times as big as their present population. Assump¬
tions, on the other hand, of calorie supplies at the same
level as in, say, the western European countries, and a
diet of a high animal protein content would Imply that
many countries, even at the very high Japanese levels
of land productivity, could support fewer people than
their present populations...'
In addition to the programmes for increasing
agricultural efficiency through fertilizers,
seeds, mechanization and better techniques, there is the
technical possibility, although at somewhat higher costs,
of producing foods from sources not now exploited: algae,
yeasts, fish meals, and hydroponics (crop growing
without use of soil), and by the use of extractive methods
for converting plants directly into proteins and oils
instead of raising secondary sources of nutrients such as
fish and animals.
By 1970, the population of the earth will be increased
by over 500,000,000. Most of this increase can be expected
to occur in the underdeveloped, food-short regions of
Asia, Africa and Latin America, where population growth
rates in some countries are now higher than any that
have been known in the history of the human race.
Time is too precious to be wasted in arguments over
what steps should be taken first to deal with the problem
of population and food supply. Nothing less than an
'all out' attack on all major aspects of the problem can
bring success. To banish hunger and achieve a minimal
diet for all people in the face of rapid population growth
will at best take time. To check population growth in
those countries where such is the desire of the people and
their governments will also take time. And time is of
the essenoe."
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
46
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
A BOOST FOR PRODUCTIVITY
I N time of need, man has found ways
to win more food than he believed
possible from the soil. Switzerland, for
instance, despite its limited arable land
area, nearly doubled Its agricultural pro¬
duction during the Second World War.
1ULf OULD you like to know, for any
region of the world, which kind of
corn you can cross with another so as
to obtain a hybrid suitable for a given
climate or a given degree of humidity,
resistant to a certain kind of plant
disease or animal pest? At FAO Head¬
quarters in Rome, a young woman
presses buttons and the information you
need shoots out of a filing cabinet.
Like a huge matrimonial agency for
members of the grain family, this collec¬
tion of information has made possible
millions of successful marriages.
lUlAIZE production has been multiplied
thanks to hybrid varieties. Where
a harvest of 1,350 lbs per acre was con¬
sidered a great triumph a generation
ago, 3,500 lbs is now possible. New fer¬
tilizers have also enabled the yield of
many other cereals to be tripled or
quadrupled.
THE oceans are a vast food hamper of
practically inexhaustible resources.
The nutrient material produced annually
by the sea amounts to one hundred
million million tons, of which only a
minute proportion, the world over, is
recovered as edible fish. . .
THE upward trend of world fish pro¬
duction continued in 1961, rising to
a total of about 40 million tons, or some
7 % more than In 1960. A large part of
this expanded catch came from Peru
which has quickly become third largest
fish producer in the world, with 4.5 mil¬
lion tons in 1961 compared with only
500,000 tons in 1957. Production in¬
creased rapidly In the U.S.S.R. and also
in Japan where it Is estimated to have
reached six million tons in 1960 for the
first time. In several important fisheries
of Western Europe, however, catches
were smaller.
COFFEE, soybeans, cocoa, sugar, maize
and rice showed the largest increas¬
es in the world production of major
agricultural commodities in 1960-1961,
in comparison with average production
figures for 1953-1957.
A GRICULTURAL prices continued
to drift downwards during 1961
although more slowly than in 1960. By
the end of 1961, sugar prices were the
lowest in twenty-five years.
UiORLD meat production In 1961
(59.8 million tons) was 19% above
the average production between 1953-
1957.
|N the less-developed regions of the
world, the upward trend of food pro¬
duction has been especially marked In
Brazil, Egypt, the Federation of Malaya,
Iran, Israel, Japan and Mexico.
QCEANIA'S food production rose by
6% in 1960-1961. Australia's wheat
production was 13% more than in
1959-1960.
A surprising fact about increased food
production In Western Europe is
that the majority of countries where per
capita increases were most marked be¬
tween 19C2 and 1960 (Greece, Italy,
Spain and Yugoslavia) are in the eco¬
nomically less developed southern part
of the region.
rice production increased by
6% in 1960-1961 as the result of
abundant harvests in India, Japan and
Pakistan and in secondary producing
countries.
THE world's per capita food production
(excluding Mainland China) which
recovered Its pre-war level during the
period 1948-1949 and 1952-1953, has
now risen to about 14 % above the pre¬
war figure.
PRELIMINARY estimates show that
world milk production rose by about
2% in 1961. The largest proportional
Increase (about 4%) was in Western
Europe and Canada. In Australia pro¬
duction declined by about 5% owing
to adverse weather.
POLAND had a record grain harvest
of about 16 million tons In 1961 and
its agricultural output rose to a new
peak over 8 % above the previous year.
FIRST VICTORIES
Ihe fight against hunger has been going on
since the world began and man, until recently,
has not been well equipped for the struggle. Even
when he turned from hunting to agriculture, which did
much to secure a regular supply of food, the struggle
was still unrelenting. Droughts and floods, the vagaries
of weather and the attacks of diseases and pests often
destroyed his crops. Indeed, the history of mankind in
agriculture is marked by disastrous famines.
Records are incomplete, but we know that in the first
1,800 years of the Christian era there were 350 famine
years in Europe a famine in one year out of every
five. Even in Britain, a fertile island not usually
associated with famines, there was a recorded famine in
one year out of every ten. In other parts of the world
people suffered more severely. For instance, during the
2,000 years for which records are available in China there
have been 1,800 famines, almost an average of une every
year.
by Dr. Frank W. Parker
Assistant Director-General, Technical Dept., FAO
Real progress in the fight against hunger and malnutri¬
tion has been recent. Before 1800 most of the world
was ill-fed by the standards of today. As late as 1840
the French food supply was largely cereals and starchy
roots, with only one-third as much meat as they have
now. It had much the same characteristics as that of
some of the underdeveloped countries of today. % What
produced the change in the developed countries of the
world during the last 120 years?
Modern agricultural research may be said to have had
its beginning in the 1840's with the establishment of the
Rothamsted Agricultural Experimental Station in England
by Lawes and Gilbert and the chemical research of Liebig
in Germany. These pioneer research workers also
initiated the production and use of chemical fertilizers
and experiments that led to the understanding of the
value of legumes and their use in crop rotations. From
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
FIRST VICTORIES (Cont'd)
MOTORIZED FISHING BOATS and improved gear have done much to boost harvests from the
sea in areas of the world where boats and equipment have changed little since far-off times. Here,
traditional fishing craft now fitted with outboard motor shoots past sail-driven vessel off the coast
of Ghana, where fish catches have shown great increases, adding valuable protein to food supplies.
U.N.-Unesco
The spectacular example of Japan
48
this beginning, research expanded in Europe and in North
America with the establishment of the Federal Depart¬
ment of Agriculture and the Land Grant Colleges and
Experiment Stations in the 1860-90 period. The research
programme expanded from production and the utilization
of natural resources to include work on marketing, nutri¬
tion, and economic, social and organizational problems.
Agricultural development proceeded slowly throughout
the nineteenth and beginning of the twentieth century.
For example, in the United States the index of agricultural
production only increased about 20 per cent in the 25 years
from 1914 to 1939. In this period, however, production and
economic research, agricultural education and extension
laid the basis for rapid progress when increased produc¬
tion was essential.
World War II and the post-war period produced the
demand and the other economic incentives favourable to
increased production in North America, Western Europe,
Japan and Oceania. Throughout these regions program¬
mes were developed to make this demand felt effectively
at the farm level, and supplies of credit were provided to
enable farmers to secure the material needed to put
advanced technical knowledge into practice on a wide
scale.
In North America, despite some restrictions, agricultural
production is currently 50 per cent greater than in the pre¬
war period. That is, the rate of increase over the last
20 years has been more than three times the 1914-1939
rate. In Europe, current production is about 25 per cent
greater than before the war. These regions, and
Oceania, have attained adequate levels of nutrition for
nearly the entire population, and they are currently more
concerned with the difficulties associated with agricultural
abundance than with the means of increasing production.
This new situation may be attributed in large measure
to the wide-scale application of the accumulated store of
science and technology to agriculture, as well as to
changes in the economic and institutional conditions at
the farm level which encourage its use. The work that
was started in the 1840's is paying great dividends. Let
us now see what is occurring in the rest of the world.
Japan, the most highly industrialized country in Asia,
steadily increased agricultural production in the period
1880-1940. Current production is more than one-third
greater than pre-war. The population growth in recent
years has been about one "per cent per year. Agriculture
has made a substantial contribution to the great improve¬
ment in the national economy and diet in the last decade.
As in the West, Japan's increased production is due to
the rapid application of science and technology to
agriculture. This is reflected in the level of use of
insecticides, fertilizers, and increased mechanization by
the use of garden tractors and other machinery. This
progress was made possible by suitable institutions to
serve agriculture and economic incentives, including
agrarian reform, to encourage farmers to make the
investments required.
The example of Japan and Taiwan, which is also
increasing agricultural production at a good rate, is of
great significance for the rest of Asia. Their record shows
that the application of scientific methods and practices is
as effective in Asia as in North America and Europe.
The foregoing examples of positive achievements in the
fight against hunger show that in the more developed
and industrialized countries of North America, Western
Europe, Asia (Japan) and Oceania the battle against
hunger has been largely won, the great achievements
having been made in the last 35 years. The real question
before the world today is whether similar, or even greater,
progress can be made in the underdeveloped countries of
the world. We shall now examine some evidence that
gives at least a tentative answer to that question.
A number of the less developed countries, including
Mexico, Greece, Yugoslavia and Israel, have rapidly
increased agricultural production in the 1950's. Produc¬
tion in this group of countries has increased at the rate
of 5 to 8 per cent per year, whereas, with the exception of
Mexico and Israel, the rate of increase in population has
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
Almasy, Paris H. P. VERSUS OX POWER. Studies and experiments to evolve cultivation methods appropriate
to local and regional conditions and material resources have already paid big dividends in richer
harvests. Above, comparative experiment in tractor and ox-drawn ploughing takes place in same
Mexican field to ensure identical soil and weather conditions for a fair comparison of results.
been less than 1.5 per cent. In Greece, the production of
cereals increased from an average of 1.5 million tons per
year in 1949-52 to 2.5 million tons in 1959-60. In Mexico,
the increase was from 4.0 to 7.4 million tons in the same
period.
How was this accomplished? Both countries Increased
the area under irrigation, and developed and now use
improved high yielding, disease-resistant varieties of
major cereal crops. The use of chemical fertilizers
increased from 48.0 to 129.2 thousand tons of plant
nutrient in Greece, and from 21.5 to 172.5 thousand tons
in Mexico. In other words, these countries applied
essentially the same practices and technology that had
increased agricultural production effectively in North
America, Western Europe, Oceania and Japan. Associated
with the improved technology were good agricultural
research, extension, the provision of credit and cost-price
relationships that gave an incentive for production.
The countries were substantially assisted by foreign aid
programmes. Greece, for example, is estimated to have
CONT'D ON PAGE 52
THE 'ALCHEMY' OF FOOD
I N a farm in Malaya, pig raising and
fish breeding complement each other.
Pig manure Is put into the fish pond as
fertilizer for a water plant on which the
fish feed. The fish in turn are used as
pig food. Another plant called ipomoea
grows in the pond and provides the pigs
with fresh fodder. According to an FAO
specialist, "a pond suitably prepared to
receive the wastes from a pigsty can
produce, at no cost whatever, 250 lbs
of ipomoea and 7 lbs of fish per acre
daily."
BT ISH breeding has still plenty of
resources In reserve. The African
tilapia, which has been called a "mira¬
cle" fish, is now being bred on an
industrial scale in different areas of
Asia and in the West Indies.
T HE first factory for the commercial
production of fish flour was built in
Sweden in 1959. With a high (80%)
protein content, this flour is a foodstuff
five times as rich as the fish it is made
from. Added to traditional foods, fish
flour is likely to become an important
arm in the struggle against protein
deficiency.
CHLORELLA, a tiny fresh water algae,
is capable of transforming practically
all the energy It absorbs from sunlight
into vegetation. In 12 hours it increases
its weight fourfold. Its annual yield per
acre is over 100 tons ten times that of
wheat. An area five miles square can
produce enough protein for 80 million
people. Chlorella has six times as
much protein as rice, 30 times as much
vitamin A as calf's liver and four times
as much vitamin C as spinach, which it
resembles in taste.
I N the Far East noodles are now being
made of Zooplankton. In Thailand,
for example, more than 5,000 tons of
this highly nourishing foodstuff which
abounds in the sea, are eaten yearly.
Living on a diet composed almost entire¬
ly of plankton, the whale becomes
huge enough to provide 15 tons of oil,
as much fat as 500 pigs and as much
meat as 72 head of cattle.
Dr. Melvln Calvin has been awarded
the Nobel Prize for having, with the
help of radioactive tracers, worked out
the complete cycle by which the grow¬
ing plant takes the energy from the sun,
the elements from the air and the miner¬
als from the soil and converts them
into the sugars and starches of our basic
foodstuffs. Work is going on, notably in
the U.S.S.R., on the further stages by
which plants produce proteins. Perhaps
man may one day be able to start with
the elements themselves and, by-passing
the intermediates of the soil, the plants
and the animals which eat them In order
to feed us, make food as a druggist
compounds a prescription.
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
FARMING GOES NORTH. Big changes are now
taking place in the world's bleak Arctic tundra, until
recently the domain of animals, with only sparse and
scattered populations such as the Lapps of Northern
Europe and the j-eindeer-herding peoples of Siberia.
Today farming is going north and the Soviet, Canadian
and American peoples are growing wheat in their northern
territories. Alaska's lands under cultivation now cover
over 100,000 square miles, or about half the area of
France. On the Taymyr Peninsula, within the Arctic
Circle, Soviet farmers are growing maize and potatoes.
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
51
Official Soviet photo
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
FIRST VICTORIES (Cont'd)
Modern technology opens the way
received the services of 10 agricultural experts per year
from 1955-61, and about 25 fellows were sent abroad each
year for study of approved agricultural methods. Mexico
has probably had the assistance of 30-40 foreign experts
and has sent about 50 men abroad for training in each
year of the same six-year period. Yugoslavia has had a
rather exceptional technical assistance programme in that
great emphasis was placed on sending men for observa¬
tion and training abroad at least 1,400 in the six years.
It also received the services of about 25 international
experts per year.
This assistance made it possible for these countries to
accelerate agricultural production more rapidly than if
they had had to depend strictly on their own resources.
The transfer of knowledge, together with the economic
assistance provided by foreign aid programmes, was
undoubtedly a major factor in their success, even though
they themselves had to do virtually all the work.
Another group of 10 to 15 countries, of which
Brazil, the United Arab Republic, the Philip¬
pines and India may be considered examples, made good
progress in agricultural production during the post-war
period, even though the progress was not as striking as
in the countries just discussed. Most of the countries in
this large group increased production at a rate of 2.5 to
4.0 per cent per year, while the population was increasing
at the rate of 1.5 to 2.5 per cent.
This, plus some degree of economic expansion provided
for a modest increase in per capita food supplies and
living standards. We should keep in mind that all of
these countries are predominantly agricultural; crop
yields are low and illiteracy is high. In other words, they
are in a relatively early stage of economic development.
We may now examine the progress of India in more
detail, since complete data are available in the recent
publication "The Third Five-Year Plan." During the
period of the first two Five Year Plans (in 1950-51 and
1960-61) India Increased agricultural production by 41
per cent and food grains production by 46 per cent. This
approximates to an increase of 3.5 per cent per year. During
the same period the population increased 21.5 per cent;
consequently, with agricultural production increasing
substantially faster than the population, there was some
improvement in food supplies per capita and levels of
nutrition. Of course, receipt of agricultural surpluses
from other countries has helped as well. It is estimated
that per capita food consumption increased from 1,800 to
2,100 calories per day, and that per capita consumption
of cloth increased from 9.2 to 15.5 yards per annum, or 68
per cent.
These gains in agricultural production were accom¬
panied by an increase in the area irrigated of 36 per cent,
318 per cent in the use of nitrogen fertilizers, 773 per cent
in the amount of credit provided by co-operatives, and
similar increases in other items that contribute to im¬
proved agricultural production.
Of equal, or greater, importance for long-term deve¬
lopment is the foundation that has been laid through edu¬
cation, training and the development of institutions
which support and serve agriculture. The community
development programme, starting in 1952, now reaches
370,000 of India's 500,000 villages. Some 35,000 village-level
workers were trained and placed in service during the
co ten-year period. Local government has been given grea¬
ter powers and increased responsibility for development.
A National Farmers' Organisation, with an affiliated
Young Farmers' Association, has grown and functioned
with increasing effectiveness since 1955. Many new agri¬
cultural colleges were started. The number of entering
students increased from about 1,200 in 1950-51 to 4,600
in 1960-61. This obviously provides for a substantial
increase in trained personnel to serve agriculture.
India's agricultural development has been accompanied
and supported by development in other fields. For exam¬
ple, the Index of industrial production increased 94 per
cent in the ten-year period. The installed power capacity
increased 148 per cent; general education, as Indicated by
student enrolment, increased 85 per cent, and technical
education 239 per cent.
India is believed to represent a substantial number of
countries that have made reasonably good, but not out¬
standing, progress in agricultural production and deve¬
lopment during the last ten years. Probably of greater
importance than their actual physical achievement in
production is the groundwork that has been laid for even
more rapid production increases in the 1960's. The hope
of this is indicated in India's Third Five-Year Plan tar¬
gets which call for a 30 per cent increase in agricultural
production, or at a rate of about 5 per cent per year.
India's agricultural development was assisted by the
work of about 150 foreign experts per year through various
international programmes, and by a much larger number
of Indians receiving training abroad under the same pro¬
gramme. These technical assistance programmes made
significant contributions in dairy development and animal
health; agricultural education, research and training; fer¬
tilizer requirements and use; soil conservation and fores¬
try; fisheries; and crop improvement, including the deve¬
lopment of hybrid maize.
The results of ten years of technical assistance in India
give strong support to the thesis that it is one effective
means of accelerating agricultural development. It has
made an important contribution to the development of
institutions and trained manpower that undoubtedly will
provide great assistance to future development.
There are many countries in Asia, Africa and Latin
America where the increase in agricultural production in
the post-war period has been unsatisfactory, especially
when considered in relation to the growth of population.
There are many technical, social, economic and political
reasons for this. However, it is not lack of technical
knowledge of what needs to be done.
Among the great positive achievements of the
last 10-15 years is the improved understanding
of the ways and means of accelerating agricultural
production and development under a wide range of
conditions. Increasingly effective use of this knowledge
will doubtless be made in the decades ahead.
A second positive achievement is the realisation in all
countries that technical and economic assistance can
make a great contribution to accelerate agricultural and
economic development in the new nations of the world.
As a result it seems probable that the level of technical
and economic assistance in the next ten years will double
or treble that of the last ten.
In 1970 and 1980 we should look back on a period of
greater growth in improvement of living standards and
levels of nutrition than in the past 10 to 15 years. At the
same time, through continued research new facts and
methods will be developed that will provide the basis for
continued progress in the fight for improved nutrition and
living standards for the increased population of the world.
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
E. Khaldéia, A.P.N., Moscow
THE BOUNTIFUL STEPPE. In the Soviet Union, the dread Golodnaïa, or Hunger
Steppe, has been given a new name: "The Bountiful Steppe." Between 1 949 and 1 956,
175 million acres of virgin land were brought under cultivation and produced rich
grain harvests (above). There are still vast amounts of empty space in the world. In
Ethiopia alone, more than 180 million of the world's most fertile acres lie fallow.
Brazil's Amazon basin (nearly one-twentieth of world's land surface) is still virgin soil.
53
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
-
NEW WORLD STRATEGY
FOR SURPLUS STOCKS
NEWS ITEM: A 100 million dollar
World Food Programme using sur¬
plus food to promote economic and
social development, and conducted
jointly by FAO and the U.N. Is
expected to go into operation by
mid-1962 following final endors¬
ement of the plan by the U.N.
Economic and Social Council in
April of this year.
../
54
THE global picture of millions of
people going hungry in many
countries while the well-fed inhabitants of
others put great surplus stocks into stor¬
age has been described as "the paradox
of a world starving to death knee-deep
in food." The paradox is more apparent
than real, however, for if all surplus stocks
of food were shared out they could no¬
where near meet the needs of all the
food-deficient countries.
The primary answer to the world's food
problem is the development of food pro¬
duction where it is needed. With a few
exceptions the underfed countries have
the basic conditions necessary for produc¬
ing more food. They have fertile land,
manpower, and water to bring up the
crops. Scientific knowledge and advice
are available and are being made increas¬
ingly available. But these are not enough.
More complicated resources must be un¬
locked: dams and irrigation channels must
be built; fertilizer factories and seed farms
must be set up and vaccines produced
to protect livestock against disease.
Schools and colleges must be built and
staffed to produce a new generation of
skilled and scientific agriculturists; roads
and railroads must be developed.
These are the material resources needed.
If the under-privileged countries are to
accumulate these resources by themselves
from the little bit of their production that
they can spare over and above their day-
to-day needs they will be a long time
accumulating them.
The fact is that there Is very little sur¬
plus income to spare for long-term invest¬
ment in most of these countries. Their
choice is between reducing even further
the standards of living of their people in
order to devote a larger part of national
production to long-term development, or
inaction which will perpetuate the present
conditions unless help comes from out¬
side.
Since the war substantial aid has been
coming from the more prosperous nations.
Under a plan begun In 1954, for example,
the U.S.A. has given away or sold on
special terms 10,000 million dollars worth
of food and farm products to 40 countries.
Since 1960 this programme has been en¬
larged in the U.S. "Food for Peace" plan.
Canada and Australia have also been in
the forefront of surplus food distribution
to. countries within the British Common¬
wealth under the Colombo plan. But until
now almost all past surplus disposal pro¬
grammes have been carried out by bilateral
arrangements and not as a world-wide
plan.
In October 1960, the U.N. General
USIS OVERFLOWING grain storage elevator In the U.S. A., which has large
surpluses of agricultural produce. A large-scale distribution of surplus
food through U.N. channels should now help under-privileged countries
Assembly unanimously adopted a resolu¬
tion, proposed by the U.S., asking for a
study of the possibilities of distributing
surplus food through the United Nations
system as a contribution to social and
economic development. As a result, In
June 1961, FAO presented a report to the
U.N. Economic and Social Council for a
plan to "end the days of surplus food
disposal and usher in an era of surplus
food utilization for the social and economic
development of the world at large."
Entitled "Development through Food"
(see bibliography p. 64), the study examined
the potential uses of aid in the form of
food in under-privileged countries; it show¬
ed how surplus food supplies could be
used as capital to help give work to
unemployed men on development projects
such as roads, dams, school buildings and
industrial schemes, the workers being
paid partly in food, or the recipient country
selling the food to its people (thereby
helping to combat inflationary prices) and
using the resulting domestic currency
received to pay wages and other national
development costs. The report also showed
how surplus food could be used to. establish
national food reserves, allow governments
to undertake land reforms without causing
crippling food shortages, and be used in
developing livestock industries by taking
pressure off eroded and over-worked graz¬
ing lands.
Food surpluses could also provide school
lunches and supplement the rations of
workers on special heavy industrial develop¬
ment projects. Finally, food surpluses could
be used for more effective international
emergency relief in cases of disaster.
On the basis of this study, the FAO
governing conference last November
approved the plan for a World Food Pro¬
gramme to be carried out jointly by U.N.
and FAO with headquarters based at FAO
in Rome, and working under the supervision
of a 20-nation Intergovernmental Committee.
This group met in February and drew up
details for the establishment and operation
of a 5100 million three-year World Food
Programme with voluntary contributions
made in food, cash and services.
It was this plan that the Economic and
Social Council approved in April thus giving
the green liaht to the World Food Pro¬
gramme. A special "pledging" conference
is expected to be held later in 1962. But
already the United States has pledged
$40 million worth of food, and Canada
and Denmark have offered 55 million
and $2 million respectively in food and
cash.
The World Food Programme opens a
new international chapter In the problem
of distributing food surpluses to those
regions where there are food shortages
and where they can do the most "economic
and social good."
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
THE ANATO
UNDERDEVELOP
With this issue The Unesco Courier begins publication of a series of
articles on the main aspects of the economic development process,
particularly as they impinge on the work of the United Nations family
of organizations. These articles are taken from a new study produced
by the United Nations as part of the World Campaign Against Hunger.
Y OF
ENT
H ARDLY any international problem is more
frequently discussed in our time than econo¬
mic development. Few questions, however, are more
complex or less understood by the non-specialist.
An important initiative within the context of economic
development was taken on July 1, 1960 when the Food
and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations
launched the Freedom from Hunger Campaign.
Dr. Norman Wright, Deputy Director-General of FAO,
has said that, "from the physical and biological point of
view," there is no reason why food production should not
be expanded to meet even the world's anticipated needs,
at least to the end of the century.
It is important, however, to view this authoritative
statement realistically. It will not be possible to under¬
take and, still more, to sustain so great an increase of
food production without the help of economic and social
measures which go far beyond the improvement of
agriculture and fisheries. It is this background theme
which is treated in the present study.
A major objective of economic development is to ensure
higher earnings, and therefore increased purchasing
power, for the mass of the people in the economically
less developed countries, of which many are the concern
of the Freedom from Hunger Campaign. It is well-
known that most of the inhabitants of the poorer coun¬
tries have to spend a much higher proportion of their
earnings on food than do most of those in the countries
classified as economically advanced. The margin of
money left over for other purposes is therefore pitiably
small and this fact serves as a brake on the whole process
of economic development by which alone the lot of the
impoverished and underfed could be improved.
Some simple figures on earnings give further point to
the existing imbalance. In 1959 the average annual per
capita income was about $2,250 for the United States,
about $1,000 for some of the West European countries
and for Australia and New Zealand. For the less deve¬
loped countries as a whole it was in the neighbourhood
of $100 with an average of only $70 - $80 over great areas
of Asia, Africa and Latin America.
This imbalance is likely to become more and more
marked for, at the present time, average incomes are
increasing very much faster in the more prosperous
countries than in the rest. During the 1950's they rose
by over $200 in the United States and Western Europe
and probably by less than $10 in the other countries.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
Sunil Janah, Calcutta Ancient water wheel of the kind still used to Irrigate crops in India.
55
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
56
All countries in some
way underdeveloped
(Cont'd from previous page)
If countries classed today as economically underdevel¬
oped are to experience a real rise incomes and to move
into the category of the more prosperous, malnutrition is
one of the principal evils which must be attacked. It is,
however, by no means alone. Both health and education
need to be vastly improved. Technical training must
make possible a far better utilization of resources. The
economies of countries that depend for earnings on one
or two primary products must be diversified to absorb
the shocks and uncertainties of world trade. Capital
must be forthcoming for investment in roads, railways,
harbours, airfields, factories, hospitals, schools, training
colleges, as well as for industry.
It is therefore important to see hunger and malnutri¬
tion as part of a vicious circle of factors opposing econo¬
mic advance. The physical weakness to which they give
rise reduces the working capacity of many millions and
opens the way to increasing poverty and disease. Disease
is hard to combat where the hungry and poverty-stricken
are ignorant of hygiene, but their ignorance also extends
to the new techniques and methods which, if introduced
among them, could help to increase their output of food,
both to eat and to sell. Until far-reaching measures are
taken in the economic and social fields, these people will
have neither funds to start the process of economic
development nor the possibility of acquiring them by
their own efforts.
While the problem of eradicating or reducing hunger is
not one that can be approached in isolation, malnutrition
constitutes in itself a major obstacle to economic progress.
Not much is likely to be accomplished in other respects,
as long as hunger continues to afflict so many of the
world's potential producers of wealth.
Each of the two forms of solution the direct or agri¬
cultural approach to the production of food and the indi¬
rect approach through a supporting movement over the
economy as a whole must pay full attention to the needs
and problems of the farmers, not only because it is they
who produce the food but also because they still form a
majority of the world's population. Their co-operation
will be essential to any programme by which economic
progress is sought through industrialization and other
methods not connected with food production as such.
General industrial and economic development is a vital
part of Freedom from Hunger. The success of that cam¬
paign depends upon expanding markets for food as well
as upon rising production of food. Increased commercial
demand for the food that farmers produce can come
only from greater buying power on the part of consumers
who are not farmers, both in the same country and in
other countries.
Economic development, putting more people at work,'
and raising the productivity and the income of workers
generally, is the only road to greater buying power and
greater demand for food. For all these reasons, speeding
economic development is one of the essential steps
towards a world free from hunger.
What do economists mean when they call a country
underdeveloped? The expression "underdeveloped" is
difficult to define in precise terms.
All countries are in some respects underdeveloped, for
all are still in the developing process. There is none
which has reached the stage where no further progress
is possible or where no useful changes could be intro¬
duced. It is nevertheless clear that we can distinguish
between those countries which have reached an advanced
stage of economic development and those who are still in
a more primitive phase.
Probably the broadest distinction is to be found in the
distribution of the national income through various levels
of the population. Those countries which are economi¬
cally advanced have a much higher general level of pros¬
perity and superior standards of living among the mass
of their people.
(To be Lintinued)
efr \
FAR EAST
EUROPE
U.S.S.R.
NORTH AMERICA
LATIN AMERICA
AFRICA
NEAR EAST
W
U RLD'S
FARM AND
NON-FARM
POPULATIUN,
1959
Farm population
shown in white
Non-Farm
in black
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
Air France, ParisLEPTIS THE MAGNIFICENT. To the people of present-day Libya launched on a programme of economic
betterment and higher living standards, the magnificent ruins of Leptis Magna, one of the oldest cities on the
Tripolitanian coast, are a reminder that their forebears built grandly and lived well on the products of a then fertile soil.
Buildings like amphitheatre (above) with its colonnaded courts, made Leptis one of the proudest cities of Roman Africa.
WAKING THE SLEEPING LANDS
T:
by Kathleen McLaughlin
he mediterranean region has been called the
cradle of western civilization. Since the
prewar era, the cradle has been rocking again at an
unprecedented rate.
In 1937 the population was 136,000,000. By 1957 it was up
to 175,000,000. Statistics indicate that by 1975 it will have
reached approximately 275,000,000.
- From any angle, an 80 per cent upsurge in population
in less than 40 years poses grave problems. They become
graver when, as in this instance, the countries affected
can even now provide only a pinched existence for their
multitudes.
Here civilization is in a race against the calendar.
Economic progress must be accelerated, while the margin
of time still holds, between the rising generation and
looming disaster.
The challenge is to erase deterioration stemming from
a thousand years of misuse of the land; to achieve
balance between agriculture and other sections of the
economies; and to lift average per capita income to a
point somewhat more comparable to that of industrialized
nations.
For countries on the European side of the Mediterra¬
nean, conditions are less difficult and prospects brighter
than for the Middle East and African nations on the
opposite shore.
Despite severe handicaps, progress here has been
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
57
]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[
SLEEPING LANDS (Cont'd)
Where every drop of water counts
definite since 1950. In industrial phases at least,
advancement has been fairly remarkable and regardless of
fluctuations, national income has risen at the satisfactory
average of six per cent annually. To expedite improve¬
ment, United Nations experts contemplate measures
tailored to conditions In each country. For these southern
European nations the goal Is to raise gross domestic
production from $27,500,000,000 In 1956 to $69,000,000,000
by 1975, continuing the present rate of advancement of
five per cent per year.
Across the water to the south, the assets in the Middle
East and North African countries shrink in ratio as
liabilities expand. Four-fifths of this land is desert.
Inadequate communications have always hampered
efficient administration, and destructive use of the soil
continues virtually unabated.
Average per capita income in these countries at present
is just about $155 a year.
In the Middle East and North African countries the
U.N. objective is to bring their combined production to
$29,000,000,000 by 1975. The proposed annual rate of
increase of 5.5 per cent would be more than twice the
current momentum. This would double the 1956 agricul¬
tural volume, and triple the output of goods and services.
More than five years ago the United Nations began
assessment of debits and credits that would have to be
weighed, within the scope of the Mediterranean project.
Experts compiled the data and wrote the report. Its more
than 200 pages of text, tables and graphs show widely
divergent conditions, rates of progress, and future
potentials.
Water is the key to the major problems. Enough dams,
reservoirs and irrigation canals to conserve and utilize
rainfall and surface waters to the maximum would open
up and make arable extensive areas not now cultivated
and increase many-fold the yields in those presently
tilled. Systematic searches for underground Water
sources are already proceeding. Adoption of dry-farming
methods in the most amenable arid areas holds further
promise for the unfolding years. Reforestation of
suitable treeless areas is a "must".
Here is a project of proportions so mammoth that it
has taken years merely to outline what must be done,
and where, and when. There is only one executor possible
United Nations and its family of specialized
agencies.
By this time the natural priorities have been worked
out. In the van will come the United Nations Special
Fund to make the indispensable preliminary surveys,
whenever the resources of a country prove insufficient to
finance them alone. Once the findings have been
weighed, plans can be adjusted to determine which of the
other agencies will be required, and on what scale and
timing.
F REQUENTLY FAO or ILO or WMO will have had
occasion to make concurrent preliminary
reconnaissances in their particular spheres, and can
plunge forthwith into their different programmes.
Unesco will take on the educational facets and WHO will
set about prevention and control of any existing
communicable diseases, as well as teaching hygiene and
sanitation, opening clinics and instructing native
technicians.
There will be need in plenty for OPEX (Operation and
Executive Personnel), to recruit administrators for two-
or three-year contracts, to serve in and with the minis¬
tries of countries still plagued with a shortage of top¬
flight officials of their own. Each one will train his suc¬
cessor "on the job."
To forge ahead in its contest with population growth
the Mediterranean region must plan shrewdly and swiftly,
taking first things first. Encouragement for those most
hopeful of progress came recently through a decision of
co the Special Fund to help finance several long-term
development projects there.
They cover ground-water development in Greece; pilot-
programming of the Antalya area in Turkey; watershed
management and ground-water collection programmes in
Israel; soil surveys and irrigation and drainage projects in
the United Arab Republic; agricultural research in
Tunisia, and a survey for preparation of an agricultural
development plan in the Rif region of Morocco. Total
investment by the Special Fund will amount to $3,624,100.
In these cases the Special Fund leads the way for
eventual programmes which sooner or later will engage
the services of every one of the U.N. agencies, as many
are already at work in some of the countries named. They
are active on reform of land tenure systems; water and
flood control; training of additional technicians; weather
and climate recordings; civil aviation problems; transport
and telecommunications; health services; and improve¬
ment of basic energy supplies.
All these and many more aspects ' of life in the
Mediterranean countries have to march forward in
concert if the region is to be saved and restored to its
former glory as the centre of western culture and civiliza¬
tion.
S pace precludes detailed examination of the
individual countries and their pace of progress
to date, with "assists" from certain U.N. agencies. One
country closeup, however, can bring the sjene alive.
On Christmas Eve of 1951 a new and sovereign nation
emerged in an ancient land on the shores of the-
Mediterranean. Libyans celebrated in an atmosphere of
gaiety touched with solemnity.
Their ancestors in past ages had walked proudly and
built grandly, but on that December 24 of Libya's
independence only crumbling ruins were left to testify to
their imposing cities, their thriving commerce, the
productiveness of their once fertile soil. Even in decay,
the great city-port of Leptis Magna, birthplace of one of
Rome's greatest emperors, Septimus Severus, still speaks
eloquently of former beauty, culture and prosperity.
Rarely has a state raised its standard with so little on
which to rely to meet the expectations of the future.
With one of the lowest levels of living in the Middle East,
and a very high birth rate, Libya had few apparent natural
resources; a terrain 85 per cent of which is sand and rock
desert; light and capricious rainfall, and frequent
droughts.
Only 5,000 Libyans had had as much as five years of
schooling, and there were just 14 university graduates in
the entire country.
Civil service administrators were nonexistent for fairly
obvious reasons. Under the Italian occupation they were
neither required, nor trained. In the postwar period of
United Nations trusteeship the three provinces Tripoli-
tania, Cyrenaica and the Fezzan were administered by
the British and the French, engrossed with immediate
emergencies.
The most fertile soil occupies a narrow strip bordering
the Mediterranean. The rest is now arid, except for a
few oases. Yet 93 per cent of Libyan production is
agricultural, and 87 per cent of the population depends
for its living on the land. More than 90 per cent of the
people are nomadic, roving with their herds in search of
pasturage and practicing shifting cultivation.
As a "Child of the United Nations," Libya looked for
economic and financial help to the same source from
which had come its political sovereignty.
United Nations technical assistance in the average less-
developed country is confined to a few sectors of the
economy. In Libya, it has radiated out in every direction
like the spokes of a wheel.
On this largely barren land a depressed agriculture has
been and remains the crux of economic woes. At times
a score of experts from FAO have been busy there on a
wide variety of projects.
Since 1953 Malcolm Amott, an Australian sheep expert,
CONT'D ON PAGE 60
]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[
:3ító&
FROM SAND
AND DESERT ROCK
Since achieving independence In 1951, as
"A Child of the United Nations", Libya has
been striving to overcome overwhelming
obstacles to economic and social development:
a terrain 85 % of which is sand and rock
desert, sparse rainfall and a depressed agri¬
culture (on which 87 % of people look for a
livelihood). With help and advice from U.N.
technical assistance specialists, more and more
farmers are replacing outmoded farming
methods (left) with newer techniques and
better tools. Under a programme to achieve
a better balance between farming and other
sections of the economy, young Libyans
receive technical Instruction (below) In the
Vocational Training Institution at Tripoli
Unesco photos
59
]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[
THE SLEEPING LANDS (CONT'D)
Metamorphosis of a nation
has been in Libya, commissioned by FAO to improve the
breed of fat-tailed Barbary sheep as a first step toward
establishment of an industry to supply wool blankets and
carpets. These animals, believed to be survivors of flocks
that roamed the Nile valley as long ago as 2,000 B.C.,
represent the wealth of the nomads.
Tough and hardy, they are among the few beasts able
to subsist in so Inhospitable an environment. During
drought periods they live on the fat stored in their tails,
while other animals perish of thirst. This hazard has
been reduced through the sinking of tube wells, the
stocks of fodder and the re-seeding of ranges fostered by
Mr. Arnott and his colleagues.
E
60
STiMATES are that some 7,000 sheep alive today
wo,uld have died under conditions prevailing
only a few years ago, and that 20,000 others have reached
a peak of physical well-being.
On two experimental farms in Tripolitania the Austral¬
ian has scored notable gains with his work of up-grading
the strain. From Turkey he imported the superior
Karaman type for selective cross-breeding with the Libyan
Barbarys, whose short, nondescript coats held scant
promise of the quality of wool fibre demanded for rug-
making.
He Introduced inoculation against the diseases and pests
to which all sheep are susceptible; the process of the
sheep-dip to prevent their recurrence; mechanical wool-
shearing, and other modern techniques.
Nomads who paused in their wanderings for a look at
these goings-on were more than cynical at first. A
couple of years later they were inclined to be impressed,
scanning the first generation of the new strain produced
by cross-breeding, and comparing their larger, sturdier
bodies and thick white fleece with their own rag-tag and
bob-tail sheep. About 100 owners of sizable flocks have
adopted these procedures, and have been more than
gratified by the visible improvements. Converting the
nomad sheep farmers will take time, but the trend is
gaining.
Since 1956, the principal research station for sheep-
improvement has been competently operated by a young
Libyan, trained under the EPTAS fellowship programme
in a two-year course in Australia. Arnott has moved on to
establish another in the Fezzan.
On permanent farms response has been speedier
and resistance far less. At points, dry-farming
methods have been demonstrated, as they are practiced
in the southwestern Great Plains region of the United
States, and in the dry areas of Australia. Each season
they have been adopted by more of the cultivators. The
Government allocated $411,000 for the purchase of the
requisite equipment, earmarking almost one-fourth for
improved types of hand tools.
The latter were loaned without fee to the farmers
co-operating. Scythes, motor pumps, animal-drawn carts
and steel ploughs replaced many of the primitive sickles,
spades, wooden plough, stone hammers and threshing
sledges used in Libya for centuries.
They have helped materially in lifting the annual
output levels. They have also provided an appreciated
dividend, by way of their contribution toward modest rises
in rural living standards.
Heavier, powered machines were put into Cyrenaica
province in the autumn of 1958, accompanied by demons¬
trations of their use and care. In that season 6,600 acres
of forage and cereal crops were seeded and cultivated,
most of which would normally have been allowed to lie
fallow. The superiority of the yields carried its message.
In 1959 the acreage was tripled.
BLINDFOLDED STUDENTS learn touch-typing
in clerical classes of Libya's Vocational Training
Institution at Tripoli. In a country in which, ten
years ago, only 5,000 people had had as much as
five years of schooling and civil service administrators
were non-existent, clerical class students can find
jobs immediately on completion of their course.
A MATTER
The problem before us is that of overcoming grinding
povertynothing more, nothing less. The challenge
of survival bolls down to this: we must multiply today's
output of goods and services. It is food that hungry mouths
need, employment that idle muscles long for, creative
tasks that their minds and energies are eager to tackle.
Can we win this war against want ? Can enough be accom¬
plished in time to meet reasonable demands of these people
now on this planet and those of the tremendous numbers
of additional people who will be with us in the near future ?
]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[
In every phase of agriculture the gradual evolution
continues. The Government actively supports mechaniza¬
tion and newer techniques; extended use of chemical
fertilizers; dissemination of better seeds; credit plans for
farmers; anchoring of shifting sand dunes by plantings
of grasses and shrubs; the processing and marketing of
dates; the spread of veterinary services, and training of
students destined to administer the extension services
familiar in more advanced countries.
Education from the primary level on up was imperative
in Libya. But in a country with so many illiterates, few
teachers could be located. They had to be trained, and
the question arose where? Existing schoolhouses were
Unesco - Guy de Belleval
OF LIFE OR DEATH
The job before us is indeed one of appalling dimen¬
sions, of bewildering complexity and terrible urgency.
But that job is not insuperable. There is no question in
my mind that at least ninety of the hundred low-income
countries have the resources physical and human to
provide in reasonable time decent living standards for their
people. The underlying reason for underdevelopment is
under-utilization of these resources.
Paul G, Hoffman,
Director General of the U.N. Special Fund,
The War We Must Win, W.A.Y. Forum, Spring 1961.
either destroyed or badly damaged, and were in any case
far from adequate in number. Makeshift quarters had to
serve, and many Arab-speaking instructors were made
available through a cultural agreement the Government
signed with Egypt.
Improvization, under the circumstances, was a natural
alternative for one of the educators sent by Unesco
to organize a primary grade system in Libya. Dr. Ade¬
line Babbitt of the United States calmly seated her
classes of small pupils on the ground. She used the sand
for a blackboard on which to do sums, draw maps or
teach writing; date pits and small pebbles to inculcate
the fundamentals or arithmetic, and a story-hour to
convey the lessons of history in the absence of textbooks,
blackboards, paper or pencils. And the children learned.
Conditions improved gradually. Buildings were repair¬
ed, class-room equipment was provided, young Libyan
teachers managed to keep at least one lesson ahead of
their students. Enrolment grew, especially among girls,
for whom educational opportunities have traditionally
been all but nonexistent.
At the elementary level an Increase of 119.7 per
cent was registered for girls in the first five
years of free schooling, compared with 69.2 per cent for
boys. By 1957 school attendance for both was 46,299 as
against 26,269 in 1952. Libya does not yet boast a
university, but in the first half-decade preparatory school
enrollment rose from 393 to 1,954, or 497.2 per cent, and
that of secondary schools from 142 to 620, or 436.6 per
cent.
Star rating' for performance belongs to the Libyan
Government Vocational Training Institution at Tripoli,
which the International Labour Organization of the
United Nations took over in 1953. By 1957 ILO represen¬
tatives were able on schedule to turn over the installa¬
tion to Libyans they had prepared, and who now carry on
as instructors.
From the beginning, the objective was to train junior-
grade skilled workers for Government shops. Need for
the former was so intense that a veritable tug-of-war
developed over these youths. Instructors struggled to
keep them at their desks until they had finished their
courses. Administrators tried to wrest them away pre¬
maturely, to fill some of the yawning gaps in their bureau
staffs.
Yet since 1952, 500 clerical-section students have been
graduated, and snatched up promptly for waiting jobs.
Much more time and effort has been needed to place
technical-section graduates, numbering about 300,
although prospects brightened so much last year that the
United Nations Special Fund has allocated over
$1,000,000 to help establish an institute of higher
technology.
There, young Libyans will get training in mechanical,
civil and electrical engineering as well as in food process¬
ing, to meet demand for technicians in Government and
in private enterprises. The staffs to date have comprised
largely foreigners. The Government will furnish
$2,000,000 toward the $3,057,800 cost of the five-year
programmes.
Recently the whole Libyan situation took a sudden and
dramatic turn, with the announcement of oil strikes in the
desert. Government contracts with foreign oil companies
for exploration rights now promise to pay off fairly
handsomely.
If indeed, oil and gas revenues from the Libyan desert
are about to propel into relative opulence a nation so
long and so harshly buffeted, its people are better
prepared than before to sustain the symbolism of ma¬
gnificence their forbears expressed exquisitely in Leptis
Magna, 2,000 years ago.
This article is condensed from a chapter in "What's
the U.N. Doing There Some Success Stories of United
Nations Technical Assistance," by Kathleen McLaughlin,
published by the Institute for International Order, New q.
York, 1961. For copies write to: Institute for International
Order, Suite 1034, 11 West 42nd Street, New York 36, N.Y.
]]>
</page>
<page number="61">
<![CDATA[
Unesco - Alfred Bernheim
In Israel a combination of effort, skill and
the application of science is vanquishing
the desert and making crop growing possi¬
ble In hitherto barren areas. Above
temperature readings being taken at the
Negev Institute for Arid Zone Research.
SEEDS FOR BETTER CROPS
In over 60 countries nation-wide programmes aimed at making
available and promoting the use of high quality seeds a vital
element in obtaining better harvests have been sparked by the
World Seed Campaign, an integral part of the FAO Freedom
from Hunger Campaign. Unesco has contributed to the World
Seed Campaign by naming it as a Unesco Gift Coupon Project,
thus enabling individual people, groups and schools to make
donations to support it. Up to present gifts totalling over
$30,000 have been received by Unesco's Public Liaison Divi¬
sion ¡n Paris for the World Seed Campaign (Project N° 340).
These funds are now helping to provide such items as seed
stocks, equipment for processing and testing seeds and instruc¬
tional equipment like films, projectors, filmstrips and publications.
FAO photo by Eric Schwab
At Cuttack in India, the FAO, in co-operation with the
Indian and other Asian governments is experimenting in1
the production of new hybrid varieties of rice that will give
greater yields. Rice Is the basic food of half the world.
62
U.N.-UNESCO FILMS
FOR TV SHOWING
The United Nations and Unesco are at
present preparing a series of three films
on social and economic development in the
world today, and some of the obstacles
to it, including the problem of hunger.
The films which will be completed later
this year, are being written and directed
by Stephen Hearst of the B.B.C. televi¬
sion service, who has been seconded to
the U.N. and Unesco, and will be made
available fur TV showing in various coun¬
tries. Advanced stills published here show
(left) India's new nuclear reactor at
Trombe, near Bombay; (centre) heavy
cargo being manhandled on the beach
at Accra, Ghana. Method is now being
superseded by use of modern port Instal¬
lations at nearby Tema; (right) money
lender in India. Crippling peasant debts
to money lenders in the Far East are one
of the obstacles to agricultural productivity.
Photos U. N.-Unesco
]]>
</page>
<page number="62">
<![CDATA[
Photo Vauthey © Almasy, Pans
V"
In West Africa, research is being carried out in these nurseries to determine which
plants will grow best in the desert. Once established, the plant roots will help to
fix loose, shifting sands and plants will provide cover for a natural soil regeneration.
5 11
fe 1
I ** 1 x
* 1
j ' ' 1
<
1 4- i *l
XV l iii_i^^H\m
63
]]>
</page>
<page number="63">
<![CDATA[
USIS
The potential produce of the earth, if sought after with skill and
energy, would provide adequate sustenance for a world popula¬
tion far greater than exists today. Already in some of the great
producing countries, rich harvests leave ever greater surplus
stocks of grain (above). As for the oceans, they are an Inexhaus¬
tible storehouse of food from which man has hardly begun to
profit. The possibilities of the sea are shown by the case of Peru
where annual fish production (right) has increased during the
past 1 6 years from 30,000 tons to four and a half million tons.
THE PROMISE
OF LAND
AND SEA
Unesco
FOR FURTHER READING
64
The Biology of Human Starvation, A. Keys - Univ. of
Minnesota Press, U.S.A., 1950.
Common Sense About a Starving World, Ritchie Calder -
Gollancz, London, 1962.
Food For Life - Food For Throught (Vol. 2 of a Study Guide
Series on the U.N.) - Oceana Publications, Inc., Dobbs
Ferry, New York.
The World Must Eat (excerpted from the above and prepar¬
ed by FAO and Unesco's Gauting Institute, Germany) -
Oceana Publications Inc.
The Geography of Hunger, Josué de Castro - Little Brown,
Boston, U.S.A., 1952; Gollancz, 1952.
Hunger Can It Be Averted ?, British Assoc, for the
Advancement of Science, 1961.
Our Developing World, L. Dudley Stamp - Faber & Faber,
London, 1960.
Road to Survival, William Vogt - Gollancz, 1949.
To Plow With Hope, Donald K. Faris - Gollancz, 1958.
BASIC STUDIES FOR THE FREEDOM FROM
HUNGER CAMPAIGN
Third World Food Survey - FAO, Rome (in preparation).
Possibilities of Increasing World Food Production - FAO
Marketing, Its Role In Increasing Productivity - FAO
Increasing Food Production Through Education, Research &
Extension - FAO
Education and Training in Nutrition - FAO
Nutrition and Working Efficiency - FAO
Animal Disease and Human Health - FAO
Development Through Food (Revised 1962 edition) - FAO
Population and Food Supplies - U.N., New York
Aspects of Economic Development - The Background to
Freedom from Hunger - U.N.
National Economic Development Policies & the Demand for
Food - U.N.
Hunger and Social Policy - ILO, Geneva
Malnutrition and Disease - A Major Problem of the Human
Race - WHO, Geneva
Weather and Food - WMO, Geneva
]]>
</page>
<page number="64">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
VICTORY FOR FREEDOM, DEMO¬
CRACY AND...
Sir,
I am sorry to see that a reader,
M. Thumble, expressed his contempt
for the French Revolution and its
"panegyric" which he says The
Unesco Courier published in "The
Story of the Metric System" (March,
1962). I believe that this was the
greatest event of modern times and
though it may appear to some as
"the most savage and sanguinary
period of French history", historically
it is a period so rich in idealism as
to be unparalleled in world history.
Despite innumerable crimes, terrible
injustices and cruel repressions, the sons
of France won for the whole world the
freedom and democracy which are
the paramount values of our present
age. I am a student and in the text¬
books scorned by M. Thumble I find
all the facts that have been confirmed
by historical texts. If it were not
for the French Revolution, he would
not be able to say the things he did
about your article.
Fernando Meacci
Lonigo, Italy
... DECENT LIVING STANDARDS
Sir,
I am a labourer and I believe that
the French Revolution and the
Republic were decisive factors for
progress. You were more than justified
in evoking them recently in "The Story
of the Metric System." It is thanks
to them that we have been able to
achieve better standards of living.
Lucien Vermède
Nimes, France
PRIZE FOR FRIENDSHIP
Sir,
I agree that The Unesco Courier
should be widely publicized and in
this connexion I think you might be
interested to know that for the past
two years the father of a boy attending
a Buenos Aires school has offered a
year's subcription to your magazine as
a prize for the boy judged to be
"the best pal" by his schoolmates in
each of the top primary school classes.
If this initiative was followed every¬
where the diffusion of your magazine
would be appreciably increased as we
all wish it could be.
R. Aprea
Buenos Aires, Argentina
NO ROYAL ROAD TO GEOMETRY
Sir,
Re "The Story of the Metric
System": it is perhaps best to
consider the metric system as the
focal point of an historical controversy
between physics and metaphysics ;
between idealism and realism. Its
historical basis to the contrary
notwithstanding, the meter owes its
origin to the decree, or edict, or
agreement of the International Metric
Convention on May 20, 1875. Such
a measure is a royal measure, or royal
cubit, as opposed to a common
measure, or common cubit.
Metaphysics postulates a straight
line transcribed between two points.
The distance between the points is
not postulated and must therefore be
proven. I say that a royal measure
requires geometrical proof. Only
geometry is the royal approach to the
dimensional sciences ; there is no royal
road to geometry.
John F. Powers
Worcester, Mass., U.S.A.
THE POWER OF THE PEN
Sir,
I am a poet who lives in Fukuoka,
south-western part of Japan. The
Latin-American number of the Japa¬
nese edition of The Unesco Courier
gave me new hope when I came across
the words "The Pen before the Sword"
in the article "Prelude to In¬
dependence." History is a repetition
of order and chaos. The Pen has lived
through those changing years and has
helped countries to independence. It
has also given a much better life to
people than in colonial days. I believe,
not only in Latin America, but in
other parts of the world there are
great thinkers, writers, and phi¬
losophers who represent the power of
the Pen.
Tagore, Schweitzer, and Pushkin
must be counted as geniuses of this
kind.
I hope The Unesco Courier will
issue a special number or use one of
the numbers to introduce the works
of these revered representatives of the
Pen.
Sanruku Sugiyama
Fukuoka City, Japan
Ed. note: The life and work of
Rabindranath Tagore was the theme
of our December 1961 issue.
IN DEFENCE OF CHILDREN
Sir,
It it some time since I saw an
article in your magazine on the
problem of child education, though
this is one of the most important
aspects of the fight for peace and
social justice the aim of all inter¬
national efforts. I should like to hear
what your readers think about it.
Speaking for teachers, I say that
today's "education" is totally wrong
because everywhere it is still based
on coercion. We should speak out
and act courageously against this
brutal system. We should have laws
and sanctions aimed against the in¬
conceivable "right" to whip, torment
and humiliate the weak and innocent.
Already in 1937 Maria Montessori
declared: "The child ought to be
represented in his country's parliament;
there should be a Ministry for
Children." The Unesco Courier
should lead a world campaign in
support of these urgent, needful and
humane laws.
Anna Mazziotti di Celso
Rome, Italy
WORK FOR TOMORROW TODAY
Sir,
To live in a harmonious world,
whom should we educate or re-educate
the children or the adults? For
centuries it has been said that children
are the hope for tomorrow. But how can
we properly plan a future without
having a present? To protect children's
rights with an international sense of
responsibility we must begin by educ¬
ating the educators. The men and
women of tomorrow will not enjoy
any peace of mind nor any political
peace or plenty, if they are not made
conscious of their responsibility
towards life and mankind as a whole.
It is not by filling our children's minds
with intellectual or technological
concepts that we shall succeed in
protecting them of freeing them, or
their children, from poverty and
endless suffering. This result must
come today through our own deep
psychological renewal.
Pedro Ysas Ferrer,
Barcelona, Spain
A CLASSROOM AID
Sir,
Last year your magazine often
replaced the reading texts I use in
my secondary school classes. This I
was able to do because of the keen
interest shown by my pupils in ways
of life, so different from ours, illustra¬
ted in your pages. The Unesco
Courier is a purposeful and important
publication because it brings to our
notice situations and problems that
distance or lack of information
generally keep in the dark.
M. Elisa Ghirlanda
Buenos Aires, Argentina
ARE WE POISONING OURSELVES 7
Sir,
In your issue on "The Two Faces
of World Health" (April 1962) you
note the important change in medical
science, with a new emphasis on
preventative, as compared to curative,
medicine. There is another, and to
my mind important, factor, to which
you did not refer: hygiene. It does
seem paradoxical to find that bodily
hygiene has greatly developed in the
past half century, yet alimentary
hygiene is retrogressing. Today it is
practically impossible to find healthy,
natural foodstuffs. From the earth
itself which is "poisoned" with
fertilizers so that it may produce
bumper crops, to the flesh of animals '
leared on chemical foods and in un¬
natural living conditions, it is im¬
possible to find the nutritive elements
indispensable to health in their proper
proportions. What one could say
about bread is best left unsaid.
Many doctors deplore this situation
and fight against it with medicines.
Have we not here the subject of a
campaign corresponding perfectly with
The Unesco Courier's field of
interest?
Michel Lambert
Paris, France
65
]]>
</page>
<page number="65">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
A BOOM YEAR FOR EXPLORERS:
The Royal Geographic Society in
the United Kingdom has approved a total
of 62 expeditions to be carried out this
year in various parts of the world by
500 explorers mostly university students.
Expeditions range from a search for Phoe¬
nician wrecks off the coast of Sicily to the
study of relics of Indian civilization on a
site due to be flooded by a dam in
Colombia.
ACTORS' SCHOOL FOR ANIMALS:
A school in Oxfordshire, England, is
producing a variety of well-trained profes¬
sional animal actors and actresses destined
to appear in films and on TV. Its pupils,
include squirrels, horses, birds, cats, dogs,
rabbits, badgers, goats and sheep.
|~1HILDREN'S PALACE IN MOSCOW:
^ Built within a new park and sur¬
rounded by sports fields, greenhouses and a
pond with a flotilla of boats, a Children's
Palace, has been opened in Moscow. It has
rooms for games, meetings and exhibitions
and its annexes include a theatre, cinema,
concert halls, a planetarium and an astro¬
nomical observatory.
ACURE FOR SHARKS: Australian
skin-divers returned recently from the
Great Barrier Reef after successfully testing
a new weapon designed to kill their most
deadly enemy, the shark. The weapon is
a hypodermic spear gun, adapted from a
veterinary hypodermic syringe, the needle
being set in a cylinder containing poison
which is in turn screwed on to an under¬
water spear gun. It is intended for use by
skin-divers and life-saving teams in shark-
infested waters.
T\TOT SO COLD CLIMATE: Two New
-L' Zealand scientists believe that the
"warm waters" of Lake Vanda in Antarc¬
tica are heated by trapped sunlight and not,
as hitherto thought, from a heat source
within the_ earth's crust. When samples of
sulphur from the lake were analyzed it was
found that they did not have a volcanic
origin, but came from sea water.
ALEXANDER'S FLEET IN SIGHT:
Wrecks of several triremes believed to
have belonged to the fleet used by Alexan¬
der the Great in his siege of Tyre in 332
B.C. have been found on the sea bed off
the coast of Lebanon. Objects from Greek
and Phoenician vessels have already been
recovered here.
Wm^EATHER FORECASTING MA-
* CHINE: Using an electronic calcula¬
tor and information transmitted by radio
balloons from 20 miles above the earth,
meteorologists in Berlin are now able to pre¬
dict weather conditions in a matter of min¬
utes. The specially designed calculator
66 can process in about three minutes com¬
plicated weather data that would have taken
several hours by human calculation.
TRAINING CENTRE FOR ARAB EDU¬
CATORS: A Regional Centre for the
Advanced Training of Educational Person¬
nel in the Arab States was opened recently
at Beirut in the Lebanon by Mr. Kamal el
Assad, Lebanese Minister of Education, and
Mr. René Maheu, Acting Director-General
of Unesco.
TpOGO'S FIRST NEWSPAPER: The
Republic of Togo now has its first
newspaper, the "Togo-Presse" an S-page
tabloid published in French with one page
in Ewe Togo's chief vernacular language.
It was created with the aid of Unesco Tech¬
nical Assistance. Produced by an all-Togo-
lese editorial and mechanical staff, it began
life as a weekly publication, but is now
being transformed into a daily newspaper.
SCIENCE KITS FOR BRAZIL: Nine
thousand science teaching kits have
been distributed to Brazilian schools by
the Brazilian Institute of Education, Science
and Culture, a branch of the Brazilian Na¬
tional Commission for Unesco. With
these kits secondary pupils will be able to
perform experiments in physics, chemistry,
biology and natural history.
TP UTANKHAMUN'S TREASURES ON
-* TOUR: A selection of precious
objects from the tomb of Tutankhamun,
dating from about 1350 B.C., have been
loaned for the first time by a Cairo mu¬
seum and are now on a two-year across-
country tour of 16 museums in the United
States. It is hoped that the exhibition
will stimulate interest in America in the
Unesco programme to save Nubian monu¬
ments threatened by the construction of
the Aswan Dam.
BIG-GAME HUNT WITHOUT GUNS:
Covering over 4,000 miles on ski in
the past two years, patrols of game experts,
armed only with pens and notebooks, have
been tracking bears, wolves, lynxes and
wolverines in the north of Sweden to note
their habits and movements. Although
between 20 and 30 bears are shot
annually, it is believed there are still
between 250 and 300 in Sweden.
F/ashes...
Milk distributed by Unicef, during the
past 15 years would fill 22 containers each
as tall as the U.N. Headquarters Building
in New York.
| The Peruvian Government is devoting
25% of its budget to educational needs.
¡I Samples of fossil pollen found on the
now barren and desolate Easter Island in
the Pacific, and analyzed at Stockholm's
Museum of Natural History, suggest that
the island was once covered with tropical
vegetation.
| In the past three years the U.S.S.R. has
published 1,540 fiction works, totalling 181
million copies. These include books by
writers of 68 countries.
¡| Under a $40 million educational develop¬
ment plan, Ecuador is to construct 9,854
new classrooms by the end of 1967.
| Canada has now joined 40 other
countries in the Universal Copyright
Convention under which states grant to
foreign works the same protection accorded
works by their own nationals.
g Last year the World Health Organization
undertook 825 projects in 137 countries
and territories, its principal target being the
world-wide malaria eradication campaign.
You may be seeing our magazine for the first time. If so, we hope you will
want to become a regular reader.
To take out a subscription, all you need to do is fill in the form below and send
it, together with your remittance, to the sales agent in your country (see opposite
page for list of agents and subscription rates in your local currency).
10/-(stg)
Annual subscription rates: $3.00
7 New Francs
SUBSCRIPTION FORM
Name	
(block letters)
Address
(street)
Town Country	
Please enter my subscription for	year (s).
I wish to receive the ARABIC - ENGLISH - FRENCH - GERMAN - JAPANESE -
RUSSIAN - SPANISH - editions (s). Circle edition wanted.
]]>
</page>
<page number="66">
<![CDATA[
A w/ndow open on the world
Every month
ONE AND A HALF MILLION
PEOPLE READ
THE UNESCO COURIER
in English, Arabic, French, German,
Japanese, Russian and Spanish.
of The Unesco Courier* is to be neither
technical" nor too "popular". Its articles,
richly illustrated with striking photographs, offer
a vivid picture of the endless diversity of peoples
and countries, a world on the march, the great
adventures in science and the problems of our time.
Recent issues included
ANTARCTICA-INT'L LAND OF SCIENCE
THE AWAKENING AFRICAN CINEMA
TODAY'S CRISIS IN ANTHROPOLOGY
ART & SCIENCE IN THE LIFE OF MAN
RABINDRANATH TAGORE
HOW THE CINEMA AFFECTS CHILDREN
Where to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; rates quoted are
for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO COU¬
RIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. PanuzaT, Press Department, Royal
Afghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Melbourne University Press, 369 Lonsdale Street,
Melbourne, C. I., Victoria. (A. 15/-). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C*., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Seh. 60.-). BELGIUM. Office de Publicité S.A..
16, rte Marq, Brussels. CCP 285.98. NV Standaard-
Boekhandel, Belgielei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (I00FB) and art slides only: Louis de Lannoy,
22, place de Brouckère, Brussels. CCP 3380.00
BURMA. Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road,
Rangoon. (K. 5.50). CANADA. Queen's Primer,
Ottawa, Ont. ($ 3.00). CEYLON. The Associated
Newspapers of Ceylon Ltd.. Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Colombo, 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99 Chungking South
Rd., Section I, Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa). CUBA.
Librería Económica, Pte Zayas 505-7, Apartado 113,
Havana. (2.25 pesos). CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia
Ltd., 30 Ve Smeckách, Prague 2. DENMARK. Ejnar
Munksgaard, A/S Tidsskriftafdelingen, 6 Nórregade,
Köbenhavn K. (D.kr. 12). ETHIOPIA. International
Press Agency. P.O. Box I 20. Addis Ababa. FINLAND.
Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
(Fmk. 540). FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, Place
de Fontenoy, Paris. 7». C.C.P. 12598-48. (7 NF.).
GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier, Vertrieb Bahren¬
felder-Chaussee 160, Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, CCP.
276650 (DM 8). Other Publications: R. Oldenbourg
Verlag, Rosenheimerstrasse 145, Munich. GHANA.
Methodist Book Depot Ltd. Atlantis House, Commercial
St., POB 100, Cape Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See
United Kingdom. GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann,
28, rue du Stade, Athens. HONG-KONG. Swindon
Book Co., 64. Nathan Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY.
Kultura, P.O. Box 149. Budapest, 62. INDIA Orient
Longmans Ltd. Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; Gun-
foundry Road, Hyderabad, I; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/1 Asal Ali Road, P.O. Box 386, New
Delhi, I ; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.,
17 Park Street, Calcutta 16, Scindia House. New Delhi.
(Rs. 7). INDONESIA. P. N. Fadjar Bhakti,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Djakarta. IRAQ. Mackenzie's
Bookshop, Baghdad. IRELAND. The National Press,
2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd., 35, Allenby
Road and 48, Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv ( I £ 5.50).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour
Street, Kingston. Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
( 1 0/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd.. 6 Tori-Nichome,
Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605 Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
(Yen 670). JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman.
KENYA. E.S.A. Bookshop, P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. LUXEMBURG.
Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue, Luxemburg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND SINGAPORE.
Federal Publications Ltd., Times House, River Valley
Rd., Singapore. MALTA. Sapienza's Library,
26 Kingswiy, Valetta. (10/-). MAURITIUS. Nalanda
Company Ltd.. 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis.
MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid des Moulins,
Monte-Carlo. (7 NF.). NETHERLANDS. N. V.
Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9. The Hague,
(fl. 6). NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES. G.C.T.
Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.) N.V.. Willemstad, Curacao.
NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Office,
Wellington, and Government Bookshops, Auckland,
Wellington, Christchurch, Dunedin, ( I 0/-). NIGERIA
C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box 174, Lagos. (10/-). NOR-
W AY. For the Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Lit-
teratur-Tjeneste, Stortingsgt. 4, Oslo, Postboks 115 (kn
I 3.20) Other publications. A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille Grenser
7, Oslo. PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing Co.
Ltd., Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box 374, 56-N
Gulberg Industrial Colony, Lahore. PANAMA.
Cultural Panameña, Avenida 7a, No. TI-49, Apartado
de Correos 2018, Panama, D.F. (Balboas 3-).
LIPPINES. Philippine Education Co. Inc., I 104 Castille¬
jos, Quiapo, P.O. Box 620, Manila. POLAND.
" RUCH " ul.Wiloza Nr. 46, Warsaw 10 (Zl. 50).
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada Lda, Livrana Portugal,
Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. RHODESIA & NYASA-
LAND. The Book Centre, First Street, Salisbury,
Southern Rhodesia. SWEDEN. For The Unesco
Courier: Svenska Unescoradet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 7.50); other publications A/B C.E. Fritzes
Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse
Zurich. Payot, 40, rue du Marché, Geneva. C.C.P.
1-236. «Courier» only: Georges Losmaz, I, rue des
Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. C.C.P. 1-4811. (Fr. S. 8).
TANGANYIKA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B.
9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND. Suks apan
Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok. (35
ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda
Bookshop, P.O., Box 145, Kampala. UNION OF
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Bookstore, Libri
Building, Church Street, Pretoria. For the Unesco
Courier: Central News Agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johan¬
nesburg. (10/-). UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC
(EGYPT). La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha,
Cairo. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I. (10/-). UNITED
STATES. Unesco Publications Center, 801 Third
Avenue, New York, 22, N.Y. ($ 5.00.) and (except
periodicals): Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y. U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja
Kniga, Moscow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugosto-
venska Knjiga, Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="67">
<![CDATA[
%«"
*fVi
j£ p w \
: ,
y^mmm
Almasy. Paris
HIDDEN HUNGER Chronic malnutrition, sometimes called "hidden hunger", claims most of
its victims among young children, causing illnesses which prevent their
normal development and producing long-lasting effects. (See page 20)
]]>
</page>
</document>
