<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="063808eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
lï m
WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
HTriH
MARCH 1961 (14th year) - Price: 1/-stg. (U.K.) - 30 cents (U.S.) 0.70 NF. (FRANCE)
fc¿-
*fi
^
à*
55 V,
^
mm
I
$>*Ä
ta» #«
t
iv*C
IPS
SBd
i
OK*
up
0 y*r**tHtHfmB^
X
1
OW THE CINEMA
FFECTS CHILDREN
REBIRTH OF A SHATTERED CITY
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
1 / ' . *3~î *0+--
,'~ *.
1"
' m U*
#
..:
fill! i
f I f 1 1
Ifllll Iff
m » tt
i r
m m
in
lit
« I
n ii
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier
MARCH 1961
14TH YEAR
Contents
No. 3
Page
4 REBIRTH OF A SHATTERED CITY
By Jerzy Hryniewiecki
8 CANALETTO, THE PAINTER OF WARSAW
His works helped to restore a city
14 THE WORLD OF PREHISTORIC MAN
By Nino Frank
17 HOMO SAPIENS IS TEN MINUTES OLD
COVER PHOTO
Miles of pages have been
written In the past 30 years
about the effects of the cin¬
ema on children. An analy¬
sis of the major conclusions
that can be drawn Is pre¬
sented on page 24, based on
a new bibliographic study
Just published by Unesco.
© Karen Juliane, Copenhagen
18 NEW HORIZONS FOR ASIA'S MOSLEM WOMEN
By Anne-Marie Hussein
23 WEDDING IN SUMATRA
24 HOW THE CINEMA AFFECTS CHILDREN
By Gordon Mirams
29 A MARINER'S MYTH
The curse of the albatross
By David Gunston.
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
35 UNESCO COURIER CONTENTS I960
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7', France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
Gordon Behrens
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition.: Celia Bertin
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey
Russian Edition : Venlamin Matchavarlanl (Moscow)
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Amin Chaker (Cairo)
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (except In July and August when
it is bi-monthiy) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German and Arabic. In the
United States of America it is distributed bs the UNESCO Publications Center.
U.S.A. 80 I Third Avenue, New York 22, N.Y., Plaza 1-3860. Second-class mail
privileges authorized at NewYork, N.Y. (M.C. 6 1. 1. 1 56 A).
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in The Readers' Guide to Perio¬
dical Literature.
Annual subscription rates: S 3.00; IO/-stg. ; 7.00 New
Francs or equivalent. Single copies l/-stg. 30 cents
(U.S.); 0.70 New Francs.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
REBIRTH OF A
In 1945, Warsaw
was simply a name
on the map marking
a wasteland of ruins
For many of the world's largest cities, the past fifteen
years have been, more or less, a normal period In
the continuous process of urban development. Out¬
wardly for them, not much has changed. True
enough, some old buildings have been torn down to make
room for lean and graceful modern towers in the hope of
relieving that universal city bugbear, the ever growing
traffic problem.
Other cities have had a face-lifting. There have been
the scars of war to erase, both by modernizing and
rebuilding old sections, and by raising great complexes of
modern buildings which are virtually cities in themselves.
A few cities have literally been born overnight during
the past fifteen years owing to the vision of some
statesman or architect. At least one or two have sprung
up from the bare ground providing their designers with
a rare freedom to make of them the very last word in
modern city planning.
The story of Warsaw is different.
There are few examples in history of the tragic fate
which befell this city.
It is a story which begins in 1945 when virtually nothing
but ruins remained of the city, yet which today has risen
from the ashes and rubble and has amazingly regained
its pre-war population of over a million inhabitants.
Warsaw offers a lesson on the workings of an urban
society which is astonishing. It would seem to prove that
neither the complete destruction of a people, nor their
WARSAW 1945
Central Photographic Agency, Warsaw
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
SHATTERED CITY
property can ring down the curtain of history on the
life of a great city.
A visitor to Warsaw today will find it hard to believe
that this thriving, bustling metropolis was a wasteland of
ruins in January 1945 when the first of the citizens began
to trickle back. Where the proud and historic city had
once stood, they found nothing but a vague outline visible
here and there among ruins and rubble. It was a vast
cemetery for hundreds of thousands. Here and there a
pock-marked building which had escaped total destruc¬
tion rose up like a lonely sentinel, and on the right bank
of the Vistula, a whole quarter the poorest in the city
where ten per cent of Warsaw's population once lived,
alone escaped the holocaust.
For all practical purposes, however, Warsaw existed only
because of its geographical position and its name.
Even though Warsaw was an empty shell, a city without
life, half of its people were still alive, scattered throughout
the world in many places but bereft of all their
possessions. They had suffered much from the war, but
with them they carried memories of the Warsaw they
had known, its traditions, its life and its people. The
barbarous order which had reduced Warsaw to rubble,
could not obliterate this city from the hearts and the
minds of her people no matter where they might be.
As the citizenry returned in ever greater numbers,
Warsaw's future became the main topic of discussion.
Some were all for turning the entire area into a giant
Today, rebuilt and
modernized, it has
grown to six times
its pre-war size
by Jerzy Hryniewiecki
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
Polish Information Office, Paris
WARSAW 1961
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Shimmering ribbons
of light on the Vistula
reflect Poland's reborn
capital of 1,200,000 people
Polish Information Office, Paris
construction camp, off limits to the public, in order to
carry out a rush rebuilding programme. Others were
inclined to pick a new site and rebuild the capital city
elsewhere.
There were Utopian visions of a futuristic city, many
very attractive but often not too practical because of the
lack of economic and technical resources available just
after the war to carry out such far-sighted, and,
unfortunately, enormously expensive plans. While some
wanted to rebuild upon the old city, restoring and re¬
creating the best of the past, others talked about a
clean break with the old sweeping away all the past
shortcomings of an unplanned city which just "grew"
from mediaeval village times, and In its stead creating an
absolutely new city based on the most modern and up-
to-the-minute ideas and tastes.
And, of course, there were the "Brave New World"
variety of planners who attacked the problem statistically
and proposed a project in which the inhabitants would
be classified according to profession and allotted precisely
fixed areas of living space on the basis of the density of
population.
But real life did not wait for plans, theories and long
discussions. Within hours and days after Liberation,
thousands of former citizens were flooding back to the
deserted ruins. The new government decided to set up
its capital there, not because conditions were ideal for
an administrative centre, but because the name Warsaw
still meant so much, not only to its own people, but
throughout the world. In no time at all, the rows of
ruined houses and buildings took on the appearance of
ant hills as the people themselves set busily about the
task of rebuilding their capital with their own hands
and with whatever materials they could salvage among
the rubble.
During this first period of heroic, but primitive re¬
construction of the city, all Poland seemed to be on
the move. Not only were former citizens of Warsaw
constantly swelling the population, but large numbers of
other people too, drawn by the reviving economic system,
added to their numbers. There was also a flood of people
uprooted from territories no longer a part of Poland who
headed for the city, as well as many peasants from over-
populated rural areas. As Warsaw's industries were re¬
constructed and expanded, a far greater labour force
was required than before the war, a fact which also drew
more people to the city.
With this phenomenon of an old population and a new
population in an old city being rebuilt, Warsaw became
a crucible in which not only the people, but sweeping
changes in the social and professional structure created a
situation of extraordinary dynamism. Within fifteen
years this great force has moulded a uniform society
out of the most disparate elements. This has been
surprising to all but old inhabitants of Warsaw who are
well aware of their city's long tradition of assimilating
all that comes within its gates.
In the new Warsaw, almost all former inhabitants have
changed their residences. Many are doing jobs they
never dreamed of before the war. More recent arrivals
from generations of country folk have become city-
dwellers in a very short space of time which has made
profound changes in their habits and way of life.
It is difficult for us to realize just how all these popula¬
tion movements have affected the life of the people of
Warsaw. It is only by meeting and talking to someone
who knew Warsaw before the war and who can compare
the old order with the new that we can begin to
appreciate the kind of metamorphosis that has taken
place in so short a time.
We might compare it to compressing into a brief
span of fifteen years all the things that in other
countries have taken hundred of years to achieve.
We have seen with our own eyes mediaeval squares and
18th century house rising out of the ruins. Yet behind
the façades are dwellings with every modern convenience.
We have watched the reconstruction of the Gothic
cathedral with the same stones with which the original
was built, and we have seen the splendid 17th and 18th
century palaces of noblemen painstakingly restored in
every detail to become cultural and administrative
centres.
The restored classical façade of the Opera House, built
at the beginning of the last century, has been faithfully
copied, but behind it is a modern concert and operatic
theatre which is technically one of the best-equipped in
Europe. New and broader bridges have been constructed
on the piles of the old ones. New homes have risen on
the foundations and rubble of those destroyed. The new
city of Warsaw draws its character from this harmonious
blending of the vestiges of the past with the techniques
and living needs of modern life.
Is it then a kind of 20th century anachronism in which
museum-like façades spring up artificially to shield the
comforts of modern life which lie behind ? Certainly not,
if we consider the people of Warsaw themselves. This
recreation of the past has taken into full account the
needs, nostalgia, and feelings of a people whose past was
all but torn away from them. This reconstruction has
been a labour of love, and one cannot find a single false
note.
The task of reconstructing the old demanded tre¬
mendous effort from specialists who had to work with
CONT'D ON PAGE 12
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1961
The people of Warsaw
have retraced
the cavalcade of centuries
in 15 years of toil
Newly rebuilt market place in the Old City Zygniunt Szartk, W*riaw
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
CANALE
THE PAINTER
OF WARSAW
An 18th century painter
of unmatched fidelity
helped Warsaw recapture
the beauty of its past
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
C? Zygmunt Szarek, Warsaw
From "Canaletto" published 1959, Warsaw
To the people of Poland the
name Canaletto evokes Warsaw
not Venice. In 1767 Bernardo
Bellotto, better known as Canaletto
the Younger (not to be confused
with his uncle, Antonio Canalthe
famous Canaletto of Venice scenes)
arrived in Warsaw. He immedia¬
tely fell in love with the city and
remained there until his death in
1780. When he died he left behind
him a series of paintings of Poland's
capital of unrivalled fidelity and
exactness. His keen eye recorded
an inexhaustible wealth of detail
in living street scenes, details of
Warsaw's houses, churches and
public buildings and grandiose
panoramic views. When Warsaw's
architects sought to rebuild the
old town after wartime destruction,
they turned to Cahaletto's paint-
ngs to help them reconstitute the
buildings of the past (see follow¬
ing pages). Skyline on the Vistula
(top of page) with its recently re¬
constructed buildings reveals same
forms which Canaletto painted
(below and left) some 200 years ago.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
CANALETTO HIS PAINTINGS HELPED
TO RESTORE A CITY
Canaletto's pictures have been
called a fascinating full-colour
film of Warsaw's life in the 18th
century ". He never painted any
building apart from its own surround¬
ings, but always showed it with
adjoining buildings, its square or
street with people and teams of
horses and carriages, and all the
traffic and life of the city swarming
about it. Warsaw's architects made
enormous enlargements of Cana¬
letto's paintings when they were
rebuilding the old town, but they
were often as fascinated by the
people in his works as by his build¬
ings. Canaletto recorded the fea¬
tures of Warsaw at a time when it
was becoming one of the most
beautiful towns of northern Europe.
The collection of twenty-five of his
townscapes is now hanging in
the National Museum, Warsaw.
From "Canaletto" published I 959, Warsaw
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Left, Krakowskie Przedmiescie
Street with the Holy Cross Church
following its recent reconstruction.
Above, the same street, already one
of Warsaw's busy thoroughfares
when Canaletto painted it nearly 200
years ago. Top, opposite page, re¬
constructed New Town market
place with the Holy Sacrament
Sisters Church. Architects used
Canaletto's painting (bottom, oppo¬
site page) to guide them in rebuild¬
ing the church and nearby houses.
Miecryslaw Kusma, the architect
who rebuilt the Old Town in Warsaw.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
REBIRTH OF A SHATTERED CITY (^
WARSAW'S NEW LOOK
absolute precision on what we might term "scientific"
rebuilding of the ruins. The measure of their success is
found in the fact that the results are not eclectic, nor
has their work shown signs of being cold or impersonal.
In fact, the earlier stages of reconstruction were so
fraught with difficulties and primitive technical resources
that as a result often the working methods and materials
were relatively the same as those employed in the original
constructions. This perhaps, more than any other single
factor, brings authenticity to restored Warsaw.
Today it is a fact that most people of Warsaw
instinctively try to live In "old-style" houses in preference
to modern dwellings built with air, light and parks
surrounding them. It may be that living in the "new-
old" places they feel more like old established residents
of the city. But, it is typical of the people of Warsaw
to be strong individualists, and it may be they feel more
at ease in the less ordered and more fanciful surround¬
ings than those offered by large modern blocks of flats.
With the reconstruction of the city, its old shape has
come to life again. The network of streets, established
centuries ago, and which were recognizable as an odd
geometric pattern in the ruined city, have become the
framework for the new plan. Still, the monotonous criss¬
cross of 19th century streets have been made more
functional in the new city.
It was inevitable that the resumption of city life and
the demands of town planning would lead to conflicts.
In these, sometimes one side wins, and sometimes another.
But as is often the case, lively Interest, however partisan,
lends vigour to the cause.
It is thus that a new school of town planning has
emerged in Warsaw in which the emphasis is laid on
actual execution of plans which have been shed of their
more glowing and yet impractical aspects. The people of
Warsaw themselves have learned that their opinions count
in the plans of the municipal draughtsmen, and more
than once they have caused changes in what they
considered unduly abstract plans.
It is true that Warsaw's population has now reached
the pre-war figure, but its area has increased six¬
fold. Density of population in 1939 was appalling. It
reached 5,000 inhabitants per acre in some parts of the
city's centre. Today the population is properly distributed
and green spaces spread out, shaded with trees, where
once stood some of the most wretched and densely packed
tenements. Warsaw has changed too, from a labyrinth
of dreary streets into a city of gardens and open areas.
It is not only in relation to history that we citizens
of Warsaw have spanned whole centuries in the space
of a few years. The past fifteen years can be split into
two separate parts, each representing a different phase
of development. The first was a period of primitive,
spontaneous reconstruction. Groups of buildings based on
new architectonic systems grew up within the framework
of a city organically re-established on its old foundations,
retaining the boundaries of its former buildings. Former
unimportant areas thus have become prominent hubs of
communication which draw life to the city's centre.
Difficulties created in trying to reconcile the old with
the new encouraged the construction of new housing
estates on the outskirts of the city where there is still
free land which permits unrestricted development of
12
modern buildings. There was something paradoxical
about this great ring of modern buildings pushing
skyward around the ruins of a provisionally re-established
centre and there was bound to be criticism of the de-
urbanization trend.
The result was a move in favour of establishing re¬
sidential districts in the heart of the city, and eventually
a number of relatively sparsely populated districts sprang
up there. It produces, moreover, an eclectic tendency to
repeat the faults, but also the rich ornamentation of
architectural forms of the 19th century. But thanks to
help from traditional craftsmanship and materials, this
trend made it possible to build on a scale appropriate to
a large city, even though only out-dated technical means
were available.
During this period of rebuilding certain sections of
the centre of the city became alive again with in¬
habitants. The period ended with the building of
the Palace of Culture and Science, 750 feet in height,
which houses the Polish Academy of Science. Located in
the very centre of the city, its traditional approach belongs
to another age, yet, by its size and social significance, it
marks the beginning of the construction of Warsaw's
modern centre.
Today Warsaw lives continually under pressure of an
exploding population, and ever more crowded living space.
We are compelled to build more and more modern apart¬
ment houses, schools, hospitals, and other buildings to
meet the growing public needs.
There is the beginning of a great push forward in the
fields of pre-fabrication and industrialization in building
and in the use of new materials for construction. Against
the impressive backdrop of the reconstructed old city of
Warsaw, a new city is rising, equipped with all the mod¬
ern advantages and caring for all the needs of a rapidly
expanding population. For, you may be sure, despite the
tragedies of war, the uprooting, the destruction, Warsaw's
people are filled with life and vigour.
From the shattered remains of the old city, from the
miseries of the past, from the hopes and aspirations of
its scattered inhabitants, from their sweat and toil, rises
the new Warsaw. May the joy of living flourish here
everafter.
VISION OF THE FUTURE. To the Poles,
architecture is a real passion. "Nobody should
oppose its expansion," one Polish architect
recently wrote, "for it represents a victory of
inventive thought, modern solutions and a new
approach." Many Polish designs have registered
victories at international competitions and have
turned into reality in various parts of the world
from Brazil and the U.S. to India and the Middle
East. Top, opposite page, a bold building project
called "The East Wal!" proposed for the heart
of Warsaw by architect Marek Leyckham has caus¬
ed a sensation and. much debate in Poland. Right,
apartments in Warsaw. Note effort to balance
"green spaces" and buildings in photo on left.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
From Poland Magazine iO I. Jarosin'-ka, Warsaw
Zygmunt Szarek, Warsaw
Hint n
nr.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
THE WORLD OF
PREHISTORIC
by Nino Frank
To think in terms, of geography
is to think in terms of the
universe, someone has said.
In our day, when we are ever
more oriented to thinking in
world terms, the teaching of geogra¬
phy has become a matter of major
concern. It is not »that scientific study
and school teaching are to be con¬
fused, nor should we attempt to make
every schoolchild into an infant geo¬
grapher. But geography, treated as
a genuine study of the world, can be
used more effectively than other
subjects as a means of laying the
foundations of International under¬
standing.
A glance at the school curricula
of most countries, however, shows
that the subject of geography is
almost invariably cut to the minimum
and treated as an adjunct to his¬
tory. One hour a week is usually all
the time allotted to it, and indeed in
some schools (North America, Aus¬
tralia and Japan) it is often merely
combined with social studies or the
study of family and community life.
Yet, great new perspectives are
now open to the student of geo¬
graphy through television and
films. Aerial photographs taken
from helicopters and more recently
from artificial satellites have brought
"the whole world within reach".
Teachers of geography are now better
equipped than ever before to bring
their subject to life and to broaden
the horizons of their pupils.
Let us take only one area of new
geographic knowledge, the study of
prehistoric times. Now, as never
before, it is possible to describe the
life of prehistoric men who lived far
back in the mists of time. Only a
few years ago they were shadowy
figures compounded of legend and
guess work, but we now know so
much about their lives, surroundings
and migrations that we are able to
form a precise picture of them.
Historians and geographers now
have all kinds of research techniques
at their disposal which give them
reliable evidence on which to base
their studies of prehistory. These
are made up of a combination of
facts about climatic cycles, the evo¬
lution of animal species and of man,
as well as his cultural development.
Stratigraphy, or the study of soils,
pollen analysis and palaeonto¬
logy are all used to reconstruct
a picture of the past. Dating
has long been possible through the
study of tree rings (dendrology to
the specialist) such as the basic
research work first carried out with
the centuries-old Sequoias of Cali¬
fornia. Another method of dating
is the time-scaling of the gradual
retreat of the great Scandinavian ice
sheet since the end of the last ice-
age. But dating by these means has
never been precise enough.
During the last twelve years or so,
it has been possible to devise a more
accurate method by measuring the
radio-activity of certain elements
contained in the soil. This method is
based on the properties of carbon-14,
an isotope of carbon which develops
in every living thing when exposed
to the effects of cosmic rays and, on
its death, enters on a cycle of disin¬
tegration.
All that is needed in this process
is to discover a site where well-pre¬
served carbon is in evidence (wood
charcoal from a hearth, or carbonized
bone) and the state of disintegration
provides the clue to the precise age
of the material. This has made it
possible to reconsider the whole
subject of prehistory and to revise
estimates of the geographical areas
inhabited by man in earliest times.
A new branch of geography has
4 "Ä^
\ ' nfc
^H * J^
-fcfv "^
MEV
^P%,;
. m
Hm
Among the earliest traces of prehis¬
toric man are petroglyphs, or carvings
in stone, like this "Face" from Brittany.
only just come into being which
estimates and describes the inhabited
regions of prehistoric times. Today,
800,000 years and perhaps even a
million years after early man first
began to grope his way across the
globe, science has found a way to
reconstitute the geographical world
our ancestors knew.
Professor L.R. Nougier of the Uni¬
versity of Toulouse, and director
of the French Institute of Pre¬
historic Art, has published what
appears to be the first survey of Hu¬
man Geography in Prehistoric Times
(1). The book, well-illustrated with
maps and drawings, records the
achievements of geographers and
scientists in many fields, from which
the author is able to date, list and
describe the peoples and cultures of
prehistoric times with more than a
hypothetical degree of accuracy.
His method is based on the num¬
ber, character and location of palae-
ontological deposits, aerial surveys,
the use of radio-activity for dating
and other new scientific research
methods.
(1) Géographie humaine préhistorique, Li¬
brairie Gallimard, Paris, 1959.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Aerial photographs shed new light on the study of prehistoric limes. Photo abovo
is a striking example, showing the alignment of huge stones, 982 In number, set
up by a megalithic civilization many thousands of years ago near Carnac, Franco.
Using this approach, Professor Nou-
gier presents a veritable geographical
panorama of life in Western Europe
(France, in particular) from Palaeoli¬
thic times down to the "Neolithic
Revolution". During the period of
time he covers, the configuration of
the continent remained virtually the
same as we know it now.
Professor Nougier takes us back to
the first food gatherers who used
chipped-stone axes and flake-tools
and did not reach the peak of their
development until the advent of
hunting some forty thousand years
ago. In the time of these earliest
food gatherers, it is roughly estimated
that there were not more than
20,000 inhabitants in the whole of
lower Palaeolithic Gaul.
It was a time when the area around
what is now Paris was the ha¬
bitat of rhinoceroses and elephas
antiquus, where wild fig and Judas
trees grew in abundance. Men used
natural caves for shelter, and fed as
they could on the meat of sick or
wounded game. This was the ecu-
mene of the last glacial period before
the time of Neanderthal man.
After the food gatherers came the
hunters of the carved and painted
caves of the Upper Palaeolithic age.
They invented a magic art of extra¬
ordinary poetic power, only to forget
it later for a reason which remains
one of the unsolved riddles of pre¬
history. Their period ranged from
30,000 years to 8,500 years before the
first Christian era. During that time
the population of the whole of France
was not more than 50,000 inhabitants
according to Professor Nougier.
The nomadic tendency of early
prehistoric men gradually gave
way to settlement in fixed and
densely populated areas. It was
in that way that the prosperity of the
valley of the Lolng, an important
route to the north, came about.
Countless palaeontological remains
have been found there. The valley
leads directly to the Paris region.
Although Paris recently celebrated
her two thousandth birthday, there
is evidence that settlement of the
region dates back centuries before
that time. Traces of past cultures
have been found in the region, parti¬
cularly at the confluence of the Seine
and the Bièvre where there was once
a rocky spur, dating back to the mists
of antiquity.
Somewhere between ten and twen¬
ty thousand years B.C., the first of
the new men arrived, bringing with
them their marvellous secrets agri¬
culture, domesticated animals, per¬
haps even the knowledge of how to
construct megalithic monuments.
This period a forerunner of the
"Neolithic Revolution"was first her¬
alded by the gatherers of shell fish
and wild berries, and later by men
who set out to conquer the mighty
forests.
Thus the earliest forest farming
civilizations were born, developing
their particular round huts and their
herds of cattle somewhere about
8,500 B.C., and marking the dawn of
the Neolithic age (this occurred
much later in the West than in the
Middle East and North Africa).
Between 3,000 B.C., and 2,000 B.C.,
came the thousand-year era of
the Neolithicthe great "Neo¬
lithic Explosion" which saw an
amazing Increase in human popula¬
tion not only in France but in all of
the inhabited regions of the globe.
From a mere 250,000 the population
of the hexagon which was to be
occupied by the Gauls In the third
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
THE WORLD OF PREHISTORIC MAN (Cont'd)
millennium, Increased in the course
of ten centuries to five millions.
This twentyfold increase was made
possible by man's changed attitude
towards nature, by abandoning his
mere parasitic existence for the sys¬
tematic exploitation of the earth's
resources. Professor Nougier esti¬
mates that, at this time, the total
population of the Inhabited world
was around 200 millions. Such an
amazing increase was not to occur
again for at least five or six thousand
years, that is, the beginning of the
Industrial Revolution.
Geography really began when
prehistoric man first asked the ques¬
tion "Where?" Where is such and
such a river. Where Is the large
uninhabited cave? Where is the
reindeer's plateau? This need of
some graphic representation of a
place, however rudimentary, was the
first step in developing geography.
Of course, primitive man's know¬
ledge of geography was confined
to a few rudimentary notions of
topography and to an area of a
few square miles. This was still the
time of wandering peoples with their
fabulous tales, and he could not yet
know the immensity of the terra in¬
cognita which his children would
inherit.
The earliest signs of geographical
Interest so far discovered are the
petroglyphs, or rock carvings, found
both in Brittany and in Scandinavia.
They indicate that even men of the
Bronze age had been wondering about
the particular region in which they
lived. Neither the Sumerlans nor the
Hittites who came later left any
evidence of geographical curiosity,
but we do know that the Pharaohs
of the Middle Kingdom had made a
cadastral survey of all the lands and
plots of land under their rule.
It was inevitable that having begun
by placing things, man sooner or
later would wonder just why things
were as they were. So it was that
having started to explore the earth,
men began starting to explain it.
In effect, the term "geographical"
applies to any fact that answers the
double question "Where?" and "Why
there?".
All geography from the time of the
Ionians and Pythagoreans to that of
Henry the Navigator, Mercator and
Varenius, swings back and forth be¬
tween empirical investigation and
learning confined to measuring and
listing. It Is as if man was, and
still were, the lord of a manor not
yet well known, and In which he re¬
mained a stranger.
It was not until the eighteenth
century, thanks to contributions made
by such other sciences as botany,
zoology and geology that the geogra¬
pher's awareness broadened. Kant
first regarded the relationship bet¬
ween man and nature as an essential
part of geography. After him came
Ritter and Humboldt who proclaimed
the principle of the interdependence
of all natural phenomena, of which
man is merely one.
This planet approach to geogra¬
phy, exemplified by the "human geo¬
graphy" of P. Vidal de La Blache and
his followers, involves constant refe¬
rence to other branches of science.
"Geography, as the meeting-place of
the physical sciences and the huma¬
nities", writes Professor R. Clozier,
"calls into play a wide variety of
concepts. These can be broken down
into facts and if taken singly or in
isolation belong to other sciences.
But geography puts them back into
place in the natural scheme of
things."
The question "Why there?" has
become paramount. Its influence is
particularly apparent in one of the
most active fields of geographical
research, world monographs, and
cross-sectional studies of some iso¬
lated factors such as "man and
forest", "honey cultures", and the
"geography of stock-breeding". One
geographer, Josué de Castro, has em¬
barked on a "Geography of Hunger"
which a colleague describes as "even
more important than a geography of
shelter." And what better name to
give the detailed research on arid
zones now being carried out at
Unesco's instance than a contribution
to the "geography of thirst".
Another study of great importance
today is oceanography. It is
true that we know less about
the seas than we do about the
moon. With men of the future ever
more in need of extra food supplies,
food from the ocean depths (as well
as zones no longer arid) will be in
great need. But though one result of
océanographie research may provide
much needed food for future genera¬
tions the geographers will be bound
to reap the first benefits.
A number of congresses on broad
geographical themes were held last
year in the Scandinavian countries
at Copenhagen, Helsinki, and Stock¬
holm. These meetings, on the ini¬
tiative of Unesco and the Interna¬
tional Geographical Union, discussed
oceanographical, geodesic and geo¬
physical research. Useful results
have been achieved. Special mention
should be made of the work done by
the Commission on Geography
Teaching in Schools at the Geogra¬
phic Union Congress in Stockholm
for improving the teaching of this
subject as the basis for a new type
of humanism.
The thousand million years or
more which have passed in the
history of our planet since the
first forms of life made their
appearance seem to us so astro¬
nomical and overwhelming that
to distinguish eras and dates is
almost impossible. We, who
think in hours, days and months,
need a convenient yardstick.
Professor Louis-René Nougier in
his book "Human Geography in
Prehistoric Times" has provided
one (below) by condensing the
history of life into one year. THE
UNESCO COURIER'S graphic re¬
presentation of this condensation
is shown on the opposite page.
"Man is a late arrival in the world's
long biological development, though
his existence extends over thou¬
sands of years. We can show this
by a simple transposition of the
scale of time. Let us suppose that
the major events of the biological
evolution on our planet were con¬
densed into a single calendar year
and that January 1 represents the
first appearance of life in the world.
We must wait until the end of July
to find the first marine vertebrates.
The great reptiles and first mam¬
mals do not appear until the second
half of October. December 13 marks
the beginning of the Tertiary Age
with the first ape-like creatures.
Not until 2 p.m. on December 31 do
we enter the Quaternary Age, the
last of the vast geological periods in
which man appears. At 5.30 p.m.
the pre-hominids (Pithecanthropes
and Sinanthropes) arrive, but the
first vestiges of " homo sapiens "
are still to come. Swanscombe Man
and Fontéchevado Man enter the
scene about 8 or 9 p.m., and the
many traces of the Neanderthal
Race appear about 11.40 p.m.
"It is not until ten minutes to
midnight that homo sapiens defi¬
nitely comes on to the stage... Now
we must count only in seconds.
The Neolithic Revolution explodes
in the West at six minutes to twelve,
15 seconds. The Bronze Age begins
at one minute to twelve when record¬
ed history is barely a few seconds
old, and somewhere in the Orient
man has invented writing. At just
fifteen seconds before midnight the
Princess of Vix is buried at the foot
of Mount Lassois with her enormous
funeral chariot. At midnight our
condensed year ends. And, in 2000
A.D., forty years from now, we will
have spent only one full minute of
the new year on this reduced scale."
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
HOMO SAPIENS IS TEN MINUTES OLD
13
DECEMBER
First signs of unicellular The first fish-like marine Great reptiles and first Tertiary Age begins with
life appear on earth over vertebrates appear more mammals appear more than first ape-like creatures more
1,000 million years ago. than 450 million years ago. 200 million years ago. than 50 million years ago.
«
THE YEAR 2000 A.D.
12.01 A.M. 2 P.M. QUATERNARY AGE
(one million years ago)
12.00
MIDNIGHT
CHRISTIAN ERA BEGINS
11.59 P.M.
45 sec. .
PRINCESS OF VIX
(525 B. C.)
5.30 P.M.
PITHECANTHROPUS
(850,000 years ago)
8 P.M.
SWANSCOMBE MAN
(500,000 years ago)
11.59 P.M. 11.40 P.M.
THE BRONZE AGE
(2,000 B. C.) 11.54 P.M.
15 sec.
11.50 P.M.
NEANDERTHAL MAN
(40,000 years ago)
NEOLITHIC PERIOD
(8,500 B. C.)
HOMO SAPIENS
(20,000 years ago)
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
NEW HORIZONS FOR ASIA'S
MOSLEM WOMEN
By Anne-Marie Hussein
&*£&Q£' *M:
UtS's'
ILO
A WOMAN'S PLACE in Moslem society has traditionally
been strictly in the home. But a new wind of social change
sweeping through Moslem countries is giving more women
the chance to train for careers and professions. Right a
young woman sociologist in Pakistan studies model of pro¬
posed building for her country's future capital, to be named
Islamabad. Traditional work in tea field is shown in photo
above of Moslem woman from Indonesia on Java plantation.
Indonesian women have always had a large degree of free¬
dom and the veil of Purdah is practically unknown there.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
hat does the average westerner think of
when he hears the words "Moslem women
Vof Asia?" More likely than not he conjures
up a vision of princesses straight out of One
Thousand and One Nights, clad in diapha¬
nous veils and spending their lives nibbling sweetmeats
while confined in harems guarded by great silent eunuchs.
How much truth is there in this legend? How much
of it can survive in comparison with real life, say in
Karachi or Djakarta, two great capital cities which,
though far apart and different in many respects, are both
Asian and Moslem. For, in these two Asian countries of
Pakistan and Indonesia, live eighty million Moslem
women.
At the outset we should say that the fact that she
may be Moslem is no handicap for a woman, paradoxical
as that may seem to those nurtured on the legend of
storybooks. On the contrary, there are few communities
where women's rights are so carefully protected, at least
in theory, as they are among Moslems.
"Paradise is at your mother's feet," proclaims an old
Islamic proverb. It sums up the position a woman occu¬
pies in Moslem society. She is in the centre of her world,
The Unesco Courler. Morch 1961
and indeed, that Is her position according to the tra¬
ditional laws of Islam.
Fourteen hundred years ago the Koran decreed that
women's rights should be "the same as men's" and that
they should "receive as much as they give." What was
the effect of the equality taught by the Prophet himself.
It meant that as far back as the Middle Ages a Moslem
woman was free to choose her own husband, and to
govern the terms of her marriage contract. She could
even reserve for herself the right to divorce! She could
own property and therefore go Into business and handle
financial and legal matters without having to have
authorization from her husband.
She was also entitled to inherit half the share set aside
for male descendants, and at her husband's death, she
had the right to an eighth part of his property. If ehe
were divorced, she had sole custody of all daughters of
the marriage, and sons remained in her charge until the
age of seven.
The interests of married women were as well protected.
Marriage was a civil contract, freely accepted by both
parties and concluded In the presence of two witnesses.
It is true that a man was entitled to have four wives at
the same time, but only on condition that he obeyed the
CONT'D ON NC XT PAGE
(Q Paul Alfriasy, Par!
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
MOSLEM WOMEN (o*'*)
Deprived of rights
by a web of customs
Prophet's explicit Injunction to place them all on a
footing of absolute equality, both in matters of affection
and money.
We are told that the Prophet Introduced this provision
in the Interest of women themselves, and supported it by
his own example. In those days, when war was endemic,
destitute widows were so numerous that to marry several
at a time was one means of alleviating the problem. It
must be admitted that the generous motives which
prompted this custom degenerated over the years.
But according to law, what was true fourteen hundred
years ago remains so today.
Too shy to stand for election
Political rights have been granted to Moslem women
without a struggle. Faithful to the traditions of
Islam, the modern states of Indonesia and Pakistan,
from the moment they came Into being, recognized the
political Independence of their women. They also took
steps to ensure that women should by law remain the
equals of men in their working life. Pakistani and
Indonesian women have the vote, and may stand as
candidates In any kind of election. In Indonesia it is
not unusual for women to be members of municipal and
departmental councils, and there have been several
women Cabinet Members.
The Pakistan government has taken special steps to
encourage women to enter into public life and
affairs, fearing perhaps that they might otherwise be
prevented by shyness or inexperience from assuming their
share in the direction of community affairs. In each of
the local councils, only recently elected, the Government
has reserved a number of seats which will automatically
fall to women after the elections should they not be
adequately represented.
Although Pakistani women may be too shy to present
themselves as candidates, they are by no means in¬
different to matters of public interest. In some provincial
elections, for example, 12% more women went to the polls
than did men.
In theory the same equality holds true for working
women. Nearly all civil service posts are open to them,
and salaries must be exactly the same as for men.
Married to an unknown suitor
This rosy picture of women's rights does not hold true,
however, for the condition in which the majority of
the women of Indonesia and Pakistan found them¬
selves at the beginning of the century, and in which many
of them still find themselves today. For we must always
bear in mind that one of the chief consequences of coloniz¬
ation was the moulding of the community in such a way
as to arrest and paralyse its normal evolution. In such
circumstances, the role of woman became insignificant,
and a splderweb of customs prevented her from exercising
even the most trivial rights, which, theoretically, at least,
were hers.
Women were still respected as mothers, but chlldbearing
was regarded as virtually their only function, and it
occupied the greater part of their time and energy.
Many women were uninterruptedly pregnant from
the age of fourteen on, and it was not unusual for them
to give birth to a score of children during their lifetime.
That, however, was all a woman did. She had no part
in the education of her sons, and as for daughters, she
simply trained them for a life like her own.
She took no part in activities outside the family circle,
and even there, her situation was often precarious. She
was married at a very young age, without being- consult¬
ed, to an unknown suitor chosen for social or economic
reasons. And during her married life she was in constant
fear of being rejected by her husband or supplanted by
Paul Almasy, Paris
Pakistani women journalists, above, exa¬
mine their notes at a press conference in
Karachi. Below, student nurses atop roof of
Lahore clinic discuss anatomy lesson against
backdrop of mosque cupolas and minarets.
United Nations
20
CONT'D ON PAGE 22
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Unesco-Pierre Pittet
Above, Moslem girls and boys mix freely at Gadjah Mada
University in Djakarta, Indonesia during break in class
schedule. Below, Moslem women parade in tho stroots of
Indonesia's capital during a recently-held political rally,
Cartier-Bresson © Magnum
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
MOSLEM WOMEN (Confd)
In Indonesia the veil is unknown
another woman. Her fear was doubled if she failed to
present her husband with a male heir. Possibly the worst
feature of her life, however, was the utter seclusion in
which she was forced to live, without the slightest
opportunity for education.
This was really her chief cause for complaint. A great
deal has been said about Islam's indifference to the fate
of its women. Divorce and polygamy are most frequently
mentioned as evidence of that indifference. In actual
fact, these practices were mostly confined to the wealthy
and powerful.
Polygamy is not easy to practise in a community with
a very low standard of living. It is a luxury in which
few men can afford to indulge. In recent years there has
been a growing tendency to reject the custom of polygamy
entirely, as evidenced by the criticism heard in both
Indonesia and Pakistan a few years ago when two
statesmen President Soekarno of Indonesia and Mo¬
hammed All, the former Prime Minister of Pakistan each
decided to take a second wife.
As for divorce, it is true that it is very easy for a man
to reject his wife. He need only repeat the prescribed
words three times. Still, census returns show that the
number of divorces registered is negligible. This may be
because there are very few divorces, or possibly because
divorced couples are afraid to declare their new status.
For, to be sure, divorce Is severely frowned upon.
The custom of arranged marriages, still widely
prevalent, undoubtedly contributes to stability of the
union for It creates links between families which are gen¬
erally less vulnerable than those formed between two
Individuals. Most divorces occur today among those
classes who have been thrown off balance by too rapid a
social evolution. Traditional values have been undermin¬
ed and the Western concept of love and marriage has
not yet been assimilated, although this concept has spread
widely in both countries since the Second World War.
The Koran and purdah
The situation of a woman today In both Indonesia and
Pakistan depends largely on what class of the com¬
munity she belongs to.
Peasant women in the villages cannot indulge in the
luxury of a quiet, idle life. They work in the fields side
by side with the men. They go to market, sell their
produce, and some of the very poorest of them work as
servants in private homes or shops. Economic necessity,
in their case, takes precedence over tradition. So it is
that many peasant women enjoy greater freedom and
more consideration than many of their women compatriots
who are financially better off.
One should bear in mind in this respect that both
Indonesia and Pakistan are mainly agricultural countries,
and farmers form the majority class. Woman's im¬
portance in a village family is singularly illustrated by a
custom widespread among Indonesian peasants. When a
young man cannot afford to pay the traditional bride-
price, he enters the bride's family and pays his debt by
working for his in-laws (See "Wedding in Sumatra,"
p. 23).
It is the middle class which has the greatest difficulty
adapting itself to a modern way of life. A mistaken
interpretation of the spirit of Islam leads some of its
followers to believe that accepting any change in a
woman's status is tantamount to disobedience to the laws
and traditions of the Koran.
There is no better example of this attitude than the
survival in Pakistan of the custom of "purdah." This
term which has come to signify the complete segregation
of women takes its name from the curtain which is hung
between the women's quarters and the rest of the house
as an Impassable barrier.
The world of Islam has often been reproached for this
custom with all its many consequences, and yet its origin
22
cannot be traced to sacred texts. True enough, the Koran
orders men to have "authority over woman," Allah having
made them her superior, and enjoins women to be modest;
but there is no verse requiring women to wear the veil or
to live in retirement. These practices are not based on
any religious" teaching.
"Purdah," under various names, was common in pre-
Islamic societies of the Orient as an essentially middle-
class custom with nothing compulsory about it. If the
Prophet lent it any authority, it was by not discouraging
it. He even adopted the custom for his own wives. It
thus became firmly established in the countries converted
to Islam, and where it was already practised it grew into
a regular institution. That is the case in Pakistan.
Looking like a walking tent
A woman is not allowed to show herself unveiled
except to her husband. She may not go out unless
she is hung from head to foot with a stiff drapery
that makes her look like a walking tent. It has a slit at
eye level so that she can find her way about, but even this
small aperture is covered with crocheted mesh which
conceals the lustre of her eyes. In this way she is barred
from all social life, and she Is taught nothing except a
few domestic virtues, the most important of which Is
obedience.
Some women of strong character have undoubtedly held
great power, been feared and obeyed even from behind
the veil. But "purdah" has engendered a kind of atrophy
of isolation that cannot be cured overnight. It is difficult
to shake off an apathy which has endured for centuries,
and which men, themselves, have been reluctant to
change. An Englishwoman travelling in Pakistan in 1954
reported that in one village she saw a woman about. to
die in childbirth. Her husband adamantly refused to
allow the local male doctor to attend her because no
midwife was present.
Such extreme cases are becoming increasingly rare,
but even when women have set aside the veil and emerged
from "purdah," they seem to retain a certain mental
attitude, a shyness and reserve, which set limits to their
participation in life outside.
Unfortunately there are no statistics to show the extent
to which "purdah" still prevails in Pakistan and how
much the position has altered since 1947. The fact that
increasing numbers of girls are attending co-educational
schools and universities is evidence of a gradual change.
Pioneers of women's rights
It is not women belonging to the wealthier classes who
are most faithful to the old traditions, for they were
the first to admit the liberal ideas. One result pro¬
duced In these rich families a generation of daughters
who scornfully refused to interest themselves in purely
domestic subjects and embarked instead on more intellec¬
tual studies.
Their studies were seldom carried very far since
marriage soon intervened. More often than not, they
were neither good housewives, nor real intellectuals. And
this situation lent some weight to the attacks of the old
die-hards who were anxious to preserve traditions.
Fortunately this was only a temporary phase, and in any
case many pioneers of the feminist movement in
Pakistan are found among these women.
One factor sharply differentiates the Moslem women of
Pakistan from those of Indonesia. It is the practice of
"purdah." In Indonesia it is virtually unknown. That
is true in part because Mohammedanism is a relative
newcomer to the country and it was long resisted by the
Hindu courts of the various principalities. Thus it is that
Moslem traditions as practised by the upper levels of Java
society are less orthodox, even today, than those of the
rest of the population, especially city dwellers such as
CONT'D ON PAGE 32
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
WEDDING
IN SUMATRA
H ,-*:
' *
Vi*. . \
The photos on this page
show a traditional Moslem
wedding in Sumatra, often
a lavish affair lasting about
six days. The bride wears
an elaborate diadem (pho¬
to above). Great quantities
of food are prepared and
are set on brass trays piled
high with plates of many-
coloured cakes and sweets
(left). These will be served
at the bride's home where
the couple will take up
residence. The groom, or
''borrowed man" as he is
called, plays but a minor
part at the ceremony
which starts with a reli¬
gious service. In photo be¬
low the whole party takes
a jungle path to the bride's
house. Traditional dances
are an important feature
in this as in many other
ceremonies in Indonesia.
Unesco. Marc Riboud
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Karen Juliane, Copenhagen
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1961
îles of pages and millions of words have been
H^^HH written in the past thirty years about the
W effects of the cinema on children. No one
W disputes the obvious fact that children flock
I 1 T 1 eagerly to the cinema the world over. But
111 «from there on the arguments come thick and
kA|AJ ~ast. A new bibliographic study just pub-
I .ished by Unesco (1) now helps us to an
understanding of conclusions reached by the abundant
research and studies into this subject which so actively
interests parents and educators.
Books and articles by some 400 writers from nearly
30 countries are dealt with in this volume and on reading
it, one fact quickly becomes clear: if one thing is known
with certainty about children and the cinema, it is that
very little is known with certainty as one writer
jokingly puts it.
But once this note of caution has been sounded, some
broad, significant trends can be discerned.
At various points in this world debate on the cinema's
influence it is possible, without taking a show of hands,
to gauge "the feeling of the meeting".
Studies on the educational film that is, on the use of
the film strictly as a teaching aid have been excluded
from this bibliography in order to keep the publication
within manageable proportions, but such action does not
rule out the topic of film education or, as it is called in
several countries, "film appreciation". In point of fact,
the growing interest in film education, allied with the
development of ciné-clubs for the young, the production
and distribution of special children's entertainment
films, and the presentation of special programmes, rep¬
resents the most noticeable of the trends which can
be detected.
Large numbers of writers advocate that teaching
about the cinema should not merely be encouraged
but that it should be given formal recognition in
the school curriculum.' In several countries (e.g. the
U.S.S.R., and the United Kingdom) even before the period
covered by this book, this attitude existed. Any attempt
to classify a collection of data such as this into positive
and negative categories would have been "unscientific",
yet, as against those viewpoints which are plainly anta¬
gonistic towards the cinema and its effects on the young,
one cannot help being impressed by the volume of opinion
in favour of the educational aspects and practical
measures which are considered as positive influences of
the film.
The largest sections of the book, in fact, are those
dealing with these topics, and even censorship, tradi¬
tionally regarded as essentially negative, is represented
as capable of being a positive factor. For example, in
a country such as New Zealand the Censor, who is a statu¬
tory official, is able, in effect, to certify not merely that
a film is harmless for children to see but even that it is
entertainment which they should particularly enjoy.
The individual opinions expressed by writers are often
sharply contradictory, but nowhere more so than in the
field of "juvenile delinquency". However, two or three
assumptions can safely be made after an examination
of material published on this tendentious and contro¬
versial subject. One is that, on the evidence so far
available, it is extremely difficult indeed, virtually im¬
possible to establish that the cinema has a direct
influence on juvenile delinquency. While a great deal of
research has been carried out to decide whether or not
films corrupt youth, what has been done is conflicting
both as to methods and results.
(1) The Influence of the Cinema on Children and Adolescents ; an
annotated international bibliography, Paris, Unesco, 1961. (Reports
and Papers on Mass Communication N" 31) Published in English and
French; price: $1.50; 7/6d; 5.25 NF. A companion volume on the
influence of television on children and adolescents is in preparation.
There are a number of psychiatric theories on the
subject, but the evidence in support of them is incon¬
clusive. At the one extreme it is claimed that films acti¬
vely incite young people to delinquency; at the other
that they are safety-valves which may help to prevent
it: on the one hand, that they supply first-hand know¬
ledge of how to commit criminal acts; on the other that,
by keeping children off the streets, they prevent Juvenile
misbehaviour and crime. A "half-way" attitude is that
the Influence of films on young people cannot be isolated
from other social factors and that criminal and amoral
behaviour is to be imputed to deeper and more subtle
influences than the film alone; although much that is
shown on the screen is unsuitable for children.
Possibly It will be said that anybody who wants support
for his pet theory will find It somewhere In this
survey. There is no doubt that a good many hobby¬
horses are ridden through Its pages. Nevertheless, while
there is no unanimity about the direct Influence of the
cinema, a majority of authors do speak of indirect and
unconscious Influences. The consensus of their opinion
Is that such Influences are rarely the product of a single
film or even of several, but are much more likely to be the
outcome of a succession of movies with similar themes
and tendencies, causing by repetition a new state of mind
or change of outlook in the young spectator.
To put it another way, it is widely argued that the
repeated presentation of certain themes and behaviour
patterns on the screen Is much more likely to produce
a long-term indirect effect than the immediate, overt
influence of any individual film, however specific Its
message. The broad generalization which might be made
is that the film has mainly a provocative effect but Is
rarely a basic cause of delinquent acts.
It would seem to be accepted now as almost beyond
doubt that boys and girls get Ideas from the movies on
such superficial and generally harmless matters as dress,
hair-styles, speech, recreations and games. So far as
harmful influences are concerned, the factors most fre¬
quently cited as responsible are over-emphasis and dis¬
torted presentation of crime, cruelty and horror, and of
those elements which may be put under the generic label
of "sex".
However, as the evidence of the bibliographical entries
reveals, considerable concern Is also felt among parents
and educators about the effects of a number of rather
less obvious elements in cinema entertainment. There
is a prevailing objection to the artificial conception of
life in the world of the cinema (where what is extreme
is presented as normal) which is said to endanger the
sense of values of the immature.
Among aspects in this category that draw critical fire
are: the recurrent portrayal of luxury and of the
"easy life"; the "glorification" of revenge as a
motive; the unrealistic solutions put forward when
difficulties arise; and the artificial patterns of the "boy-
meets-glrl" situation. Several writers draw attention to
the stereotyped Images which the screen creates both of
characters (e.g. the cowboy and the gangster) and of
modes of behaviour; and the question is raised whether this
stereotyping may give a wrong conception of national life
and customs to young audiences in other countries. There
Is some evidence that In the case of racial attitudes or
prejudices, these can be influenced in one direction or
the other by a few striking films only.
It might have been expected that the entries in the
section of the bibliography headed "juvenile delinquency"
would all be of comparatively recent vintage. But this
is not so. There are studies on the subject dating back
to 1933 and 1929; and the opinion of one writer is quoted
to the effect that study in this field began soon after
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
CHILDREN AND THE CINEMA (Cont'd)
DO YOU KNOW THEIR
FOUR CINEMA AGES?
1910in other words practically as soon as the cinema
started to make an Impact on the general public.
Furthermore, writers and theorists appear to have been
divided from the outset as to whether the film has any
direct influence on the youngand if so, why. Even the
Increased availability and use of scientific research
techniques has not noticeably clarified the situation in
this branch of the subject. In this context it is justi¬
fiable to draw attention to the wish expressed by one
writer that there should be closer co-operation between
the different investigators in the field of film and youth.
In other sections of the Unesco survey the issues are
rather more clearcut than they are in those devoted to
juvenile delinquency and other of the cinema after-effects.
For instance, in the sections on cinema attendance and
film preferences, several trends emerge fairly clearly. . .
Some of these trends may seem obvious: nevertheless
it is useful to find confirmation, from many quarters, of
the view that children in general go to the cinema more
often than their parents and that as they grow older
they go less and less in parental company; that boys
tend to go more often than girls; and that the children
who are most frequent attenders are (to generalize) those
who are unhappy or lonely, those who want "to escape
from daily life" and therefore are seeking distraction,
and those who have least interest in other activities.
Rather more specifically, there is evidence to show
that attendance is affected by standards of income, intel¬
ligence and education, with children at the lower levels
in these three aspects going to the movies more fre¬
quently than children who are well off, of high intelli¬
gence, and carefully educated.
In very many works on the influence of the cinema,
the age of the audience under review assumes first-rank
importance, because of its bearing on their habits and
behaviour as fllmgoers, on their understanding of the
medium and the effects it has upon them, on measures
of censorship and legislation, and on the production and
selection of what are regarded as suitable programmes.
From a perusal of the items in this bibliography, four
significant stages or periods in the development of young
people's filmgoing can be distinguished reasonably clearly,
even though it will be realized that one should not be
arbitrary about age- grouping and that one phase will
merge into another.
The first stage is that up »to the age of 7 years, the
so-called, "fairy-tale age" in which children live in
an imaginary world. It may be noted here that a
substantial body of opinion Inclines to the view that the
movie theatre is no place for infants and therefore, in
general, that children should not start picture-going
before the age of 7, and certainly not without the
company of a parent or some other responsible adult.
The second age-group covers the period between 7 and
12. This is what is known as "the Robinson age", when
experience of realism comes more and more to the fore
and children are mostly interested in adventure and
action. But it is also noticeable that they can already
adopt an objective attitude, and can follow the main
lines of action in a story.
This period merges into the third stage, that of the
age of puberty, between 12 and 16, when the child's
personality Is markedly developing and tensions are
rising. By this time the average child is strongly
attracted towards the cinema, although aware of its
fictitious nature. He can not only comprehend the film
26
FILMS BOYS PREFER
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
FILMS GIRLS PREFER
t¿ s-
MUSICALS
The Unesco Courler. * March 1961
as a whole, but can also form some Interpretation of the
screenplay's internal structure and meaning.
This view is supported by those writers who claim that
"film language" cannot be understood by children before
the age of puberty. A variation of this Is the theory that
two phases can be distinguished in the development of
the child's understanding of the cinema, a«-mcntal level
of 10 years being necessary to keep pace with sequences
and with the various techniques of film expression, while
a proper grasp of a film's real significance demands a
mental age of at least 12 years.
Most writers consider that the fourth stage in film
comprehension starts at about 16 or 17 which, in a num¬
ber of countries, is the age when young fllmgoers are
legally regarded as having reached adult status and arc
therefore no longer subject to censorship restrictions.
Their Interest in the cinema is largely Influenced by the
desire to penetrate the mysteries of the adult world
which they themselves are now entering.
LOVE STORIES
EVERYDAY LIFE
But it Is the age of 12 or 13 which Is seen as the
crucial dlvlding-Une. The problem of the film
begins at 12 years, it is said, and among the writers
on the subject whose works are represented In the
Unesco. bibliography it is fairly generally agreed that the
reactions of adolescents at the cinema are noticeably
different from those of children, the onset of puberty
producing not only a new outlook on films and a better
understanding of what films are saying, but also sharper
impressions and stronger effects on Imagination and
sentiments, with the consequent appearance of new
problems. It Is, for example, In adolescence that the cult
of "star worship" becomes most evident.
So far as preferences In screen entertainment are
concerned, it is a commonplace to say that tastes in films
mature as the individual himself matures. However, it
may safely be adduced from the evidence available here
that boys prefer films of adventure, action and violence,
while girls like those concerned with love, private Ufe,
and "glamour".
These categories may be broken down a little further, '
as follows: for boys Westerns, war films, comedies, ani¬
mal films, musicals, detective and crime thrillers, sports
stories; for girls musicals, nature and animal films,
comedies, stories about love, everyday life and human
relations.
One may sum up these particular trends by saying
that in addition to levels of education, intelligence, age
and income, the social milieu and conditions at home
exert an influence on the frequency of children's visits
to the cinema and on their preferences, tastes, and re¬
actions to films. But It would be hazardous to make a
more precise statement than I have here attempted.
It seems to be generally agreed that there is such a
thing as "film language" and that educators must take
account of its existence, for the reason that films cannot
be properly understood and appreciated without some
knowledge of this visual language and Its "grammar".
Similarly, as regards production, there appears to be
little doubt that simplicity is a prerequisite in the making
of films for children, particularly young children, who
have difficulty in following "film language" (camera
movement, time symbols, etc.) which involves a different
process from that required for reading and understanding
a book.
Those writers and there are many who favour en¬
couragement of "film-teaching", especially through
ciné-clubs and film discussions (either at the club or in
the classroom Itself), have a generally consistent idea
about the broad lines along which such activities should
be conducted. Again, there is virtual unanimity that it
is highly desirable for films to be made and distributed
specially for children, just as there are few divergences
of opinion about the pitfalls which will be encountered
if this valuable task is attempted or the ways in which
difficulties might be avoided.
27
NATURE
Photos Hoveyda Collection
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
WORLD'S
YOUNGEST
CINEMAGOERS
Small children will watch the shooting down of scores
of Indians in a Western film with perfect equanimity,
but the sight of a sick horse or bird in a film immediately
upsets them. This is one of the findings from a special
study carried out over a period of ten years by Danish
educators on the effects of films on kindergarten chil¬
dren aged 3 to 7. The study was carried out with govern¬
ment support and Denmark is one of the few countries
in which kindergarten children visit government granted
film performances regularly. Here they are supervised
by Mrs. Ellen Siersted, a child psychologist attached to
the Danish Government Film Office (above right). Some
of the findings: Contrary to common belief many car¬
toons and Tarzanlike films frighten very young children ;
some cried and tried to leave the cinema, others had
nausea, and parents later reported cases of bedwetting
and nightmares. Yet the same children said they thought
the films funny and at first, refused to admit they were
scared. Child audiences get particularly upset when
they see small animals or children get lost. They become
frightened and cry and ask if the animals or children
will get back to mother again. Equally significant are
the positive impressions revealed in the classroom
where children recapture the ¡mages with pencil and
brush. Drawing (below right) was made by a five-
year-old girl to explain a film she had seen about a little
ship and its crew. (Photos on this page, on front
cover and page 26 were taken during the Danish study.)
Photos © Karen Juliane, Copenhagen
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Morch 1961
The curse of the Albatross
A MARINER'S
MYTH
by David Gunston
Illustration by Gustave Doré
Not long ago the British cargo liner Calpean
Star arrived at Liverpool from South Georgia
carrying In addition to its usual cargo a
consignment of live penguins and other local
fauna secured by a professional animal-
collector and destined for a German zoo. Among the
other specimens was an albatross, said to be a wandering
albatross, the largest of the known species and the
biggest of all sea-birds. At the time this was claimed,
probably correctly, to be the only live albatross in Europe
or in captivity anywhere.
Soon after the ship docked the albatross died In its
cage, allegedly through being given a sausage-roll to eat
by a well-meaning but misguided sailor, but more probably
because of the impossibility of keeping a large oceanic
bird in confinement for more than a brief period.
At once, a cloud hung over the Calpean Star. Her
crew blamed various misfortunes of the voyage just
ended on the bird's presence on board, and rather than
man the ship for the return trip they went on strike.
This attracted a good deal of attention, and in subsequent
press and TV interviews various members of the crew
and the captain all professed their belief that the hapless
albatross was a creature of Ill-omen, responsible for their
troubles, that never ought to have been shipped.
The master himself admitted that the bird had been
taken on board against his better judgment, and
that he had regretted its very presence on his ship,
vowing never to repeat the mistake. Some of the crew
swore never to sail the ship again, and on every hand
there was firm proof of the power of the ancient legend
of the albatross.
Public interest in this odd case was centred not only
upon yet another strange reason for a strike in a strike-
torn land, but also upon the indisputable fact that here
were tough, grown men so afraid of the consequences of
a sea-bird's death that they refused to return to their
ship. Now sailors are by long tradition superstitious folk,
but this seemed to be carrying things rather too far.
All through, there was much mention of The Rime of
the Ancient Mariner, and how that famous character In
English literature had killed an albatross and lived to
regret it. Even the cynical few who felt that not all
merchant seamen read poetry, believed that these other¬
wise normal men were simply responding to a deep-
seated, age-old belief that to kill one of these noble birds
meant bad weather at sea, mounting misfortune, and
worse.
Yet the odd thing is that such a familiar legend is in
fact suspect. There is hardly any evidence whatever for
including it among the superstitions of the sea. On the
contrary, sailors generally have never had the slightest
compunction in destroying albatrosses. Could it be that
twentieth-century mariners were superstitiousand to
such lengthsabout a piece of eighteenth-century liter¬
ary invention? Let us examine the facts.
Many sea-fowl, notably gulls, petrels and gannets, have
for centuries been believed by seamen to be creatures of
ill-omen, chiefly because they were thought to be the
doomed souls of dead sailors transmigrated Into lonely,
restless denizens of the sea. Few mariners, even to this
day, would willingly kill a storm-petrel, devll-blrd, or
"Mother Carey's Chicken" for this reason. But careful
research among accounts of nautical credulities and
superstitions over several centuries fails to reveal any
mention of albatrosses.
In fact, whatever the period of history, albatrosses were
regarded as Just another creature met with at sea, to
be killed, if need be, without turning a hair. During
Drake's circumnavigation of the globe, 1577-9, large num¬
bers were encountered and eaten as food. The stomachs
of the first Elizabethans were clearly stronger than those
of today, but even In this century albatross flesh has
been eaten in South Georgia, particularly from the young
birds taken from their nests.
Dr. L. Harrison Matthews, Director of the London Zoo,
writing In 1951 of earlier experience In these far southern
albatross breeding-grounds, said:
Albatrosses, like all sea-birds, must be skinned soon
after they are killed If they are to be worth eating... It Is
the fat under the skin and round the Intestines that
taints the meat with a fishy flavour.
And his first-hand accounts of the butchery by Nor¬
wegian whalemen of nesting albatrosses, to say nothing
of the large-scale thefts of the birds' single gigantic eggs
(each fills a large frying-pan) during the 1930s, dispel
any lingering belief in the traditional superstition.
Old-time sailors often had great sport "fishing" for
albatrosses, especially when becalmed in those
lonely waters. After Drake's day, albatross flesh was
less commonly eaten, though another great voyager, Cap¬
tain Cook, writing in 1775, described how : "a few alba¬
trosses and petrels were shot as a necessary treat for our
table."
A mariner of his experience and wisdom would never
have allowed such a thing if there had been any deep-
seated feeling amongst his men against it. Most of the
birds were captured and killed for sheer wanton sport.
They are absurdly easy to secure with a large hook baited
with salt pork, or with a brass triangle baited with meat
and proffered at the end of a cod-line. On grasping the
CONT'D ON PAGE 3 I
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
A MARINER'S MYTH (Cont'd)
'I shot the albatross'
When in 1798 the English poet and philosopher Samuel Coleridge wrote "The Rime of the Ancient Mariner", a long poem in
ballad form, he little guessed the extraordinary repercussions it would have. By telling the story of a sailor who killed an
albatross and thus brought down misfortune on his ship and its crew, he created the legend of the albatross as a bird of ill
fate and the strong superstition of mariners against killing albatrosses. When Coleridge wrote the poem he was collaborating
with William Wordsworth on a joint volume in which Coleridge was to treat supernatural subjects. It was Wordsworth who
suggested the idea for the poem after having read an English navigator's account of the killing of an albatross in the South
Seas, and later Coleridge admitted his Rime to be "a work of pure imagination". Since then dictionaries and encyclopaedias
have further perpetuated the fallacious fable of the sea, quoting Coleridge's poem as following the legend, not creating it.
Above, how Gustave Doré, depicted the shooting of the albatross in one of the. first French translations of the poem.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courler. March 1961
This was no bird of ill omen
meat, the bird refuses to let go and is readily pulled down
on the deck though some accounts speak of two men
being needed to haul in the larger species.
Once on board, the line may be released, for the huge
almost entirely aerial creature cannot rise again easily,
even after dropping the bait and "lightening ship" by
bringing up the oily contents of Its stomach. This is a
natural reaction of many sea-birds when they require
increased manoeuvrability in the face of danger or
difficulty, and not a symptom of albatross sea-sickness as
was formerly believed.
Anyway, most sailors were ready for such sport,
laughing at the helpless bird's inability either to walk
properly or to take off again, and captured albatrosses
were put to a number of ingenious uses. The oily vomit
was saved and used to waterproof sea-boots, but the
feathers and feet were most in demand. The downy
breasts made handsome muffs, surpassing in beauty the
once-fashionable grebe muffs, while two or three sewn
together made a very beautiful cape that was sure to
meet with feminine favour at home.
Skins of the birds also made excellent feather-rugs
(hence perhaps the nickname "Cape Sheep" for alba-
trosses), and sometimes the complete head, neck
and beak were preserved as trophies. The webbing from
the large feet was always in demand for making tobacco-
pouches: it seems that the slight oiliness of the skin kept
the tobacco agreeably moist. The wing-bones, cleaned
and blown hollow, made excellent, unbreakable pipe-
stems, much enjoyed for cool smoking. In South Georgia
to this day, albatross wings, cut off at the elbow, are used
as sweeping-brushes.
Nevertheless, during the nineteenth century in
particular, even after the Ancient Mariner's debut, there
was much wanton shooting of albatrosses from the in¬
creasing number of ships that were sailing the oceans.
Passengers having little else to do would often take pot
shots at the trusting birds that followed their ships.
According to the famous scientific explorer William Sco-
resby, voyaging in 1856, this was "'a prevalent usage in
many ships travelling to Australia," while another
observer of 1862 spoke of what he called the "murder
of the innocents."
How, then, did the albatross legend arise? The man
chiefly responsible seems to be the English poet, Samuel
Taylor Coleridge (1772-1834), solely through his most
famous poem The Rime of the Ancient Mariner, first
published in 1798.
The genesis of the story in the poet's mind is of
relevant interest. In the autumn of 1797 he set off on
a walking tour in Somerset with his friend the poet
Wordsworth, and his sister Dorothy. Each poet decided
to write a poem to meet the expenses of the trip, and
Coleridge planned his narrative of what he afterwards
called his "old navigator," partly from a dream
experienced by another friend.
Coleridge discussed this idea with Wordsworth who at
once delighted in It and suggested additions. Re¬
counting to a friend in later years, Wordsworth revealed:
"Much the greater part of the story was Mr. Coleridge's
invention; but certain parts I myself suggested... I had
been reading in Shelvocke's Voyages, a day or two before,
that, while doubling Cape Horn, they frequently saw
albatrosses in that latitude... "Suppose," said I,"you
represent him as having killed one of these birds on
entering the South Sea, and that the tutelary spirits of
these regions take upon them to revenge the crime?"
This appealed to Coleridge's strong sense of the su¬
pernatural, and with his own extensive reading of the old
voyagers, his powerful gift of words, and his individual
dream-fantasies (doubtless partly due to his addiction to
opium), he at once created in the lengthy Rime a
masterpiece of English literature, little guessing the
extraordinary results it was to have.
The book that started off Wordsworth's thought-trails
towards the subject of albatrosses was In fact Cap¬
tain George Shelvocke's A Voyage Round the World
by Way of the Great South Sea, published In London In
1757, and in it the author describes the seals, penguins,
petrels and albatrosses his ship encounters in those
southerly latitudes. He goes on to tell how, one day in
October 1719, his vessel, the little Speedwell, was subjected
"to continuous squalls of sleet, snow and rain" for days
on end, with the heavens overcast and not a single ilsh'or
sea-bird to be seen:
Excepting a disconsolate black Albitross (.sic), who
accompanied us for several days, and hovered about us
as if he had lost himself, till Hatley (my second captain)
concluding, In a gloomy fit, that the company of this
melancholy blrd^ brought us 111 luck, resolved to destroy
him In the hopes we might then have better weather,
and more favourable winds...
Hatley did in fact shoot the bird, but Shelvockc
mentions no particular result either way, and the
Speedwell continued her voyage as before.
It is strange that whereas Shelvocke's albatross was
considered to be a creature of 111 omen, that killed by the
Ancient Mariner was a bird of good omen. In fact,
there Is strong evidence that Coleridge intended his poem
to be a strong parable, not only teaching a love of animals
as is usually supposed, but inculcating a love of God. Ills
use of the albatross was symbolic a messenger of God
and the Mariner's crime the very real one of blasphemy.
When later in the story, the Ancient Mariner", his penance
done, repents in prayer, the dead bird falls from his neck
"like lead into the sea," never to trouble him again.
Writing a few years before his death, Coleridge
admitted his Rime to be "a work of pure Imagi¬
nation", but it is almost Incredible how such a work,
dreamed up on holiday by two enthusiastic young poets,
should have created a fallacious fable of the sea.
Yet the legend of the albatross is deeply engrained.
Almost every dictionary and reference book includes
under "Albatross" some such remark as: "It is a su¬
perstition among sailors that it is disastrous to shoot
one," while the world's great encyclopaedias further
perpetuate the misconception. For example, the En¬
cyclopaedia Britannica: "Sailors are fond of them and
have a strong superstition against killing them; and the
Americana: Sailors' superstition about killing them was
used In Coleridge's Rime of the Ancient Mariner.
In every case, Coleridge's poem is quoted as following
the legend, not creating it. Of course, the albatross is
particularly suited to such a legend the largest of sea-
birds, gliding for miles over ships' sterns with scarcely
a wing-flap.
So whether the crew of the Calpean Star ever read
Coleridge and his Ancient Mariner is irrelevant. The
legend he created is now, after over 150 years, so deep-
rooted that they, and doubtless others as well, believe in
it so strongly that they are prepared to go on strike over
Here, surely, is the strangest of all the many strange
superstitions of the sea.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
MOSLEM WOMEN (Cont'd from page 22)
A startling goal: back to the Middle Ages
tradespeople and government employees, whose numbers
are constantly increasing.
Notwithstanding this, the seclusion of women (by no
means the exclusive prerogative of Islam as so many
people think) was also practised in aristocratic circles of
Indonesia although not with the same austerity found
in other Islamic countries. This is evident from the long
struggle that Adjeng Kartlni, the pioneer of Indonesia's
emancipation movement, had to wage early in the
century. A vivid account of her struggle is given in her
Letters which will soon be published in French and
English translations in Unesco's Collection of Representa¬
tive Works (Indonesia Series). Her example has inspired
many upper class Indonesian women to follow in her
footsteps and these women are now among the leaders
of their country's emancipation movement.
With the great mass of Indonesia's women, however, the
problem is less acute, for they have remained more or
less free, despite the fact that there is a good deal of
traditionalism found in most villages. On the whole,
however, one can say that Indonesia has not known the
strictness and severity that Islamlsm assumed in the
Middle East. It is not at all unusual, for example, to
see a woman in Indonesia seated by the roadside pub¬
licly breast-feeding her child.
We have seen how important divorce, polygamy and
purdah have been as retarding factors in the lives of
Moslem women, but these pale almost to insignificance
when compared to the isolation which the women of both
Indonesia and Pakistan have suffered as a result of
ignorance and total lack of education.
Education unfeminine ?
This situation affects even the well-to-do. Until very
recently, most fathers considered education superflu¬
ous and even harmful for their daughters. A good
marriage, they said, was the only suitable career, and they
feared that education would make them less feminine.
Nowadays, education for women may be accepted, but it
is still often regarded as a mere ornament, a plus-factor
that sends a girl's stock up on the marriage market. Few
girls advance beyond secondary schools. Those who do
are often tempted into continuing by the Domestic Science
course offered as bait for future housewives.
We should not jump to the conclusion from this that
Indonesian and Pakistani women never train for a
profession. They do, but their choice is sharply limited
because of a still prevalent feeling that women should
have no contact with the masculine world. The favourite
profession for women is teaching. Next in popularity is
medicine, but all her patients must be women. When
a young lady enters such professions, neither her father or
her husband feels that he is losing prestige, and these
are not considered big money-making positions. So far
there is little competition between the two sexes. Like
their European brothers a few years ago, Moslem men
have long frowned upon the emergence of women into
their own workaday world.
Art careers still taboo
But today things are changing. The Moslem woman
now has a status which, though still modest, affords
her ever expanding opportunities. Indonesia has
already had a woman Minister of Labour. Pakistan has
a woman ambassador. And more and more Moslem
women from both countries are now studying science in
Europe on fellowships.
At the same time, office work and secretarial employ¬
ment still attract large numbers of women. "Air Pa¬
kistan" is extremely proud of its air hostesses, and their
attractive and picturesque uniforms, green tunics over
ample white trousers, are symbolic of the present transi
tional period. There is still one profession, however,
which remains taboo even today. Anything concerned
with art Is still kept squarely within the male domain.
We might say that middle class people seem to be
following the same line of development as one has found
in Europe, but among the poorer classes the situation is
markedly different.
In 1940, 90% of the population of Indonesia was
illiterate. According to official figures, that high propor¬
tion has been reduced to 57%. In Pakistan in 1951,
official figures indicated that 25% of the men could read,
but only 11.4% of the women. School attendance among
the poorer » Inhabitants of both countries is still far too
low despite efforts made by governments and women's
groups. There is still a great shortage of schools for girls,
but there is much improvement over the situation 60
years ago when neither country had any such institution.
No gossiping matrons
Efforts already made In this field have been consider¬
able. But the effort still required is tremendous.
Take for example the statistics from the State of
Punjab In Pakistan which are fairly typical although
overall figures are lacking. In 1949, with a population of
19,000,000, the number of girls attending school was a
bare 6,145. By 1953 this number had risen to 102,369 and
today it has doubled.
But despite the improvement, girls from poor families
have very little prospect of continuing their education
beyond primary school which they leave at the age of
ten. Taking again the Punjab figures, there were
1,845 primary schools as against only 145 secondary
schools.
Progress in the education of women has been slow, re¬
tarded by the indifference of the wealthy, the timidity of
the middle class and the extreme poverty of the humble
people. Yet the improvement has been sufficient to en¬
courage those who have tackled this gigantic task
principally government departments, aided and abetted by
a number of courageous voluntary organizations.
The latter are worth our attention. Most of them are
women's organizations, but they should not be confused
with either frivolous social meetings of gossiping ma¬
trons, or suffragette groups stridently proclaiming their
rights. They devote themselves with great energy and
efficiency to social welfare work.
Age-old rights of Islam
Some of the chief aims of the Federation of Indonesian
Women founded in 1928 are to improve the social
status of women, particularly those who are married ;
to eradicate prostitution; to prohibit child marriages, and
most important of all, to open schools and establish
funds for education. The All Pakistan Women's Associa¬
tion has similar aims. Under its sponsorship teaching
centres have been established where mothers are taught
to read and write, and social centres have been formed
where they can obtain free medical and legal advice.
In simple fact, the work being done by these associa¬
tions is really rehabilitation, for most of the rights for
which Western women waged such a long struggle, have
always been part of the traditional heritage of Moslem
women.
These associations are battling to restore the age-old
rights of the Islamic woman. They are determined to
ensure that in this twentieth century, she will be worthy
of all the rights enjoyed by her eighth century predecess¬
or. They strive, above all, to make her capable of exercis¬
ing these rights. They are revealing to her the ever
broadening horizons now open to Asia's Moslem women.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courler. March 1961
Letters to the Editor...
THE RACISM ISSUE
Sir,
My felicitations on the October
"Racism" issue. I have a certain
proprietary interest in it, since the
famous inside-cover picture of the
terrified little boy in the Warsaw
ghetto was first discovered by me.
This happened in 1945 when I was a
T/Sgt. with the International Military
Tribunal. Mr. Justice Jackson asked
me to screen tons of Reichssicher¬
heitshauptamt files to find documents
of probative value for the indictment.
In the course of several twenty-hour
days, one document I came across
was a photograph-adorned report to
Himmler which bore the matter-of-
fact title: "Das Warschauer Juden¬
viertel besteht nicht mehr" (The
Jewish quarter in Warsaw no longer
exists) and had been written by SS
General Jürgen Stroop.
Paul W. Freedman
Casablanca, Morocco
Sir,
Just a brief note of appreciation
for your recent issue on Racism.
A. Gargantilla Rodriguez
Madrid, Spain
Sir,
The October issue of The Unesco
Courier has special meaning for
South Africa, and it is only a pity
that the people who could most
benefit from it will not even see it.
I write to thank you for this excellent
issue on what you call "Racism"
and we call "Racialism", and to
give you a recent example of what
racialism means in action to human
beings.
It is the case of a little boy, called
by the newspapers "George X". He
had a white skin, blue eyes and fair
hair, and he lived in the country
with an old African couple whom
he regarded as his grandparents, and
who had adopted him.
Inevitably, his "white" appearance
attracted attention, newspapers took
up the story, and he was summarily
removed from his home while efforts
were made to trace his parents. At
first the newspapers thought he was
the son of a white woman who had
abandoned her baby eight years
previously. After investigation it
was found that the couple with whom
he had been living were actually his
grand parents, and the little boy was
what we call "Coloured" child of
a mixed marriage between his African
mother and a white man. Being
Coloured, and of light skin, the
authorities could not permit him to
go on living with Africans. He is
now in a Children's Home. The
parting from the couple who cared
for him was so moving, the news¬
papers told us, that even the officials
who effected it had tears in their
eyes. Warm-hearted people! A
second result of the newspapers
chasing this story was that they also
"discovered" the little white boy who
had been abandoned by his mother.
He was living with an Indian couple
who had adopted him and brought
him up as their son. He was removed
from them.
It is not necessary to comment.
These are the less spectacular results
of racialism in South Africa. The
poison twists and maims not «only
those against whom it is directed, but
the white racialists who propagate it.
Hilda Bernstein
Johannesburg, South Africa
Sir,
Congratulations on your power¬
fully reasoned issue on Racism. It
was one of the best numbers I have
seen and one worthy of being banned
anywhere where the four-million
lessons of Auschwitz have not been
learnt.
James Corbett
London, England
THE WORLD'S HUMOUR
Sir,
Humour and comedy are inter¬
national in scope and content, but
it is difficult to find material except in
books and magazines in English, pub¬
lished in the United Kingdom or in
the United States of America. I am
collecting humorous books and maga¬
zines and am beginning a study of
Humour, National and International.
I would be pleased to hear from
any reader with similar interests, par¬
ticularly those in Asian, Scandinavian
and South American countries. Refe¬
rences to any published studies of the
humour of particular countries would
be very valuable to me.
Although I am primarily interested
in written material, I include film,
theatre, television and radio comedy
too; my study is concerned with the
psychological and philosophical aspects
of humour, with its associated artis¬
tic and literary interest.
Eric G. Linfield
233 Shephall Way
Half Hyde, Stevenage, England
DELIGHTS OF HAIKU
Sir,
In the teaching of creative writing
to children, ages 10-12, the delights
of Haiku were introduced to them
last year. This form of Japanese
poetry, at once so limiting and at
the same time so challenging and
free, seems to be virtually unheard
of in our country. In one of the
few recent books on Haiku, I read
where there are some fifty or more
magazines published in Japan devoted
exclusively to this form of poetry.
Perhaps a feature article in the
near future would bring this noble
art form within reach of poets every¬
where. I would also be interested
in hearing from Japanese classroom
teachers who devote a part of their
teaching to this area of Japanese
descriptive writing.
Lloyd V. Rogers
O'Connor School, Elliott
Drive, Mcnlo Park
California, U.S.A.
THE MEANING OF LAUGHTER
Sir,
Just one particular comment I
should like to make: the article, "I
weep, therefore I am" (March 1960)
was very interesting but there arc
three points on which I found I
differed with the author:
First, concerning laughter laughter
is not always a "harsh" sound.
Many of us know persons whose
laughter is delightfully melodic or
pleasingly resonant. Then, humour is
not always derived from "our own
or somebody else's discomfiture".
Has no one laughed at a cute baby
blissfully sucking its toe, at fluffy
kittens or woolly lambs enjoying a
game, at a cavorting comedian or at
exciting good news7 And, thirdly, we
are not the only creatures who laugh,
as anyone will know who has ever
seen a dog anticipating a good frolic.
Moreover, how does the psychologist
know a hyena isn't enjoying himself
sometimes, when he "laughs"?
It seems to me our psychologists
some of them at any rate arc far
too ready to attribute all actions and
emotions to baser instincts.
A. Freda Davles
Victoria, B.C. Canada
NO APPEAL IN MASS APPEAL
Sir,
Much as we approve the general
purposes of Unesco, we feel your
magazine rarely covers any of its
subjects adequately... Perhaps your
attempt at mass appeal through use
of a popular format just does not
appeal to us. Your similarity to such
publications as "Life" Magazine is
obvious, but not seemly, we think, for
an institution stressing education,
science and culture !
Mrs. Robert Clark
Bristol, Great Britain
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Ne
THE UNESCO
PHILATELIC SERVICE
I'NITKI» NATIONS
- INTERNATIONAL £
% COURT OK JUSTICE =
y !a
NATIONS UNIES
The first United Nations comm¬
emorative stamp for 1961 (above)
honours the International Court
of Justice, the judicial arm of the
United Nations. The Court, with
Its permanent seat at The Hague,
Netherlands, Is composed of 1 5
judges, and adjudicates, In accor¬
dance with International law, all
disputes submitted to it by states.
The stamp commemorating its work
was Issued on February 1 3 in
two denominations of 4c. (brown,
black and yellow) and 8c. (green,
black and yellow), the motif being
a detail from Raphael's "Stanze".
It can be obtained from the Unesco
Philatelic Service which has stamps
and first day covers issued by many
member states to commemorate
important events in the history of
Unesco and the United Nations.
As the agent in France of the U.N.
Postal Administration, Unesco's
Philatelic Service stocks all the
United Nations stamps currently
on sale. Information on Items avail¬
able, their price and methods of
payment, will be sent on request
by the Unesco Philatelic Service,
Place de Fontenoy, Paris (7").
w ORK CAMP LEADERS FOR A
CONTINENT: Youth leaders from all
parts of Latin America have recently been
attending a special regional training
course for work camp leaders the first
of its kind to be held in this continent
in Paraguay. Organized by the Interna¬
tional Voluntary Work Camp movement,
its aim has been to encourage youth in
Latin American countries to help in
constructive social and community work.
Unesco has been aiding this leader's
training project through its Gift Coupon
programme. Donor groups participating
in the scheme have been purchasing Unesco
34
Gift Coupons which are being used to pay
travel expenses for youth leaders who
have to travel long distances, and also
to provide books, audio-visuai aids and
other teaching materials for the training
course.
WESTERN MUSIC GOES EAST:
Can classical Western music be
understood and appreciated by Asian
listeners accustomed to entirely diffe¬
rent musical traditions? The answer is
yes, according to one Pakistani music-
lover, Ershad AH Bokhari, who is
planning with a group of friends to
establish an Academy of Western
Music at Karachi probably the first
of its kind in Asia. The Academy will
have a double goal: to train young mu¬
sicians and to develop an already
growing taste for Western music in
Pakistan.
SiUNCOAT FOR A LAKE: To
combat natural evaporation which is
causing the level of Lake Sevan in the
mountains of the Armenian Soviet Soc¬
ialist Republic to drop excessively,
scientists are to cover the lake's surface
with a film of chemical liquid. The
composition of the film is harmless to
fish and other animal life, lets through
the rain, but blocks the scorching rays of
the sun. After tests in inlets, the whole
of Lake Sevan will be covered and this
should reduce evaporation by a thousand
million cubic metres of water yearly.
PHYSICS AT UPPSALA: The Uni¬
versity of Uppsala, Sweden, is or¬
ganizing an International Seminar for
Research and Education in Physics
this year. Co-sponsored by the Inter¬
national Atomic Energy Agency,
Unesco and the Central Committee for
Swedish Technical Assistance, it is
open to foreign students, mainly from
developing countries, who will be able
to take part in experimental research
work in one of the various fields of
physics. They will also learn about
methods of organizing research pro¬
jects, physical laboratories and teaching
of graduate and undergraduate stu¬
dents. Applications for attending the
1961-62 course (Sept 1 - July 1) should
be sent to International Seminar, Ins¬
titute of Physics, University of Uppsala,
Sweden, and should arrive not later
than April 15, 1961.
JLeTTERS ABROAD: To further
international understanding through the
exchange of letters between people of
Asia, Europe, Africa and Latin America
with the people of the United States is
the aim of Letters Abroad, Inc., a clearing
house for International Correspondence.
The only U.S. organization which spe¬
cializes in serving adults. Letters Abroad
is now particularly seeking to contact
Americans in the 18-25 age group to
meet the large number of requests it
receives from young people in other lands,
and also to hear from older men and
women (aged over 25) in other countries.
Correspondence is in English and prospec¬
tive correspondents should write to Letters
Abroad Inc., 45 East 65th St., New York
21, N.Y., U.S.A.
KEEPING LITERATES LITE¬
RATE '.The literacy rate in Ceylon
68 per cent in 1953 -is one of the
highest in Asia, but a literate population
does not necessarily mean a large read¬
ing public. To keep literate people
literate is one of the aims of the Na¬
tional Book Trust of Ceylon, set up
just over a year ago as part of the
Academy of Letters in Colombo, with
Unesco's assistance. In addition to
providing reading materials for new
literates, its aim is also to encourage
the reading habit among people in gene¬
ral. It has organized art festivals,
exhibitions of books and public lectures
and it now intends to make a six-month
survey on the reading interests of out-
of-school readers, results of which will
guide authors, publishers, librarians and
booksellers in the production and dis¬
tribution of suitable reading materials.
l^HILD WELFARE IN ISRAEL: An
Afro-Asian Seminar on Social Services for
Children is being organized in Israel this
year by the International Union for Child
Welfare, 1, rue de Varembé, Geneva
(Switzerland). Israel was chosen as the
setting for this 3 -months' seminar, which
begins on March 15, because of its
remarkable community development pro¬
gramme. Here, those taking part in the
seminar will have plenty of opportunities
to observe and join in the work being
done with children in the field.
A BOOST FOR M.E. SCIENCE:
Middle Eastern countries have been
urged to set up central science councils
and to devote at least 1 per cent of
their national incomes to scientific
research, by a regional conference held
recently in Cairo under the sponsorship
of Unesco and the Science Council of
the United Arab Republic. Delegates,
who represented eight countries, also
suggested that Middle East lands
should establish national scientific
documentation centres.
&EA LIFE IN PARIS: Exotic sea
.creatures from all over the world are on
view at the Museum of the Sea, which
opened its doors recently in Paris. Among
the 1,000 specimens in the Museum's
collection are octopus, spiny dog-fish,
Chinese paradise fish, neon fish from
Brazil and Indian Danios.
u
2
<
a.
z
<
a
O
LU
O
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
CONTENTS OF THE UNESCO COURIER 1960
January
ANTON CHEKHOV. The life and work of Anton Chekhov Pata¬
gonia, paradox of desolation and prosperity The story of modern elec¬
tronic computers A library comes to a Greek village Laboratory
for desert living.
February
SAVE THE TREASURES OF NUBIA. UNESCO launches world
appeal The drama of Nubia The legacy of Nubia The temples of
Rameses II at Abu Simbel The saga of the discovery of Abu Simbel
Colour map of the Nile valley The marriage of Rameses II carved
In stone Philae, the sacred isle Graeco-Roman Nubia Cairo Docu¬
mentation Centre on Ancient Egypt The modern pyramid of Aswan
Sudanese Nubia, "Terra incognita" of archaeologists.
March
MAGIC ART OF CZECH GLASS. The Sound Hunters, a new
international family A baby chick is born No schools for one child
in two The purpose of tears, yawns and laughter Unesco Co\our
Art Slides The life and works of Sholem Aleichem World's farming
census begins.
April
WORLD MOBILIZATION AGAINST MALARIA. 1,000 million
lives in danger Was ancient Greece vanquished by malaria i New
drugs join battle The conquest of space The story of place
names Nature's oldest-living creatures.
May
BUDDHIST PAINTINGS OF ANCIENT JAPAN. UNESCO's
Nubian campaign is launched Appeal by Director-General of Unesco
Aklavik, the moving of a city 1,000 schools for Poland's 1,000th
birthday.
June
NEW PATHWAYS FOR THE BLIND. When is a person considered VELAZQUEZ. Special colour Issue.
blind ? Four-fifth's of world's sightless In rural areas The unifica¬
tion of Braille Stamps for the blind Psychology and behaviour of the
blind The blind In the U.S.S.R. Do's and Don'ts for the sighted.
July - August
THE OCEAN'S SECRETS. Laboratory of the universe Stations In
the sea Ringside view of underwater life Taking the sea's pulse
Green pastures of tomorrow Giant vacuum cleaners to mine the sea
floor Unesco vessel to sail the seas Expedition to the Indian Ocean
Exploring the world's deepest trenches The wreck of the Wasa
From acqualung to bathyscaph Ballet of the Ophurlans Danger!
500 mph tidal wave approaching The wave mystery of D-Day 1944
From tropical waters to Islands of ice Weather and the seas
Wanted: better oceangoing research ships Neptune's tiny |ewels
Fish, the great food potential Atoms overboard !
September
BOUBA AND JACQUES. Pitoa, pilot school In a Cameroon village
France builds world's first "ecotron" Ricefields reaching up to the
sky Fine arts on postage stamps A century of "black gold " Air¬
plane and spade uncover treasures of the Sudan.
October
RACISM. The social cancer of our time Race, prejudice and educa¬
tion A look at modern anti-semltlsm Mein Kampf The racial
landscape of Latin America X-ray of the racist mind Race preju¬
dice in India The cinema says no ! to racism.
November
A NEW MAGNA CARTA FOR CHILDREN. 3 Rs for 130 million
Asian children 15 nations plan a school revolution The mentally
handicapped Unicef greeting cards Jane Addams, crusader for peace
and youth Masterpieces of an ancient treasure trove.
December
Where to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write
direct to the National Distributor
in your country. (See list below ;
! names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.)
Payment is made in the national
currency ; rates quoted are for an
annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Press
Department Royal Afghan Ministry of
Education, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 369 Lonsdale Street, Melbourne,
C I, Victoria. (A. 15/-).
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C°., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V (Sch.
50.-)
BELGIUM. For The Unesco Courier:
I Louis de Lannoy, 22, Place De Brouckère,
Brussels, CCP. 338.000. (fr. b. 100.)
Other publications: Office de Publicité,
16, rueMarcq, Bruxelles, CCP. 285.98;
N.V. Standaard-Boekhandel, Belgiëlei 15 1,
Antwerp.
BURMA. Burma Translation Society
529-531 Merchant Street, Rangoon.
CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa
Ont. ($ 3.00).
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd, Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 24-4, Co¬
lombo, 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co, Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
I Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Librería Económica, Pte Zayas
505-7, Aparcado 113, Havana.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia Ltd., 30
Ve Smeckich, Prague 2.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6 Nörregade, Copenhagen K. (D.kr. 12).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agen¬
cy, P.O. Box 120. Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (F.mk. 540).
FRANCE. Unesco Bookshop, Place de
Fontenoy. Paris, T. CCP. 12598-48.
(7 NF.).
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb fur Deutschland, Rosen¬
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8. (DM. 8).
GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28,
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Kultura, P.O. Box 149.
Budapest, 62.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; Gunfoundry Road, Hyde¬
rabad, I; 3 6a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House. 24/1 Asaf Ali Road, P.O.
Box 386, New Delhi, I ; Sub-Depots:
Oxford Book & Stationery Co., I 7 Park
Street Calcutta 1 6, Scindia House,
New Delhi. (Rs. 6.70).
INDONESIA. Bappit Pusat "Permata",
Dialan Nusantara 22, Djakarta.
IRAQ. -- Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The National Press, 2. Wel¬
lington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
35, Allenby Road and 48, Nahlat Benja¬
min Street. Tel-Aviv (l£ 4.-).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 9 I
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services. Spaldings.( I 0/-)
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central. Tokyo. (Yen 500).
JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road, P.O.B. 66,
Amman.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul.
LIBERIA. ). Momolu Kamari, 69, Front
and Gurley Streets, Monrovia.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück,
33, Grand-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications
Ltd., Times House, River Valley Rd.,
Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta. (10/-).
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd.
30, .Bourbon Street, Port-Louis.
MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid des
Moulins. Monte-Carlo. (7 NF).
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl 6)
NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES.
G. CT. Van Dorp & C- (Ned Ant.) N.V.
Willemstad, Curacao.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackchorne Road, Chrut-
church. (10/-).
NIGERIA. CM.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos. (10/-).
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille Gren-
sen,7, Oslo. (N. kr. 13.20).
PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing
Co, Ltd., Unesco Publications House,
P.O. Box 374. 56-N Gulberg Industrial
Colony, Lahore.
PANAMA. Cultural Panameña, Avenida
7a, No. TI-49, Apartado de Correos 2018,
Panama, D.F. (Balboas 3.-).
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo, P.O. Box
620. Manila.
POLAND. "RUCH" ul. Wiloia Nr. 46.
Wariaw. 10 (Zl. 50).
PORTUGAL Dias & Andridi Lda,
Livraria Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70,
Lisbon.
RHODESIA & NYASALAND. The
Book Centre, First Street, Salisbury,
Southern-Rhodeiia.
SWEDEN. For The Unesco Courier: Sven-
ska Unescoradet, Vaiagatan I S- 1 7, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 7.50); other" publications
A/B CE. Friiezes, Kungl. Hovbokhandel,
Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Ramistraste, Zurich.
Payot, 40, ru du March*, Geneva. CCP.
1-236.
"Courier" only: Georges Losmaz, I, rue
des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CCP.
1-481 I (Fr. S. 8).
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Maniion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Itli-
klal Caddesi. Beyoglu, Istanbul.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church'
Street, Pretoria. (10/-).
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT).
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Patha,
Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 5 69, London, S.E.I.( I 0/-).
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22. N.Y. ($ 3.00.) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York. 27, N.Y.
U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja
Moscow. G-200.
Knigs,
YUGOSLAVIA. |ugosloventka Knjlga,
Terazije 27/11. Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
.' '
NEW HORIZONS IN VIEW
The veiled Moslem women of Asia
are becoming more and more a
rare sight. How they are discov¬
ering new horizons in the twen¬
tieth century is told on page 1 8 by
a Pakistani woman who writes on
their past, their present and their
future in Pakistan and Indonesia.
Unesco
_ : J
]]>
</page>
</document>
