<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="063847eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
m MIIIM
MAY 1961 (14TH YEAR) - PRICE : 1 -STG. (U.K.) - 30 CENTS (U.S.) 0,70 NF (FRANCE)
ANDRÉ MAUROIS SPEAKS OF BOOKS
AND OF LIBRARIES
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
STUDY OF HANDS
How much effort and how many
motions are made in getting out of a
car ? Strobophotography captures each
of these successive movements which
the eye does not see. Here in a nega¬
tive, the positions of the hands are
easily distinguishable. For a positive
of this picture see "Strobophotography:
What the Eye Cannot See", page 28.
Photo © André J. Salesse-Lavergne, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier
MAY 1961
14TH YEAR
Contents
No. 5
PUBLISHED IN
EIGHT EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
American
Japanese
COVER PHOTO
"Books can take us out of
ourselves... Books are our
gateways into other minds
and other peoples... Books
are the only way in which
we can learn about past ages,
and are the best key to an
understanding of other social
groups." André Maurois
Speaks of Books, see page 4.
Photo © Steven Trefonides
Page
4 ANDRÉ MAUROIS SPEAKS OF BOOKS AND LIBRARIES
The role of the public library in the world today
14 WORLD PROFILE OF LEISURE AND LEARNING
Samplings from the Unesco survey on education
culture and mass communications
15 BANKS FOR EYESIGHT
Legacy of sight for the sightless
By David Gunston
18 BLOOD VESSELS IN BOTTLES
Modern science's latest donor bank
20 MICROPHOTOGRAPHY REVEALS THE INVISIBLE WORLD
A whole universe of great beauty lies at the bottom of a microscope
By Daniel Behrman
28 STROBOPHOTOGRAPHY: WHAT OUR EYES DO NOT SEE
The strobo-camera captures the world in motion
By André Salesse-Lavergne
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
(M C 61. 1. 158 A)
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7', France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
Gordon Behrens
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Célia Bertin
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey
Russian Edition : Venlamln Matchavariani (Moscow;
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Amin Chaker (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in July and August when,
it is bi-monthly ( I I issues a year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German
Arabic and Japanese. In the United Kingdom it is distributed by H. Ma
Stationery Office, P. O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Uneaco Courier ¡a indexed monthly in The Readers' Guide to
Periodical Literature published by H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates: U. S. S 3.00; IO/-stg. ; 7.00
New Francs or equivalent. Single copies l/-stg. 30
cents (U.S.) ; 0.70 New Francs.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
ANDRÉ MAUROIS SPEAKS
AND OF LIBRARI
h
c
o
>
Ol
55
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
BY
ANDRÉ
MAUROIS
of the French
Academy
Our civilization is the sum of the knowledge and
memories accumulated by the generations that
have gone before us. Wc can only partake of
it if we are able to make contact with ideas of
these past generations. The only way to do
this and so become a "cultured" personis by reading.
Nothing can take the place of readingno lecture or
image on a screen has the same power to enlighten.
Pictures are a most valuable means of illustrating a
written text, but they hardly enable us to form general
ideas. Films, like the spoken word, flow by and arc lost
to us. Books abide, as life-long companions.
Montaigne confessed to needing three kinds of
communionlove, friendship and books. All three are
much the same. One can love books they are always
faithful friends. I would even say that I have often
found them wittier and wiser than those who wrote them.
A writer puts the best that is in him into his books. Ills
conversation may sparkle, yet it does not endure. But
one has never finished wrestling with the mysteries of a
book.
can be shared, without
all over the world. Writers
Cervantes, Goethe, Dante
bond between people who
Japanese, a Russian or an
to me, but he and I have
War and Peace, Fabrice in
Mlcawber in David Coppcr-
Moreover, this friendship
jealousy, by millions of people
like Balzac, Dickens, Tolstoy
or Melville are a wonderful
appear to be poles apart. A
American may be a stranger
mutual friends Natasha in
La Chartreuse de Parme and
field.
Books can take us out of ourselves. None of us has
had enough personal experience to know other people
or, indeed, himselfthoroughly. Wc all feel lonely In this
vast, irresponsive world. We suffer because of it; we are
shocked by the injustice of the world and the hardships
of life. But from books we learn that others greater
men than we have suffered and have sought as wc have.
Books are our gateways into other minds and other
peoples. Through them we can escape from the narrow
little world we live in and from fruitless brooding over
our own selves. An evening spent reading great books
does for our mind what a holiday in the mountains does
for our bodies. We come down from those lofty heights
stronger, our lungs and our mind cleansed of all im¬
purities, and we are better equipped to face with courage
the battles on the plains of daily life.
Books are the only way in which we can learn about
past ages, and are the best key to an understanding of
social groups that we never frequent. The plays of
Federico Garcia Lorca can teach me more about the soul
of Spain than twenty trips to the country as a tourist.
Chekhov and Tolstoy have revealed to me some aspects
of the Russian soul which are still true today. Saint-
Simon's Mémoires have made a France long dead live-
again for me, just as Hawthorne's or Mark Twain's novels
have helped me to visualize an America that has vanished.
And my delight is all the greater because of the amazing
likeness between these worlds, so remote from us in time
and space, and the world we live in.
Human beings all have a great deal in common. The
passions that move Homer's kings are not unlike those
felt by generals in a modern alliance. When I was lectur¬
ing on Marcel Proust to students at Kansas City, those
Middle West farmers' sons saw their own likeness in the
French characters. "There is, after all, but one race
the human race." Even the great differ from us not in
essence but In degree, and that is why the lives of great
men are of such interest to us all.
Thus, one reason why we read is to get beyond our own
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
SWEDEN'S GARDEN-GIRDED MODERN LIBRARIES
Stt
.t-**» m
A few years ago the people of Vasteras, Sweden,
built a modern library in the heart of their small
city. Plans were drawn up to construct the building
near the town's school with gardens surrounding
it and a view of the city's historic cathedral. The
	 very modern building and interior shown here are«g
like many constructed throughout the Scandinavian* "<r
countries. Sweden, for example, with a pcjfí
of less than eight million, has 3 000 public frl
housing more than 13 and one-half million^
4> ,' i
ANDRE' MAUROIS
SPEAKS OF
BOOKS
AND LIBRARIES «~*
lives and understand those of others. But this is not the
only reason for the pleasure we derive from books. In
everyday life we are too involved in what is happening to
see events clearly, too much under the sway of our emo¬
tions to savour them properly. The lives of many of us
would make a novel worthy of Dickens or Balzac, but we
get no pleasure from the experience quite the contrary.
The writer's task is to give us a faithful picture of life,
but to keep it far enough away for us to be able to
appreciate it without fear or entanglement.
A person reading a great novel or biography lives a
great adventure without disturbance to his peace of mind.
In the words of Santayana, art brings before our eyes
what we cannot find in action the union of life and
peace. To read history is good for our health of mind; it
teaches us moderation and tolerance, and shows us that
the terrible disputes over which civil wars or world wars
were once fought are now mere wrangles, dead and
buried. And that is a lesson in wisdom and in the
relativity of values. A great book never leaves the reader
the same as he was before he Is always a better man for
having read it.
Nothing, then, is more important for mankind than to
bring within the reach of all, these means of broadening
our horizons, escaping from ourselves and making
discoveries which literally transform Ufe and make the
individual a more valuable member of society. And the
only way to do this is through pubUc libraries.
We are living in an age in which, in an increasing
number of countries, all people have equal rights, share
in the work of government and shape pubUc opinion,
which, by its influence on governments, determines in the
last resort the choice of peace or war, justice or injustice
in short, the life of the nation and the world as a whole.
This power of the people, which is democracy, demands
that .the masses, who have become the source of authority,
should be well informed on aU important problems. I
agree that, ever more and more, they are receiving this
instruction in the schools, but the work of the schools
cannot be complete without libraries to back it.
Listening even to the best of teachers will not of itself
produce a trained mind the pupil must think and reflect.
The teacher's task is to provide a sound framework which
must then be filled in by the pupil himself essentially,
by reading. No pupil, no student, however brilliant, can
hope to do all over again by himself what mankind has
taken thousands of years to evolve. All worth-while
ref.ection is, above all, reflection on the ideas of great
writers. History would be of little value if it were
reduced to facts and ideas which can be explained in a
few hours by a school-teacher. But if the student, under
the teacher's guidance, searches among memoirs,
witnesses' accounts and statistics to find the fabric of
history itself, then he will learn a great deal about Ufe.
Reading is more than invigorating mental exercise; it
makes young people realize that truth lies hidden, that it
never yields itself ready-made to those who search for
it but must be pieced together by them by dint of labour,
methodical work and sincerity. The library is an
essential companion to school and universiy. / would go
so far as to say that education is but a key to open the
doors of libraries.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Plan and photos from the book "Landsbiblioteket Vasteras."
This is even more true of adult education. The citizen
of a democracy who wishes to fulfil his duties conscien¬
tiously must go on learning all his life. The world does
not stand still the day we leave our class-room.
History marches steadily on, posing problems in which
the fate of the human race is at stake. How are we to
make up our minds, how are we to uphold what is
reasonable and oppose what is criminal folly, if we do not
know what it is all about?
What is true of history is also true of political economy
and of all branches of science and technology. In fifty
years, man's knowledge has been revolutionized. Who will
explain these changes to the men and women whose
lives and happiness depend on them? Who will help
them to keep abreast of the latest discoveries, and yet
perform their daily task? Books, and books alone.
The public library must give children, young people,
men and women the opportunity to keep in touch with
their, times, in every sphere. By offering them, im¬
partially, works representing conflicting points of view, it
enables them to. form their own opinions and preserve
that attitude of constructive criticism towards public
affairs without which there is no freedom. The library,
too, may reveal to them their true vocation. Through
reading the works of the masters, gifted minds still un¬
certain of the path they should take will find themselves
drawn towards science, Uterature or the arts and in turn
will make their contribution to the common heritage of
mankind.
Finally, and above all, a well-chosen library open to
all will enrich the inner lives of its readers. Now that the
machine, partly replacing man, has given him more
leisure, this leisure must be used to the best advantage
both of individuals and of society. Games, sport and
travel will help, no doubt, but nothing will do as much
as reading to produce well-furnished minds with a broad
human outlook.
Just as scientific and historical works train men's minds,
so, too, will novels and plays develop their sympathies.
A reader who knows the great writers of a country well
is no longer a stranger there, even if he has never visited
the country and does not speak its language. Every
library is a centre for international understanding. By
its very existence, free from propaganda and prejudice
and with no axe of its own to grind, the public library
serves peace as well as democracy.
A modern public library is therefore an active, dynamic
institution. It goes half-way to meet the reader, anxious
to know his needs and meet them, and to attract him by
offering various ways and means of obtaining informa¬
tion, cultivating his mind and finding relaxation. The
library's collections must be suited to this purpose. Re¬
ference works dictionaries, encyclopaedias, bibliographies,
atlases and chronologies must be there for all to consult.
The historical section should contain both general works
(world history, history of the principal countries, par¬
ticularly that of the library's home country, the history
of the arts, literature and science) and also monographs
on local history. The biography shelves will always
attract readers. Books on geography, travel and science
and technical works are also essential.
As for the classics, only those should be chosen which
still have their faithful band of readers. Great poets
are few and it is quite easy to make a coUectlon of their
works. Novels and plays are the biggest problem. The
abundance ls such that some omissions, however unfair,
are unavoidable. The main thing ls that the library
should possess the works of the great writers of all
countries.
But the collections must also include technical and
professional works and textbooks on various trades and
crafts, especially those practised in the district where the
library is situated. The library must cater for the needs
of its readers and reflect the local economic structure.
There should be free access to the shelves. Card cata¬
logues must be available to guide the reader to the book
he wants and to show him, by the classification system,
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
ANDRÉ MAUROIS (Cont'd)
THE INALIENABLE RIGHT TO READ
what publications the library has on the subject in which
he ls interested.
A modern public library's programme also includes
various cultural and educational activities talks, debates
on literary, artistic or social questions, exhibitions,
theatrical or cinematographic performances and concerts.
In various ways these activities lead people towards books
and stimulate the craving to read.
Thus a public library is a real centre of culture, pro¬
pagating human knowledge and dispensing delight. It is
a channel for the spread of Ideas and provides the
members of the community with a means of making
Intelligent use of their leisure. Its influence is not con¬
fined to its Immediate neighbourhood but reaches the
people in country districts, who have long been very
poorly served. Some villages may have a school library,
but it does not always lend books to adults. Besides, its
stock of books is very small, and an inquiring mind soon
exhausts its resources. Some countries have an excellent
public library network. In other places, similar schemes of
great interest and promise for the future have been tried.
Regional libraries have been established in the chief
town of a province or district and these supply mobile
libraries which take books to rural communities.
In each of these communities, some centre the mu¬
nicipal library, a school Ubrary, or the town hall is
chosen to serve as a deposit station and someone
(usually the teacher) is put in charge, to give readers
advice and, if possible, encourage people to read. The
director of the central library trains these local librarians
and they in their turn train the readers. In country
districts the public library is a co-operative venture.
This is one system; there are others, but wherever there
is a public scheme for reading in country districts this
system has met with immense success among the inhabi¬
tants. It is of the utmost importance that it should be
organized throughout the world. It is not a luxury not
just a way for country people to spend their leisure
although that in itself is valuable enough; it Is essential,
because it is only through books and reading that civiliza¬
tion can be spread.
HP
here is truth in the saying that today the right
H to read is one of man's inalienable rights. All
JL men and women must have free access to books.
Books, if they are given the chance, will transform
human beings, by making them the heirs to the
accumulated experience of past generations.
It is in early life that a taste for books and the habit
of reading are most easily acquired. A public library
must have a "children's corner." Most children have not
enough money to buy books, nor have their parents
enough money to give them books. Only in a library
will they find good books, which will save them from
reading mediocre or dangerous ones. Although the
school library is useful, it is often inadequate, owing to
lack of funds. To an intelligent chUd, shelves full of
books among which he is free to browse open up a
veritable paradise.
But it is at home, in the evening, or in a garden
during the summer days, that a child will enjoy most of
all a long and delightful read. A bright child with a
thirst for knowledge is a voracious reader. He will come
to the library to work and do his homework, because he
will find the library an intellectual centre, where he can
listen to stories, or take part in play reading, and later
on in group debates.
This children's corner should not be too big. It is
important for the librarian to get to know each of the
children who come there, from the recluse who likes to
be left to himself to the hesitating child who needs
guidance. The setting should be bright and colourful, so
that the idea of books may be associated in the child's
mind with a feeling of well-being. One cannot fail to
be impressed by the good behaviour of young readers.
Reading teaches them consideration for others.
The library will of course co-operate with the teachers
of the local schools and with the children's parents.
When a teacher is studying a particular subject with his
pupils, he may ask for a smaU exhibition on the subject
to be organized by the library. He may suggest that the
library purchase books which would be useful to his class.
Mothers who accompany their youngest children to the
library may find themselves acquiring a taste for reading.
The children's library should not serve too narrow a
purpose. It should lead on to the adults' library. For a
librarian who loves his work, there is nothing more in¬
teresting than watching a child grow into an adolescent.
There comes a day when children's books cease to interest
the young reader and one senses that he is ripe for the
great writers. This is the moment to guide him towards
the general library and advise him on books he should
choose to begin with. If he likes, a children's librarian
can be second to none as an awakener of young minds.
he librarian plays a tremendous part in community
H life. He has the culture of mankind in his
JL keeping and serves as an intermediary between
the products of that culture, accumulated throughout
the ages, and the people who are alive and working today.
There are so many books, and they are turned out so
fast that nobody can even know which ones he ought to
read, let alone read them all. The specialist runs the
risk of wasting his whole life uselessly doing again the
work that has already been done by someone else. Like
a planter who has sown too prolific a species and is stifled
by the very crop he has raised, the reader without
guidance is likely to be swamped by the vastness of man's
culture.
The librarian can and should protect him. A good
bibliography and a detailed catalogue can guide people
through the jungle of man's accumulated knowledge. The
year's crop of books, gigantic though it is, is at once
digested and assimilated by Ubraries. Since the number
of books makes it increasingly difficult to find what one
is seeking, it is essential that the classification system
should be constantly improved. It is the task of the
great libraries and therefore of their librarians to
blaze wide trails through this forest, which otherwise
would soon become impenetrable. It is their duty, too,
to see that everything the human mind has produced is
preserved.
Even in a small public library, the work of the librarian
is of no less importance. In a mass civilization such as
ours, no moral or technical progress can be regarded as
truly achieved unless it reaches all levels of the popula¬
tion. The librarian who does his work well helps to
bring this about. It has been said that he acts like a
filter between the flood of books and the people's thirst
for knowledge. This means that he must not only know
his job but also possess a sound general culture.
XT
^^ü^H e will need this, too, when building up his
H H library. Admittedly when he takes up his post,
.^L. -^L. he will inherit a stock of books from his pre¬
decessors. It is important, however, that he should both
use his funds to the best advantage every year in order
to add to this stock the best new books that have appeared
and, even as far as older works are concerned, should fill
up the gaps in his Ubrary in the Ught of his own
experience and public demand.
In every library, the Ubrarian acts as an adviser. He
guides people in their reading, and shows them how to
consult the card-index and use the collections. In fact,
apart from professional qualifications, the job of being a
CONT'D ON PAGE I 0
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
USIS
MORE THAN LENDING BOOKS
Modern libraries throughout the world provide many services besides
the traditional lending of books. One of the world's most modern
libraries in Louisville, Kentucky, U.S.A., houses two FM radio stations
with a complete control room for the wire network (above). The
two stations broadcast twelve hours a day, seven days a week, all year
round. A library card at this library entitles you not only to borrow
books, but also films, records, paintings, and even an umbrella on
rainy days. Many public libraries like the one below at Medcllin, Colom¬
bia, sponsor regular art shows. Another rapidly growing service of
public libraries Is microfilm viewers which permit visitors to study
books, documents and newspapers on film not available In the original.
The battery of viewers at left is In the Royal Library, Stockholm.
UNCOCO
UNESCO
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
STORY TIME
Latecomers take a short-cut through the fence..
* ***** *?~ *r
tüSíf.' .:' s
to the tree-shaded park where the story hour is about to begin.,
ANDRÉ MAUROIS (Cont'd;
PILOT LIBRARIES
PUT INTO PRACTICE
UNESCO AIMS
librarian calls for a real passion for this noble ministry,
an unbounded passion, unfailing good will and a keen
desire to help those who are searching for knowledge.
In Unesco's educational work, considerable emphasis
has of course been placed on libraries. All its efforts
to eliminate illiteracy would be in vain unless reading
matter could be made available to those who have
acquired the ability to enjoy it. Unesco's main task is to
work for peace through international culture. In this,
the public library is its natural assistant.
Accordingly, Unesco has contributed to the develop¬
ment of Ubraries, by organizing meetings of librarians
from the different regions of the world, Improving the
system of exchanges and working methods, sending
experts on mission, awarding fellowships and most im¬
portant of all by setting up model libraries to be a
driving force in the service of the community.
The most effective preaching is by example. Unesco
was the first to put into practice the advice it has given
to countries and cities. It set up pilot libraries, to act
both as models and testing grounds, and they have met
with great success. The first pilot Ubrary was established
at Delhi (India). It was founded In 1950 by the Govern¬
ment of India and Unesco, and Inaugurated by Mr. Nehru
In 1951, Its principal object being to provide reading
matter for new literates, in four languages Hindi, Urdu,
Punjabi and English.
There ls a travelUng library, which serves fifteen
neighbouring districts, in town and country. The stock
of books has been rapidly enlarged, and now numbers
about 165,000 volumes. About 750,000 books are borrowed
every year. Analysis of the readers' age groups shows
that the majority are young people old people read little,
or not at all.
The obvious explanation for this is that education has
only recently made any progress in that area. Many of
the reader members had not a single book, and no means
of obtaining any, until the library was set up. Because
of the customs of the country, few women came to the
library, but in many cases the men explain that the
books they borrow are for their family, and that they
are often read aloud. Apart from fiction, the favourite
reading is the lives of famous men and women, handbooks
on arts and crafts, and the history of India.
The Delhi pilot experiment has shown that there is a
great interest in reading. India's needs are many and
varied, but reading is one of the most urgent. It is
especially important that the needs of the new reading
public should be met, by producing reading matter in
all the principal languages of the country. A survey of
readers' tastes and interests recently conducted by Delhi
librarians provided valuable information on that subject.
Unesco has also estabUshed a pilot Ubrary at Colombia's
beautiful university city of Medellin. It was opened in
October 1954, and now houses nearly 50,000 volumes. The
central library, branch Ubraries and bookmobile centres
together serve nearly a thousand readers every day.
Here, too, there has been convincing evidence of the
efficacy of Ubraries as a driving force in popular educa¬
tion. As in Delhi, young people have been most eager
to avail themselves of the new faciUty. Almost as many
books have been borrowed by children as by adults. And
the "children's corner" is as lively as can be. A book¬
mobile serves not only villages but factories as well. The
central library has become a cultural centre for the
whole town, providing a full and varied programme of
cultural activities.
A similar scheme was launched by Unesco at Enugu,
in East Nigeria. This third experiment has proved just
as successful as the first two. The Ubrary, which was
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
IN BROOKLYN
In New York's punishing summer
heat with apartments so stifling
that even TV is out of the question,
the youngsters take to the parks.
There the public libraries provide
a summer programme of reading and
games. In the borough of Brook¬
lyn, the public library, along with
eleven of Its branches, holds out¬
door story hours every week. The
ancient magic of the storyteller is
still as fresh and appealing to the
present generation as it has been
for children throughout all the ages.
Photos © Bernard M. Jaffe
and on the outskirts a timid child listens attentively.
opened not more than a year ago, has a stock of nearly
20,000 volumes," and serves about 6,000 readers. Here, too,
a programme of educational activities supplements the
work of the reading-room, and the bookmobile serves
neighbouring districts. A book-box service, by rail, road
or canoe will shortly bring books to isolated readers and
to the inhabitants of out-of-the-way areas.
The aims of Unesco and those of public libraries coin¬
cide, they are: to help the various peoples to know each
other better; to give a new stimulus to popular educa¬
tion; to promote the ideal of equal opportunities for
everyone to share in cultural life; to preserve and pro¬
tect the immense legacy of books bequeathed by man to
man; and to give all nations of the world access to the
books published by every 'other nation. This common
ideal is the best guarantee that there will be ever closer
co-operation between Unesco and Ubraries.
Public libraries already play a very important part in
the Ufe of modern communities, a part which, for seve¬
ral reasons, will certainly become still greater in the
coming decades.
The number of people who can read is increasing every
year, and will continue to do so. The campaign to elimi¬
nate illiteracy is being vigorously carried out throughout
the world. It is certainly needed. More and more, people
who cannot read feel like outsiders in their own times.
Education is not the exclusive privilege of any one
class it has become compulsory for all. As a result,
hosts of readers are springing up everywhere. It is to
meet their needs that so many pocket books, cheap edi¬
tions and popular classics are being issued. These series
are extremely popular everywhere which shows that they
are meeting a need.
It is gratifying to note that the standard of the books
selected is steadily improving. New readers want books
of real spiritual, educational and Uterary value. The
vast majority of mankind, however, has not the where¬
withal to buy even cheap editions. For the masses, the
only way to get books to read is to go to the public
Ubrary. It should be compulsory for every village to have
its own public library, just as it is now compulsory for
it to have a school, of which the pubUc Ubrary is the
complement.
Economic and technical progress intensifies the need
for education. It does so in two ways. In the first place,
it enables people to look beyond their day-to-day needs.
A poor wretch who does not know where his next meal
is coming from and who has no shelter from the cold
and wet has no desire to improve his mind. The higher
the standard of living, the more concerned people will
be with their dignity as human beings, and the greater
will be their demand for the means of educating them¬
selves.
Moreover, as machines and techniques become more
and more complicated, a skilled worker has to be educated
in order to do his work satisfactorily. The machine is
replacing the labourer, who worked with his hands
alone; the workman ls becoming a technician who uses
his brain. And so we see young workmen flocking to
bookshops as well as to libraries in their eagerness to
learn. Even agriculture, now become a science, demands
of the farmer a proficiency that he can only acquire
through books. The need for learning begets a need for
reading.
Many countries are suddenly achieving self-determina¬
tion the right to self-government. This right ls a just
one, if it is accompanied by adequate knowledge not only
of their own past, their traditions, racial and historical
peculiarities, their products and consequently their eco¬
nomic future, but also of other countries, their history,
their place in the world, their characteristics in short,
everything that is needed for the maintenance of sen¬
sible and proper relations with them.
A new State, which is beginning its life as an indepen¬
dent nation, must have a sense of national Identity. In
many cases, however, the new citizens, who formerly
lived without any strong bond between them and formed
part of a different political system, cannot have that true,
deep sense of national Identity which comes from a
knowledge of the past and an understanding of the pre¬
sent. Where can they get this knowledge? They will
find it in books in which the scattered traditions have
been brought together. A library is not only a valuable
instrument for the nation's use it helps to shape the
nation itself.
Civilization creates new needs. Man today Is no longer
CONT'D ON PAGE I 3
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
\\ Il I Y \ 1
UNESCO now has three pilot libraries in opera¬
tion, one at New Delhi, India, another at Medellin,
Colombia, and the most recent at Enugu, Nigeria.
In addition, UNESCO experts have helped to
establish, expand, or reorganize libraries in a.
host of other countries. The pilot project at
New Delhi has helped to bring books within the
reach of thousands of people in outlying districts
thanks to the library's travelling book buses.
The two youngsters above pore over the shelves
in the book van as it makes its regular visit to
their village. The pilot library in Enugu, Nigeria
(below right) , has open shelves and an ever growing
number of volumes where readers may browse
at will. The Kochi Citizens Library in Japan
(below) is typical of more than 800 public librar¬
ies in Japan. Some smaller countries have more
libraries than Japan but few can boast the astound¬
ing figure of 20 million regular readers, who
probably make Japan's libraries the best attended
in the worjd. The people of the USSR are ardent
patrons of their libraries as this photo (right) of
the main reading room of the Leningrad public
library indicates. The USSR holds the world's
record in the number of their public libraries
with a total number of more than 130,000.
UNESCO PHOTOS
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
ANDRÉ MAUROIS (Cont'd;
content to be a pawn In the hands of powers greater than
himself. He wants, as far as possible, to know and to
learn. In the past, only a philosopher or a poet could
say, "I am a man, and nothing human is alien to me."
Today every man would like to be able to say this, because
he knows that the fate of far-off peoples who are stran¬
gers to him will affect his own and also because he has
become more sensitive, and is moved by an unjust deed
committed at the other end of the world. Libraries are
the most important arid the richest source of information
oti problems which concern mankind as a whole.
Lastly, through the abundant supply of energy and the
advances made In automation, our civilization, whether
we want it to or not, will become more and more a civi¬
lization of leisure. It cannot be anything but gratifying
to see how working hours are being shortened and man's
labour eased. Nevertheless, in the long run too much
leisure might become dangerous, unless tastes and in¬
terests are broadened at the same time.
Sports, games, public entertainments and television
will of course help to keep people occupied, but the length
of time for which they can do so will always be limited
by the large amount of preparation they require, and In
any case a man worthy of the name will fairly soon grow
weary of being a mere spectator. Libraries will provide
him with the means of creating for himself an unending
spectacle of space and time.
Aldous Huxley has said that "Every man who knows
how to read has it in his power to magnify himself, to
multiply the ways in which he exists, to make his life
full, significant and interesting." It is this full life,
enriched by the lives of others, that we would like all to
be able to enjoy. Other mass communication media the
cinema, television, radio and gramophone records will
take new forms, spread and help mankind to share the
delights of the arts. Yet none of them has so profound
and lasting an effect as reading, none of them brings
before us so wide a range of emotion and knowledge.
When he was opening the Eton Public Library In 1833,
Sir John Herschel said "...Give a man the taste of reading,
and the means of gratifying it, and you can hardly fail
of making a happy man... You place him in contact with
the best society in every period of history with the
wisest, the wittiest, with the tendcrest, the bravest, and
the purest characters who have adorned humanity. You
make him a denizen of all nations a contemporary of
all ages."
We might well say to any community: "Tell me what
you give your people to read, and I will tell you who
you are."
The text of this article by André Maurois has bcc7i
published in an attractive illustrated booklet entitled
"Public Libraries and their Mission." A limited number of
copies are available free to subscribers to "The Unesco
Courier". To obtain a copy, write to the Division of
Libraries, Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris (T).
AN IMPORTANT BULLETIN
ON LIBRARIES
A few months after the First Session of the UNESCO Gener¬
al Conference In April 1947, the first periodical was pub¬
lished by the newly organized association of states the
Unesco Bulletin for Libraries. The Bulletin began its career
primarily as a means of helping war-damaged libraries to
rebuild their collections by publishing Information on Insti¬
tutions throughout the world which had books and periodicals
for exchange. Now in its 14th year of publication, the
Bulletin still continues this important service, but has
gradually grown through the years in importance as an
international medium on all matters concerning libraries. The
Bulletin appears monthly in separate English, French, Russian
and Spanish editions. The annual subscription price is $3.50,
17s. 6d (stg), 10 NF or the equivalent In local currency.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
WORLD PROFILE
OF LEISURE
AND LEARNING
Britons read more newspapers
than anyone else on the face
of the earth, but Soviet citizens
have the largest number of public
library books at their disposal. No
one goes to the cinema as often as
an Austrian, even though Japan leads
the world in the number of full-
length films produced annually. The
United States has the most university
students, but the U.S.S.R. has the
most students studying engineering.
These are only a few of the nuggets
to be gleaned from 182 pages of
statistical ore contained in the
newest edition of "Basic Facts and
Figures" a Unesco annual publication
which, at first sight, is about as
attractive reading as a bank state¬
ment or a telephone directory.
But, despite this dense packing of
"international statistics relating to
education, culture and mass com¬
munication" into lists of countries
(no less than 219 countries and
territories are mentioned), columns of
figures and slabs of footnotes, a
profile of our world in its learning
and at its leisure can be drawn from
"Basic Facts and Figures."
/^k OME of the data are ím-
ir pressive (only 59 out of 1,000
Americans do not possess radios)
and some are rather startling (the
world's most fortunate schoolchil¬
dren, and perhaps the world's most
fortunate teachers at least in terms
of number of pupils per teacher
are to be found on St Pierre and
Miquelon, two French islands off the
coast of Canada, where there are
only twelve children per teacher).
Some of it is tragic, too, in the long
ranks of nations with only 16 or 17 or
25 per cent of their school-age
children actually afforded an oppor¬
tunity to go to school.
Let's turn to a few of the facets
of this statistical portrait (or better,
panorama) of the world, because no
one could hope to take in all of them
in one dose.
Thumbing through the pages of
"Basic Facts and Figures", you learn
that the United States leads the
world in the number of university
students, with 3,236,414, foUowed by
the U.S.S.R. with 2,260,000 (287,164
American students are listed as
studying engineering and the parallel
figure in the Soviet Union is 765,000).
Next come India with 833,450
students and Japan with 636,232.
France leads in Europe with 226,173
students, followed by the Federal
Republic of Germany and Italy in
a near dead-heat : 164,015 and
163,945 respectively.
One word of warning: there is
not much agreement through¬
out the world as to what constitutes
a "university student." As a famous
man is supposed to have said,
"There are lies, damned lies and
statistics."
But the figures do show the United
States also leads the world in the
annual number of university
graduates 438,023 followed by the
U.S.S.R. with 290,700 (the two leaders
change places in the figures for
scientific and technical graduates
114,600 in the U.S.S.R. and 96,509 in
the U.S.A.).
More foreign students 47,245, to
be exact study in the United States
than anywhere else. The next biggest
attraction is France with 17,456
foreign students followed by the
Federal Republic of Germany with
15,115.
Rather scanty figures on over-all
percentages of national income spent
in 1958 on education show Puerto
Rico in the lead with 6.9% and Fin¬
land second with 6,5%.
Now for a digest of what the world
does in its spare time: for the
Soviet citizen, there are 752,604,000
public library books, compared to
200,000,000 in the United States and
71,000,000 in the United Kingdom, the
two runners-up. The U.S.S.R. also
ranks first in the number of museum-
goers with 39,900,000 annually, com¬
pared to 10,994,000 in the United
Kingdom and 10,439,000 in Japan
(the three leaders according to
available figures).
Newspapers are another story.
Here are the readership rates per
1,000 in the world's most newspaper-
14
minded countries: United Kingdom,
573; Sweden, 464; Luxembourg, 429;
and Finland, 420. The United States
leads in the number of daily papers,
1,745, but sells them to only 327 out
of every 1,000 Americans. On the
other hand, 475 out of every 1,000
Americans read magazines of general
interest, the highest figure in the
world.
When the American buys a news¬
paper, he is offered an impressive
number of pages. That is why news¬
print consumption per capita in the
United States is 33.6 kilogrammes
(74 pounds), the world's highest
figure, followed by 27.2 kilogrammes
(60 lbs) in Australia and 25.5 Kg.
(56 lbs) in New Zealand.
Other countries appear when you
turn to the chapter of film attend¬
ance. Austrians are the most
avid cinema-goers: 17.4 per thousand.
Next come Malta with 17.3, New
Zealand with 16.7 and the U.S.S.R.
with 16.2. In North America, Green¬
land with 14.8 outstrips the United
States with 12.5.
Who makes the most pictures?
The answer is Japan, whose 516 full-
length films in 1958 rank it first over
India, 295; the United States, 288;
Hong Kong, 240; France, 126; and the
United Kingdom, 121.
Latest available figures (at the end
of 1959) for television-viewing show
that the country with the most sets
per thousand inhabitants is Monaco
(a staggering 524). Next are the
United States, 290; Canada, 196; the
United Kingdom, 195; and Bermuda,
182.
Again, leadership changes
hands when you turn to
books. First is the U.S.S.R.
with 69,072 new titles annuaUy,
followed by Japan, 24,152; the
United Kingdom, 20,690; the Federal
Republic of Germany, 16,552; the
United States, 14,876 and France,
12,032.
The Soviet Union also published the
most translations in 1958 a total of
4,457 in the various languages of the
Union followed by Germany (figures
are for the Federal and the Democra¬
tic Republics) with 2,512 and Czecho¬
slovakia with 1,462. English was the
world's most translated language that
year: 9,675 works out of a total of
29,209. Next were Russian, 4,320;
French, 4,010, and German, 2,951.
There is some eclectic reading, too,
to be found among the world's five
most translated authors in 1958.
They are Lenin, Shakespeare, Jule's
Verne, Tolstoy and Dostoevsky in
that order, with Gorky and Simenon
as runners-up. The world's most
translated single book, though, was
the Bible.
Basic Facts and Figures Unesco,
Paris. Price: §3; 15/-(stg.); 10,50 NF.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
BANKS
FOR
EYESIGHT
by
David Gu nsIon
T
person
o look into happiness through another man's
eyes" the phrase is Shakespeare's but today it
can literally be true. For through the perfecting
of corneal graft surgery, it is possible for a blind
to regain sight by having a small section of a
recently deceased person's eye implanted in his own.
This quite wonderful operation, the culmination of a
century and a half of experiment and research by workers
in many countries, translates into reality a dream as old
as man. It also gives to each and every one of us an
opportunity unique in human history: that of giving
sight to others. For through this operation, modern
medical science has made it possible for anyone to
bequeath this most precious gift to those who live after
us and who are either blind or are in grave danger of
becoming so.
No other generation has held so profound and precious
a legacy in its keeping yet the world-wide ignorance of
this subject is appalling. In some small way, it ls the
purpose of this article to disseminate the up-to-date facts
about corneal grafting and those unique organizations
set up to obtain, store and provide usable eyes the eye
banks of the world.
At the outset it must be made clear that the implanta¬
tion of another person's corneal tissue Is not a magical
cure-all for blindness. Many blind people have eye
defects that are not confined to the cornea, so unfortu¬
nately this modern miracle cannot help them.
The cornea of the human eye is the transparent surface
tissue of the eyeball, covering the iris and pupil. In
normal sight, light is admitted through this transparent
window. But if light cannot penetrate the central
section of the cornea because of its clouding over or
scarring, vision is impaired and may be completely lost.
Fortunately, however, the cornea is unique in that It
is the only transparent and, so far as we know at present,
the only truly transplantable tissue of the human body.
Even grafted skin must come from the patient's own
body. But corneal tissue from another person, if properly
implanted, will knit into the surrounding eye tissue, grow,
and eventually restore the patient's sight.
At present, between 60 per cent, and 90 per cent, of
cases can be sure of improvement In their vision, or
benefit by clearer or restored sight. Even if perfect
eyesight cannot be guaranteed owing to previous damage
to the eye by disease or injury, particularly burns, the
improvement the operation can give ensures a person's
independence of movement and activity.
The only Inescapable conditions this operation demands
are that the donated eye tissue must be healthy and sound,
and it must be removed within a few hours of death,
preserved if need be at a low temperature, and grafted
(Q Atlantic Press
within a limited period while the implanted corneal
tissue is still living.
It was the British scientific investigator Eras¬
mus Darwin who seems first to have felt that this daring
operation might succeed. Writing in the period 1794-1796
he suggested: "Could not a small piece of the cornea be
cut out with a kind of trephine about the size of a thick
bristle, or a small crowquill, and would it not heal with
a transparent scar?"
These early attempts were largely made with animal
eyes: tissues from rabbits, dogs, sheep, pigs, even a
gazelle, were Implanted in humans, but although the
graft "took", In each case the patients' corneas became
opaque, so no Improvement in vision resulted.
In the first half of the last century blindness due to
disease and corneal ulceration was rife and surgical
treatment became a highly desirable goal. But
initial work was disappointing and furthermore was
bedevilled by gross scepticism, both medical and lay, by
high risk of infection, lack of anaesthetics and imperfect
instruments and technique. Although a corneal transplant
was first performed by Frans Relsinger in 1818, and a
successful case achieved by Bigger in 1837, it was much
later, about 1878-1888, before the operation could be
accepted as being more than Just a wild experiment.
In 1879, Wolfe discovered from his own successes that
a freshly-removed human eye must be used, that the
graft Inserted must be highly accurately sectioned, and
that the surrounding in the treated eye must not be
damaged. In the same year, the French eye surgeon
Louis de Wecher, addressing his fellow surgeons, declared:
We have no right In these cases to refuse the slightest
aid to sufferers who have but this one remaining chance
to recover a little sight; neither should we be deterred
by the reproach of eccentricity which will certainly be
levelled at anyone who attempts to graft a cornea.
But the greatest pioneering figure in this work was the
German ophthalmologist Arthur von Hippel. From 1878
onwards he had done corneal grafting In both man and
animals, and in 1886-1837 publicly showed at Heidelberg
a patient on whom he had done a successful animal graft,
keeping accurate records of this case for two years.
In 1888 von Hippel achieved the first completely
successful corneal transplantation from one human eye
to another, though he continued to experiment with ani¬
mal tissue, chiefly from rabbits. Above all, he devised
an accurate clockwork trephine for cutting the graft
tissue before Insertion into the patient's cornea, and
under the growing Influence of Lister and Pasteur devised
CONT'D NEXT PAGE 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
BANKS FOR EYESIGHT (Cont'd)
THERE IS NO SUCH THING
AS A WORN-OUT EYE
surgical principles and technique that still govern this
operation today.
In 1905 a Moravian surgeon named Zlrm achieved fame
for skilfully saving the sight of a man blinded by a lime
splash by Implanting tissue from a young boy's eye that
had to be removed for medical reasons. He followed
the man's Improving vision over a long period. Since
then, the art of keratoplasty, as it is known scientifically,
has been greatly developed by the unstinting work of
eye specialists in many countries, notably Elschnlg and
Fuchs, in Germany; Morax, who used graft tissue from
a patient's other eye for the first time In 1912 ; Vladi¬
mir Filatov In Russia from 1922 onwards, who showed
the value of eyes removed from a corpse ; the French
surgeons Pauflque, Sourdllle and Offret; Castravieglo
and Paton in the U.S.A. since 1939; Franschetti, In
Switzerland ; and the British surgeons Tudor Thomas and
Sir Benjamin Rycroft.
What exactly Is Involved In such an operation to restore
or repair a person's sight, and how does the eye bank
come into the story?
HP
he remarkable thing is that provided the eye
H tissue used for grafting is itself healthy and free
JL. of scarring, it matters not what the age, state of
health, effectiveness of vision or cause of death of the
donor are. The corneas of elderly people are actually
better for the purpose than those of young children, and
even if a person had poor sight or wore glasses, his or her
tissue after death may prove to be the means whereby
someone else is saved from blindness or near-blindness.
In this context, there ls no such thing as a "worn-out
eye": it ls the surface corneal tissue, not the lens, that
is used.
The Important thing Is that the eye or eyes be removed
from the body as soon as possible after death, ideally
within two hours, and with an outside limit of perhaps
ten hours. This naturally causes difficulty, but is essen¬
tial if any subsequent grafting operation is to succeed.
The removal of the eyes, their enucleation, can be easily
undertaken by any doctor, and, it should be stressed,
causes no mutilation or visible disfigurement of a loved
one's body. The length of time fresh eyes are in fact
kept in storage in an eye bank is relatively of less impor¬
tance than the immediacy of their enucleation.
This ls probably the single greatest problem in corneal
surgery: relatives are naturally loth to grant permission
so soon after decease, and post-mortem permission may
all too frequently arrive too late. The complete eye Is
removed, and usually placed on a gauze pad in a small
glass jar of paraffin oil, the Inertia of which protects the
soft, unsupported tissue. It Is then usually sent swiftly
to an eye bank in a watertight copper container embedded
inside a metal ice box.
On arrival at the eye bank an eye is Immersed for an
hour In an antibiotic solution to ensure complete sterility,
and bacterial cultures are always taken on arrival at the
eye bank and again 48 hours before use to ensure that no
infection Is introduced into the patient's open eye.
Ideally, eye tissue is used very soon after enucleation,
as may sometimes be possible in an eye hospital, or when
wanted for a patient who has himself supplied the tissue
from a useless eye to save the sight of the other, called
an autograft. But in practice, donated corneal material
must be brought to wherever it is required.
The problem of effective storage of the living eye tissue
from someone now dead has received much attention, and
is an aspect still being widely researched upon. Several
methods are currently used. For short-term storage, up
to about four days, the eye is simply kept at 4° C. in an
ordinary hospital refrigerator after its antibiotic
Amabile Battistelio, seventeen-year-old girl of
Cusano Milanino, Italy, has partially recovered
her sight thanks to theeyes of the Rev. Don
Carlo Gnocchi who, before dying in Milan
some time ago, willed his eyes to a blind girl.
Amabile was chosen as the recipient of the Rev.
Gnocchi's legacy. The operation was carried
out successfully and today, her sight partially,
restored, the young Italian girl has begun to
live the normal life of a teen-ager. Her bene¬
factor, who achieved recognition as sponsor
of Italy's war-strlcken youngsters, has joined
an ever increasing number of men and women
throughout the world who have willed their
eyes to eye banks in their communities to
provide restored or improved sight for those
who are blind or suffer from defective eyesight.
Photos © Atlantic Press
immersion. This method is ideal in a busy hospital
where grafting is regularly carried out. For longer sto¬
rage, the donated eye is kept in liquid paraffin at the
same low temperature, treated with one or more anti¬
biotics and sometimes nourished with dextrose to feed
the tissue during storage.
For even longer storage periods, that is more than
about three weeks, other methods are currently being
investigated, notably the slow freezing of the eye in gly¬
cerol Immersed In a vial in carbon dioxide "snow" at
the extremely low temperature of minus 79° C. Another
method, preferred in the U.S.A., Is to dehydrate the cornea
and store it in nitrogen gas. When reconstituted, the
tissue is as good as new.
In practice, however, the description eye bank is often
something of a misnomer, since all available graft mate¬
rial is used just as soon as it can be obtained. The
waiting list for corneal operations is frequently far longer
than the expected supply of donor eyes. Nevertheless,
there must often be storage, particularly in large countries
where great distances between surgeon, donor and patient
are involved.
The operation itself is a marvellous example of ophthal¬
mic surgical skill. Since 1945 the techniques and
Instruments used have been greatly Improved and now
contribute a strange and striking beauty to this unique
human feat. All cases are of course most carefully
selected, and waiting lists are often longer than is gene¬
rally imagined: in the U.S.A., for example, it was recently
estimated that upwards of 30,000 people could be assisted
if more donated eyes (and more skilled eye surgeons)
were available.
A patient spends between a fortnight and a month in
hospital. The pupil is contracted with drugs, and drops
of a local anaesthetic are inserted into the eye at brief
intervals throughout the operation. Basically, a circular
concave section of the opaque cornea ls cut away with
the sharp trephine, which is then used to cut out a disc,
or graft, of fresh tissue from a donor eye of exactly the
same size. With Infinite care, this tiny section is lifted
with delicate forceps, placed in position, and painstakingly
secured with about eight minute sutures of fine braided
silk or monofilament, stitched with a specially designed
needle just 4 mm. in length.
The trephine, still based on von Hippel's invention of
1880, can be adjusted at various depths to cut grafts of
any thickness as demanded by the diseased or injured
eye. The renovated eye is then treated with atropine
and covered for several days. The stitches are removed
in 18-20 days, and although the graft tends to bulge
outwards a little at first, it gradually flattens out natur¬
ally within six months, and, miraculously, becomes part
of the patient's living body.
Above all, he or she finds that sight is improved or even
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
restored where before there was only darkness. In many
countries there are records of people whose vision was
limited perhaps to a a vague appreciation of movement
to whom the corneal grafting operation has given normal
vision for both distance and reading, even with the
difficult full-thickness graft. And the implanted tissue
becomes as clear and even as a normal healthy cornea.
No wonder one lady declared in a poetic burst of
astonished realization: "Through eyes made
whole by mine, I'll see." Her sentiments when
she realized that her own eyes may well help someone else
to see after her death were well expressed but unfortun¬
ately are by no means universal. If they were, the
immense task of keratoplasty surgeons and eye bank
directors the world over would be greatly eased.
The eye bank organization is a recent Idea much
hampered by apathy, ignorance and legal and religious
obstacles. Many otherwise enlightened people object to
eyes being removed after death, while many countries
cling to outdated legal restrictions more suited to the
days of body-snatching. For example, some national
laws specify a 24-hour waiting period before any tissue
can be removed from the dead, which destroys the
potential value of the eyes.
The world's leading eye bank, and the first to be estab¬
lished, is The Eye Bank for Sight Restoration, set up
by a few interested doctors in 1944 at the Manhattan Eye,
Ear and Throat Hospital, at 210, East 64th Street, New
York 21, U.S.A., as a non-profit-making organization.
Now, with a long list of outstanding successes behind it,
with 16 affiliated eye banks throughout the United States,
it offers to the rest of the world a wonderful example not
only in the storage and allocation of donor eyes, but in
their swift supply to where the need ls greatest (by air,
if need be), and in the special training of eye surgeons.
It also runs a weekly clinic for corneal sufferers and
maintains a unique research laboratory wherein the study
of donated eye tissue (often after providing a successful
graft) plays a big part in furthering mankind's knowledge
of its optical equipment. Operating at much more than
a local community level, this eye bank is a major enter¬
prise, backed by the most careful organization.
In 1948, profiting by a 1947 decree removing the 24-hour
limitation on eye removal, La Banque Française des Yeux,
now at 21, rue Francois- 1", Paris (8e), France, was
founded, chiefly through the combined efforts of ophthal¬
mologists, veterans' groups and associations for the blind.
It now works assiduously on a broad programme, ls
backed by local or regional eye banks throughout France,
and is well supported both officially and voluntarily. This
major European development was followed In 1950 by the
setting up of the Banco Nacional de Ojos, at the Hospital
Provincial In Madrid, after legislative authorization, and
this eye bank now maintains a national programme
throughout Spain.
In 1952, thanks to a realistic educational campaign, the
Corneal Grafting Act was passed in Great Britain without
opposition, and eyes can now be removed promptly after
death If relatives have no objection, while anyone may
bequeath his eyes for this purpose without specific legal
deposition. A number of eye banks are In operation in
regional areas as well as in London, and much research
work goes on, notably at the Queen Victoria Hospital at
East Grlnstead in Sussex, under Sir Benjamin Rycroft.
Indeed, U.S.A., France, Spain, Britain and Syria have
led the way In furthering this noble work by removing
legal and other hindrances to using fresh eyes from the
recently dead. But other countries are not so fortunate.
Italy, for example, needs clearer laws on this matter, and
the legal requirements vary in Germany, where eye bank
planning ls well behind other nations.
The law is insufficiently specific in Canada, Greece,
Peru and Brazil, while in Venezuela difficulties arise with
relatives. Morocco has one eye bank and Mohammedan
spokesmen have helped in allaying religious fears. No
real legal obstacles exist In Austria or Switzerland, while
Denmark and Norway are in the happy position of having
very little eye disease and so the demand for eyes is
small. Yet Finland has a condition not considered
necessary In say Holland, and the legal procedure in
Sweden ls very different from that in Czechoslovakia.
Surgeons in Egypt still have to fight ancient prejudices,
but the greatest need of all ls in India, where a vast need
is met by two small eye banks only, one In Madras and
one in Aligarh.
Clearly, there is much need for uniformity of legislation
controlling the removal of eyes, but the problem goes
deeper than that. The real need ls for an Eye Crusade,
since helpful legislation or even tacit agreement about
the securing of fresh graft material cannot make much
headway without popular education designed to achieve
universal enlightenment.
All too often today the skill and power of this branch
of eye surgery Is balked by apathy, prejudice and
conflict. France, Great Britain, the U.S.A. and one or
two other countries already apply simple systems whereby
a person's witnessed signature on a card or form is suffi¬
cient to ensure that his or her eyes will be used after
death, but of course many more eye banks (and with
them, many more surgeons) are needed everywhere.
No one who has seen the human tragedy caused solely
by corneal opacity and the great Joy brought to many
patients by a graft of this kind can doubt the need or
the urgency.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
BLOOD VESSELS IN E
Blood banks, eye banks (see page I 5) and bone banks have given the
world new ways of combating the age-old plagues of man disease
and disability. The latest "bank" provided by modern science is the
Blood Vessel Bank established at the New York Hospital, New York
City. In certain operations the surgeon is impeded by blood vessels
which have ceased to function normally and which must be sacrificed
to ensure a successful operation. Experiments have proved that sections
of arteries and other blood vessels can successfully be inserted to replace
malfunctioning ones. This led to the establishment of a bank In which
grafts from donors are kept in a large double door refrigerator (right).
The bank sends the blood vessels as they are required to other hospitals.
The nurse above is withdrawing an aorta from the bank which will
be sent to Its destination in a special refrigerated container. Two or
more hours at room temperature would damage the graft. Donor
grafts must be preserved in a special solution of buffered salt to which
human serum and antibiotics are added. The technician below weighs
one of the several salts employed in making this special solution.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
tOTTLES
Because donor grafts must be brought to the bank swiftly, sugeons, technicians and nurses on
duty all hours must be prepared to move out on short notice both to take grafts from donors
(recently deceased people in good health so far as the vascular system Is concerned) and to deliver
grafts to surgeons requiring them for operation. The sterilized equipment and Instruments
including two complete surgical kits fill two large suitcases. All Instruments and equipment arc
sterilized in the bank's own autoclave (above) and are packed and ready to go at a moment's notice.
The actual removal of the graft like the one below is done in as sterile a manner as possible under
operating room conditions. The graft immediately goes Into the prepared solution and is later
kept under observation to ensure that it is not diseased. It will be good from four to six weeks.
All photos (Q Gcor E. Picl'ow, Nrw-York
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
MICROPHOTOGRAPHY REVEALS
THE
INVISIBLE
WORLD
by Daniel Behrman
Aworld of phantasmagorical shapes, breath¬
taking beauty, nightmarish monsters, sur¬
realist dreams, certain mortality, apparently-
eternal immortality, baroque fantasy,
»abstract starkness, utter chaos, perfect
order... this is a world as remote from our own as any
undiscovered planet beyond the edge of the solar
system and yet seldom any further away than our
fingertips. This is the invisible world, entered not
through Alice's looking-glass, but through the
microscope.
Men have been exploring it since the invention of
the microscope three-and-a-half centuries ago. It has
revealed to them countless secrets which have con¬
tained the answers to riddles of life and death. When
the biologist aims the barrel of his lens upon a deadly
organism or the chemist focuses upon a mysterious
crystal, he is usually hunting the answer to one of
these specific riddles. And yet, there are moments
when the imperative demands of science or technol¬
ogy arc suddenly overshadowed by a vision of har¬
mony or horror. Moments like these are seldom for¬
gotten by anyone who has experienced them, even
though they may have no immediate bearing on the
progress of science.
Not so very long ago, this hidden world could be
seen only by a person lucky enough to have a micro¬
scope available that is, by scientific research workers
and a handful of enthusiasts who installed micro¬
scopes in their parlours at a time when their neigh¬
bours were installing magic lanterns. Patient obser¬
vers, it is true, had painstakingly produced drawings
of microscopic images but they could not hope to
catch anything more than two-dimensional cross-sec¬
tions in which the added dimension of emotion was
lacking.
The eye of the camera changed all this. Now it was
possible to capture the hnage under the microscope
in the same way as any image of the normal world.
Still, it was no easy task. The cumbersome ancestors
of present-day cameras could be adapted to micro-
photography only with the help of equally cumber¬
some optical apparatus.
As a science and as an aid to science, microphoto-
graphy made a relatively early appearance, but it had
to await the development of modern cameras to
become an art... if we accept that definition of art as
the superfluous which makes life worth living.
Today, a good 35-millimetre camera, a simple adap¬
tor, a microscope and a stand to keep the camera
steady (for some exposures may last as long as
100 seconds) are all that is needed for microphoto-
graphy.
Not quite all, though. Perhaps the most important
prerequisite is that elusive quality of inspiration and
20 CONT'D ON PAGE 22
Tiny anchors and filigree pendants are not
from Madame's jewelbox but a microscopic
bit of the skin of a tiny sea creature.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
This exquisite doily of sheer¬
est lace is only a section of a
common chestnut tree stem.
kr®
Feathery reeds in a floral arrangement are
the microscopic crystals of salicylic acid.
Photos ¡0 Louis-Jacques Lapone, Paris
It might be a wasp's nest, or some strange
fabricactually these are bay salt crystals.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
THE INVISIBLE WORLD (Cont'd;
FIFTY THOUSAND
MICROSCOPE SLIDES
imagination which can distinguish what is beautiful
or unusual in one microscopic image out of a
thousand others. And, of course, the thousand other
images are needed, too.
There are no less than 50,000 of them in the lab¬
oratory of Dr. Louis-Jacques Laporte in Paris, on one
of those quiet residential streets in the Passy district
where nothing ever seems to happen. Dr. Laporte is
the leading supplier of microscopic slides for science
teaching in French universities and lycées, an occupa¬
tion which keeps him busy seventy-two hours a week
in this age when educators are discovering "audio¬
visual teaching aids", one of the fields in which
Uni:sco is working. It certainly keeps him too busy
to wonder what the reactions of the groceries-laden
housewives hurrying past his ground-floor quarters
would be if they knew that, only a few feet away, all
the afilictions of man from cancer to the plague were
jn storage (harmlessly, of course) on glass slides.
Even if they entered his laboratory, as we did the
olhcr day, they probably would not be very enligh¬
tened. It is one of the last citadels of the lone experi¬
menter in this era of air-conditioned assembly lines,
functioning to the rhythm of piped-in music selected
by psychologists.
The Laporte laboratory, housing one of the world's
specialists in the new science of microphotography,
might well serve as a stage setting for a play by Cour-
tclinc, the turn-of-thc-century French dramatist who
delighted in satirizing the bureaucracy of his day.
All the props are there: roll-top desk, a huge table
covered with scarred linoleum and assorted flasks,
bottles and papers, a gas radiator which has a habit
of turning itself on and off with disconcerting pops,
and files, files, files climbing the walls to the ceiling.
Over this citadel reigns Dr. Laporte, a mild, dis¬
tinguished-looking man who wears the discreet
rosette of the French Legion of Honour in his lapel.
Adjoining this office is another room containing the
simple stand used for microphotography, hundreds of
photographs and more files filled with microscopic
slides.
There is also a kitchen, converted into a warehouse,
whose contents include a few boxes of carefully
labelled sacks of earth from Barbados, brought back
after an expedition two years ago in search of new
specimens of diatoma, the fossilized algae which are
a delight to the eye of the microphotographer and
anyone else fortunate enough to see them.
Dr. Laporte is a rather rare specimen himself he
comes quite close to that 18th century notion of a
"universal man". He is not only a scientist and a
photographer, but he also happens to be a singer (he
is president of one of Paris's leading choral societies),
a writer and a painter. True, he hasn't done very
much painting since he sold sketches of the Luxem7
bourg Gardens in the Latin Quarter to help pay his
way through the Sorbonne, but he has been writing
all his life. Among his books are "The Invisible
World", "What You Should Know about the Micro¬
scopic World", a collection of poems entitled "Souls
and Landscapes"... and a detective story.
Yet it might be said that all of his talents even a
musician's sense of harmony met in one of his most
recent works, "Panorama of the Micro-World". Here,
as he explained to us in his laboratory, art took pre¬
cedence over science. Its 300-odd illustrations from
his own collection of micro-photographs and other
equally rich collections are a gallery of portraits,
The curious baubles, below left, would enhance a Christmas tree, but
a microscopic one. The pattern is the tooth of a sea fish. In centre
photo below the design is simply a minute area of the surface of
an ordinary gramophone record. The abstraction, (below right)
22 CONT'D ON PAGE 24
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. May 1961
It .could be a brooch of precious stones as seen here magnified 1,860
times. In reality it is a secreted valve from a Madagascar diatom cell.
would be right at home in a collection of modern drawingsbut you'd
need a microscope to see it. It is an arrangement of body scales from
a hawk-moth. Above, a cross-section of a vine tendril running with sap
shows, under the microscope, a great variety of intricate layers.
Microphotography discovers an unusual plaid fabric design in this
section of a striped muscle of a sea insect larva magnified 1,340 times.
Photos Ç) Louis-Jacques Laporte, Parts 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
THE INVISIBLE WORLD (Cont'd)
GALLERY OF N O N- F I G U R AT I VE ART
landscapes, vignettes and non-figurative compositions
visible to the naked eye only because they have been
magnified anywhere up to 40,000 times (a ratio which
can be achieved with the electron microscope).
As wc browsed through the "Panorama of the
Micro-World" in his laboratory, Dr. Laporte deter¬
minedly went to work on his morning's mail, in¬
terrupted occasionally by the doorbell announcing
students who needed slides for an experiment or a
thesis.
"Look at this letter," he remarked, "I only get
about one a year like this nowadays." It was from a
French priest in Lc Havre who wanted a "Diatoma
Rose-Window" with some very stern specifications:
"What is important to me is the beauty of the slide.
You know that I am very demanding. You have my
entire confidence."
Dr. Laporte sighed. "There you have a vanishing
race the diatom collector," he remarked. This
species of collector is interested either in individual
specimens or else in unbelievably-complicated com¬
positions in which 'pearl-like diatoma are used to
decorate floral bouquets composed of butterfly scales.
A surface of 5 square millimetres is usually enough
for a picture.
This is the way Dr. Laporte has described a dia¬
tom collector in his "Panorama of the Micro-
World": "His penchant is revealed the day he sees
for the first time under the microscope the stained-
glass window design of a Lepidodiscus elegans and
his delight never ceases after that. When he is
making observations, he forgets his dinner time and
he consents to get some sleep only when dawn comes
to brighten the windows of his study.
Crystallization of common and uncommon chemical bodies produces some
of the most beautiful of all photographs taken through the microscope.
"If he hears of a species which lives only in the
tropics and he does not possess it, then he can love
nothing else. He moves heaven and earth to obtain it
and, if it were not for the obligations tying him to
his country, his family and his modest office job, you
would see him steal it or sail off to seek it. For it is
missing from his collection and he has set aside a
place for it in his box, as the philatelist does for
stamps in his album. This empty space hurts his eyes
and he will not be able to live until it has been filled."
And here is the happiest day in the life of a
diatomist: "In his collection, he has an extremely rare
diatom which can be gathered only on a certain small
island lost in the Indian Ocean and found on maps
only as a nameless speck. And this island, he has
just learned, has been swallowed up forever in an
earthquake; the sea has engulfed its beach and its
rocks, its mangroves, its population and (he thinks)
its diatoma. He gazes with renewed love upon the
unique specimen he possesses. His heart brims with
happiness..."
Among microscopophiles and micro-photographers,
the diatomist is in an extreme class by himself. He
not only wants to explore the micro-world; he wants
to change it to suit his own tastes. In a less acute and
more widespread form, his viewpoint is reflected in
those who see parallels between the world under
their lenses and the world around them. Magnified
21 times, a cross-section of a bramble stem becomes
the head of a grinning cat. Three caterpillar hairs
(magnified seventy-five times) reproduce the sophisti¬
cated brushwork of a Japanese artist. The cross-
section of a sea-urchin's spike (magnified 300 times)
could inspire many a jeweller. As common an object
CONT'D ON PAGE 26
So striking are some of them that even modern artists have been known
to use them as Inspiration for their abstractions. Those pictured below
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Photos © Louis-Jacques Laporte, Paris
Coffee-lovers claim this ingredient keeps them awake at night. Under the microscope however, a crystal of caffeine appears more beautiful than harmful.
from left to right show, in the first two photos, crystals of a deadly poison
(chlorohydrate of pilocarpine) used in the manufacture of certain eye
washes. The third is crystallization of common soda, and the last which
looks like a butterfly's wing Is the crystallization of vegetable asparaglne.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
THE INVISIBLE WORLD (Cont'd)
A UNIVERSE REVEALED BEHIND A LENS
as a nylon stocking takes on a mysterious pattern of
endless links when magnified 45 times. There is even
a micro-painter, Rene Ferter, in Dr. Laporte's "Pano¬
rama" who has created landscapes inspired by the
microscope: for example, the crystallization of tar¬
taric acid is the basis for a landscape, "The Tall
Palissades," showing a walled city perched on a
rocky spur.
As you might imagine, insects take on new dimen¬
sions under the microscope. Microphotography
explains many of their amazing feats. Blown up
10() times, for example, an ant's head shows jaws as
cruelly efficient and ftinctional as a pair of wire-
cutters. Many of the tools which man has taken
thousands of years to devise, ranging from the drill
to the bulldozer, have always existed in the insect
world. Some of them even resemble the marvellous
electronic tools which we are just devising. A photo
of the antennae (magnified 125 times) of a small
scarab could easily be mistaken for one of the sensi¬
tive space probes mounted on the shells of artificial
satellites.
Up until now, Dr. Laporte had been talking to us
mainly about the giants of the micro-world. His pano¬
rama changes completely, however, when it takes in
organisms which have to be magnified hundreds of
times before they become visible to the naked eye.
Then all the landmarks of the normal world disappear
and you arc plunged into a new universe living under
laws of its own.
Take the Paramecium, for example, a roughly
oblong mass with a fringe of delicate hairs which are
actually the "oars" with which it rows along. Magni¬
fied 8G0 limes, the microphotograph can show the
Paramecium reproducing by division if it is suffi
ciently nourished, or else, when food runs low,
joining with another to form one but never dying.
Here, as Dr. Laporte told us, is a world with im¬
mortality.
Parasites and bacilli which are among man's dead¬
liest enemies also appear in this world. Some are far
more horrible than the diseases they cause (we cer¬
tainly would not advise looking at a spotted, flaccid
liver fluke, for example, before lunch). Others are
quite innocuous in appearance. Magnified 3,080 times,
Koch's bacilli are nothing but little stems meaning
nothing except to the experienced eye of the physician
who knows the signs of tuberculosis.
The great strides which have been made by public
health in recent years have complicated the task of
Dr. Laporte. "It's almost impossible to furnish slides
to medical students of certain diseases, which have
been virtually wiped but," he commented.
The doorbell in the musty old office housing these
micro-marvels was now beginning to ring more in¬
sistently. Dr. Laporte, with a trace of regret, closed
the covers of his "panorama" and returned to his
everyday profession. He had not covered the subject
by any stretch of imagination and it is unlikely that
it will ever be covered. Why not? The answer lies in
the conclusion he wrote to his book:
"In the dark night of the Middle Ages, the poet
showed us Doctor Faust vainly labouring over his
retorts to learn the mysteries of the world. Yet how
many 'ardent hours' will have to be spent by the
Doctor Fausts of the future if they want to under¬
stand anything about a living cell, because this cell,
in order to be understood, apparently must be
enlarged to the dimensions of a universe!"
***!t!^
An elephant's trunk I That's almost it. The trunk (or proboscis) of a
butterfly takes on such elephantine proportions under the microscope.
26
Man never seems to go nature one better, not even with braided rugs.
This handsome specimen is the cross-section of a sea-urchin's spine.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courler. Moy 1961
Photos© Louis-Jacques Laporte, Paris
The ayid diatom collectors prize such jewel-like creations as this one, arranged with diatoma from Madagascar.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Strobophotography sees
WHAT OUR
28
WHICH MAN IS THE PROFESSIONAL?
Two men striking a nail into a board seem to the ordinary observer
to be making an almost identical motion. By the process of strobo¬
photography, however, a marked difference between the two is imme¬
diately revealed. Not only does the strobophoto show, even to the
unpractised eye, that there is a difference in the way the hammer
descends in the hand of the man on the left as compared to that of
the man at the right, but an expert can look at the two photos and
tell immediately who is the professional and who is the "Sunday" car¬
penter. Strobophotography tells why. The hammer at the right seems
to plunge smoothly toward its goal while the one on the left is obviously
moving along a more jerky path... but the one on the left is being wielded
by a professional. Now look closely. Up at the top of its trajectory,
the hammer hesitates (two images). The empty space between these
two hammers and the five below it indicates that the carpenter has
decided to strike and the series of five shows that he held back his
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
EYES DO NOT SEE
AM Photos André Salesse-Lavergne
hammer slightly while he was aiming it. Then there is only a blank
space as the hammer crashes down on the head of the nail. This means
that it was a hard, determined blow (the blurred image between the
seventh position and the nail is the hammer photographed on the
rebound, returning upward for a second blow). As for that even-
spaced movement in the right-hand photo, it actually shows nothing
but inexperiencethe man with the hammer held back his stroke
all the way down to the nail because he was afraid of missing it... and
perhaps he was afraid, too, of hitting his finger instead of the nail.
by André J. Salesso-Lavergne
Take a look at the minute hand and the hour
hand of your watch. Can you see them move ?
Of course not. Yet, you know from experience
that they are moving at dilïercnt speeds but
always constantly and regularly.
Now open the hood of a car with its engine running
and look at the fan. What can you see ? At best, you
will be able to make out a vaguely circular blur, sur¬
rounded by a halo and shot through with moving lines
resembling rays without any solid substance. You
certainly will not be able to describe the exact shape
of the fan blades.
Our eye may be very sensitive to certain phenomena
of light, but it does not enable us to observe directly
either slow movement (the hands of a watch) or rapid
movement (the blades of a fan).
To tell the truth, this relative infirmity of our eye
does not bother us at all in dally life. All wc ask from
our eyesight and its often-Indispensable ally, our
hearing, is to give us a quick and adequate picture of
our surroundings so that we can act to preserve and
maintain our lives.
Actually, by limiting the range and acuteness of our
senses to grasp the world surrounding us, nature has
tried to spare us an Incessant assault by an Infinite num¬
ber of sensations which are not really needed for our
mental or physical activities and which might even
harm us by creating disturbances In our lives.
But man in his evolution and progressive conquest
of the forces of nature has always sought to penetrate
the mysterious laws which force him to think "univers¬
ally" that is, beyond the range of his own senses.
Little by little, he has conceived ways of enabling him
to expand the frontiers of his knowledge. As far as
eyesight is concerned, the magnlfying-glass, the micro¬
scope and the telescope have opened the long-forbidden
worlds of the infinitely small and the infinitely large.
With the Invention of photography, man took a
new and very Important step. It meant that
he could halt the march of time to obtain eye¬
witness evidence and irrefutable proof of phenomena
which he previously had studied only through guesswork
and hypotheses based solely upon sensory observations
which were often erroneous or else the whims of his
memory.
In other words, photography gave man a new sense.
It amounted to a concrete form of memory retaining
only facts. This infallible "memory" certainly meant
steady progress along the road to an objective study
of events and facts, but one Important element was
still lacking.
As we all know, photography can offer us only a
snapshot of a very brief aspect of an event observed
in space and time. If all we want to learn is this
aspect, then we can be satisfied. But if we also want 29
;ONTD ON NEXT PAGF
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
^4 SEC
THE STROBOPHOTOGRAPH
(Cont'd;
Optical illusion known as the "stroboscope effect" was discovered
In 1828 by Plateau, a Belgian scientist who showed that two
spoked wheels placed on the same axle and rotating at the same
speed, but in opposite directions, will appear to the human eye
as a single and motionless wheel. Today, In films, spoked wheels
of cars or machines occasionally seem to be rotating backwards.
Each image remains motionless on the screen in front of your eyes
for 1/24 of a second. If, during this interval, the wheel moves the
exact distance separating one spoke from another, then the
spokes and the wheel appear to be stationary (Fig. I). But if
the wheel moves over a shorter distance than that separating
two of its spokes, it will appear to be moving backwards because
your eye will have the illusion that the spoke has moved slightly
backward instead of forward. Another phenomenon occurs when
a wheel, during this 1/24 of a second, moves exactly half the
distance between two spokes. It appears to have twice its true
number of spokes. At right is shown one of the pioneer
stroboscopic photos made by General Libessart of France, who
studied what happens to a golf ball when it is hit. He used a
device known as "stroborama", capable of 1,500 images per second.
Photos © André Salesse-Lavergne
HOW TO TAKE A STROBOPHOTOGRAPH. These three
photos of the same subject illustrate the difference between strobo¬
photography and photography. At left, a snapshot made at one-
fiftieth of a second of a woman striking a match to light a candle.
In the centre photo, the lens of the camera has been left open while
she struck the match, placed it on the candle and then moved the
candle. The result ¡s a "photogram". At right, the lens has remain¬
ed open but the photographer has used a special apparatus, called
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Th« Unesco Courier. Mor t"l
Magic of an orchestra conductor's hand as it creates music is dissected
here by this strobophotograph, taken in the dim light over his stand.
Long, delicate fingers contrast with the confident and authoritative
movements of the baton, none of which could be seen by normal sight.
(
Right and wrong way of designing a car's boot lid are shown in these
two photographs. In the model tested at far left, the lid showed a
tendency to smack the startled motorist's nose on its way down, a
design fault brought out clearly by the stroboscope camera (the driver
has to lean forward to close it). At left, a lid comes down effortlessly,
enabling the driver to stand well clear of it. The manufacturer thus
knows even before production begins that the problem has been solved.
a flash generator, which flashed while the candle was being lighted
with the burning match. This is a true strobophotograph, breaking
down the individual phases of motion. Industry has already used stro¬
bophotography very profitably and educators now realize its value.
Photos © André Salesse-Lavergne
AMAZING
SURREALISTIC
BALLET
to know what preceded it and what is going to follow it,
we must have a method of investigation which ls capable
of capturing the event In Its full run through space
and time.
The principle of this method was Invented by a French
physiologist, Etienne Marey, when he succeeded In
taking successive snapshots at the rate of twelve Images
per second with his famed "chronophotographlc gun".
This enabled him to study the entire process of an object
in motion.
Later, other inventors, including the Lumière brothers,
discovered a mechanical system for "parading" Images
in front of a lens. This meant that motion could not
only be photographed but reproduced as well. Chrono-
photography became cinematography. Both of these
techniques offered an extremely Important new opport¬
unity to scientific research: the events they recorded
could now be analysed as many times as was required.
Strobophotography ls a method of investigation based
both on chronophotography and clnemaphotography.
The methods it uses are rather similar. But It presents
one striking difference which anyone can detect : the
apparent strangeness of the final result. For a strobo¬
photograph gives us a very unusual picture of human
beings in motion. Their familiar gestures are turned
into amazing and surrealistic ballet movements. They
look as if double exposures had given them additional
limbs or even bodies. One is even tempted to believe
that it is all a fake just as if a number of Images liad
been superimposed. It is not a fake however. A strobo¬
photograph Is absolutely authentic. It ls taken with
only one shot and during the elapsed time of the motion
it represents.
If a person being photographed seems to be using
five arms to greet a friend or a worker is apparently
using a dozen Identical tools, the explanation ls
very simple. A motion picture film would capture these
same movements with a number of small images. Each of
these images is a "snapshot" of an infinitely small phase
of the movement. Later, the images are developed over
a certain length of film which must then be projected
for the movement to be analysed.
But strobophotography does not use a number oí
pictures to capture these different and separate snap¬
shots. Instead, it registers them on a single negative
which remains motionless inside the camera. On this
single negative, all the phases of a movement are
recorded.
Those multiple hands, ghostly bodies, two-headed
creatures and doors opening on to infinity form a dream
world which can inspire artists, attract poets and
stimulate our imagination. But the scientist and the
technician are interested in them as well. To tell the
truth, strobophotography ls used most often by scientists
for it is the child of science.
In 1934, General Libessart used a "stroborama" invent¬
ed by the Seguin brothers to study what happens to a
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
STROBOPHOTOGRAPHY (Cont'd)
VALUABLE AID
FOR EDUCATORS
golf ball when It is hit. It enabled him to determine its
speed (147 feet per second) and its rate of rotation (200
revolutions per minute). Edgerton in the United States
has been carrying out major research along these lines
at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. He is
particularly famous for the shots he made in 1949 of
Abdessalam, the tennis champion, with the help of a
lamp flashing at a rate of fifty times per second.
Since strobophotography can supply the exact data
needed to solve a large number of problems, it has many
applications. Among them are : the study of simple
movements in order to achieve a scientific organization
of work ; the study of human conduct in thé presence
of natural or accidental situations ; the study of indi¬
vidual or group reactions to certain tests; and generally
speaking, objective observation of outward manifestations.
Strobophotography can also be used profitably by
industry. For example, the styling department of a big
European car manufacturing firm recently put it to work
in order to study ways of increasing driving safety and
comfort in its new bodies.
There are two fields, however, where strobo¬
photography can play an extremely important
part: education and the preservation of our
culture. Today, education is making increasing use of
visual aids which stimulate individual effort through their
stress on observation, attention, learning by memory,
reasoning, and aesthetic sensitiveness. Strobophoto¬
graphy would be an extremely valuable aid if educators
were willing to use it. In developing countries where new
"active" methods of learning are to be introduced, it
would help young minds to grasp facts.
In these same countries, there is also a vital need to
train workers in those basic movements which are to be
found in modern industry. In this connexion, you need
only look at the hammer-blow experiment shown on
page 29 to realize the contribution that strobophotography
can make to vocational education.
As for our cultural heritage, it can also derive great
benefit from strobophotography. As a result of economic,
technological and social progress throughout the world,
traditional gestures are vanishing every day and others
are condemned to vanish very shortly. Just about every¬
where on earth, customs are dying out, so-called folk
dances are losing their original meaning and ways of
life are doomed to oblivion. Yet the least of these customs
is fraught with joy, suffering, belief, hope or simply
humble truth making it worthy to be preserved in
mankind's heritage.
We could make a precious contribution to forthcoming
generations if we recorded these human "relics" which
are now expressed in so many different ways. Strobo-
photographic archives would be a priceless treasure for
ethnology and the humanities. Just imagine for a
moment if, through some miracle, we had a series of
strobophotographs showing the life of our Cro-Magnon
ancestor and, particularly, the way he shaped his flints.
32 Then you will understand the value of such archives.
André Salesse-Lavergne
Setting in and out of a car is easy... thanks to the engineers who
have ironed out any design quirks forcing passengers to undergo
contortions. In running down such quirks, strobophotography is
an Invaluable ally. Above, a passenger gets out of a car's seat in a
laboratory. Below, a breakdown of the movement made by the
passenger sitting next to the driver when he enters a car. For
a negative of the photo above in which the movement of the hands
can be studied to greater advantage, see the same photo page two.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Unetco Courier. May 1961
Letters to the Editor
TELL US ABOUT FOLKLORE
Sir,
The presentation of your magazine
and the quality of the articles are both
remarkable. However, I should be
glad to read some articles dealing
with the folklore of different coun¬
tries. I believe that a knowledge of
folklore can help to encourage real
understanding between peoples. As
such it is well in line with the princi¬
ples of Unesco which stands for bro¬
therhood and mutual understanding.
G. Carol
St-Brieuc, France
CULTURE IS UNIVERSAL
Sir,
One of your readers recently wrote
that in his opinion, "Unesco is found¬
ed on a fiction: the equality of peo¬
ples, nations and races. This equa¬
lity is true before God, but does not
exist in fact... Your magazine there¬
fore faces two obstacles: either you
describe the countries of the world as
they are, thus risking the criticism and
resentment of your less privileged
members or else you look at every¬
thing through rose-coloured spectacles
with the result that you place the
Papuan tom-tom on the same level as
Mozart . . ."
Learned . anthropologists, theolo¬
gians and others will answer this un¬
realistic criticism of Unesco better
than I can ... I would say this: it
is a fact of science that peoples and
races are equal, not only before God,
but also biologically. Some races,
peoples, and nations are underde¬
veloped culturally as well as technolo¬
gically. Yet every group has some¬
thing to offer from which all may
learn. For example, the American
Indians, although they never produced
a United Nations building in New
York or a Victor Hugo, did produce
a working, successful parliament of
the Indian nations from which the
founders of the United States are
believed to have taken ideas.
As far as Unesco's placing of "the
Papuan tom-tom on the same level
with Mozart" is concerned, I am not
aware that Unesco does this. This
would be as silly as placing America's
singing commercial, which Adlai Ste¬
venson has called our "national
litany", on a level with Marian
Anderson's transcendent interpretation
of Brahms' "Alto Rhapsody". But,
Unesco might give us an anthro¬
pological study of the singing
commercial, and such a study might
be not only interesting but valuable.
There is much in primitive cultures
that is not good but *bad. In our
effort to "understand" these cultures
we should not overlook the bad any¬
more than we should overlook the
good. Polygamy and polyandry, for
example, are not good, but then
neither is promiscuity and my own
country, the United States, is certain¬
ly not free of the latter. So, without
being the ones to cast the first stone,
we can at the same time be realistic
in our evaluation of what is good and
what is bad. Meanwhile, Unesco is
doing a great service in helping nations
and peoples to understand each other.
It deserves our wholehearted support.
Palmer Van Gundy
Glendale, California, U.S.A.
THE MENTALLY HANDICAPPED
Sir,
I think one issue, or part of an issue,
of your magazine might be devoted to
the problem of France's 600,000 men¬
tally deficient children which is the
same problem all over the world,
where mental defectives exist in simi¬
lar proportions. This is a tragedy
which can strike any family, for con¬
genital mental deficiency (mongolism,
deficiencies occurring as a result of
German measles in the mother or
complications of tubercular meningitis,
the Rhesus factor, anoxaenia, vacci¬
nal encephalitis or a forceps birth)
has nothing to do with alcoholism.
In France there are only 3,000
classes for the slightly sub-normal,
whereas over 20,000 are required.
As for the seriously sub-normal, when¬
ever a vacancy occurs in one of the
institutions for remedial education
two or three hundred applicants are
waiting.
After school-age the problem of
mental deficiency is even more tra¬
gic. The adolescent (and there are
tens of thousands of them) has no
hope of becoming a worker, or even
having some occupation. Once his
parents are no longer there to care
for him, there is only the asylum.
Scientific progress saves many child¬
ren who were condemned before the
discovery of "miracle" drugs, leaving
doctors with other problems for which
there are so far no solutions. But as
Professor Heuyer, creator of the chair
of child psychiatry in France, has
said, "Any progress a child can make,
even at the lowest intellectual level,
is worth while." We must not forget it.
P. Carême
Virey-Ie-Grand, France
THE CLOCK WAS SLOW
The March issue of the Unesco
Courier gives a very graphic picture of
how young geologically speaking
man really is. It is not altogether
easy to date the fossils that are found,
but some of the estimates of their
age given in the article are too high,
arid others too low. The following
points need to be corrected for the
period after "six p.m.".
The lower jaw of the Heidelberg
Man (the oldest find in F.uropc) is
450,000 years old; the Swanscomhc
skull about 300,000-275.000; the
remains found by Iîhringsdorf ne.ir
Weimar 130,000; and NeanJerthal
Man 120,000-100,000. Homo Sa¬
piens (the present type of man) who
supplanted Neanderthal Man can look
back on at least 100,000 years' exis¬
tence.
Dr. G.H.K. von Kocnigswald
Holland
FOUR.LEGGED GUIDES
Sir,
In your issue, "New Pathways for
the Blind" (June 1960), I feel thai
a serious omission was made in the
lack of any reference to Guide Dogs
for the blind, or "Sccing-IIyc" dogs.
This movement, which started in Ger¬
many towards the end of the first
world war, has now developed, both
rapidly and soutidly, in many coun¬
tries of the world, in particular the
United States of America and the
United Kingdom. Australia, South
Africa and Israel now have training
centres, too, as have many Iluropcan
countries.
The training of both dog and blind
person has been developed to a high
degree, is scientifically based and is
constantly being improved to give
blind people the benefit of the most
advanced training methods and tech¬
niques. The value of a Guide Dog,
properly trained by qualified trainers,
is being more and more appreciated
by blind people who work with than
or know of them, thus the demand is
ever increasing.
Here, in Australia, the movement
has been established for some ten
years and this national organization
is supplying Guide Dogs, trained to
the highest standards, to blind people
throughout the Commonwealth.
J. K. Iloldsvvorlli
Director of Training
Guide Dogs for (lie Illind Association
Ilelmonf, Western Australia.
Sir,
As usual I enjoyed reading your
issue on "New Pathways for the
Blind", but in all the articles I did
not see any mention of guide dogs.
There has been some controversy in
Australia as to whether there should
be guide dogs, an expensive matter.
Those against them say that they
tend to make blind people less inde¬
pendent and self-reliant.
From a purely lay point of view
it does seem a tremendous waste of
time and money to spend on a dog
which does not live as long as its
master or mistress.
A. L. Mackay
Lindfleld, Australia
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New;
UNESCO SALUTES FIRST MAN IN SPACE
'
* \\t%
On the occasion of the first man being fired into
space from the Soviet Union, Dr. Vittorino Vero¬
nese, Director-General of Unesco, sent the following
message to the Chairman of the Soviet National
Commission for Unesco in Moscow :
"Have learned with deep satisfaction news of
successful achievement of most recent Soviet
experiment in outer space. The Government and
people of the Soviet Union may be proud of this
new scientific achievement. I beg you to convey
to the Soviet National Commission for Unesco and
to Soviet scientists and engineers my wholehearted
congratulations.
Vittorino Veronese, Director-General."
Yuri Gagarine
It.	IEFUGEE CAMPS TO CLOSE:
There will be no more refugees living in
camps in Europe by 1962 according to
Mr. Felix Schnyder, recently appointed
U.N. High Commissioner for Refugees.
Most camps in Austria, he said, would be
closed down in 1961, and those in Ger¬
many and Austria during 1962. At the
beginning of this year, there were still
13,000 refugees living in camps in these
countries, under the U.N. High Commis¬
sioner's mandate. Another 60,000 were
living outside in sub-standard homes.
MOUNTAIN OF SALT: Near the
town of Kulab in South Tajikistan,
U3.S.R., there is a mountain of salt
which, say scientists, is sufficient to
supply the domestic needs of the world's
present population for a million years.
The hill, called Hoja Mumin, is com¬
posed of pure salt covered with a thin
layer of wind-borne sand and dust. The
salt not only rises to a height of 2,600
feet above the surrounding countryside,
but penetrates into the earth to a depth
of nearly two and a half miles. It is
over five miles in diameter.
fU LASSES IN THE SNOW : "Snow
Classes", an experiment started in France
in 1953, have proved beneficial to
children's intellectual as well as physical
development say French educators. The
classes, in which thousands of French
schoolchildren take part each year, enable
boys and girls from the cities to spend
about a month in the mountains with
their teachers and physical training
instructors. In the mornings, lessons are
held as usual, while in the afternoons the
children are taught skiing and other
outdoor sports.
TAGORE CENTENARY CELE¬
BRATED: Countries all over the
world are this month honouring the
centenary of the birth of Rabindranath
Tagore, India's celebrated poet and
writer. As a prelude to this year's
celebrations, a special performance of
"Chitra", a play by Tagore, was given
in Paris last November at Unesco
House, during the Unesco General
Conference. Two films are being
produced to commemorate the Tagore
Centenary by one of India's foremost
film-makers, Satyajit Ray. One is a
medium-length documentary on Tagore's
life; the other is a full-length feature
based on three of his short stories.
S CHOOLS FOR AFRICA: Tropical
Africa, comprising 30 countries from
Ethiopia to the Congo and from Senegal
to Madagascar, has 25 million children
of school age. Yet 17 million have no
schools to attend and of the "privileged"
8 million only a minority complete primary
education. Forty African states and terri¬
tories and five European countries with
African responsibilities have been invited
to a meeting in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia, this
month, to discuss ways and means of
developing education in Africa. Held
under the joint auspices of Unesco and
the U.N. Economic Commission lor Africa,
the conference will be attended by
Ministers or Directors of Education for
the African countries. Unesco's own
programme for 28 countries in Tropical
Africa during 1961-62 amounts to about
$11.5 million, including sums administered
on behalf of the U.N. Special Fund and
Technical Assistance.
MOST MODERN MUSEUM:
Visitors to the zoo and botanical
gardens of the future Kuwait National
Museum won't notice the baking heat
of the Persian Gulf (sometimes 120
degrees F. in the shade). They will be
taken arpund in a glass-roofed, air-
conditioned train. When completed, the
Kuwait Museum will be the world's
most modern. In addition to the zoo
and botanical gardens, it will have
sections on ethnology, folklore, astro¬
nomy and the techniques of extracting
and refining oil (source of Kuwait's
riches). There will be vessels 120 feet
long in its naval museum and, in its
aquarium, a tunnel 40 feet long will
enable visitors to walk along the
"seabed" with fish on all sides.
THE UNESCO
PHILATELIC SERVICE
umiu
The work of the International Mone¬
tary Fund to promote a freer system
of world trade and payments as a
means of helping Its member coun¬
tries achieve economic growth,
high levels of employment and im¬
proved standards of living is comme¬
morated in the stamp above, which
was issued on April 17 by the
United Nations Postal Administra¬
tion. Issued In 4 cent (blue and
white) and 7 cent (brick red, yellow
and white) denominations, this is
the second of the 1961 series of
U.N. commemorative stamps hon¬
ouring U.N. Specialized Agencies.
As the agent in France of the U.N.
Postal Administration, UNESCO'S
Philatelic Service stocks all the
United Nations stamps currently
on sale. It also has stamps and first
day covers issued by many UNESCO
member states to commemorate
important events in the history of
UNESCO and the U.N. (inaugura¬
tion of UNESCO'S new head¬
quarters. Human Rights Day, World
Refugee Year). Information on
items available, their price and the
methods of payment will be sent on
request by the UNESCO Philatelic
Service, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7*.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
TELEVISIO
TEACHING
TODAY
by Henry R. Cassiror
Educators everywhere are faced with the challenge of
rapidly-growing school and college populations and tho
need for a new approach to the content and methods of
teaching. Television may provide one of the answers
to their problems. Dr. Henry R. Cassirer has under¬
taken a general survey of most of the principal countries
which are using television for educational purposes.
Some countries employ television for the enrichment
of normal classroom lessons, others undertake direct
teaching of numerous subjects to young or adult stu¬
dents who seek to improve and pursue their education.
The book presents the problems which television poses
to teacher and learner alike, and Indicates ways in which
television may be used constructively in support of tho
traditional values of teaching.
Paper cover $3.00 15/- 10.50 NF
Cloth bound: $ 4.00 20/- 14. NF
Where to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write
direct to the National Distributor
in your country. (See list below;
names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.)
Payment is made in the national
currency ; rates quoted are for an
annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Press
Department, Royal Afghan Ministry of
Education, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 369 Lonsdale Street, Melbourne,
C. I. Victoria. (A. 15/-).
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C°., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V (Sch.
SO.-)
BELGIUM. For The Unesco Courier:
Louis de Lannoy, 22, Place De Brouckère,
Brussels, C.C.P. 338.000. (fr. b. 100.)
Other publications: Office de Publicité,
16, rueMarcq, Bruxelles, C.C.P. 285.98;
N.V. Standaard-Boekhandel, Belgielei 151,
Antwerp.
BURMA. Burma Translation Society
361 Prome Road, Rangoon.
CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa
Ont. (S 3.00).
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd, Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 2-44, Co¬
lombo, 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co, Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Talpeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Librería Económica, Pte Zayas
5 05-7, Apartado 113, Havana. (2.25 pesos)
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia Ltd., 30
Ve Smeckách, Prague 2.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard, A/S
Tidsskriftafdelingen, 6 Nórregade, Koben-
havn K. (D.kr. 12).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agen¬
cy, P.O. Box 120, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (F.mk. 540).
FRANCE. Unesco Bookshop, Place de
Fontenoy. Paris. T. C.C.P. 12598-48.
(7 NF.).
GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier,
Vertrieb Bahrenfelder-Chaussee 160,
Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, C.C.P. 276650
(DM 8). Other Publications: R. Older-
burg, Verlag, Rosenheimerstr. 145, Munich
GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kaufímann, 28,
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25.
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Kultura, P.O. Box 149.
Budapest, 62.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd. Indian
Mercantile Chamber. Nicol Road. Bombay
I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13;
Gunfoundry Road, Hyderabad, I; 36a,
Mount Road, Madras 2; Kanson House,
24/1 Asaf Ali Road, P.O. Box 386, New
Delhi, I ; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book &
Stationery Co., 17 Park Street Calcutta 16,
Scindia House, New Delhi. (Rs. 6.70).
INDONESIA. Bappit Pusat "Permata",
Djalan Nusantara 22, Djakarta.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The National Press, 2, Wel¬
lington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-).
ISRAEL. Btumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
35, Allenby Road and 48, Nahlat Benja¬
min Streec, Tel-Aviv (l£ 4.-).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.( I 0/-)
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo. (Yen 500).
JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road, P.O.B. 66,
Amman.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul.
LIBERIA. ). Momolu Kamara, 69, Front
and Gurley Streets, Monrovia.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück,
22, Grand-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications
Ltd., Times House, River Valley Rd.,
Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta. ( I 0/-).
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd.
30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis.
MONACO. British Library. 30 Bid des
Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (7 NF).
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff. Lange Voorhout. 9, The Hague, (fl 6)
NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES.
G. CT. Van Dorp & C- (Ned Ant.) N.V.
Willemstad, Curacao.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church. (10/-).
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos. (10/-).
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille Gren-
sen,7, Oslo. (N. kr. 13.20).
PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing
Co, Ltd., Unesco Publications House,
P.O. Box 374. 56-N Gulberg Industrial
Colony, Lahore.
PANAMA. Cultural Panameña, Avenida
7a, No. TI-49, Apartado de Correos 20 I 8,
Panama, D.F. (Balboas 3.-).
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc. 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo, P.O. Box
620. Manila.
POLAND. "RUCH" ul. Wiloia Nr. 46,
Warsaw. 10 (Zl. 50).
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada Lda,
Livraria Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70,
Lisbon,
RHODESIA & NYASALAND. The
Book Centre, First Street, Salisbury,
Southern Rhodesia.
SWEDEN. For The Unesco Courier: Sven-
ska Uncscoradet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 7.50); other publications
A/B CE. Frities. Kungl. Hovbokhandol,
Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Ramistraise, Zurich.
Payot. 40, rue du Marche, Geneva. C.C.P.
1-236.
"Courier" only: Georges Losmaz, I, rue
des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CCP.
1-481 I. (Fr. S. 8).
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Isti-
klal Caddesi. Beyoglu, Istanbul.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Street, Pretoria. ( I 0/-).
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT).
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha,
Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 5 69, London, S.E.I.( I 0/-).
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22. N.Y. ($ 5.00.) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York. 27, N.Y.
U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjlga,
Terazija 27/1 I. Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
//v
» ^a
»
mtm
^::-:. ' &*.?, 3
*.*:.
act
«a
Tf-"
P ] l|
*.
1 > *
» fM
J 1
5 r* " e. a "a" ra^mß w m*. a r33 a, a : ,.,
aT*A ° fc* A ^i ät\ ikV" A FALSE ROSE WINDOW. Tl
|M^ |y% Jj|\ * «fXl ^^k . ^^& - Ixl ' photograph would appear to be a re
j Jhk 4|tt tfNk &KÍ- 'JKsW JH^ window from a Gothic cathedral. T
Ö
I I
'r- V, N
A FALSE ROSE I . This
t l t o
window fro a othic cathedral. Th
exterior frame is indeed that of one
of the famous windows of Notre Dame
Cathedral, Paris, but the centre sec¬
tion has been replaced by a micro-
photograph of a tiny sea plant (a
diatom, Lepidodiscus elegans) not
more than one-six-hundred-and-for-
tieths of an inch in diameter. It not
only fits perfectly into the window
but is astonishingly similar to the
original design. See "Microphotogra¬
phy Reveals the Invisible World", p. 20.
Photo <; L.-J. Laporte and P. Lefcbure, Paris
]]>
</page>
</document>
