<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="064074eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
A WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
*<"ju
^^s^""^^«. A it / IK u u it wren u n inc wr \j n i. u
Courier
NE 1961 (14TH YEAR) - PRICE : 1/-STG. (U.K.) - 30 CENTS (U.S.) - 0.70 NF (FRANCE)
wt
«J** LATIN
AMERICA
150 years of
independence
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Time, distance and literary endeavour have turned the gauchos of Argentina and Uruguay into glamorous,
colourful figures and, in the case of Argentina, into the epitome of a national hero. As skilled riders
and ranchers, the gauchos played an important part in the development of both countries. Their way
of life changed, however, as cattle raising became a big business and open ranges were transformed
Into wheatfields and pastures for a more domesticated kind of cattle than the swift, lean animals of the
wild pampas. Argentine writers and musicians have found rich material in gaucho tunes and legends.
Ç Paul Almasy, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier JUNE 1961
14TH YEAR
Contents
No. 6
PUBLISHED IN
EIGHT EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
American
Japanese
COVER PHOTO
These twin figures standing
guard before the Court of Jus¬
tice of the world's newest ca¬
pital, Brasilia, symbolize the
new upsurge of Latin America
as a whole. Capital of the
continent's largest nation,
Brasilia sprang up in less than
five years from a deserted
plateau In Brazil's interior.
(See centre page)
© Paul Almasy, Paris
Page
SPECIAL ISSUE
Latin America 150 years of independence
5 PRELUDE TO INDEPENDENCE
by German Arciniegas
10 THE REVOLT WHICH SWEPT A CONTINENT
by Mariano Picon-Salas
14 THESE MEN LIBERATED LATIN AMERICA
I 9 MODERN ARCHITECTURE : TRIUMPH OF LATIN AMERICA
by Enrique Mindlin
22 BRASILIA
Newest capital in the world
24 THE CHANGING FACE OF LATIN AMERICA
by Alfred Métraux
33 70 MILLION ILLITERATES
by Oscar Vera
36 MEN OF THE LAND
Latin America's pressing agrarian problems
by Tibor Mende
41 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
42 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
(MC, 61. 1. 159 A)
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational,
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7', France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
Gordon Behrens
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani (Moscow;
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Amin Chaker (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Scientific and Cultural
THE UNESCO COURIER ¡i published monthly, except in July and August when
it is bi-monthly ( I I issues a year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German
Arabic and Japanese. In the Umced Kingdom it is distributed by H. M
Stationery Office, P. O. Box 5 69. London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted Irom THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Unetco Courier if indexed monthly in The Readera' Guide to
Periodical Literature published by H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates: U. S. S 3.00; IO/-stg. ; 7.00
New Francs or equivalent. Single copies l/-stg. 30
cents (U.S.) ; 0.70 New Francs.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Havana
(HONDURAS
"Belize
.HONDURAS
ealpa
HAITI DOMINICAN
JAMAICA "¿^PUBLIC
K/n?îton au-Prince
udad Trujillo
GUADELOUPE
cs
MARTINIQUE
VENEZUELA
N&TftERLANDS
1'GuHna
i » >a
|t is a remarkable fact of history that all of the countries of
Spanish and Portuguese speaking America achieved national
independence between the years 1811 and 1830, with the
exception of the Dominican Republic (1844), Cuba (1898)
and Panama (1903). On the occasion of the 150th anniversary
of this great struggle for freedom, The Unesco Courier
is proud to devote an entire special issue to the lands and
people of Hispano-America.
With its dramatic contrasts in geography, climate, ways of
life, races and cultures, the world of Latin America offers
us a vast and varied mosaic. The Unesco Courier has
attempted to open a small window on this part of the worldits
past history, some of its current problems, and the enormous
strides it has been making for its future development.
To produce this issue, The Unesco Courier has had the
help and guidance of the countries and Unesco Nationa
Commissions of this vast continent, and sent its photographic
reporter, Paul Almasy, on a 32,000 kilometre journey across
Latin America, from Ciudad Juarez on Mexico's northern
frontier, to Punta Arenas at the extreme southern tip of the
hemisphere. The University City of Mexico, the historical
sites of the ancient civilizations of the Aztecs and Mayas,
various scientific institutions in Central and South America,
the High Plateau of the Andes, the great industrial towns
of Argentina and the pampas are some of the important
phases of Mr. Almasy's voyage. Throughout his trip,
Mr. Almasy paid particular attention to achievements in
architecturea domain in which Latin America stands in
the forefront of progress, to the problems of agrarian reform
and to the broad field of education ranging from the struggle
against illiteracy to advanced scientific education. Only a
portion of his photo coverage is presented in this special
number. Other photo stories will appear in future issues.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1961
PRELUDE TO INDEPENDENCE
-*
^
Paramaribo
Cayenne
<
GUIANA Y
1>
O
O
o
THE PEN BEFORE
THE SWORD
by German Arciniegas
Jhlrty years before Jean-Jacques Rousseau
wrote his Social Contract, José de Antequera
and Fernando Mompox, two Panamanian criollos (des¬
cendants of the original Spanish settlers) living in
Asunción, Paraguay, set down the fundamentals of a
doctrine of human rights which was a forerunner of
Rousseau's.
"The people have the right to oppose a ruler who docs
not act ex aequo et bono (according to what ls Just and
good)," wrote Antequera. "Not all his commands must
necessarily be obeyed. Defending this right, the various
peoples have created and commissioned councils to speak
in their name."
His colleague, Mompox, continued by writing that the
power of the people (común) of any state, city, town
or village is greater than that of the king himself. It
rests with the people to have the laws or the governor of
their choice. "Even though the ruler so decrees, if it be
against the will of the people, they may justly resist and
cease to obey."
We might wonder how much such theories had pene¬
trated the minds of ordinary people in the Paraguay of
that day. One historian, Father Lozano, provides us
with an insight in recounting the history of the wars of
the comuneros or early patriots In Paraguay. He tells
of a country worker who had heard Antequcra speak.
Later he returned to his own village and repeated the
story to the peasants.
"By heaven, brothers, what wonderful things I heard
the learned man in town say about the power of the
people. He said they could do more than the king, and
sometimes more than the Pope. So you see, brothers,
how strong we were and never knew it. We know now
that they kept quiet because they didn't want us to know
that the people could just stop obeying the viceroy."
Antequera was eventually defeated at Asunción by
authorities loyal to the crown, but five years later, in
1725, a new movement against the evils of mlsgovernment
sprang up, thanks to the efforts of Mompox.
Of this movement, the historian Lozano relates one in¬
cident. A militia of the comuneros entered a town and
the "chief of police came out on the balcony to exhort
them to withdraw and return to their homes in orderly
fashion."
A voice from the crowd interrupted him. "Señor Pro-
visor, what is the meaning of Vox Populi Vox Dei? You
may answer what you will, but we want you to know that
we, gathered here, are the people!"
Later when the writings of Rousseau appeared, they
attracted immediate attention in the Spanish colonies in
America. A sympathetic attitude on the part of the
ministers of Charles III aided their circulation. Under
the system of "enlightened despotism" the writings of
the authors of the Encyclopaedia were received and distri¬
buted in Spain.
Ships of the Guipuzcoan Company which sailed regu¬
larly from the Basque country to Venezuela carrying
French literature and returning with cocoa came to be
known as "the ships of enlightenment." Smuggling was
the method by which such literature reached the colo¬
nists once the "enlightened" ships docked.
Publications in Mexico began discussing the works of
CONT'D ON PAGE 7
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
COLOMBIA SALUTES
COLUMBUS
Twin obelisks tower above figures of Chris¬
topher Columbus and Queen Isabella of
Spain in this striking modern monument in
Bogota, the capital of Colombia, raised (by the
people to honour the navigator who disco¬
vered the New World, and his royal patron.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
PRELUDE TO INDEPENDENCE (Cont'd)
The Unesco Courier. June 1961
THE 'ENLIGHTENMENT' CROSSES THE ATLANTIC
Rousseau almost at the same time as publications in his
native France certainly long before such commentaries
appeared in Spain. It is recorded that the Bishop of
Trujillo in Peru quoted from Rousseau's Social Contract
in explaining the relations between the ruler and the
Indian people. The Contract was published both in Chu-
quisaca and Buenos Aires by Belgrano. In Venezuela,
readings from Rousseau were used by Picornell to instruct
the conspirators of La Guaira. According to one historian,
so many copies of Rousseau's books were received from
Trinidad that pages of Le Contrat Social were being used
in Cumana in 1807 to wrap up food in the shops.
The war of independence was not just the fruit of mili¬
tary imagination in the Spanish colonies. It had been pre¬
ceded by a revolution of "enlightenment", and even
before that by the development of a popular conscience.
Its full force was felt in the Paraguayan revolutions, in
the Tupac Amaru uprising in Peru, among the comuneros
of New Granada all during the 18th century.
F iNALLY there came the resort to arms by
forces composed of criollos, Indians, Negroes
and half-castes. Between 1809 and 1810 all the colonies
rose in armed revolt. It was the last chapter of a move¬
ment which had been developing for forty years. In¬
dependence was first a popular idea. Later it was
accepted by the era of "Enlightenment." In its final form
it became an armed expression of Romanticism.
The armed revolts came after two and a half centuries
of peace, an almost unbelievable record by comparison
with Europe during the same period. As the idea of self-
government began to take shape, there were risings of
the settlers, the Indians, and in some cases the Negroes,
against misgovernment. It was a note of warning, a
prelude to the final movement for emancipation.
A new study of the true situation in America was ini¬
tiated under the auspices of both the university reform
movement of the 18th century and its contemporary
counterpart instituted in Spain by the Ministers of
EnlightenmentJovellanos, Campomanes and Florida-
blanca.
The expulsion of the Jesuits from the Spanish colonies
accelerated this movement. As the Jesuit Fathers left,
colonial authorities were compelled to take over their
empty colleges. New curricula were drawn up and for
the first time, physical and natural sciences were given
unexpected pride of place in all academic syllabuses.
Within the Church itself, eminent figures supported the
new policy. The most severe criticism of the old curri¬
cula came from Archbishop-Viceroy Caballero y Gongora
in New Granada. In sponsoring the reform of university
studies he gave the following explanation:
"The whole object of the plan is to teach the exact
sciences in place of the merely speculative, upon which,
unfortunately, time has been wasted hitherto."
Again in New Granada, it was a priest, José
Celestino Entis, a doctor of the University of
Seville, who founded a Botanical Mission, later to become
a Natural Science laboratory. In 1764, Entis had to face
the Court of the Inquisition at Santa Fé, Bogotá, for
teaching the theory, never before expounded, that the
earth revolved round the sun. A bold reformer, he even
brought out a mission of Swedish Protestant miners to
transform the old mineral works in New Granada.
There are two outstanding works which tell of the
circumstances in which scholarly creóles worked to pre¬
pare the way for independence: the Memorias Secretas,
by the Spaniards, Jorge Juan and Antonio Ulloa, and the
writings of Alexander von Humboldt.
Jorge Juan and Antonio Ulloa made a penetrating and
detailed report to the Crown giving the facts about mis-
government, the abuses of the magistrates (corregidores)
and doctrinaire priests, the deficiencies in education, the
state of the roads, and local customs and economy.
Humboldt presented a grandiose picture of the natural
wealth of Mexico and Equatorial America, showed n
passionate interest in its historical problems, encouraged
creóle scholars, and made the second discovery of the
New World.
"Enlightened despotism" authorized Humboldt to make
his journey to the colonies, and it also allowed scholars
from other European countries to travel there. The Paris
Academy of Science was thus able to organize a great
expedition, led by three of its members, Louis Godin des
Odonnais, Pierre Bougner and Charles Marie de La Conda-
mine. Its Immediate purpose was to check the exact
measurements of a degree along the Equator. The result
of this expedition was to arouse new ambitions in a
colony already predisposed towards emancipation.
An Italian navigator, Alessandro Malasplna, received
definite support from the Spanish Crown for an ambitious
plan to make a hydrographie exploration of the rivers
and sea-coast of the whole of Spanish America, check
the level of the two oceans, study the botany and zoology
and report on social conditions.
The Government of Charles III not only opened the
doors of the Colonies for the first time to study by
Europeans, but also tried to sec that Spanish students
or scholars were Included in the scientific missions. At
the same time they made preparations for expeditions
of their own. In New Granada, Mutis set up the
Botanical Mission while in Peru and Ecuador the
botanists, José Pavón and Hipólito Ruiz, were the authors
of the best known works on the cinchona tree.
Humboldt was surprised to find university movements
in all the colonies he visited. In Mexico he admired Don
Joaquin Velasquez, who had built the Santa Ana Obser¬
vatory himself and made his own instruments. Velasquez's
precise calculations astonished the learned German, the
French Abbé, Chappe, and the Spanish astronomers, Doz
and Medina. The astronomer had drawn his knowledge
not only from European science but also from that of the
Indians, particularly the Aztec scholar, Manuel Asentzio.
The Mexican Mining School which they visited
was a study and research centre, with a labor¬
atory, a museum and science rooms better than could be
found in Spain. In Venezuela, Humboldt had discussions
with Don André Bella, who was later to organize the juri¬
dical systems of the Republics which had won their in¬
dependence from Spain. In New Granada, Humboldt was
amazed by the knowledge of the scientists at the Botanical
Mission, prominent among whom was Francisco José de
Caldas, the most scholarly man In Spanish America,
passionately Interested In mathematical research and
natural science. This great educator's life ended
abruptly in 1816 when he was shot by the "pacifying
forces" during the time of the "Reconquest." It was the
independence movement's darkest hour.
In Quito, scholars who had inherited the teachings of
La Condamine, continued their scientific and political
research. Eventually, one of them, a priest named Miguel
Rodriguez, translated the Declaration of the Rights of
Man, the "Ten Commandments" of the French Revolu¬
tion, following in the footsteps of Narino In Bogotá, who
had already translated it, and Picornell who had publi¬
cized it in Venezuela.
Quito also produced Eugenio Espejo, a revolutionary
doctor and satiric journalist, who not only criticized the
rhetorical metaphysicians but also devoted himself to the
study of epidemics and protection from them.
Among the great scholars of Peru, Don Pablo Olavido
is a famous figure. Olavido went to Spain and took a
leading part in prompting the reforms carried out under
Jovellanos. In Chuquisca (Peru) and Cordoba (Argentina)
the writings of the Encyclopaedists were well known.
The O'Higgins family in Chile was the product of a
similar background. In Uruguay, Artigas was formulating
basic democratic doctrines during the years of the Inde¬
pendence movement. It is surprising that men were found
in these remote settings who were familiar with the
essence of a political philosophy which in Europe had not
yet toppled a single monarch from his throne.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
ORNATELY CARVED PILLARS adorn façade of the church of St Francis in La Paz, Bolivia. Outstanding feature of architecture in
Spanish America during the 16th, 17th and 18th centuries was the number, quality and character of the religious buildings that rose
through the co-operation between monks and Indian craftsmen and artists. Indian motifs figure among carvings on church above.
The awakening of the press in Spanish America is yet
another instance which contributes to our understanding
of this drive towards emancipation. Here again there were
links between Spain and America. The most important of
these, deserving a whole study in itself, was a certain
gazette, El espíritu de los Mejores Diarios, published in
Madrid, about the time of the French Revolution. It
was an abridged selection of the best articles from the
main periodicals of the world, on science, history, politics
and letters.
Charles Ill's Ministers, who were anxious to bring
enlightenment to Spain, inadvertently let in a flood of
Information that was to open up new horizons for those
engaged in the struggle for democracy, both in Madrid
and in Spanish America. It was through this publication
that Spanish Americans became acquainted with what
they called the philosophy of Philadelphia, received clear
and concise accounts of the revolt of the North American
Colonies and were aware of those developments which
in Paris were to lead to the storming of the Bastille.
Collections of this little review are still to be found in
Spanish American towns, carefully bound and preserved
in libraries as treasures of great value. Small publications
on similar lines began to appear in Mexico, Guatemala,
Caracas, Bogotá, Quito, Lima and Buenos Aires. In some
cases Mexico for example they pre-dated the Spanish
gazette. As the new trend gained momentum, studies of
Spanish American problems began to appear in the form
of small articles, cleverly drafted in order to avoid risk of
censorship. They were mild at first but they increased in
harshness as the Crown authorities became aware that
they had opened a breach which was destined to enlarge
itself until the full tumult of revolution engulfed the
entire continent.
On a par with such publications were the Sociedades de
Amigos del Pais (Societies of Friends of the Country).
These societies first existed in Spain, the earliest being the
Sociedad Guipuzcoana in the Basque country, which later
set up business in Venezuela.
At Vergara, where they were first founded, they took
the form of very small academies of science where experi¬
ments were carried out in chemistry, physics and the
social sciences.
For the first time, countries were studied in the light
of possible economic revolutions. As models the Spanish
American Colonies could not have been better, for pro¬
duction there had not yet been developed, a failing already
criticized by Jorge Juan, Antonio Ulloa and Humboldt.
The idea of forming such societies spread from Vene¬
zuela to almost all the other Spanish American countries.
Perhaps the most important work of Eugenio Espejo,
written in Bogotá and published in instalments in Las
Primicias de Quito, is the one referring to the foundation
of one of these societies. This publication alone would be
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
BAROQUE PALACE, shown here, adjoins Cathedral in the Plaza de Armas, the vast central square of Lima, Peru. Façade has
twin wooden 18th century balconies with rich Baroque designs. Spanish American architecture left monuments of great beauty as
it underwent Renaissance and Baroque influences and finally developed into the striking ultra Baroque style of the 18th century.
enough to place Espejo among the heralds of the new
revolutionary times in his country.
El Papel Periódico of Santa Fé published articles about
the Sociedades de Amigos del Pais similar to that published
in Quito. In Havana the movement was of such impor¬
tance that it continued into our own times. The far-
reaching influence of these societies may be judged by
the fact that not long ago, when a survey of the economic
life of Colombia was to be made, the Society was revived
after more than 150 years which is the highest tribute
that could be paid to the memory of those early patriots.
If we examine Spanish America before Independence
with this background in mind, we can see that the ardent
intellectual movement which preceded independence and
was intensely active over a period of forty years was
not merely the product of an intellectual unrest but the
result of existing economic and human circumstances.
These circumstances were studied so earnestly and
thoroughly at the time that the roots of the Spanish
American revolt can best be found in contemporary
writings.
Obviously they received stimulus from the revolutionary
ideas introduced by the "Enlightenment", but the main
impetus came from the study of actual local conditions,
which in its turn led to the birth of what might be
called a patriotic sensitivity.
Certain decisive actions, such as the experiment of
opening the ports to European trade, were a revelation
to theorists in merchant shipping. Under the magic power
of this stimulus, Buenos Aires acquired for Itself not
merely an Independent existence, but also a place In the
international world. The whole of Spanish America began
to realize that the traditional monopoly exercised by
Spain was an obstacle which it must remove either by
reason or by force.
To students of Spanish-American history, this period of
formation, awakening and enlightenment is perhaps more
attractive than the war which followed. It is to those
years, throbbing with the revolutionary spirit, that we
must turn in order to discover the real beginnings of the
republics. It is that period which explains the appearance
of the first libertadores Francisco Miranda, Antonio
Narino, Mariano Moreno, Fray Servando Teresa de Mler,
and any and all throughout the colonies who sought first
to mobilize minds before calling out troops.
German Arciniegas is one of Latin America's leading historians and
thinkers. Through his many books in translation, he has intro¬
duced Latin American history and present-day social conditions to
the English-speaking world. Among his works in English are: The
State of Latin America, Caribbean: Sea of the New World and
Green Continent, an anthology of works by leading Latin-American
writers which he edited. He is co-author of the Unesco book,
Freedom and Culture (out of print).
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
10.
THE REVOLT
WHICH SWEPT
ACROSS
A CONTINENT
by Mariano Picon-Salas
Tíhe War of Independence of Spanish America
Ls one of the world's great movements of
historical change. It began in 1810 and continued for
fourteen years until 1824 with the victory of the
insurgents over the Spanish crown. Like all great
movements of its kind, the Spanish-American Revolution
reflected the spirit of its timein this case liberalism
and democratic representationand was a rallying
ground for the aspirations and isolated movements
which were springing up everywhere in the . vast
conglomeration which was then the Spanish colonial
empire of the New World.
Both the War of Independence of the United States
in 1776 and the French Revolution in 1789, which served
as an inspiration for the men of the Spanish-American
Revolution, had dealt telling blows to the great monar¬
chies and dynasties of the "Old Regime". With them
were born a new spirit and a new era marked by the
will of the people, which was to find expression in a new
form of political structure.
Spain's colonies in America had by that time grown
too big and unwieldy. They stretched for thousands of
miles across the face of a continent, from the broad
grasslands of California in North America to the southern¬
most limits of Chile and Argentina in South America.
Economically, however, the inhabitants considered them¬
selves minimized by the trade monopoly or "closed market"
imposed upon them by their mother country, Spain,
which prevented them from engaging in free trade at
the very time that the growing economy of Europe was
crying for more raw materials and foodstuffs from the
colonies.
The most far-sighted of the Spanish-Americans also
considered that it was imperative to win independence
before other nations more powerful than Spain embarked
on Imperialistic ventures on the American continent.
And then the Napoleonic Wars broke out in
Europe. In 1808, Napoleon Bonaparte drove
Ferdinand VII off the throne of Spain and replaced him
with his own brother, Joseph. This produced violent
reactions throughout Spanish America.
In April and May 1810, Venezuelan and Argentine revo¬
lutionists overthrew Joseph's Vice-Roy in Buenos Aires
and the Captain-General of Caracas and swore
allegiance to Ferdinand. Everywhere the rumblings of
revolt could be heard. By June of the same year, it
was enough for a village priest like Miguel Hidalgo of
Mexico to begin tolling the church bells as a call to the
population or for a group of youths to throw themselves
in the path of the Spanish military commandant of
Caracas for "open councils" to spring up in the towns
and countryside. Everywhere the unanimous cry for revolt
echoed across the land on behalf of political freedom.
To defend its rebellious colonies, Spain dispatched its
best officers and veterans of the Napoleonic campaign to
CONT'D ON PAGE 13
5Ö&
"AyTT<-i
'-" '
JBm.
WAY OF THE LIBERATORS. Between these
jagged peaks of the Andes, General San Martin's
army crossed from Argentina into Chile to join
up with the forces of General Bernardo O'Higgins.
The combined armies liberated Chile at the battles
of Chacabuco and Maipu. Signpost recalls that on
February 2, 1817, the Army's advance guard
under General Las Heras here made a night march
at a higher altitude than any other in history.
Paul Almasy, Paris
$£*&
Api
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
SENDA DEL BERMÉ^t
^ l.l ... .1
K smms Lmkmhoi . ri¡aluai«.« u «*
r\m
i ,t-i
'-***
riy \
ti
\h*
' r «
£$£££
*mjr% '
"#"_
äs*
«!»
, **'¿rí*f»4f 'o¿ff»">. \"fj ' v^- »,
í¿*2
*>'
15* :*
&/.:
'
[*»"
«
saß
:«r«
a*
B^'
- A>i,
* y¿<.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
REVOLT OF A CONTINENT (Cont'd)
12
HEAD OF A HERO. On September I 6, I 8 I 0, the church bells of the little Mexican village of Dolores began tolling.
From all around came the people at the call of their parish priest Father Miguel Hidalgo."Will you be free >"he
asked them. "Will you fight for your land Î". Hidalgo's call sparked off a revolt in which he himself led the patriots
until his capture and execution in July 1 8 I I. Giant head, above, ¡s a monument to him at Ciudad Juarez, Mexico.
© Paul Almasy, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1961
THE LONG, ARDUOUS ROAD TO FREEDOM
the Americas. The war was to be a drawn-out, bloody
struggle.
The movement for independence revolved around many
great names: Francisco de Miranda and Simon Bolivar
of Venezuela, José de San Martin of Argentina, Bernardo
O'Higgins of Chile, and other heroic leaders. Many of
them had lived in Europe where the ideas of social change
then sweeping the Old World had filled them with inspi¬
ration. From these extensive travels and studies they
had evolved their own philosophy of state and society.
Miranda had witnessed and taken a personal
part in the North American war of in¬
dependence. He was a friend of Washington, Jefferson
and Hamilton, and was also in touch with Pitt and other
English statesmen whose support and benevolent neu¬
trality he sought for the great undertaking he dreamed
of. He took part in the French Revolution, alongside the
Girondins, and his name is engraved in stone on the Arch
of Triumph of Paris as one of the generals who gave their
service to the cause of France.
When Napoleon I was crowned emperor at Notre-Dame
in Paris in 1804, Bolivar was present in the cathedral.
His deep republicanism was shocked by what he consi¬
dered the betrayal of the great democratic heritage of
the French Revolution to the pomp and inequalities of
another empire. San Martin served his military appren¬
ticeship in Spain. In the secret lodges and societies
which he frequented during this period he had already
conceived the romantic design of rising against "servi¬
tude and tyrants".
In his fascinating memoirs, the Mexican priest, Ser¬
vando Teresa de Mier, has left us a graphic account
of the lodging houses of Madrid at the end of the 18th
and beginning of the 19th centuries. He tells us how
they served as the favourite meeting centres for hosts
of students and other youth from every corner of America,
and how from their heated discussions the ideal of
American independence took shape, how it emerged as
the common goal of the whole younger generation and
fired them with an eagerness to alter the course of
history.
In London the great centre for the independence
conspiracy was the house of Francisco de Miranda. It
was there that several of the men who were later to
rocket to fame met secretly to listen to the great Vene¬
zuelan. Among them was a youth from Chile named
Bernardo O'Higgins who was to become the chief leader
of the independence movement in his country.
BjEFORE war was to plunge them into the most
extraordinary of adventures, these men and
others as well (such as Antonio Nariño of Colombia) had
lived daringly and dangerously in their American
provinces, spreading the idea of independence and
agitating for action in intellectual circles. Those who
began their lives as students and intellectuals were soon
to find themselves military strategists and men of action
as a result of the revolution.
As is the case for all great political upheavals, powerful
oratory and individual courage and energy revealed
themselves as important factors in gaining the objectives
of the Spanish-American revolution. Many of its leaders,
like Bolivar, were writers and orators of great brilliance,
and like Caesar not only wrote accounts of their campaigns
but went into the theory of every situation they en¬
countered. And, in fact, the first to tell the story of
his life, of the momentous events, the many examples
of heroism and daring, and the first to paint a picture
of the social realities he saw in the vast lands reaching
from Venezuela to the Peruvian highlands of the Andes,
was none other than Simon Bolivar himself.
The insurgent leaders never lost sight of the high goals
they were struggling for, whether they were battling in
the scorched tropical plains near the coast or among
the frozen peaks of the Cordillera. For to them political
independence did not mean a narrow, xenophobic nation¬
alism but the free integration and participation of
America in the benefits and achievements of the Western
world. That is why even during the very height of the
campaign the Liberators never stood aloof from the
ferment of ideas of their day and followed them with
passionate Interest.
It was their common belief that the unity which had
sprung from the Spanish language and the inter-marriage
of races throughout the vast American provinces would
be maintained, and that the confederation of united
states in the north would find a counterpart in another
great United States of Spanish America in the south.
As the prophet of this unity, and once the guns were
silent and independence had been achieved, Simon Bolivar
convened the plenipotentiaries of America to a congress
in Panama. There, he thought, would be sealed for ever
the legal instruments of America's unity in an alliance
of co-operation for the democratic advancement of all
the peoples of the continent.
There is no need, here, to go into the complicated
interplay of intrigues and political interests of the Great
Powers which sealed the fate of Bolivar's great dream.
Nevertheless, even today, it stands as the most cherished
moral heritage for all Latin Americans.
Like other Latin-American leaders of the war
i of independence, Bolivar passed his later
years in a shadow, crushed by the failure of his Idea. He
died in 1830, still a relatively young man, when the new
nations of America were barely beginning to recover from
the havoc of the war and to create their civil institutions.
San Martin too returned home to Argentina to find
the country rent by conflict and anarchy. Harassed
and disillusioned he was forced to seek refuge in Europe.
He died in France in 1850.
No prominent, universally respected personality thus
remained to carry out the tremendous task of unification.
In the place of one or two large Latin American Republics
there emerged instead twenty separate states. Despite
the linguistic and spiritual tics which bound them to¬
gether, other factors geographical differences and com¬
munication barriers have managed to keep them firmly
apart.
And yet how ironical It is to think that it was during
the heroic years of the war for independence that the
national history of every one of these countries really
merged and amalgamated in one great crucible, rein¬
forcing as never before their common heritage.
The liberation movements began in 1810 at Caracas
and Buenos Aires, at the two extremes of South America.
After a long series of battles, two armies from north and
south converged in a vast pincer movement of continental
dimensions towards Lima, capital of Peru, then the
greatest centre of Spanish power in the Americas.
Simon Bolivar won the independence of New Granada
(now Colombia) at Boyacá and that of Venezuela at
Garabobo. His deputy, Antonio José de Sucre, achieved
the independence of Ecuador at the battle of Pichincha,
and with troops from the north marched towards Peru
to fight the two great battles of Junin and Ayacucho.
Meanwhile, from the south, General San Martin had
already ordered his army forward. In a remarkable
march over the snow-capped Andes, he Joined up with
O'Higgins and liberated Chile at two famous battles,
Chacabuco in 1817 and Maipu the following year. From
the Chilean coast a fleet of warships, rapidly fitted and
manned, set sail to harass the Spanish armada patrol¬
ling the Pacific.
The last battle of the war was fought on December 9,
1824, at Ayacucho, Peru. Sucre was the liberation general
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
14
REVOLT OF A CONTINENT (Cont'd)
THESE MEN FREED
LATIN AMERICA
in command and under him served troops who had joined
his forces from all over the continent. They included
plainsmen (llaneros) from Venezuela, highlanders from
New Granada, mountaineers from Ecuador and Peru,
peasants from Chile and gaucho horsemen from the Rio
de la Plata.
Mexico achieved Its independence separately
from the two South American movements
unfurling towards Peru. Hidalgo's bell-tolling call for
revolt in 1810 was eventually crushed and Hidalgo captured
and executed. But eleven years later, in 1821, Mexico
finally achieved its independence. For a short time it in¬
cluded the small states of Central America Guatemala, El
Salvador, Honduras, Nicaragua and Costa Rica. Like
South America, Central America too had its statesmen and
fighters of genius, like Francisco Morazan, who raised his
voice against isolating regionalism and the splitting up of
countries, and sought to achieve a strong Central
American land of unity.
All of these men from Mexico to the Rio de la Plata
lived extraordinary lives, and their biographies bear
witness to their deep love of liberty in the face of torture
and death. Thus, for example, the soldiers who had
set out from the steaming plains of the Orinoco valley
in Venezuela made a special detour to plant the flag
of freedom on the snow-roof of the Andes at Potosí (in
present day Bolivia) at 14,000 feet, one of the highest
towns in the world. This expedition alone took several
years and was won at the price of bitter fighting in
bitter cold, of starvation and isolation amidst a bleak,
desolate terrain. It brings to mind the daring, perilous
exploit of the Spanish Conquistadores three hundred
years earlier in the Andean Cordillera.
If one reads the books written about the liberation
period, such as the Memoirs of O'Leary, an Irish officer
who served under Bolivar, or the Autobiography of
General José Antonio Páez, or the celebrated Song of
Junin by the Ecuadorian poet José Joaquin Olmedo, one
understands why their contemporaries thought of these
exploits as an American Iliad and their protagonists as
new Homeric heroes.
And indeed, the story of how the llaneros of Bolivar
and the gauchos of San Martin left their flat prairie
lands astride half-wild horses and proceeded to scale
the highest, most vertiginous mountain peaks of the
Andes, is one of the most extraordinary episodes of world
history.
In the forbidding terrains of the vast
continent, the great generals Bolivar, San
Martin, Sucre, O'Higgins, Páez, Carrera, Santa Cruz and
others were obliged not only to devise sudden changes in
strategy and tactics but to feed and clothe the new
recruits who rallied to their cause as they advanced.
Between Buenos Aires and Lima, between Caracas and
Ayacucho the ultimate goal of the long journey lay
an arduous, painful road, beset with precipices, escarp¬
ments and volcanoes. And yet they marched and rode
on, clambering from the sandy wastes along the shores
of the Peruvian coast up into the enveloping cold of the
jagged mountains.
This was the price in heroism and sacrifice of the
unity of the American Republics which, in the words
of Ruben Darío, one of their greatest poets, "still worship
the Lord and speak Spanish".
Mariano Picon-Salas, distinguished essayist is author of many,
works, including Crisis, Cambio, Tradición (Crisis, Change and
Tradition); Suramerica (South America) and Dependencia e Inde¬
pendencia en la Historia Hispano Americana (From Conquest to
Independence in Spanish American History). He is now Vene¬
zuela's permanent delegate to Unesco.
JOSE DE SAN MARTIN (1778-
1850). The great hero, along with
Bolivar, of Latin America's indepen¬
dence. He freed his native Argentina,
and made an epic crossing of the
Andes into Chile in I 8 I 7 to liberate
the southern part of the continent.
He gave to South American youth an
unforgettable model of moral nobi¬
lity. San Martin eventually withdrew
to Europe, where he died in 1850.
wMf"
Me*-' àn
fÈff&;~
ma
JpïïM>AiA
\^mr À yy^m
BERNARDO O'HIGGINS (1778-
1842). Born in Chile, the son of an
Irish father, O'Higgins took up arms
and led partisan forces in the early
phase of the Chilean war of indepen¬
dence. He joined his forces to San
Martin's army to help liberate his
country. He became the head of the
first government of the Chilean Repu¬
blic but resigned five years later. A
Chilean province is named after him.
ANTONIO JOSE DE SUCRE
(1793-1830) won independence for
Ecuador at the battle of Pichincha
while serving as Simon Bolivar's
deputy. In July 1824, an army under
his command defeated Spanish forces
at Junin, paving the way for the libe¬
ration of Peru, finally assured by his
victory at Ayacucho. In 1825 he was
elected provisional president of the
Bolivian Republic, but resigned in 1828.
FRANCISCO DE MIRANDA
(1752-1816) was the most ardent
and eloquent advocate for the cause
of Spanish American independence
abroad. His efforts led him to the
United States, Britain, France and as
far as Turkey and Russia. Returning
to Venezuela after sjme 30 years of
exile, he led two expeditions against
the Spaniards, was captured by them
in 18 12 and died a prisoner in 1816.
JOSE MARIA MARTI (1853-
1895), the Cuban patriot, was a
journalist and poet. Twice deported
for his revolutionary ideas and acti¬
vities, he was a leading figure in the
Cuban independence movement in
exile and in the Ten Years Civil War,
from 1868 to 1878. Civil war broke
out again in 189 5. Marti took up
arms and was one of the first to fall.
Cuba achieved independence in 1898.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier, June 1961
LIVAR
THE GREAT LIBERATOR
E
<
Statesman and soldier of the revolutions which resulted
in the independence of six Latin American countries,
Simon Bolivar was born in Caracas, Venezuela, in
1783. His short life (he died when 47) was a tremendous
historical canvas of adventure and tragedy, triumph and
defeat. Prophet and would-be architect of a strong
confederation of Latin American republics following
the liberation of these lands from Spain, he failed to
realize this great aspiration. Instead there emerged
twenty separate states. But his name is universally
remembered and respected throughout the continent.
It lives on in the name Bolivia, given to a country formed
from what was formerly southeastern Peru. Bolivar was
officially invested with the title Libertador by the con¬
gresses of Venezuela, Colombia, Ecuador, Panama,
Peru and Boliviasix countries which owe the debt
of freedom to him. Towns and cities have been named
after him and great monuments, like the one shown
here at Caracas, have been raised in his honour across
Latin America. Others are shown on following pages.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
LA PAZ
LIMA
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Photos © Paul Almasy, Paris
MONUMENTS IN HIS HONOUR
ACROSS THE AMERICAS
MEXICO CITY
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
UNIVERSITY CITY. Mexico's
National University near to its
capital, is one of the architectural
landmarks of modern Latin Ame¬
rica. Inaugurated nine years ago,
the campus is a bold integration
of striking buildings, paintings,
mosaic murals, sculpture and land¬
scape planning. The university
accommodates 60,000 students.
18
O
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
s MODERN ARCHITECTURE
TRIUMPH OF LATIN AMERICA
The Unesco Courier. June 1961
by Enrique Mindlin
All modern architecture In Latin America has
stemmed from two main sources. From
Europe came the inspiration of the masters who created
the so-called International Architecture after the First
World WarLe Corbusier, Van der Rohe, Groplus, Aalto
and others. From North America came the brilliant Ideas
motivating the highly personal work of Frank Lloyd
Wright.
Yet in Latin America it did not follow the same lines as
in Europe or the United States. In most Latin-American
countries, the impact of the new architecture imported
from abroad by a few "avant-garde" architects was
forceful and fruitful because It was generally enhanced by
concurrent movements of cultural nationalism.
Although modern architecture In Latin America began,
in a way, as an Import from abroad, it soon acquired a
motivation of its own, a fighting quality and a banner-
bearing approach which finally found its particular
expression in every Latin American country. The kind of
"missionary" touch marking most early work in this part
of the world ls a parallel to the idealistic striving for a
better and happier existence which fed the countless
political uprisings in the hemisphere and the Innumerable
developments in art and literature.
Architecture was thus given a deeper meaning as an
indispensable part in the building up of the young na¬
tions of the New World. It was thus led along special
paths in whatever direction this striving towards a kind
of Utopia was most strongly felt. The impact of plastic
forms created an emotional quality which became often
more important than the functional or economic aspects.
Broadly speaking, modern architecture In Latin
America may be said to have played a greater role actually
expressing ideals and aspirations of the people than in
effectively solving, in one way or another, Its day-to-day
problems. Economic conditions in most Latin American
countries make this almost inevitable. When so much Is
still to be done, stimulating courage and determination
and "keeping lit the sacred flame" may be Just as nec¬
essary as doggedly pursuing the rather meagre practical
results which are all that can be hoped for at present.
Among the striking examples found in many countries
are the ambitious and Impressive "University Cities".
Throughout Latin America everyone feels strongly and
definitely that illiteracy must be wiped out. Yet no one
asserts that in order to achieve this goal, less effort should
be expended in trying to reach the summit of academic
development. Architecturally, the happy results of this
typical Latin American attitude are magnificent works like
the university cities of Mexico, Caracas and Rio de Janeiro.
The same idealistic approach is found in public housing.
Although national resources make sweeping solutions to
the problem of housing the underprivileged classes out of
the question, in most Latin American countries one finds
alongside the rather cheap and drab workers' housing
areas, buildings which belong in a much better world.
Handsomely integrated housing areas in Santiago, Lima,
Caracas, Mexico City, and Rio de Janeiro underscore the
valid possibilities of creating, architecturally, community
dwellings of a truly humane social character.
A constant undercurrent In Latin American archi-
19
CONT'D ON PAGE 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
/ f %>
Paul Almasy, Paris
CAMPUS CONTRASTS are shown in these views of two Latin
American universities. Above, Indian style designs blend happily with
modern architecture on facade of University of Mexico Library. On
right, students cross University's 1,000 ft. long campus. Building in
rear is part of the Science Faculty. A team of I 56 architects and
Mexico's leading painters, sculptors and designers combined their
efforts to create this University City which cost some S 50 million.
Left, ladder-like clock tower at Caracas University. Below, exterior
and interior aspects of the new Caracas University auditorium.
Suspended ceiling decorations were designed by Alexander Calder.
L'Architecture d'Aujourd'hui, Paris
E
<
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
TRIUMPH OF ARCHITECTURE (Cont'd;
AN ART AS MUCH AS
A NEW TECHNIQUE
tectural thinking ls the Idealistic formulation of
problems coupled with an almost single-minded devotion
to artistic perfection. Today, it has found Its most
dramatic and far-reaching expression in the creation of
Brasilia, the new capital city of Brazil. (See pages 22/23.)
Where others might have started with a small civic
centre, with sensible temporary quarters and with
commonplace pre-fabrlcated dwellings, the builders of
Brasilia decided that an exactly opposite approach was
the only possible answer. They felt that nothing less than
the daring vision of a perfect capital city could capture
the imagination of the Brazilian people and command
its support in the herculean efforts required to complete
the building of this metropolis In record time.
Building Brasilia did, In fact, put a heavy strain on the
economy of the country, but It also catalyzed with mag¬
netic power the will of the people, tapping Its dormant
potentialities to a degree unprecedented in the history of
Brazil. Through this capital, risen as If by magic from
the bare ground, fundamentals in architecture and city
planning were brought home to the man-in-the-strcet as
never before, creating among formerly Indifferent people
a new awareness of artistic standards and Ideals.
I have already said that a certain feeling of kinship
uniting much of the continent's modern architecture also
reaches Into apparently typical and characteristic
differences from one country to another. The reason for
this seems to originate, once more, in the distinctive Latin-
American vision of architecture as, first and foremost, an
art and not merely a deeply complex technique. Regional
differences in basic conditions are therefore not approach¬
ed by architects with the exclusive idea of finding
satisfactory answers to strictly functional problems. They
use these same conditions as so many excuses or sources
of Inspiration to advance into the higher levels of
architectural expression.
One example ls the modern "brlse-solell," a
device designed to protect parts of a building
against overexposure to the burning tropical sunlight,
which quickly became just as important as a means of
creating rich textual patterns and pleasant modulations of
light and shade in the architectural composition.
The need to reduce the effect of excessive rain or dust
on outside walls led to many kinds of ceramic surface
treatments which in turn brought about a characteristic
development of mural compositions. The azulejos of Brazil
(blue and white glazed tiles which echo the Colonial tra¬
dition), the multicoloured glass or tile murals typical of
Mexico, Venezuela or Brazil, and similar types of wall
surfacing stress a basic identity In architectural thinking.
Yet these too, through a varied approach to colour and
subject and the relative Importance given to them in the
overall design, emphasize regional differences, in terms of
climatic conditions and in artistic outlook and purpose.
There would be much to say about the most important
works of today's architecture in Latin American countries.
Briefly, it must at least be affirmed that Its works already
make a definite contribution to modern civilization.
We must remember too that these accomplishments
have been made against tremendous obstacles of all kinds,
far more so than in any other part of the Western World.
Now that these obstacles are being gradually removed by
mass education, by economic and Industrial development
and by the ever-growing need to face the challenges to
architecture inherent in modern life, architecture in Latin
America will develop at an even faster pace.
If, in the process, its characteristic strains of idealism,
lyricism and artistic endeavour are preserved, then this
same architecture is destined to make a growing interna¬
tional impact, offering its own particular gift for har¬
monizing daring reality with the vision of a better world
Enrique Mindlin is one of the leading architects of Latin America.
Born in Brazil, heis the author of Modern Architecture in Brazil
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
22
Brasilia, the new capital of Brazil, is the first
large city of the world conceived entirely
according to the principles of abstract archi¬
tecture. But it is more than a marvel of
modern architecture, a skyscraper city sprung,
in less than five years, from a desert plateau
in the interior. It is an act of faith, of the
determined pioneering spirit of a people bent
on conquering its untapped lands and esta¬
blishing a new Brazil of the 20th century.
In the words of former president Juscelino
Kubitschek, who built Brasilia: "In the world's
fifth largest country enormous fertile lands
are as empty as the Sahara, while millions of
Brazilians cling to the crowded shoreline."
Above left, Brasilia's cathedral during cons¬
truction. Its 16 concrete pillars, 130 ft. high,
form a circle 220 ft. across. Great sheets of
tinted, sun-filter glass fitted between them
will form the cathedral "walls". Left, several
of the ten-storey ministry buildings. In fore¬
ground is part of bowl-shaped Chamber of
Deputies. Above right, Government Centre,
known as the Plaza of.jhe Three Powers, with
dome-shaped Senate (lip), Chamber of Depu¬
ties (right) and twin skyscrapers for congres¬
sional offices. Right, stóie offices as seen from
between wing-shaped Columns of presidential
office building. Tapered columns are used in
various arrangements to unify design of key
public buildings. Brazil's first capital from
1549 to 1763 was Bahia on the north-east
coast. Afterwards Rio de Janeiro became the
seat of government, it remained so for the
rest of the colonial period, during the achie¬
vement of independence (In 1822), and
throughout the Brazilian empire and the
republic which succeeded it. The transfer of
the capital to Brasilia last year opened a new
era in the history of the largest and most
populous of the South-American countries.
Photos © Paul Almasy, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
THE CHANGING
FACE OF
LATIN AMERICA
by Dr Alfred Métraux
I t has become commonplace to speak of Latin
America as a land of contrasts and to
compare its strikingly modern aspects with its archaic
rural life. Some years ago, André Siegfried wisely observ¬
ed that the cities of Latin America were still not Integrated
Into the surrounding country-side. Indeed, it would often
seem that they are islands of civilization encompassed by
vast wildernesses which deny the very presence of man.
Just a few miles from Lima, for example, one finds a
desert as formidable as the Sahara. Not far from Rio de
Janeiro vestiges of the dense tropical forests still remain
which are as isolated from the world as the heart of the
Amazon. It ls contrasts such as these which proclaim
Latin America as a "new" land.
Yet, it is also a very ancient land. Long before the
white man set foot on these shores, great cities had been
built. Within walking distance of Trujillo on the
Peruvian coast lie the remains of a great metropolis
(Chanchan) whose ruins cover six square miles and show
regularly spaced streets and squares which compare with
our great modern cities. A short bus ride away from
Mexico City rise the great pyramids of Teotihuacan and
the ruins of another large city, both far older than the
gigantic modern capital of Mexico today.
But we need not return to the time of the Incas and
Aztecs to find the past in Latin America. The little
provincial towns of Peru, Guatemala and even Argentina
provide us with a picture of Old Spain more faithful than
one can find in many cities of the mother country. Vast
areas of Latin America have preserved the feeling of
18th and 19th century Europe virtually intact. Not only
the settings are there unchanged, but so too are many of
the attitudes, customs and festivals of the people. Even
today, tales of mediaeval chivalry are still read en¬
thusiastically in small provincial towns, and Charlemagne
and the twelve peers of his kingdom are familiar figures to
the village folk of rural Brazil.
It is easy to understand that many Latin-Americans
show annoyance when visitors concentrate all their
interest on the vestiges of the past and describe with
such great relish the customs of bygone days. For Latin-
Americans are very proud, and well they may be, of their
great modern cities which stand as testimony to their
determination to build a new world civilization. Does not
Rio de Janeiro, and even more so the new capital city of
Brasilia, give a glimpse of the world of tomorrow? In
Caracas, Mexico City or Rio, the visitor coming from
CONT'D ON PAGE 26
SKYSCRAPER SKYLINE In centre of Bogotá is symbolic of Colombia's
rapid modernization and industrial development. Founded in 1538 on the
site of the ancient Chibcha Indian capital, named Bacati, It still has narrow
cobblestone streets overhung by balconies but as is seen in this photo, taken
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
GLASS TOWER topped by TV transmitter aerial (above) looms
above turn-of-century buildings and busy street scene In the centre
of Mexico City, built In the I 6th century on the site of a lake. Though
much of Mexico's industrial potential is centred on the capital, many
aspects of the city still reflect the meeting of Spanish and Indian cultures.
SIX MILLION INHABITANTS make Buenos Aires the most popu¬
lous city In South America. From the start of the century and until
recent times, Argentina's capital was unrivalled as the Continent's
most modern and bustling metropolis. Photo shows entrance to a
station on its underground railwaythe only one In South America.
from one of the mountain slopes encircling it (Bogotá lies on an Andean plateau
8,660 feet high), towering buildings of concrete, glass and aluminium are
swiftly replacing the traditional old houses with their red-tiled roofs and iron-
barred windows. Colombia's National University was founded here in I 572.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
CHANGING FACE OF LATIN AMERICA (Cont'd)
T*S POPULATION INFLUX TO THE CITIES
Europe is overwhelmed and
bewildered. Standing amid
their bold, soaring sky¬
scrapers, he will feel that he
has suddenly not only crossed
the Atlantic but been trans¬
ported in time and space far
into the future.
These "cities of tomorrow"
are a recent phenomenon in
Latin-American life. Only
fifty years ago, her great
capitals looked to France with its dignified and opulent
18th and 19th century styles, for their inspiration. In
certain sections of Buenos Aires today, a visitor will be
reminded of the Auteull or Passy districts of Paris.
Santiago de Chile recalls Germany during the era of the
Weimar Republic. Mexico City presents an assortment of
styles ranging from Colonial Spanish and late 19th
century French to 20th century Callfornian.
However debatable some of the results of Latin-
American architecture may be, they do confirm a concern
for town planning which is often missing in many North-
American cities. Latin-American architects have made
particular efforts to relieve the chess-board monotony
of city streets with sumptuous public buildings and a
great abundance of parks and plazas.
Any consideration of the continent of Latin America
must inevitably be made in terms of her cities. Although
the economy of most of the republics is based on
agriculture, the strong urban tradition which the
Spaniards and Portuguese brought with them from the
Old World still prevails.
Since the beginning of the colonial period a sharp
division has existed between the city and rural areas.
The effect of this cleavage on the growth and develop¬
ment of the young nations has often been disastrous.
The rural areas and their inhabitants were formerly
considered to exist for the sole benefit of the cities, as
the purveyors of essential commodities and those
amenities which made life more agréable for the towns¬
folk. This explains the striking contrast that still
exists today between the cultured society of the cities
profoundly European in taste and the unpolished, often
wretched rural population.
Spain and Portugal bequeathed to their former
colonies a heavy bureaucracy and a small minority of
people who held a monopoly of land and wealth. During
the 19th century, a middle class slowly began to develop.
But it has succeeded in exerting real influence only in
the most economically advanced coun¬
tries. It is with the appearance of this
middle class that the new face of Latin
America is being moulded. The trend
has been favoured by the rise of indus¬
trialization which many Latin-Ameri¬
cans see as the solution to their mul¬
tiple problems.
In Mexico, Brazil and Argentina,
industrial development has produced a
city working class far different from
the one which existed in the days when
great landowners dominated the
political scene. A militant trade union
movement has emerged, and on every
hand governments are faced with the
same difficulties which marked in¬
dustrial development during the 19th
MOUNTAIN ROAD, twisting and turning along the slopes of the Peruvian Andes, illustrates one of many communication problems in Latin America
terrains, vast distances, immense, unpopulated regions. Five centuries ago a complex network of roads built by the Incas criss-crossed
the Andes. Some of the highways hacked out of the mountainside during this prodigious feat of construction are still in use today.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
century in Europe and elsewhere. As
a result, political antagonisms have
grown more bitter. But the rhythm of
industrialization has been so sharply
accelerated that its results are now
evident everywhere. Brazil, for example,
today manufactures its own automobiles
which can be seen streaming along the
nation's newly constructed super¬
highways
The industrial "explosion" has been
accompanied by a mass influx of
peasants to the cities. Although when
they arrive they feel out of place in
their new surroundings, it is probably
only a matter of a few years before
their whole concept of things changes.
The fact is that the isolation in which
great masses of Latin Americans once lived is now broken.
Today they have become conscious of their position and
are voicing their demands for a higher standard of living.
This change is strikingly apparent in the Andes region.
There for centuries the Indians lived in isolated
communities, refusing all contact with the towns and
cities. Today they are abandoning their former homes
and settling in the outskirts of Lima, La Paz and Quito,
where huge shantytowns have sprung up. Lima, which
was once a city made up mostly of European stock, now
counts an Indian population of half a million.
It will not be long before the consequences of this
population shift to the cities will be felt everywhere. The
Indian who learns Spanish has made a break with his
past and taken a step toward integrating himself
into the rest of the country's society. He realizes the
extent of his poverty and knows that a better life is
possible than the destitute and humiliating existence
which was formerly his lot. A similar development is
taking place in Brazil where Negro farmers are flocking
to the great industrial city of Sao Paulo in the south
to find work in the factories.
The Unesco Courier. June 1961
With these migrations an archaic way of life, yet rich
In artistic traditions, ls adding Its stamp to the traditional
modes and manners of the city. To the cities of Peru
the Indians have brought their deeply melancholy music.
Every Sunday, under great circus tents erected for the
occasion, and before a gaudily dressed throng, Indian folk
groups play the mountain tunes which until now were
practically unknown to all but a few fortunate travellers.
In Brazil, the Negro has brought to the cities his African
cults with their ecstatic dances and ritual music. From
these extraordinarily fertile sources writers, musicians and
painters are drawing rich Inspiration.
The people of Latin America dislike being lumped
together into a single homogeneous group. They take
pleasure in pointing out, even in stressing, the differences
which distinguish them. The differences, in fact, arc
very real.
On one hand there is the Andes region and the plateaux
of Central America whose populations are basically Indian
and upon which the great Indian civilizations have left
their mark. On the other, In the plains and pampas of
the far south In Argentina and Uruguay, the European
descendants have almost completely replaced the Indige¬
nous races. Elsewhere in
Latin America are the great
forests and tropical savannahs
farmed by the descendants
of Negro slaves. There, more
often than not, the country¬
side takes its character from
single crop agriculture. Every¬
where throughout Latin Ame¬
rica we come upon these
contrasts of people and
differences of terrain and
climate. Yet, a visitor im¬
mediately senses the feeling
of unity among Latin Ame¬
ricans as a whole, a feeling
which Latin Americans them¬
selves are fully conscious of.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
FARMING FAMILY on its way to market in the highlands of Colombia. Women wear distinctive feodora-like hats and shawls and the men, ponchos
or blanket-like cloaks. Colombia, fourth largest country in South America, has both Pacific and Atlantic Ocean coastlines. Most of Its people live
on the high plateaux and in the^valleys of the western highlands-three great arms of the Andes crossing the country from north to south
27
Photos '© Piul Almwy, Pirii
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
CHANGING FACE OF LATIN AMERICA (Cont'd)
CAFES AND BOOKSHOPS
This basic unity she owes to Iberian traditions which
have proved to be stronger than the diverse natural
settings and the whims of history. For three centuries,
the people of Latin America have lived the same kind
of life and shared the same traditions. From this has
come a social order and a view of the world which is
very similar among them. The Mexican and the Argentine
may be separated by thousands of miles, but they still
react much the same way under the same circumstances.
In fine nuances of expression they may differ somewhat,
but at heart they possess the same sensitivities.
It ls difficult in trying to sum up the problems
of an entire continent In a few words, not to
lose sight of the simple human realities. Life in all great
cities follows a familiar pattern and the large cities of
Latin America are no exception.
Every morning, people get up, have their breakfast,
crowd into buses or trams or get into their cars and join
the stream of automobiles making for the centre of town.
In the evening the same process is reversed when office
and factory workers return to their homes and the
business and commercial districts fall silent. People seek
relaxation and throng to the theatre; cinemas, showing
New and Old World films, are always crowded. Argentina,
Brazil and Mexico have long had a thriving cinema
industry and all over Latin America the seventh art is
coming into its own displaying new and vigorous talents.
Modern art In which many Latin American painters
and sculptors excel is extremely popular in most of the
large cities. New art galleries are opened daily, holding
vernissages and exhibitions in the true Parisian fashion.
One thing which never ceases to impress travellers is
the abundance of bookshops, their spaciousness and
modern presentation, and the huge number of people
always browsing through them. The same can be said
of the many cafés Latin America's delightful legacy from
the Mediterranean world where everyone gathers to talk
of literature, art, and especially politics, and all can find
refuge from loneliness, and take part in the pulsating
life of the city.
Any attempt to describe the artistic and intellectual
life of South America in such brief space would be im¬
possible. Except to a select few, the literary and artistic
achievements of Latin America remain a closed book.
Yet the continent has produced works of literature which
deserve a place alongside the great masterpieces of world
letters. For many people, though, names such as Sar¬
miento, Machado de Assis, Euclides da Cunha, Romulo
Gallegos, Gabriela Mistral, Ruben Dario, still draw a blank
stare. Unesco, and many private publishers, are attempt¬
ing to remedy this situation through the Latin-American
series of Translations of Representative Works (see The
Unesco Courier, June 1957), but much still needs to be
done to give Latin-American arts and letters their just
due.
P;Perhaps the most characteristic attitude of the
younger generation is a feeling which they
themselves call "Inquietud" (anxiety) and which reflects
their dissatisfaction with the state of things around
them. Dissatisfaction with the political and economic
situation, but above all with the possibilities available to
creative artists. In the absence of a substantial and cul¬
tivated middle class, the groups which can give more than
lip-service support to artists are still small in number.
Few writers or artists in Latin America are able to live
28
CONT'D ON PAGE 3 0
Arts d'aujourd'hui, Paris
MODERN SCULPTURE by Henry Laurens is one of the works by Euro¬
pean and North American artists who were asked to contribute to the deco¬
ration of the new University City at Caracas, Venezuela. Caracas itself has
been virtually rebuilt and enormously extended during the past I 5 years. It
is now a city of green spaces and striking modern architecture.
BOLD APPROACH in architecture is found in all types of buildings in
Latin America today. Less unconventional than the Cathedral of Brasilia
(see centre pages) this newly built church in Santiago de Chile is nevertheless
a magnificent example of contemporary architectural treatment. In Chile,
architects must also incorporate earthquake-proof qualities in their buildings.
Paul Almasy, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
OPEN-AIR THEATRE In Guatemala City. Mosaic figures recall ancient carvings on Pre-Columbian Mayan stelae. The theatre is
in a spacious park arranged with varied decorative elements. Close by is an unusual monument to modern industry (not shown).
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
CHANGING FACE OF LATIN AMERICA (Cont'd;
UNIVERSITIES OF ASTONISHING VITALITY
by pen or brush alone. The most striking social
characteristic of intellectual life in Latin America today
ls perhaps Its isolation. The struggle the artist and
Intellectual must wage gives their professions an intensity
and nobility of purpose which ls reminiscent of the revival
sparked by the Romantic period in early 19th century
Europe.
Writers and artists have become the self-appointed
interpreters and champions of the silent masses. Many
have launched into politics and used pen and word as
weapons. In this respect, the universities of Latin
America play an important role. They are, of course,
Influential centres in all spheres of activity but particul¬
arly so in politics. Ever since the great university reform
movement took place In Latin America in the 1920s
these institutions have resembled small states where
studies lead not only to a profession but also to an active
career in political life. It is from this that they draw
much of their astonishing vitality.
What tasks must Latin America prepare to undertake
if she is not to remain a marginal land? First and
foremost is education. She can hope for no real progress
If illiteracy continues at its present level. Civilization has
become too complex to be carried forward by men and
women who cannot read or write.
The obstacles to education are formidable. First of
all, there are the problems of the distance, Isolation and
poverty of many of her peoples. In the past, govern¬
ments have often failed to provide sufficient facilities for
the training of teachers.
The desire for education is strong throughout Latin
America, and this holds true among the Indians as well
who have often been described as "primitive." In many
parts of the Andes, in villages built at altitudes of 12,000
to 14,000 feet above sea level, the people have built schools
of their own accord and collected funds to pay the
teacher's salary. Indian villages have scraped money
together to permit a particularly gifted student to
continue his studies away from home in the hope that
he would return later with this knowledge to help his
village. For the great mass of the people education is the
one road to salvation.
These countries badly need trained executives and have
a shortage of technicians. The liberal professions, such
as medicine and law, still attract the greatest number of
students while other professions are scorned. This no
doubt is a tradition going back to colonial days, but a
change must come about, if these countries are to survive.
Education must do more than simply banish illiteracy.
A great effort in community development is needed -to
wipe out ignorance which is the greatest obstacle to
productivity. Similarly, communications and transporta¬
tion must be modernized and enlarged to free communities
from their isolated positions and make possible a more
rational system of distribution.
These transformations in Latin-American life will only
be possible when the great mass of people are no longer
condemned to a life of stagnation and when education
has fostered in them the hope for a better life. To this
task Unesco has long devoted its efforts.
Alfred Metraux is a noted anthropologist in charge of
"Human Rights" in the Department of Social Sciences of Unesco,
and is professor of South American Anthropology at the Ecole
Pratique des Hautes Etudes in Paris. Born in Switzerland, he has
travelled and worked extensively throughout Latin America. He
was former director and founder of the Ethnological Institute of
the National University of Tucuman (Argentina). One of his
major interests has long been cultural diffusion in Latin America.
He is the author of many scientific and popular works including
Easter Island (L'Ile de Pâques), Voodoo in Haiti (Le voudou
haitien), and The Black Peasants of Haiti (Haiti, la Terre et les
Hommes). His latest book, The Incas (Les Incas, Editions du
Seuil), will shortly be published.
30
STUDIOUS ARTIST attending classes in Guatemala City design
school uses articulated "Pinocchio" as model for the human figure.
INTENT SCIENTIST checks the incidence of city smog with a special
recording device placed on the roof of a building at Mexico University.
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
ENGROSSED READERS in Bogota, Colombia, pore over books in
Luis Arango Library, one of the country's most modern institutions.
FRIENDLY LIBRARIAN In San Salvador helps schoolchildren who
have come to her library for information to supplement classroom work.
RELAXED FARMER curls up with his newspaper in a Mexican village. Hammocks are widely used in towns and villages In all parts of Latin America.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
32
Elementary education is free and compulsory for children in all Latin American
countries yet some 12 million children are still without schools and through¬
out the continent there are 60 million illiterate adults (40 % of the adult popu¬
lation). In their drive to wipe out illiteracy, governments have been helped
since 19 56 by Unesco's Major Project for the Extension of Primary Education
in Latin America. Between 1956 and 1959 primary school attendance rose
by about four million and the number of teachers increased by 90,000. Above,
village women in Mexico, where Unesco helped to set up a regional Funda¬
mental Education Centre for Latin America, learn to read and write in an
improvised classroom. Right, radio school teacher's voice Is heard by thousands
of students, young and old, scattered over length and breadth of Colombia.
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1961
A CONTINENTAL CHALLENGE
70 MILLION
ILLITERATES
by Oscar Vera
D URiNG a trip to Ecuador two years ago, I visited
a little village on the shores of Lake Otvalo. It
was a Sunday but I noticed a party of Indians working
with unaccustomed vigour, carrying stones, levelling the
ground and digging out the foundations for what was
to be a school.
Three or four months later when I revisited the village,
I found that the little school was finishedbuilt by volun¬
tary labour and with some help from the authorities, who
paid for materials the village was too poor to buy. Eighty
very well-behaved small boys were seated on the simple
school benches doing their lessons under the supervision
of a woman teacher.
Today, the same thing is happening over and over again
in village communities of Mexico, Bolivia, Peru, Guate¬
mala and nearly all the Latin-American countries a
striking testimony to the efforts that men and women are
willing to make so that the new generation may enjoy
a fuller life. Such endeavours encourage the governments
of all countries in the region to build schools and extend
education, and thus remove one of the gravest obstacles
to social and economic development illiteracy.
The proportion of illiterates in Latin America (approxi¬
mately 40% of the population above the age of fifteen)
is still high in comparison with the United States, Japan,
or the majority of European countries, though it has been
considerably reduced from the beginning-of-the-century
figure of over 80%. We must remember, however, that
despite the common origin and closely related cultural
traditions of the twenty Latin-American countries, con¬
ditions vary considerably not only from one country to
another, but even within the individual countries.
In several of them (Mexico, Guatemala, Ecuador, Peru,
Bolivia) large groups of the original Indian inhabitants
have lived through conquest, colonial periods and the
years of independence without ever becoming completely
assimilated in the national life. They still preserve many
of their native characteristics.
In all Latin-American countries agriculture predomi¬
nates, and in almost all of them most people live in the
country. Consequently there is a profound disparity in
living conditions between the considerable urban devel¬
opment, comparable in many respects to that of the more
advanced countries, and the extremely backward state
of the rural masses. These differences are evident from
economic, social and cultural standpoints.
The measure of this difference is shown clearly in the
table published on this page, which lists the Latin-Ame¬
rican countries in ascending order of percentage of illi¬
teracy in 1950. The table also shows the close relationship
between the proportion of rural population, per capita
income, and the incidence of illiteracy. Generally speak¬
ing it is the poorest countries, with a predominantly rural
OSCAR VERA, professor of sociology and education at the Peda¬
gogical Institute of the University of Chile, is co-ordinator of Unesco's
Major Project for the extension of Primary Education in Latin America.
population, which have had the most difficulty In
expanding their education services. There are, however,
certain exceptions, which are worth mentioning because
they suggest that the backwardness or progress of a coun¬
try's educational system is determined not merely by high
or low income, but by other factors as well.
Costa Rica, for example, is a small agricultural country
which boasts that its schoolteachers constitute Its only
army. The proportion of illiterates is as low there as in
the most advanced .countries of the continent. On the
other hand, Venezuela, with the highest per capita income
in Latin America (thanks to its huge oil reserves) has a
comparatively high percentage of illiteracy. Since 1958,
however, the Venezuelan Government has been making
a vigorous effort and in the near future, through the Judi-
LATIN AMERICA
POPULATION, ILLITERACY,
INCOME PER CAPITA (1950)
Country
Argentina
Uruguay
Chile
Costa Rica
Cuba
Panama
Paraguay
Colombia
Mexico
Ecuador
Venezuela
Brazil
Peru
Dominican Rep.
El Salvador
Nicaragua
Honduras
Bolivia
Guatemala
Haiti
Population
Illiterate
Aged 15 yrs
and over
(percen¬
tage)
Total
(In thou¬
sands)
Aged
15 yrs
and-
over
o'
/y
Income
per capita
(USdollars)
17,189 69 13.6 (1) 300-449
2,407 69 15.0 (E) 300-449
6,073 61 19.9 150-299
801 57 20.6 100-149
5,508 64 22.1 300-449
797 58 30.1 150-299
1,397 56 34.2 100
11,334 57 37.6 100-149
25,826 58 38.0 (E) 100-149
3,197 57 44.3 100
4,974 58 47.8 300-449
51,976 58 50.6 100-149
8,521 56 53.0 (E) 100-149
2,131 56 57.1 100
1,868 59 60.6 100-149
1,060 57 61.6 100-149
1,428 59 64.8 100
3,019 60 67.9 100
2,805 57 70.6 100
3,112 61 89.5 100
Rural
population
(per¬
centage)
37.5
40.1
66.5
43.0
64.0
65.4
63.7
57.4
71.5
46.2
63.8
64.6
76.2
63.5
65.1
71.0
66.4
75.0
87.8
(I) Population ajed I 4 yean and over.
(E) Estimate.
Source« : U.N. Demojraphic Year Book I955, 1956, 1957, 1958.
UN : Preliminary Report on the Social Situation in the world (New York
Unetco : World Illiteracy in Mid-Century.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
CUBAN CLASSMATES
IN UNIFORM
In Cuba, 1961 has become "edu¬
cation year" by government order.
Plans are being put into effect to
eliminate illiteracy from the island
by opening classrooms for the
whole of the school-age population
and launching a vigorous adult
education campaign. Right, special
literacy class for soldiers. Campaign
slogan on blackboard tells Cubans:
"How you can help Cuba if you
are a teacher, make others literate;
if you can't read, learn how." Criti¬
cal problem of classroom shortage
is subject of cartoon, far right,
in Peruvian newspaper "Hoy".
Cuban Government photo
34
clous use of its resources, will bring education to the whole
school-age population. In this way, within the next few
years, illiteracy will have been uprooted at its source.
The percentage of illiteracy cannot alone give an idea
of how far education has been developed, or to what
extent it reaches the population as a whole. Thus, for
Instance, the proportion of illiterates in the United States
and Japan is less than 3%; yet the average educational
level of the population in the two countries is respectively
9 and 7.2 years of schooling. In other words, in the United
States the average adult has attended school for nine
years, and in Japan for only seven.
From this standpoint the average educational level of
the Latin-American population in 1950 was two years
ranging from six months' school attendance in the coun¬
try with the least developed educational system to just
over four years in the most educationally advanced. It
takes about four years of school attendance to attain
what specialists call "functional literacy", that is, a suffi¬
cient command of reading and writing to ensure that
these skills will not be forgotten and can be used with at
least a minimum of efficiency in the problems and acti¬
vities of daily life.
As a distinguished Brazilian educator has put it,
education in Latin America is the privilege of a small
minority which has access to the various levels of the
educational system, while the great majority of the popu¬
lation is neither equipped to make an effective contri¬
bution to economic development nor able to take a full
share in democratic life.
The two main reasons for this situation are school
absenteeism and school-leaving. Many children do not go
to school either because their parents, even when they
recognize the value of education, cannot do without the
extra income from the children's work, or simply because
there is no local school for them to attend.
A very high proportion of those who do start school
never complete the full course. Less than twenty-five per
cent of the children who enrol in primary schools stay
on to the end of the compulsory education period.
In 1959 primary school enrolments in Latin America
stood at about 25 million, out of a total of 37 million
children of school age. About a third of the children
were therefore not attending school. To provide proper
education for them at the right time would mean building
about 400,000 classrooms, training an equal number of
teachers, and recruiting the corresponding administra¬
tive staff and inspectors.
There is also the problem of providing equipment and
teaching materials. Finally, some financial assistance must
be given to poor children or to their families.
Such measures, and others of a purely pedagogic nature,
would get rid of absenteeism. They would also consid¬
erably reduce school-leaving, which reaches alarming pro¬
portions in nearly all the countries concerned, especially
in rural districts. They would also eradicate illiteracy
within a few years.
The Latin-American countries have decided to under¬
take this formidable task. But it is a particularly difficult
one for them not only because of their under-developed
economies but also because of the tremendous speed at
which their populations are increasing. While the total
world population is growing at the rate of 1.6% per
annum, the annual rate of increase in Latin American is
2,6%, and in a number of countries it exceeds 3 per cent.
This calls for a far greater effort to maintain adequate
educational services than is required in other countries.
It is not only necessary because of the rapid and tremen¬
dous growth of the population, but also because the pro¬
portion of those over twenty years of age who can make
an effective contribution to economic life in all its aspects,
and pay for the education of their juniors, is less than
50% in nearly all the Latin-American countries. In
other countries, where population increase is more gra¬
dual, the proportion is from 65 to 70 per cent.
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
LA CARICATURA DE HOY
V'Ní^
Without neglecting adult education campaigns, the only
means of rapidly bringing illiterate adults into full parti¬
cipation in community life and fitting them for new
economic activities, the Latin-American countries are
concentrating their efforts on extirpating illiteracy at
its root. One of the most important weapons in this
campaign is making primary education available to the
whole school-age population. These countries have there¬
fore been playing an active part, since 1956, in an unpre¬
cedented venture, Unesco's Major Project for the Extension
of Primary Education in Latin America.
Despite the short time this project has been in opera¬
tion, encouraging results have already been obtained.
Between 1956 and 1959, primary school attendance in
Latin America increased by about four million, while the
number of teachers rose by more than 90,000. In certain
countries the increase in primary school enrolments was
positively sensational: 40% in Honduras in the past three
years; 40% in Venezuela since 1958; 40% in a single year
in Cuba, where the Government has decided to make
1961 "education year" and plans to eliminate illiteracy
completely by providing schools for the whole of the
school-age population and conducting a vigorous adult
education campaign.
Brazil and Mexico, which between them account for
half the population of Latin America, have increased their
primary school attendance by 22% and 18% respectively
in the past three years. All countries, in varying degrees,
are adopting measures which testify to an increasingly
firm determination to extend and improve their educa¬
tional services. They have resolved that in ten years'
time there shall be schools available for all their children.
Unesco is sharing in this project to the limit of its
resources. It is encouraging and facilitating the powerful
movement initiated in the Latin-American countries to
make primary education universally available. It is also
co-operating with those countries and with various inter¬
national organizations particularly the Organization of
American States and the Ibero-American Bureau of Edu
cation in an extensive plan for improving the quality
of education.
Under this plan the training of education directors and
experts is being carried out, especially in the universities
associated with the Major Project, Santiago de Chile and
Sao Paulo, Brazil. Similar training is also given at the
Inter-American Rural Education Centre at Rublo (Vene¬
zuela) and in some European countries, including Bel¬
gium, Czechoslovakia, France, Italy and Spain.
The training of teachers, also associated with the Pro¬
ject, has been undertaken in Colombia, Ecuador, Hondu¬
ras and Nicaragua. The chief function of these schools
is to act as pilot schools, contributing to the improvement
of teacher-training methods. The plan also Includes
direct technical assistance In education, the organization
of short courses, seminars and national and regional
meetings, and the issue of publications by the Office for
the Co-ordination of the Major Project.
Some idea of the magnitude of the effort made to
train experts and directors of education may be gained
from the fact that from 1958 to 1960, 580 Latin-American
fellowship-holders took advanced courses In connexion
with the Major Project. Each of these fellowship-holders
is being equipped to play a part in directing education
or to teach in the teacher-training schools, and will
influence great numbers of present and future teachers
as well as the future policy of the education services.
The experience acquired in putting the Latin-American
Major Project into operation has aroused keen interest in
other parts of the world where similar problems exist,
and it is now being applied and adapted to the needs of
South-East Asia, the Arab countries, and Africa.
These countries, like the Latin-American States, are
hoping, by progressively expanding their education ser¬
vices, to solve their urgent illiteracy problem within the
next few years, and with it overcome the greatest obstacle
to the integration of national life and to the social and
economic development of the population as a whole.
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
MEN OF THE LAND
Latin America today faces two pressing problems
o The need for agrarian reform
o The challenge of industrial expansion
by Tibor Mende
Afew years ago on a visit to Latin America 1
was admiring the capital city of a certain
Latin-American Republic. A local official informed me
that about once every minute a new building was
completed.
Several days later while travelling only a few hundred
miles west of this great metropolis, I was informed that
in that region the consumption of candles for lighting
was steadily on the increase. The modern city was one
of the world's fastest growing capitals, but the country¬
side I visited was probably among the last remaining
regions anywhere in the world where the sale of candles
is still growing.
Anyone who travels in Latin America will come across
similar contradictions. They will find rural areas of
abject misery not far from scintillating, skyscraper-
studded cities where wide avenues are packed with
luxury cars and bordered by sumptuous villas complete
with their own swimming pools.
It is said frequently that Latin America is a continent of
contrasts. It is an attractive phrase for the tourist
brochures, one that promises picturesque scenery and
plenty of opportunity for unusual colour photographs.
In reality, however, these contrasts mean a disequilibrium,
an uneven development, and all the tension and suffer¬
ing that implies. The main cause of such disequilibrium
in Latin America is an unequal development between
industry and agriculture.
This disequilibrium is so great in several Latin-Ameri¬
can countries that the slow progress of agricultural
development is beginning to hamper further industrial
development.
The traditional pattern of Latin-American economic
development has been in the form of concentric circles.
In the centre there is the minority with high incomes,
and it is on the needs of this group that industries are
based. This circle tends to broaden as it generates
industrialization and economic progress.
As the prosperity spreads, other groups enter the
privileged circle. As the incomes of these new groups
increase, they also begin to contribute to the nation's
savings and thus the progress of the economy continues.
The circles enlarge and growing numbers are absorbed
into the ever-widening field of the modern economy.
But, too often these circles stop dead once they reach
CONT'D ON PAGE 38
LANDSCAPE IN TRANSITION. From modern industrial com¬
plexes, like this one' in Mexico, to the timeless labouring of the soil
with a primitive wooden plough in the Puno region of Peru (opposite
page) and from llama transport to travel by jet aircraft, Latin America
is a continent of striking diversity. One of the major obstacles to its full
economic development is the present land distribution the existence
of vast estates (latifundia) owned by the few and not fully exploited.
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
m
m
TT*'
Photos © Paul Almasy. Par 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
MEN OF THE LAND (Cont'd)
38
LANDLESS FARM WORKERS
AND RURAL DISCONTENT
the world of the rural inhabitants who, we must re¬
member, form the majority class throughout Latin
America. So it ls that the large peasant class fails to
benefit, In the most part, from the burgeoning blessings
of an expanding economy. How to remedy this situation
ls rapidly becoming the number one problem throughout
Latin America.
Both natural and man-made causes are responsible
for the abject poverty and general inertia found in rural
areas. The nature of the soil itself is a primary natural
cause of this disparity. The major part of Latin America
lies in tropical and sub-tropical zones. Soil erosion,
excessive rainfall, prolonged drought, and crop yields far
below those in temperate zones, all combine to limit
productivity of the land.
Another natural cause is the uneven distribution of the
population. Much of Latin America resembles islands of
densely settled Inhabitants, divided by seas of wilderness.
This archipelago of islands of population has always
suffered from inadequate communication and an irrational
division which cuts them off from the necessary centres
of modern economy. A striking example is found in
Brazil where not much more than two per cent of the
country's surface is cultivated, and only half of that is
devoted to the production of foodstuffs.
Agriculture in Latin America is hindered as
well by man-made causes. Some are the
legacies of history, but others have their roots in existing
Institutions. Rural modernization suffers mainly from
two such obstacles monoculture and land tenure.
Often the most fertile regions are devoted to the produc¬
tion of industrial crops, most of which are intended for
export. In this way a large part of the best land grows
crops whose prices on the world market tend to change
frequently, and sometimes disastrously, causing great
economic uncertainty. This system of monoculture,
though it may bring in needed foreign currency, seldom
ever helps directly to alleviate malnutrition or famine.
The problem of land tenure is of greater importance.
In a number of Latin-American countries, a tiny fraction
of landowners hold the overwhelming proportion of
cultivated land. Huge and wasteful estates sometimes
co-exist with extreme poverty on the part of the rural
workers. In some cases large land holdings are exploited
along modern lines and assure a reasonable living
standard for the worker, but more often they do not,
and the standard of living of the workers is far below
what the yield of the land ought to sustain.
There is also the problem of the landless labourers.
They depend on seasonal work or are simply unemployed.
They are yet another aspect of the bottomless reservoir
of rural discontent found throughout Latin America.
It ls this rural majority of landless, low-income people
who are prisoners of the vicious circle of poverty, low
productivity, apathy and backwardness. It is their lack
of purchasing power that fatally limits the scope of
indigenous industries and, in the long run, tends to slow
down their development.
To make matters worse, the problem is rendered even
less tractable due to rapid population increase.
Perhaps nowhere in the world today is population
growing faster than in Latin America. The increase is
about 1.5 per cent in Asia as a whole. It is around 2 per
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1961
THE FASTEST GROWING
POPULATION IN THE WORLD
cent in Africa. Over Latin America as a whole, popula¬
tion growth ls believed to surpass the 2.5 per cent. Nor
is it likely that It will slow down in the foreseeable future.
On the contrary, progress In public health and the
effectiveness of the battle against epidemics are likely to
speed It still further. Yet, even now, Latin America
produces less food per head than before the war.
It is generally admitted that merely to maintain the
existing living standards of a population expanding at
such a rate, the Latin American countries ought to Invest
in their future 10 to 12 per cent of their national Income.
To go slightly further and to raise the present level by
only one per cent each year, such Investments ought to
reach 13 to 15 per cent of the national income.
Investments in most Latin-American countries, however,
are well below that level. Even large-scale foreign aid
could not fill the gap. Only by industrialization and the
modernization of agriculture, so that the peasant masses
become consumers of domestic Industries, can such des¬
irable investment levels be reached.
That, in essence, is the Latin-American dilemma.
Capital is scarce. It is, therefore, all the more urgent
to utilize fully all available resources. The two most
important among these are land and manpower. This
implies, first of all, the expansion of cultivated lands.
Hitherto uncultivated land which is potentially fertile
must be brought under the plough. It also implies all
the measures which would diversify the production of
the land, improve the efficiency of agriculture, and help
increase yields.
Many development and land reclamation proJets
are being launched all over Latin America to
speed the progress of agriculture. In Argentina, a Na¬
tional Institute of Technology has been functioning to
promote better practices on the farms. A subsidized wheat
expansion programme is gathering momentum in Brazil,
and large-scale irrigation schemes are under way in the
northeast of the country.
Chile has launched an eight-year agricultural develop¬
ment programme. Colombia ls co-ordinating her various
measures aiming at agricultural modernization, Mexico is
improving her rural marketing facilities and Ls pushing
ahead with irrigation programmes. Venezuela is launch¬
ing a five-year plan for Increasing meat production. And
in Peru a large-scale development programme is under
study, aimed at the opening up of the country's interior
to serve the welfare of the Andean Indians.
It would be impossible to list in a brief article all the
projects and schemes taking shape. Nor would the
generalization be justified that all of them have produced
the expected results. Desirable and helpful as these
projects may be, practically none of them affect the
systems of land tenure.
The land holding system In most Latin-American
countries has changed but little since colonial days.
Though the importance of land reform has repeatedly
been admitted by Latin America's political leaders, two
or three countries excepted, little has been done about it.
Several Latin-American countries have already reached
a stage in their economic development where further
expansion demands a measure of income redistribution
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
WINNING BACK WASTED LAND. Agricultural reforms and better exploitation of the land are both vital to Latin America
according to a recent U.N. report published in New York. Certain countries, says the report, though predominantly agricultural
must nevertheless import much food from abroad. They could obtain at least part of this from their own land if they used more
modern methods and put wasteland under cultivation. Lack of available land has provoked a mass exodus from rural areas to
towns as peasants search for work. Above, Paraguayans clear away trees and brushwood to win back wasted land for cultivation.
A NEW APPROACH THROUGH COMMON ACTION
40
which would widen the potential home market for the
products of existing industries.
Among the arguments advanced in opposition to such
measures, most frequently one hears the claim that the
mere carving up of large estates, as happened in Bolivia,
would tend to decrease production rather than help to
raise it. The simple slicing up of the land appears to
clash with the modern trend towards large-scale, mech¬
anical farming.
Indeed land reforms in a number of Asian countries
tend to confirm that the mere distribution of land without
simultaneous measures to provide the new owners with
basic equipment, with rural credit, with access to educa¬
tion, or eventually with the incentives to form co¬
operatives, may have an adverse effect on production.
In the prevailing political context of economically un¬
derdeveloped countries, however, the first purpose of land
reform is not to get more out of the soil but rather to
spread agricultural incomes and so to disarm political
passions generated by rural discontent. Only recently,
Latin America has been the theatre of political develop¬
ments which tend to underline the urgency of such
conclusions.
Fortunately, there are signs of growing awareness that
this political aspect is fast becoming the central theme
of Latin America's land problem. More and more, land
reform is viewed as an immunizing measure against
revolutionary temptations. At the September 1960 meeting
of the Organization of American States the need was
clearly recognized.
The final resolution, which has become known as the
Act of Bogotá, called for a re-examination of legislation
"with a view to ensuring a wider and more equitable
distribution of the ownership of land." In the same text,
new legislation concerning the system of land tenure,
rural credit and taxation policy was specifically
referred to as an indispensable preliminary both to
encourage foreign aid and investments, and to render the
countries of Latin America better prepared to make the
best use of such aid.
Such reforms would no doubt help to encourage rural
initiative and would greatly contribute to political
stability. To that extent, they would also encourage
foreign investors and help the flow of foreign aid.
Such a new approach to the land question in Latin
America could become decisive in providing the required
stimulant to revive and to modernize the region's agri¬
culture and to permit it to support, rather than to lag
behind industrial development. Finally, such a new
approach might herald Latin America's final offensive
against her intolerable heritage of rural poverty, mal¬
nutrition and famine.
Tibor Mende, author and journalist, has travelled widely in
Latin America and the Far East. His many books include
L'Amérique Latine entre en scène (Latin America enters the World
Scene), China and Her Shadow and South-East Asia between Two
Worlds.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
The Uneico Courier. June 1961
MALTA'S NEGLECTED MONUMENTS
Sir,
I was extremely interested in the
world-wide campaign to save the
monuments of Nubia (The Unesco
Courier, February 1960) as it would
be tragic if such monuments were lost
for ever. Here in the Maltese islands
we have Neolithic Temples which need
looking after, and although much is
said about a tourist industry in Malta,
neither money nor real interest have
been allocated for preserving such
treasures which are left to wither at
the mercy of mother nature. Thus no
encouragement whatever exists for the
younger generations who would be
interested in archaeology and these
museum treasures. I am passing on
this information to you because I
would like something to be done for
our islands and (he treasures they hold.
I enclose some Maltese stamps which
show some of the monuments.
George J. Dcspoft
Conspicua, Malta
Three Maltese stamps depicting some of the island's monuments. From left to right:
the Wignacourt Viaduct, built in 1614, a Neolithic Hypogeum and the Mosta Dome.
PERNICIOUS WEED
Sir,
Foolish and harmful habits such as
smoking, the drinking of alcohol and
addiction to drugs, are prevalent in all
countries; they show no signs of
abating and are causing great injury
to mankind.
Since the measures adopted in some
countries to eradicate these scourges
of the human race have achieved little
(one has only to recall the "prohibi¬
tion" fiasco in the USA), it seems high
time to give serious thought to raising
the question on a world scale through
the United Nations.
The following example may serve
to show that measures adopted by
U.N. could be more fruitful; one of
the reasons for the further spreading
of the smoking habit is that cinema
heroes often appear on the screen
with cigarettes in their mouths. Young
people, teenagers especially, are apt to
imitate their screen heroes, and if
those heroes smoke their young fans
want to do likewise. It is quite
obvious that the smoking hero can
only be forced off the cinema, and,
consequently, off the TV screen if
measures are adopted on an inter¬
national scale.
U.N. measures to eradicate addiction
to drugs and alcohol could be still
more effective. The opium traffic
was stopped only by an international
convention. Without such a conven¬
tion the fight against drug-taking is
hopeless, because drug smugglers are
always liable to circumvent the regu¬
lations of individual countries.
In my opinion this is an urgent
question that ought to be discussed at
the U.N., and several of The Unesco
Courier issues should be devoted to it.
David Eisenberg
Moscow, U.S.S.R.
MEANING OF MONTEVIDEO
Sir,
In The Unesco Courier (April
1960) I read a version of the origin of
the name Montevideo ("A mountain
saw I") which nowadays my compa¬
triots tend to consider erroneous. The
Uruguayan historian Buenaventura
Caviglia, in his book Etymology of the
name Montevideo, tells this other
story: The first Spanish navigators
to explore the River Plate found, as
they lost sight of the flatlands of
Southern Brazil and came acros the
Uruguayan coastline, a series of hills
they marked on their maps with
Roman numerals. Their direction along
the river was East-West (Este-Oeste).
The hill that towers over the city
of Montevideo was indicated on their
maps with the numeral VI. As an
important landmark for the ships that
wanted to take shelter in the bay, the
hill, or monte, was thus marked on
maps: MONTE-VI-D.E.O. (these last
three initials meaning "direction
East-West"), an abbreviation that
eventually became a single word and
the name of the Uruguayan capital.
Mirllia C. Curri-rus
Trinidad, Flores, Uruguay
OTHER VOICES, OTHER VIEWS
Sir,
For the year during which I have
been reading The Unesco Courier I
have not seen in it any article
expressing a contrary viewpoint. Thus
there was no defence for racial discri¬
mination (although there must be
someone somewhere who would
defend the doctrine); the treasures of
Nubia were, without reservation, inva¬
luable (though, surely, there are people
who care little whether they are lost
or saved) and Anton Chekhov was a
first-rate writer (though, no doubt,
critics have found major faults with
his work).
Thus a preponderance of the space
in The Unesco Courier is devoted to
editorial opinion, rather than to a
multi-lateral appraisal of the matter
under consideration.
lohn Stuart Mill wrote, in his essay
on "Liberty," that "if all mankind
minus one were of one opinion, and
only one person were of the contrary
opinion, mankind would be no more
justified in silencing that one person
than he... would be justified in si¬
lencing mankind." If it adheres to this
principle, and if it claims to be "a
window open on the world," The
Unesco Courier must broaden the
scope of its articles, not to include
more subjects, but to include more
viewpoints on the same subjects; it
must not only open the windows, it
must raise the blind, part the curtains,
and throw back the shutters, so that
the reader may have a complete,
unobstructed view of the aspect of the
world under examination.
Terence C. Moore
Winnipeg, Canada
WORLD AT PLAY
Sir,
As a teacher I am interested in chil¬
dren's games as played in different
parts of the world. I would like to
hear from readers of The Unesco
Courier about children's games, both
individual and group, played in their
own country.
I feel that our children in schools
would be far more likely to take an
interest in international affairs if they
were shown how their contemporaries
in other countries amuse themselves.
B. T. Penzer,
89 Vicarage Lane, Water Oxton
Birmingham, England
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
U.N. urges expansion of mass media in three continents
Aseries of measures to help the less developed countries of Africa, Asia
and Latin America build up (heir press, radio, film and television facilities
has been recommended by the Economic and Social Council of the United
Nations, which met in New York. The recommended measures emerge from a
report prepared by Unesco on the problems of assisting development of the mass
media in those countries.
The report Is based on a survey which Unesco is conducting at the Council's
request through a scries of regional meetings. The first meeting, for South East
Asia, was held in Bangkok, in January 1960 and the second, for Latin America
at Santiago, Chile, in February 1961. The third meeting, for Africa, will be
held in that continent early in 1962. The survey has shown that nearly 70 per
cent of the world's peoples, living in over 100 countries, lack the barest means
of proper public information.
Under the recommended U. N. measures, countries would draw up programmes
for development of mass media as part of their planning for economic and social
expansion. National committees would be set up to help in preparing and
carrying out these programmes.
In addition, countries would establish national training programmes for mass
media personnel, study the present and future needs of the media in planning
their communication and transport services and consider the adoption of fiscal,
customs tariff and other measures to aid development of the media.
42
JtjI AN IN SPACE: Unesco is to help
prepare a symposium on "Man in Space",
to be held in 1963 under the auspices of
the International Astronautical Federation.
Under a programme approved by the
Unesco General Conference last December,
Unesco will also aid the Federation in
preparing a multilingual handbook of
some 50,000 terms used in space research.
For the Committee on Space Research of
the International Council of Scientific
Unions, Unesco will help to organize
symposiums this year and next in three
fields: precision tracking and telemetering
methods; ultra-violet astronomical observa¬
tions which cannot be made from the
ground; effects of high temperature and
vacuum on small biological organisms.
NURSERY SCHOOL LANGUAGE
CLASSES: At what age should children
start learning a foreign language?
According to a group of educators from
the A.I. Herzen Pedagogical Institute in
Leningrad, children aged 5 and 6 have
no difficulty in assimilating phonetics
and syntax and can learn a second
language more quickly and retain their
knowledge longer than children aged
11 and 12. These conclusions are
based on several years of language
teaching experiments in Leningrad's
kindergartens.
C^RIME PREVENTION IN ASIA:
Under its world-wide programme of social
defence, the United Nations recently signed
an agreement with the Japanese Govern¬
ment for the creation in Tokyo of the
"Asia and Far East Institute for the
Prevention of Crime and the Treatment
of Offenders". Later this year the Institute
will begin operations as a centre for the
training of staff, and for research and
study on crime prevention and treatment
of offenders. Particular attention will be
given to the problem of juvenile delin¬
quency and the treatment of young
offenders.
SCHOOLS FOR AFRICA: Tropical
Africa, comprising 30 countries from
Ethiopia to the Congo and from Senegal
to Madagascar, has 25 million children
of school age. Yet 17 million have no
schools to attend and of the "privileged"
8 million only a minority complete
primary education. Forty African states
and territories and five European
countries with African responsibilities
were invited to a meeting in Ethiopia,
last month, to discuss ways and means
of developing education in Africa.
Held under the auspices of Unesco
and the U.N. Economic Commission
for Africa, the conference was attended
by Ministers or Directors of Education
for the African countries. Unesco's
own programme for 28 countries in
Tropical Africa during 1961-62 amounts
to about $11,5 million, including sums
administered on behalf of the U.N.
Special Fund and Technical Assistance.
A BORIGINAL ART ON SLIDES:
A new series of Art Slides has just been
issued by Unesco devoted to paintings by
aborigines of Arnhem Land in the extreme
north of Australia. The works shown are
linked with ancient forms of art dating
back to the palaeolithic age and the set
of 30 colour slides includes examples of
both rock and bark paintings. Explanatory
texts and captions in English, French and
Spanish accompany each set, the price of
which is $10 or the equivalent in other
currencies. Orders may be placed with
Publications filmées d'Art et d'Histoire,
11, rue Carvès, Montrouge, Seine, France.
TWENTY MILLION TEXTBOOKS:
Dr. James Torres Bodet, Mexico's
Minister of Education, has announced
that over 20 million textbooks will be
published and distributed free to pupils
in primary schools all over the country
during 1961. This figure represents an
increase of nearly 2,800,000 over the
number of manuals printed last year,
and shows the results already being
achieved under Mexico's ll-year plan
for the extension of primary education.
F,ARMING FROM THE AIR: An
experiment in sowing grass seed from a
low-flying plane over an area of nearly
500 acres of rangeland in the United
States is to be made in July by American
scientists from the University of Arizona.
The scientists have prepared small seed-
pellets made of clay and grass seed and
containing fertilizer for the seeds and
repellents for insects and other pests. The
pellets will be dropped just before heavy
seasonal rainfall.
UNESCO PHILATELIC SERVICE
U.N. STAMPS
Some 274 million United Nations
stamps and items of postal sta¬
tionery have been printed since the
U.N. Postal Administration was estab¬
lished ten years ago. In addition to
focusing attention on the work of the
United Nations and its specialized
agencies in the political, economic and
social fields, the stamps and stationery
have produced a gross revenue of
$ I 0 million since 1951. Gross revenue
for 1961 is anticipated at S 1-5. The
international popularity of collecting
U.N. stamps has continued to grow
with the increasing activities of the U.N.
In addition to being an interesting
hobby for millions of people, the
collection of these stamps enables
people to support in a direct way the
work of the United Nations. As the
agent in France of the U.N. Postal
Administration, Unesco's Philatelic
Service stocks all the United Nations
stamps currently on sale. It also has
stamps and first day covers issued by
many Unesco member states to com¬
memorate important events in the
history of Unesco and the U.N. (inau¬
guration of Unesco's new headquar¬
ters, Human Rights Day, World Refugee
Year). Information on items available,
price and methods of payment will be
sent on request by the Unesco Philatelic
Service, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7*.
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
WANTED
SECONDARY SCHOOL TEACHERS
FOR SERVICE IN AFRICA
Unesco invites applications from secondary school
teachers in the following subjects:
Modern languages (English and French)
Science
Mathematics
Technical education
For teaching posts in Africa (Liberia, Mali, Niger,
Nigeria, Sierra Leone, Somalia, Tanganyika, Uganda, etc.).
Applicants must possess the following minimum
qualifications:
>%ß They must be fully qualified to teach in a
recognized secondary school of their own
country the subject to be taught in Africa.
^ They must possess a minimum of 3 years'
secondary school teaching experience in their
subject.
Q Since teaching will be done in English or
French, depending on country, absolute fluency
in the language is essential.
Q Language teachers must be native-born
speakers of the language taught.
Assignments will be made by contract for a period
of two years beginning with the academic year 1961-
I 962. Salaries will range from USS 4,800 to 8,000 per
annum (income tax free or reimbursed if levied), plus
family, post and other allowances.
Candidates should send curriculum vitac, with name,
address, age, nationality, mother tongue, academic
qualifications, subjects taught, years of teaching exper¬
ience, knowledge of foreign languages, to:
The Personnel Officer, Field Staff Division,
Unesco,
Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7e, France.
Where to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write
direct to the National Distributor
in your country. (See list below ;
names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.)
Payment is made in the national
currency ; rates quoted are for an
annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. PanuzaT, Press
Department, Royal Afghan Ministry of
Education, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 369 tonsdale Street, Melbourne,
C. I. Victoria. (A. 15/-).
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C0., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V (Sch.
50.-)
BELGIUM. For The Unesco Courier:
Louis de Lannoy, 22, Place De Brouckère,
Brussels, C.C.P. 338.000. (fr. b. 100.)
Other publications: Office de Publicité,
16, rueMarcq, Bruxelles, C.C.P. 285.98;
N.V. Standaard-Boekhandel, Belgielei 151,
Antwerp.
BURMA. Burma Translation Society
361 Prome Road, Rangoon.
CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa
Ont. (S 3.00).
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd, Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Co¬
lombo, 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co, Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Librería Económica, Pte Zayas
505-7,Apartado 113, Havana. (2.25 pesos)
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia Ltd., 30
Ve Smeckách, Prague 2.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard, A/S
Tidsskriftafdelingen, 6 Nörregade, Koben-
havn K. (D.kr. 12).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agen¬
cy. P.O. Box 120. Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kiriakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (F.mk. 540).
FRANCE. Unesco Bookshop, Place de
Fontenoy, Pans. 7». C.C.P. 12598-48.
(7 NF.).
GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier.
Vertrieb Bahrenfelder-Chaussee 160,
Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, C.C.P. 276650
(DM 8). Other Publications: R. Older-
burg, Verlag, Rosenheimerstr. 145, Munich
GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kaufímann, 28,
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Kultura, P.O. Box 149.
Budapest, 62.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd. Indian
Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road, Bombay
t; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13;
Gunfoundry Road, Hyderabad, I ; 36a,
Mount Road, Madras 2; Kanson House.
24/1 Asaf AM Road, P.O. Box 3 86, New
Delhi, I ; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book &
Stationery Co., 17 Park Street Calcutta 16,
Scindia House, New Delhi. (Rs. 6.70).
INDONESIA. Bappit Pusat "Permita",
Djalan Nusantara 22, Djakarta.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The National Press, 2. Wel¬
lington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-).
ISRAEL, Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
. 35, Allenby Road and 48, Nahlat Benja¬
min Street, Tel-Aviv (l£ 4.-).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.( I 0/-)
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central. Tokyo. (Yen 670).
JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road, P.O.B. 66,
Amman.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul.
LIBERIA, J. Momolu Kamara, 69, Front
and Gurley Streets, Monrovia.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück,
22, Grand-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications
Ltd., Times House, River Valley Rd.,
Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta. (10/-).
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd.
30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis.
MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid des
Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (7 NF).
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl 6)
NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES.
G. CT. Van Dorp & C- (Ned Ant.) N.V.
Willemstad, Curacao.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church. (10/-).
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos. (10/-).
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille Gren-
sen,7, Oslo. (N. kr. 13.20).
PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing
Co, Ltd., Unesco Publications House,
P.O. Box 374. 56-N Gulberg Industrial
Colony, Lahore.
PANAMA. Cultural Panameña. Avenida
7a, No. TI-49, Apartado de Correos 20 I 8,
Panama, D.F. (Balboas 3.-).
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo, P.O. Box
620. Manila.
POLAND. "RUCH" ul. Wiloia Nr. 46,
Warsaw. 10 (Zl. 50).
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada Lda,
Livrana Portugal, Rua do Cirmo 70,
Lisbon.
RHODESIA A NYASALAND. The
Book Centre, First Street, Salisbury,
Southern Rhodesia.
SWEDEN, For The Unesco Courier: Sven-
ska Unescoradet, Vasigatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 7.50); other publications
A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl. Hovbokhandtl,
Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag. 5
Ramistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40, rue du Marché, Ganeva. C.C.P.
1-236.
"Courier" only: Georges Losmaz, I, rue
des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. C.C.P.
1-481 I. (Fr. S. 8).
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 liti-
klal Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Street. Pretoria. (10/-).
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT).
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adlv-Pasha.
Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 5 69, London, S.E.I.( I 0/-).
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22, N.Y. ($ 5.00.) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y.
U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjlga,
Terazije 27/11. Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
MEXICO CITY'S
Mosaic murals are a distinctive feature of Communica¬
tions and Public Works building in Mexico City. Latin
American architects and designers soften the austere
modern lines of their buildings with many kinds of surface
! Paul Almasy, Paris
treatments. Here, the artist blends designs of three historic
phases of Mexican culture the Pre-Columbian epoch,
Spanish Colonial period and Modern Era. Latin American
architecture is more than a technique it is an art. (See p. 19)
]]>
</page>
</document>
