<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="064255eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
WINDOWOPEN ON THE WORLD
m « IiM
NOVEMBER 1961 (14TH YEAR) - PRICE : 1/-STG. (U.K.) - 30 CENTS (U.S.) - 0.70 NF (FRANCE)
^'AMftAALIM
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
FRANCE
15 YEARS OF
UNESCO STAMPS
On the 4th of this month, Unesco celebrates its 15th anni¬
versary. Twenty member states were charter members, a
number which has grown to 101, more than five times the
original membership. Stamps have marked many milestones
along the way. The first Unesco commemorative stamp
(left) was issued by the French Government shortly after
Unesco began work in Paris. The latest Unesco stamp is also
a French issue (above right) available in three denominations
since January 21, 1961. Some of these Unesco stamps have
won prizes in international competitions such as the 70 kips
stamp issued by the Kingdom of Laos, one of a series of four
(pictured below right). This stamp was judged the most
beautiful at Monaco this year. Other stamps on this page,
selected from those issued by thirty member states, picture
various views of the Unesco building. They are available from
the Unesco Philatelic Service, Place Fontenoy, Paris, France.
FRANCE
KINGDOM OF LAOS
AFGHANISTAN
COLLECTOR'S ITEM,
a cover issued from
Unesco House in 1959
with French stamp, now
withdrawn, and special
UN stamp.
DOMINICAN
REPUBLIC FRANCE
ECUADOR
SU£2g?gAffi!î!4g7iyS8 "
ROtiBUG Of MWtf.
iV_I.* m
.. - T . - - 25
JOURNEES DES TIMBRES
DES NATIONS UNIES
PARIS .18-18 MAI I S S S
UNESCO
Place de Fontenoy
PARIS 7 ème
KOREA
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
DOW OMN ON THI WOULD
ner
NOVEMBER 1961
14TH YEAR
Contents
No. II
PUBLISHED IN
EIGHT EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
American
Japanese
r «if
COVER PHOTO
Young Indian prepares fea¬
thered ritual objects for
tribal ceremony in French
Guiana. At a time when
the public has come to recog¬
nize the true value of anthro¬
pology, the disappearance
or transformation of so many
" primitive" peoples has pro¬
voked the question: Has
anthropology reached the
point where it has nothing
more left to study? See
article by Claude Levi-Strauss
page 12. © Dominique Darbois
Page
5 SAVING OUR VANISHING FORESTS
By K. H. Oedekoven
1 2 TODAY'S CRISIS IN ANTHROPOLOGY
By Claude Lévi-Strauss
18 UNITED NATIONS FAMILY AT WORK
22 RAYS FROM OUTER SPACE
By Alexander Gusev
25 THE SAGA OF FRIDTJOF NANSEN
By Robert Gladwell
30 UNICEF GREETING CARDS 1962
31 ARTISTS FROM CANADA'S FAR NORTH
32 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
33 A LIGHTER SIDE TO WILDLIFE
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
(M.C. 6 1. 1. 163 A)
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
Gordon Behrens
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition :
Spanish Edition
Russian Edition :
German Edition
Arabic Edition :
Japanese Edition
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Jane Albert Hesse
: Arturo Despouey
Veniamin Matchavariani (Moscow)
: Hans Rieben (Berne)
Amin Shaker (Cairo)
: Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in July and August when
it is bi-monthly ( I I issues a year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German
Arabic and Japanese. In the United Kingdom it is distributed by H. M
Stationery Office, P. O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credic line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in The Readers' Guide to
Periodical Literature published by H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates: U. S. S 3.00; IO/-stg. ; 7.00
New Francs or equivalent. Single copies l/-stg. 30
cents (U.S.) ; 0.70 New Francs.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
SAVING OUR
VANISHING
FORESTS
by K. H. Oedekoven
As far back as the unknown origin of mankind,
the path of human activity has been marked
by the thoughtless destruction of forest and vegetation.
In the course of history, civilizations have flourished
and disappeared with a resultant depletion of trees and
plants, leaving only steppe and desert behind. Only in
recent centuries has man begun to realize that he was
cutting off the branch that he was sitting on.
Man is becoming more aware today of nature's ven¬
geance and, at the same time, of the challenge which
confronts him in preserving his dwindling natural assets
while endeavouring to extend the fertile earth which is
the very basis of his existence. The demands of an ever
increasing population make his task more and more
insistent.
The forest, our largest and most durable soil cover, was
once regarded as only an obstacle to settlement, agri¬
culture and communications. It was recklessly burned
or exploited until it suddenly became a focus of intense
human interest.
Man has come to learn that the two most important
elements of his existence soil and water owe their
stability and availability to the presence of sufficient
forest cover. In many countries, this knowledge has not
been confined only to a few informed specialists, but is
today appreciated by a majority of the citizens.
After visiting the denuded mountains of Natal, the
former Prime Minister of South Africa, Jan Smuts,
declared in Parliament: "This is the vital problem of our
people, it is more Important than all politics!"
In some distant future, this change of mind, this great
turning back from the destruction of forests to reaf¬
forestation, may perhaps appear to the historian as a
more important landmark in the development of mankind
than all the great wars of our age.
But awareness alone does not solve problems. Ministers
of agriculture in most countries are deeply perplexed.
World population increases by more than 50,000 people
daily but the available area of productive land steadily
declines.
Three quarters of the world's population are under¬
nourished. There is only about one acre of land per head
for food production and no less than twice this area is
needed to ensure satisfactory nutrition. The true Enemy
No. 1 in the world is not a political or military opponent,
but the deterioration of the soil, the dryness, the irres¬
istible progress of semi-deserts and deserts.
Karl Heinz Oedekoven is Regional Forestry Officer in ¡he Near
East Regional Office, Cairo, of the U.N. Food and Agriculture
Organization. For the past 20 years he has closely studied
problems of world forestry. In 1958 he was Vice-Chairman of
the European Forestry Commission.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAG E
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Arid deserts
replace Babylon's
golden harvests
In some countries, like the United States of America
and the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, soil conser¬
vation has become almost a "State religion. " In
Southern America, all over Africa, Asia and Australia
there is great concern over the manifold dangers which
threaten the soil.
While international rivalries change, while political
leaders come and go, this destructive process of soil
deterioration remains a permanent menace. Each
government inherits this problem from its predecessor.
Yet, even today, the efforts of many countries to remedy
the situation are merely in their infancy.
Only a few years ago the streets of Swakopmund in
South-West Africa were swept over by a sandstorm that
piled up sand dunes 20 feet high. We know from the
experience of 500 years that the Sahara desert progresses
towards the south at the rate of over three feet a year
on a wide front of 2,000 miles. Lake Chad, which, some
decades ago was still an Ideal refuge for migrating birds
from Europe, is steadily diminishing in surface area and
depth and its shores are turning from fertile green to
steppe brown. All far-reaching plans for the development
of Africa as the "Continent of the Future", all plans for
water use and industrialization will fail unless the neces¬
sary attention is paid to the importance of trees and
forests.
In classifying the great list of lost or endan¬
gered productive lands we find first that two
extensive desert belts have developed along both sides of
the equator. The one in the south reaches from Australia
to South Africa and South America. The one in the
northern hemisphere spreads north from China, all across
Asia, North America and Mexico.'
The northern belt includes those nations which, as we
learned in our history classes at school, were once rulers
of the world. We were puzzled to hear in geography
class that large areas of these once powerful nations are
now sterile. The truth is, of course, that in ancient times
they were not so.
Ctesiphon and Baghdad, . once centres of concentrated
power, were described by Herodotus more than two
thousand years ago: "Of all the countries we know this
is the most suitable for growing grain. It is so well
favoured that it yields two hundredfold and, where condi¬
tions are best, even three-hundredfold. The ears of
wheat and barley grow to the width of four fingers. But
to the height of what tree millet and barley grow I shall
not disclose, though I know it exactly. No one who has
not seen Babylon would believe me."
NATURE'S VENGEANCE on man for his thoughtless destruction
of forest and vegetation has been terrible. A natural forest canopy,
like the richly timbered Russian hillside (top of page) maintains water
infiltration at a maximum and keeps erosion down to a minimum. But
without the protective cover of trees and the firm grip of their roots
"-<-<«* -ï^-*~~:x^ÊÊÊÊi
ïïmmm m
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
a topsoil layer becomes loosened and is eventually carried away by
water and wind. Thus the disastrous chain reaction is set in motion
network of veins and then slight gullies appears in the soil, finally
deepening into real gorges. Eventually there remains only bare rock,
the kind of lunar landscape shown below, in an eroded area of Bolivia.
Official Soviet photo
For Herodotus, Babylon was the essence of fertility. He
also accorded the same honour to Cinyps, a region in
North Africa: "This country produces grain equal to the
best I have seen, for it has black soil and springs water
it. The yield is equal to that of Babylon, three-
hundredfold under the best conditions."
Soldiers in the sand and torrid conditions of this region
(part of modern Cyrenaica) during the last war would
have had difficulty in imagining that a now desolate
desert was 'the richest of farming land two millennia ago.
Mankind has lost a considerable part of its cultivable
soil during the course of recorded history, and through
this process, nations which once ruled the world have
gone down to poverty and misery.
There are three zones on the globe which successively
were homes of dominating civilizations but where the sou
became progressively devastated in proportion to the age
of their settlement.
T¡he first zone is the desert of North Africa. In
the Sahara, hundreds of archaeological finds
and cave paintings indicate that this was once a flour¬
ishing country of many lakes and rivers. One cave
painting shows men swimming. Imagine swimmers in the
Sahara desert today !
A second zone is the continuous range of stone, salt
and sand deserts which spread from West China, across
Turkestan, Afghanistan, Iran, Iraq, Jordan, Sinai and up
to North Africa. In ancient times these latitudes were
inhabited by Sumerians, Babylonians, Persians, Mace¬
donians, and Phoenicians names which are all connec¬
ted with world power and wealth.
The third zone covers Palestine, Syria, Asia Minor,
Greece, Italy and Spain. It is true that the Southern
European States, Greece, Italy and Spain, are neither
steppes nor deserts, but their deforested mountains justify
the statement once made by Henry C. Wallace, former
United States Minister of Agriculture: "Nations live as
long as their humus !"
These countries to which for centuries numerous
foreigners came in search of fertile land, nowadays see
their own inhabitants emigrating to all parts of the world
to find better living conditions.
Zones of depleted land extend slowly from the south
to the north, and this epidemic of devastated soil seems
to be a contagious one. Attempts at reafforestation in
Spain, Italy and Greece would certainly have been more
successful had the opposite shores of the Mediterranean
still been covered with a wide belt of fertile land as once
they were. But the terrible desert has already reached
the shore of the Mediterranean on a wide front and sends
out its drying winds to the European countries.
The ever-blue sky of Italy has not always been as blue.
Some 2,000 years ago it was just as grey and cloudy as in
northern parts of Europe and the complaints of the old
Romans about frost and snow-fall which seem so
strange to those who know Italy today were probably
justified.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
^iitf:;~-^^
A RICH HARVEST OF TIMBER, sufficient to supply a population larger than now exists, can be taken
from the world's total forest area estimated to cover about 10,000 million acres. But to use up this amount
of wood without endangering future needs means that present productive forests must be treated as
"renewable crops", those not at present accessible must be opened up and present devastation must cease.
A continent swept away by its rivers
Much of the world's population (except in East and
South Asia) has left its earlier home and shifted more
and more to the north. What caused this change from
paradise to desert? Is this dreadful development un¬
avoidable, or is man himself to blame?
While once it took millennia, or at least centuries to
deplete fertile land, modern history offers a striking
example of how man can start and complete this
disastrous chain-reaction in only a few decades. Hardly
a hundred years, ago the American farmer moved into
the Middle West, full of initiative and energy.
At first, the existing forests seemed inexhaustible. They
were cut down, houses and bridges were built, the wood
was burned in locomotives, on ships and in stoves. Great
quantities were felled and burned on the spot to make
large areas of ash-fertilized farming land. A little later,
monocultures and tractors cleared away those clumps of
trees and hedges which had survived.
The result was that water ran off the land too rapidly,
soil was eroded, floods occurred and drought appeared
between rainy periods. This process was accelerated
8 during the First World War when large areas of what
remained of tree-covered prairie were ploughed up for
more intensive wheat production .
After the war, part of this land was left idle,- but there
was no longer any deep-rooting grass or other soil cover
to conserve the moisture and stabilize the soil. Storms
swept the land from the Mexican Gulf and Canada
unchecked, for there were no forests to break their force.
The wind carried away the fertile topsoil leaving only
sterile layers and rocks.
The same thing happened to former forest areas.
Without the protection of the trees, without the firm grip
of their roots, without humus, the soil was carried away.
In the South, where the frost which usually stabilises the
soil during winter seldom occurs, and where there is
seldom snow cover to prevent the damage, soil and wind
erosion had the same detrimental effect.
Like a network of veins the first small gullies appeared
in the soil, gradually deepening to real gorges. The
process was repeated a million times all over the country
until finally only the naked rock was left in some regions.
Even today American rivers carry away so much fertile
soil that an old Indian once said: "Our country is a new
Atlantis; one day it will disappear in the Ocean! " It
is significant that the Americans, aware of their
responsibility for this destruction of their productive land,
call their deserts "man-made."
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
WASTELAND OF STUMPS was a luxuriant evergreen forest in the Magallanes Province of southern
Chile before fire raged through it. Such outbreaks are not always accidental. Many forest fires hereabouts
have been started by isolated farmers who find flames an easier tool than the axe when they wish to clear
the land for cultivation and have thus caused the loss of hundreds of thousands of acres of Chile's forests.
If we were to summarize the direct repercussions of
the destruction of forest land on human society the list
of wasteful and harmful effects would be a long one.
They would include soil deterioration, increased difficulty
of watershed management, climatic deteriorations, lack
of wood for many purposes which it fills in man's daily
life, heavy expenditure for imported timber for countries
whose supply has disappeared, loss of employment and
Income which forests and forest industries naturally
provide, shortage of recreation areas, loss of additional
incomes from small woods which help small farmers
make ends meet, lack of shade for livestock and animals,
to mention only a few. These effects in turn set off a
whole chain of other negative reactions far too numerous
to set down In detail.
But to state the problem in general terms, all measures
and efforts must be combined and incorporated in a
sound forest policy. Each country must define for itself
the role which forests, primary forests, forest and ancillary
activities must play in relation to the physical, economic
and social environment. Physical environments alter
little with time, but economic and social conditions, on
the contrary, change as a country seeks to improve the
living standard of its people. Hence, forest policy must
be a continued creation. This makes it all the more
difficult since the objectives set are for the future. It
always takes a long time for any action on the forest to
show appreciable results.
The protective and indirect influences which forests
provide is a comparatively young branch of study, greatly
neglected by our technical age. It is true in many places
that schoolchildren can identify almost any type of auto¬
mobile at a glance but are often unable to distinguish
an oak tree from a beech. It is thus all the more
necessary to inform the public of the beneficial functions
of trees in nature.
The forest has many indirect effects upon the economy,
the prosperity and the well-being of a country and Its
people. One of Its most Important actions is the pre¬
vention or reduction of soil erosion. This protective
action results from the fact that forest cover increases
the degree of precipitation and checks run-off. Even
small forest plants like shrub and bush in hot arid regions
offer valuable defence if they are reasonably dense.
In many parts of the world where forests have been
destroyed or depleted, all the fertile humus and topsoil
has been washed away and only sterile rock has been left
on the slopes. Not only these slopes are thereby con¬
demned to sterility, but also vast areas in valleys and
plains are overlaid with sterile sediment, not to speak of
damage to roads, buildings, etc. The cost of such losses
and outlays involved in repairing the damage dons by
erosion in the world reaches a figure of incredible size.
Erosion is only the first phase of a serious chain reac¬
tion which starts with the regression or disappearance of
forests. Sediment deposited in reservoirs, water-courses,
fields and cities is an important part of the total damage.
This damage seldom comes to public attention because
It is often invisible. Sediment increases the total volume
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
TRADITIONAL TREE of the Lebanon, the cedar, has been replaced (above) near Beirut by these umbrella
pines, descendants of those planted a century ago by a far-seeing emir, to prevent encroachment of sand
dunes. In ancient times cedar wood was used in the building of Solomon's temple (a cedar still figures
in the flag of the Republic of Lebanon). But many forests that once flourished in the Middle East
and North Africa have disappearedvictims of man's improvidenceand are replaced by invading sands.
Plant a tree to feed a man
and weight of flow in water-courses thus raising the
height of flood peaks and their destructive power. In
drainage basins and reservoirs, sediment can reduce
water capacity in a short time.
Investigations made into the effect of silting on the
capacity of dams in Algeria, show several dams lost 100
per cent of their original capacity in a period of 74 to 96
years. Similar findings In the United States with respect
to annual storage depletion in numerous dams indicate
that from 0.09 to 31.53 per cent of the original storage
capacity is lost as a result of silting. Recently a mono¬
graph on the Arno river basin in Italy revealed that
2,670,000 tons of solid material are carried away annually
by the water flow, thus causing an average lowering of
land surface of almost one-inch a year.
Silting Is almost always associated with deforestation.
Dams fed from completely wooded watersheds practically
never silt up. Experiments carried out by the Tennessee
Valley Authority in 1955 showed that after reafforestation
and protection works had been completed, the volume of
sediment carried down by the river was reduced by 90 %.
The forest also plays an Important part in protecting
the soil against wind erosion and sand encroachment.
Dune stabilization by tree planting is a well-known
10 practice in many parts of the world. It is true that
almost any vegetation cover will stabilize loose soil and
prevent it from being eroded by wind and rain, but
forests are probably more effective because of their
height, density, deep-reaching roots and permanency.
It is a keenly debated question whether or not the
forest can bring about increased rainfall, or, at least,
make for its better distribution. There are indications
that the presence of forests may increase local rainfall,
though effects on a regional or continental scale have
not been demonstrated.
The denser the forest, the greater will be its power to
reduce wind velocity. One authority has proved this
protective effect and noted reductions in velocity of over
85 per cent. In Italy, tests have shown that the Cecina
forest reduced wind velocity by 56 per cent and a
hardwood coppice In the same region was responsible for
reductions of 89 per cent.
The importance of such protection against wind erosion
can hardly be exaggerated. In dry periods and on bare
land the particles of certain types of soil become so
severed from each other that a strong wind can easily
carry them away. The finer particles form clouds and
the coarser particles, whipped by the wind, roll and
bounce over the surface of the soil. Their movement is
halted whenever the wind slackens and they bank up In
pits, ditches, canals and sunken roads, or in the neigh¬
bourhood of sheltering objects where they may suffocate
crops. This is only one of the perils of strong winds.
Drying out of soil, direct damage to delicate products like
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
REBUILDING A FOREST. Arab schoolboy plants a seedling tree during a reafforestation campaign
near Gaza. Here, Palestine Arab refugees, young and old alike, have helped to reclothe these sandy wastes
with shrubs and trees. Campaigns of this kind are only one of the multifold efforts made by the United
Nations Relief and Works Agency (UNRWA) during the past 12 yearsprovision of food, living accommo¬
dation, schools, work, training facilities, etc.to help nearly one million refugees rebuild their lives.
fruit, and the distortion and stunting of exposed trees
can all be traced to this cause.
In countries where forests have to be restored, reaffor¬
estation offers an excellent opportunity to provide tran¬
sitional employment for workers who may find their
ultimate destination in forest industries which do not
yet exist. In Greece, for example, the proposed reaffor¬
estation programme could absorb several thousands of
people, mainly from mountain districts where work is
often hard to get. In Spain, the government's forestry
programme employed between 30,000 and 100,000 men,
according to the season, in 1956. A bold reafforestation
programme for the Eastern Mediterranean would provide
employment for some 145,000 to 200,000 men annually
over the next 10 to 20 years.
It is a striking fact that a number of countries have
never formulated a forest policy or passed a forest law,
in spite of evident symptoms of soil deterioration and in
spite of repeated warnings about the results of a further
decline.
One of them comes from Professor Flatscher, scientist
of the Academy for Soil Cultivation in Vienna. He has
estimated that the world's forests produce about 1,600
million cubic metres of timber a year whereas the volume
cut annually amounts to between 2,200 and 2,600 million
cubic metres. This indicates that the annual fellings are
about 50 per cent above the allowable cut.
Any private individual who sanctioned such improvid¬
ence would be held responsible for bad management and
would certainly be heavily penalized. But mankind as a
whole, It seems, can indulge in prodigal waste of this kind
without being in conflict with any law. The only explan
ation is perhaps that the inevitable results of violence
against the laws of nature seldom fall directly on those
who commit the offence.
Though forest areas and timber reserves are still
decreasing, there are a few bright spots where we may
confidently expect steady progress. The total forested
area of the world is estimated to be about 10,000 million
acres and these forests should be capable of providing
reasonably adequate supplies for a population larger than
now exists. But the provision of such supplies will entail
the treatment of all productive forests as renewable
crops, the opening up of forests which are not yet
accessible and the cessation of the widespread devasta¬
tion of forests which still continues.
Of the 4,000 million acres of the earth's original forest
area which man has destroyed, 1,000 million might well
be replanted especially since much of this land Is to be
found in places where the population is in greatest need
of the products of the forest.
The cost per day of the second world war was a little
over $500 million. The cost of one day of this war would
reafforest, at least, 20 million acres, and the cost of
50 days would be sufficient to reclothe the entire 1,000
million devastated acres with proper tree cover. Of
course, no one is so naive as to believe we are on the
verge of any such undertaking. But we are in possession
of scientific knowledge, industrial skill and technical
equipment which could be used to spread the potential
benefits of the forest to the uttermost ends of the
inhabited earth.
Condensed from Unesco's quarterly review "Impact of
Science on Society" - Vol. XI, 1961 n" 1.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
TODAY'S
CRISIS IN
ANTHROPOLOGY
by Claude Lévi-Strauss
IN A SHRINKING WORLD, from the tributaries
of the Amazon (right) to the mountain fastnesses
of New Guinea (below), traditional ways of life are
being transformed. But the so-called "archaic"
peoples are not simply vanishing into a void. They
are merging swiftly with other civilizations. Below,
in New Guinea, members of the Irabun clan wearing
ornate tribal headdresses listen to' a chief (now a
businessman and plantation owner) as he shows them
location of territory's government at Port Moresby.
Unesco - Dominique Darbois
W. Bindle - Australian News and Information Bureau.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
T;he important place social anthropology
holds in contemporary thinking may seem
paradoxical to many people. It is a science very much
in vogue: witness not only the fashion for films and books
about travel, but also the interest of the educated public
in books on anthropology.
Towards the end of the 19th century people were apt
to look to the biologist in their quest for a philosophy
of man and the world, and then later to the sociologist,
the historian, and even the philosopher.
But for the past several years anthropology has come
to play the same role, and today it too is expected to
provide us with deep reflections on our world and a
philosophy of life and hope.
It is in the United States that this approach to
anthropology seems to have begun. As a young nation
intent on creating a humanism of its own, America
broke with traditional European thinking. It saw no
reason why the civilizations of Greece and Rome should
be admired to the exclusion of all others merely because
in the Old World of the Renaissance, when mankind
One of the world's greatest living anthropologists, Claude Lévi-
Strauss has been professor of social anthropology at the famed
College de France, Paris, since 1959. Between 1935 and 1939,
he was professor of sociology at the University of Sao Paulo, and
led many scientific expeditions in central Brazil. He has written
many authoritative works including A World on the Wane
(Hutchinson, London) also published by USA. Criterion Books,
New York, under its French title, Tristes Tropiques.
came to be considered the most proper and necessary
study of man, these were the only two civilizations
sufficiently known.
Since the 19th century and especially the 20th,
practically every human society on our planet has become
accessible to study. Why then limit our interests? And
indeed, when we contemplate humanity in its entirety
we cannot fail to recognize the fact that for 99/100ths
of mankind's existence, and over most of the inhabited
globe, there have been no customs, no beliefs, no
institutions which do not fall within the province of
anthropological study.
This was strikingly emphasized during the last war
with the struggle waged on a world-wide scale. Even
the most obscure and remote corners of our planet were
suddenly catapulted into our lives and consciousness and
took on three-dimensional reality. These were the lands
where the last "savage" peoples on earth had sought
safety'in isolation the far north of America, New Guinea,
the hinterlands of south-east Asia, and certain islands
in the Indonesian archipelago.
Since the war many names, once charged with
mystery and romance, have remained on our maps but
now they designate landing spots for long-distance jet
liners. Under the impact of aviation and with increase
in world population our planet has shrunk in size, and
improved communications and travel facilities permit us
no longer to close our eyes or remain indifferent to other
peoples.
Today there is no fraction of the human race, no 13
matter how remote and retarded it may still appear,
which is not directly or indirectly in contact with others,
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
CRISIS IN ANTHROPOLOGY (Cont'd/
Last great sanctuary
of 'primitives'
and whose feelings, ambitions, desires and fears do not
affect the security and prosperity and the very existence
of those to whom material progress may once have given
a feeling of ascendancy.
Even If we wanted to, we could no longer ignore or.
shrug off with indifference, say, the last head-hunters of
New Guinea, for the simple reason that they are interested
in us. And surprising though it may be, the result of
our contacts with them means that both they and we
are now part of the same world, and it will not be long
before we are all part of the same civilization.
For even societies with the most widely divergent
patterns of thought and whose customs and mores took
thousands of years to evolve along isolated paths,
impregnate one another once contact is established.
This occurs in many, devious ways; sometimes we are
clearly aware of them, often we are not.
As they spread throughout the world, the civilizations
which (rightly or wrongly) felt that they had reached the
height of development, such as Christianity, Islamism,
Buddhism, and on a different level the ' technological
civilization which is now bringing them together, are all
tinged with "primitive" ways of life, "primitive" thinking
and "primitive" behaviour which have always been the
subject of anthropological research. Without our
realizing it the "primitive" ways are transforming these
civilizations from within.
For the so-called primitive or archaic peoples do not
simply vanish into a vacuum. They dissolve and are
incorporated with greater or lesser speed into the civiliza¬
tion surrounding them. At the same time the latter
acquires a universal character.
Thus, far from diminishing in Importance, primitive
peoples concern us more with each passing day. To take
only one example, the great civilization the West is
justly proud of and which has spread its roots across the
inhabited globe, is everywhere emerging as a "hybrid."
Many foreign elements, both spiritual and material, are
being absorbed Into its stream.
As a result, the problems of anthropology have
ceased to be a matter for specialists, limited
to scholars and explorers, they have become the direct
and immediate concern of every one of us.
Where, then, lies the paradox? In reality there are
two insofar as anthropology is chiefly concerned with
the study of "primitive" peoples. At the moment when
the public has come to recognize its true value, we may
well ask whether it has not reached the point where it
has nothing more left to study.
For the very transformations which are spurring a
growing theoretical interest in "primitives" are in fact
bringing about their extinction. This is not really a new
phenomenon. As early as 1908, when he inaugurated the
chair of Social Anthropology at the University of Liver¬
pool, Sir James Frazer (author of the monumental Golden
Bough) dramatically called the attention of governments
and scholars to this very problem. Yet we can hardly
compare the situation half a century ago with the large-
scale extinction of "primitive" peoples which we have
witnessed since then.
Let me cite a few examples. At the beginning of white
settlement in Australia, the Aborigénes numbered 250,000
individuals. Today no more than 40,000 are left..
Official reports describe them herded in reserves or
clustered near mining centres where in the place of their
traditional wild food gathering parties they are reduced
to sneak-scavenging in rubbish heaps outside the mining
shacks. Other aborigénes, who had retreated deep into
the forbidding desert, have been uprooted by the installa¬
tion of atomic explosion bases or rocket launching sites.
14 Protected by its exceptionally hostile environment, New
Guinea, with its several million tribesmen, may well be
the last great sanctuary- of primitive society on earth.
Madeiros
FROM JUNGLE TO FOOTBALL MATCH. Brazil's forest Indians have
declined in number drastically (I 00 tribes became extinct between I 900 and
I 950). But many of the surviving tribes continue to live under exactly the
same conditions and to observe the same customs of dress and ceremonial as
did their far-off ancestors. In Central Brazil, Kubenkranken Indians still consider
as an attribute of manhood their deformed lower lip (above left) which they
Indian Protection Service - N. Velloso.
&'^*
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Indian Protection Service - H. Foerthmann, '
stretch with progressively larger wooden plugs. At tribal ceremonies, Bororo
Indian men (above right) don the magnificent plumed headdress (made from
the feathers of the gaudy arara parrot). Yet a few years' contact with modern
civilization is sufficient to transform the dress, habits and tastes of these same
Indians. Below, Indian footballers from the same region as the tribesmen who
are shown above proudjy pose for a photographer before the start of a match.
All photos courtesy Darcy Ribeiro.
100 Brazilian tribes
disappear in 50 years
But here too, civilization is making such rapid inroads
that the 600,000 inhabitants of the central mountains,
who were totally unknown a mere twenty years ago,
are now providing labour contingents for the building of
roads. And it is no rarity today to see road signs and
milestones parachuted into the unexplored jungle!
But with civilization have come strange diseases, against
which "primitives" have no natural immunization and
which have wrought deadly havoc in their ranks. They
are succombing rapidly to tuberculosis, malaria, tra¬
choma, leprosy, dysentery, gonorrhea, syphilis, and the
mysterious disease known as kuru. The result of primi¬
tive man's contact with civilization, though not actually
introduced by it, kuru is a genetic deterioration which
inevitably ends in death and for which no treatment or
remedy is known.
In Brazil, 100 tribes became extinct between 1900 and
1950. The Kaingang, from the State of Sao Paulo,
numbering 1,200 in 1912, were no more than 200 in 1916,
and today have dwindled to 80.
The Munduruku were 20,000 in 1925in 1950 they
numbered 1,200. Of the 10,000 Nambikwara in 1900, I
could trace only a thousand in 1940. The Kayapo of the
River Araguaya were 2,500 in 1902 and 10 in 1950. The
Timbira 1,000 in 1900 and 40 in 1950.
How can this rapid decimation be explained? Fore¬
most, by the introduction of Western diseases against
which the Indian's body had no defence. The tragic fate
of the Urubu, an Indian tribe from north-eastern Brazil,
is typical of many others. In 1950, only a few years after
they were discovered, they contracted the measles. Within
a few days, out of the population of 750 there were 160
deaths. An eyewitness has left this stark description:
"We found the first village abandoned. All the
inhabitants had fled, convinced that if they ran far away
they would escape the sickness which they believed was a
spirit attacking the villages.
"We discovered them in the forest, halted in their
flight. Exhausted and shivering with fever in the rain,
nearly all of them had fallen victim to the disease.
Intestinal and pulmonary complications had so weakened
them that they no longer had strength to seek food.
"Even water was lacking, and they were dying as much
from hunger and thirst as from the disease. The children
were crawling about on the forest floor trying to keep the
fires alight in the rain and hoping to keep warm. The
men lay burning and paralyzed by fever; the women
indifferently thrust away their babes seeking the breast."
B ut in addition to infectious diseases, vitamin
and other nutritional deficiencies are also an
important problem. Motor-vascular disorders, eye lesions
and dental decay, unknown to primitive man when he
lived according to his ancient ways, make their appear¬
ance when he is confined to villages and must eat food
which does not come from his native forest. Then, even
the old and tried traditional remedies, such as charcoal
dressings for severe burns, prove useless. And simple
diseases to which tribesmen have long been accustomed,
become extraordinarily virulent.
The decimation of the Indians is due to other, less
direct, causes, such as the collapse of the social structure
or pattern of living. The Kaingang of Sao Paulo, already
mentioned, lived by a series of strict social rules with
which every anthropologist is acquainted. The inhabitants
of each village were divided into two groups on the
principle that the men from the first group could marry
only women from the second group and vice versa.
When their population diminished, the foundations
permitting their survival collapsed. Under the rigid
system of the Kaingang, it was no longer possible for
every man to find a wife and many had no choice but ,.-
celibacy unless they resigned themselves to mating within ia
their own group which to them was incest, and even
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
CRISIS IN ANTHROPOLOGY (Cont'd)
Taboo subject in new
independent states
then their marriage had to be childless. In such cases a
whole population can disappear within a few years (1).
Bearing this in mind, need we be surprised that it is
more and more difficult not only to study the so-called
primitive peoples but even to define them satisfactorily.
In recent years, a serious attempt has been made to revise
existing thinking regarding protective legislation in the
countries facing this problem.
Neither language nor culture nor the conviction of
belonging to a group, are valid as criteria for a definition.
As enquiries of the International Labour Organization
have emphasized, the notion oí indigenous people is being
superseded by the concept of indigence (2).
B
16
ut this is only one half on the picture. There
are other parte of the world where tens and
hundreds of millions of people live who were traditionally
the subject of anthropology. These populations are
increasing rapidly in number in Central America, the
Andes, south-east Asia and Africa. But here too, anthro¬
pology faces a crisis. Not because the populations are
dying out but because of the nature of the people involved.
These peoples are changing and their civilizations are
gradually becoming Westernized. Anthropology, however,
has never yet included the West within its competence
or province. Furthermore, and even more important,
there is a growing opposition in these regions to
anthropological enquiries. Instances have occurred
where regional museums of "Anthropology" have been
forced to change their names and can only continue dis¬
guised as "Museums of Popular Art and Tradition."
In the young states which have recently obtained
independence, economists, psychologists and sociologists
are warmly welcomed toy universities. The same can
hardly be said of the anthropologist.
Thus it would almost seem that anthropology is on the
point of falling victim to a dual conspiracy. On the one
hand are the peoples who have ceased physically to lend
themselves to study by simply vanishing from the face
of the earth. On the other are those who, far from dead,
are living a great population "explosion," yet are
categorically hostile to anthropology for psychological
and ethical reasons.
There Is no problem about how to meet the first of these
crises. Research must be speeded up and we must take
advantage of the few years that remain to gather all the
information we can on these vanishing islands of human¬
ity. Such information is vital for, unlike the natural
sciences, the sciences of man cannot originate their own
experimentation.
Every type of society, of belief or institution, every way
of life, constitutes a ready-made experiment the prepara¬
tion of which has taken thousands of years and as such
is irreplaceable. When a community disappears, a door
closes forever locking away knowledge which is unique.
That is why the anthropologist believes that it is
essential, before these societies are lost and their social
customs destroyed, to create sharper observation
techniques, rather like the astronomer who has brought
electronic amplifiers into play to capture the weakening
signals of light from distant stars racing away from us.
The second crisis in anthropology is much less serious
in the absolute since there is no threat of extinction to
the civilizations concerned. But it is much more difficult
to deal with out of hand. I wonder whether it would
help matters if we tried to dispel the distrust of the
people who were formerly the anthropologist's field work
by proposing that our research should henceforth no
longer be "one way only." Might not anthropology find
its place again if, in exchange for our continued freedom
(1) These observations on the disappearance oí the Indians of
Brazil are drawn chiefly from a study by the noted Brazilian
anthropologist, Dr. Darcy Rlbelro, entitled "Convivio et Contamlnaçao"
published In "Sociológica,", Vol. XVIII, No. 1, Sao Paulo, 1956.
(2) ILO. The Aboriginal Populations. Geneva. 1953.
ONE OF WORLD'S LAST UNEXPLORED REGIONS. New
Guinea is one of the last places in the world where "primitive tribes
exist which have never seen a white man". One of the last unexplored
regions here ceased to be so recently when a French anthropological
expedition led by Pierre-Dominique Gaisseau fought its way through
dense jungles, over 12,000 feet high mountains and along streams and
to investigate, we invited African or Melanesian
anthropologists to come and study us in the same way
that up to now only we have studied them?
Such an exchange would be very desirable for it would
enrich the science of anthropology by widening its
horizons, and set us on the road to further progress.
But let us have no illusions this would not resolve the
problem, for it does not take into consideration the deep
motives underlying the former colonized peoples' negative
attitude to anthropology. They are afraid that under the
cloak of an anthropological interpretation of history what
they consider to be intolerable inequality will be justified
as the desirable diversity of mankind.
If I may be permitted a formula which, coming from
an anthropologist, can have no derogatory connotation
even as pure scientific observation, I would say that
Westerners will never (except in make-believe) be able to
act the role of "savages" opposite those whom they once
dominated. For when we Westerners cast them in this
role they existed for us only as objects whether for
scientific study or political and economic domination.
Whereas we, who in their eyes are responsible for their
past fate, now appear to them inevitably as directing
forces and therefore it is much harder for them to look
at us with an attitude of detached appraisal.
By a curious paradox, it was undoubtedly a feeling of
sympathy that prompted many anthropologists to adopt
the idea of pluralism (this asserts the diversity of human
cultures and concommitantly denies that certain civiliza¬
tions can be classified as "superior" and others as
"inferior." Yet these very anthropologists and indeed
all anthropology are . now accused of denying this
inferiority merely to conceal it, and hence of contributing
more or less directly to its continued existence.
If therefore, anthropology is to survive in the modern
world, there can be no disguising that it must be at the
price of much deeper changes than a mere enlarging of
the circle (very restricted it is true up to now) by the
rather childish formula of offering to lend our toys to the
newcomers provided they let us go on playing with theirs.
Anthropology must transform its very nature and must
admit that, logically and morally, it is almost impossible
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
rivers from the Arafura Sea in the south to the north coast of New
Guineathe first expedition to cross the island from south to north.
To cover 500 miles as the crow flies it was obliged to travel 1,000 by
raft, canoe and on foot. From this epic seven-month journey, the anthro¬
pologists brought back much information including a magnificent record
on film of the isolated peoples in the heart of New Guinea. The seven
man team accompanied by sixty bearers was supplied from the air
twelve loads totalling ten tons were parachuted to them. Photos from
their full-length colour film, Le Ciel et la Boue (The River without a
Name) show tribesmen, some of whom had never seen a white man
before, in their pirogues (above) and supplies being dropped by para¬
chute (left) after radio operators have contacted the expedition's base.
to continue to view societies as scientific objects, which
the scientist may even wish to preserve, but which are
now collective subjects and claim the right to change as
they please.
The modification of anthropology's subject matter also
implies modifications in its aims and methods. And these
fortunately appear quite feasible for our branch of science
has never defined its purposes in the absolute but rather
as a relationship between the observer and his subject.
And it has always agreed to change whenever this
relationship has been modified.
Doubtless, the property of anthropology has always
been to investigate on the spot of "from within". But
only because it was impossible to investigate at a distance
or "from without." In the field of the social sciences,
the great revolution of our times is that whole civilizations
have become conscious of their existence, and having
acquired the necessary means to do so through literacy,
have embarked on the study of their own past and
traditions and every unique aspect of their culture which
has survived to the present day.
Thus, if Africa, for instance, is escaping from
anthropology, it will not so easily escape from science. In
place of the anthropologist that is the outside analyst,
working from the outsidestudy of the continent will
be in the hands of African scientists, or foreigners who
will use the same methods as their African colleagues.
They will no longer toe anthropologists but linguists,
philologists, historians of facts and ideas. Anthropology
will gladly accept this transition to richer, more subtle
methods than its own, confident that it has fulfilled its
mission by keeping alive so much of the great riches of
humanity on behalf of scientific knowledge, so long as it
was the only branch of science able to do so.
As to the future of anthropology itself, it seems to lie
now at the far extreme and the near extreme of its
traditional positions. At the far extreme, in the
geographical sense first, since we must go further and
further afield to reach the last of the so-called primitive
populations, and they are getting fewer and fewer; but
in the far extreme in its logical meaning too, since we
are now interested In the essentials.
On the near extreme, in the sense that the collapse
of the material foundations of the last primitive civiliza¬
tions has made their intimate experiences one of our last
fields of investigation in place of the weapons, tools and
household objects that have disappeared. But also
because as Western civilization becomes more complex
with each passing day and spreads across the whole of
the earth, it is already beginning to show signs of the
sharp differences which anthropology has made it its
business to study but which it could formerly do only by
comparing dissimilar and widely separated cultures.
Here, no doubt, lies the permanent function of
anthropology. For if there exists, as anthropologists
have always affirmed, a certain "optimum diversity"
which they see as a permanent condition of human
development then we may be sure that divergencies
between societies and groups within societies will
disappear only to spring up again in other forms.
Who knows if the conflict between the old and new
generations, which so many countries are now experienc¬
ing, may not be the ransom that must be paid for the
growing homogenization of our social and material
culture? Such phenomena seem to me pathological but
anthropology has always been characterized by its ability
to explain and justify forms of human behaviour which
men found strange and could not understand.
In this way anthropology at every phase has helped to
enlarge the currently held and always too constricting
view of humanity. To picture the disappearance of
anthropology, one would have to conjure up. a civiliza¬
tion where all men no matter what corner of the globe
they inhabited, and whatever their way of life, their educ¬
ation, their professional activities, their age, beliefs,
sympathies and aversions were, to the very roots of their
consciousness, totally intelligible to all other men.
Whether one deplores it, approves it, or merely states it
as a fact, technical progress and the development of
communications hardly seem to be leading us to this end.
And as long as the ways of thinking or of acting of some
men perplex other men, there will be scope for meditation
on these differences; and this, in a constantly renewing
form, will be the abiding province of anthropology.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18
UNITED NATIONS
FAMILY AT WORK
An International Labour Exhibition at Turin
from May until the end of October marked the
first centenary of Italian unification. Countries
and organizations from all over the world pro¬
vided exhibits offering a wide panorama of the
social and technical developments, as well as
deeper significances of human labour. On this
occasion the Italia 6 I Exposition arranged and
paid for a United Nations exhibition giving a
comprehensive picture of the work being done
by its family of specialized agencies in such fields
as food, hygiene, health, education, industry and
arid zones which influence directly or indirectly
many aspects of man and his labour. The UN
exhibit included not only a visual presentation
of UN institutions and agencies, but provided
as well an auditorium for film projections and
a reading room and library where UN publi¬
cations were on display. The Uneso Courier
sent photographer Paul Almasy to Turin for
pictures of the exhibition shown on these and
the following pages. Above left, a night-time
view of neon-studded Energy Pavilion. Left, a
symbolic presentation of the cost of armaments,
a tank- weighed on scales balancing on the
other side its cost in peaceful materials.
IHH
il
l
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Above, a graphic presentation
of the problem of over-popula¬
tion, one of a series of three at
the UN exhibit in Turin showing
the increase in population from
I860 to I960 and to the year
2000. Other problems which
the exhibit posed were those
arising from hunger, epidemics,
destruction of soil, poor working
conditions, unproductive working
methods, lack of hygiene and
educational facilities and unem¬
ployment. In all these fields,
the UN exhibit showed what its
agencies are doing to combat the
problems. Left, main exhibi¬
tion hall housing the UN exhibit.
19
All photos fg> Paul Almasy
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
A towering crankshaft (above
left) symbolizes the United
Nations with all its specia-
ized agencies labeled, show¬
ing how they work together.
Above, the display dealing
with peaceful uses of atomic
energy, atomic research and
regional economic commis¬
sions. Far left, a part of the
triple scales weighing the
cost of armaments against
productive social and econo¬
mic expenditures. Here a
submarine is balanced off
against the cost of a modern
school. The other two scales
weigh a tank and super bomb
against a modern factory and
a city skyscraper. Centre,
left, Unesco's arid zone exhi¬
bit showing uses of solar
energy. Left, FAO'S display
of locusts in connexion with
its exhibit on pest control.
All photos © Plul Almssy
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
RAYS FROM OUTER SPACE
by Alexander Gusev
T:he phenomenon of cosmic rays was discovered
some fifty years ago but still remains .in
many respects a puzzle to science.
We know that an inexhaustible stream of these rays
pours down on our earth from all directions, invading
us day and night with never a moment's rest.
This was the case when scientists first discovered the
rays ; this was the case before man existed on earth
countless millions of years before the earth itself was
born. And it will continue to be the case far into the
future.
The mysterious source of cosmic rays and the
amazingly constant state of the phenomenon have
remained undiscovered because they . "shine" simul¬
taneously in all directions. If it were possible to imagine
that they really did shine as brightly as the sun, we
should be imagining eternal daylight everywhere on the
surface of our planet. Cosmic rays, however, are invisible
and their "brightness" is about that of the night sky
when there is no moon.
P'hysicists have been making a careful study
of the rays ever since they were discovered.
Scientists have learned quite a lot. They have learned,
for example, that cosmic rays are not really rays at all,
such as, light rays or radio waves. They are a stream
of the tiniest particles moving at terrific (cosmic) veloci¬
ties, tens of thousands of times faster than our rockets
or artificial satellites.
There is nothing unusual about the particles that
constitute cosmic rays they are the atomic nuclei of the
lightest gases, hydrogen (known as protons) and helium
(alpha particles) which are well known to physicists.
These nuclei make up 85% to 90% of the stream. The other
part also consists of atomic nuclei, but they are those
of the heavier elements lithium, nitrogen, iron...
These particles are so small that if they could be
compared with a grain of sand they would look like
that grain of sand compared with the earth. Some
of them possess colossal energy, sufficient to melt the
grain of sand.
As soon as physicists discovered this, they asked dozens
of "whys".
Why is the stream of cosmic particles made up
precisely of these elements, how are the particles formed,
where are. they, how does the gigantic generator work
that for thousands of millions of years has been
producing these cosmic rays; where does the energy that
feeds them come from?
Science has not found conclusive answers to all these
questions. They can only assure us that the cosmic
rays come to us from our stellar system, from our own
galaxy, that their origin is probably connected with the
bursting of "super-nova" stars and that part of the
stream comes to us from the nearest star, the sun.
A great deal, however, has been discovered; needless
to say, scientists can explain that which is closer to
us and available for study the fate of the cosmic
particles in the earth's atmosphere and their "behaviour"
in the vicinity of the earth.
When people who have no connexion with science
first hear of cosmic rays and their study they often
ask: Why study them? To what practical use can they
be put ?
We may say straight out that no practical use for
cosmic rays is at present foreseen, but there is no doubt
that a double benefit is obtained from the study of them.
First, the study of cosmic rays gives scientists greater
insight into the secrets of our boundless universe and
also into the micro-world of the atoms, into the secrets
of the atomic nuclei, their component particles, and of
many other particles called elementary. To know more
about the properties of elementary particles and atomic
nuclei, scientists have to find out exactly what happens
when there are collisions between particles moving at
high velocities and, therefore, possessing tremendous
energy.
For this purpose huge accelerators have been built to
drive particles at velocities of 10 thousand million electron-
volts (Joint Institute for Nuclear Research, Dubna, USSR),
29 thousand million electron-volts (CERN the European
Centre for Nuclear Research, created by Unesco and
located in Switzerland), 33 thousand million electron-
volts (Brookhaven, USA). Still more powerful acceler¬
ators are being designed. None of the existing acceler¬
ators, nor those now projected, however, can compare
with the unknown cosmic accelerators.
Particles are met with in the cosmic stream that possess
energy hundreds of millions of times greater than that
obtained in the accelerators. These are the particles in
which physicists studying cosmic rays are most interested
If it is possible to learn the nature and properties of
elementary particles and, therefore, of atomic nuclei,
scientists may be able to design sources of energy so
powerful that they will greatly exceed the most fantastic
expectations of what controlled thermo-nuclear reactions
will bring; changes in natural conditions on earth and
other planets, flights to the planetary systems around
other stars, etc. will then become practically possible.
Si ECONDLY, the era of space flights, opened by
Soviet scientists and engineers on October 4,
1957 by the launching of the first artificial earth satellite
was soon followed by manned flights into outer space (1).
Cosmic rays are close "relations" to radio-active radia¬
tions, like those that cause radiation diseases. The earth
is protected by its atmospheric armour and, furthermore,
man is accustomed to the weak rays that penetrate that
armour. But in outer space? Is It not possible that future
rocket travellers, once they have left the atmosphere and
are on the threshold of outer space, will meet with death-
dealing rays? The study of cosmic rays has already pro¬
vided, the answer to this question.
The fate of cosmic particles flyng towards the earth
depends on their velocity, that Is, on their energy. Some
of them, moving at relatively low velocities, are deviated
from their straight-line flight at a considerable distance
above the earth's atmospheric layer and are caught in
the "trap" of the terrestrial magnetic field; the more
energetic of them break through the earth's magnetic
defences and enter the atmosphere.
Here they collide with atoms and atomic nuclei of gases
making up the atmosphere-oxygen, nitrogen, etc. In so
doing they destroy the atoms, converting them into ions
and, colliding with the atomic nuclei, split some of them,
Alexander Gusev is a doctor of physical sciences and a senior
22 research worker at the U.S.S.R. Academy of Sciences. He is Scien¬
tific Editor at the Foreign Literature Publishing House, Moscow,
and he has written several works on the theory of magnetism.
(1) by Major Youri A. Gagarin April 12, 1961, Commander
Alan B. Shepard, Jr. May 5, 1961, Captain Virgil I. Grissom
July 21, 1961, Major Gherman S. Titov landed August 1, 1961
after 25 hours' flight.
CONT'D ON PAGE 24
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
CERN
COLLISIONS
IN THE MICRO-WORLD
Cosmic rays, the nuclear particles which come from outer
space, collide with atoms and atomic nuclei in the earth's
atmosphere creating an avalanche of nuclear "catastrophes"
right down to the earth's surface. To find out what happens
when there are collisions between particules moving at high
velocities science has produced many devices, some huge,
all ingenious. At left and above, collisions of particles are
photographed in hydrogen bubble chamber experiments.
At left, one of 49,000 pictures taken during a series of
experiments in bubble chamber at CERN (European Orga¬
nization for Nuclear Research) Laboratory near Geneva. It
shows disintegration of two particlesa lambda zero and an
anti-lambda zero. Above, photo from the Dubna Atomic
Research Centre, U.S.S.R., showing explosion produced when
a cosmic particle collides with a nuclear atom. Below, a tech¬
nician at Dubna Centre operates accelerator control panel.
Official Soviet photos
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
RAYS FROM OUTER SPACE (Cont'd)
Thousands of particles pierce us every second
lose their energy and are dissipated in the atmosphere.
The fastest of the particles, those whose velocity is close
to that of light, are of the greatest interest. There is
nothing that can stop them they are not affected by the
magnetic field and even penetrate the thousand-kilometre
thickness of the atmosphere as easily as a bullet penetrates
a sheet of paper; and they "perish" only when they
reach the depths of the earth. Particles that enter the
atmosphere at such velocities may collide with atomic
nuclei but they do not change course and scarcely feel
the force of the collision. If, however, the fraction of
energy lost and transfered to the nucleus is an infinites¬
imal part of the particle's tremendous energy, for the
nucleus the collision is a catastrophe. The nucleus, in
a way, explodes. "Splinters" of it, the particles of
which it is composed, fly out in all directions. The
particles knocked off by the collision then collide
with other nuclei and cause countless new catastrophes,
although each successive one is of lesser power than those
that preceded it. This is called a cascade process; the
particles so formed are like an avalanche, constantly
increasing in number until they eventually reach the
earth's surface.
T he fast-moving particle from outer space that
sets the whole process in motion, therefore,
arrives on earth accompanied by its countless "progeny",
a suite that sometimes numbers thousands of millions
and covers several square kilometres. Physicists call these
streams cosmic showers.
Cosmic rays are sometimes studied by "capturing" one
of the particles in a pack of photographic plates made
with extra thick emulsion. When the fast-moving particle
is caught, one of the nuclei of the emulsion layer bursts,
leaving a bunch of traces or a "star" that is visible when
the plate is developed. The lower the energy of a cosmic
particle entering the earth's atmosphere, the fewer its
"progeny". All of them together, however, form the
shower that saturates the atmosphere and is constantly
descending on to the earth's surface; this incessant
stream was given the name of "cosmic rays" when it
was first discovered. Obviously, however, the fragments
resulting from collisions are secondary rays; the primary
rays are those that pierce the outer space.
The intensity of the secondary rays is such that one
particle per second passes through every square centi¬
metre at sea-level. Since we live at sea-level, or near it,
on the surface of the earth, every one of us is pierced
by thousands of cosmic particles every second. In the
course of the millions of years that life has been develop¬
ing on earth, the plants, animals and people have grown
"accustomed" to the particles and pay no particular
attention to them; biologists even believe that cosmic
rays are an important factor in evolution: that their
influence on heredity has caused the mutability of fea¬
tures thus assisting in natural selection.
The era of space rockets and artificial satellites marks
a new stage in the study of cosmic rays. Physicists have
now been able to send their instruments into outer space.
The earliest observations produced results of basic
significance. Belts of fast-moving particles were found
to encircle the earth one of them at a height of 600 to
5,000 kilometres from the earth's surface and the other
much higher, at about 12,000-60,000 kilometres. They
were called the inner and outer radiation belts. They
were formed and are maintained by the earth's magnetic
field, that field which causes the compass needle to deviate
(the earth itself is a gigantic magnet whose poles are
close to but do not coincide with the geographic poles).
It had long been known that this magnet causes the
deviation of the slow-moving particles from their path,
producing the latitude effect (the intensity of cosmic
rays on the earth's surface varies with latitude, being
weakest at the equator and increasing towards the higher
latitudes). Nobody, however, suspected the existence of
radiation belts. The discovery resulted from Soviet and
24 American observations carried out by artificial satellites.
Research in this field has been carried out by Prof. S.N.
Vernov in the U.S.S.R. and Dr. James A. Van Allen in the
U.S.A. Not only were the belts themselves discovered but
their origin was explained as being due to the effect of
the terrestrial magnetic field on cosmic particles.
Particles possessing relatively low energy, that is, those
whose energy is less than 10 thousand million electron-
volts (energies that we can obtain in our accelerators) are
captured by the magnetic field and revolve round the
earth, following a spiral path. When they reach the
polar area where the magnetic field Is stronger they are
reflected like light rays from a mirror and sent off
towards the opposite pole. Since the space in which
they move Is practically speaking a vacuum, there is
nothing to hinder their movement and they expend very
little energy; they are, therefore, able to make millions
of journeys back and forth from pole to pole, each of
which again reflects them as a mirror would. They cannot
fly off into outer space because they are held by the
magnetic field. They are, as it were, caught in a trap in
the vicinity of the earth. This is what we mean when we
speak of magnetic traps. The edge of the outer belt
approaches the earth in the region of the two poles where
it causes the phenomena of Aurora Borealis, magnetic
storms and radio interference.
The outer belt is "inhabited" mainly by electrons. The
inner belt consists mainly of protons and extends from
the plane of the equator to 40" latitude north and south.
It is higher in the southern than in the northern hemi¬
sphere. This is because the magnetic and geographic
poles do not coincide.
The intensity of the stream of particles within the belt
is very great so that their discovery has important prac¬
tical as well as purely theoretical significance. Flights to
outer space are being envisaged by scientists and en¬
gineers. Before much longer man, as well as instruments,
will fly into outer space to visit, first the nearer worlds
and then those that are more distant.
Among the thousands of dangers that lie in wait
for man in outer space one is very well known
radiation disease. We know that In "empty" space the
radiation level (two particles per second per square centi¬
metre) is not dangerous to man. Flight through a radia¬
tion belt will be dangerous. There are probably similar
belts around other planets that possess magnetic fields.
We now know that the radiation belts turn inwards
towards the poles, like the surface of an apple towards
the stalk on which it hangs. The poles, therefore, may be
regarded as conical funnels through which a rocket may
fly in safety and thus avoid crossing the radiation belt.
We also know that there are areas in outer space in
which fields of magnetic force exist. There must also be
a concentration of cosmic particles in those places. It is
possible that clouds of particles, captured by magnetic
fields, are moving in outer space. If a rocket should
accidentally pass through one of those clouds its crew
might die from radiation disease. In addition to this,
when a rocket is moving at a high velocity outside these
clouds the number of collisions with cosmic particles and
the energy of the collisions greatly increase. The walls
of the rocket become a source of secondary radiation of
great intensity.
These are all phenomena that must be investigated so
that the necessary protective measures can be effected. It
is, therefore, important to study the magnetic fields of
other planets together with their radiation belts in order
to find the funnels that will ensure freedom from radia¬
tion during a landing. So far the only measurements that
have been made are those that concern our immediate
neighbour, the moon. Information received from the
Soviet cosmic rockets shows that the moon has no
magnetic field and no radiation belts. We now know,
also, that the radiation belt depends on the magnetic
field.
It is possible that we shall soon learn a great deal about
the moon and other planets such as Mars and Venus,
especially about their magnetic fields, and shall be able
to start work on the first projects for a safe landing on
their surfaces.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
t
'
<9 -»»>-^
- *?=*
Jfl*
Photos Norwegian Embassy, Paris
Fridtjof Nansen, the centenary of whose birth is being celebrated this year, was an Arctic explorer of original
genius. His revolutionary ideas were derided and greeted with scepticism by other experts of his day.
Yet all his projects met with resounding success. Above, the Fram, Nansen's ship drifted locked in the
Arctic ice three years and then came safely home. Inset, Nansen in 1897, after his Polar Sea expedition.
THE SAGA OF
FRIDTJOF NANSEN
by Robert Gladwell
Aman shall and must be valiant; he must march
forward and quit himself like a man."
These words, written by the English historian, Thomas
Carlyle, serve well to introduce Fridtjof Nansen, for
during the 68 years of his life (he was born near Oslo in
Norway in 1861 and died in May 1930) Nansen can be
said to have lived up to all they mean and imply. He
himself, in 1926, in an address to the students of St.
Andrew's University, chose to quote these words from
Thomas Carlyle : "The first of all problems for a man is to
find out is what kind of work he is to do in the universe."
And then Nansen added: "But even this little problem
Robert Gladwell is a prominent British TV and radio writer and
producer. He has written a number of biographical radio documentary
programmes for Unesco including the one commemorating the
100/A anniversary of Nansen's birth from which the article on this
page has been adapted.
I had not been able to solve. I had a leaning to science;
but which science? Physics and chemistry interested me
most; but Master Irresponsible over whom I had no
control at that time did not like that kind of life much.
One day he suddenly took it into his head that zoology
would be better, as that promised more fun more
shooting, and outdoor life. Consequently we went In
for zoology.
"Then one day the irresponsible creature suddenly
suggested we should go on a voyage to the Arctic Sea,
under the pretext of studying the animal life of the
Polar Regions. I was twenty then and off we went!
That was the first fatal step that Jed me astray from the
quiet life of science."
Nansen ended his speech to the students of St.
Andrew's with this statement: "The first great thing is
to find yourself, and for that you need solitude and
contemplation; at least sometimes. I tell you deliverance
will not come from the rushing, noisy centres of civiliza¬
tion. It will come from the lonely places."
25
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Norwegian Embassy, Paris
MOUNTAINOUS GLACIERS of
Greenland, the world's largest island
(left). The interior of this barren terrain
had never been explored when Nansen
decided to cross it on skis from east to
west in 1888. His hazardous and
exhausting journeyat times the thermo¬
meter dropped to 45 degrees C
took two and a half months. Above, Nan-
sen on an Arctic hunting trip in 1896.
Paul Almasy
NANSEN (Cont'd)
Champion of starving and homeless peoples
By the time he had spoken those words, at the age of
64, Fridtjof Nansen could claim not only to be familiar
with, but also an expert on, the lonely places. At the
age of 26, he had made the first successful crossing of
Greenland, on skis.
When he proposed to his first wife, the singer, Eva Sans,
he is reputed to have added: "But I must get up to the
North Pole." In 189.3 his polar ship, the Fram, built to
his special design, set sail for Arctic waters, and it was
another three years before Nansen saw civilization again.
Years later, too after the 1914-1918 war in his work for
the victims of famine and refugees, he often stood alone,
fighting a fearless battle against the indifference,
hypocrisy and prejudice of politicians.
Fridtjof Nansen had two great claims to fame. He was
an Arctic explorer of original genius who defied tradition
in his expeditions across Greenland in 1888, and in the
polar ship Fram (which significantly means Forward)
during 1893 to 1896. His second claim is symbolized in
the award to him of the Nobel Peace Prize in 1922.
Between 1896 and 1914 he gave himself to the scientific
research he loved so much, with a brief interlude as
Norwegian Minister in London, after his country had
gained its full Independence by leaving the union with
Sweden due in no small part to his efforts and advocacy.
After the end of the first world war he devoted himself
to humanitarian work and to the League of Nations.
His first great task was the repatriation of half a million
"lost" prisoners-of-war: and then, indefatigably, he
turned to the far more difficult task of finding homes for
refugees.
Thousands and thousands of men and women came to
bless the introduction of the Nansen Certificate, the
Nansen Passport, as the key to citizenship. One of the
causes he embraced with typical compassion and vigour
was that of the Armenian people. This was after the
near extermination of large groups of the Armenian
people in 1915.
By 1928 Nansen had settled no less than 7,000 refugees
in Armenia, and in 1922 he signed an agreement which
ensured 12,000 new dwellings there. That was a great
joy to him, but he had to inform the Council of the
26 League of Nations that, in view of the apathy of the
Great Powers, he had been unable to raise the loan
necessary to carry on the work.
Nansen's faith in the League of Nations was often
shaken, but not his faith in the Armenians and their
future. Eight years after his death, Michael Hansson,
the then head of the Office which carried on Nansen's
work, in a speech, accepting the Nobel Peace Prize on
behalf of the Nansen Office, said:
"I remember on a visit to Aleppo, a dinner that was
given in my honour by the Armenians there. Of course,
I had to make a speech, and at the first mention of
Nansen's name the entire company rose to its feet and
stood for a minute or two in silent prayer. Later when I
mentioned this incident to one of my Armenian hosts,
he said: "We Armenians believe that Nansen sits at the
side of our Lord watching over the Armenian people."
In his twenties, Nansen himself had spoken with
homage of another people, the Eskimos; and his
experiences among "that brave little people," as he
called them, and his deep affection for them, was reflected
and turned to practical account years later in his work
on behalf of refugees, such as the Armenians, and other
homeless minorities. After the Greenland adventure in
1888 he wrote:
"The Eskimo considers his foremost social duty is to
help others. They find it unthinkable that some should
live in plenty while others suffer want. They live lives
of constant danger and suffering, and yet they take joy
in life. And yet this Is the people that we Europeans
have thought ourselves justified in looking down upon.
"The purpose of our mission and civilizing work in
Greenland should be to benefit the natives. But what
have we done? All we have achieved with our reforms
is to demoralize this natural people, ruin their health
and destroy their freedom and independence."
These were brave words for a young man of twenty-
eight. But then Nansen was never lacking in bravery,
just as he never lacked moral courage, determination or
enterprise. When, for instance, he first put forward his
plan for crossing Greenland on skis he was greeted from
quite a few knowledgeable quarters with scorn and
derision.
The very method, remarked one Danish explorer, by
which Nansen proposes to reach the coast, that is to say,
by abandoning the firm ship's deck and creeping like a
polar bear from one rocking icefloe to another on his
way to the shore, shows such absolute recklessness that
it is scarcely possible to criticize it seriously.
CONT'D ON PAGE 28
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Viollet Collection
Taken from "Great Norwegian Expeditions", Dreyers Forlag, Oslo
ARCTIC ENCOUNTER of Nansen and Johansen with the
British explorer Frederick Jackson and members of his party
(above), took place in 1896 when the two Norwegians were
travelling south after journeying on foot to within 200 miles
of the North Pole. Left, icefloes in the polar night, a drawing
by Nansen, who was a talented artist. After the first world war,
Nansen added to his already world-famed achievements by
devoting himself to the repatriation of prisoners and relief of
refugees. Below, the steamship "Baghdad" arrives at Stettin
loaded with prisoners of war repatriated from Russia. Inset,
the Nansen medal, awarded annually in recompense for excep¬
tional services to the cause of refugees. It bears the words
taken from Nansen's writing: "Love of man is practical policy."
jzWÊp^,
UNHCR
- i
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
NANSEN (Cont'd)
Drifting for three years on the Arctic ice
What, exactly, was Nansen's plan for crossing Green¬
land? He published it in the Norwegian journal, Naturen,
in January 1888. "The points on which I wish to lay most
emphasis "he wrote," are that the party should consist of
three or four expert skiers. And that they should land
as near to the east coast of Greenland as possible and
cross over to the settlements on the west.
"I feel certain from my own experiences as a skier
and from the results of Nordenskiold's Expedition of 1883,
that where the snow conditions are favourable greater
progress can be made on ski than by any other means.
By crossing from east to west one will burn one's boats
behind one; there will be no need to urge one's men on,
as the east coast will attract no one back, while in front
will be the colonies of the west coast with all the allure¬
ments and amenities of civilization."
This policy of cutting off the line of retreat was typical
of Nansen. It can be seen in much of his work as an
explorer. He preferred to work with small parties so that
risk of loss of life might be minimized in fact no life
was ever lost on his expeditions and then to take the
most straightforward, even if most hazardous, course of
action.
He was sometimes criticized for the apparently
foolhardy risks that he ran, but there was more than
boldness in his schemes; there was also infinite care and
labour in the preliminary arrangements. He was no
impractical dreamer. The problems that faced him in
planning his Greenland expedition were no simple ones.
He had to consider how to reach the coast, how to
surmount the difficulties of the rugged costline and how
best to prepare for crossing the ice-sheet. Nansen's
careful preparations show that he had clearly visualized
each of these problems.
In May, 1888, Nansen and his small party set
sail for Iceland. They then boarded a sealer
(called the Jason) that was to take them through the
Denmark Strait to the east coast of Greenland. Once on
the ice, it took Nansen two months to reach the highest
point 9,000 feet but the party still had to labour hard
against a head-wind as they hauled their sledges over
the bad surface.
It was at this moment of the journey on September
5 that one of the Lapps in the party exclaimed:
"O, Satan, no one can know how far it is from coast
to coast, for no one has ever been here before!"
Nansen himself was not quite certain how far they still
had to go. He was beginning to fear that they had over¬
estimated the day's marches. On September 17, 1888,
two months had elapsed since they had left the Jason,
but it was also the first morning that the inside walls
of their tent had not been thick with hoar frost. Then,
all at once, they thought they could hear a bird twittering.
They leapt from the tent and there was a snow-bunting.
Soon they caught sight of another.
Later Nansen recalled "we blessed the two snow-
buntings: the one which gave us a last greeting from the
east coast and the other that bade us welcome to the
west coast."
The news of the first successful crossing of Greenland
reached Europe on November 9, 1888, but as no ship dared
risk coming that far North to take them back to civiliza¬
tion, the members of the expedition had to settle down
to a winter In Greenland. It was not till May 30, 1889,
that Nansen and his party sailed back into Oslo Fjord,
with the sun shining, to be greeted by hundreds of sailing
boats, a whole fleet of steamers, and wildly cheering
crowds. Fridtjof Nansen suddenly found himself world-
famous.
Nansen's expedition established that Greenland Is a
land covered with ice, and provides a fairly accurate
picture of what conditions were in Northern Europe and
North America during the Ice-Age. It was Nansen who
discovered that the interior of Greenland constitutes a
28 pole of maximum cold that is of the greatest significance
for large parts of the Northern Hemisphere. The expedi
tion supplied other valuable scientific information and
also an impetus to further exploration.
Fridtjof Nansen's reaction to fame was typical of the
man. He summed it up this way: "Now that I have had
a taste of fame, and can see what its real value is, I
aspire after it no more."
On his return to Norway, Nansen again took up his job
as curator of the Zoological Museum in Bergen and he
toured most of the countries of Europe giving lectures.
But while still in Greenland he had been working on
another plan. He had dreams of another expedition, a
plan to cross the North Pole. It was a bold and original
idea based on two bits of evidence.
In 1884, Nansen had read of how an American yacht,
having become frozen in the Arctic, had drifted with the
ice across the polar regions; and a piece of Siberian
larchwood was also known to have drifted right across
the Pole. He therefore planned a ship so strong and of
such a shape that instead of being crushed by the ice
when the sea froze, she would rise above it, like an orange
pip when pinched between the fingers.
The result was his famous polar vessel, the Fram.
Schooner-rigged, and fitted with engines, she was a ship
of 400 tons, 128 feet long, 36 feet broad and with sides
two feet thick.
In November of 1892 Nansen journeyed to London to
lay his sensational North Pole Plan before the Royal
Geographical Society. Most of the Society received it
with scepticism, even alarm. It was, exclaimed the
President, the most daring plan ever put before the
Society.
According to Nansen's daughter that famous evening
was of minor significance as far as her father was
concerned. She wrote: "The expedition had to go
forward. Mother believed in him and everybody else
could think what they liked. Four years later he was back
in London, this time to report on the results of the Fram
expedition. Most of those who had been at the meeting
of November 14, 1892 were among the several thousand
assembled in the Albert Hall. Everyone stood up as
Nansen came in, and the orchestra struck up the victor's
hymn from Handel's 'Judas Maccabeus.' Nansen said that
was probably the proudest moment of his life.
"It was not the hope of fame or material gain that
impelled Nansen, but it was certainly in his nature to
want to know and see. He would gladly hazard his life
to lift the fringe of the veil that hid the secrets of the
Arctic Ocean. Many had tried to do so before him, and
many had perished thereby. But they had been working
against the forces of nature, not with them, and it was
that which was decisive."
"The idea of using the ocean current had come to
Nansen in a flash of inspiration and had grown into a
mighty plan which he could no longer give up without
being untrue to himself."
The Fram sailed from Oslo, then called Chris¬
tiana, in June 1893, with a crew of thirteen
and thirty sledge dogs. By September she had got as
far as Chelyuskin, the most northerly point of Siberia.
Soon the ice was 30 feet thick. Then came the 'nip':
the ship groaned and trembled and then, as Nansen had
predicted, she broke from the terrifying grip of the ice
and rose upward till she was safe on top of it. The drift
of the Fram had begun and there was no going back.
This, Nansen knew, was a time when all his crew must
be fully occupied, so the scientific instruments were set
up, a camp built on the ice for the dogs, and hunting
expeditions organized. The ship drifted slowly northward
for a year; and then began to drift westward. It was
then, Nansen decided, that the moment had come to
leave the Fram and make a dash for the Pole. He tells
of his plans himself: "With Johansen as my one compan¬
ion, and twenty-eight dogs, three sledges, carrying our
two kayaks, our Eskimo canoes, a tent, sleeping bags,
scientific instruments and stores, we parted from the
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Fram and set off across the ice. By April, 1895, Johansen
and I had reached a point only 200 miles from the Pole,
farther North than any previous explorer. The
temperatures were forty below zero, our clothes and
sleeping bags were frozen stiff: the dogs were exhausted.
I decided to turn back, to give up the attempt to reach
the Pole."
Nansen and Johansen travelled for four months, during
which time the Fram was drifting. More than once they
were in danger of their lives. At one point they were
suddenly attacked by a polar bear. Another time as they
climbed on an iceberg to get their bearings, their kayaks
went adrift, and were only saved by Nansen's plunging
into the icy waters to retrieve them. Another time
Nansen's canoe was attacked by a huge bull walrus and
nearly destroyed. Finally the two men had to dig
themselves in for the winter, which they did by building
themselves a hut with tools made from walrus tusks.
When eventually Nansen and Johansen got back to
Norway, after their winter in the ice, they had been away
for more than three years, and they got back to be told
that there was no news of the Fram and her crew. A
week later she turned up, having drifted right round the
Pole and come safely back, just as Nansen had hoped and
predicted.
The greatest geographical result of the expedition was
the unexpected discovery of a deep polar sea. It was the
Arctic deep with its covering of ice and extraordinary
temperatures that interested Nansen most. As a trained
zoologist, he devoted his energies to the physical problems
of oceanography, a science that was growing rapidly then,
at the turn of the century, and which he did much to
promote.
While the Fram was drifting, he noticed that the ice
always moved to the right of the direction of the wind
and concluded that this must be due to the effect of the
earth's rotation. He expanded this idea; it was the wind
that sets the ice in motion. The rotation of the earth
causes every movement on the earth to be exposed to
a stress that in the northern hemisphere works to the
right. Because of this stress the ice does not drift in the
direction of the wind but to the right of it. Thus it was
Nansen who was the originator of the modern theory of
wind-driven currents.
Like so many of Nansen's new ideas, that of wind-driven
currents encountered opposition from many experts. But
today most manuals of oceanography give Nansen the
honour of being the first to have thought out a solution
to the problem.
Nansen would have preferred to have pursued his
scientific work, 'the quiet life of science,' but after the
first world war, he felt that his greatest duty lay in serving
the victims of that war. In 1922 he was awarded the
Nobel Peace Prize in recognition of his untiring work for
the benefit of mankind. He made many speeches at
the League of Nations on behalf of distressed peoples,
but his pleas for the victims of famine and political
discrimination, were not always successful.
With the years Nansen, the scientist, became over¬
shadowed by Nansen the humanitarian. His polar
explorations, as was natural, were better known than his
scientific activities though both the Greenland and Fram
expeditions were for scientific purposes. Nevertheless a
scientist he was heart and soul.
In 1930, he planned to celebrate his 69th birthday by
flying to the North Pole in Dr. Eckener's Graf Zeppelin.
He saw the Zeppelin as an aid to scientific investigation,
but he died that year at the age of 68. On his death
tributes came from all over the world; and by many
thousands his name was remembered as that of the man
who had brought them home from exile.
In the Eleventh Assembly of the League of Nations his
achievements were recalled with gratitude and pride.
Here are the words of the British delegate, Lord Robert
Cecil: "We all remember his striking figure when he came
to the tribune, with that rugged eloquence so peculiarly
his own, to support some cause in the interests of peace
and humanity. It is no exaggeration to say that Dr. Nan-
sen was the very embodiment of truth, candour and
upright feeling. Every good cause had his support. His
work for refugees was characteristic of the man, and was
admirable work done without regard to the interests of
himself, or even his health, work which conferred
immense benefits on some of the most helpless of his
fellow men."
Nansen was buried on May 17, Norway's Constitution
Day, an anniversary that had been celebrated in the
Fram, out on the Arctic wastes with Johansen, and in 1905
by his great speech to his countrymen when Norway
gained her independence.
The above article is an abridgement of a radio pro¬
gramme produced by the Radio Division of Unesco in the
Studios of Unesco House in Paris.
SAMPLING THE SOUP at a children's relief feeding centre in Armenia, Nansen demonstrates the
devotion with which he shouldered the tremendous problem of caring for millions of refugees and displaced
persons. Below right, a young Greek refugee doing justice to a meal supplied by "Nansen Relief". The
work carried on by Nansen right up to his death saved countless lives including those of six million
children who would otherwise have perished during the great famine which occurred in Russia in 1921-22.
Norwegian Embassy, Paris UNHCR
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30
UNICEF
GREETING
CARDS 1962
From a modest beginning of 130,000
in 1950, UNICEF (The United Nations
Children's Fund) greeting cards sold
more than 17 million last year, pro¬
viding enough funds to equip 20,000
small maternal and child health
centres. Nowadays, UNICEF is not
only known for its world-wide pro¬
grammes to help children, but also
for its greeting cards designed by
some of the world's great artists.
All proceeds from the sales of cards
are used to help supply food and
medicine to sick and hungry children.
This year UNICEF has added Picasso
to its gallery of well-known names.
"Haven," a design by this world-
renowned artist and reproduced from
a tapestry which hangs at United
Nations Headquarters in New York,
has been chosen as the official
United Nations card. From Pakistan,
M,A. Rahman Chughtai, a master of
that country's contemporary art has
contributed a delicately toned desert
scene, "The Star" and Turkish artist
Bedri Rahmi Eyuboglu has offered a
design "The Journey" characteristic
of contemporary art in his country,
which shows a woman, wearing a
yashmak, and two children on horse¬
back. French illustrator André Fran¬
çois has created five designs on the
theme, "A Child's World," showing
youngsters having the time of their
lives on swings, at a party, on a boat
ride, at a circus and riding on the
back of a violin-playing whale. Fin¬
ally, Eskimos from Baffin Island, Can¬
ada, have contributed five designs,
"Arctic Life" (see opposite page).
UNICEF cards come in boxes of ten
(at $ 1.25 (U.S.A.); 7/6 (U.K.) and
5 NF (France) per box, and each
box sold makes it possible for UNI¬
CEF to supply vaccine to protect
50 children against tuberculosis.
For Further information, orders etc.,
write: UNICEF Greeting Card Fund, 1 4/ 1 5
Stratford Place, London W. I.; United
Nations Association in Canada, Committee
for UNICEF, 280 Bloor Street West,
Toronto 5, Ontario (Att: Mrs. G. Richard);
U.S. Committee for UNICEF, P.O. Box 22,
Church Street Station, New York 8, N.Y.
\Att: Miss Olga Gechas) or UNICEF, Ser¬
vice des Cartes deV 24, rue Borghèse,
Neuilly-sur-Seine, France.
Happy Landing, a "Child's World" design by André François of France.
The Star, designed by Pakistani
artist M.A. Rahman Chughtai.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
ARTISTS FROM
CANADA'S
FAR NORTH
Cape Dorset is a tiny Eskimo trading village
in Canada's Baffin Island, an isolated speck
amid the frozen inlets and howling winds of
the Arctic Circle. Yet here in a small cluster
of frame houses and snow huts lives a
remarkably talented group of artists. Some
of the finest Eskimo stone and ivory carvings
come from Cape Dorset which is also the
birthplace of a newly developed Eskimo
graphic art form. The handsome designs
on this page are the work of Cape Dorset
Eskimos. Entitled "Arctic Life," their designs
are being sold this year as greetings cards
by UNICEF. These artists of the far north,
who first cut out the UNICEF designs into
sealskin stencils, have depicted scenes from
their everyday lives: children and dogs
playing before an igloo ; a caribou, arctic
gulls in flight; an Eskimo with a dog team
and sled ; and sea pigeons (known as pen¬
guins in the Antarctic). In his art, the Eskimo
can capture the look of an injured bear, the
tension of a hunter standing over a seal
hole or the rhythm in a flight of birds. But
the work of these artists, whose ancestors
already lived at Cape Dorset 3,000 years
ago, is also alive with the mythological.
December Igloo, by Mungituk.
4W
Sea Pigeons, by Ikhaluk.
Arctic Gulls, by Kananginak.
Caribou, by Pootagook.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor...
MEXICO'S PRIMARY SCHOOLS
Sir,
With reference to your June (Latin-
American) issue, Mr. Oscar Vera,
author of the article "70 Million Illi¬
terates," states that over the last three
years primary school attendance in
Mexico has increased by 18%. This
is inaccurate; the true increase in the
percentage of attendance within the
federal primary school system of my
country is 46.39.
I take the liberty of sending you
the following data on the number of
pupils enrolled over the last three
years in federal primary schools, as
well as in private, municipal and state
establishments of the same kind.
Pupils registered in 1958 in
federal primary schools 2,166,650
Enrolment in 1959 	 306,949
2,473,599
Enrolment in 1960 	 444,083
2,917,682
Enrolment in 1961 	 254,086
3,171,768
The total number of
registrations in private,
municipal and state pri¬
mary schools is : 	 2,196,479
Total number of stu¬
dents in primary schools
in 1961 : 	 5,368,247
Dr. Silvio Zavala
Permanent Representative of Mexico
to Unesco, Paris
I LIKE PICASSO
Sir,
In the July-August issue of The
Unesco Courier you published a let¬
ter from a Soviet reader expressing
doubts concerning Picasso's talent. I
am well aware that some people may
not like Picasso. But such expressions
as "disgustingly distorting" deeply
shock me.
I like Picasso very much. Often I
hear people say of some formless,
meaningless work in bad taste, "it
looks like Picasso". And that pains
me.
"What benefit do his drawings, pub¬
lished in your journal, bring to peo¬
ple?" asks your Soviet reader. Well,
I would like to say briefly what bene¬
fit Picasso has brought to me.
' At a time when I was full of doubts
about the use and beauty of living I
came across Picasso's work, and
"Guernica" in particular, which caus¬
ed me one of the greatest human and
artistic emotions I have ever expe¬
rienced. Picasso and his "Guernica"
contributed in a large measure to res¬
toring my joy in diving and the desire
to fight with brother men throughout
the world so that the tragedy of life
might become an optimistic tragedy.
What is so helpful in Picasso's work
(at least to me) is his controlled
strength and his confidence in the
beauty and greatness of man despite
all the horror and pettiness of life.
A special issue of The Unesco Cou¬
rier on Picasso (like the December
1960 issue on Velazquez) might en¬
able certain readers to learn to like
Picasso. In any case it would be a
great pleasure to those who like him
already.
Mme Camelin
Teacher, Jura, France
A PERFECT BALANCE
Sir,
Congratulations on your July-Au¬
gust 1961 issue. Each article in it
was worth being featured as the lead
article in any journal in the world;
and all the articles together formed
the ideal the dream of any editor:
the perflectly balanced issue. I shall
save it and show it around as
an example of what can be done to
achieve the goal of merging the arts,
the natural, and the social sciences.
Frederick C. Dyer
Washington, D. C.
Sir,
I am not given to writing "letters
to the editor" they are so often
suspect vehicles for ill-informed ob¬
servation.
But I am moved strongly to write
in very real appreciation of your July-
August issue. The juxtaposition of
these two erudite examinations of
man's complementary means of expres¬
sion {Art and Science) is masterly;
the articles are model epitomes of the
vast subjects they survey.
Very many thanks to all those
who helped to prepare so worthy an
addition to the "Courier" treasure-
house.
Brian Sheppard
Woodford Green
Essex
ROUSSEAU WAS SWISS
Sir,
In The Unesco Courier (June
1961) I was surprised to see J.-J. Rous¬
seau described as French. As a
Swiss I can assure you that Rous¬
seau was a citizen of the Republic of
Geneva in Switzerland. So he was
therefore of Swiss origin.
Dr. W. Lotz
Riehen, Switzerland
DANGEROUS LIBRARIES
Sir,
While your May issue filled me
with enthusiasm and taught me much
about photography, tnicrophotography
and strobophotography, I smile with
indulgence at the academic tommyrot
of André Maurois... Libraries are
more dangerous than the atomic bomb.
Claude L. Autant-Lara
Producer, Paris
THE INTERNATIONAL SHEAF
Sir,
I was pleasantly surprised to see a
long article devoted to one of the
extracurricular activities of my friend,
Lagrave, a teacher in Cameroon.
Some years ago my class corresponded
with the Pitoa class for quite a while
and we even sent Lagrave a few docu¬
ments on Belgium to help him to pre¬
pare a new scheme: Children round
the World.
I belong to the same educational
group as Lagrave and help to run a
children's magazine which publishes
writings and drawings, by schoolchil¬
dren from all over the world. Some
114 classes from wide and far have
responded to our appeal to date.
This magazine well deserves its
name, La Gerbe Internationale (The
International Sheaf). Its sole aim is to
enable children to work together in¬
ternationally and thus bring about
better mutual understanding.
Maurice Joachim
Waremme, Belgium
WHY IGNORE HAITI?
Sir,
It is difficult to understand how
any issue on Latin American Indepen¬
dence could fail to mention Toussaint
L'Ouverture, and Haiti, the country
he liberated.
Actually, the Haitians started then-
revolution against their French rulers
before the Boston Tea Party. While
still fighting the French, on Haitian
soil, they shipped men and arms to
aid the American colonies in their
struggle against the British.
Simon Bolivar lived in Haiti, while
in exile. After his return to South
America, he received financial support
from this same country, where his
revolutionary strategy was drawn up.
Its political history has been a
stormy one, because in 1804 there was
no organization like the United Na¬
tions to help new nations. Never¬
theless, Haiti was the world's first
negro republic, and the New World's
first colony to fight for independence.
Carolyn J. Seefeldt
Director of Social Service
Northville State Hospital
Michigan (U.S.A.)
Ed. note: The February 1954 issue
of the Unesco Courier was devoted
in major part to Haiti on the occasion
of the 150th anniversary of its inde¬
pendence.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
A
LIGHTER
SIDE
TO
WILD
LIFE
Our September issue on the
protection of wild life in
Africa has inspired this
series of humorous drawings
by Cram, a young Spanish
painter from Barcelona, who
is probably better known
for his paintings under
his real name, Marc Aleu.
jyt
M ¡¡PIÉ
«ps
«iM.'.V
"." -s
'"W'lllijMJjWU
ill '.....'!i,1'/''lli'''!
<..'lll'|l,nU,l,ll ..n'1'."" 	 « " , ''|,|l.,,l;-,'!'" V,',^- '"' I
WILD GAME RESERVE
títOKi,
33
tiimt^nwfliiHdiiii1
WE WANT PEACE (TOO)
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
SYMBOL OF SPIRITUAL UNITY
The striking building (above) is the proposed
design for "The Temple of Understanding, "
a centre providing knowledge and informa¬
tion on the world's six major religions, which
is planned for construction in Washington,
D.C., U.S.A. Sponsors of the project, originat¬
ed by an American, Juliet Hollister, see the
structure as a symbol of spiritual unity and
universal understanding for all people on
eartha sort of " Spiritual United Nations. "
The building, designed by the American
architect Lathrop Douglass, will consist of a
central core of glass and marble from which
six wings will radiate, each representing one
of the six religions which are international in
scope: Hinduism, Judaism, Buddhism, Confu¬
cianism, Christianity and Islam. The Temple
is not intended as a h >use of worship, but as
an educational edifice and it will contain
comprehensive libraries on each of the major
faiths. It is hoped to construct and maintain
it through small contributions from all parts
of the globe.
NEW HOMES FOR SALMON: In
recent years Soviet scientists have been
transferring Far Eastern varieties of sal¬
mon to the White and Barents Seas.
The spawn of the humpback and dog
salmon that has been fertilized in Sa¬
khalin Island has been carried by air to
hatcheries in Murmansk. Enormous
numbers of young fish some 17 mil¬
lion in 1959 have been released, and
in 1960 fishermen in the northern seas
found full-grown humpbacks in their
nets.
wE AND THE U.N.: A 39-frame
colour filmstrip showing how the United
Nations and its Specialized Agencies deal
with things that are of direct importance in
the daily life of a child has now been
issued by Unesco. The purpose of the
filmstrip is not so much to teach a lesson
with detailed explanations of names and
facts, but to stimulate interest and dis¬
cussion about the work of the members of
the U.N. Family and to show how they,
the children, can contribute towards the
aims and ideals of the United Nations.
The filmstrip can be obtained from Unesco
distributors in member states (see opposite
page) together with a descriptive booklet.
Further information can be obtained from
34 'he Radio and Visual Information Division,
Mass Communications Dept., Unesco,
Place de Fontenoy, Paris.
FOOD PRESERVATIVES may be
dangerous if constantly consumed.
Similarly, natural or synthetic substances
added to improve the flavour, nutrition¬
al value or appearance of food. Just
how much of such toxic substances
can be consumed daily without harmful
effects is the question that has just
been studied by the Joint FAO/WHO
Expert Committee on Food Additives.
The Committee also prepared mono¬
graphs on 35 anti-microbials and anti¬
oxidants widely used, particularly in
tropical countries, to prevent food
wastage. These monographs will
eventually be published in the WHO
Technical Report Series and will be of
use to developing countries which have
to frame health regulations. Though
ultimately each country would have to
find its own solution to this problem,
the Committee believes that baby foods
should always be prepared without any
additives, the risk of poisoning being
much greater.
A UNESCO POSTER CONTEST on
international understanding and co-opera¬
tion has been announced by Unesco in
Paris. It is open to adults over 18 years
of age, who should submit not more than
one design to the National Commission
for Unesco in their country. National
Commissions will select not more than
three designs, which they will submit to
Unesco Headquarters in Paris before Feb¬
ruary 28, 1962. A first prize of $1000 (US),
or the equivalent, will be awarded by an in¬
ternational jury appointed by Unesco's Di¬
rector-General. Second and third prizes
of $500 and S3 00 (US), or the equivalent,
are also offered. For further details apply
to the National Commission for Unesco
in your country.
ASIAN BOOK LIST: A list of some
500 titles in English or French on the
countries of the Orient has been com¬
piled by the Canadian National Com¬
mission for Unesco as a contribution to
Unesco's East-West Major Project.
Designed for Canadian use, it will be a
valuable guide to all readers who wish
to deepen their knowledge of the his¬
tory, culture and ways of life of the
peoples of Islam, India and South-East
Asia or the Far East.
A]RAB REFUGEE SCHOOLS are
now benefiting from contributions of
54,500,000 made during World Refugee
Year, in 1960. Unesco is responsible for
the educational programme of these
schools which UNRWA has been operating
since its establishment in 1949. At present
there are 390 UNRWA-Unesco schools,
where 188,000 pupils study under 4,036
teachers. Some 50,000 pupils attend other
schools with the help of UNRWA schol¬
arships. The funds collected during World
Refugee Year will make possible the
launching of an ambitious vocational and
teacher training programme. Under the
previous programme only 350 specialized
workers a year could be trained. Once
the new programme has been put into
effect 2,500 young refugees will be prepared
for promising careers every year. Further
contributions are still being received and
will enable this programme to be expanded.
THE UNESCO PHILATELIC
SERVICE
UNITED NATIONS
<
O
z
z
o|
«
z
ECONOMIC COMMISSION
FOR LATIN AMERICA
o
m
It»
S
I
.
I
In»
X
J>
11=
IS
Is
towards
economic
9 development "*"
NATIONS UNIES
CHOWN above is the third in the
1961 series of U.N. commemo¬
rative stamps, which honours the
U.N. Economic Commission for
Latin America. It was issued on
September 18 in two denomina¬
tions: 4 cents (dark blue, light
blue, red and green) and I I cents
(dark green, violet and orange).
The Economic Commission for
Latin America (ECLA), one of four
U.N. regional economic commis¬
sions, was created by the U.N.
Economic and Social Council in
1948 to aid the co-ordinated pro¬
motion of economic and social
development in the countries of
this region. As the agent in France
of the U.N. Postal Administration,
UNESCO'S Philatelic Service stocks
all the United Nations stamps
currently on sale. It also has
stamps and first day covers issued
by many UNESCO member states
to commemorate important events
in the history of UNESCO and the
U.N. (inauguration of UNESCO'S
new headquarters, Human Rights
Day, World Refugee Year). Infor¬
mation on items available, their
price and the methods of payment
will be sent on request by the
UNESCO Philatelic Service, Place
de Fontenoy, Paris-7*.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Julian huxley
OT Will
and
natural habitats
in central and
east áfrica
Just published :
The conservation
of wild life
and natural habitats
in central
and East Africa
by Sir Julian Huxley
"The most interesting assignment I have ever had."
These are the words Sir Julian Huxley recently used to
describe the investigation which Unesco asked him to
undertake last year on the conservation of wild life and
natural reserves in Central and East Africa.
The noted British zoologist and first Director-General of
Unesco visited 25 national parks and reserves and had
discussions with hundreds of scientists, statesmen, game
wardens and administrators. In his report, now published
by Unesco, Professor Huxley concludes that Africa's
wild life belongs not merely to the local inhabitants but to
the world. It is unique among the world's various riches.
120 p., many illustrations 1 .25 6/- 4.50 N F
ere to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write
direct to the National Distributor
in your country. (See list below ;
names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.)
Payment is made in the national
currency ; rates quoted are for an
annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. PanuzaT, Press
Department, Royal Afghan Ministry of
Education, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 369 Lonsdale Street, Melbourne,
C. 1, Victoria. (A. 15/-).
AUSTRIA.. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C0., Spengergas5e 39, Vienna V (Seh.
50.-)
BELGIUM. For The Unesco Courier:
Louis de Lannoy, 22, Place de Brouckère,
Brussels, C.C.P. 338.000. (fr. b. 100.)
Other publications: Office de Publicité,
16, rueMarcq, Bruxelles, C.C.P. 285.98;
N.V. Standaard-Boekhandel, Belgiëlei 151,
Antwerp.
BURMA. Burma Translation Society,
361 Prome Road, Rangoon. (K. 5.50)
CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa
Ont. ($ 3.00).
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd, Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Co¬
lombo, 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co, Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Librería Económica, Pte Zayas
505-7, Apartado 1 13, Havana. (2.25 pesos)
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia Ltd., 30
Ve Smeckách, Prague 2.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard, A/S
Tidsskriftafdelingen, 6 Nörregade, Köben-
havn K. (D.kr. 12).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agen¬
cy. P.O. Box 120. Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskacu, Helsinki. (F.mk. 540).
FRANCE. Unesco Bookshop, Place de
Fontenoy. Paris, V. C.C.P. 12598-48.
(7 NF.).
GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier,
Vertrieb Bahrenfelder-Chaussee 1 60,
Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, C.C.P. 276650
(DM 8). Other Publications : R. Olden¬
bourg. Verlag, Rosenheimerstrasse 145,
Munich.
GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28,
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nachan Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Kultura, P.O. Box 149.
Budapest, 62.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd. Indian
Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road, Bombay
I; 17 Chitcaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13;
Gunfoundry Road, Hyderabad, I ; 36a,
Mount Road, Madras 2; Kanson House,
24/1 Asaf Ali Road, P.O. Box 386, New
Delhi, I ; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book &
Stationery Co., 17 Park Street Calcutta 16,
Scindia House, New Delhi. (Rs. 6.70).
INDONESIA. Bappit Pusat "Permata",
Djatan Nusantara 22, Djakarta.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The National Press, 2, Wel¬
lington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
35, Allenby Road and 48, Nahlat Benja¬
min Street, Tel-Aviv (l£ 4.-).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 9 1
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.( I 0/-)
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo. (Yen 670).
JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road , P.O.B. 66,
Amman.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul.
LIBERIA. J. Momolu Kamara, 69, Front
and Gurley Streets, Monrovia.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück,
22, Grand-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications
Ltd., Times House, River Valley Rd.,
Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta. ( 1 0/-).
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd.
30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis.
MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid des
Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (7 NF).
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl 6)
NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES.
G. CT. Van Dorp & C- (Ned Ant.) N.V.
Willemstad, Curacao.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church. (10/-).
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174. Lagos. (10/-).
NORWAY. For The Unesco Courier :
A.S. Narvesens Litteratur-Tjeneste, Stor-
tingsgt. 4 Oslo, Postboks I I 5 (kr. I 3.20).
Other publications. A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille
Grensen, 7, Oslo.
PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing
Co, Ltd., Unesco Publications House,
P.O. Box 374. 56-N Gulberg Industrial
Colony, Lahore.
PANAMA. Cultural Panameña, Avenida
7a, No. TI-49, Apartado de Correos 20 I 8,
Panama, D.F. (Balboas 3.-).
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., I 104 Castillejos, Quiapo, P.O. Box
620, Manila.
POLAND. " RUCH" ul. Wiloza Nr. 46,
Warsaw. 10 (Zl. 50).
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada Lda,
Livraria Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70,
Lisbon.
RHODESIA & NYASALAND. The
Book Centre, First Street, Salisbury,
Southern Rhodesia.
SWEDEN. For The Unesco Courier: Sven-
ska Unescorädet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 7.50); other publications
A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl. Hovbokhandel,
Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40, rue du Marché, Geneva. C.C.P.
1-236.
"Courier" only: Georges Losmaz, I, rue
des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. C.C.P.
1-481 I. (Fr. S. 8).
TANGANYIKA Dar-es-Salaam Book¬
shop, P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam.
THAILAND. Suksapan Panic, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok. (35
ticals).
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Isti-
klal Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul.
UGANDA Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box
145, Kampala.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Street, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier:
Central News Agency, P.O.Box 1033,
Johannesburg. (10/-).
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT).
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha,
Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I.( I 0/-).
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22, N.Y. (S 5.00.) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press,' 2960 Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y.
U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga,
Terazije 27/11. Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
COSMIC RAY BALLOON
Scientists inflate a high altitude balloon which is to carry aloft a rocket containing instruments to measure cosmic ray
intensity. Throughout the world men of science are investigating the mysterious field of cosmic rays. See article p. 2'..
]]>
</page>
</document>
