<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="064331eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
W/ö/L
WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
m «illM
DECEMBER 1961 (14TH YEAR) - PRICE : 1 -STG. (U.K.) 30 CENTS (U.S.) 0.70 NF (FRAN
f
-
,1
'/¡w
HB
V
w
AGORE
universal voice
Ä
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
**
W
-VSfe"
¿«s
THE FOUNTAIN OF LIFE, an illustration from an Ethiopian religious manuscript. The fullest and
most varied expression of Ethiopian art is found in the illuminated manuscripts of this African Christian
kingdom. Striking examples are now published in a Uoesco World Art Series Album (See p. 30).
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
^*~~*\ * """0 Dtr OPIM Ott TNI >OI(D
Courier
Contents
No. 12 .
DECEMBER 1961
14TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN
EIGHT EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
American
Japanese
COVER PHOTO
In a long life filled with
creative literary and artistic
activities and occupations,
Rabindranath Tagore also
found time for extensive
travel as an Ambassador
of Goodwill, seeking to
promote International under¬
standing. Here, wearing a
garland of roses, he was pho¬
tographed in Teheran, capital
of Iran, on the occasion of
his 71st birthday, in 1932,
© Rabindra-Sadana, Visva
Bharati, India.
Page
4 HOMAGE TO RABINDRANATH TAGORE
For the I 00th anniversary of his birth
By Vittorino Veronese
5 PORTRAIT OF A MAN
By Satyajlt Ray
12 REBEL WITH A UNIVERSAL CAUSE
He named his school "Abode of Peace"
By Humayun Kabir
17 A LITTLE-KNOWN REALM
OF HAUNTING SONGS AND MELODIES
Tagore, a composer unshackled by tradition
By Philippe Stern & Arnold A. Bake
18 THE ENCHANTMENT OF LINES
22 REVELATIONS OF A NOBEL PRIZE IN LITERATURE
By Mahmud Shah Qureshi
26 READINGS FROM TAGORE
27 WORLD HOMAGE TO A UNIVERSAL MAN
28 THE ART OF ETHIOPIA'S PAINTER-SCRIBES
A new Unesco art album reveals little-known masterpieces
By Abbé Jules Leroy
30 THE TUMULTUOUS HISTORY OF ANCIENT NUBIA
A Soviet archaeologist retraces 3,000 years of Nubian history
By Boris Piotrovsky
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
(M.C. 61. 1.164 A)
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7", France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
Gordon Behrens
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani (Moscow;
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Amin Shaker (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Scientific and Cultural
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except In July ind August ohm
it is bi-monthly ( I I issues l year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German
Arabic and Japanese. In the United Kingdom it is distributed by H. M
Stationery Office, P. O. Box S69, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering pottage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Unetco Courier if Indexed monthly In The Readers' Guide to
Periodical Literature published by H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates: U. S. $ 3.00; IO/-stg. ; 7.00
New Francs or equivalent. Single copies l/-stg. 30
cents (U.S.) ; 0.70 New Francs.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7'.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Edaor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
A centenary tribute to
RABINDRANATH
TAGORE
Rabindranath Tagore, philosopher, educator, novelist, poet and painter, is
without challenge one of the greatest and most noble figures of modern
times. Not only was he awarded the rare honour of the Nobel Prize for Literature, but
he also won the distinction far more rare, less spectacular but much more significant,
of having his works translated into different languages by writers of equal glory, Nobel
Prize winners in their own right, such as André Gide in French and Juan Ramon
Jimenez in Spanish.
India today does not celebrate merely the thinker and writer. Above all, India reveres
Tagore's generous, universal soul, open to the problems not only of his own land but
of the world, the son of the Maharshi Debendranath Tagore, who had been one of the
guiding spirits of the Brahma-Samaj. For one of his greatest works, the monumental
novel Gora, Rabindranath was to choose as theme the trials and problems of this
movement. It is not merely by chance that Unesco, among its many undertakings
towards the celebration of Tagore's Centenary, has decided to publish the first French
translation of this very novel. For in this book the poet stresses with great fervour
and by moving scenes depicted with all his skill as a writer, his zealous devotion to the
¡deal of a casteless world, a world without cruel, irrational discrimination between
one human being and his fellow men. His hero, Gora, cries out: "It is you who are
my mother. The imaginary mother whom I long sought during my wandering and
vagabonding was sitting at home, waiting before my own room. You have no caste,
you make no distinction between men, you know no hatred, you give flesh to nothing
but the good that is in all of us. It is you who are India." And then come these words
of Gora, which one might well apply to Tagore himself: "No longer is there opposed
within me the Hindu, Moslem and Christian. Today all foods are my food." For indeed,
Tagore took nourishment from what all the world had to offer, and his message of
mutual understanding and tolerance is directed far beyond the boundaries of India,
to all cultures and to all men. A message of freedom too, not merely freedom for
oneself, but for all: "He who wishes freedom for himself", he affirmed," yet fears
freedom for his neighbour, is not worthy of freedom."
It is only fitting that the entire globe should unite with India in rendering solemn
homage to a man whose glory ennobled ¡ndissolubly both his own country and the
world.
Writing days after Tagore's death in August I 94 I, Jawaharlal Nehru said : "Both
Gurudev and Gandhlji took much from the West and from other countries, especially
Gurudev. Neither was narrowly national. Their message was for the world." Tagore
was in truth a living link between East and West. And so he willed it. His entire life
he fought against narrow distrust of foreign cultures. He had faith in the fruitfulness
of cultural intercourse and friendship. With this message he was and remains a Guru
to Unesco, and it is both fitting and imperative that Unesco's homage to Tagore should
join that of the rest of mankind.
VITTORINO VERONESE
Message from the Director-General of Unesco, to the
Tagore Centenary celebrations in Bombay in January.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
RABINDRANATH TAGORE WITH A GROUP OF STUDENTS IN THE SCHOOL HE FOUNDED AT SANTINIKETAN IN 1801.
PORTRAIT OF A MAN
by Satyajit Ray
This year the world celebrates the birth, one hundred years
ago, of one of India's greatest figures, Rabindranath Tagore. As
part of the commemorations organized in Tagore's honour,
the Indian Government asked Satyajit Ray to produce a
documentary film on the poet, his background and his contri¬
bution to the arts and international understanding. Satyajit
Ray is one of India's leading film directors. His best-known
film, Pather Panchall, received the "Most Human Document"
award at the Cannes Film Festival in 1956, and Aparajlto won
the Venice Film Festival grand prize in 1957. THE UNESCO
COURIER wishes to thank the Films Division of the Ministry of
Information and Broadcasting, Government of India, for
permission to reproduce the text of Mr. Ray's commentary for
his just completed film. The article below is copyright
and may not be reproduced without prior permission.
On August 7, 1941, in the city of Calcutta, a man
died. His mortal remains perished, but he left
behind him a. heritage which no fire could consume.
It was a heritage of words and music and poetry, of
ideas and of ideals, and it has the power to move us today
and in the days to come.
We, who owe him so much, salute his memory.
Founded in the year 1690 by an Englishman named Job
Charnock, the city of Calcutta, one hundred years ago,
was a thriving metropolis. As the capital of India,
Calcutta was the seat of government.
In the northern part of this sprawling city, in the area
known as Jorasanko In Chitpore, was the family resi¬
dence of the Tagores. The Tagores had an Impressive
lineage. It dated back to the first group of learned
Brahmins that came from Kanauj and settled In Bengal
in the 8th century. One thousand years later, Pancha-
nan, a descendant, came to the new city of Calcutta and
found a lucrative position with a British shipping com¬
pany. His grandson Nllmonl added considerably to the
family fortune and built the house at Jorasanko In 1789.
The peak was reached, however, with Nllmonl's grand¬
son, Dwarkanath, one of the most brilliant and colourful
figures of the 19th century. Dwarkanath Tagore combin¬
ed cultured sophistication with largeness of heart and a
rare degree of business acumen. Coal, sugar, Indigo,
export, banking, newspapers, there was no end to his
enterprise and he succeeded In all. If his earnings were
fabulous, so were his spendings.
Although a Hindu and a Vaishnab, Dwarkanath defied
the ban of Brahmin orthodoxy and twice went to England.
There he had an audience with Queen Victoria, discus¬
sions with Gladstone, and dinner with men like Dickens,
Thackeray and Max Müller.
Before his death in England, Dwarkanath had written
a letter to his eldest son Debendranath reproving him
for neglecting the family's business affairs. For some
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
PORTRAIT OF A MAN (Cont'd)
Growing up in a family
of scholars and artists
years past, young Debendranath had been developing ten¬
dencies which might well have distressed his father.
It began In a burning ghat. The last rites were being
administered to Debendranath's grandmother. Not far
away, on the river bank, sat Debendranath. Like many a
rich man's son, he had been leading a wayward life. But
tonight, he was overcome by a strange feeling. Wordly
possessions seemed to lose their meaning for him.
This led to a period of profound disquiet, followed by
a ceaseless quest for the meaning of existence in the
great source books of the East and West. He read the
materialist philosophers of modern Europe Locke, Hume,
Bentham and others whose Ideas were so much in vogue
among the students of the time. Then he learnt Sans¬
krit and read the Mahabharata. But peace of mind
would not come until one day he chanced upon a torn
page of a Sanskrit book. There was a sloka in it which
said: God ls supreme and all-pervading. Be content with
what He gives. Do not covet another's wealth.
T his happened to be a page of the Ishopa-
nishad, edited by Raja Rammohun Roy.
Rammohun had been a close friend of Dwarkanath's. As
a boy. Debendranath had a deep and silent admiration
for the man. But the greatness of the Raja's vision and
the magnitude and nobility of the tasks he had set before
himself, were beyond the boy's comprehension. The Raja
lived in times when India's spiritual heritage was being
submerged in ritual and superstition.
Rammohun advocated Western education for Indians
because he wanted the new Ideas of the West to spread
in the country. But he also wanted us to respect what
was old and true in our own heritage. His own study of
the Upanishads had led him to the monotheistic bases
of Hinduism, which he sought to spread through writings
and lecturers.
His work was left unfinished by his death in England.
And now Debendranath Inspired by the two lines of
Sanskrit text, went on to prove himself to be his true
spiritual son and heir.
Debendranath suffered social ostracism for preaching
the monotheistic faith that he called Brahmoism, but to
his followers and there were many he was Maharshi,
the Great Sage.
When Rablndranath was born, the Maharshi was
45 years old. His wife Saradamonl was 33. Rabin-
dranath was the fourteenth child. The eldest was
Dwijendranath poet, philosopher, mathematician. The
second son Satyendranath was a Sanskrit scholar who
translated the Glta and Meghdoot into Bengali verse,
went to England and returned as the first Indian member
of the Indian Civil Service. The fifth son Jyotirindranath
was a born musician, translated Molière and Sanskrit
dramas into Bengali, and wrote and staged some of the
most popular Bengali plays of his time. Among the
daughters was Swarnakumari, the first woman novelist
and the first woman to edit a literary journal In India.
Indeed it was a household which hummed with activity.
At the age of seven, Rabi was sent to school. He
went to four schools and hated them all. But to say that
he lacked education would be wrong, for his third brother,
Hemendranath, saw to his studies at home, and it was
all done by the clock.
Rabi was 13 when his first book of verse, Kabikahini,
came out. When Rabi was 16, Dwijendranath brought
out a literary magazine called Bharati, and Rabi found
an admirable platform for his literary activities. His
essays Included pieces on European poets like Dante and
Petrarch whose acquaintance Rabi had already made
THE TALENTED FAMILY into which Tagore was born
proved a potent factor in the flowering of his genius. His
grandfather went to England in defiance of contemporary
conventions. His father was a leader of revolt against ortho¬
doxy in his championship of the Brahmo faith and among
Rabindranath's brothers and sisters were a scholar, a poet, a
musician and the first woman to edit a literary journal in India.
It was a household which hummed with activity. Above left,
CONT'D ON PAGE 8
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
P.abindranath in 1881, aged 20, in the role of Valmiki in
his opera Valmiki Prativa (Countenance of the Great Sage
Valmiki) at its first performance in the Tagore home in
Calcutta. Above, photo taken after a family presentation of
Tagore's play, Phalgunl. From left, Abanindrath, Samaren-
dranath and Gaganendranath, all nephews of Tagore, Willie
Pearson, an English friend, and Tagore himself. Below right,
Tagore and his bride, Mrinalini Devi. Below, Tagore's parents.
All photos © Rabindra-Sadana, Visva Bharati
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
PORTRAIT OF A MAN (Cont'd)
Philosopher, educator, novelist, poet & painter
In the library of his elder brother Satyendranath.
Satyendranath's wife Gnanadanandini, who had been
staying in England with her two children, was a remark¬
able woman who had been persuaded by her husband to
come out of orthodox seclusion. Rabi set out for
England in the summer of 1879 and joined Gnanadanan¬
dini at Brighton. If the plan was to provide the boy with
a proper education, it came to nought. For Rabi returned
a year later without completing his course of studies at
London University.
While In England, Rabi had become acquainted with
Western music Some of the tunes he had learnt found
their way into' the enchanting opera Valmiki-Prativa.
There were other tunes, however, which had their origin
In classical Indian ragas, used for the first time in an
operatic context.
Valmiki-Prativa was performed in the Tagore residence
with Rabindranath himself in the role of the bandit-
turned-poet. The rest of the cast too was composed of
members of the Tagore family, all gifted with varying
degrees of talent.
Among those who saw and praised this perfor¬
mance was the greatest literary figure of the
time, Banklm Chandra Chatterjl. A year later, when
Rablndranath's Sandhya-Sangeet was published, Bankim-
chandra personally congratulated the poet and acknow¬
ledged his pre-eminence among the rising writers of the
day.
At the age of 22, Rabindranath married Bhabatarini
Devi; the old-fashioned name was later changed to
Mrlnalinl. Two months before the wedding Rabin¬
dranath had received a letter from his father In which
he was asked to prepare himself to look after the family
estates. After a period of initial training In the Estate's
Offices In Calcutta, Rabindranath found himself In the
very heart of rural Bengal, in the area of the river Padma.
. With a worldly wisdom unusual in a poet but character¬
istic of the Tagores Rabindranath in later life set out
in a practical way to Improve the lot of the poor peasants
of his estates and his varied work In this field is on
record. But his own gain from this intimate contact
with the fundamental aspects of life and nature, and the
influence of this contact on his own life and work are
beyond measure.
Living mostly in his boat and watching the life through
the window, a whole new world of sights and sounds and
feelings opened up before him. It was a world in which
the moods of people and the moods of nature were
Inextricably Interwoven. The people found room in a
succession of great short stories, and nature, in an out¬
pouring of exquisite songs and poems. Dominant was the
mood of the rains, exultant and terrible.
In 1901, Rabindranath was 40 years old. His already
enormous output of poems and plays had been gathered
in one big volume. It comprised 21 books and included
Sojiar Tari, his first masterpiece.
The same year, 1901, marked an event of a somewhat
different nature. In 1862, one year after Rabindranath
was born, the Maharshi had acquired some property In
Bolpur, in the district of BIrbhum in West Bengal. The
property was made over to a board of trustees, and the
deed specified that the place was to be used for medit¬
ation on the Supreme Formless Being. According to the
Maharshl's wishes, a seat of prayer and a temple of wor¬
ship had been built, and close to the temple, a residence
which was called Santiniketan the Abode of Peace.
Rabindranath had been worrying about the education of
his children, and he decided to start an experimental
educational institution in Santiniketan. It was to be a
school but not like the schools that had been the night¬
mare of his own childhood. It was to be like the forest
hermitages of classical India.
8 But to bring it into being was not an easy task. For
one thing it cost money and Rabindranath had to sell,
among other things, the copyright of his books. His wife
added her bit by selling her wedding ornaments. Three
months after the school was opened, 6he was taken ill.
Two months later, she died. For Rabindranath it was
the beginning of a series of personal tragedies.
Nine months after his wife's death, his second daughter
Renuka passed away. The hardest blow of all came four
years later. The youngest son Saml, who took after his
father in many ways, fell a victim to cholera when he was
only 12.
It was in the midst of these bereavements that Rabin¬
dranath participated In one of the greatest political
upheavals in the history of India. In December 1903 was
published the decision of Governor-General Lord Curzon
to split up Bengal into two provinces. The idea was to
create a separate province with a Moslem majority, which
would induce a rift between the two main religious groups
and thus avert the possible growth of a united front
against the Government.
But in proposing the Partition, Curzon merely fanned
the flame of patriotism that had been smouldering in the
minds of certain visionaries all through the period of the
renaissance in Bengal. These men now came to the fore
and led the millions to rise in a protest. The series of
stirring patriotic songs which Rabindranath composed
for the occasion were sung in processions in the streets
of Calcutta with the poet himself in the lead.
On October 27, 1905, the Partition became an accom¬
plished fact. In a form of protest that only a poet could
conceive, Rabindranath turned the Black Day into a mass
festival of Rakhibandhan the tying of the band of
friendship.
But the Swadeshi movement was fated to grow and
assume a character which was not possible to foresee in
its early stages. While admitting the bravery and patriot¬
ism of those who killed or were killed in a reckless bid
for freedom Rabindranath could not condone terrorism.
He stated his credo in clear terms. The path of violence
was not for India. Good could come only out of con¬
structive work carried out in a spirit of tolerance.
He had himself followed up his retirement from the
political soene by undertaking the work of rural welfare
in his estates. And there were other activities: he was
teaching at school, editing journals, and engaging himself
in almost every conceivable form of literary activity.
T hat his own countrymen now regarded him
as their leading man of letters was proved by
his 50th birthday celebrations in Calcutta. Sponsored
by the Bengal Academy of Letters and attended by
thousands, it was a unique literary manifestation in India.
But to the outside world, Rabindranath was still an
unknown name.
The object of Rablndranath's visit to England in 1912
was to study the educational methods of the West and
also to acquaint the West with his work at Santiniketan.
He happened to carry with him on this occasion a note
book containing his own English translations of some of
his poems, mainly from Gitanjail. He showed these
translations to the English painter William Rothenstein
who had met the poet on an earlier visit to India.
Rothenstein was so Impressed that he sent a copy of the
translation to the great Irish poet William Butler Yeats.
Introducing the poems to a gathering of English writers
and intellectuals, Yeats said: "I know of no man in my
time who has done anything in the English language
to equal these lyrics. Even as I read them in these literal
English translations, they are exquisite in style and
thought."
Gitanjali was published in England in
There has rarely been another instance of
world fame In like manner. The Nobel
1913 and knighthood in 1915, while war
Europe. Touring the United States and
Rabindranath made eloquent appeals for
that world peace could be achieved
the same year,
a poet gaining
Prize came in
was raging in
Japan in 1916,
peace. He felt
only through
CONT'D ON PAGE 10
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
*»f*H
KINDRED SPIRITS: In 1921 Tagore met the great French writer and thinker Romain Rolland for the first timo. Despite tho barriers
of language the two men reached such, a degree of sympathetic understanding that Tagore wrote to one of his friends : "Of all tho
men I confronted in the Occident it was Romain Rolland that struck me as the nearest to my heart and tho most akin to my spirit."
In 1926, when Tagore was again travelling in Europe he sat and talked with Rolland in the latter's garden at Villeneuve In
Switzerland where the photo below was taken. Above, Tagore with the famous German theologian and educator, Paul
Geheeb, in 1930. Paul Geheeb, who died last year aged 90, founded the Oldenwald School Germany, as well as tho
Ecole d'Humanité at Goldern, in Switzerland. Paul Geheeb's ideas have inspired educators in many other countries.
Photos (©) Rabindra-Sadana, Vi'.va Clurati
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
TWO GREAT MINDS and two great humanists were confronted
when Tagore met Albert Einstein during a visit to Berlin in 1930. Tag-
ore's humanist ideas found an echo in the best minds of Europe and
some of its great men became his closest friends. Other Europeans
came to India and worked devotedly for the poet and his cause.
No nation can be proud of isolating its life & culture
10
intellectual co-operation between nations. He said, "The
call has come to every Individual in the present age to
prepare himself for the dawn of a new era, when man
shall discover his soul In the spiritual unity of all human
beings."
Pursuing this noble idea of International co-operation,
Rabindranath gave the school at Santiniketan a new
status and a new name. "Yatra Visvam Bharati Eka-
nirham" Where the world makes home In a single nest
this was the motto of Visvam Bharati, the World Uni¬
versity, which was inaugurated in December 1918 with the
aged philosopher Brijendranath Seal presiding.
While peace had been restored in Europe, in India there
was unrest. The occasion was the Rowlatt Bill, designed
to suppress all political movements. It dashed India's
hopes of gaining the self-government that the British
rulers had kept promising through the war years.
Dominating the Indian political scene at this time was
Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi. As a barrister In South
Africa, Gandhi had fought for the rights of the Indians
living in that country. As a protest against the Rowlatt
Act, Gandhi launched a movement of passive resistance.
But the masses misinterpreted the movement and follow¬
ing a rumour of Gandhi's arrest, violence broke out in
many parts of the country. As a result of this the
Government started taking repressive measures out of all
proportion to the magnitude of the violence.
In the Punjab, martial law was declared. In charge of
the troops at Amritsar was Brigadier General Dyer. On
the first day of the month of Vaisakh, a crowd gathered
in Jalllanwallabagh, as It had done every other year. It
was a peaceful crowd. But Dyer was taking no chances.
Machine guns rattled.
The news of the Amritsar incident was suppressed by
the Government, but details of It filtered through to
other parts of the country and even to the Abode of
Peace.
Rabindranath rushed to Calcutta. But the Defence of
India Act was still in force and no leaders would support
him in a plea for a meeting of protest.
At four o'clock on the morning of May 30, Rabindra¬
nath finished writing a letter. It was addressed to the
Viceroy, Lord Chelmsford, and it was published in the
newspapers. Condemning the Government for the
killing at Jalllanwallabagh, Rabindranath concluded by
saying: "And I for my part wish to stand, shorn of all
special distinctions, by the side of my countrymen whíf
for their so-called insignificance are liable to suffer
degradation not fit for human beings. And these are the
reasons which have painfully compelled me to ask your
Excellency to relieve me of my title of knighthood."
The next ten years of Rablndranath's life were filled
with ceaseless activity. The urge to travel, and the
necessity to collect funds for his university, took him to
all parts of the world and the West as much as the East,
welcomed him with open arms.
Wherever he went, he spread the message of peace and
stressed the importance of intellectual co-operation
between nations. He said: "We ought to know that isol¬
ation of life and culture is not a thing of which any
nation can be proud. In the human world, giving is
exchanging, it ls not one-sided."
His great humanist ideas found an echo in the best
minds of Europe, and some became his close friends.
In the meanwhile, the institution at Santiniketan had
come a long way from its modest beginnings. Its scope
for studies had greatly increased. There was Kalabha-
wan for the study of painting, under masters like
Nandalal Bose, who was himself a pupil of Abanindranath,
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
THE QUEST for the unity of man in the midst of diversity led Tagore to travel to the farthest corners of tho world. "Uniformity Is
not unity," he once said ; "only those who are different can unite. Nations that wipe out the Independence of other nations aro tho
destroyers of interdépendance.". He was the first great Indian in recent times to embark on a cultural mission for
restoring contacts and establishing friendship with peoples of other countries. Above, In 1930, Soviet citizens gather to
greet Tagore in Moscow and youngsters crowd around him as he visits a centre of the "Pioneers" children's organization.
a nephew of the poet. The Sangeet Bhawan which
neglected no brand of Indian music had also grown under
Dinendranath, another of the poet's nephews. Special
provisions had been made for conducting oriental studies,
and scholars came from abroad and stayed to lecture for
study and research. Such men were Moriz Winternitz
from Austria, Sylvain Levi from France, Victor Lesny
from Austria, and Sten Konow from Norway.
But there were some Europeans who did even more
than that. Charles Freer Andrews, a missionary who was
present at Yeats' reading of Gitanjali, and William Win-
stanely Pearson, who had also met the poet in England,
came to the Ashram in its early days drawn by the
poet's personality and stayed on until their death,
working with a selfless devotion to the poet and his cause
that few Indians could equal. Leonard Elmhirst was
another Englishmen who was drawn by the poet's person¬
ality, came over ito Santiniketan and took charge of the
Santiniketan at Surul, two miles away.
The poet's last European tour began with a visit to
Oxford where he delivered the series of HIbbert lectures
which were later published as The Religion of Man.
It was also on this last tour that Rabindranath went
to Soviet Russia for the first time. On the eve of his
departure from Moscow he told his hosts: "You have
recognized the truth that in extirpating all special evils
one has to go to the root, and the only way to it is through
education." In Russia as well as In other places that he
visited on this tour, Rabindranath held exhibitions of his
paintings. At the age of 70, Rabindranath had found a
new outlet for his creative urge.
In 1931, the leading citizens of Calcutta united in an
appeal to observe the poet's 70th birthday. It was
celebrated in a manner that was truly worthy of the
occasion. The Golden Book of Tagore was a testimony
to the love and reverence that the intellectuals of the
world bore for the poet. Its sponsors consisted of three
Europeans and two Indians. There was- Romain Rolland
from France, Albert Einstein from Germany, and the poet
Kostes Palamas from Greece. One of the two Indians
was the scientist Jagadlsh Chandra Bose, the other was
Mahatma Gandhi.
The last years of the poet's life were spent largely In
his beloved Santiniketan. He had a choice of small
houses built for him, for he never liked to stay In the
same house, or even in the same room for long. It was
In a way symbolic of the refusal to get Into a rut which
had marked his whole life. In his writings he was now
producing some of his most mature, original and striking
works, and these included text books and nonsense
rhymes for children, not an unusual occupation for some¬
one who had loved and understood children all his life
and done so much to mould them for a better future. His
health was falling but calls of duty, which he was ever
ready to answer, gave him little rest.
On May 7, 1941, Radindranath was 80 years old. Three
months later, he was to leave the Ashram, never to
return. He would be taken to his ancestral house in
Calcutta, fatally ill.
Rabindranath attended his 80th birthday celebrations
in Santiniketan In spite of his falling health. For the
occasion, he had composed a message his last message
to the world. It was called Crisis in Civilization. It
concerned Itself with the state of the so-called modern
civilization, a civilization that was being shaken to Its
very roots by barbaric wars of aggression.
In the course of the message, Rabindranath said:
"I had at one time believed that the springs of civiliza¬
tion could issue out of the heart of Europe. But today,
when I am about to leave the world, that faith has
deserted me. I look around and see the crumbling ruins
of a proud civilization strewn like a vast heap of futility.
And yet, I shall not commit the previous sin of losing
faith In Man. I shall await for the day when the holo¬
caust will end and the air will be rendered clean with the
spirit of service and sacrifice. Perhaps that dawn will
come from this horizon, from the East, where the sun
rises. On that day will unvanqulshed man retrench his ^
path of conquest, surmounting all barriers, to win back
his lost human heritage."
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
*41tf;
STELE UNDER A TREE with Tagore, at the age of
44, seated beside it, marks the lonely spot where his
father stopped to meditate while going on a pilgrim¬
age towards the Himalayas. Here years later, Tagore
created his experimental school which won world
renown as Santiniketanthe Abode of Peace.
- »V
.:*
>ra
m $
SM
»».*«,«*,'
«*A*
**-;¿ J»^*îîr5
«rrJi
"^t
<* *
r » .st*»
K-r-
< i
s --.
..*_-. -tK -
..-"
~í*.>-v r
a*: ->>
VïàirtAu
k*i
'^
à* o;;
f
«»^
#Jfe
^
»'Ji*-
'W*
12
? ',.VW<-'
' **&«fi
*#
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
;--í* r
- L. * «- _ 1^
y > ^ - ?
He named his school
'Abode of Peace'
REBEL WITH
A UNIVERSAL
CAUSE
by Humay¡in Kabir
Tacore believed and everyone who ponders the
question must believe with him that educa¬
tion ls the foundation of society; that the teachers of
today are the arbiters of the destiny of society of to¬
morrow and the day after. How men arc trained, what
ideals they imbibe: what type of character they develop,
what knowledge Ls Imparted to them: what are the dis¬
ciplines through which they go; what Ls the way In which
their mind is formed these are the things which ulti¬
mately shape the destinies of man.
Tagore's Ideal of education was at the same time
revolutionary and traditional. He had the wisdom to see
that revolutions are successful only if they grow out of
the past. A revolution which seeks to break away
completely from the past, a revolution which totally
denies tradition, ultimately defeats Itself. Revolutions
are successful only when values of the past arc re¬
discovered and reshaped to meet the needs of changing
times.
Tagore was an educational revolutionary In both theory
and practice. His own experience he left oil formal
schooling quite early in life convinced him that the
routine of the school, In particular the dull imposition of
textbooks and subjects In which the chlJd ls not Interest¬
ed, is more a hindrance than a help to the unfoldment
of its spirit. He realized that the child's mind does not
blossom in that way. From his own experience Tagore
learnt that education divorced from social life and
cultural traditions, and, more important still, bereft of
contacts with nature became for the child an imposition
and a burden.
Tagore held that education must allow the child to
develop in the context of nature. He believed that the
sweep of the earth and the expanse of the sky, the
quietness of the evening and the promise of the morning,
the beauty of the stars and the radiance of the sun must
permeate the personality of the child. Gradually they
must become a part of his being so that there may be
harmony in his inner nature as there is harmony in the
outside world.
Tagore knew that there are plenty of clashes and
conflicts in life, but he held that there Ls a larger harmony
In which the smaller clashes and conflicts always find
reconciliation. We must strive to attain the same
harmony among our faculties. Tagore taught that the
intellect should be developed along with the emotions and
HUMAYUN KABIR is minister for Scientific Research and Cul¬
tural Affairs of the Government of India and a former Minister
for Civil Aviation. A distinguished imiter and educator, Pro¬
fessor Kabir was president of the All-India Education Con¬
ference in 1955 and of the Indian Philosophical Congress. All-
India Writer's Convention in 1956. His many works include :
Men and Rivers, The Indian Heritage, Education In New India,
Science, Democracy and Islam, and Immanuel Kant.
13
Rabindra-Sadana, Visva Bharati CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
A UNIVERSAL CAUSE (Cont'd)
Far-seeing pioneer of modern education
14
the volition, and all these aspects should grow
harmoniously through activity of many kinds.
Tagore did not believe In any narrow or rigid
educational formulae. His conception of education was
in broad human terms. In his system, art had its place
along with mathematics and science. He believed, and
he tried to carry out his beliefs in his school, that all
aspects of the child's personality must develop harmon¬
iously. He was one of the earliest among modern
educational thinkers to emphaslve activity as an
essential principle of education.
Many of his Ideals have been shared by educational
thinkers In all countries of the world, but Tagore's
special contribution lay In the emphasis on harmony, on
balance, on all-sided development of the human
personality. He felt that if any aspect was submerged,
It would warp the entire human outlook. For Tagore
beauty had to be moral, and morality had to be imbued
with the spirit of beauty. The pursuit of truth, beauty
and goodness was the end of human life and the purpose
of education was to train men and women to seek,
recognize and achieve them.
Tagore established Santiniketan as a school in 1901.
He started with hardly a dozen pupils and one of them
was his own son. It was natural that Tagore's son should
come to study in his own school, for he was not one
of those educational politicians who talk much about new
systems but send their own children to traditional schools.
Tagore's son came to Santiniketan because Tagore believed
In it, but some of the other pupils came because they had
proved misfits In the existing schools. In the beginning,
recruits to Tagore's school were sometimes the neglected
children of the family, and yet these very children have
turned out to be some of the most distinguished sons of
modern India. In its short life of sixty years Santiniketan
has given us a Chief Justice of India, Chief Ministers and
Minister of States and Judges of the High Courts, great
educationists, scientists, artists and philosophers.
T1 1
acore believed that every individual has In
him or her the seed of divinity. Every man
has the promise of greatness if only we know how to
develop his potentiality. Santiniketan has justified his
faith and proved that if the educational approach be
right and imaginative, and if there be a spirit like
Tagore's to inspire and guide, there is no height that the
individual may not reach. It is only because we do not
recognize our powers, only because we allow our person¬
ality to be warped by lesser considerations, that human
beings do not grow. One word of caution is however
necessary. A Socrates or a Kalldasa, an Ibn Khalidun
or a Rabindranath Tagore is rare, even in the best of
circumstances but given the proper education and envi¬
ronment, everyone can become a useful and creative
member of the community, a member who contributes as
much as he receives, a citizen of whom any country can be
proud.
These are the educational ideals which Tagore
preached; the ideal of harmony among the different
subjects, of harmony among all aspects of the personality,
with a proper emphasis on emotions, Intellect and volition
of harmony of man with nature. These ideals of Tagore
are now the common currency of the educational world.
I have sometimes felt that if Tagore had only formulated
his educational ideals and carried them out in
Santiniketan, he would have been honoured as one of
the greatest educational thinkers the world has known in
the last 100 years.
Tagore did not believe in blind conformity. He always
protested against what he called Achalayatan, the
Institution which has become immobile, customs that have
become out-moded, beliefs that have become dead.
Schools which do not allow the free development of the
mind were for him prison houses and not centres of light.
Tagore revolted against rigidity and believed that it is
only through change, only through a forward march that
the values of the spirit can be maintained.
Every country, every community has Its own peculiar
culture, Its own peculiar needs. Every age, every period
has its own requirements. Tagore held that our pro¬
grammes must change with changing times. Values are
eternal but their expression in institutions, traditions and
practices must change if we are to remain true to their
spirit.
One of the things of which modern India is proud, one
of the things in which we have great hopes pride in
what has been achieved, hopes in the promise they hold
is what we call the community development pro¬
gramme. This programme has become a symbol of hope
in our villages, and it is not accidental that it flows out
of what Tagore taught and did. More than sixty years
ago, Tagore said that the greatest misfortune of modern
India is that Shree (grace and beauty) has left the
villages.
Modern culture has become predominantly urban. The
very word "civilization" suggests that it has always had
something to do with cities,, but in the modern age
concentration on cities has become even greater.
Throughout the world there is today a drift of the abler
and more enterprising men and women, men and women
of will and vision, away from rural areas to the towns.
In consequence, village life becomes steadily more
impoverished and the gap between the town and the
village continually grows. In spite of the admonitions of
many great men of Ruskin some 100 years ago, and of
Tolstoy, and Gandhi In the present century nobody goes
back to the village.
Tagore saw the answer to their problem more than sixty
years ago. He said that this vicious circle can be broken
not by admonitions, not by speaking in lyric terms about
the beauties of village life, but by improving the villages
till they again become the home of culture and grace.
If we can change the pattern of rural life and make
the villages more like towns, if the great gap which exists
today between village and town is 'gradually overcome,
then and then only will the drift to the town stop.
Villages today do not have the health services, the
communication and the social amenities and the hundreds
of other things which make the town such an attractive
place for young men and women. Tagore said that able
men will stay in villages only when village life is re¬
constructed to provide educational facilities, health
services, improved communications and adequate and
wholesome water supply. Able men and women will
stay in the villages only if there are opportunities for
the fullest development of their personality. The pro-
TAGORE'S BELIEF that education is the foundation of society led him in
I 90 I to create an experimental school at Santiniketan. It was given a new
status and a new nameVisva Bharati, the World Universityin 1918. Be¬
low, Sylvain Levy, the French orientalist and close friend of Tagore, lecturing
at Santiniketan in 1923, with Tagore listening intently in the background.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
gramme of rural reconstruction that India has undertaken
today, the community development programme which is
being accepted also by other countries of the world, is a
direct outcome of Tagore's teaching.
It is I think true to say that after 3,000 years, the
Indian village ls today on the march. For almost 3,000
years our agriculture had hardly changed, our ways of
living in the villages had hardly changed, and the little
changes that had taken place were often for the worse.
6,000 years ago we had in India the great civilization of
Harappa and Mohenjo Daro. This civilization was marked
by a pattern of planned towns with planned streets and
drainage which would compare favourably with some of
the most modern towns of Western Europe and America.
But during the last 3,000 years something happened
which changed things for the worse. We in India lost that
knowledge and energy so that today conditions of sanita¬
tion in rural areas are such that the less we speak about
them the better.
Village housing is so poor that we are ashamed
of it. Roads, water supply and other social
services in the villages are completely inadequate. Misery
and squalor, poverty, ignorance and disease continued for
oyer 3,000 years, but in the course of the last ten years
since India became free a massive effort is being made
to remove these evils. We are today seeking to revive the
old spirit of initiative and enterprise and bring back
conditions of new life to rural areas. We aim to bring
water to villages where there was no supply before, to
transform old and traditional methods of agriculture and
develop new roads and civic centres, in a word, build a
new system of rural economy and rural life.
It will come as a surprise to many that this is a
programme which Tagore spelled out some 60 years ago.
Sixty years ago, around Santiniketan where he started
his school, he drew up the first blueprint for the recon¬
struction of village life. And it is remarkable that he
sought to carry out the programme by evoking the
interest and the initiative of the villages himself. The
work which began on a very small scale grew till In 1921
it developed into the Rural Institute at Srinlketan through
the help and co-operation of an enlightened English
friend and admirer.
Even before the advent of the twentieth century,
Tagore had declared that there can be no question of
economic regeneration or political freedom for India,
there can be no question of raising the standard of life
of the people and building a new humanity in India,
unless the villages changed. He pleaded that we must
create conditions so that the villages may again become
creative, and rural people find satisfaction In life. He
pointed out that there ls a close link between economic
and cultural Ufe, between political and moral urges.
The Indian people will again become creative only when
their social and economic problems have been solved.
Tagore declared that political bondage ls merely an
external symptom of an Inner disease. He held that It
is a mistake to fight political bondage on a merely political
programme. Such attempts, he said, are doomed to fall.
When Indians regain their character and develop moral
purpose and aesthetic perceptions, when they begin to
strive for economic self-sufficiency and personal dignity,
political bondage will drop like the slough off the snake's
back when the winter ls past.
I wish to refer to one other element In Tagore's
economic ideal. He was no obscurantist and knew that
the day of the machine had come. He loved handicrafts
and knew that some of the most beautiful things have
been made by manual labour, but he also knew that in
the modern world, there ls no alternative to the machine
if we are to provide necessary goods and services for
millions of human beings. All that Tagore wanted was
that the machine must be the slave of man, not his
master. Subject to this condition, he accepted the
machine freely and without any mental reservation.
The economic pattern which one is seeking to develop
in India today is in conformity with this Ideal of Tagore.
It ls an economic pattern in which heavy Industry will
grow side by side with consumer industries, a pattern in
which certain trades, certain industries will be under
public control and management, but side by side there
will be other spheres of economic activity where private
enterprise will have freedom and initiative.
Tagore Is largely responsible for the growth of a
universal outlook in modem India. We Uve in an age
when great differences divide great nations, when sharp
conflicts reach down to the bases of society, when
philosophical, religious and moral differences threaten
the future of man. Catastrophe can be averted only If
we learn to tolerate differences and develop an attitude
of respect for and acceptance of diversity and change.
Borrowing the language of Buddhism, we have called the
principle underlying such an attitude the principle of
Panchsila. We may call it co-operation, we may call It
co-existence, but in fact It is nothing but another name
for the basic principle of federalism, in which there ls
recognition of the dignity of every unit and of loyalty to
the whole based on loyalty to the unity of society.
(Address delivered In Rome In June, 1901.)
Rabindra-Sadana, Visva Bharati Courtesy Christine Bossenec
GANDHI AND TAGORE differed greatly in physical appearance, personal
habits and In general outlook. At several moments of crisis In India's political
history, the two had disagreed over the course of action to be taken. But these
were on the surface; their deeper affinity transcended all occasional barriers.
Below, Mahatma Gandhi Is received by Tagore at Santiniketan In 1940.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Très, trèstièj/rès Uni, J=<39
dolee
^ï^ti7"^¿LÍA)
me -gher po -re megh joiine che an - dhar koL
PjijpJBwiiP
pa _ Nhe	 me-gher	 pîi-re megh joime - che an fin ar-
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
A LITTLE-KNOWN
REALM OF
HAUNTING SONGS
AND MELODIES
by Philippe Stern and Arnold A. liahe
Rabindra-Sadana, Visva Bharati
m 5
Sáááf*£g
re a
ITT
»
she ka -jer.
It Is not always known In the West that Tagore
was 'not only a poet, but a musician as well.
In his work, Indeed, poetry and music cannot be separat¬
ed. Songs form an important part of his creative work
and In these words and melody complete each other.
In his Reminiscences, he writes: "...I am always
reluctant to publish books of the words of my songs, for
therein the soul must needs be lacking." And again,
speaking of a Baul song: "Besides, the best part of a song
ls missed when the tune ls absent, for thereby Its move¬
ment and Its colour are lost and It becomes like a butterfly
whose wings have been plucked." (Indian Folk Religion.
Creative Unity.)
Tagore's works have reached us without the music, and
moreover the original has been modified. The "Poet," as
his disciples called him, did not think it necessary to
preserve in the English version composed by himself the
repetitions and refrains which give so much charm to the
Bengali text. He has rendered the Ideas to the neglect of
the spontaneity, the directness and vitality of their
original form.
From the musical point of view, Tagore stands at the
meeting-place of three different influences: that of
European rnuslc, that of classical Hindu music (an
extremely sophisticated one, bound by strict rules) and
thirdly that of the popular religious music of Bengal.
It is not without a struggle that Tagore managed to
throw off the Influence both of European and of classical
Indian music, so that he might Immerse himself In the
popular music of his own country and pick up the great
mystical traditions of Bengal which are carried on in his
own work.
One has only to glance at his Reminiscences to feel the
musical atmosphere in which he was steeped. Indians of
traditionalist tendencies appreciated music, but its
practice was looked down on and left to professionals.
Not so however In the vast home of the Tagore family.
One of the family wrote books on music, the father of
the poet composed religious chants, and one of his
brothers a national hymn. Another brother, Jyotlrlndra,
used to remain for days at the piano, arranging the old
classical melodies, according to his fancy, while the poet
and a friend endeavoured to compose lines to these same
tunes (Reminiscences).
PHILIPPE STERN, Chief Curator of the Musée Guimet in
Paris, is an archaeologist who, after a meeting with Tagore,
became intensely interested in his music and prepared, with
Arnold Bake, a volume called "Twenty-Six Songs of Rabindra¬
nath Tagore" (Librairie Orientaliste Paul Geuthner, Paris), from
the text of which this article Tíos been adapted. ARNOLD
BAKE, of the Netherlands, is a noted Orientalist and professor
of Sanskrit at London University.
17
CONPD ON PAGE 20
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
THE ENCHANTMENT OF LINES
18
Illustrations © Rabindra-Sadana, Visva Bharati
"People often ask me about the meaning of my pictures", wrote Rabindranath Tagore. "I
remain silent even as my pictures are. ft is for them to express not to explain. They have
nothing ulterior behind their own appearance for the thoughts to explore and words to describe
and if that appearance carries its ultimate worth then they remain, otherwise they are rejected
and forgotten even though they may have some scientific truth or ethical justification". In I 928,
at the age of 67, Tagore, to use his own words, "fell under the enchantment of lines" when he
discovered that his hand was moving automatica|y across the pages of his manuscripts trans¬
forming the scratches and erasures into designs. For the next 1 2 years of his life he gave full rein
to this irresistible urge and produced nearly 2,()f00 paintings. Although he used all kinds of
paints and produced coloured chalk drawings, pastels, and later dry-points and etchings, Tagore's
preferred medium was liquid colour. He often used ordinary fountain-pen ink and when this
was not available, he crushed flower petals and used them as pigments. He rarely used a brush,
disdained an artist's palette and instead, worked with a cloth soaked in colour, the back of a
fountain-pen, his thumb, a stick or, more often, a knife. As these illustrations show, Tagore's art
was peculiarly his own, and though he held his first exhibition in I 930, Rabindranath Tagore the
Painter has until recently remained practically unknown. (An] illustrated article on his work
figured in the issue of The Unesco Courier, "Famous Authors as Artists", in August 1957).
iVv
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
REALM OF SONGS & MELODIES (Cont'd from page 16)
Musician unshackled by tradition
Young Rabindranath also "tried to set to music the
poems of Chakravartl whose enthusiasm and creative joy
were such that "the expressiveness of his voice made up
for what It lacked In execution." And "on moonlight
nights, pacing round and round the extensive terrace
overlooking the river," Rabindranath Tagore composed
for the first time melodies for his own songs. He had
had no technical training in music. Urged by their
youthful enthusiasm and curiosity, immersed in this
musical atmosphere, nothing seemed Impossible to the
poet and his companions: they wrote, sang and acted
plays.
European influences were welcome in those days.
Whereas today the striving is against external influences
and towards a national culture, it was against a narrow
and oppressive traditionalism that certain liberal, rich
and respected families like the Tagores rose up in those
days. European harmonization, damaging to Indian
music because it distorts It, was for instance, applied to
certain songs of the poet's father by one of the latter's
granddaughters, who was given a diamond pin as a reward,
such was his satisfaction. Rabindranath had sung foreign
airs at school without understanding them; later, as a
youth, he sang Beethoven's "Adelaide." When he came
back from a visit to England, where he had been interested
In, though a little disappointed by, Irish melodies, his
manner of singing had become so westernized that his
familiy exclaimed in astonishment: "What is the matter
with Rabl's voice? How funny and foreign it sounds!"
Tagore was now entering his twentieth year. The
melodies he inserted for the first time in one of his dramas
Valmiki Prativa, and which were so essential to it, that
speaking of them in his complete works, the author
declared one could not judge the play without them, were
thus the result of the most varied influences, some being
built on a classical mode, others composed by his brother
Jyatlrlndra, and Anally some being of European origin.
Later however, Tagore's powerful personality asserted
itself, and he threw off both the Western influences of his
childhood and youth and that of Indian classical music.
Western influence still appears fleetingly in his songs,
but so intimately blended with Indian melodic phrases
that their tonality is not altered, only enriched with a
novel hue. It should be noted that Tagore never liked
polyphonic music.
As for classical Indian music, which is itself connected
with Mohammedan music, Tagore never followed the strict
rules which bind the musician in a network of precepts.
This often compels the creative faculty, bound in a rigid
frame, to develop in depth. But on the other hand it
may lead especially at the present day to a dry, stiff
and lifeless form which turns the remarkable qualities of
classical Indian music into as many failings.
Ornaments, beautiful in themselves, and necessary to
monodic music, abound to the point of suffocating both
words and melody; flexible and varied rhythms detach
themselves from the whole and focus the interest,
becoming the pretext for a contest between the drummer
and the musician he is accompanying; the râgas, which
gave such moving effects of atmosphere and colour by
their strict scales, by their few dominant notes, by other
notes which are left out or lightly suggested, by the
differences between their ascending and descending
movements, by their prescribed ornaments and pro¬
gressions, now sometimes became a tyranny.
Being connected with the hours of the day or the
seasons, with certain feelings, or even with visual forms,
these imperative formulae gradually became little more
than the pretext for a certain virtuosity, that of unlimited
development within a stereotyped frame. In this classical
music, composer and performer no longer seem to exist
separately. The musician receives and observes the
traditional outlines, and his task is to develop them,
recreate them, and enrich them with his improvisations.
His pride therein is legitimate, for in this art which is
never rejuvenated and never written down, he represents
the whole value of music.
Tagore's achievement as regards the classical music has
been, as with everything else, that of breaking fetters.
His whole life-work is imbued with that appeal to freedom
and simplicity, to the spontaneous and youthful élan
which no convention can bind. The things to be
destroyed are the hollow forms and the veneration given
to them. Hence the wrath of the old-fashioned musicians
20
MUSICAL DRAMA. Ra¬
bindranath Tagore grew up
in a home whose atmosphere
was inherently musical and
all his work is imbued with
melody, harmony and
rhythm. It has even been
said that a play by Tagore is
little more than a setting
for his songs, of which he
wrote more than 2,000.
Left and right, scenes from
Chltra, one of Tagore's
great dramatic masterpieces,
which was presented with
special musical accompani¬
ment at Unesco House last
year, in a new French trans¬
lation by Georges Fradier.
Photos D. Berretty-Unesco
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
brought up against a new kind of music which does not
pretend to replace their own, but which introduces the
composer as quite distinct from the performer, which
rejects rigid rules, and reverts to the simple melodic
contour of popular song that the professional musicians
held in such scorn.
In his reaction against both classical Indian and
Western music, Tagore finds his source of inspiration in
the mystic poetry and folk-songs of Bengal. Thus he
never was the "creator ex nihilo" that the Western world
sometimes imagines him to be. To see him as he really
is, rooted in his own soil, steeped in an age-long popular
tradition which culminates with him, is not to belittle
him.
In Tagore's music can be found certain modes and
certain râgas; these he sometimes uses so fantastically
that he scandalizes the votaries of classical Indian music.
His style is a simple one, and yet the melodic contour
is not harsh. It ls softened by numerous ornamentations:
guttural sounds, light, barely suggested appogiature and
discreet portandos. These never obscure or clog up the
musical phrase, but rather emphasize it by rendering it
softer and more pliable.
Equally simple are his rhythms, especially as compared
with those of classical Indian music or Kirtan, and they
seem to grow ever simpler as Tagore finds himself. They
are strict, flexible, and the beat is usually marked by a
snap of the fingers which is the only accompaniment of
this delicate music.
Music plays a great part in Tagore's life. In his Remi¬
niscences he recalls his childhood and youth steeped in
music, of long hours spent in a drifting boat while the
poet sang and his brother accompanied him on the violin,
of days spent at the piano or on the terraces, composing
songs.
In his later years, he found the same atmosphere at
Santiniketan, the school he founded to give a simple,
human education in contact with nature. Here the day
began and ended with the singing of Tagore's poems by
choirs of children. Other songs celebrated festivals. At
the frequent evening gatherings music had the place of
honour.
The Bengali system of notation Is a recent and
incomplete one, what it conveys by means of letters is the
mere skeleton of a song; the ornamentations and details
are practically left out; it is little more than a memor¬
andum which can only be of use to one who ls already
familiar with the melody. Oral tradition alone ensures
the survival of songs. Tagore knew his memory to be
poor and sometimes he even wished to forget previous
works so as to be free to create fresh ones; therefore when
he had composed a new song, he used to sing It to his
nephew Dlnendranath, thanks to whose excellent memory
the song was saved from oblivion. Sometimes the poet
had to learn his own songs afresh from Dlnendranath
whom he called "the treasure house of all my sones "
(Cycle of Spring.)
Tagore was quite conscious of the value of his own
musical compositions. "I have Introduced," he once said
"some new elements in our music, I know. I have
composed five hundred new tunes, perhaps more. This
ls a parallel growth to my poetry. Anyhow, I love this
aspect of my activity. I get lost In my songs and then
I think that those are my best work; I get quite Intoxicat¬
ed. I often think that, If all my poetry is forgotten, my
songs will live with my countrymen, and have a perma¬
nent place... All the same, I know the artistic value of
my songs. They have a great beauty. Though they
will not be known outside my province, and much of my
work will gradually be lost, I leave them as a legacy "
wrote Rabindranath Tagore.
A play by Tagore ls often little more than a setting for
the songs. The very titles of his books often suggest
music, for Instance "Sharps and Flats."
As often In Asian music, the songs of Tagore will not
suffer harmonization. The most Important things they
offer, it seems, are continuity of melodic line, delicacy,
suppleness, Intervals other than those of the temperate
scale, Inflections drawn out which melt Into tenderness
nostalgia (of which Krishna's far-off flute is the poetic
symbol). Everything which contributes to their value ls
destroyed if they are encased in the frame of too simple
a rhythm, too much cut-up, with too Insistent a beat, If
they are to become mechanical In order to give them
emphasis.
It Is thus my fervent hope that a tradition will remain
which will keep alive for ussung by a single voice and
practically without accompaniment the tenderness, the
supple, delicate and penetrating nostalgic charm of
Tagore's real songs, perhaps the most precious, moving
part of his work.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
^-s
REVELATIONS
OF A
NOBEL PRIZE
IN LITERATURE
by Mahmud Shah Qureshi
Bronze bust of Tagore
made by Jacob Epstein.
H. Roger Viollet, Paris
Among the modern thinkers of the Indo-Pakl-
stan subcontinent Tagore is undoubtedly
the most widely known to Western Intellectuals. The
reason Is obvious: he himself translated his exquisite
thought into English just as other writers rendered it in
divers tongues.
The award to him of the Nobel Prize in 1913 was probab¬
ly of little Importance in the West, but for the Oriental
intelligentsia its effect was considerable. It was not
Tagore a poet of the East or of Asia, of India or of
Bengal who was honoured, but rather a regional
literature which, although the most developed among its
Indian contemporaries, remained unnoticed by the world
until this dramatic recognition of its maturity.
In fact, since the early nineteenth century Bengal
spurred by the impact of Western civilization was heading
towards a Renaissance, reflected particularly in its
literature. Now, after eight-hundred years of a
predominantly agrestic character, Bengali literature
acquired a fresh sophistication.
The literary efforts of Ishwarchandra Vidyasager,
Michael Madhusudhan Dutt, Dinabandhu Mitra, Tekchand
Thakur, Bankimchandra Chatterji and Mir Musharraf
Hussain not only satisfied the new Bengal middle class
but are still regarded as the classics of its literature.
Bengal had already adopted Western literary forms
which it employed to give a new vitality to Indian
thought. Born in one of the families of Calcutta which
was active in furthering this Renaissance, Tagore directly
understood that it was his task to create a synthesis bet¬
ween old and new, between Eastern thought and Western
expression. This mission he brilliantly discharged.
T he living avatar of the Bengali Renaissance,
Tagore naturally drew his inspirations from
its old literature, from its religious and folk songs and
Sanskrit classics, but he also remained assiduously aware
of modern Western thought.
What did Tagore add to this rich heritage in the course
of a literary career protracted for more than sixty years?
MAHMUD QURESHI, Pakistani writer and poet in the
22 Bengali language, is professor of Bengali literature at
Chittagong University, Pakistan.
He wrote more than one thousand remarkable poems,
more than two thousand enchanting songs, nearly two
dozen plays, eight novels, eight or more volumes of short
stories in addition to several travel books and essays on
literary cultural, political or linguistic subjects.
Besides his humanitarian or educational services,
Tagore's paintings (1) and the abundance and variety of
his work evoke for Bengali critics the three universal
geniuses: Leonardo da Vinci, Goethe and Victor Hugo.
Every one has his personal predilection for Tagore as
poet or prose writer. Nevertheless his prose writings
such as the memorable short stories in Galpagucha,
novels like Gora, Choker-Bali, Ghare-Baire (The Home &
The World) , Shesher Kabita (The Last Poem) are epochal
events in Bengali literature. The rich personality of
Tagore, his warm human sympathies, his narrative gifts
are to be found only in his short stories.
DI eriving inspiration from Tagore, the novelist
Sharatchandra Chatterji was to give a new
orientation to the craft of fiction writing. Sharatchandra
and his followers had the signal advantage of greater
intimacy with the Bengal middle class and thus could
depict the insistent reality of its sufferings and joys better
than Tagore whose aristocratic upbringing constituted in
this respect a serious obstacle.
Among others who gave or are giving new directions to
Bengali prose literature, a few important names may be
mentioned: Pramatha Chowdhury (a great connoisseur of
French literature who exhorted Bengali prose writers to
follow French literary precedents) Rajshekhar Basu,
Bibhuti Bhushan Bondopadhyaya (author of Pother
Panchali, and Aparajita), Banaphul, Tarashankar,
Humayun Kabir, Annada Shankar Roy, Manik
Boudopadhyaya and Kazi Abdul Wadud.
In the domain of the novel and short story, Bengali
literature seeks to attain a level comparable with that of
the West. Yet it must be admitted quite frankly that
the greater part of its corpus lacks major stature because
of a certain sentimentality and an unduly restricted vision
of life.
(1) It is still a matter of controversy whether Tagore started
painting at the age of 65 or 70.
CONT'D ON PAGE 24
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
%JL tW* PLtJft id Y^K
23
Rabindra-Sadana, Visva Bharati Tagore at work in his study in I 93 I, the year he celebrated his 70th birthday.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
REVELATIONS (Cont'd)
Renaissance
of Bengali letters
Let us return to Tagore. This time let us observe the
mystery-world of his poetry. All Tagore's life constituted
an immense creative effort to communicate his most
sublime Intuitions to the world. The manifold variety
and profound depth of his poetic universe are so
remarkable that It seemed he was "redeeming the debt of
the world," a world which Induced all the anguish and
ecstasy of creation. It is not enough to have read
Gitanjali or Balaka (The Swan) to understand this
mysterious world; it is also necessary to read the poems
that reflect the different phases of his poetic career.
In addition to his personal experience and the associa¬
tion of his great father, Debendranath, who had a
profound understanding of the Persian mysticism, it is
the influence of the Upanishads which left the decisive
Imprint upon his poetic vision his love of nature, search
for truth and for humanity; to him these are nothing but
the characteristic signs of the Infinite.
This quest for the Infinite, as revealed in the Upanishads
"Bhumaiva sukama naipe sukhamasti" (Beatitude
reposes in the Infinite, not in the Finite) became the
motto of his poetic philosophy. It is astonishing to
discover that Tagore's patriotism, under the influence of
the Upanishads, was frequently at variance with public
opinion. His predecessor Bankimchandra said:
Do not forget that love of one's countrymen ranks
above all religion.
Rabindranath wrote:
Build high the throne of your nation
But remember it is not higher than truth
If you really love your country,
You must not rise above it,
Not place your country above humanity.
In his last years Rabindranath understood that with all
his philosophical pretensions and poetic illusions he was
inhabiting an ivory tower and suddenly felt the need to
draw closer to plebeian reality. Now he wrote:
Sweet is the earth, sweet the dust of it,
I've taken it in my heart,
This great hymn
Is the precept of my life.
Day after day, I've received
The gift of the truth,
And its sweetness has no end...
Or,
On the shores of Rupanarayan
I awoke
And I realized the world
Is not a dream.
I beheld my image
In letters of blood.
And I came to know myself
Though profound wounds
And through countless sufferings... (2).
Although Balaka had been written in a new style and
published before the First World War, Tagore realized
that all he had written before then was highly conven¬
tional. Thus, with the changing situation, he started
writing prose-poems on unconventional but quotidian
subjects.
This new direction Tagore gave to Bengali poetry by
his later writings served as a model for the young writers
while the writers of his generation were still imitating
his earlier style. Because of their conventional style and
poor poetic techniques they were soon eclipsed by the
brilliant achievement of Tagore.
Nonetheless two poets Satyen Dutt and Mohitlal
Majumdar (also a great critic) deserve particular men¬
tion. Satyen Dutt, besides his innumerable poems on
nature and patriotism which reveal extraordinary metrical
24 (2) The French version of the last poems of Tagore, trans¬
lated by Mahmud Shah Qureshi and André Guimbrétière was
published in the Revue Générale Belge, June, 1961.
Drawing by 1. Ross, Rumanian National Commission for Unesco
Rabindra-Sadana, Visva Bharati
.AfMr^fôt*"^-*- r ,,
f \:^jN^$rbTVn^'árír faw<^n^ %ïsffy~ ~
\4jjfc$t¡r '.wfafàs íiTírtf *t*t- -xniôr
«<*, f£rjlr»f-j$4? a»?¿far -
At y jlfcîfv** - wY, W-- .aV*/** -
ffiLT^SL'»***^ ¿*wr **>?C
«? otff c>r*r.*rr, inn- j*f"^«r^i^-I
¡ysjrSYy- <yiv>f-sns-~ xriQ0&kJ*t*Jn*' saifbr
tft&hr *«?f»v '&&>- &&Ç fié&HOiPfâ^J
Atixirf vffirtyp/ iSffSir -*a*r fcy-Aa/- / ', ,
-3 *w^ vrnr .- J Mil
y f :
les'
Q
)&*rrtri
H
*Qa
^,\
-/?(& Anyy-jr
V**"'
<* rH
fit
i.\s
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
C) Rdbindra-j-idana, Visva ßhufali
A GREAT DAY in the life of Tagore was the laying of the foundation stone of Vlsva Bharati, tho Inter¬
national university which grew from the school Tagore founded in 1901 at Santiniketan, as an experiment
with only twelve pupils, including his own son. Photo above, was taken in 1921 at a Vlsva Bharati ceremony
and shows, seated from left to right, Sylvain Levi, the French Orientalist, Tagore, and scholars who colla¬
borated closely with him including, foreground, famous philosopher Brljendranath Seal. Loft, a striking
portrait of Tagore drawn by I. Ross and taken from "Tagore In Rumania", a selected bibliography published
this year by the Rumanian National Commission for Unesco. The poet went to Rumania in 1926 during
a long trip through Europe when he visited Italy, France, England, Sweden, Norway, Denmark, Czecho¬
slovakia, Yugoslavia, and Bulgaria, before crossing the Danube into Rumania. Below left, the first extant
manuscript written by Tagore aged 17, It is a Bengali poem in which the young poet calls on the muses.
skill, translated more than five hundred poems from
different languages retaining all of their initial flavour
and content. His translations of Victor Hugo, Ezra Pound,
Verlaine, Maeterlinck, Baudelaire, Valéry, etc., preserve
the original rhyme and rhythm yet offer the savour and
qualities of true Bengali compositions. Satyen Dutt also
re-introduced many Arabo-Persian words which are
currently used In modern society or once were In medie¬
val literature. This gave new vitality to poetry, particular¬
ly in the passionate poems of Mohitlal Majumdar.
The new literary fashion reached its height with the
advent of a soldier-poet, Nazrul Islam, who accomplished
a synthesis between the revolutionary tradition of Islam
and the cult of Shakta (worship of the god of power).
These two thought currents are absent in Tagore, yet,
with the true generosity of genius, he acclaimed young
Nazrul. Indeed, Nazrul set off a veritable explosion in
the halcyon sweetness of Bengali poetry. The new
awareness which he reflected quickly gained the attentive
respect of the young writers. Thus he expressed himself
in his famous poem Vidrohi (The Rebel):
J am a rebel, a hothead,
I do what my heart desires,
Good, bad, true or false
I grapple with Satan himself
I welcome death with a song...
I am the rebel, weary of struggle
Still I will not rest till the day
The aggressor's sword be sheathed
In the field of battle
And the cries of the oppressed
No longer rend the air, etc. (3).
In addition to a great number of poetic works, short
stories and journalistic writings, Nazrul composed more
than three thousand songs which are still extremely
popular.
Jlvanananda Das and Buddhadeva Bose, two great
modern poets, derived their first Inspiration from Nazrul.
The genius of Tagore, In fact, offered an Insuperable
challenge to the young writers of the thirties, yet thanks
to the example of Nazrul and to the new poetic creations
of Tagore, they finally articulated a mature poetic idiom
which is still In vogue. Western symbolism certainly has
occupied a prominent place In the new poetry. Blshnu
Dey, Sudhln Dutt and Samar Sen are names indlssolubly
linked with this movement. Besides these examples,
Amiya Chakravarty in the tradition of Tagore, Jashl-
muddin (4) in the folklorique style and Farrukn Ahmad
in the footsteps of Iqbal (5) added new chapters In the
history of Bengali poetry.
In spite of that, whether in day-to-day activities or In
intellectual pursuits, the Bengalis still remain dazzled by
the luminous achievement and magnificent personality of
Tagore. For the Bengali Intelligentsia of India and
Pakistan, perhaps Tagore's greatest contribution lies in
the universal intellectual citizenship this achievement has
so lavishly conferred upon their literature.
(3) Luce Claude Maître in "Les Poètes Rebelles du Bengale"
(Revue Europe, May, 1954), dealt with Nazrul and some other
young poets.
(4) Two poems of Jashimuddin have been translated into
French by Jacques Stepowski. An English translation under
the title, The Field of Embroidered Quilt was published by
Oxford University Press. Another book will constitute a
Unesco Translation Project.
(5) Muhammad Iqbal (1873-1938) i3 the greatest Urdu poet
and most original thinker of Pakistan.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
éM&MSi «tfTTùïVr
k tuG&xr
1SHí5S>
£55535 Asxc^îc^a^zsï^si
*-vw?e-<*>»7jr<
READINGS FROM TAGORE
To celebrate Uie centenary of Rabindranath
Tagore's birth in 1861, Unesco arranged
this year for the translation and publication
of six books (see boxed bibliography).
On these pages we publish passages from
A Tagore Reader just issued by the Mac-
millan Co., as part of the Unesco Collec¬
tion of Representative Works Indian
Scries. The reader offers a comprehensive
view of Tagore's writing including passages
from his books on travel, his letters, short
stories, dramas, autobiographical sketches,
conversations with famous people includ¬
ing Einstein, fables, philosophical medita¬
tions, art and literary criticism, education
and selections from his poetry.
From 'A Sojourner
in Japan'
When I took my seat at early dawn on
a mat by the window, I realized that not only
are the Japanese master-painters but they
have reduced the whole of man's life to
an art.
From Letters
to a Friend
But by nature all men are dwija or
twice-born, first they are born to their
home, and then, for this fulfillment, they
have to be born to the larger world. Do
you not feel yourself that you have had
your second birth among us? And with
this second birth you have found your
true place in the heart of humanity.
From 'Pathe O Pather
Prante'
Something is taking shape throughout the
universe and through all eternity. We
feel the impact of it in the pain of our
hearts. The stage at which man has arrived
in the march of civilization has been
attained by the creative endeavours of
countless millions of unknown individuals,
the history of whose personal struggles lies
merged in oblivion. Whatever abides in
creation is the momentary handiwork of the
countless many who have passed away.
Those architects of creation, those that are
gone, are functioning within me the thing
called "I" only furnished them with a
sort of prop. The scaffolding of a house
in construction may be necessary today; by
tomorrow when there is no trace left of
it, no one will miss it. The completed
building never sorrows for its lost scaffold¬
ing. The point is that as I pace this path
I feel that much of the construction going
26 on within me is being stored in the
treasury of Man's creation, with the signa¬
ture of my name obliterated.
From 'My Life'
In regard to music I claim to be some¬
thing of a musician myself. I have composed
many songs which have defied the canons
of respectable orthodoxy, and good people
are disgusted at the impudence of a man
who is audacious, because he is untrained.
But I persist, and God forgives me because
I do not know what I do. Possibly that
is the best way of doing things in the
sphere of art, for I find that people blame
me, but also sing my songs, even if not
always correctly...
In the night we stumble over things and
become acutely conscious of their separate-
ness, but the day reveals the unity which
embraces them. And the man whose inner
vision is bathed in consciousness at once
realizes the spiritual union which reigns
over all racial differences, and his mind no
longer stumbles over individual facts,
accepting them as final. He realizes that
peace is an inner harmony and not an
outer adjustment, that beauty carries our
assurance of our relationship to reality,
which waits for its perfection in the
response of our love.
Conversation
with H. G. Wells
Tagore: The tendency in modern civili¬
zation is to make the world uniform.
Calcutta, Bombay, Hong Kong and other
cities are more or less alike, wearing big
masKs which represent no country in parti¬
cular.
Wells: Yet, don't you think this very fact
is an indication that we are reaching out
for a new world-wide human order which
refuses to be localized?
Tagore: Our individual physiognomy
need not be the same. Let the mind be
universal. The individual should not be
sacrificed.
Wells: We are gradually thinking now
of one human civilization on the founda¬
tions of which individualities will have
great chance of fulfillment. The individual,
as we take him, has suffered for the fact
that civilization has been split up into
separate units, instead of being merged
into a universal whole, which seems to be
the natural destiny of humankind.
Tagore: I believe the unity of human
civilization can be better maintained by
the linking up in fellowship and co-opera¬
tion of the different civilizations of the
world..."
From 'A Vision of India's
History'
...We have come to know that what
India seeks is not the peace of negation
or of some mechanical adjustment, but that
which is in goodness, and in truth of perfect
union... The true prayer of mother India
is:
He who is one, who is above all colour
distinctions, who dispenses the needs
of men of all colours, who compre¬
hends all things from their beginning
to the end, let Him unite us to one
another with that wisdom which is the
wisdom of goodness.
On Education
When races come together as in the
present age, it should not be merely the
gathering of a crowd; there must be a bond
of relation, or they will collide with each
other...
The object of education is to give man
the unity of truth. Formerly, when life
was simple, all the different elements of
man were in complete harmony. But when
there came the separation of the intellect
from the spiritual and the physical, the
school education put entire emphasis on the
physical side of man. We devote our sole
attention to giving children information, not
knowing that by this emphasis we are
accentuating a break between the intellect¬
ual, the physical and the spiritual way of
life...
The child learns so easily because he
has a natural gift, but adults, because they
are tyrants, ignore natural gifts and say
that children must learn through the same
process that they learned by. We insist
upon forced mental feeding and our lessons
become a form of torture. This is one of
man's most cruel and wasteful mistakes.
We rob the child of his earth to teach
him geography, of language to teach him
grammar. His hunger is for the Epic, but
he is supplied with chronicles of facts and
dates. He was born in the human world,
but is banished into the world of living
gramophones, to expiate for the original sin
of being born in ignorance. Child-nature
protests against such calamity with all its
power of suffering, subdued at last into
silence by punishment.
On Art and Literary
Criticism
A fight has been going on for a long
time around the saying, "Art for Art's
sake," which seems to have fallen into
disrepute among a section of Western
critics. It is a sign of the recurrence of
the ascetic ideal of the puritanic age, when
enjoyment as an end in itself was held to
be sinful. But all puritanism is a reaction.
It does not represent truth in its normal
aspect. When enjoyment loses its direct
touch with life, growing fastidious and
fantastic in its world of elaborate conven¬
tions, then comes the call for renunciation
which rejects happiness itself as a snare.
I am not going into the history of modern
art, which I am not at all competent to
discuss, yet, I can assert, as a general truth,
that when man tries to thwart himself in
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
.«r~ rrrtjïw
lusxr?
¿&MX:üg&Et&&.' Téff ypjm**
"Ol^rr^i
r*ifc*.rniigzffii5r *»«»»?»
'iSEBSET'
-V^/^^frtfT«-*
his desire for delight, converting merely
into his desire to know, or to do good, then
the cause must be that his power of feeling
delight has lost its natural bloom and
healthiness.
WORLD'S HOMAGE
TO A UNIVERSAL MAN
From 'Thoughts'
The true universal finds its manifestation
in the individuality which is true. Beauty
is universal, and a rose reveals it because,
as a rose, it is individually beautiful. By
making a decoction of a rose, jasmine, and
lotus, you do not get a realization of some
larger beauty which is interfloral. The true
universality is not breaking down the walls
of one's own house, but the offering of
hospitality to one's guests and neighbours.
Children are living beings more living
than grown-up people who have built shells
of habit around themselves. Therefore it
is absolutely necessary for their mental
health and development that they should
not have mere schools for their lessons, but
a world whose guiding spirit is personal
love. It must be an ashram where men
have gathered for the highest end of life,
in the peace of nature; where life is not
merely meditative, but fully awake in its
activities; where boys' minds are not being
perpetually drilled into believing that the
ideal of the idolatry of the nation is the
truest ideal for them to accept... where the
sunrise and sunset and the silent glory of
stars are not daily ignored; where nature's
festivities of flowers and fruit have their
joyous recognition from man; and where
the young and the old, the teacher and
the student, sit at the same table to take
their daily food and the food of their
eternal life.
We are like a stray line of a poem,
which ever feels that it rhymes with another
line and must find it, or miss its own
fulfillment. This quest of the unattained is
the great impulse in man which brings forth
all his best creations.
Our greatest men have shown immense
respect for mankind in their expectations.
The old is prudent but is not wise.
Wisdom is that freshness of mind which
enables one to realize that truth is not
hoarded in caskets of maxims, it is free
and living.
We come nearest to the great when we
are great in humility.
If you shut your door to all errors truth
will be shut out.
The false can never grow into truth by
growing in power.
Man's history is waiting in patience for
the triumph of the insulted man.
MANY countries marked the anniversary of
Tagore's birth throughout the year with
special radio and television programmes,
lectures, conferences, exhibitions, new trans¬
lations of the poet's works, and essay contests
in the secondary schools. Participating count¬
ries, in addition to those listed below, were
Austria, Chile, Costa Rica, Cuba, Nepal, the
Netherlands, Mexico, Poland, Rumania and
Uruguay.
BRAZIL issued a Tagore commemorative
stamp; translated several of Tagore's works
into Portuguese, the books being distributed
without charge to libraries and cultural centres
in Brazil and neighbouring countries. New
recordings of Tagore songs by Brazilian artists
were made and given to libraries. A Tagore
in Brazil exhibition held in Rio de Janeiro
early in 1961 is now on tour in Brazil.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA: The committee for the
Tagore Centenary arranged an exhibition on
Rabindranath Tagore and Czechoslovakia at the
Naprstek Museum in Prague, organized a con¬
ference at Prague's Municipal Library, put on
concerts of Czech music composed for Tagore's
poems and translated much yerse and prose.
FRANCE: On November 25, the Bibliothèque
Nationale in Paris opened a comprehensive
exhibition on Tagore featuring rare documents,
photographs, a special painting section. The
complete collection of Tagore's works in Ben¬
gali were shown to the public along with trans-
FROM UNESCO'S COLLECTION
OF REPRESENTATIVE WORKS
Indian Translations Series:
Gora by Rabindranath Tagore.
French translation by Marguer¬
ite Glotz and Pierre Fallon.
Published in 1961 by Ed. Rob¬
ert Laffont (Paris).
A Tagore Reader, anthology
edited by A. Chakravarty, Mac-
millan, New York ($6,50), Lon¬
don. (45/-)
Poems of Kabir translated by
Tagore To be republished by
Macmillan, London.
In preparation:
Choix de Contes (Selected
Tales) of R. Tagore. Being
translated into French by Mile
Bossenec. To be published by
Editions Gallimard.
Poèmes et Souvenirs d'En¬
fance de Tagore. Translated by
Mlle Bossenec and Mr. Balbis.
Republished with
Unesco's Endorsement:
Balaka (Cygne) by Rabindra¬
nath Tagore. French transla¬
tion by P.J. Jouve and Kalidas
Nag. Editions Stock, Paris.
lotions of his works in French and other lan¬
guages. The exhibition continues until De¬
cember 17...
Other celebrations were held in Paris at the
Musée Guimet, the Ecole des Longues Orientales
and by the Comité France-Inde and in Lille.
GERMANY (FEDERAL REPUBLIC): Tributes
to the great Indian poet began with a cele¬
bration in Cologne organized by the Deutsch-
Indische Gesellschaft under the auspices of
President Heinrich Lübkc. Other cities pre¬
sented such plays as The Post Ollice, Sacrifice
and The Red Oleander, and an exhibition of
Tagore's paintings.
INDIA: 1961 has been Tagore year through¬
out India. One of the highlights of many
commemorative ceremonies in Tagore's own
country was the International Literary Seminar,
organized in New Delhi with the participation
of Unesco, devoted to Tagore's immense in¬
fluence on both Orient and Occident. A mela
(lair) for Tagore the traditional Indian way
of honouring poets was held in November and
emphasized the cultural life and folk art of
West Bengal... An All-India Bengali Literary
Conference was held in co-operation with
Unesco at the beginning of this year devoted
to Tagore, the organization's first president.
Tho session was opened by Prime Minister
Nehru. Representatives of 23 countries attend¬
ed discussions on philosophy, religion, rural
reconstruction and other fields in which Tagore
was engaged.
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC: A Tagore week
was observed in November with visiting Indian
scholars invited to lecture. Works of Tagore
in Arabic were published and an exhibition of
the poet's painting displayed.
UNITED KINGDOM: A Tagore Foundation
lectureship was established at the London
University School of Oriental and African
Studies providing for three to four lectures on
Tagore each year in the summer term. In
England also the dance-drama Shyama was
produced with a full Indian cast and was such
a success in London that it went on tour in the
provinces and was recorded.
U.S.A. A Tagore chair of literature was
established for a distinguished Indian scholar
or public servant to visit the U.S. yearly to
lecture at one the following universities:
Chicago, California (Berkeley), Harvard, Michi¬
gan, Pennsylvania and Wisconsin. The Asia
Society, the Library of Congress and the New
York Public Library all arranged special exhib¬
itions. A Tribute to Tagore evening was held
at Town Hall, New York, with the American
poet, Robert Frost, as principal speaker. Times
Square, N. Y., was officially named Tagore
Square for a day.
U.S.S.R. The Russians have always been avid
readers of Tagore and although a 8-volume
series of his works already existed, this year a
14-volume jubilee edition of his complete works
wos published. A Russian documentary film
for the anniversary, produced by S. Boubrick and
scripted by Soviet poet Mikhail Matusovsky,
featured scenes shot in India and the Soviet
Union, the Tagore pointings shown when he
visited the U.S.S.R. in 1930, and excerpts from
a ballet bosed on his play Chitra, staged during 27
the yeor by the Kuibyshev Opera and Ballet
Company.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
THE TUMULTUOUS HISTORY
OF ANCIENT NUBIA
by Boris Piotrovsky
\\
D awn was just breaking and there was a slight
breeze blowing as we left the enchanting
Island of Philae. The greater the distance between us and
the island, the more picturesque became Its rows of
columns and the higher Its pyramidal pylons rose into the
air. With every movement of our boat the gloomy cliffs
took on different fantastic shapes and looked for all the
world like supernatural beings. But no sooner had the
first rays of the sun appeared than the visions of dawn
vanished like a meteor..."
These words were written more than a hundred years
ago by A. S. Norov, the Russian orientalist and states¬
man who visited Egypt at the beginning of 1835. His
Journey Through Egypt and Nubia contains colourful
descriptions of the majestic monuments to the past that
are scattered between the First and Second Cataracts
of the Nile.
When I made my trip from Aswan to Wadi Haifa in
the Sudan in 1956 to study the archaeological monuments
In the area that will be flooded by the new Aswan Dam,
I frequently recalled Norov's expressive descriptions.
For a long time only the magnificent Egyptian temples
attracted the attention of scholars. Then a systematic
archaeological survey, carried out at the time the first
Aswan dam was built, revealed the civilization of ancient
Nubia, a country whose riches constantly attracted
Egyptian conquerors.
In the fourth millenlum B.C., the formative period of
the ancient Egyptian state, upper Egypt and Nubia were
Inhabited by tribes with a common culture.
T he Nubian civilization began to
develop independently when
the centre of the Egyptian state
was moved to the north at the time of the
Ancient Kingdom. Nubia became an Egyptian border
region and the pharaohs of the 2nd, 3rd and 4th Dynasties
sent many expeditions there to bring back slaves, cattle,
gold and Ivory.
These predatory raids gave way to more peaceful
relations at a later date, at the time of the 6th Dynasty.
Although the Egyptian frontier passed through a point
near Aswan there were Egyptian fortresses farther to
the south, in the area occupied by the Nubian tribes,
and their garrisons fought off the attacks of the Bedouins.
Inscriptions made by the Egyptian nobles Una and
Huefkhor (middle of the third millenlum B.C.) record
interesting facts about the Nubians. Una tells how the
BORIS PIOTROVSKY is Director of the Leningrad Branch
of the Institute of Archceology, Academy of Sciences of
the U.S.S.R., and a member of the International Com-
28 mittee of Experts for the Safeguard of the Monuments
of Nubia.
Pharaoh Meren-ra ordered him to build cargo boats in
Nubia for the transport of stone: the timber was supplied
by the rulers of Nubia. Huefkhor's inscription contains
fascinating details about the "exploration of the road"
to the land that lay beyond the Second Cataract and
also about three expeditions that returned from it safely
with rich gifts.
N oticeable changes took place in
the ethnic composition of the
population of Nubia
in the latter half of the third mlllenium
B.C.; this was due to the infiltration of tribes of Negro
herdsmen who established a new and independent culture
and maintained intercourse with Egypt and the Red Sea
coastal tribes.
Nubia began to grow stronger in the 19th century B.C.,
the period of the Middle Kingdom, and the Egyptian
pharaohs sent their troops to subdue the country.
Inscriptions by Pharaohs Amenemhet I and Senusret I
tell of the stubborn struggle put up by the Nubian tribes
in defence of their independence and of the cruel treat¬
ment meted out to them by the Egyptians. Egyptian texts
then began to describe Nubia as "The Land of Kush."
Excavations made in various places in the Nile Valley
have provided enough evidence to enable us to define
the culture of these Nubian tribes.
As a result of the Egyptian advance against the north¬
ern frontiers of Nubia, the centre of the Nubian state
was moved to the city of Napata, near the Fourth Catar¬
act, far to the south. By the time of the 18th Dynasty
(16th Century B.C.) the Egyptians had reached even this
distant point. However, they succeeded In subjugating
only the banks of the Nile and the fortresses they built
were harassed by raiding tribes of nomads that appeared
suddenly out of the desert.
The conquest of the whole of Nubia was completed dur¬
ing the 18th Dynasty: an Egyptian nomarch (ruler of an
Egyptian nome or province), given the title of "Royal
Son of Kush," headed the administration. The famous
Egyptian conqueror, Tuthmosis III, left a triumphal
inscription at Napata, the Nubian capital: it tells of his
victories in Anterior Asia and of the Egyptian subjugation
of Nubia to its southernmost limits, as far as the "horn
of the earth." This short description tells of the conquest
of all Nubia:
"I, the Pharaoh have all the Nubians as my subjects,
they work for me as one man and are compelled to pay
tribute in the form of a host of articles from the horn
of the earth and an immeasurable quantity of gold from
Waut. There they build big barges and ships, and in
addition they pay tribute in ivory and ebony." The mag¬
nificent temples erected by the pharaohs of the 18th
Dynasty confirm that they regarded Nubia as their own
country.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
The situation remained unchanged throughout the
19th Dynasty. Rameses II, the most famous represent¬
ative of that dynasty, built a number of splendid temples
In the first half of the 13th century B.C. in Northern
Nubia (at Kalabsha, Gerf-Husein, Wadi-es-Sebua and
Derr). The most famous of all is the huge temple at Abu
Simbel.
The temples built by Rameses II are the last monuments
to Egyptian rule In Nubia; the decline set in at the end
of the 19th dynasty. At this time invasions from the
north increased and although Herihor, the High Priest
of Ammon, still held the title of nomarch of Nubia under
Rameses XI, the country was gradually becoming
Independent. This was the beginning of the ascendency
of the Kingdom of Napata.
The story of the rise of the Napata Kingdom remains
unknown to us, for we know the history of Nubia (Ethio¬
pia) mainly from the evidence of conquerors, from
Egyptian written sources in particular. And, Indeed, the
magnificent Egyptian architectural monuments diverted
the attention of archaeologists from the ancient
settlements and burial sites, the less Imposing remnants
of Nubian civilization.
In the 13th century B.C., the Kingdom of Napata was a
powerful centralized state embracing the huge territory
from the First (Aswan) Cataract in the North to the Sixth
Cataract in the South. Some of the southern nomes of
Egypt, those to the South of Aswan, fell to Nubia (the
Ethiopian Kingdom).
When King Piankhi ascended the Napata throne (circa
740 B.C.) he took advantage of the Internal dissension
and the enmity between the rulers of the different nomes
to launch a campaign against the country. He had
adopted Egyptian culture and the Egyptian religion and
Invaded the country as Its legitimate pharaoh, the wor¬
shipper of the supreme deity, Ammon.
An inscription by Piankhi in
Egyptian has been discovered
on a granite monument
near Napata; it describes the victories of
the Nubian king in Lower Egypt, in particular the capture
of Heliopolis and Memphis.
The king issued the following order to his troops on
their behaviour In Thebes, In the Temple of Ammon:
"When you reach Thebes and stand before Karnak, enter
the water, cleanse yourselves In the river, put on your
best linen raiment, lay aside your bows and arrows-
There is no strength in those who know not Ammon...
Sprinkle water on his altar. Kiss the ground before
him."
Piankhi's victories were not consolidated, however, and
when he returned to Nubia, Egypt again split up into a
multitude of petty nomes.
The Nubian kings consolidated their power over Egypt
under Piankhi's successor, Shabaka, the first pharaoh of
the 25th (Ethiopian) Dynasty, who had to carry on a
burdensome war against Assyria for Egypt's independence.
Piankhi's son Tcharka also took part In battles against the
Assyrians on the approaches to Egypt.
Tcharka became Pharaoh of Egypt in 690 B.C., at the
time of the fiercest struggle against Assyria. The Nubian
ruler met with temporary success In the early stages of
the war but in 671 B.C., Assyrian troops under King
Esarhaddon invaded Egypt; seized first Memphis and
then the capital, Thebes. Tlrhaka fled to Nubia, and
Esarhaddon, to mark his victory, erected a statue of
Tcharka, brought from Egypt, on the gates of his own
capital, Nineveh.
When the pharaohs of the Sals Dynasty ascended the
throne of Egypt, relations with Nubia became strained
and intercourse between the two countries ceased. The
Napata kings, however, retained Egyptian traditions,
considered themselves legitimate successors to the phar¬
aohs whose titles they bore, and were burled In pyramidal
tombs.
Even this brief survey of the long and ancient history
of Nubia shows it to have been one filled with conquests
and destruction, undergoing periods of development and
decline. Egyptian written records and art treasures are
almost the only sources from which the history of this
rich country may be studied. On the Egyptian monu¬
ments we come across Images of black Nubian prisoners
in leopard skins with ostrich feathers adorning their
heads; there are scenes in which they are portrayed
paying tribute In gold, ivory and strange animals. But
the civilization of this country that brought such rich
gifts to Egypt has not been studied archacologically.
Monumental edifices, gems of Egyptian architecture,
were erected in northern Nubia and have remained to Uns
day, victorious in the great battle against time.
But in addition to these grandiose monuments to the
majesty of Egypt, there remain hidden In Nubia the
relics of the little-known culture of those tribes on whose
land and by whose hands these magnificent buildings
were erected. The original and exalted culture of Nubia
undoubtedly had considerable influence on the history
of the entire North-East African area; for this reason
archaeologists and historians must make a careful study
of the records of the ancient Nubian culture now await¬
ing discovery on the site of the future reservoir to be
formed by the new Aswan Dam.
'Foto-Henrcd, 5lockho(rr>
Photo shows King Gustav VI Adolph of Sweden, chairman
of the Committee of Patrons of the Unesco Campaign to
Save the Monuments of Nubia, discussing the progress of
the campaign with Dr. Mohamed Awad, Chairman of the
Executive Board of Unesco. It was taken at a special
session of the Swedish National Commission for Unesco
attended by the King in Stockholm earlier this year.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
THE ART OF ETHIOPIA'S PAINTER-SCRIBES
by Abbé Jules Leroy
Two years ago, in October 1959, the Unesco Courier devoted an issue to the
lost past of Africa. At that time, the archaeologist, J. Doresse, sketched a
brief but evocative picture of the marvelous and legendary history of Ethiopia
and described the essential characteristics of the Ethiopian personality and
the way in which it has been formed by geography, ethnic mixtures and the
often dramatic events of the past. His account of the "Empire of Préster
John" naturally gave some space to its art. Unesco's recent publication of
an album of reproductions of some of the most beautiful of the Ethiopian
miniatures (1) reveals certain of the specific qualities underlying this supremely
religious art which draws its inspiration from the Old and New Testaments
and the Lives of the Saints.
Ethiopia is a land of moun¬
tain peaks. In fact, it is in
the high plateau region, where one
gasps for breath on wind-swept slopes
that the life of the nation ls
concentrated. Here, at an elevation
of seven to thirteen thousand feet,
was created and developed a civiliz¬
ation which, from the point of view
of political and cultural achievement
and from that of the artistic monu¬
ments which record its long history,
has no parallel in all Tropical Africa.
The monuments which date from
the earliest period of Ethiopian
culture, the famous monolithic
"obelisks" of Axum, as huge as those
of the Pharaohs, are a lasting tribute
to the technical mastery that enabled
these artists of the last centuries
before our era to cut, decorate,
transport and erect enormous stone
blocks. They also cast light on the
origins of this civilization. Although
(1) Unesco World Art Series Album:
Ethiopia, Illuminated Manuscripts, price:
$18.00; £6.8.0. Published by the New York
Graphic Society, 95 East Putnam Av¬
enue, Greenwich, Conn., U.S.A.
Since Christianity was Introduced Into the ancient kingdom of Axum (today
Ethiopia) In the 4th century, art and literature In this country have been almost
exclusively ecclesiastical, and monasteries and churches have remained until
recent times the sole guardians of culture. Below, on the Dabra Damo cliff,
which can be climbed only with a rope, stands Ethiopia's oldest monastery church.
Through the arrival of Christianity, Ethio¬
pia shared In the flowering of art In the
Byzantine world. Monasteries and Churches
became centres of religious, cultural and
political development. Ethiopian Chris-
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
it has often been erroneously traced
to Egypt, Its real birthplace Is the
kingdoms of the Arabian coast, which
is only separated from the Abyssinian
highlands by a narrow stretch of sea.
Engaged primarily in the spice
trade, whieh long made Arabia Felix
wealthy, and trading also In goods
from Central Africa, these South
Arabian kingdoms (Hadramut, Saba,
Mina, Yemen...) obeyed a fundament¬
al rule imposed upon aU maritime
communities. In order to survive,
they had to establish trading posts
abroad and, to defend them, colonize
the surrounding countryside.
There can be no doubt that this
historic law governed the foundation
of the Axumlte kingdom. There Is
much evidence to prove the common
ancestry of the Ethiopian people and
their neighbours. They do not
belong to the Negro race. Both the
color of their skin and their cultural
traits relate them to the people of
the Arabian peninsula. From them
they took their first art, now well-
known because of archaeological ex¬
cavations in the region of Axum.
From them they also borrowed their
Semitic language, Geez and even their
Sabaean writing. They were not,
however, slow in transforming the
latter Into the admirable Ethiopian
alphabet which, with its 182 charac¬
ters, is capable of rendering every
nuance of pronunciation. As Mr.
Doresse noted, Ethiopian borrowing
has never been a simple copying.
Everything was assimilated and
transformed, and became the birth¬
right of a united, active people who,
at one time In their history (the third
and fourth centuries A.D.), even
succeeded In imposing their domin¬
ation over the Arabian regions from
which their ancestors came.
No doubt Ethiopia would have
remained a part of Semitic civiliz¬
ation and culture had its destiny not
been changed by a momentous event
In the fourth century. This was King
Ezana's conversion to Christianity by
Frumentlus, a native of Tyre in Syria.
The conversion, which took place
around 340 A.D., had a double effect.
It made Ethiopia the first Christian
state of Tropical Africa. It also creat¬
ed a new mentality, a consciousness
of being a special race, "chosen" by
its acceptance and maintenance of
the religion of Christ, an island in a
sea of Infidels. This frame of mind,
whose roots are so evident In the
Judaism which Ethiopian Christianity
combined with the teachings of the
New Testament to a greater extent
than was done anywhere else, finds
expression In the coronation cerem¬
ony which makes the Negus a kind
of African Byzantine Emperor. One
of his functions, according to the
text of the Constitution of 1955, ls
In fact, "to defend the Holy Orthodox
Faith based on the doctrines of
Saint Mark of Alexandria" (art. 21).
This psychology has given the
Ethiopian Church a privileged place
In the organization of the State.
With the Emperor, it ls even today
the real unifying agent of a vast
kingdom where several ethnic groups
Uve side by side and where the large
number of different languages and
dialects could easily fragment the
country. From this point of view,
Ethiopia resembles all African coun¬
tries, and has the same need for
another language to make commun¬
ication possible among Its peoples.
The Imperial proclamations, as well
as the laws, are now drawn up In
two languages, Amharlc, the language
of the Court, and English, which ls
thus promoted to the rank of a second
official language.
tianity, in common with other Eastern
churches, has never shown much interest
in sculpture. The ancient Axumite King¬
dom, however, boasted craftsmen capable
of producing works like this ornate cross.
í ...
No people has ever written so copiously on parchment as the Ethiopians. Today
the art of writing and producing books In manuscript Is still practised with the
same traditional methods and processes as for centuries past. There are many
remote churches and monasteries in the mountains where sacred books and
prayer books are still hand written. Below, miniature Illustrating the Nativity.
f\T<D£\ x-hCh-ftir. a\ 1t> i. hh-físsrftl-tfí
u
u
©
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
PAINTER-SCRIBES (Cont'd)
32
Illumination in the mediaeval manner
Historically speaking, the Ethiopian
Church has played a role analogous
to that of the Latin and Greek
Churches in the feudal society of the
Middle Ages. In a very real sense, it
has been the educator of the nation.
It ls In the Church that Ethiopia
has found Its scholars, artists and
schoolteachers. Although the State
ls employing more and more teachers
each year to staff the many schools
It ls constructing, It ls still not un¬
usual to find some priest or dabtara
providing the ancestral form of
Instruction In country villages. He
assembles all the school-age popu¬
lation under a shady sycamore at the
edge of the village. Swaying rhythm¬
ically, the children chant In unison
the letters or texts he has written
on the blackboard. The long staff
he carries ls not just a badge of
authority. He often uses It to call
the children to order. For It ls
difficult to concentrate on the
complicated Geez letters when
thousands of the brlghtly-hued birds
that enliven the Ethiopian landscape
are flitting through the boughs over¬
head, their song mingling with the
chorus of young voices.
The sole function of priest and
dabtaras has not been the education
of children. They have also been
the principal artisans of Ethiopian
culture as it is expressed in literature
and art.
Enrico Cerulll, who ls probably the
greatest contemporary authority on
Ethiopian literature, provides a
penetrating study of Its essential
characteristics in his Litteratura
Etiópica (2nd ed., 1960). These can
be reduced to three: receptivity, in
the sense that the Ethiopians have
found their inspiration and doctrines
In Greek, Syrian, Arab-Christian and
Western sources; ability to adapt
foreign elements to the taste of the
country; and, finally, a sort of
sclerosis, which compels authors to
shackle their work in rigid, unchang¬
ing literary forms fixed by rules
which nobody dares break.
The art of Ethiopia reflects
the same tendencies. Ar¬
chaeologists became aware of this
when they discovered the influence
of the architecture and sculpture of
the South Arabian founders of
Abyssinia upon the monuments of
the Axumite period. But the quality
of dependence is even more striking
in the works Christian Ethiopia. One
sees it in the astonishing rock chur¬
ches, of which the ensemble of Lali-
bela offers the most remarkable
examples, as well as in the paintings
that decorate the waUs of churches
and the pages of manuscripts.
Of all forms of Ethiopian art, the
illuminated manuscripts are known
best. Painter-scribes have produced
an incalculable number of them,
following traditional methods which
are still current in monasteries and
at the Court. Beginning In the six¬
teenth century, many of these books,
often decorated with brilliantly color¬
ed paintings, have found their way
Into large libraries like those of
London, Paris and the Vatican. Their
presence among us makes study of
their themes, techniques and sources
much easier.
In a general way, one can say
that Ethiopian painting
exactly reflects the various contacts
this far-off Christian kingdom has
had with the rest of the world. A
first period, as far as can be deter¬
mined at present, seems to be fairly
recent. These are the works of the
14th and 15th centuries, the period
covered by the Unesco albums. Be¬
neath the naive features and the
often clumsy drawing, analysis reveals
the influence of Byzantine or Middle
Eastern art which the Ethiopian
painters could have known either
from Imported books or because they
had seen it when they went on pil¬
grimages to Jerusalem.
A second period begins after the
arrival of the Portuguese who, at the
beginning of the 16th century, helped
the Christians drive out the Moslem
invaders led by Mohammed Granyé.
With this contact, a new style appear¬
ed. Inspired by Western painting, it
was more linear and elaborate than
the earlier work. This was the epoch
of the civilization of Gondar, which
lasted for nearly two centuries. In
the course of this long period tastes
changed, and the imitation of West¬
ern styles became more marked,
particularly as regards the use of
perspective and relief, which were
absolutely unknown before the
massive penetration by Europeans.
The penetration, which was much
facilitated by the opening of the
Suez Canal and the European policy
of Menellk and his successors, has
excercised a pronounced Influence
upon modern Ethiopian painting, and
particularly upon the work of young
contemporary artists. While some
remain faithful to the aesthetic and
iconographie rules Inherited from the
past, others, trained in the methods
taught in foreign schools, are
completely Western in technique and
style. It is too early to say what
effect their innovations will have on
the traditional painting of Ethiopia.
But one thing is sure. It will remain
true to itself and, as It has always
done in the past, will once again
assimilate outside Influence without
losing its own personality.
A scholar and authority on Middle East
manuscripts, Abbé Jules Leroy is a former
director of the Imperial Section of
Archrology in Addis Ababa. He is now
attached to the Centre National de Re¬
cherche Scientifique in France.
Paintings from Unesco World Art Series Album: 'Ethiopia, Illuminated Manuscripts'
>.<>^ää<>:o:<^<^<>;<^<>:<^<«
LUKE THE EVANGELIST. A portrait of St. Luke
writing the first words of his gospel. Miniature from
the Kebran Manuscript (early I 5th cent.). Preserv¬
ed In St. Gabriel's Church In the Lake Tana region.
SitfcftiJhs;
THE ANNOUNCEMENT TO MARY. In this
stiff, formalized version of the annunciation scene,
the Virgin is shown spinning. Taken from the manu¬
scripts of the Jahjah Giyorgis gospels (Mid- 1 5th cent.)
THE ENTOMBMENT. Here the Ethiopian minia¬
turist has depicted disciples bearing the body of
Jesus towards a grave depicted as a geometric,
abstract shape. From the manuscript of St. Arsima.
«*£»*
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
AFRICA'S WILD LIFE IN PERIL
Sir,
The success of the recent Arusha
Conference must largely be ascribed
to the change of attitude so clearly
brought out by the African partici¬
pants themselves toward their unique
wildlife resources. The earnest desire
of modern African States to continue
and actively expand the efforts made
in the field of wildlife management is
greatly encouraged by the interest and
support of international organizations.
Your Sept. 1961 issue devoted to the
world's wildlife heritage, not only
showed Unesco's interest, but the
excellent choice of the cover photo¬
graphs ably illustrated the fact that the
Organization understood the problems
involved "from beginning to end."
Your choice of the elephant, as the
most striking, as well as the most
adaptable of all animals after man
could not have been a happier one.
Gerald G. Watterson
Secretary-General - IUCN
Morges près Lausanne, Switzerland
Sir,
Your issue on Africa's Wildlife in
Peril (Sept. 1961) was absolutely
magnificent. As a member of the
Fauna Preservation Society and as
"A Friend of I.U.C.N." I was delight¬
ed with it. I have just ordered four
more copies to send to some of my
friends.
Dr. T. H. Basse«
Lethbridge, Alberta, Canada
Sir,
Having spent two months on safari
(photographic) in East Africa this
winter, I read with much interest and
understanding Sir Julian Huxley's
article in the September Courier on
"Poaching". The fact of knowing
beforehand about the systematic
slaughter by organized commercial
poachers of the wild game in Africa,
made me view the relatively few
remaining animals with wonder closely
allied to a sense of sadness and
despair.
Were these gazelles moving across
the plains, these rhinos, elephants and
giraffes who form our last link with
the prehistoric age, soon to disappear
from the world, leaving future gene¬
rations with only written and pictor¬
ial records of what Africa once
meant to everyone who, if only in
their imaginations, loved and revered
its great wild life heritage? And the
new States of Africa, how would
they develop and progress when
deprived of one of their main eco¬
nomic revenues?
Sir Julian speaks of the vital neces¬
sity of the new African governments
recognizing and supporting their na
tional parks to achieve "Profit, Pro¬
tein, Pride and Prestige." It is signi¬
ficant and depressing to note, in the
words of Sydney Downey, one of East
Africa's leading conservationists, in
connexion with the recent Internation¬
al Game Conference in Arusha,
Tanganyika that "no member of the
Kenya Government and no Kenya
African politician could take the
trouble to attend." Obviously at pre¬
sent little help or co-operation can be
expected in this direction.
What can be done, then, to prevent
one of the few remaining wonders,
not only of Africa but of the world,
from being totally annihilated through
ignorance, savagery and greed? Until
the inexperienced and short-sighted
African Governments can be shown
the inestimable value to themselves and
their countries of this wild life heri¬
tage, it remains the task of world
organizations and of influential indi¬
viduals, to give aid both in financing
the upkeep of the National Parks
(thereby eliminating poaching) and in
conünually educating the African peo¬
ple and their leaders to the realization
that without this unique inheritance,
East Africa particularly would lose its
greatest natural resource.
If world opinion has been roused
to save the monuments of Nubia
(monuments which exist in a country
already overrich in historical build¬
ings, etc.) surely "the task of saving
the threatened wild life in Africa"
should take priority? If this aid is
not given now, Africa's only living
monument to the past will be lost
forever.
Noreen Curry
Winnipeg, Canada
JAPAN MISREPRESENTED
Sir,
I welcomed the article "Japan
Misrepresented" having felt for some
time that there are gross misrepre¬
sentations and therefore gross mis¬
conceptions taught in schools in the
subjects of geography and history.
Particularly is this inexcusable in
the highly educated countries of the
western world, where large sums are
spent on education. Schools seem
to set a national identity for a
country, and stick with it regardless
of changes within that country.
Colin Jose
Moose Jaw, Saskatchewan), Canada
Sir,
Can you kindly forward the en¬
closed chapter on Japan from the
textbook Eurasia to Mr. Tatsumi Shi-
mada, author or the article "Japan
Misrepresented" in the April, 1961,
issue of The Unesco Courier.
Dr. Robert M. Giendinning, the
author of Eurasia, and the editorial
staff at Ginn and Company have
made every effort to present an
accurate picture of Japan to school
children in the United States.
We will welcome Mr. Shimada's
evaluation of our material and will
give serious consideration to all sug¬
gestions which he may have for its
improvement.
Robert N. Suvcland, Editor
Lands and Peoples of the World
Hosion, Mass, U-S.A.
Ed. note: The Unesco Courier
applauds this initiative of Lands and
Peoples of the World in seeking to
present a true picture of Japan to
U.S. schools and hopes the example
will be followed hy other publishers.
The text of Eurasia has been for¬
warded to Mr. Sh imada.
Sir,
"Japan Misrepresented" A Look
at Foreign Textbooks, was very
interesting. Textbooks with inap¬
propriate pictures were exhibited at
an Exhibition Hall in Tokyo recently
and I saw many of them with my
own eyes. That article reminds me
that the Japanese themselves may
misunderstand the real life of other
nations. Naturally, the mutual
understanding of all the nations in
the world must be attained through
the medium of periodicals of many
countries. I am much impressed that
the Unesco Courier took up such
problems and showed actual mistakes
with pictures to the readers. However,
I believe it would have been much
more effective if you had printed
those examples with the right pictures
of present-day Japan.
Masaharu Inafoml
Nerima ku, Tokyo
THE CURSE OF THE ALBATROSS
AN APOLOGY
Sir,
In my article "The Curse of the
Albatross A Mariner's Myth", which
was published in the March 1961 issue
of The Unesco Courier, I did not
indicate that I was very largely inspir¬
ed, when writing this article, by the
book entitled "The Wandering Alba¬
tross" by Admiral Sir William Jame¬
son. I very much regret that I omitted
to indicate such an important source.
For this omission I wish to apologize
both to Admiral Jameson and to
Unesco.
I would be obliged if you would
publish this rectification in an early
issue.
David Gunston
Denmead, England
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Ne
DIRECTOR-GENERAL OF UNESCO RESIGNS
Mr. RENÉ MAHEU NAMED AS ACTING HEAD
34
Dr. VITTORINO VERONESE
THE resignation of Dr. Vittorino
Veronese as Director-General of
Unesco and the appointment of
Mr. René Maheu as Acting Director-Gene¬
ral until the November 1962 session of
the General Conference were announced
on November 2. The resignation of
Dr. Veronese was announced in the follow¬
ing statement made by Dr. Mohamed
Awad of The United Arab Republic, chair¬
man of the Unesco Executive Board.
"The Executive Board of Unesco deep¬
ly regrets to announce that it has received
from the Director-General of Unesco,
Dr. Vittorino Veronese, a letter asking that
he be relieved of his post as Director-
General. Dr. Vittorino Veronese has been
lately on leave for medical reasons; and,
although he has fully recovered his health,
docs not consider it advisable that he
should continue to assume the heavy du¬
ties and responsibilities »hich his post as
Director-General of Unesco demands. For
this reason he has asked the Board to
accept his resignation as soon as possible.
The Executive Board, while recognizing
the great services rendered to the Organi¬
zation by Dr. Veronese in the past three
years, cannot nevertheless, oppose the
wishes of one to whom it is so deeply ¡n-
Mr. RENÉ MAHEU
debted, and has therefore no other course
but to accede to his wish and accept his
resignation."
The Executive Board then unanimously
appointed Mr. René Maheu as Acting
Director-General until the next session of
the General Conference elects Dr. Vero¬
nese's permanent successor.
Dr. Veronese was born in Italy on March
1, 1910. After becoming a member of the
Italian National Commission for Unesco
he was elected to membership of Unesco's
Executive Board in 1952, and became its
chairman in 1956. He was elected Direct¬
or-General of Unesco in December 1958.
Mr. René Maheu was born in France on
March 28, 1905. He graduated from the
Ecole Normale Supérieure and taught phil¬
osophy at the University of Cologne
(1931-33), the French Institute of London
(1933-1939) and the Franco-Moslem Col¬
lege of Fez (1940-42). From 1936 to 1939,
he served as Cultural Attaché with the
French Embassy in London, before entering
military service. Mr. Maheu joined
Unesco in September 1946, as head of the
Division of Free Flow of Information.
In 1949, Dr. Jaimes Torres Bodet, then
Director-General of Unesco, appointed him
as Director of his Office. He was appoint¬
ed Assistant Director-General in July 1954,
and, with the same rank, Unesco Represen¬
tative to the United Nations in New York
in November 1955. Mr. Maheu return¬
ed to Unesco Headquarters in December
1958 and in November 1959 was appointed
Deputy Director-General by Dr. Vittorino
Veronese.
THE UNESCO PHILATELIC
SERVICE
NACIONES UNIDAS «í>W
OBbEAMHEHHblE HAUiVW
The work of the U.N. Economic
Commission for Africa has been com¬
memorated in the stamp above
which was issued by the United Na¬
tions Postal Administration on Octo¬
ber 24 (U.N. Day) as the fourth in
its 1961 series of commemorative
stamps. This U.N. Commission
seeks to promote concerted action
for the economic development of
Africa, including its social aspects,
especially the standard of living
of its peoples. The stamp has been
issued In two denominations: 4 cent
(blue, orange, yellow and light
brown) and I I cent (green, orange,
yellow and dark brown). As the
agent in France of the U.N. Postal
Administration, Unesco's Philatelic
Service stocks all the United
Nations stamps currently on sale.
It also has stamps and first day
covers issued by many Unesco
member states to commemorate
important events in the history,
of Unesco and the U.N. (inaugura¬
tion of Unesco's headquarters.
Human Rights Day, World Refugee
Year). Information on Items avail¬
able, their price and the methods
of payment will be sent on request
by the Unesco Philatelic Service,
Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
O
UJ
u
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO
ART
SLIDES
A collection of colour transparencies to make known to the
public masterpieces of world art which, in spite of their Impor¬
tance for the history of art and for the understanding of the
genius of the nation which created them, are all too often
unknown. Most of the slides are based on the Unesco World
Art Series Albums, with which readers of the Unesco Courier
are already familiar.
The slides, produced for Unesco by Publications Filmées
d'Art et d'Histoire in Paris, are of top quality and reasonably
priced. They are presented in a plastic case for ready projec¬
tion, each series containing thirty transparencies, in mounts
5x5 cm, and an explanatory booklet with text and titles in
French, English and Spanish.
The very high standard of colour reproduction makes these
slides valuable not only to teachers and lecturers but also to
art lovers everywhere.
Series now available:
1. EGYPT: Paintings from Tombs and Temples.
2. YUGOSLAVIA: Mediaeval Frescoes.
3. INDIA: Paintings from the Ajanta Caves.
4. IRAN: Persian Miniatures, Imperial Library.
5. SPAIN: Romanesque Paintings.
6. NORWAY: Paintings from the Stave Churches.
7. MASACCIO: Frescoes in Florence.
8. AUSTRALIA: Aboriginal Paintings from Arnhem Land.
9. CEYLON: Paintings from Temple, Shrine and Rock.
10. NUBIA: Masterpieces in Danger.
I I. U.S.S.R.: Early Russian Icons.
To be published shortly:
12. MEXICO: Prehispanic Paintings.
13. JAPAN: Early Buddhist Paintings.
14. CZECHOSLOVAKIA: Manuscripts with Roman and Gothic Paint¬
ings.
Prices vary according to country, but do not exceed the
equivalent of $10 In local currency.
In certain countries special agents have been appointed for
the sale of Unesco Art Slides (see following list)orders and
requests for further information should be sent direct to
these addresses.
Argentine: Editorial Sudamericana, S.A., Alslna, 500, Buenos Aires.
Australia: Tradco Agencies, 109, Swanston Street, Melbourne, C.I.
Belgium: Louis de Lannoy, 22, place de Brouckère, Brussels.
Denmark: Mellemfolkelight Samvirke, Kronprlnsessegade 32 (4),
Copenhagen.
France: Unesco, DPV, 7, place de Fontenoy, Paris (VII").
Publications Filmées d'Art et d'Histoire, 44, rue du Dragon, Paris (VI*).
Rousseau, 6, place Chapou, Cahors (Lot).
India: National Education and Information Films Ltd., National House,
Tulloch Road, Apollo Bunder, Bombay I.
Israel: Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd., 35, Allenby Road, and 48 Nahlat
Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv.
Spain: Librelra Científica Medinaceli, Duque de Medinaceli 4,
Madrid 14.
Sweden: Svenska Unescoradet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stockholm C.
Switzerland: Films Fixes Fribourg S.A., 20, rue du Romont, Fribourg.
United Kingdom: Educational Productions Ltd., East Ardsley, Wake¬
field, Yorkshire.
All branches of H.M. Stationery Office.
U.S.A.: Unesco Publications Center, 80 I, Third Avenue, New York 22,
N.Y.
For countries not listed, application should be made to
National Distributors for Unesco Publications (see list below).
ere to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; rates quoted are
for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO COU¬
RIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Press Department, Royal
Afghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Melbourne University Press, 369 Lonsdale Street,
Melbourne, C. I., Victoria. (A. 1 5/-). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C\, Spengergasse 3 9, Vienna V
(Sch. 50.-). BELGIUM. Office de Publicité S.A.,
16, rte Marq, Brussels. CCP 285.98. NV Standaard-
Boekhandel, Belgielei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courrier ( I 00 FB) and art slides only : Louis de Lannoy,
22, place de Brouckère, Brussels. CCP 3380.00
BURMA. Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road,
Rangoon. (K. 5.50). CANADA. Queen's Printer,
Ottawa, Ont. (S 3.00). CEYLON. The Associated
Newspapers of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Colombo, 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World'Book Co. Ltd., 99 Chungking South
Rd., Section I, Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa). CUBA.
Librería Económica, Pte Zayas 505-7, Apartado 113,
Havana. (2.25 pesos). CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia
Ltd., 30 Ve Smeckach, Prague 2. DENMARK. E|nar
Munksgaard, A/S Tidsskriftafdelingen, 6 Nórregade,
Kóbenhavn K. (D.kr. 12). ETHIOPIA. International
Press Agency. P.O. Box I 20. Addis Ababa. FINLAND.
Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinski.
(Fmk. 540). FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco. Place
de Fontenoy, Paris, 7». C.C.P. 12598-48. (7 NF.).
GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier, Vertrieb Bahren¬
feld ïr-Chaussee 160, Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, C.C.P.
276650 (DM 8).- Other Publications: R. Oldenbourg
Verlag. Rosenheimerstrasse 145, Munich. GHANA.
Methodist Book Depot Ltd. Atlantis House, Commercial
St., POB 100, Cape Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See
United Kingdom. GREECE. Librairie H. Kaufímann,
28, rue du Stade, Athens. HONG-KONG. Swindon
Book Co., 25. Nathan Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY.
Kultura, P.O. Box 149. Budapest, 62. INDIA Orient
Longmans Ltd. Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcucta 13; Gun-
foundry Road, Hyderabad, I; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/1 Asal Ah Road, P.O. Box 386, New
Delhi, I ; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.,
17 Park Street. Calcutta 16, Scindia House, New Delhi.
(Rs. 6.70). INDONESIA. Bappit Pusat Permata ".
Djalan Nusantara 22, Diakarta. IRAQ. Mackenzie's
Bookshop. Baghdad. IRELAND. The National Press,
2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd., 3 5, Allenby
Road and 48, Nahlat Ben|amin Street, Tel-Aviv (l£ 4.-).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour
Street, Kingston. Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
(10/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Ton-Nichome,
Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605 Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
(Yen 670). JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co ,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road, P.O.B. 66, Amman.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. LIBERIA. ). Momolu
Kamara, 69, Front and Gurley Streets, Monrovia.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück. 22. Grand-
Rue, Luxembourg. MALAYAN FEDERATION
AND SINGAPORE. Federal Publications Ltd.. Times
House, River Valley Rd., Singapore. MALTA. Sa-
pienza's Library, 26 Kingsway, Valetta. ( I 0 -). MAU¬
RITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street,
Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid des
Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (7 NF.). NETHERLANDS.
N.V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9. The Hague,
(fl. 6). NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES. G.C.T.
Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.) N.V., Willemstad, Curacao.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications Centre,
lOOHackthorne Road, Christchurch. ( I 0 -). NIGERIA
CM. S. Bookshop. P.O. Box 174, Lagos. ( I 0 -). NOR¬
WAY. For the Unesco Courier: A.S. Narvesens Littera-
tur-Tieneste, Stortingsgt. 4, Olio, Postboks II 5(kr. I 3 20)
Other publications. A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille Grenien,
7, Oslo. PAKISTAN. The Wcit-Pak Publishing Co.,
Ltd., Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box 374, 56-N
Gulberg Induscnal Colony, Lahore. PANAMA.
Cultural Panameña, Avenida 7a. No, TI-49, Apartado
de Correos 2018, Panama, D.F. (Balboas 3-).
LIPPINES. Philippine Education Co. Inc., I 104 Canilló¬
los. Quiapo, P.O. Box 620, Manila. POLAND.
" RUCH " ul.Wiloza Nr. 46, Warsaw 10 (Zl. 50).
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada Lda. Livrana Portugal.
Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. RHODESIA & NYASA-
LAND. The Book Centre, First Street, Salisbury,
Southern Rhodesia. SWEDEN. For The Unesco
Courier: Svenska Unescoradet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 7.50); other publications A B CE. Fruits
Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasi«
Zurich. Payot, 40, rue du Marché, Geneva. CCP.
1-236. «Courier» only: Georges Losmaz, I, rue des
Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. C.C.P. 1-481 I. (Fr. S. 8).
TANGANYIKA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B.
9030. Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND. Suksapan
Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok. (35
ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu. Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda
Bookshop, P.O.. Box 145, Kampala. UNION OF
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Bookstore. Libri
Building, Church Street, Pretoria. For the Unesco
Courier: Central News Agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johan¬
nesburg. (10-). UNITED ARAB 'REPUBLIC
(EGYPT). La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha,
Cairo. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E I. (10 -). UNITED
STATES. Unesco Publications Center, 801 Third
Avenue. New York, 22, N.Y. (S 5 00) and (except
periodicals): Columbia University Press. 2960 Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y. U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja
Kniga, Moscow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslo-
venska KnjTga, Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
L'ART DANS U VIE DE LTOMME S
\*r*"
X '
Jy-
LA SCIENCE DANS LA VIE DE L'HOMME
WmFïMmi
«Wrica
'50 years ol
'"dependence . ,
mer
1( v"
<
"BiGöürier
Unesco Courier
subscription makes an
ideal and inexpensive New
.ear's gift for your friends and
relatives which will be remembered
every month Have them join the more
than one million readers of The Unesco Courier
Write to the agent in your country listed overleaf.
ONE YEAR'S SUBSCRIPTION 10 - - $3.00 - 7 NF.
]]>
</page>
</document>
