<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="064591eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
mm* mtm MM mm
-*>
East Africain Railways and Harbours
F. Bourlière
RHINO AND OFFSPRING turn quizzical looks on the photographer in the unique Ngorongoro Crater of the
Serengeti National Park, Tanganyika. Not really dangerous unless startled or annoyed into charging, rhinos will
usually make off with a loud steam-engine snorting when disturbed. Ngorongoro is to be shorn from the National
Park, according to a Government plan. Below, herds of Topi antelope and (background) buffaloes in the Congo's
vast Albert National Park. National Parks form an irreplaceable network of protected zones for African wild life
incomparable laboratories for animal research and centres of natural beauty for the enjoyment of the public.
'
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
^^-^»i A WINDOW OH» O« THI WONLO
Courier
SEPTEMBER
14TH YEAR
Contents
No. 9
PUBLISHED IN
EIGHT EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
American
Japanese
COVER PHOTO
The elephant plays a unique
role In nature by combining
functions of aerating the soil,
opening uptrackways through
forests, providing water for
the animal community by
digging, and making food
available to other species
such as the baboon, by
knocking down fruit from off
the trees. Elephants often
seem the most peaceable of
animals and may be watched
quietly from no great dis¬
tance If the wind Is blowing
from them. But when the
great ears are spread and
the trunk rises In alarn. or
anger, It Is time to retire.
Photo Dr. B. Grzimek © Tier-
bilder Okapia, 'Frankfort
Page
4 AFRICA'S WILD LIFE IN PERIL. EDITORIAL
5 THE VANISHING HERDS
By F. Bourlière
8 POACHING : THE SLAUGHTER OF WILD LIFE
By Sir Julian Huxley
15 WILD LIFE AS A WORLD ASSET
Quotations from Sir Julian Huxley on Africa
18 THE DRAMA OF SERENGETI
19 (I) TWO MEN AND A «FLYING ZEBRA'
By Pauline Bentley
23 (2) FIGHT FOR LIFE AT NGORONGORO CRATER
By Sir Julian Huxley
24 THE CANADIAN CARIBOU-A DISAPPEARING SPECIES
By A.W.F. Banfleld
28 WHERE TIME STOOD STILL
The Galapagos Islands, living laboratory of evolution
By Jean Dorst
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
(r-I.C. 6 1. 1. 16 I A)
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7', France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
Gordon Behrens
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition
Spanish Edition
Russian Edition :
German Edition
Arabic Edition :
Japanese Edition
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Jane Albert Hesse
: Arturo Despouey
Veniamin Matchavarlanl (Moscow)
: Hans Rieben (Berne)
Amin Chaker (Cairo)
: Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in July and August when
It is bi-monthly ( I I issues a year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German
Arabic and Japanese. In the United Kingdom it is distributed by H. M
Stationery Office, P. O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinced providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represenc
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in The Readers' Guide to
Periodical Literature published by H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates: U. S. S 3.00; IO/-stg. ; 7.00
New Francs or equivalent. Single copies l/-stg. 30
cents (U.S.) ; 0.70 New Francs.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
AFRICA'S WILD LI
| he conservation of the world's natural resources and particularly Its wild life has been
a serious preoccupation of Unesco since its creation.
The Unesco Courier, in the past, has devoted space in several issues to this vast
problem (1). The present number deals in major part with the wild life of Africa. It is published
on the eve of an important international conference, to be held this month In Tanganyika, on
the threat to nature and the need for conservation in tropical Africa. The meeting under the
auspices of Unesco and FAO has been called by the International Union for the Conserva¬
tion of Nature and Natural Resources (IUCN) and the Commission for Technical Co-operation
In Africa South of the Sahara.
Last year, Unesco commissioned Sir Julian Huxley to make an on-the-spot Investigation
of the state of wild fauna and natural habitats in central and east Africa. Sir Julian's book
on this subject is to be published by Unesco in October. This issue brings readers salient
passages from his alarming and challenging report.
Unesco has just completed, too, a broad survey of the natural resources of the entire Afri¬
can continent. More technical [in nature, It is probably the most. complete analytical survey
yet made of our present knowledge of the vast resources of this awakening continent. Pro¬
fessor Bourlière's article, on the facing page, is an edited version of a chapter from this volume
to be published at the end of the year.
It has become almost commonplace nowadays to speak of the spiralling growth in our
planet's population which has increased by 500,000,000 persons since the beginning of
the present century. But this and the concomitant demands of modern civilization for more
food and more. space, have meant that the few untouched natural areas of our planet where
animal herds can still roam freely are being steadily encroached upon. They are rapidly shrink¬
ing in size and their wild life is threatened with extinction.
That is why national parks and nature reserves, which now exist in practically every civilized
country, are considered of greater importance than ever before. That is why the United Nations
Economic and Social Council recently deemed it both urgent and vital to ask the IUCN to com¬
plete a study of the world's existing national parks and reserves.
4 Wild life and its natural habitats are a scientific and cultural heritage of all mankind.
The editors present this issue as a warning cry to alert public opinion to the perils which endanger
this heritage today.
(1) Jan. 1952; April 1954; Jan. 1958; April 1958; Jan. 1959.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
FE IN PERIL
Wild cattle in this panoramic view are herds
of wildebeest (gnu) which range the mid-Afri¬
can plain by the thousand. Many now face
the danger of extinction if left unprotected.
Photo A. Milotte, from the film The African Lion "
© Walt Disney
THE VANISHING HERDS
by Professor F. Bourlière
Professor at the Faculté de Médecine, Paris
Vice-President of the International Union for Conservation
of Nature and Natural Resources
Among all the continents, Africa is remarkable
for its wealth of large mammals, representing
at the same time a zoological community unmatched
elsewhere in the world and a traditional source of protein
food for the human population.
Prior to the European penetration of the continent,
there was a balance between this fauna especially
abundant in the savannah regions and Man. The
hunting methods then in use could not seriously endanger
any wild species, and domestic livestock, their only
possible competitor, was extensively raised only in certain
parts of the continent, mainly in the east and the Sudan.
The drying up of the Sahara at the end of the
Pleistocene era had, of course, driven many species
southwards; yet, even in 1750, Michael Adamson noted the
presence of elephants and hippopotamuses in the lower
valley of the Senegal, and hippopotamuses were .still to
be found in Egypt- about 1815. At the other end of
Africa, the first Dutch colonists who landed in the Cape
region saw a kind of zebra the quagga now extinct, as
well as elephants, black rhinoceros, hippopotamuses and
countless antelopes, as was testified by Van Rlebeck in
his comments in 1653.
The extension of European influence rapidly destroyed
this delicate balance, which had been maintained for
thousands of years and had been chiefly due to the
small size of the human communities, to demographic
stagnation and static technology. The decline of wild life
came earliest and was most rapid in South Africa. The
development of colonization by whites very soon drove
many species northwards, and this tendency increased in
pace during the nineteenth century and at the beginning
of the twentieth. Road building, the advance of stock
farming, and the fencing of grazing lands completely
did away with the large ungulates (these are chiefly
grazing animals) in most of this region.
In East Africa, the same causes produced the same
effects, though at a later date. In these regions, however,
as well as in some places in Central and West Africa, the
spread of certain methods of combating human and
animal epidemics resulted in a sharp decrease in the game 5
animal population; game eradication campaigns, for
instance, destroyed hundreds of thousands of ungulates.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
THE VANISHING HERDS (Cont'd;
Network of protected zones
More recently, in all the savannah zones, the increase
in the human population, and consequently in the
number of cattle, sheep and goats, accentuated the
tendency, since all these domestic animals came into
direct food competition with the wild species. Meanwhile,
the use of firearms and the practice of poaching with
wire snares had spread all over the continent.
All these demographic and technological factors have
combined to produce a considerable reduction in the area
of distribution and in the density of the wild animal
population. In the last twenty years, it has become
possible to cover hundreds of miles in Africa without
seeing any of the animals so closely associated in our
minds with the very name of that continent.
This situation soon began to alarm many far-seeing
people. In 1933, the first Conference for the Protection
of the Fauna and Flora of Africa was held in London, to
study methods of dealing with this problem, without, of
course, in any way prejudicing the necessary improvement
in the standard of living of the human population.
As a result of the conference, a convention was
signed, to which most of the countries then
responsible for the administration of African territories
officially acceded. This London convention provided for
the establishment of nature reserves and national parks
in all the territories of the signatory governments; it also
laid down a set of principles relating to the trade in skins
of wild animals, to certain prohibited hunting methods
and practices, and to the special protection to be given to
some particularly threatened species.
Provision was also made for periodical meetings to
consider how the convention was being applied and to
improve it if necessary. The first of these meetings took
place in London in 1938, and significant progress was
recorded in the conservation of wild life. Because of the
Second World War, it was impossible to hold the next
meeting before 1953; it then took place at Bukavu
(Congo) , on the initiative of the Commission for Technical
Co-operation in Africa South of the Sahara. Important
amendments to the 1933 convention were proposed, in the
light of twenty years' experience and of the advances
made in animal and plant ecology.
Apart from its provisions relating to hunting and
forests, the London convention had, then, implicitly been
mainly concerned to ensure the establishment of a
network of national parks and nature reserves in which
the flora and fauna would be entirely protected and
which would thus preserve for posterity as complete a
sample as possible of the various African biotic commu¬
nities.
This policy, was the logical outcome of the ecological
concepts prevailing at the time, according to which a
"natural balance" was capable of maintaining the flora
and fauna of a region unchanged, provided that Man
and his train of domestic animals were kept out. What
happened later in the best studied large national parks in
Africa was, paradoxically, to prove the falseness of this
concept; this result alone would justify the existence of
such parks and reserves, for they are as indispensable to
research in pure and applied ecology as are hospitals to
medical research.
The list of African national parks and nature reserves
is a long one and cannot be given here. Readers interest-
ed in this question may consult Derniers Refuges (Last
Refuges), a remarkable Atlas of the world's national
parks and nature reserves, prepared in 1956 by the Inter¬
national Union for Conservation of Nature and Natural
Resources. It should be mentioned, however, that the
parks there referred to are not all comparable as regards
their statutes, their objectives, the extent of the work
carried out in them, or even the effectiveness of their
surveillance.
6 The parks which have enjoyed the most efficient su¬
pervision and where the most intensive research has
taken place are unquestionably those of the former
Belgian Congo, and especially the Albert National Park.
No part of the tropical world has been the subject of such
long, careful, and exhaustive study, by specialists of 15
different nationalities. This research is still continuing,
and decades will be needed before all the material collect¬
ed can be fully examined.
The Nimba Reserve, in Guinea, is the best known
among those in West Africa. It has been continuously
explored since 1942, and has formed the subject of a
number of. important publications. Next comes the
Niokolo-Koba National Park in Senegal, which protects
a fine sample of savannah fairly near to Dakar.
The famous Kruger Park, in the Transvaal, began to
be the subject of systematic scientific study only in 1958,
although it is the oldest of the African parks, having
been established in 1926.
In East Africa, most of the ecological research has been
done especially by a series of Fulbright research scholars
from the United States in the national parks of Uganda,
the Queen Elizabeth National Park and the Murchison
Falls National Park. We should also mention the game
census made by the Grzimeks at the Serengeti National
Park in Tanganyika, and the ecological studies and
research into animal behaviour carried out at the Nairobi
National Park and the Mara Reserve by various English
and American naturalists.
In Madagascar, the ten nature reserves established in
1927 have been studied mainly by zoologists from the
Scientific Research Institute of Madagascar. Most of
the ecological work, however, still remains to be done.
Apart from the important Institutions mentioned above,
which have played a notable part in the history of
African biology, there are a number of parks and reserves
which have not as yet been systematically prospected;
they are chiefly known as tourist attractions and as
economic assets for the countries which own them.
Among these are the parks of Kenya (Tsavroand Am-
boseli), the Wankie and Kafue National Parks in the
Rhodesias, Waza in Cameroon, St. Floris, Zacouma and
Baningi-Bangorram in the' Central African Republic, etc.
All these reserves now form an irreplaceable network
of protected zones within which most of the interesting
species of African savannah fauna have been able to
maintain themselves; at the same time, they are in¬
comparable laboratories for the study of tropical ecology
and all its implications; agricultural, zootechnie, and
medical.
But nature conservation is not merely a matter of
protecting species and environments and constituting, in
the form of national parks, a series of "standard" natural
habitats through which it becomes possible to appraise
the good or bad effects of the transformations imposed by
man on nature. It must also be deliberately dynamic,
for progress in ecology makes it possible to give mankind
effective help in its fight against hunger and to contribute
towards better living conditions.
Tihere are now, besides classical conservation
techniques, new methods of wild life manage¬
ment which have already yielded remarkable results in
other parts of the world, notably in North America and
the Soviet Union. These techniques would appear to be
applicable to game animals of the African savannahs,
even perhaps under particularly favourable conditions.
A quantitative study of the wild African ungulates-
counting their numbers, analysis of their structure by
age and sex, determination of birth and death rates4ias
demonstrated something that had previously been only
suspected and the full importance of which had not been
grasped: namely, the vast size of the mammal game
population and its domination of the whole savannah
community. The tonnage of live animal matter (still
called standing crop biomass) they represent per acre is
such that these grazing animals normally make up
almost the whole of the consumers of the plant food
produced by the savannahs.
CONT'D ON PAGE 34
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Unesco - Alain Gille
Uganda Dept. of Information
STRONGHOLD OF THE WILD. East Africa has been called "The Stronghold of the Wild", yet
even here where 28,000 square miles of territory have been declared as National Parks or Reserves,
the wild life resource has been shockingly reduced from its past abundance. Below, bathtime for
hippos in Murchison Falls Park, Uganda's largest national park, which is bisected by the Nile.
Above, the world's tallest grazing animal. Giraffes, which may grow to be from 16 to 20 feet tall,
are splendidly adapted to the tree-browsing habit. The giraffe's tongue may be a foot and a half
long and using this and its long upper lip, it can quite easily wrench loose mouthfuls of leaves.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
POACHING
by Sir Julian Huxley
ÉÍ"PHE most interesting assignment I have T;
Julian Huxley recently used to describe
the investigation which Unesco asked him to
undertake last year on the conservation of
wild life and natural resources in Central and
East Africa. Sir Julian's journey lasted three
months and took him to ten countries the
Federation of the Rhodesias and Nyasaland,
Tanganyika, Kenya, Uganda, Zanzibar, Mo¬
zambique, Ruanda Urundi and the eastern
strip of the Congo an area of 1,500,000 square
miles, equal to the size of Europe (excluding
Russia). The noted British zoologist and first
Director-General of Unesco visited 25 national
parks and reserves in these countries as well
as in South Africa, and had discussions with
hundreds of scientists, statesmen, game war¬
dens and administrators both black and white.
The following article is taken from the Intro¬
duction to the forthcoming Unesco book by
Sir Julian Huxley on his mission.
he wild life of eastern Africa Is the wonder
and envy of the . rest of the world. Unique
in abundance and variety, it has been gravely diminished
in the past and is seriously threatened in the immediate
future. Its natural habitats and wild lands cover more
than half of its immense area, and are of tremendous
potential importance if properly used. But they too have
been reduced in extent, their value has been sadly
reduced by improper use and they are threatened with
drastic misdevelopment in the immediate future.
With the alarming increase in organized poaching, the
equally alarming increase in population, the new methods
of controlling tsetse-fly and diseases of livestock, the
fashionable urge towards technological and agricultural
development, the spread of money values among the
African population, and the rapid emergence of African
Governments, the situation is critical.
The future of African wild life is bound up with that
of the conservation of natural resources. Both are now
in the balance. The next five or at most ten years will
be decisive in determining whether they are headed
downhill towards a point of no return, or set on the
upward path of beneficial development.
The situation can still be saved, provided that the
conservationists can induce African Governments and '
the African public to understand and follow an ecological
approach.
WASTE-PAPER BASKETS. Most poaching is done not to obtain food but trophies
like rhino horn, tails for flywhisks and elephant tusks for curios. Carcasses are left to rot.
Below, 77 elephants' feet turned into waste-paper baskets for sale to tourists. Elephants have
been known to tear half their trunks off in frantic efforts to escape the poacher's wire snare. Photos Dr. B. Grzimek,
Tierbilder Okapia, Frankfort
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
THE SHOCKING SLAUGHTER
OF AFRICA'S WILD LIFE
Ecology is the science of interrelations. It studies the
balance to be achieved in a system of interacting factors.
Some ecological systems are in stable equilibrium for
instance, climax communities in nature, such as un¬
disturbed rain-förest or mountain heathland. But in
others the equilibrium may be upset, either by natural
causes like climatic change, or by human interference,
accidental or deliberate deforestation as in Greece or
China or Syria; or introduction of alien species of animals
or plants, as most strikingly in places like Australia or
Hawaii.
Let me state the African situation in ecological terms.
The ecological problem is fundamentally one of balancing
resources against human needs, both in the short and
in the long terms. It thus must be related to a proper
evaluation of human needs, and it must be based on
resource conservation and resource use, including
optimum land use and conservation of the habitat.
Over the whole of south-eastern Africa, the wild life
resource has been shockingly reduced from its astonishing
past abundance. In the Union of South Africa today,
large wild animals have virtually ceased to exist save in
scattered National Parks and Reserves or on farms where
they are deliberately preserved as a source of revenue;
the white-tailed gnu is almost extinct, and the quagga
has disappeared for ever. Less than a century ago, we
have many accounts (Baldwin's African Hunting is a
well-known . example) of abundance of elephant, hippo
and rhino, and truly vast herds of antelope and zebra.
In East Africa, a similar abundance of big game
survived into the present century. In, his Kenya Diaxy
(1957) Meinertzhagen records seeing in 1903 a procession
of some 700 elephants marching across what is now the
township of Nyeri; he states that the country swarmed
with rhino, one of which charged into a race-meeting;
and in one day in an area of 24 square miles actually
adjacent to Nairobi he counted 684 Zebra, 894 Wildebeest,
276 Coke's Hartebeest (Kongoni), 326 Grant's Gazelle,
426 Thomson's Gazelle, 184 Impala and 46 Eland, besides
Giraffe, Rhino, Wart-hog, Wild Dog, and over 4,000 Masai
cattle.
At the same time, Abel Chapman in his African Safari
(1908) recorded the same profusion of Wild Life in all
these East African territories, and for many years later
the suburban gardens of Nairobi would be visited by
lions.Everyone, including myself, who was in East Africa
a mere thirty years ago, can testify to the striking dim¬
inution of its large wild life since then, and Cullen
and Downey (1960) give a picture of its present grave
state. Fraser Darling (1960) records a similar deterioration
of the game situation in Northern Rhodesia since Charles
Pitman made his survey in 1934.
In spite of all this, the wild life of this region Is still
SLOW DEATH. Wire snares are by far the cruellest method used by African poachers.
Animals often die slow, agonizing deaths. In the Northern Range of Uganda alone more
than 2,000 snares were found last year,' and reports from all over East Africa tell the same
story. Here a zebra, strangled by poachers, lies dead in Serengeti Park, Tanganyika.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
AI Malotte from the film "The African Lion Walt Disney
WATER HOLES and salt licks are favourite spots for snares. Game wardens in
Uganda recently reported discovering a full grown lioness (like one above) which,
snared by the leg, had wrenched the limb off onlyto perish through gangrene. Unless
stopped, authorities say, the wire snare may ultimately exterminate Africa's wild life.
a resource of unique value. It must be preserved both
as an object of study and as a spectacle to be enjoyed.
Its scientific study is a necessary basis for proper land
use policies, and an increasing number of people from
all over the world are finding unique satisfaction and
interest in it as a spectacle.
Proper management of wild lands can yield a large
crop of wild meat as well as numerous ancillary animal
and plant products. The meat-crop could in particular
areas be commercially profitable, but of more general
importance is the fact that it would go a long way to
satisfying the Africans' meat-hunger, which springs from
the region's marked protein deficiency.
This in turn would help in reducing the threat of
poaching to African wild life. "Poaching" today is in
reality a large-scale illegal trade in slaughtered wild
animals. It is by no means confined to killing for meat:
all too often it takes the horrible and wasteful form of
merely taking the valuable trophies, such as rhino horn,
wildebeest tails, or elephant ivory, and leaving the
slaughtered carcasses to rot.
The abolition of this shocking trade is becoming just
as compelling an aim in the Africa of the present as
was the abolition of the slave trade in the Africa of a
century ago. Like the slave trade, it is profitable, highly
organized, extremely cruel, and quite ruthless.
Poaching is sometimes condoned, or at least leniently
treated, by those in authority as a result of the not un¬
common feeling among administrators that tribal Africans
should in general be favoured in getting what they want,
and specifically on the ground that they need all the
meat they can get.
This may hold in theory for the African who is permitt¬
ed a muzzleloader primarily to protect his crops, or even
for the bowmen from traditional hunting tribes who are
permitted to use arrow-poison. But it does not work out
that way in practice.
For one thing, it is quite certain that many slaughtered
10 animals described as raiding crops are really killed for
meat, with crop-raiding given as an excuse. But much
more important is the fact that illegal killing for meat
has now in several areas become a large-scale organized
racket, notably to supply the protein needs of the Africans
working in the Northern Rhodesian copper belt. Bicycle
boys deliver the meat, either directly or to lorries which
transport it to mine townships. Although often in bad
or even disgusting condition, it fetches high prices, almost
as high as beef or mutton in European shops.
Since game is naturally more abundant in National
Parks and Reserves, these are the favourite target for the
poachers. The Kafue Park in Northern Rhodesia, for
instance, is suffering heavily: large areas are being
devastated by fires lit deliberately by poachers to drive
the game to where it can be killed. This February the
Wardens in the Murchison Falls Park in Uganda had to
cope with a poaching gang of 70 Africans.
But killing for meat is a minor menace. Most "poach¬
ing" is frankly killing for money money from the sale,
often for export, of commercially valuable "trophies."
The main trophy is elephant ivory, employed chiefly for
knicknacks and curios. This is followed closely by rhino
horn, whose alleged but entirely mythical aphrodisiac
properties have led to its commanding the fantastic price
of over £4.10. a lb, for export to the East.
Hides of tangulatons, skins of leopards, colobes, monkeys
and other species, antelope and buffalo horns, sinews,
bones, and (on a surprisingly large scale) tails for
fly-whisks also find a ready market. From most of the
tens of thousands of animals killed by poachers in eastern
Africa today, the trophies are cut out, most of them to
be used for trivial or ignoble purposes, and the meat
simply left to rot.
A reliable informant in Kenya has given me the
following facts. For rhino horn, the poacher receives
from 7/- to 10/- per lb, and for elephant ivory 2/- to
3/- per lb (except in Kambaland, where the price is much
higher.) The horn and ivory passes through the hands
of several middlemen, all of whom take considerable
profits. The legal auction price in Mombasa during the
first ten months of 1960 was between 90/- and 94/- per
lb for rhino horn, and between 9/- and 23/- per lb for
ivory, according to quality.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Atlantic Press
TRIBAL PARTY, armed with antiquated guns and cheap muzzle-loaders, leaves for poaching
expedition. Guns are made available for the protection of crops, but are often used for illegal poach¬
ing. In Tanganyika alone, it is estimated that there are 80,000 muzzle-loaders and shotguns in the
hands of the inhabitants. Animals shot by such weapons are often maimed and die a lingering death.
In London, ivory prices are about 5/- a lb higher.
The yearly legal sales for 1955-1960 averaged 1,400 lbs
for horn and 73,500 lbs (nearly 3 1/2 long tons) for ivory,
representing 175-200 rhino and around 1,000 elephants.
Poaching, however, accounts for many more deaths.
The annual total of elephants legally and illegally killed
in Kenya is estimated at 4,000 to 5,000, and of rhinos at
675 to 950. While the Kenya elephants seem able to hold
their own, the much smaller and less biologically re¬
sourceful rhino population cannot possibly support such
a drain for more than a few years. Wildebeest tails for
fly-whisks may sell for as much as £2.
The poacher's methods are not only wasteful, but
extremely cruel. It is bad enough when gangs of
bowmen with poisoned arrows wait near a waterhole or
at a gap in a prepared barrier, and shoot large numbers
of animals, which then die an agonizing death. However,
pitfalls are worse; in the Serengeti, for instance, whole
series of carefully-sited pitfalls have been laboriously dug
(providing proof of the value of the proceeds).
The large numbers of animals which fall into them
suffer a much more lingering death than those shot with
poisoned arrows. But wire snares are the worst of all.
Wire is cheap, and can be obtained in all sizes, up to a
strength which will hold an elephant. Long lines of
wire nooses are laid out; zebra, wildebeest, antelope,
rhinos and elephants get caught by the leg.
A few animals are caught by the muzzle, and some
elephants by the trunk. In the Murchison Falls Park,
the Warden has seen an elephant which had lost its
trunk, undoubtedly In this way. In spite of this, it was
able to feed by kneeling on its forelegs, raising its hind
legs, and cropping coarse herbage with its lips a re¬
markable evidence of the elephant's adaptability.
The wire is attached to a stump or to a log which the
animal can barely move. Its struggles tighten the wire
and make it bite deeper; the wound festers; and the
creature dies a slow and horrible death, sometimes beset
by. vultures and hyenas. It is too often a lingering death,
for the poachers usually put off visiting the snares until
the animals are dead or dying.
The killing of game is facilitated by the abundance of
muzzle-loading guns in the hands of Africans. This is
especially serious in Northern Rhodesia and Tanganyika
(in Kenya and Uganda, muzzle-loaders are not permitted
except in a few cases for prestige reasons.) In
Tanganyika, for instance, the Kenya Wild Life Society
estimated that In 1958 there were about 70,000 muzzle-
loaders and 10,000 shotguns in African hands, while the
number of unlicensed weapons was probably greater.
In Northern Rhodesia between 45,000 and 60,000 muzzle-
loaders and guns are estimated to be in the hands of
poachers. Muzzle-loaders are either antique or home¬
made. They are essentially cruel weapons, for they are
usually inefficient and often only wound their victims.
In areas like Kenya it is to be hoped that the new
African governments will realize the importance of
continuing their prohibition, in the interests of law and
order as well as of game conservation. In territories
where they are now permitted, It would be unwise and
perhaps impossible to prohibit them by law, and measures
must be taken to reduce their numbers. This could
probably best be accomplished by raising licence fees.
One often hears of unfair discrimination against
Africans, but in this matter of licences the discrimination
is the other way round: gun and shooting licenses are
very expensive for Europeans, but very cheap for Africans.
A considerable rise in license fees for Africans, coupled
with strict enforcement of their payment, should bring
about a corresponding fall in the number of muzzle-
loaders. And there would be little sense of grievance if
at the same time governments were to take on more of
the responsibility for crop-protection, and to start game-
cropping schemes to provide more legal meat. The
poaching trade flourishes as it does because of another
factor in the human ecological situation the unim¬
portance of wild life in the eyes of most administrators in
the region.
In general, it is fair to say that Wild Life and Nature
Conservation are regarded as of little- importance 11
compared with Agriculture or Veterinary or Social
Services. Game Departments and National Parks
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
PROFIT
PROTEIN
PRIDE
PRESTIGE
PROFIT FROM TOURIST REVENUE-PROTEIN FROM
SALES OF MEAT AND GAME-CROPPING - A SOURCE
OF LOCAL PRIDE AND INTERNATIONAL PRESTIGE
Organizations are starved of staff and funds, and so
rendered incapable, not only of preventing poaching, but
of performing any of their other functions adequately
research, survey, game-control, provision of tourist
facilities, publicity.
The other basic ecological factor in our region is the
existence of vast areas of wild and marginal land,
unutilized or too often misutilized. These probably in¬
clude more than half of its one-and-a-half million square
miles. Much of this is infested with tsetse (1), and much
is too arid for agriculture or domestic stock. However,
cultivation has been permitted in large areas and has
often led to their deterioration and to the reduction of
their wild life.
In other large areas, notably In Masailand and northern
Kenya, traditional nomadic pastoralism is practised. Here
we come up against human ecology: the pastoralists do
not hunt game, but cattle have a central position in their
way of life and thought, and are valued for this and not
as a source of profit. Accordingly with the help of
veterinary science, stock has multiplied, and these regions
are suffering, in some cases severely, from overgrazing.
In general, there has been a tendency to satisfy the
immediate demands of African tribes at the expense of
long-term planning, and to embark on sporadic projects
of a traditionally respectable nature, like agricultural
development, without considering alternatives like wild
life management.
What is needed is a comprehensive and conservationist
land use policy for the region, based on proper survey, to
decide which land should be allocated primarily for
agriculture and for commercial or industrial develop¬
ment; which allocated for game-cropping, watershed
protection, forests, National Parks and Nature Reserves, or
merely kept undeveloped in reserve until its best use can
be determined; and which could be best developed by
establishing a fruitful symbiosis between wild life and
domestic stock.
In official thinking and practice, projects involving
conservation, especially of wild life, are usually subject
to provisoes about "human interests" or "utility." Thus
the establishment of the Tsavo National Park in Kenya
was only permitted because the area was regarded as
"useless;" and the Conservation Unit which was set up
to conserve the resources of the Crater Highlands in
Tanganyika, including that unique wonder of the World,
the Ngorongoro crater with its herds of wild game, was
officially instructed to do so primarily in the "human
interests" of the local Masai these being of course to
keep the maximum number of domestic stock in the area.
The constant use of these phrases betrays a misconcep¬
tion of the real situation, which would be ludicrous if it
were not so serious. The term "utility" should not be
confined to customary types of development and land use,
or to the production of marketable products like beef,
groundnuts, timber, or hydroelectic power. It should be
regarded as "useful," and is certainly valuable, to
preserve land from deterioration, to maintain forest cover,
to keep habitats for scientific study, and to conserve wild
life to attract those who want to enjoy it in natural
surroundings. In any modern planning, the concept of
utility in the customary sense must give way to the
overall concept of value not only utilitarian value, but
(1) It is estimated that at least one quarter of the entire area of
the African continent is infested with one or more species of tsetse.
12
ELEPHANT TUSK below, obtained legally several years ago in the Congo, is reputed to be the world's
largest. A brisk illegal trade in ivory obtained from poaching exists throughout tropical Africa despite
government efforts to halt it. In Kenya it brings up to 23 shillings per pound while rhino horn commands
the fantastic price of£4.10. a lb. ($12.50). From 4,000 to 5,000 elephants are killed annually in Kenya alone.
UNESCO - Alain Gille
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
also physiological value, social value, scientific value and
enjoyment value. Enjoyment value applies notably to
wild life and natural scenery.
Sir Edward Grey (1933) has written of the significance
of this resource in human life. In amplification of
Wordsworth, he writes "When feeling is raised to an
unusual height by contemplation of natural beauty, by
something that quickens while it soothes and calms, the
mental and moral perceptions may penetrate more deeply
into the life of things." Elsewhere he tells us how "the
watching of wild animals or birds gives yet another
pleasure, that of a sense of privilege" in witnessing many
things that are usually concealed from human eyes.
This is very true: but the witnessing of wild life on
the grand scale can give not only a sense of privilege
but of wonder and deep emotion. To see large animals
going about their natural business in their own natural
way, assured and unafraid, is one of the most exciting
and moving experiences in the world, comparable with
the sight of a noble building or the hearing of a great
symphony or mass. A processional frieze of antelopes
moving across the African horizon rivals any theatrical
spectacle.
The world at large cannot afford to let this great
human resource disappear.
Wild life in Africa as a resource may be summed up
in the phrase Profit, Protein, Pride and Prestige, with
enjoyment and scientific interest thrown in. It can yield
Profit from tourist revenue, sales of meat and trophies,
and Protein from game-cropping schemes; it can be a
source of local Pride and of international Prestige; while
its importance as a source of scientific knowledge is very
great.
The best way of realizing its exceptional enjoyment
value is by means of National Parks. These are areas
established by Statute (and therefore only to be abolished
or altered by special legislation), designed to conserve
wild life and natural beauty for the enjoyment of the
public as well as for scientific reasons. Game and Nature
Reserves can also be useful, but they do not have the same
guarantee of permanence; and so can local parks and
sanctuaries, but they do not enjoy the same prestige and
international status (2).
All countries have resources or achievements of which
they are proud, .and which visitors from other countries
come to see. Eastern Africa is fortunate in being endowed
by nature with the unique resource of its wild life. All
it has to do to turn it into a source of prestige and profit
is to preserve it whole-heartedly and manage it efficiently.
This could be an important element in the develop¬
ment of its under-developed territories, and international
finance could properly and hopefully be sought for any
projects with such an aim.
In our region (and to a somewhat lesser extent in the
Union) National Parks are the main basis of the tourist
trade. This is already very valuable, but could un¬
doubtedly be increased five or even tenfold provided that
the territories develop peacefully.
Public opinion in Africa can play a vital part in the
present situation in which one of the numerous urgencies
is. the need to educate and rouse local opinion in favour
of conserving the heritage of wild life and to persuade
Africans of the international importance of their National
Parks. The rousing of world opinion is equally important.
The world is one: but it is also various. Africa's wild
life belongs not merely to the local inhabitants but to
the world, not only to the present but to the whole future
of mankind. It is unique among the world's riches.
To let it die or be destroyed would be to allow a pre¬
cious element in that rich variety to be submerged for
ever in the drab monotonous flood of uniformity that is
threatening to engulf our mass-produced technological
civilization. Unesco has roused world opinion to save
the threatened monuments of Nubia: it should take on
the responsibility of rousing world opinion for the equally
worthy task of saving .the threatened wild life of Africa.
(2) National Parks are now a matter of official international concern.
The U.N. Social and Economic Council has asked all Member States
to submit descriptions of all their National Parks and equivalent
reserves, in order that an official U.N. list, may be prepared and
kept always up to date. In this, the U. N. Economic and Social
Council is being assisted by the International Union for the Protection
of Nature and Natural Resources and Unesco.
National Parks Board. Republic of South Africa
THERE HAS BEEN a remarkable change in South Africa's attitude toward wild life. In the
early days, almost every farmer killed wild game such as these Gemsbok antelope. Practically
exterminated, they are now protected on Park Reserves and farmers breed and crop them
scientifically for meat and hides. In the Transvaal alone, 2,000 farms now stock wild game.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
OPERATION NOAH
Construction of the Kariba Dam on the
mighty Zambezi river in the Rhodesias
threatened to drown the wild
life of the proposed lake area. To save
the animals "Operation Noah" was
launched in 1959 with the joint effort
of Africans and Europeans. Left, an
African game warden with a little dui¬
ker he has just rescued. Below, a lion,
oblivious of the traffic, nonchalant¬
ly crosses a road in the Kruger Nation¬
al Park, Republic of South Africa.
Sir Julian Huxley
W.F. Schack, National Board, Pretoria
14
. . ...
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
WILD LIFE AS A WORLD ASSET
On this and the following page we present excerpts culled from the
forthcoming Unesco book on East African wild life by Sir Julian Huxley
T HE European in Africa often starts not
unnaturally from the assumption that
African soils and African habitats can
stand up to the same kind of treatment that
has led to successful agriculture and stock-
raising in his homeland. The error of such
assumptions was disastrously illustrated by the
failure of the notorious groundnut scheme in
Tanganyika. Similar assumptions hare led to
the temporary or permanent ruination of
large habitats elsewhere in many drier parts
of South Africa, in the shortgrass prairies of
North America, in the once-fertile lands
of North Africa, in the Western Highlands of
Scotland.
11 UCH the same is true of the tropical rain-
forest. The European sees the astonishing
bulk of vegetation growing in it, and
jumps to the conclusion that the forest soils
must be very rich. This, however, is unfounded.
The trees are rooted in something more like a
sponge than what we think of as good soil.
When its vegetation cover is removed, and it is
put under cultivation, it rapidly deteriorates;
and the process is virtually irreversible.
N South Africa there has been a remarkable
change in the attitude to wild life. In the
early days, almost every farmer, Boer or
Briton, habitually killed wild game for meat
and hides, or less usually for sport. Now that
almost all large wild animals have been exter¬
minated in the farming areas, the process is
being reversed. Various National Parks autho¬
rities, provincial governments and even muni¬
cipalities are managing Nature Reserves partly
as game-farms, to build up stocks of game.
Some of the stock may be converted into meat
for the local market, but most of it (which
includes Bles-bok, Springbok, Impala and
Zebra) is sold to farmers and transported "on
the hoof" to the farms, sometimes up to
1,000 miles distant. The wild species breed
on the farms, and the surplus animals are
cropped for their meat and hides. The value
of the products from the wild animals may
equal that obtained from the domestic stock,
and in any case constitutes an important
addition to the farmer's livelihood. This me¬
thod of utilizing the productivity of wild ani¬
mals is now being practised on a large and
increasing scale.
Qi/e/ea quelea provides an example of human
interference with the habitat resulting in
an indigenous species becoming a pest.
This species of colonial-nesting Weaverbird is
widespread and abundant in inter-tropical
Africa. It originally fed on the seeds of wild
grasses; but wherever extensive cultivation has
taken place, and especially where monoculture
of crops like millet and rice is practised, it has
multiplied excessively and is now often a serious
pest. One colony near Birchenough Bridge in
Southern Rhodesia is estimated to contain
11 million individuals. This exceeds even
Tokyo and New York, and must be the largest
single community of any higher animal in
existence. Shooting, poison, even flame¬
throwers, are being employed against Queleas,
but no satisfactory method of control has yet
been discovered.
11 OST tribal Africans regard wild animals
either as a pest to be destroyed or simply
as meat on the hoof to be killed and
eaten. This latter point of view is semantically
fostered by the fact that in Swahili, as in
several other African languages, the same word
Uyama in Swahili does duty both for wild
animals and meat; and it is physiologically
encouraged by the shortage of animal protein
in the area and the prevalent meat-hunger of
its African inhabitants.
A"\ NCE local Africans understand that orga-
^^ nized game-cropping can provide them
with more and probably cheaper meat
than organized poaching, and that illicit indi¬
vidual shooting is killing the goose that lays
the golden eggs, they will begin to see wild life,
and all the measures designed to conserve it,
in a very different light.
I N some areas, wild game is not merely shot to
provide meat, but hunted by Africans as a
sport. This is natural enough and experience
in many lands (e.g. with fowlers in Great Britain
and deer-hunters in the U.S.A.) show that,
with goodwill and understanding, widespread
hunting and shooting can be enjoyed without
detriment to wild life, indeed with advantage
to it, when reserves are established for the
express purpose of conserving the numbers of
game animals and birds for the hunter.
p DUCATED and politically-minded Africans
tend to have rather different attitudes.
Some of them regard National Parks and
Controlled Shooting Areas as relics of white
"colonialism'", or merely as places for white men
to indulge their peculiar habit of enjoying the
sight or the pursuit of wild animals; and accor¬
dingly to be abolished or at any rate not encou¬
raged. Others retort in ways like, this: "You
white men have killed all your wolves and
bears: why do you want us Africans to preserve
our lions and elephants?" This type of argu¬
ment often accompanies a more deep-seated
attitude the feeling that emergent Africa must
at all costs become "modern", and that large
wild animals in a country are the reverse of
modern, and indeed o badge of primitmsm.
\A/ ILD life is today a Cinderella: the gloo-
' * ~ mier prophets wonder if Cinderella may
not come to be regarded as an unne¬
cessary nuisance, and simply liquidated.
n ESPONSIBLE African opinion is becoming
' ^* aware of the political and prestige value
of wild life. In the modern world, as
Africa is beginning to realize, a country without
a National Park can hardly be regarded as
civilized. And for an African territory to abo¬
lish National Parks already set up or to destroy
its existing wild life resource would shock the
world and incur the reproach of barbarism and
ignorance.
I N the past, the cause of wild life conservation
' has been fighting, and usually losing, a
series of rearguard actions against economic
and social pressures and general human
thoughtlessness and blindness. It is certainly
encouraging to see it stepping into the centre
of the political stage in Africa and demanding
attention. But conservation must become a
central feature of policy. The emergent Afri¬
can nations must come to learn the harsh lesson
that without proper conservation of soil and
water and natural vegetation their lands vrili
become unprofitable and useless, and also the
hopeful lesson of the positive values of their
natural resources, including wild life and natural
beauty.
T HE first thing needed is to make Africans
' at all levels aware of the wild life that
they possess. The interest is there, only
waiting to be aroused. In Uganda, visits of
students and townsmen and chiefs to the Na¬
tional Parks have been organized by the autho¬
rities, with encouraging results. Most of them ,3
have never seen any large wild animals and
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
WILD LIFE AS A WORLD ASSET (Cont'd)
AFRICANS CAN BE PROUD OF THEIR HERITAGE
they are deeply interested and excited when
they do so. "These are our wonder animals
our elephants, our lions, our zebra, our ante¬
lopes. We must protect them and help other
Africans to enjoy the sight of them" that, I
was told, is the usual type of reaction.
I N Britain, a Conservation Corps of young
' volunteers has been organized under the aegis
of the Council for Nature. Its members take
part in schemes for improving Nature Reserves
and similar areas. If something of the sort
could be organized to harness the enthusiasm
of young Africans, it could be of great ser¬
vice. Such schemes could be affiliated to the
International Youth Federation for Nature
Conservation.
T HE African Crocodile is a freshwater verte-
' brate of considerable economic importance.
Long regarded only as a pest, its skin has
recently provided the basis for a valuable trade.
However, unregulated and illegal shooting has
virtually exterminated the species in some
areas, and seriously reduced its numbers and
its size in many others. The African crocodile
is clearly a valuable natural resource deserving
of scientific management, whose cropping must
be carefully regulated.
N 1934 C.R.S. Pitman estimated the total
Lechwe Antelope population of the Kafue
River Flats at a quarter of a million: today it
is less than 30,000. Their numbers could
readily be raised to at least 100,000 by proper
management; 20,000 Lechwe a year could prob¬
ably be safely cropped, and would yield
2,000 tons of meat or more.
T HE Lechwe Antelope is easily hunted and
' killed by African spearmen and their dogs.
In comparatively recent years, the local
Africans organized large-scale hunts or chilas,
described as "Lechwe blood-baths" in which
men, women and dogs drove large herds into
the water and speared thousands at a time.
The large majority of those killed were females,
most of them gravid. This cruel slaughter was
also wasteful, as it rapidly reduced the total
Lechwe population. If it were replaced by a
carefully organized cropping system, selected
local tribesmen could presumably still partici¬
pate in the operation.
I T will be difficult to get Africans to abandon
their traditional practices, even when these
are flagrantly inimical to good land use and
*e their own prosperity, but it can be done. Some¬
thing has already been accomplished in per¬
suading pastoralists to limit their stocks and
sell their surplus beasts; and the new agricul¬
tural revolution in the Kenya Highlands, which
has produced an array of prosperous individ¬
ually-owned African farms and smallholdings,
has been an outstanding success. It has also
had the rather unexpected result of alerting
this new class of African farm-owners to
the dangers of over-population. However, in
Africa as elsewhere, men must be brought to
have respect for land theirs and their coun¬
try's; and the importance of right land use for
the prosperity and indeed the economic and
social viability of African territories must be
urgently impressed on public opinion, both Euro¬
pean and African.
I N Uganda, there are now about 5,000 visitors
' to the National Parks each year, and it has
been estimated that they bring in a revenue
of about £300,000 gross from expenditure on
Park fees, transport, and curios (to which I
would add a considerable sum for expenditure
on photographic, camping and other equip¬
ment).
I N Kenya, tourism already provides the second
* largest source of revenue some £8 million
a year. Not only does Kenya possess its
own famous National Parks and Reserves but
it has always been the headquarters of East
African tourism in general, and Nairobi the
main centre where the tourist outfits himself
for game-viewing and other tours, in Ken
itself and also in Uganda and Tanganyika.
Q OME people dislike the idea of making a
** profit out of rich men's desire to kill ani¬
mals for sport. However, in East Africa
as in almost all African territories, there are
strict bag limits, and most of those who go on
safari to shoot are sportsmen who, though they
enjoy the excitement of hunting big game in
wild surroundings, are genuinely anxious to
conserve it. Furthermore, an increasing number
go on safari in order to take photographs and
to embark on adventure in the African bush,
far from crowds and civilization.
HE shooting of a limited number of wild
' animals for sport is essentially another
form of game-cropping, and equally legiti¬
mate as a mean of utilizing and conserving
the country's wild habitats and wild life
resources. However, safaris should always be
subsidiary to National Parks in a territory's wild
life policy.
Il OUNTAINEERING is another pursuit which
'" could expand spectacularly in East Africa
during the rest of this century. As the
Alps and the Rockies become increasingly
crowded, we may expect that more and more
mountaineers will want to attack noble peaks
like Mount Kenya, Mount Mikesco and those of
the great Newenzori range. Kilimanjaro is not
a mountaineers' mountain, but its vast height
and portentous crater will always tempt
climbers; and volcanic peaks overtopping
13,000 feet, like Meru and Elgon, Karissimbi
and Muhavura, not to mention lower volcanoes
like Suswa, Longonot, and Oldongo Lengai, will
attract an increasing number of adventurous
mountain-walkers.
T HE Victoria Falls are one of the natural
wonders of the world, already enjoyed by
thousands of visitors. Beautiful lakes like
Bunyoni with its fringe of blue water-lilies in
the cool green uplands of western Uganda
could be made into excellent tourist centres.
Proper development of access and accommo¬
dation could bring in a greatly increased
number of visitors, not only to the foothill
regions of eastern Africa, but also to the lovely
cool uplands like those of Inyanga in eastern
Southern Rhodesia, of the Aberdares in Kenya,
or of the Nyika Plateau in Nyasaland.
T HE total revenue from tourism in the four
' territories of East Africa together is today
well over £10 million. I would prophesy
that this could certainly be increased fivefold,
and quite probably tenfold, within the present
decade. So long as western prosperity con¬
tinues, with Western populations (and their
revenues) increasing and Western industriali¬
zation being intensified, it is safe to forecast
that more and more people will want to escape
further and further from it and its concomi¬
tants, in. the shape of over-large or over¬
crowded cities, urban sprawl, noise, smog, boring
routine, deprivation of contact with nature, and
general over-mechanization of existence.
T HERE must be hundreds of thousands of
' people in the world who, though they may
not be able to travel to see African wild
life in nature, are yet deeply concerned over
its future, or whose concern could readily be
aroused. The Fauna Society's appeal for "Ope¬
ration Noah1" to save the wild life of Kariba
from destruction met with an immediate and
generous response. I believe that a well-
planned international appeal for a continuing
campaign to save the world's wild life from
destruction and to establish an array of Natio¬
nal Parks and other areas devoted to the pro¬
tection of nature as a kind of world-wide
Green Belt for our over-mechanized civilization
would meet with an equally immediate and
generous response.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
HEY TAXI! Once a formidable ex¬
pedition, a trip to Kenya's Nairobi
Royal National Park can now be
made in 20 minutes by taxi from
the capital. Covered with' open
plains and tree savannah, the park
is one of the most famous places
in Africa to see wild life. In 1958,
110,000 people visited the plains.
© Almasy, Paris
Í ./ *QF:
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
THOUSANDS OF ZEBRAS, Wildebeest (gnus) and Thomson
gazelles roam across the grassy plains of Tanganyika's great
Serengeti Park, one of the last refuges of the vanishing herds of
Africa. To count their numbers and chart their migrations the
Tanganyikan Government several years ago called upon Bernhard
Grzimek of Frankfurt and his son Michael. By zebra-striped light
18
^r
V
'm..
* *i*~ Ä.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Drama of Serengeti
TWO MEN & A FLYING ZEBRA
by Pauline Bentley
One of the most magnificent reserves of
wild life in Africa and probably in the world
is to be found in the Serengeti Park and the
Ngorongoro Highlands of northern Tan¬
ganyika. Here in a setting almost untouched
by man, of limitless horizons, beauty and
grandeur, dwell remarkable species of ani¬
mals and birds which have drawn to this
unrivalled corner of East Africa nature
lovers, tourists, hunters and photographers.
The article below tells the story of the
animals census undertaken a few years ago.
On page 23, Sir Julian Huxley gives afrank
account of today's drama in Serengeti Park.
plane and Land Rover they spent months counting and tracking
the herds of zebra (above) and wildebeest (below) which,
although greatly reduced in numbers, still abound in Serengeti.
i TQE' t
T AKE two men, enough scientific knowledge, a
tiny aeroplane and limitless dedication, and
the result is one of the most moving adventure stories in
the struggle for the preservation of wild life. The story
starts in 1957, when Dr. Bernhard Grzimek, Director of the
Frankfurt Zoo, was asked with his son Michael to make
a census of the huge herds in Serengeti National Park.
Serengeti is Tanganyika's only National Park, 4,500
square miles shaped rather like a kneeling elephant with
its trunk extended, and stretching from Lake Victoria to
just beyond the mighty Ngorongoro crater. It is the home
of presumably the last great herds of wild animals still
surviving in Africa, where zebra, wildebeest and Thomson's
and Grant's gazelles as well as elephants, lions, flamingoes
and ostriches roam freely.
The reason for the census was a British Government
plan to reduce the size of the Park in favour of the many
Masai tribesmen; this plan had been based on an official
survey made in 1957, but the information on the seasonal
migrations of the large plains animals in this study was
sketchy and inaccurate. Dr. Grzimek realized the impor¬
tance of accurate information not only to the destiny of
the Park but to its unique herds themselves. He de¬
termined to establish .the number of animals in the Park
as well as whether the herds were actually protected by
the present Park boundaries and would continue to be so
by the proposed new boundaries.
His work had often taken him to Serengeti before, and
both he and his son Michael were passionately interested
in its fate. They accepted the task joyfully. It took
them endless patience, courage, ingenuity and sacrifice
which did not stop short of life itself, for in 1959 Michael
Grzimek was killed at the age of 25 while flying on the
Serengeti assignment. As a memorial to him we can
enjoy his father's book, Serengeti Shall Not Die (1) describ¬
ing their two years' work in Tanganyika, and Michael
Grzimek's own film of the same name which he completed
just before his death and which was awarded the 1960
"Oscar" for the best documentary of the year by the
American Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Science.
Taking into account the vast area they had to cover,
and, the fact that the number of animals in the Park
was estimated to be about a million, the Grzimeks realized
that a comprehensive survey could not be attempted by
car. They therefore decided to carry out their census
from the air ; they learned to fly. In a little single-engined
19
(1) Published by Hamish Hamilton, London, 1960, and Dutton, New
York, 1961.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
'Jfc.
i
9 *
V
BELLING THE ZEBRA. It takes energy and
ingenuity to strap a collar on a zebra, for these
fleet-footed and timid animals just won't stand still
even in their own interest. To discover what
migratory patterns the herds followed in Serengeti
Park, the Grzimeks decided to mark certain zebras
so that they could be spotted later from the air.
They tried catching them by the tail (above) but
the razor sharp hairs proved too dangerous. Later,
they mounted a platform on top of their Land Rover
and lassoed them from above with a noose at forty
miles an hour. Once caught, four men were needed
to slip a brightly coloured featherweight collar
around the animal's neck (above right and below).
Very quickly the zebra was freed to rejoin the herd
(far right). Once collared, the zebras can eas¬
ily be spotted from a plane flying at 1,500 feet.
Photos Dr. Bernhard Grzimek © Tierbilder Okapia, Munich
20
Dornier 27 painted in bright black and white zebra stripes
so that it should be easily spotted in case of emergency
landings, they set off in December 1957 on the 6,000 mile
flight to Equatorial Africa.
The little plane, specially highlegged from the ground
as protection against long grass, had excellent visibility
from its cockpit, it was able to fly at very low speeds close
to the ground and it could operate easily independently
of airstrips and landing fields.
The Grzimeks' first intention was to fly over the whole
Park and photograph it with automatic cameras, but this
idea proved impractical and prohibitively expensive;
instead they decided to divide the area into zones
demarcated by natural landmarks and fly at 150-300 feet
over each zone in parallel sweeps, counting the animals
on each side of the plane in 550 yard wide strips at a
time.
This idea worked well in practice, but it turned out
to be exhausting and earsplitting work; the plane had
no insulation against the noise . of its own engine and it
was some time before the Grzimeks became accustomed
to it; counting herds of often moving animals from a hot
and noisy plane takes some concentration, but before very
long Dr. Grzimek evolved a method of counting the larger
herds in groups of 12 to 50 at a time.
They were shocked to discover that the estimated num¬
ber of one million quadruped was far in excess of that
actually in the Park. Through poaching by Africans and
the hazards of wandering into unprotected areas, Seren-
geti's great herds now numbered approximatively 367,000
..less than one-half of the original estimate. It became
of even greater importance to discover the areas into
which they were wandering, and to ensure that these
areas should be protected, if their numbers were not to
be reduced even further.
It became obvious that the herds must in some way be
identified if their movements were to be traced and the
present and proposed Park boundaries to be studied.
The Grzimeks had already had to consider the extraordi¬
narily varying reactions of the different animals, zebra,
gazelles, wart-hog, elephant and lion, gnu, ostrich and
giraffe, to the sound of their low-flying plane while taking
the census, now they had to come down from the skies
and catch their animals to mark them !
As a veterinarian, Dr. Grzimek rejected various ideas,
such as narcotics put in the water holes used by the
herds, but he finally accepted the idea of a new "miracle
gun" a weapon looking like an ordinary gun but which
instead of bullets fires a steel hypodermic with a narcotic
that temporarily and harmlessly renders its victim docile.
They found the gun far from perfect and Michael Grzi¬
mek eventually modified It on a trip back to Germany and
they finally selected nicotine salicylate as the most suit¬
able drug to use.
Armed with this improved weapon they returned to
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
mm mm K ¥mw.<. '
Serengeti, still faced with the problem of catching and
marking their animals. The average speed on the ground
of the larger Serengeti herds of zebra, Thomson's and
Grant's gazelles and gnu is a high thirty miles an hour.
Temporarily abandoning the faithful plane, the Grzimeks
took to a Land Rover, an all-terrains vehicle also painted
in zebra stripes. Only the zebras would never allow them
near enough to "shoot" them with the miracle gun and
they therefore had to be caught by hand or rather, by
the tail. This proved a highly tricky and painful opera¬
tion, for the hairs of the tail are razor sharp. Later the
Grzimeks discovered the Thomson's and Grant's gazelles
could be caught in the dazzle of the Land Rover head¬
lamps provided there was moonlight. They spent many
extremely active nights doing this and marking the gentle
and elegant gazelles, without having to drug them first.
The usual methods of marking animals are by earclip
or dye, but the first would be invisible from the air and
the dye brought from Europe did not take on the zebra's
rough hide. Finally, the Grzimeks decided on a brightly
coloured light plastic collar which not only remained
distinguishable from the air but proved to have no
adverse effect on other animals in the herd.
From the air they were thus able to identify particular
herds and then study their movements; the results were
disquieting. They found that every year the large herds
move far beyond the new borders proposed for the Seren¬
geti Park. This means that the already shrinking herds
will be exposed to further dangers if the new boundaries
become law.
Michael Grzimek made Innumerable trips to different
parts of Serengeti, taking samples of soil and grasses
which were sent to Europe for analysis in an attempt to
find out why the herds wandered as they did. It was
found from this that their preferred grazing grows largely
outside the future Park boundaries in the rainy season
and that what grows within the future Serengeti is not
eaten by the animals during some parts of the year. In
other words, the conclusion was that the herds need the
area destined to be shorn from Serengeti. Dr. Grzimek
also noted that the land in the park which is adequate
for wild animals would be Inadequate for the large herds
of Masai cattle to whom it is suggested it should be given.
Dr. Grzimek's conclusion is that the new boundaries pro¬
posed for Serengeti spell certain death for large parts of
the great wild herds.
As he has written "Neither today, nor tomorrow, but
in three or four generations' time, many people may be
glad that during our era someone gave a thought to the
wild animals in Africa... Most national and political am¬
bitions for which men suffer and die are transient, bub
Nature is of abiding importance to us all. In a hundred
years' time... men will still consider it important that 21
wildebeest should roam across the plains and leopards
growl at night."
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
-
Photos Dr B. Grzimek © Tierbilder Okapia, Frankfort
BABY THOMSON GAZELLE (left) allows itself to be
caressed by Michael Grzimek at Serengeti shortly after
its ear has been tagged for identification. Within minutes
it will be on its feet, and a danger, despite its age, to
anyone who gets in the way of its needle-pointed horns.
Michael was killed not long after this picture was taken,
when his plane crashed near Ngorongoro Crater.
Michael's father (above) gives orphaned baby rhinoceros
a refreshing drink. Giraffes, like these below bounding
across the veld, proved to be among the least discon¬
certed of all animals by the low-flying plane. Census
count numbered 837 of them in Serengeti. Gazelles
were most numerous, and then wildebeest and zebras.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
THE DRAMA OF SERENGETI
Natures fight for life
at Ngorongoro Crater
by Sir Julian Huxley
At the time of my visit to Africa in 1931 there
were no National Parks either In East Africa
or the Federation of the Rhodesias and Nyasaland, and I
urged the need for their speedy establishment. Great
progress has been made in the subsequent three decades,
and today there are in the region some 15 devoted primar¬
ily to the conservation of wild life or wild scenery, besides
a number of Reserves with essentially the same function
but not officially designated as National Parks, as well
as some Parks of archaeological or historical interest.
But this has been a slow operation, often carried out
in the face of official Inertia or even resistance, always
handicapped by inadequate funds and personnel, and
without benefit of any consistent and positive policy.
As a result of these handicaps and of the common
tendency of administrations to underestimate the impor¬
tance of wild life and its value as a resource, to give
priority to agricultural and other "human" development
schemes as opposed to projects for wild life conservation,
and generally to favour the interests of tribal Africans
whenever they appear to conflict with those of wild life
conservation, many opportunities have been missed; exist¬
ing National Parks systems. have generally had to struggle
along at a low level of efficiency, and have been unable
to perform their functions fully; poaching has made
many wild animals shy; a number of wild habitats,
including even some in Parks or Reserves, have been
invaded, damaged or lost; and there is as yet little or
no sign of the framing of challenging plans for the
; future of National Parks in the region.
The Serengeti may be cited as an example of the
unfortunate treatment which an ideal National Park
area received in actual reality.
In the mid-twentieth century the Serengeti area of
Tanganyika, with the continuous Crater Highlands,
retained an abundance and variety of large wild animals
unrivalled elsewhere in Africa or indeed in the world.
The annual migration of the large herbivores, compris¬
ing hundreds of thousands of wildebeest, zebra, and gaz¬
elle, were inconceivably spectacular, and so, though in
a different way, was Ngorongoro, the second largest crater
on earth, 11 miles in diameter, with its vast floor liberally
sprinkled with antelopes, zebras, elephants and rhinos,
together with fair numbers of lions, hyenas and other car¬
nivores. I made the mental calculation that the wilde¬
beests stood in the same size-relation to the crater floor
as would fleas to the flank of a blue whale.
Other habitats in the original Serengeti area
ranged from hot and semi-arid level plains to
forested volcanic highlands, and its mammalian fauna
included no less than 170 species, comprising almost all the
most striking large forms, from giraffes and buffaloes to
lions and cheetahs. The present populations of Wilde¬
beest, Zebra, Grant's and Thomson's Gazelle are estimated
at about 100,000, 60,000, 40,000 and 200,000 respectively,
besides some 15,000 other large herbivores and 1,500
ostriches.
Two further points must be mentioned. First that
the Masai had traditional rights over the area (though
into much of It they did not penetrate owing to its infest¬
ation with tsetse or to lack of water for their stock) :
and secondly that ever since Tanganyika became a Brit¬
ish Mandated Territory, the Administration has tended
to regard the interests of wild life as subordinate to those
of local Africans.
A Serengeti National Park was nominally established
in 1940, but a National Parks Ordinance was not passed
until 1948, and the Park was not formally proclaimed
until 1951. During 1953-56 a number of reports showed
that the Park and its marvellous fauna were being
gravely threatened, partly by poaching, but largely by the
rapidly increasing Masai.
In 1956 a Government Sessional Paper set forth the
Government's policy for the area. This would so clearly
and drastically have impaired the value of the Park, that
it raised an international storm. The Fauna Preserva¬
tion Society in Britain commissioned the eminent ecologist
Professor W.H. Pearsall to examine the problem, and his
report, together with much other scientific and expert
evidence, was presented to the Committee of Enquiry
which the Government was impelled to set up. .
In 1957, the Committee recommended that the plains
area in the West, supplemented by an uninhabited north¬
ward extension to the Mara River and the Kenya border,
should remain as a true National Park, that the Ngo¬
rongoro Crater should become a Nature Sanctuary (vir¬
tually a small National Park) ; and that the rest of the
area, including the Crater Highlands, as recommended
in principle by Professor Pearsall, should become some¬
thing new in Africa a "Conservation Area," devoted
primarily to conserving the water-supplies, the forests,
the grazing potential (and therefore the wild life) of
the whole Serengeti region.
In 1958 a Government White Paper stated that
the conclusions of the Committee were
"broadly acceptable," and proposed a solution which, it
said, was to be "simple, clear and final." In point of fact,
the solution was not at all simple; it has not (as might
have been foreseen) proved final; and several of the
Committee's recommendations far from proving "accept¬
able," were rejected.
Prior to 1958, the National Parks Trustees had spent
over £150,000 on the provision of a fine lodge and
numerous other facilities for visitors to the world-famous
crater of Ngorongoro. In spite of this, and of the
Committee's recommendation, Ngorongoro was not pro¬
claimed as a Nature Sanctuary, but simply included in
the Conservation Area. The whole eastern sector of the
proposed Serengeti National Park was also added to the
Conservation Area, and this was to be administered
primarily in the interests of its human inhabitants, the
Masai, and not primarily to conserve the resources of
the entire region.
At the time of my visit, the Masai were bringing large
herds of stock to graze in the crater, and were in
contravention of the regulations invading and damaging
the forests on the crater rim, lighting fires and even
setting up bomas there. They were also killing numerous
rhinos (over 30 during the last 12 months), always
allegedly in self-defence, but pretty certainly with a view
to selling the horns. The Warusha were also attempting
to start cultivation in parts of the forest area.
Since then, new studies have made it clear that the
new boundaries of the National Park ought not to be
regarded as final, but should be redrawn, after a renewed
ecological survey of the area, including study of the
animals' habits as well as a land use survey, to guarantee
safe migration and good grazing to the enormous herds
of game that annually flood back and forth across the
Serengeti region.
Meanwhile, in 1959, the Colonial Development . and
Welfare Fund allocated £182,000 to the Conservation
Authority to be spent over 4 years for the following pur¬
poses: rehabilitation of eroded lands and prevention of 23
further erosion; increase of stock-carrying capacity; forest
conservation; and wild life conservation as far as
CONT'D ON PAGE 34
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
THE CANADIAN CARIBOU
A DISAPPEARING SPECIES
by A.W.F. Banfield
Chief Zoologist, National Museum of Canada,
Dept. of Northern Affairs & National Resources
Arelict species from the Ice Age is waging
what may be a losing battle for survival
against the relentless advance of modern civilization.
That species is the barren-ground caribou (Rangifer ta-
randus arcticus) of northern Canada which is closely
related to the reindeer (Rangifer tarandus) of northern
Europe and Asia. It Is a mammal particularly well adapted
to withstand the rigours of an arctic environment with its
long, dense fur, short ears and tail, furred muzzle and
feet, and widely splayed hooves. The latter act as
snowshoes to bear the animal's weight on the crusted
snow In winter.
The time and place of origin of the world's reindeer is
quite naturally unknown. However, the geological and
anatomical evidence points to the mountainous regions
of north-western America or north-eastern Asia. We do
know that the reindeer was a characteristic mammal of
the colder phases of the Last Glaciation associated with
a tundra and taiga vegetation on the edges of the advanc¬
ing or retreating continental glaciations (about 75,000-
10,000 years ago.) Its companions were the woolly
mammoth and musk-ox on the subarctic landscape, of
western Europe. During intervening warmer phases when
deciduous forests and meadows covered the land, the
reindeer was replaced by aurochs (ancestral cattle), bison,
horses and red deer.
The reindeer was closely associated with man during
the Early Stone Age of Europe and northern Asia. Early
Europeans have left a clear record of the reindeer, bison
and woolly mammoth in the powerfully simple cave
drawings of the Dordogne Valley of France and Altamira
Cave of Spain. Those drawings Indicate an intimate
knowledge of the reindeer's life history born from their
pursuit for the staples of human life. The drawings,
models, tools and fragments from those early cultures
indicate that reindeer provided food, clothes, fuel, thread
and tools for our species so long ago.
At the time that reindeer were so important in the
economy of Europe, the ancestors of the American barren-
ground caribou were thought to have been penned-up in
an unglaciated refugium in Alaska and the Yukon
Territory. The gradual eastward retreat of the Keewatin
Ice Cap during the past 10,000 years permitted, the caribou
to colonize the tundra of northern Canada. It is likely
that the early Eskimos were quick to follow the caribou
and to migrate eastward across northern Canada
eventually to reach Greenland.
While the reindeer gradually withdrew northward and
disappeared from the economic picture of Europe, the
barren-ground caribou continued to serve as the
cornerstone of the comparatively Stone Age cultures of
the Eskimos and Athabascan Indians until recent times.
The Chipewayan Indians of the Athabascan language
group, who live in the boreal forest region were practically
dependent upon caribou for the basic necessities of food,
clothing, fuel oil for lamps, sinews for sewing and tools.
They earned the name "caribou-eaters."
Modern Eskimos were less dependent upon caribou and
more upon marine mammals such as seals, walrus and
smaller whales. However, caribou were always cherished
game of the chase for winter clothing. The summer
caribou hunt held certain connotations -of recreation or
spiritual renewal. However even among . .the Eskimos,
bands remained inland and were primarily dependent
upon caribou.
These races relied upon a primitive hunting culture for
their sustenance. They speared the migrating caribou
24 from canoes and kayaks. They captured them in pounds
constructed of spruce trees, or guided them to slaughter¬
ing points at natural defiles by the construction of long
M tmrn
A SNOW-DEEP
PROCESSION
of Canada's barren-
ground caribou
forms striking sil¬
houette against
mountain backdrop.
Photo National Museum
of Canada, Ottawa
drift fences (or stone columns on the treeless tundra).
They sometimes stalked them with bow and arrow, the
hunters 'disguised in caribou hides and antlers, or
constructed pitfalls on caribou paths in the forests or of
frozen snow blocks in winter.
Such hunting methods were probably similar to those
used by our Stone Age ancestors and could be observed
in northern Canada until quite recently. The domestica¬
tion of the reindeer developed in north-eastern Asia about
3,000 years ago and was brought to northern Europe by
the Lapps. However the Eskimos and Indians of North
America never developed a similar form of animal
husbandry .with their caribou.
One can well imagine the sights of natural bounty
which greeted the first European explorers to northern
Canada in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries.
Great herds of caribou roamed the arctic tundra in
summer in seemingly countless numbers. In winter they
migrated in massed columns, distances up to 1,000 kms.
to the subarctic taiga. While nomadic bands of Eskimos
and Indians followed the caribou herds across the forests
and tundra for their livelihood.
It is difficult to remember now in highly organized Ca¬
nada, that a century ago, vast herds of bison and caribou
roamed across plain and tundra, rivalling in number
the teeming antelope of the African veldt. The bison
virtually disappeared from the plains as a result of
excessive hunting in the nineteenth century. Saved from
extinction it survives in National Park sanctuaries. Its
place in the ecological scheme of things has been taken
by beef cattle. The caribou still lingers on in its arctic do¬
main in numbers only suggestive of its former abundance.
The advent of Europeans upset the centuries-old
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
_
3M
' \. .,
^tok
*t¿fc^ '« %>w >\ >*.
balance which had existed between caribou herds and
their human predators. For the primitive weapons of
the Eskimos and Indians scarcely gave them any advan¬
tage over their swift wide-ranging prey. The introduction
of the fur-trade to northern areas indirectly tipped the
balance against the caribou. The natives became trappers
and for the new pursuit increased their dog teams for
winter travel. This led to larger caches of caribou meat
to feed both the trappers and the dogs on the trail.
With these changes were introduced the tools ne¬
cessary to facilitate the killing of caribou the white
man's firearms. For the first time the Indian and Eskimo
found themselves able to kill at will. The ease with which
the unwary caribou could be killled by the rifle led to great
wastage of the resource. The seemingly numberless
caribou herds began to melt away, while the northern
people seemed unable to adopt the conservation concept.
The remoteness of the caribou range, together with the
sparse and primitive human population, hindered a really
accurate appraisal of the animal's population. Exaggerat¬
ed estimates ran as high as 100 million. The famous
Canadian naturalist Ernest Thompson Seton estimated the
caribou numbers at 30 million in 1911. As late as 1938,
the population was estimated at 2 1/2 million.
With the increased post-war tempo of development in
Canada's northern regions fears grew for the fate of this
important natural resource. Federal and provincial game
authorities recognized the urgent need for an intensive
investigation and undertook a co-operative preliminary
survey in 1948 and 1949.
Previous attempts at estimating the caribou population
had been handicapped because of the slowness of the
traditional northern transportation methods of dog team
and canoe. Now full advantage was taken of the aeroplane
and an aerial survey technique was developed for nor¬
thern big-game animals. During the spring migrations
caribou herds travel in closely packed columns. They
tend to follow the frozen waterways and on sunny after¬
noons rest on the snow covered lakes. At that time they
are easily photographed and counted from the air.
The preliminary aerial survey of 1948 and 1949 dis¬
closed an estimated population of about 670,000 barren-
ground caribou between Hudson Bay and the Mackenzie
River. The annual crop of calves was estimated at 145,000.
The number killed every year by hunters, based upon
hunting returns, was about 100,000. -Wolf prédation,
diseases, accidents and severe spring blizzards at calving
time caused losses that appeared to exceed the annual
increment and to result in a declining population. A con¬
tinuing caribou research programme disclosed a series of
poor calf crops during succeeding years and a similar
aerial resurvey in the winter of 1955-1956 indicated an
alarming drop in the population to an estimated 275,000.
This crisis led to a second co-operative caribou research
programme jointly sponsored by Federal Government agen¬
cies: Canadian Wildlife Service and Northern Adminis¬
tration Branch of the Department of Northern Affairs and
National Resources, the Indian Affairs Branch and the
Game Departments of the Provinces of Manitoba, Saskat¬
chewan and Alberta. Whereas the first project had been
extensive in nature, the second was an Intensive study
of all the factors affecting caribou mortality.
One large herd numbering approximately 100,000 ani¬
mals was chosen for intensive study from April 1, 1957 to
August 31, 1958. During that period teams of game bio¬
logists, range managers, veterinarians, physiologists and
ethologists kept constant contact with the herd as it
migrated approximately 2,000 km. between summer and
25
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
CANADIAN CARIBOU (Cont'd)
STRYCHNINE TRAPS
FOR MARAUDING WOLVES
winter ranges. The biologists lived in tent camps under
Canadian subarctic weather conditions. The scientists
leap-frogged after the migrating herds by means of light
aircraft. This was certainly the most intensive research
programme on any Canadian mammal yet undertaken
and significant contributions to our understanding of the
caribou decline were achieved.
The human kill was verified as the most important fac¬
tor in the caribou decline. Although the kill declined to
73,400 in 1955 and to 15,000 in 1957-58, those figures repre¬
sent the decreasing availability of caribou rather than
the effectiveness of conservation methods. The high rate
of human utilization was unfortunately coupled with a
series of years with low calf crops so that 1956-57 the calf
crop was about 8.1 per cent of the herd and the human
kill 9 per cent, resulting in a further decline.
Steps have been taken to restrict the killing of caribou
in northern Canada to those families living in the remote
areas. At the same time a conservation programme has
been initiated in the schools and among adults by means
of posters, cartoon booklets and fllmstrips. Additional
sources of meat have been sought to relieve the drain on
caribou. In this connexion, bison, whale and walrus
hunts have been organized where the stocks were suffi¬
cient. Frozen food lockers and natural storage facilities
in the permafrost have been developed where practical.
Unfortunately conservation programmes are woefully slow
and the caribou population has continued to decline. to
about 200,000 animals by 1960, in spite of two unusually
favourable calf crops in 1958 and 1959.
It was not difficult to convince northern resi¬
dents of the need for increased wolf control.
Bounties had not been paid on wolves in the North-West
Territories for many years, and the decline in fur prices
in recent years has discouraged wolf-trappers.
For that reason an intensive co-operative wolf control
programme was organized over the barren-ground caribou
winter range. Advantage was taken of the wolf packs'
habit of travelling on the broad frozen lakes. Lesser fur-
bearers seldom ventured so far from shore. Strychnine
baits were placed at sites carefully marked to protect
trappers and their dog teams. The sites were revisited
and biological information gathered. During the 1953-58
programme, over 6,500 wolf carcasses were tallied. The
wolf population was effectively reduced over much of the
caribou range.
Other corollary research programmes have clarified the
role of snow depth and texture in controlling caribou
movements in winter. It was found that caribou chose
areas of shallow, light snowfall. Crusting severely handi¬
capped the caribou's ground feeding habits. It was also
confirmed that severe wind chill caused by strong winds
at low temperatures could place a strain upon a new-born
calf's resistance.
Fortunately some pressure has been taken off the cari¬
bou by new economic developments in which Eskimos
may participate. Work in mining and military establish¬
ments, in government services and air transportation has
reduced the need for caribou as the main source of suste¬
nance. This change came at a fortuitous moment, for
the disappearance of the caribou herds resulted in star¬
vation in some remote Eskimo camps in Keewatin Dis¬
trict, and caused grave hardship over a much larger area
of northern Canada.
Some say that northern development has doomed the
caribou in any case to a subordinate role. But the stunted
subarctic forests and tundra pastures underlaid .by perma¬
frost are of little use for modern agriculture or forestry
practices. The native caribou is the animal best adapted
to utilize this environment and transform it to proteins
available for human consumption. The wide-ranging cari¬
bou lends itself to an open type of animal husbandry, and
26 if properly managed could continue to provide bounty
"on the hoof" to northern people remote from supplies
of domestic meats.
ismJffS^mÑ
BARREN-GROUND CARIBOU spend the summer in
the arctic tundra of Canada and the winter in the subarctic
taiga (above) some 800 miles south. Below, they are
seen crossing the frozen lakes of the taiga, where they
often rest on the ice. When migrating, they average
19 miles a day. Hunted by Indians and Eskimos as a
source of livelihood, they dwindled from 30 million at
the beginning of the century to a mere 200,000 in 1960.
Right, abandoned carcasses of slaughtered caribou.
National Museum of Canada, Ottawa
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
m^m^mm^^iM^^ s I~
i hi ,,.
J mjtMwtmww*
ÏSmkWfMMiïrMÏ?.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
WHERE TIME STOOD STILL
The Galapagos Islands and
their prehistoric creatures
by Dr Jean Dorst
Assistant Director, Museum of Natural History, Paris
iUNG RED-FOOTED BOOBY (shown here) and
cousin, the blue-faced booby, flourish on Tower
and in the Galapagos archipelago. They are so tame
Wat they allow people to approach close to their nests
without taking flight. Legend has it that their name was
given to them by sailors on the Pacific because they
wo¿:^|,light on the decks of passing ships and allow
Paves to be caught without trying to fly away.
© Philippa Scott, Siimbridge, U.K.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
ei* Tmí 4
7k -m
Philippa Scott, Slimbridge, U.K.
«L
BLACK LAVA CLIFFS are typical of the Galapagos Islands, Pacific archipelago of thirteen main islands
and many islets, 600 miles off the coast of Ecuador. To conserve and study the unusual flora and fauna of
these islands, Unesco helped found the Charles Darwin Foundation in 1959. The field station's labora¬
tory has now been built and an ambitious biological research programme is expected to get under way soon.
MELVILLE'S DESCRIPTION
Herman Melville, the author of "Moby Dick", visited the Gala¬
pagos Islands in 1841, only a few years after Charles Darwin.
His description of the "Enchanted Isles", published in 1854
under the title Las Encantadas, makes fascinating reading.
A few paragraphs are published below.
Take five-and-twenty heaps of cinders dumped here
and there in an outside city lot ; imagine some of them
magnified into mountains, and the vacant lot the sea ;
and you will have a fit idea of the general aspect of the
Encantadas, or Enchanted Isles. A group rather of
extinct volcanoes than of isles ; looking much as the
world at large might, after a penal conflagration.
...Cut by the Equator, they know not autumn, and they
know not spring ; while already reduced to the lees of
fire, ruin itself can work little more upon them. The
showers refresh the deserts ; but in these isles, rain never
falls.
...Little but reptile life is here found; tortoises, lizards,
immense spiders, snakes, and that strangest anomaly of
outlandish nature, the iguana. No voice, no low, no howl
is heard ; the chief sound of life here is a hiss.
On most of the isles where vegetation is found at all,
it is more ungrateful than the blankness of Atacama.
Tangled thickets of wiry bushes, without fruit and without
a name, springing up among deep fissures of calcined
rock, and treacherously masking them ; or a parched
growth of distorted cactus trees.
In many places the coast is rock-bound, or, more pro¬
perly, clinker-bound ; tumbled masses of blackish or
greenish stuff like the dross of an iron-furnace, forming
dark clefts and caves here and there, into which a cease¬
less sea pours a fury of foam ; overhanging them with a
swirl of gray, haggard mist, amidst which sail screaming
flights of unearthly birds heightening the dismal din.
Nor would the appellation, enchanted, seem misapplied
in still another sense. For concerning the peculiar reptile
inhabitant of these wildswhose presence gives the group
its second Spanish name, Galapagosconcerning the
tortoises found here, most mariners have long cherished
a superstition, not more frightful than grotesque. They
earnestly believe that all wicked sea-officers, more
especially commodores and captains, are at death (and,
in some cases, before death) transformed into tortoises ;
thenceforth dwelling upon thèse hot aridities, sole solitary
lords of Asphaltum.
From Complete Stories of Herman Melville,
Random House, New York, 1951.
R:ecent celebrations marking the centenary of
.Charles Darwin's famous work, The Origin of
Species (published in London in 1859), turned a world
spotlight on the Galapagos Islands. On this occasion
people in all parts of the globe heard about these islands
whose scientific importance had, in any case, long since
become known to a wider audience than that of the
world's biologists.
The Galapagos Archipelago, lying on and near the
Equator, some 600 miles out in the Pacific to the west of
the coast of Ecuador, to which it belongs, directly inspired
the famous British naturalist. As early as 1837 Darwin
wrote in one of his journals: "In July I opened my first
notebook on transmutation of species. Had been greatly
struck from about month of previous March on character
of South American fossils and species of Galapagos Archi¬
pelago. These facts origin (especially latter) of all my
views."
There is no doubt that the Galapagos Islands were a
determining factor in the development of Darwinism.
But what were the reasons for this profound influence?
Superficially, this tiny archipelago appears to have
nothing of particular interest to the scientist. A handful
of dots on most maps (their total area covers less than
3,000 square miles), the 13 islands of the Galapagos group
include five which are fairly large (the largest is Albe¬
marle Island, 60 miles in length), numerous islets and
rocks. Of volcanic origin, they are the peaks of a range
of submarine volcanoes thrust up from the sea by suc¬
cessive eruptions. It is more than probable that they
were never" joined in any way to the American continent.
The visitor finds mountains of black or red lava which
has poured out of the archipelago's 2,000 craters. Some
of these mountains are over 5,000 feet above sea level.
Curiously, the Galapagos Islands, though so close to the
equator, are washed by fairly cool seas. Unusual océano¬
graphie conditions exist in the east Pacific because of the
famous Humboldt Current, which brings cold water from
the Antarctic along the coasts of Chile and Peru, then
turns west at the equator and runs towards the Galapagos
Islands, after which it loses Itself in the ocean depths.
The low temperature of the water in the region of
14 °c produced far-reaching effects in the climate of
the islands. As along the shores of Peru, and for the same
reasons, rainfalls are sparse, occurring only between
January and March, and drought conditions often prevail.
The vegetation is in keeping with this arid climate.
The lowlands are covered with a vegetation adapted to
dry conditions, with an abundance of giant cacti (Opun¬
tia and Cereus) and spiny shrubs which lose their leaves
in the dry season.
29
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
GALAPAGOS (Cont'd)
LIVING
LABORATORY
OF EVOLUTION
The hilly slopes exposed to the more humid south-east
winds and often shrouded in fog are clothed with thicker
vegetation and, in a few areas, veritable forests of trees
laden with parasitical vegetation. This natural environ¬
ment makes a sharp contrast with the more usual land¬
scape in the islands a barren prospect of naked lava with
nothing but a few cacti here and there.
The fauna living in the archipelago is limited to very
few species. The reason for this is quite simple. As these
species were isolated by large stretches of ocean right
from the beginning, they form what is, in fact, a world
on their ownwhich has followed its own evolutionary
laws shut off from the world outside. Plants and animals
arrived there from the American continent as best they
could, swimming, flying or borne forward by the winds on
natural rafts composed of a tangle of tree trunks and
deadwood like those often carried along by many big
tropical rivers.
T
30
AKing into account the theoretical existence,
at one period, of an American continent
jutting out further into the ocean than it does today, it
is reasonable to assume that these means of locomotion
were then easier than they are now. But even so the
ocean crossing would have been a difficult enterprise and,
in fact, only a limited number of creatures made the
voyage safely. This explains the starling paucity of the
Galapagos fauna and flora, especially as compared with
the luxuriance of tropical America.
It may thus seem surprising that biologists regard these
apparently barren islands as a scientific wonderland. But
the scientists are right, for the Galapagos Islands are
no less than a natural laboratory in which evolution has
been made manifest. As the botanist, Howell, so rightly
said they are the workroom and show-window of Evolu¬
tion. They are important for the study of this funda¬
mental problem for three reasons.
Being so remote, the Galapagos Islands have served as
a refuge for animals of an archaic type and for a bio¬
logical complex which has disappeared everywhere else
in the world. As mammals could not reach these islands,
the reptiles developed unhindered by their natural com¬
petitors and the animals to which they fall prey.
A visitor setting foot on these shores for the first time
feels as though he has gone back to the secondary period,
the age of the reptiles. Along the beaches live marine
iguanas 3 1/2 feet long, the only sea-bound sauria still in
existence. They feed on sea-weed, grazing at low tide,
and bask in the sun in colonies sometimes running into
hundreds.
In the interior, land iguanas of a different type live
amongst the cactus along with the giant tortoises which
are such a characteristic sight that their Spanish name,
"Galapagos", was applied to the islands. These giants,
whose shells alone measure 3 1/2 feet, are now found only
in the Galapagos Islands and the Seychelles, though
fossilized remains extend over a vast area encompassing
North America and Europe. This example is typical of
the prehistoric character of so much of the wild life of
the Galapagos Islands, which are truly a Noah's Ark for
animals that have disappeared from the face of the earth.
But this is not all. On the Galapagos Islands an evolu¬
tionary differentiation occurred isolated from the currents
in evolution taking place on the continents. This explains
the presence of such a high proportion of endemic ani¬
mals sometimes over 50% in one single group.
Owing to the remoteness of the archipelago, the num¬
ber of ancestors is of course very limited. Hence a sim¬
plification in the fauna which makes the laws of evolution
much easier to distinguish than in the rest of the world,
where the complexity of natural phenomena and the
multiplicity of ancestors complicate inextricably the
tracing of relationships. The Galapagos Islands thus
stand out as Nature's experimental station.
THE ANIMALS of Galapagos are unique in the world. The
islands, now believed to be of oceanic origin, received flora and
fauna that either drifted there on ocean currents or flew there
through the air. Thus isolated, the animal and plant life has
followed evolutionary patterns of its own. The photo below
of the Galapagos iguanas basking in the sun might have come
from the earth's reptile age. They are found exclusively in this
tiny archipelago. The giant tortoise above is found in only one
other place in the world the Seychelles. At right a flightless
cormorant, also found only in the Galapagos, regards a sea lion
as a marine ¡guana retreats from the water. The most surpris¬
ing thing about Galapagos animals is their lack of fear of humans.
Photos © Philippa Scott, Slimbridge, U.K.
v
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
m
8m2£
M
-^' <
^K
--^
*$ .
Dr. I. Eibl-Eibejfeldc
REPTILES
OUT OF
THE PAST
This is particularly true of the famous Darwin finches,
or Geospizidae, sparrows indigenous to the Galapagos
Islands and belonging to the Fringillidae or finch family.
The Islands' 14 species are all derived from a common
ancestor, which obviously arrived there at a time when
there were no other birds. Several lines then evolved in
such a way as to make the fullest use of available food¬
stuff. The group as a whole thus fills all the ecological
niches normally held by birds of very different families.
Accordingly some Darwin finches resemble granivorous
sparrows with their big beaks for crushing seeds, while
others are not unlike warblers with their tiny pointed
beaks and insect diet. The Darwin sparrows illustrate in
striking fashion the whole process of the evolution of
sparrows. Such an evolution was of course made possible
by the absence of any competitor. It will be readily,
understood that the study of these birds lends weight to
Darwinian theories.
So the Galapagos Islands are an ideal spot for studying
the dynamics of evolution. A more recent evolution may
also be witnessed. Owing to the paradoxical conditions of
the natural environment; mainly due to the presence of
cold currents at the equator alongside masses of warm
water fauna of very diverse origins has mixed in the
islands.
Here penguins, usually connected with Antarctic climes,
rub shoulders with frigate and tropic birds and other avi¬
fauna found near warm tropical waters. The combined
presence of creatures having such widely different origins
and ecological preferences is an important factor in the
evolution now taking place. These peculiar circumstances
enable us to study at first hand the adaptation of animals
to their environment.
Here are but a few of the research possibilities of the
Galapagos Islands, though they already give some idea of
the importance of the islands to biology. Discovered (in
terms of science) by Charles Darwin in 1835 when he
made his famous voyage on the "Beagle", their scientific
value has in no way diminished. Yet the situation of
their fauna and flora is so precarious that this unique bio¬
logical complex is threatened with extinction. Up till the
sixteenth century the islands remained untouched by
man. Then came successive waves of pirates, buccaneers
and settlers mostly mutineers or ex-prisoners.
F1 ORTUNATELY the present population is made up
of law-abiding and friendly settlers, but like
many elsewhere, they are not always aware of the imper¬
atives of nature conservation. Furthermore, they have
thought fit to introduce animals previously unknown in
the islands, most of which are now overrun with goats,
pigs, dogs and cattle bred from domestic animals turned
wild, not to mention the rats and mice introduced
accidentally. So in addition to the direct depredations
of Man, the natural fauna finds itself up against the
vigorous competition of animals better equipped for the
struggle for life than are reptiles.
Everywhere in the islands the reptiles have regressed
especially the tortoises. In former times they were
massacred for their fat; now their eggs and young are
devoured by the dogs and pigs. Some species are already
extinct, while others are in a perilous situation. The
fauna as a whole is seriously threatened. We are in
danger of seeing a priceless natural heritage disappear
before our very eyes.
As early as 1934 this state of affairs alarmed the Ecua¬
dorian Government, which passed laws placing the Gala¬
pagos fauna and flora under its protection and setting
aside much of the islands as national parks. Unfortu¬
nately these regulations were hardly applied at all. So,
after the Second World War, Ecuador contacted Unesco
and the International Union for the Conservation of
Nature and asked them to send a mission to study
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Philippa Scott, Slimbridge, U.K IN DANGER of extinction is the colourful Frigate bird on Galapagos. The males of the species
display brilliantly red inflated throat sacks during the mating season (above) and seemto com¬
pete for the attention of females with this flamboyant show. Because these birds breed in only
one or two concentrated areas and frequently nest on the ground, they are quite vulnerable.
A NATURAL COMPLEX
UNIQUE IN THE WORLD
32
the islands, and to suggest how best the Galapagos fauna
and flora might be preserved.
Dr I. Eibl-Eibesfeldt, an expert named by Unesco, and
Dr. R. Bowman (University of California) went on a
mission to the Islands in 1957." On their return it was
decided to set up a field station on the Galapagos Islands
to be run by an international body with the support of
Ecuador, which declared its intention to promulgate more
effective laws and to see that they were respected.
Following a mission on which I was sent by Unesco in
1958, a preliminary agreement was reached with the Ecua¬
dorian Government and construction of the biological
station began in 1960. The site chosen was on Indefati¬
gable Island (Santa Cruz) close to the little village where
most of this island's settlers live. The work, a large and
complicated scientific and technical task, is being super¬
vised by M. Raymond Lévêque, a biologist entrusted with
the mission by Unesco in 1960.
The Charles Darwin Foundation for the Galapagos
Islands was formed in Brussels in 1959, under the presi¬
dency of Professor V. Van Straelen, to put all these
plans into effect. Sir Julian Huxley, who was one of the
first to defend the cause, became its honorary president,
and Dr L. Jaramillo, permanent delegate of Ecuador to
Unesco, accepted the vice-presidency. All countries
directly concerned in research in this part of the world
are represented on the executive board.
The Foundation immediately set about collecting funds
to defray the cost of building the Charles Darwin Station.
It succeeded so well that we now have two buildings
one to be used as a laboratory, the other as residential
quarters as well as basic equipment, purchased largely
with the credits made available to us by Unesco.
The first research-workers are now able to begin their
investigations. However, there are still many improve¬
ments to be made in the present organization. Additional
buildings, scientific equipment and an océanographic-
research vessel are urgently required to enable scientists
to work effectively in a difficult natural environment.
Following close consultations with the Charles Darwin
Foundation, satisfactory legislation has now been in¬
troduced by the Ecuadorian Government. Large areas
have recently been decreed natural reserves, notably Nar-
borough Island (Fernandina) , which has retained its ori¬
ginal appearance, and the western part of Indefatigable
Island (Santa Cruz), where tortoises are still fairly nu¬
merous. The foundation will continue to suggest to the
Ecuadorian authorities measures aimed at protecting and
conserving a natural complex found nowhere else in the
world.
The Foundation has mapped out an ambitious research
programme. It includes geological and pedological stud¬
ies, which thanks to the structure and origin of the
islands, should yield interesting findings. In the bio¬
logical field, the work has hardly begun insofar as soil
biology and invertebrata are concerned. It may even¬
tually reveal some hitherto unknown aspects of the laws
of evolution. This fertile field of investigation is now
open to scientists from all over the world thanks to the
founding of the new biological station.
Economic aspects will not be forgotten. The seas
around the Galapagos Islands abound in marine life,
especially fish, which could provide Ecuador with much-
needed proteins. Our biological station, though primarily
devoted to basic research, will thus play a part in the
economic development projects for the Galapagos Islands
without compromising the survival of their natural
wealth.
The combined efforts of scientists from all over the
world will in this way make up in some measure for the
depredations committed by other men. The Foundation
will also stand as a monument to Charles Darwin, whose
evolutionary theories were conceived on the desolate
shores of this tiny volcanic archipelago.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
UNESCO'S CALENDAR
Sir,
In The Unesco Courier I read
the Unicef Greeting Cards and
the success, they have. I wonder
if there is also a Unesco Calendar (for
instance with photographs about
Unesco's work in different countries).
Perhaps a lot of people or institutions
(schools, offices) would be interested
in such a calendar, and besides, I can
imagine it would help in spreading
the ideas of Unesco, as a calendar is
a thing one looks at quite often.
R. Kats
Voorburg, Netherlands
Unesco is considering the publica¬
tion next year of a calendar or desk
agenda in English and French.
FOOD AND PEOPLE
Sir,
I am afraid that Mr. McNicholas
(letter to the Editor, February 1961)
views the problem of food and popu¬
lation in a different time dimension
than I did. He wrote: "The real prob¬
lem we are facing in the world today
is that of distribution, not overpopu¬
lation" (my italics). I can agree with
this thesis when it is put in the present
time. ' But the present generation has
to think about and to plan for
tomorrow as well.
As to his homely example: ("If ten
people need hats and there are only
eight hats available, the common sense
solution is to get two more hats from
somewhere, not to cut off two peo¬
ple's heads") he interprets my point
of view in a rather free manner. I'll
try to translate it in terms of his own
(dangerous) analogy: if you are not
quite certain about having more than
eight hats, try to prevent to provide
for more than eight people.
It may be (and sounds) easy to get
another two hats, and that's why this
analogy is a dangerous one. It may,
however, become progressively difficult
to find enough food for, say, another
1,000,000,000 people. Am I going
against the facts? In India alone the
population increased by 80,000,000
persons within the last ten years. Is
Mr. McNicholas quite sure that the
fast eroding earth-surface can feed
such an explosive population increase
the coming millenium?
On the probability of the answer to
this question rests the common sense
(or non sense) character of his solu¬
tion. So far my experience as a
student of geography reaches, the
scientists are not as optimistic as my
opponent suggests. I hope that The
Unesco Courier in the issue on popu¬
lation and food production will lend
an ear to those who are pessimistically
minded as well.
P. Kloos
Amsterdam, Netherlands
THE RACISM ISSUE
Sir, .
Assuming that the letters to the
editor you publish are in quantitati¬
vely proportionate ratio to those you
receive on a given issue, I must say
I have seldom read anything so dis¬
couraging as the reactions to your
Racism issue. To think that this
represents the readership of a maga¬
zine devoted to international under¬
standing!!! My sympathy and best
wishes.
Eva Schiffer
Kew Gardens, N. Y., U.S.A.
'MORE POWER TO YOU'
Sir,
I am not sure which type of Unesco
Courier issue is most satisfying and
stimulating the kind devoted chiefly
to one important topic such as "Ra¬
cism" or the richly varied kind
exemplified by the recent March issue.
The latter kept me nailed to my chair
until I reached the final letter on the
Letters-to-the-Editor page and read
the charge of inadequate subject cov¬
erage and resemblance to "Life."
Then I rose to brandish my typewriter
to hoot down such criticism.
"More power to you" as my Irish
grandmother used to say. I think
you bring the world to my home
better than half a dozen other peri¬
odicals and newspapers I subcribe to.
Thank you.
Fredericka Martin
Cuernavaca, Morelos, Mexico
VELAZQUEZ A LA PICASSO
Sir,
It takes all sorts of tastes to make
a world and for that reason I would
be loath to regard myself as the cus¬
todian of the absolute truth in
matters of art. I simply wish to offer
you the opinion of an average French¬
man, which is what I am in spite of
my Spanish origins. The Picasso
mural in the Unesco conference
building is, in my view, awful. As
for Velazquez, he has nothing to gain
through interpretation by this painter
blessed with "extraordinary imagina¬
tion." As you had available a double
page you would have put it to better
use had you offered us preferably in
colour a true reproduction of Las
Meninas (Ladies in Waiting).
At this rate, Picasso or Dali will
soon be asked to provide the Venus
de Milo with arms or to replace the
missing head of the Victory of Samo-
thrace.
As Unesco has its headquarters
building in France, a French painter
worthy of the name could have been
asked to produce a work for the
space allocated to Picasso. There is
no shortage of good painters and
designers in our country.
Leaving aside this question, I may
say that I find your magazine most
interesting.
François Ribera
Toulouse, France
A SPANKING IN TIME...
Sir,
I read every issue of The Unesco
Courier with great interest and profit.
Your April 1961 on "Accidents Need
Not Happen" was exceptionally good.
Wisely, there was emphasis on
teaching the young child to avoid
certain known dangers as well as on
his protection by adults. But nowhere
was it suggested that parental appli¬
cation of pain to teach the little word
No! is essential in teaching safety to
the tot no mention of obedience.
May I call to your attention
Obedience Means Safety for Your
Child, published recently by the Ame¬
rican Academy of Pediatrics.
To quote: "The prick of a pin, a
kitten's scratch, a broken dish, a
bruise or bump, some such natural
consequence of disobedience may
make a child hesitate to repeat a per¬
formance. But when nothing happens,
as is often and happily the case, you
will do well to render punishment of
some kind. What kind of punishment
does not matter as long as it serves to
influence future behaviour. A spank¬
ing is quick, often effective."
Garry Cleveland Myers
Editor, Highlights for Children
Honesdale, Pennsylvania, U.S.A.
FOR HARMONY & UNIVERSALITY
Sir,
With reference to your March 1961
edition, I feel unable to agree with the
views of Mrs. Robert Clark, of Bristol,
Gt Britain.
The Unesco Courier has to cater
for a wide range of people and inte¬
rests. However that need not mean
that the result is what we derogatorily
call "mass appeal." Topics are gene¬
rally treated interestingly and adequa¬
tely, as befits Unesco. In addition
many of them point to further and
more detailed material on the topics.
The great value of your magazine
lies in the way it brings th<i peoples
of the world together, directly and
indirectly, and in its wide scope serves
towards the harmony and universality
of Mankind.
Terence Waurwright
London, England
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
THE VANISHING HERDS (Cont'd from page 6)
. Wild African ungulates are capable, on poor natural
grazing land, of reaching a biomass as high or almost as
high as domestic cattle on excellent artificial grazing
lands. What is the reason for this?
The principal one, already suggested by Lebrun in 1947,
is that wild grazing animals really use all the food re¬
sources of their environment. Some species, like the
elephant, eat practically anything, leaves, grass, bark,
roots and even graminaceous plants on which other
animals do not graze. The various species of ungulates
inhabiting the savannahs use absolutely all types of
vegetation: young shoots (many small antelopes), thorny
bushes (black rhinoceros), foliage of average sized trees
(giraffes, elephants). The total load of grazing animals
Is therefore spread over the whole plant biomass.
The natural resistance of wild ungulates to many para¬
sites also gives them a great advantage over their
domestic competitors. The same applies to their better
adaptation to high tropical temperatures. All this no
doubt explains why the assimilation of food and the rate
of growth are generally higher among wild herbivores.
Riney observed that the Cape eland can attain a weight
of 320 kg. in two years on pastures where domestic cattle
would literally starve to death.
These facts have led ecologists to wonder whether it
would not sometimes be economically more profitable to
"manage" this wild ungulate population, adapted for
thousands of years to the hard conditions of its natural
surroundings, rather than try to acclimatize domestic
cattle, at great cost, in areas ecologically unfavourable
to them, where they use only part of the meagre re¬
sources available and where they also do much to
accelerate the processes of erosion.
The great objection to this view has, until now, been
the obvious practical difficulty of "managing" wild ani¬
mal populations. To take a sufficient number of head
annually for the production of a large quantity of meat,
while maintaining the herds at a constant level, in bal¬
ance with the food resources of the environment, is easy
in theory, but infinitely more difficult in practice. The
cost price of this "wild" meat might for the most part
be higher than that of "domestic" meat, because of the
bad transport facilities and preservation difficulties.
But new techniques are now under study which will
probably change the whole basis of the problem. Long-
hurst has shown that it is perfectly possible to use light
aircraft to head back certain large species such as ele¬
phants, thus making It possible to guide them, at certain
times of the year, to corrals where the selection and
slaughter of the animals would be easier than in the
heart of the bush. The development of drugs immobili¬
zing large ungulates at a distance, for a certain period
of time, without danger for them or for the consumer,
also offers new possibilities of transporting live animals
to zones which need restocking or even to slaughter
houses with modern equipment and cold storage.
The research done in Uganda by Buechner, Harthorn
and Lock is highly encouraging in this connexion. Field
spraying with antibiotics in order to help preserve meat
is also being studied. It is therefore not unreasonable
to envisage rational exploitation of the large wild ungu¬
late population in the near future, and under profitable
conditions. A few "pilot operations" are now under way
in Kenya and Uganda; their outcome is eagerly awaited.
In what areas can this new conservation policy for
African ungulates be applied? First and foremost, in all
marginal areas where agriculture and stock breeding are
possible only by heavy investment over a long period.
Such zones cover vast stretches of Africa: Fraser Darling
estimates that 90% of Northern Rhodesia cannot, because
of the poverty of its soil, support intensive agriculture
and stock farming, and this is, unfortunately, not the
only example. This means that the traditional source
of animal proteins represented by large game animals may
therefore play a great part in feeding Africa tomorrow.
The establishment of areas of fauna exploitation
around the national parks is also quite conceivable. The
parks would then, in addition to their invaluable services
as natural laboratories and tourist attractions, become
restocking grounds for neighbouring regions.
Thus a dynamic and radically new conservation policy
is being worked out for the large animals of Africa,
opening up prospects undreamed of until recently.
THE DRAMA OF SERENGETI (Cont'd from page 23)
34
compatible with the reasonable interests of the African
pastoralists. The Nuffield Foundation gave a further
£20,000 for pasture research in the area.
With these large funds made available to the
Conservation Authority, it might have been thought
natural to give it more power and more adequate member¬
ship, to place it under competent scientific direction, and
to provide it with a well-thought out management plan
(such as is given to National Nature Reserves in Britain) ;
but nothing of the sort was done for two years. However,
it now appears that a radical reorganization of the
Conservation Authority is contemplated, and a draft for
a management plan has been prepared.
As a result of my visit; and of discussions with numer¬
ous people both in Africa and in England, I came to the
following main conclusions. (1) That it would be wrong
and indeed immoral to jeopardize the future of the
Serengeti National ' Park area, as the most outstanding
wild life region left in the world, by undesirable restriction
of its boundaries in the supposed interests of the Masai
or of economy. (2) That it would be equally wrong, and
indeed egregiously foolish, not to give National Park
status to the uniquely spectacular Ngorongoro Crater with
all its wild life. (3) That high priority should be given (a)
to projects for improving road and air access to and
accommodation in the Serengeti National Park and
Ngorongoro; (b) to scientific surveys and research projects
concerned with conservation and basic ecology in the
area. (4) That stricter measures should be taken against
poaching and illegal killing of animals, not only in the
Serengeti-Ngorongoro area but throughout Tanganyika.
(5) That the Olduvai Gorge, with the unique exposure
of Pleistocene history, including human origins, revealed
by Dr. L.J.B. Leakey's excavations, should be accorded
National Park status. (6) That the Masai should be
encouraged to co-operate in every way in a policy of
conservation for the region, by constituting the Ngoron¬
goro crater and that part of the Serengeti plains within
the Conservation Area as Masai Tribal Parks, by giving
them a share of the financial benefits accruing from
tourists, and by educating them to appreciate the
importance of habitat conservation for their own future.
(7) That the Conservation Authority should be thoroughly
reorganized so as to give it greater autonomy and greater
efficiency.
The Authority's objectives should be redefined so as
to include conservation of soil, water-resources, forest
cover and wild life for the entire Serengeti-Crater High¬
lands area. It should be furnished with a scientific
management plan; and the specialists on the Authority
should include scientists and experts from other territories
and countries, including representatives of the East
African Agricultural and Forestry Organization (EAFRO) ;
the corresponding Veterinary Research Organization
(EAVRO) ; the newly-constituted University of East
Africa ; F.A.O. ; and the International Union for the
Conservation of Nature (I.U.C.N.). The closest possible
liaison should be maintained both centrally and locally
with the Tanganyika National Parks organization.
Only by some such means can the Masai lands in this
region be salvaged from progressive ruination, and the
area's unique heritage of wild life and spectacular scenery
be preserved in perpetuity for the benefit of Tanganyika
and the world at large.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
': ;..'.
current
trends
in scientific
research
by Pierre Auger, special consultant
Just published :
A UNIQUE SURVEY
OF WORLD
SCIENTIFIC
TRENDS
by Pierre Auger
A book which is not only the first of its kind, but likely to be
one of the most important basic scientific works. of the coming
decade. It will be of exceptional interest to science research
institutions, universities, government science officers, science
teachers and industryin fact, to all who are interested in
the history and development of scientific research.
In 1960, the General Assembly of the United Nations decided
that a survey should be made on the current trends of enquiry
in the fields of the natural sciences and on the dissemination
and application for peaceful purposes of such knowledge.
Twenty-nine intergovernmental organizations, 66 inter¬
national non-governmental organizations, the national research
organizations of 42 countries and 255 scientific experts have
collaborated to produce this book under the direction of
Professor Pierre Auger, a leading physicist and the former
head of Unesco's Department of Natural Sciences. His book
was reviewed in the July-August issue of The Unesco Courier.
Cloth bound; $6.75 33/- 23.50 NF.
Where to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write
direct to the National Distributor
in your country. (See list below ;
names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.)
Payment is made in the national
currency ; rates quoted are for an
annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Press
Department, Royal Afghan Ministry of
Education, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 369 Lonsdale Street, Melbourne,
C I, Victoria. (A. 1 5/-).
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C0., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V (Sch.
50.-)
BELGIUM. For The Unesco Courier:
Louis de Lannoy, 22, Place de Brouckère,
Brussels, C.C.P. 338.000. (fr. b. 1 00.)
Other publications: Office de Publicité,
I 6, rue Marcq, Bruxelles, C.C.P. 285.98;
N.V. Standaard-Boekhandel, Belgiëlei I 5 I,
Antwerp.
BURMA. Sarpay Beikman Institute.
36I Prome Road, Rangoon. (K. 5.50)
CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa
Ont. ($ 3.00).
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd, Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Co¬
lombo,^. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co, Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Librería Económica, Pte Zayas
505-7,Apartado 113, Havana. (2.25 pesos)
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia Ltd., 30
Ve Smeckách, Prague 2.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard, A/S
Tidsskriftafdelingen, 6 Nörregade, Köben-
havn K. (D.kr. 12).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agen¬
cy, P.O. Box 120, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu. Helsinki. (F.mk. 540).
FRANCE. Unesco Bookshop, Place de
Fontenoy.. Paris, 7«. C.C.P. 12598-48.
(7 NF.).
GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier,
Vertrieb Bahrenfelder-Chaussee 160,
Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, C.C.P. 276650
(DM 8). Other Publications : R. Olden¬
bourg, Verlag, Rosenheimerstrasse 145,
Munich.
GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28,
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Kultura, P.O. Box 149.
Budapest, 62.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd. Indian
Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road, Bombay
I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13;
Gunfoundry Road, Hyderabad, I ; 36a,
Mount Road, Madras 2; Kanson House,
24/1 Asaf Ali Road, P.O. Box 386, New
Delhi, I ; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book &
Stationery Co., 17 Park Street Calcutta 16,
Scindia House, New Delhi. (Rs. 6.70).
INDONESIA. Bappit Pusat "Permata",
D jalan Nusantara 22, Djakarta.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The National Press, 2, Wel¬
lington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
35, Allenby Road and 48, Nahlat Benja¬
min Street, Tel-Aviv (l£ 4.-).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 9 1
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.( I 0/-)
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central. Tokyo. (Yen 670).
JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road , P.O.B. 66,
Amman.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul.
LIBERIA. J. Momolu Kamara, 69, Front
and Gurley Streets, Monrovia.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück,
22, Grand-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications
Ltd., Times House, River Valley Rd.,
Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta. (10/-).
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd.
30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis.
MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid des
Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (7 NF).
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Ni¡-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl 6)
NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES.
G. CT. Van Dorp & C- (Ned Ant.) N.V.
Willemstad, Curacao.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church. (10/-).
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
I 74, Lagos. ( I 0/-).
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille Gren-
sen,7, Oslo. (N. kr. 13.20).
PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing
Co, Ltd., Unesco Publications House,
P.O. Box 374, 56-N Gulberg Industrial
Colony, Lahore.
PANAMA. Cultural Panameña, Avenida
7a, No. TI-49, Apartado de Correos 20 I 8,
Panama, D.F. (Balboas 3.-).
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1 104 Castillejos, Quiapo, P.O. Box
620, Manila.
POLAND. "RUCH" ul. Wiloza Nr. 46,
Warsaw. 1.0 (Zl. 50).
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada Lda,
Livraria Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70,
Lisbon.
RHODESIA & NYASALAND. The
Book Centre, First Street, Salisbury,
Southern Rhodesia.
SWEDEN. For The Unesco Courier: Sven*
ska Unescorädet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 7.50); other publications
A/B C.E. Fritzes, Kungl. Hovbokhandel,
Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40, rue du Marché, Geneva. C.C.P.
1-236.
"Courier" only: Georges Losmaz, I, rue
des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. C.C.P.
1-4811. (Fr. S. 8).
TANGANYIKA Dar-es-Salaam Book¬
shop, P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam.
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok. (35
ticals).
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Isti-
klal Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Street, Pretoria. (10/-).
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT).
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha,
Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.1.( I 0/-).
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22, N.Y. ($ 5.00.) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y.
U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga,
Terazije 27/1 I. Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
¿JS%'
y
view of an elep
A type apart from other wild life in Africa, it eats anythingherbage, foliage, fruit, seeds, bark and roots.
]]>
</page>
</document>
