<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="064696eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
5*
.
V APRIL
1960
(/3th year)
Price : I /-stg. (U.K.)
30 cents (U. S.)
0.7 0 NF. (France)
1,000 MILLION PERSONS IN DANGER
WORLD MOBILIZATION
ABA IN ST MALARIA
\
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
^!¿\<*l$»
î':V.
À
.*¿f
.-jätes
*"^X
f
rf -
ËAifei'
ÎUÉS
ISLAND IN SPACE. A Soviet artist's impression of a space-ship refueling station far above the earth. The launching
of orbital rockets as far as the moon is already a signpost pointing to the era of interplanetary travel in which relay stations
unique constructions whirling in space like the artificial satellite shown here will play a vital role. See page 23.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
SOW OriN ON TN| WOI10
1er
APRIL 1960
1 3 T H YEAR
Contents
No. 4
Page
4 WORLD ASSAULT ON A SINGLE ENEMY
By G. Candau
COVER PHOTO
Greece was once the most
malaria-ridden country in
Europe. Fourteen years ago
it was picked as an advance
post In the world war against
the disease. Today, with
malaria practically driven out
It has scored a resounding
victory. Photo shows two
girls in a malaria-free village
of Greece. (See story p. 14)
© F. Barzilay
6 1,000 MILLION LIVES IN DANGER
9 SPECTRE OF DEATH OR SLAVERY
12 OUTWITTING THE WILY ANOPHELES
14 WAS ANCIENT GREECE VANQUISHED BY MALARIA?
17 U.S.S.R.: VICTORY AHEAD IN A LONG CAMPAIGN
By L. J. Bruce-Chwatt
18 MALARIA PATROL AT THE FOOT OF ANAPURNA
22 A BATTERY OF NEW DRUGS
23 WHAT SHALL WE GAIN BY THE CONQUEST OF SPACE?
By V.G. Fesenkov
26 THE STORY OF PLACE NAMES
By Mario Pei
30 HOW LONG DO THEY LIVE?
The diverse longevity of plants & animals
By David Gunston
Drawing page 2 by N. Kol-
chitsky, from " Travel to
Distant Worlds " by Karl
Gllzln, Foreign Languages
Publishing House, Moscow,
1957.
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7', France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (II issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. In the United States of America it is distri¬
buted by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 80 I Third Avenue, New
York 22, N.Y., Plaza 1-3860. Second-class mail privileges authorized at New
York, N.Y. (M.C. 60. 1. 146 A).
individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author*s name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: $ 3.00; IO/-stg. ; 7.00 New
Francs or equivalent. Single copies I /-stg. 30 cents
(U.S.); 0.70 New Francs.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7\
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
World Health Day this year is devoted to the world's most costly disease, malaria, and the world
campaign for its eradication.
Never before in history have the nations concerted their efforts on such a scale against a
single disease. Without a dissenting voice the ninety Members of the World Health Organization
have resolved to pool their knowledge and resources to achieve nothing less than the complete
elimination of this disease from our globe. This year's World Health Day will, I hope, serve to recall
to all peoples the urgency of this great undertaking.
Malaria remains in 1960 a constant threat to more than 1,000 million human- beings. For the most
part these are people who already have more than their share of sickness and poverty, and can least
afford to be further weakened in their struggle against misfortune.
Malaria strikes first at a country's most precious resource, its young children. The disease is held
responsible for 10% to 15% of infant mortality. It can also depopulate large territories.
The man who carries the malaria parasite in his blood is a man of blunted initiative. To him few
things seem worth the trouble, he becomes fatalistic, and the physical deterioration that he suffers makes
him an easy prey to other dangerous diseases.
Today we know how malaria is transmitted, and by what mosquitos. We know how the malaria para¬
site behaves within the human body, and how it causes a fever that may lead to death. We have
found effective ways of destroying the mosquitos and we possess drugs that successfully attack the parasites
within the human body. Techniques for fighting malaria are becoming more powerful and precise.
But we know also that the deadly mosquitos have found ways of fighting back ; that is why speed is
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1960
essential. The campaign against malaria must be carried through while the weapons still remain effec¬
tive. There must be no slackening of effort until the disease has been entirely stamped out, and the
last remaining case in the remotest corner of the earth has been tracked down and cured.
WHO's member countries have given the Organization a heavy responsibility ; that of guiding a global
campaign for the complete and unconditional liberation from malaria of twelve hundred million human
beings in 148 countries and territories throughout the world.
The antimalaria operations that are at present proceeding, at one stage or another, in 92 countries
and territories constitute the greatest co-ordinated public health programme ever undertaken in the
world's history. In 13 of these countries, malaria cases have been reduced to a handful occurring
sporadically or introduced from outside. However, there are still 56 countries where no effort has yet
been made to subdue the malaria monster.
The (world antimalaria campaign evidently calls for large numbers of trained workers of many kinds,
quantities of equipment and supplies, considerable financial investment and efficient administrative
machinery. It is even more important, however, that the governments engaged in the campaign should
pursue it with conviction and with the determination to succeed.
The eradication of malaria is a challenge to all the world. In an era when man thinks he is about
to set foot on the moon, he should on his own planet be capable of stamping out one of his oldest and most
destructive enemies.
There is no doubt in my mind that the countries of the world are today in a position to accept this
challenge. To do so is indeed a question of honour. What is needed more than anything else is the will
to eradicate malaria, for today the way is there.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
1,000 MILLION
LIVES IN DANGER
nODAY twelve hundred million human beings are living
under the constant threat of malaria. It Is not a
spectacular disease. Its victims show no wounds or
mutilations to excite our pity ; it comes upon them
as they sleep, In the stillness of the night, carried
by a silent attacker, the mosquito. It is the "'fever" long
believed to be inescapable in tropical countries, more of a
nuisance than an illness people said.
The truth is that malaria is a disaster, and its terrible
consequences among that third of the world's population
which already has more than its fair share of disease and
poverty cannot be easily visualized in countries that are
free of it. Malaria epidemics can be just as destructive as
plague epidemics. Those Who live in malaria-ridden areas,
however, have become resigned to it, and accept it as a
natural part of their everyday life. Its victims are quite
unaware of the physical and moral deterioration it has
brought about as through countless centuries it has sapped
their strength, robbed them of initiative, and made them
vulnerable to other, more deadly infections. Moreover, it is
estimated that malaria accounts for 10-15 per cent, of infant
mortality in these countries.
The ultimate aim of the present world-wide antimalaria
campaign is to eliminate the disease, to wipe it off the
face of the globe, never giving up until the very last case
in the remotest corner of the earth has been tracked down.
The necessity for this giant undertaking was formally
and unanimously recognized by the representatives of all
the governments attending the Eighth World Health Assem¬
bly in Mexico City in 1955. The World Health Organization
was given charge of this world-wide operation which was
to be something quite new in medical annals.
This was to be a health programme presenting many
features of a military campaign, and one Whose aim was
not merely the surrender, but the extermination of the
enemy. An antimalaria army came into being, with its
intelligence service, its supply lines, its transport facilities,
its arms and munitions depots, its logistics offices, its general
staff and its high command: the last an office of modest
dimensions in the pleasant setting of Geneva. It is
occupied by Dr C. A. Alvarado, Director of WHO's Division
W.H.O map.
have concerted international for¬
ces on such a scale been de¬
ployed against a single disease.
Never before
Never before
have doctors, engineers, lab¬
oratory workers and helpers of
all kinds been mobilized in such large numbers in so
many different countries to combat the same evil.
Never before has a scheme been launched
that so intimately affects the
living conditions of such vast numbers of the earth's
inhabitants.
Hi
of Malaria Eradication and chief of the 329 international
malaria experts now at work in 73 different countries.
"We are engaged on a monster programme", Dr Alvarado
admits. "It calls for tens of thousands of teams, and mil¬
lions of tons of supplies and equipment. Hundreds of
millions of homes must be visited, hundreds of millions of
blood tests carried out, and tons of drugs supplied.
Thousands of lorries, cars, bicycles, donkeys, camels,
elephants and boats are needed. We must co-ordinate the
work of hundreds of laboratories, help establish contacts
and exchange of information between hundreds of research
and laboratory workers, arrange meetings of experts, trans¬
late reports from many different countries so that they can
be understood in the others.
"This drive to wipe out malaria also means making
thousands of maps, taking a census of population in the
affected areas, keeping a check on the movements of mil¬
lions of nomads, giving lectures, and holding open-air
discussions with villagers to convince them of the need for
the action being taken.
"'Malaria eradication", says Dr Alvarado, "is above all an
organizational and administrative problem, for we now know
almost all we need to know about its scientific and technical
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1960
g¿	
w
Eradication programme
being prepared
Noeradication pro-
gramme
Some species of mos¬
quitos resistant to
insecticides
f^SSÄfeäSS*«!
aspects and researchers are working hard on the few remain¬
ing unknowns. But malaria eradication is also a question
of money. According to our estimates, the campaign costs
rather less than one dollar for. each human being being
freed from the menace of malaria".
For thousands of years malaria remained a mysterious
affliction, which seemed connected with the presence of
marshes or other unhealthy surroundings. The foul smells
arising from stagnant water were also held responsible. The
first step towards solving the mystery was the discovery, in
1880, by a Frenchman, Laveran, that malaria was caused by
a parasitic organism, a haemosporidium (Plasmodium). In
1898 a British doctor, Ronald Ross, showed that the parasite
of bird malaria is transmitted by female mosquitos, and the
same year Italian scientists proved that the human parasite
is carried by Anopheles mosquitos.
Up to that time malaria patients had been treated with
cinchona bark, which later became quinine, and blood-let¬
ting was also practised. Whenever they could, people would
move away from areas that were believed unhealthy, thus,
without realizing it, escaping the risk of contact with mos¬
quitos. Water management and marsh drainage schemes
were also carried out.
It was the discovery of DDT by a Swiss, Paul Müller, who
was awarded the Nobel Prize for it, that completely chang¬
ed the outlook in the fight against malaria after the Second
World War.
It transformed malaria control into a simple operation
of spraying this "residual" insecticide on the inside walls of
dwellings, where the mosquitos rest after feeding on human
blood. The poison killed off the mosquitos. Malaria sufferers
were then given medical treatment, and the spread of the
-disease was thus halted.
It seemed that the battle had been won. At last the anti-
malaria campaigns would extend beyond the privileged
areas to all the villages and hamlets where they were most
badly needed. It would be possible for the first time to
estimate the time and money required on the basis of the
size of the population to be protected and the average wall
surface to be sprayed per head. The amount of insecticide
needed, the number of spraying pumps, the manpower
involved, and so on could then be accurately worked out.
The war against malaria had entered a new phase, in
which science and logistics were paramount. The way was
now open for the huge eradication programme that was
soon to be launched.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
VICIOUS CIRCLE
OF INFECTION
1. A female anopheles mosquito
sucks a sick person's blood that
contains sexual forms of malaria
parasites. 2. Cysts, produced by the
sexual malaria parasites, develop in
the stomach of the mosquito. 3. Mal¬
aria parasites, fully developed and
multiplied, are present in the salivary
glands of the mosquito. The healthy
person bitten by the mosquito be¬
comes infected. 4. The parasites first
develop in the liver of the infected
person. 5. Then the parasites deve¬
lop and multiply in the red blood cells
of the infected person. This phase
coincides with attacks of malaria,
with fever, anaemia and other symp¬
toms often leading to death. 6. Sexual
forms of the parasite develop in the
blood stream of the infected person.
WHO drawing.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1960
SPECTRE OF DEATH OR SLAVERY
The eradication of malaria will free humanity from a
ruinous disease that is a disgrace to our time.
Other diseases may decimate a population; malaria
can depopulate a whole region. Those it does not kill it
enslaves. Throughout history it has driven men off vast
tracts of fertile land. And those that stay on, drag out
a miserable existence.
These are facts that no one questions. Yet conclusive
proofs of the economic benefits resulting from malaria
eradication are difficult to obtain.
Nevertheless, the reports that WHO receives from all
over the world provide some valuable indications about
the economic, social and human significance of the
present antimalaria drive.
IN Afghanistan, about one million peasants lived under
the constant shadow of malaria, and some of the most
fertile land could not be
cultivated because of the rava¬
ges of the disease. The total
cost of antimalaria operations
between 1949 and 1959 did not
exceed $750,000, whereas mala¬
ria was the cause of a yearly
loss of earnings amounting to
about $20,000,000.
In Ceylon, the disappear¬
ance of malaria has resulted
in a saving of about $30,000,000
per year, that is, six times
the total expenditure on
the ten-year antimalaria cam¬
paign.
In India, the figures supplied
by Dr. K. Viswanathan, mal¬
aria adviser at the WHO
Regional Office in New Delhi,
are really astronomic. He
estimates that the annual
economic losses caused by
malaria in that country are
in the neighbourhood of
$ 500,000,000 corresponding to loss of wages, loss of output,
etc. affecting the fifty million Indians who fall victims to
the disease every year. On the other hand, he has cal¬
culated that the total cost of a malaria eradication pro¬
gramme of several years' duration in India would not
exceed $ 190,000,000, i. e. much less than the amount of the
present yearly losses.
In Mexico, where 175,000,000 dollars' worth of economic
damage is caused every year by malaria, the total cost of
the five-year eradication programme is expected to be
about $20,000,000.
In the Philippines, the uprooting of malaria has made
possible many projects which previously were out of the
question: construction of roads, opening of mines, building
of houses and industrial premises.
In Thailand, it has been estimated that fifty million
agricultural-worker/days were lost each year on account
of malaria. This is equivalent to a rice harvest worth
$15,000,000, whereas the cost of the malaria eradication
programme from 1954 to 1958 was $500,000 per year.
In French Guiana, infant mortality decreased by more
than 50 per cent, since the large-scale antimalaria op¬
erations carried out in 1949-1951.
According to a survey made in Nigeria, babies born of
malaria-infected mothers weighed on an average about
150 grammes (5 oz.) less than ordinary babies.
Laporte
According to Dr. Belios, Director of the Malaria Depart¬
ment in Greece, the average height of army recruits has
increased by 4-5 cm. since malaria has practically
disappeared from that country.
Behind these dry facts and figures, and ignored in the
economists' calculations, is an ocean of human misery and
despairgeneration following hopeless generation in half-
alive villages amid half cultivated fields.
Through the centuries entire peoples have physically
and mentally deteriorated under the repeated attacks of
the shivering fever. Physical Weakness has undermined
their spirit, and brought mental apathy and listlessness.
Malaria has destroyed any sense of initiative, any interest
in what lies outside the daily. round.
It is exhausting to be always exhausted, depressing to be
always depressed: people become resigned and regard their
misfortunes as an inescapable heritage.
"But," says Dr. Emilio Pam¬
pana, who was WHO's first
Director of Malaria Eradic¬
ation, "'as soon as malaria has
disappeared, new settlers ap¬
pear and begin to work the
fertile land that was formerly
uninhabitable. Their arrival
acts like an injection of ener¬
gy, a transfusion of new blood,
on the unhappy populations
who had clung to the malaria-
infested land that no one ever
thought of claiming from
them.
"Freed from malaria, the
people begin to rediscover
their strength, and regain
their energy: they realise how
much they have been depriv¬
ed of, and demand something
better. In short, they return
again to life."
This was what happened in
Sardinia, according to Dr. Paul
F\Rvfesk\a World Health Organization consultant who re-
viSftea tnVt island after an interval of 20 years. "When I
first vlsite\ the island in 1929,"' he says, I was distressed
by the pitiaWe condition of many of the children in ma¬
larious village«. In a typical street there would almost
alwaykbe sad lütle creatures with large bellies and pale
faces sitting listlessly in the doorways of their homes.
When l\ast visited Sardinia in 1950, after malaria had
been eradicated, the village children everywhere seemed
to be playing vigorously, kicking balls and romping about
in a normal healthy manner, with rosy cheeks and with¬
out swollen bellies, a vivid and striking contrast that left
no doubt in me about the beneficial effects of malaria
eradication.
"In the same year I visited Oristano, in Western Sar¬
dinia. This marshy area had been so malarious that It
gave rise to a local proverb: 'Chi va al Oristano resta al
Oristano (Who goes to Oristano stays in Oristano)'. Here
Mussolini carried out a huge 'bonification' that failed
because the drainage did not stop malaria transmission;
the land could not be profitably farmed because local and
imported labourers rapidly «became incapacitated by mala¬
ria. But in 1950, malaria had been eradicated and pros¬
perous farmers were the rule in this area. In fact, later
in the year I was told that the successful harvest had creat¬
ed several 'lire millionaires'. There was no room for
doubt about the economic benefits of malaria eradication."
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
IRAN
Mobile brigades strike
at a village scourge
WHO Photos by Philip Bouca-:
The world malaria eradication campaign is based on the mosquito's
habit of resting on interior walls after he has fed on someone's blood,
and on the possibility of spraying those walls with "residual" insecti¬
cides that will kill most of the mosquitos settling on them over a period
of several months. In this way, the chain of infection can be interrupted
(the mosquito becomes infected by biting an infected person and passes
on the disease by biting a healthy person). Above, member of a malaria
eradication team working in Iran takes a mosquito from a wall which
was sprayed with DDT insecticide ten days previously. The insect
will be studied in the Kaserun Malaria Centre where research is being
made into mosquito resistance to insecticides. Right, and above
right, Iranians watch an anti-malaria team at work in their village.,
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1960
CHILDREN ARE
HARDEST HIT
Malaria strikes first at a country's most precious resource, its young
children, and the disease is actually held responsible for I 0% to 15%
of Infant mortality. Above, a boy of the Gourjii tribe in Iran, is exa¬
mined by the visiting malaria specialist. Father and mother reassure
their son; the doctor can make him well again. Below, the case of
this little Iranian girl is recorded during campaign now in operation.
WHO Photos by Philip Boucas
Ft.
Mr*;-
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
WHO Photo by Philip Boucas
At first sight, it seems like a
straightforward fight between
man and mosquito.
The female of the Anopheles
, mosquito bites a malaria suf¬
ferer and sucks up the malaria
parasite together with his blood. Two
weeks later she is able to pass on the infec¬
tion by biting a healthy person.
To break the chain of infection, therefore,
all that is needed is to kill the mosquito
before the malaria parasite has had time to
develop within its body and become a
danger for the next person bitten.
The whole theory of malaria eradication
is based on the mosquito's habit of resting
on interior walls after it has fed on
someone's blood, and on the possibility
of spraying those walls with "residual"
insecticides that will kill all the mosquitos
settling on them over a period of several
months. Yet in actual practice, unbeliev¬
ably intricate problems arise.
The world-wide campaign to stamp out
malaria is aimed at protecting twelve
hundred million human beings,
widely different in their way of life and
habits. The majority live in villages diffi¬
cult to reach and far from any main roads.
Such people regard as intruders those who
come to spray the walls of their homes. In
some places the houses have no walls, only
a primitive roof. In others, the mosquito
does not settle on the walls, but prefers
to go and digest the blood of its victims
in some outdoor retreat away from the
houses. Elsewhere the mosquito bites only
outside. It may happen that the mosquito
is irritated by the presence of the insecticide
and learns to avoid it, or else does not
settle long enough for the poison to take
effect.
A still more serious problem is that of
resistance to the insecticide. It was this
that prompted the decision of the WHO
Member Governments at the Eighth World
Health Assembly in Mexico City in 1955
to declare all-out war on malaria. It had
become imperative to stamp out the disease
from the world before all the species of
12
OUTWITTING
THE WILY
ANOPHELES
malaria-carrying mosquitos would develop
resistance to the insecticides used.
Almost everywhere until then, the fight
against malaria had been carried on in a
spirit of optimism. The spraying of the
inside walls of houses with insecticides went
on without undue haste; when one village
had been done, the workers moved on to
the next. More and more districts were
gradually being protected against the
disease. The work went on, slowly but
steadily, the idea being that with per¬
severance and plenty of time it would
sooner or later be possible to treat all the
malarial regions of the earth.
It was in 1951 that the cry of alarm
first went up: "The insecticide we are using
is no longer active!" This was the first
counter-attack; the mosquito was putting up
resistance. At first resistance was assumed
to be the result of the mosquito becoming
accustomed to the insecticide as is the case
with alcoholics or drug-addicts whose
intake of alcohol or drugs is constantly
increasing and yet produces less and less
effect. The mosquitos too, seemed to
become inured to bigger doses of insec¬
ticide, which at last failed to kill them.
They appeared to have "acquired" im¬
munity.
Out of this situation was born the idea
of world-wide malaria eradication. It was
decided to replace piecemeal campaigns by
total war. The operation, it was realized,
must be completed while the insecticide
continued to kill and before the hitherto
sporadic resistance became general.
This resistance was believed to be due
to spraying at insufficient strength, thus
giving the mosquitos a chance to grow
accustomed to the insecticide. The essence
of the eradication policy was therefore to
make an all-out effort to engage in mass
slaughter of the malaria-carrying mosquitos
for the length of time required to cure the
existing malaria victims and eliminate the
infection. After that, even if the mosquitos
came back, there would no longer be any
infection for them to spread.
If the idea had ever been entertained
that it might be possible to eliminate once
and for all the malaria-carrying species of
mosquitos, it was now abandoned. The
mosquito had given its answer.
Then it was the turn of the entomologists,
the geneticists, and the biochemists to
launch their counter-attack, and this time
the battle was engaged in the calm
atmosphere of the laboratories.
Mosquitos take very kindly to life in
confinement. From all over the world,
mosquito eggs, tiny grey specks, are sent
by post in boxes or in ordinary envelopes,
to the famous Ross Institute of Tropical
Medicine in London. Twenty-four hours
later the eggs hatch out, and the wriggling
larvae that emerge are fed, one item of
their diet being baby-food in powder form,
the same that builds bonny British babies.
In a week's time the aduUs begin to fly,
in cages of very fine netting. The males
are fed on sugar, the females on blood
which is sometimes taken from an ento¬
mologist's forearm but more frequently
from the shaved belly of a guinea-pig.
The mosquitos are then exposed to
insecticides, and those that resist are
separated from those that do not. The
next step is mating: "resisters" are mated
with "resisters", "non-resisters" with "non-
resisters", and then "resisters" with "non-
resisters". Some species of mosquitos
refuse to mate in captivity, and for them
a few entomologists have succeeded in
carrying out artificial insemination.
rom these couples come new families,
I which may be resisters, non-resisters
or hybrids, each reacting in their own
way to the' various insecticides to which
they are exposed. Scores of generations
are studied in this way, and their behaviour
is carefully noted.
This patient, meticulous research work
has made it possible for entomologists and
geneticists to determine with some accuracy
the nature of this phenomenon of
resistance.
Mosquitos do not acquire resistance, they
are born with it; in fact it can now be
affirmed that even before the residual
insecticides were invented, some individual
mosquitos were already "resisters". They
had in them the genes of resistance, and
were protected even against insecticides that
were still in the future.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1960
In the all-out war to kill off malaria-bearing
mosquitos, entomologists, geneticists and
biochemists are helping to launch a counter¬
attack to the resistance which mosquitos ¡tit
showing to insecticides. Far left, in the Rosa
Institute of Tropical Medicine, London, mos¬
quitos are exposed to insecticides, their
resistance is studied and new generations are
bred for further research. Left, in Communi¬
cable Disease Centre of U.S. Public Health
Service, insects are exposed to radiation beams
from Cobalt 60 Chamber during similar
studies. Such patient, meticulous research
work helps to determine the nature of the
mosquitos' resistance. Below, in a Philippines
village, health team prepares to spray walls
of houses where mosquitos settle after feeding.
WHO Photo by Homer Page
It has now been established beyond
doubt that at first the insecticide killed off
the susceptible mosquitos. The remainder,
the resisters, all survived and multiplied,
producing a whole new population of
mosquitos gradually less and less affected
by the lethal properties of the insecticide.
The scientists then set about finding out
something more about the mechanism
of resistance. In the case of a parti¬
cular insecticide they discovered that, for¬
tunately for the mosquito and unfortuna¬
tely for us, its organism contains an enzyme
which sets about altering the chemical com¬
position of the insecticide by dissociating
the atoms which make the substance toxic.
The insecticide manufacturers were inform¬
ed of this discovery, and their chemists
are now trying to develop an insecticide
which will become more effective when
acted upon by the enzyme in the mosqui¬
to's organism.
There are unfortunately other insecticide
troubles besides mosquito resistance. For
instance the walls to be sprayed may inter¬
fere with the action of the insecticide.
There are walls which soak up the
insecticide and prevent it from doing its
lethal work, and there are walls which
decompose it and render it harmless. Then
there is the good housewife, anxious to
keep her house clean, who whitewashes or
papers her walls, thus covering up the
insecticide.
All these factors have to be taken
carefully into account in organizing a world
antimalaria campaign. Every detail must
be watched and every eventuality guarded
against. This calls for a thorough know¬
ledge of the mosquito and its reactions to
the various insecticides, a careful choice
of the insecticide to be used, the precise
determination of the dosage required, and
so on.
The results of laboratory research should
make it possible to get round most of
these difficulties. By careful preliminary
studies costly mistakes can be avoided and
the road can be smoothed towards final
eradication.
WHO
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
WAS ANCIENT GREECE
VANQUISHED BY MALARIA?
WHO photo by K. Rafaelidis
Only when the last case has been tracked down and treated and the possibility of infection has ceased
to exist will the earth be truly rid of malaria. Migrants, who are counted in millions, present a
tricky problem. Ifj they carry the malaria parasite in their bloodstream they may reinfect areas
that have been cleared. Above, a some of the dwellers in nomad encampment near Skala, Greece.
I as the real enemy which caused the fall of
ancient Greece the malaria mosquito, whose
ravages so weakened the country's inhabi¬
tants that its frontiers were left defenceless
in the face of threatening enemies? This is
a hypothesis of Professor G.D. Belios, head
of Greece's antimalaria services.
"Greece has been a prey to the disease for more than
two thousand years," he says, "'and it has left deep scars
on the country.
"If we read the legends of Hercules, We find references
to schemes of land improvement through the draining
of marshes. For instance, there was the Hydra of the
Lernaean marshes Iwhich worked havoc among the popu¬
lation and the flocks. Again, Hercules succeeded in
cleaning the Augean stables by changing the course of
a river.
"Nevertheless, malaria was less prevalent in ancient
Greece than it was just before modem eradication cam¬
paigns Were launched. Changes have occurred in geo¬
graphical and probably also meteorological conditions.
The forests were much more extensive and the mountain
slopes were not as naked and barren as they loofk today;
the ground was more evenly watered, heavy rains did not
produce raging torrents, the temperature was less variable,
the land ¡was extensively cultivated and waterworks had
been constructed. Finally, the rules of hygiene that were
14
strictly observed in the Greece of those days helped to
keep the inhabitants in good health."
Professor Belios thinks it conceivable, however, that
malaria ultimately weakened the resistance of the soldiers
of ancient Greece, so that her frontiers were laid open
to the invader. Her institutions collapsed, the water¬
works fell into ruin, agriculture was neglected, and the
fertile plains gradually changed into barren wastes, until
at last the country which had led the world was plunged
into long centuries of darkness.
1938 : I million cases
1958 : twelve hundred
Greece, once the most malaria-ridden country in Eu¬
rope, is today an advance post in the world war
against this disease. It was the scene of the first
internationally-supported large-scale operations involving
the use of the all-powerful DDT. From Greece came the
first proof that the interruption of spraying operations
did not necessarily mean that malaria would reoccupy the
land. It was also in Greece that resistance to insecticides
was first observed in mosquitos.
"In 1938 we had nearly a million cases of malaria, and
ten thousand people died of the disease; in 1958 we had
twelve hundred cases and not a single death, although
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
our population has increased by two million1", says Pro¬
fessor Belios.
"Between 1930 and 1938, malaria was costing us fifty
million dollars a year in working days lost, hospital
expenses, drugs at that time we were importing thirty
tons of quinine a year. At present our antimalaria ser¬
vices do not cost more than eight hundred thousand
dollars yearly.
"Greece's national income showed an increase of more
than 75 per cent over the years 1950 to 1956, and although
the successful antimalaria drive is not the only reason
it has certainly been an important factor.
"The virtual disappearance of malaria has had a consi¬
derable effect on the general mortality rate in Greece,
which is seven per thousand today as compared with
seventeen per thousand in 1921. Infant mortality has
dropped from 135 per thousand in 1931 to 40 today.
"The average height of our recruits nowadays is 4 to 5
centimetres above what it was twenty years ago."
The campaign against malaria in Greece was launched
with a great flourish in 1946. While vast areas of marsh
and ricefields were being systematically covered with
larvicide sprayed from 17 aeroplanes, antimalaria squads
were visiting some 5,000 out of the country's 11,000 villages
to treat the insides of the houses with insecticides.
Mosquitos, flies, fleas, bugs and lice died off as if by
magic. There was a marked drop in the number of cases
of dysentery, a disease often spread by flies. Where fields
of olive trees had been sprayed with insecticides from
the air, the year's crop showed a 25 per cent, increase.
"'Our wildest dreams were coming true before our
eyes", says Professor Belios. "It was more than we had
ever dared to hope for. But in 1951 it became difficult
to obtain the insecticide, mainly because of the Korean
war, and we had to discontinue spraying."
It was this combination of circumstances which led to
The Unesco Courier. April 1960
the discovery that stopping insecticide spraying did not
necessarily mean the return of malaria. Greece was to
serve as a precious example five years later when the prin¬
ciples of malaria eradication were laid down, comprising
two main stages: an all-out attack on the mosquitos that
carry the disease, and then consolidation through syste¬
matic tracking down of the remaining cases.
Laughter in the village
and money in the bank
Today malaria has been practically driven out of
Greece, so effective are the operations of the
country's antimalaria service, both on the mainland
and on the countless islands of the archipelago. Case-
spotting teams are doing house-to-house visiting in
thousands of village, while private practitioners, teachers,
mayors and priests regard it as their duty to report suspect¬
ed cases. The Ministry's 1,100 rural and communal dispen¬
saries also play their part. All patients admitted to hospi¬
tal undergo routine blood tests, and twenty-four laborato¬
ries are devoting all their time to blood testing. Insec¬
ticide spraying has been reduced to an absolute minimum.
That is how Greece has almost rid herself of a scourge
which has had a tragic influence on her destiny.
Nowadays in the southern Péloponnèse there are great
rice plantations and the cotton fields at Skala are vast.
Only ten years ago half this land lay fallow, and mala¬
ria was general. Now at harvest time the village streets
are alive with laughter and high spirits, the bank stays
open day and night to pay for the crops, and there is
a big fair in the olive groves to which the country people
come to lay in their winter supplies.
In 1959 there was only one case of malaria in the whole
of the Skala district, a soldier back from military service
) F. Barzilay
Once the most malaria-ridden country in Europe, Greece is today an advance post in the world war against this disease. After being a prey to malaria
for more than 2,000 years, Greece is now virtually rid of the scourge. But case-spotting teams still do house-to-house visits in thousands of villages
like the one shown here, and over 1,100 rural and communal dispensaries play their part in the complete eradication of malaria from the country.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
who had somehow slipped through the malaria defence
network. The antimalaria service is very much on the
alert at Skala. Since spraying operations finished, the
mosquitos have come back in the same numbers as before,
ready to act as carriers of any malaria that may appear.
The greatest care is therefore necessary.
It was at Skala, too, and in Nauplia a little further
north, that mosquito resistance to insecticides appeared
for the very first time. This was in October 1951 when
spraying was still going on; mosquitos began to be seen
again in the houses, and the country folk blamed the
spraying teams for not doing their work properly.
While on a visit to London, Professor Belios went to see
the experts at the Ross Institute, but they at first refus¬
ed to believe that the insecticide had ceased to act. The
facts soon compelled them to admit that the Greek mos¬
quitos had won a real victory. Fortunately it proved
possible to replace the insecticide by others which were
still effective for a certain period. Then followed the
attack on the malaria parasite by tracking down and
treating the remaining sick people.
Since that October day in 1951 some 19 species of mala¬
ria-carrying mosquitos in different parts of the world
have developed resistance to one or other of the insec¬
ticides used. Up to now, however, only three species have
proved resistant, to a greater or lesser degree, to all the
insecticides that can be used in the world campaign
against malaria.
Since October 1951, laboratory research has been speed¬
ed up so that before launching an eradication campaign,
antimalaria services can obtain accurate information as
to how their enemies, the mosquitos, will react to the
insecticides that are to be used against them.
Photos © F. Barzilay
With the virtual disappearance of malaria there has been a vast impro¬
vement in the life of people in the Greek countryside. In some areas
there are now great rice plantations and vast cotton fields where only
ten years ago half the land lay fallow, and malaria was generalone
million cases in 1938. The country's general mortality rate has dropped
by nearly two-thirds as compared with 1921 ; it was then 1 7 per 1,000.
THE GOAL FOR EUROPE :
MALARIA OUSTED BY 1962
IN Europe, does malaria still matter? It this not one
of those outmoded diseases long banished from the
continent? In a good many countries it is true that
malaria has been driven out, in some at great cost.
The honours list includes Italy, the Netherlands, France,
Hungary, Poland, Czechoslovakia, the Ukraine and
Byelorussia.
Around the shores of the Mediterranean, the battle
is still sharply contested. Eleven countries in the Euro¬
pean Region of WHO, which includes Morocco, Algeria
and Turkey, are still in varying degrees infested with
malaria. A severe problem is faced in the three countries
named where great efforts will be needed to get rid of
the infection. On the European continent, the situation
is more favourable: it is expected that by 1962 malaria
will have disappeared for good.
As little as a decade ago, malaria still claimed hun¬
dreds of thousands of victims in certain areas where 'it
had reigned supreme for centuries. In Rumania, Spain,
Portugal, the Soviet Union, Greece and other countries,
malariologists and the governments that supported their
work are on the eve of a victory that will bring great
benefit not only to the national populations but to
Europe as a whole.
The matter is indeed one of concern to Europe, for
both the mosquito that transmits malaria and the man
who carries the malaria parasite in his blood can easily
cross a national boundary and reintroduce the infection
in areas laboriously cleared of it. This is one reason
for pursuing the battle with vigour and ridding the conti¬
nent in its entirety of the danger as soon as possible.
Mopping up the last cases is the task facing European
malaria workers today.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1960
U.S.S.R. SEES VICTORY AHEAD
IN 40 YEAR WAR ON MALARIA
by L.J. Bruce-Chwatt
BuRiNG the nineteenth century and the early part
of the twentieth, malaria was one of the main
endemic diseases in Russia, occurring through¬
out the country but being particularly
prevalent in the Caucasus, in Transcaucasia,
in Central Asia, and along the lower Volga.
The annual mortality in the garrisons stationed during
the latter part of the nineteenth century along the
northern shore of the Black Sea and near the Persian
frontier amounted to as much as 25 %. It was estimated
that 5,000,000 people were affected annually in the years
1890-1900, and at least 3,500,000 during World War I.
In the wake of that war, the huge movements of popu¬
lation that took place, and the general lowering of eco¬
nomic and social standards, led to the greatest malaria
epidemic of modern times in Europe, which ravaged a
large part of the TJ.S.S.R. in 1922-1923. There were 600,000
fatal cases of malaria in each year, and in parts of Cen¬
tral Asia, the Caucasus and the Volga basin 75-100 %
of the population were infected. One report claimed that
not less than 12,000,000 cases were involved.
In the early twenties an Institute of Protozoology and
Chemotherapy (now the Institute of Malaria, Medical
Parasitology, and Helminthology) was set up in Moscow,
and rural antimalaria stations were created in growing
numbers. By 1930 the situation had improved: public
health measures in general, and malaria control in parti¬
cular, were more widely undertaken and better executed,
and institutes of tropical medicine had been established
in a number of places.
Apart from 1934-1936, when there was a temporary
increase especially in Central Asia and the
Caucasus, the morbidity rate for Malaria fell
gradually year by year, until in 1939 it was the lowest
that had ever been recorded in the U.S.S.R. The Second
World War caused a temporary setback; there was,
almost inevitably, a great increase in the number of cases
in the devastated areas, particularly in the Ukraine and
Byelorussia.
In the post-war years public health services were
reorganized and malaria control tightened up. In 1951
a national antimalaria programme was included in the
Five-Year Plan, with striking results: whereas in 1952
...the number of cases of malaria in the U.S.S.R. had been
183,603, in 1958 it was 4,678. In 1952 the concept of eli¬
mination of malaria as a mass disease was adopted, and
by 1955 it had become obvious that total eradication could
be achieved by 1960.
The comprehensive programme for the elimination of
malaria as a mass disease from the U.S.S.R. has been
carried out with an impressive drive and determination
that could not have been possible without adequate
medical, scientific, and auxiliary personnel. In 1956 no
less than 2,780,000 persons, or about 1.3 % of the entire
population, worked in one capacity or another in the
field of public health; there was therefore no shortage
of staff for malaria elimination.
From the outset the programme was based on the
existing wide network of dispensaries, health centres,
polyclinics, and the like. Notification of cases of malaria
had been compulsory in some parts of the country ever
This account of malaria eradication in the U.S.S.R. is condensed
from an article by Dr. Bruce-Chwatt, Chief, Planning, Division of
Malaria Eradication, W.B.O., which appeared in the "Bulletin of the
World Heallth Organization".
since 1921. It was extended to other areas in 1947-1948,
and registration of cases, made on a much more stringent
procedure, has covered the entire country since 1951.
A comprehensive training programme was put into
effect. In addition to chemiotherapy and spraying, other
available methods of control were pressed into use, tech¬
nical guidance being given by the Moscow Institute of
Malaria, Medical Parasitology, and Helminthology and by
the regional institutes. An outstanding characteristic of
the whole programme is the careful planning of anti¬
malaria measures in relation to both general and specific
economic and social development. Public health educa¬
tion has received much emphasis, and is carried out by
meetings, discussions groups, pamphlets, posters and films.
On the basis of general directives sent out by the
Ministry of Health, the planning of antimalaria
measures within each district is done by the district
medical unit, with the advice of the corresponding health
centre.
The medical follow-up and drug administration are
carried out by the hospitals, .polyclinics, dispensaries and
other health units. Small-scale insecticidal measures are
carried out by local health units, with the co-operation
of other health organizations if necessary. Large-scale
spraying is always done by the district health centres.
Much attention is paid to the blood examination of
all fever cases reporting for medical attention. Medical
and paramedical personnel are often reminded of the
possibility of malaria in cases of obscure fever, and the
population is encouraged to go to medical aid centres for
the diagnosis and treatment of even minor aliments. All
overt cases of malaria and all persons found to be posi¬
tive for malaria are registered. These registrations are
sent monthly to the provincial health authority.
In addition to passive surveillance of this kind, there
is active surveillance during the transmission season in
all areas where malaria used to be common. It is carried
out by district health visitors or voluntary drug distri¬
butors, visits being made every five or ten days, accord¬
ing to the size of the district. All local inhabitants or
visitors with fever or vague general symptoms have their
blood examined for malaria parasites, but no immediate
treatment is given.
This work is often carried out by non-medical
personnel, such as members of the Red Cross.
Mass surveys of the population are also occa¬
sionally carried out. Some surveys cover individuals who
are known to have had malaria during previous years,
who have had undiagnosed fevers, or have come from
malarious areas; but in smaller localities the whole popu¬
lation is examined.
The results of this intensive programme have been
spectacular. In the largest administrative unit, the
Russian Socialist Federated Soviet Republic, the trend
of morbidity can be assessed by taking the 1940 figures
as 100%. After a peak of 103 % in 1945, the percentage
fell to 55 in 1948, to 42 in 1949, to 19 in 1950, to 8 in 1951,
to 4 in 1952, to 1.5 in 1954, and to 0.25 in 1956.
According to recent information supplied to WHO, the
total number of cases of malaria in the U.S.S.R. was 5,097
CONT'D ON PAGE- 32
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
PATROL
FOOT OF
World Health Organization expert,
T.S. Maclnnes, sets out on a ten-day
march through the Himalayan foot¬
hills to organize supply lines for
Nepal's malaria eradication campaign.
His reconnaissance trek begins in
the village of Pokhra (right) in the
shadow of giant Mount Anapurna.
With village leaders (above left) he
discusses the forthcoming campaign
and arranges storage space for medi¬
cal supplies. Mealtime halts (left) find
Maclnnes and his party surrounded by
a fascinated audience of youngsters.
WHO Photos by Eric Schwab
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courler. April 1960
-". ^m/. "-;' -,'
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
#a*ö MALARIA
PATROL
^mwm
4K-
X
(Continued)
From the aerodrome at Pokhra,
Maclnnes's team and its porters
set out through the local rice
fields and cross one of the
swiftly-flowing rivers that race
out of the foothills (photos left).
Below, during its 150-mile march
to Khatmandu, the heavily-
laden party approaches some
of the terraced cultivation
strips of a Nepalese village.
e& "
^ '£
Ü ÍSÍS3S
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1960
WHO Photos by Eric Schwab
JOURNEY'S END. A busy scene outside the temple of Hanuman Doka.in Khatmandu, capital of Nepal.
Here Maclnnes reported on his mission to the H. Q. of the Nepal Malaria Eradication Organization.
During his trek he was able to brief village social workers and education officers on the campaign.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
BATTERY OF NEW DRUGS
JOINS BATTLE WITH WORLD'S
OST COSTLY DISEASE
WHO photo by Paul Almasy
In a village in Liberia, the doctor has dis¬
covered many malaria cases and is distribut¬
ing anti-malaria pills which children and
grown-ups obediently swallow on the spot.
There is a whole battery of drugs
against malaria. Some are preventive
drugs, taken as a protective measure
by visitors to malarious regions, and some
are effective in treating malaria sufferers.
One might then ask whether the present
campaign for the eradication of malaria is
on the right lines with its complicated
insecticide spraying operations, its delicate
laboratory work, the enormous transport
problem involved, and the costly army of
workers needed.
Would it not be simpler to distribute
drugs to everyone living in malarious areas?
In this way malaria sufferers would be
cured and others protected. "No", say the
experts.
In the first place, the experts say that
the antimalarial drugs only keep the blood
parasite at bay for a short time; scarcely
one week, in fact. This means that an
immense and very efficient organization
would be needed for the regular distribution
of drugs over vast territories with widely-
scattered, and often nomadic, inhabitants.
Then the population would soon tire of
coming, so often for treatment.
Nevertheless, the antimalarial drugs play
an extremely important and indeed essential
role in the eradication campaign, particu¬
larly in the final phases when the last
foci of infection must be mopped up.
Here again a problem arises that only
the laboratories can solve. They
must try to produce a drug which
maintains its efficacy for a long enough
period and which can be given in a single
dose at long intervals.
The scientists are therefore directing their
efforts to finding a drug that can be
injected. One advantage is that some peo¬
ple may feel more confidence in a treat¬
ment that hurts than in tablets which are
merely swallowed without discomfort.
Another is that an injection is more diffi¬
cult to evade during mass campaigns which
systematically treat the whole population.
For centuries, powdered cinchona bark
(which became quinine) was used to cure
malaria.
The discovery of modern antimalarial
drugs was an indirect consequence of the
two world wars. The first synthetic
22
products were obtained in the laboratory
between 1924 and 1927 by the Germans
who had been working on the problem since
their quinine supplies were cut off by the
war. From 1939 to 1945 it was the Allies
who manufactured products to replace the
cinchona bark which no longer arrived
from Japanese-occupied Java.
Through a strange series of coincidences
in the inter-war period, research work on
synthetic antimalarials opened the way
to further progress in two apparently unre¬
lated fields: the behaviour of the malaria
parasite in the human organism, and the
treatment of syphilitic nervous disorders.
In order to test the effectiveness of the
new drugs, European research workers
needed malaria patients. These were rare
in Europe and understandably the few
attending a hospital preferred to be given
treatment rather than be used as guinea-
pigs. The solution was to find people
willing to be inoculated with malaria. The
neuro-syphilitic cases provided the answer.
This story goes back to the time of
Hippocrates who, five centuries before
Christ, recognized that violent fevers
sometimes had a beneficial effect on
sufferers from certain diseases. Galen,
seven centuries later, described the cure
of an epileptic after an attack of quartan
fever. In the nineteenth century, some
observers found that certain mental patients
were returned to sanity after an access of
fever (malaria, typhoid fever). In 1917, an
Austrian psychiatrist for the first time ino¬
culated malaria into nine patients suffering
from general paralysis, and cured three.
It was in England that an Indian sailor
from Madagascar disembarked in 1925,
shivering with malaria, and went for treat¬
ment to the Horton Hospital, Epsom. He
was treated, but a little of his blood
infected with the malaria parasite, Plasmo¬
dium vivax, was carefully preserved. This
strain of the parasite was maintained in the
laboratory, and over a period of thirty
years it has been used to infect sixty-eight
thousand mosquitos, which in turn have
infected ten thousand neurosyphilitic
patients suffering from general paralysis.
Many of these patients have left the Horton
Hospital, cured. The others, by consenting
to be first infected with and then cured of
malaria, have made it possible to determine
the limitations of quinine, to test certain
modern drugs and, finally, to establish the
fact the liver plays an important rôle in the
development of the malaria parasite.
With the discovery of penicillin, the
queen of all drugs against syphilis, cases of
general paralysis have almost disappeared
and consequently there is no further need
for malaria therapy of neurosyphilitic cases,
and the antimalarial drugs can no longer
be tested in this way.
Nevertheless, some experiments with
these drugs are still continuing with the
help of human volunteers, particularly in
Italy, Rumania and the United States.
Although control of malaria with drugs
alone has not been found practicable in
most of the territories in which eradication
campaigns are being conducted, quite a
new method is being employed in Brazil.
The Brazilian eradication campaign was
making slow progress in the vast,
impenetrable forests of the Amazon
basin. Three million people live there un¬
der the menace of malaria. Most of their
houses have no walls and consist only of
a roof over four supports. The mosquitos,
after biting, go outside in the open to rest.
Many nomads move about the country
according to season and availability of agri¬
cultural work. Spraying offers therefore
little chance of interrupting transmission of
the disease.
A Brazilian specialist, Dr. Mario Pinotti,
conceived the idea of adding an anti¬
malarial drug to the cooking salt used at
every meal by the people of the Amazon
zone in the same way as iodine is added
to the salt in regions where goitre is present
in endemic fortm.
The first experiment was made in the
State of Para. Two zones were created:
an experimental zone containing nine
hundred inhabitants, and a control zone
with four hundred inhabitants. After forty
days' use of the antimalarial salt there were
only two cases among the nine hundred
inhabitants of the experimental zone. One
was a newly-born, breast-fed baby, and the
other a stranger who had only been in the
zone for the last three days.
In view of these results, the World Health
Organization has asked scientists in the
U.S.A. to do further research. WHO is also
proposing to help several countries to
try out this new method, which seems to
promise good results in areas where classic
spraying operations meet special difficulties.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1960
People sometimes ask what purpose is served by
launching rockets into outer space and how this
can benefit mankind? The answers are that
rocket flights have already helped to solve a
host of scientific problems and are now
throwing light on a number of questions still
awaiting solution. Their greatest importance, however,
lies in the magnificent prospects they open up for the
future. That is Why We feel justified in saying that the
launching of space rockets opens up a new era in the
history of man's conquest of outer space.
All our technical progress and all our civilization are,
in general, closely bound up with our knowledge of
natural laws, that is," laws governing the Universe that
surrounds us. Natural laws cannot be adequately studied
within the narrow walls of our laboratories. For their
proper study we must get out into the boundless expanses
of outer space. Atoms of matter are the same everywhere
but their nature is infinite, with the manifestations
depending on external conditions that can only be partly
reproduced on Earth.
In outer space we find matter in states of great density
and great dispersion. The average density of the white
dwarf stars, for example, is ten thousand times that of
water; such bodies may exist for thousands of millions
of years. The density of interstellar space, on the con¬
trary, is about thirty degrees of magnitude less, being
about one atom to the cubic centimetre.
The temperature of the central regions of the Sun is
about twenty million degrees; at such temperatures
nuclear reactions are set off spontaneously and keep the
Sun's radiation going. The temperature inside the giant
red stars reaches thousands of millions of degrees and
is appropriate for the formation of chemical elements
heavier than hydrogen or helium. Material particles, the
nuclei of elements, mainly of hydrogen, that constitute
the streams of cosmic rays, are accelerated by the mag¬
netic fields of our galaxy to velocities approaching that of
light. All these processes take place in infinite space and
have been going on for a period of time that is, for all
practical purposes, also infinite.
We cannot understand the laws of nature and master
her secrets if we do not study the entire Universe in all
its more important manifestations. Nor can we properly
understand the nature of our Earth if we do not compare
it with related planets, even if only with those that cons¬
titute our own solar system.
So far the only bodies from outer space that have come
into contact with Earth are those meteorites and perhaps
remains of. comet nuclei that have broken through our
atmosphere and reached the Earth's surface without being
fully destroyed. Even ordinary meteors are burned up
in the upper layers of the atmosphere; we can only get
a glimpse of other cosmic bodies at a distance of millions
and millions of miles and, what is more, from the bottom
of an ocean of air.
It is this atmospheric envelope around the Earth that
hampers the study of the Universe. Constant atmospheric
turbulences distort optic images and they blur to such
an extent that really big magnifications cannot be
employed. It has therefore been found possible to observe
finer details of the structure of the solar surface by send¬
ing telescopes up in balloons, if only to a height of 6-10
miles, than it has been possible to do at terrestrial obser¬
vatories, even those located high up in the mountains.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
CONQUEST
OF SPACE
(Continued)
Launched on A October, 1959, a Soviet
Automatic Space Station photographs the
far side of the moon for the first time. Far
right, Soviet vehicle at moment of taking
photograph. On signal from Earth, gas jets
stopped space station's spinning, lined it up
with sun's rays (shown by arrows) and focused
two lenses on moon. Exposed film was
automatically developed. A scanner changed
picture to electric pulses that were sent to
Earth. Right, diagram of flight trajectory.
Official Soviet photos
POSITION. OF THE MOON IN THE END
OF THE ASS'S CKU OF ROTATION
POSITION OF THE MOON
AT THE TIME
OF IT BEING
CIRCUMNAVIGATED
BY THE ASS -
The diffusion of sunlight in the atmosphere in daytime
and the luminosity of the high ionosphere at night
prevent the observation of such faint objects as the solar
corona at a great enough distance from the Sun or the
many indistinct nebulae that have recently been
discovered by the use of rockets. The Earth's magnetic
field prevents the penetration of primary cosmic rays
from outer space and in places where they do break
through they are fully absorbed by the upper layers of
the atmosphere so that we can only observe their
secondary effect.
It is equally true that the particularly active and, con¬
sequently, the most interesting radiations from the Sun
and other cosmic bodies are completely absorbed by those
upper layers of the atmosphere that affect them most
strongly. Until recently it has been possible to observe
the Universe from Earth only through a '"window"' limited
to radiations to which the eye is receptive.
It is only during the past few decades that another
"window" has been opened through which the much
longer radio waves can be received. The most active
cosmic radiations (which have the very shortest wave¬
lengths) are still beyond the reach of direct observation
however, because they are fully absorbed by the upper
layers of the atmosphere.
All these difficulties disappear once we reach outer
space. Imagine, for example, an astronomical observatory
flying through space as an independent planet. It would
be very easy for it to take samples of interplanetary
matter. What does this matter consist of, what gases and
dusts does it contain? Such a simple test would im¬
mediately solve the still disputed question of the sources
supplying the interplanetary matter which appears to
observers on Earth in the form of zodiacal light (1). If it
is dust it may come from comets and, partially, from
asteroids as the product of their constant disintegration
and would indicate the intensity of that process. If it is
gas it is emitted mainly from the solar atmosphere and
characterises the corpuscular radiation of the Sun. The
answers, obtained by a rocket observatory, will enable us
to check up on our conceptions of the nature of inter¬
planetary space and give them greater precision and, at
the same time, to draw new conclusions on the processes
that are going on within our solar system.
(1) A tract of nebulous light sometimes visible before sunrise or
after sunset extending along the zodiac on each side of the sun in
the form of an elongated ellipse.
Even a simple glance at the Sun or a planet through a
rocket telescope will tell us a great deal. We shall be able
to see the long streams of the solar corona that at present
can only be seen during a total eclipse and of which
only the part closest to the Sun is visible at other times
through a special instrument. Outside the atmosphere it
will be possible to see, against the black background of
space, how the corona gradually changes into zodiacal
light and begins to spread out along the ecliptic. The
aspect of the solar corona at various distances from the
Sun's surface will enable us to judge the extent to which
it is supplied with matter in the form of dust gathered
from interplanetary space and to what extent it is made
up of gases radiated from the Sun itself.
Space camera surveys the lunar 'seas'
Asimple spectral photograph of the Sun's corona and
other solar envelopes would enable us to register the
basic radiations of hydrogen and espacially of other
more heavy elements connected with transitions at the
lowest energy levels, that are outside the range of
observers on Earth. It is precisely these radiations, possible
only at corona temperatures of several million degrees,
that have the greatest effect on the upper layers of the
atmosphere and condition their considerable extension
and high temperature. The study of this solar radiation
in the X-ray region of the spectrum will most likely
enable us to understand the nature of the mechanism by
which the Sun influences the Earth and also the mecha¬
nism by which the so-called "flares" and other solar
phenomena arise; they are possibly connected with some
nuclear reactions.
There is also very much that can be explained in the
nature of the planets that form the solar system.
For the first time in history it has been proved possible
to obtain a picture of the hidden side of the "Moon and
to transmit it back to Earth from a telephoto installation
mounted on an automatic interplanetary station. The
image so obtained is clear enough to show even such
details as the central peaks inside the craters that have
been named Lomonosov and Tsiolkovsky. This is an
achievement that does credit to our scientists working in
the field of electronics. Since the camera was between
the Sun and the Moon at the time the photographs were
taken, the relief of the lunar surface is not discernible.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1960
The following features distinguish the hidden side from
the earthward side of the Moon. On the earthward side
many of the craters have bright rays running from them
that are very distinct at full moon; those surrounding
some of the craters are very extensive and clearly marked.
They are always connected with the central peaks in the
craters and, it is believed, with their former volcanic
activity. Not a sign of any such formation is to be seen
on the other side of the Moon.
The far side of the Moon also seems to be deficient in
those dark patches that are called '"seas" and this is very
informative. The biggest of these "seas" on the earthward
side is the Oceanus Procellarum; the surface directly
opposite on the other side is bright and level with nothing
on it resembling a "sea".
Such a great difference cannot be a matter of chance.
It will be remembered that the Moon is not a perfect
sphere: the earthward side is pulled outwards in the
direction of our planet to a distance of several dozen
kilometres as though it were formed by the hardening of
a gigantic tidal wave. This makes it safe to assume that
the thickness of the lunar crust varies in different parts
of that body. It is of interest to connect this with the
intensity of lunar volcanic processes, in particular with
the process that gave rise to the lunar "seas". At a
certain period in the Moon's development, when the
craters and annular mountains had already taken shape,
large areas of the surface were in a molten state and later
hardened to form "seas" surrounded by high eruptive
formations, the mountain ranges. On the hidden side of
the Moon this process is scarcely noticeable.
A detailed study of this phenomenon will cast much
new light on the development of the Moon's crust; it will
also help towards a better understanding of the evolution
of our planet.
It is rather difficult to give a list of the various problems
that, it will be possible to solve by the use of a space
laboratory since its possibilities are immense. Here on
Earth we usually have to employ telescopes with a
magnification of no more than 300 to 400 diameters on
account of the interference of the atmosphere. Even at
the present level of optics it will be possible to make
telescopes for a cosmic laboratory that have a magnifi¬
cation of tens of thousands of diameters ; this means,
for example, that objects with dimensions of about ten
metres will be clearly visible on the Moon. It follows
from this that it will be possible to investigate the smal
lest features such as the crater mouths on the peaks in
the centre of lunar ring formations.
And how much that is new will be discovered by similar
observations of other planets, especially Mars! Schiapa-
relli and Lovell, who made their observations at the turn
of the century, worked under the best conditions available
on Earth. They discovered the canals on Mars and
believed them to be artificial engineering works. But
there are no canals in the sense in which they understood
them, and no regular formations ' of any sort on Mars.
There is something else there, something connected with
constant, systematic change. If a telescope a hundred
times more powerful than those in use today could be
turned on Mars many new facts concerning that planet
would come to light.
Will man migrate to distant worlds?
Even a simple photograph of Mars's spectrum simul¬
taneously in its infra-red and ultra-violet regions will
provide an ultimate solution to the problem of
whether oxygen is present or not. This may be proved by
studying the ozone bands, which cannot be done from
Earth on account of the mighty bands of ozone at great
heights in Earth's atmosphere. If there is oxygen on Mars
there should also be ozone, the latter being much easier to
detect than oxygen because of its absorbent qualities in
appropriate wavelengths. In order to "see" this ozone
we have to get rid on the interference of Earth's
atmosphere, we have to get beyond its bounds.
Everything that has been said so far is based on the
assumption that our cosmic observatory will conduct
observations at distances of millions of miles in the same
way as terrestrial observers. But motion in the practically
empty interplanetary space within the Sun's gravitational
field as, for example, the motion of all planets including
the Earth, does not involve the expenditure of any form
of energy, requiring only time, and one may easily ima¬
gine the possibility of approaching close to one of the
planets and even landing on it.
Is it worth while dreaming of the migration of man to
other planets in our own or some other system? We do
not think there is any need for it. Our planet is the best
for us in all the Universe. We have inherited it from
many past generations and we must try to make it better
for all mankind!
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
THE STORY
OF PLACE
NAMES
by Mario Pei
Professor of Romance Languages,
Columbia University, New York
TALE OF
THREE CITIES
STRASBOURG, today dominated by
its soaring cathedral spire (630 feet),
was once more famous for its streets. In
the early centuries of the Christian era,
Germanic tribes called it Stratarum Bur-
gum (the community of streets) from which
its present name comes. BAGHDAD,
(right), today capital and largest city of
Iraq, is said to be named after a holy man.
Dad ("The Garden of Dad"). Founded in
762 by the Caliph Al-Mansur, the city
became a centre of culture and learning
and is today, as always, a great trading
centre. MONTEVIDEO (opposite page),
capital of Uruguay, has a strange meaning:
"a mountain saw I." This name was be¬
stowed by Magellan in 1 520, when he
anchored at the mouth of the La Plata
River, and saw a single hill rising high
out of the midst of universally flat lands.
Photos, taken from "La Découverte Aérienne du
Monde" published by Horizons de France, Paris, are
copyright. Strasbourg (Spehner), Baghdad (Aero-
films Ltd.), Montevideo (Government Information
Office, Montevideo).
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
In the story of mankind, When other sources of
information are lacking, important clues to the move¬
ments of races of men and the spread and progress of
civilizations can often be found in the names of places
and peoples. Such names reflect the history, culture and
-thought of the people who inhabit a country, as well as
that country's development.
If we let our imagination run back to prehistoric times,
we can visualize small groups of wanderers, still living in
a semi-savage state, but with each group speaking some
sort of primitive language, out of which will evolve the
great languages of yesterday, today and tomorrow. While
these languages are different, they all contain one word,
a word that signifies something without which the tribe
will perish "Water". One group calls water ab, another
says da, a third uses akwa.
As the tribe comes to a promising watercourse, the
headman triumphantly points to the stream and exclaims
"Ab!", and all his followers echo the word. Centuries
later, when all memory of the wandering tribe is lost, its
Word for water will be reflected in the stream's name,
Avon. Another tribe that calls water da bestows that
name upon streams that will later become the Don of
England and Russia, the Danube of the Balkans, while
early Greeks dwelling on the coast will call themselves
Danaoi, "'water people". The akwa tribe will give its name
for water to places like Aquileia in Italy and Aquisgrana
(later Aix or Aachen) in western Germany.
But another group of nomads, of entirely different
language habits, coming across a region of hot, burning,
waterless sands, will bestow upon it their name for "'wide",
"'burned out", sahra, and today the world's largest
desert still bears the name of Sahara.
The process is the same, regardless of race or group.
Many centuries ago, the Anglo-Saxons of England found
a suitable cattle crossing in a river and called it Oxford.
Thousands of years before them, the Greeks had found a
similar passage and called it Bosporus, which is Greek
for "Oxford". The Arabs called their burnt-out region
Sahara; the Papago Indians of the American Southwest
called a region not quite so waterless Arizonac, "'place of
few springs".
But "water" alone was often not deemed sufficient. A
The Unesco Courier. April 1960
more specific word was used, like '"river", as is the case
with India's Ganges. Or an adjective was added, like the
Grande that in Spanish modifies Rio, or the kabir that in
Arabic modifies wadi, turning it into the Guadalquivir
(wadi al kabir) of Spain. Often religious imagery played
a part, as in India's Brahmaputra, the "son of Brahma",
chief god of the Hindu Trinity and creator of the universe,
or the Brazos of Texas, which is short for Brazos de Dios,
"arms of God".
The naming of mountains also lent itself to descriptive
or poetic imagery. On the one hand |we have the Celtic
pen, "head", which enters into the Pennine Mountains of
Britain and the Appennines of Italy, the Sierra Nevada
which means "snowy range", the Caucasus which means
"icegleaming". On the other we have Switzerland's Jung¬
frau ("maiden"), Africa's Ruwenzori ("cloud king"),
Mexico's Popocatepetl ("mountain of he who smokes").
Seas and oceans are latecomers in the race for names.
A name like Mediterranean, or Mare Internum ("Inner
Sea"), as the Romans called it, could have been devised
only after people had sailed around it and discovered
that it is almost entirely surrounded by land. Even
names like Atlantic and Arctic, drawn from mythological
Atlas and from the Great Bear constellation, make their
appearance in historic times, and Pacific is due to the
accident of its having been peaceful at the time of its
discovery in the sixteenth century.
Names of countries, continents and regions were also
largely bestowed in historical times. Continent names are
often the continuators of names originally given to much
smaller land units (Asia, for instance, was in ancient
times merely what we now ,call Asia Minor, and Africa
was restricted to a strip of the North African coast).
Some countries and regions bear names which are des¬
criptive of physical characteristics: Finland, for example,
is Fen-land, a translation of the Finnish Suomi, meaning
'"swamp" or "'marsh"; Poland gets its name from a root
meaning "'flat" or "level", which also appears in the
Slavic Iword for '"field", "meadow" (pole or polje) ; India is
the land of the river Hind or Sind; Panjab is "five rivers";
Dekkan is "'south" or "what lies on the right hand";
Mesopotamia is "between rivers".
Other countries bear the names of the people that
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
PLACE NAMES (Continued)
From Aa to Llanf airpwl Igwyngy llgoger-
ychwyrndrobwll I landysi liogogogoch
settled in them: Gaul, land of the Gauls, turned into
France when the Franks occupied it, (just as Britain,
land of the Britons, later became England, the country
of the Angles). Still other names reflect historical epi¬
sodes: the Soviet Ukraine means "'frontier district", and
refers to the period when it was a no-man's-land between
the Russians and the Turks; Honduras means "'depths",
and was applied at the time of its discovery because its
coast had deep waters that made good anchorages;
Venezuela was named "little Venice" because the explor¬
ers found the people living in villages built over the
water on stilts, something that reminded them of the
canals of Venice.
Then there is the thoroughly historical process of
naming places after individuals,' usually famous ones.
The channel island of Jersey and the American State of
New Jersey take their name from Caesar (Caesarea was
"'Caesar's town") ; so does Zaragoza in Spain, which shows
the addition of Augusta to Caesarea; while the Italian
region of Friuli, northeast of Venice, is Forum Julii, the
"Forum of Julius Caesar", which he fortified in that area
to prevent barbarian invasions of the Italian plain.
Cairo's name came
from outer space
There are many cities that bear the name of Alexander
of Macedón: Alexandria in Egypt and Alessandretta.
or Iskanderun, in Turkey, are two of them (Iskander
is the form assumed by Alexander in Turkish) . Barcelona
bears the name of the Barca or Barak family of Carthage,
to which Hamilcar and Hannibal belonged (Barak, "light¬
ning", was an appropriate name for one who invented the
ancient version of the Blitzkrieg). Constantinople bears
the name of Constantine the Great. France's Orléans
and America's New Orleans are named after the Aurelian
emperors of Rome.
In the Soviet Union, Stalingrad is only one of many
localities that bear Stalin's name. An entire region,
Lotharingia or Lorraine, bears the name of one of Char¬
lemagne's grandsons, Lothaire, who was its ruler. Other
examples are Washington, Christiania, Pretoria, Monro¬
via, Charleroi, Leopoldville, Port Saïd, Gibraltar (the last
is Jebel Tarik, the "Mountain of Tarik", the Moorish
leader who successfully led the invasion of Visigothic
Spain in 711). Among names of countries we have Rho¬
desia, named after Cecil Rhodes, and Bolivia, bearing the
name of Simon Bolivar.
A name that is unique, since it comes from outer space,
is that of Cairo, the Arabic El-Qahirah, "the Victorious
One", which is the Arabic name of the planet Mars,
clearly visible at the time the city Was founded in 970 A.D.
Among the earliest place-names on record are the
ancient name of Egypt, Kern, "the Black", probably
bestowed because of the color of the rich soil of the Nile
valley; Babylon, Bab-Ilu, "the gate of the god"; Jeru¬
salem, the Akkadian Urusalim, "city of the god of peace".
Assyria Was named after the god Assur. Smyrna, the
modern Izmir, has borne its name over three thousand
years; it is said to have been named after an Amazon
warrior-maid. Phoenician Gaddir, oldest town in Europe,
turned into the Roman Carteia and the modern Cádiz.
Strabo, the Greek geographer, calls present-day Afghanis¬
tan by its ancient name of Aryana, "land of the Aryans".
To offset these very ancient place names, we have very
new and modern ones: Canberra, capital of Australia;
Brazilia, the new capital of Brazil; the great continent
of Antarctica, once mapped as Incognita, or "Unknown".
There are place names so short as to consist of a single
syllable, like Ur of the Chaldees, the Aa river of Denmark,
the Po of Italy, the literary Ys and Yf of France. There
are others so long that they take up most of a line, like
the Törökszentmiklos of Hungary, the Llanfairpwllgwyn-
gyllgogerychwyrndrobwllllandysiliogogogoch of Wales, the
Taumawathakatangihangakoauauatamateapokaiwhenu a -
kitanatahu of New Zealand, the Chargoggagoggmanchau-
gagoggchaubunagungamaugg of Massachusetts.
23
There are animal names, like the Eriga or Erie that
means "'wildcat", the Les Ecureuils of Québec that means
"the Squirrels", the Alacranes ("Scorpions") of Cuba, the
Camarôes or Cameroons ("'Shrimp") of West Africa, the
Canary or Dog Islands, so named by Columbus because
of the wild dogs he found there, the El Tigrito ("Tiger
Cub") of Venezuela, the Gatico ("Kitty-Cat") of Chile.
There are vegetable, and even mineral place names,
like the Los Alamos ("the Poplars") of New Mexico, the
Naranjito ("Little Orange") of Honduras, the Barbados
("Bearded Fig-Trees") of the West Indies; and the Altai
("'Gold") Mountains of central Asia, the Andes ("Cop¬
per") Mountains of South America, the Iwo Jima ("Sul¬
phur Island") of Japan.
In the United States are many cities and towns named
after abstract qualities: Liberty, Independence, Hope,
even Decorum, Defiance, Competition and Candor.
Similar uses appear in Colombia's la Gloria, Cuba's
Consolación del Sur, Bulgaria's Sofia ("Wisdom"), Ruma¬
nia's Bucaresti (from the word that means "'pleasure").
Poetic names include Minnesota's Lac Qui Parle ("'Speak¬
ing Lake"), Argentina's Buenos Aires ("Good Winds"),
Chile's Canto del Agua and Viña del Mar ("'Song of the
Water", "'Sea Vineyard"), Brazil's Belo Horizonte and
Très Coraçôes ("Beautiful Horizon", "'Three Hearts"),
China's Tien Tsin ("'Heavenly Place"), one of the alter¬
native names for Korea, Chosen, which is "'Land of the
Morning Calm".
The southern tier of South American countries are
dotted with places bearing the names of relatively obscure
people, but these names are historically significant
because they trace the streams of European immigration
to those countries. Englishmen are represented in Chile's
Stokes Bay and Wollaston, Uruguay's Canning and
Chamberlain, while Italian immigration is evident in
Peru's Bolognesi, Paraguay's Fassardi, Argentina's Cipol-
letti, Rufino and Ingeniero Jacobacci.
Honeymoon and Prosperity
Worry ÄWidowville, U.S.A.
If one were asked to name the word that most fre¬
quently appears in place names, regardless of the
language, that Word would have to be "new". On the
one hand, this indicates a desire to mark a place as
newly founded or discovered; on the other hand, it
shows the natural desire for people migrating to a distant
country to remind themselves of their original homeland.
So We' have New England and New York, New Zealand
and New Guinea, Nova Scotia, Newfoundland and Novaya
Zemlya, even Nueva Armenia in Honduras. We have
Newton, Naples (the Greek Neapolis, or "'Newtown"),
Novgorod, Neustadt, Civitanuova, Villeneuve.
Joy and sorrow occasionally appear in place names.
In the United States are towns named Honeymoon, Pros¬
perity, Wealthy and Bountiful. Italy has Bellagio ("Fine
Ease") and Benevento ("Fine Wind" or, perhaps, "Wel¬
come"). But the United States also has Worry, Drab,
Great Misery Island, and Widowville, in Ohio, where
many Civil War widows settled down. . Latin America
has such dismal names as Isla Desolación ("'Desolation
Island") and Punto Maldonado ("Ill-Given Point"),
France has Mont Dolent ("Sorrowful Mountain") and
Italy has Monte Disgrazia ("Mount Misfortune").
The Hindu Kush Mountains of India mean "Hindu
Killer". Bab-el-Mandeb is "'The Gate of Tears", and the
Kalahari Desert of Southwest Africa is "Those Who Are
Tormented by Thirst". Possibly the most despondent
place name of all is Crèveo "'Big Heart¬
break", in France's Department of the Oise.
Misnomers in place names include, first and foremost,
America, named after its supposed discoverer, Amerigo
Vespucci; Yucatán and the Aleutian Islands, which are
mere inquiries in the native languages ("What are you
saying?", "What is this all about?"); Rio de Janeiro, so
named in the erroneous belief that it was the mouth of
a river; Nome, Alaska, which resulted from a misreading
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1960
TOWN WITHIN A TOWN.
The colleges of the ancient univer¬
sity of Oxford are a town within a
town, their beauty and unity a
fitting framework for a tradition of
learning that dates back to the
early 12th century. The town is
considerably older than the univer¬
sity. It owes its name to the fact
that centuries before, the Anglo-
Saxons found a spot across a river
that was suitable as a cattle crossing
and called it Oxnaford. Oxford
just appears in history when Ed¬
ward the Elder, in A.D. 912, "held
Lundenbyrg (London) and Oxna¬
ford and all the lands that were
obedient thereto" as flanking for¬
tresses of his Thames Valley frontier.
Photo © Aerofilms Ltd., taken from "Our
World from the Air" by E. A. Gutkind,
published by Chatto & Windus, London.
of a pencilled inquiry "Name?" on an incomplete map.
Then there are names which are distortions of an
original in another language, like America's Picketwire
(Purgatoire), Smackover (Chemin Couvert), Low Freight
River (l'Eau Froide, at a time when froide was still pro¬
nounced fraide), and Loose (l'Ours) Creek; or Britain's
Teddymore (Tête de Mort) and Marylebone (Marie la
Bonne). Repetitiousness in place names is frequent:
Mount Ararat is "mountain" said twice; "Ganges River"
is a repetition of "river". The two most striking examples,
perhaps, are the fortress in the Russo-Turkish War of
1878 iknown as Krepost' Redoute Soukhoum Kalé, where
the first word is "fortress" in Russian, the second in
French, the last in Turkish; and Britain's Torpenhow
Hill, "'hill-hill-hill-hill" in four different languages.
Then there are humorous names, in which the humour
is sometimes deliberate, sometimes accidental. Deliberate
are America's Double Trouble, N. J., Whynot, N. C, Igo
and Ono, Cal., Punkeydoodles Corner, Ontario, Accidental
are Beaucoup, 111., Pastoutville, La., Upper, Nether and
Middle Wallop and Great Snoring, in England. There is
something a little humorous in Peru's Caballocoche
("Horse and Carriage") and Reventazón ("'Big Bust");
Paraguay's Puerto Casado ("Married Port"), Bolivia's
Torotoro ("Bull-bull") and Haiti's Trou ("Hole"). Ger¬
many's Irrendorf ("Madmen's Town") has recently
changed its name.
Confusing' place names are Georgia, common to the
U.S.A. and the U.S.S.R.; Santiago (de Compostela, de
Cuba, de Chile) ; Tripoli (in Syria and in Lybia) ; Ragusa
(in Sicily and in Dalmatia, though the latter is better
known by its Serbo-Croatian name Dubrovnik). Some¬
times a very slight difference in spelling and pronuncia¬
tion leads to confusion, as in the case of Darien, in
Connecticut and Panama, and Dairen, in Manchuria;
Burgos, in Spain, and Burgas, in Bulgaria; Acre, in the
Holy Land, Accra, in West Africa, and Agra, in India.
Sometimes the confusing names are within the same
country, as is the case with Falencia and Valencia, Spain,
or with Calcutta and Calicut, India.
It is also surprising how many repetitions of the same
name appear in different lands and diverse languages.
Tifus (or Tbilisi) in Soviet Georgia is duplicated by Ame¬
rica's Hot Springs; New York State's Stony Point is Vene¬
zuela's Punta de Piedras; Mississippi, Río Grande and
Guadalquivir all mean "'Big River"; Nepal and Piedmont
are both "at the foot of the mountains". Other samples
are the Cape of Good Hope and Greenland's Godthaab,
Britain's Land's End and France's Finistère, Malaya's
Singapore and India's Hyderabad ("Lion City"), Le Havre
and Ceylon's Colombo.
There are many place name endings that have identical
meanings: Britain's -ham, Germany's -heim, Scandina¬
via's -hjem, are duplicated by Hungary's -haz and the
Persian-Urdu -abad; Britain's Anglo-Saxon -ton and
France's Celtic -dun have as their equivalents the Greek
-polis, the Slavic -gorod or -grad, the Sanscrit -pur, the
German -stadt, the French -ville, the Hungarian -vár.
There is little question that a knowledge of place names
leads to a better understanding of the world we live in.
But a study of such names also teaches us that the
human mind displays the same traits of imagination,
ingenuity, humour, regardless of the locality where it is
at work, or of the colour or race of its possessors. It
indicates universal respect for what has been accomplish¬
ed by individuals or groups, appreciation of the physical
features of a World which is, in the main, bountiful,
understanding of human feelings and emotions all
qualities which pertain to the human race as a Whole
rather than to any of its parts.
It also shows that all human beings are subject to
errors and mistakes, and this, too, is a universal attribute
of mankind; but our place names also show a striving
toward higher and better things, a world in which there
will be more peace, tolerance and mutual understanding.
This article is based on "The Book of Place Names", by Eloise Lam¬
bert and Mario Pei, fust published by Lothrop, Lee and Shepard Co.,
Inc., New York ($3.00). A companion volume, "The Story of Personal
Names" is scheduled for publication shortly.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
HOW LONG DO THEY LIVE ?
by David Gunston
Sow long do wild things live? Is man's normal
lifespan puny by comparison with many of
them? Like many other fascinating aspects of
nature, records here have been much distort¬
ed. Genuine Methuselahs are as rare in nature
as they are amongst human beings. In point
of fact, only trees live a great deal longer than men, and
from the animal kingdom only the giant tortoises of the
Galapagos and Seychelles Islands regularly live beyond
the human limit. Elephants, the next longest-lived ani¬
mals, occasionally outlive man, but very few other creat¬
ures achieve such a feat under normal conditions.
Nevertheless, some quite remarkable facts do emerge
from an undistorted study of longevity in the wild. Man
has always tended to overestimate nature's powers of
granting long life to her creatures. Once he realized
that some things do outlive him he fell for every exagge¬
ration that was thought up by quack sages, from the
6,000 years of every churchyard yew to the phoenix which
"lyveth 300 or 500 yeares, when whiche yeares have pass¬
ed she maketh a neste."
It is strange that trees should have such a hold on
life, especially since the shortest lives in all nature are
also found in the vegetable kingdom: many flowers of
cacti live for a few hours only, and the flowers of wheat
live for two hours at the most. The claim for the oldest
tree in the world comes from Queensland, Australia, where
a macrozamia tree is reputed to be at least 12,000 years
old, although it is still only 20 feet high.
Trees 3,000 years old
when Christ was born
Trees of obvious age have inspired more popular falla¬
cies than any other living things. The famous dra¬
gon trees of Orotava, in the Canary Islands, most of
which have now been destroyed, were widely held to be
anything from 8,000 to 10,000 years old, perhaps With some
justification, although no reliable ring-counts were ever
made to prove this.
Probably the crown for the genuinely oldest tree alive
to-day is held by the gigantic Tule cypress growing in a
spacious churchyard in the village of Santa Maria de
Tule, near Oaxaca, in Southern Mexico. Fully vigorous
and of a spreading Weeping habit, this amazing tree has
a trunk diameter of 52 feet, which means that 28 people
touching finger-tips can barely encircle it with ease. Yet
it is only about 150 feet high, and is therefore over-topp¬
ed by many ancient Californian sequoias, or redwoods,
for which extravagant claims are also made. Yet the
average girth of a sequoia 3,000 to 4,000 years old is
seldom much above 36 feet. The Tule cypress's history
is lost in the mists of Mexican time, but it is undoubtedly
every day of 5,000 years old.
The oldest proved age for a giant sequoia, based on a
careful ring-count, is 4,000, and many still growing are
over 3,000 years old. Indeed, a 1,000-year-old sequoia is
still a youngster. Even so, it is a staggering fact that
any living organism which was contemporary with the
Bronze Age and the Ancient Egyptians and Mesopotamian
civilization, and which was over 3,000 years old at the
birth of Christ, should still be thriving to-day. It is
deserving of moré respect than that given it by visiting
fools with their initial-carving penknives.
Churchyard yews are often over 1,000 years old. Beech
trees rarely exceed 400 years, and the normal life-span
of most trees of this kind is not more than 250-300 years.
30
Many others die before they reach 150. Frequently the
Iknown dates of alien trees artificially introduced into
other countries disprove false claims of old age. For
instance, it is commonly held that Francis Bacon plant¬
ed the catalpa in Gray's Inn, London, but this species
was not introduced from America until 1726, when Bacon
had been dead exactly a century.
The Galapagos and Seychelle tortoises are the only real
Methuselahs of the animal world, regularly attaining a
life-span of 100 to 150 and occasionally 200 years. Tor¬
toises, notoriously slow a-dying, have a firm grip on life,
for many species may live to be centenarians. One famous
Marion's tortoise lived in ithe army barracks at Mauritius
from 1766 until 1918, when it was killed accidentally at the
age of 152. Mediterranean tortoises live long, too, and
one has been reliably recorded as dying when 125, while
the little box turtle has been known to reach 123.
Of all mammals only
elephants outlive men
Of all the mammals, from mice to Whales, only the ele¬
phant sometimes outlives man, although many speci¬
mens enjoy the traditional human span or less. Ac¬
cording to the records of the Bombay-Burmah Trading
Company, of their 17,000 working elephants, only about
nine per cent, live to between 55 and 65, and less than
two per cent, beyond 65. Quite a number of elephants
over fifty years of age have been known in zoos, and one
in the U.S.A. was said to be 85 When it died.
It is the rare exception that reaches the full century,
and the stories of zoo elephants having carried "several
generations of children" on their backs are somewhat
exaggerated. The original "Jumbo" of the London Zoo,
whose popularity started such tales, died from an acci¬
dent when only 24. Nevertheless, some of the tawny old
bulls in herds of wild elephants have probably lived for
longer than the average man.
The domestic horse, if allowed to survive into senility,
probably lives next longest amongst the mammals, and
several cases of fifty-year-old horses are on record, and"
one exceptional case of 62. Even so, a horse living to 47,
as one did recently, attracts a good deal of attention.
Most horse-owners have their animals destroyed long
before that.
Tiniest beings have
shortest life spans
A donkey has been known to live to 47 also, and in va¬
rious zoos, a hippopotamus of 41, a rhinoceros of 40
several bears from 30 to 34, a spiny anteater of 42 and
a chimpanzee of 26 are all authenticated instances of
comparative longevity. The oldest dog whose claim seems
allowable was 34; one of over 20 is exceptional, and 18
a remarkably good age for the average pet. Cats however
do live rather longer, and specimens known to be 39, 31
and 27 are recorded and many over 20 are known.
The longest reliably accurate life-span for a whale is
37 years, but it is generally thought that the larger whales
normally reach 30 or over if the whalers let them. At
the other end of the size scale insects have notoriously
short lives, although a tapeworm once lived inside a man
for 35 years.
CONT'D ON PAGE 32
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April I960
RECORD HOLDERS
IN THE LONGEVITY
STAKES
CAT
39 years
PARROT
140 years
**$j&
TORTOISE
200 years
DOG
34 years
"Slow and steady wins the race", according to the
fable of The Hare and the Tortoise in which the
slowest mover was the first home. The wisdom
of the maxim seems to be borne out by statistics.
In the animal world only the giant tortoises of the
Galapagos and Seychelles Islands regularly live
beyond the human limit. Here are some examples
of lifespans in the animal and vegetable kingdoms
arranged clockwise in order of their maximum
known longevity. Between the ages of the duck
and the cypress tree is a difference of 5,000 years.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
HOW LONG DO
THEY LIVE? (Continued)
In all these cases the records of creatures kept in arti¬
ficial captivity are longer than they would be for wild
creatures. The hazards of nature are such that real old
age is comparatively rare and is achieved only by fluke
or good fortune. Loss of vigour, failing eyesight, and
above all, deteriorating teeth take their swift toll in the
wild, leaving only a tiny proportion of the original popu¬
lation to enjoy a lengthy span.
Cockatoos go bald
& lose their memory
In a Zoo, things are different: food is plentiful, with
no need for hunting; there is permanent shelter and
freedom from enemies. Even accidents are rare.
The 25-year-old fox in captivity is really abnormal, for
its opposite number in the wild is already at 14 or 15
ancient, with broken teeth, scarred muzzle and grizzled
emaciated body. There is an authentic record of a wild
tiger of 17, but among the smaller hunters the Weasel
is decrepit at eight. Badgers may live to be 16 or so, and
they are closely followed, surprisingly enough, by toads,
which live much longer than frogs. Generally speaking,
the smaller and more prolific the creature, the shorter
its average expectation of life. There is undoubtedly some
link between physical size, low reproductive powers and
longevity.
The oldest known bird is always said to be the mute
swan shot in Derbyshire in 1887 bearing a ring on one leg
dated either 1717 or 1711, which seems .to indicate that it
was at least 170 years old at the time of its death. An eagle
shot in France in 1845 was found to be Wearing a metal
collar with a Latin inscription indicating that the bird
had been used for falconry in the Caucasus in 1750, over
90 years before. Both these cases, if true, are quite excep¬
tional.
The raven is probably the commonest bird Methuselah,
records of 69 years being known. Other birds surviving
for over half a century include pelicans and condors, 52;
eagle-owl, 68; golden eagle, 56. Amongst captive birds
parrots achieve the greatest age, 140 being about the
record here, while a number have lived well over the
century. Cockatoos also enjoy long life, several reaching
their nineties without loss of perkiness, although baldness
and loss of memory are usual.
Genuine old age amongst truly wild birds is difficult
to prove, but is undoubtedly infrequent. A magpie of 30,
an Arctic skua of 25, a chaffinch of 17 and several ducks
of 14 are all probably holders of maximum ages. Indeed,
to reach 10 is a feat for most small birds, and larger birds
of 20 or so are quite uncommon. Captive geese live for
much longer than their wild brethren: one was 44 when
it died, and records of 33 and 37 have been proved accu¬
rate. I also know of a pet canary aged 23, and an Am¬
erican bird is said to be 32 and still singing. An eel of
56 and a mirror carp of 47 lead the known fish veterans.
Although cases are known of a goldfish of 30 and a plaice
of 25, most of the larger fish seldom reach their twentieth
birthday, and nearly all the smaller species die before
they are 10 or 12.
All in all, man with his traditional threescore years
and ten fares batter than most of his fellow creatures.
Only the silent immutable trees make him look a mere
baby.
U.S.S.R. WAR ON MALARIA
(Continued from page 17)
in 1957 (3,652 primary infections and 1,445 relapses) and
4,678 in 1958 (this figure is provisional).
The figure of 10 cases of malaria per 10,000 population
was accepted as the limit above which malaria was regard¬
ed as a mass disease. According to this criterion malaria
was eliminated as a mass disease from wide areas of the
U.S.S.R. about five years ago.
It would be justifiable to say that eradication has
already been, or is about to be, attained in 88 % of the
total potentially malarious area of the U.S.S.R. This
undeniable success has been attributed to three simul¬
taneously executed measures which are given in the order
of importance attributed to them : first, the early diagnosis
of individual cases of the disease, intensive treatment,
and a careful follow-up of each case for not less than
two years; second, the use of residual insecticides for the
total coverage of an area, or for either barrier, village,
or focal spraying; and third, the widespread prevention
of mosquito breeding by the use of all available methods.
Plans have been outlined for the posteradication period
1959-1965. Attention will be concentrated on preventing
the introduction of malaria from outside, and on improv¬
ing mosquito control, preferably by antilarval measures.
New methods are to be developed for the early recogni¬
tion of symptomless parasite carriers, anti-relapse treat¬
ment is to be improved, better measures of preventing
epidemics from imported cases sought, the development
of old and new insecticides encouraged, insecticidal
methods adapted for use in areas with silkworm
industries, and the study of the epidemiology and eradica¬
tion of malaria in other countries encouraged.
Now that malaria is close to the point of eradication
in the U.S.S.R., there are a number of epidemiological
points of interest. One is the sharp decrease in the over¬
all incidence of malaria. Another is the absence of any
sizeable foci of malaria. Small foci are still to be found,
indeed, and present a potential danger.
Over the whole potentially malarious area of the Soviet
Union there are now three groups of communities: those
(by far the most common) where eradication has been
achieved, and where cases of malaria are totally absent
or only, in exceptional cases, imported; those where
malaria persists as a small focus of infection; and those
where, after an absence of cases for one to three years,
a few local cases have appeared.
From the point of view of an epidemiologist this last
group of cases is particularly important, and it has been
carefully investigated. The results of this investigation
have shown that, while population movements are occa¬
sionally responsible for the reinfestation of a small area,
the main cause is either premature discontinuance of
antimalaria measures or gaps in the system of sur¬
veillance.
The problem of the importation of cases of malaria
from outside the country is also under investigation. The
leading Soviet malariologists are emphatic in their warn¬
ing that the success achieved in the malaria eradication
campaign should not lead to a casual attitude to the
problem and thus to a premature weakening of a vast
organization which is geared to the complete and per¬
manent elimination of malaria from the whole of the
U.S.S.R.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. April 1960
Letters to the Editor
THE DRAMA OF NUBIA
Sir.
The special issue (Feb. 1960) of The
Unesco Courier (Save the Treasures of
Nubia) was a specially fine achievement
and passionately interesting. It brought
home to me most vividly the dramatic
situation created by the threatened
inundation of the wonders of Philae
and Abu Simbel. It is to be hoped that
international solidarity will now play its
part in resolving this problem.
Madame Lugardon
Toulouse, France
IMPACT OF THE CINEMA
Sir,
In view of the importance of the
cinema as a medium of artistic
expression, I think I am expressing the
wish of many readers in asking you
to devote an issue of your magazine to
this subject. In it you could deal with
its history and its technical, aesthetic,
economic and social problems. The
fact, pointed out by Georges Sadoul in
the article you published last April, that
the cinema has now penetrated into
every corner of the globe enormously
increases the interest of this theme.
Ruth Cecilia Levit
Buenos Aires, Argentine
Ed. note: The Unesco Courier has
already devoted two issues to the
cinema (Sept. 1951 and Ian. 1955) as
well as a large part of the April 1959
issue referred to by our reader.
However, this does not exclude the
possibility of this vast and interesting
subject being explored still further in
future issues.
FAITH REVIVED
Sir,
As a new reader I was immediately
struck by the attractive appearance of
your magazine and your choice of
subjects. I am now able to measure
the scope of the progress that has been
made in humanitarian work. As I see it,
Unesco's main task is to bring about a
greater measure of equality between the
living standards of all peoples and,
above all, to fight against the great
scourge commonly called racialism
which spreads its contamination among
the simple-minded.
I realize that Unesco has undertaken
a work of edification in the widest sense
of the expression, a humanitarian one
demanding much sacrifice yet offering
unbounded promise. The thought of
this great work, so patiently pursued,
puts new heart into me. Seeing so much
evil around me I had become blasé, no
longer able to believe in human virtue.
Reading The Unesco Courier has
made me realize, with feelings in which
bitterness and satisfaction are inter¬
mingled, that I was deluding myself and
that my ideas, so full of pessimism,
were completely unjustified. Becoming
conscious of the fact that there are
men and women who, both in thought
and act, work for the good of others
has revived my flagging spirits, and
restored my vitality. So saying, may
I pay tribute to all those who are inspir¬
ed by a humanitarian ideal and who
devote their lives to it with enthusiasm
and unselfishness. The results achieved
so far are still insufficient, but they
point the way to broader and more
hopeful perspectives.
Bensahli Mustapha
WHAT REPLACES 'THE COUCH'?
Sir,
I am very curious to know just what
method of treating the mentally ill is
being used in the Soviet Union if
psychoanalysis is taboo in that country.
W. H. Schobert
Hillsdale, Michigan, U.S.A.
Ed. note: An article on this subject
will appear in a future issue.
HOW MANY ESPERANTISTS?
Sir,
The article on Dr Zamenhof and
Esperanto published in your December
issue unfortunately included information
that was incorrect. There are certainly
not several million Esperanto speakers.
The petition asking Unesco to give its
patronage to the language admittedly
bore the signatures of 895,432 individual
persons and 492 organizations grouping
15,454,780 members who were never
consulted and who therefore can only
be considered as approving the auxiliary
language.
According to Esperanto Revue,
official organ of the Universala
Esperanto Asocio (federative association
of the national groups) this body then
had 27,138 members (Esperanto speakers
and supporters) at the end of 1958, and
the review itself had 4,988 subscribers.
If something like 5,000 members of
another association, Sennacieca Tut-
monda Asocio, and perhaps 10,000
non-affiliated members in eastern Europe
and China are taken into account, the
total number of persons able to use the
language, with varying ability, is
between 45,000 and 50,000. Esperanto
is by no means the sole auxiliary
language. Other, more modern idioms
exist which have the advantage of
being immediately comprehensible to
people with Anglo-Roman cultural
backgrounds. These are Interlingue
(ex-Occidental) with headquarters at
Cheseaux-sur-Lausanne, Switzerland and
spoken in 40 countries, and Interlingua,
a variant which is more Latin in
content. Abstracts in this variant are
published in more than 20 medico-
scientific reviews, chiefly in the United
States.
M. L. de Guesnet
President, Interlingue Union
Cheseaux-sur-Lausanne
Ed. note: A Unesco book entitled
Scientific and Technical Translating
(second edition 1958, page 194 § 6.6.8.)
gives the following information on this
subject:
"For various reasons, the number and
distribution of people in the world who
can both understand and speak Espe¬
ranto is not known with accuracy.
Statistics claimed to have been compiled
as objectively as possible showed that,
in 1952, there were 280,000 persons in
32 countries reliably known to
understand and speak it. This is stated
to be more than double the world's total
in 1926, even though teaching of the
language had meanwhile been forbidden
by various régimes. It does not include
scientists in China, Japan, the Soviet
Union, Bulgaria and various other
countries who, it is thought, would
bring up the total to at least 380,000."
ZAMENHOF & THE PHILATELIST
Sir,
Your issue of last December included
an article on Dr. Zamenhof, creator of
Esperanto. I should like to add some
information from the philatelist's point
of view. The first stamps commemor¬
ating Esperanto and its creator were
published in the U.S.S.R. in 1926 during
the international congress of Esperantists
and in 1927 to commemorate the 40th
anniversary of the international
language. After the U.S.S.R. it was
the turn of Brazil, which marked the
ninth Esperantist Congress in 1936 with
a stamp, with another the following
year for the 50th Esperanto anniversary
and eight years later with two stamps
during the Rio de Janeiro Congress.
Other nations, chiefly in Central
Europe, have taken Zamenhof and
Esperanto as subjects for their stamps:
Bulgaria in 1947 and 1957; Austria,
which included the star symbol of
Esperanto on a stamp design in 1945
and issued an Esperanto stamp in 1954;
Yugoslavia, which issued two com¬
memorative stamps for the 38th Uni¬
versal Congress in 1953, overprinted
with the letters "'STT. Vujna" in red
for its zone in Trieste, and Poland,
which celebrated the International
Congress in Warsaw and Zamenhof's
centenary in 1959 with two stamps.
Pierre Girot
Association Française de Philatélie
Educative et Culturelle, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Ne
WcORLD PRESS PICTURE: Some
30,000 newspapers (8,000 of them dailies)
are published in the world. Daily news¬
papers (250 million copies) represent a
circulation of about 92 copies per 1,000
inhabitants. These facts are revealed in a
Unesco study (1) following surveys made
in 146 countries. Roughly one-third of all
newspapers are published in North America,
one third in Europe (including the Soviet
Union) and the remaining third spread over
the rest of the world.
MOST POPULAR PROFESSION:
Engineering is the most popular pro¬
fession for both boys and girls in Poland
according to a public opinion poll
carried out by the Polish Radio Orga¬
nization among 2,400 graduate students.
Professions selected by male students in
order of popularity were: engineering,
scientific research, medicine, law and
the army. For the girls the choice was:
engineering, teaching, medicine, artistic
professions, scientific research, law.
Or,Jn EQUAL TERMS WITH MEN:
Thirty-four countries have now ratified or
acceded to the United Nations Convention
on the Political Rights of Women, the
latest country to do so being Turkey. Under
the Convention, women are entitled to vote,
hold public office and exercise other public
functions on equal terms with men.
AIRBORNE TV FOR CLASSROOM:
Later this year schools in six states in
the Middle West of the United States
will tune in to televised classroom cour¬
ses beamed from an airliner circling
thousands of feet above. Programmes
will be broadcast from Purdue Univer¬
sity in Indiana and relayed to the flying
transmitter overhead which will retrans¬
mit them to an area of 300 to 400 miles
in diameter, thus bringing 13,000 schools
and 5,000,000 students within range of
one TV transmitter.
IVuCLEUS OF A NEW SCIENCE
MUSEUM: After a three-and-a-ihalf-year
Odyssey to ten countries where it was seen
by more than half a million persons, a
Unesco science exhibition, "Energy and its
its Transformation" has been presented to
Ceylon where it will serve as the nucleus
of a new science museum in Colombo.
With more than 100 pieces of scientific
apparatus and many descriptive panels,
"Energy and Its Transformation" covers
all phases of its subject from nuclear power
reactors to the use of sunlight by algae.
Other Unesco science exhibitions have
travelled to many parts of the world,
attracting a large number of visitors.
(1) "Statistics of Newspapers and Other
Periodicals", Unesco, Paris. Price $1.00 ; 5/-
(stg.): 3.50 N.F.
34
VATICAN CITY: CULTURAL PROPERTY
UNDER SPECIAL PROTECTION
THE entire State of Vatican City was recently inscribed in the "International
Register of Cultural Property under Special Protection" at a ceremony held
in Unesco House, Paris. The Holy See is the first State, among those
that are parties to the Convention for the Protection of Cultural Property in
the Event of Armed Conflict, which has asked for the inscription of a monumental
centre in the Register.
The Vatican City territory, an area of. 44 square kilometres, contains priceless
artistic and historic treasures: |£he Basilica of St. Peter, the Vatican Palace with
its galleries and museums, the Library and Secret Archives, etc.
The International Convention for the Protection of Cultural Property in the
Event of Armed Conflict was adopted on May 14, 1954, by an intergovernmental
conference convened at The Hague under the auspices of Unesco. Under its
terms contracting parties undertake, in the event of armed conflict, to safeguard
as well as to respect cultural property on their own territory or on that of other
contracting parties. So far, thirty states have deposited instruments of ratification
or accession.
UNESCO MEMBERSHIP NOW 82:
The representative of the Republic of
Guinea in London has signed, on behalf
of his Government, the Constitution of
Unesco which is deposited at the
Foreign Office. Guinea, admitted to
the United Nations on December 12,
1958, by unanimous vote of the U.N.
General Assembly, thus becomes the
82nd member of UNESCO.
" C^HOPIN YEAR' Musicians and
musicologists from all over the world
gathered in Warsaw on February 22, the
150th anniversary of the birth of Frederic
Chopin, for the inaugural ceremonies of
the "Chopin Year" which is being organ¬
ized by the Polish Government. First offi¬
cial event of the "year" has been an inter¬
national competition for pianists under 30
years of age, and many other commemora¬
tive events have been announced for the
rest of 1960 by the Polish organizing
committee.
'CLOUDS AND METEORS': A
colour filmstrip entitled "Clouds and
Meteors" and a set of colour slides have
been produced by Unesco in co-opera¬
tion with the World Meteorological
Organization (WMO) based on photo¬
graphic material published by WMO in
the "International Cloud Atlas". They
demonstrate technical data' on cloud
classification and cloud codes and are
intended for university classes as well as
special courses for meteorological ob¬
servers. A detailed commentary ac¬
companying the filmstrip and slides is
available in English only, but French
and Spanish versions are being prepared.
9 UPER-SOUND AND BUMPER
CROPS: Soviet scientists are studying the
use of super-sound for increasing crop yields
and accelerating their maturity. Experi¬
ments in treatment of seed before sowing
are being made in laboratories of the
U.S.S.R. Institute of Plant Breeding. These
show that ultra-sound treatment of seeds
increases their germinating power, the
vegetation period is reduced and the yield
considerably increased nearly 50% in the
case of potatoes. Scientists explain the
action of super-sound by its influence on
the mutability of hereditary characteristics.
RADIOISOTOPES & SNAKEBITES:
A radioactive meal eaten by a snake
may help to provide the key to an
effective antidote for its venom, accord¬
ing to Mr Norman Veall, an expert of
the International Atomic Energy Agency
who recently spent six months in Thai¬
land, studying medical applications of
radioisotopes. One experiment he
carried out was to "mark" a cobra's
venom with radioiodine. The snake was
fed with radioactive meat and its venom
was then extracted for use in studies
on snakebite immunity and in research
for antidotes to the poison.
IL N. CANCER RESEARCH
PRIZES: The General Assembly of the
United Nations has instituted prizes
totalling $100,000 to be awarded for the
most outstanding scientific research work
in the causes and control of cancerous
diseases. The Assembly's decision was
taken as the result of a proposal made by
the Byelorussian S.S.R., which' pointed out
that two million people die of cancer each
year (1 per 1,000 of the world's population).
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Where to obtain
Unesco
publications
Order from any bookseller, or write
direct to the National Distributor
in your country. (See list below ;
names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request )
Payment is made in the national
currency ; rates quoted are for an
annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Press
Department, Royal Afghan Ministry of
Education, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 3 69 Lonsdale Street, Melbourne,
C. I, Victoria. (A. 13/-).
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C°., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V (Sch.
37.50.)
BELGIUM. For The Unesco Courier:
Louis de Lannoy, 22, Place De Brouckère,
Brussels, CCP. 3 3 8.000. (fr. b. 100.)
Other publications: Office de Publicité,
16, rue Marcq, Bruxelles, CCP. 285-98;
N.V. Standaard-Boekhandel, Belgiëlei 15 1,
Antwerp.
BURMA. S.P.C.K. (Burma) 54?, Merchant
Street, P.O. Box 222, Rangoon.
CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa
Ont. (5 3.00).
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd, Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Co¬
lombo. 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co, Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Librería Económica, Pte Zayas
505-7 Apartado I 13, Havana.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia Ltd., 30
Ve Smeckách, Prague 2.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6 Norregade, Copenhagen K. (D.kr. 12).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agen¬
cy, P.O. Box 120, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (F.mk. 540).
FRANCE. Unesco Bookshop, Place de
Fontenoy. Paris, 7". CCP. 12598-48
(7 NF.).
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8. (DM. 6).
GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28,
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Kultura, P.O. Box 149.
Budapest, 62.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chitcaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; Gunfoundry Road, Hyde¬
rabad, I; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/1 Asaf AM Road, P.O.
Box 386, New Delhi, I; Sub-Depots:
Oxford Book & Stationery Co., Scindia
House, New Delhi; Rajkamal Prakashan
Private Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby
Road, Bombay I. (Rs. 6.70).
INDONESIA. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Djakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco. Avenue du Musée. Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The National Press, 2, Wel¬
lington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-)
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
35, Allenby Road and 48, Nahlat Benja¬
min Street, Tel-Aviv (l£ 4.-)
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.( I 0/-)
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo. (Yen 500).
JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub. Sale Road, P.O.B. 66,
Amman.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück,
33, Grand-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications
Ltd., Times House, River Valley Rd., 135,
Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta. (10/-)
MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid des
Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (7 NF.)
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl 6)
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church. (10/-).
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
I 74, Lagos. ( 1 0/-)
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass, 7, Oslo. (N. kr. I 0)
PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing
Co, Ltd., Unesco Publications House
P.O. Box 374, 56-N Gulberg Industrial
Colony Lahore.
PANAMA. Cultural Panameña, Avenida
7a, No. Ti-49, Apartado de Correos 20 I 8,
Panama, D.F.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo, P.O. Box
620, Manila.
POLAND. " RUCH" ul. Wiloza Nr. 46.
Warsaw. I 0 (Zl. 50.)
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada Lda,
Livraria Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70,
Lisbon.
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Libri Building, Church Street, P.O.
Box 724, Pretoria. (10/-)
SWEDEN, For The Unesco Courier: Sven-
ska Unescorädet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 7.50) other publications
A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl. Hovbokhandel,
Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40, rue du Marché, Geneva. CCP.
1-236. (fr. s. 7.)
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Isti-
klal Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church'
Street, Pretoria ( I 0/-).
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT).
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha,
Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.1.( I 0/-).
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22, N.Y. (S 3.00.) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y.
U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaia Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjlga,
Terazije 27/11. Belgrade.
Vol. XII W61'
Vacations Abroad
Vacances à l'étranger
Vacaciones
CouriCi en el extranjero
Work Comp»
Cours rt
voyage* d'étude»,
chantiers internall
Curios r »lai« de
This concerns all members of the younger
generationthe young, and the young in spirit.
Do you want to plan your vacations to the best
advantage? Do you want to make friends of
your own age in foreign countries? Do you
want to know about all the opportunities that are
open to you? If so, you will be interested in this
handbook. It will give you all the Information you
need ; a choice of activities for young people In
over 75 countries and in 5 continents, extending
from vacation courses in languages and the arts
to international work camps.
Order your copy of "Vacations Abroad" now
from the Unesco national distributors whose
names you will find listed opposite. Failing that,
write to: Unesco Distribution Division, place de
Fontenoy, Paris-78 (France).
190 pages. U.S.S 1.25 ; 6/- (stg.) ; 4,50 NF
BINDERS FOR YOUR
COLLECTION OF
Unesco Courier
We offer subscribers a special binder for their copies of
THE UNESCO COURIER holding 1 2 issues of the maga¬
zine. Handsomely produced in halfcloth with the spine
in an attractive blue and the title (in English, French or
Spanish according to the edition to which you subscribe)
and Unesco colophon embossed in gold, these convenient
and attractive binders, costing $2.50; 1 2/6 stg.; or
6 N.F., can be ordered from UNESCO agents.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Eé
lT'S IN A PLACE NAME? History, legend, drama and romanceall have contributed to the names by which
. throughout the world, from towns and villages to hills and valleys, have become known. Above, part of the
port of Copenhagen, whose English name comes from the Danish Kobenhavn or "Merchants' Port." See page 26 .
]]>
</page>
</document>
