<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="064888eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
WINDOW OPEN O N T H E WORLD
fea lo 1 sSL
1
DECEMBER 1960 (13th year) - Price : 1/9-stg. (U.K.) - 50 cents (U.S.) - 1.25 NF. (FRANCE)
#*
,;
, '
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
" i3!5*w
Self-Portrait of Velazquez. Detail of "The Maids of Honour" (Las Meninas). This is
the only authenticated self-portrait of the artist. Painted in 1656. Prado Museum, Madrid.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Couri er
DECEMBER 1960
1 3 T H YEAR
Contents
No. I2
COVER PHOTO
Portrait of a Girl, thought to
have been painted by Velaz¬
quez about 1648 and now In
the Collection of the New
York Hispanic Society. All
colour photographs in this
Issue are published by
courtesy of Publications Fil¬
mées d'Art et d'Histoire
(See note page 32)
14
THE LADY WITH THE FAN
Supreme representation of the Spanish woman
VENUS AND THE MIRROR
Impressionist view of a classical subject
THE PAINTER WITH THE HUMAN TOUCH
By Enrique Lafuente Ferrari
16 THE MAIDS IN WAITING
"This is no painting; it is life perpetuated"
19 FOUR-PAGE FULL COLOUR SUPPLEMENT
23 VELAZQUEZ AND MODERN ART
By Julian Gallego
26 VIEW OF SARAGOSSA
A city and its people captured on canvas
THE SPINNERS
Four paintings in one
THE UPS AND DOWNS OF FAME
By Juan de Contreras, Marquis of Lozoya
THE MAN IN THE TREASURE TOWER OF THE ALCAZAR
By Francisco Javier Sanchez Canton
POPE INNOCENT X
An unforgettable portrait
30
32
34
35
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational,
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, PJace de Fontenoy, Paris 7*, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
Alexandre Leventis
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Celia Bertin
Spanish Edition : Amparo Alvajar
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani
German Edition : Hans Rieben
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Scientific and Cultural
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (12 issues a year) in English.
French , Spanish, Russian and German. In the United States of America it is dis¬
tributed by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 80 I Third Avenue, New
York 22, N.Y., Plaza 1-3860. Second-class mail privileges authorized at New
York, N.Y. (M.C 60. 1. 1 53 A).
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: S 3.00 ; IO/-stg. ; 7.00 New
Francs or equivalent. Single copies l/-stg. 30 cents
(U.S.) ; 0.70 New Francs.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
PAINTER
OF LIFE
by Pierre Luent
^^^^^ in the relentless heat, a group of men
walked briskly through the galleries and cool
rooms of the royal palace which led to the King's
chambers. At their head strode a dark young man
whose long upturned moustache emphasized a
strong, tip-tilted nose. His long black hair fell in
waves over a collar of white lace. His eyes sparkled
under strongly marked brows and his cool manner
gave no hint that in the next few minutes his whole
future would be decided.
The doors of the royal chamber opened and Don
Diego Rodriguez de Silva y Velazquez was ushered
in. The young man knelt and bowed his head.
When he rose, he saw before him for the first time,
King Philip IV of Spain.
Don Rodriguez de Silva y Velazquez was born in
4 CONT'D ON PAGE 7
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. December 1960
Anderson © Editions du Dimanche, from the album "Velazquez"
The Old Cook. "I should prefer to be the leading painter of what are considered common subjects than the second-best of
the refined", Velazquez is said to have declared. The great Spanish artist is generally known as a painter of the Court in the
17th century and of dainty 'little princesses. But he was an artist who appreciated life in all its forms even the most humble.
As a youth he painted kitchen scenes and peasants. He was about twenty when he completed "The Old Cook" (sometimes
called "The Omelette") bringing a strange beauty to these familiar objects with a skill already remarkable. (See detail page 6)
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
PAINTER OF LIFE (Cont'd)
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. December 1960
A career of genius begins in the uproar
and disorder of a Seville art academy
Seville on Sunday June 6, 1599, in a small house on the
narrow, twisting Calle de la Gorgoja, in the parish of San
Pedro. In the middle of the previous century, a Portuguese
gentleman, Don Diego Rodriguez de Silva, together with
his wife Dona Ana and ¡his son Juan left the town of
Oporto and settled in Seville. There Juan married Dona
Jeronrma Velazquez y Buen Rostro, niece of an aristocratic
lady, The child of this marriage was Don Diego Velaz¬
quez.
His first years were spent in the San Pedro district
among the rambling streets, the whitewashed houses
huddled together in an incredible jumble with their little
shady patios and tlheir azulojos which emphasized the
hues of the jasmines and carnations planted there.
His parents were well-to-do but far from rich, and had
originally planned .that Don Diego should study law. But
although proficient in philosophy and Latin, the boy
revealed a passion for something quite different: drawing.
At first his father took this for no more than a child's
simple amusement but he soon realized (that it was some¬
thing much deeper and accordingly decided to send his
son to the studio of the great Francisco de Herrera.
This was a strange studio: classes were held amidst the
wildest disorder and uproar, dominated by the piercing
voice of the Master who delivered insults and blows gene¬
rously and indiscriminately with his cane which was
conveniently tipped with a piece of charcoal for drawing.
The following year, Don Diego, then barely twelve enter¬
ed the school of another master, Don Francisco Pacheco,
whose lessons were given with much more discrimination
and method. Little Diego's neighbour and fellow pupil
was a certain Zunbaran, who was also destined to make
a name for himself and who became Diego's life-long
friend.
In 1617, Pacheco felt that the child prodigy
Velazquez had learned enough to be awarded
the diploma 'entitling him to exercise the
profession of painter. But Pacheco did much more than
give him a diploma. He also gave him his daughter. In
1618, in the Church of St. Michel, Diego Velazquez married
the gentle and charming Juana Pachecofurther evidence,
of .the Master's great confidence in his pupil's future.
In 1622, Velazquez decided to try his fortune in Madrid.
The prospects were favourable: he had friends at Court,
among them Juan de Fonseca, Luis de Gongora and the
Duke of Olivares. But his first stay there led to nothing
and Diego was unable to achieve his ambition to paint the
King's portrait. Unable to obtain access to the King,
he painted the portrait from memory and then returned
to Seville. The following year, however, he received a
letter from Fonseca with an order from the Duke of Oli¬
vares, at that time the King's favourite, instructing him to
return to Madrid. Accompanying the letter was the tidy
sum of fifty crowns.
The young man lost no time in presenting himself at
the "'Corte" in Madrid. He was accompanied toy his father-
in-law and his half-Moorish servant Juan Pareja who was
also his pupil and friend. Within a few days of his arri¬
val he had painted Fonseca's portrait. A friend of the
latter showed it to the King who found it magnificent and
expressed the wish to meet the artist.
This was the first meeting between the twenty-four-
year-old painter and the seventeen-year-old King. Phi¬
lip TV was not handsome but Velazquez gave nobility and
dignity to his stem and melancholy countenance. The
King was so pleased with the portrait that he at once
ordered a second, this time fulMength. This was follow
ed by portraits of other members of the royal family, of
the Duke oí Olivares and even of the Prince of Wales,
the future Charles I of England who was in Madrid at the
time. The King granted Velazquez a stipend of twenty
ducats per month. Though he had not yet made his
fortune, Velazquez nonetheless brought his family to
Madrid.
e began to attract attention. One day he
H^ ^B exhibited an equestrian portrait of the King
-^^- in the Caille Mayor. The painting caused a
sensation and aroused some envy. Criticism was levelled
at the shape of the horse ! On one occasion, the King
himself told him slydy, "T have heard that you can only
paint heads", to which Diego replied, "Your Majesty
flatters me; personally, I know no one capable of painting
them!"'
He painted a good many other heads for all that. In
particular, he did the portrait of the strange child, Don
Carlos, the King's brother, whom he showed with a cape
on his shoulder, the collar of the Golden Fleece on his
breast and capriciously holding a glove by the finger.
What Velazquez was able to catchand it Is an indication
of the mastery over his art which he already possessed
was the Prince's strange expression, his calm disdainful
attitude.
In 1627, the King decided to make Velazquez an usher;
but according to court customs he could only be paid a
salary corresponding to the lowest category of palace
employees.
The following year he met Rubens who was passing
through Madrid. The two artists compared their aesthe¬
tic ideas. One day Rubens described a Bacchic Flemish
festival. The subject appealed to Velazquez but not in
the Rubens manner. It resulted in El Dios Baco, the
God Bacchus, which was purchased by the King for one
hundred silver ducats. But the painter did not invent
figures dressed in the style of Sophocles. He took his ins¬
piration from the taverns of Madrid and the common
' people, and with a true understanding of the significance
of the picture, he gave it the name which it still bears
today Los Borrachos, the drunkards or drinkers. It
was, in fact, a portrayal of a group of drunkards seen
through the eyes of a man who never got drunk.
This was Velazquez's first period. It was one of vigour,
solidity, where dark hues and chiaroscura were used to
provide relief. He stripped his subjects like a child
taking a toy apart to see what lies inside. At this time
he was still at the stage of analyzing; later, possessed of
all the necessary elements he was to combine them in his
works of synthesis.
Not satisfied with buying "Los Borrachos'" for
one hundred ducats, the King paid him
another three hundred as arrears of salary.
For Velazquez, the total represented two year's salary.
Instead of devoting the sum to his family, the painter
took the advice of his ifather-in-law and of Rubens and
set off for Italy to see the masterpieces of that country
and learn everything he could. He left Madrid on
August 10, 1629, with the faithful Pareja, his pocket .the
heavier by two hundred ducats which the Duke of Olivares
had given him as a parting gift.
During the journey he met the renowned General Am¬
brosio de ßpinola. This was a Genoese soldier who had
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
PAINTER OF LIFE (Cont'd)
'Imitate nothing and nobody...
paint all things as you see them'
fought in Flanders in the service of Spain and received
the surrender of Breda. Velazquez Was much taken with
his pleasant personality and his intelligence. Later on,
he included the General's portrait from memory In his
famous painting, The Surrender of Breda.
Velazquez then spent a period 'at the Villa Medici.
Amidst the reminders of classical times he returned to
mythology and painted Vulcan's Forge, abounding in
irony but also in life: every figure possessed its own indi¬
viduality and expression and every object its form and
volume.
In 1630 he returned to Spain. Henceforward he had
no more doubts. His study of the Italian masterpieces
had confirmed him in his vocation: "'Imitate nothing and
nobody, paint men and things as you see them."
This was Velazquez's great period as a portraitist. His
works reached such a pitch of realism, that there is an
anecdote about Philip IV entering the painter's studio and
seeing the face of Admiral Pulido Pareja in the shadows.
"What's this," the King is said to have exclaimed "'are you
still here? I thought you'd left." Then, realizing that he
had spoken to a portrait, the King remarked to the paint¬
er, "T assure you I really was taken in!"
\r
w# ELAZQUEZ painted the court jesters and his
^F daughter, Juana Velazquez. He also painted
T a number of religious subjects at the urging
of several devout memlbers of .the court: The Visit of Saint
Anthony to Saint Paul was one; Another was Christ
on the Cross, painted about 1630. Although painted by
an .artist who scarcely ever touched religious themes, it
is perhaps .the most remarkable and profound religious
painting of the century.
Memories of his journey through Italy led him to paint
the portrait of General Spinola and various other persons
in the Surrender of Breda, also known as The Lances.
But Velazquez was now back in Madrid; and the back¬
ground of his picture is not the landscape of the Nether¬
lands but the country around the Corte. In spite
of this, the picture is one of the most valued works of
its kind.
In 1643, Don Gaspar de Guzman, Duke of Olivares,
Velazquez's patron, who was not liked by the Queen, fell
into .disgrace. AM his proteges at the Court departed but
the King kept the painter with him. He even acquainted
him with his ambition to create a gallery which should
assemble works by all the greatest Spanish masters.
Velazquez at once suggested that he should also acquire
some of the best paintings of the Italian masters and
requested permission to go to Italy to buy them.
But grave (events were taking place in Madrid.
First, the Queen died; then Prince Balthazar
Carlos, the King's only son, .died at seventeen
on the eve of his wedding to his cousin, Mariana of
Austria. Some years later, and in order to solve the
political problem caused by .these deaths, Philip TV decided
to marry his son's fiancée. He sent an emissary to Trento
to meet his fiancee on her way to Spain.
This was Velazquez's long-awaited opportunity to leave
Madrid. After a difficult journey he reached Genoa with
the faithful Juan de Pareja and, leaving the other mem¬
bers of the mission, travelled to Milan where he studied
the famous Last Supper of Leonardo da Vinci; then he
passed through Padua and reached Venice where he
8
bought five pictures for Philip IV. Next he visited Flor¬
ence and Rome and then Naples.
At this point Pope Innocent X who had been Nuncio in
Madrid asked Velazquez to paint his portrait. Diego who
saw a resemblance between the Sovereign Pontiff and
Juan de Pareja, painted a portrait of the latter by way
of preparation. The result was brilliant and Velazquez
ventured to present it to the Pope. Another masterpiece
had been created: the brilliant gaze, the chiaroscura, the
details, the wrinkles everything combined to form an
immediate revelation of character.
This was the painter's second period. He was still ana¬
lysing but he was also interpreting. Innocent X, contrary
Dominguez-Garcfa, Madrid
to all expectations, was highly pleased with the picture
and made a gift to Velazquez of a gold chain and a medal
engraved with his likeness.
When Velazquez returned to Madrid there was no
shortage of work. Philip TV had commandeered the
painter from the moment of his return. Portraits were
wanted of the new Queen, Mariana of Austria, of the
aging King himself and of the Infanta Margarita.
Velazquez had 'become such an Important figure at Court
that he requested and obtained the post of. King's Har¬
binger, his duties being to prepare the . monarch's
lodgings during his travels.
But he continued to paint and devoted himself in par¬
ticular to the court jesters: Barbarroja, Don John of
Austria, Don Antonio the Englishman and others. These
were a humorist's canvasses, like the portrait of Mars,
God of War, who was none other than a blustering
rogue of Seville; for under the influence of the literature
of the day, Velazquez sometimes dealt with mythology
and the pagan gods whom he portrayed not as gods but
as men:
CONT'D ON PAGE 10
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. December 1960
Wallace Collection. © Editions du Dimanche, from the album "Velazquez"
Lady with a fan. This portrait painted by Velazquez between 1644 and 1648 has been called
"a supreme representation of the Spanish woman". It was once thought that Velazquez used
his daughter as a model for this work, but nowadays it is generally agreed that the portrait is of
an unknown woman. The grave reticent expression, the mysterious, languid eyes reveal Velaz¬
quez's remarkable gift for probing beyond the human features in his deep search of the under¬
lying character. In this painting, justly considered one of Velazquez's masterpieces, sober browns
and greys harmonize perfectly with the luminous tints of the skin and the black shawl and dress.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
PAINTER OF LIFE (Cont'd from, page 8)
Nevertheless the painter remained faithful to his
ideal: to paint the truth, the reality of life. A striking
example is seen in the famous picture The Spinners,
painted at the time of the setting-up of the royal tapes¬
try works. Perfectly composed, his figures are natural
and their attitudes denote a complete freedom of move¬
ment. The play of light is varied, in direction and in¬
tensity; and the whole gives an impression of depth and
space. The viewer feels that Velazquez has not grouped
figures on a canvas but that his observer's eye has
caught them, in an instant of reality.
It was not long before the King expressed a wish to
have a large family portrait and it was now that Velaz¬
quez produced what is undoubtedly and rightly his
most celebrated work: The Maids of Honour (Las Meni¬
nas).
The King and the Queen have taken up their position
in front of the painter. Beside Velazquez is the Infanta
Margarita and her little retinue of jesters and compa¬
nions; the painter appears at the left of the canvas,
brush in hand; he is looking at the King and Queen who
are seen in the background reflected in a looking-glass;
in the foreground is the Infanta, flanked by two maids of
honour, Agustina Sarmiento and Isabel de Velasco.
Further to the right, the dwarf Maribarbola looks at the
and the dwarf Nicolasiilo Pertusato slyly kicks a
dog asleep in the foreground. In the shadows, the lady-
in-waiting Dona Marcela de Ulla dressed as a nun
whispers to a squire. Finally, right in the background
and framed by a doorway, the Queen's Harbinger, Don
José Nieto de Velasco, looks on.
B^H ach face reflects a different thought, each
^Ê i ' costume and object has its own colour, altered
-^^ by the reflection of the neighbouring object.
The feeling of space and depth is as marked as with The
Spinners. Velazquez haJd gone Ibeyond the limits known
in this fieflld at the time. And here again he painted
what he saw. The Flemish primitives too had painted
things exactly as they were tout all with the same wealth
of detail, whether hi the foreground or .the 'background.
It was not enough to paint things smaller when they were
further away. It was also necessary to include fewer
details. In this picture Velazquez went beyond his own
technique and (reached the culminating point of his art.
This was his last period: for the beholder, the .artist's
'"reality" was transformed into' illusion, the
illusion of naturalness, space, life and light.
Henceforth the artist was at the height of his fame.
The King made him a Knight of the Order of Santiago
in 1659 after having ennobled him. Velazquez's last years
were drawing dose. The painter returned to religious
themes with the Coronation of the Virgin where he
seems to have been inspired by El Greco." He also paint¬
ed the portrait of his friend, the sculptor Alonso Cano,-
and his last portrait of alll, the Infanta Margarita.
e made one last voyage. In 1660 Velazquez
JÊ ^(L_ set off for the French frontier where, on
June 1, on .the Tüe des Faisans, in the middle
of the Bidassoa River, Phillip IV met Louis XTV. The
voyage was an exhausting one over rain-soaked roads.
On June 26, the King's Harbinger ¡returned to Madrid. He
was 61 years olid. Weary from working alll day and
moving about all night, as he wrote to a friend, Velazquez
was obliged to take to his bed on July 31. Afflicted with
"tertiary fever," he died on August 6, 1660 surrounded by
his family, his closest friends and the inseparable Juan
de Pareja.
Velazquez was given a full court funeral in the Church
of St John the Baptist in Madrid where he was buried.
The only people missing at this last tribute were mem¬
bers of the Chapter of the Knights of Santiago who had
never welcomed him in their Order. It is said that the
King revenged himself for this insult by having the
great cross of Santiago painted in on the artist's doublet
in "'The Maids of Honour so that he might wear it for¬
ever in the great masterpiece of his career.
Anderson © Editions du Dimanche, from the album "Velazquez"
Pablo of Valladolid. Once believed to be the portrait of
an actor, this painting is now recognized as that of Pablo of
Valladolid, a jester at the Spanish Court. The true nature of
the jester is strikingly depicted a sad man whose haunt¬
ing eyes betray his deep melancholy. 1633, Prado Museum.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. December 1960
National Gallery, London, © Editions du Dimanche, from the album "Velazquez"
Venus and Cupid. Velazquez helped to lay the foundations
of modern Impressionist painting. When, centuries later, the
Impressionists made it their aim to study the effect of light
and atmosphere, they turned to Velazquez who was hailed as
their precursor. His modem treatment is strongly evident in
this head of Venus, a detail of "Venus and Cupid" (right)
where Velazquez did not depict the face of Venus directly,
but revealed it as a faint and ghostly reflection in the mirror
held by Cupid. This work is one of the mythological paintings
executed by Velazquez. Several of the works perished in the
fire which swept the Alcazar in 1734. "Venus and Cupid" was
bought in 1905 for £45,000 by the National Gallery, London.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
THE ROYAL CANVAS
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. December 1960
National Gallery © Editions du Dimanche, from the album "Velazquez"
The boar hunt. In Velazquez's day, the three great annual hunts of the Spanish court were the occasion for entertainments
and tournaments in which luxury and fanciful costumes and decorations were displayed with the greatest possible osten¬
tation. About 1640 the observant eye and dextrous brush of Velazquez recorded the thousand and one colourful and
dramatic details of one of these hunts as King Philip IV and his nobles pitted' their skill with lance and horse against the
fiercest boars that could be found in the kingdom. His finished work (above left) was a monumental composition measur¬
ing about ten feet by four. In it he depicted more than one hundred figures from the king, being watched by the queen
and her ladies seated in their carriages (detail left) to the crowd of huntsmen, peasants, beggars and other lookers on
(above). Velazquez painted other scenes of the chase, but many were destroyed in the fire which ravaged the Alcazar
palace in the 18th century. The Boar Hunt, also damaged in the fire, was copied by Goya and then offered
as a present by Ferdinand VII of Spain to Sir Richard Wellesley, the British Ambassador. National Gallery, London.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Anderson © Edi.tions du Dimanche, from the album "Velazquez"
THE PAINTER
WITH THE
HUMAN TOUCH
by Enrique Lafuente Ferrari
Director, Museum of Modern Art, Madrid
T̂
M his year, the wonlid celebrates the three
^^B^ hundredth anniversary of the death of one of
the greatest artists Europe has known: the
Spanish painter Diego de Suva y Velazquez.
Velazquez was a precocious child whose interest in art
showed itself early and he began his apprenticeship when
only ten. But even during ¡his formative years,
Velazquez revealed that he had rejected the artistic
conventionalism of his times. The ideal of tihe Renais¬
sance, conceived by Italian genius, had ushered in a
period during which art had as its aim the representation
of Beauty, the creation of a world peopled by lovely and
perfect creatures not to be met with in this life.
But for Velazquez only life was of any interest, the life
14
of reality, hum/ble and prosaic, the visual world before
our eyes. And he set about to perpetuate this world in
his works of art. His was a radical departure in the
very conception of painting.
Velazquez was no lover of rhetoric. or the mere anec¬
dote: he preferred the modest and serious prose of every¬
day life. It was for this reason that even as a young man
he devoted himself to the painting of stall life and por¬
traits. And when subjects from the Christian iconography
such, as Christ in the House of Mary and Martha were pro¬
posed ¡to him, he departed from tradition and painted
a kitchen in the foreground, putting the main theme
itself into the distant background, reducing it to its most
human dimensions.
CONT'D ON PAGE 18
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. December 1960
Photos Anderson © Editions du Dimanche, from the album "Velazquez"
COURT
DWARFS
AND JESTERS
Within the grandeur and pomp of the court of
Philip IV lived a strange little world of deformed
people who wandered about the palace and often
found their way into the studio of the King's painter.
To Velazquez they offered ideal models for experi¬
menting freely with his views on the techniques of
painting. Ortega y Gasset has even declared that
these portraits of dwarfs and jesters are among the
painter's best works. Velazquez did not believe that
the values most often praised, such as beauty,
strength and wealth, were the most worthy. Above
these and more intensely deep and moving he felt
was the value of ordinary life which he saw as far
more sad and dramatic. That is why the negative
aspects of these misshapen creatures emerge in his
paintings here with positive values. Portrait on oppo¬
site page is that of Menippus, the Greek cynic and
satirist, for which Velazquez used an unknown model
of seedy appearance. This often-reproduced work
was a companion piece for his portrait of Aesop.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Photos Anderson © Editions du Dimanche, album "Velazquez
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. December 1960
Prado Museum, Madrid
Las Meninas. "What realism! What a magnificent achievement!" Picasso exclaimed years before
he began his series of paintings directly inspired by this great masterpiece. When Théophile Gautier
first saw the work in the Prado he cried out: "This is no painting; it is life perpetuated." Velazquez's
picture of the royal princess and her entourage is in fact one of the most remarkable paintings of all
times. And like many of the artist's great works it is a paradox of art. When we gaze at it from a
distance it appears as an extremely precise, realistic work which gives an extraordinary feeling of depth;
but if we approach closely the realism evaporates and we behold an ethereal fantasy. Here the central
figure of the Infanta Margarita is merely suggested with rare touches of pigment that gives an impres¬
sionistic atmosphere to the flesh and clothes. Amazingly enough, Velazquez achieved this magic with
surprisingly few brushstrokes "No one has painted a subject with fewer," Ortega y Gasset once remarked.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
THE HUMAN TOUCH (Cont'd from page 1 4)
'Avant-garde' in audacity
What attracted him most in portrait painting was the
opportunity to penetrate the mystery of life and to
capture the human personality of the individual. He
found no pleasure in constructing his compositions
analytically but strove rather for the total impression
conveyed by colour and atmosphere.
In 1621 Spain had a young king on the throne,
Philip IV, who had inherited from his father the greatest
empire in the world. But Spain was exhausted by the
frequent wars it had waged in Europe and its far-flung
Empire was already showing signs of weakness. In Velaz¬
quez's time, during the seventeenth century, this had
ibecome accentuated and Spanish political superiority was
being replaced by that off France amd England. And yet
it was in this century .that Spain produced her greatest
writers, poets and artists; happily genius does not depend
on political power.
Thanks to the help of the Duke of Olivares, Minister
of Pbiilip IV, the descendant of a family of Seville,
Velazquez was given an opportunity to paint a portrait of
the King in 1623. Charmed by Velazquez's talent, the
King appointed him to (be his official painter. From then
on he was to paint not kitchens but princes, yet he made
no concessions in his aesthetic principles. He remained
faithful to his purpose to immortalize the individual and
life around him.
As a painter, Velazquez, never allowed himself
to be dazzaled by social rank and devoted his
art to what Unamuno called "the man of
flesh and bone." He refused to flatter his royal models,
and portrays them, as ordinary humian beings no different
from the rest of us. In his extraordinary series off por¬
traits the models appear both miraculously alive and sim¬
ple, their personalities strikingly individualized and each
portrait endowed with .that mysterious "'presence" and
reality which he managed to bring to alll his works of art.
He painted not only the great nobility but also the
unfortunate and the lowQy, the rogues and buffoons, the
half-witted and demented, whom the kings accepted in
their palaces in surprising contrast to the life of luxury
of the Court. For these humble and monstrous people
Velazquez set about his canvasses with the same grave
respect for their human dignity as he did for his noble
subjects: in his approach to the mystery of the social and
physical inequality of man he maintained the profound
feeling that all men are intrinsically equal in the face of
Ufe itself. That is why men of all races and of all condi¬
tions understand and appreciate him so easily.
Velazquez is the most human of painters because he
neither embellishes nor beautifies what he sees; he
captures the essentials with a technique all his own; his
sober, unassuming compositions reveal not only the
physical appearance of his models, but their attitude and
bearing and the atmosphere surrounding them, in which
each figure lives.
Velazquez spent thirty-seven years with Philip IV, not
only as his Court painter but as his friend, and thus
received palace appointments rarely accorded to persons
who did not belong to the upper classes of society. He
was a calm man, taking no vanity from his success as an
artist and his situation at the Count.
The only events off his life were two journeys to Italy,
the country of art, in 1629 and 1649. During his second
visit he was called upon to paint the portrait off Pope
Innocent X, a painting which the English artist Reynolds
esteemed as the "finest picture in Roane." But before
painting the Pope he went into training by doing the
portrait of his servant and pupil, the half-Moorish painter
Juan de Pareja. This too is a masterpiece.
With an audacity that would mark him today as
"avant-garde," Velazquez dared to declare in Italy that
he saw nothing in Raphael, the great artist of the Ren¬
aissance, the painter off superhuman beauty admired by
academic painters. Velazquez preferred Titian and the
masters otf the Venetian School, more akin to his own
human art.
18
The portraits of Velazquez form . an . impressive gallery
in which all levels of humanity are represented: King
Philip IV and his two wives, Isabella of Bourbon and
Mariana of Austria, the princes and princesses born of
the two royal marriages, the two brothers of Philip IV,
artists, poets 'and palace officials and, cheek by jowl, men
and women otf the people, cooks, street water vendors,
women at their work, clowns, dwarfs and the insane . . .
His palette became gradually richer in tone, finally
attaining a sober and exquisite harmony, as in the rose
and silver of the portrait of Philip IV in the Frick Col¬
lection or in the children's portraits in the Vienna Museum.
Nevertheless, his most ambitious works were the large
composition pictures in which he perieoted his vision-syn¬
thesis technique with its "atmosphere", capturing the
fleeting moment. One of the most remarkable is the
Surrender of Breda. In the war of the Low Countries
the Spanish army had succeeded in capturing the fort
of Breda. Velazquez has chosen the moment when the
conqueror receives the symbolic key from the vanquished
general, both surrounded by their soldiers. Once again he
gives us a lesson in humanity. Spinoia, the victor, receives
the defeated leader with courteous grace and, placing a
friendly hand on the loser's shoulder, prevents him from
kneeling, thus eliminating humiliation from the defeat.
This interpretation is a lesson in "fair play" and
elegance off spirit.
In the Palacio del Buen Retiro in Madrid The
Surrender of Breda stood next to a group of equestrian
portraits in which Velazquez is seen as the forerunner
otf modern landscape painting, with its distant views,
coloured skies, the view upon the woods at Pardo and the
snow-covered mountains around Madrid. His two views
otf the Villa Medici in Rome are landscapes even more
modern in approach: here, using rapid brush strokes, the
artist suggests the noonday sun on the distant cypress
trees or the melancholy of an afternoon in the silent
garden.
Towards 1656 he painted Las Meninas, an interior
scene in which the intimate life of the Royal Palace is
caught with the painter's habitual noble serenity. The
picture shows the artist himself painting the Royal couple
who can be seen in the background reflected in a mirror.
But the real subject otf the painting is the appearance
in the room off a blond-haired child, the Infanta
Margarita, accompanied toy her maids of honour, her
dwarfs and her dog.
Velazquez has here achieved a painting in which the
lines vanish, leaving only a pure impression of light and
colour. He succeeds in recreating for us, across the
centuries, a passing instant off time, as if we had half-
closed our eyes and found ourselves immersed within the
confined space which gives the picture its unity.
T
he painting called Las Hilanderas, or the
^B Spinners, in which the real protagonists are
-^^ light and its gradations, produces a similar
effect. A mythological subject had been proposed to
Velazquez the legend of Minerva and Arachne, rivals in
the art of weaving tout he relegates the allusion, briefly,
to the background and, taking his inspiration as ever
from life, offers us what Ortega y Gasset calls his "loga¬
rithm of reality:" working women who are weaving and
winding their thread in the foreground. Once again, as
when he painted the kitchens of his youth, this painting,
without precedent in the history otf European art, immor¬
talizes the work of women.
Velazquez abides by the world around him, the
circumstances of mere existence, and he knows how to
convert into a lofty art subjects considered until then
unworthy of being painted on account of a false idea of
artistic nobility and hierarchy which he refutes with his
human painting that extracts poetry from the experience
of pure visuality. That which man sees is what Velazquez
judges worthy .to receive artistic treatment in his works.
This was his great feat, his modernity.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Las Meninas, painted in 1656, is considered by many critics as one of Velazquez's most
remarkable paintings. This detail, which brings to mind Degas and Renoir, reveals why
Velazquez is now called the great forerunner of the French Impressionist movement
which reached its full flowering in the second half of the 19th century. Prado Museum.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
The Surrender of Breda,
often known as "Las Lan¬
zas" from the serried rank
of lances breaking the sky.
Painted about 1634-35, it
shows the keys of the besieg¬
ed city being handed to the
victorious Spanish General,
Marques Ambrosio de Spi¬
noia. The figure on the
extreme right was once be¬
lieved to be a self-portrait of
Velazquez. This view is not
shared today by all autho¬
rities. Now in the Collec¬
tion of the Prado Museum.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
n
"'^I
»
^B
7* - ma
^âgíBr**-
tbz*
,. ,
n Jr
- L< " 1
HrL^^ftft^^^« «ft.
ftj
1 ": "'.**!
idfetääi?
"'
The Drinkers. Group of peasants seen in this detail from "Los Borrachos" graphically ex¬
presses the wealth of humanity with which Velazquez imbued the profusion of subjects he
found among humble people. Painted about 1628, the work is now in the Prado Museum.
Hand Holding a Rose. Detail from a portrait of the Infanta Margarita, painted about 1659-
60. For many years the painting was mistakenly believed to be a portrait of Dona
Maria Teresa, the eldest daughter of Philip IV of Spain. Now in the Prado Museum.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. December 1960
Prado Museum, Madrid
Ladies of the Fountain. This charming detail from a large painting entitled "Fountain of the
Tritons", is another illustration of Velazquez's amazingly modern technique. The blurred outlines
of the two seated ladies in profile were achieved by the artist with quick daubs from his brush.
As one approaches the painting, the forms melt into the background. This is one of the later
works of Velazquez, and the detail might almost have come from the brush of Edouard Manet.
VELAZQUEZ
AND MODERN ART
by Julian Gallego
Velazquez's most astonishing quality is that he
makes us feel he belongs to our age. His
pictures look as if they were fresh from (the
brush of a contemporary artist, .and have nothing of the
"period" atmosphere ¡characteristic of galleries of olid
paintings. They would not toe out off place in a Modern
Art Museum. The only anachronism would be the clothes
of the people he portrays, tfor naturally they are dressed
in the style of 17th century Spain, the men in dark clothes
with unotostrusive starched colars, (the women in the
voluminous skirts know as "farthingales," on which they
rest their hands, surmounted by a bodice, bejewelled and
colourful, their hair elaborately curled.
The costumes are, it is true, very alien to us; but be
cause the faces and eyes of their wearers are still alive
and full of expression, because the velvets and silks are
still fresh, and because the whole scene is painted in bold
technique with clear tones and free brush-work, we have
the intriguing impression of watching the life of bygone
centuries; it is as though a modern painter had been able,
like the "Connecticut Yankee at King Arthur's Court", to
live in a past age, and had brought us back his impres¬
sions, seen through the eyes of modern man.
Examined in detail, many of Velazquez's pictures look
like the work of an artist belonging to the Impressionist
school, which flourished in France at the end of the 19th
century, that is three hundred years after the birth of
Velazquez. His landscapes of the Villa Medici in Rome,
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
VELAZQUEZ AND MODERN ART (Cont'd)
Diego's 17th Century 'New Look'
painted with broad strokes, and his figures, silhouetted
by the light, might well be the work of Claude Monet.
The strong drawing and the restrained expressive model¬
ling of some of the headsin The Spinners for example
remind us of certain portraits by Degas. The portraits of
the Infanta Margarita, where the delicacy of the subject
is matched by the freshness of the colours and the lustre
of the sparkling brushwork might well belong to the same
period as the best work of Auguste Renoir, whose Ger¬
maine Laceu with her spreading skirt and her bouquet is,
as it were, an echo of Velazquez.
But the artist most profoundly influenced by Velazquez
was Edouard Manet who declared, in his letters from
Madrid, that he had discovered his ideal in painting in the
pictures of the great Spaniard, the contemplation of whose
work filled him with new hope and boundless confidence.
Manet made a copy of the portrait of the buffoon Pabillos
of Valladolid at the Prado, about which he said that the
background melted away, leaving only the air surrounding
the intensely alive figure; he imitated this picture in his
famous Fife-player, by no means the only one off Manet's
paintings which reveals the profound influence of Velaz¬
quez's technique, colour and handling of light.
Thus Velazquez could, without exaggeration, be called
an "Impressionist" painter. His main concern in paint¬
ing, as with Sisley or Monet, is to convey the impression
of light, otf light and air. He does not want his figures to
be statues, but to give the effect of life and even move¬
ment at the touch of the light. Velazquez paints through
his eyes alone. Though be began by painting figures and
objects enclosed by the outline of the drawing, standing
out solid and almost tangible as Caravaggio had done
in Italy he soon realized that such strictly defined mas¬
ses and shapes belonged to' sculpture rather than to paint¬
ing, and in painting that meant not to touch but to
look at. He therefore felt that the visual element should
predominate.
His pictures are like open windows r when we look, for
instance, at the portrait of the Infante Baltasar Carlos on
horseback, we seem to catch a breath of the pure air of
the Guadarrama. This background of snowcapped moun¬
tains is executed with a few strokes, in tones so accurate
as to give the impression of air and distance. In his late
work, the painter uses touches of pure colour in juxtapo¬
sition which then blend in the eye of the spectator, a
few yards away, to give the effect of vibrating light.
That is why it is so interesting to look at Velazquez's mas¬
terpieces, such as Las Meninas and The Spinners or some
of his late portraits at a close distance. We realize that
neither flesh nor fabrics are ever painted in one colour.
^K -^m enerally speaking, painters before Velazquez,
^^^H and even 'his contemporaries, 'believed that the
parts off an object in shadow were the same
colour as those exposed to 'the light so that, for painting
shadows, it was sufficient merely to add a little brown or
"earth shadow pigment."
But Velazquez declared that the parts off an object in
the light are not the same colour as the parts in shadow,
since the colour is transformed by the atmosphere and the
reflexion of other objects. He therefore mixed the colours
for his shadows separately; and examined close to, every
inch of fabric, flesh or air is seen to be composed of a
variety of colours. Which is precisely what the Impres¬
sionists did, much later.
We observe in the works of old masters a disturbing lack
of unity between figures and background: the people
seem to be posing in front of a backdrop, as in old photo¬
graphs. But Velazquez's pictures achieved visual unity,
everything being 'equally important, and equally real.
Figures in real life do not appear to be more strongly
outlined than the surrounding scene. Velazquez is objec¬
tive, putting down what he sees; and his objectivity, far
from springing from any lack of inspiration, is a sign of
genius.
The Impressionists and with them Paul Cezanne revo¬
lutionized contemporary art by attaching the same pic-
24
torial value to everything a human head, a book, a fruit
or a hat; but they were influenced considerably, in thus
breaking down the hierarchical classification of natural
objects, by the results of photography, which had just
been invented.
In the middle of the 17th century, to see things as
Velazquez saw them was not as natural as it appears to
us now. Let me explain what I mean: though we see
as our predecessors did, we now look at things differently.
Seeing is natural, but looking is something that has to be
learned. And artists as a rule are the people who teach
us to look, to pick out, from amongst the lines of land¬
scape or a figure, those which they consider essential; and
to distinguish, amongst the infinite number of tones of
light, those which correspond and harmonize with one
another.
11
l or example if, being acquainted with Chinese
^B painting, wè see a mountain landscape, our
-^^^- eyes will pick out certain idetails, the intersect¬
ing outlines otf the rocks, .the patches off fir-trees, and
the lanidscape will seem to ,us to toe carefully designed
and harmonious just like a Chinese painting; if we are
not familiar with Chinese painting it might well appear
disordered and without form. Then again if after looking
at the river scenes painted toy the French Impressionists,
we pass by a river one spring day, we shall discern certain
tones of blue, white and pink and we shall, say: "This
river looks like a picture by Claude Monet."
So it is that artists teach us to look, and everyone is
enriched by visiting art galleries. Everyone, that is,
except the creators of a new way of looking. Velazquez,
by taking the human figure, hitherto enclosed, and plac¬
ing it in the full light, doing away with the conception
of the background and, by subtle gradations of tone, mak¬
ing the air flow round the objects depicted, revolutioniz¬
ed not only painting tout also our way of looking at things.
It was this that caused the famous French critic, H. Taine,
to write that in comparison with Velazquez's paintings all
others looked lifeless and academic.
Another feature of Velazquez that makes him one of
the painters closest to our understanding is his attention
to "values." The term "value" in painting is used to
denote the degree of lightness or darkness of the tone
of objects, regardless of their colour. A yellow may have
a lower value than a (blue ,as we shall see if we half close
our eyes. This conception of values was unknown in
Velazquez's day. It is for this Teason that we find some of
the works of great painters, even great colourists, unpleas-
ing there may be some object, a cloak for instance, which
seems to be much nearer to our eye than the wearer,
because its tone value is wrong.
Velazquez, though knowing nothing of this conception
of values, nevertheless used them with such mastery that
he sometimes painted pictures with very few colours
such as Lets Meninas, for instances which yet give the im¬
pression of being as highly coloured as a Rubens canvas.
Picasso when he undertook recently to give his own inter¬
pretation of this famous picture worked mainly, in his
most successful versions, on the basis of this subtle gra¬
dation of values, painting almost exclusively in shades of
grey, the colour most characteristic of Velazquez's work.
Velazquez's greys shimmer and vibrate, so exquisitely
subtle are their tones. There is no other painter to equal
him in rendering the pearly lustre of the Madrid light
reflected in the landscape and the skin of women.
Venus and Cupid his sole and extremely chaste nude, is
painted in greys and pinks; but the reclining figure stands
out against a background of vivid green and red.
Velazquez was not afraid to use strong, warm tones.
His portrait of Innocent X is a magnificent symphony in
crimson. Like a Soutine, everything in this canvas is red,
including the head of the Pontiff.
In his portraits of the Infanta Margarita (hanging in
Madrid and Vienna), Velazquez's palette is so rich and
varied that he surpasses even the Impressionists, coming
closer to the painters of our day. The poetic vase of
CONT'D ON PAGE 28
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. December 1960
Anderson © Editions du Dimanche, from the album "Velazquez"
Souvenirs of the eternal city. Velazquez made two visits to Rome, in 1629 and again
in 1649-51. He bequeathed to posterity two remarkable souvenirs of his visit to the Eternal
City in the form of views of the garden of the Villa Medici, painted on his second visit.
The one shown here, which has been named "Noon", shows a landscape full of luminosity
in the middle of the day with the sun, very high, filtering through the leaves. Velazquez
made much use of the brush point and the contrast of sombre colours of olive green,
brown and black in this work. Its companion painting, "Evening", full of melancholy and
with a sky of grey clouds, seems to represent an hour of evening peace in the classical garden.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. December 1960
Anderson © Editions du Dimanche, from the album "Velazquez"
View of Saragossa. Although this painting bears a Latin inscription stating that it was completed in 1647
by. Juan Bautista del Mazo, Velazquez's son-in-law and pupil, authorities generally agree that Velazquez
painted most of the landscape and the striking figures of ladies, gentlemen, beggars, students and merchants
Which recall those of "The Boar Hunt" (page 12). Velazquez accompanied the court to Saragossa during the
war in Catalonia. It is said that Prince Balthasar Carlos himself chose the viewpoint from which the scene
was to be painted: the bank of the Ebro on the outskirts of the town, facing the city proper and offering a
view of the broken stone bridge (above) and the city's churches and houses. The various groups (details left
and following page) are shown going about their everyday tasks. The people and the boats along the river are
painted with a freedom of treatment strongly recalling Watteau's "Embarkation for Cythera." Prado Museum.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
VELAZQUEZ AND MODERN ART (Cont'd from page 24)
Detail from View of Saragossa. (Prado Museum)
flowers in the portrait of Margarita wearing a salmon pink
and silver dress sparkles with colour it might have come
straight from the brush of Marc Chagall.
But Velazquez has affinities with painters much nearer
even to the present day. A great many modern artists
have abandoned the representation of objects considering,
rightly or wrongly, that photography has relieved them
of the task of keeping documentary records. There are
people who now look askance at Velazquez's pictures be¬
cause they are figurative. In fact nothing is simpler than
to prove this prejudice unfounded.
We have only to approach one of his works and cut out
a fragment here, a sleeve, a piece of farthingale, of wall
or of landscape there; and we shall find ourselves con¬
fronted with an abstract picture. The beauty of the
colours, the free arrangement of the forms and the variety
of the pictorial qualities are fully equal to those of any
non-figurative picture.
Formerly, quality was held to lie in the ability to imi-
28
täte in painting, the particular texture of a material
silk, velvet, wood, glass... (The minor Dutch masters, such
as Metsu or Terborg, excelled in this respect.) Nowadays,
the word quality is used to denote ithe original beauty of
the actual pictorial matter, with its impasto and thin
paint effects, smoothness and roughness, lustre and matt
passages. :
In both these senses, Velazquez's pictures are admirable.
Standing a few steps away from one of his portraits, we
seem to see the silver and satin of a ceremonial robe; then
as we draw nearer, we realize that this effect is obtained
by a combination off exquisite colours, transparent and
opaque, applied, some lavishly, others in barely perceptible
touches, with consummate mastery.
All this raises Velazquez's works above the level of mere
illustration to the heights of pure art. What does The
Spinners represent? According to the learned, a myth
(that of Minerva and Arachne) treated with the painter's
characteristic realism. But those in search of a subject
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. December 1960
Anderson © Editions du Dimanche, from the album "Velazquez"
say that it is a tapestry workshop with various women at
work whilst in the background visitors look at the finished
work; then again, admirers of Impressionist paint¬
ing see the picture as a treatment of the problem of
light and atmosphere, with a dark foreground and a very
light background; lovers of abstract ant, as a superb play
of strokes and colours.
And what about Las Meninas? In this famous picture
there is a revolutionary change even in the subject mat¬
ter, in that the King and Queen whose portrait Velazquez
is painting are outside the picture (in the place occupied
by the spectator) , and we only know who they are because
there is a mirror in the back of the Salon, which reflects
the faces of the King and Queen instead of our own. We
are thus enclosed in the atmosphere of the picture to
which we add, as it were, another personage.
In the Prado Museum there is, in front of Las Meninas,
a mirror reflecting, at the same time, both the painted
figures and the flesh-and-blood spectators. "But where
is the picture?" exclaimed Théophile Gautier, the famous
writer and art expert, on seeing this canvas for the first
time, for he realized that the real subject was not so
much a domestic scene in the Royal Palace as a magnifi¬
cent depiction of atmospheric and light effects. If we
draw nearer, we shall appreciate the exquisite subtlety of
its tone values, the freedom and boldness of the brush-
work and the beauty and variety of the paint.
Any other of Velazquez's great works prove to be equally
"modern" and accessible. This perennial freshness is a
quality exclusive to a small number of works of art which
are appreciated by each individual and each epoch on
different grounds, and always with good reason.
I have tried in this article to describe Velazquez's main
qualities, the ones which make us feel that his works
belong to our age. But naturally the subject is vast and
there is much more to be said. I leave it to each reader
to add those reflexions which this special issue may
inspire.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. December 1960
Photos Anderson and Boissonas © Editions du Dimanche, from the album "Velazquez"
THE SPINNERS
FOUR PAINTINGS
IN ONE
"The Spinners" was the last of Velazquez's great composition
paintings, completed in 1657, just three years before his
death. Ortega y Gasset has called it "the pinnacle" of his
works. The architecture of the composition the sweep of
a broad "U" is the same as that of "Las Meninas" and
"Las Lanzas". But here none of the figures is individualized.
The forms are reduced to phantom-like splashes of colour
in juxtaposition which nevertheless blend to give the effect of
vibrating light. Velazquez's technique was an innovation for
his age. The Impressionists took this discovery to its extreme,
making the elements explode into particules of colour. "The
Spinners" in fact is several paintings in one. To some people
it is the mythological story of Minerva and Arachne. To
those in search of a subject it is a tapestry workshop with
women busy in the foreground, and in the background visitors
inspecting a finished work. Admirers of Impressionist
painting see it as a treatment of problems of light and
atmosphere, with a dark foreground and a luminious back¬
ground. To lovers of abstract art it is a superb play of
strokes and colours. The work is now in the Prado Museum.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
THE UPS & DOWNS OF FAME
by Juan de Contreras, Marquis of Lozoya
Professor of the History of Art, University of Madrid
and author of "Historia del Arte Hispánico"
Good fortune always attended the
affairs of Diego Velazquez. And
this year's tercentenary of his
death comes at a time when his work
is . attracting widespread attention
throughout the world. His few au-,
thentic paintings now fetch fabulous
prices and his works are reproduced
and commented upon in albums and
art books of high standard.
Yet world fame neither came swiftly
to Velazquez nor remained constant
and unfluctuating as was the case
with such artists as Raphael, Titian
and Rubens; it has, in fact, known
many ups and downs.
During his lifetime, Velazquez en¬
joyed both in his art and his everyday
life the satisfying knowledge that he
was greatly esteemed. In his early
youth while a student in the cele¬
brated art school of Seville under
Francis Pacheco, he was the "favour¬
ite" of the noblemen and scholars
who were drawn to his master's stu¬
dio, and the idea of sending him to
the Court of Philip IV certainly origi¬
nated here.
At the Court of the King of Spain,
master of the greatest monarchy the
world had ever known, the paintings
of Velazquez, as the preferred artist
of so discriminating a connoisseur as
Philip IV, were extolled by the pam¬
phleteers and sung by the poets who
abounded in Madrid during" the reign
of the House of Austria. Velazquez
also knew fame abroad. During his
second visit to Roane several of his
works were exhibited in the portico
of Agrippa's Pantheon, and astound¬
ed the city's art lovers.
Though the esteem of his contem¬
poraries was undoubtedly .the most
powerful stimulus in the artist's life,
the practical effects were limited and
transitory. The immediaite impact of
Velazquez's work was slight and
short-lived even in Spain itself, where
only a few of his pupils, such as Juan
del Mazo, continued his style of
painting for a brief period. Outside
the Peninsula he exerted no influence
whatsoever.
Velazquez lived at a time when the
power of the Spanish monarchy was
in decline. Spain withdrew into her¬
self, allowing the glory of Louis XTV to
spread over Europe. With Louis XIV
came, the triumph of official "Acade¬
my" art. With the kings of the Bour¬
bon dynasty in Madrid came French
and Italian painters Rano, Houasse,
Van Loo, Giaquinto, Amicoini, Tiepolo
and anany others 'and the surviving
heirs of ¡the olid Spanish school were
completely ignored.
Thus the art circles of the 18th
century were unaware of the work of
the genius of Seville, for most of his
paintings remained locked away in
the palaces of Madrid and Vienna.
No more than a few were glimpsed by
some discerning minds and aroused
interest. One great painter, Sir
Joshua Reynolds, declared the por¬
trait of Pope Innocent X to be the
finest painting in Rome.
The works of -Velazquez became
better known and appreciated in the
19th century following their dispersal
during the Peninsula War. Yet the
Spanish painter who enjoyed the most
esteem among critics and collectors
during the first half of that century
was Murillo. But then travel became
easier and it was possible to study
and copy the pictures of Velazquez
hanging in the Prado and the galle¬
ries of London and Vienna.
During .the second half of the 19th
century, when realism predominated
in art and literature, critics and ar¬
tists came to realize that, in terms of
placing subjects in an authentic
setting, of illuminating them with
'true and natural light and of cap¬
turing the essential qualities of ob¬
jects, Diego Velazquez was the great¬
est painter of all times.
It has been said that all who paint¬
ed well at that period had learned
from him. Solomon Reinaeh went so
far as to say, in a work as well known
as his "'Apollo", which became a text¬
book in every European art school,
that from the professional point of
view Velazquez represented the sum¬
mit of world painting.
Towards the turn of the century,
interest in Velazquez's paintings be¬
gan to decline. Critics and painters,
strongly influenced by contemporary
literature, found the Spanish painter
cold and lacking in emotion; they
would concede only that he was a
superb exponent of "photographic
art". Among the artists of .the Span¬
ish school the long-forgotten El
Greco became the favourite painter
and within a decade his renown had
spread with astonishing rapidity
among all art lovers. This period too
marked the beginning of the world¬
wide acclaim for Francisco Goya.
The Unesco Courier wishes to thank Editions du Dimanche, Paris,
for making available many of the black and white reproductions of the
works of Velazquez published in this special issue. These reproduc¬
tions are taken from a remarkable album, "Velazquez", prepared for
Editions du Dimanche by the late Anna Marsan (Text by Léon-Paul
Fargue) and printed in 1946.
In our own time when art is exclu¬
sively preoccupied by the balance of
volumes and masses and by chromatic
harmonies, the paintings of Velaz¬
quez, who resolved these problems in
incomparable fashion three centuries
ago, are being studied with growing
interest.
Three centuries after Velazquez,
another Andalusian artist, Pablo Ruiz
Picasso, has taken Las Meninas, and
in a totally different atmosphere,
dissected the composition in a series
of nuore than 50 paintings.
VELAZQUEZ
COLOUR SLIDES
An important exhibition of
the works of Velazquez, as¬
sembled from many countries,
opens in Madrid on December
3 to mark the 300th anniversary
of the death of the Spanish
artist. The exhibition will con¬
tinue until February 28, 1961.
For this occasion the Spanish
National Commission for Unes¬
co has undertaken, in conjunc¬
tion with Publications Filmées
d'Art et d'Histoire, the publi¬
cation of a collection of colour¬
ed slides of Velazquez's work.
The slides are presented in
plastic boxes, each consisting
of 20 framed slides (5x5 cms)
of works photographed at the
Prado Museum, Madrid, and
in other countries. Each box
is accompanied by a booklet
written by Enrico Lafuente Fer¬
rari, Director of the Museum
of Modern Art, Madrid.
The collections will be avail¬
able before the end of the
year in three language edi¬
tions: English, French and
Spanish. The price of each
box in France and other coun¬
tries (carriage paid) is 30 NF
or equivalent. A special price
of 25 NF applies to educational
and cultural institutions. In the
U.S.A. and Canada the price
is $9 U.S.; in Australia, £ A4.
The Velazquez colour slides
will be on sale at the Unesco
Gift Shop, Place de Fontenoy,
Paris, and at the Madrid exhi¬
bitions. ORDERS SHOULD
NOT BE SENT TO UNESCO.
For further information or to
order by post, write to Publi¬
cations Filmées d'Art et d'His¬
toire, 44, rue du Dragon,
Paris (6e).
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. December 1960
Rapid Strokes of brown and gold
reveal Velazquez's technique in this
detail of "The Jester, Antonio The
Englishman". Antonio, a dwarf,
carries a hat decorated with long
white plumes and in the full painting
is seen beside a huge dog, almost as
high as himself. Prado Museum.
Anderson © Editions du Diman-
, che, from the album "Velazquez"
Little White Dog is a detail from
a portrait of Prince Philip Prosper
óf Spain which was painted by Velaz¬
quez in 1659. Vienna Museum.
Dominguez-Garcia, Madrid
Still Life Study is a detail from
Velazquez's "Christ in the House of
Martha". Velazquez situated his painting
in the kitchen of the house with a
woman and young girl attending to the
preparation of a meal. The religious
subject, Christ talking to Martha and
Mary, he placed in the background as
a picture hanging on the kitchen wall.
Now in the National Gallery, London.
Anderson © Editions du Diman¬
che, from the album "Velazquez''
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Anderson© Editions du Dimanche, from the album "Velazquez"
Surrender of Breda. Detail of the great composition painting (1635) published in our centre page
which is widely regarded as one of the greatest historical works in European painting. From the
heads of the Spanish and Dutch leaders to the vast landscape with the fires of Breda smoking on
the horizon, the work is one of striking originality. It reveals a gayer and richer use of colours than
Velazquez had hitherto employed. Velazquez was inspired to paint the surrender scene after he
had travelled to Italy with General Spinola, the Spanish commander, in 1629. Prado Museum.
THE MAN IN THE TREASURE
TOWER OF THE ALCAZAR
by F.J. Sanchez Canton
Director, Prado Museum, Madrid
W7
^^f^Lf e are indebted to Ortega y Gasset for a
^m ^F number of apt, though at times extreme com-
» » ments on Velazquez which, by virtue of the
philosopher's authority and the magic of his style, have
helped to establish the currently accepted view of the man
and the artist.
The chief points Ortega y Gasset makes are these :
The life of Velazquez was one of the simplest that
a human being has ever lived ;
As far as can be ascertained, only one important
event marked his life : his appointment as the King's
painter... when he was only twenty-four ;
It is not clear whether (his life) was that of a
painter or of a gentleman of the Court ;
Deep down in his heart, he was driven by one per¬
vading thought to become a nobleman... but this
road was closed to him ;
At the very threshhold of his youth he discovered
the most extraordinary gift for art... Nevertheless, he
did not want and never wanted to be a painter ;
34 CONT'D ON PAGE 3 6
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. December 1960
Anderson© Editions du Dimanche, from the album "Velazquez"
Pope Innocent X. Few paintings have aroused such instantaneous enthusiam as the seated portrait of
Innocent X which Velazquez did in Rome in 1650. The Pontiff was 76 at the time. Velazquez made
no attempt to flatter his features, but revealed him to us with implacable objectivity, yet with dignity and
grandeur. Schopenhauer saw in the painting the "majesty of the earth" and Reynolds pronounced it "the
finest picture in Rome" and condescended to copy it. The painting is remarkable not only for the vivid¬
ness and vigour of the face and eyes, but also for the masterly harmonizing of crimson, white and gold.
Illustration shows detail of the head. The painting now hangs in the Doria Pamphili Gallery, Rome.
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
MAN OF THE ALCAZAR (Cont'd from page 34)
He is a painter who distinguishes himself by the
smallness of his output... I maintain that no painter
had more time to paint.
In addition, Ortega asserts that Velazquez dM not finish
his canvasses.
These isolated quotations from the philosopher's
conclusions raise many problems. Without wishing to
cross swords with him, I should like to set forth very
briefly facts and considerations concerning them so that
the reader can judge for himself as to the nature of this
extraordinary artist.
It may seem unnecessary to go into the question of
Velazquez's physical appearance and personality, since
we know what he looked like firom portraits of him and
have some insight into his personality not only from his
works of art but also from what ¡his contemporaries wrote
about him.
"He did portraits of himself on various occasions",
wrote the Spanish art critic and painter Palomino in
1724, basing his statement on the biography of Alfaro,
a disciple of Velazquez. Yet a careful study of the suppos¬
ed self-portraits of the artist reveals that they do not
portray the same person.
In point of fact there is only one self-portrait
which can be regarded as authentic, the one
in Las Meninas. He is also shown with his
back to us in a painting, entitled The Mazo Family, which
is the work of another artist. Velazquez is here seen
painting the portrait of the Infanta Dona Margarita.
And what, one may ask, of the portrait of Velazquez
in The Surrender of Breda, and the heads and ¡half-length
portraits also said to represent ¡him ?
The light-skinned, fair-haired young man who is seen
between the horse and the right-hand edge of the canvas
in the Surrender of Breda (see centre pages) cannot be
Velazquez who .twenty years later depicted ¡himself as
swarthy, with jet-black (hair in Las Meninas. Nor do
the two figures (have (the same nose.
The slight resemblance may be explained by the simi¬
larity to be found between people who dress in the same
fashion and by the fact that Juan Velazquez, the artist's
brother, wiith whom he perhaps shared some physical
likenesses, may have been the model for the portrait.
As for ithe other portraits referred to, including the one
in .the Valencia Museum, these are accepted by scholars
only with great reservation.
If we take as our guide the two undisputed pictures
of Velazquez, we note that he appears as a slightly-built
man, not more than five feet three inches tall and well-
proportioned. His large head seems even more massive
because of the crop of thick, long hair. His eyes, neither
deep-set nor prominent, look out beneath a rounded
forehead and well-spaced, arched eyebrows. Beneath his
fleshy nose is a broad mouth with protruding lower lip,
a thick moustache and a strong chin.
At the age of fifty-seven, he had neither the grey hair
nor wrinkles of advancing age, and three years later, if
we are to judge from the painting in Vienna, he was
still a fine figure of a man and of such bearing that the
Venetian poet Boschini wrote of him :
Cavalier che spirava un gran decoro
Quanto ogn'altra autorevole persona
36
Prado Museum, Madrid
King Philip IV, painted in 1656. Prado Museum.
Domingeuz-Garcia, Madrid
The Infanta Margarita, in blue. 1659. Vienna Museum.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Hermitage Museum, Moscow
The Duke of Olivares. About 1638-40. Hermitage Museum.
Dominguez-Garcia, Madrid
Prince Balthasar Carlos. About 1640-42. Vienna Museum.
The Unesco Courier. December 1960
(A gentleman with an air of great dignity
. like all persons of high degree).
The personal distinction of Velazquez was heightened
by the care with which he dressed. Six suits of clothes,
various accessories and eleven hats are mentioned in
the inventory of his possessions drawn up after his death.
The only woman in Velazquez's life about which
anything is known is his wife Juana de Miranda, the
daughter of his art 'teacher, who was not yet seventeen
when he married her just before his nineteenth birthday.
Their marriage lasted throughout their lives and both
died within a week of each other.
Did Velazquez ever paint his devoted and self-effacing
wife ?
In all likelihood, she posed before their marriage for
the Virgin in The Immaculate Conception and, as a young
bride, for two religious works, The Adoration of the Magi
and Saint Ildefonso Donning the Chasuble. She is also
thought to have been the model for Head in Profile
which is in the Lázaro Museum, Madrid, and The Sybil
or The Painter's Wife, now in .the Prado. In the back¬
ground of the Vienna canvas, she is seen walking towards
Velazquez accompanied by a grandchild. She is a
silhouette, a mere shadow in this work, but was she, in
fact, anything more than a shadow in the painter's
household, more than a quiet island in the stormy sea
of the Court ?
\7
^Ä# ELAZQUEZ appears to have led a sober and re-
Wr served life. Nevertheless, there were three
» women who interested and perhaps fascinated
him,' the models for his Venus and Cupid, The Spin¬
ners and The Lady with a Fan all of them unknown.
In examining the list of books in Velazquez's personal
library we are surprised by the absence of certain authors
and the presence of others. Certain works are exactly
what one would expect to find there, and all in all
they enable us to break through the artist's reserve. The
list contains 156 titles, only one of which Is religious.
But the fact is that his library included very few literary
works either : one novel, not a particularly good one at
that, an anthology of poetry, Spanish translations of
Horace, and Ovid's MefcamorpTioses, a volume in Italian
of Petrarch and Ariosto's Orlando Furioso.
Philosophy was represented by Aristotle's Politics and
Ethics. The only volumes of history in 'the collection were
classical works by ¡Livy and Quintus Curcius Rufus, a
book on the Flemish wars and two or three other un¬
identified titles.
This dearth is compensated for by the abundance of
treatises on painting and sculpture (including Leonardo
da Vinci's Art of Painting published in Paris in 1651) and
an equal number of volumes on architecture. In addition
there were many works on arithmetic, geometry and
perspective, a knowledge of which is basic to the art of
drawing. The professional side of his library also contain¬
ed at least four treatises on anatomy as well as Albrecht
Durer's Symmetry of the Human Body and works on
archaeology, mythology and iconology.
It was to be expected that such books would be found
on his shelves when on August 29, 1660 the executors of
Velazquez's will drew up their inventory of his vault-
ceiling appartment in the Treasure Tower of the Alcazar
Palace at Madrid. The library was one befitting a
cultivated artist.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
MAN OF THE ALCAZAR (Cont'd)
Anderson © Editions du Dimanche, from the album "Velazquez"
Joseph's Coat. Detail of a work painted in Rome in 1630
together with "The Forge of Vulcan", both pictures marking
the end of the first period in Velazquez's art. The painter
was at this time influenced by the Italian masters whose
works he had studied in Venice. Escorial Palace, Madrid.
Prado Museum, Madrid
The Fountain of the Tritons. Another detail full of grace
and elegance of this composition one of Velazquez's last
works (see page 23). The gallant and his lady who is seated
close to the fountain, might easily be taken for figures from
some of the gay scenes painted by Watteau. Prado Museum.
But the executors also found on the shelves other books
which give us a glimpse of Velazquez's more intimate
tastes and interests. Concern with questions of health
may account for the presence of several books on medi¬
cine and health administration and another entitled
Treasure of the Poor.
Surprising in so clear-minded a man as Velazquez,
however, is his apparent interest in "the arts that should
not be studied" (las artes non cumplidores) and hence the
presence in his library of almanacs, calendars and books
on the movement of the planets. It is even stranger to
come upon Giovanni Battista idella Porta's On Physio¬
gnomy and Jean Taisnier's Art of Divination and Intro¬
duction to Astrology.
T1
H-^w rom the time he entered 'the king's service as
I court artist and portrait painter, Velazquez's
-^^- relations with Philip IV developed rapidly into
a friendship which was not to end until the artist's death.
Although remuneration in the royal household was
always insufficient and overdue, Velazquez's situation was
improved by successive royal favours.
It is commonly, though incorrectly, asserted that the
non-artistic activities involved in Velazquez's various
functions took up too much of his time. Inasmuch as
there exist many documents pertaining to this "sphere
of his activity, there can be no doubt that the time
employed in such prosaic, bureaucratic tasks was not to
38
the detriment of his painting. If he was not a prolific
artist it was because of his phlegmatic temperament, his
studiousness, his meditative nature and the great pains
he took in the practise of his art.
His relations with the court and the king's protection
must have rekindled 'the pretension to nobility of the
ancient da Silva family of Oporto and have aroused envy
among painters and courtiers.
His association with noblemen and dignitaries height¬
ened the artist's desire to rise in the social scale, and he
never lacked royal favour. The decree "I appoint Velaz¬
quez" which Phillip IV wrote in the margin of the report
submitted by the Palace Council for the appointment of
a gentleman usher (the decree ran counter to the recom¬
mendation of all its members) ; and his order: "Set
down that his quality is evident to me" with which the
monarch put an end to 'the doubts of the authorities
who had investigated Velazquez's qualifications for
admission to the Military Order of Saint James, were
energetic, perhaps arbitrary acts which revealed the
king's singular admiration and affection.
Velazquez responded to such marked favour with loyal
service and took great, care that his conduct and style
of life be in keeping with that of the perfect courtier,
a man worthy of attaining the "'highest honours", as
Palomino' put it. This explains why his library contained
works on courtiers, knighthood, the art of archery and
hunting, and why in keeping with his wish to become an
accomplished courtier he wished to Uve like a gentleman
and be surrounded by fine 'furniture, jewels, tapestries
and books.
o
z
<
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Prince Balthasar Carlos on Horseback. Portrait painted about 1634 of the son of
King Philip IV of Spain, patron and friend of Velazquez. Now in the Prado Museum.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
THE SPINNERS. Detail
from one of Velazquez's
most famous paintings"Las
Hilanderas ", representing
women in a tapestry works.
Prado Museum, Madrid.
>
y
]]>
</page>
</document>
