<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="064833eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
Youth
^&
m
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A time to live...
35 American Samoa
Pensive pupils of Pago Pago
Pupils from a girls' school in Pago Pago, capital
of American Samoa, examine a sample of
plankton during an offshore science field trip.
The development of school and out-of-school
teaching of science and technology is an impor¬
tant aspect of Unesco's Major Progamme V,
Education, Training and Society. A special ef¬
fort is made to support activities designed to give
girls and women improved access to education
and training in science and technology.
Photo Deighton Emmons Jr. Reprinted with permission from 77ie
Science Teacher. Published by the National Science Teachers'
Association, USA
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Courier
A window open on the worià
Editorial
FOLLOWING one another as they do in rapid success¬
ion, International "Years" have a tendency to
become International "Yawns". Although they
often achieve positive results, which seldom seem to receive
the publicity they deserve, when the 365 days are up we tend
to consider the chapter closed.
1985, International Youth Year, is different. Youth is the
opening chapter of a book we cannot put down. Further¬
more, we are all experts, so we believe, on youth because we
were all young once. This does not, however, prevent us
from expressing largely irrelevant opinions on what we label
' 'The Problem of Youth" . They are irrelevant because socie¬
ty does not face a "problem of youth"; on the contrary,
young people are faced with the problems of society, yet have
little or no opportunity to express their opinions as to what
should be done to resolve them.
This is why, in preparing this issue of the Unesco Courier,
we decided to throw it open to the voice of youth. In addition
to assessments of the situation of young people in various
parts of the world compiled by the editors of twelve of our
thirty-one language editions, we publish the results of a
worldwide inquiry carried out within a cross-section of inter¬
national youth in which young people themselves tell us
about their hopes and fears for themselves and for society to¬
day and in the future.
Six young people provide us with a more personal insight
into their way of life three of them describe in detail the
happenings of a single, ordinary day, while the other three
offer more general reflections.
The experts too have their say. Not faceless experts but
men and women who work with young people and who
represent a new loving and caring, down-to-earth approach
to youth.
We pride ourselves that this is also the Unesco approach.
Without exception, all Unesco's programmes are designed in
such a way as not only to help youth, but also to demand
their active participation.
In an uncertain world, young people, who constitute
forty-five per cent of the world's population, bear a major
portion of the burdens of poverty, hunger, unemployment
and violence. Perhaps this is as it should be. After all, no one
can deny that they stand accused, as did William Pitt, who
became prime minister of England at the age of 24, of "the
atrocious crime of being young".
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
June 1985
38th year
á¡P\
Emblem of International Youth Year
Photo © United Nations
4 In search of the present
by Eduardo Khaliffé
8 That first job
12 World Congress on Youth
An open letter from the Mayor of Barcelona
13 A Unesco Courier International Survey
The voice of youth from every continent
18 A day in the life of...
Three young people recount
the happenings of a typical day
20 Spotlight on youth
The Arab World, Belgium, Brazil, Catalonia, Finland, India,
Italy, Republic of Korea, Pakistan, Senegal, Switzerland,
United Republic of Tanzania, Thailand, USSR
25 Streets apart
by Merrick Fall
28 Africa's generation gap
by Boubakar Ly
32 China's most precious energy source
by Tang Ruoxin
34 A truce for children
by Hélène Ahrweiler
2 A time to live...
AMERICAN SAMOA: Pensive pupils of Pago Pago
Published monthly in 31 languages
by Unesco,
The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Malaysian
Korean
Swahili
Croato-Serb
Macedonian
Serbo-Croat
Slovene
Chinese
Bulgarian
Greek
Sinhala
Finnish
Swedish
Basque
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French,
Spanish and Korean
N° 6 - 1985 - OPI - 85 - 1 423 A
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
by Eduardo Khaliffé
THE fact that every generation asks
its parents about the meaning of life
is nothing new. It is not unusual for
young people to ask whatever questions are
necessary until they have passed through all
the physical, emotional and intellectual
stages involved in growing up. Youth is very
old, and whether or not it realizes that its
qualities have persisted down the centuries,
it is eternally condemned to rechart its own
course under a crossfire of myths, norms
and sanctions. As it makes its way into the
social arena of its time, it illustrates the
eternal polarity of humankind the
simultaneous existence of the old and the
new, sharing a moment in time and place in
the cycle of evolution.
As a rule, however, society tolerates the
rhetorical profanation of its conventions
as part of a ritual devoid of faith. Taking
refuge in "common sense" ("we were all
young once"), it grants its young people a
brief margin of tolerance while seeking ex¬
planations for their behaviour. In fact,
adult society prefers to believe in the
biblical maxim that "what will be will be,
what has been done will be done again, and
there is nothing new under the sun".
As the Italian film-maker and writer Pier
Paolo Pasolini once wrote, youth possesses
a "readiness to believe" which strictly
speaking lies in its inclination not to believe,
in its desire to challenge and contradict the
biblical prophecy, in its eagerness to rebel
against the squandering of its energy and
the restriction of its action and thought to a
social routine that admits no change.
These attitudes led to the extraordinary
revolt which took the West by surprise in
the late 1960s and early 1970s, when
political thought rediscovered its kinship
with poetry, as shown by the passionate
slogans scrawled on the walls of Paris and
the flowers planted in the barrels of guns.
Few attempts have been made to identify
the source and explain the widespread im¬
pact of this movement. But there is no
doubt that the events of May 1968 in Paris,
and the demonstrations at Kent State
University and on Tlatelolco square in Mex¬
ico City (important manifestations of a
more general movement) helped to create in
young people a universal awareness of their
existence, a feeling that they belonged to the
same tremor of renewal that shook the
organs of power not only in the capitals of
the industrialized world but also in the poor
and dependent countries.
Looking back today, many people pro¬
bably remember those days with the feeling
that they had worshipped an illusion. But it
was an illusion that set off a social alarm
bell and mobilized vast intellectual and
material resources, in some cases to inter¬
pret the syndrome of revolt, and in others to
exorcise it by violence.
In Latin America events often ended in
bloodshed. Writing in 1969 about young
people, the Mexican author Octavio Paz
said, "Society mimics them and by mimick¬
ing them it exorcises them. For a few weeks
it abdicates its authority, giving free rein to
the blasphemies and sacrileges of the
In search of
"Youth is very old and whether or not it
realizes that its qualities have persisted
down the centuries, it is eternally con¬
demned to rechart Its own course, under
a crossfire of myths, norms and sanc¬
tions". Young people today are creating
and affirming their own values vis-à-vis
adult society, joinedbya sense ofbelong¬
ing to a vast group with a shared sensi¬
bility, tastes and ways of living.
Demographically speaking, today's is a
youthful world, for young people con-
"
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
the present
stitute 45% of world population. In 1975
there were 730 million people between
the ages of 15 and 24. This figure is ex¬
pected to rise to 1, 180 million by the year
2000an Increase of 60% in 25years. It is
estimated that the number of young peo¬
ple In the developing countries will In¬
crease by 80% between now and the end
of the century, as against 5% in the in¬
dustrialized countries. Below, a crowd of
young people during a mass meeting in
Italy.
w&BS$t3X&
young, then it reasserts itself more
thoroughly in ruthless repression".
Supported by political doctrines or issu¬
ing a challenge to orthodoxy, the youth
movement aimed to give new life to certain
elementary truths by rescuing them from
the mechanistic rationality of established
authority. It looked for certainties which, in
face of the intolerable pressures of the pre¬
sent, are axiomatic for perceptive humani¬
ty: the struggle against war and the rejection
of all unjustified forms of violence.
This appeal to conscience was made with
the lucidity of the emotions rather than with
practical clearsightedness. Subsequently,
with ill-concealed contempt, political
theory and sociology passed the buck to
other disciplines such as psychology and
education. Hope and the spirit of transcen¬
dent excitement died, and were replaced by
a purely psychological interest, sometimes
not devoid of precision and honesty, in the
rebellious masses, their rowdy behaviour,
their group attitudes, their iconoclastic
ideas, their ego, their superego, their ideal
self. Much of this interest was prompted by
a desire to convert the social styles of young
people into consumer goods. Think of the
sophistication of the "youth" industry
films, records, clothing which has
developed since the years of revolt. Teenage
violence, drug use by the young, the conflict
between the generations, all fuelled the
curiosity of the news media, and many of
this generation of young people ended up
on the psychiatrist's couch.
Then came the creation of cultural codes,
fashions and social habits which are pale
copies of the spirit of "disobedient" youth,
although the relationship is not
acknowledged. But this is not an attempt to
compare the young of that time with those
of today in the expansive cultures of the
West.
It is pointless to speculate about the dif¬
ferences between the "beat generation"
and the generation of "Saturday night
fever", or to review young people's forms
of expression, whether authentic or not, in
the societies of Europe and North America.
This is a very complex situation which we
tend to simplify through a mixture of ig¬
norance and confusion, obscure com¬
ponents of our own way of life.
We must accept the mounting influx into
Latin America of goods produced for the
youth market by the powerful commercial
forces of the industrialized countries. This
penetration revives in us the painful convic¬
tion that we were born in a second-rate con¬
tinent, at the same time possessing the
customs and inner thoughts of another
culture and language. A sense of internal
exile has grown in us, haunting the empty
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
spaces of our consciousness. This terrible
dichotomy is nothing new, for Latin
America is an amalgam of divisions. If we
look at our hybrid continent we find what
the Mexican philosopher and writer
Leopoldo Zea has called "the source of all
its ambiguity and ambivalence". We find a
Latin American "who is equally ill at ease
with his father's people and his mother's.
Rejected by one group, he is ashamed to
belong to the other".
Here comics compete with ancient
legends. The culture of the future and the
culture of the past, the tormentor and his
victim rub shoulders on the street. To
whom, then, do we refer when we speak of
the young? Here, as in so many other fields,
our diversity betrays us. For if we agree to
be this multiple species, what right do we
have to speak of youth as a single entity in
Latin America?
We can always repeat that ours is a young
continent. The extraordinary thing is that
the origins of its culture and history are so
far-flung and so varied. For instance, we
never cease to be surprised on discovering
our remotest pastthe delicately
reconstituted objects of pottery and bone,
the carvings and paintings through which
their authors have triumphed over time. We
are familiar with cities built over the re¬
mains of colonial cities which themselves
stood on the ruins of Amerindian set¬
tlements, traces of which survive in the
"On a continent where entire generations
are condemned to unemployment, ig¬
norance and all the other symptoms of
underdevelopment and poverty, there is
no alternative but to fight to conquer the
present, especially when the boundary
between childhood and youth is steadily
fading. Who could tell the exact age of the
millions of child workers In Latin America
today?" Left, a youth dressed as a miner
at a folk festival in Chile.
"We Latin Americans... are 'young' in the
sense that we are subject to the tutelage
ofan 'adult' world dedicated to the task of
'guiding' our economic, cultural and
political destiny..." "Young Latin
Americans have always been required to
be 'the country's future'. In other words,
we spend one half of our lives represen¬
ting the future and the other bearing the
weight of the past." Below, young
women from a shanty-town, Santiago de
Chile.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
form of societies whose existence is
tolerated because of the inertia of the
system.
The urgent demand for a hearing voiced
by the young is that of a whole continent ex¬
pressing the primordial truths of its ex¬
istence in defiance of the powers opposed to
it. This insistence on expression has been
dearly bought throughout our history, for
Latin America is a continent of violence.
Rarely has the silence of so many succeeded
in denouncing the cruelty and ferocity en¬
dured by a people as have the silenced
voices of the thousands who disappeared
under Latin American dictatorships
whole generations of young people
obliterated from their time by imprison¬
ment and exile.
We Latin Americans do not have the con¬
trol of our destiny that would enable us to
avoid courses that are harmful to us and
choose those that suit us. To this extent we
are "young", in the sense that we are sub¬
ject to the tutelage of an "adult" world
dedicated to the task of "guiding" our
economic, cultural and political destiny.
Even for its people, Latin America is still El
Dorado, a dream created and pursued by
other worlds which conquer it and then
deny its existence. "America's specific Uto¬
pian future has not been given expression,"
says the Argentine essayist Horacio Cerutti,
"simply because America has no future
or what amounts to the same thing it is
pure future with no present". What does
this present mean for us?
Latin America, it is said, "is a land of
hope and promise". Thus we are granted
the dubious destiny of crossing an expanse
of time without definition, of involvement
in a cycle of events that is never completed,
of sowing our seed in an instant that is a fic¬
tion of the present.
Young Latin Americans have always
been required to be "the country's future".
In other words, we spend one half of our
lives representing the future, and the other
bearing the weight of the past.
It is natural that young people should
associate themselves with the defence of
life. This gives them an identity as a group,
although it is not enough to transform them
into "agents of history". Nevertheless, on a
continent where entire generations are con¬
demned to unemployment, ignorance and
all the other symptoms of under¬
development and poverty, there is no alter¬
native but to fight to conquer the present,
especially when the boundary between
childhood and youth is steadily fading.
Who could tell the age of the millions of
child workers in Latin America today?
The young people of Latin America have
not faltered in the struggle to recover the
present. They are espousing universal
values while discovering their own identity,
and are imaginatively conscious of the
historical and cultural depth of their past.
In their hands culture is a feast at which
they simultaneously create and com¬
memorate. The cultural and social expres¬
sions of this sense of purpose have ceased to
be marginal and are becoming progressively
stronger.
Young people are emerging from the
cultural isolation in which they awaited the
moment when society would allow it to take
possession of its heritage. They are flinging
themselves into every collective movement
which enables them to live fully in their
time.
EDUARDO KHALIFFE, a young Ecuadorian
journalist, has produced a series of television
programmes entitled "Identidad" on his coun¬
try's traditional cultural values. He has taken
part in programmes produced by the Andine
television service created by the Cartagena
Agreement, to which Venezuela, Colombia,
Ecuador, Peru and Bolivia are parties.
"We must accept the mounting influx into
Latin America of goods produced for the
youth market by the powerful commercial
forces of the industrialized countries".
This penetration "revives in us the pain¬
ful conviction that we were born in a
'second-rate' continent, at the same time
possessing the customs and inner
thoughts of another culture and
language". Above, U.S. pop star Michael
Jackson, the idol of millions of young
people in Latin America and elsewhere,
during a concert.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
That first
©
A survey o/"The situation; the attitudes and life styles of
young industrial workers" was recently undertaken by the
International Councilfor Social Sciences at Unesco 's request
and with itsfinancial backing. The survey covered six coun¬
tries of varying degrees of industrialization: relatively in¬
dustrialized (Hungary and Spain), intermediate (India and
Uruguay), recently becoming industrialized (Senegal and
Algeria). Some six hundred young people from four con¬
tinents were interviewedfor the survey on whosefindings the
article below is based.
FOR young people today, getting
their first job means not only the
assurance of an income still, asjn^
the past, an overriding motivation tjt '
also the assertion of their personal identity,
a way of proving that they "exisf'through
the exercise of what they view as a creative
activity.
They are aware that in getting their first
job they acquire a new social status and a
new life style which differs from that of a
student still dependent upon his family and
even more so from that of the unemployed
for whom life is a matter of privation and
bare survival. In other words, they realize
that becoming employed is the natural con¬
clusion of a long period of apprenticeship
for entry into society, the preparation for
which both in the home and at school has
basically been a preparation for work.
This hoped-for incorporation into the
world of work is no easy matter. Not only
8
are employment opportunities rare (in all
the countries surveyed except Hungary), it
is also virtually impossible for most young
people to find the kind of work for which
they have been trained and to which they
aspire. Those who are lucky enough to find
their first job quickly, because they are
assumed to lack professional experience
and skills, are often subject to various kinds
of overt or covert discrimination, even
though they may be doing exactly the same
tasks as older or longer-serving employees.
Thus the search for a job is a difficult and
chancy undertaking which is not always
crowned with success. Having just left
school or technical institute, where they had
their place and a task to fulfil and where
they were known and esteemed by their col¬
leagues, those young people who do not
land that first job they were so eagerly look¬
ing forward to have to face up for the first
time to unemployment, a situation for
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
which neither family nor school has
prepared them. This unemployment and the
marginalization that goes with it brings on
a period of crisis and a questioning of the
social and cultural values previously
assimilated.
A "baptism of fire" of this sort is a fairly
common experience among young boys and
girls in the countries covered by the survey,
although it varies, of course, according to
the nature of the obstacles encountered, the
type of society and family to which they
belong, as well as to the age, sex and
temperament of the individual concerned.
In this respect, the survey indicates that the
categories of young people most affected
are girls, younger youths and those with
little or no schooling.
In some cases, finding employment may
depend more . on chance, family cir¬
cumstances and contacts than on personal
qualifications. In others, possession of a
diploma or sound practical experience may
offer the key to a job. Except in Hungary,
where formal education seems to be a sure
road to employment (although not
necessarily in the kind of job desired), in all
the countries surveyed the links between
education and employment are often in¬
direct and uncertain.
In Spain, for example, the findings of the
survey reveal a gap between the educational
system and the needs of the economy and
the labour market. In Uruguay, most of the
young people interviewed thought that for¬
mal education had been of little or no use to
them either in obtaining a job or in perfor¬
ming tasks assigned to them. Nevertheless,
they considered their studies useful from
the point of view of personal development,
status and social contacts and felt that they
might later facilitate promotion and ad¬
vancement, for example, from manual
worker to office employee.
Of the six countries surveyed, Hungary
appears to be a case apart and, generally
speaking, stands out in marked contrast to
the others. Development of secondary and
higher education in Hungary seems to have
outpaced the evolution of the labour
market and, although there is no unemploy¬
ment, young people of both sexes are often
over-qualified for the work they do. This
results in a certain tension between the
world of education and that of labour, since
the former is relatively homogeneous and
there is a tendency for educational levels to
rise, whereas wide differences persist in the
labour market as regards types of job and
the degree of personal satisfaction that they
offer.
The phenomenon of "over-
qualification" also appears to be very
significant in India and Senegal, where a
high proportion of the young people inter¬
viewed said that the education they had
received was above the level needed for the
work they were doing or, in the case of
those who were unemployed, of the jobs
available. This state of affairs is more
prevalent in the large urban centres, where
improvements in the education system are
more in evidence. In the cities, semi-
qualified young people are increasingly
entering the "informal" sector of the
economy, which is growing and spreading
to the city outskirts.
Unlike general education, specialized
training for a specific job facilitates obtain¬
ing employment and the desired level of
wages. In this respect, boys seem to be in a
more favourable position than girls. In
Hungary, for instance, most of the students
in technical schools are boys, whereas in
secondary schools the girls are in the ma¬
jority. As a result, the girls have a higher
level of general education, but the boys are
better placed for getting employment.
Facilities for obtaining technical training
vary, sometimes quite widely, from one
country to another. In Hungary, for exam¬
ple, technical training is only obtainable in
specialized schools, whereas in Uruguay
many young people get their technical train¬
ing "on. the job", in work centres where
they enter as apprentices, or in the family,
where skills are transmitted to them by their
parents. These differences have evident
consequences from both the legal and the
employment point of view. As a general
rule, young workers in the industrialized
countries (in this case Hungary) are legally
and socially better protected than their
counterparts in the developing world who
acquire their training empirically.
It is harder for adolescents than for
adults to find permanent employment. Ac¬
cording to those interviewed, there are
several reasons for this. Many employers
are reluctant to employ young people
because they think that they are more
accident-prone or that they will reduce the ^
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
WORLD DEVELOPED COUNTRIES
1960 Mm
Á
DEVELOPING
COUNTRIES
1982
Enrolment at 1 st level / 2nd level / 3rd level / 1 st level .' 2nd level . 3rd level ' ' 1 st level / 2nd level / 3rd level
Changes in the educational pyramid by sex between 1960
and 1982 by regions (male first level enrolment = 100)
Source: A Summary
Statistical Review of
Education in the World,
1960-1982, Unesco
rate of output; others want to avoid addi¬
tional training costs or fear the interrup¬
tions caused by absences for military ser¬
vice, in the case of boys, and by pregnan¬
cies, in the case of girls; finally, young
workers are often considered to be more
recalcitrant and more likely to make trouble
than adults or immigrant workers.
Because of these prejudices, many young
people work without permanent contracts
or any social security protection and in
practice become part of a "parallel" or
"underground" economy. In Spain, for in¬
stance, as in other countries among those
surveyed, they often obtain poorly paid
part-time or seasonal employment, or else
they work in small family businesses or sub¬
sistence enterprises where sometimes no
wages are paid at all. Training courses
within these enterprises are the exception
A university system
within the European Community
EUROPE is more than just an econo¬
mic association, but its political
unification will remain a dead
letter if the educational dimension is not
taken into account. In short, there is an
urgent need to create a truly European
university community. This was one of
the main conclusions to emerge from the
first Congress of the EGEE (Les Etats
Généraux des Etudiants de l'Europe), an
association of European students found¬
ed by students at French universities and
Grandes Ecoles. The Congress was held
in Paris from 16 to 22 April, 1985, and was
attended by over four hundred students
from member countries of the European
Economic Community (EEC).
Although, since 1976, the EEC has had
its own action programme for education,
whose main objective is to develop ex¬
changes of both students and teachers,
national barriers still remain.
The Congress recognized that any at¬
tempt to move towards centralization of
education at EEC level would have little
hope of success. The ideal would be to in¬
troduce standard periods of study and a
system of accepted equivalents for
degrees and diplomas. Although EEC
regulations provide for mutual profes¬
sional recognition of medical diplomas,
for example, there is, at present, no
generally applicable mechanism within
the Community allowing for automatic
recognition of diplomas or periods of
study completed. As a result periods of
study undertaken abroad cannot be
counted towards a student's national
degree or diploma course.
Furthermore, the conditions that have
to be met in order to enter a course of
studies vary from one country to another
within the EEC and it would be a good
thing if students could be more fully in¬
formed on this.
One possible solution would be to
create diplomas with a European "label"
which, with the introduction of a Euro¬
pean Baccalauréat, would be applicable
to the secondary as well as to the univer¬
sity level of education. To get to this
point, one of the first tasks would be to in¬
form young people of their rights and the
opportunities open to them within the
EEC. National education systems should,
therefore, see themselves as situated
within the framework of an integrated
European dimension. Only by so doing
will they be able to encourage the
emergence of a truly European identity.
It was with these considerations in
mind that Mr. Sutherland, EEC Com¬
missioner with responsibility for educa¬
tion, presented the proposed COMET pro¬
ject, a wide-ranging scheme for ex¬
changes between the universities of
member countries of the Community, to
be financed by the European Commis¬
sion. As a further means of contributing
to the emergence of a European spirit a
project was also announced for the
publication of a History of Europe,
designed to appeal to young people in the
ten to fifteen age bracket.
rather than the rule, and when they do exist
they are rarely as good or as effective as
they appear on paper.
The situation is even more difficult for
girls. As the surveys on Spain and India in¬
dicate, they are subject to more frequent
and more serious discrimination than are
the boys. In their replies, young people of
both sexes agreed that girls are regarded by
employers as less capable than boys even
when they have the same or better qualifica¬
tions. In practice the girls are given the most
lowly tasks, receive lower wages and have
much more limited career prospects than
their male colleagues. In addition, as
emerged clearly from the survey on Spain,
both the initial securing of a job and the
possibility of promotion depend very large¬
ly on a girl's physical attractiveness.
Most of the young people interviewed, ir¬
respective of sex, had a very positive at¬
titude to entry into the world of work.
Nevertheless, the initial motivation and en¬
thusiasm tends to give way to scepticism
and apathy, and anxiety and tension grow
with the increasing difficulty of finding the
first job.
Many young people reported that, after
several unsuccessful attempts to obtain a
job, they had to resign themselves to tem¬
porary or permanent unemployment. In the
cases of Senegal and Algeria, the survey
clearly shows that a very low level of school¬
ing and lack of vocational training almost
inevitably leads to unemployment, especial¬
ly in times of economic recession. In
Algeria, for example, most of the young
unemployed have had no vocational train¬
ing and were educated only to primary level.
Uneducated and without work, these
young people find themselves doubly re¬
jected. In these conditions the struggle for
survival is even more difficult, since what is
at stake is not only material subsistence, but
also the need to establish a new personal
identity. One of the conclusions reached by
the authors of the survey concerning the
situation in Algeria is worth quoting here:
"Without seeking to establish a clear con¬
nexion between unemployment, lack of
schooling and juvenile delinquency, it is
notable that juveniles make up sixty per
cent of the prison population (and thirty-
seven per cent of the active population)".
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
For young people today, therefore,
employment almost everywhere is an ex¬
perience fraught with uncertainty and in¬
security. Only a few can be sure of enjoying
fixed, long-term contracts of employment
and the benefits of social security. As a
result, rather than accept employment on
onerous or unjust terms, many of them
either take the risk of setting up small
businesses of their own in the "informal"
or "underground" sector of the economy,
or they emigrate in the hope of doing better
elsewhere.
The survey also shows that, in times of
economic difficulty, the girls and younger
boys are the first to be laid off, in most
cases, especially in the developing coun¬
tries, without any form of compensation or
allowances.
There are also marked differences in
regard to stability of employment between
large and small enterprises. Young workers
in large firms usually have permanent con¬
tracts and social security, whereas most of
those working in small firms have neither.
Moreover, in several of the countries
surveyed, young workers commonly work
longer hours than their adult colleagues,
since regulations to protect them are either
non-existent or are not enforced.
Wage levels are often so low as to prevent
young people from leading decent, indepen¬
dent lives. Remuneration is frequently
below the level to which their professional
qualifications entitle them and this is a
source of great discontent. Furthermore,
working conditions for young people are
often oppressive and unhealthy and they are
frequently allotted the most unpleasant and
dangerous tasks which increases the risk of
work accidents.
Opportunities for promotion for the
young are very rare and they feel the weight
of the old-established hierarchical struc¬
tures that exist within most businesses bear¬
ing down upon them in a way that deprives
them of their rights and offends their sense
of dignity. In this respect, as in all others, it
is the girls who suffer most.
An unemployed Portuguese youth seeks
information and guidance from an official
of the French National Employment
Agency.
Will there be enough jobs?
The need for new jobs grows each year.
The number of job-seekers each year is determin¬
ed by the number of births 15 to 20 years earlier.
Thus today's birth rate determines the number of
jobs needed in the years 2000 to 2005.
Projected increase in the youth population in
urban and rural areas ¡970 to 2000.
Urban Rural
All developing
countries 	 200 % 34 "In
Africa 	 364 % 83 %
South Asia 	 233 % 54 %
Latin America 	 160 % 13 %
Source: UN Population Division Assessment 1980, Unicef
News.
Where will they be?
Population, ages 15-24,
World
1985 BaTaTaTa1
2000 «a*aHMML*aaan
2025 ««^b^b^bIbb^bV
Africa
1985 CJ
2000 ^Bj
2025 «a*a*a*a*a*a*a*aL>
Asia
1 985 «ab^bVbVKJ
2000 "Ab^bb^b^HbMJ
2025 fa*B^BB^aHHK
Latin America
1985 O
2000 tSJ
2025
D 940 million
1.100 million
b^b^HJ 1 .300 million
105 million
1 70 million
341 million
583 million
627 million
.) 679 million
82 million
105 million
129 million
Source: UN Population Division Assessment 1982, Unicef
News.
Where will they work?
Per cent of labour force in agriculture, 1980
Most of the world's population is rural and
agricultural. Even though large numbers of
youth live in the world's cities, many still turn to
agriculture for employment.
But for those who do there will be no guarantee
of steady work. Many will be lucky to find
seasonal jobs. In Bangladesh, for example, 80
per cent of the population is rural and half of
those are landless dependent for work on the
seasonal needs of those who own land.
Source: World Bank/World Development Report 1984,
Unicef News.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
World Congress on Youth
ONE of the most important events
marking International Youth Year
will undoubtedly be the World
Congress on Youth, to be held in Barcelona
(Spain) from 8 to 15 July and sponsored by
Unesco in collaboration with the Spanish
authorities and the municipality. Six hun¬
dred participants and observers, most of
them young people, from all over the world
are expected to attend. They will review the
situation and role of young people in society
since the first conference on youth, held in
Grenoble in 1964, and will attempt to iden¬
tify future orientations.
The main work of the Congress will be
conducted in three commissions each of
which will examine one major theme. On
Youth, Education and Work participants
will put forward their views on the in¬
dividual and collective contribution of
young people to development, research,
production and creation, as well as their
attitude to work. They will discuss leisure
activities and family life, technological
change, migration, economic and social
marginalization, as well as problems that
are specific, for example, to women. Final¬
ly, they will attempt to establish the outlines
of a youth policy that would guarantee the
right of young people to work and make it
easier for them to take part in the produc¬
tion process.
On the theme Youth and Cultural
Development participants will take a closer
look at the forms of cultural expression
specific to young people, their new values,
their speech forms and behaviour, the links
between tradition and modernity and the
conquest of new fields of creativity. They
A group of young Japanese, some of
them dressed in traditional costume, on
"Adult's Day", which is celebrated on 15
January every year. It marks the transi¬
tion from youth to adulthood which, in
Japan, occurs during a person's twen¬
tieth year.
will seek together new development models
in which culture will be restored to its cen¬
tral place in the evolution of society, as well
as ways of putting into practice cultural
policies for young people and with young
people, considered as fully involved in the
process of cultural development.
On the theme of Youth, Mutual
Understanding and International Co¬
operation five young people from the major
regions of the world will express their views
on poverty, ignorance, racism, intolerance,
unemployment, human rights, the arms
. race, degradation of the environment and
the crisis in international co-operation. The
participants will attempt to lay down the
conditions for greater mutual understand¬
ing and perhaps also to suggest the different
ways in which young people, as agents of
development, as the intermediaries in the
dialogue between the developing and the in¬
dustrialized countries and as fashioners of
peace, can harness their efforts in the ser¬
vice of international co-operation.
An open letter from the Mayor of Barcelona
W%Y its history and by vocation, Bar-
M-£ celona is a European, Mediterra-
MJ nean city, open to the world and
receptive to new suggestions for ways of
marking International Youth Year, whether
put forward by her own citizens or from
outside.
For six years now, the municipal
authorities of Barcelona have been paying
particular attention to the needs of young
people; a special youth department, headed
by a municipal councillor, has been created
which is responsible for all the services the
city has to offer its young citizens.
Drawing on the experience it has acquired
in this domain, as its contribution to Inter¬
national Youth Year the municipality has
launched Projecte Jove (Project for
Youth), which provides a working basisfor
an analysis ofthe situation ofyoung people
today and the response that this requires
from the authorities.
In Barcelona in 1985, as elsewhere in the
View of the port and city of Barcelona,
Spain, where the World Congress on
Youth Is to be held from 8 to 15 July this
year.
world, a young person is quite likely to be
unemployed or living on thefringe ofsocie¬
ty. This is a situation to which we cannot
close our eyes and which we must do
everything in our power to remedy.
International Youth Year provides us
with an opportunity toface up energetically
to theproblems and hopes ofyouth. It is the
hope of the municipality which I head that
Barcelona will enter enthusiastically into
the spirit of this Year. The World Youth
Congress, organized by Unesco, and the ac¬
tivities taking place in parallel with it will
make our city during the month ofJuly the
world capital ofyouth.
Barcelona, whose vocation and desire it is
to become an international tribune, will
always offer an enthusiastic welcome to in¬
itiatives such as these. With its long history,
its dynamism and its innovative spirit,
Barcelona is a young city for the young.
Pasqual Maragall Mira
Mayor of Barcelona
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
A UNESCO COURIER INTERNATIONAL SURVEY
The voice of youth
from every continent
The Unesco Courier recently sent a questionnaire to
Unesco Clubs, Non-Governmental Organizations,
Unesco Associated Schools and a variety of other in¬
stitutions and associations in many parts of the world
in order to find out at first hand about young people 's
ideas, aspirations and fears.
We received 1,050 replies from 41 countries and ter¬
ritories representing every continent: Austria, Argen¬
tina, Bangladesh, Belgium, Chad, Czechoslovakia,
Denmark, Egypt, Ecuador, the Federal Republic of Ger¬
many, France, Gabon, Ghana, Grenada, Hong Kong,
Hungary, Ireland, Israel, Italy, Kenya, Lebanon,
Malaysia, Mali, Malta, Mauritius, Mexico, New Zealand,
Nigeria, Norway, Pakistan, Panama, the Philippines,
Puerto Rico, Spain, Switzerland, Tunisia, the United
Kingdom, the United States, Zaire, Zambia, Zimbabwe.
1 . What is the problem of most concern to all young people
today?
2. Which of the following problems do you think are most impor¬
tant? Money, the future, sex education, studies and educational
guidance, leisure activities, work, fashion, politics, International
problems, social problems, scientific and technological pro¬
gress, relations with adults, relations of young people among
themselves, values.
3. Which of the international problems listed here do you think
are most Important and why? Aid to developing countries, getting
to know young people in other countries, the destruction of
nuclear arsenals, the eradication of racism, the war on hunger,
the need for contacts with other countries, world peace, friend¬
ship between peoples.
4. Politics. What does the word politics mean to you? Are you
willing to take part in public life? If so, how?
5. Studies and educational guidance. Do you think it is possi¬
ble to find solutions to these problems: world illiteracy, the
democratization of education, educational and vocational
guidance.
6. The future. What is your role and place in society today?
What does It offer you? What do you feel about your future? What
lies in store for those without educational qualifications?
7. Sex education. Are you for or against? Should it be provided
in the family or at school?
8. Money. Adults say that you don't know the value of money.
Are they right or wrong? Are you just consumers or are you pro¬
ducers too?
9. The relations of young people among themselves. Do you
experience any difficulties in your contact with others? Do you
feel the need for a youth centre where you could meet and take
part in activities that interest you? Do you feel there is a need for
youth organizers?
10. Work. What do you expect from your work? Is it an obstacle
to fulfilment? Are you working or unemployed? Did you become
unemployed before ever having a job?
11. Relations with adults. When the authority of the family
disappears, what is left? Have the role and importance of the
family been reduced? What are the consequences for the
elderly?
1 2. Social problems. Do you think these are adults' problems or
do you feel concerned yourself? If you do, which do you think is
the most important problem? Delinquency, drugs, equality of the
sexes, maladjusted children, young people living in rural areas,
housing, the elderly, human problems, relations between the
working class and the middle class.
13. Scientific and technological progress. What do you think
about the application of scientific and technological progress in
today's world?
14. Leisure activities. What are your favourite leisure activities?
The arts, reading, cinema or television, sport. Do you organize
them alone or in a group?
15. Fashion. Does it mean being up-to-date, "in the swim"? Is
it a form of progress?
16. It is often said that young people have no ideas, only aspira¬
tions? Is this true?
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
THE outcome of any survey, clearly, is largely predetermin¬
ed by the nature of the questions asked. In presenting the
results, we have opted for a "global" approach in record¬
ing the 1,000 replies without reference to the Inherent dif¬
ferences of each country. Hence there are big differences in the
priority given to different problems.
For example, young people in the Socialist countries stated
that there Is no unemployment in their countries and that those
without educational qualifications have an equal right to work.
This necessarily affected their replies to several other questions,
including their overwhelming choice of peace (in answer to the
first question), whereas young people from other parts of Europe
are primarily preoccupied with questions of work, unemploy¬
ment, the future.
Analysis of the replies leads to the following conclusions.
1. What is the problem of most concern to all young people
today?
Many did not answer this question. Of those who did so, 50%
chose problems of war and peace, 30% unemployment and
work, 10% the future, and 10% various other problems including
drugs, hunger and the quality of life.
2. Which of the following problems do you think are most im¬
portant? Money, the future, sex education, studies and
educational guidance, leisure activities, work, fashion,
politics, international problems, social problems, scientific
and technological progress, relations with adults, relations
of young people among themselves, values.
The most widely chosen top-priority problem was that of the
future (57%)the young people's own future. In second place
came studies, a problem directly related to the first, followed by
values, social problems and money. The relations of young peo¬
ple among themselves, progress, politics, relations with adults,
sex education and fashion were far down the field. Close scrutiny
of the answers to this question casts doubt on the priority given
to problems of peace and disarmament In the replies to the first
question.
3. International problems. Which of those listed here do you
think are most important and why? Aid to developing coun¬
tries, getting to know young people in other countries, the
destruction of nuclear arsenals, the eradication of racism,
the war on hunger, the need for contacts with other coun¬
tries, world peace, friendship between peoples.
85% of the votes went to world peace. This choice was closely
followed (and qualified) by the war on hunger, the destruction of
nuclear arsenals, the eradication of racism, and aid to develop¬
ing countries. But the desire to get to know young people in other
countries, the need for contacts and friendship between peoples
seemed to be considered far less important.
4. Politics. What does the word politics mean to you? Are
you willing to take part in public life? If so, how?
Politics seems to attract little interest. 30% of those polled did
not answer this question and only 2 out of 1,000 declared that
they held serious political opinions. 24% considered politics to
be useless if not dangerous, 21 % considered It to be the product
of an ideology without specifying which, 16% gave a stereotyped
definition, 2% gave answers that were beside the point, and only
7% thought politics could be useful.
The possibility of taking part in public life aroused even more
significant reactions: 50% did not reply, 17% categorically
replied no, and 33% replied by a "yes, but..." which they clearly
explained: yes, they wanted to take part, but through teaching,
help to individuals or countries, medical and social actions,
voting, and a desire to "reconstruct".
5. Studies and educationalguidance. Do you think it is possi¬
ble to find solutions to these problems: world illiteracy, the
democratization of education, educational and vocational
guidance?
Young people think that solutions to these problems can be
found. But they feel it is easier to solve the illiteracy problem and
to speed up the democratization of education than to solve
problems of education and above all vocational guidance and
counselling. In many cases they believe that these are questions
for adults.
6. The future. What is your role and place in society today?
What does it offer you? What do you feel about your future?
What lies in store for those without educational
qualifications?
Many did not answer this question. Some gave quite long
answers, expressing their anxieties and hopes for the future.
Regarding the first part of the question, 90% thought they
occupied their rightful place in society, I.e. as schoolchildren or
students; some went so far as to say that they were "their
parents' responsibility".
Only slightly more than 50% answered the second part of the
question. 40% believe that society helps them, gives them moral
support and the means to pursue their studies. 40% consider on
the contrary that society is a source of difficulties, 10% consider
that it has little or nothing to offer, and 10% just hope. In several
cases, the word vocation was described as unrealistic or old-
fashioned.
On the third point, 71 % of young people replied that the future
of the unqualified was very precarious, 10% thought that there
was no future for them, and 6% that only the toughest and most
degrading jobs are open to them.
7. Sex education. Are you for or against? Should it be provid¬
ed in the family or at school?
Only 10% did not answer this question. Perhaps these absten¬
tions and a large number of the noes can be explained by
religious or cultural prohibitions. 88% were in favour of sex
education and only 1 2% against. 1 9% would like it to be provided
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
World peace is the international problem
of most concern to young people today,
as symbolized, left, by the hundreds of
doves flourished by participants at the
11th World Youth Festival held in Havana,
Cuba, in July-August 1978. The Festival
was organized by the World Federation of
Democratic Youth, a movement created
after World War II to ' 'fight for the unity of
youth... and for a just and lasting peace ' '.
The Federation now has 270 member
youth organizations from 112 countries.
The 12th World Youth Festival, co¬
inciding with International Youth Year,
will be held in Moscow this summer.
The hopes and anxieties which thoughts
of their future prospects arouse in young
people invariably lead back to their
studies. The young are unanimous In
thinking that lackofeducational qualifica¬
tions is a severe handicap in life. Below,
an experiment in computer-assisted Latin
teaching at the Lycée Ampère, Lyons,
France.
by the family, 13% by the school, 46% by both family and school.
The others would like it to be done elsewhere, but did not say
where.
8. Money. Adults say that you don't know the value of
money. Are they right or wrong? Are you just consumers or
are you producers too?
38% admitted that they didn't know the value of money, 43%
said on the other hand that the reproach was unjustified and that
they knew the value of money very well because they had learn¬
ed how to earn their living. Some thought the reproach to a cer¬
tain extent justified, but that when adults were young they were
just as ignorant of the value of money because they had too much
of it and were thus encouraged to spend too much. 73% con¬
sidered themselves, often most unwillingly, as consumers, 22%
as consumers and producers, and 5% said they were producers.
9. The relations of young people among themselves. Do you
experience any difficulties in your contact with others? Do
you feel the need for a youth centre where you could meet
and take part in activities that interest you? Do you feel there
is a need for youth organizers?
65% claimed to have no difficulties. 35% confessed that they
encountered psychological obstacles. On the question of youth
centres, the negative replies came largely from developed coun¬
tries and the positive replies from developing countries. 65% of
those polled would like to have a place to meet. The presence of
organizers was only considered desirable by 33% of the young
people, especially those from developing countries, 61% con¬
sidered them unnecessary, 6% were not sure.
10. Work. What do you expect from your work? Is it an
obstacle to fulfilment? Are you working or unemployed? Did
you become unemployed before ever having a job?
Many did not reply to this question (which received 630 replies
in the 1,000 questionnaires received). 80% of those who
answered expected fulfilment and happiness from their jobs,
10% expected money, 9% hoped or wished to be able to help
others through their job, 1% expected nothing positive at all.
21 % thought that a job was a factor in fulfilment, 30% thought
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Young people do not think that the world
illiteracy problem Is insoluble. Many of
them want to take part in public life
through doing some form of educational
work. Above, literacy session in a refugee
camp in El Salvador.
it could have a disturbing impact when it was unsuitable or did
not provide satisfaction, when the pace was too quick or when It
did not leave enough leisure time. The overwhelming majority felt
unable to answer this question today. As for the final point, 93%
said they were students or schoolchildren, 4% were at work, 3%
unemployed.
11. Relations with adults. When the authority of the family
disappears, what is left? Have the role and importance of the
family been reduced? What are the consequences for the
elderly?
Only 43% gave replies, most of them fairly short, to this ques¬
tion. 33% of those who answered thought that nothing was left
when family authority had disappeared; 26% believed that in¬
dividual liberty was left; 21% considered that respect and
sometimes friendship were left; 1 0% simply stated that authority
had disappeared, and 10% added that this was a good thing.
In addition, 62% considered that the role of the family had
been reduced, and 32% believed the opposite. The others were
undecided.
On the third point (answered in less than 40% of the question¬
naires returned), 78% believed that the consequences for the
elderly were serious (neglect, being put in a "home", distance,
material or moral difficulties), 10% thought it had no effect on
their situation, 5% thought it meant more freedom for them, 7%
gave irrelevant replies.
12. Socialproblems. Do you think these are adults' problems
or do you feel concerned yourself? If you do, which do you
think is the most important problem? Delinquency, drugs,
equality of the sexes, maladjusted children, young people
living in rural areas, housing, the elderly, human problems,
relations between the working class and the middle class.
Human problems were considered the most important (20%),
followed by delinquency (15%), housing (13%), equality between
the sexes (12%), maladjusted children (12%), drugs (12%), rela-
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
tions between the working class and the middle class (5%), and
young people living in rural areas (1%).
1 3. Scientific and technologicalprogress. What do you think
about the application of scientific and technological pro¬
gress in today's world?
No one believed that scientific progress was entirely positive.
15% were against any form of progress, 6% accused it of caus¬
ing all kinds of harm (war, the atomic bomb, pollution, unemploy¬
ment), 79% were in favour of progress, especially in medical
research; they were very sceptical about all the other applica¬
tions of science and technology.
14. Leisure activities. What are your favourite leisure ac¬
tivities? The arts, reading, cinema or television, sport. Do
you organize them alone or in a group?
Sport came first (57%), followed by reading, then cinema and
television. The arts, including music, came far behind.
43% practiced hobbies In groups, 40% alone or in a group,
depending on the activity, 17% preferred to be alone.
15. Fashion. Does it mean being up-to-date, "in the swim"?
Is it a form of progress?
51 % thought that fashion meant "being up-to-date". For 28%
it meant "being in the swim", and only 20% believed that it was
a form of progress. For some, following the fashion was a sign
of personality and freedom; for others, it was a form of slavery,
and a form of consumption like any other.
16. It is often said that young people have no ideas, only
aspirations? Is this true?
1 % were not sure. 1 1 % said that adults are right. On the other
hand, 88% declared that they had ideas, aspirations, and many
other things that adults lack, and that in many cases they even
had more ideas, sometimes amounting to genius, than adults.
But they felt that society, constructed by and for adults,
prevented them from voicing their ideas and from putting them
into effect.
According to the results of the Unesco
Courier survey, most young people prac¬
tice a sport, mainly in groups, during their
leisure time. Above, a cycle race in the
Federal Republic of Germany.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
A day in the life of.
Three young people recount
the happenings of a typical day
Taylan Coskun
Nationality Turkish
Pupil at the Lycée Turgot, Paris
Age 15
Day described: 29 April 1985
Season: Spring
Temperature: 1 1 degrees Centigrade
Weather showery
I got up at 0800 after putting off the
evil moment for fifteen minutes. Still half
asleep, I took a cold shower, ate my
breakfast and rushed out of the house.
Getting to the Underground station
was torture, but, stifled in the crowd, I
finally managed to wake up almost com¬
pletely. When I got out of the
Underground I had to run, but I managed
to get to school in time for the first class,
which was drawing.
The next class was history. Like my
other foreign schoolfellows I wasn't very
attentive. It isn't always easy to concen¬
trate on a lesson when you don't speak
the language perfectly. The effort involv¬
ed is much greater, especially when the
subject is French history!
Then it was time for a period of
physical education which we all enjoy
even though it is quite strenuous.
At lunchtime I didn't waste time
eating; instead I played chess with some
friends who are also chess fanatics like
me.
In the afternoon I had a biology class.
When it was over I rushed out of school
and went home as fast as I could. As
usual the Underground was packed.
When I got home I said a brief "hello"
to the family, dumped my school books in
my room and dashed off to play ping-
pong with some friends who live nearby.
We often spend hours playing together;
today we played until 1900.
Back home again, I had dinner and after
doing two hours homework I went to
bed. I didn't watch television at all today.
Below, immigrant workers arriving in
France.
James Amar
Nationality French
Pupil at the Ecole de Danse de l'Opéra
de Paris
(The French National Ballet School, Paris)
Age 15
Day described: 2 May 1985
Season: Spring
Temperature: 12 degrees Centigrade
Weather showery and overcast
My alarm went off as usual at 0715
and I got up at 0730. I don't have
breakfast as this is not advisable im¬
mediately before strenuous exercise.
I took the Underground to the Palais
Gamier (the Paris Opera House), climbed
the five flights of stairs to the practice
studio and changed into my practice
clothes. In the studio, before the ballet
master arrives, we usually spend about
ten minutes warming up and practising
the movements or positions we find most
difficult.
When the ballet master and the pianist
came in we all bowed to them as usual
and then the hard work really began. We
did exercises at the bar followed by
"floor work" (exercises to make you
supple). By this time we were all
sweating hard. Then came "centre
work", starting with adage (this is slow
tempo work involving controlled lifting of
the legs and balance exercises), followed
James Amar (second from left) during a
"centre work" class. This photo was
taken when he was twelve years old.
by pirouettes and turns, as well as small
jumps and high jumps which are very im¬
portant for male dancers. Our ballet
master is Monsieur Lucien Duthoit. He is
a premier danseur and I enjoy his classes.
At about 1015 1 got Into my track suit
to go to another studio for more work on
variations, stage presence, breathing,
etc. which lasted for about an hour and a
half. When that was over, at about mid¬
day, we all charged down the stairs and
gathered on the steps outside the front
entrance of the Opera House ready to
walk round to the Collège de l'Opéra, in
the Rue de Surène, where we do our or¬
dinary academic work.
I had lunch in the canteen and at 1 330
school work began. I had two hours of
French which is one of my favourite
lessons. Normally we have four hours of
school work, but today it was different
because I had to go round to the Opéra
Comique to rehearse for the Gala perfor¬
mance we are giving on 6 May to raise
money for our school.
After an hour and a half of rehearsal I
had a snack and a rest and then at about
1 830 I went to the dressing room to get
ready for the evening show. This was the
Spectacle de l'Ecole de Danse, a series of
six end of term performances put on by
the Ballet School. The programme con¬
sists of two ballets. Soir de Fête and La
Fille Mal Gardée. I take the part of one of
the peasants In La Fille Mal Gardée. I like
the music of this ballet and the dancing
was fun too because we had to do quite
a lot of miming. It's really very exciting
being on stage in front of a real audience,
and especially during Gala performances
when we dance with the big stars.
The performance ended around 2200.
When it was over, I changed and went
outside where my mother was waiting
for me. We went home together and had
something to eat and then sat chatting
about the show and I did not get to bed
until about 2330. What a day!
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Tina Ungalaq
Eskimo boarding student at Frobisher
Bay, Northwest Territories, Canada
Home town: Igloolik, Melville Peninsula,
Northwest Territories, Canada
Age 16
Day described: 10 April 1985
Season: Spring
Temperature: - 28 degrees Centigrade
Blue and sunny sky with no wind
This morning, Millie, the night-watch
person at the student residence where I
stay, made her usual rounds at 0630 to
wake everyone up. But I didn't hear her
so I didn't get up until my friend woke me
up at 071 5. 1 usually take a shower, but
this morning I only had time to wash my
hair and my face. I was almost late for
breakfast which is served in the cafeteria
from 0700 to 0745; I managed to get
breakfast at 0740. 1 had eggs, sausages,
orange juice and toast.
When I had finished eating, I went back
to my room to get ready for school. At
0815 the buses came to take us to
school. Classes started at 0830 so I went
to my classroom for roll call. At 0835 I
went to Mathematics class where we did
some problems. Maths is one of my best
subjects. The second class was Inuktitut
and we didn't do much of anything to¬
day. So far I have been the top student in
Inuktitut which is my first language. At
0955 we had a ten-minute break. My
good friend Kayrene told me about her
Spring break last week, in her home
town, Broughton Island, Northwest Ter¬
ritories. I then had a double period of
related arts. We are doing a project on the
Middle Ages. I am making an imitation
stained-glass window out of brightly col¬
oured tissue paper. In the second period
we looked at some slides of fellow
students which our related arts teacher
took last term. Our last class before lunch
was English. We listened to a tape of
Building an igloo.
Wood-cut by Nanogak © All rights reserved
Shakespeare's The Taming of the Shrew
which we are studying.
Lunch was from 1205 to 1300. We
had hamburgers and French fries. I sat
with Kayrene and talked with her. When
we had finished eating, we walked to a
shop called The Purple Daisy to look
around and to see if they had any new
clothes. We found some clothes but they
were too expensive.
We only had one class in the afternoon
because school closed early at 1400 so
that the teachers and students could go
to Nakasuk Elementary School for the
opening ceremonies of the Baffin
Regional Divisional Board which is taking
over education from the Government of
the Northwest Territories.
When we got out of school, Kayrene
and I walked to the Bay to shop. I bought
a pair of running-shoes and Kayrene did
too. We got a Coke at the snack bar. We
were going to go back to the residence by
taxi, but the residence van came along sox.
we got in it to go back to Ukkivik
residence.
We went and played in the video
games room. I lost a game of board
hockey by four goals to two. After the
hockey game I went upstairs to my room.
My room-mate Mary was there; she had
been home for a Spring break too and she
was tired after her long trip from
Sanikiluaq to Montreal and then on here
to Frobisher Bay. I went to the super¬
visor's office to see if I had a letter from
one of my friends back home in Iglooklik.
To my surprise I saw Janice who is a
supervisor here in Ukkivik residence. She
had just come back from Ottawa where
she had been making wedding plans. She
told me her wedding was planned for 17
August and she was very excited about
It.
Supper was from 1700 to 1800. To¬
day is Wednesday so we had fish,
potatoes and turnips (yuk!) for supper.
After supper I went up to my room to get
my homework for study hour at 1815.
During the study hour I worked on
English and Biology and this essay.
Because I am a junior (16 to 17 years
old) I have to be upstairs at 2200. We
have snacks, usually fruit and muffins or
cakes, and from 2230 to 2300 we get
ready for bed and talk with friends about
our day until 2300, when it is time for
lights out. I stayed up until 2330 to
watch the news on television tonight,
but this was exceptional.
As you can see, my day is not so dif¬
ferent from any other young person's
day. However, if I want to graduate, and
I do want to, I have to live in this Ukkivik
residence from September to June to
study for grades 10,11 and 12. This is
because the school at home only goes up
to grade 9.
At times life in the residence can be
boring and sometimes the rules are a
drag; but deep inside me I know we need
rules if we are to be successful in school.
Although I am many miles away from my
home and family, many of the people
who work at the residence and the
students who live in it make this life style
enjoyable.
My Job
I shall do my job
Be it great, be it small
I shall pride where my sweat dances
I shall sow the seeds and wait for rain to weed,
Work my land and gather my hard won harvest.
I shall do my job
Be it great, be it small;
Priding myself where my sweat dances.
I shall do my job
Which comes from my hands
From my try and hope
From my duty and search
I shall do that job
For deep in myself
I'll know it's my job
A job in which
I tried, I tried
As a man of my time.
Lwanga Mwanje
21 years old
Kampala, Uganda; 1985
This entry for Unesco 's com¬
petition to find a poster for
International Literacy Day
earned a special mention for
Paola Rigger! (17), of
Switzerland.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Spotlight
on
youth
As part of its coverage of
International Youth Year, the
Unesco Courier asked the
Managing Editors of those of
its editions which are
published away from
Unesco's Paris Headquarters
to prepare a brief exposé of
the youth situation in their
respective countries. We
present below edited and
abridged versions of their
reports, as well as personal
reflections by two high school
pupils, one Senegalese, one
Swiss, and by a young Soviet
worker.
Photo Gilles Salvia, Unesco
Youths wearing punk outfits in a Belgian
street
Belgium
THE basic problem facing young
Belgians today is finding a job. The
18-to-25-year-olds are hardest hit by
unemployment (between 1 0 and 1 2 per cent
of the working population as a whole are out
of work). The situation is particularly painful
for graduates, whose education requires a
big investment in terms of money and
energy.
Nevertheless, the attraction of higher
education is still as strong as ever. Between
30 and 35 per cent of young people are in
higher education, showing a strong predilec¬
tion for economics and informatics.
A recent law raised the school leaving age
to 1 8. But this has scarcely changed the real
situation, as most young people already con¬
tinued their studies beyond the age of 15.
In spite of the crisis, the standard of living
is still very high and the system of social
benefits relatively generous. Cases of van¬
dalism, drug use, asocial and antisocial
behaviour exist, but not to an alarming ex¬
tent, and this phenomenon does not seem to
have been influenced by the decline in the
socio-economic situation.
There are examples of vitality, enthusiasm
and generosity. Initiatives on behalf of en¬
vironmental conservation, disarmament,
and aid to developing countries aroused in¬
terest and commitment early on, as did the
work of youth centres and cultural
organizations.
Photo Hervé Donnezan © Rapho, Paris
Young lumberjacks at work on a river in
Finland
Finland
IN Finland young people constitute a
smaller and smaller proportion of the
population. In 1950, 30 per cent of the
population was under 15 years of age; in
1980, only 20 per cent. The physical needs
of young Finns today are well provided for.
Some think that they are too affluent.
Various sub-cultures have spread as a result
of the modern transnational culture. A need
for conformity may be seen in the popularity
of video game arcades and in the preference
for garments with well-known brand names.
But young Finns are not only consumers;
they have many hobbies. Some 64 per cent
of 7-to-24-year-olds are members of one or
more voluntary organizations. They are avid
readers and active library users. According
to a survey, nearly all children and some 90
per cent of the young read at least one book
every six months.
The picture is not entirely cloudless,
however. For one thing, youth unemploy¬
ment seems to be here to stay. The
unemployment rate among the young is
twice that for adults. Because of unemploy¬
ment and because their studies last longer
than in the past, young Finns are leaving
home later than they did (every other Finn in
the 20-24 age group still lives with his or her
parents). When they do leave home, they
face an acute housing problem. The
greatest fear of young Finns is war, even
though they have no personal experience of
it. In their choice of career the young rate
an interesting job first, advancement
possibilities second and wages or salary
only third.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Photo Diego Goldberg © Parimage, Paris
A group of schoolchildren dwarfed by the
dome of the Palace of Congress in Brasilia,
capital of Brazil
Brazil
THE situation for young people is far
from satisfactory. 85 per cent of Bra¬
zilian children have no chance of
going beyond the first years of primary
schooling. Of 100 pupils who complete
primary schooling, only 8 go on to secondary
education. And only one-third of the pupils
who finish secondary education reach
university level.
In Brazil today some 400,000 young peo¬
ple enter universities or other institutions of
higher education each year, around 2.5 per
cent of the 1 8-to-23 age group.
Young Brazilians are also feeling the
dangerous and disturbing impact of several
social and economic problems, not the least
of which is unemployment. Galloping infla¬
tion is also having a serious impact on the
vast majority of the population, whose stan¬
dard of living is continuing to fall.
Much of the critical behaviour of young
Brazilians can be attributed to youthful high
spirits. People tend to be incendiaries at 18
and firemen at 40.
It would be extremely unjust to hold the
young exclusively responsible for antisocial
attitudes and reactions which are certainly
due in large part to the trauma of economic
uncertainty with no end in sight.
Photo © Roger Viollet, Paris
Painted wooden statuette from ancient
Egypt (Vlth Dynasty, 2345 to 2200 BC).
The Arab World
BECAUSE of the pre-eminence of the
family system In the rural world, it
is primarily in the big cities that
young people have emerged as a social
category with their own culture. The city thus
provides the best framework for observing
the specific problems of young Arabs.
Schooling is, ideally, a State service pro¬
vided for all social strata, and guarantees
equality of opportunity. But while the same
educational rules are applied to all pupils,
both the inclination to acquire knowledge
and school failure rates vary widely among
pupils from different socio-cultural
backgrounds.
In order to subsist, the "young adults" re¬
jected by the school and not integrated into
the economic system create their own social
environment: gangs of young people
graduate rapidly from petty misdemeanours
to serious delinquency.
For girls, education is the ideal way of
achieving liberation from the restraints of the
Arab-Muslim tradition. But those who ex¬
perience this liberation without serious
problems come from already acculturated
backgrounds. It is mainly middle-class girl
students and high school pupils who feel the
dramatic consequences of this double
culture. One consequence can be found in
the demonstrations of young city dwellers of
both sexes in favour of a return to tradition
and to Islam.
In spite of high failure rates at every level
of education, there is a growing number of
graduates and, as a corollary, their price on
the labour market is falling. In other words
the system is creating increasing numbers of
drop-outs and graduates: the former are vir¬
tually excluded from the labour market, the
latter are obliged to accept posts for which
they have not been prepared.
Photo Rajak Chantan © Rapho, Paris
Teenage talkfest in Rome
Italy
THE youth unemployment situation in
Italy has worsened during the last
few years. In 1 974, 2.6 per cent of the
workforce were unemployed young people
whereas in 1984 the figure had risen to 7.7
per cent. This problem is now the source of
the gravest concern to the country's social
and political institutions.
The educational system lags far behind
the extraordinary economic and technical
progress of recent years. To enable it to
catch up on lost time, many solutions have
been put forward and are now being put into
effect.
Notable among them is the raising of the
school-leaving age by two years (to age 1 6)
through a law which is currently being ex¬
amined by Parliament. This may help to
solve the problem by modernizing voca¬
tional education and making the system
more coherent.
There is reason to hope that current
preventive measures to cope with such
problems as delinquency and drugs (slightly
on the increase) will prove effective. But
these phenomena, which are less acute in
Italy than in other industrially developed
countries, will only entirely disappear when
the root causes of the malaise affecting
young people have been eliminatedthe
difficulty of finding a job, the disappearance
of traditional values and ideas, the harmful
influence of the media in propagating the
myth of glittering success achieved without
effort.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Photo Paul Almasy, Unesco
A translator working on a scientific
document at Pakistan's National Scientific
and Technical Documentation Centre
(PANSDOC), Karachi. The Centre was
created with the aid of Unesco.
Pakistan
SPIRITUAL and intellectual confusion
naturally accompanies the tensions
which arise during the transition
from an agricultural to an industrial society.
Young people are the most affected by this.
Young people constitute more than half of
Pakistan's population today. Since in¬
dependence they have become more con¬
vinced of the need for education and the
literacy rate has risen. In response to the
demands of the modern world, more and
more of them have acquired a scientific
education. But the acquisition of a
theoretical scientific education has not
brought them the material success which
was their goal in switching over from arts to
science. The educational system, which has
not yet found its bearings, has failed to give
young people a clear cultural identity or ap¬
preciable economic support. During the last
decade particularly many Pakistanis have
emigrated to the Gulf countries in search of
economic prosperity.
Highly educated young people who can¬
not find job opportunities commensurate
with their qualifications have begun to fall
victim to frustration and loneliness. A few
have been tempted to take refuge in drugs.
Rapid industrialization and urbanization
have also exposed cultural traditions to
change, and restlessness and ambition to
get rich quick have overwhelmed old values.
The clash between old and new values is
causing a growing dissatisfaction among
young people. Both the young and the older
generations have begun to realize that
young people should be entrusted with more
responsibility.
Photo Gary Fullerton, Unesco
Typical house door in Zanzibar
United Republic
of Tanzania
IN Tanzania today there are some
13,500,000 people under the age of 35,
just under three-quarters of the total. An
estimated 83 per cent of them live in rural
areas, and the majority of them have either
graduated from primary school or are at
school.
After independence young people were at
the forefront in programmes for
rehabilitating the inherited economy and
culture. The Arusha Declaration of 1967
charted out a strategy for development
based on socialism and self-reliance. This
blueprint ushered in new initiatives for
young people, who took part in launching
Ujamaa villages, helping the peasants to
move to new villages, opening up new farms,
building houses, schools, dispensaries, and
roads, and conducting literacy campaigns.
The Tanzania-Zambia railway was basically
built by young people, and its impact was to
provide them with employment and
technical training.
Today the Universal Primary Education
(UPE) Programme enables all school-age
young people to have primary education. By
1983 there were some 9,897 primary
schools with 3.37 million pupils. In 1977 a
youth organization called Umoja wa Vijana
was created to mobilize and unite all Tanza-
nian young people in the process of building
a socialist self-reliant society. Its organiza¬
tional structure reaches from national level
down to the grassroots; at each level there
are youth leaders elected every five years.
Umoja wa Vijana has a total membership of
over 4 million.
Photo Hervé Donnezan © Rapho, Paris
Students at the entrance to the Faculty of
Medicine in Barcelona
Catalonia
YOUNG Catalans are noted for their
long associationist tradition which
has left a strong mark on their lives
and behaviour and has strongly encouraged
their involvement In the life of their society.
Catalan society today is concerned to
preserve and consolidate these associations
and movements and also to assimilate the
new forms of expression and participation
that are practiced by young people and
spring from their special needs and
situation.
One of the most striking aspects of the
situation of young Catalans nowadays is un¬
doubtedly the problem of unemployment
which, if nothing is done, may seriously
jeopardize their integration into society. The
problem is not confined to those who are out
of work; it creates a state of mind and a
general climate which affect all young
people.
Since the restoration of democracy, many
communities, like the Autonomous Govern¬
ment of Catalonia itself, have created
organizations concerned with youth affairs,
taking care as far as possible to avoid in¬
terfering with young people's activities
through excessive paternalism or control.
Today these organizations are seeking to
convince society at large and its relevant in¬
stitutions that public action on behalf of
young people must weld the whole range of
different initiatives into a coherent whole.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Photo Sunil Janah, Unesco
Detail of sculpture in the 1 3th-century Sun
Temple, Konarak, Orissa State
India
YOUNG people in India today feel
restless and resentful at the prevail¬
ing socio-economic injustice,
poverty, unemployment, corruption and the
irrelevant system of education imparted by
many of the country's institutions. Campus
unrest is widespread. Most young Indians
live in rural areas. They work in agriculture,
but there is not enough work to keep them
busy throughout the year. Most of them have
not reached the secondary level of educa¬
tion. The small numbers of young villagers
who have completed schooling or higher
education and training are victims of open
unemployment. Lack of job opportunities
forces some of them to migrate to the towns
or cities; the rest remain in the villages,
frustrated.
Thousands of young graduates remained
unemployed or underemployed for years.
With some exceptions, schools and univer¬
sities provide education which is not skill- or
career-oriented. Even though many millions
of jobs have been created during the past
three decades, the unemployment problem
has not been fully solved, owing to lack of
proper manpower planning, an outdated
system of general education, and consistent
population growth. The new pattern of diver¬
sified and vocational education introduced
in the last two years is a step in the right
direction.
With the expansion of the world media net¬
work, Indian young people are able to get a
glimpse of social and economic conditions in
other countries, especially developed coun¬
tries. This makes them impatient with the
pace of social and economic change at
home.
Photo © Magnum, Paris
Young workers in an electronics factory
Republic of Korea
THE under-25s of the Republic of
Korea were children in the 1960s
and 1970s when the country ex¬
perienced unprecedented social and
economic changes. \
A generation conflict in the 1980s has
been one of the unintended consequences
of these changes. As part of the moderniza¬
tion policy people were exposed to Western
influences; this brought discontinuity and
alienation to the lives of young people, who
emerged as a new generation with different
attitudes and life-styles from those of their
predecessors. They are deeply concerned
about the meaning of life and the quality of
society and show great interest in political
problems. At home they are ruder and more
aggressive than their predecessors; they are
impatient with lack of relevance in education
and with a society that often practices
hypocrisy.
The younger generation is experiencing
an identity crisis. They are living in a period
of transition both in their own lives and in the
social development of Korean society. Some
of them are active in youth movements
which propagate civil rights and find their
historical roots through activities related to
the traditional culture. With industrialization,
the traditional extended family system has
given ground to the nuclear family system,
and generally speaking the function of the
family has been weakened.
Urbanization and the rapid increase in the
educational population have negatively in¬
fluenced the quality of education. The in¬
crease of students in the higher education
system has raised serious problems in the
structure of employment. Many young
workers face unfavourable employment pro¬
spects. Most (73.2 per cent) work in
manufacturing industries. In 1983, 54.8 per
cent of the country's population (39,951 ,000)
were under 24. The proportion of young peo¬
ple in the total population has been declining
since 1960.
Photo Silvester © Rapho, Paris
Cleaning a statue of the Buddha in Bangkok
Thailand
IN 1981 there were approximately 11
million under-25s in Thailand, re¬
presenting about 23 per cent of a total
population of 48 million. Young people living
in rural areas (where more than 80 per cent
of Thais live) vastly outnumber the rest. In
1978 it was reported that about 67 per cent
of young people in the 15-25 age group had
only a lower primary education.
Most are employed as unskilled labourers
in agriculture, industry or business. The
small numbers who reach higher education
often find that their study programmes do
not prepare them for an occupation and are
not related to the labour market. There is a
growing awareness of this problem, and the
Government is also pursuing other
possibilities such as non-formal education
and education through the mass media.
Unemployment is considered to be the
most important problem. In 1981 the
unemployment rate was highest in the 20-24
age group. Young Thais have become
restless in the last decade. In 1973 a Na¬
tional Youth Bureau was established to plan,
co-ordinate, supervise and evaluate youth
development programmes. The State is pro¬
moting opportunities for vocational training,
club activities, sports and recreation.
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Photo © François Dupuy, Paris
Wall painted in trompe-1'sil, Geneva
Switzerland
YOUNG people today have far greater
access to education than the pre¬
vious generation, and most of them
are able to take courses suited to their tastes
and abilities. But competition for jobs re¬
mains acute and the economic recession
has resulted in the loss of large numbers of
posts, leaving many technicians and
graduates without employment.
With the spread of home computers and
electronic games, young people are becom¬
ing familiar with informatics at an early age
and courses for beginners in this field are
very popular. More than just an amusement,
modern means of communication are also
making young people more aware of how
other peoples live and helping them to
become more mature and responsible.
Finally, as the contribution below from a
young Swiss student demonstrates, conser¬
vation of nature has become a major con¬
cern of young people.
Fine prospects open up before us. In this
respect, there is a vast difference between
teenagers in the developing countries and
those in the industrialized countries. Unfor¬
tunately, many people in our country are pre¬
judiced against foreigners in general.
School work is the most important factor in
my life at present, followed by leisure ac¬
tivities. When you spend up to 8 hours a day
at school, you need a healthy dose of diver¬
sion and relaxation to keep your balance.
As far as racial and religious problems are
concerned, I live in an extremely tolerant en¬
vironment both at school and at home.
When I think of the future, the most impor¬
tant thing for me is preparation for working
life. My second major preoccupation Is the
protection of the environment. I think also of
world peace and what I would call the unarm¬
ed dialogue between peoples.
Thomas Bittet
student
Photo A. Tessore, Unesco
Children at play beneath the mosque at
Djourbel
Senegal
WHERE the future of young people
is concerned, there is a big dif¬
ference between industrialized
countries and developing countries. In the
latter, high illiteracy rates and slender
education and professional training oppor¬
tunities make for an uncertain future. In addi¬
tion, increasing thoughtlessness among
young people is a trend which is finding ex¬
pression in delinquency.
The first priority for us is employment,
which offers the only means of achieving
fulfilment, meeting one's own needs and
providing for the future. Next come problems
of health and housing, domestic needs, the
organization of the family, the acquisition of
knowledge, leisure activities and participa¬
tion in political life. In Senegal there are
several linguistic, cultural and religious com¬
munities and this promotes a high level of
tolerance. I have learned to love all living
creatures.
I belong to several youth movements. In a
Muslim association called the "Dahira", I
learn about my religion and about how to
contribute actively to religious life. The
socio-educative hostel at my school
familiarizes me with community action
techniques and encourages pupils from
widely different backgrounds to mix. Finally,
as a result of the secular scout movement I
have discovered my environment, improved
the circumstances of my life, mastered cer¬
tain forms of technical knowledge and ac¬
quired or developed such qualities as a
sense of initiative, fraternity, and an
awareness of the importance of community
development for the neediest groups in
society.
Djiby Fediore
student
Photo A. Gorelovski © APN, Moscow
Students of the Institute of Engineers and
Physicians in Moscow prepare for an
academic festival
USSR
I was born and grew up in the village of
Kujnoie, 500 kilometres southeast of
Moscow. I have been living in Moscow
for 7 years. One day when I read a
newspaper article about a ball-bearing fac¬
tory in the capital I decided to come and work
here. Precision tools interested me. I set off.
To begin with, the factory hired me as a
labourer on a modest salary. I shared a room
with a work-mate. Then I studied at the
machine-tool manufacturing technical col¬
lege. Three evenings a week I studied after
work. After a year I became a fitter. It was
more interesting: I was working with ball¬
bearings and I was better paid.
When I finished my technical college
studies, I became an adjuster. That's what I
am today. It's close to the work of an
engineer, but I'm still a workman. I could
become an engineer; I would have to study
some more. But that calls for a very big ef¬
fort. And then I have new responsibilities; I
got married three years ago.
Where I come from people say: build your
house before you get married. When I
became a fitter and had an appartment I
returned to my village where Tonia, my
fiancée, was waiting for me. We came back
to Moscow together. Today we have a two-
year-old son. Tonia is a nurse. Our material
situation has considerably improved. We
can even save a little.
Anatoli Medvedev
worker
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
í*^
*fe..
Streets apart by Merrick Fall
With a total of some 5,000 youngsters
aged from 8 to 15 roaming wild in its
streets, Bogotá has earned the reputation
of being the world capital of street
children. Established by the Salesian
Congregation, the Bosconia-La Florida
project is aimedat weaning partly or total¬
ly abandoned children away from the
street in a series of carefully designed
stages. They learn first to play in an open
setting during the day, then to spend the
night in a dormitory, then to attend
classes and, finally, to learn a trade.
Above, learning to become a welder.
Like the other projects illustrated on the
following two pages, the Bosconia-La
Florida project is linked with the Inter-
NGO Programme on Street Children and
Street Youth launched in 1982 by the In¬
ternational Catholic Child Bureau as a
follow-up to the International Year of the
Child, 1981.
THE deep-felt sense of security,
warmth and belonging that we
recognize in the idea of "home" is
a birthright common to men and women
everywhere, and yet there are millions of
young people approaching adulthood today
for whom such emotions can only remain a
distant dream. These are youngsters from
the fragile families who are drawn like
moths to the bright lights of the big cities of
the developing world Sao Paulo, Nairobi,
Bombayby hopes of jobs, salaries and a
better future. All too often they find instead
only menial tasks, lonely disappointment
and systematic exclusion.
Rural populations are unprepared for the
strains and stresses inseparable from social
change on such a huge scale. Marriages
crumble and disintegrate; their teenage off¬
spring, lacking moral support, drop out of
school, supposing they have been lucky
enough to get near one, and, with no
qualifications for employment, have
nothing to do except drift around the
streets, answerable to no one. In a word,
street youths are youngsters who through
This depressing picture is not entirely
new, but in recent years, with the explosive
growth of urban areas, it has taken on alar
ming proportions. Naturally enough, very
few statistics concerning those not at
school, at work or in prison have been pro¬
duced. For developing countries, estimates
put the combined total of children and
youths in this situation at not less than
seventy million and numbers are rising
rapidly. Nor is the problem restricted to
developing countries. In New York there
are said to be twenty thousand runaway or
destitute youngsters on the streets at any
given time. With variations, many in¬
dustrial cities affected by high unemploy¬
ment and poor housing now face similar
problems.
no fault of their own have missed out on
love and find themselves morally or
physically abandoned. They do not matter.
For them home is somewhere between the
bus station, the market-place and a corner
of someone else's slum.
The street, therefore, can be a bleak and
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Founded by Father Bruce Ritter, a Fran¬
ciscan priest, Covenant House is an inter¬
national child care agency whose "Under
21" programme aids homeless and
runaway youth and operates short-term
crisis centres in New York City, Houston,
Boston and Toronto, as well as a long-
term residential programme in Antigua,
Guatemala. Above, a young person gets
advice from an "Under 21" Counsellor at
Covenant House, Toronto.
dangerous place where drug's, violence and
prostitution lurk beneath the surface. It
would be wrong, however, to think of the
street as being invariably a hostile milieu.
Throughout the Mediterranean it has
traditionally been an extension of the home,
as well as combining elements of the sports
field, the department store and the universi¬
ty. In the modern city, however, whether in
industrial or developing countries, the
street is an anonymous, unstructured,
neutral area where social norms and codes
of conduct are undefined. Its values are
those of the jungle, where good and right
are terms applied to what one can get away
with and where only the fittest survive. In
the street only the present moment counts;
it cancels out the past and puts everyone on
an equal footing.
The causal pathways leading to this state
of affairs are tortuous. No youngster can be
said to be abandoned for any single reason.
Whatever the immediate circumstances, in
developing countries the underlying social
pressures lie in the complex push-pull rela¬
tionship between the city and the coun¬
tryside. The massive transfer of population
into the cities that we are now witnessing
can be seen as the final act in the process of
industrialization which began in eighteenth
century England and is only now reaching
the far corners of the developing world.
Would you like to live in a shanty-town?
Probably not; but for many village families,
barely scratching a living from the soil, the
answer is yes. The media have shown them
what the modern world has to offer and
they want a share in its bounty, if not for
themselves then at least for their children.
The consequences for family life are
often disastrous; disgruntled husbands
move on and the children often face a suc¬
cession of stepfathers who have no interest
in their welfare or even survival. At the age
of ten or less they may be forced out to
"work" in the street. In some depressed
areas the proportion of female-headed
households is over fifty per cent. By con¬
trast, in closely-knit rural communities
where child-rearing has traditionally been
the responsibility of the extended family,
children whose biological family has
broken up, for whatever reason, are never
left to their own devices but as a matter of
course are sustained through childhood and
adolescence by a network of relatives or
foster parents. Today, however, even in
Africa, the most rural of continents, this
tradition is crumbling under the impact of
the consumer society.
The problem, to which there are no easy
solutions, has often been neglected by
governments. Youngsters on the street with
no visible means of support are sometimes
assumed to be delinquents, or pre¬
delinquents, and thus justifiable targets for
peirodical incarceration. Part of their
predicament, perhaps, is that as objects of
compassion they are unattractive. As street
children they require protection from moral
and physical danger; a few years later, when
they are rowdy street youths, it is society
that is seen as requiring protection from
them. Their most common "official" fate,
therefore, is to be placed in a State-run
home, which tends to be a poor substitute
for a proper family. One cannot love an
institution.
The non-governmental sector, by con¬
trast, has been quicker to grasp the nettle.
Many NGOS (non-governmental organiza¬
tions) have initiated original projects which
are models of drive and imagination. Con¬
sider, for example, the Bosconia-La Florida
project in Bogotá, Colombia, where life for
hard-bitten street youngsters is notoriously
precarious. Founded by the Salesian Con-
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
A project established in Kigali, the capital
of Rwanda, by a committee of the
Jeunesse Ouvrière Catholique, under the
auspices of the local diocese, seeks to
help young people aged from 14 to 25
who have migrated to Kigali from rural
areas. Its objectives are to provide lodg¬
ings, training, work and healthy leisure
pursuits, to foster a sense of solidarity
and self-respect and to encourage the
establishment of local small-scale in¬
dustries. The training provided includes
literacy classes, woodwork, sewing,
book-keeping and car maintenance and
repair (left).
Founded in 1972, in Dhaka, Bangladesh,
UCEP (Underprivileged Children's Educa¬
tional Programs) is an educationalproject
which reaches some 14,000 working
street children in four cities in
Bangladesh and Nepal. Right, a student at
work in a UCEP technical school in
Bangladesh.
Developing from a modest child care unit
established in 1955 by a doctor and his
wife, the Adharashram Community
Development Centre offers protection,
education and training to destitute
women and children, most of whom come
from the unauthorized shanty-towns
around the industrial city of Nashik, not
far from Bombay. Today the Centre offers
residential accommodation to a total of
116 young people, most of whom are
girls. Half the residents are aged between
5 and 12. Left, a cultural performance put
on by the residents.
Founded by Father Arnold Krol, of the
White Fathers the Undugu Society of
Kenya (' 'undugu "means' 'fellowship "or
"brotherhood") aims to help street boys
In the 10 to 14 age group who have come
from the shanty-towns on the outskirts of
Nairobi, Kenya, and who work and sleep
in the city centre. The main objective is to
rehabilitate the boys and provide them
with a minimum, practical form of educa¬
tion. In addition, with a view to
strengthening the community as a whole,
programmes have been developed for
women which include literacy classes, In¬
struction andadvice on hygiene and child
care and practical training in sewing and
dressmaking (above).
gregation, the scheme has evolved a whole
methodology of weaning the boys back into
society in successive stages. Based on gen¬
uine friendship and respect, it uses group
therapy to develop self-confidence and
motivation. Positive qualities such as loyal¬
ty, ingenuity and resourcefulness which the
youngsters have demonstrated by surviving
on the street are harnessed to the establish-
menl of a self-governing "Republic". The
process culminates in a fully-fledged com¬
mercial firm, Industrias Bosconia, which
manufactures solar heating panels and is
largely self-financing.
The pioneering experience gained on the
non-governmental side is now being drawn
together by the Inter-NGO Programme on
Street Children and Street Youth, founded
by a group of nine NGOs, both lay and
religious. As well as showing authorities
and agencies what can be done, it aims to
create a world-wide network of support for
fieldworkers and to organize a series of sub-
regional forums in Abidjan, Bogotá and
New Delhi during International Youth
Year. The vital role that such information
diffusion and advocacy can play is perhaps
best illustrated in the case of Brazil where
Unicef has been particularly active. While
the scale and intensity of the country's
problems are second to none, awareness has
reached a point at which a national move¬
ment and strategy are emerging. Today,
two hundred and forty-three projects are
under way, mostly with official support, at
the community level.
In the longer term, governments are like¬
ly to place less emphasis on supporting in¬
dividual projects and more on multi¬
dimensional preventive strategies. These
still require definition. Today, nobody real¬
ly knows why more youngsters are left on
the streets in some communities than in
others and it is only now that policy-makers
are beginning to consider the effects of
development on the family as a unit rather
than on its individual members. Paradox¬
ically, it is precisely at a time when the fami¬
ly is most threatened that its virtues are be¬
ing rediscovered. The family will once again
be the essential building-block of sound
social progress, a partner and not an instru¬
ment of the State.
MERRICK FALL, of the UK, is Executive
Secretary of the Inter-Non-Governmental
Organization Programme on Street Children
and Street Youth, Geneva.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Africa's
generation gap
by Boubakar Ly
ONE of the salient characteristics of
African society, as of the vast
majority of Third World societies,
is its rate of demographic growth. Accor¬
ding to some estimates, the population of
Africa may double between now and the
end of the century. As a result of this
demographic trend this population is very
young.
The predominance of young people both
in the rural areas and in the popular districts
of the big cities raises the problem of their
integration into society. Young people can-
Many young Senegalese are members of
the Traditional M'Botai mutual aid
associations which take a wide range of
initiatives in social, economic and
cultural life. M'Botai associations are
groups of friends united by age, affinity,
ethnic group, interest in a chosen activi¬
ty, or simply the pleasure of being
together. They flourish both in the towns
and in rural areas where they promote
solidarity at times of birth, marriage and
death and help finance festivals and the
management of collective granaries.
Below, an M'Botai group meets fora work
session.
not be successfully integrated into society
unless the institutions concerning them are
also well integrated, or unless they par¬
ticipate in a society which functions suc¬
cessfully as a whole. This is not the case in
Africa, where society is facing a general
crisis, especially in its relations with young
people.
Most of the migrants who pour into the
towns and cities from the countryside are,
as in most Third World countries, young
people seeking jobs in mines, on plantations
and elsewhere.
In the countries of the Sahel, this
phenomenon began in the colonial period
when these, countries were integrated into
the international economic system; it has
become more widespread because . of
drought and other climatic factors. In the
past migrations were temporary; today
migrants are everywhere tending to settle
down permanently. In addition, many
young people are migrating to the in¬
dustrialized countries of the West. The
result is that the rural areas are becoming
depopulated; those who live there tend in¬
creasingly to be adult women, children and
the elderly.
Young people seem to feel condemned to
an inevitable fate which, when analysed,
appears to be the result of a number of fac
tors, the most important of which are
economic, social and cultural.
Among the economic causes is the system
of land-ownership which, in spite of the
conditions specific to Africa, make for
social inequality, the irregularity of farm
yields as a result of climatic conditions and
technological backwardness, and the
regrouping of industries in urban centres.
The social causes are due to a variety of
factors: the inequality of individual in¬
comes between rural and urban areas; the
centralization of essential social and
(especially) political activities; the limited
extent to which young people participate in
the organization and execution of local ac¬
tivities; the weight of administrative and
supervisory structures in the rural areas;
and the inadequacy of infrastructures:
roads, electricity, water, transport,
hospitals, schools, leisure and information
facilities all that can make village life self-
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
sufficient and counteract the attraction of
city life.
A cultural factor worth noting is the
burden of community-based customs and
traditional values which impose constraints
on the individual and imply constant
reference to the group. Migration to the
towns is sometimes felt to be a liberation,
even though it is prompted by material
conditions.
Young people who have been through the
educational system are particularly sensitive
to this. They form a large proportion of the
migrant masses since it is more difficult for
them than the rest to make a place for
themselves in rural society; their education
turns them into misfits in their own
environment.
For African schools are usually incapable
of integrating young people into society. In
view of the widely admitted fact that the
modern school system inherited from col-
onialization has failed, reforms have been
widely attempted. However, it must be ad¬
mitted that the problems remain.
One of these problems is the small
number of children in school. In spite of big
efforts and often-repeated declarations of
principle, many children are still excluded
from any form of schooling. In some cases,
the percentage of children in school is even
falling. Illiteracy is high both among young
people and adults, in spite of the organiza¬
tion of literacy campaigns in national
languages.
Generally speaking, the percentage of
children in school is less high in rural areas
than in the towns and cities. There are not
so many schools in the countryside, and
they are often so few and far between that
parents prefer to keep children, especially
their daughters, at home. If the number of
schools in urban areas is also limited in rela¬
tion to the very high level of demand, the
Above, a group of young Malians cross
the Niger with cattle from their village. In
Mali, where more than half the population
is between the age of 20 and 25, young
villagers of the same age group belong to
a "Ton", a traditional association whose
members perform farming and other
tasks of importance to the community as
a whole. "Ton-ci", the culture based on
the association, teaches young people
respect for the group, solidarity and
mutual aid, and prepares them for life in
the community.
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
situation is nevertheless better than in rural
areas.
In both cases, the school system rejects
numbers of young people and produces
drop-outs. Very few of those who start
school reach the end of their1 course,
especially in the rural areas where those who
go beyond the elementary stage are rare.
Furthermore, the school is still cut off
from its true cultural environment so that it
perpetuates among young people a sense of
alienation, aggravated by the fact that the
socialization process, especially carried out
by the family, takes place elsewhere.
Schools place young people in an environ¬
ment characterized by intellectuality,
abstraction and anonymity, as opposed to
the personalization, individuality and affec-
tivity of the family. The need to use a
language other than the mother tongue
sometimes makes the transition from fami¬
ly to school a harrowing experience involv¬
ing traumas which result in failure at
school. This duality of language and
cultural environment makes it difficult, and
sometimes impossible, for the former to ex¬
press the latter, and this ambiguity is
reflected in school programmes, textbooks,
and texts which are incapable of describing
in a foreign language the reality of ex¬
perience within a unique culture. In this
situation, the children, who understand
neither the languages nor the cultural
models vehicled by them, easily fall victim
to failure. In addition, the teaching pro¬
grammes take no account of the distinctive
features of the school's historical,
geographical or social environment.
Nor does the school provide professional
training, and the institutions established for
this purpose are inadequate and ill-fitted to
the needs of the different productive sec
tors. Young people find it difficult to in¬
tegrate themselves into economic systems
which do not function to increase a coun¬
try's potential and wealth; the activities of
these systems are determined by the roles,
inherited from colonial times, which have
devolved upon them in the international
division of labour. In addition to the effects
of crises, this situation essentially generates
underemployment and unemployment, two
Important facts of life for young Africans.
Rural populations which are under¬
employed because of the seasonal nature of
their work are forced to leave the coun¬
tryside. Young people in urban areas face
the problem of unemployment which af¬
fects both the illiterate and those who have
received an education, whatever its level.
But a new phenomenon, which more than
any other reveals the stagnation of the
employment situation, has appeared in
African societies: the unemployment of
those who have earned degrees in higher
education.
In the Republic of Niger, the Samaria
(from the Hausa word meaning youth; are
groups ofyoung people which were tradi¬
tionally organized in the villages under a
Sarkin Samari ("youth leader") to per¬
form tasks delegated to them by the chief.
Today the Samaria Is the name of Niger's
national youth movement whose
members are taking part in many develop¬
ment projects including reforestation,
measures to stop desert encroachment
and the construction of classrooms and
schools. Left, the Samaria on-site during
the building of a school.
The centuries-old Naam tradition in
Burkina-Faso (formerly Upper Volta) was
based on equality and shared labour for
the benefit of all members of the com¬
munity. Today the Naam movement is
undergoing a revival, serving both as a
structure for training and giving young
people greater responsibilities and as a
communal production organization deep¬
ly rooted in the village social and cultural
system. Since 1966 over a thousand
Naam groups have been formed, usually
consisting of young men and women
from the same village or group of
districts. Members of the groups par¬
ticipate In the development of their com¬
munity by cultivating the land, construc¬
ting wells and small dams and in many
other ways. Right, in the province of
Yatenga, a Naam group digs a pond.
Left, young and old work shoulder to
shoulder, busily tilling the soil in one of
Tanzania's communal Ujamaa villages
(see page 22).
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The unemployment problem is
qualitative as well as quantitative, for the
quality of the jobs available to young peo¬
ple has a direct impact on their participation
in the life of the society in which they live.
Young villagers work in such difficult con¬
ditions that they are forced to swell the
ranks of the floating and unproductive ur¬
ban masses in the informal sector, living on
their wits and in many cases turning to
delinquency.
Young workers of both sexes doing jobs
which require no qualifications are involved
in productive work which has little meaning
for them. Within the working class they
form a mass seeking survival at all cost's;
they are excluded from the power to take
decisions which is in the hands of a foreign
minority and work in accordance with
norms which they have not chosen, for ob¬
jectives which often run counter to the in¬
terests of development and are misapplied
to the profit of a few.
Young workers and supervisory staff in
the administrative and commercial sector
also feel frustrated because of their exclu¬
sion from any form of participation and
decision-making. They are profoundly
discouraged and in time their feeling of
uselessness overflows beyond their work
situation. In administrative work their reac¬
tion takes the form of laxity and lack of
civic spirit and leads to all kinds of social
deviations.
This social crisis is accompanied by a
crisis in the family. Previously integrated
into a wider structure of relationships of a
patriarchal nature, the family today is ten¬
ding to become a nuclear family, especially
in the towns and cities. This has encouraged
the development of individualism. The
gradual disappearance of the patriarchal
system is creating authority problems in the
family and in society at large, where it
formerly cemented a wide range of social
relationships. Incomprehension prevails
between young people and adults, who
judge each other in terms of different socio-
historical contexts and value systems. All
the same, these conflicts are still latent, for
respect for age and the elders is still an im¬
portant fact of African life and psychology.
The adoption by young people of foreign
values and libertarian principles is not
leading to the kind of far-reaching criticism
of the social and cultural order that can be
seen elsewhere.
Lack of participation by young people is
accentuated by the lack of an African na¬
tional consciousness, that is, of a feeling of
identification with and integration in socie¬
ty as a whole. Its absence explains among
other things why young Africans do not
feel concerned by mobilization for
development.
The problem of youth in Africa hinges on
the question of participation. What can be
done to make young people aware of their
responsibilities and mobilize them?
Generally speaking, development
strategies must be redirected and aim at a
greater independence from the interna¬
tional economic system and a reduction of
social inequalities. A rural development
policy must be promoted in order to
transform the living conditions of rural
populations. Action must be taken on the
job market and employment structures.
Grass-roots community participation in
' development plans must be encouraged and
production structures transformed with a
view to greater participation of workers in
conception and decision-making processes.
Institutions must be established to promote
a co-operative approach to the organization
of production, human settlements (which
must be rethought both in urban and rural
areas), health, education and leisure.
For young people, education must be ex¬
tended and educational systems be reform¬
ed so that they are more deeply rooted in the
real situation in each country, so that more
attention is paid to environmental ques¬
tions, and so that these systems are more ef¬
fectively dovetailed into the structures of
production and employment. Less selective
educational methods should be introduced,
giving more responsibility to young people.
The encouragement of responsible attitudes
is a process that must take place at all levels
of society: young people should be en¬
couraged to assume responsibility for their
own organizations and define the objectives
of these organizations within the global
development strategy of each society.
Greater efforts must be made to encourage
them to feel that they belong to the com¬
munity, and their creativity, their spirit of
initiative and their critical sense must be
developed.
BOUBAKAR LY, Senegalese educator, Is lec¬
turer in sociology at the University of Dakar.
He is the author of many sociological studies
on A frican institutions. The present article has
been extracted from a paper presented to an
international symposium on "Youth, Popula¬
tion and Development in the Third World"
organized by the United Nations in Bucharest
in June 1984.
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
China's most precious
energy source
by Tang Ruoxin
AS the most active, sensitive and
vigorous element in modern
societies, the young people of the
world represent the future. They are our
most precious "energy source" and the
motor that pushes society forward. On
them depends the direction the human race
will take in the twenty-first century.
There is, however, a dual aspect of youth.
Young people are always the pioneers who
break with undesirable customs and social
traditions, bravely challenging all kinds of
chronic social ills; yet their naivety and im¬
patient discontent can often disturb other
people's daily lives and obstruct social
development.
As a group, young people are in the ma¬
jority. China, for example, is a country of
young people with more than sixty per cent
of the population under the age of thirty
and about seventy per cent under thirty-
five. Young people make up fifty per cent
of the total rural labour force and sixty per
cent of the total industrial work force.
Similar increases in the proportion of young
people in total population are forecast
world-wide and in particular in the develop¬
ing countries.
Modern life is changing young people's
values very rapidly. In China today they
have much greater self-esteem and self-
confidence than twenty years ago; they
stress the importance of the individual in
social life and. are eager to make a more
creative contribution to social progress.
There are two main raisons for this. The
first of these is the spread of scientific
knowledge. Ten times as many young
Chinese . receive higher education today
than was the case twenty years ago and they
form a group which is dedicated to the pur¬
suit of science and progress. Furthermore,
statistics show that more than ninety per
cent of young workers have received
primary education and, even in those rural
areas where education is relatively
backward, the cultural level of young
peasants has risen considerably.
The second reason is that social turmoil
"The traditional view that has prevailed In
China for thousands of years of the
superiority of agriculture as a form of
employment constitutes a serious
psychological barrier to the acceptance
by young people of jobs in commerce or
in the service sector. A serious effort has
been made to convince young people that
all types of jobs are equally worthwhile
and make no difference to social status. "
has subsided and a policy of reform has
been adopted. The Chinese Government is
devoting a major effort to reform of the
economy, thus creating conditions which
enable young people to give free rein to
their creative ability and talents.
Changing values are also reflected in
changing patterns of consumption. Young
Chinese people's life styles, including the
food they eat, the clothes they wear, their
transportation and their homes, their hob¬
bies and interests, have undergone a
remarkable change. The general trend is
towards high consumption, a factor which
will be of great significance for economic
development in China as in other develop¬
ing countries. A recent survey shows that
the sale of high-quality goods in China has
increased fifty times in twenty years and
that seventy per cent of buyers of these
goods are young people.
Providing young people with jobs has
become a serious problem for all countries
and China, with its large population is no
exception. The young people born in the
1960s are coming on to the labour market
and providing jobs for such large numbers
has put great pressure on the Government.
Experts have forecast that China's labour
force will increase by two hundred and thir¬
ty million over the next two decades,
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
'sti'^-*
m te
reaching more than six hundred million by
the year 2000.
In recent years, specialists in youth
research, who have studied this problem in
collaboration with economists, sociologists
and educationists, have proposed that
young people should be allowed the
freedom to look for jobs themselves and
have suggested a number of ways of
creating more job opportunities for them.
Combined with State economic reforms this
has created favourable conditions for solv¬
ing the youth employment problem. Since
1980, about fifty million young people have
found jobs.
To meet the needs of economic develop¬
ment in China, the quality of the labour
force must be rapidly improved. A research
report shows that China's young workers,
although more skilled than their parents,
are still far from matching the demands im¬
posed by the world revolution in science and
technology. To meet these demands we
need to make education more widespread,
raise the educational level and improve
vocational and pre-employment job-
training. A survey of two enterprises in
Suzhou City shows that trained workers are
superior in adaptability and creativity to
untrained workers and that their produc¬
tivity is 16.5 per cent higher.
Youth research experts also point out
that, in view of changes and reforms in the
economic system, the educational system
should undertake to alter young people's
traditional attitudes towards employment.
For example, the traditional view that has
prevailed in China for thousands of years of
the superiority of agriculture as a form of
employment constitutes a serious
psychological barrier to the acceptance by
young people of jobs in commerce or in the
service sector. A serious effort has been
made to convince young people that all
types of jobs are equally worthwhile and
make no difference to social status.
"As the most active, sensitive and
vigorous element in modern societies,
the young people of the world represent
the future... On them depends the direc¬
tion the human race will take in the
twenty-first century".
Juvenile delinquency is another com¬
plicated social phenomenon common to
many countries which requires serious
scientific research. Since the 1970s, juvenile
delinquency has become an increasingly
serious problem in China. In 1983, the
crime rate among teenagers amounted to
nine per 10,000. Although this figure is not
very high, juvenile crime represented
seventy-five per cent of all crimes commit¬
ted, a tenfold increase over the 1950s.
A social problem such as juvenile delin¬
quency can only be tackled by mobilizing
the resources of society as a whole. In
China, government departments are
responsible for co-ordinating the work of
the various social sectors. The research
departments are responsible for social in¬
vestigations, case analysis and have an ad¬
visory role and they work in close co¬
operation with the judicial departments and
social organizations such as neighbourhood
committees and the Youth League.
The public security departments and the
courts ensure that criminal offences are
punished in accordance with the law and at¬
tempt to reform culprits who are serving
sentences through corrective study and
labour.
The neighbourhood committees and the
Youth League have a preventive and
rehabilitative role. First of all they try to
spot potential delinquents and to prevent
them from committing crimes. Their se¬
cond task is to care for delinquents return¬
ing home after a period of imprisonment
,1 Ï
and to ensure that they do not relapse into
crime. Returning delinquents are given
preferential treatment as regards education
and employment in order to encourage
them to mend their ways, and these
measures have been very effective in reduc¬
ing juvenile delinquency and maintaining
public security.
Physical and psychological factors are
also important elements in youth research.
Researchers have discovered, for example,
that young Chinese are reaching physical
maturity two to three years earlier than did
the same age group of twenty years ago, a
fact which has important implications for
the country's economic and political life
and for the legal and educational systems.
Youth is a period of rapid physical
growth and of the attainment of sexual
maturity. It is a period during which
character, the sentiments and emotions are
unstable and this can lead to irrational ac¬
tion. This is why research on youth
psychology in China concentrates on the
specific characteristics of young people's
conceptual, emotional and sentimental
development and self-awareness.
There remains the important task of
adapting education to meet the new needs
of youth. This must be done in a scientific
way if we are to bring up a generation
capable of meeting the demands of the
twenty-first century.
TANG RUOXIN, of China, is bureau chief of
the Youth Research Institute of the Chinese
Academy of Social Sciences and deputy
editor-in-chief of the series To the Future.
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
A truce for children
by Hélène Ahrweiler
Photo © Felix Tinhes Jaramillo, Bogotá
SPECIFIC texts designed to ensure the
protection of children engaged in
national or international armed
conflicts have already been drawn up by the
Red Cross and the United Nations.
However, these often remain a dead letter
since many conflicts occur with no official
declaration of war.
Cases have been known of thirteen-year-
old paratroopers in action, ten-year-olds
being used to clear minefields and seven-
year-olds taking part in terrorist
operations.
Some obscure and primitive reasoning,
which merits careful psychoanalytical ex¬
amination, seems to prevent us from taking
a bold stand against the indoctrination and
mental preparation of children for war,
their paramilitary training, their employ¬
ment in the preparation of military defence
works, their enrolment in combat units and
even their widespread use in the front line
from the age of ten.
For the militarization of children is not a
new phenomenon. We have only to recall
the children's crusades of the early thir¬
teenth century, one of the causes of which
was probably the population explosion. In
the year 1212, twenty thousand children,
some of them barely eight years old, set out
from Marseilles for the Holy Land. Of the
seven ships in which they embarked, two
sank and the remaining five reached land at
Bougie (present day Bejaia, Algeria) and
Alexandria, where the surviving children
were sold as slaves. Other children's
crusades set out from Italy, Flanders and
from the Rhineland.
It would seem that the time has come to
set out in more detail the rights of children,
to be inscribed alongside the rights of man.
It is true that, in November 1959, the
General Assembly of the United Nations
adopted a ten-point Declaration of the
Rights of the Child. Nevertheless, the in¬
creasingly widespread militarization of
children has not only resulted in the deaths
of many, with others left permanently han¬
dicapped or enclosed in prisoner of war
camps, it also means that whole sections of
the youth of the world are growing up in an
atmosphere of violence; this calls for addi¬
tional, more specific measures.
Unesco has mobilized the international
community for the protection of historic
monuments, that is to say the world's
cultural heritage. Should not similar steps
be taken to mobilize support for the protec¬
tion of children, who make up the world's
human heritage?
Any Convention that might be drawn up
should give priority to two simple measures:
(a) Prohibition of the enlistment of any
child under the age of sixteen for whatever
purpose.
(b) Recognition of the right to education,
which would imply the evacuation of
schools and schoolchildren from any area
which, for whatever reason, had become
destabilized.
On the analogy of truces declared to
enable the wounded to be evacuated and
cared for, a "truce for children" should be
instituted, since children are just as helpless
as the wounded.
"The world", wrote the French author
Georges Bernanos (1888-1948) in his book
A Diary of my Times, "will be judged by
the children." Nor should we forget
another of the same author's sayings:
"Blessed is he who saves from despair the
heart of a child."
HELENE AHRWEILER, who was born in
Athens, has been Rector of the Academy of
Paris and Chancellor of the Universities of
Paris since 1982.
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices:
Unesco, 7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 68 French francs. 2 years (valid only in
France): 1 20 French francs. Binder for a year's issues:
52 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering pos¬
tage. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions and
headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boun¬
daries on maps published in the magazine do not imply offi¬
cial endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the United
Nations.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm and/or
microfiche! by: (Il Unesco, 7 Place da Fontenoy, 75700 Paris :
(2) University Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor, Michigan 481 00,
U.S.A.: 13) NCR. Microcard Edition. Indian Head, Inc., 111
West 40th Street, New York, U.S.A.: (4) Bell and Howell Co.,
Old Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
Roy Malkin
French: Alain Lévêque (Paris)
Neda el Khazen
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Jorge Enrique Adoum
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov (Paris)
Arabic: Sayed Osman (Paris)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Rajmani Tiwari (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Brotdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: Hossein Razmdjou (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Vitomir Sudarski (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Inger Raaby (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Braille: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Servat
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Special projects: Peggy Julien
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
34 BRODARO GRAPHIQUE. COULOMMIERS - Dépit légal C 1 Juin 1985 - IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed ¡n France)
PHOTOCOMPOSITION CHRISTIAN PAGNOUD - 6/8, rue des Épinettes - 75017 PARIS - PHOTOGRAVURE DAWANT - 13, rue des Arquebusiers - 75003 PARIS.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Just published
Education and
the world of work
Michel Carton
The training of young people for productive
work is a subject which has aroused great in¬
terest in recent years. In this study prepared
for the International Bureau of Education,
Michel Carton, of the University of Geneva,
traces the interaction between education and
productive work through different historical
periods and against a variety of cultural,
political and economic backgrounds. Educa¬
tion and the World of Work examines topics
relating to:
Work and society
h Work and training policies
Work and skills
Initial education and productive work
Work and further training
(unesoo
ISBN 92-3-102220-2 237 Pages 50 French francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Colling-
wood Victoria 3066; Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd.
P.O. Box 33, Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty.
Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-
agent: United Nations Association of Australia, P.O. Box 175,
Sth floor. Ana House, 28 Elizabeth Street, Melbourne Victoria
3000. AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31,
A-l 01 1 , Vienna. BAHAMAS. Nassau Stationers Ltd., P.O. Box
N-3138, Nassau. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books
International Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola,
Dacca 3. BARBADOS. University of the West Indies
Bookshop, Cave Hill Campus, P.O. Box 64, Bridgetown.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V.
Handelmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. BOTSWANA. Botswana Book Centre, P.O.
Box 91, Gaborone. BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co.
Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H 1M7.
CHINA. China National Publications Import and Export
Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Beijing. CYPRUS. "MAM",
Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box 1 722, Nicosia.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena 51-113 02, Prague
1 ; Ve Smeckach 30, P.O.B. 790 - 1 1 1 - 27 Prague 1 (Permanent
display); Zahranicni literatura, 1 1 Soukenicka, Prague 1 . For
Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893
31 Bratislava - CSSR. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export-OG
Tidsskriftservice 35 Norre Sogade, DK-1970 Kobenhavn K.
EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco
Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo. ETHIOPIA.
National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100
Helsinki 10; Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, Koivuvaarankuja 2,
01640 Vantaa 64. FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de
Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP. 12598-48. GERMAN
DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710
Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R.
FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier (German,
English, French and Spanish editions): Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher
Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57, D5300 Bonn 3. For
other Unesco publications: Karger Verlag, Germering/München.
For scientific maps only: Geo Center, Postfach 800830,
Stuttgart 80. GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O.
Box 195, Accra: Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University
Bookshop of Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legón,
P.O. Box 1, Legón. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
HONG KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen
Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book
Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon. Hong Kong Government
Information Services, Publication Centre, Baskerville House, 22
Ice Street. HUNGARY. Kultura-Bushimport - ABT, P.O.B. 1 49 -
H-l 389, Budapest 62. ICELAND. Snaebjörn Jonsson & Co.,
H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd.,
Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan
Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2;
5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh, Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahatma
Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001. Sub-Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.
17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House, New Delhi;
Publication Unit, Ministry of Education and Culture, Ex. AFO
Hutments, Dr. Rajendra Prasad Road, New Delhi 1 10001.
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl. Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Indira P. T., Jl Dr Sam Ratulangie 37,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co.,
28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Enghélab Avenue. P.O. Box 314/1486,
Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco. 1 188 Enghlab Av.,
Rostam Give Building, Zip Code 13158, P.O. Box 11365-4498,
Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, Al Rashid Street,
Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL. A.B.C.
Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1 283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv
61000. ITALY. Licosa (Librería Commissionana Sansoni, S.p.A.)
Via Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552, 50121 Florence.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101
Water Lane, Kingston. University of the West Indies Bookshop,
Mona, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo
3-chome Bunkyo-ku Tokyo 1 13. KENYA. East African Publishing
House, P.O. Box 30571, Nairobi; Africa Book Services Ltd.,
Quran House, Mfangano Street, P.O. Box 45245, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box
Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd,
POB 2942, Kuwait; for the Unesco Courier; Farafalla Press
Agency, P.O. Box SAFA 4541, Kuwait. LESOTHO. Mazenod
Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod. Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA.
Code and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LIECHTENSTEIN : Eurocan Trust Reg. P.O.B. 5 - 9494 Schaan.
LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication & Distribution,
P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück,
22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg. MALAWI. Malawi Book Service,
Head Office, P.O. Box 30044 Chichiri, Blantyre 3. MALAYSIA.
University of Malaya Cooperative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur
22-11. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta.
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-
Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-
Carlo. NEPAL. Sajha Prakashan Polchowk, Kathmandu.
NETHERLANDS. KEESING BOEKEN B.V., Joan Muyskenweg.
22, Postbus 1118. 1000 BC Amsterdam. NETHERLANDS
ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad,
Curaçao. N.A. NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Office,
Government Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344,
Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace. P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch;
Alma Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box
1104, Dunedin, Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington.
NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The University
Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka; The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zaria. NORWAY. Johan Grundt Tanum,
P.O.B. 1 177 Sentrum Oslo 1, Narvesen A/S; Subscription and
Trade Book Service. P.O.B. 6125 Etterstad, Oslo 6; Universitets
Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, Postboks 307 Blindem, Oslo 3.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O.
Box No. 729, Lahore 3; Unesco Publications Centre, Regional
Office for Book development in Asia and the Pacific, 39 Delhi
Housing Society, P.O. Box 8950, Karachi 29. PHILIPPINES.
National Book Store, Inc. 701, Rizal Avenue, Manila D-404.
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068 WARSAW.
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livraria Portugal, rua do
Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES. National Bookshop, P.O. Box
48, Mahé; New Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131,
Mahé. SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra
Leone Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown. SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (SI Pte Ltd. Times Jurong, 2 Jurong Port Road,
Singapore 2261. SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern
Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951, Mogadiscio. SOUTH
AFRICA. For the Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Central
News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg. SRI LANKA. Lake
House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B.
244 Colombo 2. SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118,
Khartoum. SWEDEN. All publications A/B.C.E. Fritzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356. 10327
Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN Förbundet,
Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm; Wennergren-
Williams, Box 30004-S-104, 25 Stockholm; Esselte
Tidskriftscentralen, Gamla Brogatan 26, Box 62 - 101 20
Stockholm. SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag. 5
Rämistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva
11, CCP. 12-236. Librairies Payot also in Lausanne, Basle,
Berne, Vevey, Montreux, Neuchâtel and Zurich. TANZANIA.
Dares Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam.
THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road,
Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402; Bangkok: Suksapan Panit,
Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Sukstt Siam
Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street. St. Clair, Trinidad, W.l. TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S.,
Istiklâl Caddesi, N° 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu, Istambul.
UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 7145, Kampala.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, H.M.S.O., P.O.
Box 276, London, SWS 5DT, and Govt. Bookshops in London.
Edinburgh, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol; for
scientific maps only: McCarta Ltd., 122 King's Cross Road,
London WC IX 9 OS. UNITED STATES. Unipub, 205 East
42nd Street, New York, N.Y. 1 001 7. Orders for books &
Periodicals: P.O. Box 1 222, Ann Arbor. Ml 48 1 06. U.S.S.R.
Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Moscow, 121200. YEMEN. 14th
October Corporation, P.O. Box 4227, Aden. YUGOSLAVIA.
Mladost, Mica 30/1 1 , Zagreb; Cankarjeva Zalozba, Zopitarjeva 2,
Lubljana; Nolit, Terazije 27/1 1, Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd., P.O. Box 2664
Lusaka. ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union
Avenue, Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Photo Unesco
When words take wing
In the modern world, literacy is the part of the celebration of Internation-
sine qua non of both national develop- al Youth Year, Unesco has organized
ment and individual fulfilment. Yet a competition, open to the youth of
though the proportion of illiterates in the world, on the theme "Youth and
the world population is falling, the Literacy", to find a poster to publicize
absolute number of illiterates is still International Literacy Day, 8 Sept-
rising. Only by a determined attack ember 1985. Above, an entry submit-
on illiteracy among young people will ted by 15-year-old Abdelhak El Bech,
this scourge finally be eradicated. As of Haouaria, Tunisia.
]]>
</page>
</document>
