<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="064933eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The
11
i m I
FEBRUARY NOBEL PRIZE WINNERS' ROUND TABLE Price: i/-stfl. (U.K.)
(/2th year) SCI EN CE 6t AtW A N Iv I N O 60 francs (France)
30 cents (U . S.)
60 francs ( rance)
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
People foolishly think that if they ban the hydrogen
bomb they have finished. Make no mistake., if a war
starts, every hydrogen bomb and every weapon of war
will be thrown in. The only way to save humanity is to
ban war itself.
Lord John Boyd Orr,
Nobel Peace Prize
It is clear that with thermo-nuclear weapons a total war
is not feasible any more. It would amount to mass
suicide or mass murder. But there is a more insidious
danger and that danger is the so-called small tactical
atomic weapon. Such a weapon is of a size comparable
with the Hiroshima bomb. It may be a quarter the size
but it is several hundred times more powerful than the
largest block-buster of the last war. Such a weapon must
be a fission weapon and cannot be " clean ". By its very
nature a considerable area of the ground would be
contaminated by the radio-active fall-out. To talk of
such weapons as "small tactical weapons" is to deceive
the public.
Homi Jehangir Bhabha,
Chairman of the Indian
Atomic Energy Commission
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
FEBRUARY 1959
12 T H YEAR
No. 2
CONTENTS
NOBEL PRIZE WINNERS' ROUND TABLE
PAGE
Special Issue
3 EDITORIAL
4 SCIENCE, TECHNOLOGY & MAN
By J. Boyd Orr
8 THE GAP BETWEEN RICH & POOR NATIONS
By P.M.S. Blackett
12 REDUCING ARMAMENTS TO PAY FOR
EDUCATION
By G. Berger
A NEW WORLD OPENING UP
IS THE REVOLUTION IN MEDICINE
By B. Houssay
17 HAVE WE THE RIGHT TO USE OUR SOIL
RECKLESSLY?
By W. Noyes
SCIENCE AGAINST WAR
21 PEACE OR WAR: WHICH ROAD WILL MEN TAKE Î
By N. Semenav
23 WAR IS NOW OBSOLETE
By H.J. Bhabha
25 THE CAUSES OF WAR: FEAR, PRIDE, POVERTY
By G. Berger
THE MARCH OF SCIENCE
27
28
33
CAN SCIENCE CHANGE A PERSON'S HEREDITY?
By W. Noyes and B. Houssay
FRONTIERS BETWEEN INANIMATE & ANIMATE
MATTER
By N. Semenov and D. Bovet
FOOD FOR ALL: A PROBLEM OF KILOWATT-
HOURS
By H.J. Bhabha
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7', France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7'
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly ( I 2 issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. The United States of America edition is distri¬
buted by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 801 Third Avenue, New
York 22, N.Y., Plaza 1-3860. Second-class mail privileges authorized at New
York, N.Y. (M.C. 58.1.133 A)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER plus date
of issue", and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the' opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: $3.00; I 0/-stg. ; 600 Fr. frs. or equivalent.
COVER PHOTO
What structural changes occur in ura¬
nium when it is subjected to immense
heat in a nuclear reactor ? To help
science to answer this question an
American company built the plastic
models of the crystal structure of
uranium shown here, together with
the special measuring equipment used
by the scientist studying the models.
USIS
C C T N general there are now two groups of people in the
I world: those full of hope but living in poverty and
those enjoying prosperity yet haunted by fear of the
future. Perhaps science furnish the means to break
this hellish circle... If we are rational, if we achieve
freedom through science, then, carried onward by it, we
may perhaps taste the pleasures of culture, promised to
all men yet still far from accessible to all. This thought
itself should be like an open wound to us for we could
never, without a pang of conscience, take pleasure in
even the finest of cultural things while knowing that
there are millions of men and women in the world who
suffer from hunger."
In these words, Professor Gaston Berger, the eminent
French psychologist, concisely summed up the problem
and the promise of science and society in our day.
Professor Berger, who has been called "a bridge-builder
between the social sciences and the exact sciences," was
participating in the International Round Table of world-
renowned scientists which recently debated the vital
question, "Man and Scientific and Technical Progress," in
Unesco's new headquarters in Paris.
"Unesco," Professor Berger told the audience in the
great Conference Hall, "is far more than an organization
whose job it is to provide technical and financial aid for
a certain number of scientific, educational and cultural
projects. Unesco must stimulate the efforts of others,
bring about meetings, call up new ideas. In a world of
constant change it must be in the vanguard of research
and invention. And in the same world, restless, disturbed
and fearful, it knows too that it must be a pillar of great
moral strength.
"To justify the hopes that men place in it, Unesco
keeps a double goal in view. It can and must turn to
the most eminent men in every field, yet it must never
forget that it is at the service of all men: on the one
hand the scientists, artists, writers and great teachers; on
the other, the immense numbers of men and women who
aspire to knowledge, who have a right to culture and who
must be given access to education. Between the two
Unesco lays down its bridges."
Today, technology and its creations are no longer the
exclusive realm of engineers and industrialists. They are
part of the everyday scene, of immediate concern to all
of us. How are men and women to adjust themselves to
the impact of science and technology on their lives?
Educational programmes and broad campaigns pub¬
licizing the work of scientists and technologists could do
much to make the ever-expanding frontiers of scientific
knowledge seem less remote. And the value of a broad
appraisal such as that made at the Unesco Round Table
lies in its ability to bring into perspective for the man-in-
the-street the vast new World which the triumphs of
science and technology are creating for him. That too
is the purpose of this issue of The Unesco Courier,
entirely devoted to the debates of the great scientists at
the International Round Table.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Sei ë nee, Technology & Man
NOBEL PRIZE WINNERS
ROUND TABLE
Today, science and the tremendous technical advances it has made possible are reshaping our lives at an over¬
whelming speed, bringing both benefits and hazards, constantly posing moral, economic and social problems.-
In Paris recently, eight world-famous scientists, five of them Nobel Prize winners set outto explore the ever-advancing
frontiers of today's science and technology and to examine some of the problems created by the increasing pace
of scientific conquests, at an International Round Table debate on "Man and Scientific and Technical Progress".
Seated ata "Round Table" set up under the immense shell of reinforced concrete housing Unesco's new Con¬
ference Hall, these top-ranking scientists were taking part in what was probably the most important event of
"Unesco Month", a succession of scientific and cultural events organized on the occasion of the inauguration of
Unesco's new Headquarters and Unesco's Tenth General Conference.
During three remarkable evening meetings vital questions arising from the impact of science and technology on
human life were discussed by members of the Round Table whose debates were also followed on the third evening
by radio and T.V. audiences In many European countries.
In this issue we present significant passages from the debates of the international Round Table, beginning with
the introductory remarks of Lord John Boyd Orr, Great Britain, who presided at the meetings (see opposite page).
.*/-.-<
I
Uiu
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1959
EThe men of science who are here
do not represent their govern¬
ments. They come here as scien¬
tists and the only master that a
scientist knows is the truth. What
will they speak about? They are
going to discuss the advance of
science and the effect of science
on human society.
It is the advance of science,
leading to technology and to the
birth of new ideas, which has
guided the full evolution of our
civilization. Every advance of
LORD BOYD orr science demands and brings about
some change in the structure of
human society. Thus civilization has advanced in the
last 10,000 years, adjusting itself to these changes,
sometimes with difficulty, but managing to survive.
The problem of the present day, however, is that in
our generation science has advanced at an accelerating
rate. In the last 50 years science has advanced more than
in the 2,000 previous years and in this advance has given
man enormous new powers. Physicists tell us they have
produced the hydrogen bomb, which makes war
impossible. No great power can now declare war on
another great power with these instruments of death and
destruction without committing suicide.
The advance of modern technology has also enabled us
to produce in abundance everything that mankind needs.
Let me give you an illustration. In my day we have had
two world wars when science and technology were geared
for destruction. And since the last world war a third of
national incomes has been devoted to armaments. In
spite of that destruction, in spite of that diversion of
wealth to armaments which gives no rise in the standard
of living, the standard of living today in the industrialized
countries is very much higher than in 1914.
In biological science it is the same and in agriculture
the greatly increased yields per acre, and per annum
enable us to produce food in abundance. The problem of
today is totally different from the problems of the 19th
century and earlier. Today we can produce goods in such
abundance that the problem is how to get them distribut¬
ed and consumed so to prevent an accumulation of
surpluses and resulting unemployment.
In medicine there has been the great conquest of
disease. Medicine has enabled us to control the great
killing diseases, with the exception of one or two, like
cancer, to cure them and in most cases to prevent them.
What has been the result? Great expansion in the length
of human life. Twenty to thirty years of increased life
to every child born today is a greater gift of modern
science than the gift of the hydrogen bomb.
In the past, hunger and disease limited the growth of
population. Today hunger can be abolished, disease is
rapidly being defeated and we are having an explosive
rise in population. This is one of the problems we shall
need to deal with. Thus, you see, the advance of science
has driven us into an entirely new age an age where war
is impossible. That is the biggest revolution which has
ever taken place since the beginning of civilization.
Can we adjust ourselves to that? It has changed the
age of inevitable scarcity, with poverty for the majority
of mankind, into a new age of potential abundance for
everybody. Can we adjust society to these great new
changes? It is not so easy. Jet planes have made the
world so small and they have made the affairs of all
countries so deeply, intimately interlocked that the whole
world has to change before any single country can survive
and adopt these changes. Can we adjust human society
to these great changes? Some people think we cannot.
I believe we can. But it depends upon whether the
people of the world realize what it is we have to face up
to, and to make it possible for our governments to lead
us to a wonderful new age.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
JOHN BOYD ORR (Great Britain)
has spent a large part of his career as a
scientist fighting man's battle against
hunger. As a doctor and agronomist,
he has devoted special attention to
problems of nutrition and agriculture
on a world scale. From 1945 to I 948 he
was Director-General of the U.N. Food
and Agriculture Organization. In 1949
he was made a peer and was awarded
the Nobel Peace Prize. Lord Boyd Orr
¡s a member of the Royal Society and a
was formerly a Member of Parliament.
GASTON BERGER (France) ¡s a
distinguished philosopher and psycholo¬
gist and the author of many authoritative
works especially in the field of charac-
terology. A Member of the Institut de
France, and President of the International
Institute of Philosophy, Gaston Berger is
also Director-General of Higher Educa¬
tion in France, and President of the
French National Commission for Unesco.
NIKOLAI SEMENOV (U.S.S.R.), win¬
ner of the Nobel Prize for Chemistry,
1956, is one of the world's leading
authorities on the chemistry of chain
reactions. His theories on simple chain
reactions and on branching chain reac¬
tions have had a profound effect on
chemical thinking. He is a member of
the Praesidium of the Academy of Sciences,
Moscow, and Director of the Academy's
Institute of Physics and Chemistry.
DANIEL BOVET (Italy) was one of
the discoverers of the sulphonamides
and is one of the world's leading autho¬
rities on synthetic curares which play
important roles in surgery and In physio¬
logical research. He Is head and founder
of the Therapeutical Chemistry Labora¬
tory at the Institute of Health in Rome.
Daniel Bovet was awarded the 1957
Nobel Prize for Physiology and Medicine.
BERNARDO ALBERT HOUSSAY
(Argentine) winner of the Nobel Prize
for physiology and medicine in 1947, is
one of the creators of endocrinology, the
science of hormones. His research work
in internal secretions and his studies on
diabetes have brought him wide recog¬
nition. A member of the Argentine
Academies of Medicine, Letters and
Sciences, and of the National Academy
of XL in Rome, Bernardo Houssay is now
Director of the Instituto de Biología y
Medicina Expérimental, in Buenos Aires.
WILLIAM ALBERT NOYES (United
States) a distinguished educator and
scientist who is widely known for his
work both in physical chemistry and
international affairs. Vice-chairman of
the Committee on Space Research of the
International Council of Scientific Unions,
he is also a member of the Executive
Committee of the International Union
of Pure and Applied Chemistry. In 1957
he was awarded the Willard Gibbs
Medal, one of the highest awards which
can be made to an American chemist.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1959
BLACKETT (Great
if the world's greatest authorities
on cosmic rays and in particular on elec¬
tronic showers. He has recently carried
out research on new fundamental particles
of matter. President of the British
Association for the Advancement of
Science (1957-58), Professor Blackett
has been called the "father" of "opera¬
tional research" (the technique of pro¬
viding executives with the scientific basis
for practical decisions). A member of the
Royal Society, Professor Blackett received
the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1 948.
HOMI JEHANGIR BHABHA (India)
has gained great distinction through his
original research in theoretical nuclear
physics, and in particular on the quantum
theory and on cosmic radiations. Direc¬
tor of the Tata Institute of Fundamental
Research, Bombay, and Chairman of the
Atomic Energy Commission, Govern¬
ment of India, since 1954, Homi Bhabha
was president of the first international
conference on the peaceful uses of
atomic energy, which was organized at
Geneva by the United Nations in 1955.
if T1 nriïjii1
xx x jlnil
PORTALS OF
A NEW AGE
We are at the portals of a new
age. A new world is coming into
being before our very eyes yet men
seem unaware of it. This, then, is the
message which science has for man:
you are witnessing the birth of a
different kind of world, a world in
which there are new duties and res¬
ponsibilities. For we are not advancing
towards an era of assured peace and
tranquillity. Before us lie unknown
dangers, undreamed-of adventures and
countless inventions the embryos of
countless others.
Disquieting, but grandiose and full
of promise - that is the new world
towards which we march. True it will
bring with it a host of new problems as
does every phase of human existence:
adolescence, when the child becomes
the man, the ripe years of maturity
and finally, old age, when hearts and
minds are opened to wisdom. Science
has faced man with the challenge of
fresh problems. Can it help him to
resolve them? Can it aid him to make
the best use of the resources it has
created for his benefit? These are the
momentous questions to which we
must reply.
Gaston Berger
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE. CAN CLOSE
THE GAP BETWEEN
RICH & POOR NATIONS
P. M. S. BLACKETT
If we look at the future of science, it is quite useful
to distinguish what I may call the three faces or the
three aspects of science.
The first is science as a creative scientific research
worker sees it and feels it. It is an activity of intense
value and attractiveness in its own right, and, necessar¬
ily, only a few people at any one time in the world can
be right in the forefront of advancing fundamental
knowledge, just as very few people can be the first to
climb Mount Everest, the first to cross the Antarctic or
the first to go under the Arctic ice. But this is an acti¬
vity of the practising of pure science, whether experi¬
mental or theoretical, which taxes all the skill of mind
and skill of hand and is invaluable as an experience.
The second aspect is science as a body of knowledge.
This body of knowledge created up to date by centuries
of patient work by thousands of scientists of all coun¬
tries of the (world must rank as one of the greatest
achievements of the human mind and ability, comparable
to the greatest achievements in art and literature. Now
this body of scientific knowledge which has great beauty in
Itself can be appreciated by anyone of any nation who
takes the trouble to learn its language.
The third aspect with which we are mostly concerned
here, I think, is science as power over nature. Science is
the force which has changed the world ; the whole struc¬
ture of society has been changed and in a relatively short
time in fact, in the last 200 years or so. Now in this
process, the changing of the world by science, there are
various distinct steps which it is extremely important
to keep in mind.
Firstly, there is the fundamental discovery which is
often part of the structure of pure science. Then this
work has to be applied to some definite, practical objec¬
tive. The pure scientific discovery is very often made
by someone with no interest in applications at all very
often the best pure scientists have no interest but to
be useful it has to be applied. Then We get the era of
applied science leading on to development work, and,
finally, to exploitation in the practical making of the
goods of life ; either making much cheaper the old goods
of civilized life (clothes, houses, baths, foods and so on),
making them available to a very much larger number of
people than in the past, or by producing entirely new
things such as motor-cars, aeroplanes, television, which
had never existed before.
Europe's wealth increased tenfold
Now, that is the last stage in the process and we must
keep these stages distinct the fundamental science,
the applied work and the final exploitation because
it is In this distinction I think that important conse¬
quences lie.
I think that if one does accept this distinction, we
should make this point. What the governments of coun¬
tries spend this immense amount of money on, the 1 per
cent of the national income, is applied science for its
material benefits for mankind. That is the object of the
expenditure, and it is a vast activity nowadays. It is an
enormously profitable investment for any country, and
8
the high standards of life of the rich countries depend
on this investment in science, the cheap part being the
pure science ana the most expensive part being the actual
application to real human needs.
An astonishing achievement of this scientific revolution
has been to increase by a factor of ten in 150 years the
wealth of Western European countries. But, looking
round the world today, we see that these great material
benefits of science are very unevenly distributed over the
world as a whole. Although the ¡knowledge of science is
widespread, the material benefits are extremely unevenly
distributed, and I think it is this uneven distribution of
the applications of science which today provides man's
greatest challenge.
(Here, Professor Gaston Berger of France, describing
Professor Blackett as the "father" of "operational
research", asked him to describe how this technique could
make a scientific contribution to the world of tomorrow.)
I am glad that this question of "operational research"
has been raised as I am intensely interested by this tech¬
nique which was brought into being to assist the efficient
prosecution of the war, and which has been aptly defined
as the technique for providing executives with the numer¬
ical basis for practical decisions.
Rich & getting richer all the time
We all, as citizens of our various countries, are indi¬
rectly executives by controlling government actions
in the long run, and so it is very apt at this point to
know what is the numerical basis for the statements that,
for instance, I have been making, and other people have
been making, and what are the figures we ought to know
if we are going to do something about it.
I think that the essential figures (which one has to
appreciate to understand the magnitude of the problem
are quite simple. Something like one quarter of the
world's population of 2,500 million or so live in what can
be called rich countries. These people have an income
per head of about $1,000 a year. They comprise, of
course, most of Europe, the United States, Canada, Aus¬
tralasia and so on. Then on the other extreme, there
are between one half and three-quarters of the peoples
of the world who are definitely excessively poor and who
have an income per head of about a tenth as much as
the rich countries: $100 a year, compared with $1,000 a
year of the rich countries. Thus there are at least three
people with the law income for every one with the high
income.
This is the famous gap between the "have" and the
"have not" countries. Moreover, the rich countries are
getting richer at an average rate of about 2 per cent, per
year, averaging over booms and slumps. And it is this
rate of increase since 1800 or so which has led to the
very high standard of life in Western Europe.
Each year the Western countries, the
rich countries, get richer by 2 per cent.,
so in five years they get richer by 10 per
cent., 10 per cent of $1,000 is $800, so in
five years a rich country will add to its
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Februory 1959
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
THE GAP BETWEEN
RICH AND POOR ^'«;
r
wealth $100, which is as much as anybody in the poorer
countries has to live on. No wonder that the rich countries
are getting richer very much faster than the poor
countries are getting less poor.
Now, this widening gap is statistically true for a large
part of the peoples of the world. Why is it true? Why
isn't something done about it? This comes down to the
question of the cost of development work and manufac¬
ture. Many of the poor countries know how to make
things, but they cannot do so because they lack the skill
in enough of their people, or the capital to put into the
machines and the factories to make the goods. It is the
extreme expense of starting off an industrialization pro¬
cess which is holding up the application of known science
throughout the world.
It is very important to réalise that science, although it
has achieved these marvellous things, is not a magic
wand to wave over a poor country and make it into a
rich one. Science text-books are cheap ; it is reasonably
cheap to train scientists ; but it is extremely expensive
to embody the science in the factories, the steel works,
the transport systems, the power station, the mines and
the chemical plants. They all cost an enormous amount
of capital, and the poor countries are very hard put to
find capital. And that simple economic reason is why
science is so very unevenly applied over the world today.
I agree that the most important thing for mankind is
not to blow itself up. But I am curiously an optimist
about this matter. Some of my friends I call rational
pessimists, and I call myself an irrational optimist. But
I am an optimist. And assuming ' that we won't blow
ourselves up, what is the next main problem?
I think the next main problem is to do something about
the widening gap between the rich and the poor parts of
the world, the rich countries which have successfully used
science and obtained all the benefits, and the poor ones
which have not. Now, if we don't do something about this
widening gap, in a few decades, if the standard of life in
the West goes up at the present rate, we may end up with
a large part of the world poverty-stricken, as for cen¬
turies past, while the advanced countries of the West
are enjoying (if "enjoying" is the right term) what has
been called a "five-day week-end."
So great is the productive possibility of mankind that
that is not an impossibility. Let me say quite definitely
that all the evidence is that Western Europe has been the
source of science for accidental social reasons and not
because of any Innate superiority whatever, and there is
no reason why all the other nations of the World shall
not be as good scientists and engineers as ourselves.
Professor 'Blackett was asked if he thought that aid
for science in other countries should be given through-
the United Nations and its Specialized Agencies, or by
existing national programmes of technical assistance.
I think all methods have to be used. I think that as
much aid as possible should be fed through the United
Nations but, of course, there will be bilateral arrange¬
ments going on, and every sort of aid is needed. The
total amount of aid is about one to two per cent of the
national income of the West. That is only a fraction of
what we are spending on armaments. If that was canal¬
ized into the under-developed countries, not as a charity
but as a long period investment without political strings,
it would enormously help them to get over the extremely
difficult problem of the first years of industrialization.
B. A. HOUSSAY
PURE SCIENCE:
THE ROOT OF
HUMAN PROGRESS
It is a mistake to talk of pure
and applied science. There are
not two kinds of science but
only one, and there are the applications of that science.
The public in general and governments, too, think that
only applied science is useful. They are very much mis¬
taken. People should realize that all the knowledge on
which applied science is based comes from theoretical
or pure science. If theoretical or pure science is brought
to a halt or loses its impetus, then application, too, becomes
sluggish or stops. So we should make no distinction
between these two aspects of science.
Industry draws off the best academic scientists and
thus deprives research of their services. This is an
unfortunate situation which society must counteract by
enabling more scientists to devote themselves to research
and to the training of new research workers. Pasteur
said: it is not the long and involved political discussions
we may read about in the newspapers that help mankind
to progress, but only the great discoveries of science, of
human thought, and the uses to which they are put.
CONFLICT OVER
APPLIED VERSUS
PURE SCIENCE
We are witnessing a change in
the personality of the scien¬
tist. He is now an essential
element in society, for which he is becoming a source of
wealth though also a potential source of danger.
While scientific research has become one of the pri¬
mary concerns of governments, their support is, unhappily,
most often given to research applicable to the waging of
war. We are here to plead the cause of pure research,
disinterested research, research for peace.
Research, alas, has become an asset to be administered,
used for gain and closely controlled. Governments are
strong to the extent that their research yields results of
economic value. The modern world is assimilating
research in the same way as it is using oil and coal.
While recognizing the fact that science enjoys certain
material benefits, we cannot help being alarmed by some
aspects of the problem; that is why we scientists feel
ourselves to be responsible and are here to examine our
consciences.
We must see to it that university teaching is not
impoverished; that humanistic teaching is not im¬
poverished. We must see to it that, where science is
concerned, authority is not transferred from the
university to politics. We must do everything to avoid
the militarization of our endeavours and our culture.
The question of the degree of responsibility of the
scientist, and particularly the physicist, for all our
weapons, all our wars, has sometimes been raised. Let
me take up his defence a task which is easier for me as J
am not a physicist.
Science is innocent of the crimes of which it is accused.
The only guilty party is society a society insufficiently
permeated with the scientific spirit.
-10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Februory 1959
NO PLACE
FOR GERMS
Bottling of penicillin and
other anti-biotics demands
precision and stringently
sterile conditions. In this
French anti-biotics manu¬
facturing plant (left) elabo¬
rate precautions are taken
to ensure this. Air entering
the workplace is put through
a conditioning plant, then
filtered and sterilized and
is finally given a pressure
slightly higher than the out¬
side air to prevent any
non-sterilized air from infil¬
trating. Workers, wearing
masks and sterilized cloth¬
ing, must enter through
a special room in which
they go under the germ-
killing rays of ultra-violet
lamps. Machine shown here
fills and seals 2,000 bottles
an hour. Woman on right
feeds it with empty bottles
while the one on the left
collects bottles at the end
of the operation. Three
other women workers, not
seen here, keep the machine
supplied with aatírbjotics,
stoppers and capsules.
© Laboratoires Roger Bellon,
Neuilly-sur-Seine
TAKING NO
CHANCES
Slip-on protectors are worn
over shoes by U.S. atomic
plant workers as a precau¬
tionary measure against the
possibility of walking on
floors that may have been
contaminated by radiation.
Measures of this kind help
to explain why the U.S.
atomic industry's safety re¬
cord is three times as good
as the average safety record
for all industries in that
country. Wherever nuclear
energy is used for any pur¬
pose there ¡s a rigid enfor¬
cement of safety standards.
USIS
il
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
REDUCING ARMAMENTS BY 1°/°
MEANS $1,500,000,000 SAVED
FOR USEFUL CONSTRUCTIVE WORK
G. BERGER
Today we hear a great deal of talk about society, and
society of course merits this attention. Some
societies are prosperous, others are underdeveloped,
but in every case it is man and man alone who experiences
the suffering, grief, anxiety and despair, and whenever
we forget man, then civilization is in peril.
The sciences of man are complex and difficult more
difficult than all the rest. But they are no less necessary
for that. We are all agreed that war does nothing to
solve our problems, that It is the worst of all evils; yet
nations continue to prepare for war. To take a less
obvious but no less telling example, it is very obvious that
increased agricultural output calls for some mechanization
and proper ways of fertilizing the soil. But the peasant
has to be persuaded to give up his usual habits and to use
fertilizer in the right way and in the right place. In
other words, the problems besetting the world today are
first and foremost human problems.
If we are unhappy or anxious, it is not only because we
have not enough power or raw materials or machinery,
but because we do not know how to set about working
one with another instead of preparing to fight one
against another.
It takes more than conviction, enthusiasm and sincerity
to put over a point of view to other people, to convince
them and arouse their enthusiasm. A certain technique
is needed, too. Social and psychological techniques exist,
but I am afraid that these techniques have not yet been
given all the attention they deserve from those responsible
for the allocation of funds.
There is one kind of research for which everyone is
willing to give money applied research which produces
immediate results. "We want such and such a thing;
make it for us straight away !" and money flows freely.
But basic research rouses far less enthusiasm. To some
it is a kind of luxury. Yet I feel that one of the very real
benefits of this Round Table has been to prove that the
basic sciences are as useful as and perhaps even more
Indispensable than any other kinds of science, and that
they deserve the fullest official support.
The sciences of man, however seem useless and they are
systematically neglected. Yet these sciences offer the
surest means of solving the world's problems today and
the proof of their potency lies in the very fact that they
can do harm.
A science reveals its real power when people doubt that
it is capable of doing good and point out that it actually
does harm. We have heard about the dangers of
psychological warfare, and We, are all aware of the
dreadful insidious influence of propaganda. Propaganda
has a power to influence our deepest thoughts and
feelings, and instead of compelling us, by overt, external
force, to do things we do not wish to do, it makes us
condone and acquiesce in injustice, crime and the vilest
of acts I
If psychological techniques can thus corrupt men's
minds through propaganda which is the great danger
threatening us then it follows that psychological and
social techniques may also be an effective antidote to the
poison of propaganda.
People sometimes say though it seems to me
ridiculous that the machine age threatens mankind, and
that soon we shall resemble the robots depicted in certain
films of the past, spending our lives mechanically pressing
buttons. That is not the kind of future that awaits us.
We are not in danger of being enslaved by the machine
but by our fellow men. It is society, equipped with every
instrument of propaganda, which will instil into our
minds the subtle, imperceptible poison that Will make us
bring about our own downfall.
Science is a search for light and truth. We must see
12
things as they are and develop our sciences of man openly,
fully aware of our acts, knowing the dangers they may
hold, but at the same time conscious that, like other
branches of science, they offer great possibilities. We
should realize that the sciences of man must not be set
up in opposition to the other sciences that would be
ridiculous but must be used with them in an attempt
to bring men greater happiness, a little more wisdom and
perhaps the kind of life that we all dream ofa life
giving us a true feeling of the dignity of man.
Science and culture are not foes but friends, helping
and strengthening each other. It is a mistake to
suppose that we have to choose between technology
and culture, as. if culture were not based on precise
technical ¡knowledge and vice versa.
We have the technical facilities for spreading culture,
just as we also have the technical means of fertilizing
the soil, feeding mankind and, perhaps, of transforming
the world.
We have the money to do this, far more, in fact, than
we need. Each year, the expenditure on armaments of
the member countries of the United Nations adds up to
more than one hundred and fifty thousand million dollars.
If 1% of this vast sum Were set aside for science, educa¬
tion and culture, and for feeding mankind, we should
have at least $1,500,000,000 available each year for this
peaceful, constructive work.
I know the serious domestic difficulties that arise over
the transfer of a percentage of any country's military
budget to its education budget. But such difficulties are
removed when the same effort is made by all countries
and the relative expenditure on armaments remains the
same for all.
No doubt the day will come when countries will no
longer spend money on arms. But we cannot afford to
wait until governments learn wisdom and peoples develop
confidence in each other. Something can be done and
done now.
I think we might very well consider a line of action
which combines great symbolic significance with real
practical value. This idea, which has been put forward
by others before me, is that all the governments should
make a 1% cut in their military, budgets and use this
money for the development of education, science and
culture and for improving general standards of living.
Science is useful, and it has been clearly shown that
pure science is as useful as what is called applied
science. It is necessary for the laboratories to work
in close touch with industry, but it is equally necessary
for scientists to have\good working conditions, and one
more essential thing enough time for their Work.
One of the greatest difficulties We have to face in these
days when everything is moving so fast is that we no
longer have time. A scientist must have leisure. Discov¬
eries do not come to order. They come from the work
of suitable research teams provided with proper equip¬
ment. For I speak from experience when I say that what
tempts academic staff most in the offers made to them
by industry are not high salaries but the Working facilities
they are given. If we want to keep scientists in our labo¬
ratories, if we want men for basic research, We must equip
those laboratories. For scientists, that is more important
than material gain.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1959
É^
Jk y
M *^x
***£, ' ^?v
Yâvtm H îBTi
l^ywy-TT
am W -ímJfV*' ^S^-
mSîm
pfi Tj3fc**H*^ ¡55HSBBI
FLYING 'BRAIN':
6,500 DECISIONS
PER MINUTE
Science and technology are
today liberating man from
drab repetitive "thought".
Today, one man at the
controls of a giant cal¬
culator can have at his
command the computing
ability of 25,000 trained
mathematicians. At the
other end of the scale,
" miniature " calculators
are being developed to take
decisions for pilots flying
above the speed of sound.
Small " brain " (right), which
can produce 6,500 deci¬
sions per minute is now
used in U.S. jet plane (left).
USIS
Compagnie des Machines Bull
GAMMA CALCULATOR, the first of its type to be designed and built in France, can add and subtract figures of 12 digits
in 0.17 thousandths of a second and gives the answer to a multiplication of eleven digits by twelve digits in twenty-one
thousandths of a second. The machine not only prints the answers to the problems posed to it, but stores them in a " memory".
Business men already envision a day when electronic brains will be used not only for paper work problems, but to operate
factories, to run automobile production lines or any plant where the process can be reduced to a pre-set repetitive system.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
(1) Atomic energy has proved to be an amazing
tool for medical research, diagnosis and treatment.
In the U.S.A. alone more than 2,000 hospitals and
physicians use radiation for the benefit of more than
one million patients per year. Here, a U.S. surgeon
(on right) implants radio-active pellets of yttrium-90
in the pituitary gland of a cancer patienta method
used to destroy those cancers susceptible to hor¬
monal alteration. Assistant (left) watches an ampli¬
fied image of the patient's skull on a TV screen and
guides the operation, which is performed quickly
and only requires the use of a local anaesthetic.
(2) New equipment for treating brain tumours being
demonstrated at the Massachusetts Institute of
Technology. In an adjustable bed the patient can be
raised to the desired position directly under the
ceiling vent ready for release of the beam from the
Institute's new reactor. (3) People who are hard of
hearing can thank this strange looking headgear and
the scientists who invented it for constant impro¬
vements being made in hearing aids. It enables
scientists to make a rapid check on the efficiency
of different types of earphones. (4) Doctor at the
Moncorvo Filho Hospital, Rio de Janeiro, uses a
scintillation probe to measure. the amount of radio¬
active iodine which has been secreted in a young
boy's thyroid gland, following an injection of this
radio-active isotope. Using the probe, the doctor
can determine how well the gland is functioning.
I, 2, 3) USIS. - 4) UNITED NAT.jONS.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1959
THE MEDICAL
REVOLUTION
IN THE FIELD
OF NUTRITION B. HOUSSAY
Medicine was really born with the first man. Since
then it has passed through widely divergent stages.
From being the prerogative of priests and magi¬
cians it became empirical and finally scientific. In the
early stages, priests or wise men tried, by exorcism, to
drive out evil spirits or to invoke the beneficent inter¬
vention of the gods. Later, as men found that obser¬
vation yielded better practical results, empirical medicine
came into being. A body of scientific data was slowly
amassed down the years and in the 19th century, following
the great advances made in the natural sciences biology,
chemistry and physics medicine adopted the scientific
method and, above all, the method of experiment.
It was the experimental method which brought about
such far-reaching changes in medical science. The dis¬
covery, for instance, that some diseases were caused by
microbes made it possible to take precautions against and
to combat several kinds of infections, and also to ward off
or to arrest the course of the great pestilential epidemics
which used to take such a heavy toll of human life.
In our own time another great revolution has taken
place in the field of nutrition. Although it is perhaps
not yet understood by the general public, this is perhaps
the most important. We now know man's needs for
proper nourishment through the discovery of vitamins
and our understanding of the role of proteins and min¬
erals in human diet. This has been responsible for a
tremendous improvement in human health.
Even a few facts show this trend. Infant mortality
was once extremely high; one child in three died before
its third birthday; nowadays, in countries with high
living standards infant mortality has dropped to one out
of 15 or even 20. In many countries at the beginning of
this century, average life expectation was 40 years; today
it is now anything up to 70.
Longer life and a lower death rate have had many
other effects. The increased number of old people
has made it necessary to give attention to geronto¬
logy which concerns the medical care and health problems
of the aged. Infectious diseases have undoubtedly been
fought and conquered, but as the average expectation of
life increased, man was found to be suffering from diffe¬
rent ailments. The arteries, the joints and the heart were
affected by age, and this made new research necessary.
Other diseases have abruptly increased, among them
cancer. This can be treated to some extent, although the
real goal should be to attack the disease in all its forms.
The discovery of hormones, which play such a great
part in therapeutic medicine, deserves mention as does the
discovery of insulin. What used to be pernicious anaemia
no longer merits the use of the adjective pernicious;
people who would once have died of it can now be cured.
In recent years, much important research has been done
on nucleic acids. You' can prepare nucleic acid and store
it in a jar; then one day a few drops of this preparation
given to a plant will cause the pl'ant to catch a disease
which can be transmitted to others; this crystal therefore
propagates a disease, as with a living being. Even more
strange is the fact that it has been possible to modify the
chemical molecule of these nucleic acids and thus produce
mutations. Thus, diseases can also be changed in form.
One of the great biochemists working in the U.S.A. has
found a way of synthesizing enzymes, which in turn can
synthesize nucleic acids. The way is thus open to the
production of many things viruses, genes and so on. A
whole new world is opening up before us.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Patient suffering from a deep-seated malignant tumor
is prepared for treatment at the Institute of Scientific
Research for Radiology in Moscow. Specially designed
for tumor treatment, the X-ray machine (below) directs
its rays with a high precision on the tumor thus sparing
healthy tissues surrounding it. The patient is subjected
to the rays from two X-ray tubes which rotate conti¬
nuously around him, working automatically to a pre-set
pattern. Photo, right, shows a patient at the Royal
Marsden Hospital, England, receiving treatment for
cancer from radio-active caesium which is placed in a
rotating treatment head (centre, above patient). In
background is a small television camera which enables
the radiographer to watch the patient from her control
room (photo, bottom right) without coming into contact
with the gamma rays emitted by the caesium. The pa¬
tient can speak to the operator through an amplifier.
I - Official Soviet Photo 2 - 3 - Photos Royal Marsden Hospital, England
^BT
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1959
Official Soviet photo
Ultrasonicsthe study and use of high-frequency, inaudible sound waveshas found countless applications in research, medi¬
cine and industryfrom industrial drilling and the removal of barnacles from ships' hulls to the aging of whisky. Here two glass
objectsa jar and a valvehave been pierced by ultrasonic vibrations. Razor blade and pocket knife simply mark the holes.
W. NOYES
HAVE WE THE
RIGHT TO USE
UP OUR SOIL
RECKLESSLY?
Raw materials are not distributed evenly over the
surface of the globe and some of them are being
used up very rapidly. In the United States of
America, iron ore or at least the best quality iron ore is
beginning to run out. Some important elements, such as
copper, for instance, are no longer to be found, and now
have to be imported. Similarly, there is not an inex¬
haustible supply of coal and fuel oil.
It is, of course, the industrialized countries which are
such heavy consumers of all these raw materials. These
countries have therefore had to look for raw materials
wherever they happen to be available, and this raises not
only a practical but also a moral question.
Have Americans or Europeans, the right to use raw
materials coming from a country which may not be
industrialized just now but which will perhaps be indus¬
trialized in 50 years' time and will then need these raw
materials for its own development?
I do not pretend to be able to solve this problem, but
am merely putting it to you as an issue that will be
important in the future.
Let us look at the matter from a slightly different angle.
We export foodstuffs from the United States; the same
is true of South America and many other countries. Have
we the right to use our soil recklessly and let it wash away
into the Mississippi, for instance? Have we the right to
let it become exhausted, with the prospect of not being
able to use it for growing food in another fifty years?
By doing so, may we not run the risk of leaving the people
of other countries to starve to death?
I do not mean that you should make war on us because
we are misusing our soil, but I would emphasize that this
is a matter on which you should reflect. Have Americans
the right to do exactly what they like with their country?
I am quite aware that this view is not very popular in
the United States but I for my part Would like to stress
these facts because of their moral aspect and, above all,
because they bring us face to face with one of the causes
of wars.
Everyone ought to think seriously not only about the
way existing raw materials are used, but also about the
means of preserving them for future generations.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
TECHNOLOGY'S HAND IN
OUR CHANGING LANDSCAPE
The Unesco Courier. February 1959
A technical revolution is now creating countless new forms and uses for old
familiar materials. New ways of producing and fabricating such common metals
as iron and aluminium give them far greater strength. The man-in-the-street
finds himself confronted with unfamilar shapes now taken more and more often
by industrial equipment and buildings. Above, geodesic dome fabricated entirely
of steel at Baton Rouge in the U.S.A., will be a railroad tank car repair and
maintenance depot. Panels of sheet steel, one-eighth of an inch thick were used.
Right, another geodesic dome, this time of aluminum panels, also in the U.S.A.
Left, huge echo-proof chamber being used to sound-test a transformer. By meas¬
uring the amount of noise made by different appliances, engineers can deter¬
mine their working efficiencythe less noise, the greater efficiency. Walls
are nearly five feet thickmade up of concrete, galvanized sheet, and fibreglass.
USIS
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
TEN THOUSAND MILLION ELECTRON-VOLTS FROM DUBNA'S GIANT ACCELERATOR
Atoms for peace have already found a thousand and one uses. The basis for future developments, however will continue to be laid
in research and experimental laboratories where scientists delve with mighty machines into the still mysterious world within
the atom. The most impressive of these machines are giant particle accelerators, like the huge ring type accelerator in the High
Energies Laboratory of the Joint Institute for Nuclear Research at Dubna, near Moscow, shown on these pages. Known as a
synchrophasotron, this machine can accelerate protons to reach an energy of I 0,000 million electron-volts. Its electro-magnet
(seen In photo, above) has a diameter of over I 80 feet and weighs 36,000 tons. Below, the main control room of the synchro¬
phasotron. Another accelerator at Dubna, a synchrocyclotron, can create energies of up to 680 million electron-volts.
Official Soviet photos
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Februory 1959
PEACE OR WAR:
WHICH ROAD WILL HUMANITY TAKE?
What is the situation facing us today?
Science has the means to bring happi¬
ness and contentment to the world and
N. SEMENOY collective efforts can lay the foundation of a
truly great future. But should a new war
break out (it would inevitably be an atomic one) then
mankind would experience the most dreadful fate it has
ever known.
Which road will humanity take? The decision rests
with us, on our goodwill, our efforts and our determi¬
nation. What we can and must do is to put an end, once
and for all, to the testing of nuclear weapons. Though
this is perhaps not the main problem it is of primary
importance, for the first effect of prohibiting nuclear tests
would be to prevent any further improvement of devas¬
tating nuclear weapons. It would put a stop to radiation
contamination and would help to re-establish interna¬
tional confidence.
This would do much to dispel the present worldwide
fears and depression caused by the "cold war".
Finally, and most important of all, it Would hasten
the next and most decisive action a banning of the pro¬
duction and use of nuclear weapons, the destruction of
all existing stocks of such weapons, general disarmament,
and the renunciation of war as a means of settling inter¬
national disputes.
War is a relic from the past, a terrible and barbarous
survival which should have no place in a civilized world.
The menace of war has a disastrous psychological effect
on people and entails the squandering of a vast amount
of labour and resources; an enormous number of men do
nothing but learn how to kill one another. The overall
effect is to prevent nations from concentrating their
efforts and using their resources to improve living
standards, to enrich their cultural life and to assist econo¬
mically under-developed countries; it prevents them from
feeding and clothing their people properly and hinders
normal technological development.
The most important task today is to end this nightmare.
A unanimous and active world opinion could have a deci¬
sive effect in settling these questions, leaving aside other
relatively secondary problems not directly related to them.
In this collective effort to safeguard international peace,
to ban the testing of nuclear weapons and these weapons
themselves and to abolish war, the scientists, in all coun¬
tries, who are sincerely concerned for man's future and
for the progress and integrity of science, must unite and
take a leading part.
I am convinced that the vast majority of true scientists
do not work simply for the money they earn. Thus they
cannot stand idly by while science is destroyed and the
prospects which are opening up for it are brought to
nothing. It is a great blow for us to see the results of
our scientific work used to the detriment of mankind,
and in the present case we cannot tolerate it. We scien¬
tists must not stifle our humanitarian feelings but on the
contrary, give them full freedom, as should every honest
person. We should be keenly aware of our responsibilities,
and then act accordingly, uniting our efforts to solve
these problems. All of us living in the 20th century,
whether scientists or not, have a great obligation, not only
to ourselves but to future generations. If we succeed in
dispelling the heavy threat of war and concentrating our
efforts on opening up a new and enlightened era, mankind
can look forward to a truly happy existence even during
our own century.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Photos © United Kingdom Atomic Energy Authority
MORE HEAT THAN IN
THE HEART OF THE SUN
Among the most exciting of all atomic energy
projects is the possibility of creating energy by
the fusion (or joining) of light atoms such as those
of hydrogen. (Most nuclear reactors are based
on the fissionor splittingof heavy atoms like
those of uranium.) The fusion process has been
studied for some years past at Harwell, Great
Britain, with the aid of an apparatus called ZETA
(Zero Energy Thermonuclear Assembly). Photo
right, shows model of ZETA at the Science Museum,
London. In this apparatus, pulsed electrical cur¬
rents are passed through heavy hydrogen gas
held in a "doughnut" shaped tube. Magnetic forces
generated by the high current and those of exter¬
nal coils have held the hot gas discharge clear
of the metal tube walls long enough to enable
nuclear reactions to take place. (In diagram,
above, white strip represents hot gas pinched
by current.) So far it has been possible to main¬
tain hot gas at temperatures of up to five million
degrees Centigrade for about three-thousandths
of a second. With extra equipment it is hoped
to produce temperatures of up to 25 million
degreesfar greater than the central temperature
of the sun (15 million degrees Centigrade). But
temperatures exceeding 50 million degrees must
be achieved before a thermonuclear power sta¬
tion can be seriously considered. Another record
breaker, this time in supersonic flight, is the
Faire Delta II (opposite page), a prototype Brit¬
ish jet aircraft which has been used for research
into the multifold problems of high-speed flight.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1959
As H-Bombs WAR IS NOW
mean mass
»* OBSOLETTE
BHABHA W
tab. is the greatest waster of
raw material that we have.
In many industrialized
countries l/3rd of the entire national expenditure goes
into producing instruments of war, which we hope will
never be used. We all know that atomic and hydrogen
weapons are very destructive, but I doubt if the ordinary
citizen fully realizes how destructive they are.
One has only to remember the bomb-damage, the des¬
truction in France, the devastation of Germany and the
Soviet Union most of this destruction was caused by con¬
ventional explosives. And the total amount of explosives
used by both sides together in the last war amounted to
between two and three million tons of TNT.
Now, one hydrogen bomb can have several times this
explosive power. It is of importance to realize in con¬
crete terms what this explosive force means. The area
of total destruction for a multi-megaton weapon, say a
15 megaton bomb is 5 miles or about 8 kms. An expert
has said that buildings in this area would be fraction-
alized, pulverized and vaporized. Irreparable damage
would be caused to houses within a radius of some 12 kms.
In addition, there is the radiation effect and the fall¬
out. Depending on the direction and the velocity of the
wind, 50% of the population would receive a lethal dose
in a strip 40 kms. wide and about 300 kms. long. Draw
this on a map of France and you will see how large it is.
I fervently hope that such a weapon will never be used.
It is the responsibility of every one of you to see that it
is never used. This matter is one where the ordinary
citizen has to express himself. It is now clear that with
these weapons a total war is not feasible any more. It
would amount to mass suicide or mass murder.
But there is a more insidious danger which I would
like to point out and that danger is the so-called small
tactical atomic weapon. Today such a weapon is of a
size comparable with the Hiroshima bomb. It may be a
quarter the size, but it is several hundred times bigger
than the largest block-buster of the last war. Such a
weapon must be a fission weapon and cannot be clean.
By its very nature a considerable area of the ground
would be contaminated with the radio-active fall-out.
To talk of such weapons as "small, tactical weapons" is
to deceive the public. And it is this which has such
serious consequences.
Now, it is a matter of some disagreement among experts
and specialists of atomic weapons and military experts
whether small, tactical weapons could be used in a
limited war without leading to the use of larger weapons.
As long as there is this doubt, the use must be a gamble
a gamble with the future of civilization and the future
of humanity itself. Would any responsible person agree
to permit such a gamble? It seems clear to me that
the progress of science and technology has made major
wars impossible and, indeed, wars in effect impossible
and we are only slow in adjusting our minds to the
changed situation. But it is essentially the duty of every
citizen to think about this matter and to express himself
forcibly. This matter is too important to be left to the
politicians and the military experts.
Charles E. Brown, Worcester Park, England
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The construction of nuclear reactors and atomic power
stations has made new demands on industry and on
the materials it uses. Above, steel workers in special
protective clothing are subjected to intense heat as
a carbon steel disk, I 5 feet in diameter, is formed into
the head of a vessel in which a pressurized water reactor
will be installed. This reactor will provide heat for the
production of 275,000 kilowatts of electricity at an
atomic power plant near New York. Photos, opposite
page, show two aspects of the main French"1 Atomic
Energy Centre at Marcoule. Left, fuel for an atomic
reactor uranium rods suspended in readiness for
lowering into the reactor. Right, special metal cons¬
truction is embodied in the pre-stressed cgncrete
of the reactor shield. The concrete cylinder in which
the fuel of the moderator will be contained is circled
by steel cables exerting a pressure superior to
that of the gas which is generated in the cylinder.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1959
Photos Jean Pierre Sudre, French Commissariat of Atomic Energy
THE CAUSES OF WAR: FEAR, PRIDE, POVERTY
FTjNDAMENTALY I think there
are three main causes of
war. Firstly I think that
war is brought about by pride, the
pride either of those who feel they
are minor powers and want to
increase their importance, or of
those who already consider them¬
selves powerful, but who wish to
extend their power.
The second cause of war is fear.
Fear is always a bad counsellor.
G. BERGER Fear sets little dogs barking and
snapping and makes them the most
dangerous. Fear has been the cause of many a war. One
of the best antidotes to fear is knowledge which brings
understanding and a clear view of things.
The third cause is want. I think it takes third place
because poverty sometimes weighs down so heavily on men
that they lose all hope and with it the spirit of revolt.
Here science can help us. With its aid and that of the
techniques it has made possible We can vanquish want.
Science can also help to cast out fear; this task is
largely one of providing proper information and using
common sense.
Pride is perhaps a more difficult nut to crack. The urge
for power is implanted in the hearts of individuals and
of nations alike and it can take a thousand devious,
insidious forms. Here perhaps something more than
science is needed. We must turn to ethics and to the
techniques of the sciences of man. These sciences I take
to include the techniques of social psychology and the
study of man in a form which, though less mathematical,
is no less exacting and precise. The sciences of man can
show up the futility of pride and deflate the ego. We
can never do too much in this direction.
Problems must be taken seriously, but we must never
take ourselves too seriously. Here again there is a great
deal of education to be done on these lines; nations and
individuals alike have to be educated, and science, in the
broadest meaning of the term, can help to banish the risk
of war.
When want has become a thing of the past, when fear
no longer grips men's hearts and when pride has been
shown up as something ridiculous, then science will have
done its work and true peace will be established among
men.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
THE ASTOUNDING CASE OF THE 'SNOW WHITE' DUCKS
Can science artificially modify or influence certain hereditary
characteristics of creatures on the higher levels of animal life ?
Until a few years ago the answer given by biologists was a firm
No! Experiments had however shown that it was possible to
obtain mutations among bacteria by the use of desoxyribonucleic
acid... more simply known by the initials DNA. Then, just under
two years ago, Professor J. Benoit, of the College de France in
Paris, carried out similar experiments on ducks helped by the
Reverend Father Leroy, and by Dr. Roger Vendrely and his wife
Colette, directors of the biological section of the Strasburg Ins¬
titute of Macro-molecules. DNA obtained from ducks of the
Khaki breed was injected Into male and female ducklings of the
Peking breed for several months. By the end of the treatment
important changes had taken place in the physical characteristics
of the ducks. They were neither Khaki nor Peking, but seemed
to belong to a new breed having a smooth white plumage and in
some cases a rose-coloured beak. Professor Benoit named them
"snow whites". Since then the "snow whites" have had many off
spring and these have shownthesamecharacteristicsastheirparents.
Despite these results, Professor Benoit maintains that it Is still
too soon to draw definite conclusions from them and that further
experiments are necessary. Photos on this page show : (I) Adult
female duck of Peking breed (7 % lbs) ; heavy body, large head,
upright stance, low belly. (2) Male duck of the Khaki breed (4 lbs)
which provided the desoxyribonucleic acid with which the Peking
breed ducklings were injected. (3) Peking breed duck (5 l/2 lbs)
which was injected with DNA from the Khaki breed duck when
eight days old. The head and body are more slender and the stance
is more inclined. The beak is partially coloured black. The plu¬
mage is no longer the typical yellow of the Peking breed, but has
become discoloured following the injections. This characteristic
(absence of yellow pigmentation) was noted among a number
of subjects of the succeeding generations. (4) Female duck, the
offspring of parents injected with DNA from a khaki duck. This
bird, weighing nearly four pounds, was not itself Injected. The
yellow colouring has now completely disappeared from its beak.
Photos © Michel Berthoumieux
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Februory 1939
CAN SCIENCE CHANGE
A PERSON'S HEREDITY?
GREY & AGING MICE
Many generations of mice have travelled around the sides of this
rotating exercise wheel (below) used to determine the effect of
exercise on normal aging and on recovery from injury caused by
exposure to atomic radiation. The two groups of mice (photo,
above) were used in the studies and demonstrate the aging effects
of radiation. The mice are all the same age, but the group at the
right which turned grey and aged prematurely from exposure to
radiation, present a marked contrast to. the unexposed group on
the left. Studies of this type yield vital data on genetics.
USIS
w
W . NOYES
'E have long been familiar
with the basic laws of gene¬
tics. We know that if
parents, display certain tendencies,
their children will in all likelihood
inherit these. We know from our
experiments with animals that by
selecting the parents we can pro¬
duce among progeny animals with
particular characteristics. I am not
necessarily suggesting that we
should apply this knowledge to the
human race, and select those people
who should have children and weed
out those who should not. That
would be rather dangerous, although
experiments on those lines have occasionally been made
on a limited scale.
There are other things of which we know less. There
are certain molecules in the body .which could at least
give an indication of the future of the race, or indeed
determine it. We have molecules that are known to
chemists as steroids. There are about thirty of them in
the human body. In a more or less normal person, the
quantities of these molecules remain in a fixed ratio, but
this ratio varies in any person who has a tendency to
illness. Can science do anything to keep this ratio
constant once and for all?
Heredity is more or less determined by nucleic acids.
If a family shows an undesirable tendency, may it not be
possible to alter the character of these acids and the
relationships between the different groups?
Nucleic acids are necessary to
maintain cell life, for the
formation of proteins, for
growth and for heredity. It is well
¡known that if a cell has its nucleus
removed, the protoplasm dies and
the cell can no longer survive. We
also know that the growth of
abnormal cells, such as cancer cells,
depends on nucleic acids. Several
types of medicine used in cases of
cancer are effective because they
act on the nucleic acids. But it is
difficult to make sure that they act
only on the nucleic acids of can¬
cerous cells and not on normal cells
as well. That is why these types of medicine must be
used in moderation, for fear of killing the patient.
Nucleic acids are also to be found in viruses. The
active substance of viruses has been crystallized and
found to be a super-protein. Division of this substance
yielded pure nucleic acids which can be crystallized at
will. They retain their properties. They are pure
products and can be kept in a jar. If they are. used for
innoculation, they will reproduce, like a living organism.
Following certain experiments, the distinction between a
chemical substance and a living organism has gone.
Mutations have been obtained by changing some parts
of these nucleic acids. Moreover, we know that
chromosomes, which are formed from nucleo-protein, are
of basic importance in heredity. We know the particular
points in these chromosomes which determine a given
characteristic. It has also been possible to interfere with
these nucleic acids so as to produce mutations. One of
the ill effects of radio-activity is precisely that it modifies
these nucleic acids. When this happens, the person
affected may have quite abnormal offspring, which is one
of the terrible dangers of radio-activity.
These nucleic acids are now beginning to be synthesized.
If research along these lines continues successfully, we
shall be able to produce substances either to promote or
to arrest growth. It will be possible to influence heredity.
27
B. HOUSSAY
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
EXPLORING THE FRONTIERS BETWEEN
INANIMATE AND ANIMATE MATTER
N. SEMENOV
Most people have not yet fully
realized what extraordinary
possibilities have been opened
up by science since the middle of
the 20th century, or the tremendous
power which it will achieve during
the next twenty to forty years.
Never before in history has such
a situation existed: mankind now
possesses a volume of power so
great that if it is used rapidly and
wisely it will be possible to satisfy
the needs of everyone. The speed
of scientific development outpaces
the rate of population increase, so
that as the major technical and
industrial problems are solved, the number of hours each
individual needs to work for the benefit of the community
will steadily decrease,
Just as machines have already liberated men from hard
physical labour, so electronic computers and, in general,
the devices of automation and telemechanics which are
making prodigious progress, will liberate man from such
mental work as is of an essentially, automatic and not
creative nature.
Computers of the near future will probably also be able
to provide systematized and partially analysed data.
Man's creative possibilities will thus be enriched to an
exceptional degree; his brain will no longer be burdened
with memorizing and pre-analysing a vast collection of
facts. Scientists, engineers and economists will thus be
able to concentrate their intellects to a much greater
extent on purely creative activities. Scientists will no
longer be confined to narrow specialization.
Chemistry, in particular, will be faced with some major
tasks. If existing chemical processes were more fully
applied to agriculture in food-poor countries, this problem
would soon be solved, not only for existing populations but
also for future ones several times greater.
The chemistry of the future will undoubtedly find new
and more effective ways of producing food. It will dis¬
cover the mechanism of the chemical reactions which
take place In an organism under the influence of fermen¬
tation, and will show how these principles can be applied
industrially; industry will then perhaps succeed in
achieving a biosynthesis of food products outside the
living organism, using as raw materials albumins and
carbohydrates of algae as well as the green matter of
plants, and perhaps also ügnine. Chlorella, for instance,
is an alga which is now attracting great attention in this
connexion.
Continuing research in this way, chemistry will perhaps
evolve new types of machines functioning according
to the principle of muscular contraction and, with a
high coefficient of useful work, directly converting
chemical energy into mechanical action. Most remarkable
of all is that chemistry, by studying the mechanism of
chemical reactions, has started creating new kinds of
materials which by now are familiar to most people
synthetic fibres, plastics and rubber, obtained through the
chemical treatment of petroleum and coal-tar. These are
already found in everyday use on a large scale, in building
and in the construction of precision machines.
Thanks to chemistry, the quality of these materials
will be progressively improved and their production costs
lowered so that they will become the basic materials of
the future, suitable for general as well as technical needs.
Let us remember that materials are the most stable
factors in, and mainstays of, technical progress. It is not
surprising that the various eras in the history are named
after the materials then used: Stone Age, Bronze Age,
.28
Iron Age. Some thirty to forty years ago, the develop¬
ment of chemistry opened up a new era that of synthetic
polymeric materials. Thanks to chemistry, -it will be
possible to give these materials any qualities desired, so
that they will have a wide range of uses, from clothing
manufacture to machine construction, in which they will
replace metals.
During the last few decades, chemistry has also scored
remarkable successes in the field of medicine, including
the discovery of cures for once-fatal diseases. A future
task of chemistry, in co-operation with biology, is to
ascertain the precise chemical mechanism of the action
of any particular substance on an organism. This will
give a new and powerful impetus to therapeutical che¬
mistry; one of the first results, in my opinion, will be the
solution of the problem of cancer.
Probably science's most important task is in the field
of chemistry: the interpretation, on a chemical basis, of
the transition from inanimate to animate matter, as well
as the explanation of the nature of heredity. I am
convinced that inanimate matter when it changes into
animate matter, acquires new physico-chemical qualities,
the discovery and explanation of which constitute chem¬
istry's most important undertaking.
The present development of biochemistry and biology
will lead, in the near future, to striking results and will
probably result in a scientific and technical revolution no
less important than that which. came with the discovery
of atomic energy. Everything possible must be done to
ensure that these discoveries are used for the good of
mankind, and not as in the case of atomic energy, for
harmful purposes.
Without entering the field of
science fiction, I should like
to mention some of the
spheres in which research seems to
me likely to yield promising results.
Reference has been made to the
problems affecting changes in our
genetic heritage, nowadays the
distinction between inanimate and
animate matter does not strike us
as such an unfathomable problem.
Although we are not yet at the
stage of creating life in fact we
are very far from doing so we are
beginning to visualise the hypo¬
theses which should reveal to us
just how life first appeared on earth.
Then there are all the problems of nutrition and of the
transformation of inorganic matter into assimilable
organic matter, which are bound up with the problems
of photo-synthesis.
Today we can point without hesitation to a number of
problems that have been solved by chemical therapy.
It has found a cure for once-deadly diseases which
are now practically non-existant or which are rapidly
becoming so. Two such examples are cerebro-spinal
meningitis, once the dread of all children's doctors, and
pneumonia, no longer the danger it once was for old
people. Already a century ago vaccination was used to
prevent smallpox and serotherapy afforded protection
against diphtheria.
The chemical agents now used in medicine, belonging
to very different chemical groups, but often having a
natural origin, include the very large group of antibiotics.
The healing action of these antibiotics is accompanied by
the creation of new problems to which many of us have
had to turn our attention. These problems are caused by
the sudden upsetting of the balance maintained by
microbes in the human body, and by the ensuing
phenomena of vitamin deficiency, particularly after oral
administration of antibiotics. But all these problems
are now under study. It is our business to solve them,
D. BOVET
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1959
'PUSH BUTTON' TOMATOES. Healthy
tomato plants flourish under artificial light,
are warmed by artificially-controlled tem¬
peratures and cooled by artificial rain at the
plant research laboratory of the California
Institute of Technology. They are rotated
on a revolving platform under bands of
varicoloured light in what is called the
"rainbow" room. A giant electronic panel
enables scientists to regulate temperatures
by simply pushing buttons. The plants have
been found to yield more than those grown
outdoors or In ordinary greenhouses.
USIS
BOY OR GIRL? For many years poultry
farmers have needed an accurate method
of sexing their day-old chicks. A new
instrument, the "Sexascope" claims to give
100% accuracy. The principle of the ins¬
trument consists of a specially designed tube
which is passed into the chick's vent. A
light shone through the tube illuminates the
rudimentary ovaries or testicles of the chick.
CO.I., London
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
NO EARTH, NO SUN. From these single
blossoms dropped into test tubes of nutrient
solution (above, left), scientists at the plant
research laboratory of the California Institute
of Technology hope to grow complete straw¬
berries and peas. The plants grow without
direct contact with soil, sun or rain and
produce more than their country cousins.
USIS
COBALT THE BOOSTER. At the Insti¬
tute of Biophysics of the U.S.S.R. Academy of
Sciences seeds are exposed to the radio-active
rays of radio-cobalt (above, right). The effect
is to accelerate the growth of the seeds; the
aim is to produce more and bigger harvests.
Official Soviet photo
POULTRY PROTECTION. A vaccine
expert sent to Thailand by the U.N. Food and
Agriculture Organization carries out a post¬
mortem examination of a chicken (right) to
determine whether the bird died of chicken
Newcastle disease. Some 50,000 fowls were
vaccinated and later showed solid immunity
to local strains of this chicken disease virus.
FAO photo
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1959
ENOUGH FOOD FOR EVERYONE:
A PROBLEM OF KILOWATT-HOURS
H.J. BHABHA
We are all used to hearing of
the so-called industrially
advanced and the under¬
developed countries. What is
implied by this nomenclature? If
you look at the countries of the
world today you find that there are certain countries,
and indeed most of the countries of Asia and Africa,
whose national income per head is about $40 to $50 per
annum. In the countries of Western Europe the national
income per head ranges from $300 to some $900 per
annum, while in the United States of America the nation¬
al income per head is a high as ? 1,800 per annum.
This national income per head is a measure of the well-
being of the people of the countries concerned. This, as
can be seen from the figures I have given, shows an
enormous disparity between the low standard of living
of the countries generally speaking, of Asia and Africa
that we call "under-developed", and the countries of the
West, for example, that are called industrially advanced.
On what is this disparity based? The. high standard of
.living of the industrially-advanced countries is due to a
better exploitation of the forces and resources of nature
based upon present science and technology. The energy
consumption per head in the so-called under-developed
countries is the equivalent to the burning of about one-
third of a ton of coal per head per annum, whereas in
the countries of Western Europe it is eight times as much,
and in America it is as much as eight tons per annum
per head. This utilization of energy is the basis of the
higher standard of living and the higher well-being of
these countries.
Now we all owe a great debt and also our cultural values
to the ancient civilizations of Egypt, India, China, Greece
and later Western Europe. It is important to realize,
however, that despite many differences, of habits, culture
and social pattern, all these civilizations were built
essentially on the same foundation. All the energy for
doing mechanical work, for tilling the ground, for drawing
water, for carrying loads and for locomotion was supplied
by muscle, whether human muscle or animal muscle.
Molecular or chemical energy, as, for example, obtained
by the burning of wood, was only used to a limited extent
for cooking and heating and a few technical processes, as
in metallurgy.
It is important to note the severe limitation that the
restricted supply of energy puts on the development of
civilization. A man in the course of a hard day's work
can only produce about half a kilowatt hour of energy,
whereas in the industrially advanced countries as much
as forty-five kilowatt hours of energy are used per day
per head. It follows that a high level of physical comfort
and culture could only be enjoyed by a few in the ancient
civilizations by concentrating the surplus labour of many
for the benefit of a few. In other words, the ancient
civilizations of the world were essentially non-democratic.
It is only today on the basis of modern science and tech¬
nology that for the first time we have the possibility of
building a democratic civilization and culture.
I recall that on one occasion Lord Boyd Orr said that
one man can produce today as much food as ten did
fifty years ago as the result of the application of modern
science and techniques in agriculture. Now, nobody knows
this problem better than he does. In India and in many
countries of Asia the productivity of agriculture per man
remains the same as it has been for centuries. This shows
that a mere application of present knowledge and tech¬
niques in these countries could easily solve the food
problem in these areas.
It should be emphasized that the food problem of which
you hear so much is a marginal one. In years in which
the rainfall is good there is no food shortage. In years
when the climatic conditions are adverse there is a food
shortage. Hence, the manifold increase of the productivity
of the soil on the basis of modern techniques could easily
ensure that even in bad years there is no food shortage.
NoWj one important reason for the greater productivity
of agriculture is the widespread use of fertilizer such as
sulphate or nitrate of ammonia. In India on the average
about five kilogrammes of sulphate of ammonia are used
per hectare. In England this figure is 200, in Japan 550;
in other words, a hundred times as much as in India. It
is this lavish use for fertilizer, made possible and produced
by modern industrial processes, which is responsible for
the greater productivity of the soil. Here we see directly
the impact of the chemical industry namely, the produc¬
tion of fertilizer on the productivity of agriculture.
Now the rate at which the production of food can be
increased is far greater than the rate at which the
population increases, which is 1.3 % per annum in
India. I emphasize this point because many people are
under the misapprehension that the over-population and
the increase of population in the under-developed areas
are the causes of their low standard of living. This is
clearly not so. Even With an increasing population,
modern technology enables one to raise the standards of
living of the people as a whole, because the increase in
production, the rate of increase in production, is much
greater, or can be much greater, than the rate of increase
of population.
For example, the population of the United States
increases at a rate higher than the rate of increase in
India, but nevertheless the standard of living continues
to go up because their productivity rises faster. I need
not mention the rapid rise of the rate of productivity in
the Soviet Union which is phenomenal. It has set a new
standard.
The over-populated countries are not India and China
in the sense of the density of population the density
of population is higher in such countries as England and,
for example, Belgium. So it is important for all of us to
realize that there is a certain responsibility on us to see
that modern techniques are applied everywhere for the
benefit of these areas. It is not the population problem
which is the cause of their low standard of living.
(Here, Professor Gaston Berger asked Professor Bhabha
if he thought that difficulties over the increase of
agricultural production were only technical ones the
need for proper machinery and a chemical industry or
if there were not also difficulties due to psychological and
social conditions.)
There are of course, two sorts of difficulties. It is easy
enough to erect a steel plant because this requires a
certain limited number of highly qualified, technical
personnel. To improve agriculture you have to teach
practically the entire population, or a greater part of the
population, and this is in some ways a much bigger
problem. But the problem is also to some extent a matter
merely of time. We are, in fact, building a number of
fertilizer plants. But there is no doubt that, for the size
of the country, the number of such plants and the rate
of their construction, should be increased. So this is
connected with the general industrial development and
what we are now laying the foundation of is not merely
fertilizer plants, but factories to produce fertilizer plants,
for only in this way can we be independent of outside
assistance.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
AT THE SPEED
OF SOUND
IN A TUNNEL
Technicians prepare to test the model of a
new aircraft design in a trisonic wind tunnel
(right) in the U.S.A. This test chamber,
55 feet long, can be adjusted In height to
simulate air speeds ranging from below to
above the rate of sound. Equipment photo¬
graphs and records the results of research.
Below, left, a six-foot man is dwarfed by the
colander-shaped muffler through which air
used for testing model planes is discharged
from the wind tunnel. This muffler reduces
to a murmur the howling blasts that race
through the test chamber. Below, right, a
test pilot equipped with special head camera
helmet for making aerial films of the flight
performances of experimental planes. With
a camera mounted on each side of his helmet,
he can take pictures by simply aiming his
head, leaving his own hands free to handle
his controls. This equipment is used on "chase
flights" when the cameraman-pilot accom¬
panies another plane to record its flight.
USIS photos
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1959
Letters to the Editor
WANTEDA WORLD CALENDAR
Sir,
An article written by Y.G. Perel and
entitled "The Calendar and the project
for its reform" was published in the
monthly popular science magazine of
the U.S.S.R. Academy of Sciences. It
dealt with the proposals made by India
to the United Nations in 1953 for the
introduction of a new World Calendar.
One wonders why such a remarkable
project so very useful and simple has
been shelved indefinitely.
Could you publish some more detailed
information about this proposed calendar
and describe how its introduction was
debated at the United Nations? If
possible I should like to know something
about the public's views on this subject.
P.S. Faingold
Moscow, U.S.S.R.
Ed. Note: The possibility of introduc¬
ing a World Calendar was discussed by
the U.N. Economic and Social Council
on the basis of reports submitted by 38
governments. In April 1956 the Council
expressed the view that the time was
not yet ripe for the introduction of such
a calendar, and adjourned the discussion
sine die. It did, however, consider that
further studies of the project by the
United Nations would be useful. Our
reader in Moscow can obtain more details
of the discussions from the U.N. Infor¬
mation Centre, 15 Hohlovski Pereulok,
Apartment 36, Moscow. An article on
The World Calendar and the history of
calendar reform down the ages appeared
in our lanuary 1954 issue.
NOTE ON THE RUHR
Sir,
A reader of The Unesco Courier-
has drawn my attention to the article
"One of the Grandest Views of Central
Europe", published in the August 1958
issue. In stating "Austria already exports
power to Italy and Germany, and other
European countries and the Ruhr arc
prospective future customers" the article
creates the impression that the Ruhr is
an independent European State. Some
of your readers may be interested to
know that it is a small river which gives
its name to a coal-mining and industrial
district within the boundaries of the
Federal Republic of Germany.
Dr. Wilhelm Platz
German National Commission forUnesco,
Cologne, German Federal Republic
POCKET HEATER FOR PILOTS
Sir,
As a glider pilot I was most interested
by an article in your March 1957 issue
concerning the "sausage stove" used by
Japanese mountain climbers, the "kairo",
consisting of a "sausage" of powdered
charcoal which burns for several hours
in a simple metal container, and which
these mountaineers place in their
clothing.
In certain atmospheric conditions
gliders are able to reach altitudes varying
between 15,000 and 30,000 feet where
pilots find the discomfort of extreme
cold difficult to stand for hours on end.
I think the "kairo" could be used in
gliders where it would provide pilots
with a convenient source of heat which
they lack today.
A. Cázalas
Paris, France
LANGUAGE BARRIERS
Sir,
Let me say how delighted I am with
The Unesco Courier. I anticipate each
issue with some excitement and read
every number with great satisfaction.
Particularly those issues which have
dealt with the curse of illiteracyiand
blight of prejudice have informed me
and encouraged me. These are severe
and effectual obstacles to intercultural
communication.
In this connexion I venture to say
that the barrier of language is likewise
a stubborn obstacle to the participation
of scientists, artists and ordinary men
and women in those unique cultural
values which each ethnic language
represents. It would please me much if
you could devote some future issue to
the problem of the language barrier.
Floyd Hardin
The International Language Review
Denver 1, Colorado, U.S.A.
OCTOGENARIAN ACHIEVEMENTS
Sir,
I read in The Unesco Courier (Octo¬
ber 1958) that Titian began to paint a^
"Descent from the Cross" at the age of
97. According to the latest researches
Titian was born in 1487 and not 1477
as was believed hitherto. If this proves
to be right, he worked on his last work
at the "early" age of 87. A similar case
is A. Stradivarius who possibly was mis¬
taken in indicating his age as 93 on
one of his unsurpassable masterworks.
It can be that he too was "only" 87
years old when he worked on it.
W.A. Schocken
Tel Aviv, Israel
INGRAINED COSMOPOLITANISM
Sir,
Your magazine disregards the dis¬
turbing problem of man's moral capacity
and spiritual maturity in the face of
the constant growth of his intellectual
and material power a development
which you extol throughout your pages.
And yet you surely know that according
to man's conception of life, according to
whether he gives primacy to things
spiritual or material, to the group
(national or ideological) or to the
individual, so will he reap from this
growing strength his full development
or his own destruction.
Your ingrained cosmopolitanism pre¬
vents you from joining this vital debate;
if you wished to enter the discussion
your prudence would induce you to
attempt an impossible conciliation of
every belief and philosophy or to unite
them in an arid and lifeless syncretism.
I admit that your magazine has been
providing me with worthwhile know¬
ledge about scientific and technical
progress, but this is something that
other . specialized reviews offer in
greater detail. Furthermore this is
merely the outward expression of an
inward and vital force which urgently
needs to be guided by a taking into
account of certain higher values. Your
way of lighting up the world is to add
more fuel to the fire.
P. Tochon
Paris, France
FORMULA WHICH PLEASES
Sir,
I am very pleased with the formula
you have adopted for your review.
Your fine photographs relieve the
dryness of figures and statistics which
would otherwise remain outside the ken
of the man-in-the-street, and this would
be a great pity for the cause of peace
and friendship between peoples.
Ch. Cheno
Montreuil-sous-Bois, France
Sir,
Always keep The Unesco Courier
at the present high standard which
helps us to round off our knowledge.
The culture we gain helps us to com¬
prehend men and facts thanks to the
great concern for objectivity and the
feeling for different shades of meaning
shown by all your contributors. The
quality and choice of photographs are
generally very high.
M. Bitozzo
Cannes-La Bocea, France
Sir,
Congratulations on the articles of
great merit you publish which are of
use to everyone. Please do your best
to include some on North Africa and
the Near and Middle East, dealing, for
example, with antique art, the history
of these regions and the progress that
has been made since countries became
independent.
Chahid Abdelaziz
Casablanca, Morocco
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom...
M AGNETIC MAP OF THE
EARTH: Countries taking part in the
International Geophysical Year have
agreed to carry out a world-wide sur¬
vey of magnetic phenomena at the
earth's surface, probably in about five
years' time when solar disturbances
will be at a minimum and geomag¬
netic conditions at their most stable.
Two hundred observatories now main¬
tain regular magnetic records on
land; the main problem in the future
survey will be how to make available
sufficient non-magnetic ships to ob¬
tain measurements at sea. Very few
such ships exist at present. Surveys
of this kind enable specialists to
establish charts needed by navigators
and scientists. The last world survey
of the earth's magnetism was carried
out nearly 30 years ago.
LISTENING IN TO FISH: Ac¬
cording to S.K. Otoo, a former
Unesco Fellowship holder now
loorking with the Bureau of Ghana
Languages, "every experienced
fisherman in Ghana can recognize
the 'voices' of -many different kinds
of fish, atid is able to locate them
by a simple yet effective device."
The fisherman puts his paddle
blade into the water, grasping the
handle with his little finger and
the loioer part of the palm, the
other fingers being closed and the
thumb placed over them. The
fisherman puts his ear to the
holloiu thus made, and he can hear
all the twises going on under the
water, including the "voice" of any
fish in the area.
USICAL ANTHOLOGY OF AFRICAN LIFE
A
musical anthology of special interest was issued recently under
the auspices of the International Music Council. Entitled
"An Anthology of African Life1', the material, recorded on
three discs, was collected in the Middle Congo and Gaboon areas of
French Equatorial Africa by Herbert Pepper, an ethnologist and
musicologist of the French Overseas Scientific Research Organization.
The recordings he has assembled go far beyond the purely aesthetic
or the merely picturesque. African music is intimately linked with
the duties, prayers, rites, games and dances that go to make up
everyday existence hence the title chosen for the worlk.
The anthology is divided into six parts: scenes of childhood and
adolescence; work, marching songs, games; musical 'language and
dances; healing rites, religion, magic; spoken literature; scenes of old
age, death and birth.
Detailed' information on each recording is given in a richly
illustrated brochure, including texts with translations. In a preface,
Leopold Sédar Senghor, poet and member of parliament for Senegal,
writes: "The title chosen indicates a new approach which aims at a
total grasp of reality, as does African Negro art. Herbert Pepper...
has left nothing out, neither tears nor laughter, work or play. In
Negro Africa, every social activity achieves its fulfilment and
effectiveness by virtue of art. "
A-TOMIC WASTE IN THE SEA:
Problems created by the disposal of
radio-active waste in the seas ¡were
studied by experts recently at the
Vienna headquarters of the United
Nations Atomic Energy Agency. Dis
cussions covered the prevention of
radio-active pollution of the seas due
to the peaceful uses of atomic energy,
through "controlled" releases of radio¬
active wastes and also due to acciden¬
tal escape into the sea of radio-active
materials. Results of the study will
aid the drafting of a proposed inter¬
national convention.
INDIA'S GANDHI MUSEUMS:
Collections devoted to the life and
work of Gandhi are to be set up in
India, financed by a special fund
started in Gandhi's memory. Each
museum will have a library of some
10,000 volumes, and the story of
the Mahatma's life will be told
with the aid of pictures, photo-
GOVERNMENTS TAKING ACTION
TO AID FLOW OF WORLD NEWS
Broader facilities which will ease the international transmission of
news by cable and radio will shortly be put info effect by
the world's governments. These concessions result from the
66-nation Telegraph and Telephone Conference of the International
Telecommunication Union, held at Geneva last October-November,
which adopted a number of proposals recommended by Unesco for
furthering the free flow of information betwen countries.
The conference agreed to telegrams of all kinds being sent "collect";
to reduced rates on jointly leased teleprinter lines and to the
establishment of uniform provisions for the operation of teleprinter,
telex, telephoto and telephone services in non-European as well as
European countries.
Other conference decisions: the provision of wider facilities for
radio-communications (multiple address), including permission to
incorporate editorial instructions in dispatches; liberalization provi¬
sions concerning the identity of persons who may submit or receive
press telegrams; the removal of limitations in the application of press
rates to press telegrams; and easier leasing of telephone circuits for
radio and television transmissions.
The new provisions are due to come into effect on January 1 1960.
graphs, photostats of letters, arti¬
cles and other personal objects. It
is also planned to build hostels at¬
tached to the museums where scho¬
lars from other parts of India or
from abroad may stay while
carrying out research work.
M ALARIA OUT«ICE IN: Ma¬
laria has been almost completely era¬
dicated in Portugal where prior to the
last war 15,000 cases were recorded
annually, with a toll of 500 deaths.
During 1957 there were no deaths and
only 49 cases were recorded, while in
the first half of 1958 only one case
was notified. One result is that Portu¬
gal has again become a rice-producing
country. Rice cultivation had been
forbidden so as to prevent malaria
mosquitoes breeding in the stagnant
water of the fields. Now, instead of
importing rice, Portugal has become
an exporter and the savings effected
more than cover the cost of the
Malaria Eradication Service.
TOO FEW SCHOOLS: According
to a recently published Unesco sur¬
vey of primary education through¬
out the world (*) there are ap¬
proximately 550,000,000 children
aged five to 14 in the world today,
but only 300,000,000 of them are in
school. Collected over a period of
three years, the figures show that
the situation is however improv¬
ing. During the early 1950s, the
world passed the halfway mark in
getting school - age youngsters into
classrooms the enrolment figure
was 48% in 1950 and 55% in 1954.
Between 1930 and 1954, the world's
child population rose by 22%, pri¬
mary school enrolment by 33%.
* World Survey of Education
II Primary Education. Price:
$26.00; £6.10.0d; 7,800 Fr. francs.
oí
O
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Today there are more than 1,200 international organizations,
governmental and non-governmental, whose existence and
activities show how men and women of goodwill from all
countries have joined together in creating machinery for co¬
operation and understanding in every sphere of life. An autho¬
ritative guide to this multitude of organizations is provided by
The Yearbook of International Organizations whose 7th edition
(1958-59) which is in English, is now available.
Compiled by the Union of International Associations on the
basis of a world-wide survey, the latest edition gives essential data
on 1,222 international organizations (149 governmental and 1,073
non-governmental). Endorsed by and published in official collabo¬
ration with the United Nations, the Yearbook can be obtained
through the Union of International Associations, Palais d'Egmont,
Brussels, Belgium, to which all enquiries should be made regarding
availability in other countries. Price of the Yearbook is: $14.00;
78/- (stg.); 5,800 Fr. fr. ; 580 Bel. frs.; 52 Sw. frs.; 52 D.M
YEARBOOK
»/
INTERNATIONAL
ORGANIZATIONS
7tb Edition
1958-59
Union of International Associations
The broadest aspects of the scientific and cultural development
of mankind are described fully and regularly in the JOUR¬
NAL OF WORLD HISTORY. Published quarterly with the
financial assistance of Unesco, this review has become an impor¬
tant source of information and opinion which contribute to a
better understanding of the problems of science and culture among
all peoples and at all periods of history.
Contributions to the JOURNAL OF WORLD HISTORY from
historians and scholars in all parts of the world include short
monographs, discussions of important historical questions, general
studies and critical bibliographies. These are used in the prepa¬
ration . of a six-volume History which was entrusted to the
International Commission for a History of the Scientific and
Cultural Development of Mankind by Unesco.
The annual subscription to the JOURNAL OF WORLD
HISTORY (about 1,000 pages in four numbers) is $8.00 (or the
equivalent in local currency) which can be paid to Editions de
La Baconnière, Boudry (Neuchatel) Switzerland, CCP, 1226, or
to agents whose addresses are obtainable from the Secretariat of
the International Commission, Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris.
WHERE TO OBTAIN UNESCO PUBLICATIONS
Order from any bookseller, or write
direct to the National Distributor
¡n your country (See list below ;
names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request).
Payment is made in the national
currency ; rates quoted are for an
annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Press
Department, Royal Afghan Ministry of
Education, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 369 Lonsdale Street, Melbourne,
C.I. Victoria. (A. 13/-)
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C"., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V (seh.
37.50.)
BELGIUM. For The Unesco Courier:
Louis de Lan noy, 47, rue du Midi,
Brussels, CCP. 338.000. (fr.b. 100.)
Other publications: Office de Publicité,
22, Place De Brouckère, CCP 285-98;
N.V. Standaard-Boekhandel, Belgiëlei 151,
Antwerp.
BRAZIL. Livraria Agir Editora, Rua
Mexico 98-B, Caixa Postal 3291, Rio de
Janeiro.
BURMA. S.P.C.K. (Burma) 549, Merchant
Street, P.O. Box 222, Rangoon,
of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House Bookshop,
I 00 Parsons Road P.O. Box 244, Colombo
2. (Rs.9)
CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa,
Ont. ($ 3.00).
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd, Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Co¬
lombo 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Libreria Económica, Pte Zayas
505-7 Apartado I 13, Havana.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia Ltd., 30
Ve Smeckách, Prague 2.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6 Nörregade, Copenhagen K. (D.kr. 12)
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agen¬
cy, P.O. Box 120, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (F.mk. 540)
FRANCE. Unesco Bookshop, Place de
Fontenoy, Paris, 7\ CCP. 12598-48.
(600 fr.)
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8. (DM. 6)
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Kultura, P.O. Box 149.
Budapest, 62.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I ; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; Gunfoundry Road, Hyde¬
rabad, I; 36a, Mount Road., Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/ 1 Asaf Ali Road, P. O.
Box 386, New Delhi, I; Sub-Depots :
Oxford Book & Stationery Co.. Scindia
House, New Delhi; Raikamal Prakashan
Private Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby
Road, Bombay I. (Rs. 6.70)
INDONESIA. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Djakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The National Press. 2 Wel¬
lington Road Ballsbridge. Dublin. (10/-)
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd..
35, Allenby Road and 48, Nahlat Benja¬
min Street, Tel-Aviv. ,(£.l./4.--.)
ITALY. Libreria Commissionaria San-
soni. Via Gino Capponi 26, Casella Pos¬
tale 552, Florence, (lire 950)
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings. (10/-)
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo. (Yen 500)
JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road, P.O.B. 66,
Amman.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul
Brück, 33 Grand'Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Peter Chong & Co.,
Post Office Box 135, Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta. ( I 0/-)
MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid. des
Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (600 fr.).
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl. 6)
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church. (10/-.)
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos. (10/-)
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass 7, Oslo. (N. kr. 10)
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60 The Mall
Lahore ; Bunder Road, Karachi and
35 The Mall. Peshawar, (rs.6)
PANAMA. Cultural Panameña, Ave¬
nida 7a, No. Ti-49, Apartado de Correos
201 8, Panama, D.F.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo, P.O. Box
620, Manila.
POLAND. Osrodek Rozpowszechniania
Wydawnictw Naukowych PAN, Palac
Kultury i Nauki, Warsaw. (Zl. 50).
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada Lda,
Livraria Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70,
Lisbon.
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Libri Building, Church Street, P.O.
Box 724. Pretoria. (10/-)
SWEDEN. A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm
16. (Sw.kr. 7.50)
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40 rue du Marché, Geneva. CCP.
1-236. For the Unesco Courier only ;
Georges Losmaz, I, rue des Vieux-Gre¬
nadiers, Genève, CCP. 1. 4811 (frs. S. 6.50)
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Isti-
klal Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul.
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT).
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha,
Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office. P.O. Box 5 69. London, S.E. I. ( I 0/-)
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22, N.Y. (S3. 00.) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y.
U. S. S. R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga,
Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Werner Bischof © Magnum photos
"In many countries of Asia the productivity of agriculture per man remains the same as it has been for centuries... Many
people are under the misapprehension that the overpopulation and the increase of population in the under-developed
areas are the causes of their low standard of living. This is clearly not so. Even with an increasing population, modern
technology enables one to raise the standard of living of the people as a whole, because the rate of increase in produc¬
tion can be much greater than the rate of increase of population." (See p. 31 , Homi Bhabha on Science & Living Standards)
]]>
</page>
</document>
