<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="065278eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
DOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
New cities reborn
from the ashes of war
THE MIRACLE
OF ROTTERDAM
JULY-AUGUST
19 5 9
(12th year)
IS THE OCEAN IN DANGER?
(See page 28)
Price: 1/-stg. (U.K.)
30 cents (U . S .)
60 francs (France)
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
SINE
VISITS
UNESCO
MOORE'S RECLINING FIGURE
-f-
W-£-
FIREMEN'S STAIR WAY
© Unesco Courier - Reproduction prohibited
CALDER'S MOBILE
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier
JULY-AUGUST 1959
1 2 T H YEAR
Conte n t s
N°" 7-8
PAGE
4 PEERING INTO THE MIND OF A CHILD
8 THE SALT OF LIFE
By Arthur Nettleton
II WHAT TIME IS IT ?
A fictitious sun gives us the answer
By David Gunston
COVER PHOTO
In May 1 940, a devastating
bombardment transformed Rot¬
terdam into a sea of flames which
burned for 40 days and 40 nights
and left 6,000 million cubic feet
of rubble to be cleared away.
Today Rotterdam is one of the
world's most imposing cities.
This is the ''miracle" of Rotter¬
dam. Striking works of art in
the streets and squares, like
Zadkine's monument (above)
erected to commemorate Rot¬
terdam's ordeal, also serve as
symbols of its resurrection.
Lies Wiegman © Agence
de Diffusion Internationale
13 THE MIRACLE OF ROTTERDAM
City risen from the ashes
By Michel Salmon
21 ELECTRONIC TRANSLATORS WITH
BUILT-IN DICTIONARIES
By Emile Delavenay
22 A DESERT IN THE HEART OF LONDON
War against locusts
By Daniel Behrman
28 IS THE OCEAN IN DANGER?
By Nicolas Gorsky
32 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7', France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
THE UNESCO COURIER Is published monthly (I 2 issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. The United States of America edition is distri¬
buted by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 801 Third Avenue, New'
York 22, N.Y., Plaza 1-3860. Second-class mail privileges authorized at New
York, N.Y. (M.C. 59.1.138 A)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER plus date
of Issue", and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: $3.00; IO/-stg. ; ¿OOFr. frs. or equivalent.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
When does a child start to "think"? At what age can
he understand such ideas as length and number?
When is he capable of. what is called "scientific
thought"?
Educators and parents the world over would be
extremely interested in knowing the answers to such
questions. Today, they are being sought in Switzerland at
the Institute for the Sciences of Education in Geneva. The
Institute was founded in 1912 iand attached to the
University of Geneva in 1929, but its origins go even further
back. In 1901, at the dawn of the new century, the
Medical Society of Geneva heard a daring proposal by
Edouard Claparède, the future co-founder of the Institute
along with Pierre Bovet. Claparède called for nothing
less than a school "made to measure" for children. Into
his startled audience, he dropped this bombshell: "We
now pay more attention to children's feet than we do to
their minds."
Five years later, Claparède was to state: "It is just
as important for the educator to know the laws of the
mind and its growth as it is for the horticulturist to know
the biology of plants or the doctor to know the physiology
of organs." It Was on this principle that the Institute
started a laboratory in which experimental psychology is
applied to education. For the past thirty years, both at
Geneva and at Neuchatel, this work has been carried on
by Prof. Jean Piaget, a leading figure in psychological
research which has a bearing on education.
Prof. Piaget's studies had previously shown that the
development of a child's thought processes can be compar¬
ed ito a ladder. The child goes from one step or level to
another. At each level, corresponding to a certain age,
there is an equilibrium in his thinking.
Then, two years ago, a special section of the Institute
was created to study how the child passes from one stage
to another. This study, directed by Dr. Bärbel Inhelder,
professor at the Institute of Child Psychology, and Dr.
Gerald Noelting, is based upon a long-term experiment.
Twenty children, divided into four age groups, have been
selected from Geneva schools for study. They come from
all social classes, have average intelligence test ratings and
have experienced no special difficulties in school.
They have ¡t all taped
Some fifty tests based on special observation techniques
developed by Prof. Piaget over the years are used
with these children. In addition, the research
workers have at their disposal an experimental psychology
laboratory set up by the state of Geneva and provided
with ultra-modern equipment through a grant from an
American foundation.
In this laboratory, each conversation between the
scientist and a child is recorded on tape. At key points
in the interview, a motion picture camera comes into play.
The result is that the Institute has been able to "produce"
records and a film on each child, showing the changes in
his social behaviour and the way his mind works at various
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courrier. July-August 1959
WHO photoi by Eric Schw»
HOW DO YOU THINK I SEE THIS LANDSCAPE? An educational researcher puts the above question to a
child who must select the drawing corresponding to what she believes the experimenter sees from his position
opposite her (above). Thus she shows her capacity for judging how perspective varies according to the position
of the observer. Below, a close-up of experimental equipment used for this test. Using a variety of similar
experiments, researchers at the Institute for the Sciences of Education in Geneva study the development of
a child's thought processes. Opposite page« the little girl tsmilingly says goodbye to Institute psychologist.
stages of growth over the years. These experiments have
already shown that the child first groups familiar objects
or even geometrical elements into "logical classes" between
the ages of four and seven. By pouring liquids from one
glass to another, for example, he grasps the idea of a quan¬
tity which does not vary even if its appearance changes.
He understands concepts of length and number between
the ages of five and seven. Weight and volume come later
between nine and twelve and now the framework of
his thought processes has been erected. At the age of ten,
he begins to experiment and then, research shows, he is
capable of scientific thinking at twelve when he starts
formulating theories and searching for proofs.
As is often the case in science, the answers to the first
questions have now raised new ones. For example,
scientists now wonder if this development is the result of
mental and nervous "maturing1" or whether it is the fruit
of education and ijust plain practice. Professor Piaget has
already shown that external and internal factors always
inter-act that is, you cannot separate them. How this
"inter-action" takes place is yet to be answered. There is
also an even bigger question: how is the young child's
mind, concentrated on the present and on what he can see
and touch, transformed into the mind of the adolescent
conscious of the world and capable of co-operating with
his fellow men?
This is pure research at present, but Prof. Piaget and
the Swiss scientists working with him believe that its
results may represent a valuable contribution to education.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
CHILD'S MIND (Continued)
CUBES AND 'COVERED WAGGONS'
TEST YOUNGSTERS' THINKING
PROFESSOR JEAN PIAGET, Co-Director of
the Institute for the Sciences of Education and
Director of the International Bureau of Education,
Geneva. Prof. Piaget, who is Swiss, was formerly
a member of the Executive Board of Unesco.
We are now paying more attention to children's feet than we do to
their minds, a famous educator remarked some sixty years ago. In
Geneva, the Institute of the Sciences of Education has set its sights on
the child's mind. By direct observation it is trying to find out about
the different stages in children's thinking and how a child passes from
one stage to the other. Some of their techniques are shown here:
(I & 2) covered waggon-like apparatus is used to test girl's ability to
understand the law of falling bodies along an inclined plane; Angle of
chute (shaft of "covered waggon") is altered and child is asked to judge
how far object will fall each time. (3) study of the concept of size.
The object is to measure the height of a tower standing on a stool.
The child is asked to build a tower of the same height on the ground;
(4) the concept of volume. Child must construct houses with iden¬
tical volumes on islands with different surface areas; (5 and 6)
representation in two and three dimensions. Child draws on a plain
sheet the opened-out surfaces of a geometrical solid she is shown.
WHO photos by Eric Schwab
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courrier. July-August 1959
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
THESALT
LIFE
by Arthur Nettleton
Fellow of the Royal Geographical
Society, London
Most people think of salt as being used
mostly to season food in the kitchen,
but this is one of the least important uses
of salt. The largest users of salt are
meat and fish packers, chemical industries,
hide, textile and leather processors and
soap manufacturers. Photo right, shows
salt being used for skin curing; below,
salt being mined deep underground.
Photos © Imperial Chemical Industries
Of all the substances found in the earth, few are more
essential than common salt. . If we were to be
denied this natural compound the human race
would die and much animal life would vanish. Without
salt many modern industries would come to a halt.
Centuries ago it was recognized that to deprive a man
of his salt was a sure way of causing his lingering death.
Few could survive more than a month if subjected to
complete salt starvation, and the sentence was a
dreadful punishment.
Today medical science is making the reverse approach
by investigating the uses of salt in fighting and curing ill
health. Doctors are aWare that the amount of salt
introduced into the human body affects the adrenal
glands, and controlling or omitting salt from the diet is
a well-known treatment for kidney ailments.
The importance of salt to health has certainly long been
known to peoples who dwell in hot climates. Extra salt
is needed to replace that lost from the body by profuse
perspiration. Heat exhaustion and sunstroke are less
likely if this precaution is taken.
Workers in heavy industries such as steel-making who
perspire greatly, similarly require to replace their lost salt.
Failure to do this is believed to be a cause of muscular
8
cramp, and to avoid that crippling complaint specially
flavoured salt tablets were issued to American steel
workers during the War. The practice proved so bene¬
ficial that it is still continued.
Many animals, too, know instinctively that salt is
essential to their well-being. Experiments have shown
that dogs deprived of it can live only about three weeks,
and cattle and sheep must have their "salt licks" if they
are to remain healthy. Carnivorous animals also need
salt, though they get it from the raw meat they eat.
The story of salt in modern industry is no less absorbing,
and its uses in these fields are being continually expanded.
It is used in glass-making, in the production of alumi¬
nium, in smelting, and in meat packing. It is the
prime raw material of the modern chemical industries,
and is used in soap-making, in refining fats and oils, and
in the manufacture of bleaching powders, insecticides,
fungicides, and fertilizers. The list of processes using salt
is legion, and it can truly be called the most versatile of
common compounds.
It is needed for water purification, for the manufacture
of paper, for bacon curing, and for butter making. World
consumption of salt is rapidly increasing, and production
is being stepped up to meet the growing demand. Canada
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
opened a new rock salt mine near Windsor, Ontario, three
years ago, and it has been equipped to produce 500 tons a
day from a 27ft. seam 700ft. down. Another new salt
seam of exceptionally pure quality has been tapped near
Goderich, Ontario.
Salt production in Canada alone has trebled during the
last 20 years. Altogether we need 20,000,000 tons a year
for consumption and industries throughout the world.
Salt was so valuable in early times that it gave us our
word salary, from the Latin solarium, meaning "salt
money" the allowance given Roman soldiers to buy salt.
One of the oldest roads of Italy was called the Via Salaria
(salt road) because it (was the route by which salt was
transported. Among the ancients, to "eat salt" with a
man was to create a sacred bond of friendship, ancfc this
is still so with some Oriental peoples today. In the
Middle Ages one's social rank was shown by whether one
sat above or below (the salt at table. In some parts of
the world today salt is regarded as more to be coveted
than money. Six pounds of salt was the only reward
three Naga hillmen asked .for building a church in Burma.
The value placed on this commodity may be gauged
from the lengthy treks which take place regularly to the
main salt markets. Tibetans descend from the "'Roof of
The Unesco Courrier. July-August 1959
the World" to bring back a few pounds of salt, and one of
the sights of the Sahara is the annual progression of
camel caravans to the salt centre of Timbuktu, the
fabulous city which founded its wealth on the salt trade
centuries ago.
Salt has promoted learning, too. In its greatest days
as a salt mart Timbuktu boasted large libraries, and was
a major centre of education.
Agricultural scientists have experimented with salt as
a soil dressing during the last 15 years, and much has
been learned about its value as a crop improver. Tests
have shown that if 3-5 hundredweights of salt are added
to an acre of land, sugar beet grown there will yield that
much extra sugar. American research has revealed that
salt dressings make the beet stronger and more suitable
for machine harvesting an important point in these days
of mechanized farming.
Salt refiners have also introduced a variety of salt
specially suited to mechanical spreading. It is of uniform
cubical structure, so that it passes freely through the
spreader, and it does not readily blow from the surface of
the soil.
Washing out the soil
to make arid arable
On the other hand, salt is far from being a complete
boon to agriculture. An excess of this substance in
the ground destroys the fertility of the soil, and
some of the largest areas of arid land owe their sterility
to an overabundance of salt.
Whereas the human body does not demur at one part
of salt in each 1,000 parts of water, animals will normally
drink a stronger saline solution than this. Most plants
do not require much salt. If the soil becomes too salty,
it is unsuitable for cultivation.
Lands once fertile have changed into deserts as the
rivers irrigating them have impregnated the soil with
salt. The water has evaporated and the salt it contained
has been left behind, so that in course of time the region
has been rendered unsuitable for crops. Research has
shown that as much as four tons of salt per acre may
accumulate in this way during a single year.
This negative aspect of salt and its uses is now being
investigated by agriculturalists, soil scientists, chemists,
and botanists. One of their aims is to determine whether
projected sources of irrigation water, in areas it is hoped
to reclaim for cultivation, are suitable for given crops on
the type of soil concerned. Matching the crop to the
salinity of the soil will be a vital factor In solving the
problems of the world's arid regions, and the successful
restoration of agriculture there over a period of time will
depend largely on methods of draining off the iwater used
for irrigation and washing soils impregnated with salt.
At the same time efforts are being made to produce
varieties of useful plants which will thrive even if the soil
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
THE SALT OF LIFE
(Continued)
is unusually salty. Botanists can help by providing
plants which do not suffer under such conditions.
As to the sources for industrial salt and agricultural
salt, it may be mined in rock form or obtained by
evaporating brine from salt lakes or the sea. A third
method is to dissolve the deposits of rock salt under¬
ground by introducing water through a bore-hole and
then pumping this brine to the surface.
In the last-named case it was customary until recently
to drill by percussion methods or by rotary shot, but the
job has been speeded up by adopting the American oil
well technique. Boring is done by high speed rotary bits
in conjunction With a high pressure stream of liquid mud,
which flushes the debris to the surface as it is produced.
Salt is being obtained through a bore-hole made in that
way near the mouth of the River Tees, England, and the
brine is being refined into table salt. By this method of
drilling, a well 1,000ft. deep can be drilled in days instead
of weeks.
The most extensive salt mines in the world, at
Wieliczka, Poland, have been (worked for centuries and
still show no signs of becoming exhausted. The salt here
is not high grade, being mixed with clay, but the deposits
are more than 400 yards thick and the galleries have a
total length of more than 500 miles.
Deposits in Britain supply about one-tenth of the
world's needs. Utah, America, has the largest salt lake
in the world, 75 miles long and 20-50 miles Wide, with
brine one-sixth salt. The harvesting ponds to which the
brine flows are the biggest salt pans in the world. Here
the salt is obtained by evaporation.
Salt produced in Britain is similarly obtained mainly
Photos © Imperial Chemical Industries
UNDERGROUND LAKES & WELLS provide much of the salt for
many countries. Those in Cheshire, England, have the strongest
natural brine in the world, most of the salt produced in Britain being
obtained from underground lakes. Above, this dryer with its battery
of curved pipes removes the last traces of moisture from the salt.
10
COMMON SALT is found in the oceans, salt lakes, salt wells and
salt mines. In almost every part of the world salt can be found in
underground mines. Most lie far beneath the surface and the salt is
mined like coal. Photo above shows rock salt being mined in Great
Britain where deposits supply about one-tenth of the world's needs.
from brine, though the lakes are underground. Cheshire,
England, has the strongest natural brine in the world.
The liquid is evaporated in artificially heated pans, and
the size of the crystals depends upon the speed of
evaporation, fine salt being produced rapidly and coarse
salt slowly.
Some facts about salt are startling to the layman.
Thus, if an active cell in a mild saline solution has its
medium changed to one of pure water it swells and bursts.
Saltless water kills a higher animal partly by causing the
blood corpuscles to rupture and discharge potassium salts
into the blood stream, and partly by stopping the kidneys
from functioning they cannot do so Iwithout salt. The
burst blood cells also paralyze the heart, not only directly
by the potassium, but also indirectly because they are no
longer able to carry oxygen from the lungs.
A quarter ounce a day
keeps the doctor away
It has been computed that the human body needs about
ioz. of salt a day to keep it healthy. Among the
functions of the salt we eat is the protection of the
body against microbes; it has been found that serums
which can kill bacteria are unable to do iso if the salt is
extracted.
Perhaps the strangest use for salt is in road building.
America has a highway made of solid blocks of salt
connecting Ithaca (New York) with the nearby airport,
and this extraordinary highway has lasted 20 years
without signs of serious deterioration.
London owes its situation indirectly to salt. Over
1,000 years ago Britain's salt mines supplied Western
European countries, and on their (way to the south coast
of England the pack pony trains crossed the River Thames
at a convenient ford near the present Westminster
Bridge. Around the site of the ford a settlement grew
up the nucleus of the present city.
Today, despite the continually increasing demand for
salt, the world is never likely to experience a shortage.
Even in the inconceivable event of the salt mines and
brine lakes becoming exhausted, the oceans contain
enough of this vital commodity to meet our needs for
thousands of years.
You do not have to take this .statement with the
proverbial "'grain of salt." SeaWater contains an average
of three per cent of salt, and there are about
500,000,000 cubic miles of brine in the oceans of the world.
Clearly the name common salt is no misnomer, and its
expanding uses today are not likely to be handicapped by
any lack of the raw substance.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courrier. July-August 1959
WHAT TIME IS IT?
A fictitious sun gives us the answer
by David Gunston
Since the very earliest times man has always been
aware of the passing of time. It is something
fundamental in life which, like space, we feel we
understand but cannot easily define. Pulse beats, the
movements of sun and moon, day and night, the tides, the
changing seasons, youth and age all these gave even
primitive man this feeling of time's existence.
But although as we know from the evidence of the first
sundials and the Egyptian water-clocks, he has long been
interested in measuring the passage of time, human life
got by quite well for many centuries without feeling the
necessity of having a standard universal time. Cave men
adjusted their lives according to the sun's movements, and
so, basically, did civilized people until after the middle of
the last century. Local time was all that mattered to the
vast majority of the human race long after the perfection
of mechanical timekeeping.
It was the development of railroad communications in
North America that really led to the adoption of the
universally recognized time system we know today. In
Europe, English trains began to run to Greenwich time,
French trains to Paris time, German trains to Berlin time.
Local communities kept to their own mean sun time, and
for a while it all worked fairly well.
But it was hardly to be expected that railroads extend¬
ing their services over the Middle and Far West would
adopt Washington time, which frequently differed by
several hours from the local time of the regions they
served. Owing to the vast E-W size of the American
Continent the moment at which the sun appeared to pass
immediately overhead at the meridian (noon) differed
considerably in places of different longitude. So railroads
in the United States actually started their own time, o
with the longer lines, their own time zones.
As the system grew and more folk wanted to travel, this
of course led to much confusion, especially at change-over
stations, and it became obvious that a better solution
would have to be found. The whole question of a
standardized time-keeping system was discussed in
conferences by the principal countries of the world during
the years 1870-1880. Thanks primarily to scientists Char¬
les F. DOwd in America and Sandford Fleming in Canada,
a workable scheme was put forward and, after much
debating, was finally adopted by the railroad companies
of North America and eventually, in 1883-1884, by almost
the entire civilized globe.
Stepping over a line
makes today tomorrow
The idea, like most good ones, was basically simple.
There were to be accepted for the whole earth 24
standard meridians each 15° apart in longitude, for
this purpose a meridian being taken to be an imaginary
line circling the earth and passing through the poles. The
prime meridian (0°), from which these were to be calculat¬
ed was, by arbitrary agreement, that running through
Greenwich, on the eastern fringe of London. Greenwich
was partly chosen by Way of international recognition of
the importance of its famous Royal Observatory's contri¬
butions to astronomy and nautical science since its foun¬
dation by King Charles II in 1675.
Each longitudinal meridian was to be the centre of the
one of the 24 fixed time zones each changing by one hour
in passing to the next, back for westward from Greenwich,
on for eastward. This also meant that at longitude 180° E.
longitude 180° W. was also found, and so arose what is
now known as the International Date Line and the
convention of jumping a whole day of 24 hours when this
point is crossed, gaining it in one direction and losing It
in another. In practice, today, the Date Line does not
keep strictly to, the meridian, but curves round the
Aleutian Islands and Fiji to enable the people of these,
and neighbouring islands, to have the same day.
The advantages of this standard system were
immediately obvious and now almost everywhere zone time
based on Greenwich Mean Time (G.M.T.) is the rule.
G.M.T. is kept all over Britain, and other countries have
long adopted time zones corresponding to the selected
meridians. Thus much of Europe keeps to Continental
Time, 1 hour fast on Greenwich, while in North America
the five time zones are used Atlantic, Eastern, Central,
Mountain and Pacific, respectively 4, 5, 6, 7 and 8 hours
behind G.M.T. If New York preferred to adopt G.M.T.,
the sun would not be overhead until 5 p.m. Thus the
system of "'five hours back" is the answer. Certainly it
is infinitely better than the chaos of 80 years ago, when
there were almost as many time meridians as there were
railroad companies.
Modern time begins
at the G in G. M.T.
So, in the strictly practical sense, Greenwich is the place
where modern time begins. In point of fact, the Royal
Observatory has now moved to the village of Hurst-
monceux (pronounced Hurst-roon-soo) near Eastbourne,
Sussex, on the South Coast of England, but as this place
is close to the Greenwich meridian and allowance is made
for the difference, the change in no way affects the
validity of Greenwich Mean Time.
So far, however, we have been concerned with what is
termed the mean solar day based upon arbitrary
meridians. This would be completely accurate and useful
if the earth and the sun were bodies rigidly accurate in
their motions. But things are not quite so easy as that.
The earth itself is tilted on its axis at an angle of 23 i °
from vertical, and its path round the sun is elliptical, not
circular. What, then, are the basic concepts for the
measurement of time?
All our sense of time is bound up with some movement,
whether it be the sun in the sky or the hands on the face
of a clock. But movement requires space, so it is evident
at once that time and space are closely related, though
of course if measuring time is one thing, defining it
precisely is quite another. Indeed, the world's meta¬
physicians are still not entirely agreed upon a definition
of time, which may therefore be long delayed.
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
WHAT TIME IS IT?
(Continued)
On the scientific level, however, all our measurements
of time depend primarily on the movement of the earth
spinning round on its axis, and round the sun the first
enabling us to count off successive days, the second
successive years. Thus we see clearly why time-measuring
has always been an important part of practical astronomy.
Why, in fact, what we call "'the right time" is originally
given to the world by observatories and not by railroad
stations or shipping offices.
To tell the time of day We need first of all a moment
at which we consider each day to begin. Whereas for
civil purposes in our daily lives this point is taken to be
midnight, the natural day commences at noon that is,
when the sun crosses the meridian. But the intervals
between successive noons throughout the year as measur¬
ed by this method are far from equal, because of the
eccentricities of the earth's behaviour in space. The
daily errors mount up, and clocks set solely by the sun
would be hours wrong within months. The sun is, in fact,
not a particularly good timekeeper.
If instead of using the sun we measure time by the
apparent daytime movement of the stars no such
inequalities are noticeable. Star time, thus obtained, is
called Sidereal Time and for strictly scientific use, as in
astronomy, it is the only true time. Why should this be
so? When compared with our sun the stars are infinitely
distant, and even when the earth moves round the sun
for say six months to occupy a position in space which has
changed by nearly 200 million miles, the apparent position
to us of the stars has changed only by amounts too
inflnitesimally small to affect earthly calculations to any
important degree.
So, aware of these basic errors in solar time, the system
of Mean Time had to be introduced, which is based on
the movements of a fictitious sun which gives us every
day of exactly the same length and equal to the apparent
length of the solar day. Mean Time can best be defined
by the going of a perfect clock which is so set that, in
the average (mean) of the whole year, it shall be as much
ahead of solar time as behind it.
Most accurate 'clock' gains
twelve hours in six months
The greatest difference between clock and sun would
then be about 16 minutes, occurring in one direction
early in November and in the other about the middle
of February. This vital difference is called the Equation
of Time, and it represents (from a highly accurate
astronomical point of view, only roughly) the difference
between apparent solar time and G.M.T. This data is
given for each day in Nautical and Domestic Almanacs,
thus enabling domestic clocks and ship's chronometers to
be set by the sun. Wherever reasonably exact time is of
importance, a similar system to this is in use.
For the astronomer, Sidereal Time is of the utmost
importance. He reads it by measuring the daily motion
of that point in the equator from which the true right
ascension of the stars is reckoned what he calls the
vernal equinox. Two upper transits of this over the same
meridian determine a sidereal day, which is actually
shorter than a mean solar day:
1 Mean Solar Day = 24 hrs. 3 mins. 56.5554 seconds,
sidereal time.
1 Sidereal Day = 23 hrs. 56 mins. 4.091 seconds, mean
solar time.
When he is about to make time observations the
12
astronomer sets his telescope at the proper angle to watch
the passage of the star across the meridian. His instru¬
ment has between 5 and 11 spider-lines ruled across its
glass, the centre one set on the meridian. He records
on a chronograph, or highly precise stop-watch, the star's
transit over each line by interrupting his electric circuit
with a hand-held key, which itself is connected
electrically to the chronograph and on which a break-
circuit chronometer is making a continuous record. The
chronograph sheet can afterwards easily be interpreted,
and Sidereal Time calculated. A sidereal clock, however,
is useless for ordinary day-to-day timekeeping, since it
gains 12 hours on an ordinary clock in 6 months.
Ordinarily speaking, we must still live our lives by the
sun, getting up around sunrise and going to bed when
darkness has fallen. So we must have a practical system
based on the sun, and the thing works better if we
replace the unreliable real sun by this imaginary (mean)
sun, which crosses the meridian at uniform intervals and
goes round the equator at a fixed rate adjusted so that
the real sun and itself each take exactly one year to make
the circuit.
Quartz crystal clock keeps
time to 1/ 1,000th of a second
This man-devised compromise brings us back to Green¬
wich and its long-proved Mean Time, which is actual¬
ly the Greenwich Hour Angle of the mean sun, plus
12 hours to make the day begin at midnight. And as such
it meets all the needs of the ordinary world though of
course under zone time systems the true (sun) time is
applicable only exactly on the meridians, which however
causes little inconvenience in practice.
The famous old Royal Observatory at Greenwich
suffered some bomb damage in World War H, but it was
moved from London chiefly because that city's brilliant
street-lighting (unknown in Charles II's day) had made
night-sky observations and long-exposure photography
practically impossible. The move to Hurstmonceux Castle,
"the most perfect example of the mansion of a feudal lord
in the South of England," and built in 1446, is now almost
complete, but the new Observatory still retains its ancient
description of Royal Greenwich Observatory.
Six telescope domes one for the new 100-inch "Isaac
Newton" and modern office blocks now ring the Tudor
turrets, but all the old work of time-keeping and
astronomical observation continues and is expanding in
ideal surroundings and with up-to-date equipment. The
well-known Greenwich Time Signal, or "pips," is still
broadcast to the world every 15 mins. from an astronomical
"Regulator" radio clock governed by a quartz crystal clock.
This is constantly checked and compared with the time
signals of Paris and elsewhere, so that it and all the
Observatory clocks keep time to within l/l,000th of a
second per day.
Before the telegraph was invented, observatories gave
their time signals by bell-ringing, whistle-blowing and the
dropping of elevated time-ball signals on their towers,
but nowadays G.M.T. is relayed by radio continuously all
over the globe for the benefit of other observatories, radio
stations, ships and aircraft. Any individual or traveller
with suitable radio receiving equipment can receive a time-
signal over the ether correct to within l/100th of a second,
but in general it is the ordinary broadcasting stations
which perform the most public service by regularly issuing
time checks. The U.S. Navy Observatory at Georgetown
Heights, Washington, however, accepts no responsibility
for tirrie signals other than its own, and every day at noon
still uses a time-ball, as well as automatically correcting
all the clocks in the Government Buildings there.
As you will have seen, time-keeping is a trickier business
than it at first seems, but it has now been perfected as
much as is humanly possible. It's not often science's
fault' if you are late for an appointment!
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courrier. July-August 1959
Almost all of central Rotter¬
dam was razed to the ground
by a single bombing attack
on May 14, I 940 and by the
great fire which followed.
Today Rotterdam is one of
the most imposing cities in
the Western world, with
fine modern buildings, a
simple yet daring architec¬
tural style, spacious avenues,
and works of art, which are
all strikingly integrated into
the new urbanization plan.
Left, "Construction", a motif
in metal by the sculptor
Naum Gabo which stands
on the Coolsingel, Rot¬
terdam's "Champs-Elysées".
All photos Lies Wie£man (Ç,
Agence de Diffusion Internationale
MIRACLE AT
ROTTERDAM
by Michel Salmon
I love Rotterdam as some people love rain or the blustering wind or cold, stimulating weather
that quickens one to activity. There is a good reason for comparing it with the weather.
The sea is Rotterdam's cradle; it is the backcloth to its great stage crowded with docks,
houses, esplanades and factories on which rain, wind and cold often appear as actors and
"extras."
But Rotterdam also has its ruins, or rather its memories of ruins clean and tidy sites from
which rubble has been carefully cleared. "Rotterdam has not yet recovered from its wounds, but
the scars are not too unsightly," my friends in Rotterdam say, with a smile. Yet wounds like
these take a long time to heal; a town can be destroyed in a few hours, but takes a
decade or more to rebuild.
And now I am back in the centre of the city, walking down the Coolsingelthe
"Champs-Elysées" of Rotterdam. It looks futuristic with its fountains, striking statues,
parks, large new buildings and houses, its model shops and its glittering cinemas
*
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
MIRACLE AT
ROTTERDAM
(Continued)
ingenious combinations of glass, aluminium, stucco and
lights. The crowds surge and hurry along, and every¬
where there is a smell of roasting coffee, petrol and
freshly laid cement.
At the liberation, on May 5, 1945, more than 20,000 of
Rotterdam's citizens had been killed by the Nazis. Nearly
800 of these perished in the bombing of May, 1940.
As a result of the raid 11,000 buildings were destroyed,
and 25,000 families, or 80,000 people were left homeless.
Altogether, 2,393 shops, 1,500 offices, 1,212 factories and
mills, 675 warehouses, 526 restaurants and cafés, 184
garages, 69 schools, 21 churches, 12 cinemas, 6 concert
halls, 4 hospitals, the 4 stations, 2 theatres and 2 museums
were reduced to ashes. Over- an area bf 642 acres
everything was reduced to dust. There was nothing left
of the centre of the city or of the old harbour, so dear to
novelists of the sea, from Conrad to Cendrars.
On that tragic May 14, Rotterdam was set on fire by
incendiary bombs. High explosive bombs had already
destroyed the water mains and the firemen were unable
to stop the blaze from spreading. Rotterdam burned for
forty days and forty nights. When the last fire had
burned itself out there were over 6,000 million cubic feet
of rubble to be cleared away.
In the ensuing weeks and months, workmen had to dig
out of the ground, like so many stumps of decayed teeth,
160,000 foundation piles, of a total length of 1,240 miles
as far as from London to Moscow. (The soil in Rotterdam
is so loose and damp that buildings have to be set on a
foundation of piles.)
14
Mijnheer W.G. Witteveen, the chief architect of Rotter¬
dam, found a room in the municipal library, which was
still standing, and began to work feverishly on a plan
for the rebuilding. Though no rebuilding was permitted
during the occupation. The famous Witteveen plan
became a kind of a symbol and never was a secret so well
and yet so badly kept. The whole town knew of it ; and
the thought of the garden-cities and skyscrapers to be,
made destruction, hunger and fear seem less terrible.
I do not know how much of the Witteveen plan there
is in the Rotterdam of today. I have watched the city
recover; and, every time I have come back, there has been
still more feverish activity, with scaffolding everywhere
and the suburbs spreading outwards in all directions, so
that it gives the impression of a new city "sprung up
overnight," rather than an old city rebuilt.
All I know is that in July 1959, Rotterdam is one
of the most impressive cities in the West. From the
top of the Groothandelsgebowu), one of the biggest
commercial buildings in the world (it has 11 storeys and
is 720 feet long and 280 wide), you can see that a master
plan has been followed. In the background is the
harbour, with its stately lines of ships anchored at the
docks, its forest of cranes, hoists and oil-cracking towers
(the native of Rotterdam tends to think first of the
harbour and then of the city beside it). And from the
harbour to the polders delimiting the city to the north,
south and east, the 1,980 acres of this town of 750,000
souls is divided up into broad avenues, huge squares and
compact blocks of modern houses with green spaces
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courrier. July-August 1959
between them. (Almost 70% of the area of Rotterdam
consists of open spaces)
This is architecture on a humanistic level, architecture
to the measure of man, resisting the temptation to build
on a colossal scale and yet not infected by the nostalgic
conservatism which thinks it sacrilege to touch what is
old, even though it be a slum.
On the "'CooLsingeF' is the massive, Mycenaean cube of
the '"Bijenkorf", a department store designed by A Elzas,
of the Netherlands, Marcel Breuer, of the U.S.A., (one of
the three architects who planned the new Unesco Head¬
quarters building) and another American, Daniel Schwartz-
man. At every turn you find a masterpiece of modern
art a fresco by Louis Van Roode on the wall of the
post-office; a bronze by Marino Marini, taut as a bow
on the "Zuidplein"; in the station hall a sinister-looking
rock with the beauty of a black diamond, carved by
Umberto Mastroianni; an animal group by Anne Grim-
dalen in front of the Town Hall ; and of course Zadkine's
touching statue, symbolizing the desecration and resur¬
gence of the city.
Rotterdam has opened its doors to a "'League of
Nations" of architects, decorators and sculptors. From all
over the world they have come, and have created here a
universal idiom for the cities of the XXIst century. It is
a triumph of internationalism, in both mind and heart.
It is a triumph of understanding and international co¬
operation, in this great seaport opening onto adventure
the wide world over, and teaches the sceptical the lesson
that miracles can be worked by determination.
CITY OF AIR,
LIGHT & WIDE
OPEN SPACES
The new Rotterdam which has risen from the ashes of
war is a city of air, light and wide open spaces. In
the heart of town, shown in this panoramic view, seventy
per cent of the total area has been reserved for open
spaces, compared with some 45% in the pre-war city.
Though the area available for building sites has been
nearly halved, the erection of taller buildingsmade
possible by new, wider roadsand a more rational use
of space, has kept the building volume virtually un¬
changed. In this photo, taken in 1957, work was still
being carried out on the Central Station (left) and on
the Post Office building (left, background). Completed
station is seen in photo, opposite page. Other Important
buildings visible in rooftop view of Rotterdam: old town
hall with its tower and new 14-storey blocks of flats. In
planning urbanization, city authorities kept area on right
of photo clear for future development. New projects In¬
clude a hotel, a vast office building and a concert hall.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
ROTTERDAM (Cont'd)
SYMPHONY
OF ART AND
ARCHITECTURE
A symphony in concrete, glass and stone, the new office
buildings and appartment houses of Rotterdam glisten in the
afternoon sun. The Rotterdam of today can truly be said
to be both beautiful and functional for its architects have
added to the basic utilitarianism of their designs the varied
works of decorators, sculptors and other artists of different
schools. The whole destroyed area of Rotterdam was requi¬
sitioned by the municipality to make a centralized planning
scheme. Former property owners were given options on new
building sites, but could claim compensation only if they used
the full amount for rebuilding. The result has been a rational
growth of shops and buildings (left and below left). Under¬
neath the great blocks of flats are a variety of small shops
which have brought the shopping public back again to the
heart of Rotterdam. Amid all these transformations, those
who died in the holocaust of May 1940 and throughout the
war years are not forgotten. In the Stadhuisplein now stands
a memorial to the victims of wara group of massively-hewn
figures by the sculptor Mari Andriessen (right and below).
I6
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courrier. July-August 1959
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
ROTTERDAM (Cont'd)
T IS REBOR
AS THE C I T
RISES A G A I
art which decorate the streets and squares of Rotterdam
are a triumph of international co-operation, coming as they do.from the hands of
artists of many lands. Many of these works have been erected as testimonies to
Rotterdam's destruction and suffering. In the Zuidplein» which is destined to
become the new cultural centre of south Rotterdam, stands "II Grande Miracolo"
(left) a bronze by the Italian sculptor Marino Marini, in honour of Rotterdam's
war victims. Centre, a group of bear cubs at playthe work ofAnne Grimalden of
MIBiaiMMIIWIHMgai
The Unesco Courrier. July-August 1959
the Netherlands. In the background is the City Hall with its tall towerone of the
few buildings which escaped complete destruction in the bombardment of 1940.
Since the city was reconstructed this building has been thrown into new-found
prominence by the widening of the pavement in front of it and the construction of a
new square opening in the Coolsingel Boulevard. Further along this sweep¬
ing boulevard is a small yet poignant reminder to those who pass of the city's
past ordealsthe statue of a mother shielding a child as walls crumble around her.
HI MliWIIIIWIIII
Ml Hi \
.<** m :
" «ÉPÎ
P 1*1
,;
18 19
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
ROTTERDAM (Cont'd)
**Í. ...
HARBOUR FLANKED
BY A CITY
The people of Rotterdam tend to think of their town as "a port surrounded
by a city", for Rotterdam is the Netherland's chief port and the second largest
in the world. Extensively damaged in 1944, it was back in working order only
six months after VE Day. Photo, above, shows the River Maas. An embank¬
ment and a broad boulevard have been laid out and a new inland shipping
lane extends right to the city centre. Monument at right, "The Bow" is for
war victims of the merchant navy. Below, two views of central Rotterdam.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courrier. July-August 1959
ELECTRONIC TRANSLATORS WITH
BUILT-IN DICTIONARIES
by Emile Delavenay
The idea that an electronic machine should be able
to do automatically all or part of a translator's
consult a dictionary or translate a written
text from one language into another may seem fantastic
at first sight.
Yet the idea has been gaining ground ever since it
was first put forward by an Englishman, A.D. Booth, in
1946 ; and today the goal is almost in sight for the many
British, American and Soviet scientists who have been
working on this problem for the past twelve years.
Automatic digital computers were invented to carry out
at high speed sequences of arithmetic operations which
would have been too time-consuming for human beings
and which involved too great a risk of error. They have
proved that they can solve problems of industrial and
business management which, in addition to automatic
computing, call for certain logical decisions.
In both cases scientific calculation and business
management (of which operational research is one aspect)
the machine receives two typea| of information: nume¬
rical information in digital form, and alphabetical infor¬
mation i.e. words in current use fed in as letters of the
alphabet. It automatically converts both types of infor¬
mation into a code suited to the particular operations it
has to perform.
These include, for example, the logical identification of
a quantity or a word with its equivalent stored in an
electronic memory; automatic computation; the shifting
of partial results from one memory to another; the selec¬
tion of instructions depending on the type of result
obtained; and lastly, the "output" of the final result,
which may be in typewritten form. The most important
feature of these machines is their breath-taking speed:
some operations are performed in a millionth of a second.
Automatic translation could be envisaged as the follow¬
ing sequence of lightning operations without human inter¬
vention: feeding of a word into the machine, looking up
and identification of the word in the electronic dictionary,
simultaneous identification of the word's equivalent in
the second language, and finally typing of this equivalent.
The electronic dictionary is therefore a bilingual dic¬
tionary like those used for ordinary translating but
recorded in a magnetic memory.
This series of very simple operations is only suitable,
however, for words recorded in the dictionary in
the same form as they appear in the sentences i.e.
Invariable words and which, moreover, have only one
meaning. Special problems are raised by variable words,
by those having several different meanings, and also by
the word-order, and by idioms, or expressions whose
general sense is different from the sum of meanings
conveyed by the individual words.
In Britain, the United States, the TJ.S.S.R. and Japan,
research has therefore concentrated for a number of years
on the problems raised by the variable forms of words,
by syntax, idioms and words with multiple meanings.
Russian, English, German, French, Hungarian, Norwegian,
Arabic, Chinese and Japanese have been analyzed for the
purpose of reducing all the facts and rules of each lan¬
guage to algorithms, or numerical systems enabling the
machine to translate sentences from language A into
language B.
Highly complex programmes have been worked out
which may involve up to ten thousand logical operations
for the translation of a twenty-word sentence. Yet even
so, the speed of the machine is such that the process
is faster than ordinary translation. Just as the digital
computer consults tables of logarithms or of functions,
so the automatic translator will consult grammatical,
morphological or syntactical tables in addition to its
electronic dictionary. It scans tables of prepositions,
tenses of verbs, declensions or conjugations doing in fact
the same work as the translator has to do when deci¬
phering a text in a complex foreign language. These
tables and the dictionary are made up of series of digits
representing the algorithms of the input and output
languages.
Before the facts of language could be reduced to algo¬
rithms, it Was necessary to discover certain rules over¬
looked in the old type of grammar, because these grammar
books were written for thinking human beings and not
for unconscious machines which can only recognize explicit
signals.
Thus research to put translation on an automatic
basis is opening up new vistas for the linguist. It
is leading to various kinds of studies on "signalling"
systems of spoken and written language. Each language
is being studied scientifically, in the minutest detail, and
valid mechanical criteria are being discovered for the
understanding of sentences a field in which intuition
might Well have been thought the only possible guide.
The day of the translation machine is not far off,
but much still remains to be done. Electronic machines
can translate, but men have not yet learned to exploit
their amazing potential. It is now up to the linguists
those of today who can and must adapt themselves to
the new world of electronics, and those of to-morrow
who, with the help of machines, will extend the scope
of linguistics to cover all languages and all aspects of
language. For the linguistic research required to perfect
a translation machine is impossible without the aid of
ultra-rapid new machinery.
The future belongs to the linguists and mathematicians,
the "'programmers'", who can grasp the behaviour of words
in a sentence, as well as language statistics and the work¬
ing methods of computers. As in automatic computing
and in management by computer, the machine can only
perform automatic and repetitive operations. All the
creative work, the most important task, will devolve upon
man; he must use his imagination and judgement to
work out programmes which the machine will then per¬
form blindly and unconsciously.
For all sorts of reasons, scientific texts are the first
which can and should be submitted to the special analysis
required for automatic translation. Up till now, research
by American, British and Soviet scientists, has been con¬
cerned with texts dealing with mathematics, chemistry,
electronics and plant genetics. The need for scientific
translations is such in all countries that we cannot even
begin to solve this problem without the help of machines.
But will machines ever be able to translate "literary"
texts? The more optimistic research workers are begin¬
ning to hope so, and already have notions of the way to
set about it. When this day comes, when all prose works
can be translated automatically at scarcely believable
speeds (there is talk of 20,000 Words an hour), the peoples
of the world will truly be able to learn about one another
and appreciate each other's scientific and literary riches.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
»V
<*l/SR2
A DESERT IN
THE HEART
OF LONDON
COI London
-Í 1
by Daniel Behrman
UNATIONS
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
C.O.I. London
There may be a "pea-soup" fog or a sharp frost outside, but at the
Anti-Locust Research Centre in the heart of London, a hot desert
exists all year round. Here a million locusts are bred annually and their
behaviour studied to help the world fight against locust invasions.
Left, locusts are bred in the laboratory where they are induced to lay
their eggs in aluminium tubes. Eggs are about the size of a wheat seed,
laid in batches of 40 to 100 in moist sand in a pencil-shaped burrow.
A glue-like substance holds them and the sand grains together (below).
Larger cages at laboratory (above) hold adult locusts, fed on fresh grass
and bran. Large electric light bulb replaces sun; sticks, for climbing
and to fly from, give recreation. Full generation takes three months.
UNATIONS
The Unesco Courrier. July-August 1959
JcrsT the other day, an alert English lady with an interest
in zoology breathlessly brought a schistocerca gregaria
Into a London police station.
"It's a desert locust," she told the sergeant on duty,
"I found it in Hyde Park."
When news of the discovery reached the Anti-Locust
Research Centre in London, the man who is perhaps the
world's leading authority on locusts, Dr. B.P. Uvarov,
merely remarked:
"Why not? We raise a million desert locusts a year
across the road from Hyde Park . . . and some of them are
bound to get away."
Dr. Uvarov is not worried' because he knows they do so at
their own risk. For the desert locust does not stand a
chance of surviving in the English climate. Unfortunately,
in an area covering no less than 11,000,000 square miles of
the earth's surface, it not only survives but flourishes to
the point where it is an epidemic plague and such a
plague is now afflicting much of Africa and Asia.
Desert locusts in swarms have been known to darken
the sky as far west as the Canary Islands in the Atlantic
Ocean and as far east as Assam. They ravage North and
East Africa and even fan out south to Tanganyika and
northward to Spain and Portugal. Every year, the Anti-
Locust Research Centre estimates, they do £30,000,000
worth of damage to cash crops in some 65 countries. No
estimate, however, can be made of the harvest of suffering
and starvation they sow in the arid and semi- arid belts
of Africa and Asia.
The Anti-Locust Research Centre, operated by the
British Government, has been in existence for fifteen
years, but Dr. Uvarov has spent most of his life with
locusts. In his office overlooking Hyde Park, Dr. Uvarov
stated the centre's objective in few and clear words:
"We want to find out what conditions produce the initial
swarms which cause all the trouble and then, if possible,
we want to find out if these conditions can be changed
economically."
Africa freed from two plagues
When Dr. Uvarov first began to study locusts (they
interested him even as a small boy), there were
three main species plaguing Asia and Africa: the
red locust, the migratory locust and the desert locust. In
1929, a locust invasion of the Middle East led to the birth
of the predecessor of the present-day research centre.
Then, it was only Dr. Uvarov and an assistant.
But, even thirty years ago, Dr. Uvarov was already
preaching that "locusts ignore boundaries" and the scope
of his work quickly became international. He and his
collaborators attacked the problem from all sides: bio¬
logical, geographical, physiological and meteorological.
It was the most unglamorous side of the job the
patient collecting of locust reports, and plotting them on
mapswhich led to their first victory. Once records
covering a sufficiently long period had been analyzed
geographically (evidence of the desert locust goes back
more than 2,000 years), they showed that swarms of the
migratory locust started in what is now the Sudan Re¬
public and that the red locust swarms originated in
Tanganyika and Northern Rhodesia.
This methodical spadework in London led to the
establishment of the International African Migratory
Locust Organization and the International Red Locust
Control Service which concentrate on preventing locusts
from swarming in these regions. The result is that Africa
has been free of red and migratory locust plagues for the
past fifteen years, though Dr. Uvarov refuses to claim at
present that this is definitive.
The desert locust is a much harder nut to crack. It is
a nomad, like all the other creatures adapted to survival
in the desert, and it travels in giant leaps. Breeding
places of successive generations may be as much as 1,000
miles apart.
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
A DESERT IN THE HEART OF LONDON
(Continued)
An ecological survey of its breeding places is now being
conducted by two scientists, George Popov of England and
Charles Rossetti of Switzerland, financed jointly by FAO
and Unesco (Unesco's contribution is part of its major
project on scientific research to aid arid lands).
The job is an enormous one: last year, the two men
visited Sudan, Chad and Ethiopia and this year are
working in Mauritania, the Sudan Republic (formerly
French Sudan) and Niger. This is a long-term study of
the conditions under ¡which desert locusts breed.
In London, one huge room of the centre is devoted
mainly to keeping track of the desert locust's movements.
In this geographical service as well as in every other
section of the centre, basic and applied research . are
happily married.
Each year the centre's geographers receive thousands of
reports of locust movements which are invaluable to the
basic research task of trying to pin down the insect's
principal breeding areas. At the same time, these reports
form the raw material which goes into the monthly
bulletins of the International Desert Locust Information
Service operated by the centre and sponsored by. FAO.
For example, one morning, a short while ago, a sheaf
of cables and letters was awaiting Miss Zean Waloff, who
is in charge of this service :
"About half dozen swarms entering Pakistan from west.
Locuswar."
"Eritrea no swarms reported hopper infestation Arkiko
Wangabo now controlled. Locust Asmara."
Miss Waloff turned to a huge map covering one end of
the room, but still not large enough to chart all the
wanderings of the desert locust which has even been seen
1,200 miles out in the Atlantic Ocean.
"The situation is serious this year, she explained, there
has been spring breeding in northern and northwest
Africa from Morocco to Libya. We knew about heavy
swarms in Arabia and the Middle East and now some are
reported in Pakistan."
'Your country is being invaded'
On the basis of this information, the anti-locust
centre publishes forecasts in its monthly bulletin.
If the situation is dangerous, special warnings are
issued. The last one, in October 1958, reported heavy
breeding in the Sudan, northern Ethiopia, Niger and
Mauritania and predicted serious breeding early this year.
In emergencies, the centre uses "'signals" by cable or
even telephone. One such "signal" involved ringing up
an ambassador in London to inform him that locusts
were headed for his country from across the border of
another country with which his capital had no diplomatic
relations.
Locusts pay no attention to politics.
The Anti-Locust Research Centre in London is now
directed by Dr. T.H.C. Taylor with Dr. Uvarov, his
predecessor, in retirement, as a highly active consultant.
A few doors away from Dr. Uvarov's office is a locust-
breeding laboratory known to experts the world over. The
locusts are either used for experimental purposes on the
spot or are shipped out to universities and research
institutes.
This is another case of basic and applied research going
hand-in-hand. Locust-raising here is mass production at
the rate of a million eggs and 50,000 adult locusts a year.
In England alone, locusts are shipped (by ordinary post)
to seventy scientists conducting research and they go to
five universities in continental Europe as well.
BABIES BY THE THOUSAND are produced daily in the Anti-Locust
Research Centre and raised to adulthood. Fully-grown insects are then
shipped to scientists in England and to universities in continental Europe. Even
laboratories in Africa order supplies when locusts are "out of season" there.
C.O.I. London
'MERRY-GO-ROUND' for locusts used at London Research Centre. When
the insects find themselves suspended in air, they begin to fly and turn
the wire frame "roundabout". In this way, some estimate of the
speed and duration of the flight of which they are capable can be made.
CONT'D ON PAGE 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courrier. July-August 1959
From "Climatology and Microclimatology", Unesco, 1958
INVASION ZONE of desert locust, divided into two parts covering
I I million square miles of Africa and Asia, shows size of the problem.
Light shaded area shows total invasion area; central dark zone covers
region where breeding or swarms occur at least one year in two.
HOPPERS ON THE MARCH
Life cycle of the locust consists of three stages: egg, hopper and adult.
Locusts breed in the desert, yet lay their eggs only after rain. To develop,
the eggs must absorb more than their weight in water. If not in contact
with water during the incubation period (two weeks) the eggs die.
During the hopper stage, lasting 5 to 6 weeks, the young locusts are
unable to fly. They come together in bands of thousands, millions or
even hundreds of millions and begin to march in search of green food,
again only to be found in desert areas after rain. Excessive heat or
dryness may kill the hoppers. For a few days after becoming adults the
locust swarms take short daily flights to test their wings, prolonging
these flights until a true migration starts. The hopper stage is the most
vulnerable to attack by ground bait and aircraft spraying. Photo shows
part of a vast army of hoppers on the march in a wheat field near
Baghdad, stopped by an irrigation ditch too broad for them to cross.
FAO-Peter Collins
INT'L AIR SQUADRON
IN ANTI-LOCUST WAR
An international anti-locust aircraft squadron
may soon join scientists on the ground in a
stepped-up attack on desert locust invasions.
The creation of the aircraft unit has been
proposed by the Food and Agriculture Organiza¬
tion of the U.N. following impressive results
achieved by aircraft in the past few years. In
1957, for example, 171 aeroplanes and helicopters
were used in operations against the desert locust
in 23 countries, and proved both far more
economical and more effective than ground
techniques.
FAO reports that aircraft spraying of only 60
gallons of the pesticide dlazinon killed an
estimated 180 million adult locusts during one
invasion. Air operations in Morocco this year
successfully sprayed swarms of locusts at about
half the price of traditional ground methods
using, bran as poisoned bait. Similar results
have been achieved in Pakistan and Iran.
Aircraft have been found to be the only way to
determine the number and size of swarms during
invasions. Aircraft have regularly sighted swarms
at distances of up to 100 kilometres, and have
been effective in searching areas 9,000 square
kilometres in size.
The international anti-locust aircraft squadron
would be made up of specially equipped planes
belonging to individual nations. When an inva¬
sion alert sounded the squadron Would be united
in a concentrated attack on the threatened or
infested area.
One of the latest battles in the war against the
desert locusts is now taking place in Jordan. The
locust invasion has built up over the past few
weeks and has now reached serious proportions.
The swarms have laid eggs across 50,000 hectares
of cultivated land and the breeding area is still
increasing. A shortage of- poisoned bran has
heightened the crisis. Turkey, Lebanon and the
Syrian Region of the United Arab Republic have
responded to an FAO appeal and are coming to
Jordan's aid.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
2
6
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courrier. July-August 1959
They came
They saw
They conquered
Photos Anti-Locust Research Centre, London
Devastation caused by the desert locust is
vividly illustrated in these three photographs.
Top, healthy orange grove in the Souss Valley
(Morocco) before a locust swarm spotted it.
Centre, locusts form vast cloud blotting out
trees and landscape as they swoop down on
target. Bottom, orange grove stripped clean
and soil nibbled bare after passage of marau¬
ders. A single swarm may range 3,000 miles
and may number as many as 1 ,000 million
locusts. In 1954 remnants of a desert locust
swarm from Africa reached the British Isles
after a flight of more than 1,500 miles over
the open seas. A single locust weighs only a
tenth of an ounce but a swarm can weigh
20,000 tons and must eat its weight in green
food daily. Locust clouds leave not only ruin
and despair in their trail but further poten¬
tial scourges, for if the locust meets favour¬
able weather conditions it breeds and lays eggs
as it moves alongand another swarm is born.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
-N
Photo André Lestage
IS THE OCEAN IN DANGER?
by Nicolas Gorsky
Member of the U.S.S.R, Geographical Society
The amount of radio-active substances dissolved in the
waters of the oceans and seas is infinitesimal. The
rocks forming the Earth's crust contain a hundred
times as much radio-active potassium as sea water and
thousands of times more uranium. The radio-activity of
the sediment at the bottom of the ocean is somewhat
higher than that of the water above it. The concentration
of radium in the iron-manganese concretions that form
at the bottom of oceans and seas is relatively high, even
higher than in the underlying sediment, but the mysterious
source from which they derive radium has not been
definitely established.
28
Manganese and radium are to a certain degree related
and manganese apparently has the ability to extract
radium from the sediment; it is a fact that there is
always more radium on the bottom side of the concretion.
Radio-active substances in the sediment are probably
fission products of uranium, washed into the sea in solu¬
tion by the rivers.
What must be borne in mind is that the highly
diversified plant and animal life of the seas and oceans
is accustomed to a very low concentration of radio-active
substances. It is precisely from this quarter that a grave
danger has arisen.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
It has not yet been established what doses of radio¬
activity are innocuous for marine plants and animals. It
is only known that fishes concentrate phosphorus and
zinc in their bodies, while molluscs and crustaceans
concentrate calcium, strontium and a number of other
elements included in radio-active fission products.
Two days after atomic bomb tests at Bikini atoll, the
radio-activity of the upper layer of water increased a
million times over the normal. Four months later the
radio-activity of the water 1,500 miles away was three
times greater than the normal. In thirteen months the
contaminated water had spread over an area of over one
million square miles. The artificially caused radio-activity
had decreased by this time until it was only one-fifth
higher than the normal but it could easily be detected
2,500 miles away from the source.
How old are the deepest waters ?
It is interesting to note the manner in which this radio¬
activity was dispersed through the ocean. Three long
strips of high radio-activity were discovered: one
stretched westward from the site of the explosion along
the North Equatorial current, a second dipped aWay from
the first to the southwest, while a third extended east¬
ward in a direction opposite to that of the Equatorial
current.
In the first and second strips, equal radio-activity was
found at a distance of 2,000 and 1,000 miles from the
atoll; in the third, the radio-activity at a distance of 750
miles was three times higher. In the case of the first strip
the ocean current played the major role; the second and
third strips are assumed to have been formed by radio¬
active dust borne by air-currents. According to Japanese
scientists, the concentration of radio-active elements in
the water after the explosion was considerably higher than
the safety limit.
The immediate and urgent task confronting science is
to study the dispersion of radio-active fission products,
and their effect on marine life, both plant and animal.
Due to the rapid development of the atomic industry the
problem of safely disposing of radio-active waste-products
has become urgent. In Britain, radio-active wastes are
in some places drained by pipes into the Irish Sea, while
at Oak Ridge in the United States they are drained into
the Tennessee River system. Some wastes in the United
States are buried in the ground or sunk in the deep sea
in special containers.
The sea water, however, will very quickly eat through
the walls of these containers and dissolve their dangerous
The Utiesco Courrier. July-August 1959
contents. Then, too, if scores, or it may be hundreds, of
containers with their sinister contents are being thrown
into the sea today, the number will rise to tens or even
hundreds of thousands in the near future.
There are deep places or trenches in the oceans,
particularly the Pacific. The average depth of the ocean
is about two and a half miles, but in these depressions
it reaches between four and five miles and in places up
to seven miles. Proposals are being made to use these
depressions as dumping-grounds for radio-active wastes.
This confronts oceanographers with the problem of
determining the age of the waters in the ocean depths.
Once purely theoretical, the question has now come to
have great practical significance. How long will it take
radio-active substances dissolved by the water at the
ocean bottom to rise to the surface? Will the process of
radio-active decay which is always at /work render them
innocuous before they reach the surface, or will they still
be sufficiently radio-active to poison the upper, productive
layers? It should be noted that the annual production of
the sea-fisheries (fish, crustaceans and molluscs) comes
to some twenty million tons, and that over half a million
boats are engaged in the industry.
There is not a gulf or sea that is not connected with
the oceans in a general system of water circulation. It is
impossible to localize or isolate the poisoning of sea water.
The map of the ocean currents on this page graphically
illustrates this unity.
Scientists hold widely differing views as to the time
required for the water at the ocean bottom to be renewed.
Wüst (Germany) has calculated that the cold, heavy
Antarctic waters, after descending to the depths of the
Weddell Sea, reach the equator in five years four months,
while Deacon (Britain) puts the figure at eighteen years.
At the same time Worthington (United States) holds that
the waters at the bottom of the Atlantic date back to
1810 when the climate became much colder, and have not
been renewed in the century and a half that has elapsed
since then.
The New Zealand oceanographers, Brodie and Burling,
have put the age of the Antarctic waters 150 miles to the
north of Scott Island at a depth of 8,500 feet at 2,500
years, and of the waters near Campbell Island at a depth
of 2,624 feet at 1,900 years. The New Zealanders used the
Carbon 14 method to determine the age of the water, but
others hold that there are a number of factors besides
time affecting Carbon 14, and accordingly that these
conclusions must be accepted with caution.
Oxygen miles down in the Pacific
THE OCEAN: AN INDIVISIBLE WHOLE. There is not a gulf or
sea that is not connected with the oceans in a general system of water
circulation (as map above shows).. In other words, the oceans and seas
are joined to form an indivisible wholethe World Ocean. It is impos¬
sible to isolate or localize the poisoning of sea water. When
radio-active substances are introduced into the ocean at any spot they
are dispersed for thousands of miles to contaminate an enormous area.
The Danish expedition on the Galatea and Soviet expe¬
ditions on the Vityaz found dissolved oxygen in
water from the very deepest Pacific trenches. It can
be confidently stated that water buried at the bottom of
the ocean for hundreds of years, let alone thousands, could
contain no oxygen. It would be consumed in a much
shorter time in various processes, both physico-chemical
(the oxidation of mineral substances) and biochemical
(the respiration of living organisms and the putrefaction
of dead ones) processes that are constantly at work at
the bottom of the ocean and in the water above.
The Danish and Soviet expeditions discovered various
forms of animal life at the bottom of the ocean trenches,
which had till then been thought to be void of life. These
animals included among others coelenterates, echiurides,
goloturians and bivalve molluscs. All these animals
consume oxygen continually and they would long since
have exhausted the supply in the water round them if
there were no currents.
What, then is the source, of the oxygen at depths of
up to seven miles? Up to now scientists have explained
the aeration of the bottom layers of the ocean as being a
consequence of the general circulation of the ocean
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
IS THE OCEAN
IN DANGER? (Continued)
water. In the Polar regions the cold, heavy water
submerges into the depths and slowly moves toward the
equator, bearing with it the oxygen dissolved at the
surface. But it takes scores of years for it to reach the
equator. The dissolved oxygen could hardly be preserved
for such ia lengthy period that is the weak place in the
hypothesis.
Some oceanographers consider that oxygen is carried to
the bottom of ocean trenches by turbidity currents. This
is the term applied to the avalanches and landslides on
the slopes surrounding the depressions. These are due to
earthquakes or other causes, and as they plunge to the
bottom of the depressions they carry along with them
large volumes of water saturated with oxygen. But
turbidity currents are only chance occurrences. In the
intervals between them life at the bottom of the de¬
pressions should be extinguished for want of oxygen. This,
however, has not happened during the millions of years
that the ocean and its trenches have been in existence.
Evidently the oxygen must penetrate to the depths of the
ocean in some other way.
Professor N.N. Zubov, the Soviet oceanographer, recently
suggested a new and more plausible hypothesis.
It seems that when volumes of sea water of different
temperature are mixed, the density of the mixture is
greater than either of the components. Being heavier
than the surrounding water, it descends to the lower layers
of the ocean carrying dissolved oxygen with it.
Perpetual motion in deep places
The Water in the ocean is not homogeneous; its tempe¬
rature varies both vertically and horizontally. What
is more, the water in the ocean is continually in mo¬
tion, neighbouring layers often moving in different direc¬
tions. In this way Water of different temperatures is being
constantly mixed and is sinking as it becomes heavier.
An equivalent volume of lighter water is displaced and
rises to the surface. This eternal process extends to all
the depth of the ocean, apparently penetrating to the
bottom of the trenches.
We do not know as yet how long it takes surface water
to descend to the ocean bottom, but evidently its movement
is relatively rapid since it retains dissolved oxygen.
Among the many depressions studied by this year's Soviet
expedition on the Vityaz was the Tonga trench, investigat¬
ed six years ago by the Danish expedition on the Galatea.
Measurements made this year igave a difference of 0.2° in
the temperature of the water.
When one takes into consideration the great accuracy
of the deep-water thermometers used by oceanographers,
one realises that this is a significant deviation indicating
the existence of what is probably a very slow but
continuous exchange of water between the bottom, inter¬
mediate, and surface layers of the ocean, even in the
regions of the deepest depressions.
The vertical circulation .Which is a consequence of the
mixing of the sea water and its increase in density, as
described by Professor Zubov, ventilates the deep layers
of the ocean and also raises to the surface a layer rich
in nutrient phosphates and nitrates, forming a basis for
abundant life. But this process will bring death if
pernicious radio-active solutions from the waste-products
of the atomic industry accumulate in the ocean depths.
In this connexion another phenomenon occurring in the
oceans and seas should be mentioned what is known as
upwelling. Due to winds, currents or the relief of the
ocean bed, deep, cold layers of water, rich in nutrient salts,
30
Photos André Lestage
rise to the surface in some regions along the continental
slope or along submerged banks. This phenomenon is
well known along the Atlantic coast of North America, the
California coast and the Western coast of South America
and Africa. The regions where upwelling occurs are
exceptionally rich in plant and animal life, including fish.
If the water rising to the surface should be contaminated
with substances dissolved out of radio-active wastes it iwill
mean the end of the highly productive fisheries in these
regions.
The oceans and seas are joined to form an indivisible
whole the World Ocean. No open part can be considered
isolated and cannot belong to any one country. Radio¬
active substances introduced into the ocean at any spot
will.be dispersed for thousands of miles and will conta¬
minate an area of millions of square miles. For that
reason, all questions concerning the contamination of the
ocean by radio-active substances, irrespective of their
origin or purpose, just as investigations into the effect of
radio-active substances on marine life, acquire in¬
ternational significance and should be solved through
friendly, concerted international scientific co-operation.
The rate at Iwhich the atomic industry is developing
shows that it is necessary to set about the study of this
problem immediately. Uncontrolled contamination of the
oceans and seas can lead to irreparable catastrophe
within ten to twenty years. The Ocean, that great and
inexhaustible source of food for man must be protected.
The Ocean is in danger.
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courrier. July-August 1959
A DESERT IN THE
HEART OF LONDON
(Continued from page 24)
THE GRASSHOPPER & THE LOCUST:
DR. JEKYLL & MR. HYDE OF INSECTS
"We have a budget of only £70,000 a year," Dr. Uvarov
pointed out. "If we tried to do everything ourselves we
would get nothing done. So we encourage others to help
us by supplying them with research grants and raw
material that is, locusts."
With a ¿twinkle in his eye, he added: "Why we even send
locusts to laboratories in Rhodesia and Ghana it's more
practical to write to us than to try to catch them out-of-
season.
In the laboratory, under the direction of Mr. Philip
Hunter-Jones, desert locusts are raised under conditions
as close to normal environment as possible. They are
bred in constant-temperature rooms where the ther¬
mometer always stands at 29 degrees C, laying their eggs
in small tubes of moist sand. They are fed on succulent
grass which often raises a food supply problem in the
middle of an English winter.
The desert locust needs moist sand to lay its eggs and
this characteristic is worrying scientists as they watch
the spread of irrigation in semi-arid lands. In certain
cases, and at great expense, man seems to be unwittingly
creating new locust breeding grounds.
Locusts' 'rain-sense' myth exploded
With the help of its. laboratory and the world's
biggest library on locusts, the centre has been able
to explode a number of myths concerning the
desert locust and is now exploring certain characteristics
of this insect which may hold the key to its ultimate
control.
Dr. R.C. Rainey, a "biometeorologist" (that is, a biologist
and meteorologist) is one of the men responsible for
shattering some of the myths. His studies both in East
Africa and at the centre have explained much of what
used to be called "the psychology of the locust."
Popular belief once held (and often still does) that
desert locusts move with unvarying intent and purpose,
and that they are even capable of sensing rain from a
distance in the desert, swarming down at the right mo¬
ment to eat the plants it produces.
But studies of swarms tooth from the air and with
cameras on the ground show that locusts consistently
move downwind at a speed equal to or less than the speed
of the wind (their own flying speed is from 10 to 12
m.p.h.).
Actually, Dr. (Rainey stated, the individual locusts fly in
all directions, making it impossible for a man on the
ground to tell in which way the swarm as a whole is
moving. The swarm's course is exactly like that of an
aeroplane pilot who is lost: he flies around in circles but
his position changes because he is drifting with the wind.
This downwind movement often takes the locusts into
what meteorologists call "areas of convergent wind flow"
which can produce rain in arid regions. That, in Dr.
Rainey's opinion, is how desert locusts "find" rain.
According to another old belief, locust swarms fly when
the barometer drops, but the centre's research has shown
that atmospheric pressure has nothing to do with flight.
"The locust can only take off when its muscles are warm,"
Dr. Rainey explained. "At a temperature of about 25
degrees C. (77 degrees F.), its 'engine' is warmed up for
flight. The atmospheric pressure often drops in arid
regions when temperature rises and that is why people
once thought the barometer had something to do with the
flying of swarms."
Meteorology has also provided the answer to the
astonishing heights reached by desert locusts. Aircraft
have sighted them flying at 10,000 feet and some have
been seen on mountain passes 20,000 feet above sea level.
In this case it is the powerful convection currents from
the desert which send them spiralling upward.
As for the biological side of biometeorology, Dr. Rainey
is studying the insecticides used against the desert locust.
These insecticides must be powerful enough to kill tons
and tons of locusts and yet at the same time do no harm
to plant and other animal life.
Insecticides involve the study of the physiology of the
locust one of the most fascinating aspects of the London
centre. It is carried out under Dr. Peter T. Haskell, a
young scientist who works in a room filled with electronic
apparatus capable of measuring such things as the smell,
eyesight and hearing of a locust. There is even a "wind
tunnel" for flight-testing.
Dr. Haskell and Mr. Hunter-Jones are attacking different
aspects of the problem of why desert locusts swarm. This
is one of the most puzzling metamorphoses of nature. If
left alone, the species is an ordinary green grasshopper.
But, in a crowd the relatively inoffensive grasshopper
becomes the gregarious, predatory desert locust. Its
colour turns to yellow and black, its wings lengthen and
its head thickens.
No differences explaining this Jekyll-and-Hyde conduct
can be detected when a locust and a grasshopper are
dissected and examined under a microscope. Dr. Haskell
suspects that there must be some aspects of the desert
locust's central nervous system which causes it to seek the
company of other locusts and to form a havoc-making
swarm.
In his research, he uses some rather amazing devices.
One, for example, which could be called a locust-tickler,
was developed by Dr. Peggy E. Ellis, a member of the
centre Working at Oxford. It consists of a jam-jar with
an electrically driven wheel bearing rope fibres turning
inside it. The fibres stimulate the tactile organs of a
young locust in the hopper stage and, so far, the
experiments show that exciting its sense of touch seems
to make it more willing to seek the company of other
locusts.
Infra-red lamps warm the desert
DR. Haskell also ¡rules the only artificial desert in
London. It is a flat wooden tray about ten feet
square with a sand floor an inch thick. Two infra¬
red lamps beat down through its glass roof while wind is
created by an electric fan. This artificial desert has
already demonstrated that young hoppers are quite
capable of finding grass by their sense of smell. It also
shows that they congregate in still air and disperse in
a wind.
With all these weapons, the centre has hopes of solving
the desert locust problem but not overnight. Basic
research must first give science the explanation of the
dreaded insect's life before control measures can be taken.
Dr. Uvarov is cheered by a precedent. A team from the
Anti-Locust Centre spent five years in Cyprus studying
the ' so-called Moroccan locust. They learned that the
insect flourished on overgrazed patchy terrain because it
needs bare soil to lay its eggs and grass for food and
shelter. On this basis, the centre was able to recommend
a moderate control of grazing to eliminate the locust's
grassless breeding grounds.
"The locust will be there but it will not swarm," said
Dr. Uvarov. "And that is what we are trying to do with
the desert locust as well. We will succeed if we have the
time. Even if we had unlimited money and equipment at
our disposal, we would still need time. There are no
shortcuts in science."
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
NEGRO DANCES & CUSTOMS
Sir,
I want to make a humble protest
against so much lauding of the Negro
races. They have great values, and must
be treated with equal opportunities and
I know we must do them justice in
every way. But to pretend to see
spiritual values in all their dances and
in some of their revolting habits and
customs is going too far.
E. Piclon-Tubervill
Cheltenham, England
BREAKING LANGUAGE BARRIERS
Sir,
...Language still continues to be the
chief barrier standing in the way of the
peoples of the world coming together.
May I, therefore, suggest that The
Unesco Courier give greater attention
to the major languages of the world?
Articles to stimulate interest in the
study of languages should be published
in every issue of this magazine. Lin¬
guistic habits and customs, parallels and
peculiarities, famous books from diffe¬
rent languages and similar subjects
would go a long way in bringing closer
the nations of the world.
D. Viswanadha Babu
Vlzianagram, Andhra, India
THE RIGHT APPROACH
Sir,
I am a student, and although I only
recently made my first acquaintance
with The Unesco Courier it has
already added to my understanding of
many things. I was especially pleased
with the issues devoted to the Inter¬
national Geophysical Year and to the
Brussels World Fair. I also enjoyed
those telling about the drawings of
famous writers, the archaeological find¬
ings in Mexico, and the ancient art
of Ceylon.
Your publication offers much to
those interested in art and ethnology.
I disagree with those readers who have
asked you to publish more "specialized"
and "scholarly" articles. I believe the
purpose of the magazine is best served
by the type of article it now prints. I
find the illustrations excellent and should
like more of them they liven up the
text.
S.V. Lashin
Krasnodar, U.S.S.R.
INTEREST REVIVED
Sir,
May I congratulate you on the De¬
cember 1958 issue of The Unesco
Courier. I must say that my interest
in the magazine had waned because for
a few months, it was rather boring to
read save for an odd article. Anyway
the December 1958 issue has ended
with a more appetizing flavour... Spe¬
cial mention must be made of articles
re "The Orient Today and Yesterday,"
"All Men are Brothers" and "The
World is Sick of Hatred." I certainly
enjoyed reading them.
Olga M. Stephens
London, England
SCIENCE HAS A PURPOSE
Sir,
I was very much interested in the
speech made by Bertrand Russell on re¬
ceiving the Kalinga Prize for 1957 (Feb¬
ruary 1958 issue), but I beg to differ
with Russell when he says that "At pre¬
sent, scientific technique advances like an
army of tanks that have lost their
drivers, blindly, ruthlessly, without goal
or purpose/' That is not so. There
is both a goal and a definite plan for
achieving it. It seems to me that if
nature, "working" without a plan and in
a laboratory as imperfect as our planet,
has been able through countless num¬
bers of experiments (as Darwin has
pointed out) to produce as complicated
a mechanism as the human brain, hu¬
man beings armed with plans and the
latest achievements of science will be
able to produce a life of plenty for all
peoples on the earth.
A. Khizh
Moscow, U.S.S.R.
EACH ONE REACH MANY
Sir,
I read with interest your appeal for
new readers in the June issue of The
Unesco Courier. Please find enclosed
a cheque for £4.0.0 together with the
names of eight new subscribers. I find
great satisfaction in doing this, knowing
that perhaps I am contributing to foster
understanding among people and I
would like to continue to increase the
number of readers.
A. Martinez
Chelmsford, England
ART & ABNORMALITY
Sir,
The May number of The Unesco
Courier is extremely interesting. The
care and cure of mental patients is an
urgent need, and the progress made is
impressive.
However, one sometimes wonders if
the psychiatrists are not creating their
own patients. We have learnt to
accept maladjustment as the new ex¬
planation for bad behaviour, and we
struggle to comprehend the jargon of
psychiatry. But the explanation given
of the child's drawing on the back cover
is straining credulity too far. The
turnip-headed little creature on a tight¬
rope could surely have been drawn by
any normal child? One wonders what
this psychiatrist would have said of the
child who made a drawing of a poli¬
ceman, with blue helmet and tunic, and
bright yellow buttons, but no feet. Ob¬
viously a subconcious fear of the law
as symbolized by those slow, sinister,
tramping feet. The child's explana¬
tion was much simpler. He had no
black chalk!
Elinor D. Rhodes
Faversham, England
BRICKBATS & BACK PATS
Sir,
... I am afraid I expected something
definitely more educational than I found
in the issues received by me for last
year. It seems a pity that with the
wonderful opportunities Unesco has that
they have not produced a magazine of
greater value.
M. J. Clarke
Port Elizabeth, South Africa
Sir,
Congratulations on the high standard
of quality of the articles you publish
and also on the fine photographs which
illustrate them.
Jeanne Bouet
Paris, France
Sir,
I have the feeling that your maga¬
zine is less interesting than it used to
be when I first became a subscriber. I
would like to find in it fewer scientific
articles and more reports about every¬
day life in all countries written in a
simple style, thus making the reading of
it a pleasure and not a chore.
E. Boudot
Nantes, France
Sir,
I get the greatest satisfaction from
reading your magazine each month.
One recent article, in which deserved tri¬
bute is paid to Mahatma Gandhi, is a
case in point, for in our epoch of
upheavals, starved of moral awareness,
constantly threatened with a shattering
of the peace which he so ardently
desired, you show us a most extraordi¬
nary personality, one most worthy to be
known by the whole of humanity.
Gladys Viola
Rosario, Argentina
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courrier. July-August 1959
NATURE'S INVENTIVE
GENIUS IN STONE
Sir,
In the summer of 1957 I set out to
make a film on the subject of erosion.
In the Crimea, the Caucasus and the
Urals, particularly on the banks of
rivers like the Petchora and the Tchus-
sovaya, I came across the most extraor¬
dinary stone statues with forms as
striking as they were varied. But it
was not the hand of a sculptor which
had shaped these bizarre monuments ;
it was Nature herself water, variations
in temperature, the wind, the erosive
action of glaciers which over millions
of years had gradually produced them.
The most remarkable of these stone
forms are found in the northern Urals,
on the mountain where the Petchora
River has its source. They have strik¬
ingly different shapes, which are com¬
pletely transformed according to the
angle from which they are seen.
I was particularly struck by a group
of seven great stones, for all the world
like petrified giants. Close by, another
rock rose up in the form of a lion's head
complete with mane and not far off was
a great mass of rock looming up like, a
medieval fortress, its summit, viewed
from another angle, recalling the shape
of a crouching camel.
Nature has embodied much that is
artistic in these age-old works. But
this is not the only reason why I believe
these natural monuments should be
preserved and protected from the ele¬
ments from man's negligence.
These "stone mysteries" have a great
scientific importance for they will aid
future generations of geologists to
understand and write the history of the
earth, deepen our knowledge of the pro¬
cess of erosion and also help the disco¬
very of veins of useful or valuable mate¬
rials such as marble, iron, coal, gold,
platinum to name but a few.
It is not only possible, but also very
vital to preserve these natural monu¬
ments which are certainly to be found
in great numbers around the world, and
an active campaign aimed at this work
of protection should be launched.
M. Zaplatine.
Moscow U.S.S.R.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom...
A.L NNIVERSARIES OF GREAT
MEN: This year, Unesco will give its
patronage to celebrations marking Chekov's
centenary and to cultural events in Poland
commemorating the 150th anniversary of the
birth of Chopin. It will also help to orga¬
nize a symposium on the work of Darwin
to mark the 100th anniversary of the publi¬
cation of "The Origin of Species". Unesco
will also invite its 81 Member States to
associate themselves with the celebration of
other anniversaries that fall in 1959-1960
those of Shalom Aleichem, Henri Berg-
son, Pierre Janet, Franz Josef Haydn,
Alexander von Humboldt and Friedrich von
Schiller and will itself publish and distri¬
bute articles and prepare sound recordings,
radio scripts and filmstrips devoted to these
anniversaries.
' XJS. AND U.S.S.R. ARRANGE
YOUTH EXCHANGE: Seventy-two
American and 24 Soviet young people
are due to participate this year in the
second exchange of youth groups
between the U.S.A. and the U.S.S.R.
under an agreement between the Council
on Student Travel, New York and the
Soviet Committee of Youth Organiza¬
tions. This provides for the Americans
to spend 40 days in the U.S.S.R., includ¬
ing vacations in summer camps and
visits to Moscow and Leningrad, meet¬
ing young people, interviewing youth
leaders and sight-seeing. The Soviet
group wilt arrive in the U.S.A. in Octo¬
ber for 30 days of visits to colleges and
American homes.
JLr¡ NERGY-HUNGRY WORLD:
World consumption of commercial energy
has about doubled in the past twenty years
reports the International Labour Office.
As the world's population has increased
during the same period from an estimated
2,000 million to 2,740 million, per capita
consumption has therefore risen by about
44 per cent. Other facts from the report:
petroleum is now the principal competitor
of coal, followed by natural gas, and hydro¬
electric power; nuclear power will play a
significant role in the future, but so also
will other sources solar energy, wind and
tides at present only playing relatively mi¬
nor roles.
$10 MILLION AID FOR THE
WORLD'S CHILDREN: Assistance for
the world's children totalling over
$10 million was approved recently by
the Executive Board of the United Na¬
tions Children's Fund (Unicef). This
represents about half the total Unicef
aid planned for 1959. The rest will be
allocated in the autumn. The money
will be devoted mainly to general dis¬
ease control (42%) nutrition (41%) and
basic maternal and child welfare (17%)
in programmes which will benefit fifty
countries and territories.
Asia Week in Perth;' and as a follow up
sponsored a 1,350-mile tour of the State's
country districts in which seven Asian and
ten Australian students combined their ef¬
forts in a campaign to tell Australians
about Asia. The Asian students Colom¬
bo Plan scholars from Burma, Indonesia,
Malaya, Singapore and Thailand lectured
at schools, talked to public organizations
and .made broadcasts over local radio sta¬
tions.
CUBA'S EMERGENCY CLASS¬
ROOMS: The Government of Cuba re¬
cently launched ''a campaign aimed at
finding 5,000 temporary classrooms.
Farmers have been asked to lend to
local education I committees, houses,
barns and store-rooms where classes can
be held until new schools are built. As
soon as temporary accomodation be¬
comes available, the Ministry of Educa¬
tion sends a teacher with the necessary
equipment to turn it into a classroom.
l^OLISH ART; GOES HOME: Some
of Poland's most historical art treasures
which were taken from the country on the
outbreak of war for safe keeping abroad
have now returned to their original owners
the National Museum of Warsaw, the
Polish National Library, the Gallery of
Wawel Castle in Cracow and the library
of Pelplin Seminary. Items from these
collections include the coronation insignia
of the kings of Poland in particular the
famous "Szczerbiec7 (Jagged) Sword his¬
torical manuscripts and early printed works
including a Gutenberg Bible, works of me¬
dieval and Renaissance craftsmen as well
as some of Chopin's manuscripts and letters.
COLOMBIA FIGHTS TO WIPE
OUT ILLITERACY: A ten-year cam¬
paign to wipe out illiteracy has been
launched by Colombia. School teachers
and all persons holding diplomas as well
as priests in every parish of the country
have been asked to help. The govern¬
ment plans to eliminate illiteracy by
1969. At present an estimated three
million out of a total population of
nearly 11,500,000 are illiterate in Co¬
lombia.
!rEOTHERMAL ENERGY FOR
THE U.S.S.R.: Construction of the first
geothermal power station in the U.S.S.R.
has started in the Baudjedka Valley area
of southern Kamchatka (Soviet Far East).
The station will run on underground steam
which is plentiful in areas of volcanic acti¬
vity. Steam resources on the volcano-
surrounded Baudjedka Valley are believed
to be practically inexhaustible. Wells are
now being drilled on the construction site
through which steam will pass to reach the
turbine blades. The station will take two
or three years to complete.
FOUR-LEAF CLOVER
We apologize to readers for an error
made by our printers in the last issue.
A caption on page 9 was inadvertently re¬
peated on page 8. The page 8 caption
should have read "Four-leaf clover design
solves road junction traffic problems on
one of the motorways near New York.
This is a classic formula used at a simple
intersection of highways, allowing one
stream of traffic to cross or change direc¬
tion without having to cut through other
traffic lanes."
AxAUSTRALIA'S ASIA WEEK: The
International Club of the University of
Western Australia recently arranged an
Nations to help in preservation of
monuments menaced by Aswan Dam
\
THE United Arab Republic has asked Unesco for international aid to help
preserve historical treasures in Nubia which are destined to be swallowed
up by the' Aswan Dam on which work will begin at the end of this year. A
few years from now a huge lake created by this dam will irrigate much of Upper
Egypt, but when this happens monuments as irreplaceable as the temples of Abu
Simbel, Debod and Kalabchah will be inundated by a man-made flood.
Egyptian authorities have already made plans to conserve this artistic and cultura]
heritage. Since 1955, a Documentation and Study Centre for the Art and
Civilization of ¿Ancient Egypt, set up with Unesco's help, has been preserving,
through photographs, drawings, copies of paintings and plaster casts, the sanctuaries
of Rameses II.'
A plan under, which Unesco would prepare a detailed programme of operations
to be carried out, if necessary with the help of a special fund supported by Member
States, was presented recently to Unesco's Executive Board. It calls for preliminary
studies to be completed by the autumn.
Unesco is now to call a meeting of experts to decide how the work should
be done. A photogrammetric survey of the region will be made in August or
September and the experts will then estimate <he cost of the programme so as to
set a figure of contributions by Member States. The plan as a whole was approved
by Unesco's Executive Board which will discuss at its next session the experts'
report and fliat of Unesco's Secretariat concerning the preliminary work to be
carried out
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Just issued
Catalogue of Colour Reproductions of Paintings
de reproductions e.
couleurs de peintur
* 9 v -- 7SS
1860-1959
(5th revised and enlarged edition)
Unesco is systematically building up archives of colour
reproductions of paintings. Copies of all available repro¬
ductions are collected by the Secretariat and from these,
selections are made by an international committee of experts
for a descriptive catalogue which is regularly produced in
two volumes.
The International Committee (composed of Sir Philip
Hendy, Mr. Jean Lemayre, Mr. Jean Cassou, Mr. Sanchez
Cauton and Mr. Lionello Venturi) is guided in its selection
by three main criteria : the fidelity of the reproduction,
the significance of the artist, and the Importance of the
original painting. The fifth revised and enlarged edition
of the catalogue contains more than 1,000 reproductions.
The reception given to these catalogues by teachers,
students, art publishers, and art lovers of all kinds has
provided convincing proof of their quality and usefulness.
Catalogue of Colour Reproductions of Paintings 1860/1959
S 5.00 ; 25/- ; 1 ,775 F.F.
Obtainable from the Unesco national distributors, below.
A new edition of the leaflet, "Unesco publications in the Field
of Education" is available free of charge. Please send self-
addressed envelope to Unesco DPV, Place de Fontenoy, Paris.
WHERE TO OBTAIN UNESCO PUBLICATIONS
Order from any bookseller, or write
direct to the National Distributor
in your country (See list below ;
names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request).
Payment is made in the national
currency; rates quoted are for an
annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Press
Department, Royal Afghan Ministry of
Education, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 369 Lonsdale Street, Melbourne,
CI, Victoria. (A. 13/-)
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg. Fromme
& C'., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V (Seh.
37.50.)
BELGIUM. For The Unesco Courier:
Louis de Lannoy, 22, Place De Brouckère,
Brussels, CCP. 3 38.000. (fr.b. 100.)
Other publications: Office de Publicité,
16, rue Marcq, Bruxelles, CCP 285-98;
N.V. Standaard-Boekhandel, Belgiélei 151,
Antwerp.
BURMA. S.P.CK. (Burma) 549, Merchant
Street, P.O. Box 222, Rangoon.
CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa,
Ont. ($ 3.00).
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd, Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Co¬
lombo 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Librería Económica, Pte Zayas
505-7 Apartado 113, Havana.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artja Ltd., 30
Ve Smeckách, Prague 2.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6 Norregade, Copenhagen K. (D.kr. 12)
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agen¬
cy, P.O. Box 120, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (F.mk. 540)
FRANCE. Unesco Bookshop, Place de
Fontenoy, Paris, 7'. CCP. 12598-48.
(600 fr.)
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8. (DM. 6)
GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Kultura, P.O. Box 149.
Budapest, 62.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; Gunfoundry Road, Hyde¬
rabad, I; 36a, Mount Road., Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/ I Asaf Ali Road, P. O.
Box 386, New Delhi, I ; Sub-Depots :
Oxford Book & Stationery Co., Scindia
House. New Delhi ; Raikamal Prakashan
Private Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby
Road, Bombay I. (Rs. 6.70)
INDONESIA. G.CT. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Djakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco. Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
IRELAND	 The National Press, 2 Wel¬
lington Road, Ballsbridge. Dublin. (10/-)
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
35, Allenby Road and 48, Nahlat Benja¬
min Street, Tel-Aviv. (£.l./4..)
ITALY. Librería Commissionaria San-
soni. Via Gino Capponi 26, Casella Pos¬
tale 552, Florence, (lire 950)
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings. (10/-)
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo. (Yen 500)
JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road, P.O.B. 66,
Amman.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, P. O. Box Central 64, Seoul.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul
Brück, 33 Grand'Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Peter Chong & Co.;
Post Office Box 135, Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta. ( 1 0/-)
MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid. des
Moulins. Monte-Carlo. (600 fr.).
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff. Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl. 6)
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church. (10/-.)
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
1 74. Lagos. ( 1 0/-)
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass 7, Oslo. (N. kr. 10)
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60 The Mall
Lahore ; Bunder Road, Karachi and
35 The Mall, Peshawar, (rs.6)
PANAMA. Cultural Panameña, Ave¬
nida 7a, No. Ti-49, Apartado de Correos
201 8, Panama, D.F.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.-
Inc, 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo, P.O. Box
620. Manila.
POLAND. Osrodek Rozpowszechniania
Wydawnictw Naukowych PAN, Palac
Kultury i Nauki, Warsaw. (Zl. 50).
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada Lda,
Livraria Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70,
Lisbon.
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Libri Building, Church Street, P.O.
Box 724. Pretoria. (10/-)
SWEDEN. For The Unesco Courier: Sven-
ska Unescorädet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 7.50) other publications
A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl. Hovbokhandel,
Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40 rue du Marché, Geneva. CCP.
1-236. For " Le Courrier de l'Unesco"
only: Georges Losmaz, I, rue des Vieux-
Grenadiers, Genève, CCP. 1.4811 (frs. S.
6.50)
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Isti-
klal Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul.
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT).
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha,
Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E. I. ( I 0/-)
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22, N.Y. ($3.00.) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y.
U. S. S. R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga,
Teraziie 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
WAR ON LOCUSTS
V,
«*-*£*
«<-"X --
N
!«y
W ..-
^
^¿CÔ^p?^'"'^--®'.!-^-- " P ^"~
Ig JZ¿*¡**~ '*T* " """"* "*» "Vi ¿p - -
»Ä jet*. - ^^àjs^^ÈÂfi^^
- XV . -i . . .».-P»
r^"*-
_. (Ç 1p
^!P* - . »
x ...
;N .*-
3K4 à»* t
FAO
The world's desert locust zone is an area covering no less than 11 million square miles of territory, englobiflg 65 countries and terri¬
tories on three continents. The battle against this age-old plague js now organized on an international scale, and a large share has
fallen to the United Nations. As a last resort, when preventative measures have not been taken in time, swarms have to be attacked
on the ground with poison bait. Above, poisoned bran being sown during an invasion in Morocco. Below, handful of dead locusts,
picked up from the thousands littering the ground afterthe sowers have passed, shows effectiveness of such campaigns. (See page 22)
UNATIONS
r/ >*f&
' '
J V
'* t
7%
]]>
</page>
</document>
