<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="066059eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
m
W OPEN ON THE WORLD
T? !
NOVEMBER
19 5 9
(I2th year)
Prîce : l/-stg. (U.K.)
30 cents (U. S.)
60 francs (France)
F S
FOR SOCIAL JUSTICE
/flSàl
ORGANIZATION
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Äri
** . .... . yfÄirffci* .._	 -	 	-	Jass&ic
» _%*»* . - Arí^í.?*- :
:...v
ILO
THE LAND IS A MOTHER
THAT NEVER DIES
Maori saying
More than 600 millions of the world's thousand million
workers are estimated to be employed in agriculturea
large proportion of them still using primitive methods.
In many parts of the world, agriculture is organized into
family enterprises and for this and other reasons it some¬
times has been easier to create standards for the protec¬
tion of industrial workers than for farm labour. In 1921,
two years after the International Labour Organization
came into being, its annual conference held a special
"agricultural session" and adopted three conventions on
the minimum working age, workmen's compensation
and the right of association of farm labour. . Since then
the ILO has adopted a large number of international
standards covering agricultural workers and has sought
to improve the conditions of rural populations by pro¬
moting vocational training, handicrafts and cooperatives.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
NOVEMBER 1959
12TH YEAR
Contents
No. Il
COVER PHOTO
Today, out of a total world
. population of 2,500 million,
workers number some 1,025
million. Over half, 528 million,
are In Asia ; Europe has 190
million, the U.S.S.R. 88
million, Africa 89 million,
North and Central America
84 million and South Ame¬
rica 41 million. Sixty per cent
are engaged in agriculture.
Wherever men are at work,
their problems are the con¬
cern of the International
Labour Organization which
promotes better working and
living standards, Improved
ways of production and gre¬
ater co-operation between
labour and management.
© Almasy, Paris,
4 THE IMPACT OF SOCIAL CHANGE
By David A. Morse
6 40 YEARS OF STRUGGLE FOR SOCIAL JUSTICE
By Edward J. Phelan
9 WORLD SURVEY OF FREEDOM OF ASSOCIATION
I I LABOUR'S UNION: AN INTERNATIONAL TRIANGLE
By Ronald S. Fenton
1 2 SAFETY FIRST FOR MINERS
14 TRAINING BETTER WORKERS
1 5 IT ALL BEGAN WITH A MATCH
1 6 BOATMEN ON THE RHINE
17 THE WORLD'S DISABLED
21 7 MILLION FORGOTTEN INDIANS IN THE ANDES
27 AUTOMATION : ITS EFFECT ON LIVES AND JOBS
Special report from the ILO
1) 90 % OF ALL LIGHT [BULBS IN AMERICA
MADE BY 14 WORKERS AT 14 MACHINES
2) PROBLEM N° I : WHAT WILL BECOME OF WORKERS
IN AN ERA OF PUSH-BUTTON INDUSTRIES ?
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7', France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (12 issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. In the United States of America it is distri¬
buted by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 801 Third Avenue, New
York 22, N.Y., Plaza 1-3860. Second-class mail privileges authorized at New
York, N.Y. (M.C. 59. 1. M I A).
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: $ 3.00; l0/-stg. ; 600 Fr. frs.
(6 New Francs) or equivalent. Single copies l/-stg. (U.K.) ;
30 cents (U.S.) ; 60 Fr. frs. (60 centimes, New Franc).
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
ILO
I welcome the initiative taken by The Unesco
I Courier in devoting this issue to the 40th anniver¬
sary of the International Labour Organization,
I not only as an unusual opportunity for its readers
I to acquire a better understanding of the wide
I range of activities of the ILO, but also as a
I reflection of the close and friendly contacts exist¬
ing among the organizations of the United Nations family.
Forty years ago, when the ILO began its work, it
devoted its main attention to the formulation of inter¬
national labour standards and the promotion of national
legislation as a means of protecting the worker and his
interests. But the growth of the idea that economic
policies must serve a social purpose an idea which the
very existence of the ILO has helped to promote and a
better understanding of the many inter-related factors
that affect living and working conditions have led the
ILO to adjust its work and methods.
The past ten years, for instance, have seen a vast
increase in direct technical assistance designed to deal
with specific tasks in newly developing countries the
improvement of (workers' skills, the organization of
manpower, the attainment of higher productivity in both
industrial and non-industrial enterprises and the promo¬
tion of better labour-management relations.
The ILO has thus had to focus its attention on the
entire process of social change which accompanies
economic development both in industrially advanced as
well as in the less developed countries. This dynamic
view of social development has led to a gradual shift of
emphasis from the adoption of standards to questions
relating to the application of measures of social policy in
the different countries and in strengthening the institu¬
tions which are responsible for the implementation of
these measures.
This evolution of the ILO over the years has been
marked by three continuing trends: the widening of the
geographical range of its influence, the diversification of
the nature of its activities, and the progressive integra¬
tion of its various activities into a comprehensive
programme of action. The need for flexibility and for
continuous adjustment to changing world conditions has
resulted in a series of changes in the relative emphasis
given to the different methods of action available.
The exchange of information and research, the formula¬
tion and application of international standards, technical
assistance and operations, and educational and promotional
activities must all be regarded as complementary to each
other. In the present phase of the development of the
ILO's work special attention is being given to the
educational and promotional approach. Programmes of
'workers' education, management development and labour-
management relations all of these represent important
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courler. November 1959
Almasy, Paris
steps in the more intensive use of this approach.
The workers' education programme, for example, which
is a natural complement to the educational activities of
Unesco, is designed primarily to enable workers and trade
unions to equip themselves to meet their increasingly
heavy economic and social responsibilities. It includes
provision for fellowships, seminars, the exchange of
information, the issue of teaching materials and assistance
and advice in the preparation and implementation of
workers' education programmes.
This type of Work is particularly important in countries
where the trade union movement is relatively new and
not yet firmly established. In the field of management
development, the ILO seeks to promote sound principles
and techniques of management including such aspects as
the raising of productivity and supervisory training, while
the labour-management relations programme is intended
to foster a better understanding of industrial relations and
methods of co-operation between labour and management.
The ILO has become increasingly aware of the need
to strengthen the capacity of individuals to understand
social problems and to find solutions for them. This
need cannot be met from a book of rules or by a set of
rigid formulas but rather by the encouragement of the
creative response of individuals to the challenge before
them. It is primarily the task of education to increase
this capacity not by formal instruction alone but by the
fullest development of latent abilities. In this period of
rapid social and technological change, the need for
leadership at all levels and in all sections of the community
is great, and the ILO is increasingly called upon to help in
meeting the need for workers' education, for management
training and for education in labour administration.
In response to this need, and as a further step forward
in this expanding educational effort, it is hoped to establish
in Geneva an International Institute for Labour Studies
under the auspioes of the ILO and in co-operation with
the United Nations and Unesco. This Institute would give
particular attention to the problems of labour policy in
relation to social and economic change. It would combine
research and comparative study by scholars and would
provide an opportunity for mature individuals, experienced
in government,, trade unions and management, to
exchange views both with the scholars and amongst
themselves, and thus increase an understanding of social
forces in the present-day fworld.
The aims and purposes of the ILO remain today what
they were 40 years ago but the means of action available
to it have increased and widened in scope enormously.
It is through this variety of approaches that the Organiza¬
tion continues to help its Member States in dealing
effectively with their diverse problems and continues to
work for the improvement of the living and working
conditions of people everywhere in a world at peace.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1959
The ILO was born in 1919 but its origin is to be found
in the introduction of steam driven machinery into
the factories nearly a century earlier. This produced
an industrial revolution of which the two main features
were immensely greater production than had been possible
by unaided human labour and conditions for factory
workers as revolting as the worst forms of slavery.
The effort of the workers to defend themselves against
pitiless exploitation led to the formation of trades unions.
Simultaneously, as public opinion became increasingly
shocked by conditions in the factories, an effort was made
to secure legislation setting up minimum standards of
employment.
Since the goods produced had to compete on the inter¬
national market, it speedily became apparent that both
these efforts must take on an international character.
Trades unions established international federations; and
an international association for international labour
legislation was formed by those who were active in seeking
remedial measures by legal enactment.
This latter body had no official character; it Was unable
to do more than formulate proposals in the hope that
some enlightened government might initiate diplomatic
action to bring them into operation. The results were
meagre but they pointed the road along which progress
could be made.
At the end of the first world war the British Govern¬
ment urged the Peace Conference to create an official
institution charged with the task of formulating
and supervising the application of international labour
by Edward J. Phelan
ILO Director 1941-1948
legislation. After long discussion all the essential
elements of the British proposals were incorporated in the
Treaty of Versailles.
The new institution embodied several bold and novel
features. Workers and employers were to take part in
its operations with the same status and powers as gov¬
ernmental representatives; a two-thirds majority could
secure the adoption of a convention; any convention
adopted had to be submitted to the national parliaments,
thus leaving the final decision on ratification with public
opinion in each country.
These provisions were a revolutionary departure from
all traditional diplomatic procedure.
The approval of the Peace Conference was given on
April 11, 1919, and five months later the ILO held its
first conference in Washington.
The Conference achieved an astonishing measure of
success. Agreement was reached on all the technical
items of the agenda including the question of the limi¬
tation of hours of work to eight in the day and 48 in the
week. But, in addition, the Conference settled a number
of general questions of fundamental importance.
It asserted its political supremacy by admitting
Germany and Austria to membership of the Organization;
it perfected its rules of procedure; and it overcame the
difficulties encountered in constituting the Governing
Body, to which fell the task of completing the structure of
the Organization by choosing the Director of the Inter¬
national Labour Office.
In appointing Albert Thomas, the great French trade
union leader, to this post the Governing Body made a
choice which was to have a profound influence on the
future of the ILO. He had a genius for creative leadership
and his new functions gave him a unique opportunity for
its exercise. He saw the ILO not only as an instrument
for formulating international labour legislation but as a
living organism to which had been confided the mission of
furthering social justice. He boldly insisted that the ILO
had rights that must be respected, and these he proceeded
to assert even before the Supreme Council whose
authority at that time dominated the international scene.
His claim that the ILO was entitled to intervene in all
international discussions which might have social
repercussions seemed wholly unrealistic. The ILO for
which he demanded so powerful a status could hardly be
said to exist.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
For social justice (Continued)
Only in the course of time did it become evident that he
had sensed the stirring of new aspirations in a troubled
world; only slowly did his view prevail that the Organiza¬
tion with its uniquely representational character could
offer the prospect of securing effective progress towards
their fulfillment.
From 1920 to 1932 the ILO pursued two efforts which
acted and reacted on one another. The task of elaborat¬
ing international labour legislation was pressed forward
with such energy that the body of decisions adopted by
the Conference began to take on the dimensions of a com¬
prehensive international labour code.
At the same time the
foundations of the Or¬
ganization were streng¬
thened in its Member
States by the steady
growth of the con¬
viction that the ILO's
activities were of direct
interest to each mem¬
ber however special or
isolated its own parti¬
cular problems might
appear.
A similar develop¬
ment took place in the
opinion of organized
labour. At the begin¬
ning, the trades unions
movement had been
sceptical about the val¬
ue of the ILO. It had
demanded that the
Peace Conference
should itself lay down
a number of labour
standards, and it was
far from satisfied by
the decision to remit
the task of defining
such standards to a
special institution.
The ILO's activities,
however, supplied con¬
vincing proof that
the Organization could
achieve results of great
importance.
It succeeded in set¬
ting standards for con¬
ditions in agriculture
where trades unions
were weak and, in¬
deed, often inexistent;
through its representa¬
tion on the Mandates
Commission it secured
active consideration for
labour conditions in
the mandated terri¬
tories; it incited greatly
increased activity con¬
cerning labour prob¬
lems in colonies and possessions; it made its voice heard
in international discussions of economic issues; its exis¬
tence led to the formation of trades unions for the first
time in some countries, while in others it secured for them
a recognition and a status not hitherto accorded. As the
possibilities inherent in such achievements began to be
understood organized labour gave the ILO its whole¬
hearted support.
Thus when Albert Thomas died in 1932 his vision of
what the ILO might become was well on the way to
realization. Under Harold Butler, his successor, the
Organization continued to progress.
As the shadow of events became steadily more menacing
the Governing Body endeavoured to provide for the
situation the ILO would face if War broke out.
The Governing Body decided that the Organization must
continue to function in every way possible. It provided for
8
the exercise of its own powers by a small Emergency
Committee if it itself should be unable to meet; and it
obtained assurances from governments that the staff of
the Office would not be disorganized by measures of
national mobilization.
The situation that developed proved far graver than
could have been anticipated. Switzerland escaped invasion
but she was isolated in the middle of a continent
dominated by the Axis powers.
The war affected every country on the globe. Govern¬
ments everywhere were faced by acute problems arising
out of the dislocation of world trade and it was not to be
expected that they
could give any great
attention to the ILO.
PREAMBLE TO ILO CHARTER
IN TREATY OF VERSAILLES
Whereas universal and lasting peace can be estab¬
lished only if it is based upon social justice.
And whereas conditions of labour exist involving
such injustice, hardship and privation to large num¬
bers of people as to produce unrest so great that the
peace and harmony of the world are imperilled; and
an improvement of those conditions is urgently
required: as, for example, by the regulation of the
hours of work, including the establishment of a
maximum working day and week, the regulation of
the labour supply, the prevention of unemployment,
the provision of an adequate living wage, the pro¬
tection of the worker against sickness, disease and
injury arising out of his employment, the protection
of children, young persons and women, provision for
old age and injury, protection of the interests of
workers when employed in countries other than
their own, recognition of the principle of equal
remuneration for work of equal value, recognition
of the principle of freedom of association, the orga¬
nization of vocational and technical education and
other measures ;
Whereas also the failure of any nation to adopt
humane conditions of labour is an obstacle in the
way of other nations which desire to improve the
conditions in their own countries;
The High Contracting Parties, moved by senti¬
ments of justice and humanity as well as by the
desire to secure the permanent peace of the world,
and with a view to attaining the objectives set forth
in this Preamble, agree to the following Constitution
of the International Labour Organization.
PREAMBLE TO THE ILO CONSTITUTION (INCORPORATED IN THE VERSAILLES TREATY).
But a new element
soon appeared in the
situation. A wave of
opinion began to sweep
through the free world.
Voices were heard on
every side, not only
from workers' organi¬
zations but from heads
of governments, reli¬
gious authorities of all
creeds, and political
leaders of all parties,
demanding that in the
reconstruction of the
post-war world social
obj ectives must be
given the predominant
place.
Here, coming to the
surface with striking
unanimity, was the
movement for social
justice the first stirring
of which Albert Tho¬
mas had sensed twenty
years before.lt was evi¬
dent that the practical
attainment of such ob¬
jectives would require
both national and in¬
ternational action.
The ILO was admi¬
rably constituted to co¬
ordinate the one and
to promote the other.
Not only was it equip¬
ped with the neces¬
sary technical know¬
ledge but it was the
only international org¬
anization of a general
character of which
the United States was
a member.
Would it be used?
Weakened as it was
could it muster the will
and the strength to claim its place?
The answer was given when on October 27, 1941 some
two hundred delegates and advisers from thirty-five of its
Member States assembled in New York.
Thus revitalized and encouraged the Organization was
able to overcome the material difficulties created by war
conditions and to hold a series of representative meetings
which culminated in the Philadelphia Conference of 1944.
That Conference formulated in clear terms the social
principles that should guide post-war policy and asserted
the right of the ^International Labour Organization to
examine and draw attention to the social repercussions of
any action taken by other international institutions.
These decisions were embodied in the Declaration of
Philadelphia, a document which President Roosevelt
enthusiastically hailed as "summing up the aspirations of
an epoch."
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courler. November 1959
ILO LAUNCHES WORLD SURVEY
OF FREEDOM OF ASSOCIATION
On December 10th Human Rights Day the world
Will celebrate the 11th anniversary of the Universal
Declaration of Human Rights, adopted by the
General Assembly of the United Nations in 1948. This
year the special theme chosen by the U.N. for Human
Rights will be the Right to Freedom of Association and the
work of the International Labour Organization.
The promotion of human rights is indeed basic to all
the Work of the ILO. Freedom of opinion and expression,
freedom of peaceful assembly and association, freedom
from arbitrary arrest, detention or exile, the right of both
sexes to equal treatment in professions, the right of young
people to be protected from exploitation, the right of
migrant workers and the physically handicapped to social
justice and security all these- are of fundamental im¬
portance for the fulfilment of the objectives of the ILO.
In the past few years, the ILO has given particular
attention to three major fields of direct interest to labour:
1) trade union rights and freedom of association, 2) forced
labour, 3) discrimination in employment and equal pay
for equal work.
Since the adoption by the International Labour Confe¬
rence of the two basic international instruments defining
the standards relating to freedom of association: the
Freedom of Association and Protection of the Right to
Organize Convention, 1948, and the Right to Organize and
Collective Bargaining Convention, 1949, the ILO has sought
to secure universal acceptance and application of these
standards. The response has been encouraging. The 1948
convention has now received 36 ratifications and the 1949
convention 40, and these ratifications have come from
countries in all parts of the world, with different eco¬
nomic systems and in all stages of industrial development.
The most significant new development, however, is the
launching this year of a world-wide fact-finding survey
into conditions relating to freedom of association including
on-the-spot studies in different countries.
The first country to invite the ILO to carry out its
freedom of association survey was the United States. The
invitation was announced last year by James P. Mitchell,
Secretary of Labour, when he spoke in support of a reso¬
lution on human rights adopted by the ILO conference.
The survey was launched in March 1959 when an ILO
mission visited the United States on a four-month study
ending in June.
The second country to invite the ILO survey mission is
the Soviet Union. The survey team, which left Geneva for
Moscow on August 24, is headed by Mr. John Price, chief of
ILO's Division of enquiry into trade union freedom. The
mission is now visiting the chief industrial, agricultural
and commercial centres of the Soviet Union including
Leningrad, Kiev, Odessa, and Minsk, and will also study
trade union activities in the Caucusus, the Urals, as well
as those in the Soviet Republics of Asia and Siberia.
The ILO survey is designed solely to elicit the facts in
an objective manner and not to relate those facts to spe¬
cific allegations or to pass judgment upon them in general
terms. Referring recently to other governments indicating
their willingness to co-operate in the world survey, ILO's
Director-General David A. Morse said: "This, I feel, is a
significant advance in international action to promote
universal respect for human rights."
FROM THE UNIVERSAL
DECLARATION OF HUMAN RIGHTS
Article 22
Everyone as a member of society, has the right to
social security and is entitled to realization, through
national effort and international co-operation and in
accordance with the organization and resource of each
State, of the economic, social and cultural rights indis¬
pensable for his dignity and the free development of his
personality.
Article 23
Everyone has the right to work, to free choice of
employment, to just and favourable conditions of work
and to protection against unemployment.
Everyone, without any discrimination, has the right to
equal pay for equal work.
Everyone who works has the right to just and favour¬
able remuneration insuring for himself and his family
an existence worthy of human dignity, and supplemented,
if necessary, by other means of social protection.
Everyone has the right to form and join trade unions
for the protection of his interests.
Article 24
Everyone has the right to rest and leisure, including
reasonable limitation of working hours and periodic holi¬
days with pay.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
THE PROBLEM OF CHILD LABOUR STILL EXISTS
Child Labour (children under (4-15) still exists. In southern Europe
and the Middle East it sometimes goes as high as I 5% of the working
population and in parts of Africa and Asia it is even higher. ILO stan¬
dards on minimum age for starting work have been a strong driving
force in reducing child labour. At the start of the century it was com¬
mon In many countries to find children working in mines (below).
Today, in North America, north and western Europe, and some coun¬
tries in the Pacific, working children under I 5 are only a small fraction
of the working population 1% or less. But much remains to be done
especially in countries undergoing industrial development, where
child labour often exists because of the low level of family life and lack
of compulsory education. For young people old enough to begin a
career, the ILO has pointed the way for adequate vocational guidance
and training facilities. All ILO standards apply to young workers,
but special ones have been designed covering night work, weekly rest
and holidays and the prohibition of their employment ¡h dangerous,
unhealthy or specially tiring jobs. Four conventions call for medical
exams to test young people's fitness before being hired for industrial
or non-industrial jobs, or as sailors or fishermen. In 1945 the ILO
urged I 6 years as a world-wide minimum age for fulltime employment.
' ILO Photos
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1959
A WOMAN'S RIGHT: EQUAL PAY FOR EQUAL WORK
In economically advanced countries women have long been an integral
part of the labour force (today, 22% of U.S. women hold jobs). Even
in the less industrialized countries they are taking an increasing share
in organized production (best example is Thailand where 48% are
employed in productive work of some kind)v And conditions under
which most women work today bear no comparison with the pitiless
exploitation which was usual before the ILO was created 40 years
ago. Improvements have come in a large measure through ILO conven¬
tions which form part of the International Labour Code. These conven¬
tions, while covering a wide range of rightsfor both men and women
also provide specifically for the protection of women in terms of health
and motherhood. In 1919 only one country had fixed the minimum
period of maternity leave at 12 weeks. Today nearly 30 countries
have established this minimum. When, in 1919, the first ILO Confe¬
rence adopted a Convention providing for maternity protection only
six countries forbade the discharge of a woman during maternity leave.
Today some 40 countries do so. ILO's Equal Pay Convention has now
been ratified by 3 0 countries. Old distinctions between "men's work"
and "women's work" are thus breaking down. A Convention to
eliminate discrimination of all types in the field of employment was adop¬
ted in I 958. To help the woman worker win a position of practical
equality with men, the ILO has also helped to develop vocational and
technical education and has encouraged the development of social services
to help working women with family responsibilities. Photos show, from
left to right, worker at a shipbuilding yard in Split, Yugoslavia;
maintenance worker in a Japanese textile mill; Canadian textile worker.
LABOUR'S UNION IN
INTERNATIONAL TRIANGLE
by Ronald S. Fenton
On March 11, 1776, the Birmingham Gazette reported: "On Friday last a Steam Engine,
constructed upon Mr. Watt's new principles, was set to work at Bloomfield Colliery in
the presence of a number of scientific gentlemen, whose Curiosity was excited to see the
first movements of so singular and powerful a machine. By this example the doubts of
the inexperienced were dispelled."
Other and far more terrible doubts were soon to take their place as the machines
steadily multiplied, throwing skilled men everywhere out of work and making it possible for
employers to pick up labour at starvation rates, in England they called it the Industrial Revolution;
a time of astonishing unprecedented prosperity for some, of abject, hopeless poverty for others.
This was the most sweeping social change to come over man since the discovery of agriculture.
Never before had there been such social insecurity. Never had the gap yawned so wide between rich
and poor.
The industrial revolution gave rise to conditions which inspired a flood of new thought within each
nation to which the revolution spread. Humanitarians, social reformers, political visionaries, revo¬
lutionaries all offered their solutions.
There were many who spake up in the closing decades of the 19th century: Robert Owen, Louis
Villerme, Charles Hindley, Jerome Blanqui, Daniel Mareska, Emile de Giradin and others. But there
were yet only individual reformers... men with a personal vision inspired by the social changes of their
times. No government yet was ready for action, until another individual, a citizen of Switzerland,
Bundesrat Emil Frey, spoke up in the Swiss National Council: "Short-sighted greed is hindering
government regulations on women and child labour and the redress of other abuses. The voice of our
people calls us to act promptly."
This time a government listened. In 1880 the Swiss invited the major industrial states of Europe
to hold a conference on labour treaties. They were rebuffed, but ten years later 12 nations gathered
in Berlin for such a conference. Unfortunately the Congress of Berlin produced nothing of real
substance but a beginning had been made.
During the First World War, trade union organizations in the two camps and in the neutral coun¬
tries had voiced insistent demands for the right to take part in the peace negotiations and called for
inclusion in the future Peace Treaty of labour guarantees proclaiming, to use the words of the ori¬
ginal proposal by the French Confederation of Labour, "the national and international rights of
labour."
This suggestion, as put forward at an Inter-Allied Trade Conference held in 1916, was, in effect,
a revival of efforts for international labour regulations that had been initiated more than a quarter
of a century earlier. These efforts culminated in the setting up of an International Association for
Labour Legislation, an unofficial body whose proposals led in turn to the conclusion by technical
and diplomatic conference held in 1905 and 1906 of Conventions prohibiting night work for women
in industry and the use of white phosphorus (whose highly poisonous fumes killed or crippled thous¬
ands of workers in the manufacture of matches).
These modest beginnings inspired primarily by social reformers took on far broader dimensions
under the pressure which organized labour was able to exert before and after the conclusion of the
1918 Armistice. The Worldwide catastrophe had put a sharp stop to many constructive efforts, but
it shook men out of their complacency and forced them to examine war's economic causes. At the
CONT'D ON PAGE I 3
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
SAFETY FIRST FOR MINERS
Coal-mining is still one of the world's most hazardous jobs. Cave-ins,
fires, and coal dust and mine gases that may cause explosions, are some of
the perils the miner faces. To guide coal-producing countries in drafting
national safety regulations, the ILO issued a Model Code of Safety Regula¬
tions for Underground Work in I 950 which deals with requirements rang¬
ing from ventilation and precautions against coal dust to the investigation
of accidents and first-aid and rescue measures. ILO'S Industrial Committee
on Coal Mines provides a forum for government, employer and worker
representatives of major coal-producing countries to discuss problems of
safety, productivity, apprenticeship and welfare schemes. Photos show (I)
Old and new in detecting deadly gases. Caged canaries (right) once helped
to warn that gas was present. Today flame safety lamps (left) indicate per¬
centage of gas in air. (2) Indian miners in Bihar province set out for the pit
with mining lamps and wicker basketstraditional hold-all for Indian
labourershooked to their picks. (3) Bihar miners take lift to pit bottom.
Average depth of the pits in this area is only between 120 and 150 feet.
ILO Photos
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courler. November 1959
: :
LABOUR'S INTERNATIONAL TRIANGLE
Peace Conference at Versailles the idea emerged that
peace must be based on social and economic justice. To
carry this theory into practice, permanent international
machinery had to be created. That is how, in 1919, the
International Labour Organization, the ILO, came into
being.
Thus began a partnership unique in international
relations... the association of workers, employers and gov¬
ernments in the ILO. From the beginning the ILO was
set up not just as an agency to regulate wages, hours and
conditions of work, but as an international forum for the
discussions of problems. In its tripartite structure each
nation is represented by four delegates: two #for the
government, one for the employers and one for the
workers. These last two vote according to the wishes of
the organizations they represent. They may, and often
do, disagree with their government's policy or with each
other. It is this tripartite character which has given the
ILO much of its strength and balance and which helped it
to survive the waves of depression, fascism and war which
swept over the world between 1919 and 1939. It continued
in existence throughout the war, which enabled it, in 1946,
to become the first "specialized agency" associated with
the United Nations.
ILO's three basic organs are: (a) the International
Labour Conference which meets once a year and whose
principal task is to work out international labour stan¬
dards; (b) the governing body or "executive council" which
meets several times a year to take policy and programme
decisions (ten seats are held permanently by the "states
of chief industrial importance", ten elective seats are held
by other countries chosen every three years, ten seats are
held by representatives of the (workers and ten are held
by employers) ; (c) the International Labour Office in
Geneva which is the permanent secretariat of the ILO and
a centre of documentation and research.
Not the U. N. Labour Ministry
The ILO sometimes has been called a 'Vorld parliament
of labour" and sometimes the "labour ministry of
the United Nations". It is neither. But 40 years ago
it wrote a new chapter in international diplomacy when
it launched its system of voluntary standards and agree¬
ments. Delegates to its conference have no power to
commit their governments to ratify International Labour
Conventions. Instead of negotiating binding treaties or
agreements these delegates establish international stan¬
dards or targets in the forms of Conventions and Recom¬
mendations.
When the ILO came into existence it was faced not
only with the problem of drafting international labour
standards to cover a wide field of activities and to
redress abuses made of human labour in many countries,
but also the need to make these standards sufficiently
flexible so as to meet the needs of countries widely di¬
vergent in their social structure and degree of industrial
development.
The nature of the most urgent tasks is revealed in the
subjects of the first conventions introduced by the ILO:
working hours, unemployment, maternity protection,
nightwork for women, age of admissions to employment,
employment of young persons at night.
Flexibility clauses have helped to make the ILO stan¬
dards applicable to the less industrialized countries. Lower
age standards have been allowed for certain Asian
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
LABOUR'S INTERNATIONAL TRIANGLE
(Continued)
countries, and ratifying countries have been allowed to
apply certain conventions by stages. The Convention
concerning minimum standards of social security allows
countries to ratify in respect of only a proportion of the
benefits (sickness, unemployment, maternity, old age and
so on) and also enables countries "whose economic and
medical facilities are insufficiently developed" to avail
themselves of certain temporary exceptions in regard to
the proportion of protected persons, duration of benefits
etc.
The 114 Conventions and 112 Recommendations
adopted so far form the "International Labour Code."
A Convention does not bind a member country unless its
parliament or other national authority approves ratifica¬
tion. In all, the number of ratifications has almost
doubled since the end of the Second World War and has
now nearly reached the 2,000 mark on Conventions which
have been adopted since 1919.
The benefits which have been obtained since 1919 have
all been the result of standards freely agreed to on a
voluntary basis, often with the unanimous votes of
workers, employers and governments.
The body of ILO standards which has grown up
gradually over the years includes of necessity matters
which are of no direct concern to certain countries.
Maritime Conventions, over two dozen in number, only
interest nations possessing a merchant navy; Conventions
for the protection of indigenous and tribal populations
concern only States on whose territory such populations
are to be found.
The great majority of the 226 instruments which now
make up the International Labour Code relate, however,
to matters of universal interest such as freedom of
association, forced labour, the protection of women and
young workers, the search for employment, safety and
hygiene on the job, hours of work and paid vacations,
labour management relations, social security inspection,
etc.
The ILO shows the way; it does not give orders. But
it does keep a watchful eye on the way in which the
standards are integrated into the labour practices of
each country. In ratifying a convention, a country
promises first of all to take all necessary measures to make
effective the provisions of the instrument and also to
report to the ILO once a year on the measures taken to
implement the terms of the Convention. The government
must also send copies of these reports to workers' and
employers' organizations in its own country.
Each year the International Labour Conference sets up
a tripartite committee which is responsible for supervising
the effect given to the previous decisions during the last
12 months. In the first half of 1959 nearly 50 countries
provided the Conference, in one way or another, with
14
ILO Photos
TRAINING BETTER WORKERS. More than half of the ILO's work
under the U.N. Technical Assistance Programme has consisted in helping
people to get more and better work done with less wastage of human
and material resources. Last year alone, more than 320 ILO experts
were on assignment in 5 1 countries, many of them showing how to make
better use of manpower, and nearly 50% of ILO projects were in man¬
power organization and vocational training. Above, an ILO team teaches
Haitians new skills ; left, instructor at work in a Tripoli school (originally
set up by Unesco) where young Libyans are being taught a score of trades
and skills from automobile engineering to operating calculating ma¬
chines; below, foreman in a Netherlands factory briefs two Yugoslav
trainees. Yugoslavia has placed hundreds of workers in industries of
other European countries under ILO's worker-trainee programme.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1959
IT ALL BEGAN
WITH A MATCH
The ordinary safety match was responsible
for the world's first international labour
convention in 1906. Until then safety
matches had usually been tipped with
white phosphorus whose poisonous vapours
killed or crippled thousands of workers in
the match-making industry. Inoffensive
red phosphorus could have been used,
but its higher cost would have placed
match-makers at a disadvantage in compet¬
ing for markets. The answer was the Berne
Convention which prohibited the use of
white phosphorus and thus put all coun¬
tries on the same footing. In 1919 the ILO
called on members to adhere to this conven¬
tion. Since then white phosphorus has been
abandoned. Most standards laid down by
ILO have some bearing on the health and
safety of workers and have led to the use
of safety devices and precautions such as
the use of protective masks like that worn
by worker (right) while spray-painting.
ILO Photo
information supplementing their reports or in answer to
comments from experts who had examined government
reports on the situation in their countries. The inter¬
play, year after year, of factual examination and moral
persuasion has proved to be the kind of international
approach most likely to bring action at the national level.
No country, however advanced, can fail to find in the
International Labour Code, certain standards higher than
its own and some indications on how to improve conditions
of work. The Code is, however, of greater importance to
the less advanced countries those just gaining political
independence and those in the early stages of industrializa¬
tion; they can draw from it the very basis of their social
legislation.
The influence of ILO standards has been most clearly
apparent when a government has /adopted specific
measures to bring its national statutes and conditions into
line with a convention it intends to ratify or has already
ratified. This is sometimes clearly stated in the law in
question as for example when Great Britain adopted a
Merchant Shipping Act "to give effect to certain Conven¬
tions adopted by the International Labour Conference."
Similarly, the Israeli laws on hours of work, on the
protection of wages and other labour subjects state clearly
that their adoption will enable Israel to ratify certain ILO
Conventions. In Greece the minimum age for employment
at sea was not regulated at all until the country ratified
the international convention which lays down a 14 year
minimum age limit.
Impact of the 'World Labour Code'
So the "World Labour Code" is not merely a rhetorical
headline. In almost every 'country of the world, and
in almost every occupation from farm-hand to filing
clerk, from deck-hand to truck-driver it has transformed
conditions of Work.
The objectives of the ILO remain today what they were
40 years ago: to secure the foundations of peace through
justice in social arrangements; and to this end to bring the
nations to work in concert for the improvement of condi¬
tions of life and labour. Yet today the ILO is a very
different kind of organization from what it (was at its
origin. When it began its work in 1919 its orientation was
primarily European and New World. Since the Second
World War it has become virtually universal and this
year, on its 40th birthday, it had eighty member states.
In the past 40 years different economic systems have
become established in different parts of the world and
nationalism has become the characteristic passion of
millions whose fathers were unrepresented when the first
sessions of the International Labour Conference met.
Political developments have made it necessary to pay more
attention to the problems of underdeveloped countries in
Latin America, Asia, the Middle East and, more recently,
in Africa.
Also there is an increasing emphasis on agricultural
workers and non-manual or professional workers an
emphasis which was, for all practical purposes, non¬
existent When the ILO Was created. For example,
agricultural workers make up the vast majority of workers
in underdeveloped countries, and non-manual workers are
coming into prominence because of technological changes
in industry.
While the traditional code-building work remains a basic
ILO occupation, more and more "operational" activities
are taking their places in its programme and the work of
the organization has come indispensably associated with
economic development, with industrialization in under¬
developed countries and ¡with such modern problems as
automation or industrial fatigue or the protection of
workers and scientists against radiation hazards. Work in
these areas falls broadly into categories such as manpower
organization, vocational training, management develop¬
ment, co-operation in handicrafts, labour administration,
social security, labour-management relations, safety and
health or workers and so on.
The ILO has assisted in the creation of productivity
centres in Egypt, Israel, Central America and elsewhere,
that distil and instil the latest productivity techniques at
all levels of management and make a major contribution
to the economic development programmes and building of
the standards of living of these countries and regions.
Similar work is being done in India. In Burma the ILO
helped by drafting basic legislation and arranging for the
training of personnel for the administration of the
country's first social security system. It undertook similar
projects in the Caribbean region, Latin America and the
Middle East.
To the high Andean plateaux, to the lands of tropical
Africa, to the hot dry countries of the Middle East and
further east to Asia and the green islands of Indonesia
have gone nearly 1,000 technical assistance experts to
help the countries of these regions with many problems of
industrial and agricultural expansion. Since 1953 the
ILO has arranged for nearly 1,200 worker-trainees to gain
experience outside their own countries.
Enormous strides have been made in improving the
condition of both the peasant and the industrial worker.
Progress has been uneven in the world, for conditions vary
greatly from one part to another, but at least certain
standards have been laid down, voluntarily accepted by
many nations, eagerly aspired to by others.
The labour policy in most countries is no longer
primarily a problem of the protection of workers, as it
was when the ILO was founded. It is now an integral part
of national economic and social policy.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
ILO Photos
BOATMEN ON THE RHINE
Forty-five thousand Rhine boatmen and their families now
benefit from international regulations concerning social
security and conditions of work aboard ships and barges
of the river fleets of five nationsBelgium, France, German
Federal Republic, Netherlands, Switzerland. The ILO
assisted In negotiations between these countries which
have led to agreements under which pensions are paid to
boatmen Irrespective of the nationality of the ships on
which they serve and social security benefit is extended
to all. Above, Rhine river housewife shops at waterborne
grocery store while another (below right) hangs out washing
and keeps a watchful eye on baby. Nearly one-fourth of
all ILO Conventions deal with seafarers and cover such
questions as wages, hours of work, food and catering,
Below, crews' quarters aboard a British trawler; right,
veteran crew member at work aboard a German freighter.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1959
ILO Photos
CRIPPLED AND DISABLED BUT NOT DEFEATED
Thanks to modern rehabilitation techniques, crippled and disabled people can learn to be useful and productive members of the community. At Solo in
Java, for instance, disabled Indonesians are being helped back to active lives at a unique centre set up by the Indonesians themselves in I 9 50. Today, the
U.N. and other international agencies are helping to run this centre. Above, left, an ILO expert directs the work of a trainee in the centre's woodwork
section. Above right, a future printerlearnshisjob. To help develop such facilities, the ILO has set standards aimed at improving existing services, provides
technical assistance and conducts year-round research. Its work is now going on in many countries from Brazil to Burma and from Turkeyto the Philippines.
ILO Photos
NEW TRADES FOR THE BLIND
Some four-fifths of the world's blind people, it is estimated, live in the
underdeveloped countries. Ceylon has some 6,000 blind and 2,000 of
them are expected to pass through workshops set up In Colombo with ILO
help. Here, blind men and women are learning some traditional trades
and, with the help of an ILO expert, some new ones. Left, trainees learn
the use of a hand loom. Above, hands of a woman trainee who will never
see again swiftly follow the raised dots of the Braille alphabet. She is being
taught a trade so she will no longer have to depend on charity to live.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
ovel in action at a
usy phosphate factory, Morocco.
ckers handling cargo on the
t Casablanca. Morocco.
"eins are transformed
eek workshop.
men in the famed
factory, France.
5. Bringing in thé day's catch at
the fishing port of Tema, Ghana.
Photos © Atmasy, Part*
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1959
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
SPECIAL AID
FOR ASIA
In Asia industrial levels and traditions deve¬
loped by many other nations over more than
a century have to be built up rapidly if economic
development is to advance. At the recent ILO
Annual Conference, David Morse, the Director-
General of the Organization sounded a warning
that unemployment coupled with a rapid popu¬
lation increase is the biggest single labour
problem facing the world. Referring to predic¬
tions that the populations of Asia, Africa and
Latin America might quadruple during the next
half century, Mr. Morse said that there would
have to be a great and rapid increase in produc¬
tion and employment if this large population
was to sustain even its present low level of life.
Recognizing that the unskilled labour forces of
Asia have to be taught to produce goods and
services for their developing communities, the
ILO last year made this continent the principal
beneficiary of its technical assistance programme.
In addition, the ILO maintains a regional office
for Asia, holds regular regional conferences
and has set up an Asian Advisory Committee
to study the problems of this continent. Tur-
baned worker in this photo is checking struc¬
ture of a railway bridge in India. In handling
some of her labour force problems, India, now
carrying out a vast railway development plan,
has received technical assistance from the ILO.
ILO
NEW LOOK
AT AFRICA
Forty years ago when the ILO was formed there
were only three Independent states in all
Africa (Ethiopia, Liberia, Union of South Africa).
Today almost a score more have achieved inde¬
pendence or autonomy, and with it a whole
range of social questions and labour policy
questions have become matters of decision by
the Africans themselves. For the ILO this has
meant a reappraisal of its responsibilities in
the entire continent. In January ILO opened
an African Field Office in Lagos, Nigeria, and
last year it completed a comprehensive fac¬
tual survey of labour and social conditions in
some 3 5 countries and territories in Africa
south of the Sahara (African Labour Survey.
ILO, Geneva, 19 58). A similar survey of North
Africa is now in preparation. The growth of
Africa's labour force is exemplified by Nigeria
where the number of wage-earners quadrupled
between 1938 and 1956 and by the opening
in November 19 58 of an African Labour Col¬
lege at Kamala, Uganda by the International
Confederation of Free Trade Unions. Photo
shows a new shoe factory operating in Senegal.
© Almasy, Paris
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1959
© Almas/, Paris
On the ¿high plateaux of the Andes and in the valleys
of the Cordillera ranges some seven million
Indians of Latin America live at altitudes of
between 9,000 and 15,000 feet. They make up a large part
of the populations of Ecuador, Peru and Bolivia and they
reach to the south of Colombia and to the north of the
Argentine. Farm hands or peons, they eke out their lives
at a bare subsistence level, struggling against a hostile
nature and an impoverished soil. For centuries they have
lived in isolation from the rest of their countrymen, out¬
side the mainstream of national economic and social life.
The challenge of this great human problem is today
being met by the people of these Andean countries helped
by five international organizations. To raise the living
standards of these mountain people, to integrate them
into the life of their countries, to bring them hope for the
future and to give the lands where they live the full
strength of their hitherto untapped human resources
these are the aims of the Andean Programme.
This vast international undertaking |was born out of
efforts made over many years by the governments of
Ecuador, Peru and Bolivia, to integrate the Andean popu¬
lations into the national life. Because of the magnitude
of the problem, these governments sought the aid of inter¬
national organizations. Today, five international orga
nizations the United Nations, Unesco, the World Health
Organization (WHO), the Food and Agriculture Organiza¬
tion (FAO) and the International Labour Organization
(Which provides the co-ordinating leadership) are work¬
ing closely with the governments in carrying out the
enterprise.
In every one of the field bases of the Andean Programme,
agronomists, teachers, technical instructors, doctors,
anthropologists, social workers, nurses and veterinarians
are at work. They are showing the Indians (most of whom
speak Quechua or Aymara) to speak, read and write in
Spanish the official language of their countries; they
explain how crop yields can be increased; how to build
roads and irrigation ditches; how to make better homes;
how to prevent illness and how to look after domestic
animals properly.
The Andean Programme builds schools and model homes;
it sets up vocational training workshops in which artisans
and qualified workmen are trained; it trains local
administrators; and in some cases it helps to organize the
movement of whole communities to more fertile land.
The Andean Programme has received the understanding,
support and collaboration of the Indians. In the three
Andean countries the Indians are building schools and
CONT'D ON PAGE 24
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
7 MILLION FORGOTTEN INDIANS
(Continued)
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1959
ILO Photos
ON THE HIGHEST
LAKE IN THE WORLD
Situated on a plateau in the Andes Mountains,
at the dizzy height of more than 12,500 feet
above sea level, Lake Titicaca Is the highest
of the world's navigable lakes. As there is no
wood available, the Indians weave their fishing
boats from totora reeds. These craft are
strong enough to withstand the terrible
storms that often whip this 130-mile long
lake. It is in this region, on the high plateaux
amidst the snow-capped peaks, that live 7
million Indians among the poorest people
on earth. The fate of these Indians is now the
deep concern of three Latin American repub¬
lics and the U.N. At stake is the future
development of Bolivia, Peru and Ecuador.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
7 MILLION
INDIANS
(Cont'd from page 21)
8 0°/° ILLITERATE AND AMONGST
THE POOREST PEOPLE IN THE WORLD
improving homes, sowing better seeds, opening roads, digg¬
ing wells, raising dikes sometimes on their own initiative;
sometimes under the stimulus of the Programme and with
the help and advice of experts from the field bases. To
help these technicians, Indians have travelled the narrow,
dangerous mountain tracks, carrying on their backs loads
of sand dug from deep quarries and heavy stones hacked
out from far-off mountains.
It would be Wrong to believe that the mass of the Indians
are complacent about their isolation and misery or that
they lack the will to improve their lot. The Indians of the
Andes have retained the love of the soil which nourishes
them; they are accustomed to toil. They possess an
extrordinary dignity and the determination to remove
their children from this crushing misery. Poor they may
be, yet they are nevertheless the descendants of a great
civilization the Empire of the Incas whose relics are
still being found.
The accounts of the conquistadores as Well as modern
archaeological discoveries and ethnological studies all
testify to the remarkable level of artistic, cultural and
social organization which these Andean Indians had
attained. Advanced methods of production and distribu¬
tion gave the Incas the chance to accumulate considerable
riches. The whole Andean region was linked by an
impressive network of communications. (See "The Royal
Highway of the Incas," The Unesco Courier, June
1959). The terraced fields provided enough food for a
people who knew how to build such remarkable cities as
Machu-Picchu and Cuzco in Peru and Tihuanaco in Boli¬
via, whose remains are admired today for their symmetry
and beauty.
But this civilization had not the strength to resist the
impact of the Spanish conquistadores who made them¬
selves masters of the Inca Empire some four centuries
ago. The economic and social organization of the Inca
Empire disintegrated rapidly, leading to the disappearance
of the ruling classes and the total decadence of the mass
of the Indians.
Most of the Indians lost the properties held by their
ancestors. They were forced to seek refuge in the most
inaccessible parts of the Cordillera, or to work in the
mines or on the great estates which Were taken over by
the conquistadores along with the people who lived on
them.
Despite past efforts of governments and organizations
to help the indigenous populations and to bring them the
advantages of modern civilization, the condition of the
Indian became more and more synonymous with economic
stagnation and social degradation.
The Indians found themselves forced back to the least
fertile land and to that Which was farthest from highways
and markets. They were reduced to bare-existence farm¬
ing and local handicrafts, scraping the exhausted and
unprofitable soil with archaic tools and Wooden ploughs,
spinning and weaving the coarse wool sheared from their
scrawny domestic animals, and living in huts made from
mud and rushes. The fate of the Indians who remained
on the great estates was no more enviable. They had
become peasants Without land, working on the soil almost
without pay under antiquated and patriarchal conditions.
This state of affairs today weighs heavily on the eco¬
nomy of countries with large Indian populations, whose
per capita income is one of the lowest in the world and
whose purchasing power is almost nil. As farmers, artisans
and miners they have long contributed to the production
of riches; in spite of this contribution their productivity
is low and they habitually consume nothing except a part
of the direct product of their labours.
How urgent is the problem? A look at the living condi¬
tions of the Andean Indians provides a clear and unequi¬
vocal answer. Their homes are sordid, dilapidated and
unhealthy. The average family consists of the father,
mother and perhaps four surviving children. Numb With
cold, they crowd themselves into a hut made of earth and
straw, a few feet square. They sleep in one promiscuous
mass on the skins of animals thrown before the hearth
whose Warmth they share With the dog, rabbits, chickens
and other domestic animals.
Surface water is scarce and they do not know how to dig
wells to tap underground Water. The few natural wells
are shallow and poorly protected against contamination.
When it is cold and the water is frozen, the Indians remove
their clothes to wash themselves only once in a matter
of weeks or even longer; their bedding is hardly ever
cleaned. "They never bathe themselves, they wash their
hands once a week, their faces on fiesta days and their
feet even more rarely", says the report of an ILO expert.
The hut is swept out once a month, and the little court¬
yard never.
In many Indian communities modern medicine is un¬
known. The doctor or the nurse have not yet replaced
the healer or the sorcerer. Herbs, potions and more or
less magical rites are the rule. The activities of the
The Indian of the Andes has an irrepressible desire for learning. "We know
that we are ignorant", they say to Andean programme experts, "We
want our children to have a better life, we want schools, schools, schools..."
The people of the village of Pulingui, Chimborazo province, Ecuador, build
themselves a new school. Mason is at work while children attend the old
school (in background). New one will have well lit, sunny class-rooms.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courler. November 1959
The Indians have been taught how to disinfect their animals and how to
fight animal diseases. Here, a group in Ecuador (left) comes to the Andean
Programme for help in improving their stock. Rams and ewes were
loaned to the farmers so that they could raise the quality of their
flocks. Centre, Bolivian women sometimes come many miles to attend
a sewing class held in a village community centre. The doctor is
beginning to replace the medicine man and hygiene to replace
superstition. Right, a doctor inspects TB vaccination of Peruvian child.
"healer" are particularly disastrous in cases of pregnancy
and childbirth. He can be said to be responsible for a
large part of the appalling infantile mortality rate one of
the highest in the world. The absence of all immunisa¬
tion measures means that smallpox and whooping cough
are endemic, causing the death of many infants. Tuber¬
culosis and other pulmonary afflictions play havoc.
Parasites are numerous and harmful. Food is monotonous
and inadequate. The diet is poor in protein and fats.
Badly housed and badly fed, the Indians are also almost
completely deprived of education. Schools are still rare
in rural areas, and where they do exist, they are short of
teachers and materials. Eighty per cent of the Indians
are illiterate and very few of them know Spanish which
thus adds to their isolation. Vocational, agricultural, and
handicrafts training is non-existent. The Indian is thus
condemned to remain an unskilled labourer receiving the
lowest pay.
The International Labour Organization has been concer¬
ned with the living and working conditions of indigenous
populations since the first years of its existence and in
1926 set up a committee to work out international stan¬
dards for their protection. (In 1953, the ILO published a
comprehensive study on this question: "Indigenous Peoples,
Living and Working Conditions of Aboriginal Populations
in Independent Countries.") It had already begun to study
the problems of the Andean Indians more than twenty
years ago, and in 1939 it reported: "Those questions which
concern principally the indigenous people... should not be
considered as part of the 'Indian problem' but rather as
part of the general social problems of the country, and
they should be dealt with rather from the angle of general
reform than of action on behalf of any particular race."
This principle was reaffirmed by the Conference of
American States Members of the ILO which met in
Montevideo in 1949 and adopted a far-reaching operation¬
al programme.
In 1952 a mission composed of representatives of the
U.N., the ILO, FAO, WHO and Unesco spent four months
in Bolivia, Peru and Ecuador making special studies of
the problems of the Andean Indians. On the basis of its
report the ILO drew up an operational programme which
was approved in 1953, and soon after the Andean Pro¬
gramme was put into action.
The first field base for the Programme was established
at Pillapi on the Bolivian shore of Lake Titicaca, on a
plateau at an altitude of nearly 14,000 feet. At the same
time an experimental school for textile handicrafts was
established at Quito, in Ecuador. In 1957 and 1958 the
Andean Programme Was being carried out from ten field
bases in the three countries with a large Indian popula¬
tion, the headquarters being in Lima, Peru.
The objectives of the programme better education,
Future local leaders receive Instruction in 3-weeks training course of
U.N. 's Andean programme. Returning home, they teach neighbours. In back¬
ground, students of La Paz University participate in first Bolivian work camp.
f^;** «.vis
ILO Photos
Campesinos build a road near Playa Verde (Green Beach) a sad, colourless
rock-strewn valley in Bolivia where the Andean Programme has established
a field base. Road will make village accessible for audio-viiual aid truck.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
7 MILLION
INDIANS
(Continued)
'WE NEED SCHOOLS AND TEACHERS
AND NEW WAYS TO EARN A LIVING'
training, health and welfare are being achieved through
action covering a wide variety of fields. For example,
following one exploratory mission an operational base was
set up in the central province of Chimborazo Which set
out to raise living standards in the rural Indian commu¬
nities of the region; to improve, diversify and stabilize
agricultural production and handicrafts; to introduce
general education and vocational training for adults and
young people and to improve housing conditions.
Here, as in other regions, the Work has not always been
easy and straightforward. In one community, for in¬
stance, it was noticed that although the local people had
reserved ground for a school they seemed to be in no hurry
to begin building it. Knowing the importance the Indians
attach to education, members of the mission asked them
to explain their indifference and slowness. "We prefer
to be careful", was the reply. "We know how these things
go. First they will send us a schoolteacher; and then will
come the tax collector."
Eventually the ice began to melt a little. "We need
schools and teachers," said the Indians, "since not being
able to go to school prevents advancement in life. We
also need potatoes that do not freeze with the first frost.
Can't we find a Way to keep water in the fields? In flood
time it carries off the little good land that is left. Can't
we be taught to produce things we can sell? We need
a bit of money in order to buy salt, trinkets for our wives,
tools. And we need something for the children, Who die,
but we don't know why."
ten times greater than in 1957. In the Playa Verde region
production has risen by between 400 to 500 per cent.
Efforts so far deployed have nevertheless been insuffi¬
cient to meet the needs of such a vast undertaking. So
the Andean programme as, yet affects only a minority of
the people and its results are essentially experimental.
The expansion of the programme will depend upon the
further development of government policies. At present,
the international organizations are helping to prepare for
the time when responsibility for the Andean programme
and its management will be transferred to the national
authorities. Thus emphasis must now be given to creating
the administrative machinery and to training personnel
for when the countries concerned continue alone the work
launched with the aid of international organizations.
The magnitude of the Andean problem and its meaning
in terms of human Welfare have evoked a truly interna¬
tional response. The Governments of Belgium and France
and employers' and woiikers' organizations in the Federal
Republic of Germany, Denmark, the United States,
Norway and Sweden have given equipment, machinery
and medicines to equip the vocational training workshops
and the medical centres of the Andean Programme. The
American organization Care and the United Nations
Children's Fund (Unicef) have given food packages.
Public opinion in Ecuador, Peru and Bolivia has been
aroused for this is a programme which seizes the imagi¬
nation. But perhaps the basic result of the Programme
is to have succeeded in reviving or arousing in the Indian
a zeal for progress and self-improvement.
Highway built by a kitchen boy
The highlands and valleys of the Andes Where the
Indians live are ripe for transformation into a region
of good pastures, in which the stock raising industry
can prosper and produce not only wool, but also meat
and dairy products, of which the Andean countries and
especially Peru are in need. It was With this in mind
that the Andean Programme began an experimental
pasturage project in the Puno region.
In the zones where the agricultural section of the Pro¬
gramme is being pushed ahead, the experts introduce the
campesinos to the use of chemical fertilizers, insecticides
and germicides. The agronomists explain the Worth of
selected plants and seeds, how to irrigate the dry lands
and how to drain the marshes. Veterinaries give demons¬
trations of cattle improvements. Sires have been imported
from abroad to improve the domestic stock.
At Playa Verde in Bolivia, emphasis is placed on the
training of local leaders among the Indians so as to pro¬
vide permanent and fruitful contact with the communities.
Candidates for the classes which were set up came in
from every part of the region and finally there Were more
students than there were places available.
When the students return to their communities they
teach their neighbours the lessons they have learned in
the centre. Their capacity for assimilating what they
are taught is extraordinary. One day an Indian arrived
at Playa Verde from Sacaca, a community north of Potosi,
about 100 miles away. Nobody had invited him and he
was not prepared to enter as a regular student. But he
did Want to find out What was going on at the base. No
one paid much attention to him and finally he installed
himself as kitchen boy.
Months later, the Playa Verde director visited Sacaca.
To his surprise he found that five miles of new highway,
a new school and three co-operatives had been built. Nine
students were having daily classes in reading and writing.
The author of all this, and also acting as teacher, was the
former kitchen boy...
In Playa Verde, ten communities were able to place part
of their crops on sale in 1957 and the areas sown in 1958
were three times greater than in the previous year. The
resulting harvest in seven communities near the base was
26
ILO
As part of the Andean Indian programme, the ILO has set up a textile
handicraft centre in Quito, Ecuador. Using the Indians' great artistic
tradition as an inspiration, the designs and colouring of the artisan
products were given new life. Exhibitions held in Quito, Geneva and
New York have revealed the high level attained In this workshop.
(See The Unesco Courier, February 1955). Here, trainees are at work.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1959
UTO M ATI ON
Modern Sorcerers Apprentice
or passport to prosperity?
Special report from ILO
Automation, , atomic energy and other technological
changes are dominating the labour and social scene
in more and more of the older industrial countries
and are a key factor in the development of the newly
industrializing countries. They pose serious problems of
economic and social adjustment for our industrial society
and throw down a challenge to our whole civilization.
True, many of the problems are not new. They arose in
earlier stage of industrialization. Today, however, they
seem to take on a more dramatic and a more drastic form.
Today, every country is caught up in the relentless
wheel of technological change. Each region and each
nation is affected, directly and indirectly, and at an ever
faster pace. There is no point in discussing here the
desirability of this evolution. There is no question of
turning back and little possibility even of regulating the
speed of development . Our problem is to move forward
in the social field fast enough to be able to ensure that
technological progress is translated into social progress.
We must give practical evidence of social growth if we are
to profit from and even to control the mighty technolo¬
gical forces which we have liberated. If we do not grow
to'the extent required of us, our whole civilization will
bend and may even break under the strain of change. If
we do grow enough and fast enough, we open the way for
creating a higher and richer civilization than man has yet
known.
The ILO's concern is with the labour and social front,
with what is happening to men and women at work, and
with the problems confronting them today in consequence
of the dynamics of technological change in our industrial
society. The ILO has much important work to do in
these fields. '
Despite substantial differences of opinion on many
aspects of automation and atomic energy, no one would
deny that they provide a powerful lever for economic
growth. They make possible a vast increase in produc¬
tion and in productivity. They make possible the more
rapid development required to keep pace with population
growth and to raise living standards. Indeed, these and
other forms of technological progress are essential if the
world economy is to grow and produce more and better
services and if it is to respond successfully to the chal¬
lenge of rising populations and higher standards of living.
This is the true perspective of the future and one of
which we should never lose sight.
Thus, the long-run outlook is good. But in the mean
time many short-run problems have to be met with ima¬
gination and vigour. Most of these relate to the labour
and social aspects of technological change rather than to
the technical aspects, and to our ability as a society to
absorb change readily to the general benefit of the people.
Employers have continued their search for technical
solutions to outstanding problems and have given increas¬
ing attention to the social aspects of technological chan¬
ges. Trade unions have been studying the implications
of these changes for workers. In many countries govern¬
ment services have taken steps to strengthen research
and other facilities so as to be able to understand and
anticipate the problems and to promote smooth adjust¬
ment to the accelerating pace of technological change. A
great many national and international conferences have
been held to discuss the impact of automation and atomic
energy and to consider the more general problems of
technological change. These questions have also been
examined by a very large number of employers' and
workers' organizations.
All these developments are symptomatic of a healthy
concern with the problems facing us today and constitute
reasonable and essential steps towards their solution.
But let us not lag behind the times. So far, we have
only probed the surface. Much remains to be done to
develop a sound basis for absorbing without unnecessary
friction the vast changes which are taking place. We
must adjust the pace of our social planning and action
to the inexorable pace of the technological developments
which are transforming the world economy. We have
a heavy responsibility to develop and pursue policies
which will facilitate the social growth now possible and
necessary for world development.
CONTO ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
O 90 °/o of all light bulbs in America
made by 14 workers at 14 machines
What is automation? Unfortunately but inevitably
there is no single answer to this question. Auto¬
mation means many different things to many
different people. Some people use the word almost as a
synonym for technological change. Others explain it as
simply advanced mechanization. Still others consider it
an entirely new philosophy of industrial operation.
Three fundamental developments account for nearly
everything that is commonly regarded as falling under
the heading of automation. The first, continuous auto¬
matic production or integration, is often called "Detroit
automation" in honour of the city where it got its start.
The second is often termed feed-back technology, based
on the use of built-in automatic devices which compare
the way work is being done with the way it is supposed
to be done and make automatically any adjustments in
the work process that may be necessary. The third is
best known as computer technology, resting primarily
on new developments in electrical engineering and cover¬
ing the use of general and special purpose computing
machines capable of recording and storing information
(usually in the form of numbers) and of performing both
simple and complex mathematical operations on such
data.
Clearly, automation is not new. What then is new
in the concept that lies behind the word "automation"?
First, perhaps, this concept implies a new way of think¬
ing about products and production. It presents our
generation with the problem of re-thinking the conduct
of industrial operations in terms of the principle of cpn-
tinuous flow governed by an electronic nervous system.
Second, there is contained within this concept the pos¬
sibility of envisaging a large and complex yet fully auto¬
matic factory in which a computer integrates and controls
the separate automatic production Unes. According to
a United Kingdom report on the subject, this is "the most
important new element in automation" even though it
cannot be realized immediately. Is it this particular
element which gives automation its dramatic and almost
frightening quality? What would such a factory be
like? One of the experts of the Radio Corporation of
America described it very clearly. He said:
People... in thinking about an automatic factory, conjure
up the idea of a very large black box into which flow a
great many varieties of raw materials and a large volume
of automatically handled data. Both the raw materials
and the data are processed, "untouched by human hands",
so that the right amounts of the right products are dis¬
tributed to the right places at the right time. However...
there will be many human workers... even though they will
have no direct connexion with processing the product.
Some will be the technical maintenance men who will keep
the machines operating. Others will design and install new
machines to take care of the changing product. There will
be production men who will no longer schedule production
28
of the parts of a given product, but instead will service the
programmes of machines in accordance with management
decision... There will be engineers and stylists who will
develop new products and who, when necessary, will deve¬
lop and design new automatic machinery or modify existing
machinery for making those new products. Thus, even in
the fully automatic factory, there would be "human hands".
Manpower is still necessary to make, tend and maintain
machines and to perform the many and more varied
functions of management. But the teams of operatives
directly engaged on the production process have vanished.
And, at the last session of the International Labour
Conference, the U.S.S.R. employers' delegate said: "...our
workshops are taking on the look of laboratories."
So far, however, fully automatic operation, while possi¬
ble of realization, has been achieved in practice in only
a few instances.
Perhaps the most significant novel feature of automa¬
tion is that it makes it possible to do many things and to
produce many goods and services which were simply not
feasible in the past. Atomic energy research could never
have reached its present stage without automatic devices
and controls. The huge oil refineries, chemical plants
and steel works of today could not be operated without
automatic controls. Compounds of ingredients formerly
too toxic to be handled safely can now be used. Many
new products have come on the market as a result of
refinements of precision work made possible by automa¬
tion. With advanced computer technology it is possible
to assemble and analyse information that was once pro¬
hibitively expensive to collect. Too often this novel
aspect of automation is overlooked. Yet it is certainly
the distinctive contribution of the new technology.
What is the impact? Fourteen glassblowing machines,
each operated by one worker, now produce 90 per cent, of
the glass light bulbs used in the United States and all
rTn
the glass tubes used in radio and television sets (except
picture tubes). Another example is the automatic manu¬
facture of equipment for attaching standard electronic
components to printed circuit boards. Machines now
print or etch or stencil on a board what were hand-wired
circuits before, soldered at all contact points; machines
make the components; machines attach them to the
printed circuit boards; machines make the parts; ma¬
chines assemble them.
Once the components are fed into a machine, for exam¬
ple, complete radio sets can be produced; and on one
body radio assembly line, turning out 1,000 radios a day,
two workers now produce more than 200 workers did with
the old methods. A food products company in the United
States has developed a machine which assembles in about
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1959
one minute the same number of parts that it normally
took one worker one full day to assemble.
"Detroit automation" (largely a matter of gains through
automatic moving and handling) is closely associated with
the automobile industry, though by no means confined
to it, of course. In the United States the non-automated
engine plant has died out for all practical purposes. In
the Ford Cleveland plant one man runs a transfer machine
performing more than 500 machine operations, whereas
conventional methods required 35 to 70 men. Formerly
400 workers took 40 minutes to turn out one engine block;
now, under automated methods, 48 workers complete a
bloc in less than half that time.
In the U.S.S.R. a fully automatic plant makes alumini¬
um pistons for heavy truck engines. No human hands
intervene throughout the process and even waste metal is
removed from the machines automatically. The line
adapts to several sizes of pistons, and change-over from
one to the other involves no delay. The machining of
engine blocks, pistons, ring-gears and crankshafts involv¬
ing a wide variety of operations is performed automati¬
cally in line transfer machines in nearly all the principal
automobile-producing factories of the world.
In these plants, wherever they are and whatever their
individual differences, many hundreds of operations are
carried out with only a handful of workers spread out
over many hundreds of feet of complex machinery. This
same type of automation is applied today in fertilizer
plants, in the handling of bulk materials and in many
other plants in many different countries.
Electronic computers use the telephone
Then, of course, there are all the "continuous flow"
industries, such as oil refining and piping, chemicals
(including atomic processing), plastics, paint, bever¬
ages, rubber, flour milling, cement, electric power, tele¬
graphs and telephones, sheet steel and steel castings, and
tanning. A modern oil refinery is almost completely auto¬
matic: the few workers in the plant watch instruments.
At the Esso Petroleum Refinery at Fawley in the United
Kingdom six men per shift handle equipment which distils
5 1/2 million gallons of crude oil per day; in the catalytic
cracking unit only eight men. per shift are used. All
operations are regulated from automatic control panels.
In the new Petrofina plant at Montreal (Canada) an
automatic log records, analyses and reports 400 process
variables, including temperature and pressure in the nine
production units. It types on a log each hour on the hour,
reports abnormal conditions between whiles and in case
of trouble gives the alarm and pinpoints the cause.
In the United States an automatic concrete plant, ope
rated from an electronic control panel, produces and loads
into ready-mix trucks any one of more than 1,500 diffe¬
rent mixing formulae that may be demanded; no manual
labour is used at any point in the process. In Czechoslo¬
vakia the newly opened cellulose factory at Henovce is
a highly automatic production unit.
In most cases, and this is a significant fact, the diffe¬
rent "types" of automation overlap. Electronics, in par¬
ticular, mixes with the others. Its special contribution
to automation is twofold: it extends the range of auto¬
matic control and it has made the processing of informa¬
tion rapid, accurate and automatic. There are two main
types of computer: analogue computers, which measure,
and digital, which calculate.
Analogue computers are used in oil research and ana¬
lysis, oil refining, defence research and operations, indus¬
trial controls of many kinds including automatic lathe
operations, and in milking machines. Digital computers
add, subtract and otherwise cope with mathematical prob¬
lems: they can compare, collate and choose between
logical alternatives; they can store information and bring
it out when they need it again; they can talk to each
other on the telephone and act on what they hear; and
they follow instructions.
Tapes tell machine tools what to do
But electronics goes far beyond office operations in
business, industry or elsewhere. Its distinctive con¬
tribution is in production operations, whether in
machine tool control or in breadbaking or in packing¬
house operations or in the steel industry. With its help,
there can be not only automatic control of continuous-
flow operations in industry but also tape control of machine
tools and operations, with the possibility of changing the
instructions after each job. While this last development
is just beginning to make its way into industry, it will, ,
according to most observers, be very important for the
future, because it means that automation can be applied
to short runs of products and thus to the very large per¬
centage of production which is in this form in all coun¬
tries. Moreover, as an industrial tool, electronics is
changing the concept and function of management as
well as of labour and bringing about many of the more
sweeping changes commonly ascribed to automation gene¬
rally.
There has been intensified concern with automation and
other forms of technological change in the U.S.S.R. and
Eastern European countries.. In the U.S.S.R. automation
is widely used in the engineering industry, in automobile
production, ball-bearing manufacture, on railroads, in
metal-working, food processing, the manufacture of build¬
ing materials, in chemicals, power production, the manu¬
facture of agricultural machinery and in a great many
other types of industrial and office work. The directives
of the 20th Communist Party Congress on the Sixth Five-
Year Plan, 1956-1960, call for a sharp increase in the rate
of automation and set forth targets for the introduction
of automation in production processes in various branches
of industry; heavy industry and the food industries are
to be the chief beneficiaries. In Czechoslovakia and
Poland as well, plans call for a considerable extension of
automation in industry.
In all the more industrialized countries, however, pro¬
gress is uneven. It varies by industries and still more by
undertakings. But the main trends converging towards
fuller automation are making their appearance in some
areas of the economy in all the industrial countries and
are even emerging in particular instances in some of the
economically less developed countries. At present, in
the most highly industrialized countries, and typically in
the U.SJS.R. and the United States, almost every major
area of the economy has been touched by some form of
automation or closely related technological developments.
The development of the peaceful uses of nuclear energy
has been even more spectacular in many ways. Only five
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
years ago it was said that its practical use in industry
could not be expected to materialize for two or three
decades. Yet by 1954 a nuclear energy plant was sup¬
plying power to industry and agriculture in one region of
the U.S.S.R.; in 1955 a town in the United States was for
a short period fully supplied with electricity from a simi¬
lar source; and in 1956 two nuclear energy plants went
into operation in France and the United Kingdom.
All these countries are already planning or constructing
a number of new and larger commercial power plants, but
the movement is by no means confined to them. More
than a score of countries, in all continents, have atomic
energy commissions to study their needs and plan their
programmes. By the autumn of 1956 there were at least
77 reactors in operation: 53 in the United States, ten in
the United Kingdom, four in the U.S.S.R., two in Canada,
seven in various countries of Western Europe and one in
India the first in Asia. Some hundreds of others are
being built or are in an advanced stage of planning. The
great majority of these are for research and experiment
and to train the specialists who will be needed in every
country that wishes to develop an atomic energy pro¬
gramme.
The use of nuclear power for various forms of transport
is developing more slowly than its use for industrial power,
because of the serious technical problems involved. Never¬
theless, the United States already has two nuclear-power¬
ed submarines and plans for nuclear-powered tankers
or large bulk cargo vessels are being developed
there and in France, Japan, Norway, the United Kingdom,
the U.S.S.R. and other countries. In the case of aircraft,
the problem of weight involved in the proper protection of
the persons on board is particularly serious, but it is
expected that a number of nuclear-powered aircraft will
be constructed within a few years.
Another use of atomic energy may well have as far-
reaching consequences as its use as a source of power.
This is the rapidly developing utilization of radio-isotopes,
a by-product of the production of nuclear energy. Radio¬
isotopes are already being used extensively in. research,
medicine and agriculture, and are being ever more widely
used in industry for a great variety of purposes. Here
there is a close link between atomic energy and automa¬
tion. But for the development of certain types of auto¬
mation, the construction of nuclear reactors would not
have been possible; in their turn, radio-isotopes make
possible many of the feedback devices which are the
essential element in one type of automation.
Radio-active Jacks of all Trades
Some idea of the rapid spread of the use of radio-active
isotopes is given by the fact that in the United States
the number of industrial firms employing them
more than doubled between 1954 and 1955. During the
first 11 months of 1955 over 11,000 shipments of isotopes
were despatched from Oak Ridge National Laboratory in
the United States, and in the United Kingdom the number
of consignments over the same period was even higher,
about one-third of the total going to overseas customers
in all parts of the world.
The U.S.S.R. is also making great and increasing use of
radio-isotopes in industry and agriculture and is sup¬
plying them to industry in Czechoslovakia, Poland and
other countries. Canada is also a large user as well as a
large supplier to foreign countries.
Radio-isotopes have many uses in industry. In nearly
every case, they are cheaper, less time-consuming and
more efficient than earlier methods, and in many cases,
they render services which were completely impossible
before; thus the annual saving to the industries of the
world is incalculable. Their use for one purpose alone
detecting the brine level in oil borings has been esti¬
mated to save oil companies some millions of pounds
sterling in a single year.
0 Problem n° 1 : what
in an era of push
will become of workers
button industries?
What is the impact of technological improvements on
employment? The answer depends on how fast and
how generally change takes place. Even more, per¬
haps, it depends on the buoyancy of the economy. So long
as improvements are introduced against a background of
high levels of economic activity and a continuing rate of
economic expansion, the maintenance of the general level
of employment is not likely to be a serious problem pro¬
vided the occupational shifts required to adjust to the
changes can be made.
There is reason to think that heavy investment in auto¬
mation, atomic energy and other technological develop¬
ments will tend to keep economies buoyant. Past experience
shows no reason to believe that technological innovations
lead to a decrease in the global volume of employment.
On the contrary it suggests that such innovations, while
they may cause declines in some areas of employment,
lead in the long run to an expansion of employment by
creating increases in other areas.
In the United States, for example, the number of em-
f\
1/
\ r
A
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1959
ployed persons increased by 25 per cent, between 1940 and
1950 a period of unusually rapid scientific and technolo¬
gical development; and has continued to increase since.
Despite all the technical advances to date, the country's-
employed labour force is at a peak level and unemploy¬
ment at a very low level.
In past years most of the industries which have gone
the furthest with advanced mechanization and automa¬
tion have been those in which employment has been ex¬
panding considerably. To follow along with the United
States example, the telephone industry introduced exten¬
sive automatic dialling and nearly doubled its employment
between 1940 and 1950.
The manufacturing industries which went further with
automation or which supplied equipment for automation
were also among those in which employment increased
considerably. In the communications equipment indus¬
try group, total employment rose from a little over 330,000
in 1947 to just over 500,000 in 1955 an increase of about
52 per cent, in comparison with a rise of only 8.2 per cent,
in all manufacturing industries over the same period.
It is certainly true that science and invention are cons¬
tantly opening up new areas of industrial and commercial
expansion. As the United States Secretary of Labour said
at the Congressional hearings on automation: "While
older and declining industries may show reducing oppor¬
tunity, new and vibrant industries are pushing out our
frontiers. This is the story of industrial America..."
Leading industrialists have pointed out that with the
progress towards automation new areas of employment
are opening up in many fields and in many new indus¬
tries. They believe that the record of economic growth
makes it seem almost absurd to fear unemployment as a
result of improved technology. In Australia, Canada, the
United Kingdom and some western European countries,
experience of the past has been somewhat similar.
On the whole the trend of opinion among employers
and trade unions as to the employment situation is opti¬
mistic but cautious. Nevertheless, and more particularly
in trade union circles, there is an evident fear that things
will not go on for ever as they are ; that a saturation point
may be reached; that, even with decreased hours of work
and increased leisure and new and growing demands, em¬
ployment will soon cease to expand; that old jobs will be
displaced faster than new jobs will be created; and that
unemployment on a wide scale will be the inevitable result
of automatic methods of production and other recent
technological development. What is the basis for these
apprehensions? Essentially, it is the implications of such
facts and figures as the following.
In the United States industrial production in 1955 was
41 per cent, above that for the years 1947-1949; employ¬
ment was up by only 8.3 per cent. In manufacturing
industries in September 1955 there were 600,000 jobs fewer
than in September 1953. In the textile industry employ¬
ment during the last five years has decreased by 20 per
cent. The fear is that employment opportunities are not
keeping pace with rising man-hour productivity.
Add to this the fact of lay-offs in the automobile indus¬
try and the prognostication that this industry, when
further automated, will employ only 200,000 workers as
compared with some 800,000 workers today; that in the
Ford automated engine plants, with only 10 per cent, of
the previous work force, production has been doubled;
that in an automated radio plant two workers turn ouc
1,000 radio sets a day where formerly 200 workers were
required; that in the electronics industry an Industry
often quoted as being one of those which will expand to
take up the slack left elsewhere output in 1952 was 275
per cent, higher than in 1947 but produced by only 40 per
cent, more workers; that in oil refining, employment fell
from 147,000 to 137,000 between 1947 and 1954 while output
rose by 22 per cent.; and, as a last example, that in
12 cases of automation ranging from chocolate refining to
railroad traffic control the reduction of worker require¬
ments ranged from 13 to 92 per cent., with an average
employment reduction of 63.4 per cent.
The same apprehensions are evident in Australia,
Belgium, France, the Federal Republic of Germany and
the United Kingdom. The same types of facts and figures
are adduced to show a clear discrepancy between the
expansion of production and the expansion of employment.
Greatest effect on white-collar workers
Thus, it seems to be the fear of creeping unemploy¬
ment, developing simultaneously with rising pro¬
duction and productivity and spreading from one
industry branch to another, that is at the root of
misgivings about the future. It is cold comfort to reiterate
that the record of the past belies gloomy predictions.
These apprehensions are real and widespread. The only
way in which they can be countered is by concentrating
on the facts in each country, in each industry, in each
undertaking by giving sustained attention to the
changing employment situation, and by careful planning
not only to promote full employment and economic
growth but also to foster social policies for such growth.
Whatever may be the trend of total employment; and
let us note that the present situation at least gives no
cause for alarm it is recognized that large-scale shifts of
workers from one industry, occupation or undertaking to
another are an inevitable consequence of technological
change and that the necessary adjustments can be made
smoothly and easily only in conditions of full employment.
In general, the shifts under way seem to continue and
reinforce trends already evident, showing a general
tendency away from agriculture and from certain manu¬
facturing industries and towards new or developing manu¬
facturing and service industries and occupations.
According to many observers, the shortrun impact of
automation and analogous developments may be greater
on . white-collar employment than on manufacturing
employment. The displacement of the routine clerical
worker by the computer is forecast. It is noted that,
outside of certain manufacturing industries, the greatest
potential for automation lies in office work and that it
is already being introduced rapidly in activities in which
data-processing plays a predominant part.
Finally, so far as the composition of the labour force is
concerned the tendency is for young workers to enter
employment later and for older workers to retire from
work earlier now that old-age pension schemes are
common. In general it is expected that these trends will
be reinforced by recent technological advances. Even
during this last year there has been considerable evidence
that the trend towards raising the school-leaving age and
with it the age for admission into full-time employment
has received a strong impetus as a result of recent
technological developments, among other factors.
For older workers it is recognized that many different
elements are involved in policy and decisions relating to
retirement. For women the general tendency has been
towards greater numerical participation in the labour
force and wider employment opportunities. It may be
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
considered probable that automation and other changes
will reinforce this tendency as well, although transitional
difficulties may be evident in certain occupational sectors
(e.g. relatively unskilled clerical and assembly work).
Both handicapped and older workers men and women
alike may find more opportunities for useful employment
in the automated factories of the future, as more of the
physical functions of production are transferred from
human beings to machines.
Some countries anticipate a slowly growing or static
labour force in future decades and therefore look to the
higher man-hour productivity of automation to compensate
for relative labour shortage in the active age groups.
They believe that this is a most important factor in the
over-all employment outlook, as well as one affecting the
future composition of the labour force.
The trade unions do not blindly oppose technological
innovation but they oppose rationalization involving
worker retrenchment, rationalization which might create
unemployment and worsen what they regard as the
most serious national economic and social problem. Most
employers, on the other hand, are anxious to make use
of modern techniques of production. In most instances
the government is anxious that they shall do so, but it
takes the view that rationalization must not involve any
large-scale displacement of workers and that workers are
entitled to social protection.
Are unemployment fears justified ?
No one can fail to appreciate the anxiety there is about
unemployment and underemployment in the less
developed countries with heavy population pressures
and the many obstacles to stepping up the rate of develop¬
ment. Yet there is no intrinsic reason to suppose that
advanced technologies will make the difficult problems of
employment in those countries any more difficult nor is
there any reason to suppose that automation or other
technological innovations will of themselves solve these
problems.
It is likely, however, that increasingly automatic
methods of production will change the employment
pattern taking shape with industrialization. It is false to
assume that the newly industrializing countries will go
through the same stages as those, experienced by the
older industrial countries. For, example, is it not possible
that the proportion of the labour force absorbed by
manufacturing will be less than might have been expected
before the advent of automation? That a larger propor¬
tion will engage in construction and service (particularly
social service) activities? In the long run, may this not
mean a fuller and more effective utilization of manpower
resources than could ever have been realized through
mass-production methods of the past?
In the Socialist economies technological improvements
do not appear either to lead to overt unemployment or to
generate fear of unemployment, but (they do, as in other
countries, change the pattern of employment opportunity
and distribution. For example, despite the wide automa¬
tion of production carried out in the U.S.S.R. the number
of workers and employees increased by 9.5 million between
1951 and 1955. Soviet authorities emphasize that the pro¬
ductivity increases brought by advancing technology are
continuously creating fresh employment opportunities.
A good many problems of adjustment have sprung up
with the needs for manpower redistribution arising out of
technological advance. A great deal of attention is being
given to their solution. In most of the eastern European
countries the further development of automation and
atomic energy is regarded as essential to compensate the
growing manpower shortage being experienced with the
process of economic development and emphasis has been
placed on the human adjustments which will be required.
Technological 'progress holds out great savings in
labour: let us not be afraid to admit this. These savings
may be taken in the form of (1) higher output (either in
the same industry or in other parts of the economy), (2)
shorter hours, (3) unemployment; or a combination of the
three. The problem, it would seem, is to reach a satis¬
factory combination of the first two and avoid the third.
For some countries the main danger of unemployment
may arise not from too rapid but from too slow progress
in automation and other technological developments. As
a result these countries may lose markets to more efficient
competitors. This is a real danger in countries where
restrictive business practices are adopted by employers
and restrictive labour practices are insisted upon by trade
unions.
Pressure for high Wages by trade unions does not clog
technological progress, but, on the contrary, may promote
it by driving management to install more efficient me¬
thods and machines and by expanding the demand for
industrial goods and services. But rigid demarcation lines
between changing skills, "feather-bedding," unrealistic
views on apprenticeship ratios or length these are among
the factors which may clog technological progress.
Again, unwillingness to take risks, inefficient work
Drop In Industrial Injury Rates In
Podolsk Metal
Goods Factory, U.S.S.R., 1935-1955
7.2
Í
78.0
I
I
I
I
I
I
I
2.97
44.3
1_9 ln|uriesper
workers
1 Days of absence
per 100 workers
I I
1935
ILO drawing
1947 1955
organization, the absence of management development
policies and training facilities these are also factors
which block advance. The dividing line between measures
which are to be regarded as unreasonable restrictions on
technological progress and those which are to' be regarded
as affording reasonable safeguards for the interests of
employers and workers affected by technological progress
is not easy to draw.
Despite many differences of opinion about automation,
especially about how fast it will come and how far
it will go, there is a surprisingly wide area of general
agreement about its impact on Work and life.
The area of agreement can be summarized this way:
Automation is rich 'with promise of higher productivity, of
more goods and services, of higher living standards. It
will have a deep impact on wages, hours, and working
conditions, on labour-management relations. There is a
need to prepare for change in all fields of labour and
social policy.
The I.L.O. has a special responsibility in this field.
Its basic task is to ensure that the human problems of
automation are not neglected. Put positively, its real job
is to make sure that social goals triumph as the new
technology makes its way into the world economy.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1959
Letters to the Editor
ABSTRACT V. REALIST ART
Sir,
My favourite issues are those' that
deal with a special theme such as art
problems, education, some scientific sub¬
ject, etc., but I feel I must say a few
words about the issue dealing with art
treatment of the new Unesco House íd
Paris (November 1958). Why is it that
"world-famous artists" of only one par¬
ticular trend have been invited for the
work only abstractionists, surrealists,
cubists and not a single realist? And
why only artists from a few countries
although the flags of 81 nations wave
over the Unesco building?
If Unesco is an impartial organization
it should have considered the tastes and
interests of all people and not only the
lovers of abstract art.
Is there any need for me to put for¬
ward arguments to support my criticism
of such "art" as the "Encounter in
Springtime" or the Wall of the Moon
and the Wall of the Sun? I do not sup¬
pose that any normal person, except
perhaps the Daltonists, ever believed
the moon to be blue... Surely the bou¬
quet of skeletons (panel in delegates'
lounge, Conference building) is not the
best of Picasso's work that could have
been chosen.
It is a great pity that such so-called
"works of art1' are alleged to be repre¬
sentative of the "products of our epoch".
If they are products of the epoch they
are not the only ones and are cer¬
tainly not the chief product of present-day
art. I should like our international journal,
The Unesco. Courier, to give publicity
not only to the abstract art that so few
people understand but also to show us
artists, prominent people in literature
and art, who have not severed all
connexion with real life our contempo¬
raries and also the great artists of the
Renaissance and of later periods.
Ravil Salievich Vakhidov
Chimkent, U.S.S.R.
Sir,
I leave to the many admirers of
Picasso the time and the pleasure to
appreciate his works. Now that The
Unesco Courier has set the fashion of
adjustment to madness in art we may
fear the worst. On looking at page 22
of your special issue on the Unesco H.Q.
one really wonders who is mad and who
is not. It is not surprising that for some
years past the number of mentally defi¬
cient persons has increased alarmingly.
I sign myself an aesthetically back¬
ward person.
A. Faes
Antwerp, Belgium
Sir,
I think it is an honour for France to
welcome in its capital the headquarters
of a world organization. It is a clear
proof of its fidelity to the humanistic
ideal and of its sense of universality in
matters of ideology and culture. Can
the country which found room for Le
Corbusier's church and the "Christ" of
Germaine Richier to quote simply
examples of religious art now condemn
this new fruit of contemporary art as
something strange and unwonted.
Paris seems to have a special role in
history as the chosen place for artistic
innovations from the Abbé Suger
building the church of St Denis in the
12th century to Gustave Eiffel erecting
his tower in 1889. Parisians quickly
took to the Eiffel Tower despite its revo¬
lutionary form. I hope too that the new
Unesco H.Q. will not only be accepted
by Parisians but by all the French peo¬
ple, not only for aesthetic reasons, but
because they realize that work for peace
is going on inside it and because of
a conviction that they should interest
themselves in it personally and help in
the realization of this work. ,
P. Gay
Lyons, France
Sir,
I am a keen student of artistic ques¬
tions, but since Soviet art critics deny
the value of abstract art, I have had no
opportunity to become acquainted with
the arguments of the followers of this
artistic trend.
I feel you could usefully devote an
issue of The Unesco Courier to the
question of abstract art, including arti¬
cles by the great theorists of this school,
accompanied, of course, by photos of
the best works all the more so because
the illustrations in your magazine are
beyond all praise. The views of connois¬
seurs of realistic art should also figure
in this issue.
Dr, D. Romanov
Gorky, U.S.S.R.
KALINGA ANTHOLOGY
Sir,
I should like to suggest that Unesco
publish the works of winners of the
Kalinga Prize (awarded annually by the
Kalinga Foundation, India, to a leading
interpreter of science), or at least a
selection of these works. Some of them,
especially those of Karl von Frisch,
who was awarded the prize last March,
are not easily obtainable especially in
French and Spanish language editions.
Mariano Celaya
Buenos Aires, Argentine
Editor's note: An issue on this subject
is scheduled for publication next year.
COURIER IN THE CLASSROOM
Sir,
Two years ago the English teacher at
our secondary school advised us to read
The Unesco Courier in place of the
usual, dry textbooks. The magazine be¬
came enormously popular and this year
everyone in the class spontaneously
took out a subscription.
We ourselves choose the subject to be
dealt with in class for we obviously can¬
not make use of all the material in each
issue. This choice is made by majority
vote, thus giving us a taste of demo¬
cracy in practice.
Lessons have gained much from this
use of The Unesco Courier because of
the rare standards of your publication:
the high-level conception of the articles
and the rich photographic presentation
and layout which contrast strongly with
German and>Austrian "illustrateds". I
am leaving school this year but I shall
go on making use of The Unesco
Courier in my future studies and work.
G. Tliur
Salzburg, Austria
MUSIC : A UNIVERSAL TONGUE
Sir,
Don't you think it would be a good
idea to talk about music a basic ele¬
ment of life in The Unesco Courier?
In addition to old-time music and that
of the romantic period, already so well
known, you should also deal with con¬
temporary music, though without going
as far as modern jazz... You should
show the extent to which past music has
influenced that of our own times.
Carlos A. Schilkrut
Buenos Aires, Argentine
GERMAN ROAD PATROLS
Sir,
In your June issue you show a num¬
ber of illustrations on traffic policemen
all over the world (Road Safety is their
Business). Picture No. 3 for the Ger¬
man Federal Republic does not show
traffic policemen, but a fleet of road
patrols of the Allgemeine Deutsche
Automobil Club (ADAC), one of Ger¬
many's large automobile associations.
These road patrols do a very valuable
service to motorists on Germany's high¬
ways in case of breakdowns and acci¬
dents, but they do not have any police
functions whatsoever. In that respect
the caption does not quite fit in the
case of this particular picture.
Velhagën «Sc Klasing
Berlin-Wilmersdorf
German Federal Republic
Sir,
My article "'The Rediscovery of
Africa" which appeared in the
October 1959 issue, is marred by
a very bad mistake. On page 8,
end of second column I am made
to say "... but they (the Africans)
knew, as ancient Asia and Europe
had known, a Bronze Age that
made a long distinctive period of
development before their Iron
Age." The mistake is that the
word "never" has been dropped
and the sentence should read
"... but they never knew, as
ancient Asia and Europe had
known../'
Basil Davidson
London
Ed. Note: We sincerely regret this
typographical error which has com¬
pletely changed the meaning of the
author's sentence.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom...
D RIVERLESS TRACTORS: Every
ninety seconds a tractor leaves a factory
conveyor belt in the U.S.S.R. Among
them are automatic ones which without the
aid of a driver can hold a course exactly
parallel to a prepared furrow, and plough,
sow and harrow. If necessary they can be
directed by radio from a distance of several
kilometres. Soviet designers are now work¬
ing on high-speed tractors which can do
field work at a speed of 25 miles per hour.
^HENT OR INDEPEND&v^
NATIONS UNIES- UNITED NATIONS
OEfcEZUlHEHHfeiE 1IAIUUI
«&NACIONES UNIDAS
U. N. DAY STAMP HONOURS
TRUSTEESHIP COUNCIL
The third U.N. commemorative
stamp for 1959, issued on October
23, the eve of United Nations Day,
honours the United Nations Trus¬
teeship Council. This stamp, the
fourth- in the series depicting the
main organs of the United Nations,
bears a design adapted from . the
sculpture "The Age of Bronze" by
Auguste Rodin. Prepared by Leon
Helguera of Mexico, the design sym¬
bolizes the aspiration of peoples in
the Trust Territories for self-govern¬
ment or independence. The text,
"Trusteeship Council To promote
self-government or independence for
Trust Territories,1" appears in English
upon the 4-cent denomination (oran¬
ge) and in French upon the 8-cent
denomination (green).
FIRE THREAT TO FORESTS:
Nearly one million acres of forest in
Europe have been destroyed by fire dur¬
ing the past five years, reports the U.N.
Food and Agriculture Organization
(FAO). In 14 countries forest fires
increased from 4,157 in 1954 to 6,354
in 1958 while the largest number of
fires and most widespread damage was
reported from Italy, France, Spain and
Greece. Sweden and Norway, coun¬
tries with large forest areas, reported
relatively few fires. Forty per cent of
all forest fires are due to carelessness.
As the FAO points out: "There is no
need of a dropped match or cigarette
end to cause a fire. It is enough when
a forgotten bottle bends the sun's rays
on dry undergrowth.
tr RISONERS HELP THE BLIND:
Inmates of Belgian prisons specially trained
in Braille transcription have produced over
10,000 volumes for the library of the
Belgian Braille League during the past
eleven years. In the Saint-Gilles prison
in Brussels, inmates have also been making
"talking books" recordings in Flemish on
magnetotape for the use of Flemish-speak¬
ing blind persons. The idea of producing
Braille books in prisons was suggested by
the example of Copenhagen where prisoners
transcribe school textbooks for blind chil¬
dren.
PROTECTING ASIA'S CHILDREN:
Over 16 million young people tested for
tuberculosis, ten million examined for
yaws and 2,400,000 mothers and chil¬
dren given a glass of milk each day
these are some of the achievements of
the United Nations Children's Fund
(Unicef) in the course of its work in
Asian countries for the first half of
1959. In addition 632 new health
centres in this region were equipped by
Unicef and supplied with drugs and
diet supplements.
Si
E ÎVERYMAN'S U.N., 1959: The
complete story of the United Nations
family is told in the sixth edition of
Everyman's United Nations, 1959 which
has just been published. This is a com¬
plete handbook of the functions and acti¬
vities of the U.N. and its Specialized Agen¬
cies from 1945 to the end of 1958, and
includes the full texts of the U.N. Charter,
the Statute of the International Court of
Justice and the Universal Declaration of
Human Rights. This issue constitutes the
full history of the first 13 years of the
U.N. Periodic supplements are planned for
the future, rather than complete new edi¬
tions. Running to approximately 650 pages,
it costs $3.50; 25/-stg; 14 Sw.frs.
SCHOOLS IN THE DESERT: In
the past six years the United Nations
Relief and Works Agency (UNRWA)
and Unesco have set up and developed
380 elementary and secondary schools
for the children of the million or so
Arab refugees from Palestine who are
now living in Jordan, the Lebanon, the
Syrian region of the United Arab Re¬
public and in Gaza. These schools which
now operate for 125,000 boys and girls,
are staffed by 3,265 teachers, practi¬
cally all of them Arab refugees and
many of them educated in the refugee
schools themselves. Unrwa also pays
for another 50,000 boys and girls to go
to government or private schools.
(IBERIA'S SCIENCE TOWN: On a
site near Novosibirsk in Siberia which, only
18 months ago, was still covered with thick
pine forests, buildings which will eventually
house the Siberian branch of the U.S.S.R.
Academy of Sciences are rising rapidly.
The scientific centre will comprise 14 re¬
search institutes, a university, residential
sections, a hotel, office buildings, schools
and clubs, all within the space of about eight
square miles. Several institutes have al¬
ready started work in temporary accomoda¬
tion at Novosibirsk where they are tackling
the problems of the development of resour¬
ces in Siberia and the Far East.
THE WORLD'S AGRICULTURE:
The Food and Agriculture Organiza¬
tion of the United Nations (FAO) is
to undertake a world-wide census of
agriculture in 1960. Thousands of train¬
ed enquirers will be used to obtain
replies to hundreds of questions includ¬
ing the number of farmers in the world;
size of farms, crops grown and yield,
kinds and number of livestock, and me¬
thods of watering (canal irrigation, rain,
pumps, etc.) The census, in fact, will
cover every kind of basic factor concern¬
ed with farming, from the land itself
to the number of bees and silkworms or
other forms of life and possessions
which appear in the farm inventory.
For instance, there are 252 different
crops to be dealt with, ranging from
corn to cabbage and from bamboos to
bananas. But this group forms only
one of the ten main sections into which
agriculture has been divided for the pur¬
poses of the census.
R ICHER BY ASIA: During the
next two years, the American Library Asso¬
ciation is organizing a nationwide campaign
to promote better understanding of Asia
and its peoples. In the United States, to
help teachers and others arranging discus¬
sion groups and other activities, a biblio¬
graphy entitled "Richer by Asia" has been
prepared by the Association's Young Adult
Services Division. It gives annotated lists
of books on Asia, sources of materials for
use in discussions and exhibitions, lists of
films, and notes on book talks with sample
quotations from various works. Books
were selected by a committee of young
librarians from school and public libraries,
and are intended as an introduction to Asia,
likely to catch the imagination and interest
of a wide circle of readers.
SUBSCRIPTION
Subscribe today to THE UNESCO COURIER
Fill in this subscription blank and mail it with your cheque or money order to our local
agent in your country listed on page 3 5
Please enter my subscription for THE UNESCO COURIER
One year $ 3.00; I 0/-stg. ; 600 French francs Cheque/Money Order enclosed
Name		
Address
City
Country
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Binders for your
collection of
*Unesco Courier5
We offer subscribers a special binder
for their copies of THE UNESCO
COURIER holding 12 issues of the
magazine. Handsomely produced in
halfcloth with the spine in an attractive
blue and the title (in English, French
or Spanish according to the edition to
which you subscribe) and Unesco co¬
lophon embossed in gold, these con¬
venient and attractive binders, costing
S2.50 ; 12/6 stg. ; or 600 Fr frs, can be
ordered from UNESCO Agents, below.
1-Ï8-.
for
international
understanding
education for
international
understanding
Examples and Suggestions
for Classroom Use
For several years Unesco has been co-operating with some of its
National Commissions to encourage experiments in education for
international understanding. Certain schools in each country have been
designated as participants in a network of "associated schools" created
by the Organization, and each school plans a project aimed at teaching
its pupils something about a foreign land.
In a publication entitled "Education for International Understanding"
Unesco offers to schoolteachers a few ideas drawn mostly from
experience in carrying out some of these projects. Most of the examples
given are taken from reports prepared for Unesco by teachers in many
countries, and they provide a practical guide for colleagues both at home
and abroad.
The booklet describes some classroom practices, methods and teaching
material which can be fitted into the usual school subjects; it shows that
the regular school curriculum offers many opportunities for developing
teaching for international understanding. The first chapters deal with
the three subjects which are basic themes for all "associated schools":
teaching about the United Nations, teaching about human rights, and
teaching about other countries. Other chapters contain supplementary
information such as extra-curricular activities, research and evaluation,
the role of the teacher, etc.
A list of Information Offices and Centres of the United Nations and Its
Specialized Agencies, and addresses of national bureaux of the Interna¬
tional Federation of Organizations for School Correspondence and
Exchanges are included in appendices.
Price: $1,50; 7/6 stg.; 525 F francs.
Where to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write
direct to the National Distributor
in your country (See list below ;
names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request).
Payment is made in the national
currency ; rates quoted are for an
annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Press
Department, Royal Afghan Ministry of
Education, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 369 Lonsdale Street, Melbourne,
C.I, Victoria. (A. 13/-)
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& O., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V (Seh.
37.50.)
BELGIUM. For The Unesco Courier:
Louis de Lannoy, 22, Place De Brouckère,
Brussels, CCP. 338.000. (fr.b. 100.)
Other publications: Office de Publicité,
16, rue Marcq, Bruxelles, CCP 285-98;
N.V. Standaard-Boekhandel, Belgiélei 151,
Antwerp.
BURMA. S.P.C.K. (Burma) 549, Merchant
Street, P.O. Box 222, Rangoon.
CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa,
Ont. (S 3.00).
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd, Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Co¬
lombo 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Librería Económica, Pte Zayas
505-7 Apartado 113, Havana.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia Ltd., 30
Ve Smeckách, Prague 2.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6 Norregade, Copenhagen K. (D.kr. 12)
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agen¬
cy, P.O. Box 120, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akdteeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (F.mk. 540)
FRANCE. Unesco Bookshop, Place de
Fontenoy, Pans, 7". CCP. 12598-48.
(600 fr.)
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8. (DM. 6)
GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Kultura, P.O. Box 149.
Budapest, 62.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; Gunfoundry Road, Hyde¬
rabad, I; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/ I Aiaf AN Road, P. O.
Box 386, New Delhi, I ; Sub-Depots :
Oxford Book & Stationery Co., Scindia
House, New Delhi: Raikamal Prakashan
Private Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby
Road, Bombay I. (Rs. 6.70)
INDONESIA. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Djakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The National Press, 2 Wel¬
lington Road, Ballsbridge. Dublin. (10/-)
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
35, Allenby Road and 48, Nahlat Benja¬
min Street. Tel-Aviv. (I£ 4.-)
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.(10/-).
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo. (Yen 500)
JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road, P.O.B. 66,
Amman.
. KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, P. O. Box Central 64, Seoul.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul
Brück, 33 Grand'Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Peter Chong 8c Co.,
Post Office Box 135, Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta. ( I 0/-)
MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid des
Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (600 fr.)
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9. The Hague, (fl. 6)
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church. (10/-.)
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos. (10/-)
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass 7, Oslo. (N. kr. 10)
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60 The Mall
Lahore ; Bunder Road, Karachi and
3 5 The Mall, Peshawar, (rs.6)
PANAMA. Cultural Panameña, Ave¬
nida 7a, No. Ti-49, Apartado de Correos
201 8, Panama, D.F.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo, P.O. Box
620, Manila.
POLAND. Osrodek Rozpowszechniania
Wydawnictw Naukowych PAN, Paiac
Kultury i Nauki, Warsaw. (Zl. 50.)
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada Lda,
Livrana Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70,
Lisbon.
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Book-
store, Libri Building, Church Street, P.O.
Box 724, Pretoria. (10/-)
SWEDEN. For The Unesco Courier: Sven-
ska Unescoradet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 7.50) other publications
A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl. Hovbokhandel,
Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40 rue du Marché, Geneva. CCP.
1-236. (fr. s. 6.50.)
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Isti-
klal Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church'
Street, Pretoria (10/
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT).
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha,
Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E. I. ( I 0/-)
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22, N.Y. (S3. 00.) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y.
U. S. S. R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska KnjTga,
Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
A FORGOTTEN PEOPLE
ON TOP OF THE ANDES
Seven million Indians living in isolation at dizzy heights
in the Andean highlands of Bolivia, Ecuador and Peru,
are being helped towards better living and working condi¬
tions through joint action by the governments of these
countries, the United Nations and several of its Specia¬
lized Agencies, under the co-ordinating leadership of
the International Labour Organization. See page 21.
.«- :.*i. - "***». , êl 	
]]>
</page>
</document>
