<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="066182eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
A WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
ner
'-.
WORLD HEALTH
TEN YEARS OF PROGRESS
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Il II M II
LIFE COMES BACK TO USELESS LIMBS
Danish child is shown using an apparatus which
frees him from the weight of his body, allowing him
to walk slowly but correctly. One of Who's most
important contributions to the fight against polio
has been the mobilization and integration of virus
researches in many parts of the world. (See page 8)
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
^~*\ A ""MO OW OMN ON TNI MOHO
Courier
MAY 1958
NTH YEAR
No. 5
CONTENTS
PAGE
3 EDITORIAL
By Dr. M.G. Candau
4 TEN YEARS OF PROGRESS
Six major diseases past and present
6 KILLING DISEASES THAT ARE DYING
9 MAN'S SMALLEST ENEMIES: THE VIRUSES
By Dr. A.M.-M. Payne
12 HOW ASIAN FLU SWEPT THE WORLD
15 DOCTOR MALARIA
One man helps 3 million patients
By Jean Manevy
18 THE NEW FACE OF LEPROSY
22 TRANQUILLIZER OR 'PEP* PILL
A modern dilemma
By Ritchie Calder
24 EDE AND THE MOON FESTIVAL
26 SCOTLAND YARD OF EPIDEMICS
Watching over the world's daily health
By Ritchje Calder
28 THE LABYRINTH OF MODERN DRUGS
WHO provides a guidebook
by Ritchie Calder
30 ROUND-THE-WORLD HEALTH REPORTS
32 WANDERING DOCTOR OF DEVIL'S MOUNTAIN
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, I 9 Avenue Kleber, Paris 16, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (12 issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. The United States of America edition is distri¬
buted by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 801 Third Avenue, New
York 22, N.Y., Plaza 1-3860. Second-class mail privileges authorized at New
York, N.Y. (M.C. 58.1.124 A)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER plus jate
of issue", and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions ol UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: $3.00 ; 10/- stg. ; 500 French francs or equi¬
valent.
WHO
COVER PHOTO
THE CULPRITS. Bacteria taken from
throat washings of a case of influenzal
pneumonia being examined at the World
Influenza Centre, set up in London under
the auspices of WHO in 1948. Most
deaths attributed to influenza are in fact
due to the complication of bacterial
pneumonia. Bacteria responsible must
be identified so that correct anti-biotic
treatment can be given. (See page 1 2)
World Health Day this year is also the tenth
anniversary of the day when the Constitution of
the World Health Organization came into force.
It therefore seems a good opportunity for all of us to
review the progress towards better health made during
the last decade in each country and throughout the world.
There have been great scientific advances new drugs,
new vaccines, new or improved insecticides and better
methods of combating and preventing disease.
This new knowledge is being rapidly applied where it
is needed. In the last ten years the flow and exchange
of scientific information and practical experience have
perhaps been greater than ever before. More scientists
and health workers than ever before have gone from
country to country to learn, to teach and to demonstrate.
Even more important is that an increasing number of
people everywhere realize that health is a way of living
and thinking, and not merely the absence of disease and
infirmity. Governments have come to accept their
responsibility for the health of their peoples, and their
obligation to provide, besides the classical hospitals and
institutions, improved environmental conditions, health
care for mothers and children, and safeguards for food
and nutrition.
In all this there is nothing very new. For a hundred
years or more, advances in the science of healing have
been shared freely by all countries, health pioneers have
been urging the importance of sanitation, and govern¬
ments have slowly brought in health legislation and built
up health services. The last ten years are remarkable,
then, for a general speeding up and extension of health
progress along established lines.
But this is not all. Underlying the accelerated progress
has been a profound change in thinking and in method.
At an international health conference held in New York
in 1946 sixty-one governments laid down new principles
for international health co-operation and embodied them
in the Constitution of the World Health Organization,
which came into force two years later.
The nations that banded themselves together twelve
years ago to set up this world co-operative for health
with a programme far out-reaching anything previously
attempted have since been joined by 27 others, bringing
Who's membership to 88.
Their action has already brought a number of benefits
to all. Rapid pooling of information and experience
makes it simpler to contend with diseases like influenza
and poliomyelitis, to meet the threat to mental health
that grows from modern conditions of life, to adapt
medical education to changing needs, and to study emerg¬
ing problems like the hereditary effects of radiations.
Those countries that are struggling to conquer age-old
diseases and to build up modern public health services
benefit further from the practical help given, in the true
"co-operative" spirit, by all countries through Who.
From all this one fact emerges clearly what, ten years
ago, was little more than fine words on paper has now
become a living reality. What was a vision seen only by
few far-sighted men has, with all its imperfections,
become a trusted instrument in the service of all countries.
And this, I venture ,to think, will be considered by future
historians as one of the most significant factors in health
progress in this ten-year period.
Dr. M. G. Candau
Director-General, World Health Organization
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
TEN YEARS
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. May 1958
OF PROGRESS
Cont'd
on
next page
WHO
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
TEN YEARS
OF PROGRESS
(Continued)
KILLING DISEASES
THAT ARE DYING
The phenomenal decline in mortality is the
most significant demographic event of the
last decade, according to the United
Nations Demographic Yearbook.. In the
world as a whole, death rates for 1950-1954
(latest available) were lower than those for
1945-1949, and countries with the highest death rates in
the earlier period (Africa and Asia) experienced the
greatest reduction.
The decline may be attributed in the main to advances
in environmental sanitation and disease control, and it
is reflected in increased life expectancy almost everywhere.
In the more developed countries a new-born girl can be
expected to live 4-5 years longer now than 10 years ago,
a new-born boy 3-4 years longer; and in some of the
countries undergoing rapid development, life expectancy
at birth has increased up to 11 years for girls and 10
years for boys.
With a decreasing rate of death and an almost
unchanged birth rate the population of the world (now
about 2,700,000,000) is growing rapidly: every hour almost
5,000 persons are added, or 120,000 _per day, or 43,000,000
per year an increase calculated to double the world's
population by the end of the century.
Pestilences that stalk no more
The last ten years have seen a dramatic decline in the
extent and severity of the pestilential diseases whose
names terrified our grandfathers cholera, typhus,
smallpox, plague, relapsing fever and yellow fever.
Cholera, for example, has dwindled in importance to
the point of being a problem only in its epidemic foci in
India and Pakistan, and even there a significant improve¬
ment has taken place: from 1945 to 1949 a total of 824,000
deaths were reported, from 1950 to 1954 less than 385,000.
Epidemic typhus is now disappearing from Europe and
North America and declining in the other continents.
Smallpox is claiming fewer and fewer victims; from 1945
to 1949 a total of 193,000 cases were reported in the whole
world compared to 178,000 from 1950 to 1954. Yellow fever
shows a decline of about 50% betwen 1950 and 1955.
Infections down, accidents up
While deaths from infectious and parasitic diseases are
only half of what they were ten years ago, accidents have
become a serious and often leading cause of death,
particularly among children and adolescents.
In North America and parts of Europe, accidents
account for nearly one-half of all deaths among boys
between 5 and 9 years of age. Road accidents claim
most young lives; then come falls, which in some countries
are responsible for up to one-third of all accidental
deaths, then drowning, fire and explosions and poisoning.
Both are doing well
Fewer and fewer women die in childbirth and more
and more babies survive their first step into this world.
In some countries, a 90% decrease in maternal mortality
6
has taken place during the last 20 years. In 1955, the
maternal death rate, as calculated per 1,000 live births,
was lowest in New Zealand: 0.4; 20 years ago it was 3.8.
The decrease is most spectacular in the countries under¬
going rapid development, for example Ceylon where the
drop was from 20.5 in 1936-1938 to 4.1 in 1955.
As regards infant mortality, the lowest rate in the world
is recorded in Sweden, where it dropped from 22 per
thousand live births in 1951 to 17 in 1956.
Malariaa monster in retreat
At least three-fourths of mankind live in malaria zones.
Up to 1948, about 300 million people were attacked by
malaria each year and 3 million died. During ten years
of malaria campaigns, these figures have been cut by 30%
but the disease still presents a huge international health
problem.
However, with the insecticides and drugs that are now
available, malaria eradication is possible almost
throughout the world, provided that campaigns are
pushed hard enough before insect-resistance to spraying
develops.
Some regions are close to the goal: in Southern Europe,
4,000,000 new cases a year were reported before the in¬
troduction of DDT spraying now less than 10,000 a year.
In the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics there were some
4,330,000 cases of malaria immediately after World War II.
In 1956 fewer than 13,000 new cases were found and no
new infections are expected to occur after 1960. In the
Americas, malaria once menaced 135,000,000 people. To
date 105,000,000 have been protected and the vigorous
campaigns now going on are expected to complete the
protection within a few years. In Africa south of the
Sahara, malaria presents the most serious and difficult
problem with which the specialists are confronted. Never¬
theless, at the end of 1955, 14,000,000 of the 116,000,000
Africans living in malarial regions had been protected
against the disease.
Even in the Eastern Mediterranean countries, tradition¬
al reservoir of malaria, striking results have been achiev¬
ed during ten years of antimalaria work; before, 40,000,000
people suffered regular attacks of the disease, now less
than 14,000,000.
These are the modern killers
Heart disease and cancer are not only the largest causes
of death in the majority of highly developed countries,
but they are on the increase.
In England and Wales, for example, deaths due to
cancer in 1947 accounted for 15.1% of all deaths. By
1955, the percentage had risen to 17.6. In Denmark the
increase was from 16.2 in 1947 to 21.8 in 1955, and in the
United States of America from 4.7 to 15.7.
In most of the highly developed countries, deaths from
cancer of the . respiratory system represent a growing
percentage of all deaths due to cancers.
Also deaths from degenerative disease of the heart and
arteries (the most frequent cause of death in North
America and most of Europe) are increasing. Among the
possible causes is the aging of the population and
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
consequent swelling in tne 40-80 age-group in which these
diseases are most prevalent. Also, diagnostic techniques
have improved, decreasing the number of deaths formerly
attributed to "senility" or to "unknown causes."
New defences against polio
The discovery in 1949 of a method of growing
poliomyelitis virus in tissue cultures revolutionized the
study of polio and eventually resulted in large-scale
vaccination campaigns with the killed-virus vaccine of the
Salk-type.
In the United States of America, for example, 70 million
people had been vaccinated by the end of 1956. That
year, the number of polio cases reported was the lowest
since 1947: 15,400 compared to 57,879 in 1952 which was a
record year for poliomyelitis. However, it has not been
possible to attribute the low incidence in 1956 entirely to
the vaccine. In 1957, Who recommended large-scale trials
with a new live-virus vaccine which can be given orally,
instead of being injected.
Tuberculosisa turning point
Tuberculosis is killing relatively fewer people each year.
For example, between 1950 and 1955 death rates per
100,000 population dropped from 58.1 to 31.1 in France;
from 13.8 to 6.3 in Denmark; and from 143.6 to 63.0 in
Portugal. Nevertheless, tuberculosis is still the greatest
killer of all infectious and parasitic diseases, and in North
America, Europe and Australia, it accounts for three-
fourths of all deaths from these diseases occurring after
the age of 15.
A considerable change in the age distribution of deaths
from tuberculosis of the respiratory system has taken
place: before World War II the majority of victims were
women between 20 and 30 years of age and men between
40 and 55. Now, deaths are most numerous among people
over 60, women and men alike.
In 1955, a turning point was reached in the world
outlook on tuberculosis with the advent of new drugs
promising a revolution in the management of the disease.
Pilot studies are being sponsored by Who to determine
whether the new drugs can effectively be used in large-
scale home treatment of tuberculosis victims.
History's greatest vaccination campaign
In history's greatest campaign of immunization, 192 mil¬
lion people have been tested, and 74 million vaccinated
against tuberculosis with BCG (Bacillus Calmette-Guérin)
between 1948 and 1957. The work was started in war-
torn Europe by Scandinavian relief organizations and later
expanded to the other continents with the aid of Who and
Unicef. Since 1951 the campaign has been supported by
these two international bodies in close co-operation with
the governments concerned. By far the largest part of
the programme, both with regard to the number of coun¬
tries and the number of persons involved, has been carried
out in Asia.
Pneumonia steady at new low
A substantial decrease in the number of deaths from
pneumonia has taken place since penicillin and other
antibiotics became available.
Most lives have been saved in New Zealand, Switzerland,
Italy, the Netherlands, the United States and Sweden,
where the decrease in pneumonia deaths ranges from
62.1% to 53.1%. Next come Norway, Denmark, Canada,
Finland, Austria, Scotland, Ireland, Germany and Japan,
The Unesco Courier. May 1958
with a drop of 43% to 32.6%. The figures for South
Africa, Northern Ireland, England and Wales, and Portu¬
gal have gone down from 26.2% to 14.1%.
Nevertheless, pneumonia still ranks among the 10
diseases causing the greatest number of deaths in the
more developed countries. It remains one of the three
leading causes of death among infants, and is even more
serious among the aged. Little variation in the death
rate for pneumonia is at present being reported from one
year to the next, and it can be assumed that it will remain
at the present level for some years to come.
Fewer beds, yet more patients
Mental patients occupy between 40 and 50% of all the
hospital beds in Europe and North America. There are
not enough beds for thousands more who might benefit
from hospitalization. How can this pressure be eased?
New mental treatment techniques now being applied in
several countries may provide one answer. Ten years ago
in Ville-Evrard, France, for example, the average stay of
patients before discharge was over one year; now it is
four months. This hospital which in 1948 had 550 beds
and admitted 100 new patients a year, now has only 270
beds but gives care to 600 new patients a year and the
percentage of patients that must be kept indefinitely has
gone down from 50% to 7%.
Diphtheria capitulates
A prevalent disease at the beginning of the twentieth
century, diphtheria is now in full regression throughout
the world, particularly in Europe which was the continent
most seriously affected. In a number of countries, among
them the United Kingdom and Denmark, diphtheria has
to all intents and purposes disappeared through vaccina¬
tion campaigns.
In 1948, 119,000 cases were reported from the whole of
Europe. Now the annual number of cases is less than
half that and in 28 countries in Asia, America and Europe,
the number of deaths from the disease dropped from 5,148
in 1950 to 2,824 in 1955.
Whooping cough still strikes
Although still the most deadly of infectious diseases for
children, whooping cough is on the retreat. In 28
countries all over the world, deaths from this disease
dropped from 26,325 in 1950 to 10,376 in 1955. The highest
death rate is among children less than one year old but
it is in this age-group also that the decrease is most
striking: from 7,874 in 1950 to 1,623 in 1955. Whooping
cough is unique among the diseases of childhoood as it
usually strikes and kills more girls than boys.
Who is getting medical care
There are now 1,236,000 physicians serving the world's
2,700,000,000 inhabitants and the 638 medical schools
operating in 85 countries graduate annually about 67,000
new doctors.
There are 14 countries fortunate enough to have one
doctor to serve every thousand or fewer people. But there
are 22 others where there is only one doctor for 20,000 or
more inhabitants. Between these two extremes, the rest
of the world shows great variations.
As a general rule, there is a shortage in rural areas,
while cities have been known to have an over-abundance
of medical practitioners.
While nine countries have one medical school for less
than one million of population, there are 13 countries with
only one such school for 9 to 17 million people.
7
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
SHIGENORI
HAS WON
HIS FIGHT
OVER POLIO
When Shigenori Kameyama was a baby living on
Kyushu Island in the south of Japan an attack of polio
paralysed him so that he could not lif: a hand nor
move a leg. His pathetic and useless life might have
continued indefinitely had he not been taken at the
age of eight to the Se/sh; Ryogo En Institution in
Tokyo, a special "hospital-school-and-home" for
the rehabilitation of crippled children which, since
1950, has been gradually transformed by the Ministry
WHO photos by Dominique Darbois
of Health and Welfare Into a demo-stration centre
for the entire country. (Beginning In 1952, Who
and Unicef helped by providing fellowships for
Japanese to learn other countries' rehabilitation
techniques.) When Shigenori entered the Tokyo
"hospital-home" he was incapable of standing on
his twisted feet, even when someone held him.
But the treatment he receivedmassages, baths, a
small surgical intervention, exercises, electrotherapy
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Moy 1958
The mysterious virus
SMALLEST ENEMY
OF MANKIND
by
A.M.-M. Payne
Chief, Section of Endemo-epidemic Diseases, World Health Organization
and above all his own tenacity, brought a wonderful
change. When he left the hospital last year he was
not I 00% rehabilitated, but he could get up unaided,
brush his teeth, dress himself, and go out into the
street unafraid. Photos show: (opposite page)
young patients in the hospital's bathing room;
(above) Shigenori smiles a victorious smile after his
first halting steps, and uses a large doll (bottom photo)
to learn simple things like buttoning his clothes.
If the era of Pasteur, Koch and Lister has been properly
called the era of bacteriological revolution, the last
twenty years equally have the right to be known as
the era of virological revolution. Technical advances in
the basic sciences have provided new tools which have
been applied to the study of viruses with remarkable
results. New techniques and methods have opened up
vast new fields in our understanding of the ecology of
micro-organisms in general and viruses in particular.
The word "ecology" needs definition since it contains a
concept which is fundamental to the modern approach
to many aspects of medicine, not only communicable
diseases but also many other problems of human life, such
as mental illness, accidents, chronic degenerative
diseases, etc. Ecology is the study of the interactions of
organisms and environments. No living thing, be it a
human being or a virus, can be studied in isolation from
its environment. Here I will confine myself to the inter¬
actions of viruses and animal organisms, especially the
human animal, and the environments in. which these
interactions occur.
It might be thought that this is an unnecessarily broad
approach to an outline of progress in the understanding
of human virus diseases, but that is not so. Indeed, it is
true to say that it is largely because of the breadth of
this approach that progress has been so rapid and
promises to continue at unreduced speed. Different
aspects of the ecology of. virus diseases have been studied
by specialists in widely different disciplines, including, as
well as virologists, biochemists, geneticists, immunologists,
epidemiologists, pathologists, clinicians, veterinarians,
sanitarians, anthropologists, zoologists, entomologists,'
plant biologists, etc., and often it is only by consideration
of the findings of all that the true picture will be seen
and a final understanding and solution of a problem
arrived at. As yet it must be admitted that we have
not reached this goal for any virus disease, although for
some diseases it appears to be within sight.
Viruses are the smallest known living things if it is
accepted that the essential quality of life is the ability
to reproduce. Viruses, however, cannot reproduce inde¬
pendently of other living cells. This, and other facts,
including the fact that certain viruses when highly puri¬
fied can be prepared in crystalline form, has led to many
arguments as to whether they are really alive. During
the past ten years a tremendous amount of information
regarding the nature of viruses, their size, shape, density,
autonomous existence, origin, reproduction, metabolic
activity, chemical composition, their antigenic qualities
which provoke defensive reactions in the animal host and
so forth has been accumulated so that now the question
as to whether they are alive seems largely philosophical.
Their ecology is that of living things.
A virus in order to survive must come into contact with
a susceptible host, or more specifically a susceptible cell
in that host, it must be able to multiply in the host, it
must be capable of being dispersed so as to reach a fresh
host, and it must be able to survive outside while seeking
a fresh host. These activities have been
neatly expressed as getting in, multiplying,
getting out, and getting about. This picture
has been modified in the process of evo¬
lution. If we can attribute a purpose to the
form of life we call a virus, that purpose is
Cont'd
next page
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
VIRUSES
(Continued)
Three types of polio
are now recognized
to survive and it can do this best by coming to terms with
its host as it were, living together without doing harm,
taking its nourishment and reproducing in as unobtrusive
a way as possible and having a way out so that its progeny
may get out into the world in search of new living quar¬
ters. Most virus infections are indeed inapparent, and a
lethal or damaging relationship is relatively uncommon,
yet it is just these latter which are important in medical
science.
Never before has this fact been so evident as now, as
a result of the technical advances of the last ten years.
Perhaps the most far reaching of these is the development
of tissue-culture techniques. Cultures of living tissues are
not new. They have been practised, albeit with some dif¬
ficulty, for three or four decades. The discovery of anti¬
biotics overcame one of the major problems of ensuring
the sterility of these culture, and this, in association with
advances in the composition of the media in which the
cells are grown, in the choice and methods of preparation
of the cells for culture and recognition of the destructive
effect of viruses on the cells, the cytopathogenic effect, has
made tissue cultures the most widely used method of
growing viruses in the laboratory. Application of these
new techniques has resulted in the isolation and identi¬
fication of many hitherto unknown viruses, some of which
have been proved to cause disease while others appear
to be harmless. Dozens of new viruses have thus been
discovered in the last ten years and no one knows how
many more remain to be discovered. The situation is
quite comparable 'with that of the era of the bacterio¬
logical revolution when many different kinds of bacteria
were recognized for the first time and the long process of
identification, classification and recognition of their signi¬
ficance began.
Broadly, the new viruses of medical importance may be
grouped under three headings according to their source
those isolated from the alimentary tract, often referred
to as enteroviruses ; those isolated from the respiratory
tract, which include the adenoviruses and the influenza
viruses; and those isolated from insects, the arthropod-
borne or "arbor" viruses.
More victims among older people
The enteroviruses include the well-known polioviruses
responsible for poliomyelitis as well as others less
well known: the Coxsackie viruses and the so-called
echo viruses. The Coxsackie viruses, named after the small
town in New York State where they were first isolated,
fall into two groups, A and B, and two dozen types have
been recognized. Many of them can be isolated from
stools or from the throat in tissue culture but their most
striking characteristic is the ability of most of them to
infect infant but not adult mice. They have been shown
to be responsible for a variety of diseases including aseptic
(i. e. non-bacterial) meningitis, herpangina (an affection
of the throat), pharyngitis, pleurodynia (a painful affec¬
tion of the chest which occurs in epidemics), and a severe
form of encephalomyocarditis in infants (an affection of
the heart and brain).
Some of the nineteen echo viruses so far discovered have
been identified as the cause of extensive epidemics of
aseptic meningitis, others cause summer diarrhoea, parti¬
cularly of infants and young children, the role of others
in producing disease is still unknown and it is quite prob¬
able that some are harmless parasites.
The most important of the enteroviruses are the polio-
viruses which I will consider in some detail, partly because
10
of the dramatic advances made during the last ten years,
and partly because it is an admirable example of the
importance of understanding the ecology of diseases in
developing control measures.
Before the last World War poliomyelitis was regarded
as a problem confined to a few countries and believed to
be rare in most parts of the world. It was thought then
to be primarily a disease of the central nervous system,
transmitted by the respiratory route, the virus probably
reaching the nervous system along the nerves of the nose
and throat. During and after the war, there was an
alarming increase in the incidence of the disease, not only
in countries already affected, but many other countries
also began to suffer epidemics of increasing severity and
frequency. Furthermore, the disease in some countries no
longer took the form of an infantile paralysis but began
to affect more and more people in older age groups, until
in some countries one third or more of the cases were
over the age of fifteen and older people seemed to suffer
more severely.
Is vaccine the final solution ?
Ten years ago the prospects for controlling such a
disease seemed remote indeed. The first big step
forward was the recognition that the infection was
widespread in areas where the clinical disease was rare,
that is to say symptomless infections were far more
common than had been thought, several hundred times
more common than clinical cases, and these infections did
not appear to involve the central nervous system. It was
already known that the alimentary tract of certain pri¬
mates could be infected so that attention was directed to
the possibility that it might be essentially an alimentary
infection which only occasionally involved the central ner¬
vous system.
The next big step was the recognition that there was
not one but three types of poliovirus, all capable of caus¬
ing disease but giving little or no cross-protection against
each other. Then came the great discovery that the
viruses could be grown in cultures of non-nervous tissue.
This not only cast further doubt on previous concepts of
the ecology of the infection but also made it possible
to undertake extensive epidemiological studies, impossible
when monkeys had to be used. It also raised the possi¬
bility of producing virus in such quantities that a vaccine
might be made.
Hopes were raised further by the discovery that the
primary site of infection was indeed the alimentary tract
and that the virus appeared to reach the nervous system
through the blood stream. This made it seem likely that
if antibodies or protective substances could be produced
in the blood by means of a vaccine they might act as a
barrier and prevent the virus from reaching the nervous
system and so causing disease. This would have been an
unlikely possibility if the virus travelled along the nerves.
Developments in tissue-culture techniques, particularly
the development of a synthetic medium for the growth
of the cells, accelerated progress which culminated, as is
well known, in the development of a vaccine now shown to
be both safe and effective in preventing paralysis after
infection with poliovirus.
However, quite apart from the problems
which still remained regarding production,
testing and use of the vaccine, it was not
regarded by many scientists as a final
solution to the problem of poliomyelitis.
Cont'd
on
page 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. May 1958
PINHE ADS
MARK POLIO'S
PATH ACROSS
A CAPITAL
WHO photos
In the hospital of Hornbeck on the Danish coast close to Elsinore, a little girl is alive and breathing thanks to a
Swedish apparatus connected directly with the trachea (above). She was one of the 3,000 people who caught
polio when the city of Copenhagen experienced its worst-ever epidemic of this disease in I 952. The outbreak
in Copenhagen was one in a long series of such epidemics which have been growing and spreading all over the
world since the first occurred in Stockholm in 1887. Map of Copenhagen (below, left) is covered with a rash
of pins, each representing a polio case (white ones show cases of paralysis of the respiratory muscles). Denmark had
a polio rate of I 3 I cases per 1 00,000 inhabitants in the I 952 epidemic. Hornbeck hospital is a rehabilitation
centre, and also does virus research. Below, right, test tubes filled with living tissue which have been infect¬
ed with polio virus and liquid allowing the tissues to grow. This is part of the work involved in finding a vaccine.
1 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
HOW ASIAN FLU SWEPT
AROUND THE WO RLD
On May 4, I 957 reports of a 'flu epidemic came to the World Health Organization from Singapore.
Within a few months "Asian 'flu" had girdled the world. (See map below). A WHO network of
57 influenza centres in 46 countries went into action. The micro-organism was found to be a "new"
virus and was given the name Virus A/Singapore/ 1/57. All possible measures were taken to isolate
the virus and produce a vaccine against it. Headquarters of the battle was the World Influenza
Centre in London (entrance shown, far right) where a constant search is made for 'flu viruses and
a universal vaccine against all types of influenza. Viruses are grown in fertile eggs for two to three
days after which the flu'd is removed from the infected eggs (right) in an ultra-violet chamber to
prevent bacteriological infection. This fluid, after several days in a refrigerator, becomes the vaccine.
WHO photos
Probable origin of epidemic
Q First wave
O First cases from May to August
H Second wave
The figures represent the months when the first cases appeared
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier.
VIRUSES
(Continued from page 10)
The
'Tamed'
1958May
ones
give immunity
The vaccine was effective, but not completely effective;
furthermore, it was shown that although it prevented
paralysis it did not prevent infection, and it was
considered probable that the immunity after vaccination
would be of relatively short duration, thus requiring
reinforcing doses at intervals throughout life. The
vaccine was unable to influence the spread of virulent
viruses in nature so that there could be no prospect of
eliminating the disease. Attention was therefore turned
to the ecology of the natural disease and it was found
that in many parts of the world the balance between
infection, immunity and disease was as favourable as we
have been able to achieve by artificial means in many
other communicable diseases.
This favourable situation seemed to be associated with
the widespread dissemination under conditions of poor
hygiene of viruses, many of which seemed to be of low
virulence, so that few very young children escaped natural
immunizing infections at an age when symptoms were
least likely to develop.
Considerable progress has now been made towards
reproducing and improving on this natural process. In
the laboratory, strains of virus of very low virulence have
been developed and initial trials on humans shown that
they can still produce alimentary infection and stimulate
the formation of protective antibodies without producing
disease, and there are good reasons to believe that this
immunity is long lasting, possibly life-long. Furthermore,
immunity is produced to reinfection of the alimentary
tract, so that control of the circulation of natural viru¬
lent viruses - becomes itheoretically possible. However,
more work is needed before we can be.^ sure that these
attenuated viruses will remain harmless when used on a
large scale in man. This is the crucial question because
these viruses get out and about in the stools and can
infect other persons just as naturally occurring viruses do.
This will not matter if they remain stable but we do not
yet know whether they will.
When antigen meets antibody
In the field of respiratory virus diseases there have been
similar developments. Many new viruses have been
discovered and much progress has been made in the
study of previously recognized viruses. Influenza remains
the most important epidemic respiratory disease and,
during the past ten years, two more influenza viruses,
influenza c and d, have been discovered. However, the
progress in the study of the two most important influenza
viruses, a and b, especially the former, has been even more
striking. World-wide studies of the evolution of the
influenza viruses have been intensified since 1947 and
certain patterns have emerged which increase our hopes
of eventually limiting the effects of this disease.
Here again it is the interaction of the* virus and its envi¬
ronment both inside and outside the host that is impor¬
tant. Protective antibodies are produced in the body in
response to the stimulus of substances known as antigens
which are part of the infecting micro-organism, and anti¬
bodies are one of the most important defences of the
body against disease. They are generally highly specific:
reacting only with the antigen which stimulated their
formation. The influenza virus behaves as if it can
change its dominant antigens so that previously existing
antibodies can no longer interfere with its ability to pro¬
duce infection and disease.
It now appears that one of the influences which brings
about this change is the presence in the population of
the antibody itself. An influenza a virus which has spread
widely begins to find it difficult to infect new hosts
because they already have antibodies, difficult to multiply,
and difficult to get out and about. It is in danger of
failing to survive. Some viruses in special circumstances
do in fact die out in this way; measles in the Pacific
Islands, where after causing a devastating epidemic the
virus dies out from lack of susceptibles, is one example.
But the influenza virus is antigenically
unstable, the dominant antigens which it
presents on its surface and which are
exposed to antibodies can change and,
when this happens, the new virus has a
Cont'd
on
next page
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
VIRUSES
(Continued)
Flu virus has its
'fingerprints' taken
much better chance of survival, finding susceptible hosts,
and getting out and about. This can be compared with
evolution by natural selection. Minor changes of this kind
occur fairly often, every two or three years, and the new
virus causes the epidemics with which we are familiar.
However, at longer intervals, every ten to fifteen years
or so, a much bigger change occurs so that the virus finds
no antibodies to restrict its multiplication and spread,
with the result that a pandemic such as occurred in 1957
may ensue. At first it seemed that the 1957 virus was
entirely new but then it was discovered that some elderly
persons already possessed antibodies which showed that a
similar virus had been prevalent in the world before, some
seventy years or so ago, and possibly had been the cause
of the pandemic which occurred in 1889-1890.
Seeking a universal vaccine
If this is true, it raises the possibility that the changes
which the influenza virus can undergo are limited and
that viruses which have been prevalent in the past but
which have apparently disappeared may reappear in the
future. The process therefore may not be truly evolu¬
tionary but rather revolutionary in the sense that it may
go round in a circle. When we know all the possible
forms the virus can take we may be able by vaccination
to produce antibodies against all of them. The virus will
then be unable to take us by surprise as it did in 1957.
Implicit in these observations is the fact that infection
with a virus leaves permanent traces in the form of the
specific antibodies already mentioned. When we have the
appropriate antigen we can discover whether man has
had previous experience of that antigen during his life¬
time. Such studies have wide applications in the under¬
standing of virus diseases. In influenza it has been shown
that the influenza virus of swine was prevalent in man
about the time of the 1918 pandemic and it seems likely
that it, or a closely related virus, may have been the cause
of that pandemic. The postulated re-emergence of the
1889 virus from some unknown situation and the fact that
the swine virus no longer affects man, but persists in
pigs, has raised the possibility that certain animals may
play a role in the ecology of human influenza. This is at
present speculation but several important studies are in
progress and, if it proves to be correct, it will be a major
advance.
A number of other viruses causing upper respiratory
infections have been discovered, the most important group
being the adenoviruses of which several types have been
identified. Some of them have been incriminated as the
cause of epidemic respiratory disease and some can infect
the eye, causing a form of conjunctivitis. An effective
vaccine has been developed against these viruses. The
common cold, although not serious in itself, remains one
of the major pests of mankind. Several viruses causing
a similar clinical picture have been discovered and it
now appears that it is not an entity but may be due to
a number of different agents. We are still a long way
from a solution of this problem but the application of the
new techniques gives us more hope for the future.
Monkeys spread yellow fever
Smallpox and yellow fever were in the past two of the
most dreaded virus diseases. We can now exercise a
large measure of control over these diseases but,
neverthless, problems still remain. With yellow fever the
problem results from its ecology. In both the Americas
and in Africa the infection persists in monkeys and cer¬
tain other animals and cannot be eradicated. It is indeed
spreading in the jungles of Central America. We can
protect man with a highly effective vaccine and we can
14
prevent occurrence of the disease in , epidemic form in
towns by eradication of the mosquito which transmits the
disease, but the prevention of the spread of the disease
to other parts of the world requires constant vigilance.
In connexion with the studies on Russian Spring Sum¬
mer encephalitis, an interesting concept has been de¬
veloped, that of natural foyers or focal areas of disease in
which, because of the total ecology of ah area, including
animal, insect and plant life and the physical conditions,
a focus of infection can persist apparently indefinitely
unless the ecological situation is disturbed by outside
interference, such as destruction of vegetation, animal or
insect life. Indeed, when the ecology of an area is known
it is possible, within limits, to anticipate which diseases
may be present. Such areas must be defined and steps
taken to prevent human disease and the possible spread of
the infection, by vaccination or other means.
The causes of other more mundane diseases such as
the viruses of measles and chicken pox have also been
isolated in the last ten years and are now being studied
in the laboratory. Others, such as the viruses of infec¬
tious hepatitis, serum hepatitis (two forms of jaundice),
glandular fever and trachoma are still elusive. The eye-
disease, trachoma, is particularly important since it is
widespread over a large part of the world. However, the
so-called virus is probably not a "true" virus for various
reasons including the fact that it responds to antibiotics
which the true viruses do not. Furthermore, coincident
bacterial infections seem to be very important in increas¬
ing the severity of the damage of the eye and these can
also be controlled by antibiotics. We can therefore exercise
a considerable degree of control over the disease even
though we cannot as yet study the virus in the laboratory.
Bats carry the dreaded rabies
A review of progress in virus diseases during the last
ten years would not be complete without mention of
that dreaded disease: rabies. There have been
several important advances. The first is the development
of a live virus vaccine which, when used to immunize dogs,
is most effective in preventing introduction of rabies into
human communities which commonly occurs through in¬
fection of dogs, sometimes by wild animals. The second
advance was the preparation of a hyper-immune serum
which, used in conjunction with vaccine, has been proved
to be much more effective in the treatment of humans,
especially after severe bites, than the vaccine alone as
was formerly practised.
The third advance has been the discovery of rabies in
insectivorous bats in the Caribbean area, in the United
States of America, and in Europe. This is different from
rabies in the vampire bat which has been known for
decades. It seems that, unlike other animal, insectivorous
bats do not always die from the infection; at least not
within a short period. A lengthy period of survival of
the bat in an infectious condition is obviously more favour¬
able for the survival of the virus than the short period
of survival usually seen in other animals. This may
explain a number of features of the ecology of the
disease which have hitherto been little understood.
In the short space available I have only been able to
touch on some of the highlights of recent progress.
However, it is evident that great strides have been made
and just as we have seen more and more bacterial diseases
brought under control in the past, so we may expect to
see an increasing number of virus diseases controlled in
the future. At the same time we must bear in mind that
no living thing exists in isolation. Its behaviour depends
on its environment which is more or less constantly
changing. We must therefore remain on the alert for
the emergence of new diseases or changes in the pattern
of old ones.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. May 1958
by Jean Manevy
Snuffling like a seal, "'Doctor Malaria" emerges from the
ice-cold water of a mountain stream, with the gills of a
four-pound trout between his finger-tips.
"'There's our dinner. All it needs is a few minutes in the pan."
In the heart of Kurdistan, in the rocky wilderness of the Gorges
of Prince Ali, on the boundaries of Iraq, Turkey and Persia, the
world is still in its Old Testament stage. If a man wants to eat,
he must know how to catch a fish and snare a wild-fowl. If he
wants to get any sleep, he must know exactly how to pick a safe
camping site, and he mustn't be afraid of scorpions or snakes.
'"In India", says Dr. Malaria, "I had to do away with a leopard
which seemed to want to make a meal of my wife, and I had my
car smashed to smithereens by elephants. In Dankala, a herd
of wild donkeys ran amok in my camp, and three of my camels
died of thirst. A bunch of bandits took me prisoner so that
they could use me as their family doctor. We've pitched camp in
all sorts of deserts and forests even voléanos. My daughter
narrowly escaped being born in a tent. One fine day, my eldest
Forbidden
to wear blue
In the territory covered
by Dr. Malaria lives
a strange religious sect
of people who are Inacces¬
sible to most foreigners.
They are called Yezidis,
number about 70,000,
and are led by the tribal
chief, Sheik Thassyn
(shown here in conver¬
sation with Dr. Malaria).
The Yezidis wear bright
colours, such as red which
they incorporate in their
intricate turbans. Unlike
most of their neighbours
they consider blue as an
evil colour. Their women¬
folk (never veiled) wear
brightly coloured robes,
but never blue ones.
WHO
son fell into the camp fire. That's been the daily ritual for the
last fifteen years."
For the last fifteen years, Doctor Malaria has gone on his
rounds in Eritrea, India, Switzerland, Liberia, Sierra Leone, Gam¬
bia, the Sudan, Iraq first for Italy's health authorities, and more
recently as a technical expert of the World Health Organization.
Doctor Malaria was born, an Italian national, in Tunis. His
father came from Sardinia. His real name is Luigi Mara. But
that name can sound so like the word "'malaria'" that, throughout
the whole length and breadth of Kurdistan and Iraq, where he
directs the struggle against the marshland plagues, he has been
christened "'Doctor Malaria", or, alternatively, "'El Mudie Malaria"
(Big Chief Malaria) which makes things simpler all round. In
the same way, when the people of those parts talk about his
family, they refer to "'The Malaria Tribe", since most of the
doctor's trips are made with the whole family in tow. The
family consists of Tina, his wife, Gian Paolo and Enrico, his
two sons, aged fifteen and thirteen (who are at present at school
and temporarily parted from rest of the family) and lordana,
his daughter, aged eight.
It was six years ago that Iraq, worried because her economic
development was threatened by the presence of malaria on the
largest stretch of her territory, applied to the World Health
Organization for help?- And it was to Doctor Malaria that there
was entrusted the most seriously threatened part of the country,
Kurdistan, which stretches east of the Tigris to the Zagros
Mountains and Anatolia.
The Kurds are mostly nomads, rough mountain folk who haunt
the valleys of Anatolia and the Zagros Mountains. You can tell
them by their heavy black woollen turbans, their caftans of bright
cotton, their baggy trousers fastened at the ankle and kept up
by thick waistbands, and their green and red and black cotton
robes. You can also tell them by their women-folk, who are
adorned with trinkets made up 01 gold and silver coins, and
who wear rings in their ears and sometimes in their noses.
How many of them are there ? Three million, say some. But
who can really take a census of tribes which drift about between
Turkey, Iraq, Persia and Syria? Who can say for sure how
many Kurds there are who have decided to stop roaming and
settle down in mud-hut villages which are evacuated whenever
the landowner decides not to go on cultivating his land, or
whenever something which looks to the Kurds like Authority
tries to count heads?
The doctor first tackled the problem of the non-nomadic clans;
his team, which consists of an entomologist (a man who spies
upon the secret life of mosquitoes), a sanitary inspector (who was
responsible for the spraying, in 1955, of twenty-five tons of DDT),
and eight other colleagues, established the
campaign's first bridgehead by covering an area
which contained five thousand villages and
245,000 miles of tracks and goat-paths.
The basic strategy of the struggle against
malaria is simple: because it is established that
Cont'd
on
next page
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
WHO
FRONTIER BRIDGE over the Prince Ali Gorge is the traditional crossing place for the Kurds at the time of their mass-migrations between Iraq and
Northern Persia. The Kurds migrate twice a year: in the Spring they cross to Persia to escape the extreme heat of the Iraqi plains ( I 20 degrees F. in
the shade); and in the Autumn they return to escape the bitter cold of the Iranian plateaux. The nomadic Kurds take shelter in mountain caves around
the gorges. Those who have settled in one place live In huts of dried mud while the local sheik has the right to a stone house such as the ones in the
photo. At the mouth of this gorge Dr. Malaria waits for nightfall and the coming of the nomadic tribes who are not allowed to cross until after
darktheir numbers make the route impassable for all other traffic. Photo shows Kurds who have settled nearby, using the bridge during the day.
the parasite resides in the blood of the infected person, that the
female mosquito of certain species feeds upon human blood (the
males have a quaint preference for the pollen of flowers) and so
transmits the malaria bug from a sick person to a healthy one.
Mosquitoes work at night, and they lie up for the day on the
inside walls and surfaces of houses. DDT, sprayed on the mos¬
quitoes during their daytime sleep, poisons them in the same
sort of way as mosquitoes poison human beings during their sleep
at night. Malaria can often be fatal in the case of very young
children, but otherwise it usually clears up itself within three
years, where there is no re-infection. So all efforts are directed
to this target: to prevent the mosquitoes themselves from being
infected during that three-year period at the end of which,
malaria itself will disappear.
For instance, if, by mischance, a traveller who has got malaria
in his bloodstream turns up in a village from which the disease
has previously been successfully eliminated, but to which
mosquitoes have returned (for it is scarcely possible to wipe out
an entire species) then there is bound to be an outbreak of fresh
cases. And, this time, the infection will be spectacular in its
severity, and may well lead to the deaths both of children and
grown-ups.
That's why Doctor Malaria was obliged to extend his field
of activity to the nomadic tribes, who carry the disease around
with them in their blood and who, in the course of their
wanderings may easily re-infect villages which have managed to
get rid of the scourge. But the time available to him for such
an operation was very limited indeed. For the Kurds wander
around the uplands of Persia throughout the whole summer, and
it is only in autumn that they come back down into the heat-
cracked lowlands of Iraq. So you have to catch them at the
exact moment when they cross the frontier passes, and before
they spill out and scatter over the whole vast plain.
This "nomad hunt" lasts nearly a fortnight. The chase takes
the pursuers over 1,400 miles of rough tracks in the dust and
debris of the mountains. Doctor Malaria, accompanied by his
wife and daughter, is at the wheel of his jeep, for several
hundreds of hours on end. A ten-man team follows along in a
truck. The stake in this race with the evasive Kurds is an
opportunity to take their blood tests and to spray the insides of
their tents with DDT.
At the mouth of the Gorges of Prince Ali, Doctor Malaria waits
for nightfall and the coming of the tribes. The latter are not
allowed to cross the gorges until after dusk, because their numbers
make the route impassable for all other traffic. The Oriental night
comes down, a purely theatrical blue, and at a single stroke.
Suddenly, there's a hubbub of whispering.
"'Doctor Malaria, they're coming!"
Already you can smell, floating abroad in the night, the sour
and suffocating stench of sickly dust, of greasy wool and rancid
animal sweat, which is seeping into the dainty freshness of the
Gorge of Prince Ali. The partridges have fallen silent. It's now
that a deep rumble of noise starts to come out of the east. The
nomads have reached the last bend in the road, heralded by a din
like that of a mountain torrent and by their shepherd with the
bird's head and the cattle-hide coat, which makes him look rather
like a huge performing nanny-goat. Behind the shepherd follow
all the cattle and stock belonging to the whole tribe.
After the cattle, the women appear, walking with a long tireless
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. May 1958
stride or rather, first comes the most beautiful woman of each
tribe, wearing her state of motherhood with the pride of an
empress. On her back, trussed up in a shawl, rides a sleeping
new-born baby, and her head rocks to the rhythm of her gait.
At the mouth of the Gorges of Prince Ali, the campfires of the
various tribes light up under the dying night, the black tents
are erected, the flocks disperse between the bushes and the rocks,
the women come back from fetching water, and the men,
squatting round the samovars, smoke their long pipes, with their
hands lying lax on their knees.
Doctor Malaria doesn't give Sheik Salim time to turn in and
recover from the night crossing of the Gorges of Prince Ali, nor
from the cumulative exhaustion of the twenty days' forced march
which has brought him to this place. He doesn't want to let
him slip for fear that tomorrow, or even this very evening, he
will vanish forever into the vast plains of Iraq. For the Sheik
Salim, crouching there in his tent, surrounded by his two wives,
his fifteen sons, his fifteen daughters-in-law and their children
fifty souls, in all, existing under one roof of woven goat's hair
represents a serious danger, not only to the villages of Kurdistan,
but also to Iraq, and to the Middle East as a whole.
Sheik Salim and his entire family have the malaria bug in their
blood. At more or less regular intervals they go down with
fevers and are knocked out for a day or two with ferocious fits
of shivering. In their particular case, it doesn't matter all that
much, because while they themselves are shaking with fever, their
flocks just go on grazing. Where it starts to become serious is
when two of the four children that the wife of the Sheik's eldest
son has brought into the world die before they are twelve months
old, when the peasants of the nearby villages and the labourers
who build the roads and the dams are away from work on the
sick list for three days out of every month, their systems under¬
mined by the mosquitoes' wicked bite.
It is true that in saying "yes" to Doctor Malaria's request, old
Sheik Salim is only thinking about his own comfort, for he knows
by common hearsay that Doctor Malaria is going to rid him of a
most irritating annoyance the mosquitoes that prevent him from
sleeping properly at night.
But, for Doctor Malaria, Sheik Salim's "yes" is the last
remaining facility that he needs in order to put in a general
attack on the disease: it gives him the control of the nomads.
This is the decisive step towards victory. For the first time DDT,
which kills mosquitoes, fleas, lice and other verminous insects,
is sprayed on to the insides of the tents; and its effect will last
for months, however many times they are folded and unfolded.
For the first time in their history, a doctor is looking after the
wild Kurd nomads. Sheik Salim grins. Tonight, he'll be sleeping
well. Without being aware of it, he, too, is one of the architects
of his country's resurrection.
In the six years in Kurdistan, Doctor Malaria has seen the
territory covered by his operations increase from an area the
size of a large city to one the size of Corsica, and then to
one the size of Switzerland (16,000 square miles). At the end of
1956, the territory liberated from malaria by him covered an
area the same as those of Belgium, the Sarre and Switzerland
combined (about 30,000 square miles). In 1960, when his anti¬
malaria campaign will have been completed, it is to a country
larger than France, populated by a mere five million inhabitants,
that he will have dedicated his vitality.
Making light
of 70 lb. loads
Kurd women are used to
doing the heavier ma¬
nual jobs. Water-duty
means carrying filled
goat-skin bags weighing
about 70 lbs. for several
miles. This water is often
extremely dangerous
because of the serious
diseases typhoid, amoe¬
bic dysentery and cholera
It can transmit.
WHO
Using drugs
& spray-guns
in a fight
against time
Pierre-André Pittet
Malaria, must be wiped from the face of the earth!
When the World Health Assembly took this
decision in 1955, it was no longer a pious inten¬
tion but an imperative necessity. Within a few years,
mosquitoes, defying all insecticide, would multiply all
over the world. Malaria would again be out of control;
eradication was the only answer. With modern drugs
and methods that has become possible. Malaria can be
attacked in two ways: by destroying the mosquitoes which
transmit it, and by fighting the parasites in the blood
of its victims. Malaria cases can thus be reduced to
numbers which can be individually treated. Thus when
resistant mosquitoes emerge in force there should be no
infection to transmit.
In the world wide strategy against malaria, Africa is
a major battle-ground. The disease is probably more
common there than in any other continent, but an adult
African appears to have a remarkable degree of immu¬
nity. When malaria control was accepted by the Who
Conference at Kampala in 1950 it was recognized that
in spite of such natural immunity in the adults, large
numbers of children were always dying of malaria.
It was therefore necessary to prosecute the campaign
most vigorously indeed. In Yaounde, the capital of the
Cameroon, there is a map spattered with multi-colour¬
ed stars. Each represents a village or a hamlet that must
be sprayed with insecticides. Among the white-robed
nomads, the naked animistic bush tribes and the village
tillers, the age-old scourge of malaria was accepted with
fatalism. Today the hopelessness has gone. The tribes
have become the doctors' willing allies.
In Mexico war has been declared. But this is a war
to save lives, not to sacrifice them. It calls for thorough¬
ness of military organization in planning and logistics.
Mexico has decided to eradicate malaria, and to deliver
its 30,000,000 citizens from the disease which has crippl¬
ed empires and destroyed civilizations. High-ranking
military officers direct the campaign from an operational
headquarters, from which they deploy their spray-teams
as though they were combat troops. "Supreme Head¬
quarters" is Who's Regional Office, the Pan American
Sanitary Bureau, which sees Mexico as a sector of the
wider battlefront of all Latin America. The U.N.
Children's Fund has provided equipment. There are
motorised columns and the "Malarial Cavalry" with
mounted spraymen and packhorses to climb the rough
paths into the High Sierras. Khaki-clad men, in para-
troop boots and helmets, boast the badges and flags of
"CNEP" (National Commission for Eradication).
When the mosquito gorges itself with blood it can
only fly so far before it has to "touch down" usually
on the walls or hangings of the room or tent where it
has bitten someone. One of the most important aspects
of any anti-malarial campaign therefore is the spraying
of insecticides on these surfaces so that mosquitoes land¬
ing on them will die before they can transmit malaria.
The killing effect of the insecticides can last for several
months, but respraying must be carried out for several
years the time needed to treat and cure people with
modern anti-malarial drugs.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
THE NEW
FACE OF
LEPROSY
Adama, the young African
woman (right) has just
learned that she has lep¬
rosy. Her situation Is tra¬
gic, but not hopeless.
Medical science now has
new drugs to arrest and In
some cases to cure leprosy.
For centuries this has been
hated and feared as the
most hideous of man's
afflictions and Its victims
called "unclean". But to¬
day more and more are
being treated in colonies
like the one at Schwebo,
Burma (opposite page)
where there is a commu¬
nity life and, after the day's
work, singing, dancing
and plenty of laughter.
Photos © by Pierre-André
Pittet and Ernest Scheidegger
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
w
The Unesco Courier. May 1958
One wet, warm day in July 1950, an eight-year
old little girl named Ma Boka Sone was brought
to the Mission Institution in Kemmendine, a
suburb of Rangoon. It seemed unlikely that she would
live very long, for she was in an advanced stage of
leprosy. But within three years little Ma Boka Sone
had made a remarkable recovery thanks to treatment
with sulphone drugs. By 1955, she was entirely free
of symptoms and without deformity. Two years later,
she Was again living happily with her family.
Maung Bone, a youth of some 20 years, is another
example. He went to the Htaukkyan sanatorium near
Rangoon in 1953. Apart from other symptoms his face
was a mass of unsightly "bulbous" tumours. He, too,
has hopes of rejoining his family this year. And yet
a third case, Tun Myint, still receiving treatment at the
Kemmendine Mission, is another Burmese child who is
being saved from a life of pain, unhappiness and
ostracism by sulphone treatment.
Burma is typical of many countries, especially in the
Far East, that have seized eagerly upon the new
techniques made available by the advances of medical
science for the relief of leprosy victims. In 1952, with
the help of the World Health Organisation, Burma
lunched a country-wide anti-leprosy campaign using
mass sulphone treatment. Not only had medical
science provided a new treatment to arrest and, in
some cases, cure leprosy but it was encouraging an
entirely new outlook toward the leprosy sufferer: the
concept that leprosy is no more contagious than, for
instance, tuberculosis and is, therefore, a disease for
which treatment should be sought in the normal way.
To encourage such thinking was progressive, but to
translate it into action was another matter. Down
the centuries, leprosy has been feared and hated as
the most hideous of all man's afflictions and the
"leper" has been ruthlessly cast out from
the society of his fellow men. Thus the
leprosy sufferer has, from necessity,
sought to conceal his disease, considering
it a disgrace. When the fatal marks
could be hidden no longer, the victim
Cont'd
on
next page
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
LEPROSY
(Continued) No longer a disease apart
was either driven out or allowed to
leave "voluntarily", to live alone,
hidden from view, or to join the bands
of wild and homeless beggars roam¬
ing the countryside and cities.
When the campaign first started,
Rangoon alone had some 6,000 cases
on record and preliminary estimates
put the total number of leprosy
sufferers in Burma at around 100,000.
Today, as more and more people
come forward for treatment, this
estimate has been revised to nearer
200,000 cases. This means that the
prevalence rate of leprosy in Burma
(over ten cases of leprosy per
thousand population) is twice that in
India or Thailand and is, therefore,
the highest among the larger
countries of S.E. Asia.
The campaign was based on the
new theory that only a small
proportion of leprosy patients
represent a danger of contagion for
their families or for the community.
The great majority can safely be
given "ambulatory" treatment at
newly-established outdoor clinics
while continuing their normal occu¬
pations and living at home. (They are
taught, nevertheless, elementary pre¬
cautions.) These patients are given
modern sulphone treatment which
not only arrests the disease but
reduces infection. (This means that
the reservoir of infection eventually
will be reduced and the spread of the
disease checked.)
The programme required five
phases of implementation: train¬
ing, propaganda, case-finding, mass
treatment in the capital and mass
treatment in the provinces. The
first need was for specially trained
leprosy inspectors who could travel
the country "screening" and treating
cases, visiting leprosy colonies and
sanatoria and organising as many
treatment points as possible. Some
elementary training in the diagnosis
and treatment of leprosy was also
given to some 250 health assistants
village workers posted in areas where
qualified doctors are unknown.
Today, there are some 30 leprosy
inspectors at work in Burma.
During the coming year, it is
hoped to increase their number to 36.
The leprosy assistants and inspectors
also played a large part in the propa¬
ganda programme. Wherever they
travelled they talked to the people,
explaining to them that "leprosy is
nothing to be ashamed of and that
effective treatment is available." The
co-operation of the religious leaders of
the villages contributed in no small
way to the successful course of the
campaign.
Training was mostly given in
Rangoon, where the first clinics for
ambulatory treatment were opened.
To emphasise that leprosy is just a
disease like any other, the site chosen
for the main centre was next to an
out patients' clinic at Rangoon
General Hospital. The Prime Minister,
His Excellency TJ Nu, who took a keen
interest in the launching of the
campaign, personally recommended
this central situation. To avoid the
stigma that superstition had attached
to the words "leper" and "leprosy,"
it was called the "'Special Skin Clinic."
Auxiliary clinics were opened in the
city's outskirts and an existing clinic
connected with one of the old-style
leprosy asylums was brought into line
with the new programme. By 1954,
24,000 people were receiving am-
WHO photo by Ernst Scheidegger
SPECIAL COLONIES for tempe nry isola¬
tion of leprosy sufferers have been opened In
Burma where so far 200,000 cases have been
reported a prevalence rate which is the
highest in South East Asia. Above, drugs are
distributed to patients at the Schwebo colony.
bulatory treatment and some 3,000
patients living in Rangoon were
attending the clinic regularly.1
For those suffering from the
disease in its dangerously contagious
stage, special colonies and sanatoria
for temporary isolation are still ne¬
cessary. But gone is the "Abandon-
hope-all-ye-that-enter-here" atmo¬
sphere of the old leprosy asylums.
The Schwebo colony is typical of
those in rural areas. Patients are
encouraged to do productive work
and to live a community life with, in
most cases, the knowledge that they
will return to normal life as useful
members of the community when the
period of contagion is over. Near
Rangoon, at Htaukkyan, a state
sanatorium has been built with acco¬
modation for 500 advanced cases.
The main buildings face a busy
highroad and bear, for passers-by to
see, the name: "'State Sanatorium for
Special Skin Diseases."
An important part of " the pro¬
paganda campaign is not. only to
break down the deep-rooted belief
that leprosy is a disease apart and
that nothing can be done to arrest
its course, but to encourage the pub¬
lic to assist patients after discharge
from leprosy institutions (in the past
many ex-patients, though fully cured,
have been shunned by family and
neighbours) and to help the depend¬
ents of patients hospitalized or un¬
employed on account of their
sickness. In rural areas, leprosy
relief associations have been formed
and are widely supported.
Like all serious illnesses, leprosy
still brings tragedy to many homes
mothers with the disease in its
contagious stage must leave their
husbands and children for what may
still be a long period of treatment in
a special colony or sanatorium;
fathers, too, often must be separated
from the families they are supporting.
By the end of June 1957, 42,000
cases had been registered and 33,500
were receiving treatment. In 1954,
the Dutch leprologist assigned by the
World Health Organisation to help
the Burmese Government get the
programme under way in 1952, moved
to another project and the Burmese
Ministry of Health carried on the
campaign. This year, with renewed
Who and Unicef assistance, it is
hoped that the number of cases
receiving treatment can be increased
to 50,000 by the end of 1959.
Among the thousands finding new
hope who, in former days, would
have been condemned to live as
outcasts, there are innumerable human
stories. Maung Tun, for instance, a
former government official, could no
longer stand the disgrace of being a
helpless burden to his wife and
children. He left home to become a
beggar, until rounded up by the police
and sent to a sanatorium for treat¬
ment. One of many "'success" stories
concerns Ma Khin Nyunt, a girl who
is now in her late teens. She was
turned out by her stepmother several
years ago when the neighbours realiz¬
ed that she had leprosy.
Frightened, she carried her sleeping
mat and little bundle of belongings
to the "Special Skin Clinic" in
Rangoon, crying only for a corner to
sleep. She is now a pupil nurse in
the hospital ward of the New State
Sanatorium for Special Skin -Dis¬
eases.
As more cases are discovered and
treated and the reservoir of infection
is reduced, children now growing up
will be less and less liable to contract
leprosy. Dr. TJ. Tha Saing, Assistant
Director of National Health Services,
who is tireless in his campaign to
bring a better understanding of lep¬
rosy and easy access to treatment
for people in all walks of life, looks
forward with confidence to the day
when this age-old scourge will be
conquered once and for all.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. May 1958
Photos © Pierre-André Pittet
OUT OF THE SHADOWS
THEY COME FOR HELP
A shadowy figure in the early morning mist, leprosy victim (left) limps
painfully out of a Bengal railway station where he has spent the night.
So begins his long day of begging from passers by. Millions like him
around the world have never had a chance to receive treatment with
sulphone drugs which could Improve their condition. Today, anti-
leprosy campaigns are seeking out these sufferers, segregating the dange¬
rously contagious cases and providing out-patient treatment for those
in the early stages of the disease. From Tirumani, in the State of Madras,
a remarkable system of mobile treatment now operates in 53 villages,
taking care of nearly 15,000 sufferers. From an Indian Ministry of
Health Centre, teams of medical workers are led and trained by a group
founded by a leading Belgian leprosy specialist, Professor Franz Heme-
rijckx (see page 36). To aid him he has a Belgian woman doctor and
three nursesFrench, Belgian and Canadian. Above, the Belgian nurse,
Simone Liégeois, at the bedside of a man in an advanced stage of leprosy,
being cared for at the Tirumani Hospital. Nobody really knows how
many leprosy sufferers there are In the world. In 1952 the estimate
was "between two and seven million." A revised one last year was "ten or
twelve million" because more and more victims are seeking treatment.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
A modern dilemma:
TRANQUILLIZER IN ONE POCKET;
'PEP' PILL IN THE OTHER
by Ritchie Calder
On July 19, 1957, letters went off from the Mental
Health Section of Who to eminent experts in Cana¬
da, Denmark, France, India, Nigeria, Sweden,
Switzerland, the United Kingdom and the United States,
inviting them to meet in Geneva to consider the use and
abuse of drugs in the treatment of mental conditions.
The letter said:'"The Organization realizes the problems
likely to be presented, and even created, by the ever-
widening use of psychotropic agents..."
"Psychotropic agents!" The "tranquillizer" in one
pocket; the "pep" pill in the other. Drugs to dispel
nightmares; drugs to invoke dreams; drugs to escape
from reality into fantasy or from fantasy into reality.
Even Alice-in-Wonderland drugs by means of which
adults can shrink back into childhood.
That is the caricature of one type of Modern Man,
harassed by headlines; tortured by the ticker-tape;
tormented by the telephone; as "'manic-depressive" as his
sales-charts; wakeful when he should be asleep and
drowsy when he should be awake; worrying about his
blood-pressure and nursing his duodenal ulcer; driving
himself like a highspeed car through dense traffic, braking
or accelerating in turn, running away from himself and
taking himself with him. He has 2,500 million neighbours
in the wider world; he is alone in that private world
himself.
There are still other types those whose . tensions
become intolerable through being chained to piece work
machines, white-collar workers dogged by economic
worries and "wife trouble," hungry and miserable peasants
driven to take hashish for solace.
An exaggeration? But also a symbol of the anxieties and
tensions and stresses which deny countless millions that
"complete physical, mental and social well-being" which
Who defines as health.
In fighting diseases and promoting conditions conducive
to health, Who is trying to fit the environment to man.
In its mental health activities the increasing problem is,
How to reconcile man and his environment?
Revolution in psychiatric treatment
The decade in which Who has "grown-up" has seen
the development of drugs which have revolutionized
psychiatric treatment, until some authorities make
bold to claim that the practice, once routine, of sending
disturbed patients directly to a mental hospital is "against
good medical practice." Instead, with drugs as the first
means of attack against acute psychosis, patients could be
cared for at home or, if home conditions Were unsuitable,
at general hospitals, even on an out-patient basis.
In the United States where the care of mental patients
costs $1,000,000,000 a year, there was in 1956 a
reduction, for the first time in 184 years of U.S. mental
institutions, in the total number of hospitalized mental
cases. Instead of the predictable 12,000 increase, there
This article is taken from "Ten Steps Forward", a book
describing the battle for world health between 1948 and
1958, written by the British science writer, Ritchie Calder,
and published by Who's Division of Publication Informa¬
tion, Geneva (Price: £0.50 ; Sw. fr. 1.50 ; 2s6d). The texts
published on pages 26. and 28 are also taken from the
Ritchie Calder book, courtesy of Who.
was a decrease of over 8,000. Nearly 20,000 fewer patients
meant a saving in treatment and hospital construction of
$200,000,000. With the advent of the new drugs into
psychiatric practice, the use of electric shock treatment,
insulin coma therapy, packs and tubs, physical restraints
could sometimes even be replaced by sedatives and
tranquillizers.
. In the hands of psychiatrists, the new drugs have thus
beneficial potentials, not only in the clinical management
of psychotic patients but also in other respects. It has
become possible to relate certain drug-induced mental
phenomena to psychoanalytic theory and to examine their
implications for individual and group psychotherapy.
It is also necessary to know the mode of action of the
drugs the "'psychophysiological '"' correlates," as the
experts would call it; and to classify them. With the
growing experience in the use of the drugs, an appraisal
of the effects on the patient under treatment and of the
general atmosphere and future functioning of the mental
hospitals should be made. Other questions are how far
such drugs can safely be used in general practice and,
most important, whether "self-medication" is permissible.
Fantasy drugs of the priest-physicians
Such problems came under review by the Who study
group which met in Geneva in November 1957. But,
included in the group, were those who could contri¬
bute something over and beyond the pharmacological, or
clinical, or psychoanalytical approach, because they
belonged to cultures still "unpressurized." One of the
items on the agenda was: "Differences in the effects of,
and need for, psychotropic drugs in different cultures."
In a way, the contribution of those experts is a kind of
reverse "lease-lend." Advanced pharmacology, in the
shrunken world of modern communications, will almost
certainly be reflected in the new medical practices of
older cultures, but experience is usually a good substitute
for experiment and these tranquillizing and hallucinatory
drugs have, apart from modern synthesis, a tradition
which goes back to time immemorial. In the history, and
prehistory, of ancient cultures they played a part.
Rauwolfia, the natural basis of synthetic "tranquillizers"
such as reserpine, rescinnamine and deserpidine, is a plant
from the foothills of the Himalayas which figured in
Aryan-Dravidian medicine and the ancient Ayurveda of
the Indian sub-continent. Medical historians are just
beginning to learn the extent of mushroom-lore and its
relationship to the hallucination-producing drugs used by
the priest-physicians in older civilizations. Moreover
cultural "conditioning" can produce strangely differing
psychiatric reactions to such drugs and, as in so much of
the experience of Who in other fields, may indicate the
hazards of transplanted practices. These are question-
marks which give wise men cause to reflect and pose the
problems which can only be resolved by shared
knowledge on a world scale.
Apart from the advances made in clinical treatment
of mental illness in the past ten years the attitude
towards the mentally sick and the "misfits" has changed.
Gradually the recognition, which it is Who's policy to
encourage, has grown that mental illness is something
as matter-of-fact as physical illness and not something
unnatural or supernatural which must be whispered
about in shame or treated in secret. There is the reali¬
zation that the demands of society can be over-exacting
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
for certain individuals, who are just as much social-
casualties as the traffic-cripples.
More and more, Who has been emphasizing the social,
as well as the medical, approach to mental health and
encouraging the examination of causes rooted in the
social structure. Who studies of the "deprived child,"
who becomes the social misfit, have stimulated new
thinking and new attitudes. The clinical psychiatrist
sees the end results; the social-psychologist sees the
family, the group, and the social relationships which
produce these results. Mental health predicates preven¬
tion, not cure.
Similarly in the studies of, and the campaign against,
alcoholism Who's attitude is that the chronic alcoholic
is not a drunken reprobate but a sick person, to be
regarded sympathetically and to be medically treated.
The drink of good-fellowship, when it is socially sanction¬
ed, may relax other people but for him it becomes the
escape-route from his private jungle of emotions and
frustrations and psychological malaise, and some who
have reached this stage become chronic alcoholics. Such
an attitude towards the alcoholic does not condone excess
nor encourage drunkenness, but it calls for a rational
approach to a growing problem the increase of chronic
alcoholism as a symptom of the stress-diseases of today.
The growing incidence of mental illness in the advanced
countries is a public health problem of the first magnitude,
but Who with its world-wide responsibilities to all peoples
and to governments has to anticipate the extension of
The Unesco Courier. May 1958
the problem, as changing conditions and the spread ol
technology bring new stresses to bear on peoples whose
cultural patterns 'are being drastically modified. Indus¬
trialization, automation, atomic energy and increased
productivity, which can bring prosperity and material
well-being to many countries, have their psychological
hazards which Who is seeking to examine. Even the
lengthening of the span of life, the fruit of medical
progress, brings its problems. Who is directing attention
to the mental health aspects of the care of the old.
Thus, in its tenth decade, the World Health Organization
is opening windows and broadening the horizons on prob¬
lems which themselves are opportunities and which, only
a few years ago, would not have been popularly regarded
as its function. But they have been since its inception
because, by definition and by charter, it is a health
organization and health is not just a question for doctors.
It is bound up with the whole social process and with
each individual who is involved in that process.
No international agency, no government and no society
can provide health but only the opportunities for the
person to enjoy it.
Just as modern medicine accepts the fact that body
Reacts on mind and mind on body, that mental and
emotional stresses produce organic disorders and organic
disorders produce mental and emotional stresses, so the
concept of world health recognizes the reciprocity of the
individual and his environment and the ideal of The
Whole Man in the Whole World.
THE INCREASE IN MENTAL ILLNESS:
RESULT OF FASTER LIVING
The problem of mental illness is one which
affects particularly the economically well-de¬
veloped countries. It has been estimated that
in these countries there is an insanity rate of some¬
thing like 20 people per thousand. Yet in most
countries of Europe the number of mental hospital
beds ranges only from one to four per thousand of
the population.
In the better-off countries, moreover, there is
also a rate of neurosis defined at the level of par¬
tially-disabling illness of about 10 per cent.
During World War II (to August 1, 1945) 18 per
cent of the nearly five million Selective Service Re¬
gistrants in the U.S., aged from 18 to 37, had been
rejected because of mental disorders. In addition,
large numbers were discharged for the same reason.
These figures, of course, are not a measure of the
incidence in the general population, since the
stresses of military life are exceptional. However,
it has recently been reported that of the men pro¬
cessed by the U.S. Selective Service for the Armed
Forces pre-introduction examination, 20 per cent are
classified as unavailable because of psychiatric
disorder.
With regard to serious mental disease in the
more developed countries, there is some pro¬
gress. Until a few decades ago many of the
patients occupying beds in mental hospitals remain¬
ed chronically ill and in need of care for the whole
of their lives. Of those who did recover many later
relapsed and had to go back to hospital for a further
period. However, new methods of physical treat¬
ment insulin therapy, electro-convulsive therapy,
and the use of drugs such as chlorpromazine have
led to a more optimistic outlook in the therapeutic
field and to the possibility of permanent cure for
many patients whose prognosis formerly offered no
hope.
Growing evidence of the influence psychological
factors can exercise on these patients has drawn
attention to the role of unfavourable psychological
states and emotional influences in the etiology of
their disorders. An individual, for instance, whose
personality development has been weakened in child¬
hood may fall into a state of permanent ill-health
when faced with some unaccustomed stress. There
is clinical evidence that a large number of neurotic
breakdowns take place in response to stresses which
would in healthy people create no more than a tem¬
porary disturbance.
Interest has thus been aroused in the possibility
of measures to mitigate stress situations that
may impinge upon basically weak personalities.
There seems no doubt, also, that many cases of
schizophrenia and melancholia can be prevented by
mental hygiene methods, particularly through the
prompt handling of emotional disorders brought
about by immediate environmental stresses.
In European communities many patients have
physical symptoms without signs of mental disorder.
Such patients can often be shown to be suffering
from a prolonged emotional state which either
causes, or contributes to, what is essentially a neu¬
rotic condition. The trouble can frequently be trac¬
ed to unfavourable attitudes developed in early
childhood within the familly. The numbers concer¬
ned are so vast, however, that a wholesale attack
on the problem would require an expenditure of time
and money which could not readily be made avail¬
able.
We can nevertheless hope to mitigate certain
forms of ill-health and reduce their incidence
through the protection of persons at periods of
stress ; and we can, through existing medical ser¬
vices, make earlier treatment available.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
V
' i -Tíf'~fri '
*%** ." ¿
lJ9
v i -t^tí
EDE AND THE MOON FESTIVAL
Afew months ago 5-year-old Ede
Nwaebgo was a very unhappy little
boy. For Ede, who lives with his
father and mother in a bush village known
as Owo, in the Udi Division of Eastern
Nigeria, suffered from the painful and un¬
sightly disease of yaws.
Few outsiders ever take the narrow dirt
road that branches off the main highway
from Enugu to Bamenda, winding through
dense jungle and across streams straddled
only by rough logs, to the huddle of
forty-odd conical-shaped clay huts with
thatched roofs that make up Owo village.
Ede's parents have a small yam field
and a few chickens. Ede is their remaining
child: they had previously lost four prob¬
ably through nutritional disease. When
Ede fell ill with yaws the family, disheart¬
ened, took less and less interest in village
life. His mother rarely went to market as
she did not like leaving Ede alone. Village
children rarely play together: from their
earliest years they are too busy helping
their parents. Chasing the few mongrel
dogs, pushing wooden carts or trailing tin
cans comprise the rare childish games.
Little Ede was too sick even to play at
anything. He just sadly sat and watched.
24
He was not the only one. Many of the
villagers, children and grownups, were
suffering from the same disease, their
bodies covered in the painful lesions. Little
work was done: what was more, the
monthly moon festival had not been cele¬
brated for some time.
One day a messenger arrived and an¬
nounced that a doctor would visit the vil¬
lage and cure the villagers of their crippling
disease. The villagers were not impressed.
They had never seen a doctor in their lives
and nobody imagined that any great change
would take place if one were to come. Five
days later, Dr. Oboiha, a Nigerian working
with the World Health Organization's yaws
team in the Enugu area, found no crowds
awaiting his arrival. Patiently he explained
the purpose of his visit and of the help he
could bring to the suffering people of Owo.
One or two of the more adventurous
villagers volunteered for treatment. Little
Ede, accompanied by his mother, was
among them. Those suffering from yaws
were given a shot of long-acting penicillin
which clears up the disease within eight to
ten days. After two days, when the lesions
of the first patients treated had started
healing, the number of villagers presenting
themselves for treatment increased. Eight
days later, when Ede and his little friend
Igwe were shown to the assembled villa¬
gers their skins clear but for a few small
scars everybody in Owo queued for ex¬
amination. Dr. Oboiha had won. Every
yaws case in the village was treated.
The next moon feast was celebrated with
gay abandon. But as it had always been a
tradition among the villagers long before
the village was stricken by yaws to
paint their bodies with red and black spots
for each moon festival, young Ede was
painted with nut juice by his mother.
When the make-up job was finished, little
Ede was just as spotty as he had been
before the yaws team arrived the only
difference being that these spots did not
hurt.
Yaws is widespread throughout Nigeria
in some areas the prevalence is as high as
20%. But, like little Ede, thousands of
Nigerians have been freed from the disease
by penicillin injections. In 1954 a mass
campaign began with the aid of Who and
Unicef, and by the middle of 1955,
1,107,000 people had been examined and
237,000 active cases as well as many con¬
tacts and latent cases had been treated.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. May 1958
'THE NIGHTMARE OF THE TROPICS'
Yaws begins as a small insignificant sore on the foot
or leg, a sore which grows, and as the disease
develops fresh sores break out anew elsewhere.
The disease attacks the bones and eats away the tissues
like termites, undermining the strongest physiques. The
face may lose all human aspect and become nothing more
than a nightmarish mask worthy of the legends of the
Middle Ages.
These are the effects of yaws (also known as fram-
boesia) which ravages the tropical regions of Africa,
America, Oceania and Asia.
The contagious disease of yaws has for a long time
been confused with syphilis. Both diseases are caused
by identical micro-organisms, or tréponèmes, i.e. T. palli¬
dum in the case of syphilis and T. pertenue in that of
yaws. Bejel, another treponemal disease, is prevalent
above all in the Eastern Mediterranean area. The
climate most favourable to yaws is a humid tropical one,
where intense heat alternating with heavy rain, falls
on a soil which is not very porous and gives rise to a
luxuriant vegetation. It has been found that yaws tends
to decrease during the dry season and to increase during
the wet season. Primarily a rural disease, yaws is
transmitted by human contact as well as by contact with
dirty linen or clothing and other articles of everyday use.
No decision has yet been reached as to whether insects
act as vectors of the disease (flies, mosquitoes, etc.).
Undernourished individuals living in overpopulated areas
are much more receptive than others.
It is extremely difficult to discover, before the charac¬
teristic lesions appear, whether a patient is suffering
from syphilis or from yaws. Yaws itself is not hereditary,
but a child born healthy to infected parents will in
turn be infected by contact with them during infancy.
One of the main obstacles confronting doctors combat¬
ing the disease is superstition. In fact, in some regions
there is a popular belief that the men will not be strong
and able to face life successfully unless they have
contracted some very spectacular form of yaws.
Not only do those infected adopt completely inadequate
measures to check the disease (e.g. by swallowing a
decoction made from snakes with a skin showing patterns
similar to those left by yaws on the human skin), but
children may even be deliberately infected from earliest
youth, with the possible resultant mutilation of their
bodies by the age of 12.
Doctors often need much ingenuity to coax patients
to come for treatment. For example, a Who physician
has related how he lured sufferers in Haiti by giving them
a cake of soap and then, at the end of the consultation,
a red ticket with the promise of a second piece of soap
some days later on presentation of the ticket... and a
second treatment. Unfortunately, the doctor did not
foresee that the ticket might be given away or... sold.
This is what happened. The patients who attended
the second time were not always those whom he had
treated on the first occasion.
It should be noted that the majority of patients prefer
to undergo injections, sometimes painful ones, rather than
swallow other remedies, such as pills, etc., perhaps in
accordance with the theory that "something that doesn't
hurt cannot do any good". Nowadays the disastrous
consequences of yaws can be prevented: a single shot
of penicillin will cure it in about nine cases out of ten;
a second shot will usually cure the tenth. The effects
are rapid: the worst skin lesions clear up in about ten
days, and the average cost of each cure, including exami¬
nations and other expenses, is about $1 per person.
Mass campaigns to treat yaws with penicillin are being
carried out by national health authorities in many parts
of the world with the aid of the World Health Organi¬
zation. To treat the 20 million or so Africans who are
affected by it will take an estimated ten years, but already
remarkable results have been achieved. The job of
curing the 15 million cases in Asia was begun eight years
ago and is already half accomplished. Campaigns are
also being waged in the Pacific. Thus are men stamping
out the disease that has been called "'The Nightmare of
the Tropics".
WHO photos by Eric Schwab
Photos show: Opposite page, "three faces of Ede"before he had received a shot of penicillin; five days later and, finally, after ten days, when his
sores had almost disappeared and he was able to smile again. His happiness had cost about SI. Right, on the day of the Moon Festival, Ede's mother
paints spots on his skin with nut juice. Above, after they have seen effects of penicillin, villagers of Owo come for examination and treatment.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
SCOTLAND YARD OF EPIDEMICS
Broadcasts the daily health
bulletin of the world
On February 18, 1948 the following signal went out
from Geneva to the health authorities of the world:
"'Egypt now declares whole country free from choi¬
ra Epidnations."
The doctors in the public health administrations could
now relax, after four anxious months; to them, it was as
though a major war had been averted. Once again, the
"West Wall" in the defences against Asian cholera had
held, as it had done for thirty years but not without heavy
casualties. The Egyptian death-roll had been 20,472.
The outbreak began at El Korein, on September 22, 1947.
The merchants had gathered from all the Egyptian pro¬
vinces for the annual date fair at this centre on the
eastern edge of the Nile Delta, close to the Sweet Water
Canal, which provides the drinking water for the cities
and villages of Suez. Besides the traders, there were 6,000
workmen engaged on construction work nearby.
Three labourers contracted cholera, from a source never
officially established; but it must have come from one of
the areas of the East where cholera persists. The sick men
carried it into the crowded billets of the workers and,
before quarantine measures could be established, the
transients, the hired labour and the merchants, panicked.
So great is the dread of cholera that, as throughout his¬
tory, they fled from El Korein.
Instead of escaping the disease, they took it with them.
Within three days, cases had appeared in Cairo. Within
four, it had spread to Ismailia. By October, the whole
of Egypt was involved and 33,000 cases of cholera had
been discovered.
Vaccine flowed to Cairo
Within a few hours of cholera being recognised in El
Korein, Epidnations had warned the world that
cholera was on the march. Epidnations is a code
name which, since 1923, has been impressively familiar to
public health administrators in all countries. Throughout
the entire existence of the League of Nations; throughout
the war, with the concurrence of the belligerents; during
the transfer from the League, through the United Nations,
to the World Health Organization to this day, Epidnations
has been the password on the picket-lines of disease. It
stands for the Section of International Quarantine.
When cholera broke loose in Egypt, the World Health
Organization did not yet officially exist; it was still an
"Interim Commission". That did not hamper action in
an emergency of this seriousness. In those hectic first
hours, telegrams went out from Geneva to vaccine labor¬
atories in several countries, including the Pasteur Insti¬
tute in Paris, the Lister Institute in London and the
Haffkine Institute in Bombay, asking how much cholera
vaccine they had available; how much they could produce
within a week and how quickly they could get it to Cairo.
The response was immediate and ungrudging.
This was followed by the "'Cholera Air-lift" which made
medical history. In America, stocks of vaccine were
rushed to the airport with motor-cycle siren escorts to
clear the traffic. The Russians dispatched supplies.
From India, where cholera is still persistent, succour
was sent to the Egyptians. Crates converged on Cairo,
until there were 20,000,000 doses enough to vaccinate
every man, woman and child in Egypt. A third of the
supplies were gifts.
The ship nobody wanted
Within the first fortnight, a group of experts assem¬
bled in Geneva. They included authorities on the
disease and on quarantine methods, and the doctor
who had diagnosed the first cases. They re-examined
cholera quarantine regulations which had been made 20
years before and found them adequate for the emergency.
One country which had prohibited entry to anyone coming
from Egypt had to be reminded, sharply, that this exceeded
the International Sanitary Conventions and was putting
the clock back a hundred years.
At that time (in 1848) cases of cholera were discovered
on board the Matteo Bruzzo, out of Genoa with 200 passen¬
gers. Country after country on both sides of the Atlantic
refused to allow the ship to dock or the passengers to
land. For four months they were kept at sea before being
disembarked at Leghorn, 78 miles from where they start¬
ed. This and many other incidents, in which the dread of
cholera and other pestilential diseases had frightened
countries into excessive quarantine measures, led the
mercantile nations of the world into international co¬
operation. Cholera, it has been said of that period, was
the founder of the public health services, and this is
indeed true of many countries.
When, with material help from outside and prodigious
efforts by its own doctors, Egypt quenched the epidemic
of cholera, the disease had once again served as a salutary
reminder. In September, when it broke out, only 19
countries had ratified their membership of the World.
Health Organization, which could not formally exist
until 26 states had done so. Before the "All Clear" was
sounded, ten more had ratified and all was set for the
First World Health Assembly to meet on June 24, 1948.
For all practical purposes, and despite this dilatoriness
of governments, however, Who had existed since 1946.
The United Nations had inherited the functions of the
League of Nations, including Epidnations,
the epidemiological control. An inter¬
national Health Conference had been
held and the need for Who had been
wholeheartedly endorsed. An Interim Com-
Cont'd
on
page 28
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. May 1958
PATIENT FROM A
COUNTRY OF
JAGGED PEAKS
A Moslem priest, or Mullah, was troubled by a cough and
fevers, and decided to travel the 200 miles from his home
In the solitude of the Hindu Kush mountains, a gigantic
"cactus hedge" of jagged peaks, in northern Afghanistan, to
the Government's Tuberculosis Control and Training Centre
in the capital, Kabul, for advice and treatment. This centre,
which also serves to train health personnel, was started in
I9S3 with the aid of WHO. Left, arriving at the centre,
the Mullah waits for his examination card to be filled in.
Below, a miniature X-ray is taken of his lungs. It has been
estimated that there are some five million active cases of
tuberculosis in Asia. The disease is treacherous, highly
communicable and hard to cure. Even so, the outlook is
today more promising, and if it does not worsen, medical
authorities believe that this disease can be brought far down
the list of Important enemies within the next 25 years.
WHO photos by Marc Riboud
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
SCOTLAND YARD OF EPIDEMICS
(Continued)
mission had been set up and with money advanced by
the United Nations and funds from Unrra (United Nations
Relief and Rehabilitation Administration), it had begun
operations, manning the defence lines of health in a.
world ravaged by war and menaced by pestilences which
are the campfollowers of wars. , ,
Epidnations, which had acted so swiftly and thoroughly
when cholera appeared in Egypt, was itself the product
of the diseases which ran amök after the first World War.
Then, in Eastern Europe, there were at least twelve and
a half million cases of typhus, spread by the lice infesting
broken armies and wandering refugees. To prevent its
spread westwards a "'Cordon Sanitaire" a health fron¬
tier was established from the Baltic to the Black Sea. To
assist the control, epidemiological centres were established
by the League of Nations in _ Moscow and Warsaw, in
January 1922. The collection and dissemination of infor¬
mation by those centres were so effective that the system
was extended to the whole world in 1923.
Pestilences have no politics
Since then, despite political upheavals and total war,
the epidemiological services have continued without
interruption: pestilences have no politics and even
belligerents can recognize a common enemy. In 1948, the
World Health Organization improved and extended the
system and speeded up the exchange of information. Its
radio network, based on Geneva, was expanded to cover
the whole world a necessary measure when carriers of
disease can travel with the speed of the fastest aeroplane.
A typhus louse or a plague flea brushed off the rags of a
beggar in an Eastern bazaar can be in Tokio or Oslo, New
York, Moscow or Sydney, within a few hours.
Today, a daily epidemiological bulletin is broadcast on
eight wavelengths from the transmitters at Geneva-
Prangins. The information is relayed by stations through¬
out the world. Public health authorities, seaport and air¬
port medical services and ships at sea, monitor those
broadcasts as a fixed routine. The main concern is still
with the quarantinable diseases smallpox, cholera,
typhus, plague, yellow fever and relapsing feverbut
information is also given about other diseases, like the
sudden emergence of Asian influenza in 1957.
With such information, the authorities can apply qua¬
rantine or medical inspection measures immediately to
any ships or aircraft coming from danger areas or suspect¬
ed of having cases on board. They can also relax those
measures immediately the danger has passed just as
important, in these days when people travel fast about
their business, and when keeping a ship idle in quarantine
costs a fortune each day. By common consent of all
governments, this network of defences has been spread
around the world. As long as such diseases persist
anywhere such constant vigilance is necessary. The world
is not yet rid of them.
Nevertheless progress has been made. While smallpox
infection is still widespread in many areas of Africa, Asia
and South America, the other quarantinable diseases are
entrenched in "'plague spots". But is was possible to say
in 1958 that, during the past 10. years, not one case of
quarantinable diseases except for smallpoxhas been
brought into a country from abroad by ship or plane, and
given rise to secondary cases.
R. C.
28
THE LABYRINTH
OF
MODERN DRUGS
On May 19, 1950, the Third World Health Assembly
formally approved the publication of the Pharma¬
copoeia Internationalis, the first volume of which
was ready for the printer.
Nobody paid much attention. It will not be found in
the headlines of the day and historians will not consult
that volume to find, on page 11, acidum acetylsalicylicum
as the cure for the political headaches of that moment.
Nevertheless it was topical and it was historic.
Doctors, who knew, sensed the urgency. Medical science
was advancing rapidly and pharmacologists were moving
even faster than the doctors themselves. Patients,
encouraged by newspaper discussion of "miracle drugs"
sulfa compounds, like sulfathiazolum; antibiotics, like
penicillin; and hormones, like cortisone were expecting
"White Magic" from the practitioners.
Here was a drastic new departure. Every culture,
throughout history and from prehistory, has had its
traditional drugs. Many countries have had their phar¬
macopoeia, assemblages and assays of drugs. Four thou¬
sand years ago, the Chinese produced the Neiching, the
Canons of Medicine. The Ancient Hindus, the Babylo¬
nians, the Egyptians, the Persians, the Greeks, the Romans,
the Arabs, the American Indians and the apothecaries of
medieval Europe, had contributed their herbáis and
métairies. By observation and experience, they had mea¬
sured their values and dispensed their virtues.
In the first half of this century, the advance in
knowledge of the behaviour of germs within the body
made possible vaccines, sera and antitoxins, to help the
human system to repel infections. Understanding of the
endocrine glands had produced biological extracts, like
insulin for diabetes. The discovery of vitamins had
placed a new range of substances at the disposal of the
doctors. Ehrlich had discovered that certain dyestuffs
had an affinity for specific organisms and his salvarsan
against syphilis began a new era in chemotherapy drugs
could be "tailormade" in the laboratories.
The big breakaway, began around 1935, when the
discovery of the sulfa drugs underlined ' Ehrlich's
principle that specific germs could be attacked
within the body, enabling doctors to treat causes instead
of just relieving symptoms. Then came penicillin and
other antibiotics again drugs to attack specific causes.
When the Second World War finished, medical science
and the chemists had produced an armoury of new phar¬
maceutical weapons. This new-found mastery over man's
invisible enemies was a gratifying achievement, but the
multiplication and world-wide use of the new drugs
involved hazards. They replaced traditional drugs, the
production and use of which had the safeguards of long
experience.
They were adopted and manufactured in many different
countries, and standards and assays varied. They were
placed in the hands of doctors and pharmacists who had
to accept them at their face-value.
That was why an International Pharmacopoeia became
essential. Many attempts had been made during the
preceding century to produce such a work. Limited
agreements had been reached about certain potent drugs
and methods of assay and dispensing, but there was
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. May 1958
CODEX
MEDIC AM ENTARIUS.
S F. U
PHARMACOPPA
PARISIENS1S.
EX KANDATO FACULTATIS klEDICINyC
I^iifuiilu in luccm ..lui,
M.JOANNE-BAPTISTA-THOMA
M ART 1 NEN Í, Dtuvt.
Editio juilior A eincndjrior.
P A R 1 s 1 1 S,
Apud GUILLELMUM CAVELIER, Pitrtm.vU
Ucobzî , fub infigne Lilii AurcL
M. DCC XLV1II.
CVM VlIVll&CIO R&Clt.
WHO photos
ROW UPON ROW of jars, each Inscribed with the Latin name of Its contents, still give some chemists' shops (centre) the traditional appearance
of the old apothecaries' establishments. But there is as great a difference between the skill and knowledge required by the modern druggist and
that of his predecessors as there Is between the International Pharmacopoeia recently published by the World Health Organization (photo, left-
French edition cover) and the two centuries' old volume Codex Medicamentarius seu Pharmacopoeia (right) which came out In Paris In 1768.
nothing comprehensive. True, excellent national phar¬
macopoeias were available but there were variations in
national specifications and, in a world of fast travel, a
patient's prescription could mean many things in different
countries, and drugs acceptable in one. country would be
rejected by another. Nomenclature varied and proprie¬
tary names added to the confusion.
The World Health Organization ventured into this dif¬
ficult field. Apart from national susceptibilities,
pharmaceuticals had grown into a vast industry and
firms were naturally suspicious and sensitive about inter¬
vention which might impugn their products or restrict
their freedom of action. Even in laboratory terms, the
assaying, checking, counter-checking and defining of basic
substances and the application of standards with respect
to the safety, purity and potency of biological, pharma¬
ceutical and similar products was a major undertaking.
What was made abundantly clear from the outset was
that Who had neither the power nor the intention to
impose this pharmacopoeia. It was designed to be a
basic document, the recommendations of which govern¬
ments, or the national pharmacopoeia commissions, could
either adopt, or reject.
The first volume included a greater proportion of tradi¬
tional drugs than of new drugs; the second included more
new drugs than traditional ones; and the supplement to
both dealt preponderantly with innovations. Modern
drugs wax and wane in medical popularity. A new
discovery, or a fresh variant, will prove more effective, or
safer, and will displace predecessors.
Another cause of uncertainty and confusion was the use
of proprietary names, in addition to the introduction of
trade names. It was soon apparent that international
usage must find non-proprietary names which could have
universal validity, and now the object is to provide a
proposed non-proprietary name in advance. Again, this
has no legal sanction. Yet the practice works smoothly
through the goodwill of governments, of pharmacologists
and of manufacturing concerns. The doubts and suspi¬
cions of ten years ago have long since disappeared. Over
40 leading pharmacologists in various parts of the world
have placed themselves and their laboratories freely at
the disposal of Who, and the misgivings of commercial
concerns have given place to full co-operation.
In the public interest, it is well that this is so. A Who
Study Group of Experts, meeting in December 1956,
pointed out: "It has been estimated that several hundreds
of new medicinal substances are being introduced into the
materia medica every year. This large number of new
substances presents a certain hazard to public health,
especially considering the relatively short time between
the production of a new substance and its use. Twenty
years ago, this interval may have been five to ten years.
Today it may be as short as six months."
As a further safeguard, Who arranged, in May 1957, for
a chemical reference centre to be established in Stockholm.
There, authentic chemical substances are held by the
Apotekarsocieteten ready for distribution to governments
and manufacturers for comparative assays.
That was one more addition to the Who international
reference centres, which already dealt with biological
standards, blood-groups, salmonella, shigella, escherichia,
poliomyelitis and influenza viruses. And these world
centres are only part of the network of co-operating
laboratories which has grown up. There exist six regional
laboratories for polio inquiries, six stations for rabies
research and 57 centres in 46 countries for the constant
checks on influenza.
By 1957, with the completion of the Supplement to the
two volumes of the first edition of the International
Pharmacopoeia, the World Health Organization had
to consider a new approach to the problem of multiplying
drugs. Printed volumes take time to prepare, especially
when every detail has to be checked and checked again by
references to forty experts in all parts of the world. As
the 1956 Study Group pointed out, in certain cases,
by the time of publication, the actual use of a preparation
may be already . diminishing or may have practically
disappeared.
To meet this situation, it was proposed that the Organi¬
zation should compile information sheets on new products
which, on the best advice available, would provide accurate
appraisals of new preparations and methods of assay for
the use of doctors and pharmacists everywhere.
All this is possible only because of the earnest goodwill
which experts everywhere have shown towards the Orga¬
nization. It now maintains close and active collaboration
with nearly 1,800 scientific institutions and laboratories,
all over the world. The great majority of these work
voluntarily, solely in the interests of scientific progress
and for the benefit of mankind. In the same spirit, more
than a thousand scientists are on call for service on the
expert advisory panels.
Thus, in the first ten years of its existence, the World
Health Organization has established mutual confidence
among those engaged in this work and, by providing
services, can command disinterested service.
R. C.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
HEALTH NEWS
FROM AROUND
THE GLOBE
The year 1957 was a bad one for
smallpox with about 120,000 cases
reported (of which 70 per cent were
in Asia) compared with about 85,000
in 1956. The world has seen worse
outbreaks with many more casualties,
but the disease has not lost its ability
to travel and to attack unsuspecting
persons who are not protected by
vaccination. Today smallpox persists
in many areas of Africa, Asia and
South America, but it is in countries
outside such areas where it has
become practically extinct that out¬
breaks are becoming more likely to
occur. One reason is that because of
its rarity it is not almost immediately
recognized; another is that in many
countries people are less protected by
vaccination than at any time in the
past century. Smallpox is not defeated
and as long as it persists anywhere
in the world, health authorities every¬
where must be on the alert.
Europe's bloodthirsty roads
The risk of death on the roads of
Europe, for a given distance, is ten
times that involved in travel either
by train or aircraft. In 1955 the
number of fatal road accidents in 14
countries of western Europe reached
a total of 35,000 and well over 600,000
people were injured. Since then the
number of vehicles on Europe's roads
has been rising by 12% each year.
Recent figures for every 100 millions
of kilometres travelled by road
vehicles were: 18 people killed in
Western Europe, 10 in Great Britain
and less than 5 in the U.S.A. Accident
responsibility on the roads of Europe
has been apportioned as follows:
Faults of motor vehicle drivers: 20
p.c.; faults of cyclists and pedes¬
trians: 5 p.c.; faulty vehicles 5 p.c.;
faulty roads : 70 p.c.
Air travel and health
Last year 90,000,000 people travelled
by air scheduled flights throughout
the world compared with 2,500,000 in
1937. During 1958 the figure is expect¬
ed to reach the 100,000,000 mark.
This tremendous increase in air travel
may soon overtax the facilities at
many international airports and not
least of all with regard to sanitary
conditions. The problem was discuss¬
ed recently by the Who Expert Com¬
mittee on Sanitation of International
Airports, at its first meeting in Gen¬
eva. International Sanitary Regula¬
tions already set up by Who deal
with quarantinable diseases such as
smallpox, cholera, yellow fever, etc.
30
WHO-INCAP
CIRCLE = GOITRE. Six countries of the AmericasCosta Rica, El Salvador, Guatemala,
Honduras, Nicaragua and Panamacombined, with the help of WHO and the Kellogg Founda¬
tion, to attack their nutrition problems by setting up the Institute of Nutrition of Central America
and Panama. Since INCAP came into existence over eight years ago It has made possible preven¬
tative measures, on an international scale, against endemic goitre, and has attacked the problem
of undernourishment by finding inexpensive means of improving local diets. Above, the circle
being marked on the throat means the child has goitre. Photo was taken during a survey which
revealed endemic goitre as a grave public health problem in INCAP countries. One of the
ways in which it is being tackled is through the iodization of salt for all human consumption.
and such questions as safe water sup¬
plies, disposal of waste, control of in¬
sects, rats and other disease carriers.
What do doctors die of?
The life expectancy of physicians
corresponds to that of the population
as a whole according to a recent study
in the United States. However, there
is a striking prevalence among
doctors of cardio-vascular diseases,
which cause the death of two doc¬
tors out of three, while the rate
for the male population in general is
one to three. According to the study,
cancer is the second largest killer of
American doctors, causing one death
out of every six.
Perils of air pollution
With industrial growth, more and
more gases, vapours, fumes, dusts and
other impurities are poured into the
air we breathe. This increasing
pollution of the atmosphere must be
prevented if our health is to be
safeguarded from its disastrous
effects. Some cases of air pollution
in Europe: Harmful effects on animal
and plant life have been reported
near aluminum factories in Swit¬
zerland and on plant life in Sweden
through gases from shale-oil factories,
iron works, phosphate factories and
other works. In Germany animal
losses have occurred near plants
releasing arsenic compounds into
the air. A recent study of air
pollution in Paris showed that motor-
traffic accounts for 30-40% of the
total pollution and domestic heating
for about 50%. Who has set up an
Expert Committee on Air Pollution
which groups medical and public
health specialists from Africa, Ame¬
rica, Asia and Europe.
Occupational hazards
The prevalence of peptic ulcers
among business executives over 50
years of age was 78.43 per cent.,
compared with 23.56 per cent among
other employees of the same age,
according to a recent study in the
U.S.A. In another study on 5,000
executives chosen from 30 American
companies, large and small, it was
found that 51.3 per cent, betweeen
the ages of 40 and 65 suffered from
either hypertension, organic heart
disease, overweight or such serious
conditions as diabetes,, prostatitis,
hernia, blood deficiencies etc. Yet
more than half of the executives
examined had previously shown no
symptoms and expressed no
complaints.
Deathtraps in the home
Accidental death is nowadays of
increasing concern to public health
authorities. Among children and
adolescents it often ranks as the
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
leading cause of death, primarily
because preventative medicine has
succeeded in lowering the loss of life
which previously occurred through
infectious and parasitic diseases.
Forty per cent, of fatal accidents
which happen to children between
one and four years of age take place
in and around the home. Pills con¬
taining dangerous substances, but
sugarcoated to make them palatable
are often left lying around. Some¬
times children chew cigarettes imi¬
tating their elders smoking, and get
nicotine poisoning.
The snail menace
One of the most difficult diseases
to fight is being tackled with the help
of Who in various countries today.
It is snail fever (medical term:
schistosomiasis or bilharziasis) and
it is estimated that 150 million people
are menaced by it in Asia, Africa and
Central and South America. It is
caused by the presence in the human
body of parasitic worms which feed
on the blood. Water snails help to
transmit the disease because embryos
from eggs laid by the worms use
them as hosts while reproducing
about 200,000 larvae which attack
humans by penetrating the skin.
For centuries snail fever has been a
scourge. Eggs have been found in
Egyptian mummies dating back to
2000 B.C. Egyptian medical authorities
say it is "the most serious and ruinous
disease" in their country.
'Harmless' little house-fly.
House-flies are, far and away, the
most numerous of all insects which
live close to man. They have fan¬
tastic powers of reproduction with
all the dangers that this implies in
the spreading of many diseases. It
has been calculated that one single
female house-fly laying 120 eggs on
April 15, could theoretically, by Sep¬
tember 10 have been responsible for
a "family" of no fewer than 5,598,720
million adult flies. Another estim¬
ation was that one pair of flies
could produce in a single summer,
325,923,000 million descendants. In
one single fly 100,000 bacteria origin¬
ating in human excrement have
been found. Few realize the losses
caused to the dairy industry by flies.
In U.S. tests during the fly season
insecticide-treated beef cattle gained
an average of 50 lbs more in weight
than those heavily infested by the
biting horn- fly.
Puzzle for pathologists
A puzzle has been set for patho¬
logists in a Who study which
compares mortality from various
types of cancer occurring in different
countries, and shows that a malignant
tumour of a kind which is particularly
fatal in one country may be relatively
much less so in another. It shows
that by far the highest death-rate
from cancer of the respiratory
system in men occurs in England
and Wales (45.5 per 100,000). Japan,
where the death rate from this type
of cancer is lowest (6 per 100,000) has
the highest rate of deaths from
cancer in the digestive system in men
(98.2- per 100,000).
The Unesco Courier. May 1958
WHO
what it stands for
The creation of the World Health Organization in 1948 was the
culmination of a long series of efforts made over the centuries
to prevent the spread of disease from one continent to
another and to achieve international co-operation for better health
throughout the world.
After the Second World War, when the Charter of the United
Nations was drawn up in San Francisco (1945), Brazil proposed that
health should be included in the U.N. Charter as one of the vital
factors for the stability and wellbeing essential for world peace.
The World Health Organization was set up the following year
in New York, at an international conference called by the United
Nations. It gradually absorbed the existing international health
organizations (Office International d'Hygiene Publique, Health
Organization of the League of Nations, Unrra Health Division).
The Pan-American Sanitary Bureau retains its name and indivi¬
duality while acting as the Who Regional Office for the Americas.
In April 1948 sufficient countries had ratified their membership
to enable Who to come into official existence, and in June 1948
the World Health Assembly met for the first time.
By 1958, its tenth anniversary year, Who had grown from the
26 states who were members on April 7, 1948 to 88. Ten years
ago its budget, contributed by Member States, was less than
$5 million; in 1958 it is $13,500,000.
In 1948, direct assistance to national governments in the form
of international staff and field projects was a new and almost
revolutionary idea. Today the World Health Organization has
over 500 professors, doctors, nurses and other health personnel in
the field, and in one way or another is assisting 700 health
projects in 120 countries and territories.
To enable it to adapt its programme to varying and evolving
needs, Who set up six regional organizations with offices: for
Africa at Brazzaville, French Equatorial Africa; for the Americas
at Washington D.C.; for South East Asia at New Delhi, India; for
Europe at Copenhagen, Denmark; for the Eastern Mediterranean
at Alexandria, Egypt; and for the Western Pacific at Manila, Phi¬
lippines. These regional offices maintain close co-operation with
national health services "to assist public health administrations
everywhere to take the next feasible step in their development."
In Geneva, a true nerve centre of international health work,
regional programmes are co-ordinated in a single programme
of Who activities with accompanying budget, which are studi¬
ed, discussed and approved by the annual World Health Assembly.
Types of assistance which Who has given during its first ten
years include: strengthening of national health services; establish¬
ing and maintaining epidemiological and statistical services;
controlling epidemic and endemic diseases; maternal and child
health services; promotion of mental health; improvement of sani¬
tation and preventative and curative medical services.
Who Member States benefit from its technical services (epide¬
miological intelligence, international quarantine, statistical, stan¬
dardization of therapeutic substances, technical publications) and
from its training programmes and fellowship awards (6,396
fellowships given to health personnel from 149 countries).
The day-to-day work of Who is carried out by a Secretariat of
about 850 international officials (54 different nationalities) either
at headquarters in Geneva, at Regional Offices or with field
projects. First Director-General of the Who was Dr. Brock
Chisholm (Canada) ; present Director-General is Dr. M.G. Candau
(Brazil) .
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
THE WANDERING DOCTOR
OF DEVIL'S MOUNTAIN
ALONG A STONY TRACK,
Dr. Hugh Russell's mobile health
team sets out (left) to visit an
Ethiopian mountain village. Armed
guard on right Is to protect party
against bandits. At the village the
first patients wait for attention
(right) even before the camp is
ready. Woman on ground has
collapsed In front of Dr. Russell's
tent. Her husband watches over
her. Below, the doctor examines
a village woman. He found many
of the people suffering from tuber¬
culosis due to undernourishment.
WHO photos
Few physicians have ever been given so difficult a task
as that assigned to New Zealander Dr. Hugh Russell
by the Ethiopian Government and the World Health
Organization. His two-year mission is to discover
from which diseases Ethiopians suffer and die. From his
report the Government will be able to organize health ser¬
vices on a practical basis among some 15 million people
who so far have never received any kind of medical care.
For staff he has a British male nurse, Robert Ousby (a
much-travelled ex-member of the Royal Navy), a French
administrator named Mr. Schilling (the right name for the man
who holds the purse strings), two Ethiopian male nurses
and a Somali cook. He is always escorted by an armed
guard to protect him against the shiftas (the bandits who
sometimes roam the mountains). And he takes with him
thousands of doses of penicillin, vaccines against smallpox,
typhus and rabies, ampules of vitamins, pills against malaria
and intestinal worms, aspirins and powdered milk.
Journeying by Land Rover, by truck and by mule but
often on foot among some of the world's most magnificent
scenery the rugged Devil's Mountain region bordering Ethio¬
pia's northern frontier with Sudan "The Quiet Doctor", as
the members of his team call him, invites sick people to
his camp. Often it is the whole village which arrives they
are all sick in one way or another with malaria, syphilis,
tuberculosis, anaemia, typhus, leprosy and a whole gamut of
intestinal diseases.
Bending over to listen to the chest of a child he detects
a shrill note. He shakes his head. The father of the
child leans towards the interpreter who translates the blunt
verdict: "Double pneumonia. It's too late. I can do
nothing for him; the child will die." The doctor neverthe¬
less orders a pencillin injection so that the parents, who have
tramped all night and morning to reach him, may not feel
they have come for nothing. Dr. Russell has to pass on
without waiting to find out what happens to his patients.
He must fold his tent and move on to the next village for
his survey will only be of value if it covers a sufficiently
large number of people.
32
The result of his work will be of paramount importance
for Ethiopia which has today only seven national and about
150 foreign physicians the latter being of 15 different
nationalities and, as a rule, not speaking any of the country's
ten dialects. Later this year his report will enable the
Ethiopean Government to organize, on a firm and permanent
basis, the health services of which these rural areas are in
such urgent need.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. May 1958
Letters to the Editor
KEEP IT SIMPLE
Sir,
As you ask for suggestions and criti¬
cisms, here are mine. Tell us about
the daily life of people in all parts of
the world as often as possible. I should
like to see, for example, articles like
-"A Woman's Life in an African
Village" (March and April, 1957). I
also feel that your magazine can and
should be widely read by countryfolk
and industrial workers... but the tech¬
nical and scientific language in which
many of the articles are written is
somewhat discouraging. Very often the
articles would be far more pleasant to
read if the same things were expressed
in more familiar terms which could be
immediately understood. It is a great
pity that people who are intelligent,
.though they may not have attained the
top standards of education, should be
forced to say "It's quite above my head"
or "The subject is far too difficult for
me", because of a few phrases or words
which could easily be replaced by more
simple ones. In making this point I am
solely concerned with the wider reader¬
ship of your magazine, and I hope
that you will also think of readers who
are not "'intellectuals" but who wish
to educate themselves and also develop
a better understanding of the rest of
the world. Take it from me, there are
many such people.
Mile J. Raiton
Paris, France
PROTECTING THE CHILD
Sir, .
In Paul Almasy's article, "The Rights
of 900 Million Children" (The Unesco
Courier, October 1957) no mention is
made of Spain. In issue N° 55 of the
Revista de la Protección de Menores (a
review dealing with the protection of
young people) there appeared a very full
account of the legislation applied by the
juvenile courts which exist in all the
provinces of Spain. One would have to
consult the Fuero Real (King's Grant),
the Leyes de Partida (Local Bye Laws),
the Institución de Padre de Huérfanos
(The Creation of Orphanages) and
especially the Cédula del Consejo
(Royal Council Charter) of luly 12,
1771, recorded in the Novissima Reco¬
pilación (Code of Laws), to find the
earliest antecedents of Spain's preoccup¬
ation with the problems of children in
need.
A law of 1904 created bodies for the
protection of children and in 1918
another law set up protective courts for
minors. Institutions operating under
these laws are alone taking care of
60,000 boys and girls in boarding and
semi-boarding schools, special homes,
reform schools, supervisory establish¬
ments, agricultural centres etc., There
are also other official organizations and
many centres run by the Church which
look after young people and make them¬
selves responsible for children even
before their birth, and until they reach
their majority. Corporal punishment is
forbidden and in the centres for minors
needing special education, the latest
psycho-pedagogical methods are em¬
ployed. The work thus carried out by
the Committees for the Protection of
Minors and by the Ministry of Educa¬
tion is of an educational and preven¬
tative nature and it has so reduced the
proportion of young delinquents that we
have been obliged to transform certain
reform schools into protective centres.
The legislation on education is a model
one. Since 1535 preoccupation with
social problems has been reflected in
Spain's laws. A -law on the employment
of women and young people which went
into effect last summer is one of the
most advanced forms of labour legis¬
lation in the world.
Candido Martin Alvarez
Consejo Superior de Protección
de Menores, Ministerio de Justicia,
Madrid
NEGLECTED NORTHERN AUTHORS
Sir,
I read with great interest The Unesco
Courier of lune, 1957 and in particu¬
lar Mr. Arrhe's "Great Literature of
East and West." I would like both to
congratulate and thank you for your
work in breaking the "translation cur¬
tain." In reading through your list of
published and to-be-published books in
English, I thought of a few suggestions.
In your series of the works of writers no
longer living why not Karl Gjellerup and
Henrik Pontoppidan, Danish co-winners
of the Nobel-Prizç for Literature (1917).
None of their works is available in
either English or French. luhani Aho
is highly regarded in Finnish literature.
The works of Nikolay S. Leskov are,
unfortunately, totally unavailable in
English. Surely Leskov as a Russian
classic deserves translation. In Mirsky's
classic on Russian literature, Leskov is
described as "generally recognized by
Russians as the most Russian of Russian
writers and the one who had the deepest
and widest knowledge of the people.4''
In your listings of contemporary
writers I noticed a Swedish to English
and Norwegian to French Unesco
translation. With no disrespect to
Swedish literature, surely with Par La-
gerkvist, Peter Nisser, Vilhelm Moberg,
Frans G. Bengtsson, and Harry Martin¬
son all available in English Swedish
would not be "a language of little diffu¬
sion". However, the absence of Finnish
writers seems apparent. None of the
works of Frans Eemil Sillanpää, Nobel
prize winner (1939) is available in
English. Heikki Toppila, Toivo Pekka-
nen, Unto Seppänen and Pentti Haanpää
all seem to be languishing behind the
translation barrier.
Howard L. Landon
Bedford, Indiana, U.S.A.
Ed. Note: Unesco is very conscious of
the importance of translation from the
Scandinavian' languages, particularly
Finnish. In the immediate future,
however, attention is being concentrated
on translations from the Asian lan¬
guages. Future projects envisage at
least one translation from Finnish.
DANGERS OF NUCLEAR FALLOUT
Sir,
I would like to suggest an issue on
the scientific facts regarding the dangers
of fallout from nuclear weapons; also
the need for enlightened public opinion
regarding the moral implication of bomb
testing.
Albert V. Baez
California, U.S.A.
WEATHER DOWN THE AGES
Sir,
Would it be' possible to publish an
article showing and explaining the cli¬
matic changes over historical periods.
One could touch on the Upper, Lower
and Middle Paleolithic, the Mesolithic
and Neolithic and enlarge as far as
possible on historical times. Vineyards
were once common in England, at Lin¬
coln, in the Salisbury area and else¬
where, then a cold spell came in; recent¬
ly it has been warming up again. A
comparison between England, the rest
of Europe, the Americas and elsewhere
would be of interest, I know of no
book which covers the subject from any
angle.
Climatic changes must affect history
but no history attempts to deal with the
effects. Food habits, clothing, housing,
apart from agriculture are all influenced
by the temperature and humidity.
I often wonder if the old castles built
say in the 12th century were erected for
a warmer climate and what was the
climate like in Britain during the Roman
occupation? Again what was the Ita¬
lian climate like in early Roman times,
did it get warmer so that malaria
spread?
S.N. Jenkinson
Bradford, England
TELLING THE UNESCO STORY
Sir;..
I would like to express my appre¬
ciation for your excellent magazine
whose papers have unfolded to me
during the last year a great wealth of
knowledge and interesting facts on
countless topics. As I have an interest
in nearly all the arts and in many fields
of science, I find the breadth and scope
your magazine remarkable and pleasing.
The most impressive thing, however,
that your magazine has conveyed to me
is the wonderful and extensive work
that Unesco carries out to impart peace
and humanity and liberty in this far
from perfect world of ours. I shall
continue to bring your magazine to the
notice of my friends, as I feel everyone
should interest themselves in the prob¬
lems and tasks with which Unesco
deals, and which I strongly feel concern
us all.
Marian Leach
Croydon, England
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom...
IVeWCOMER TO U.N.: A new
U.N. Specialized AgencyThe Inter¬
governmental Maritime Consultative
Organization (Imco) has just come
into being in London. The Convention
governing the functions of Imco to
serve the interests of international
shipping and seaborne trade was
drawn up in 1948, but needed ratifica¬
tion by 21 states, including seven with
at least one million tons of shipping
each, to bring the Agency into being.
Recent ratification of the Convention
by Japan fulfilled these conditions.
ATOMS FOR PEACE: More
than 200 scientists from 26 coun¬
tries have been invited by the
European Organization for Nuclear
Research (Cern) to attend the In¬
ternational Conference on High
Energy Physics which opens in
Geneva on June 30. India's third
atomic reactor is expected to go
into operation during 1958-59.
Known as "Zerlina," it will assist
scientists and engineers making
research in new designs for atomic
reactors. An "Atom School for
Business Men" will open in the
United Kingdom in September.
It will demonstrate to senior in¬
dustrial executives the many
applications of radio-isotopes in
industry and research.
M. HE UNIVERSE OF MUSIC:
One of the largest gatherings of
musicians, composers and conductors
from all parts of the world ever to
meet in Paris will take place in
SUBSCRIPTION
Subscribe to THE UNESCO COURIER
today
Fill in this subscription blank and mail
it with your cheque or money order
to our local agent in your country
listed on page 3 5
Please enter my subscription for
THE UNESCO COURIER
D One year S3. 00; IO/-stg. ; 500
French francs n Cheque/Money Order
enclosed
O Two years S5.50; £1 stg.; 1,000
French francs
Name	
Address 	
City	
Country....
Profession..
October and November next. This
Music Festival, together with a
Congress on "The Universe of Music
and its Different Cultures," is being
organized by the International Music
Council which was created by
Unesco in 1949. These events will
coincide with Unesco's Tenth General
Conference, in Paris and the
inauguration of the Organization's
new headquarters building.
PICASSO MURAL FOR UNESCO:
Last month Pablo Picasso handed
over to Dr . Luther H. Evans, Di¬
rector-General of Unesco, the
monumental mural he has complet¬
ed for Unesco's new building
in Paris. Commissioned as one of
the works by internationally fa¬
mous artists to decorate the
new building, Picasso's painting
consisting of 40 panels will be
mounted on a wall 31 feet wide
and will cover nearly 900 square
feet in the Conference building.
IjIBRARY FROM SUGAR: The
National Library of Cuba recently
vacated a former artillery barracks
where it had been housed for many
years and moved to a new home in
Havana. The cost of the new
building was obtained partly from
a duty of 0,005 pesos imposed on
every sack of sugar produced in Cuba
and partly from an advance by the
Bank for Economic and Social
Development. Its facilities include a
museum, a theatre and a music room.
It has a 17-storey tower which can
house one and a quarter million
books.
UNESCO BEST SELLERS': The
two most translated Unesco pub¬
lications are The Unesco Source
Book for Science Teaching (See
The Unesco Courier, February,
1958) and Nuclear Energy and Its
Uses in Peace by Gerald Wendt.
The book on Nuclear Energy has
already been translated into 15
languages and the Source Book
for Science into ten, although
other translations are being
considered. The first edition of
the science teaching book is now
practically sold out, but the second
edition (cloth bound) can be
obtained from Unesco's National
Distributors (See page 35). The
price is U.S. $3.00 or 15/- (stg.)
T V̂ GUIDES TO MUSEUMS:
Museum, film and TV specialists are to
meet during the International Exhibi¬
tion which opened in Brussels last
month to discuss how they can
collaborate to give better service to
the public. Films and TV offer new
opportunities of showing unique
collections in museums to a wider
public than over before, providing
certain technical problems are
overcome. The Brussels meeting, or-
ENTRY OF GHANA
BRINGS UNESCO
MEMBERSHIP TO 79
Unesco now has 79 Member
States. Last month Ghana, the
year-old West African nation
deposited the instrument of ac¬
ceptance of membership in
Unesco, in London, and thus
became its 80th Member State;-
But a few days later, the listing
of Egypt and Syria as two states
was formally changed to one
the United Arab Republic.
Unesco officially came into exis¬
tence on November 4, 1946 with
20 Member States. Since then its
home has been the Hotel Majestic
in the Avenue Kleber, in Paris.
This year it will move to its new
permanent headquarters now
nearing completion near the
Eiffel Tower on Paris's Left Bank.
Ghana became Unesco's newest
member on April 11 when its
representative signed the Unesco
Constitution which is kept in the
Foreign Office in London. The
state of Ghana was born at mid¬
night on March 5, 1957, when the
former colony of the Gold Coast
joined with the former British-
administered trust territory of
Togoland, to become an indepen¬
dent sovereign nation. The Gold
Coast had been an Associate Mem¬
ber of Unesco for some years.
ganized by the International Council
of Museums, will enable specialists
from different countries to exchange
ideas and experience.
SUN-MADE FRESH WATER:
Sun energy in the Antarctic is
being used to operate a solar still
for transforming salt water into
fresh by the Australian Expedition
at Davis base in Antarctica.
With a simple, compact still, which
produces fresh water by evapora¬
tion, the expedition is making
about two gallons of drinking
water daily. It can be used in all
climates since normal daylight is
all that is needed to set the
process in motion.
It»EAUTY IN ROCKS: Nearly 100
tons of decorative rocks and stones
are now being put in place in the
20th century Japanese garden which
is one of the decorative elements of
Unesco's new headquarters in Paris.
Construction of the garden is being
supervised by Isamu Noguchi, an
artist, sculptor and landscape gar¬
dener, who recently arrived from
Tokio bringing magnolia, cherry,
plum and bamboo trees a gift from
the peoples of Japan.
o
z
<
s
a
O
Z
LU
U
cC
O
LU
O
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
l* t '&- " '" i,,«>' '"t'-'ji x*. L.J A. jVjL AtS^R
m^y,
ÍICKIEWICZ
»\;#Aâ:ëiv'É^^
lV»ívV' .'
fV..-yag
DEATH
CO
UNESCO'S tribute to Adam Mickiewicz on the 100th anniversary of his death
(1855) was the publication of a work which pays, homage to the memory
of a great poet who "brought honour not only to Poland but to all mankind".
This work, which has since aroused the greatest interest in all parts of the world,
consists of two parts. The first comprises a series of studies and essays by pro¬
minent writers and professors on the various aspects of the life and works of the
great Polish author. Jan Parandowski, President of the Polish Pen Club, has contri¬
buted an introduction to the life and work of Mickiewicz, while Jean Fabre of the
University of Paris analyses the role of Mickiewicz in the European Romantic Move¬
ment. The influence of Mickiewicz's writings in Russia, France and Italy is examined
by Serge Sovietov of Leningrad University, Maxime Leroy of the Institut de France,
and Giovanni Maver of the University of Rome. In another essay, Karel Krejci,
of the Charles IV University in Prague, discusses Mickiewicz's influence on the lite¬
rature of the western and southern Slavs, while his most famous poem Pan Tadeusz
is analysed by Jules Kleiner of the Polish Academy of Sciences. To complete the
volume there are selections from some of Mickiewicz's major works.
BINDERS FOR YOUR
COLLECTION OF
Unesco Courier
We offer subscribers a spe¬
cial binder for their copies of
THE UNESCO COURIER hold¬
ing 12 issues of the magazine.
Handsomely produced in half-
cloth with the spine in an
attractive blue and the title (in
English, French or Spanish ac¬
cording to the edition to which
you subscribe) and Unesco co¬
lophon embossed in gold, these
convenient and attractive bind¬
ers, costing $2.50 ; 12/6 stg. ; or
600 Fr. frs, can be ordered from
UNESCO Agents listed below.
Unesco Publication, Paris. Price: U.S. S3. 00; I 5/6 (stg.); 750 fr. F.
Obtainable from UNESCO'S National distributors, see below.
WHERE TO SUBSCRIBE
Unesco's national distributors from
whom the English, French, Spanish
and Russian editions of the UNESCO
COURIER can be obtained are listed
below.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Press
Department, Royal Alghan Ministry of
Education, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 369 Lonsdale Street, Melbourne,
C.I, Victoria. (£A. 13/-.)
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C'., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V (seh.
37.50.)
BELGIUM. Louis de Lannoy, 15 rue
du Tilleul, Genval (Brabant). (Ir.b. 100.)
CANADA. University ol Toronto Press,
Baldwin House, 33 St. Georges Street,
Toronto 5. (S3.00.)
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House, P.O. Box
244, I 00 Parsons Road Colombo. (Rs. 9.)
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Libreria Económica, Pte Zayas
- 505-7 Apartado 113, Havana.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6 Norregade, Copenhagen K. (D.kr. 12.)
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (F.mk. 540)
FRANCE. Unesco Sales Section,
19 Avenue Kléber, Paris, 16'. CCP.
12598-48, Unesco Bookshop, Paris.
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8. (DM. 6.)
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Kultura, P.O. Box 149.
Budapest, 62.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; Gunfoundry Road, Hyde¬
rabad, I; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/ 1 Asal Ali Road, P. O.
Box 386, New Delhi, I; Sub-Depots :
Oxford Book & Stationery Co., Scindia
House, New Delhi; Raikamal Ltd.;
Himalaya House, Hornby Road, Bombay
I. (Rs. 6.70.)
INDONESIA. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Djakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
35, Allenby Road and 48, Nahlat Benja¬
min Street, Tel-Aviv. (I. L. 4.) -
ITALY. Libreria Commissionaria San-
soni, Via Gino Capponi 26, Casella Pos¬
tale 552, Florence, (lire 960.)
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 99
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings. (10/-)
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo. (Yen 500.)
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Peter Chong & Co.,
Post Office Box 135, Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta. ( 10/-.)
NETHERLANDS. - N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl. 6.)
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church. (10/-.)
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos. (10/-.)
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass 7, Oslo. (N. kr. 10.)
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60 The Mall,
Lahore ; Bunder Road, Karachi and
35 The Mall, Peshawar, (rs.6.)
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc.. 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo, P.O. Box
620. Manila.
REPUBLIC OF IRELAND. The
National Press, 16 South Frederick St.,
Dublin. (10/-.)
SWEDEN. - A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm
16. (Sw.kr. 7.50.)
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Pavot, 40 rue du Marché, Geneva. CCP.
1-236. (frs. S. 6.50.)
TANGIER. Paul Fekete, 2 rue Cook,
Tangier.
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
UNION OF BURMA.- S.P.C.K. (Burma)
549, Merchant Street, P.O. Box 222,
Rangoon.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Street, P.O. Box 724. Pretoria. (10/-.)
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 5 69, London, S.E. I. ( 1 0/-)
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22, N.Y. ($3.00.)
U. S. S. R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska KnjTga
Terazijt 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
'DOCTOR, DO I HAVE LEPROSY?'
Patient in the special leprosy centre at Polam-
bakkam, Madras, India, receives sad news, in answer
to his question, from Dr. Franz Hemerijckx of Bel¬
gium. Veteran of a 25 years' fight against leprosy
n the Congo, Dr. Hemerijckx opened the centre
in India in 1955. Eighteen months later he had
13,500 patients. Leprosy is still widespread in the
world, but as the effectiveness of new-found drugs
becomes known, more and more secret sufferers
appear for medical aid. The World Health Organi¬
zation has joined in the campaigns of many
countries to discover and treat leprosy sufferers.
Today the leprosy victim is no longer a person
without hope, no longer an outcast. (See page I 8)
Pierre-André Pittet
]]>
</page>
</document>
