<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="066244eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
ï
ß
FROM THE
The art of
decorating
ourselves
(See page 14)
%M'*W£¿£%*'**Vk
f2BH ' itW'i
1 5 _J»_ W
ß
W. ,*yr~f^A\
V
'Tfà^i «S
y* j A M%
ff
ß i
u - ' Imt
vmSá V
J
£WWÂ/ * .^ \^
i¥ ri££ "
ë
J U L Y
10 5 8
(llth year)
Price: I /-stg. (U. K.)
30 cents (U. S.)
5 0 francs (France)
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
WEST MEETS EAST
ON BRITISH TV
One of the most popular of British TV pro¬
grammes is an East-West forum called "Asian
Club", in which Asians, many of them in
national costumes, come together to discuss
questions of interest to Asia and the West.
Under an Asian chairman, British guest
answer questions posed by Asian
/clcib guests. Photos show participant in
'audience (above) asking question of Sir
- 'Compton Mackenzie, British author and trav¬
eller (right), seen with the evening's chair¬
man, Miss Shakuntala Shrinagesh. (See p. 22)
Photos © B. B. C.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
*£
JULY 1958
NTH YEAR
CONTEÍ
PAGE
3 EDITORIAL
4 THE MAKIOKA SISTERS
An inside view of life in Japan
By Irving Jaffe
7 WHEN CAN THEY GET MARRIED?
A recent U.N. Inquiry
8 BRIDE MEETS GROOM IN HISTORIC JAPAN
10 WHY JAPANESE GIRLS WON'T MARRY FARMERS
13 BILINGUALISM
How Wales solved this great educational problem
By Sir Ben Bowen Thomas
14 FROM THE NECK UP
The art of decorating ourselves
By Harry L. Shapiro
20 THE ROOTS OF PREJUDICE
Racial "superiority complex"
By Arnold Rose
22 ASIAN CLUB
An East-West Forum on Britain's TV
By Henry L. Cassirer
24 ONE PERSON OUT OF 44 IS A TWIN
By David Gunston
30 THE UNITED NATIONS IN BRUSSELS
32 MEET THE WOMEN OF GHANA
By Victor Akinyele Williams
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, I 9 Avenue Kleber, Paris 16, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade ^
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (12 issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. The United States of America edición is distri¬
buted by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 801 Third Avenue, New
York 22, N.Y. , Plaza 1-3860. Second-class mail privileges authorized at New
York, N.Y. (M.C. 58.1.126 A)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted prcviding
the credit line reads " Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER plus date
of issue", and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an internacional reply coupon covering poscage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represenc
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual lubscrlption rates: $3.00 ; 10/- stg. ; 500 French franci or equi¬
valent.
f^
'OflÄ
/TB
Wr? »ïiCî-^
COVER PHOTO
One of the elaborate designs which
Indians of the Peruvian Rainforest paint
on their faces. See story and photos
"From the Neck UpThe art of decorat¬
ing ourselves," on pages 14 to 19.
© American Mus. of Natural History, New York
How can the great creative minds of our times, such
as the great musicians, painters, writers, scientists
and statesmen -who live in different corners of the
globe be drawn more closely to Unesco ? This was the
deep-reaching question raised in a recent issue of Unesco
House News, a monthly bulletin produced for Unesco staff
members in Paris and in the field.
"I believe, and have often defended the idea at Unesco
and elsewhere," replied Professor Henri Laugier, France's
representative to the Unesco Executive Board, "'that one
of the best methods (though not the only one) of rallying
the great creative minds of our epoch and of mobilizing
certain of their activities for the benefit of Unesco's objec¬
tives, would be to organize great universal prize compe¬
titions open to all countries and to all thinkers.
"If, for example, Prizes were instituted to crown the
best film or the best essay, or the best novel or the best
work of music, or the best theatrical production dealing
with the emancipation of mankind in the course of his¬
tory, with the victorious advances made in Human Rights,
with mankind's efforts to break the shackles of ignorance,
poverty, political oppression (or economic or other forms
of tyranny), disease and slavery which bind him, we
would see a powerful movement of thought and art
develop in the world on behalf of one of the essential
objectives of Unesco. We would witness a great competi¬
tive effort and emulation by thinkers and artists, inspired
by the noble aims inscribed in the Charter of the Organi¬
zation. And we would have grounds to hope that from
such a Unesco initiative great works of art would be born
and see the light of day."
Professor Pierre Auger, noted French physicist and
director of Unesco's Natural Sciences Department, ex¬
pressed his frank views in the following terms :
"Unesco's programme already contains many elements
the principles of which should attract the attention of
scientists, artists and men of letters, and which can form
the basis for fruitful collaboration. The difficulties
encountered in establishing such collaboration stem, at
least in part, from a kind of incompatibility of tempera¬
ment between great creative minds and great administra¬
tors, be they national or international. Great or small,
the wind of the spirit blows where it will and it is not
always in the direction that the organizations expect.
'"This results in disappointment on both sides. The
difficulty can be compared to that of the harnessing and
utilization of free natural forces such as the wind, or to
the taming of wild though beautiful beasts. Much
patience, ingenuity and tact are called for. The promises
held forth must be both generous and tempting and above
all the promises must be kept. We should offer the crea¬
tive mind great occasions to express itself freely, yet we
should not hesitate afterwards to change plans labori¬
ously established in advance. For creation, by its very
nature, is unpredictable.
"The Prize competitions proposed by Professor Laugier
are excellent bait; Cern (European Nuclear Research
Centre) is a great snare-for-scientists but it is a voluntary
snare. And when a few years from now the first inter¬
national océanographie vessel lifts anchor and sets out to
sea under Unesco's auspices it should be allowed to char¬
ter its own course unhindered."
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
THE MAKIOKA SISTERS
A great contemporary novel that
shows how a Japanese woman
finds a husband
gives an 'inside' picture of
day-by-day life in Japan by Irving Jaile
ow does a Japanese woman find a husband ? What
J~l are the important factors governing her choice:
romantic love, money, physical attraction, the
man's health, family, social position ? The answer, as
revealed in a newly-published translation of a famous
Japanese novel The Makioka Sisters is: all of them
but least important of all, perhaps, at least for girls of the
upper middle classes, is romantic love.
Although Japan, unlike many other Asian nations, has
long been prominent on the international scene, most
Westerners know little about, her life, customs and tradi¬
tions. An increasing number of sociological, historical
and literary studies devoted to Japan is available to
Western readers. But important as such studies are for
a comprehensive knowledge of the country, none of them
perhaps can give us the intimate "feel" of day-by-day life
in Japan that is provided by this work of fiction.
The Makioka Sisters represents the culmination of a
life-long intellectual and artistic evolution by the author,
Junichiro Tanizaki, who is generally regarded as Japan's
leading contemporary novelist. In his earlier days, under
the influence of such Western writers as Poe, Baudelaire
and Oscar Wilde, TanizaM wrote bizarre, sometimes gro¬
tesque stories, often dealing with aberrations in human
behaviour.
In his more mature years, Tanizaki acquired a growing
interest both in the traditional Japanese esthetic as
evidenced by his modern-language translation of the
early eleventh century Japanese classic novel The Tale of
Genji and in the unfolding of ordinary Japanese lives.
Novel born of war & peace
As a high point in this development, The Makioka
Sisters is ideally suited to take us "inside" the Japan
of the recent past and of a certain milieu: the
immediate pre-war Japan of the upper middle classes in
the Osaka-Kyoto region where something of the tradi¬
tional Japanese ways and douceur de vivre still exist.
Begun toward the end of the war, The Makioka Sisters
(published in Japan as Sasame-yuki) was completed in
the early post-war years. Recommended for translation
by Unesco and the Japanese National Commission for
Unesco, as representative of Japanese culture, it has now
been published in four countries in a strikingly readable
English translation by Edward G. Seidensticker (1).
Structurally, the novel, with its lack of any strong plot
or dramatic climaxes, its up-in-the-air ending, may dis¬
concert the Western reader. But this very absence of a
"story" structure, this meandering through all the details
of daily living, produce a fidelity to life which is highly
informative to the foreign reader.
With infinite patience, Tanizaki threads his way
through some five years immediately preceding Japan's
entry into World War H in the lives of the four Makioka
sisters, members of a respected merchant family which is
gradually declining both in wealth and in social standing.
Tanizaki has said he tried to confine himself to "what
was attractive" in the graceful pre-war life, "but I was
not able to withdraw completely from the enveloping
storm. This was the necessary fate of a novel born of
war and peace."
Retiring Yukiko & rebellious Taeko
The main theme of the novel is the series of repeated
failures in the family's attempt to find a socially
acceptable husband for the third sister: silent, mild-
mannered, retiring Yukiko, the most '"traditional" Japan¬
ese of them all. The impact of the modern world on
traditional Japanese ways, and the disturbances this
causes, are reflected in the hectic life of the bright,
modern, independent and somewhat rebellious youngest
sister, Taeko, Who finally is excluded from the family
circle.
Yet no ultimate, irretrievable tragedy befalls any of the
main characters: life just goes on. Yukiko finally finds
a husband, and Taeko ends up as the wife of a bartender
but, even here, it is clear that the bonds of affection
and loyalty between Taeko and her sisters will endure
despite official ostracism.
The main interest of the novel for Western readers lies
in the wealth of intimate detail about Japanese life
glimpses both of thoroughly modern daily life and of
ancient customs which, even though some of them are
undoubtedly on the decline in present-day Japan, show
us a side of life which still persists.
The flashing beauty of a night-time fire-fly hunt and
(1) "The Makioka Sisters": New York - Alfred A. Knopf; London -
Seeker and Warburg ; Tokyo - Charles E. Tuttle ; Toronto - McClelland
and Stewart. "The Makioka Sisters" is one of the works whose
translation has been sponsored by Unesco under Its "Translation of
Representative Works" programme.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July 1958
Photo by Takamasa Inamu'ra © Camera Press Ltd.
the serene and timeless quality of the annual cherry-
blossom viewing take their place in Tanizaki's novel along
with close-up views of Japanese homes, offices, hospitals,
and innumerable other scenes of daily life.
We see the unfolding of family relations in all their
subtleties, both the formal relations between the house of
the head of the family and related households, and the
interplay of individual personalities, the intricate match¬
making négociations, and the traditional miai ceremony
in which prospective bride and bride-groom meet in the
presence of family members and go-betweens.
The vivid description of a flood is followed by an
account of the Japanese at the mercy of violent typhoon
winds in their frail wooden houses which almost literally
burst at the seams.
The Western reader is struck, perhaps above all, by the
pervasive presence of the West in the midst of traditional
Japanese life the co-existence of Western and Eastern
elements in virtually all aspects of daily living, as evi¬
denced, for example, by the Japanese practice of furnish¬
ing some rooms in their homes in Western style and
others in traditional Japanese fashion.
One is tempted to see in Japanese life as portrayed in
Tanizaki's book a new synthesis between Oriental and
Western ways, just as, in the literary field, Donald Keene,
a leading student of Japanese literature, sees in The
Makioka Sisters evidence of a new period in which
European literary influences may "have finally been
absorbed into the native tradition, and techniques evolved
with which we are as yet unfamiliar."
When we realize that the tradition of the novel in
Japan dates back to the tenth century, the literary as
well as the intensely human interest of The Makioka
Sisters to the Western reader becomes very evident.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
JAPAN (Continued)
All photos by Takamasa Inamura. © Camera Press Ltd.
METAMORPHOSIS FOR MARRIAGE. A modern Japanese girl, Noriko Kamimura (above left), aged 20, becomes a
beautiful bride garbed in the ancient and traditional style. First change comes (above, right) when her permanent is hidden
under the elaborate taka-shimada coiffure, worn exclusively by brides. Wigs of different sizes for this coiffure are seen below,
left. Below, right Noriko, looking almost doll-like, is ready for the ceremony. White turban worn round coiffure is called
tsuno-kakushi, literally "to hide the horns", a decoration based on the superstition that brides have horns of jealousy.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
When can they
get married ?
A U.N. inquiry
In Japan, as in a great many other countries, the
free consent of both intending spouses is
necessary for the validity of the marriage. A
Japanese man can take a wife when he has reached
the age of 18, and a Japanese woman can get
married at the age of 16, but Japan's Civil Code lays
down that a minor having limited civil capacity
may contract marriage only with the consent of the
person who exercises parental authority over him
(father or mother as the case may be), or of the
person who is his guardian or trustee.
The minimum age of marriage varies widely in
different parts of the world. A young girl living in
Ireland, Bolivia or Swaziland may legally marry at
the age of twelve; in Denmark, Czechoslovakia or
Ethiopia she must wait until she is 18. Boys in
Burma, Chile and Spain may marry at fourteen,
but in the German Federal Republic, Peru and
Sweden they may not marry before they are 21.
In some countries, particularly in Asia and Africa,
there are no restrictions and young people are al¬
lowed to marry as soon as they reach the age of
puberty, according to traditional or religious prac¬
tice. Even in some of the more socially and econo¬
mically advanced nations, girls may marry at the
age of twelve and boys at fourteen.
' Preferably not under
fourteen years of age '
A study on the subject made by the United
Nations was discussed recently in Geneva by
the U.N. Commission on the Status of Women.
The meeting had before it a recommendation on
"the desirability of free consent of both parties, and
the establishment of a minimum age for marriage,
preferably not less than fourteen years."
According to the U.N. study, differences exist not
only between one country and another but also
within certain countries with a federal system of
government. In Australia, for instance, legislation
in some states sets the marriageable age of a girl
at sixteen, while in others the age is twelve. Similar
variations are found between the provinces of
Canada and the states of the United States.
A number of countries, among them the U.S.S.R.
and Yugoslavia, require only the consent of the
parties to be married, assuming they have reached
the legal age. Young people in most of Western
Europe, Latin America, the British Commonwealth
and the United States may marry before the speci¬
fied age with the consent of their parents or guar¬
dians. In some areas, parents or guardians of the
prospective bride must give their consent but this
is not required for the groom. In yet others, the
consent of parents or guardians is considered a
major requirement for marriage.
The Unesco Courier. July 1958
CEREMONIAL COSTUME worn by Noriko Kamimura at her marriage calls
for dressing session which is almost a ceremony in itself. Above, expert cos-
turner ties a pink naga-jiban, or long under kimono with a stiff ribbon sash.
Bride's mother, wearing a ceremonial kimono, looks on proudly. After Noriko
has donned bridal costume an obi, or embroidered sash, is wound twice over
the costume and tied in the back (below) with an immense butterfly knot.
photos by Takamasa Inamura. © Camera Press Ltd.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Bride meets groom
in historic Japan
In the West love usually precedes
marriage, but in traditional Japan it came
after marriage. It was, and sometimes
still is, considered dishonourable for a
young person of either sex to select a life-
mate. According to a feudal idea, a girl
married more into the family of the bride¬
groom than to the young man, and in
the past if a boy and a girl got married
through mutual love their union was
considered a "free marriage" and condem¬
ned. In modern Japan, however, with
the increased independence of women,
love marriages are now more common and
accepted occurrences.
Hierarchy is basic to Japan's whole
notion of traditional social relations.
Hierarchy is observed above all in family
life. The Japanese family is a tightly-
knit social unit. The sense of belonging
to a family, of acting in the family name,
of defending family honour, is extremely
powerful, particularly in rural regions.
Authority is vested in the father (or the
grandfather, if he is alive). Immediately
after the father in seniority comes the
eldest son. Within the family, rank is
determined by age and by relationship to
the head of the family. The head of the
family's wife, in particular, has authority
8
over the other women and is entitled to
special respect from the younger men.
In ancient times young men and women
were to a large extent free to choose mates
for themselves, and as a rule all the parents
had to do was agree. In feudal Japan,
marriages were usually arranged by the
families concerned without consulting the
wishes of the future couple. Although
this custom has not completely vanished,
it has been replaced in recent times by
two other ways of arranging a marriage :
1) the type of marriage in which the
wishes of the couple concerned are exclu¬
sively the deciding factor. 2) a type of
arranged marriage in which both the
interests and preferences of the two fami¬
lies and the wishes of the prospective hus¬
band and wife are taken into account.
Negotiated marriages are arranged in
Japan by a match-maker, known as a
Nakodo (literally, go-between) who may be
a close friend or a relative. Originally,
go-betweens did not seek payment for their
services but simply the happiness of the
married couple and the maintenance of the
two families' lineage. In modern times
not a few go-betweens perform their func¬
tion for the sole purpose of making money.
The main function of the go-between is to
find suitable candidates, act as liaison
between the families by providing photo¬
graphs and curriculum vitce of the young
persons, and especially to arrange an inter¬
view (miai) between the prospective bride
and groom and to carry out an exchange
of gifts between their families.
The wedding ceremony is called San-san-
kudo (literally 3-3-9 times), for the bride
and bridegroom exchange rice-wine cups
3x3 = 9 times, i. e. they drink nine sym¬
bolic cupfuls from a set of three lucky
wine-cups beautifully lacquered with lucky
designs painted on them.
A Japanese bride of old wore a raw
cotton hood to hide her face at a wedding.
Modern brides have a piece of paper called
Tsuno-kakushi (horn hider) over their
dressed hair. It is proverbially said that
a jealous woman has horns and her ima¬
ginary horns are thus symbolically hidden
by the headband. According to Onna
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July 1958
Daigaku (Women's Great Learning), a
17th century book which a Japanese bride
in feudal days put in her trousseau,
jealousy was included among seven causes
for which a wife could be divorced.
(Among other causes formerly accepted as
justifying divorce : disobedience to her
parents-in-law, talkativeness and indiscreet
speech for which '"she shall leave lest she
should cause discord among the relatives
of her husband or discord in her home.").
Today Japanese wives are recognized by
the law a human beings with the same rights
as their husbands. "'Marriage shall be
based only on the mutual consent of both
sexes, and it shall be maintained through
mutual co-operation with the equal rights
of husband and wife as a basis," says the
Japanese Constitution. If a wife owns
property in her own right her husband
cannot take it from her. And if the
worst comes to the worst she can apply
for a divorce. Japanese women were
granted the right to vote in October 1945,
and exercised this right for first time in
the general election held on March 11,
1946, when 13,767,300 women (67% of
those eligible) went to the polling stations
and elected 39 out of 82 women candidates'
to the Diet.
RICE WINE TOAST
TO THE NEWLYWEDS
In Japan, most weddings are celebrated according to the Shinto ritual.
The ceremony usually takes place in a special marriage room or at home.
Once all the guests have been seated by ushers, robed musicians sitting
cross-legged (far left) begin to play wind instruments. This is a signal
for the Shinto priests in full regalia to enter with their attendants.
Then begins a solemn service during which many prayers are offered
at the altar, cups of rice wine (omiki) are exchanged between bride and
groom and a toast is drunk (left) to the future happiness and longevity
of the newly-weds. The couple then proceed to the altar, renew their
pledges to the gods and offer branches of the sacred sakaki tree. Western
style weddings are also popular in Japan. In photo below, bride and
groom are seated at far right, with bride wearing a white robe and veil
and her husband-to-be in frock coat and striped trousers. (Even in
traditional Japanese weddings, however, it is usual for the groom to
wear Western dress). Although a Japanese officially reaches his
majority when he is 20, the traditional line of demarcation between
adolescence and adulthood is generally considered to be marriage.
Photos by Takamasa Inamura and Nakada. ® Camera Press Ltd.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
WHY JAPANESE GIRLS
WON'T MARRY FARMERS
Last year in some 40 villages around the cities of Tokyo, Osaka and Nagoya, people gathered
around newly-installed TV sets to watch a programme entitled "Why do girls dislike marrying
farmers?"one of a series of 13 telecasts on the theme "For the progress of farming
villages". These programmes marked the launching in Japan, under UNESCO sponsorship,
of the community tele-club movement, first developed in France and later in Italy with
UNESCO support. By evoking basic problems of rural life, the Japanese telecasts aimed
to show village people how they might improve their living conditions and rural amenities
in general. On the following pages we reproduce two of the TV scripts"The Life of
Japanese farmers" and "Why do girls dislike marrying farmers" (an audience survey
showed that this second programme made the greatest impact of all). Although great
changes and improvements in the status of women have come about in recent years in
Japan, the TV series reveals that much can still be done to improve the condition of women
in farming areas where changes have come more slowly and are often slower to be accepted.
At present, we hear various rumours about farming
villages in Japan. Some say that farmers are very
rich and can buy such luxurious things as auto-
tricycles, electric washing machines, mixers etc. while
others report that farmers are compelled to live just as
miserably as before, and sometimes forced to sell their
daughters to prostitute dealers.
Now setting aside these rumours, we should look into
the real life of the Japanese farmers.
We shall start from the centre of Tokyo. About half
an hour's drive by motor car takes us into the suburb
district, and soon the rural areas spread out before us.
Okagami is one of the rural villages not very far from the
centre of Tokyo. It consists of 83 families wholly engaged
in farming. The area of arable land per family is one
and a half acres.
It is already late autumn and the farmers' busy season
will soon be over.
We can see a few farmers using small-sized cultivating
machines, but most of them" are cultivating with hoes as
their ancesters did. Human body and cattle back are
the most familiar instruments for transportation. Motors
are not sufficiently introduced. This village being
situated near the city of Tokyo, arable land is specifically
utilized for vegetable-growing. But transportation and
fertilization are entirely dependent on human power.
Rich farmers sometimes engage in dairy or poultry-
farming on the side. Persimmon trees, mandarins for
flower arrangement and other heritages from the
ancestors also bring about some side income to villagers.
Most of the farmers have sewing machines, but the
insides of the houses have scarcely changed since the
days of their parents and grandparents. The old-
fashioned paper sack of patent medicine from Toyama
is a symbol of conventionality. The kitchen remains
dark and the toilet as unsanitary as of old. The branch
school for lower-grade children is provided With neat
establishments for food supply, but the ground is narrow
and muddy. Children's paradise is the precincts of a
temple called Tôkôin. Here, a sand bed and a library
for children are provided by the chief priest. But boys
and girls cannot spend much time at the temple precincts,
because as soon as they come back from school they must
go to help their parents working in the fields.
As in the case of the farmers throughout Japan, vil¬
lagers of Okagami return from the fields after dark.
^
^
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July 1958
UNESCO photos
FARMER'S WIFE in Japan is usually the busiest person in the family. As well as looking after husband and children she often
has to take care of silk raising, lend a hand with wheat harvesting and rice-planting and do other heavy chores. Above, with
youngest child riding pick-a-back, farmer's wife returns from far-off well with drinking water. Opposite page (bottom, right)
drawing water from a community-built tank in a mountain village (Japanese telecasts have stressed the need for collective
action in villages); left, stone wall cultivation of strawberries and their preparation for market are jobs for women workers.
After feeding the cattle, they sit at a table for supper.
After supper they engage till late at night in the packing
of vegetables to be transported to the market the
following morning.
Mr. NINOMIYA, CHAIRMAN: The above is the real
situation of Okagami Village. Now, what do the villagers
think about their life? Let us hear some frank opinions
from Mr. Yamada, one of the conscientious farmers, and
Mr. Kaji, one of the leaders of a 4H club.
Mr. YAMADA: I have eight family members to support,
and three daughters are salary earners. Only three of
us are wholly engaged in farming. I have 3.5 tan
(0.85 acres) of paddy fields and 8 tan (2 acres) of farms.
They say we had a good harvest last year, but so far as
our village is concerned, it is not true. When I was young,
farmers had to work from early in the morning till late
at night. The situation has very much improved, it is
true, but owing to the advance in the standard of living
we must work as much as we did twenty years ago.
Mr. KAJI: I cultivate 2.4 tan. (0.6 acres) of rice fields
and 7 tan (1.5 acres) of field with three other family
members. Four other family members are salary earners.
I admit that farmers must work very hard, but in my
opinion farmers too have the right to live an ordinary
cultural life.
Mr. YAMADA: Young men want to lead an easy and
luxurious life, and somehow lack the will to work.
Consequently they venture on a large-scale management
without concrete plans and sufficient funds only to face
miserable failures. Studies of agricultural experimental
stations and other institutions seem so impractical to us.
Mr. KAJI: in my opinion, to consider cultural life itself
as a luxury stems from an inferiority complex of tradi¬
tional farmers. I don't want to lead an easy life but I
wonder whether farmers must work as if they were horses
or cows. I want to be a farmer who can use his own
brains. Farmers in future should be well-acquainted
with the progress of agricultural techniques and carry
out scientific management. Of course, the improvement
of living conditions is important but it must be
accompanied by the improvement of agricultural man¬
agement.
In our previous programme we took up the problem of
whether Japanese rural villages should stay as they
are. Concerning this problem we have received
various reactions. Especially young men and women have
sent us various opinions. The following is the opinion of
a young woman who lives in a farming village.
"I don't agree with adults who think that
farming villages have been much improved.
As long as the farming villagers remairi as
they are, I feel disinclined to marry a
Cont'd
on
next page
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
JAPANESE
FARMERS
(Continued)
Td rather marry a salaried man'
farmer. Marrying a salaried man even if he earns a small
income seems to be happier than that to a farmer."
This is rather a bitter opinion, but many young women
share the same view. Let us now begin by listening to
what women think of rural life today. Mrs. Yokota and
Mrs. Ebizawa will speak from the viewpoint of housewives
and Miss Yamada as a young woman. All three ladies
live at Okagami Village.
MISS YAMADA: My parents are farmers but I have a
job at a cinema-house in the neighbouring town. So, I
do not help on the farm even on holidays. I am of the
same opinion as the writer of the letter you have just
read,
Mr. NINOMIYA: Of the factors which make girls dis¬
like marrying farmers, such as feudalists family system,
structure of house buildings, severe labour, rare oppor¬
tunity for amusement, etc., which Would you say is the
strongest reason for your disinclination to marrying a
farmer?
MISS YAMADA: What makes me disinclined most is the
fact that farmers still regard the wife as a kind of
instrument of farming. And While the man is taking a
rest with a newspaper in his hand, the woman must work
hard in such jobs as cooking, washing, infant rearing,
and so on. The other day I saw a picture entitled
"Record of a Mother" in which the hard, back-aching
work of the farmer's wife was shown very realistically.
(The film is projected on the- TV screen.)
Dawn to dusk work & mother-in-law's moods
Announcer: Most of the farmers in the Ina Valley
along the River Tenryu are pursuing silk-raising as
a side job. Slopes of the hills are covered with
mulberry-trees. Dwelling-houses are built very large
because silkworms are raised in them.
This is Mr. Miyazawa's house. His family is made up
of seven people in all. His eldest daughter works at the
filature factory in the town. He possesses only 1.6 acres
of land 0.5 acres of wheat-field 0.5 acres of rice-field.
The income from silk-raising is therefore very important
to Mr. Miyazawa. June is the busiest month when both
silk-raising and rice-planting require many hands. The
mother is the busiest person in the family and she is
obliged to have her supper after the rest of the family
have finished theirs. The business of silk-raising is
mainly left to the house-wife, but at the busiest season,
the school is closed to allow schoolchildren to help the
family. Mr. Miyazawa raised 40 grammes of silkworms
this year. Silk-raising is not as profitable nowadays
because of the development of the nylon industry.
Excrements of silkworms are important as they are used
for fertilizer.
After taking care of the silkworms the mother goes to
help in the wheat-harvesting. She goes on reaping, never
taking a rest. The former land-owner comes to ask for
help. Mr. Miyazawa cannot refuse it because of his
former relations with him, and he and his sons go to till
the land-owner's fields. The mother, left alone, fertilizes
the rice field. It begins to rain. Wet mulberry-leaves
make silk-worms ill, and so the farmers gather them in
in all haste.
12
A letter has come from the eldest daughter who ia
working at the filature factory, she says, "T hear mulberry-
leaves are suffering from noxious insects and I wonder
if you have enough leaves. How about the price of
cocoons? I am thinking of mother who must be working
very hard." Indeed, mother is working very hard from
morning till night. She also has to humour her mother-
in-law's temperament.
The shortage of mulberry-leaves has proved real, as
expected. The agricultural cooperative union buys
mulberry-leaves through the intermediaries on behalf of
the farmers. It is very clear that the raising of silkworms
with purchased mulberry-leaves does not pay, but the
farmers have no alternative.
Town girls are unfit for a farmer's life
Voice of the Daughter: My mother was born in a
farmer's family, and, when young, worked at a
filature factory. She has been working all her life.
Will my married life be like my mother's? Nevertheless
mother looks very calm...
Mr. NINOMIYA: What do you think about the mother's
life just introduced in the film? And what is your opin¬
ion about Miss Yamada'á view against the marriage to
a farmer? Lastly, what type of a girl do you want as
your son's bride? ^
Mrs. EBIZAWA AND Mrs. YOKOTA: The mother's life
introduced in this film is very much like ours. We can
understand the sentiment of rural girls who dislike
marrying farmers. We hope they will not suffer from
such a miserable life as we have led in the past.
But as to our sons' Wives, town girls are unfit for a
farmer's life. We want girls born in the farmer's family
as our son's wives.
Mr. NINOMIYA: You want, on the one hand, your
daughter not to marry a farmer, and on the other hand,
you want a girl from a farmer's family as your son's wife.
These two desires seem to contradict each other,
nevertheless it seems reasonable in the present case.
Wanted ! cheerful & comfortable villages
N ow let us listen to the opinion of Mrs. Sue Sumii, a
writer, who has a profound knowledge of farming
life.
Mrs. SUMII: These two desires, which seem to contra¬
dict each other, in a sense, seem to be the products of a
mother's love for her son and daughter. At the bottom
of these desires, lies the farmer's miserable life. If the
farmer should get rid of the poverty, such contradiction
will naturally disappear. Farmers must try to heighten
their productive capacity and also hasten the rationali¬
zation of consumption. Reorganization of life must first
start from renewing of ideas. Construction of cheerful
and comfortable villages and homes by farmer's own
hands may be the surest way to make girls willingly
marry farmers.
Mr. NINOMIYA: We have indeed many problems to
consider, all of which are difficult to be solved at once,
but I hope you will study and discuss with each other
these problems conforming to the actual situation of your
own villages.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July 1958
BILINGUALISM
How Wales solved this great educational problem
by Sir Ben Bowen Thomas
We hear so much today
about Bilingualism in
Education. We cannot
escape from it in Wales, and
in this experience we are not
unique. On the continent of
Europe you have only to think
of Belgium, Holland, Switzer¬
land, Yugoslavia and the states
of the U.S.S.R. to realize how
many countries are involved.
Nor is this a matter that ex¬
clusively concerns the smaller
countries. The so-called Great
Powers, whose language may
be English, Russian, Spanish or
French are increasingly realiz¬
ing that . monolingualism no
longer meets the needs of the
present situation and that every
intelligent citizen of the future
should have a working know¬
ledge of at least one other
modern language besides his
own. In. Wales it is a case of
"Escape Me Never". Something
has been done about it for
three generations or more; it is
still a live educational issue.
What do we mean by Biling¬
ualism? It is the acceptance
of the educational aim that, if
possible, the average pupil in
our schools should attain a
mastery of his mother tongue
and a working knowledge of the
second language current within
his society by the time he
reaches his twelfth year, and in
any case by the time he reaches
the end of his period of com¬
pulsory education.
There is the general aim. In
Wales, Welsh is the historic
language. It has an honour¬
able literary history of a thous¬
and years; it was a well-estab¬
lished and standardized lan¬
guage before English was,
though today English is the
first language of two-thirds of
the people.
In this matter of bilingualism
in Wales the Education Acts
impose three duties upon the
administrators in the Ministry.
The first requires the promo-
Sir Ben Bowen Thomas, Perma¬
nent Secretary, Welsh Department,
Ministry of Education, is the re¬
presentative of the United King¬
dom on the Executive Board of
Unesco. This article is based on a
Broadcast by Sir Ben in the Welsh
Home Service.
tion and development of the
education of the people of
Wales and the development of
their institutions, pre-eminent
amongst which is the Welsh
language. In the last fifty years
there has been no slackening
of vigilance in this matter.
Language surveys have been
made so as to devise suitable
ways and means of dealing
with the children of every area
in terms of their own condi¬
tions. Hundreds of summer
schools, conferences and local
courses have been arranged to
help teachers to cope With prob¬
lems of school organization
and curricula. Publishers have
been stimulated to provide
school readers, the School
Broadcasting Council for Wales
has been helped in the prepara¬
tion of its Welsh programmes,
and, as a result of these efforts,
there has been a great impro¬
vement in the development of
clear language policies by local
education authorities, in in¬
creasing the number of com¬
petent, teachers of Welsh, in
improving school organization
and in applying better class¬
room techniques.
The second duty is concerned
with the training of teachers.
There is no problem of numbers
in Wales, but there has been a
problem of getting the right
kind of teachers and of using
them in Wales. Training col¬
leges have met both these
needs increasingly. In addition,
courses of training through the
medium of Welsh have now
been established at two of our
colleges, and the Minister has
asked the Welsh Joint Educa¬
tion Committee to encourage
Welsh local education authori¬
ties to see that these qualified
bilingual teachers should toe
employed in due course.
The third duty derives from
the section of the Act that says
that pupils are to be educated
in accordance with the wishes
of their parents. This is often
referred to in connection with
bilingualism.
In recent years the Ministry
has approved the establishment,
in mixed linguistic areas, of
Welsh schools for Welsh-speak¬
ing children on educational
grounds.
The local education authori¬
ties have also made consider¬
able progress, both singly and
collectively. Some have ap¬
pointed language organizers; a
few have stimulated the pro¬
duction of suitable school text¬
books and very good they are.
Several have reorganized their
schools in the interest of better
bilingual teaching. Where com¬
munities are overwhelmingly
Welsh-speaking or English-
speaking, arrangements can be
simple and little change may be
required. Welsh language pri¬
mary schools or English lan¬
guage primary schools can be
established and the second lan¬
guage English or Welsh can
be gradually introduced when
the child enters Junior School.
But where the communities
are very mixed in a linguistic
sense, other solutions become
necessary. Sometimes all the
children will enter the same
school and then they will be
classified on a language basis,
the unity of the school being
maintained through its acts of
worship, social functions and
games. In such schools the
dominating language of the
playground will be the ascen¬
dant one. The second solution
in linguistically mixed areas
may also involve the assembling
of children of the minority lan¬
guage group from a wider area
than is usual and concentrating
them in one school. In this
way Welsh language schools
have appeared in recent years
in city, town and urban areas.
The Welsh Joint Education
Committee has stimulated the
production of Welsh books by
levying sums of money from the
local education authorities so as
to guarantee something like
£16,000 a year for these books.
And so we have both central
and local government playing
their part to establish as fair a
bilingual policy in the schools
of Wales as is possible.
The result can be far-reach¬
ing. Only recently the maga¬
zine "Education" declared:
"The Welsh crucible can yield
results that might radically in¬
fluence not only other bilingual
countries, but the teaching of
language everywhere."
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
w s
^L ^^dPMfljMHjfcÉ^jlHj
WkW W-
WÊtk
1 i:'ikr .^^^ImmÊ^ÊM -'fl
Fi flMTflflflfll
II
P.-, M
ÍlKffi9l
:i , i ' ' ^kr
#fl,2^ ^ :" MP
\ft*y' -- a - flW
FROM THE NECK UP
The Art of Decorating Ourselves
by Professor Harry L Shapiro
American Museum of Natural History, New York
There used to be a theory, current
at the turn of the century, that
Art began with primitive man's
habit of adorning his body. Nowa¬
days we are less certain of this. But,
nevertheless, if we grant that the
practice may be a form of self ex¬
pression and if its universality is any
criterion of its antiquity, we would
still be obliged to consider it one of
the most ancient of arts.
One can, I admit, find some rare
communities where personal adorn¬
ment seems to be so little valued
that the body is left completely un¬
derrated and, where the climate
permits, even naked. But it is always
astonishing to encounter such a
complete lack of interest in. personal
embellishment, for among all kinds
and conditions of men and women it
is as prevalent as we can expect any
custom to be. Arid this suggests that
it satisfies some deep-seated psycho¬
logical need, a need so spontaneous
and strong that in the few religious
sects where it is vigorously . disap¬
proved, stringent rules must be en¬
forced to suppress it. Most cultures,
however, recognize that adorning the
14
body is a natural form of behaviour
and accommodate it within their
social patterns.
Some scholars, speculating about
the origin of personal embellishment,
have given it a sexual basis. While
the use of such decoration for sexual
attraction can scarcely be gainsaid, it
appears in so many contexts where
sexual attraction is not the dominant
factor that a broader interpretation is
called for. Perhaps there are clues
for one in the behaviour of little
children who pleased by the pattern
or colour of an object will seize and
treasure it.
Sometimes they attach these pleas¬
ing bits to themselves merely for the
pleasure it gives them. And their
joy is increased if they become, as a
result, a focus of attention. "Look
at me" they cry, as they exhibit their
new found decoration, not yet having
learnt to . conceal their desire for
approbation or to adopt subtler
methods of achieving it. The child
is thereby distinguished, becoming an
object of envy and approval. As a
psychologist might put it, personal
ornamentation provides ego-enchant
ment. This aspect is especially noti¬
ceable when children deliberately put
on even strange or unusual, not
necessarily pleasing, objects in order
to evoke attention from their mates.
The purpose obviously is to draw
admiring or favorable attention, not
ridicule or disdain.
As a general thing, we all like to be
noticed and admired. Some of us
can achieve such a desirable condi¬
tion by one means or another: by
words, by special skills, by physical
prowess, or by beauty, but nothing
is so universally available or so
widely used as the adornment of the
body. For our bodies, particularly
our heads and faces, are what the
world sees of us and on what, for
better or worse, first and often
enduring impressions are based.
What depths of meaning and judg¬
ment are embodied in the countless
phrases that sum up such impressions.
Thus art steps in to improve on
nature. And even objects of utility,
like clothing or spectacles, become
media for the decoration that we
hope will win approval for ourselves.
Decoration however, need not be
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July 19S8
IMPROVING ON NATURE
Few forms of behaviour are more common than
the urge to improve on nature by adorning the
bodyparticularly from the neck up. Bodily
decoration has taken an amazing number of forms:
body and face painting, ornaments, headdress and
vast arrays of jewellery, flowers, hats, clothing and
shoes. Contrasts in facial decoration depict (from
left to right) Tsimshiam Indian with green face
paint and copper appliqué ornaments representing
the raven ; Charoti Indian, South America ; Arunta
man of Australia with face covered by feathers and
blood for a ceremonial ritual ; Modern Theatrical
make-up, by Del Russo of Prince Matchabelli ; Mask¬
like effect of face paint which is used by tribes¬
men in New Guinea on ceremonial occasions.
ALL PHOTOGRAPHS PAGES 1 4 TO 19,© AMERICAN
MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY, NEW YORK
only in terms of beauty. And we
may seek approval by other routes
than aesthetic adornment. The body
can also be the shield on which we
display symbols of various kinds
whether they are beautiful or not
may be beside the point. If they
mark their bearers as persons
of distinction, that is enough.
Thus we wear status symbols like
jewels, honour decorations, or organi¬
zational badges because in our society
their possessors are admired by those
whose admiration is sought and the
wearing of them accomplishes that
purpose.
Women who frequently declare
they dress for other women are often
right. The cherished elegance of
detail that is lost on most men
carries a special meaning to women,
so that only women can fully
appreciate the artistry of another
woman's attire and envy or admire
her for it. Thus the sources for the
custom of decorating ourselves range
from aesthetic pleasure to status
symbols, but the positive purpose is
to attract favourable notice. In cer¬
tain age groups and under certain
circumstances, the notice most desired
may be strongly affected by sex, but
this does not mean that the practice
of personal adornment either origi¬
nates in sex or is primarily devoted
to its service.
There is also a negative aspect to
all this. Standards of adornment
become so fixed in many societies
that a failure to con¬
form tends to draw un¬
favourable notice or
ridicule.
It takes a very strong-
Cont'd
on
next page
DOG'S TEETH in a bristling circlet, surmounted by a basketry cap adorned with feathers and
bone hairpins worn by principal wife of Mayogo chief, northern Ituri District, Equatorial Africa.
IS
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
FROM THE
NECK UP
(Continued)
We are all slaves of fashion
minded woman to appear in plain day
clothes at a formal evening party
and to face the mingled pity, shock,
amusement or disdain she would
expect to encounter. And not so long
ago very few men of substantial posi¬
tion would have ventured into public
view without a cravat neatly tied
under the collar. There surely\ were
some women in pre-War Japan who
would gladly have given up the beauti¬
ful, but uncomfortable, obi or would
have welcomed a release from the
tedium of their elaborate coiffures if
the consequences in social disapproval
were not too great to outweigh the
personal relief they might have
attained.
Slave of fashion is more than a
mere phrase. Not only do we adorn
ourselves because our cultural con¬
ventions require it, but we do so in
strictly regulated ways that are
characteristic of our culture. An
extended lip surrounding a large disc
would obviously be rejected by all but
Ubangl women to whom, on the
contrary, its absence would be
embarrassing. Such a mutilation
would have appeared as a disgusting
disfigurement to European women
of 1900 or to contemporary Mandarin
women; yet the former were willing
to distort their hips to the point of
caricature and the latter were proud
to hobble on feet folded and bound
to keep them small.
If it takes a certain kind of courage
to abstain from any of the con¬
ventional adornments of one's own
society, it takes an equal amount of
perhaps another kind to adopt those
of another culture. Some borrowing
is permitted if there is already a
certain degree of acculturation in
style. For example, the Indian sari
and the diamond stud in the nostril
are acceptable and even chic in some
circles of Western society. But on
the whole, style or fashion in adorn¬
ment is generally fairly rigid and too
great a deviation is not likely to be
acceptable.
Rather be dead than demode
But fashions and styles change.
They do so in most areas, with
the notable exception of the
West, without conscious planning.
Nevertheless the "drift" or evolution
of style seems to some students to
follow certain regularities. Even in
16
Western countries where styles in
clothing and ornament have become a
business and are artificially developed,
Kroeber claims that predictable cycles
exist. Other students have gone
farther and have linked styles in
clothing with broad cultural trends.
One of the strangest aspects of
fashion is its capricious tyranny.
What is most desirable and sought
after, today may be completely
démodé tomorrow. It is not only the
lady of fashion who would rather be
dead than to be seen in last year's
hat, but her sisters and brothers
everywhere who share this distaste
for a recently abandoned style.
Nothing seems more comic.
There are only two ways of altering
the body to improve on nature: one
is permanent, the other temporary.
Each has its own advantages and
TATTOOED DESIGNS that covered men
of the Marquesas Islands entranced early
voyagers In the Pacific. Above, drawing of a
young Nukahivan from the Marquesas, covered
almost from head to foot with tattoo designs.
drawbacks. Under the former, we
may list tattooing, scarification, head
deformation, piercing and enlarge¬
ment of lips, nose and ear lobes, foot
binding, tooth evulsion or filing, the
amputation of fingers, and various
deformations and mutilations of the
sex organs.
. Designs and modifications of this
kind need no refurbishing. The
elegant tattooed designs that covered
the Marquesan males from head to
toe in delicate patterns that entranc¬
ed the early voyagers would have
been far too laborious, if they were
impermanent, to apply for anything
but rare and special occasions. To
achieve these remarkable effects,
however, the Marquesans had to
endure a long series of painful
sessions with the tattooing comb.
And once committed to a particular
pattern, there was no provision for
a change. Similarly, the bound foot
of the upper class Chinese lady, or
the flattened head of a Northwest
Coast Indian, became unchangeable
features of the anatomy. Such modi¬
fications of the anatomy were a
long, often painful, process that
began in infancy and required res¬
tricting bandages.
Wearing a small fortune
Although the temporary forms of
decoration involve constant
upkeep and attention, they
leave room for change. This type of
embellishment covers an enormous
range of styles and material: body and
face . painting, ornaments, headdress,
a vast array of jewellery, flowers, hats,
clothing, and shoes. Although some
ot these items, like flowers, are ephe¬
meral and may be had with little
effort, others represent great wealth
and a considerable investment of
capital. The jewels worn by Oriental,
as well as European, women often
amount to a fortune. Perhaps most
tedious are the elaborate coiffures
and make-ups. Japanese women
used to devote much time to their
hair-do's, and the enamel-like make¬
up of the ladies of the Chinese courts
must have consumed hours. Even in
simpler cultures, great pains may be
taken to produce such elegant
patterns as the hair dressing of many
African cultures.
Frequently the styles of adornment
and even the materials used were
regulated by class distinctions or were
used as insignia of status and posi¬
tion. In this category we find the
tribal scarifications of Africa and,
perhaps, the caste mark in India.
The illustrations shown here repre¬
sent only a small fraction of the
range of material and manner that
people have adopted to embellish
themselves. But they demonstrate
how ingenious are the means em¬
ployed and how few the opportunities
overlooked. They also remind us
that man is the only animal that
tries to improve on what nature has
provided.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July 1958
FURS AND FEATHERS FOR The ingenuity and fancy shown by both women and men in their hairdress and headgearare depicted in thesestyles
HATS AND HAIRDRESSES. from North America and Central Asia. (I) Fur and silk hat from Mongolia. (2) Iroquois (New York State) man
wearing dyed deer hair roached headdress, face paint, silver, crescent-shaped earrings and bear-claw necklace. Type of headdress worn 300 years ago by
Indians of New York State and New England. (3) Woman's red silk hat from Tibet. (4) Hopi Indian (Arizona, U.S.A.) headdress worn by unmarried girls.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July 1958
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
THE ROOTS OF PREJUDICE
Racism, or the 'superiority complex'
by Arnold M. Rose
(2)
In this issue we continue the serialization begun last month of "The Roots of Prejudice,"
by Arnold Rose, Professor of Sociology at the University of Minnesota, U.S.A.,
published by Unesco in its series "The Raqe Question in Modern Science". (See
bibliography page 35). In this article, Professor Rose discusses ignorance of other
peoples and the "superiority complex" as causes of racial prejudice and shows how
prejudice harms those who indulge in it as much as those against whom it is directed;
Prejudice is nearly always accompanied by incorrect or
ill-informed opinions regarding the people against
whom it is felt. Many of the false beliefs take the
form of what social scientists call "'stereotypes'". These
are exaggerations of certain physical traits or cultural
characteristics which are found among members of the
minority group and are then attributed to all members of
the group. When stereotypes exist, an individual is
judged, not on the basis of his own characteristics, but on
the basis of exaggerated and distorted beliefs regarding
what are thought to be the characteristics of his group.
All members of the group are falsely assumed to be alike,
exceptions being ignored or their existence denied.
Stereotypes take strange forms. They are usually un¬
favourable to the subordinated group, but not always.
Stereotypes about Negroes in South Africa and the United
States, for example, depict them as brutal, stupid, and
immoral, but also as happy, generous and faithful. This
pattern makes sense in terms of the effort to use Negroes
as servants and unskilled workers, because the "good"
traits seem to justify their treatment as childlike subor¬
dinates and to indicate their satisfaction with this treat¬
ment.
A stereotype applied to one group of people at one time
may be applied to another group at a later time. In
England during the seventeenth century the Scottish Low-
landers were stereotyped as coarse, cruel and animal¬
like people. By the nineteenth century, this stereotype
was applied no longer to the Scots, but to the Irish.
Stereotypes can change very rapidly: in Western countries
before 1940, the Japanese were thought of as sly but weak,
rigid and unimaginative. After the outbreak of war with
Japan in 1941 the stereotype of the Japanese still included
slyness, but shifted to include toughness and resource¬
fulness as well. After the victory over Japan in 1945, and
the beginning of a successful occupation, the stereotype
dropped slyness and substituted gullibility.
A stereotype applied to a group of people in one country
may not be applied to that group in another country, but
rather to another minority group. The stereotype about
Jews in Central Europe includes a belief in their strong
sexuality and tendency towards sexual perversion. This
is not the case in the United States, where, although there
are other stereotypes regarding Jews, the sexual stereo¬
type is applied rather to Negroes, especially in the
Southern States.
The ' ignorance which supports prejudice has a great
range. It may take the form of false information about
people's physical characteristics, cultural practices, or
beliefs. It may take the form of myths about superhuman
powers or childlike weaknesses. The prejudice of Germans
about other peoples included sterotypes about the French
as immoral degenerates, about the British as bumbling
fools, about the Americans as narrow-minded wastrels,
about the Russians as stolid and stupid ignoramuses, about
the Jews as scheming perverts. This is just an illustra¬
tion of the astounding range of ignorance that can occur
in one modern country.
20
Stereotypes and other incorrect beliefs about groups of
people are not necessarily least frequent when there are
many members of the minority group about, who, through
their appearance and behaviour, disprove the false beliefs.
The strongest prejudice and the largest number of false
beliefs about Negroes are to be found among the whites
of South Africa, who live among a black population which
outnumbers them by four or five to one. There are many
more stereotypes about Negroes in the Southern States
of the United States than in the Northern States, although
Negroes form a much higher proportion of the population
in the former than in the latter area.
But no generalization can be made in the opposite sense
either: areas with a small minority group are not necessar¬
ily freer of stereotypes about their members than are
areas where they exist in large numbers. In Germany after
World War I there were proportionately few Jews living
in Bavaria. Yet there were apparently many more false
beliefs about Jews in Bavaria than in cosmopolitan Berlin,
where there were more Jews. Until a few decades ago
there were more false beliefs about American Indians in
North America, where they were few in number, than in
South America, where they are much more numerous.
These and similar facts disprove the Widely held opinion
that prejudice is strongest where minority races are
largest.
One of the requirements for ignorance about a group of
people is social isolation, which can occur even where
there is considerable contact. People can live next door
to each other as neighbours, one person can even work in
another's home or shop, but still they will not necessarily
get to know each other as human beings. Both physical
and social segregation usually accompany prejudice: they
are among its effects, but also among its causes, as they
promote ignorance and ignorance bolsters prejudice.
Ignorance opens the way
for racist propaganda
Ignorance among the mass of people enables the propa¬
gandist for economic exploitation or political domina¬
tion to gain his ends more easily. II one group of
people knows nothing about another group or has false
beliefs about it, it is susceptible to the camouflaged
demands of the exploiters. People can even be misled as
to who their real enemy is by a propagandist who plays
on their ignorance.
It is apparent from this brief discussion (a) that igno¬
rance takes the form either of absence of knowledge or
of false belief; (b) that ignorance itself is not so much a
direct cause of prejudice as it is a pre-condition or bolster
of prejudice. In the latter capacity, ignorance is a more
important factor in prejudice against some groups than
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July 1958
it is against other groups. Where it is a significant factor,
information which fills gaps in knowledge or contradicts
false beliefs can be a valuable weapon against prejudice.
Not only does such information weaken directly one of
the supports of prejudice/but it partially nullifies the pro¬
pagandist's attempts at exploitation.
The problems of intergroup relations may be classified
according to three types. One kind is political in motive.
This intergroup tension is based on a struggle for power.
Such rivalries have been frequent in international rela¬
tions, and a modern example of them may be found in
the long-standing hatred between France and Germany.
Sometimes one country may contain two groups struggling
against each other for political power. Much of the vio¬
lence, discrimination, and prejudice that has divided the
Serbs and Croats in Yugoslavia was of this nature.
A second class of intergroup tensions arises from
differences of religious belief. The history of the West
was marked for many centuries by violence between
Christians and Muslims and later between Catholics and
Protestants. Part of the modern conflict between
Fascism , Communism, and democracy is caused by a
difference in belief, although most of it is based on a
struggle for political power. Belief differences between
groups frequently involve the notion that nonbelievers are
agents or advocates of sin, heresy, corruption, or some
other. form of evil. To persecute them is to do justice or
perform a service for the Lord.
Grading men like animals
into higher or lower races
Belief differences are especially associated with preju¬
dice when one group has. a strongly developed con¬
viction that its own beliefs are superior to all others.
Such an ideology has been more strongly developed in
connexion with the Jewish, Christian, Muslim, and Shin-
toist religions than with the Hindu, Buddhist, Confu-
cianist, and most- forms of pagan religion. It is perhaps
for this reason that prejudice is more frequently found
where followers of one of the former religions are domi¬
nant. This- is true even though some of these religions
consider unfairness and violence to be abhorrent.
Whereas intergroup tensions based on the struggle for
power or on differences- of belief have existed since the
beginning of recorded history, the third type racism
seems to ' be largely a modern phenomenon. It was at
least rare until its modern development less than two
centuries ago as a perversion of early biological science,
and it still has not spread much into cultures other than
those of the West. .
That there were physical differences among people had
always been obvious, of course. Some individuals of
ancient and medieval times regarded individuals with
different physical features as obnoxious (although others
considered such physical differences to be especially
interesting or desirable). Yet all men, whatever their
physical traits, were regarded as human beings (or at
worst fallen angels), quite different from the creatures
called animals.
When the natural historians of the eighteenth and
early nineteenth centuries were classifying and describing
species, they introduced the notion that men were to be
classified into five races, which could be graded like
species of animals, into higher and lower. Scientific
biologists soon corrected this early error by showing that
mankind was of one origin and that racial differences
were later developments, so that no one race could be
ranked higher than any other. Nevertheless, the concept
of races was seized upon and elaborated into a whole
new basis for intergroup antagonism which is now called
racism.
Racism is a set of popular beliefs which includes the
following elements:
1. The differences between groups differences in body
and in mind are all due to hereditary biology, and
nothing can change them. According to this theory,
for example, if Negroes are, on the average, not as
intelligent as whites, this is due to their heredity and
can no more be changed than their skin colour.
2. A second part of this theory is that habits, attitudes,
beliefs, behaviour and all the things we learn are
determined for us before we are born. For example
according to this popular theory, Jews are born to be
sharp businessmen and Japanese are born to act in an
insincere manner.
3. All differences between a minority group and the
majority group are thought to be signs of inferiority.
For example, according to this popular theory, Jewish
religion, Catholic religion, and the Negro's expression
of religion are all inferior to the white Protestant's
religion.
4. If there should be biological crossing of the groups, the
children will be more degenerate than either of the
parent groups. Civilization including family life,
religion and morals will disappear and men will
become savage animals.- The details of what would
happen if there were "intermarriage" are usually left
to the imagination, and. just the ugly word
" mongrelization" is used to suggest the results.
Because of this, everything must be done to prevent
the two groups from having easy social relations with
each other. For example, if parents allowed a Jewish
boy to. "'date" a Gentile girl, the two might want to
get married, and the children of such a marriage
. would be "lost" according to this theory. Another
example: if Negroes were allowed to eat in the same
restaurants as whites, they might become so bold as to
ask whites for their daughters' hands in marriage
according to the racist theory.
These racist beliefs have become so widespread, so
unconscious, and so traditional among many peoples of
the West that racism may be regarded as an independent
cause of prejudice today. Some social scientists consider
it to be the only really important kind of prejudice
between peoples, and they use the term "'race prejudice"
to refer to all the things we are considering in this
study. Where racist beliefs occur they apply as much
to religious groups, national groups, or groups of other
types as to the strictly racial groups defined by anthro¬
pologists.
To understand better how racism has become a root of
modern prejudice, it is important to examine its history
in several countries. One of the first countries in which
it developed was the United States. At the beginning of
the nineteenth century Negro slavery was well established
in the United States. Little attempt was made to justify
it, however, except on the grounds of economic conve¬
nience and the fact that it had existed for a long time.
Many people, including large slaveholders, were in favour
of abolishing it as incompatible with the growth of
democracy. Prejudice was not particularly associated
slavery, since white people accepted freed slaves on
their own merits and since many wealthy white people
allowed their slaves to go free. Certainly there was no
prejudice against Negroes on any of the racial grounds
we have just examined.
Unpleasant jobs to be done
were good enough for slaves
About that time a great new profit was discovered in
slaves: the invention of the cotton gin and of a
process for extracting sugar from cane, coupled with
new facilities for international trade, made the Southern
States a region of great potential wealth. This required
cheap labour that could be held to the unpleasant task of
growing and picking cotton and sugar cane. Not enough
free people would do this work; not even immigrants from
Europe, brought over especially for the task. So, many
more Negro slaves were brought in (although this was
now illegal); the area of cotton growing was greatly
extended; many people grew wealthy rapidly; and the
South maintained a precarious dominance of power in
the nation as a whole because of its wealth.
During this period pressures were exerted
to abolish slavery: other countries were
abolishing slavery, it was, now considered
to be immoral and barbarous; and some of
the poor whites of the South did not like
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
ASIAN CLUB
An East-West Forum
on Britain's TV
by Henry Cassirer
The sarongs and sonjkohs worn
by the young men from Singa¬
pore, the longyis draping the
girls from Burma with gay flowers in
their hair and the brilliantly coloured
saris of the Indian women gave the
London TV studio of the B.B.C. an
unaccustomed and exotic air. Sud¬
denly a voice called for silence and,
as the hands of the studio clocks
reached the half hour, technicians
threw their switches and some fifteen
million people throughout Britain
joined "Asian Club."
Asian Club is a half-hour pro¬
gramme which, on sound and televi¬
sion services of the British Broad¬
casting Corporation, has given the
of East ..and West a new
medium for- understanding one an¬
other. It began as a weekly discussion
programme broadcast in the B.B.C. 's
Photos © B.B.C.
NATIONAL COSTUMES worn by most of the members of "Asian Club" make an exotic and
colourful spectacle in London TV studio. A cross-section of Asians in London, the studio audience
confronts and puts impromptu questions to distinguished British guest speakers. (I) Chairman
of programme, Mrs. Anil de Silva, of Ceylon, with guest speaker, Professor A.L. Goodhart, Master
of University College, Oxford. Standing behind them are participants from Ceylon, Korea, India
and Nepal (from left to right). (2) Under chairmanship of Kushwant Singh, Indian author, Miss
Margaret Godden, Matron of London's Hammersmith Hospital, speaks on the work and status of
nurses. (3) Miss Ter-Rao Chang, from Peking, uses microphone to put a question to Miss Godden.
22
"London Calling Asia" radio services.
As a programme involving Asian
listener participation by means of an
Asian audience gathered together in
a B.B.C. studio it proved so fascinating
from a visual viewpoint that a year
after the club was inaugurated it was
decided to televise one of the sessions.
The success of the experiment
startled even the most optimistic of
its sponsors. The British viewing
public, keenly interested in the affairs
of the East, were delighted at this
opportunity .for a more intimate
acquaintance with the many peoples
of Asia. The press was enthusiastic:
"the lid off an oriental jewel box",
said one paper. And ' as . this first
broadcast took place just before
Christmas 1952, hundreds of people
wrote in offering hospitality to Asian
participants for Christmas.
Asian Club is simply a gathering of
Asians in England, from the many
thousands of Asian students, teachers
and visitors to London who, often
dressed in their national costumes,
meet together in the TV studio to
discuss varied topics, including con¬
troversial ones, in science, religion,
philosophy, the arts and many other
fields. It has proved so convincing
that many people believe it to be a
real club and the B.B.C. is kept busy
explaining that this is a radio and TV
programme with no premises or other
activities.
At first the programme had no
chairman and then ran with a
British chairman. But it was soon
realized that an Asian formed the
best bridge between the speaker and
the audience. Thus, under the
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July 1958
guidance of an Asian chairman, a
long line of distinguished British
guest-speakers philosophers, scien¬
tists, explorers, churchmen, social
workers, musicians and many more
have since discussed subjects" raised
by the Asian Club guests during the
half hour.
The distinguished English jurist
and educator, Sir Ivor Jennings, for
instance; spoke on "The Effect of
English Education in Asia;" Miss
G.M. Godden, Matron of Hammer¬
smith Hospital in London, answered
questions on the status and work of
nurses; an explorer, Colonel Van der
Post, delighted his audience with
anecdotes about African courting
customs ; and there have been other
provocative programmes on such
subjects as "The Mystery of Clothes"
and "Family Relations."'
Recently, a different form of the
programme was tried out without a
European guest. Only Asian speakers
engaged in a discussion organized on
the lines of famous debating societies
such as the Oxford Union. The first
programme of this type, given on
May 28, 1958, took up the motion:
"In the opinion of this House, any
benefits of British rule to Asia were
more by accident than design." The
motion was proposed by Mrs. Nandini
Iyer, of India, and was supported by
Peter Williams, a Tamil from Singa¬
pore, former Secretary of the Singa¬
pore Labour Party and now a law
student in London. Opposing the
motion were Mr. Kemal Faruki, of
Pakistan, also a law student and
Mr. Ved Mehta, a blind student of
history. During this particular pro
gramme presided over by Mr. Ragha-
van Iyer, the husband of Mrs. Iyer,
speakers from Japan, Burma, Malaya
and other Asian countries took part
in the discussion from the floor.
The impact of the programme
comes not merely from what is being
said, but also from the personalities
of those taking part. As the B.B.C.
Audience Research Department has
put it: "Viewers feel that the Asian
Club is a refreshing and educational
programme which helps them to
understand the outlooks of other
nations. They always feel, too, that
the company assembled makes a
fascinating and decorative picture.
Indeed, to see the audience seems to
be one of . the most interesting
features of the programme."
' I saw you on TV
the other evening '
The real importance of the pro¬
gramme lies in the impression
it makes on ordinary viewers.
Here are some of their reactions:
"This programme brings the Asians
into our lives and makes one think
of the problem more deeply than by
mere reading." an Accountant.
"'This type of programme should,
in my opinion, be seen more often as
by so doing it will help people to
overcome the colour bar which is
largely due to ignorance in this
country." a Housewife.
"A really good out-of-the-ordinary
discussion. We really enjoy the
different viewpoints and sympathize
with the questioners and we learn
plenty about ourselves! We like the
friendly atmosphere too." a Master
Baker.
To ensure this friendly, informal
and relaxed atmosphere, and to
present a spontaneous and unscripted
programme with the necessary im¬
pression of ease and naturalness,
with a cast of some 40 people, calls
for plenty of hard work behind the
scenes.
But the producers say their reward
comes from letters Which viewers
send them; from the high Apprecia¬
tion Indexes that are reported; from
the people in Britain who greet
Asians in the street all over the
country by saying "T saw your club
on TV the other evening", and who
then settle down to continue an
argument with them on whatever
the subject of the meeting happened
to be; and finally from the people
of Asia who write to give their views
and say they have heard their friends
or relations on the radio programme
and that they themselves will pay a
visit to Asian Club when next they
are in London.
The B.B.C. programme is one
example of the way in which tele¬
vision stations can utilize the pre¬
sence of people from other lands in
their country to produce a pro¬
gramme series of wide popularity
which promotes better comprehen¬
sion among nations. In the spirit of
its Major Project on mutual appre¬
ciation between Orient and Occident,
Unesco would welcome the production
of similar programmes by other tele¬
vision stations throughout the world.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
ONE PERSON OUT
OF 44 IS A TWIN
by David Gunston
ODILE AND GENEVIEVE, daughters of a French art critic, are iden¬
tical twins. As a result only their parents and a few close friends
are able to distinguish between them. Their tastes, interests and acti¬
vities are also identical. As students at the School of Decorative,Arts
in Paris they achieved an equal measure of success. Later they took up
theatrical careers and have since appeared in several Paris productions.
Photos © Paul Almasy
Are you a married woman between
35 and 39 with a family of
eight? If so, then you are the
most likely mother in the world to
have twins! The next most likely
mother of twins is the woman bet¬
ween 35 and 39 who already has seven
children, then the woman of the
same age who has six children, and
so on. The woman between 30 and
35 who has eight children comes next,
then those of that age with seven, six,
five children, and so on. If you are
outside the 30-39 age group, or have
more than eight single children al¬
ready, then your chances of having
twins decrease considerably.
These facts emerge from a recent
close study of some 3,000 twin cases
and birth statistics over the past ten
years. The findings apply only to
fraternal, or dissimilar twins, how¬
ever. Identical twins occur about
once in every three sets of twins, and
most mothers have a roughly equal
chance of having them at any child-
bearing age.
It has long been known that the
ratio of the occurrence of twins to
single children is the same as the
ratio of triplets to twins. Quadruplets,
in turn, appear in the same ratio to
triplets as triplets to twins, and so on.
At the end of the last century, the
French genetecist, Hellin, discovered
the proportion of these ratios, and
the biological law now known as
"Hellin's laW" summarizes his find¬
ings. Twins of either kind, fraternal
or identical, occur about once in every
87 normal births. Triplets arrive
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July 1958
about once every 87 x 87 births,
quadruplets once every 87 x 87 X 87,
and so on. Hellin's useful calculations
are proved to be approximately cor¬
rect from a wide range of birth regis¬
tration statistics, although there are
some variations in the frequency of
twins among races and countries.
American Negroes seem to have the
highest twin-birth rate of any civili¬
zed racial group, and the . Japanese
the lowest, at only 35 pairs of twins,
on average, to every 10,000 single
births. In the United States twins
are born once in every 86 to 88 deli¬
veries, and one out of every 44 Ame¬
ricans is a twin. In very hot coun¬
tries the twin rate tends to be lower
than the average, and in colder
northern lands the number of twins
becomes greater the further north,
with peoples like the Eskimoes and
the Lapps, the higher the percentage.
This would seem to be nature's way
of safeguarding the populations of
the arctic regions, where conditions
of survival are less favourable than
elsewhere. *
There are normally two ways in
which twins may be born, and they
represent the two distinct types of
twins universally recognized. If two
separately-produced eggs are fertili¬
zed together, they may develop side
by side in the mother's incredibly
elastic womb and be born as two or¬
dinary children. This is the common¬
est kind of twinning, when fraternal
twins result. Identical twins, on the
other hand, are the result of a single
egg dividing, or being split, into two
embryos after fertilization.
It is not known just how often this
strange division occurs, since we only
become aware that it has happened
when the surviving embryos are born
together as twins. It may be the
case that such a division takes place
more often than is supposed, and
that the stronger of the twins sup¬
presses the life in its fellow-embryo,
which eventually vanishes, absorbed
by the blood-stream. We know that
this phenomenon does occur, as occa¬
sionally the suppressed twin is not
absorbed but is found on delivery of
the live child, a strange, paper-thin
mummy.
Nature's tragic freaks
When this splitting is incomplete,
which happens perhaps once
in ten million births, the two
babies are born as Siamese twins
joined together at the trunk. Of
these fewer than one set in five sur¬
vive, and even today fewer still can
be surgically separated and live.
Occasionally, too, twins are produced
as a result of incomplete splitting of
the egg that have large parts of their
bodies unseparated sometimes with
two heads on a single trunk, or one
trunk having four arms and legs.
These unhappy freaks rarely survive
birth or a few days, and are nowa¬
days so rare as not to cause any
expectant mothers anxiety.
As is well known, twins are not
always born very close together.
There are many instances of one or
two whole days separating the birth
of twins, and several (most excep¬
tional) cases of as much as a month
intervening. The longest proved
time-lapse between the arrival of
twins was that of a Bengali woman
in India some years ago, whose babies
were born 45 days apart.
Fraternal twins can usually be told
at a glance from the always uncan¬
nily similar identical twins. Two-egg
twins are invariably two completely
independent individuals whose only
common endowment is that they had
the same mother and developed at
the same time in her womb. They
may be, and frequently are, of diffe¬
rent sexes, and as we have just seen,
their birthdays may not be on the
same days. Theoretically, too, they
could have different fathers.
Much research is still going on into
the question of fraternal twinning,
but there now seems to be no doubt
that the tendency towards it is di¬
rectly inherited solely through wom¬
en, and never through men. It is,
after all, a wholly feminine pheno¬
menon. A woman who is herself a
fraternal twin is much more likely
to have fraternal twin babies than
other mothers who are not twins.
But a man who is such a twin is no
more likely to father such a pair than
any other man.
Many women have
had three sets of fra¬
ternal twins, and not
long ago an Italian mo¬
ther gave birth to her
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
TWINS
(Continued)
STRANGE KINSHIP OF 'PEOPLE IN DUPLICATE'
sixth set. Many years ago a Sicilian
woman made obstetric history by
producing 11 sets of fraternal twins
in the same number of years. In 1929
an American mother set up a record
of another kind by having two sets
of fraternal twins in that year. An¬
other woman, with no other children,
had two sets of these twins in fifteen
months, while an English mother has
had three sets in just over three years.
All these cases show that in some
women there is a marked predilection
for producing two-egg twins.
In contrast, one-egg twins are basi¬
cally different from the ordinary
brother-and-sister type fraternals.
They are really people in duplicate
duplicate creations of one and the
same person. It is on identical
twins that most of the fascination
and most of the age-old lore of this
subject is centred. A newly-fertilized
egg, or an embryo not more than a
few days old, splits itself into two
halves, and these halves then re-form
themselves as complete, if closely-re¬
lated, persons. Identical twins must
therefore be of the same sex, and
although they may not invariably
look alike at birth, they always
develop along parallel lines and are
usually so alike that strangers and
sometimes even their own friends,
find difficulty in telling them apart.
At this point we arrive at the one
sure test for distinguishing from out¬
side the two types of twins. Identical
twins can exchange roles or places
without others being aware of it,
whereas fraternal twins can never
boast sufficient similarity to do this.
Therefore, when Shakespeare in
Twelfth Night made Viola masque¬
rade as her twin brother Sebastian,
he erred, for identicals are invariably
of the same sex. The strange kinship
that keeps them together does not
usually weaken as they grow older.
She talked to a mirror
Sir Francis Galton, the famous
heredity expert, who founded
the modern science of eugenics,
and who made a lifelong study of
twins, confirmed that it is not
uncommon to find sets of identical
twins practically impossible to tell
apart. But it is not often that
the twins themselves get confused.
Yet Galton cited an instance where
a girl identical twin had actually
spoken to her own reflection in a
mirror, thinking she was address¬
ing her twin sister! No matter how
closely allied identical twins may be,
physically and mentally, they possess
different finger-prints and, in most
cases, easily distinguishable hand¬
writing. Galton found only one pair
of twins among 85 whose case-his¬
tories he studied in detail who
themselves could not tell their hand¬
writing apart.
The remarkable affinity between
identical twins has been proved time
and again. One of the most interest¬
ing cases was that of a pair of iden
tical boy twins in America who were
adopted as very young babies by two
different, unconnected families. At
the age of eight, one of the foster
families moved from the town where
both boys had been living so that
they were then separated by over
1,000 miles. They did not in fact see
each other again until they had
reached their early twenties. Yet the
following characteristics were then
found to be the same in each case;
they had both married girls of a very
similar type of the same age; they
had both become electricians and
were actually working for different
branches of the same large firm; and,
coincidence or not, they both had pet
terriers with the same name !
Identical twins often contract the
same illnesses at the same time, even
when separated, and sometimes their
teeth decay at the same time. A
Paris doctor, Dr. J. Moreau, tells of an
extreme case of male twins who
although not living .together were
both certified for monomania at the
same time. They both had the same
persecution mania, the same hallu¬
cinations and other symptoms,
although they never communicated
during this time.
This affinity rarely lessens
throughout life, even in old age. One
of the many facts that emerged from
Dr. F.J. Kallman's study of over 1,000
New York identical twins aged 60 or
more was that even when the pairs
had lived most of their lives under
totally different circumstances and
surroundings, they continued to be
closely alike in the physical and psy¬
chological changes that accompanied
their growing old. Some, indeed,
tended to become even more alike in
old age, which showed that some
genetical similarities between twins
do not manifest themselves until ad¬
vanced years are reached.
Whilst there may be minor psycho¬
logical differences and dissimilar in¬
terests between identical twins, they
invariably tally in their outstanding
personality characteristics. Thus a
neurotic, an artistic, or a mentally
immature identical twin (will be
found to have a partner with similar
traits of character and make-up.
Observations On twins seem to bear
out the suggestion that our psycholo¬
gical make-up is in many important
respects geneticaly determined.
Chang, Eng & Barnum
The type of twins who are,
literally, closest together are
those luckily rare unfortunates,
Siamese twins, whose horrible fate
seems to catch popular fancy most.
The name was originally given to
the male twins born of a Chinese
mother in Siam in 1811, Chang
and Eng. They Were joined, a
little obliquely, by a thick fleshy
band extending between their breast¬
bones and their hip. Their mother
sold them as freaks to a showman,
who exhibited them in Europe.
They eventually passed into the
hands of Phineas T. Barnum, and
travelled in his shows for many years.
They settled down in North Carolina,
married two sisters, and between
them had 22 children, all normal,
save that two were deaf and dumb.
They lost their property in the Civil
War, and died in 1874. One died
from the effects of drink, and the
other expired, apparently from shock,
2 i hours later. When they were about
to be exhibited in France, the autho¬
rities refused, believing that any
expectant mothers Who saw them
might have similar babies!
A later pair of female Siamese
twins, the English Hilton sisters, were
refused permission by the authorities
to marry when they wanted to. But
neither of these pairs were the first
twins to be so joined. There is plenty
of evidence to show that in the
Middle Ages, in the tiny village of
Biddenden, Kent, England, Eliza and
Mary Chulkhurst, were born joined
together at the hips. They lived
until their thirties, and did good
works about the place, leaving lands
and accruing income for an annual
gift of cakes to the poor, a ceremony
still observed.
Twins are not always regarded as
a blessing. Many primitive tribes
have never been able to understand
the phenomenon of multiple births.
In some communities a mother of
twins is branded as unfaithful and
the babies may be put to death, since
it is believed that the husband cannot
have fathered two children at the
same time. Other races refuse to let
the mother keep both her twin babies.
Australian aborigines still do this,
handing over the . other child to
another family.
Many and horrible are the strange
rites and practices connected with
twin births in unenlightened coun¬
tries, all bound up with the supersti¬
tion that twins are wrong, magical
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July 1958
INTERCHANGEABLE ACTRESSES, Odile and Geneviève study
their parts for a play in which both will appear. When one of the twins
replaces the other on the stage neither the audience nor the theatre
staff is any the wiser. Once, when Odile was ill, the producer asked
Geneviève to step into her sister's shoes for 12 days. The audience
Photos © Paul Almasy
never suspected there had been a replacement in the cast. When
Odile had recovered, the girls decided to go one better. One evening
they took it in turns to play the same roleOdile appeared in the first
and third acts and Geneviève in the second and fourth. Once again the
theatre audience was duped by the interchangeable actress twins.
and unlucky. In several East African
tribes various weird purification rites
have to be endured by every mother
of twins before she can be accepted
back as a respected and healthy
member of the tribe. There have
been cases where a mother has been
killed as a Witch for producing
duplicate babies. It is a happier
thought that impels some other races
to bury twins, when they die, where
two paths cross. On the other hand,
history is ifull of examples where
other, more intelligent peoples have
regarded twins with wonderment and
awe, admired especially * for their
great similarity. The mythology of
many races is rich in tales of won¬
derful, heroic and revered twins.
Some members of the medical pro¬
fession believe that the grafting of
quite new and separate bodily tissues,
such as the transfer of glands and
other organs from one person to
another, which so far has not met
with much success in the majority of
cases tried, would be a much simpler
matter with identical twins. How¬
ever, many experiments are needed
before this can be proved correct.
Mankind has always found a pecu¬
liar fascination in twins, particularly
identical twins, and indeed, the idea
of human beings in duplicate, as it
were, does stir the imagination. For
centuries this interest has operated
on two levels: the popular and the
scientific; and nowadays the two use¬
fully converge. Thus twin associa¬
tions help in medical investigations
by offering abundant material in all
age groups and walks of life. The
Soviet Government runs a Twins
Institute in Moscow for research into
the genetic and eugenic problems
raised by the incidence of twins, and
in the United States is a National
Twins Association, which holds an
annual rally of twins from all over
the country, awarding prizes for the
oldest and the youngest sets, the
most attractive and the most alike,
and so forth.
The study of twins indicates that
we owe more to heredity and the cir¬
cumstances of birth than to any ex¬
ternal conditions later in life. Whilst
we cannot, on any balanced view,
afford to neglect environment, here¬
dity holds the key to our earthly fates.
Another striking fact that is confirm¬
ed by every investigator is that twins
very rarely, if ever, achieve any great
eminence or distinction in life. This
is largely because, it is thought, the
presence of a twin brother or sister
makes each over-dependant upon the
other. A twin partner would there¬
fore seem to be rather a handicap to
great success in any sphere. Indivi¬
dual initiative tends to be lacking
among twins: by their very existence
they rely upon and support each other
too much for one to be personally
well above average.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
THE ROOTS OF
PREJUDICE
(Continued from page 21)
Boomerang victims
HOISTED WITH THEIR
OWN RACIST PETARDS
a system which gave all power to the wealthy slave owners.
In this setting, the concepts of racism served perfectly
as a justification. The Negroes were declared to be a
childlike race, which must be directed in work for its
own good and which must be kept inferior to the poor
whites for the good of civilization. Prejudice of the racist
variety took hold of the South and has remained there to
the present day.
In Western Europe during the first half of the
nineteenth contury, racism was a doctrine elaborated only
by a few writers. This does not mean that there was no
prejudice, but simply that prejudice was then religious
and cultural in character rather than racial. At first,
racism had little popular appeal, as democratic and
humanitarian ideology was generally dominant over the
older aristocratic ideology. By 1870, however, the aristo¬
crats, in a desperate search for tools and allies to support
their waning power, seized upon racism as a useful
propaganda device. In Germany two groups of poli¬
ticians discovered that by building up anti-Semitism, then
a weak remnant of an ancient religious antagonism, they
could also build their own political strength.
One of these groups was led by court chaplain Stoecker
and other "romantics", who wanted to create a new
kind of reactionary social order much like modern
Fascism. The other group Was led by Chancellor
Bismarck who was trying to maintain himself in office
against the opposition of the growing Liberal and
Socialist parties. The latter had Jewish leaders, and
anti-Semitism seemed a useful policy even though Bis¬
marck was not personally anti-Semitic. His successors in
the German Government continued to use anti-Semitism
until it became part of the popular tradition.
In Russia, the corrupt and inefficient Tsarist govern¬
ment also sought to gain political support by adopting
racism. In 1880 the Tsarist police began a programme
of propaganda against Jews Which was racist in tone, and
instigated the first of a series of pogroms against them.
The device did help to divert the peasants and some city
workers from their real troubles for a number of years,
but nevertheless the Tsarist government ultimately fell.
In France there was the famous Dreyfus case, in which
anti-Semitism was used as a political weapon.
Racism was thus a body of traditions some general,
some specific that became part of the popular culture
of some Western countries but not of others. Where it
was accepted, it influenced people to think in terms of
biological race superiority and to act in a violent and
prejudiced manner towards certain minority groups.
Wherever it has existed it has superseded, or at least
become interwoven with, all other bases of group
antagonism.
TEN EVILS OF PREJUDICE
Many people believe that the harmful effects of preju¬
dice are felt only by those against whom it is indulg¬
ed. There can be no doubt that restriction of job
opportunities, lack of access to facilities (both publicly and
privately owned) that are meant to serve the population
in- general, the presence of bias and antagonism in law
enforcement officials, and many other manifestations of
prejudice, are directly harmful to those people whom they
affect. But it is not so obvious that those Who feel the
prejudice, and who enforce the discriminations which are
its visible manifestations, are themselves victims of their
own attitude and behaviour. This misunderstanding
might itself be regarded as one contributory root of
prejudice, since few people would so strongly maintain a
kind of behaviour which they considered to be harmful
28
to themselves. It is therefore necessary for us first to
examine the ways in which prejudice is harmful to the
prejudiced.
Loss of manpower & productivity
mm In the first place, there is the direct economic waste
m^ entailed by failure to use the full productivity of
manpower and the fullest demands of the market. In
so far as people are kept unemployed because of
(prejudice, or are employed at lower tasks than they
are capable of handling, there is waste. Every
employer loses by not hiring the most efficient workers
available, and every consumer loses by having to pay
higher prices for his purchases.
The loss is most serious and most obvious during
periods of manpower shortage, but it can be demon¬
strated to exist at other times also. It usually takes
an indirect form, and thus is not readily apparent to
most persons. Also, as we have seen, some people
benefit directly from prejudice, and so are especially
' unlikely to notice the indirect loss.
While prejudice is just one among many sources of
loss, it is seen to be a significant one when We note its
connexion with low standards of living in several parts
of the world. In such regions, even if natural resources
are abundant and there is no overpopulation, prejudice
keeps productivity per person low. The Southern
States of the U.S.A. offer an obvious example of this.
Increases in sickness and crime
m% A second type of economic cost of prejudice is that
u^ which arises out of social problems Which are
aggravated. Much of this cost is borne by a govern¬
ment budget. Where prejudice creates social problems,
the government must control. or alleviate them. Even
a government run by the most prejudiced people finds
it imperative to' control communicable diseases and
epidemics, maintain a police and jail system, offer
some protection against accidents, and provide a
minimum of direct relief so that starvation will not.
be too obvious. The costs are frequently more direct.
The bad health of a group of people kept down by pre¬
judice creates an unhealthy environment for the pre--
judiced. The costs of crime are met not only by the
government but also by the criminals' victims.
Waste in time, talk & money
n A third group of costs is to be measured in terms of
time wasted before being translated into terms of
money. A casual inspection of the front pages of the
world's newspapers would indicate that the people of
countries where prejudice prevails spend much time in
discussions on how to treat minority groups. Only in
prejudiced countries are congresses and parliaments
frequently engaged in debate and legislation concern¬
ing minority groups. Many of the private organiza¬
tions ranging from businessmen's groups and unions
to sports groups and social clubs in these countries
find it necessary to take time to consider how and in
what degree to apply their prejudiced policies in
specific cases. In terms of the primary aims of these
congresses and organizations, such activity is a waste
of time. The group could turn its attention to matters
more directly connected with its own well-being, or
it could release its members sooner to pursue their own
interests.
Then, too, the existence of more laws and rules
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July 1958
creates more opportunities for litigation and for
contesting the rules. Give people a grievance and an
enormous amount of time will be spent in indulging
it. The prejudiced peoples of the world impose on
ithemselves a huge burden simply by obliging them¬
selves to decide how and to what extent in specific
cases they shall hold down the people against whom
they are prejudiced. This burden has to be measured
in terms of time and mental energy.
Undermines international goodwill
| A fourth cost of prejudice is seen most clearly in the
relation between nations today. Each nation is
anxious to gain the good will or respect of other
nations, whether its ultimate aim be peaceful accom¬
modation or domination. Diplomacy, international eco¬
nomic assistance, participation in world organizations,
and all other governmental activities directed towards
other nations, are aimed at acquiring prestige and
influence. These efforts on the part of some nations
are partially nullified by acts of prejudice within those
nations. Few people will regard with complacency
acts of violence and discrimination against members
pf their own race or nationality in another country.
And many other people wonder whether an ally is to
be trusted if it engages in acts of prejudice against
minority groups. While prejudice is only one factor
among many, a survey of international attitudes today
would show that there is no complete trust or respect
for nations in which prejudice prevails.
The diplomatic efforts and goodwill activities of
these nations cannot have their full influence. This
is especially true when the diplomats themselves
manifest prejudice against their allies.
Fully two-thirds of the people of the world today
are members of races towards whom much prejudice
has been shown. Some of these people have now
formed important nations, and others show signs of
developing in that direction. It is these peoples espe¬
cially which regard prejudice in other nations as part
of the foreign policy of those nations. Much of the
rational and expensive efforts in the diplomacy of the
latter nations is thus wasted by prejudice.
Builds barriers to knowledge
) Thus far we have been counting the measurable eco¬
nomic waste caused by prejudice. There are also psy¬
chological forms of waste that cannot be easily trans¬
lated into money, time or effort, although their effects
may be more devastating in the long run. Our fifth
damaging effect of prejudice on the prejudiced arises
from the fact that it creates barriers to communica¬
tion. A great deal of knowledge and culture is lost
to prejudiced people, because they will not meet and
talk with those who have this knowledge and culture.
There is little realization on the part of the preju¬
diced of how much they miss in this way, but the
lack of recognition does not alter the fact. As the
hitherto subordinated peoples have secured indepen¬
dence, they have turned particular attention to learn¬
ing and science. Though they have a great deal of
lag to make up, some of their developments in this
field are already approaching those of the hitherto
dominant peoples. Thus the barrier to communica¬
tion created by prejudice is having an ever-increasing
damaging effect on the prejudiced.
Useless outlet for frustration
i Prejudice serves as an outlet for frustration, as we
shall have occasion to emphasize later. A number of
studies have shown that the presentation of a frustrat¬
ing situation will, in most circumstances, increase
prejudice towards any group that happens to provide
a convenient outlet. Since the prejudices we are
concerned with are manifested by whole groups of
people, the frustrations which give rise to them must
(be extensive and serious ones. Such frustrations arise
from external circumstances such as economic depres¬
sions, lack of satisfaction in family relations, and so
on. These are admittedly difficult problems. But
prejudice does not solve them. At best it can tempo¬
rarily relieve the feeling of frustration. This tempo¬
rary relief is harmful, since it prevents the search
for, and action towards, the real solution of the
frustration. This point will be given fuller attention
in a later section.
Closes the door to progress
Recent researches have shown the correlation between
prejudice and other kinds of rigidity and narrowness,
at least in Western culture. While the cause is not
(yet clear, the connexion is so strong that it may fairly
be inferred that the maintenance of prejudice will be
accompanied by a closed mind towards anything new
and an inability to accept and reciprocate fully any
human relationship. Clearly, anyone who has these
personality defects is missing much of what life has
to offer.
Breeding ground for terrorism
I Prejudice is partially characterized by fear and
anxiety in relation to the groups against which it is
directed. In Europe during the Middle Ages, many
people terrified themselves, and their neighbours with
beliefs that Jews were agents of the Devil and that
they engaged in ritual sacrifices of Gentile children.
Many of the minor Nazis of modern Germany were
convinced that Jews were engaged in an international
plot to enslave their country. Prejudiced people every¬
where exaggerate the numbers and power of the mi¬
nority groups in their home areas. These and other
facts indicate that a feeling of terror is a motive for
an act of terrorism. The fears and anxieties are
based on false beliefs, but the psychological pain they
cause to those who feel them is real enough. Preju¬
dice thus contributes to unhappiness.
Can spread like a contagion
| When prejudice is part of the culture of a people, it
can shift its direction from one group to another.
The history of countries where prejudice has existed
shows that different minorities have been the objects
of prejudice at different times. The objects of preju¬
dice are not as stable as is commonly thought. The
immigration of a new nationality group to a country
where prejudice is entrenched as of Indians to
South Africa or of Chinese to the United States can
be the basis of a new focusing of prejudice which had
previously been directed to another group. The devel¬
opment of tensions between governments as between
France and Germany in 1914 and 1938 or as between
the Vatican and Germany in the late 1930s can
become the basis of popular false beliefs and discri¬
mination against peoples or religious groups. No
group of people is safe from prejudice when any other
group is already its object.
Ultimate effect: violation of the law
J Closely associated with prejudice is disrespect for law
and unwillingness to settle disputes peacefully. When
one group of people is prejudiced against another
group, it is generally unwilling to apply the usual laws
and standards of behaviour to the persons who are
objects of prejudice. Violation of the law when
it is to be applied to such persons is one of the most
typical forms of discrimination. In many countries
of the world it has been found that unchecked violence
and deprivation of civil rights directed against one
group can easily spread to all other groups. When
laws are misused or ignored, they become weakened,
and illegality becomes part of the entire culture.
Where a dangerous cultural practice exists, any person
or group may become its victim.
Yet there can be little doubt that prejudiced people
believe that prejudice cannot be directed against them
or that it has no harmful effects on them. If they
understood the consequences of their own attitudes and
behaviour, they could at least question their own preju¬
dices. This has not only been demonstrated logically,
but also empirically, by direct questioning of prejudiced
people. Even when aware of the action of prejudice on
minority groups, they are not aware of the reaction of
prejudice on themselves. Ignorance of the full conse¬
quences and repercussions of prejudice is thus a pre¬
condition or necessary cause although not a sufficient
explanation of prejudice.
To be continued next month
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
THE UNITED
NATIONS IN
BRUSSELS
Under a concrete cupola the
largest ever built in Europe
without central supports is
housed the most international of all
the pavilions in the Brussels World
Fair the United Nations Pavilion.
Formally dedicated on April 26, an¬
niversary of the opening of the San
Francisco Conference which drew up
the United Nations Charter, the U.N.
Pavilion brings together under one
roof all the members of the United
Nations family.
The exhibits of the U.N. and the
specialized agencies have a common
theme: the challenge which the
modern world presents to man and
how each member of the U.N. family
is working to help meet that chal-
30
lenge. Striking displays demonstrate
examples of work done by the diffe¬
rent agencies in their special fields:
the International Labour Organiza¬
tion shows its work for social deve¬
lopment in the Andes; the Interna¬
tional Civil Aviation Organization has
maps demonstrating air traffic control
over the North Atlantic; the World
Meteorological Organization exhibits
facsimile equipment for weather fore¬
casting; typical of the projects aided
by the International Bank is one
illustrated by a miniature dam in
operation.
Unesco has several stands dealing
with some of its most important pro¬
jects: Orient-Occident cultural inter¬
dependence, elimination of racial
prejudice, education, arid zone prob-
United Nations
lems and their solution, promoting
the free floW of information.
A special set of sixteen stamps
commemorating U.N. participation in
the Exhibition is on sale in the Pavi¬
lion. The stamps, ivalued at the
equivalent of $2, are only valid for
letters posted on the spot.
A United Nations week was held
from June 23 to June 26, during
which debates were held on subjects
connected with the U.N. family. One
of the principal speakers in this pro¬
gramme was Dr. Luther H. Evans,
Director-General of Unesco. June 26,
anniversary of the signing of the
United Nations Charter (at San
Francisco, in 1945) was marked by a
special ceremony attended by leading
U.N. officials.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July 1958
United Nations
GLEAMING ATOMIUM (left) dwarfs visitors
to the Brussels World Fair. In background
(arrowed) is U.N. Pavilion. Above, entrance,
and below, interior of U.N. Pavilion whose con¬
crete cupola is the largest ever built in Europe
without central supports. Right, a Unesco stand,
"People Have the Right to Information". This
exhibit illustrates Unesco's campaign to bring
press, radio, television and cinema facilities
within reach of all. (See The Unesco Courier,
July I 957, special issue on the Brussels Exhibition.)
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Meet the women of Ghana
by Victor Akinyele Williams
ççrr%His is the Ghana Broadcasting System. The
I time is now half past three... Here is the Ewe
Woman's Half Hour Programme." How often
on tuning in their radio receivers have listeners in
West Africa heard the familiar tones of this woman
announcer. And travellers coming over into Ghana
by plane hear the sweet voice of the air hostess
announcing their time of arrival at Kumasi airport.
These are two of the many evidences of women's
emancipation in Ghana. Women now hold all sorts
of public appointments formerly held by men. You
buy your stamps from a woman clerk behind the
post office counter, and it is now a familiar sight
in Accra to see a woman police officer shepherding
a child across the street, while almost every mail
boat that arrives from abroad brings more Ghanian
women who have gone abroad for further study as
social welfare officers, nurses and for other posts.
Women compete vigorously in all fields of learn¬
ing With men. There are now women doctors,
opticians, physiotherapists and dieticians. There
are women lawyers too, and several Ghanian women
hold high posts in the Civil Service, While those
with academic degrees work as lecturers in institu¬
tions of higher learning.
But what of the ordinary housewife? Like
women everywhere she has her share of domestic
chores and troubles cooking, nursing, laundry and
generally looking after the home. She has her
headaches too, but she keeps cool and level-headed,
for she is not possessed by that demon of the modern
world worry. She is seldom bored because she is
too busy to worry over petty things and she enjoys
her Work.
Triumphantly and good-naturedly the housewife
of Ghana combines the tasks of looking after her
home and bread-winning, helping in this way to
supplement the family budget.
How does she do it? Well, let's start the day with
an average housewife in Accra. She gets up earlier
than any other member of the family, usually about
5 a.m., makes the fire and puts a big pot of water
to boil. While the water is heating, she busies her¬
self, sweeping the compound and cleaning the
rooms. Within a half hour the Water is boiling and
with it she prepares starch for the laundered
dresses, cooks the breakfast for the family, and uses
the remainder for the children's bath.
Loves pomp, pageantry & colour
By 7 a.m. everything is ready for breakfast. The
children and their father eat theirs and go off
to school and the office. But the housewife
does not breakfast along with the rest. She washes
and starches the dresses which she has soaked over¬
night, and bathes her baby one of the highlights
of her day, for children are adored in Ghana.
By 10 a.m. she is off to the market with her
baby cosily wrapped on her back. First she does
her own domestic marketing, and then branches out
to buy supplies for her "work" banana, yam, fish
or whatever her edible merchandise may require.
Some women sell tinned provisions and cigarettes.
In this case let's assume that our friend the house¬
wife sells tataye (fried plaintain). On her return
from market, she makes two fires. On one she pre
pares the family lunch, and on the other she fries
tataye, fish and probably yam. Soon schoolchildren
from the neighbourhood come streaming into her
compound with their ha'pennies and pennies for
their midday meals. Workers from offices, too,
send messengers for her delicious tataye and fish,
both having been fried to a golden brown colour
with coconut oil. By half past one the tataye is
exhausted and the family cooking is ready. Our
housewife can take a short nap while awaiting her
husband and the children.
Jack of all trades? Maybe, but she is master of
them all. She works hard but she plays hard too
for she believes that "'all Work and no play makes
Jack a dull boy".
She loves pomp, pageantry and colour. The
gorgeous multicoloured kente dresses are admirably
suited to her plump figure (one rarely sees a thin
woman in Ghana), her attractive, ebony black
complexion, ivory White teeth and large expressive
eyes. She is fond of the gold jewelry for which
Ghana is famous and on festivals and other special
occasions displays heavy rings, bangles, bracelets,
necklaces, brooches for the hair and dress, ear-rings
~>d sometimes gold bangles round the ankles.
The 'Rock'n' Roll' of West Africa
She loves dancing and singing and, at least once
a week, usually on Sunday, she spends the
evening at her local club. Besides folklore and
tribal " dancing, our housewife and her friends
indulge in a special kind of music called "'High Life"
with lots of rhythm and a quick tempo, that is very
popular not only in Ghana but all down the coast
from Dakar to Douala. "'High Life" is the "Rock'n'
Roll" of West Africa.
Dancing is the number one programme of any
great occasion: a Wedding celebration or anniver¬
sary, the birth of a baby and funerals are all
celebrated with much dancing.
At the theatre and the cinema you will see a host
of women with their families. And on the last
Week-end of each month Accra's places of amusement
are thronged with happy married couples. The
same is true of a host of other towns all over the
country Tamale, Kumasi, Cape Coast all celebrate
the month-end with much felicity.
Do not think for a moment that I am talking
about the sophisticated women of Ghana only. No,
I am talking about people from all walks of life,
rich and poor, educated and uneducated (who still
constitute but increasingly less so the majority of
the Womenfolk of Ghana). They all dance away
their cares with the result that they become care¬
free, but, mind you, not irresponsible. Though
placid and serene in their outlook on life they are
not unambitious. They are keeping up the struggle
to reduce the gap between themselves and their
more advanced sisters in other lands. In a few
short decades education has brought the women of
Ghana out of the misery of illiteracy and supersti¬
tion into a fuller and richer life. Today, girls study
not only at the co-educational school at Achimota,
but also at the Kumasi College of Arts, Science and
Technology and the University of Ghana, Accra.
Now, the parliament and not merely the kitchen is
their goal.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. July 1958
Letters to the Editor
MAN AGAINST NATURE
Sir,
I recently read with great interest your
report... concerning the plight of the
world's wildlife populations (January
1958 issue). Possibly, coming from your
great organization, people will be stirred
into some type of positive action. In
a small local way, this non-profit orga¬
nization (Alberta Wildlife Tours) has
been endeavouring to foster interest in
wildlife preservation and conservation,
by showing productions of 25 mm. col¬
our slides, and 16 mm. wildlife motion
pictures throughout the schools and to
the public in this province. We have
shown to over 32,000 people, mostly in
the rural areas, and purely on a spare
time basis with no financial support
from any source. Only constant pres¬
sure of a national or world-wide scope
will help to save what we have left.
Congratulations on your fine effort to
awaken Man '"The Destroyer".
Edgar T. Jones
Edmonton, Alberta, Canada
Sir,
We should like to offer our congratu¬
lations on your issue of January, 1958.
Your magazine emphasizes the impor¬
tance of natural balance in the animal
world and the need to guard against
its disturbance, and for this reason it
should be widely distributed and read
in all countries.
J. Dumont
Editor-in-Chief,
"La Tribune des Eleveurs et
des Agriculteurs", Brussels
Sir,
I read in your January issue, "Austra¬
lia protects its remarkable natural
features and its marsupials kangaroos,
koala bears, Tasmanian wolves and dev¬
ils and curious duck-billed platypus."
We in Australia do possess some of
the most fascinating wild life, but it is
depressing to know that so many species
are extinct or on their way to inevitable
extinction. The main reasons for this
are that although some animals are
protected, the restrictions are not far-
reaching enough. The policing of this
protection is insufficient and there are
too few natural reserves to save many
species. It is of universal importance
that Australia's wild life be preserved.
There is great opportunity for naturalists
interested in this work in Australia, to
act before it is too late.
Antony Symons (aged 15)
Sydney, Autralia
IN DEFENCE OF THE GOAT
Sir,
Members of the British Goat Society
have drawn my attention to the article
contained in the January issue of The
Unesco Courier, relating to the goat
and written by Mr. Raymond Furon.
This Society considers that the goat,
when managed in a proper manner, is
a most useful animal which produces
milk and, to a lesser extent, meat, skins
and hair under certain conditions which
are not favourable to cattle e.g. climatic
conditions and lack of space. The subs¬
tance of Mr. Furon's article as to the
destruction that can be wrought by goats
is probably true but it Would seem that
your organization would be doing good
work if it could educate people keeping
goats to look after them in a proper
manner. Controlled grazing, electric
fencing and isolation in limited areas are
all surely steps in the right direction.
My Society has done much to im¬
prove the breeding of goats and has
exported first class pedigree stock to all
parts of the world. The members of
my Society who have written to me did,
however, feel that the destructive nature
of the goat has been over-emphasized
and the benefits derived from the use
of goat's milk forgotten. It has been
proved on many occasions that goat's
milk is of great help to children and
old people and often helps cure cases
of eczema and asthma which are caused
by an allergy to beef protein absorbed
through the consumption of cow's milk
and beef products.
H.R. Fortescue
Chairman, The British Goat Society
Norfolk, England
EDITOR'S NOTE: Of course, the goat il
a most useful animal if it is managed prop¬
erly; the trouble is that unlill recently it
has not been managed at all, and then only
in countries where there is an awareness of
the havoc it has wrought; elsewhere (parti¬
cularly in the Mediterranean region) the
goat has for centuries been spreading the
desert wherever it has set foot. It is true,
the problem does not exist in Great Britain.
ARTISTS IN PARIS
Sir,
As a painter I read with much interest
the article "'Young Artists in Paris'"
(The Unesco Courier, April, 1958),
and, according to the definition given
("A painter is young at 60, if he has
not yet made his name"), I can classify
myself among the young ones as I shall
not be sixty until next year.
I can tell you from first-hand expe¬
rience that the material difficulties to
which you refer are very real. I married
young and have two children and I have
many times found myself faced with this
dilemma: Should I subject my wife and
children to the risk of a precarious
existence or should I give up painting?
But it is not possible to abandon one's
art, unless one's passsion for it is super¬
ficial and such is not the case for me.
So, in order to balance the family
budget I have very often had to take
up other, more lucrative kinds of work,
though without ever abandoning my
palette completely. If I also tell you
that I have very independent views on
art, that I do not belong to any particu¬
lar school or group of artists and that I
have never wished to imitate any of the
well-known painters though sometimes
asked to do so by certain art dealers
you will understand that there are many
factors which mitigate against achieving
success.
P. Malard
Paris
Sir,
I have just read with great pleasure
your April, 1958 issue with the articles
on: "'Gypsies, Wanderers for Two
Thousand Years" by Gerald Barry and
"Young Artists in Paris", by Professor
Jacques Pinset.
Both articles have the same 'Leit¬
motiv': Wanderers, artists: lovers of Na¬
ture and often lonely dreamers Bohe¬
mians all. I have lived and worked as
an English Artist in Paris for 49 years.
I left my studio in the old Rue du
Dragon many years ago, but remember
with pleasure the many evenings spent
in Le Père Chambon's old "'Dôme" and
at the "Rotonde" in Montparnasse and
Frede's "'Lapin Agile" in Montmartre
with Warnod, Dorgeles, Vlaminck, Pi¬
casso and many others. I do not know
what things are like in the "Quartier"
now, but, as Professor Jacques Pinset
writes: ""La Vie de Bohème' is a thing
of the past". It was good to read that
both Montparnasse and Montmartre still
vie for the honours of being the most
flourishing artist's quarter in Paris, as
they will remain for many years.
Morse-Rummel
Paris
TEEN-AGERS STUDY UNESCO
Sir,
I wish to express my pleasure in the
continued high quality of The Unesco
Courier. I have been a reader and
subscriber for some few years and, in
my capacity as librarian, have found the
publication most useful, both for source
material in its varied fields, and for its
interest and entertainment value to both
students and staff of the school.
Owing to the apparently increasing
world-wide problems relating to youth¬
ful vandalism and anti-social behaviour,
would it be possible to produce at least
one issue covering successful positive
approaches to these problems, or dis¬
cussing the causes and background?
Lists of suitable "teen-ageJ' literature,
films and other suitable teen-age mate¬
rials available for parents and teachers
would certainly receive much apprecia¬
tion from all concerned.
I should be grateful if you could
arrange to forward suitable library and
display material publicizing the work of
Unesco to the children who are cover¬
ing the work of your organization for
social studies. Our boys concerned in
this study, are aged from 12 years to
174 years of age.
E. Kibel
Moorabbin, Vic, Australia
EDIOR'S NOTE: A list of available
Unesco information materials has been
sent to our correspondent.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom...
TIDAL WAVE WARNINGS : An
international system to give warn¬
ing of tidal waves was forseen by
the Executive Committee of the
World Meteorological Organization
meeting recently in Geneva. Tidal
waves are caused by underwater
earth tremors, tropical storms and
other geophysical phenomena and
often cause enormous destruction
and loss of life in coastal areas.
For this reason the Committee
considered that there must be in¬
ternational investigations into the
formation of tidal waves, and that
the results of research should be
shared between nations. This
would lead to the planning of an
international warning system. The
International Union for Geodesy
and Geophysics (a member of the
International Council of Scientific
Unions, which receives financial
support from Unesco) was asked to
deal with the oceanographical
and seismological aspects of the
problem.
AUSTRALIA'S SUN FURNACE:
A special solar furnace is being
constructed by Australian scientists in
the grounds of Sydney University and
be used to test the resistance of
metals to temperatures of 3,000 to
4,000 degrees centigrade. Its main
feature will be a 65 foot four-legged
tower which Will support a concave
paraboloidal mirror 12 feet in dia¬
meter. This mirror will collect sun¬
light reflected onto it by another
mirror on the ground. Material to be
tested will be lowered to where solar
SUBSCRIPTION
Subscribe today to
THE UNESCO COURIER
Fill in this subscription blank and mail
it with your cheque or money order
to our local agent In your country
listed on page 35
Please enter my subscription for
THE UNESCO COURIER
One year 83.00; 1 0/-stg. ; 500
French francs Cheque/Money Order
enclosed
D Two years $5.50; £| stg.; 1,000
French francs
Name	
Address 	
City	
Country....
Profession.
EUROPE'S WORKERS GO A- VISITING
OVER 1,000 people from 20 European countries will travel abroad this year on
UNESCO-organized study tours which enable workers to meet men and women
who earn their living in the same way in other countries.
Some visits made possible by this year's programme : Members of the All Union Central
Council of Trade Unions, Moscow are booked for visits to German cities ; co-operative
employees from the Central Union of Consumers Co-operative Societies of the U.S.S.R.
In Moscow will visit Stockholm ; Swiss workers will visit Holland, Denmark, Belgium,
Italy and Germany; Danish night-watchmen, Belgian building workers, Dutch and Finnish
co-operative employees and Finnish education association students will travel to Switz¬
erland ; French gas and electricity workers will visit Greece and Greek workers will
travel to Austria and Italy.
UNESCO study tours began in 1952 and since then 6,170 workers have benefited
by them. This year trips are planned for 57 groups of from 8 to 25 persons, although
this represents only a fraction of the number of requests received. UNESCO grants
cover the cost of travel between countries while workers' organizations, employers or
the workers themselves meet all other expenses. This year UNESCO will contribute
$40,000 to the study tours while organizations will spend approximately $120,000. Each
group is received by a kindred association for a programme of studies in the host
country or countries, covering living and working conditions, education, social welfare,
family life and cultural achievements.
heat can be concentrated onto a
small area of its surface.
ALL ABOUT ANTHROPOLOGY:
Scholars around the world have
contributed to the International
Bibliography of Social and Cul¬
tural Anthropology, a world-wide
survey of literature in these fields,
whose first edition (bilingual: Eng¬
lish French) was recently pub¬
lished by Unesco in its series of
studies, Documentation in the
Social Sciences. The book was
prepared by the International
Committee for Social Sciences
Documentation co-operating with
the International Congress of
Anthropological and Ethnological
Sciences. It can be obtained from
Unesco National Distributors (See
list opposite page), price $5.50;
27/6; 1,650 Fr.fr.
asked th,e U.N. for aid in rehabili¬
tating displaced farmers and in
maintaining living standards in the
provinces affected.
It
HiOUSEWIVES' HOLIDAYS:
More than 10,000 Norwegian house¬
wives will benefit from a free fort¬
night's holiday during 1958 and 1959.
The Norwegian Government will allo¬
cate more than $150,000 to 24 organi¬
zations and institutions providing
holiday facilities to needy housewives.
Funds will also be available for chil¬
dren under ten years of age accom¬
panying their mothers.
BAN ON OPIUM GROWING:
Afghanistan has informed the U.N.
Commission on Narcotic Drugs that
it will ban cultivation and export
of opium. Cultivation of the poppy
has long been an important source
of income for the population in
parts of Afghanistan. To offset
the economic effects of the ban,
the Afghanistan Government has
URAL SCHOOL PROBLEMS:
A total of 250 million children in
the world's rural areas still have no
schools and even in educationally ad¬
vanced countries, "one teacher"
schools predominate. One of the
most pressing needs for the extension
of compulsory education is the impro¬
vement of rural education. The In¬
ternational Conference on Public
Education which meets each year in
Geneva to discuss current educational
problems has therefore chosen for its
themes this year, "Facilities for edu¬
cation in rural areas" and "The pre¬
paration and issues of the primary
school curriculum." Convened jointly
by Unesco and the International
Bureau of Education, the Conference
will tafee place between July 7 and
16. Ninety countries have been invit¬
ed to send representatives.
UNESCO CLUBS IN FRANCE:
There are now some 350 Unesco
Clubs in France whose activities
range from the organization of
travel abroad through contacts
with other clubs (Unesco Clubs
now exist in ten countries) to dis¬
cussions on international problems.
Recently members of the French
Unesco clubs met at Boulouris, on
the French Riviera, to discuss the
further development of the move¬
ment. These clubs are usually
attached to secondary schools, but
an increasing number of youth or¬
ganizations in France are becoming
interested in the idea, and several
clubs have been formed in youth
hostels and similar groups.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
THE RACE QUESTION IN MODERN SCIENCE
Unesco has called upon outstanding anthropologists, sociologists,
biologists and physiologists of international renown to prepare a
series of publications each dealing with a different aspect of the
race question. These small volumes written for the lay reader are
most effective in combating racial misconceptions, false theories
and prejudices. Their success prompted Unesco to publish them
for the first time in one collective volume, forming a full study
of the race question in modern science. The nine titles included are:
+ Race and Culture, by Michel Leiris
+ Race and Psychology, by Otto Klineberg
Race and Biology, by L. C. Dunn
+ Racial Myths, by Juan Comas
+ The Roots of Prejudice, by Arnold M. Rose
+ Race and History, by Claude Lévi-Strauss
+ Race and Society, by Kenneth L. Little
+ The Significance of Racial Differences, by G. M. Morant
Race Mixture, by Harry L. Shapiro
U.K. edition published jointly with Sidgwick & Jackson Ltd,
London.
U.S. edition published jointly with Whiteside Inc., New York.
Cloth: $5.00; 17/6 (stg.); 850 F. fr.
The nine foregoing titles and a tenth, not included in the
collective volume (The Race Concept Result of an Enquiry,
$.85; 4/- (stg.); 250 F. fr.) are also available separately. The price
of those marked + is $.30; 1/6 (stg.); 100 F. fr.; others are priced
$.25; 1/- (stg.); 75 F. fr.
Orders for the separate volumes should not be sent to co-
publishers of the collective volume but direct to Unesco National
Distributors.
THE RACE QUESTION IN MODERN THOUGHT
The Catholic Church and the Race Question
by the Reverend Father Yves M. J. Congar, O.P.
The race question in relation to Catholic dogma is here reviewed
by an eminent Catholic theologian. Father Congar sets forth the
position of the Catholic Church as regards the problem from the
spiritual, the social and the historical points of view, and shows
that the principles of Catholicism are profoundly opposed to racial
discrimination. $.40; 2/- (stg.); 100 F. fr.
Jewish Thought as a Factor in Civilization
by Professor Leon Roth.
A short description of Judaism's specific contribution to world
civilization, underlining what in Judaism in the very negation of
racial exclusivism. Professor Roth writes of the history of the
Jewish people and explains how ideas which have become in one
shape or another part of the heritage of Western man, evolved
from the basic laws of the ancient Jews. $.40; 21- (stg.); 100 F. fr.
The Ecumenical Movement and the Racial Problem
by Dr. W. A. Visser't Hooft.
A study of the basic beliefs and convictions of the World Council
of Churches concerning the racial problem. The World Council
groups over 160 Protestant, Anglican and Orthodox churches all
over the world. The author describes the historical background
during the periods of slavery and missionary expansion and examines
the present situation in the United States and South Africa, where
Protestantism is faced with the greatest problems and the greatest
opportunities in the field of race relations. $.40; 21- (stg.); 100 F. fr.
Buddhism and the Race Question
by G. P. Malalasekera and K. N. Jayatilleke.
Two eminent specialists in the history of Buddhism, show
Buddhism's special contribution to the understanding and solution
of the race question. One of the main novelties of this work is
that it shows how close the Buddha's ideas are to the findings of
modern biologists and social scientists. Special attention is given
to the caste system and to the different doctrines of Buddhism in
relation toi this problem. $.50; 2/6 (stg.); 150 F. fr.
HOW TO OBTAIN UNESCO PUBLICATIONS
Order from any bookseller, or write
direct to the National Distributor
in your country (See list below ;
names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request).
Payment is made in the national
currency ; rates quoted are for an
annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. - Panuzaï, Press
Department, Royal Afghan Ministry of
Education, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 369 Lonsdale Street, Melbourne,
C.I, Victoria. (A. 13/-)
' AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C"., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V (seh.
37.50.)
BELGIUM. For The Unesco Courier:
Louis de Lannoy, 47, rue du Midi,
Brussels, (Brabant), (fr.b. 100.) Other
publications: Office de Publicité, 16 rue
Marcq, Bruxelles, CCP 285-98; N.V.
Standaard-Boekhandel, Belgiëlei 151,
Antwerp.
BRAZIL. Livraria Agir Editora, Rua
Mexico 98-B, Caixa Postal 3291, Rio de
Janeiro.
CANADA. University of Toronto Press,
Baldwin House, 33 St. George Street,
Toronto 5. (S3. 00)
CEYLON-. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House, P.O. Box
244, I 00 Parsons RoadColombo 2. (Rs. 9)
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Libreria Económica, Pte Zayas
505-7 Apartado 1 13, Havana.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia Ltd., 30
Ve Smeckách, Prague 2.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6 Norregade, Copenhagen K. (D.kr. 12)
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agen-
cy, P.O. Box 120, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (F.mk. 540)
FRANCE. Unesco Sales Section,
Place de Fontenoy, Paris, 7*. CCP.
12598-48, Unesco Bookshop, Paris.
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8. (DM. 6)
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Kultura, P.O. Box 149.
Budapest, 62.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nícol Road,
Bombay I ; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 1 3 ; Gunfoundry Road, Hyde¬
rabad, I; 36a, Mount Road., Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/ 1 Asaf Ali Road, P, O.
Box 386, New Delhi, I; Sub-Depots :
Oxford Book & Stationery Co., Scindia
House, New Delhi; Raikamal Prakashan
Private Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby
Road, Bombay I. (Rs. 6.70)
INDONESIA. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Djakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
35, Allenby Road and 48. Nahlat Benja¬
min Street, Tel-Aviv. (£.ls. 4/-.-.)
ITALY. Libreria Commissionaria San¬
son!, Via Gino Capponi 26, Casella Pos¬
tale 552, Florence, (lire 950)
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 99
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings. (10/-)
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo. (Yen 500)
JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar u|-Kucub, Salt Road, P.O.B. 66,
Amman.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul. .
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul
Brück, 33 Grand'Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Peter Chong & Co.,
Post Office Box 135, Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta. ( I 0/-)
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl. 6)
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church. (10/-.)
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos. (10/-)
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass 7, Oslo. (N. kr. 10)
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60 The Mall,
Lahore ; Bunder Road, Karachi and
35 The Mall, Peshawar, (rs.6)
PANAMA. Cultural Panameña, Ave¬
nida 7a, No. 49, Apartado de Correos
201 8, Panama, D.F.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo, P.O. Box
620. Manila.
POLAND. Osrodek Rozpowszeshniania
Wydawnictw Navkowych Pan, Palac
Kultury i Nauki, Warsaw. (Zl. 50).
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada Lda,
Livraria Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70,
Lisbon.
REPUBLIC OF IRELAND. The
Nacional Press, 16 South Frederick St.,
Dublin. (10/-)
SWEDEN. A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl.
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm
16. (Sw.kr. 7.50)
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40 rue du Marché, Geneva. CCP.
1-236. (frs. S. 6.50)
TANGIER. Paul Fekete, 2 rue Cook,
Tangier.
THAILAND. Suksapan Panic, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Isti-
klal Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul.
UNION OF BURMA. S.P.CK. (Burma)
549, Merchant Street, P.O. Box 222,
Rangoon.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Streec, P.O. Box 724, Precoria. (10/-)
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London. S.E. I. ( 1 0/-)
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22, N.Y. (S3. 00.) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y.
U. S. S. R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjïga
Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
WEDDING DAY
IN MODERN JAPAN
Western and Oriental elements found in
many aspects of Japanese life are seen in
these two wedding ceremonies for which
the brides are garbed in the traditional
kimonos and the bridegrooms are dressed
in Western style. Elaborate hair-dos worn
by brides are wigs. Important feature of
marriage ceremony is the ritual of drinking
rice wine by bride and. groom. In top
photo, attendants hold recipients for rice
wine. According to custom, marriage
room is decorated with emblemsstorks
for fertility, bamboo for plenty and tortoises
for wisdom. In traditional Japan all mar¬
riages were arranged by parents. Today,
with new legal freedom, young people can
choose their own spouses. (See page 4)
Courtesy Japanese Embassy, Paris.
]]>
</page>
</document>
