<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="066222eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
Im I
;«í HC-W&-
JUNE
19 5 8
(llth year)
Price: I /-stg. (U. K.)
30 cents (U. S.)
5 0 francs (France)
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
I
fe
t^ra¡p|il*¡
HHnmi
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO'S NEW HOME will be opened to the public later this
year, and during the course of the next few weeks the large-scale opera¬
tion of moving in the Secretariat will begin. Late this year the Unesco
Courier will devote a special issue to the new Unesco House which,
while still under construction, has become one of the best known modern
buildings In the world, and to the works of art which decorate it. Pho¬
tos show : Left, an interior view of Conference Building with Its massive
fluted walls In reinforced concrete; above, end view of a wing of Y-shaped
Secretariat Building; below, the old makes way for the new as workmen
demolish the last traces of a building which formerly occupied the site.
UNESCO photos by Marc Kiboud (left) and Benetty (above and below).
Courier
JUNE 1958
NTH YEAR
COVER PHOTO
Monkey modelled In clay is one
of the remarkable sculptural
figures which were placed in
hundreds around the great burial
mounds of Japan almost two
thousand years ago. For story on
Stone Age Japanese Art see p. 14.
No. 6
CONTENTS
PAGE
2 UNESCO'S NEW HOME
4 CELEBRATION IN CUZCO
Old Inca capital restores Its 'quake-torn monuments
12 THE ROOTS OF PREJUDICE
By Arnold Rose
14 MASTERWORKS OF JAPAN'S STONE AGE ART
By Seiroku Noma
24 THE LANGUAGE OF COLOURS
Its myths and symbols
By Roger Bastide
26 SINGING SANDS
A strange concert heard In the desert
By E.R. Yarham
PRESERVING THE CREAM OF THE SCREEN
By David Gunston «
SCHOOL FOR BALLET
Soviet youngsters follow a great tradition
By E. Souritz
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
28
31
33
34
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, 19 Avenue Kleber, Paris 16, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemln
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (12 issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. The United States of America edition is distri¬
buted by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 801 Third Avenue, New
York 22, N.Y. , Plaza 1-3860. Second-class mail privileges authorized at New
York, N.Y. (M.C. 58. 1.125 A)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads " Reprinted from. THE UNESCO COURIER plus date
of issue", and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rate»: $3.00; IO/-itg. ; 500 French francs or equi¬
valent.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
CELEBRATION
IN CUZCO
Old Inca capital restores
its quake-torn monuments
INCA CEREMONY is re-enacted (right) by people of
Cuzco, Peru, wearing costumes of their ancestors.
Most solemn feast of ancient Incas was that dedicated to
the Sun, which was attended by nobles from every corner
of their vast empire. In the Cuzco of today the walls of
Inca palaces and temples (below) serve as foundations of
Hispanic convents, churches and mansions. Magnificent
green and grey blocks of Inca stonework with beautifully
worked surfaces were fitted together without mortar.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1958
t f
Shaped like an open hand, the Peruvian city of Cuzco
spreads out at the head of a strategic valley. The
fingers reach up towards steep hillsides, the base of
the hand lies at the confluence of three small rivers.
The city's site has been inhabited since a remote antiquity
from the very earliest urban civilization of the central
Andes. During the 15th century, Cuzco was the capital
of the Incas "'The People of the Sun" whose empire
was the most extensive of any in ancient America.
Cuzco is in reality three cities. One is Inca, the second
is Colonial and the third is modern. Inca Cuzco lies at
ground level and beneath the Colonial city. It consists of
massive, beautifully fashioned walls. Colonial Cuzco
overlies it with religious buildings and courtyard dwellings.
Modern Cuzco, to a great extent, has still to take form
for it lacks many of the buildings required, by a large
regional capital.
Eight years ago, on the afternoon of Sunday, May 21,
1950, Cuzco rocked and trembled in the grip of a major
earthquake. Within six seconds 300 people were killed
or injured, 3,000 dwellings were destroyed and damage
was done to many churches, including the 17th century
Cathedral, to the university, to historic Colonial mansions
and other monuments. All told, damage was estimated
at 500 million soles (33 million U.S. dollars in 1951).
The Peruvian Government took immediate steps to meet
the appalling situation in the city. It instituted a new
tobacco tax to help pay for Cuzco's public and private
housing reconstruction, and the Peruvian Congress made
a special appropriation for the restoration of churches
and historical monuments. The Government also asked
Unesco to send a special mission to study the situation in
Cuzco and to make suggestions for conservation and res¬
toration.
Headed by Professor George Kubier, of Yale University,
U.S.A., and including Luis MacGregor Ceballos, a Mexican
architect-restorer and Oscar Ladron de Guevara, a Peru¬
vian architect-archaeologist, the mission went to Peru in
June 1951. Its report (later published by Unesco: Cuzco:
Reconstruction of the Town and Restoration of its Monu¬
ments (1) included a survey of the earthquake damage
and a plan for preserving and restoring the damaged
buildings.
When, in 1956, Professor Kubier again visited Cuzco on
Unesco's behalf he was able to report that "the achieve¬
ment of rebuilding and restoring nearly three-quarters
of the monumental architecture of the city in five years-
remains impressive."
Today, Peruvian architects and engineers have rebuilt
most of the city's damaged churches and cloisters, consoli¬
dated shaky structures and repaired the stone surfaces.
In addition hundreds of new dwellings have been
constructed for homeless families, a courthouse has been
erected and improved public services, such as electric
power supplies, have been put into operation.
As the people of Cuzco masons, artisans and labour¬
ers rebuild their city it seems as though history is
repeating itself. In 1650, almost exactly three centuries
before the recent catastrophe, another great earthquake
left Cuzco in ruins. But the city recovered from this
disaster and Went on to experience its great Colonial flor¬
escence between 1650 and 1780. Between 1930 and 1950
the population of Cuzco grew from 20,000 to 80,000. The
creation of a Cuzco Development Authority with United
Nations participation, aiming at an intensive programme
of rural and urban improvements, gives hope that this
rate of growth will continue until Cuzco ranks among
the largest cities of Peru, with a population of at
least 150,000.
(1) No. 3 oí Unesco's "Museums and Monuments" series. Price
$1.50; 5/6; 400 frs.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
CUZCO (Continued)
. Capa-Magnum Photos Inc
ORNATE DECORATIONS in the churches of Cuzco Include what Is probably the best collection of
mid-seventeenth century wood sculpture In Peru. Above, left, lavishly carved wooden pulpit in Church
of San Bias. It Is said that no country in South America can equal Peru in the number and quality of
wood-carved pulpits and in the variety of types and styles. Above, right, congregation attends Mass In
church of San Sebastian, in the suburbs of Cuzco, which was severely damaged by the I9S0 earth¬
quake. Opposite page, high altar of the same church before damage caused by falling stones was repaired.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1958
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
CUZCO (Continued)
G. de Reparez-Unesco
CITY OF STURDY
BROWN STONE
The fine brown Andean stone, called
Andésite, with its slight, reddish cast
which the Incas and later the Spaniards
used to build Cuzco, gives the city a unifor¬
mity like Florence with Its palaces of the
Renaissance. Cuzco is a city of sturdy
stone which abounds In all of Its churches,
cloisters, arcaded plazas and In the portals
and patios of its houses. Right, roof-top
, view of Cuzco, I 1, 000 feet up in the Andes.
One of the city's architectural gems is the
main cloister of La Merced, a monastery
which was entirely rebuilt after an earth¬
quake destroyed Cuzco In 1650. Above,
cloister pillars shored up after the 1950
earthquake. Left, pillars after restoration.
) C. Capa-Magnum Photos Inc.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1958
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
CUZCO (Continued)
ÇÇ) C,Capa-Magnum Photos Inc.
GREAT MAKERS
OF BRICKS AND
GROWERS OF FOOD
Innumerable sun-dried clay bricks (left) have
been used in Cuzco to rebuild the houses
destroyed by the earthquake. Traditional
building materialthe clays of Cuzco are
inexhaustible these bricks are toughened
by chopped straw and formed by hand in a
simple wooden mould. Below, old wood¬
worker, Juan Estrada, puts finishing touches to
the bases of two carved wooden columns. All
wooden sculptures and carvings In Cuzco's
reconstruction have been executed by local
craftsmen. Right, hustle and bustle of Cuzco
market, little changed since the days of the
Inca Empire, which was based on intensive
agriculture, including cultivation of more than
40 domesticated plants. Markets were there¬
fore an Important feature of Inca life, and it
was decreed that there should be three fairs
every month, when labourers In the field
should come to the market and hear anything
the Inca or his Council might have ordained.
Unesco-Eric Schwab
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1958
Ç; C.Capa-Masnum Photos Inc.
n
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
THE ROOTS
OF PREJUDICE
by Arnold M. Rose
With this issue, THE UNESCO COURIER begins the presentation in serial form of The Roots
of Prejudice, by Arnold Rose, Professor of Sociology at the University of Minnesota, U.S.A.
Published by Unesco in its series The Race Question in Modern Science, The Roots of Preju¬
dice is one of Unesco's most popular and provoking studies. It can be obtained from Unesco's
National Distributors (see list, page 35), price: 30 cents ; 1/6 ; 100 fr. In this first article, Pro¬
fessor Rose discusses personal advantage as one of the important causes of prejudice. In future
issues he will show how ignorance of other groups of people and racism, or the "superiority
complex" are the profound roots of prejudice. Professor Rose will also deal with the important
problems of transmission of prejudice to children, the psychology of prejudice and prejudice
as a warping of the personality. © by UNESCO. Unauthorized reproduction prohibited.
Prejudice of one group of people against another
group has existed in most parts of the 'world and
at all periods of history. It has not been
universal, in the sense that all cultures or all people
have displayed it; but it has been prevalent enough
to serve as a basis for conflict between nations and
between groups within a nation. It practically always
involves discrimination, which means mistreatment of
people without their having done anything to merit
such mistreatment (1). It has thus been a source of
human unhappiness and misunderstanding wherever
and whenever it has arisen. Although certain in¬
dividuals have exploited prejudice to gain political
power or economic advantage for themselves, there is
no example of a whole people advancing themselves
or their civilization on the basis of it. It has been,
rather, a blight from almost every standpoint.
Yet there is still relatively little understanding of
the causes or even of the effects of prejudice, except on
the superficial, obvious level. It has not even been
studied by scientists sufficiently to make them certain
of its causes, although there have been some startling
(1) We use the term prejudice to refer to a set of atti¬
tudes which causes, supports or justifies discrimination.
Since discrimination itself consists of observable behaviour,
it is a more useful subject for study. But since in this
study, we are searching for causes of behaviour, we
must direct our attention to the mind of the person who
practises discrimination. Prejudice is taken as the mental
state corresponding to the practice of discrimination.
discoveries and stimulating suggestions. Outside the
ranks of social science, most people hold quite
erroneous ideas about it^ideas which themselves are
sometimes born of prejudice and which are sometimes
even detrimental to those holding them. We shall
now proceed to consider the varied sources of pre¬
judice, moving from the more obvious and rational
causes to the less apparent and unconscious ones.
Excuse for economic or
political exploitation
Perhaps the most obvious cause of prejudice is that
it creates advantages and material benefits for
those who are prejudiced. Prejudice can provide
an excuse or rationalization for economic exploitation
or political domination. It can enable a man to
justify to himself acts that he would ordinarily be
unwilling to engage in. It can be exploited by
shrewd, self-seeking manipulators when it occurs in
other people. It can offer opportunities for taking
sexual advantage of minority group women, and it
may give people at the bottom of the social ladder
an apparent superiority over the minority group. The
fact that individuals and groups can and do gain
advantages for themselves out of prejudice, becomes
a cause of prejudice.
Imperialism has frequently been attended by pre¬
judice. Even when there has been no noteworthy
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1958
development of prejudice in the home country, those
who go forth as colonial administrators, traders, or
extractors of the natural resources of undeveloped
lands learn that callousness toward subject peoples,
and an attitude of racial superiority will aid
them in their venture. Within limits, a harsh manner
and exacting demands will gain a large output from
workers who have no means of defence or retaliation.
Payment of low wages and provision of only a mini¬
mum of life needs to these workers will mean larger
profits.
Maxim for dictators :
and conquer
Racial, national, or religious antagonisms can be
built up to deflect class antagonisms. A relati¬
vely small number of exploiters can maintain
their dominant position by dividing their subordinates
and encouraging them to be hostile to one another.
One group may be given the sergeant's role of keep¬
ing all other groups in line by force. In return for
this they have the satisfaction of being regarded as
belonging to the superior group, even though they are
themselves exploited. This procedure may be used in
a perfectly "'natural" way, so that it is obvious to no
one.
Techniques akin to those of imperialism may be
employed within an independent nation. Prices or
rents of houses can be kept at a high level by obliging
people to live within certain small, segregated areas.
Wages can be kept low for people who are not allowed
to work in any but certain exploited jobs. Public
facilities and benefits may be kept at a minimum for
people who are segregated to the greatest extent.
It is difficult to tell how much of this use of pre¬
judice and discrimination for purposes of exploitation
is conscious and how much unconscious. Some that
appears unplanned and unconscious is occasionally
revealed to be quite deliberate. One young man who
had just answered a questionnaire designed to test for
anti-Semitism made a revealing remark in this
connexion. He said, "I have no strong feelings about
Jews either way" (the test did not show him to be
anti-Semitic). "'But I am studying to be a banker,
and if my employers are anti-Semitic, I'm going to be
anti-Semitic too, as I want to get ahead/'
Perhaps we shall never discover for certain how
much of prejudice is deliberate and how much
unconscious. But that is of little consequence, as the
effects and the underlying causes are always the same.
Deliberate use of prejudice to exploit a group of people
is hardly different from the unplanned and non-
directed utilization of group differences to gain every
possible advantage from the situation. Both can be
considered together as a cause of prejudice.
The gains to be secured may be political as well as
economic. Group differences can be fostered to keep
a certain party in political power. Modern dictators
have been experts in the technique of "divide and
conquer" both to retain power in their own country
and to extend their conquests abroad. Studies have
been conducted in several countries which show how
Hitler secured supporters now called fifth columnists
offering them the positions and property then
held by Jews and by appealing to a latent feeling of
racial superiority. In democratic countries where
prejudice is prevalent, some politicians successfully
base their campaign for office on theories of racial
supremacy. Most of the organizations formed for the
apparent purpose of fostering race hatred have been
shown to have political domination as their ultimate
aim.
Economic or political exploitation as a cause of pre¬
judice has definite limitations. In the first place, it
must be balanced against the costs of prejudice. It is
probable that in the long run imperialistic countries
could have gained even greater economic advantages
if they had not employed prejudice, discrimination
and violence. Individuals who exploit prejudice be¬
come extreme victims of the psychological costs of
prejudice. Another burden they lay upon themselves
is the realization that they are exploiting and cheat¬
ing. Most people dislike thinking of themselves as
unfair and dishonest, or without ideals. Even the
building up of a psychological defence to rationalize
unfairness and dishonesty may be only partially
successful; it certainly creates rigidities in the
personality. Thus, the advantages of prejudice do not
seem great when balanced against its cost. Moreover,
there are progressively fewer opportunities for
exploitation through prejudice as hitherto subordinat¬
ed peoples have now organized themselves to stop it.
Throughout the world
imperialism is in retreat
"T HROUGHouT the world, imperialism is retreating.
Exploited minority groups within nations have
also made great strides towards improving their
position and reducing victimization. They have had
active support from many members of the majority
group who have realized the costs and dangers of pre¬
judice. Thus, exploitation and domination are de¬
creasing, at least in so far as they stem from pre¬
judice, and they are thus less effective as causes of
prejudice.
There are other apparent advantages of prejudice.
We can only refer briefly to the difficult subject of
men of the dominant group taking sexual advantage
of minority group women. "Gains" of this sort are
obviously balanced by social losses for the dominant
group as a whole. A society in which there are fre¬
quent demands for casual and loveless sexual inter¬
course is not a well-organized or satisfying society,
either to its men or to its women.
Finally there are some prestige gains in a society
based on prejudice. If people have no other basis of
prestige, they get a certain satisfaction simply out of
being members of the dominant group. Although
they are at the bottom of their own racial, national,
or religious group, they can feel superior to the mi¬
nority groups.
The weakness of this kind of gain is surely obvious ;
the prejudiced person who gains a prestige satisfac¬
tion out of feeling superior to a minority group is
diverted from other, more important, kinds of prestige
satisfaction. He loses ambition, and allows himself
to be manipulated by those higher on the prestige
scale in his own dominant group. People who live
under such unfavourable circumstances that they
might be expected to join reform or revolutionary
movements are sometimes kept from doing so by re¬
luctance to lose the trivial prestige that raises them
above the minority group.
(To be continued next month)
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Masterworks of Japan's
Stone Age Art
by Seiroku Noma
The history of Japanese art stretches far back into
the mists of antiquity possibly some 6,000 years.
To most ol these six millenia from the time when
the earliest inhabitants settled in the Japanese islands,
between 4,000 and 6,000 years ago, to the dawn of Bud¬
dhism, which was introduced in 552 A.D. the Japanese
have given the name Joko Jidai (The Ancient Age).
There is no historical record of this period since there
was no system of writing, but archaeological studies have
reconstructed for us an image of the early Japanese peo¬
ple and their way of life in the Stone Age.
These men were hunters and fishermen. They gather¬
ed wild fruits and shellfish and used stone tools and
implements. Their era is known as the Period of Jomon
(rope-pattern) Type Pottery Culture as their civilization
is represented by crude earthenware with surface decora¬
tions of impressed patterns like those produced by pres¬
sing the clay with rice-straw rope or matting. The peo¬
ple lived in primitive houses which were no more than
pits dug in the ground (hence known as pit-houses) with
hearths in the centre and tent-like roofs. Excavations
from the remains of their dwelling places have produced
not only pottery but flint arrowheads, hatchets and dogu
(clay images).
These clay figurines or human figures of the Stone Age
are the oldest existing works of sculptural art in Japan
and together with the later Haniwa figures form the two
characteristic kinds of sculpture of Japan's pre-Buddhis-
tic period.
Just as the human f at first presents a grotesque
shape, so is the embryo of sculpture always bizarre, and
the clay figurines of early Stone Age Japan, with their
squat bodies and flattened heads, are no exception to
this rule. Most of them are about fifteen or twenty
centimetres in height, though there are some as small as
five and others as large as thirty centimetres high. They
have been found in the centre and north of Japan.
How old is this sculpture? Until recent times archaeo¬
logists have been reluctant to make precise asser¬
tions. Of the 200 or so clay figurines so far discov¬
ered, most appear to date from the Middle or Late Jomon
Period.
Recent radio-carbon tests for dating ancient objects
now enable archaeologists to divide the Jomon Culture
into five periods, the first beginning roughly 5,000 years
before the Christian Era and the fifth and last period
ending towards the first or second century B.C. (1).
The distribution of these clay figures shows that they
began to be made in the Middle Jomon Period and became
conventionalized as they came to be more fashionable.
Later treatment of exaggeration and ornateness was prob¬
ably an attempt to break through the conventionalism.
Why did these ancient people make such figurines?
Like the many primitive clay figurines of similar fantas¬
tic shapes which have been excavated in Central Europe
and Siberia, many of the Japanese figurines represent
pregnant women with swollen breasts and bellies. It is
(1) See La Culture Préhistorique du Japon by Yukio Koba-
yaschi, in the Journal of World History, Vol. IV, N° 1, 1957, a
quarterly review published under Unesco's auspices.
14
therefore presumed that men prayed to these symbols of
fertility that their families might multiply and prosper.
The fact that there were figures other than those of
pregnant women is not hard to explain. Once man has
learned to make a figure as an object of prayers, he can
go on to make figures symbolizing other wishes and desires.
The clay figurines then were a kind of icon, but most
likely they were not for community use, but were worship¬
ped in houses by individual families, for they have gen¬
erally been found in groups numbering several scores.
Their small size (mostly about 15 cm. high) suggests that
they were kept in the "'pit-houses", and they must have
been hung, for they are unstable in shape and some have
perforations on the shoulders.
The expression of these figurines is strong and vigo¬
rous. They were made by the same craftsmen who
produced the Jomon Type Pottery and who possessed
a fine formative talent rarely found among primitive men.
Their earthenware pieces, which were food vessels for
daily use, were also ornaments to enrich their lives, and
these reveal most strongly the pleasure and pride the
makers took in producing them. While the Jomon Pot¬
tery pieces were utilities of daily life, the clay figurines
were made on rare occasions.
Following the clay figurines in ancient Japanese sculp¬
ture come the Haniwa, quite different from the figurines
in age and location. Produced in about the third and
fourth centuries A.D., these belong to a different culture.
The term Haniwa means wa (circle) of hani (clay), that
is, clay objects arranged in a circle or circles. They
are so called because they were set up in a circle or
concentric circles on the slopes of burial mounds which
began to be built in Japan in about the third century
A.D., a custom which continued until the second half of
the sixth century when the introduction of Buddhism
brought the cremation system.
The Haniwa or terra-cotta tomb figures or posts can
be classified into two groups: (1) those in the shape of
simple cylinders placed around a mound to border the
tomb compounds or along the foot of the mound to pre¬
vent the earth crumbling down; (2) those in the shape
of men, animals, houses, furniture and other objects
dedicated to the persons buried there. While clay figur¬
ines are found in Japan's eastern regions, Haniwa are
discovered chiefly in the west, although some have also
been unearthed (like the clay figurines) in the Kanto
District. But in all cases they have been excavated from
ancient burial mounds which shows their purpose was
different from the clay figurines.
There is an old legend relating to the origin of Haniwa
recorded in the Nihon Shoki (Japan Chronicle) a book of
Japanese history completed on Imperial order in the year
720. This records that when a prominent person died
it was customary in Japan for his or her servants to be
buried alive in the same tomb. However, on the death
of the Empress Hihasuhime-no-mikoto, consort of the
Emperor Suinin (c. 3rd century), the bene¬
volent Emperor had pity on her followers
and asked his advisers how this cruel
custom might be replaced. The solution
was found by the courtier Nomi-no-sukune
Cont'd
page 20
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1958
DANCERS IN THE MOONLIGHT. Arranged in circles around the burial mounds which began to be erected in Japan in
the 3rd century A.D., archaeologists have found clay sculpture in the form of human figures, animals and objects. Named
"Haniwa" from wa (a circle) and hani (clay) this ancient sculpture has chiefly come to light in western Japan. Largest in number
among the Haniwa figures are men and women, some in armour, others dancing and singing. Those shown here are Haniwa
dancers, the larger one (thought to represent a woman) being 18 in. high and the smaller (a man) I I in.. Tops of these
cylindrical figures are modelled into faces with large eyes and noses, and despite their simplicity the figures have a lively, joyous
air. Looking at them, says Seiroku Noma, one might well imagine men and women of antiquity dancing in some moonlit field.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
STONE AGE ART (Continued)
SCULPTURE BY
JAPAN'S FIRST
CRAFTSMEN
This clay figurine, dating from the
Stone Age, is an example of the oldest
existing sculptural works of art found
in Japan. These are presumed to date
from the early part of the Neolithic
Age in Japan during what is called
the Period of Jomon Pottery. The
name "Jomon" means "rope pattern,"
as the crude earthenware of this period
has surface decorations of impressed
patterns likethose produced by pressing
the clay with rice-straw or matting.
Figurine shown here, which lacks the
right arm and the lower part of the
body, dates from the Middle Jomon
Period (between 2000 and 3000 B. C.)
With the exception of the shoulders,
which are black, it is coloured brown.
Its present size of I 0 in. shows that
the complete work was larger than
the average among such figurines.
One of the "hill-shaped" figurines,
so called because their heads are shaped
like gently sloping hills. They have
broad, raised shoulders and stout legs
and wear waistcloths resembling tight
shorts. Figures ofthis type are believed
to date from the Late Jomon Period,
(about I 000 B. C.) as they have been
unearthed along with earthenware
pieces identified as belonging to
this period. Jomon Period figurines
have chiefly been found in the
central and northern parts of Japan.
Photos and documentation on pages I and
I 4 to 23 are from "Japanese Sculpture-
Archaic Period" by Seiroku Noma, repro¬
duced by courtesy of the publishers,
Bijutsu Shuppan-Sha, Tokyo : Photos
by M. Sakamoto. All rights reserved.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1958
GOGGLED FIGURE. Figures with faces like this have been named "goggled" figurines
on the assumption that a kind of protector like those employed by the Eskimos to guard
their eyes against snow glare was also in use in the northeastern part of Japan. Clay
figurines of this kind were venerated and hung in the primitive homes of Stone Age Japan,
called "pit-houses" because dug in the ground. Many figurines represent pregnant women
to whom, it is believed, men prayed that their families might grow and prosper.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
STONE AGE ART (Continued)
HAIRSTYLES
AND BEAUTY
1,500 YEARS
AGO
HEAD OF A GIRL. The
top of this Haniwa figure
probably formed a large hair-
dress, but most of it is now
missing. The delicate curve
from the forehead to the nose
and the expression of the eyes
which have not been perfor¬
ated at right angles, but
obliquely, with a spatula, are
admirably life-like. Other fig¬
ures of the 5th and 6th cen¬
turies reveal the different
hairstyles and modes of dress
of both men and women.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1958
SAD-FACED WOMAN with
a large hairdress. In general
the eyes of the Haniwa heads
are most expressive. They
are generally almond-shaped,
but slight differences in the
shape can be used to express
dignity, joy or sorrow. Here,
the sculptor has represented
the ears by two simple rings
of clay applied to the head.
Haniwa figurines show women
wearing jewellery round their
necks, on their wrists, and
sometimes round their ankles.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
STONE AGE ART (Continued)
ANIMALS JOIN
THE FUNERAL
PROCESSIONS
TETHERED HORSES were
most common of Haniwa ani¬
mal figures. In the one shown
here the form and the trap¬
pings have been executed with
great skill. It has a saddle,
ring-shaped stirrups, tethers,
and a bit in its mouth. Pen¬
dants hanging from the tethers
are "horse-bells." One inter¬
pretation of Haniwa works
is that they were inspired
by ancient Chinese custom of
burying pottery funeral figures
in the tomb for the comfort
of "life beyond the grave."
who called a hundred haji or clay workers from Izumo
Province and had them make clay figures of men, horses
and other things which he set around the grave of the
dead Empress in place of the real persons.
But this is only one of the ways in which the origin of
the Haniwa have been interpreted and it is generally
regarded as more legendary than real, for the Haniwa are
primarily terra-cotta cylinders and could not be consider¬
ed as symbolic substitutes for human victims. Another
theory is that these original cylinders enclosing the burial
mounds first came to have human faces on top and
gradually developed into full figures. A third interpreta¬
tion is that they were inspired by the Chinese custom of
burying pottery funeral figures in the tomb for the
comfort of "life beyond the grave".
Whichever of the theories is correct, it seems likely that
they were indeed intended to be part of a funeral pro¬
cession. Largest in number are those of men and
women, some in armour, some dancing or singing or en¬
gaged in other activities. Some are smiling, others are
weeping or have angry expressions. Most of the animal
figures are horses in full trappings, though the sculptors
have also depicted dogs, monkeys, boars and deer. The
fact that there are swords, shields, desks, chairs and
other objects as Well as houses of various type may be
taken as a token of the influence of the Chinese Ming-
chi'i (Pottery figures of men, birds, beasts and objects
placed in ancient Chinese tombs and mausoleums to be
of eternal service to the dead).
Haniwa figures were made for the huge tombs of men
of rank from the fourth to the sixth centuries. (Perhaps
the most impressive of the mounds is the Emperor Nintoku
Mound in Osaka which covers an area of about 5,000,000
square feet). On the death of one of these men the work
20
of "mass producing" the Haniwa began, the greatest
number required being cylinders to surround the burial
mound. They were erected in many circles" so that hun¬
dreds and sometimes thousands were needed. They were
made rapidly by haji and other clay workers normally
engaged in making earthenware vessels, helped by other
workers in the community.
Human figures, animals and other shapes were made
amidst the bustle and rush of this large-scale activity.
It should thus be remembered that Haniwa figures were
not made by sculptors working intently from models, but
by craftsmen reproducing forms they carried in their
minds. Elaborate treatment of details was not required
as they were intended to be set up on a mound and looked
at from a distance. Yet though they are not refined in
style they are full of fresh vigour.
The process used in making Haniwa figures was to
knead clay into the form of a rope, then to cut it into
pieces of suitable length. These were then piled up to
form the rough shape and this in turn was smoothed with
the hands to its final form before being heated. Ordi¬
narily the figures were between 50 and 100 cms. in height,
the largest being the figure of a man found in the
Mushashi Province, which measured 124 cms. They were
made hollow for the economy of clay and to lessen the
weight, as a large number had to be made at the same
time. Had they been solid they would not have dried
quickly and would have cracked while being heated.
The clay figurines of the Jomon Period and the Haniwa
figures, which have come to light only recently after being
hidden underground for many centuries, have a remark¬
able freshness. Innumerable others are probably still
waiting to be discovered.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1958
WILD BOAR has body and legs
modelled from cylinders. Though
horses in full trappings make up
the greater part of animal figures,
the Haniwa sculptors modeled many
other familiar animals such as dogs,
birds, monkeys and deer. In earlier
periods, hunters used crude wooden
bows and stone-tipped arrows.
Those who lived during the Hani¬
wa era employed iron arrow-heads.
DOMESTIC FOWL illustrates the origi¬
nality of Haniwa sculpture which lies in its
vivid representation within simple forms.
The skill of this particular craftsman is seen
in his treatment of the well-rounded belly,
the powerful feet and the delicate change
of the sweep from the belly to the neck.
Until the fifth century A.D. dogs and fowls
were Japan's only domesticated animals.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
STONE AGE ART (Continued)
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1958
PORTRAITS
IN CLAY
IRON-CLAD WARRIORS. These two
ancient warriors are among the finest of
Haniwa figures. The one on the left is
wearing full armour and a "peach-shaped"
helmet. He carries a quiver on his back
and a bow in his left hand, the right hand
holding the hilt of his sword. Below, a
warrior wearing a cuirass and a necklace
and with a sword slung at his side.
POWERFUL PEASANT. This Haniwa
figure of a man with powerful, vigorous
body is presumed to represent someone
in the prime of life who does heavy work
such as farming. The cheeks are painted
red and the ears are indicated by two large
perforations. Holes also exist in the arm¬
pits, but these were probably made to pre¬
vent the figure being cracked in firing.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
THE LANGUAGE OF COLOURS
MYTHS AND SYMBOLS
by Roger Bastide
What's in a colour? The answer is, sometimes a great
deal. Down the centuries particular colours have
been used to signify certain qualities or conditions.
Crimson was the imperial colour of the ancients, just as
today yellow is the imperial colour in the Far East.
Among English-speaking people blue often stands for
wisdom and spiritual truth and red for courage. Colours
are often given spiritual or religious significance.
Although this symbolic significance is generally recogniz¬
ed the symbolism itself gives rise to some controversy.
Some people among them Frederic Portal, author of a
well-known book, Les Couleurs Symboliques, published in
Paris in 1938 maintain that colours have the same
meaning for all peoples and at all periods of history;
that white, for instance, is always the symbol of divine
wisdom and red that of love. Yet a study of Portal's
book shows that all the examples he gives are taken,
with very few exceptions, from the same cultural region.
If the inquiry was extended to other parts of the world
should we come across the same tradition or find different
symbolic meanings?
Why paint fathers blue
and cypress trees red ?
Furthermore, are such systems based, in the final
analysis, on actual observation? In other words is
there any real basis for the symbolism of colour, and,
if so, should it be sought in outward, visible things or in
man himself? Should we attribute the significance of red,
for example, to the fact that this is the colour of blood
or instead, to the stimulating effect red-coloured objects
are known to produce on the human nervous system?
Psycho-analysts have recently taken a hand in the
solution of this problem and they have tried to combine
the individual symbolism of colours with their traditional
symbolism by a theory of the collective libido [the energy
or motive force, either so far as derived from the sex
instinct (according to Freud) or as derived from the
primal and all-inclusive instinct to live (according to
Jung).]
It is certainly no accident that Leonardo da Vinci,
depicting a snake biting the belly of a woman, employed
exactly the same colours as those used long, before by
Indian artists in Mexico painting a similar scene; in both
cases the colours represent and express the same impulses
of the sub-conscious.
Certain aspects of nature, such as the blue of the sky
or the green of grass and trees, obviously tend to arouse
in all human beings, whatever their racial origin or
culture, identical feelings which may produce the same
kinds of symbolism. It has also been shown that the
various wave-lengths of light have similar effects on all
nervous systems, and, applying this knowledge, doctors
sometimes use red in the treatment of smallpox, or blue
bandages for patients who have just had an operation.
Psychiatry has confirmed these facts. Havelock Ellis,
the British psychologist, observed that green is the favour¬
ite colour of homosexuals, and studies of the painting
of mental patients reveal that the colours used correspond
to changes in the patient's emotional behaviour and that,
in cases of periodic psychosis, dark and light periods
alternate (1).
(1) R. Volinat, L'Art psychopathologique, P.U.F., Paris, 1956.
24
However, neither nature nor emotions can do more
than suggest things to the mind; they do not offer a
basis for a coherent system of symbols. Psycho-analysis
may attribute a certain variation in the significance
attached to colours to the fact that human feelings are
ambivalent; thus red can express both love and hate;
yellow, the mystic impulse and deceit; and green, hope
and perversity. While these extremes may explain certain
traditional systems of symbols, where yellow, for instance,
can stand equally for God the Omnipotent, for strike¬
breakers and for a cuckold, they cannot account for a
whole series of facts emerging both from the paintings
of great artists and from those of mental patients. Here,
the symbolism is an individual one, and not that of a
group and this becomes clear when either painters or
patients are questioned when they are asked, for exam¬
ple, why they have painted their fathers blue or cypresses
red. And when individual and group symbolism tally,
it is not because psychological factors explain sociological
features, but because, on the contrary, outward civilization
imposes its standards and traditions on the individual,
even though he may be mentally ill.
Colour as the expression of certain emotional reactions
must therefore be dissociated from the problem of colour
as a symbol. The physiological impressions of our sense
organs, which cause us to talk of stimulating or depress¬
ing, cheerful or gloomy colours, may well, like the un¬
derlying impulses of the libido, converge with the cultural
symbolism of colour; they may also oppose it or even
ignore it completely. The cultural symbolism of colour
must, therefore, be considered independently of physio¬
logy or psycho-analysis.
Every civilization has its system of symbols. Historians
of mediaeval art come across many examples. At that
time the church laid down the colours that artists were
to use for the figures in religious paintings: the Virgin
Mary had to have a blue robe and Christ, who is also
attired in blue during his period of preparation, is clad
in black during the temptation in the wilderness, and
in white or red after His resurrection. The reason for
the blue garments is that the Virgin Mary and the Mes¬
siah come from heaven, black represents the encounter
with the prince of Darkness, and white and red stand
for the two aspects of God's nature, His wisdom and His
love.
Red for love (or hate)
Black for the devil
The real question, however, is whether or not the same
system of symbols recurs in all civilizations. So far
it has been the practice to compare the use of the
same colour in a number of entirely different countries or
during periods of history as distant as possible from one
another. We might take as an example, Bacchus' red
cloak, the crimson robe of the priest of Eleusis, the red
mantle donned by Mohammed on Fridays, the garments
of the Roman Emperors, the robes of Roman Catholic
cardinals, and so on, and seek the same significance in
things which may have a variety of meanings. (To find the
real meaning, one really needs to study colour in every
historical or cultural context and, above all, to consider
all the uses made of red: for example the practice of the
Amerindians who smeared their bodies with annatto before
going off to hunt or to do battle although this may have
only prophylactic significance or the use of the red
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1958
palanquin at Chinese weddings, which is connected with
the dualism of yin and yang (2).
Research on the symbolism of colour is within the
sphere of ethnography and, before using the comparative
method, one must first make a study of each of the
various systems of myths, proceeding slowly from one
cultural area to the next, or following the routes of the
great proto-historic or historic invasions. If we take two
African systems as examples, we shall see that colours
have a given significance only within certain contexts.
For the Dogons, the Blacksmith, who is to fashion men
and their society, comes down to earth on the rainbow
and takes its various hues to colour the stones from which
the limbs of men are to be wrought, the various human
organs, the seeds of plants and the compartments of the
celestial granary. However, although this system is coher¬
ent, it would be very difficult to establish a link between
the black of the left leg, the red of the left arm, or the
white of the right arm and the Western tradition of
black for the devil, red for love (or for hate) and white
for innocence. The significance of the colours depends
upon the myth as a whole; in another myth, they would
have a different meaning (3).
When Ogoun, the god
of war, turned crimson
The Dogon system is very familiar to Africanists, but
the Yoruba system is less well known, at least in this
particular connexion, so I shall describe it in rather
more detail. Every god has his own special colour: Oshala
(the sky-god), white; Shangô (the thunder-god), red;
Oshossi (the god of hunting), green and yellow; Oshoum
(the goddess of fresh water and love), yellow, and so on.
It is easy to understand how this classification of colours
originated; white is reminiscent of the dazzling bright¬
ness of the sky, red of the fiery thunderbolt, green and
yellow of the forest, and Oshoum's yellow of the muddy
water of the rivers.
After that, however, the system runs on by itself, that
is to say, any god, even if his powers or sphere of
action do not suggest any colour, has one attributed
to him in order that there may be no gap in the series. The
history of the gods also connects further colours with
them; for instance, because Shangô carried his father,
Oshala, who could no longer walk, in his arms, white is
henceforth added to his red, although white has nothing
to connect it in the first instance, with the thunder-god.
It is the myth which creates the symbols and not the
existence of symbols with constant and previously fixed
meanings which explains the myths. Moreover, as Oshala
is white and it is he who created the first man and
woman, white becomes the symbol of birth, and young
women who enter a "convent" for initiation ceremonies
that is, to be reborn wear white, even if they are
subsequently to dedicate themselves to some other god,
whose symbolic colour they will then wear.
Another example is provided by the chief wife of
Shangô, Yansan, who, as she steals the '"magic" of light¬
ning from her husband, also takes on his two colours, red
and white, while his two other wives or concubines keep
their original colours. Here once more the colour owes
its significance to the myth, or, in other words, it is the
god who transforms it into a symbol.
The example of the Yoruba is interesting from another
point of view: the Negroes of that nation, borne off to
America as slaves, took with them their own symbolic
classification of colours, which there, clashed with another
classification, that of Christianity. This is proof that each
civilization attributes different meanings to colours.
Oshun, for example, whose daughters wear yellow, was
assimilated with one of the forms of the Virgin Mary,
whose children are dressed in blue.
As time passed, however, in Rio de Janeiro the African
system began to show the influence of the Christian
(2) Terms of a dualism which runs through much of Chinese
philosophy, folklore, divination, religion, medicine and magic.
The yin is the female, negative, dark, evil principle as con¬
trasted with the yang, the male, positive, bright, beneficent
principle.
(3) Marcel Graule, Dieu d'Eau, Ed. du Chêne, Paris, 1948.
system and certain gods, like Ogoun, the god of war,
changed their colour. He took on the red of Shangô,
while Shangô's sons .wore white and Oshala added yellow
to his white. The reason why Ogoun became red is that,
for Western people, red is one of the symbols of war'
(when angry, we "'see red"), and Oshala added yellow
to his original colour because golden-yellow is the symbol
of the supreme Being. However, as one realizes on reading
the books published by the leaders of Umbanda Spiritism
(this being the form which the African religion takes in
Rio), the symbolism and the myth are so closely linked
that, in changing colour, the gods also change their
personality.
An interpretation of colour systems should be under¬
taken with reference to an interpretation of cultures, and
it would then become obvious that certain patterns can,
in fact, be distinguished. There is, for instance, the
dualistic pattern, which need not necessarily be white
and black; in China, it is red and green and, among
the Etruscans, it was red and black. There is also the
cosmic pattern, based on the cardinal points or the
different directions in space, which, of course changes,
in passing from one hemisphere to the other, if the colours
are linked, as they are among the Mexican Indians, with
the seasons, winds, forms of vegetation and natural
elements.
The problem of symbolism is not only of theoretical
interest; it also has practical implications. Although we
may not believe that the system of accepted symbols
depends wholly or mainly on feelings, we do believe, on
the other hand, that the opposite is true and that symbols
may influence feelings in certain ways. There is not only
colour symbolism: there is also colour prejudice, which
is affected by the symbolism. Examples might be taken
from Ancient Egypt, where the classification of beings
was reflected in the order or colours, or from India, where
each caste has its own colour. We need only consider
the forms of colour prejudice at present existing among
white men.
We have inherited from the Greeks and Christianity
the two extremes of white and black, representing purity
and evil. There is the example of Theseus, using the
black sail to symbolize failure, and the white sail success,
when he returned from Crete to Greece. In Christianity,
the chosen ones wear white tunics, and devils are black.
And this dualism can be seen even in our playing cards!
Colour prejudices: Negro
with a 'white man's' soul
Although we do not realize it, this association of
black with hell, death, the shades of night and sin,
inevitably influences the European view of Africans,
as if the colour of their skin had laid a curse upon them.
This is so true that when someone white is speaking of a
Negro Whom he admires or of one who has become in¬
tegrated into the white civilization, he may say that the
person in question may be a Negro, but he has the "soul of
a white man," as if, in order to make him acceptable, he
must at all costs discover something white in the Negro.
Similarly, in the system of colour symbols, grey is to
some extent ambivalent, being regarded either as
white tinged with black or as black tinged with white;
and in the same way attitudes towards half-castes tend to
be unfavourable or favourable, according to whether they
are seen as a travesty of white (white tinged with black)
or as an approach to white (black tinged with white).
Hence the existence of two contrasting forms of prejudice
among white people who thus may be prejudiced to a
greater or lesser extent against half-castes than against
Negroes.
It certainly cannot be said that colour prejudice is based
solely on such symbolism, but the latter definitely has an
influence, even among well-meaning white men. To re¬
cognize the relativity of systems of symbols may therefore
be an effective aid in eradicating race prejudices (both
against Asians, whom an Occidental may tend to consider
untrustworthy or hypocritical because he has been told
at school that they are yellow, and against Africans) and
of doing away with ethnic stereotypes two of the great
tasks that Unesco has set itself.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
SINGING SANDS
A strange concert heard in the desert
by E.R. Yarham
Two explorers, Bertram Thomas and H. St. John
Philby (1), who crossed the Great Desert of the so-
called "'Empty Quarter" of Arabia, both describe how
they were startled by a phenomenon known as "Singing
Sands", the mechanism of which has long been discussed.
Thomas and his party were in the heart of the desert,
floundering through heavy sand dunes, when a loud
droning like a musical note broke the silence. One of
his Badu companions pointed to a steep sand cliff about
200ft. high and shouted, "Listen to that ridge of sand
bellowing!" All that Thomas could see was a filmy
wisp of sand being carried up the gentle windward slope
to spill like smoke over its top. On another occasion,
he was similarly startled by a curious note emitted from
the sand as his camel trod on it, but the tribesman at
his side, a Murri who was familiar with the phenomenon,
could only give as an explanation that it was some acti¬
vity in the uppermost of the seven underworlds. The
Arabs, in fact, believed the sounds to be the spirits of
the sand dunes talking.
In Thomas's experience, the note continued for about
two minutes, ceasing as abruptly as it had begun. When
Philby noted a similar phenomenon a few months later,
it was set up artificially and unintentionally. He, too,
was in the heart of the Empty Quarter, and he heard
(1) Bertram Thomas's book, Arabia Felix, describing his jour¬
ney in 1930-31, was published by Jonathan Cape, 30 Bedford
Square, London, in 1932 ; H. St. John Philby's account, The
Empty Quarter, being a description of the Great South Desert
of Arabia, known as Rub'all Kbali, was published by Constable
& Co., 10 Orange St., London, in 1933.
u. N.
the noise in the afternoon, at about the same time as
Thomas had. He was resting in his tent when he heard
a deep, musical, booming sound. Looking out, he discov¬
ered that it had been set up by one of the party walking
up the steep sand slope of the dune encircling the camp.
His description is worth quoting:
"Quite suddenly the great amphitheatre began to boom
and drone with a sound not unlike that of a siren or
perhaps an aeroplane engine quite a musical, pleasing,
rhythmic sound of astonishing depth... The conditions
were ideal for the study of the sand concert, and the first
item was sufficiently prolonged it lasted perhaps about
four minutes for me to recover from my surprise and
take in every detail. The men working at the well
started a rival and less musical concert of ribaldry
directed at the Jinns (desert spirits) who were supposed
to be responsible for the occurrence... I realized that the
key to the situation was Sa'dan, seated on the top of the
slope. It was evident that the music was being engen¬
dered by the sand sliding down the steep slope from
under him.'"
Philby followed Sa'dan's example and found that he,
too, was able to produce the same sound by setting masses
of sand in motion down the side. The noise commenced
with a grating sound and increased gradually to a musical
booming, which just as gradually decreased and died
away. He experimented by pushing a bottle into the
singing sand, and as he withdrew it there followed a wail
like that of a trombone. At another time he plunged
into the moving mass of sand half-way down the slope,
and it appeared to throb beneath him like a great organ.
The singing sands of southern Arabia have become
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
known to science only during the present century. But
the phenomenon was known to the Chinese at least a
thousand years ago. One of their writers left an account
of an area in the province of Kansu where it had been
noted in the ninth century. He described the "Hill of
Sounding Sand", which was 500ft. high in places and
possessed strange qualities: "Its peaks taper up to a point,
and between them there is a mysterious hole which the
sand has not been able to cover up." The writer said
that in the height of summer this hill of sand gave out
sounds by itself, but if trodden by men or horses, the notes
could be heard for long distances.
The same scribe described a custom which was followed
to induce the singing: "It is customary on the "tuanwa
day" (the Dragon Festival on the fifth day of the fifth
moon) for men and women from the city to clamber up
to some of the highest points and rush down again in
a body, which causes the sand to give forth a rumbling
noise like thunder. Yet when you come to look at it
the next morning the hill is found to be just as steep as
before. The ancients called this the Hill of Sounding
Sand: they deified the sand and worshipped there."
Two missionaries in inland China, Miss F. French and
Miss M. Cable, have also recorded their observations of
the phenomenon in Chinese Turkestan. The City of
Sands (Tunwang) takes its name from the ranges of sand
dunes that lie to the south, stretching out into the great
desert of Lob. These sand hills possess the property of
"singing" when the sand is moved. Before a desert gale
blows, a sound like the rattle of drums is heard, but at
any time the hills can be made to "sing" by climbing to
the knife-like edge of the highest point and sliding down.
The great vibration then produced seemed to spring from
the very centre of the dune.
'Iron Swiss' heard
drums of the dead
Tschiffely, the "Iron Swiss" (2) who rode on horse¬
back from Buenos Aires to Washington, records an
experience on the Peruvian coast. He fell asleep
one night on a sand hill, but was awakened several times
by a noise like, the beating of drums or like a motor
launch travelling on a river. As he could see nothing, he
went to sleep again.
The next morning he noticed that he had been sleeping
near a gentilar, as the ancient Indian burial grounds are
called. He was asked by the Indians if he had heard
the manchang. This sounded rather like Chinese to
Tschiffely, and he asked them what it meant. They
explained that the sand hill was haunted and that every
night the dead Indians of the gentilar danced to the
beating of drums. In fact, they told him so many blood¬
curdling stories about the hill that he began to consider
himself lucky to be alive. He heard later that the
explorers, Baron von Humboldt and Raimondi believed
that the sounds heard so often during the night from
this hill were due to underground waters that moved as
the temperature changed. Another theory is that sea
breezes blowing from a certain direction hit the sandy
ripples on the slopes of the hill to produce this strange
sound.
Although it is to the deserts that one must turn to hear
the finest exhibitions produced by singing sands, a
somewhat similar phenomenon has been reported from
beach sands. An example, unique along the west coast
of Scotland, is afforded by the singing sands of the Bay
of Laig on the little island of Eigg in the Hebrides. The
first such discovery in England appears to have been made
by C. Carus-Wilson, who about 60 years ago found singing
sands at Studland Bay on the coast of Dorset. They
have been recorded also on the coast of North Wales; and
in the United States two observers have reported them
at seventy-four places on the Atlantic Coast alone.
Beach sands "sing" differently from desert dunes. The
beach sands are best described as "whistling" or
"squeaking," according to R.A. Bagnold, who summarizes
existing knowledge in the final chapter of his book The
Physics of Blown Sand and Desert Dunes. The squeak
or whistle is produced, he explains, by any rapid distur¬
bance of the dry top layer, especially just above the high
water level when the sand has recently dried out after
a shower. It is produced when the palm of the hand is
(2) Aimé Felix Tschiffely made his great ride "Southern Cross
to Pole Star", from the Argentine to the United States, on two
native horses, Gato and Mancha.
The Unesco Courier. June 1958
swept across it quickly or when the sand is given ajlight
stab with end of a pencil. When the sand is removed
from the beach, it does not long retain its sound-
producing quality. Grains of singing beach ," sand
examined were rounded, but not markedly so, and were
fairly uniform in size.
In contrast to the whistling of the beach sands, "the
great sound which in some places startles the silence of
the desert" is quite a different noise, according to
Bagnold, who wrote:
"I have heard it in south-western Egypt 300 miles from
the nearest habitation. On two occasions it happened
on a still night, suddenlya vibrant booming so loud
that I had to shout to be heard by my companion. Soon
other sources, set going by the disturbance, joined their
music to the first, with so close a note that a slow beat
was clearly recognized. This weird chorus went on for
more than five minutes continuously... Native tales
have woven it into fantasy; sometimes it is the song of
sirens who lure travellers to a waterless doom; sometimes
it is said to come upwards from bells still tolling under¬
ground in a sand-engulfed monastery..."
The sounds produced by desert dunes certainly vary;
travellers have compared them to a ship's siren, a
throbbing organ, the beat of a drum, a trombone, and the
twanging of a monster harp. In some instances, it
seems that the softer tones are missing; others say that
standing on the sand when it is singing is like resting
on a huge stringed instrument while a bow is being drawn
slowly across it. The note emitted by the desert sand
is much lower than that of the beach sand and at a
distance of 600 yards has been likened to thunder.
Writing from Egypt some few years ago, Lieutenant-
Colonel de Lancey-Forth spoke of the following experience
in the great sand-dune country to the south of Siwa:
"I found, after a strong westerly wind had blown
throughout the day and banked the fine drift sand high
up on the knife-edged tops of the dunes, that sometimes
in the evening, when the wind had died away, leaving
a deep stillness in the air, this fine drift sand slid down
in streaks over the coarse big-grained red sand which
forms the steep slopes of the solid part of the dunes,
and the friction of the one rolling over the other gave
out a noise like distant rumbling thunder with a deep
musical note as that of a cello in it."
Forth's reference to the evening is parallelled in Philby's
account. When he was listening to the singing in the
afternoon, one of his men (referring to the desert spirits)
said, "You Wait, just wait till the evening and you will
hear them letting off their big guns."
Beaches that 'whistle'
and 'booming' deserts
Bertram Thomas, too, noticed the noise late in the
afternoon, when the heat of the day was fading
Apparently, another factor also favours the close of
day. During the day the wind blows the fine drift sand to
the tops of the dunes, and toward sunset, when the wind
usually dies down, it begins to roll down the slopes.
Dryness seems essential, for the ancient Chinese
manuscript states that the Hill of Sounding Sand gave
out noises only at the height of summer; and H. St John
Philby, the explorer already referred to, likewise reported
that early in the morning, when the air was cool and the
sand somewhat moist, he failed to elicit any response
from it. And a few weeks later when there had been
a little rain, there was no music in the sands.
Examination of the sand has not revealed any
peculiarity linking the whistling sands of the beach with
the booming sands of the desert. Samples from the
dunes do not reveal any distinguishing features. The
grains are no more uniform in size than those of many;
silent sands; and though clean sand sometimes seems'.
to sing best, Bagnold heard it in a desert region where
the sand was dirtier than usual and was wetted
appreciably only once or twice in a decade.
Physicists are generally agreed that the sounds are
caused by the rubbing of grains against each other, but
as yet there is no real explanation of the mechanism by
which they are produced. When further critical studies
are made, the answers may be forthcoming. Meanwhile,
when you are in the desert, keep an ear open for one
of the strangest concerts ever to come from nature's
versatile music box.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
PRESERVING THE CREAM
OF THE SCREEN
by David Gunston
Archives Cinematheque Français
VISUAL ILLUSIONS on the screen were first created by Georges Méliès, whose work in France permanently enriched
the technique and scope for film-making by introducing it to fancy and to fantasy and by making it tell a story. In 1900
Méliès made a series of films embodying tricks, fantasies and illusions. Above, illusionist effects in early Méliès film.
It has been said, with no little truth, that one of the
marks of civilized man is his instinctive sense of
history, both past and future, expressing itself in
the desire to preserve for posterity the best that he has
inherited and produced himself. This has certainly been
true of the arts for a very long time. Books, poetry, plays,
music, sculpture, painting and architecture have all been
preserved for succeeding generations, or kept alive for
the future. This was originally done primarily by interest¬
ed wealthy' patrons, but for a long time now states and
governments have lent an increasingly supporting hand,
and now usually supplant the private patron.
Yet as a new medium arriving at a time when preserva¬
tion was a fully accepted practice, the cinema has not
been so fortunate.
The very transience of the screen image has been
against any sense of permanency from the start. In
addition, being ineradicably linked with large-scale
commercial interests, the cinema has sometimes had a
considerable struggle for permanent preservation in any
historical sense. This has always been especially ironi¬
cal, since a popular motion picture still continues to reach
a wider international audience than any other form of
contemporary art, popular or otherwise.
Pious hopes were expressed during the days of the
28
early silent films that some sort of museum might be
made of films of particular interest, especially newsreels
of notable events, but very little was done.
However, the prospects are now brighter and more
encouraging than they have ever been, thanks to the
continuing and remarkable growth of the international
film archive movement. Started in the 1930's by France,
Great Britain and the United States, this has now taken
root in very many countries and in many different forms,
yet always with the basic aim of keeping from oblivion
and the usual limbo of actual physical destruction the
best that the screen offers the world over. In spite of
some irretrievable losses occasioned by such a late start,
the postwar spread of the archive idea may now be said
not only to be vital and thriving wherever it is found
but, largely unheralded and unobserved as it is, "one of
the significant cultural developments of our time."
Some of the archives began as small private collections,
others have always been partly State-aided, whilst others
again are off-shoots of Government .Departments. Some
may be concerned mainly with the physical preservation
of the old films they possess, or with the presentation to
the public or interested students of historical film pro¬
grammes. Many do both. All have to consider the many
problems of the international exchange of films, the safe-
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1958
guarding of rare or exceptional films from extinction,
and the paramount necessity for maintaining a satisfac¬
tory relationship with the commercial film world.
The film archive movement began more or less simul¬
taneously in the three countries mentioned, thanks to
the enthusiasm and determination of three leading
experts. In 1935, with the aid of a generous grant from
the Rockefeller Foundation, the Museum of Modern Art
Film Library was set up in New York under the dynamic
Miss Iris Barry, who forthwith went to Europe on an
extensive and invaluable "shopping expedition" for dis¬
appearing film classics. In the same year in Britain, the
National Film Library (now re-shaped and re-named the
National Film Archive) was established by the British
Film Institute in London to carry out one of the Govern¬
ment-sponsored Institute's objects on its own foundation
two years earlier, viz. "to establish a national repository
of films of permanent value", and the scholarly Mr. Ernest
Lindgren became its Curator. At about the same time
in France was born the Paris Cinémathèque Française,
presided over by the distinctive figure of M. Henri Lan-
glois with his passionate love for any rare, old or de¬
faced film. Each of these three assiduously built up inde¬
pendent collections for permanent preservation, but the
ultimately international aspect of the matter was never
far from their thoughts.
Similar "cinémathèques" began to appear in other
countries, and in 1938 the three original archives combin¬
ed with the biggest of the newcomers, the Reichsfilm¬
archiv in Berlin, to form the International Federation
of Film Archives, which held its first meeting in New
York. Since the war the former Reichsfilmarchiv has
disappeared, but the Federation itself has advanced
enormously, strengthened by the adhesion of other
archives created in Amsterdam, Belgrade, Bogota, Brus¬
sels, Budapest, Buenos Aires, Copenhagen, Lausanne,
Lisbon, Madrid, Milan, Montevideo, Moscow, Oslo, Prague,
Rabat, Rome, Sao Paulo, Stockholm, Teheran, Tokyo,
Vienna, Warsaw, among other places. In all there are
now some 30 effective and provisional members, not
counting the corresponding members in Australia, China,
Archives Cinematheque Française
NEWSREELS of topical events were the type of films with which the motion picture industry
started on its world career as an entertainment medium. The first real newsreel was made by the
Lumière Brothers in Paris in 1895. They filmed the arrival of delegates to a Congress of French
Photographic Societies and created a sensation by screening film two days later. Early newsreel
photo, showing Kaiser William II (on right facing camera) entering open carriage during a state visit.
Cuba, the Republic of Ireland, Finland, Israel, Peru and
Venezuela.
Many of these archives are national bodies, financed by
their governments, and almost all have some official
status, which of course is a good thing. They are organiz¬
ed by men and women of enthusiasm and integrity who
have as great a sense of their vocation as curators and
librarians in older fields of art and mass communications.
The Federation is now a truly international body that
goes beyond the hopes of its founders twenty years ago.
Under the Presidency, of M. Jerzy Toeplitz, of the Warsaw
Central Film Archives, the germs of interest and endea¬
vour it has been able to sow in recent years are spring¬
ing up and bearing fruit almost everywhere. It has
its headquarters in Paris, where its Executive Committee
meets four times a year, and holds an annual Congress
in the various member countries in turn. Its purposes
are officially defined as the promotion of personal
contacts between all its members to facilitate the
exchange of both films and information about them, and
the maintenance of an agreed code of rules to ensure
that all members exercise that self-discipline in the use
of their films which will entitle them, individually and
collectively, to the confidence and support of the com¬
mercial film industry in every country.
This last factor is highly important, for inevitably the
goodwill of any archivist movement depends for its healthy
continuance on happy relations with the suppliers
themselves. Almost all new acquisitions by archives have
to come from contemporary film-producing countries.
Older films, some of them perhaps originally owned by
companies no longer in existence, may be salvaged from
a variety of sources, but often one archive can obtain
them only by exchange and duplication with archives
fortunate enough to hold copies.
Yet in practice the Federation does much more for its
little-known cause. It organizes International Film Exhi¬
bitions, as held in Paris and Berlin recently, the next
being planned for Prague in 1958. It runs "Weeks" or
"Days" of some national cinema in other countries, like
the Week of Italian Cinema in Poland,
or of the Scandinavian Cinema in
France, already held with such
success. It has further founded the
International Bureau of Historical
Cinema Research, which in November
1957 held its first International
Congress in Paris, and which is
regarded as an important step towards
making available data on film history
to all who seek it. The Federation
feels itself directly responsible for the
serious work done in the field of
cinema history, and gives all possible
help to bona fide students. Indeed,
there now exist in many countries
national film research commissions
closely linked with archive-members
of the Federation.
Apart from the commercial restric¬
tions which may hedge round fairly
recent films, and the often intermin¬
able copyright tangles of earlier films
(some of which, ¿ike the earlier
Chaplin and similar short comedies,
have passed through many hands
since they were made), the greatest
single problem of any film archive,
great or small, official or private, is
the appallingly short exectancy of
life of the average reel of film. Unlike
a book or painting, a film cannot be
effectively preserved
simply by being owned
by a far-sighted person
or organization.
If it is an old nitrate
Cont'd
next page
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Which films deserve saving from oblivion?
or celluloid film, the base will undergo chemical changes
in a surprisingly short space of time, say 30-50 years.
This celluloid base will give off gases which unite with
the atmosphere to form nitric acid, which immediately
attacks the still stable photographic image, turning base
and emulsion into a sticky mess a process that, once
started, may swiftly eat through priceless reels of film-
If the film to be kept is printed on the newer cellulose
acetate base, generally used in the industry since 1951,
it does have a longer optimum life, but unless given
: certain physical conditions of storage, will readily dry
out, and become brittle, shrunk and quite impossible either
to project or duplicate.
Although it is theoretically possible for the various film-
producing companies to preserve copies of their own
pictures rather after the manner in which book publishers
and newspaper offices keep "'file copies" of all their wares,
in practice very few do so, and hardly any in the sense
of protecting them for 'posterity. This may seem odd,
but is partly because a film-
producing or distributing com¬
pany is a commercial concern
primarily interested in the finan¬
cial exploitation of its products.
Once a film's box-office life is
regarded as over, it may well be
actually destroyed to give up
precious storage space for new
movies. Nevertheless there is an
element of short-sightedness,
even business shortsightedness in
this policy, as many firms have
now realized.
Apart from the whole range of
films that may be sold to tele¬
vision, the popularity of selected
"revivals", first proved by the
postwar re-issues of Chaplin
feature favourites like City Lights,
Modern Times and The Gold
Rush in many European coun¬
tries, is proving to them that
the time is coming when a good
film is no longer to be dismissed
just because it is "'old". Hence
there is a growing interest in and
appreciation of the film archive
movement, since few producing
companies have the time, space
or the technical skill needed to
offer adequate preservation faci¬
lities to earlier pictures. This
trend of offering to archives,
under copyright safeguards, films
that may still be financially
valuable for preservation under
ideal conditions and care is a
growing one. It was advanced
in spectacular fashion recently
when Lord Rank, of the British film industry, presented
to the National Film Archive in London nearly 250 master
fine grain prints of films made by British firms from 1930
to date.
Nitrate films in storage also present a grave added risk
of fire danger, since celluloid is highly inflammable, so
they need to be stored in metal cans on metal shelving
under special safety precautions. Furthermore, the best
storage conditions for such films, which represent the
bulk of the collections of all archives, may involve expen¬
sive air-conditioning: such prints, being physically
unstable, require a steady, cool temperature of about
33°-40" F., with a 50% relative humidity. Underground
vaults provide these conditions most readily, but the ideal
is always costly, awkward to maintain and sometimes
30
U5I5
ENDLESS GAGS were worked into the comic films
of Mack Sennett, undisputed master of early comedy
producers in the U.S.A. His use of slapstick and unexpect¬
ed situations and his extraordinary sense of the ridiculous
were revealed in hundreds of films. Two groups he used
frequently and made famous were the Bathing Beauties
and the Keystone Cops. Above, two cops in trouble.
difficult to attain. In consequence there is a growing
tendency to copy or "'dupe" crumbling old nitrate films
on to new acetate stock. If this is given the necessary
degree of humidity, its chemical stability is assured for
a reasonable life, and it presents little or no fire risk.
Under good conditions, acetate films may survive for as
long as 200 years, and theoretically they can then be
duped again on to fresh stock.
This procedure is the ideal of every archive, but in
practice the expense involved often rules out the extensive
copying of very old films. A compromise that is becom¬
ing increasingly adopted is that now followed as a
matter of regular policy by the British National Film
Archive. All 25 year-old films in its collection are
regularly subjected to a chemical ageing test, in which
a small circle is punched out of a single frame on the
reel and subjected to laboratory testing that artificially
speeds up its chemical disintegration. In this way, the
likely future life span of any reel of any film can be
estimated and the necessary
duping done before it is too late.
This immediately brings in the
question : what films in poor
state shall have duping priority
with the funds available?
This, and similar technical
matters are discussed freely bet¬
ween members of the Federation,
which is responsible for a growing
interchange of opinions and
films. There is always the possi¬
bility of exchange of rarities for
showing or copying, for it would
be futile for one archive to spend
a lot of money duping a
crumbling copy of some screen
classic when a more fortunate
archive can supply a better copy
from its own collection.
There remains the all-impor¬
tant problem of just what to
preserve. No archive wants, or
can hope, to preserve everything.
Only the cream of the world's
vast output of films are worth
keeping anyway. But beneath
this high level of quality, there
are many productions that ought
not to perish, whether for their
intrinsic artistic merit, their
place in cinema history, their
realism or imaginativeness, the
technical innovations or acting
performances they contain, or
with documentaries and news-
reels, the actual events they
portray.
It is the aim of every archive
to strive to protect the best in
every sphere and from all sources wherever possible, which
makes the co-ordination of the Federation invaluable.
And always there is the burning question of to what
extent is an archive to allow its treasures to be shown
publicly. Quite a number of archives already give regular
showings of many of their films, but there are sometimes
copyright and other snags, and the fact is that where
a single copy of a rare film is held, to project it at all will
shorten its life. So unless and until duplicate copies of
everything can be taken, some films cannot be shown to
the public ad lib.
Yet a wide availability of viewing is ultimately the aim
of the whole idea, since unlike a book in a library or a
painting on a gallery wall, a film in a can is quite useless
unless it can be properly projected and shown publicly.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1958
SCHOOL FOR BALLET
Soviet youngsters follow
a great tradition
by E. Souritz
Tamara Karsavina, one of the
greatest of Russian ballerinas,
called her Memoirs Theatre
Street formerly the name of the
street where the Leningrad School of
Ballet is located. This school also
figures in the Memoirs of Anna Pav¬
lova. More recently, Galina Oulanova
gave the title, "The Ballerinas'
School" to the story of her artistic
career , and although she used the
word "school" in a wider sense, mean¬
ing the experience gained by an artist
throughout her career, she too re¬
ferred to the years she had spent at
the Leningrad School of Ballet.
School certainly plays a more im¬
portant role in the life of a dancer
than in that of any other kind of
professional artist. Ineluctably, the
unique road leading to a ballet com¬
pany starts from a dancing school.
Entering the choreography classes
about the age of nine or ten, the
future ballet dancer spends the rest
of his or her childhood there and not
until the age of 18 does the student
enter a ballet company.
In the early Autumn just before
the school term begins, boys and girls
(boys are usually a minority) invade
il Soviet photos
PRIMA BALLERINA. Anna Pavlova, one of the world's most admired dancers, was trained
at the oldest of Russian ballet schools in Leningrad. The uniform she wore as a student in the
last decade of the I 9th century (top of page) resembles those worn by today's pupils (above).
the corridors of the oldest ballet
school in the Soviet Union. Some
girls are still wearing their light
summer dresses; others have put on
their school uniforms (only children
who have already attended school for
three years can be accepted as can¬
didates). All the girls are excited and
nervous as they wait their turn to be
examined.
The first hurdle is the medical
examination. Only children with
sound hearts and healthy lungs can
hope to stand up to the many years
of hard physical effort that lie ahead.
Weak eyesight can also be an obstacle
to a ballerina's career; a poor ear
for music is an even greater one.
Finally a committee of teachers from
the school judges each child's apti¬
tude for dancing.
Eventually the children complete
their entry examinations. The doctor
has found them physically fit, the
music master has judged that they
have a good ear for music and a
sense of rhythm, the teachers are
satisfied with their aptitude for danc¬
ing, and they have passed the educ¬
ational tests. As pupils in the School
of Ballet they now begin a new life
"a life of hard work and suffering",
as Anna Pavlova called it, but also
one filled with the joys of creative-
ness. The unwavering rule is the
daily exercise, "the lesson", as danc¬
ers call it. "For a dancer every day is
a working day," writes Oulanova, "in
summer, on holiday, work is still
indispensable."
Schools reopen throughout the So¬
viet Union on September 1. On that
day a small pupil in the beginners'
class, wearing a white starched dress,
white stockings and slippers, enters
the large, bright classroom for the
first time. On the teacher's command
she goes over and
stands beside "the
bar" the practice rail
running the length of
the wall. From this
moment, unfailingly,
Cont'd
next page
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Official Soviet photo
NURSERY OF THE BALLET : Young pupils at the Leningrad School of Ballet practise in the classroom where some of the greatest names in
ballet received their training. Many changes have taken place In the organization and programme of the school since its foundation 200 years ago.
right to the end of her career, the
dancer will begin the day with this
rite, continuing to do the same move¬
ments she learned in her childhood.
Many changes have taken place in
the Leningrad School during the two
centuries since it was founded. Once
it was a boarding school for 100 pu¬
pils and much of the building was
taken up with dormitories, bathrooms
and dining rooms. Now there are four
times as many students, and the
building has had to be enlarged. So
today most of the students live
outside, and only those from other
parts of the country are boarders.
The present school not only trains
artists for the Leningrad Ballet, but
also for those of many other Russian
cities. To the different national
groups of the school come youngsters
from republics all over the U.S.S.R.
They arrive too from foreign coun¬
tries, Rumania, for example, and even
from as far away as Mexico, Cuba
and Indonesia. To ensure that they
shall all have a solid educational
background, they are taught the
same subjects as children in normal
secondary schools. The future balle¬
rinas do geometry problems, perform
chemistry and physics experiments
and study geography and natural
sciences. Seven years of secondary
education are followed by three years
of literature, history, foreign langua¬
ges, and studies of the history of the
theatre, the ballet and music.
The life of the school is fuller, freer
and more active than it Was 50 years
ago. Yet inside its walls the new and
the old mingle as nowhere else. In
its corridors the past seems to live
again and the ancient traditions are
in evidence imprinted on a modern
backcloth. Faces of famous ballerinas
who were once pupils look down from
photographs on the walls. They too
worked at the same practice rails.
They too walked, somewhat sedately
in double files, along these vaulted
corridors, followed by the swish of
their long skirts. The marks made
by their tiny feet can still be seen in
the worn, tiled floors of the landings
where today little girls wearing the
red neck-ties of Pioneers are playing.
Yet, these same little girls will
greet a grown-up with a deep curtsy,
following a tradition still maintained
in schools of ballet.
Another tradition handed down
from the past is the performance
given at the end of each school year.
Over a century old, the custom con¬
tinued during the days of Pavlova
and Fokine and also when Oulanova
completed her training, and so it goes
on today. But changes have come in
the repertoires of these shows. Nowa¬
days the pupils draw inspiration from
the heroes of classical literature.
They have based performances on
Till Eulenspiegel by the Belgian writer
Charles de Coster, on Gogol's Christ¬
mas Night and on Pushkin's The
Postmaster.
They also look for ideas in modern
events. Last year, for example, the
school presented a new ballet, The
Girl of the Snows, based on a popular
Soviet novel which tells of life in
Russia's far northern territories.
They draw too on their country's rich
folklore, and on those of other lands.
In the remotest republics of the
Soviet Union dancing is taught ' by
teachers trained in the Leningrad
School of Ballet and by their pupils.
In Europe, America, Africa and Aus¬
tralia dancing is taught by the pupils
of the former ballerinas of St Peters¬
burg. The traditions of the School
continue today as little girls from all
over Russia practise in the same
large, bright classroom of the build¬
ing in "Theatre Street", where Anna
Pavlova, Fokine, Karsavina and Oula¬
nova began their careers.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. June 1958
Letters to the Editor
FACTS ABOUT HAFFKINE
Sir,
I am a Soviet writer and I devote
most of my works to men of science.
Of all human activities, science, and
particularly medicine is, to my mind,
the most fascinating. Recently I had a
stroke of luck: I came across some
papers dealing with a remarkable per¬
sonality, the Russian doctor, Vladi¬
mir Khavkine (Haffkine).
In these papers were accounts of the.
work carried out by the Bacteriological
Institute of Bombay, which has been
named after my distinguished com¬
patriot. There was a short biography of
this man and from it I learned the
following facts.
Born in Odessa, Vladimir Marcovitch
Haffkine studied at the university of this
city. A collaborator of Pasteur and of
Metchnikov (the famous Russian biolo¬
gist), he made several stays in India and
devoted 18 years of his life (from 1893
to 1915) to that country. His work there
earned for him the affection and highest
esteem of the Indian people.
He first went to India during the worst
period of a cholera epidemic. In 1892
in the Paris laboratory of Metchnikov,
Haffkine had discovered a new vaccine
against cholera and, after testing it on
himself and on several friends (all of
them Russian engineers and doctors), he
decided to carry out mass inoculations
with it on people in India. Despite the
worst threats of people who were
opposed to inoculation, Haffkine tra¬
velled for two years in the farthest cor¬
ners of the Punjab, of Assam and other
regions of the sub-continent, inoculating
thousands upon thousands of people.
The success of his vaccine was univer¬
sally recognized.
In 1896 an even greater scourge,
plague, swept India. Dr. Haffkine was
one of the first Europeans to hurry to
Bombay, centre of the epidemic, whose
inhabitants were fleeing in terror.
Within six weeks he had prepared the
world's first anti-plague vaccine.
On lanuary 10, 1897 Dr Haffkine
carried out a courageous experiment.
Without saying anything to his co¬
workers he gave himself an injection of
a preparation containing plague germs.
The reaction it produced was agonizing,
but the doctor never absented himself
from his laboratory. This experiment
further increased the admiration felt by
the Indians for the Russian doctor.
Several leading citizens of Bombay
allowed themselves to be publicly
inoculated and this act of faith opened
the way to a wider use of the vaccine
in the cities and in the countryside.
Between 1899 and 1909 alone, more
than eight million people were
inoculated. The number of deaths
from plague dropped to one fifteenth of
what it had been before.
The Indian Government showered
Haffkine with honours and he was
received with great ceremony by the
Royal Medical Society. In August 1899
at the inauguration of the new anti-
plague laboratory, the Governor of
Bombay declared: "The discovery of
this great scientist Haffkine has saved
and is still saving countless lives. When
the history of our time is written there
is no doubt that his name will be given
an honoured place."
Vladimir Haffkine died in Switzerland
in 1930 at the age of 70. In India his
death was an occasion of national
mourning. In recognition of all he had
accomplished for India the Institute
which he had created was renamed the
Haffkine Institute in 1925.
VLADIMIR HAFFKINE
The life story of this man so appealed
to me that I felt I must write a book
about him. To supplement the infor¬
mation I already possessed, I looked up
many Russian and foreign periodicals
published at the end of the 19th and at
the beginning of the 20th century.
I was greatly disappointed. The
Russian press had given hardly any
space whatever to Haffkine and I was
only able to get hold of a small number
of foreign publications. Fortunately,
however, I was able to contact Dr. Sahib
Singh Sockhay, a former director of the
Haffkine Institute, while he was visiting
the Soviet Union. He offered to send
me more documents on the life of this
courageous man of science and great
friend of India. The present director
of the Institute, Dr. D.V. Soman, also
answered my appeal. But the fact
remains that most of the documentation
on Haffkine is still out of my reach in
French, Indian and British libraries.
I should be very grateful if you would
publish my letter. I hope that among
the many European and Asian readers
of The Unesco Courier, there are some
who could give me some facts about
the life, the work and the physical
appearance of this distinguished doctor
and researcher. My deepest gratitude
would go to those willing to assist me
in my research.
Mark Alexandrovitch Popovski
Sophievskaia naberejnaia 36 ap. No 22
Moscow, U.S.S.R.
MUSIC OF THE ORIENT
Sir, .
I have been getting your magazine for
four months and find it most helpful.
Your November article on "The Music
of the Orient in Reach of Western Ears"
by Yehudi Menuhin is very true. Music
is worldwide and the Indian melodies
very moving and inspiring. Could you
have an issue dealing more on this
subject.
Clara Morrow
Seattle, Washington, U.S.A.
AS OTHERS SEE US
Sir,
From time to time you devote an
issue to a specific question seen in terms
of different parts of the world: literature,
women's rights etc. I find this very
interesting, but I should also like to see
from time to time an issue dealing with
a country which current world develop¬
ments have brought into the Hmelight,
as, for example, Egypt, Palestine and
Algeria.
Among my friends there is a tendency
to consider the people of the United
States as a little too materialistic and
the peoples of the Orient extremely
mystical, leaving us, with our naturally
tolerant judgment on ourselves, some¬
where between the two. I should be
curious to know what Oriental people
think of the Americans and how the
Americans judge us and the people of
the Orient.
Marie-Claire Douxchamps
Namur, Belgium
OCTOGENARIAN GOOD WISHES
Sir,
As a former teacher I find The
Unesco Courier of great interest for I
see it as the best and most rapid
instrument for the progress of mankind.
Although I am 85 years of age I receive
many visits from former pupils, young
men and women, in whom I try to
develop an interest for the great
civilizing and cultural movement of
Unesco. Best wishes for the complete
success of your work of goodwill.
Mme J. NicoIIe
Les Ormes-sur-VouIzie, France
CLASSROOM RAW MATERIAL
Sir,
May I take this opportunity to tell
you how stimulating and how thought-
provoking your magazine is to me as a
school teacher. Thank you for making
available to me, from all over the world,
problems and concerns of people. This
is the raw data of curriculum material
a teacher must have, to see his little
problems in terms of a big World that
can be and is, at the center, a friendly
World.
John Kneisly
Bethesda, Maryland, U.S.A.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom...
For reasons beyond our control
there has been some delay in
the publication of the present
issue. Owing to the forth¬
coming transfer to Unesco's
new headquarters of our dis¬
tribution and dispatch services,
the July issue may also reach
subscribers later than usual.
We ask our readers' indulgence
for these delays.
ATOMS-FOR-PEACE PARLEY:
Some 2,000 scientific papers have
so far been prepared for presenta¬
tion to the Second International
Atoms-for-Peace Conference which
is being organized by the United
Nations this year. Invitations to
the Conference, which will be held
in Geneva from September 1 to 13,
have been sent to 88 countries and
12 Specialized Agencies of the Uni¬
ted Nations.
CiLASSROOM MAGIC CARPET':
During this year pupils of the Zmi-
chowska school in Warsaw are making
regular "classroom visits" to France,
Japan, Switzerland, Vietnam and the
United Kingdom. They do so dur¬
ing the special lessons devoted to
international affairs which the school
(like six others in Poland) runs in
collaboration with the Unesco experi¬
ment in education for international
understanding, in which 170 schools
in 40 countries are now taking part.
In addition to classroom activities,
children collect books, periodicals,
pictures and photos, and correspond
with "pen friends" in the country of
their choice.
m TV SCHOOLS FOR ADULTS:
The possibilities of television for
adult education and ways of pro¬
ducing programmes of educational,
scientific and cultural value were
discussed by television experts and
adult education authorities from
some 20 European countries and
from the U.S.A., Canada and
Japan, who met recently at Marly-
le-Roi, near Paris, at a conference
arranged by the French National
Commission for Unesco and the
French Ministry of Education, with
assistance from Unesco. Experts
studied the results of experiments
in the use of TV for adult educa¬
tion being carried on in various
parts of the world, particularly the
large-scale programmes in group
viewing in such countries as Italy,
France and Japan.
Si
Travel Service which specializes in
school party travel to over 70 centres
in all parts of Western Europe. In
1957, over 600 parties totalling nearly
20,000 children and staff, went on
STS-arranged trips which included
winter sports, art tours and a Rhine
cruise, as well as others to the more
traditional European capitals and
beauty spots. The purpose of this
travel is to broaden pupils' minds and
to foster international friendship.
REBUILDING A FOREST:
Schoolchildren of Portland, Ore¬
gon, U.S.A., spend a great many
hours each year helping to make
a forest grow again on the charred
slopes of a hill near the city.
Each secondary school in the city
is responsible for its own forty
acres of ground and under the
supervision of state foresters, pu¬
pils have gradually become expert
tree planters. At least ten States
in the U.S.A. are nowadays using
camps to give children first hand
experience with nature's resources.
IVEW UNESCO FILMSTRIPS:
Three new filmstrips are now avail¬
able to help school-teachers, youth
group leaders and others to illustrate
the aims and work of Unesco. "Ten
Years of Unesco" is a pictorial history
of the Organization's development
since its creation in 1946; "'Study
Abroad" explains the programme
which helps individuals and groups to
go abroad for study and to get to
know other people ; "Unesco Fables"
explains, for children from three to
12 years of age, Unesco's aims in very
simple terms. The filmstrips can be
obtained from National Commissions
for Unesco. Commentaries are avail¬
able in English, French and Spanish,
and other language versions are being
prepared locally.
fl WILDLIFE THREATENED:
Special measures to protect bears,
wolves and eagles from extermina¬
tion are being taken in Sweden.
A recent report states that about
20 bears are being killed every
year and only about 270 remain.
Wolverines now number 126 com¬
pared with 200 in 1942 and about
100 pairs of golden eagles and 40
pairs of sea eagles survive. Mem¬
bers of nature protection societies
in all Scandinavian countries are
co-operating to preserve existing
stocks of these species. (See The
Unesco Courier, "'Man Against
Nature", January 1958.)
Ci
>CHOOL TRAVEL SERVICE:
This year has marked the 25th anni¬
versary of the founding of School
34
PHEAVAL IN SCHOOLS: The
influence of science and technology,
the complexity of modern life and an
ever-growing student body have
created an upheaval in traditional
European school systems, a revolution
in education which is particularly
marked at the secondary school level.
This is one of the conclusions from
reports of the European Conference
on Secondary Education held at
Sevres, near Paris, recently under the
auspices of the French National
Commission for Unesco and attended
by educators from 23 European
countries plus Morocco. The back¬
ground to the meeting was sum¬
med up by Unesco's Director-General,
Dr. Luther H. Evans, who stated:
"The European secondary school
curriculum has been built up over
many years. How can educators
now expand courses in science and
social studies to meet new techno¬
logical demands in an already full
curriculum without overburdening
the student? How can they reconcile
traditional cultural values with the
needs of a society progressively more
oriented towards science, technology
and economics?"
SOLAR POWER STATION :
Soviet scientists have designed
what is to be the world's largest
solar power station. In the Ararat
Valley, Armenia, 1,300 mirrors,
totalling an area of about five
acres, will be mounted on special
carriages which will move auto¬
matically, according to the sun's
position, along 23 concentric rail¬
way lines. They will focus the sun's
rays onto a boiler mounted on a
130-foot tower. It is estimated
that 2,500,000 kilowatt hours of
electricity will be produced an¬
nually by the installation.
SUBSCRIPTION
Subscribe today to
THE UNESCO COURIER
Fill In this subscription blank and mail
it with your cheque or money order
to our local agent in your country
listed on page 35
Please enter my subscription for
THE UNESCO COURIER
One year S3.00; IO/-stg.; 500
French francs Cheque/Money Order
enclosed
Two years S5.50; £1 stg.; 1,000
French francs
Name	
Address 	
City	
Country....
Profession..
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
u
e
2
"3
unesco
source book
for science
teaching
UNESCO'S DO IT
YOURSELF'
SCIENCE BOOK
Material for making laboratory equipment exists every¬
where the home, around the school itself, in the
junkyard, at the food market, in the garage and in the
countryside, to mention but a few sources. Science
teaching facilities and resources are all around us and just
waiting to be made use of.
In 220 pages the Unesco Source Book For Science Teaching
tells you how to do it. There are directions for making
general pieces of equipment such as balances, heat sources,
filters, pumps, tweezers, ring stands. Experiments and
material for the study of plants are described. Directions
for the study of animals tell how to make a collecting
cage, a wormery, homes for spiders and ants, aquariums.
Astronomy, meteorology, hydrology, machines, mass and
force, heat, sound, light, electricity, and magnetism are
covered by a wide range of simple, inexpensive apparatus
and revealing experiments. More than 300 diagrams
render the use of the volume very easy.
The Unesco Source Book For Science Teaching answers
the needs of teachers all over the world who clamour for
ways to plan and carry out science programmes in which
the subject is experienced and not just learned.
Paper: §2.50; 1216; 600 frs.
Cloth : §3.00; 15/-; 750 frs.
HOW TO OBTAIN UNESCO PUBLICATIONS
Order from any bookseller, or write
direct .to the National Distributor
in your country (See list below ;
names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request).
Payment is made in the national
currency ; rates quoted are for an
annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. - Panuzaï, Press
Department, Royal Afghan Ministry of
Education, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 369 Lonsdale Street, Melbourne,
C.I, Victoria. (£A. 13/-)
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C"., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V (seh.
37.50.)
BELGIUM. For The Unesco Courier:
Louis de Lannoy, 47, rue du Midi,
Brussels, (Brabant), (fr.b. 100.) Other
publications: Office de Publicité, I 6 rue
Marcq, Bruxelles, CCP 285-98; N.V.
Standaard-Boekhandel, Belgiëlei 151,
Antwerp.
BRAZIL. Livraria Agir Editora, Rua
Mexico 98-B, Caixa Postal 3291, Rio de
Janeiro.
CANADA. University of Toronto Press,
Baldwin House, 33 St. Georges Street,
Toronto 5. (S3.00)
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House, P.O. Box
244, I 00 Parsons RoadColombo 2- (Rs. 9)
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Libreria Económica, Pte Zayas
505-7 Apartado 113, Havana.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia Ltd., 30
Ve Smeckách, Prague 2.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6 Norregade, Copenhagen K. (D.kr. 12)
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agen¬
cy, P.O. Box 120, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (F.mk. 540)
FRANCE. Unesco Sales Section,
19 Avenue Kléber, Paris, 16«. CCP.
12598-48, Unesco Bookshop, Paris.
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8. (DM. 6)
GREECE, y- Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Kultura, P.O. Box 149.
Budapest, 62.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nico) Road,
Bombay I ; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; Gunfoundry Road, Hyde¬
rabad, I ; 36a, Mount Road , Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/ 1 Asaf AN Road, P. O.
Box 386, New Delhi, I; Sub-Depots :
Oxford Book & Stationery Co., Scindia
House, New Delhi; Raikamal Prakashan
Private Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby
Road, Bombay I. (Rs. 6.70)
INDONESIA. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Djakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
35, Allenby Road and 48, Nahlat Benja¬
min Street, Tel-Aviv. (£.is.4/-.-.)
ITALY. Libreria Commissionaria San¬
son!, Via Gino Capponi 26, Casella Pos¬
tale 552, Florence, (lire 960)
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 99
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings. (10/-)
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo. (Yen 500)
JORDAN. Josoph L. Bahovs & Co.,
Dar ui-Kutub, Salt Road, P.O.B. 66,
Amman.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
LUXEMBOURG. - Librairie Paul
Brück, 33 Grand'Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Peter Chong & Co.,
Post Office Box 135, Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta. ( I 0/-)
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl. 6)
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church. (10/-.)
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos. (10/-)
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass 7, Oslo. (N. kr. 10)
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60 The Mall,
Lahore ; Bunder Road, Karachi and
35 The Mall, Peshawar, (rs.6)
PANAMA. Cultural Panameña, Ave¬
nida Ta, Noti-49, Apartado de Correos
201 8, Panama, D.F.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejo Quiapo, P.O. Box
620. Manila.
POLAND. Osrodnek Rozpowszech-
nina Widawnictw Navkowich Pan, Palac
Kultury i Navki, Warsaw. (Zl. 50).
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada Lda,
Livraria Portugal, Rua da Carmo 70,
Lisbon.
REPUBLIC OF IRELAND. The
National Press, 16 South Frederick St.,
Dublin. (10/-)
SWEDEN. A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm
16. (Sw.kr. 7.50)
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payoc, 40 rue du Marché, Geneva. CCP.
1-236. (frs. S. 6.50)
TANGIER. Paul Fekete, 2 rue Cook,
Tangier.
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Isti-
keal Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul.
UNION OF BURMA. S.P.C.K. (Burma)
549, Merchant Street, P.O. Box 222,
Rangoon. .
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Street, P.O. Box 724, Pretoria. (10/-)
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E. I. ( 1 0/-)
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22, N.Y. (S3. 00.) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y.
U. S. S. R. Mezhdunarodnaja Knîga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjïg
Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
PEOPLE OF CUZCO, in Peru, former capital
of the Incas and perhaps the greatest centre
of Hispanic architecture in South America,
gather for ceremony marking restoration
of their cathedral which was damaged
during major earthquake in 1950. (See page 4)
."© C Capa-Magnum Photos Inc.
.
/'
!5BRP
.#' I5
]]>
</page>
</document>
