<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="066675eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
9 ** VW fe t» "^ ^»
9 %?l<*fc,
f f'?
Xhe^
«tè f *
W l*N
i 'V
\
**r
-***
/ I m
fl^***»*
f "N
L
> SEPTEMBER
19 5 9
(72t/i yeor^
Price: 1/-stg. (U.K.)
30 cents (U . S.)
60 francs * (France)
!
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
-^J-Vîi-E	1
f
i
r ^
[CM
/¿Ê0^<L5U í/^í<f(ííl
SÈÊIlS^ I l^-5^^^P
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
SEPTEMBER 1959
12TH YEAR
Contents
No. 9
PAGES
COVER PHOTO
BBC, London
Since I 955 radio sets have out¬
numbered copies of daily news¬
papers sold around the world.
Radio receivers now number an
estimated 350 million and news¬
papers under 300 million. Photo
shows Hisato Okuse, " Miss
Japan 1 958 ", speaking from the
BBC, London to listeners in the
Far East. With 90 transmitters
and 1 5 million receivers, Japan
is now one of the world's major
broadcasting countries. The Japan
Broadcasting Corporation is rapid¬
ly developing closed circuit radio
among farming and fishing com¬
munities and plans to cover all
Japan with a frequency modula¬
tion service within five years.
4 THE FREEDOM TO LISTEN
By George Codding Jr.
9 TRAFFIC JAM ON THE BROADCASTING BANDS
By Julian Behrstock
10 RADIO «HAMS': AN INTERNATIONAL FAMILY
By David Gunston
14 INTO. OUTER SPACE ON RADIO WAVES
By Werner Buedeler
15 CALLING THE FLYING DOCTOR
16 PIONEERS OF RADIO
18 SNAPS FROM THE FAMILY ALBUM
20 THE LIGHT PROGRAMME
By Sine
21 THE COBRA AND THE ELECTRONIC CHARMER
22 RADIO'S MAGIC EYE ON THE RIVER THAMES
By Martin Chisholm
25 THE MUSEUM INSIDE THE RECEIVER
26 CENTRAL AFRICA'S 'SAUCEPAN SPECIAL'
28 A LITTLE LESS NOISE, PLEASE
By M. H. Thompson
33 MIGHTY HANDY THAT WALKIE-TALKIE
34 \ FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7', France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (I 2 issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. The United States of America edition is distri¬
buted by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 801 Third Avenue, New
York 22, N.Y., Plaza 1-3860. Second-class mail privileges authorized at New
York, N.Y. (M.C. 59.1.139 A)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER" plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: $3.00; I 0/-stg. ; 600 Fr. frs. or equivalent.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Just four short decades ago, the voice of broadcasting
was little more than a whisper coming from half a
dozen experimental stations in Europe and America
operated by men inspired by an idea and a hope. A
small but equally devoted band of amateurs, who had
painstakingly created their own primitive receivers, were
the only ones to hear that whisper. Good music and
up-to-date news were not the objective for which these
individuals searched, but simply a few spoken words or a
snatch of unidentifiable music being hurled miraculously
across space.
Today broadcasting is one of our most important means
of mass communication. Over 9,000 transmitters and
more than 300 million receivers are available to bring the
voice of broadcasting into the lives of mankind. Radio is
an instantaneous and efficient method of keeping people
informed of important events no matter where they occur.
The listener in Japan can have reports of a top-level
conference over his local station in the time it takes for
interpretation and translation of the proceedings directly
by short wave from the United Nations building in
Geneva. The sports fan in Argentina can follow the
progress of his soccer team just as easily whether it is
playing in Buenos Aires or at the Olympic games in
Melbourne. It is also- an inexpensive way of bringing the
world's greatest music and drama directly into the homes
of a widely scattered and heterogeneous audience.
Above all, radio is the ideal instrument for promoting
the free exchange of ideas and attitudes between nations
and their peoples. European listeners, for example, can
pick up broadcasts from several neighboring , countries
with a normal type of medium-Wave set. With a slightly
modified receiver, they also can receive short-wave
broadcasts of talks and commentary directly from the
far corners of the globe. So important has broadcasting
become' that the nations of the world have affirmed
through the United Nations and Unesco that freedom to
listen is an essential corollary to man's right to freedom
of opinion and expression.
Different countries have adopted different methods of
bringing the advantages of broadcasting to their peoples.
In the United States and most of South America the free
enterprise system is in common application for domestic
needs. Government interference is kept to a minimum
and the competitive spirit is relied upon to provide a
varied programme fare. Radio is financed by the sale of
time to advertisers.
In most of the rest of the world broadcasting is
regarded as a public service. The authorities seek to
enable everyone to listen to one, two, or three national
programmes of varied content. In order to bring some
broadcasting to every citizen, there is a tendency to
establish a fairly comprehensive coverage throughout
their territory, even if some of the stations would be
"uneconomic" by commercial standards. The cost of the
service is met by license fees on receivers, reinforced
Where necessary by government appropriations.
Bigoted propaganda machine
or source of unbiased news
Some countries, like Canada, use a combination of the
two systems in order to ensure that there will be
both adequate coverage and certain cultural stan¬
dards in a variety of programmes. Broadcasting for
foreign consumption, on the other hand, is almost exclu¬
sively a state function, whether only a few hours of pro¬
grammes are transmitted per day, as in the case of Ice¬
land and Thailand, or Whether the external services
operate "around the clock" as. in the case of several of
the larger countries. Responsibility is usually shared
between the foreign affairs branch of the government and
a governmental operating agency, and the expenses are
met by state grants.
No matter what system is used, the pervasiveness,
immediacy and intimacy of radio place a heavy burden
on those Who control its use. By design or accident
broadcasting can be turned into a wearisome, bigoted
governmental propaganda machine, or it can be used to
present unbiased news and to help the listener to under¬
stand his neighbour's problems. It can also be transformed
into a mere outlet for "popular" music and singing
commercials, at best just another background noise of
modern civilization, or it can be used to widen cultural
horizons and to aid in educational advancement.
Constant vigilance is necessary to keep broadcasting from
sliding into either of these undesirable extremes.
There are several serious obstacles economic, technical
and political that impede the most effective use of
broadcasting and thus deny far too many the freedom to
listen. Probably the most important is the lack of success
in making broadcasting facilities, especially receivers,
available to all parts of the world. While Europe and
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1959
North America have a fairly adequate distribution' of
receivers half of the world's total being in the United
States alone and South America is in a relatively good
position, the condition is still shocking in many parts of
Asia and in most of Africa.
In Asia, with the exception of certain countries
bordering on the Mediterranean in the west, and Japan
and the Philippines in the east, the average number of
receivers per 100 persons rarely exceeds six, and in some
areas there are less than one per 100 inhabitants. In
Africa, with the exception of Algeria, Egypt, Morocco,
Tunisia, and the Union of South Africa, few countries
have as many as one receiver per 100 inhabitants.
It is important to note that the areas which do not
have adequate broadcasting facilities are those where the
need is the greatest. While lack of adequate trans¬
portation may make it difficult or even impossible to
distribute newsprint, books or film, radio can com¬
municate over long distances despite mountains, rivers,
and jungles. Broadcasting can also overcome economic
barriers that exist in most underdeveloped countries.
After the costs of installation have been met, the
maintenance of a broadcasting service is relatively in¬
expensive in relation to the area that it can cover and
considerable use may be made of local resources. Film
and newsprint, on the other hand, are expensive and must
be purchased from abroad in the currencies of the major
producers. The third and most important advantage of
radio is that it can inform and educate whether or not
the listener is literate. As Unesco has pointed out, the
countries which are poor in information media are also
those where the level of illiteracy is the highest.
The expansion of broadcasting to meet the needs of
underdeveloped areas, and perhaps even its continuation
on the same level in more fortunate areas, depends upon
the solution of another basic problem. The radio
spectrum is used by many services in addition to broad¬
casting ships, aircraft, telegraph and telephone, and
amateurs, to mention but a few and new ones are being
introduced. Since the radio spectrum is limited, and the
appetites of the radio services are not, over the years it
has become more and more crowded especially in some
of the more desirable frequency bands. The interference
between stations that has resulted is so serious in certain
bands that the future of broadcasting as well as other
radio services is actually in serious danger.
One possible remedy has been explored by the Inter¬
national Telecommunication Union (ITU), the world's
guardian of the radio spectrum. At its first post-World
War II conference in 1947, it decided to draw on the
experience of the European broadcasters and establish
a world international frequency list in which all available
frequencies would be assigned to countries on the basis
of their individual needs. In addition, an International
Frequency Registration Board was to be created with the
duty of assuring that any future operating changes
would cause no interference to the stations operating
according to the new list.
After eleven years of exhaustive labour in which the
technical representatives of almost every country met
time and time ^again, the ITU still has not reached the
objectives set for itself. Limited success was obtained
in assigning frequencies in the low and medium bands
where most domestic broadcasting is carried out, but there
was almost complete failure in the bands with long-range
propagation characteristics, especially those used for
broadcasting directly from one nation to another. The
reason lay in the fact that the total requirements sub¬
mitted greatly exceeded the spectrum space available.
Some requirements were most- certainly legitimate but
others were exaggerated in the hope that a minimum
would remain after bargaining; still others were inflated
to provide for any possible expansion in the future.
The position of high frequency broadcasting was further
complicated by the division of responsibility in most
international services between the telecommunication or
broadcasting authorities responsible for programming
and operating and the non-technical and political
government departments Which oftimes decide the areas'
to be covered, the languages to be used, and the times
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
w^&êl yjA 	 m
in
>»
I
i
/
'Il
4.
7 jÊÊP Mu II
Mil
1
1*
BE¿*^|r.r^/í \
¿wt £ illl
\/ÉÊ *ßZZ\J]WMF *mñ\u
© BBC, London
INSIDE VIEW of a soaring radio mast at the British Broadcasting
Corporation's Very High Frequency transmitting station, near Norwich,
England. The Very High Frequency Band has only come into large-scale
use for broadcasting within the last ten years. All frequency modulation
stations, and most television stations operate within this band.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
FREEDOM
TO LISTEN
(Continued)
STUDIO DEADLINE. Announcer gives last
minute look at news script while producer
and scriptwriter check production readi¬
ness in control room seen in background.
© BBC, London
of transmission. Whatever the reason, the countries
of the World have so far failed in this endeavour.
Fortunately, another opportunity to reach agreement
will present itself when the nations of the world meet this
fall in Geneva for the second post-World War II ITU
Administrative Radio Conference. (See page 8.)
There is another approach to the technical problem of
radio which can perhaps aid in the quest for a political
solution: frequency spectrum conservation. If the limits
of the desired frequency bands cannot be enlarged, the
frequencies available should be used in the most effective
manner. Many radio services have found the means of
reducing the frequency space used by their transmissions
to permit a greater volume of traffic Iwithin their
allocated bands through time sharing, geographical
sharing and the introduction of new technical methods
such as single side band emissions.
An excellent example is the short-range mobile services
employed by fire prevention, police, public utilities, taxis
and other similar organizations. In the past few years
the spectrum requirement for one channel of the mobile
service has been reduced by a quarter and equipment has
been developed that may permit a further reduction of
one half, or even one sixteenth of what was previously
considered necessary.
Of all the radio services, broadcasting has perhaps done
the least in this respect. Even if it is conceded that the
special nature of broadcasting has prevented such action
in the past, the perfection of frequency modulation (FM)
broadcasting in the very high frequencies opens the door
to an effective contribution. In 1947 the ITU assigned
an additional band to broadcasting in the newly
developed very high frequency area of the spectrum.
Later it was found that the use of the FM technique on
PROPHET OF THE
'ELECTRIC AGE
In the 1 880's Albert Robida, French artist-
writer, amused his readers with imagi¬
native pictures of the "Electric Age"
which in reality bears strong resemblance,
to the 20th century's "Electronic Age".
In his drawings, Robida depicted such
modern developments as television enter¬
tainment, television advertising, radio
news broadcasts and music recordings.
A far-seeing drawing by Robida (right)
showed a news correspondent broad¬
casting an eyewitness report to a distant
audience from the back of a camel via
radio. Today Robida's dream is an every¬
day event with the camel replaced simply
by the mobile broadcasting units and staffs
of roving radio reporters (far right).
USIS photos
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
these frequencies provided the man at the receiver with
clearer and better listening and there was a decided
reduction in the possibility of interference from other
transmitters operating on or near the same frequency.
If very high frequency FM broadcasting could be
introduced wherever practicable throughout the world for
local broadcasting needs, as it is being done in some
countries in Europe, the medium waves could be made
available for national coverage and even intermediate
range international broadcasting. This in turn could free
many of the high frequencies, which are now being used
for national or medium range international broadcasting,
for their proper use as long-range services. The savings
that could result from such a procedure could relieve
much of the present pressure in the medium and high
frequency bands, thus contributing materially to solving
the frequency problem as a whole.
If broadcasting does not find a method of giving the
listener the service that he desires and deserves he may
turn to a competitor such as (wired broadcasting.
Basically, this service consists of picking up broadcast
programmes from a . central point or exchange, and
distributing them by wire to those subscribing to' the
system. The principal advantages claimed by the wire
broadcasters cover most of the situations where regular
The Unesco Courier. September 1959
broadcasters are falling in their duty to the listener.
There is little or no interference from other stations and
electrical apparatus, and the general cost to the subscriber
is low.
The great disadvantage of wired broadcasting is, of
course, that the listener has no say in the selection of
programmes and must take what the organization chooses
to give him. The man with the regular radio set, on the
other hand, has a much greater choice of local programmes
and if equipped with a high frequency band can roam
the ether to pick up broadcasts directly from other
countries. If broadcasters do not adopt the necessary
innovations to assure that radio remains an effective
means for the exchange of ideas, wired broadcasting may
become a serious competitor.
At this point a word is due about radio's new challenger,
television. Obviously if television is destined to replace
broadcasting in the near future there is less need to
spend the time and effort necessary to give the broad¬
casting a new lease on life. Although the experience
available to date is fragmentary, it is definitely reassuring
to radio. In the first place it has been found that in the
few countries where television coverage now is close to
equalling that of radio the purchase of radio sets has
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
RADIO CITY IN PARIS. A huge circular structure nearly 500 feet in diameter which is now rising on the right bank of the Seine
in West Paris will be the new headquarters of French radio. When completed it will have 15 special studios for musical, theatrical
and variety performances, five large halls for shows with live audiences (one hall will seat 900 people) ; a vast collection of books,
scores, recordings and other background and documentary material ; a central recording section ; two special halls fortelevised variety
programmes ; a special section for the production of cultural and artistic programmes intended for listeners outside France.
7
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
The world total of receiving-sets Is estimat¬
ed at over 350 million. These sets are
unevenly distributed, however. One half of
them are located on the North American
continent alone. Another third are distribut¬
ed throughout Europe, ' with the greatest
concentration In the West, and the remain¬
ing sixth are scattered over Asia, Africa and
Pictograph from
the Near East. The United States is In first
place both from the point of view of total
receivers (160 mllUon) and density (88 per
100 Inhabitants). Second place In total
number of receivers belongs to the U.S.S.B.
(33 million), although second place In density
goes to Canada with 56 receivers ' per 100
population. In contrast Ethiopia and Eritrea
Unesco's "Broadcasting Without Barriers," 1959.
have only 16,000 receivers for a population of
some 20 million or an average of 0.1 per 100
people. Even India with over a million recei¬
vers has an average of only 0.3 per 100 people.
Map above shows distribution of world's radio
receivers, each symbol representing one recei¬
ver per 100 Inhabitants. Boxed symbols
Indicate Increases between 1949 and 1956.
FREEDOM TO LISTEN
(Continued)
not declined but to the contrary has continued to increase
at a steady rate.
The obvious reason is that television's extra attraction,
the appeal to the visual, is also its greatest drawback.
Those people whose vocations demand visual con¬
centration cannot take advantage of television as they
can of broadcasting. Further, there seems to be a great
number of individuals who continue to prefer radio
because they believe it can do a better job in such fields
as news and music, or find that television is not
compatible with leisure pursuits such as reading.
There is also an economic factor that must not
be overlooked. Television is extremely expensive in
relation to broadcasting, as concerns both upkeep and
programming. In addition it is a voracious consumer of
talent. Underdeveloped countries and those areas where
the economy is weak will have to wait a very long time
indeed for the introduction of television, and the
possibility of achieving saturation on a level with broad¬
casting is exceedingly remote. There are also more
advanced countries, for example Norway, Australia, and
New Zealand, where geographical difficulties and
scattered populations will delay television expansion and
where' the final achievement of television coverage will be
measured not in years, but in decades.
Even where adequate coverage is achieved, it seems
unlikely that 24-hour programming, as is the case in
8
c
several large cities in the United States, or even
continuous 12-hour programming, will be practicable.
Where commercial television is not adopted, the European
plan of restricting television to the evening leisure hours,
with perhaps a few minutes of "telecasting" in the
morning or at noon, will probably toe continued.
Consequently, it seems clear that even where the-
authorities can provide for television coverage as
extensive as that of radio, and where the same number
of families have television sets, there still will remain an
audience sufficiently large to justify a continuing and
extensive radio service.
Although such a situation will most probably demand
some adjustment in programming and changes in
emphasis, radio will continue to be an essential medium
of information and entertainment. In the larger portion
of the World, on the other hand, where such an ideal
situation is still only in the dim future, radio will
continue to be the most important all-around medium of
mass communication.
If any conclusion can be drawn from an examination
of the situation of broadcasting today it is that broad¬
casting is one of the most important means of mass
communication at mankind's disposal and if it is to have
a future worthy of its potentialities positive action must
be taken by all concerned. It is everyone's responsibility
to see that broadcasting facilities, both transmitting and
receiving, are available to all. It is everyone's responsi¬
bility to see that the programmes that are offered contain
all that is necessary to provide the listener with means
of enriching his life. It does not follow, of course, that
the listener will always take advantage of the best in
broadcasting, but if he does not have access to radio, and
to a choice of good programmes, he is being denied the
basic right to listen. -<
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1959
TRAFFIC JAM
ON THE BROADCASTING BANDS
by Julian Behrstock
The African villager who joins his
neighbours to hear local broad¬
casts on the community set and
the uptown New Yorker who twirls
the dial of his high-powered short- .
wave receiver in a skyscraper apart¬
ment alike have a stake in a world
radio conference which opened in
Geneva, Switzerland, in August.
This conference, sponsored by the
International Telecommunication
Union (ITU), will gather together
government officials and radio broad¬
casters from 100 countries. During
four months in Geneva, they will
seek to hammer out agreement on
pressing problems affecting the role
of radio in the world today.
The problems concern both trans¬
mission and reception of broadcasts.
Competition between countries in
expanding their overseas broadcasting
services in recent years has hindered
agreement on an orderly system for
the international allocation of fre¬
quencies. Meanwhile, new stations
are being built, more powerful trans¬
mitters are coming into operation and
rival transmissions increase. Pirating
of frequencies and jamming add to
the difficulties of the listener.
Wanted ! 400 million sets
Aproblem of a different kind is
experienced by nearly 60 per cent
of the world's people, most of
them in Asia and Africa, who lack
efficient, low-cost receivers to pick up
even local broadcasts. Community
sets, inconvenient for many listeners
and often costly because of high
taxes, are the only means of reception
in many areas. Nearly 400 million
receivers would have to be mass-pro¬
duced to assure an individual set for
each family in the under-developed
countries (For one example see
"Saucepan Radio", page 260.
These will be among the questions
preoccupying delegates to the ITU's
Administrative Radio Conference, the
first such conference to be convened
in eight years. They are also a major
concern of Unesco, dedicated as it is
to promoting the use of broadcasting,
and all the other means of mass com¬
munication, for the free flow of
information and ideas.
Unesco has sent its Member States
a series of four proposals for possible
submission to the Radio Conference.
The principal proposal urges that
agreement be reached on a sound plan
for distribution of high frequencies
the frequencies used for long-distance
broadcasting. It suggests that proce¬
dures should be established by which
the ITU could assist radio services in
making more effective use of frequen¬
cies. Consultation with each other
through the ITU would enable them,
for example, to minimize the occur¬
rence of broadcasts at the same time
and on the same frequencies, which
results in little more than noise for
the listener.
The Geneva conference will mark
a further and perhaps decisive step
in an effort dating back more than
SO years to reach world agreement on
frequencies. Since 1928, when a first
international frequency list was drawn
up, a series of conferences has sought
to put a plan into effect. It became
progressively more difficult to cut up
the pie as governments made mount¬
ing requests based on expanding radio
services. Demands for high frequen¬
cies have been three times in excess
of available resources.
Today the. great majority of States
maintain international broadcasting
services beaming numerous program¬
mes daily on high 'frequencies to all
parts of the world. Despite the vast
expenditure of time, money and ef¬
fort, the audience remains small and
in some areas is numbered only in
thousands or even hundreds of listen¬
ers. Broadcasters themselves will be
the first to acknowledge the crying
need for agreement on frequencies,
schedules and programme exchanges.
Unesco has drawn these points to
the attention of its Member States in
urging remedial action at the Geneva
Conference. Such action, says Unesco,
would help broadcasting achieve "its
great potentialities as a vehicle for
the exchange of information and ideas
throughout the world".
A second Unesco proposal deals
with the interference hindering even
local reception of broadcasts in some
areas as a result of overcrowding of
the low and medium frequency bands^
The experience of a number of coun¬
tries, particularly in Europe and North
America, has shown that frequency
modulation (FM) broadcasting in the
very high frequency band may be
expanded for use in local broadcast¬
ing, relieving much of the burden in
other bands. It provides the listener,
moreover, with a high quality signal
relatively free from interference.
Unesco recommends that FM be in¬
troduced more widely.
Remove crushing taxes
The widespread need for radio
receivers in the under-developed
countries is the object of a third
proposal. It suggests that the ITU
and Unesco explore the possibility of
designing a robust, wideband, inex¬
pensive receiver, with standardized
parts. A study would be made of the
feasibility of pooling markets to en¬
courage mass production of receivers
of this kind.
Even in some of the more advanced
countries, radio receivers are still a
luxury, due to their high original
price, cost of upkeep and the imposi¬
tion of import duties and sales taxes.
A Unesco survey shows that some
85 countries levy import duties on
radio receivers; these charges often
represent 50 per cent or more of the
value. Reduction of duties and sales
taxes is accordingly suggested in
Unesco's fourth proposal.
Indications are that all four pro¬
posals suggested by Unesco will be
sponsored by governments and sub¬
mitted to the Administrative Radio
Conference. Their adoption would
help to improve conditions for both
transmission and reception of radio
broadcasts, making ' this a ' better
medium to entertain, enlighten and
lirik people all over the world.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
RADIO HAMS':
AN INTERNATIONAL FAMILY
by
David
Gunston
In almost every corner of the globe.
In living rooms, dens, attics and special
"shacks", 260,000 radio "hams" main¬
tain a vast network of personal contact
by voice or Morse Code. Most amateurs
use self-built apparatus costing from £25
to £50. Right, a very elaborate set-up
operated by a U.S. amateur in California.
J. B. Knight Jnr., U.S.A.
USIS
ALL AGES AND PROFESSIONS are numbered among the more than one quarter of a million amateur radio operators scattered
over the globe. Above, Leonard Ross of Tujunga, California, who was believed to be the youngest ham operator in the world when
in 1953 he passed the General Licence class test at the age of eight. To pass the test he had to demonstrate his ability to send and
to receive at least 13 words of Morse code a minute. Photo shows Leonard, aged eight, operating the equipment in his radio shack.
I0
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
No study of communications in the modern world
would be complete without an account of the unique
contribution of amateur short-wave radio enthu¬
siasts, or "hams," |who form a great army of private indi¬
vidual communicators. In almost every corner of the globe,
in living-rooms, dens, offices, cabins, attics, cubby-holes
and outbuildings (all universally referred to as "shacks")
some 260,000 licensed operators maintain a vast network
of personal contact by voice or Morse Code signals that
is entirely free from political or propaganda influence.
Daily, hourly in fact, "hams" are in touch with fellow-
enthusiasts of both sexes and all ages in countries near
and far. It is an achievement without parallel, impossible
to envisage even fifty years ago, and the contribution
towards fuller international understanding and goodwill
cannot be measured.
1 Iff
^9^ . < ^
ft , «L "fl^S X
*
Official Soviet photo
SOVIET «HAMS' in 1958 received and sent 854,000 cards, known
as QSL-cards, which are the amateurs' method of confirming the estab¬
lishment of two-way radio contact. Here two novice "hams" at the
Pedagogical Institutein Karaganda, Soviet Kazakhstan, are seen assemb¬
ling one of ten ultra-short wave transmitters which they are building
as a gift for rural schools. They are members of a special radio club
where they study the international "ham language", operate their radio
station and join in contests and shows of self-built radio equipment.
Amateur radio and every "ham" will stress the - vital
importance of his status is primarily a hobby,
but as such must be the only one duly defined by an
international treaty drawn up by 90 nations. At the
International Radio-Communications Conference held in
Atlantic City, U.S.A., in 1947, it was defined as: "A service
of self-training, intercommunication and technical inves¬
tigations carried on by duly authorised persons interested
The Unesco Courier. S-eptember 1959
in radio technique solely with a personal aim and without
pecuniary interest."
Most amateurs, however, would probably define their
compelling interest more simply as "the practice of two-
way, short-wave radio-communication, not as a business
or means of profit, but as a spare-time hobby pursued for
the pleasure to be derived from an interest in radio tech¬
nique and construction, and for the ensuing friendships
with like-minded individuals throughout the world."
Strictly speaking, the description "amateur" in this
connexion is not applied to any neophyte or dabbler with
radio apparatus, but only to duly licensed transmitting
operators whose stations, or "rigs", have the official
sanction of their respective governments. Whatever
the connotation in other spheres, in the field of
amateur radio the prefix is a mark of distinction, superior
knowledge and accomplishment, and very much a cachet
to be achieved. In addition, there are large numbers of
persons with no desire to become transmitters operating
under official license, but who follow the hobby purely as
listeners using short-wave receivers. They are known in
"ham" parlance as SWLs (short-wave listeners).
The pursuit is just about as old as radio itself. It had
its beginnings in the very earliest days of the invention.
Around the turn of the century, when vague details of
the newly-born art of wireless telegraphy, as it was then
known, began to filter through to scientific journals and
beyond, technically-inclined persons began to feel the
first glimmerings of the very real fascination that now
absorbs the attention of over a quarter-of-a-million
people.
Marconi considered himself an amateur, and when he
finally succeeded in spanning the Atlantic Ocean by radio
in 1901, small groups of youthful experimenters in many
countries resolved to find out for themselves how it was
done. Initially, their work was crude and limited: they
were at first fortunate in sending and receiving wireless
waves over distances of a few feet. Gradually the range
increased to yards and eventually to many miles as new
detectors, new circuits and new aerial antennae were
constantly tried out.
Transmitting to the moon
Amateur radio began long before there were short¬
wave bands fitted as a matter of course to ordinary
radio sets, indeed long before radio receivers were
widely known at all. Oddly enough, the first '"hams" were
eventually to prove that messages could be sent and
received all over the world on low power by using the very
short waves which the experts said were useless, and the
period 1921-1926 witnessed epoch-maMng discoveries in
the field.
Amateurs In many scattered countries demonstrated
that high-powered transmitters such as are used for
normal daily long-and medium-wave transmissions or
programme broadcasts were unnecessary when wave¬
lengths below 100 metres were adapted for world-wide
communication. This brought the hobby within the scope
and purse of ordinary folk everywhere, and although
large sums can easily be spent on short-wave radio equip¬
ment, most of today's amateurs operate on apparatus
they have built themselves costing less than £50, whilst
there are many small but complete and reasonably effi¬
cient stations constructed by their owners for half of
this figure or even less.
Naturally, keen operators may spend more than these
figures renovating or extending their equipment, and the
annual turnover in apparatus, though not essential, may
be large. Surveys show that whereas about 80% of ama¬
teur transmitters are home-made and the rest are bought
ready-made, the reverse is the case with receivers. This
is because the modern superheterodyne radio receiver is
such a complex and precise instrument that elaborate
factory equipment is needed to construct it. So receiving
sets are usually cheaper and better-made than those built
at home, whereas transmitters are costly when made
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
RADIO HAMS'
(Continued)
commercially, and are best modified to local needs when
built by the operator himself.
However, apart from practical and financial considera¬
tions, many "hams" have no wish to deprive themselves
of the sheer creative delight of seeing the fruits of their
own hands perform the continuing miracle of transport¬
ing their voice or code signals across enormous distances
and bringing back the immediate reply of a kindred spirit
perhaps on the other side of the globe.
Nowadays the range of Well-equipped amateurs is
limited only by the dimensions of the earth, and in fact
not always by that. Several "hams" have managed to
transmit signals to the moon and record their reflection,
whilst many operators have tracked the various earth
satellites, and continue to work as monitoring stations
for this purpose. Naturally, conditions vary with the
seasons, the weather, the time of day and sunspot in¬
fluence, but to talk with friends many thousands of miles
away is a daily occurrence for all "hams'". The most im¬
portant factor in securing good results is the choice of
the most suitable frequency band for transmissions, for
each wavelength has its own peculiar properties.
Although nowadays many official broadcasting stations
as well as ships and aircraft use the short-waves, almost
every country by international agreement allots ama¬
teurs certain fixed bands, outside the limits of which
they must not operate. However, every amateur is allowed
at any time to choose the band he wishes to use and he
is also allowed (subject to certain band-planning schemes
designed for the general good) to select his own fre¬
quency and to change it when he desires.
' DX hounds' & 'ragchewers'
This is an important point on the more crowded short¬
wave-bands since it allows the keen amateur to
search for and then use a clear frequency (or
"channel") , then should heavy interference be experienc¬
ed later, to move immediately to another position on the
same band. With code signalling, it enables what is known
as "Singlechannel operation" (with both stations on
approximately the same frequency) to be used. Every
short wave-band has its limitations and problems, but
while they are never too great to allow free operation,
the amateur has always some new field to conquer.
Most "'hams" have equipment that will operate by voice
or by Morse Code, with roughly half the messages' being
transmitted by each method. Code work requires less
complex apparatus and may include the use of specialized
codes like the International Q Code which reduce the
language barrier. All licensed amateurs have to prove
their proficiency in Morse Code before they are allowed
fo operate. Indeed, no one in any country can expect
to.secure his amateur license without preliminary study,
application and practice, though self-training is not
difficult.
Most countries insist on written as well as practical
tests, and there is usually an age-limit of 16 or 18, though
several countries have reduced this to 14 or even 12. The
United States, Japan, Ireland and Israel are noteworthy
exceptions to this rule, fixing no age limit. Again, most
but not all countries insist on their operators possessing
citizenship: Germany, Finland, Morocco and Chile being
among the exceptions here.
How many "hams" are there in action today? The Am¬
erican Radio Relay League, largest member-body of the
International Amateur Radio Union, currently estimates
that there are rising 260,000 of them, of which 190,000 are
in the United States and its possessions. There are at
least a few amateurs in every country, and the countries
of Eastern Europe and the U.S.S.R. are no exceptions.
Amateur radio ignores the existence of frontiers and
though the fact is not generally realized, there are today
perhaps 10,000 "hams" in the Soviet Union, freely communi¬
cating iwith the rest of the world. Only in the reluctance
of national amateur radio societies in the Communist
countries to join the IARU does the shadow of politics
fall across the encouraging picture. At present, only the
Polish and Yugoslav societies are members. Czechoslo¬
vakia was formely a member, but resigned some years ago
because the IARU headquarters in the U.S.A. refused to
print the Stockholm "Peace Appeal" in their Calendar
Bulletin.
At present, some 54 countries have their own member-
societies affiliated to the International Amateur Radio
Union, with three others under consideration. India is
a particularly welcome new admission, with about 200
operators, while other representative countries (with
approximate number of amateurs) are: France, 2,800
Brazil, 9,000; Poland,' 250; South Africa, 2,000; Cuba, 900
Mexico, 900; Venezuela, 320; Canada, 8,000; Japan, 5,200
HAM ON WHEELS. More and
more amateur radio enthusiasts are
turning their automobiles into
mobile radio stations' by installing
equipment like that shown below.
Right, Canadian radio" "ham" ope¬
rates a short-wave mobile unit. In
Britain too, aerials like the one on
the rear of this car are becoming a
familiar sight. Amateur station
number is carried on bumper bar.
Photos T. Holloway, England
Great Britain, 8,500; Yugoslavia, 300; Spain, 830 and Ger¬
many, 5,000. In addition to these, there are organized
groups of amateurs in such widely-separated places as
Hong Kong, the Philippines, Austria, Costa Rica, Iceland,
Peru, Syria, Uruguay, Malaya, Colombia, Burma, Ecuador,
Finland, Australia and the Belgian Congo.
To the outsider, the amateur radio movement would
seem to be a particularly well-organized one, with flourish¬
ing if small national societies (all distinguished, in true
amateur radio fashion, by their initialsPZK (Poland),
EDR (Denmark), USKA (Switzerland), etc.in almost all
countries. Banded together into the well-organized IARU
they seek continual improvement in "hams'" relations with
their governments, arrange international agreements
affecting radio communications and in the words of the
IARU's Constitution, "'the encouragement of international
fraternalism". International Conferences have in fact
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
been successfully held in Madrid (1932), Cairo (1939),
Atlantic City (1947) and the next World Radio (Interna¬
tional Telecommunications Union) Conference is due to
be held at Geneva in the summer and autumn of this year.
But what, on the personal level, of the "hams" them¬
selves? What do they talk about, and how do they
contribute towards international understanding? Most
licence regulations expressly forbid the dissemination of
any messages of political, religious or commercial content,
leaving the amateur free to talk on personal and technical
matters to his heart's content. In actual fact, innume¬
rable individual topics are daily discussed over the ether,
with radio equipment and performance easily the most
popular!
Despite its high degree of specialization, amateur radio
consists of many phases of activity. An experimenter
will chat about his "rig" and compare endless notes with
others. A "DX hound" (DX meaning long-distance) is
a kind of angler of the ether, always hoping to pick up
some rare or remote station in another part of the world.
A "ragchewer", or born gossip, is Content to talk for hours
on end about his country and home, the weather, his
friends, his fellow-amateurs and the like. A "trafflc-
handlei" will spend much of his time at his station in
the clear service of others, relaying messages free of
charge for .the general public, simulating a regular com¬
munications system with national trunk lines and feeder
networks for possible emergency need, though all ama¬
teurs rise to the occasion when difficulties or disasters
occur.
Wherever there is a large-scale natural or man-made
disaster, with the frequent disabling of telephone and
commercial radio systems, amateurs step into the breach
to provide substitute communication links to the affected
areas. For example, an earthquake may cut off local
rescue teams from the outside! world, to which they can
be speedily linked by radio "hams", or in cases of fire or
The Unesco Courier. September 1959
explosion nearby amateurs can direct calls for help swiftly
to the right quarters when other means of communication
are out of action. This actually happened In the Texas
City disaster of 1947 when, had it not been for radio
amateurs, communication links would have been non¬
existent and rescue work gravely delayed. In the disas¬
trous floods in Eastern England in January and February
1953, '"hams" set up an emergency network which operated
continuously in conjunction' with the police and ambu¬
lance services.
Many "hams" in Europe, South Africa and America have
assisted expeditions and similar ventures by providing
constant radio links. The famous Kon-Tiki expedition
of Thor Heyerdahl was In regular contact with amateurs
in many countries as it drifted across the Pacific, while
more recent Arctic and Antarctic teams have benefited
not only by radio links provided by amateurs, but by the
regular relaying to their distant outposts of personal
messages from the homes of the men themselves.
Many others make a special point of relaying such
messages at fixed times to servicemen of their country
stationed in remote places, even the North Pole. Eighteen-
year-old Julius Madey, of New Jersey, U.S.A., winner of
the 1958 General Electric Edison Radio Amateur Award,
was cited for relaying more than 12,000 messages for
American servicemen at isolated Antarctic, Arctic and
South Pacific posts, and once through his station a young
mother announced the birth of her baby directly from
her hospital bed to her husband in Antarctica. Another
American amateur who was also specially commended
recently for his public services was 54-year-old Kenneth
M. Blaney of Sacramento, California, who spends twelve
hours a day handling messages and recording important
data on the Explorer satellites.
Amateurs win a race for life
When the inspired French film "Race for Life" (Si
tous les gars du monde...), which received the Bri¬
tish Film Academy United Nations Award for 1957,
was released, its story of help provided in a case of sick¬
ness at sea by a chain of "hams" all over the world, bring¬
ing an injection serum to the North Atlantic by means of
messages relayed via Togoland, Paris, Munich, East Ber¬
lin and Norway, Was viewed by many critics with scepti¬
cism.
It provided, in fact, a typical instance of just how ama¬
teurs can and do provide help in emergencies, and was
based on actual occurrences. Furthermore, whilst making
the film, director Christian Jaque was personally involved
,in a like case, wherein a French '"ham" picked up an
urgent call sent out by two amateurs in Brazil. They
were sending out a call for information on the correct
dosage of a new antidote not then in general use they
had received from Peru. Within the hour, the details from
Paris were in the hands of the Peruvian doctor.
Many other amateurs assist their governments in
service and civil defence work, notably the Military Ama¬
teur Radio System in the U.S.A. (MARS), which provides
a nationwide communications network consisting entirely
of amateurs upon which the services can rely in an emer¬
gency. Some "hams" aid coastguards, police and weather
forecasters, report on traffic problems, speed the rescue
of men from wrecked ships and aircraft, even assist in
the training of young people and the blind in electronics.
In addition to these practical services, amateurs
constantly further the development of the art and science
of radio by their experiments and observations. Being
usually unencumbered with ponderous knowledge, they
sometimes get to the heart of a technical problem quicker
than the professionals, while advances in many fields
of electronics, radar and long-distance radiotelegraphy
have originated in "'shacks'" all over the world.
From the schoolboy in Chile and the mining engineer
in Australia to the missionary in Samoa and the student
in Lithuania, the growing army of "'hams" is a truly
dedicated group with a spirit of human service hard to
equal.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
INTO OUTER SPACE
ON RADIO WAVES
by Werner Buedeler
Fellow of the Royal Astronomical Society
Only for the past thirty years have astronomers known
that radio waves, one of man's most useful servants
on earth, are being created within stars and in
inter-stellar space as well. Since the end of the Second
World War, however, these "messages" from outer space
have been recorded and scientifically evaluated. In this
way, a new science radio-astronomy has come into
being.
In the same way that the ordinary astronomer observes
the stars through his telescope, the radio astronomer lis¬
tens to strange sounds giving him information about elec¬
tronic processes in the solar corona (that is, the outer
region of the sun), invisible phenomena in the centre of
our own galaxy, and the expansion of the universe. Spe¬
cial receiving antennae, occasionally of tremendous, size,
have been constructed in order to pick up the faintest
noise from cosmic space.
Radio astronomers have obtained such a wealth of new
information in recent years that radio telescopes have
now become almost standard equipment in many obser¬
vatories. Radio-astronomy has enabled scientists to disco¬
ver colliding galaxies in space and the remains of super-
novae which exploded thousands of years ago. By carefully
recording cosmic noise (the name now given to radio
signals from outer space) they can trace interstellar
clouds of hydrogen, masses of this lightest of all ele¬
ments which are distributed among the stars. Recording
the electromagnetic or radio waves "broadcast" by
interstellar hydrogen on a precise wavelength (21.1 cen¬
timetres) has enabled astronomers to prove that our
own Miliky Way has spiral arms like those which other
galaxies in space Were already ¡known to possess. Today,
radio-astronomy is one of science's most flourishing and
exciting fields.
Photos USIS
EAR ON THE UNIVERSE. Giant antenna (right)
is one of two 90-feet diameter saucer-shaped
"ears" which work as a team at a California obser¬
vatory, picking up waves from radio-active stars
up to 30,000 million light years away. Some day
they may be used to track and guide space ships
as they speed far out into the universe. Above,
radio signals from the "Explorer" satellite launched
in January last year. This is how the first few seconds
of its flight were recorded on the graph of an oscillo¬
scope at one of a network of I 0 powerful Minitrack
radio stations in Australia, Cuba and the U.S.A.
set up to receive the satellite's radio messages
which it relayed during its globe-circling trips.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1959
First, astronomers discovered radio communication in
space (it does not consist of "messages" sent by living
beings on other planets but of crackling sounds and
noises relayed back and forth between atoms) . Then they
tried to send man-made radio waves into space. Shortly
after the Second World War, they succeeded in estab¬
lishing radio contact with our nearest cosmic neighbour,
the moon. With the help of a powerful transmitter, a
radar signal was flashed toward the moon and received
almost three seconds later when it returned to earth after
bouncing off the moon's surface. This confirmed earlier
calculations of the distance of the moon from the earth
(it averages 238,600 miles). As We know that the speed
of all electromagnetic waves whether light waves, radio
Waves or X-rays is always 186,000 miles per second, it
was an easy task to calculate this distance on the basis
of the time which elapsed between the broadcasting of the
radar signal and its return to earth.
Making radar contacts with the moon is almost routine
today and, like radio astronomy, it tells us more about
this body in space which man himself might reach in the
near future. In the same way, astronomers have tried to
"'contact" the sun, Mars and Venus.
Radio waves in outer space came into their true glory,
however, with rocket exploration of the upper atmosphere
and the launching of artificial earth satellites. Here, man
was able to send a transmitter into space for the first
time and to receive its messages. The Sputniks, and the
Explorer, Vanguard, Discoverer and Score satellites all had
their own special transmitters telemetering back to earth
information on physical phenomena in space such as
temperature and intensity of cosmic rays and ultraviolet
sclar radiation (which does not penetrate to the ground) .
A wealth of new information was gained.
Then, with the launching of the Score satellite roaring
into space aboard a 70-foot Atlas rocket weighing 115 tons,
a human voice recorded on a tape (the voice of the Pre¬
sident of the United States) was transmitted back to
earth from the world beyond. Simple as it may look to
the layman, this experiment answered many questions
for scientists and spurred thinking in terms of true com¬
munication satellites.
A few years ago, an American telephone company had
already calculated that within the near future, communi¬
cation satellites used as relays for transatlantic telephone
calls and world-wide television service would be feasible,
even from a business viewpoint. Three such satellites
circling the earth in a 24-hour orbit (this means that
they would need 24 hours to go around the world and thus
they would appear stationary from' any given point on
earth if they orbited in a west-east direction) could trans¬
mit a television programme to any part of the world.
Very-high-frequency radio, now limited by the short
range of VHF Waves requiring costly relay stations every
30 miles, Would also benefit from such satellites.
The art of communication in space is still young and
We have much to learn before man can flash messages
from one side df the globe to the other via a space satel¬
lite or even a relay station on the surface of the moon
But the many successes which have been achieved in so
short a period of time prove that communication is no
longer restricted to our own planet.
THE TALKATIVE SATELLITE
Running on solar batteries, the radio transmitter of
"'Vanguard I" is- still functioning a year after it was
launched and it has created a rather unusual problem for
American scientists: they just don't know how to make it
shut up. Dr. John Hagen, director of the Vanguard rocket
programme, has commented that there is no way of
stopping it and it is now interfering with the transmission of
radio messages from other satellites. American scientists
are now looking for a way of turning off the sun-powered
radios aboard the Vanguards. Future satellites may be
equipped with remote control off-on switches.
CALLING THE FLYING DOCTOR. In the vast open spaces
of Australia radio is a vital link for people who live beyond
the reach of the ordinary medical services. Thanks to radio
links between isolated homesteads and the centres run by
the Royal Flying Doctor Service, people in practically every
area of the continent can ask for advice and obtain treatment.
Above, farmer's wife takes down the doctor's instructions
by radio. Pedal-operated generators are now generally replaced
by batteries. Australia also has its "schools of the air" for
children living far from town. The classroom of the two boys
(below) is their living-room with receiver-transmitter. They
live on an isolated sheep station and can talk to their teacher
miles away as easily as if she were in the same room.
Photos Australian News and Information Bureau
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
PIONEERS OF RADIO
The story of radio is in no way the result of one man's genius.
Rather it is the accumulation of a whole series of discoveries of
scientists, engineers, physicists, chemists and philosophers of many
nations, who in exploring the secrets of nature made electricity and
electromagnetism accessible to mankind. On these pages we present
only a few .of the pioneers of radio.
heikrich hertz, German physi¬
cist and electrical engineer (1857-
1894) discovered electromagnetic
waves which are the basis of
modern radio, television and ra¬
dar. Studying cathode rays,
Hertz proved that these would
penetrate thin sheets of metal.
Edouard BRANLY, French
physicist (1844-1940). His ad¬
vance research led to the in¬
vention of the "'Coherer" unit
in 1890. The Coherer. made
wireless telegraphy, as it is
known, possible.
Nikola tesla (1857-1943), naturali¬
zed American of Yugoslav origin. Bet¬
ween 1890-93 he devised a system of
wireless communication using high
frequency alternators to produce long
waves, to light lamps and send signals
at a distance. He used metallic pla¬
ques to form condensers for reception.
He invented a system of transmitting
electric power without wires, the Tesla
coil and condensers vital to radio.
lee de forest (1873), American
engineer who invented the vacuum
tube in 1906 an invention con¬
sidered as great as radio itself.'
By amplifying a weak current, it
made it possible to magnify radio
waves to audibility and to receive
TV and radar images. It opened
the way to the whole field of
electronics. rca
W. H. BRATTAIN (1902) AND J. BARDEN (1908)
American physicists who won
1956 Nobel Prize for Physics
for their invention of the tran¬
sistor in 1948. Rapidly replac¬
ing the vacuum tube, the tiny
amplifier uses differences in
atomic structure to - create an
electron current using a hun¬
dred thousandth of the power
needed by the tube.
Aleksander Popov
This year the Soviet Union
celebrates the centenary of the
birth of Aleksander Popov (1859-
1905) whom it considers the in¬
ventor of the first radio receiver.
In May 1895, Popov demons¬
trated before the St. Petersburg
Physical Society an apparatus for
receiving electrical air waves,
then known as hertzian waves.
Later the same year he created a
"lightning recorder" to detect
and register the discharges of
electrical storms at some distance.
Popov's experiments were inspired
by the works of Faraday, Maxwell, Lodge, Hertz, Branly
and Tesla. He predicted that if man could reproduce
an electrical disturbance of the type emitted by electrical
storms he might be able to communicate across space.
Popov's first radio transmission took place in 1896.
In November 1899, a Russian warship, the General-
Admiral Apraksin ran aground near Gogland Island.
To facilitate salvage operations, Popov and his assistant
P. Rybkin were called upon to set up radio communi¬
cation between the island and the stricken vessel. Early
the next year, a wireless telegraph circuit was put into
operation. Photos show, left, the radio statiorg on
, Gogland Island; right, battleship Apraksin aground off
the island, and behind it the ice-breaker Yormak.
<
Geni¿ü3J50
Bell Telephone Laboratories
The stamps on these pages are reproduced from Radio Philatelia by
Herbert Rosen, a history of telecommunications told through stamps
'publisher : Audiomaster Corp., 17 East 45th Street, New York 17. $2.00).
POSTE ITALIANE
It was Guglielmo Marconi
(1874-1937) who took out the
first patent ever granted for a
system of wireless telegraphy, in
June 1896, and who was the first
to use and develop radio commu¬
nication on a commercial basis.
Marconi's experiments had begun
several years before in the vege¬
table garden of his father's farm
in Italy, where as a boy of 20 he
watched experiments by Prof. A.
Righi with electromagnetic waves.
After_ unsuccessfully attempting
to interest the Italian Govt, in his work, Marconi reached
England in 1896.. His apparatus combined an improved
Righi oscillator and Sir Oliver Lodge receiver circuit
with a Morse Apparatus and a 30-metre antenna. In
July 1896 he succeeded in sending and receiving a signal
over a distance of 100 yards, later between two land
stations, and from ship to shore and shore to ship, then
between two ships at sea. In 1898, Marconi bridged the
English Channel connecting England and France and in
1901 spanned the .Atlantic between Newfoundland and
England. Photos show kite-aerial he raised in New¬
foundland (right), and radio operators with early Marconi
installation on board a British lightship in 1898 (left).
The wireless was used to bring help to the ship when
it was damaged in a storm a month later and when it
was rammed by a freighter in a fog, thus convincing
shipping people of the. value of Tadio.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1959
Officia! Soviet photos Official Soviet photos
Marconi Wireless Telegraphy Co. Ltd COI. London
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
IS
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1959
SNAPS FROM THE
FAMILY ALBUM
1 In the 1 920's .when broadcasting
'" was taking its first hesitant steps,
this photograph was "hot news". It shows
Rosine, one of the celebrated Dolly
Sisters, dancing on a French beach to the
rhythm of music picked up from the ether.
© Vlollat, Paris
0 A machine for sending wireless tele-
L' graphy messages was installed on the
top platform of the Eiffel Tower on July
29, I 898, and experimental transmissions
were made. In the same year, the
Frenchmen Ducretet and Roger estab¬
lished communication across Paris from
the Eiffel Tower summit to the Panthéon.
, © Vlollat, Paris
0 Dame Nellie Melba, the famous Aus-
"* tralian soprano, sings into a micro¬
phone set up at Marconi's works on June
15, 1920. This was the occasion of first
broadcast programme of public enter¬
tainment to be presented in Great Britain.
Marconi International Communication Co. Ltd.
AtL Microphones were massive, box-
* J' like'affairs when these photos of the
cast in a radio play were taken in the
studios of the British Broadcasting Cor¬
poration in 1928. The latest thing in
feminine headgear at the time was the
toqueworn well down over the ears.
BBC photo»
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
THE LIGHT
PROGRAMME
by Sine
*
c£> -' ®*L * ear i--T rfiv-.- "<£
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1959
THE COBRA
AND THE
ELECTRONIC
CHARMER
One of the most feared of all poisonous snakes is
the cobra, the "hooded terror" of India; whose bite
spells cartain death. Each year these creatures
are responsible for most of the 20,000 deaths caused
by snake bites on the Indian sub-continent, and the
bite of the king cobra has been known to kijl an
elephant in three hours. Yet despite all the dangers
associated with it, the cobra is the favourite of
snake charmers. A few simple notes played on the
charmer's flute and the cobra rears itself up, its
curious hood extended, and begins to sway in time
to the music. Some people believe that snake
charmers possess secret powers and that it is not
the music that captivates the cobra but rather the
charmer's motions with his .flute. A recent expe¬
riment in India, however, showed that once a cobra
is trained to dance to the music of a flute, it will
do so even when the flute-playing charmer is replac¬
ed by an electronic instrument. A Swiss reporter-
photographer, Pierre Pittet, recorded the flute-
playing of a snake charmer and then played the
recording in front of a cobra. As these photos show,
the reptile immediately rose up and went into its
dance... it was hearing "its master's voice".
Photos © Pierre André Pittet, Geneva
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
RADIOS
ON THE RIVER THAMES
A great step forward in the
movement that is going on all
over the world to speed up the
turn-round of shipping in the ports
has been, taken with the opening in
recent weeks of a new radio infor¬
mation service at Gravesend, on the
River Thames, the gateway to the
Port of London. This service which
has been designed to give shipmasters
and pilots every piece of information
that they may, need about the state
of the river at any hour of the day
or night, and particularly in fog, has
been made possible by the conclusion
at the Hague in 1957 of the Inter-X
national Maritime Agreement on
the allocation of V.H.F. frequency
modulated wavebands.
Gateway to the
port of London
The Thames, with one of the
longest systems of docks and
wharves in the world, traces a
winding course of fifty miles from its
seaward end to London Bridge which
is the upper limit of navigation for
22
practically all seagoing vessels. Gra¬
vesend, twenty-four miles- up-river
from the sea is a focal; point for all
shipping bound to or from the docks
because it is here that vessels have to
pass the customs and the port health
authorities and it is here, too, that
they pick up or put ashore their sea
or river pilots. The channel at Grave¬
send is under half-a-mile Wide and it
has to carry a tremendous volume
of shipping. As many as eighty ves¬
sels or more may pass through on a
single tide.
For just over ten years the Port of
London Authority, which controls the
tidal sections of the river, had been
using amplitude modulated radio
equipment to give information to
ships but, With the conclusion of the
Hague agreement on V.H.F. fre¬
quencies a very much more efficient
service giving better quality of speech
together with freedom from noise and
interference became possible and as
a result the new Thames Navigation
Service, which may well become a
prototype for port radio services all
over the world, was brought into
being. Its facilities are available
free to any ship equipped with even
very simple V.H.F. radio equipment.
© Camera Press, London
This ' equipment is not limited . in its
uses to the Thames service; it can
equally well be used with radio services
already established or planned for
ports in other countries, and, of
course, it can be used, too, for direct
speech between ship and ship at sea,
and for public telephone corres¬
pondence ashore.
Panoramic view of
all river traffic
The great advance that has been
made in planning and equip¬
ping the Gravesend station is
that facilities for the reception of in¬
formation, for broadcasting it to
ships and for a radar scan of some
of the busiest and most important
sectors of the river, are all housed in
one very carefully designed operation
room. Because the 'Trinity House
pilots who take ships up the river to
the docks or down it to the sea are
as much concerned as the ships' cap¬
tains themselves with the state of the
channel and the traffic on it, the
Navigation Service building has been
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1959
erected close alongside the pilot pier
and there is direct access for pilots
from their own rooms on the pier to
a gallery in the operation room
where they can study a panoramic
plan of the whole river from London
to the sea.
This panoramic plan occupies the
whole of one wall of the operation
room and below it is the radar scan
which keeps watch over Gravesend
reach at night and in fog. Eventually
further radar scans will be installed
so that thirty-one miles of the river
can be kept constantly under watch.
The operation room is linked by
telephone to the various docks from
which programmes of the docking
and undocking of ships are received.
These programmes are noted along¬
side the river plan. Constant radio
touch is kept, too, with the Port of
London Authority's launches which
report movements, of shipping in¬
wards and outwards and other
essential information such as where
vessels are anchored in the river,
where dredgers are working, the
position of wrecks, or where pile-
driving operations are being carried
out.
Robot 'watchdogs' of
tide and visibility
All this information is noted on
the illuminated river plan. The
state of the tide is noted, too, as
well as the degree of visibility at
various points. Eventually data about
tide and visibility which are at pre¬
sent received by telephone, will be
automatically relayed by radio link
from distant recording instruments
which will keep it up to date from
moment to moment.
Once in every half-hour, day and
night, the duty officer working
from the information on the plan
prepares and broadcasts a short
bulletin on the state of the river. For
the remainder of the time the service
is available at any minute to answer
queries from any ship that calls it up.
The caller makes contact on the
international "calling and safety"
channel and he is then directed to
switch over to one of the four radio
channels at present in use, two for
the western and two for the eastern
section of the river. Eventually the
number of channels will be extended
to three for each section.
A tanker, for instance, which is
deeply laden, may want information
that is accurate to within inches of
the depth of- water at one of the oil
jetties lower down the river. The
Gravesend radio service can give it
within a few moments. Or, again, a
steamer moving in poor visibility or
at night, may pick up on its radar
The port of London can boast a unique radio
Information service for shipping which may
well become a prototype for port radio ser¬
vices all over the world. A special operations
room has been built where movements of all
traffic are plotted by radar (above) on a huge
panoramic wall plan (left) of the whole river
from London to the sea. Using VHF radio
equipment, officers (below) flash vital infor¬
mation to all vessels on the Thames (opposite).
) A' Court Photographs, London
Photos <C) Fox Photos. London
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
RADIO'S MAGIC EYE
(Continued)
another vessel lying on its course
ahead. Naturally the captain is
anxious to know whether the vessel
seen on his radar is moving or not,
and he is anxious to know it quickly.
He can call the Information Service
and at once- the radar scan at
Gravesend picks up the two vessels
and makes a check. Within a very
short time the duty officer is able to
tell the enquirer whether the ship he
has spotted is moving or at anchor.
The radar scan can also show the
line along which a particular vessel
is moving and give an indication
whether it is heading clear of any
obstacle.
The Information Service is linked
direct by teleprinter with the Port of
London's head office and movements
of shipping are relayed immediately
they occur. This is likely to result
in making the publication of ship
movements both simpler and quicker.
Another function of the Service is to
pass information at once to customs
and port health authorities as well
as to the pilots waiting to take vessels
in and out.
Pioneering for better
port radio services
It is perhaps here as much as in
the giving of information to the
ships themselves that the Ser¬
vice will help to speed up movement.
On a busy tide there may be several
ships awaiting clearance at the same
time, with more following up astern
of them. Anything that enables
customs officers and port doctors, as
well as the waiting tugmasters, to
get on with their work smoothly and
quickly is bound to assist in keeping
all traffic on the move.
As yet the Thames Navigation
Service is only at its beginnings. It
has been planned for flexible develop¬
ment and very full statistics are
being collected of the ways in which
it is used. These will give a
pointer to future modifications and
extensions. In setting up this service
the Port of London Authority is
pioneering new ground and looking to
the future. At the present time
comparatively few ships out of the
whole of the world's tonnage that
uses the Thames are equipped with
the necessary V.H.F. radio sets, but
the expectation and the belief is that
once the facilities that are available
become more widely known installa¬
tions will be made on a rapidly
growing number of vessels belonging
to many nations of the world.
UpenBaar Kunstbezit.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1959
Openbaar Kunstbezit.
THE MUSEUM INSIDE
THE RECEIVER
Every Monday after the evening
meal, thousands of people in the
Netherlands turn on the radio
and go on a guided tour of some of
the art masterpieces in their country's
great museums. The guides on these
broadcast tours are prominent art
connoisseurs, museum directors or
art historians who tell listeners about
the origin of a particular work, the
significance of its composition and
beauty, about the artist who made it,
its period of origin and so on.
Gathered around the radio, families
(left) follow the talks with the aid
of a reproduction of the work being
presented. Well over 90,000 people
joined the "art by radio" club last
year. In return for a small fee sub¬
scribers receive in advance four
reproductions of the works to be
discussed every month colour repro¬
ductions of paintings,, reproductions
in black and white of drawings,
sculpture, graphic wofk and an
occasional example of applied work.
Works are selected to offer charac¬
teristic examples of alternately old
and contemporary artists such as
Rembrandt's "The Return of the
Prodigal Son" (below left) and
"Portrait of the Artist's Wife" by
Paul Citroen of the Netherlands
(opposite page)-. Subscribers also re¬
ceive texts of the broadcast commen¬
taries and special binders which
enable them to assemble at each
year's end a personal collection of
40 reproductions and related texts.
This project, now a firm favourite
on the Netherlands Radio network,
was started by a group of art
historians and artists who founded
a non-profit organization called
Openbaar Kunstbezit (Our Art Heri¬
tage) which arranges the broadcasts.
This form of museum visiting at
home has proved a real boon to many
who are too old to travel, to the sick
and those who live in isolated places.
Subscriptions cover schools, sanatoria,
hospitals (opposite page, below) youth
welfare centres and even prisons.
Members are also provided with a
free pass giving them access to over
50 museums in the Netherlands.
Museum attendance has risen by an
estimated 50,000 to 60,000 since the
broadcasts began, and for days after
some broadcasts many people can be
seen studying the original of the
work of art presented over the air.
Through the letters it receives, the'
Foundation has regular confirmation
that its work is opening the door to
art and culture for many people. An
82-year-old listener recently wrote:
"You do more than television, for
besides the voice you give us the
colours and the image is not gone
when the programme ends. My
album remains my treasured pos¬
session to which I turn again and
again."
Teyler Museum, Haarlem.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
CENTRAL AFRICA'S
'SAUCEPAN SP
THE challenge to the Central Afri¬
can Broadcasting Station was
immense and exciting: to bring
education by radio to 7 million Afri¬
cans. We were the first in Africa to
try this and there were no precedents
we could follow.
The station had had its beginnings
in 1941, first at Kitwe, then at
Lusaka, the capital of Northern
Rhodesia. It then broadcast mainly
war-news to the Africans of the,
territory. After the war its range
was extended to Southern Rhodesia
and Nyasaland and its broadcasts
became primarily educational. It
remained a government-run station
until 1957 When it became part of the
Federal Broadcasting Corporation of
Rhodesia and Nyasaland.
The problems were many: for one,
we had to use nine of the languages
of the Rhodesias and Nyasaland and
even that left out large minorities.
But even more difficult was a prob¬
lem that broadcasting stations in
most other countries do not even
have to think of: radio receivers.
At the end of the last war there
were two or three hundred community
receivers in welfare halls and mission-
stations and at administrative cen¬
tres, but hardly any Africans had sets
of their own. These community
receivers had not proved a success.
Our pioneer staff set out to try and
have a set made that Africans could
afford to have in their homes. The
requirements were unusual: it had to
be a short-wave set because only
short waves can cover economically
the immense area of the Rhodesias
and Nyasaland an area larger than
that of the British Isles, France, all
of Germany and Holland together
(485,000 square miles). It had to be
a battery set because few African
houses have electricity. But above all
it had to be cheap.
26
Such a set did not exist and it took
the first director, Harry Franklin,
three years to find a firm which
could be persuaded to make one.
In the end a company specializing
in batteries agreed to produce one
for him. It turned out to be a sturdy,
round little set which looked like a
saucepan on its side, and that is why
they called it the "Saucepan Special".
(The original "Saucepan Special" has
now been replaced by another model
of different shape.)
In 1948 twenty sample sets were
flown out to Northern Rhodesia and
within a few days they had been
snapped up by Africans who paid
£ 5 ($ 14) for the set and 25/- ($ 3.50)
for the battery. The manufacturers
sent their manager to investigate
further and when he visited the new
owners unexpectedly, he was met with
such overwhelming enthusiasm that
the company decided to go into mass
production.
'I have the whole
world in my hut'
The sets were bought up faster
than they could be manu¬
factured and over the thatched
huts of neglected villages and over
the concrete-box houses of urban
"compounds" aerials started to rise,
dozens, hundreds, thousands and
within a few years, tens of thousands.
Letters started to arrive at our
broadcasting station in Lusaka in
ever increasing numbers some typed
neatly, others scrawled painfully in
one of the many vernaculars of the
land.
"I have pleasure in telling you
that ever since my life I have
never had anything which could
please my life better than the
wireless I have got."
"Broadcasting is to Africans as
the great invention of printing
was to European countries in the
Renaissance era... We are no lon¬
ger isolated." '
"Nowadays I will be enjoying a
lot if I don't die quickly. I do en¬
joy very much listening to my set
although I don't get satisfied (sa¬
tiated) as I do when eating
"nsima" (Maize meal porridge)."
"I feel proud when I switch on
my Saucepan Special and have
the whole world in my hut."
Before long the languages of Cen¬
tral Africa had been enriched by a
new word "wayaleshi" the local way
of pronouncing (the English word)
"wireless".
We experimented with many types
of programmes: There were discussion
programmes in which the participants
were a dozen or two "men in the
street" recorded in remote villages
and urban beer-halls, on farms and
in mines some of them educated and
sophisticated, others illiterate and
traditionalist. There was a serial
about a Copperbelt family, designed
to let our audience identify itself
with the hero who suffers the common
experiences of recent migrants to the
towns and solves his problems in an
intelligent, modern way. There were
radio refresher courses for rural
teachers who are normally cut off
from all mental stimulation.
Blind historians found a great new
audience for the oral- traditions of
their tribes through our station. We
persuaded shy, timid African women
to discuss marriages and what could
and did go wrong with them. Soon
we were surprised to receive letters
of comment from women, some from
illiterates dictated to better-educated
husbands. There was something
stirring when the voiceless women of
Central Africa came to write their
opinions to broadcasters who were
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1959
not members of their family or clan,
but total strangers.
We had many spectacular successes.
But far more, we learnt from our
failures. One of these we had with
slogans.
Originally we had imagined that as
broadcasting became less of a novelty
our listeners would become more
sophisticated. What we had left out
of account was the increase in the
number of listeners. As radio-owner¬
ship spread down the social pyramid
the average standard of sophisti¬
cation became lower. It all coincided
with the increasing industrialization
of the Rhodesias and the rapid in¬
crease in African incomes. Radio was
becoming a "must" a coveted symbol
of status. We had to simplify and
simplify still more.
That was when we 'decided to try
slogans hammering home a few sim¬
ple lessons with repetitive little ver¬
ses, not unlike advertising in com¬
mercial radio. Since ours was a
public service station and carried no
advertising, our audience had no
experience of this approachnor had
we broadcasters.
For our first campaign we selected
the advantages of education for girls
and the dangers of the common
house-fly.
I got together a team of helpers,
among them an African author who
was then working on a collection of
proverbs in the Bemba language. I
suggested that these might be useful.
We might hook the new teaching-
matter on to the known, traditional
wisdom.
The others suggested we should use
the traditional form, too. The chief
or elder who uses a proverb never
says the entire saying. He says one
half, the other is added by the man
he is speaking to. One says: "A
garden does not grow by itself..."
the other adds: "Unlike teeth in the
mouth." (In other words, it needs
effort.)
Theme and variations
on a proverb-slogan
This was the pattern We decided
to follow, having the second
half chanted by a small
chorus. Before many minutes had
elapsed the five or six of us Were
scribbling away enthusiastically at
possible proverb-slogan combinations.
In the end we recorded a number,
including the following. (The words
in italics were spoken by a chorus of
three.)
"Young trees: they make the future
forest.
Let us educate little girls: tomorrow
they are th,e young mothers."
Northern Rhodesia Information Service
A STURDY LITTLE SET, the "Saucepan Special", helps to bring education by radio to seven
million people in Rhodesia and Nyasaland. Since the first of these low-priced battery sets was
put on the market in 1948, tens of thousands of aerials have risen above thatched hut villages
and concrete houses of urban compounds. For the people of the two territories radio has become
a "must". "Broadcasting is to Africans as the great invention of printing was to European countries...
we are no longer isolated", wrote one listener to the Central African Broadcasting Station in
Lusaka. Broadcasts go out in nine languages and listeners themselves take part in discussion program¬
mes. The original "Saucepan" model shown here has been improved and has a different shape.
Another:
"Though it's small: yet it's a heavy
load.
The fly: though small, is dangerous.
It gives us disease: You, kill that
fiyi"
We broadcast these and similar
slogans for several weeks, then tried
to assess their effect by interviewing
listeners. Our interviewers chanted
the first half and then wherever
they went the remaining words were
supplied word-perfect. But only very
lew listeners understood what we
were trying to get at.
The better - educated townsfolk
knew all about the need for female
education and about the dangers of
the common housefly.
"You are quite right", said one,
"there are many reasons why women
should be educated. They are like
the front wheel of a bicycle and the
one behind are the men. As a bicycle
cannot run with one wheel, so we
men cannot raise the country lonely."
However, these new townsmen in
most cases only a decade or two out
of their villages were completely
bewildered by the proverbs. First
they ignored them, but when the
interviewers pressed them they tried
to interpret them literally.
In remote villages we found the
opposite reaction. The proverbs were
known and commented on at length,
but these villagers saw no connexion
between them and our new lessons.
Yet all those interviewed had been
regular listeners. Since these slogans
were designed largely for the illiterate
townsmen who might become listeners
if incomes continued to rise; we
decided to extend the enquiry.
We brought groups of such potential
listeners into our studios, played
them recordings of the slogans and
tried to get their reactions. It took
a long time to overcome their
suspicions, but when at long last their
reactions came, they were even more
startling. There were many different
reactions, but they all had one thing
in common: they were deeply alle¬
gorical. Nothing was ever inter¬
preted literally:
"You speak wisely," said one,
"though small, yet it's a heavy load.
The fly is small, but it brings disease.
It's like this: One man can spoil the
happiness of an entire village. He
may be a witch. He brings fear and
hatred and suspicion among the
people. He may even give the chief
an illness by his witchcraft. "Kill
that fly" means we should send such
a man out of the village. One such
man can spoil an entire village.
Though it's small, yet it's a heavy
load."
There was much that we had to
learn the hard way... by trial and
error!
Peter Fraenkel, who has long been associat¬
ed with the Central African Broadcasting
Station, is the author of "Wayaleshi," a
newly-published book devoted to the work
of this radio station at Lusaka. (Publisher:
Weidenfeld & Nicolson, London; price: 21/-.)
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
A LITTLE LESS NOISE, PLEASE
by M. H. Thompson
Louis Joyex-RTF
GIANT 'GOLF BALLS' studding the ceiling of a French broadcasting studio are one of the many kinds
of sound absorbing materials used nowadays in acoustics. Cheap and easy to apply, they range from
stone-like tile with the appearance of travertine marble, to wood fibre tile punched full of holes and blankets
of absorbent mineral wool rolled in long strips. Opposite page, general view of same studio ceiling.
To hear or not to hear... That is the problem.
Haven't you heard people say they couldn't hear
a lecture well because the acoustics were so bad?
These people wanted to hear. On the other hand, haven't
you heard people say they couldn't sleep a wink all night
because some noise kept them awake? (Maybe it Was
only a cat rubbing his whiskers.) At any rate, these
people didn't want to hear. Music from the Hi . Fi is
wanted while, at the same time, traffic noise is not.
Furthermore, loud noises that constantly assault our
hearing organs produce fatigue, while certain other
sounds are pleasant without our realizing just why. Phy¬
siologically the ear is built to take only so much noise.
Nature's sounds are usually muted the ripple of a brook,
the song of a bird, the mooing of a cow. ' Civilization's
are often the opposite the wail of a siren, the din of
traffic, the roar of aeroplanes in the sky. There are other
reasons too why we would preserve one sound and suppress
another. Hi Fi, for example, can be merely high finance
unless the high fidelity sounds are truly heard, which they
cannot be in many noisy rooms. The problem then is to
hear or not to hear, and involves a .knowledge of the
laws of sound or the science of acoustics.
Ancient Greeks studied acoustics
but a Frenchman coined the name
The word acoustics is from the Greek and means :'to
hear"'. Ancient Greeks were aware that sound
somehow arises from the motion of parts of bodies
and is transmitted by the air through some undefined
motion of the air and in this way, striking the eardrums,
produces the sensation of hearing. Aristotle emphasized
that in hearing actual ;hTötion of the air is involved.
28
Pythagoras in the 6th century B.C. studied the origin of
musical sounds and discovered that of two stretched
strings fastened at the ends the higher note is emitted by
the shorter string and that if one has twice the length of
the other the shorter will emit a note an octave above the
other.
Joseph Sauveur, who pioneered in the study of sound
in the early 18th century, first used the name "acoustics"
for the science of sound. Today the word means the
properties of a room which make it conducive to ready
and faithful transmission of sound. Also, as to present-
day nomenclature, acoustic refers to things distinctly
related to the functions of sound, such as acoustic absorp¬
tion, acoustic response, and acoustic spectrum (the range
of frequencies or wave lengths that are audible) . "Acous¬
tical" refers to associated things, such as acoustical tile,
treatment, engineers, instruments.
In the 19th century more work was done in the science
of acoustics. Lord Rayleigh learned something about how
sound is propagated, its speed in various mediums, such
as air and fluids and solids, and the determination of
pitch and its dependence upon frequency of vibration.
But even with his research, and that of Sauveur and a
few other men, acoustics remained a little known science
until after 1895.
Up until then a room with good acoustics was more or
less an accident. When such a room or auditorium was
found, architects copied the design to try to get another
room or auditorium with equally good acoustics. Some¬
times they succeeded and sometimes they didn't. But
about this time there lived a man Who was a member of
the Harvard University physics faculty, and he became
interested in the science of acoustics and began to study
more about sound absorption.
The new Fogg Auditorium of the University of that time
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
had been copied after the Sanders Theatre in Boston,
which had very good acoustics. But in spite of that the
Fogg Hall was a failure acoustically. So this physics
professor, W. C. Sabine by name, undertook to learn what
had gone wrong. He learned that the Fogg Hall hadn't
supplied seat cushions and when this was done the acous¬
tics were almost perfect. But his search and research
didn't end there.
As he learned more about the laws of sound, he began to
establish standards of measurements and units of acous¬
tic energy. He finally established a unit, later called a
"sabin" after his own name in recognition of his work.
It is the amount of sound energy lost to a room through
one square foot of open space such as an open window.
The energy is minute. It takes the combined power of
about fifteen million voices to equal one horse-power, a
unit of work equal to 550 foot-pounds per second.
In time Sabine found that the easiest way to work
with sound energy was to convert it to electrical energy,
where units and procedures of. measurement were already
well established. This changed acoustics from the realm
of architecture to electrical engineering. But until the
invention of the vacuum tube just before World' War I
minute values of electricity were extremely difficult to
handle or measure, and only the amplification of these
minute energies to measurable amounts made the study
of sound possible in all its phases.
Briefly expressing sound power in the electrical unit
of the watt, and remembering that the average light bulb
takes 100 watts of
energy, we find that the
human voice at con¬
versational levels equals
.002 watts, the clarinet
.05, the trumpet .3, and
the bass drum 25 watts
of sound power. While
the sound power of
energy is minute, yet so
enormous is the range of
the human ear that the
ratio between the intens¬
ity of the least noise
we can hear a baby's
breath, for instance
and the greatest sound
intensity we can stand
without pain or injury,
is one thousand million
to one.
Naturally such ratios
would require long
strings of zeros in any
calculation relating to
sound, so the physicist
and the acoustical
engineer use a sort of
mathematical shorthand, employing the logarithmic unit
of the decibel.
Much of the science of sound cannot be explained
easily to the average person. Information is buried in
technical journals of limited circulation^ or in textbooks
so technical that they serve only the acoustical engineer
or the advanced student of physics.
Confused noises bounced from
the walls, floor and ceiling
But the average person can understand something
about acoustics by comparisons. Most of us know
that we hear best in a quiet location out of doors.
Here voice or music is heard in natural beauty. This is
true because outdoor sound can travel freely in all direc¬
tions, unconfused by echoic repetition of sounds previously
uttered. In an enclosed space, however, the walls, floor
and ceiling do not absorb the sound as do the grass and
shrubbery and open sky of a quiet location outside. Sound
is reflected back to mingle in confused noise.
In fact, at a distance of more than a few feet we hear
not so much by the direct sound from the source as by
the sound reflected from room surfaces. And at the rear
of some auditoriums the reflected sound may be nine-
The Unesco Courler. September 1959
tenths of the total reaching the listener. In its many
reflections eh route the sound is changed in quality by
having more of some tones than of others removed or
absorbed by the reflecting surfaces. Thus sound plays in
our daily lives a part scarcely less important than motion
and light, and rooms present acoustical problems.
And the problems of suppressing unwanted sounds
without altering the quality of the wanted sounds are
scientific problems. For each room of known intended
use there is a correct amount of acoustic absorption at
each pitch of sound, which absorption will suppress
unwanted echoes while at the same time preserving
distortion the maximum of wanted sound. The
difference between this correct amount of absorption at
each frequency and that already existing in the room
itself its boundaries and furniture and occupants is the
amount that must be supplied by the acoustical treatment.
To suppress an unwanted
sound wavemake it work
For each occupied room there is a correct distribution
of the total acoustic absorption in the vertical, trans¬
verse, and longitudinal directions. It is essential
that absorption and reflection shall be so distributed as
to diffuse the sound as well as to absorb some of it. Cal¬
culation of these factors for the room on the drawing
board requires some ma¬
thematics and much re¬
ference to graphs and
tables already in exis¬
tence, and often involves
the construction of a
scale model. Precision
instruments and acqui¬
red skill are also used.
If the room turns out to
provide maximum dis¬
tribution of undistorted
voice or music with a
minimum of unwanted
echo, that room is said
to have good acoustics.
Perhaps more accurately
we would call it a quiet
room, a room free from
unwanted sound.
Not only are new
buildings constructed to
the laws of acoustics but
old buildings are worked
over at the advice of
acoustical engineers to
eliminate noise. For in-
stance, many au¬
ditoriums built twenty-five years or more ago have
echoes so intense that an ordinary voice on the stage
can't be understood more than half way back; and there
are places where the echoes from the back wall cancel
out the voice from the stage and make -music sound quite
unnatural.
Thus buildings, both old and new, are acquiring better
acoustics by both sound proofing and sound conditioning.
True sound proofing is keeping sound out; sound condi¬
tioning is absorbing sound that is already in. The first
requires mass, thickness and weight of the barriers; the
latter requires light porous material such as acoustical
tiles and boards.
In fact, noise control is possible because of the develop¬
ment of cheap and easily applied absorbent materials, and
these are of great variety, ranging from stone-like tile
with the appearance of travertine marble, through wood-
fibre tile punched full of holes, to blankets of absorbent
mineral wool rolled in long strips. The materials are all
indexed as to sound absorption at each of six octaves of
the piano keyboard, flame resistance, light reflection, and
weight per square foot.
Certainly there is plenty of choice but the very plethora
of available materials makes a proper choice more impe¬
rative. Moreover, the cost per square foot may range
from 25 cents to $1.50, which also makes choice the
wrong one expensive. So it is up to the acoustical
engineer to advise about the product too.
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
LESS NOISE,
PLEASE
(Continued)
The drum: 500 times more
power than the clarinet
Scientifically, by the use of acoustical absorbent mater¬
ials, the energy in the sound wave is changed into some
form of work done so that the energy is no longer appre-
hended as sound. For instance, in fibrous materials the
filaments making up the tile or board are set in motion
by the sound waves and the energy required to make
them move is- work done. Hence this is energy lost to
the sound wave. Or movement of the fibres may cause
friction which is dissipated as heat and again the energy
has been converted into something else and is no longer
sound.
Because there are so many different types of sound-
absorbing materials, all good, and so many ways of
applying them, and because they vary from type to type
in the amount of sound they absorb at different frequen¬
cies (pitch) of sound, great care is necessary in choosing
the right material and its method of mounting for the
particular room, or occupancy, or expected sound levels
encountered.
Too much proofing leaves
the room hollow & boomy
For example, suppose a room is being designed for
orchestra practice. The instructor must be able to
hear each instrument as a separate sound source if
he is to correct mistakes of each player. Expressing the
sound power in the electrical unit of the watt, the drum
would release 12,600 times as much power into the room
as the human voice, and 80 times the power of the trum¬
pet and 500 times the power of the clarinet. Usually the
notes of the clarinet are several octaves above the drum.
Whatever acoustical material is applied in the room
must of necessity give a lot of absorption at the low fre¬
quencies of the drum if its enormous power is not to
drown out the higher pitches entirely. Since most
acoustical tile of the sort usually applied in stores and
offices is six to ten times as absorbent at high frequencies
as at low ones, they must be ruled out of this particular
job.
And not only is the selection of the kind of material
important but the placing of the material is just as
important. Also, the exact quantity of material is
necessary too. If too much treatment is applied, usually
the echoes are gone, that's true, but the remaining sound
is often badly distorted as to pitch, for most materials
reduce the high pitched sounds far better than the low
ones, so that what is left for us to hear is the low pitched
tones, and the room then sounds hollow and boomy.
one could hear double and triple, beats. Some bands
wouldn't play in the hall, so an acoustical engineer was
called in to solve the problems.
With electrical instruments he made exhaustive mea¬
surements of the sound and echoes, explored the hidden
structure of the walls and ceiling, and contrary to the
procedure followed in 99 % of such problems, specified a
ceiling hung 17 1/2 inches below the original one, in an
aluminium gridWork of channels, and put Into the grid
sheets of Fibreglas 2' x 4' in symetrical patches that
totalled less than one-third of the ceiling. He filled in
the rest of the area with sheets of sheetrocjk the same
size as the fibreglas, then had the whole ceiling painted.
SOUNDING OFF
BEHIND THE MIKE
Few background noises are the real thing on radio. A
crackling fire ma/ be only cellophane being crumpled,
something moving in the bushes merely twisted straw, a
body blow a fist punching a rubber sponge. Sound effects
can imitate almost any noise, but nothing can duplicate
the sound of water except water itself. Photos show (I)
diving and splashing effects; (2) staircase, half stone half
wood, used for effects. Staff is shown how not to fall
down stairs; (3) submarine commander (rear) shouts
instructions while actors lie on floor to give right acous¬
tics for scene taking place In dinghy at sea; (4) effects
men imitate creaking of ship's rigging during storm at
sea and breaking up of the mainmast while woman in
background plays effects records of howling winds and
raging seas; (5) a duel... with electronic firearms! Two
actors fire the "guns" but the shots come from the two .
little grey boxes being adjusted by effects woman; (6)
agile feet and hands are needed to start right sound
effects recordings listed under "train", "cheers", "drums".
All photos © BBC, London.
False ceiling cures the problem
of three orchestras in one
Thus each job has its own special problems for the
acoustical engineer to solve. It may be interesting to
know how one acoustical engineer solved the prob¬
lem of noise in one auditorium. This public auditorium
was built years ago. The room was 110 feet by 70 feet
with a ceiling only 20 feet high, and the stage on the long
side.
The echoes were so intense that an ordinary voice on
the stage couldn't be understood more than half way back,
there were three rows in the middle where the echo from
the back wall cancelled out the voice from the stage, and
the only expedient had been to put so much power behind
a loud speaker that the resultant roar, while annoying in
the extreme, did force enough clear sound out over the
floor that speech was at least partly intelligible. But a
dance band generated so much echo that in the corners
Also on the walls, in several selected areas that were
reflecting the measured echoes, he glued large panels of
fibreglas, 3/4" thick to absorb the sound. Now in the
auditorium, a listener can understand a low voice on the
stage at any place in the room provided the audience is
between 200 and 1,000 people. And dance bands that
have played there before and after treatment call it
"Wonderful."
Sound control does not apply to auditoriums only.
Corrections extend to commercial buildings too. As the
world became noisier the problem of sound control began
to apply in factories, in office rooms, and in busy public
places. Machinery has contributed to much of this noise,
including many typewriters in one room, or address-
ographs, for instance. The human voice has done its share
to make places noisy too. It has been ascertained that
noise made at a restaurant by 250 women having lunch
registered 75 decibels. Sound engineers have looked into
the household too and what they have found in the way
of noise is startling. In the ordinary house, radio, TV
sets, defective refrigerator motors, vacuum cleaners and
the like produce much unwanted sound.
30 CONTINUED ON PAGE 32
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. September 1959
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
No doubt more and more in the future truly acoustical
architecture will be applied even to homes, especially to
those in the higher cost brackets, so that annoying noises
can be kept to a minimum. And perhaps some acoustical
engineer will devise some inexpensive gadgets that could
be mailed to home owners with instructions for use in
rooms much as the engineer uses equipment on his jobs.
Then a consulting-by-mail business could be built up to
help people with their problems of noise control. . The
home owner could draw a rough plan of the room, its
furnishings, and give the number of people usually
occupying it, etc. He would report the results of the
simple tests taken with the gadgets, and a suitable treat¬
ment could be recommended for a modest fee at probably
far less cost than the usual risky allover-ceillng coverage
so often used.
Acoustics are for 'do
it yourself amateurs
Until then, however, people who can't afford acous¬
tically engineered rooms can learn lessons from the
facts now known about the laws of sound to help
keep down noise.
A basic principle in reducing noise is to attack it at its
source. If the kitchen is the noisiest place, then an entire
ceiling of acoustical tile Will accomplish as much as a
40 per cent reduction of noise, thus vastly reducing the
amount available for transmission to other areas of the
house. The next step is to make a sound trap between
noisy areas such as the kitchen or rumpus room and the
bedrooms or study where quiet is wanted. This can often
be accomplished by covering the ceiling and upper two
feet of the walls of a connecting hallway with acoustical
material.
The range of waves known as
the electromagnetic spectrum
is like a long piano keyboard.
The string struck by each white
key vibrates at half the rate of
the string eight notes higher, so
that for each octave, frequency
doubles and wave length halves.
About 50 octaves, represent
the electromagnetic spectrum.
COI, London
In the living room a complete ceiling of acoustical tile
or other material would kill or distort the quality of music
from the radio and TV. Here acoustical "damping" of
sound must be obtained on two walls that intersect each
othernot on walls opposite each other. In fact, the
main causes of poor hearing conditions in such rooms are
parallel wall surfaces of plaster or plywood. So acoustical
material could be used on adjoining walls, not parallel, to
cut down noise. Or if one can't afford acoustical material,
if one wall' has heavy lined window drapes, one can
experiment with a heavy wool blanket on the adjoining
wall. A tapestry can be hung over the blanket. But
home owners who think a mere ceiling of acoustical tile
will solve their problem are more often disappointed than
pleased, for they usually ruin it so far as hearing phono¬
graph or radio music is concerned.
There are a few more pertinent facts about cutting
down noise in the home. If the telephone bell bothers
you, you might try cutting a little square of sponge rubber
to fit underneath it. The same trick will work for a
radio or TV set or a noisy typewriter. A pad of sponge
rubber under them will keep the sound from traveling
down the table and along the floor. However, it won't
affect the sound that comes out of the speaker. Radios
and phonographs should be set in a corner for best sound.
A sponge rubber rug under a carpet will cut down the
noise of clattering feet. Rugs themselves, as well as pads
under them, are a help in this respect.
In fact, the ancients used rugs, draperies, and pillows
to cut down noise. They didn't know why, but a lot of
the trouble comes when sound bounces about the room.
The noise hits a hard surface and flies off; in a different
direction. . Any type of soft covering that 'will absorb this
extra sound will make a big difference in personal comfort.
Curtains or drapes around the windows help. Weather
stripping on doors and windows help keep out traffic noise.
Shrubbery or a row of trees on the outside will help too.
Windows facing the street should be double weight or
plate glass to cut down noise. Double thick ceiling plaster
will cut out the noise of aeroplanes three times better
than rock wool heat insulation would do.
A little common sense, too, can protect your hearing
from jarring noises. Keep the radio tuned down, also
the TV. Wear ear plugs (made especially for noise) if
construction or other loud continuous noise is going on
near you. Anyone can have some extra pillow around to .
help absorb noise. For noise, according to the dictionary,
is unwanted sound and quiet is freedom from noise. And
nowadays "Quiet Please" can mean a lot more than telling
someone not to make noise. It can include the whole
gamut of acoustical data in all its scientific phases.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
MIGHTY HANDY
THAT WALKIE-TALKIE
As equipment becomes more compact and yet more
powerful the vast possibilities of radio are being
exploited In Innumerable ways. Photos here show
farmers, film-makers, explorers and rallwaymen
radio to make their work easier, safer and more
efficient. (I) French film-maker uses "walkie-
talkie" transmitter-receiver while shooting a
mountain-climbing documentary on some of the
most difficult and dangerous French Alpine peaks.
(2) French explorers observing the giant lizard of
Komodo (largest of the lizard tribe; sometimes
12 feet long) in Borneo, communicate with collea¬
gues in other hidden observation posts. (3) Russian
farmer reports back on progress made with har¬
vesting. (4) Railwayman in the United States
uses two-way portable radio to give Instructions
to other crew members of a long goods train.
(1) Production Filmartic-Marcel Ichac
(2) Thomson-Houston
(3) Official Soviet photo
(4) USIS
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom...
M: ROM PRINT TO BRAILLE BY
COMPUTER : Exciting new prospects for
blind readers are being opened up by one
of the latest ' applications of ' electronic
computers. With the aid of one of these
machines, a' 300-page book can now be
translated into Braille in one hour a task
which would take almost a week for seve¬
ral skilled translators to complete. It takes
about two years to train specialists of
Braille whereas the new method does not
require a knowledge of Braille on the part
of the operator. The machine translates
4,000 words a minute.
BUDDHIST ART IN JAPAN: A
new album - "Japan: Ancient Buddhist
Paintings" - has just been published in
the Unesco World Art Series which
offers high-quality colour reproductions
of works not previously well-known
outside their own countries. Devoted to
works painted between the 8th and 12th
centuries, the album offers an impres¬
sive overall view of Japanese Buddhist
art which runs from mystical images to
realistic portaits. . The album is publish¬
ed by the New York Graphic Society,
Price : $ 18 ; £ 6 7. O. ; 8,850 Fr. Frs.
Sahara soil-less farming:
Tomatoes, cabbages, radishes, lettuce,
maize and groundnuts can be grown in des¬
ert sand 'without any special shelter and
with only a small quantity of irrigation
water, the French National Centre for
Scientific Research has just revealed follow¬
ing its "soil-less farming" experiments at
Colomb-Bechar on the edge of the Sahara.,
Actually it is farming without humus. The
process consists of placing a layer of sandy
gravel and plant nutrients in a big concrete
trough. The sand is regularly "nourished"
' through plastic tubes. Only three litres of
water per day and per square metre are
required.
U.S. SIGNS TREE FLOW' PACT :
The United States has signed the
UtiESCO-sponsored Agreement on the
duty free importation of educational,
scientific and cultural materials which
eliminates customs duties on books,
newspapers, magazines, works of art,
geographic maps and musical scores.
Customs exemption is also granted to
newsreels, educational films, sound re¬
cordings and scientific apparatus when
destined for approved institutions. So far
31 countries have ratified the Agree¬
ment; it becomes operative in the United
States upon ratification by the U.S.
Congress.
J.RAN RATIFIES' 'CULTURAL
RED CROSS' PACT : The Convention and
Protocol for the .Protection of Cultural
Property in the Event of Armed Conflict
EDUCATION FOR THE NUCLEAR AGE
THE pressing educational problem of training technical and scientific per¬
sonnel for the world's ever-expanding industrial and technological installa¬
tions and in particular for the development of peaceful uses of atomic
energy was discussed recently at two important international conferences convened
by Unesco jointly with other organizations.
This year's annual Unesco-International Bureau of Education Conference at
Geneva discussed aspects of the training of technical and scientific personnel:
financial, administrative, educational, as well as social. These included the use of
funds for training, long-term planning to put an end to the shortage of qualified
personnel, increasing the number of technical training institutions, and the study
of social measures fellowships, housing, employment offices likely to
stimulate the recruitment of future candidates. Delegates studied a survey of these
problems in 50 countries and drew up a recommendation to Ministries of Edu¬
cation designed to promote bigger training programmes.
A the French Centre for Nuclear Research at Saclay, near Paris, scientists from
30 countries discussed educational problems specifically concerned with the deve¬
lopment of atoms for peace. In technically advanced countries there is a lack
of trained manpower to meet the needs of rapid nuclear development, both in
nuclear science technology and in the operational phases of atomic energy.
Delegates discussed the role of universities, engineering colleges, nuclear research
centres and international organizations in the education of nuclear personnel.
Special attention was given to the need to train more health physicists and to
introduce nuclear science at the secondary school level.
was recently ratified by Iran,- the 29th coun¬
try to do so. The Convention was adopted
in 1954 by a conference convened under
Unesco's auspices. Under its terms, nations ,
undertake in the event of armed conflict to
safeguard as well as to respect cultural
property located on their own territory or
that of other contracting parties.
JOURNALISM CENTRE EX¬
PANDS PROGRAMME : The Inter¬
national Centre of Higher Education in
Journalism created two years ago at
Strasbourg University on the initiative
of Unesco ij expanding its activities,
and from December will be offering
six-month courses in methods of teach¬
ing journalism. Until now it has run a
one month training course each year for
teachers of journalism, covering me¬
thods of newsgathering and presentation,
and the journalisfs role in relation to
radio, television and film. Thirty-four
participants from 25 countries attended
the last course of this kind.
JrAPER FROM CORN STALKS:
Israeli businessmen will probably soon be
writing on "'home-made" paper produced
from, corn stalk pulp. ' A paper mill near
Tel Aviv is pushing ahead with plans to ,
use corn stalks, a local agricultural waste
product, in its paper making. This is be¬
lieved to be the first commercial use of
corn stalks in paper manufacture. Depend¬
ing on the kind of paper being produced,,
corn stalk and cereal straw pulp will cons¬
titute between 20 % and 100 % of the final
product. Israel's growing need for paper
is reflected in the fact that it now ranks'
third in the world in the per capita pub¬
lishing of books.
SCIENCE-MINDED JAPANESE :
In Japan the number of young people
studying science and technology is in¬
creasing far more rapidly than the num¬
ber of students taking arts degrees, re¬
ports the International Bureau of Edu¬
cation in a recent survey. Last year, out
of every fourteen Japanese students,
nine were studying science and only five
literature, as compared with 1957 when
the proportion was exactly the reverse.
MIRACLE AT ROTTERDAM
We apologize to readers for an error
made in the last issue. The caption on
pages 18/19 identified the' sculpture in
the centre photo as the work of Anne
Grimalden of the Netherlands. This
sculpture is the work of the Norwegian
artist, Anne Grimdalen, and was a gift
from Norway to the city of Rotterdam.
o
z
<
OL
<
z
<
o
LU
O
à.
E
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
g george a. codding ¡r. brOäGCdStlllg
without barriers
Just published
Unsurpassed in speed, range and economy, radio broad¬
casting is an ideal means of informing and entertaining the
world's peoples and promoting the free flow of ideas between
countries. But many obstacles impede its effective use.
The development of broadcasting in various regions has
been extremely disparate, with the result that 6 0 per cent
of the world population still lacks adequate transmitting and
reception services. Broadcasting organizations and indus¬
tries have not always kept pace with technical advances,
with the changing requirements of public interest, or with
the challenge of the new medium, television. Insufficient
effort has been made to promote the international exchange
of programmes. And finally, failure to agree on the rational
use of frequencies for broadcasting has hindered expansion
in the advanced as well as the less advanced countries.
These problems are examined, and solutions suggested
in this study, which is an indispensable aid to everyone inter-
rested in the progress of broadcasting, nationally and inter¬
nationally. It contains pictographs, photographs and an
extensive bibliography. A Unesco publication; obtainable
from Unesco's Sales Agents, see below.
Price : Paper : $ 3.00; 15/- (stg.); 1,050 FF.
Cloth : $ 4.50 ; 22/6 (stg.) ; 1,600 FF.
WHERE TO OBTAIN UNESCO PUBLICATIONS
Order from any bookseller, or write
direct to the National Distributor
in your country (See list below ;
names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request).
Payment is made in the national
currency ; rates quoted are for an
annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. - Panuzaï, Press
Department, Royal Afghan Ministry of
Education, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 369 Lonsdale Street, Melbourne,
C.I, Victoria. (A. 13/-)
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C*., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V (Seh.
37.50.)
BELGIUM. For The Unesco Courier:
Louis de Lannoy, 22, Place De Brouckère,
Brussels, CCP. 338.000. (fr.b. 100.)
Other publications: Office de Publicité,
16, rue Marcq, Bruxelles, CCP 285-98;
N.V. Standaard-Boekhandel, Belgiélei 151,
Antwerp.
BURMA. S.P.C.K. (Burma) 549, Merchant
Street, P.O. Box 222, Rangoon.
CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa,
Ont. ($ 3.00).
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd, Lake House Bookshop,
1 00 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Co¬
lombo 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh.
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Librería Económica, Pte Zayas
505-7 Apartado I 13, Havana.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia Ltd., 30
Ve Smeckách, Prague 2.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6 Nörregade, Copenhagen K. (D.kr. 12)
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agen¬
cy, P.O. Box 120, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (F.mk. 540)
FRANCE. Unesco Bookshop, Place de
Fontenoy, Paris, T. CCP. 12598-48.
(600 fr.)
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8. (DM. 6)
GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Kultura, P.O. Box 149.
Budapest, 62.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; Gunfoundry Road, Hyde¬
rabad, I ; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/1 Asaf Ali Road, P. O.
Box 386. New Delhi, I; Sub-Depots :
Oxford Book & Stationery Co., Scindia
House, New Delhi; Rajkamal Prakashan
Private Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby
Road, Bombay I. (Rs. 6.70)
INDONESIA. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Djakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
IRELAND	 The National Press, 2 Wel¬
lington Road, Ballsbridge. Dublin. (10/-)
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
35, Allenby Road and 48, Nahlat Benja¬
min Street, Tel-Aviv. (£.l./4..)
ITALY. Librería Commissionaría San-
soni, Via Gino Capponi 26, Casella Pos¬
tale 552, Florence, (lire 950)
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings. (10/-)
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo. (Yen 500)
JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road, P.O.B. 66,
Amman.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, P. O. Box Central 64, Seoul.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul
Brück, 33 Grand'Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Peter Chong & Co.,
Post Office Box 135, Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta. ( I 0/-)
MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid des
Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (600 fr.)
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl. 6)
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church. (10/-.)
NIGERIA. CM. S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
I 74, Lagos. ( I 0/-)
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass 7, Oslo. (N. kr. 10)
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60 The Mall
Lahore ; Bunder Road, Karachi and
35 The Mall. Peshawar, (rs.6)
PANAMA. Cultural Panameña, Ave¬
nida 7a, No. Ti-49, Apartado de Correos
2018, Panama, D.F.
PHILIPPINES	 Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo, P.O. Box
620. Manila.
POLAND. Osrodek Rozpowszechniania
Wydawnictw Naukowych PAN, Palac
Kultury i Nauki, Warsaw. (Zl. 50.)
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada Lda,
Livraria Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70,
Lisbon.
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Libri Building, Church Street. P.O.
Box 724. Pretoria. (10/-)
SWEDEN. For The Unesco Courier: Sven-
ska Unescoradet, Vasagatan I 5-1 7, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 7.50) other publications
A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl. Hovbokhandel,
Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag. 5
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40 rue du Marché, Geneva. CCP.
1-236. (fr. s. 6.50.)
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Raidamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Isti-
klal Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul.
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT).
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha,
Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569. London, S.E.I. (10/-)
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22, N.Y. ($3.00.) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y.
U. S. S. R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga,
Terazije 27/1 I, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Recent air disasters have shown how diffi¬
cult it is for rescue services to locate survi¬
vors, especially when the aircraft has come
down in the sea. They have also highlighted
the work of rescue services in many parts of
the world and new efforts to improve techni¬
ques and devices for locating and rescuing
victims of shipwreck or aircraft crashes.
Typical of such research is Operation "Por¬
poise" carried out in the Mediterranean by
the French Search and Rescue Service to
test equipment used by survivors of an
imaginary transport plane making a forced
landing in the sea.
Thirty volunteer "survivors" were put into
two aircraft dinghies somewhere between
the French coast and Corsica and as soon
as the alarm was given three aircraft took
off to search for them. The survivors made
use of medium radio transmitter-receivers
then in current use and also a new Ultra-
High-Frequency apparatus operating on short
waves and shown in the photos on this page
taken during Operation "Porpoise". Five
hours after the theoretical forced landing,
the dinghies were located by a radio-fix
from the searching aircraft.
The tiny Ultra-High-Frequency transmitter-
receiver, which gave convincing proof of
its effectiveness, weighs only 1 lb. and can
be held in the hand. It works on transistor
batteries and its transmitting range despite
its size and short two foot aerial, is 100 kms.
Unlike older equipment, the new transistor
sets require no cranking of generators and
are instantly ready for use even by physi¬
cally exhausted victims.
Photos Thomson-Houston
]]>
</page>
</document>
