<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="066613eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
m I
i^Lsl (
W¿*
&yym**(K
w
win
»
#'£ ,71
///
L>*.*.'~-
OCTOBER
19 5 9
(/2th year)
Price : I /-stg. (U.K.)
30 cents (U. S)
60 francs (France)
X
*,."" : .*
. . xfc ft ., i
The startling
rediscovery
of a continent
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
3te
'*- *Jl
H«**
1-1 ' I*
V '-^»'-
¡T - ---A . ' *. -V" -", VS^ir*"'.	 - *!
.»-» T« '' 4 ;"
;fe^^i^te
GIANT OBELISK OF
ANCIENT ETHIOPIA
One of the most intriguing chapters in African
history concerns the growth and survival of Ethio¬
pia, a country converted to Christianity some
1,600 years ago, which conserved its religion and
developed a highly advanced civilization inde¬
pendent of the Muslims to the north and east
and of the Negro cultures to the south. Its foun¬
dations were laid when highly sophisticated and
technically advanced peoples crossed over the
Red Sea during the millennium before Christ and
set up a powerful kingdom with its capital at
Axum. The people of this Axumite Kingdom cut
enormous blocks of hard stone and erected the
giant monoliths and other kinds of standing stones
still found in Ethiopia today. Some, like the giant
"obelisk" (left), the tallest in Ethiopia, standing
nearly 70 feet high and dominating the tombs of
the kings in the ancient capital of Axum, have
resisted the ravages of time. Others, their engrav¬
ed lines and symbols a still unexplained mys¬
tery, have come crashing down to earth (photo
above). The .Axumite Kingdom and its Amharic
successor acquired an identity and distinction
which have helped to give the Ethiopia of today
a unique culture and civilization. (See page 30)
Photos © Almasy, Paris
feroÍH
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
A WINDOW OMN ON THE WOILD
ner
OCTOBER 1959
12TH YEAR
Contents
No. 10
COVER PHOTO
Bronze head from Ife in
West Africa which is the
spiritual capital of the Yo-
ruba peoples. Lines scor¬
ed on the features may
represent facial scarification
or be a way of suggesting
long strings of small beads
such as many of the Yoruba
divine kings still wear
hanging from their crowns.
(See pages 12 and 15)
Photo Eliot Elisofon from "The
Sculpture of Africa". © Thames
and Hudson, Ltd., London, I 958
PAGES
4 THE REDISCOVERY OF AFRICA
By Basil Davidson
10 GREAT ZIMBABWE
Ruins of an unknown Negro civilization
By Henri Bart
12 THE KINGDOM OF BENIN
Great forest realm of mediaeval Nigeria
By K. Onwonwu Dike
15 TWO PINNACLES OF AFRICAN ART
By William Fagg
20 THE MARCH OF IRON ACROSS A CONTINENT
By R. R. Inskeep
22 FORGOTTEN CITIES OF EAST AFRICA
By Gervase Mathew
24 KUMBI SALEH : CAPITAL OF THE 'LAND OF GOLD'
By Raymond Mauny
26 JOURNEYS OF DISCOVERY
Ancient chroniclers of West Africa's past
By Thomas Hodgkin
28 LOST TEMPLES IN THE DESERT
30 THE GREATNESS OF ETHIOPIA
Its legends and realities
By Jean Doresse
33 THE EL DORADO OF THE ASHANTIS
By Jacqueline Delange
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7', France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (12 issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. In the United States of America it is distri¬
buted by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 801 Third Avenue, New
York 22, N.Y., Plaza 1-3860. Second-class mail privileges authorized at New
York, N.Y. (M.C. 59. 1. 1 40 A).
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an internatiopal reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: S 3.00; IO/-stg. ; 600 Fr. frs.
(6 New Francs) or equivalent. Single copies I /-stg. (U.K.) ;
30 cents (U.S.) ; 60 Fr. frs. (60 centimes, New Franc).
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7'.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
THE REDISCOVERY OF AFRICA
by Basil Davidson
ROYAL CONGO STATUE: This head is a detail of
the effigy of the I I 9th monarch of the Bushongo King¬
dom in the Belgian Congo. The practice of making royal
portrait statues during the lifetime of the kings appar¬
ently began with Shamba Bolongongo, the 93rd and
greatest of the Bushóngo kings (c. A.D. 1600). The
kings are usually shown sitting cross-legged with some
object (like a drum, an anvil etc.) symbolizing the special
achievements for which they are still remenbered.
Van de Straete Collection
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1959
) Almasy, Paris
SAND-BLURRED RUIN of Musawarat es Safa, to the north of Khartoum, in the Sudan, was once a palace or temple, built at
the beginning of the Christian era as the residence of a god-king or goddess-queen. Today there remain only the solitary ruins
of palaces and temples lying amid the sands surrounded by the undisturbed city mounds of the Kush civilization which [built them.
s the negro a man without a past? Not many years have passed since the outside
world took an affirmative answer more or less for. granted: to what point, indeed,
will be easily remembered by those many Africanists who watched the stubborn
efforts of Melville Herskovits and notably in his book, The Myth of the Negro Past
arguing that the answer should be no.
But now of recent years, in the wake of the colonial hurricane, there emerges a
new approach to the whole question. It is increasingly realized that the cultural con¬
tributions of African peoples to the general history and progress of mankind were not
limited to interesting works of art, whether in wood or ivory or in bronze or gold,
but comprehended a wide range of political and social achievements that were none the
less important or remarkable because they were ignored or little known. It is seen,
indeed, that these works of art that so many Asians and Americans and Europeans
have now admired were not the more or less mysterious products of a social vacuum,
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
REDISCOVERY
1
MABRUK
OF AFRICA w TICHIT | u r>
^m MAURETANIA t5t	.-\ GAO
I
(Continued) r^x
1
TIMBUKTU a\ ^a
<l^¿>^ 1
1
/
W V<!. >v
" Vc KUMBI SALEH 1 \( \
C. VERDE ^ \*<r /// 1
SENEGAL *Sf *'''
L v^Ä'	 ~ _/_/ DJENNE /
A . I -r ~l% y ^»*r~z.*'Z>-» *, RERX SUDÁN .'" v\ i'"~" ****
\* /^<~~^ ''X--'
0 V
il / »'"*"»-.
es." rx - -v¿---^ X //)UPPER VOLTA
K /^ J1
1 A
^^^ r^ \ (^ DAHOMEY i \
>
Î GHANA
I* n/i g e R 1
# * i / * i i 'CfïTA/ ' ¿V V^" s. I \ -i
n «* IVORY COAST { VORUBA & IFE ¿^->«*
->^^^^p ' »N»
I BAULE / ) Î
w
É* ASHANTI 1 '
_' BENINLIBERIA
#
/ \ \ _a ' CROSS R
*W^^
but, on the contrary, the ornament and attribute of early
African civilizations.
This reassessment of the African past occurs when
many African peoples achieve new positions of indepen¬
dence in the world, and when their voice begins to be
heard at the United Nations headquarters and other
places where governments and nations meet. These
middle years of the 20th century may be remembered
for many troubles and upheavals, and for risks and
dangers greater than any that humanity had ever run
before: on the side of good they will also be remembered
as the central years of African emancipation. And they
mean, of course, much more than a purely political
emancipation much more than that some 80 million
Africans, within a few years from now, will be governing
themselves: they mean, as well, an intellectual and moral
emancipation, a breaking down of obstacles that have
stood between Africans and a sense of full equality with
the rest of the world, and of barriers that have helped
to isolate these African peoples from the general family
of man.
Enquiry into the course of pre-European African history
is an important aspect of this reassessment. It is the
work of many scholars and specialists in many lands.
International scholarship, these past ten or twenty years,
has joined together in a common effort to make good,
as well as may be, much of the mutilation that was done
to African repute through four centuries of slaving and
another century of imperialist rule. And what is happen¬
ing now this special issue of The Unesco Courier is
something of a symbol of its happening is that the fruits
of all this patient work and painstaking research are
now being gathered in. Let me offer one small but typical
example. For the last twenty years the standard British
work on East African history was that of Sir Reginald
Coupland, who devoted some forty pages to the pre-
European past. Last year one of Britain's leading uni¬
versity presses decided to commission a multi-volume
history of British East Africa ; and this will devote a
whole volume to the pre-European past.
Something of the range and often bewildering variety
of the work that is being done, up and down the conti¬
nent, can be glimpsed from articles which distinguished
specialists contribute to this special issue of The Courier.
It would be invidious to mention names where so many
men and women are at work. There is almost no African
territory, however outwardly silent and remote, that has
failed to produce some contribution, however small, to the
vivid and compelling picture of African history that is
now beginning to emerge.
Colonial government; in British territories, notably
those of Tanganyika and Southern Rhodesia have passed
careful ordinances for the safeguarding and maintenance
AFRICA SOUTH OF THE SAHARA is
shown in almost its entirety on this adaptation of
a map by Palacios, originally published in " The
Sculpture of Africa ", ©Thames and Hudson Ltd.,
London. To it have been added the names of
important archaeological and historical sites
mentioned in this special issue of " The Unesco
Courier ". From these sites modern historians and
archaeologists have unearthed a vast body of
evidence which proves that remarkable African
civilizations flourished long before the arrival of the
Europeans on this continent, civilizations which
were mostly unknown to other peoples and whose
achievements are only now being recognized.
of ancient monuments. They have given money, little
but precious, for the subsidizing of museums and research.
They have begun to appoint salaried specialists in the
fields of history and archaeology. In French territories
the pioneering labours of M. Monod and his colleagues
of the Institut Français de l'Afrique Noire have laid bold
and solid foundations in this new soil of interest and
enquiry.- The Emperor of Ethiopia, in a land so often
barred to archaeology in the past, has shown himself
magnanimous and enlightened. The Government of the
Republic of the Sudan, increasingly aware of its rich
inheritance from ancient Kush, has embarked on the
building of what promises to be one of the greatest
museums of all Africa. Such examples could easily be
multiplied.
And now African scholars, working in African universi¬
ties, have themselves begun to take a hand. Nothing
more clearly shows the progress that is being made, and
may increasingly be made, than the way in which this
history of the mediaeval Nigerian kingdom of Benin is
now being sought and written. Three years ago the
British and Nigerian Governments joined with the Car¬
negie Foundation to award a sum of £42,000 for team
research into the story of mediaeval Benin; and the leader
of this distinguished team is an African, Dr. Onwonwu
Dike of Ibadan University College. (See page 13.)
Homo sapiens may first have seen the light in central
or east Africa. For some thirty years now, Africa has
yielded discovery after discovery revolutionizing earlier
concepts of the remote origins of humanity; and the
work of men like Dart, Breuil and Leakey has a much
more than purely African significance. But the present
enquiry, the subject of this special issue, has another
direction. What now becomes possible is to sketch the
outline of the comparatively recent pre-history and
history of large regions of Africa: the record, that is, of
CONT'D ON PAGE 8
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
v .-	-í
The Unesco Courier. October 1959
I« MEROE
~ MUSAWARAT /
I
NAQA I
V,
^*VH>/M/
\!.\ BIQO
ETHIOPIA
;.. vierOria
BUSHONGO
L. TANGANYIKA
C-"-*"*--_
TANGANYIKA
NORTHERN RHODESIA MOZAMBIQUE
SOUTHERN
RHODESIA
INVANGA
(old Terracing)
SOUTH WEST
AFRICA
BECHUANALAND \
ZIMBABWE çfoFALA
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
REDISCOVERY
OF AFRICA
(Continued)
A FACTUAL REAPPRAISAL
OF THE AFRICAN PAST
the pre-mediaeval and mediaeval centuries that came
immediately before European contact and penetration.
It is this that is really new this assertion that Africans
went through successive, distinctive, and knowable phases
of growth and development in the fifteen or twenty
centuries before the European records of Africa become
frequent and various. Reassessment of the African past,
in the sense that I have spoken of, is essentially the
unravelling and writing of the history of the African
Metal Age in the lands that lie to the south of the Sahara
desert.
Let us try and summarize the core and heart of this
great matter. Late Stone Age peoples on the lower
reaches of the Nile, and in nearby regions that were much
more fertile then, thrust their way into history in about
3,000 b.c., when the "first dynasty" of the Pharoahs took
power iñ the delta of the Nile. This great forward step
in northernmost Africa, interwoven with the comparable
achievements of peoples in the Near East and the Medi¬
terranean, acted and reacted as the centuries went by on
lands to the South and West. Its influence spread south¬
ward up the Nile and there, reacting on the peoples that
it found, stimulated and helped to create the civilization
of Kush of that renowned kingdom of Napate and Meroe
whose kings and queens would rule in more or less conti¬
nuous succession for a thousand years after about 800 b.c.
With a mastery of metals
came victory over Nature
Its influence also spread westward along the southern
shores of the Mediterranean: Phoenician Carthage,
founded in the ninth century b.c., helped to stimulate
and create the Libyco-Berber civilizations of northern
Africa. And, thirdly, these ancient civilizations of the
Near East and of Egypt produced in the southernmost tip
of Arabia that Arabia of the Queen of Sheba whom
Solomon knew and loved another region of high
civilization; and from southern Arabia this civilization of
antiquity despatched its settlers and traders and warriors
across the Red Sea into the Horn of Africa, and its
mariners and colonists down the long east coast of what
is now Somaliland, Kenya, Tanganyika, and Mozambique.
These pioneers and their mastery of metal-working and
of other material techniques did not move into a void.
They moved into a land that was peopled then, if thinly,
by several branches of the human family to which anthro¬
pologists have awarded the names of bushman, negrillo,
hottentot, negro, a.nd hamite. Now the origins of these
peoples of continental Africa are obscure and confused.
They too, apparently, had moved southward across the
continent, coming perhaps from outside it, in centuries
beyond calculation.
Probably the bushmen and the negrillos the pygmies
were the first of all the surviving peoples of Africa to
inhabit the land. Some of them survive today in a more
or less Stone Age simplicity: there are groups of pygmies
in the central forests of the Congo, and bushmen in the
wastes of the Kalahari, who live only by hunting and
fishing and collecting food.
Perhaps the Hottentots the natives whom the first
Dutch settlers would find at the Cape of Good Hope in
1652 were the next to arrive. At some time after about
5,000 b.c. but nothing of this is clearly known the peoples
whom we know as negro and hamite began to emerge,
multiply, and follow the earlier migrants in a generally
southward direction. As they wandered across the con¬
tinent these later peoples, often mingling with earlier
peoples whom they found, worked out new ways of living.
They invented tropical agriculture. They began to settle
and raise new crops. They learned how to smelt natural
copper and make primitive tools and weapons of this
metal.
8
At a time that was shortly before or after the beginning
of the Christian era these peoples of the southern conti¬
nent began to mine and smelt iron, and to make more
efficient tools and weapons; and with this they acquired
a new and, as it would prove, revolutionary control over
the material environment in which they lived. It is from
about this time from about 2,000 years ago that the
peoples of the continental heart of Africa begin to mul¬
tiply and form their present major groupings.
It is from then, as it seems, that the largest of all of
Africa's existing human groups begins to spread into and
populate the empty or near-empty forests and savannahs.
This group is called the Bantu; but the term has little
or no racial significance, being a linguistic term for all
these many peoples who speak a closely related language.
Racially the Bantu are the product of intermingling over
long periods of time between negro and hamite and
bushman and hottentot. Physically, therefore, they vary
greatly among themselves; but all their languages go
back, more or less obviously, to a common root. We do
not know the origins of this root.
Thus it is the last 2,000 years, more or less, that emerge
as the formative period of most of the peoples of conti¬
nental Africa. This is the period of their Iron Age.
Some authorities prefer to call this their Metal or
Palaeometallic Age, because, although knowledge of
ferrous metallurgy was the decisive influence, African
peoples also knew the working of several other minerals,
including gold and copper and tin. In time, too, some
of them worked extensively in brass and bronze; but they
knew, as ancient Asia and Europe had known, a Bronze
Age that made a long distinctive period of development
before their Iron Age.
© Herman J. Hahndiek,
Bilthoven, Netherlands
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1959
Now it is in studying this Metal Ageor, more narrowly,
the fifteen or sixteen centuries before European contact
along the coast that present research is principally and
dramatically engaged. Advancing along three different
but related lines, history and archaeology and anthropo¬
logy now begin to bring their findings together and to
offer a coherent picture that Was invisible only a handful
of years ago.
Anthropology in its wide sense comprehending the
study of language and institutions has embarked on a
systematic recording of the oral history of a significant
number of African peoples. Archaeology has at last turn¬
ed its attention to some of the major site-regions of
the continent. And history, working against the back¬
ground of this growing knowledge has renewed its study
of written sources, which, for the mediaeval period, are
mainly in Arabic, Portuguese, English and Chinese.
New translations edited with the new and fuller
knowledge of the past twenty years are now being pro¬
jected or prepared of several classic works, such as the
first century a.d. Periplus of the Erythraean Sea (in Bri¬
tain) and the 16th century writing's on the Western Sudan
of Leo Africanus (in France). The Central African Ar¬
chives (of the Federation of Central Africa) is collabora¬
ting with Arquivo Histórico de Mozambique in the editing
and publication of some 15,000 hitherto unpublished docu¬
ments from the libraries of Goa, Lisbon, and the Vatican;
and these, when they finally appear, should throw much
new light on early European contacts. Joseph Needham,
in his monumental study of the history of science in
China, has meanwhile devoted part of his sixth volume
due for publication in the not distant future to Chinese
maritime technology, and, in so doing, has shown how
great was the Chinese contribution to that Indian Ocean
trade which had its western terminals on the East African .
coast.
HIGH COLLARS of copper or beadwork rings tradi¬
tionally a major item of adornment among Africans are
still widely favoured. Left, woman of the N'dbele, a
Bantu people living in the Transvaal. Right, 12-inch
high Benin bronze from Nigeria (c. 17th century). It is
an example of numerous "choker" bronze heads, so called
on account of the high coral collars of Benin court dress.
African archaeology has had important successes in the
past few years. Mauny and Thomassey have gone far
towards completing the excavation of the ancient city of
Kumbi Saleh, probable site of the capital of mediaeval
Ghana. Lebeuf and Masson-Detourbet have uncovered
the remarkable bronze-using civilization of the Sao people
of early mediaeval Chad. Vercoutter, in the Sudan, has
completed a preliminary list of sites of the imposing civi¬
lisation of Kush. Other French specialists have continued
the investigation of early Ethiopia.
In British Africa Mathew and Freeman-Grenville have
listed ancient and mediaeval sites on the coast of Kenya
and Tanganyika, while Kirkman has excavated the late
mediaeval ruins of Gedi, near the Kenyan port of Malindi.
Further to the north, in Italian Somaliland, Cerulli and
Grottanelli have thrown important light on early settle¬
ments and migrations on the coast and coastal islands.
Throughout this large region there is good hope of pro¬
gress, if funds are forthcoming, not only of writing the
history of the coastal cities and trading stations which
flourished in pre-European times, but also of discovering
much more about the nature of their suppliers and mar¬
kets in the hinterland.
Coins and durable imports such as china offer hopeful
means of dating these many stone ruins of the coast and
interior. "I have never in my life," remarked Sir Morti¬
mer Wheeler after a fortnight's visit to Tanganyika in
1955, "seen so much broken china as I have seen in the past
fortnight along the coast here and the Kilwa Islands:
literally, fragments of Chinese porcelain by the shovelful...
In fact, I think it is fair to say that as far as the Middle
Ages are concerned, from the tenth century onwards, the
buried history of Tanganyika is written in Chinese por¬
celain."
To the southward there is fresh effort at uncovering
the story of another great complex of stone ruins forts
and huts and vast hillside terrace systems that stretch
© British Museum.
over several thousands of square miles in Southern Rho¬
desia and neighbouring lands. Summers has lately com¬
pleted an initial survey of the stone ruins of Inyanga on
the Rhodesian-Mozambique border; and now, with Robin¬
son, is working on the foundations of the great walls at
Zimbabwe in the hope of finding out whether those tall
ruins were built on the site of a previous and more humble
culture, or whether the first settlers were also those who
built so well in stone. A full list of all the sites that
archaeologists have looked at in the past twenty years
or so, and are looking at now, would fill many pages.
Even so, we are only at the beginning of this search
for the history of pre-mediaeval and mediaeval Africa.
Beyond the barriers of ignorance we may glimpse an his¬
torical landscape that is thick with cities or strong stone
settlements and loud with the din of ports and ocean¬
going shipping, that glitters with old armies and the pomp
of states and empires and is restless with the rise and fall
of dynasties and powers. But at present we can do little
more than glimpse at this.
What is now required can be stated bluntly in a few
words: it is more money and a closer co-ordination of
effort. As to money, resources even in favoured territories
are almost always slender; and many potentially fruitful
territories are still a void on the archaeological map.
Next to nothing, for example, is known of the archaeology
of Portuguese West and East Africa; yet both may have
much to contribute, the first to a study of the origins of
the stone-building civilizations of southern Africa, and
the second to a study of the links between these and the
trading cities of the Indian Ocean seaboard.
Yet this great taäk of unravelling the African past re¬
mains, and must remain, an international endeavour.
Occasional conferences on African pre-history and history
have proved, over the past few years, how much can be
gained from the pooling of knowledge and the wide dis¬
cussion of problems. They have stimulated public interest,
and helped to create an atmosphere that is favourable to
more intensive research. It is to be hoped that they are
only the forerunners of many others of their kind. To
this end, indeed, Unesco can powerfully contribute.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
by Henri Bart
Ninety-one years ago a wandering hunter named Adam
Renders returned southward from the unexplored
lands of what would become Southern Rhodesia,
beyond the river Limpopo, and made himself famous
with a strange tale. Not far. beyond the river, not as
much as 200 miles beyond it, he had seen tall grey ruins in
the bush. He could say little more than that, for he had
never seen such walls and towers before; but the tale
passed round, and grew the stranger as it passed, and
those who heard it reckoned that Africa had once,again
sprung one of its surprises. A hidden civilization in the
northern plains: who could have expected that? "-
A German geologist called Mauch was next to see this
mystery in towering stone. Four years after Renders, he
in his turn came back across the Limpopo and declared
that he had seen a fortress on a hilltop that was surely a
copy of King Solomon's temple on Mount Moriah; below
it, in the valley, he had seen a great building in stone that
was just as surely a copy of the palace in which the Queen
of Sheba had dwelt at Jerusalem in the 10th century b.c.
. The story spread across the world. Thirteen years after
Mauch's return, an unknown writer called Rider Haggard
made name and fortune with a book called King Solo¬
mon's Mines, a fine romantic tale of diamonds and Africa.
And a few years later the land was opened for European
occupation by an invading British column, and many more
reports came back. Yet Renders and Mauch, it seemed,
had not exaggerated: the ruins really were tall and spa¬
cious and inexplicable. Could any African "native"
have built them? The idea seemed absurd. Here an
alien hand had been at Work: another and much earlier
conqueror from outside. England Was only entering on
that vanished conqueror's heritage.
Gold rush in the ' Land of Ophir '
QCy ODAY then", wrote one of the pioneers of 1891, the
I year When the British took possession of these
lands to the north of the Limpopo, "The English¬
man is in the land of Ophir opening afresh the treasure
house of antiquity... (and soon) we may expect to see the
image of Queen Victoria stamped on the gold with which
King Solomon overlaid his ivory throne, and wreathed the
cedar pillars of his temple."
And then it was discovered that the ruins of Zimbabwe
were not alone. Little by little, as pioneering columns
pushed northward across the plains and spread away on
either side, men stumbled on many other such ruins: none
of them so large and splendid as Zimbabwe, but all of
them bearing an undeniable stamp of dignity and civic
strength.
Yet if this was the Land of Ophir, the source of all those
talents of gold which the Queen of Sheba gave to Solomon,
surely much of it must still remain? Many asked them¬
selves this question; and many hastened northwards in
the hope of treasure. They found unmistakable signs of
ancient mining: hundreds, even thousands, of aban¬
doned mine Workings thirty or sixty feet deep or so, scat¬
tered across the land. They staked new claims; and they
were not always disappointed.
Others took -an easier road to wealth. They plundered
the ruins. A prospector called Neal teamed up with a
couple of hopeful investors In Johannesburg to form an
Ancient Ruins Company Limited, and managed to loot
500 ounces of worked gold from burials in the ruins of
Rhodesia before high authority, realizing what precious
knowledge was probably being lost for ever with the gold,
ordered them to stop. That was in 1900. "But the
damage done", wrote the late J.F. Schofield, "was immense,
for everything except the gold was treated in a- most
reckless manner" while the gold, or most of it, was
melted down and sold.
When it came to explaining the origin of these ruins
and mine workings, the "legend of Ophir" for long led. the
field. Amateur archaeologists, eagerly investigating
these ruins with their minds full of remote antiquity,
declared they were Sabaean and Phoenician. They belong¬
ed, that is, to a period going back some thousand years
and more beyond the beginning of the Christian era.
These towers and battlements, it was said, were manifest¬
ly the work of civilizing intruders from the north, from
beyond the seas: they were not the work of native Afri¬
cans. Nothing like them, after all, existed anywhere in
southern Africa: nor was it in any case thinkable, it
was added, that the savage ancestors of these savage
natives whom Europeans were even then subduing with
such toil and bloodshed could ever have raised such monu¬
ments to a civilized past.
But a few others were not of this opinion. On the
contrary replied Selous, some of these Africans are still
building in stone in much the same way: and some of
them are still sinking mines. It was hard to deny autho¬
rity to Selous, for none of the wandering hunters of those
pioneering days knew the country half so well. The con¬
troversy raged.
Impressed by the bitterness of argument,, the British
Association entered the fray in 1905. It appointed a train-
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1959
ed archaeologist called David Randall-Maclver to make
a report on these much disputed ruins. Maclver's find¬
ings added fuel to the flames. He dismissed as nonsense
the claims of ancient or foreign origin: the ruins, he said,
could be proved to be relatively modern dating perhaps
to the 14th or 15th century a.d. and in his opinion they
were undoubtedly the work of native Africans.
The "Ophir-ites" were not dismayed. They returned
to the charge. And they returned with such good effect
that a quarter of a century later, in 1929, the British
Association appointed another trained archaeologist
whose work, it was thought, must surely carry conviction.
To the south of Salisbury, capital of Southern Rhodesia, lie the ruins
of G-eat Zimbabwe, former capital of a powerful Negro state. With
its massive stone walls, terraced battlements and towers, Zimbabwe
is only onethough the best preserved of a score of ruins in Rhodesia
which, together with even more numerous sites where gold, copper,
iron and tin were mined, prove that an age of metals grew and flowered
across some 12 centuries before Europeans entered a land they thought
entirely savage. Vital evidence about the Negro civilization which
built Zimbabwe was lost when gold, jewels and other objects were
looted from the ruins towards the end of the I 9th century. Mapun-
gubwe, another site to the south in the Transvaal escaped this fate and
important finds of gold and other objects made here have thrown
light on the metal culture that gave birth to this city. At Zimbabwe
two buildings stand out. One, the "Acropolis" (top of opposite page),
was a hilltop stronghold built into a natural mass of rocks. The other,
"the elliptical building" (above), rests on the plain below, its massive
girdling walls 30 feet high and 20 feet thick. Among the remains
which have been found within the ramparts is a conical tower (left),
at the foot of which important findings have recently been made.
Photos Office the High Commissioner for the Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland
Three years later Miss Gertrude Caton-Thömpson publish¬
ed her great book, The Zimbabwe Culture, and confirmed
the substance of everything that Maclver had said about
Zimbabwe. The ruins, she found, were mediaeval in date
and Bantu in origin! They were probably a little older
than Maclver had thought; but not by much.
Stone monuments to, an Iron Age
Even in face of this and Miss Caton-Thompson's book
has since become the "Bible" of all serious archaeolo¬
gical investigation in southern Africa for the relative¬
ly modern perioda few wishful-thinking romantics still
cling to the legend of Ophir. All authorities now accept the
general conclusions which Miss Caton-Thompson reached.
A radio-carbon dating from pieces of timber, taken from
the base of the main encircling wall at Zimbabwe, suggests
that some structure was already here in the fith or 8th
century a.d.: and the general time-scale of these ruins is
now agreed to refer to a period ranging from about 500 a.d.
to about 1750 a.d. Valuable information tending to the
same conclusion has come from the painstaking work of
Mr. Roger Summers, Keeper of the National Museums of
Southern Rhodesia, and his colleagues.
What, then, should one think about this most remark¬
able complex of stone ruins in a land where people had
never been known to have built in stone, nor possessed
the civic coherence to need and justify such palaces and
forts and chiefly dwelling places? The answer of the
experts is that these many ruins of Rhodesia, with Great
Zimbabwe most prominent among them, mark the early
growth and steady flowering of an Iron Age an age of
metals across some twelve centuries before Europeans
entered on a land they thought entirely savage (see page
20). They are the solid and indisputable fragments of a
truly African civilization which, if illiterate and technic¬
ally limited, nonetheless offers once again proof of the
skill and ingenuity of men who are thrown, as these Afri¬
cans were thrown, almost entirely on their own resources.
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Great forest kingdom
of mediaeval Nigeria
BENIN
by K. Onwonwu Dike
Director, Benin Scheme, Dept. of History
University College, Ibadan, Nigeria
N
1 ^ owadays more and more African schol¬
ars working in African colleges are
helping to lift the veil which has so
long obscured the past history and culture of their continent.
One example is to be found in the Department of History
at University College, Ibadan, in Nigeria where, since 1956,
a team of researchers has been piecing together the story
of the great mediaeval Nigerian kingdom of Benin under the
leadership of a distinguished African, Dr. Onwonwu Dike,
Professor of History at University College. In the absence
I2
MOUNTED WARRIOR
and his steed was made by
a craftsman of the Benin
Kingdom in Nigeria where
remarkable techniques of
bronze casting were deve¬
loped many centuries ago.
More than a dozen of
these figures of warriors and
chiefs mounted on horses or
mules are known and may
be attributed to the 1 7th
or early 1 8th century.
Photo by Eliot Elisfon./rom " The
Sculpture of Africa ", © Thames
and Hudson, Ltd., London, 1 958
of written archives, the Benin researchers are experimenting
in a new historical technique: the abundant use of unwritten
sources such as archaeological evidence, oral traditions,
linguistic findings, ethnographic data and material artefacts.
It is hoped through intensive study of Benin's history and
culture to evolve techniques and general principles which
should guide scholars working on the history of non-literate
African peoples. Here, Dr. Dike tells the story of Benin,
an ancient Nigerian kingdom, its institutions and culture, and
the remarkable flowering of art to which it gave expression.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1959
The Kingdom of Benin is undoubtedly one of the most
ancient Nigerian Kingdoms and before the advent
of Europeans perhaps the most powerful state in
Southern Nigeria. It remains the best example of an
African forest kingdom which originated and developed
away from all Arab and European influence.
From Nigerian standards Benin is very rich in oral
tradition and material artefacts. There are, for example,
the works of art in bronze, ivory, wood, iron, pottery and
other materials for which Benin is justly famed
throughout the world; Works which reveal a superb
degree of artistry and technical skills and which were
fully developed before the coming of Europeans. This art
was produced at the command of the Obas (Kings of
Benin) to commemorate outstanding events and persons
of their reigns and the results are, consequently, invalu¬
able historical records provided they can be properly
interpreted.
Finally Benin is one of the few West African kingdoms
that maintained contact with the trading Europeans
from the 15th century. The Portuguese arrived in 1485
and were followed by the Dutch, the French and the
English. Spaniards, Danes and Brandenburgers occa¬
sionally joined in the scramble for Benin pepper, ivory,
slaves and palm oil. But the contact between Benin and
Europe from 1485 to 1897 was largely commercial; and
contact of this kind produced business letters, ships logs,
personal letters, diaries and an occasional official report.
Since the 15th century persistent but intermittent efforts
were made by Roman Catholic Missions to establish
outposts in Benin and because of that contact missionary
archives may yield useful material on Benin history.
The work of the Benin scheme is in the early stages
and much of the history of the Kingdom still lies buried
in legend and oral tradition, illustrated in brass and
ivory, represented in existing customs and ceremonial, or
alluded to in the records of traders and missionaries.
When these sources are fully unearthed new light will
be thrown on the history of Benin. At this stage only a
very brief account of this mediaeval West African king¬
dom can be attempted here.
The ancient Kingdom of Benin, which maintained its
independence until 1897 (when it was overthrown by a
British punitive expedition) was situated in the tropical
rain forest of West Africa, bounded on the east by the
River Niger and the vast swamplands of the Niger delta,
on the south by the sea, to the west by the Yoruba king¬
doms of Oyo and Ijebu, and to the north by the savannah
lands where cavalry came into its own. When and how
the Kingdom ¡was founded can only be conjectured, for
the Bims were a non-literate people, and the first Euro¬
pean who visited them in 1486 found the Kingdom at the
height of its power with traditions reaching far into the
past.
Reigning king 35th of his line
Those traditions which the Binis still remember do not
refer to any general migration, but they agree that a
first dynasty of kings came to them from Ife (pro¬
nounced "eefay"). the spiritual capital of the Yoruba
peoples. Most of the stories concerning the twelve kings
of this first dynasty nave a mythical and magical cha¬
racter which throws little light on the history of Benin.
Their rule is said to have been ended by a revolt that es¬
tablished a short-lived republican form a government.
Before long a new ruler from Ife established himself
in Benin either by force or, as tradition maintains, by
invitation. He founded the dynasty of kings (or Obas,
as they are known in Benin) which has ruled until the
present day, the reigning Oba being the 35th of his line.
The names of all these rulers is still recited, with minor
variations, and the arrival in 1386 of the first European,
the Portuguese Joao Afonso d'Aveiro, is usually placed
in the reign of the 15th Oba, Ozolua. So that the most
probable date for the founding of the new dynasty would
seem to be sometime in the 12th century.
The greatest Obas united in their persons the spiritual,
political and military leadership of their people. They
enjoyed absolute religious and political authority over
their subjects, to whom their person was sacred and
endowed with magical powers. An elaborate ritual which
surrounded every act of the Oba, even his eating and
sleeping, kept him withdrawn in his palace save on great
ceremonial occasions, and thereby heightened the awe
of his people. As high priest of the nation, on his per
formance of numerous ceremonies in honour of the goäa,
the royal ancestors and his Own divine attributes hung the
fate of the harvest and the well-being of the nation.
Certain groups of priests participated in these ceremonies,
many of which involved human sacrifice, but there was
no priestly caste able to wield divine sanctions against
an Oba.
To his mystical powers the Oba joined a political abso¬
lutism limited only by his ability to impose his will
through force and religious sanctions. Justice, legislation
and the conduct of all political business within and
without the Kingdom lay in his hands. In practice, even
the ablest or most ruthless of rulers was compelled to
seek advice from important men in the kingdom and
palace and eventually a royal council emerged composed
of three groups of title holders.
A royal agent in every village
One group traced its origin to the first dynasty and its
seven titles were hereditary. The other two "town
chiefs" and "palace chiefs" owed their origin to the
reigning dynasty, were hardly ever hereditary, but were
bestowed by the Oba on whom he pleased and added to
or altered whenever political expediency dictated.
Besides advising the Oba, the members of these title
groups individually or in groups performed all ritual and
administrative duties.
The oldest order, the Uzama, installed the Oba and its
members were responsible for the conduct of wars, the
watch on a city gateway and the welfare of the heir to
the throne. Among the "town chiefs" were the second-
in-command of the army and the priest of the people.
The principal duties of the "palace chiefs" were to super¬
vise the royal wardrobe and act as personal servants to
the Oba. All title groups included warrior chiefs among
their members.
To make his power effective in the numerous small
towns and villages scattered in the dense forest, the Oba
appointed a title holder in Benin to be responsible for a
town, a group of villages, a single village or an even
smaller unit. It was the duty of this man to act as
intermediary between the Oba and his subjects in the
collection and delivery to the palace of the tribute of
foodstuffs for which the village or group was assessed.
He also acted as spokesman for his group whenever they
wished to communicate directly with the Oba.
The tribute of foodstuffs was not the sole economic
support of the elaborate court in Benin: large numbers
of slaves laboured for the Oba in Benin and in villages
and farm settlements throughout the Kingdom. He
gathered, too, a large revenue from his monopoly of the
most important articles of external trade, notably slaves,
ivory and palm ¡kernels.
Religion as well as the law guarded these privileges for
him. The advent of European traders made the mono¬
polies still more profitable, and usually they ensured that
the Oba was the richest man in his kingdom. Even so
an enterprising man could amass great wealth, and there
are stories of such men who lost their riches and their
lives at the hands of a jealous monarch.
Benin City, the capital of the Kingdom, lay within a
high earthen wall and deep ditch roughly rectangular
in shape and enclosing an area some three miles across.
Broad, straight avenues crossed the city from gate to
gate at right angles, lined neatly by houses built of the
local red earth in a distinctive style. An outer and inner
rectangular wall roofed with a thatch of leaves provided
living quarters and left in the middle of the house an open
sunken courtyard from which the torrential rain could
be drained, and around which the overhang of the roof
afforded the use of an open verandah.
Altars for the worship of one or more of an elaborate
pantheon of gods were incorporated in the house, the
choice of deity depending upon the predilection or duty
of the owner. Most important of the deities were a high
god, the god of the sea, the god of iron, the god of medi¬
cine, the god of death, the god of fertility and the god
of divination. But the most personal aspect of Bini reli¬
gion was represented in each house by an altar for the
worship of the spirits of the owner's ancestors, who were
daily propitiated, consulted and honoured.
The more important the man, the more elaborate would
be his house, so that the greater title-holders might own
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
BENIN
(Continued)
An advanced civilization
deep in the tropical forest
many buildings grouped together within a wall, but still
adhering to the general pattern. The palace of the Oba
which stood entirely apart from the rest of the city, was
the largest and most complex of all. In general plan it
consisted of a number of very large courtyards surrounded
by high Iwalls and Verandahs. Each courtyard [was
entered by a gateway surmounted by a high pitched
roof covered with wooden shingles and crowned |with
a large brass snake.
In the apartments around the courtyards lived the
palace officials, servants and the Oba's guard. Stables
for the royal horses were ranged around another court¬
yard, while in the inmost parts of the palace and
inaccessible to most visitors, were the quarters of the Oba
and his harem. Shrines and altars for the worship of
the deities and the royal ancestors were prominent
everywhere, and most were magnificently decorated with
carved ivory tusks and brass heads and figures of superb
workmanship. Brasswork illustrating the deeds of heroes
and kings also adorned many Wooden roof supports and
carved beams within the palace.
Tribute sustained a costly state
Brasswork, ivory carving, iron work, wood carving
leather work, weaving, drum making, etc. all neces¬
sary to the ceremonial of the palace was the specia¬
lized work of distinct and highly-organised guilds, each of
which occupied a particular street in the city. Each had
its own hierarchy of titles, a system of apprenticeship and
its own communal shrine. Some, especially the brass-
workers and ivory carvers, worked almost exclusively for
the Oba and a few important title-holders. Thus a high
proportion of the population of Benin City was engaged
in the service of the palace.
In order to sustain the economy of this highly cen¬
tralised and elaborate government, the Obas had to exact
heavy tribute from their subjects and ensure a steady
inflow of slaves. The latter need and the struggle to
extend the frontiers kept the Kingdom constantly at
war with its neighbours. As late as the sixteenth century
the Oba himself accompanied his warriors and directed
campaigns, and in this way carried Benin to the height
of its power. Later Obas were confined more strictly
to the palace and the conduct of war passed into the
hands of title-holders.
Benin warriors depicted by the brassworkers are
equipped with sword, spear and shield. At the beginning
of the sixteenth century the lure of firearms brought a
hard-pressed Oba to send ambassadors to Portugal, but
since the Papacy had forbidden the export of arms to
infidels, he had first to receive Christian missionaries.
For brief periods different Catholic missions seemed to
make headway in converting the princes and sons of
noblemen, they may even have begun to build a church,
then either the Oba ceased to need Portuguese arms, or
else he felt his supernatural power undermined, for the
priests Were compelled to leave.
It is noteworthy that the great period of Benin expan¬
sion coincided With the introduction of firearms by the
Portuguese in the reigns of Ozolua, Esigie and Orhogba.
Ozolua conquered- large areas in the Agbor, Kukuruku, Ora
and Ekiti districts. The Benin army occupied and spread
Benin influence in places as far apart as Idah, Lagos,
Akotogbo, Ikale and Agenebode. Portuguese missionaries
reported that they accompanied the Oba to the Idah war
in 1515-1516. Groups of Benin migrants fleeing from
oppression at home settled in various parts of Southern
Nigeria. Thus the Kingdom of Warri was founded by
Prince Ginuwa from Benin, in the reign of Oba Olua
and parts of the Niger Delta and the Urhobo country
were according to Benin tradition, settled by Benin
emigrants.
Within a century Portuguese traders were joined by
French, English and Dutch who bought thousands of
slaves for the American plantations as well as ivory and
pepper. It became necessary for the Obas of Benin to
increase the supply of slaves in order to feed this market,
and the fact they Were less successful in doing so than
many other West African states may indicate that the
power of Benin declined from the end of the sixteenth
century. Certainly artistic skill, as manifested in brass-
casting, deteriorated and the city itself was more than
once devastated by civil war.
Although the power of Benin evidently declined in the
last century of independence, the Kingdom did preserve
its ancient institutions and culture essentially unchanged
up to the time of its fall. In themselves these institu¬
tions and culture are Well Worthy of study, for they
present" us with a detailed picture of a tropical-forest
civilization which, despite the difficulties of environment,
evolved a complex political and social structure based on
a divine kingship whose sway extended over a great area.
Intrinsically too the culture merits our attention, for in
their best Work the craftsmen of Benin gave inspired
expression to the values which underlay their civilization.
THE FIRST EUROPEAN
to/Visit the Benin Kingdom
of West Africa in I486
found this realm at the
height of its power with
traditions reaching far back
into the past. Benin City,
capital of the Kingdom,
enclosed behind its high
earthen wall an area some
three miles across on which
straight avenues crossed from
gate to gate, lined by houses
built of the local red earth.
Right, a European impres¬
sion of Benin City depicted
in an engraving published
in Dapper's "Description of
Africa" in Amsterdam in
1686. It shows the "Oba"
or King of Benin leaving the
city in ceremonial proces¬
sion. (The present Oba is
the 3 5th of this same
dynasty). On the left are
buildings of the royal palace.
Musée de l'Homme, Paris
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1959
Photos© William Fage
IVORY MASKS (above right) are probably the most valuable works of West African Benin art in existence. The nearer of the
two was sold last year for £20,000 to the Museum of Primitive Art, New York, the other being in the British Museum, where this
photo was taken. Nine inches in height, the masks were probably made in the 16th century to be worn at the king's waist in the
annual ceremony of banishing evil spirits. Above left, three carved posts before the throne of the Ogoga of Ikere in eastern Yoru-
baland (neighbour to Benin). They were carved about 40 years ago by Olowe of Ise, one of the great Yoruba masters of modern times.
Ife & Benin
TWO PINNACLES OF AFRICAN ART
by William Fagg
Deputy Keeper, Dept. of Ethnography, British Museum
The extraordinary growth of museums and still more,
in Malraux's phrase, of "museums without walls" or
reproductions of art in book form has put at our
disposal not only the fine arts of the high civilizations of
Europe and Asia, but also the far more varied arts of the
tribal cultures all over the world.
These have been discovered and appreciated by
travellers and ethnologists during the past three centuries,
and especially in the last seventy years, but it is chiefly
thanks to the modern movement in art that we are now
able to think of them on the same plane as the high arts
of Eurasia. The term "primitive art" (though still often
used for want of a better) no longer refers to the bottom
rungs of a ladder at whose top stand Praxiteles and
Qonatello.
But the chief centres for this new appreciation of the
tribal arts (as I prefer to call them) were in France and
Germany, and later in Belgium, and thus, by historical
accident, it was ¡works from the colonies of these powers
which chiefly caught the eye of the modern artists, and
also occupied most of the plates in the picture books which
appeared in ever-increasing numbers from 1915 onwards.
The arts of the western Sudan, the Ivory Coast, the
Cameroons and the Congo received full recognition, but
those of the most prolific and populous of all the African
territories Nigeria remained, with one notable excep¬
tion, hidden under a veil of ignorance, simply because they
were not well enough represented at the centres where
modern art was in ferment.
The exception was the art of Benin, which had burst
upon the civilized world with such disconcerting force
after the discoveries of the 1897 British Expedition that
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Musée de l'Homme, Paris
HEADS FROM A HOLY CITY. These terracotta heads fashioned between seven and eight centuries ago, were discovered
recently by British archaeologists on the site of Ife, the holy city of the Yoruba people in Nigeria. Used to decorate sacrificial altars,
they illustrate the Yoruba taste for naturalistic representation with a scrupulous respect for anatomical proportions. Loaned by
the Oni (king and religious leader) of Ife they were photographed here during a special exhibition at the Musée de l'Homme, Pans.
IFE & BENIN
(Continued)
BRONZE-CASTING WORTHY OF CELLINI
it could not be ignored. Yet although it included some
of the very finest works of African art, the greater part
of its enormous output was unworthy of much of the
praise which was lavished upon it, and was moreover
unrepresentative, as we shall see, of the essential nature
of African art in general. Nevertheless, the realization,
with general amazement, that Africans could perform
such complicated feats of bronze-casting (worthy, as one
authority put it, of Cellini) did much to prepare the way
for the acceptance of tribal art in the art world'of Europe
a few years later.
Research has been proceeding apace on the antiquities
of Nigeria, especially since the Second World War. Only
a part of these recent researches, by many fieldworkers,
is as yet published, but enough is known for us to present
a summary picture of Nigerian art which is remarkable
for its chronological depth and suggests that Nigeria
was the scene of some of the most striking developments
in all African art history.
Nigeria is known to have been inhabited in Lower
Palaeolithic times, perhaps a quarter of a million years
ago, but the first known appearance of art there and
the earliest art in all Negro Africa to which we can assign
a datewas in the first millennium b.c. This was the
extraordinary terra-cotta sculpture of the Ndk Culture
(discovered in the tin mines near Jos on the plateau of
Central Africa in 1943 by Bernard Fagg, now Director of
Antiquities in Nigeria), which was recently shown by the
Carbon-14 testthat happy by-product of the atomic
bomb to have flourished during the period 900 B.c. to
A.D. 200.
Sculptures in this style have now been identified oyer
a very large area of central Nigeria, at least 300 miles
wide, and We have no reason to think that the limits of
its distribution have yet been reached. Though there is a
certain superficial similarity to some Etruscan Work, any
historical connexion between the two is in the last degree
improbable; and a study of the hundreds of fragmentary
heads and 'figures in the Jos Museum reveals an
astonishing degree of artistic invention, especially in the
imaginative treatment of the human ¡head in terms of
cones, cylinders, spheres and many other conceptual,
forms, which idoes not suggest that this art can be
attached to any other known tradition. In particular, no
connexion has been found With ancient Egyptian art, and
it is not inconceivable that its antecedents go even farther
back than the Pre-dynastic Period, when Itribal art was
expiring in Egypt.
It seems that the Nok Culture may not have died
without issue, but may rather have formed a kind of
artistic substratum from which later sculptural traditions
in the Nigerian area drew some of their sustenance. The
16
Sao Culture, which was excavated by J.P. Lebeuf in French
territory to the east and south of Lake Chad and which
seems to have flourished during the Middle Ages of
Europe, does not appear to owe anything to Nok, although
excavations projected by the Department of Antiquities
in Nigerian Bornu might possibly establish a link.
There is, however, a strong possibility that the World-
famous art of Ife derived in part from Nok. The Yoruba
tribes, who made Ife their holy city and to (whom we
almost certainly owe the marvellous bronzes and terra¬
cottas which are found there, seem to be latecomers to
the Nigerian scene, most of them probably having arrived,
no doubt from an easterly direction, during the first
millenium after Christ.
. It may be that the aboriginal people with Whom the
Yoruba warriors intermarried after conquering them had
inherited from the Nok people the skill of making large
pottery figures for their shrines; the more sophisticated
and materialistic Yoruba hierarchy of Ife may then have
developed a taste for naturalistic representation. Such
at least is the impression gained
from a close study of the
fragments from Nok and Ife.
These alone among the past or
present cultures of Negro Africa
have attempted life-size statues
in terra-cotta; and although
they treated the human head
in very different ways, the
bodies and their copious orn¬
aments are very much alike.
But such speculations can
hardly be confirmed in the
present state of our knowledge.
Ife art is dated to about the
twelfth to fourteenth centuries
chiefly on the basis of the trad¬
ition accepted at Benin that
the Oni of Ife sent a master
bronze-founder to his fellow
ruler, the Oba Oguola of Benin,
perhaps about a.D. 1350-1400,
to teach his people the craft.
This tradition squares plausibly
enough with a comparison of
the styles; the earliest extant
heads from Benin seem hardly
less naturalistic than those of
Ife, although they show a
diminishing interest in prob¬
lems of representing bony struc¬
ture and fleshy contours, besides
some technical differences.
I Musée de l'Homme, Paris
PENDANT MASK from
Benin, Nigeria. Head wears
a band of coral beads and
is crowned by a carved
"halo" of stylized catfish.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Octobe 1959
With Benin art wé leave prehistory behind and reach
the realm of proto-history and later, when the Portuguese
arrive there in 1486, of history itself (although the tribal
history still has a large content of legend).
A series of great warrior kings had established at Benin
by the late fifteenth century an absolutist regime Which
subsisted, with minor fluctuations, until 1897, and, in its
forms, to the present time. At that time, the apogee of
Benin power, there took place, I surmise, a subtle but vital
deviation from the classical or "pure" form of divine
kingship in which king and people are the interdependent
parts of an indissoluble unity of tribal life force.
At Benin, as in early Dynastic Egypt, I think that this
balance was upset and the king became an end in himself,
even though the outward forms of the divine kingship
were in both cases, and at Benin still are, maintained;
the people continued to depend on the ¡king for their
wellbeing, but the king's Will was no longer subordinate
to that end. And this was to have profound effects on
Bini art during the next four centuries.
Benin art as it is generally known is not really tribal
art at all; it is the art of the royal court, an alien art
transplanted from the more sophisticated urban culture
of Ife. Dynamism is absent, or virtually
so, from this style, as it was also from
the art of Ife that strange florescence
of idealized naturalism, indigenous or
imported. Rather it inherited from Ife
art its essentially static quality, and for
perhaps one or two centuries the court
artists (whether Yoruba or Bini) kept
alive this humanistic mode of art, pro¬
ducing many works technically and
artistically worthy of Ife, and a few,
such as the priceless ivory masks, which
are the truly distinctive contribution of
Benin to the world's masterpieces.
But as the Benin kingdom begins,
about the late sixteenth century, to
decline from its apogee, we see a corres¬
ponding change in the court style :
uniformity supplants the individualized
variety of the Ife style; the bronzes
grow heavier and more massive and a
kind of defensive stolidity seems to
express a need to make up with outward
pomp for the loss of real power.
In this middle period, with inexhaus¬
tible supplies of European bronze, the
Oba's bronze-founders produced, within
perhaps 150 years, not only a great
many bronze heads and figures in the
"round, but the great series of rectangu¬
lar plaques, numbering many hundreds,
which seem to have commemorat¬
ed noteworthy events and personages.
These works are consistently impressive,
in a manner somewhat reminiscent of Assyrian sculpture,
and similarly lacking in any really free exercise of the
artist's imagination. In short, this period, on which the
fame of Benin chiefly rests, is one of high competence
rather than of brilliance.
Throughout the middle period, the aesthetic canons of
Ife seem still to have exerted enough influence in the
bronze-workers' guild to maintain strict standards of
pleasing proportion; but suddenly, perhaps towards the
middle eighteenth century, these standards seem to
collapse, giving (way to increasing flamboyance and
exaggeration, and above all to an undisciplined variability
of design, technique and quality. In this, the late period,
which lasted to the end of the nineteenth century and
the birth of the tourist trade, there are rare works which
show the hand of a master, but the great majority are
ugly and badly executed, by mediocre or inferior artists
With no safely classical uniformity to fall back upon.
From all that We know of Benin political history in this
period, it appears that the court style in its decadence
faithfully represented the increasing deterioration of the
state. We find examples of this dating from the time of
Oba Osemwenede (1816-1848), whose reign coincided with
the contraction of the slave trade from an international
to a much less lucrative local commerce. (Contrary to a
widespread belief, the arts of Africa seem to have suffered
more from the abolition of the trade than from its earlier
excesses.)
At about the same time the beautiful wooden ram and
© Musée de l'Homme, Paris
DANCE HEADDRESS of the Ekoi
of Southern Nigeria. Masks like this
are used at festivals and funerals.
From the National Museum, Stockholm.
antelope heads in the tribal style, which Edo chiefs place
on the altars of their ancestors, began to be supplanted in
Benin City itself, with the Oba's permission, by wooden
imitations of the bronze heads used in the royal cult; and
thus after some four centuries the alien tradition which
began at Ife at last penetrated and leavened not to its
advantage the tribal style in the capital and its environs,
though fine examples of the old style may still be seen in
many outlying areas of the kingdom.
Yet the immense artistic output of the Bini tribe is only
a small part of that of Nigeria, and the least representative
part because of the dual character already described.
Far more numerous and more varied are the Works in
bronze, iron, ivory and above all wood of the five millions
of the Yoruba tribe, the most prolific in art in all Africa.
Yoruba wood sculpture is among the more naturalistic
styles of African a,rt, but it is impossible to say whether its
naturalism is derived from the style of Ife or whether that
style was a specialization which developed there within an
already existing Yoruba tradition.
Of the hundreds of thousands of carvings still extant
in Yorubaland, all but a few are immediately recognizable
as Yoruba work by the use of certain conventions, as in
the form of the mouth; yet the variety
of sculptural forms employed by the
artists is immense and it is possible by
careful fieldwork to distinguish the
styles and substyles of different areas,
towns, families and individual carvers
in the same way and by much the same
methods as is done by the art his¬
torians of Europe.
The richness of Yoruba art must be
closely connected with the great
complexity of Yoruba religion, which is
perhaps the most "advanced" to be
found in Africa and is rather like the
Hindu and Ancient Greek religions in
the way in which ancient and imper¬
sonal nature deities have been humaniz¬
ed and have even come to be regarded
as deified kings or heroes.
Only in recent years have we become
aware that there flourished in the lower
Niger Valley a group of bronze-found¬
ing industries whose works are quite
independent of the Benin court style
and show a far greater artistic imagi¬
nation. Perhaps the finest example is
the figure of a huntsman, collected at
Benin in 1897 and now in the British
Museum. Many of the pieces seem
related to the work of the Ijebu Yoruba
to the west of Benin, but others seem
to lead us east to places on the Niger
itself such as Idah. Here lies scope
for great advances in the study of Ni¬
gerian art history. In the Delta itself are the Ijo, who
are thought on linguistic and other grounds to be one of
the earliest of Nigerian populations; their wood sculpture,
concerned mostly With water spirits and snakes, is a pre¬
eminent example of something very like Cubism in tribal
art. The Ibo, who form most of the population of Eastern
Nigeria, are probably almost as numerous as the Yoruba,
but rather less prolific in art.
Of all the African territories Nigeria is the richest not
only in the extant products of traditional art but also in
its practice, although the number of carvers in the tribal
styles continues to diminish, and their work too seldom
equals that of their fathers. Fortunately, the devoted
work during the past 20 years of a few British servants of
Nigeria, and the increasing appreciation of Nigerians in
authority, have given the country the best-equipped
museums service and the finest museum collections in
Africa between the Sahara and the Zambezi. Research
schemes under the direction of scholarly Nigerians, with
valuable financial help from abroad, are making
important contributions to our knowledge of Bini and
Yoruba history, including art history.
There is urgent need to encourage all such efforts, for
the field still to be covered before it is too late remains
immense. Any people in the world can as Nigeria also
does produce contemporary artists working in the inter¬
national styles; only Nigeria can make the unique
contribution to the sum of beauty in the world which
derives from her millennia of tribal art.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1959
TREASURES IN BRONZE
(iW ê
»it ,
i %
y**%$(É
m /
#tó¡
\MP^/}-
^t:/,,-l»* ^
R*¥* íí I V
V * t£
ijwSsDä
'i- ' ¡I
Before the coming oí the European to Africa, a great
civilization flourished in Nigeria which produced a
remarkable bronze art. The Kingdoms of Benin and
Yorubaland and the city of Ife are rightly famous for
the many masterpieces in bronze which have come
IBs», down to us, and some of which are shown here. Left,
- casting found at Benin of a huntsman returning from
"3 the chase with his dog and carrying a dead waterbuck.
, n Above, two leopards, the symbol of kingly power,
- jtT'-^/ff T 1 are among the most technically perfect of Benin
-«f '"leí '& casf'n9s' Right, Yoruba memorial figure. This cast-
i. Í ing, found in 1938, with seventeen brass heads, prob
ably represents an early Oni (divine king) of the city-
state of Ife. Regalia, with exception of the crown, are
like those used by modern Onis at their coronation.
Photos : Eliot Elisofon © Thames and Hudson, Ltd., London 1958.
"t-t-rl *t-¿~',¿
^mwtouw
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
THE MARCH
OF IRON
A CONTINENT
by R.R. Inskeep
Keeper of Prehistory, The Rhodes Livingstone Museum
Livingstone (Northern Rhodesia)
Everywhere in the ancient world the development
of iron metallurgy was a revolutionary advance that
permitted men to build new and more complex so¬
cieties. Africa was no exception to this rule. It
saw the rise of great African kingdoms equipped
with a new mastery over the soil and the forest and
over their non-iron-using neighbours. This iron¬
work was the product of home industries practised
for generations and which originally owed nothing
to the white man. It is now known that great iron
civilizations developed as early as the beginnings
of the Christian era in at least two widely separated
regions of the continent: one in West Africa (the
Sudan, Dahomey, Ghana etc.) ; another in eastern
and south-central Africa. A few years ago it was
hardly suspected that iron technology in south-
central Africa dated back so far, but since 1953
evidence has been piling up with the discovery of
early Christian period iron centres near Lake Tan¬
ganyika and elsewhere. Photo below shows an
ancient smelting furnace recently discovered in
southern Africa, and above, an early type of iron
arrow head showing marks of binding to hold poison
on the tang. Photos opposite show metal ornaments
worn by modern Bantu women of this region today.
Photos Rhodes Livingstone Museum.
If you were to tour Africa to-day, almost anywhere from
the Cape to Nairobi you would find abundant evidence
of the iron and steel industries of the Continent; rail¬
ways, bridges, steel-reinforced buildings, and even steel
barges sailing the peaceful Zambezi. These are all
reflections of the metal age as introduced to Africa by
European colonists. But if you wandered off the beaten
track almost anywhere along the same routes, you Would
find more or less primitive Africans also using iron; iron
spears and knives, iron arrow-heads, iron axes and hoes,
and even iron musical instruments.
This ironwork is the product of a home industry which
has been practised for generations in and around Bantu
villages, and which originally owes nothing to the white
man. In a few places in Tanganyika, the Equatorial
forests of the Congo, and the remote Kalahari desert you
would find small groups of hunting peoples who still do
not know the art of smelting and shaping iron. But even
these most primitive folk now have tools and Weapons of
iron which they obtain by trade from neighbouring Bantu
or Europeans. Some will obtain odd scraps of the metal
which they shape to their own requirements, not by the
methods of the metal worker, but by the age-old methods
of the stone-age; beating and hammering the cold metal
with a lump of stone on a stone anvil.
It is hard to think of an Africa in which no one hade any
knowledge of metal working, and where all tools, weapons
and ornaments were of stone, bone, ivory, wood, or other
non-metalic materials. But archaeologists have shown
that this was the case in Africa just as it was many years
earlier in Europe ajid the Near East. Everywhere from
the south coast to the southern fringes of the Sahara we
find the old camp sites and living places of stone-age
hunters. Then,, occasionally, we find in the living places
of some of the latest of the Stone Age peoples fragments
of Bantu pottery and even traces of iron smelting. These
are the sites which show us a picture of the old stone-
using, hunting peoples coming into contact with the first
metal-using farmers in the subcontinent.
Hunters turned to farming
pottery and iron-working
Hunting peoples must essentially be mobile, and they
have little use for cumbersome and brittle pottery. I
mention this because we generally associate the
appearance of pottery with the coming of iron. The
earliest pottery in Southern Africa is probably that of the
Hottentots, a cattle-owning, non-agricultural people who
migrated into South Africa ahead of the Bantu. We shall
have more to say about these people in connexion with
metals a little later.
Iron-working did not arrive in the sub-continent as an
isolated trait. It was accompanied by Well-made pottery
in use on a large scale, and, more important still, by
agriculture. Normally when we find evidence of any one
of these three things we can generally infer the others.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1959
H.J. Hahndiek. Netherlands
Agriculture meant that man could produce his own food
instead of having to chase and gather it about the country
side. For the first time in history it became possible to
live a settled existence in permanent villages. This led
to the development of more complex and closely-knit
societies, with more time to develop their arts and crafts.
The advent of these earliest farmers in Southern Africa,
with their knowledge of smelting and smithing was
without a doubt the most significant change that the
country had seen during half-a-million years of human
occupation.
Were first skills brought
by southward moving Bantus ?
But who were the earliest iron-using peoples in
Southern Africa ? Whence came they ? And when
did they first appear on the scene ? These are
question to which we must admit that we don't know the
complete answers. But We do have some clues, and
archaeologists are now actively engaged in looking for
others. It is relatively easy to go into the bush and find
sites where there is evidence of early iron-working, but it
is another matter entirely to say how old the site is, or
Who the people Were who lived there.
The immense period of the Stone Age, and the various
cultures represented in the period can be divided up and
given some sort of dating on the basis of geological events,
but the period of iron-working is far too recent for
geology to be able to provide a clue. Some help can be
had from the writings of early European explorers, and it
is from these that we learn something of the early use of
metals in the extreme south.
It is clear from records dating back to 1510 that the
Cape Hottentots had no tools, weapons or ornaments of
metal and that during the ensuing centuries they only
acquired the art of metal Working from the Dutch ships
that called there. They always relied on the ships for
their supplies of raw material. In 1661 an expedition
despatched by Jan van Riebeeck to the Namaqua Hotten¬
tots some 200 miles from the Cape found these people in
possession of beads and chains of copper and iron which
they had mined and smelted themselves. Similar reports
exist from 1719 for the Ba Tlaping Hottentots who were,
however, in fairly close contact with the earliest Bantu in
the area. We thus see that metal working in the extreme
south is a comparatively recently acquired skill, and was
in all probability learned from first Bantu immigrants in
the- 16th or 17th centuries.
If the knowledge of iron-working was introduced by
southward moving Bantu then we should expect to find
it at earlier dates the further north we travel. This is in
fact borne out by the archaeological evidence from Central
Africa. Here, however, dating becomes much more diffi¬
cult as there are no records earlier than the 18th century
and very little of any value until Livingstone's explora
tions during the latter half of the 19th century. The
answers must lie almost entirely with the archaeologist
aided by the radio-chemist who, by processing carbon
recovered from old living sites, can tell us approximately
how old the sites are.
Let us digress for a moment and consider when the
knowledge of iron-working may have come to Africa.
Objects of iron are found in Mesopotamia in deposits
dated to the middle part of the 3rd millenium b.c. The
real focus of iron production in prehistoric times, however,
was in the Hittite empire during the period 1400 to 1200
b.c. and it is most likely that it was from here that the
craft first spread, into Europe, and south to Egypt, and
to other points along the North African coast. Iron does
not become really common in Egypt until around 600 to
500 b.c. The inhabitants of Meroe (650 b.c. to 350 a.D.),
an island in the Nile just north of Khartoum knew the
use of iron, and settlements, which can be linked with
Meroe by the pottery they contain, have been traced
considerably further south on the Blue Nile.
Here then is a possible route by which iron might have
been introduced to the people who later carried it by
migration to areas of Central and Southern Africa. Alter¬
natively the Horn of Africa and the East coast have been
suggested as a possible route. So too has the West coast
of Africa along the margins of the Sahara desert. But
at present there is insufficient evidence to favour any of
these suggestions, although the physical characteristics
of the Bantu, Who form the largest element in Africa's
population suggest that they came from the North East of
the continent.
'History book' inscribed
in thirty feet of clay
A few sites in the Rhodesias help to provide something
a little more certain in the way of dates. At
Kalambo Falls, at the south end of Lake Tangan¬
yika. Dr. J. D. Clark has found a hollow containing up
to thirty feet of swamp clays which contain early Iron Age
pottery at all levels from top to bottom. There is also
iron slag at some levels, and traces of hearths and clay
floors. A carbon sample from near the middle of the
deposit has given a date of 100 a.d. Since the pottery is
typologically early this may be a living site of some of the
earliest iron-using folk to reach Northern Rhodesia.
Another interesting and much discussed site is Zim¬
babwe in Southern Rhodesia. All romantic claims that
this intriguing ruin was once a temple of the Queen of
Sheba, or that it was built by the Phoenicians must, in
the light of scientific discoveries, be dropped. Careful
excavation, and close examination of the objects found
shows quite clearly that Zimbabwe (See page 10) is to be
attributed to early Bantu settlers: the same Bantu who
carried into the country the earliest knowledge of metal
working and farming.
CONT'D ON PAGE 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
FORGOTTEN CITIES
OF THE EAST AFRICAN COAST
by Gervase Mathew
Lecturer, Oxford University
Official photograph: Public Relations Office, Tanganyika Territory
MARITIME TRADING CITIES of African origin grew up and flourished on the East coast of
the continent in pre-European times. Greatest of them was Kilwa which was built on an island
off the coast of Tanganyika and which once stretched for a mile in length and half a mile inland.
Today only the low houses of a small village cluster on and around ruins like those of its old fort
(above). Growing rich on Indian Ocean trade with countries as far off as Siam and China, these
coastal markets knew their greatest prosperity from the 13th to the 15th centuries. Their decline
came with the arrival of the Portuguese who altered the immemorial Indian Ocean trade routes.
The western shore of the Indian Ocean is littered
with fragments of ruined towns. It is now clear
that the largest group among them dates from
the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries. Sometimes
they are completely deserted towns almost as well
preserved as Pompeii, like Au Garvin in Somalia, a little
to the north of Merca and Kua in the Mafia islands off
the coast of Tanganyika. Sometimes there are the reed
huts of a modern fishing voilage among the fallen
masonry. But all are linked by masses of broken shards
of blue and white Chinese porcelain and by similar types
of house and palace, mosque and pillar tomb.
They represent the Swahili culture of the coast between
the fading of the power of Portugal and the rise of the
nineteenth century Arab Empire of Zanzibar. They form¬
ed a group of small city states, oligarchic in social
structure and grown wealthy through trade in ivory and
Assisted by Dr. Freeman-Grenville, Father Gervase Mathew
completed an archaeological survey of the coastline and of the
islands from the British ' Somaliland Protectorate south to
Portuguese East Africa. An archaeological map of the sites that
have been recorded will be published from the Oxford University
Press as part of the first volume of a History of East Africa.
22
slaves. As a culture it was elaborate and in many ways
sophisticated.
The small two storeyed palaces built of coral were ring¬
ed by the houses of nobles, and among the rich the stan¬
dard of luxury seems to have been high. There were
elaborate series of niches in the inner rooms for the dis¬
play of porcelain; in the words of a Swahili proverb, silver
ladders led to ivory beds. It was a culture that was
evolving its own art forms; an intricate style in wood
carving and in many-coloured textiles and in verse.
All this was only possible because of the trade that
came south With the Monsoon. But they remained Afri¬
can towns. It is revealing that alone among the trading
centres of the Indian Ocean in the seventeenth and
eighteenth centuries they did not use coins except occa¬
sionally as amulets. Their economic system was based on
barter and on currency of beads and rolls of cloth.
Though nominally Islamic, the chief religious forces
seem to have been the fear of spirits, the belief in propi¬
tiatory sacrifice that accompanied it and elaborate witch¬
craft. Women held a position quite different from that
accorded to them elsewhere in the Indian Ocean world.
They were the guardians of the ritual objects of each
little state, they were frequently the nominal rulers; even
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
the Decorated Ones, the courtesans, seem to have posses¬
sed status.
The deportment expected of a noble was African; the
author of that greatest of Swahili poems, Al Inkishafi,
remembered the nobles of eighteenth century Pate
arching their long necks and swaying their supple-jointed
arms as the common people gazed on them. Most signifi¬
cant of all the strength and spirit of each state was
conceived of as enshrined in a single sacred object, an
Ivory Horn or a Great Drum.
There are also the remains of far larger cities of a much
earlier period. Only two of these sites are occupied or
partly occupied by modern towns Mombasa and Moga¬
dishu. The low houses of a small village cluster among
the tall ruins on Kilwa island in Tanganyika. A little
to the south the palace city of Songo Mnara is over¬
grown by bush. In Kenya the city of Gedi lies deserted in
the forest. At Port Durnford, in Somalia, fragments of
masonry and occasional pillars stretch along the estuary
for nearly a mile and a half above the reed huts of the
Baguin fishermen.
It is the extent of each of these earlier sites that is so
unexpected. It was estimated that there were twenty
thousand inhabitants of Mombasa at the time of the
coming of the Portuguese. Mediaeval Mogadishu was lar¬
ger still, it spread far beyond the modern town across the
modern air field. Mediaeval Kilwa stretched for over a
mile along the coast and for half a mile inland.
All these cities had grown rich through the Indian
Ocean traffic; they had trade contacts as far as Siam
and China. They exported slaves but it is easy to exagge¬
rate the importance of the slave trade for their economy
perhaps the majority of negro slaves in this period were
brought to the South Arabian markets by the short sea
passage from more northerly ports like Aidhab on the Red
Sea, Zeila or Berbera. But Mogadishu and Kilwa had
grown rich as storehouses for the gold trade that had its
source far south in the Rhodesian workings. Both to the
The Unesco Courier. October 1959
east and to the north there was an unsated demand for
African ivory.
It is not yet clear when any of these cities came into
existence; there were trading centres in the Roman
period, though the most important of these, the Metro¬
polis of Raphta, is not yet found, and there are Greek
and Roman coins from Port Durnford and Roman and
Persian coins from Zanzibar. Still, their chief prosperity
was from the thirteenth to the fifteenth century. Already
by the fifteenth century some of them seem to be decli¬
ning. They were doomed when the Portuguese altered
the immemorial trade routes of the Indian Ocean.
Unlike the small Swahili towns that succeeded them
they were an essential part of the structure of Indian
Ocean trade. Mr. Kirkman's excavations at Gedi have
shown that in the Malindi area in Kenya the chief cur¬
rency Was in cowrie shells. But elsewhere there was a
money economy; there were three mediaeval East African
mints. The number and elaboration of the Mosques show
that all the mediaeval cities had become Islamic. But it
is becoming untenable to consider them as Persian or
Arab colonies though some like Kilwa and old Zanzibar
may well have come into existence clustered round a trad¬
ing settlement from the Persian Gulf.
The cities described by mediaeval geographers seem
negro cities more negroid than any present inhabitant of
the coast. In the fourteenth century Ibn Batuta describes
the citizens of Kilwa as jet black with incised faces, and
his account of the royal ceremonial at Mogadishu the
state umbrella and the birds of gold borne high on staves
is reminiscent of West African Kingship. A fifteenth
century Chinese visitor to Mogadishu noted not only the
tall stone houses "four or five storeys high" but the fact
that the women there "'apply yellow varnish to their
shaven crowns, hang several strings of discs from their
ears and Wear silver rings round their necks."
At least in my present judgement the deserted cities
of the East African coast are deserted African cities.
THE MARCH OF IRON (Continued from page 21)
The builders of Zimbabwe were a lively, energetic people;
farmers and cattle owners, producing tools and ornaments
in copper, gold and iron, and acquiring beads of foreign
origin by trade. A radiocarbon date for Zimbabwe sug¬
gests that it Was in occupation during the 7th century a.d.
although it must be admitted that for technical reasons
this date is slightly suspect, and Zimbabwe may not be
as old as this. It does, however, give us an approximate
idea of when these folk first arrived in Rhodesia.
Pottery from the earliest levels at Zimbabwe is closely
related to pottery from several sites in Northern Rhodesia.
Two such sites in the south of Barotseland have been
dated by radiocarbon tests to between 100 and 400 a.d.
Unfortunately, owing no doubt to the acid conditions of
the soil, no iron has yet been discovered at these sites, and
because no proper excavation has been carried out we
know nothing of what the settlement was like.
A recent discovery about a hundred miles north
of the Victoria Falls may help to provide a link between
the earliest iron age folk hereabouts and the present day
inhabitants. At a tiny settlement ¡known as Kalomo has
been discovered what is virtually a miniature tell ; that
is, a mound formed from the accumulation of centuries
of rubbish. The occupants of this old village lived so
long on the one spot that they ended up by sitting on a
heap of their own rubbish some nine feet high ! A trial
excavation showed us that the last inhabitants lived there
comparatively recently, perhaps in the last century. The
earliest levels have not yet been dated, but they will
almost certainly take us back several centuries.
These folk were farmers who decorated themselves
with snail shell beads, and fashioned razors and arrow¬
heads from iron. They also made little figurines of
cattle and fat tailed sheep, but whether these were chil¬
dren's toys, or fertility cult objects we cannot yet say.
Their grain they stored in large bottle-shaped pits dug
up to nine feet into the rotten granite subsoil. It may
be that the man-made mound at Kalomo was fortified,
but whether against attack from neighbouring Bantu, or
from the last of the Stone Age tribes into whose territory
they had moved, we cannot say until more work has been
done.
To sum up then we may say that the period in question
has been so little studied that we are not yet in a position
to describe in detail what was happening during the
change from Stone Age to Metal Age. All the evidence
suggests, however, that the knowledge of iron-working
was not discovered independently in Southern Africa, but
was brought here by migrant peoples; simple farmers
from some unknown area either to the north east or north
west of the sub-continent, or perhaps, who reached Cen¬
tral Africa fairly soon after the beginning of the Christian
era, but who did not penetrate to the extreme south until
as late as the 15th or 16th centuries a.d. These migrant
peoples were undoubtedly the direct ancestors of the pres¬
ent day Bantu-speaking inhabitants of the country.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
KUMBI SALEH
ancient capital of
the 'Land of Gold'
by Raymond Mauny
Head of the Archeology-Prehistory Section
Institut Français d'Afrique Noire, Dakar, Sénégal.
On March 6 1957 a new. State Ghana, formerly the
British-administered territory of the Gold Coast
came into existence on the shores of the Gulf of
Guinea.
The choice of Ghana as the name for the new-born
state may have puzzled some students of African history.
No part of the former Gold Coast was ever included in the
Empire of Ghana, which extended over the Western Sudan
and the Southern Sahara from the seventh century untiK
at least the thirteenth century a.D., but whose southern
expansion seems to have stopped at the Niger. Some
writers have suggested that the Akan, one of the principal '
local tribes, may have been connected with the Empire of
Ghana. The selection of this name for the new West
African State was actually probably due to the glamour
surrounding the first great Sudanese Empire.
Nothing definite is known about its origins. The only
documents that touch on the question the Tarikh el-
Fettach and the Tarikh es-Sudan, both written by scholars
from Timbuktu belong to a very late period (sixteenth-
seventeenth centuries) ; these give a long list of kings
said to have reigned before the Hegira. (The date from
which the Mohammedan era is reckoned 622 a.d.
We find the first mention of the Empire of Ghana in
the works of the astronomer Al-Fazari, written just before
800 a.D. He calls it "the land of gold." Certain ninth
and tenth century authors mention it briefly, but the
only good description of the State and its capital is given
by El-Bekri (1067). In his day, the Empire was at the
height of its prosperity and stretched from the Sahara,
the Niger and Central Senegal to the Lake Debo area.
Despite the great tolerance it showed towards Moham¬
medans, this State with its animistic religion, offended
the fanatical Almorávides, who invaded and conquered it
in 1077. An Arab dynasty, possibly of Sheriflan origin,
ousted the Sarakole Negro kings and, until its destruction
by the Mandingos in 1240, the capital continued to play
an important part as a centre of trade between the Arab
and Berber merchants from the Mograb and Egypt, and
the "Dioulas" from West Africa. Sudanese gold was
brought there to be exchanged for salt from the Sahara
and manufactured goods from the Mediterranean
countries.
For at least 500 years the city of Ghana was one of the
best known markets in the Moslem world. Its trade later
passed to Oualata, founded in the thirteenth century,
which in its turn was supplanted, in the fifteenth century,
by Timbuktu.
What traces of the ancient capital have remained?
Strangely enough it Was not until 1914 that its ruins were
discovered by A. Bonnel de Mézières, following up
suggestions made by the historian, Maurice Delafosse.
The site was that known as Kumbi Saleh, 200 miles due
north of Bamako and just north of the Mauritanian
frontier.
The identification of thé town of Ghana or, at least,
of the trading centre described by El-Bekri with the
Kumbi Saleh ruins is, in my opinion, the most plausible
yet advanced. The Tarikh el-Fettach says definitely that
24
the capital of Ghana "was Kumbi, and this Kumbi is a
great city" ; and the tradition that Kumbi and Ghana
were the same still survived at Oualata at the beginning
of the present century. Moreover, this is the largest group
of ruins to have been discovered in the Mauritanian Sahel,
and all the objects found there date from the early Middle
Ages.
Neither the study of aerial photographs nor re-
connoitering at ground level has as yet, however, revealed
any trace of the royal city, which El-Bekri declares to
have been situated at a distance of six miles from the
merchant settlement.
The Kumbi Saleh ruins extend over an area of
approximately one square kilometre, lying between two
pools which are generally dry and flanked on the
north-west and south-east by two burial grounds covering
almost twice that extent. The outskirts of the city are
strewn with pottery shards and must have been built
over with straw huts. The town itself is constructed
entirely of stone a grey shale, found locally, which splits
into symmetrical slabs. This was used everywhere for
walls, floors, ornamental work, the tombstones in the
graveyards, and so on.
Thousands of tombs yet
not a single gravestone
The houses had upper storeys, and when these subsided
they filled in the ground-floor rooms which when
uncovered were found to be magnificently preserved
under >a mass of rubble averaging 12 feet in tickness.
The central part of the town is built round a large
square, from which several streets branch out; the most
important of these, which is very wide, led eastward and
was marked on the plans as the "Main Avenue". It was
lined by quite high buildings, including a mosque of which
the mirhab has been excavated. The streets are clearly
visible at ground level, despite the collapse of the walls,
and also stand out in aerial photographs.
As already mentioned, two very large burial grounds lie
just outside the town. In the one to the north-east, the
section nearest to the city contains simple Moslem graves,
edged with stones. Further away there are collective
burial-places, surrounded by walls; the largest of these,
with at its centre the so-called "pillared tomb", is
surrounded by six square walls, the outermost of which is
over half a mile in circumference.
The south-eastern burial ground stretches from the city
to the pool of Sohobi, beside which stands the tomb of
Bouhahim, reputed by tradition to have been the comrade
of Abu Bakr ibn Omar, the Almoravide. This, too,
contains several collective burial-places surrounded by
concentric walls.
Though these cemeteries contain thousands of tombs,
no ancient gravestones have been found; cattle, wild
animals, forest fires and rain must have destroyed the
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1959
brittle shale. Unless some new finds are made therefore,
we shall lack the invaluable data provided by inscribed
tombstones, such as was the case at Gao, where the royal
burial ground of Sane was found to contain a whole series
dating from the twelfth century. (See page 26)
We have learned quite a lot about the architecture of
the city through successive excavations conducted by
A. Bonnel de Mézières in 1914, D. Lazartigues in 1939,
P. Thomassey in 1949 and 1950, and G. Szumowski and
myself in the latter part of 1951. Bonnel de Mézières'
work was the most extensive; helped by some 50 workers,
he excavated 22 structures (houses, tombs and various
other buildings). Unfortunately nothing is now known
about the material he collected through his excavations.
Of greater practical value was the work done between
1949-1951, especially by P. Thomassey, who lived on the
site for several months and cleared two groups of
buildings of very fine architectural style. The flagged
floors, the wall-tablets painted with passages from the
Koran, the graceful lines of the niches carved in walls
and pillars, the stone staircases, and the wealth of
skilfully-fashioned objects (iron tools and weapons,
. pottery, beads, grindstones, and some extremely rare glass
weights used for weighing gold) give us a good idea of the
type of civilization that flourished here.
Cradle of a Sudanese
Negro-Islamic culture
These must have been the houses of wealthy Arab or
Arab-influenced merchants, or of Sarakole or other
grandees who had been converted to Islam. For
everything discovered at Kumbi dates from the con¬
cluding period of Ghana's existence, the twelfth and
thirteenth centuries, shortly before its destruction by the
Mandingos. No pre-Islamic finds have been made and
it is highly probable that everything suggestive of aotiimism
was destroyed by the Almorávides.
El-Bekri relates how the town of Awdaghost, a
dependency of Ghana, was sacked in 1054, only 23 years
before the capture .of Kumbi, for the simple reason that
it "acknowledged the authority of the Sultan of Ghana".
We may be sure that the Almorávides must have treated
Kumbi itself in the same way, and that the temples of
the "idols" and the royal tumuli were razed to the ground
and pillaged. No trace of the pre-Islamic civilization of
Ghana now survives in the former capital of the Sarakole
kings. Everything brought to . light is Islamic in origin,
the, architecture being particularly reminiscent of that of
the Arab-Berber caravan cities in Southern Mauritania.
But the ancient capital of Ghana has another claim to
distinction: it was the cradle of the Negro-Islamic culture
which flourished in the Sudan from the eighth century
to our own day, bringing fame to centres such as Tim¬
buktu and Djenné.
Arab merchants, and scholars from The Magrab attract¬
ed by the renown of the land of gold, founded families at
Ghana and elsewhere. Their descendants of mixed blood
spread all over the Sudan, more especially in the big
trading settlements, taking with them the Koran, and
Moslem civilization, from the confines of Senegal to
Chad. It is no accident that the foundation of all the
great empires Ghana, Mali, Songai and the Hausa^States
can be traced back to the Sarakoles and their near
relations, the Malinkes, or that people of the same stock
should have carried some semblance of the Islamic
civilization of the Sudan into the very heart of the forests
of the Bondoukou country, Ashanti and elsewhere, to
which they were drawn by the gold trade.
There is a direct, clear and indisputable connexion
between Kumbi, Tichit, Oualata and the other towns of
Southern Mauritania. But there is also an undeniable,
though more distant and less obvious, connexion between
Kumbi and the Sudanese "banco"-built towns Tim¬
buktu and Djenné in times past; Kayes, Bamako and
Mopti today. Their architecture is the same, though
clumsier in appearance, since the building material is
dried earth "banco". And the deeply-rooted Moslem
culture of the inhabitants is also the same.
This is the old and wondrous heritage bequeathed to the
Sudanese by Ghana. Could anything do greater honour
to the ancient city whose remains are gradually being
brought to light by archaeologists? .
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
HELMET MASK made by the Bobo Finga tribe of the
Sudan in West Africa is a single-piece wooden carving with
a surmounting female figure. The most important examples
of sculpture in the Sudan the vast belt of subdesert and
savannah country south of the Sahara, stretching" across
Africa from the coast of Senegal to the Red Seaare found in
the western part, in and to the west of the Niger River bend.
Ancient chroniclers
of West Africa's past
by Thomas Hodgkin
Photo Eliot Elisofon, taken from "The Sculpture of Africa"
& Hudson Ltd., London 1958
26
Thames
When people talk, as they still sometimes do, about
Africa south of the Sahara as "a continent without
a history", what they really mean is that Africa
is a continent about whose history we Europeans are still
deplorably ignorant. The reasons for this are complex.
Partly, whether we like it or not, we remain absurdly
ethnocentric: "history" for most of us means national,
or at best "European" or "Western", history; if any African
history creeps into our curricula, it is usually under the
oldfashioned rubric "the Expansion of Europe."
Partly, so far as West African history is concerned, the
documentary evidence for the mediaeval period say, up
to 1500 a.d. comes almost entirely from Arabic sources:
few Arabists have taken much interest in Africa south of
the Sahara; few Africanists most of them Frenchmen, or
Africans trained in the French tradition have been
equipped to handle the Arabic material. Finally, one
must admit, we are all to some extent still victims of a
colonial mentality: we find it hard to realize that Africans
possessed their own indigenous civilizations for many
centuries before we Europeans, beginning with the Portu¬
guese at the end of the 15th-century, conceived the idea
of trying to sell them ours.
Yet in fact extremely interesting civilizations existed,
from at least the 8th century, and probably much earlier,
in the region known to the Arabs as bilad al-sudan
meaning literally "the country of the black people", but
used conventionally to refer to the great belt of savannah
to the south of the Sahara, from the Atlantic to the Red
Sea. The major States of the western Sudan Ghana,
and later Mali, in the area of the upper Niger; Gao,
dominating the Niger bend; Kanem-Bornu, in the region
of Lake Chad had certain common characteristics. Their
wealth depended above all on the fact that they controlled
the southern end of the trans-Saharan trade-routes, by
which they exported to North Africa, and thence to
Europe, their main supplies of gold, as well as slaves, ivory,
and kola nuts, receiving exchange copper, cowries, cloth,
horses, cattle and beads.
These States developed relatively centralized forms of
government under dynasties of divine kings which,
^ in most cases, showed a remarkable continuity (the
Sefawa dynasty in Kanem-Bornu survived for a
millennium from approximately the middle of 9th to the
middle of the 19th century). They possessed a complicat¬
ed hierarchy of officials, closely associated with the palace;
an elaborate court ritual; considerable military forces;
and an administrative system capable in normal times, of
preserving public order and raising taxes in the outlying
provinces.
From the 11th century on, the royal families and ruling
classes of these States were converted to Islam either by
Almoravid pressure, or by the peaceful penetration of
Moslem missionaries from North Africa. As a consequence
of the spread of Islam, and the developing relations be¬
tween the States of the western Sudan and the wider
Moslem world through such focal points as Fez, Tlemcen,
Tunis, Cairo and Mecca West African centres of learning
grew up, above all at Timbuktu and Jenne.
Until the journeys of Mungo Park and his successors
Horneman, Denham and Clapperton, Laing and Caillé
at the end of the 18th and beginning of the 19th century,
Europe was almost totally cut off from direct contact with
the civilizations of the western Sudan. Hence our depend-
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1959
OF DISCOVERY THROUGH
'COUNTRY OF THE BLACK PEOPLE'
ence upon Arabic sources for an understanding of the
histories of these States. These sources include not only
the works of Arab geographers and historians, from the
9th century on, . but also the writings of local West
African historians and chroniclers trained in such
centres as Timbuktu and also (though these are rare)
Arabic inscriptions.
How, for example, do we know that the ruling dynasties
of Ghana, Mali (or Kangaba, as it was called at this time),
Gao, and Kanem, were converted to Islam in the 11th
century? Partly from literary sources: Ibn-Khaldun, the
great 14th century Tunisian historian, sociologist, and
philosopher, gives a brief account of the Almoravid
conquest of Ghana, in 1076. But, in the case of Gao, the
evidence of the historians is supplemented by a remark¬
able series of dated tombstones of members of the Gao
royal house bearing Arabic inscriptions, discovered in 1939
a few kilometres from modern Gao.
The earliest of these bears the Hijra date 494, i.e. 1100
a.d.; the latest is dated 663 a.h. (1264/5 a.d.). The
earlier tombstones are beautifully carved in Qufic
characters, whose style has led Professor Sauvaget to
suggest that they were the work of craftsmen from
Almeria in southern Spain, the craftsmen, or more
probably the finished stones, being transported by camel
across the Sahara for the purpose. Others are clearly of
local workmanship. Here is a translation of one of the
inscriptions:
"Everything on earth is destined for annihilation.
This is the tomb of a very powerful king, of noble station,
who protected the religion of God, who trusted in God,
who carried out the commandments of God, .who fought
for the cause of God, Mama, son of Kma, the son of
Ai, known by the name of Omar ibn al-Khattab. May
God have mercy on him. He was called to God on Sunday,
17 Muharram, 514 a.h. (18 April, 1120)."
The Koranic text with which the epitaph opens, the
use of indigenous Songhai names (the Songhai are the
people of Gao) side by side with Moslem names, the
evidence of cultural and commercial ties between the
western Sudan and southern Spain during this period of
Almoravid rule all these bear out the historians' view,
that the 11th century was essentially the period When
Islam began to be diffused throughout the region.
From the 9th century on, the Arab geographers and
historians begin to provide valuable information about
the States of the western Sudan. For example, Yaqubi,
writing in about 872, knew of the kingdoms of Ghana and
Kanem, and described the gold trade of Ghana and
Kanem's trade in slaves with North Africa, by way of the
Fezzan. Ibn Hlawqual of Baghdad, in the first half of the
10th Century, travelled as far as the Saharan town of
Audoghast, on the outskirts of the Ghana Empire. Al-
Bakri, who wrote his Masalik wa Mamali, an account
of "Routes and Kingdoms", in about 1067, just aftsr the
Norman conquest of England, though he lived most of
his life in the Moslem State of Cordoba, in southern Spain,
was clearly well informed about the western Sudan.
He has given us the classic account of the Empire of
Ghana at the height of its power, before the Almoravid
conquest: The capital, consisting of two towns, about six
miles apart, one Pagan, where the King lived, the other
Moslem, containing twelve mosques; the court, where the
King held audience, surrounded by his horses in gold
trappings, his hounds, pages holding gold-hilted swords,
the sons of vassal princes, his viziers, who were mainly
Moslems, and the governor of the city; the army, consist
ing of 200,000 men, of whom 40,000 were archers; the royal
monopoly of gold nuggets, and the use of gold-dust for
currency.
Here again, the evidence of the Arab historians has
been supplemented by the archaeologists. We know, from
a 16th century Timbuktu historian, Hahmud Kati, that
the name of the capital of the Kingdom of Ghana was
"Kumbi". Recent excavations, carried out by MM. Mauny
and Thomassey at Kumbi Saleh in French West Africa,
about 250 miles north of Bamaka, have uncovered what
is almost certainly part of the Moslem town referred to
by Al-Barki well-constructed stone houses, a mosque,
and tombs outside the town. (See page 24.)
In some ways the most valuable of all the Arab sources
are the first-hand reports of the two as far as I' know,
the only two Arab traveller-authors who made extensive
journeys through the western Sudan: Ibn-Battuta and
Leo Africanus. Both were remarkable men. Muhammed
ibn-Abdullah ibn-Battuta was born at Tangier in 1304,
and spent the greater part of his life travelling through
the Moslem world of his day, visiting Arabia, Asia Minor,
Khurasan, India, China, and Indonesia, as well as West
Africa, which he reached in 1352. At this time the Empire
of Mali still dominated the western Sudan, and Ibn-
Battuta gives an extremely interesting and human account
of some of its institutions:
"The Negroes possess some admirable qualities. They
are seldom unjust, and have a greater abhorrence of
injustice than any other people. Their Sultan shows no
mercy to anyone who is guilty of the least act of it. There
is complete security in their country. Neither traveller
nor inhabitant in it has anything to fear from robbers of
men of violence... They are careful to observe the hours
of prayer... On Fridays, if a man does not go early to
the mosque, he cannot find a corner to pray in, on account
of the crowd... Another of their good qualities is their
habit of wearing clean white garments on. Fridays. Even
if a man has nothing but an old shirt, he washes it and
cleans it and wears it to the Friday service. Yet another
is their zeal for learning the Koran by heart..."
Leo Africanus, originally known as El-Hasan ibn-
Muhammad el-Wazzan el-Zayyati, was born at
Granada in Spain in about the year 1490. At the
age of about 17 he accompanied his uncle on a diplomatic
mission from the Sultan of Morocco to the court of
Muhammad Askia, ruler of the Gao Empire, which had by
that time taken Mali's place as the dominant power in the
western Sudan. He later followed this by a second
journey through Africa south of the Sahara. In about
the year 1518 he was captured by a Sicilian corsair, and
handed over to Pope Leo X, who baptised him with his
own names, Johannes Leo de Medecis, in 1520.
Thereupon Leo Africanus settled down to write his
famous Description of Africa, which was first published in
Italian in 1550, and provided Europe with its main, though
increasingly out-of-date, information regarding the States
and peoples of the western Sudan for the next two
centuries. His account of the flourishing commercial and
intellectual life of Timbuktu and other centres of the
Gao Empire at the height of its power remains of the
greatest value: -
"There are at Timbuktu numerous judges, doctors, and
clerics, all appointed by the King. He greatly honours
men of learning. Many books in manuscript, imported
from Barbary, are also on sale here. More profit is made
from the book trade than from all other branches of
commerce."
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
LOST TEMPLES
Among the low, dry hills to the north of Khartoum in the Sudan lies a practically
untouched archaeological site which may be one of the richest that remains
anywhere in the world. Here, in the former kingdom of Kush ("in some
respects the most African of all the great civilizations of Antiquity") are the
great monuments of Meroe and its sister cities of Naga, Musawarat es Safra,
Nuri and Napata. Meroe, once the centre of the largest iron-smelting industry
in Africa south of the Mediterranean coast, has been called "The Birmingham
of Ancient Africa." Its products and later its technology moved progressively
into other African lands to the south and west. Among the most impressive
of the Kushite ruins are those at Naga, dating back some 2,000 years, and
shown in these photos: (1) The "kiosk," as this columned building is called,
recalls a Roman example. It is thought to have been a temple. (2) Coiled
serpent with lion's head climbs out of a lotus flower on a column forming a
corner of the Lion Temple. (3) Figures sculpted on Lion Temple wall include
Lion God (left) and Aminitere, one of the goddess-queens who ruled in splen¬
dour during the Kushite Civilization. (4) The ram became one of Kush's div¬
ine symbols and today many granite rams lie discarded inthesand at Naga.
Photos @ Almasy, Paris
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1959
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
THE GREATNESS
OF ETHIOPIA:
LEGENDS
& REALITY
by Jean Doresse
) Jean Doresse
Although a variety of races with, widely differing lan¬
guages has met and mingled in Ethiopia, a remark¬
ably closely-knit culture has developed there over
the centuries. The primary reason for this unity is prob¬
ably geographical the peaceful scenery, greenness and
cool temperatures of these high plateaux, at an altitude
of over 6,500 feet, which call to mind some of Europe's
mountains rather than Africa. There is another element
making for unity the majority of the peoples living in
these uplands are, despite their dark skins, akin to the
white race.
It is for these reasons that long ago a civilization grew
up which distinguishes Ethiopia from the Negro-inhabited
parts of Africa, by which it is largely surrounded, and
which gives to the country affinities with the lands of
ancient civilization Egypt, Syria and Arabia with which
it had historical contacts.
Let us first of all set aside a myth still too
current; that ancient Ethiopia had ties With the
land of the Pharaohs. This romantic idea was widely
advanced by classical writers two thousand years ago.
Yet the country referred to both in the writings of Hero¬
dotus and in the Aethiopica of Heliodorus was not Ethiopia
itself, but merely the Sudanese Kingdom of Meroe. There
is, however, evidence that a protohistorical Ethiopian
30
ANCIENT LEGENDS are written large into the story of Ethiopia,
a country of ancient and distinctive civilization. They are still told
graphically, for example, in the brightly coloured paintings which in the
"cartoon" style of a series of panels reproduce scenes from the 1 4th cen¬
tury "Glory of the Kings," Ethiopia's National Book, which has. a biblical
civilization already existed some thousands of years before
our era, though it left behind no monuments.
Ancient Ethiopia was known to the Egyptians as the
"Land of Punt" or the "Land of the Gods", names which
covered more specifically the regions producing incense
which lay along the southern shores of the Red Sea, both
in East Africa and Arabia. Egypt in its earliest times had
traditions that some of its gods and legends had come
from those parts of the world, and its traders brought
back rare marchandise from these coasts. The expedi¬
tions sent by the Pharaohs, however, never penetrated to
the high plateaux; some merely went up the Nile to the.
markets of the Sudan; others, coming by sea, put in at
the points on the coast where wood, ivory and costly ani¬
mals were to be bought.
It is worth noting that, while the Minaean, Sabaean and
other kingdoms of Southern Arabia began to be famous
for their wealth and their culture about a thousand years
b.c., it was not until eight or ten centuries later that the
first travellers from the shores of the Mediterranean
reached the Abyssinian highlands, where they found large
cities and powerful rulers.
What they tell us is borne out by monuments still extant.
There was undoubtedly, at that time, a lively civilization
in Ethiopia, with firmly established, characteristic institu-
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1959
Musée de l'Homme, Paris
background. Painting reproduced above dates from the 19th century.
It tells the story of Solomon and the Queen of Sheba and of the birth of
Menelik, first Emperor of Ethiopia whom Ethiopians believe was the son
of Solomon and the Quenn. Left, early Ethiopian gold coin minted at
the end the 3 rd century A. D. It is inscribed in the Geez alphabet.
a form of writing that originated in Arabia, crossed the Red Sea and
became assimilated and adapted in Ethiopia. The Geez alphabet has
survived to the present day although Ethiopia's principal language is
Amharic. The Ethiopian money which was struck in the third century
had its own distinctive designs and was used until the 9th century.
tions of its own. The gateway to the country was the
great port of Adulis, where fleets from the Egypt of the
Ptolemies and from the Indian Ocean alike put in. The
chief towns were Coloë, the centre of the ivory trade, on
the edge of the plateau above Adulis, and Axum in the
interior of the country.
The peoples who held these cities belonged to races
which had been long settled on either coast of the Red
Sea. The most highly civilized of them used a Semitic
language and, in their inscriptions, they even employed the
Sabaean writing; they had abandoned the religion of
Africa in favour of one, with temples and altars, akin to
that of the great kingdoms of Southern Arabia. The
earliest monuments they had built had drawn inspiration
from the remarkable buildings whose countless remains
are still to be seen today on the plateaux of the Yemen
and the Hadramaut. i
But these were not mere imitations. All had been assi¬
milated and transformed on African soil. The Sabaean
.writing was soon to develop into Geez, which Ethiopia
has preserved to modern times^ The Sabaean architec¬
ture was to be treated in new ways by races accustomed
to cutting enormous blocks of hard stone and to erecting
monolithic obelisks as huge as those of the Pharaohs.
It was certainly a powerful nation, for the rulers of
Axum extended their power even to Arabia, from which
the first seeds of their own culture had come. In the
third and fourth centuries, the Ethiopian nation thus
secured a monopoly of trade in the south of the Red Sea,
on which, up to that time, only the Southern Arabian
kingdoms, producing incense and spices, had built their
greatness. From the end of the third century, Axum's
international importance was emphasized by the fact
that, for a short time, Greek was used in certain inscrip¬
tions and even on coins. For an Ethiopian coinage was
struck, using the same weights of metal as the. various
Roman gold pieces of the time but with its own quite
distinctive designs; it was to survive until the ninth
century.
The man who did most to develop this Ethiopian civi¬
lization was the Emperor Aizanas (about 320-350 a.D.),
who introduced the general use of Geez writing, based on
the Sabaean script, for the Semitic language spoken by
his people. At the same time, about 340 a.D., he intro¬
duced Christianity, which has ever since been the nation's
religion. It very soon developed characteristic features
of its own, however, being very biblical in inspiration and
sometimes showing a marked tendency towards Judaism,
clear traces of which are still to be seen in its myths and
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
THE GREATNESS OF ETHIOPIA
(Continued)
practices. Churches were built for the new religion,
reminiscent in design of the Axumite temples and combin¬
ing decorative features drawn from Arabia, Syria, Persia
and Coptic Egypt. Many monasteries were founded, in
which libraries grew up, starting with collections of
translations.
From the beginning of the seventh century onwards,
the Axumite Empire felt the repercussions of the decad¬
ence which had recently destroyed the last splendours
of the Southern Arabian states. The maritime trade of
the Red Sea on which its prosperity had been founded
also collapsed and in a short time an impoverished Ethio¬
pia found itself cut off, except for a few ties with Egypt,
from the rest of the world. This situation lasted until the
sixteenth century. Nevertheless, its culture scarcely
suffered and under the dynasty of the Zagués' (tenth or
twelfth century to 1270 a.d.) a fantastic capital, the city
of King Lalibela, grew up in the mountainous province of
Lasta. Its twelve monolithic churches mark the end of
the old Axumite artistic tradition as well as representing,
no doubt, its highest achievement.
Then began the Middle Ages, with the greatest develop¬
ment taking place further south than the provinces of
Tigre and Lasta, in the bleak mountains of Amhara and
the fertile plains of Shoa. There the Geez script had to
be adapted to a vernacular in which only a few traces of
the old Sabaean contribution were to be seen. This was
Amharic, which is still today the principal language of the
nation. But Geez was not forgotten; it was still used in
Christian liturgy and literature.
Against this new background, a series of kings who
proved themselves as distinguished statesmen, heroic
warriors, strict jurists, theologians and, in some cases,
inspired poets too one of the greatest was Zar'a Ya'kub
(1434-1468) brought into being a prosperous nation
which, in its monuments and paintings, its extensive lite¬
rature and its practical and detailed chronicles, calls to
mind the Middle Ages of Western Europe. In both litera¬
ture and art, the recognizable outside influences at work
come mainly from Coptic Egypt and from Syria, though
occasionally a few European features, brought there in
some way unknown, were sometimes mingled with the
others.
Unfortunately, the Middle Ages in Ethiopia were marked
by violent religious struggles. Islam, with which the old
rulers of Axum had maintained the most cordial relations,
had gained a foothold to the east of the high plateaux]
in low-lying regions where independent kingdoms had
been established. This branch of Islam, thoroughly
Ethiopian in spirit and (although it adopted Arabic as its
language) in its writings, remained peaceable for a time.
Then it allowed itself to be drawn on by certain hitherto
uncivilized peoples for whom it provided the unifying
element to make an all-out attack on the more prosperous
Christian table-lands. This was basically an economic
war; only at rare intervals did it assume the cha¬
racter of a holy one. The
fiercest challenge came short¬
ly before the middle of the
sixteenth century, when the
assault of the armies united
by the Imam Gragne laid
waste the great trading cen¬
tres, towns and churches of
Shoa, Amhara and Tigre.
Only the intervention, in
1541, of a small band of Por¬
tuguese soldiers led by Dom
Christophe de Gama saved
this 1,500 years-old empire
from ruin.
These men from the West,
though few in numbers, were
bearers of new techniques,,
yet they brought about no
change in the traditional
culture of Ethiopia. The
Western influence in fact
died out particularly quickly
because the only people who
came after the Portuguese
) Jean Doresse.
fíñflIíMii
l Almasy, Paris
AXUM, holy city of Ethiopia, adopted Christianity in the 4th century.
Today the imposing vestiges of its past still stand. Above, view of the
ancient cathedral. Below left, stone statue of a prince dating from the
3rd century which was found in the Tigre region of northern Ethiopia.
soldiers (the survivors of whom were very soon absorbed
and lost in the mass of the Ethiopian population) were a
handful of Catholic missionaries whose teachings were
immediately rejected by the nation.
Ethiopia clung to its rich, ancient culture, although, at
the end of this period, there were fresh developments in
its painting, its miniatures and a picturesque form of
architecture which is particularly well represented in the
imperial castles of Gondar. The Western influences to be
seen in these Works, however, are more or less indirect
and probably came not by way of European masters, but
through builders or painters from India, where the Por¬
tuguese had recently been spreading a wide knowledge of
their techniques and their art-forms.
Ethiopia was to undergo yet one more trial before the
advent of modern times a sudden invasion by wave
upon wave of the Galla peoples coming from the south and
the south-east. Within a few centuries, however, the
nation was to absord this hardy strain, some groups of
the invaders adopting Christianity and some Islam.
Once again, Ethiopian culture emerged untouched from
this period of turmoil, while the invaders, on the contrary,
adopted the classical dignity, of Ethiopian dress and cer¬
tain features of the law and the social organization of ths
old empire.
Ethiopia's real contacts with Europe date from the
opening of the Suez canal, from which time European
specialists were called in by some of the rulers to teach
the people those modern practices and techniques that
could be integrated with the country's simple way of life.
Ethiopia's contacts With European culture were made
easier by the fact that, the nation had throughout its
history been familiar with writing and legislation, and
had its own characteristic code of aesthetics.
The personality of Ethiopia developed in circumstances
exceptionally favourable to a proper balance, in a part of
Africa in which it could gather together elements of all
the great civilizations, from the most "classic" to those of
the distant East.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1959
THE EL DORADO RULED
BY THE ASHANTI KINGS
by Jacqueline Delange
Département d'Afrique Noire, Musée de l'Homme, Paris
To the martial din of drums, bells, gongs, horns and
rattles, amid puffs of smoke from muskets fired in
salute and under German, Danish and British flags
gaily fluttering in the breeze, the British emissaries to the
monarch of the Ashanti peoples made their way to the
Kumasi Palace through a host of over 5,000 soldiers and
war chiefs in full dress array. Their slow progress
through this amazing assembly had taken them no less
than one-and-a-half hours.
The head of the mission wrote an account, of this
occasion, which is a veritable panegyric on gold and
silver and the dazzling use made of them by this royal
court at a time the early nineteenth century when it
was barely known to the outside world. The Europeans
were astounded by the wealth of Ashanti, but the things
in all this glowing pageantry which struck them most
were what they took to be barbaric elements; they did
not discover therein the history of a culture.
"...A hundred or so great parasols or canopies, large
enough to shelter at least thirty persons, were being con¬
tinually waved to and fro by their bearers ; they were
made of silk, in scarlet, yellow and other bright colours,
and surmounted by crescents, pelicans, elephants, swords
and other weapons, all of solid gold... The king's messen¬
gers wore great gold breast-plates, captains and persons
of consequence wore solid gold necklaces skilfully wrought,
the chief executioner bore on his breast a solid gold axe,
maidens carried golden bowls and the interpreters stood
behind clusters of gold-knobbed sticks...".
Gold was everywhere, glaring more intensely than the
sun itself; it was more heavily concentrated in the palace,
where it was worn by the officers responsible for the royal
household, the chamberlain, the hornblower, the captain
of the messengers, the king's executioner, the controller
of markets and the priest in charge of the land where
members of the royal family were buried. But, above all,
it cast a glow of light and prestige on the great sovereign
descended from Osai Tutu, the founder of the Ashanti
nation, whose reign had presaged the future glory of the
kingdom, a golden stool, symbol of the royal authority,
having been sent to him from the skies.
Fire-bearing smiths led
emigrants to new lands
Even today we cannot help being astounded by this
elaborate metalwork, through we know of only a frac¬
tion of its countless treasures. The techniques them¬
selves casting by the loss wax process, hammering and
repoussé work, and the application of metal to a wooden
core show a peerless mastery of the materials used. In
all probability this exquisite workmanship as early as
1700 a traveller considered some (of these works "quite
pleasing"' must be regarded as the fruit of ancient craft
traditions which had been the monopoly of- the smiths'
caste.
In the old Alkan communities of which the Ashanti are
a branch, the smiths, bearing their fires with them, used
to set out" at the head of groups of emigrants, leading
them to new lands. But as Ashanti power grew and the
royal court increased in importance, the various craftsmen
all turned their steps to Kumasi and the arts were used
for the service of the king. All the African monarchies,
such as the kingdoms of Ife, Benin and Abomey in the
West, and of the Loango and Bakuba in the Congo and
the great sultanates or chiefdoms of the Cameroons,
greatly increased the demand for art objects as the out¬
ward signs of power were built up.
Corporations of craftsmen serving the royal families,
ritual institutions on a more or less national scale, and a
victorious nation, took the place of the castes and the
initiated artists of the little peasant communities in which
wood-carving, either as a stylized or a realistic art, had
been linked directly Iwith ancestor and divinity worship.
Uproar and torchlight marked
the Spring festival of the yam
The "Odwirä" or yam ceremony of the Ashanti, a Spring
festival and also the feast of the dead, still has the
feudal pomp and splendour of a great day including
sacrificial rites and entertainments, uproar and torch¬
light by night, dancing, the Waving of feathers and ele¬
phant tails by young people, endless processions of
dignitaries Weighed down with gold and supported by
slaves, other slaves bearing golden pipes, ostrich-feather
fans, golden swords, silver vases and the king's ivory and
gold chair.
Among the pendant masks, breast-plates, rings, brace¬
lets and other jewelry, ornaments on ceremonial weapons,
vases and weights for weighing gold dust, all are so richly
decorated that one is at a loss to single out any object
as more remarkable than the rest. The pendant masks
depicting human features, are well known. All the
Akan kingdoms made heads finely cast by the lost wax
process, some of which are genuine likenesses.
An amazing variety of weights were used for weighing
gold dust, some having geometrical designs, others repre¬
senting proverbs. The imagination displayed in the
former type of weight knew no bounds and the goldsmith's
genius for decoration is matched by the accuracy of his
observation. The geometric designs are by no means
unlimited in number but it is difficult for us to grasp
their meaning, which would provide the clue to the weight
system used.
The lids of Kuduo or ritual vases, the shapes and orna¬
mentation of which bear a certain resemblance to antique
cists or to Chinese bronzes, are also surmounted by sym¬
bolic decorative motifs; an orchestra conductor surrounded
by his musicians represents the undisputed pre-eminence
of the chief. The elaboration and lavish decoration found
in these vases are also a feature of the splendid ornamen¬
tation of the great inlaid-copper hexagonal chests, covered
with black velvet and golden rosettes, in which members
of the royal family were laid to rest in the funeral cham¬
bers set aside for each of the kings in the Royal Mau¬
soleum.
Legends, proverbs and popular sayings reflecting not
only aristocratic institutions but also everyday activities
are likewise represented in the Ashanti textiles.
Besides goldsmiths and weavers the royal institutions
also required potters. Women were not permitted to make
anthropomorphic ceramics, vases or pipes for ritual use;
they had to confine themselves to commercial or everyday
pottery. But in their terra-cotta works, the women, too,
show the flair lor decoration, instinct for beauty of form
and technical skill so characteristic of the Ashanti.
The Ashanti genius for expressing beauty in form is
perhaps yet more strikingly revealed in the so-called
"Akua Ba" figurines, finely carved in wood with a reddish-
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
GOLDEN DEATH MASK
of King Kofi of Ashanti
is now stored in the Wal¬
lace Collection in London.
It demonstrates the peerless
skill displayed by Ashanti
metal craftsmen, for whom
gold was a working material
par excellence. Nineteenth-
century Western envoys to
an Ashanti king found gold
decorations widely used in
his palace and worn by his
chief officers of state. The
king himself wore necklaces
of golden shells and a breast¬
plate in the form of a full¬
blown rose and he carried
gold castanets which he
clicked to attract attention.
© Wallace Collection, London.
brown or black patina and representing the stylized image
of beauty. It is believed that pregnant women possessing
one are bound to have a child as handsome as these well-
proportioned Wooden figurines.
Once diverted from the religious uses of ancestor
worship and from aiding small groups, struggling to
survive, in placating supernatural powers, the Ashanti arts
were used exclusively in the service of the royal insti¬
tutions. The availability of gold, favourable economic
relations, power and prestige, and extensive contacts with
the outside world account for the luxury, refinement and
beauty of the art that grew out of the traditional qualities
of the old castes of craftsmen.
The rich arts ,of the Ashanti kingdom thus take their
place among all the other African arts, and the cultures
behind them, as the embodiment of an impressive civiliza¬
tion. For was this not a civilization whose exceptional
destiny was miraculously revealed to the people? The
story is told that in the presence of a great multitude,
under lowering clouds and amid resounding claps of
thunder, the air grew thick with white smoke and a
threelegged golden stool with its gold and silver bells
dropped gently from the skies into the lap of the Ashanti
king. In later days, neither the Ashanti nation nor its
artists were ever likely to forget this supernatural wonder
of their kingship's origin.
34
SOME BOOKS ON AFRICA
"Old Africa Rediscovered" by Basil Davidson is the first
book which deals in a general and non-specialist way with
the history of Africa south of the Sahara in the 15 or 20
centuries before the colonial period began. Must reading
for all those interested in "knowing more of the discoveries
made in recent years concerning Africa's little known past.
Publisher Victor Gollancz Ltd., London; 25/-. American
title: "The Lost Cities of Africa," published by Atlantic
Monthly Press, Boston 16, Mass., U.S.A.
Other works on specific aspects of Africa's past which may
interest readers:
Fagg, W., and Elisofon, E., The Sculpture of Africa, 1958
(Thames and Hudson, London, 70/-).
Forde, Daryll (Ed.), African Worlds, 1954.
Frobenius, L., Histoire de la Civilisation Africaine, Paris.
Herskovits, M. J., The Myth of the Negro Past, 1941.
Nadel, S. F., A Black Byzantium, 1942.
Arkell, A. J., A History of the Sudan, 1955.
Bovill, E. W., Golden Trade of the Moors, 1958.
Lebeuf, J. P., and Masson-Detourbet, A. La Civilisation du
Tchad, 1950.
Park, Mungo. Travels.
Doresse, J., L'Empire du Prêtre Jean, 2 vol. 1957.
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
September/ October 1359
The shortage of doctors
in the world
world health!
Newly-qualified physician at one of the world's most ancient and most famous universities : Leyden.
Why
the lack of
doctors
in the world?
There are 1,300,000 doctors for the 2,700,000,000 human beings
in the world : one doctor per 700 inhabitants in some coun¬
tries and one per 180,000 inhabitants in others. This means
that at the present time there are immense populations
without any medical aid.
"World Health", the magazine published by the World
Health Organization, devotes a special number to this dra¬
matic situation.
WOrlCl h 631th can be obtained from the Division of
Public Information, World Health Organization, Palais des Nations,
Geneva, Switzerland.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
SKIEHf
IRON SCULPTURE
This shrine figure is the largest piece of
wrought-iron sculpture known from Africa,
It is five feet five inches high. The sculpt
very modern in appearance, comes fr
Dahomey, West Africa, and is said to h;
been made for the cult of Gu, God of I
and War. Headdress bears various imple¬
ments symbolizing the metal-working trade.
Photo Eliot Elisofon,. taken from "The Sculpture of
Africa" © Thames & Hudson Ltd., London 1958
]]>
</page>
</document>
