<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="066651eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
Special Issue
UNESCO'S NEW
HEADQUARTERS
. rice: 2/6 stg. (U.K.,
50 cents (U . S.)
150 francs (France)
November 1958 (11th year)
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
DESCENDING SPIRAL of concrete stairway blends with gently
curving facade of one wing of Unesco's Y-shaped Secretariat
building. Stairway, for use of firefighters, has water supply
column running up its centre. However, in case of fire,
Unesco staff would leave building by interior stairways.
Horizontal partition bars projecting from building's facade
at each floor level are concrete. Vertical window partition
slabs are cut from travertine, a light-coloured Italian marble.
© Almasy, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
1 WINDOW OMN ON* THI irOILD
ner
NOVEMBER 1958
I I T H YEAR
No. II
CONTENTS
PAGE
3
4
EDITORIAL
A NEW ART OF BUILDING
By Françoise Choay
5 THREE-POINTED STAR IN PARIS
10 MURALS BY AFRO, APPEL AND MATTA
16 UNESCO HOUSE IS THEIR HANDIWORK
18 THE LANGUAGE OF ABSTRACT ART
By Roque Javier Laurenza
19 UNESCO AND ITS DECOR IN COLOUR
23 TRIUMPH IN CONCRETE
Feats of imaginative engineering
26 PROMETHEUS BRINGING FIRE TO MAN
The glowing red fresco of Rufino Tamayo
27 PICASSO AND THE 40 PANELS
Giant composition on wood
29 BRONZE FORMS AND STONE PATTERNS
Haut-relief by Arp; Mosaic by Bazaine
30 GYRATIONS IN SPACE
Alexander Calder's clockwise spiral
31 REPOSE IN STONE
Henry's Moore's largest statue
32 GARDEN OF PEACE
Japanese invitation to meditation
34 MY LATEST WORK-A WALL
By Joan Miró
37 UNESCO: WHAT IS IT 7 WHAT DOES IT DO ?
Scientific and Cultural
France
French Edition
Spanish Edition
Russian Edition
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational,
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7"
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
Alexandre Leventis
Jorge Carrera Andrade
Veniamin Matchavariani
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (I 2 issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. The United States of America edition is distri¬
buted by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 801 Third Avenue, New
York 22, N.Y., Plaza 1-3860. Second-class mail privileges authorized ac New
York, N.Y. (M.C. 58.1.130 A)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER plus date
of issue", and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: $3.00; IO/-stg. ; 500 Fr. frs. or equivalent.
a,
COVER PHOTO
An immense "three-pointed star",
Unesco's Secretariat building is raised
16 feet off the ground throughout its
entire length by 72 concrete pilotis.
Photo shows an end wall with four of the
pilotis and the graceful sweep of this
building's south-west facade. In fore¬
ground is part of delegates' lobby linking
Secretariat and Conference buildings.
UNESCO-Albert Raccah
Today Unesco possesses a home of its own in Paris, a
headquarters commensurate 'with its needs and with
the goals it has set itself. This is a building which
rests on something more than its foundations of concrete
for it harbours some of the noblest hopes of man-
The international character of its construction becomes
visible the moment one crosses its threshold: the floor is
of Norwegian quartzite, aluminium panels have come from
Belgium, lighting equipment "was made in the United
States and on the French-made glass doors are teak
finger plates from Burma.
Architects from France, America, Italy, Brazil and
Sweden conceived and carried out the plans or gave
their help and advice. Industrial and technological
skills from many countries were brought to bear on the
construction and, as the buildings rose to join the Paris
skyline, the tongues of many nations were heard among
the workers and craftsmen on the site.
Within the large perimeter of this seven-and-a-half
acre site there has been a harmonious blending of
architecture and art. And like the architects, technicians,
contractors and workmen, the painters and sculptors too
are from many lands. They were born in places as far
apart as Amsterdam and Santiago, Strasbourg and Phila¬
delphia, and they include some of the best-known figures
in contemporary art.
In building the new headquarters Unesco received un¬
failing help from its Member States. First and foremost
came the contribution of the French Government which
enabled Unesco to build its home on an attractive site in
Paris. And throughout the buildings there is tangible
proof of the generosity shown by other countries in the
many and valuable gifts of furnishings and decorations.
Unesco House is far more than a collection of new forms
and decorative details, a synthesis of 20th century artistic
and architectural expression. It is above all a place in
which to work. The design of the Secretariat building
a "'three-pointed star*' which might lead one to suspect
a formal aesthetic effort, is, in fact, completely functional.
It is an architectural formula which has enabled commu¬
nications within each department and between depart¬
ments to be greatly shortened. The same concern for
efficiency has determined the layout of the Conference
building. The location of its committee rooms and offices
and its lighting and acoustical arrangements should all
make for good working conditions.
From a small flat in Grosvenor Square and two adjoin¬
ing houses in Belgrave Square, London, where Unesco
was founded 13 years ago, the Organization went to the
Hotel Majestic in Paris. Here it continued to grow in
strength and authority until the day when Member
States decided that it could no longer be content with
makeshift premises.
As the new headquarters was inaugurated on November
3, 1958, the measure of this growth and maturity was
symbolized by the flags of Member States flying proudly
from their 81 masts.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
NEW ART
BIT I T T\ ¥ TiT f**
U 1 Jj .D 1 N \J>
The visitor who stands at the foot of the Conference
Building at Unesco's new headquarters in Paris
finds himself facing a Wall of folded concrete unlike
any other a wall which, if one must find comparisons,
suggests the large surfaces that the Egyptians designed for
the sun and our modern builders of dams design for the
waters of rivers. And when he turns to the Secretariat
building he must sense in the double row of its supporting
concrete pilotis the power of the thrust that lifts the
building high into the air.
Here, on the left bank of the Seine, an international
team of architects, artists, industrial designers and
builders has conceived and wrought a work whose style
springs directly from the heart of the materials and
techhiques exclusive to our age.
In erecting its headquarters, Unesco sought a functional
solution that could be carried out as economically as
possible rather than the erection of a sumptuous building
designed purely for purposes of prestige. Thus it chose
as basic element the most inexpensive and widely used
of modern building materials^reinforced concrete.
The builders made full use of its essential quality,
plasticity, to devise structures most appropriate to the
functions of Unesco. These are spread over two buildings,
the Secretariat and the Conference building, which are
joined by a broad, low lobby. Third unit in this
architectural ensemble is the building for permanent
delegations.
The Secretariat building presents a striking variation
of a construction technique that has become a standard
one ever since the age of supporting arches and walls
was superseded by the age of structures with supporting
posts and beams. The architects took advantage of the
freedom this allows to use a Y-form with curved prongs
that made it possible both to complete the empty half of.
the semi-circular Place de Fontenoy and to arrange the
offices in simple linear_succession. The common
circulation and service facilities^ (lifts, stairways, wash¬
rooms) are grouped at the meeting-point of the prongs
of the Y.
The chief problems raised by the Conference Building
(to be used for meetings and discussions) were acoustical.
Sound had to break constantly against the surfaces of its
large walls. The solution chosen was a system of walls
and roofing of folded concrete, a material whose plasticity
has made possible a complex set of emergent and re-
entrant angles, which create a succession of folds such as
might be obtained with a metallic sheet. The walls, which
are of unequal height and slope outward, support the
extremities of the roofing. This sloping roofing, set on
two asymetrical levels, rests at its centre on a row of
concrete pillars.
Thus, the plasticity of concrete not only plays a role in
the choice of structure, but also makes for a greater
freedom (of which modern architecture often fails to take
sufficient advantage), and reveals itself in the fashioning
of these buildings, in the forms given to their elements.
The folding of the concrete, the contour of the pillars,
whose forms defy description, appear as unhampered
variations on a material of which anything can be
demanded. The 72 pilotis of the Secretar¬
iat which lift the building five metres
from the ground and create' a marvellous
sweep of space, are' like something out of a
dream; thin and elliptical at the base and
slanting inward, they are extended at the
THREE-POINTED STAR
RISES IN PARIS
To the rear of the Military College In Paris, on a site previously
occupied by a cavalry regiment barracks, now stands a group
of three buildingsUnesco's new headquarters. As shown on
architects' model (left) they are: left, the Conference building;
foreground, the building for permanent delegations; centre, the
Secretariat building. Lower photo on opposite page (taken
from the Eiffel. Tower) shows how the new Unesco head¬
quarters has been integrated with an ensemble of classical
monuments and has Introduced into the Paris landscape an
architectural pattern which represents a new art of building.
Aerial photo (top of page) shows an axis of Parisian landmarks,
old and new. From the foreground these are: semi-circular
Palais de Chaillot (1937); Eiffel Tower (987 feet high; built
1889-90); and at far end of the Champs de Mars with its trees
and gardens, 18th century buildings of the Military Staff
College. Unesco buildings (not constructed when photo was
taken) now stand at top right-hand corner of this rectangle
and complete the semi-circle of the Place de Fontenoy.
UNESCO
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1958
© von Werthern
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Ä NEW ART
OF BUILDING **_«
top by consoles, which pair them in veritable porticos.
Following on the aesthetic reaction, a closer study
reveals that these forms in no way represent a striving
for effect. They are the mathematical expression of the
smallest quantity of material to be employed for the
effort required. Indeed, it is the portico structure, applied
to pilotis, that makes it possible for the shafts to be so
slender, and if the ellipse of their base has been placed
perpendicularly to the axis of the upper pillars, this was
done in order to ensure the transversal rigidity of the
building. This dynamic arrangement also made it
possible to set the pilotis six metres apart and thus to
serve aü a proportional unit for the entire building.
In the three buildings, the principle of economy of
material makes for complex forms. Thus, the chief
girders of the Secretariat, like metallic girders, taper at
their extremities in a slope that expresses the falling-off
of the load; the thickness of the slabs which they support
is similarly reduced on the cantilever surface of the
offices, so that the ceilings of these rooms are not
horizontal but slope upward, heightening the effect of
the glass surfaces of the facades.
Flights of fancy for
down-to-earth reasons
Similarly, the pillars of the Conference Building whose
splendid cement shafts justify their comparison to
the columns of antique structures are the result of
strict calculations which required a circular section at
their base and a rectangular one at the apex in order to
ensure the longitudinal rigidity of the edifice.
Moreover, the corrugations in the concrete of this
building have more than an acoustical function. In
stiffening the thin, 35-centimetre wall, they also resist
the static stress of the roof.
All of these forms, whose diversity and elaboration seem
to be the product of flights of imagination, are really the
result of strict economic logic. The inside of the buildings
is a reflection of the outside, for there too the concrete
structures are quite bare, as is testified by the walls of
the conference rooms, by the columns of the delegates'
lobby, or by the lift shaft, which acts as a support in the
central core of the Secretariat building.
The expressiveness of the handsome structural forms
has been enhanced by a metamorphosis of concrete, which,
though used in its crude form, has been raised by skilful
and ingenious techniques to the level of the finest of
materials.
In the case of the girders and pillars, a striated texture
that catches the light was obtained by the use of a
prepared shuttering. The once formless and lifeless
matter was shaped and quickened by the regular outline
of the woodwork. The walls of the Conference Building
are crossed horizontally and vertically by grooves which
divide them into separate elements, and they are
perforated with circular holes. The grooves and holes are
traces of the operations performed at each pouring to
ensure the homogeneity of the concrete and to avoid
distorting the form-work. These markings were not only
willingly accepted but even exploited to bring life to the
characterless surface of the concrete, by testifying that
this was the work of human hands.
What materials were chosen to go along with the rough
concrete of^the structures? Firstly, glass was used as a
thin insulating skin on the principal façades, then Wood,
being inexpensive, was employed for the entire window-
casing (except that of the ground floor, which is of
HOUSE OF GLASS. Between April 1955 when ground was first
broken on the seven-and-a-half acre site of Unesco's new headquarters
and July 1956 when the basic construction work was completed two
striking buildings rose to join the Paris landscape. The Secretariat
aluminium), and finally, travertine, a handsome Italian
stone which offers a contrast in texture and colour with
the concrete. . It was chosen to cover the outer and, in
many cases, even the inner, non-supporting masonry
surfaces. The primary function of the travertine is not
to provide decoration but rather to emphasize the
framework elements, to outline and point them up by
means of contrast. For example, the hollow-brick filling
that closes each of the- side walls of the Secretariat is
faced from top to bottom with a thin layer of travertine,
which is cut' horizontally just above the pilotis, thus
emphasizing the graceful slope and dynamic significance
of the pilotis.
Interplay of light on
vast, glassed facades
In the Conference Building, the role of the two non-
supporting façades is expressed by a facing of tra¬
vertine which, in certain places, reveals the concrete
structural elements. The contrast between the struc¬
tural and non-structural elements is heightened here by a
gap which completely dissociates the folded concrete roof
from the façades, to allow for continual movements of
expansion and contraction of the concrete.
The interiors, which are a counterpart of the façade,
offer the same contrasts. In the lobby of the Secretariat,
the concrete pilotis are enhanced by a grey Norwegian
quartzite floor, and in the large conference hall the same
contrast of colour is provided by the ebony of the
speakers' platform. Rough concrete posts and travertine
walls set each other off on the seventh floor of the
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1958
M|H
building might well be called the "House of Glass" with its 1,068 win¬
dows set in their array of concrete supports. Glass surfaces on the
three buildings at the headquarters cover a total area of nearly five
acres, the weight of the glass amounting to 175 tons. Photo on right,
Secretariat while the uniform grey of the offices stands
out against the whiteness of the accoustical tiles on the
concrete ceiling.
A tracery of horizontal and vertical lines has brought
intense life to the vast, glassed façades of the Secretariat
Building. This result was achieved except in the case of
the north façade by elements that give the window-
structure a three-dimensional effect, thereby creating
new volumes. Wooden window-frames are kept in place
by a system of prefabricated posts fixed at intervals of
three metres; every second post is set off by a thin vertical
slab of travertine joined at each extremity to louvered
elements of prefabricated concrete sun screens that
extend the cantilever of the floor slab.
The light can in this way play in and out between the
concrete vanes in a myriad fashions and create various
patterns of shadow among this network of interstices,
thus giving an intense animation to the whole. The
combinations of light are made even more complex by the
alternation of the travertine slabs on each floor. The
alternating arrangement practised here is the only
variation on the north façade, where the face not the
edge of the slabs is visible. On the south and east
façades sun filters of tempered grey glass attached to the
concrete elements create a third level in depth.
The same animation has been achieved in another way
by the treatment of stairways and porticos. One example
is the outside stairway of the east façade which is for the
use of firefighters. It is made entirely of identical parts
prefabricated in concrete forms. The fantastic upward
winding of this stairway, which is joined to the building
at each floor, gives a kind of rapid synthesis of curves,
straight lines and diagonals that vie with the harmony
of the façades.
Photos © von Werthern
taken during construction period, shows north-east facade of Sec¬
retariat building (446 feet long). In centre is firefighters' stairway
(see also page 2). Some of the 72 pilotis, set in pairs 20 feet apart,
on which building rests are seen through ground floor windows.
Similarly, on the large piazza of the Avenue de Suffren,
a canopy made up of two curved surfaces rests its
imposing cantilever on two small concrete masses and
continues, on an ampler scale, the themes of the right and
acute angles and of the sweep of the façades.
Vying with the boldest
creations of plastic arts
The architecture of the new Unesco Headquarters is
marked by a freedom, expressed in a wealth of
forms in which functionalism does not' exclude
poetry. The stairway of the east façade and the folded
walls of the Conference Hall have the quality of fanciful
images or of the boldest creations of the plastic arts. It
is also characterized by the attention it pays to a strict
economy of material, which bases its forms on closely
observed calculation and makes them a direct expression
of a dynamic plan. Finally, it is distinguished by its
frankness, which makes for an immediate "readability",
and by its uncompromising employment of materials and
constant use of emphasis and contrast. It is indeed, the
brilliant manifestation of a style.
Another version of this article appears in "Unesco Head¬
quarters Symbol of the 20th Century," an album published
by Gerd Hatje, Heidehofstrasse 40, Stuttgart, German Federal
Republic. This album can be obtained in English, French or
German editions from Unesco House, Place de Fontenoy, Paris.
It costs 1,000 Fr. frs. (or equivalent in other currencies) plus
postage. Orders should be accompanied by an international
money order. For full information, write directly to Unesco,
Place de Fontenoy, Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
IT T ' ImmWtPW
UNESCO - Berret
«THE REEDS'
Works by artists of widely
different origins decorate the
walls on the seventh floor
of the Secretariat building. In
addition to paintings by Afro
(Italy), Matta (Chile) and Appel
(Netherlands) there is a large
photomontage (9 feet by
24 feet) by Brassai. Right,
Brassaï and his work, "The
Reeds," which decorates the
cafeteria. One of the best-
known French photographers,
Brassai is of Hungarian origin.
UNESCO - Brent Hannon
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1958
Top floor view (left) from the
western end of the Secre¬
tariat building, 95 feet above
the ground, highlights the strik¬
ing effect achieved by the use
of a corrugated roof and fluted
end walls in the design of the
Conference building (right of
photo). Afternoon sun reflected
in myriad windows of the Secre¬
tariat building has painted a
speckled pattern on travertine
side wall facings of the Conference
building. A long, low hall links
the two structures and in front
of this stand the two ceramic-
decorated walls of Joan Miró
and Llorens-Artigas. The ceramic
visible here is the "Wall of the
Sun", the "Wall of the Moon"
being behind and at right angles
to it.
Functional reasons even more
than aesthetic ones prompted the
choice of a three-pointed star
form for the Secretariat building.
Its seventh floorfrom where
this photograph was takenis
almost entirely reserved for
Unesco staff services: restaurant,
cafeteria, bar, staff lounge, all of
which offer magnificent views
over Paris. Staff members and
visitors reach it in fully-automa¬
tic, electronically-operated lifts,
each capable of carrying 20 per¬
sons at a speed of 5 feet a second.
At the extremities of each
wing of the Secretariat building
are open-air terraces paved with
travertine, an Italian stone which
comes from Carrara, the region
where the raw material for Michel¬
angelo's sculptures came from
some 450 years ago. Each
slab of travertine is 13 feet
square and weighs nearly one ton.
The varied treatment of the
three curved facades . of the
Secretariat building results from
detailed research into the use of
and protection from sun radia¬
tion. The various seasons of the
year and the critical hours of the
day have been considered. The
resulting design shades the inte¬
riors from the high summer and
midday sun, transmits, however,
the low winter and morning and
evening sun. This is achieved,
without reducing the natural
light and the free view from the
interiors, by a combination of
projecting ceiling slabs and parti¬
tions with horizontal or vertical
solar glass filters. These grey
glass sheets (seen in upper photo,
left) filter out the infra-red rays
from the sun. but let through
the ultra-violet ones.
Photos UNESCO - Von Werthern
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
CROSS-SECTION
OF MODERN ART
IN the selection of the works of art that deco¬
rate the new Unesco headquarters, the Direc¬
tor-General was counselled by an Interna¬
tional Committee of Art Advisers formed of
Dr. C. Parra-Perez, of Venezuela (chairman),
M. Georges Salles (France), Mr. Shahid Suhra-
wady (Pakistan) and Sir Herbert Read (Great
Britain). Architects who prepared the headquar¬
ters' plans were represented on this committee by
M. Bernard Zehrfuss of France and the interna¬
tional panel of consultative architects by Mr. Er¬
nesto Rogers of Italy.
By recommendation of the advisory committee
paintings by Afro (Italy), Karel Appel (Nether¬
lands) and Roberto Matta (Chile) were commis¬
sioned for the seventh floor, where there is also a
photomontage done by Brassai. Pablo Picasso
and Rufino Tamayo (Mexico) painted murals, the
former a painting on wood that dominates the
delegates' hall, the latter a fresco in the large
commission room of the Conference building. A
statue by Henry Moore (U.K.), and a mobile by
Alexander Calder (U.S.A.) adorn the grounds;
sculptured motifs in haut relief by Jean Arp
(France) decorate the end wall of the library ;
ceramics by Miro and Artigas cover two walls
between the Conference and Secretariat buildings;
and at the foot of the building for permanent dele¬
gations extends a garden designed by Isamu Nogu-
chi and executed under his direction by Japanese
gardeners. Another work of art, a mosaic by the
French painter Jean Bazaine has been commis¬
sioned for the wall of the delegations' building
overlooking the Japanese garden. (Reproductions
of these works and facts about them and their
authors are published on other pages).
All these artists were chosen not as representa¬
tives of any particular school of painting or
national form of art, but as internationally recog¬
nized figures in contemporary art.
'GARDEN OF HOPE'
Born In Udine, Italy, in 1912, Afro (Afro
Basaldella) was 18 years old when he held
his first exhibition in Milan. At this time
his painting was post-Impressionistic. Later,
he showed an interest in Cubism, but after
the war he turned to abstract painting in a
very personal style. He now lives in Rome
where, last year, he was doing theatrical
decor in addition to his painting. "La
Chronique Noire," a painting he did in I 950,
was among the works exhibited at Brussels
this year in the exhibition: "Fifty Years of
Modern Art." Photo, right, shows Afro
(on right of photo) helping to mount his
painting, "The Garden of Hope," on a wall
of the 7th floor of the Secretariat building.
UNESCO - Marc Laloux
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1958
A WORLD OF HIS OWN
"If one wants to place Appel, it is fruitless to
look for a general term. It is hard to classify
him. His mind is independent and certainly
his attitude towards classicism is anarchistic.
In considering his work it is more appropriate
to speak of expressionism." Karel Appel,
of whom a French art critic wrote these
words, is a Netherlands' painter who was
born in Amsterdam in 1921. "Appel,"
wrote the same critic, "has succeeded in
creating his own adventurous world in a
style which he himself has devised. His
art reflects a direct approach to his subjects,
which he treats with violence and strength."
Since 1950 Karel Appel (left, at work in
his studio) has been living and painting in
Paris where he has held several exhibitions.
UNESCO-Pablo Volta
ARCHITECT TURNED PAINTER
At 1 7 years of age Roberto Matta entered
the School of Beaux-Arts at his birthplace,
Santiago, Chile, with the intention of becom¬
ing an architect. Three years later he went
to Paris where he enrolled in the School of
Town Planning and afterwards began work
with Le Corbusier who predicted a brilliant
architectural career for him. But Matta
suddenly turned to painting. He was at
first strongly influenced by surrealism and
until 1948 he remained in the group of
surrealists, but his art later evolved towards
expressionism. In I 957theMuseumof Modern
Art in New York held an important retros¬
pective exhibition of his painting. Matta has
lived and painted in the United States, Mexico
and Italy, but has now returned to Paris.
UNESCO-Pablo Volta
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO STAMPS
AND SOUVENIRS
Many of UNESCO'S Member States are issuing com¬
memorative postage stamps to mark the inauguration
of the Organization's new Headquarters. Stamps
reproduced here are from France and Poland.
On November 1,1958, the French Government issued
two new postage stamps in denominations of 20 and
3 5 francs representing two different views of the
UNESCO Headquarters. First day covers, both enve¬
lopes and postcards, featuring printed enlargements of
the new French issues were available to philatelists on
November I and 2, 1958, the first days of issue and
cancellation. Philatelists may still obtain these first
day covers while the supply lasts, by placing orders
with: Unesco Staff Service, Office 7122, UNESCO,
9, place de Fontenoy, Paris-7e, accompanied by advance
payment (plus postage) either by cheque or money
order payable to UNESCO Staff Service. Payments made
in currency other than French francs will be converted
at the official exchange rate in Paris on the date of
receipt of cheque or money order.
Cost of a set of two envelopes and a set of two postcards,
each set containinga20fr. and a 35 fr. French stamp, is
500 francs. On orders for less than ten sets, I 00 francs
should be added to the cost of the cards and the enve¬
lopes to cover mailing costs.
Collectors visiting UNESCO Headquarters will also be
able to buy stamps issued by the United Nations Postal
Administration and certain of the commemorative
stamps issued by UNESCO Member States. These stamps
are on sale in the Main Lobby at the Gift Shop, a kiosk
of metal and wood construction presented by Norway.
Similar in purpose to the shops of the United Nations
in New York and Geneva, this shop will display for sale
handicrafts from Member States.
1,200 FEET
OF BOOKSHELVES
Built around eight of the giant pilotis which dominate
the ground floor of the Secretariat building, the UNESCO
Library is a gift of the Swedish Government, which entrusted
its design and construction to the "Svenska Slojdforeningen"
(Swedish Association for Arts and Crafts) and the Swedish
National Commission for UNESCO.
A reading room and reference library for UNESCO staff,
it features 1,200 feet of shelving in light wood for books
and periodicals. The furniture is in natural fir and red beech
with plastic lacquer finish, most of It fixed to the floor, and
supported by black terrazo bases, rising from the natural
coloured cork floor.
Special lighting has been installed on all the work tables and
the bookshelves Book lifts connect the reference library
(12,000 volumes) with a storeroom of books not in current
use and with departmental reference libraries located in this
building. There are 50,000 books in the reserve stock and
the Library has a permanent collection of 3,000 periodicals.
Area of the Library, for which the architects were Hans
Borgstrom and Bengt Lindroos, is 3,300 square feet.
UNESCO - Marc Laloux
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1958
STANDARD SIZE of the 650 offices in the
Secretariat building is 13 feet by 10 feet
by 8 feet 6 inches in height. From its centre,
each ceiling rises a further foot or so towards
the windows, whose French-made frames run
on German-made ball-bearings. The ceilings
are covered with white slabs of sound proofing
material, floors with grey linoleum (over
3 00,000 sq. ft. were used in the building).
Central heating pipes running at the base of
the windows are hidden under slabs of grey
slate. Interior doors came from the Nether¬
lands and have metal fittings from the U.S.A.
UNESCO
MAIN LOBBY occupies most of the ground
floor of the Secretariat building. It has a
floor of grey Norwegian quartzite underneath
which central heating pipes are concealed.
Its great length is broken at regular intervals
by the 72 remarkable concrete pilotis on which
the building is supported. Copper pipes
inside the pilotis drain the rainwater from the
roof. In this glass enclosed public space are
the bank, bookstore, travel and information
services, a gift shop and the entry to an under¬
ground cinema. At one end of the lobby is the
Unesco Library while the other end of this
main artery of circulation leads into the dele¬
gates' lobby and the Conference building.
UNESCO-Berretty
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
O
<
Photos UNESCO - Berretty
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1958
i von Werthen
UNESCO-Berretty
'WINGED COIF'
ENTRANCE
Shape of the large concrete portico standing
before the entrance of the longest facade of the
Secretariat building is suggestive of a nun's
winged coif. It is 50 feet in length (about one-
tenth of the total length of the facade) and
over 100 tons of concrete were poured in its
construction. Dominating the whole facade
it has been described as a "triumph of imagina¬
tive engineering" and "coming close to being
a piece of sculpture in itself." Main entrance
to Unesco Headquarters, on the opposite side
of the Secretariat building, also has a portico,
but of much smaller dimensions. Photo, above,
is a close-up, looking skywards, of the hori¬
zontal concrete louvers and vertical travertine
slabs which help to shade the interior of the
Secretariat building from the sun. Extra pro¬
tection is provided on south-west and parts
of south-east facades by glass solar filters.
UNESCO-Pablo Volta
m&JMWÊÊM
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Unesco
House
is their
handiwork
CHARLES
LE CORBUSIER
(FRANCE)
WALTER GROPIUS
(U.S.A.)
BERNARD ZEHRFUSS
(FRANCE)
PIER LUIGI NERVI
(ITALY)
MARCEL BREUER
(U.S.A.)
Designed by an international panel of architects, UNESCO'S new headquarters
occupies a seven and a half acre site made available to UNESCO by the French
Government.
Plans for the three buildings of the headquarters were prepared jointly by Marcel
Breuer of the United States, Pier Luigi Nervi of Italy and Bernard Zehrfuss of
France; they were approved by an international panel of five architects: Lucio
Costa (Brazil), Walter Gropius (United States), Charles Le Corbusier (France),
Sven Markelius (Sweden) and Ernesto Rogers (Italy). American architect Eero
Saarinen was also consulted.
Architectand designer, Marcel Breuer has taught and lectured in universities and
art institutes in the United States and other countries. He is the author of many
widely published articles on art and architecture. Important projects of his now
being built include: Arts Centre and Theatre, Sarah Lawrence College, New York;
Grosse Pointe Public Library, Michigan; and the Airport Terminal buildings at
Fairbanks and Anchorage, Alaska.
Pier Luigi Nervi, engineer, architect, teacher and writer, has designed and cons¬
tructed many buildings in Italy, making special use of reinforced concrete. These
projects include stadiums, theatres, industrial plants, department stores and
aerodrome buildings.
Bernard Zehrfuss, winner of the Rome Grand Prix is architect and adviser to
many official and private organizations. Among his recent works are the National
Centre for Mechanized Industries, in Paris, the Renault motor car works at Flins
and many housing projects in France, Algeria and Tunisia.
Charles Le Corbusier is widely known for his bold architectural conceptions which
have materialized in such projects as the city of Chandigarh in India and the ultra¬
modern building, the cité radieuse, in Marseilles, France.
Walter Gropius is one of the pioneers of modern conceptions of architecture and
the founder of the famous Bauhaus school in Germany.
Ernesto Rogers has carried out many important town-planning and architectural
projects and has taught in several universities.
Sven Markelius is town planner for Stockholm.
Lucio Costa drew up the plans for Brazil's new capital, Brasilia.
Eero Saarinen is architectural consultant to General Motors.
The technical construction work at the Unesco headquarters site was directed by
Eugene H. Callison, American architect and engineer.
UNESCO'S new home is the result oftheir joint efforts.
LUCIO COSTA
(BRAZIL)
SVEN MARKELIUS
(SWEDEN)
ERNESTO ROGERS
(ITALY)
EERO SAARINEN
(U.S.A.)
A Secretariat build¬
ing. - B Conference
building. - C Third
building. - D Car park.
- E Car entrance. -
F Piazza. - G Dele¬
gates' patio. - H Japa¬
nese garden.
I Library - 2 Visitors'
service - 3 Lifts -
4 Bookshop - 5 News¬
paper stand - 6 Travel
and hotel accommo¬
dation - 7 To the cine¬
ma and radio studios -
8 Bank - 9 Tourism -
10 Salle des Pas Per¬
dus - I I Plenary hall
1-12 Cloak-room -
13 Bar - 14 Reception
>
<
P V-
u 	
$£
Ol
i
t>
JÇ> -.
\
1.6
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1958
- 1 5 Documents distri<
bution - 16 Commit
tee room
17 Commission room
II - 18 To Rooms IV
and V - 19 To Press
room - 20 Way to
Rooms VI, VII & VIII.
U E 5 U
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
THE LANGUAGE OF
ABSTRACT ART
by Roque Javier Laurenza
Among the many people who have visited Unesco's
new headquarters on Place de Fontenoy in Paris,
d there are some who have made unfavourable
comments about the predominating abstract style of the
works of art which decorate the Organization's new
home.
Such criticisms are not new, nor are the arguments
in favour. But perhaps a further comment will not be
out of place.
For anyone who does not have frequent contact with
works of art, abstract art like so-called pure poetry
and musicdoes not reflect human interests or
conflicts. It is an impenetrable phenomenon, gratuitous
and incomprehensible. Basically, this criticism is
founded on the debatable premise of the antagonism
between form and content, the old belief that the
aesthetic value of a work lies in its meaning, in
something anecdotal, logical and discursive. But in
reality a work of art is an autonomous universe, a
world in itself.
A story is told which gives point to this argument.
A distinguished lady, on meeting Delacroix, said to
him: "Oh what a pity that you were not at the British
Embassy ball! Just imagine, the Duke of Wellington
was talking to Prince Metternich in a corner for ages
what a subject for a painter!" And Delacroix, bowing
to the lady, replied: "Madam, for a true painter there
was only a blue spot beside a red spot..."
It is difficult to reproach abstract art with being
completely estranged from life. What could be more
expressive of human feeling than the intimate landscapes
and the secret perspectives of the soul of an artist?
Of course, abstract painting is not a definitive style, nor
an example for all time. But it is an undeniable fact
that it represents one of man's artistic expressions
through the ages, and that it reappears with a strangely
cyclical regularity.
Nor is it necessary to take a stand and say, cate¬
gorically, that abstract art is the only valid art form
of our time. It is better to adopt a long view and to
consider it as a very generalized expression of this
century's culture. Artistic phenomena do not spring
up like mushrooms. It is a historical fact that abstract
art forms have appeared simultaneously in the United
States and in France, in Brazil and Greece, in Peru
and India.
TN the case of abstract or non-figurative art, the
first thing that strikes us is that wherever it
appears, it seems as if it were emerging from deep
historical strata and not simply from the whim of an
isolated group of artists. A second look will show
that the tendency towards the purely abstract is not
new and that it has a special significance. And lastly,
it does not indicate the absence or decadence of a
technical ability to reproduce reality in its precise
details. On the contrary it responds to an express
will of art, or Kunstwollen, as the Germans say.
One of the principal characteristics of abstract art
(as of all art) lies in the free and autonomous use of
artistic elements: lines and colours in the case of
painting; sounds in certain classical musical composi¬
tions, as for example in a Bach fugue, and the
pleasures produced by them do not have a pathetic
relationship with the private feelings of one person
or another, as Ortega y Gasset once pointed out.
A factor which has played an important part in the
evolution of abstract art is the development of
photography. The faithful eye of the camera has
liberated the arts from their servitude to concrete
reality. For deep down in human consciousness there
is always the desire to perpetuate one's memory on
earth. The custom of erecting monuments and painting
pictures to record the profiles and acts of men whether
it be a Caesar or just an ordinary man arises from
this psychological need.
There is another factor to be taken into account
when considering abstract art. Art historians
J have pointed out that the existence of natural¬
istic and antinaturalistic styles through the centuries
are an echo of different spiritual realities. Naturalistic
tendencies generally appear in times of stability, when
man is content with his lot and when violent anta¬
gonisms do not exist. The trend towards abstrac¬
tionism, on the other hand, generally appears in times
when this happy relationship between man and his
environment does not exist. In this case, since the
artist reflects his time, it often happens that he creates
abstract forms because he can introduce in them a har¬
mony that responds to a basic human desire for
balance and concord.
We live in a time of vital change, when men are
wrestling with vast problems to which they cannot yet
find the answers. This may explain the retreat of the
artist from reality. Then there is also the impact of
science. The world is full of mathematical formulas
and abstract forms of scientific discoveries charted in
laboratories. It may toe that the artist, influenced by
these factors, is trying to translate such mathematical
images into the algebra of an artistic style.
All this goes to show that, after all, abstract art does
mean something. In fact, each form of art has its own
particular language and those who study it must know
or at least understand this language. It is by no means
certain that all classical forms are understood at first
glance, for the work of art speaks only to sympathetic
ears.
In any case, the works of art exhibited in the new
Unesco headquarters are in harmony with the
architecture. They are the creations of artists of
international repute and are examples of contemporary
art. The saying: "I do not propose anything, I do not
impose anything, I expose" would be a very apt motto
for any collection of modern works of art.
The rest is a debate for tomorrow. Time will show
whether these particular works are Horace's "eternal
monument" or Malraux's "scar on the earth". But
they are the products of our time, and as such they
may have many meanings and bring further proof that
the twentieth century is striving for unity and order
among the diversity and chaos of our time.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
f -
Uli M 1
II1III1 s s
lililí a
a s
li
t >
Î^WWTOTOÎï,
UNESCO Albert Raccah
LONGEST FACADE of the Unesco Secretariat building (486 feet) overlooking the spacious headquarters piazza.
KAREL APPEL "Encounter in Springtime." Painting decorating wall of restaurant, Secretariat building.
UNESCO Claude Ferrand
XI
$ &s
3*
ft. ¡<i
YAft
M
^Jfc
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
THE WALL OF THE MOON
THE WALL OF THE SUN
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Standing in the gravelled court between the Secretariat
and Conference buildings are two free walls at right
angles to each other, decorated with ceramics which
constitute a striking ensemble in the new Unesco
headquarters. The joint work of two Spanish artists,
Joan Miro and José Llorens-Artigas, the ceramics form
two murals symbolizing day and night. The smaller
wall has as its central theme the blue crescent of the
moon (above), the larger wall representing the burning
red disc of the sun (below). Miro and Artigas executed
this great work of art in a tiny village in Spain, painting
and firing 585 tiles of different sizes which were
then transported to Paris for assembling at Unesco
House. See page 34, 'My Latest Work A Wall'.
UNESCO Photos - Claude Ferrand
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
\
V
UNESCO Jean-Pierre Grabet
PABLO PICASSO. Painting in delegates' lounge, Conference building.
22
UNESCO - Pablo Volta
AFRO. "Garden of Hope." Wall painting, 7th floor, Secretariat building.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1958
TRIUMPH IN
CONCRETE
UNESCO - Marc Laloux
The Unesco Conference building with ¡tsrfluted end walls and corrugated roof ¡s a striking monument
to the decorative use of reinforced concrete. This concrete has been treated in such a way that it
bears the imprint of the wood shutterings. The roof slopes from a height of 40 feet at one end
and 46 feet at the other down to a centre height of just over 32 feet. Here it is supported on six
columns. The roof is covered by 20 tons of copper sheet which has been treated chemically to
produce the green patina which age normally gives to this metal. Above, the folded concrete
ceiling of the Plenary hall. This exposed structural ceiling and the end wall of the hall both offer
a number of acoustical advantages. Below, the corrugated roof seen from the Secretariat building.
von Westhern
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO
UNESCO - Marc Laloux
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
ULTRA-MODERN
MEETING PLACE
All conference and committee rooms
at Unesco's Headquarters are group¬
ed, together with their services, under
a single roof in a structure of singular
architectural character. This Conference
building, which is linked to the main hall
of the Secretariat building by a long, low
hall, has three levels.
On the lower level, there are the offices
of the Conference Secretariat, the press,
radio and television rooms, and three com¬
mittee rooms; on the main (ground) level,
the plenary hall, the main commission room
and the delegates' bar and snack bar; on the
upper level, the Executive Board room and
a committee room.
Photos on these pages show some as¬
pects of these conference halls and com¬
mittee rooms. Largest of all is the Plenary
Hall (left, lower photo) covering an area
of 1,000 square metres and accomodating
nearly 1,000 people. Its seating arrange¬
ments include 477 seats for delegates and
observers, 359 for the public and 42 for
the press. It is equipped for simultaneous
interpretation in four languages and for the
projection of films. Photo was taken at
the opening of Unesco's 10th General
Conference. On either side of the hall are
ebony-covered cabins for interpreters,
photographers, radio and TV representatives.
Next largest hall is the Main Commission
Room. Unlike the Plenary Hall which
relies entirely on concealed lighting for its
illumination, the Commission Room has
4,300 square feet of special double glass
set in an unusual pattern of windows (left,
upper photo). Above the entrance to the
room Rufino Tamayo has painted his "Pro¬
metheus bringing fire to Man", which is
flanked by decorative plaster panels.
Slatted walls, a hanging ceiling in acoustic
tiles and natural ash furniture are other
features.
Photos, right, show three of the commit¬
tee rooms which have been decorated and
furnished by Member States.
Top, in the German room, the remark¬
able white stucco "draped" ceiling which
was placed between the concrete beams to
give a wavy effect and an impression of
height and light. Grey marble table in this
room has 24 walnut working surfaces.
Floor is of darker Wallenfels marble.
Centre, Denmark's contribution. Room
has pinewood slatted ceiling, bright coir
oured wood and natural ash walls. Semi¬
circular oak and teak tables face long rec¬
tangular presidential table. Copper lamp
fixtures following the shape of the table are
suspended from the ceiling.
Bottom, room given by Switzerland.
Circular walnut table is overhung by circu¬
lar metal light fixture. Table can be taken
down and re-arranged, and its height
adjusted. Glass panels separate committee
room from foyer giving view of Picasso
mural. Windows look out on Secretariat
Photos UNESCO - Marc Laloux
The Unesco Courier. November 1958
mw^mf mmr^
' I w^ mm
WWWA
J0m^a iflfflP Kff is«
1 bI ft'i 5 U :m\ i*
^^
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
'PROMETHEUS BRINGING
FIRE TO MAN'
0ufinoTamaya, the Mexican painter, climbed
down from the scaffolding on which he
had been working for two months to
complete his mural, "Prometheus bringing
fire to Man." "All my friends were telling
me that I should decorate the new UNESCO
building," he said. "Here is my contribution,"
he added, presenting his great mural in which
all the colours of fire itself burned.
"I had successively been offered the chance to
make ceramics on a terrace, a painting along
a passage or in the restaurant. Finally, the
Main Commission room, which is the most
suitable for me as I prefer painting large
murals, seemed to me to be fit for a theme
dedicated to UNESCO. The work is done on
plaster; the paint itself has a plastic base.
It dries fast and can be washed. I have already
used this in previous murals and can obtain
exactly the same colours as I would with
normal paint.
"When I wasa child," said Tamayo, "I was more
inclined to be a musician than a painter. In
South Mexico, where my family lived, I learned
music. When I was eleven years old we went
to Mexico City and I discovered I had a gift
for drawing. But at home they wanted me
to study something practical and to become a
merchant. So I went to the School of Fine
Arts without telling my parents."
Photos show (top) Tamayo working in his stu¬
dio and (bottom) on his mural at UNESCO'S
headquarters. The note reproduced at the top
of the page was written by Tamayo specially
for this souvenirlssue of THE UNESCO COURI ER.
It says: May the light which is supposed to
come from the fire of my little-illuminated
"Prometheus" illumine the minds of all who
undertake the immense task of uniting the
world through culture. Friendly Greetings,
R. Tamayo.
26
Photos UNESCO - Pablo Volta
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1958
FW^Efí ith a laconic D'accord "Agreed" (see above), Pablo
LTAtJ Picasso indicated his willingness in November 1957 to
ÄA4I contribute to the decoration of Unesco's new headquarters.
His painting was executed on 40 wooden panels. Covering
an area of 860 square feet, it was placed on a 28 feet high wall
at the end of the delegates' lounge in the Conference building.
As soon as this enormous mural (35 feet by 30 feet) was shown to
the public it stimulated comments and discussions sometimes
lively ones. Hî.re is whit M. Gîarges Salles, Honorary Director
of French Museums, had to say about it in "The Unesco Chronicle"
"At the entrance to the main conference hall is a composition by
Picasso. What does this represent ? Bathers on a beach ? If one
wants a symbol one can see in it a struggle between the forces of
good and evil and what I have described as the fall of an Icarus-like
figure into the shadows."
Pablo Picasso, born in Malaga, Spain, in I 88 I, was already recognized
while in his teens as an "artistic phenomenon." After his "Blue
Period" and his "Rose Period" in the early years of this century,
he turned to an increasingly abstract cubism. From 1919 onwards
realist pictures alternated with more formalized works and great
nudes inspired by Greek sculpture of the antique period. Picasso
was hailed by the surrealists as the great forerunner of their move¬
ment, and in the middle thirties his work was pronouncedly surrea¬
list. After 1948 he took up all his old themes in still life, portrait
and landscape.
Photos show: above, the mural being mounted for its first public
showing in Vallauris, in April 1958; left, Picasso with his painting
Phuto Tony Saulnier © Paris-Match, reproduced by permission
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
GIFTS FROM
19 NATIONS
Something like a score of nations
has contributed to the furnishing
and decoration of Unesco's new
headquarters. Photos on this page
show three examples of these donations
which in their ensemble compose a
mosaic of current trends in decoration
and furnishing in various countries.
Top, the committee room furnished
and decorated by Italy. It features
olivewood walls and ceiling with rounded
angles and a floor of Vincenza marble.
Olivewood tables are arranged in an
oval. Black polished metal chairs are
upholstered in natural calf. Forty-
five Murano lampshades are incor¬
porated in the ceiling.
Centre, modern tapestries on end
wall and floor are striking features of
the committee room presented by France.
Tapestries were made at Aubusson
from designs prepared by Adam (grey,
black and white) and Singier (reds and
blues). Room has mahogany tables and
metal chairs covered with grey leather.
Bottom, the Executive Board Room,
a contribution of the United States,
whose decoration was carried out by
the International Council of the Museum
of Modern Art, New York. It has 42 white
plastic sculptured wall panels suspended
like heraldic emblems from enamelled
steel poles, against velvet walls. A
striking contrast to this is provided
by the bush - hammered concrete wall
(on right of photo). The elliptical tables
of ebonized walnut on black anodized
aluminium frames have white parch¬
ment tops. Eighty-two suspended
lights in concentric ellipses reflect
the lay-out of the furniture.
Three other committee rooms were
furnished and decorated by Denmark,
Switzerland and Germany (see page 25).
Other gifts from Member States in¬
clude : Non-governmental Organiza¬
tions' Room (Czechoslovakia) ; Press
Room (Netherlands) ; Library (Sweden) ;
Unesco Information Office (Canada) ;
Gift Shop (Norway) ; Hall furniture
on each floor tables in light wood
with special Finnish veneers and metal
legs arranged in groups with sofa and
two armchairs(Finland) ; Office of the
Chairman of the Executive Board (United
Kingdom) ; Office of the Director-Gene¬
ral furnished thanks to a donation
from Belgium.
80 tons of rocks,
and the assistance
gardeners to carry
out the design of the Japanese garden.
Morocco and Tunisia have donated
rugs. The Director-General has also
accepted on behalf of Unesco the offer
of a tapestry from Lebanon and the
gift of a painting and a marble plaque
by Afghanistan.
Japan supplied
60 tree saplings
of 3 specialized
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1958
PATTERNS
IN STONE
On the outside wall of the delegates' building at Unesco's Headquarters, a
space has been reserved for a mosaic to be executed by the French painter,
Jean Bazaine.
Bazaine says he has chosen a movement of water as its theme, as this fits in
with the long and narrow surface he has to decorate and with the Japanese
garden to which the mosaic will provide a background. He has decided not
to work directly on the wall (to facilitate any retouching work he may have
to do) but at a mosaicist's where he has found exactly the same lighting condi¬
tions as those on the site. He intends to use enamels and stones (according
to whether brilliant or dull effects are required) of quite small dimensions, and
also, by the use of inequalities in the size and arrangements of the stones,
to give an animation to the entire surface.
Born in 1904 in Paris, where he still lives, Jean Bazaine ¡s an Important figure
in contemporary French painting. He has frequently exhibited in Paris and
in 1948 he published Notes sur la peinture d'aujourd'hui. He has made
stained glass windows for the church of striking modern design at Assy In the
Haute Savoie, and in 1951 he executed a large frontal mosaic measuring 60 feet
by 12 (photo, below) for the church of Audincourt, also In Eastern France.
The mosaic Bazaine has planned for Unesco will be similar in style to his work
at Audincourt, but composed of much smaller elements.
© Paul Bony, Paris
FORMS IN
BRONZE
Rarely is the work and
personality of an artist
so connected with the aes¬
thetics of his times as is
the case with Jean Arp, who
was born in 1887 at Stras¬
bourg, France. Friendship
and association with the
early theoreticians and pioneers of modern art have
given him a place in every major artistic movement
since the first world war.
The work he has executed for Unesco is an abstract bronze
haut-relief which has been placed on the outer wall of
the library on the ground floor of the Secretariat
building. Photo, left shows in foreground an element
of Arp's haut-relief on which he worked in his studio
at Meudon near Paris.
Photos UNESCO - Pablo Volta
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
« SPIRALE
In a note (above) which he sent to Unesco's Press Officer, Alexander
Calder wrote: " I have decided to call the mobile simply 'Spirale'."
UNESCO - Berretty
GYRATIONS IN SPACE
Alexander Calder, whose blackened steel mobile
sculpture, "Spirale," stands in the piazza of Unesco's
new headquarters, has been creating mobiles since
1932. Born in Philadelphia, U.S.A. in 1898, he
studied to become an engineer, then took up painting'
and techniques for sculpture. During the I920's
he went to Paris where he. was associated with the
Surrealists, Dadaists and Cubists. His sculptures in
wire and metal were first exhibited in New York in
1928. Attracted soon to non-figurative art, he made
his first mobiles four years later. The mobile he has
made for Unesco (above) is the largest in Europe,
having a height of 32 feet and a span of 24 feet. The
base weighs nearly one and a half tons and the mobile
head 1,100 lbs. Right, Alexander Calder supervising
the erection of "Spirale." Its five carefully balanced
arms revolve in a clockwise spiral with the wind.
UNESCO
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1958
UNESCO - Marc Laloux
REPOSE IN STONE
Massive "Reclining Figure" shown above silhouetted
against the brightly-lit facade of the Unesco Secre¬
tariat building is the largest statue ever made by
British sculptor. Henry Moore. The statue itself weighs
39 tons, the table on which it rests 12 tons and the three
feet of the table about 4 tons eachover 60 tons for the
whole. That is why Henry Moore had to go to a mountain
in Italy to make it, instead of working in his studio in England.
The travertine block he worked from in Querceta at the foot
of the Carrara mountains on and off for nearly a year, weighed
sixty tons. When finished, the statue was transported to
Paris in four pieces. Moore (seen on left, with his finished
work) is pleased with the site allocated to the figure. "The
architects have placed it facing the right d i rectiontowards
the sun," he says. "The sun brings a piece of sculpture
to life." Speaking of the forms his art takes, Moore has
said: "Beauty, in the later Greek or Renaissance sense, is
not the aim of my sculpture. Between beauty of expression
and power of expression, there is a difference in function.
The first aims at pleasing the senses, the second has a spiritual
vitality... more moving and going deeper than the senses."
UNESCO - Sabine Weiss
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
GARDEN OF PEACE
Keystone
STRANGELY - SHAPED ROCKS, a brook, green hummocks, waterfalls, fruit trees and pineswith these elements Isamu
Noguchi has shaped a Japanese garden of distinctive character with a reverie-provoking landscape for the headquarters of Unesco.
The visitor to Unesco House who leaves the Conference
building and follows the long gallery leading to the dele¬
gates' patio enters a new hemisphere and emerges into
the Orient. Here ¡s a Japanese garden with its invitation to
meditation. This is the work of Isamu Noguchi, the American
sculptor and landscape gardener (born in Los Angeles of a Japa¬
nese father and an American mother).
Though designed in the traditional Japanese manner by
Noguchi, the garden is entirely modern in inspiration, and
bears the original stamp of the sculptor's own Ingenuity. Dwarf
trees and 80 tons of rocks, great and small (selected for
32
their sculptural beauty and shipped directly from Japan as
a gift from the Japanese government) a brook, a pond, a
bridge, green hummocks all these form a reverie- provoking
landscape.
From Japan too came three gardeners to help Noguchi in
laying out the garden. One of them brought with him trees
to decorate itmagnolia, cherry, plum, bamboowhich were
a gift from UNESCO well-wishers in Japan.
For .this souvenir Issue of The Unesco Courier, Isamu
Noguchi explains the ideas which have given such a distinctive
character to his garden :
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1958
© Paul Almasy, Paris
PEACE is engraved in Japanese on a giant rock weighing
eight tons from which water cascades into a series of falls.
My original commission was to design the upper patio. The lower
garden came about following my suggestion that this area would be
enhanced by the inclusion of greenery which could be gained by including
the adjoining sunken area as a part of a general plan. This is how the
roadway came into being as a means of achieving this interrelation
of great changes in level.
It serves the same purpose as the Japanese veranda (roka) for viewing
the garden. In theatrical terms, it is like the "flowery path" or
bridge of entry (hanamichi).
The lower garden is often referred to as the "Japanese garden".
In my estimation, it would be almost more correct to say that the
truly Japanese part is that which is least obviously so.
It is true that I have paid a more obvious homage to the Japanese
garden In the lower area. This follows the nature of the commission,
and because of the very generous gift of all the stones from Japan.
To learn but still to control, not to be overwhelmed by so strong a
tradition, ¡s a challenge. My effort was to find a way to link that ritual
of rocks which comes down to us through the Japanese from the dawn
of history to our modern times and needs. In Japan the worship of
stones changed into an appreciation of nature. The search for the
essence of sculpture seems to carry me to the same end.
This is an ambulatory garden, the enjoyment of which is enhanced
by walking In it whereby one perceives the relative value of all things.
The raised paved area in the centre of the lower garden recalls the
upper patio. One arrives on it and departs from it againwith time
barriers of stepping stones betweenit is the land of voyage, the place
for dancing and music which may be viewed from all around the garden
and from all levels of the surrounding buildings.
I have included two very old chosubachi or water basins In deference
to the quality of age (shibui) which is so much a part of the Japanese
garden. Everything else was both designed and executed by me.
The UNESCO garden does not attempt to reproduce the old or the
traditional, excepting In allusion and as a point of departure. A con¬
sideration of the tea ceremony resulted in one arrangement of seats
on the upper level.
Paul Almasy, Paris
DELEGATES' PATIO between the Conference and Secret¬
ariat buildings forms the upper level of the Japanese garden.
l/^ev V%%. *»/ AsC<r~VK «sAv
UNESCO - Berretty
TREE-PLANTING operations in the garden being super¬
vised by Isamu Noguchi (pointing, with his back to camera).
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
MY LATEST WORK
-A WALL
by Joan Miro
IN HIS STUDIO at Gallifa, Spain, José Llorens-
Artigas (on right) prepares one of the 585 tiles
used in making the two surrealist ceramics:
Wall of the Sun" and "Wall of the Moon".
All photos UNESCO-Català Roca
In 1955 Unesco asked me to take
part in the decoration of its new
headquarters buildings, then
under construction in the Place Font¬
enoy, Paris. Ttvo perpendicular walls
one 24J feet long, the other 50 feet
long near the Conference building
were put at my disposal. My idea
was to decorate them with ceramics,
in collaboration with Llorens-Artigas,
using the same sharp fire process
we had recently used to make over
200 works which were later exhibited
at the Maeght gallery in Paris.
Once my proposal had been adopt¬
ed, I began discussions with the ar¬
chitects. I wanted to work closely
with them so as to be quite sure that
my work would integrate as perfectly
as possible into the architectural
scheme. The art of mural decoration
has nothing in common with the
creation of works "in isolation"; while
retaining its individual characteris¬
tics, the work must also become an
intimate part of its surroundings.
So I went to the site to look for
ideas and it was there that my plan
was conceived and developed. I was
given a room near the architects'
office; I talked with the architects
and with the engineers and workmen;
I studied' models of the structures,
and I meditated before the concrete
walls, surrounded by piles of building
material and the hustle and bustle of
the operations, and from all these
things I drew inspiration.
The design and colouring for the
walls I was to decorate were suggested
by the shapes of the buildings
themselves, their spatial structure,
and the play of light. I sought to
incorporate my wprk in the whole by
making it provide a contrast with the
architecture.
Thus, as a reaction to the huge
concrete surfaces around the larger
wall came the idea of a large, vivid
red disc. Its counterpart on the
smaller wall would be a blue crescent
to accord with the more confined area
it was to occupy. I could see these
two shapes in powerful colours and
JOINT CREATORS of the two Unesco ceramics, Joan Miro (right) and Llorens-Artigas discuss
their work in front of a small-scale preliminary painting of the smaller work: "Wall of the Moon".
34
given still more force by incised work.
The chessboard compositions and the
forms of the human figures were
inspired by details of the building,
such as the design of the windows.
I aimed at a crude and forceful
expression in the large wall and at
something more poetic in the smaller
one. I also Wanted to provide an
element of contrast within each
composition itself, and for this reason
I conceived harsh, dynamic outlines
side by side with restful coloured
shapes, in flat-tinted or in check
design.
These first compositions were
considerably altered when I trans¬
ferred them to larger sketches.
Indeed, modifications were made at
every stage in the work, a good many
changes being needed both in form
and colour, in order to adapt my
work to a larger scale and to transfer
my ideas from the paper to the clay.
The second stage in the task was
to study with Artigas how my plan
in ceramics was to be carried out.
No ceramist had ever before been
faced with an undertaking of this
scope. Besides this, as both walls
were to be in the open air and un¬
protected, we had to keep in mind the
extent to which the materials used
would resist differences in tem¬
perature, humidity, and the sun's
rays. There is no doubt that Artigas
was the only person capable of solving
these extremely difficult problems.
Modern techniques concentrate on
the production of earthenware or
stoneware. The former would not
stand up well to the.Parisian climate,
and the latter is unsuited to my
palette. Artigas adopted a combined
process he used fire-clay covered
with a white slip, the whole being
fired at a temperature of 1,000 de¬
grees; after this the background
was laid on in coloured sandstone, a
different colour being used for each
square, and this was fired at a
temperature of 1,300 degrees. Next
came the firing to apply the decora-
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1958
tion, at a temperature of 1,000 de¬
grees, in enamel and colour. Wood
was used for the firing of the whole
work, since it gives effects that are
not obtainable with gas, charcoal or
electricity.
Thus, Llorens-Artigas sought, like
an alchemist of old, the type of earth,
the sandstone enamels and the
colours that he Would use. It was
true creative work, starting from
natural products feldspar from Pa-
lamos, clay from Alcaniz, sand from
Fontainebleau, and metal oxides,
copper, cobalt, uranium, etc., from
every sort of place. The amounts and
proportions in which they were used
are age-old secrets once lost, but
now rediscovered thanks to the know¬
ledge and intuition displayed by Arti¬
gas. Meanwhile, working with Joan
Artigas (the ceramist's son), I trans¬
ferred my plan to a fullsize .charcoal
sketch on paper and coloured it in
gouache. Now the preparatory stage
was ended and we were ready to
begin the actual work.
MIRO'S UNESCO MURALS
WIN INTERNATIONAL
PRIZE COMPETITION
Joan Miro has been named the 1958
winner of the S 10,000 Guggenheim
International Art Award for his two
ceramic wall designs at Unesco's new
headquarters. This awardprobably
the largest in the artswas established
by the Solomon R. Guggenheim Foun¬
dation in 1956, and is granted every
two years. This year I 14 artists from
twenty-two countries participated.
It was then that we suddenly decid¬
ed to visit Santillana del Mar to have
another look at the famous cave
paintings of Altamira and gain
inspiration from the world's earliest
mural art. While we were in the
"Collegiata," the old Romanesque
church at Santillana, we were deeply
moved by the extraordinary beauty of
the material used on an old wall,
rotten with damp. Artigas made
notes about it for the purpose of his
backgrounds.
Having made our journey to the
fountain-head, we thought we should
also go where we could feel the in¬
fluence of the Catalan Romanesque
artists and of Gaudi. The Barcelona
museum has wonderful Roman¬
esque frescoes, which have inspired
me since I first began to paint. I hope
their inspiration has not failed me
now; the rhythm of the larger wall in.
particular, I think, owes much to
them. Finally, we visited Gaudi's
work in the Guell park; and here I
was struck by the sight of an enor¬
mous disc set into the wall, revealing
the bare rock. It bore a strong re¬
semblance to the disc which I had
intended to carve and paint on the
larger wall in Paris, and this coincid¬
ence I took both as confirmation and
as encouragement of my purpose.
We went back to Gallifa, the old
village With its stone houses and its
greenery, where Artigas had set up
his kiln and his workshop. The
village is dominated by a great
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO Cátala Roca
BOLD SOLUTION chosen by painter Joan Miro in executing large forms and lines requiring single brush strokes was to
use a long-handled brush of palm fibres (above). A single mistake could easily have ruined months of preparatory work.
amphitheatre of rocks; these replac¬
ed, for me, the towering concrete
walls of the Unesco building, and I
considered my larger sketches in
relation to them. . It was vital for me
to be able to test the effect of the
sketches against the grandeur of this
background, and I made various
alterations as a result. The surface
of my plan Was divided into equal-
sized rectangles to correspond with
the slabs that now had to be modell¬
ed in earth,, dried and fired for the
first time, with simply a layer of
sandstone to strengthen this "biscuit"
or unglazed work. I then had to
apply . the sandstone enamel in
colour, for the second and last firing.
After Artigas had completed the
firing of 250 slabs in 33 batches he
told me that he was not confident of
success. He was not satisfied with
the basic material we were using and
he feared that the geometrical re¬
gularity of the tiles might harm the
feeling and "life" of the work. He
realized that it was his own technical
skill which had led him to go so far,
and that the backgrounds he had
produced, remarkable though they
were, were not what was needed.
36
Then he remembered the wall of
the Collegiata, and succeeded in
reproducing, in his tests, the
wonderful depth of feeling we had
found there. In much the same way,
the sight of the walls of the old
chapel at Gallifa, with their irregular
courses, was a revelation to us. We
saw that, in deciding how to divide
up the surface we were to cover, we
should think of the "throbbing"
irregularity of the stones at Gallifa.
We had to begin again, using slabs of
different sizes.
Now that we had discovered how
to arrange the slabs and the base, the
first firing gave no trouble whatever.
Now it was up to me to reproduce
my plan and to apply the enamel
colouring to the material spread out
on the ground. Here again, my
shapes were altered. As for the
colouring, I had to rely on Artigas'
knowledge for the enamel only
assumes its true colour after it has
been fired. No matter what pre¬
cautions are taken, the firing is the
decisive factor; its action is unpre¬
dictable, its decision final. This, I
think, is what gives this form of
artistic expression its value.
One more difficulty lay ahead the
large size of the surface I was to
paint. If some of the shapes and
lines were to retain their original
form and spontaneity, they would
have to be made with single brush
strokes. For this purpose I used a
long-handled brush made of palm
fibres. Artigas held his breath when
he saw me take the brush and paint
in shapes of five or six metres. One
mistake could have ruined the work
of several months.
The last firing was on May 29, 1958.
It was the thirty-fifth of the whole
series. We had used 25 tons of wood,
4 tons of earth, nearly a quarter of a
ton of enamel and 15 lbs of colouring
matter. We had only seen the pieces
that composed our work lying on the
ground there had been no opportuni¬
ty to see the whole from a distance.
We were therefore waiting anxiously
and impatiently, to see both walls
erected in the setting, and in the
light, for which they were designed.
Reproduced from "Derrière le Mi¬
roir," numbers 107, 108 and 109,
1958, by courtesy of the publisher,
C. Maeght.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1958
WHAT IS IT AND
WHAT DOES IT DO?
Unesco seeks "to contribute to peace and security by
promoting collaboration among the nations through
education, science and culture, in order to further
universal respect for justice, for the rule of law and
for the human rights and fundamental freedoms which
are affirmed for the peoples of the world, without
distinction of race, sex, language or religion, by the
Charter of the United Nations."
The Constitution of Unesco was drawn up in London by
representatives of 44 countries attending a conference
convened by France and the United Kingdom in
November 1945. The Organization came officially into
existence on November 4 1946. By November 1958, Unesco .
had 81 Member States. The Organization has three
principal organs:
The General Conference, consisting of delegates of
Member States, chooses the Executive Board, elects
the Director-General, passes the financial and staff
regulations, admits new Member States, determines the
policies of the Organization, decides upon the programme
for a two-year period and votes the corresponding budget,
to which all Member States contribute in proportion to
their population and their national income. The spending
level for Unesco's operations in the two-year period
1957-58 was set at $22,679,638.
More schools for Latin America
The Executive Board (24 members) meets at least
twice a year. It supervises .the execution of the pro¬
gramme and advises the Director-General on many
matters, including the preparation of proposed pro¬
grammes and budgets for consideration by the General
Conference.
The Secretariat, with. headquarters in Paris,. consists of
about 1,000 international civil servants recruited from
more than 50 Member States. It is headed by a Director-
General, Who holds . office íor six years and can be
re-elected for a second term.
The Secretariat is composed of several programme
departments and services: Education, Natural Sciences,
Social Sciences, Cultural Activities, Mass Communication,
and Exchange of Persons. In addition, there are
administrative bureaux such as: the Bureau of Member
States, the Legal Bureau, the Bureau of Programme and
Budget, the Documents 'and Publications Service, and the
Bureau of Conference Planning and General Services.
An innovation in the 1957-58 programme was the launch¬
ing of three major projects designed to concentrate the
resources of both Member States and the Secretariat on
work of major significance in the three fields of educa¬
tion, science and culture. They deal with the extension of
primary education in Latin America, scientific research
on arid lands, and the promotion of mutual appreciation
of Eastern and Western cultural values.
Forty-five per cent of all the adults in the world are
unable to read and write. Over 250 million children have
no schooling at all. Unesco is therefore concerned with
the teaching of illiterates, in addition to dealing with many
other problems of education, including those arising in
the most highly specialized fields. In every instance, the
aim remains the sameto improve education through
international action and to increase international under¬
standing through education. For the present, Unesco's
Department of Education is concentrating on two types
of work.
One is Fundamental Education, which is designed to
help uneducated people, often living in abject poverty, to
solve the problems of their immediate environment by
giving them the knowledge and skills necessary for good
use of their natural resources, for health, for home-
making, for literacy and for the development of their
community life, and so helping them to improve their
standard of living and to realize their potentialities more
fully as individuals and as members of society. Two
Unesco regional centres for training future fundamental
education leaders and producing teaching materials have
been established, one in Patzcuaro, Mexico, for Latin
America, and the other in Sirs-el-Layyan, Egypt, for the
Arab States. National fundamental education centres are
also in operation in Ethiopia, Cambodia, Indonesia,
Jordan, Korea, Liberia, the Sudan and Thailand.
The other main concept is free and compulsory educa¬
tion, which must eventually be accessible to all children
throughout the world, as stated in Article 26 of the
Universal Declaration of Human Rights. Unesco seeks to
make the experience of countries which have realized free
and compulsory education available to governments that
are now introducing it, or broadening its present scope,
so that decades of trial and error may be avoided.
The major project for the extension of primary educa¬
tion in Latin America, for example, aims at putting
every Latin American child into school within the next
10 years. At present about 17 million children in that
area do not attend school and it is estimated that some
400,000 more teachers would be required to teach then.i
if sufficient buildings Were available-
In both fundamental education and school educati'on,
the present need is for quick results in quantity more
school buildings and more teachers. But the question of
quality is quite as important. Hence Unesco's programme
includes work in the organization of school systems,
teacher training, curriculum reform and. the improvement
of textbooks.
Unesco's work in out-of-school education is concen¬
trated on youth groups and adult education activities.
Recognizing that study and travel abroad can be one of
the most effective means of transmitting knowledge and
skills between nations and of encouraging international
understanding, Unesco actively promotes the Exchange of
Persons, whether as students, professors, teachers, workers
or youth leaders.
Better living in the 'dry belt'
Since Unesco works more to encourage than to itself
finance such exchanges, it concentrates mainly on
collecting and distributing information about oppor¬
tunities for educational travel abroad. For this purpose
an annual handbook, Study Abroad, is published. But
Unesco does itself award a certain number of fellowships-
as a means of giving international training and experience
to persons who are helping to carry out its programme.
In 10 years, about 1,500 awards, have been made. Unesco
also administers fellowships awarded by governments and
other organizations, and gives active assistance to inter¬
national exchanges between particular groups.
Unesco promotes international co-operation by bring¬
ing scientists together, individually and through their
international organizations. It brings science to the
public by helping to improve science teaching in the
schools, by circulating information through articles in
specialized journals, and by organizing travelling exhibi¬
tions. It also helps to promote research for raising the
living standards of mankind.
For example, the major project in science seeks, through
co-ordinated research, to improve living conditions in 16
countries situated in the dry belt that runs from North
Africa, through the Middle East to South Asia. The aim
of the project is to develop and assemble all experience
and research in aridity problems. Spe¬
cialists are being trained; desert research
institutions strengthened or created; the
interchange of scientists facilitated through
fellowships. An international Advisory
Committee on Arid Zone Research set up
Cont'd
next page
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO (Continued)
by Unesco, will be at the centre of a network of natio¬
nal and local committees engaged not only on the
scientific aspect of the problem but also conducting a
broad education programme to inform the public on the
scope of the project which covers such subjects as water
prospecting, irrigation, use of dew, purification of saline
water, wind and solar energy, and adaptation of human,
animal and plant life to desert conditions.
Since economic development depends in large measure
upon science, Unesco has opened four science offices
whose activities cover large regions deficient in scientific
knowledge: in Uruguay for Latin America; in Egypt
for the Middle East; and in India and Indonesia for
South Asia. These offices encourage scientific research
work, assist in improving science teaching, help local
scientists to keep in touch with developments in other
parts of the world, and organize lecture tours, visits by
outside experts and refresher seminars in special fields of
scientific research.
Unesco is seeking to organize international co-opera¬
tion between relatively new branches of study, in which
there are not always enough specialists to deal with the
work waiting to be done. It is encouraging new studies
which must be pressed on rapidly if the problems of our
time are to be solved. If it is true that "all tensions can be
resolved by peaceful means," it is the role of the social
sciences the sciences concerned With people and their
relationships to each other as groups and individuals to
discover causes of tensions and the means of resolving
them. In the underdeveloped countries, new tensions are
liable to be created by industrialization and the shift of
population from rural areas. Unesco considers that, by
utilizing the expert knowledge and methods of social
science, governments can greatly ameliorate the conditions
.under which their peoples adjust themselves to the often
far-reaching changes brought about by current pro¬
grammes of economic development.
Unesco's role is to make available to governments all
the knowledge which has resulted from research on the
causes of these problems in human relationships, as well
as to report methods Which have been used to deal with
them successfully in various parts of the world. It supports
an International Research Office on this subject located
in Paris and a regional office which opened in Calcutta
in 1956.
Spotlight on the facts of race
Some 22 countries have asked Unesco for expert help
in social science teaching and several missions have
been dispatched in response to these requests.
The question of race prejudice has been studied in
detail by Unesco. As part of its programme to promote
human rights for all peoples, the United Nations re¬
quested Unesco to undertake a scientific investigation of
this question by bringing together experts in all the social
sciences concerned.
Such meetings in 1949 and again in 1951 led to a general
statement of scientific facts concerning race. The state¬
ment showed that from all the evidence available today,
there is no justification for the contention that one race
is inherently superior to another.
It is generally accepted that there is an urgent need for
greater understanding between peoples and it is agreed
that knowledge of, and respect for, the outstanding
features of various cultures can contribute greatly to better
understanding. Unesco's cultural programme, therefore,
seeks to spread this knowledge and respect through a
broader use of museum and library facilities; through
exhibitions, art reproductions and translations; through
promotion of the arts in school curricula, and through the
establishment of professional societies.
Within this general framework, the major project pro¬
moting the mutual appreciation of Eastern and Western
cultural values was started in 1957 as a vital effort to
increase understanding between these two vast regions.
Accelerated exchange of persons, ideas, information,
literature and art is to be emphasized in the first stages of
this programme.
In recent years Unesco has published catalogues of the
best available colour reproductions of the world's greatest
38
paintings, and albums of significant but little known art
in various Member States, such as medieval frescoes in
Yugoslavia and Norwegian Stave Churches. It has begun
a programme of translations from Arabic, Persian, the
Indian languages, Japanese, Chinese, Italian, Spanish and
Portuguese in order to make world masterpieces better
known in major languages. It has organized travelling
exhibitions of colour reproductions which are sent to
Member States on extensive tours of towns and villages.
It has introduced public library systems into South Asia
and Latin America, It has initiated the establishment of
10 professional societies in art, music, theatre, architecture
and philosophy.
Down with barriers to knowledge
To increase international protection of the rights of
those who produce the World's books as well as its
art and entertainment, Unesco sponsored the
Universal Copyright Convention. At the beginning of
1958 it had been ratified by 29 countries.
The press, films, radio and television can and should be
a principal means of producing an intelligent, informed
body of opinion. Since they are a powerful force in
creating understanding between peoples and nations, it is
vital that they should be put to their fullest use for the
advancement of education, science and culture.
Unesco seeks, therefore, through publications, seminars
and professional meetings to promote the interchange of
experience in these fields in order that techniques which
have proved successful in one country may be equally
applied in others.
Unesco's world-wide reports and surveys on com¬
munication facilities show the great inequalities existing
in large areas of the World. To help alleviate the
poverty in communication facilities, expert missions are
dispatched to advise on the expansion of the existing
facilities and the construction of new ones.
There are many obstacles to the free flow of information
between countries. Some of them can be removed by
international agreements, and Unesco is striving to secure
the adoption of such instruments as the Agreement for
facilitating the international circulation of visual and
auditory materials of an educational, scientific and
cultural character, which eliminates customs duties on
books, periodicals and newspapers. By January 1958, 26
countries had ratified this Agreement.
Again, the Unesco Coupon Schemes enable persons in
soft-currency areas to buy books, films and scientific
equipment from hard-currency countries, and help reduce
foreign exchange restrictions on educational travel.
Gift Coupons offer people all over the world a simple
means of taking a direct and active part in Unesco's
programme by making voluntary contributions for
equipping educational * establishments in countries in
special need of this type of help.
Unesco's broad public information task of telling as
many people as possible about the aims and activities of
the Organization and promoting human rights, better
international understanding and teaching about the work
of the United Nations in general, is carried out through
direct contacts With press, film, radio and television
organizations and through co-operation with Unesco
National Commissions and international and national
non-governmental organizations.
Unesco is annually allocated a share of the Special
United Nations Fund for Technical Assistance. In 1957,
this share was approximately $5 million. In 1957, 246
Unesco experts were on mission operating 122 technical
assistance projects in 53 countries. In addition, more
than $500,000 worth of equipment Was found for these
projects and more than 150 fellowships were provided.
To help Unesco carry out its world-wide programme,
which here can merely be outlined, most Member States
have set up National Commissions, which link the Secre¬
tariat with government departments as well as with
national groups. Unesco maintains constant contact
with the United Nations and the .other U.N. Specialized
Agencies and also co-operates closely. With some four
hundred international non-governmental organizations.
In short, Unesco is striving, in all countries, to co¬
ordinate the efforts of all people who are working offi¬
cially or voluntarily, for the progress of learning, culture
and research and are seeking to lay the foundations of a
peaceful, abundant future for the World.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
TWELVE WINDOWS OPEN ON THE WORLD
This issue of The Unesco Courier is an exceptional
one^a special souvenir number devoted entirely
to the story of Unesco's new headquarters. For
this reason it cannot convey to those who are making
the acquaintance of the magazine for the first time an ade¬
quate idea of its normal style and content. As Unesco's
monthly illustrated magazine it has followed a set goal :
to serve as a window open on the world, presenting in both
text and image informative and thought-provoking reports
on events and problems of world significance in the arts,
the sciences and education. On this page we reproduce
covers of issues which illustrate the broad range of subjects
dealt with during the past twelve months : John Comenius,
Apostle of Modern' Education ; Treasures of World Art
(a special colour issuej on Russian Icon Paintings, Mayan
Wall Paintings and Temple Paintings from Ceylon); Man
Against Nature; The Divorce of Science and Culture;
700 Million Illiterates in the World ¡World Health; Young
Artists in Paris; Masterworks of Japanese Stone Age
Art; The Art of Decorating Ourselves; Giant Dams : The
Pyramids of Today; Solar Energy Today & Tomorrow;
Science v. Old Age. A subcription to The Unesco Courier
is the best way of keeping in permanent touch with
Unesco and the goals for which it stands. Annual sub¬
scription (12 issues) only S3. 00; 10/- (stg.); 500 Fr. frs.
Orders are accepted by any bookseller or by Unesco's
National Distributors. In the U.S.A., write directly
to Unesco Publications Center, 801 Third Avenue, New
York, 22, N. Y. ; in the United Kingdom, write to
H. M. Stationery Office, P. O. Box 569, London, S.E.I.
Courier »Courier
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
RUFINO TAMAYO
"Prometheus bringing fire
to Man." Fresco in the
main commission room of
the Conference building.
UNESCO Jean-Pierre Grabet
ROBERTO MATTA
working on the painting
which decorates a wall on
the seventh floor of the
Unesco Secretariat building.
UNESCO - Pablo Volta
]]>
</page>
</document>
