<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="066970eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
ner
RARE
TREASURES
OF WORLD
ART
JANUARY
1957
(10th year)
Price : 2/- (U. K.)
50 cents (U. S.)
100 francs (France) .
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
ANGELS OF THE LAST JUDG¬
MENT. Detail from 13th century Span¬
ish Romanesque mural at St. Paul's
church, Casserres, northeast Spain, exe¬
cuted around 1200 A.D. by a painter
known as the Master of Llucá, whose re¬
markably fine decorative work inspired
many artists in this region of Spain. This
mural is now in the Archaeological Mu¬
seum of the Diocese, Solsona. (Unesco
Album: Spain)
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1957
JANUARY 1957 10th YEAR
CONTENTS
PAGE
3 EDITORIAL
4 MASACCIO THE FLORENTINE GENIUS
He flashed through life like a meteor
By Gabrielle Cabrini
12 FLORENCE: CRADLE OF THE RENAISSANCE
13 THE ART OF THE PILGRIMS' WAY
23 SPECIAL SUPPLEMENT
Eight pages of full colour plates of
masterpieces from Italy, Iran and Spain
3 I ISFAHAN IS HALF OF THE WORLD
36 THE TREASURES OF IRAN'S IMPERIAL LIBRARY
43 PERSEPOLIS: FABULOUS CAPITAL OF AN EMPIRE
46 MAGIC ARTISAN OF MILAN
49 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
50 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
The colour pages In this issue have been printed
In Milan, Italy, by Amilcare Pizzl, with the co¬
operation of the New York Graphic Society.
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, I 9 Avenue Kleber, Paris I 6, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Circulation Manager
Jean Groffier
(M.C 56.1.108 A)
COVER PHOTOS
One of world's finest collections of Persian miniatures, preserved in
the Gulistan Imperial Library, Teheran, was unknown to the public up to
25 years ago. Perhaps the most famous of them all is shown on front
cover in full colour. Done in I 480 it is one of the rare miniatures actually
signed by its author (Bihzad). It represents the garden of an art-loving
sultan, and is one side of a double page miniature in the Muraqqa Gulshan
or Flower Garden Album, a remarkable collection of miniatures and
calligraphy bound in a luxurious volume by the Moghul emperor Jahan-
gir in the I 7th century. Back cover also in colour is from same volume,
shows prince on horseback before a magnificently decorated pavilion.
Unless otherwise stated, all colour plates in this issue are taken from Unesco
Art Albums. All reproductions in these albums are copyright Unesco, 19 56.
Somewhere in Turkey today it may be in the fabulous
"green mosque" of Bursa, former capital of the
Ottoman Empire south of Istanbul, or in the Hittite
ruins of Central Anatolia a three-man expedition is en¬
gaged in a treasure hunt which has already taken it
100,000 miles across four continents during the past three
years. The three men are Peter Bellew, Unesco visual art
expert, Anton Schutz, director of the New York Graphic
Society, and Mario Dolfi, chief colour photographer of the
Italian printing firm of Amilcare Pizzi. Their mission:
to study and photograph little known or inaccessible na¬
tional art treasures for Unesco's World Art Series albums.
Large numbers of extraordinary works of art have been
reproduced in the past and made available in the form oí
albums. Superb reproductions in colour of the greatest
masterpieces continue to come off the presses of the
world's best art publishers. Nevertheless there are obvious
gaps. Unesco launched its World Art Series when it
took stock of the fact that it is the better known and more
accessible masterpieces which are most frequently re¬
produced by private publishers.
It is of course easier and less expensive to photograph
works in the Louvre, the Prado or the Vatican than it is
to scour the world in search of treasures buried in tombs,
in caves or under desert sands. The technical and finan¬
cial resources needed are usually beyond the reach of all
but a few private publishers or else the volumes are priced
so high that they are beyond the reach of the average
buyer.
As an international organization, Unesco has been able
to mobilize such resources with the aid of its member
states. Every expedition is carefully planned with
the collaboration of government officials and national
authorities who join up with the Unesco three-man team
in the field.
To collect their material, the Unesco team, though
weighed down with some 300 pounds of equipment, have
used rope ladders to reach caves dug into a cliff face,
inched their way to the summit of a steep mountain rock
in Ceylon, crawled into Egyptian tombs and driven a bul¬
lock team up the steep hills of old Serbia in Yugoslavia to
photograph little known paintings in colour. Eight vol¬
umes have now been published.
They include the mural paintings discovered in the
"Stave" churches of Norway, of which only 25 still exist;
the irescoes found in the caves of Ajanta, India, painted
by Buddhist monks centuries before the Christian era;
the medioeval frescoes recently discovered under several
layers of plaster in Yugoslav monasteries; paintings from
Egyptian tombs and temples; and bark paintings by
Australian aborigines (1).
This issue is devoted to the latest albums: Iran, Spain
and Masaccio (the last of these is not part of the World
Art Series). Forthcoming volumes will present the Icons
of Russia. Japanese Buddhist art, early Buddhist wall
paintings of Ceylon. The three-man Unesco expedition
is now preparing to visit Mexico, Peru, Burma and Greece
to collect material for other albums.
(1) See Unesco Courier, No. 11, 1954 (.U.S. Feb. 1955).
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
MASACCIO
Florentine genius who flashed
through life like a meteor
by
Gabrielle
C abri ni
SCHOOLROOM OF
THE RENAISSANCE.
For nearly a century after
1428, the Brancacci Chapel
in the Church of St. Maria
del Carmine, Florence, was
the schoolroom of Florentine
artists. Botticelli, Leonardo
da Vinci, Michelangelo, Ra¬
phael and other giants of
the Italian Renaissance went
there to study and to copy
the frescoes of the young
painter Masaccio. The cha¬
pel was decorated on the
order of the wealthy Floren¬
tine, Felice di Piuvichese
Brancacci. The frescoes were
damaged by the fire which
gutted the church in 1771
and by the treatment which
they subsequently received.
The history of art up to the 15th century records no
painter who achieved so much in so short a time as
the Florentine artist, Masaccio, who '"'flashed
through life like a meteor."
The masterpieces which revealed his genius and powers
to the world are the few frescoes he painted in 1427 and
1428 in the Brancacci Chapel of the Carmelite Church at
Florence works which place him as one of the
"fathers" of modern painting.
It was as if Masaccio had been destined for a brief
existence, 'for he only needed a few years to complete the
cycle of his passage in the history of art. But though
small in space and short in time his achievement was to
blaze like a beacon down the centuries.
In Masaccio's 27th year his life and the soaring flight
of his masterpieces were alike cut off by a death so
sudden that many of his Florentine contemporaries
believed he had been murdered by poisoning.
To his creative life of six short years he brought such
a thirst for research, so ardent a desire to excel all others,
that after his death and for more than a century later,
the "giants" of Italian painting came to study his work
minutely. They came to marvel at his innovations, to
analyse his discoveries and to learn from his composition
and colour. What chiefly attracted them was what
Masaccio strove most of all to accomplish: the painting
of human forms which stand out in relief against
background. One painter who lived long after him and
who, like so many others, sought in his work fresh
creative inspiration, has described them as "bodies
pulsating with life".
Masaccio, or Tommaso, as he was baptized, was the son
of a notary and was born at San Giovanni Valdarno,
about 30 miles 'from Florence, on December 21, 1401. At
that time, despite the civil wars which mark its entire
history, Florence was experiencing an extraordinary
flowering of talent in building and in the arts.
Travellers from elsewhere in Italy and from other lands
who passed through the country of Dante all wrote
accounts of what they had seen to their rulers and their
friends, describing the Florence of that time as one vast
workshop. On every side buildings were going up, or
being pulled down and rebuilt. The only thread erf con¬
tinuity in a political life forever interrupted by changes
of the parties in power and by their internecine feuds
was a passionate love of the arts.
So great was this affection that when Cont'd
decadence had already set in and freedom
was at an end in the 16th century, Giorgio
Vasari, the remarkable author of "Lives of
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1957
TWO CARMELITES. A detail from The Enthroned St. Peter venerated by the
Faithful. This fresco in the Brancacci Chapel, which also depicts St. Peter raising
the son of Theophilus, was left unfinished by Masaccio in 1428 when he departed
for Rome, where he died soon after. The work was completed in 1484 by Filippino
Lippi. This reproduction and those on pages six to ten are taken from the Unesco
Album, "Masaccio, Frescoes in Florence", which is to be published shortly.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
MASACCIO (Continued)
the greatest painters, sculptors and architects" concocted
for himself an entirely apocryphal grandfather who was
supposed to have been a great artist at Arezzo. He did
this simply to win the admiration and esteem of the
Florentines, for whom ambition was so closely linked with
artistic glory. Had Vasari lived elsewhere he would have
invented distinguished soldiers, or men of noble birth as
forebears.
The sun of artistic glory shone generously on Florence.
For centuries, Tuscany peopled the world of art from its
nursery of studios and workshops. But though the work
of creation went on, its masterpieces quickly failed to
satisfy; people felt that there had once been something
other than the so-called medieval art which had so far
held sway, and above all that there could yet be something
else awaiting discovery.
Masaccio grew up at this moment of crisis and search
child, being dissatisfied within art. It is said that as a
what surrounded him in
his own ' village, he wan¬
dered everywhere making
drawings, though he was
as displeased with his own
efforts as he was with what
was done by others. Like
all artists of his time,
Masaccio was still living in
the imposing shadow of
Giotto, born a century and
a half earlier. Yet he felt
that painting not only
could, but should be taken
further than Giotto had
carried it.
Young Tommaso was so
absorbed and carried away
by his problem that, at a
time and in a country
which prided itself on a
refined elegance, he was
completely blind to his own
appearance. He was obli¬
vious to everything, Giorgio
Vasari tells us, except to
drawing and mixing colours
which never satisfied him.
His carelessness and his
disregard for everything
not connected with art
were so great; to the end
o'f his life he lent money to
friends and never re¬
membered afterwards to
whom, and would only try
to remember when he
himself was without a
penny piece that his name
"Tommaso" was soon
changed to "Masaccio" (an
abbreviation of Tomasac-
cio), a rather disparaging
diminutive o'ften used for slipshod, muddle-headed and
good-for-nothing children and youths.
While Masaccio paid no attention to his immediate
surroundings, he did not lose sight of the contours of the
Tuscan countryside, and the villages which seemed blurred
in its luminosity," and he strove continuously to convey
this sense of distance, which no one had yet been able to
do before him.
Masaccio, in his short life, had the great good fortune
to meet and to become the intimate friend of two men,
very much older than himself, whose names were
synonymous with the artistic glory o'f their country. One
wasBrunelleschi, the architectural genius who sought to
create an impression of infinite space in a building of
modest proportions like his chapel of the Pazzi, which
has not a single rectangular line. The other was
Donatello, the sculptor who dreamed of making people
who looked at his statues afraid, less they emerge from
their niches and advance towards them.
Why, reasoned. Masaccio, should not this problem of
perspective, which Brunelleschi and Donatello had solved
in the case of architecture and sculpture, be overcome by
him in painting? Why should he not break up the flat
outline of surfaces by giving them the semblance of
relief? Suddenly the masterpiece took shape. After
producing a number of works in his research, Masaccio
WOMAN AND CHILD. Det
Goods of the Community which
Masaccio's portraits. For a larger
knew at last that he had found the solution to the
problem, that he would thenceforth be able to give depth,
a natural depth to something as mundane as a wall.
The opportunity (Florence was an inexhaustible mine of
opportunities) was offered him, as might be expected in
this great commercial city, by a wealthy merchant named
Brancacci, who, wishing his name to go down in history,
had chosen the most appropriate way of doing so at that
time through the arts. Having decided to offer his city
a work of art, he engaged the successful artist Masolino
to decorate a chapel o'f the Carmelite Church with
a number of frescoes.
Masolino undertook the work, a work full of charm, in
the most classical Florentine style in 1424-25. Later,
Masaccio took his place, and at last his teaching, his
conversations with the architect and sculptor of genius
bore their fruit: Masaccio painted living beings. His
Adam and Eve, driven out of the earthly paradise, have
the ravaged expression of
human beings unable to
face the life that awaits
them, and fills them with
horror; they are indeed
"bodies pulsating with life".
The scenes recounted in
the Gospel or in the Acts
of the Apostles, those first
accounts of the life of
Christ and his disciples that
Masaccio depicts with his
brush, are scenes of real
life and no longer mere
conventions. Masaccio
adds a sense of reality to a
dramatic genius like that
of Giotto, depicting men
who fit naturally into their
proper walks of life, who
are truly made for the roles
which destiny has reserved
for them.
The apostle Peter is a
fisherman tanned by the
sun, broad shouldered, who
knows how to draw up nets
and launch his boat into
the sea. The sick and the
beggars are wretched speci¬
mens of humanity, craven
and downtrodden. Christ is
not God triumphant; he
has the dignity and sadness
of one who will be betrayed
and cannot forget it.
Around them, behind them,
in that chiaroscuro which
was to be the admiration
of future generations, the
trees, the houses fade away,
lose themselves in the dis¬
tance, as, for example, in
the case of the extraordinary castle wrapped in the mist,
in "St. Peter distributing the Goods of the Community",
which might have been painted by an Impressionist.
Masaccio died leaving his work unfinished, but his
renown was such that many painters, including those who
were to become the most famous, while not knowing for
generations how to follow the path he had so barely
outlined, came to meditate in front of his work, trying to
decipher its message. Today, as we contemplate Ma¬
saccio's work, we may well ask ourselves, as did Vasari, to
what heights would he not have attained had not death
cut short his career?
2¡l from St. Peter distributing the
illustrates the realistic humanism of
detail of the same fresco see page 29.
LIFESPAN OF THE «GIANTS'
Masaccio, who died in his 27th. year, had the shortest life of
any of the "giants" of the Italian Renaissance. Here are the
ages to which other great Italian painters of this time lived.
Caravaggio
Raphaël
Correggio
Ghirlandaio
Veronese
Botticelli
37 Leonardo da Vinci 67
37 Fra Angélico 68
40 Tintoretto 76
45 Donatello 80
60 Michelangelo 89
66 Titian 99
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1957
HIGHPOINT IN ART was reached by Masaccio in The Tribute Money whose majestic central group is reproduced above. The apostles in a
compact group around Christ have an epic grandeur in them, and the whole, a three-dimensional quality. The scene, in three episodes, tells the
story of Christ being asked for the toll to enter the city of Capernaum. St. Peter appears three times in the fresco: (I) In the central group at
right hand of Christ when he is told to find a piece of money in the first fish he will draw from the lake (2) catching a fish in which he finds a
coin with which to pay the toll (below, right) and (3) paying the tax collector (below, left). For a detail of St. Peter's head, see page 28.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
MASACCIO (Continued)
ST. PETER
CURING
THE SICK
FLORENTINE STREET SCENE was painted by Masaccio
as setting for St. Peter curing the Sick by his Shadow (left). As
the Brancacci Chapel was dedicated to St. Peter, subjects prescrib¬
ed for its decoration were drawn from the "Acts of the Apostles"
and "The Golden Legend" (a 13th century collection of bio¬
graphies of saints). Masaccio drew his scenes from real
life and painted living beings. Details from the same fresco
show (above) a sick man and (opposite page) two heads.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1957
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
MASACCIO (Continued)
Copyright UNESCO
CASTLE IN THE MIST, detail from Masaccio's St. Peter distributing the Goods of the Commu¬
nity, (see page 29) might almost have been painted by one of the Impressionists. Through his
treatment of light and shade, Masaccio's trees and houses fade away, losing themselves in the
distance. His street scenes were often inspired by the palaces and houses of Florence such
as those on the XlVth century Ponte Vecchio (Old Bridge) over River Arno (right). Camera study
of light and shadow recalls Masaccio's art in which one form blends insensibly into another.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1957
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
'ARCHWAY TO ART' One of the richest palaces of art in Florence, a city
phenomenally wealthy in artistic collections, is the 16th century Uffizi Palace
(on either side of archway), housing the Uffizi Art Gallery, the National Library
and the State Archives. Its collection includes about 4,000 paintings. Build¬
ing in background with tall tower is early 14th century Palazzo Vecchio.
ROOFTOP VIEW of Florence with the Gothic church of Santa
Croce outlined against the shadow of the Tuscan hills. Begun
in 1294, this church was completed in 1442, with the exception
of the façade which was executed in the 19th century. Its decora¬
tions include many frescoes by Giotto and by his successors.
'GATES OF PARADISE'. Magnificent bronze doors of the Baptistry,
facing Cathedral in Florence, were designed and created by Lorenzo Ghiberti.
They took 27 years (I425-S2) to complete. The ten scenes from the Old
Testament were depicted so exquisitely that no less a sculptor than
Michelangelo described these doors as worthy to be the Gates of Paradise.
12
CRADLE OF THE
RENAISSANCE
From the beauty of the city of Florence and its neighbouring
hills comes its name in Italian, Firenze, meaning "the flower¬
ing", and in the history of Florence the most prolific period of
this flowering was during the XlVth and the XVth centuries
when it became a centre of art and culture. Gifted architects,
painters, sculptors and metal craftsmen joined to embellish Flor¬
ence with magnificent buildings and works of art, and the beauty,
zest and daring of Florence and its people combined to make it the
cradle of the Renaissance. Here Dante wrote his exquisite poetry
and from here too came Petrarch's sonnets and the brilliant poli¬
tical writings of Machiavelli. But above all it was a capital of art.
Michelangelo created his immortal paintings and statues here.
Leonardo da Vinci learned to paint in Florence, where
Donatello, the sculptor, Raphael and Luca delta Robbia were stu¬
dents. As their priceless works gathered through the centuries,
Florence became one of the great treasure houses of the world.
Art galleries, like the Uffizi and the Pitti, and churches and pala¬
ces are filled with masterpieces by Raphael, Botticelli, Masaccio,
Uccello, the Lippi, Ghirlandaio, Perugino, Andrea del Sarto,
Titian and many other Florentine, Umbrian, and Venetian artists.
Treasures of sculpture, ivory, enamel and bronze ware, medieval
and Renaissance antiquities, drawings, engravings and ancient
books fill its museums and libraries. And the entire city with its
churches, great stone palaces and halls is a fitting setting for this
wealth ofart and culture so carefully preserved down the centuries.
Photos copyright Almasy
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1957
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Wçph the approach of the year one thousand, a great
fear gripped Christian Europe. Though not offi¬
cially endorsed by the Church, the belief was
widespread that the Millenium and Judgment Day were
at hand, and that the world was coming to an end. A
wave of' religious fervour and mysticism swept Chris¬
tendom. Pilgrims, who in normal times flocked to the
holy places, found their ranks swollen by thousands of
new followers and new faithful.
But with the passing of the year 1000 the religious
fervour sparked by the '"Great Fear" not only did not
subside but was greatly increased. As never before,
"monks, pilgrims, soldiers and merchants" set out for
one of the great centres of pilgrimage in the far north¬
west corner of Spain where the tomb of the Apostle St
James had been found about the year 800, and which,
as an attraction for pilgrims, was soon second only to
Rome and Jerusalem.
A legend had sprung up that St. James had become the
champion of the Christian kingdoms of northern Spain
which were battling the Moors in an effort to regain the
rest of the country still in Muslim hands. It was re¬
counted that St. James had appeared mounted on a
white horse fighting against the Moors.
To visit the saint's tomb pilgrims from every part of
Europe headed for the Pyrenees in their thousands, using
the stars of the Milky Way to guide them. Both the land
route and the Milky Way. itself became known as the
"Road of St. James" and the centre of pilgrimage was
named Compostela, in Latin, Campus Stellae "the place
marked by the stars" (Today, Santiago de Compostela).
Pilgrims passing through France, where the chief halt¬
ing places were Paris and Vezelay, entered Spain through
Navarre, the central Pyrenees and, in the east, along the
14
Catalan coast. Monasteries with hostels for travellers
and places of worship were built along the route.
Thus the Christians of northern Spain were brought
more than ever before into contact with their neighbours
north of the Pyrenees, who brought with them fresh
customs and ideas, images and manuscripts and a new
form of art then developing in Europe Romanesque art,
later to develop its own distinctive style in Spain.
There still exists an idea, though it is becoming more
and more outmoded, that the Middle Ages represented no
more than a dark interregnum between the Graeco-
Roman age and the "Renaissance" (a term which itself
supports this idea). Romanesque art, born of the new
spirit of Christian enthusiasm, clearly refutes this belief.
The spirit which fed this art was fostered by the mon¬
asteries which grew up all over Western Europe after
St. Benedict founded the Benedictine Order of monks in
526 A. D. With their communities planted in different
countries, the monastic orders were probably the first
international institutions. They were churches, schools,
libraries and hospitals all in one, and the sculpture and
architecture which they helped to develop were embodied
in their abbey churches.
The young and vigorous Romanesque art found expres¬
sion in many fields. The new forms it developed in
architecture were those which finally gave birth to the
Gothic style. Its sculpture was largely architectural in
nature, and its painting and mural decorations, though
at first owing much to Byzantine influence, later developed
along other lines.
Though having a basic unity of style, Romanesque art
developed individual characteristics in different localities
according to the tastes of the craftsmen and the tradi¬
tions they followed. The most important influence was
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1957
CATALONIA'S ANONYMOUS MASTER PAINTERS
still Roman art, closely followed by Byzantine. Another
element came directly from the Near East through textiles
whose ornamental forms were copied in stone carvings
and on manuscripts. Northern influences Lombard,
Goth, Teuton and Celt were also in evidence.
In Spain, where the Romanesque art penetrated later
than elsewhere, the presence of the Moors and the in¬
fluence of the Orient stamped the new style with Hispanic
features of its own. Soon, Hispano-Romanesque archi¬
tecture flourished in Castile, Leon, Navarre, Asturias,
Galicia and Aragon, though the style imported from
France was modified by climatic conditions.
The proximity of the Moors and the exuberance of their
ornament inspired the carvers to a richer expression.
The capitals and cloisters of the great churches and
cathedrals like those of Santo Domingo de Silos, San
Isidoro at Leon and the "Old Cathedral" at Salamanca
are notable examples of this fusion of two arts. Side
by side with capitals on which biblical scenes are carved
THE VIRGIN AND ST. JOHN. Two 13th century painted statuettes in wood. Though they
are of the same period, there is a striking contrast between the primitive style of the St. Jcr n and
the masterly execution of the Virgin which suggests the style of sculpture of much kter centuries.
with striking realism are others with figures of Oriental
character, Persian motifs or Egyptian ibises. These
buildings and carvings are often the handiwork of Chris¬
tian and Moorish artists working side by side. Thus was
Romanesque architecture and sculpture enriched and
advanced in Spain.
At the same time Catalan painters were making an
important and until recently little known chapter in the
history of medioeval European art. In their cnurches,
chiefly in tiny villages in the Pyrenees, they painted
striking murals in the naves and apses. At first they drew
inspiration from the form and colour of Byzantine
mosaics and from the northern styles, coming from Poi¬
tiers and Toulouse, through the pilgrim routes to Com¬
postela.
Then more and more prolific local adapters changed
the styles and went on to complete church decorations by
painting altarpieces. Under their skill and invention the
painting ceased to be a mere decorative addition to
architecture and sculpture and be¬
came an independent art with its
own rules and standards.
On most of these paintings the per¬
sonality of the artists, or the indivi¬
dual stamps of the schools, have left
their distinctive marks, making it
possible to fix the origins of the works
and the identity of those artists who,
in their local adaptations, worked
with particular techniques and styles.
Their names unfortunately have not
come down to us, but they are iden¬
tified by the places in which they
worked: The Master of Pedret, the
Master of Lluca, the Master of Espi-
nelves, the Master of Soriguerola, to
mention a few o'f the most famous.
All their works were painted between
the 11th and 13th centuries.
For long years these Romanesque
masterpieces were hidden from
the world in the churches and
monasteries of Catalonia and it is
only since the beginning of this cen¬
tury that study and expert assessment
have revealed the full riches of a
school of painting that was almost
entirely unknown to most people.
The Board of Museums of Bar¬
celona which had previously had
reproductions made of the Catalan
murals, decided after the First World
War to remove the original works
from their walls in many cases so as
to save them from the progressive and
Irreparable damage they would
certainly have suffered (they were
usually done in distemper, and are not
true frescoes in the Italian manner).
The region of Catalonia, especially
the museums of Barcelona and Vich,
boasts the richest concentration of
Spanish Romanesque art, and the
collections of altarpieces are probably
the finest anywhere in the world.
The grouping of these works in
museums has aided their study in
recent years and this has been useful
^not only from a local or regional
point of view, but has also extended
the horizon of our knowledge of
medioeval European painting in gene¬
ral. The reproduction of some of
them in the Unesco World Art Series
now brings an idea of their distinctive
style and beauty within the reach of
people in all countries.
15
MAS Archives, Barcelona
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
THE DESCENT FROM THE CROSS. The 12th century marks
the high point in the development of Romanesque art, particularly
Spanish Romanesque sculpture. The remarkable examples on these
pages show, above, a Descent from the Cross, in wood, now at the
Episcopal Museum at Vich (detail of which is seen top right) and an
ivory figure of Christ from the Museum of San Marcos at Leon. The
similarity of technique used by Spanish Romanesque artists in working
16
ivory and wood is here particularly striking. The Descent from
the Cross is generally considered one of the greatest examples of
Romanesque carvings existing today. Its powerful message Is obtained
with a purity and simplicity only possible from the hand of a
master artist craftsman. The Episcopal Museum of Vich is probably
the richest museum in Spain from the point of view of Romanesque
carvings and its collection of polychrome wooden virgins is unique.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1957
Photos MAS Archives, Barcelona
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
v #r *
\m )&.
vT1
iimWi
m
' * * * * * % f * *
./' : ;V..-
< 5l
3
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1957
THE HOLY SUPPER. Detail from a I 3th century painted
frontal dedicated to St. Michael, by an artist
now referred to as the Master of Soriguerola (the name of
a Catalan village which is close to the French frontier).
2 THE DOUBLE AXE, an international motif of medieval
times, figures in this detail of a decorative frieze of 12th
century murals from El Burgal, Catalonia. The work has
been attributed to the school of the Master of Pedret.
3 ST JULIET'S MARTYRDOM depicted by an unknown
» I Ith century artist. Detail from frontal panel of St.
Quirico and St. Juliet in church of Durro, northwest of Bar¬
celona. The colouring is very bright with black outlines.
4 HOLY APOSTLE, detail from a 12th century mural in
. the church of Ginnestarre de Cardos, on the Franco-
Spanish frontier. This painting and those described above
are now in the Art Museum of Catalonia, at Barcelona.
5 MARTYRDOM OF ST. MARGARET. An episode from a
. twelfth century painting on a wood panel on the frontal
dedicated to the Saint in church of Sescorts, Catalonia. This
work is now preserved in the Episcopal Museum at Vich.
Unesco Album, "Spain: Romanesque Paintings"
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
CARVED IN EBONY, the "Black Virgin"
of Montserrat, near Barcelona (left), is one of
the finest existing examples of Catalonian
Romanesque sculpture. Many legends have
grown up around the extraordinary site of
Montserrat which is said to have inspired
Wagner to write his opera "Parsifal." Newly-
married couples in Catalonia traditionally
go there on a pilgrimage to seek the Virgin's
blessing, and have a saying: "Those who have
not been to Montserrat are not properly
married." Of the same period as the "Black
Virgin" (12th century), but with an entirely
different expression, is the painted wooden
Virgin (below, left) in the Barcelona Museum).
&
i*!*"
MOUNTED WARRIORS with flying banners
in this detail of a 13th century fresco are
believed to represent the armies raised by
the Kings of Aragon and the Counts of Bar¬
celona to fight against the Moors in Spain.
Formerly in the Royal Palace in Barcelona,
this fresco was saved when the palace was
destroyed by a fire in the 19th century.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1957
THE CREATION OF ADAM and the temptation of Eve depicted by a Spanish medieval painter
known todayas the MasterofMaderuelos. Originally in Segovia, now in the Prado Museum, Madrid.
MAS Archives, Barcelona
CATALAN AND LOMBARD decorative elements are mingled in the sculpture of the main
doorway to the Monastery of St. Mary at Ripoll, in the Province of Gerona. Ripoll, principal
cultural centre of Catalonia in the I Ith century, has some remarkable examples of Roma¬
nesque painting, sculpture and architecture. A distinctive school of painting flourished here.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
PERCHED ON A MOUNTAIN TOP, the I Ith century Abbey of Silos near Burgos (north-
central Spain) is one of the most famous sites of Romanesque history. On the ancient Pilgrims'
Road leading to Santiago de Compostela, it became celebrated throughout Europe during the
I Ith century under the rule of St. Domingo. It is today one of the rare places in the world where
the Gregorian chant can still be heard in all its purity. Architecturally, its cloister is considered
a wonder of Romanesque art, the result cf Spanish, Moorish and French artists. Above, left,
the capital of a column adorned with ibises. Right, two griffins in the old cathedral of Salamanca.
MAS Archives, Barcelona
Candido Ansede, Salamanca and MAS archives, Barcelona
THE 'OLD CATHEDRAL' at Salamanca is a marvel of Romanesque architecture whose con¬
struction occupied mostofthe 12th century. Above, interior and exterior views of its famous
"Cock Tower" crowned with an octagonal dome one of the finest of its kind in Spain. Masses
according to the ancient Mozarabic rite once practiced by Spanish Christians living in territories
occupied by the Moors, are still celebrated several times a year in one of the Cathedral's chapels.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
CATALONIAN ARTISTS working toward the end of the 12th
century produced many masterpieces, hidden until recently in little-
visited churches of the region. The names of few of these painters
have come down to us. The author of this St. John the Evangelist
and the Virgin is simply known as The Master of Valltarga, from
the frontal dedicated to St. Andrew which he painted in the church
of Valltarga, northeast Spain.
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
r^ir^n ^^ P^ ^^h
1 %- * i jB^
,. »
..
^ * ^i'»pp"
^^" ^^
»Or ^5
won
0^G3L2/A '^r^ '"
Bk ^w^t?C
<<al p^^^HilyP^^è^^*^ Iä^SR
1 1 ^fl KJMMJ^^^Ê^k.
^bbb ^** ^^ril /j ^^Y^ín ==^,<^^y «p u
f/
7
N^B
KING MELCHIOR. Detail (opposite page) of a 12th century
mural from the church of St. Maria de Aneu, northeastern
Spain, depicting adoration of The Infant Christ by the three
Wise Men. This work, now in the Art Museum of Barcelona,
is attributed to the School of The Master of Pedret, a painter
whose style inspired many medieval artists of the region.
ST. MICHAEL WEIGHING THE SOULS. This painting,
a 13th century altar piece from a church in the Ribas Valley,
100 miles north of Barcelona, is by an artist known as The
Master of Soriguerola, one of the most prolific of medieval
Romanesque painters in northeastern Spain. Painting is now
in the Episcopal Museum at Vich, Catalonia.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
MASACCIO, considered the most representative Florentine artist
of the first half of the 15th century, painted his foremost masterpieces
in the Brancaccl Chapel, Florence. Here are details from Adam and
Eve driven out of Paradise (left), and (above) from St. Peter raising the
Son of Theophilus.
ST. PETER and his apostolate was depicted by Masaccio in several
of the Brancacci Chapel murals. Examples of two works are reproduced
on the two following pages. Left, Head of St. Peter, detail from the
Tribute Money. Right, detail of St. Peter distributing the Goods of
the Community to the Faithful.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
'J' M
>~
.''.*""
-'. (JA^'^
; a.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
I
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
LION, FOX AND ASS, are three
characters from "Kalila and Dimna",
a Persian rendering of Indian fables
translated from the Sanscrit. The manu¬
script containing 35 miniatures was
completed in approximately 1410.
IN A PERSIAN GARDEN.
When Isfahan became the ca¬
pital of Persia in the 16th
century, the country's artistic
forces were concentrated there
under Shah Abbas the Great.
Paintings here are 17th cen¬
tury murals in the Chihil Su-
tun Palace. They are not in¬
cluded in the Unesco Album on
Iran but are taken from a
Unesco Travelling Exhibition
of Persian Miniatures, now
on tour throughout the world.
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1957
UNESCO-Marc Riboud
SHAFTS OF SUNLIGHT PIERCE THE GLOOM OF THE COVERED BAZAAR IN THE ANCIENT IRANIAN CITY OF ISFAHAN.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1957
ISFAHAN
IS HALF OF
THE WORLD
The 16th century was a wonderful
epoch alike in Europe and Asia. It
was an epoch of great rulers like
Charles V, Elizabeth of England, Suleiman
the Great of Turkey and the Great Moghul
Akbar a remarkable group in which an
Iranian monarch, Shah Abbas I, can fit¬
tingly take his place. Shah Abbas came
to the throne in 1587. Sir Anthony Sher-
ley, an English soldier of fortune in his
service, wrote of him: "His furniture of
mind infinitely royal, wise, valiant, liberal,
temperate, merciful, and an exceeding lover
of Justice..." In 1598 he made his capital
at Isfahan where, on almost the only river
on a plateau over 5,300 feet above sea level,
a superb city grew up, approached by sta¬
tely bridges which led past the luxurious
gardens of courtiers to the Royal Square,
the Maidan-i-Shah. Favoured with royal
concern, Isfahan soon hummed with acti¬
vity in the arts and crafts and the new
Imperial City was filled with the splendid
monuments which still exist in good condi¬
tion today. Early in the 17th century it
had a population of over 600,000 whence
the Iranian saying Isfahan nisf-i-jahan
(Isfahan is half the world). Enclosed
within mud brick walls the city had 162
mosques, 48 religious colleges, 1,802 cara¬
vanserais and 273 public baths. Isfahan's
epoch of splendour lasted nearly a century
and a half until it was partially destroyed
when Iran was invaded in the 18th century.
In 1788 the capital was moved to Teheran.
**&W&
-"*. '
UNESCO - Marc Riboud
HALL OF FORTY COLUMNS, or Chehel Sutun
(left and opposite page) is so named for its 20 real
columns and their 20 reflections in the lake fronting it.
Famous as the throne room of Shah Abbas in Isfahan,
it is one of the courts and pavilions with which he
filled the gardens of his palace in the early 17th
century. Shah Abbas, who made Isfahan one of the
architectural wonders of the world, built several
magnificent palaces, planted gardens and avenues, and
distributed amongst them the waters of the Zendeh-
rud, on whose bank the city is built, in an endless series
of reservoirs, fountains and cascades. Above, the
magnificently decorated dome of the Madrasseh
Chahar-Bagh, one of the religious colleges of which
there were once over 50 in the city. Enamelled
tiles like those on archway make geometric and
floral patterns on city walls, domes and minarets.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
ISFAHAN (Continuée.)
INTERLACED DESIGNS in Intricate
patterns sculptured in plaster decorate
this prayer niche or mehrab at the Djuma
Mosque, the oldest of Isfahan's mosques.
BHbbbbb
UNESCO-Marc Riboud.
VEILED SILHOUETTES of women in black
robes are a familiar sight in Isfahan. Those above
are In the courtyard of the Masjld-Shah or
Royal Mosque, which Is completely covered with
enamelled bricks of great brilliancy. Built by
Shah Abbas I and completed in 1612, it is still
one of the most beautiful buildings In the world.
Left, one of the particular features of the landscape
around Isfahan and elsewhere In Iran are the
constructions used to collect rain water. Water
drains through the ground Into the domes and is
cooled by air which enters shafts In the chimneys
from whatever direction the wind may blow.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1957
UNESCO-Marc Riboud
HEART OF ISFAHAN and central point of interest in the city is the Maldan-I-Shah, the great Imperial Square (below), an immense and imposing
space 560 yards long by 174 yards wide, bordered by buildings of recessed arches or arcades. On the far side of square is the Royal Mosque; at
right, the ancient Mongol palace rebuilt by Shah Abbas. Viewed from the air, Isfahan presents an immense expanse of mingled buildings and gardens.
Above, graceful tiled arches of Isfahan's Royal Mosque reflect their colours In the clear waters of the basin where the faithful perform their ablutions.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Ib^Ï**^'
THE TREASURES OF IRAN'S
IMPERIAL LIBRARY
«*#¿
IF
Geographically Persia was situated in the centre of
the ancient world. Historically, a distinctly Persian
civilization goes back as much as twenty five cen¬
turies when the great Persian Empire stretched westward
to the Danube and south to the Nile Valley. Culturally, it
is one of the few countries which can still claim a contin¬
uous tradition in literature, art and philosophy going far
back into the pre-Christian world.
It is almost as a direct outcome of Persia's geographical
situation that one of the chief characteristics of Persian
art was its extraordinary power of assimilating foreign
influences such as Greek, Egyptian, Islamic and Chinese,
and of combining them with others to create an original
and homogeneous style. This is especially true in
painting.
In the long history of Persia (the Iran of today) paint¬
ing developed at a comparatively late stage. Art under
the Achaemenid kings enhanced and adorned the public
life of the court from the 6th to the 4th centuries B.C.
The twin capitals of Susa and Persepolis were unmis-
takeably royal, with their friezes of attendants, guards
and tribute bearers sharply cut in stone, or brightly
coloured in the equally clear and hard tiled facings. This
was the art proper to an open-air court ceremonial.
The period of Hellenistic dominion, after the conquest
of the Persian Empire by Alexander the Great, saw the
introduction of a less priestly, more human art, followed
by a return to national ideals and a deliberate revival of
the monumental rock carving of earlier Achaemenid
times. Only when a site was unsuitable for carving was
there recourse to painting as a substitute.
Then, in 639 A.D. came the invasion of Islam, changing
the Persian mood and spirit. Islam had always had a
great respect for calligraphy, since it was a way of
preserving the inspired words of the Prophet. Such was
the prestige of calligraphy, that when painting was asso¬
ciated with it, it was only, so to speak, as a subordinate.
Followers of Islam considered the countries which
they conquered and ruled idolatrous, with their
temples and their gods almost always represented in
human form and therefore in conflict with the Semitic
sentiment expressed in the Book of Exodus: "...Thou shalt
not make unto thee any graven image, or any likeness of
anything that is in heaven above, or that is in the earth
beneath, or that is in the water under the earth."
Well before the rise of Islam, however, the Persians had
enjoyed depicting heroic scenes and pastimes of the nobles
such as hunting and feasting. The new Islamic rulers,
the Caliphs, revived the tradition, but for this work, which
Islam regarded as unorthodox, they employed foreign
artists. Such of these paintings as are known to us often
represent huntsmen on horseback pursuing wild animals,
36
or the king on his throne surrounded by courtiers, guards
and musicians. The decoration of religious works in this
way was forbidden, but nothing prevented rulers and
other dignitaries from employing painters to illustrate the
great works of Firdausi, Nizami, Jami and other authors.
The Mongols, who invaded Persia at the beginning of
the 13th century, paid no heed to the prohibitions of
Islam though they became Mohammedans later.
Worshippers of the Heavens and the infinity of Space,
they brought in their train painters and decorative artists
from China, and the Far Eastern influence became the
dominant one.
The earliest illuminated Iranian manuscripts which
survive are from this time. The Chinese influence
radically affected the whole conception. For the
moment colour almost disappeared. The drawing became
nervous and calligraphic; and above all, the attempt was
made to set the figures in a landscape. But the figures
of men or oí animals still dominated these compositions,
there was a vividness of presentation, a sense of action
and drama which were the heritage of the old Iran.
In the next generation this style seems to have been
further absorbed into the Iranian tradition. In the great
manuscript of the national epic, the Shahnameh or Book
of Kings completed by the poet Firdausi in the early Xlth
century, copied about 1330 and now divided between many
collections, figures and landscape are perfectly matched
in memorable compositions of powerful drama, or
romantic invention.
At the end of the 14th century Iran was once more
ravaged by a conqueror from the Steppe, Timur-leng,
the Lame" the world conqueror Tamerlane. Yet
despite these events, Iranian culture showed astonishing
vitality. Poetry, philosophy and history flourished;"
architecture put on the most splendid robe of brilliant
faience; and metalwork continued the great tradition of
bronze casting which had been one of the glories of Iran,
since the late 12th century.
In the arts of the book, the later 14th century saw the
birth of a new style that was to persist in its main charac¬
teristics for three hundred years, and is one of the great
gifts of Iran to the world. Of this period, Basil Gray,
Keeper of the Department of Oriental Antiquities at the
British Museum, has written, "Craftsmanship went hand-
in-hand with invention. Craftsmanship supplied super¬
lative materials: paper, mineral pigments, gilding, and the
skill to use them in calligraphy, illumination and painting.
"The splendours of carpet and tile revetment were
transferred to the page in these glowing miniatures and
in that setting stood the cyprus-like figures of lovers sung
by the poets, while overhead moved the birds pouring out
their song to the air scented by unfading blossoms. The
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
nearest that Western art has approached to this in feeling
and richness is in French tapestry of the 14th century;
and in pure colour in some Sienese panel-painting, nearly
contemporary with them.
"It was a golden moment which could not be prolonged.
But when it passed the art did not perish, but gave birth
to more numerous progeny in the next generation. The
conquests of Tamerlane uprooted this school of art from
Tabriz and Baghdad (then a Persian city) and spread it
all over the country. Shiraz in the south, the capital of
Fars, the heart of ancient Iran; and Herat in the far east,
capital of Khurasan, became the principal centres at the
courts of Timur's son and grandchildren."
Perhaps the most beautiful of Persia's miniatures are
in the remarkable collection preserved in the Gulistan
Imperial Library at Teheran. These were almost comple¬
tely unknown to the world until the Library sent them
for exhibition in London in 1931 and later in Leningrad.
They include those from the manuscript of the Iranian
epic, the Shahnameh, in which the romance of chivalry
and the exploits of heroes are given expression in the
setting of the Iranian Spring, when the bare hills are
dotted with flowers for a few weeks and the foliage is
Copyright Unesco Album, Iran
THE IMPERIAL LIBRARY of the Gulistan (Rose Garden) Palace at Teheran, where a remarkable
collection of Persian miniatures is preserved. This palace is used for official state receptions. It
contains the fabulous Peacock Throne of the Shahs of Iran which is studded with precious stones.
The Unesco Courier. January 1957
fresh. The Shahnameh contains 20 large miniatures and
a double-page frontispiece, and the name of Prince
Baysunqur, the greatest patron of art and poetry among
Timur's descendants, is found in various places throughout
the manuscript.
A second work from the Gulistan Library also a prod¬
uct of Prince Baysunqur's studio is Kalila and Dimna, a
collection of animal fables. These miniatures show a
sensibility and intimacy with the natural world missing
from the more formal epic scenes. These Indian fables
were also partially translated into French in the 17th
century. La Fontaine learned of them through François
Bernier, a French doctor who came across them while in
Asia, and used some of them in writing his own fables.
In addition to these important manuscripts the Gulistan
Library possesses an equally remarkable collection of
calligraphy and miniatures of different dates and origins
bound together in a luxurious volume by the Moghul
Emperor Jehangir, in the early 17th century. The most
famous miniature of this album, the Muraqqa Gulshan, or
Flower Garden Album, is by Bihzad, the foremost of the
few Persian painters whose names are known today. It
represents the garden of the art-loving Prince Husayn
Bayqara, at whose court in Herat,
Bihzad worked. This illustration,
signed by the artist, who is believed
to have been the first to have ever
mentioned his own name on an illu¬
minated manuscript, probably dates
from about 1480.
Bihzad has been hailed as the
greatest master of Persian painting.
He was a reformer in the treatment
of landscape, which appears more
realistically in his pages than in
those of his forerunners. Moreover
he revolted against the dictation of
the calligraphers and admitted, at
best, only a few lines of text in the
pages he illustrated.
At the end of the 16th century, all
the artistic forces in Persia were
being concentrated at the new
capital, Isfahan, under the impulse of
Shah Abbas the Great (see page 31).
Here arose a new and important
centre for the art of book production.
Parallel to this, a new development
was taking place at the court of the
Moghul emperors in India. One of
them, Humayun, who visited Persia
half way through the 16th century,
returned to India with two Iranian
painters who became heads of the
new painting workshop he established
in his royal library. This patronage
of the arts was continued by his
successor, Akbar the Great, and a new
style of painting was born, owing aca¬
demic discipline and technical know¬
ledge to the Iranian tradition, but in¬
formed with quite another spirit.
This Moghul art is at its most
characteristic in depicting historical
events and in portraiture. In their
wish to record, Akbar and his son and
successor, Jahangir, found the Euro¬
pean science of picture making with
perspective and chiaroscuro, interest¬
ing, and for a time the influence of
Flemish and German line engraving
is clearly visible in Moghul painting.
The Persian miniatures reproduced
in Unesco's Album are taken from
manuscripts which were prepared in
court workshops and which have
remained to this day in royal posses¬
sion. Now, knowledge of these mas¬
terpieces of Iranian and Moghul art
is being made available to an im¬
mensely wider public than has enjoy¬
ed them in the four or 'five hundred
years since they were produced.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1957
THE SAD KING and the wonderful
bird. A king, distressed at the dis¬
cord he sees everywhere around
him, asks the bird if there is a place
anywhere in the world where every¬
one is good and harmony reigns. One
of the most beautiful 15th century
miniatures in Kalila and Dimna, the
book of animal fables executed in the
studios of Prince Baysunqur Mirza.
MIXED POLO MATCH. A scene
frequently reproduced by Iranian
painters: the game of polo, which
originated in Persia. A I 6th century
illustration of one of the stories in
the Khamseh of Nizami, a poet and
one of the great thinkers of ancient
Iran. Here, young men, led by Khus-
rau, play against young women
led by Khusrau's beloved, Shirin.
YOUNG NOBLEMAN carrying a
falcon. A work attributed to Far-
rukh Beg, a Kalmuk, and one of the
most gifted and original artists who
worked for the Great Moghul, Akbar,
and later for his son the Emperor
Jahangir, towards the end of the I 6th
century. Taken, as is our cover
illustration, from the Muraqqa Gul-
shan, or Flower Garden Album.
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
THE BOOK OF KINGS. Prince Baysunqur Mirza, a 15th century
descendant of the Mongol conqueror, Tamerlane, was an enthusiastic
admirer of the Shahnameh, or "Book of Kings", the epic history of
Persia written by the I Oth century poet, Firdausi. He ordered a copy
of it to be made and the result was one of the world's most magnificent
illuminated manuscriptsa gem of painting, calligraphy and book¬
binding. The calligraphist, Ja'far Baysunquiri, completed the copy in
I 430, but the work carries no other date and no painter's name. This
illustration from the Shahnameh depicts King Kaikus receiving a bard,
in reality a div (evil spirit of Persian mythology) come to deceive him.
40
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1957
EXPLOITS OF HEROES and the romance of Chivalry are given expression
in the Shahnameh in the setting of the Iranian Spring, when the bare hills are
dotted with flowers for a few weeks and the foliage is fresh. Here, one the
heroes of the Shahnameh, Isfandiyar, kills two wolvesone of a series of deeds
which he, and a rival hero, Rustam, must perform to prove their courage.
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
A GAME DRIVE in the presence of Prince Baysunqur Mirza, from the copy of the Shahnameh
executed in the studios of this Prince, a passionate book collector and a gifted calligraphist'
42
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier, January 1957
Persepolis : fabulous capital of an empire
Splendour and magnificence of Persepolis, capital of the ancient Persian
Empire, astounded Alexander the Great and the victorious Greeks
who captured and burned it about 331 B.C. The regal city with its
portals, royal quarters and audience halls, was built some 40 miles
north east of present-day Shiraz by Darius, third ruler of the Achaemenid
dynasty, who came to the throne in 521 B.C., and by his son, Xerxes I.
It was constructed on a great, rectangular terrace, jutting out from
Copyright CG. Troeller-C. Deffarge
cliffs, on which remain the ruins of colossal buildings of dark grey marble
from the nearby mountain, and hundreds of bas-reliefs executed for the
Achaemenid kings and later dynasties. Above, bas-relief on cliff face
north of Persepolis, showing a Sasanian ruler. King Shapur I (241-271
A.D.), receiving homage of the Roman emperor Valerian, whom he
captured in battle. Below, two bas-reliefs from Persepolis Itself:
King Darius enthroned, holding royal audience, and slaying a lion.
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
44
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1957
Processions in stone
The Great Apadana, or audience hall, built by Xerxes I in Persepolis,
is approached by a double stair whose sides are lined with two groups
of figures cut in low relief on the stone masonry. One of them (below)
shows a long procession of subject peoples of the empire bringing
tribute offerings for the annual spring festival held at Persepolis. The
other (left) depicts the Persian, Median and Susian members of the
royal guard. The vast interior hall of the Apadana, about 200 feet
on each side, contained six rows of six columns, 65 feet in height. The
most striking of the audience halls at Persepolis was the famous "Hall
of a hundred columns", several of which still remain standing. Workmen
and materials were brought to the site of the new Persian capital from
all over the empire, and the style of the architectural details and the
carved reliefs is a composite of the art of Egypt, Babylonia and Asia Minor.
Copyright CG. Troeller - C. DefTarge
-:S
The ghost city of Bam
Until the latter part of the 18th century, the city of Bam,
guarded by its citadel and secure within its 100 feet high
walls, was a thriving centre of trade set in an oasis in the
salt desert of southeast Iran. Then, Agha Muhammad Khan,
leader of the Qajar tribes attacked the forces of the Shah
of Iran. He besieged the city of Bam, and ordered the eyes
of 10,000 people to be put out. The city was taken and
destroyed and the remaining inhabitants made their homes in
the nearby oasis. Today, the streets of this ghost city are
empty except for jackals and porcupines and occasional
groups of nomads who camp in the ruins of former mosques.
Copyright C.G. Troeller - C. Deffarge
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
Magic artisan of Milan
Early one afternoon a few weeks
ago a 65-year old printer in Milan
bent over a huge proof sheet cover¬
ed with a series of delicate colour pla¬
tes. It was probably the hundredth time
he had seen the same proofs. On each
occasion before, he had peered intently at
every detail of colour, at every shade
and tone, had shaken his head and scrib-.
bled a few rapid marks in one spot or
another. To these, each time, he had
added a comment such as '"troppo rosso"
(too much red) or "'blu troppo debile"
(not enough blue). This time, however,
he looked up and nodded to a Unesco
expert. There was a twinkle in his eye
as he smiled and said "perfetto."
The man was Amilcare Pizzi, the
"magic artisan of Milan" and the word
he uttered meant that another album in
the Unesco World Series was now
ready or perhaps just about almost
ready to come off the presses.
When in 1954 the New York Graphic
Society decided to launch the Unesco
series of albums of little known national
art treasures, each with 32 coloui
plates to be reproduced with the highest
technical quality and fidelity, the firm of
Amilcare Pizzi was the immediate and
unanimous choice.
Pizzi brought to Unesco almost half
a century of exceptional craftsmanship
and devotion to beauty which had earned
for him the undisputed title as the finest
colour printer of all Italy ("the wizard
of Italian colour printing" his compa¬
triots call him) and undoubtedly one of
the most meticulous colour printers
anywhere in the world.
Apart from the Unesco World Art
Series, Pizzi's greatest pride is his monu¬
mental tour de force in publishing an
exact replica of the famous Codex Resta,
a 17th century bound collection of paint¬
ings and drawings preserved at the
Ambrosiana Library, Milan. He and his
staff of 300 worked for more than two
years to finish the work in which every
stain, every blotch and every shade of
colour of the ancient paper was repro¬
duced along with one hundred plates
reprinted with the same measurements
and colours as the originals. When the
Codex Resta was completed (2,000 copies
were printed) it astounded book pub¬
lishers the world over and was hailed as
the most perfect publishing achievement
of the graphic arts.
For one of his latest volumes on the
Mosaics of Ravenna in the "Silvana Col¬
lection" he had bagfuls of the tiny
mosaics shipped to Milan to be sure that
his colour reproduction would be replicas
of each stone. During the war he ma¬
naged to photograph all the frescoes of
Mantegna at Padua just three days before
they were destroyed by bombing. His
colour reproductions are the only remain¬
ing testimony of these masterpieces.
Curiously, Pizzi opened his first printing
plant with savings from his exploits as a
football champion (he was halfback on
Italy's national team in his youth).
Photos show stages in colour printing of
Unesco albums. (I) Films for Masaccio vol¬
ume are treated in retouching room.
(2) Photo shop prepares negative for Spain
album. (3) Amilcare Pizzi (white smock) and
Anton Schutz, director of New York Graphic
Society, check colour fidelity of sheet proofs.
(4) Workman pulls colour hand proof from
plate for Spain album, photos UNESCO-Farabola
46
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1957
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
»»*.
The UNESCO WORLD ART SERIES
1
THE UNESCO WORLD ART SERIES is published by arrangement with
UNESCO, by the New York Graphic Society, for more than a quarter of a
century one of the world's leading publishers of fine colour reproductions.
The UNESCO WORLD ART SERIES is a unique
publishing venture, jointly launched in 1954 by
New York Graphic Society and UNESCO with the
co-operation of the various governments. It has
resulted to date in the publication of eight books
considered by authorities as among the most faith¬
ful art reproductions ever issued. Published in a
standard format, each book contains 32 high-fidelity
extra-large colour plates, mostly 15 by 11 inches
(38 by 28 cm), plus several black and white illus¬
trations in the text. The page size is 18i by 13 inches
(14 by 33 cm). Each volume is published in five
languages, and often a sixth that of the country
of origin.
The price per volume is §16.50 (U.S.A.) Colour plates
from any books may be purchased individually; des¬
criptive captions in several languages on each plate.
Price, S 2.00 each.
New additions to the series
IRAN Early Persian Miniatures from the Imperial Li¬
brary of the Shah of Iran at the Gulistan Palace. Text
by Basil Gray. Introduction by André Godard.
SPAIN Romanesque Painting of the 10th, 11th, 12th
and 13th centuries an extraordinary chapter in art
history. Text by Juan Ainaud.
MASACCIO Frescoes in Florence from the Brancacci
Chapel and Santa Maria Novella. Text for Latin
languages by Mario Salmi ; English and German by Sir
Phillip Hendy. (Not part of the series)
Previously published
INDIA Paintings from the Ajanta Caves. Text by
Mandanjeet Singh. Introduction by Jawaharlal Nehru.
EGYPT Paintings from Tombs and Temples. Text by
Jacques Vandier. Introduction by Mohamed Naguib.
AUSTRALIA Aboriginal Paintings from Arnhem Land
Introduction by Sir Herbert Read.
YUGOSLAVIA Medieval Frescoes. Text by Svetozar
Radojcic. Introduction by Talbot Rice.
NORWAY Paintings from Stave Churches. The Gol¬
den Age of medieval painting in Norway. Text by Roar
Hauglid. Introduction by Louis Grodecki.
In preparation
Further volumes on CEYLON, JAPAN, U.S.S.R.,
l; I \l i I' '' _^a^
CZECHOSLOVAKIA and TURKEY will continue to
augment this valuable co-operative series of beautiful
and unique books.
If UNESCO WORLD ART SERIES books are not
available at your local bookstore, they may be obtained
by writing directly to New York Graphic Society.
NEW YORK GRAPHIC SOCIETY 95, East Put¬
nam Ave., Greenwich, Connecticut U.S.A.
UNESCO WORLD ART SERIES Agents:
Argentina : Carlos Hirsch, Buenos-Aires ; Australia :
Ure Smith, Ltd., Sydney ; Canada : Burns and Mac-
Eachern, Toronto ; Denmark: G.E.C. Gad, Copenha¬
gen ; England : The Zwemmer Gallery, London ; Fin¬
land : Akademiska Bokhandeln, Helsinki ; France, Bel¬
gium, Luxembourg : Etablissements Braun et Cié.,
Mulhouse-Dornach, Haut-Rhin, France ; Germany :
R. Piper & Co., Munich ; Holland: Meulenhoff & Co.,
Amsterdam ; Italy : Silvana Editoriale d'arte, Milan ;
Spain : Sociedad General Española de Libreria, Madrid ;
Sweden : Importbokhandeln, Stockholm ; Switzerland :
Office du Livre, S.A., Fribourg ; Uruguay : Ibana, Mon¬
tevideo.
(discounts for members of educational and cultural
organizations available from national distributors)
48
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. January 1957
Letters to the Editor
Sir,
The task of uniting the peoples of this
shrinking planet we call our "wide"
world in mutual trust and co-operation
is one confronted by opposition from
some quarters, but it is, nevertheless, a
task with an inevitable outcome: success.
Successful accomplishment of the long
needed era of peace and universal
friendship is inevitable because it is the
prime hope of that group that stands
above nations and governments: the
people of the world. Your publication
is a great tool in furthering this task of
international unity and trust.
Gordon V. Carr
Rhode Island, U.S.
Sir,
... I should like to make a suggestion for
a future issue. I think that a well-
illustrated study of national dishes
would interest many readers, and it could
perhaps be linked with the question
of diet in relation to climate and even
with the character of different peoples.
It could also cover the cooking utensils
used around the world...
H. Vialatte
Paris, France
Sir,
I think good quality is maintained
throughout the unesco courier pho¬
tographs, articles, paper, printing and
cover. But why do you send it to us
in a wrapper after folding it. As a
result, an attractive magazine is dis
figured by a crease which spoils the
cover photo and, in fact, every page.
Your magazine deserves better treatment.
I am convinced that you could find a
solution not prohibitively expensive
which would enable you to deliver it
unmarked.
M. Lebel
Issy-Ics-Moulineaux,
Seine, France
Editor's note : Because of the exceptionally
low subscription rales, it is not possible to
mail The Unesco Courier in envelopes. Our
distribution service is, however, studying ways
in whiclt the problem raised by our reader
might be overcome.
Sir,
I do appreciate your efforts to make
people explain and understand each
other. A German edition of the
unesco courier would help to make
friends between Germans and people of
any nationality.
Régine Heller
Wuppertal-Elberfeld,
Germany (Fed. Rep.)
Sir,
I was glad you published the article
"Better understanding through foreign
languages" by Henri Kerst. We need
more articles on this vital subject.
School graduates should be encouraged
to continue their studies of foreign
languages through newspaper reading
and conversation groups. Many people
have a good knowledge of a foreign
language on leaving school, but a few
years of neglect cause a deplorable loss.
Reading a newspaper once a week
would have kept the knowledge alive...
I would like to suggest a column in each
issue of the unesco courier on the
correct pronunciation of foreign names
used in the magazine .
Sadie Stave
New York, U.S.
Sir,
Hearty congratulations on the remark¬
able issue you devoted to Buddhist
Art and Culture (June 1956; U.S.
August). Would it be possible to devote
other numbers to such subjects as Islam,
medieval Christianity, symbolism, the
world's great cathedrals, Brahmanism
and to the great epochs in world art: the
century of Pericles, the century of
Augustus, the 13th century, the Renais¬
sance, Baroque art, etc? By studying
art, religions and techniques, the
unesco courier could thus provide a
true summing up of the various civiliza¬
tions of which mankind may well be
proud.
R. Navailh
Alençon, France
Sir,
I have enjoyed reading the unesco
courier, month after month, but your
August, 1956 (European, June 1956
2,500 Years of Buddhist Art and Cul¬
ture) is nothing short of superlative.
What a relief to read a publication with
a world-view. I must say it makes our
U.S. magazines seem very provincial.
Eugene Burns
McCIure Newspaper
Syndicate, New York, U.S.
WHERE TO SUBSCRIBE
Unesco's national distributors from
whom the English, French and Spanish
editions of the UNESCO COURIER
can be obtained are listed below.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 303 Flinders Street, Melbourne,
C I, Victoria.
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C*., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V.
BELGIUM. Louis de Lannoy, Editeur-
Libraire, I 5 rue du Tilleul, Genval (Bra¬
bant). 60 Belgian francs.
CANADA. University of Toronto Press,
Toronto 5.
Periodica Inc., 5090 Avenue Papineau,
Montreal 34.
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House, P.O. Box
244, 100 Parsons Road Colombo I.
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Libreria Económica, Calle
O' Reilly 505, Havana.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6 Nörregade, Copenhagen K.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
FRANCE. Unesco Sales Section,
19 Avenue Kleber, Paris, I6\
CCP. 12598-48, Unesco Bookshop,
Paris.
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2.
Sub-Depots : Oxford Book & Stationery
Co., Scindia House, New Delhi; Rajkamal
Publications Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby
Road, Bombay I.
INDONESIA. G.CT. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Djakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
P. O. B. 4154, Tel-Aviv.
ITALY. Libreria Commissionaria San-
soni, Via Gino Capponi 26, Casella Pos¬
tale 552, Florence.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 99
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND SIN¬
GAPORE. Peter Chong & Co., Post
Office Box I 35, Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta.
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church.
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos.
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass 7, Oslo.
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60 The Mall,
Lahore ; Bunder Road, Karachi and
35 The Mall, Pashawar.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejos. Qjiapo, P.O. Box
620. Manila.
REPUBLIC OF IRELAND. The
National Press, 16 South Frederick St.,
Dublin.
SWEDEN. A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl.
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgaten 2, Stockholm
16.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payor, 40 rue du Marché, Geneva.
5.20 Swiss Irancs.
TANGIER. Paul Fekete,' 2 rue Cook.
Tangier.
THAILAND. Suksapan Panic, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
UNION OF BURMA. Burma Educa¬
tional Bookshop, 55 1-3 Merchant Street,
P.O. Box 222, Rangoon.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Street, P.O. Box 724, Pretoria.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569. London, S.E.I.
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 152 West 42nd St, New York,
36, N.Y,
U. S. S. R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjïga
Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom..
A,USTRALIAN ART AFLOAT.
An original travelling exhibition of con¬
temporary Australian art recently went on
a six weeks' tour of the Pacific. Believed
to be the first floating art exhibition ever
to cross an ocean, the show visited New
Zealand, Hawaii, the United States and
Canada in the course of a 15,000 mile
voyage from Sydney. It included 88 con¬
temporary Australian works loaned by
state galleries and private owners, which
made the trip in the S.S. Orcades.
Showings on board ship were arranged in
Auckland, New Zealand, Honolulu, San
Francisco and Vancouver.
a TELECLUBS IN TOWN. Tele-
clubs, first started in rural areas of
France to provide community TV
viewing and thus overcome some rural
isolation problems, are now springing
up with Unesco assistance in country
districts of Southern Italy and Japan.
But teleclubs can also play a useful role
in towns, in the opinion of Belgian adult
education specialists who recently held
a seminar on this question in co-opera¬
tion with Unesco TV representatives.
Teachers, youth leaders, trade union
representatives, ministers of religion and
TV producers all agreed that collective
viewing was of value to schools, youth
groups, social and church clubs, sana¬
toria and similar groups in an indus¬
trialized community.
I REEING KNOWLEDGE. Just
about 500 million people now enjoy the
benefits of the UNESCO-sponsored Agree¬
ment which exempts books, newspapers,
magazines, works of art, music scores and
articles for the blind from import duties.
Also exempt are newsreels, educational
films, sound recordings and scientific
equipment, if consigned to approved
institutions. Twenty-three countries apply
the Unesco Agreement and one of them,
the United Kingdom, has extended its pro
vision to almost all of its overseas territo¬
ries, as, more recently, has Belgium in the
case of the Belgian Congo and Ruanda-
Urundi.
J. AST VERSUS PRESENT. How
to reconcile the demands of modern town
planning with the desire to preserve histori¬
cal monuments which are "in the way",
is a problem which plagues many countries.
It is now being tackled in Syria which
boasts some of the world's most beautiful
vestiges of ancient architecture and monu¬
ments, and where new office buildings,
offices and factories and hotels are spring¬
ing up on the sites of ancient cities. In
1953 a survey of the problem, greatest in
the old towns with their ancient bazaars,
caravanserais, and mosques, was made by
a three-man Unesco team. On the basis
of its report, Unesco is sending a French
specialist in architecture and archaeology
to Syria to carry the work forward a step
further under its programme of aid to
Member States.
H SHAPELY, SPEEDIER SHIPS.
The first ship-model testing tank in
South-East Asia, installed with the co¬
operation of Unesco is now in opera¬
tion at the Central Water and Power
Station, in Poona, India. Tests already
made in the 500 feet long tank with
models of fishing boats used near
Bombay have proved that the speed of
these boats could be increased by 10 per
cent without any additional power
simply by changing the design. The
tests climax a three years' co-operation
between Unesco and the Poona research
station.
A CUMULATIVE INDEX OF THE
"UNESCO COURIER" FOR THE TWO
YEARS 1955-1956 WILL BE PUBLISH¬
ED SHORTLY.
Coming in February
Special UNESCO COURIER
report on world book
publishing and translations
SPOTLIGHT ON
THE WORLD
OF BOOKS
5,000 million books are pub¬
lished annually, three quarters
of them in I 0 countries.
-^ 22,000 translations were pub¬
lished In I 954. Seventy per cent
were in four languages (English,
Russian, French, German).
-^- When is a book not a book ?
There is still no standard Inter¬
national definition.
SUBSCRIPTION
Subscribe to THE UNESCO COURIER today -$ 2.50; 8/; 400 francs per year (12 issues)
Fill in this subscription blank and mail it with your cheque or money order
to our local agent in your country listed at bottom of previous' page.
Please enter my subscription for THE UNESCO COURIER
D One year $2.50; 8/-; 400 French francs D Two years $4.50; 16/-; 800 French francs
D Cheque /Money Order enclosed D Please bill me
u
z
<
Name	
Address..
o
z
<
City Country	Profession.
o
ci
o
O
50
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
THE ANNUNCIATION TO THE SHEPHERDS. Detail from
12th century mural one of the vast compositions on the life of Christ
decorating vaults of Collegiate Church of St. Isidore, León, northwest
Spain. León conserves the most important surviving paintings which
mark the road followed by medieval pilgrims from Limoges in France
to the shrine of St. James at Compostela. (Unesco Album: Spain)
PRINTED IN ITALY - A. PIZZI - MILAN
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
X
]]>
</page>
</document>
