<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="067211eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
VMM!M»I'M i ON THE WO R LD
4 '
"u']
5.000 million
books
a year
»
v
957
(IOth year)
Ice: 9d. (U. K.)
cents (U. S.Ï
^ ^M
"j^5
*¥>
^£j^r
^
POTLIGHT ON
THE WORLD
OF BOOKS
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
GARGANTUA
AMONG TOMES
Giant atlas of King Charles II,
largest book in British Museum,
measures 5 feet 9 ]/2 inches by
3 feet 2 y, inches, and required
eight morocco goatskins for its
binding. Each map was en¬
graved on 20 separate copper¬
plates; sections were almost
invisibly joined and hand-colour¬
ed. Maps are ss fresh as when
printed in I 7th century. Photo
is taken from a 270-page
book Bookmen's Bedlam (Rutgers
Univ. Press, Brunswick, New
Jersey, 1955) which its author,
Walter Hart Blumenthal des¬
cribes as "an olio of literary
oddities". From Lilliputs to the
Goliaths of bookdom; from
round and heartshaped books
to specimens with twin bind¬
ings; from books buried in
coffins to those salvaged from
sunken ships, Mr. Blumenthal
describes the strange sideshow
and literary circus of droll,
wayward and eccentric speci¬
mens of the book world. (For
other items from Bookmen's
Bedlam see pages I 5, I 6 and 33,
and for some photos lent by Mr.
Blumenthal, see pages 27 to 30).
TWELVE BOOKS
IN A SOUP SPOON
According to Walter Hart Blumenthal, the dozen
minute books held in the soup spoon hold the
world's record as the tiniest in their respective
fields. They include a Koran; an Englishdictionary
of 12,000 words; A Galileo (half the size of a
postage stamp, with 208 pages and probably
the smallest volume ever printed from actual
type); a Testament; the Mite (up to 1896 the
world's most diminutive book); Robert Burns
(vellum); Petit Poucet; French Constitution (gold-
stamped leather binding); Gita (Sanscrit); Tasche
Kalender (1839); Laws of Moses (world's smallest
Hebrew book); and Scotch-Irish songs (with
music). Thumbnail size volume (right) is a copy
of Abraham Lincoln's Gettysburg Address.
From Bookmen's Bed/am, (Ç) 19 55 by W.H. Blumenthal.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
FEBRUARY 1957 I Oth YEAR -
CONTENTS
PAGE
3 WHEN IS A BOOK NOT A BOOK?
4 ON A STROLL WITH IMMORTAL FRIENDS
By Gabrielle Cabrini (I)
12 AGATHA CHRISTIE LEADS DANTE AND HOMER
In world translation Derby (II)
7 ROUND TRIP FOR BIDPAI THE SAGE
8 WORLD'S MOST TRANSLATED AUTHORS
(1948-55)
10 I955*s MOST TRANSLATED AUTHORS IN 15
COUNTRIES
15 TIDBITS, ECCENTRICA AND OTHER MORSELS
17 SAVED FROM FIRE AND WATER
Story of Rome's Book Hospital
20 5,000 MILLION BOOKS A YEAR
A look at the world's book trade
22 A COIN IN THE SLOTAND OUT POPS PLATO
The amazing growth of pocket books
By Bertha Gaster
24 SOVIET BOOK NEWS FOR 1957
Hemingway, Faulkner, Maugham in Russian
27 MEN IN LONG BLACK ROBES
Mass-produced books before printing presses
By Jorge Carrera Andrade
31 WHAT HAS TV DONE TO BOOK READING?
By Henry Cassirer
32 THE PUBLISHER'S DILEMMA
33 SOME BEST SELLERS IN SCIENCE
34 SIXTY YEARS OF U.S. BEST SELLERS
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, 19 Avenue Kleber, Paris 16, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Circulation Manager
Jean Groffier
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (12 issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. A small Japanese version is published in Tokyo
and a Danish version in Copenhagen. The United States of America edition
is distributed by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 152, West 42nd
Street, New York 36, N.Y,, Pennsylvania 6-0851. Second-class mail privileges
authorized at New York, N.Y.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
credit is given to THE UNESCO COURIER and two voucher copies are sent
to the editor. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied
by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles express
the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent the opinions of
UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: $2.50 ; 8/- ; 400 French francs or equivalent«
(M.C. 56.1.109 A)
The Unesco Courier. February 1957
COVER PHOTO
Book vendor in Indian bazaar has
aura of mystery as he displays his
stock under glare of kerosene lamp.
Recent Unesco statistics show that
fiction is first choice of book readers
in most countries. In India and U.K.
it is over 60% of total reading; in
U.S. over 50%; In Thailand and Phi¬
lippines 40%. In Unesco's Delhi
Public Library English non fiction is
preferred to fiction. (See page 3 3)
© Almasy 19 56
Over 60 countries throughout the world publish books,
and about 5,000 million books come off the world's
presses each year. That at any rate is about as
close as experts can place global book production for
there is no general agreement as to what constitutes a
book, and even the chief producing countries have failed
to adopt a common definition.
The United Kingdom considers that a book is a pub¬
lication priced at a minimum of sixpence (7 US cents).
Ireland and Italy say a book must have at least 100 pages;
in Iceland it can have as few as 17; Hungary lays down
a minimum of 64 pages. Several countries, among them
India, Indonesia and the U.S.S.R., do not distinguish
between books and pamphlets and classify them all as
books. U.S. book statistics exclude all pamphlets and
government publications not sold commercially.
In addition, there is little agreement as to how the pro¬
duction, export and import of books should be recorded.
In most countries, it is impossible to estimate accurately
the production of books by copies because no one has any
precise idea about the production of cheap reprints-
paper-backed pocket books, etc. And in their export-
import figures, many countries lump books with unknown-
quantities of other printed matter. Others again, exclude
postal book exports and consignments below certain values
which play an important part in world trade in books.
Unesco is working to secure agreement among govern¬
mental and other bibliographical agencies on these ques¬
tions. For example, it has recommended that a book be
defined for statistical purposes as a "non-periodical pub¬
lication containing 49 or more pages"; that both books
and pamphlets be included in total annual production, as
is now the general practice, but that they be recorded
separately; that government books, academic papers,
reference books, atlases should be included (also under a
separate heading) provided they are sold commercially;
and that textbooks should not be excluded from national
book statistics. On the other hand, it has recommended
that governments should include book post exports and all
other consignments of books however small they may be.
Unesco has turned the spotlight on other problems af¬
fecting the book trade and the international flow of books.
"Books for All," its latest survey of the book trade, reveals
that three quarters of all books come from only ten coun¬
tries, that nine-tenths of all books are produced in only
eight languages, and that seventy per cent of the world's
translations are made in only four languages.
To this unbalanced and often confused situation is
added the complexity of trade barriers to books. Twelve
per cent of all countries levy import duties and 70 per
cent impose currency restrictions on books. Less than
half the world's postal administrations apply a provision
of the Universal Postal Convention which allows books to
be mailed at half the ordinary rate for printed matter.
Unesco has sponsored an international agreement (now
applied by 24 countries) granting duty free entry to books,
and the Universal Copyright Convention which gives
greater protection to authors and publishers. It is pro¬
moting the translation of representative works of litera¬
ture into various languages, and working "to give the peo¬
ple of all countries access to the printed and published
materials produced by any of them."
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
ON ASTROLL
WITH IMMORTAL
FRIENDS
by Gabrielle C abri ni
The trade in second-hand books is nowadays an
international industry whose annual turnover runs
into astronomic figures. Organized on an inter¬
national scale, it has its own directories of book¬
shops in many lands. One published in France,
for instance, lists I, I 63 addresses of book dealers
in 13 countries. Another, the "A.B. Bookman's
Yearbook," printed in London, gives 5,500 names
of second-hand bookshops throughout the world,
while a weekly specialist publication, " The Clique"
supplies its readers with the titles of some
1,000,000 second-hand books of interest, which,
according to still another catalogue, fill 58 different
categories and 759 sub-categories. One of the
great centres of the trade is Paris where many
second-hand book dealers are installed on the
banks of the Seine, especially around the cathedral
of Notre-Dame (above). Browsing for books
among the curious "box stalls" (above, right)
is a popular pastime for Parisians who sometimes
describe the Seine, along its course through their
city, as "a river lined with books and fishermen."
© Almasy 1956
There are times in everyone's life when destiny seems
to change its course and reshape the future. How
many of us have ever thought back to the important
milestones in" our life and tried to recall the things that
seemed to exert a strong influence at those moments of
change and decision? We probably would find that, in
our childhood at any rate, one book or perhaps several
books somehow played a part in changing the course of
our existence.
If we put this same question to our family and friends,
many of them would certainly tell us that books, stand¬
ing out like landmarks in a voyage of exploration, had also
been decisive factors in their lives. Sometimes books
encouraged them to step out more firmly along an already
chosen road; sometimes books made them hesitate and
finally seek a new path to follow. Like us, they too
perhaps heard in a book the call of adventure or found
the door to fresh discoveries.
These are universally shared experiences and if we were
able to carFy our inquiries to other lands we would find
that for hundreds of years certain works have formed the
very basis of human thought and feeling. The names of
their authors are immortal: Homer, Dante, Shakespeare,
Cervantes, Tolstoy» Victor Hugo... a complete list would
fill many pages.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1957
And yet, how many of us ever considered what propor¬
tion of these works, which have been a source of delight
and heart-searching to us and to so many generations of
human beings, were actually conceived and written in our
language or even in one of those in which the majority of
people have read them?
Down the centuries, poets, philosophers and scholars
have all had a share in moulding you, and the men, women
and children of your country. If today they could return
on earth how many of them could even suspect that it is
of them that people are talking in many lands. How
surprised they would be to find their poems in the hands
of a Japanese student, to see that it is their stories that
set a child a-dreaming in Peru, or to discover that their
teachings, expounded in strange characters quite unintel¬
ligible to them, are being pored over by a host of readers,
intent on grasping their inner meaning.
"No man is an island", wrote John Donne, the English
poet and divine, three and a half centuries ago. Man's
nature prevents him from remaining indifferent to what
affects others of his kind. Though separated by languages
and customs and often divided by wars, men have always
wanted to know and to understand the thoughts, the likes
and the dislikes of other peoples those who wore such
funny clothes, those who invaded and overran their
country or tried to make it adopt their way of life. For
this understanding they needed translations.
The first translations we know of include sacred writings.
These were made slowly and tediously for their meaning
had to be rendered with perfect fidelity. Later came non-
religious texts. It would perhaps be wrong to consider
these as translations for those who made them were
adapters rather than true translators. In a language they
had mastered by diligent study or learned by chance they
looked for a world of wonders, costumes and customs to
delight and amuse those who would read about them.
Yet while depicting this unfamiliar and exotic world, the
adapter, consciously or unconsciously, was careful to
preserve certain basic features, certain elements of the
known world which enabled the readers in his own country
to feel at one with the king and the shepherd, the courtier
and the beauty whose adventures, in lands which seemed
so different from their own, they followed with a rapt
interest.
That is why we sometimes find it hard to believe that
certain stories did actually originate in far-off |
places. Some which seem to have been I
created in the minds of our own countrymen I
and to mirror perfectly their outlook and way |
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
IMMORTAL FRIENDS
(Continued)
of thinking have, in fact, reached us after strange
journeys across the earth. One of the most remarkable
was made by one of the great books of India, the Pancha-
tantra or "Five Cases of Wisdom", regarded as India's
most outstanding imaginative work. The fables are
attributed to a legendary Brahmin named Vishnusarman
and are said to have been written for a king of southern
India who was famed for his might and learning, but
cursed with lazy and ignorant sons. Of the seventy fables
and stories in the Panchatantra, written between the
second and sixth centuries A.D.', some have been translat¬
ed into practically every one of the languages of ancient
and modern India.
The Odyssey of these fables led them along devious
routes to the Western World, and showed what changes
and adaptations a writing can undergo in the course of
time. About the 6th century A.D. the fables were translat¬
ed into Persian, and from Persian into Arabic around
750 A.D. By the 12th century they had been translated
from Arabic into Hebrew and a Jewish convert to Christi¬
anity, who later became the monk John of Capua, adapted
them into Latin. Spanish, French and German language
texts followed and Italian versions were produced by Doni
(1552) and Firenzuola (1548). The version of Doni was
translated into English by Sir Thomas North (The Morall
Philosophie of Doni, 1601).
The collection became best known in Europe as the
fables of Bidpal (derived from the wise Bidpai who tells
the stories). In France the ancient storyteller had
become "Pilpay the Sage", and the stories were read in the
17th century by the writer Jean de la Fontaine, who, when
writing his own famous fables, took ideas from the Indian
ones ("I owe most of them to Pilpay1", he wrote with some
exaggeration) and material which he transposed.
Marco fires fever for knowledge
One day the westward journey was halted and Pilpay
retraced his steps towards the east in translations
and adaptations. La Fontaine's fables, today fa¬
mous the world over, made their way back to the country
of their birth. They were translated into Arabic, Persian
and Coptic, and so returned to India where illuminated
manuscripts now illustrate many which had set out from
there so many centuries earlier.
The same thing happened to the great romances that
enthralled the people of the Middle Ages the Romance of
Alexander, the Romance of Tristan and Isolde and many
others. Their origins have become so obscure that it is
hard to say who was their first and true begetter.
One of the most widely translated books at the end of
the Middle Ages was The Travels of Marco Polo. This
Venetian, most famous of all travellers, recounted in
French a fabulous yet real journey to China in the second
half of the thirteenth century. His work created in the
West an obsession with the treasures and riches of
India and "Cathay", the Empire of the Great Khan. It
was translated in record time not only into all European
languages, but also into all manner of dialects: Genoese,
Provencal, Catalan, Aragonese, Tuscan and many others.
Yet this first great European "eye witness" account of the
Far East was not translated and published in Chinese and
Japanese until quite recently.
Fired by the great and successful voyages of discovery,
a kind of fever of desire to know and to translate spread
over the world. Dazzled by the appearance of new races
which seemed to spring from nowhere and delighted by so
much diversity, scholars and monks did their best to collect
and preserve the treasures of literature from destruction.
Many works which can never be replaced, however, fell
victim to the flames of war and conquest.
In Mexico alone, dictionaries were compiled of dozens of
languages transliterated into Latin characters. And the
world continued to shrink as the craving for knowledge
grew ever stronger in the West. What were the men who
lived in other lands really like? What had
the people of ancient times really been like?
Collectors princes, scholars and rich mer¬
chants searched abbeys and monasteries, PaSe
Animal heroes of La Fontaine's fables in Persian.
Animals with the plague. Abyssinian manuscript.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1957
ROUND TRIP FOR BIDPAI THE SAGE
Last year, translations of the celebrated fables of Jean de la
Fontaine, the I 7th century French writer, were published
In nine languages: Danish, German, Spanish, Finnish,
Esperanto, Hungarian, Polish, Rumanian and English. These
fables have already been translated into most of the world's
languages and in this waythrough adaptations and transla¬
tions have travelled back to some of the countries
from whose stories La Fontaine drew inspiration. First of
all, La Fontaine, like many French writers before him, drew
on the great wealth of fables attributed to Aesop, the ancient
Greek "master of stories". His originality was to revive
the fable in verse and to endow it with a realism based on
a close observation of beasts and men. La Fontaine also
owes a debt, which he acknowledges in his edition of
I 678-79, to a collection of Indian fables collected under the
title of the Ponchotontro or "Five Cases of Wisdom". The
collection became best known in Europe as the fables of
Bidpal (from the wise Bidpai who tells the stories). In the
French translation of I 644, Bidpal became "Pilpay the Sage".
When La Fontaine's fables were translated into Arabic,
Persian and Coptic, "Pilpay" retraced his steps to the East.
Eventually, the stories once again reached India, where
illuminated manuscripts now illustrate many of them which
had set out from that country many centuries before.
Characters from La Fontaine's "The Miller, his Son and the Ass" in Indian guise. (Feuillet de Conches Collection)
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
WORLD TRANSLATED AUTHORS
Table below shows authors whose works have been pub¬
lished in translation at least 100 times in past eight years.
(Pearl Buck is first living author and first woman). Photos,
opposite, show authors of five countries who have been most
translated throughout the world In past eight years (in order
of importance from left to right). Table on Page 10 lists
most translated authors In 1955 in 15 major translating
countries and gives' further explanations on table below.
1955 1955
AUTHOR NATIONALITY
1948-1955
No OF
TRANS¬
LATIONS
ONLY
AUTHOR NATIONALITY
1948-1955
No OF
TRANS¬
LATIONS
ONLY
TRANS COUN
!
TRANS- COUN-
PUB¬
LISHED
LATIONS TRIES
PUB¬
LISHED
LATIONS TRIES
V. 1. Lenin U.S.S.R. 968 37I 14 H. Fast U.S.A. I63 32 1 1
The Bible 887 99 II E. Hemingway U.S.A. 157 35 II
J. V. Stalin U.S.S.R. 689 200 12 Cervantes Spain 154 24 12
L. N. Tolstoy U.S.S.R. 495 I05 23 Pius XII 151 I9 10
M. Gorki U.S.S.R. 489 I02 19 A. Daudet France 149 19 II
C. Dickens U.K. 443- 54 18 S. Lagerlöt Sweden 148 20 8
J. Verne France 432 92 16 L. Bromfield U.S.A. 145 20 12
W. Shakespeare U.K. 424 74 22 E. R. Burroughs U.S.A. 145 15 7
H. Balzac France 424 50 19 L. M. Alcott U.S.A. 144 ' 13 6
K. Marx Germany 4I5 6I 12 A. Maurois France 143 21 15
F. Engels Germany 409 64 14 T. Mann Germany 142 29 14
H. C. Andersen Denmark 366 7I 22 E. A. Poe U.S.A. 142 19 10
F. M. Dostoïevski U.S.S.R. 358 62 18 F. Mauriac France 141 29 1 1
J. London U.S.A. 347 55 19 W. Scott U.K. 141 31 15
R. L. Stevenson U.K. 307 35 13 J. Swift U.K. 138 21 1 1
A. P. Chekhov U.S.S.R. 305 66 19 M. de la Roche Canada 138 17 7
P. Buck U.S.A. 304 32 17 Molière France 137 13 1 1
M. Twain U.S.A. 303 52 16 V. Baum U.S.A. 137 13 9
S. Zweig Austria 290 41 13 G. Flaubert France 135 19 12
A. S. Pushkin U.S.S.R. 289 61 17 A. France France 135 14 9
A. Dumas (père) France 279 49 18 W. Disney U.S.A. 134 31 6
G. Simenon Belgium . 273 54 12 M. Delly France 131 24 4
G. de Maupassant France 273 40 16 E. Blyton U.K. 129 37 9
A. J. Cronin Ireland 272 44 14 B. Russell U.K. 129 19 1 1
A. Christie U.K. 264 45 13 1. Ehrenbourg U.S.S.R. 128 30 14
E. S. Gardner U.S.A. 26I 50 12 A. N. Tolstoy U.S.S.R. 126 28 12
W. S. Maugham U.K. 258 40 16 E. Queen U.S.A. 126 20 12
1. S. Turgenev U.S.S.R. 25I 41 18 S. Freud Austria 124 15 7
J. W. Goethe Germany 244 32 1 1 M. Brand U.S.A. 122 9 5
S. & W. Grimm Germany 235 43 13 A. S. Makarenko U.S.S.R. 121 31 9
N. V. Gogol U.S.S.R. 230 35 14 M. J. Min U.S.S.R. 120 14 5
Plato Greece 229 41 16 A. Huxley U.K. 1 18 II 7
A. Gide France 222 22 8 H. Sienkiewicz Poland 116 20 II
E. Zola France 2I8 37 16 A. Conan Doyle U.K. 1 16 20 8
J. F. Cooper U.S.A. 2I0 30 15 L. Charteris U.S.A. 1 16 14 4
W. Johns U.K. 208 21 6 R. M. Rilke Germany 1 15 15 7
V. Hugo France 203 37 16 G. B. Shaw U.K. 1 1 1 12 8
R. Rolland France 200 27 1 12 Sophocles Greece 1 10 13 6
R. Kipling U.K. I96 21 1 1 J.. Galsworthy U.K. 1 10 8 6
G. Greene U.K. 195 28 12 E. Salgari Italy 109 22 3
Z. Grey U.S.A. 194 33 8 J. Conrad U.K. 109 13 7
D. Defoe U.K. 192 39 15 E. Caldwell U.S.A. 108 13 7
Arabian Nights Iran 186 28 1 1 J. Dickson Carr U.S.A. . 106 22 1 1
P. Cheyney U. K. 180 29. 10 P. G. Wodehouse U.K. 106 13 6
Stendhal France 176 27 14 U. Sinclair U.S.A. 106 1 1 5
J. Steinbeck U.S.A. 174 32 14 H. Melville U.S.A. 105 18 10
Homer Greece 172 20 1 1 H. Hesse Switzerland' 104 17 7
E. Wallace U.K. 171 30 9 J. Hilton U.K. 101 16 12
0. Wilde U.K. 167 14 6 St Augustine Roman Empire 100 27 9
D. du Maurier U.K. 166 21 16 (Carthage)
W. Churchill U.K. 163 6 6 Voltaire France 100 II 9
Table prepared by staff of The Unesco Courier
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 19S7
MOST
TRANSLATED
FRENCH
AUTHORS
RUSSIAN
AUTHORS
BRITISH
AUTHORS
AMERICAN
AUTHORS
GERMAN
AUTHORS
J. VERNE BALZAC A. DUMAS (PERE) G. DE MAUPASSANT A. GIDE
C. DICKENS W. SHAKESPEARE R. L. STEVENSON A. J. CRONIN A. CHRISTIE
W. GCETHE Wilhelm an¿ Jacob GRIMM T. MANN R. M. RILKE
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
THEY WERE MOST TRANSLATED
BY THESE COUNTRIES IN 1955
TITLES
CZECHOSLOVAKIA
1. Jules Verne	 14
2. Lenin 13
3. Gorki .7
4. Jack London 	 6
5. Goldonl, Mayakowsky, Push¬
kin, Tolstoy, Mark Twain ... 5
FRANCE
1. Chekov	 12
2. Bible II
3. Hans Andersen	 10
4. W.E.Johns 8
5. Gorki, Erie Stanley Gardner. 7
GERMANY
1. Bible, Edgar Wallace	 16
2. Tolstoy, Enid Blyton 	 9
3. Daniel Defoe, Zane Grey,
S. Teleford 	 8
4. Robert Louis Stevenson,
Pittlgrilll, S. Lagerlof,
G. Bomans 	 7
5. François Mauriac, Hans An¬
dersen, Lenin, Giono 	 6
INDIA
1. Tagore	 14
2. Gandhi II
3. Lenin 8
4. Gorki 7
5. S.C. Chattopadhyaya 	 6
ITALY
1. Jules Verne	 13
2. Dickens 12
3. Shakespeare 9
4. Mark Twain, Delly 	 7
5. Bible, Plato, Dostoïevski, Erle
Stanley Gardner, Jack London 6
JAPAN
1. Maugham, de Maupassant,
Tolstoy 	 13
2. Hemingway, Hermann Hesse. I I
3. A. Christie, Dostoïevski 	 10
TITLES
4. A.J. Conin, Simenon 	 8
5. John Dickson Carr, Erie Stan¬
ley Gardner, Gide, Rilke,
Steinbeck 	 7
NETHERLANDS
1. Bible 10
2. Hans Andersen	 7
3. Upton Sinclair 6
POLAND
1. Lenin	 8
2. Jack London 	 7
3. Hugo, Tolstoy 6
4. Balzac, Ehrenbourg, Howard
Fast, Goethe, Turgenev 	 4
PORTUGAL
1. Shakespeare 	 14
2. Delly, C. de Santander,
Mme de Ségur 	 7
SPAIN
1. Emilio Salgari	 15
2. Simenon 13
3. Jules Verne 9
4. Dickens, Zane Grey 	 8
5. Grimm, Edgar Allen Poe.... 7
SWEDEN
1. Edward S. Ellis 	 18
2. Enid Blyton, Peter Cheyney,
José Mallorqui, Paul Zilso. . . II
UNITED KINGDOM
1. Bible	 6
2. Dumas (père)	 5
3. Hans Andersen, Simenon... 4
4. Dante, Dostoïevski, Thomas
Mann, Alfred de Musset,
Ovid, J. Spyri, Stalin 	 3
UNITED STATES OF
AMERICA
1. Bible	 18
2. Simenon 9
3. Dostoïevski	 8
TITLES
4. Dante	 7
5. St. Augustine	 7
U.S.S.R.
1. Lenin	 328
2. Stalin 126
3. Bulganin 71
4. Gorki 49
5. Krushchev	 40
In field of literature top 5 authors
are all Russian :
1. Gorki	 49
2. Pushkin 35
3. Nosov 27
4. Mayakowsky	 26
5. Tolstoy 26
A large percentage of Soviet translation
figures concerns Russian-language works
published in the many languages of the
U.S.S.R. and of translations of these lan¬
guages Into Russian.
Top I 0 non-Russian authors
1. Jules Verne	 20
2. Theodore Dreiser 	 17
3. Jack London 15
4. Victor Hugo	 13
5. Balzac 10
6. Mark Twain, H. Fast	 9
7. Daniel Defoe 	 8
8. Hans Andersen 7
9. Dickens, Dumas (père), Emi¬
lio Rodari 	 6
10. Fenimore Cooper, A. Dau¬
det, Zola, Romain Rolland . . 5
YUGOSLAVIA
1. Jules Verne	 7
2. Dumas (père), Grimm, Mark
Twain 6
3. Karl May, E.M. Remarque,
Tolstoy 	 5
4. Balzac 4
TOP TRANSLATING
COUNTRIES
IN 1955
TITLES
1. U.S.S.R	 4,282
2. Germany 2,056
3. Czechoslovakia 	 1,478
4. France	 1,424
5. Japan 1,103
6. Italy	 1,118
7. Netherlands	 1, 1 04
8. Poland	 1,071
9. Sweden 949
10. Spain	 894
11. U.S.A '.. 818
12. Yugoslavia 	 738
13. U.K	 659
14. Rumania 658
15. Norway 	 644
INDEX OF CONTEMPORARY HISTORY
For years the Bible has occupied first place in lists of most frequently published
books in translations. Figures for 1955 have changed the picture, and as shown
in table on page 8, the Bible has dropped to second place behind Lenin.
However, it is interesting to note that of the 371 translations of Lenin published in
14 countries during 1955, only 43 were produced outside the Soviet Union, the
remaining 328 being translations published within the U.S.S.R. in languages other
than Russian (see table above).
Tables on these pages are based on information collated from past eight years of
UNESCO's Index Translationum: International Bibliography of Translations (price per
volume: $14; 70/-; 3,500 francs). The Index, first started in 1932 by the International
Institute of Intellectual Co-operation, then listed only six countries. Unesco resumed
publication of the Index in 1950 (none appeared between 1941-47) the first volume
covering 8,000 translations in 26 countries for the year 1948. The latest Volume VIII
covers a record 51 countries and lists 24,274 translations published in 1955.
The volumes of Index Translationum have been hailed as "a remarkable storehouse
of contemporary history... a register of intellectual co-operation which richly repay
people of very varying interests for whatever time they can devote to them." As
one librarian recently wrote: '"Their historical importance increases as every new
annual volume is added to their ranks... It is unfortunate that many who would
appreciate the information given in ' the annual volumes of the Index Translationum
remain unaware of its existence... A glance at the well-printed pages reveals that
the material here given in such prosaic fashion would provide a journalist with enough
facts for half-a-dozen rousing articles, a sociologist with the basis for a searching
study of current trends in tastes and interests, and a historian with more than sufficient
material for almost any theory on contemporary problems he cared to elaborate."'
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1957
A STROLL WITH
IMMORTAL FRIENDS
(Continued) How many from the East?
in out of the way places, in the earth itself, hopeful of
discovering, alongside the broken statues and columns,
some fragments of great books lost to the world.
One of these collectors was Francesco Patrizi da Cherso,
the Italian Renaissance philosopher. The son of a long
line of navigators, he had sailed the Mediterranean from
the age of ten. Now he made journeys to Spain and
Southern Italy where his searches brought to light ancient
manuscripts.
Down the centuries translators of genius have tackled
the great works of the human mind and famous writers
have counted it an honour to revive the writings of the
ancients for their contemporaries. In the 16th century
Jacques Amyot in France and Lope de Vega in Spain made
masterly translations of Plutarch's Lives. In the follow¬
ing century the Arabian Nights were translated from the
Arabic and thus Arab literature enriched that of the
West. The fashion for translations reached such a
pitch that to be sure of success, writers sometimes passed
off their own works as translations that had been made
from another tongue.
From all this it might be
concluded that each country is
well acquainted with the litera¬
ture of others. This is, unhappi¬
ly, not the case. A look through
the volumes of Index Transla¬
tionum, published by Unesco
each year, reveals the fact that
no regular and balanced two-way
flow of translations between dif¬
ferent countries exists. While a
surprisingly large number of
translations may be made in one
particular country, this does not
mean that its own books enjoy
the same popularity elsewhere.
The most striking example is
that of Japan. This is one of the
countries where people read
most. Something like 16 million
copies of daily newspapers are
printed, and these have far more
pages than those published in
England or France.
According to statistics, 2,360
works were translated into Ja¬
panese from other languages in
1953-54 and 1,203 in 1955. Al¬
though this is a high figure, it is
not exceptional when compared
with those (for 1953-54 and for
1955) of several other countries:
Germany (2,473 and 2,056); Italy
(2,336 and 1,118); Yugoslavia (1,408 and 738); or France
(2,674 and 1,424). It is rather in the choice of books that
Japan's case becomes practically unique. The list of titles
is really astounding. It gives the impression that no great
writer, no leading thinker and no important poet has been
overlooked by the translators.
Writers of every period and from every country seem
to be covered. They offer a vast panorama of human
culture, history, science, politics and poetry. All the
great "super length" novels are there, old and new, and
sometimes even those from Western literature scarcely
known in the West because they happen to have been
written in languages with a small diffusion. Poetry is
well represented. We find the names of the greatest poets
of ancient and modern times.
The general impression given is that the Japanese
reader is well versed in every aspect of Western civilization
Jean Paul Sartre to Agatha Christie, from philo¬
sophers and the polemics they inspire, and the success¬
ful first novel of an 18-year.old French girl student to the
stir created by the latest thriller.
What has the West done to compare with this great
coverage? All we find of translations from the Japanese in
all countries is a mere handful of works, including two
taken from the scenarios of two famous filmsRashomon
© Bibliothèque Nationale, Pans
Eusebius Sophronius Hieronymus (St. Jer¬
ome) the first great translator of the
Christian world. Drawing by Rembrandt.
and The Gates of Hell and presented in that form.
Germany has translated, and in an abridged form,
the great Japanese novel, Genji Monogatari. Many West¬
ern publishers would say it was too long, yet the Japanese
have translated the longest Western novels, including A la
Recherche du temps perdu, Les Thibault and Les Hommes
de bonne volonté, to name a few of the recent French ones.
Between 1928 and 1933 an English publisher brought out
the first complete translation of the six-volume master¬
piece of Japanese psychological literature under the allur¬
ing titles of The Tale of Genji, The Sacred Tree, A Wreath
of Cloud, Blue Trousers, The Lady of the Boat and The
Bridge of Dreams, the last two of which were later trans¬
lated into Italian.
When this monumental translation appeared it was
hailed as a great literary event in Western countries and
the works enjoyed great success. An ambitious pro¬
gramme for making unabridged translations was prepared
and launched in a number of Western countries, but this
was unfortunately interrupted by the outbreak of war.
Despite its small population,
Israel, after Japan, is one of the
countries with the broadest of
tastes in literature. Index Trans¬
lationum (N° 7) lists 1,070 trans¬
lations for Israel. (N° 8, the latest
Index, gives no figures) . The list
Includes, for example, classical
masterpieces in Persian and
Arabic, and also those written in
languages less widely used, such
as Norwegian, Croat, Hungarian,
Czech, modern Greek, Danish,
Dutch and Turkish, and works in
the languages most widely used:
Spanish, Russian, French, Ger¬
man, English and Chinese.
There are, of course, many
reasons why different countries
are so unevenly represented in
the field of translations. Those
which use languages which have
the widest diffusion perhaps tend
to take the easiest course. In
France, where . 1,424 titles were
recorded as having been trans¬
lated in 1955 there was, leaving
aside the great classical master¬
pieces, a great predominance of
Anglo - Saxon literature. Then
again, children in nearly every
country read Alice in Wonderland,
Hans Andersen's Fairy Tales and
Pinocchio (I can still see the
delightful Japanese illustrations of a very oriental-looking
Pinocchio, with such a novel expression on his little
wooden face).
In 1949 I met a publisher who was launching the first
collection of world masterpieces, complete or abridged,
in the Indonesian national language. I was idly turning
the pages of the books, though not understanding a single
word I saw. Suddenly I saw on one cover the black
silhouette of a horseman against a distant background of
tropical foliage where the arms of a windmill could be
seen. He carried a lance and his knees gripped the flanks
of a cadaverous horse. Don Quixote, the "knight of the
woeful countenance" was beginning his wanderings in a
new country.
I felt full of envy for the people in Indonesia who would
get to know the greatest work of Spanish literature. For
how many Indonesians, I wondered, would it serve as a
doorway to Spain.And then it occurred to me that it was
not only Spain they would get to know better through this
masterpiece of writing. Through Don Quixote they would
learn to know men everywhere a little better; through him
they would better understand themselves, for the great
unchanging features of mankind are revealed even more
clearly in the world's literary masterpieces than in the
outward characteristics of the countries which conceived
them and brought them forth.
1 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
PINUCCftflF'^ </«/"W
PINOCCHIO, Italian writer Carlo Collodi's
famous story of a puppet, as published in England.
IN WORLD TRANSLATION DERBY
Agatha Christie,
Peter Cheyney
Lead Cervantes
Homer & Dante
0
Which of the world's books enjoy the greatest popu¬
larity? In other words, apart from the literature
of their own mother tongue, what do people like
reading most? Do their tastes vary greatly? Do works
from one country suddenly become popular in others or
does literary popularity follow a regular pattern? Ques¬
tions like these spring to one's mind on looking through
Index Translationum, Unesco's annual index of books
which are translations from an original version into
another language and which have been published during
the previous year.
But to answer these questions with any degree of
accuracy we have to exclude from our calculations those
books which people read, not because they necessarily like
them but because of a religious, educational, political or
scientific need or duty.
Books on mathematics and grammar are certainly not
favourites with children, yet in countries where compul¬
sory education is really an established fact, almost as
many such books are printed as there are children. The
Bible, of which an enormous number of translations is
made, is usually read as a religious duty and is often dis¬
tributed free in the course of missionary work. Works of
political doctrine, like those of Marx and Lenin, are
constantly being reprinted in many countries to serve as
textbooks for political instruction, and certain important
scientific works are translated into many languages, often
because no exactly equivalent works exist, and they are
therefore indispensable.
We shall find the answers to our questions, therefore,
by considering the books which the main libraries of the
world classify, according to the Universal Decimal Classi¬
fication system, under the number 8. In libraries around
the globe, from the Library of Congress at Washington to
the National. Libraries in Paris and Tokyo, the number 8
is applied to all books classified as "literature" all those
works which men down the ages have written for their
own enjoyment, or because of something they wished to
forget or other men to remember, or out of a desire to
place on record (both for themselves and for others) their
enthusiasms and convictions, their hatred and despair,
their emotions and hopes, or simply the stories they spun
to while away the time.
. Thanks to Unesco's comprehensive comparative studies
of translations throughout the world presented in Index
Translationum and in Book Production 1937-1954 and
Translation 1950-1954, we can find our way through the
maze of literary translation without giving to certain figu¬
res (accurate in themselves), an absolute value to which
they are certainly not entitled.
12
In 1954, for example, the U.S.S.R. reported its transla¬
tions (actually spread over a number of years) as 776.
Now this figure does not have the same meaning it would
have if given by, say, France, Germany or any other
country where one principal language is spoken and read
by practically the entire population. Owing to the large
number of languages in the U.S.S.R. 328 of the total of
776 translations made were from Russian into other lan¬
guages of the Soviet Union, which thus reduces the
number of translations of works coming from outside the
U.S.S.R. to 448.
Another unusual case is found in Greece where of 358
translations in 1955, 260 were "literary." Out of these,
BABBITT, a satire on the average businessman
by Sinclair Lewis, as it appears in a Polish edition.
SINCLAIR I-EWI
í Jlñ. f\ Tt
BABBiT
P ' I I
» III I r
::¡¡!itii mm
:¡¡SÍ¡*:¡ es mm
ÏÏUÎ Ü 3°
} -
m
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
HARD TIMES a novel written by Charles Dickens
in I8S4, as it appeared when published in Polish.
49 were translations from classical Greek, a much higher
proportion than in any other country. The people of
Greece, understandably enough, never tire of the great
masterpieces of a past that is still very much alive. In
France, during the same year, 1,452 books were translated,
including 861 works of literature.
In drawing a balanced and accurate picture of the
world's literature translations several other factors must
be taken into account. A distinction must be made
between first or original translations and re-issues of
translations. These figures, however, are difficult to pick
out from literary production as a whole though easily
identified in the case of recent works, they are almost
unobtainable for the older books.
Again, in the case of these older works, a number of
translations may have been made in the same language.
Generally speaking, books whose authors have died too
recently for the copyright to have lapsed on their works
can only be translated and published in each country by
one publisher who has acquired the exclusive rights. But
once the copyright has lapsed, translations of the book
can follow each other thick and fast in every country
where it is read, and may sometimes appear simultan¬
eously. Thus in Italy, for example, ten publishers may
bring out their own translations of a Shakespearean
tragedy at the same time, whereas a novel by the great
German writer Thomas Mann, who died only a few years
ago, can only be translated by one publisher who has
exclusive rights over the work for fifty years.
And the final rule in this game of discovering which
authors' books are the most widely read is to consider the
figures for any one year in relation to those for preceding
years. Sometimes the popularity of an author whose
works have been re-issued regularly year after year
suddenly seems to be on the wane. Is he being less widely
read? Not necessarily so, and, in fact, the contrary is
sometimes the case. What has happened is that publish¬
ers, counting on large sales, have printed big editions to
cut down overhead costs. Thus the market is temporarily
saturated and no new editions need be published for the
time being.
If we were to think of the translation of the world's
great literary masterpieces in terms of a horse or motor
racing contest, with each new language covered represent¬
ing an obstacle overcome, who would be the winners in
1955?
Heading the field, both by the number of works translat¬
ed and the variety of languages in which he continues his
steady course, comes Leo Tolstoy, a true giant amongst
writers. Since 1948 he has been at the head of the leading
group, and in 1955 no writer or poet, past or present, can
The Unesco Courier. February 1957
compete with the author of War and Peace. Translated
in 23 countries and read all over the world, from Japan to
Brazil by way of India and Indonesia, his works, complete
or abridged, are always to be found.
Following Tolstoy and running neck and neck (in the
language of the turf) are two authors translated in
22 countries the creator of angelic beings and of monsters,
William Shakespeare, the greatest dramatist of the modern
world, and Hans Christian Andersen, the father of the
little mermaid and the ugly duckling, for whom so many
adults have retained their childhood affection.
Just behind these two comes a group of four made up of
two Russians, a Frenchman and an American: Maxim
Gorki, Anton Chekov, Honoré de Balzac and Jack London.
In 1955 each of them was translated in 19 countries. Of
the four, however, Chekov appears to have made the most
progress since the Second World War and to have had the
greatest number of new works translated.
Two more Russians, Dostoievski and Turgenev follow
close behind, along with Charles Dickens and Alexandre
Dumas, all of them having translations in 18 countries.
They are all familiar figures among the leaders in this
annual contest for it is many years since The Brothers
Karamazov, David Copperfield and Fathers and Sons first,
journeyed forth from their own countries. As to The
Three Musketeers, the fame of their swashbuckling
adventures has long since spread to Africa, Asia and the
Americas.
Here comes the first woman contestant: Pearl Buck, an
American, alongside a fabulous poet and storyteller,
Pushkin, both of them having translations in 17 countries.
Following them is a compact group of eight: Jules Verne,
Mark Twain, Guy de Maupassant, Plato, Victor Hugo, Emile
Zola, Somerset Maugham, and Daphne du Maurier
(16 countries).
But why continue to place the arrivals? Anyone picking
up the Index Translationum for 1955, which will shortly be
published, can make scores of interesting and amusing
discoveries like these. A few more, however, are worth
mentioning here: Aristophanes and the Brothers Grimm
have been translated in 14 countries, Fenimore Cooper
in 13, Goethe and Cervantes in 12, and Homer, .
Dante and Cervantes in 11 countries.
Yet the number of translations is no yard¬
stick of genius and it would be absurd to draw next page
THE SUN ALSO RISES, Hemingway's novel of a
"lost generation" became "Fiesta" in its Italian version.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
WORLD
TRANSLATION
DERBY
(Continued)
from the statistics
which seem to show
Dante, Homer and
Cervantes as losers,
other conclusions
than the proper
ones. So let us look
at some different
figures, and, keeping
in mind that this is
still a sort of game,
since genius again
cannot be measured
by the number of
works it produces, let us see how many works of the 1955
winners were published during the year in the countries
where their translations were made.
Tolstoy still leads with 105 titles, Gorki follows with
102 and the unforgettable Jules Verne, despite the extra¬
ordinary scientific discoveries since his time, holds third
place with 92. Shakespeare boasts 74 titles (Julius Caesar
and A Midsummer Night's Dream, by the way, recently
appeared for the first time in the Indonesian language),
then Hans Andersen with 71, followed by Chekov, 66;
Dostoievski, 62; and Pushkin, 61.
Ninth in the list comes Jack London, the friend of
outlaws, icy wastes and wild beasts, with 55 titles, then
Mark Twain (52) in tenth place, followed by Balzac (50)
and Dumas (49). Several authors tie for the following
places: Plato and Turgenev (13th with 41 each); de Mau¬
passant and Somerset Maugham (40) and Victor Hugo and
Zola (37). Leaders among the women authors are Pearl
Buck with 32 and Daphne du Maurier (21). There is
certainly no question about it, the Russians are the
undoubted champions of the "translation Derby".
As our look into the world of translations has shown us,
one type of literature which holds a leading place and
which has for long left its imprint on grown-ups and
young people alike, is the adventure story. It has many
variations from cloak and dagger plots to exploits in
far-off lands, from flashbacks to the days of chivalry to
forward-looking accounts of life in future times.
Its heroes seem to combine both the qualities and roles
of law-enforcers and bandits, those romantic outlaws to
whom the continuing vogue of "westerns" appears to be
giving a permanent lease of life. The adventures nearly
always take place in some exotic setting the frozen wastes
of the Far North, the virgin forest, the parched desert, the
forgotten island, unless it happens to be... the Moon. These
kinds of books are firmly entrenched in public taste, and
who knows what astronomical publishing figures may one
day be credited to the latest conqueror, Davy Crockett.
Now a newcomer has joined the school of Jack London,
Oliver Curwood, and Fenimore Cooper José Mallorqui, a
writer who has taken the Spanish-speaking world by
storm, and whose
Prairie Wolf ad¬
venture series is now
also being widely
translated in four
northern European
countries (Denmark,
Finland, Norway
and Sweden).
Another type of
book, whose leading
producers are trans¬
lated more widely
than Dante, Cer¬
vantes or Sophocles,
is now challenging
the supremacy of
the adventure stor¬
ies. This is the de¬
tective novel which
one half of the read¬
ing public prefers
not to regard as
literature, but which
the other half often
reads to the exclu¬
sion of all else. Its
once undisputed
GERMAN VERSION of last publi- leading exponents,
shed work by H. G. Wells, Mind Conan Doyle (trans
at the End of its Tether. (This was lated in eight lan-
published in Zurich, Switzerland) guages in 1955) and
14
II.GWrLLS
DER GEIST
AMENDE
SEINER
MÖGLICH¬
KEITEN
V*nA.A*¿**».**tmUtoiUAai¿ti-fitA-anmitB^4*rAiri*tÍAki»
K*li.*litíAA,liA,mmA..*^*At>,*AmiiFt»'':4-VAAat**A,rí»<<
Simenon (12 languages) are now being outstripped by
others: Agatha Christie (translated in 13 countries; ten
different titles in Japan alone and three in Spain) and
Peter Cheyney (translated in nine countries) to mention
only two of the most popular writers at the present time.
Here is a significant fact. Of the six titles of literary
translations given in Thailand's bibliography for 1955,
three are detective novels of the Sherlock Holmes series by
Conan Doyle. The "'thriller's" world-wide success inspir¬
ed us to carry out a little research into the fate of two of
its pathfinders, Eugène Sue and Ponson de Terrail. They
were among the most widely translated authors of the
19th century and had' many devotees and imitators.
Brazil, Norway, Portugal and Yugoslavia, we found, were
still translating ' Ponson de Terrail while Finland and
Norway still read Eugène Sue.
Do films have any influence on translations? A great
deal, according to booksellers who find sales of great
ANTHOLOGY OF
JAPANESE LITERATURE
COMPILED AND EDITED BY DONALD KEENE
TRANSLATION OF GREAT WORKS into languages
of wider diffusion has been a Unesco activity since
1948. So far translations into five languagesArabic,
English, French, Persian and Spanishhave either been
published or are in preparation. Thirty volumes have
already appeared and 70 others are under preparation
(altogether they will cover 25 literatures). Above,
book jacket of the Anthology of Japanese Literature
in the Japanese series of Unesco's Collection of
Representative Works. The Unesco Courier will
devote part of a forthcoming issue to this Collection.
books increasing whenever they are made into successful
films. Does this mean that the best literary works will
have to depend on cinema box office successes to find
admirers? Will Cinemascope encourage reading? In view
of the many great works now being adapted for the cinema
we should soon know the answer.
Finally, we think it is worth while to list all the authors
given under the "Literature" column of the bibliography
for Iran, whose works were translated in 1955. The list is.
quite short: Honoré de Balzac (Le Père Goriot); Joseph
Bédier (Le Roman de Tristan et Yseult); Edward Brown
(A Literary History of Persia) ; Alphonse Daudet (Les
Femmes d'Artistes); Nicholas Gogol (Tarass Bulba);
Nathaniel Hawthorne (The Scarlet Letter); Victor Hugo
(Quatrevingt-treize and Les Travailleurs de la Mer) ; and
Friedrich Schiller (Wilhelm Tell). Eight names in all:
four Frenchmen, one German, one American, one English¬
man and one Russian.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1957
TIDBITS, ECCENTRICA AND OTHER MORSELS
Curious garb
Books have been bound in all
manner of shoddy and rich 'fabrics,
from bandana cotton and burlap
sacking to silk brocade and Venice
velvet, from homespun to satin and
from canvas to tapestry. Their
covers have been graced by even
more precious stuffs, studded with
jewels and inlaid with ivory, enamels,
filigree silver and mosaic leathers.
Even royal raiment has been used.
Several books in England were cover¬
ed with silk material from the waist¬
coats of King Charles I. (Bookmen's
Bedlam)
Stenographic versions
Abbreviated writing dates back to
the earliest efforts at recording in
ancient Egypt. Among early Christi¬
ans, St. Augustine and St. Jerome
employed a corps of stenographers.
Between 1600 and 1750 more than
200 shorthand systems were publish¬
ed. Today renditions of literary
works exist in more than fifty recog¬
nized shorthand systems the world
over. Among these works the Bible
takes leading place. Samuel Pepys'
unique picture of Restoration England
was written in shorthand in the
diary he kept between 1660 and 1669.
(Bookmen's Bedlam)
French favourites
According to a 1955 survey the
French read more books than the
Americans or the English and prefer
novels more than any other kind of
literature (72% of women and 51%
of men). Classics are as popular as
modern works and tastes differ only
slightly between old and young people.
Fifty-three per cent of readers like
both foreign and French books, 31%
prefer French authors and 16% like
foreign ones. (French Institute of
Public Opinion)
Picture parade
Colour 'films based on the best
contemporary children's picture books
have been attracting much interest
from publishers, educators, librarians
and psychologists in the United
States. The films, available for TV
programmes or for schools, libraries
and other institutions, aim to transfer
the book's dramatic and artistic
qualities directly from the printed
page to the screen. Picture and text
remain virtually unaltered, the cam¬
era exploring the movement created
by the artist in his illustrations, to
the accompaniment of the spoken
text and a specially written musical
score. (Unesco)
Miniature marvel
Earliest in age among tiny books is
the Offices of the Blessed Virgin
printed by Nicholas Jenson at Venice,
in 1475. Although this great typo¬
grapher produced many a larger
volume, none was more lovely than
this one, which has been called "a
miniature epitome of the whole art
of bookmaking". Ornamented with
three borders and many richly illu¬
minated letters, it was only two and
a quarter inches tall. It was printed
on vellum in red and black, with
twelve lines to the page, the morocco
sides richly tooled and painted.
(Bookmen's Bedlam)
25 million new readers
Bach year 25 million more people,
many of them adults, learn to read.
Present total of literate persons h,
about one thousand three hundred
million, or half the world's popula¬
tion. The proportion of regular
book readers varies according to coun¬
tries. In Western countries it is
estimated despite counter attrac¬
tions of the cinema, radio and TV
at around 60%. (Unesco)
Eighty miles of books
No one knows the exact number of
books in the library of the British
Museum, London, but it is believed
that there are about five million in
the sixty miles of shelves. A com¬
prehensive cataloguing was begun in
1931, but after 23 years, experts rea¬
lised that it would take another
82 years to finish the catalogue. At
the present tempo of work the com¬
plete catalogue will be ready in the
year 2036, and will run to 200 vol¬
umes. By that time the museum
bookshelves will have a total length
of 80 miles. (Unesco)
Goliaths of bookdom
Up the River Nile at Thebes, on two
massive walls of the second pylon of
the main temple of Rameses III, is
chiseled the largest "book" in all the
world. Its "pages" are 138 feet wide.
This ancient chronicle of triumph has
defied obliteration and oblivion for
more than 3,000 years. One of the
legendary giants of bookdom is the
Great Koran of the Samarkand
Palace courtyard, made about 1403.
The book has disappeared but its size
is suggested by the surviving stone
lectern on which it is said to have
rested. This measures seven and a
half feet by six and a half feet.
(Bookmen's Bedlam)
Shakespeare in Esperanto
Many great literary works have
been put into Esperanto. Hamlet
(Hamleto) was translated by Ludwig
Zamenhof, the Polish inventor of
Esperanto. Other translated Shakes¬
pearean plays include King Lear (La
Rego Lear). Midsummer Night's
Dream (Songo de Someromeza Nokto),
and the Merchant of Venice (La
Venecia Komercisto). Not only the
Bible, but the Psalms separately are
published in Esperanto. (Bookmen's
Bedlam)
Trust in books
A National Book Trust is being
created by the Government of India
to encourage production _ , ,
of good literature and I
make books available at I
moderate prices to libra- I
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
TIDBITS (Continued)
ries, educational institutions and the
public. Besides the classical litera¬
ture of India and books on Indian
art, the Trust will be responsible for
publishing translations of Important
works in foreign languages, and will
arrange for the translation of books
from one Indian language into an¬
other. (Unesco)
Workers' playtime
One day last year, workers in a
Tennessee (U.S.) factory found that
illustrated story books had been plac¬
ed near their rest rooms. A sign
above said: "Take one home to read
to your children. They will have a
good time and so will you." All the
books have since been borrowed and
read in turn by scores of families.
One man commented: "If I'd had
books like these when I was a child
perhaps I would have taken to read¬
ing and made more of myself". The
experiment is now being extended
to other factories. (Unesco)
An idea for others
To overcome difficulties Norwegian
authors meet in getting their books
translated and published in other
countries, Norway has launched a
scheme under which specimen works
of fiction are translated into English
for submission to foreign publishers.
Because foreign publishers' readers
"hardly ever know any of the Scan¬
dinavian languages" says the Norwe¬
gian Authors' Association, "'books by
these authors are filed away without
even being opened". Thus, until now
choice of books for translation has
been arbitrary and has not truly
reflected the trends of modern Nor¬
wegian literature. (Unesco)
Recipe for wisdom
It is said in China that there are
seven essential occupations for the
cultured person: books, chess, music,
painting, poetry, wine and flowers.
Towards books there are two general
attitudes. The first is respect for the
printed word. Thus a person can
usually win an argument or dominate
a discussion by citing a passage from
a well-known book, as for example,
the Confucian classics. The second
attitude is one of reasonable scepti¬
cism, well summed up by Mencius,
who is quoted as saying: "If you
believed entirely in books, it were bet¬
ter to have no books at all." (Unesco)
Kingdom for a book
Joao de Barros, a 16th century Por¬
tuguese historian and author, wrote
a work entitled Crónica do Empera¬
dor Clarimundo in 1522 and dedicated
it to King Joao III of Portugal. He
received as royal recompense the
entire province o'f Maranhao (part of
Brazil) covering 177,000 square miles,
or about the size of France. This
book and another by de Barros, a
History of Asia, inspired the Portu¬
guese poet Camoens to compose Os
Lusiadas of the world's great
literary works. (Bookmen's Bedlam)
Multi-millionaires
The world's great libraries with
collections of one million or more
books include: The British Museum
(5,000,000) ; Library of CQngress, Wash¬
ington (10,000,000) ; Bibliothèque Na¬
tionale, Paris (approx. 6 million);
Öffentlich Wissenschafftliche Biblio-
tek, Berlin (2.9 million) ; National-
bibliotek, Vienna (1.5 million) ; Biblio¬
thèque Royale, Brussels (2 million) ;
National Diet, Tokyo (3,5 million);
New York Public Library (6 million);
Lenin State Library, Moscow (report¬
ed to contain 15 million volumes);
Public Library, Leningrad (about
10 million volumes) ; U.S.S.R. Academy
of Sciences Library (8 millions).
(Unesco)
One-book library
Two remarkable library contrasts:
As oí June 30, 1954, the Library of
Congress in Washington had 10,155,307
books and pamphlets, and 14,282,594
manuscripts, letters and written
documents. In India there is a library
that 'holds only one book. Built at
Amritsar of costly marble, copper and
gold leaf, it enshrines the holy book
of the Sikhs. (Bookmen's Bedlam)
Verbosity in verse
The Bodleian Library in Oxford,
England, possesses the longest occi¬
dental poem ever written more than
68,000 lines. Written in 1610 by
Robert Barret, and entitled: The
Sacrèd War, an History conteyning
the Christian Conquest of the Holy
Land from 568 till 1588: Reduced into
a Poem Epike, it treated the Cru¬
sades in rhymed quatrains. Other
bards pale beside such sustained
poetic flight: Homer's Iliad (15,773
lines) and Odyssey (12,107); Dante's
Divine Comedy. (14,533); Milton's
Paradise Lost (10,565).
Longest sentence in the English
language was written in 1675 by
Edward Phillips in his Preface to
Theatrum Poetarum. An elaborate
weave of clauses, it runs to a total of
1.012 words. (Bookmen's Bedlam)
Books from the U.S.A.
According to the new American
monthly publication, "Books from
the U.S.A.", about 10,000 new books
and 2,500 new editions were published
in the U.S.A. during 1955. Of these,
works of fiction lead with 2,073 follow¬
ed by juvenile books with 1,485, reli¬
gious works (849), biographies (833)
and science books (801). Fewest books
were published on agriculture and
gardening (168), philology (168) and
music (103).
Continental model
When a public library was opened
in Medellin, Colombia, in 1954, it
created quite a stir. It was not only
the city's first public library, but also
the first in Colombia and one of the
few in the whole of Latin America.
It was set up as a pilot project by the
Colombian Government and Unesco,
to encourage similar deve¬
lopments elsewhere in
Latin America. During
1956 it had 285,000 visitors Pa?e 3A
Cont'd
on
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Istituto di Patologia del Libro photos
Story of Rome's Book Hospital
The Unesco Courier. February 1957
Scrolls from the ashes of Pompeii,
ancient Egyptian papyri, Indian
tablets, books and manuscripts
from every country and every century
all rest side by side in a remarkable
Institution in the heart of Rome, al¬
most unknown to the general public.
The scrolls and books all have one
thing in common. They have been
victims of a variety of afflictions.
They have survived fire, floods,
bullets, bombs, chemical attack, des¬
tructive insects or just plain old age.
Their rescuers: a group of scientists
in Rome's unique "Book Hospital"
(officially the Institute of Book Pa¬
thology) headed by Professor Gio¬
vanni Muzzloli.
On display at the "hospital's" mu¬
seum are parchments burned to a
crisp, volumes buried for years in the
sea, books attacked by mould or eaten
away by tiny insects. One heap of
documents, reduced to a mass of
pulp, was recovered from a sunken
submarine; others were plucked from
blazing buildings. Restoring these
objects seemed almost Impossible but
the Book Hospital took on the job and
in each case succeeded.
Books are the prey not only of
external factors such as insects,
mould or fire. Some ancient books
were doomed from the day they were
printed. Thus in Sicily long' ago,
book publishers and paper makers
were proud of the beautiful volumes
they produced on what they thought
SAVED FROM
FIRE & WATER
INSECT VANDALS which have feasted
on the pages of valuable books get
short shrift In "gas chamber" of Rome's
Institute of Book Pathology. Protected
by respirator, a specialist (above) carries
out book disinfection. This book hos¬
pital has a microbiological laboratory
entirely devoted to the study of bacteria
and mould damage. Below, taking a
sample of micro-organisms from a dam¬
aged book. Studies of these organisms
will establish the exact reasons for the
damage, will help scientists to devise
methods of protection and restoration.
was top-quality paper. What they
didn't know was that the paper was
manufactured with water which came
from a stream extremely rich in
copper. The copper penetrated the
paper, and with time all the pages
turned black and brittle. The Book
Hospital has devised a chemical treat¬
ment which whitens the paper and
revives paper texture.
Many old books were once printed
with inks containing acids which
slowly destroyed the pages. The
process can now be arrested by the
use of chemical baths which have the
effect of neutralizing the acid.
In one room of the Book Hospital
museum stands an apparatus invent¬
ed by Antonio Piaggio in 1773 which
can accomplish the apparently im¬
possible task of restoring a book
which has been completely burned.
The pages, reduced to
curled ashes, are flattened
piece by piece and rein¬
forced with silk threads. next Pa8e
17
Cont'd
on
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1957
SAVED FROM
FIRE & WATER
(Continued)
This work, requiring inexhaustible
patience, has given astonishing re¬
sults. In Italy, where the loss of
priceless documents by fire has not
been an infrequent occurrence, the
woik is considered of the utmost
importance. In 1904, fire destroyed
the Library of Turin; in 1908 it gutted
the University Library of Messina; and
during the two world wars losses were
particularly heavy. Thousands of
volumes were burned or cut to pieces
by shrapnel during the last war
alone, among them treasures from'
the National Library of Naples and
the archives of Monte Cassino mo¬
nastery which were reduced to rubble.
Many of these incalculable treasures,
transformed into shapeless tatters,
have now been rescued and restored
by the Book Hospital.
Most of the delicate work is carried
out in the Institute's special labora¬
tories. Here craftsmen unsew the
pages from their ancient bindings,
place them in separate frames and
slide them carefully into chemical
solutions for bleaching and whitening.
Other chemical baths give the paper
new life and flexibility. Torn pages
are carefully pasted together and
covered with a clear varnish. Every
chemical or other type of material
used is specially prepared according
to the nature and state of the object
treated. When required, damaged
pages are consolidated with a piece
of gossamer-thin silk fabric. After
each part of the book has received ap¬
propriate treatment all the elements
are re-assembled, re-sewn and re¬
bound, the bindings too having been
carefully repaired.
Often, a particularly fragile speci¬
men is photographed. The original
document is then carefully stored to
protect it from further deterioration
and full-sized replicas or microfilm
reproductions made available for con¬
sultation. The Institute possesses a
highly specialized photo laboratory
equipped to bring out faded or va¬
nished writing, reveal ancient texts
overlaid by others on parchments, or
verify the authenticity of seals and
stamps on bocks and documents.
A microbiological laboratory is en¬
tirely reserved for the study of the
depradatioiis caused by bacteria and
mould, another to that of insect dam¬
age. Chemical and physical labo¬
ratories study paper resistance, and
tensile strength, paper bleaching and
washing, and are continually analyz¬
ing and experimenting with various
printing inks.
The Institute of Book Pathology
possesses a library containing an im¬
portant collection of specialized books
on the graphic arts, paper (some
manuscripts date back to the 13th
century), and on the art of preserving
and "healing" documents. It pub¬
lishes a regular information bulletin
describing experiments in process and
research carried out both at the
Institute and other centres.
18
stituto di Patología del Libro photos
BOOK SURGEONS in Rome Institute accomplish some seemingly impossible feats of restoration.
They can transform a torn and warped piece of leather into a handsome binding (above), exactly as it
appeared when new. Under delicate treatment, the charred and tattered pages of a burned book.
once again become legible (below, right). Even a document completely blacked out by long immer¬
sion in sea water can be restored to some semblance of its former self (below, left). Many valuable
volumes reduced to tatters during the last war have been restored by the Rome Book Hospital.
1"V>
" -C, <}-~/V -*-^**rf .'it^, id, fir*- [
frr-r- > h- f fy
CI -M^^TaW J- 4~aJI
¿V»^^Sff A& f~AAÍ,
«V, %~*r- >
A-- ll^-l	A-'
Ihf-i	A ' *^&A*n4f r\ (* A~~ri	 W .
^ =j$T V^. -»- * -Jj3 ', Ja-ïj
f~r4- aG>^ J* Ife- *- *L-r fa
Ô j."ÎW^-r-_*(-+ **-»- f - Í-? f-A-,r
' ?*-» f-tí a*1
P-*- Jf für C*y+<A0y+, «*-#»
IK«
2
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
WORLD
PRODUCTION:
5,000 MILLION
BOOKS A YEAR
Upwards of five thousand million copies of books are
produced annually throughout the world, but large
as this figure seems it represents only two books
per person per year. About three-quarters of all books
published come from ten countries, and half of all our
books are used in schools while a large part of the
remainder are housed in public or institutional libraries.
These striking facts come from a new Unesco publica¬
tion Books for All by R.E. Barker, deputy secretary of the
Publishers' Association of Great Britain, who was commis¬
sioned by Unesco to survey problems confronting the inter¬
national book trade.
A dearth of printing and publishing facilities In large
areas of the world, coupled with a maze of obstacles at
national frontiers impedes the full production and free
circulation of books. The difficulties range from tariff
and currency restrictions to inadequate copyright protec¬
tion, from a paucity of translation services to high trans¬
port costs.
The Unesco survey reveals that statistics normally
provided rarely show the actual output of books in any
given country, that is, the total number of copies printed,
as opposed to the total number of "titles" the statistical
unit of book production; Titles do however illustrate the
variety of books produced in individual countries through¬
out the world.
Mr. Barker's study is laced with many statistical tables
and pictographs which show some surprising situations:
Thus, as seen in table (right), very few countries publish
more than 10,000 titles a year and not many come into the
major producer group with more than 4,000 or 5,000.
Belgium, China, Czechoslovakia, German Federal Republic,
Italy, Japan, Netherlands, Poland and Yugoslavia are to
be found in this high range mainly because of the large
number of translations they publish.
The Netherlands publishes the most titles in proportion
' to its population, with tiny Switzerland only slightly less.
In contrast, major producers such as the U.S.A., the
U.S.S.R. and India come low on the per capita list.
Many a first novel never sells more than 2,500 copies
even in countries of high literacy and extensive book
production. Rarely does it exceed 5,000 copies, and only a
foolhardy publisher incurs the expense of regularly bind¬
ing the entire printing of a first novel. Novels of establish¬
ed authors sometimes run into editions of hundreds of
thousands of copies but these are a small minority.
General works of non-fiction may occasionally reach
almost fabulous editions (Heyerdahl's Kon Tiki is an
example; for others see U.S. best sellers on page 34) but on
an average the number is small.
The Unesco survey reveals that nearly 22 per cent of the
world's books are in the English language, followed by
Russian (17%), German (15%), Japanese (12%), French
(10%), Spanish (7.5%), Italian (6.7%), Portuguese (5.4%),
and Chinese (4.8%).
The United Kingdom is the world's largest book exporter.
20
The U.S.A. is second, France third, Netherlands fourth,
German Federal Republic fifth, Spain sixth, and Switz¬
erland seventh. In only 12 cases does the value of Inter¬
national book exchange exceed $2 million. U.S. exports to
Canada are by far the largest in the world to a single
country, being three times greater than the nearest
"rival"the U.K.'s exports to Australia. Other Important
exports: U.K. to the United States, South Africa, Canada,
New Zealand and India, in that order; U.S. exports to the
Philippines and the U.K.; French exports to the Benelux
countries; Netherlands exports to Indonesia and Benelux;
German exports to Switzerland and Austria, and Swiss
exports to Germany. Spanish exports to Argentina are
not far behind.
One of the most striking postwar developments has been
the rapid expansion of the German book trade. It has
already gone far towards regaining its pre-war eminence.
The Swiss book trade, which gained international promin¬
ence after the rise of Nazism in Germany, seems not to
have suffered by this post-war German expansion. In
fact, the German-speaking countries import more of each
other's books each year just as the French and English-
speaking countries do.
In Spanish America, only Mexico, Argentina, Chile, are
considerable book producers. They export in quantity to
most other Latin-American countries as well as to Spain
and the U.S.A. Norway, Sweden and Denmark export
regularly to each other, publication in other Scandinavian
languages being a common feature of their book trade.
While the volume of the international book trade is
considerable, there is comparatively little movement
towards those economically underdeveloped countries
where books are most needed. Much of present world
trade in books follows traditional channels. With current
advances in book production, translation and transport
new channels could be developed which could bring the
heritage of the world's literature to vast new audiences.
The crux of the problem of providing reading material
for the underdeveloped nations was clearly stated by a
committee of educational specialists convened by Unesco
Giants
Country
U.S.S.R	
Japan
United Kingdom	
German Fed. Republic 	
U.S.A	
France
Italy
Netherlands 	
Poland
Thailand
German Democratic Republic
Yugoslavia	
Spain
Sweden
Portugal	
Czechoslovakia	
Belgium
Total
number
of
titles
54 732(1)
21 653
19 962
15837
12 589(2)
II 793
9 320
7 353
7 199
5 475
5 359
5 105
4812
4 756
4 754
4 399
4212
Number
of first
editions
?
13 042
14 192
12 701
10 226
î
?
4 260
5 823
?
?
4 659
?
3 912
4 472
f
3 706
This table includes all countries which published more than 4,000 titles.
Exceptions are India and the People's Republic of China for which
Unesco has no precise figures for 1955. The 17 countries included in
this table published a total of 175,930 titles, or a large proportion
of world production, the 1955 production figures for 53 countries
being 2 1 4,360. Figures given cover both books and pamphlets with the
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
in 1951: "The difficulty is not so much in printing, since
there are various machines and techniques in existence
which are designed to produce books and other printed
matter in small quantity... The difficulty is to find or train
competent authors or translators; to obtain supplies of
materials (such as paper, type and macninery)... to dis¬
tribute the finished product under conditions of great
distances and poor communications; and above all to find
the money."
In India, for example, where the world's largest illiterate
population administered by a central government is found,
the basic need is to make the population literate in Hindi
and in the vernacular languages. The first five year
national development plan includes a mass education
programme for children and adults.
Among the reading materials needed: textbooks and
"follow-up" reading materials. Many literacy campaigns
have failed because such materials have been lacking.
The basic need is a link between the elementary primer and
advanced books, periodicals and other publications which
are normally read for pleasure and profit.
Unesco is helping to encourage writers and translators
in India by establishing "literary workshops" and offering
awards in literature. Prizes are also offered by the Indian
Government for original works in native languages, par¬
ticularly- Hindi. Unesco is now studying successful
projects in South-east Asia, the South Pacific and Latin
America, and is developing an advisory service to produc¬
ing agencies on such matters as low-cost printing of good
quality books and their distribution.
The world's fast reducing illiteracy rate is one of the
most promising aspects noted in Mr. Baker's report.
The development of photo-typesetting to allow rapid
composition of Asiatic "scripts together with increasing
use of modern high speed printing presses In the under¬
developed countries suggest that the next decade will
witness a substantial increase in books produced.
Among the many barriers to the free flow of books the
imposition of import duties is perhaps the most formid¬
able. Two-thirds of the countries of the world apply
import licensing to books, and there are many other
The Unesco Courier. February 1957
irksome formalities which representations made by
Unesco and other bodies have to some extent removed.
Twelve per cent of the world's countries levy import duties,
40 per cent charge internal taxes and 70 per cent impose
currency restrictions on books.
The U.S.A. charges a duty of five per cent ad valorem
on books in the English language, books in other languages
being duty-free. Largely because of this, Canada main¬
tains a 10 per cent levy on U.S. books though none is
imposed on British books. Austria charges importers a
51 per cent "equalization" tax; Spain and Denmark both
impose duties on books in their languages; Italy charges
13 per cent on books bound in leather.
"The revenue collected by these duties can hardly offset
the cost of collecting them," Mr. Barker comments. "For
example, the annual return from the U.S. Government's
import duties on books in the English language cannot
exceed $500,000less than 0.000002 per cent of the total
national income. France's 8 per cent tax on the invoice
value of imported books yields only about 200 million
francs, or 0.00002 per cent of the total national income.
Belgium's 4i per cent taxe de transmission can hardly
balance the cost of collecting it."
As Mr. Barker remarks, "The principle behind these
duties' is thus anachronistic and unreal...
What then is the excuse for these barriers?" (See also
Unesco's manual Trade Barriers to Knowledge and article
"Violins taxed by the kilogram" in Unesco Courier. July-
Aug. 1956-U.S. edition Sept.)
Public libraries are at present the biggest buyers of
many general books and in some countries they purchase
one half of all works distributed. Since no library can
contain all books, a comprehensive. service for internation¬
al library loans has been built up. In addition to loans
there are many arrangements for exchanging publications.
Unesco's Clearing House for Libraries has working arran¬
gements with centres in almost 50 countries. At present
69 countries exchange 35,000 new titles annually in a
plethora of agreements. Unesco is now working on a
single, universal convention to cover all publication
exchanges.
of the book world in 1955
Percentage by si bject of total number of titles
Gen.
Works
Philosophy Religion
Social
Sciences
Philology
Pure
Science
Applied
Science
Fine
Arts
Literature
History-
Geography
Un.
spec.
(0) (1) (2) (3) (4) (5) (6) (7) (8) (9)
3 ? I 17 3 7 52 4 12 î 2
2 3 2 12 3 3 14 5 27 A 25
_ 2 5 16 4 6 16 6 35 10
3 2 6 28 2 6 13 5 26 8 1
3 3 7 9 1 6 14 5 37 15
1 4 7 9 ? 8 20 5 35 II
4 3 5 21 5 4 13 7 29 9
3 2 6 9 19 14 7 6 14 4 16
4 1 1 19 2 II 34 3 18 7
69 1 5 2 4 1 1 15 2
2 1 3 17 4 7 25 7 24 10
2 1 1 27 2 8 20 8 21 7 3
7 2 7 II 3 3 8 5 43 1 1
2 1 6 9 5 10 16 5 34 12
3 2 6 18 3 7 25 9 17 10
	_ ? ? 35 2 4 28 8 23 1
II 2 7 15 4 5 12 7 29 8 ~~
exception of those for the U.S.A. and Italy which refer to books only.
(1) If only those works "placed on the market" In the U.S.S.R. were
taken into account, the total production would be 30,81 I titles.
(2) These figures relate solely to U.S. commercial book production
(chiefly the Industry publishing books intended for the general public)
and ignore a large part of book production (government and university
publications, those published by churches and organizations, and most
of the reports, theses, laboratory and working papers that appear.
They do, however, include "pocket books" (an Important part of U.S.
book production which in I 953 exceeded the production of hard cover
books), in all kinds of formats, providing they have 65 pages or more.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
ANCHO» A23
o
85c
MAGIC,
SCIENCE and |
RFLIGION |
to '{ AND OTHER
'i ESSAYS
rnÏP
ROBERT
REDFIELO
POCKET BOOKS
A coin in the
slot and out
pops Plato
by Bertha Gaster
0jSJ#j$^
Any Londoner passing the Holy Trinity Church in the
Euston Road early in 1935 might well have been
taken aback on observing a steady stream of
packages disappearing down a mysterious chute in the
graveyard, apparently into the bowels of the church.
Venturing inside, he would have been still more disconcert¬
ed to hear sounds of sinister activity coming from the
crypt. There, against walls panelled with marble slabs
giving the names and "in memorium" inscriptions of long
defunct parishioners, he would have found bales piled
ceiling-high, and discovered a man busily checking invoice
books in a disused family vault, with piles of money being
counted in another.
If half-forgotten tales of smuggling, body-snatching
and counterfeiting dens flashed across his mind, he could
hardly be blamed. He was not to know that Trinity
Church was being used as the improvised headquarters of
:a new experiment in publishing which would help to
change the face of book buying and selling over the
greater part of the English-speaking world in the course
of the next twenty years, and make a small black and
white penguin the symbol of this revolution.
The idea of cheap reprints of more expensive editions
was by no means new in 1935 when the Penguin Series
was first planned. Something of the sort had existed as
far back as the period of ancient Rome. According to
Martial, the Roman satirist, who lived in the first century
A.D., a copy of his epigrams was selling for five denarii
at Atrectur's, while round the corner it could be got at
Tryphon's for only half a denarius. And Tryphon was
making a good thing out of it too, Martial
assures us.
Not very long alter the arrival of printing
in England came cheap books "chapbooks"
for the masses, badly printed little pamphlets
of popular stories and farces, sold by wander¬
ing pedlars, such as Aytolycus sold to the
eager villagers in Shakespeare's Winter's
Tale. The Puritan masterpiece of John
Bunyan Pilgrim's Progress in the seven¬
teenth century was not only the first
European best seller, but perhaps the only
work of great literature that began as cheap
reading for the cottage and the servants'
hall, and ended in de luxe bindings 'for the
connoisseur.
The first great era of cheap reprints,
however, came into being in the nineteenth
century with the industrial revolution. There
22
was a fresh reading public In the rising middle class, and
later, as popular education spread, in a newly-literate
working class. There were also the technical means of
-satisfying their demands through the recently-invented,
machine-made paper in which wood pulp replaced the less
abundant and more expensive rags, as well as through
cheaper railway and canal transport.
Two tendencies can be discerned from the very begin¬
ning in the first cheap editions that came off the press in
the eighteen-twenties. The first in England, such ' as
Constable's '"Miscellany," Murray's "'Family Library" and
Colburn and Bentley's "Novels", were followed a few years
later by the parchment-coloured Tauchnitz reprints of
English-language fiction from Germany, now familiar all
over Europe for well over a century. They may be roughly
divided into the educational and the ephemeral.
Constable the publisher, summed up the ideal of the
educational In his phrase "literature for the million". It
is no accident, for instance, that in that development
period of working-men's colleges and evening schools
there was close co-operation between the famous cheap
reprint firm of Reclam in Germany with its Universal
Bibliothek, selling over 31 million copies of classics and
philosophy, at approximately ten cents a volume, between
1867 and 1917, and the German Society for Popular Educa¬
tion (Gesellschaft für Volksbildung) , which set up 137,000
libraries in the same time; nor that the first paperbound
books in the United States were sponsored by the Boston
Society for the Diffusion of Knowledge.
And the ephemeral? The book that was meant to be
read and chucked away; the type of light
fiction sold in the 1840's on the newly-open¬
ed bookstalls in the newly-opened railway
stations for a new type of journeysitting
in comfort in a railway compartment.
Note the distinction. It is still valid
today, in a world-wide paperbook industry
running into hundreds of millions of copies
annually. The two types of reading overlap
and merge at the edges, but the difference is
still there classics, fine literature, informa¬
tive and cultural books this way; sensational
fiction, thrillers, westerns, that. "Heavy
going" snorts one set of readers; "trash"
retorts the other. But the pocket book has
provided a bridge.
The real revolution came in two stages.
The paperback as we know itpocket book
is the more exact descriptionbegan in 1935
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
when the three Lane brothers in England, on a nominal
capital of £100, took a gamble with cheap reprints of good
modern books. Their attractive format was something
new the publishers were determined to illustrate that
good printing and attractive lay-out cost no more than
bad. The striking covers in two-colour horizontal bands
not forgetting the little black and white penguin were
new, and easily recognisable; the size was new, and has
become the standard size for nearly all its successors.
And newest of all was the price 6d, the price of a packet
of cigarettes.
The booksellers shook their heads, but the gamble came
off. By 1937 Penguin titles had reached the hundred mark,
and the subsidiary ventures began original commissioned
'work, like the Pelican Specials on Spain, and Germany
and Mussolini and so forth, which exercised a political
influence comparable to Gollancz's Left Book Club; the
children's Puffins, the books on modern art, archaeology,
literary criticism, as well as the Penguin Classics, which
sold three quarters of a million copies of their translation
of the Odyssey.
In 1935 most of the Penguin titles were fiction; in 1956
less than half the ten million sold were fiction; the
others of all sorts were published with the "explicit
intention of providing the public with the varied pleasures
and discoveries of the mind". And of the ten million
copies sold in 1955, as many as five million went to the
overseas market.
A certain number of Penguins were in fact exported to
the United States before the war, and it is generally
agreed that they gave the first impetus to that country's
now colossal industry. For the second and determining
stage in the revolution which
made the cheap paperback a
new and dynamic phenome¬
non in U.S. publishing, and
also spread to many countries
of the world, began in 1939
when Robert F. de Graff start¬
ed the first, mass production
of modern U.S. paperbacks.
Immense thought went into
selecting a suitable name; the
one finally chosen was sim¬
plicity itself "Pocket Books
Inc."; and pocket books has
become the generic name by
which all types of cheap pa¬
perbacks are known in the
United States. Most of these
pocket books are unabridged
reproductions of copyrighted
books originally sold at two
and a half to three dollars. They run from 25 to 75 cents,
generally much the same in format and size, the covers
of lacquered paper nearly always carrying a garish illus¬
tration designed to catch the passing eye. America is
flooded. with them.
Consider some of the figures. In 1939 Pocket Books
produced 34 titles and over a million and a half copies.
For 1953, estimates for sixteen publishing firms indicated
1,061 titles and no less than 292 million copies. Over
5,000 titles, both reprints and originals, covering the clas¬
sics, fiction, science, travel, philosophy, crafts, etc., are
now available. In 1949 about the same number of paper¬
backed books and hard cover books were published; in
1953 the pocket books outstripped the hard cover books by
about 100 million copies.
The size of each edition is equally something new in
the publishing world. An average edition of an ordinary
thriller or western runs to something between 150,000 and
200,000 copies; best sellers may reach several million.
Pocket Books, for instance, recently announced that by
the end of 1957 they expect to have sold 75 million copies
of Erie Gardner's mystery novels; the stories of Luke
Short, a popular writer of Westerns, amount already to
8 million copies. More serious writers also run into fan¬
tastic figures; reprints of Erskine Caldwell's novels top the
37 million mark, and one of the latest best sellers, Bonjour
.Tristesse by the young French writer Françoise Sagan,
has already sold one million six hundred thousand copies.
The total amount paid for reprint rights in 1954 has been
estimated at between five and six million dollars.
Pocket books are Big Business to-day. And this is
largely due to two new factors technical advances in
printing, and mass methods in sale and distribution.
Enormous book presses have been evolved for pocket
The Unesco Courier. February 1957
books, rolling them off from
rubber plates at the rate of
12.000 copies for a 192-page
book every hour. Special bind¬
ing methods eliminate the
expensive sewing process, new
glues give added strength to
the spine.
The second factor, however,
is more important. Instead of
being sold like other books,
through bookshops and book¬
stalls, pocket books were treat¬
ed as merchandise, and are
sold like magazines through a
network of wholesalers to any
unspeciallzed outlet that pre¬
sents itself news-stands, drug
stores, stationery shops, supermarkets, chain stores, big
department stores, hotels, airports, railway stations, as
well as the conventional bookshops 100,000 outlets
instead of 1,500.
Between 30 to 50 million pocket books all over the
country are constantly on display in racks supplied by the
publishers, jostling for space in the 10-cent stores, or
among the ice-cream and coca-colas, cigarettes, watches
and what have you of the small town store, changed
every so often as new titles come in, and picked up by the
passing customer with his cigarettes or his newspaper.
A 25 cent piece popped into a slot machine at an airport
will produce a pocket book; bookshops devote special
space to them or set up branches on the university campus
to sell the text pocket books and "recommended reading"
that are being produced every day in ever greater quan¬
tity; public libraries are beginning to use them, with
"Put N'Take" shelves where the reader puts a pocket book
in for every one he takes out; the army and navy buy
large quantities, and in some of the big towns special all-
pocket-books shops have been set up for the discriminat¬
ing reader unable to find exactly what he wants in the
mass displays on drug store racks.
The vast size of the industry brings its own problems.
Some are on the way to being solved. Booksellers no
longer fear their competition; nor, on the whole, do
publishers of hard cover books. They no longer believe,
with Dr. Johnson, who had little faith in cheap editions,
that such publishers are "Robin Hoods, who rob the rich
in order to give to the poor".
Nowadays, indeed, the reprint
rights on a serious book first
commissioned and published
by a pocket book publisher
may well be secured by a hard
cover publisher for later repro¬
duction, thus reversing the
usual process. Not long ago in
England, the experiment was
tried of bringing out hard
cover and pocket book editions
simultaneously. It was not a
success, but "don't ask me
why" said one O'f the publish¬
ers. "Covers dull? Book¬
sellers didn't like the idea?
Paperbacks anyway taking a
dive just then? You could
take your pick".
But competition grows as more firms come into the
market, the supply of suitable new books is after all limit¬
ed, and the get-rich-qulck publisher is not after quality.
"'A good book is one thing, a quick seller another" said a
cynical publisher, and many claim that serious literature
tends to be swamped in the flood of mysteries with a
quick turnover, and lost In the ever more sensational
covers which are used even for serious fiction. Some
jackets certainly distort the contents. A publisher at an
American book trade meeting recalled that a book
presented at a recent House of Representatives enquiry
into pornography had the following line on the jacket
'"Take me, take me' she said". "Actually" he explained,
"what she wanted was to be taken of Philadelphia. That
was distortion."
In 1953 it was estimated that the total
production of pocket books in the United
States included 51.3 per cent general fiction, .
18 per ce nt mysteries, slightly over 18 per cent |
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
HEMINGWAY, FAULKNER, MAUGHAM :
THE BIG U.S.S.R. BOOK NEWS FOR 1957
VS**'
Ki.
n3J*
^£-"
PASSION FOR BOOKS is so great
in the U.S.S.R. that overcrowded
bookstores, especially those in Mos¬
cow, are unable to cope with the
rush, and make use of services of
street vendors, whose stocks are
soon snapped up. Moscow, Lenin¬
grad and other great cities regu¬
larly organize "poetry days" when
poets visit the bookshops to read
their poems, meet their admirers
and autograph copies of their
works. Right, Serge Smlrnov, a
Moscow poet, reads his verses in
Bookshop No. 6. (All Moscow's
bookshops are .numbered). The
Inscription behind him reads:
"Poetry Day. Works ofSoviet poets".
Left, bookstall in Soviet village.
Photos Soviet Information Service, Paris
A foreign visitor to the Soviet Union last year expressed
surprise at the large number of street vendors he saw
selling books on a commission basis for the over¬
crowded bookstores of Moscow. The street vendors are
almost as common as the ice cream stands, he reported,
adding : "Russia today is a nation of readers, and book
production, although immensely increased since the
Second World War, has not yet begun to satisfy the
demands."
How much of a demand there is and how much pro¬
duction is increasing can be gleaned from some of the
latest information on Soviet book production and book
translations which has reached Unesco. Figures for a
single year are staggering ; those 'for the 38-year period
from 1918 to 1955 (since the Soviet regime came into
being) are almost astronomic.
In 1955, according to official U.S.S.R. book industry
reports, 54,732 titles of books were published in the Soviet
Union, and copies printed topped the one thousand million
mark. During the same year, Japan (the world's second
largest book producer) published 21,653 titles or less than
half the number. Between 1918 and 1955 over 1,268,000
titles were published in the U.S.S.R., in editions totalling
more than 18 thousand million copies.
Soviet translation figures are almost as impressive :
14,580 titles by 1,730 foreign authors with a total of over
371 million copies printed during the past 38 years. For
1955 alone, Unesco's latest volume of Index Translationum
lists 4,282 translated works published, by far the highest
of any country and more than double the figure of
Germany, which is in second place.
Today the book industry of the Soviet Union leads all
countries of the world both in number of titles published
and in number of translated works produced.
A large percentage of Soviet translation figures is made
up of Russian-language works published in the many
languages of the U.S.S.R., and of translations from these
languages into Russian. The production of many language
versions 'for internal consumption has always been an
24
important part of the Soviet book industry. In regular
use are 80 chief languages, and some 140 language groups
are recognized. Each of the 16 Republics has its own
official language. In the past 38 years books have been
published in 122 languages, and in 59 languages in 1955
alone. Books have been translated into tongues ranging
from Uzbek to Kazakh, but the most important are
Russian, Ukrainian, Georgian, Lithuanian, Latvian and
Armenian, in that order.
As early as 1927 the Soviet Commissariat of Education
decided that education should be given as far as possible
in the vernacular. Where Russian was not the mother
tongue it was to be the compulsory second language. By
1935 teaching was being conducted in more than 80 lan¬
guages, and the various publishing houses were issuing
books in all these languages as well as publishing works
in various foreign ones.
Libraries best customers
In the Soviet Union, where publishing houses are State-
or union-owned, the principal houses are co-ordinated
under the Ministry of Culture. An important producer
in the country is the Writers' Union, which has its own
publishing house for new books. The most successful
publications of the Soviet Writers' Union are reprinted
in mass editions by the State Literary Publishers. Most
Soviet publishing firms are "central institutions" which
have headquarters in Moscow and maintain provincial
branches, although some are local or are centred in
provincial capitals.
A large part of book distribution is handled by a Ministry
of Culture organization, the Central Book Sales Adminis¬
tration, which sends the publishers' lists to the 24,000 book
sellers in the country and supplies orders. Another outlet
is the "Book Post", a department of the Post Office, which
supplies public libraries and bookstalls and runs a sub¬
scription scheme whereby individual buyers can order
books and pay on delivery at their local post office.
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1957
Libraries buy more than half of all books published in
the U.S.S.R.
Centred in Moscow are the three major translation
houses in the Union, each specializing in a particular
field. The Foreign Literature Publishers deals exclusively
with modern writers who are translated into Russian and
other Soviet languages. Its production is not limited to
literary works but ranges over the entire field of non-
It is this publishing house which has undertaken
the translation and publication of a Russian-language
edition of The Unesco Courier (see inside back cover).
The State Literary Publishers is the big classics
producer both Russian classics appearing in Russian
and translations of Russian and foreign classics into
Soviet languages. Thousands of Russian classics were
destroyed by the last war and the publishing house work¬
ed overtime for years to restore the supply. The third
major translating house is the Foreign Languages Pub¬
lishers which is limited to works translated from the
Russian into languages other than those of the Soviet
Union. The U.S.S.R. is a major book exporter, and most
of its exported books are printed in foreign languages.
Many of these foreign-language books are also used for
internal consumption (see below).
The people of the Soviet Union have so great a passion
for things cultural that it is said they will read any good
book they can lay their hands on. The works of Russian
authors such as Pushkin, Gorki, Leon Tolstoy, Chekov
Gogol and Mayakowsky are so popular that they have been
printed in editions running into millions of copies. Scores
of foreign authors have been no less successful. Victor
Hugo, Jack London, Mark Twain, Balzac, Jules Verne,
Dickens, O. Henry and Maupassant; to name only a few
have been favourites for many years and their translated
works have been published in editions totalling many
millions of copies.
Most translated of all foreign authors are the French,
followed by the Americans, the British and the Germans,
in that order. . Between 1918 and 1954, nearly 77 million
copies of French authors in translation appeared (the
volumes would fill a bookshelf running from Paris to Ber¬
lin) as well as over 50 million copies of translations of
American writers, 38 million volumes by British authors,
and 36 million by German writers.
Among French writers, Victor Hugo is by far the most
popular with over nine million copies of his books printed
in translation during the past 38 years. Charles Per-
rault's Fairy Tales is close behind having topped the eight
million mark, while Balzac, Jules Verne and Maupassant
are almost tied at six million copies, although Balzac has
a slight edge over his two compatriots. (For the names of
the 1955 leaders, see page 10)
The most popular U.S. writer in the past 38 years has
been Jack London, with Mark Twain and O. Henry close
behind him. Among British authors, Dickens has long
stood at the top of the list.
No. 1 American Author
Among contemporary Western writers who have become
"best sellers" in Russian and other Soviet languages,
two American names stand out: Theodore Dreiser and
Howard Fast (though neither has managed to obtain any¬
where near the same success in the United States) . Dreiser
is so popular in the Soviet Union that according to one
report few cultured persons in Moscow, Leningrad and
Kiev are unacquainted with at least one of his books.
Along with separate translations of his novels, a 12-
volume edition' of his collected works in Russian was un¬
dertaken in 1951. Though sales of his books cannot be
compared with those of the old standbys like Jack Lon¬
don, Mark Twain or O. Henry, he is well on his way to
becoming a "classic" in the Soviet Union.
Of contemporary French authors, Romain Rolland has
probably had the greatest sales. Between 1918 and 1954
almost 2,500,000 copies of his books had been printed, and
in 1955 a 14-volume edition of his works was Cont'd
launched. The same year saw the publication
of G.B. Shaw's Devil's Disciple, A.J. Cronin's °n
Hatter's Castle, Carlo Levi's Christ Stopped at next We
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
U.S.S.R. BOOK NEWS
(Continued)
Eboli, as well as translations of Lion Feuchtwanger, Stefen
Zweig, Halldor Laxness, and Martin Andersen Nexö (a
15-volume edition of his works was started in 1951).
Last year, a 570-page volume of Erskine Caldwell's
novels and short stories appeared and found a large
following. Scores of current British and American books
became "best sellers" including Cronin's The Citadel and
The Stars Look Down; Sinclair Lewis's Arrowsmith, Sean
O'Casey's play Juno and the Peacock, Upton Sinclair's
Jungle, along with 19th century authors such as Thackery,
Emily Brontë (Wuthering Heights) and Charlotte Brontë
(Jane Eyre). The year 1956 was also marked by a series of
translations of mystery stories and adventure. Rider
Haggard, Conan Doyle, William Wilkie Collins (Moon¬
stone). H.G. Wells's fantastic stories (War of the Worlds,
Invisible Man, etc.) appeared in two volumes. This year,
James Cain, author of The Postman Always Rings Twice,
will appear for the first time in a Russian translation.
One of the most talked about novels of recent years is
Ernest Hemingway's The Old Man and the Sea, published
early in 1956 in the first two issues of a new magazine
Inostrannaya (Foreign) Literatura. This was Heming¬
way's first Russian translation in 17 years. In 1957, sev¬
eral of his novels and many of his short stories are
scheduled for publication in a special two-volume omnibus
edition.
In fact, 1957 promises to be a bumper year for contem¬
porary foreign works in translation. In a special report
to The Unesco Courier, A. Krassilnlkov, assistant director
of the Foreign Literature Press in Moscow, announces that
more than 540 titles are scheduled for translation this
year an increase of 20 per cent over 1956 production.
Editions totalling at least seven and a half million copies
are to be published of which four million copies will be
works of literature a high proportion for the Soviet
Union where political, social and economic publications
usually far outnumber literary works. Translations will
be made irom over 30 foreign (non-Soviet) languages.
Asian 'firsts' for 1957
published. One general work, dealing witn German,
Swiss, English and American authors between 1930 and
1940 has already gone to press; the translation of another,
->n contemporary Icelandic literature, is being completed.
As in past years many novelists and poets from the
People's Republic of China and the Popular Democracies
of Poland, Rumania, Bulgaria and Czechoslovakia will be
translated. Twice as many Yugoslav prose and poetry
works will be published in 1957 as compared with last year.
(There are numerous book stores in Moscow, Leningrad
and other large cities devoted exclusively to the literature
of the Popular Democracies.) Some of the authors: Maria
Dombrovska (Poland); Sacharia Stanou (Rumania); Di-
mitri Tolev (Bulgaria) ; K. Sedlacek (Czechoslovakia) ;
M. Kranets (Yugoslavia) ; Lei Tsia, Chou Li-Bo (China).
A collection of short stories by 18 contemporary Indian
'writers as well as various Indian novels are at present in
press.
Long waiting lists
An interesting sidelight on Russian reading habits can
be noted in the number of foreign books read in their
original languages. It is not uncommon in Moscow
and other cities of the U.S.S.R. to find persons discussing a
contemporary French author they have read in the ori¬
ginal French or an American or British writer they have
read in English.
An American visitor to the Soviet Union recently report¬
ed that a young woman showed him her copy of a Soviet
edition of O. Henry in English. The size of the edition
20,000 copies was printed on the end page (as it is in all
Soviet books). Compared to Russian-language editions of
translated books this was small (a 1956 edition of Dreiser's
The Titan in Russian was printed in 225,000 copies).
"But," commented the visitor, '"imagine trying to sell
20,000 copies of a Russian-language edition of, say, Chekov,
in the United States."
The complete works of many foreign authors are often
available in their original languages in Soviet public li¬
braries, long before translations are undertaken. Thus,
all of Faulkner's and Hemingway's books in their Ame¬
rican editions have been on public library shelves for
years. Their books are in constant circulation and the
waiting lists are long (Russians read American, British and
French literature in great quantities). Extra English co¬
pies of Faulkner and other American authors have re¬
cently been ordered for the public libraries to meet the
growing demand.
Western European and American writers are to
receive special attention this year, Mr. Krassilnlkov
informed The Unesco Courier. Sean O'Casey's
selected works will appear for the first time in Russian in
a two-volume edition. The first volume by the Irish
novelist came off the press in January 1957 while the
second is due for publication at the end of the year.
Novels by Cronin, Steinbeck, Sinclair Lewis, François
Mauriac, and Vercors are scheduled for publication in
Russian this year, as are works by Italian, German, Swiss,
Canadian, Swedish and Argentine contemporary writers.
But for Western fiction, the most important translation
events of 1957 will be the two-volume Hemingway already
referred to, a volume of plays by Somerset Maugham, and
a volume of short stories by Nobel Prize winner William
Faulkner. The books by Maugham and Faulkner will be
the first to appear in the Russian language. Until now
only three of Faulkner's short stories have been published
in Russian. The first appeared in an anthology in 1934;
the second was printed in a magazine in 1935; the third
was published last year in Inostrannaya Literatura. As
Mr. Krassilnlkov reports, Faulkner and Maugham are
expected to arouse considerable interest among readers
throughout the Soviet Union.
Several other "firsts" are in store for Soviet readers this
year, the Foreign Literature Press announces. For the
first time Indonesian, Burmese and Thai works will be
translated into Russian, including a volume of short
stories by Tur Pramudia Anat of Indonesia, an anthology
of Burmese epic poetry, and a novel (Facing the Future)
by Si Burapa of Thailand. For the first time too, transla¬
tions of histories of literature by foreign authors will be
26
Soviet Information Service, Paris
ARCTIC CIRCLE BOOKSHOP. Well-stocked shelves
of bookstore at Kirovsk, a Russian town In the Kola
Peninsula, north of the Arctic Circle. Kirovsk, which
is an important scientific agricultural station, has
the only Polar Arctic Botanical Garden in the world.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1957
ONE IN THREE. Unusual example of the bookbinder's art, this
French 19th century Book of Hours(the part of a breviary contain
ing offices to be said during the day) was divided in three and given
a triple binding. Now in a Harvard College collection, U.S.A.
They mass-produced
books long before
printing presses
by Jorge
Carrera Andrade BLACK ROBES
Some thirty-five years before the start of the Christian
era, Latin philosophers gathered in the shade of the
columns of the Asinus Pollio public library the first
in Rome to discuss the fruits of Greek thought as record¬
ed in the library's voluminous papyrus scrolls. These were
the troubled times of the Second Triumvirate, the govern¬
ing coalition of Mark Antony, Octavian and Lepidus, and
young Romans, unsettled by the changes which they
sensed were imminent, turned with enthusiasm to studies
of literature and the arts.
Asinus Pollio, formerly a people's tribune, had retired
from politics, but wishing to continue to serve his fellow
citizens, he opened an "Academy of Eloquence" in his villa
at Tusculum. Here, over the entrance to its library he
caused the inscription Atrium libertatis ("sanctuary of
freedom") to be engraved. Pollio, a great orator, poet,
historian and critic, was a widely travelled man having
journeyed through North Africa, Spain, Gaul and Mace¬
donia. From one of his moving speeches, Pliny records
these famous words: "The fruits of man's intellect are the
common heritage."" Were there any translations of
foreign authors among the Greek books in this first Roman
public library? We know of none, probably because Greek
writers, satisfied with the glories of their own civilization,
considered all the other peoples as barbarians and were
not interested either in their language or their literature.
They were blind to the brilliance of Hebrew and Egyptian
intellectual achievements, and while this may have helped
to preserve the originality of Greek thought, it also
explained why Greece was surpassed by the Latin world
in universality.
All well-educated Romans knew Greek and read the
works of Aristotle, Plato and the epic or bucolic poets in
the original. Pollio was the first to entrust to his protégés,
Horace and Virgil, the task of translating Greek works
into Latin. Naturally Virgil, with his love of rural life,
chose Theocritus's poems in praise of the countryside,
while the peaceful Horace, perhaps out of sheer contrari¬
ness, translated the resonant Odes of Pindar. Apart from
these works, there were few translations in Pollio's library.
The Odyssey, translated much earlier by Livius Andro-
nicus, some comedies adapted by Plautus, and the trage¬
dies in which Naevius the Roman poet and dramatist,
attacked the Roman aristocracy more than two centuries
before Christ.
Not until the advent of Christianity and the great
days of Roman Africa, in the first centuries of the Christ¬
ian Era, did Latin begin to be used more widely, with the
resultant need to include among the treasures
of that language the essential works enshrin- I
ing religious thought, which had hitherto been I
written in the Hebrew language. Amid the next page
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
BLACK ROBES
(Continued) Pride of monks & princes: translating
sands of Carthage, Tertullian composed his Apologeticus.
Cyprian, Arnobius, St. Augustine and Ruflnus all from
North Africa undertook the task of translating passages
from the books of the Bible into Latin. "The fire of
impatience" of which Tertullian spoke seemed to devour
the religious writers of the African continent. At the end
of the 4th century, North Africa was considered as the
true home of Latin-Christian literature and Latin reigned
supreme as the language of learning.
In this same century, Pope Damasus whose library in
Rome was a centre of learning asked the Dalmatian
monk, Sophorius Hieronymus (St. Jerome) to translate
the Bible into Latin. After 23 years of work, during which
the good monk, although beset by every kind of tribulation,
never failed to write 1,000 lines a day (including his
famous letters and commentaries), the task was complet¬
ed. This translation, which testifies to astonishing lin¬
guistic ability, is still known as the Vulgate. The Dal¬
matian scholar, who was canonized, went down to posterity
as "the patron saint of translators".
At the beginning of the 6th century, an Italian monk,
wearing a simple black habit, symbolical of his austere life,
founded the Monte Cassino monastery on the site of an
old fortified castle and set up the Benedictine Order; this
event, of such importance in the history of human culture,
was as significant for the Middle Ages as was the invention
of printing for the modern world.
The Benedictines were, in fact, Europe's first "mass
production" publishers, for these thousands of monks.
From "Bookmen's Bedlam", © W. H. Blumenthal 19 55
BOOKS IN CHAINS. Famous old library at Hereford Cathedra],
England, dating from the days when librarians chained their books
to the shelves. An ancient monastic library, it still retains several
rare manuscripts and relics. At one time parts of the book stacks were
dismantled and used elsewhere in the cathedral, but in recent years
the original old woodwork has been restored to its proper place. (See
also Unesco Courier, June 1953, " Books without chains ")
working as copyists and illuminators, made the reproduc¬
tion of manuscripts the core of their monastic activities.
Eight centuries after the foundation of the Benedictine
Order, there were 17,000 Benedictine monasteries in
Europe in other words, 17,000 workshops for the pro¬
duction of books.
From the cells of Cluny, Citeaux or Subiaco, flowed
countless volumes of beautiful manuscripts each chapter
beginning with a large capital letter, ornamented with
miniatures and flowers, and the whole luxuriously bound
which filled the libraries of convents, palaces and the
"cathedral schools", the precursors of universities. One of
the most extraordinary phenomena in the history of the
Middle Ages, was the speed with which books spread from
one end of Europe to the other.
Among the "best sellers" of the early Middle Ages was
the Latin translation of Aristotle's works by Boethius,
28
Minister of Theodoric the Great, King of the Ostrogoths.
The VTIth century had a superb translator in Isidore of
Seville, regarded as the man who continued the work of
Saint Jerome, and whose Etymologies one of the 'first
encyclopaedias of the Christian world was widely distri¬
buted through the "editions" issued, one after the other,
by the Benedictine monks.
The great cultural movement of the 8th, 9th and
10th centuries swept like a fertile tide over the lands of
France and on to the island kingdom of Alfred the Great.
That learned monarch, once he was able to sheathe the
sword with which he had expelled the Danes from his
shores, not only founded Oxford University and extended
his protection to men of letters, but also himself undertook
to translate St. Augustine and Orosio and prepared an
Anglo-Saxon version of Bede's Ecclesiastical History and
of several parts of Boethius's Consolation of Philosophy.
Finally, in the 10th century a new France stirred to life
in the apartments of southern castles, surrounded by
grapevines and lulled by the music of Latin cicadas.
France became a great cultural centre, where the influ¬
ences of East and West were blended and the most illus¬
trious schools of art inspired the whole of Europe.
Then, in the 11th century, came the great cultural
awakening in Spain. Cordova and Toledo were the two
intellectual poles of the period: Cordova the refuge of
Eastern scholars was the farthest bastion of Islamic
culture, while Toledo was recognized as the highest citadel
of Western thought. Cordova, in succession to Baghdad
and Cairo, became the "capital of books". Abderraman III
sponsored the production of paper books, while at the
same time enacting laws on literacy teaching for the poor.
The great linguists of Toledo
Never had a people displayed such a taste for reading.
Under the protection of the Caliph, thousands of
copyists and booksellers prospered. Bibliophiles,
bookbinders, illuminators and illustrators were welcomed
at the Court. Scholarly translators, who usually spoke
four languages Arabic, Greek, Hebrew and Latin, enjoyed
the sovereign's special favour. The library oí Alhacam II
was the pride and glory of those days; it contained 400,000
books.
The imperial city of Toledo, crowned by rocky heights
and encircled by the blue ribbon of the Tagus, became a
hive of culture when King Alfonso VI retook it from the
Moors. Toledo collected the Arab texts and made them
known to the West. Thus the Moslem occupation of the
peninsula bore its fruits, and world culture was enriched
by the contribution of Islamic thought. Here, in Toledo
in the 12th century, was founded, for the first time in
European history, an international institute of translators,
for the purpose of spreading knowledge of the most
v important works of the age.
The "Toledo College of Translators" was composed of
learned men from various countries: Gerard of Cremona,
an Italian philologist; Daniel de Morlay, an English
gentleman attached to the court of Richard Coeur de Lion,
Domingo Gundisalvo, a Spanish archdeacon; Hermann, a
German monk who enjoyed the patronage of King Man-
fredo of Sicily, and who, despite his foreign origin, became
Bishop of Astorga.
The learned men belonging to this illustrious school
of translation also included Juan Hispalense, a converted
Jew who translated Ptolemy, another Englishman, Michael
Scott, who introduced Averroism into southern Europe and
who won a mysterious reputation for necromancy at the
court of Frederick II and, lastly, Juan de Toledo, the
Benedictine monk, alchemist, poet and prophet, who
became a Cardinal and was even on the point of acceding
to the pontifical throne in Rome.
Gundisalvo's most famous translation was of a work
in Arabic, the Fountain of Life a monument of Judaic
philosophy and an encyclopedia of a system j
of science based on metaphysics written by I
Salomon Ben Gabirol, a native of Malaga.
This scholar and philosopher, whom the page 30
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1957
PINHEAD CALLIGRAPHY
Among the wide selection of religious texts in
Lilliputian form is this miniature Koran (actual
size shown here) made by a 17th-century calli¬
graphist. Another Koran, even more unusual
and precious because of its octagonal shape, was
written in Persian about 1800 in microscopic
characters, on gold-edged, one and a half inch
pages. Its shape made it a collection showpiece
for there are probably fewer octagonal books
than Gutenberg Bibles in existence nowadays.
(C) W. H. Blumenthal 19 55
HEART FOR
A PRINCESS
Heart-shaped book in calf binding, hand-tooled In gold,
made about I 590 by Casper Meuser, court binder to the
Prince Elector of Saxony. Measuring eight inches across,
it contains two little worksa book of prayers and dom¬
estic household rules. Bound for the Princess Anna
von Sachsen, it recalls another famous book, the lily-
shaped missal made for Diane de Poitiers in 1555. A
singular circular book was also made by Casper Meuser.
From "Bookmen's Bedlam" © W. H. Blumenthal 1955
FOR NOBLE GIRDLES
This strangely-shaped volume is a "girdle book", bound into a
soft doeskin pouch and intended to be carried fastened on a belt
or girdle. It is a Latin breviary in manuscript written in 1454,
measuring three inches by four. Few of these devotional
girdle books, once com mon to the waistbands of nobles, still exist.
From "Bookmen's Bedlam" ;Ç, W. H. ßlumenthal 1955
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
BLACK ROBES (Continued)
BRAILLE BIBLE for blind fills these 21 huge
volumes produced in 1923 and occupies over
two yards of shelf space. New era for blind opened
when recording of entire books was initiated in
1934 in U.S.A., Talking Books of the Bible now
exist on I 69 discs each playing for a half hour or
a total of just over 84 hours. The longest novel re¬
corded, Tolstoy's " War and Peace " needs I 19
records and a total listening time of nearly 60 hours
as against 9 hours for a book of average length.
© W. H. Blumenthal 1955
Spaniards called Avicebron, wrote his philosophical doc¬
trines in Arabic and his poetry in Hebrew. From the pens
of the Toledo translators, there emerged, in Latin garb,
the works of Euclid, Avicenna, Algazel, Aristotle and others
who contributed to the flowering of Western learning.
The whole of the 13th century resounds with the echoes
of a book which was translated in all the countries of
Europe, and which could be called one of the "best sellers"
of the Middle Ages: the Canticle of Brother Sun, written
by St. Francis of Assist, shortly before his death. In
Umbria, central Italy, arose a new vision of the world, a
philosophy o'f humility and meekness.
The gracious landscapes of Italy left their mark on this
new intellectual trend, which set out to discover man the
man of flesh and blood, as opposed to the metaphysical
being concerned solely with the after-world. It was a
search conducted through letters and the visual arts.
While the scholar Leo Pilatus was teaching Greek to the
Italians and translating Homer, the artist Giotto di Bon-
done was painting figures of intense realism, and giving
lifelike expression to the characters of his frescoes in the
Basilica at Assis!. The shades of Dante and Boccaccio,
strolling through the Florentine arcades, seemed to meet
Geoffrey Chaucer, the first great English poet, who was
visiting the cities of Italy as the envoy of the King of
England. The English writer and traveller subsequently
won a reputation as a great translator of the Italians.
The age of humanism and the Renaissance opened
gloriously with the appearance of the printed book which,
though regarded askance by the bibliophiles, was to
transform the face of the world by bringing into the
humblest home knowledge which had hitherto been
restricted to the palace and the monastery, and reserved
for the enjoyment of princes, scholars and prelates.
The Benedictine monks, who in earlier centuries had
spread learning by means of illuminated manuscripts,
were the first to recognize the importance of Gutenberg's
invention and they installed the first printing press after
Gutenberg in the monastery at Subiaco, near Rome.
At all events, the translation of books was regarded
until the 15th century, as valuable literary work, compar¬
able to the writing of the originals and many famous men
chose to work as simple translators. One wonders for
what obscure reasons translating was reduced to its
present estate as the "Cinderella of Literature".
CHINESE SYNAGOGUE MANUSCRIPTS. The city of Kai-fung,
on the Yellow River about 350 miles south of Peking, is one of the
most historic of the early settlement sites of China. It was long the
centre of the main Jewish colony in China, a few remnants of which
still exist today. Records show that a synagogue was built there In 1190
A.D. from which the ancient Hebrew manuscripts shown above origi-
© W. H. Blumenthal 1955
nated. Fifty-nine of these unique manuscripts, composed of several
folds of thin Chinese paper pasted together, are now preserved In the
library of the Hebrew University of Cincinnati (U.S.A.). Photo shows
various prayers with a Memorial Book In Chinese characters, hymns
in Hebrew and Jewish-Persian, New Year prayers folded in shape of a
fan, a book of morning and Sabbath prayers damaged by flood waters.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1957
WHAT HAS TV DONE
TO BOOK READING?
by Henry Cassirer
c "New York Times
What is television doing to the reading of books? The
head of the Detroit Public Library's home-read¬
ing service put it this way in an address to the
American Library Association: "When TV was new, li¬
braries noted a falling off of readers but as the novelty
wore off, people began to return to the library to ask for
books on subjects brought to their attention on the TV
screen." Or as a woman said apologetically to a librarian
at Cleveland, "I remember reading it years ago but it never
meant as much as seeing it last night. Now I want to
read it again."
This double effect of television, first replacing book-
reading and then drawing attention to specific books
through dramatic or literary programmes, is noted also in
England. "Undoubtedly reading is the chief sufferer of
television," said a speaker at the 1956 conference of the
British Library Association. An estimated British televi¬
sion public of 16
million had to be
compared with
about 13 million
registered bor¬
rowers at public
libraries. Less
than a third of
the people with
television sets
were estimated
to read to any
extent and the
remainder read
few books or
none at all. But
con currently,
issues of .books
from a large
number of Brit¬
ish public and
county libra¬
ries continue to
rise year after
year, reported
the same
speaker, and the
tastes of the
reading public
have changed.
Fiction had suf¬
fered, but non-
fiction had benefitted. Other librarians confirmed that
television was freeing them from the obligation to cater
for the light entertainment reader and opening the way
for them to serve readers with more serious tastes as well
as to win new readers.
A certain decline in book reading is noted in the United
States. It is not clear whether this is exclusively due to
television. Nevertheless it is significant that in 1954,
Americans spent about 500 million dollars for books,
13 million less than in 1953, though the population increas¬
ed by about 2.8 million people in the same period. During
the same year, Americans spent 600 million dollars just to
get their radio and television sets repaired. An article in
"U.S. News and World Report" of September 1955 noted:
"There are more people, and particularly children, in the
United States than there were 10 years ago. They have
more money to spend yet they are spending less for books
and little more for other reading material than they used
to spend."
This sombre trend is offset by indications that television
is stimulating the reading of significant books. Perhaps
there is here, too, a change in reading habits as in the
United Kingdom, with television supplying the feature and
fiction entertainment formerly sought in books, and mak¬
ing such entertainment available to large sections of the
population who never read books before, while at the same
time drawing attention to literature which formerly had
only a very small audience.
When the American writer and biographer, Carl
Sandburg, was portrayed in a special nation-wide pro¬
gramme, booksellers and librarians throughout the coun¬
try reported such a run on Sandburg books during the
next week that all their stocks were exhausted. In Los
Angeles, Professor Baxter, professor of literature at the
University of South California, broadcast a weekly talk on
Shakespeare which was viewed by an estimated 400,000
persons and later rebroadcast in other parts of the coun¬
try. These programmes, as well as numerous dramatic
presentations of Shakespeare on American TV, have
created a vast new audience and reading public for the
Bard. The in¬
fluence of televi¬
sion on book-
reading is not a
static phenomen¬
on. Television
can replace book
reading but it
can also be used
to promote It ac¬
tively. A 19 55
report from the
Cleveland public
library notes an
increase in bor¬
rowings and adds
significantly,
"While a reading
boom traceable
to TV influence
is not peculiar to
Cleveland, nei¬
ther is it a na¬
tional phenomen¬
on. It seems to
occur chiefly in
cities where a
well-directed li¬
brary staff with a
far-seeing plan
in mind actively
does something
to capitalize on
TV-prompted interest." The library, for instance, promi¬
nently displays inside its main lobby and in display
windows outside, information regarding outstanding future
TV programmes.
The presentation of recent books through interviews
with their authors and visualization by means of films,
photographs and other applicable pictures, is the feature
of one of the most important weekly television programmes
in France, Lecture Pour Tous. Regular interviews with
authors figure on TV in Germany, Italy and elsewhere.
Thanks to this stimulating power of television, British
librarians took a rather cheerful view about TV's influence
at their recent conference. As The Times reported, "It
was felt that TV is managing to create both among adults
and children a lively new reading public. There are those
whose interest in more or less serious subjects has been
aroused and who have gone almost straight from their sets
to their libraries in search of books on subjects like
archaeology. And it is a common experience that televi¬
sion serial broadcasts set strong temporary fashions for
such writers as Jane Austen, Galsworthy and Dickens.
All in all, so far the librarians seem to think that the
good byproducts of TV outweigh what harm it may do."
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Publisher's
Dilemma
Publishing is not the profitable busi¬
ness which many people suppose it to
be. In fact in many countries today
publishers actually lose money in the
physical production and sale of books.
These startling findings are revealed in
Unesco's Books for All by R.E. Bar¬
ker who points out that publishers today
have to look to subsidiary rights such
as book clubs, serialization and reprints
in order to compensate for losses they
incur from original book production.
Recently nine leading general and fic
tion publishers provided figures for the
British Publishers Association which
show that the average discount to book
sellers is 39.07%; average royalty to
authors 11.88%; average cost of pro¬
duction 28.24 % ; average overheads
(including advertising) 17.20%; and
average profit only 3.61 %. The aver¬
age "profit" of 3.61 % is reduced al¬
most to nothing when allowance is made
for the depreciation of stock.
Depreciation is an important factor.
A book that promises to sell 5,000 co¬
pies may only sell 2,000. The balance
represents a potential loss of 3,000 times
the published price, and within six
months unsold books may represent one-
tenth of their original price. Of course
the book may sell steadily and even
call for a reprinting, but sales only occa¬
sionally exceed expectations. When
they do publisher and author naturally
expect to benefit, since no one pays the
publisher for his failures. Such failu¬
res have to be regarded as investment,
but they can easily turn a publisher's
"profit1' into loss. Published prices are
necessarily related to the nature and
length of a book and to its potential
sale. If the publisher sets his prices
too high, his books will not sell. If
his prices are too low, he will go out
of business. As Sir Stanley Unwin
points out in his book The Truth about
Publishing: "It is easy to become a pub¬
lisher but difficult to remain one; the
mortality rate in infancy is higher than
in any other trade or profession."
Austria is best- off
for bookshops :
one for every
2,745 people
A bookseller's job is more com¬
plicated than most people think.
Besides a thorough knowledge of
books and publishing, he must
decide what books are likely to
sell, have a large stock to meet
demand and yet avoid over¬
stocking. He must be able to
advise customers on any book
from a juvenile for 7-year-olds to
to latest studies on astronomy.
In some European countries
booksellers have to pass exams
and serve apprenticeships before
they can start in business. Nor¬
way insists on a special examina¬
tion plus 10 years experience at
the trade before a bookseller is
qualified to open a shop of his
. own. (If he wants to take over
an existing shop six to eight years
is considered enough.) Great
Britain and Ireland have recently
organized courses in book selling.
As a rule standards of service are
higher in countries where entry
to the trade is subject to specific
qualifications.
According to Unesco's Books
for All, Austria leads the world
in number of bookshops in rela¬
tion to population: one bookshop
for every 2,745 persons. Den¬
mark is second with one bookshop
for every 4 000 people. Next in
order come: Australia (4,315),
Italy (4,896), the United King¬
dom (6,000), Netherlands (7,281),
Belgium (7,609), U.S.S.R. (8,708),
Federal German Republic
(1 1,970), France (12,023), Switzer¬
land (12,375), Sweden (13,195),
Norway (14,986), Canada
(18,125), the U.S.A. (18,616).
J
q?
;».
ss,*>
SN,
^"
© Almasy 1956.
RAW MATERIAL of education. Printer inspects assembled texts and Illustrations for a Bolivian
primary school reader before pages are printed. Illustrations include Inca and Aymara Indian
motifs. Unesco now co-operates in the work of Bolivia's Pillapi educational research centre.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
TIDBITS
(Cont'd from page 16)
(one third children) and a collection
of 32,000 volumes. Some 34,000 people
were enrolled in the lending service.
Odd-shaped and occult
In a collection of occult books
belonging to a Parisian collector
which were sold some years ago was
a vellum manuscript written and cut
in triangular shape. This French
treatise of ceremonial magic and
alchemy was executed in cipher and
cabalistic symbols about 1750 by the
Comte de St. Germain (Marquis de
Betmar), and is known as a grimoire
or book of magic spells and rituals of
the black art. (Bookmen's Bedlam)
Fiction tops the list
Recent statistics collected by Unesco
show that fiction is the first choice of
most countries. But in choosing books
on particular subjects, British and
American readers are likely to choose
a book on a technical subject or
science or failing these, travel or bio¬
graphy. Indian or Nigerian readers
will choose something on the social
sciences, next biography, then litera¬
ture. Social sciences are not very
popular in Thailand, travel, biography
and history being overwhelmingly the
popular choice. Choice in the Philip¬
pines is more similar to U.S. and U.K.
patterns, literature being the most
popular subject. (Unesco)
Drawings on this page and pages
The Unesco Courier. February 1957
15-16 are by Gerhard Oberländer
taken from Buch und Buchhandel in
Zahlen (Statistics on books and the
book industry) 1955, 1956, published
by Borsenverein des Deutschen Buch¬
handels E.V., Frankfurt am Main.
Some best sellers in science
Charles Darwin's Origin of Species has probably reached more
people over the years than any other scientific book published,
according to the British science magazine "Discovery" in a short
report on scientific best sellers in Great Britain (December 1955 &
February 1956 issues). It is almost impossible, the magazine says, to
find any exact figures for the sales of the famous book. One reason
given for its success: Darwin's plain, unpretentious but very lucid
style.
Darwin's book on worms (The Formation of Vegetable Mould
through the Action of Worms, 1881) sold 8,500 copies in about two
years, but even this figure, "Discovery" says, "'is more than many so-
called popular science books of modern times sell."
Books on astronomy have been among the most popular of our
times. Sir James Jeans's Thß Mysterious Universe (1930) sold well
over 240,000 copies in the Cambridge University Press edition alone,
and the book is now available in a score of languages from Bengali to
Finnish. Most successful British book on astronomy produced since
the war is probably F. Hoyle's Nature of the Universe (over 110,000
copies); his latest book Frontiers of Astronomy (1955) sold 13,000 copies
in the United Kingdom within six months of publication.
Another highly successful book has been King Solomon's Ring by
the Austrian naturalist Konrad Lorenz: over 300,000 copies sold of
this fascinating account of Lorenz's studies of behaviour and "lang¬
uage" of animals. Surprisingly, Einstein's Relativity: The Special and
the General Theory (probably his easiest book on relativity to under¬
stand) sold 32,000 in its English edition.
The recent Pelican book Five Hundred Years of Printing mentions a
few science best sellers: Rachel Carson's The Sea Around Us, Thor
Heyerdahl's Kon-Tiki, La Vie des Abeilles by Maeterlinck; The
Universe Around Us by Sir James Jeans.
Other best sellers in science: Ceram's Gods, Graves and Scholars;
the two Kinsey studies on male and female sexual behaviour; The
World of Mathematics by James Newman; Science for the Citizen and
Mathematics for the Million by Lancelot Hogben. Science textbooks
used in schools and universities can sell exceedingly well and some¬
times reach the six-figure bracket.
SUBSCRIPTION
Subscribe to THE UNESCO COURIER today- $2.50; 8/; 400 francs per year (12 issues)
Fill in this subscription blank and mail it with your cheque or money order
to our local agent in your country listed on inside back cover.
Please enter my subscription for THE UNESCO COURIER
D One year $2.50; 8/-; 400 French francs D Two years $4.50; 16/-; 800 French francs
D Cheque /Money Order enclosed D Please bill me
Name..
Add ress.,
City	Country	Profession.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
SIXTY YEARS OF
U.S. BEST SELLERS
A
list of the best selling books
in the United States since
1895 is given in a recently-
published hook by Alice Payne
Hackett entitled "Sixty Years of
Best Sellers".
The first ten titles in her list
are :
In His Steps by Charles Monroe
Sheldon (1897), 8,000,000 copies.
The Common Sense Book of Baby
and Child Care by Benjamin
Spock (1946), 7,850,000 copies.
God's Little Acre by Erskine Cald¬
well (1933), 6,582,553 copies.
Better Homes and Gardens Cook
Book (1930), 5,806,585 copies.
Gone With the Wind by Margaret
Mitchell (1937), 5,000,000 copies.
How to Win Friends and Influence
People by Dale Carnegie (1937),
4,877,511 copies.
I, the Jury by Mickey Spillane
(1947), 4,441,837 copies.
The Big Kill by Mickey Spillane
(1951), 4,158,840 copies.
A Message to Garcia by Elbert
Hubbard (1898), 4,000,000 copies.
My Gun is Quick by Mickey Spil¬
lane (1950), 3,912,419 copies.
A list of best sellers for the last
sixty years in the U.S. recently
compiled by the "New York Times"
shows that Sinclair Lewis, Thorn¬
ton Wilder and John Steinbeck
made the grade. Faulkner and
Hemingway did not. Foreign writ¬
ers on the list ;
England: H.G.
History) ;
Wells (Outline of
France: André Maurois (Disraeli);
Germany: Erich Maria Remarque
(All Quiet on the Western Front) ,
and Franz Werfel (Song of Ber¬
nadette) ;
Spain: Blasco Ibanez (Four Hor¬
semen of the Apocalypse);
Sweden: Axel Munthe (Story of
San Michèle);
Finland: Mika Waltari (The Egyp¬
tian).
Only two writers succeeded in
staying on the best seller list for
more than a year, both women :
Pearl Buck (The Good Earth), and
Margaret Mitchell (Gone With the
Wind). There was one book which
kept top place for three years a
new version of the Bible.
Pocket books (Cont'd from page 23)
westerns, 6 per cent non-fiction, and about 7 per cent
miscellaneous. Practically every type of book is reflected
in pocket books to-day; science and technology; literature,
from Chaucer to the latest avant-garde writers; transla¬
tions of the great classics and modern best sellers of
Europe and elsewhere; "Do It Yourself" manuals, cook¬
books, and reference books; here classics re-issued with
screaming "skylines" to tie up with the latest movie
releases, there a new Dictionary advertising itself as "not
made into a movie"; all of them opening up new worlds
for a whole new world of readers.
The Midwestern housewife in a small town with no
library writes: "If you knew how bored I get looking after
two small children, doing housework and seeing the same
old neighbours day after day, you'd understand what a
godsend your inexpensive books have been". A man wrote
to the publisher of the 35-cent edition of the Odyssey
"Just read the Odyssey! Boy, that guy Homer sure can
write! Do you have any other books by him?"
Pocket books are published now in every corner of the
world, many of them indistinguishable
from their American prototype save in
their language. In England Penguins
have been followed by a number of
others in the same field. In France,
though the booksellers are still wary, the
pocket book reprint of classic authors
has reached out to a new public, the
student, the little midinette, the working
man from St. Denis and Roanne. Zola,
for instance, is one of the authors who
continue to enjoy great popularity.
34
In Germany, where some 25 million copies of pocket
books have been sold between 1951 and 1955, various com-,
munity groups have also organized the publication of"
selected paperbacks, sometimes in superior format and
binding, just as in Israel the only successful attempt to
publish general pocket books was that organized by the big
labour union of the country, the Histraduth with volun¬
tary committees formed in factories, business firms and
collective farms to push the sale. Both in Israel and
Norway books are taken so seriously that the average
reader prefers the hard cover to add to his library.
In some countries, like Belgium and Spain, the experi¬
ment has not succeeded; in Italy, on the other hand, half
the books published annually are paperback. The Soviet
Union, the only country to compare with the United
States in the size of its literate population, has no pocket
books; there the average hard cover book sells cheaply at
6 or 7 roubles. And though the spread of pocket books
has reached around the world, no country has attacked
the question with the mass methods of the U.S., nor
invested the same sums of moneys in expensive machinery
and marketing networks.
No one can foretell the future ; it may well be that
with the gradual spread of literacy to
the vast populations of India, Africa
and the Far East, the future of the cheap
pocket book as a cultural weapon of the
first order may well outstrip any posi¬
tion it has achieved today. But what it
has done today is to make the literature
and wisdom of the world available to
millions of men and women ignorant
before of its pleasures and possibilities.
It is -now there for them to takefor the
price of a packet of cigarettes.
z
13
od
o
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER
IN RUSSIAN
The Unesco Courier is happy to
announce the creation of a Rus¬
sian-language edition. The Rus¬
sian edition, translated and print¬
ed in Moscow, has now been
launched with the January 1957
issue and, like the English, French
and Spanish editions, will appear
monthly. The Unesco Courier.
is thus privileged to become
the first large-circulation, general
magazine of international stand¬
ing edited outside the Soviet
Union to be translated and publi¬
shed regularly in the U.S.S.R.
'Publication of the Russian edition
has been entrusted by the Com¬
mission of the U.S.S.R. for Unesco
to the "Foreign Literature Press"
in Moscow, the chief publisher of
modern foreign literature in the
Soviet Union.
The Unesco Courier is now
published in English, French, Spa¬
nish and Russian. A small Japan¬
ese version is published in
Tokyo, and a Danish version in
Copenhagen.
Readers interested in receiving
the Russian edition may place
their subscriptions with our reg¬
ular Sales Agents (listed below)
at the same rate as that of the
other language editions.
Wa^-JÙ
ypbep
HEBEAOMblE
C0KP0BHU1A
MHPOBGTO
HCKYCCTBA
SHBAPb
1957
((Q+Hj roduUQHua)
Hens 5 pyff.
K"S.
WHERE TO SUBSCRIBE
Unesco's national distributors from
whom the English, French, Spanish
and Russian editions of the UNESCO
COURIER can be obtained are listed
below.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Press Dep¬
artment, Royal Afghan Ministry of Educ¬
ation, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 303 Flinders Street, Melbourne,
C. I, Victoria.
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C"., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V.
BELGIUM. Louis de Lannoy, Editeur-
Libraire, 15 rue du Tilleul, Genval (Bra¬
bant). 80 Belgian francs.
CANADA. University of Toronto Press,
Toronto 5.
Periodica Inc., 5090 Avenue Papineau,
Montreal 34.
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House, P.O. Box
44, I 00 Parsons Road Colombo I.
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Libreria Económica, Calle
O' Reilly 505, Havana.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6 Nörregade, Copenhagen K.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
FRANCE. Unesco Sales Section,
19 Avenue Kleber, Paris, 16». CCP.
12598-48, Unesco Bookshop, Paris.
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2.
Sub-Depots : Oxford Book & Stationery
Co., Scindia House, New Delhi; Rajkamal
Publications Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby
Road, Bombay I.
INDONESIA. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Djakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
P. O. B. 4154, Tel-Aviv.
ITALY. Libreria Commissionaria San-
soni, Via Gino Capponi 26, Casella Pos¬
tale 552, Florence.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 99
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND SIN¬
GAPORE. Peter Chong & Co., Post
Office Box 135, Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta.
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church.
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
I 74, Lagos.
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass 7, Oslo.
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60 The Mall,
Lahore ; Bunder Road, Karachi and
35 The Mall. Pashawar.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Ouiapo, P.O. Box
620. Manila.
REPUBLIC OF IRELAND. The
National Press, 16 South Frederick St.,
Dublin.
SWEDEN. A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl'
Hovbokhandel, Frcdsgaten 2, Stockholm
16.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40 rue du Marché, Geneva
5.20 Swiss francs.
TANGIER. Paul Fckete, 2 rue Cook,
Tangier.
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
UNION OF BURMA. Burma Educa¬
tional Bookshop, 55 1-3 Merchant Street,
P.O. Box 222, Rangoon.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Street, P.O. Box 724. Pretoria.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London. S.E.I.
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, I 52 West 42nd St, New York,
36, N.Y,
U. S. S. R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga
Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
pecming o
have to learn to type. My second novel is
going too slowly."
Illustrations (6) " New York Times " 1956
]]>
</page>
</document>
