<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="067651eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
m
Special report
FAMOUS
AUTHORS
AS ARTISTS
Their paintings
drawings & sketches
KAt 7
<c%l)
*-y>
iZe& ^m^uac
A-J>
LEO TOLSTOY
*J ¡L A' to OjVuU OfCfA.
AUGUST 1957
. (U. K.)
25 cents (U. S.)
4 0 francs (France)
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
v»
¿S
ig*
VA_
r
i
> i
2^nNMJË i
1 -^--;-
-vi
/
/
m
/
fr ft \ ( '
î -M
WASHINGTON IRVING. (1783-1859) was the first of the great Amer¬
ican writers. In his youth he studied art and was almost persuaded, while
in Rome in 1805, to become a painter. It is interesting to note that for
The Sketch Book (which includes his immortal tales Rip Van Winkle and
The Legend of Sleepy Hollow) Washington Irving chose the pseudonym
"Geoffrey Crayon". Above, a group of sketches by Irving with, in centre,
a view of Cincinnati sketched in September 1832. Originals are in his
diaries and journals which are preserved in the New York Public Library.
THE LOST LENORE.
Edgar Allan Poe (1809-
1849) is known on at least
three occasions to have
tried his hand at drawing.
He made the pencil sketch
(right) of his childhood
sweetheart-fiancee, Elmira
Royster. Her marriage to
another man inspired Poe's
poem Lenore, and he later
used the name again in
The Raven as "the lost
Lenore." Years later when
she had become a widow
and he a widower they
contemplated marriage, but
his death in I 849 prevented
consummation of this ro¬
mance. In I 829 Poe design¬
ed a cover illustration for
The Stylus, a monthly journal
he sought to found and edit
but never did. Second draw¬
ing shown here, a portrait
of Poe, is attributed to the
author himself, and was
probably made about 1845.
Poe, once described by
Bernard Shaw as "this finest
of finest of artists," has also
been called "the founder of
the modern detective story."
\
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. August 1957
AUGUST 1957
No 8
I Oth YEAR
CONTENTS
PAGES
4 FAMOUS AUTHORS AS ARTISTS By B. Gaster
5 PAUL VALERY
7 HERMANN HESSE
I I HANS CHRISTIAN ANDERSEN
12 LEO TOLSTOY By A. Chifman
15 ROBERT LOUIS STEVENSON
16 RABINDRANATH TAGORE By S. Koffler
20 MY PAINTINGS... By R. Tagore
21 JEAN COCTEAU
22 THE UNKNOWN VICTOR HUGO By J. Sergent
25 CARLO LEVI
26 THE OWL By Carlo Levi
28 LEWIS CARROLL
30 CHARLES BEAUDELAIRE
32 H.G. WELLS
34 PIERRE LOTI
36 ALEXANDER PUSHKIN
37 AUGUST STRINDBERG
38 FEDERICO GARCIA LORCA
40 WILLIAM BLAKE
43 JOHANN WOLFGANG GOETHE
44 RUDYARD KIPLING
45 GOTTFRIED KELLER
46 WILLIAM THACKERAY
48 GEORGE SAND, MÉRIMÉE, MUSSET
49 ARTHUR RIMBAUD
50 MARK TWAIN
Other drawings & paintings by
p. 2 W. Irving; E. A. Poe; p. 4 Su Tung P'o; p. 6 D. G. Ros-
setti; p.8 N. Gogol; p.9 E. T. A. Hoffmann; p. 1 0 D. H.
Lawrence; p. 42 T. Hardy; C. Brontë; p. 5 1 R. Alberti;
V. Mayakowsky.
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, I 9 Avenue Kleber, Paris 16, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (12 issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. A small Japanese version Is published In Tokyo
and a Danish version in Copenhagen. The United States of America edition
is distributed by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 152, West 42nd
Street, New York 36, N.Y.. Pennsylvania 6-0851. Second-class mail privileges
authorized at New York, N.Y. (M.C. 57.1.1 15 A)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
credit is given to THE UNESCO COURIER and two voucher copies are sent
to the editor. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied
by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles express
the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent the opinions of
UNESCO or those ol the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: $2.50 ; 8/- stg. ; 400 French francs or equi¬
valent.
AFTER NOVEMBER I, 1957 : S3.00 ¡ 10/- stg., 500 frs.
COVER PHOTO
At the age of 67, the Indian poet Rabin-
dranath Tagore "fell under the enchant¬
ment of lines." Thus began an artist's
career which ended with his death. The
Nobel Prize winner for Literature who
wtote that the voice of the universe is
one of "pictures and dance," rarely
gave a descriptive title to his paintings.
"People often ask me about the meaning
of my pictures," he said, "It Is for them to
express not to explain." (Seepage 16).
This issue presents a glimpse of what the Editors
believe to be a unique panorama of vast though
little-explored perspectives.
Much has been written about famous authors in biogra¬
phies, encyclopedias and literary studies. But no one, as
far as we are aware, has yet attempted a study, on a
world-wide basis, of famous authors as artists, that is, of
the many great men and women of letters who have
sought to satisfy their hunger for self-expression not
only by writing novels, plays or poetry but also by sketch¬
ing, drawing or painting either as a vocation or as an
amusing pastime.
In his monumental work on Bach, Albert Schweitzer
(doctor, author, theologian and musician all in one) has
written: "We are in the habit of designating an artist
according to the medium he uses to translate his inner
life: musician, if he employs sound; painter, if he uses
colours; poet, if he uses words. One must admit, however,
that these categories, established by external criteria, are
somewhat arbitrary. The soul of the artist is a complex
whole in which the gifts of the poet, the painter and the
musician are all blended in proportions infinitely variable."
And was it not Schweitzer, again, who asked: "Is it the
painter or the poet who dominates in the soul of Michel¬
angelo?" and then added, "Many artists, like Goethe, have
passed from painting to verbal description and yet remain
what they were, that is, artists."
The preparation of this number has meant wading
through hundreds of biographies, autobiographies, intim¬
ate journals and letters. Indeed, if there is one thing
noteworthy about information on "author-artists" it is its
absence or inaccessibility.
This issue has no pretensions of being exhaustive either
in treatment or in coverage. Certain names have
undoubtedly been omitted because the authors' artistic
inclinations have escaped us; many others simply through
lack of space. We have therefore sought to restrict our
choice to a number of well-known novelists, playwrights
and poets from different lands. Painters who also wrote,
or musicians who also painted are not included. Thus,
Richard Wagner, for example, does not appear despite the
fact that there is hardly a scene, hardly a costume in his
Tetralogy and other operas for which he himself did not
make the preliminary sketches.
Nor are great works of art or masterpieces the major
criteria for inclusion. In most cases the author's genius
is obviously to be found in his writings not in his drawings.
Yet these drawings and paintings reveal an important
aspect of the author's character, and help us toward a
better understanding of the man and his writings. In
some cases, however, genius has revealed itself in both
writing and painting.
THE UNESCO COURIER hopes that readers will find as
much enjoyment and pleasure in this issue as the Editors
had in putting it together.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
FAMOUS AUTHORS
AS ARTISTS
******
? « * * *
* £ -i * A
6 ** .Í
"ONE MAY LIVE WITHOUT MEAT, but one
cannot dispense with bamboo. Lack of meat makes
one lean but lack of bamboo leads to vulgarity."
So runs a line of the famous poet-painter Su Tung P'o,
whose "Bamboo Branch" is reproduced above.
4.
by Bertha Gaster
Q Cavante once prepared to paint an angel", wrote the famous
1 J English poet Robert Browning, recreating Dante's descrip¬
tion of himself when he settled down to his only attempt
at painting when,
"Certain people of importance...
Entered and would seize forsooth, the poet.
Says the poet 'Then I stopped my painting'."
For Browning, the poet's desire to express himself, if only once,
in a medium alien to his genius, was inspired by love. "'Whom to
please? You whisper Beatrice. " Yet time and again great masters
of their own craft have been tempted by the sister arts, sometimes
in relaxation or play, sometimes in serious emulation. Raphael
wrote sonnets lost unfortunately, so we may never know their
value; Michelangelo wrote sonnets, and they have passed into the
Italian literary heritage. Ingres played the violin with passion, and
the phrase violon d'Ingres has passed into the French language
to describe any hobby.
Writers and poets, however, seem to have been more attracted to
the brush than painters to the pen, and the tradition goes back a
long way. It is said that Euripedes was fond of drawing, and that
it was one of Petrarch's amusements in his hours of ease. In
various civilizations a certain ability to paint or draw was as much
a part of a gentleman's education as the power to touch a lute
gracefully or turn a sonnet was in Renaissance Italy or Elizabethan
England. Under the Guptas in India, for example, from the fourth
to the sixth century, even the kings indulged in the painting of
miniatures, and every cultivated man owned his set of brushes and
.paints, though none of their works exists to-day.
With a few exceptions, however, the cultivated man who plays
with the arts, or the great writer who dabbles in painting or drawing,
is rarely more than a gifted amateur. It is the glory of China to
have produced, from the eighth to the twelfth centuries, a
constellation of poet-painters :" gentlemen-painters", they were
called to whom painting, writing and calligraphy were arts to be
practised in leisure hours when free from their duties as high and
responsible Government officials. Yet their poems are among the
finest jewels of Chinese literature, and their paintings enjoy the same
reputation, though few fully authenticated specimens survive.
The basis of their technical mastery was a profound study of
calligraphy, which in China, it should be remembered, is an art of
the brush. It is appreciated as a form of abstract painting, as a
"dance on paper", and the same technique in line and brush stroke,
the same standards of criticism, applied equally to the masterpieces
of handwriting and painting, all of the three arts, as it were,
intermingling. "When enjoying myself with Wang-Wei's poems,"
said Su Tung p'o, "I find pictures in them; when looking at Wang-
Wei's pictures I find in them poems."
Wang-Wei (699-759 A.D.), who for most of his
life occupied one important Government post after
another, and ended his life in Buddhist retreat, was
one of the earliest and greatest of the "gentlemen-
painters." Music, calligraphy, poetry, gardening,
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. August 1957
PAUL VALÉRY
Pupil of Degas
When in 1956 the Bibliothèque
Nationale in Paris held an
exhibition devoted to the works
of Paul Valéry, just 11 years after his
death, it gave a large section to the
many paintings, water colours, drawings,
and etchings which the great philoso¬
phical poet and French Academician
had produced during his lifetime. In
addition, two wax statuettes were shown,
one he had done of Mallarmé, the
other of Degas. Nine drawing books
were exhibited, the first done when he
was 17, the last when he was 71.
Valéry, in the "interior island" he had
created for himself had a veritable
passion for both art and architecture.
He was a pupil of Degas, copied the
Old Masters at the Louvre, and
deepened his knowledge of Italian art.
In the pages of his literary notebooks
and diaries one finds numerous drawings
full of fantasy which usually had
nothing to do with the subjects he was
writing about. Valéry did however
illustrate a number of his works himself,
amongst them The Graveyard by the
Sea (he was enchanted by what he
called "the sea eternally renewed" and
"the only intact and most ancient thing
in the world"). Valéry also did a series
of illustrations for his famous book
Monsieur Teste. Two of these, a water
colour and a wash drawing are repro¬
duced below and above. Left, a water
colour by Valéry of his study in the Rue
Gay-Lussac, in the Latin Quarter, Paris.
Wash-drawing (below) is owned by
Mme Paul Valéry, water-colour (above)
by Richard Anacréon, the author's
studio by Julien Cain.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
AUTHOR-ARTISTS
(Continued)
Line-and-brush 'dances on paper'
with China's gentlemen-painters
painting, in all of which he passed as
a master, were to him all alike as
pleasant recreations of his spare time.
His poems live today as part of
Chinese literature; his paintings
but listen to the tale told long ago by
one of his early biographers of
how one of them was accidentally
discovered.
The picture was called "Clearing
after Snowfall on the Mountains
. Along a River", and had been hidden
for many years in a lacquered bamboo
tube serving as a door bolt, which
eventually broke, revealing the scrolls.
"At first", related the owner, "I did
not believe in it, but after looking at
it several times my spirit was aroused.
I closed my door, burned incense, and
made myself free from all other
thingsthen I felt
the spirit of the 	
mountains, the
freshness of the
streams, and the
mist over the spring
garden... It was
really Wang-Wei's
refined spirit, fused
into water and ink,
which had produced
this precious thing."
Another of these
"gentlemen-paint¬
ers", perhaps the
greatest of them all,
was Su Tung p'o
(1036 - 1101 A.D.),
outstanding person¬
ality and great poet,
philosopher and
painter, who lived
under the Northern
Sung dynasty. As a
government official
he was enlightened
and progressive.
He built dams. He
improved the condi¬
tions of prisoners.
He even started a
very much earlier
Save the Children
Fund to rescue the
babies of poor pea¬
sants who were often
drowned because
their parents could
not afford to raise
them. His courage
and composure, his
human delight in the beauties of art
and nature, bore him through the
adversities of a political career which
would have broken the spirit of a
lesser man, and which left him to die
in poverty and exile. Here is his
own trenchant comment on political
life, in the poem written when his
infant son was three days old:
''Families, when a child is born
Want it to be intelligent.
I, through intelligence,
Having wrecked my whole life,
Only hope the baby will prove
Ignorant and stupid.
Then he will crown a tranquil life
By becoming a Cabinet Minister."
There are many stories of Su Tung
p'o and his group oí brilliant friends
6
meeting to make merry over wine, and
amusing themselves with the arts, the
great figure painter Li Lung-mien
adding figures to Su's landscapes, Su
making poems on Li's pictures. Su
specialized in the painting of bamboos,
and twisted dry trees beside stone and
water. "His wrinkled and sharp
rocks", said his friend Mi Fei, a
passionate collector of paintings and
calligraphy, "were queerly tangled
like sorrows coiled up in his breast."
One day Mi Fei invited Su Tung p'o
to dinner. "Two long tables were
placed facing each other, and on
them were piled fine brushes, exquisite
ink, and 300 sheets of paper, with
some food and drink at the side.
When Su Tung p'o saw this arrange¬
ment he laughed heartily and sat
TíS, Í* \
i
\,
M
' V
*M ^
DANTE GABRIEL ROSSETTI, lyric poet and painter, and leader of-the
Pre-Raphaelite School, was a great admirer of Dante, translating and illustrat¬
ing his works. Above, Rossetti's early pen and ink version (1849) of his
painting "Dante Drawing an Angel for First Anniversary of Beatrice's Death".
City Museum and Art Gallery, Birmingham.
down. Between each drink they
would flatten the paper and write.
(Su used to say that it was only when
exhilarated by wine that he could
write the "large grass characters" and
the "small model characters" really
well). Towards evening the wine was
giving out, and so was the paper.
Then each of them took the other's
papers and said good-bye. Afterwards
they found they had never done
better writing."
With a few strokes of the brush Su
Tung p'o would dash off little poems
on the shawl or fan presented by one
of the entertainers at the convivial
banquets he loved to attend:
"Oh hush the night, each minute an
[ounce of gold,
While -faintly floats the music of
[flute and song.
So fragrant the air, so cool the
[moonlit courtyard,
While darkly glides the silent night
[along." (1)
There have been periods in Euro¬
pean cultural history, moments, it
would seem, of great intellectual and
aesthetic expansion, like the Renais¬
sance, when the divisions between the
arts faded; when a Leonardo da Vinci
was painter, engineer, botanist, ana¬
tomist; a Cellini, painter, goldsmith,
writer; a Michelangelo, painter
sculptor and poet; but in the whole
course of European art there is
perhaps only one comparable figure
whose genius entitles him to rank
beside the "gentlemen-painters" of
China as an equally
undisputed master
in both literature
and painting the
English artist and
poet William Blake
(1757-1827).
Blake's poems and
designs might in one
sense be considered
his recreation after
the tedious toil of
engraving by which
he earned a humble
living a number of
the poems were en¬
graved and pulled
on single sheets and
then coloured by
hand for sale with
the assistance of his
devoted wife. Yet in
the deepest sense
they were the dedi¬
cated work of the
isolated and fiercely
independent mystic
who saw visions and
talked familiarly
with angels, dictat¬
ed, he claimed, by
the spiritual world.
"I may praise it",
he said, "since I dare
not pretend to be
any other than the
Secretary; the Au¬
thors are in Eter¬
nity", but he could
resort to blunt com¬
ment and caustic
epigram when roused:
"Thy friendship oft has made my
[heart to ache,
Do be my enemy, -for friendship's
[sake."
Blake was an isolated phenomenon,
unrecognized in his own lifetime by
all save a few perceptive friends. A
passion for painting, sketching and
drawing, however, seems to have
possessed many of the writers and
poets of the Romantic revival and
later European movements.
It may have been, as
an eminent critic of
Victor Hugo maintain-
(1) Translated by Lin
Yutang in The Gag Genius.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. August 1957
Hermann Hesse
FAIRY TALE
IN PARADISE
Hermann Hesse has been rank¬
ed with Thomas Mann as "'the
greatest contemporary German
author," yet his writings were
little known outside German-
speaking countries until he won
the Nobel Prize for Literature
in 1946. Since then the author
of Steppenwolf, Narcissus and
Goldmitnd, Siddharta, Magister
Lttdi, and Demian has become
one of the world's most trans¬
lated authors (see the Unesco
Courier, Feb. 1957: 104 trans¬
lations published between 1948-
1955; 16 of his great philo¬
sophical novels translated in
Japan alone during 1955).
Hesse, born in Germany 80 years ago, has lived in Swit¬
zerland since 1912 and became a Swiss citizen in 1923.
In 1921, an album of his water colours, Elf Aquarelle aus
dem Tessin (Eleven Water Colours of the Canton of Ticino)
was issued by a Munich publisher. One of these, The village
of Ticino, is reproduced here. But perhaps Hesse's most
interesting undertaking as an artist is his delightful, though
unfortunately untranslated and little-known fairy tale Piktor's
Verwandlungen (The Metamorphosis of Piktor) which he
wrote and illustrated in the twenties. The tiny volume was
produced with the text either in Hesse's own handwriting
or typewritten, the illustrations for each copy being hand-
coloured by Hesse. For each copy Hesse modified his draw¬
ings according to his mood of the moment. A facsimile
edition of one of the handwritten manuscript copies was
published in 1954 by a German publisher, Suhrkamp Verlag
(Frankfurt-am-Main). The two illustrations, left, are taken
from this manuscript copy.
The Metamorphosis of Piktor is a fairy tale about a young
man, Piktor (the German word contains the meaning of
"painter") who arrives in Paradise in search of happiness.
He finds a world peopled by trees which are both man and
woman, moon and sun. He watches a bird turn into a
flower, then into a butterfly, then into a dazzling precious
stone. Learning that the stone will grant his wish, he seizes
it and asks to become a tree. For years he is content to be
a tree, until he realizes that everything else round him can
change form at will. True happiness, he discovers, requires
change. But Piktor remains a tree until one day a beautiful
girl appears and sits beneath his tree. A bird flies past,
drops the magic jewel from its beak. On picking it up, the
girl's secret wish is immediately granted. She turns into a
branch on the Piktor-tree and
rises until she is alongside him.
From a half-tree Piktor has
become a full-tree. Henceforth
he is able to change into any
form he wants and has found
true Paradise. "He became a
deer, he became a fish, he
became a man, a snake and a
cloud and a bird. But in every
shape he was complete for he
was a pair. In him he had the
sun and the moon, man and
wife; he flowed like a twin-
stream through the land, and
stood like a double-star in the
heavens." Inset (right) is from
a typewritten manuscript.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
NIKOLAI GOGOL
Illustrator of 'Dead Souls'
Nikolai Gogol (1809-1852) the great Russian novelist and dramatist, is
one author whose drawings have been used to illustrate the cover of
his books. He drew the illustration for the cover of his classic
novel, Mertvuiyo Dushi ('Dead Souls') with its amazingly descriptive pic¬
tures of Russian provincial life and types of Russian society. Gogol had
originally intended to be a painter, and art problems figure prominently
in his works. He looked at the world around him with the eyes of a painter,
and once wrote: "My imagination... has never created anything that my
eyes have not chanced upon somewhere in Nature." Gogol's Dead Souls,
written while he was staying in Romea city which left a deep impression
on his mindwas first published in 1842, with his own drawing on the cover.
The same cover was used for the second edition (above) in 1846.
AUTHOR- ARTISTS (Cont'd)
THE PROLIFIC
19TH CENTURY
ed, that the arts never overlapped in
more classical periods, but that in the
Romantic Revival a palpitating sensi¬
bility took precedent over reason, and
language and painting came closer
together, language being used some¬
what as a brush, to paint impressions
rather than to express thoughts.
But it may also be connected more
prosaically with the 'fact that drawing
was one of the accomplishments of
the polite young person of the period.
woman must have a thorough
knowledge of music, singing, drawing,
dancing and the modern languages to
deserve the word accomplished", cries
Miss Bingley in Jane Austen's Pride
and Prejudice. Young Goethe (1749-
1832) for instance, who led the way,
was promptly given a drawing teacher
by his father when he displayed a
taste for art. He studied art seriously
at Leipzig during his student days,
drew and sketched throughout most
his life, and on several occasions had
thoughts of giving up poetry and
devoting himself entirely to painting.
Landscapes of his abound, and he did
illustrations to some of his books and
portraits of intimate friends.
In France, in the eighteen-twenties,
they all painted and drew. As
Wordsworth wrote: "Bliss was it in
that dawn to be alive, but to be young
was very heaven." There was Prosper
Mérimée (1803-1870), the brilliant and
cynical young author who passed off
his first book, a series of mordant
one-act sketches, as the work of a
non-existent refugee Spanish actress,
and later became the trusted coun¬
sellor of the Empress Eugenie whom
he had taken out to buy ices when she
was nothing but the engaging little
daughter of a close friend. On his
journeys as Inspector of Antiquities
he filled notebooks with sketches of
the country; he drew caricatures with
easy familiarity and "scattered them
around like cigar butts" "sufficiently
amusing", said Sainte Beuve, the
French literary critic "'for everyone to
recognize himself as rather more ugly
than in reality." And a whole series
of water colours and drawings,
unpublished as yet, which were to
remind a woman of the charmed
hours they spent together, bear wit¬
ness to a love affair of more than
twenty years that nearly broke his
heart when it ended.
There was young Théophile Gau¬
tier (1811-1870) in his defiant red
waistcoat and with his hair floating
to his shoulders, who started as an art
student and abandoned painting for
poetry and novels and art criticism.
There was Alfred de Musset (1810-
1857) with his charming portrait of
Pauline de Garcia. And there was
young Mme Dudevant, (1804-1876)
preparing to break away from hus¬
band and home for the independence
she later found as a novelist under
the name of George Sand, who thought
she might turn to account a gift for
sketching and catching a resemblance,
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. August 1957
and sat down to draw ten hours a day
at her country house. She soon
relinquished the idea, but the young
woman who finally arrived in Paris
in 1831 and jumped 'from the coach in
her velvet jacket and coarse hunting
trousers, cap and men's boots, looking
a duplicate of the two excited
students waiting to welcome her, had
also made attempts to earn money by
decorating little boxes and fans with
flowers and birds in water colour, and
exposing them, vainly, for sale in shop
windows.
There was one among them,
however the greatest whose draw¬
ings and paintings bear in them some
authentic overspill of genius. A visitor
to the Victor Hugo Museum, situated
in the author's old home in Paris, is
immediately struck by the profusion
of drawings, sketches and paintings
by Victor Hugo (1802-1885), hung
along the walls, and by their remark¬
able quality.
Some 450 drawings are in existence,
varying from stamp to canvas
size. The drawings of old Gothic
castles and cathedrals recall his
travels through France, Germany and
Switzerland, and his passion for pic¬
turesque architecture, set high on
rocky summits over sombre gorges and
rushing rivers, all seen through the
wild gleams of storm and lightning
and set in the play of menacing
darknesses. He drew illustrations for
some of his books such as the
completed series for Toilers of the
Sea sketched out ideas and rough
conceptions on the same page of the
notebooks as the written descriptions,
and though uninterested in portrait¬
ure, produced drawing after drawing
of grotesque and preternatural figures,
grimacing and monstrous faces. Many
spring from the hallucinations which
haunted him in his first years of exile
in Jersey, and which he would
sometimes jot down in the dark on
awakening.
A few large, carefully conceived
designs date from the middle of his
career, the period after the death of
his daughter from drowning when for
a while he could write no more. These,
such as Bourg à la Croix and Castle
in Moonlight, are not drawn, but
painted in ink. He worked on them
in the early morning, when his first
breakfast was brought him when a
sprinkling of black coffee bronzed the
black with warm tones, the coffee
grounds added to the texture of old
rock, a streak of sunlight on the slope
of brown hillside was laid on with
café au lait.
Responsible critics took his work
seriously. The volume of Son¬
nets and Etchings of 1869 which
marked the emergence of a new school
of etching included a design of Victor
Hugo's among such names as Corot,
Doré, Daubigny and Manet. Baude
laire and Gautier, both fine critics oí
art, spoke enthusiastically of his
drawings. "Victor Hugo's talent",
wrote Gautier, "whether in writing or
drawing is remarkable in that it is
accurate and iantastic at the same
time", while another critic described
him as a "Turner of the night."
Just as the visitor to the Hugo
Museum in Paris is struck by Hugo's
artistic capacity, so the pilgrim who
visits an old parsonage at Haworth
on the edge of the Yorkshire moors
in England where a great English
writer, Charlotte Brontë (1816-1855)
and her equally famous sister Emily
lived out their short and solitary lives,
is struck by the strange imaginative
fervour that breathes through the
correctly drawn, minutely detailed
drawings of Charlotte Brontë display¬
ed on the walls. Her drawings illus¬
trated the amazing saga of the
private world invented by the Brontë
children and set down in tiny
volumes; Charlotte copied engravings
with such detailed exactness as to
injure her sight; and there at Haworth
Parsonage hanging on the wall is a
water colour by her which in a flash
calls to mind the incident in Jane
Eyre where Mr. Rochester examines
Jane's drawings, so similar Ls the
subject. "Were you happy when you
painted those pictures?", asked
Mr. Rochester, and who can doubt
that it is Charlotte Brontë answering
in Jane's voice: "I was absorbed, sir;
yes, and I was happy. To paint
them, in short, was to enjoy one of
the keenest pleasures I have known."
Alexander Pushkin (1799-1837),
Russia's greatest poet, drew intermin¬
ably in his lighter moments, cari¬
catures of himsel'f and his friends and
enemies, half portraits, women's faces
scribbled on the margins of his
manuscripts. In the year of his
death another famous Russian writer,
Nicolai Gogol (1809-1852) who was
staying in Italy, passed days in the
company of his friend, the Russian
poet Dzukovsky, sketching views
Rome. Gogol had
originally intended to
be a painter. When he
he first went to St.
Petersburg from his
native U k r ai n e, he
E.T.A. HOFFMANN. Ernst Theodor
Wilhelm (he later changed "Wilhelm" to
"Amedeus" to conform to the then-prevailing
" Mozart " cult) Hoffmann, the German
Romance writer, was also a composer, thea¬
trical manager, lawyer and many other things
in the course of his diversified career.
Hoffmann (1776-1822) provided the Inspi¬
ration and the book for Offenbach's Tales of
Hoffmann, based on three of his fantastic stor¬
ies. Among the many drawings and carica¬
tures he left were sketches for costumes,
theatrical plans, scenery for his opera Undine
and cover illustrations for his humoristic story,
Lebensonsichten des Katers Murr. Below
and left, Hoffmann's illustrations for volumes II
and III of this work and, above, an aquarelle.
on
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
AUTHOR-ARTISTS
(Continued)
Twentieth century names
Follow in swift succession
wrote to his mother how he still went
to classes at the Academy of Fine
Arts three times a week. "I'm attend¬
ing a course in painting ; I cannot
give it up."
All through the nineteenth century
writer-artists follow each other in
swift succession. We have a brief
glimpse of Charles Dickens interview¬
ing and turning down a young
artist who presented himself with
sample drawings applying to take
over the illustrations to the Pickwick
Paperp, then appearing in fortnightly
parts. The young man later turned
to literature, and became Dickens's
most formidable rival as W.M. Thack¬
eray. Gautier, Thackeray, the Swiss
novelist Keller, the English critic
Ruskin, all started with the intention
of becoming professional painters, and
found their true vocation later.
Dante Gabriel Rossetti was equally
a poet and a professional painter;
William Morris, poet, decorator, dyer,
printer, socialist and revolutionary in
nearly everything he touched, was for
a brief period influenced by Ruskin to
try to paint. Charles Baudelaire, the
French poet, haunting the studios of
Delacroix, Manet and Daumier in his
youth, had a remarkable power of
fixing a likeness in a few astonishing
lines. "He would have been a great
artist", said Daumier, "if he had not
preferred to be a great poet."
For most of these writers sketching
was a light-hearted exuberance,
another way of writing letters, another
way of expressing the warmth and
laughter of companionship. Verlaine,
Rimbaud and their friend Delahaye
illustrated their letters to each other
with caricatures and recounted their
adventures and experiences as Ver¬
laine himself put it:
"Two comrades let us be, gossiping
[each to each
Quick with our fingers in sharp
[sketch and in laughing speech."
So did H.G. Wells, the English
novelist. So did Garcia Lorca, the
Spanish poet and dramatist.
Other names come crowding to
mindTolstoy, Pierre Loti, G. B. Shaw,
Apollinaire, Valéry, George Moore,
Max Jacob, Saint-Exupéry, Henri Mi¬
chaux, Dostoeivsky, Winston Chur¬
chill, Gustavo Bécquer, O. Henry,
Alfred de Vigny, Eugene Sue, W.
James, Vercors, Rodolphe TöpfTer,
Wyndham Lewis, Ibsen, Yeats, Evelyn
Waugh, Samuel Butler, Anatole France
and many others. But let us finish
with an American loved on both sides
of the Atlantic for the drawings he
turns out of his sinister dogs, lugu¬
brious males and battle-axe females,
and for his enchanting and wry
essays in humour James Thurber, a
master in both mediums.
Photo courtesy Dictionnaire des fuvres. Laffont-Bompiani.
D.H. Lawrence: Stormy petrel of English letters
Perhaps as much for his personality and for his ideas and attitudes as for his actual writing, D.H. (David Herbert) Lawrence, the English novel¬
ist, poet, essayist and playwright, is regarded as one of the outstanding literary figures of the 20th century. During the time he was writing
famous novels like Sons and Lovers and The Plumed Serpent and his many poems and short stories, he travelled widely, visiting or
living at one time or another Italy, Switzerland, Australia, Ceylon, New Zealand, Tahiti, the French Riviera, Mexico and the United States.
In Taos, New Mexico, an artists' colony, he once dreamed of setting up an ideal social community. Towards the end of his life (he died in I 930
of tuberculosis at the age of 44) he began to paint and in I 928 held an exhibition of his works in London. It was raided by the police on
the grounds of immorality. Today the exhibition would hardly cause astir. Three figures shown here are from his work, "The Resurrection".
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
HANS
CHRISTIAN
ANDERSEN
'Scissor fantasies'
for gingerbread
The Unesco Courier. August 1957
Hans Christian Andersen could
do amazing things with a pair of
scissors. It was the queer
deftness of his huge hands which was
partly responsible for his mother's
determination to make him
a tailor in his early youth.
In his autobiography, The
True Story of My Life, the
Danish author of The Ugly
Duckling and other immor¬
tal fairy tales recalls that
"I spent my time over my
peep show and my puppet
theatre, and my greatest
happiness consisted in col¬
lecting bright pieces of
cloth and silk which I cut
out myself and sewed. My
mother regarded it as a
good exercise preparatory to
my becoming a tailor."
In Copenhagen and else¬
where he later delighted
children by cutting fantas¬
tic figures dancers, swans,
storks and castles out of
paper as rapidly as he talk¬
ed. One midsummer eve¬
ning, his biographer Signe
Toksvig relates, he was
sitting in a country inn in
Sweden by the clear bright¬
ness of Lake Siljan when
the little granddaughter of
his hostess ran in, eager to
have a look at his coloured carpet-bag,
Scotch plaid, and the bright red lining
in his small trunk. Quickly he seized a
sheet of paper and cut out a whole
Turkish mosque, minarets and windows,
and she ran happily out with it. Soon
he saw a crowd of men and women in
the yard standing around the girl's
grandmother who was holding the mos¬
que over her head, out of reach of the
child. A few minutes later, the grand¬
mother came to Andersen's room with
a plateful of gingerbread in various
shapes.
"I bake the best gingerbread in
Dalarne," she said, "but the shapes are
old. The gentleman cuts out such
beautiful things. Might he not be able
to cut us some new shapes?"
Bewitched by her pleading and by the
polite Swedish use of the third person,
Andersen stayed up almost the entire
Northern midsummer night and cut out
shapes for gingerbread: nutcrackers with
long boots, windmills that
included the miller, men in
slippers with a door in the
stomach, dancers who
pointed a leg skywards. The
old woman was delighted.
"New shapes they will be,"
she chanted, "but difficult !"
Andersen also liked to
draw and did it fairly well,
though with a little stiffness.
He has left a number of
albums filled with little
drawings, little verses and
soft sentiments about
muses and poetry (he
always considered him¬
self a poet even after
gaining fame with his
children's tales). Most are
sketches he made during his
trips to Elsinore, to Flor¬
ence, Rome and other
places in Italy, or are sou¬
venirs of his voyages to
Turkey and Germany. Hans
Christian Andersen suffered
great privations in his youth
but in later life he was
honoured by kings, queens,
poets and scholars who vied
with one another in sharing his company.
Illustrations on this page are three
fairy tale "scissor fantasies", cut out in
paper by Andersen. They are owned
by the Andersen Museum in Odense,
the little town in Denmark where Hans
Christian was born.
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Pen drawings for his children
ROUND THE WORLD
IN EIGHTY DAYS
WITH LEO TOLSTOY
by A. Chifman
Leo Tolstoy Museum, Moscow
ALL DRAWINGS COURTESY L. TOLSTOY MUSEUM. MOSCOW
ifcii*
TT, 2om
, ^ftíjm meó*
LEO TOLSTOY added some expressive strokes to the vast panorama
of the Caucasus that unfolds in his written works with drawings (top of
these pages) he made as a young officer stationed In this part of Russia.
Later In life he compiled a merry reading book in which he drew men,
animals or objects familiar to children to correspond to each
letter. Thus he made the study of the alphabet easy and amusing.
12
Among the 160,000 pages of the precious manuscripts
of Leo Tolstoy, which are carefully preserved in a
specially equipped "steel room" in the Moscow
museum, are a number oí drawing by the great writer
rapid sketches in ordinary pencil or ink that stir the heart
and fire the imagination.
Leo Tolstoy had a very lofty conception of the visual
arts, claiming that they were capable of uniting all men
in the bonds of love and friendship. He counted many
painters among his friends and encouraged their work.
He himself drew but seldom, being convinced that he had
no artistic talent. The few drawings which have been
handed down to us among his manuscripts and papers are
therefore all the more precious.
The first series ai Tolstoy's drawings dates from the
middle of the last century, when, as a young officer, he
was doing his military service in the Russian army in the
Caucasus. The iwild beauty of the Caucasian landscape,
the men of the Caucasus, strong and free as the wind, the
romantic ruggedness of the mountains all captivated him.
Of his literary masterpieces, the tales: The Invasion, A
Wood Felling, The Cossacks and, later, his unrivalled
Hadji Murat, reveal the young writer's admiration for the
Caucasus and its people. Tolstoy's drawings of that period
add some expressive strokes to his vast panorama of the
Caucasus.
One of them (drawing 1) is the figure of an old man.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courler. August 1)57
?^«1tii
©
The proud poise of his head, the steady gaze of his eyes,
show that he has a proper self-respect. He is obviously
poor, for his shirt is in tatters and, through the holes,
his broad bare chest can be seen; but he will never bend
the knee to any man. Who is he? Probably a simple
Cossack, dwelling in one of the Russian villages of the
North Caucasian plain. Tolstoy met many such men, and
it is they who subsequently became the heroes of his
wonderful tale, The Cossacks.
There is another head of an old man (drawing 2) ;
something in this face also must have attracted the writer.
What is it? Let us cast our minds back to the picturesque
figure of Uncle Erochka in The Cossacks. He was a huge
Cossack, with a thick mop of tangled hair, bristling eye¬
brows and penetrating eyes. A free son of the steppes,
he personified the rugged beauty and courageous spirit of
the peasants of the Caucasian foot-hills. It can hardly
be claimed that this is a drawing oí Erochka himself; it
may represent another of the author's friends at that
time. Yet this old man undoubtedly reminds us of the
hero of Tolstoy's tale.
The head of. an old man with a fur cap (drawing 3)
belongs this time to one of another type. He is certainly
a highlander, a warlike inhabitant of one of the Cauca¬
sian mountain hamlets which are always on bad terms
with the Russian villages. Did that proud bearing and
the steady and resolute gaze, fixed on some distant hori
zon, perhaps suggest to the author the -future hero of one
of his stories, the legendary figure of Hadji Murat? In
this tale, written towards the end of his life, Tolstoy
extolled the courage, pride and inflexible will of a free
man. At the same time, in Hadji Murat, he expressed his
hatred of war and his longing to see peace and friendship
reign among the nations.
The second series of Tolstoy's drawings consists oí 17
illustrations of Jules Verne's novel: Around the World in
Eighty Days. Tolstoy loved Jules Verne for his intelli¬
gence and unquenchable thirst for knowledge, his consum¬
mate skill in winding up a story, and the boldness of his
heroes. Tolstoy read Jules Verne's novels aloud to his
children during the long winter evenings at Yasnaya
Polyana. In order to impress the episodes of the novel
with greater vividness and clarity on the minds of his
young listeners, he produced these simple and amusing
drawings (drawings 5 to 7, next page).
Tolstoy's son, Ilya, tells in his memoirs how this remark¬
able series came into being: "At this point in our child¬
hood, we were tremendously keen on Jules Verne's novels.
Father used to bring us these books from
Moscow and, every evening, we gathered
round to hear him read The Adventures of
Captain Grant's Children, Twenty Thous¬
and Leagueß under the Sea, From the
Earth to the Moon, Meridiana; or the
13
Cont'd
on
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
ROUND THE WORLD
WITH LEO TOLSTOY
(Continued)
Adventures of Three Englishmen and
Three Russians in South Africa and
Around the World in Eighty Days.
"As this last novel was not illustrat¬
ed, Father set about Illustrating it
himself. Every day, he prepared pen
drawings for the evening and they
were so attractive that we liked them
far better than the illustrations in
the other books.
"I remember, as though it were still
before my eyes, one of his drawings of
a Buddhist goddess, with several heads
adorned with serpents she was fan¬
tastic and terrible. My father had
never learned to draw, but he could
turn his hand to anything, and we
were all delighted.
"We looked forward impatiently to
the evening. We scrambled over the
round table towards him every time
he came to an episode which he had
illustrated, when he would stop read¬
ing and pull out his drawing from
under the book."
Tolstoy produced his third and
last series of drawings in the
eighteen-seventies, when he was
working on his famous Reading-book.
Not satisfied with those in existence,
the author invented one of his own a
merry reading-book, to be used, he
hoped, by all Russian children, from
those of the Czar of those of the
humblest peasant. In this book, each
letter had a corresponding drawing of
a man, animal or object familiar to
children (drawing 4). The vivid draw¬
ing was intended to help the child to
learn the necessary letter and then
the whole word. In this way Tolstoy
linked up reading with real life and
made the study of the alphabet easy
and amusing.
Tolstoy's desire to express his ideas
not only in words but also in drawings
persisted throughout his life. Spe¬
cialists who study War and Peace are
familiar with his pencil sketches of
the battlefield of Borodino, for exam¬
ple, which he made when he visited
that spot for the purposes of his novel.
Later, Tolstoy often made drawings
in his diary and notebooks when he
felt the need to give visual expression
to a particularly difficult and compli¬
cated idea.
Tolstoy's genius is not to be sought
in his drawings. It lay in his extra¬
ordinary ability to convey images in
words. We nevertheless prize these
drawings, which have fortunately
been preserved; in a way, they help
us to a -fuller understanding and ap¬
preciation of this great man.
14
0
/ ,
l/'/¿C/J 'S*f¿t'(í.}¿ :r rW<* V-l^y.. ,-;/>- '
&
GREAT ADMIRER OF JULES VERNE, Tolstoy read the French writer's novels
aloud to his children. Each evening they gathered around him to listen to these
prophetic stories of submarines, airplanes and other inventions which then had the
quality of dreams. As one of the books, Around the World in 80 Days was not illustrated,
Tolstoy set about making drawings for it himself, including the three shown here.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. August 1957
THE TRUE TREASURE
OF 'TREASURE ISLAND'
nm
Considering the tale behind it, the true treasure of
Treasure Island is a map 16 inches by 10 inches
drawn by Robert Louis Stevenson and which inspired
him to write his masterpiece of adventure.
Stevenson himself has told the story of how his famous
romance came to be written. In an article which appear¬
ed in the Idler, August 1894, Stevenson recounts that he
drew a map one day
in collaboration with
his schoolboy step¬
son, Lloyd Osbour-
ne. Of it Stevenson
says that he "made
the map of an is¬
land ; it was elabor¬
ately and (I thought)
beautifully coloured;
the shape of it took
my fancy beyond ex¬
pression: it contained
harbours that pleased
me like sonnets: with
the unconsciousness
of the predestined,
I ticketed my perfor¬
mance Treasure Is¬
land."
Further on, in the
same article, Steven¬
son recounts the sad
fate of this first map,
and tells how the
present map, known
through reproduction
to thousands of his
readers, came to be
drawn: "The time
came when it was
decided to publish,
and I sent in my
manuscript and the
map along with it...
The proofs came, they
were corrected, but I
heard nothing of the
map. I wrote and
asked; was told it had
never been received,
and sat aghast. It is
one thing to draw a
map at random, set a
scale in one corner of
it at a venture, and write up a story to the measurements.
It is quite another to have to examine a whole book, make
an inventory of all the allusions contained in it, and with
a pair of compasses, painfully design a map to suit the
data. I did it, and the map was drawn again in my
father's office, with embellishments of blowing whales
and sailing ships, and my father himself brought into
service a knack he had of various writing, and elaborately
Photo courtesy N.Y. Put-:ic Library
forged the signature of Captain Flint and the sailing
directions of Billy Bones."
This famous manuscript map, reproduced here, is
beautifully drawn in exact imitation of an old engraved
map of the period of the story, with an elaborate vignette
at top depicting mermen with dolphins and sea-birds, and
further embellished with sailing vessels of the 18th cent¬
ury. At a spot in the
island a notation in
red ink reads "Bulk
of Treasure Here".
At bottom is Captain
Flint's note of Treas-'
ure Island, dated
August 1, 1750, and
words "Facsimile of
Chart; latitude and
longitude struck out
by J. Hawkins".
Below this is written,
"Given by above J.F.
(lint) to Mr. W. Bones,
Maite of ye Walrus,
Savannah, this twenty
July, 1754, W. B."
Manuscript map is
now in A. Edward
Newton Collection and
is reproduced and
described in Mr. New¬
ton's This Book-Col¬
lecting Game.
Stevenson's ability
. to draw this map
came from his train¬
ing as a civil engineer
and his study of
drawing as a youth.
He has left us a
number of landscapes
drawn while living in
southern France, and
wood engravings. He
often made quick
sketches of the char¬
acters in his books
before setting about
describing them in
words. Stevenson's
inherent gift for re¬
taining the images of
the places he visited and the people he met is revealed
in the descriptive mastery of his works.
Although seriously ill all his life Stevenson lived adven¬
turously and travelled widely in Belgium, France and the
Pacific Islands. For his health's sake he eventually settled
with his family in Samoa. When he died in 1894 at the
age of 44, sixty Samoans carried his body to the top of
Mount Vaea where he now lies buried.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
RABINDRANATH TAGORE
1 have fallen under the enchantment of lines'
Ir was 1928. Rabindranath Tagore stood
at the pinnacle of fame and success. He
was the Poet Laureate of Asia, the Sen¬
tinel of the East, Asia's first Nobel Prize
winner for Literature. His writings had
been translated into all the major languages
of the world. Honours had been heaped
upon him by learned societies and humble
institutions alike, and he was the subject of
a veritable cult in India and his native
Bengal. As poet, dramatist, essayist, short
story writer, musician, humanist, philoso¬
pher and educationist, his genius was uni¬
versally recognized.
Then, at the age of 67, Tagore felt an
irresistible urge for a new form of expres¬
sion. A latent genius long asleep within
him suddenly revealed itself, and the vener¬
able sage of India became a painter. For
twelve years he devoted his energy to
drawing and painting, little by little aban¬
doning his writer's pen. When he died in
1941 at the age of 80, he had produced
nearly 2,000 works of art, of extraordinary
design and strange rhythmic beauty.
The poet turned to painting when he dis¬
covered that his hand was moving automa¬
tically across the pages of his manuscripts,
transforming the scratches and erasures into
by
Sandy Koffler
Mother and child
designs. "I have fallen under the enchant¬
ment of lines," he explained.
Rabindranath's scratches and erasures
took the form of thin horizontal threads
which he enclosed in an outline something
like a cartouche. Various cartouches
scattered over a page became so many
islands, each with its own form and volume.
Tagore joined up this archipelago of scrat¬
ches with soft and flowy curves to form a
rhythmic arabesque of masses and discon¬
nections, nerves and flexures that stretched
out into a beak, a bird in the air, or a vase
decorated with incisions and designs.
Never before had Rabindranath felt this
impulse to convert his manuscripts into
patterns and shapes. At first he considered
them the playful products of his leisure
hours. (In his younger days he had made
pencil sketches and ink designs in a drawing
book, magnificently bound in black leather.)
But he soon discovered that "the scratches
in my manuscript cried, like sinners, for
salvation," and that the desire to "rescue
them into a merciful finality of rhythm"
was too strong to be easily shaken off.
Thus more designs and drawings came to
be made until Tagore became conscious
that a hidden force was being manifested
within him, and undertook to paint in
earnest.
His first exhibition, held
in the Galerie Pigalle in Continued
Paris in 1930, created a
sensation not only in the
French capital but in India
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
K\:
ï *'
S _ »l'JEÎi , *t 4T1? « '
Wr -X -i -Î.- *1 ^-;; ¿f£ it. .
-r * ,' -
* . * . >v *
Tagore painted most of his works on paper using Ink or flower petals as pigments.
He rarely gave them titles, though he called them "my versification in lines."
The Unesco Courier. August 1957
Ami.
i it, *Om fJtA, Af iifv^J ibfuA^t, ttc.liiy* ft U\U*tjli*<
U .'»i.*, *k¡ A^Af uUt Lu*** (vu f**t, Ik it w»«A»«Ç
1¿A.,¡H (a ¡jtltcAt, uittkmA «O lVW.».,í,í«j lAA.t\.<.i*
jj*n* tU «uWiuHlti IaÍ^a^. tt uiAtuCrtj Ut akJ. 4v<
kMMl.. A. It, 6 ImA Kt fa,trA t ~,«fe tmUtUit nttmAmrU.
Ami tUf-AjA A) r*.t. v eWt***¿M «O <&&*m £ a,Ía.Jf)fift.J.L
¿'aaLy**} tnulihlm*. % f*tM* utiU k\a,o lu, i ín\ i¿, tjjmti
-*H CUL IWÍaa Ía *
4^V* Ha ,
H
""f*
í IaaA A tU UaJZík n.n£,í¿t
* Jfcfc,
7/.»
» *fj.*.\f<e¿s
?.U*.L *df Lut / ít-^/lá/lüC 44 C
K»l 4.4 ^.».¿.¿.l ¿tV »V, tMÂtÂKQ VU- K¿tvtlLj./
rV*»«*f
^«***?*""' »y.Zi-VCT
"<AnÄ ^^tm^,A^¡
JttlLvt itMAjttf tt tt^AjJ. 4{\xLa*J <(-. (,;f»/«4*. Xl &4.£t Ä*C t\
«J¿4% .n> X,\,L\t £,.
AX./.T,.
6n <-»
NIWVttA** Wv(t IVVt I&JÍ ' -4 ÍjC A««. (*.* 4
- t-X^fJ..* \Aa*JUL fi C|
« «<W«*J *
A Tagore manuscript in English. Scratches such as
these inspired him to turn to painting and etching.
Figure
The exhausted pilgrims
TAGORE ACCOMPANIED ABOVE
PAINTING BY THE FOLLOWING POEM :
The pain has ceased
though its pathos lingers
like a still evening
at the close of a rain-loud day.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
where nis own countrymen were astounded to learn that their
beloved poet was also a painter. The same year a few examples
of his works were shown in London, Berlin and New York. His
first exhibition in India came in February, 1932 when 265 of
his drawings, paintings and engravings were displayed to the public
in Calcutta, followed the next year by another exhibition in
Bombay. In 1946, four of his paintings were included in an
international exhibition of modern art organized by Unesco in
Paris.
Nevertheless, to the world at large, Rabindranath Tagore the
Painter still remains practically unknown.
Many of the great poet's drawings and paintings have an air of
having been done on the spur of the moment and often were.
Once begun, a painting took possession of him and left him no
pause until it was finished. He worked with great zest and gusto,
drawing rapidly and without faltering or stopping to ponder and
correct.
Although he used all kinds of paints and produced coloured
chalk drawings, pastels, and later dry-points and etchings, Tagore's
preferred medium was liquid colour. He used any ink at hand,
usually ordinary fountain-pen ink. When this was not available,
he crushed flower petals and used them as pigments. To obtain
a glossy effect he chose different kinds of oils, particularly coconut
oil and mustard oil. He rarely used a brush (when he did it was
a home-made version) and disdained the artist's palette. Instead,
he worked with cloth soaked in colour, the back of a fountain pen,
his thumb, a stick or, more often, a knife.
Tagore was associated with the most celebrated painters and
artists of the world for over half a century. In the course of his
many voyages to foreign lands he acquired a profound first-hand
knowledge of both Oriental and Western art. On a visit to Japan,
for instance, he once left on a week-end trip to see a private art
collection in Yokohama and stayed on for three months to make
a minute study of the technique and styles of Japanese and Chi¬
nese painting. So deep was his interest in art that in 1920 he
even founded an art school at Santiniketan.
Yet, despite all this, Tagore's art is peculiarly his own, without
ties to either the past or the present. Rabindranath followed no set
rules ; his works are the spontaneous creations which sprang from
his fertile imagination, simple, yet disconcerting, original, totally
sincere and idealistic. Like his poetry they are deeply thought-
provoking and shrouded in mystery, the outpouring of a man ena¬
moured of pure beauty, form and colour. "My morning was full
of songs," Tagore said, "'let sunset days be full of colour."
When Tagore began to paint after fifty years as a writer, he
discarded many barriers and explored new ground. "He seemed,"
cJt-aXritd ft M\ -¿Wu/t^eZ" 'thMJ)
^l/r\2s its ILftnuAÛ tAJy^
Ajit Mookerjee recently wrote, '"to have broken away from an
inhibited world and released the primal forces of the unconscious."
When his painting was called that of a madman, Tagore remark¬
ed : '"My pictures did not have their origin in trained discipline,
in tradition, and deliberate attempt at illustration."
The poet's imagination delighted in the mysterious, but his
works of art were not intended as a metaphysical or mystical
expression. "It would be a great mistake," Ananda K. Coomaras-
wamy pointed out before Tagore's death, '"to search in them for
hidden spiritual symbolism ; they are not meant to be deciphered
like puzzles or code messages. ...It is obvious that the poet must
have looked at many pictures in the course of his long life ; but
there is nothing in his own work to show that he has seen them.
This is a genuinely original, genuinely naive expression; extraor¬
dinary evidence of eternal youth persistent in a hoary and vener¬
able personage."
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. August 1957
Rabindranath Tagore
(continued)
Let sunset days
be full of colour'
¿¿JIM Hj. 4<Ü\tM tf b* »¿VMAly ,
^¿kk.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
'A TINY BUBBLE IN THE SILENCE
OF THE INFINITE'
by Rabindranaih Tagore
An apology is due from me for my intrusion into the
world of pictures and thus offering a perfect instance
to the saying that those who do not know that they
know not are apt to be rash where angels are timidly
careful. I, as an artist, cannot claim any merit for my
courage; for it is the unconscious courage of the unsophis¬
ticated, like that of one who walks in dream on perilous path,
who is saved only because he is blind to the risk.
The only training which I
had from my young days was
the training in rhythm, the
rhythm in thought, the rhythm
in sound. I had come to
know that rhythm gives reality
to that which is desultory,
which is insignificant in itself.
And therefore, when the scrat¬
ches in my manuscript cried,
like sinners, for salvation, and
assailed my eyes with the
ugliness of their irrelevance, I
often took more time in
rescuing them into a merciful
finality of rhythm than in
carrying on what was my
obvious task.
in the process of this salvage
work I came to discover one
fact, that in the universe of
forms there is a perpetual acti¬
vity of natural selection in
lines, and only the fittest sur¬
vives which has in itself the
fitness of cadence, and I felt
that to solve the unemployment
problem of the homeless hete¬
rogeneous into interrelated
balance of fulfilment, is crea¬
tion itself.
My pictures are my versifi¬
ca! ion in lines. If by chance they are entitled to claim recog¬
nition it must be primarily for some rhythmic significance
of form which is ultimate, and not for any interpretation of
an idea, or representation of a fact.
The world of sound is a tiny bubble in the silence of the
infinite. The Universe has its only language of gesture, it
talks in the voice of pictures and dance. Every object in
this world proclaims in the dumb signal of lines and colours
the fact that it is not a mere logical abstraction or a mere
thing of use, but is unique in itself, it carries the miracle of
its existence.
There are countless things which we know but do not
recognize them in their own dignity of truth, independent of
the fact that they are injurious or beneficial. It is enough
that a flower exists as a flower, but my cigarette has no other
claim upon me for its recognition but as being subservient to
my smoking habit.
20
But there are other things which in their dynamic quality
of rhythm or character make us insistently acknowledge the
fact that they are. In the book of creation they are the
sentences that are underlined with coloured pencil and we
cannot pass them by. They seem to cry to us "See, here I
am," and our mind bows its head and never questions, "Why
are you? "
In a picture the artist creates the language of undoubted
reality, and we are satisfied that
we see. It may not be the
representation of a beautiful
woman but that of a common¬
place donkey, or of something
that has no external credential
of truth in nature but only in
its own inner artistic signifi¬
cance.
People often ask me about
the meaning of my pictures.
I remain silent even as my
pictures are. It is for them
to express and not to explain.
They have nothing ulterior
behind their own appearance
for the thoughts to explore and
words to describe and if that
v appearance carries its ultimate
worth then they remain, other¬
wise they are rejected and
forgotten even though they
may have some scientific truth
or ethical justification.
It is related in the drama
of Shakuntala, how one busy
morning there stood humbly
before the maiden of the
forest-hermitage a stranger
youth who did not give his
name. Her soul acknow¬
ledged him at once without
question. She did not know him but only saw him and foi
her he was the artist God's masterpiece to which must be
offered the full value of love.
Days passed by. There came at her gate another
guest, a venerable sage who was formidable. And, sure of
his claim to a dutiful welcome, proudly he announced "I am
here!" But she missed his voice, for it did not carry
with it an inherent meaning, it needed a commentary of
household virtue, pious words of sanction which could assign
a sacred value to a guest, the value that was not of the irres¬
ponsible art, but of moral responsibility. Love is kindred to
art, it is inexplicable. Duty can be measured by the degree
of its benefit, utility by the profit and power it may bring,
but art by nothing but itself. There are other factors of life
which are visitors that come and go. Art is the guest that
comes and remains. The others may be important, but art
is inevitable.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Hb MM
Photos Courtesy Match © I 957
The Unesco Courier. August 1957
JEAN COCTEAU
Fishermen's chapel
For twenty years or more the fishermen of Villefranche-
sur-Mer, a tiny port on the French Riviera had an
unusual place to hang their fishnets and store their
tackle the 14th century chapel of St. Peter, an aban¬
doned Romanesque barrel-vault, situated by the sea.
Last year, they were persuaded to store their parapher¬
nalia elsewhere and handed over the keys to Jean Cocteau,
who has spent a good six months decorating the chapel.
This month it will be officially opened to worshippers and
rededicated to St Peter, the patron saint of fishermen.
Cocteau has painted a series of murals running along
the walls and vaulted ceiling of the chapel. Drawn in
flowing linear style, they depict scenes in the life of St.
Peter and are done in charcoal brightened with mono¬
chrome painting. Angels in the Cocteau manner, looking
as if they had escaped from his poems, bridge the vaults.
"As an artist", he has said, '"I wanted to create a chapel
in which the poet, without losing any of his prerogatives,
would become immediately accessible to fishermen and
simple people."
These frescoes, his first religious subject, represent the
peak of Cocteau's artistic activities. In previous years, he
has held several exhibitions of his paintings and illustrat¬
ed many of his own books: for his novel, Les Enfants
Terribles, he produced 60 drawings, and he has
assembled his pen-drawings in albums under the gener¬
al title Graphic Poems.
At the age of 17 Cocteau published his first book of
verse, La Lampe d'Aladin (1909), and since that time has
been faithful to his motto: "In art one must serve the
nine muses". He has even served a tenth muse, the cinema.
His artistic activities range from literature, theatre and
music, to ballet, circus and painting. Innovator in letters
and the cinematographic art, Jean Cocteau, who has
described himself as "'having always lived standing up",
was recently honoured with a seat in the hallowed Aca¬
démie Française.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
THE UNKNOWN VICTOR HUGO
by Jean Sergent
Curator, Victor Hugo Museum, Paris
Despite the enormous array of books on Victor Hugo, a recent
biographer chose for his study the title "Victor Hugo the
Unknown."
Victor Hugo the artist is certainly unknown.
Hugo left 450 or so drawings, some larger in size than the
average easel painting. Despite his known aversion to wasting
time he devoted countless hours to these drawings. Only his most
treasured friends received them as gifts, often adorned with an
enormous signature added as a decorative element. And in a
score of ways, Hugo has left us proof that he considered his
drawings on an equal level with his poems. Yet despite all this,
little has been written on Hugo's drawings, and those art
historians who mention him at all dismiss him in a few lines.
How can we account for this lack of recognition ?
Undoubtedly, the fact that the bulk of his drawings is con¬
centrated in the Victor Hugo Museum, located in a less frequented
quarter of Paris, has not helped to make them easily accessible
and better known. But the real misfortune of Victor Hugo the
artist is the very fact that he is... Victor Hugo.
The Renaissance had its great universal
geniuses and recognized them. But our
age and Victor Hugo's as well have persist¬
ed in treating people outside their own
speciality as nothing more than amateurs
more or less gifted. No one, it would
seem, has the right any longer to be a
genius in two fields at the same time, and
Hugo was mistaken if he imagined himself
great enough to overthrow this rule.
He began to draw shortly after he
turned thirty, when he and Juliette Drouet
embarked on the travels which liberated
him from his toils and her from the
sequestered life she had been leading.
Like most people, he took drawing
lessons as a child and as a young man ;
his friends were painters : L. Boulanger,
the Deveria brothers, Célestin Nanteuil
and he often watched them at work. His
wife, a fairly gifted woman, had a society
woman-artist of some talent to advise
her, and Hugo looked on as they worked.
But neither this nor his visits to
museums, nor his familiarity with ancient
and contemporary engravings, can account
for his sudden emergence in 1838, after
three or four years' experimenting, as an
accomplished artist.
The fact is that Victor Hugo possessed
all kinds of latent gifts awaiting the
opportunity to burst forth. He had acute
vision ; a memory so retentive that he was
able to delineate clearly a certain house
he had seen in Blois forty years earlier ;
visual imagination (was he not always reproached for being unable
to think except in images?); and, in addition, a skill and readiness
of hand inherited from his humble social origins. His travels
provided the stimulus for bringing his artist's talent to fruition.
He began simply by taking careful notes of what his eye
perceived. Travelling in Normandy and Brittany in 1836 with
Juliette, . he made sketches barely distinguishable from those of
his other travelling companion, the lanky, kind-hearted Nanteuil,
whose album he borrowed. But by 1839 he was already going
beyond mere "recording", and was interpreting what he saw.
The. Rats' Tower, one of the five or six finished drawings
which Hugo brought back from his travels in the Rhineland in
1839-40, is remarkable both for its utter simplicity of composition
with the dominant lines leading the eye to the centres of
interest, as in the work of Poussin or Lorrain and for its
richness of texture and the evocative force of its luminous
shadows.
From this date onwards, these two styles are' combined in
Hugo's work. First there are the minute drawings from life,
22
" NUDE WEARING A COAT and a feather
In her hat." This picture, as well as those which
Illustrate the following two pages, has been
kindly made available by the Victor Hugo
Museum, housed In the author's former home.
tending, however, to become increasingly free and synthesized as
time goes on ; and then there are the "visionary compositions",
as Hugo himself called them.
As an artist, he was always scrupulously conscientious. He
had inherited from his carpenter-ancestors a love of "fine work"".
He had his own techniques, not to say "tricks". He was not
averse from adopting some rather unorthodox methods, such as
preparing his paper with a wash of black coffee which gave
a fine warm brown background ; or from using a scraper or hot
curling-tongs to put movement into his skies. At the same time,
he knew that fantasy must be kept within bounds and, above all,
that every art has its own needs and its own laws, transgression
of which impairs the strength and vitality of the work. Artists are
struck by the professional competence of this "amateur", the
vigour of his lines, and the solidity of his volumes. Hugo draws
like Delacroix, or like the sculptors Barye, or David d'Angers.
So much for the form. But what of the content ? The latter
is invariably governed, to a. great degree, by the former.
The fact that Hugo's drawing is based on contrasts of light and
shade violent contrasts, often makes it
tempting and easy to say that Hugo the
artist, like Hugo the poet, is interested only
in the beauty of contrasts, and to add at
once that the drawings are a recapitulation
of the poems; an expression, in another
medium, of the same over-simplified, super¬
ficial philosophy of life.
This is not the place to discuss whether
Hugo's philosophy is superficial or other¬
wise. What I mean is that his drawing is
never, or is only very rarely, a continuation
of his writing. It has a purpose of its
own: to enable Hugo to convey his
meaning more clearly, more fully and
very often more effectively as, for
instance, in his Landscape with Three
Trees, which has a sobriety and conciseness
seldom found in his poems. His drawings
certainly cannot be regarded as mere
appendages to his writings ; indeed, several
dominant themes are expressed in drawing
before they appear in a poem. This is
true, for instance, of the belief in the soul
passing from reign to reign in accordance
with its sins and deserts. Where Hugo
uses both media to assail the execution of
a criminal the hanging of John Brown in
particular and to protest once again
against the death penalty, his drawings
(Hugo repeats the drawing of the hanged
man four times) strike us more forcibly
than any words could do. (See photo
page 24.)
Unfortunately, Hugo started too early
having his drawing reproduced in the illu¬
strated journals before his talent had fully
ripened, with the result that they aroused nothing more than
sympathetic curiosity. The fact that so expert and reputed a
connoisseur of art as Gautier praised these drawings was of
no avail ; they were regarded as the chance success of a highly
gifted amateur. And it was perhaps a mistake on Theophile Gau-
tier's part, when in 1852 he compared Hugo to the foremost
living artists. In this there was a risk of Hugo not being placed
at the top of the list, as Gautier intended, but at the bottom.
When Castel, in 1863, collected together 80 reproductions of
his best work in an album, Hugo, who never much cared for
taking second place, enjoined his faithful and obedient friend
Gautier, who was writing the preface, to give him no rating
in relation to contemporary artists on the grounds that he was
merely an amateur who had no thought "of using his natural
painting gifts for any purpose beyond that of relaxation, knowing
full well that for one man, one art suffices." It looked, then, as
if the question had been settled. There are some of us now who
are trying to have the question re-opened, so that Hugo, the artist
may take his rightful place among his peers: Piranesi, Goya, Rem¬
brandt. ' .
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. August 1957
MYSTERIOUS LIGHT AND
SHADE. Although Victor Hugo
did not take painting lessons during
his lifetime, there ¡s a mark of
genius in the works of art he pro¬
duced. Drawing and sketching were
no mere hobby or means of relax¬
ation for him. They were a more ra¬
pid and precise way than writing for
him to fix what he perceived or
was inspired by in nature. "How
often", wrote Théophile Gautier,
"did we not follow with amaze¬
ment the transformation of an ink
or coffee spot on the envelope of a
letter or on another odd peice of
paper, into a landscape, a castle, a
strangely original seascape, where
the contrast between light and shade
produced an unexpected effect both
striking and mysterious, which
astonished even professional pain¬
ters." Many of Hugo's sketches,
drawings and washes are an ink-
and-colour reflection of scenes
which he had described in his writ¬
ten works. Others, however, were
fixed in colour long before his
books were written and thus his
first inspiration found expression
not In words but in the form and
shape of a drawing or sketch.
Illustrations on this page show,
above, Hugo's "Town on a Hill¬
side", probably inspired by a visit
he made to the old towns along
the banks of the Rhine; and below,
one of his most famous works,
"Landscape with Three Trees".
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Victor Hugo (Continued)
'HANGED.' For years Victor Hugo raised his voice against
the execution of criminals and assailed the death penalty as
a means of meting out justice. This subject aroused such
. deep emotions in him that he made at least four drawings
of a hanged man. The execution of the American abolition¬
ist, John Brown, in 1859, is believed to have inspired Hugo
to do these drawings, one of which is today In the Louvre.
EDDYSTONE LIGHTHOUSE. The date inscribed by
Victor Hugo on this work ( 1 866) shows that it was executed
during the author's exile In Guernsey, at a period when he
was "the savage old wanderer of the sea". This lighthouse
is situated in the English Channel off the Cornish coast.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
CARLO LEVI
The Unesco Courier. August 1957
ARTIST BY DAY
AUTHOR BY NIGHT
LOVERS, a painting
done in 1955 by Carlo
Levi. Below, Levi's por¬
trait of the great Italian
poet, Umberto Saba (in
the National Gallery of
Modern Art, Rome).
Photos © Oscar Savio, Rome
Carlo Levi gained international in 1945 his
prize-winning novel Christ Stopped at Eboli, but
prior to that he had already begun to make a name
for himself as a professional painter. Levi's life has been
a long series of adventures and struggles since he was
born in Turin 55 years ago. Painter, journalist, novelist,
medical doctor, he was formerly the editor of an anti-
Fascist underground publication and a wartime resistance
leader in Italy. But a few years ago he wrote: "Of the
many enterprises I have undertaken in my li'fe, I consider
only two to be fundamental: painting and writing."
Levi began to take up painting seriously In the 1920s
while studying for his medical degree. In this early period
he followed the neoclassical style. After receiving his
M.D. he abandoned medicine to devote himself to
painting, reacting against his earlier style to become a
post-impressionist. Between 1929 and 1934 he held one-
man exhibitions in Turin, Milan, Rome, Genoa, London
and Paris; and since the war has exhibited in many
countries. His paintings have been described as "ranking
with the very best of his generation."
For anti-Fascist activities he was exiled in 1935 to the
isolated village of Gagliano in Lucania and there he not
only painted some of his best pictures but also collected
the material for the 'famous novel he was to write nine
years later during the last war. He has since said that
his year in Gagliano (he gave clandestine medical care
to the peasants in defiance of the authorities) "had more
influence on my painting than any period of my life."
Today he has a studio on the top floor of a 17th century
palazzo from where he can see the whole oí Rome. Here
he keeps a cat, a turtle and a ping-pong table which he
uses "either as a drawing board or for sport". He divides
his time between painting and writing, rising late to
paint during the afternoon, reserving his writing for the
night "when darkness and silence induce a sense of soli¬
tude."
Another animal that Carlo Levi loves is a rare and
beautiful Royal Owl from Ethiopia which he has named
Graziadio. He first saw it nearly 17 years ago in a small
ambulant zoo and was immediately attracted to the bird.
"Was it the almost human quality which struck Carlo the
philosopher", his close friend, the noted photographer
David Seymour wrote a few years before he was killed
in a jeep during the Suez affair, "or was it the extraordi¬
nary yellow-gray plumage, combined with the bird's
reddish eyelids and bluish beak which impressed Carlo
the painter? It might even have been the striking
resemblance of the owl to Carlo Levi himself, who looks
like the human edition of an owl."
At any event, Graziadio became Levi's obsession and he
painted, wrote and even composed poetry about it. Soon
his studio was filled with drawings, sketches and paintings
of the owl. Today, Graziadio has become Carlo Levi's
signature and symbol.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
THE O L
by Carlo Levi
I have always admired, and perhaps loved, nocturnal birds
of every kind; the numerous and solitary family of
tawny owls, screech owls, hoopoes, wonderful animals
which, more than any other, resemble gods, very ancient
gods which, as is but natural, can only be hairy or feathered.
This attachment of mine or attraction, passion, sympa¬
thy or love is certainly not strange, since from the earliest
times the round eye of the owl and its cry have struck the
imagination of men with strange mystical force. As classi¬
cal and romantic emblems they have accompanied men
across the centuries, from the wise old owls of Athens to
the funereal nightbirds of the poems of Ossian. I cannot
state with certainty whether they appeared to me in either
classical or romantic form; they have always seemed to me
like heraldic angels of the Last Judgment, eye-witnesses of
time eternal, beings who have "always existed since the birth
of time . . . Thus I have always associated the image of the
26
owl with that of time, with that of the origin of time in its
unlimited antiquity; with that of the end of time and its
character of the Last Judgment. That is why my book The
Clock was born under the nocturnal image of the owl,
eternal like the city of Rome, eternal like poverty, like the
courage to live, like saints, brigands and gods.
Of all the owls I have ever seen or imagined, the most
beautiful is the owl Graziadio: the most heraldic, the most
ancient, the most timeless, the most divine. I saw him for
the first time in a travelling collection of rare animals
touring the cities of Italy. In the cages near the birds there
were vampires, little crocodiles, iguanas, and above all, ser¬
pents. And I could not help thinking that if in ancient
mythology the serpent is at the beginning of time, then
the owl Graziadio was its "angel-equivalent" if what the
great Italian poet Umberto Saba has said is true that birds
are "... the sublimation of the reptile in nature."
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. August 1957
I saw Graziadio from time to time in one city or another.
His cage was usually lit up and this gave his countenance
an angry appearance. It was as ri his head were engulfed
in pain or anguish by the light that fell upon it, so that
when he moved or shifted his position he often appeared
fierce and ferocious, and his claws would tighten their grip
on a morsel of food or a stone with a primeval fury. Never¬
theless, his noble air never left him and he always main¬
tained that hoary, royal, detached, even moving and perhaps
grotesque, look about him (as had the gods and semi-gods O'f
Greece and the simulacra of phallic divinity). Nor did his
old face ever lose the marks of an all-embracing, incompre¬
hensible wisdom. Though he appeared severe and
inaccessible even when he seemed to be playing, shutting
one eye and describing a circle with his head, he never had
the obtuse and hysterical harshness of the eagle. For even
Photos David Seymour @ Magnum
while he played there remained about him an air of mytho¬
logical solitude.
I have seen owls flying through the woods, I have seen
them traverse the sky amongst the trees in the first glimmer
of daylight, like flying cats or witches surprised by the
coming of dawn. Everyone has seen the little owl perched
on the shoulder o'f Picasso and has seen owls, living or
stuffed, in the studios of painters and writers and some¬
times, perhaps, even on the hats women wear. So, this
terrible angel can indeed become an everyday subject, an
instrument, an extravagance.
But my owl, Graziadio, comes from the centre of Africa
and the savage deserts, and he is as great as the greatest of
birds or angels. With his huge black eye, like a Negro king
or a sorcerer or a cherub, he has seen all those things
which have come to pass, and who knows, perhaps too, things
which have never occurred.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
LEWIS CARROLL'S
own wonderland
of drawings
In 1865 the
world was as¬
tonished and de¬
lighted with a
book called Ali¬
ce's Adventures
in Wonderland
by one Lewis
Carroll. The
world was fur¬
ther astonished
to discover that
Lewis Carroll
was none other
than Charles
Lutwidge Dodgson, an Oxford don
and mathematician who had step¬
ped out of his academic role to
write what has since become the
greatest of all English books for
children. When the Alice stories
were published in book form they
owed much of the immediate fame
they won to the illustrations of an
English cartoonist and artist, Sir
John Tenniel, of Punch. What few
people knew at the time and few
persons, realize even today is that
the original manuscript, entitled
Alice's Adventures Under Ground,
had been illustrated by another
artist Lewis Carroll himself.
Carroll had always been interest¬
ed in drawing. As a boy he had a
little book specially set aside for
humorous sketches in which he
took great pleasure. Throughout
his life he continued to draw with
remarkable zest and perseverance
despite John Ruskin's later com¬
ment "that he had not enough
talent to make it worth his while
to devote much time to sketching."
Dodgson preferred figures to land¬
scapes, and at one time seriously
toyed with the idea of becoming a
free-lance cartoonist. After the
Comic Times returned his humor¬
ous sketches in 1855 he seems to
have accepted the decision that his
work was not good enough, though
in fact many of his early attempts
"were hardly inferior," as one
modern critic has said, "to Lear's
famous nonsense drawings and
exhibit a wild brilliance and unin¬
hibited draughtsmanship."
Dodgson thus dropped the idea
of becoming a professional artist.
He turned to an art form which
had just been born photography.
Between 1856 to 1880 it was his
chief hobby, his favourite subjects
being his child-friends. The re¬
cent re-discovery of his. fine photo¬
graphic work shows him to have
been the best photographer of
children in the 19th century.
The real Alice in Alice in Won¬
derland was one of the three
daughters of his. friend Dean
Liddell. Dodgson has called her
"my ideal child-friend," and has
recorded in his diary the origins of
the whimsical stories. Under July
4, 1862 is the entry: "I made an
expedition up the river to Dostow
with the three Liddells; we had tea
on the bank there." On the oppo¬
site page of the diary he added, on
February 10, 1863: "On which
occasion I told them the fairy tale
of Alice's Adventures Under
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. August 1957
% -> .-SVaBjrrvS?. A» Si, >
The drawings on these two pages
are examples of the original illus¬
trations done by Lewis Carroll for
his manuscript copy of Alice in
Wonderland which he first called
Alice Under Ground. Photograph on
opposite page shows the real-life
Alice who inspired Carroll's mas¬
terpiece, Alice Liddell, photo¬
graphed by Carroll himself in the
studio which he had installed
above his apartment at Oxford.
Ground, which I undertook to
write out for Alice."
Long afterwards, Alice herself
(then Mrs. Alice Pleasance Har-
greaves) gave this account of how
the stories were first told to her and
her two sisters: "Most of Mr. Dodg-
son's stories were told to us on
river expeditions near Oxford. I
believe the beginning of Alice
was told one summer afternoon
when the sun was so burning that
we had landed in the meadows
down the river, deserting the boat
to take refuge in the shade of a
new-made hayrick. Here from all
three came the petition of 'Tell us a
story', and so began the ever-de¬
lightful tale."
Dodgson then embarked on the
slow process of illustrating his
original manuscript as a gift for
"a dear child in memory of a sum¬
mer day". This took him such a
long time that he did not get it
done until the autumn of 1864.
The story was exquisitely written
in a clear script as legible as print
(see photo). It contained 92 pages
with 18,000 words, but for the
published book Carroll later enlarg¬
ed it to nearly 35,000 words.
In 1928, the manuscript volume
was sold to a private American
collection for £15,400 (then $77,000)
"the highest price which any book
has ever brought in an English
auction room," but 20 years later
it reached the British Museum
through American generosity. The
manuscripts from which Alice in
Wonderland and Through the
Looking Glass were set up by the
printer, however, have never been
discovered.
Although Carroll's contempora¬
ries and Carroll himself seem to
have had little regard for his
ability as an artist, his illustrations
deserve a better fate than the
oblivion to which they have been
relegated up to a few years ago.
Of these illustrations, a recent
biographer of Lewis Carroll, Derek
Hudson, has remarked: "As. the
earnestness of the amateur draugh¬
tsman occasionally rises in them
to a weird frenzy that is almost
Blake-like in its intensity, this is
an exciting rather than a disappoint¬
ing experience. Carroll's draw¬
ings, lacking Tenniel's professional
accomplishment, could never have
assisted Alice to a popular success,
but unlike Tenniel's, they are the
work of a poet and have a private
anguish which is more moving than
it is amusing. They represent a
genuine artistic achievement which
has never been properly appreciat¬
ed." (Derek Hudson: Lewis Car¬
roll. 1954. Constable, London.)
A French critic, Henri Parisot,
has gone even further. "Car¬
roll's drawings," he has writ¬
ten, "were too stylized, too modern
to seem anything but the work of
an amateur during his time. Since
our aesthetic notions differ from
those of the Victorian Era, and
since our contemporary artists
have accustomed us to modes of
expression which are increasingly
divorced from the realistic acade¬
mism so dear to the 19th century,
we today find Carroll's drawings
illustrating the manuscript of Alice
strangely expressive indeed far
superior to the drawings of Tenniel
which were substituted for his."
(Henri Parisot: Lewis Carroll. 1952.
Pierre Seghers, Editeur, Paris.)
Irrespective of whether Carroll's
drawings are or are not superior
to those of Tenniel, it is indeed
regrettable that no edition of Alice
containing Lewis Carroll's own
illustrations is available to the
public today.
Drawings on these pages are
examples of those done by Carroll
for Alice Under Ground.
Si* W«t « 5»**1 d-tm¿
f*tmktÂAXAd hy ~th,t V*^y
C.A»-noi, but » 'A« dt.d Axmi
}A-ri«¿ tLrty fmrtttér, and Kmml
not drepptd tíu\ ~tôp e/ ¿At
htit^roim, »A« did ruft- gtvt
up A©/>» V«t- TkvA* w»* ímrdly
ntrm. ~Í* cftA. h*A ta.aÍÍ,
JlCa- ihtAX prxn'un* 43aua.tr- Ltr
foct, tut »A. dU lh oí UmÍ,
¿r.J. myAtmAti U tttt off a
UtXt. tti 'i <** "t>f *f **«
mu»Ar»»tn.
« «
'Co~*. ' An, Ai»/'» fnx
*i lut '" *-a¿- *l¿* "» *
k cf «/«A.U-, -A.J cA*ju*í
¿xfi, alt-Am i-> a.Auitfu.A m»-
. wA~ »a* ¿~~t eut-
¿el. .hcu.Ul** wir* ru.«*«»
t, U se"» k***«t ¿*"
^n. «.* An.An*AA^í UrL,1S.
Mlfc, «A.A ""»'^ « nt~
Uto <a s^'* « "i * "*
«Mil líA-Af, #W i»Jf ft
Int:, A«.r
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
BAUDELAIRE
an artist haunted
by his own face
rrr-p«HE whole lower part of the face is bad... the chin not
I protruding enough... too many criss-cross lines in the
shaded areas... a better effect can be obtained with a
few well-placed lines..."
These observations, scribbled by Charles Baudelaire on the
margins of his self-portraits, reveal how severely critical he
was, how meticulous and painstaking when he worked on his
drawings.
Art played as great a part in Baudelaire's life as did poetry
and love. "Les images, mon unique, ma primitive passion,"
he once cried out. Pictures were, indeed, his earliest passion
and his lifelong rapture. His father, "a detestable painter"
and one-time drawing teacher, had delighted in fostering in
Charles an appreciation of painting, and before the age of
six took him on regular visits to Paris's many museums.
The author of Les Fleurs du Mal (published and condemned
by the courts just 100 years ago) is today famous not only for
his poetry and his translations of Poe, but for his critical
studies on art, his Salons (1845-1859) and other essays of
aesthetic criticism which he began to write at the age of 24,
revealing his remarkable perspicacity, vision and feeling.
Though he wrote mostly about painting, three other tech¬
niques had a strange fascination for him drawing, etching
and caricature. He considered Delacroix "the most original
painter of ancient and modern times," yet it was his etchings
not his paintings that he hung in his room. He once bought
the entire series of Delacroix's lithographs on Hamlet and cov¬
ered his walls with them. He was the great champion and
defender of Daumier, "one of the most important men not
only of caricature but of all modern art," and contemplated
a complete history of caricature which he never wrote. He
did, however, publish three studies on the subject, now
assembled in his Curiosités esthétiques. His loudest praise
went to Daumier and Goya but he did not neglect Gavarni,
Grandville, Cruikshank, Hogarth and Breughel. He sought
to show the dignity and importance of caricatures which he
called "often the most faithful mirror of life," and affirmed
that they deserved "the attention of the historian, the ar¬
chaeologist and even the philosopher, and should take their
place in the biographical registers of human thought."
Baudelaire himself produced a few caricature sketches
which he executed with great speed, perhaps mindful of De¬
lacroix's remark to him one day: "If you are not skilful
enough to complete the sketch of a man who has jumped out
of a fourth floor window by the time he hits the ground, you
will never produce any big things." But Baudelaire concen¬
trated mostly on ink or pencil portraits, of his friends and
above all of himself, where speed was no factor. Haunted
by his own face, he would scrutinize every inch of it in the
mirror and then attempt to portray its quality. He worked
hard at rendering the melancholy look in his eyes, the line
of his thin lips and the lock of hair that fell across his fore¬
head.
In one self-portrait, drawn under the influence of hashish
in 1845, he appears with a cigar in his mouth, twice as tall as
the Place Vendôme column, surrounded by a rising sun and
a halo of bright stars. Of this drawing, a friend of his
wrote: "From time to time, he would put down his pen, and
rolling a pointed paper stump between his fingers, caress his
picture with evident pleasure."
In one of his essays on portraits, Baudelaire exclaimed:
"A portrait! What is there more simple, yet more complicat¬
ed, more evident yet more profound?" He saw two manners
of treating a portrait: in the first, "the contours and relief
of the model must be faithfully, severely and minutely ren¬
dered." In the second, the portrait becomes "a poem with
accessories, full of spaces and dreams" where imagination
plays a greater, part. Here the artist "must know how to
bathe a head in soft vapours of a warm atmosphere or make
it emerge from the depths of a twilight evening." To Baude¬
laire, a portrait was "a dramatized biography, or rather the
natural drama inherent in every man."
30
Self-portrait. I860. Under this drawing Baudelaire noted:
"Here, the line of the mouth is better."
Baudelaire entitled this an "Example of Ancient Beauty.'
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. August 1957
Woman without a name.
Self-portrait. 1845. Honoré Daumier. Ink drawing by Baudelaire.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
THE 'PICSHUA'
DIARY OF
H.G. WELLS
.'^h^^ô^K
Ua¿ ¡Kin »mc. tji iL, mi JU~¡ t^jvrtr \ C*~¿ L' - 0_ ?
fr, _ u-i ^~ .yfl«* £^. H+ » s-:f\ tf~-3 IUa^aS. di cxi>
ijJlAaIa. ?-m~ it^vn^ i««t «. ?je c¿w tü (u^uz£a-, r¡A-A. >y^Y- **-~~ **
llcT""k->3 ^ C***"- ««- «-* ^ ^C ST/W« .
HG. Wells devoted his great talent to an exception¬
ally wide range of subjects. His work as a whole
* deals with practically every facet of modern life.
Such novels as Kipps, The History of Mr. Polly, are regard¬
ed as classics of English literature. Having had scientific
training, Wells also pioneered "science fiction" with his
Time Machine, The War of the Worlds, and The First Men
on the Moon.
Wells came from a family in very modest circumstances.
His parents were unable to afford a good education for
their son who was therefore largely self-taught until
scholarships took him to London University. He had to
contend with ill-health, undernourishment and poverty
before he was able to establish himself as an author.
Wells never took his artistic gifts very seriously but got
into the habit of making many little sketches which he
called "picshuas". He is probably the only famous author
who unconsciously at first kept a diary in the form of
humorous sketches. In his Experiment in Autobiography,
subtitled "Discoveries and Conclusions of a very ordinary
brain (since 1866)" he describes how "in the evening, with
my writing things before me I would break off work to do
'picshuas', these silly little sketches about this or that
incident which became at last a sort of burlesque diary of
our lives and accumulated in boxes until there were
hundreds of them. Many perhaps most are lost but
still there remain hundreds."
Years later Wells noted: "These may seem at first glance
to be the most idle of scribblings but in fact they are acute
statements in personal interpretation. Mostly they were
done on sheets of manuscript paper, so that they here
suffer considerable reduction and compression." The
"picshuas" are in fact a delightful and vivid record of
H.G. Wells's rise to fame. Six are reproduced here, giv¬
ing an intimate glimpse of a rich and varied life and
conveying a humorous detachment alike from misery and
good fortune.
"Picshua", above, illustrates a letter to Wells's brother
written in 1890 when H.G. was a young biological demon¬
strator in London. His legend reads: "What is this?
Why do the people in the tramcar shrink from his pre¬
sence? Why in this hot weather sit there in a heap
together? Can it be Satan? Or the Hangman? Or the
Whitechapel Murder (er) ? No it is none of these things.
It is simply a young biological demonstrator who has been
dissecting with a large class that particular form of life
known as the Dog Fish (scylla canícula). He STINKS."
Drawing, left, dated 1892, heads a letter to his mother
which opens with "You observe a doubtless familiar figure
above, keeping his 26th birthday. In the background are
bookshelves recently erect¬
ed by your eldest, who came
up here Thursday and has
been doing things like that
ever since." In the corner
of a drawing dated Septem¬
ber 8, 1897, Wells drew an
"Invisible Man", to indicate
the publication day of one
his most popular books.
Invisible Man is shown at
right with the words "Just
out" written alongside.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. August 1957
FD-!©
The above picshua was done in November 1895 when Wells had
become somewhat known and was living at Woking outside London.
He had withdrawn to "a little house in the country where I could
follow up with another book the success that I felt was coming to
The Time Machine and my short-story volume". It was here that he
planned and wrote the War of The Worlds, the Wheels of Chance
and The Invisible Man. "I wheeled about the district", he wrote,
"marking down suitable places and people for destruction by my
Martians." This picshua Wells said: "reeks with the 'shop' of
authorship; one observes also the pride of Jane [his second wife,
Amy Catherine Robbins], the author's family in a state of wonder,
the envious hostile reviewer with a forked tail... much sordid
exultation about royalties and cheques. But we were very young
still, we had hada hard and risky time and it was exciting to succeed."
In the summer of 1898, Wells went to the south coast to
recuperate from a kidney ailment. "All this," he wrote,
"is brought back to me by the hieroglyphics of the picshuas...
Before October I did some little drawings as I lay In bed, and
amused myself by colouring them and these I think prevented
the Immediate resumption of the picshua diary." On Octo¬
ber 5th the picshuas testify that he "hatched out a new pro¬
ject called K/pps, and completed Love and Mr. Lewisham.
And on October 8th (date of picshua below) "there seems
to have been a bout of drawing to put all the momentous
events of the previous months on record. The picshuas
recall a score of particulars that I should otherwise have for¬
gotten completely." The delightful drawing below depicts
the interruption of a picnic by Intrusive cows. Mrs. Wells,
he noted in his. Autobiography, "...was town bred and she did
not like cows. She distrusted these kind fragrant animals."
ÍA1 </
y<x-
*s-
j~í
<£m
Left, is an impression sketched by
H.G. Wells at the time of a Royal
Institution audience in 1902. "We were
"getting on", he wrote. "At first it was
very exciting and then it became less
marvellous. We still found ourselves
rising. I remember about this time to
be exact on January 24th, 1902 was
asked to read a paper to the Royal In¬
stitution and I wrote and read The Discov¬
ery of the Future... I sketched at the
time a Royal Institution audience... I
regard this picshua as a masterpiece only
to be compared to the Palaeolithic draw¬
ings in the Caves of Altimira. It marks
our steady invasion of the world of
influential and authoritative people."
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
PIERRE LOTI AT EASTER ISLAND
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. August 1957
Photo left (and detail above) ¡s a water colour
painting which Pierre Loti dedicated to
Sarah Bernhardt. Loti wrote under it:
"Easter Island. 7 January 1872, about
5 a.m.; inhabitants watching me arrive."
Apart from giant statues strewn about,
painting shows Easter Island tattooing; a
Janus-headed dance paddle or club; various
hair styles: tuft or pompom arrangement,
and diadem of rooster feathers. Skulls of
former dead are found everywhere on Island
which has been termed a "giant ossuary."
Photo, right, shows five statues atop a large
burial platform made up of four superim¬
posed terraces. Each statue wears a cylin¬
drical turban headdress made of red tufa.
Loti's drawing reveals that, contrary to
even recent reports, all these statues had
not then been toppled from their platforms.
On January 3, 1872, the French
frigate Flore dropped anchor In
Cook's Bay at Easter Island.
Among the men who went ashore
was a midshipman of 22 with a re¬
markable gift for drawing, named
Julien Viaud. Sketch-book in hand
he toured the island and recorded his
observations in notes and images.
Julien Viaud was later to become fa¬
mous for his exotic fiction under the
pseudonym Pierre Loti.
The Flore had stopped at Easter
Island to bring back to France the
head of one of the huge stone statues,
made of soft volcanic stone, for which
the Island ls famed. Loti participated
in the operation, supervising the job
of sawing the head from a long bur¬
ial-platform Image and of transport¬
ing it aboard ship. It is now at the
Musée de l'Homme in Paris.
Because of his skill as an artist he
was assigned to make a series of
drawings of the statues. "It is
amazing," he wrote in his journal,
"how my ability to draw came in
useful and afforded me shore leave to
roam about." Loti executed his draw¬
ings with the eye of a keen observer
and the hand of a deft draughtsman
which already foreshadowed the rich¬
ness of his later literary works. He
sketched not only the statues, "from
every angle" as he said, but the inha¬
bitants, and the various dwellings,
weapons and artifacts they possessed.
Loti made a series of drawings of the
tattoo patterns that made some men's
bodies real works of art. These draw¬
ings represent graphic testimony of
no small anthropological value, show¬
ing Easter Island as it looked In 1872.
In addition, Loti brought back from
the "isle at the edge of the world" a
host of objects of inestimable value:
shark bone earrings, a statuette with
a rooster feather hairdress, and par¬
ticularly, an amazing wooden figurine
of a bird-man 'tangata manu) one of
the predominant symbols of Easter
Island, and two slender huas, Janus-
headed dance paddles, the chief
symbol of the bird ceremony.
Loti made drawings of the two types
of statues found on Easter Island:
the familiar bust type standing on
the slopes of the crater of a volcano,
Rano-raraku; and a long-bodied type
which in the past surmounted the
funerary cairns (ahuß) that fringe
the coast in an almost continuous
procession. It was believed that, as a
result of fierce inter-tribal wars not
a single ahu statue remained stand¬
ing after 1864, and that the last
white man to see them before they
were overthrown was Admiral du
Petit-Thouars in 1838. But Loti's
drawing (bottom left) reveals that
this one group was Intact in 1872.
The publication of Loti's Easter
Island sketches in L'Illustration and
Le Monde Illustré in 1872 marked the
beginning of his eight-year collabora¬
tion with these and other periodicals
in France and England. He became
a roving correspondent - illustrator,
regularly furnishing material on
exotic lands such as Tierra del Fuego,
Nuka-Hiva, Senegal, Guinea, Dakar,
Constantinople and Salonika. After
he gained fame as a novelist, the au¬
thor of Iceland Fisherman ended his
art association with magazines but
continued to sketch and illustrate
several of his own works.
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
PUSHKIN
His gallery
of portraits
ALEXANDER SERGEYEVICH PUSHKIN,
poet, dramatist, novelist and
author of tales, was the first of
the giants of literature of modern Rus¬
sia. He was strongly influenced by the
Romantic movement, especially by
Lord Byron, and had a profound
knowledge of European literature,
translating many works from English
into Russian. Though he was no pro¬
fessional painter, drawing and sketch¬
ing occupied an important place in his
life. His manuscripts and notebooks
are covered with innumerable drawings
of the characters he was describing in
his works, his friends, the women he
loved, members of his family, as well
as Russian and foreign literary figures.
One of his biographers has called,
Pushkin's drawings "his graphic diary".
(1) This self-portrait of Pushkin
showing him "On the Road to Erze-
rum" to participate in the Russo-Tur-
kish war in 1829 was drawn by the poet
on a draft page of his tale Voyage to
Erzerum. Despite the Czar's opposition,
he had gone off to the Caucasus. He
found himself in trouble on his return
to St. Petersburg.
(2) Pushkin and Onegin. This
sketch shows the author with the hero
of his masterpiece novel in verse Eugene
Onegin. They are leaning on a para¬
pet along the River Neva at St. Peters¬
burg opposite the Peter and Paul
fortress. The drawing was part of a
letter which Pushkin wrote to his
brother Leon asking him to have a
professional artist do an illustration
based on It for the first chapter of his
book. The illustration was never made
however. As a rule, Pushkin never
intended to publish his own drawings.
The year 1830 marks the beginning
of what was probably the most fertile
and intensive period in Pushkin's life.
Drawing (3) made at the end of 1830
illustrates a manuscript page of his
short story The Coffin Maker. It shows
two characters in the story, the Ger¬
man cobbler Gotlieb Schultz, left, hav¬
ing a glass of tea with Andrian Prok-
horov, the coffin maker. Between
them, he added a Russian samovar.
Among the many sketches and draw¬
ings left by the author of Boris Godun-
ov and The Queen of Spades, one finds
a series of sketches of Anna Alexevyena
Olenina with whom he was passionately
in love in 1828. She is depicted in (4)
in profile, with an opulent, upswept
hairdress which hides all but a few
features of her face. Another portrait
of Oleninain verse this timewas
done by Pushkin, entitled "Her eyes".
The amusing sketch of a "Mouj Ik
and his glass of vodka" (5) was drawn
by Pushkin in 1834, three years before
his death in a duel at the age of 38.
36
/
. /e, o'J - jsiL»	~-"\7¿. , \a. J />>""
> , /. <±$¿£a***p. "'* ' ? <f/^ t "
¡flnsw
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. August 1957
i^^^^^r^n <* »£*r--* VJip-
t¡Ar*l' f »A*V~l*-tA( OAfA-
ÍAAAt/ .
¿A^^A. ¿*~f'"**È A^AAAA^i, ^	«^«*~<6* /
©
STRINDBERG
The Impressionist
Photo © Nordiika Museet, Stockholm
August Strindberg (1849-1912) Swedish dramatist
and novelist was one of the strangest figures
in all. literary history, and there are few more
painful stories than his. No brief space can do
justice to him. Strindberg was never at peace with
himself and on several occasions was almost
completely mad. His books, filled with violence,
bitterness and sadness, are magnificently written
and have a brutal beauty. His Master Olaf revealed
him as a dramatist of the highest rank and a master
of the Swedish language, and he is today considered
"without doubt the greatest dramatic artist that the
Swedes have produced, perhaps the greatest literary
genius that has come out of Sweden." When he
died, 30,000 people came to his funeral. To relax
from his interior torment, Strindberg seriously took
up painting. On the Baltic coast near Stockholm
he made numerous sketches and gathered inform¬
ation about the fishermen's life in the Swedish
archipelago. He has left many richly coloured
impressionistic paintings, such as the Evening
Breeze at the Sea, above, now in the Nordiska
Museum, Stockholm.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
GARCIA LORCA
troubadour of Andalusia
Federico Garcia Lorca held poetry above all else, but
painting was his secret love to which he remained
Irresistibly attracted. All his works are marked by
the influence of his native soilthe countryside around
Granada in Andalusia, a land of orange groves and gui¬
tars, where a heritage of Arabic refinement mingles
with the joyous spirit of the gipsies.
As a youth Garcia Lorca learned to play the piano, to
sing, to act in plays and to decorate his writings and
letters with drawings of extraordinary fantasy. Is there
any well-known Spanish author who, between 1920 and
1935, did not receive letters with his signature and
flourishes which assumed a vegetation-like form, growing
stems, leaves and flowers ?
At 22 Garcia Lorca published his first Book of Poems
(1921) which he later illustrated for a friend with pano¬
ramic drawings of the city of Granada as seen from the
celebrated Alhambra. Seven years later came his master¬
piece, Romancero Gitano in which he revived the Spanish
ballad tradition enriched with the most brilliant colours.
To the Andalusian painter, Gregorio Prieto, he remarked
one day: "The poetry of your painting and the painting of
my poetry surge* forth from the same fount." Garcia
Lorca drew and coloured unreal and naive pictures which
he gave to his friends as gifts. In his drawings the figures
often evoke characters of his own theatrical works or of
the old folk songs of 14th and 15th century Spain which
he sang, accompanying himself on the piano.
In 1931, Federico as he was affectionately known in¬
stalled a puppet theatre in his family's house in Gra¬
nada. Here with two distinguished collaborators
Manuel de Falla to compose the music, and the painter
Manuel Angeles Ortiz to design the sets he produced
charming, witty puppet plays such as El Retablillo de
Don Cristobal (Don Cristobal Pulchinela is the Spanish
"Mr. Punch").
Shortly afterwards, he set off along the roads of Spain
as director of a travelling university theatre, La Barraca.
In village square and In the open countryside he presented
the magnificent but little-known works of the Spanish
theatre of the "The Golden Age".
From 1931 until his death in 1936 Garcia Lorca's work
as a poet grew in intensity. He came under the influence
of Surrealistic painting as is seen in the drawings (1,4,
5 and 6) reproduced here. At the foot of drawing 5 the
poet wrote "Solo el misterio nos hace vivir..." (Only
through mystery do we live.) In all his drawings Garcia
Lorca is haunted by obsessive memories: tears and flowers,
bells and curtains, the crescent moon and blood falling in
drops. The drawings of his early period (2 and 3) "have
a childish, primitive quality which delights in minute
detail and lively colour", as Gregorio Prieto has written In
his bilingualSpanish-Englishbook Dibujos de Garcia
Lorca ("Garcia Lorca as a Painter") published in Madrid
in 1949. -
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. August 1957
A tACAy^t.tAAy.. I) AAaJa*^ -, « j ç-
,'f'
' , « '
. ' I \
0/*C ¿L I ' ' '
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
WILLIAM BLAKE IN A WORLD OF VISIONS
William Blake, the bi-centenary of
whose birth occurs this year, is
equally well-known as an artist
and poet. He is unique among English
writers because of the mystical quality
of his works.
At the age of four he is supposed to
have seen God's head at the window,
and at seven to have seen Ezekiel in the
fields and angels among the trees "their
bright wings bespangling the boughs
like stars."
A nervous child who never went to
school, he was apprenticed at the age
of fourteen to an engraver in London.
Here he learned a craft which enabled
him to earn a living in his future life.
Because of this training, he put his faith
in line and stated that artists who do
not work by line are liars hired by Satan
"to depress art."
Blake was a visionary with a keen
sense of the spiritual dimension in
which the world is set. He had little
use for "vegetable" existence. For
him art was a spiritual activity and the
artist was a soul sent by God to fulfil
this activity at the expense, if need be,
of all others.
' Wild effusions of
a distempered brain*
Obscure as an artist all his life, he
decided in 1809 to force public
recognition of his works by
staging an exhibition, for which
he also contributed a catalogue. The
exhibition was a complete failure.
Hardly anyone went. Critics talked
of the pictures as "wretched" and
of the artist as an "unfortunate
lunatic whose personal inoffensiveness
secures him from confinement."
The catalogue was described as a
"farrago of nonsense... the wild ef¬
fusions of a distempered brain."
Happily to-day, William Blake has
won universal recognition.
Blake, together with his wife, Cathe¬
rine, published his works almost en¬
tirely alone. By a process all his own,
he etched words on copper, decorated
the plates with designs of great beauty
and added an occasional full-page pic¬
ture. He blended the ink, ground the
colours and mixed his own paint. His
40
wife made impressions, tinted the prints
and bound them on boards. Together
they had made everything but the paper.
Such a publication was Jerusalem, a
book of one hundred engraved plates,
for which all the pictures on these two
pages were drawn.
In his introductory notice "To the
Public" Blake wrote, "The Spirit of
Jesus is continual forgiveness of Sin	
I am perhaps the most sinful of men!
I pretend not to holiness! yet I pretend
to love, to see, to converse with daily,
as man with man, and the more to
have an interest in the Friend of Sinners.
Therefore dear Reader, forgive what
you do not approve, and love me for
this energetic exertion of my talent."
Blake did the powerful pencil
sketch (above) of "Time's
Triple Bow" for his book
Jerusalem. Final drawing
as published, Is shown at left.
From Pencil Drawings by William
Blake. Geoffrey Keynes editor.
Nonesuch Press 1956.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. August 19S7
William Blake was an Imaginative genius of tremendous originality. His mystical paintings and sketches evoke another world, and he
has often been compared with Michelangelo in the expressiveness of his physical forms. Among the different kinds of work done by
Blake are unique engravings that illustrate his own sensitive poetry as well as the works of Dante and the Bible. Reproduced on this
page are three of his engravings forJerusalem (done between I 804- 1 820) for which he evolved a special method of printing and engraving.
WA
mi
ho *' S
y-> t.-:''
7\ ajaa
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
**-tíF!¡ -. "V
HARDY
admired only one
master at a time
Though Thomas Hardy was not a very
accomplished artist, and much of his
painting and drawing is somewhat morbid,
he was an enthusiastic amateur. During his
youth (he was an architect before becoming a
writer) he went to the National Gallery in
London "on every day that it was open for
twenty minutes after lunch." The future au¬
thor of Jude the Obscure and Far from the
Madding Crowd had a self-appointed method
of studying art, confining his attention to a
single master on each visit and forbidding his
eyes to stray to any other. Hardy's own
water colours are preserved in the Dorset
County museum. He made other drawings to
illustrate some of his own works particularly
his first book of verse Wessex Poems from
which the two sketches, here, are taken.
CHARLOTTE BRONTE
'One of the keenest
pleasures I have known'
The Haworth parsonage, where the three
Brontë sisters lived, was a gloomy place
overlooking a graveyard. The dreary
mist-covered Yorkshire moors stretched
on every side. Here the three famous
sisters thought up stories to break the
dullness and rigour of their lives, which
they later wrote down in some of the
best-known novels in English literature
(Charlotte's Jane Eyre; Emily's Wither¬
ing Heights). Here Charlotte drew and
painted landscapes with such detailed
exactness that she eventually injured her
eyesight. Charlotte was a quite gifted
amateur who, in the words of the heroine
of Jane Eyre, felt that to paint pictures
"was to enjoy one of the keenest pleasures
I have known." Minutely detailed pencil
drawing of "Ashburnham Church" (left)
was made by Charlotte Brontë in 1845,
. two years before Jone Eyre appeared.
42
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. August 1957
GwTHE
CI paint as others smoke'
Gnthe was probably the last uotno uni¬
versale of Western civilization. Like
Faust, he desired all knowledge and
sought to squeeze the lemon of life dry.
To him, painting was a serious business
which exerted a tremendous influence upon
his aesthetic conceptions. "Since my early
childhood," GBthe wrote in Dichtung und
Wahrheit (Poetry and Truth), "I had been
surrounded by painters and had formed
the habit, like them, of seeing things in
their relation to art... Everywhere my eyes
passed, I saw a tableau, and began to draw
from nature in the most awkward fashion."
Gjthe flung himself into art with the
same intense zeal as he did into every other
subject which interested him, believing that
"one should be able to make oneself mas¬
ter of any subject." He tried everything :
drawing, water colours, oils, engraving,
frescoes; most of all he did landscapes.
Perhaps like many people today who
find themselves fragmented by the inces¬
sant wagging of the human tongue, Ghthe
once confided to a friend that we should
all speak less and draw more. "For my
part," he said, "I should like to disso¬
ciate myself from speech altogether and, in
imitation of nature, express my thoughts
only in design." '
Gsthe considered that he had a natural
talent for painting worthy of cultivation,
but he was his own harshest critic. After
his long stay in Italy between 1786 and
1788 he decided "to renounce the practice
of the plastic art." But nothing could stop
him from painting: "I lacked everything
Invocation to the Moon
needed to succeed" he wrote, "but 1 per¬
sisted stubbornly."
In one of his letters, written when he
was 60, he mentions that he is busy painting
landscapes "but always in the same style
which leads to nothing." He added philo¬
sophically, "since I practise in the same
way as others smoke tobacco, it does not
matter very much."
In 1821, twenty-two drawings executed
in 1810 were published in an album for
which G himself wrote the preface and
asked his readers to "judge my ability as
well as my shortcomings." The magnifi¬
cent drawing, (above left) "Evocation of
the Spirit of the Earth", which he did for
Faust, appeared in this album.
G later summed up his artistic deve¬
lopment and came to the following very
severe conclusions : "My tendency to prac¬
tise art was in reality a false tendency for
I had no natural aptitude, and hence
nothing touching art could develop spon¬
taneously in me. ...Despite all my efforts I
did not become an artist. But by practising
art I learned the value of every line and
learned to differentiate between what is
praiseworthy and what is inadequate. This
is no small advantage."
Perhaps it would be truer to say that
G failed to rise above the common¬
place when he adhered too closely to all
the rules and copied directly from nature.
But when he allowed his imagination free
rein (as in his Faust drawing) or worked
from memory (as in the "Invocation to the
Moon", left) his natural artistic talent
came into play, enabling him to produce
results of unquestionable originality.
Above, right, a water colour by G
in hommage to France after the battle
of Valmy in 1792. On a pole topped by a
Phrygian cap, G wrote: "Passers-by.
this land is free."
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
THE WHALE'S EYE HAUNTED KIPLING
A striking picture of Kipling's inter¬
est in drawing and painting has
been left to us by his daughter, Elsie
(Mrs. George Bambridge). "My
father", she wrote, "inherited a
great deal of his own father's artistic
ability and was often busy with
pencil and paint-brush illuminating,
for instance, his various copies of
Horace's Odes with designs and
pictures. His knowledge of lettering
of all ages and his skill in reproducing it was great, and he took
infinite pleasure in the drawing of the delicate and fantastic
letters for 'How the Alphabet was made' in the Just So Stories.
Sometimes to amuse himself he would fake old documents, and
the results, having been 'aged' by careful rubbing with soot and
dust, were marvels of convincing antiquity. If painted masks or
gilded paper crowns with splendidly real-looking jewels were
wanted for theatricals or fancy-dress parties, he made them with
the greatest skill and endless trouble." (In Rudyard Kipling: His
Life & Work, by Ch. Carrington.)
Although the famous drawings published in the Jungle Book
were executed by Kipling's father, an art school and museum of
fine arts director in India where Kipling was born, the drawings
of the Just So Stories, (examples are published here) were Kipling's
original creations. "The Just So Stories", his daughter wrote,
"were first told to my brother and myself during those Cape
(South Africa) winters, and when written were read aloud to us
for such suggestions as could be expected from small children.
The illustrating of the stories gave their author immense pleasure.,
and he worked at them (mostly in Indian ink) with meticulous
care and was delighted when we approved the results."
The Nobel Prize winner for Literature (1907) recalls in his
autobiography Something of Myself, that "between '92 and '96 we
managed to pay two flying visits to England... and we learned to
loathe the cold North Atlantic more and more. On one trip
our steamer came almost atop of a whale, who submerged just in
time to clear us, and looked up into my face with an unforgettable
little eye the size of a bullock's... When I was illustrating the
Just So Stories, I remembered and strove after that eye." Captions
and drawings on these pages are Kipling's own.
OLD MAN KANGAROO: "This is... Old Man Kangaroo at
five in the afternoon, when he had got his beautiful hind
legs just as Big God Nqong had promised. You can see that
it is five o'clock, because Big God Nqong's pet tame clock
says so. That is Nqong, in his bath, sticking his feet out.
Old Man Kangaroo is being rude to Yellow-Dog Dingo. Yellow-
Dog Dingo has been trying to catch Kangaroo all across
Australia. You can see the marks of Kangaroo's' big new
feet running ever so far back over the bare hills. "
HOW THE WHALE GOT
HIS THROAT: "This is the
picture of the Whale swallowing
the Mariner with his infinite-
resource-and-sagacity, and the
raft and the jack-knife and his
suspenders, which you must not
forget. The buttony-things are
the Mariner's suspenders, and
you can see the knife close by
them. He is sitting on the raft,
but it has tilted up sideways, so
you don't see much of it. The
whity thing by the Mariner's
left hand Is a piece of wood
that he was trying to row the
raft with when the Whale came
along. The wood is called the
jaws-of-a-gaff. The mariner left
It outside when he went In."
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. August 1957
mm
mm
mm
mm
iwidw
ahmt
mm:
mvvf
mm
Mm
mm
raw
ftp
U NU toh
i
mm
mam
mm
mm
itml
mm
mm
mm
mm.
ami
km
HOW THE ALPHABET WAS MADE: "This is the story of Taffimai
Metallumai carved on an old tusk a very long time ago by the Ancient
Peoples. If you read my story, or have It read to you, you can see how it
is all told out on the tusk. The tusk was part of an old tribal trumpet
that belonged to the Tribe of Tegumai. The pictures were scratched on it
with a nail or something, and then the scratches were filled up with black
wax, but all the dividing lines and the five little rounds at the bottom were
filled with red wax."
THE CAT THAT WALKED BY HIMSELF: This is the picture of the
Cat that Walked by Himself, walking by his wild lone through the Wet
Wild Woods and waving his wild tail. There Is nothing else In the picture
except some toadstools. They had to grow there because the woods were
so wet. The lumpy thing on the low branch isn't a bird. It is moss that
grew there because the Wild Woods were so wet."
GOTTFRIED KELLER
The painter not the poet
held the pen
Gottfried Keller, the great Swiss novelist and
poet of the German language was a painter who,
having discovered his talents for writing,
abandoned art altogether for literature. Keller determin¬
ed to become an artist in 1834. For three years he
groped to find his way, falling upon a series of
incompetent teachers, and finally moving to Munich in
1840. Here he spent a couple of lean years as an exile
living amongst the local Swiss community and trying to
develop his style. After illness and poverty had
undermined his strength he returned to Zurich and
began increasingly to occupy himself with writing. In
1846, on the basis of a volume of poems published by
Keller, the Cantonal Government awarded him a pension
which he used to study philosophy at Heidelberg, thereby
finally breaking with his active interest in painting.
Albert Schweitzer said that Keller's writings "only
become intelligible when one recalls that a dramatic
painter, not a poet, is holding the pen."
Keller's pictures show a keen feeling for nature, for
the rivers, forest, lakes and mountains amongst which
he was born and reared.
He was not very original either in his choice of
subjects or in his treatment, nor did his haphazard
training permit him to acquire a sureness of technique.
The sketch of a medieval town (above) which dates from
his return to Zurich (1843) is an interesting illustration
of the conflict within Keller at that time. The inspi¬
ration is plainly literary, the idea having originally been
to depict a town of gables and turrets over which there
hangs a kind of sleepy, timeless, enchantment. In the
foreground there was to have been a meeting of two
animated processions but his evident inability to grapple
with the problems of figure drawing discouraged Keller
and he never completed the romance he so clearly saw
in his mind's eye.
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
'A certain Thackeray', caricaturist
William Makepeace Thackeray first won fame a century
ago as a writer. Yet, looking over the shoulder of
Thackeray the novelist and satirical humorist, there
was always Thackeray the artist and caricaturist, ever ready
with pencil and sketch book to reinforce the wit and satire
of his pen.
Like one of his own characters, Clive, in The Newcomes,
Thackeray had shown early talent as a caricaturist and in
1834 (at the age of 23), deciding that he could draw better
than he could do anything else, he determined to qualify as
an artist and went to study in Paris. There he worked in
an atelier and afterwards copied pictures industriously at the
Louvre.
He pursued this ambition to be a professional painter for
a number of years yet though we find him in 1836 applying
to Charles Dickens to take over the illustrations of the
Pickwick Papers (Dickens turned him down) he was already
beginning to direct a part of his efforts towards literature.
The following year, Thomas Carlyle, whose History of the
Ui*j^ 2 -i s«is
A um«! wd\\exd LX U-UVÛ
J! Y
WILLIAM MAKEPEACE THAfKEHAT
French Revolution Thackeray had reviewed in the Times,
wrote of him as "one Thackeray, a half monstrous Cornish
giant, kind of painter, Cambridge man and Paris newspaper
correspondent who is now writing for his life in London."
Soon Thackeray was invited to write for the newly-started
Punch, and though he contributed to many periodicals
during his life, it was to Punch that he gave his best criticism,
satire, parody, versifying, caricatures, political comment and
drawing. Altogether he contributed 380 sketches to the
magazine.
Thackeray's Vanity Fair appearing
in monthly instalments during 1847
and '48 established him as one of the
first of English novelists. He received
50 guineas a number, including
illustrations. He supplied the illus¬
trations for many more of his own
works, including Comic Tales and
Sketches, The Irish Sketch Book,
Memoirs of Mr. Char¬
les Yellowplush, and
The Book of Snobs.
At all times in his
life he delighted in
drawing caricatures to
amuse children and
some of them which he
made in Rome in 1853 '
were expanded into the
delightful burlesque The Rose and the Ring,
written under his favourite pen name of
"M.A. (Michael Angelo) Titmarsh" which
Îhe took because his own nose had been
broken by a schoolmate just as Michel¬
angelo's had been broken more than three
centuries before.
Today many of Thackeray's drawings are
preserved in three London museums the
British Museum, the Victoria and Albert and
the South' Kensington reminders of the
artistic talent of a great author of whom one
critic has said: "Had he finally chosen draw¬
ing as his preferred medium he would have
belonged to the Hogarth school."
All the drawings shown here were done
by Thackeray for Vanity Fair except for the
sketch of a page of the "time of Mary,
Queen of Scots". This was drawn by
Thackeray while with an American family
in New York in 1852. In Thackeray's Letters
to an American Family (1904), it is noted
that he took great interest in the plans and
amusements of this family and on one
occasion when the costume for a juvenile
fancy dress ball was under discussion "he
took pen and paper as he sat chatting... and
drew little sketches of the proper dress for a
page of various periods, being well-versed in
all the details belonging to each costume."
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. August 1957
/,
~%x
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
GEORGE SAND
and her entourage
AN entry in George Sand's private diary dated
25 November 1834 reads thus: "Delacroix showed
me a collection of drawings by Goya, at the same
time mentioning Alfred's name and saying that he
would have made a fine painter if he had wished which I
can well believe ! He intends to copy the sketches in
Alfred's album..."
This praise throws fresh light on the great romantic
poet, Alfred de Musset, the centenary of whose death is
being celebrated this year. Musset did not paint, but
his drawings and pen-and-ink sketches, often pungent and
witty, enable us to appreciate his real talent.
As a young man he hesitated between taking up law,
medicine, music or art before choosing poetry. In those
days he spent many mornings in the Louvre copying Old
Masters. But pretty soon he destroyed all these efforts.
With the exception of a few fashionable portraits and
sketches inspired by Goya, to which George Sand refers
in her diary, this mournful poet tried mainly to draw cari¬
catures and humorous cartoons.
GEORGIA S. is a poor disguise for George Sand who appears
partly hidden by her fan. This drawing by Alfred de Musset is
included in a sketch book which Musset kept during a trip to
Italy with her. The sketch above, right, is a caricature of George
Sand done by Mérimée in 1854. She was then a middle-aged
lady with "beautiful black eyes." Twenty years separate the two
drawings. George Sand was herself an artist and tried to make a
living from her painting when she separated from her husband.
Whether as artist or writer, the best period of
Musset's life was spent during his friendship
with George Sand, who also painted. Of her
own pencil and water colour portraits she said. "My
little heads were not too bad, but they lacked originality."
When she separated from her husband she tried to live
by painting flowers and birds on snuff-boxes and on
other little Spa-wood boxes. Later, with her son Maurice,
who was a painter, designer and sculptor, she helped
decorate the theatre, and a marionette theatre in her
native town of Nohant. Towards the end of her life
she painted water-colours in order to build up a dowry
for her granddaughters.
George Sand was the centre of attraction of a large
circle of artists and writers. One of these was Prosper
Mérimée, the great short-story writer. He, too, was
fond of drawing. During the trips he had to make as
inspector of historic monuments, he filled notebooks with
sketches of the country through which he passed. Draw¬
ing caricatures came easily to him and he "scattered
sketches around him like cigar butts", according to
Sainte-Beuve who also said of him: "But it is pleasant
enough for each of us to recognize himself uglier than he
really is." To a woman he loved for more than twenty
years, Mérimée dedicated a series of water colours and
drawings which have not yet been published.
48
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. August 1957
ARTHUR RIMBAUD
Maps and atlases
were his canvas
STENDHAL DANCING, below, is also in Musset's "Italian
Sketchbook", though he did the drawing in France. This scene
was described by George Sand in The Story of my Life. She
shows Stendhal "... dancing around the table with his fur lined
boots... rather grotesque and not at all attractive." Below, left,
a drawing of Chopin by George Sand, of whom she said: "He
is the only man who has devoted himself entirely to me, with
no regret for the past, and no reservation about the future."
BY the age of 19 Arthur Rimbaud had written all his poetry
and washed his hands of literature. The rest of his life
(he died in Marseilles at 37 unaware that Verlaine's study of
him in Les poètes maudits (1881) had made him famous) he spent
wandering about the world described by him as "so big and full
of magnificent countries that the life of a thousand men would
not suffice to visit them." Even as a child Rimbaud was fas¬
cinated with foreign places and spent much time in his native
Charleville poring over maps and atlases. It is on these that
his earliest drawings are found. "Three Citizens of Charleville"
(above) was drawn on the back of a map of India when he
was 15; "Man in a Frock-Coat" (below) was done on the back
of a map of ancient Greece; another was drawn on a map of
Gaul. A large in-folio atlas belonging to his family was found,
after his death, to be covered with caricatures and sketches.
Drawing was Rimbaud's hobby all his life. He has left delicate
drawings, including one of Aden in 1880 and sketches of Abyssinia
where ha spent his last years as a trader.
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
YOL II. SO. 3333, SEW YORK : SUNDAY, OCTOBER 2, 1870. PRICE FTVE CENTS'.
MARK TWAIN'S MAP
OF THE
FORTIFICATIONS OF PARIS.
azuiwMTuafÖ ¡¡AH1**
We reproduce here a burlesque map of the fortifications
of Paris drawn by Mark Twain and published in the "New
York Herald" of Sunday, October 2, 1870. At this time,
the siege of Paris during the Franco-Prussian war had
just begun and newspapers the world over were filled
with maps of Paris as is journalistic practice. Below we
publish the text written by Mark Twain for his map.
TO THE READER
The above map explains itself.
The idea of this map is not original with me, but is
borrowed from the Tribune and the other great metro¬
politan journals.
I claim no other merit for this production (if I may so
call it) than that it is accurate. The main blemish of
the city paper maps, of which it is an imitation, is that
in them more attention seems paid to artistic pictur-
esqueness than geographical reliability.
Inasmuch as this is the first time I ever tried to draft
and engrave a map, or attempt anything in the line of
art at all, the commendations the work has received and
the admiration it has excited among the people have been
very grateful to my feelings. And it is touching to reflect
that by far the most enthusiastic of these praises have
come from people who know nothing at all about art.
By an unimportant oversight I have engraved the map
so that it reads wrong-end first, except to left-handed
people. I forgot that in order to make it right in print
it should be drawn and engraved upside down. However,
let the student who desires to contemplate the map standr
on his head or hold it before her looking-glass. That will
bring it right.
The reader will comprehend at a glance that that piece
of river with the "High Bridge" over it got left out to one
side by reason of a slip of the graving-tool which rendered
SO
it necessary to change the entire course of the River
Rhine or else spoil the map. After having spent two days
in digging and gouging at the map, I would have changed
the course of the Atlantic Ocean before I would have lost
so much work.
I have never had so much trouble with anything in my
life as I did with this map. I had heaps of little fortifi¬
cations scattered all around Paris, at first, but every now
and then my instruments would slip and fetch away
whole miles of batteries, and leave the vicinity as clean
as if the Prussians had been there.
The reader will find it well to frame this map for future
reference, so that it may aid in extending popular intelli¬
gence and dispelling the widespread ignorance of the day.
MARK TWAIN.
OFFICIAL COMMENDATIONS
It is the only map of the kind I ever saw. (U.S. Grant.)
It places the situation in an entirely new light. (Bis¬
marck.)
I cannot look upon it .without shedding tears. (Brigham
Young.)
My wife was for years afflicted with freckles, and
though everything was done for her relief that could be
done, all was in vain. But, sir, since her first glance at
your map, they have entirely left her. She has nothing
but convulsions now. (J. Smith.)
If I had had this map I could have got out of Metz
without any trouble. (Bazaine.)
It is very nice, large print. (Napoleon.)
I have seen a great many maps in my time, but none
that this one reminds me of. (Trochu.)
It is but fair to say that in some respects it is a truly
remarkable map. (W.T. Sherman.)
I said to my son, Frederic William, "If you could only
make a map like that, I would be perfectly willing to see
you dieeven anxious." (William III.)
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
com-o jÇ/n y-vcs- noche 1. l<*/wva¿i/-me j
THE 'LYRICOGRAPHIES'
OF RAFAEL ALBERTI
Rafael Alberti the Spanish poet who won inter¬
national fame in 1929 with his masterpiece
Sobre los Angeles (About Angels) was first
attracted to painting when still a student at
a Jesuit college. He was only 16 when he
held his first exhibition in Madrid, in 1918.
He later decided that poetry was his real voca¬
tion and published several books of verse, first
in Madrid and later in Buenos Aires where he
has lived for I 5 years. He did not forsake his
love of the plastic arts, however, and continued
to work at his painting. In I 954 he published
a collection of his best drawings in colour
under the title Liricografias planografiadas (a
series of poems interpreted graphically) in a
limited edition of I 00 copies (Ediciones Galcria
Bonino, Buenos Aires). The painting published
here is one of the most c thereal in the collec¬
tion, with delicate shades of red, blue and
grey. A personal friend of Garcia Lorca in
his youth, Alberti, like Lorca, was fond of both
popular and erudite themes. His originality
as a poet grew as his taste for colour
developed. One of his most beautiful works
is his song-poem A la Pintura (To Painting),
which he took three years to complete.
VLADIMIR MAYAKOWSKY (1893-
1930), poet and dramatist, is considered
In the U.S.S.R. as the great poet of the
Soviet Revolution. He was also a profes¬
sional painter and caricaturist. He stu¬
died at the Beaux Arts school in Moscow,
joining the newly emerging Futurist
Movement in painting and poetry which
called for scrapping the whole cultural
tradition of the past. He later broke
with this movement. During the Revolu¬
tion he did some 3,000 satirical drawings
for street and shop-window panels. His
illustrated abecedarium is now a textbook
for Soviet children. Mayakowsky not
only wrote successful plays (the revival
of K/op The Bedbug was a tremendous
hit in Moscow recently) but also acted,
did the costume designs, and stage decor.
Right, one of a series of costume sketches
for his satirical play Mystery Bouffe. j t,a.n'!-k
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
ROYAL BIRD WITH ARTIST ADMIRER
Carlo Levi, of Christ Stopped at Eboli fame is also a painter of note.
He loves nocturnal birds of every kind wonderful animals' , he
says, "which more than any other resemble gods. Among all these
creatures of the night, the author-artist gives first place to a rare and
beautiful Royal Owl from Ethiopia which he has named Graziadio
(shown on left). Carlo Levi has painted Graziadio, written and even
composed poetry about him, and his studio (above) is filled with
paintings, drawings and sketches of the owl My owl, he says,
which comes from the centre of Africa and the savage deserts,
and which is as great as the greatest of birds and of angels. " (For
story about Carlo Levi, the artist, and a special article entitled
" The Owl " by the internationally-famous author, see pages 25-27).
]]>
</page>
</document>
