<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="068278eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
He *5. ( ,q<?. £
m
FEBRUARY
19 5 6
(9th yeor)
Price : 9d. (U. K.)
40 francs (France)
Iff FAMILY
OF MAN
A camera
testament
TECHNICAL
ASSISTANCE
Pitfalls, snags
and a look at
human side
iThe earthworm,
our N° 1 farmer
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
v
-"lift!
mu
S K
!Wä
«H
mai
- HS?~Jki: <
P » <S#Jfc
Wt
l&e- A ¿JP
%Wé f-
I >\
J *"""
iite
""*n» m. ,î,'*l'.*4 I
«F
&&>?
The Family of Man at work.
(See page 18)
India Copyright Howard Sochurek-Lifc.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
/
U'KESCO
archives yJ
FEBRUARY - 1956
9th YEAR
CONTENTS
PAGE
3 EDITORIAL
4 FIVE READERS A MINUTE I I HOURS EVERY DAY
Inside Asia's busiest public library
By Frank M. Gardner
9 GREAT HOPE OF THE 20th CENTURY
Technical Assistance for economic development
12 THE HUMAN SIDE OF PROGRESS
By Luther H. Evans
15 THE EARTHWORM
The world's N° I farmer
By David Gunston
18 THE FAMILY OF MAN
A camera testament
20 HIS NAME IS ALL MEN
By Carl Sandburg
24 THE POWER OF WORDS
Expressions which poison race relations
By Cyril Bibby
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organi¬
zation
Editorial Offices
Unesco, 19, Avenue Kleber, Paris 16, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Circulation Manager
Jean Groffier
U.S.A. : Henry Evans
Individual articles not copyrighted may be reprinted from THE UNESCO
COURIER but must be accompanied by the following credit line: "Reprinted
from UNESCO COURIER". Signed articles reprinted must carry the author's
name. Prints of non-copyright photos are available on request.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied by an inter¬
national reply coupon covering postage.
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of THE UNESCO
COURIER.
Annual subscription rates of THE UNESCO COURIER : 8/-¡ $ 2.00 or 400
French 1rs or equivalent (U.S. edition % 2.50)
(MC. S5.I 99 A)
The Unesco Courier. February 1956
COVER PHOTO
Cover and photo on opposite page are
taken from " The Family of Man ", a
photographic exhibition which Carl
Sandburg, the famous American poet,
has called " a drama of the grand canyon
of humanity. " (See page 18)
Switzerland. Copyright Jakob Tuggencr
P
I HOTOGRAPHY has been hailed as the most typical art
of the 20th century. Yet it is hardly more than a
hundred years since the invention of "writing with light"
opened a new window on the world to mankind. Certain
persons can still remember the time when good pictures
were a rarity; when only the most expensive books had
good illustrations; when only the wealthy could afford
good pictures in their homes.
Today photographs are everywhere around us. We see
them in books and magazines, in newspapers, on posters
in shops, and in the high-quality colour reproductions of
works of art hanging on our walls. We can see pictures
in motion on a cinema screen or projected thousands of
miles through space by television. We can read cumber¬
some, weighty books from tiny microfilm records stored
easily in libraries, and we can record what scientists see
with a telescope, an electron microscope or an X-ray
machine. Photography is now more widely used by
science, industry, the arts and schools than even the
most fanatic of its early prophets had ever dared to
imagine.
Certain notes of alarm, it is true, have been voiced of
late against this mass invasion o-f photography. "Nothing
is more vain," one art historian recently wrote, "than to
believe in the all-powerfulness of the pictorial image." .
At a Unesco-supported international colloquium in Geneva
last September, a distinguished group of thinkers debated
the subject under the general theme "Is Culture in Peril ?".
The French writer André Chamson, in a profound analysis
of the achievements of ' photography, warned of the
danger of a "possible imperialism" of the pictorial image
which is flooding the world "like a burglar, armed with
a jemmy, snapping the lock off a door and entering a
house by surprise."
But even the severest critics do not seek to deny that
photography has helped to enrich our lives, that it has
given us a new vision of the world, and that it speaks a
universal language. Last summer an international round
table on the role of the image in contemporary civiliza¬
tion was held at Unesco House under the auspices of the
French National Commission for Unesco and the Interna¬
tional Biennal of Photography Cinema and Optics. Scien¬
tists, educators, artists and technicians from many
countries engaged in a broad exchange oí views on the
many domains of human activity now dependent on
photography. They stressed the importance of the
pictorial image in information and education and its
value as a new "universal language capable of being
understood by everyone regardless of degree of culture."
They pointed to the use that could be made of pictures
in promoting international understanding. Their meeting
also saw the creation of an International Centre for still
and animated Photography with headquarters in Paris.
The round table discussed the 'familiar saying that "a
picture is worth a thousand words" and took the view
that certain photographs are "worth ten million words
provided they are accompanied by about ten words." In
certain cases, it was admitted, appropriate arrangement
or lay-out can take the place of captions. Every good
photograph has a specific meaning but its inclusion into
a group or ensemble imparts new meaning to it.
One exhibition entitled "The Family of Man" was cited
as an example where each photograph by itself "does not
tell the story" but the message is conveyed by the
ensemble of photographs. In this issue a section is
devoted to a presentation of "The Family of Man" a
camera testament that illustrates one of the principal
goals of Unesco today: the unity of all mankind within its
varied diversity.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
READERSAMINUTE.il HOURS EVERY
I BUSIEST
PUBLIC LIBRARY
'
:&*<
£fc
by Frank M. Gardner
hen the Government of India and UNESCO opened
an experimental public library In Delhi just over four
years ago pessimists pointed out that' most of the city's
population was illiterate. Nevertheless at the end of
the first year 2,300 readers a day were visiting the
library, and for 78 per cent of them this was their first
visit to a public library. Today the library has over
60,000 books in English, Urdu and Hindi and serves
70,000 people a month. As Asia's busiest and most
modern public libraryopen 1 1 hours a day, and every
day of the weekit recently served as headquarters and
"laboratory" for a UNESCO seminar on the develop¬
ment of public libraries in Asia directed by Mr. Frank,
M. Gardner, author of the accompanying article. Mr.
Gardner who is Borough Librarian of Luton in the
United Kingdom spent eight months in Delhi in 1951
and 1952 as UNESCO consultant to the Indian Government
and helped to set up the library which today has a staff
of 47 directed by Mr. Des Raj Kalia, a UNESCO-trained
Indian librarian. Its present services include a Children's
Department, Reference Section, Lending Library and a
Social Education and Extension Service. Photos on these
pages show (from left to right): an assistant librarian
bringing new books to the Delhi Library, the Library
building opposite the Delhi Railway Station, library users
keeping up to date with the news in the reading room.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Somewhere in Asia a young man is on his way to the
public library. He appears to be under thirty, he is
probably unmarried, and he is either a student or a
clerical worker of some kind. The library is some distance
from his home, and he has to make a special journey to
get there, since it is not on his regular route to office or
university, but he goes fairly regularly, and has been a
member for quite a long time. When he gets to the
library he will spend a little time reading, probably a
newspaper, or perhaps one of the reference works, be-fore
he changes his book, which he prefers to read at home.
He is allowed only one book he would like more but the
library has not yet a large enough stock to permit this.
Though he can read English and possibly Urdu, he
usually prefers a book in his native language, Hindi if he
can find one. He probably chooses a
novel by an author he knows, most
likely a love story or a story of
modern India. He is not greatly
concerned about the newness of the
book it is the contents that interest
him. If he wants a non-fiction book
he takes it because of its general in¬
terest rather than as a source of in¬
formation for use in an examination
or a college assignment. He would
probably prefer a biography, but
there aren't enough in Hindi, so he
may take out a book of plays or
poetry, of which there are plenty.
This is not. any particular young
man. It is a composite picture of the
typical reader at the Delhi Public
Library in India as shown by a survey
recently undertaken by Unesco of the
use and reading habits of the
members. The survey is an appraisal
of what the Library has achieved in
its five years of existence, the nature
of its problems in the past, and what
its problems are likely to be in the
future. This is the first survey to be
undertaken "for a public library in
Asia, and the results are not only of
vital, interest to library development
in Asia, but also tell a fascinating
story of social habits which sometimes
diverge from and sometimes parallel social habits in
other countries.
The story is told by the people themselves, through
answers given to 1,300 questionnaires by groups of users
and non-users of the Library. It is itself a commentary
on social habits for whereas in the West the questionnaire
has become an object of some suspicion, in Delhi,
according to the Delhi School of Social Work which
undertook the distribution and recording of the ques¬
tionnaires, the utmost- co-operation was achieved in
obtaining answers to the 40 or so questions put to each
person.
One startling fact that immediately emerges is that the
The Unesco Courier. February 1956
membership of the library is almost exclusively male, only
6 % of the readers being women, and only 14 % over
thirty years old. Though the Library has not been
successful in attracting the female sex, it has been a great
draw for children, for 29 % of the members are children
under 16 an encouraging sign for the future. Even
though women are shy about coming to the Library, they
possibly induce the menfolk to come on their behalf, as
over a third of readers report that their books are used
by other members of the family. Even the old-fashioned,
though pleasant habit of reading aloud survives, for 10 %
of people questioned say they read aloud to their families.
Eleven percent of readers are university students a
high figure, but not as high as was feared by those who
thought that a public library in Asia was likely to be
swamped by students seeking additional textbooks.
Nearly all the readers have at least a primary education,
and most have a secondary education.
What do these young people come to read at the library?
What languages do they read in? What subjects do they
prefer? Primarily they do not come to read in the library
at all. Like Western readers, they prefer to read their
books at home, and though the library has reading rooms
for newspapers and periodicals, and a growing reference
section, its main business is lending books over a million
in the last four years. Of members questioned, 90 %
gave the reading of books as their first preference, and
nearly 90 % prefer to read them at home, which may
surprise those who have thought that the demand for
public libraries in Asia could be satisfied by newspaper
reading rooms, and that home conditions might limit the
value of lending libraries.
The purposes oí reading are wide, and not easily defined.
But of 220 readers questioned, only 17 said they used the
public library for college or school assignments, and
another 17 to prepare for examinations. Eighty-four
people said they read for general interest, 49 to increase
general knowledge. Ten had the laudable ambition of
getting a better job, and 35 wanted to improve their
reading ability. It would be hard to find a better all-
round justification of public library objectives than is
contained in these statements.
About half the readers prefer fiction, about a quarter
non-fiction, and the others have no preference. Romance
is an important -factor, since love stories come first in
fiction favour (possibly the women at home exerting in¬
fluence here!), next come stories about modern India,
crime and detective stories, and stories about historical
India. Political novels and psychological novels are
among the least liked, as also, curiously enough are love
stories. Apparently the romantic novel is both actively
liked and actively disliked.
In non-fiction, the greatest preference is
for biography (chosen nearly twice as often
as any other subject) then -follow literature,
(Cont'd on
page 7)
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
ASIA'S BUSIEST LIBRARY (Cont'd)
NO RESISTING THE MAGIC LURE
Children seem to be drawn into the Delhi public library as if by the legendary Pied Piper. Around 30%
of members are under 16 years of age an encouraging sign for the future. Hundreds of children visit
the library every day attracted by a special reading room where they can enjoy simple games and suitable
books. Library received toys and games (above, left) through Unesco's Voluntary International Assis¬
tance Division. As there is a shortage of books in Hindi and Urdu, English words in young girl's book
(above, right) have been transcribed by hand under the original text. But older children are only too
glad to show off their knowledge of English by explaining the texts to their younger companions (right).
A rapt audience (below) assembles for the- "Story Hour" in the children's room at the Library.
UNESCO photos.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
40»/o OF VILLAGERS, BO'/i OF
TOWNSFOLK CHOOSE FICTION
The Unesco Courier. February 1956
(Continued from
page 5)
politics, and self-improvement. The
most disliked subjects, according to
replies given by readers, are politics,
psychology and technology.
When the enquiry was extended beyond the Central
Library to other service points that have been established,
some further interesting facts came out. The Mobile
Library service covers parts of Delhi and also extends
into rural areas. One would naturally expect the villages
to have a simpler outlook on reading, but in fact, it
emerges quite definitely that the taste of the villager is
more solid than that of the -urban reader. In the urban
area, 80 % of the books loaned are fiction, but when the
library goes to the villages, carrying the same stock, only
40 % of the books issued are fiction. The village reader
prefers biography, religion and literature.
Deposit stations have been established by the Library
in Social Education Centres, and here again the pattern
of readers and their choices vary from those who use the
Central Library and the Mobile Library. : Readers at
deposit stations include more older people and more
women, 21 % of the readers being female. The standard
of education is also lower, which is what one would
expect, since the social education centres are specifically
for the less-educated
classes.
But if these readers
are less-educated, they
are much more vocal
about possible improve¬
ments in the library
service than readers at
the Central Library.
Whereas very few read-,
ers there have any
complaint, 73 readers
questioned at deposit
stations voiced 161
complaints. Nearly all
want more books, some
want simpler books,
some want more books
in Hindi, others more
books in English, some
want more variety,
others more books by
modern writers. They
are all united, however,
on one thing they
want more books.
And here lies one of
the major expansion
problems of the Delhi
Public Library. In five
years, it has accumu¬
lated a stock of over
60,000 books. Only,
half of these are in
Hindi, whereas nearly
two-thirds of the libra¬
ry's use is in this lan¬
guage and the demand
is increasing all the
time. But the books are simply not available and even
those that exist wear out faster than they can be replaced.
The life oî a book in Hindi averages, as shown by this
inquiry, about 16 loans before it is worn out, as against
between fifty and a hundred loans in a Western library.
Thus the Delhi Library is being defeated by its own
success. The fact that nearly 50 % of its readers travel
a mile or more to use it, that the unbearably hot summer
of Delhi makes no difference at all to library use, shows
the eagerness of the readers. But speed of expansion is
dictated by the availability of books -for purchase, and the
facilities for maintaining and increasing a" usable
bookstock.
There are, of course, other problems too, shown, up by
the survey, problems that must be solved before the public
UNESCO photos.
EAGER READERS: Children are among the most enthusiastic rural readers
and crowd eagerly around the "bookmobile" to see what new "treasures" it
carries on Its shelves this time. Little girl (top of page) can't wait to get home but
starts to read her book on the steps of the mobile library visiting her village.
library is a
completely in¬
tegrated part
of community
life. Not near¬
ly enough
women, older
people (only
2,5 % are over
45), and above
all, not nearly
enough newly-
literates or less
educated peo¬
ple use the fa¬
cilities offered
by the library.
The children at school, the students, the educated
professional classes have seized the opportunity to profit
by the facilities of a modern public library, but the others
have not come forward, perhaps because the books avail¬
able are too difficult, perhaps because they, are overawed
by the atmosphere of a large library, perhaps because
they have no leisure to go to the library, or facilities to
read in comfort. Even the many extension activities of
the library lectures,
film shows, discussion
groups which it was
thought would attract
and hold the less edu¬
cated, are used almost
entirely by the better
educated of the library
members.
In bringing out these
facts the survey pre¬
sents a challenge and
a line of policy for the
future that will un¬
doubtedly be taken up.
The problems are
those of circumstances
and ones not easily
overcome. But once
realized, they can be
met, for not only does
the report show up
clearly and unmistak-
, ably what are the pro-
' blems, it also offers a
line of approach. By
placing its branches in
fundamental educa¬
tion centres, with the
backing of a central
library organization
and trained staff, a
public library can fur¬
ther its own purposes
and those of social
education. In its first
Ave years the library
has achieved a great
deal. Now that this objective report has been compiled,
it can extend its horizons and can advance towards
further goals.
But it should not be thought that the better-educated
in Asia can fend for themselves in their reading needs.
They are the people who can benefit immediately from
public libraries, and here the Delhi Public Library's
success is unqualified.
One of the most startling facts brought out by the
survey is that 26 % of the Library's 20,000 readers did not
read at all before joining the library, and 60 % have no
books whatever at home. More than anything else, the
need for more public library services in Asia is shown by
these two facts.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
ASIA'S BUSIEST LIBRARY (Cont'd)
SMALL FRY CRITICS compare notes on the books they have just
drawn from the mobile library which has made its regular visit.
YOUNG FRUIT SELLER settles down for a quiet read while he waits
for customers to come along. Children are among the most avid readers.
SELF-IMPROVEMENT BOOKS are among
first four non-fiction choices of readers at the
Delhi public library. Greatest preference is
for biography (chosen nearly twice as often
as any other subject). .'Mother (right) reads
a book in Hindi on child care while a craftsman
(above) consults a work which will help him
improve his technical knowledge and skill.
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1956
TECHNICAL
ASSISTANCE
GREAT
HOPE OF
THE 20th
CENTURY
During the past five years, thousands of men and
women have left their home countries and have
gone to all parts of the world ranging from the
plateaux of Bolivia to the rice paddies of the Philip¬
pines to work for a common ideal: to help other peoples
fight three great evils: hunger, poverty and ignorance.
They have been transplanting their special skills and
experience to help these peoples to modernize their
industries, increase their knowledge and develop their
natural resources, under the United Nations Expanded
Programme of Technical Assistance.
Technical Assistance covers a wide range of diverse
activities. As one authority has said: "'Truly to judge and
assay technical assistance, one must go out into the fields
and to the factories, the fishing grounds and the hospitals,
the classrooms and the airfields in which the Programme
operates. It is there that one finds out what technical
assistance means and with what true appreciation and
regard the governments and peoples of these countries
look upon those who perform its works."
The degree of under-development differs from country
to country; consequently, the nature and the types of
UNESCO is expanding its technical assistance programme in education and science
this year to the highest point it has ever reached since the United Nations
world programme of technical assistance for economic development went
into operation five years ago. Following recent approval by the U.N. General
Assembly of a $29,734,000 programme of technical assistance by the United Nations
and its agencies in 1956, unesco announced that its share of this programme will
amount to $4,940,933 as compared to $3,937,653 in 1955.
Malcolm S. Adiseshiah, Assistant Unesco Director-General and former head of
UNESCO's technical assistance department, reported that UNESCO will have 300
technical assistance experts in the field in 51 countries this year. At the end
of 1955, 162 experts were working in 43 countries.
The expansion of UNESCO's programme and also the rise in its share of the
total U.N. technical assistance budget from 13 % to 16.6 % were attributed by
Mr. Adiseshiah to an increased demand for aid in education and science. Requests
now total 327 and come from 52 countries on four continents. Demand is highest
for international specialists to assist countries in modernizing their systems of
primary and secondary education. Next biggest field is that of fundamental
education (education aimed at raising living standards), followed by scientific
research, technical education, science teaching and scientific documentation centres.
Among its other technical assistance operations, UNESCO has helped to set up a
national fundamental education training centre in the back country of Liberia, has
helped to reorganize primary and secondary schools in Thailand, has shared in the
launching of two modern institutes of technology in India and has participated in
the study of water resources in Brazil and in desert research in Egypt.
assistance vary greatly in different parts of the world.
In some cases, projects may be in the preliminary stage,
designed to advise and assist the less-developed countries,
to survey their potential resources, to formulate general
plans of development and to establish the institutional
framework: administrative services and institutions
covering labour, agriculture, education, health, civil
aviation, meteorology and telecommunications.
In other cases experts or teams of experts carry out
specific assignments in connexion with particular develop¬
ment programmes. International experts are helping to
establish penicillin and DDT factories, steel and cement
plants and fertilizer and food-processing factories. They
are helping to carry out man-power organization and
vocational and technical training programmes. They are
co-operating in the development of land and water
resources, o-f livestock production, of modern slaughter¬
houses and improved systems of production and distri¬
bution of milk, with United Nations Children's Fund
(UNICEF) assistance for pasteurization plants, mechani¬
zation of fishing craft, effective use for farm implements,
and improvement of nutritional levels.
They are helping in the organi¬
zation of schools to train teachers
and provide specialized experts to
develop courses in particular bran¬
ches in technological colleges and
institutes. They are aiding in cam¬
paigns to wipe out common epidemics
and diseases such as malaria and
tuberculosis, and helping to train
personnel for the development of civil
aviation and telecommunications and
meteorological services.
The major emphasis In technical
assistance activities is on the training
of the nationals of less-developed
countries so that, in time, they can
assume the work initiated by the
experts. Special training program¬
mes are provided, such as regional
training seminars or fellowships for
study abroad at particular institu¬
tions or for practical observation and
training in the more advanced
countries.
Most technical assistance projects
also involve on-the-job
training of local person- (Cont'd on
nel under international next page)
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
TECHNICAL
ASSISTANCE
(Continued)
experts. Training is provided
for a host of administrative, cleri¬
cal and accounting staff, engine¬
ers, nurses, health workers, gen¬
eral mechanics, leather-tanners,
plumbers, carpenters, agricultural
extension workers, economists,
statisticians, teachers and commu¬
nity-development workers, radio, telephone and telegraph
technicians, air navigation and aircraft maintenance
personnel, and meteorologists. Courses are provided in
different countries by the eight organizations which
participate in the Programme.
A few illustrations show the vast range and the scope
of the U.N. Expanded Programme activities. In Brazil, in
Libya and in Turkey, the public administration schools
organized by the Technical Assistance Administration
have trained a large number of nationals in public
administration, accounting and general clerical work. In
Mexico and other Latin-American countries, in Libya, and
Haiti, in Egypt, Iraq and other Arab States, in Ceylon and
Thailand, more than 1,000 trained specialists in funda¬
mental education and community development are now
at work on national plans for decreasing illiteracy and
raising living standards.
Over 600 engineers, foremen and skilled workers from
various branches of industry in Yugoslavia, Turkey,
Bolivia, Colombia, Israel and Iran have been placed under
the International Labour Organization (ILO) worker-
trainees' programme for observation and for on-the-job
training in 314 different firms of sixteen host countries.
In Haiti ILO experts have assisted in developing training
courses through which many automobile mechanics,
general mechanics, woodworkers and leather-tánners
have been trained.
In Afghanistan, Ceylon, India and Thailand malaria
control according to standards and methods recommend¬
ed by World Health Organization (WHO) experts has been
expanded under local responsibility and has become an
integral part of the national health services.
In Bolivia, Brazil, Ecuador, Gold Coast, Greece, Iran,
Iraq, Jamaica, Pakistan, Syria, Tanganyika and Yugo¬
slavia international experts were provided to assist in the
development of water resources for power production,
land reclamation, irrigation and consumption in connexion
with the over-all development programmes of these
countries.
Vast projects for years ahead
As a result of preliminary surveys carried out in 1952-
53, planned and systematic assistance is now being
provided by the Food and Agriculture Organization
(FAO) to Brazil for the development oí the Amazon Valley.
In Ceylon and in India, the fishing-boat mechanization
programme of FAO has reached a stage where practical
results in terms of better and larger catches can be
realized.
Assistance is being given under regional and inter¬
regional projects. A number of problems concern more
than one country, and thus could often be handled more
economically and more effectively on a regional basis.
Training seminars, in which nationals of countries with
similar climatic and physical conditions participate, provi¬
de practical demonstration and training. The eradication
of human and animal diseases which do not respect
national frontiers, depends on joint action on the part of
the countries concerned. The improvement in the living
conditions of particular groups, such as the Andean-
Indian population in Bolivia, Ecuador and Peru, can be
brought about more effectively through special regional
projects. The Central American States have decided to
promote their economic co-operation and to carry out a
programme of economic integration, and experts are
being provided, on a regional basis, to advise the States
concerned.
National and international problems that call for
technical assistance are on a vast, even an alarming
scale. They will take years to work out satisfactorily.
And, in the long run, the solutions will depend on the
efforts of the people themselves. Many countries are
now engaged in far-reaching development schemes of
their own, but where technical assistance is applied
properly, the process may be shortened in innumerable
ways for more than half of the world's people.
33 EMBLEMS
OF INTERNATIONAL
CO-OPERATION
Natural Resources
Survey
Productivity Cottage Industries,
Handicrafts
land and Water Use Crop Production
and Protection
n m es
Medical Education
and Training
r^ikT
Public Health
Administration
Teacher Training Science Teaching
To give a complete picture of all work being done
under the U.N. Expanded Programme of Technical Assis¬
tance around the world would require a map many times
the size of the one above. Only the locations of regional
and inter-regional projects, seminars and training centres
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1956
Economic Planning Statistics
and Policy
LuHJ Mi5-**>^S
Public Power Production Transport
Administration and Distribution
ö E
Civil Aviation Manufacturing,
Processing
Mining
s a
\nimal Production Fisheries
ind Disease Control
Forestry
n ra
Agricultural
Economics
Agricultural
Extension
Malaria and
Insect Control
m f1
Communicable
Diseases
Health Demonstration
Areas
p.i m
rechnical Education Vocational Training Labour Conditions Social Security Housing and
and Administration and Social Welfare Planning
ÇÎ FS G
Fundamental
Education
Nutrition and
Home Economics
Co-operatives
together with symbols indicating type of work being
done last year are shown here. Where development
problems concern several countries, they can be handled
more economically by regional projects. Bolivia, Ecuador
and Peru, for example, are working together to improve
the living standards of the Indians on the-high plateaux
of the Andes and are being aided by the Andean Indian
Mission. The Central American ¿States are carrying
out a programme of economic Integration with advice
and assistance given by United Nations technical experts.
I I
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
TECHNICAL
ASSISTANCE
(Continued)
THE HUMAN SIDE
OF PROGRESS
by Luther H. Evans
Director-General of Unesco.
r-p-i ECHNicAL assistance to the so-
^ J_ called underdeveloped coun-
^Lm ^f^^m ^B tries has been referred to as
^m ^^^Ê 1 "the great hope of the 20th cen-
^1 *^^L9 ^M tury". The initial enthusiasms,
^^ mm^ ^H however, which characterized the
^^^^^_ ^H launching of this great pro-
^L^L^L^L^k ^^k gramme, whether in the form of
^^^^^y T^LU bilateral or regional national
agreements or through the United
Nations and the Specialized
Agencies, has been associated recently with an increasing
concern with what such a programme does to the human
beings and to the societies at the receiving end of
Technical Assistance.
Many people and many organizations have undertaken
a reappraisal of both the goals and the methods of the
"bold new programme," drawing our attention to what
has been called "the human cost of progress," and raising
the question of how this cost can be reduced or at least
can be kept within reasonable limits.
As we look back now on a good many years
of collective experience in this field, we
cannot fail to be struck by the errors we
could have avoided and the time and energy
we could have saved, if we had started out
with an adequate knowledge of the culture
into which an innovation was introduced.
Too often we have assumed that i'f something
was obviously good and acceptable to us, it
would prove to be equally good and
acceptable to others.
A school for the training of nurses, for
example, is set up in a particular region, and
then it is discovered that the attitude
toward nursing is such that "respectable" girls will not
enrol; courses are instituted for instruction in agricul¬
tural techniques in a community where long-stand¬
ing tradition is opposed to the tilling of the soil, etc.
These are perhaps extreme examples, but in varying de¬
grees we have proceeded without sufficient concern for
the value systems of others. It was, I believe, George
Bernard Shaw who suggested a revised version of the
Golden Rule, which would read somewhat as follows : Do
not unto others what you would have others do unto you.
Their tastes may be different!
It seems to me that a knowledge of motivations,
particularly economic motivations, is primary and essen¬
tial. What makes people work ? "What kinds of incentives
will make them work harder, produce more ? What kinds
of work do they like and why ? .How do they rank the
various occupations open to them ?
These questions are not always easy to answer, even
within a culture with which we are reasonably familiar.
Interviews with Western workers indicate that their
choice of occupation is by no means always determined by
practical economic motives. Other factors such as
pleasant companionship, working hours, attractive
surroundings, prestige, and the feeling of accomplishment,
may be much more powerful in many cases. When we
compare different cultures the variations are even more
striking. In some cases the prestige motive is so strong
as to override all others.
In parts of Africa, for example, it is reported that an
improvement in methods of breeding and caring for
cattle has resulted not in bringing more cattle to market,
but merely in the accretion of ever larger herds in order
to prove one's superiority over others. A knowledge of
the nature and strength of such motivations may help us
to predict the results of any change which we are plan¬
ning to introduce, and in that way pave the way for more
intelligent and effective action programmes.
Economists and administrators in many parts of the
world have become increasingly concerned with motiva¬
tions, and in some cases have even called in the survey
expert to give them the necessary background informa¬
tion. To cite only one instance, the United ' States Gov¬
ernment during the last War arranged for a survey to
be conducted on the factors which influenced Americans
to buy War Bonds. The interviews showed
a wide variety of motives to be operative,
and a new War Bond campaign, based on
this information, resulted in a definite
Increase m sales. There is no reason to
believe that a knowledge of motivations in
other societies and under other conditions
should prove less fruitful.
Our present concern is with motivations in
zonnexion with change, technological change.
The prevailing attitudes toward change
represent an area in which we are in need of
background data. Some cultural groups ac¬
cept change, almost any change, more
readily than do others; all cultural groups
are likely to accept change in some fields more readily
than in others. Anthropologists have discussed this
problem in some detail in connexion with the general
phenomenon of acculturation or cultural contact, but here
too their findings need tp be supplemented by data
referring to larger social units.
Psychologists have conducted investigations of resist¬
ance to technological change, but almost exclusively in
countries already highly industrialized; they have studied
resistance to further changes among people accustomed
to a complicated technology. We need to know more
about resistance to technological change on the part of
relatively unindustrialized com¬
munities why there is resistance,
under what conditions, to what
extent, and to what kinds of
change. This would be a fertile
field for further investigations by
social scientists which should
yield the practical guidance
which we require.
In overcoming resistance to
technological change there can
be little doubt that a major rôle
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Fcbiuary 1956
BREE
should be a step ahead of the surrounding culture ; they
should be adapted to the situation which is coming rather
than to the one which is here. This may entail certain
hardships, at least for a time. Schools and universities
may turn out Bantus or Egyptians or Brazilians with
advanced training as technicians or teachers in numbers
greater than can be absorbed by existing opportunities,
and some of these will unfortunately find themselves in
occupations far below the level for which they are fitted.
is played by the school, and by other, related, educational
influences. That is why we have always operated on the
assumption of a close and intimate relation between
unesco's programme in the field of education funda¬
mental education, primary and secondary schools, adult
education, etc. and the whole programme of Technical
Assistance. The school has rightly been described as the
connecting link between the old and the new culture. It
provides new skills and techniques ; opens up new horizons
of action; adds new values, and modifies pre-existing
attitudes. Through children it influences the adults and
therefore the community as a whole. Some concrete
evidence of the influence of the schools is furnished by
reports from Africa (by Meyer Fortes and Margaret Read)
which indicate that a large proportion of the boys who
attend school move to the cities to work for wages; it
appears that there is a direct relation between the amount
of schooling and the frequency of such migration.
Danger of wasted skills
At a more advanced level technical and university
training, whether at home or abroad, is beginning
to provide a group of leaders in many countries (the
French refer to them as évolués) who play a special rôle
as intermediaries between the old culture and the new.
Sometimes they are in competition with traditional leader¬
ship ; sometimes they find themselves uprooted and
insecure in their position. Frequently, however, they play
an important rôle as interpreters of the new technology
and as teachers of others in their community. Frequently
too they develop a deep sense of their mission as inter¬
preters of the new way of life. We have been so im¬
pressed by the potential importance of this group that
our Social Sciences Department is conducting a series of
studies of actual and potential leaders in various regions
of Africa, and we are now extending the investigation to
include the role of feminine leaders. It is quite possible
that women in such a position may prepare the way more
easily than men for some kinds of technological change.
We have all been reminded on many occasions of the
difficulties and dangers inherent in the direct transplan¬
tation of an educational system developed in one area
into another quite different cultural and economic
context. Certainly the schools must serve the needs of
the community, and be adapted to those needs. For this
reason we have welcomed and co-operated in the creation
in Brazil of a National Centre for Educational Research,
which is directed towards this very end of reorganizing
the Brazilian education system in order to make it fit
the present conditions of Brazilian life, with all its local
and regional variations.
At the same time we venture to suggest that the schools
Their very existence may, however, lead the way to
further progress and may help to bring on the next stage
of technological change. There is a dilemma here, since
no one wishes to see training go to waste, but it still seems
to me that the schools have the special function of point¬
ing the way to further progress.
It is difficult to over-emphasize the importance of the
educational process in technological change, when we re¬
member that resources in raw materials go to waste if
there are no adequate resources in trained personnel.
Economists have recognized the fact that in assessing the
real wealth of a community the range and extent of the
skills possessed by its men and women are of the greatest
importance. Whatever we can do to add to those skills
represents a contribution of present or potential wealth.
We in Unesco have recognized this fact by devoting a
considerable proportion aï our fellowships, in the Ex¬
change of Persons programme, to precisely this purpose of
adding to the skills of nationals from relatively unin¬
dustrialized countries.
All old ways 'go west'
It is sometimes argued that technological change de¬
stroys indigenous cultures, that it replaces many diffe-
rent traditional ways of life by one way the Western
way, that it will mean eventually the loss of all the rich¬
ness and variety which at present characterize the civili¬
zation or civilizations of the world. Since we in unesco, as
well as in the United Nations family generally, profess
respect for the values of all cultures, do we not run the risk
of endangering precisely those values by substituting for
them those which inevitably accompany technological
change? Should we not devote our skills to the preserva¬
tion of those cultures, rather than contributing, whether
we wish it or not, to their eventual disappearance ?
To these difficult questions I would propose the follow¬
ing answers. Of course we are interested in the preserva¬
tion of the cultural contributions of all peoples of the
world. Within unesco we are working toward this end.
We are doing what we can to make the world aware
of the artistic and philosophical achievements of cultures
with which most of us are not sufficiently familiar. We
Q^SEs
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
TECHNICAL
ASSISTANCE
(Continued)
are committed to the belief in
the value of cultural diversity.
At the same time we must face
the fact that in many parts of
the world technological change
is necessary for the improvement
of living conditions, if not for
survival: We must also face the fact that with the
increase of contact and communication among the peoples
of the world, technological change is inevitable. iWe do
not have the possibility of keeping each tribal culture fully
intact on a kind of reservation. We have rather the alter¬
native between technological change which is haphazard
and mechanical, and one which is based on a knowledge of
pre-existing cultural values, and on a genuine desire to
preserve them, as far as possible, in the new framework.
This is not an impossible goal, but it is by no means
easily achieved. A change in one aspect of the culture
may have repercussions on other aspects : there are
"chain effects" which have consequences far beyond those
originally envisaged.
One of our publications, prepared by the World Federa¬
tion for Mental Health under the editorship of Margaret
Mead, deals precisely with this question of "Cultural
Patterns and Technical Change," and shows how under
certain conditions technological change may be intro¬
duced in a manner to fit the prevailing culture. Professor
Raymond Firth in his book on "Social Changes in the
Western Pacific" shows the possibility of maintaining
community solidarity in spite of the rapid economic chan¬
ges which have occurred. In any case there is no reason
to assume that the arts must necessarily fly
out of the window as soon as technological
change darkens the door. There are still
some people who write poetry in London or
New York, or paint their pictures in Paris
or Sao Paulo or Sydney and Melbourne!
The second source of concern over techno¬
logical change is closely related to the first.
The words "social implications" have some¬
times been used as if they necessarily
referred to harmful consequences increased
disorganization, disruption of the normal
lines of authority, maladjustment, delin¬
quency and crime, mental disorder, etc.
Since industrialization has usually meant
also urbanization, there has been some tendency to blame
these unhappy phenomena on the rapid growth of new
cities, which draw off the surrounding rural populations
into a situation where the old regulations no longer apply.
Without the restraint of the mores and public opinion,
the individual may find himself adrift without proper
bearings, and antisocial behaviour may be a result.
This may happen ; in fact, it has happened in many
places. It should be pointed out, however, that in some
cases the frequency of such behaviour has beenexaggerat-
ed. A recent report by the International Research Office
on the Social Implications of Technological Change in¬
dicates that the statistics for delinquency and crime
sometimes give a wrong impression because the alleged
misdemeanours may be explained by the temporary con¬
flict between two sets of standards of behaviour, and not
represent acts of far-reaching importance or consequence.
More significant from our present standpoint is the fact
that urbanization, even rapid urbanization, is not ne¬
cessarily accompanied by such
phenomena. There are new
African cities which show a great
deal of crime and delinquency,
and others that show very little.
It would be most helpful if we
could have detailed studies of
such contrasts which would bring
into relief the differentiating
conditions in the two situations,
and enable us to discover why
things went wrong in one case
and not in the other. We should
look at both the sucessful and
unsuccessful cases of adjustment
to technological change in order
to get a balanced picture.
A few years ago, Mr. Nehru,
speaking at a conference on
community projects, pointed out
that advice given from outside,
even good advice, was not always
welcome.
"We have got into the habit"
he said, "of doling out good advice to everybody, to the
country, to our people... Obviously it is necessary to plan,
to direct, to organize and to co-ordinate, but it is even
more necessary to create conditions where spontaneous
growth from below is possible and can take place."
The United Nations and the Specialized Agencies had a
somewhat similar point in mind when they set up a very
broad programme of community development with all its
ramifications. It is when local communities themselves
become identified with new techniques, aid in their de¬
velopment and application, take responsibility for their
success, that the changes introduced have the best chance
of being fully adapted to the local situation. Indeed, one
might almost go so far as to say that the main criterion
for the success of any project is the degree of involvement
at the grass roots level ; the capacity of the people to
carry it forward after outside assistance has ended. .
In connexion with Western technology we have been
hearing a great deal lately about "human relations in in¬
dustry," which represents an attempt to take
into account the personal or social relation¬
ships within a factory or other industrial
enterprise in order to improve its function¬
ing. One of the aspects of this approach
which seems to me to be most pertinent to
our present discussion is the demonstration
that it is much easier to have a new tech¬
nique adopted and successfully applied if the
workers themselves have a voice in the
decision, if they are consulted in advance
instead of being presented with a fait accom¬
pli. It then becomes their decision, and
they react accordingly.
There is always danger in generalizing
from one cultural situation to another, but I venture to
suggest that here we are on relatively safe ground. To
the extent that a society adopts a new technique after
consultation, it will be more likely, other things being
equal, to see it through. When, as so often happens in
the contacts between relatively untrained local workers
and visiting experts, feelings of inferiority are developed
by the discrepancy in skills, the workers may gain self-
respect and dignity if the "human relations" aspects of
their jobs are given due consideration.
Human relations become complicated, in many situa¬
tions, by race relations. Here the position of unesco
and of the other United Nations agencies is clear and
unequivocal ; there is no place in our Organizations for
prejudice or discrimination.
It is, however, possible that we have not always been
successful in choosing for technical assistance missions
or for other related assignments individuals who have
been entirely free from such attitudes. It seems to me
most important that the people we send to represent us
in other cultures should have a wholesome respect for
ways of life different from their own, should be able to
forget distinctions of race, and to contribute by their own
example to a better understanding between the peoples
brought into intimate contact through the process of
industrialization.
This article is taken from an address given by Dr. Luther
Evans to the Australian Library Association at Brisbane, on
August 22, 1955.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1956
Underground
workers round
the clock
1,750,000
ploughmen
per acre
by David Gunston
Turned up by your fork in the garden, or lying
shrivelled and stranded on a pathway or
road, a worm looks a helpless, insignificant
enough creature. The everyday epithet "worm"
seems well-chosen. Yet without him and his
kin, human civilization would not only be the
poorer: it would be impossible, at least as we
know it today.
Earthworms are nature's own cultivators of
the soil. Nothing lush can grow on rock or
chalk or gravel. There must be a 'fertile topsoil
in which to raise the world's crops. The solu¬
tion to the grave and little-realized world prob¬
lem of declining soil fertility may yet prove to
lie with that widely-despised creature, the
earthworm.
By ceasless boring and tunnelling earthworms
make and renew the vital layer of topsoil. They
keep it friable, transform animal and vegetable
waste, particularly dead leaves and plants, into
rich humus. They turn natural minerals in the
soil into soluble and easily assimilable plant food.
They break up and aerate the earth, allowing
rain to drain through. They bury stones and
rubbish, scavenging and cleansing. In short,
they are the first husbandmen, and still the most
important. What is more, they live extraordi¬
narily long lives for such lowly animals up to
15 years if unmolested and they never cease
working, night or day.
In an age that is speedily and terrifyingly
losing its natural soil fertility through over¬
cropping, mis-management and erosion, it is
high time to take stock of the worm's true
value. It can be said with some truth that after
centuries of mild interest and little knowledge,
the earthworm is at last coming to be 'fully
recognized as an important factor in human
affairs. Ever since Aristotle there has
been a good deal of legend about (Cont'd
worms, but ' little real information, on next
Naturalists and scientists of all ages page)
IS
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
THE EARTHWORM
(Continued)
^^A**'
Research work can of course only be
based upon a prolonged and detailed
study of the worms themselves.
What sort of a creature is an
earthworm ? Pick up a garden worm
and examine it closely, and you
will see that it consists of a closely-
linked series of rings. There may
be anything from 100 to 400 of these,
according to the size and kind ai the
worm, and they form a rr^uscular
chain from the elongated head
(without eyes, nose or ears), to the
tapering tail. For its size, one of
the strongest creatures on earth, the
worm is tough, flexible, wiry and
perfectly streamlined for its burrow¬
ing existence underground. A spe¬
cimen weighing, less than one-
thirtieth of an ounce can shift a
stone weighing two ounces, or over
sixty times its own weight.
By its very nature, a worm is
little more than a digestive organism,
perpetually feeding. Everything in
a worm's design is subserviated to
the endless processes of the alimen¬
tary canal which runs the length o'f
its elastic body. Blind and impe¬
tuous, questing and tireless, the
have been curious about them, but
few recognized their rightful place in
the scheme of things.
Gilbert White, of Selborne, the
English naturalist, had more than an
inkling of the true status of the little
wriggling creatures he watched in his
eighteenth-century Hampshire gar¬
den, yet his plea for what he called
"a good monograph of worms" was
not to be answered 'for something
like a hundred years, until Charles
Darwin published his great book,
"The Formation of Vegetable Mould
Through the Action of Earthworms,
with Observations on Their Habits",
at the end of his life, in 1881.
Darwin had studied earthworms all
his life, beginning in his college days,
45 years before, and he placed on
record his conclusions about the
power for world good that lay in
its worm population. -"Vegetable
mould" was his name for fertile
humus in the layers of topsoil, and,
he stated: "Worms have played a
more important part in the history
of the world than most persons would
at first suppose." He found that
"all the vegetable mould over the
whole world has passed many times
through, and will again pass many
times through, the intestinal canals
of worms". So when Aristotle had
spoken of worms as "the intestines of
the earth", he had not been 'far
wrong.
Much of Darwin's book was found
to be . true and helpful, but he was
factually wrong on several matters,
notably the numbers of worms in the
soil. He estimated that arable land
carries an average of some 53,000 to
the acre, but recent research at the
Rothamstead Experimental Station in
England, have shown that even poor
soil may support 250,000 worms to the
acre, while rich fertile 'farmland may
have up to 1,750,000.
More important still, recent work
tends to accept the conclusion that
the only way to restore soil ferti¬
lity before it is too late is to em-
16
ploy earthworms. By harnessing
them, in fact, mankind may yet save
its future food supplies. It is impera¬
tive to restore immediate fertility
to the earth's soil for maximum food
production. Normally, earthworms
would do this anyway, but such is the
rate of cropping nowadays, that
they would require 500 to 1,000 years
the task. Under artificially
controlled conditions, provided* other
circumstances were favourable, a
vast regulated "task force" of spe¬
cially-bred earthworms might be able
to do the job within 5 or 10 years.
Methods of cross-breeding worms
have been devised to produce the
most suitable types for use in farm¬
ing, and various techniques for
raising large numbers of healthy,
active worms in a limited space
under cover have already been per¬
fected. The present trend, although
still in the experimental stage, is
towards the setting-up of "earth¬
worm 'farms", where vast stocks of
worms can be raised in beds of
humus. These are in commercial
production in U.S.A. and Canada,
whilst amateur enthusiasts in Britain
and other lands are breeding their
own stocks from specially selected
strains in gardens and holdings.
Greedy soil swallower
IN ,all cases, the emphasis is on
worm topsoil the predigested,
pulverised humus after it has
passed through an earthworm's di¬
gestive organs. Scientific analyses
have shown that this topsoil happens
to be the richest medium in the world
for growing things in. It normally
contains five times as much nitrate
nitrogen, eleven times as much
potash, seven times as much phos¬
phorus, three times as much magne¬
sium and about 40 per cent more
humus than is found in the first six
inches depth of ordinary soil. All
these plant foods are also in a "far
more readily assimilated form than
those found in average topsoil.
worm seeks and disposes of food
without pause. It is endowed with
sufficient instinctive intelligence to
enable it to exist, satisfactorily wher¬
ever it happens to find itself.
If you run a finger along a worm's
body from tail to head, it feels rough.
It is not the smooth creature you
might expect. This roughness is
caused by tiny clusters, of erectile
bristles set at intervals along its
length. With these, and a self-
secreted slimy lubricating mucus, the
worm is able to burrow through all
types o'f soil sandy, rocky, heavy or
waterlogged. Cut a hapless worm
in two with your spade, and the
head end will usually grow a new
tail and live, but never vice-versa.
From the creature's own point of
view its most important feature is
its oval mouth, which is protected
by a long, overhanging lip. As it
tunnels its way along, this helps to
push aside most of the soil, while
the rest is swallowed greedily,
passing straight into a bird-like crop
in the neck, where minute 'fragments
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1956
of grit grind everything down into a
fine, moist paste. Leaves, grass, roots,
stems, rubbish all are reduced to a
smooth residue, which is then
swiftly digested in the threadlike
stomach, the worm extracting its own
nourishment from the bacteria in the
soil. Stones up to one-twentieth
of an inch across are swallowed and
incorporated in the gizzard, larger
ones are eaten around and thus
started on their slow sinking pro¬
cess which is finally completed by the
depositing of layers of worms-casts
on the surface.
Bracing its body for the effort, and
anchoring itself by its tail under¬
ground, a worm can grasp and pull
down beneath the surface quite large,
fragments of rotting vegetation and
animal matter all the dead and
dying refuse that litters the earth.
Tougher -food is first coated with a
kind of saliva to aid the digestive
processes. In Britain it has been
estimated that three inches of com¬
pletely new topsoil from worm-
castings or excrement is deposited
every fifteen years or so, and the
same is probably true of most lands.
Where the native earthworm popula¬
tion can be artificially increased, of
course, the rate of this vital work
can be stepped up.
Although blind, worms are sensitive
to light, and 'feed mostly at night,
rising to the surface after dusk and
burying themselves again before day¬
break. There are in fact a number
of different species of worms, includ¬
ing the brandling, found in manure-
heaps and beloved oí anglers for bait,
and the four-foot monsters which
gurgle their way into the squelchy
forest mud of parts of Australia.
Worms are found all over the globe,
except where it is too hot and dry
for them to exist, as in parched
deserts, but even in hot lands they
teem by the rivers and lakes. As
these untold myriads never rest or
hibernate, but dig and tunnel maybe
for years, constantly yielding this
incredibly fertile layer of cast soil, it
is small wonder that the earth has
been rich for so long.
So the vision of the lowly earth¬
worm as the key to the world's
deepest problem that of unfailing
food suplies for an ever-increasing
population may not prove to be as
fantastic as it first sounds. Cer¬
tainly nature is co-operative in the
way that these creatures respond to
artificial rearing.
When two meet, they clasp toge¬
ther in a strange, slimy embrace,
overlapping one another to about
one-third of their lengths, heads
facing opposite ways, and locked
together for all the world like a
Turk's head knot. Thus, each ferti¬
lizes the other's eggs, and these are
then passed over the body in a tube
which is eventually cast off in the
form of a yellow, lemon-shaped
cocoon. Each cocoon may contain
up to 20-odd tiny eggs, which hatch
out into minute, white, thread-like
worms in about ten days. But if
these cocoons are dried out, or kept
in a refrigerator, they may be pre¬
served for as long as eighteen
months, and may thus be sent all
over the world. Once placed in the
right conditions for hatching, the
eggs then yield healthy young worms
after the usual incubation period.
As all worms are male and female
in one body, only a single cocoon-full
of eggs is needed to start up a colony.
Worm harnessing crusade
The leading figure in the Ameri¬
can worm-harnessing movement
is a bespectacled physiothera¬
pist, Dr. Thomas J. Barrett, who first
became interested in worms when in
France in 1918. Noticing an aged
French peasant carefully sweeping up
some loose soil by a damp well near
the Argonne Forest, quite oblivious of
nearby gunfire, he asked him why
this particular earth should be so
precious. "Le Bon Dieu knows how
to build good earth and He has given
the secret to the earthworms", the
old man replied. Barrett was much
impressed, and began a long study o'f
the subject which convinced him of
the potential value of these creatures.
Eighteen years later, his business
a failure, and his assets only $9, he
decided to stake his future on
earth-worms and to press for their
scientific culture. In a few years he
had turned a barren Californian hill¬
side into a lush paradise of a garden,
full of outsize vegetables, fruit,
flowers and shrubsall thanks to the
rich cast-soil in which he had grown
them. He figured that a horse could
do only a limited amount of
ploughing, and then only on suitable
terrain, yet a million worms roughly
equal a horse in weight, are in the
aggregate much stronger and more
enduring, need only waste matter
and the existing soil for 'food, yet
deposit 100 tons of topsoil to the acre
every year without fail. His faith
was justified, and he now breeds
worms for sale in a dozen countries,
and leads the campaign, supported
by a growing body o'f disciples, not
for more soil under cultivation, but
for more worm soil in existing arable
areas.
"'Crowded on the face of the earth
are over two thousand million peo¬
ple", says Barrett, "depending on the
topsoil for food. There are on the
earth approximately four thousand
million acres of cultivable land two
acres per person. We barely feed
ourselves and our topsoil is dwindling.
It is time we harnessed the earth¬
worm to rebuild it."
It would indeed be remarkable if
man finally recognized the worm's
good turn to humanity by working
with him, cultivating him instead of
continually impoverishing the soil,
and relying upon nature to do the
rest. Remarkable, but by now means
impossible.
xsrssn
/^¿'/yg'O «g 0"2> ¿3 lS"cl>o g'pga -^
"-»i
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1956
U.S.A., Nina Leen, Life.
' With all beings and all things
we shall be as relatives'
SIOUX INDIAN
0
n these and the following pages the
Unesco Courier presents a selection
of photographs from a remarkable exhi¬
bition which drew 300,000 visitors to the
New York Museum of Modern Art last
year. Created by Edward Steichen, Head
of the Museum's Department of Photo¬
graphy, "The Family of Man" Exhibition
is composed of 503 photographs selected
from a total of two million from 68
countries. It has begun a round-the-
world tour and is at present in the Paris
Musée d'Art Moderne. The message of
this "vast photographic symphony" has
been summed up by André Maurois in
these words: "We all knowor at least
we shouldthat between all men there
exists a great depth of similarity. This^
similarity ought to engender universal
kinship and help men toward an under¬
standing and love of one another, 'di.t
preachers of hatred are at work to make
us forget these similarities. Hencr> ;he
scorn, the resentments, the brutal revolts
and wars. That is why It is necessary,
even imperative that the unity of the
human family should be revealed to the
sceptics. That is why this group of pho¬
tographs Is both useful and moving and
not merely beautiful and interesting."
Sicily, Vito Fiorenza Japan, Carl Mydans, Life
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
THE FAMILY
OF MAN
(Continued)
THERE IS ONLY ON
AND HIS NAME IS
Thu first cry of a newborn baby in Chicago or
Zamboango, in Amsterdam or Rangoon, has
the same pitch and key, each saying, "I am!
I have come through ! I belong ! I am a member
of the Family."
Many the babies and grownups here from
photographs made in sixty-eight nations round
our planet Earth. You travel and see what
the camera saw. The wonder of human mind,
heart, wit and instinct, is here. You might
catch yourself saying, "I'm not a stranger
here."
People! flung wide and far, born into toil,
struggle, blood and dreams, among lovers,
eaters, drinkers, workers, loafers, fighters,
players, gamblers. Here are ironworkers,
bridgemen, musicians, sandhogs, miners, build¬
ers of huts and skyscrapers, jungle hunters,
landlords and the landless, the loved and the
unloved, the lonely and abandoned, the brutal
and the compassionate one big family hugging
close to the ball of Earth for its life and being.
Here or there you may witness a startling
harmony where you say, "This will be haunt¬
ing me a long time with a loveliness I hope to
understand better."
In a seething of saints and sinners, winners
or losers, in a womb of superstition, faith,
genius, crime, sacrifice, here is the People, the
one and only source of armies, navies, work-
gangs, the living flowing breath of the history
of nations, ever lighted by the reality or illu¬
sion of hope. Hope is a sustaining human
gift.
Everywhere is love and love-making, wed¬
dings and babies from generation to generation
keeping the Family of Man alive and continu¬
ing. Everywhere the sun, moon and stars,
the climates and weathers, have meanings for
people. Though meanings vary, we are alike
in all countries and tribes in trying to read what
sky, land and sea say to us. Alike and ever alike we
are on all continents in the need of love, food, cloth¬
ing, work, speech, worship, sleep, games, dancing,
fun. From tropics to arctics humanity lives with
these needs so alike, so inexorably alike.
Hands here, hands gnarled as thorntree roots and
others soft as faded rose leaves. Hands reaching,
praying and groping, hands holding tools, torches,
brooms, fishnets, hands doubled in fists of flaring
20
anger, hands moving in caress of beloved faces. The
hands and feet of children playing ring-around-a-
rosy countries and languages different but the little
ones alike in playing the same game.
'Flow, flow, flow, the current of life is
Fifth Avenue New York, Andreas Feininger, Life
Here are set forth babies arriving, suckling, grow¬
ing into youths restless and questioning. Then as
grownups they seek and hope. They mate, toil, fish,
quarrel, sing, fight, pray, on all parallels and meri¬
dians having likeness. The earliest man, ages ago,
had tools, weapons, cattle, as seen in his cave draw¬
ings. And like him the latest man of our day has his
tools, weapons, cattle. The earliest man struggled
through inexpressibly dark chaos of hunger, fear, vio¬
lence, sex. A long journey it has been from that
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1956
E MAN IN THE WORLD
£^ L L l^\ E N by Cari Sandbur9
early Family of Man to the one of today which has
become a still more prodigious spectacle.
If the human face is "the masterpiece of God" it is
here then in a thousand fateful registrations. Often
ever onward...' kobodaishi
U.S.A., Jerry Cooke, Life
..I am alone with the beating of my heart...'
lui CHI
the faces speak what words can never say. Some tell
of eternity and others only the latest tattlings. Child
faces of blossom smiles or mouths of hunger are
followed by homely faces of majesty carved and worn
by love, prayer and hope, along with others light and
carefree as thistledown in a late summer wind. Faces
having land and sea on them, faces honest as the
morning sun flooding a clean kitchen with light, faces
crooked and lost and wondering where to go this
afternoon or tomorrow morning. Faces in crowds,
laughing and windblown leaf faces, profiles in an
instant of agony, mouths in a dumbshow mockery
lacking speech, faces of music in gay song or a twist
of pain, a hate ready to kill, or calm and ready-for-
death faces. Some of them arc worth a long
look now and deep contemplation later. Faces
betokening a serene blue sky or faces dark with
storm winds and lashing night rain. And faces
beyond forgetting, written over with faiths in
men and dreams of man surpassing himself.
An alphabet here and a multiplication table of
living breathing human faces.
In the times to come as the past there will be
generations taking hold as though loneliness
and the genuis of struggle has always dwelt
in the hearts of pioneers. To the question,
"What will the story be of the Family of Man
across the near or far future?" some would
reply, "For the answers read if you can the
strange and baffling eyes of youth."
There is only one man in the world
and his name is All Men.
There is only one woman in the world
and her name is All Women.
There is only one child in the world
and the child's name is All Children.
A camera testament, a drama of the grand
canyon of humanity, an epic woven of fun,
mystery and holiness here is the Family of
Man !
Peru, Robert Frank
Carl Sandburg, famed American poet and winner of
the Pulitzer Prize for poetry in 1951, wrote the above
text as a prologue to "The Family of Man" exhibition.
Text copyright by the Museum of Modern Art, New York.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
THE FAMILY
OF MAN
(Continued)
She is a tree of
life to them... '
PROVERBS 3:18
U.S.A., Consuelo Kanaka
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1956
U.S.A., Elliott Erwin, Magnum
Arctic, Richard Harrington, Three Lions Austria, David Seymour, Magnum Unesco
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
THE FAMILY
OF MAN
(Continued)
The power of words
by Cyril Bibby
No one who has ever seen a white man's lip curl as
he spits out the word "nigger" or who has felt the
deep contempt in a Negro's voice as he refers to
"while trash", can have any doubt about the emotional
content of such terms. True, when the English child
learns the nursery rhyme about the "Ten Little Nigger
Boys" who sat down to dine, the word "nigger1" is used
in a warm, friendly way; but words have an emotive
power for the recipient as well as for the dispenser, and
many Negroes rise in resentment at what they imagine to
be racial prejudice. Similarly, although the word, "Ne¬
gress" may be used in its simple descriptive sense, with¬
out any offensive intent, it may nevertheless carry
objectionable connotations of the days when plantation
owners took female slaves as concubines.
To take another example, the words "Jew" and
"Jewess" are in essence simply classiflcatory terms, no
more objectionable than "author"
and "authoress"; yet, so sensitive to
possibilities of antisemitic prejudice
have some individuals become, they
will circumlocute about "a man (or
a woman) of the Hebrew faith" to
avoid the risk of giving offence.
Just as, in poetry, certain words
have not only a surface insignifi¬
cance, but also a rich emotional
content which gives them layer
upon layer of meaning, so many
words relating to race have complex
associations which introduce thick
incrustations of prejudice. And, if
the child is to learn to use his
native language really well, he must
become fully aware of this complex
quality of words.
Take (he adjectives "black",
"brown", "yellow", and "white".
Applied to paints or fabrics, they
are simple descriptive words im¬
plying nothing beyond the facts of
colour difference.
How should a teacher deal with race
relations in the classroom? How can
an atmosphere of freedom and tole¬
rance which will stop children from
developing racial prejudices be created?
Unesco recently asked sociologists and
educators from different countries to
discuss these problems and to suggest
ways of fostering education in race and
inter-group relations. To help teachers
and to enlist their aid in its campaign
against racial discrimination, Unesco is
to publish two handbooks giving facts
about race and suggesting ways these can
be introduced into history, geography,
biology, religion and other subjects. In
this article, Dr. Cyril Bibby of the Univer¬
sity of London Institute of Education,
author of one of the Unesco handbooks,
points out how, when they are used in a
certain way, words can breed misunder¬
standing and hostility in racial matters.
to be deep down in the semantic structure of the
language. This is why, by many people, a "pure" Negro
or a "pure" European or a '"pure" Indian are regarded
with equal respect, but a person of "mixed blood" is
viewed with something approaching loathing. For the
phrase "mixed blood" carries with it not only the emo¬
tive implications of "mixed" but also the extremely
powerful surcharging of the word "blood".
One speaks of one's child as being "of my own blood";
there is the common saying "blood is thicker than water";
the closest ties of comradeship are those between "blood
brothers'"; there are the metaphors of "blue blood",
"'plebeian blood" and "new blood"; an orator may arouse
high passion by talk of '"British blood" or "Russian blood"
or "American blood". Blood is the very life-stream and
its mythology is rich and varied. Similarly, the words
"half-caste" (with its implication on the one hand of
something less-than-complete and
on the other hand of something to
be ranked in a scale of social value)
and '"mulatto" (with its foreign-
sounding form, in its first syllabic
faintly reminiscent of the hybrid
progeny of the horse and ass, and
in its ending evoking memories of
the sinister stiletto) often carry con¬
notations far more complex than is
usually recognized.
While it is primarily for the bio¬
logy teacher to provide children
with the basic factual knowledge
about genes, it is essentially the task
of the teacher of language to
sharpen his pupils' awareness of
the ways in which words may carry
complex intimations of meaning.
But use them in the phrases
"black race", "brown race", '"yel¬
low race", and "white race" and
how subtly the adjectives imply grades of merit
and demerit ! Usually unrecognized on the conscious
level, but often a potent catalyst of emotion, "white" now
becomes set apart from the other three colour adjectives,
and carries with it an idea of basic cleanness which
"black*" and "brown" and "yellow" do not share. Then
there is white as the symbol of purity and virginity, and
there is white as "not-coloured" while black and brown
and yellow are "coloured". This last implication,
indeed, commonly becomes quite explicit, as when "co¬
loured" is used as a synonym or euphemism for "Negro".
This complex emotional content of the word "white"
would become apparent to children of European origin
if, for a period, they and their teacher deliberately used
the rather more appropriate adjective "pink" in class¬
room discussion of ethnic differences. The sense of
superiority which comes to many people when they think
of themselves as white rather than brown disappears
when they think of themselves as pink, and the thrill of
horror which is aroused in some by the idea of inter¬
marriage between black and white does not arise in the
same way at the thought of the mingling of black and
pink.
This word "mingling", too is richly emotive in the
context of race. "Mingling", or "mixture", is often
expressive of adulteration or impurity: there is the
dishonest dairyman mixing water with his milk, there is
the appalling consequence of sewage becoming mingled
with drinking water. Not in any conscious or verbalized
way do these ideas normally arise; they are more likely
To recognize the existence of ir¬
rational feelings is often the first
step to liberating oneself from them,
and the teacher can contribute a
good deal to the emotional eman¬
cipation of his pupils by helping
them to understand how it is that
certain words and phrases come to
arouse feelings of this kind.
It is, however, not only in the language or literature
lesson that opportunities arise to help children to cope
with the complex emotional content of words. The bio¬
logy lesson, for example, may present a suitable occasion
to isolate the proper meaning of "pure-bred", as a gene¬
tically descriptive term, from the implication of virtue and
superiority, which often attach to the term. In almost any
subject of the curriculum, the enormous emotive power of
the word "blood" may make itself felt, and care can be
taken that this power does not, as it may very easily do,
carry over into the children's attitudes to race relations.
So with the very word "race!" itself. Passing into
general usage in its present sense after Buffon gave it the
seal of his approval in 1749, the word had earlier been
used in the sense of "the human race", and in the sense of
the posterity of a person, as in the phrase "the race of
Abraham". And, subtly still today, the word carries with
it something of this complex connotation, so that on the
one hand the members of another "race" are not quite
human and on the other hand they are not quite of one's
own kith-and-kin. And, as a result, many a man who is
well aware of the scientific facts about race is nevertheless
unable to cast off completely his irrational feelings about
it. He is, indeed, in much the same position as was
Madame de Staël, who is reported to have said: "I do not
believe in ghosts, but I am afraid of them". We must
help children to pass beyond the stage of abandoning fal¬
lacious beliefs, and to progress into the stage of getting
rid also of irrational fears.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courter. February 1956
Java, Gotthard Schun
' The little ones leaped, and shouted, and laugh'd.
And all the hills echoed...'
WILLIAM BLAKE
U.S.A., Henri Leighton England, Bill Brandt
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Indonesia, Henri Cartier-Bresson, Magnum Italy, Dmitri Kessel, Life
' The land is a mother
that never dies.'
MAORI
France, Brassai, Rapho Guillumette
26
Japan, Shizuo Yamamoto
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1956
tf
.5 h ^^%A4
i à. ft-Jo****
m
Pakistan, Abdul Razaq Mehta
U.S.A., Wayne Miller, Life
China, Dmitri Kessel, Life
' If I did not work these worlds would perish...'
BHAGAVAD-GITA
U S.A., Arthur Lavine.
U.S.A., Rüssel Lee, Farm Security Adm.
' Bless thee in all the work of thy hand which
thou doest... deuteronomy 14 : 29
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
THE FAMILY
OF MAN
(Continued)
' Eat Bread and Salt and Speak the
Truth. '
RUSSIAN PROVERB
* Am
rit
tUM ? J
1 E*^
Yugoslavîa.Walter Sanders, Life
Eugene Harris, "Popular Photography"
Japan, Yoshisuke Terao
' Music and rhythm find
their way into the secret
places of the soul. '
PLATO
U.S.S.R., Robert Capa, Magnum, Ladies' Home Journal
Colombia, Kurt Severin, Black Star
Italy, John Bertolino
28
New Mexico, Ernst Haas, Magnum, Life
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1956
' ..Nothing is real to us but hunger. '
KAKUZO OKAKURA
Holland, Cas Oorthuys
U.S.A., Musya S. Sheeler
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1956
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
THE FAMILY OF MAN (Continued)
Canada, John Phillips, Life
" We two form a multitude. '
OVID.
American Indian, Alma Lavenson
32
China, Dmitri Kessel, Life
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. February 1956
' For Mercy has a human heart, Pity a human face... '
WILLIAM BLAKE
India, Margaret Bourke-White, Life U.S.A., W. Eugene Smith, Life
France, Henri Cartier-Bresson, Magnum
^L9 q vl
m
-^^hW.
-- ^1|
4
^^L
Korea, Margaret Bourke-White, Life
"To know that
what is impene¬
trable to us really
exists, manifesting
itself as the high¬
est wisdom and
the most radiant
beauty... '
ALBERT EINSTEIN
Czechoslovakia, Margaret Bourke-White, Life Sweden, Hans Hammarskjöld
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom
illURAL REVIVERS: Spe¬
cialists who -will help to improve
the health, housing, farming
and nutrition standards of
Korean villages are to be
trained in a national funda¬
mental education centre now
being set up at Suwon by the
U.N. Korean Reconstruction
Agency (UNKRA) in co-opera¬
tion with the Korean Govern¬
ment and with aid from unesco,
which is providing $80,000 for
staff services during the first
two years of operation. The
centre will offer a one-year
course for 48 men and 12 wom¬
en students. Its Director is
Howard Hayden, of the United
Kingdom and for the first two
years it will be staffed by six
international specialists and six
Korean experts who will even¬
tually take over the work. Stu¬
dents will be given practical
experience in local "laboratory"
villages, while learning latest
methods of literacy teaching
and how to develop rural crafts
and cottage industries to pro¬
vide new sources of income.
BRAZIL SCHOOL BOOM:
Enrolments in Brazil's se¬
condary schools have tripled
during the past 15 years, re¬
ports the International Bu¬
reau of Education. Secondary
schools increased from 821 to
2,485 and the total of boys
and girls attending them
rose from 170,057 in 1940 to
535,755 ¿n 1954. The average
increase of 26,000 pupils per
year was five times that of
the overall population in¬
crease during the same pe¬
riod.
w<O R L D CAMPAIGN
FOR MUSEUMS : The many
roles played by museums in the
life of the community -will be
highlighted this year in a world¬
wide campaign organized by
Member States of
unesco are preparing special
exhibits and features of particu¬
larly interesting collections will
be publicized by newpapers
and radio stations. The cam¬
paign aims to bring home the
public education role of mu¬
seums and also their contribu¬
tion to international under¬
standing, unesco is organizing
an international art competition
for children aged between six
and 16, who will be asked to de¬
pict their impressions after visit¬
ing a museum. A selection of
the best drawings -will be ex¬
hibited in Paris, in Switzerland
and in New Delhi at unesco's
Ninth General Conference later
in the year.
ORIGIN OF ALL LIFE :
An international group of
biologists met in Paris re¬
cently to plan greater deve¬
lopment of a vital field of
scientific research normal
and abnormal cell growth.
Problems of cell growth,
multiplication and differen¬
tiation are at the origin of
all forms of life. While the
research programme under
consideration is concerned
only with the fundamental
processes of the cell, the re¬
search may also shed light
on certain abnormalities
such as cancer. Specialists
from research institutes in
nine countries were invited
to the meeting, organized by
the Council for International
Organizations o f Medical
Sciences, at the request of
UNESCO.
M. OLYGLOT MEXI¬
CANS : A recent education
study in Mexico showed that
42 % of the country's secondary
school pupils can speak a for¬
eign language, usually English.
Knowledge of foreign languages
is also well-developed in the
secondary schools of two other
Latin American countries Cuba
and the Republic of Panama.
This interest in the study of
foreign languages is largely ex¬
plained by the development of
commercial, technical and tour¬
ist relations in this part of the
world.
JUST GIVE US THE
FACTS: Four ways for im¬
proving the quality and flow
of information about and
between different countries
were suggested in Paris
recently by directors of
national cultural relations
services meeting for the first
time. . They proposed the
production of special works
on different countries for
the use of secondary school
teachers, the distribution of
more documentary films and
audo-visual materials, spe¬
cial training for journalists
and the setting up of a per¬
manent exhibition of publi¬
cations on national cultures
at unesco's headquarters.
Si»EVENTH DAY MIS¬
SIONS: For the past eighteen
months, mission teams of Mexi¬
can university undergraduates
have been carrying out public
education campaigns in the
small towns and villages of the
states of Tlaxcala, Publa and
Mexico. The students chose
Sunday as their "mission" day
so as not to interfere with their
studies. Through their efforts
FREEING BOOKS, ART AND
MUSIC AT THE FRONTIERS
A proposal that tariffs on educational, scientific and cultural
materials should be reduced has been made by UNESCO to
the 35 countries which are parties to the General Agreement
on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) whose Tariff Negotiating Conference
opened in Geneva, Switzerland, on Januar/ 18, 1956. At the same
time as it made the proposal, UNESCO brought out a new revised
edition of "Trade Barriers to Knowledge" which gives a detailed
picture of the customs duties, import and export regulations, sales
taxes and exchange controls, covering books, newspapers, works
of art, music, radio and TV sets, scientific instruments and other
educational mjterials. The new manual covers 91 countries and
territories, as against 43 surveyed in the first edition, and deals
with a wider range of articles. It reveals a striking reduction in
customs duties, but also shows to what extent the flow of knowledge
is still limited by trade barriers. Many concessions gained result
directly from the application of the UNESCO Agreement on the
Importation of Educational, Scientific and Cultural Materials which
is now operated by 21 countries. The latest country to announce
ratification of this agreement is Greece.
five libraries have been opened,
hygiene committees formed and
about 150 educational films
have been screened. Much of
their educational work is car¬
ried out with the help of plays,
dances and music.
STUDY CAMP ON
WHEELS : Boys from a
Stockholm secondary school
went on an unusual study
tour of southern Sweden last
year in a special train com¬
plete with bedrooms, study
rooms and a van for storing
bicycles used in "off the
train" operations. At select¬
ed spots they left the train
to explore the region, visit¬
ing museums and historic
monuments and making no¬
tes on plants and wild ani¬
mals they saw in the coun¬
tryside. They spent each
afternoon in their mobile
classrooms writing up ac¬
counts of their visits.
*_ALL VIENNA B.21.2.63 :
A telephone call to Vienna B.21.
2.63 now solves any foreign vi¬
sitor's problems on -what places
to visit in the Austrian capital.
At the other end of the line is
the "University Service of
Tourist Guides" which promptly
sends off one of its 150 student
guides who are selected for their
knowledge of languages, history
and art. Young guides must
possess a wealth of general
knowledge about their city be¬
fore they are accepted.
IS THERE A DOCTOR?:
There are now 1,200,000
physicians practicing in the
world, and on an average,
55,000 new doctors graduate
annually from 595 medical
schools operating in 85 coun¬
tries according to figures re¬
cently published by the
World Health Organization.
It seems as though there are
plenty of doctors in the
world until the total is com¬
pared with the world popul¬
ation of 2,500 million. While
in 14 countries one doctor
may serve a thousand or few¬
er people, in 22 others there
is only one doctor for 20,000
or more inhabitants. More¬
over, many are engaged in
teaching, research, adminis¬
tration and other duties.
D AYS TO REMEMBER:
School children in Utrecht, Hol¬
land, chose two important anni¬
versaries^ U.N. Day and Human
Rights Day for opening and
closing their recent unesco gift
coupon campaign to help the
educational institute of the Sri
Ramakrishna social service mis¬
sion at Vidialaya, Madras, In¬
dia. The children began their
campaign by selling gift cou¬
pons at a unesco stall in their
city's Central Station Square,
on U.N. Day (October 24). By
the time they closed it at a
gala evening to celebrate Human
Rights Day, in Utrecht's Rem¬
brandt Theatre on December 10,
they had sold 13,200 gift cou¬
pons, thus raising nearly $1,000
for the Indian mission.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
dyAbroad
I Etudes
à l'étranger
Estudios en el
extranjero
Unesco
STUDY ABROAD
International Handbook of Fellowships, Scholarships and Educational
Exchange.
Volume VII of this annual Unesco guide, now available, contains
information on over 50,000 awards offered in 1955-56 by the United
Nations and its Specialized Agencies, other international organizations
governments, universities, cultural and professional associations in
70 countries and a number of non-selfgoverning territories. It also
indicates the probable availability of awards in 1956-57. It gives all
the necessary details: where to apply, who is eligible, field of study,
length of courses, amount of award, etc.
"Study Abroad" should be in all libraries, information centres, offices
of cultural attachés and of foreign student advisers, as well as in language
departments of universities. It can be obtained from the Unesco
national distributors listed below. Price:S2; 10/6; 500 fr.
Coming in March :
WHAT'S WRONG WITH
OUR TEXT-BOOKS?
Distortion of history
in school books
Don't miss this issue. Subscribe today
to the UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rate.': 400 French francs,-
8/- or S 2.00
NATIONAL DISTRIBUTORS
Unesco's National distributors from
whom the English, French and Spanish
editions of the UNESCO COURIER
can be obtained are listed below.
AUSTRIA. Wilhelm Frick Verlag, 27
Graben, Vienna I.
BELGIUM. Librairie Encyclopédique,
7, rue de Luxembourg, Brussels IV.
N.V.Standaard-Bockhandel, Belgiëlei, 15 1,
Antwerp.
Louis de Laanoy, Editeur-Libraire, I 5, rue
du Tilleul, Genval (Brabant). (UNESCO
COURIER only.)
CANADA. University of Toronto Press,
Toronto 5.
Periodica Inc., 5090, Avenue Papîneau,-
Montreal 3 4.
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd.. Lake House, P.O. Box
244, Colombo I.
CYPRUS. M.E. Constantinides, P.O.
Box 473, Nicosia.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6, Nörregade, Copenhagen K.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
FRANCE. Unesco Bookshop, 19, Ave¬
nue Kléber, Paris, 16*. CCP. Paris
12598-48.
Sales & Distribution Division, 19, Ave¬
nue Kléber, Paris, 16*.
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28.
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I.
17, Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13.
3 6a, Mount Road, Madras 2.
Sub-Depots :
Oxford Book & Stationery Co., Scindia
House, New Delhi.
Rajkamal Publications Ltd., Himalaya
House, Hornby Road, Bombay I.
INDONESIA. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Jakarta:
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
ISRAEL. Blumstetn's Bookstores Ltd.,
35, Allenby Road, P.O. Box 4101, Tel-
Aviv.
ITALY. Libreria Commissionaria San-
soni. Via Gino Capponi 26, Casella Pos¬
tale 552, Florence.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 99,
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6, Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND SIN¬
GAPORE. Peter Chong & Co., Post
Office Box 135, Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienia's Library, 26, Kings-
way, Valletta.
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Ni-
jhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 1 00, Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church.
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos.
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass 7, Oslo.
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60, The Mall.
Lahore.
Ferozsons : Bunder Road, Karachi.
Ferozsons : 35, The Mall, Peshawar.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo, P.O. Box
620. Manila.
SWEDEN. A/B C.E. Fritzes, Kungl.
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgaten 2, Stockholm
16.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag. 5.
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40, rue du Marché, Geneva.
TANGIER. Paul Fekete, 2, rue Cook,
Tangier.
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
UNION OF BURMA. Burma Educa¬
tional Bookshop, 551-3, Merchant Street,
P.O. Box 222, Rangoon.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Street. P.O. Box 724, Pretoria.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I.
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, National Agency for Internatio¬
nal Publications, 500, Fifth Avenue, New
York 36, N.Y.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjîga,
Terazije 27' I I, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
ner
UNESCO photo.
FIPTIflW TflP^v DesP'te sti" competition from radio, the cinema and TV, people are reading more books
lib I I Uli I UlO than ever before. Recent figures collected by Unesco show that fiction is at the top of
reading lists in almost all countries. In England it represents 60 per cent of total reading, in
RFAniNP II KTÇ the US- 50 per cent' in Thailand 40, the Philippines 40 and India 60 per cent. Photos show
rVLMUinu LIO 10 young and old readers crowding Delhi Public Library in India. (For story see page 4)
]]>
</page>
</document>
