<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="068421eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A \
^^^^^^^^^^lur _^^^Ê^^^^^^^^^K^
1^^ ^^IB9^' .^^^^^1
"'" ^ Wt.1 ' "i- ,"
mmm
A time to live . . .
43 Luxembourg
Boundless visions
On the occasion of a Unesco-sponsored
meeting of experts in the field of still photo¬
graphy, a photo exhibition entitled "Visions
sans Frontières" was held in the city of
Luxembourg from 11 December 1985 to 6
January 1986. Organized by the city author¬
ities in collaboration with the Luxembourg
National Commission for Unesco, "Vision
sans Frontières" (an international association
of professionals in the field of photography)
and RTL Productions, the exhibition pre¬
sented the work of several photographers
including Luxembourg-born Edward
Steichen (1879-1973). Among the works
shown were a number of photos by
Dominique Roger, including this one of a
child learning to sketch during an exhibition
on Unesco's work held at the Palace of
Nationalities in Beijing in 1984.
Photo Unesco-Dominique Roger
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
TheCourier
A winslow open on the world
Editorial
AT the end of the nineteenth century the ruins of a vast
city, "apparently watched over by a giant stone
tortoise", were discovered in Central Asia. They
were the vestiges of Karakorum, capital of the Mongol
Empire founded in the thirteenth century by Genghis Khan
and the jewel of the rich artistic and cultural heritage of the
Mongolia of the Khans, a region whose influence was to
dominate the history of Central Asia and reach as far as Asia
Minor and Eastern Europe.
This issue of the Unesco Courier presents a glimpse of the
artistic achievements of this ancient Mongol civilization, as
well as a variety of other themes largely related to Unesco
activities. Also under the heading "art" are articles on the
magnificent Picasso Museum in Paris, opened last year, and
on the great Chilean painter Roberto Malta, inspired by a
recent retrospective exhibition of his worlc.
The "powers of language" , a subject which falls within the
scope of the social and human sciences, are explored in a
thought-provoking article by a brilliant young French ling¬
uist, Claude Hagège, whose compatriot Elisabeth Badinter
looks at the ways in which relations between the sexes are
changing in the Western world today.
Two highly topical ventures in the fields of international
scientific co-operation and communication between peo¬
ples Halley's comet and the Channel Tunnel also receive
coverage in an issue which is completed by two features of
broadly cultural interest: the curious history of the giraffe
offered to the King of France by the pasha of Egypt in 1825
and the eventful biography of that enigmatic, evergreen
figure from Latin America, the tango. Also in this issue, our
usual 1986 feature devoted to the International Year of
Peace.
Front cover: detail of a gilded bronze statue of the Buddha Vairocana
(72 cm high, 46 cm wide) by the Mongolian sculptor Zanabazar (17th
century). The symbolic hand gesture or mudra of this Tantric Buddha
who "uproots stupidity and ignorance" the upraised index finger of
the left hand is particularly remarkable. The statue is preserved in the
Museum of Plastic Arts at Ulaanbaatar, capital of the Mongolian
People's Republic.
Photo from Zanabazar^ Eminent Mongol Sculptor, State Publisliing House, Ulaanbaatar, 1982
Back cover: poster by the French artist Alain Le Yaouanc. Copies were
sold in November 1985 for the benefit of Unesco's World Heritage
Fund.
Photo © Unesco
Editor-in-chief : Edouard Glissant
March 1986
39th year
SCIENCE
4 Rendezvous with Halley's comet
A major international venture to study a visitor from space
by Howard Brabyn
CULTURE AND COMMUNICATION
7 Home by a neck
A giraffe's epic journey from Cairo to Paris
by Georges Poisson
10 Tango time
The Latin American song and dance
that swept the world onto its feet
by Luis Bocaz
12 The Channel Tunnel
by John Ardagh
SOCIAL SCIENCES
14 His n' Hers
The changing relationship between the sexes
in the Western world
by Elisabeth Badinter
1 8 The powers of language
by Claude Hagège
ART
26 The Picasso Museum in Paris
by Dominique Bozo
28 Matta
A new way of looking at the world
by Jean-Jacques Lebel
30 Treasures of Mongolia
by Namsraïn Ser-Odjav
38 1986: Year of Peace/ 3
2 A time to live...
LUXEMBOURG: Boundless visions
Published monthly in 32 languages
by Unesco
The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
English
Ff«nch
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Malaysian
Korean
Swahili
Croato-Serb
Macedonian
Serbo-Croat
Slovene
Chinese
Bulgarian
Greek
Sinha la
Finnish
Swedish
Basque
Thai
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English. French,
Spanish and Korean
ISSN(M4t-5?78
N" 3 - 1986 CPD 86 - 1 - 432A
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Above, computerized photograph re¬
ceived from the European Space Agency's
spacecraft Giotto when It ertcountered
Helley's comet early In the morning of 14
Uarch 1986. Picture was sent from about
1,500 km from the nucleus of the comet.
n
Rendezvous with Halley's comet
A major international venture
to study a visitor from space by Howard Brabyn
LIKE courtiers dancing a stately quad¬
rille, eight instrument-packed space
probes (one launched by the Euro¬
pean Space Agency, two by the USSR, two
by Japan, and three by the USA) are weav¬
ing intricate patterns in space in the biggest
international astronomic co-operative ven¬
ture ever mounted the investigation of
Halley's comet.
Two space shuttle missions are also being
in part devoted to observation of the comet,
the trajectory of which will be continuously
monitored by the world's most powerful
land-based telescopes. Altogether some
900 professional astronomers from forty-
seven countries are taking part in the
investigation.
Why all this interest in what veteran US
astronomer Fred Whipple has described as
"a large, dirty snowball"?
The answer is that astronomers believe
that comets consist of the remnants of the
building blocks left over from the birth of
the solar system some 4,500 million years
ago. The history of the solar system is re¬
corded, so it is thought, within their frozen
hearts.
Today, for the first time ever, thanks to
the genius of two seventeenth-century En¬
glish scientists, Isaac Newton and Edmond
Halley, and the achievements of modern
space technology, we have in our hands an
entrance ticket to one of these refrigerated,
flying museums. For Halley's comet is the
only vigorously active comet whose orbit
brings it relatively close to the earth (this
time round, its thirtieth recorded appar¬
ition, it is coming to within 62 million
kilometres of our planet) and has been de¬
termined precisely enough to allow of de¬
tailed scientiñc planning for investigation
well in advance; and for the very first time
space technology is sufficiently advanced to
enable us to go out and meet a comet
beyond the blanket of the earth's atmos¬
phere instead of waiting for it to come to us,
to penetrate its coma (the fuzzy gaseous
cloud, up to 100,000 kilometres across, that
shields the nucleus from our sight), to have
a close up view of its nucleus and to analyse
the components of its tail, in short, to
understand the elements from which our
solar system was constructed.
In 1950, the Dutch astronomer Jan Hen¬
drik Oort postulated that comets originate
from a vast cloud of hundreds of millions of
small bodies (now known as the Oort
Cloud) that orbits the solar system at a
distance of one light-year. The nucleus, or
core, of a comet is thought to consist of
about 25 per cent dust and lumps of rock or
metallic matter and 75 per cent of ice, in
which are mixed compounds containing
ammonia, methane and carbon dioxide
radicals. The 700 or so comets that have
been scientifically recorded so far have had
nuclei ranging in size from 0.5 to 70
kilometres in diameter.
From time to time a passing star sends a
gravitational ripple through the Oort Cloud
sending a flurry of these "dirty snowballs"
hurtling off into space. Some of them, the
"short-period" comets, like Halley's comet,
are projected towards the solar system and,
influenced by its gravitational pull, become
members of the inner solar system, com¬
pleting their orbits around the sun in less
than 200 years. The "long-period" comets
can take millions of years to complete their
orbital cycles. An average of five new com¬
ets are discovered every year.
The outer surface of a comet nucleus is
thought to consist mainly of dust. As a
comet approaches to within three astrono¬
mical units of the sun (one astronomical
unit equals the distance between the earth
and the sun, roughly 150 million
kilometres) this outer crust heats up and the
sub-surface ice begins to sublimate (a pro¬
cess by which a solid is converted directly
into vapour without going through the liq¬
uid stage). The resulting gas streams out
from the comet carrying dust particles with
it to form the coma.
As it gets closer to the sun a comet de¬
velops two tails, a yellowish curved tail K
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The EngHsh Astronom» Royal Edmond
tWIey (1656-1742). He calculated the
orltlta of many comets and correctly pre¬
dicted the return of Ote comet of 1682
Halley's comet wMch this year Is again
^tproachlng relatively e/ose to the earOi
(tor the 30th recorded tíme).
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
^ composed of dust particles released during
the process of sublimation, and a blueish
stream of gas called the plasma tail which is
formed when the gases released from the
comet's nucleus become charged by solar
radiation.
In a few months' time, when all the data
have been gathered in, we shall have made a
tremendous leap forward in our knowledge
of the nature of comets and of the origins of
the solar system. We should not, however,
forget that this will be due not only to the
brilliance of modern astronomers but also
to a quite unprecedented effort of interna¬
tional co-operation.
Launched on 15 December 1984, the
Soviet space probe Vega 1 flew through
Halley's coma on 6 March 1986, at a dis¬
tance of about 9,600 kilometres from the
nucleus, and photographed and analysed
the gases around it. Sister satellite Vega 2
encountered Halley's comet on 9 March
1986 and analysed its coma.
The Japanese probe Sakigake (pioneer),
launched on 7 January 1985, rendezvoused
with Halley's comet on 9 March 1986 and
measured the speed and temperature of the
solar wind blowing against the comet , whilst
on 8 March 1986 its companion satellite
Suisei (comet) flew past Halley's comet at a
distance of 144,000 kilometres and studied
the enormous cloud of hydrogen gas sur¬
rounding the comet.
Playing supporting roles are the veteran
US space probes Pioneer 12, Solar Max and
ICE (International Cometary Explorer).
Pioneer 12 is turning its attention away from
its long-term task of observing the effects of
the solar wind on planet Venus to focus its
spectrometer on Halley's comet during and
after the perihelion (the period of the com¬
et's closest approach to the sun). At the
Schematic drawing above shows
trajectories of the European Space Agen¬
cy's (ESA) spacecraft Giotto (see caption
page 18) and one of two Soviet Vega
spacecraft which flew through Halley's
comet in March 1986. To enable Giotto to
pass near the comet's nucleus, which Is
disguised by coma dust and gas, the
Soviet astronomers agreed to provide
ESA with information derived from camer¬
as on board the Vega probes, the first to fly
through the comet. The US National Aero¬
nautics and Space Administration (NASA)
also supported this three-agency "Pathfin¬
der Concept" to reduce Giotto targeting
uncertainty.
same time Solar Max is studying the comet's
dust and plasma tails for comparison with
observations made by ICE last September
on the nature of the tail of comet Giacobini-
Zinner.
Last in the field is the European Space
Agency's satellite Giotto. Named after the
famous fourteenth-century Florentine pain¬
ter Giotto di Bondone, who included Hal¬
ley's comet in his Paduan fresco The Adora¬
tion of the Magi (see colour page 19) after
witnessing its apparition in 1301, space
probe Giotto was launched on 2 July 1985.
Basing its trajectory on data supplied by the
two Soviet Vega probes, Giotto's mission
was to pass near the comet's nucleus, ex¬
amining the material streaming from it and
transmitting photographs to earth every
four seconds.
This might well have been a suicide mis¬
sion. The slightest error in calculation of its
trajectory could have sent Giotto crashing
into the surface of the comet. As a precau¬
tion against the particles which surround
the comet, some of them large enough to
have inflicted fatal damage, the satellite was
fitted with an outer aluminium skin and an
inner casing made of Kelvar, the material
from which bullet-proof vests are made. As
it happened, the spacecraft functioned per¬
fectly until 2 seconds before the scheduled
time of closest approach when the telemetry
signal was lost owing to dust impacts on the
spacecraft. Just over half an hour later,
however, the signal was recovered at
ground stations in Australia, and data from
all experiments was again being received.
The results will take months to analyse
fully but first impressions are that they are
spectacular. The Halley Multicolour
Camera on board Giotto, appears to have
determined the size of the nucleus as appro¬
ximately fifteen by eight kilometres, and
the spacecraft has contributed a mass of
other information to the International Hal¬
ley Watch, perhaps the most complex inter¬
national astronomical project ever under¬
taken. And as scientists sit down to assess
the information as it comes flooding in from
the space Armada, they will surely sense
the presence of two great figures from the
past peering eagerly over their shoulders
Isaac Newton, the man who first prop¬
ounded a workable theory of the orbits of
comets, and Edmond Halley who applied
this theory to the comet named after him,
which he had seen in 1682 and which he
accurately predicted would return at regu¬
lar seventy-six-year intervals, thus blazing
the trail for the amazing adventure we are
living through today.
HOWARD BRABYN is a Paris-based British
writer andjournalist with a special interest in the
popularization ofscience. He was formerly editor
in charge of the English-language edition of the
Unesco Courier.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
IT was the year 1825, ten years after the
fall of Napoleon and the restoration of
the monarchy in France, and all Cairo
was buzzing with excitement. Muker Bey, a
Sudanese nobleman, had sent two giraffes
as a gift to the viceroy of Egypt, Muham¬
mad AH Pasha.
No one was more excited than the French
Consul-General in Cairo, an engaging if
somewhat eccentric Piedmontese called
Bernardino Drovetti. Drovetti was a great
connoisseur of Egyptian antiquities and his
collections were later to form the nucleus of
the Egyptian departments of the museums
of Berlin, Turin and the Louvre.
Relations between France and Egypt at
that time were stormy. Aroused by the
writings of Victor Hugo and the paintings of
Delacroix, the youth of France was fired
with enthusiasm for Greek independence.
In 1822, however, Egyptian troops had
assisted their Turkish allies in the massacre
of Greek revolutionaries on the island of
Chios.
Considering it to be the primary duty of
any true diplomat to do all in his power to
reduce tension between countries, Drovetti
saw in the arrival of two giraffes in Cairo an
opportunity which he was quick to seize.
Remembering that it was an ancient tradi¬
tion among Egyptian sovereigns to present
one of these fabulous beasts to other
monarchs whom they wished to honour,
Drovetti requested that one of the two new¬
comers from Sudan be offered to the king of
France, Charles X. An exceptional gift it
would indeed be, since no giraffe had ever
before been seen in France.
Muhammad AH Pasha readily gave his
consent, but, alerted by the mysterious
bush telegraph that operates within the dip¬
lomatic corps, the British consul, almost
simultaneously, put forward a similar re¬
quest on behalf of his own royal master. His
reasons for doing so were similar the de¬
plorable state of relations between Britain
and Egypt.
Appreciating the advantages to be gained
from this double proposition, the viceroy
decreed in a Solomon-like judgement that
one giraffe should go to each country, the
choice between the two beasts to be made
by the two consuls drawing lots.
A few days later, Drovetti wrote trium¬
phantly to his superior, the lugubrious
Baron de Damas: "I am happy to inform
Your Excellency that fate has been kind to
us. Our giraffe is strong and vigorous,
whereas the one destined for the King of
England is sickly and will not last long."
And indeed, the "English" giraffe was to
die a few months later. Not, perhaps, a
complete revenge for Waterloo but all the
same...!!
Then came the problem of transporting
the animal to France. Drovetti prepared the
journey with painstaking care. In Alexan¬
dria he found a Sardinian brig, I Due Fratelli
(The Two Brothers), whose captain under¬
took to treat the creature like his own
daughter. Since the space between decks
was not high enough, a hole had to be cut in
the upper deck. The giraffe was installed
below with her head (for she was a female)
In 1984, the Musée de l'Ile de France organized an
exhibition entitled Une Girafe pour le Roi (A Giraffe for
the King) which attracted several thousand visitors. Gab¬
riel Dardaud, who made a major contribution to the
preparation of the exhibition, gave its title to his book
about the story of the Charles X's giraffe. Une Girafe
pour le Roi, Dumerchez-Naoum publishers, Creit
(France), 1985.
Home by a neck
A giraffe's epic journey
from Cairo to Paris by Georges Poisson
Engraving above depicts the firstgiraffe to
have been brought to France alive. The
two-and-a-half-year-old, 12-foot-tall anim¬
al was sent as a gift to King Charles X by
the ruler of Egypt. The engraving shows
the giraffe in the "King's Garden''(now the
Jardin des Plantes) in Paris, in July 1827,
shortly after its arrival.
protruding into the open. The edges of the
hole in the deck were lined with straw to
protect her from bumps caused by the roll of
the ship. A tarpaulin was rigged overhead
to shield her from the rain.
The next problem that arose was how to
feed an animal that consumed twenty-five
litres of milk a day. Drovetti decided to
embark three milch cows and, for good
measure, put aboard two antelopes, a
cowhand to do the milking and three
Sudanese to make the giraffe feel at home.
As a final talisman to ensure that provi¬
dence would be on his side, he hung about
the animal's neck a parchment inscribed
with verses from the Qur'an to protect her
from the powers of evil. Preparations were
completed with a letter addressed to his
colleague M. Bottu, an agent of the French
Foreign Office in Marseille, advising him of
the arrangements to be made for the giraffe
on her arrival in France.
Off sailed the brig, and on 13 October
1826 it dropped anchor at Marseille after an
uneventful journey, the only casualty one
cow suffering from seasickness. Passengers,
both two-legged and four-legged, were
placed in quarantine in a hospital near the
port, this respite giving M. de Villeneuve-
Bargemon, Prefect of the Département des
Bouches-du-Rhône, time to prepare a wel¬
come fit for a present for a king.
This was the first time that such a task had
been entrusted to a member of the corps of
Prefects and M. de Villeneuve-Bargemon
devoted himself to it with conscientiousness
and enthusiasm. Naturally, the only place
that an immigrant of such distinction could
be housed was at the Prefecture itself. An
enclosure was erected in the courtyard as
well as a heated stall with direct access from
both floors of the building.
There the giraffe wintered, her transfer
to Paris awaiting a more clement period of
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
the year. Meanwhile, the Prefect kept the
Minister of the Interior regularly informed
of all the arrangements made. ..and also
raised the delicate question of the reim¬
bursement of the expenses incurred.
For fear of provoking a riot, the creature
from the tropics was transferred from the
quarantine centre to the Prefecture at dead
of night on 14 November. For seven months
M. de Villeneuve-Bargemon watched
tenderly over his lodger, even allowing a
touch of lyricism to creep into his adminis¬
trative correspondence in which he referred
to her as "my ward", or "this beautiful child
of the tropics".
For her part, his wife gave a series of
receptions, or "routs" as they were called in
those days, to display the animal to the
upper-crust of Provençal society. Day and
night a constant stream of members of the
Academy of Marseille came to gaze upon
the beast, noting every detail of her be¬
haviour and marvelling at her silence, only
to discover later that the long-necked crea¬
ture possessed no vocal chords.
Meanwhile, to keep her in good con¬
dition, the Prefect decided that his protégée
should be exercised, thus providing a choice
spectacle for the people of Marseille . Every
day, preceded by mounted gendarmes with
sabres drawn, the giraffe calmly ambled
through the streets of the city, to the great
joy of the citizenry and to the great terror of
the horses.
The king, however, was eager to receive
"his" giraffe and, the following spring, the
question arose of how she should make the
journey from Marseille to Paris. Should she
go by sea, circumnavigate Spain and then
sail up the Seine? This would be as long a
journey as that which had brought her
across the Mediterranean. Should she
travel on the internal waterways, the
Rhône, the Saône and the Seine? In the
end, since the animal had become accus¬
tomed to walking, it was decided that she
should go to Paris on foot, in short stages.
Clearly, an experienced man was needed to
supervise the convoy and the choice fell on
Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire, an illustrious natur¬
alist noted for his theory of the "compensa¬
tion of organs", and, moreover, a veteran
of Napoleon's Egyptian expedition and
perhaps the only man in France who had
ever been anywhere near a giraffe.
Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire was fifty-five
years old and suffered from rheumatism
and other ailments. Nevertheless, he
accepted the mission with enthusiasm.
"Throwing a few essentials into a bag, he
took the next stage-coach and within six and
a half days had covered the itinerary he was
later to retrace with the giraffe," writes
Gabriel Dardaud in his book Une Girafe
pour le Roi (1985). At a meeting of the
Academy of Marseille, on lOMay 1827, one
of the members, a certain M. Jauffret,
announced the arrival of his eminent col¬
league, and read out three fables he had
written on the giraffe.
Each stage of the journey to Paris was
prepared down to the last detail. The cara¬
van included the giraffe, the cows, one of
the antelopes the other one had died in
Marseille two moufflons, the cowhand,
the Sudanese, an interpreter and. a cart
loaded with forage, seeds and a variety of
other impedimenta, all ordered by the
illustrious leader of the expedition.
To protect her from the spring rains, a
Two days t>efore the giraffe's arrival In
Paris, the French naturalist Georges
Cuvler (1769-1832) made the above draw¬
ing during a session of the Council of
State. He hadneverseen a living specimen
and his not very realistic representation
was Inspired by depletions of giraffes
made In earlier times.
A giraffe-craze swept France and led to the
creation of many objects Inspired by the
giraffe's distinctive silhouette. The clavl-
harp (Ijelow), a musical Instrument in¬
vented In 1819, was renamed the "piano-
glrafe" after the animal's arrival In Paris.
two-piece set of Hned oilskins with a hood
was made to measure for the giraffe. On it
were emblazoned the arms of the King of
France and of the Pasha of Egypt. Vil¬
leneuve-Bargemon had provided for an
escort of mounted gendarmes and took care
to write to all the mayors of the communes
within his jurisdiction through which the
caravan would pass, as well as to his col¬
leagues in the other Départements, giving
them instructions and advice.
At dawn on 20 May 1827, the caravan
sallied forth with Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire at
its head. In the open country he would rest
his rheumaticky joints beside the driver of
the cart, but when the cortège passed
through a town, or arrived at a staging-post,
he was usually to be found at the side of the
giraffe, reinvigorated by the enthusiastic
welcome of the populace and the local
authorities.
Aix, Avignon, Orange, MontéHmar,
Vienne and then, on 6 June, they arrived
at Lyon, having achieved the respectable
average rate of progress of twenty-seven
kilometres a day. At Lyon, Geoffroy Saint-
Hilaire wrote to Villeneuve-Bargemon to
give him the latest news. An incident had
occurred which had slowed their progress.
"The giraffe had picked up a nail in the
membrane of a hoof; she seemed weary of
the continual walking and was somewhat
fatigued yet "very obedient". A period of
rest was needed and, for five days, installed
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The giraffe as It Is today, preserved In the
Natural History Museum at La Rochelle, In
France.
in the Place Bellecour, the giraffe happily
stripped the lime trees of their leaves and
accepted titbits from the onlookers.
Then they were on the road again, wend¬
ing their way through ever-larger crowds.
"In 1827," writes Gabriel Dardaud, "some
thirty or more inns, shops and staging-posts
adopted the sign of the giraffe to com¬
memorate her passage".
When the cortège was within fifty
kilometres of Paris, excursions were orga¬
nized to go and meet it. The crowds
streamed out in charabancs, four-wheelers
and gigs. Even Stendhal did not disdain to
join the ranks of the sightseers and, at the
Court, it was only with the greatest of diffi¬
culty that the Duchess of Berry was res¬
trained from doing as much. As for the
great scientist Georges Cuvier, instead of
giving his attention to the discussions of the
Council of State, of which he was a mem¬
ber, he spent his time covering his papers
with drawings of a giraffe based on what
little he knew of the animal and coming up
with some bizarre results.
After a journey of 880 kilometres in for¬
ty-one days, most of it on foot, Geoffroy
Saint-Hilaire arrived in Paris at the head of
the caravan on 30 June, thoroughly exhaus¬
ted. He installed the giraffe in its enclosure
at the Jardin des Plantes (the Zoological
Gardens of Paris). But scarcely had he re¬
gained the comfort of his armchair, his slip¬
pers and his own fireside than he was
obliged to forsake them again. The king,
who was spending the summer at his
château at Saint-Cloud, demanded to see
"his" giraffe the very next day.
The cortège made a fine sight as it
wended its way along the bank of the Seine.
Troops from the garrison of Paris lined the
route; plume-bedecked generals caracolled
at its head; among the robed ranks of pro¬
fessors from the Museum and university
dignitaries, ermine-lined hoods vied for
attention with medals and decorations; and
the mace-bearers of the faculties sweated
under the weight of their insignia of office.
For Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire, decked out in
ceremonial dress and walking at the side of
the giraffe, these last fifteen kilometres
were sheer martyrdom.
At Saint-Cloud, in front of the orangery
where, twenty-eight years earlier. Napo¬
leon had seized power a memory it was
wiser not to recall under the Restoration
the dignitaries in all their finery were drawn
up in strict order of precedence, with the
giraffe in pride of place. After a few
minutes, as the soldiers presented arms, the
king arrived wearing a blue sash and, as
usual, cutting a fine figure. He was followed
by his son the heir to the throne, the Duke
of Angoulême; with him were his wife the
duchess, and the petite Duchess of Berry,
gracious, elegant and holding the hands of
the two royal children who had eyes only for
the strange beast that peered at them with
no trace of emotion. The king was his usual
amiable self, courteously attentive to
Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire, whom he congratu¬
lated and questioned at length, and to the
giraffe, to whom he did the honour of offer¬
ing some rose petals in the royal hand.
"Once the audience was over," says Gabriel
Dardaud, "Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire jumped
into a carriage and drove off to the hospital
for a check-up. The giraffe went back to the
Jardin des Plantes without him, passing be¬
tween two rows of spectators held back with
some difficulty by the armed soldiers of the
garrison."
The occasion gave rise to the production
of innumerable "giraffe" objects that were
hawked the length and breadth of the land.
First came chinaware on which figured
more or less diagrammatic representations
of the animal's characteristic profile. But
the image of the giraffe also featured on
printed cloth, in popular drawings, on
smoothing irons,.warming-pans, ink-wells,
fans, snuff-boxes and almanachs and pub-
Hcations of every sort. Women wore "giraf¬
fe" hair-styles and the claviharp invented in
1819, was re-named the "giraffe-piano".
The giraffe was installed at first in the
great greenhouse of the Jardin des Plantes.
Later she took possession of the "apart¬
ment" specially prepared for her in the
rotunda. There was one room for her which
was lined with mattresses and heated by a
stove as well as by the cows and other
animals who, throughout the winter, main¬
tained the temperature at -the fifteen de¬
grees necessary for the health of this native
of Africa. Above was a room for her Egyp¬
tian keeper.
Between July and December 1827, the
Jardin des Plantes did a roaring trade, with
600,000 Parisians going to visit the new
inmate. Curiosity died down a little the
following year, but the giraffe remained the
star attraction at the Jardin, where she
could be seen out walking when the weather
permitted. In about 1835, plans were made
to find her a mate, but the husband ear¬
marked for her never left Italy. She grew
old peacefully and died in 1845 in her twen¬
ty-first year, outliving both Charles X and
Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire.
She was stuffed, and her motionless
silhouette long graced the zoological gallery
of the museum, until, one day between the
two World Wars, the curator of the
museum of La Rochelle succeeded in get¬
ting her ceded to him. And so it came about
that this creature, which had been born near
the source of the Nile, which had travelled
across part of Africa, the Mediterranean
and France to delight Parisians for eighteen
years, set out again to the ocean
shore, where now she savours a kind of
immortality.
GEORGES POISSON has been curator of the
Museum of the lie de France forSOyears. He is a
specialist in the history of architecture, which he
has taught in a number of institutions of higher
education. He has published some 40 historical
works on the architecture of Paris and the
surrounding region. Several of them have been
awarded prizes by the Académie Française or
the Académie des Beaux-Arts.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Che Bandoneón, drawing by Ricardo CarpanI
That squall the tango, that devilry,
challenges the crowded years;
man made of dust and time
lasts less than the flighty tune,
which Is only time.
Jorge Luis Borges, El Tango
Tango Time
by Luis Bocaz
The Latin American song and dance
that swept the world onto its feet
ONE of the tango's many mysteries is
its mixed cultural parentage. To ex¬
plain its origins, its chroniclers have
had to investigate the aftermath of slavery
in a region of old Spanish colonies. Vicente
Rossi, for example, suggests that the tango
was bom in the African communities of
Montevideo, a view not always enthusiasti¬
cally shared on the western bank of the
estuary of the Rio de la Plata.
Apart from the inevitable wranglings
over paternity, there is no disagreement
about the influence of the candombe on this
dance in its early years, or about the con¬
tribution to its development made by the
two Rio de la Plata capitals, Buenos Aires
and Montevideo. The sprawling Argentine
metropoHs was, in the end, to monopolize
the sobriquet ''City of the Tango", but in
both ports (La Cumparsita, one of the best
known tangos, is Uruguayan) the inter¬
mingling of its African and mestizo ances¬
tors, together with other local and Euro¬
pean strains, gave birth, in the space of a
few decades, to one of the most distinctive
cultural creations of the American con¬
tinent.
Where did the name come from? In writ¬
ings and lectures on the subject, Jorge Luis
Borges pokes fun at those who bend over
backwards in their attempts to trace its
origins to a Latin root. The distinguished
writer's amusement is provoked by the
lowHness of its earliest surroundings, the
suburbs, and by the creature's undeniable
connections with disreputable ' establish¬
ments.
In Buenos Aires, the scale of the sub¬
urban fringe was a consequence of spec¬
tacular urban growth. This unpretentious
colonial town, founded twice in the six¬
teenth century, was chosen in 1880 as the
federal capital, and rapidly became a thriv¬
ing port. Thereafter, it absorbed wave upon
wave of immigrants, who disembarked with
their cargo of dreams and solitude and, on
the so-called orillas, estabHshed a sort of
frontier way of life. People were washed up
here by the tides of fortune, as they were on
the Pacific coast, in San Francisco of the
Gold Rush, or Valparaiso, with their nos¬
talgic atmosphere of turn-of-the-century
sailing ships.
In this murky urban quarter, lone men
fought one another over fortunes and brief
affairs of the heart. So it is not difficult to
understand how this branch of humanity
found in the cortes and quebradas (literally
"cuts and slashes") of the tango a means of
escape from the teeming solitude of the
tenements.
Those heroic times have left us with the
stereotyped image of the original dancing
couple. She, with her tight-fitting dress,
split skirt and scarcely concealed hint of
erotic aggressiveness; he, perched on high
heels and wearing a narrow-brimmed hat.
Even today, magazines and shows continue
to reproduce this vignette of a bygone age.
One thing is undeniable: in the last ten years
of the nineteenth century, the music to
which they danced was held in high esteem
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
in musical circles, and, at the turn of the
century, a whole galaxy of distinguished
composers ushered it out of the suburbs and
into the city centre.
By the time the Republic celebrated its
centenary, definite rules had taken shape
governing the instruments on which it was
played. Flutes and guitars had been
banished, making way for the ensemble that
would henceforth be known as the orquesta
típica, consisting of piano, violins, double
bass and a little-known instrument called
the bandoneón. This emigrant accordéon
from Central Europe came to symbolize the
essence of the tango. Why did it become so
prominent as a popular art form? After all,
as musicologists point out, it was very diffi¬
cult to play. There is no convincing answer
to this question, but the fact remains that
from the legendary Ramos Mejia to Astor
Piazzolla in our own time , the roll of honour
of those who played it includes such glamor-
ous names in tango history as Eduardo Aro-
las and Aníbal Troilo.
On a wave of popular creativity, this sub¬
urban adolescent rose irresistibly to fame.
Before the First World War, Paris (Tango-
ville, some historians would claim) had
given her the keys to Europe. From London
to Moscow, the great cities were held spell¬
bound by the mysterious creature. Her
triumph heralded that of jazz, another child
of miscegenation in the landfall cities of
America. The tango craze spread through
the ballrooms and fashionable watering
places. Handbooks on how to dance it
appeared by the dozen, and a certain shade
of orange came to be called "tango". In
February 1914, an engraving in the French
magazine L'Illustration showed the Pope
thoughtfully watching the circlings of a
dancing couple. The Holy See found itself
obHged to make a pronouncement, having
heard voices raised in condemnation of the
morals of this Latin-American upstart. Its
concern was justified. Some of the vitupera¬
tion came from Argentine circles. The poet
Leopoldo Lugones called the tango a "rep¬
tile from the brothel", and more than one
diplomat showed distaste for the discon¬
certing way in which this ignoble compatriot
had won general acceptance.
The international renown of this ambas¬
sador of working-class descent was decisive¬
ly heightened by a man of obscure extrac¬
tion with an extraordinary voice. His name
was Carlos Gardel. He came to the tango
when it had already acquired cosmopoHtan
status. Nevertheless, his indisputable artis¬
tic talent and and a modicum of publicity in
the media, combined with the strange cir¬
cumstances in which his life began and
ended, were enough to give him mythical
stature: the accident at the airport of
Medellin, which cost him his Hfe, and the
shadows which, for years, surrounded his
birth. More than one town boasted of being
his birthplace. After his death, in June
1935, conflicting evidence came to light. An
official document announced that his place
of birth was Tacuarembó, in the Republic of
Uruguay. Meanwhile, the Argentine Gar-
del cult reconstructed the childhood of its
idol in the market quarter of Buenos Aires
and exhibited a signed handwritten docu¬
ment referring to his birth in Toulouse,
France.
A reproduction of the birth certificate of
a baby boy, Charles Romuald Gardes, bom
in the maternity wing of the La Grave hos
pital at 2 a.m. on 11 December 1890, in
Toulouse, finally put an end to the
arguments. The singer was the illegitimate
son of an unknown father and a laundry
worker, Berthe Gardes. Like others from
southern France, she emigrated to the Rio
de la Plata region, taking her two-year-old
son with her. Moreover, on the occasion of
the fiftieth anniversary of the death of Car¬
los Gardel, the Toulouse municipal author¬
ities mobilised its cultural facilities to pay
him an impressive tribute. The programme,
which lasted for several weeks, included the
unveiling of a monument, public exhibi¬
tions and the first scienfific congress on the
tango. This was convened by the University
of Toulouse, a highly respected centre for
Hispanic and Latin-American studies, and
was attended by specialists from Latin
America, Europe and the United States.
The 1970s witnessed a partial revival of
the tango on the European scene as a form
of music for instruments and voice. Follow¬
ing a fairly long period of eclipse, this re¬
newal was foreseeable, in view of the
admiradon that it still commanded in the
cities of Latin America, and, indeed, in
such an unexpected country as Japan,
where a huge trade in recordings is to be
found, together with orquestas típicas, col¬
lectors and specialized magazines. Never¬
theless, some observers would point to a
paradox: while Cuba organizes tango festi¬
vals, and while Amsterdam and Paris are
enthralled by the classical rigour of Osvaldo
Pugliese, the formal audacity of Piazzolla or
the splendid voice of Susana Rinaldi, there
are signs in its cities of origin of a slackening
of the fervour that gripped them from the
1930s to the 1950s. The great tango orches¬
tras and soloists have watched their sources
of work drying up one by one, partly as a
result of changes in pubHc taste, which
seems less drawn to this art form than it was
in days gone by.
It can be argued that, since the "codifica¬
tion" by Julio de Caro, in the 1920s, the
structures which shaped the tango have
changed in ways comparable to the changes
occurring in the societies which produced it,
and in the various attitudes of mind and
. feeling which embraced it as their own.
Perhaps for this reason, following the tmce
between traditionalists and modernists,
creators and performers have come to agree
that the tango can change and develop.
Accordingly, such essential works as Re¬
cuerdo (1924) by Pugliese or Adlos, Nonino
(1959) by Piazzolla are valued in their con¬
temporary context as innovative land¬
marks, and the tango is seen to embody the
pathos prevailing in the painting, the films
or the poetry of the day.
Worth noting is the enthusiasm with
which, in the first few months of 1986, tango
demonstrations are being greeted in New
York. Will they, perhaps, provide the
necessary impetus for this complex Latin
American character to make a glorious and
majestic come-back to the international
stage?
LUIS BOCAZ, of Chile, is a specialist in Latin
American literature and culture. A lecturer at the
Sorbonne, he also directs a seminar on "Cultural
production and society in Latin America" at the
Institut des Hautes Etudes de l'Amérique Latine,
in Paris. He has served as a consultant with
Unesco's culture sector.
With the urbanization ofpopular culture at
the turn of the century, the tango appeared
In suburban bars around the cities of the
Rio de la Plata, In the so-called "low-life"
houses. In the districts near the abattoirs
and In the homes of the poor like these
photographed In Buenos Aires at the be¬
ginning of the century.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
The Channel Tunnel by John Ardagh
Right, artist's impression of the "Euro-
bridge" ("Europont") concept of a fixed
link between Britain and continental
Europe: a suspension bridge with 5,000-
metre-iong spans. Two 6-iane motorways
would tte enclosed with theprotective con¬
crete tul>e.
Opposite page: section of theproject for a
Channel Tunnel which was adoptedby the
British and French Governments In Janu¬
ary 1986. Passenger trains and special
shuttle trains for transporting vehicles
and their passengers will run through twin
tunnels (diameter 7.3 metres) bored 40
metres under thesea t)ed. Between the two
main tunnels Is a smaller service tunnel
(diameter 4.5 metres).
12
THE Channel Tunnel between Britain
and France, a dream nearly two cen¬
turies old, is to become reality at
last. And this is most warmly to be wel¬
comed by all those who care for the future
of Europe, for in all kinds of ways eco¬
nomic, touristic, political, even psycholo¬
gical it will serve to strengthen Britain's
Hnks with the Confinent, and especiaUy
with France. Thus it will strike a blow at that
old insularity which has shrouded the island
of Britain for so long. We shall be islanders
no more.
The joint decision to build the Tunnel
was announced by President François Mit¬
terrand and Prime Minister Margaret
Thatcher in a ceremony at Lille on 21
January. The project chosen from among
several contenders is for a twin-bore railway
tunnel. This is what the French wanted, for
express railways are France's forte. The
Brifish might have preferred a combined
road and rail tunnel, but this would have
been more costly. However, it has been
agreed that a separate road tunnel might be
added some time after the year 2000. In the
meantime, so long as the two parliaments
ratify the plan, digging will begin next year
on a fifty-one-kilometre tunnel from a point
near Folkestone, in Kent, to a point near
Calais. British and French banks are pro¬
viding the main part of the budget, which
will be at least £2.3 bilHon.
When the Tunnel opens, in 1993, it will
be able to carry up to thirty million passen¬
gers a year. Fast trains will Unk London with
Paris (some 450 km) in just over three
hours, and London with Brussels in even
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Two 19th-century conceptions of a Chan¬
nel TunneL Above left, a scheme for a
"submarine railway between France and
England" by HectorMoreau (1851). Above,
drawing of a project for a Dover-Calais
tunnel devisedby French engineer Thome
de Gamondin 1875. Smoke from the steam
trains was to be evacuated by ventilation
chimneys one of which, in mid-Channel, Is
topped by a lighthouse.
less time. And a rail shuttle service will
carry freight trucks and private cars be¬
tween terminals at either end of the tunnel,
with trains leaving every three minutes at
peak periods.
It was a French engineer in 1802 who first
proposed a tunnel under the English Chan¬
nel: Napoleon was interested, for he
thought it might assist his planned invasion
of England. In the 1880s the scheme was
revived, and private companies began to
bore pilot tunnels; but the British Govern¬
ment took fright, mainly for defence
reasons, and the project was stopped. Not
until the 1950s did it surface again, and after
much discussion new preHminary diggings
began in 1974. But again the British Gov¬
ernment cancelled the scheme (in 1975),
this time for economic reasons.
Throughout that long period, the French
showed noticeably more enthusiasm for a
Channel tunnel than the British. This may
seem curious, seeing that France already
has many land frontiers, whereas for Britain
a tunnel would be its first fixed link with the
Continent, and thus more valuable. But the
British were held back by their insularity,
and especially by . fears that an invader
might be able to make use of the scheme.
Happily, all that is past. Today Britain's
politicians and business circles have shown
themselves as eager as the French.
It is true that ordinary British public opin¬
ion remains sceptical. Some people point
out that the train shuttle for cars will take
almost the same time as the hovercraft ser¬
vice (thirty-five minutes) and wiU be only
forty minutes faster than the present ferry
crossings: these critics wonder whether
enough people will use the tunnel to amor¬
tize its huge costs. The inhabitants of the
Dover and Folkestone areas are alarmed
for their environment, and for the future of
jobs with the ferry services. And many ex¬
perts predict that in economic terms the
tunnel will benefit France more than Britain
if, as they believe, the new industry
attracted to its vicinity opts less for prosper¬
ous Kent than for the stmggling Nord-Pas
de Calais region with its wider spaces, lower
costs and more central position in the Euro¬
pean Economic Community.
However, those who take a wider and
longer-term view believe that these possible
drawbacks for Britain will be far out¬
weighed by the advantages. Passengers by
express train will be able to do the journey
at least an hour faster than by air, city centre
to city centre, and without any tedious waits
at airports. Also the fares will be cheaper.
So the tunnel will probably stimulate a vast
increase in tourism and business travel be¬
tween London and Paris and Brussels,
much of it in the form of day excursions. It
will also encourage new export trade by
train and tmck, and it will help to build the
Kent and Pas-de-Calais areas into a vital
nerve-centre of the European Economic
Community, buzzing with new modem in¬
dustry. Above all, as Mrs Thatcher has said,
the tunnel venture is a symbol of Britain's
involvement in Europe and of its close ties
with France. In my own view, it will streng¬
then the exchanges between peoples and
thus lead to better understanding, for
it is ignorance that breeds prejudice and
chauvinism.
JOHN ARDAGH is a British journalist who has
written a number of studies of French life in¬
cluding The New France (Pelican Books, 1970-
1977) and France in the 1 980s (Penguin Books,
1982). In 1983he was awarded the EnidMcLeod
Prize for books promoting Franco-British
understanding.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
His n' Hers
by Elisabeth Badinter
The changing relationship
WE have known for a long time that
the organization of any particular
society is influenced by the defini¬
tion of the sexes and the distinction drawn
between them. But we have realized only
recently that the identity of each sex is not
so easy to pin down, and that definitions
evolve in accordance with the different
types of culture known to us, scientific dis¬
coveries and ideological revolutions. Our
nature is not considered immutable, either
socially or biologically. As we approach the
end of the century, the substantial progress
made in biology and genetics is radically
challenging the roles, responsibilities and
specific characteristics attributed to each
sex; and yet, scarcely twenty years ago,
these were thought to be "beyond dispute".
We can safely say, with a few minor ex¬
ceptions, that the definition of the sexes and
their respective functions remained un¬
changed in the West from the beginning of
the nineteenth century to the 1960s. The
role distinction, raised in some cases to the
status of uncompromising dualism on a
strongly hierarchical model, lasted
throughout this period, appealing for its
justification to nature, religion and customs
alleged to have existed since the dawn of
time. The woman bore children and took
care of the home. The man set out to con¬
quer the world and was responsible for the
survival of his family, by satisfying their
needs in peacetime and by going to war
when necessary.
The entire world order rested on the
divergence of the sexes. Any overlapping or
confusion between the roles was seen as a
threat to the time-honoured order of things.
It was felt to be against nature, a deviation
from the norm.
Sex roles were determined according to
the "place" appropriate to each. Woman's
place was, first and foremost, in the home.
The outside world, i.e. workshops, factor¬
ies and business firms, belonged to men.
This sex-based division of the world (pri¬
vate and public) gave rise to a strict dicho¬
tomy between the attitudes which conferred
on each its special identity. The woman,
sequestered at home, "cared, nurtured and
conserved". To do this, she had no need to
be daring, ambitious, tough or competitive.
The man, on the other hand, competing
with his fellow men, was caught up every
day in the stmggle for survival, and hence
developed those characteristics which were
thought natural in a man.
Today, many women go out to work, and
their reasons for doing so have changed
considerably. Besides the traditional finan¬
cial incentives, we find ambition and per¬
sonal fulfilment motivating those in the
"Passivity, patience (...) are no longer the
salient characteristics of the female sex. "
Right, detail ofJhe Departure of the Volun¬
teers of 1792 (also known as La Marseil¬
laise;, a high-reliefsculpture by the French
sculptor Francois Rude (1784-1855) which
adorns the Arc de Triomphe in Paris.
most favourable circumstances, and the
wish to have a social life and to get out of
their domestic isolation influencing others.
But, for all women, work is connected with
the desire for independence. Above all,
they do not wish to be forced to live with a
man whom they can no longer tolerate ; they
want to reclaim their freedom without un¬
duly harming their standard of living.
Whether we like it or not, these shared
experiences profoundly alter the rela¬
tionship between the sexes and the specific
definition of each. The change assuredly
makes for greater equality, but also,
perhaps, for a degree of fraternal similarity.
By dint of experiencing the same situations
as the other, one learns to react as he does,
and although he may thereby lose some of
his mystery, he gains in being better under¬
stood.
Furthermore, contraception has made it
possible to keep motherhood at bay. Now
that it is neither a physiological necessity
nor a moral obligation, child-bearing is no
longer endured but chosen. It thus becomes
something contingent and voluntary; it is no
longer left to "chance" in the form of
nature.
Late twentieth-century woman is no
longer automatically to be regarded as a
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
between the sexes in the Western World
mother. For the first time in our history,
women are allowed to find fulfilment in
spheres other than procreation. One reason
for this development is probably women's
increased life expectancy. Active mother¬
hood no longer takes up more than an aver¬
age of fifteen years in a woman's life, and is
one stage among others in female existence.
This change of attitude towards child-
bearing has gone hand in hand with a mod¬
ification of the stereotypes of female iden¬
tity; moreover, there has been a change in
those which, not so long ago, still defined
male identity. Passivity, patience, devotion
and altruism are no longer the salient char¬
acteristics of the female sex. For one thing,
women no longer recognize themselves in
this summary description, which conceals
other, equally real characteristics, once
thought to belong exclusively to the male:
ambition, activity, selfishness and indepen¬
dence. For another, because for the past ten
or fifteen years women have tirelessly urged
their companions to share in the joys and
duties of "mothering", men in turn are dis¬
playing virtues which used to be considered
feminine: genUeness, devotion and atten-
tiveness to small children. It is undeniable
that young fathers who take care of their
newbom offspring quickly acquire a body
language and set of attitudes, concerns and
feeHngs which in the past were alleged to
"come naturaUy" to women.
In reaHty, and within a very short time,
the specific characteristics of fatherhood
and motherhood have begun to converge. It
is no longer the mother alone who shows
affection, and the father is no longer the
exclusive embodiment of authority, law and
the outside world. All these roles are shared
between the sexes, and attitudes vary more
according to personal temperament than in
alignment with sexual differences.
If women no longer define themselves as
mothers first and foremost, nor do they
recognize themselves any longer as wives.
Their lives are an altemation between
celibacy and togetherness, with the result
that autonomy is taking precedence over
complementarity, and women, like men,
are coming to define themselves as beings in
their own right and no longer, as formerly,
in terms of another person. The bi-polar
relationship is still sought after by both men
and women, but is nevertheless losing
ground, in actuality, to periods of soHtude.
This new lifestyle is conducive to the
emergence of new psychological and social
characteristics in both sexes. Men and
"The level of civilization attained by the
different human societies Isproportionate
to the independence enjoyed by women in
these societies," wrote Flora Tristan
(1803-1844), the pioneer French feminist
andsocialist (right) in her book Pérégrlna-
tlons d'une Parla (1838). The daughter of a
Peruvian nobleman and a Frenchwoman,
she married the engraver and lithographer
André Chazal and was tfie grandmother of
Peut Gauguin (1848-1903).
women are tending to express that "other
half of themselves which their upbringing
in the past would have taught them they
must repress. Archetypal androgyny has
returned, sweeping before it the inequality
of the sexes and their strict comple¬
mentarity.
Another new development is eroding the
age-old stereotype of the male warrior, an
image that we find confronting us as far
back as we are able to trace it in history.
Today, the threat of nuclear war on a world
scale renders meaningless to us the warrior
virtues attributed to men when we try to
imagine the future. We see ourselves, men
and women, rightly or wrongly, as the im¬
mediate victims of such a war, with neither
the time nor the ability to defend ourselves
individually. The spectre of the atomic
bomb emphasizes still more the idea of fate,
passivity and the indistinguishability of the
sexes. On the one hand, men would be as
passive as women. On the other, the person
to "press the button" might equally well be
female or male.
Apart from this apocalyptic image of
war, other forms of modem warfare have
brought us pictures of women, and even
children, carrying weapons. This image, is
no longer startling: it shows that war is no
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
^ longer the prerogative of men and that ac¬
tion or passivity are Hkewise no longer the
property of one sex rather than the other.
Oddly enough, male identity has not so
far given rise to as much discussion and
controversy as that of females. And yet we
venture to predict that male identity will be
a major issue in the next half-century.
Women seem to have interiorized male
othemess without thereby abandoning their
traditional female identity. Twentieth-cen¬
tury Western woman is truly an androgy¬
nous creature. She is both virile and femi¬
nine, and she sHps out of one role and into
another according to the time of day or at
different times in her life. She is unwilling to
forgo anything, and walks a tightrope by
no means always easy to do between her
female and male desires. By turns passive
and active, devoted mothers and ambitious
egoists, gentle and aggressive, patient and
commanding, modern women have shuf¬
fled the identity cards that they were dealt.
In this period of upheaval brought about
by women, men's resistance, not to say
uneasiness, is immediately apparent. The
changes occurring in their partners and the
latter's new demands are forcing them to
caU their traditional model in question. The
fact that women can do everything men can
do, and that they have claimed men's time-
honoured characteristics for themselves, is
often felt by men as an experience of dispos¬
session and loss with which they are unable
to come to terms.
Trapped between an outdated model
which women no longer want and a new
model which men seem to fear, many men
are reacting by fleeing from women and
from family responsibilities.
Their difficulty in fully assimilating
female otherness and in expressing it out¬
wardly without any inhibitions stems from
the threat that they feel to their viriUty. This
dilemma does not seem to affect women in
the same way. The most convincing ex¬
planation for this male conflict is given by
the American psychoanalyst Robert J. Stol-
ler. Disagreeing with Freud, he claims that
"male" identity is not the stronger or the
more natural of the two. Throughout the
first few months of life, the male newbom
"Because for the past 10 or 15 years
women have tirelessly urged their com¬
panions to share in the Joys and duties of
'mothering' (...) young fathers in turn are
taking care of their newborn offspring and
quickly acquiring a body language and set
of attitudes, concerns and feelings which
In thepast were alleged to 'come naturally'
to women." Below, "Men's roles as
fathers," a photo used by Sweden's
National Social Security Office in a cam¬
paign to facilitate the leave of fathers to
take care of their children.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
baby identifies strongly with his mother,
with whom he lives in a state of symbiosis.
Sexual differentiation, therefore, is
achieved only as the culmination of an "in¬
tense and painful struggle to break away
from this symbiosis. The male child must
thus "de-identify himself with his mother"
in order to jettison his female nature and
develop his subsequent gender identity:
maleness. But, observes StoUer, maleness
is always under latent threat from the ex¬
perience of bliss with the mother. Hence
men's much greater fear of androgyny,
which is experienced as a danger of
homosexuality, i.e. a loss of virility.
The dawn of the third millennium is co¬
inciding with an extraordinary reversal in
the power structure.
Not only will the patriarchal system be
dead and buried in most of the industrial¬
ized West, but we shall see the birth of a
new imbalance in the relations between the
sexes, this time exclusively to women's
advantage.
Women may at last be sharing control of
the outside world with their male compan¬
ions as they create and produce on an equal
footing with them. But the fact is that they
also have absolute control over procre¬
ation. They can, at any time, refuse to have
children. Tomorrow, thanks to sperm
banks, they will be able to produce children
without men's active assistance. But the
contrary is not trae. A man still needs a
woman's body in order to procreate. The
complementary relationship between the
sexes that seemed incontrovertible where
procreation was concerned is now being
challenged. And when we consider that
biologists and geneticists predict that before
long it will be possible to fertilize a female
nucleus without any need for a spermata-
zoon, we can see how close we have come to
achieving the powerful age-old fantasy of
parthenogenesis: in this case feminine.
Even if women in the third millennium
refrain from using this inordinate power, it
is probable that men will be painfully aware
of their possible eviction from the process of
fertilization and of the new imbalance in
their disfavour. There are probably hard
times ahead for men. Perhaps they will
experience an even greater feeling of loss of
identity, uniqueness and necessity. So it is
by no means absurd to suppose that they
will do all they can to win back some of their
power. Already, biologists are predicting
the incredible possibility that men will be
able to "carry" a child, within less than half
a century. The hypothesis no longer belongs
to the realm of science fiction. It will soon
call for some entirely new thinking about
the relationship between the sexes, their
identity and their equality.
To be continued in the third millennium.
ELISABETH BADINTER, ofFrance, was trained
as a philosopher and directs a seminar on the
history andpsychology of the family at the Ecole
Polytechnique, Paris. She is the author of,
L'Amour en plus, oA Emilie, Emilie une Femme
du 18e Siècle, and of the forthcoming L'Un est
l'Autre, a studyof the relations between men and
women. The above article has been extracted
from a paper entitled "Le Rapport des Sexes:
Egalité, Différence, Altérité", which Elisabeth
Badinter presented to an international seminar
on the new roles of men and women in private
and public life, held in Athens under Unesco
auspices from 26 to 29 November 1985.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
The powers
of language
by Claude Hagège
FOR the sake of simplicity, let us di¬
vide the powers of language into two
categories: internal and external.
The former concerns language as a system
and its relationship with those who use it
and whose attitudes of mind and activities
are shaped by it. The latter has to do with
the use of language in the activity of speech
or parole, and the capabilities that this con¬
fers on its users.
Language is older than the individual.
From birth to adulthood, we have no choice
but to learn it. True, the individual can also
steer language in a particular direction: in¬
deed, it is he who shapes it and causes it to
change by the way in which he uses it. But
this process is spread over very long
periods. In what linguists call synchrony,
that is, the time in which the user is actually
living, he seems to be a receptive substance
on which language stamps its indelible im¬
print. That imprint shows itself in two
essential ways: in representation of the real
world, and in the sphere of psycho-social
symbolism and nationalism.
We can all see for ourselves, in our daily
lives, that different languages construct
different images of the universe. Far from
mirroring the world's phenomena in a way
that is universally identical, languages tend
to organize them according to their own
ever-changing systems of classification,
reinventing and even creating them so that
they exert considerable influence over the
way in which each community thinks about
these phenomena.
Some would even claim that there is a
causal link between language and world-
view. Such a link, for example, provides the
basis for the so-called Sapir-Whorf
hypothesis, named after two twentieth-cen¬
tury linguists who most openly defended it.
"It is quite an illusion," wrote Edward Sapir
(1884-1939), "to imagine that one adjusts to
reality essentially without the use of lan¬
guage, and that language is merely an in¬
cidental means of solving specific problems
of communication or reflection. The fact of
the matter is that the 'real world' is to a
large extent unconsciously built up on the
language habits of different cultural
groups." (1) Benjamin Lee Whorf (1897-
1941), Sapir's pupil, believed that we cut up
nature along "the lines drawn by our lan¬
guage (...) No individual is free to describe
18
nature with absolute impartiaUty; on the
contrary, he is forced to submit to certain
modes of interpretation, even when he be¬
lieves he is free." (2) Whorf adds that the
Hopi Indians, who Uve on the desert
plateaux of northern Arizona, are quite
unable to imagine such places as heaven or
hell as described by missionaries.
The Jesuits in China ran into difficulties
which were probably similar. Their experi¬
ence prompts a number of doubts about the
universality of the ten grammatical categor¬
ies which Aristotle established and which
are still used as guidelines for research by
many Hnguists. "What Aristotle gives us as
a checklist of universal and immutable con¬
ditions is merely the conceptual projection
of a particular linguistic state (...) Beyond
the terms of the Aristotelians, and tran¬
scending this categorization, there stretches
the concept of 'being' which encompasses
everything (...). Greek not only has a verb
'to be' (which is by no means a necessity in
every language), but it has developed whol¬
ly distinctive uses for this verb."^
So we find that the existence of a verb "to
be" in Greek and the way in which Greek
maps out grammatical categories in the uni¬
verse of the sayable have given rise to the
grammar which is used by all Western ling¬
uists and which is artificially overlaid on the
languages of other parts of the world.
Father Matteo Ricci could find nothing bet¬
ter than the expression "Lord of the Sky" to
make the concept of God acceptable to the
Chinese. He encountered a very thorny
problem in his attempts at adaptation, for
"Chinese thought (...) does not deal in posi¬
tive and negative, being and non-being, but
in contraries which follow one another in
succession, combine and complement one
another (...). Using the Chinese language
brings other thought processes into play,
and develops other abilities, than those
which have been given pride of place in the
West".w The same problem arose concern¬
ing the concept of substance, of the adjec¬
tive (which is a verb in Chinese), and of
everything in language which gives form to
representation.
We all pay less attention to that which our
language does not name, even if we are
quite capable of conceiving of it. The power
of objects and concepts over individuals is
much greater when language gives them a
CONTINUED PAGE 23
Colour pages
Opposite page
Above left: On 2 July 1985, the European
Space Agency's (ESA) spacecraft Giotto
began an 8-monthJourney that would take
it to meetHalley's cometon 13 March 1986.
On 18 October 1985, the HalleyMulticolour
Camera (HMC), the high-resolution Imag¬
ingsystem on board Giotto, lookedbackat
the earth from a distance of 21 million
kilometres. On this Image, taken at 6:00 UT
(Universal Time), cloud formations above
Australia and Antarctica can be seen.
Photo © ESA, Paris
Above right: Halley's cometphotographed
on 19 May 1910 at the Lowell Observatory
(USA). The comet, which had passed
through Its perihelion (the closestpoint of
its orbit to the sun) a month earlier, was
then at a distance of 0.9 AU from the sun
and 0.3 AU from the earth (one astrono¬
mical unit or AU Is equivalent to around
150 million km).
Photo © ESA, Paris, by courtesy ol Lowell Observatory and the
National Optical Astronomy Observatory, USA
Below: The Adoration of the Magi, a scene
from a fresco cycle executed between
1303-1305 In the Scrovegnl chapel, Padua,
by the Italian painter Giotto di Bondone
(1266-1337). Halley's comet appeared in
1301 and served as a model for Giotto's
Star of Bethlehem. The European Space
Agency named its mission to Halley's
comet "Giotto" In recognition of the fact
that Giotto di Bondone made the first re¬
corded "scientific"depiction of the comet.
Photo © ESA, Paris
Page 20
Carlos Gardel (1890-1935), the celebrated
composer andsinger of the Argentine tan¬
go, can be seen at top of this pastel draw¬
ing on canvas, Te Fuistes sin que Nos
Diéramos Cuenta (You Left Without Our
Noticing, 250 x 200 cm) by the Argentine
painter Antonio Seguí (1976).
Photo © Fernando Chaves
Page 21
The Earth Is a Man, 1942, oil on canvas
(183 x 239 cm) by the Chilean painter
Roberto Matta. Joseph R. Shapiro Collec¬
tion, Chicago.
Photo Bétrice Hatala © Centre Georges Pompidou, Paris
Correction
We apologize to our readers tor the fact
that a technical error In our February
issue, The New World of the Ocean, re¬
sulted in the inversion of two captions
Identifying the photos of relief maps of the
Pacific and Atlantic ocean floors repro¬
duced on page 19 and on the back cover.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
m
y.. Í ' . <m^ '
^r;i
^4SÎ.é Ç|5'
I
7/
Cf
'^'JS&.
-\,JC: V*»
/ f.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
c
s
1
e
u
t
c
e
v
o
u
o
u
t
e
c
o
u
t
IL PLEUT
u
a
e
s
a
u
s
s
g
e
3
O
ni
b
o
i
X
c
B
e
u
t
q,
u
i a
n
e
m
m
e
a
q
u
m
e
o
m
m
e
v
e
n
n
e
n
e
u
a
e
h
e
n
n
i
e
t
i
e
n
n
e
n
r
e
n
c
o
u
Q.
10
E
1
e
n
V
m
o
t
r
e
s
u
n
é
d
a
I
h
a
r
t
e
8
d
e
m
a
u
n
i
v
e
p
8
ê
m
e
d
a
n
e
n
g
o
u
t
n
u
n
c
e
n
I
E
S
1
c
u
I
r
e
e
m
u
s
i
q
. u
e
Colour page opposite
Gilded bronze statue of the Buddha Vajra-
sattva (possessor of the vajra, a thunder¬
bolt or diamond) by the sculptor Zanaba-
zar (1635-1723), one of the masters of
Mongolfan religious art. In one hand the
Buddha Is holding a vajra (symbol of the
maleprinciple) andin the othera smallbell
(symbol of the female principle); his head
Is very slightly tilted to the left. The statue
Is In the Cholfin lama temple museum,
Ulaanbaatar.
Photo © All Rights Reserved
In his book L'Homme de Paroles, Claude
Hagège writes that "The autonomy of the
written word establishes it as an end in
itself. (...) Disposed on a flat surface, writ¬
ing can exploit the possibilities of com¬
binations between directions: vertical,
horizontal, left to right, right to left." The
French poet Guillaume Apollinaire (1880-
1918) considered his famous Calligram¬
mes, as "an idealization ofpoetry (...) and a
form of typographical precision at a time
when the careerof typography is ending in
a blaze of glory..." Above, Apollinaire's
calligramme II Pleut.
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 18
name than when it does not. Nevertheless,
this power of language should not be over¬
estimated. We may feel some reservations
at Nietzsche's enthusiasm when he writes,
in order to explain "the strange family re¬
semblance shared by all Hindu, Greek and
German thought", that "when there is ling¬
uistic kinship, it is inevitable that a common
grammatically-based philosophy (...) pre¬
disposes thought to produce philosophical
systems which develop along the same
lines". All we can say, and this is already a
large claim, is that the parallels between
language structures and thought patterns in
substantially differing cultures are suffi¬
ciently regular to appeal to the observer's
imagination.
Psycho-social symbolism and nationalism
constitute another sphere in which the pow¬
ers of language operate. The use of a lan¬
guage is experienced by the individual as an
umbilical cord to which he owes his identity
and even his existence. Language is much
more than the straightforward tool that it
would be if we were to accept the reduction¬
ist definition which sees it as a mere instru¬
ment of communication.
What is true of the individual is even
more so of the community elevated to the
status of a nation. A Hungarian linguist
writes: "In 'minor' countries which are pre¬
vented by statistical and geographical cir¬
cumstances from aspiring to the rank of
great powers, there is often a certain cult of
the national language and of various other
components of the national and folk heri¬
tage, on which patriotic feeling feeds and
thrives". (5) There is a Hungarian proverb,
likewise, which says: "nyelvében él a nem-
zet", or "a nation lives through its lan¬
guage".
Language, then, has the power to rally
support for a national cause that it em¬
bodies more effectively than any other com¬
ponent of the culture. This can be seen in
the nationalist claims of many minorities
which appeal for justification to their dis¬
tinctive languages: Catalans, Berbers,
Ukrainians, Kurds, Tibetans, Bretons,
Welsh, Basques and Macedonians. And
nationalism which arms groups to defend
their culture by defending their language
can take such violent forms as military
clashes, rebellion in the world of school
against the obligation to teach children in an
alien tongue, and demonstrations. Such
reactions have occurred in the past in India
and in Greece (where, in 1901, the con¬
servative uprising against the translation of
the New Testament into demotic resulted in
several deaths).
Some great nations impose their lan¬
guage through the power that it derives
from their own power. This is true today of
the United States of America, and it is also
true on the scale of that largest of countries,
the Soviet Union. The Indian languages of
North America have all yielded to the press¬
ure of American English, and those which,
like Navajo in Arizona, are still spoken in
scattered village groups are exceedingly
rare and, in any case, threatened. In the
Soviet Union, Koryak in north-eastern
Siberia, Chechen, Ingush, Circassian,
Abkhasian of the Caucasus, Udmurt, the
Turkic languages such as Kirghiz or Uzbek,
and many other languages such as Chere-
miss of the Volga basin, the Samoyed di¬
alects spoken by the nomads of the Lower
Ob, and Zyryan of the Pechora basin all
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
^ these languages seem helpless before the
onslaught of Russian, which they absorb
haphazardly, with a great many uncon¬
trolled borrowings from it.
As they become aware of the powers of
language. States set up official planning
machinery. History is, as a result, studded
with the foundation of academies for a great
many languages: Italy (Academy of La
Crusca, 1582), Germany (1617, 1633,
1641), France (1635), Spain (1713), Sweden
(1786), Hungary (1825), Romania (1879),
Syria (1919), Egypt (1932) and Israel
(1953). These bodies are set up in order to
harness the power of language in a rational
manner, by singhng out national languages
in cases of multilingualism, by pubUshing
lists of officially recognized neologisms,
thereby defending the prevailing idea of the
purity of the language, by systematizing
spelling or reforming it, as the case may be,
by compiling lexicons of dialects regarded
as the most archaic (as in the case of Turkey
under Atatürk), and by compiling grammar
books and dictionaries.
The intemal power of language pertains
not to a system but to an activity. We are
concerned here with what Hnguists call
parole. It is not a matter of chance if those
who use speech for purposes of command,
in all organized stmctures, starting with
that of the State, are nearly always highly
attentive to questions of language. In their
support for or participation in scholarly re¬
search, governments are very eager for
standardization, and, when it suits them,
for Hnguistic reform. This is no innocent
flirtation on the part of lovers of words and
phrases, but very definitely a political acti¬
vity. This is brought out by expUcit state¬
ments of position, such as that of Stalin in
the famous Pravda article which, in 1950,
put an end to the reign of the linguist Marr,
whose linguistic theories, dominating the
Soviet scene, had long been a hindrance to
all progress: "As regards Marxism in ling¬
uistics", wrote Stalin in the article, "... this
is a matter which concerns me personally".
Indeed, political regimes which rest on a
particular way of manipulating parole are,
in a way, logocracies, i.e. systems which
build their dominion on the power of words.
In fiction, Orwell's newspeak was the very
essence of a "language" aimed at eradicat¬
ing all unorthodox thought by banishing the
names which might sustain it. In the real
world, logocracies abound. To varying de¬
grees, all political power is tempted to ex¬
ploit the force of words that have been
drained of their meaning and moulded into
stereotypes, in order to disguise the facts.
Officialese provides some examples of
special techniques. One of these, which has
already been studied, consists of replacing
the greatest possible number of verbs and
adjectives by nouns, thereby manipulating
parole to avoid the head-on confrontation
with reality which the views of verbs would
convey. For example, in the shift from my
views are right to the rightness of my views,
there is a real transition from an assertion,
which might call forth criticism, to an impli¬
cit assumption, which purports to reflect
something already evident. The user of this
type of parole thereby not only sidesteps
explicit responsibility for a claim: he also
dodges any objections. For it is much less
easy for a listener to disagree with the un¬
finished sentence that begins: the rightness
of my views, than with a complete sentence:
my views are right.
With his "object poems", the Czech artist
Jirl Kolar seeks to make poetry "Imme¬
diately clear to everyone" and to fulfil his
prediction that "one day It will t)ecome
possible to make poetry out of anything at
all." As the materials of his art he uses
small objects such as razorblades, match¬
boxes, keys, and remnants of fabrics as If
they were the embodiment of words. In
collages such as The Apple (1967), atmve,
he Incorporates all thegraphic techniques
invented by man: fragments of ancient
manuscripts, letters, dictionaries, and va¬
rious forms of writing: Arabic, Hebraic,
Chinese, Persian, Gothic, Cyrillic, Latin
and Greek.
"The oral style is a literary genre in Its own
right. It is a cultural tradition which seems
to Justify the creation of a term, orature,
which would be symmetrical to that of
literature (...), In the sense that it preserves
the monuments of a culture but leaves no
material trace." (Claude Hagège,
L'Homme de Paroles/ Above, 40-cm-high
ceremonial carved axe of the Lelo people
of Zaire symbolizes thepower of language
and the spoken word. Lett, wooden stool
adorned with an ancestor-figure (height 76
cm) Is used by the latmui people of Papua-
New Guinea as a ceremonial chair during
debates atiout myths and genealogies.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
In some languages, words say expUcitly
that they confer power, whereas, in others,
that distinctive capacity of language to be a
secret power, and hence a power inevitably
attractive to dictatorships, usually reluctant
to be identified as such, is not expUcitly
stated. Náhuatl, the language of the Aztecs,
belonged to the former category: "He who
in Mexico City was caUed 'emperor' bore
the title tlatoani, 'he who speaks', from the
verb tlatoa, 'to speak'; the same root is to be
found in words connected with speech, such
as tlatolli, 'language', and in words con¬
nected vrith power, such as tlatocan, which
designates the supreme council, the place
where one speaks and from which authority
emanates. It is no accident that the
sovereign is known as tlatoani: at the root of
his power is the art of speaking, the palavers
in council, the skill and dignity of those
high-flown and colourful speeches so great¬
ly appreciated by the Aztecs". ^*^
So, whether by virtue of the pressure that
language exerts from birth on the mental
representations of the person who speaks it
in his natural environment, and whose
thought it fashions, or whether by virtue of
the use to which language-in-action can be
put, i.e.paro/e, for purposes ofdomination,
the powers of language are universally man¬
ifest. The human science which studies
them, linguistics, is necessarily also a study
of the innermost being of humanity. The
human race, which has brought nature
under its yoke, transforms biological data
by making a persevering and thorough
study of their properties and of ways of
acting on them.
The human race acts in the same way on
language. What about the machines with
which the computer revolution and studies
of artificial intelligence are lavishly sup¬
plying the market? WiU human beings find
in these no more than a pale reflection of
their inimitable abilities, or will they see
new masters coming to mle them, after the
fashion of the sorcerer's apprentice, victim
of his own inventions? Only time will tell.
But the Unguist who studies the power of
natural languages has a number of reasons
to beUeve that the power of artificial lan¬
guages is not something that will develop
overnight.
/. E. Sapir, "The Status of Linguistics oj a Science",
Language, 5, 1929. p. 209 (207-214)
2. B.L. Whorf, Language, Thought and Reality, New
York, The Technology Press, 1956.
3. E. Benveniste, "Catégories de Pensée et Catégories de
Langue", Les Etudes Philosophiques, 4, 1958, reprinted
in Problèmes de Linguistique Générale, Paris, Galli¬
mard, 1966, pp. 70-71 (63-74).
4. J. Gemet, Chine et Christianisme: Action et Réac¬
tion, Paris, Gallimard, "Bibliothèque des Histoires",
1982, pp. 326-327.
5. 1. Erdôdi, as reported by G. Barczi, A magyar nyelv
életrajza (Budapest 1975), Etudes Finno-ougriennes 12,
1976, p. 304 (304-307).
6. J. Soustelle, La Vie Quotidienne des Aztèques à la
Veille de la Conquête Espagnole, Paris, Hachette, 1955,
p. 114.
CLAUDE HAGEGE, French university teacher,
is director of studies at the Ecole Pratique des
Hautes Etudes and a member of the language
laboratory of the National Centre of Scientific
Research (CNRS). He is the author of 10 books
on language, the most recent of which is
L'Homme de Paroles (1986). His linguistic re¬
search has taken him from Africa to Oceania,
from Europe to the Arab worldand from China to
the Indian reserves of the United States.
Cheikh Anta Diop (1923 - 1986)
Professor Cheikh Anta Diop, who died in
Dakar on 7 February 1986, was an out¬
standingly versatile man of culture whose
name will always be associated with the
renaissance of African history. His works
revealed uncharted areas of the African
past and filled many gaps in our knowledge
of the evolution of humanity. Today it is no
longer possible to write a history of ancient
Egypt without referring to his work on the
origins of African and pharaonic civiliza¬
tions. A man of science and a man of
letters. Cheikh Anta Diop was anthropolog¬
ist and historian, physicist and Egyptolo¬
gist, linguist and philosopher. After working
for several years with the French physicist
Frédéric Joliot-Curie, he specialized in nuc¬
lear physics at the Collège de France. In the
human sciences, he was trained by two
eminent French scholars, the philosopher
Gaston Bachelard and the prehistorian
André Leroi-Gourhan. He submitted a
thesis at the Sorbonne on the comparative
study of the social systems of Europe and
black Africa from Antiquity to the formation
of modern States. Professor of Egyptology
at the University of Dakar, founder-director
of the Radiocarbon Laboratory at the Uni¬
versity's Institut Fondamentat d'Afrique
Noire (IFAN), Cheikh Anta Diop was one of
the most active members of the Internation¬
al Scientific Committee for the Drafting of a
General History of Africa. Sponsored by
Unesco, this major work in eight volumes,
some of which have already appeared, is
now in the final stages of preparation.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The Picasso Museum in Paris
The Picasso Museum in Paris, which opened its doors to the
public on 1 October 1985, contains Picasso's collection of works
by other artists and the major dation of "Picasso's Picassos"
which was made by his heirs to the French State in 1979. The
total amounts to some 230 paintings, 150 sculptures, 90 cera¬
mics, 1,500 drawings and 1,500 engravings. This outstanding
ensemble is housed in one of the finest historic buildings in the
Marais quarter of Paris, the Hôtel Aubert de Fontenay, com¬
monly known as the Hôtel Salé (built in 1659) which has been
specially restored and altered for the purpose. Below, a Unesco
Courier interview with Dominique Bozo, who played a leading
part in the creation of the Picasso Museum.
Courier: Can Picasso's personal collection
(whether of his own works which he kept for
himselfor of the works of other artists which
he acquired) offer the art enthusiast any
indications as to the line of direction taken
by the artist in his work?
Bozo: This is a difficult question to answer
inasmuch as a personal collection is not
necessarily intended to be either a guide to
an artist's work or the reflection of a con¬
frontation of ideas. What is remarkable in
Picasso's case is that he started to establish
his personal collection, by purchase or by
exchange with other artists, very early on,
from the beginning of the century. It has
therefore been possible to assemble in the
Museum works of others that he selected at
the same time that he was producing key
works of his own. Thus the paintings of
Henri Rousseau "Le Douanier", acquired
by Picasso around 1919 and 1920 at the time
when, after a foray into cubism, he was
returning to the classical style, are, in a way,
a recognition of the scope for figurative art
that derived from the cubist revolution.
Similarly, the thirty works by Cézanne,
even though they did not become part of the
collection at the time of the birth of cubism,
around 1907, are important to the under¬
standing of space and light in the work of
the great native of Aix-en-Provence, and,
indeed, of the cubist upheaval. The paint¬
ings of other fellow artists André Derain,
Georges Braque, Henri Matisse give rise
to encounters which enable us to assess the
directions being taken by Picasso in his
work.
Courier: Does the panorama presented by
the collection give any indications as to
Picasso's ability to encompass the
"universal" implications of art contact
with other cultures, continuity and rela¬
tionships with preceding artistic periods?
Bozo: From the beginning of the century up
until the start of the Second World War,
Picasso collected and hung in his studio
works of primitive art from Oceania and, in
particular, from Africa. The bulk of these
works are on display at the Picasso
Museum. What we learn from them is that
Picasso did not actually copy primitive art,
but that he found in the reasoning that lay
behind its creation, its colour and its style of
cubism, a kinship, an emotional affinity
which reinforced him in his own approach.
Picasso was also an observer of prehistoric
art, in particular Iberian prehistoric art, and
these works too can teach the art enthusiast
something about his creative development.
Primitive art, however, never encroached
upon Picasso's artistic or philosophical
autonomy.
Seen in this way, and in so far as it brings
together the testimony of other cultures and
the works of contemporaries who might be
considered as sources, the Picasso Museum
is a place in which we can learn about and
leam to understand an exceptional
personality.
One great achievement of the Museum is
to have brought together almost all Picas¬
so's preliminary studies, to have, as it were,
catalogued the archives of his thought.
Through this experimental laboratory of his
work (the testimony of other cultures, or
affinities with other artists), the Museum
has developed an extraordinary pedagogic¬
al tool which enables us to select themes or
subjects from Picasso's work and to show
The staircase of the Hôtel Salé, home of
the Picasso Museum In Paris. The chande¬
lier Is by Diego GiacomettL
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
their continuity and development, or the
deviations during a given period or
throughout his work as a whole. We know
that he always went further than he had
expected to go, that at times his creativity
deserted him and that he felt the need to
pause from time to time to consider what he
had achieved. This led him to acquire a
certain mastery over his thought, and this
re-ordering of his ideas took place by refer¬
ence to the works of the great masters who
had preceded him. Regularly in his work we
find paraphrases of the great universal
artists; and as a consequence of these con¬
frontations there is a very great sense of
Hberty in his work as compared to other
attitudes and methods that are fixed once
and for all. The other great achievement of
the Museum is that it also contains a collec¬
tion of major works and series of paintings
leading up to or developing from them.
Courier: Did wide-ranging considerations
such as those we have discussed influence the
organization of the Museum?
Bozo: The Museum was conceived with the
aim of showing that each of Picasso's works
stands alone and of highlighting the master¬
pieces, while at the same time demonstrat¬
ing the strength of the artistic renewal from
one period to another and the way in which
each period draws inspiration from the one
that has gone before. For example, a work
from the 1950s may be placed beside a work
dated 1919 to show the continuity in form or
theme. This gives the pubUc food for
thought. Similarly, sculpture and paintings
are juxtaposed, for Picasso turned to sculp¬
ture when a spatial problem arose in his
painting.
Courier: Is the current layout and presenta¬
tion of the Museum definitive?
Bozo: By no means. Our attitudes to
museums have changed since the
nineteenth century. Nowadays, the more
one is involved with a museum the more one
appreciates its wealth and the potential for
modification. The inner resources of the
works themselves are such that it should be
possible to present them in different com¬
binations. At the moment they are hung in
such a way as to show off the richness of the
collection, to make it easily accessible to the
public and to provide a harmonious contrast
with the seventeenth century building in
which it is housed.
Courier: Are there other museums in the
world conceived and established on the same
principles?
Bozo: There are several museums of this
kind in the world: the Rodin museum in
Paris, the Matisse museum at Nice, the Van
Gogh museum in Amsterdam and the
Edvard Munch museum in Oslo are just a
few examples. Almost all countries would
Hke their greatest national artist to have a
museum. This is fine if the artist in question
is of a high standard and if the country owns
the best or the largest collection of his or her
work. In this case it is less a matter of
creating a museum in the practical sense of
the term than of an artistic "space" close to
the place of creation. We are very fortunate
to have the Hôtel Salé as a setting for the
Picasso collection since this enables us to
demonstrate that twentieth-century art can
cohabit with and indeed be an extension of
the art of the seventeenth century. On the
great staircase, for example, Picasso's
in this part of the Picasso Museum are 5
sculptures from different periods of the
artist's life: ¡eft and foreground, two
bronze Heads of a Woman, 1931; right, the
famous Woman with a Baby Carriage
(bronze), 1950; in background, two cera¬
mics. Standing Flautist and Seated Flaut¬
ist Playing a Double Flute, both 1958.
monumental sculptures from the 1930s
mingle happily with the works of Flemish
sculptors who came to work in France dur¬
ing the seventeenth century. Furthermore,
during the 1930s and later, Picasso lived in
private town houses or country residences
very similar in style and atmosphere to that
of the Hôtel Salé and many of his works
were created in this kind of setting. Finally,
the fact that the furnishings are the work of
another artist (Diego Giacometti, the
brother of the sculptor Alberto Giacometti)
gives another dimension to the concept of
artistic encounter.
Courier: What lessons can be learned from
such a venture?
Bozo: Today members of the general public
are encouraged to go to museums, but they
often lack the necessary knowledge and the
means of informing themselves to benefit
fully from them. They often feel somewhat
lost even though fascinated. Twentieth-cen¬
tury art is something of a problem. There is
such a wide variety of seemingly contradic¬
tory trends, ranging from a continuation of
the classical tradition to the most severely
critical art of today, that it is easy to become
lost in the diversity of modern thought. The
Picasso Museum gives the general public an
introduction to twentieth-century art. Get¬
ting to know a particular artist is a good way
of acquiring an understanding of the cen¬
tury, especially when his work spans eighty
years of creative activity. In short, we are
concerned with the work of an artist who
was also a humanist; and his relationship
with the past, with art as part of our heritage
and of the historical process, gives the
Museum a universal character which is both
instructive and stimulating.
DOMINiQUE BOZO, of France, is directorof the
National Museum of Modem Art at the Georges
Pompidou Centre in Paris.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Matta
A new way of looking at the world
by Jean-Jacques Lebel
CULTURE has never been so much
discussed as it has since technocratic
societies have tried to get rid of it.
At major exhibitions in Paris, Milan, Mos¬
cow, Tokyo and New York, swarms of visi¬
tors file at top speed past ancient and mod¬
ern masterpieces on display. The success of
these exhibitions is not measured by the
rarity of the works displayed or by the
quality of the aesthetic pleasure they give,
but by the number of spectators they
attract.
The trend towards uniformity imposed by
the media and by cultural mass production
not only outlaws the works of a particular
artist, film-maker, writer, philosopher or
musician, but inhibits the very function of
culture and art as a means of expressing,
exploring and recording the world of the
imagination. The way is barred, not to mas-
terworks, superficial and furtive though our
perception of them may be, but to the im¬
aginative powers and the creative genius of
each one of us. Surely the total monopoliza¬
tion of communication technologies and the
media of creation for exclusively political or
commercial ends is having the crushing
effect, not only of controlling the behaviour
of ordinary citizens, but of preventing them
from seeing, feeling, imagining or desiring
anything except that which it is considered
appropriate for them to see, feel, imagine
or desire.
We may well wonder whether the in¬
creasingly harmful environment created by
the media will not bring about a retrogres¬
sion: in other words, the disappearance of
certain cultural activities that are regarded
as too subjective or too complex. Deserti¬
fication and the steady poisoning of the
environment have, as we know, resulted in
the extinction of many animal species. The
sole survivors are species which have
adapted by mutation to deleterious
changes. Does the same fate lie in store for
those artists, poets, philosophers, musi¬
cians and film-makers who refuse to adapt
to the equally harmful mediocrity and
money grubbing of the cultural industry?
These were the unanswered questions
raised by three recent exhibitions in Paris
which, simultaneously but from different
points of view, tested the ability of consum¬
ers to see anything but soap operas or pop
singers. These were the exhibitions of Rem¬
brandt's engravings at the Petit Palais, the
Bemard Saby retrospective at the Museum
of Modem Art of the city of Paris, and the
Matta retrospective at the Beaubourg Cen¬
tre. Three oases, three pockets of resistance
to cultural desertification.
Take Matta, for instance. Marcel
Duchamp said of him, as long ago as 1946,
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
k
Above, George and the Dragon, 1965. Wax
crayon and lead pencil on paper
(54.5x75.5 cm). Private collection, Paris.
Left, The Birth of Venus, 1965. Wax crayon
and leadpencil on paper (SO x 66 cm). Pri¬
vate collection, París.
that he was "the profoundest painter of his
generation", and yet he calls himself not a
painter but a seeker a seeker of himself
and of the Other. He is an archaeologist of
human desire and a reorganizer of ReaHty,
and has coined the term econography to
describe his work. Here we have one of the
most highly inventive minds to have ex¬
plored the problem of what it means to see.
For half a century, he has kept the social
and mental stmctures of the West perpe¬
tually shifting, and hence in danger of losing
their balance and finding, subsequently, a
new kind of balance. He is an architect who
started out working with Le Corbusier, but
whose Utopias have been built only in
mythical and Hnguistic space, transcending
the urban context in which the citizen of the
nuclear age is locked. He is an exceptional
person, a man who has crossed the Andes
and the Atlantic and travelled through sur-
reaHsm and communism; who was a friend
of Pablo Picasso, André Breton, Victor
Brauner, Max Ernst, Henri Michaux and
Salvador Allende; who studied with de
Sade, Marx and Lautréamont; who has
illustrated Cervantes, Shakespeare, Rim¬
baud and Jarry, and been acquainted with
Marat, Gramsci and Lao Zi; who was a
lover of Danaê, Penthesileia and the Scarlet
Empress, and dreamed of being Genghis
Khan, Leonardo de Vinci and Che
Guevara. Here is an artist who wanted to
paint what no one had painted before him:
the living being in the process of rethinking
the world and its place in the world. His was
one of the most important exhibitions to be
held in this last quarter of a century.
How can one "consume" this painting,
which defies market forces? What did the
endless crowds flowing through the
Beaubourg Centre find in this major re¬
trospective exhibition, by turns dazzling
and arcane? This polyglot Chilean nomad
clearly cannot be reduced to fit any school,
style or dogma he is neither abstract nor
figurative, neither an expressionist nor a
social realist, nor even wholly a surrealist
he refuses to align himself with a fixed idea
or specific doctrine. TTiis creates problems
for people who need an ideological "key" in
order to feel that they can appreciate a work
of art (thereby confusing art with a puzzle or
a locked door). Matta can be bewildering in
his playfulness and the youthful, quicksil¬
ver, changeable side of his nature. What he
offers us is an art of seeing.
"Potentiating space
space in Space
expanding space"
wrote Henri Michaux about Matta's paint¬
ing, which seizes on reaHty only in order to
transform it. Matta makes no secret of this.
Indeed he proclaims it: "Obviously! Art is
revolution".
JEAN-JACQUES LEBEL, French writer and
theatre and film director, is the author of several
books including La Poésie de la Beat Generation
(Poetry of the Beat Generation) 1965, Le Hap¬
pening, 1966 and L'Amour et l'Argent (Love and
Money), 1979.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Treasures of Mongolia
by Namsraïn Ser-Odjav
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Granite tortoise forms part of the remains
of Karakorum, the ancient capital of the
Mongol ruler Ogdal, son of Genghis Khan.
The ruins lie on the right bank of the Orhon
river at the foot of the Khangal mountains.
The tortoise once formed the base of a
stela engraved with ancient texts. Stones
on its back are offerings made in accord¬
ance with a still current tradition known as
obo In Mongolian.
The soyombo Ideogram (left) which fea¬
tures on the national flag of the Mongolian
People's Republic is regarded by Mongo¬
lians as their national emblem of liberty
and independence. Each sign takes its
meaning from ancient symbolism. For in¬
stance, the fire-sign situated above a sun
and a quarter moon (legendary father and
mother, respectively, of the Mongolian
people) here signifies: "May the Mongo¬
lian people always live and prosper!"
IN the late nineteenth century, the world
scientific community learned of an ex¬
traordinary archaeological discovery in
the valley of the upper Orhon Gol in Cen¬
tral Asia. Where this river emerges from
deep gorges and flows in a wide curve into
the plain, the ruins of a vast city had been
discovered, apparently watched over by a
giant stone tortoise, symbol of eternity.
This was the famous Karakorum, capital
of the Mongol Empire founded in the thir¬
teenth century by Genghis Khan. It was
situated on the right bank of the river, 400
kilometres south-west of Ulaanbaatar, the
present capital of Mongolia, in an area
which was suitable for both crops and live¬
stock and which possessed very old-estab¬
lished mining deposits, the Dalakyn-tal
an area which, indeed, had been the cradle
of many Central Asian civilizations. The
strange inscriptions found on the statues
and stone stelae discovered in the city were
later attributed to the "Blue Turks"; many
writings from the period between the sixth
and the eighth centuries describe this peo¬
ple's glory and its tragic destiny.
Karakorum was a settlement of several
thousand inhabitants. Its agriculture and
crafts were highly developed, trade
flourished, and it boasted a sophisticated
intellectual community. Its foundation has
been traced back to 1220, when Genghis
Khan's headquarters were transferred to
the banks of the Orhon Gol, probably near
Mount Melekhit, the "Tortoise Mountain".
On the heights which today overlook the
village of Kharkorim, one can see the im¬
posing granite tortoise which probably gave
the site its name.
AH around this stronghold, craftworkers'
and traders' quarters and other houses were
graudally built, until, by about 1230, the
area had taken on the appearance of a town.
Subsequently, in order to house the ad¬
ministration that was his gift to the Empire
and to receive ambassadors with all due
ceremony, the great Khan Ogödei, third
son of Genghis Khan, ordered major con¬
struction work to be carried out.
In the various foreign sources which men¬
tion it, the capital of Genghis Khan's im¬
mediate successors is described first as a
sort of mysterious reservoir from which
wave upon wave of savage conquering
hordes come pouring out; later it is seen as
the economic, political and cultural centre
of the united Mongol tribes in the thirteenth
century; and, ultimately, as an archaeolo¬
gical cemetery. But the real Karakorum was
quite different.
An envoy from King Louis IX of France,
the monk William of Rubrouck, who was
received in 1256 by Möngke Khan, has left
us a detailed description of the community.
Twelve different religions coexisted in
Karakorum, where mosques, Buddhist
monasteries and a Christian church clus¬
tered cheek by jowl. The earth rampart
which surrounded the city had four gates,
each with its own market.
The palace of Ogödei Khan was a master¬
piece of the architecture of the period. The
two-storey building contained a vast central
reception hall, supported by sixty-four col¬
umns and tastefully appointed; its walls
were adorned with paintings and the floor
was of green glazed tiles. All the roofs,
made of green and red tiles, had orna¬
mentation in relief. This love of ornament
and the inventive use of a few decorative
motifs, characteristic of the architecture of
the time, gave this palace a festive air.
The archaeological excavations carried
out in recent years in Karakorum add to the
written records on a number of points. The
palace and the other major constructions
were built of sun-dried bricks, some of
which still bear the trade-mark of the manu¬
facturer, and the houses could be warmed
by a system of underfloor heating. The aris¬
tocratic areas extended to north and south
along the Orhon river. The craftworkers'
and traders' quarters and the administrative
districts that have come to light have
yielded rich finds: fragments of porcelain
and glazed pottery, farming implements,
craftworkers' tools, cast iron hubs of
wheels, domestic utensils and all sorts of
ornaments in gold, silver and bronze. Coins
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
^^Ê
were particularly numerous, of both Mon¬
gol and foreign minting.
In 1380, Karakorum was destroyed. But
approximately two centuries later, on the
same site, there arose the yurt of Avtai
Khan, founder of the Erdeni Dzu Monas¬
tery. The great circular platform which
formed its base is still visible today.
The Erdeni Dzu architectural complex is
an outstanding example of Mongol
architecture, and its establishment by the
Khalkha Mongol chief Avtaï Khan can be
traced precisely to the year 1586. Its layout
was quadrangular, and in the seventeenth
century an unusual precinct was added,
consisting of 108 small buildings in the
shape of pagodas, the soubourgan. On each
of these is inscribed the name of the person
to whom it is dedicated. Erdeni Dzu con¬
tains other remarkable monuments, either
restored or under restoration, in particular
the Labrang, a palace, and three large tem¬
ples. These are set side by side on an earth
terrace raised for that purpose, and form a
harmonious whole, despite certain dissimi¬
larities: the temple in the centre has two
storeys, whereas those on either side have
only one, and each has a double pitched
roof.
The monastery of Erdeni Dzu is a focal
point in the history and culture of the Mon¬
gol people. Besides paintings, ornaments
and embroideries dating from the fifteenth
to the seventeenth centuries, it houses a
whole library of rare manuscripts and
wood-block printed editions. Here, too, are
preserved the works of the seventeenth-
century painter and sculptor Zanabazar,
great illustrator of the Buddhist canon and
one of the first Mongol artists to have
attained universal stature. In his day there
was an extraordinary flowering of the arts
and culture in Mongolia.
One of the most remarkable monuments
of the Orhon valley is the funerary complex
of the Turkish chiefs Köl and Bilge Kagan.
Besides the tombs, it contained tall com¬
memorative stelae with runic inscriptions
and a great many stone statues. More than
ten centuries ago, the roofs of the sacrificial
temple collapsed, and gradually the clay soil
formed a protective shell over the ruins. An
avenue lined with sculptures representing
princes and great army chiefs used to form
an approach to the temple from the east.
Apart from two grey marble statues, head¬
less but still virtually intact, this ceremonial
guard had been reduced to a shapeless mass
of mbble.
A section of marble jutting out of the
ground was the sole clue to the whereabouts
of the great stone tortoise. The stela erected
on its back was covered with ancient, angu¬
lar Turkish characters, inscribed in regular
Unes. More than two centuries of history of
the nomadic tribes of Central Asia were
contained in that narrow compass. These
CONTINUED PAGE 37
32
-^
statue of a warrior-guardian on the site of
a cemetery for Turkic chiefs (7th-8th cen¬
tury) In the Orhon valley. Stones In front of
the effigy of the valiant warrior are known
as ba\aba\ and Indicate the numlier ofene¬
mies he had vanquished.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The temple of Labrang (above) ¡s situated
In the vast precinct of the Erdenl-Dzu
monastery, a monument of major
architectural and cultural importance lo¬
cated some 400 km west of Ulaanbaatar,
the Mongolian capitaL The building is a
massive Tibetan-style edifice with a flat
roof, trapezoidal windows and walls
whose exterior face inclines slightly In¬
wards. Dating from 1780, it was the resi¬
dence of the Lama and a place of worship.
Stela, (left) which once stood on the back
of a sculpture of a tortoise at Karakorum,
Is carved with inscriptions in ancient Tur¬
kic letters which relate episodes from the
history of the nomad tribes of CentralAsia.
One passage declares: "Listen until the
end to what I say to you here, you who
come after me. O Turkic people! May the
Turkic people never perish, may they be a
people forever!"
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Since 1980 Unesco and the
Mongolian Government have
t>een carrying out restoration
work on the monastery of
Amartjayasgalam, which
stands 2,000 metres above
sea level, 300 km north of
Ulaanbaatar. The roofs are
being covered with varnished
tiles manufactured using the
same techniques as those
with which the original tiles
were made. The monastery
consists of some 30 buildings.
PtKJto © CorrtHlle Jest, Pans
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
The traditional dwelling of the Turkic and
Mongolian nomad herdsmen of central
Asia, the yurt is a collapsible circular tent
In which a wooden latticed structure Is
covered with felt. In thepast massive royal
yurts were transported from place to place
on ox-drawn platforms. In the 13th cen¬
tury, William of Rubrouck claimed to have
seen a yurt drawn by 22 oxen. Although
such great mobile dwellings have dis¬
appeared today, the yurt Itself (Rül In Tur¬
kish; gher In Mongolian) Is still a striking
feature of the Mongolian landscape.
Above, a 13th-century scene as depicted
by an artist In the 19th century.
Photo taken (rom Art de la Mongolie de l'Antiquité au Délxit du
20e Siècle by Niam Ossorine and Tsulten, Plastic Arts. Moscow,
1984
Photography, the memory of peoples
From 9 to 12 December 1985, some forty
specialists attended a meeting on still
photography held in Luxembourg (see
page 2). Most of the leading press agencies
from the Industrially developed countries
(AFP, Reuters, Tass, Keystone) and the
developing countries (PANA, XINHUA)
were represented at the meeting, the first
organized by Unesco in this field of creative
activity.
The participants recommended a num¬
ber of guidelines for Unesco's action in the
field of photography. They suggested that
Unesco sfwuld carry out studies on the
economic and socio-cultural Impact of
modern communication techniques, includ¬
ing photography and "visual writing", con¬
sidered as a new mode of expression. They
also proposed that Unesco contribute to the
publication of monographs relating to
photography, especially in the developing
countries. Finally they asked Unesco to
bring together users and manufacturers of
photographic equipment and to encourage
the manufacturers to produce robust, reli¬
able cameras adapted to conditions In
countries where the climate is unsuitable
for highly sophisticated equipment, as well
as durable photochemical and photo-
magnetic material.
The participants encouraged Unesco to
contribute to the creation of photo archives,
in which to preserve the memory of peo¬
ples. They also expressed the wish that a
meeting of specialists be held to bring the
copyright conventions up to date and to
Include in them the protection of photo¬
graphic images. Unesco was also invited to
support photography training programmes
in developing countries.
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
77ie 18th-century drawing below depicts
the entrance of thepalace of Karakorum as
It appeared In the 13th century, when It
was adorned with a magnificent silver tree
wrought by a French craftsman. In his
Travels In the Mongol Empire (1253-1255),
the monk William of Rubrouck, envoy of
the French King Louis IX to Möngke Khan,
left a detailed description of this extraor¬
dinary tree, "at the roots of which are 4
silver lions, each vomiting white mare's
milk. At the top, one of the four ducts pours
forth wine; another caracomos, clarified
mare's milk; another bal, a drink made
from honey; and another rice-beer. As a
receptacle for each drink a silver bowl is
placed at the foot of the tree. At the top of
tfie tree he has made an angel holding a
trumpet, and beneath the tree a vault
where a man can hide."
Photo taken horn Art de la Mongolie de l'Antiquité au OétMt du
20e Siècle by Niam Ossorine and Tsulten, Plastic Arts publishing
house, Moscow, 1964
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 32
tombs, then, are outstanding examples of
the art and culture of the Turks of the
Mongol steppe, but they are also an essen¬
tial Hnk in our knowledge of the past.
The sculpted stone warriors are power¬
fully original works of art. They are usually
represented in a traditional upright pose,
holding a chaUce in the right hand. Their
costumes, hairstyles, earrings and belts, de¬
corated with a variety of plaques, to which
their weapons are attached, are depicted
with great precision. The faces have slant¬
ing eyes set very close together, a long nose
and a small mouth with a moustache. But
the realism of this model is combined with
considerable imagination in the invention
of individual features. These statues stood
as silent witnesses to the ceremonies and
funeral rites which took place in the monu¬
ments raised in their honour, facing east. In
front of the statue of the valiant warrior was
set up a row of rough stones, balbals, which
indicated the number of enemies he had
killed.
In the Orhon valley there are also an
incalculable number of ancient rock draw¬
ings: animals, people, signs and decorative
patterns of various kinds. When we begin to
decipher these scriptures in stones, a whole
world starts once again to stir into life and
meaning. For a moment we feel the joy and
the fear aroused at night, before the fire, by
the sacred ceremonies. In the rock forma¬
tions of the steppe, worn away by wind and
rain, we see the faces of divinities or terrify¬
ing idols, emerging as they were seen or
imagined by the artists of old and by those
of their tribe.
Horses, the valiant steeds of the steppe,
were held in high esteem. They appear in
complex compositions, often with necks
outstretched, caught in full gallop. Some¬
times the horse is bestridden by a horse¬
man, drawing his bow or reaching out an
arm. The oven-hot air makes the drawings
shimmer and seems to give them a Hfe of
their own, adding to their evocative power.
The stag is another animal often portrayed.
It was apparently an object of worship and
an important factor in the economy of these
tribes.
This rapid survey of the Mongol cultural
heritage is necessarily incomplete. And the
Orhon valley undoubtedly still holds count¬
less hidden riches. Such a fine historical site
deserves a place among the treasures of the
world cultural heritage. For here, on the
banks of the Orhon, dwelt the people who,
for twenty centuries, set the course of his¬
tory not only in Central Asia but in Asia
Minor and Western Europe by mapping out
this vast area where flourished what is
commonly known as the "Empire of the
Steppe".
NAMSRAÏN SER-ODJAV is head of the ar¬
chaeology department at the Institute of History
of the Academy of Sciences of the Mongolian
People's Republic, a member of the Permanent
Council of the International Union of Prehistoric
andProtohistoric Sciences, andprincipalscienti¬
fic adviser to the Mongolian National Commis¬
sion for the Study of Central Asian Civilizations.
He has participated in a collective work on the
history of the cultures of Central Asia currently
being prepared by Unesco.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
1986: Year of Peace / 3
Messages from young people
TD encourage young people to reflect on
"the maintenance and strengthening of
peace", Unesco recently asked its
National Commissions to send in essays on
this theme written by young people tietween
the ages of fifteen and twenty-four.
Forty-four young people from all over the
world responded with messages expressing
their desire for peace and their awareness of
the fragility of peace. They unanimously con¬
demn the arms race, considering that the
money swallowed up in amis spending should
be devoted to the development of the poorer
nations, and that peace Is inconceivable as
long as hunger, poverty and sickness prevail
in many parts of the world in short, that
peace is inseparable from development and
justice. They believe that armed conflicts
mainly originate in Ideological and political
intolerance, racism and social inequality.
They all see the conflict between generations
as a form of social Injustice, especially in a
period of economic crisis. Misunderstood by
older generations, young people, they say,
often feel they are outsiders!
Most of the young people advocate the
same road to peace. In politics, they consider
that solutions to disputes should always be
negotiated, and describe the United Nations
as the only international body capable of en¬
suring peace. Many of them feel that the
family should instil the values of peace in
young people from a very early age. They
deplore literature and mass media program¬
mes that encourage violence for its own sake,
and render human suffering commonplace.
Most of them consider fraternity and generos¬
ity to be the fundamental values and maintain
that the latter will only become a living force
when they are professed by each Individual.
For them, everything begins with the indi¬
vidual. Hence the decisive role of family unity,
the keystone of a peace that will extend to join
communities and nations.
Below, extracts from some of the letters:
m)
"1 should like to be part of an organization of
children between the ages of ten and thirteen
which would try to influence and convince
younger children that war is a bad thing for all
mankind."
Branimir Majcica (Yugoslavia)
"War does not necessarily mean bombing.
Today certain dictatorships use torture or
psychological terror. Thus people do not die
from bullets, but from malnutrition or pneumo¬
nia, or If the machine of State Is strong and
allows it, by 'suicide'. It is difficult to challenge
this, because only falling bombs can be
seen."
Christine Kasper (Austria)
"¡When elephants fight, the grass suffers.'
The struggle for military superiority between
the super-powers has hit the Third World
countries hardest."
Basanta Raj Sharma (Nepal)
"In the developing countries there Is only one
doctor for every 3,700 people, but the figure
for army personnel is one for every 250."
A.R.M. Saifuddin Ekram (Bangladesh)
"When I ask a child who has not yet reached
the age of five 'What does peace mean?' he
replies, 'I don't know'.' If I ask him what war
means, he says: 'People fighting, that Is
dying'. The child knows much about war, but
nothing about peace."
Issam All Abdel Rahman (Egypt)
"Holding out a bunch of flowers the little- girt
said with a smile: 'Buy flowers, sir. Flowers
are the messengers of the heart.' 'I do not
want to buy,' he said. 'I would like to ask you a
question. Do you think selling flowers is
appropriate in the present circumstances?
Thousands of people are dying. Innocent peo¬
ple are being swept away. They are darkening
children's eyes. And you? You sell flowers!" In
a sad voice she said, 'You are not the only one
who is surprised about this.... All the flowers in
the world would not be enough to decorate the
graves of those of whom you speak with such
pity. The dew on the flowers reminds me of the
tears of my young brother who lay in the dark
sucking my mother's breast smeared with
bjood. I know why I sell flowers. Their beauty
Is the beauty of life. But it seems that you have
not yet understood their message..."
. . Gadàh AI Qudsi (Jordan)
"Mothers, when you give birth, say 'Peace'!"
Alejandro Angel Puja Campos (Chile)
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Oftice :
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris,
Subscription rates
1 year: 78 French francs 2 years (valid only in France):
144 French francs Binder tor a years issues : 56 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly
IndividuaJ articles ar^cj photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credil line reads "Reprinted tram Itie
LHtESCO COURIER . pJus date ot issue, and three veuoher
copies are sent to Iha editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear
author s name. Non-cdpynght photos will be supplied on request.
Unsoliclled manu&onple cannot be returned unless accorrvpanied
by an inlemallonal reply coupon covering postage. Signed arti¬
cles express the opinions ot ihe authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of UMESCO or those of tt>e editors ot the
UNESCO COURIER Photo capitions and headlines are written
by the Unesco Courler steft. The twundarieson maps published
in the magazine do not Imply official endorsement or acceptance
by Unesco or the United Nations. The Unesco Couner is pro¬
duced in mlcrotorm {microtllm and^or microfiche) by : Unesco. 7
Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Pans: Í2I Unlversl^ Microfilms
(Xeroi), Ann Arbor, (iiichigan J8100. U.S.A.: [30 N.C.Fl. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head. Inc.. 1 1 1 West 40th Street. New Yorl^.
U.S.A.: (4) Bell and Howell Co.. did Mansfield Road. Wooster.
Ohio «691, USA.
Editorial staff (Paris)
Assistant EdHor-ln-chlal : Olga Rudel
Managing Editor : Gillian Whitcon^b
Editors :
Engiisfi :
Rqy Malidn
Frer>cfi : AJain Lévêquo
Neda el Khazen
Spanish : Francisco Famandez-Sanlos
Jorge Enrique Adounr)
Russian : Niiioiai Kuznelsov
Arabic : Abdeirashid Eisadek Uahmcudi
Braille : Frederick Potter
: Christiane eoucfier
iliustrattonft : Ariane Bailey
Ijyaul and Doilgn : Georges Servait
Promolion : Fernando Ainsa
Special projects : Peggy Julien
All corTsspondOfKa should be addressed to tie BOttor-irt-
Cttiel in Paris
Non-Headquarters editions
German : Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japar>ese : Selichiro Kcjima (Tokyoj
Italian : Mario GuidottI (Rome)
Hindi : Rajmani Tlwari {Delhi}
Tamil : M. Moftan^meö Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew : Alexander Broido (Tel Aviv)
Persian :
Dutch : Paul Mcrren (Antwerp)
Portuguese : Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turffish : Meira tlgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu : Hakim Marianrmed Said (Karachi)
Catalan : Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian : Azizah Hamiari (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean . Paik SyeungGil (Seoul)
Swatiili : Domino Rutayebesibwah (Oar-es-Saiam)
Ctoato-Serb. Macedonian. Serbo-Croat. Stovene :
Boîidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Cliinese Stien Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgariari : Goran Gctev (Sofia)
Greek : Nicolas Papageorg iou (Athens)
Sinhala : S J Sumanasekera Banda (Colomt»)
Finnish . Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish : inger Raaby (Stockholm)
Basque : Gurutz l^rrañaga (San Sebastie(n| .
Thai : Savitfi Suwansathit (Bangkok) '''"'
38 IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France) - Dépôt légal : C 1 - Mars 1986
PHOTOCOMPOSITION : Ateliers de lUNESCO - PHOTOGRAVURE-IMPRESSION : MAURY-IMPRIMEUR S.A.. Z.l. route d'Étampes, 45330 MALESHERBES.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
otvt\^emove
\Jnesco
;c an attempt
VVo-.To^^t^^^^^^^^^
societies, n fe ^^^^ ^ dw ^^^
betvieeti tn Viouseno o-
^-^nte broaden tS areas-.
tViatattt^e çg ^Tintertia-
t^^^^^'fn internal ^fpaUetns-,
bo^^^ ^nthe\abou^í°'^^pnotities
^'^'^omen'siss^^^f
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTTtAUA. Hunier Publications. &8a Gipps St. Colling<«ood, Vtctona 3066;
Publications : Educahonal Supplies Pty. Ltd., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100,
NSW; Penodtcals : Domime Pty. Subscnptions Depl, P O. Box 33, Brookvale
2100, NSW. Sub-agenI : Unried Nations Assoaalion of Australia, P.O. Box
17S, 5tti floor. Ana House, 28 Elizabetti St., Melbourne. Victoria 3000.
AUSTDIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31. A-1011, Vienna.
BAHAMAS. Nassau Stationers Ltd., P.O. Box N-3138, Nassau. BAHRAIN.
The Arabian Agencies and Distributing Co., AI Mulanabi St., P O. Box 156,
Manama BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books Intemabonal Ltd.. ttteraq Build¬
ing, 1 . R K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola. Dacca 3. BARBADOS. University of Itie
Wast Indies Bookshop, Cave Hill Campus, P.O. Box 64, Bndgetown.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Couner" Dutch edition only : N V. Handeimaatschappi
Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deume-Anlwerp>en. French edition arx)
general Unesco publications agent : Jean de Lannoy, 202 Ave. du Roi, 1060
Brussels, CCP 000-0070823-13. BOTSWANA. Botswana Book Centre. P.O.
Box 91 , Gaborone. BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, S50-552 Merchant
Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Rerwut Publishing Co. Ltd.. 2182 St. Cattienne
St West, Montreal. Oué. H3H 1 M7. CHINA. China National Publications
Import arx) Export Corporation, PO. Box 88. Beijing. CYPRUS. 'MAM",
Archbishop Makanos 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S NTL, Spalena 51-1 13 02, Prague 1; Ve Smeckach
30. P.OB. 790-1 1 1-27 Prague 1 (Permzuient di5play);Zahrantcni literatura, 1 1
SoukerwAa. Prague 1. For Stovakiaonty : Alfa Verlag. -Publishers, Hurtianovo
nam. 6.893 31 Bralislava-CSSR. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export-OG, Tids-
skriftservica, 35 Norre Sogade. DK-1970 Kobenhavn K. EGYPT (ARAB
REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Hart>
St. Cairo. ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis
Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kiqakauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100 Hel-
sinkj 1 0: Suomalainen Kinakauppa Oy, Koivuvaarankuia 2. Ot 640 Vantaa 64.
FRANCE. Utxaine de I'Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Pans. CCP
12598-48. GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REPUBLKÏ. Buchhaus Leipzig. Post¬
fach 140, 710 Leipzig, or from IntematKXialen Buchhandlungen in the G DR.
FEO. REP. OF GERMANY. For ttie Unesco Couner (German, English. French
and Spanish ediborts) : Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb.
BasaJtstrasse 57,05300 Bonn 3 GHANA. Presbylenan Bookshop Depot Ltd..
P O. Box 195. Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O Box 7869. Accra; The
Universily Bookstwp of Ghana. Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape
Coast: The University Bookshop of Legón. P.O. Box 1, Legón. GREAT
BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. HONG KONG. Federal Publications (HK)
Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat St. Aberdeen. Swindon
Book Co., 13-15, Lock Rd..Kowloon.Hor>gKor>g Govt Irrformabon Services,
Publication Centre. Baskerville House. 22 Ice St. HUNGARY. Kultura-
Bushvnport-ABT. P.OB. 149-H-1389. Budapest 62. ICELAND. SnaebiOm
Jortsson ana Co., H.F. Hafrtarstraeti 9, Ftey^avik. INDIA. Onent Longman
Ltd., Kamani Marg. Ballard Estate. Bombay 400038; 17 Chitaranian Ave.,
Calcutta 13: 36a, Anna Salai. Mount Road, Madras 2; 5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh,
Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahalma Gandhi Rd., Bangalore 560001;
3-5-B20 Hyderguda. Hyderabad-SOOOOI. Sub-depots : Oxford Book and Sta¬
tionery Co., 17 Park St, Calcutta 70016, Scirxlia House, New Delhi; Publica-
bon urn. Ministry of Education and Culture. Ex AFO Hutments. Dr. Rajendra
Prasad Rd., New Delhi. 110001. INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Book¬
sellers, 29 Jl. Oto IskarKlardtnala 111, Jakarta; IrxJira P.T., Jl Dr. Sam
Ratulangie 37, Jakarta Pusat IRAfL Kharazmie Publishing and Distnbution
Co., 28 Vess^ Shirazi St., Enghélab Ave.. P.O. Box 314/1486, Teheran;
Iranian Nat Comm. for Unesco, 1 186 Englab Ave.. Roslam Give Building. Zip
Code 13158, P.O. Box 1 1365-4498. Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzie s Bookshop,
AI Rashid St, Bagtidad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd.,
Ballymouni Rd., Walkinstovm. Dublin 12. ISRAEL ABC. Bookstore Ltd.,
P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Rd., Tel Aviv 61000. ITALY. Ucosa (Ubrena
Commissionana Sar^soni, S.p A.), Via Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552.
50121 Florence. JAMAICA. Sangster's Bookstores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101
Waler Lane. Kingston; University of the West Indies Bookshop, Mona. Kings-
ton. JAPAN. Eastern Book Sennca Inc., 37-3 Hongo 3-chome Bunkyo-ku.
Tokyo 113. KENYA. East Afncan Publishing House, P.O. Box 30571, Nairobi:
Africa Book Services Ltd.. Curan House, Mfangano St., P.O. Box 45245,
Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission tor Unesco, P.O. Box Central
64.Seoul KUWATT.The Kuwait BookshopCo., Ltd. POB2942.Kuwait;for the
Unesco Couner : Farafalla Press Agency. P.O. Box SAFA 4541, Kuwait.
LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho. Southern Atnca.
LIBERIA. Code and Yancy Bookshops Ltd.. P.O. Box 2Ô6, Monrovia.
UEOfTENSTEJN. Eurocan Tmst Reg. P.OB. 5-9494 Schaan. UBYAN
ARAB JAMAMRIYA. Agency for Development of Publication and Distnbu¬
tion, P.O. Box 34-35. Tnpoli. LUXEMBOURG. Ubrairie Paul Brück. 22,
Grarxle-Rue. LuxemtMurg. MALAWI Malawi Book Service, Head Office, P.O.
Box 30044 Chichiri. Blantyre 3. MALAYSUL University ot Malaya Co-opera¬
tive Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur 22-11. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic St,
Valletta. MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd.. 30 Bourbon St. Port-Louis.
UOt4ACO. British Ubrary. 30 Bd. des Moulins, Morne Carlo. NEPAL. Sajha
Prakashan Pok:howk, Kathmandu. NETHERLANDS. Keesing Boeken B.V.,
Joan Muyskenweg. 22, Postbus 1118, 1000 BC Amsterdam.
NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V.. P.O. Box 200, Willem-
slad. Curaçao. N.A. NEW ZEALAND. Government Publishing P.O. Box
14277-Kilbimie, Wenington; 130, Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Chnst-
church; Aima St, P.O. Box 857. Hamilton; Pnnces St, P.O. Box 1104,
Dunedin. NIGERIA. The University Bookstwp ot Ite; The University Booksftop
of Ibadan, P.O. 286; The Universrty Bookshop of Nsukka: The University
Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of Zana.
NORWAY. Johan Gnjndt Tanum. P.O B. 1 1 77 Sentrurn - Oslo 1 , Narvesen
A/S; Subscnption and Trade Book Service, P O B. 6125 Etterstad, Oslo 6;
Universitets Bokhandelen. Universitetssenlret, Posttxiks 307 Blir>dem, Oslo
3 PAKISTAN. Mir7a Book Agency. 65 Shahrah Ouaid-i-azam, P.O. Box No.
729, Lahore 3; Unesco Publications Centre, Regional Office for Book De-
vek>pmerti m Asia and the Pacific. 39 Delhi Housing Society. P O. Box 8950.
Karactv 29. PHILIPPINES. National Book Store, Inc., 701 , Rizal Ave., Manila
D-404. POLAND. Orpan-lmport. Palac Kuttury I Nauki. Warsaw; Ars Polona-
Ruch. Krakowskie Przedmiescie No 7. 00-066 Warsaw PORTUGAL Dias &
Andrade Ltda. Uvrana PonugaJ, rua do Carmo 70. Lisbon. SEYCHELLES.
National Bookshop, P.O Box 48. Mahé, New Sen/ice Ltd., Kingsgate House,
P.O. Box 131. Mahé. SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Niala University and
Siena Leone Diocesan Bookshops. Freetown. SINGAPORE. Federal Pub-
bcations (S) Pte Ltd. Times Jurong. 2 Jurong Port Rd.. Singapore 2261.
SOMAU DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modem Bookshop and General. P O.
Box 951, Mogadiscio. SOUTH AFRICA. For the Unesco Courier (single
copies) only : Central News Agency. P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg. SRI
LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata,
POa 244, Cotombo 2. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop. PO. Box 1118,
Khartoum. SWEDEN. All publk^tions A/B.C.E. Fntzes Kungel, Hovbokhan-
del, Regenngsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16. f^x the Unesco
Couner : Svenska FN Fôrtiundet Skoigrand 2, Box 150 50 S-104, 65 Stock¬
holm; WennergrervWilliams. Box 30004-S-104. 25 Stockholm; EsseFte Tids-
knftscentralen. Gamla Brogatan 26. Box 62 - 101 20 Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. All publications : Europa Verlag. 5 Râmistrasse, Zúnch;
Libraine Payot Hue Grenus 6, 1211. Geneva 11, C C.P. 12-236: Ubrames
Payot also in Laus»ir>e, Basle. Berne, Vevey, Montreux, Neuchätel and
Zünch. TANZANIA. Dar-es- Salaam Bookshop, P.O B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam.
THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Kiung Road. Siyaeg Phaya
Sri. P.O. Box 402, Bangkok; Suksapan Panrt, MansKïn 9. Rajdamnem Ave..
Bangkok: Suksrt Siam Company. 1715 Rama IV Road. Bangkok. TRINIDAD
AND TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 1 8 Alexandra St., St Clair,
Trinidad W 1. TURKEY. Haset Kriapevi A.S., Istikläl Caddesi, No 469, Posta
Kutusu 219. Beyoglu. Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop. P.O. Box 7145.
Karrpala. UNITED KINGDOM. H M. Stationery Otiice. KM 5 O.. P O. Box
276, London 5W8 5DT, and Govt Bookshops in London. Edinburgh. Belfast
Manchester, Birmingham. Bristol, for scientific maps only iMcCarta Ltd.. 122
King's Cross Rd., London WC1X 9DS. UNITED STATES. Unipub, 205 East
42nd St, f^ew Yortt. N Y. 1001 7. Orders for books and penodicals : P.O. Box
1 222, Ann Arbor, Ml 481 06 USSR. V/O Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga. Ul. Dimitro-
va 39, Moskva 1 13095. YEMEN. 14th October Corporation, P O. Box 4227,
Aden. YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost Hica 30/11. Zagreb; Car^arjeva Zaiozba,
ZopAaneva 2. Lubfana; Nolit Teraz^e 27/11, Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educatkxial Distribution Ca of Zambia Ltd., P.O. Box 2664 Lusaka.
ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union Ave., Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO
i (
ám
jÊ^m
'Á,
u¡
^
)
i¿^
í««v
THE WORLD HERITAGE
MEMORY OF MANKIND
]]>
</page>
</document>
