<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="068976eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
Hess, iqo P\
K M
W/NDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
N° 3-4
1955
(8th year)
Price : I - (U. K.)
SO francs (France)
68 PAGES
PUPPETS
Magic world in miniature
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
I CAN HARDLY SEE I Some thirty miles
from Cairo, Unesco has created a Fun¬
damental Education Centre for the Arab
world. jHere, teachers are learning to
meet problems of education, health,
farming and vocational training await¬
ing thenWn their home countries. Photo
sbows boy victim of trachoma, the
crippling eye disease, one of health
problems dealt with at Sirs el Layyan.
In Egypt ajane trachoma afflicts about
half the (Aviation. (See page 4.)
**tr
S
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
* UNESCO Courier
À WIHfiOW OMN OM THE WOULD
Unesco Courier. Nr 3.4. _ 1955
Number 3-4 1955
8th YEAR
PAGE
CONTENTS
Puppets Magic World in Miniature
3 EDITORIAL
27 HOW DO THEY GET AWAY WITH IT?
By Maurice Kurtz
28 'SHAKES V. SHAV
Battle of the centuries
By James Douglas
30 CREFALITO
Unesco's most popular teacher
By Gabriel Anzola Gomez
33 INDIAN CAVALCADE
By T. S. Satyan
37 PUPPETS OF THE FAR EAST (BURMA, JAPAN,
INDONESIA)
By Rosnan Dhunjibhoy
43 PETROUCHKA 1955
44 MY NAME IS MR. PUNCH
By Geneviève Sigisbert
48 TURKEY'S STONEMASON KARAGÖZ
50 STRANGE ECHOES FROM THE PUPPET WORLD
56 PUPPETS, SOURCE OF LITERARY INSPIRATION
By Jacques Chesnais
58 TEATRO DEI PICCOLI
60 CZECH TALES FROM THE PAST
Other Articles and Features
4 SIRS-EL-LAYYAN
Face to face with an Arab village
By Georges Fradier
11 A GHOST VILLAGE COMES TO LIFE
12 WEATHER VANE FOR CHILDREN'S BOOKS
By Brigitte Gnauck
15 THE CASE OF THE FOUR-HANDLED JARS
By Darsie Gillie
18 GOOD HEALTH-A WORLD THREAT?
By Jean Manevy
25 WATER, WATER EVERYWHERE
Facts and figures
64 UNESCO IN PICTURES
66 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Published monthly by
The Department of Mass Communication of the United Nations
Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, I 9, Avenue Kleber, Paris I 6, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Circulation Manager
Jean Groffier
U.S.A. : Henry Evans
Individual articles noc cop/righted may be repnnced from THE COURIER but
must be accompanied by the following credit line: "Reprinted from UNESCO
COURIER". Signed articles reprinted must carry the author's name. .
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied by an inter¬
national reply coupon covering postage.
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of THE COURIER.
Annual subscription rates of THE COURIER : 6/-; t 1.50 or 300 French 1rs
or equivalent (U.S. edition $ 2.50)
MC 5S.I 90. A
There seems to be an unfortunate prejudice today that
puppet shows are merely a form of entertainment for
children. While it is true that children and youngsters
make an ideal audience since they are more apt to accept
fantasies as perfectly natural, the scope of the puppet is
much wider. What a pity to want to limit it to juvenile
entertainment.
The puppet theatre is of universal appeal and can offer
rich nourishment to people of all ages, to the ordinary citizen
as well as to the highly cultivated. In the Far East, puppetry
has for many hundreds of years been considered on a par
with the highest forms of theatrical art. In the past quarter
of a century a great puppetry revival has been taking place
in Western Europe and in North and South America.
Professional showmen are today touring their own and
foreign countries with fully equipped theatres in which
serious, full-length adult dramas are staged, sometimes with
many hundreds of puppets.
In ever-increasing numbers adults are coming to recognize
the puppet theatre's unique quality as a versatile form of art
and entertainment. The moving figures often transcend
human actors. They can be shaped to play any role. They
can be realistic, expressionistic, fantastic or satirical. They
can present classical drama, ballet, comedy or farce. They
are being used in hospitals as a form of therapeutic
treatment for children and adults. They are an excellent
drawing-card in shop windows and for advertisements
generally. And they have found new, sparkling roles in the
cinema and in television. Their possibilities are as vast as
they themselves may be small. Puppet shows exist today for
almost every occasion and every type of audience.
Perhaps the most recent development of puppetry has been
its widespread adoption by schools in many countries as a
handicrait subject. Teachers who have pulled strings or
manipulated fists and fingers realize the power of puppetry
in freeing the student from self-consciousness and physical
limitations, and in releasing untapped depths of emotion and
imagination. Puppetry is a unifying factor in the school
curriculum. Through it. pupils gain both in their social
relationships and in knowledge and skills. Making a puppet
and building a puppet theatre develops skill in drawing,
cutting, carving, modelling, embroidering, and painting.
Staging a puppet play develops imagination and writing
ability and is excellent training for the eye and the ear.
At the university level puppets can be used to present plays
which cannot be performed as successfully by human actors.
For experiments where the real stage is too expensive or
unwieldy, the puppet theatre is usually ideal. Scenes acted
out on a stage are much more forceful than if read from a
book. Puppets have been used in foreign language courses,
in history classes and for improvising current social and
political events.
Unesco is today using the puppet theatre at its two
fundamental education centres in Mexico and Egypt as well
as in Thailand to dramatize the advantages of reading'and
writing, oí brushing one's teeth and keeping clean. Where
other educational methods have failed, the puppet has often
succeeded in getting results. Jules Romains foresaw the
versatility of puppets when he wrote: "The day puppets
resume their proper place among us, those people who dis¬
missed them will be amazed to see how much they are really
capable of doing."
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
THESE ARE THE EGYPTIAN FELLAHINA WORD THAT TO THE WORLD SUGGESTS HUMILITY AND POVERTY, BUT IN FACT MEANS SIMPLY " FARMERS
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 3-4. 1955
by Georges Fradier
Here, the earth has no respite. No sooner is the harvest
gathered than the fields are ploughed and, at the same
time, sown; year in year out, each acre yields cereals,
then fodder, and then cotton. It is the land where the fields
are ever green the Nile delta, which for 5,000 years has
produced the finest crops in the world.
Nor have the peasants any easier lot. Regularly, at the
appointed hour, they must irrigate the fields : the water
must be pumped, directed into a complex network of cuts,
and distributed; every inch of ground must be flooded for
just the necessary length of time; the channels must be filled
up and then opened again. The men never part from their
fas, the proverbial hoe so often depicted by
the Pharaonic painters in their frescoes ;
it is an all-purpose tool, almost the only
tool they have.
All day long they dig, weed, cart compost,
clean the canals and, waist-deep in water,
work the Archimedean screws, or toil at the
ancient swing-plough which has no wheel
or mould-board, or work on their knees in
the rich mud that they seem almost to be
modelling into a fetish. Men of the earth
indeed, they are wedded to the soil. They
are the fellahin a word that to the world
suggests humility and poverty, but in fact
means simply "farmers".
The women, too, work in the fields ; they
look after the poultry, cows and black
water-buffaloes ; they mould the slabs of
cow-dung, the only form of fuel ; they go
to market to sell eggs, fowls and vegetables,
all packed into big bundles that they carry
on their heads ; and as travellers say, they
walk like goddesses, head erect, until they
die. They prepare the evening meal and
make bread, but cooking is the least of their
burdens. The children, boys and girls
alike, also have their set tasks ; at the age
of 10 they are already experienced workers.
Little importance is attached to villages
and houses. Land is far too dear for the
people to be able to build comfortably on it. Only the mosque
and the church are relatively spacious. The little dried-mud
houses, huddled together, have two or three dark rooms
shared by people and animals alike. They are furnished with
a marriage chest, a few bowls, and perhaps a mat or two
nothing more. In winter, the occupants sleep on the clay
stove.
In this province, known as Menufia, there are more than
740 inhabitants to the square kilometre. The town of Menuf,
45 miles distant from Cairo, has over 60,000 inhabitants, but
is smaller than the Park of Versailles. "Little villages" here
may have five or ten thousand inhabitants ; the fellahin do
not take up much space.
From a distance these villages are a beautiful sight, nestling
on the banks of a canal or pool, or in the fields under giant
palms and eucalyptuses. The little houses, too, which line
the smelly, unbearably dusty alley-ways, are often pleasingly
built ; and some visitors admire the rough frescoes re
presenting a train, the sea, a steamer, or famous monuments
which pilgrims returning from Jerusalem or Mecca paint
on the front of their homes. Many of these houses are
indeed more attractive than the square cement buildings of
the capital ; yet the visitor wonders now anyone could
possibly live in them.
The fact remains that people do liveand die in these
dwellings with their mud floors. For the fellahin, the earth
is never dirty it is the earth. Likewise, for them, the water
is never impure ; it is the sacred, life-giving water of the
Nile ; if it were too clean and too well-filtered, many people
would think it lifeless and useless.
But life is perhaps not long in these
surroundings ; few old folk are about in the
villages ; that toothless, wrinkled, spent
old woman in the street may not have seen
60. All the same, the fellahin are rightly
renowned for their strength and toughness,
their muscular arms and broad shoulders
as are the girls for their supple sturdiness.
There has been no degeneration in the race,
it is said, since the epoch of the Pyramids.
It might be said that their faces, too, are
still as handsome ; but trachoma has too
often overlaid their deep-set brown or black
eyes with a whitish stain, or the eyelids are
covered with pus. Whether of native stock
or Arab origin, the Egyptians have always
lived frugally ; but today they are stalked
by hunger. Of all the crops they grow
they only keep some wheat or maize for
making bread, some beans for making soup,
and a few vegetables to eat raw. They
work the same soil as their forbears, with
the same tools, though their crops are worth
more because of the cotton thousands of
acres, cared for like "gardens". But land
seems harder and harder to come by.
For this is the vital fact : Seven or eight
million men are working on the land in
Egypt, and at least three million of them
own the land they work. But most of them
own less than a feddan (some one and a quarter acres), while
the country's population has doubled in 40 years, the area of
land under cultivation has only increased by one quarter.
These tireless workers, these sturdy fellahin, are all sick
men. Ninety-two per cent of them suffer from bilharziasis',
a disease caused by a microscopic worm which is peculiar to
swampy land or irrigation channels. The worm breeds in
the snails which abound in the irrigation cuts where men
work, children bathe and women draw drinking-water. It
penetrates the skin of human beings and circulates through
the body, lodging in the intestines or bladder and eating
them away. A vicious circle is set up : the infection leaves
the body with the excrement, which goes into the irrigation
canals, where the snails are waiting. And so on. Ninety-
two per cent !
And besides endemic diseases there are other scourges. Of
cholera there have been only sporadic outbursts since the
1948 epidemic, but the threat is ever present. Malaria seems
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Fellahin : 'nothing good
comes from city folk'
Feluccas on the Nile
The Great Nile3,900 miles long from Lake
Victoria to the Mediterraneanis Egypt's
commercial highway and its source of life.
The yearly flood of the Nile has for centuries
been the secret of Egypt's fertility. The heavy
April rains in the basin of the White Nile in
Central Africa start the first flood and the May
rains in Ethiopia give the real flood of rlcn
muddy water that fertilizes as well as Irrigates.
The great dam at Aswan stores up the surplus
flood and releases It later on, to water the Nile
Valley all the year round. (Unesco photos)
now to be under control, as a result of the introduction of
DDT as a prophylactic. (The last epidemic, in 1946, is
thought to have cost a million lives.) Tuberculosis, however,
is rife ; the Ministry of Health records 55,000 deaths from it
every year, which means that some 500,000 people must be
suffering from the disease, in its active or arrested form, and
that the annual death-rate from it is about 200 per 100,000
inhabitants. In France the corresponding figure is 42, in
Denmark eight.
It should be added that in Egypt, as in many Middle
Eastern countries, infantile mortality amounts to over 65
per cent in the first five years. Trachoma afflicts about half
the population, or even more, for the primary stage often
escapes diagnosis. Sufferers will not consult the doctor for
"mere conjunctivitis".
But when such economic conditions are combined with lack
of hygiene and over-population, it is not easy to find solutions
which go to the root of the trouble. We cannot in this
instance say "the Government need only do so and so" ;
Egypt's official social services are exemplary in their scope
and good sense.
But what can in fact be done, not to bring about miraculous
reforms, but simply to help these people to lead lives that are
less hard and less narrow? And, after that, how can they be
brought to share in the economic, technical, political and
cultural exchanges which are the currency of modern civili¬
zation? How can we turn this inarticulate people into a
body of citizens enjoying full rights? These are the questions
facing the hundred members of the Sirs-el-Layyan funda¬
mental education centre today.
Sirs-el-Layyan, in the Menufia district, is a large straggling
village where, in 1952, the Egyptian Government and Unesco,
with the help of other United Nations Specialized Agencies,
opened a training-centre for the men and women who will be
in charge of fundamental education in the Arab countries.
It is thus not an institution working for merely local progress
and the benefit of the Egyptian fellahin alone. Candidates
come to it from nine countries Egypt, Iraq, Hashemite
Kingdom of Jordan, Lebanon, Libya, Palestine (Arab
refugees), Saudi-Arabia, Syria and Yemen.
They are there to prepare themselves for the tasks awaiting
them when they return to their homeland. But around Sirs-
el-Layyan each member of the centre sees, basically, the
same kind of peasant society that he has known in his own
country. It is a form of society found with, of course, many
variations throughout the Arab world. The Egyptian delta
is, however, a particularly valuable field for experiment
because of the density of its population. Within a radius of
a few miles a hamlet, a small town and five or six villages
may be studied at the same time some of them quite
flourishing, others completely poverty-stricken; some entirely
Muslim, others with a Christian minority; some peopled by
small farmers, others by day-labourers and workmen who
own no land.
It was, moreover, in this district that the Egyptian Gov¬
ernment a few years ago embarked on an educational and
social service scheme which was to lead to a nation-wide
enterprise for social and economic progress. The "social
centres" found in several villages comprise dispensaries,
maternity clinics and assembly rooms. Evening classes for
illiterates have been started, health campaigns organized,
and agricultural information offices opened; playgrounds
have been provided for children, as well as garden plots for
them to tend. Thus with the help of trained staff, and
thanks to tried methods, as well as experiments (sometimes
successful, sometimes a failure, but always providing a
valuable lesson), the centre's work is greatly facilitated.
At all events, even though the surrounding villages are
primarily the centre's "laboratories", the trainees know that
their daily work must contribute to the people's welfare. If
they fail here, what will they do later? The solutions they
will have to apply then must be worked out now, on the spot.
Picture a team of 10 or 12 trainees of every nationality
represented at the centre. In front of them is a village,
which is to be their village for the next two years. They
rent a house there, and at first visit it for one day a week
(later they will live in it permanently) ; they are really face
to face with the village, and for weeks will be looked upon as
strangers, intruders, embarrassing and embarrassed.
They are not young students; their average age is 30.
Some are university graduates, while others have already
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Cotirier. Nr 3-4. 1955
started their careers as teachers, social workers, agricultural
engineers, or nurses; there are specialists in adult education,
in anti-epidemic work, or in education by visual aids. But
at first they lose their self-confidence, and walk about like
shy visitors.
The village with which they have to contend is an
amorphous mass of men and women whose first instinct is to
reject, to mistrust. The fellahin generally expect nothing
good from the ladies and gentlemen of the towns. For centu¬
ries the city's only interest in them has been to send them
masters, tax-collectors and police. It takes days and weeks
of mutual observation, patient explanations and experience
of working with others, before the students are accepted and
their role understood. They have come to help the village a
little. But what can be done without money? They are not
going to build, or put in drinking-water, or dig a new irriga¬
tion canal, or distribute presents. And besides, what are
their qualifications?
"We simply want to help you help yourselves." It is a good
formula; but no amount of talking will make it understand¬
able to the peasants, who have little faith in novelties and
automatically run away from the idea of any new scheme.
The trainees look through their list (which they think they
know by heart) of the needs of every village in the delta,
needs that are doubtless those of every village in the East:
economic reform, agriculture, hygiene, education. But where
are they to begin, and how? Which men and women would
it be best to approach first?
The trainees soon discover the ganglia, the nervous system
as it were, of the mass. They identify the village "notables"
peasants more prosperous or better educated than the rest,
influential and respected priests or religious teachers, or
young people with a taste for progress and action. The Sirs-
el-Layyan centre has now been operating for two years. If
its efforts in the villages selected had to be described in a
single sentence, it could be said that in every instance the
trainees had achieved something unheard of: they have
created true communities. Using a variety of tactics, they
are gradually bringing into being an organized village life, by
giving self-realization to groups of men with a civic
conscience, potential "leaders" in a system which, based on
service, is the nucleus of a local democracy.
Of course, to start a sewing-school or a dispensary and
attract women and children to it, it "was enough" to gain the
confidence of the village; it seemed quite a simple matter.
But such confidence is not easily gained quite the contrary.
It is not the custom for women to go out at will except when
going to work, or for them to meet apart from their families;
they are afraid of ridicule, and normally do not dare to
venture into a quarter other than their own; and as for girls,
they are expected to remain shut up at home from the
beginning of puberty until marriage.
These customs and conventions seemed immutable. Yet
the young women trainees of the centre do not merely visit
homes; because their own hostel is practically sacrosanct,
they can, and regularly do, receive children, girls and married
women there. The hostel at Deberki, for instance, is built on
exactly the same lines as the rest of the village, mud walls,
three rooms and a cattleshed under a single roof, a small
closed court and a rickety staircase giving on to the roof-
terrace. In other aspects, however, the difference leaps to
the eye: the whole hostel is spotless and almost comfortable,
and all at the price of no more than a little work, the aim
being to show the villages by example that they too, without
dipping into their pockets, can live in healthier and
pleasanter houses. The lesson has driven itself home, and
several families have built themselves well-ventilated, white¬
washed living-rooms, which are swept every morning.
Again, it was probably only necessary to win the trust of a
few to persuade people that a "family" kitchen garden was
possible and profitable. A few square metres set aside for
vegetables and fruits to be eaten in the household and not
marketed can have an influence on the children's diet out of
all proportion to the expenses involved. Nor is Egypt the
only country where we find peasant children wasting away
for lack of vitamins.
However, the Sirs-el-Layyan centre by no means confines
itself to such undertakings as these, where success depends
upon calling forth a friendly feeling that might prove very
ephemeral. In the same village of Deberki which, lying at
the far end of the irrigation system, has the least fertile
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
The 'Blind River' where
girls steer the boats
farmlands of the region, 150 peasants have combined to form
a co-operative, contributing from their scanty resources at
rates ranging from 50 piastres for the poorest to £E5 for the
richest; and they have bought a tractor. Now these people
are cautious and suspicious in the extreme; they are usually
terrified by the idea of the slightest form of "investment" :
being firmly convinced that money should be used only to buy
land. To get them embarked on something as audacious as
this, more than mere friendly advice was needed.
The centre's trainees had,' in fact, to unearth in the village
qualities of organization and initiative whose existence the
villagers themselves had never suspected. The trainees did
not form the co-operative; they merely helped it into being.
They certainly argued, and most persuasively, the virtues of
pooled work and explained the operation of combines on a
share basis, but they never postulated the need of a tractor.
The village actually possessed potential leaders whose
abilities were not being used; and it is these who now form
the board of the co-operative, with its chairman, treasurer,
secretary and so forth men of all ages, meeting ceremo¬
niously to discuss the crops to be sown, the maintenance
of tractor and tools and the liquidation of the debt incurred
in their purchase. They are men who, for the first time in
their lives, feel that they are managing their future, running
their own affairs and deliberating about them publicly,
instead of merely suffering in silence and submitting to fate.
It may seem strange that, in writing about fundamental
education, we have not yet spoken of actual teaching. It is
generally admitted nowadays that "it is not enough to learn
how to read" and that, in a peasant community, inability to
write is merely one problem among many. Astonishment,
however, is sometimes felt that educational work does not
begin in a classroom; evening classes are an old institution,
and history now records many well-known "literacy
campaigns."
The trainees of Sirs-el-Layyan would reply that education
can begin anywhere, as they prove in all sorts of ways in a
group gathered round a tractor, in connexion with a health
campaign, or on an open-air stage. The main thing, they
would always tell you, is that people should want to learn.
Once that desire is expressed, no teaching, no form of edu¬
cation is really difficult. Evening courses are, generally
speaking, an outcome rather than a starting-point. Once
such courses have begun, at the request of the future pupils,
education is already on the right road.
At Qalatta, the reading-classes would not have attracted
many pupils had the trainees appeared at the outset in the
guise of school-teachers. Qalatta is a charming village; it
has plenty of trees, and lies on the bank of an ancient canal,
wide as a river the "blind river", as it is called, where white
birds glide and little girls steer the boats.
For all its beauty of setting, however, Qalatta is one of the
most neglected villages of the region. Land here is even
scarcer and more broken up than in. the neighbouring areas;
on the plan, the farms look like a sprinkling of tiny -gardens.
The people of Qalatta, moreover, are famed for their feuds
which are forever dividing man from man and setting
districts, streets and families at odds. Possibly this is
already a thing of the past, but at all events the village, two
years ago, had an atmosphere charged with suspicion and
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 3-4. 1955
ANCIENT WHEEL turned by yoked oxen Is still used to pump water for irrigation in the Nile Delta. Irrigation systems are age-old and farming tools
are of the most primitive kind, but the skill and labour of the fellahin have made this land one of the most productive in the world. (Unesco photo).
seemed doomed to chronic anarchy, mingled with apathy and
dejection.
Yet it was at Qalatta, one evening in February 1954, that
hundreds of peasants could be seen, queueing up in orderly
fashion in front of the trainees' house. Adolescents, respec¬
table citizens, grey-bearded grandfathers all were illiterates
waiting to enrol for the evening classes which were being
organized at the village's request. One by one, they sat
down before the table where the "literacy expert", Mr. Rushdi
Khatir, examined them and entered them for the appropriate
class. Some of them in fact knew nothing at all; others
could sign their names; a third group could still display the
elementary knowledge acquired, in the past, during a few
months at school.
The last-comers waited patiently in the moonlight at the
roadside, in the garden, or on the terrace overlooking the
water. It was past midnight by the time the enrolment was
completed; and there was an air of mystery about the scene,
as if the occasion had been a meeting of conspirators or a
gathering of volunteers. The fellahin may indeed have felt
that they were taking an adventurous or, at any rate,
important step in submitting their names for this initiation
into the mysterious world of books.
In order to achieve this result, the students had worked
with unfailing tact for over a year to put an end to the feuds
which, hitherto, had defeated every good intention. No
reforms could be effected in Qalatta before a spirit of
comradeship and mutual trust had been re-created among
the people and the value of co-operation demonstrated to
them. The first step was to set up a club to be operated,
almost at once, by the villagers themselves.
During Ramadan the new club increased the number of its
social evenings, calling for this purpose on all the talent of
the village. Next a dispensary was organized, with two
"attendants" trained by the students. The club was thrown
open to the young people, who formed a special "cultural
activities" section; and the officers, with the trainees' help,
are now organizing a small public library.
The club, in effect, acts as a municipal council; on
complaints from the village, last year, that there was a
shortage of water for irrigation, it sent a delegation,
accompanied by two trainees, to the Water Department. And
when the engineer explained that the shortage was due to
neglect of the canals in the Qalatta area, it was once again
the club, at its regular meetings and at the mosque on
Fridays, which campaigned for a general labour service. The
canals were duly cleaned and, the following season, the water
supply was so plentiful that irrigation was ensured with
unexpected ease. Co-operation had proved its worth.
Today the people of Qalatta, like those of Deberki and other
villages, are learning to read and write. Twice or three times
a week they go to the club or the village school and pore
patiently over their spelling primers or plough through their
first books; the methods and books they use are prepared for
them by the experts at Sirs-el-Layyan, and are thoroughly
up to date. That they make this effort at the close of a long
day's work shows that they want to make it and know what
they want. For them, elementary education is not an end in
itself; in the old days, they still regarded it as an unnecessary
luxury, or perhaps as a means of becoming a police constable.
Now they see that it can bring them definite advantages.
One man wants to read so that he shall know the Koran
better; another, so that he can examine his bills and tax
forms. The majority want to have access to the practical
knowledge provided by the pamphlets and books already
displayed in their meeting-rooms manuals on agriculture,
co-operative farming or odd-jobbing, and illustrated
pamphlets on hygiene, cattle diseases or cotton pests. This
mine of valuable information is there, within reach; and
each peasant feels that he will be able to take full advantage
of it just as soon as he has completed the course he is
conscientiously following.
"Everything hangs together", said one of the trainees.
"When we set out to raise the standard of living a little, each
step leads to another . . . but then the result depends on a
third factor, which was not reckoned with." What goes by
the name of poverty, in the villages, is not a superficial
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
A TIMELESS FEATURE of the Middle East scene is a shepherd and his flock on their way to
new pastures. In addition to rearing sheep for their meat and wool, farmers in the district of
Menufiasite of the Sirs-el-Layyan Centreuse ewe's milk to make a cheese which is reputed
throughout Egypt. Local producers have now received certificates of quality from the Centre.
condition arising from a single simple cause which can be
dealt with at one stroke. It is due to a whole tangle of
causes, almost impossible to root out one by one.
Hundreds of children fall victims to an epidemic. Why?
Because the mothers have no notion of hygiene? Probably
because there were no schools for them, and there are still
all too few for their daughters. 3ut there are other reasons
too: polluted water (and who is going to pay for a public
water-system?) and, above all, insanitary housing. Homes
are insanitary because the fellahin have only the vaguest
notions of what a proper, healthy house is. We must teach
them, if we can. But whether they are taught or not, the
fact remains that the fellahin lack the wherewithal to build
better houses.
This argument seems decisive; in fact it is not entirely
valid. In these villages and towns, every street, every square
looks the same as it has looked for centuries past yet no
house is more than 20 years old. Everything built falls to
pieces after 20 years, and the fellahin rebuild it at great
expense. What happens is that the foundations rot away;
if the brick foundations could be reinforced, every fellah
would have at least one less house to build in his lifetime, and
could thus enlarge and improve his home without spending
more than he does at present. An expert from Yugoslavia is
investigating this question at Sirs-el-Layyan, and has reason¬
able hopes of being able to introduce a cheap type of concrete
which would revolutionize peasant housing.
The same expert is co-operating with the trainees to
produce a new stove a simple clay model designed to be
much more effective and economical than the traditional
type. This may seem a trivial matter; but if their stoves
consumed less fuel, the latter could be supplied exclusively
from wood, branches and twigs, and straw. The cattle-dung
could then be used as manure. The invention of a good
stove may, one day, spare them this vast expenditure of
time and labour.
One fellah admitted as much, when he smilingly said:
"'It's better to save your strength when you haven't enough
to eat." It is shameful that such skilled and hardworking
farmers should have to feed themselves and their families so
badly. Apart from raw vegetables, the fellahin eat practically
nothing but bread, beans and a little cheese. If they raise
poultry, they do so for sale, and they themselves only eat
eggs on special occasions: "They cost too much," a fellah
will tell you.
It is, in fact, these slender profits that enable them occa¬
sionally to buy a few clothes or tools, or even to save a little
money to buy another water-buffalo or donkey to replace a
beast that has died. What then remains from all their work?
People will quote an old proverb: "The fellah is like a needle,
which dresses other people but itself remains naked."
But once the peasants can succeed in organizing a sound
co-operative, escaping from the money-lender's clutches,
selling their corn or cotton crop at a proper price, obtaining
good seed at the right time, and combining for the purpose
of major irrigation, ploughing and harvesting work, they are
freed from a host of daily cares.
The conclusions of the women trainees are the same as
those of their colleagues who are concerned with farming or
rural planning. "Import progress ready-made from outside?
Useless, ridiculous. Even the finest examples of progress
would leave the community indifferent people would not
even look at them. You might as well give a refrigerator to
a fellah who has nothing to put in it and has never set eyes
on an electric lamp. No; true progress takes place in the
mind, it comes from within."
Unesco has recently published a booklet entitled "Sirs-el-Layyan" which
describes the work of the fundamental education, training centre for men
and women teachers in the Arab slates. 'llus publication can be obtained
from Unesco national distributors listed on page 66, price : $ 0.25 ; 1/6 ;
75 Fr francs.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
For three hundred years the port
of Brouage on the Atlantic coast
had been one of France's greatest
harbours rich in peacetime, powerful
in wartime, and known throughout the
world. All that ended several centuries
ago. Brouage became a ghost village
almost deserted, almost derelict.
Two years ago, however, sixty
students from ten countries came to
Brouage to try to restore it to life.
The students all belonged to the inter¬
national voluntary work camp move¬
ment. Brouage was their latest assign¬
ment in the "pick and shovel" interna¬
tional co-operation for which the mo¬
vement is famous.
One of France's greatest scholars at
the time of the Renaissance, Nicolas
Alain, described the Brouage of his day
in these terms. "Right in the centre
of this plain," he wrote, "you see a
great arm of the sea reaching into the
land, forming a port which is famous
throughout Europe." Alain pointed out
that access to Brouage was as easy as it
was safe. And he added: "Vessels come
here from Germany, Flanders, England
and other countries to load salt which
is produced here in enormous quanti¬
ties."
That was the Brouage that existed
until about three centuries ago a
major Atlantic port and a famous city
mm jm
A gn<
Unesco Courier. Nr 3-4 1955
ost
e o m e s
vill age
to life
Going abroad?
Persons wishing to combine their summer vacations with an
educational experience should read Unesco's latest edition of
" Vacations Abroad ". It gives details in English, French or Spanish
of nearly 800 courses, study tours or work camps up to Octo¬
ber 1955. Activities in 67 countries in Europe, Asia, Africa and
America are listed. There is a section on special travel rates for
students and young people going abroad for their vacations.
Obtainable from Unesco national distributors listed on page 66 :
Price: S0.75; 4/6; 225 francs.
that occupied an important place in
French history. It was, for instance,
the birthplace of Samuel Champlain,
the founder of Quebec in French
Canada. Most important of all, Brouage
played a key role in the struggle waged
by Cardinal Richelieu during the
Seventeenth Century Wars of Religion.
To counterbalance a hostile La Ro¬
chelle to the north, Richelieu ringed
Brouage with a mile of ramparts that
stood thirty feet high, crowned by
tall watch-towers. At one time four
thousand men were garrisoned inside
its walls, and ships-of-the-line rode at
anchor in the harbour.
But then history turned against
Brouage. Richelieu's enemies sank
ships in the harbour mouth. Gradually
the sand accumulated and the great
natural inlet sil¬
ted up. Ships
found other
ports. The people
left and the
houses fell to
ruins. Inhabi¬
tants of sur¬
rounding villages
used Brouage as
rock quarry to
build their homes.
Moss and ivy
overgrew what
was left of the
ramparts.
Today, the tra¬
veller will search
in vain for this
historic harbour.
The sea has
retreated long ago
and Brouage nas
become an inland
village. Where
there once lived
thousands of peo¬
ple, today only
two hundred and
fifty r e m a i n
mostly oyster
fishermen and
their families.
However,
Brouage still has
friends anxious
to see it preserv¬
ed as an histo¬
rical site. One
of them made
its plight known
to Concordia, a
French organiza¬
tion set up to
help direct inter¬
national camp
activities on French soil. Before long,
Brouage was assigned ' to the inter¬
national volunteers as a new project
that needed their help actually as
one ,of the more than nine hundred
projects taken on by the work camp
movement in 1953 throughout the
world.
In July 1953 tents went up outside
Brouage for the first time in three
centuries. The tents housed a peaceful
army of sixty students. Some came
from France and nearby countries.
Others came from as far away as India,
Togoland, and Viet Nam. Together the
students got down to work. They
stormed the ancient ramparts with
ladders and mountain-climbing gear
and began to restore them. They
attacked the encroaching sand dunes
with shovels, and they hacked away at
the unsightly underbrush. Once all
this preliminary work had been com¬
pleted, the French Historical Monu¬
ments Office was able to go ahead with
the delicate job of restoring the watch-
towers and the other ruins.
Brouage's inhabitants quickly adopted
the campers. The fishermen took the
foreign visitors out to the famed oyster
beds and showed them how a French
fishing village works and lives. For
both campers and fishermen, the whole
scheme was a great success a fine
experiment in international co-opera¬
tion. And the officials of Concordia,
the sponsoring organization, were so
pleased that they organized a new work
camp in 1954 to continue the job of
restoring the almost-forgotten town a
task which will be carried forward
again this year by a new group of
students.
The work camp at Brouage is only
one of hundreds of projects organized
in all parts of the world by the inter¬
national work camp movement. Re¬
cently, reports on such projects were
made at the Eighth Conference of
Organizers of International Voluntary
Work Camps, sponsored by Unesco, and
held at Marly-le-Roi, near Paris.
They showed that 69,283 young people
took part in 1859 work camps organized
during 1954. Almost half of them
(31,780) worked in village development
schemes in India: digging wells, build¬
ing roads, improving sanitation and
irrigation.
Seventy-seven camps were organized
to assist in the construction of youth
centres playgrounds or sports fields and
2,527 volunteers in 36 camps assisted
in reconstruction work after the earth¬
quakes in Greece and Algeria, the
avalanches in Austria and the floods in'
India.
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
^jVtvtv
Ve\v
Vtv
ie
ttv*
t\°
tv^
\
^a
tve
\\vet
\)
bV
$r»9l
\tfe
G*
0ac
or the past six years a unique project, the Inter¬
national Youth library, (Internationale Jugend-Biblio-
tek) in Munich, Germany, has been actively furthering
international understanding among children and young
people through their books. Founded as a model
library for children and as an international centre for
all persons interested in youth literature, it has now
collected some 24,000 books from 39 countries. In
January 1954 it was made an Associated Project of
Unesco in recognition of the pioneering work it has
done for international youth literature and education.
w
hen you walk through the ruins of Kaulbachstrasse,
Munich, a stone's throw from the university, you will see, as
everywhere in Germany's bombed cities, a sight most touch¬
ing to those unaccustom'ed to ruins: A slender birch-tree
or a sappy lilac bush perched high upon a crumbling wall or
a heap of rubble. It seems a miracle that they should take
root and a mystery how they are nourished. But there they
are, and they thrive.
Nearly six years ago, when the International Youth Library
was set up in a little villa in one of the backyards of this
street, it was no less adventurous than those lonely trees or
bushes. Of all countries, Germany seemed to be the most
barren soil for such a project. But a journalist from London
and a true friend of youth, Mrs. Jella Lepman, did not think
so, and time justified her optimism.
"Children whose world has been destroyed, are just as
hungry for food of the mind as for bread," she said in a
speech at the International Congress on Books for Young
People, held in Zurich two years ago.
The International Youth Library grew a little haphazardly
at first, but for that very reason it had and has retained a
charm so often absent from many state-run institutions for
youth. The 200 to 300 children who walk in every afternoon
seem to look on the library as their home. There are no
entrance cards or fees. They move about freely among the
shelves stocked with 24,000 children's books from 39 countries.
Most of them are gifts from publishers all over the world,
from America or Turkey, Indonesia, India or Denmark.
Dr. Brigitte GNAUCK. journalist and author, is a member of the Secretariat of the German
National Commission for Unesco in Cologne.
12
When Mrs. Lepman asked publishers to send her free copies
of their new publications the response was generous though
not all the material that came in was really valuable, and
some was even worthless. Little by little, however,
Mrs. Lepman's small staff one administrator, four librarians
and one assistanthave sorted the books, putting aside the
inferior ones, and arranging the rest on shelves according to
the countries they come from. Every year the best are
displayed around Christmas time, in an exhibition which is
visited by authors, publishers, parents, and people interested
in juvenile literature from many places.
But the final judges are the youngsters themselves. When¬
ever they return a book, they are asked to put down their
opinion about it. And then there are the "Book Reviewers'
Groups" for youngsters between 9 and 17, who, under the
guidance of a psychologist or a librarian, read books fre¬
quently those by foreign authors and discuss and review
them. And they love it.
Mrs. Lepman's main object, of course, was to acquaint the
children with literature from abroad. Did she attain her
goal? It must be admitted that the language barrier still
is a serious difficulty. The smaller children certainly take
the attractive French, English, Italian or "still more foreign"
(Chinese, Indonesian) picture books from their shelves and
gaze at the illustrations. But they don't understand the text.
One of the library's future tasks, with an enlarged staff,
might be to make tests with at least some of these books by
adding typed or mimeographed translations. Otherwise the
diversity of languages remains forbidding.
However, there is a great variety of translated books. (Up
to 25% of Germany's yearly juvenile book (C ,.
production are translations). How do the ^ il\
youngsters react to them? 'iage '
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 3-4. 1955
* The fish I had for lunch '
Children have thrown themselves heart and soul into varied
activities that flourish In the friendly atmosphere of the Munich
Youth Library. Domain of the painters is an attic-studio, but
in fine weather easels are moved into the garden. Exhibitions
of these children's work have gone round the world and some of
their self-portraits were included In Unesco's publication,
"Art and Education". One of these (below) illustrates why a
child's concrete and imaginative mode of thought is rarely
accessible to adult understanding. When a teacher asked the
six-year old author of this painting if she was supposed to be
carrying a basket, she replied: "Of course not, that's the fish I
had for lunch." (Photos copyright Hans Schurer and Ikki Lúdeke,
Munich. Drawing taken from "Art and Education")
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Munich Weather vane
(Continued)
It is quite apparent that, as a whole, German youth is more
serious-minded than non-German children who visit the
library. "Truthful" is the highest attribute German children
can give to a book. This applies not only to the older ones,
but even the 8 to 9-year-olds. In the written reviews
"too sentimental" is a much repeated comment, or "... a
valuable book, because of its high moral interest".
For instance, the majority deem "Alice in Wonderland" or
P.L. Travers' "Mary Poppins", the flying nursemaid who
drops from the sky, "too confusing and fantastic". Adven¬
ture books are in high demand, if they describe something
"one might do oneself". For the same reason most "Uto¬
pian" ones are condemned with a smile as: "Too improbable".
Of the foreign authors clear favourites besides the old
classics like Swift or Defoe are: Hemingway ("The Old Man
and the Sea"), Kipling, Pearl Buck, Lawson, Thurber, CS.
Forester, Catherine Pinkerton, St. Exupéry, Guareschi, Heyer¬
dahl, Selma Lagerlöf, Hamsun, Monroe Leaf ("Ferdinand, the
Bull") and, naturally, Felix Salten ("Bambi").
Findings of this sort are being collected and tabulated more
and more and put at the disposal of
interested writers, illustrators, publish¬
ers. Mrs. Lepman's institute tries to
become a sort of clearing house for
youth literature by collecting informa¬
tion from all over the world. She
began by sending out questionnaires
on youth book production, children's
libraries etc., to 24 countries, 21 of
which have replied so far. And she
hopes to extend this inquiry to all
member states of Unesco.
Due to her stimulation, an Interna¬
tional Board on Books for Young
People was founded, uniting for the
first time, publishers, librarians, writers
and educators. It held its first inter¬
national meeting last year in Zurich
Unaware of this growing clearing
house and research work, for which
they are the happy "guinea pigs", the
children enthusiastically embark upon
the many more delightful activities
that have sprung up like wild saplings
in the friendly atmosphere of the house.
The attic is the domain of Mr. Steidle,
a gifted young painter and art educator,
and his youthful artists. Exhibitions
of their work have gone around the
world, and some of their self-portraits
were included in Unesco's publication,
"Art and Education".
There are the language classes
English and French, so far taught
from picture books; there are lectures by authors of youth
books, who often have a hard time coping with the mer¬
ciless criticism of their young audience.
And once a month the easels are moved out of the attic
and the "United Nations" moves in. Sixty-eight children,
aged from 12 to 17, find it fun to sacrifice their free Saturday
afternoons to listen to 10-minute speeches, in which the
youthful delegates give what an adult would often think a
highly technical description of "their"' country. The
favourite countries, mostly far-off ones, are represented by
two or three delegates.
The youngsters take their assembly very seriously and ask
questions that might well embarrass a teacher. Yet most
delegates can provide the answers, as they are excellently
informed. Before they make their speech, they ransack
library shelves for material. And without being aware of it,
they become acquainted with many countries they never
thought of before and, at the same time, with the forms of
international parliamentary life. Adults, by the way, are
not admitted to the sessions. "We want to keep this strictly
a youth affair," says Dieter Dederichs, the president, aged 16.
The whole library is strictly a youth affair. Its refreshing,
youthful atmosphere in itself is international. For, as
Mrs. Lepman says, "The child still possesses the whole globe.
Only the grown-ups are fenced in, or think they are."
14
Junior U.N.
Once a' month under
their I 6-years-old chair¬
man, some seventy young
people meet together fcr
a " Junior U.N. Assem¬
bly " (above) at which
delegates give well docu¬
mented reports on coun¬
tries they have chosen to
represent. No less seri¬
ous despite the smiles
Is the work of the book
reviewing group (left).
Discussions between the
young critics are some¬
times broadcast by Mu¬
nich Radio. Final judges
of the books are, after
all, the children (below)
who throng the library.
(Photos copyright Hans
Schürer and Inge Lceffler)
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier Nr 3-4 1955
How code-breaking techniques unravelled a lost Greek tongue
THE CASE OF
THE FOUR-
HANDLED JARS
" ' : . . ' ' '-#-yy-syA'-yy:^-;-
by
Darsie Gillie
Arecent discovery has made Greek
the only rival to Chinese as the
language with the longest written
record. Both languages can now be
traced back from their present modern
spoken forms, through successive chan¬
ges, to somewhere around 1400 B.C.,
that is to say for three thousand three
hundred and fifty years.
The history of writing goes back for
another fifteen hundred years in Egypt
and Mesopotamia, and probably in
India. But these earlier languages
have all long ago died out. No one
today speaks a language derived from
Egyptian. There are very ancient
Sumerian or Babylonian or ancient
compositions in Sanskrit, but these
were preserved for many centuries not
by writing but by a very accurate sys¬
tem of- memorising. At all events,
Sanskrit became a purely literary lan¬
guage more than two thousand years
ago.
There are big differences between
the oldest Chinese and the oldest
Greek documents. Chinese writing,
like Chinese speech, has had one con¬
tinuous history. The modern charac¬
ters are derived from the earliest, even
though there has been so much change
that only a few scholars can read the
latter. The earliest Greek documents
on the other hand are in a script that
has nothing to do with the alphabet
that the Greeks adapted from the
Phoenicians about 750 B.C. and con¬
tinue to use to this day. This "less
ancient" Greek alphabet was the pa¬
rent of the Cyrillic alphabet, used in
some modern Slav languages, and of
the Latin alphabet used throughout
western Europe, both the Americas,
much of Africa and part of Asia.
The documents on which the earlier
script had come to light are clay
tablets, found from 1886 onwards in
Crete, and after 1939 at Pylos on the
Greek mainland. Until their secret
was finally broken by an Englishman,
Michael Ventris, nobody knew in what
language they were written, or whether
the language was one to which we had
a key.
There are other differences between
the early Chinese and early Greek
documents. The early Chinese writ¬
ing is picture-writing and gives no clue
to pronunciation. The earliest Greek
is phonetic and expresses the sound of
the word though very inexactly. The
t=~m 43 MEN
-S- mi
à in
7 WOMEN
¡Ail 4 HORSES
^xn 1 CHARIOT
earliest Chinese documents are ques¬
tions inscribed on bone, so that the
gods may give an answer by cracking
the bone in one way or another when
it is placed in the fire. The earliest
Greek documents seem to be household
accounts though the household is
generally a palace and the resources
drawn on are those of a small kingdom.
When we hear of an ancient system
of writing being deciphered, most of us
think of the Rosetta stone with its
texts in Greek that was known and in
Egyptian that was not yet known. But
that is not the only way a script can
be deciphered. Just as any military
cipher can be broken in time, provided
the language is known, so any ancient
writing can with patience be made to
yield its secret provided the language
is closely enough related to another
known language. If the language is
unknown, then there is no hope unless
a document comes to light which gives
the text in both the unknown and a
known language as did the Rosetta
stone.
The excavations of Sir Arthur Evans
at Knossos in Crete toward the end of
the last century revealed a palace seve¬
ral times rebuilt and on the last occa¬
sion destroyed about 1400 B. C. In the
ruins were found tablets in three
scripts a hieroglyphic or picture writ¬
ing, a more sophisticated writing called
Minoan Linear A and, in much greater
quantities and connected with the last
palace, a third system called Minoan
Linear B. This was derived from the
second, as the second was from the
first. It was long supposed that all
IS
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
THE CASE OF
THE FOU R-
HANDLEO JARS
Royal kitchen
records from
Minoan Palace
1400 B.C.
Until three years ago oldest surviving
record of Greek language and earliest
readable European writing was inscrip¬
tion on a Dipylon vase from Athens
(750 B.C.). Older inscriptions found
were undecipherable until British expert
Michael Ventns, using wartime de-coding
techniques, broke secret of Minoan
script. Tablet (right) unearthed in 1952
proved his deciphering correct. It con¬
tains list of handled jars in royal kitchens
dating back to 1 400 B.C. Second and
third lines show vases with two, three,
four or no handles. Decipherment
would have been practically impossible
without small vertical stroke separating
each word. (Photo C.W. Biegen, drawn
inscriptions Ventns ; from "Archaeology")
t-ri-po-de, Ai-ge-us K-re-si-jos we-chei :
"Two tripods; Aigeus the Cretan ( Î) brings them:
2 TRIPODS."
QE-TO (P) :
"Wine-jars ( ?): 3 JARS." (Orquel-thos "tribute" ?)
tárimm c
di-pa-he me-zo-he t-n-o-we-he :
"Two larger cups with 3 handles: 2 CUPS."
three systems of writing represented
the language of the people who created
the so-called Minoan civilization of'
Crete ; that the palace had been des¬
troyed by the early Greeks from the
mainland who called themselves
Achaeans.
It is certain that the Achaeans first
learned from and then conquered the
Minoans, but it now appears that they
did it rather earlier than was first sup¬
posed. Already before the Minoan
Linear B script was deciphered some
archaeologists had pointed out resem¬
blances between the art in the last
palace of Knossos and the palaces of
the Achaeans on the mainland. Then
came the discovery of Professor Biegen
at Pylos in South Greece in 1939 of
600 "Minoan" tablets in an undoubtedly
Achaean palace. Perhaps the Linear B
tablets were in some early form of
Greek and might be read I
The tablets of Knossos had been
carefully scanned for years by scholars
with little result. It was apparent that
most of them were lists. Numerals
could be distinguished. They seemed
to be rather hurriedly written like the
day-to-day accounts of an office. There
were about 80 different symbols,
apart from little picture signs which
seemed to indicate the kind of objects
in a list; jars, men, chariots.
Eighty signs were too many for an
alphabet, that is a system of writing in
which each sound has a sign of its own,
but too few for one of the early compli¬
cated systems in which many whole
words have a picture sign to them¬
selves. It must therefore be a sylla¬
bary, that is a system of writing in
which each sign represents a syllable.
But with only 80 signs, it must have
been devised for a language in which
most syllables consisted of one conso¬
nant and one vowel, rather like Japa¬
nese, in which there are rarely two
PALACE OF KING MINOS AT KNOSSOS IN NORTHERN CRETE. A VAST BUILDING KNOWN AS "THE LABYRINTH" AND FABLED LAIR OF THE MINOTAUR. THE MONSTER OF
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier Nr 3.4 1955
mm*AMM »
t-ri-pos, he-mei po-dei O-WO-WE (= ou holwei?) :
"One tripod; it is not sound (?) as regards one
foot: I TRIPOD."
i\nfw<z% T/w©w<WYfi
t-ri-pos, K-r'e-si-jos we-chei; a-pu-ke-ka-u-me- (nos) sk-ie-a (...) :
"One tripod; the Cretan (!) brings it; charred around the legs... (I TRIPOD)."
t.TfA.©TT2 V1
di-pas me-zo-he que-t-ro-wes : (for Mezon !)
"One larger cup with 4 handles: 1 CUP."
T'TO©T+6
di-pas me-w-jon que-t-ro-wes :
" One smaller cup with 3 handles: I CUP.':
tw. Airs
di-pas me-w-jon t-ri-j'o-wes :
"One smaller cup with 3 handles: CUP.'
hfmwi
di-pas me-w-jon a-no-wes :
"One smaller cup with no handle: I CUP."
consonants together. This did not
seem very like Greek, but an American
scholar, the late Alice Kober, showed
that there were changes in the termi¬
nations of words, as in Greek and other
Indo-European languages, which might
well correspond to masculine and femi¬
nine and to case-endings.
Finally, when all the tablets found
at Knossos and Pylos had at last been
published so that scholars could work
on them, Mr. Ventris applied the prin¬
ciples used to break ciphers during the
war and offered a hypothetical list of
values for the signs. Making allowan¬
ces for the fact that the Greek'of these
new texts was from five to seven
GREEK MYTHOLOGY SLAIN BY THESEUS. (Photos Viollec)
hundred years older than any that had
hitherto been read, the proposed solu¬
tion did seem to work. Might this be
chance ? Then in 1952 a tablet was
discovered at Pylos, which contained a
list of jars in the royal store rooms.
There were little pictures of jars
without handles, with two handles,
with three and with four. The words
beside them read, as deciphered by
Mr. Ventris, "with no ears", "with two
ears", "with three ears" and "with four
ears". There could be no more doubt
the right solution had been found.
Greek had changed a great deal bet¬
ween the time of the tablets of Knossos
(C. 1400 B.C.) and of Pylos (1200 B.C.)
and even the time of Homer (perhaps
750 B.C.), although the exacting rhy¬
thm in which the poems attributed to
him are composed had preserved many
old words. Secondly the Minoan B.
script must originally have been devis¬
ed for quite a different language. It
does not distinguish between P and B,
K and G, R and L. It cannot express
exactly any syllable which ends with a
consonant. Thus the words "pater"
meaning "father" and "pantes" mean¬
ing "all" are written by the same two
signs indicating "pa-te". You have to
know the subject matter to avoid
errors. That is why the little picture
signs had to be used.
Strangely enough, all that has sur¬
vived are bills, invoices, lists of persons
owing money or services, lists of cattle
and the like. The tablets were probab¬
ly of unbaked clay only kept until
final entries could be made on more
expensive material, vellum or papyrus.
The palaces where they were kept were
destroyed by fire. The "permanent"
records perished in the same flames
which baked and so made permanent
the rough notes of the bailiffs, tax col¬
lectors and merchants.
Have we lost in those flames the
works of earlier Homers ? That does
not seem probable. So ill-fitting a
script would be a very awkward instru¬
ment for writing down a poem or even
a prose-history. It was apparently
used chiefly by tax collectors and
accountants. When the Dorian Greeks
who had hitherto lived too far north
to feel the influence of Cretan civiliza¬
tion swept south and destroyed the
kingdoms of the Achaeans, the Minoan
Linear B script seems to have dis¬
appeared along with the Achaean tax
gatherers.
The records that have come down to
us are very limited in scope, but they
will provide a great deal of information
about the Greeks, whose warrior kings
besieged Troy. They show that the
names of Homer's heroes were common
in the days of which he sang. They
show that the gods of classical Greece
were already worshipped in the second
millennium B.C. They give a voice to
centuries of which we had found the
handiwork, but of which no words
remained to us.
Further, the deciphering of Minoan
B, may yet lead to an understanding of
the much rarer tablets in Minoan A ;
also to those in a kindred script of
about the same date now coming to
light in Cyprus. These still undeci-
phered Cypriot tablets do not look like
lists, but appear to contain texts of
some length. One is perhaps a letter.
But in what language ? That is ano¬
ther mystery and another story.
Da'Ste GILUE, Pans correspondent of the " Manchester
Guardian ", has been a foreign correspondent in Warsaw.
Berlin and Paris since 1926. He has specialized in report¬
ing on archaeology and in general on man's early history.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
WATER:
LIFE SAVER
AND
DEADLY
an can live without clothes, without shelter and for some
time without food. Without water, he soon perishes.
The earliest settlements grew up around rivers,
springs, wells and other primitive sources of water.
Later, great civilizations and cultures were nurtured in the valleys of
famous riversthe Nile, the Euphrates, the Indus and the Ganges.
And as they grew always more and more water was needed. In
fact, it has been said that throughout history, "after the passion of
love, water rights have caused more trouble than anything else to
the human species."
As time went on, the search for water for survival was gradually
paralleled by an equally persistent quest for "pure" water. For thou¬
sands of years people increasingly demanded a more satisfactory
sort of water for drinking and other purposes.
"It is good to keep water in copper vessels, to expose it to sunlight,
and filter through charcoal" is a dictum not out of an engineer's
report in modern times. It goes back about 2,000 years and was
found in a collection of medical lore written in Sanscrit.
Another Sanscrit source of the same period gives more comprehen¬
sive and remarkably modern water purification suggestions: "Impure
water should be purified by being boiled over a fire, or being heated
in the sun, or by dipping a heated iron into it, or by filtration
through sand and coarse gravel and then allowed to cool."
Unfortunately sensible advice like this has often been ignored in
the past. As great civilizations flourished their growing populations
very often themselves poisoned the waters on which their lives
depended. Even a century ago cholera, typhoid, the dysenteries
and other diseases caused by polluted water still ravaged the peoples
of all the continents.
Since then, spectacular results have been achieved in protecting
people against the menace of the many water-borne diseases. But
no country in the world can afford to relax its vigilance concerning
water sources and supplies. Serious and widespread cholera and
typhoid epidemics were still occurring in Europe and America at the
end of the nineteenth century. As late as 1937, a momentary break¬
down in the water-purification system of Croydon, near London, let
loose a terrible epidemic of typhoid fever. In Marseilles in 1943
there were 639 cases of typhoid with 127 deaths.
In the immediate post-war years 250,000 cases of typhoid with
25,000 deaths were occurring annually in Europe. In Mexico it was
estimated that in 1948, 22 per cent of all deaths were caused by water-
borne diseases. Experts believe that in many Asian countries the
sickness rate could be halved by protecting water supplies and provid¬
ing proper facilities for the disposal of wastes.
So long as sanitation remains at a primitive level and water sup¬
plies continue to be dangerously polluted, there is little hope of
reducing the heavy loss of life that is brought about by water-borne
disease. Moreover, the continuing drain on the finances of the
underdeveloped countries resulting from the consumption of disease-
ridden water constitutes a major obstacle in the path of their progress
towards economic) and social betterment. The provision of supplies
of pure water adequate for their needs is a basic requirement of all
countries and one that demands the highest priority in planning for
the future welfare of their peoples.
A vast problem such as this calls for world action and a wider
understanding of the basic relationship between water resources,
health and civilization. This was why the World Health Organization
chose "Clean Water Means Better Health" as the theme for this year's
World Health Day on April 7. As such it served to emphasize who's
concern for wider sanitation programmes and underlined a problem
facing authorities in countries at all stages of health development.
But there are some people who view the prospect of millions more
people enjoying better health with some misgiving. Lower death
rates, they point out, mean more and more mouths to feed in a world
which already seems unable to adequately feed its present popula¬
tion. In the following article, Jean Manevy, of the World Health
Organization, outlines the basic facts of this problem of food,
people and health, and suggests how it may be solved in the future.
PLANNING FOR HEALTH in any community afflicted
by water-borne diseases involves detective -work to
discover the Incidence of sickness and the existence of
human carriers of diseases such as typhoid. Here, by the
light of an oil lamp, an Egyptian medical officer collects
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 3-4. 1955
data on enteric diseases in the village of Mit Hafa. He
has come at night so as to question the men who work
in the fields during the day. Bacteria and parasite studies
were made on every third person among 1,783 villagers.
Results were used in planning a new health campaign.
Jean V . Ma nev y
here do we go from here? In practically every country
throughout the world life expectancy is rising and the
death rate is dropping. The pessimists, though, are
wringing their hands in anguish over this and are fore¬
casting the blackest future for humanity.
"All this is very fine," they say, "but what are we going to do
with all these extra people? With all this better health there
will be fewer epidemics and people will live longer. How is our
planet going to support them when there are millions now who
haven't got enough to eat?"
Some pessimists have even gone so far as to label DDT the
"demographic curse" because it saves lives by destroying malaria-
carrying mosquitos.
The cry of danger has been heard many times before. Even
before the industrial revolution swept across Europe, economists
saw that an improvement in world health would bring about a
sharp increase in population and the pessimists predicted that the
world would soon starve to death.
On the other hand it is just as easy to be over-optimistic and
look at the problem through rose-coloured glasses. What are the
facts? And is man capable of really meeting one of the greatest
challenges he has ever faced?
Two hundred years ago, in 1750, the world's population stood at
700 million. By 1850 it had gone up to 1,000 million, and by 1950
reached the figure of 2,500 million people. Thus, in the last
century our planet's population has doubled. Present calculations
show that the world's population is increasing at the phenomenal
rate of 85,000 to 100,000 persons per day .
By 1980, if the present rate continues, there will be an additional
1,000,000,000 people in the world making a total of 3,500,000,000.
This means another increase of 51 per cent. Continent-wise the
increase would look something like this: Africa, 45 per cent; the
Americas, 61 per cent (32 per cent in North America and 96 per
cent in certain tropical regions of South America) ; (Cont'd on
Asia, 52 per cent; Europe 31 per cent; Oceania, ^ page)
30 per cent.
lean V. MANEVY, French journalist and writer, is a member of the Division of Public Information, World
Health Organization. The opinions he expresses in his article do not necessarily represent those of the
World Health Organization.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Pessimists and Optimists in Hot Debate
What do all these figures show? That our population is
growing fastest in two-thirds of the world which is also the
poorest and the least developed economically.
In the more highly developed countries the rate of increase
is much lower. At the beginning of the present century these
countries saw the start of a concerted programme for improv¬
ing health conditions.
Hygienic measures, the reduction of working hours, slum
clearance and the building of better houses, the spread of
education all helped, first to reduce the general death rate
and then to win impressive victories over the death rate for
infants and young children.
The average expectancy of life was 22 years among the
Egyptians in the first century before the Christian era. In
17th century Europe it was from 30 to 40 years. The great
medical discoveries of recent times have further contributed
to reducing the death rate and extending the life span. It is
now as much as 77 years among white women in North Ame¬
rica.
In the most under-developed countries, however, precarious
living conditions, lack of proper food, low wages and illiteracy
are linked with a high death rate (one in two among young
children), the prevalence of deadly epidemics, and also with
a high birth rate.
Nevertheless, there has been progress though small
during recent decades. Industrialization is under way, vast
campaigns have been undertaken against tuberculosis and
malaria, international action has been taken to check epide¬
mics of plague, typhus and yellow fever, and new kinds of
treatment have been more widely used. All
this has saved a larger number of lives
every year. A lower death rate and a longer
life span combined with a high birth rate
have caused the total population to increase
at a faster pace than that of the production
of consumer goods.
Optimists and pessimists are engaged in
a hot debate about ihe "daily quantity of
calories needed for the subsistence of the
individual." Among optimists, estimates as
to what the globe can maintain in the way
of population range from 5,000 million to
16,000 million human beings. The pessi¬
mists, basing themselves on the one hand on
the present Asian standards of consumption
and on the other, on North American stan¬
dards, reach the conclusion that the earth's
maximum population should not exceed, in
the first case, 2,800 million and, in the second case, only
900 million.
In addition, experts in population problems disagree as to
what the future size of the world's population is likely to be.
Some think it risky to presume that the earth will be submer¬
ged by its population at the beginning of the 21st century.
They judge that the curve of the birth rate must surely follow
the descending curve of the death rate, and that the increase
of population will lessen. At the same time production,
manned by young and healthy workers and freed from the
costly waste of ill-health, will tend to increase.
Population specialists do agree, however, that there are
three stages in population evolution.
First, there is the period of extremely high rates, both of
births and of deaths. Populations tend to increase because
of the high birth rate, but the increase is limited by the high
death rate.
Then, there is the period during which both rates become
subject to controls. First, the death rate tends to become
lower in the direction of the ideal minimum which the pre¬
sent state of medical knowledge can hope to establish. But
the birth rate remains high and is slow to follow the dimi¬
nishing curve of death rate. The result is a spectacular rise
in population.
Finally, there is the period during which both rates are
maintained at a low level, with the result that the popula¬
tion remains stationary or tends slightly toward a decrease.
The countries which have reached these different stages
have been classed as under-developed, semi-developed and
developed. The fact is that the natural evolution of popu¬
lation corresponds with economic evolution: the effect of
industrial development is to improve living conditions and
to lengthen the average life span.
20
Good health
(Continued)
The estimated annual death rate in the whole world varies
from 22 to 25 per 1,000 persons. In the most highly econo¬
mically developed regions it falls as low as 6 per 1,000 while
in the least developed regions it soars as high as 30 per 1,000.
Death rates vary within countries according to social groups.
They are highest among the poorest classes and lowest among
the top income groups.
Between the years, 1000 and 1855, no fewer than 450 famines
occurred in Western Europe alone, causing sharp increases
in the death rate. Along with famines, great epidemics of
plague, cholera, smallpox and typhus have until the recent
past wiped out large numbers of persons. Plague alone
claimed 10,000,000 victims during the Byzantine period and
25,000,000 (a quarter of Europe's population) in the 14th cen¬
tury. Smallpox and typhoid were responsible for from 10 to
20 per cent of all deaths in the 18th and 19th centuries
(40 000 deaths in Prussia yearly at the start of the 19th cen¬
tury). Typhus, a dreaded result of wars and famines, was
particularly deadly to children and adolescents.
Living conditions in the towns were often worse than in the
country. In Stockholm, in the middle of the 18th century,
the average length of life was 14 years for men and 18 for
women, while in the whole of Sweden the averages at the
same period were 33 and 36. In the United States in the
1850's, half of the five-year old children in the countryside
could hope to live to 65, those in the small towns to the age
of 56, and those in the large towns to the age of 41.
The struggle to bring down the death rate really began
about 1850 when important social and economic changes
were taking place. Between 1840 and 1940
the average length of life in Europe rose
steadily from 39 years to 63 years for men,
and from 42 to 66 for women. Since then
the upward movement has continued.
This does not mean that the progress of
science and medicine has succeeded in
lengthening the span of human life. Taken
as an individual, a man of the 20th century
does not live any longer than one who, two
centuries earlier, was lucky enough to
escape illness until an advanced age. But,
In the 20th century, an infinitely larger pro¬
portion of men and women reach old age.
It is the reduction of the death rate among
children, and especially among infants, that
has had a decisive effect on the extension
of the human life span.
Better knowledge of hygiene and increases
in incomes have both affected the infant death rate. For
example, in the United States during the 1920's the rate
among the poorest classes was 170 per 1,000 births while among
the richer classes it was only 50 per 1,000 births.
For a long time, while over-population was linked with
bad housing conditions, the rate was higher in the towns
than in the country. Nowadays, however, this situation has
reversed. Wars, accompanied by serious food restrictions,
quickly cause rises in the infant mortality rate. The example
of Leningrad is especially dramatic : before the war, the
rate varied between 140 and 150 per 1,000 births ; during the
siege of 1942, it shot up to 748 per 1,000.
Recently the rate has decreased in a most spectacular
manner in the highly developed countries. In some it has
fallen to the record low figure of 20 per 1,000 births,
whereas at the start of the 20th century more than 30 out
of every 100 infants died in their first year. There is a
startling similarity between the health situation today in
the underdeveloped countries and those that prevailed 150
or 200 years ago in the countries now considered developed.
Infant mortality still reaches 500 per 1,000 births. The
average length of life is little longer than 30 years. Epi¬
demics still sporadically take their terrible toll. Tropical
countries have even more of their share of illnesses :
sleeping sickness, yellow fever, yaws and many others.
Experts agree, however, that the death rate caused by such
illnesses can also be reduced by improved living conditions.
Important and successful steps have already been taken
to force down the death rate in large areas of the world :
great vaccination campaigns, a struggle against malaria on
the international scale, quarantine measures to control
epidemics, and the vigorous co-operative lr ,.
activities carried out by the governments of ,Cont ,,°.n
the countries concerned. -page 2i)
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 3-4. 1955
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Good health
(Continued)
IN PERILOUS WATERS-The moderniza¬
tion of agriculture* the growth of indus«
try and the rapid expansion of cities have
ail increased the threat- of contamination
to water supplies. (WHO photo, left).
Rivers and canals in some countries are
often the-home of the snail that harbours
the bilharzia parasite. Boys swimming
in the irrigation canal (centre) run every
chance of catching the intestinal and
Madder disease caused , by this parasite.
Governments are attacking the problem
on two fronts; through education in hygiene
and by mass injections against bilharzia.
(Unesco Photos taken in Egypt)
Nevertheless, the infant death rate in these countries is still
from 40 to 50 per cent of the general mortality. Thus, a
decisive factor in the campaign depends ultimately on
substantial improvements in economic conditions.
The birth of a child is considered a happy event in every
class of society in every country of the world. Within the
family, it means that there will be someone to go on living
in the home, that the soil will be tilled, that the care of
parents in their old age will be assured.
To the nation, it means that the people have a future,
that the homeland will be defended, and that the economy
will have the manpower it needs to expand. Everywhere on
earth, children and young people symbolize vigour and
prosperity.
In the under-developed countries, the birth rate is infini¬
tely higher than that in other countries, but so is the death
rate. Though one out of every two children dies before his
first birthday, this does not check the natural growth of the
population. But when the total population of these countries
rises through high birth and death rates, it does so waste-
fully because such a growth of population means a high
proportion of dependent persons.
It has been calculated that each new child represents an
economic deficit until he is 15 years old. From then on, the
work done by the adolescent each year pays back the cost
of his maintenance during a previous year. At 30 years,
the "capital" invested in the child ,is paid back by the young
man After 30, the grown man represents economic credit
22
"active capital" capable not only of taking care of
himself, but also of a dependent person. But in the under¬
developed countries, infant mortality alone accounts for
from 40 to 50 per cent of the total death rate, and the
average expectancy of life scarcely exceeds 30 years.
The demographic situation in the largest part of the world
today can be summed up as follows. The efforts of medical
science have almost everywhere reduced the general death
rate, but the infant death rate has not diminished in the
same proportions. The lowered death rate and the mainte¬
nance of the birth rate at a high level has speeded up
population growth, but the development of young, healthy,
productive generations has not been accelerated. If the
death rate can be lowered for all ages, there is a chance that
the proportion of children surviving until the period of their
productivity will increase. And this will also mean an
increased return on the investment in their upbringing.
The situation can be compared to that of a young married
couple with limited resources who, expecting a baby, get
quintuplets. If the couple does not get outside help and
if it has no chance of increasing its income, the result will
be disastrous ; the children will starve. But, if by some
miracle, the quintuplets can reach an age at which they
can earn money, the family will be saved, and may even
become prosperous.
Today overpopulation is no longer a problem for individual
nations ; it is one of the most important international ques¬
tions. That is why the United Nations recently convened a
congress of leading population experts from all over the
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 3-4. 1955
world in Rome. They included specialists of the World
Health Organization, whose activities have greatly contribut¬
ed to reducing the death rate ; of the Food and Agricultural
Organization, and Unesco.
Three major theses were presented at the World Popula¬
tion Congress.
First, that "in order to build a family in a rational
manner" man should use various birth control methods.
Second that mechanical or chemical methods of birth
control would be contrary to the laws of nature, but that
man, as a superior being, should be able to master his
instincts and to decide for himself the size of his family,
adapting himself to the economic conditions which he faces.
Finally, there was the view that the growth of population
is not a problem which can be solved by birth control, but
by a better division of consumer goods and resources.
Nevertheless, the supporters of the three different view¬
points seemed to agree on one thing that the generation
which discovered the secrets of the atom should be able to
find a constructive answer to the oft asked question : will
the vast number of human beings who are being saved today
by the progress of medical science be condemned to die of
hunger tomorrow?
Every night, more than half the people on earth go to bed
hungry. Some 1,400 million men and women in Asia have
only enough food to keep them alive. The situation as nu¬
trition experts see it is that each of these people has less
than the 2,400 calories which are considered the daily mini
mum requirement to maintain life. Immense numbers of
people in Africa, Latin America and Europe have only a
trifle more than that minimum. The people of some
countries of Europe, North America and Oceania have rations
equal to or more than the 2,800 calories which the
specialists consider every human being should have daily.
Growth of the population will make the situation even
worse unless better means are found to increase the produc¬
tion of consumer goods and to improve their distribution.
At a time when some regions are threatened by famine,
other parts of the world face the problem of disposing of
surplus stocks of cereals, and of reducing planted acreage.
The earth has far from reached its maximum capacity of
production. Some people believe production can be increas¬
ed from 40 to 50 per cent. Others are convinced that if all
the farmers of the world adopted the best methods now
known, food production could be doubled without adding to
the present acreage.
In the United States, for example, the 1952-1953 crop was
double the annual crops during the 1934-1938 period. The
yield per acre increased by 70 per cent while the planted
area increased by only 20 per cent. However, increases in
the yield of land will not suffice to feed mankind if during
coming years the birth rate continues to be high, if more
lives are saved by science, and if the life span is lengthened
even more.
At present the sea furnishes only about one /cont'd on
percent of mankind's food, although it covers l 24)
some 'three quarters of the surface of the v s '
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
FRIEND AND FOE. Man has always settled near water, but fishermen such as these on the River Niger in the French Sudan live closest to It. It Is their
friend and their foe, It provides their livelihood and may also destroy them. Millions still fail to understand the link between polluted water and disease.
globe. Improvement in fishing methods could bring vast ad¬
ditional quantities of food out of the sea.
About one fifth of the earth's surface is unproductive be¬
cause of its cold climate. But the earth's temperature is
now tending to rise ; the ice is receding toward the poles.
Every year new soil, varying from a few dozen yards to
several miles, is being reclaimed for planting.
The arid zones can also be used if they can be supplied
with water (by dams and irrigation canals) ; if the water
can be kept from evaporating (by reservoirs or vegetation);
if sub-surface water can be extracted and used ; if sea
water can be de-salted (although such foods as cucumbers,
carrots, corn, cabbage can be grown in soil irrigated by salt
water). Some plants, such as the eucalyptus, grow perfectly
in the desert and provide shade and fuel. The extension
of desert areas can be checked by controlling the foraging
of certain animals; goats, rabbits and various birds destroy
the vegetation and permit the advance of the sands.
In the absence of electric and other power, the bringing
of water into arid zones presents serious problems. Yet,
studies are under way to solve them, for instance, by the
use of solar and wind energy.
Considerable progress has been made to increase the yield
of various crops. But new discoveries open far broader pers¬
pectives. For example, by adding a tiny dose of certain
antibiotics to the food of cattle and fowl, their rate of
growth is increased rapidly. Pigs fatten three times as
quickly, hens lay a larger number of eggs. A pig raised with
aureomycine reaches the weight of 43 kilos in a period of
time during which it would normally reach only 30 kilos.
Hybridization or cross-breeding of plants also can increase
the yield of acreage. In the United States, for example, new
hybrids of corn have led to a 25 per cent increase in produc¬
tion, to an additional profit of $700,000,000, and to an annual
increase of about 5,000 million pounds of meat, that is, about
40 pounds of meat more for each person.
In addition to increasing the area and the yield of planted
ground, steps must be taken to protect the soil against the
rains (which, every year, wash millions of tons of good earth
toward the sea) ; against drought (which, in the absence of
irrigation systems, can transform fertile earth into dust, as
for example, the immense Tigris desert area which was once
able to feed 30,000,000 human beings) ; against insects and
parasites which every year destroy at least 10 per cent of the
world's food crop (an amount which could nourish the whole
population of Africa or North America).
Moreover, there are possibilities beyond those which have
been stated briefly here by which man can feed everyone
on earth : there are the new perspectives opened since the
beginning of the atomic era.
The people of the world will have the chance for stu¬
pendous improvements in their food and way of life when
atomic energy is fully used for peaceful, industrial purposes.
The possibilities in this field seem limitless. Dr. Powell, of
Bristol University, Nobel Prize winner, declared recently :
"Used for production, the power of five hydrogen bombs
could furnish a quantity of energy equal to that now produc¬
ed by the work of all Britain's miners during one year.''
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Water
Unesco Courier Nr 3-4. 1955
©
WATER
everywhere Did you Know that...?
u
NIVERSALITY OF WATER. 	 Water
covers about five-sevenths of the
earths surface to an average depth of
three miles. The Polar regions of the
globe are covered with great ice caps
water in solid form. The atmosphere
contains enormous quantities of water
vapour often as much as 50,000 tons in
the air over a square mile of tha earth's
surface at summer temperature. All our
focd contains water, from about 60 % in
lean meat to as much as 95 % in watery
fruits. About 70 % of the human body is
water. Even the solid rocks of the earth's
crust hold water in chemical combination
with different mineral substances so much
of it, that most of the land areas of the
earth would be submerged, if this water
were suddenly returned to the ocean.
THE WISDOM OF THE ANCIENTS : The
Palace of Minos, at Knossos, dat¬
ing from about 2,030 B.C., possessed a
system, of drainage, Nineveh had its
sewers more than 3,000 years ago and,
about 588 B.C., the Cloaca Maxima of
ancient Rome was built. Nevertheless,
in the modern world in general, sani¬
tation may be considered as having
originated within the last two hun¬
dred years and as having been de¬
veloped, uninfluenced by ancient
knowledge, mostly during the last
century.
In Finland a great problem is connec¬
ted with the wood-pulp industry.
An average-sized Finnish pulp-mill dis¬
charges waste comparable with that of a
city of one million population, demanding
expensive treatment in order to prevent
stream pollution.
In Denmark the National Public
Health Service, in collaboration
with the Danish dairy organizations,
has undertaken an examination of
water from 13.000 wells serving rural
communities. Action has also been
taken against the use of town sewage
for watering farm-land, since domes¬
tic sewage has been found to contain
eggs from the tapeworm.
Some facts about water in the Uni¬
ted States : More and more air
conditioning, for instance, is a factor in
our trend to comfortable living. But the
air conditioning system of a large building
may use 3,000,000 gallons of water a day
as much as a city of 25,000 people.
In industry today, water is the universal
raw material. We use pure water in
fabulous quantities :
24 gallons to produce a pound of paper;
up to 10 gallons to produce a can of vege¬
tables; 70 gallons to make a pound of
woollen cloth; 10 gallons of -water to pro¬
duce every gallon of petrol; 65,000 gallons
to produce a ton of highly-finished steel;
750 gallons of water to produce a ton of
dry cement.
But even as the need for more water
grows, the watersheds which nature fa¬
shioned to give us an ample supply are
being despoiled. Cut-over, burned over
land has bîen exposed to the gouge of the
rain, letting it cut off topsoil and run use¬
lessly away with a load of silt to clog dams
and reservoirs.
Because of silt deposits, it is estimated
one out of five of the nation's reservoirs
will be useless in less than 50 years.
Water supply is a big industry in the
United States of America. By weight of
material handled, it is seven times as big
as all other industries put together.
But vast thojgh today's Waterworks ins¬
tallations may be, they are not sufficient
for the years ahead.
The US PuWic Health Service reports
that almost 6,000 communities with no
waterworks need and could support such
facilities. To meet these needs, as well as
to provide for the normal expansion of
existing waterworks, will mean an estimat¬
ed 3,0j3 new treatment plants, 9,000 wells
and well-pumps, 8,000 storage tanks, and
more than 45,u00 miles of water-pipe.
In Prance in 1950, two thirds of
country-dwellers did not have piped
water in their homes. Of 37,000 ru¬
ral communes only 10,500 had a pub¬
lic service of potable water. Out
of 38,000 French communes, scarcely
1,000 had any system of sewerage
whatever, 300 had a reasonably good
drainage system and only 80 possessed
sewage treatment plants.
In Europe only one in four homes
have an indoor water supply and
even in most advanced countries running
water does not reach more than two thirds
of houses in rural areas. In urban areas in
most European countries indoor water sup¬
ply is found in 56 to 96 houses out of every
hundred.
Lucky Iceland. Iceland has plenty
of excellent drinking water (for its
sparse population of one person to the
square kilometre) from springs, rivers
and brooks and it is so pure, clear
and free from bacteria that no puri¬
fication is needed.
More than half the population
makes use of natural hot water, to¬
gether " with electricity from hydro¬
electric plants, for heating, lighting
and cooking.
The many swimming pools and
swimming halls use natural hot water
almost entirely and it is quite free
from bacteria. In most cases the
quantity is so great that no recircula¬
tion is used and the hot water flows
straight through.
If pure drinking water can be
provided to people and if human
excreta can be disposed of without it
contaminatmg the food and drink of man,
a solution would be found for half the ill-
health of people in the South-East Asia
Region. The countries in this region
comprise Afghanistan, Burma, Ceylon,
India, Indonesia, Nepal and Thailand.
Total population: nearly 500 million.
Buried treasure. "In the area
north of Enugu all the way to
Nsukka, water is available from a sin¬
gle stream during the dry season
which lasts for about six months.
People live up to about 30 miles .from
this stream and most of the popula¬
tion of about 200,000 store water in
the wet season for use during the dry
months. Pots of three to four gallons
capacity are used for storage and the
more well-to-do possess up to 300 such
pots sunk in the earth to keep the
water cool. In a survey about a mil¬
lion and a half of these pots were
counted." (From a report by a WHO
Public-Health Engineer on rural
conditions in Africa south of the
Sahara.)
Keeping salt out of the water is one
of the big problems in the Ne¬
therlands, much of which lies below sea
level. The fact that the Rhine contains
salt before it even enters the country is
causing some anxiety. In 50 years' time,
salt content of the great river has doubled,
and apparently continues to rise steadily.
Heavy industrialization, very high
density of population, a small
coastline and the absence of great riv¬
ers make for a serious pollution prob¬
lem in Belgium. Some rivers, for
example the Scheldt, are polluted be¬
fore they even enter the country.
Other rivers, the Lys, the Sambre, the
Meuse, are polluted for long stretches.
Sewage pollution of the coast, which
in the holiday season is packed with
people, is also an urgent problem. Re¬
search, the building of sewage treat¬
ment plants and the enforcement of
laws against pollution are being ener¬
getically pursued by the authorities.
Iv Denmark public opinion is strong
in condemning river polluticn. This
is partly due to the popularity of angling.
Increasing interest is being taken in this
sport and the angling clubs are very active
in drawmg attention to cases of pollution
and agitating for its removal.
In Sweden, there is a strong public
opinion that something must be
done about the pollution of rivers.
This is partly because of the recent
salmonella epidemic, on account of
which numerous bathing places were
closed. Though in Sweden, as else¬
where, it seems easier to prevent new
pollution than to deal with that which
has been long established, pollution of
rivers has been increasing. Of recent
years there has been progressive urba¬
nization of the country and sewage
treatment has not kept pace with this
development. Improvement, however,
may be expected.
B't etter living threatens water. 	
The higher tha standard of living,
the greater the danger of pollution. Im¬
proved hygiene means the rapid removal
of dirt and waste, which leads to pollution.
Greater material wealth mu't mean an
increase in manufacture, which leads to
pollution. Less drudgery means a greater
use of machines, which particularly
through the processing of food leads to
pollution. The more, we have advanced,
the more waste we have produced, and to
expect our lakes and rivers to cope with
the mess as they were often able to do in
the past, is today asking too much.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
WATER (Cont'd;
SOURCE OF DANGER: For more than a hundred years people have
taken water from this well in the French Sudan, and with every pail of
water drawn the rope has cut more deeply into the beam. Thousands
of open wells all over Africa contain, unsafe water which undermines the
health of the population. In many villages the water supply causes
half the illness in the community. (WHO photo by Dr Holstein)
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier Nr 3-4 1955
Choracters from "Marionettes' by Pierre
Gauchat (Editions Rentsch, Zurich)
by Maurice Kurtz
Çr-T"* HEATRE not cnly gives us a lesson", exclaimed Dr. Wil-
I liam Beeby, New Zealand educator, "but it even
makes us pay fifteen shillings a seat for it." He ad¬
ded with a wry smile: "How do theatre folk get away with it?"
Puppets have their answer: for centuries now they have
been lecturing and moralizing, and been loved for it, thanks
to their innocent frames being so cleverly dipped into devil¬
ries and foibles of every kind of person from every clime.
The French dictum that "ridicule kills" might well serve as
the marionette's motto, since its stock in trade is just that:
to sell an audience laughter, mostly at itself, yet so deftly
performed that no one realizes the moral has been driven
home and the lesson learnt willy-nilly.
In fact, before we know it, there is no longer before us a
mere show-case, puppets clowning "just" for the sake of
entertainment. We now see a laboratory teeming with
absurd little guinea-pigs who attract their audience by
meaningful antics that puncture a host of human peccadilloes
including those of their masters and on-lookers who have
not yet donned a sanctimonious armour against fun and its
unnredictable consequences. For sooner or later the puppets
reach out and seize that unique opportunity to turn the
thousand eyes and ears of their audience back upon itself,
to hear its own thought-provoking rumblings above the din
of its own laughter.
And so once again the dressed-up dolls can make their stiff
clumsy bow, rake in the applause, and retain their somewhat
pompous title of Master Satirists.
How puppetry manages to perpetuate this feat through the
ages is an open secret, for all theatre people to use if they
can ! But can they all create the illusion that we are looking
through a strange keyhole, straight into another world full of
fascinating creatures who have few qualms and much
talent! in revealing the inhibited side of Man?
True, Sophocles and Euripides, who had their own vision of
Man as a marionette strung from Olympus, portrayed Life
and Earth has a playground for the gods of destiny.
True, Goethe turned to the puppet-like world of the theatre
because it seeks to unveil the secret of life, which is Living
itself. And in this way the author of Faust hoped to satisfy
Man's unquenchable thirst for self-realization, his need of
pleasure, beauty, emotion, excitement.
True, Somerset Maugham, like Aristotle, declares that "the
value of art is not beauty, but right action" which Luis de
Leon, a sixteenth-century Spanish poet defined as acting in
conformity with one's nature and business.
True, Jean-Paul Sartre and his French existentialist
cohorts are concerned less with the action of man as an
individual, and more with "the state of man in its entirety...
to present to modern man a portrait of himself, his problems,
his hopes and his struggles."
These and many other schools of thought have gripped the
theatre public's imagination for almost three thousand years.
Yet puppetry continues to sail across them all, because there
is no school, no philosophy or formula or style to compete
with the disarming simplicity and the naked truthfulness of
an irrepressible puppet that plucks at the gamut of emotions
inside the eternal child forever playacting within each of us.
Nor is it a small tribute to the magic of Theatre that a
lifeless Thing called Puppet can command the attention, the
affection and the loyalty of people everywhere sometimes
"at fifteen shillings a seat"!
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
SHAKES versus
By
James Douglas
A
I I/though the fact is not generally known, the last play
completed by the late George Bernard Shaw was a puppet
play. Intriguingly entitled "'Shakes versus Shav", it was
given its first performance at the Shaw Malvern Festival
in 1949 only 15 months before the world lost one of its
greatest modern dramatists. In the preface to the play GBS
noted, "This in all actuarial probability is my last play and
the climax of my eminence, such as it is."
Written in blank verse, a medium which GBS described as
being "easy and expeditious", it only runs for ten minutes.
The preface, which is cast in the inimitable GBS mould,
contains some stimulating views on the art of puppetry.
"I have learnt part of my craft," he says, "as conductor of
rehearsals (producer, they call it) from puppets. Their
unvarying intensity of facial expression, impossible for living
actors, keeps the imagination of the spectators continuously
stimulated.
"When one of them is speaking or tumbling and the rest
left aside, these, though in full view, are invisible, as they
should be. Living actors have to learn that they too must
not move a muscle nor change their expression, instead of, as
beginners mostly do, playing to them and robbing them of the
audience's undivided attention.
"Puppets have also a fascination of their own, because
there is nothing wonderful in a living actor moving and
28
speaking, but that woodenheaded dolls should do so is a
marvel that never palls.
"And they can survive treatment that would kill live actors.
When I first saw them in my boyhood nothing delighted me
more than when all the puppets went up in a balloon and
presently dropped from the skies with an appalling crash.
"'Nowadays the development of stagecraft into filmerait
may destroy the idiosyncratic puppet charm. Televised
puppets could enjoy the scenic backgrounds of the cinema.
Sound recording could enable the puppet master to give all
his attention to the strings he is manipulating, the dialogue
being spoken by first-rate speakers as in the theatre.
"The old puppet master spoke all the parts himself in
accents which he differentiated by Punch-and-Judy squeaks
and the like. I can imagine puppets simulating living per¬
formers so perfectly that the spectators will be completely
illuded. The result will be the death of puppetry; for it
would lose its charm with its magic. So let reformers beware."
Happily what GBS feared has not come to pass. Puppet
plays on television entertain and fascinate young and old
alike. The magic and charm has not been lost as witness
the tremendous popularity of puppets when televised in
Britain and other countries. The children of Britain, and
their parents, clamoured for more.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 3-4 1955
BLOW BY BLOW
DESCRIPTION
As "'Shakes versus Shav"
opens, Shakespeare
appears first on the
scene, and decries the Mal¬
vern Festival as a "presump¬
tuous mockery" of his own
festival at Stratford.
His castigation of the
caitiff Shav, the "fiend from
Ireland," is interrupted by
Shaw's own entrance. "Who
art thou that rearest a fore¬
head almost rivalling mine ?"
Shakespeare demands. "Nay"
counters Shav, "who art thou,
that knowest not these
features pictured throughout
the globe? Who should I be,
but GBS?"
Tempers quickly rise and
they fight it out with the
result that each knocks the
other down in turn. But
Shaw, by reason of his
greater youth "Younger you
are by full three hundred
years" knocks down Shakes¬
peare for a count of ten.
Shakespeare then carries
the battle forward with
words. They resume their
argument in quieter mood.
"Couldst write Macbeth?"
asks Shakespeare. "No need,"
says Shaw, "'He has been
bettered," and he calls up
Scott's Rob Roy. Both char¬
acters appear and fight a
duel. Rob Roy decapitates
Macbeth and the latter, head¬
less, remarks "I will return
to Stratford: the hotels are
cheaper there."
Shakespeare, however, is
not satisfied with this display
of virtuosity and quotes a line
from Macbeth "'worth", he
says, "a thousand of your
piffling plays." Shaw res¬
ponds by quoting some heavy
cockney rhymes by Adam
Lindsay Gordon on the same
subject. Shakespeare is
amused but returns to attack
Shaw again and challenges
him to produce anything to
match Hamlet and King Lear.
Shaw replies with an imag¬
ined extract from Heart¬
break House, but Shakespeare
accuses him of plagiarism.
Shaw then proceeds to
plagiarize Shakespeare in a
subtly twisted fashion "To¬
morrow and tomorrow and
tomorrow we puppets shall
replay our scene. Meanwhile,
immortal William dead and
turned to clay may stop a
hole to keep the wind away."
Shakespeare protests,
"Peace, jealous Bard" says
Shaw, "we are both mortal,
for a moment suffer my
glimmering light "to shine."
A light appears. "'Out, out,
brief candle" says Shakes¬
peare. He puffs it out, and
the puppet plays ends. (Pho¬
tos Black Star-Illustrated.)
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
WHERE CLEVER
DOLLS ARE BORN
Under guidance of theatre workshop head, A. Mendoza, students at CREFAL, Unesco fundamental education
centre in Mexico, develop skill in puppet-making (left). Right, Cuban fellowship holder examines extra-light
wood used for bodies while companion saws pieces as easily as any man. Carving can be done with penknife.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 3-4. 1955
Unesco's most
popular teacher
by Gabriel Anzola Gomez
There is hardly a Tarascan Indian in Mexico's Lake Patzcuaro
region who can restrain from breaking into a broad grin
when the name Crefalito pops up in a conversation.
A howlingly funny, adventurous little glovepuppet, Crefalito is
well on his way to becoming a legendary figure of farce and good
sense for thousands of simple fishermen and farmers round
Patzcuaro. Yet only a few years ago he 'wasn't even born. His
sing-song Mexican accent was first heard when Alfredo Mendoza
Gutierrez set up a puppet section in the rural theatre workshop
he directs at Unesco's Regional Fundamental Education Centre for
Latin America. The Spanish initials for the Patzcuaro Centre are
CREFAL. Mendoza naturally christened his new puppet Crefalito.
Since then, Crefalito has been joined by a cohort of other comic
characters: Don Coyote, Indio Panza Rota (Indian Broken-Belly) ,
Charalito (Skinny Bones), Mechudo (Rufflehead) and many more
almost as popular. Their antics, scraps and scrapes are eagerly
followed by old and young Tarascans alike. The puppets have
slapstick family arguments (in local dialect), fancy folk dances,
drinking sprees, but in every play an educational point (such as
literacy, hygiene or commupity development) is skilfully and
subtly woven in. "We can get our message across and give them
amusing entertainment at the same time," Mendoza Gutierrez says.
All Latin American teacher-students enrolled at the theatre
workshop study every aspect of puppetry art: carving the wooden
figures, painting and dressing them, stage designing and writing
plays. They then learn to manipulate the dolls and go out into
the villages to put on their own shows. Similar training is offered
Arab students in Unesco's second regional education centre at Sirs-
el-Layyan, Egypt.
Hundreds of puppets made at Patzcuaro have left Mexico with
their teacher-student authors for other Latin-American countries
where they are being used once again both "to delight and to
teach."
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
CREFALITO (Cont'dj
The big bad
Don Coyote
Chief job of Unesco puppet workshop at Patzcuaro
is writing full-fledged scripts, both witty and educa¬
tional. Student-teachers at first make adaptations
of well-known tales, rapidly learn to write new
original comedies. Right, student-made puppets in
nterpretation of "Snow White and the Seven
Dwarfs." Colour film strip of play was also produced.
Below, two scenes from "Don Coyote va por lana"
(Don CoyoteThe Tables Turned), a comedy by
director of workshop about a big bad coyote who
gets into trouble trying to catch a rabbit and a pig.
Moral of home cleanliness is woven deftly into script.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 3-4. 1955
Cavalea
India's history
by
T s. Satyan
fe*
TROUPE ARRIVES
in village carrying
its equipment (left).
Right, artists unpack
their articles. All
members of house¬
hold join in produc¬
ing plays. Profession
is handed down from
generation to gener¬
ation. (Photo Fea¬
ture, Govt of India
Information Bureau.)
STAGE IS SET for puppet show in North Indian village. Simple and easily put up, it consists of a few bamboo poles and some well-tailored curtains.
Drum-beater sits at left and supplies music which synchronizes with movements of dolls. The puppet master can be glimpsed behind the curtain.
etA. .
»5^"«?£aíejg¿"rr^- - *~s»*e	
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
INDIAN CAVALCADE (continued;
TEN-HEADED KING. In ancient Indian epic, the "Ramayana",
Hindu God Sri Rama slays ten-headed King Ravana of Lanka. Gandhi
often referred to the reign of Rama as India's Golden Age.
BACKSTAGE WIREPULLERS. South Indian puppet players
dexterously manipulate dolls while others (also shown below) wait
their cue. Players have own interpretation of Hindu mythology. à
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N' 3-4. 1955
Scenes from
a Mogul Court
The scene may be anywhere in Delhi
or in the State of Rajasthan,
northern India. Hidden behind a
colourful curtain, a puppet player begins
to manipulate his gorgeously robed and
decorated marionettes. The melody of
his songs, the beat of the drum quickly
reach the ears of passers-by. Very soon
an inquisitive crowd is gathered before
the small '"theatre". The farmer come
to town for his week-end purchases, the
schoolmaster, the office clerks hurrying
past, and the group of young boys
running home after school all are
drawn together by the tunes. A hundred
pairs of eyes are focussed on the beauti¬
ful dolls which now begin to dance and
play, weep and shout.
The cavalcade of Indian history com¬
mences. The court-dancer, wearing a
crimson costume interwoven with gold
and silver thread, swings across the stage
while Akbar, the Great Mogul, watches
her in profound admiration. The spec¬
tators laugh as the two court jesters,
Birbal and Todarmal, the one reputed
for his wit the other for his wisdom,
affectionately hug each other in greeting.
They share the tribulations of Laila and
her lover Majnu India's Romeo and Ju¬
liet.
There is a striking difference between,
these puppet plays (or putliwallas as they
are called) of northern India and those
of the southern part of the Indian sub¬
continent. The northern Indian puppet
artist presents true stories and episodes
in the great pageant of Mogul history
which reached its peak with Akbar during
the 16th century.
The characters vividly portray the lives
of prince and peasant and the manner
in which they lived, dressed and behaved
during the Mogul period. The southern
puppeteer specializes in dramatizations
of mythological stories drawn from the
two Hindu epics, the Ramayana and the
Mahabharata. By watching South In¬
dian puppet shows, the peasant audien¬
ces have learned the moral stature of
epic heroes like Rama and Dharmaraya.
Scenes like these have been enter¬
taining village folk in India for genera¬
tions untold. There was a time when
the puppeteer could rely for his income
on the purses of villagers either at the
weekly bazaar or during the frequent
melas, or festive gatherings. But today
things have changed considerably. The
Indian peasants have been captured by
the spell of the cinema and the ancient
folk art is beginning to lose its powerful
hold on the people.
Modern Indian educators feel that
these puppet plays can be used to spread
education. The puppet player who edu¬
cates the ordinary people by describing
Mogul history, they say, can also be
taught to show stories of modern India.
This idea is now being given serious
thought in India, and if a successful
scheme can be worked out, education
would then go side by side with popular
entertainment in rural India.
_;'.'
* *i
AA
KING'S JESTERS. In courtyard of Mogul
King Aktar's palace, the two clowns of the court,
Birbal and Todarmal, embrace (left) in the tradi¬
tional Mogul greeting. Later in the puppet play,
combat scenes (above) depict a number of elephants
for defence. These histrionic incidents are spectacu¬
larly displayed by the puppet players cf India. They
keep interest of spectators and reduce mono¬
tony of watching a single spectacle lasting many hours.
"ROMEO AND JULIET". Popular tales are inter¬
mixed with historical stories to achieve variety of
effects. Here are two scenes from Laila and Majnu,
the Indian counterpart of Shakespeare's "Romeo
and Juliet". Right, Laila is seen during first meeting
with Majnu. They love each other greatly, but as
is the rule, the course of true love never did run
smooth. Below, poor Majnu, bitten by a snake, rests
on lap of his sweetheart who constantly fans him. ^^ÀÎJr
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
ALL-NIGHT PLAYS are performed In Indonesian Wayang-Golek Theatre (above and below, left), by rod puppetsone of five different
types of Wayang-puppets found in Java and Bali. Good and refined characters have long, thin features, evil puppets have huge bulbous
noses and fat bodies. Men have privileged places and watch actual puppets; women sit behind screen and see puppets as shadow show.
Plays begin after sundownand long, complicated plots are acted out until morning. (Photos ATP Museum and P. Lessing)
?
im
m
1
,f p
SHADOW SHOWS are today performed with
puppets all over China and In other Asian 'countries.
Above, two Chinese figures tinted In rich, translucent
colours. Below, two Siamese puppets from a Bang¬
kok theatre. (Photos Musée de l'Homme, Paris)
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier Nr 3-4 1955
TRAVELLING PUPPETEER of China in 18th century
carried his theatre on his head and manipulated the puppets
from beneath a curtain. (Jacques Chesnais Collection.)
ASIAN PUPPETRY
A VANISHING ART
by Roshan Dhunjibhoy
It has been said that puppetry is universal and as old as civiliza¬
tion itself. Nowhere is this more true than in Asia where the
origins of the puppet play are buried deep in the mists of
antiquity. Writing one thousand years before the birth of Christ
the Chinese chronicler, Let-Tse tells us how the puppets of that
epoch were made and how the puppet plays were performed.
In the East where the present lives side-by-side with the past,
the stories of the puppet plays have been handed down from genera¬
tion to generation and thus many old legends and traditions have
been kept alive. In the seventh century A.D. the shadow theatre
in Java was already a well-established art form and this early tra¬
dition can still be seen today in the "Wayang puppet plays. In
Asian eyes the puppet is not simply a doll-like figure portraying a
story ; it is a living ancestral symbol and an intrinsic part of each
country's religious life. The puppet drama remains to this day in
Asia as a true Peoples' Theatre, presenting in vivid form and colour
old folklore and legends in a manner easily understood by all.
Although it has never been definitely established whether puppets
first originated in China or India the early Indian Sanskrit writers
ascribe their origin to Parvati, the consort of the God Shiva.
According to thé legend she made an ingenious doll which she
refused to show to her husband for fear of the evil power the figure
might possess. So she took it away secretly to a mountain and hid
it. Shiva, however, could not resist the temptation of seeing this
figure and followed his wife. Eventually he found the doll and was so
struck with its beauty and grace that he gave it life and power of
movement and sent it down to the world of men.
Tales from the epic Ramayana
WHETHER or not this charming tale is true it is certain that
there are many and varied allusions to puppets and animated
figures in the legends of Indian literature. In the puppet plays
performed today in South and North India the whole cavalcade of
Indian history and mythology marches past in an endless procession
of amazing scenes. Episodes taken from the great Hindu classics,
the Ramayana and the Mahabharata, are the classic themes for
South Indian showmen. For generations puppet dramas of this na¬
ture have been enacted before village audiences throughout India.
Today, however, the Indian peasants have increasingly been brought
under the spell of the cinema and ancient arts are losing their hold
on the people.
This is also true of Ceylon where the puppet theatre is now confined
to a single coastal town in the south of the island. Ceylon most pro¬
bably inherited her puppet art from India and references to methods
of manipulating puppets are found in ancient literary works written
in the days of the island's kings. Although there is no record of a
continued tradition, or even patronage, puppetry in Ceylon still exists
in its primitive form and the reason for its survival most probably lies
in its traditional significance and folk connexions.
In Java and Bali the development of the art of puppetry has been
complex. There are no fewer than five different types of Wayang-
puppets, each with its own individual method of colouring, carving
and dressing the figures. The Wayang Poerwa, one of the five types,
was originally used as a rite to communicate with the dead. The
puppeteer (the Dalang) was believed to possess occult powers which
enabled him to entice the spirits of the dead into his
puppets. Although much of this religious significance Cont d on
has been lost, these plays are usually performed on page 42.
Roshan DHUNjIBHOY of Pakistan became interested in puppetry while on a dancing and theatre tour in the
United Stales several years ago. She helped organize puppet shows for children in Boston and then turned
her attention to puppetry in India and the Far East.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
THIRTY YEARS TO MASTER
THE ART OF ' BUNRAKU '
Centuries of life-time devotion and painstaking study by generations of
artists have gone Into the development of Bunraku, Japan's unique
form of puppetry. What makes Bunraku really different is that the
puppets are two-thirds life-size and are manipulated on a stage in full
view of the audience. It takes three persons to manipulate a Bunraku
puppet: the chief puppeteer garbed in an ancient ceremonial robe works
the head and the right arm, and two assistants, one to work the left arm and
the other, the feet. The assistants, whose presence on the stage Is supposed
to be unnoticed, are clad in black robes and hoods which signify "noth¬
ingness." Once the Bunraku play has started, the audience is no longer
conscious that the puppeteers exist. It sees only the graceful or forceful
"actors" whose every gesture is perfectly timed to the accompaniment of
samisen music and the jorurl singers reciting the theme of the play and
speaking the lines. Japanese consider that perfection comes after 30 years
of training and experience. Japan's most celebrated puppeteer, Bungoro
Yoshida (above) has spent more than 70 years in the world of puppets.
He is renowned for his skilful manipulation of female figures. A complete
language of gesture and movement Is used to express emotion. The master
puppeteer (below, right) is making the woman puppet convey her grief by
using a handkerchief, one end in the mouth, the other In the right hand.
One assistant moves the left hand while another suggests the movement of
the legsa woman puppet having none. (Photos Iwanami Films, Tokyo)
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 3-4. 1955
^1P»
Wy
Wa
/^J^jjiBf
W 4'/A9 .¡É
B * ' '
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
A look into the
puppet chamber
of Bunraku
The first thing that strikes the visitor to
the puppet chamber of a Bunraku Theatre
is the disharmony In the features of the
puppets, the eyes, eye-brows and mouths
being wholly out of proportion, and even the
left and right features being dissimilar.
These proud Samurai, venerable old men,
shifty villains, lovely young women and
droll jesters are not simply dolls to be admired.
They are actors and in each of them the
character and personality of the person to
be played is personified in the puppet's facial
make-up. Some faces, painted dark red (evil
characters), are quite grotesque. A close look
at a female puppet which appears so lovely
on the stage reveals that its face has the quality
of white porcelain, with not a trace of life¬
like colouring. Frigid eyes and mouth reveal
little that is human. The reason is that exag¬
geration is an important trait of the puppet
which otherwise would lose much of its
dramatic effectiveness at a distance. And it is
amazing to observe how, from a distance, the
expressions of a Bunraku puppet can be dis¬
cerned on an oversized stage. Puppet heads
which have been handed down from long ago
have the name of the maker Inscribed on the
central stick. Prior to each performance a
puppet is carefully prepared with Its wig
smoothed down, or its hair put up in such a
way as to suit its role. Uncanny and grotesque
as they may appear off the stage, the puppets
immediately become graceful and lively figures
as they are handled by Bunraku master
puppeteers. (Photos Iwanaml Films, Tokyo)
m
-til
40
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier Nr 3-4. 1955
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
Asian puppetrya fast disappearing art
(Continued from page 37)
occasions such as marriages and in connexion with cere¬
monies to celebrate pregnancy or circumcision. On such
occasions the puppeteer is accorded almost the same respect
as a priest.
The Wayang puppets influenced other theatrical arts,
especially the dance which adopted many of the same move¬
ments. The plays are usually performed after sundown with
the men sitting in the privileged positions behind the
puppeteer so that they can watch the actual manipulation of
the puppets. On the stage itself there is a large transparent
white cloth with a symbolic red border stretched much in the
fashion of a home cinema screen. Behind this stands the
puppeteer with a finely-fashioned oil lamp hanging above his
head. In front of the screen the women sit and watch the
spectacle as a shadow play.
It commences with a long prelude by a Javanese orchestra,
but before the last sounds of the gong have died away the
puppeteer brings on his puppets made from buffalo hide and
decorated and painted in symbolic colours. They are divided
into two groups the good and refined with long thin
features and bowed heads, as a sign of humility, and the evil
puppets with huge bulbous noses, fat bodies and heads held
high in pride. The complicated plots, many drawn from the
Hindu epic, the Mahabharata, familiar to the Javanese, take
an entire night to perform. Despite their length the audience
listens fascinated.
As long ago as a thousand years before the birth of Christ
puppets were as popular in China as the cinema is today. It
is said of the Chinese Emperor, Muh, that on one occasion
he called in a famous puppet showman, Yen Sze, to entertain
him and his many wives. The puppeteer, elated at being
invited to exhibit at the Royal Palace, went happily to work
and made a wonderful set of puppets which could open their
lips, move their hands and roll their eyes at the audience.
But during the performance the puppets appeared so life¬
like that the Emperor imagined them to be flirting with his
wives. He ordered the puppeteer's head chopped off on the
spot. The showman begged for his life and to prove his
innocence tore his puppets into shreds. The Emperor, realiz¬
ing that he had been made jealous by mere coloured scraps
of paper, relented and granted him his life.
Perhaps not all puppets are as realistic as those of Yen Sze,
but the measure of Chinese artistry is shown by the fact that
today shadow plays are performed all over China. The
tradition of the puppet theatre has been preserved intact and
to old folk tales and legends have been added adaptations
of Chinese plays and translations of foreign works.
The making of shadow puppets in China is a special craft.
The figures, cut by scissors, are individually styled. Open¬
work and embroideries are indicated by delicate traceries.
Tinted in rich translucent colours the puppets have a decora¬
tive appeal which fascinates the audience. The travelling
puppeteer is his own theatre as he carries his stage on his
head and manipulates the puppets from underneath his
voluminous robe. In the 1939-1945 war the Chinese puppet
theatre was used as an effective method of anti-Japanese
propa'ganda^a good indication of the profound influence of
puppetry on the modern Chinese peasant.
Kabuki actors out-classed
The Chinese taught the art of making puppets to the
Japanese and although the growth of puppetry in
Japan was comparatively recent, by the mid-eighteenth
century the Japanese puppet theatre had become the most
lavish in the world. Through the rivalry of two puppet
companies, drama reached such heights that it outshone
the traditional Japanese Kabuki. Human actors watched
the puppets to learn the niceties of acting: the revolving
stage was introduced in the puppet theatre ; the greatest
Japanese playwright of his day, Chikamatsu, found greater
freedom in writing plays for inanimate actors. This was
by reason of the fact that the oriental drama had kept to,
its ritualistic and stylized character with the result that the
puppets became more human than the humans.
Following this apex of Japanese puppetry a decline set in
and it was not until 1871 that a puppet company in Osaka
brought new life to tlie art. From Osaka the new form of
puppetry spread to Kyoto and thence throughout the length
and breadth of the country. The name of this Osaka
company, Bunraku, has since become synonymous with the
classical puppet theatre.
Bunkaru puppetry is actually a puppet play co-ordinated
with ballad singing the musical instrument used being the
Japanese samisen, a three-stringed instrument which was
brought to Japan from the Ryukyu Islands at the beginning
of the Tokugawa era. The puppets and the recital are one
as the figures move in harmony with the recitation and a
form of musical drama is thus produced. Perfect harmony
and synchronization are required and even the slightest de¬
viation will disorganize the movements of the puppet.
The puppets, which are almost two-thirds life size and
weigh about thirty pounds, are beautifully dressed. They
are manipulated from behind by puppeteers who make no
'attempt to conceal themselves from the public. The principal
puppeis are each manipulated by three men one for ine
head and right arm, one for the left arm and a third for
the feet who co-ordinate their movements with the lilting
rhythm of the samisen and the moves of the puppet's head.
Burmese Kings portrayed
Foreigners, witnessing a Bunraku performance, are invari¬
ably impressed with the harmony of the performance
and are curious to know how three men moving one
puppet can read each others minds so perfectly. This
harmony is achieved only by assiduous practice. It has long
been an established rule among Japanese puppeteers that it
takes ten years to handle the feet properly, ten more years
to control the left hand and another ten to control the
central movements.
Thirty years spent in perfecting the art of puppet mani¬
pulation is something which could be found nowhere else but
in Japan. It should not be imagined, however, that the
puppeteers are the most important part of the Bunraku per¬
formance: the singers and the samisen players must also
co-ordinate exactly in observing the traditional rhythmic
pattern which is maintained by all participants throughout
the entire performance.
The puppets themselves are extremely complicated in
construction. One figure may have as many as five different
kinds of string controls. The faces are carefully painted and
the wigs and garments prepared with infinite care. After
each performance the puppet's clothes are taken off and
stored away. As witness of the importance of puppet per¬
sonalities it is of some significance that the script-writer of
a Japanese puppet play will commence his work with the
existing puppets in his mind's eye. The theme of the puppet
plays has always remained the same the triumph of justice
and the struggle of good against evil.
In contrast with the high moral tone of the Japanese
puppet plays the Burmese puppeteer gives his performance
with the primary purpose of entertaining his audience, and
many of his puppets are lively laughable figures of fun.
However, in common with Japan music plays its part on the
Burmese puppet stage. The Burmese puppeteer shows a
fight between a dragon and a peasant. The dragon is killed
and then quickly resuscitated since for the Burmese to show
the taking of life would be an impropriety. Genial-looking
puppet giants are brought on to dance, and animal puppets
perform intricate figures each having its own signature tune.
The true Burmese puppet play, however, is more often
than not concerned with events in the lives of the former
Burmese Kings. These semi-divine Kings did not, appar¬
ently, object to stage representation of themselves provided
that every detail shown of the court dress, manners and
customs was accurate. This custom is still followed today.
Puppetry in Burma now is a declining art and the spirit of
the puppet theatre is largely kept alive here, as in India and
Ceylon, by the itinerant puppeteer wandering from village to
village and fair to fair, playing to those audiences who still
remain out of touch with the cinema particularly true in
Burma where the cinema has not spread to the same degree
as in other Asian countries. These simple yet dedicated
artists have most probably been given the secrets of their
calling by their fathers as the art of the puppeteer tends to
run in families.
Asia still has its puppet theatre but the art of puppetry
is fast disappearing in face of the ever-increasing advance of
the travelling cinema and the radio. If this fascinating link
with the past is not to be lost entirely, urgent steps will have
to be taken. A new renaissance is certainly needed if this
Peoples' Theatre of the East is to continue to function, as it
has for centuries past, bringing art into the everyday lives of
the ordinary people.
42
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier Nr 3-4 1955
Petrouchka
1955
Puppet shows are extremely popu¬
lar with adults and children
throughout the Soviet Union.
Each Republic has its own national
puppet theatre which sends out tour¬
ing shows to farms and villages.
Training centre for puppeteers in
Russia is the Moscow State Puppet
Theatre, directed by Sergei Obrazt-
sov who has supervised 16,000 perfor¬
mances since he started the theatre
in 1931. Shows are given every even¬
ing for adults and in the daytime
for children. The theatre has a
unique museum with over 3,000 pup¬
pets and marionettes from different
lands. Obraztsov has brought hand
puppetry the most common form in
Russia to an elevated position as a
branch of the theatre, an art in which
actors, painters, designers, writers,
composers and producers combine
their talents to create spectacles
ranging from fairy tales to biting
satires. Photo, left, shows Sergei
Obraztsov manipulating "The Drunk¬
ard", a character he uses to satirize
what he describes as the "dangerous
romance" of drunkenness in many
countries. To collect liquid "drunk"
by the puppet, Obraztsov has a rubber
bottle on his knee. Photos below
show other puppets he uses in shows.
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
(Photos Museum of Po¬
pular Arts and Tradi¬
tions, Paris, and H Ro¬
ger -VioUet)
.
name is
Punch
by Genevieve Sigisbert
I hate to boast but everybody knows me. I'm an institution
like Father Christmas, summer vacation at the seaside
or a good cup of tea. Every now and again the rumour
may go round that I'm on my way out but you pay no mind,
I'll still be in business, alive and kicking when you're all
gone.
Kings and princes give me a good laugh. Can any of them
trace their ancestors back more than a paltry thousand
years ? Look at me, I've got a history that stretches three
thousand years behind me.
Yes I know, the chronicles say I first began to thump,
thwack and thqueak in Naples towards the end of the 16th
century. But chronicles be hanged! I was an up-and-going
concern long before your serious-minded, grim-jawed chro¬
niclers began to take any real notice of me.
I'm as old as Homer's Greek warrior Thersites, "squinting,
bandy, misshapen and deformed, with long pointed head
and a strand or two of hair"; as old as the hunch-backed
figures in those ancient Egyptian tombs. And who knows,
maybe I'm even older than that, perhaps as old as creation
itself and the first wry cry of mockery and revolt that hit
the world.
Of one thing you can be sure. That saucy buffoon, Maccus,
who had the ancient Romans howling with laughter in his
Atellan farces, was a great-great grandpappy of mine. He
had my features, a long beaked nose, a humped back and
a protuberant belly, and was a gay dog, witty, insolent and
ferocious who ran all sorts of risks to satisfy his appetites.
There was that other fellow too, Buceo, a sort of hanger-
on of Maccus's, a braggart, a coward and a flatterer. I have
something of each of them in me.
Where did my name come from? The historians are still
puzzling their brains over that one and some pretty far¬
fetched explanations have been put forward. But it is gene¬
rally agreed now that my name has something to do with
the word pulcino, a chicken (my beak, walk and chirping
voice do resemble a bird's, I'll admit). My barnyard squawks
earned me the latin name Pullus Gallinaceus. Pulcino
became Pulcinella in Italy, Polichinelle in France, Punchi¬
nello and then just plain Punch in England.
My voice, by the way, comes from a curious little metal
whistle called "schwazzle" or "'squeaker" which goes back
to the ancient Greeks who first used it for their string ma¬
rionettes. When my master holds the schwazzle in his
44
mouth and doesn't make the mistake of swallowing it it
gives me my earsplitting falsetto.
During the night of the Middle Ages, by which I mean the
obscurity in which we lived during the vogue for mystery
plays, I led a lusty but undistinguished life in the market
place. Then came the Êenaissance in Italy. A popular
drama of stock characters grew up, some of them grotesquely
padded the Commedia dell'arte.
Each of the characters spoke a different dialect; Pantaloon
was a Venetian, the Doctor hailed from Bologna, and I
became a Neapolitan. I was no longer hunch-backed but
stood as straight as anyone, wearing a loose white smock
held in by a leather belt, from which hung a money-bag and
a wooden sword, loosely gathered trousers, a black half-
mask with a beak nose and long mustachios and a beard,
a white scull-cap and an enormous grey hat with the brim
turned up on each side to form an over-sized peak.
I was a boaster, conceited, cowardly, greedy, shameless
and profligate, a real child of Naples, and Naples took me
to its heart. It cracked me up to the skies, gave me a
theatre, and created special plays for me in which I could
disport myself as I pleased. Wooden puppet or flesh-and-
blood, Naples rushed to see me, crowding in, from the king
to the basest of the lazzaroni. And it went on for ages. I
might lose my beard and grow wrinkled, change my hat
for a sugar-loaf cap, and grow a wart on my nose, but Naples
was still true to me and adored me. It was prouder of me
than of Virgil's tomb!
In the meantime, having become a star, I began to travel.
In 1653 I arrived in France. The welcome I received was
not very enthusiastic; the audiences thought me crude, and
gave me the cold shoulder. You will find me only in a few
of Lulli's and Campra's ballets, in an interlude of Moliere's
"Le Malade imaginaire" and in plays where strolling players
appear on the scene. And I should have led an obscure
exile's life indeed had I not found at fairs, in the little
puppet theatres, the success denied me on the stage proper.
As a marionette, I suddenly imbibed a Gallic with and
became a hunch-back again. Certain French scholars have
explained that I am a caricature, if not of Henry IV, at
least of the Gascon officers who paraded around their master
at Saint Germain or the old Louvre; that the hump on my
back is the eternal symbol of raillery and that on my chest
is the soldier's breast-plate fashionable at the time; that
my cocked hat is the one worn by gallants of the day; that
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 3-4 1955
OLD VENICE street scene of Pulcmella in I 8th century engraving (J. Ches- master. Right, Pulcinella in Roman park today, backstage and public's
nais Collection, Paris). Punch has climbed out of booth to argue with his view. (Photos Museum of Popular Arts and Traditions, Paris; Atinelli)
COMMEDIA DELL'ARTE THEATRE WHICH SAW BIRTH OF PUNCH IN ITALY SHOWN IN MINIATURE AT VENICE PUPPET THEATRE OF 1800 (PHOTO ATINELLI)
IP* V ^ ¿jßM
M
~T
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
Mr. PUNCH (Continued)
Koàï
Mnff
^HH
vm Ki .
m 'i^H
KL ' Jl
my jovial bold and amorous humour is modelled on King
Henry's; and in short, that I am, from head to foot, a spon¬
taneous product of the French imagination.
Others, more cautious, agree that I hailed from Italy but
became identified with the typical mercenary soldier of the
French religious wars, a swashbuckler, a pillager. My bom¬
bast, my ruffianly insolence and my showy garb were suggest¬
ed by the absurd ostentation the Castilian nobles affected
at Court when peace had been restored.
At all events, now that I was a Parisian, I had to strip
myself of clownishness, gluttony, cowardice, base vanity and
brutish sensuality. Though still rather... Rabelaisian, I
grew brisk, lively, gay and witty. In 1649, in the hands of
Jean Brioché on the left bank of the Seine, by the Pont-
Neuf, I came out boldly on the side of the Fronde against
Mazarin; in 1686, just after the revocation of the Edict of
Nantes, with François Brioché at the Château-Gaillard, I
made sport of the discomfiture of the Huguenots.
But my real battlefield and happy hunting ground were
the great Fairs of Paris, the Foire Saint-Germain and the
Foire Saint-Laurent, where, for more than a hundred years,
I played to full houses and I don't mean wooden benches
in the open but proper theatres with pit and boxes and bal¬
cony making game, more or less with impunity, of every¬
body and everything. I was not content with my repertory
of often rather unsavoury short plays but provided a run¬
ning commentary on major and minor contemporary events,
from the occasion when Madame de Saint-Sulpice's panniers
caught afire to Law's Mississippi Scheme.
Above all, I flung myself heart and soul into the "Hundred
Years War" then raging between the privileged players the
Opera and the French and Italian Players and the stroll¬
ing players. My little wooden body could snap its fingers
at edicts and penalties, so, in 1722, Lesage and other authors
gave to me the plays. they had intended for the Opéra-
Comique.
French oil painting of 1670 showing
French and Italian farce actors at Comédie-
Française. First farceur at left is Molière.
I'm the eleventh Pulcinella Napolitano
(cut). (Photo A.T.P. Museum, Paris)
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 3-4. 1955
And what a success they were! All Paris flocked to see
them. We played, from ten o'clock one morning to two
o'clock the next. I found I liked singing and dancing;
painted and bedizened, tricked out with red and green and
yellow, I parodied one by one all the successes of our rivals;
Destouches and Voltaire had no terrors for me, and I was,
in turn, Apollo, Cupid, Anadis and Alcide.
Alas, with the eighteenth century, the Golden Age of the
puppet theatre came to an end. The Foire Saint-Germain
and the Foire Saint-Laurent faded away, and the fair on
the Boulevard du Temple became the rage. There was no
room for me there except in a few pantomimes not made
to my -measure, and I preferred to retire to the world of
children. I who loved no one, wanted to be loved. And
they loved my bright motley, my cocked hat, my hooked
nose, my nutcracker chin and my squeaky voice. I beat
my wife, my creditors and the policeman, and they clapped;
I was a creature of instinct, like them, and we were friends
even though that upstart Guignol was a very much milder
version of my character.
During the Revolution, in 1793, when Paris was the scene
of bloodshed at the Carousel and the Champ de Mars, my
plays ended, fittingly, with my death at the guillotine.
And speaking of revolutions, it was not I but Mr. Payne
Collier who said that the Revolution of 1688 brought about
two memorable events: the accession of the House of Orange
and my own arrival in England. In point of fact, it seems
that I came not from Holland in the train of William III,
but from France in the train of the Stuarts. At first I was
a string marionette and only at the end of the 18th century
did I become the glove-puppet Punch.
I was a little over-awed at the beginning but still put on
a gay, rowdy, boastful and rakish air, though there was no
real harm in me. I gave light relief with my buffooneries
to the puppet plays based on the Bible, as Sir John Spendall
and the Old Vice had done and continued to do. But I
soon put them in the shade and, in London as in Paris,
became the king of the marionettes. Addison and Steele
had something to do with it. Thanks to the articles in the
Tatler, Powell, who I must admit was a very clever puppeteer,
and I became famous. When we settled in London in 1710,
Steele went so far as to say that we outshone the new Ita¬
lian Opera and that I, Punch, was as popular with the fair
sex as the famous singer Nicolini.
The following year, when we had established ourselves in
Covent Garden, we had such a success they used to call us
"cathedral emptiers", and our friend Addison said that
Punch's Theatre, was the place in all London where you
were n ost likely to meet a violent death. I had the honour
of appearing in Swift's verse and Hogarth's engravings.
All this success not unnaturally went to my head. I sat
on the lap of the Queen of Sheba, sent the King of Spain
about his business, attacked Saint George with his foot on
the dragon, and made the most unsuitable jokes in the
middle of the most pathetic scenes. And the more impudent
I was, the more mocking, the more overbearing, irascible,
rough and violent, the more the spectators loved it. It was
really their fault that I became a rogue.
By the end of the eighteenth century, the script makes
me a sort of Henry VIII, a Blue Beard, a "Don Juan of the
people"; I intrigue, beat my wife and her relations, throw
my child out of the window, roam about the world and win
all women's hearts, save three. I slay fathers and brothers,
hang the hangman and kill the devil.
And in the Tragical Comedy of Punch and Judy, published
by Payne Collier in 1828, I am a combination of corpulent,
sensual Falstaff and cold, inhuman Richard Crookback. I
knock senseless the dog, the neighbour, my baby, my wife,
the doctor, the servant, the policeman, the sergeant, the
hangman and the devil, and I laugh. And everybody else
laughs with me. No doubt, the merciless severity of the old
customs made people kindly disposed towards those who fell
into the clutches of the law, but there was a difference bet¬
ween that and applauding my crimes and urging me on to
commit more.
I believe that after all I personified one aspect of the
English character presence of mind, strength of character,
self control. I might be a bad husband and a bad father
but the English appreciated the stout-hearted mockery with
which I met the sentence of death, the ruse I devised to
take the hangman prisoner in my place, and my courageous
struggle with the devil. This struggle with the devil was
a great thing. In the old moralities, the Old Vice stood up
boldly to the demon but was finally carried off to Hell; I
killed him, so that we had something like the duel of Satan
and Sin in Milton. And this out-deviller of the devil which
Byron, smiling, finds akin to himself, this persevering and
resourceful spirit which triumphs always and in everything
was the kind of hero the English wanted.
I might say that, in Germany, I am called Hanswurst, in
Austria, Kasperle, in Holland, Hans Pickelharing and Jan-
Klaassen, in Spain, Don Cristobal Pulchinela, in Russia,
Petrouchka and, in Turkey, Karagoz. It would not be liter¬
ally true, and yet there would be something in it.
At the end of* the 15th century the buffoon in the German
puppet plays was Hanswurst (John Sausage). His part was
that of Polichinelle or Harlequin, and the character was
similar, but his behaviour was quite different.
His two outstanding features were gluttony
particularly excessive fondness for the
(Cont'd on
next page)
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
A stonemason named Kara»«/
Karagöz, the famous puppet character of Turkey,
who looks strangely like Popeye, is now only a memory
in the minds of old men. Puppets came to Persia and
the Byzantine Empire from India. Their spread .was
quickened by their association with the Muslim faith.
Karagöz moved from Turkey along the shores of North
Africa to Macedonia and from there to Greece.
The plays revolve around the
personality of one man, a stone¬
mason named Karagöz. It is
believed that this man really
did exist and was employed,
together with a companion cal¬
led Hacivad, to build a mosque
for the Turkish Sultan. How¬
ever, so the tale relates, the two
masons were apparently great
talkers and the other workers
in the mosque would gather
round and listen to them.
Work was brought to a stand¬
still and the Sultan hearing of
this ordered the two executed.
After the sentence had been
carried out the Sultan regretted
his hasty action as he too had
enjoyed listening to their con¬
versation. To distract his mas¬
ter the Vizier made two puppets,
Karagöz and Hacivad, and with
these he enacted the conversa¬
tions of the two friends for the
Sultan's pleasure.
Although the story
may be apocryphal
there could be no
question of the popula¬
rity of Karagöz, who
was presented as a ra¬
ther crude rough and
ready person. His op¬
posite number, Hacivad,
was a would-be aes¬
thete who spoke Per¬
sian and Arabic and
had some knowledge of
music and literature.
The scenes of the plays
were laid in Turkey .
and typical local cha¬
racters such as the
seductive dancing girl,
the village simpleton
Beberuhi, the opium
addict, the local Don
Juan and foreigners
from Greece, Albania
and the Levant all played their parts. However, the
real charm of the plays lay in the dialogues between
the two principal characters. These would often sati¬
rize day to day events, old literary classics and human
nature itself. Although ribald in tone the plays
usually contained a simple moral based rather on
common sense than on any strict ethical code. The
Karagöz puppet plays can no longer be seen in Turkey
but still flourish today in North Africa and Greece.
MR. PUNCH (cont'd)
national dish to which he owes his name and stupidity.
He was so successful that he was gradually introduced into
all the plays in the repertory.
The monotony of his character is therefore offset by the
variety of his adventures; he is constantly struggling with
bears, apes, snakes and dragons; he rides a flying horse
and has an encounter with Death. He bears the head of
Cyrus and, as a night watchman, sounds the last hour of
Faust. With his materialism, his vulgarity and his cowardice,
he is the living antithesis to the fearless, distinguished,
metaphysically minded masters he serves. But he has the
pedestrian common sense that they disdain and that is why,
unlike Don Juan, he is saved and unlike Faust, gets the
better of the Devil. Driven off the stage in the eighteenth
century by the ascendency of French taste in the theatre,
condemned and outlawed, he yet survived, or rather his place
was taken by Kasperle.
Kasperle is the Austrian member of the family, from
Vienna. Though foolish and credulous, he is less crude and
unmannerly. He is a young peasant who combines simple
mindedness with a certain native wit, and arouses laughter
by his artless reflections and improbable schemes.
In Holland, Hanswurst was supplanted by Hans Pickel-
haring (John Salted Herring) and later by Jan-Klaassen
(John Nicholas), who inherited the boisterousness and cheer¬
ful roguery of France's Polichinelle and England's Punch.
In Spain, although most of the puppeteers were foreigners,
and although the Italians had a great influence on the art,
the subjects and characters are entirely Spanish. Only the
strong personality of Pulcinella made a place for himself
under the name of Don Cristobal Pulchinela. But in spite of
the dignity of naturalization, he kept company for the most
part with performing monkeys and blind men.
Little is known about Petrouchka, the Russian buffoon. He
has quite possibly been influenced by Germany, Italy and
France, but there is not much sign of it. He is impetuous,
48
shameless, pugnacious and slightly fatalistic in character.
Lastly, Karagöz, the national hero of the Turks, lewd,
shameless, an inveterate maker of puns and outrageous jokes,
is surely the character through whom an oppressed people
critized an oppressive government, and those who lived
under constraint gave free rein to their imagination.
And what is it that gives us all, despite our clear-cut and
distinct national features, an undeniable family likeness
Punch, Polichinelle and all the others, my ancestors, my des-
cendents, my brothers or distant cousins?
Though bearing the stamp of different national characters
and tastes, we are the incarnations of a single popular tra¬
dition; we represent revolt, the revolt of instinct against the
prohibitions of law and morality, of simplicity against the
complexities of civilization, of common sense against follies
and stupidities and vices, of the love of justice whatever its
shortcomings and
of freedom against
serfdom and slavery.
One of the most
recent works I have
inspired, Stravins¬
ky's Pulcinella, is not
the least eloquent in
this respectPunch,
though slain, comes
to life again, with a
double, and raises a
whole crop of little
Punchinellos, sym¬
bolizing my ubiquity
and my immortality-
Mr. Punch christens a
magazine in July 1841.
First Punch " cover
drawn by A.S. Henning
(A. T. P. Museum, Paris).
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 3-4 1955
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
Strange tales from
the puppet world
Puppets were once as famous and
popular in the Western world as Mickey
Mouse is today. In Greece "string-
pullers" jogged along the roads to
entertain the populations of Athens,
Sparta and Thebes offering real mario¬
nette shows. Xenophon, in the 5th
century B.C., tells the story of a Syra-
cusan who earned his living at Athens
with puppet shows, and relates how the
man was called in to divert the guests
at a famous banquet given by the great
statesman Callias. At one period a
puppeteer was permitted to play at the
Theatre of Dionysius where the greai
tragedies of Euripedes had formerly
been staged. Antioch, King of Syria,
had a puppet theatre in his palace and
even manipulated the dolls himself.
What's the difference between a ma¬
rionette and a puppet? In English,
puppet is a much older word, coming
from the Latin pupa for "doll" or
"girl" or "little creature". It's been
spelled poupette, poppit and -poppet.
Shakespeare speaks of it many times,
and as the story goes, he may have
written "A Midsummer Night's Dream"
and "Julius Caesar" with puppets in
mind. In his day a puppet show was
called a motion. Today the general
word for animated figures is puppet,
which may be operated from below,
from the plane of action, or from above,
with sticks, rods, strings or wires.
Puppeteers refer to hand (or glove)
puppets, finger puppets, rod puppets, or
string puppets. There are other types
such as the shadow plays, the lever-
operated Japanese puppets and "'jigging
puppets", a popular street entertain¬
ment for centuries in which a string
passed horizontally through the breast
of one or two figures to the performer's
knee. Marionette is the preferred word
today for string or wire puppets, and is
a relative newcomer to English.
Legend has it that in the early days
of the Renaissance the name mario¬
nette was affectionately given to the
little articulated Images of the Virgin
Mary. The word is of Italian-French
origin, and a mariolette was a "little
little Mary". The early Christians used
the dolls to teach the new religion.
.Later in mystery, miracle and passion
plays jointed figures of madonnas,
saints, angels and demons were used in
church festivals. The church banned
the practice in a 16th century edict.
H It is a matter of opinion whether
these religious figures used during the
Middle Ages and also up to compara
tively modern times could justly be
called true puppets. The same is true
of today's Giant Figures of animal effi¬
gies, inflated rubber figures in human
shape and awe-inspiring dragons car¬
ried in street processions.
In Europe the puppet theatre is re¬
garded as part of the folk art and tra¬
dition of each country and is respected
as such. Up to the end of the 19th
century, the travelling puppet theatres
were regular visitors to country fairs
and remote villages throughout western
Europe. Their performances were
usually crude and sometimes vulgar
but they carried the drama to places
where even the strolling players never
ventured. Puppet shows were essen¬
tially the drama of the people and
preserved, often for centuries, age-old
dramatic types and popular legends.
In the past, puppet showmen were
usually simple, unlettered men who
earned a meagre livelihood enacting
what their fathers had taught them.
The chivalric romances, for example,
have been enacted from medieval times
on as puppet plays in Sicily, southern
Italy, northern France and Belgium.
The noble paladins of the Crusades,
Charlemagne, Roland, the four sons of
These airy plastic marionette toys are
from a kit (above) designed by American
art teacher Mildred Osgood especially
for children. Puppet (adjoining photo)
is a weatherman giving instruction to
dancing flowers. His ears, eyelids,
eyebrows and mouth move. Today a
great puppet revival is sweeping Amer¬
ica and England with help of schools and
TV. Puppets are being shown, talked
and written about as never before.
(Courtesy Craft Horizons, USA.)
50
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 3-4 1955
TOY KNIGHTS IN ARMOUR. Seven centuries separate medieval marionettes (left) in 12th century illuminated manuscript (now
destroyed) of Strasbourg Library from I 9th century Sicilian puppet. (Photos ATP Museum Paris; Sicilian Ethnographic Museum-G. Pitre.)
Aymon and many others have battled
incessantly in their richly decorated
suits of armour, their flowery plumed
helmets and their capes of brightly-
coloured fabrics. Most of these puppets
are both heavy and large (three to five
feet tall) and are operated by two iron
rods attached to the head or to the
wooden shoulder piece as well as
strings. They must be strong and
durable to carry their elaborate armour
and heavy swords. Until recently they
could also be seen in New York when
"Orlando Furioso" was presented in
Sicilian dialect with some 400 puppets
each weighing nearly 100 pounds. The
medieval knights fought so hard that
the floor boards of the stage had to be
renewed every two weeks. They per¬
formed for two hours or more every
night and the complete cycle of the
play lasted 13 months!
Bible stories were an important
feature of puppet theatres in France
for many years, in the pre-Revolution
days of Paris and especially in Aix-en-
Provence, Marseille, Nice and Besançon
during the last two centuries. At
Christmas time the little theatres
showed the rising Star of Bethlehem,
the journey of the Three Wise Men and
the Nativity. No one minded when the
Wise Men arrived by rail or a salvo of
cannon shots greeted the birth of Jesus.
Similar crib plays are still enacted in
Poland today, and were the first type
of puppetry to be shown in England.
Puppets were so popular in England
in Shakespeare's day that it is said that
actors protested against them for
taking customers away from the regu¬
lar theatres. When the English Parlia¬
ment closed the regular theatres in
1642, at the start of the Civil War,
puppet shows had their heyday. They
fell heir to the wealth of plays that had
been barred from the stage, and some
of the former actors began speaking
their lines under the direction of
puppet masters.
Charles the Second of England ap¬
pears to have been a keen puppet fan.
Samuel Pepys also noted that the
King's mistress, Lady Castlemaine,
created a traffic block and attracted a
large crowd when she visited the pup¬
pet theatre. Oliver Goldsmith, so
Boswell says, almost broke a leg once
trying to prove, he could jump over a
broomstick as gracefully as a puppet.
At certain periods the puppet has
been admired for its mechanism rather
than for its dramatic qualities. Its
SCHOOL PUPPETRY is a rapidly developing subject In schools around the globe. It has been widely adopted for its educational value
and as a means of creative expression. Right, children put on a puppet show at Unesco's education centre in Cha-Choeng-Sao Thailand.
Left, youngsters in a New York elementary school give a performance with simple class-made rod puppets. (Unesco photos)
51
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
DEATH THE FIDDLER plays for Lady in
White two ghostly Dutch puppet characters.
£AA
ABDULAY THE SUDANESE, a leading per¬
sonality in the puppet shows of the French Sudan.
Strange tales from
the puppet world
(Continued)
movements were regarded as a sort of
conjuring trick and the secret of its
construction was jealously guarded.
This aspect of puppetry was probably
first highly developed by the Italians
in the Fantoccini of the late 18th cen¬
tury. It was advanced by the English
showman, Thomas Holden and is fur¬
ther developed today in several coun¬
tries especially Italy and Britain.
Among the favourite tricks are the
"dissecting skeleton" whose bones gra¬
dually float apart and dance separately
all over the stage and then reunite, and
a figure whose arms, legs, head and
trunk fly apart, each becoming a sepa¬
rate puppet.
Hernando Cortez had a puppeteer
along with him when he set off in 1524
from Mexico City for Honduras in
search of gold. The chronicler of his
expedition, Bernai Diaz del Castillo,
noted in his diary that Cortez had
"five players on the oboe, sackbut and
THE MAGIC FLUTE, Mozart's opera presen¬
ted by Salzburg Marionette Theatre, Austria.
52
dulcimer, and an acrobat and another
who did sleight-of-hand and worked
puppets." According to the same chro¬
nicler, the Aztec Indians of Mexico
understood conjuring and working pup¬
pets, ("saben jugar de mano y hazer
titeres"). American Indians in the
Southwest United States and Northwest
Pacific coast of Canada produced reli¬
gious puppets before the arrival of
white men. Puppets have also been
found in the Pacific Islands of Hawaii
and in Easter Island.
Charles Dickens who was interested
in everything having to do with the
theatre failed to see a puppet show in
America during a visit. Arriving in
New York in 1842, he wrote: "But how
quiet the streets are!... Are there no
Punches, Fantoccini?... No, not one."
He apparently didn't look hard enough.
Punch had arrived in Philadelphia
exactly 100 years before.
During the Manchu Dynasty in
China, high-born women were not per¬
mitted to go out to the theatre. Sha
dow figures were brought to homes
and courtyards for these women, but
ordinary folk saw the heroic legends
and historical tales performed in rural
market places and country fairs. To
this day, the centre of the art of
shadow figures is not in the large cities
but in the little country districts and
small towns. So common is the affec¬
tion for shadows in China that modern
motion pictures are called "electric
shadows".
In Mexico, the Ministry of Educa¬
tion has a puppetry programme for
mass education of the people. In
March 1945 the Ministry launched its
campaign to stamp out illiteracy and
called in two of the nation's most
famous puppeteers, Roberto Lago and
Lola Cueto. They built a special thea¬
tre mounted on a lorry and travelled
to public squares and parks in towns
and villages. During one tour through
the state of Oaxaca, the puppets played
to more than 10,000 people. A special
puppet celebration was given in the
village of Soledad de Etla when it
was first to reach 100 per cent literacy.
A survey conducted on puppetry in
American schools and colleges in 1941
revealed that 35 institutions offered
accredited courses and many had been
doing so for ten years or more. Great¬
est number was given in art depart¬
ments; some appeared in education,
English, foreign language and speech
departments. Puppetry was found to
be faring better in colleges than in ele¬
mentary schools since it was treated
as a subject to be studied not only for
itself but as an enrichment of other
courses.
In the old French and English fairs
puppets were used as advertising de
vices. Spectacular shows have been
presented in modern times at interna¬
tional expositions. At the New York
World's Fair in 1939, puppets told the
story of refrigeration in a series of
dramatic episodes from prehistoric
times when man dragged his meat into
cool caves to preserve it to modern
electric refrigerators. One of Ameri¬
ca's greatest puppeteers, Remo Búfano,
told the story of pharmacy with his
huge marionettes in a trjly specta¬
cular show-
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 3-4. 1955
SILK WEAVER FROM LYONS
In I790's, Laurent Mourguet, silk weaver
from Lyons, created new world of puppets
with Guignol who become most famous
hero after Punch. Prankish Guignol (right
with Gendarme) was soon joined by wife,
Madelon, Gnafron the winebibber (above)
and host of local peasant characters (below).
Today Guignol Is common French word
for Punch shows. (Photo ATP Museum).
PEASANT FROM PICARDY
If Lyons gave all France Guignol other
regions created their own provincial
puppets which have remained famous.
Amiens produced the peasant buffoon
Lafleur (below) who spoke in strong
Picardy dialect, Lille in the north, created
Long Nez (Long Nose), above, and a host
of other rascals. (Photos ATP Museum.)
53
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
Brazil's mamolengo
One of Brazil's most colourful puppeteers was an old vendor of natural
flower oils at Pernambuco fairs. Nicknamed "Cheiroso" (the perfumed
one) he delighted audiences until his death recently with his one-man
shows In the public squares and sometimes in schools and private homes.
Above, he puts on quick "mamolengo" or puppet show for group of
children friends. Left, some of his carved finger puppets. Puppetry
has developed widely ¡n Brazil in past ten years under impetus of Brazil's
Pestalozzi Society, Olga Obry and others. Portuguese and Brazilian
plays based on country's rich folklore and music are aimed at adult
public in Rio and other large cities. (Photos copyright Verger-Adep)
A FEW BOOKS ON PUPPETRY
A large literature on puppetry exists today in many
languages. For a bibliography, see Grace G. Ransome,
Puppets and Shadows, A Bibliography (1931). The
history of puppets was written by Charles Magnin in
1852 : Histoires des marionnettes en Europe. Helen H.
Joseph's A Book of Marionettes (1931) is a good general
history in English. Other general books worth con¬
sulting: Cyril Beaumont's pictorial survey Puppets and
the Puppet Stage (1938) ; Puppetry, the official yearbook
since 1930 of The Puppeteers of America; Marjorie
Batchelder The Puppet Theatre Handbook (1947) ; Paul
McPharlin The Puppet Theatre in America - A History
(1949) ; Philip J. Stead Mr. Punch (1950) ; Puppetry in
the Curriculum, a manual for elementary and secon¬
dary schools, published by New York City Board of Edu¬
cation as No. 1 of its Curriculum Bulletin. 1947-48 Series.
RETIRED
ACTO RS
Liège, in Belgium,
is a famous centre
for puppet plays.
Romances of chi¬
valry are still per¬
formed there with
Charlemagne as
their central figure.
Left, head of a
Liège historical pup¬
pet. Right, old pup¬
pets five Tchant-
chès and a Variasse
their stage days
ended, are conserv¬
ed in the Museum
of Walloon Folklore
at Liège. (Jacques
Chesnais Collection
and Musée de la
Vie Wallonne.)
54
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 3-4 1955
BALLET OF
THE SPRITES
Delightful cabaret glove-
puppets of Compagnie
des Marottes . gather in
flower-pot cluster during
Paris spectacle. Other
French puppeteers like
Yves Joly, Maurice Tem¬
poral, and the Arc-en-
Ciel group have today
become famous for their
intelligent, witty work.
(Photo Marinier.)
55
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
Puppets, source of
literary inspiration
by Jacques Chesnais
After more than a quarter of a century of struggle and
innovation as one of France's most famous theatrical
producers, Gaston Baty whose name is linked with
those of Louis Jouvet, Sacha Pitoeff and Charles Dullin in
the period between the two world wars startled the world
by announcing his withdrawal from the legitimate stage to-
set up a puppet theatre.
Gaston Baty had not suddenly gone mad nor was his
decision a wild spur-of-the-moment flight of fancy. Baty
had come to realize that puppetry was a new form of art
which, though sometimes primitive in technique, opened vast
potentialities for creative expression Impossible to achieve in
the legitimate theatre.
In the history of modern art, a break occurred between
figurative art which produced naturalism and abstract art
which exploded on the world with surrealism. This eruption
was to place puppetry which had always been the theatre
of the people on a new level as a true art form.
Baty was following in the footsteps of many great men of
letters and artists of the past who have found a deep source
of inspiration in puppetry.
Almost all of the great writers of antiquity mention
puppets. Even before they became a great means of
expression puppets embodied a whole philosophy of their
own. This did not escape the great Cervantes when he
devoted a chapter of his "Don Quixote" to "the braying
adventures and the droll one of the puppet master." Cer¬
vantes perceived that the marionette could portray the true
image of Man as reflected in his caricature and could give
credulity to the poetic folly of his hero and his combination
of idealism and plain logic.
In his description of Master Pedro and one of the popular
road puppet theatres of his time Cervantes blends reality
with fantasy. The whole chapter is imbued with a profound
sense of humanity. "In all earnestness, gentlemen," says
Don Quixote after he has slashed at all the puppets to save
a doll-damsel in distress, knocking some over, beheading
others, crippling this one and mangling that one, "I can
assure you that everything that took place here seemed to
me very real indeed, and Melisandra, Don Gaiteros, Marsilio
and Charlemagne were all their flesh-and-blood selves."
The same episode inspired the modern Spanish composer
Manuel de Falla to write a musical score entitled "Master
Pedro's Puppet Show". De Falla also worked with Federico
Garcia Lorca, who has been called the "poet of the puppets",
in productions of several puppet plays.
Ben Jonson, the English dramatist, writing at almost the
same period as Cervantes, used puppets in his "Bartholomew
Fair" one of the great London fairs of his time to
stigmatize fanaticism and intolerance. The puppets, serving
as accessory but vitally important characters, helped to tell
a highly dramatic and human story.
'Shakespeare of the Far East'
Since the 12th century, puppets have been part and
parcel of Japanese drama and even were the basis of the
theatre in Japan. They inspired more than 100 plays
during the 17th century from the pen of Japan's greatest
dramatist, Chikamatsu Monzaemon. Born in 1653, Chika-
matsu first lived the life of a Knight Errant until he settled in
Osaka and began to write plays for the Joruri puppet stage.
Chikamatsu has been called the "Shakespeare of the Far
East."
In the West, puppetry has still to reach the great heights
attained in Japan. Asian cultures are particularly suited to
the conventions and symbolism which evolved in puppetry
where every movement of the face or limbs of the dolls is
part of a veritable language of gestures.
Nevertheless Western puppets have played important roles.
On several occasions the miniature theatres have served as
a place of refuge for oppressed or victimized dramatists. In
18th century France, for example, the -legitimate theatres
held a virtual monopoly of dramatic productions and pre¬
vented competition from independent groups. A number of
56
Parisian dramatists had resort to the puppet theatres of their
time to maintain their right to self-expression.
Among the many men who have found deep inspiration in
puppet shows is the great German poet Goethe. The legend
of Dr. Faustus had been a frequent and popular theme of
marionette theatres in Germany as early as the 16th century.
During the Romantic period of Goethe's time it struck a
particularly sympathetic chord and like all his con¬
temporaries, Goethe found himself captivated by the puppet
play. He was to transform this elementary tale of
necromancy and mysticism into a theme that is today
immortal. From the conflict naively expressed in the puppet
drama, Goethe was to draw out a series of problems of
universal impact and produce his greatest play.
The same period saw another great German dramatist,
Heinrich von Kleist, complete a tiny essay entiled "The
Puppet Theatre." Though small in size it was considerable
in importance. Here for the first time, marionettes inspired
a text in which the technique of puppetry was the basis
for deep reflexions of a psychological nature and the basis
of an admirable comparative study between the moving
marionette and the human dancer.
Rendez-vous of sophisticates
Puppet shows had always been manifestations of folk art.
In technique and repertory they were mainly traditional
and handed down from generation to generation. That
they could also provide fashionable, sophisticated entertain¬
ment was amply demonstrated in the private and semi-pri¬
vate performances in France during the mid-19th century.
With her son Maurice, the novelist George Sand built the
Theatre des Amis first at Nohant and then in Paris. The
puppet theatre, with its satirical plays, soon became the ren¬
dez-vous of all fashionable people in Paris, and George Sand
a champion of the cause of puppetry.
Other authors and poets of the time were also inspired to
write passages on marionettes which are now considered
famous. (Théophile Gautier, Gerard de Nerval, Charles No¬
dier and Louis Duranty are four outstanding names.) But
it was not until the closing years of the 19th century that a
real revival took place. Puppets were then "discovered" as
an artistic medium and writers and artists accorded them a
serious respect they had not enjoyed before.
The year 1887 saw the birth of the now internationally
famous "Black Cat" cabaret in Montmartre where successful
poets, musicians and painters gathered to produce artistic
shadow shows. It was followed by the "Little Theatre"
which gave performances of Cervantes, Aristophanes and
Shakespeare with stately rod puppets and revealed the great
marionette poet Maurice Bouchor.
Puppets have continued to hold a great attraction for
writers ever since. Maeterlink, the Belgian poet-dramatist,
wrote some of his earliest plays for the puppet stage, though
he later abandoned the little wooden actors. Collodi's
"Pinocchio" has become a classic; Bernard Shaw wrote
"Shakes v. Shav" (see page 28) ; Bizet paid his tribute in "The
Funeral March of a Marionette" and Paul Claudel wrote a
puppet farce "The Bear and the Moon." Alfred Jarry's
satirical play, "Ubu Roi" greatly influenced the surrealist
movement in literature. The list of authors Is almost endless.
The puppet revival in our own time has gained momentum
among playwrights and producers. Gordon Craig in his
essay "On the Art of the Theatre" sees the future of the
theatre in the creation of a super-marionette who is the
"complete actor." To Craig puppets are a serious matter
and he restores them to their rightful place as an integral
part of dramatic art.
Today a new road is open to puppetry. Alongside the
puppet theatre as a cultural medium on the one hand, and
as an educational vehicle for children on the other, a new
poetic form of marionette theatre has been born. Where the
living actor cannot pretend to reach, the puppet, unshackled
by human laws or limitations and symbol of dreams and
fantasy, attains heights only the imagination can follow.
]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 3-4. 1955
120 hours to carve
and clothe a puppet
Jacques Chesnais (above) manages to convey his own
passion for the world of marionettes in the miniature
size plays he stages with his large family of "wooden
actors", all of whom he designs and makes in his work¬
shop. It takes 60 hours to carve a puppet, says
Chesnais, and 60 more hours to make the clothes.
A wig costs 3,000 francs (£3) and the entire puppet
adds up to 50,000 francs (£50). Thus, the kings
and queens and fairy tale characters hanging side
by side in their dormitory at the Comédie des Champs-
Elysées Theatre, In Pans, add up to a tidy fortune.
Jacques Chesnais, one of France's leading marionette
artists, is the author of a recent history of world
puppetry. (Photos USIS and A.T.P. Museum, Paris.)
57
]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[
58
V
Vi
r^A
"TrA Si
S¿*4
<*
V^
X
OdeiPIcCOU
1 !
tti . s
..
. 	
1
4
m
]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 3-4. 1955
-
i
M
3?8Hh?? Be
nwfTTjromfti §g[
ES¿a¡ iw.gi^Ljgj
i
«^xrtrvvwMfit UV TT p-"\i IUP«:
?
Al* .| ->v~
Ir a ^
L '
CHILDREN MEET TURBULENT CONCERT PIANIST "PICCOLOVSKI", WHOSE COMIC ACT CONTRASTS WELL WITH STAGECRAFT OF "VENETIAN SERENADE" SCENE.
Twelve hundred marionettes, 15 tons of equipment and
props, 100 packing cases, 1,000 costumes and 40 artists,
technicians, musicians and singers these are some of
the factors which go to make up the famous Italian
"Piccoli" Theatre of Vittorio Podrecca.
It is 43 years since Podrecca, then a journalist, art critic
and secretary of a musical academy in Rome, decided to
make his favourite childhood toy his life's work. After
minute studies of the art and history of marionettes, he
gathered a group around his little wooden actors, three feet
high, and presented his first spectacle of opera, variety and
circus scenes in miniature.
His blending of the decorative, the musical and the dra¬
matic was an immediate success in Rome. Since then, the
"Teatro dei Piccoli" has been round the world three times
with Its remarkable repertory of operas, variety shows, fairy
tales, ballet and folklore scenes. The reactions of audiences
everywhere were well summed up by one theatre critic who
wrote: "The quaint notion that the puppet show is exclusi¬
vely for children has been gently buried by Signor Podrecca,
who uses it brilliantly for all its quality of humour, satire
and sophistication."
Podrecca's art represents an advance in the intricate
technique of puppet articulation. The result is a skilful
combination of dancing figures, acting and comedy, music
and singing. Podrecca is today recognized as one of the
great craftsmen and artists of his time, and his performances
have a depth and richness which go beyond the realm of
mere entertainment. (Photos Vieno, Rome ; Vego, Paris arid
"Piccoli di Podrecca".)
TAKING A BOW AFTER THE SHOW, PUPPETS AND THEIR ANIMATORS LINE UP WITH VITTORIO PODRECCA (FOREGROUND) FOUNDER DIRECTOR OF THE "PICCOLI".
59
]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[
TALES F THE PAST
Folklore and comedy flourish
on Czech stage and screen
OLD CZECH FOLK TALES were woven into a puppet film of great artistry by Jlri Trnka, who brought to the screen some of his country's best-loved
legends such as "The war between men and women" (top of page) and other stories of Czech peasant life. (Czech State Film Photos.)
60
]]>
</page>
<page number="61">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N' 3-4. 1955
EARLY SLAV PEOPLES, WHO SETTLED ON CZECH SOIL, WERE DEPICTED BY JIRI TRNKA IN HIS FILM "OLD CZECH LEGENDS.
In few countries are puppets held in such warm affection
as in Czechoslovakia. Today they are almost a national
institution3,000 amateur groups operate regularly in
schools, co-operatives and cultural centres, and puppet thea¬
tres are to be found in practically every town in Czecho¬
slovakia.
Long before the dream of the Czechs to possess a national
theatre was realized, the puppet stage was, in fact, the peo¬
ple's national theatre. Puppets have always been deeply
rooted in Czech history and even participated in the long
struggle for national freedom. When the Habsburgs tried to
stifle Czech nationalism, travelling puppet theatres helped
to keep it alive. In the First World War they sparked popu¬
lar resistance movements. Josef Skupa, today an interna¬
tional figure and a Czech State artist, used the voice of his
mocking little Kasparek half brother to Punch, Guignol
and Pulcinellato rouse the people of Pilsen against the
Austro-Hungarian monarchy.
During the last war, Skupa's marionettes again spoke out
for freedom through his now internationally famous cha¬
racters, Spejbl, the vain, narrow-minded father, and Hurvi-
nek, his young scamp of a son, cheeky, argumentative and
full of mischief. Spejbl and Hurvinek were soon locked up
in a cupboard at Gestapo headquarters in Pilsen, and Skupa
found himself in a prison cell at Dresden. But other coura¬
geous marionettists like Jan Malik took his place and their
secret performances were seen by hundreds of people".
In 1948, a law placed puppetry on a level with all other
branches of drama. Today Czechoslovakia has ten profession¬
al marionette art theatres and even a Chair of Puppetry in
the Prague Academy of Musical Arts. In schools and colleges
the puppet show is widely used as a means of developing
self-expression, arts and crafts and as -an effective way of
teaching different subjects.
Since 1946, Czechoslovakia has received international
acclaim for its work in the new field of film puppetry. Films
by Hermina Tyrlova, Karel Zerman and especially Jiri Trnka
have won leading awards at the Festivals of Venice, Cannes,
Brussels, Edinburgh and elsewhere. Jiri Trnka, a former
student of Josef Skupa, produced three full-length puppet
films between 1947 and 1951. In Spalicek (The Czech Year)
his puppets brought to the screen six merry peasant festi¬
vals. His "The Emperor and the Nightingale" was based on
Hans Anderson's fairy tale and in "'Prince Bayaya" he
recounted one of his country's best-known folk tales.
Hermina Tyrlova scored a great success with "The Toys'
Revolt", an echo of Nazi occupation days, in which she used
both living actors and puppets, as did Karel Zerman, in his
"Christmas Dream."
Drawing on the rich ancient traditions of the Czech
puppet theatres, these masters have succeeded in developing
a new art form in today's popular medium of entertainment
the cinema.
61
]]>
</page>
<page number="62">
<![CDATA[
CZECHOSLOVAKIA (Cont'd;
Josef Skupa, papa
of two national heroes:
Spejbl, vain and
narrow-minded...
... his son Hurvinek,
mischievous scamp
DANCING GRACE, in coloured, blown glass, "came to life" in "Inspiration" In which
Karel Zerman explored a new technique in puppet film making. (Czech. State Film Photo)
62
]]>
</page>
<page number="63">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 3-4. 1955
ONE FOR THE ROAD. A puppet film produced by Bretislav Pojar
and Jiri Trnka was a warning to motorists that "That Extra Glass" may
be the quickest way Into the ditch. A motor-cyclist on his way to Pilsen
stops "for a quick one" ii a wayside inn, stays to join in a wedding cele
bration. One toast leads to another, and in the general conviviality
the motor-cyclist has one drink too many. During the rest of his jour¬
ney he passes everything on the road, overtakes a train and even tries
to race an aeroplane till he comes to grief. (Czech. State Film Photos.)
63
]]>
</page>
<page number="64">
<![CDATA[
Unesco in pictures*
I
I
Welcome visitors in
an Indian village
At Yelwal, In Mysore, India, Unesco trains
students from many parts of the world for
international work in fundamental education.
Photo (far right) shows a social science team
being welcomed at a small village where it
carried out a social survey of the people,
their numbers, needs and the pattern of their
life. Friendly personal contact and the accu¬
mulated knowledge and experience from all
countries these are the foundations on which
fundamental education programmes are built.
When the village education programme began
a member of the Unesco Centre's literacy
team recited prayers with the villagers.
These prayers were later written on black¬
boards and posters and printed in booklets
and the villagers read them for the first
time. (Unesco photos).
U.N. competition makes multi-colonred carpet
TWO THOUSAND DESIGNS recently
filled a large conference hall in Unesco House,
Paris. They were spread on the floor like
a gay, multi-coloured carpet (above), for there
was not enough wall space to take them
all. They were entries in a United Nations
Day poster design contest organized by the
French liaison committee of non-governmen¬
tal organizations and the French United
Nations Association, and open to all French
schoolchildren between the ages of eleven
and eighteen. A jury of experts selected
200 designs for exhibition in Unesco House.
Of these, fifty were awarded prizes or com¬
mendations and are being sent to U.N. head¬
quarters in New York. Below, left, poster
by Yves Morillon aged 15 of Paris, winner
of the U.N. prize, and (right) that of Odette
Dumont, aged 13, of Montrouge, Seine
winner of the Unesco Prize. (Unesco photos).
64
]]>
</page>
<page number="65">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 3-4. 1955
Javelin lessons
in t II c desert
Physical education has been given a big
boost in Libyan schools since teachers
attended special courses organized by
Unesco's ten-man technical assistance
mission to Libya. Here, with their
javelins at the ready, are some of the
teachers who attended one of the
physical training courses. Libyan tea¬
chers gave up their summer holidays
to learn these and other new lessons
from members of the Unesco mission
which has been helping the Libyan
Government to improve teacher train¬
ing facilities and text book production.
A special course in arts and crafts was
run by an expert in manual education.
Far left, some of his teacher-students
put finishing touches to models of im¬
proved village layouts. (Unesco photos)
Young 'Uncscans'
of New York City
Twelve hundred members of New
York's High School Unesco Coun¬
cil, which is composed of Unesco
Clubs throughout the city, recently
visited United Nations headquar¬
ters for studies and discussions on
the United Nations and Unesco.
The visit was made during the
Council's Fourth Annual Conference.
Gathering in the U. N. General
Assembly Hall, the students (left)
heard talks by Andrew W. Cordier,
Executive Assistant to the U.N.
Secretary-General ; Dr. Solomon V.
Arnaldo, Director of Unesco's New
York Office, and Mr. Richard Peder-
son, Adviser on Economic and
Social Affairs at the United States
Mission to the U.N. Right, students
listening to Dr. Arnaldo in U. N.
Assembly Hall. (U. N. Photos)
]]>
</page>
<page number="66">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom
I*AUSE FOR THOUGHT:
Travellers who usually hurry
through one of Paris's largest
railway stations nowadays stop
to take a look at an exhibition
which tells the story of man's
long fight for human rights.
Organized by the French Na¬
tional Commission for Unesco,
the exhibition stresses one par¬
ticular article in the Universal
Declaration of Human Rights,
adopted by the U.N. General
Assembly in 1948 Article 13
which deals with the right to
travel freely. The exhibition
will eventually move to other
French railway stations.
ISOTOPE TRAINING:
The first radio-isotope re¬
search and training centre in
the Middle East will shortly
begin operations in Cairo.
The Egyptian Government
announces that teams of
Egyptian doctors, physicists,
chemists and other scientists
will study radio-activity
problems in U.S. universities
and then return to work at
the Cairo centre.
'European' high
SCHOOL: The first "European"
secondary school Is now operat¬
ing in Luxembourg on the
principle of "five nationalities
Belgian, Dutch, French, Ger¬
man and Italian four langua¬
ges and one teaching method."
Altogether, in the new school, in
a primary school opened a year
ago, and in a kindergarten, a
community of 225 children now
receive a common education in
four different languages.
ART ON TOUR: Prints of
works by Japanese artists,
many of which have never
' been shown outside Japan
before, are now being seen by
people in twenty countries
through Unesco Travelling
Exhibitions. Twenty sets of
one hundred prints, repres¬
enting the work of Japan¬
ese artists from the 11th to
the 19th centuries, were
offered by Unesco to its
member states. A new Unes¬
co Travelling Exhibition of
colour reproductions of Chi¬
nese paintings is now also
starting on a world tour. (See
Unesco Courier, No. 1, Vol. 8,
1955.)
AlD FROM NORWAY:
Seventy-two Norwegian spe¬
cialists now work in various
parts of the world under the U.N.
Technical Assistance Program¬
me, and others are employed at
Travancore, India, under Nor¬
way's own India Aid Pro¬
gramme. In addition, 244 stu¬
dents from underdeveloped
countries have studied in Nor¬
way under U.N. Fellowships.
This year, Norway intends to
raise its U.N. Technical Assist¬
ance contribution sharply
probably donating four times
the money it gave last year.
INDIA'S NEW INDUS¬
TRY: India's first news¬
print factory recently start¬
ed production at Nepa Nagar
in the State of Madhya
Predesh. It will shortly be
producing 100 tons of news¬
print a day one third of the
country's newsprint require¬
ments. Though it is using
imported chemical pulp at
the start of production, the
factory's own chemical sec¬
tion will be ready before the
end of the year.
II OW OTHERS LIVE:
Swiss master bakers, Italian
fishery workers, Danish taxi-
drivers, German postal em¬
ployees, Swedish printers and
people holding many other
different jobs in 17 countries
will be packing their bags dur¬
ing the next few months and
setting off on Unesco study
tours to see how their opposite
numbers in other countries live
and work. Altogether some
1,200 workers will benefit from
the 1955 study tours sponsored
by Unesco which help to open
international travel to many
people whose budgets would
otherwise keep them at home.
Unesco is paying the travel ex¬
penses of 68 groups of from 10
to 25 persons while the people
concerned and their organiz¬
ations meet other expenses.
Since 1952, 139 workers' groups
numbering 3,270 travellers have
taken part in Unesco study
tours.
ATOMS FOR PEACE:
Demonstrations by an oper¬
ating atomic reactor will be
given at the forthcoming
U.N. International Atoms for
Peace Conference. The Con¬
ference meets in Geneva
in August and will bring
together scientific leaders
from all parts of the world
in search of fuller peaceful
applications of nuclear ener¬
gy. Demonstrations of the
reactor, which will be built
in the United States, will
enable scientists and techni¬
cians at the meeting to ob¬
serve some of its research
possibilities. They will be
able to operate the controls
to start and stop nuclear
chain reactions. From a
small platform on top of the
reactor a lecturer will direct
the demonstrations and ex¬
plain the reactor's operations
to the general public attend¬
ing the Geneva Conference.
(See special issue of the
Unesco Courier, "The Pro¬
mise of Atomic Power", No.
12, Volume 7, 1954.)
Going to town: Just
as city-bred children benefit
physically from country holi¬
days, so those from rural areas
can gain educationally from vis-
sits to cities. In Poland, during
the past three years, educational
authorities have helped more
than 100,000 country children to
spend their holidays visiting his¬
torical monuments, theatres,
art galleries and other places of
interest in Polish cities. Last
year, eight holiday centres in
the chief towns were opened for
these children.
* COLLECTED CLASSICS:
Two of Latin America's great
classics have just been trans¬
lated into French and added
to Unesco's "Collection of
Representative Works". One
is Gabriel René Moreno's
"The Last Days of the High
Peru Colony" a 19th cen¬
tury history of the region
that is now Bolivia. The
other, "Tabaré", by Uru¬
guay's famous poet, Juan Zo-
rilla de San Martin, is an
epic poem which helped the
growth of a national senti¬
ment among the Uruguayan
people. Unesco's collection
of translations from the
world's classics now numbers
twenty-one.
UNESCO'S STAMP :
The United Nations is issuing
its second commemorative stamp
of 1955 to honour the work of
unesco. Designed by George
Hamori of Israel, the stamp
shows the agency's symbol, a
Doric temple whose pillars are
formed by the letters u-n-e-s-
c-o. The stamp will be printed
in three and eight cent denomi¬
nations, and will be on sale to
collectors only in Europe.
* FISHING FLEET FOR
KOREA : Almost the entire
Korean fishing fleet was des¬
troyed during the recent war,
depriving the 'country of an
important source of income
and food. One of the pro¬
jects undertaken by the Uni¬
ted Nations Korean Recon¬
struction Agency is to rebuild
the fleet at a cost of
$ 3,500,000. Today shipyards
all over the country are par¬
ticipating in the building
programme. The first five
fishing boats were launched
in Pusan in January 1955.
Unesco's National Distributors from whom
the English edition of THE COURIER can be
obtained are listed below. Other Unesco
Distributors are listed in the French and
Spanish editions of THE COURIER
Australia : Oxford University Press, 346,
Little Collins Street, Melbourne.
Austria : Wilhelm Fnck Verlag, 27, Gra¬
ben, Vienna I.
Burma : Burma Educational Bookshop,
551-3 Merchant Street, P.Q. Box 222,
Rangoon. "^
Canada : University of Toronto Press,
Toronto.
Ceylon : Lake House Bookshop, The Asso¬
ciated Newspapers of Ceylon, Ltd., P.O.
Box 244, Colombo I. Rs. 5.
Cyprus : M. E. Constantinides,»P.O B. 473,
Nicosia.
Denmark : Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd , 6 Nor-
regade, Copenhagen, K.
Egypt : La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9, Adly
Pasha Street, Cairo.
E thiopia : International Press Agency,
P.O.B. 120, Add.s-Ababa.
NATIONAL DISTRIBUTORS
Finland : Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, 2 Kes-
kuskatu, Helsinki.
Formosa : The World Book Company Ltd.,
99, Chung King South Rd, Section I,
Taipeh.
France : Sales Division, Unesco, I 9, Avenue
Kléber, Pans- I 6e.
Germany : Unesco Vertrieb fur Deutsch¬
land, R. Oldenbourg, München.
Greece : Librairie H. Kauffman, 28, Rue
du Stade, Athens.
Hong Kong : Swindon Book Co., 25 Nathan
Road, Kowloon.
India: Orient Longmans Ltd., Bombay, Cal¬
cutta, Madras : sub-depots : Oxford Book
& Stationery Co., Sandia House, New
Delhi; Rajkamal Publications Ltd., Hima¬
laya House, Bombay 7. Rs. 4.
Indonesia : G.C.T. van Dorp & Do. NV.,
Djalan Nusantara, 22, Djakarta.
Iran : Iranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
Iraq : McKenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
Israel : Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd., 35,
Allenby Road, P.O. Box 5154. Tel-Aviv.
Jamaica : Sangster's Book Room, 99, Har¬
bour Street, Kingston; Knox Educational
Services, Spaldings.
Japan : Maruzen Co, Inc., 6 Ton-Nichome,
Nihonbashi, Tokyo.
Jordan : J.I. Bahous and Co , Dar-ul-Kucub,
Salt Road, Amman.
Korea : Korean National Commission for
Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
Liberia : J. Momolu Kamara, 69, Front
and Gurley Streets, Monrovia
Malayan Federation and Singapore :
Peter Chong and Co., P.O. Box 135,
Singapore.
Malta : Sapienza's Library, 26, Kingsway,
Valletta.
Netherlands : N V. Martinus Nijhoff,
Lange Voorhout 9. The Hague.
New Zealand: Unesco Publication s Centre ¡
100, Hackthorne Rd., Chnstchurch. ;
Nigeria : C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box 174, ¡
Lagos. i
Norway : A/S Bokhjornet, Stortîngsplass, 7, '
Oslo. ,|
Pakistan : Ferozsons Ltd., Karachi, Lahore, '
Peshawar. Rs. 3. <
i
Philippines : Philippine Education Co., '
Inc., 1 1 04 Castillejos, Quiapo, Manila. 3.00
Surinam : Radhakishun and Company Ltd.,
(Book Dept.), Watermolenstraat 36, Para¬
maribo.
Sweden : A.B.C.E. Fritzes Kungh Hov-
bokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 16.
Thailand ; Suksapan Panit, Arkarn 9,
Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok. 20 ticals.
Union of South Africa : Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Ltd., P.O. Box 724, Pretoria.
United Kingdom : H.M. Stationery Office,
P.O. Box 569, London S E.L
U.S.A. : Unesco Publications Service, 475
5th Ave., New York 17. N.Y.
66
]]>
</page>
<page number="67">
<![CDATA[
Courier COMINO IN NEXT
11 /MJTU'C IC C HE
UNTH 5 IjsUe
OPERATION FISH
Exploiting new resources from the sea. Latest developments in marine
research. International action to harvest sea crops. Fish as a symbol
in different nations and in history.
Don't miss these
future Issues
MAN AND THE DESERT. An excit¬
ing 60-page issue on the latest world-wide
efforts to make the desert bloom. Deve¬
lopments in solar energy, wind energy,
fresh water from sea, soilless cultivation,
artificial rain-making, myths about the
tropics, old rain gods of primitive peoples.
HOW NATIONS SEE THE FOREIGNER.
How the French farmer sees the stranger. A
Britisher looks at Americans. A Britisher dis¬
sects British character, etc. Do you have to
live among people to know or understand them?
WELCOME STRANGER. Interna¬
tional fellowships and exchange of
people between countries as one of the
most powerful roads to building peace
and international understanding. Unes¬
co's exchange programme. Student and
teacher exchange, workers abroad.
WHAT'S WRONG WITH OUR TEXT¬
BOOKS? Distortion of history in school
books. Textbook publishinga great
unknown industry.
ARE WOMEN INFERIOR BEINGS?
Advances in women's status in recent
years in education, politics, society.
SUBSCBIBE TO THE UNESCO COURIER TODAY. - English, French, Spanish, U.S. editions
ONE FULL YEAR'S SUBSCRIPTION AT THE AMAZINGLY LOW PRICE OF :
300 French francs; 6/-; $1.50 or equivalent in local currency (U.S. edition $2.50).
]]>
</page>
<page number="68">
<![CDATA[
MIRROR OF HEALTH
This year, World Health Day slogan is "Clean
Water Means Better Health". Here, boys
in French Cameroons, Equatorial Africa, splash
happily under new school shower and shun
disease-infested swimming hole. Seepage 18.
(WHO Photo by Pierre Pittet).
]]>
</page>
</document>
