<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="068910eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
HC.5L. t toy W
A WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
m
Twenty-five
centuries of
(9th year)
Price: 9d. (U. K.)
40 francs (France)
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Rudyard Kipling once described the great carvings which flourished in north-west India and Pakistan between the
1st and 7th centuries A.D. as "Greco-Buddhist sculptures, dons savants know how long since, by forgotten workmen
whose hands were feeling, and not unskilfully, for the mysterious Grecian touch." Actually the term "Greco-
Buddhist" still used today to describe this school of architecture and sculpture is misleading. It is more closely
allied to Roman art. Many Roman coins and statuettes from Alexandria, Syrian glass and Roman metals have been
unearthed in this "easternmost region of the Roman Empire." Some of the most notable examples of Greco-Roman
art are found in the region of Gandhara from which this detail, above, is taken. It depicts Buddha descending from
Heaven watched by worshippers The resemblance to the cathedral sculptures of medieval Europe is striking.
Victoria and Albert Museum
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
N° 6
9th
PAGE
JUNE 1956
YEAR
CONTENTS
3 EDITORIAL
5 GAUTAMA THE BUDDHA
Teacher of infinite compassion
By Sarvepalli Radhakrishnan
10 ACROSS THE FACE OF ASIA
By Anil de Silva Vigier
(I) The Spread of Buddhist Culture
13 (2) The Spread of Buddhist Art
15 INDIA : FOUNTAIN-HEAD OF BUDDHIST ART
22 ANIMALS TOUCHED BY A MAGICAL WAND
Buddhist Jataka tales
By Jeannine Auboyer
25 500 MILLION FOLLOW THE 'MIDDLE WAY'
26 CITY OF TOWER FACES
Angkor Thorn summit of Khmer art
29 THE FOREST OF STUPAS
Burma's ancient holy city of Pagan
34 NO RIGHT TO DESPISE A FELLOW CREATURE
By G.P. Malalasekara
36 THE CAVE OF THE THOUSAND BUDDHAS
Tun Huang and other Chinese cave temples
42 THE DHAMMAPADA: «PATH OF VIRTUE*
43 BOROBUDUR «THE TERRACED MOUNTAIN*
Java's monument to Buddhism
46 THE IMAGES OUTNUMBER THE PEOPLE
Thailand's wealth of Buddhist art
49 WORLD'S TALLEST BUDDHA
Afghanistan's 173 feet high Bamiyan statue
50 PAINTED BANNERS FROM THE HIMALAYAS
The strange art of Tibet and Nepal
52 THE WOODEN IMAGE FLOATED ASHORE
Japan's unique Buddhist sculpture
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organi¬
zation
Editorial Offices
Unesco, 19, Avenue Kleber, Paris 16, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Circulation Manager
Jean Groffier
U.S.A. : Henry Evans
Individual articles not copyrighted may be reprinted from THE UNESCO
COURIER but must be accompanied by the following credit line: "Reprinted
from UNESCO COURIER". Signed articles reprinted must carry the author's
name. Prints of non-copyright photos are available on request.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied by an inter¬
national reply coupon covering postage.
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of THE UNESCO
COURIER
Annual subscription rates of THE UNESCO COURIER : 8/-; $2.50 or 400
French frs or equivalent.
(MC. 56.1.103 A)
COVER PHOTO
The "Smile of Bayon" is seen on this
head of a Buddhist monk carved by an
unknown 1 3th century sculptor and
found In the ruins of the Bayon temples
at Angkor, ancient capital of Cambodia.
The smile of Bayon has been called
"without doubt the supreme expression
of Buddhist beatitude". Head is presum¬
ed portrait of King Jayavarman VII, build¬
er of the Bayon Temple. (See paget26).
Copyright Magnum-Bischof
One of the great merits of our present century is the
attempt being made to know and to appreciate the
arts of other lands, other peoples and ages. The
parochial attitude of the past, marked so often by snap-
judgment antipathy of blind-spot vision, has been super¬
seded by a broader, more catholic taste and a sincere
desire to understand and love works of art which are the
expression of cultures wholly different from our own.
We have come a long way from the astounding statement
made by Ruskin that the art of India was "unnatural...
and wanting in truth," or such peremptory announcements
concerning Asian art as the one made by a European
professor of archaeology who wrote in 1864: "There is no
temptation to dwell at length on the sculpture of Hindu¬
stan. It affords no assistance in tracing the history of
art, and its debased quality deprives it of all interest as
a work of art."
Yet even in more recent times, the appreciation of the
ancient arts of Asia has often been hampered by those
who have most ardently attempted to interpret them to
the newcomer. As one writer recently expressed it in
India, we must take care lest a "smokescreen of spiritual¬
ism" be laid between the uninitiated beholder and the
simple aesthetic enjoyment of art, with the result that
one is left with the feeling that without a full knowledge
of the philosophical writings and religious canon of
Buddhism, for example, no approach to the understand¬
ing of Buddhist art can be made.
Buddhist art is essentially religious, but the arts of.
Egypt, of Medieval Europe, of Negro Africa and the ancient
Mayas were religious too. Are we to say that no attempt
to grasp the beauty of Luxor or Chartres can be made
without a fine knowledge of their religious portent?
In this special issue, prepared on the occasion of the
2,500th anniversary of the Supreme Enlightenment and
death (pari-nirvana) of the Buddha, the Unesco Courier
has sought to give its readers both a panorama of the
great masterpieces of sculpture, architecture and painting
of Buddhist art in Asia, and a glimpse of some of the
ethical ideals and the message of peace, gentleness and
mercy which Buddhism, "one of the noblest edifices of
thought ever created by the human spirit," has inspired.
Buddhists, particularly in South Asia, celebrate the
birth, the Enlightenment and the death of the Buddha on
May 24, the day of the May full moon. But for the
2,500th anniversary special festivals, ceremonies and
pilgrimages will continue for one full year. As the birth¬
place of Buddhism, India has made elaborate arrange¬
ments for the historic event. At the great historical
centres of Buddhismthe village of Lumbini, outside
Kapilavastu (now in Nepal) where Buddha was born; Bodh
Gaya where he achieved Enlightenment, Sarnath, where
he preached his first sermon, and Kusingar where he
died pilgrims have already arrived from all parts of the
world.
In November, a congress on Buddhism and an exhibition
of Buddhist art will coincide with Unesco's 9th General
Conference in New Delhi, and with a symposium organized
there by Unesco on Buddhism's contribution to philosophy,
literature and the arts during its 2,500 years' history.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
Gautama the Buddha
Teacher of infinite compassion
by Sarvepalli Radhakrishnan
Vice-President of the Republic of India
IN Gautama the Buddha we have a master mind from the
East second to none so far as the influence on the
thought and life of the human race is concerned, and
sacred as the founder of a religious tradition whose hold
is hardly less wide and deep than any other. He was born
in the year 563 B.C., the son of Suddhodana, at Kapilavastu
on the Nepalese border one hundred miles north of
Benares. The spot was afterwards marked by the emperor
Asoka with a column which
is still standing. His own
name was Siddhartha, Gau¬
tama being his family name.
His mother died seven days
after his birth, and Suddho-
dana's second wife, Mahapra-
japati, brought up the baby.
In due course Gautama mar¬
ried his cousin Yasodhara
and had a son Rahula. Gau¬
tama was of a religious tem¬
perament and found the
pleasures and ambitions of
the world unsatisfying. The
ideal of the mendicant life
attracted him and we hear
frequently in his discourses of
the "highest goal of the holy
life for the sake of which
clansmen leave their homes
and go forth into homeless-
ness". The efforts of his
father to turn his mind to
secular interests failed, and at the age of twenty-nine he
left his home, put on the ascetic's garb, and became a wan¬
dering seeker of truth. This was the great renunciation.
Determined to attain illumination by the practice of
asceticism, he withdrew with five disciples to Uruvela, "a
pleasant spot and a beautiful forest", soothing to the senses
and stimulating to the mind. He started a series of severe
fasts, practised exercises of meditation, and inflicted on
himself terrible austerities. Weakness of body brought
lassitude of spirit. Though often during this period he
found himself at death's door, he got no glimpse into the
riddle of Ufe.
He therefore decided that asceticism was not the way to
enlightenment and tried to think out another way to it.
He remembered how once in his youth he had an
experience of mystic contemplation, and now tried to
pursue that line. It was then that he found the answer.
In the last watch of the night "'ignorance was destroyed,
Sir Sarvepalli RADHAKRISHNAN, one of the greatest thinkers of mod¬
ern Asia, has done much to explain the philosophy and religions of the
orient to the western world. Among his many works: " Indian Philosophy" ,
"East and West in Religion", "Eastern Religions and Western Thoughts" ,
"Religion and Society", an English translation of Dhammapada and "Gau¬
tama the Buddha".
SACRED STUPAS AND GIANT
STATUES. After the Buddha's
death and cremation, his ashes were
divided into eight parts and
enshrined in eight great stupas, or
pagodas (the number 8 corresponds
to the Noble Eightfold Path of
Buddhism and The Wheel of the
Law with Its eight spokes). Later,
thousands of these domeortower-
like shrines to house sacred relics
of the Buddha or his disciples were
built in cities and in the countryside
throughout the Buddhist world.
Upper photo shows ancient Ruwa-
weli Stupa, at Anuradhapura, Ceylon,
restored in the I 9th century. Giant
statues, below, depict the Reclining
Buddha (46 feet long) at the
moment of his death, and beside
him his favourite disciple, Ananda
(23 feet high). These colossal
1 2th century statues were cut from
solid rock at Polonnaruva, Ceylon.
knowledge had arisen... as I sat there, earnest, strenuous,
resolute". Gautama had attained bodhi or illumination
and becomes the Budhha, the Enlightened One.
Buddha started on his ministry after much hesitation.
He not merely preached, which is easy, but lived the kind
of life which he taught men should live. He adopted a
mendicant missionary's life with all its dangers of poverty,
unpopularity, and opposition.
In the deer park near the modern Sarnath "where
ascetics were allowed to dwell and animals might not be
killed", he preached his first sermon. Disciples began to
flock to him. At the end of three months there were sixty.
He said to them one day: "'Go now and wander for the
gain of many, for the welfare of many, out of compassion
for the world, for the good, for the gain and for the
welfare of gods and men. Let not two of you go the same
way. Preach .the doctrine which is glorious in the
beginning, glorious in the middle and glorious in the end,
in the spirit and in the letter: proclaim a consummate,
perfect and pure life of holiness." The
Buddha himself travelled far and wide for (Cont'd on
forty-five years and gathered many followers, next page)
Courtesy A. Vigier
THE BIRTH BENEATH THE TREE: The birth of Buddha as
depicted in an Nth century relief from Ananda Temple, Pagan, in
Burma. Maya, Mother of the Buddha holds a branch of the Sala tree
while the infant is seen emerging from above her right side. This
richly gilded relief has a contrasting background of deep red terracotta.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
GAUTAMA THE BUDDHA
(Cont'd} Test by logic and life
In view of the variety of counsel he advised his disciples
to test by logic and life the different programmes submitted
to them and not to accept anything out of regard for their
authors. He did not make an exception of himself. He
says: "Accept not what you hear by report, accept not
tradition: do not hastily conclude that it must be so. Do
not accept a statement on the ground that it is found in our
books, nor on the supposition that this is acceptable, nor
because it is the saying of your teacher."
With a touching solicitude he begs his followers not to
be hampered in their thought by the prestige of his name.
" Such faith have I, Lord",
said Sariputta (one of his
closest disciples) "that me-
thinks there never has
been nor will be nor is now
any other greater or wiser
than the Blessed One".
"Of course, Sariputta",
is the reply, "you have
known all the Buddhas of
the past?" "No, Lord."
"Well then you know
those of the future?" "No,
Lord." "Then at least you
know me and have pene¬
trated my mind thorough¬
ly?" "'Not even that,
Lord." "'Then why, Sa¬
riputta, are your words so
grand and bold?"
There is nothing esoteric
about Buddha's teaching.
"O disciples, there are
three to whom secrecy
belongs and not openness.
Who are they? Secrecy be¬
longs to women, not
openness; secrecy belongs
to priestly wisdom, not
openness; secrecy belongs
to false doctrine, not open¬
ness... The doctrines and
the rules proclaimed by
the perfect Buddha shine
before all the world and
not in secret."
There is little of what
we call dogma in the Buddha's teaching. With a breadth of
view rare in that age and not common in ours he refuses to
stifle criticism. Intolerance seemed to him the greatest
enemy of religion. Once he entered a public hall at Am-
balatthika and found some of his disciples talking of a
Brahmin who had just been accusing Gautama of impiety
and finding fault with the order of mendicants he had
founded. "Brethren", said Gautama, "if others speak
against my religion, or against the Order, there is no reason
why you should be angry, discontented or displeased with
them. If you are so, you will not only bring yourselves
into danger of spiritual loss, but you will not be able to
judge whether what they say is correct or not correct" a
most enlightened sentiment, even after 2,500 years of ener¬
getic enlightenment.
He denounced unfair criticism of other creeds. "It is",
he said, "'as a man who looks up and spits at heaven; the
6
THE GREAT DEPARTURE of the future Buddha from the palace
of his father, King Suddhodana. As Prince Siddhartha, he left his wife
and child and renounced a life of ease and plenty, setting forth on his
search for enlightenment. This major event is depicted here on a
fragment of an 1 Ith century fresco from Chortchuk, Central Asia.
spittle does not soil the heaven, but comes back and defiles
his own person."
There was never an occasion when the Buddha flamed
forth in anger, never an incident when an unkind word
escaped his lips. He had vast tolerance for his kind. He
thought of the world as ignorant rather than wicked, as
unsatisfactory rather than rebellious. He met opposition
with calm and confidence. There was no nervous irri¬
tability or fierce anger about him. His conduct was the
perfect expression of courtesy and good feeling with a
spice of irony in it.
On one of his rounds
he was repulsed by a
householder with words
of abuse. He replied:
"Friend, if a householdei
sets food before a beggar,
but the beggar refuses to
accept the food, to whom
does the food then be¬
long?" The man replied:
"Why, to the householder
of course."
The Buddha said:
"Then, if I refuse to ac¬
cept your abuse and ill
will, it returns to you, does
it not? But I must go
away the poorer because I
have lost a friend." Con¬
version by compulsion was
unknown to him. Prac¬
tice, not belief, is the
foundation of his system.
After many years of toil
and travel, the Buddha
died at the age of 80 in a
village in Utar Pradesh.
The message of the
Buddha was not only for
his age but for all time.
The impermanence of the
world, its sorrow and suf¬
fering provoked his reli¬
gious quest. When he
met the old man bowed
down with years, the dead
man being carried to the
cremation ground and the man stricken with a foul disease
as also the holy man who carried himself with great dignity
and detachment, he was distressed by the first three sights
and attracted by the serenity of the ascetic. Buddha felt
the threat of nothingness, of non-being which one expe¬
riences when one looks upon the passing world of birth and
death, of disease and old age. The question is whether we
can acquire strength and courage, whether we can discover
the centre of freedom in ourselves which will save us from
the insecurity of time, from the body of this death. Buddha
gives us the answer, " By deepening our awareness and by
changing ourselves". The way to change the world is to
change the nature of man.
This change of nature is not automatic: The
seed becomes a plant, the puppy becomes a (Cont'd on
dog, but the human being has to develop his pages;
potentiality consciously and deliberately. The
Skeel
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
LIFE OF POVERTY. This re¬
markable 2nd century tablet also
from Amaravati depicts the Eleva¬
tion of the Buddha's Begging Bowl.
As a religious mendicant the Buddha
carried an alms bowl and never
refused what was offered him for
his daily food. Today a life of
poverty is essential for a Buddhist
monk whose belongings include
only his robe, an alms bowl, a
needle, a string of beads to count
while meditating, a razor to shave
his head, and a filter to strain
insects from his drinking water lest
he inflict suffering on living beings.
Amaravati sculptures are often
marked by frenzied body move
ments as is seen in photo, left
Photos Govt. Museum. Madras
THE TALE OF THE MAD
ELEPHANT is recalled in this
medallion made between 2nd and
3rd century A.D., from Amaravati
in Andhra Province, southern India.
The legend associated with this
incident relates: "Now Devadatta,
a kinsman of the Exalted One, was
filled with a jealous fury and tried
to murder the Blessed One, for
when the Buddha was in Rajagriha
he caused an elephant to be mad¬
dened with intoxicating liquor and
sent him across the path of the
Buddha. The great beast, running
amok, saw the Blessed One ap¬
proach and was overcome by his
calm power and knelt before him."
Kneeling elephant is seen at right.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
GAUTAMA THE BUDDHA (Cont'd
Noble eightfold path to perfection
Buddha asks us to find the teacher within ourselves and
attain enlightenment. He asks us to develop strength of
spirit through meditation and moral discipline. He asks
us to abstain from injury to living beings, to refrain from
taking other people's possessions, to develop chastity of
body and mind, to refrain from telling lies and to avoid
intoxicants. He does not merely say, "Thou shalt not
kill". He says, "thou shalt remove the inward attitudes
towards other beings, of anger, of resentment, of exploi¬
tation, of the lust of the heart." His morality was not
one of outward conformity but of inward cleansing.
The text of his first sermon has come down to us.
There is no reason to doubt that it contains the words and
the ideas of the Buddha. Its teaching is quite simple.
Honolulu Academy of Arts
YEARS OF ASCETICISM, fasting and terrible austerities often brought Buddha to death's
door. During six years he underwent many fasts such as are hard for a man to endure and resisted
the attempts of King Mara, a demon, to tempt him away from his purpose. But he still got no
glimpse of the riddle of life and he decided that this was not the way to gain enlightenment. He
therefore broke his fast. This I 6th century statuette of The Penitent Buddha is from Fukien, China.
8
After observing that those who wish to lead a religious life
should avoid the two extremes of self-indulgence and self-
mortification and follow the middle way, he enunciates the
four truths about sorrow, the cause of sorrow, the removal
of sorrow, and the way leading to it.
For the removal of ignorance a strict morality is
essential. Simple goodness in spirit and deed is the basis
of his religion. The noble eightfold path represents a
ladder of perfection. Right views, right aspirations, right
speech, right action, right living, right effort, right mind¬
fulness, right contemplation. The eightfold path is more
than a code of morality. It is a way of life.
The Budhha gave a workable system for monks and lay
people. He laid down five moral rules binding on all
people, which are: refraining from
taking what is not given, from wrong¬
ful indulgence in the passions, from
lying and from intoxicants. It is not
abstention from work that he de¬
manded. A Jain layman asked him
if he taught the doctrine of inaction,
and the Buddha replied: "How
might one rightly say of me that the
ascetic Gautama holds the principle
of inaction? I proclaim the non-
doing of evil conduct of body, speech
and thought. I proclaim the non-
doing of various kinds of wicked and
evil things... I proclaim the doing
of good conduct of the body, speech
and thought. I proclaim the doing
of various kinds of good things."
In the Buddha's scheme of ethics,
the spirit of love was more important
than good works. "All good works
whatever are not worth one-sixteenth
part of love which sets free the heart.
Love which sets free the heart com¬
prises them. It shines, gives light
and radiance." "As a mother, at
the risk of her life watches over her
only child, so let every one cultivate
a boundless love towards all beings."
Respect for animal life is an in¬
tegral part of morality. A good
Buddhist does not kill animals for
pleasure or eat flesh. They are his
humble brethren and not lower
creatures over whom he has domi¬
nion by divine right. He does
not speak of sin but only of ignor¬
ance and foolishness which could
be cured by enlightenment and sym¬
pathy. When the individual over¬
comes ignorance, breaks the pow¬
er of his own deeds to drag him
back into expiation, ceases to desire
and to regret and attains enlighten¬
ment, he passes into the world of
being as distinct from that of exist¬
ence, being which is free from form
and formlessness, from pain and de¬
light, though that state is not human¬
ly conceivable. It is deliverance,
freedom from rebirth, Nirvana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
Honolulu Academy of Arts, Hawaii
At the age of 29 Gautama left his house, his young wife, his newly-born child and his parents. He wandered for
six years in search of Wisdom and Truth, accepting the teachings of well-known ascetics and practising self-mortifi¬
cation including starvation, without finding the answer. One day he found a beautiful place on the bank of a river
under a large tree not far from the town of Gaya and there he sat in meditation, determined to arrive at the truth.
While plunged in his thoughts he was tempted by the Demon Mara and his hordes. Despite the temptations he
remained calm and steadfast, plunged in meditation. It was then that he attained Supreme Wisdom or Enlighten¬
ment. He then rose and proceeded to Benares where he first undertook to spread his message. Photo shows a
Bodisattva (Gautama before he became the Buddha) meditating underthe Bodhitree. (Lung-Men, China 6th century)
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
From India across the face of Asia
THE SPREAD
OF BUDDHIST
CULTURE
by Anil de Silva Vigier
Two thousand five hundred years ago a great part of
the world was still plunged in the darkness of
ignorance and barbarism. New centres of civilization
had appeared in Greece and Italy, but the Parthenon had
still to be built and Rome was only a small town.
Yet already for , many centuries, in the Middle East,
China and India, men had known how to write and build ;
their ships travelled far and wide exchanging goods,
works of art and ideas. All over this antique world men,
becoming more and more masters of their own destinies,
felt a growing need for a more human creed. Buddhism
in India, Taoism in China and, five centuries later,
Christianity in the West, all played the same role : man
ceased to be dominated by superstition and was given
an opportunity to achieve his own salvation. Buddhism
spread its message in Asia as, later, Christianity spread
over Europe.
Two thousand five hundred years ago Gautama Buddha
lived and preached his doctrine. He taught that all men
were equal in the face of suffering. By his own example
he showed that suffering could be overcome by the
renunciation of desire and the elimination of ignorance.
This doctrine is today the living faith of many millions of
Asian people.
Buddha's message is essentially a peaceful one and
there is no instance in the whole history of Buddhism
where violence in the form of torture or war has ever
been used in its name. In a world of permanent conflicts,
Buddhism met man's eternal desire for peace. In India,
the Emperor Asoka (3rd century B.C.) after a bloody
war against the neighbouring Kalinga Kingdom, was
converted to Buddhism and issued his famous edict which
he caused to be carved on rock and stone throughout his
kingdom. It said : "' One hundred and fifty thousand
people were deported, one hundred thousand people were
killed, many times this number perished... Remorse fills
the King friend of the Gods since he has conquered
Kalinga. The conquest of an independent country means
murder, death or captivity for men. All are victims of
violence and death and separation from those who are
dear to them. These thoughts weigh heavily on the King
friend of the Gods...
'"Even if the number of victims in the conquest of
Kalinga were a hundred thousand times smaller, the
thought of this would afflict the King friend of the Gods.
Even if they were in the wrong the King friend of the
Gods believes we should have been as patient as possible.
The victory that is the best of all is the Victory of the
Mme Anil de Silva Vigier of Ceylon, is the first Asian woman to specia¬
lize in archaeology and art history, and has spent many years of study and
research on Buddhist painting and sculpture. She is the author of "The
Life of the Buddha" retold from ancient sources, published by the Phaidon
Press, London, in 1955. Mme Vigier has greatly assisted in the preparation
of this special issue.
Pakistan
Bamiyan
\ /
Kabul %/
AFGHANISTAN
AJANTA CAVES
(India)
Good Law (Buddhism) . This text
of the Law is engraved for my
sons and grandchildren so that
they will not dream of new
victories. Let them seek real
victories through the exercise of
patience..."
The world in which Buddhism
was born and spread was a world
of vast movements of men and
ideas, much vaster than we gen¬
erally imagine. In this world
India was, geographically, the
crossroads between Western and
Far Eastern civilizations. Both
the great land routes entered her
Northern passes from the West
through Persia and from the East
through China and Central Asia,
over the old silk caravan route.
On the maritime routes, Per¬
sian, Greek, Roman and Alexan¬
drian ships scoured the ports of
Gujerath and Konkan oh "the
west coast, and Coimbatore,
Andhra, Bengal and Ceylon in
the South. India was also the
port of call for Far Eastern ships
going westwards, and her own
ships sailed out in all directions.
Contacts between the Western
world and India were continuous.
The Persian Emperor Darius left
his great terraced palace at Per-
sepolis to lead an expedition into
the Punjab and the Indus valley
a few years before the death of
Buddha in the 5th century B.C.
Alexander's expedition in the fourth century B.C.,
bringing with it topographers and scientists, helped to
strengthen the land route kept up by the couriers of the
Persian monarchs. Alexander built a port and a fleet
on the Indus and his captain, Nearque, sailed down the
Indus, forging a maritime route between the Indus and
the Tigris. Alexander returned through Afghanistan with
elephants and Indian soldiers in his army.
The whole of North West India, Afghanistan, Gandhara
(Afghanistan and Pakistan territory) and the Punjab re¬
mained for centuries under a succession of Greek princes,
one of whom, Milanda (Menander), became a Buddhist.
These Greek kingdoms favoured the penetration of Greek,
Hellenistic and Roman culture. Greeks intermarried with
Indians and these colonies formed centres of a new
Greco-Roman Buddhist culture. The new culture develop¬
ed rapidly under the Kushana Empire which succeeded
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
UNESCO COURIER ' MAP
the Greeks in the 1st century A.D. (The Kushana were
nomads who invaded India from China and Central Asia
and whose emperors were converted to Buddhism)
More important than wars and conquests was the long
period of friendship between Alexander's successors, the
Seleucid kings in Persia and the Mauryan kings in North
India, whose palace was modelled on that of Darius at
Persepolis, Persia. Ambassadors were exchanged and for¬
eign merchants thronged the capital Pataliputra (today
Patna, capital of Bihar province, N.E. India). The Emperor
Asoka married a Greek princess and sent his missionaries
both to the East and the West. His emissaries to the
West, carrying the message of Buddha, reached Persia,
Egypt, Macedonia, Cyrenaica and N.W. Greece.
The Roman historian Pliny tells us that Rome bought
50 million sesterces worth of merchandise from India
every year: cotton from Malwa, lacquer and nard from
Pataliputra, indigo, spices and precious stones from Kon-
kan, jades, ivories, silk and elephants which the Romans
used in large numbers for their army and circus. Roman
coins of gold have been found in the North West
and along the coast of South India at Cannanore, Coim-
batore and Mahabalipurum with effigies of Augustus,
Caracalla, Claudius, Theodore and Constantine. A Roman-
Asian artist named Titus painted Buddhist frescoes at
Miran in Central Asia. Alexandrine merchants aided
Buddhist convents at Nasik and Junnar near Bombay.
History gives us only a glimpse of the vast movement
of men at this time: prisoners of war, recruits in various
armies (Indian archers excelled in the Persian army) , and
deserters who roamed about from place to
place; craftsmen, metal workers, ivory carvers (Cont'd on
(Indian ivories have been found in Pompeii); next page)
weavers, jewellers, sculptors and ceramists
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Buddhist Culture (Cont'd;
were sought after at any price and protected by great
merchants and prices.
Central Asia was composed of the regions of Bamiyan
(south of ancient Bactria in Afghanistan), and of Kashgar
and Kutsha, up to the frontier town of Tun Huang in
North West China. This territory, closed in between
immense mountains, the T'ien-chan or Celestial Mountain
in the North and the massifs of Karakorum and Kouen-
Lun in the south had two routes through the desert: the
northern one passing by the oases of Kashgar and Kutsha,
Kizil and Tourfan, and the southern one through Yarkand,
Khotan, Miran and Lobnor.
All of them met at Tun Huang. These were the princip¬
al arteries of Buddhist expansion in Central Asia and
China and all became powerful centres of Buddhist
.culture. Thousands of grottos were excavated and open-
air constructions were built. At Kizil alone, the Mingoi
or Thousand Grottos (not to be confused with the Cave
of the Thousand Buddhas at Tun Huang, see below) were
cut out, painted and carved by hundreds of artisans from
the Middle East, India and Chinai
Cavaliers escorted Hsuan Tsang
HsuAN Tsang the famous Chinese scholar who made
his pilgrimage to India by the northern route in the
7th century A.D., leaves us an unforgettable account
of his journey through burning deserts and snow-clad
passes, whose hardships were relieved only by the
luxury and plenty of these oasis kingdoms in Central Asia.
Of Kutsha he says: "The Kingdom was about a thousand
li (1 li = 654 yards) to the East and West and six hundred
li to the South and North. The soil produces rice, red
millet, raisins, pomegranates, pears, prunes, peaches and
apricots. There are mines of gold, copper, tin and plum¬
bago. The climate is mild, the ways of the people pure
and honest and their writing is taken from India. Their
musicians are renowned for their skill in flute and guitar
playing."
We find too historians of the Chinese T'ang dynasty
talking of the charm of the women of Kutsha and re¬
cording that musicians and dancers from Kutsha were
seen at the Imperial Chinese fêtes, dressed in crimson
silk turbans. We are told that they san.g "The Meeting of
the Seventh Evening," "The Woman of Jade Takes Round
the Cup," and "The Battle of Flowers."
The frescoes of Kutsha, Kizil and Kumtura show us the
splendid cavaliers those who, Hsuan Tsang tells us,
escorted him on his way, for many of these paintings
were made by contemporaries of Hsuan Tsang. They
'show cavaliers wearing long boots, riding coats of silk
falling to the knees and taken in at the waist with metal
belts. Their tunics of blue, grey, white and olive green
were embroidered with pearls, lined and bordered with
fur. Their reddish hair was caught up with ribbons at the
neck. They must have formed a glorious sight with their
coloured and gilded banners and standards, sculptured and
painted with heraldic animals like the tiger and the
dragon. Hsuan Tsang returned to China laden with
manuscripts and images of the Buddha.
Marco Polo stopped here
Marco Polo, who in the 14th century seems to have
gone by Kashgar, Yarkand and Lobnor, also
stresses in his memoirs the luxury and refinement
in these kingdoms. For instance, writing of Khotan, he
says: "Everything necessary for human life is here in the
greatest plenty cotton, flax, hemp, grain, wine. The in¬
habitants cultivate farms and vineyards and have
numerous gardens. They also make a living by trade and
manufacture." Of Lobnor he writes: "'Travellers who
intend to cross the desert usually halt for a considerable
time, both to rest from their fatigues and to make the
necessary preparations for their further journey."
But most interesting for us is his obvious reference to
the large composition of the Parinirvana or The Death
of Buddha. He says: "The town of Camipichu is large
and magnificent. The bulk of the people worship idols
and they have many monasteries and abbeys built after
the manner of the country. In these are a multitude of
idols, some of wood, some of stone and some of clay. They
are all highly polished and covered with gilding. They
are carved in a masterly style. Some are of very great
size and others are small. The former lie in a recumbent
posture, the smaller figures stand behind them and have
the appearance of disciples in the act of reverential
salutation. Both great and small are held in extreme
veneration."
Bamiyan in Afghanistan was the halting place for ca¬
ravans either going to or coming from the difficult passes
of the Hindu Kush which barred the way into India. Into
the façade of the great cliff of Bamiyan, cave sanctuaries
with colossal Buddhas were carved and painted, two of
these images reaching 173 and 120 feet in height. Mer¬
chants paid craftsmen and artists to paint and carve
statues as thank-offerings for a safe journey.
Tun Huang at the other end of the route was developed
with the help of merchants and royal benefactors, for
the Wei, the T'ang and the Sung dynasties in China all
contributed to the creation of one of the most extraordi¬
nary monuments of Buddhist culture. Among the
hundreds of cave temples at Tun Huang the Cave of the
Thousand Buddhas, sealed up for centuries, housed price¬
less treasures of manuscripts and paintings on silk. Today
archaeologists look after the preservation of the Tun
Huang monuments, while dozens of artists make copies
from the innumerable frescoes. Yang Kang and Lung-
Men are two of the other great Buddhist sites in China.
The first time we hear of Buddhism in China is in
65 A.D. when the Han prince, Tch'ou protected a small
Buddhist community at Lo-yang. The translation of Bud¬
dhist texts from Sanskrit and Pali into Chinese was offi¬
cially encouraged by the Kushna Empire in India (30-224
A.D.). Kushna missionaries were heard reciting Buddhist
scriptures to a Chinese official named Ching Lu in the
2nd century A.D. In addition, Chinese travellers, mer¬
chants, imperial envoys and pilgrims came to India by
sea. In fact it is to Chinese historians that we owe the
only written accounts of these early kingdoms in South
East Asia.
Yi-T'sin saw a thousand monks
Eventually there were large monasteries and univer¬
sities in all the Buddhist countries of south east Asia,
Japan and Korea. Pilgrims in their thousands from
all over Asia thronged the great Buddhist universities of
Takila in Pakistan and Nalanda in India. Hostels were
built by the kings of Ceylon and Java to house the
students and pilgrims from their countries at Nalanda
and at Bodh Gaya in the Indian state of Bihar, where
Buddha attained enlightenment under the Bodhi tree.
Many of the ships leaving Bengal and the southern India
ports carried pilgrims and missionaries and, in addition to
the spices, precious stones, muslins and silks in their
holds, they bore statues of the Buddha made in the busy
centres of Mathura and Nalanda.
Yi-T'sin, another Chinese pilgrim, travelling by sea
stopped in the kingdom of Crivijaya (Malay peninsula),
for six months to learn Sanskrit grammar. He says :
"There are more than a thousand Buddhist monks whose
minds are set on study and good works. They examine
and discuss all possible subjects exactly as in India itself.
If a Chinese monk wishes to go to the West (India) in
order to read and study he cannot do better than stay
here for a year or two. He will then be fitted to go to
India for further study." Yi T'sin spent ten years at
Nalanda and later copied and translated into Chinese
many Buddhist texts, and also wrote his memoirs.
The coming of Buddhism, coinciding as it did with
increased trade and intercourse between Asian countries,
resulted in a period of intense intellectual life. The mes¬
sage of the brotherhood of men "No one is a Brahmin
or an outcast by birth, but one becomes a Brahmin or an
outcast by one's actions" (Vasala Sutra) was like rain
falling on parched earth. It stimulated a resurgence of
popular feeling just as Christ's message did in Rome in
early Christian times.
The richly human content of the Buddhist message was
the spiritual basis of an art which overrode the frontiers
of artistic expression, revitalized local traditions, making
them truly Buddhist and at the same time free expres¬
sions of national character. It was a message of hope. It
was a message of peace. And these two important factors
helped the development and maturity of a noble art that
has enriched the artistic traditions of the world.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
0
The
Spread of
Buddhist
Art
Two worshippers, one with folded arms, the
other carrying offerings, walk within an arched
niche in this fragment of sculpture made by
an artist of the Gandhara school in the 2nd to
3rd century A.D. The term Gandhara art
is applied to the school of architecture, sculp¬
ture and painting which flourished In north¬
western India and in parts of what are today
Pakistan and Afghanistan, from the 1st to
the 7th centuries A.D., the designation
coming from the ancient name of the region.
Gandhara art was outside the main stream
of Indian tradition, 'and though its subject
matter was Indian, In certain aspects it is
entirely Western in form. The surrounding
arch of the niche with leaf pendants, griffin
socles and draped figures leaning on Its outer
curve shown in this 10-inches high fragment,
is a well-known motif in Gandhara reliefs.
(See also the photograph shown on page 2)
Reproduced from " The Art of India " by Stella Kramrish, courtesy The Phaidon Press, London
The first notable monument to perpetuate the memory
of Buddha was built at Sanchi in Central India
some 2,200 years ago, three centuries after his death.
And although Buddhism disappeared from its native soil,
it spread to other countries of Asia to become the living
faith of millions (some 500 million people today) who in
their turn built monuments to honour Buddha throughout
the vast continent.
Some of these lay hidden for over a thousand years,
buried under sand or lost in the solitudes of impenetrable
tropical jungles. It is only in the past 70 years or so that
explorers and archaeologists have made systematic
studies of these monuments, hacking their way through
entangled undergrowth or digging in the desert wastes
to reveal art that has amazed the world great Buddhas
in eternal sleep or standing in watchful meditation.
The opening up of the Cave of the Thousand Buddhas,
at Tun Huang in Northern China, which had been walled
up since the 11th century A.D., brought to light the
thousand Buddhas whose mysterious smiles had remained
hidden in the dark ; frescoes with gorgeous colours, lapis
lazuli blue, ruby red, gold, topaz, emerald green, glowed
like jewels in the dim light of these incredible caves. In
Cambodia, Indonesia, Burma and Siam were abandoned
monuments around which huge trees had wrapped their
monstrous roots like octopus tentacles.
At the death of the Buddha his ashes were divided up
into eight parts; these were put in jewelled caskets and
enshrined in eight stupas. (A stupa is a sacred shrine
built as an enormous dome mounted on a pedestal with
a stylized umbrella, symbol of royalty, on top.) Around
the main Buddhist stupas containing important relics of
the Buddha or his disciples, there are often smaller ones
containing other reminders such as images, sacred
writings and prayers.
The choice of the dome-like form may have been
suggested by the sepulchral mounds or barrows of ancient
times. However, according to legend, the form of the
stupa was dictated by Buddha himself. It is said that
when his disciples asked him how they should honour his
remains, he laid out his garments one on top of the other
like the steps of a pedestal, placed his alms bowl over them
in reverse and held his stick over it to represent an
umbrella.
The first stupas gave birth to a million others. The
Emperor Asoka (3rd century B.C.) took the relics of
Buddha from seven of the eight original stupas and
redivided them, building another 84,000 stupas in which
to house them. Down the centuries the stupa modified its
form and in each country in Asia it took on distinct
national characteristics. The great stupa of Borobudur
in Java has been described by A.K. Coomaraswamy, the
eminent Indian archaeologist as being like "a ripe fruit
matured in breathless air". In China the stupa was given
a different form and name the pagoda. In Ceylon and
Burma where it is called a dagoba, and in Siam, it soared
skywards till its spire looked like an arrow.
Probably the most remarkable monuments of early
Buddhist art (3rd to 1st century B.C.) are the stupas at
Sanchi in the former Bopal State of India and at Bharut
and Bodh Gaya in Central and Northern India. The
striking thing about this early art is its profound kinship
with nature. Processions led by gaily caparisoned horses
and elephants, men, women and children, animals,
luxuriant vegetation, flowers, fishes, birds, deer, tree
spirits, snakes, are modelled with a natural quality which
carries with it the pulse of life, of tenderness,
of movement, and vitality. (Cont'd on
At this time, Buddha was portrayed symbo- next page)
lically. His birth scene simply showed his
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
BuddhlSt Art (Continued)
mother on a lotus flower with an elephant above. (His
mother, Maya, is said to have dreamt of an elephant
entering her womb; the lotus is an emblem of fertility).
A riderless horse symbolized the Great Departure, when
the Buddha left his palace, his wife and his child to
become an ascetic. The tree with an empty seat under¬
neath stood .for the attainment of Supreme Wisdom,
Buddha having sat in meditation under a tree* the sacred
Bodhi tree when he achieved Enlightenment. Buddha's
first sermon is represented by a wheel The Wheel of the
Law; and finally, the stupa represented death or salvation.
It is significant that early Christian art also expressed
itself in symbols, the Fish, the Dove, and the Cross, while
Christ on the Cross was only seen very much later.
About the 2nd century A.D. these symbols were replaced
by images of the Buddha himself. The horse got its rider,
the empty seat its occupant
and the stupa gave way to the
recumbent figure of Buddha
himself with two trees near his
head and feet and a group of
mourning disciples. The first
images of the Buddha were
made independently by the
sculptors of Mathura and
Gandhara in the north of
India. Mathura was the great
trading centre where Buddhist
images were made to be sold all
over Asia. The Mathura artists
used the earlier genii or yaksha
statue of pre-Buddhist cults as
their model ; the sculptors of
Gandhara and Taxila in the
north-west (Afghanistan and
Pakistan) used Greco-Roman
models of the Apollo for their
first Buddhas.
Later, the classical or Gupta
style, (5th century A.D.) of the
Buddha image was influenced by
both these early types, and all
three, the Mathura, the Gan-
dharan, and the matured classi¬
cal Buddha, influenced later
Buddhist art in general. Indian
influence on the art of Asia of
the time is reflected all over the
Continent in the flying figures
of the Yun Kang caves in
Shansi in China ; in the calm
nobility of the reliefs of Boro-
budur in Java, in the strength
of the early Siamese Buddhas,
in the frescoes of Pagan in
Burma, in the sensuousness of
the women of Sigiriya in Ceylon
and in the movement of the
dancers in the grottos of Kizil
in Central Asia.
The problem that faced the
Buddhist artists at this time was
how to standardize the Buddha's
image so that it would be easily
recognizable. Basing themsel¬
ves on the legend that tells how
Gautama the Buddha was born with certain signs of
greatness, the artists depicted him with a protuberance on
the skull, a third eye and long ear lobes. Right down to
the present time, images of Buddha have borne these
unmistakable characteristics.
The ancient Buddhist artists also depicted particular
moods, such as the tenderness and compassion which
characterize the Buddha. Unlike the later Christian
artists who portrayed Christ undergoing human suffering
on the Cross, they present the Buddha as one completely
detached from human pain, looking with compassion on
all humanity.
Buddha's message is conveyed through graceful gestures
or mudras, derived from earlier gesture language in
common use in ancient India, and from which the ela¬
borate Indian classical dance mudras are developed. Most
frequently the Buddha is shown seated on a lotus throne,
the lotus being in this case the symbol of purity; the
gestures express various things, a state of Illumination,
Meditation, Preaching, The Act of Giving or Charity,
Fearlessness or Reassurance, setting The Wheel of the
Law in motion, etc.
The main themes for the Buddhist artist were the Jataka
tales (stories of Buddha's previous lives, see page 22)
and incidents of his life. Side by side with these are
scenes of everyday life. The figures of prince and prin¬
cess, slave and peasant, soldier and merchant; ships sail¬
ing on rough seas, dancing girls whirling to the music of
ancient instruments in painted and sculptured pavilions;
pious devotees, standing or kneeling in reverence, holding
bronze incense burners; horsemen riding out, their steeds
galloping into space, leaving behind strong fortified
cities; landscapes with curious shaped mountains dotted
with streams and waterfalls;
pools covered with lotus; peas¬
ants ploughing the earth with
the help of bullocks; peacocks
strutting around formal gar¬
dens; women waiting for their
lovers...
The spread of Buddhism
throughout Asia came in several
waves emanating from India
from the first century A.D.
Bronze statues of the time have
been unearthed from the jun¬
gles of Annam, Borneo and
Celebes. Buddhist culture ap¬
parently superimposed itself on
the whole of South East Asia.
Nevertheless each region retain¬
ed much of its own personality
and character. In the 8th cen¬
tury A.D. Buddhist art began
to mature and flower in these
countries, gaining in movement
and vigour when local tradition
dominated. We see this clearly
at Borobudur (Java) in whose
1,400 panels and 504 statues of
the Buddha the Javanese pat¬
tern of composition, harmony
and repose are blended with
the Indian style of art. Later
Javanese art threw off this
influence and asserted its own
national characteristics.
tf,
Musée Guimet Archives, Paris
First portrayals of Buddha as a man rather than as a
symbol are accredited to the Gandhara school whose
images reveal its debt to Greco-Roman art in the 1st
century. The resemblance of some of the Buddha
heads to the Apollo Belvedere is apparent. Buddha's
cranial protuberance has been disguised by the adapta¬
tion of the top-knot of the Greek sun-god, though the
other marks of greatness the third eye between the
brows and the ear lobes are in the Indian tradition.
Chinese Buddhist sculpture
includes some of the most
beautiful religious sculpture in
the world. The Buddha as¬
sumes a strange smile, his eyes
half closed, robes fall in a
gracious pattern, scarves float
boldly, creating arabesques in
space, groups of court ladies
holding lotus buds walk out of
the rock on their way to worship,
flying figures plunge down like
soft curling clouds.
The Chinese Buddhist artist
produced countless steles which
he carved out in wood, stone and bronze, as these were
in great demand for shrines in Buddhist homes. These
steles were decorated with interlaced dragons, floral
motifs, the figures adorned with scarves, necklaces, brace¬
lets and diadems.
In China there are literally thousands of grottos and
temples. The Emperors of the Wei, the Sui and the T'ang
dynasties constructed grottos in the four main sites of
Tun Huang in the north (started in 366 A.D.) where there
are several hundred caves of all periods; Yun Kang
(455 A.D.) in Shansi ; Lung Men (494 A.D.) and Tien Lang
Chan (713 A.D.) near Lolang. Work on these sites went
on for generations. One of the earliest sculptors whose
name we know and whose work still stands is the artist
monk, Hai-t'ong, who in 73 A.D. finished the
colossal stone statue of the Buddha nearly C-0"1 ° on
170 feet high at the temple of Kai-ting fou. page S8)
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
Ml \
1
1
Ib^JWM , rfllt» i
1
W A
. ~» r. ^tWT^
(TT ¿\
| ? Í
1 1 W" 4
Í
I
.
^Ê i if
m i Jul
^b, **
jX
--.
a
***-*
^3jj ^»v- -.
JHÊ* -»..'
ELLORA GROTTOS (Central India) are a series of rock-cut temples and cave sanctuaries which
offer the only example In India of the monuments of three religionsBuddhism, Hinduism and
Jainism standing side by side. Carved out over many centuries they present a diversity of styles.
Above, inner hall of one the great Buddhist carved cathedrals at Ellora. The colossal figure of the
Buddha seated In teaching position at its far end is made more Impressive by the arrangement of
the natural lighting. The beam of light seen shining at the Buddha's feet comes into the
cave through a special window. Below, one of five pillared aisles in the Tin Thai ("three-storied")
cave at Ellora. At far end is the Buddha in the posture of calling the earth to witness.
Photos Eliot Elisofon, from "The Art of Indian Asia" by Heinrich Zimmer. Copyright Bollingen Foundation Inc..
INDIA
Fountain-head
and glory of
Buddhist Art
It is a great paradox that Buddhism, as
a religion, has practically ceased to
exist in its own birthplace, India, since
the 12th century A.D. But the art which
was created and developed in India under
the direct influence of Buddhism has
bequeathed to this country works of art
whose beauty and magnitude place them
among the foremost of mankind's cultural
treasures.
As Buddhism spread across the face of
the Asian continent and down into south
east Asia, Indian Buddhist art inspired and
influenced the painting and sculpture of
countries as far away as Japan and Java.
Episodes in the Buddha's life and legends
telling of his previous existences offered
painters and sculptors a rich variety of
themes with .which to express their faith.
For, as the texts of Buddhism declared that
the making of images led to heaven,
sculptors carved the image of the Enlighten¬
ed One in wood and stone and on the
living rock of mountainsides.
Little remains of the earliest Indian
Buddhist art that was done on perishable
buildings of wood and brick, carved in clay
and wood or painted on walls, wooden
panels, palm leaves and cloth. What do
remain are the rock temples and dwellings
of the early Buddhist monks like those at
Karli, Ajanta, Ellora and many other sites
whose semi-obscurity gave an added touch
of mystery to the paintings and sculpture
decorating their walls and pillars.
Other early storehouses of Buddhist art
are the stupas which, in their earliest forms,
like those at Sanchi and Bharut, are
moundlike shrines containing sacred relics
surrounded by railings and sumptuously
carved gates. Most art historians regard
the 4th century A.D. as the richest period
of India's Buddhist art. From the new
ideas brought by contacts with other lands
and from the greater skills and improved
techniques of the Indian painters and
sculptors came a great flowering of art.
This period can well be described as
"classic" in the sense of describing a
degree of perfection never achieved before
or since and in the perfect balance and
harmony of all elements stylistic and icono¬
graphie. The magnificent frescoes at
Ajanta are a reflection of this supremacy
of aesthetic achievement.
Despite the great evolution it underwent
and the many styles it developed during its
history of ten centuries, Indian Buddhist
art maintained a striking unity, due to the
fact that the various styles followed each
other in the same religious sites: the tem¬
ples and sanctuaries which art and faith
enriched down the centuries.
Buddhist art lost its vitality as the reli¬
gion declined in India, but its last phase
has enjoyed a prolongation of nearly a
thousand years in the Himalayan regions of
Nepal and Tibet.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
INDIA (Cont'd;
Copyright Allahabad Museum
Seen with
mirrors
The founding of the first
Buddhist shrine at Bodh Gaya
InN.E. India where the Buddha
achieved Illumination under
the Bodhi tree, Is attributed
to the great king Asoka In
the 3rd century B.C. Many
alterations have been made
since and elements exist there
from nearly every period of
Buddhist art. In the 7th and
8th centuries A.D. Buddhists
raised a magnificent edifice,
the Mahabodhi Temple (right),
In the form of a truncated
pyramid, to replace Asoka's
shrine. Between the 7th and
10th centuries the temple con¬
tained a statue of Sakyamuni
(one of Buddha's names :
"Sage of the Sakyaclan")
which stood In a dark chamber
and could be seen properly
only with the help of a mirror
to reflect the sun's rays.
The stupa at Bharut, a famous
Buddhist centre in the northern
part of central India, Is also
rich in examples of early
Buddhist art. Above, carving
on a pillar at Bharut depicts
a pyramid of acrobats flanked
by a yaksa and a yaks! (the
male and female guardians of
the treasures of *he earth).
Indian Embassy, Paris
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
Photo by Gilbert Etienne, taken from "Inde Sacrée", Copyright Éditions Ides et Calendes, Neuchatel, Switzerland. Unesco
AJANTA
Primitive austerity
to mellow richness
The Ajanta caves, northeast of Bombay, are justly renowned as one of the remarkable
collections of the world's religious art, and its enchanting frescoes and wall paintings
of Bodhisattvas, female figures, various flower and animal motifs are now fairly well known
In most countries (see The Unesco Courler Nos. I & II, 1954). Ajanta's sculpture,
architecture and decorative pillars, however, deserve to be better known too. The
earlier of the 29 cave-monasteries and chapels, all hewn from the rock In the 2nd century
B.C., reflect the simple, ascetic character of Hinayana Buddhism (see page 25). Photos
on this page are examples of 5th and 6th century A.D. Mahayana art. The primitive
austerity and purely spiritual appeal have completely vanished, and the art has become
rich, mellow and gracious under the Influence of the Gupta stylethe Golden Age of
Indian art. While in the earlier sanctuaries of Ajanta Buddha was never represented,
his ¡mages here shine forth in supramondane beauty, both in seated and standing positions
(photos above and below left; detail below right). An example of how the pillars and
panels were decorated with lavish bas-reliefs and carvings is seen in photo, above right.
1 ^*tj_»
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
INDIA (Continued)
KARLI
Rock cave chapel
The history of Buddhist architecture is defaced
by many sad and dark chapters, for the monu¬
ments were levelled time and again by con¬
quering invaders. India, like Europe, is covered
with ruins of princely towns and wondrous
temples. The most impressive religious re¬
mains from the period B.C., besides the great
stupas, are Buddhist cave-monasteries (viha-
ras) and chapels (chaitya) at Karli, Bhaja and
Nasik in the Western Hills near the Bombay
coast. There are others in the east in Orissa.
They have survived only because they were
carved in absolutely solid stone. Photo shows
one façade of Karli chaitya (2nd century B.C.)
bearing a finely sculptured donor couple.
Copyright Phaidon Press, London.
SANCHI
The pilgrims' way
The Great Stupa at Sanchi in the Indian
province of Bhopal is one of the oldest
and best preserved of early Buddhist
sanctuaries (1st to 2nd centuries A.D.).
Photos show: (I) The ambulatory of the
Great Stupa along which multitudes .of
pilgrims have walked around the monu¬
ment. (2-3) Damaged torsos of two
statues of a kind often found on the gates
to the Stupa. (4) One of the richly
decorated pillars flanking the East Gate.
Copyright Phaidon Press, London
1-2-3-4'Govt. of India photos.
ROCK-HEWN BEAMS. In the early period of Buddhism, wood"
and thatch buildings were raised to house images or sacred relics.
When these were replaced by structures built of stone or hewn from
18
Copyright Werner Bischof-Magnum.
cliffs and rocks, the sculptors often made replicas in stone of the former
wooden vaulting. The two fine examples shown above are 7th century
carvings at Aurangabad, in the state of Hyderabad, Central India.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
* * ^ .
J**1 ... -> *s=r-Ai
:l
5- kid i a/L^ï»
I9
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
A lesend carved in stone
Musée Guimet Archives
The ancient masters who carved bas-reliefs and friezes on the walls and doorways of
the sacred pagodas often took for their subject the Jataka tales (stories of the former
existences of the Buddha). Many of these tales are told in stone on one of the most
famous monuments of Buddhist art, the Great Stupa at Sanchi, in the Indian province
of Madhya Bharat, which contains some of the oldest (1st century A.D.) and best-
preserved of Buddhist carvings.
The carving on the North Gate, one of four main gates of the Sanchi Stupa, recounts the
story of Prince Visvantara (the last of Buddha's incarnations before he was born as
Gautama) who practised the virtue of "the perfection of giving." Prince Visvantara
(the name means "one who transcends or conquers all") was the most charitable of
men and could never refuse a request for alms.
According to the legend he owned a white elephant endowed with the magical power
of bringing rain. When the king of a nearby drought-stricken country asked for the
elephant, Visvantara gave it to him. This so angered the people that they banished the
prince, his wife and his two children. Thus began a series of trials by which Visvantara's
steadfastness and charity were put to the test. Other trials came when, as he left his
kingdom, two Brahmins stopped him and asked for the two horses pulling his chariot,
while a third asked for the chariot itself. The prince granted their requests,
The part of the story told in the South Gate frieze shown here begins on the right, when
the exiled prince and his wife Madri, have reached the foot of the Himalayas after a thou¬
sand hardships. They are shown clad as forest dwellers, tending the fire in front of
their leaf-domed hut.
In the peaceable jungle, the children, the animals and the trees are friends. Then,
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
Reproduced from "The Art of India" by Stella Kramrisch courtesy, of The Phaidon Press
The unselfish hermit-prince
while Madri has gone into the jungle to seek fruit and roots, a wicked Brahmin arrives
and asks Visvantara to give him his children as servants. Despite their tears and his
own anguish, Visvantara acquiesces. Even when he sees his children being tied and
beaten (left of centre) he does not interfere or protest.
Finally another Brahmin appears and asks the hermit-prince to relinquish his beloved
wife (centre left). But as the prince accepts, the trials end for the Brahmin is none other
than the god Indra who has come down to earth in disguise to subject the prince to this
supreme test. Directly above, Indra crowned and carrying his thunderbolts, is shown
reuniting the prince and his wife.
The rest of the relief reads from the left. It shows (bottom row) the prince's father,
who has purchased the children's freedom from the Brahmin, setting off to meet his
son and daughter-in-law. Top row, the parents and the children (mounted on an ele¬
phant) are seen regaining their kingdom.
Sanchi art, one of the earliest of Buddhist art forms, depicts such scenes from the Jataka
and from the life of Buddha in continuous narrative reliefs. The carved gateways of
the Sanchi Stupa mark the transition from ivory to stone carving and at least one of the
gateways was donated by the ivory carvers' guild of the Andhra Kingdom.
In effect, these carvings do give the impression of a delicate work of ivory, with their
figures crowded closely together and the great attention given to details. As one
critic has said, the carvings suggest that the artists were still so used to working on
small ivory that they did not adapt their technique to the greater space and freedom
afforded by huge blocks of stone.
. Musée Guimet Archives
V-rrffi'
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
TATAKA BIRTH TALES
Th
by
e jungle
a magical
le touched
wand
by Jeannine Auboyer
Curator, Musée Guimet, Paris
The ancient writings relating to Buddhism are neither
esoteric nor philosophical; they are a collection of
fables, legends and. tales about the previous lives of
the Buddha. This follows logically from the Indian doc¬
trine of the transmigration of souls which teaches that
the individual dies only to be born anew time after time
reborn as an animal or as a man according to his deserts.
Thus the whole of nature is united in a single indissoluble
fellowship, since all living creatures are partners in the
same great adventure of shared immortality, whatever the
in which they are reborn. Indians thus adopt a spe¬
cial attitude towards animals, for these may be reincar¬
nations of near kinsfolk ; they suffer as humans do ; and
so it is natural to treat them with the greatest of consi¬
deration.
In the third century B.C. the emperor Asoka, alone of
Mile Jeannine Auboyer is a leading French authority on ancient India. In
1950 her book Le Trône et son Symbolisme dans l'Inde Ancienne won the
Paul Pelliot Prize. Her other works Include Art et Style de l'Inde. She has
collaborated with French orientalist, Alfred Foucher, in a recent book on
the Jataka Tales, Les Vies antérieures du Bouddha.
all rulers throughout history, issued edicts renouncing
hunting and war for himself, advocating a vegetarian
diet and urging his subjects to treat every form of life
with respect. In the next century the death penalty was
actually abolished. Throughout the whole course of Hindu
history, both in India itself and in other lands where
Indian culture penetrated innumerable hospitals and refu¬
ges for sick or aged animals have been built, and when
the 1949 Constitution of the Republic of India was drawn
up, a special article on the protection of the cow was
included.
Despite this compassionate attitude, however, cases do
unfortunately occur in India, as elsewhere, of animals
being ill-treated, sacrificed or (killed for food. But, as
Alfred Foucher, the French archaeologist and scholar of
Buddhism, has said, belief in the brotherhood of all living
beings still flourishes more in India than anywhere else.
Buddhism, which originated in India, made this out¬
standing and all embracing compassion its own and carried
it to its highest pitch of perfection, while reinterpreting it
in terms of Buddhist thinking. As the sole objective of
KANTHAKA, THE FAITHFUL STEED. When Prince Gautama
left his palace and his family to seek supreme wisdom, the legend says
that he secretly rode off on his faithful horse, Kanthaka, accompanied
by his charioteer. This 9th century relief from Borobudur, Java, depicts
the prince saying farewell to his horse and his charioteer. On their
22
Musée Guimet Archives, Paris
return to the palace, Prince Gautama's father, the King, reproached
Kanthaka: "Ungrateful steed! You have received at my hands all marks
of affection and much kindness and now you have borne my beloved
son away from me." Hearing this reproach Kanthaka, unable to bear
his grief, sinks to the ground and dies, to be born again in heaven.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
Unesco
A FOREST SCENEA SUBJECT IN WHICH BUDDHIST ARTISTS, EXCELLEDCARVED ON A DOOR AT WAT SUTATTEÎ1PLE, BANGKOK, PROBABLY XVIII CENTURY A.D.
the Way was deliverance from suffering and hence the
escape from the terrors of transmigration, it therefore had
not only to proclaim the great Law of Love but to get
people to put it into practice.
So it is that animals figure largely in the Jataka, the
tales of the Buddha's previous lives, showing how before
the final human incarnation in which' he attained
Enlightenment (Bodhi), the Buddha himself had been
reborn innumerable times as an animal as various kinds
of fish, a crab, a cock, a woodpecker, a partridge, a fran¬
colín, a quail, a goose, a pigeon, a crow, a zebra, a buffalo,
several times as a monkey or an elephant, as an antelope,
as a stag and as a horse. In other tales the characters
are animals but the Bodhisattva appears as a man.
These tales are often spiced with a sly humour. Inci¬
dentally we know that they inspired La Fontaine; he must
have heard many of them from Dr. François Bernier, who
had learned them while serving for eight years as physi¬
cian to one of the nobles of the Great Moghul.
The stories are perfect illustrations both of how Indians
feel about animals and of their intimate understanding of
animals' reactions. The tales about monkeys are parti¬
cularly good examples. Indians, we should remember, are
extremely well acquainted with the. "bandarlog" of
Kipling's "Jungle Books" and their faults, every one of
which curiosity, grasshopper minds, impudence and stu¬
pidity is faithfully recorded.
For instance, there is the tale of the King of Benares's
gardener. This man thought he had earned a holiday,
but he did not want to leave his garden unattended while
he was away, or to pay the wages of a substitute. So he
decided to ask a tribe of monkeys which had settled in the
royal park to do the job gratis. Before he left, he gave
them lengthy instructions, urging them in particular not
to forget to water his tree-nurseries. The King of the
Monkeys had a methodical mind: to spare his subjects
useless exertion, he decided that the first thing to do was
to pull up all the saplings and see how much water the
roots were likely to need! The feelings of the
gardener on his return can easily be imagined.
Then there is the story of the monkey who (Cont'd on
made a butt of a zebu, teasing it endlessly and next page)
¿3
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
JATAKA TALES
(Continued)
Legends and imagery
of the animal world
playing all sorts of tricks on it of which the least painful
was to jump on its back and cover its eyes with his hands.
Everyone was amazed at the zebu's patience until one day
the monkey, while up to his pranks as usual, was thrown
to the* ground, trampled on and killed: it was a different
zebu! The first was the Bodhisattva; the second had no
Buddhist forbearance in its heart.
In all these stories and it is indeed their whole point
the future Buddha, in whatever shape he happens to be
incarnate, is always a model of virtue. Usually, for
instance, the foolishness of the monkey is emphasized
rather harshly, but when the Buddha takes this form, the
animal shows wisdom and courage.
The tale of the self-sacrifice of Mahâkapi, King of the
Monkeys, is typical. The King of Benares had set off with
an army up the Ganges to seek a wonderful fig tree whose
fruit he desired, but when he got to the place he found the
monkey people in the branches wreaking ruin on what he
considered his property. Night was falling and the king
had to wait till daylight for his bowmen to be sure of
hitting their marks, but realizing his intentions the mon¬
keys became terrified.
Their king then made up his mind to get them away
from the danger spot. With a mighty bound he leapt over
the Ganges to the farther bank and, cutting a long rattan,
tied one end to a tree opposite the fig tree and the other
to his own leg. Then he leapt back again and with the
rattan and his own body made a bridge from tree to tree.
The whole monkey people passed safely to the other side,
but when the last was over their king, exhausted, let go
his hold. And the King of Benares, moved by such self-
sacrifice, had a cloth stretched beneath the fig tree so
that the monkey should come to no harm.
Charity carried to the point of sacrificing one's own
life is a favourite subject in the Jataka. The hero may be
a man or an animalthe King of the Gazelles offering
himself to the King's cook so that his people and in parti¬
cular a doe in fawn may be spared; a captured elephant
fasting to make his captors release him and let him return
to his blind and lonely mother; the great six-tusked
elephant letting himself be struck down and his priceless
ivory be taken to make good a slight fault he had made.
Thus animals have their undisputed place in the drama
of life; they are made to act, speak, suffer and behave in
every respect like men. The reason, as we have seen, is
the Indian concept of the brotherhood of all living things,
from the least to the greatest, as beings bound to the
Wheel of Life. r
While the attitude of Buddha towards nature is made
clear enough in ancient writings, it is brought out even
more strongly in the visual arts. Even the earliest
sculptures known to us (dating back to the second or third
centuries B.C.) are impressive for the loving care and skill
with which the forms and attitudes of animals are shown.
Gazelles, birds, elephants
in a harmonious cavalcade
The portrayal of animals is indeed one of the chief
branches of Indian art and at no stage in its de¬
velopment has the skill of the artists faltered. At
the very beginning we get the Dhauli elephant (at
Orissa), carved from a single block, quietly impressive in
its representation of mass and power. True, it is un¬
completed since only the forequarters have been carved
out of the blocki but the craftsmanship is so fine and
sensitive that it is hard to believe that the sculptor
stopped there because he lacked the skill or knowledge
to complete his work.
Ancient Buddhist art, taking its themes from the tales
of the Jataka, draws abundantly on the animal world for
its images, and the storied bas-reliefs of the period from
the second century B.C. to the third century A.D. are a
harmonious cavalcade of beasts ponderously majestic
bull elephants; gentler cows, and calves appealing in their
infant combination of clumsiness and grace; bounding
gazelles, alert with heads high; fish; turtles; birds; stags
24
calmly dignified; predatory beasts crouching menacingly;
all the animal folk whom the Indians know so well, seem¬
ing to want no more than the touch of a wand to come
alive. They are sketches from daily life in the forest
hermitages, where familiarity with the denizens of the
wild imparts that sense of oneness already referred to.
The scenes unfold like an endless fresco, with the same
themes repeated again and again the six-tusked elephant .
at Bharut, Sanchi, and Ajanta; the self-sacrifice of the
monkey king at Bharut, Sanchi and elsewhere. All the
heroes of Buddhist legend are there, singly or in groups,
portrayed against backgrounds which, though conven¬
tionalized and reduced in scale, are sufficient to indicate
the setting, whether forest, town or royal park. Like the
human beings, the beasts play an active part in these
scenes. For instance, it is they who assemble to pay
homage to the sacred fig tree of the Enlightenment ;
or again, it is elephants who sprinkle water with their
trunks on the mother of the future Buddha, echoing the
Brahmin ritual for the anointing of a king.
Nothing escapes the trained eyes of the old sculptors
and painters. Their naturalistic representation of the
beasts speaks of long hours spent in studying the attitudes
of each species. Anatomical details are accurate. Even
though an element of caricature may sometimes appear,
this always follows a recognizable aesthetic principle: the
corpulence of the elephant is exaggerated boldly to bring
out to the full the impression of giant power and mass he
conveys; the slimness of the gazelle, the grace and dignity
of the stag, are exquisitely stylized; and a note of humour
is supplied by comic monkeys. In a word, a whole world is
called to life by no other magic than that of an artistry
which despite its apparent simplicity can only have been
attained by long experience.
To the two-legged, love ;
to the many-legged, love
This world is an image both of the eternal succession
of transmigrations and of daily life, a world where
any of us may recognize a kinsman in the animal
hero of a legend and where, at the same time, man plays
the part of an elder brother. Anything further removed
from abstruse philosophy it would be hard to conceive ;
at the origin is an earnest concern to threaten no form
of life, and this idea recurs time after time in Buddhist
writings. Hunters, fishermen and butchers are held in
the lowest esteem because of the destruction they commit.
"For him," we read, "who rejoices wickedly at the
slaughter of a living creature or at seeing a living
creature led to the slaughter, long ages of pain and
misery are reserved." (Samugutta Nikaya, III, 301.)
The life of the infinitely small is equally precious. We
read again: "Fools! How can you dig the soil or have it
dug by others? People think there are living beings in
the soil and any monk who digs it or has it dug commits
an offence for which he must atone. Fools! How can
you fell a tree or have it felled? The people think that
there are living beings in a tree. Destroying the growth
of a plant is an offence for which atonement must be
made." (Vinaya, Pitaka, IV, 32 and 34.) So likewise it is a
fault in a monk knowingly to take the life of a breathing
creature, to use water Which he knows contains breathing
creatures or to cast it on the grass or the soil (Vinaya
Pitaka, IV, 124, 125, 49).
There is, on occasion, a kind of calculation in this
attitude. It is not absolutely selfless charity, since the
ultimate ground for reverence for all living beings is the
hope that they will return it. What is remarkable and a
point to be emphasized. is that this reverence is based
first and foremost on love:
To the two-legged, love;
To the legless, love;
To the four-legged, love;
To the many-legged, love.
(Angtjttara Nikaya, II, 72-73.)
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
INDIA
INDONESIA
TIBET
CHINA
THAILAND
500 million ior the 'Middle Way'
The exact number of Buddhists
in the world is not known.
In Asia as many as 500 mil¬
lion people or one-fifth of the
earth's population are followers of
the religion of the Middle Way.
Countries of southeast Asia today
have the highest proportion of
Buddhists: Ceylon (62%) ; Burma
(80 %) ; Thailand (90 %) ; Cambo¬
dia (80 %) ; Laos (83 %). Buddhists
in China and Japan are more numer¬
ous than those in any other country
although the two countries are no
longer predominantly Buddhist.
Japanese Buddhists are estimated at
46 million, including numerous sects
and doctrines ranging from the
vastly popular Shin to the austere,
contemplative sects of the Zen
Buddhists who believe that enlight¬
enment, comes from a sudden flash
of intuition during disciplined medi¬
tation. In India, birthplace of
Buddhism, the religion has practi¬
cally died out since the 12th century.
Buddhist thought and teaching
fall into two great schools.
The first, called The Way of
the Elders (Theravada) is often
referred to by other Buddists as
the Lesser Vehicle (Hinayana). It
seeks to retain the early teachings
of Buddha down to the letter, views
the Buddha as a human being, a
teacher whose Enlightenment raised
him above all others. His Nir
vana was the same as that of any
other person who attains it." He
dispensed no divine power. The¬
ravada Buddhism stresses that man's
destiny is moulded by his own acts;
salvation comes by following mo¬
nastic self-discipline. Since it exists
today chiefly in Ceylon, Burma,
Thailand, and Cambodia, it is often
spoken of as the Southern School.
JAPAN
The Northern School which
spread from India to Nepal,
Tibet, China, Korea and Japan
is known as The Greater Vehicle
(Mahayana), i.e. the boat in which
all can ride. Its doctrine is less
rigorous and does not limit salvation
to the monastic order. Every per¬
son, however humble, may become
a candidate for Buddhahood if he
but wills it and holds to his purpose.
The historical Gautama falls into
the background, making way for a
Pantheon of Buddhas viewed as
redeemers or gods. The most
conspicuous is Buddha Amitabha
(He of Infinite Light). Each
Buddha dwells in a paradise amidst
a retinue of Bodhisattvas or future
Buddhas who have vowed not to
enter Nirvana until they have led
all living creatures there. The path
to salvation: love for the holy
Buddhas and Bodhisattvas of the
past, love for one's fellow creatures
by self-sacrifice for their needs, ac¬
tive compassion and charity.
Despite the differences in some
of the outward trappings and
symbolic mythology of the
two schools, no violent break ever
split Buddhism into two hostile
camps. Instead there was contact
and mutual exchange of views with
members of both schools living
within the same monastery. The
World Fellowship of Buddhists
groups members from both schools
from all countries.
The total amount of Buddhist
literature is enormous. Al¬
though the Buddhist canon
exists in Sanskrit, Chinese and Tibet¬
an versions, the only complete col¬
lection of the Buddhist scriptures
now existing in an Indian language
is the Pali Canon of Ceylon. It
is known as the Tipitakas (or Tri-
pitakas), meaning "The Threefold
Basket". These comprise Vinaya,
the rules of discipline ; Sutta (or Su¬
tra) sermons, commentaries and pa¬
rables; Abhidhamma, philosophy,
psychology, and physics. In addi¬
tion there is the anthology of verses
known as the Dhammapada (see
page 42) and several collections of
moral tales, the best known being
the Jataka stories (see page 22).
Six great Councils have been
held during the history of
Buddhism to re-examine and
revise the teachings of Buddha.
Four took place before the Christian
era, the last in about 29 to 13 B.C.
when the texts of the teachings were
committed to writing for the first
time. At the Fifth Council, in
Mandalay, Burma, in 1871, the texts
were recorded on 729 marble slabs.
At the Sixth Buddhist World
Council which has just ended
in Rangoon, 500 monks were
appointed to re-examine the texts of
the Buddhist scriptures after a large
corps of lay scholars had first edited
versions in the Pali language and
had made draft translations into
Burmese. These texts were the
Tipitakas (above) and filled 54 books
totalling 14,804 pages, but it was
believed that the essential parts of
the Buddha's teachings could be
aranged in two or three volumes of
about 500 pages each. The abridg¬
ed Tipitakas would contain the
essence of the doctrine in proper
sequence.
The Buddha has been known by
many names. His family
name was Gautama and the
name he was given at his birth, Sid-
dhartha, means "He who has
reached his goal". Buddha has also
been called Baghavât, or "The
Blessed One" and Jina "The Victo¬
rious One". Another of his names,
Sakyamuni, means '"The Sage of the
Sakyas" while Tathagata has been
rendered as "He who has fully come
through" or, more briefly, "The Per¬
fect One". The name Buddha comes
from "Budh", meaning, "to awa¬
ken", and signifies "The Enlightened
One". This last name describes not
only the Prince Siddhartha Gau¬
tama, but every being who has van¬
quished ignorance and achieved su¬
preme wisdom.
Suggestions for further reading
Many books exist in English on Buddhism and Buddhist philo¬
sophy. A few are listed below. Others will be found in many
of the volumes indicated.
The Dhammapada, Tr. and com¬
mentary by S. Radhakrishnan ;
Allen and Unwirt London, 1954.
(See also page 42.)
Buddhist Texts through the Ages,
ed. by E. Conze, I.B. Horner
and A. Waley ; Bruno Cassirer,
Oxford, 1955.
Buddhism its Essence and Deve¬
lopment, Edward Conze ; Bruno
Cassirer, Oxford, 1955.
Some Sayings of the Buddha, F.L.
Woodward (tr.) ; Oxford, World
Classics, 1938.
Buddha and the Gospel of.- Bud¬
dhism, Ananda K. Coomaraswa-
my ; John Day, New York, 1947.
Introduction to Zen Buddhism, D.T.
Suzuki ; Philosophical Library,
New York, 1949.
Jataka TalesBirth Stories of the
Buddha, Ethel and Beswick ;
Wisdom of the East series, John
Murray, London, 1956. (Several
other books on Buddhism are in¬
cluded in this series).
The Splendour of Asia or The Life
of Buddha, Adams-Beck ; Cassell,
London 1950.
Buddhism, Christmas Humphreys ;
Penguin Books, London, 1954.
The Meaning of Life In Hinduism
and Buddhism, Floyd H. Ross ;
Routledge and Kegan Paul, Lon¬
don, 1952.
In the Footsteps of the Buddha,
René Grousset ; G. Routledge,
London, 1932.
The Teachings of the Compassion¬
ate Buddha, E.A. Burtt ; Mentor
Religious Classics, New American
Library, New York, 1955.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
ANGKOR
CITY OF
TOWER
FACES
Almost a century ago, Henri Mouhot, a
French botanist who had been intrigued by
reports of ancient cities hidden deep
in the jungle, was making his way through
the great forests of the Mekong River in
Cambodia. One morning he saw an
amazing spectacle a series of stately
towers rising like peaks above a sea of
jungle. Mouhot had come across the city
of Angkor, ancient capital of the Khmer
Empire (9th to 15th centuries) and the mas¬
terpiece of an art and an architecture
that had hitherto been hidden from the
world.
When the Khmer Empire collapsed about
1440 A.D. after a hundred years' war with
Siam, the capital was withdrawn from
Angkor to Pnompenh, present capital of
Cambodia. Angkor had been described in
1490 by' a Chinese pilgrim Chou Ta-kuan,
and in the 17th century Spanish mission¬
aries had brought back descriptions, but
their stories were hardly believed.
It was only at the end of the 19th cen¬
tury that archaeologists were able to make
proper studies of the Angkor temples freed
at last from the invading jungle. They
found on the site more than twenty major
monuments covering some 10,000 acres.
Gradually they reconstructed the story of
an empire whose dominion extended over
what is today Cochin China and part of
Cambodia, and retraced the development of
the singularly harmonious Khmer art.
Musée Guimet Archives, Paris.
-'J-
ífil|«j,¿í
¿ÙvêO.
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The first city of Angkor and its Great
Temple were the creation of Suryavar-
man II (1112-52) who was not a Buddhist.
In 1181, one of his successors, Jayavar-
man VII, a Buddhist king, founded a new
capital, Angkor Thorn, close by. It was
Jayavarman VII who adorned the Great
Temple of the former capital (previously
dedicated to the Hindu god Vishnu) with
Buddhist decorations and gave it the title
which this great temple . fortress still bears
Angkor Wat (the palace monastery).
In the centre of Angkor Thom, at the
point where the four roads leading inwards
from the principal gates meet, stands the
Bayon Temple, built at the end of the 12th
century as a Buddhist . shrine of the
Mahayana school dedicated to Lokesvara,
the compassionate Bodhisattva. The
Bayon itself is not so much a work of
architecture as one of sculpture with towers
like so many statues in the round. The en¬
tire site of Angkor Thom is a vast,
brilliantly planned and ordered arrangement
of buildings. Not only are the temples
magnificent in themselves, but the great
roads along which the faithful passed to
the holy place were conceived and execut¬
ed with genius.
Photos of Angkor on these pages show :
Left, detail of a bas-relief in the Bayon
Temple, depicting the legend of the Leper
King. The king is shown in his palace
and, on the lower part of the relief, two
The Unesco Courier
women are dancing on a stage to the
accompaniment of a harp. Centre, The
Footprint of Buddha covered with sacred
signs and symbols including, at centre, The
Wheel of the Law, carved at Angkor Wat
in the 12th century. The Buddha is said io
have been born with certain imprints on the
soles of his feet and Buddhist iconographers
have made great use of these signs of pre¬
destination, adding many other symbols
including the Wheel of the Law.
Right, A manyheaded naga (snake) held
by the hands of several deities. A series
of figures all gripping the body of the ser¬
pent, form a balustrade along the main
approaches to the Bayon Temple at Angkor
Thom.
Copyright Giraudon. Musée Guimet Archives, Paris.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
ANGKOR (Cont'd)
LORD OF THE WORLD. The most dis¬
tinctive feature of Bayon Temple at Angkor
Thom is the carving of gigantic masks of the
Bodhisattva Lokesvara ("The Lord of the
World") to whom the temple Is dedicated,
on the four sides of each of the 50 or so
towers. Similar heads are repeated on the-
towers of the chapels on the corners of the
city walls and over the four main gateways
at the points of the compass. The faces have
been interpreted as ideal portraits of the
king as an incarnation of the Bodhisattva
Lokesvara and their multiplication at every
point of the compass as signifying and ensuring
radiation1 of royal power over all the realm.
Top photos by Hélène Hoppenot, taken from
"Extrême-Orient", Copyright by Editions Ides and
Calendes, Neuchatel, Switzerland.
Photo right, Copyright Cartier-Bresson-Magnum.
ROYAL CITY of Angkor Thom shown in
this plan was built on similar lines to the
palace monastery of Angkor Wat about one
mile away. It is a palace city with moats
measuring about 100 yards across and walls
broken by five gates from which roads lead
to the central temple-mountain, The Bayon.
Drawing taken from "The Art and Architecture of
India" by Benjamin Rowland. Copyright by Penguin
Books, London.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
Burma
Courtesy A. Vigier.
COLOSSAL STATUES OF BUDDHA
in Burma are usually covered with white
plaster which is then painted or entirely
gilded over with real gold leaf. Time
has washed away the plaster which once
covered the llth century Phandawgyer
Buddha of Pagan (bottom, left), leaving an
extraordinary figure full of power and
grandeur. The two disemboweled sta¬
tues (left and below) are typical of the
state of most of the Buddhist statues in the
ruined temples of Pagan. Centuries ago,
plunderers and vandals smashed open the
chest and abdomen of every statue they
found in search of gold treasures or relics
often sealed there by Buddhist benefactors.
Photos Copyright J. Lavaud.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
BURMA (Continued)
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
PAGAN
Forest of stupas
OF all the great centres of Buddhism in Asia, few can boast a more Impressive
concentration of monuments than the ancient holy city of Pagan (accent last
syllable). For eight miles along the Irrawaddy River, in central Burma, and for
two miles inland, a forest of pagodas and stupas of every size and shape extends into
the horizon. Some stand out glistening white against their red-brown weather-
beaten neighbours like medieval cathedrals in a fantastic landscape. About them rise
round towers, bulbous mushrooms, slender pinnacles, bell-shaped pyramids, knob¬
like domes and pumpkin pagodas. (Photos here show general views of the former
holy city). Pagan was a teeming capital of Burma a thousand years ago. It was built
by King Anawrahta in the llth century and once had no fewer than 4,000 pagodas.
It remained one of the great royal and religious cities of Asia until it was reduced by
the armies of Kublai Khan in I 287.
Burma is greatly indebted to India for Its religion, its philosophy and its art.
Buddhism reached Burma in force from India about I 057 A.D. though Buddhist colonies
had appeared in Burma much earlier. Today It is virtually a one-religion country:
out of I 9 million people, I 5,200,000 (80%) are practising Buddhists. Every Burmese
lad spends a period of his boyhood in a monastery, shaves his head and wears the
saffron robe as a novice. (The same colour robe is also worn in Ceylon and Thailand.)
Most boys remain only a few months, a few become monks (pongyi) for life. Thus in
every Burmese village are found golden-spired monasteries and pagodas. It is amazing
how many pagodas jut out of every part of the Burmese countryside. No hill is too
steep or rocky to prevent one from being erected.
Greatest of Burma's pagodas, and Holy of Holies to the Buddhist world, is the superb¬
ly beautiful Shwe Dagon in Rangoon (see photo on map page I I). It is the most
universally visited of Asia's Buddhist shrines, its peculiar sanctity being due to the fact
that it contains several original relics of Gautama including four hairs from the head
of the Buddha. Built on the highest point of land in Rangoon, the Shwe Dagon is
visible fora distance of 20 miles or more, brilliantly lit by floodlights at night, dazzling
in the sun by day. Its spire is covered with pure gold which is renewed each generation
by public subscription. Actually, though, its regilding goes on perpetually. Almost
daily the devout climb its sides with little handfuls of gold leaf which they fasten on
some part of its vast surface, thus adding their bit to its grandeur.
Photos copyright J. Lavaud.
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
BURMA (Cont'd)
Courtesy A. Vigier.
Each of these gleaming white shrines is a stupa containing a marble slab
engraved on back and front with a chapter from the Buddhist Scripture
Bltaghat. Hundreds of these airy stupas are part of the Ku-thu-daw
32
Pagoda, the "Royal-Merit House" built in the 19th century just outside
the palace city of Mandalay. It is one of the most compact and tastefully
adorned of Burmese pagodas and has beautifully carved gilt gates.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
Copyright J. Lavaud.
GARBED IN WHITE & CAPPED IN GOLD. Glittering in the
afternoon sky, Ananda pagoda is the most famous and best preserved of
the temples of Pagan. It is considered one of the wonders of Burma's
former holy capital. Completed in the llth century, its form may have
been inspired by the great cave temples of India, accounts of which were
brought to Burma by a group of Indian Buddhist monks from Orissa.
Outside the temple are 1,500 plaques depicting Buddha's previous lives.
The centre is a solid mass of brickwork with narrow galleries between
the core and the outer walls. The dim light that filters into these
galleries gives the effect of a deep natural grotto. Recesses In the
galleries hold deep red and gold covered figures portraying the life of
Buddha. One of these (below left) shows Buddha's mother Maya who
died one week after his birth. Most of the temples of Pagan were cover¬
ed with elaborate frescoes, the earliest of which recall the masterpieces
of Ajanta in India. Many of the temples were also decorated with
delicate wooden sculptures such as the painted wooden torch bearer
(below right) now at Pagan Museum. Centre photo is a beautiful exam¬
ple of wood carving found in the Shwe Gyaung pagoda, Mandalay.
Copyright J. Lavaud., Courtesy A. Vigier. Courtesy A. Vigier.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
'No one has the right to
despise a fellow creature'
by G. P. Malalasekera
If we contemplate the vastness of cosmic space and
the seemingly endless number of worlds of which
the human worlds form a very small part, the prob¬
lems of race would appear in a different light and seem
very trifling indeed. One is reminded of a comparison
the Buddha made when he rebuked a section of his
monks who felt superior to the rest in that they had
more fame and gain than the others. He likens them
to worms, who born in dung, bred in dung, and living
on dung, feel superior to other worms who are not so
privileged in this respect.
Whatever the picture we may get from a cosmic
perspective of humanity crawling" over the surface of the
earth and trying to eke out an existence on it, humility
is one of the lessons we have to learn from it. "'King¬
ship on earth is a beggarly existence, in comparison with
the joys of the heavenly worlds." The span of life of
mortal men is insignificantly small in comparison with
cosmic time and may be compared in its duration to a
line drawn on the earth.
Although human life appears insignificant from a
cosmic standpoint, yet it is constantly pointed out in the
Buddhist texts as being of tremendous worth, as man
has within him the capacity of gaining the highest
knowledge or of attaining a moral pre-eminence which
can make him worthy of becoming a "ruler of a world-
system". This is not possible for those in lower-than-
human states of existence whose actions are instinctual
and too pre-occupied with securing elementary needs;
nor is it possible for those in the higher worlds who are
too distracted by the joys of the present for serious
contemplation to be possible.
All beings are potential Buddhas
When the Buddha was asked whether he was man
or god, he answered that he was neither since he
was the Buddha. The heights that man can
attain in the matter of his intellectual, moral and spi¬
ritual attainments are so great that those who have
attained them are as different from ordinary men as
men are from animals. Yet such men are not mere
freaks nor have they been specially favoured by any
divine agency. They have attained such heights by their
dint of effort directed towards developing their intellec¬
tual, moral and spiritual nature extending over many
lives. And what has been achieved by one or a few is
within the capacity of all to achieve.
As the Mahayana texts put it, it is not only men but
all sentient beings down to the very lowest who are
potential Buddhas in that a Buddha nature (Buddha-
bhàva) is present within them. If only for this reason,
no one has a right to despise a fellow creature since all
are subject to the same laws of existence, have ultimately
the same nature and the same potentialities though they
Professor Malalasekera is Dean of the Faculty of Oriental Studies and
Professor of Pali and Buddhist Civilization at the University of Ceylon.
He is Preside it o) the World Fellowship of Buddhists and of the All Ceylon
Buddhist Congress. His publications include: "The Pali Literature of Ceylon"
(A Royal Asiatic Society Prize publication) and other works. The above
article is taken fiom a study written especially for Unesco as part of the
series "The Race Question and Modern Thought". The volume will be
entitled "Buddhism and the Race Question",
34
POLONNARUVA, ancient capital of the Kingdom of Ceylon, is today
only a village, but the remains of its former palaces, temples and shrines
tell of one of the most glorious periods in the island's history. Polon-
naruva owes much of its architectural grandeur to two 12th century
monarchs, Parakramabahu I and King Nissanka-Malla, his successor,
who adorned the city with splendid buildings and laid out parks and
are in varying stages of growth or development arid their
rates of growth may differ from time to time.
At the human level the lessons that man can learn by
realizing his position in the universe are not only that he
needs to be humble but also that he need not despair,
since he has the power to understand the world and
overcome it and cease to be a mere mechanism within
it. Both these lessons, the realization of our common
plight as well as the potentialities within each of us,
teach us but one moral namely that it is everyone's
duty to help his fellow beings and that no one has any
right or valid grounds to despise another.
Although all sentient beings are often treated as one
community in Buddhism, a special emphasis is placed on
the worth and dignity of human existence in view of the
opportunities and potentialities that man possesses for
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
self-development. Pointed attention is also made to the
unity of mankind where a comparison is made and a
distinction drawn between human beings and the animal
and plant kingdoms.
It is argued on biological grounds that unlike the
plant' and animal kingdoms where differences of species
are noticeable, mankind is one species, a view which
accords most remarkably with the findings of modern
biological science. Not only is this view in disagreement
with the scientific pretensions of the biologists of the
eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries, who tried to
classify men into different races which could be graded
like species of animals into the higher and lower, but it
cuts the ground beneath the very foundations of any
racist doctrine which would divide human beings into
more or less isolated groups and argue that their varying
human characteristics are in their entirety genetically
determined. It is also interesting to note that this
passage occurs in a polemic against the pretensions of
the Brahmanic caste theory and incidentally shows by
implication how the Brahmins were claiming superiority
for themselves on genetical grounds.
Copyright Cartier-Bresson-Magnui.
ornamental gardens. Photos show, Left: a decorative motif on a stone
pillar standing amid the ruins of the Temple of the Tooth, at Polon-
naruva, with a finely draped statue of Buddha looking silently on.
Right: one of a pair of cobra kings in human form (frequently found in
Buddhist art) guarding the Vatadage Temple, which contains the most
complete collection of ancient relics and religious statuary of Ceylon.
"We have a controversy regarding (the distinction of)
birth, O Gotama!", we read in the Sutta Nipata.
"Bharadvaja says, one is a Brahman by birth, and I
say by deeds; know this, O thou clearly-seeing!
"We are both unable to convince each other, (there¬
fore) we have come to ask thee (who art) celebrated as
perfectly enlightened."
"I will explain to you, O Vasettha", so said Bhagavat,
"in due order the exact distinction of living beings accord¬
ing to species, for their species are manifold.
"'Know ye the grass and the trees, although they do not
exhibit (it), the marks that constitute species are for
them, and (their) species are manifold.
"Then know ye the worms, and the moths, and the
different sorts of ants... also the four-footed (animals),
small and great, ... also the serpents, the long-backed
snakes... also the fish which range in the water... also the
birds that are borne along on wings and move through
the air.
"As in these species the marks that constitute species
are abundant, so in men the marks that constitute spe¬
cies are not abundant.
'"Difference there is in beings endowed with bodies,
but amongst men this is not the case, the difference
amongst men is nominal (only).
"For whoever amongst men lives by cow-keeping, he
is a husbandman, not a Brahman. And whoever amongst
men lives by archery, he is a soldier, not a Brahman.
"And I do not call one a Brahman on account of his
birth or of his origin from a (particular) mother..."
What is apparent from the above is that according to
the Buddha there are no distinguishing characteristics of
genus and species among men unlike the case of
grasses, trees, worms, moths, fishes, beasts, birds, etc.,
and as Chalmers says: "'Herein, Gotama was in accord
with the conclusion of modern biologists that 'the
Anthropidae are represented by the single genus and
species, Man' a conclusion which was the more remark¬
able inasmuch as the accident of colour did not mislead
Gotama."
Caste-consciousness came from colour
The Buddha goes on to show, that the apparent di¬
visions between men are not due to basic biological
factors but that they are "conventional classifica¬
tions." The distinctions made in respect of the differen¬
ces in skin colour, hair-form, the shape of the head or the
shape of the nose etc. are not absolute categories. One
is almost reminded of the statement of the scientists that
"the concept of race is unanimously regarded by anthropo¬
logists as a classificatory device..."
It would thus appear that Buddhism is in accord with
the findings of the modern biologists who exploded the
doctrines of racism and would urge the biological unity
of mankind in support of the concept of a common
humanity.
In spite of the fact that the above passage brings out
the Buddhist attitude to the problem of race, it is not
possible to say that Early Buddhism was confronted with
a racial problem as such. Such a problem was, no doubt,
there in Rigvedic society where the race-conscious Aryan
who spoke derisively of the dark-skinned and noseless
aborigines treated the latter as an inferior race. But by
the time of the rise of Buddhism this race-consciousness
had given place to a caste-consciousness and it was the
Brahmin in particular and the "'higher" castes in general
who were probably derived largely from Aryan stock who
claimed superiority by virtue of the fairness of their skin
colour. It was claimed by the Brahmins to be one of the
hereditary characteristics of a Brahmin that
he was "handsome", fair, endowed with an (Cont'd on
excellent complexion and of the fairest colour page ¡g\
by virtue of which he claimed superiority over
BEJEWELLED WOMEN,
right and top of opposite
page, are among oldest and
best preserved of Ceylon's
wall paintings (5th century)
in the palace-fortress on the
summit of a tremendous
rock at Sigurya. In all there
are 21 female figures depict¬
ed rising from the clouds, and
hence all cut off at waist.
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
China
ES5""-
L
:?f¿ IVY* IW Fs*TT^* ***íf<^
'f in»; *
Art travelled the Silk Route to China
Buddhism appeared in China for the first time about 65 A. D.
when Indian monks were travelling northwards across the
mountain passes as missionaries and Chinese pilgrims
went to India to learn about the new religion of enlightenment.
When Buddhism came to China over trade routes like the
famous Silk Route through Central Asia, it had already developed
a ritual with definite needs temples, monasteries, statues and
paintings. It therefore brought with it a new idea about the
function of art; namely that art had to serve the divinity.
One of the effects of the new religion was greatly to increase
foreign contacts. One great Buddhist pilgrim, Fa-Hsien left China
for India in 399 A.D. and returned in 414 after spending 15 years
compiling an eye-witness account of the country. Another scholar
monk, Hsuan-Tsang, went to India in 629 A.D., staying 16 years.
Between the 4th and 6th centuries Buddhist art experienced
a great period of expansion especially in northern China under
the Wei dynasty. The Chinese artist was by now altering
according to his own' ideal the forms he had received from the
west. This development continued under the Sui dynasty (581-
36
618), one of whose emperors ordered the making of over 105,000
statues and statuettes of the Buddha in gold, silver, wood, dried
lacquer, ivory and stone.
The richest period of Chinese Buddhist art came in the years of
the T'ang dynasty (618 to 906 A.D.). After initial setbacks at the
beginning of the dynasty, Buddhism again expanded and flourished
in close association with the best artists of the period. In the
T'ang capital (modern Sian) a great Buddhist monument, The
Grey Goose Pagoda, was raised and in all parts of the newly-
expanded Empire temples were built and richly decorated
with carvings, sculptures and frescoes.
In the llth and 12th centuries the quality of Buddhist painting
was still high, but . sculpture was already in a state of decline.
While many sculptured works were still being produced, they
lacked the inspiration and the religious fervour which the Wei
period six centuries earlier, for example, had provided. The same
is true, though at a much later date, of Buddhist painting,
which never again reached the heights it had achieved under the
great artists of the T'ang dynasty.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
TEMPLES IN LIVING ROCK
were excavated by Chinese Bud¬
dhists to whom the idea came from
India via Afghanistan. Some of the
most impressive Buddhist rock tem¬
ples in China are those hewn out
of the cliff face at Lung Men in the
north, about 5 I 0 A.D. At that time,
the Wei dynasty, which controlled
nearly all the north of China, estab¬
lished Its capital close to Lung Men,
near the Yellow River. The grottos
were enriched with hundreds of
¡mages and stelae by the Wei kings
and later by those of the T'ang
dynasty which held sway until 759
A.D. Among Lung Men's celebrated
works are giant Buddhas (one is
nearly 50 feet in height) and count¬
less smaller Buddha figures which
are placed in the minor shrines.
I
Photos by Hélène Hoppenot, re-
. produced from "Extrême-Orient",
copyright by Editions Ides et
Calendes, Neuchâtel, Switzerland.
Chinese Buddhist
Association, Peking
INNUMERABLE IMAGES of Buddha adorn the entrances and inside walls of the
grottos and shrines cut into the rock face at Yun Kang, near Ta tung, the first capital
of the Wei kings in Shansi Province, northern China. Of earlier date (around 414 A.D.)
than the Lung Men temples (opposite page), those at Yun Kang have some of the
finest existing examples of Wei period reliefs. The beauty and number of the carvings
reflect the enthusiasm with which Buddhism was taken up by the Wei people. At
this period, Northern Chinese Buddhist sculptors took as models the clay and mud
statues of Buddha from Kucha in Central Asia, and tried to copy them as faithfully
as possible. By the end of the same century, Chinese artists had begun to alter,
according to their own ideals, the forms they had received from the West. Photos
show, top: Facade of weatherworn Buddha images flanking the entrance to the Yun
Kang grottos; bottom: Imagesand paintings on the wall of the I 3th grotto at Yun Kang.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
CHINA (Cont'd)
The Cave of the
Some of the finest treasures of Chinese
Buddhist painting and sculpture are preserv¬
ed In three great "art galleries" hewn out
of the cliff sides of northern China. These
are the Buddhist cave temples and shrines
at Lung Men in Shansi Province and those at
Tun Huang and Maichishan in Kansu province.
Though many paintings have been damaged
by time and weather, thousands of others,
still in remarkably good condition, offer a
panorama of Chinese Buddhist art from the
3rd to the 13th century A.D.
Portraits of merchants and princes, whose
donations helped to build and decorate the
shrines and temples, are often found on the
walls. Group of nobles (I) were benefactors
of Lung Men temples where this stone relief
was carved and painted during the sixth
century A. D.
Fragment of a painting on silk showing
the head of a temple benefactor (2) isa I 0 th
century work found in the Caves of the Thou¬
sand Buddhas at Tun Huang. Two thousand
years ago, caravans travelling on the Great
Silk Road from China to Persia and India,
halted at Tun Huang to rest and replenish
their food and water supplies before crossing
the Gobi or Lop Nor deserts. Before facing
the perils of the journey, many merchants
and travellers visited the great temple
which Buddhist monks had established in a
cave outside the city to pray for safety and
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
1,000 Buddhas
success and to give donations. During the
thousand years that this practice continued
hundreds of temples were dug out of the
rock and richly decorated with paintings,
frescoes and images of the Buddha. The
dry desert air has helped to preserve many
of the paintings which are still exquisitely
coloured, even though some of them date
back some 1,400 years.
In one of the Tun Huang caves there is a
remarkable painted panel whose centrepiece
depicts a scene from the Buddhist paradise.
Fragment of this panel (3) reveals skill and
imagination of ancient Chinese artists in
executing delicately frescoed figures.
More than 180 Buddhist shrines and
grottos cut into a sheer cliff-face at Maichishan
were found during investigations in 1941
and 1953. Here, not all the frescoes are
of religious subjects. Many present a vivid
picture of everyday life in past centuries,
showing costumes, carriages, ceremonies
and hunting and battle scenes. Painting
from Maichishan (4) is thought to date from
the end of the 4th century A.D.
In a different style but equally remarkable
is the detail of a painting on silk (5) dating
from the 9th century A.D., and found in
one of the Caves of the Thousand Buddhas
at Tun Huang.
Photos : (I) Musée Guimet Archives, Paris ; (2 and 4)
Courtesy A. Vigier ; (3 and 5) Copyright Skeel-
British Museum.
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
CHINA (Cont'd)
IN A SMALL STREET just inside one of the city gates of Peking is
a Buddhist nunnery. Here, some 40 nuns of all ages live a cloistared
existence in pious search for Nirvana, rarely leaving the confines of
the nunnery except to go on pilgrimages. Their life is purely devotional,
prayers and meditation taking upmost of the day. They have shaven.
Photos by Hedda Morrisson, copyright Camera Press.
heads and wear dark red or purple robes. Each morning they hold
a service in the main temple building where prayers are said and Buddhist
scriptures read to the accompaniment of percussion instruments.
Above, left: A shaven-headed nun beats a wooden tablet to announce
the arrival of visitors for the Abbess. Right: A nun at prayer.
ABOUT 65 A.D. the emperor Ming-ti of the Chinese Han dynasty
is said to have dreamed that a golden image of the Buddha appeared
from out of the west, and to have sent messengers over the Himalayas
to find out the source of the dream. In 67 A.D. the mission returned
to the emperor's capital, Loyang, bringing the first Buddhist images
and scriptures to China. They later arrived in China by sea and
/
'JEJí
over Asia's trade routes. In 68, A.D. the emperor built a monastery,
known as the White Horse Temple (because the sacred images and
books had been brought on a white horse). Belon, left: The Chi Yun
Pagoda in the White Horse Temple; Right: The Wuta Temple (Five
Pagoda Temple) in the western suburbs of Peking. It was built in
1403 under the Ming dynasty, in the Indian architectural style.
Photos Chinese Buddhist Association. Peking.
40
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
The lotus: a flower rich in symbolism
Photo Hedda Morrisson, copyright Camera Press.
RARE COPPER BASIN decorated all around with figures of Buddha
from the Buddhist nunnery, Peking. Each summer it is used to grow
lotus flowers. The lotus, or " padma ", is widely used in the art and
in the religious symbolism of Buddhism. Long regarded as a sacred
plant, the lotus and its flower aptly symbolise life's fulfilment. With
its roots in the earth, its stem in water, its blossom in the air, and
blooming in the rays of the sun, the lotus thus symbolises four
elements. It is also a symbol of rebirth ; its seeds pass from the air to
the water and then into the earth where they germinate. It also sym¬
bolizes purity as well as Nirvanathe spiritual goal of Buddhism.
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
Sayings of Buddha
THE DHAMMAPADA
'Path of Virtue'
The spirit of Buddhist teaching is embodied in the Dhammapada, an anthology
of 423 verses written in Pali (an Indo-Aryan language of Buddha's time). The
name Dhammapada comes from Dhamma (discipline, law, religion) and pada
(the path, means or way) and for Buddhists it represents "the path of virtue". The
verses are attributed to The Buddha himself, as thoughts spoken during his 45 years
of missionary wandering after he had attained Enlightenment under the Bodhi tree.
Though the Dhammapada may not contain the very words of The Buddha, and though
it is only one part of the total Buddhist canon, it does embody the whole spirit of his
teaching. This collection of verses is much moré than a breviary; it englobes a way
of life and a code of conducttaught by Buddha who said: "My action is my possession,
my action is my inheritance; my action is the matrix which bears me; my action is
the race to which I belong; my action is my refuge." The verses below from the
Dhammapada are taken from the complete translation by Professor N.K. Bhagwat,
published in 1955 by Dr. M. Venkatrao, President of The Buddha Society, Bombay.
Never in this world can hatred be stilled
by hatred ; it will be stilled only by non-
hatred this is the Law Eternal.
Some quarrelers do not realize that in
this world we must all at some time cease
to live ; but there are others who do so
realize, and they will settle their quarrels.
Just as the monsoon rains fail to pene¬
trate a house that is well thatched, so
craving will not enter the mind which is
collected.
The perfume of flowers cannot travel
against the wind be it the scent of sandal,
tagara or jasmine but the sweet odour of
a good man travels even against the wind ;
the righteous pervade every place with
their fragrance.
Wakefulness is the way to immortality ;
heedlessness is the way to death ; those who
are wakeful die not, the heedless are
already dead.
As a fletcher makes straight his arrow, so
does the wise man make straight the mind
which, trembling and unsteady, is difficult
to guard and restrain.
Death bears off the man whose mind is
intent on plucking the blossoms of sense,
as a great flood sweeps away a sleeping
hamlet.
A fool brings grief on himself with the
thought : "This son is mine, this wealth is
mine." How can he, if he does not even
belong to himself, be the possessor of a son
or wealth?
An unworthy deed, like milk freshly
drawn from the cow, does not all at once
turn sour, but smouldering within as a fire
covered with ashes, it pursues the fool.
As a solid rock is not shaken by a strong
gale, so wise persons remain unaffected by
praise or censure.
42
Though one should in battle conquer a
thousand men a thousand times, he who
conquers himself has the more glorious vic¬
tory.
*
It were better to live one single day in
the commencement of strong endeavour
than to live a hundred years in idleness
and lassitude.
Think not lightly of good, saying, "It
will not come unto me;" even a jar be¬
comes full with the constant dripping of
water. So does the wise man, little by little,
fill himself with good.
The gaily painted chariots of kings wear
out ; so also does the body wear out. But
the Law of the Good wears not away; thus
do the wise proclaim to the wise.
The man of little learning goes through
life like an ox; his flesh increases, but his
wisdom does not.
The evil done by oneself, begotten of
oneself, sprung from oneself, crushes the
wicked man as a diamond crushes a hard
precious stone.
Victory breeds hatred, for the vanquished
is stricken with suffering ; but the tranquil
man lives in happiness, disregarding both
victory and defeat.
He who has enjoyed the flavour of soli¬
tude and the sweetness of tranquility is
unperturbed and free from sin as he drinks
in the sweetness of devotion for the doc¬
trines.
*
Let a man conquer anger by absence of
anger, wickedness by absence of wicked¬
ness, miserliness by liberality, and a liar by
truth.
There never was, there never will be, nor
does there now exist a being who stands
wholly praised or utterly condemned.
Very easy it is to discover flaws in others,
but very difficult to see one's own. One
winnows the shortcomings of others like
chaff, but one covers his own as a dishonest
gambler covers a losing throw.
To control the eye is good; to control
the ear is good; to control the nose is good;
to control the tongue is good. To control
the body is good; to control speech is good;
to control the mind is good; good is control
on every side. A Bhikkhu who is thus
controlled on every side is freed from all
suffering.
It is a trained elephant that is led to the
field; it is a tamed elephant whereon the
king mounts. It is the one who is self-
controlled who is best among men, who
bears patiently with abusive language.
*
If you should find a wise companion with
whom to consort, a man of good life and
self-possessed, walk with him joyfully and
deliberately, vanquishing all troubles. But if
you should not find such a wise companion,
then travel as a king who has renounced his
kingdom and his conquests ; travel alone as
an elephant who has renounced the ele¬
phant forest.
As a tree, through hewn down, grows up
again and again if its roots be uninjured
and secure, even so the yearnings of
craving, if not destroyed, will reproduce
themselves again and again.
He who has reached the goal, who is
free from worry, who is free from craving,
and who has rid himself of demeritorious
tendencies such a one has thereby des¬
troyed the darts of existence and wears this
body for the last time.
The sun shines by day; by night doth the
moon shine; resplendent in his armour ap¬
pears a warrior; lustrous in meditation a
Brahmin. But the Buddha shines radiant
by day and by night.
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
BOROBUDUR Sr^'
From India, Buddhism spread in the first
century to almost every part of Asia. Wherever
it took root, it brought artistic inspiration and
stimulated much of the greatest art that Asia
has known. One of the most noble monu¬
ments of Buddhist art is the gigantic sanctuary
raised from 750 A.D. onwards at Borobudur
on the island of Java. Details, shown here,
from one of Borobudur's hundreds of bas
reliefs, relateoneofthe "avadanas" the Buddhist
legends of saintly deeds. According to this
particular legend there existed in the time of
Buddha a realm called Roruka ruled by a
Buddhist king named Rudrayana. One day '
a tremendous sand storm buried the kingdom,
but the king's minister, Hiru, managed to
save its treasures and escaped by sea.
After a long and perilous voyage, he finally
reached a friendly land and founded agreat city.
Musée Guimet Archives, Paris.
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
BOROBUDUR (Continued)
A 'Terraced Mountain'
dressed with stone
The Statues and re¬
liefs of Borobudur,
which has been cal¬
led the supreme
monument of mys¬
tic Buddhism inJava,
illustrate the final
development of
Buddhist art in Asia.
Detail from one of
the relief panels
(left) depicts Sujata,
a herdsman's daugh¬
ter, offering milk
rice to the. Buddha
to break his fast.
. ' _ - . ..
Musée Guimet Archives, Paris
Copyright Cartier-Bresson-Magnum
1,400 bas reliefs
From the summit of the great stupa at Borobu¬
dur, a statue of the Buddha in meditation
(above, right) gazes out over the central plain
of Java towards a towering volcanic peak
on the horizon. Borobudur consists of five
walled-in rectangular terraces and above them,
three round platforms on which are seventy-
two bell-shaped stupas (left). By walking
round the monument pilgrims can read in its
504 statues and 1,400 bas reliefs the story of
man's journey through birth and death to
Copyright A. Martin
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
and 500 statues
ultimate enlightenment with the culmination
of the career of the Bodhisattva in the realms
of the mystic Buddhas. The three miles of
carvings are arranged in such a way that by
following the rite of pradaksina (walking round
them and always turning with the right shoul¬
der to the wall) pilgrims follow the footsteps
of the Buddha. Crowning Borobudur, a
"terraced mountain" clothed In stone, is a
sealed terminal stupa, seen In photo on right.
Today Indonesia is a largely Moslem country.
Courtesy A. Vigier
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
46
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
Images of Buddha
outnumber
the people
Thailand has been called the land of Buddhist images and
its capital Bangkok, is perhaps one of the most im¬
pressive Buddhist cities of all the world. For more than
1,300 years Thai artists have been making images of the
Buddha, ranging in size from tiny miniatures to huge giants.
Carved from many materials stone, plaster, terra cotta,
wood, crystal or jade, silver or gold and, most characteristic
of all, bronze images of Buddha today far outnumber the
inhabitants of Thailand.
Thailand's wealth of monuments has come chiefly from the
devotion of its kings who built magnificent resting places for
their own ashes. The great "wats", as they are known, also
serve as monasteries, schools and hospitals as well as places of
Buddhist worship.
Early Buddhist art drew its inspiration from that of ancient
India, Cambodia and China, while developing its own original
styles. The countryside of northern and central Thailand is
studded with large numbers of temples and monuments such
as those at the ancient cities of Ayudhya, Chiengmai, Sukho-
thai and Lopburi.
Bangkok itself offers a glittering spectacle of Buddhist
sculpture and architecture yet the capital is no more than two
centuries old. For when two hundred years ago King Rama I,
the first monarch of modern Siam (now Thailand) set up his
new capital in Bangkok, it was but a tiny village. Today its
skyline is enhanced by the roofs and spires of 400 temples and
its streets are thronged with yellow-robed priests.
The elaborate roofs and spires of
Bangkok's temples and palaces (all of
them built since 1782) reveal the
richness of detail which marks Thai
Buddhist architecture. The sanctuaries
are built largely of wood with elabor¬
ately carved gables. A distinctive
feature of these modern buildings are
the projecting "Ox-horns" on the
gables. (One of these can be seen
between the spires on the right of
photo above). These " ox-horns "
are actually stylized representations of
nagas, the ancient Indian water spirit
in serpent form. Left, a modern pag¬
oda at Srimahathrat, near Bangkok.
Copyright "Missi"
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
Korea Musée Guimet Archives, Paris
Brighter flame
a better year
Buddhism was Introduced Into Korea from China in 327 A.D.
and reached its apogee between the 10th and the 14th cen¬
turies, after which Confucianism replaced it as the state
religion. The Buddhist Festival, May 24, is still comme¬
morated in Korea in the picturesque Feast of the Lanterns,
when people hang lanterns of many shapes and colours
on high poles. Originally the festival commemorated the
founding of Buddhism, and on that day, Buddhists watched
the lanterns carefully, believing that the brighter the flame
burned, the better their luck would be. Still standing are
some of the magnificent temples built in Korea when
Buddhism was at its height. It was from Korea that Bud¬
dhism reached Japan through the sea routes, and Korean
carpenters laboured ten years to raise the great temple
of Horyuii near Nara In Japan. (See pages 56-57). Above,
a Bodhisattva carved on the walls of the Buddhist cave
temples of Sukku-lam, Korea, early in the 8th century.
48
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
Afghanistan
Asian 'Man
of Gaul'
In 1 922, French archaeologists brought
to light some remarkable sculpture in
the ruins of Hadda, near Jelalabad,
Afghanistan. The figures, made of lime
plaster or stucco and originally bril¬
liantly coloured, had decorated the
walls of Innumerable stupas and monas¬
teries. But the real significance of
this sculpture is its obvious Greco-
Roman Inspiration. In this region,
a "No man's land" of ancient conque¬
rors, there had flourished a Greco-
Roman Buddhist art of singular beauty.
The fragment of the figure holding a
lapful of flowers (left), for example,
is believed to be a model of the Roman
portrait of Antinous, favourite of the
Emperor Hadrian. And the title
"Warrior of ancient Gaul" could easily
be applied to the head, lower left.
Most of the sculpture at Hadda dates
from the 3 rd to the 5th centuries A.D.
Further artistic development was pre¬
vented by the invasion of the Huns
In the 6th century. (See page 2 for
other Greco-Roman Buddhist art)
Musée Guimet, Paris
Copyright Francis Brunei
World's largest Buddhist statue
To the north west of Kabul, capital of Afghanistan, in a green and fertile valley surrounded by
pink and rose red mountains, lies Bamiyan. In ancient times it was a stopping place on the
caravan route which linked Central Asia to India, and through it passed Buddhist pilgrims and
missionaries. Between the 1st and the 3rd centuries A.D. Buddhist monks at Bamiyan carved
innumerable shrines and monastic cells out of the sandstone rocks. The invasion by the
Mongol hordes of Ghengis Khan in the I 3th century brought ruin to the countryside around
Bamiyan and devastation to the Buddhist shrines and sculptures. The two most imposing
relics which still exist are colossal statues of Buddha, one 173 feet high, the other 120,
carved out of the cliffside. Photo, left, shows the largest of these statues (the largest statue
of Buddha in the world). A man can easily walk upright in the opening between the toes.
Above, the second statue in its cliffside niche, surrounded by the openings of former shrines
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
Copyright Camera Presi
Call to prayer on the roof of the world
In Nepal, the birthplace of the Buddha, religious architecture has a
character of its own, as is shown by the famous 9th century stupa at
Bodnath near Katmandou, (inset, left) The "eyes of Buddha" above the
dome are painted in blue and white on a background of gold. It was
from Nepal and the neighbouring state of Sikkim that Buddhism spread
50
to Tibet where It led to the founding of the Lama order of Buddhist
monks. Above, A lama standing beside a small shrine, holds a prayer
wheel and beads during meditation. Inset, right, before a richly deco¬
rated monastery door, a lama prepares to sound the twin metal horns
which are traditionally used to call the faithful to prayer.
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
Copyright Robert J. Sodet.
Painting on a"than-ka", or prayer banner, (above) represents the heavenly court of the Buddha with
the first twelve Dalai-lamas (religious and secular rulers) of Tibet. The present Dalai Lama ("all-
embracing" Lama) is considered to be the 14th. reincarnation of the first. This .painting follows
the general pattern of the Tibetan Buddhist spiritual portraits in which figures are grouped symme¬
trically around the central personality portrayed. Their positions above and below the deity or
saint have symbolical meanings, so also their colours, their attitudes and the details of their costumes.
Below, an allegorical fresco on a temple near Bodnath, Nepal, which showsastrong Indian influence.
Banne r
paintings
from the
Himalayas
With the caravans which toiled
their way through the Hima¬
layas from Sikkim and Nepal
in the 7th century A.D., Buddhism
came to Tibet. Its influence soon
spread with the help of the great king
Song-tseen Gam-po who had married
a Chinese princess of Buddhist faith.
The king was converted to Buddhism
and sent his chief minister to the
sacred places of India to study the
teachings of Gautama the Buddha. A
century later, in about 750 A.D., an
Indian Buddhist monk named Pad-
masambhava crossed the mountains
into Tibet and preached a doctrine
known as Tantrism. This was a mix¬
ture of Mahayana Buddhism (see page
25) and certain magical and mystical
doctrines derived from Hinduism.
In its popular aspects it involved
prayers, ritual dances and the exorcism
of devils. Padmasambhava founded
the branch of monks, or lamas,
known as the "red caps" and trans¬
formed a nation of warriors into a
vast community of monks. Today, at
the great monasteries hidden among
the Himalayas, on the high plateaux
of Tibet and Nepal or scattered over
the Tibetan countryside, thousands of
Buddhist prayer wheels turn endlessly
in the wind. Here, on the "'roof of
the world" the people are among the
most religious of any on earth, and it
has been estimated that a quarter of
the entire male population enters the
priesthood.
In Tibet, Buddhism brought forth
a strange art in which influences
from India, China and Central
Asia were intermingled. A whole
world of symbols came to life in
sculpture and painting. Artist monks
made spiritual preparations includ¬
ing fasting before painting the
than-kas or temple banners which
are a special feature of Tibetan
Buddhist art. Painted on silk or
other fabrics, these banners usually
contain a spiritual portrait of one or
other of the saints and deities, and
also many other figures and scenes,
which tell the story of the central
personality.
A great historian of Asian art, the
late Heinrich Zimmer, wrote of those
works : "One sees here an impressive,
really frightening genius for the ren¬
dition of the terrible aspect of the spi¬
ritual powers. Even the Buddhas and
Bodhisattvas, who elsewhere in the
extensive Buddhist domain are re¬
presented almost exclusively in bene¬
volent guise, here appear as veritable
demons." The Buddhist paintings of
Tibet and of Nepal have much in
common with the art of medieval In¬
dia of which they were originally the
faithful copies. This tradition of
Tibetan painting has been maintained
down the centuries.
51
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
Copyright Majnum-Bischof
Bronze colossus
The period of 80 years, when the capital of Japan was established In Nara In 7 1 0 A.D. until
its transfer to Kyoto in 794, is known as the Golden Age of Japanese sculpture. It was In
this period (referred to by art historians as the Late Nara or Tempyo era) that the famous
Great Buddha, the biggest bronze statue in the world (shown here) was made. The casting
of the Bronze Buddha was first started by the order of Emperor Shomu in 743 and completed
in 749. The seated figure measures 53 feet in height; the face 16 feet, the eye almost 4,
the ear 8]/2 ft. It Is said that the casting of the statue required 437 tons of bronze, 288
pounds of gold and seven tons of charcoal. It is enshrined in the Todaiji Temple, the Buddhist
cathedral meaning "The Great Temple of the East" which Is the largest wooden structure
In the world. Although bronze statuary flourished in the Late Nara Period, clay and dry-
lacquer sculpture were most frequently used. Buddhism In Japan at this period took on
all the characteristics of a national religion and the Buddhist monasteries were built as
national Institutions. At the same time many temples were raised, all competing with one
another in their display of grandeur. Buddhist temples and monasteries were easily
accessible to the public during this era and sculpture and architecture were emphasized.
Later, the nucleus of Buddhist art came to be painting which has held sway ever since.
52
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
Copyright Magnum-Bischol
tri
1 1 K 1
;' ^nSl H^1
Mourners' Lament
The Buddhist sanctuaries which form part of the Horyujl monastery at Nara are renowned
as being among the world's greatest treasure houses of art. In one of these, the famous
Five-Storeyed Pagoda, there is still preserved a series of clay statuettes remarkable for
their poignant realism, their expressions of emotion, tenderness and grief. The first floor
of the Pagoda is occupied by a clay miniature of Mt. Sumeru (the mountain believed in
Buddhism to be the centre of the world) with recesses on the four sides resembling mountain
caves. In these recesses more than 80 of the clay figures, each about afoot high, are arranged
to present four scenes relating to the life of Buddha Sakyamuni. Photos here show some
of the figures In the north cave which depicts a scene of the Nirvana or passing away of
Sakyamuni with various saints, disciples and ascetics lamenting his departure. The Horiuji
Inventory of 747 A. D. records that the statuettes were made in 711. They are the oldest
dated works of clay sculpture in Japan. In the late I 9th century there were I 14 pieces and
originally a good number more, but many of the statues have been lost or seriously damaged.
Most of the existing original statues have been repaired to a greater or lesser extent and
some appear to have been changed about among the four caves. But many figures still
retain their original appearance and are registered as important cultural properties of Japan.
S3
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
JAPAN (Cont'd;
Manshidi Sakamoto, copyright Toto ßunka
Co., Tokyo from "Pageant of Japanese Art'.'
Photo by Yonpachi Fujimoto taken, as are all photos on pages55 to 57,
from "Japanese Sculpture", published by Bijutsu Shuppan-Sha, Tokyo.
A Wooden Image
Floated Ashore
Japanese history, shrouded for centuries in myth and
legend, begins in a small strip of country some
225 miles southwest of Tokyo. Here, in the green
fields and tree-clad mountains around the cities of Nara
and Kyoto, the Japanese nation was born. Like Athens
in ancient Greece, Nara was the gateway through which
religion and art, education and culture entered and spread
through the land of Yamato (the native name of Japan).
Nara was Japan's first great capital, the seat of its first
emperor and the birthplace of Buddhism in the country.
According to legend, a Buddhist image made of camphor
wood floated ashore from the Bay of Chinu (present
Osaka Bay) and henceforth the new religion flourished.
Historically, Buddhism was .introduced when, in the
middle of the 6th century, emissaries from Korea present¬
ed the emperor with a statue of Buddha, several scrolls
of Buddhist scriptures and various ritual implements.
Buddhism immediately struck a sensitive note in the minds
of the people. Buddhist art in Japan starts from this
period. Within 50 years, temples and monasteries, built
under the patronage of the court, rose gracefully from
the heavily wooded landscape at Horyuji near Nara, at
Koryuji near Kyoto and from the hills and valleys of
this whole area the cradle of Japanese art and culture.
With the new religion had come echoes of the art of
India but more important the powerful impact of China
where Buddhism was so greatly transforming and enrich¬
ing Asian art. The story of Japanese architecture and
sculpture is one of successive waves of influence from
China, but like Greece which absorbed and reforged the
aesthetic elements it received from Egypt, Assyria and
Phoenicia, and like China itself in regard to India and
Afghanistan, Japan moulded to its own mode of thought
and expression the artistic traditions it received from China
and distant India. It gathered them up, gave them new
life, added a new conception of Buddhist tenderness and
dignity and a new spirit of grandeur and exaltation that
we discern in the masterpieces of the Asuka, Nara, Heian
and Kamakura periods (7th to 14th centuries.)
Why so much of Buddhist architecture and sculpture
was made of wood instead of stone (though bronze, clay
and dry lacquer were other major materials for statues) is
explained by the abundance of timber from Japan's forests
and the relatively small number of stone quarries. Many
of the wooden treasures have disappeared consumed by
fire, destroyed by earthquake or eaten away bv the ravages
of time. The great bronze Amitabha Buddha of Kama¬
kura outside Tokyo, for instance, now sits unsheltered
under the open sky, but it was once enshrined in a
majestic structure which was struck repeatedly by natural
disasters until it was finally carried away by a tidal wave
in 1495. Despite such calamities, 72,000 ancient sanc¬
tuaries and temples and countless statues, carvings and
reliefs continue to testify to the unique greatness of
Buddhist art in Japan.
In 1180 civil war and fire ravaged the great sanctuaries of Nara.
The repairs and restorations which followed (demanding meti¬
culous knowledge of the older styles) ushered in the great
school of realism of the Kamakura period in the 13th century
which attained its supremacy with the sculptures of such
geniuses as Unkel, his pupil Kaikei and his son Tankei. Left,
a detail of one of two towering doors guardians, 27 feet
high, carved in wood by Unkei and Kaikei for the ravaged
Todaiji monastery at Nara. It illustrates how "realism was the
bone and manly strength the flesh" of the sculpture produced.
The Kamakura spirit of renascence affected not only sculpture.
Old Buddhist sects of the Nara period were revived and new
sects such as Zen Buddhism appeared after the renewal of
contact with China in the I Ith century (suspended In 9th).
These sects shunned icon worship of divinities and developed
portrait sculpture and scroll-paintings to Illustrate lives of
high priests and sect founders. Outstanding example of Kama¬
kura portrait sculpture is statue of the hermit Bahisen carved
by Tankei in 1254 and now at Kyoto. Note flashing eyes In
parchment-like face furrowed by fasting, dessicated body
leaning wearily on pilgrim's wand, hand tendering prayer
scroll. This statue has been described as "one of the most
powerful monastic figures of all time".
54
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
This 7th century camphor-wood statue of the young Buddha (Miroku
Bosatsu) has been called "one of the noblest images of meditation
ever created by the hand of man." The figure which is in the same
Copyright K. Domon
half cross-legged pose as the statue on page 56 has been compared to
Rodin's "The Thinker" but the smiling lips and the non-oriental shape
of eyes and face strangely recall Leonardo da Vinci's "Mona Lisa".
55
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
JAPAN (Continued;
Matchless
calm, grace
and beauty
In the western suburbs of Kyoto, In an area
where many of Japan's film studios are today
located, stands the wooden temple of Koryuji,
one of the richest yet least known storehouses
of Japanese art. Some of the temple's master¬
pieces surpass anything to be found even in
Nara, yet until 1950 no photographs of the
treasures at Koryuji were permitted and they
remained practically unknown. Of all the
works of art In the temple, the statue of
Miroku-Bosatsu (a Bodhisattva, or future
Buddha) is probably the most graceful and
subtle. With its gentle smile, the left hand
on the left ankle and the right elbow on the
right knee, two fingers at the cheek, the
figure is of peerless beauty. This pose,
known as the "Hanka shi-i" attitude, was
the one Prince Gautami assumed when he
was plunged in meditation just prior to his
enlightenment. The statue is carved from a
single block of plain wood but it is thought
that it was originally gilded. It dates from
the early 7th century period, called Asuka.
The piece is now housed in the Treasure Hall
of the Koryuji Temple, established in 1922.
Copyright K. Domon
56
]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier
This clay statue of a deva or
deml-god has remained in
an almost perfect state of
preservation since the 8th
century in the Todaljl Mo¬
nastery at Nara. It is prized
as one of the great mile¬
stones in the history of
Japanese sculpture for Its
composed serenity and noble
humbleness. It is the out¬
standing example of how
piety and art, holiness and
beauty found perfect unity
during the period of Tempyo
sculpture. Especially expres¬
sive is the posture of the
two hands. Clasped hands
are not found in any previous
periods of Buddhist sculp¬
ture. The statue is known in
Japan as Nikko Bosatsu and
stands near an almost Iden¬
tical figure (Gakka Bos¬
atsu) almost equally well
preserved In the great Hok-
kedo Hall of the monastery.
Photo Taikichi Irie.
57
]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[
Buddhist Art (Cont'd from page 14)
In Japan the technique and even the esthetics that guided the
artists after the 6th century A.D. came from China and Korea.
The great temple of Horyuji (an extraordinary example of wood
architecture) was built in ten years by Korean carpenters working
at the Imperial Japanese court. Their national genius prevented
their art from being mere imitation of the Chinese style. The
spirit is entirely Japanese, the most characteristic sculpture being
powerful and virile, frequently leaving a disturbing impact.
As south east Asian cultures were coming into maturity in the
8th century A.D., those of Afghanistan and the Central Asian
kingdoms, ravaged by repeated invasions, started to decline. Many
peoples and many influences had mingled in the art of this region.
Here were found hundreds of terra cotta figures, mammoth
Buddhas, frescoes and reliefs in cave monasteries and in grottos
along the old silk route. The colours of the frescoes show us an
astonishing uniformity of technique and a rich mixture of styles.
The Muslim invasions of the Middle Ages destroyed the last
stronghold of Buddhism in India. Artists and monks living in the
university city of Nalanda fled for refuge to Tibet and Nepal.
Nepalese art continued the mediaeval tradition of Indian Buddhist
art. Tibetan painting and sculpture shows a strange mixture of
Chinese, Indian and local tradition.
India and China were the two countries that spread their cultural
mantle over Asia, but these two giants assimilated into their own
heritage various foreign elements. Chinese Buddhist art absorbed
Indian, Greco-Roman, Central Asian and Iranian influences.
During all those centuries right up to the late Middle Ages,
Chinese Buddhist art passed through various styles but the essential
contribution of China towards Asian Buddhist art is in the expres¬
sion of the Buddha's face. The mystic smile is purely a Chinese
creation and is the expression of a profound religious sentiment.
Wherever we find the suggestion of this smile, in Cambodia, in
Japan, in Java, Siam or Burma, we sense the affinity with China.
During the T'ang period (618-907 A.D.) the figures lose their
hieratic character and become more human, but still full of ma¬
jesty and divinity. It is predominantly T'ang sculpture and painting
that influenced Japan.
China, whose inventive genius has benefitted the world (printing,
the magnetic compass, etc.) also invented many new techniques in
art such as the use of dried lacquer and metallic sheets for sculp¬
ture, and repoussé work. Not only did Buddhist artists develop
landscape painting but Wang Wei (699-759 A.D.) created the
monochrome landscape in Chinese ink which reached its supreme
expression under the Sung dynasty (960-1127 A.D.).
Buddhist art has an amazing unity and an amazing diversity. It
can be compared only to the unity and diversity of Christian art in
Europe. All art seeks to bring us nearer to the values which
guide all men. The Buddha brings a message of peace; Christ
brings us a message of peace; the artist tries to interpret this mes¬
sage in his own way. In the knowledge of the similarity of all men
lies also the fact of the unity of all men and with an understanding
of other arts we deepen our understanding of our own.
'No one has a right' (&».« from page 35;
those members of the human family, who have dark complexions.
The use of the word "Aryan" in the sense of '"noble" and
"spiritual" and "non-Aryan" in the sense of "ignoble" and "im¬
moral" is an eloquent testimony of how Buddhism ignored racial
claims and distinctions. Thus "Aryan quest" means "'spiritual
quest" which is defined as "the quest of one who being subject
to birth, decay and death realizes the evil consequences thereof
and seeks the immortal and secure haven of Nirvana". The
"Aryan haven" means the "spiritual haven" which is "'the state
of being free from lust, hatred and delusion".
There is, however, a philosophical theory of "racism" held by
some of the religious teachers in the Buddha's time which is
mentioned and criticized in the Buddhist texts. It is associated
with two teachers both of whom denied free will to man. One
was Purana Kassapa who denied man's capacity for moral action
in virtue of the fact that he had no free will. The other was
Makkhali Gosala who denied both free will and causation and
argued that beings were miraculously saved or doomed. They
argued that human beings belonged to one or another of six
species or specific types in virtue of which they had certain genetic
constitutions, physical traits and habits and psychological natures
which they were incapable of altering by their own will or effort.
The six types were designated by six colours. They were the black
species, the blue species, the red species, the yellow species, the
white species, and the pure white species.
Whether these colours denoted a difference in their physical
complexions is of course not clear but that they were genetically
different physical cum psychological types is what is implied by
the classification. To the black species belonged the butchers,
fowlers, hunters, fishermen, dacoits and executioners and all those
who adopt a cruel mode of living. They were, incidentally, treated
among the lowest castes and their complexion was on the whole
the darkest.
The other five specific types differed in virtue of their degree of
wickedness or saintliness which it was not in their power to alter.
The pure white species were reckoned to be the perfect saints
though their saintliness was considered to be natural to them as
much as their physical constitutions and was in no way achieved
by any effort or will on their part.
Arguing from the reality of free will and the capacity that man
has within himself of becoming either moral or immoral or even
happy or unhappy by transforming himself or degenerating morally
as the case may be, the Buddha denies that there are such fixed
human types genetically determined. There are no men who are
intrinsically good or evil by nature and must necessarily remain so,
for the evil can turn out to be good and the good degenerate into
the evil.
It would be seen that the emphasis is not on what a man is
born with but what he does with himself, since man, irrespective
of his physical constitution and psychological nature at birth, can,
given the opportunity and effort, change for better or worse.
WHERE TO SUBSCRIBE
Unesco's National distributors from
whom the English, French and Spanish
editions of the UNESCO COURIER
can be obtained are listed below,
AUSTRIA. Wilhelm Frick Verlag, 27
Graben, Vienna I.
BELGIUM. Louis de Lannoy, Editeur-
Libraire, 15, rue du Tilleul, Genval (Bra¬
bant). 80 Belgian francs.
CANADA. University of Toronto Press,
Toronto 5.
Periodica Inc., 5090, Avenue Papïneau,
Montreal 34.
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House, P.O. Box
244, Colombo I.
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CYPRUS. M.E. Constantinides, P.O.
Box 473, Nicosia.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6, Norregade, Copenhagen K.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirj'akauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
FRANCE. Unesco Sales Section,
19, Avenue Kléber, Paris, 16*.
C.C.P. 1 2598-48, Unesco Bookshop,
Paris.
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28,
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd. Indian
Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road, Bom¬
bay I ; I 7, Chictaranjan Avenue, Calcutta
13. 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2.
Sub-Depots : Oxford Book & Stationery
Co., Scindia House, New Delhi; Rajkamal
Publications Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby
Road, Bombay I.
INDONESIA. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Jakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
35, Allenby Road, P.O. Box 4101, Tel-
Aviv.
ITALY. Librería Commissionaria San-
soni, Via Gino Capponi 26, Casella Pos¬
tale 552, Florence.
AMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 99,
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6, Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND SIN¬
GAPORE. Peter Chong & Co., Post
Office Box 135, Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26, Kings-
way, Valletta.
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Ni-
jhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 1 00, Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church.
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos.
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass 7, Oslo.
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60, The Mall,
Lahore ; Bunder Road, Karachi and
35. The Mall, Peshawar.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Ouiapo, P.O. Box
620, Manila.
SWEDEN. A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl.
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgaten 2, Stockholm
16.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5,
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40, rue du Marché, Geneva.
TANGIER, Paul Fekete, 2, rue Cook,
Tangier.
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
UNION OF BURMA. Burma Educa¬
tional Bookshop, 55 1-3, Merchant Street,
P.O. Box 222, Rangoon.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Street, P.O. Box 724, Pretoria.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I.
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 152 West 42 nd St, New York,
36, N.Y,
Columbia University Press, 2960, Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y. (except
periodicals).
U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodna Kniga, Moscow.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjïga,
Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
58
]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[
*0#.y- -- >. r-í nqpHp.sT
British Museum-Skeel This relief panel from a monument at Amaravati in the Andhra region of south India is a remarkable example of
early Buddhist art of the 2nd century A.D. Buddha is not yet depicted in human form. Panel shows four episodes
in the life of Buddha. Top right, the dream of Maya, Buddha's mother. The legend recounts how Maya dreamed
that an elephant descended from heaven and entered her right side, symbolizing the conception of Buddha. Top
left, Queen Maya tells her dream to the King. Bottom right, Buddha is born under a tree, emerging from his
mother's side. Bottom left, a tutelary deity worshipping the infant (not depicted). Amaravati was the capital
of the Andhra dynasty known to Pliny and Ptolemy, and Roman trading posts were set up on the Andhra coast.
]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[
DELICATE MASTERPIECE. An unknown
genius of the Himalayas, where Buddha
was born, executed this remarkable statue
of the "Illuminated One" when he was a
young prince. Made of bronze covered
with gold leaf, the figure, studded with
rubies, turquoises, emeralds and lapis
lazuli, is imbued with symbolism. The
gesture of the right hand represents know¬
ledge, the third eye in the middle of the
forehead indicates penetrating vision and
elevated thought, while the soft smile
(reminiscent of the celebrated smile of
the statues of the cathedral of Rheims)
symbolizes the "Enlightenment" that the
future Buddha ultimately reached. This
11th century statue, is one of the finest
examples extant of Nepalese-Tibetan art.
Photo copyright, Francii Brunei
ZV-
; ^ '#
&l
*z
Ài>
V:
>tf
SM
iS1 3
^
'%&
¿j^f*
M
i
:t/
<:
**v';-
<P
*f.
9
w*
Mfc Jt
'*JT1
*-4*>Í
a
JS
V
lV
Vî
tt
i -t
HU'
*-*",**"'»*»tor1 m
V1*^ *" V1
pm h
iimiitiii ' füHMUmur -m» i
'**»»..
]]>
</page>
</document>
