<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="069029eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
HC, s^f. /. £?./?
Ji S
W/NDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
- (8th year)
Price : 7d (U. K.)
30 francs (France)
SCHOOLS
N THE SAND
Saving half a million
Arab refugee children
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
* IRAQ
Ar
'
V
V
UNRWA/ UNESCO SCHOOLS . Lj
Figures show number of schools
per district .)
SYRIA
EGYPT
EGYPT
*
ARAB REFUGEE CAMPS
IN THE NEAR EAST
UNITED NATIONS ORGANISATIONS
cooperating in activities for the benefit of
ARAB REFUGEES FROM PALESTINE
tiv Refugee Camps (Tents o> Hüls)
® UNRWA Offices
UNICEF
UNRWA : United Nations
Reliel and Works Agency
(or Palestine Refugees in
the Near East.
UNICEF : United Nations
Children's Fund.
WHO : World Health Organ.
UNESCO : United Nal-ons
Educational. Scientific and
ILO : International Labou
FAO: Food and Agricul¬
tural Organisation
UNTSO : Un.led Nations
Truce Supervision Organ-
UNCCP : United Nations
Conciliation Commission
UNTAA : Un, led Nations
Technical Assistance Ad-
1 UNRWA
FAO
UNCCP
UNTAA
E£Y
SYRIA
..
JORDAN
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N" 7. 1955
Courier
A WIMAOW OPIN ON TMI WOILO
Number 7 - 1955
8th YEAR
CONTENTS
PAGE
3 EDITORIAL
5 EXILED IN THE DESERT
A million refugees pick up the threads of life
By Myrtle Winter
9 PLEASE GIVE US SCHOOLS
Arabs who put education above rations
By Felix Walter
16 MAGNA CUM LAUDE REFUGEE STUDENTS
OTHER ARTICLES AND FEATURES
17 CHINESE OPERA
Mosaic of music, acrobatics and ballet
By Balwant Gargi
21 MASTERPIECES YOU CAN NOW BUY
High quality reproductions of a century's paintings
By Jean Leymarie
27 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
28 JUNGLE INDIANS WITH AN AXE TO GRIND
The thirst for iron among primitive peoples
By Alfred Metraux
30 KOREA'S THIRTY MILLION TEXTBOOKS
32 UNESCO IN PICTURES
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Brief notes on education, science and culture
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organi¬
zation
Editorial Offices
Unesco, 19, Avenue Kleber, Paris 16, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate -Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Circulation Manager
Jean Groffier
U.S.A. : Henry Evans
UNESCO stands for United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Orga¬
nization. It is one of the Specialized Agencies of UN, the United Nations.
"The purpose of the Organization is to contribute to peace and security by
promoting collaboration among the nations through education, science and
culture... To realize this purpose the Organization will collaborate in the work
of advancing the mutual knowledge and understanding of peoples, through all
means of mass communication... maintain, increase and diffuse knowledge...
by initiating methods of international co-operation calculated to give the people
of all countries access to the printed and published materials produced by
any of them." (From the Constitution of UNESCO.)
Individual articles not copyrighted may be reprinted from THE COURIER but
must be accompanied by the following credit line: "Reprinted from UNESCO
COURIER". Signed articles reprinted must carry the author's name.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied by an inter¬
national repjy-coupon covering postage.
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of THE COURIER.
Annual subscription rates of THE COURIER : 6/-; $ I.SO or 300 French frs
or equivalent (U.S. edition $ 2.50) (MC. 55. 1 93. A)
COVER PHOTO
This child is one of the 180,000 who this
year are receiving primary or secondary
schooling under the UNRWA-UNESCO
educational programme for Arab refugee
children. The Arab refugees, in one sense,
have an advantage over many other peoples
of the Middle East in the number of their
daughters in school. In the camps of the
Jordan, girls represent 48 per cent of the
total enrolment. (UNRWA Photo)
This century has become hardened to migrations,
expulsions and "concentrations" oí human beings.
These exoduses make the headlines for a few weeks
and then the "refugees", the '"displaced persons", or the
"deportees", sink into oblivion.
In the Middle East, today, there are nearly one million
refugees from Palestine. They have no land to begin life
anew and build another country. They are scattered in
hundreds of camps... old army bivouacs, abandoned barracks,
tent cities, and tin-can towns. But they have not been
abandoned. Since 1948, help has been coming from the Arab
States and from the United Nations.
Aid to children came first. These children were growing
up among lost and bewildered adults. They had no other
horizon but their camp, and no other images in their heads
but the painful memories of their parents. The children ran
the risk of becoming natives of that frightful modern Umbo,
the universe of the refugee ignorant, bitter and useless.
At first a few dozen schools were started. These had the
sky for a roof, then they went under canvas; at first they
had neither desks nor pencils, then equipment arrived.
At present there are over 300 UNRWA-UNESCO schools
attended by over 100,000 boys and girls while grants-in-aid
enable a further 60,000 children to attend other schools, run
privately or by governments. The Unesco General Con¬
ference last December and the Unesco Executive Board in
March together allocated a total of $170,000 for the two year
period, December 1954 to December 1956, as aid to schools
for Arab refugees.
In these schools, children learn the Koran as they learn
reading, writing and arithmetic. They also learn history
and geography. They learn trades that spell independence
for them. At present vocational training teachers are
working in refugee schools with courses running from three
months to two years. These schools offer a tremendous
variety of job opportunities: printing, bookbinding, machine
shop work, car maintenance, weaving, brush-making,
carpentry, basket-making, photography, shoe-making, home
economics/radio and electricity.
Finding teachers for these schools was no easy task. As
recently as three years ago, only one-third of the teaching
staff, all of it Palestinian in origin, was considered as
qualified. Since then, more than a hundred teachers have
been able to obtain sound pedagogic training at universities
in Beirut and Damascus and at the Khadouri agricultural
school in Jordan. In addition, future teachers are able to
attend normal schools in Iraq and universities in Egypt.
Finally, more than six hundred teachers have been given an
in-service course in certain camps. Many young refugees
are now going to secondary schools. For higher education,
refugees have been admitted to Lebanese, Egyptian and
Syrian universities.
But what about the adults and even the adolescents who
are too old to go to school? Is feeding the only way of
helping them? They deserve the same opportunity as the
children of the camps, for they, too, are hunting a way out
of the stifling inertia of body and mind.
The camps, slowly but surely, are beginning to resemble
villages where people can lead a normal life with a window
on the outside world. The school is always their centre and
it is always surrounded by flowers and vegetable gardens.
Men of the camp fill its classrooms at night, not only to learn
how to read and write for illiteracy is still high but also
to hold meetings and discussions which serve the function
of a study club or a municipal council, as the case may be.
Huge tents now shelter warehouses and workshops
shoe-making shops, carpentry shops, clothing factories or co¬
operative bakeries. People no longer want to be left alone.
They have slipped back into the daily relationships of work
and of business and also of the sports which have dealt a
final blow to boredom. Instead of being a statistical item,
the refugee is now a producer and a citizen and, as his
leaders say, "Life has a meaning for him."
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
TENTS AND HUTS
AND BRAND NEW
MODEL VILLAGES
When armed conflict broke out in Palestine seven
years ago, nearly 1,000,000 Arabs packed their
belongings and took refuge in the neighbouring
countries of the Hashemite Kingdom of Jordan,
Syria, Lebanon, Iraq and in the Gaza strip. But
local resources could not cope with all of them
and many found themselves shelterless in the
desert, living in caves or existing in holes they
had dug in the ground. Food, tents and medical
supplies were the first essentials and these were
rushed to the areas öf greatest need. Today the
problem of the Palestine Arab refugees is still
unsolved. But a great deal has been done to make
living conditions more bearable. Tented villages,
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N" 7. 1955
like the Fawwar Camp in Jordan (above), have in
many cases been replaced by huts like those at
Jebalia, in the Gaza coastal strip (below, right).
The United Nations Relief and Works Agency
(UNRWA) has also builtsome experimental villages.
Marj-na'ja (below, left) in western Jordan, houses
36 families. (UNRWA and UNESCO Photos)
:»;*;«-?> f..t
N THE DESERT
by Myrtle Winter
It is just over seven years ago that
nearly a million people locked the
doors of their homes, and taking
with them only the few clothes
they could carry and provisions to last
for a day or two set off on a journey
from which there has as yet been no
return.
Armed conflict had again come to
the Holy Land, and this time the
victims were 900,000 Arabs, for the
most part unarmed civilians who could
play no part in the fighting in which
they were suddenly enveloped.
That they would return to their
homes once the shooting was over,
none of them doubted for a minute-
it might be a matter of days, or even
weeks. Yet the cruel irony of fate
decreed it otherwise. For the solution
of the world's longest-standing prob¬
lem of displaced personswith the
arrival of hundreds of thousands of
European Jews on the shores of
Palestinewas to result in the creation
of another problem, the hitherto in¬
soluble problem of the Arab Refugees.
Wherever they went in the surround¬
ing countries of Syria, Lebanon, Jordan
and Iraq the refugees met with the
traditional Arab hospitality. But local
resources were not sufficient. There
were too many refugees. To the
Kingdom of Jordan alone came half a
million. Yet Jordan, before the trou¬
bles, itself had a population of only
700,000 and, in the Gaza coastal strip,
refugees outnumbered the original
inhabitants by nearly four to one.
Lessons on the sands
In the emergency it was above all a
question of saving lives. Food,
shelter and medical supplies were
rushed to the scene of greatest need by
the United Nations, with the assistance
of the International Committee of the
Red Cross, the League of Red Cross
Societies, and the American Friends
Service Committee, who were sup¬
ported by the host governments and
countless local organizations who came
forward to help.
While people were starving and
suffering from exposure, there was no
time or money to spare for non¬
essentials; consequently, to begin with,
Myrtle Winter is Chief of the Visual Aid and Photo¬
graphic Division, United Nations Relief and Works
Agency for Palestine Refugees.
there were no schools. But as the
weeks stretched into months and the
children roamed the streets in idleness,
it was not long before this problem too
had to be faced. Before there was
any hope of tackling it as a whole, in¬
dividual teachers, themselves refugees,
took the initiative into their own
hands. Unpaid and with no shelter
from the burning sun they gathered
little groups of children around them
in the open desert.
Flour and soap salaries
Many of the teachers had known
the children from before, for
whole villages took flight from
Palestine together and have clung
together in their exile. In a world
where everything was shattered,
these first make-shift classes brought
new hope and a purpose back
to life. The parents, the village elders
and the Mukhtars (village headmen)
took heart. Bearded sheikhs did their
share in giving religious instruction.
The younger generation would not
grow up in ignorance. In recognition
of their services the teachers were
allowed an extra bag of flour, a pound
of sugar or a few cakes of soap.
A number of classes were started by
the Red Cross and the other Voluntary
Agencies. The Y.M.C.A. opened a
school near Jericho, in the largest
camp in the Jordan Valley, which
remains to this day; the Quakers
supported several in the Gaza strip.
In other places the modest needs of
the first refugee schools were met by
selling the empty containers in which
the monthly rations reached the
camps gunny sacks, kerosene cans,
and containers of all shapes and sizes.
Here and there, a spare tent was made
available, so that the children could do
their lessons in the shade.
By the time that the Third Unesco
General Conference was held in Beirut
in 1948, thousands of boys and girls
were already receiving some form of
education as a result of these efforts,
and the delegates to the congress, many
of whom made it their business to
study the plight of children at first
hand, were so impressed with what
they saw that they gave a fresh
impetus to Unesco's efforts
to raise funds. As a (Cont'd on
result contributions came next page)
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
PACKED CLASSES During the past four or
five years, half a million children among these Arab
refugees have been saved from illiteracy and Ignorance.
This year, UNRWA will be responsible for the school¬
ing of about 160,000 children of elementary school
age and another 20,000 who attend secondary classes.
In these schools, packed classes of Arab children
(photos, right) follow their lessons with touch¬
ing eagerness. (UNRWA and UNESCO photos)
from far and wide and the first Unesco
contribution of $15,000 had reached
« 90,000 before the end of 1949. This
gift, which seemed to come as an ans¬
wer to so many prayers, at last gave
the teachers the chance to organize.
By May, 1950, when the United
Nations Relief and Works Agency for
Palestine Refugees was established by
the U.N. General Assembly to relieve
the Voluntary Agencies of the burden
they could no longer carry, there were
already 33,500 children in the schools.
By 1953 that number had been doubled,
and by 1955, including children re
ceiving grants-in-aid to study in
outside schools, it had been mult'nlied
nearly six-fold to reach a total of
170,000. The upward spiral of unrwa's
schools programme with technical
assistance from unesco is indeed
remarkable, but not so remarkable
when it is considered that of the entire
Arab refugee population, no less than
50 7c are children beneath the age
of 16nearly half a million children.
It is impossible for any one to
appreciate the significance of education
amongst the refugees unless he has
seen the conditions in which they live.
A pilgrim to the Holy Land who visits
the place of Baptism on the River
Jordan will pass one camp after
another on his way to the Mount of
Temptation, and should he climb it to
the summit, where a Greek monastery
commemorates the spot, he will see
below him stretching far into the
distance a mushroom growth of tents
and ramshackle mud huts the home
of 75,000 refugees. These men, women
and children outnumber the original
people who lived in the nearby town
of Jericho by more than seventy to one.
Why such a dense concentration?
In this valley 800 feet below sea level,
where heat lies shimmering in the air
and summer temperatures are the
highest recorded in the Near East,
what employment can there be for so
many people?
The answer is simple. The refugees
are concentrated in regions where
there is water. In the Jordan Valley
there are many springs. One of the
most abundant, Elisha's fountain,
provides the water for the large camp
which lies at the foot of the Mount of
Temptation, known by its Arab name
of "Ain-el-Sultan", or Sultan's Spring.
unrwa may distribute a monthly ration
with a minimum of 1,600 calories a day,
but without water the refugees would
die of thirst. In Jordan, water is
scarce and they cannot choose.
It is true that chances of work are
remote, although in years when there
are plentiful spring rains, seasonal
employment is obtainable for a good
many of the men folk at a very low
wage. If the present survey work
carried out by unrwa in conjunction
with the Jordan Government for a
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N" 7. 1955
major irrigation scheme in the Jordan
and Yarmuk valleys is successful,
there would be opportunity for tens of
thousands of refugees and Jordanians
alike to find work in agriculture, not
to speak of the secondary economic
benefits which would create oppor¬
tunity in other fields. But today un¬
employment is the refugee's plague.
In Gaza the situation is worse, for
with 200,000 refugees amongst an
original population of only 80,000, who
themselves have lost the greater part
of their lands and trade, there is little
chance of even seasonal employment.
The Gaza strip, as it is called, which
is the only part of the coastal plain of
Palestine remaining in Arab hands, is
but 12 miles long and between three
and five miles wide, and more than half
is made up of sand dunes. Here, life
in the sense that everyone had lived it
before came to a sudden stop. Or¬
dinary economic concepts of money in
circulation and employment figures
have completely lost their meaning.
The refugees have little to do but line
up before unrwa's distribution centres
to receive their monthly ration of
flour, pulses (peas, beans, lentils), oils
and fats, sugar, rice, milk, soap and
kerosene.
The Gaza residents, without rations,
are, if anything, worse off than the
refugees, but they have nevertheless a
quantity of agricultural products which
they may barter for some otherwise
unobtainable commodity amongst re¬
fugee rations. Occasionally goods
change hands for a few coins and some
small payments may be made for
labour or services rendered. A man
may spend all day selling four
tomatoes, or finding a customer for a
a little sugar or an empty bottle.
In these circumstances the only
members of the . family who can live
anything approaching a normal life
are the children who go to school at
regular hours, who have something to
do which is worth doing and who can
have any sense of achievement. There is
never any problem of absenteeism, the
children are always punctual and do
their lessons with a gravity and
eagerness which can leave no visitor
unmoved. Education amongst girls
has progressed by leaps and bounds,
and if it is true that there are more
children in school today than there
would have been but for the exodus,
it must be borne in mind that' they
are cut off from the life of a productive
community and can no longer grow up
in the trade or tend the land of their
fathers as of old.
In present circumstances, the darker
grows the future the more desperately
do refugee fathers and mothers seek
education for their children. This is
true of all classes, including the
Bedouins. Education has become a
part of the struggle for survival.
No sooner is a new' school built toda>
and the last classes are moved out of
the tents than more children are
pressing on the doors, new teachers
are found somehow, and up go the
tents again. In Jordan alone this year
165 classrooms were built and next
year's programme provides for nearly
as many more.
Expansion has been so rapid that
there is always a scarcity of school-
books and equipment. One
school may have a wallmap (Cont'd on
but no football it is here next page)
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
that Unesco Gift Coupons have often
proved invaluable to fill the gap.
Nor does it finish with the children.
Everywhere in the world end of term
exams are no doubt much the same.
There are the same anxious faces; the
same last minute poring over notes.
But this year, in Gaza, there was a
difference. More than 300 adults, men
and women of all ages, joined the
children in sitting for the State Exams.
They were members of the unrwa-
unesco Fundamental Education Centres
whose enthusiasm made them insist on
being allowed to test
their new-found
knowledge by actually
taking the examina¬
tion. Results show
them to have been
amply justified, for
93 % of all adults
were successful.
The programme to
Introduce fundamental
education amongst the
Arab refugees, which
started in 1953 with the
help of a unesco ex¬
pert loaned to unrwa
has produced outstanding results every¬
where most of all in Gaza. The
schools have scarcely time to close after
the last child has packed up and gone
when it is time for them to open up
again, transformed into a kind of club.
In one room people will be reading
magazines, borrowing books from the
library, playing back-gammon or
dominoes, or writing their contribution
to the "Wall-Newspaper". Attached to
many centres are workshops where
members can learn carpentry, shoemak-
ing, tailoring and other crafts.
An allied development of unrwa's
Welfare Division has been the setting
up of embroidery centres, where
refugee girls have been trained to
adapt the traditional cross stitch
patterns of the Holy Land on modern
table linen and to turn out well cut
skirts and blouses. Skilfully developed
by a tireless marketing supervisor,
herself a refugee, sales of these goods
have increased so much that today in
the Gaza strip alone 700 women and
girls have full time employment.
Indeed rehabilitation in all its
aspects is the burning problem of
unrwa and the capital available for
this purpose is many times greater
than the funds available for relief. In
close co-operation with the Arab
governments, unrwa is exploring all
possible means of making the refugees
self-supporting. This may take the
form of 50 million dollars earmarked
for the Jordan Valley Development, or
a few hundred cash down to buy a
barber's chair, or a lathe to re¬
establish a refugee craftsman in his
former trade.
Here, as a result of water and soil
first modern vocational training centre
with the aid of experts from the In¬
ternational Labour Organization, two
years ago outside Jerusalem. Since
then the first trainees have all found
employment and a second centre has
been opened in Gaza, while in Lebanon
and Syria hundreds of scholarships
are given in different fields to refugees
to study in existing institutions.
In spite of these efforts it would be
misleading to suggest that a solution
had been found to the burning
problem of the Arab refugees. The
CLASSES FOR PARENTS
keep many of the refugee
schools open well into the
night. Since 1953, funda¬
mental education has been
developed with the aid of
a UNESCO expert loaned to
UNRWA. After the chil¬
dren go home, schools be¬
come "clubs" where in one
room people read or play
back-gammon and in another,
have lessons in English or
pore over their first Aratic
reader. (UNESCO photo)
surveys an agricultural co-operative
will spring up, there a factory will
receive a loan to buy new machinery
after undertaking to employ a quota
of refugee labour. To create employ¬
ment on one occasion unrwa actually
went into business itself by setting up
a large modern tent factory where
refugees are employed to manufacture
their own tents instead of importing
them from overseas.
Last but not least is the vocational
and professional training of the most
promising children who graduate from
the refugee schools, unrwa opened its
refugees cry out to be allowed to go
back to their homes a right ac¬
knowledged in early U.N. resolutions.
But political tension has run too high.
All that can be said in the meantime
is that unrwa is seeking every means
to restore to the refugees their eco¬
nomic independence, while at the same
time educating their children and
training their youth so that, whatever
the future may bring, the new
generation will not grow up in
ignorance, and will have a chance to
play its part in the rapid development
of the Middle East.
8'
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N" 7. 1955
FLIGHT TO
GAZA
In 1948, refugees from Pa¬
lestine fled to the narrow
strip of coast, some 25 miles
long by three miles wide,
around the city of Gaza, thus
increasing its population from
90,000 to nearly 300,000.
The refugees were concen¬
trated ¡n nine camps made
up mostly of tents which
were eventually replaced
by cement brick buildings.
Gaza Beach Camp (right)
whose four-room houses are
built of cement bricks and
tiles makes a sharp contrast
with houses in the ancient
city of Gaza, left. (Photos :
UNRWA and UNESCO)
TAKE AWAY OUR RATIONS
BUT GIVE US SCHOOLS
by Felix Walter
Half a million children among the Arab refugees from
Palestine have been saved during the past four or five
years from illiteracy and almost total ignorance, as well
as from the despair that ignorance breeds. These early
emergency years are over and now an educational system
devised for the children of the refugees has been set up and
is in working order. This system might almost be described
as a "'Ministry of Education", though it is difficult to conceive
of a ministry that has heavy responsibilities without a shred
of real power and that performs its international task within
the framework of four different nations each with its own
educational system.
Certainly there are a number of genuine ministries of edu¬
cation in the world today which cater to the needs of fewer
pupils and dispose of smaller budgets. During the coming
school year this make-believe ""Ministry" or, to give it its real
name, the Education and Training Division of the United
Nations Relief and Works Agency (unrwa) will be responsible
for the schooling of about 160,000 children of elementary
Felix Walter is Deputy Chief of the Educational and Training Division, United
Nations Relief and Works Agency for Palestine Refugees.
school age and of approximately 20,000 who will attend
secondary classes.
In addition it will provide education at the university level
for some 350 students and up-to-date vocational training for
about twice that number. It will be given about five million
dollars to do this job and will be expected to spend every cent
to the best advantage, for this money comes from the pockets
of the taxpayers of the United Nations.
The education of the Arab refugees has become a very large-
scale enterprise. Indeed nowhere in the world today is an
international organization embarked on an educational
project that approaches this particular one in scope and
magnitude. The United Nations have in fact been forced by
the Middle Eastern emergency to go in for school-mastering
on a mass scale, which is certainly something they never
contemplated in 1948 when the refugees first poured across
the borders of Palestine.
How is the job done? Technical guidance at the top comes
from a handful of educators who, when they are not trav¬
elling back and forth across the Arab countries
where the refugees live, do their administrative (Cont'd on
duties at the Unrwa Headquarters in Beirut. P°Se ,4)
liif*. .* ' t<L . 'J ...<ff"Ä nrr
BAKING BREAD in the Mia-Mla Camp near
Sidon, Lebanon, where over 3,000 refugees live
in tents or barracks. Bread is baked over the
fire on an iron shape which is called a "sage".
REFUGEE TRADERS in the camps deal in
anything from empty bottles, beads and bolts to
a handful of sugar. Here, ordinary economic
concepts have completely lost their meaning.
COLLECTING FIREWOOD, in the Yarmuk.
When the Yarmuk-Jordan Valley dam is built,
this now desolate land, may support more
than 150,000 refugees. (UNRWA photos)
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
GIVE US SCHOOLS
Good bill of health
Since the days of the first emergency in Palestine, when
nearly a million human beings were living on the verge
of starvation, the preservation of health and the preven¬
tion of disease among the refugees has been a major
activity of the U.N. and its Specialized Agencies. The
spread of infectious diseases had to be prevented, clean
water supplies provided and decent sanitary conditions
created In the camps. Malaria, to which many newcomers
to the Jordan Valley fell victim, had also to be combatted.
As a result of health programmes, no major epidemics
have broken out and health conditions in general have
improved. UNRWA maintains more than 80 clinics
which receive an average of half a million visits a month.
Photos, from left to right, show: Women's ward in
the Gaza T.B. clinic; youngsters waiting their turn at a
clean water supply point in one of the camps; a visitor
(not very reassured) to one of the mobile clinics which
sets out daily from the town of Tyre to call at mountain
villages ¡n Southern- Lebanon. (UNRWA photos)
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N" 7. 1955
m
i
à Milk and a hot meal
Palestine Arab refugees being helped by UNRWA receive
food rations which provide a diet of approximately
1,500 calories dally in summer and slightly more In
winter. In many cases the refugees manage to supple¬
ment their rations by finding at least part-time or sea¬
sonal employment, but where this is impossible supple¬
mentary feeding centres play an important part in allev¬
iating hardship. A daily hot meal is served to refugees
certified as suffering from under-nourishment by their
UNRWA doctor. In addition to the monthly ration, a
daily cup of milk is given (left) to all children up to the
age of 15 and to expectant and nursing mothers. At
regular intervals surveys are carried out by World
Health Organization or Food and Agriculture Organiza¬
tion specialists to watch over the general trend of refugee
health. Simple education in nutrition and health is
given at the centres and also by social workers (adjoin¬
ing) who take an active part in village community
development projects. (UNRWA and UNESCO photos)
- A*
ii
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
GIVE US SCWiDOLS^<<>
\
V \
NEEDLEWOMEN. Embroi¬
dery centre (above) created by
UNRWA in I 950 includes train¬
ing in weaving, tailoring and
sewing. It has been so successful
that branches have been devel¬
oped in six camps. Altogether it
occupies six hundred refugees
from six to 30 years of age, and its
products are sold locally and in
other Arab states. Self help of
this kind has brought new life
to many thousand hands. Aim
of such programmes has been
to fight the demoralizing effects
of years of camp life, ration lines
and unemployment with self
help instead of relief. Left, a
six -year old refugee girl learns
to embroider. (UNRWA photos)
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N" 7. 1955
SHOEMAKERS : Shoe-
making is one of the oc¬
cupational skills in which
training is given in camp
fundamental education
centres. At first, refu¬
gees learned to make
shoes for their own use,
then for each other. Then
as the centre began to be¬
come known, orders came
from outside the camp.
(UNRWA photo)
SKILLED WORKERS: In co-operation with the Egyptian Govern¬
ment, a modern vocational training centre (photo left) has been set
up by UNRWA for Arab refugees in the Gaza coastal strip. At
present, over 170 boys are following specialized training courses
lasting two years in electricity, woodwork, fitting, blacksmithing
and sheet metal work. The centre has completely modern equip¬
ment and possesses a football ground and an Olympic track. Above
students are taking the electric welding course. (UNRWA photos)
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
GIVE US
SCHOOLS
A teacher is worth
his weight in gold )*jtifcil
(Continued from page 9)
Their present head is a Dutch educator who has been all
his life a student of Arabic and the ways of Islam and who
was for some years Minister of Education in Indonesia. He is
assisted on the purely educational side by a Canadian deputy,
by a Jordanian Educational Consultant who was twice
Minister of Education in his own country and by a Consul¬
tant for Fundamental Education who is a Moslem from India.
On the vocational training side his advisers are a Scottish
deputy and an Anglo-Irish consultant. Two educational
assistants, one an Arab and one an Armenian (whom fate
has made a double refugee!) complete the Headquarters staff
which though small does at least include two real Ex-Minis¬
ters of Education.
Most of this Headquarters staff is either recruited by
Unesco or seconded from the personnel of that organization,
for it is Unesco's responsibility to provide both technicians
and technical guidance. On the other hand, the money that
pays for the area staffs, including a corps of teachers over
2,600 strong, and the money that pays for school buildings
and for school supplies comes from Unrwa funds.
This small Headquarters staff is fully occupied with the
formulation of policy, with the compilation of statistical data,
with wrestling with budget officials. as is the lot of educa¬
tion officers everywhere and with liaison with international
organizations and with the educational systems of what are
called "the host countries". At the next level, that is to say
in each of the four host countries, the elaborate educational
machine is watched over by a field education officer.
One of these officials supervises, from the Unrwa sub-
headquarters on Mount Scopus in Arab Jerusalem, the school
system which caters to the children of the close on half a
million refugees in the Hashemite Kingdom of Jordan. His
sector includes the sprawling camp schools of the lower
Jordan Valley, where summer heat is so intense that the
school year has to be cut short in May. It includes also the
trim new stone buildings the Agency has erected beside the
rock-bound refugee camps of Samaria and Judea as well as
the crowded classes packed tightly into rented buildings in
Amman and the Old City of Jerusalem.
Inspectors on horseback
His colleague in Gaza has a much more compact school
system to administer but it is a populous one too with
the children of nearly a quarter of a million refugees.
Finally, in Beirut and Damascus respectively, two other Field
Education Officers cater to the children of the two hundred
thousand refugees which Lebanon and Syria shelter between
them. There are fewer big camps here and inspecting schools
in the remote hill-country villages, in Syria particularly, may
often entail a long trip by Land Rover or on horseback.
In each host country care is taken to adhere closely but not
slavishly to the local curriculum. This entails the use of the
same text-books as are used in the local government schools.
Such a policy makes it easy for pupils attending Unrwa-
Unesco schools to sit for Government examinations and has
the further merit of lessening the gap between refugee and
local population. .
Visitors to the area often ask where all the teachers come
from. The answer is that the refugees were lucky in one
thing, namely that they came from a country which enjoyed
a relatively high standard of education. It was natural
therefore that in the long, straggling columns that fled north
and east and south in the summer of 1948, there should have
been a high proportion of school inspectors and headmasters
and teachers of every grade as Well as farmers and artisans
and the semi-nomad Bedouins.
These teachers from Old Palestine still play an important
part in the Unrwa-Unesco educational system, though their
number is being increasingly diluted by younger teachers who
never saw service in the schools of Mandatory Palestine and
whose only training has been acquired in the hard school of
experience and in brief summer refresher courses.
The Arab refugee teachers have done a heroic task, often
working under the most unfavourable conditions for long
hours and low pay. Even the new and improved scale which
is about to be introduced will only provide a minimum
monthly salary of about $45 a month with a maximum rising
to about three times that amount. The fact is that food and
14
PLANTING TREES to anchor moving sand dunes is a job in which children
can help. Here, youngsters in one of the refugee camps join rest of
population in executing one phase of the battle against encroaching sands.
onelter and medical care had first claims on available funds.
Mention of the gallant corps of Unrwa-Unesco teachers
leads directly to another question that is often asked. What
is the level and quality of the education that is imparted to
the children of the Arab refugees?
Now the quality of teaching depends directly on the quality
of the teachers themselves, and if some of these are now
rather old-fashioned and out-of-date and others largely raw
and untrained that quality is not going to be of the highest
order. But the correct answer to the question of quality
probably is that Unrwa-Unesco education is not nearly as
good as those responsible for it would like it to be and not
nearly as bad as some detractors make out.
It can certainly stand comparison with the kind of educa¬
tion that the largely underdeveloped host countries are able
to afford, though these countries are constantly straining to
improve their standards.
Still it would be folly for those responsible to the United
Nations and to the conscience of the world to rest on these
dubious laurels. The improvement of methods of teaching
and of the general quality of education is the foremost goal
of the five-year plan for education on which the Agency is
now embarking. Ways must be found of humanizing the
educational process, of rendering it less solemn and less
static, of substituting the careful development of the indivi¬
dual intelligence for the excessive reliance on memory and
AN ACCIDENT? No! Just a scene from a play written, produced and
acted by young men in one of the refugee centres. Over 30,000 persons
make regular use of the welfare centres now set up. (UNRWA photos)
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N° 7. 1955
TENT MAKING is now an industry run on modern lines at the Ghor
Nimrin factory near Jericho, where over 1,000 tents are produced each
month. This factory has become the sole supplier of tents to UNRWA.
memorizing. The teaching of the Arabic mother tongue must
be streamlined so that it is made even more effective while ¡
using up fewer of the- precious hours of the syllabus than it
does at present. Foreign languages, mathematics, the natur¬
al sciences, history, geography, can be taught much better.
As a first step in a much needed reform two experimental
teacher training centres, staffed by a selected group of inter¬
national experts, will open their doors this autumn, one in
Jerusalem for men teachers and one in Nabius for women.
These will be followed a year hence by full scale teacher
training centres in all or a majority of the host countries.
From these training centres in the next few years will
come not only a stream of teachers to fill the gaps in the
Unrwa-Unesco schools and to raise the level of the teaching
there, but also sizable quantities of teachers for export.
A good teacher is worth his weight in gold anywhere in the
Arabic-speaking region that stretches from Libya to the
Persian Gulf and from the Taurus Mountains to the Red Sea
and beyond. Some of the oil-rich, education-hungry Arab
lands put a high premium on their services and the trek of
Palestinian teachers to Kuwait, Qater, Bahrein and Saudi-
Arabia is not a new phenomenon.
Even more ambitious than the teacher training programme
are the plans for the development of vocational
and agricultural training. Modern vocational (Cont'd on
training centres are costly to build and costlier next page)
CIGARETTE PRODUCTION shot up at this Jordan factory after it
received loans from the Jordan Development Bank (80% UNRWA financed)
in return for giving increased employment to refugees. (UNRWA photos)
NEW GAME for an Arab refugee. This Bedouin is learning to play ping-
pong at one of the fundamental education centres. In 23 welfare centres
recreational programmes are organized for adult and child refugees.
FREE TIME poses a problemhow to break the monotony and drabness
of camp life ? UNRWA's Welfare Division answers it by providing sports
facilities, libraries and club rooms. Here, boys play a game of dominoes.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
GIVE US
SCHOOLS
(Continued)
SINAI PROJECT
one of UNRWA's
exploration and de¬
velopment activities
involved a topogra¬
phical survey of
230,000 acres, from
which 50,000 were
selected for irrigation
by Nile water syphon¬
ed beneath the Suez
Canal. Left, engin¬
eers study course of
future irrigation chan¬
nel. In background
is the Suez Canal.
(UNRWA photo)
to equip but they provide the
obvious and sensible alternative
to the over-developed thirst for
secondary education of the purely
academic type which is so pre¬
valent throughout the Middle
East. They are also the best
gamble for genuine rehabilitation in a region rapidly becom¬
ing industrialized.
The existing vocational training centres at Kalandia near
Jerusalem and at Gaza are likely to be supplemented within
the next twelve months by new centres in Lebanon and
possibly in Syria as well. In addition, a first agricultural
training centre is now being built in Gaza and others should
follow it in the Jordan Valley, where very special agricultural
conditions prevail, and again in Lebanon and Syria.
These agricultural training centres will not endeavour to
produce agronomists on the university level but rather agri¬
cultural leaders for present, and future communities. The
graduates of both these types of centre,.the skilled tradesmen
as well as the agriculturalists, have, like their colleagues the
teachers, a high and constant export value. Money invested
in them will be money well spent.
Some day, somehow, the politicians will have to sit down
and solve the problem of the Arab refugees from Palestine.
This is not the concern of educators and they can be thankful
that it is not. It is their particular task to equip the rising
generation to face life in the modern world, whether that life
is destined to be lived within or without the borders of their
former homeland.
There are really few sights more inspiring than a packed
class of black-eyed Arab school children almost literally
exploding in their eagerness to answer a question. Just as
touching is the faith of the parents in their schools and in
education generally. On more than one occasion, when they
feared a curtailment of the programme, protesters among the
refugees have used the slogan "take away our rations but
give us the schools we need for our children". The astonish¬
ing thing is that the people who coined this slogan and who
use it really mean it.
NEW FARM-
LANDS opened up
by using the waters
of the Yarmuk and
the Jordan is another
UNRWA project.
Irrigation from these
( sources should enable
between 1 00,000 and
I 50,000 more people
to gain a livelihood in
this area. Here, flow
water is measured at
the Maqarin dam site
on the Yarmuk river.
(UNRWA photo)
MAGNA CUM IAUDE STUDENTS
FROM ARAB REFUGEE TENTS
In 1951 a small number of Arab refugee students
enrolled in two or three of the better-known
universities of the Middle East were able to
continue their studies with Unesco aid. When
unrwa assumed financial responsibility for refugee
students in 1953, it was decided to make free uni¬
versity study available to the deserving few on a
percentage basis. It was calculated that five
percent of the pupils graduating from unrwa-
unesco elementary schools could reasonably hope
to receive a secondary education and that a further
five percent of these should be given an opportunity
of going on to the university.
Last year some three hundred students were
enrolled in the universities of Egypt, Syria and
Lebanon as wards of the United Nations and next
year this figure is likely to rise to about three
hundred and fifty.
An unrwa scholarship candidate must not only
have an above-average school record and continue
to get above-average marks throughout his uni¬
versity career, he must also be someone who seems
likely to attain real distinction in his chosen
profession, and who will, in effect, be a future
leader and mainstay in the whole community of
Palestinian Arabs.
Many Middle East universities, particularly in
Egypt, remit all fees for students who consistently
get very high marks. So every year unrwa Uni¬
versity Scholarships Project funds receive an un-
budgeted windfall of fees which its more disting¬
uished students do not have to pay.
Selection also includes a very necessary means
test. Funds provided by many nations for the
rehabilitation of the Arab refugees from Palestine
cannot in fairness be used to support a student at
the university if that student's family can possibly
find the money. All scholarship candidates must
therefore De rationed refugees, and most of them
come from the refugee camps where the economic
level is little if anything above total indigence.
.There is one further fence to jump before, a
candidate for an unrwa scholarship is finally
selected. He or she must choose studies which are
likely to lead to useful and remunerative employ¬
ment after graduation. Agriculture, Commerce,
Public Administration, Medicine, Dentistry, En¬
gineering .in all its branches, and, in the case of
future teachers, the Arts and Sciences these are
courses of study that are likely to be approved.
Once chosen, a refugee scholarship holder is
transported free of charge to the university that
has been selected, if necessary in the blue and white
United Nations plane that usually carries -unrwa
officials to and fro on their missions. His fees are
paid, he receives the text-books and instruments he
requires and an adequate, though spartan, allowance
for board and lodging and other incidentals. This
is, in fact, more than some of the countries in this
area give their government-sponsored scholarship
students.
This summer the first substantial number of
unrwa aided Arab refugee scholarship holders
graduated from universities in the Middle East.
They come from the state-supported institutions in
Cairo, Alexandria and Damascus, or from the French
or American foundations in Egypt and Lebanon.
These young men and women no longer sit in tents
in grim refugee camps. They are alert and
confident. They have mastered a calling and stand
on the threshold of their professional careers. In
the jargon of the relief specialists, they have been
"rehabilitated" and will now be privileged to serve
their fellow Arabs not only in the lands where their
Palestinian brethren have taken refuge but
throughout the Middle East.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N" 7. 1955
CHINESE OPERA
by Bafwant Gargi
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N" 7. 1955
CHINESE
OPERA
(Continued)
Mosaic
of music, acrobatics
and complex ballet
IN 1 954, some fifty thousand people attended the
performances given in Paris during the International
Theatre Festival. Twelve countries took part and
Parisians heard Norwegian, Serbo-Croat, German and
Italian spoken in their theatres. This year's festival
brought twenty-eight foreign companies to Paris as well
as thousands of people from all over Europe who flocked
to see the performances which were given in half a
dozen languages. The triumph of the 1955 Festival was
further proof of the power of the theatre whose reality
embraces and transcends language. Nowhere was this
more evident than in the performance of the Peking
Opera. In the following article, Balwant Gargi relates
the history and traditions of this classical Chinese
Opera, whose mime, dancing and music were among
the high points of the Paris Festival.
¿¿rW^ Ravel to China if you want wisdom" is an old
I Arab saying. Explorers and travellers from
Marco Polo's times down to our own have
journeyed to this mysterious land to discover this
truth. For centuries it was the dragons, the
enigmatic characters and ideographic script, the
grotesque masks and costumes of their theatre, the
strange and fantastic in Chinese art which fascinat¬
ed the Western mind. The depth and subtlety, the
shimmer and transparent richness of the art lay
hidden. Some Western critics and interpreters
cultivated the idea that Chinese art was occult and
unknowable.
This myth of unknowability broke down when
thousands poured into the Sarah Bernhardt Theatre
during the recent presentation of Chinese Opera at
the International Theatre Festival in Paris. The
Opera drew people from all over Europe. Some flew
from London to witness the spectacle.
The classical Chinese Opera differs from the
Occidental in many ways. Eastern music is not
polyphonic in form. In Chinese music, as in Indian,
strength and charm lie in subtle nuances and
variations.on the same melody. It creates a mood, a
feeling.
It has not acquired the intricate design of Western
harmony nor the pyramidal symphonic form with
motifs embroidered, expanded and interwoven with
many melodies, which tells a story and describes
scenes. Eastern music does not have a descriptive
language. It weaves a mosaic of sound within a
shorter range; it is more intense than elastic, disci¬
plined by its form.
Dance, on the other hand, in both India and China
has a highly evolved language of gesture which can
convey anything and everything. It is so perfect in
mime that an expert in Kathakali dance (one of the
four principal classical dance schools in India) can
deliver even a highly political speech, so the Gurus
(Hindu spiritual teachers )say.
This intense development of mime in the Oriental
dance sprang perhaps from the lack of descriptive
quality in its music. Stylized dance gestures which
describe songs must be exact and perfect. Dance,
both classical and folk, has always been accompanied
by vocal songs and percussion instruments. A song
is a running commentary unfolding a story which is
enacted in dance. Music and dance have walked
hand in hand and given and taken much from each
other.
In Occidental opera and theatre, the recent trends
to experiment in mixing songs and poetry with real¬
istic acting (in the manner of Berthold Brecht) and
combining action and mime in operas (as in the
Berlin Komike Opera) owe much to the Chinese.
Chinese opera in its rudimentary form is over two
thousand years old. In the eighth century small
comic and satirical pieces on political personages
and social life were knit together with songs. In the
next four or five hundred years a fuller and more
complete operatic form became crystallized. Born
in Peking, the seat of ancient kings and courts
around which all the arts flourished, the Chinese
opera assimilated the best traditions of theatre,
music, modes of singing, mime and dance. In the
19th century, artists like Tcheng Tchang-keng and
Tan Sing-pei, and in our own times Mei Lang-fan
and Tchou Sing-fan, by their brilliant performances
have carried forward and contributed to the tra¬
dition.
Chinese opera is a synthesis of dance, music and
mime. :t reveals the effect of concentration and
stylizatiijn in gesture, retaining always the essentials
of realism. The accompaniment by percussion in¬
struments underlines and reinforces the rhythm of
the movements.
In the Western theatre realistic sets and decor have
taken the form of naturalistic photographic realism
whose parallel we find in 19th century painting.
Chinese theatre does away with most of the decor.
The Indian folk theatre and the classical Chinese
theatre and opera do not strive to give an illusion of
reality. They break the "illusion of reality" and
create, in turn, a world of their own. The Chinese
opera player like the Kathakali dancer in India
through pure gesture creates palaces, chariots,
horses, rivers, forests, streets, boats, cars,
light and darkness everything required (Cont d on
as the setting for his own actions. next page)
18
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
CHINESE
OPERA
(Continued)
Rehearsals lasted twenty centuries
Masks and costumes are designed to express
particular characters. Different colours signify
different people! Style of beard, cut of moustache,
colour, angle of the eye, curves and lines of make¬
up and dress, have meaning. The flapping and
fluttering of long open double sleeves, which
unsophisticated audiences in the West may ignore
as the natural flourish of the costume, is in fact a
highly skilled manipulation by the actor. The
dropping of the sleeve, the backward and forward
toss, the ripple and tremor, circling and billow, all
denote a change of mood. These conventions and
their symbolic significance are known to all
Chinese audiences as opera has been a popular
medium since its inception.
In the Chinese Opera I saw in Paris at the Sarah
Bernhardt Theatre the performance was not one
continuous operatic drama but a series of cameos
ranging from pure mime and dance to pure music
including even a performance, on ancient Chinese
instruments.
The first episode was "The Meeting of the Three",
an adaptation of a popular 14th century romance.
A famous general, having fled enemies who had
slandered and menaced him, is staying at an inn.
A young knight and the innkeeper, both would-be
protectors of the general, are unknown to each
other and suspect each other.
At night the innkeeper steals into the knight's
room to take away his sword. In imagined pitch
darkness the knight and the innkeeper, straining
their eyes to pierce the gloom, search and grope for
each other with drawn swords. In this atmosphere
of fear and suspicion a ferocious duel begins.
Sabres slash the air and the perilous triple jumps
of the duellers, their hairbreadth
escape are full of danger, suspense and (Cont'd on
comedy. As they flash their swords page 2 7)
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
MASTERPIECES
YOU CAN
NOW BUY
by Jean Leymarie
Curator, Grenoble Museum, France.
Unesco Courier. N" 7. 1955
Pablo PICASSO. Harlequin on
Horseback. Reproduction: Raymond
and Raymond Galleries, New York,
S IS.
Claude MONET. The Studio-
Boat. Reproduction : Kröller-Müller
Foundation, Otterlo, Netherlands,
12.50 fl.
TT
I I nesco is systematically building
V	J up archives of colour reproduc¬
tions of paintings. Copies of all the
reproductions at present available are
collected and kept at the secretariat's
headquarters in Paris and, from these,
selections are made for the regular
production of a descriptive catalogue in
two volumes, one dealing with paintings
prior to 1860 and the other with mo¬
dern painting subsequent to that date,
which, with the appearance of Manet,
really marks the decisive break in tra¬
dition.
The second volume is the more popu¬
lar, for public taste is more sponta¬
neously inclined towards contemporary
art. The latest edition (Catalogue of
Colour Reproductions of Paintings, 1860
to 1955) is the third since 1949. The
previous edition, which came out in
April 1952, contained 563 items repre¬
senting 114 different artists. Since
then, 481 new productions have been
submitted to the selection committee,
which has chosen 282 for inclusion in
the latest volume an addition which
has made it possible, after reconsider¬
ing the whole list, -to omit 44 which
were really too small or not
of a very high quality and (Cont'd on
which had previously been next page)
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
MASTERPIECES
YOU CAN BUY
(Continued)
Best colour reproductions available today
James ENSOR
Carnival. Re¬
production: New
York Graphic So¬
ciety, Greenwich,
Connecticut,
U.S.A., S I 2.
accepted, provisionally, because nothing better was available.
In making their selection, the experts appointed by the
International Council of Museums are guided by three main
criteria*the fidelity of the reproduction, the significance of
the artist, and the importance of the original painting
among which a compromise of some kind has often to be
made. The purpose of these catalogues, however, apart from
encouraging the distribution of the best available reproduc¬
tions, is also to secure a steady improvement in their quality
and to co-ordinate their production.
The welcome these catalogues have received from teachers,
students and art lovers of all kinds is sufficient proof of their
usefulness. But they are perhaps most valuable to art pub¬
lishers themselves, because they indicate both the trend of
taste and the gaps that have to be filled. The latest volume,
for instance, includes a further thirty-six artists and among
these are numbered such important names as Soutine, Ensor,
Macke and Villon.
Other artists, hitherto insufficiently represented, are now
better served, both as regards the quality of the original and
the fidelity of the reproduction. In this way, each new edi¬
tion of the catalogue marks an appreciable advance on the
previous edition and represents a closer approximation to
the ideal catalogue in which the only thing that mattered
would be the choice of the artists and their works. If a
catalogue such as this could be developed to its limits, we
should have the "imaginary museum" of Malraux in which
each one of us hangs his own selection of pictures.
The universal popularity of colour reproduction means,
therefore, that it must be given a responsible place in our
artistic culture. Although too many attempts at reproduction
are disappointing or meretricious, it would be foolish to
condemn the principle or to deny its importance. It is more to
the purpose to assess from time to time what has been achiev¬
ed on the credit side, and this is what Unesco is trying to do.
Improvements in technique, competition between publishers
Maurice de
VLAMINCK. -
Cottage in Flan¬
ders. Reproduc¬
tion: New York
Graphic Society,
Greenwich, Con¬
necticut, U.S.A.
310.
Felice CAS O RA-
Tl. The Two
Sisters. Reproduc¬
tion: Istituto Geo¬
gráfico de Agos-
tini, Novara, Ita¬
ly, 4,500 lire.
mm*
1 M 1
r f\&J -J
\\V|
Hfefefc
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N" 7. 1955
Lyonel FEININGER. -
The Church of the Minorites.
Reproduction: Farm Journal,
Philadelphia, Pennsylvania,
U.S.A. SI.
Giorgio de CHIRICO.
The Antique Era. Reproduc¬
tion: New York Graphic
Society, Greenwich, Con¬
necticut, U.S.A. S 5.
and, above all, the higher standards demanded by the pu¬
blic, as they become more and more familiar with museums
and exhibitions, are bound to result in constant improve¬
ment.
Some of the reproductions seem already to be of sufficient
merit to win the approval of the artists themselves, who are
ready to sign them as a token not only of the technical fide¬
lity of the reproduction, but also of its skill in recapturing the
very spirit of the original. Spiritual affinity of this kind
between the original and the reproduction cannot be achiev¬
ed automatically, as is commonly believed, by purely mecha¬
nical means. It calls for the hand of a skilful craftsman
constantly improving on his work by reference to the original,
and himself enough of an artist to experience the vision of
another as though it were his own, and sufficiently patient
and self-effacing to refrain from putting his own personal
stamp on the finished work. This accounts for the rela¬
tively high cost of such outstandingly good reproductions,
made by the pochoir process, and for the fact that there are
so few of them.
The classic methods of large-scale reproduction can, how¬
ever, give very good results if we are more fully aware
of their limitations and their possibilities. The exact
reproduction of colour cannot in itself recapture the special
atmosphere of a painting, which is due to the quality of its
lighting and of the materials used and to its own inherent
magic. Even though his style remains fundamentally the
same, every artist changes his manner, and this difference
of tone must be rendered by appropriate means.
To take a very simple example, while the precision and
directness of letterpress may reproduce the firm accents of
the early Monet, the velvety softness of offset will perhaps
give a better rendering of the modulation of a late work like
the Nymphéas, and the sonority of photogravure come clo¬
ser to the vibrant quality of the Argenteuil period. It is up
to the publishers to discover, as one critic recently put it, "the
process of colour reproduction best suited to a particular
work of art", and to unify and combine harmoniously the
successive renderings of photographer, engraver and printer.
The choice of inks and paper also plays a very subtle part.
The successes achieved carry on the tradition of fine crafts¬
manship in the service of art.
Modern paintings, with their pure, unequivocal colours
and simple texture are easier subjects for reproduction than
are old paintings, many of which are overlaid with varnishes
and shrouded in intermediate greys and browns which are
extremely difficult to render. In the last hundred years,
painting has turned resolutely to colour. There is no doubt
that black-and-white photography, however perfect it may
be, can no longer give us the essence of an Impressionist or
Fauvist painting, and still less of an abstract painting.
Colour reproductions help not only to spread a know¬
ledge of modern art but also to" make it better understood
and to assist its development. By freeing us from the
traditional prejudices of subject and form, which have been
given spurious credit by line-engraving and monochrome
photography, they help us to a better appreciation, in
painting, of the old chromatic harmony cultivated by certain
masters and certain schools and so long belittled for the
sake of an exclusive concentration on line, composition,
relief, and other values often having nothing to do with
painting pure and simple. The development of colour
reproduction ' also accounts for the present renaissance of
such powerful forms of art as stained glass and mosaic
work, and of forms so rich in influence as miniature paint¬
ing. We are returning to a civilization full of colour.
One comment already made deserves repetition. The
artists reproduced in colour are not academic painters but
the great creative geniuses of our time. The list of
distinguished names in this catalogue is striking evidence
both of the enlightened judgment of the experts and of
the spontaneous preferences of the public. In
spite of those who disparage modern art, and (Cont'd on
notwithstanding the thousands of artists now page 2 6)
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
MASTERPIECES
YOU CAN BUY
(Continued)
Marc CHAGALL. -
The Artist and his Model.
Reproduction: The Pallas
Gallery Ltd., London,
£ I2.2.6d.
Auguste RE
NOIR. Nude
in the Sun. Re¬
production: Kuns-
tanstalt Max Jaffé,
Vienna, S I 0.
Jean LURÇAT.
The Big Cloud.
Reproduction :
The Twin Edi¬
tions, Greenwich,
Connecticut,
U.S.A. S I 5.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N" 7. 1955
Joan MIRO. Mural
No. I. Reproduction: Es¬
ther Gentle Reproduc¬
tions, New York, S5.
Georges ROUAULT. -
Pierrot Junior. Repro¬
duction : Editions M. La-
courière, Paris, 27.000frs
Paul KLEE. Picture
Album. Reproduction :
The Twin Editions,
p-. < \ ,* .1 Greenwich, Connecticut,
1*»:' W-K U.S.A. S I 5.
Chaim SOUTINE. -
Portrait of a Boy. Repro¬
duction: New York Gra¬
phic Society, Greenwich,
Connecticut, U.S.A. S I 0.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Masterpieces you eau buy
WORKS OF ART IN SCHOOLS
FACTORIES AND HOMES
(Continued from page 23)
working, there is general agreement on a small and signifi¬
cant selection of modern masters. The reproductions dis¬
carded are generally laid aside because of their own defects,
and seldom because of shortcomings in the original, for aca¬
demic artists, even if they enjoy very powerful backing, rarely
find publishing firms willing to take the risk of reproducing
their work in colour.
There are now enough good colour reproductions available
for Unesco to contemplate organizing travelling exhibitions
in the near future to illustrate a given period, country, or
artist, or a particular theme. There is no need to dwell
on the educational value of collections of this kind since,
with masterpieces scattered all over the world, as they are
today, it is hardly possible to arrange comparable exhibi¬
tions of the originals, even in the most favoured centres.
By means of colour reproductions, the highest expressions
of art can be brought, in a form approximating very closely
to the original, into schools and factories, and to remote
communities or isolated homes where people do not yet enjoy
direct access to museums, exhibitions or private collections.
For connoisseurs, art-lovers and artists, these repro¬
ductions now provide the kind of introduction and training
once given by the engravings which had such a vogue both
north and south of the Alps from the late- fifteenth century
onwards, or by the countless copies of miniatures that
circulated both in the Orient and in the West throughout
the Middle Ages. Every age creates, out of reproductions,
its own fill of "imaginary museums", while, alongside, spring
up the ever new and ever unpredictable original masterpieces
of the creative artist.
CATALOGUE DE REPRODUCTIONS
EN COULEURS DE PEINTURES
I860 A 1955
CATALOGUE
OF COLOUR REPRODUCTIONS
OF PAINTINGS I860 TO 1955
CATALOGO DE REPRODUCCIONES
w EN COLOR DE PINTURAS
I860 A 1955
UNESCO PARIS
The " Catalogue of Colour Reproductions of Paint¬
ings I 860 to I 955 ", whose cover is reproduc¬
ed above, can be obtained from booksellers and
from Unesco National Distributors listed on page
34, price: S 3.50 ; I 6/-; 800 Fr. fr. A new and
revised edition of Unesco's companion volume
on old masters"Catalogue of Colour Reproduc¬
tions of Paintings Prior to I860" will be avail¬
able this year. Readers who wish to buy repro¬
ductions from another country can overcome
currency difficulties with "Unesco Coupons".
Information on how to obtain and use these
coupons can be obtained from the Unesco
Coupon Office, 19, Avenue Kléber, Paris (16*).
Karl HOFER. Girls Playin-
Cards. Reproduction : V e r I a (
F. Bruckmann, KG, Munich
Germany, DM50.
Rufino TAMAYO. Mandolins
and Pineapples. Reproduction: New
York Graphic Society, Greenwich,
Connecticut, U.S.A. S I 5.
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
CHINESE
OPERA
(Cont'd from
page 20)
and miraculously miss each other every
time, the adversaries pant like two
blood-thirsty leopards, first making you
gasp and in the next moment roar
with laughter.
The laughter is released not from
comic facial contortions but springs out
of impossible situations, fantastic pos¬
tures and the superb orchestration of
the actors who perform a breathtaking
and precise acrobatic ballet.
The choreography which makes one's
head spin in its complex patterns has
been evolved through hundreds of years
of tradition and training, has been
worked by ancient masters, perfected
and matured through the ages. The
performances do not seem to have
been rehearsed in theatre halls at
scheduled times but through centuries,
through generations.
I do not know any theatre which
requires less knowledge of the spoken
word than the Chinese opera. In
"The River" we vividly see the old
boatman tie his boat to the bank, walk
through the mud and help the young
girl to embark. The wobbling of the
boat and the swaying of the girl as the
boatman rows her across the deep
waters seem absolutely real.
Product of time's crucible
IN the butterfly dance the acrobatic
feats of the players form a pattern
of colours and singing lines of
human limbs. Women and men in
bright costumes jump and somersault
and look like butterflies skimming and
kissing each other in the air. In its
presentation this piece is nearer to the
Western concept of ballet.
The simplification of form in Chinese
opera does not arise out of a primitive
or naive folk quality but from a highly
evolved technique, the product of
centuries of strenuous search. This art
simmered and bubbled in the crucible
of time and in the process all super¬
fluity has been shed. Its simplicity has
the conscious master's hand behind it,
the craftsmanship of the super-painter
who with a few strokes of his brush
sketches a human figure, a scene of
battle or a running horse.
In the creation of new opera China
has borrowed much from the West.
"The White Haired Girl" and "The
Butterflies" and the more recent operas
are a blend of Western realism with
native traditions, using harmonic music
patterns and symphonic orchestration
as a background to solo music.
China has much to offer Western
opera which today seems to be at a
stalemate so far as form is concerned.
This exchange of cultures is a unique
phenomena of our times when coun¬
tries like the members of one family
come together with their different
languages, songs, costumes and dances.
They have much to give and take from
each other and thereby enrich world
culture which is a heritage of all
humanity. (Photos Pic, Paris.)
Balwant Cargl is an Indian writer who has devoted
many years to a study of classical and folk drama
in India and the Far Cast.
Letters to the editor
Sir,
I have been reading with interest
your issue No. 4/5 1954 concerning
Japan today. Your articles show
the high standard of progress that
country has made in such a very
short time and the Interesting
fusion of western materialism with
Oriental philosophy that exists
there. I think it would be a pity
if, in the attempt to raise the
standards of the "backward" peo¬
ples of the world, the Western
powers were to impose not only the
advantages of their standards upon
the less fortunate, but also the
disadvantages. It seems to me that
the article giving the view of
Japanese youth could be very well
taken to heart by the "'Ijin" (for¬
eigner). You list six points of
criticism of the Western way of life
by the Japanese youth and it
appears to me that they do in the
main strike well and truly home.
This would seem to be just cause
for us to stop and consider that
when we try and aid the Asians
and Africans to reach a higher
standard of living, we should do so
through their eyes, not just through
our own. We should remember
that what is ultimately desirable
for us may be quite . despicable to
them. We should only help them
as far as we can when it is compat¬
ible with their ideals, not with our
own. We can easily measure ma¬
terial wealth but it is very difficult
for us to say that, just because we
are materially stronger than they
are, then we are also spiritually
stronger.
One example of the apparent
superiority of the outlook of those
we are supposed to be helping is
the strength of the family ties in
Japan. I venture to suggest that if
such ties were still in existence in
the Western World then such
undesirable features of our civili¬
zation as the high divorce rates,
juvenile delinquency, and the
abandoned condition of many of
the aged would not exist to the
extent that they do today. Your
apology in the following issue
(No. 6, 1954, "The American Negro")
for the racial and other discrimina¬
tion that exists in the United
States, materially the richest of
nations in the world today, may be
quoted as an example of what we
should avoid.
I would also like to point out that
in your issue prior to the one
devoted to Japanese youth (No. 3,
1954, "Freedom of Information")
you publish figures that show
Japanese-language daily newspaper
circulation as being second only to
English-language circulation. Sure¬
ly this would indicate that there
would be a ready market for a
Japanese language edition of the
Courier, particularly since you state
in the following issue that the
Japanese in general are anxious to
learn about other peoples. Or is it
that your activities are restricted
to member countries? If so there
would appear to be little hope for a
universal understanding of each
other's problems and ambitions if
only one half of the world is
allowed to see and hear those
problems and ambitions. Incident¬
ally, I notice also that German-
language dailies have a greater
circulation than either French or
Spanish.
In the matter of explaining
ourselves to each other, I feel that
it is only by so doing that we can
prevent our leaders from leading
us into another dreadful slaughter
that is so wasteful of human life
and effort. Indeed, may I make
this a plea to Unesco to try to
break down the barriers to such an
understanding that exist between
the political "East" and the political
"West", and present to each the
true picture of what we are and
what we seek. Surely both sides
are subjected to such a barrage of
propaganda and half-truths that it
is only a very distorted and
emotional picture that exists at
present.
Certainly it can be said that if
we cannot live together in peace
we shall die together in futile
strife and the slow and gradual
progress of centuries will be lost
for the average man. We have so
obviously reached the stage when
there is no advantage for either
side in pursuing their selfish ends
by force when both victors and
vanquished are losers and the
common man becomes a slave
either to the politics of one side
or the economics of the other.
Each of the major wars of this
century has brought increasing
restrictions upon the freedom and
liberty of the private individual_in
order to protect "States". Surely
it is time that men grew up and
realized that States consist of the
individuals that reside therein
and although school-boys squabble,
grown men learn to tolerate each
other.
D. Harden.
Birkdale Road,
Birkenhead,
Auckland, N.5,
New Zealand.
EDITOR'S XOTE : Japan is a member
of Unesco though not of the United
Salions. An experimental Japanese edition
of the Unesco Col'hieh in reduced form
has just begun publication in conjunction
with the Unesco Sinuun (Unesco \ews)
the organ of the Federation of Unesco
Associations in Japan.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
As an anthropologist sees it
JUNGLE INDIAN
WITH AN
AXE TO GRIND
by Alfred Metraux
T7
I ' our centuries ago the hunger
J- for gold and the promise of
great riches helped to speed fleets of
galleons to the conquest and coloniz¬
ation of the New World and lured ad¬
venturers on astounding expeditions.
Today, a strange counterpart of this
age-old lust for gold can be found in
the "Iron Hunt" of primitive tribes. The
thirst for iron is so strong that it gov¬
erns all dealings between the tribes
and white men who hold this "'precious"
metal.
It is difficult to realize what iron
means in the lives of primitive peoples
unless We stop to think of the way men
lived and worked in the distant Stone
Age. And yet in New Guinea and
Brazil there are still many tribes which
use the same tools as did our ancestors
of prehistoric times.
These tribes farm the tropical jungle
soil by scraping its thin layer of humus.
Every two or three years a tribe has
to hack a new clearing out of the jun¬
gle to make room for the grains and
tubers on which its life depends. It is
not easy to clear a jungle with a stone
axe which pounds and tears much more
than it actually cuts. Long, hard days
are needed for the job.
A simple iron hatchet can do the
same work with almost magical speed.
The man who owns such a marvellous
instrument saves his strength and no
longer needs to worry about the rains
coming before his crops are sown. The
entire rhythm of his farming is affect¬
ed. He can clear as much land as he
pleases. His crops will be more abund¬
ant, famine will no longer haunt his
door, and fewer children will die. His
tribe, grown bigger and stronger, will be
held in respect by its neighbours, and
thus threats to its existence will be re¬
moved. An Indian can visualize this
chain of cause and effect as he tries a
steel axe on a tree trunk for the first
time. .
In the plains of the Amazon basin the
fame of the '"precious metal" spreads
among the tribes long before the white
man ever makes an appearance. Tiny
bits of iron passed from hand to hand
have gone right into the very heart of
the South American continent. When
agents of Brazil's Indian Protection
Service made their first contacts with
hostile tribes in Central Brazil, they
i
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N" 7. 1955
were astounded to find the tribesmen
using steel tools they had acquired by
barter or as war booty. For the past
four centuries, attacks by tribesmen on
white men have often had no other
motive than the desire for iron. Official
reports of such attacks nearly always
reveal that the tribesmen carried off all
objects made of iron, but left those
made of other materials untouched.
Stone Age twilight
T3E primitive man who discovers
the use of iron soon finds himself
under a tyranny from which he
cannot escape : once he is familiar
with metal he can no longer return to
his Stone Age. For iron, many a tribe
has sacrificed its freedom and even
Its existence.
When the Jesuits peacefully subdued
hundreds of thousands of Indians, the
only arm they used was the lure of iron.
The promise of a steady supply of axes
and knives was enough to persuade a
belligerent people to accept the author¬
ity of the "black robes". And many
tribes have waged merciless war on
each other simply to capture the slaves
they needed to barter for metal tools.
Even today, the Indian Protection Ser¬
vice in Brazil wins over hostile tribes
by placing hatchets, scissors and ma¬
chetes in their area.
A report on Brazil's Indian assimil¬
ation policy written for Unesco by Dr.
Darcy Ribeiro of the Indian Protection
Service (See Unesco Courier, n° 8/9,
1954) tells of some of the dramatic
moments marking the twilight of the
Stone Age. We are inclined to forget
that the Stone Age which began thous¬
ands of years ago has survived down to
the Atomic Age, and is now finally
disappearing.
A clean-cut trail
Some of these stories suggest how
our own ancestors must have felt
when traders from the East
brought them their first metal axes.
Here is a story told to an Indian
Protection Service Agent by the
Xokleng Indians of Southern Brazil, a
few years after their pacification :
One day, as some of the tribe's war¬
riors were moving through the jungle,
they came across a trail quite different
from the one they themselves were
making by painfully twisting and
breaking the branches in their way. On
both sides of this trail, branches lay on
the ground, cut off cleanly by some
unknown instrument. The Indians,
puzzled by this mystery, decided to
follow the strange trail.
A little further on, they found
something that surprised them even
more. A huge tree had been chopped
down and its stump showed a clean,
flat surface. Now they felt both fear
and astonishment, but they continued
on the trail. Soon they found some¬
thing else mysterious : foot-prints
which had certainly not been made by
any animal they had ever come across.
Night was falling as they stealthily
came to a clearing where a white "hut"
stood. Around the "hut" were strange
human beings with white skins, unlike
any men they had ever seen. The In¬
dians, a warlike tribe, decided to attack
at dawn, but their impatience and curi¬
osity got the better of them. Before
dawn came they had massacred all the
white men. Groping through the tent
they began to hunt for the cutting
of finding more of those strange beings
who possessed the cutting instruments.
But the Indians who had taken the
axes did not keep them for very long.
Other tribes ambushed them, seized
their iron weapons and left them dead
or wounded. In the months and the
years that followed, more whites were
massacred, but many Indians were
killed by the little thunderclaps that
the whites held in their hands. Not
only was war waged on the whites, but
the lust for iron led to incessant tribal
wars among the Indians. When the
Indian Protection Service left a heap of
iron objects near the Parintintins one
tools whose powers they had admired.
They collected the axes and imme¬
diately began to try them out.
The next morning, they undressed
the bodies of their victims to examine
them more closely and then crushed
their skulls to prevent them from com¬
ing back to life. Then, ignoring any
other booty in the "hut", they left with
their knives and hatchets. On the way
home, they kept on trying out the
hatchets.
They couldn't believe their eyes : the
instruments cut wood without any
effort at all. Now that they owned
them, they would become the masters
of the jungle. Back in their own vil¬
lage, the warriors told the story of their
discovery and their victory. More bands
set out along the same path in the hope
day to lure them, the Indians simulated
an attack to make themselves believe
that they had won them by conquest.
In the end tribes no longer sought
iron and steel because of their useful¬
ness. Their possession became a matter
of prestige. When the Chikrin Indians
were pacified, they were willing to obey
the law in exchange for scissors. And
they kept on demanding them until
they now own more scissors per head
than any other community in the
world.
This is the first of a series of articles on
anthropological questions by Alfred Metraux,
noted social anthropologist. In our next issue
Dr Metraux will describe how a steel axe
changed the lives of an Australian aboriginal
community.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N" 7. 1955
KOREAN
A YEAR
"To have a single book for the school was a
luxury. When we didn't have a blackboard,
we used to draw our illustrations on the
mud floor." That is how Korean teachers
describe the difficult war-time and early
post-war conditions in their schools. Today,
however, a steady stream of textbor,;;s is
flowing back into Korean schools from the
new National Textbook Printing Plant (left)
now in production at Yong Dong Po, near
Seoul. The plant was built through the
combined efforts of the United Nations
Korean Reconstruction Agency (UNKRA),
UNESCO and the Republic of Korea Govern¬
ment. Geared to produce thirty million
textbooks a year, the printing, stitching and
packing equipment (below, left and centre)
is the most modern obtainable. Between
September 1954, when the plant opened,
and March 1955, 12,000,000 books were
produced. In Pusan, South Korea's main
supply port, UNKRA Is helping thousands of
sick people by providing equipment and sup¬
plies for the clinic operated by the Mary
Knoll Sisters. This has enabled the clinic
to give orthopaedic treatment to children
suffering from tuberculosis of the bone and
poliomyelitis. Long before daybreak, patients
pack the courtyard and alleyway leading to
the clinic waiting their turn for examination
and treatment. Photos (right) show a father
explaining the nature of his child's illness
to one of the sisters, and another sister taking
blood count of young orphan, one of many
thousands treated at the clinic. (U.N. photos)
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Schools spark village
progress in Philippines
Since I 948 a national movement has developed to link Philippine schools
with their communities. Classroom programmes are related to needs
and resources of communities, and schools also conduct adult education
activities and carry out projects aimed at general community develop¬
ment. A training centre has been set up at Bayambang as a joint
undertaking of the Philippines Government and UNESCO. A team
of UNESCO technical assistance specialists is working with the
centre, which is part of a system of international and national train¬
ing centres set up to produce first, leaders and teachers, and
second, teaching materials for fundamental education. The compre¬
hensive ten weeks' course makes use of audio-visual instruction,
group discussions and field work in selected villages. Experiments
are also carried out with new teaching methods and revised
curricula. Photos on this page of the training centre in action show :
(I) Dr. Urban Fleege, Chief of the UNESCO mission, lecturing
trainees on the problem of evaluation of their work; (2) A group at
work in the centre's library; (3) An educational film show in a nearby
village; (4) Charles C. Roberts, a UNESCO science teaching expert,
demonstrates the operation of a film projector; (5) Charles A. Holland,
of Australia, agricultural expert, shows trainees how to vaccinate pigs
against hog cholera; (6) Trainees working on posters. (U.N. photos.)
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N" 7. 1955
Unesco in pictures
Destructive man
The results of man's abuse and destruction of
nature's resources were graphically illustrated
at a recent exhibition organized át the Paris
Natural History Museum, with the support
of Unesco and the International Union for
the Protection of Nature. Entitled "Man
Against Nature", the exhibition offered many
examples of the destruction by man of the
delicate balance that exists between soil,
vegetation and fauna. It showed, for example,
that uncontrolled deforestation can cause
erosion which results in the devastation of
whole areas, and that the use of insecticides
may destroy useful insects along with parasites.
After the exhibition closes in September, the
section devoted to the disturbance of natural
balance will form an independent exhibit which
the International Union for the Protection of
Nature will offer to members wishing to
circulate it in their country. Above, right, an
exhibition panel showing the balance of natural
elements that thoughtless interference can
destroy, and, left, young visitors learn that
the ferocious leopard helps to protect agri¬
culture by destroying baboons and wild pigs
which eat up the vegetation. (Unesco photos)
Budding artists
of far-off lands
Many Parisians have recently been visiting an
art exhibition in Unesco House where paintings
by children from France's overseas territories
have been on view. Chief among the visitors
to admire the talents of these budding artists,
aged between seven and I 5, was Madame René
Coty, wife of the President of the French
Republic, who met and chatted with some
young citTzens of France's African territories
(left). Prizes are being awarded to the three
best paintings entered from each of the
overseas territories. (Unesco photo)
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom
s EVENTY - FOURTH
STATE: Ethiopia has become
Unesco's seventy- fourth mem¬
ber state. On July 1, the Ethio¬
pian Ambassador to the United
Kingdom deposited his govern¬
ment's acceptance of the Unesco
Constitution at a ceremony in
the Foreign Office in London,
where the Constitution is de¬
posited.
UNESCO ' POCKET-
BOOK' : The first Unesco
paper-bound pocket-size book
for mass distribution was
published recently. The book
is the English version of
Cultural Patterns and
Technical Change ", prepar¬
ed by Unesco under the
editorial supervision of the
noted anthropologist, Mar¬
garet Mead. It reports on
the traditional way of life in
the five ancient civilizations
of Greece, Burma, Nigeria,
the Palau Islands and among
the Spanish Americans of
New Mexico. And it features
guiding principles on how to
introduce modern technical
improvements into such cul¬
tures without causing new
social tensions.
M,Len with MISSIONS :
Unesco recently sent out three
more experts on new technical
assistance missions. Professor
Calamur Mahadevan, an Indian
geologist, is now in Brazil to
help survey mineral resources
in the Amazon Valley. He is
working with a U.N. Food and
Agriculture Organization team
aiding the Brazilian Govern¬
ment to develop the Amazon
region. An Australian geologist,
Mr. E. J. Harrison, has gone
to help the Egyptian Govern¬
ment in its search for under¬
ground water resources in the
desert. A third expert on
mission is Mr. A. G. Dickson, a
British educator whom Unesco
is sending to head a Unesco
fundamental education team in
Iraq. Mr. Dickson's mission
follows three years of work by
Iraqi educators and a Unesco
team in the Dujailah region,
where landless farmers have
been settled on newly-irrigated
land reclaimed from the desert.
The plan now is to establish
similar centres throughout Iraq
to train local leaders of fun¬
damental education.
PAYING FOR EDUCA-
Educators from all
parts of the world met
recently in Geneva to
discuss one of education's
greatest difficulties h o w
to find the money to expand
existing programmes and
create new ones where they
are urgently needed. The
occasion was the Eighteenth
Conference on Public Educa¬
tion, convened jointly by
Unesco and the Interna¬
tional Bureau of Education.
In previous years delegates
have recommended action in
such fields as compulsory
education, on the access of
women to education, and on
the training of teachers. For
this reason, this year's
session was concerned pri¬
marily with educational
financing. Special studies
prepared by Unesco and the
I.B.E. were used as a basis
for discussions.
w,ORKS OF LEONAR¬
DO: The Leonardo da Vinci
travelling exhibition prepared
by Unesco has now toured 23
countries. It is on show this
year from June to the end of
September at the historic Clos
Lucé in Amboise, France, once
a French royal domain, where
Leonardo spent the last years
of his life under the patronage
of King Francis I. The French
National Commission for Unes¬
co, which is sponsoring the Am¬
boise exhibit, has decided to
make it a yearly event. Each
summer the exhibition will re¬
turn to the Clos Lucé, in the
heart of the Loire country
which Leonardo loved so well.
EAST-WEST EXCHAN¬
GES : Historians and orien¬
talists studied way to broad¬
en the teaching of the hu¬
manities when they met re¬
cently at Unesco House in
Paris. They discussed how
to give greater attention to
Oriental civilizations in
Western teaching, and also
how to improve the study of
European humanities in
Asian schools. Representa¬
tives from the major uni¬
versities of thirteen coun¬
tries Ceylon, Denmark,
Egypt, England, France,
Germany, India, Iran, Italy,
Japan, Mexico, Pakistan and
the United States attend¬
ed the meeting.
¡L HEATRE OF THE NA¬
TIONS: Plans for the crea¬
tion of an international thea¬
tre in Paris are now within
sight of achievement. The idea
of setting up a theatre for re¬
gular performances by various
national theatre groups has
been considered by the Inter¬
national Theatre Institute for
a number of years. Following
two successful International
Festivals of Dramatic Art held
in Paris in 1954 and again this
year (see page 18), the Institute
has received the unanimous ap¬
proval of its twenty-three
member nations, who met re¬
cently in Dubrovnik, Yugosla¬
via, for a Theatre of the Na¬
tions to be established in Paris.
The French Government as well
as the Paris municipal autho¬
rities will co-operate in the es¬
tablishment of the theatre.
GEOGRAPHY
LESSONS : Primary school
pupils in Corbeil, near Paris
recently had their first aeri¬
al geography lesson. With
the help of the French Air
Ministry and the Touring
Club de France they flew
ever the Paris area in three
aircraft. Their teacher pre¬
pared them in class before¬
hand for the trip and each
pupil had a plan of the
flight. For the five pupils
who write the best account
of their airborne lesson, the
French Air Ministry has
offered further flights thh
summer.
H'EFENDING HUMAN
RIGHTS: The first internation¬
al authority with power to
overrule certain national gov¬
ernments when human rights
are infringed has now been
created. Six countries, all mem¬
bers of the Council of Europe,
have ratified the Council's "Eu¬
ropean Convention on Human
Rights", thereby agreeing to
Article 25 of the Convention on
the right to individual petition.
Henceforth, any person or
group who is a victim of per¬
secution in Belgium, Denmark,
Iceland, Sweden and the Ger¬
man Federal Republic can now
have his complaint investigated
and his rights and liberties res
tored by the Council of Eur¬
ope's Human Rights Commis¬
sion. This Commission will
eventually be replaced by a
European Supranational Court
of Human Rights.
f^ OUNTRY TEACHER
CLASSES : In Bogota, Colom¬
bia, an ambitious programme to
train rural school teachers has
been launched under the direc¬
tion of a graduate of Unesco's
Regional Fundamental Educa¬
tion Centre for Latin America,
located in Patzcuaro, Mexico.
Trainees in Colombia will spe¬
cialize in nutrition, domestic
science, arts and crafts and in
teaching recreational activities.
Colombia's Agricultural Credit
Union is donating houses to
forty families of workers who
will assist the training program¬
me. Students were selected
from villages across the coun¬
try, -with the understanding
that they will teach in their
home towns on graduation.
* CERN'S FIRST STONE:
The foundation stone of the
headquarters of the Euro¬
pean Organization for Nu¬
clear Research (CERN) was
laid recently at Meyrin,
near Geneva. Among those
who attended the ceremony
were M. Max Petitpierre,
President of the Swiss Con¬
federation, and Dr. Luther
Evans, Director-General of
Unesco. The idea of a Eur¬
opean scientific laboratory
where scientists from differ¬
ent nations could collabor¬
ate in nuclear research
projects too costly to be
carried out in individual
countries, was first broached
in 1949 and taken up by the
Unesco General Conference
in 1950. In 1951 plans for
the setting up of a European
organization were drawn up
by Unesco with the help óf
experts from eight countries.
The Swiss Government pro¬
vided the site for the labora¬
tory, and last September
the agreement came into
force signed by eight coun¬
tries. All the research car¬
ried out at Meyrin will be
fundamentally scientific and
of a non-military character.
None of the work will be se¬
cret. It will provide scien¬
tists with invaluable means
of investigating the structure
of matter.
Unesco's Notional Distributors from whom
the English edition of THE COURIER can be
obtained are listed below. Other Unesco
distributors are listed in the French and
Spanish editions of THE COURIER.
Australia : Oxford Universicy Press, 346,
Lítele Collins Street, Melbourne.
Austria : Wilhelm Frick Verlag, 27, Gra¬
ben, Vienna I.
Burma : Burma Educational Bookshop,
551-3 Merchant Street. P.O. Box 222,
Rangoon.
Canada : University of Toronto Press,
Toronto.
Ceylon : Lake House Bookshop, The Asso¬
ciated Newspapers of Ceylon, Ltd., P.O.
Box 244. Colombo I. Rs. 5.
Cyprus : M. E. Constantinides, P.O.B. 473,
Nicosia.
Denmark : Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd., 6 Nor-
regade, Copenhagen, K.
Egypt : La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9, Adly
Pasha Street, Cairo.
Ethiopia : International Press Agency,
P.O.B. 120, Addis-Ababa.
34
NATIONAL DISTRIBUTORS
Finland : Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, 2 Kes-
kuskatu, Helsinki.
Formosa : The World Book Company Ltd.,
99, Chung King South Rd, Section I,
Taipeh.
France : Sales Division, Unesco, I 9, Avenue
Kléber, Paris- I 6e.
Germany : Unesco Vertrieb für Deutsch¬
land, R. Oldenbourg, München.
Greece : Librairie H. Kau ffman, 28, Rue
du Stade, Athens.
Hong Kong : Swindon Book Co., 25 Nathan
Road, Kowloon.
India: Orient Longmans Ltd., Bombay, Cal¬
cutta, Madras : sub-depots : Oxford Book
& Stationery Co., Scindia House, New
Delhi; Raj kamal Publications Ltd., Hima¬
laya House, Bombay 7. Rs. 4.
Indonesia : G.C.T. van Dorp & Do. NV.,
D/alan Nusantara, 22, Djakarta.
Iran : Iranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
Iraq : McKenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
Israel : Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd., 35,
Allenby Road, P.O. Box 5154. Tel-Aviv.
Jamaica : Sangster's Book Room, 99, Har¬
bour Street, Kingston; Knox Educational
Services, Spaldings.
Japan : Maruzen Co, Inc., 6 Tori-Nichome,
Nihonbashî, Tokyo.
Jordan : J.I. Bahous and Co., Dar-ul-Kutub,
Salt Road, Amman.
Korea : Korean National Commission for
Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
Liberia : J, Momotu Kamara, 69, Front
and Gurley Streets, Monrovia.
Mafayan Federation and Singapore :
Peter Chong and Co., P.O. Box 135,
Singapore.
Malta : Sapienza's Library, 26, Kingsway,
Valletta.
Netherlands : N V. Martinus Ni ¡hoff,
Lange Voorhout 9. The Hague.
New Zealand: Unesco Publications' Centre
100, Hackthorne Rd., Christchurch.
Nigeria : C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box 174,
Lagos.
Norway : A/S Bokhjornet, Stortingsplass, 7,
Oslo.
Pakistan : Ferozsons Ltd., Karachi, Lahore,
Peshawar. Rs. 3.
Philippines : Philippine Education Co.,
Inc., 1 1 04 Castillejos, Quiapo, Manila. 3.00
Surinam : Radhakishun and Company Ltd.,
(Book Depc), Waterrnolenstraat 36, Para¬
maribo.
Sweden : A.B.C E. Fritzes Kungt. Hov-
bokhande, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 16.
Thailand : Suksapan Panit, Arkarn 9,
Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok. 20 ttcals.
Union of South Africa : Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Ltd., P.O. Box 724, Pretoria.
United Kingdom : H.M. Stationery Office,
P.O. Box 569, London S.E.I.
U.S.A. : Unesco Publications Service, 4 75
5th Ave., New York 17, N.Y.
U
Z
<
at
<
O
Z
KD
O
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
DONT MISS
FUTUR
CONQUEST OF THE DESERT
A special 68-page issue on the latest world-wide efforts to make the desert
bloom. Developments in solar energy, wind energy, fresh water from the
sea, soilless cultivation, artificial rain-making, myths about the tropics, old
rain gods of primitive peoples.
HAPPY NEW YEAR ALL AROUND THE
WORLD. A series of articles showing
how peoples of different lands celebrate
the New Year, their customs, folklore,
irrespective of when the New Year falls for
different religions and cultures. New Year
in Japan, India; the Arabic New Year, etc.
WELCOME STRANGER. - International
fellowships and exchange of people between
countries as one of the most powerful roads
to building peace and international understand¬
ing. Unesco's exchange programme. Student
and teacher exchange, workers abroad.
ARE WOMEN INFERIOR BEINGS? -
Advances in women's status in recent
years in education, politics, society.
WHAT'S WRONG WITH OUR TEXT¬
BOOKS? Distortion of history in school
books. Text book publishinga great un¬
known industry.
SUBSCBIBE TO THE UNESCO COURIER TODAY. - English , French , Spanish , U.S. editions
ONE FULL YEAR'S SUBSCRIPTION AT THE AMAZINGLY LOW PRICE OF :
300 French francs ; 6/- ; $1.50 or equivalent in local currency (U.S. edition $2.50).
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
"% *;«r»
#,*:2l*
i
DUEL I N THE DARK
Sabres slash the air as two characters in a Chinese opera duel in
imaginary pitch darkness. The perilous triple jumps of the
duellers and their hairbreadth escapes are full of both suspense
and comedy. This is a scene from a recent Peking Opera per¬
formance in Paris, which revealed to the West an almost un¬
known form of dramatic art. See page 17. (Photo Pic, Paris.)
]]>
</page>
</document>
