<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="069680eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO
7<
The Courier
v.*
»ir
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A time to live . . .
46 The People's Republic of China
Pillar of tradition
A stone lion guards the Bridge of Golden Water
leading from T'ien-an-men Square to the old
Imperial Palace in Beijing. Beside it stands a
pillar adorned with carvings of clouds and
dragons. The pillar recalls an ancient tradition
stretching back to the time of the first emperors
of China, who erected in front of the Imperial
Palace tree trunks on which the people could
carve their grievances.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Courier
A window open on the world
Editorial
T
dEACE is a virtue originating in spiritual strength." In
1986, proclaimed International Year of Peace by the
General Assembly of the United Nations, Spinoza's
definition remains as relevant as ever. If there has been no
world war for forty years, neither has there been world peace:
internecine conflicts continue to devastate certain regions, and
all mankind is haunted by the spectre of a nuclear catastrophe,
threatening the annihilation of present and future generations.
The defence of peace today is increasingly assuming the form
of a constructive effort which is not confined to the need to
prevent wars, but grapples with a whole series of imbalances
that pervade the economic and social organization of the entire
planet. All the contributors to this issue of the Unesco Courier,
whatever their field whether they be specialists in war and
peace studies, economists, historians, medical doctors, philo¬
sophers or jurists and wherever they are from, agree on this
point.
Despite the different perspectives from which they analyse
the situation, they also share more common ground in that they
stress the interdependence of peace, disarmament and develop¬
ment, and regard the Third World for historical as well as
economic reasons as today's theatre of violence. They examine
and condemn the exploitation of peoples and the lack of rap¬
prochement between them; the opposition of blocs; the ram¬
pant folly of the arms race with its crippling cost to humanity;
anachronistic rivalry between national interests; the submission
of science to political and military power. From these various
approaches emerges the pressing need for a philosophy and
practice of peace; here, as the present number shows, Unesco
clearly has an essential role to play.
To contribute to the maintenance of peace and security is the
pre-eminent task assigned to Unesco by its Constitution and,
during the forty years of the Organization's existence, it has
worked unremittingly, within its fields of competence, towards
a world in which the whole human community may live in peace.
Faithful to its mandate of constructing the defences of peace in
the minds of men, Unesco is particularly concerned to promote
education for understanding, co-operation and international
peace.
In Japan, children have understood since Hiroshima that the
destruction of an enemy is also the destruction of a friend. They
make paper birds. cranes, a Japanese symbol of longevity
and give them away because they wish, in their own words, "to
build peace in this world."
Cover design Yurek Janiszewski
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
August 1986
39th year
5
©
j
Reflections on peace
1. Peace as an absolute value
by Claude Lefort
2. Peace, disarmament and technology
by Luis Echeverría
3. The cost of peace
by Michael S. O. Olisa
4. Peace in the regional context
by Ahmad Sidqi Ad-Dajani
1 1 'There is no peace because there is no justice'
by Desmond Mpilo Tutu
13 The Piigwash movement
by Joseph Rotblat
15 Perceptions of threat and security
by Yoshikazu Sakamoto
18 Higher education and peace
19 Physicians and the nuclear threat
by Bernard Lown
20 Unesco and the international Year of Peace
24 World military spending
25 The United Nations World Disarmament Campaign
by Jan Martenson
27 Towards a new way of thinking
by Gennadi I. Gerasimov
29 A thousand paper cranes
30 Violence in the Third World
by Soedjatmoko
34 1986: Year of Peace/8
A time to live ...
THE PEOPLE'S REPUBLIC OF CHINA: Pillar of tradition
Published monthly in 32 languages
by Unesco
The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
English Italian Turkish Macedonian Finnish
French Hindi Urdu Serbo-Croat Swedish
Spanish Tamil Catalan Slovene Basque
Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese Thai
German Persian Korean Bulgarian
Arabic Dutch Swahili Greek
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French,
Spanish and Korean
ISSN 0041-5278
N°8- 1986-CPD-86- 1 436 A
Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb Sinhala
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Reflections onpeace
A Unesco-sponsored international symposium on the theme
'Philosophical Reflections on the Foundations ofPeace in the Present World Situation'
was held at Unesco's Paris headquarters from 3 to 6 December 1985.
We publish below extracts from papers presented by four of the participants.
1. Peace as
an absolute
value
by Claude Lefort
"It Is certainly true that the closer men
come together the more they seem to
touch each other's sensitive spots. But
this is only a half truth. Is it not rather
because contacts and relationships are
not frequent enough that theyarouse such
apprehension?" Right, The Ship of Fools,
by the Dutch painter Hiëronymus Bosch
(c. 1450-1516), now in the Louvre Museum,
Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
"Peace as an absolute value can only be
based on the notion that relations between
men are relations between equals." Right,
Totonac earthenware statuette In the Jala-
pa Museum, State of Veracruz, Mexico.
The civilization of the Totonacs, a pre-
Columbian Mexican people, flourished
from the 7th to the 14th centuries on the
west coast of the Gulf of Mexico.
THE great German philosopher Im¬
manuel Kant (1724-1804) outlined
the idea of a code of law for mankind
emerging from the bitter experience of war
and necessitated by the increasing proxim¬
ity of men due to the growth of populations
on the limited surface of the globe.
Kant's foresight was astonishing when we
consider how heterogeneous and scattered
was the world he knew in comparison with
our own. He was not alone in his prediction;
most of the great thinkers of the early
nineteenth century, whatever their beliefs,
from Saint-Simon or Chateaubriand, in
France, to Karl Marx, were aware of the
new and incredibly rapidly accelerating
rhythm of population growth and of the
inescapable evidence, on every hand, that
space was finite.
Such predictions, which have constantly
been repeated up to our own times, con¬
tinue to amaze us, so far are they out¬
stripped by the actual speed of change. The
words of the French poet and essayist Paul
Valéry, written in 1931 in his book Regards
sur le monde actuel (Reflections on the
World Today), which sounded so excitingly
original to his contemporaries, seem to us
today as no more than a statement of the
obvious.
. "All the habitable regions of the Earth,"
he wrote, "have today been discovered,
mapped and divided amongst the nations.
The era of no man's lands, of free territor¬
ies, of unexplored regions, of areas to which
no one lays claim, is over, and with it has
gone the era of unlimited expansion. There
is now not a rock on which a flag has not
been planted, not an empty space on a map,
not a region without its laws and its customs
officers, not a tribe whose affairs have not
been filed and classified and which, through
the evil magic of writing, is not under the
tutelage of a varied host of 'humanists' in
far-distant offices. The era ofthefinite world
has begun."
He went on: "A new, excessive and in¬
stant interdependence between regions and
events is the perceptible consequence of
this important phenomenon. Now every
political happening must be considered in
the light of this new condition of universa¬
lity." And he spoke of "a closer and closer
interdependence in human actions."
It must be said that Paul Valéry, imbued
with the heritage of the Greek spirit with its
love ofclear-cut boundaries, did not consid¬
er this new situation in which the world
found itself to be a happy one. In the same
passage his anxiety shows through: "This
complexity will be the undoing of all
prudence, wisdom, genius, since in this uni¬
verse of multiple relationships and contacts
there is neither permanence nor continuity
nor discernible causality."
<
©
This is a judgement which cannot be
ignored. It is certainly true that the closer
men come together the more they seem to
touch each other's sensitive spots. But this
is only a half truth. Is it not rather because
contacts and relationships are not frequent
enough that they arouse such
apprehension? Is it not because the growing
interdependence of human actions has not
been matched by a genuine propagation of
human rights or by the establishment of a
public domain, on a world-wide scale, in
which divisions could find a form of express¬
ion other than war? Is it not also because
the movement towards the erosion of
ancient particularisms, which all are now
agreed is irreversible, comes up against con¬
siderable resistance and provokes estab¬
lished hierarchies to invent new methods of
excluding all those who, despite their differ¬
ing condition, might otherwise appear to be
"equals"?
Peace as an absolute value can, in fact,
only be based on the notion that relations
between men are relations between equals.
In other words, this value is indissociable
from that of liberty. It also means that it
would be hypocritical to sanction, in the
name of peace, any form of exploitation of
peoples who find themselves, under the
pretext of the play of market forces, dep¬
rived of the resources of their territory and
subjected to overt or covert dictatorship; it
would be equally hypocritical to sanction
any form of totalitarianism which denies
individuals and minorities their elementary
rights.
Since, in this discussion, we have been
cautioned not to fall into a facile utopianism
but to take due account of the constraints of
the contemporary world, we must not con¬
fuse the cause of peace with unreasoned
pacifism. Nor should we, in respecting the
realities, surrender to the delirium that the
spectacle of current conflicts gives rise to.
Rather we should admit that sovereigns do
not, as Rousseau supposed, alone decide
the fate of humanity. The laborious task of
bringing men closer together can only be
achieved through a better mutual know¬
ledge of customs and mental attitudes,
through progress in education, the diffusion
of information and the propagation of hu¬
man rights; far from being a vain task, this
can spark off decisive political moves to¬
wards peace.
Are these hopes doomed to remain unful¬
filled? The question clearly has yet to be
answered. Yet rather than concur with
Rousseau that it would be madness to want
to be sane in the midst of madmen, we
would do better to recognize calmly, with
Freud, that in the unceasing struggle be¬
tween Eros and the instinct of death, the
latter has shown itself to be decidedly the
stronger.
CLAUDE LEFORT, French philosopher, is
Director of Studies at the School of Advanced
Studies in the Social Sciences, Paris, where he
divides his time between teaching and research.
Hispublished works include Eléments d'une criti¬
que de la bureaucratie (Gallimard, revised edi¬
tion 1979) and L'invention démocratique
(Fayard, 1981).
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
2. Peace, disarmament and technology
by Luis Echeverría
WE consider peace to be an active
form of wisdom and negotiation,
and it is precisely for this reason
that it is essential for us to recognize that, in
our day and age, peace cannot be merely an
"institutionalized truce". Since 1945, each
truce, each agreement, each convention has
simply heralded a new impetus to the arms
race and accelerated development of the
military technology of the atomic era.
Although it is not the only cause, this has
been due in large part to a fundamental
reality the division of the world into
opposing blocs. In military and economic
terms, these blocs have been at the root of
the division of the world; furthermore, the
political conception of blocs, with their
ideological stratification, has hampered the
evolution of philosophical theory as well as
any progress in the parallel yet independent
process of philosophical reflection.
One practical consequence of this has
been the "colonization" of science, due
largely to the ideology of power and to the
ethically anomalous divorce of science itself
from its own historical effects. In practice
this has led to a methodological sectarian¬
ism according to which science must be¬
come the servant of military rather than
human priorities. This moral aberration,
the evidence of which we encounter daily,
characterizes the science of our time. It
presupposes that alignment into blocs is a
natural state of affairs; it also explains the
moral reaction of those scientists who have
broken with the established order and with
the military/industrial complex and whose
stance allows us to hope that there is a
future for mankind.
It is clear, therefore, that for this century
peace is going to be bound up with a new
formulation of the objectives of develop¬
ment. There will be no peace worthy of the
name so long as we fail to take advantage of
each period of ideological truce that occurs
"Disarmament implies, above all, a change
in the priorities of those countries princi¬
pally engaged in the arms race; and such a
change must involve a materialand dialec¬
tical transformation, both internal and ex¬
ternal, in the aims andobjectives thatmust
be set for contemporary development in
the name of solidarity and inter¬
dependence."
to alter the existing status quo of today's
world in other words, so long as we do not
adopt the principle of a genuine liquidation
of the dominant structurally-enshrined
violence.
To speak of peace and development as
one and the same phenomenon does not
mean merely to speak in abstract terms of a
purely moral proposition or to enter an
ideological labyrinth from which there is no
exit. On the contrary, it is to pose the crucial
question of the closing years of the twen¬
tieth century. Peace today is not simply the
opposite of war; it is the political and philo¬
sophical context for the practical achieve¬
ment of a new form of development giving
effect to the suspension of conflicts and
which will give rise to a new form of society
based on negotiation, self-examination and
liberty.
So long as this aspect of peace remains
less than perfectly clear, local conflicts and
wars of tactical and strategic attrition will
continue to be the determining factor in
international relations. In other words, the
nightmare threat of local conflicts develop¬
ing into a total, catastrophic war will con¬
tinue to hover over our heads.
Worse than this, if present conditions
persist, any purely national interest, any
selfish supranational goal will be seen,
ideologically, as a factor in military policy.
Structural violence will thus menace us
daily in forms ranging from fanatical terror¬
ism to local or regional conflicts, irrational
chain explosions which are no more than
the expression of a violent departure from
the principles of solidarity, justice and law.
It is incomprehensible that, each year,
expenditure on armaments should be
almost equal to the external debt (approx¬
imately 800,000 million dollars) of the de¬
veloping countries, whose populations at
present amount to 75 per cent of total world
population, a figure that will rise to 79 per
cent by the end of the century.
Rationally speaking, we cannot dissoci¬
ate the philosophical and political aspects of
the struggle for peace from the economic
choices proposed under the project for a
new international economic order.
In every respect, the interlinkage of
peace, disarmament and development
seems fundamental. It cannot, as is some¬
times maintained, be conceived in terms of
a purely mechanical transfer to the peoples
of the developing world of the resources at
present devoted to armaments.
Disarmament implies, above all, a
change in the priorities of those countries
principally engaged in the arms race; and
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
such a change must involve a material and
dialectical transformation, both internal
and external, in the aims and objectives that
must be set for contemporary development
in the name of solidarity and inter¬
dependence.
There is another essential underlying
question: that of the transfer of scientific
and military resources to a science whose
goal is peace. This would imply the greatest
revolution of the century the divorce of
science from power politics and the moral
regeneration of research by making it possi¬
ble for science and scientists to escape from
the clutches of the powerful military/indus¬
trial complex which dominates our age.
Disarmament would free massive re¬
sources for development. One possible
joint international venture could be the
exploration of the Arctic and Antarctic for
the benefit of humanity.
LUIS ECHEVERRÍA was President of Mexico
from 1970 to 1 976. Jurist, journalist and a former
professor of political science at the National
Autonomous UniversityofMexico, he is Director-
General of the Centre for Third World Economic
and Social Studies, Mexico City.
"In 1980, out of the 3 million scientists and
engineers employed world-wide in scien¬
tific laboratories, approximately half a mil¬
lion were specifically engaged in the de¬
velopment of new weapons systems. By
1981, those in the forefront of space tech¬
nology were believed to have acquired the
ability to survey virtually every square
metre of each other's territory, but the
world-widepool ofscientific and engineer¬
ing resources had barely begun to survey
the complex ecosystems of fast-dis¬
appearing tropical rain forests or the
menacing spread of the world's deserts."
(United Nations document, April 1986.) Be¬
low, this 600-year-old pine is a symbol of
nature conservation for the people of the
Republic ofKorea. The tree, growing some
100 kilometres south-east of Seoul, is pro¬
tected by a large cage. Legend has it that
the tree was given the official title of
cabinet minister by a 15th-century Korean
king, because it raised its branches in re¬
spect when he passed by.
/
.
I
Wl
¿m&.
@
. *-
»ill
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
3. The cost of peace
by Michael S.O. Olisa
THERE are two conflicting ap¬
proaches to the question of peace.
One postulates the existence of an
ideal world. The other is more realistic. In
an ideal world an immediate end to the arms
race and to ideological confrontation would
be possible. Total acceptance of the neces¬
sary conditions for disarmament would lead
to a world without war in which the re¬
sources of all nations would be channelled
to non-military production and distribu¬
tion. All nuclear weapons would be des¬
troyed and further production banned; use
of non-nuclear arms would be restricted or
prohibited; the North-South conflict would
be virtually eliminated, with the industrially
advanced countries giving a large measure
of genuine economic assistance to the de¬
veloping world.
The realistic approach is different and
less optimistic. It is based on the assumption
that struggle and ideological polarization,
backed by advances in weapons science and
technology will be stepped up. In these
circumstances efforts towards disarmament
will meet an increasing number of obstacles
and frustrations.
These arguments point clearly to the
futility and unattainability of the ideal
world concept. At the same time they
underline the necessity for collective re¬
search by the world community into the
most practicable options for the rest of this
century and for the next.
In this connexion it is instructive to look
at some options which have been put for¬
ward within the United Nations system. In a
1984 report to the General Assembly, the
Secretary-General outlined three scenarios
relevant to the prospects of peace by the
year 2000. Although these scenarios are
based on the economic aspects of the arms
race and disarmament, they are directly
linked to the central issue of world peace
today and tomorrow.
The baseline scenario assumes that the
share of military outlay in gross national
product (GNP) and the geographical dis¬
tribution of military industry will be roughly
the same throughout the period 1970-2000.
The second scenario envisages an accel¬
eration in the arms race, with a hypothetical
doubling of the share of GNP for military
outlays by the year 2000 in comparison with
the baseline of 1970.
The third, a disarmament scenario,
assumes that United States and Soviet milit¬
ary spending as projected under the base¬
line scenario will fall by one third between
1970 and 1990 and by a further third by
2000. It also assumes that the relatively
wealthy regions of the world will transfer a
fraction of their hypothetical savings from
disarmament to the poorest regions.
An important issue raised by these sce¬
narios is that of the cost ofpeace, as opposed
"The cost of war is the continued alloca¬
tion of massive resources to armaments
production, the possible outbreak of wars
and the consequent need to continue pro¬
duction for replacement purposes." Left,
Slapende Mars, (Mars Asleep) by the
Dutch painter Hendrik Terbrugghen (1588-
1629). Mars is the god of war in classical
Roman mythology.
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
"The cost ofpeace ... will face a variety of
challenges arising from the conversion of
resources to non-military uses, the rede¬
ployment of a massive labour force from
armaments and support industries ... and
the reallocation to the world's poorer
countries of some of the resources re¬
leased from arms production." Right, a
patchwork picture created by a Kenyan
woman from scraps ofmaterial In different
colours and textures.
W/\A,
©
to the cost of war. The cost of war is the
continued allocation of massive resources
to armaments production; the possible out¬
break of wars and the consequent need to
continue production for replacement pur¬
poses.
The cost of peace implies a reversal of
these trends, a process which will face a
variety of challenges arising from the con¬
version of resources to non-military uses,
the redeployment of a massive labour force
from armaments and support industries;
plant conversion; the hostility of powerful
interest groups deprived of huge profits;
and the reallocation to the world's poorer
countries of some of the resources released
from arms production.
It is both significant and highly encourag¬
ing that positive and optimistic attitudes
exist towards these problems, especially in
non-governmental circles, suggesting
strongly that the cost of peace will not be
too great a burden. These positive indica¬
tors also suggest that it is not the objective,
material factors in the peace package dis¬
location, conversion and reallocation of the
resources hitherto invested in war which
constitute the main barriers to peace, but
rather the subjective, psychological factors
arising from contemporary economic and
political problems. In other words, the hu¬
man factor is the most serious threat to
world peace.
However, there is no dearth of public
expressions of concern and desire for peace
from world leaders and governments. Un¬
fortunately, disarmament negotiations con¬
tinue to flounder because nations dread
unilateral disarmament. They are not sure
that their opponents v\»>uld follow their
lead; they fear that their rivals may strike
first; they feverishly continue arms produc¬
tion because they suspect that the other side
has outstripped them. This "balance of sus¬
picion" results in the continuation of activi¬
ties which encourage war and threaten
peace.
MICHAEL S.O. OLISA, Nigerian political scien¬
tist and lecturer at the University of Nigeria,
Nsukka, is Director of the Nigerian Institute for
Peace Research. His published works include
Political Culture and Stability among Traditional
Ibo (7977) and Problems of National Identifica¬
tion and Unity in Nigeria (1971).
¿0' W
4. Peace in the regional
context
by Ahmad Sidqi Ad-Dajani
PEOPLE today are beginning to
understand more clearly that the sta¬
bility of relations between States is
influenced by circumstances in each indi¬
vidual State. The stability of relations be¬
tween the world's rich States is affected by
the stability of basic structures in the
world's poor States. Countries that are rich
and secure must realize that they cannot
remain so if they continue to close their eyes
to the scourge of poverty that prevails in the
entire southern half of the globe.
The term "independence" has begun to
imply responsibility as well as freedom,
both at the level of the individual State and
that of the community of States. The world
situation may be likened to that of a ship full
of people. Those at the bottom have de
cided to drill their way out. If the others
leave them to their own devices everyone
will perish, whereas if they offer assistance,
all will be saved. We owe this parable illus¬
trating the meaning of responsibility to the
Prophet of Islam.
The stability of world peace at the
national, regional and international levels is
affected by the dominant philosophies of
our age. We are currently witnessing a
reawakening of philosophical thought and a
renewal of interest in fundamental philo¬
sophical issues. The place of religion in
Western industrial societies had declined,
and the role of philosophy had shrunk. In¬
deed, some Western thinkers had asserted
that the age of philosophy was over.
Today, however, there is a revival of
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
©
interest in philosophical thought and en¬
quiry, a trend which extends to the man in
the street, whose life is dominated by the
phenomenon of mass communication. We
are also witnessing a revival of religion, the
impact of which a blend of social, cultural
and political factors is today apparent in
various societies and social milieux. The
trends emerging in these religious revival
movements and those that are likely to
emerge in contemporary philosophies will
have a decisive influence on the issue of
peace or war.
The question of peace requires a system
of values that is recognized throughout the'
world, and at the same time there must be a
growing acceptance of others, despite their
diversity. This would tend to a situation of
equilibrium. If a relativistic value system
prevails, in which some people are regarded
with contempt and differences are not
accepted, then equilibrium is disrupted and
the spectre of war must inevitably reign.
The establishment of non-homogeneous
States within a single region is a major cause
of tension and a source of local and regional
conflicts. Thus, after the withdrawal of the
Western colonial powers and the triumph of
nationalism, States with arbitrary and artifi¬
cial boundaries came into being. Within
these artificial geopolitical units were va¬
rious tribes and racial communities, one of
which eventually became dominant. Such
States have to contend with tribal or civil
war within their borders, and this phe¬
nomenon may be a lasting one inasmuch as
its main cause is deeply rooted in their
human composition. It should be noted that
civil war is frequently characterized by
savagery, sometimes spreading to a point at
which it threatens the peace of an entire
region.
Another form of heterogeneity is appa¬
rent in the multinational State. In a world in
which the nationalist impulse has grown
increasingly powerful, especially in the last
two centuries, and in which the nation-State
has come to be regarded as the ideal form of
State, the presence of a number of national
population groups within a single State
brings the danger of communal strife, un¬
less adequate steps are taken to recognize
the nationalist impulse and national lan¬
guages and to promote economic and social
progress under a strong central federal
authority.
National and religious pluralism are
closely interrelated, and conflict between
national groups is sometimes expressed as
religious conflict and vice versa. Civil wars
break out under the banner of religion:
Europe, for example, was convulsed by
wars of religion at the beginning of the
modern era. Furthermore the presence of a
number of different national groups within
a single State may lead to tension between
that State and its neighbours because of
what are termed "national minorities".
Another form of the heterogeneous State
also appears in the "bi-national States" that
arose in the modern world during the period
of the Western colonial offensive. In these
La planète affolée, oil on canvas by the
German-born (later US, then French) artist
Max Ernst (1891-1976). The picture was
painted in 1943 in the United States. Paint¬
er, sculptor, poet, essayist, Max Ernst has
been called the "Leonardo of surrealism".
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
States, minorities of European stock
dominate an indigenous majority, and the
phenomenon of "biculturalism" is clearly
apparent. In many cases this situation of
dominance has resulted in outbreaks of
deadly strife between different population
groups.
Perhaps the most dangerous form of the
heterogeneous State in a single region is the
"settler colonialist" State which is im¬
planted in a homogeneous region on a basis
of racist aggression. Both Africa and Asia
have suffered as a result of having been
selected as targets for a number of assaults
by European settler colonialism during the
colonial era.
Colonialism has been and still is a leading
cause of wars, and colonized peoples have
suffered severely as a result. It has been a
destructive force in regions which have lost
a unity formerly characterized by the in¬
tegration of natural and human elements.
The effort to halt the destructive impact of
colonialism and to repair the damage done
by it was initially expressed in the form of
resistance to colonialist assaults and subse¬
quently in the form of revolutionary wars of
liberation, such measures being regarded as
necessary to the building of peace and the
return to a normal situation.
While colonialism is a particularly blatant
form of exploitation, exploitation in gener¬
al, even within a single State or community,
is a source of tensions that may lead to wars
and revolutions. In any society, social re¬
volution is neither more nor less than a
decisive answer to the exploitation of the
downtrodden classes by the dominant class.
One distinguishing feature of the modern
world has been the appearance of ideo¬
logies, and fierce ideological struggles have
been a source of tribulation in our time.
Clearly this type of struggle was one of the
sources of tension leading to what is com¬
monly known as the "cold war". The strug¬
gle is intensified by the attacks of ideo¬
logical opponents which permeate the
communications media.
Another cause of tension at the regional
level is terrorism, which has emerged as a
phenomenon of the contemporary world. A
variety of factors nationalist, social,
ideological, political and intellectual have
interacted to give rise to this phenomenon.
While terrorism is still largely shrouded in
obscurity, it is at any rate clear that a dis¬
tinction must be made between it and resist¬
ance to colonialism. Terrorism may occur at
the level of individuals, and it may also
assume official form when practised by
States.
What can be done to remove these causes
of tension? Any successful action must be
based on an understanding of human
aspirations and instincts.
The impulse to universal brotherhood is a
natural human instinct, while the racist feel¬
ings that have come to dominate the minds
of some people are a deformation of that
instinct. Nationalist sentiment is also natu¬
ral to man, a "social animal", but chauvinis¬
tic nationalism is a clear deformation of that
sentiment. Again, man instinctively strives
after justice, bufonee he achieves power he
begins to exploit others. The spiritual
dimension is a basic feature of human
nature, and the motive force behind reli¬
gious faith. But religious fanaticism is a
deformation of that motive force. Lastly,
while it is natural for man to seek ideologies
that provide comprehensive explanations of
the universe, ideological confrontation is a
deformation of that natural desire.
The problems that have arisen in human
relations spring to a great extent from a
failure to reconcile the obligations arising
from a plurality of reference-groups and
from artificial contradictions^ between thé
demands of these multiple affiliations. Our
world has suffered greatly from an exagger¬
ated emphasis on the "national" group to
the detriment of the demands of our affilia¬
tions to the global group. This has had
disastrous consequences for all nations. In
his introduction to Bertrand Russell's book,
Has Man a Future?, Arnold Toynbee
speaks of the striking contrast between the
enormity of the dangers that we have
brought upon ourselves and the petty
nature of the national interests for which we
are fighting and which would be doomed to
extinction if the whole world were
annihilated.
AHMAD SIDQI AD-DAJANI, professor ofhistory
at the Scientific Centre on the History of Arab
Countries in Cairo, has written widely on the
history of the Arab world.
'There is no peace because there is no justice'
Desmond Mpilo Tutu, Anglican Bishop
of Johannesburg since 1985, was
awarded the Nobel Peace Prize in 1984
for his role in the opposition to apar¬
theid. As General Secretary of the
South African Council of Churches,
Bishop Tutu is a leading spokesman for
the rights of black South Africans. He
has always emphasized non-violent
means of protest. Below is an extract
from his Nobel Lecture on the occasion
of the Prize-giving ceremony held in
Oslo on 11 December 1984.
... We see before us a land bereft of much
justice, and therefore without peace and
security. Unrest is endemic, and will remain
an unchanging feature of the South African
scene until apartheid, the root cause of it
all, is finally dismantled. ... There is no
peace in Southern Africa. There is no peace
because there is no justice. There can be no
real peace and security until there be first
justice enjoyed by all the inhabitants of that
beautiful land.
I have spoken extensively about South
Africa, first because it is the land I know
best, but because it is also a microcosm of
the world and an example of what is to be
found in other lands in differing degree
when there is injustice, invariably peace
becomes a casualty.
Because there is global insecurity, na¬
tions are engaged in a mad arms race,
spending billions of dollars wastefully on
instruments of destruction, when millions
are starving. ... We have the capacity to
feed ourselves several times over, but we
are daily haunted by the spectacle of the
gaunt dregs of humanity shuffling along in
endless queues, with bowls to collect what
the charity of the world has provided, too
little too late. When will we learn, when will
the people of the world get up and say.
Enough is enough? ... When will we learn
that an escalated arms race merely escalates
global insecurity? We are now much closer
to a nuclear holocaust than when our tech¬
nology and our spending were less.
Let us work to be peacemakers. If we
want peace, let us work for justice. Let us
beat our swords into ploughshares.
Text ©The Nobel Foundation, 1985
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Nuclear war
5,000 megatons
A third of the nuclear arsenal (1)
(1) The world nuclear arsenal in 1982 was the equiva¬
lent of 1 2,000 to 1 4,000 megatons of explosive power.
Source: Association of French Physicians for the Pre¬
vention of Nuclear War
Graphics: Yurek Janiszewski - The Unesco Courier
Oxides of nitrogen
Depletion of
ozone layer
Increase in
ultraviolet radiation
Shock
Destruction
of soils
(erosion)
Destruction
of the plant
community
10 to 20. 106 km2
Breakdown
of dead
organic
matter
General
temperature rise
Desertification
of tropical regions
Warming of
nordlc regions
Melting of
polar Icecaps
and glaciers
Floods
Reduced
population -
500 million?
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Pugwash movement
by Joseph Rotblat
THE direct initiative for the Pugwash
Movement came not from a scientist
but from the British philosopher Ber¬
trand Russell. In 1955, the world situation
appeared highly dangerous and the outlook
for mankind very gloomy. The development of
the hydrogen bomb in the United States and
the Soviet Union marked the start of the nu¬
clear arms race, with both sides manufactur¬
ing and testing bombs of ever-increasing des¬
tructive power. Even at that time, before the
advent of ballistic missiles, these bombs deli¬
vered by manned aircraft could annihilate the
largest centres of population. In the climate of
intense mistrust, fear, and hostile propaganda
which then prevailed, it seemed highly prob¬
able that the cold war would change into a hot
war in which civilization would be destroyed.
It was in these circumstances that the Rus¬
sell-Einstein Manifesto was born. Russell
conceived the idea that the scientific com¬
munity should be actively concerned about
the dangers to humanity which arose largely
through the work of scientists. At that time the
greatest living scientist was Albert Einstein,
and Russell wrote to him with the idea of
convening a conference of eminent scientists
for this purpose. Einstein immediately agreed
and asked Russell to prepare a draft of a
suitable statement. This Russell did and in
April 1 955 sent it to Einstein for his signature.
Later that month, Russell was flying from
Rome to Paris, when the pilot announced to
the passengers that Einstein had died. Rus¬
sell was shattered, because he feared that
without Einstein's sponsorship the whole pro¬
ject would collapse. But when Russell arrived
at his hotel in Paris, a letter with Einstein's
signature to the statement was waiting for
him. Signing it had been one of the last acts of
the great scientist's life. In this dramatic way
the Pugwash Movement began. The signa¬
tures of nine other scientists from six coun¬
tries were obtained, and on 9 July 1955 the
Manifesto was issued at a press conference
held at Caxton Hall in London.
The press conference was attended by a
very large number of media representatives
from all over the world; it was a great success
and received huge publicity. This in turn
brought a flood of letters and cables from
individuals and groups endorsing the Mani¬
festo and offering help. One of the letters was
from Mr. Cyrus Eaton, a Canadian-American
industrialist, offering to finance the confer¬
ence of scientists which was called for in the
Manifesto, and suggesting that it be held at his
birthplace, Pugwash, a small fishing village in
Nova Scotia.
In his offer of help Eaton made it clear that
while the participants would be his guests
they would be completely independent; that
the preparatory work and organization would
be handled by Russell and his colleagues,
and that the conduct and proceedings of the
Conference would be left entirely to the parti¬
cipants.
The first of the series of conferences of
scientists held under the aegis of the Russell-
Einstein Manifesto took place in Pugwash in
July 1957. The twenty-two participants came
from ten countries, including the United
States, the United Kingdom, France, the
Soviet Union, China and Poland. The work
was divided among three committees, with
the following topics: hazards arising from the
use of atomic energy in peace and war; con¬
trol of nuclear weapons; and the social
responsibility of scientists.
The possible hazard from the radioactive
fall-out from nuclear weapons tests was a
Peace on the singing constellation of the waters
Jostling like the shoulders of the crowd
Peace in the sea's waves of goodwill
Peace on the resting place of the foundering
Peace on the drums of arrogance and the darkened pupils
And if I am the interpreter of the waves
Peace also on me.
Vicente Huidobro (Chile)
Monumento al mar
Ascn&pe . KUTHULA ^P
* ANyilale ÄNM
» Suguru Runyararo #>
AMAHORO peAc^AfWr
-KE.4-*» 17 \w*u it-*-. (/
4/no4*_- mthunlam/
TERbOlJ** I I
KEAMANAN **y* PAIX '
' "-> 6ARIS
/
Baric
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
[edzole
LAFFI 5ß
¡f^-PACE
fH/frfo«.o
FRIEDEN PAZ
***
v\n/l . L. . e.~
PEACE «a^o^f ^
Kf\Ovç^D i
Nútifafa /) .C6*6-
A/*6Ab[
-i'
Frieden
major issue at that time, and it was of con¬
siderable importance that such an internation¬
al group of scientists, covering a wide range of
political opinion, managed to reach unani¬
mous agreement on the quantitative assess¬
ment of the consequences of large-scale test¬
ing of nuclear weapons. The most controver¬
sial issue was the discussion in the committee
on the control of nuclear weapons, because
this included the whole area of arms limita¬
tions and reductions, and the steps needed to
achieve general and complete disarmament,
topics which were to occupy most of the time
of future Pugwash Conferences. But there
was unanimous agreement that scientists can
and ought to contribute to the debate on these
problems.
The committee on the social responsibility
of scientists was also unanimous in its find¬
ings, which took the form of a statement of
common beliefs. The fact that a long
statement, dealing in some detail with the
most controversial issues of the day, and
setting out the role and responsibility of scien¬
tists, was accepted by such a diverse group of
scientists, was in itself of great significance.
This was probably the first time that a truly
international conference, organized by scien¬
tists, with participants from East and West,
had been convened to discuss not purely
technical matters but the social implications of
scientific discovery.
The first Pugwash Conference proved that
scientists have a common purpose which can
transcend national frontiers without violating
basic loyalties. It had shown that, by virtue of
their training and their knowledge, scientists
are capable of discussing objectively the com-
'plex problems which have arisen from the
progress of science, with the aim of finding a
solution to these problems.
The realization of this unanimity of intent
decided the participants to make further
efforts in the same direction. For this purpose,
a Continuing Committee of five persons was
set up at the end of the Conference, with
instructions to organize further conferences of
a similar nature. This was the go-ahead for the
setting up of a Movement of Scientists, which
takes its name "The Pugwash Conferences
on Science and World Affairs" from the venue
of the first meeting.
Since then, the following characteristics of
Pugwash have gradually evolved: partici¬
pants in conferences and meetings are invited
in their personal capacity and represent no¬
body but themselves; they are scientists (this
term being used in its broadest sense) and
cover a wide spectrum of ideological and
geographical groupings within the scientific
community; the debates in Pugwash meet¬
ings are conducted in the scientific spirit; as a
private and independent entity, Pugwash
does not usually undertake joint action with
other organizations, except the United Na¬
tions and its specialized agencies, such as
Unesco.
The role and responsibility of scientists has
always been a matter of special concern for
Unesco: the Preamble to its Constitution con¬
tains the famous declaration "...since wars
begin in the minds of men, it is in the minds of
men that the defences of peace must be
constructed." In 1982, Unesco organized
jointly with Pugwash a symposium on the
theme of "Scientists, the Arms Race and Dis¬
armament", the conclusions and recom¬
mendations of which set forth specific tasks
for scientists to undertake in the fulfilment of
their social obligations. These recommenda¬
tions are based on the development of ideas
put forward in Pugwash Conferences since
1957.
One unique characteristic of Pugwash is
absence of rigidity in its make-up and a mini¬
mum of formalized structure. There is no writ¬
ten constitution and no formal membership;
any scientist who has attended a Pugwash
conference automatically becomes a "Pug-
washite". However, being without a constitu
tion is not the same as acting entirely arbitrar¬
ily. In the course of time certain guiding princi¬
ples have evolved. These are usually re¬
viewed every five years at the Quinquennial
Conference, which serves as a kind of Gener¬
al Assembly, which all who have participated
in at least two Pugwash conferences in the
past are entitled to attend.
Although the largest attendance so far, at
the 1 977 Quinquennial, was 223, it has never
been the intention to confine the Movement's
activities to a small group of scientists. One
way of involving more participants has been to
set up national Pugwash groups, and by 1982
such groups existed in thirty-six countries. An
example of a regular activity by a national
group is the International Summer School of
Disarmament and Arms Control organized
biennially by the Italian Pugwash Group.
There are also Pugwashites in thirty-nine
other countries, but they are not numerous
enough to form national groups. In such
cases, regional groups are set up such as
those which exist today for Africa and Latin
America.
Today the Pugwash Movement is estab¬
lished as an important and effective channel
of communication between scientists for the
study and discussion of many of the complex
issues which confront mankind at the present
time. Participation in these conferences by
eminent scientists from East and West, North
and South, and the constructive proposals
which have emerged from the discussions,
particularly in relation to disarmament, have
secured for the Pugwash Conferences the
respect of the scientific community, of gov¬
ernments, and of many sectors of society. The
name "Pugwash" has become a symbol of
successful international debate on controver¬
sial issues, and the conferences are cited as a
model for similar efforts in other fields.
The success of the Pugwash Conferences
is the result of resolute efforts of a group of
scientists determined to retain an indepen¬
dent and unbiased outlook, and anxious to
build and consolidate international under¬
standing and co-operation. The Conferences
have shown that it is possible to apply the
scientific approach, which has proved so suc¬
cessful in science and technology, to prob¬
lems which are only indirectly related to sci¬
ence. They have shown that even when deal¬
ing with highly controversial matters, it is
possible to tell the truth without being abusive,
to be candid without trying to embarrass, pro¬
vided that there is a common approach based
on scientific objectivity and mutual respect.
JOSEPH ROTBLAT, of the United Kingdom, isa
foundermember of the Pugwash Movement, and
was its first Secretary-General (1957- 1973). To¬
day Professor Emeritus of Physics at the Uni¬
versity of London, he has campaigned for many
years in favour ofarms control and disarmament.
He is the author of numerous publications on
world affairs, nuclear energy and the quest for
peace, including the official history of Pugwash.
He was general editor of Scientists, the Arms
Race and Disarmament, a Unesco-Pugwash
Symposium published by Unesco in 1982. The
present text has been extracted from the author's
contribution to a series of studies which Unesco
is publishing on the origins ofpeace movements
in different parts of the world.
1A
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Perceptions of threat
and security
by Yoshikazu Sakamoto
S
ECURITY", as discussed in the
context of international relations,
concerns the security of nations
"national security". The State-system is
characterized by this emphasis on the secur¬
ity of the State as the primary and para¬
mount actor in international politics.
At the same time, it is evident that, when
"national security" became a key political
symbol after the Second World War, in
Two visions, nine centuries apart, of the
end of the world. Miniature, left, from the
Saint Sever Apocalypse (1028), with com¬
mentary by the 8th-century monk Beatus,
originally belonged to Saint Sever Abbey,
south-west France, and is now in the Bib¬
liothèque Nationale, Paris. Right, detail
from Pablo Picasso's Guernica, "the most
celebratedpainting of our century" and Its
most symbolic, both in the masterly bold¬
ness of its conception and execution and
in the grim topicality of its content.
many countries the issue of "internal secur¬
ity" became as important as, if not more
important than, "external security" which
the idea of "national security" originally
referred to.
This illustrates the basic fact that the
State is not always a tightly homogenized
entity, but is composed of groups with di¬
verse and often conflicting interests. Thus,
an examination of the concepts of "secur¬
ity" and "threat" should begin by raising
two basic questions: Whose security, and
security of what? Or, threat to whom and to
what? Hence the need for an examination
of actors and values.
The emergence and consolidation of the
modern nation-State in the West involved,
firstly, the establishment of the State
machinery and, secondly, its extension and
penetration into society mobilizing the
people who would be integrated into the
State and who would constitute the
"nation".
This mobilization process has two com
ponents: domination and participation. As
a result of domination, two functionally
distinct strata emerge: the ruling elite and
the ruled masses, the former normally small
in number. But there is another form of
coercive integration in which a majority
prevails over a minority. What is crucial is
obviously not number but the locus of
power.
The political system of a State integrated
in this fashion is bound to be characterized
by an unequal and inequitable distribution
of values. Even in a democratic society, one
can observe an inequitable distribution of
the effects of external insecurity in favour of
the privileged elite. It is said that a proposal
for world peace once contained the
observation that "if the King, the President,
the Prime Minister and the Commander-in-
Chief are to be the first to go to the front
line in the battlefield when war has been
declared, there will be no war".
This being the case, measures have been
taken by the elite in the nation-State to ^
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
ensure that people's perceptions of their
interests are identical with those of the elite.
These measures are intended to strengthen
the people's sense of identification with the
elite and with the State; they point to the
second aspect of the mobilization process
participation, whether real or manipulated.
One way of strengthening the people's
sense of identification with the nation-State
is through manipulation of the popular
perception of the threat-security issue.
There are three levels on which manipula¬
tion is systematically applied.
The first has to do with the conception of
the values to be defended and secured
against threat. In the nation-State, there is
always a latent cleavage which may develop
into a situation in which values for the elite
and values for the people are no longer
compatible, and the elite and the people
constitute a threat to each other, making
"internal security" a fundamental issue to
both parties.
To counteract this withdrawal of national
allegiance and identification on the part of
the people, the elite frequently resorts to
symbols such as order, royalty, property,
cultural tradition, and national mythology,
which are conceived of as transcending sec¬
toral interests.
The second level concerns the perception
of the presence and degree of the external
threat to security. Even if the internal cleav¬
age is limited, enabling a degree of national
consensus to emerge, there is still room for
different perceptions as to the presence and
degree of external threat. Accordingly, the
elite group has to manipulate public percep¬
tion in order to mobilize the people fully in
support of a policy.
The third level has to do with the cost
involved in counteracting the perceived
threat. To facilitate public acceptance of
the cost, the manipulation of public percep¬
tion is systematically carried out by resort¬
ing to symbols of patriotism to convince the
people that the "threat" is serious and the
cost to be paid is acceptable. What fre¬
quently happens is that those citizens who
are educated and earn higher incomes con¬
stitute the "attentive public" who do not
readily conform to the policy and rhetoric of
the elite group. It is the poorer and less
educated who are more likely to fall victim
to the manipulation of patriotic symbols
and show willingness , even fanatical confor-
mism, to make sacrifices in support of
chauvinistic policy. It is indeed a tragedy
that those who get least from the existing
system often pay most.
Another way of strengthening a sense of
identification with the nation-State is by
promoting popular participation in the pro¬
cess of value allocation.
This can take two forms participation in
the political decision-making process and
sharing of the well-being distributed by the
State. The former concerns input, the latter
output. Theoretically, the West put an
emphasis on the former, the East on the
latter. In practice, the States in the West
and in the East have a similar characteristic
in common the welfare state.
The development of the welfare state has
given rise to somewhat contradictory re¬
sults. On the one hand, it has made people
more dependent on the State as far as their
welfare is concerned. On the other it has
reinforced the popular attitude toward the
State, which has come to be regarded as a
mere instrument for satisfying the welfare
needs of the people an attitude which has
led to the erosion of the authority of the
State. The welfare state offers more service
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
- :- -
"...Bleeding on the wall, living, red or half-
Infected, the wound of a man ... Strange
wounds that we encounter with embar¬
rassment and nausea, suffering oh empty
walls. " These lines are by the French poet
Henri Michaux, who also painted the
watercolour at left. Above, In this calli¬
graphic composition by Hassan Mas-
soudy, the word "peace" in Arabic sug¬
gests the shape ofa bird floating on peace¬
ful waters which are themselves depicted
by the same word repeated many times.
and distributes values more equitably than
the classic nation-State; but it evokes less
political enthusiasm and dedication. A new
form of incongruity is emerging between
people and the State.
One of the main reasons for this incon¬
gruity is the loss of "impermeability", espe¬
cially military impermeability, of the na¬
tion-State. Whereas the welfare state pro¬
vides the people with abundant welfare faci¬
lities, it fails to guarantee their survival. No
single State, including the major powers,
can protect its people from the danger of
extinction. The survival of the people of one
great power is at the mercy of another.
In Sum, the implementation of popular
participation has not led to a strengthening
of the process whereby people identify with
the nation; on the contrary, the greater
extent of participation has raised public
awareness that the nation-State is not an
adequate institutional framework for ensur¬
ing the people's security.
It is clear today that the incongruity be
tween "national security" and people's
security can be observed not only within the
nation-State but also in the field of interna¬
tional security.
At the international level, there is an
unmistakable tendency to define what con¬
stitutes security and the threat to it in
accordance with the perceptions of a very
small number of elites in the major powers.
The fact that the entire globe can be annihi¬
lated as a result of the perception or mis-
perception of a top decision-maker testifies
to the extraordinary concentration of power
whereby the security-threat nexus is de¬
fined on behalf of the people of the world
without their mandate.
While the elite of each major power per¬
ceives the threat to security as originating in
the arms buildup of the other, the people of
the world perceive the threat to security as
originating in the arms race between the
major powers and fear that this may even
escape control of the elite of these powers.
In this sense, the threat is systemic.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
The systemic character of the threat im¬
plies that attainment of global security
assuring the security of the people of the
world calls for significant modifications in
the State-system. Efforts have been made
to strengthen the institutional framework
for global security, such as the peace-keep¬
ing and peace-making machinery of the Un¬
ited Nations and the arrangements for arms
control and disarmament in a search for
"common security", but no substantive
progress has been made.
In the absence of an institutionalized
framework despite the impending systemic
crisis, transnational people's movements
for disarmament have emerged. Such
movements are an uninstitutionalized de¬
vice for coping with a crisis and are an
indispensable initiator of a new institutional
framework that has yet to be created.
YOSHIKAZU SAKAMOTO, ofJapan, isa former
Secretary-General of the International Peace
Research Association, and is currently a profes¬
sor of law at the University of Tokyo. He is a
member of the International Commission for
Peace in the Minds of Men, the jury responsible
for awarding the Unesco Prize for Peace Educa¬
tion. A longer version of this article has appeared
in the Unesco Yearbook on Peace and Conflict
Studies 1983, published by Unesco in 1985.
Higher education and peace
THE risk of a nuclear conflict is the over¬
riding problem facing humanity today
and efforts to prevent nuclear annihila¬
tion should be the first priority of peace and
disarmament education.
These were two of the major points that
emerged from a recent International Con¬
sultation on ways of improving higher educa¬
tion in the field of peace and respect for hu¬
man rights and the rights of peoples. Orga¬
nized by Unesco and the Greek National
Commission for Unesco, the meeting was
held in Athens from 20 to 24 January 1986,
and was attended by leading scientists, spe¬
cialists in the social and human sciences and
in higher education from 17 countries of
Unesco's European region, Latin America,
Africa, the Arab Region and Asia.
The participants, among whom was Profes¬
sor Bernard Lown (Nobel Peace Prize 1985;
see article opposite page), described experi¬
ences in their countries and exchanged views
on ways of informing students about problems
relating to peace. They discussed how to
teach about the dangers of a nuclear war, the
arms race, and military uses of science and
technology, as well as how to increase the
role that students, future researchers and de¬
cision-makers should play in finding solutions
to problems in these areas. .
It was pointed out that the risks of nuclear
war and the consequences of the arms race
extend to the developing world: some Third
World countries already have nuclear
weapons, while others are afraid of countries
which possess them. At the same time there
have been many wars since 1945 using con¬
ventional weapons, and the prevention of
such wars and the constant violations of hu¬
man rights should also remain priority areas.
The reduction of military arsenals is a pre¬
requisite for economic and social develop¬
ment for mankind as a whole and especially
for Third World countries.
Stressing the urgent need for radical im¬
provements in higher education on these
issues, participants made a number of sug¬
gestions about the general approach, aims,
content and forms of international education.
Among their recommendations were:
promoting the introduction of a global
approach based on the ideas of international
understanding, tolerance and solidarity
among peoples and countries, and on respect
for cultural diversity;
developing an educational strategy which
would integrate education for peace, respect
for human rights and the rights of peoples into
development education;
basing international education on a scien¬
tific approach;
including among the aims of international
education the prevention of a nuclear catas¬
trophe, the prevention of conventional wars
and the violation of human rights;
promoting the idea of a united front of
people to face the unprecedented threat of a
nuclear catastrophe in order to ensure the
survival of human civilization;
resisting the development of ideological
and psychological stereotypes dehumanizing
other peoples;
improving communications between scien¬
tists and politicians;
introducing problems related to the New
International Economic Order, underdevelop¬
ment, poverty, imperialism and neo-col-
onialism;
extending programmes of peace and hu¬
man rights education to military academies;
promoting the establishment of "linked
schools and universities" from different coun¬
tries in order to strengthen international
understanding;
establishing in universities and higher
education institutions an oath on graduation
for young scientists and engineers in which to
draw their attention to the ethical and human
consequences of scientific research and tech¬
nological achievements.
Teachers often lack documentary material
and other teaching aids to help them intro¬
duce their students to internationalaffairs.
To fill this gap, the United Nations and
Unesco's Associated Schools Project
have prepared a practical handbook,
World Concerns and the United Nations,
for primary- and secondary-school
teachers. The handbook, published In
English, French and Spanish, contains
model teaching units on subjects such as
peace and disarmament, human rights,
racism, development, the environment,
and cultural diversity, as well as advice to
help teachers plan stimulating lessons
which can be integrated into traditional
history, geography, science, languages
and even mathematics courses. Painting
right by a 12-year-old Romanian girl,
Adriana Moisln, illustrates a model
teaching unit on the theme of different
perceptions of the world.
.oi«;;*' I
BS
*^v;'í'.~JÍ' - !?a
_ - -i-
Z&SS&.
Il ¡%;tó
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Physicians and the nuclear
threat
by Bernard Lown
IN December 1980, six physicians, three
from the Soviet Union and three from
the United States, met in Geneva to
establish the International Physicians for
the Prevention of Nuclear War (IPPNW),
and in December 1985 we travelled to Oslo
to receive the Nobel Peace Prize.
I believe that this extraordinary achieve¬
ment and recognition relates to the cogency
and the urgency of the issue being ad¬
dressed by these physicians. It is also due to
the fact, as the Nobel Committee pointed
out, that the IPPNW has been "spreading
authoritative information by creating an
awareness of the catastrophic consequences
of atomic warfare".
We have resisted being sidetracked onto
other issues, no matter how morally com¬
pelling. Combating the nuclear threat has
been our exclusive preoccupation, since we
are dedicated to the proposition that to
ensure the conditions of life we must pre¬
vent the conditions of death. Ultimately, we
believe people must come to terms with the
fact that the struggle is not between diffe¬
rent national destinies or between opposing
ideologies, but rather between catastrophe
and survival. All nations share a linked
destiny nuclear weapons are their com¬
mon enemy.
IPPNW has emphasized a number of cri¬
tical conclusions.
Firstly, that no public health hazard ever
faced by humankind equals the threat of
nuclear war. Never before has man posses¬
sed the destructive resources to make this
planet uninhabitable.
Secondly, that modern medicine has no¬
thing to offer, not even a token benefit, in
the event of nuclear war.
Thirdly, while no national interest would
justify nuclear war, sober appraisals suggest
that we have created a technology which is
increasingly out of human control. Ulti¬
mately the bomb, the robot and the compu¬
ter pre-empt man's decision-making role
and take command.
Fourthly, even if war is prevented, the
arms race is exacting an enormous econo¬
mic, psychological and moral toll.
The current global economic crisis results
The officialposter of the International Year
ofPeace, showing the face ofa youth with,
superimposed, the faces of men, women
and children from all over the world. De¬
signed by the American artist Neil Wald-
man, it won first prize in the International
Year of Peace poster competition orga¬
nized by the United Nations.
largely from the mortgaging of scarce world
resources to the military. One might use the
metaphor of a metronome. Listen to a met¬
ronome set at a rate of sixty beats per
minute, imagine the sound of a pulse every
second. Every two seconds the pulse con¬
veys the message that a child has died of a
disease that could have been prevented by
immunization, by providing adequate food
and a safe water supply. With each in¬
tervening beat of the metronome, also
every two seconds, a child is permanently
crippled physically or mentally by a pre¬
ventable illness and is destined to live the
rest of its life with severe disability. Thus,
with each beat of the metronome, a child is
either killed or maimed byta preventable
affliction: 120,000 children, *the same num¬
ber of victims claimed by the first atomic
bomb, are dying every three days.
With each second's pulse, the metro¬
nome proclaims another message, a mes¬
sage of waste. Each beat conveys the spend
ing every second of $25,000 on arms; $1.5
million every minute.
Compounding the tragedy is the fact that
even a small transfer of the funds being
spent on arms to health and social needs
would result in extraordinary permanent,
long-lasting benefit, serving all of human¬
kind . Three hours of world arms spending is
equivalent to the total cost of the twenty-
year campaign to eradicate smallpox, one of
the great achievements of twentieth-cen¬
tury medicine. Half a day of world arms
spending would pay for the full immuniza¬
tion of children against common infectious
disease that now claims 3.5 million lives
annually. Four days of world arms spending
would pay for five years of a malaria control
programme, addressing what is probably
the world's greatest cause of morbidity. Six
months of world arms spending would pay
for a twenty-year programme providing
essential food and health needs in all the
developing countries.
As you listen to the metaphorical metro¬
nome pulsing at one beat every second, it
conveys a third message, that of the extra¬
ordinary danger in which the world finds
itself. Nuclear weapon stockpiles are now
equivalent to 16,000 million tons of TNT. If
each metronome beat represents the explo¬
sion of a ton of dynamite, the din of explo¬
sions would be continuously heard for 500
years.
For a cardiologist, the metronome con¬
veys a fourth message. It evokes the beating
of the human heart. We must ask ourselves
whether we will let the heartbeat of human¬
ity stop, or struggle to make certain that it
pulses for an eternity to come.
BERNARD LOWN, of the USA, is professor of
cardiology at the Harvard School of Public
Health. With Academician Evgeny Chazov of the
USSR, he is co-president of International Physi¬
cians for the Prevention of Nuclear War
(IPPNW), which was awarded the 1984 Unesco
Prize for Peace Education and the 1985 Nobel
Peace Prize. The article published here consists
of extracts from Prof. Lown's address to a
Unesco International Consultation on higher
education and problems relating to peace, held
in Athens in January 1986 (see opposite page).
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
','
Unesco
and the International
Year ofPeace
UNESCO'S activities during the Interna¬
tional Year of Peace form part of a
continuing effort which began forty
years ago. The Preamble to Unesco's Consti¬
tution, adopted on 16 November 1945,
pledges the Organization to advance,
"through the educational and scientific and
cultural relations of the peoples of the world,
the objectives of international peace and of
m m m m rr? m m
*%
n 3H
-1
SïU T+ï TTÏ f+ï Bï BT UT
ISiiiil
% t
a si mm m § t
©
First awarded in 1981, the annual Unesco
Prize for Peace Education was created to
reward outstanding examples of "activity
designed to alert public opinion and
mobilize the conscience of mankind in the
cause of peace". In 1985 the Prize went
jointly to General IndarJit Rikhye, of India,
President of the International Peace
Academy, and to the Georg-Eckert Insti¬
tute for International Textbook Research
(Fed. Rep. of Germany). The Institute
works forpeace by seeking to identify and
eliminate from textbooks factual errors,
prejudices and stereotyped ideas about
peoples, In order to encourage pupils'
readiness to understand and appreciate
different cultural systems. Its headquar¬
ters are In the Villa von Biilow, above, a
masterpiece of classical architecture
made available by the municipality of
Braunschweig.
the common welfare of mankind for which the
United Nations Organization was estab¬
lished", and states that "peace must therefore
be founded, if it is not to fail, upon the intellec¬
tual and moral solidarity of mankind".
Unesco's commitment to "international
peace" and "the common welfare of mankind"
is in a sense the keystone of all its work and
permeates every one of its activities without
exception, whether in education, science, cul¬
ture or communication. Its approach to these
issues is based on the conviction that they
cannot be dissociated from the wider canvas
of interrelated contemporary problems which
must be tackled globally by the international
community. More specifically, Unesco's
efforts to achieve and preserve peace are
today embodied in a wide range of pro¬
grammes relating to international understand¬
ing, human rights and the rights of peoples,
and to the elimination of prejudice, intoler¬
ance, racism and apartheid.
First of all, Unesco has sought to define the
very meaning of the word peace. A resolution
adopted at the 18th Session of Unesco's
General Conference in 1974 stressed that
peace "cannot consist solely in the absence of
armed conflict but implies principally a pro¬
cess of development, justice and mutual re¬
spect among peoples designed to secure the
building of an international society in which
everyone can find his true place and enjoy his
share of the world's intellectual and material
resources".
Two years later, at its 19th Session, the
General Conference went further, adopting a
resolution on "The Role of Unesco in Gener¬
ating a Climate of Public Opinion Conducive
to the Halting of the Arms Race and the Tran¬
sition to Disarmament". This resolution re¬
flected the conviction that disarmament would
make it possible to redistribute vast material
and intellectual resources for social and eco¬
nomic development and help to prepare the
ground for equitable political and economic
relations between the countries of the world.
In April 1978 Unesco organized an expert
meeting on "The Obstacles to Disarmament
and the Ways of Overcoming Them", as part
of its preparations for the United Nations First
Special Session on Disarmament held in the
I
At the end of the Second World War,
Unesco launched a majorproject aimed at
the elimination of racism, discrimination,
prejudice and tensions and the promotion
of international understanding. The need
for such a plan is no less urgent today.
Unesco's efforts are directed to analysing
and exposing the mechanisms of pre¬
judice, intolerance and racism as a first
step to mobilizing its own forces and those
of people everywhere against these phe¬
nomena and their most brutal manifesta¬
tion, apartheid. Above: "Their rightto
share a future without war" is the message
of this anti-apartheid poster from South
Africa.
same year. Participants stressed that the pur¬
pose of disarmament education was to pro¬
mote the goal of general and complete dis¬
armament, and recommended the holding of
a world congress to propose measures aimed
at the establishment of specialized education
in favour of disarmament.
This World Congress on Disarmament..
Education was duly organized by Unesco and
held in June 1 980, in Paris. Some'250 partici¬
pants and observers from all over the world
attended. The Congress set forth a number of
guidelines for an action plan to cover the
Second Disarmament Decade of the United
Nations, ending in 1989, and defined a series
of principles relating to disarmament educa¬
tion as an essential component of peace edu¬
cation. Unesco was asked to produce a
Teacher's Handbook on Disarmament
Education designed for secondary schools.
This book, now in preparation, gives a de¬
tailed presentation of the links between dis¬
armament and development education.
Unesco followed up the World Congress on
Disarmament Education by convening a
series of expert meetings and training semi¬
nars for teachers devoted to practical ques¬
tions of teaching about disarmament issues in
their relationship with peace; strengthening
international understanding and security; de-
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
WiW.W . n
The aim set forth In Unesco's Constitution
of "advancing ... the objectives of interna¬
tional peace and the common welfare of
mankind...." can never be achieved with¬
out a mobilization of world public opinion
in a united struggle against the continua¬
tion of the arms race, especially in the field
of nuclear -veapons. Above, peace march
in Romania.
Unesco encourages physical education
and sport as a means of bringing peoples
closer together on the basis of respect,
mutual understanding and disinterested
competition. It also honours the spirit of
sportsmanship through its long associa¬
tion with the International Pierre de
Coubertin Fair Play Trophy, first awarded
in 1965. Unesco is currently examining the
origins and forms of violence in sports
activities in a study which will focus on the
social and educational aspects of this
complex problem, as well as remedial
action. Photo of thejubilantjudoka, above,
featured in an international exhibition on
the theme of "Youth In the 1980s", orga¬
nized by Unesco on the occasion of Inter¬
national Youth Year (1985).
Article 10 of the Declaration of the Rights
of the Child adopted by the General
Assembly of the United Nations on 20
November 1959 stipulates that the child
"... shall be brought up in a spirit of under¬
standing, tolerance, friendship among
peoples, peace and universal
brotherhood. ..." Today there is a growing
awareness that in order to encourage this
spirit among young people all over the
world, action is called for at the earliest
possible age, during the years when a
child's fundamental outlook andpersonal¬
ity are formed. Unesco has encouraged
this interest in education for peace at pre¬
school age and in 1985 published Seeds
for Peace, a booklet presenting recent ex¬
periences in this field in the family context
and elsewhere. Photo showing 3 genera¬
tions of one family is an illustration from
the booklet.
velopment; a new international economic
order; respect for human rights and the rights
of peoples.
The Organization has also sponsored
meetings on the role of the media in increas¬
ing public awareness of the links between
disarmament and development. One such
meeting, held in Paris in November 1982,
examined different perceptions of threat and
conceptions of security. A study on "Media
Contribution to Worldwide Security and
Peace", carried out in 1984-85 in co-opera¬
tion with the International Social Science
Council, analysed among other topics cover¬
age of war and peace issues, effects of style,
vocabulary, and negative stereotypes.
Acknowledging the crucial role played by
science and technology in the debate on
peace, disarmament and development, Un¬
esco organized a joint symposium with the
Pugwash Conferences on Science and World
Affairs on the theme of "Scientists, the Arms
Race and Disarmament" in Ajaccio, France,
in February 1982. The Organization con¬
tinues to sponsor scientific research projects
and meetings such as the International Con¬
sultation on higher education, peace and re¬
spect for human rights and the rights of peo¬
ples held in Athens in January 1 986 (see page
18).
In 1980 a Unesco Prize for Peace Educa¬
tion was established to promote all forms of
action designed to "construct the defences of
peace in the minds of men". The annual prize,
worth $60,000, is financed by the interest from
a $1 million donation from the Japan Ship¬
building Industry Foundation. Among the
prizewinners are Evgeny Chazov of the
Soviet Union and Bernard Lown of the United
States, who jointly accepted the 1 984 award
on behalf of International Physicians for the
Prevention of Nuclear War (see page 19).
In the domain of culture, Unesco's pro¬
gramme is based on the conviction that de¬
velopment and peace are preconditions of the
cultural fulfilment of societies and individuals.
In this context Unesco has concentrated on
safeguarding the cultural heritage, streng¬
thening cultural identities and ¡ntercultural re¬
lations, promoting creativity and artistic
creation, and work in the field of cultural de¬
velopment and cultural policies. An interna¬
tional symposium currently being prepared on
the role of cultural workers and artists in work
for peace will "analyse ways in which co¬
ordinated action could be taken to place their
works, their creations and their talents in the
service of peace".
Of the fourteen Major Programmes featur¬
ing in Unesco's Second Medium-term Plan ^
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
À*&*
Unesco's cultural programme is based on
its constitutional obligation "to contribute
to peace and security" bypromoting inter¬
national collaboration through culture.
This basic tenet is defined in more specific
terms in the Declaration of the principles
of international cultural co-operation
(1966) which declares that "Cultural co¬
operation shall contribute to the establish¬
ment of stable, long-term relations be¬
tween peoples, which should be subjected
as little as possible to the strains which
may arise in international life". In this field
Unesco is today engaged in a broadprog¬
ramme of activities to protect the cultural
heritage, strengthen cultural Identity and
relations between cultures, encourage
creativity, and support Member States In
promoting cultural development. (1) A gor-
gon's head in the forum of Septimius
Sevetus at the ancient cityofLeptis Magna
(Libyan Arab Jamahiriya), which features
on the World Heritage List of cultural and
natural properties of outstanding univer¬
sal value. The List, which Unesco has
drawn up through the World Heritage
Committee, today includes 216 sites (27 In
Africa, 34 in the Arab States, 30 in Asia and
the Pacific, 25 in Latin America and the
Caribbean, and 100 in Europe and North
America) which enjoy special protective
measures both from the States in which
theyare locatedand from the international
community. (2) The inner courtyard of a
traditional house at Oualata, Mauritania.
(3) A staffmember of the National Museum
of Mall explains to a French boy how to
play the balaphon, a West African
xylophone, during a study tour in France
as part of the Museum's staff training
programme.
S
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
©
On a number of occasions, Unesco's
General Conference has drawn attention
to the links between peace, disarmament
and development education on the one
hand, and human rights education on the
other, considering notably that education
concerning human rights "Is capable of
making an essential contribution to the
maintenance and promotion of peace as
well as to economic development and so¬
cial progress in the world". Cartoons and
games were devised as part of one recent
Unesco-sponsored project to create hu¬
man rights teaching materials adapted to
the needs and interests ofyoungpeople in
Thailand. The project, carried out by the
Faculty of Law, Chulalongkorn University,
Bangkok, focused largely on child pros¬
titution and human rights and child labour
and human rights. Left, cover of a set of
cartoons produced as part of the project.
^ (1984-1989), No. XIII, "Peace, International
Understanding, Human Rights and the Rights
of Peoples", includes the commitment to
maintain peace and international understand¬
ing, through studying the causes and the con¬
sequences of the arms race and the condi¬
tions favourable to disarmament.
The Plan highlights the responsibility of
education in creating awareness of the inter¬
dependence of global problems, particularly
between peace, the halting of the arms race,
disarmament, respect for human rights and
the rights of peoples, the elimination of col¬
onialism, racism and apartheid, and develop¬
ment. The international educational strategy
established as part of the Medium-term Plan
seeks to develop a climate of opinion condu¬
cive to the transition to disarmament, "by
providing support for youth activities, and by
encouraging young people to think and act in
support of peace, disarmament, respect for
human rights and the rights of peoples".
Today, Unesco's normative, educational
and informational activities relating to dis¬
armament and development can be
approached from four different angles.
The arms race creates a huge burden on
national economies and on societies' re¬
sources. Defence budgets can be seen to be
inflationary in industrialized countries, and a
source of external debts in the Third World.
The present international order, the nature
of societies and of political regimes, especial¬
ly their form of economic growth, are basic
factors in the continuation of the arms race.
The third approach explores future possi¬
ble alternatives to the present relationship
between disarmament and development, in¬
cluding the creation of an international fund to
administer the resources which could be
transferred to development, and the conver¬
sion of the arms industry to civilian activities.
The fourth approach advocates a new form
of international co-operation, emerging from
research into present forms of national and
international relations which generate least
tension, with the aim of creating a favourable
context for eventual disarmament. Such a
new international order implies the rejection of
conventional models of growth and moderni- 1
c
I
As part of its major programme "Commu¬
nication in the service of man", Unesco
has prepared, in collaboration with the
French Ministry of Education, a booklet
entitled Des médias pour la paix et les
hommes (The media for peace and man¬
kind). The booklet is a presentation, writ¬
ten for young people aged between 9 and
17, of the 1978 Unesco Declaration on fun¬
damental principles concerning the con¬
tribution of the mass media to strengthen¬
ing peace and international understand¬
ing, to the promotion of human rights and
to countering racialism, apartheid and in¬
citement to war. It will be distributed in
co-operation with the World Federation of
Unesco Clubs and other non-governmen¬
tal organizations. Before publication, a
draft of the booklet was sent to 1,500
young people, some of whom created
posters inspired by its contents. Above,
poster by a group of pupils at a school in
Mompiano, Italy. Left, an Illustration from
the booklet, which will also be published
eventually In English and Spanish.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
zation, especially those imposed on develop¬
ing countries.
Finally, Unesco's publishing programme
also plays an important part in disarmament-
related activities. Relevant works include the
Unesco Yearbook on Peace and Conflict Stu¬
dies (published since 1980); World Directory
of Peace Research Institutions (5th edition,
1984); Obstacles to Disarmament and Ways
of Overcoming Them (1981); and Arm¬
aments, Arms Control and Disarmament; a
Unesco Reader for Disarmament Education
(1982). Other studies and publications which
seek to further knowledge and appreciation of
cultural values and mutual understanding
among peoples, include the History of Man¬
kind: Cultural and Scientific Development, a
new edition of which is currently being pre¬
pared, and the eight-volume General History
ofAfrica now in course of publication.
Two Moons, a poster designed by the Ja¬
panese master Kaii Higashiyama to mark
International Year of Peace (1986). The re¬
sult of collaboration between Unesco, the
Japanese Federation of Unesco Associa¬
tions and the International Association of
Art, the poster shows the moon, symbol of
truth in Asian tradition, reflected in peace¬
ful waters.
année internationale de la paix
Unesco 1986
World military spending: over $1.5 million a minute
In the developing world, 800 million people
live in absolute poverty and deprivation. 500
million are malnourished. Many millions have
no access to safe drinking-water and do not
have the income necessary to purchase food.
It has been estimated that there are more than
50,000 nuclear warheads in the world. The
total explosive power of the world stock of
nuclear weapons is about equal to one mil¬
lion times that of the Hiroshima bomb, which
had a yield of 13 kilotons. (A kiloton is equal
to 1,000 tons of conventional high explosive
or TNT; a megaton is equal to 1,000,000 tons
of TNT.)
According to a recent United Nations study
on conventional disarmament, the world
arsenal of conventional weapons includes
well over 140,000 main battle tanks, over
35,000 combat aircraft, over 21,000 helicop¬
ters, over 1 ,1 00 major surface warships, plus
more than 700 attack submarines. Approx¬
imately four fifths of the total world military
expenditure is estimated to be devoted to
conventional weapons and armed forces.
It has been estimated that some 1 50 conflicts
fought with conventional weapons have
occurred since the Second World War. It is
impossible to determine with any accuracy
the death toll arising from these conflicts. A
recent United Nations study on conventional
disarmament, however, gives an estimate of
20 million deaths.
Military expenditures represent a significant
share of the public finances of developed and
developing countries. In both cases, they
come to represent an average of some 20 per
cent of governmental expenditures. Accord¬
ing to some estimates, in the developed
countries military spending is about equal to
public expenditure on education or health; in
the developing countries it equals three
times the public expenditure on health and is
a third more than the public expenditure on
education.
Worldwide military expenditures in 1983
amounted to some $800,000 million, accord¬
ing to the most reliable estimates available,
which is the equivalent of more than $1.5
million per minute. In constant prices, this is
more than double the expenditures for 1960
and almost four times those for 1 949. At this
rate it takes just 15 days and 15 hours for
world military expenditure to reach the
$34,300 million spent in the whole of 1 983 for
all official development assistance for all de¬
veloping countries. A recent United Nations
study emphasized that, if recent trends
should persist, the world military expendi¬
ture could reach or exceed $1 ,000,000 million
a year, in current dollars, well before 1990.
Developed countries spent 20 times as much
on military expenditures as they provide for
economic aid.
70 per cent of world military spending is by
the six major military powers, 15 per cent by
other industrialized countries, and the re¬
maining 1 5 per cent by developing countries.
$1 ,000 million dollars =28,000 jobs in military
goods and services, or 57,000 jobs in person¬
al consumption industries, or 71,000 jobs in
education.
For every soldier the average world military
expenditure is $20,000. For every school-age
child the average public education expendi¬
ture is $380.
For every 100,000 people in the world there
are 556 soldiers, but only 85 doctors.
Just one fifth of annual arms expenditures
could abolish world hunger by the year 2000.
Source: United Nations
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The United Nations
World
Disarmament
Campaign
by Jan Martenson
THE World Disarmament Campaign
to inform, to educate and to gener¬
ate public understanding and sup¬
port for the objectives of the United Na¬
tions in the field of arms limitation and
disarmament represents a unique aspect of
the role of the United Nations. As an inter¬
national organization consisting of
sovereign States, the United Nations essen¬
tially deals with member governments. In
deciding to launch a world disarmament
campaign, these member governments
have provided the United Nations with an
instrument of communication with the pub¬
lic at large.
The Campaign was launched, by consen¬
sus, in June 1982 at the Twelfth Special
Session of the General Assembly devoted
to disarmament. By the time it was in¬
itiated, the process of negotiating disarma¬
ment had acquired a great complexity with
regard to the issues under consideration,
the results attained, and the status of agree¬
ments actually arrived at. At the same time,
The United Nations Postal Administration
issued a series of six stamps on 20 June
1986 to commemorate the International
Year of Peace. Designed by artists from
various countries, the stamps depict sym¬
bolic motifs (from top to bottom): doves
flying and nesting in a tree (Akira Iriguchi,
Japan); the word "peace" in several lan¬
guages encircling the United Nations
emblem (Henryk Chylinski, Poland); multi¬
coloured stylized dove (Renato Ferrini,
Italy); the word "peace" and an olive
branch (Salahattin Kanldinc, USA); olive
branch describing a rainbow above the
curve of the earth (Milo Schor, Israel);
doves within the United Nations emblem
(Mohammad Sardar, Pakistan).
there was a growing public debate over the
causes and consequences of a continuing
arms race and the problems and prospects
of disarmament, particularly of nuclear dis¬
armament. While the themes highlighted in
this debate continued to bear the imprint of
regional and local concerns, there was also
an increasing trend towards greater interna¬
tional interaction, a process facilitated by
the availability of modern means of com¬
munication which permit wide public parti¬
cipation.
United Nations objectives in the field of
arms limitation and disarmament underline
commonly shared goals which transcend
national, geographical and political dif¬
ferences'. As evolved in response to the
changing international situation, these
objectives could be attained through a
lowering of the present levels of military
build-ups in a balanced and verifiable man¬
ner and in accordance with the need for
undiminished security for all States, large
and small. Also, in a world of increasing
interdependence, not only States but issues
are becoming interlinked. As such, the
themes supported by the World Disarma¬
ment Campaign are those which emphasize
our common human destiny.
The most comprehensive statement of
United Nations objectives in this field is
given in the unanimously adopted Final
Document of the Tenth Special Session of
the General Assembly devoted to dis¬
armament: "while the efforts of all States
should continue to be general and complete
disarmament under effective international
control, the immediate goal is that of the
elimination of the danger of nuclear war
and the implementation of measures to halt
and reverse the arms race and clear the path
towards lasting peace."
These issues have been the subject of
considerable public interest in all regions of
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
the world. In providing objective, factual
and balanced information pertaining to
these questions, the Campaign primarily
relies upon the priorities and measures set
out in the Final Document; the decisions
taken at the Twelfth Special Session of the
General Assembly devoted to dis¬
armament; the views expressed by Member
States; the recommendations in the declara¬
tion of the 1980s as the Second Disarma¬
ment Decade; and the unanimous conclu¬
sions of the various expert groups nomin¬
ated by the Secretary-General to study spe¬
cific aspects of arms limitation and dis¬
armament. Within this broad framework,
the Campaign places emphasis on the in¬
teraction between the issues of disarma¬
ment and international security as well as
disarmament and development.
In order to reach the largest number of
people in all parts of the world, a consti¬
tuency-related approach is required. Such
constituencies lead to a multiplier effect in
educating, informing and generating public
understanding and support for the objec¬
tives of the United Nations in the field of
arms limitation and disarmament, where
the issues involved are often complex and
need to be explained in an easily compre¬
hensible manner.
Elected representatives, media, non-gov¬
ernmental organizations, educational com¬
munities and research institutes from diffe¬
rent political and geographical backgrounds
are thus the primary constituencies of the
World Disarmament Campaign, which en¬
courages bilateral and multilateral ex¬
changes, interpersonal communications,
and gives the widest possible dissemination
to contacts, for example, between
government officials, experts, academics,
non-governmental organizations and
journalists.
Having been entrusted with the responsi¬
bility of carrying out this Campaign on a
universal basis in a factual, objective and
balanced manner, the Department for Dis¬
armament Affairs realizes that the Cam¬
paign is a vehicle not only for informing but
also for learning/1* Our experience in the
last four years of preparing and distributing
information materials and organizing con¬
ferences, symposia and other activities in
different parts of the world has led us to the
unmistakable conclusion that, cutting
across ideological and political boundaries,
there is a universal constituency for dis¬
armament bound by concern for human
survival and well-being in the nuclear age.
Within this growing and increasingly know¬
ledgeable community, each of the primary
constituencies of the World Disarmament
Campaign has a role to play.
At this point, two observations should be
made.
First, it is unrealistic to expect disarma¬
ment to be achieved overnight. After all,
concern about security and otir resort to
some form of weaponry to achieve that end
is as old as the human race, whereas the
process of bringing about mutually accept¬
able disarmament agreements among
sovereign States is a rather recent concept.
Yet at the same time human rationality
inspires us not to accept defeat in the face of
a formidable challenge. I, for one, believe
that it is well within the reach of the human
intellect to turn a challenge to the survival
of mankind into an opportunity for human
betterment. The same ingenuity which has
produced deadly arsenals of destruction
might indeed become capable of using sci¬
ence and technology for peaceful purposes.
We need to accept the notion of common
survival in the nuclear age and thus the
indivisibility of mankind's destiny.
Second, the World Disarmament Cam¬
paign is an instrument which the interna¬
tional community has unanimously and
voluntarily devised to further its common
objectives in the field of arms limitation and
disarmament. The full potential of this
unique endeavour can be realized only
through ensuring the principles of univer¬
sality and objectivity. Unimpeded access to
a wide range of information for all sectors of
the public is a necessary condition for the
creation of the confidence and trust badly
needed to generate widespread support for
halting and eventually reversing the arms
race.
The programmes and activities under¬
taken for the World Disarmament Cam¬
paign have reached hundreds of thousands
of people in all parts of the globe through
the dissemination of information materials
and publications, the holding of regional
conferences and seminars, as well as
through the media and personal contacts. In
the last few years, such regional events have
been organized in Mexico, Kenya,
Thailand, Romania, India, Venezuela,
USSR, Egypt, Sweden, Togo, Italy and, in
May 1986, Tbilisi (Georgian SSR).
Leading representatives of non-gov¬
ernmental organizations, media, research
institutes and educational communities are
invited from various countries within a re¬
gion to participate in the discussions on
disarmament issues of specific and general
concern. The objective of these confer¬
ences is not to apportion blame or to issue
communiqués, but to facilitate a construc¬
tive exchange of views and opinion, to im¬
prove dialogue and thus further under¬
standing and communication among people
throughout the world on issues of arms
limitation and disarmament. Indeed, a well-
informed public opinion stands a much bet¬
ter chance of playing a positive, construc¬
tive and realistic role in the search for solu¬
tions to these issues.
All these contacts, in turn, have made it
possible for the United Nations to ascertain
the impact of the Campaign. Growing num¬
bers of people have manifested their in¬
terest in disarmament matters, while better
understanding the complex realities of the
arms race, on the one hand, and the difficul¬
ties surrounding the issues, on the other.
The impact made so far can perhaps be
assessed at several levels, one of them being
the generation of new ideas. As the Secre¬
tary-General of the United Nations has
said: "All the speeches made there (in the
United Nations), all the information emerg¬
ing .therefrom, all the studies undertaken
there, perhaps have no immediate effect on
national policies, although very often they
provide inspiration. But they definitely do
influence world public opinion and contri¬
bute to the way in which thinking and mor¬
als evolve. And it is ideas which transform
the world."
JAN MARTENSON, of Sweden, has been
Under-Secretary-General, Department for Dis¬
armament Affairs, at the United Nations since
1983. He was previously UN Assistant Secret¬
ary-General, Centre for Disarmament, Depart¬
ment of Political and Security Council Affairs
(1979-1982). A former head of the Information
Department of the Swedish Ministry for Foreign
Affairs, he has also served as Deputy Director of
the Stockholm International Peace Research
Institute.
(1) A detailed description of the Department's activities
can be found in the yearly report of the Secretary-
General on the activities of the World Disarmament
Campaign, which can be obtained by writing to The
Department for Disarmament Affairs, United Nations,
New York 10017, USA. The Department also publishes
a newsletter with updated information on the activities
of the Campaign throughout the world.
The University for Peace
The University for Peace, the creation of
which was approved by the UN General
Assembly on 5 December 1980, is an interna¬
tional institution located In Costa Rica. For¬
mally outside the organizational framework
of the United Nations, it is established on the
basis of an international agreement and a
charter which came into force on 7 April 1 981 .
Its activities, devoted to the promotion of
peace through education and research, are
rooted in the principles of the Charter of the
United Nations and the Universal Declaration
of Human Rights.
The University is a multidisciplinar
academic institution which focuses on
education for peace and human rights perse
but also studies problems related to the en¬
vironment, natural resources, technology,
communications and other Issues in terms of
their impact on the attainment of peace.
Tapio Varis (Finland)
Rector of the University for Peace
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Towards a new way
of thinking
by Gennadi Ivanovitch Gerasimov OVER thirty years ago, Bertrand Russell
and Albert Einstein invited us to
"learn to think in a new way" and
pointed out that "if the issues between East
and West are to be decided ... then these
issues must not be decided by war". In what
became known as the Russell-Einstein Man¬
ifesto (see article page 13), the two philo-
1 sophers suggested that people should regard
^ themselves primarily as members of the hu-
1 man race, whether they be workers, shop-
% keepers, farmers, or property-owners on a
8 large or small scale: "Consider yourselves
@ only as members of a biological species."
§ Looking more deeply into the question, I
| discovered that Russell and Einstein were by
5 no means the first to put forward such views,
§ although they had extremely cogent reasons
£ for doing so at that time. As long ago as 1 928,
the French novelist Romain Rolland called for
the creation of a Peace International, which
would discount all the "political, social, re¬
ligious, philosophical and intellectual pre¬
occupations" which divide mankind, and
would be exclusively guided by a "clear and
direct awareness of the community of all living
beings".
Rolland was sickened by the lunacy of
trench warfare, which had systematized
butchery. Russell and Einstein were anxious
about the new danger represented by the
atomic bomb which indiscriminately mas¬
sacred the population at large as well as the
armed forces. Today, three decades later, the
dangers far exceed those which they de¬
nounced, and their message has acquired a
new dimension, especially with the establish¬
ment of the now well-documented hypothesis
of "nuclear winter" as the inevitable outcome
of a nuclear conflict.
Before the "nuclear winter" theory,
armchair strategists speculated at great
length about the stages of nuclear escalation,
about second strike capabilities and the pos¬
sibility, under certain conditions, of prevailing
over the enemy in a nuclear exchange. To
encourage plans for a "lightning" war to
amputate the political and military leadership
of an enemy power, a war unleashed from
behind an antimissile shield capable of ward¬
ing off a counter-attack from a weakened
adversary, is to foster a dangerous illusion. It
is now clear that the dust, soot and ash from
many nuclear explosions will obliterate the
"victor's" sun. Whoever lifts his sword will also
die by it. Does this not encourage us to "think
in a new way"?
This 2nd-century statue of Clio, the first of
the nine Muses of Greek mythology, was
discovered in 1774 in the ruins of a villa
south-east of Tivoli, a favourite summer
resort of the Romans 2, 000years ago. Clio,
whose name means "to celebrate" in
Greek, is the Muse of epic poetry and of
history. She is often depictedseated, hold¬
ing a roll of parchment in her hand.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
The nuclear threat has taken on the dimen¬
sion of "cliocide" a word coined from Clio,
the Greek Muse whose task was to watch
over the course of human history. Today his¬
tory faces the risk of sudden termination, as
war, which formerly menaced only indi¬
viduals, now threatens the whole human
species.
Nuclear weapons sweep away the moral
problem of ends and means, because any
attempt to achieve a given end by using such
weapons nullifies that end, by liquidating the
two parties to the conflict. It would be like
burning down a house while trying to carry out
repairs on it, or killing a man in order to alter a
mean streak in his character. Nor can nuclear
war stand up to cost-benefit analysis.
The nuclear weapon, a creation of the hu¬
man intellect, threatens to arrest the march of
history through some act of political folly. Just
as the great wars of the ancient world razed
cities, sometimes wiped out entire peoples,
after nuclear war the chronicle of human his¬
tory would be ended. In any case, there would
be nobody left to read it.
Just as we inherited this planet from our
forebears, we have a responsibility towards
In a Moscow square, young Muscovites
anda visiting group ofIndian children take
part in a drawing contest organized on
Universal Children's Day, celebrated
annually on the first Monday in October.
"Peace for children" and "May the sun
always shine" were two of the themes
treated by the budding pavement artists.
future generations, each of which must hand
on the heritage to their successors. In other
words, we are all bound to Clio by a solemn
oath which commands us to carry on the
history of mankind.
If we want to preserve peace, it should be
given absolute priority; the general interest
must be seen to override the interests of
specific groups or classes. According to
Lenin, from the point of view of basic Marxist
ideas, the interests of general development
come before the Interests of the proletariat,
because when the workers gain power it is
taken not for its own sake, but rather to deliver
society from exploitation, establish social
equality, and create the conditions necessary
for balanced development of individual char¬
acteristics.
Karl Marx saw a major transformation in the
relation between capital and labour as a
necessary condition of world peace. In his
inaugural address to the International Work¬
ing Men's Association in 1864, he stressed
the necessity of creating conditions in which
the elementary laws of morality and justice
which ought to govern individual relations
should also be supreme in international
relations.
Disarmament is the only possible route to
the establishment of a new and just interna¬
tional order of world security. Only disarma¬
ment will allow us to use the vast material and
intellectual resources thus freed to promote
economic development and prosperity.
Humanity has reached a crucial point and
must choose which direction to take. It can
overcome the inertia of the past and abandon
the notion of security as based on the balance
of power and on recourse to military or tech¬
nological solutions; or it can continue to be
hostage to the arms race to nuclear and
chemical weapons, and to others no less
fearsome.
This choice between the dictates of reason
and the road to catastrophe can only be made
by mutual agreement between all States,
whatever their social system or level of econo¬
mic development. It will have to be bold and
responsible. Today we can no longer be con¬
tent with piecemeal solutions which slow
down the arms race in certain spheres only to
accelerate it in others.
It is time to remove for ever the sword of
Damocles which has been hanging over our
heads since the tragedy of Hiroshima and
Nagasaki. It would be appropriate for the
Soviet Union and the United States, holders of
the largest nuclear stockpiles, to make a first
decisive step and for other nuclear powers to
follow them.
To encourage world opinion "to think in a
new way", is one of the main tasks of the
International Year of Peace. If United Nations
Member States, together with massed public
opinion, energetically support this effort, it
may help to prevent "cliocide".
GENNADI IVANOVITCH GERASIMOV, a well-
known Soviet journalist specializing in interna¬
tional relations, is currently chief editor of the
weekly Moscow News, which is published in
Russian, French, English, Spanish and Arabic.
He was awarded the Vorovski Prize (The Union
of Journalists of the USSR) and "The Golden
Pen" (Bulgaria) for his journalistic work.
»2
V 4L
-*e *
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
THIS story starts in 1945. A girl named
Sadako Sasaki was living in a
Japanese city called Hiroshima
along with about half a million other peo¬
ple. When she was two years old the first
atomic bomb ever to be used against human
beings was dropped on Hiroshima. Most of
the city was completely smashed and
burned to the ground. Sadako was about a
mile and a half away from where the bomb
exploded, but she wasn't burned or injured
at all, at least not in any way people could
see.
A few weeks after the bomb, people in
Hiroshima began dying from a sickness
even the doctors couldn't understand. Peo¬
ple who seemed perfectly healthy would
suddenly get weak and sick and then just
die. It was so strange and new that no one
knew what to do. In fact, even today no one
really knows exactly what radiation does or
what it might do to a particular person.
By the time Sadako was in seventh grade,
she was a normal, happy, twelve-year-old
girl going to a regular school and studying
and playing like everyone else. Ten years
had passed since the bomb and she was
thinking about other things. One of the
things she thought about most was running.
One day after an important relay race
that she helped her team win she felt ex¬
tremely tired and dizzy. After a while she
felt better, so she thought it was just that she
was so tired because of the race. Over the
next few weeks she tried to forget about it,
but the dizziness kept coming back, espe¬
cially when she was running. She didn't tell
anyone about it, not even Chizuko, her best
friend. Finally, one morning, it got so bad
that she fell down and just lay on the ground
for a while. This time everyone noticed.
They took her to the Red Cross hospital to
see what was the matter. No one could
believe what they found out. Sadako had
leukaemia, akind of cancerof the blood. At
that time quite a few children about Sada-
ko's age were getting leukaemia, which the
people then called "the A-bomb disease".
Almost everyone who got the disease died
and Sadako was very scared. She didn't
want to die.
Soon after Sadako went to the hospital
her best friend, Chizuko, came to visit her.
She brought some special paper and folded
a paper crane. Chizuko told Sadako about a
legend. She said that the crane, a sacred
bird in Japan, lives for a thousand years and
A thousand paper cranes
The article below is an extract from a booklet written and
published by pupils of Hiroshima International School,
Japan. It concerns the short life of a Japanese girl, who
contracted leukaemia through the after-effects of the atomic
bomb, and the children's club which was set up after her
death to work for peace. For further information about the
Club and its activities, please write to the Hiroshima Center
for Global Education, 2-6, 2-Chome, Ushita-naka, Higashi-
ku, Hiroshima-shi, 730 Japan.
if a sick person folds a thousand cranes, that
person will get well. Sadako decided to fold
a thousand cranes. Because of the
leukaemia she often felt too weak and tired
so she couldn't work all the time, but from
that day on, whenever she could, she folded
cranes.
Sadako actually folded her thousand
cranes, but she wasn't getting any better.
But instead of getting angry or giving up,
she decided she would fold more cranes.
She started on her second thousand. Every¬
one was amazed by how brave and patient
she was. On 25 October 1955, surrounded
by her loving family, she went to sleep
peacefully for the last time.
But this story doesn't end with Sadako's
death. She had a lot of friends who loved
her and who missed her very much. And
they didn't only feel sad about Sadako. Lots
of other children in Hiroshima had died or
were dying of the A-bomb disease. Her
friends wanted very much to do something
for Sadako. So thirty-nine of her classmates
formed a club and began asking for money
for a monument for her. The word spread
quickly. Students from 3,100 schools in
Japan and from nine other countries gave
money, and finally, on 5 May 1958, almost
three years after Sadako died, they got
enough money to build the monument. It's
called the Children's Peace Monument and
it is in the Peace Park which is in the middle
of Hiroshima right where the atomic bomb
was dropped.
The movement to build this monument
became so famous and popular that a movie
called "A Thousand Paper Cranes" was
made about it. About sixty children from
Hiroshima and about twenty children from
Tokyo helped to make the movie, and when
it was finished they wanted to stay together
as friends so they started a new club called
"The Paper Crane Club". The purpose of
this club was to help children get together to
think and work for peace. This club has
continued to exist for almost thirty years.
The members take care of Sadako's
monument, visit atomic bomb survivors,
people who were in Hiroshima when the
bomb was dropped, and who are getting
sick and old or who just need help for some
reason.
One other thing they always do is fold
cranes. They use the cranes in many ways.
Sometimes they hang them on Sadako's
monument and other monuments in
Hiroshima's Peace Park. Sometimes they
send them to world leaders as a way of
reminding those leaders that the children of
the world want to get rid of nuclear bombs.
And whenever world leaders or atomic
bomb survivors or people working for peace
come to Hiroshima, members of the Paper
Crane Club greet them and put a wreath of
cranes around their necks to welcome them
and to help them think about the meaning
of Hiroshima.
But the meaning of folding cranes, and
the meaning of Hiroshima and the Paper
Crane Club are perhaps best summed up in
the words carved on the granite base of the
Children's Peace Monument:
THIS IS OUR CRY
THIS IS OUR PRAYER
TO BUILD PEACE IN THIS WORLD
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Violence
in the Third World
by Soedjatmoko The present text is an abridged version of its author's con¬
tribution to a major forthcoming study on war as a human
institution. Entitled The Quest for Peace: Transcending Col¬
lective Violence and War among Societies, Cultures and
States, the study will be published later this year under the
auspices of the Unesco-supported International Social Sci¬
ence Council. This book, prepared as a contribution from the
social sciences to the United Nations International Year of
Peace, aims at a systematic and comprehensive presentation
of the latest knowledge from different social science disci¬
plines concerning the problems of war and peace.
'V
"Societies are beginning to come apart at
the seams as the despair, frustration and
rage of the 'have nots' clash with the
fear, reluctance or intransigence of the
'haves'." Below, rural South Africans.
'IOLENCE is a sign of institution¬
al failure and system overload,"
Professor Nazli Choucri has writ¬
ten. O These conditions are by no means
unique to the Third World, but it remains a
fact that the vast majority of wars and war¬
like incidents that have taken place since
the Second World War have been fought in
the Third World. Furthermore, the daily
turmoil and frictions of life under circum¬
stances of economic struggle and rapid so¬
cial change give rise to violence among
groups and individuals within Third World
societies.
I
H0C
"V. '
là
'vi W
^ ; L-,
*¿
?
ê
1
.
Despite their great diversity, the coun¬
tries of the Third World have some charac¬
teristics in common, apart from their loca¬
tion in Africa, Asia or Latin America, that
make possible some generalizations about
violence as they experience it. In the first
place, most developing countries share the
experience of colonial domination, though
the nature and duration of it vary
tremendously among them. Most of them
are poor. Perhaps most importantly, most
are engulfed in a process of very profound
social and economic transformation that,
though a necessary condition for develop¬
ment, is in itself a source of instability.
For many developing countries, one can
begin the search for the roots of violence
with the circumstances of decolonization.
For those countries that gained their inde¬
pendence by armed struggle, the fight for
independence gave a legitimacy to the use
of violence that still clings to it in many
settings. A further legacy of colonial rule is
the forced cohabitation within a single State
of antagonistic groups that are artificially
bound together within the borders estab¬
lished by the colonizers. In many instances
quarrels that were submerged but not re¬
solved during the colonial period have re-
emerged and, often, burst into violent con¬
flict after independence.
Poverty is not necessarily a cause of vio¬
lent conflict though many argue that it is
in itself a form of violence. If can be seen as
such when it is the product of maldistribu¬
tion of resources and denial of opportunity,
and exists in the midst of plenty or even
excess. Under these conditions, poverty is
usually the result of social and economic
relations that can only be maintained by the
threat or the use of violence. One major
feature of recent decades has been the
growing self-assertiveness of poor and tra¬
ditionally powerless groups. In some cases,
groups of people have managed to move up
the economic ladder, though many have
met with violent resistance on the way.
However, it is not poverty but the attempt
(1) Nazli Choucri, "Demographics and Conflict", Bulle¬
tin of the Atomic Scientists, Vol. 42, No. 4 (April, 1986).
©
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
m.
to break out of poverty that generates vio¬
lence both as a tactic and as a response.
Heightened aspirations and a refusal to
accept a miserable lot have also contributed
to massive population movements, within
and across national boundaries. Violent
clashes with established residents are a
common result of migration. For example,
in the Indian State of Assam, many lives
have been lost in attacks by the Assamese
on illegal immigrants from Bangladesh. In
Honduras, the migration of Salvadorans in
the early 1960s not only produced local
clashes but led to a build-up of tensions that
culminated in war between the two States.
Even in cases where migration is received
peacefully or the initial violence simmers
down, the long-term basis may be laid for
communal tensions that erupt into violence
at later stages as has been the case
throughout South and South-east Asia as
well as in many parts of Africa.
The process of development itself is al¬
ways a source of turbulence and often a
source of violence. Developmental success
inevitably brings about structural change,
upsetting traditional hierarchies and often
generating violent reaction. The failures of
development lead to even greater strain on
the social fabric. The global recession of the
early 1980s , the debt burdens of many of the
developing countries, the prospect of slow
and uneven growth for many years to come,
the drawing down of the financial and eco¬
logical capital of whole nations, have cre¬
ated intolerable strains. In many parts of
the Third World, communities are on the
verge of breakdown. Societies are begin¬
ning to come apart at the seams as the
despair, frustration and rage of the "have
nots" clash with the fear, reluctance or in¬
transigence of the "haves" and erupt into
religious, ethnic, tribal, racial and class
violence.
The dislocations caused by rapid and ex¬
tensive change make countries vulnerable
to conflict arising from both internal and
external sources. Adjustment to the de¬
velopments of the late twentieth century is
threatening enough to the equanimity of
any society without the further challenge of
trying to compress centuries of technologic¬
al change and nation-building into the span
of a few decades.
It is important to keep in mind, however,
that the process of social transformation is
by no means confined to the Third World.
All countries are in some measure caught
up in sweeping value changes that respond
to new technologies and modes of organiza¬
tion, and to a pace and scale of change that
are unprecedented in human experience. It
is not only in the Third World that the
re-examination of old and newer values has
led to challenges to the State.
The fragility of young States in the face of
internal turbulence and external pressure
leads many governments to attempt to cen¬
tralize power and to rely upon the armed
forces to maintain stability. The ease with
which this tendency slides into a cycle of
militarization, repression and internal con-
"Adjustment to the developments of the
late 20th century is threatening enough to
the equanimity of any society without the
further challenge of trying to compress
centuries of technological change and na¬
tion-building into the span of a few deca¬
des." Above, village girls from Ahwa, in
Gujarat State, India, go to the communal
well early in the morning to draw water for
domestic use.
flict is all too familiar to students of Third
World political development.
Many of today's violent conflicts are pro¬
ducts of the inability to manage change.
Others have their roots in contradictory
perceptions of and beliefs about change.
The complexity of the irrterlinkages be¬
tween problems creates in many minds a
longing for simple, reductionist explana¬
tions, whose foundations in reality are so
insecure that they have no capacity for
tolerance of other approaches.
No region has quite mastered the disloca¬
tions of the twentieth century, with its
dizzying growth of populations and massive
movements of people, its instant communi¬
cations, alienating technologies, shrunken
spaces, and horrifying destructive power
and so all remain vulnerable to conflict.
Developing countries are not unique in this.
It would be difficult, for example, to draw a
clear distinction between the violence in
Northern Ireland and many of the ongoing
conflicts in the Third World. Nonetheless, ^
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
"In the developing world, 800 million peo¬
ple live In absolute poverty and depriva¬
tion. 500 million are malnourished.
Many millions have no access to safe
drinking-wateranddo nothave the income
necessary to purchase food. They lack
protection against thé consequences of
environmental degradation and natural
calamities, such as floods and drought,
which, in Africa in particular, have pro¬
duced famine and suffering of unpre¬
cedented proportions."
Source: United Nations
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
**,
^ three of the widely shared qualities that
have been mentioned colonialism, pover¬
ty, and accelerated change do give the
Third World some distinctive preconditions
for violence.
There is also a psychological sense of
belonging to the Third World, which arises
from the recognition that the international
system is dominated by and directed for the
primary benefit of countries that exclude
the Third World from decision-making and
a fair share of the benefits of interaction.
The resulting sense of vulnerability and ex¬
clusion and the often angry sense of injus¬
tice that accompanies it gives the coun¬
tries of the Third World some sense of
solidarity despite their differences and leads
them into conflict with the North.
This kind of conflict has not often been
pursued by armed warfare between States,
but it undoubtedly feeds the atmosphere of
confrontation that leads to isolated acts of
violence. And isolated acts can all too
quickly fall into a pattern of mutual escala¬
tion of violence, with States entering into
conflict as patrons, sponsors or perpetrators
of terrorist incidents, punitive responses,
campaigns of destabilization and overt or
covert interventions. Uncontrolled, indis¬
criminate and self-perpetuating cycles of
violence are thus set in motion.
One further source of violence in the
Third World should be mentioned: with the
achievement of functional nuclear parity
between the superpowers, and the virtually
uncontested recognition of spheres of influ¬
ence dominated by one or the other in the
North, the Third World has become the
only "safe" battleground for the contest
between East and West. Neither superpow¬
er is yet willing to run a serious risk of direct
nuclear confrontation, which is implied by
any armed conflict between them in the
industrialized world. Thus the Third World
has become a theatre, in both the military
and the dramatic sense, of East-West com¬
petition. Of course this competition is not a
factor in all violent conflicts in or between
developing countries, but it has prolonged
and intensified many of those in which it is
not a prominent cause. Inevitably, it adds to
the complexity of South-South or North-
South confrontations.
The sources of violence in the Third
World are thus an admixture of internal
pressures resulting from rapid change and
external pressures resulting from the clash
of outside interests. Efforts to minimize and
control violence must recognize that these
two aspects require rather different
approaches. The effort to minimize internal
violence must focus on ways of increasing
the resilience of societies; the effort to mini¬
mize external violence must focus on res¬
traint in the definition of and response to
threat.
SOEDJATMOKO, an Indonesian scholar in the '
field of international development and politics,
has been Rector of the United Nations University
in Tokyo since 1980. The author of numerous
publications on economic, social and cultural
problems, he has also served as a member of the
Indonesian Mission to the United Nations and as
his country's ambassador to the United States.
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
1 986:Year of peace/8
Love andPeace
SINCE 10 December 1985, a re¬
markable mural by the French
painter Benn has hung in Unesco
Headquarters in Paris. Entitled "Love and
Peace", the mural measures 7 metres by
2.5 metres, and has been presented to
Unesco by the painter, who has devoted his
life and art to the cause of peace and
understanding between people and na¬
tions. Born in 1905 at Bielstok in Russia,
Benn settled in Paris in 1930 and estab¬
lished a reputation before the Second
World War. Shortly before the outbreak of
war he executed a series of seventy-two
premonitory drawings in white crayon on
black paper, which as he wrote later "pre¬
figured the unprecedented monstrosities
that were to assail helpless humanity".
These drawings were exhibited at Unesco
. Headquarters in 1983. Benn's wartime ex¬
periences, including internment and over
two years spent in hiding from the Gestapo,
gave rise to a series of paintings inspired by
verses from the Psalms. The Unesco mu¬
ral, a celebration of universal harmony
achieved after a struggle against war and
violence, also reaches back to the wartime
years, originating in a drawing executed
early in 1 944. Love and peace are evoked
on its three panels by symbolism drawn
respectively from the plant, animal and hu¬
man worlds. The world of plants is repre¬
sented by peace in the form of stylized olive
branches; the animal world by two birds
kissing, sheltered by the graceful antlers of
two young stags. The world of humankind is
symbolized by hands uplifted in a gesture of
prayer to a white dove, the messenger of
peace.
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Office:
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Subscription rates
1 year: 78 French francs. Binder for a year's issues:
56 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear
author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on request.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied
by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed arti¬
cles express the opinions ol the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of the
UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions and headlines are written
by the Unesco Courier staff. The boundaries on maps published
in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or acceptance
by Unesco or the United Nations. The Unesco Courier is pro¬
duced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco,
7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2) University Microfilms
(Xerox), Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (3) N.C.R. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 1 1 1 West 40th Street, New York,
U.S.A.; (4) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road, Wooster,
Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Editorial staff (Paris)
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Edltor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Roy Malkin
French: Alain Lévêque
Neda el Khazen
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos
Jorge Enrique Adoum
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov
Arabic: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Braille: Frederick Potter
Research: Violette Ringelstein
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Setvat, George Ducret
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Sales and subscriptions: Henry Knobil
Special projects: Peggy Julien
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-
Chief in Paris
Non-Headquarters editions
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ram Babu Sharma (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian:
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: A2izah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwah (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Lina Svenzén (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrafiaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
34 IMPRIME EN FRANCE (Printed in France) - Dépôt légal : C 1 - Août 1986 -
PHOTOCOMPOSITION : Ateliers de l'UNESCO - PHOTOGRAVURE-IMPRESSION : MAURY-IMPRIMEUR S.A., Z.l. route d'Étampes, 45330 MALESHERBES.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
The Courier For people who care about
the rest of the world ...
Some reasons for subscribing
It focuses on a variety of subjects to which
Unesco has special access: education, the natural
and social sciences, culture, arts, archaeology,
history, civilization, marine and earth science ...
It presents interesting and well-illustrated
articles written by authors from different coun¬
tries representing many schools of thought.
It offers objective reporting and a truly inter¬
national outlook on educational and scientific
aspects of current world problems: unem¬
ployment, the arms race, human rights, women's
place in society, hunger ...
It serves as a valuable source of ideas and
information for teachers and students who wish
to obtain an accurate synthesis on subjects for
classroom discussions and research projects.
It is a useful aid in language instruction and
practice, with monthly publication in 32 language
versions. In addition, a quarterly selection in
Braille (English, French and Spanish) is available
free of charge.
Join or ask your friends to join our
international family of more than 3
million readers around the world
ANNUAL SUBSCRIPTION
12 issues 78 French francs
Ï^Cou,tier
^rier}^
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58a Gipps St., Collingwood, Victoria 3066;
Publications. Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100,
NSW; Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale
2100, NSW. Sub-agent: United Nations Association of Australia, P.O. Box
175, 5th floor, Ana House, 28 Elizabeth St., Melbourne, Victoria 3000.
AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31, A-1011, Vienna.
BAHAMAS. Nassau Stationers Ltd., P.O. Box N-3138. Nassau. BAHRAIN.
The Arabian Agencies and Distributing Co., AI Mutanabi St., P.O. Box 156,
Manama. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International Ltd., Ittefaq Build¬
ing, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola. Dacca 3. BARBADOS. University of the
West Indies Bookshop, Cave Hill Campus, P.O. Box 64, Bridgetown.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Handelmaatschappij
Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-Antwerpen. French edition and
general Unesco publications agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202 Ave. du Roi, 1060
Brussels, CCP 000-0070823-1 3. BOTSWANA. Botswana Book Centre. P.O.
Box 91, Gaborone. BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552 Merchant
Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine
St. West, Montreal. Qué. H3H 1M7. CHINA. China National Publications
Import and Export Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Beijing. CYPRUS. "MAM",
Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue. P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N T.L., Spalena 51-113 02, Prague 1 ; Ve Smeckach
30, P O.B. 790-1 1 1-27 Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura, 1 1
Soukenicka, Prague 1 . For Slovakia only: AHa Verlag. -Publishers, Hurbanovo
nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava-CSSR. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export-OG, Tids-
sknftservice. 35 Norre Sogade. DK-1970 Kobenhavn K. EGYPT (ARAB
REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb
St.. Cairo. ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis
Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa. Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100 Hel¬
sinki 10; Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, Koivuvaarankuja 2, 01 640 Vantaa 64.
FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco. 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris. CCP
12598-48. GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Buchhaus Leipzig, Post¬
fach 140. 710 Leipzig, or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R.
FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier (German, English, French
and Spanish editions): Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb,
Basaltstrasse 57, D5300 Bonn 3. GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd.,
P.O. Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The
University Bookshop of Ghana. Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape
Coast; The University Bookshop ot Legon. P.O. Box 1, Legon. GREAT
BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. HONG KONG. Federal Publications (HK)
Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat St., Abderdeen. Swindon
Book Co., 13-15, Lock Rd., Kowloon. Hong Kong Govt. Information Services,
Publication Centre, Baskerville House. 22 Ice St. HUNGARY. Kultura-
Bushimport-ABT, P.O.B. 149-H-1389, Budapest 62. ICELAND. Snaebjorn
Jonsson and Co., H.F. Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA. UBS Publishers'
Distributors Ltd., 5 Ansari Road, P.O. Box N° 701 5, New Delhi 1 1 0002. Orient
Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 1 7 Chitaranjan
Ave., Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; 5-9-41/1 Bashir
Bagh. Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Rd., Bangalore
560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda. Hyderabad-500001. Sub-depots: Oxford Book
and Stationery Co., 17 Park St., Calcutta 70016; Sandia House, New Delhi;
Publication Unit, Ministry of Education and Culture, Ex. AFO Hutments, Dr.
Rajendra Prasad Rd.. New Delhi, 110001. INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers
and Booksellers, 29 Jl. Oto Iskandardinata 111, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl Or. Sam
Ratulangie 37, Jakarta Pusat IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution
Co.. 28 Vcssal Shirazi St., Enghélab Ave., P.O. Box 314/1486, Teheran;
Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco, 1 188 Englab Ave., Rostam Give Building, Zip
Code 13158, P.O. Box 11365-4498, Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzies Bookshop,
AI Rashid St.. Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd..
Ballymount Rd., Walkmslown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL. A.B.C. Bookstore Ltd.,
P.O. Box 1283. 71 Allenby Rd., Tel Aviv 61000. ITALY. Licosa (Librería
Commíssíonaría Sanson!, S.p.A.), Via Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552,
50121 Florence. JAMAICA. Sangster's Bookstores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101
Water Lane, Kingston; University of the West Indies Bookshop. Mona, Kings¬
ton. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc.. 37-3 Hongo 3-chome Bunkyo-ku,
Tokyo 113. KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O. Box 30571 , Nairobi;
Africa Book Services Ltd., Quran House, Mfangano St., P.O. Box 45245.
Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central
64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd. POB 2942, Kuwait; for the
Unesco Courier: Farafalla Press Agency, P.O. Box SAFA 4541, Kuwait.
LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern Africa.
LIBERIA. Code and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LIECHTENSTEIN. Eurocan Trust Reg. P.O.B. 5-9494 Schaan. LIBYAN
ARAB JAMAH1RIYA. Agency for Development of Publication and Distribu¬
tion, P.O. Box 34-35. Tripoli. LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück. 22.
Grande-Rue. Luxembourg. MALAWI. Malawi Book Service. Head Office, P.O.
Box 30044 Chichlri, Blantyre 3. MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-opera¬
tive Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur 22-11. MALTA. Sapienzas."26 Republic St.,
Valletta. MAURITIUS. Nalanda Compariy Ltd., 30 Bourbon St.. Port-Louis.
MONACO. British Library, 30 Bd. des Moulins, Monte Carlo. NEPAL. Sajha
Prakashan Polchowk, Kathmandu. NETHERLANDS. Keesing Boeken B V.,
Joan Muyskenweg. 22, Postbus 1118, 1000 BC Amsterdam.
NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N V., P.O. Box 200, Willem-
stad. Curaçao. N.A. NEW ZEALAND. Government Publishing, P.O. Box
14277-Kilbirnie, Wellington; 130 Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721, Christ-
church; Alma St., P.O. Box 857, Hamilton; Princes St., P.O. Box 1104,
Dunedin NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop
of Ibadan, P O. 286; The University Bookshop of Nsukka; The University
Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of Zana.
" NORWAY. Johan Grundt Tanum, P.O B. 1177 Senlrum - Oslo 1, Narvesen
A/S; Subscription and Trade Book Service, P.O.B. 6125 Etterstad. Oslo 6;
Universilets Bokhandelen, Unrversitelssentret, Postboks 307 Blindem, Oslo
3. PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O. Box No.
729, Lahore 3; Unesco Publications Centre, Regional Office for Book De¬
velopment in Asia and the Pacific, 39 Delhi Housing Society, P.O. Box 8950,
Karachi 29. PHILIPPINES. National Book Store. Inc., 701, Rizal Ave., Manila
D-404. POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars Polona-
Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No.7. 00-068 Warsaw. PORTUGAL. Dias &
Andrade Ltda. Livrana Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES.
National Bookshop, P.O. Box 48, Mahé; New Service Ltd., Kingsgate House,
P.O. Box 131, Mahé. SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and
Sierra Leone Diocesan Bookshops. Freetown. SINGAPORE. Federal Pub¬
lications (S) Pte Ltd. Times Jurong, 2 Jurong Port Rd., Singapore 2261.
SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern Bookshop and General, P.O.
Box 951, Mogadiscio. SOUTH AFRICA. For the Unesco Courier (single
copies) only: Central News Agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg. SRI
LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chitlampatam Gardiner Mawaia.
P.O.B. 244, Colombo 2. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop. P.O. Box 1118.
Khartoum. SWEDEN. All publications A/B.C.E. Fritzes Kungel. Hovbokhan-
del, Regeringsgatan 12. Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16. For the Unesco
Courier: Svenska FN Förbundet, Skolgrand 2. Box 150 50 S-104, 65 Stock¬
holm; Wennergren-Williams. Box 30004-S-104, 25 Stockholm; Esselte Tids-
kriftscentraien, Gamla Brogatan 26, Box 62 - 101 20 Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag. 5 Ramistrasse. Zurich;
Librairie Payot, Rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11, CCP. 12-236; Librairies
Payot also in Lausanne, Basle. Berne, Vevey, Montreux, Neuchâtel and
Zürich. TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam.
THAILAND. Nibondhand Co. Ltd.. 40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya
Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok; Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Ave.,
Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. TRINIDAD
AND TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco. 1 8 Alexandra St.. St. Clair,
Trinidad W 1 . TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S., Istiklâl Caddesi, No 469. Posta
Kutusu 219, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop. P.O. Box 7145,
Kampala. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, H M.S.O.. P.O. Box
276, London SWS 5DT, and Govt. Bookshops in London, Edinburgh, Belfast,
Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol; for scientific maps only: McCarta Ltd., 122
King's Cross Rd., London WC1X 9DS. UNITED STATES. Unipub, 205 East
42nd St.. New York, N.Y. ,10017. Orders for books and periodicals: P.O. Box
1222, Ann Arbor, Ml 481 06. USSR. V/O Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Ul. Dimitro-
va 39, Moskva 1 1 3095. YEMEN. 1 4th October Corporation, P.O Box 4227,
Aden. YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost, llica 30/11. Zagreb; Cankarjeva Zalozba.
Zopitaqeva 2, Lubljana; Nolit, Terazije 27/11, Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd., PO. Box 2664. Lusaka.
ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union Ave., Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
iL i
#4'J&VX+
&m m ;
]]>
</page>
</document>
