<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="069729eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
WORLD
K m
N° 12
19 5 5
(8th year)
Price : 7d. (U. K.)
30 francs (France)
HAPPY
-
NEW YEAR
AROUND
THE WORLD
A voyage by
magic carpet 'p
to the festivals
rites & customs
of many lands
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
T
he unesco courier is pleased to announce that the number of paid sub¬
scriptions has now passed the 50,000 mark.
This was the first goal set early this year when the Editors agreed to spare no
effort to bring readers a better, more interesting magazine with each succeeding
issue. New features have been added, the number of pages has been increased, a
high quality white paper has been adopted, and both the contents and general
appearance have been appreciably improved.
Today, the unesco courier has the highest paid circulation of any periodical
published by the United Nations or any of its affiliated international agencies.
On this occasion, the Editors wish to express their appreciation to all readers
throughout the world for their continued, enthusiastic support, for their many letters
of praise and encouragement, and particularly for their magnificent response in
renewing subscriptions before the new increased rates go into effect on January 1,
1956. (One reader submitted a renewal for six years. The Editors regret that sub¬
scriptions cannot be accepted for more than three years at the present rates.)
Several years ago, Mexico launched a great and successful campaign against
illiteracy with the slogan "Each One Teach One". The Editors have adopted a simi¬
lar phrase for a new campaign which has as its goal 100,000 subscribers. The phrase
is : "Each One Reach One."
With this issue of the unesco courier, the Editors invite every subscriber to take
advantage of the current annual subscription rate of 300 French francs, 6/-, $1.50
by sending in a minimum of one gift subscription for a friend or relative. Many
subscribers have already led the way by accompanying their renewals with four
or five gift subscriptions.
As of January 1, 1950 the new annual rate will be 400 French francs ; 8/- or
$2.00. Gift subscriptions and renewals will be accepted at the current rate of
300 French francs; 6/- or $1.50 if postmarked not later than December 31, 1955. The
unesco courier is an ideal Christmas present which your friends will enjoy IF you
post your gift subscription today.
So please don't wait. Join the unesco courier in its current campaign for
100,000 subscribers. Each one reach one. Send in youi-gift subscriptions today:
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier
Â WINpOW O r C H ON THC «OILO
Number 12 - 1955
8th YEAR
CONTENTS
PAGE
3 EDITORIAL
4 NEW YEAR GODS AND TORCH PROCESSIONS
Revellers in ancient Greece and Rome
By Gabrielle Cabrini
7 RITUALS AND SYMBOLS OF TIME REBORN
By Mircea Eliade
8 HOW THE GIFT IDEA STARTED
By Claude Levi-Strauss
9 NEW YEAR CARDS DOWN THE AGES
10 FIVE SLEEPLESS NIGHTS OF MONGHOSAN
Festival of the Dayak head-hunters
12 HAPPY NEW YEAR IN BALI
Gifts to the gods are eaten by mortals
14 LIVING GHOSTS OF THE INCAS
Chants and Pan pipes on the Andean plateau
' By Alfred Metraux
17 INDIA: LAND OF MANY CALENDARS
By Khushwant Singh
18 COLOURFUL FAIRS OF ASSAM AND BENGAL
21 ELEPHANTS MADE ELEGANT FOR THE FESTIVAL
22 LOBSTERS FOR A LONG LIFE
And seaweed for a happy one in Japan
By Shigeo Kimura
25 NIGHT OF THE GOATS AND GILDED PLOUGHS
Old Slav legends .
By Eveline Falck
27 LANTERNS, GONGS AND FIREWORKS
A Chinese philosopher recalls his boyhood
By Lin Yutang
30 TUG OF WAR WITH HIMALAYAN SPIRITS
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organi¬
zation
Editorial Offices
Unesco, i 9, Avenue Kleber, Paris I 6, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Circulation Manager
Jean Groffier
U.S.A. : Henry Evans
Individual arcicles not copyrighted may be reprinted from THE UNESCO
COURIER but must be accompanied by the following credit line: "Reprinted
from UNESCO COURIER". Signed articles reprinted must carry the author's
name. Prints of non-copyright photos are available on request.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied by an inter¬
national reply coupon covering postage.
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of THE UNESCO
COURIER.
Annual subscription rates of THE UNESCO COURIER : 6/-: $ 1.50 or 300
French frs or equivalent (U.S. edition $ 2.50) (MC. 55. 1 97. A)
COVER PHOTO
Gifts for the gods: Balinese women carrying
beautifully-worked New Year offerings. Made
of straw and decorated with rice these offerings
sometimes exceed six feet in height. After
remaining in the temples for a traditional
three to five-day period they are removed
and the savoury rice is consumed by the Bali¬
nese themselves. See page 1 2.
Copyright André Martin
Fon almost all people, the start of a new year is a
special occasion, but whether we celebrate it on
January 1 or on. any other day of the year, we arc
following a custom which dates back to the very dawn
of civilization. The New Year, in effect, falls on different
days for different peoples. It may come in February or
April, in June or September and everywhere the customs
that go with it vary.
In its first issue of 1954, the Unesco Courier said:
"If we could travel around the world on a magic carpet
and peep at the celebrations in the various countries,
what a wonderful variety of customs we should find.
The Feast of the Lanterns concludes two weeks of a
noisy, gay spectacle ushering in the new year for the
Chinese who almost seem to be celebrating all their
holidays of the year at once.
"In Japan, New Year's Day is even gayer. No matter
how poor a Japanese may be he provides himself with
spotless new clothes and takes several days off to visit
old friends or entertain them .at home. Every gatepost
is adorned with dark green pines and light green feathery
bamboos while over the doorways hang vivid red lobsters
and crabs, and scarlet tangerinc-like-fruits, symbolic of
long life and happiness. The streets afe thronged with
children laughing and playing the whole day long, and
everyone beams with joy, bowing and offering best
wishes even to perfect strangers.
"Scotland celebrates New Year's Eve with a heartiness
rarely surpassed. The tradition that to be "first-foot"
in a house brings luck for the whole year sends midnight
revellers into the streets, each one carrying cakes and
food and drink to ensure his host a bounteous. year. So,
throughout the world, in the Orient, in Africa, in Europe
and the New World, the New Year is celebrated with
elaborate festivities. It is an occasion for making fine
new resolutions alas, not always kept for forgetting
the disappointments of the past twelve months, and for
making a new start."
In the Arab world, the "new start" during' 1956 will
be the year 1376. According to the Copt year in Egypt
and Ethiopia it will be 1673; on the Jewish calendar it
will be 5617; while in Japan it will be the 31st year of
Showa (Emperor Hirohito will be known by this name
after his death).
For Unesco, 1956 will mark the 10th anniversary of its
creation, and its General Conference in New Delhi, India
the first to be held in the Far East. In India, the great
Festival of the Lights, known as Diwali, symbolizes the
triumph of light over darkness, of truth over untruth.
The Unesco Courier offers this symbol to its readers in
re-affirming its own faith in the triumph of education
and understanding between peoples over the forces of
ignorance and obscurantism.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Nr 12. 1955
Copyright Keystone.
ew year gods
;nd torchlight
processions
Revellers in ancient
Greece and Rome
by Gabrielle Cabrini
If people who live in countries which
use the Gregorian calendar were
asked why they celebrate the New
Year, the chances are they would reply
that it is because the old year has
ended and they might as well ring in
the new one. Few among them would
be able to explain the real origin of
this deeply-rooted custom, though all
would agree that a new year "changes
something" and that January 1 -"calls
for a celebration".
There are many children who
firmly believe that the arrival of
January 1 means they will get to the
top of the class even without working
for it and even some grown-ups
subconsciously believe that their pres¬
ent troubles and problems will
disappear with the change in dates.
Though they hesitate to put it into
words, lovers often fear that the
change from one year to another cuts
them off from the days when their
love began and in some mysterious way
threatens it. All these people are
obeying instincts born of ancestral
customs going back into the dim and
distant past.
Six-day feast
Human beings have always seen
something fatalistic in the
changing of the years. At one
time or another, almost all peoples
have consulted oracles and the like in
an effort to pierce the future. For the
future suddenly seemed more frighten¬
ing or alluring simply because time
no longer appeared to be following
its normal course. Instead, it was
transformed into something called
"next year" even when this merely
meant "tomorrow". The time that
elapses between December 31 of one
year and January 1 of the next may
easily seem far longer than all the 365
days that have passed since the pre¬
vious January 1.
Just as all peoples have associated
with their celebrations of the changing
of the year the idea of the earth's
apparent death and rebirth, so, all of
them have been conscious of the hope
implicit in the thought of renewal.
All civilizations did not celebrate the
New Year at the same seasons the
Persians, Aztecs, Incas and early
Romans fixed theirs in the spring,
other peoples in January and others
again in midsummer but almost all of
them linked the change from one year
to another with the idea of joy and
hope.
The Persians, for whom fire was a
symbol of divinity, and who began the
year with the spring equinox, marked
this festival with a ceremony which
Herodotus, the Greek historian has
described.
Inside the royal palace the King
awaited the coming of dawn. Suddenly
a knock was heard on the palace door.
"Who is there ?" demanded the King.
"Open", replied a voice, "I am the
messenger of Ormuzd (the supreme
deity) and I bring with me the New
Year".
When the palace door was opened a
young man entered, followed by another
bearing a silver goblet containing
wheat, barley, peas, sesame, rice and
some newly-minted coins. The goblet
was presented to the King who then
sampled the food.
On a signal every door in the palace
was thrown open and the halls were
immediately thronged with people, who
came to celebrate for six days. During
this time, the King, who normally lived
a Spartan existence and who was
always separated from the common
people, was able to eat and drink and
mingle with the crowd. Herodotus
says that he was also allowed to get
drunk and on the first day alone to
dance. At the end of the sixth day the
palace doors were closed again and the
people returned to their homes and
work.
Satyrs and Maenads
Passing from the Persians to the
Greeks we find that in their tra¬
dition of proud independence,
even when as city states they were
linked together politically, they did not
synchronize their calendars. And even
though all of them reckoned in periods
or four full years, or olympiads, start¬
ing from the first full moon after the
summer solstice, each had a different
time for celebrating the first day of
the year.
The Spartans, Delphians, (Continued
Ephesians and Macedonians on page 6)
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Copyright Roger Viollet Cartier-Bresson, Copyright Magnum
Cartier-Bresson, Copyright Magnum
CHIMNEY SWEEPS are
symbolic figures of good
luck in Germany and a hand¬
shake with one of these
grimy faced, top-hatted work¬
ers is considered a sure way
to make certain of a happy
New Year. Little piglets,
real or in pottery and cloth,
also symbols of good luck,
find their way into the ban¬
quets and other festive
scenes on New Year's Eve.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. N"* 12. 1955
NEW
YEAR
ODS
(Continued)
MISTLETOE, the once sacred
plant of the ancient Druids, is
still a popular "good luck" deco¬
ration in homes for New Year. Copyright Keystone
Anthesteria, Diony¬
sus still played his
part. During this
festival cares were
forgotten, everything
was abandoned to.
the pursuit of plea¬
sure and sleep was
out of the question.
It was forbidden to
ask for the repay¬
ment of debts or to
insist on pledges
being redeemed; sla¬
ves were set free
and participated in
the fetes and ban¬
quets, intoxicating
themselves to hon¬
our the re-birth of
the god. Even pris¬
oners were liberated.
began the year with the autumn equi¬
nox, the Thebians with the winter
solstice. The Athenians, after follow¬
ing for a time the same pattern as the
Thebians, opted for a new year which
would fall at the time of the summer
full moon during the month of Heca-
tombeon, corresponding to our month
of July.
The Athenians feted Dionysus, the
Olympian god of Nature who had come
from Thrace and Phrygia. He was a
being of many forms guardian of the
plants and trees, a magician who could
take on the form of a goat or a white
oull, coursing the mountains with his
attendant band of Satyrs and Maenads,
who with Dionysus indulged in myster¬
ious orgies. Little by little the cult of
Dionysus mingled with other cults,
became indentified with other gods and
was transformed into the symbol of
rest and re-birth of the soil and of the
migration of the dead from their home
in the underworld.
In the Athenian festival of the
During the banquets the guests
passed a myrtle branch from hand to
hand and recited improvised couplets,
called scolions. The festival continued
with rounds of drinks interspersed with
theatrical productions, songs and
dances. It concluded with a gigantic
torchlight procession through the
streets of Athens, staged as a triumphal
march for Dionysus with Pans and
Satyrs each carrying a gilded lamp and
surrounded by Sileni clothed in purple.
Following these dwellers of the plains
and forests came a youth carrying on
a banner the morning star, and
children clothed in white to symbolize
the new year.
Finally, at the end of the immense
procession came the chariot of the god
crowned with vine leaves. Throughout
the festival there reigned the spirit of
gaiety.
These were the only days throughout
the year when the oracle at Delphi
did not prophesy, because, as she
Ernst Haas, Copyright Magnum.
said, "Apollo, who speaks through me,
is himself taking part in the festival,
and has therefore ceased to inspire
me." But rejoicing ended as night fell
on this first day of the new year.
Things went on as before. "To your
work, slaves," said the free citizens to
their servants, and then, more softly,
us shadows, the Anthesteria is
finished". And the shadows of the
dead returned to their abodes in the
underworld.
Transformed into something much
more commonplace, the Greek festivals
were handed down to Rome, where
after Caesar, the new year was cele¬
brated on the first of January. With
the Romans everything became colossal.
The saturnalia which began on Decem¬
ber 19 and lasted for seven days,
became lost in other festivals, as in the
Rome of those times, there were no
DRAGONS at Luang-Prabang, in Laos and trumpets
in Times Square, where New Yorkers gather on
fewer than 182 obligatory holidays in
the year.
Rome, however, worked on the first
day of the new year as a sort of fore¬
taste of labour and effort. The new
consuls in their white togas consulted
oracles and soothsayers. Mounted on
white horses they paid homage to Jupi¬
ter, who had vanquished the shades of
the night and who was now starting on
his new course. At first cock crow the
people opened the garlanded doors of
their houses, and in each family the
first words spoken were those of good
wishes. Among the gifts and offerings
the Romans placed oak leaves ; a sou¬
venir of the past and of a once sacred
tree.
As in Greece the slaves were also set
free during the saturnalia. The gods
spoke of death and re-birth: the re¬
birth of the soil, barren and dead in the
middle of winter. But in Rome the
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
emperors were powerful. One day,
Tiberius, distrustful successor to Au¬
gustus, wearied of the new year festivals
with their presents, good wishes and
the tiresome seekers after favours who
gave them. He stopped all the festivi¬
ties, saying that they were a waste of
time. They were, however, re-estab¬
lished by Caligula.
However, not all peoples have cele¬
brated with joy the passing of the old
year and the arrival of the new. Be¬
fore their conquest by the Spaniards,
the Aztecs and the Incas, peoples with
an advanced civilization whose scorn of
death was legendary, viewed with fear
the end of the old year.
This fear was especially heightened
at two periods at the end of each fifty
two years cycle (their equivalent of our
century) and during the last five days
of the year which were considered
Copyright Cossira.
New Year's Eve. Each country and place cele¬
brates the birth of the New Year in its own way
'"useless" days since they were not in¬
cluded in the Aztec year of 18 months
each of 20 days.
At these times a terrible fear grip¬
ped the people, the kings and the
priests. What if the sun should fail to
rise again? On the last night of the
year, all fires were put out in the
Empire of the Aztecs. In their houses
the people waited, the King kept a vigil
in his palace and on the top of their
pyramids, the priests stood watching.
When the hour struck life stopped
for a moment throughout the country.
Would the fire light? A priest rubbed
two pieces of wood together above the
heart of a sacrificial victim. There
was a moment of suspense. But the
fire caught and the waiting crowd
spilled out carrying the fire and with
it the joy which was really nothing
more than relief from the danger of
this new year of the spring equinox.
Rituals & symbols
of Time reborn
by Mircea Eliade
Primitive peoples divided time
into periods such as heat and
cold, drought and rain, sow¬
ing and harvest, but at a very
early stage of history these divi¬
sions led to the idea of a temporal
cycle and hence to the concept of
the "year". The beginning of the
year varied from country to
country and from epoch to epoch,
calendar reforms being constantly
introduced to make the ritual
meaning of festivals fit the seas¬
ons with which they were suppos¬
ed to correspond.
In most primitive societies the
"New Year" is equivalent to the
raising of the taboo on the new
harvest which is thus proclaimed
edible for the whole community.
This means that the "divisions of
time" are determined by the rituals
governing the renewal of food re¬
serves, that is, the rituals that
guarantee the continued existence
of the whole community. The
adoption of the solar year as the
unit of time is of Egyptian origin.
The majority of other historical
cultures (and Egypt itself down to
a certain period) had a year, both
lunar and solar, of 360 days (that
is, 12 months of 30 days each), to
which five extra days (called the
intercalary days) were added.
However, neither the instability
and latitude in the beginning of
the New Year, nor the varying
lengths attributed by different peo¬
ples, were able to lessen the impor¬
tance attached by all nations to
the end of one period of time and
the beginning of another. This
conception of the end and the be¬
ginning of a temporal period based
on the observation of biocosmic
rhythms, formed part of a larger
system the system of periodic
regeneration of life, presupposing
a new Creation, or symbolic repe¬
tition of the cosmos.
A scapegoat for sin
The end of the year was mark¬
ed by a number of rituals:
fasting, collective ablutions
and purification; extinguishing
the fire and ritually rekindling it.
in the second part of the ceremo¬
nial; the expulsion of "demons"
by means of noises, cries, blows,
or by the expelling of an animal
Dr. MIRCEA ELIADE is Rumanian by birth,
and now resides in France. He is the author
of a history of religions, and other works on
Shamanism, Yoga, and Primitive symbolism.
His latest essay, an interpretation of mankind's
experience of history has appeared in English
translation as "The Myth of the Eternal
Return". The book has also been translated
into German, Italian, Portuguese, Spanish and
Swedish.
(the "scapegoat" of the Israelites)
or of a man (Mamurius Veturius,
in Rome), regarded as the material
vehicle through which the sins of
the community were removed
beyond its boundaries. There were
often ceremonial combats between
two groups of actors, or collective
orgies, or processions of masked
men (representing the souls of the
ancestors, or the gods).
In many places the belief still
survives that at the year's end the
souls of the dead return to earth
and visit the living. The spirits
lavish honours upon them for seve¬
ral days, after which they are led
in procession to the outskirts of
the village, or are driven from it.
It is at the same period that the
initiation ceremonies for young
men are performed.
From chaos to cosmos
Naturally, we seldom find all
of these elements grouped
together on a equal footing
In certain societies the ceremonies
of extinguishing and re-kindling
the fire predominate; in others it
is the expulsion of demons and
diseases or the expulsion of the
"scapegoat" in animal or human
form. But the meaning of the
whole ceremony, like that of its
constituent elements is sufficient¬
ly clear with the division of time
into units or "years" we witness
not only the definite conclusion of
an interval of time and the be¬
ginning of another, but also the
complete wiping away of the pre¬
vious year and of past time.
This is also the meaning of puri¬
fication rituals to burn away and
annul the sins and errors of the
individual and of the whole com¬
munity not a mere "purifying".
Regeneration, as its name indi¬
cates, is a new birth. The annual
expulsion of sins, diseases and de¬
mons is basically an attempt to
restore "pure", primordial Time
in other words, the "instant" of
Creation. Every New Year is a
resumption of time from .the be¬
ginning, that is, a repetition of the
origin of the universe. The ritual
combats between two groups of
actors, the return of the dead, the
Saturnalia and the orgies, are so
many elements which denote that
at the end of one year and in ex¬
pectation of the New Year there
is a repetition of the mythical
moment of the passage from chaos
to cosmos.
The ceremonial for the Babylo¬
nian New Year, the
akitu, is sufficiently (Cont'd on
conclusive in this res- P°«e 32)
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. N"* 12. 1955
ROMAN OIL-
LAMP bearing a
New Year greet¬
ing. The wing¬
ed figure of Vic¬
tory is surroun¬
ded by ancient
seasonal good
luck symbols.
The custom of maJking New Year
gifts has both a simple and com¬
plicated history. It is simple
enough if we merely think of the gene¬
ral meaning of the custom itself, and
examine, for example, Japan's
New Year wish, "O-ni wa soto
- fuku wa uchi" (Out, all
demons! Let good luck come
in). Just as the old year
should take ill luck away with
it, so the enrichment and
happiness brought by the ex¬
change of gifts on New Year's
Day are regarded as an omen,
almost as a magic spell, to
ensure that the New Year will
continue as joyfully as it has
begun.
From this point of view, the
Japanese saying is very like
those used by Ovid in the first
book of the Fastes, describing
Roman customs at the festival
of Janus. Today, this has
become our January 1, al¬
though for a long time, even
in Rome, the festival did not
coincide with the beginning
of the New Year. "What is
the meaning", the poet asks
Janus, "'of the dates, the wrinkled figs
and the light-coloured honey, offered
in a white vessel?" "It is an omen",
replies the god, "they express the desire
that coming events may be impregnat¬
ed with the same sweetness..." Ovid
also relates that on the first day of the
year, the Roman shopkeepers were
careful to open their shops for a short
while, in order to make a few sales as
a good omen for the rest of the year.
Curiously enough, this tradition has
been kept up in the French language,
in which the word for New Year gifts
is étrennes. Shopkeepers reverse the
meaning in the use of the verb
étrenner, which signifies to make the
first sale of the day.
It is more difficult to trace the exact
origin of the custom of New Year gifts
in the Western world. The ancient
Celtic Druids had a ceremony which
they performed on the day which cor¬
responds to January 1. They cut
mistletoe, which was considered to be
a magical plant with protective powers
from the oak trees, and distributed it
to the people. Hence the name given
in certain parts of France, until quite
recently, to New Year gifts: guy-l'an-
neuf, corrupted cometimes into agui-
gnette (from the French gui : "mist¬
letoe" and I'an-neuf: "'New Year").
In Rome during the second half of
December and the early part of Janu¬
ary, festivals took place at which
gifts were exchanged; those offered in
December were usually of two kinds
wax candles (which we have adopted
for our Christmas trees) and dolls made
of clay or some edible substance, which
HOW THE
GIFT IDEA
STARTED
by Claude Lévi-Strauss
Known for his studies and research at the University
of Sâo Paulo in Brazil and the Institute of Ethnology
in Paris, Professor CLAUDE LEVI-STRAUSS was for¬
merly Deputy Director of the Musée de l'Homme ¡n
Paris. He ¡s now director of research In the reli¬
gious science section of the Ecole Pratiaue des Hautes
Etudes and Secretary-General of International Council
of Social Sciences in Paris.
were given to children. There were
others, too, described in great detail by
Martial in his epigrams; Roman
chroniclers related that the patricians
received gifts from their plebeian de¬
pendents, and the Emperors from the
citizens. Caligula took possession of
his gifts in person and spent the whole
day in the vestibule of his palace for
this purpose.
Traces of their dual origin in pagan
customs and Roman rites seem long
to have been preserved by New Year
gifts. Why otherwise would the Church
throughout the Middle Ages have tried
in vain to abolish them as a bar¬
baric survival ? However, by then,
these gifts were not only a periodical
tribute paid by the peasants to their
overlord, in the form of capons, fresh
cheeses and preserved fruits; or sym¬
bolic offerings, such as oranges or
lemons, spiked with cloves, hung like
charms above jars of wine to prevent
it from turning sour, or nutmegs wrap¬
ped up in gilt paper. They were part
of a much larger scheme of offerings
under which, in certain parts of Eur¬
ope, even the livestock were benefi-
caries, being gratified with juniper
fumes and sprinkled with urine.
New Year gifts, as we know them
today, are not so much a relic of these
popular customs as the democratization
of an aristocratic tradition. Very early
in modern history sovereigns demanded
New Year gifts as a means of augment¬
ing their income and affording a
further opportunity for their subjects
to prove their loyalty. In France,
Henry III and the Duc de Berri were
in the habit of receiving New Year
gifts (what we would nowadays call a
"'luxury edition" is mentioned under
this heading in the inventory of the
latter's possessions). It is well known
that Elizabeth I of England relied on
ft)
' -P " i
"V ~<'J7* ft
B-
her New Year gifts for her pocket-
money and the upkeep of her ward¬
robe ; the archbishops and bishops
each used to give her from ten to forty
pounds, while she received dresses,
skirts, silk stockings, garters, cloaks,
mantles and furs from her noblemen
and such presents as precious caskets,
pots of ginger, orange-flower and other
confections from her doctors and her
apothecaries.
During the European Renaissance,
metal pins became a favourite form of
present as they were then a great
novelty; until the fifteenth century,
women had used wooden pins to fasten
their clothing. As for New Year cards
with pictures and ornamental texts,
they are known to have been in use
from Europe to Japan. "Some in
golden letters write their love", says a
seventeenth-century English poet. In
France, illustrated New Year cards were
in fashion until the Revolution.
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
To understand why the practice of
exchanging New Year gifts is so per¬
sistent and so widespread we must look
beyond these entertaining details for
the underlying significance of the
custom. "The manner of giving is
more important than the gift", the
saying goes, and all peoples, "savage"
or civilized, appear to believe that it is
better to receive objects as presents
than to acquire them oneself, as if the
act of giving or receiving has added
to the value of the object. The Maoris
of New Zealand believed that a magic
power, which they called hau, entered
into the present and created a perma¬
nent link between the giver and the
receiver. Similarly, the Roman custom
of offering gifts seems to have grown
out of a like belief. It originated in
the offering of green boughs to the
Sabine king, Tatius, who shared the
royal power with Romulus. These
boughs were taken from the sacred
wood of the goddess Strenia, and were
thus called strenae in Latin, from
which is derived the French étrennes.
Strenia was the goddess of strength.
For the Romans and for the Maoris
alike, presents were objects endowed
with a special power through the act of
giving. From where did this power
come? By the exchange of gifts, often
of mere token value, people give ex¬
pression in outward and visible form
to the inner spirit of community life
spontaneous acceptance of interdepen¬
dence one with another. This .annual
New Year festival at which flowers and
sweets, ties and illustrated cards
change hands, is not then to be deri¬
ded. It is an occasion when all men
realize that the society in which they
live is based on this very principle of
give-and-take.
New Year echoes
round the world
THE Tamils and the Sinhalese
celebrate the New Year on the
first day of the month of
Chittirai, approximating to the
middle of Atfril in the western world.
No work of any kind should be
started after this day except at a
"lucky hour". When the hour has
been decided the work of cultivation
commences and the first basket of
manuib is carried to the field ready
to be dug in.
FRANCE has celebrated her New
Year on January 1 since the
Year 1564, before that the festi¬
vities took place on March 25.
ANCIENT Egypt also had parti¬
cular New Year customs. In
the tombs of the Pharoahs
small blue-glazed bottles, probably
scent flasks, were found bearing
inscriptions about flowers and the
coming New Year. Egyptian scarabs
with heiroglyphs, au ab nab, or all
good luck were also very probably
New Year presents. ,
(More on p. 28)
New Year cards down the ages
Medieval New Year greetings cards drawn
by nuns behind convent walls are a
far cry from most modern card designs,
but thoughts and wishes are still the same.
(1) During the past five years, the Uni¬
ted Nations Children's Fund (UNICEF) has
seen the annual sale of its greetings cards
rise from I 30,000 to three millions. Drawn
and donated between 1950 and 1954 by
artists like Raoul Dufy and Henri Matisse,
and for 1955 by Antonio Frazcati and
Edy Legrand, greetings cards have enabled
UNICEF to help children in many lands.
(2) "A good year and good health" are the
wishes of Savignac, a French artist in his
personal "weight lifter" card. (3) Medi¬
eval woodcut: The infant Jesus brings
gifts in the New Year ship. (4) Scissors in
hand, this little journalist brings wishes
from a Swiss newspaper clipping service.
(5) Concertina card by two American
artists spells out Peace. (See next page)
UNICEF
V»"9 èt^^-t)S^titci<yc%tv^\tÇjivfj
1 Graphis " Zurich
bE k-
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Nr 12. 1955
New Year cards
by Françoise Christiaen
(Cont'd)
The earliest New Year cards come
from the convents of medieval
Europe. There tne nuns De6<*<-i ><o
send New Year greetings to their fami¬
lies, living in the world outside. They
were very personal cards, hand painted,
the product of hours of patient work,
and always religious in inspiration. At
that time the Church celebrated
Christ's birthday and the New Year on
one and the same day, December 25, so
the cards would often picture the
Christ-child born to bring joy into the
coming year.
Sometimes the Child was begging to
be admitted to the hearts of men, some¬
times he came as the bearer of small
gifts which the nuns included with
their cards. As her New Year's message
one nun wrote: "I send my dear father
a little honeycomb with lavender, a
blood-letting bandage and a painted
Christ with his happy New Year".
Sometimes the gift was gingerbread,
sometimes a small box supposedly
containing a "salve of patience".
A nun might design a Christmas
rose and add a text: "He who desires
this rose must also suffer the thorns",
or she might draw a New Year clock
and enclose the wish that "all the
hours of trouble in the coming year
may end in the noon of joy".
New Year cards did not stay behind
convent walls for long. Soon the nuns'
greeting cards were being widely copied
throughout . the medieval world. Dur¬
ing the Reformation, New Year cards
lost some of their following but they
re-emerged in the 18th century larger,
more secular and more popular than
before. An Italian card of the period
pictures a Utopian world. Streams
flow with milk and honey, dinner tables
abound with every type of delicacy,
precious stones and magnificent clothes
lie at hand. There is everything that
one could desire in the New Year. Only
the prison seems at first to strike a
discordant note, but it is intended for
the man who tries to work in the per¬
fect Utopian New Year world.
A Viennese card of a century later
shows a harassed burgher of the city
surrounded by a crowd of well-wishers.*
It turns out that the well-wishers are
also , creditors, presenting the burgher
with bills as well as the season's greet¬
ings. As he receives the good wishes
the burgher is forced to dip into his
purse and pay his debts. His New Year
is thoroughly miserable.
Working men in the 19th century
began to send New Year cards that
advertised their various professions. A
news vendor might add the news of
war and peace, tell of a disaster at
home or abroad; include the weather
forecast and other informative tit bits.
School children began to use the New
Year card to show off their newly ac¬
quired skill in writing.
Some cards of the period resembled
valentines with love boughs, bouquets
of flowers, possibly a young couple and
a romantic poem. Like the valentine
these New Year greetings were sent
anonymously. Not all the 19th century
cards were so tender. A German card
shows a group of middle aged women
ignoring an immaculately dressed
dandy who represents the New Year.
The women are determined to remain
unaware of the dandy's existence and
their own advancing age.
England claims to have produced the
first true Christmas card. It was
designed in 1843 by John C. Horsley and
reads: "A Merry Christmas and Happy
New Year to You". The card shows a
family gathered round their Christmas
table, glasses raised as if to toast the
season. Though some people criticized
this first Christmas card, suspecting it
of "encouraging drunkenness", it start¬
ed a new fashion and brought an end
to the supremacy of the New Year
Card.
But this does not mean the medieval
tradition is lost. In many countries
the New Year is still the occasion
when gifts and greetings are exchang¬
ed.
And even where Christmas Day and
Christmas greeting cards are accorded
first importance no true, self-respect¬
ing Christmas card will ignore its
older more venerable, ancestor and
omit a New Year wish.
RAS ESSANA
14 centuries of the Moslem faith
RAS ESSANA '.s the term used
throughout the Arab world
for the beginning, literally the
"head", of the year. This day cele¬
brates the flight of the prophet
Mohammed from Mecca to Medina
some fourteen centuries ago. The
festival is an expression of reve¬
rence for Mohammed and his fight
against evil and dates back to the
late fifth and early sixth centu¬
ries of the Islamic calendar. On
this day the whole of the Moslem
world is united in a ceremonial
which in its main features is very
similar.
On the eve of Ras Essana build
ings in almost every city and
town are lit with multi-coloured
lights and people throng the
streets. Every Arab is under a re¬
ligious obligation to keep open
house on this day and give alms
to the needy.
The religious aspect of Ras Es¬
sana is underlined by the recital of
Suras from the Koran, particu¬
larly those which tell of the flight
of the Prophet. Panegyric poems
of a legendary character, the
Madayeh, are also chanted. These
tell of the birth and life of Mo¬
hammed, his virtues and his strug¬
gles against the forces of evil.
THE FIVE
SLEEPLESS
NIGHTS OF
MONGHOSAN
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Nr 12. 1955
New Year, or what corresponds to it among the Penihing Dayaks
(or Dyaks) of the Upper Mahakam, in Borneo, is called the Monghosan.
But as the sense of the passage of time is not particularly strong among
these people several years may elapse between each "New Year".
The date is decided by the head priest of the tribe who consults the
aso-do, a wooden pole serving as an agrarian and magical calendar (I).
Though the length of shadow cast by the aso-do helps to determine
the arrival of the Monghosan, the real decision comes when the
tribal chief notices a certain lassitude among his people, and thus the
need for a "renewal", and sends out his warriors on a head-hunting
expedition, for* which a veteran head-hunter (2) is collecting a handful
of branches with' magic powers. All fires are' put out until the head
is brought back in triumph to the village and is attached to a beam
on the communal hut (4). Huts are spread with new earth brought
back in cane baskets (6) by virgin girls, and fires are made by rubbing
a piece of cane in a dry tree trunk. The Dayaks then go out into the
forest to uproot the Mahang, (3) a sacred tree and bring it back to
the village. In this tree lives the good spirit which should now take
up its dwelling in the newly-cut head and bring good luck to the tribe.
For four days and five nights there is no sleep in the village. Everyone
joins in the slow turning circles (5). Each taking part wears the same
number of bird plumes as he has heads to his credit. At dawn on the
fifth day the entire tribe goes in procession to the river and plunges
in for a refreshing bathe. A gargantuan feast ends the festival
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
HAPPY NEW YEAR
IN BALI
The gifts to the gods
a re eaten by mortals
Each year in Bali lasts only
2 1 0 days. The date of the
" Galungan ", or Balinese New
Year, thus changes annually.
The festivities are spread out
over a ten-day period during
which it is believed that the
departed ancestors return to
earth to receive offerings and
bring happiness. Before the
festivities, houses and temples
are freshly decorated and the
offerings carefully prepared.
Many of these "constructions"
are more than six feet tall
and are made of straw, inter¬
laced with yellow, red or
white rice and ornamented
with frangipani flowers and
palm fronds (See cover photo
and photo No. I on this page).
During the Galgungan festi¬
vities the "Barong", a béné¬
ficient animal dear to the
hearts of all Balinese, makes
its appearance (2). This dra¬
gon-like animal is'manceuvered
by two dancers who weave
their way along the island
paths. The leaps and capers
of the Barong delight old and
young alike, the more so as they
symbolize the fight between
the forces of good and evil.
Work in preparing the ancestor
offerings lasts more than two
weeks. Once ready they are
taken to the temple (4) where
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Nr 12. 1955
This Balinese street scene (3) shows some traditional dishes asso¬
ciated with the Galgungan festivities being prepared. The fattest
pigs are killed, cut into small pieces and, after being heavily spiced,
impaled on sticks. A different fate awaits the suckling pigs which
are first of all roasted on a spit. The meat is chopped up and
mixed with fresh blood spiced and flavoured with edible flowers.
Photos and text copyright by Andre Martin
Preceded by the women carrying
multi-coloured offerings Balinese
men follow in procession with large
bamboo platforms on their shoul¬
ders, on which are carefully-built
scale model houses representing
the dwellings of their ancestors
bountiful gods (5 and 6). During
the Galgungan festivities, ancient
custom requires the Balinese to
carry these model houses to cer¬
tain holy places fixed by the priests.
they remain on view for some
days. After this period, the
Balinese, a realistic people full of
common sense, come to collect
them, for they realize that
although the offerings are made
for the gods, they can only
be eaten by human beings.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
When today descendants of the
Incas celebrate the New Year it
is an experience one cannot
easily forget. From every village and
hamlet high up in the Andean Cordil¬
lera down to the fringe of the tropical
forest the Indians of Bolivia and Peru
welcome the day with great merry¬
making.
These festivities, however, are but a
faint echo of the sumptuous ceremonies
of the Imperial Inca Empire of the
past. Those which took place in the
holy city of Cuzco, capital of "the four
corners of the world," have been vividly
described by Garcilaso de la Vega, the
16th century chronicler, who was him¬
self of Inca descent.
these mandones, or leaders, are chosen
by the Indians themselves in a series
of discussions and negotiations to
which white men are not admitted.
The ceremony of their installation has
both religious and secular features, and
is imbued with a grave dignity which
may equally well be Spanish or Indian
in origin.
On January 1 1954, 1 was in the Peru¬
vian village of Juli, on the shores of
Lake Titicaca, which occupies an out¬
standing place in the annals of Span¬
ish-American religious art. A huge
crowd of Indians packed the principal
church, with its gilded baroque mould¬
ings and repellent or blood-stained
statues. The impassive, stern-faced
Attended by the Emperor and all the
provincial governors, a complex ritual,
called Inti raymi, was held in June to
open a new cycle of festivities and
work. It was marked by ceremonies
of revival and purification characteris¬
tic of man's constant attempt to
express in symbols the pendulum swing
from death to resurrection.
What remains of all these sacrifices,
processions and dances? Very little.
Four centuries of wretchedness and
decadence, however, have not entire¬
ly effaced the old customs. And the
New Year, now fixed at January 1, is
one of the occasions when the ghosts
of ancient traditions emerge from the
mists of past history. The day no lon¬
ger marks the opening of the religious
year, and it has lost its seasonal impli¬
cations. But it is of political import¬
ance, for on that day the hilakata,
alcades and campos (local leaders) who
have replaced the ancient Inca officials
are installed in office,
Although nominated by the owners
of the haciendas (ranches) or by the
authorities in the Andean republics,
hilakata, wearing red woollen caps and
ample red ponchos, stood in a double
row, each holding his staff of office a
magnificent silver-knobbed cane, hand¬
ed down from one chief to the next
since Spanish colonial times.
In the half-light of the church rose
the heart-rending sadness of Aymara
Indian chants, accompanied by the
beating of drums and the plaintive
notes of Pan pipes.
Masked men in spangled coats
Groups of masked men were dancing
in the streets. Some of them
wore jaguar masks, others were
decked with condor's wings symbols
of some long-forgotten divinities
combined with the wigs and spangled
coats of 17th cçntury Spain.
That day, I encountered, a strange
procession which suddenly arrived
outside the Yunguyo church where the
Indian authorities were attending
mass. It was led by a horseman, whose
wife rode a little way behind him.
Both were reeling drunk, swaying dan
gerously in the saddle, and would in¬
evitably have fallen to the ground if
their companions had not struggled to
keep them in place. Other horsemen,
accompanied by musicians, rode mer¬
rily into view and vanished, one after
another, into the surrounding houses
from which issued the sound of flutes
and the rolling of drums. These were
the new officials, taking up their duties.
The parade would not have particu¬
larly impressed me, but for their re¬
markable get-up. Their hats and
waistcoats were made of pastry, they
wore rings of bread round their necks
and arms, and similar rings were hung
about their clothes. Bread is a delicacy
for the Indians, so it was as though the
hilakata and alcades
had dressed up as Sug¬
arplum Fairies. Their
appetizing appearance
in the literal sense of
the words at once
reminded me of the
designs on many of the
vases found in ancient
Peruvian tombs. These
depict dancers decked,
not with rolls of bread,
but with various kinds
of fruits and vegetables.
Archaeologists believe
that these scenes illus¬
trate fertility rites an
interpretation thatwould
seem to apply to the
strange dress of the
mandones, who display
these symbols of pros¬
perity to convince the
spectators that bread
will be plentiful during
their terms of office and
that the year that is
beginning will be a happy one.
One New Year's Day in the Andes
was, I think, among the most exciting
in my career as an ethno¬
grapher. It was on January 1 just
twenty years ago, that I reached the
village of the Chipaya Indians. For a
number of years I had been longing to
visit these Indians, who weçe known
only through a booklet written about
them by an amateur archaeologist,
M. Posnansky. Its contents were, how¬
ever, enough to fire the imagination of
a student who hoped to specialize in
the study of the Andean civilizations.
It revealed that in one of the most
remote regions of the Andean plateau,
at an altitude of some 13.000 feet,
beyond sandy deserts and great lagoons
where pink flamingoes congregated,
there was a village whose inhabitants
seemed to have been forgotten by his¬
tory and were living now, well into the
20th century, just äs they had in the
heyday of the Inca Empire. Moreover,
they spoke a language different from
the Quechua and Aymara tongues
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Nr 12. 1955
which are used almost everywhere in
Bolivia.
In more than one sense the Chipayas
were chullpa puchu mummified re¬
mains. I will not describe my journey
across the sand dunes, my slow pro¬
gress over the desolate plains of the
Chipaya territory. The day I arrived
within sight of the village, the mirage,
frequent at that time of year, had en¬
larged and multiplfed the' huts to a
point where I seemed to be approach¬
ing a strange city beside a great
non-existent lake in which strange,
jagged mountain peaks were reflected.
The promise held out by this optical
illusion was nothing; however, com¬
pared with the thrill I felt on being
surrounded by a group of Chipaya
women.
Imagine the stupefaction of an arch¬
aeologist on finding himself confront¬
ed by mummies who have stripped
off their bandages and dressed them¬
selves once more in the clothes of their
period. The women surrounding me
were dressed exactly like those who
had, four centuries earlier, crowded to
gaze at the conquistador Almagro when
he crossed these same deserts, and they
also resembled the dried-up bodies
found in burial caves.
I was particularly struck by one
detail the tinkling of the little bronze
figures that dangled from the innume¬
rable plaits in which these
women's hair was arranged. (Cont'd on
I had seen these humble next pogej
n>
( J^^r%k U
vr
V vWv 1
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Living Ghosts
of
the Incas
(Continued^
ornaments be¬
fore in the La
Paz museum,
among the ob¬
jects found in
the great In¬
dian city of
T i ah u anaco,
which flourish¬
ed long before the Incas gained
control of the Andean plateau.
Like their neighbours, the Aymarás,
the Chipayas were holding their New
Year festivities that day. I can still
see the interior of a round hut in
which my friend Mamani, who had
just been elected corregidor (an old
Spanish title) was standing behind a
low table whereon lay a sheep's head.
The Indiansmen and women alike-
filed past to do homage to him,
stretching out their arms with
supplicating gestures. They offered
him two goblets, in accordance with
Inca etiquette, which requires that any
invitation to drink shall be conveyed
in this way. Each of them poured a
libation of alcohol to the sacrificed
animal, and placed an offering of coca
leaves before it. Their duty thus ful¬
filled, they joined the people who were
already dancing in the open space
separating the two clans.
Mournful songs and Pan pipes
They were led by the outgoing al¬
calde, who had tied round his
body a black and white woollen
sling from which little cords hung in
skeins, covering him down to the knees.
He had stuck flowers in his hat, and
from his forehead rose two big leaves,
reminiscent of the metal stems that
topped the headbands of the Inca
chieftains. Waving a white banner and
followed by the dancers and flute
players, he advanced, stopping at each
hut to claim a tribute of chicha (a
fermented drink) for himself and his
band. In exchange he allowed the
host to take over the white banner and
direct the movements of the dancers.
A fertility rite is, however, associated
with these secular rejoicings. On
Christmas Eve the women had placed
little clay models of lamas and sheep
on the altar of the church built by the
villagers. On New Year's Day these
little figures were given back to them.
Handling them with respect, they kis¬
sed them and carried them home,
convinced that their own animals
were thus assured of many offspring.
Far into the night the relentless
silence of the Andean plateau was rent
by the notes of Pan pipes and the
sound of mournful songs; then the
voices died away, to be replaced by an
oppressive calm. The New Year cele¬
brations were over, and in their dark
huts the Indians lay asleep, preparing
to resume the monotonous course of
their cheerless lives.
Copyright Verger-ADEP
'BOWLER-HATTED' WOMEN with swirling skirts and voluminous petticoats dance in 'the village
square of Tiahuanaco, Bolivia, to the sound of drum and pipe, in honour of the New Year. In the
evening, everyone goes to the Church to ask for God's blessing on the village and its inhabitants.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Nr 12. 1955
by
Kbushwant
Singh
CANDLE-LIT
DIYVALI EVE
For those Hindus who
follow the Vikrama cal¬
endar, Diwali night is
both a festival of lights
and a New Year cele¬
bration. Here, several
Hindu women in exqui¬
site saris light the candles
in front of their house.
Far right, a building in
New Delhi brillantly illu¬
minated for Diwali night.
Land of many calendars
Gove, ol India Information Service.
India is not only a land of many races, religions, languages
and cultures but also one of many calendars. Practically
every linguistic and religious group has one of its own
and some have different ones for different purposes. If it
hadn't been for the official recognition of the Roman Calen¬
dar, the various methods of calculation in use would have
made the celebration of national days, festivals, anniversaries
and birthdays completely chaotic.
Since there are more than a dozen calendars in use, there
are more than a dozen New Year Days, some based on the
movements of the sun, some on those of the moon, and yet
others (the majority) on a combination of the two. So, the
matter of sending a New Year's greeting card to Indian
friends %is not as simple an affair as it is in Europe or the
United States. Fortunately the practice of sending New Year
cards is not very common and those who do send them, time
them for January, as in the Christian world. In recent years
the custom of sending greetings cards has also been extended
to the first Baisakh (April) and Diwali, (early November).
If we were to start with the Punjab in the North we would
find three independent systems of reckoning apart of course,
from the official one (January). The one used for determin¬
ing religious festivals is known as the Kali Era and according
to this we are already in the 51st century. The New Year is
precisely calculated to have begun "at midnight on the
Thursday corresponding to February 17-18, 3102 B.C. Old
Style". The only other purpose for which the Kali Era has
been used is writing poetry. Each letter of the alphabet has
numerical value, and poets indicate the date of an event they
are describing by using the precise number of appropriate
letters in their verse.
The most popular system in use in the whole of Northern
India (except Bengal) is the Vikrami Era. It started with
the coronation of King Vikramaditya, a monarch about whom
historians know little, but whose accession is generally consi¬
dered to have taken place two thousand and fourteen years
ago. This system, like the Kali, is both lunar and solar.
The New Year according to this calendar varies with the pur¬
pose one has in mind. If it is simply to determine a date,
the first month is the first day of the month of Chaitra
which will be some time in February. If it is to balance
accounts, then the year begins in the month of Kartika to
be precise, on Diwali, the day of the festival of the lamps.
If you happen to be a Sikh, then the matter is even more
confused. The very orthodox compute their dates from the
birthday of the founder of the Sikh religion, Nanak (1469-
1539), and call the era Nanákshahi. Most however, accept
the Vikrami calendar except that they do not take Chaitra as
the first month of the year, as do the Hindus, but the follow¬
ing month, Baisakh.
Sired by a mystic serpent king
Rivalling the popularity of the Vikrami calendar in the
North is the Saka calendar used in Central and South
India. According to this calendar 1956 A.D. will only
be 1879. The interesting thing about the Saka is its mythical
origin. It is said to commence from the day when King
Salivahan ascended the throne of the kingdom of Ujjain.
According to legend, his predecessor on the throne, Soma-
krant, had been promised immunity by the gods from all
save one who was older than his mother. King Somakrant
was led to his doom by his own anxiety to find a man who
answered this description. Salivahan, born of a virgin of
his own age, and sired by a mystic serpent king,
killed Somakrant and seized his kingdom. (Cont'd on
Apart from these three calendars there are a page 20)
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
In Bengal and Assam, New Year celebra¬
tions take place during the month of Bai¬
sakh which corresponds to the Western
month of April. The calendar followed in
these parts of India was introduced by
King Sakabda in the seventh century A.D.
On these pages are some of the varied
and picturesque spectacles which can be
seen during this New Year period. This
religious" festival is marked in towns and
villages by the mellahs, or fairs, at which
some of the scenes shown here were
photographed. (I) On the banks of the
Brahmaputra a fisherman mends his nets
ready for the first -New Year trip. (2)
Outside a small temple a priest, having
fed his goat and pigeons, awaits the arrival
of the faithful. (3) Two youthful dancers.
As girls are not allowed to dance in public,
boy on left is disguised in women's clothes.
(4) Flute, seller with his "tree" of wares
expects to make plenty of sales during the
celebrations when music and dancing are
the order of the day. (5) Clutching a kid
in his arms a boys stares fascinated at the
spectacle of a Sbdou, or holy man. (6)
The Sadou beats his tambourine and sings
of the beauties of New Year's Day. By-
foretelling that there will be no floods or
famine in the New Year, he hopes to
fill his collecting pail with rupees. (7)
Their bodies and heads painted blue and
red, and their horns silvered and gilded,
two sacred cows are led in a procession.
(8) Before an altar dedicated to different
Hindu Gods, the deer hunting dance is
performed. (9) Once a year the Boros,
people of Tibetan origin, leave their jungle
homes and travel sometimes as much as
50 miles on foot to buy goods at the vast
New Year mellahs. Here they can choose
from a variety of goods which are not
available in their villages. (10) From
early morning on New Year's Day, the
old women of the village summon up good
auguries for the coming year by making
strange calls and clapping their hands.
(II) Crowded streets on the days of the
fair need some traffic control. Here,
villagers have set up (as a joke) an effigy
of a Calcutta traffic policeman. (12) New
Year dolls, some of which represent Hindu
Gods, are made of glazed and painted clay.
( I 3) Peacock feather fans, plastic cups, oil
lamps and pictures of the Taj Mahal and
Indian films stars make up the stock-in-
trade of this itinerant merchant from
Calcutta. (14) A dance depicting the
sowing, harvesting, threshing and storing
of the grain. It is always performed at
the New Year in the belief that it will
bring good luck for the harvest in the
coming year.
All photos copyright Gabrieile Bertrand
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. N1* 12. 1955
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
INDIA
(Continued
from p. 17)
number of other important systems of time
reckoning known to the Hindu social system.
These are the Bengali San used in Bengal,
the Magi San used in Assam, the Sapta-
Rishi Kala used in Kashmir and the
Kollum used in Malabar.
Outside Hindu society there are other religious minorities
who have their own calendars and their own New Year days.
The most important group 35 million Moslems use the
lunar system starting with the Hegira, the flight of the Pro¬
phet Mohammed from Mecca to Medina. Since the lunar
month is shorter than the solar, the Moslem New Year's day
falls at different times of the year.
The Christians, second largest minority community num¬
bering over eight million, use the Roman calendar. They
celebrate it in much the same way as Christians elsewhere
exchanging greetings cards and wishing each other hap¬
piness. The smallest of all India's religious minorities, the
Parsees, who number less than half-a-million, start their
calendar with the accession of Yezdajrid to the Persian
throne in 632 A.D. Their New Year's day is the first day of
Farvirdin which corresponds to September 5.
Along with this conglomeration of calendars and commu¬
nities goes a vast variety of celebrations differing with each
sect in every part of the country. The only thing all these
festivities have in common is that New Year's day itself does
not have as much significance as the mythical or historical
events associated with it.
For six million Sikhs, New Year's day is really holy. On
the morning of the first of Baisakh (also New Year's day for
othe.r peoples in certain paits of India) the last of their ten
Gurus, (holy men), Gobind Singh (1666-1708), assembled
several thousands of his followers and asked for the heads of
five for sacrifice. One after another these men were led inside
a tent. The Guru emerged each time, his sword dripping
blood, and asked for the next victim. Actually the ceremony
was conducted only to test the faith of his disciples, for
inside the tent the only victims were goats he had killed.
He baptised these five men and made them swear to live
the lives of soldiers.
Lamps are lit for the spirits,
meteors rise from the ground
On every first Baisakh, Sikh temples and homes have a
special religious ceremony. In the afternoon their
sacred book, the Granth, is taken out on a gaily
decorated carriage guarded by five men with drawn swords
in memory of the first converts.
What April 1 is to the business world in some Western
European countries namely, the start of the new finan¬
cial year so Diwali is to the Indian merchant community.
Although it is only a matter of closing one set of account
books and starting new ones, it is done with great ceremony.
Houses are whitewashed and the appropriate gods worship¬
ped with the new account books lying at their feet. Presents
are sent to relations and friends. At night the houses are
lit with oil lamps and candles ; hence the name Diwali, the
cluster of lights.
Diwali has many origins ascribed to it. The most popular
explanation is that on this day the god Rama, a reincarna¬
tion of Vishnu, returned home after his victory over the
demon King of Ceylon who had abducted his wife, Sita.
Amongst the Maharthas of Central India, Diwali is the occa¬
sion for the worship of the god King Bali who was maliciously
overthrown by Vishnu. In Bengal lamps are lit and carried
on long poles to light the way of departed spirits to their
ultimate destination.
The common factor in all the celebrations is the use of
illuminations and fireworks. Anyone travelling by air on
Diwali night would see as many lights beneath him as in the
heavens above and many more meteors shooting upwards.
The philosophers believe that Diwali symbolises the triumph
of light over darkness, of truth over falsehood. What better
wish could one make on a New Year's day th¡j.n affirm one's
faith in the ultimate triumph of good over evil?
20
Elephants mad
elegant for th
festival
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Nr 12. 1955
I. In the jungles of Assam, the
hunters of wild elephants prepare
to celebrate the New Year. They
clear spaces in the forest and put up
their wood and rush huts. 2. To
their obvious enjoyment the ele¬
phants are given a good bath. 3.
A mahout paints the forehead and
ears of his beast in vivid colours.
4. Unpolished please! To give his
charge a manicure the mahout needs
an outsize in nail files. But the
elephant seems to appreciate the
need for having his nails trimmed.
5. Beauty treatment. Painted, ma¬
nicured, washed and draped in
sumptuous and richly-worked cloths
they are all ready to take part in a
religious procession. 6. Hunters
on the trail. A New Year hunting
party moving through the bhila or
jungle grass. The hunters are hon¬
our bound to provide plenty of
game for the New Year feast.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
ft,c$
FIREMEN'S REVIEW is time-honoured feature of
Tokyo New Year celebrations. Above, firemen
carry symbolic standards at parade in Imperial Palace
Plaza. Right, highlight of review: an amazing acro¬
batic display by firemen of the Tokyo brigade.
Lobsters for
a long life;
seaweed for
a happy one
by Shigeo Kimura
The celebration of O-STio-Gaiswthe Japanese New Year
Festival' has both a moral and mythological sig¬
nificance. Morally, it is an expression of determina¬
tion for a.new life in the coming year. Mythologically, it is
a complicated form of offering to Toski-Kami, or the God
of the Year, who supposedly grants blessings and protection
from misfortunes throughout the year.
The customs which are observed are many and varied.
Some of them are of Chinese origin and others are based
on age-old Japanese traditions. They differ according to
the.localities where they are observed, but the principal ones
are almost universal throughout the nation.
The New Year season lasts for one month beginning on
January 1, as the special name of the first month Q-Sho-
Gatsu means. However, the festivities take place only on
the first seven days, of which the first two or three are
regarded as the most important. During this period the
whole nation gives itself up to the enjoyment of festivities
in a traditional manner.
The Imperial Household, symbol of the Japanese people,
offers prayers for further benevolence of its ancestral deities,
the Government suspends its administrative activities, and
factories, shops and offices are all closed. In short, the
whole country is in a state of festive relaxation during the
holidays.
Although the hustle and bustle of modern life tend to
destroy some of the traditional distinctive features of Japa¬
nese New Year celebrations, nevertheless many still follow
their age-old pattern.
The last day of the year is called Omisoka. It is New
Year's Eve. It is, in a sense, a day of purification. We
Japanese, eager to welcome the New Year in a happy and
22
reverent mood, clean our houses and purify ourselves.
Late at night we eat a few bowlfuls of Soba or Japanese
noodles, which are long and slender and are believed to
possess magical qualities which will ensure longevity. We
then sit by' the fireside or around the hearth resting and
talking until just before midnight. A few minutes before
twelve the temple bells throughout the country start ringing.
The bells are rung 108 times to drive away 108 evils. Re¬
sounding on the wintry air, the bells toll the knell for the
parting year.
Respectful hand-claps
greet the morning sun
We decorate our houses with special devices. Outside
decorations include the Kadomatsu and Shimekazari.
"Kadomatsu", meaning the gate pine, is usually set
up on both sides of the front entrance. It consists of pine-
branches, plum-twigs and bamboo-poles bundled into the
shape of a stock. Often two tall bamboo-fronds are used as
substitutes. We believe these plants to be symbols of good
omen, and because of their hardiness, to denote longevity.
Shimekazari is a straw rope decorated with a kind of orange,
called Daidai, and fern leaves. It is usually hung above the
front door. The word Daidai has the same pronunciation as
the words meaning "'from generation to generation", while
the fern leaves with their multiplicity of fronds suggest
expanding prosperity.
For interior decoration we have Osonae which is placed on
a little stand of plain wood in the alcove. On it
are a pair of Mochi or rice-cakes and several (Cont'd on
other things of good omen. Among these is page 24)
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Nr 12. 1955
THE 'KAGAM I MOCHI' (I) is something without
which no Japanese New Year celebration would be
complete. Round rice cakes are arranged with symbols
of good luck a lobster (meaning longevity) an orange,
pieces of fern and kelp and paper festoons. (2) Tradi¬
tional game with I 00 poem cards is played by young
women in decorative kimonos. (3) Shime-kazari or
"sacred rope" is hung above front door to bring good
luck. (4) Toso (sweet rice wine) is offered to New
Year guests in small cups (right) along with delicacies
kept in a nest of boxes. (5) Pounding rice to make
the traditional mochi or rice cakes.
Photos Japanese Tourist Association and
japan Overseas Publicity Association
mWmW*^' 1 ^1
il ff
r jü
*SáW
4
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
LOBSTERS
IN JAPAN
(Continued1)
sometimes included a lobster. Since the
lobster's back is bent, this' symbol expresses
the wish that one may enjoy a very long
life until one's back is bent until it re¬
sembles that of a lobster.
At bréale of day we get up and go to a
nearby stream or well for Wakamizu, or the first water of
the year. With this we wash ourselves. This water is
believed to have the power of preserving health throughout
the year. We then exchange New Year greetings with our
family and offer prayers at the family altar. At breakfast
we sit down together in a circle, clad in our best clothes with
the grownups in formal dress and young ones in colourful
kimonos. It is also customary for adults to go out into the
garden and pay respect to the morning sun by clapping their
hands.
The first feast of the New Year is very special. We first
of all take, in the order of family seniority, a thimbleful of
Toso, sweet saké spiced
with fragrant herbs, which
is believed to promote
health. Then follow vari¬
ous sumptuous dishes. Zoni
comes first. It is a kind of
soup which is as indispen¬
sable for the New Year
celebrations as rice is on
any other day of the year.
The chief ingredient is
Mochi or ricecakes, cut in
rectangular pieces and boil¬
ed with different kinds of
vegetables.
Mochi signifies fullness,
abundance and plenty, and
is said to give warmth to
our bodies. Other foods
which accompany the Zoni
include carp, famous for its
energy and determination
to surmount obstacles; black
beans, symbolic of robust
health; chestnuts for suc¬
cess and dried sea-weed,
Kombu, which is synony¬
mous with another Japanese
word for happiness. The
yellow petals of a variety of
chrysanthemum (eaten as a
salad) are frequently used
to enrich the colour scheme
of the table, the prepara¬
tion of this meal and in
fact of all Japanese meals
being made with a special
concern for colour.
SMILING KITE-FLIERS show off
kite-flying is a serious hobby for old
colourful kites shown here is a gift
Before or after the first
meal we visit, usually with our family, the nearest shrines
and temples to seek divine bliss for the year. This visit is
called Hatsu-mode which means literally first pilgrimage.
The Shishi-mai dancers lions
with grotesque, red faces
In the morning or afternoon we make a round of visits to
our friends, carrying a large stock visiting cards.
Merchants and shopkeepers usually bring with them a
bundle of new towels with their names inscribed on them.
These are courtesy visits; an expression of gratitude for
patronage during the past year, the towels serving as visiting
cards.
On New Year's Day we are visited by a troupe of Shishi-
mai dancers, a feature of this festive season. The dancers
wear a big mask, the Shishi, or a conventionalized lion with
a grotesque red face. They perform a gay dance to the
accompaniment of a drum and a flute. Young people are
particularly fond of this comic dance and often follow the
dancers out into the streets. But the smaller children often
find the lion mask something of a frightening nightmare.
Hyakunin Isshu hundred
poems from a hundred people
OiBANE or Battledore and Shuttlecock is an outdoor game
particularly favoured by young girls. When they miss
a stroke they sometimes have to undergo the penalty
of having their faces smeared with ink. The battledores
which they use are artistically decorated with all kinds of
woven silk figures and flowers.
Boys enjoy kite-flying Tako-agé in the streets and fields.
The kites designed in gay colours make an amazing pattern
as they rise into the sky.
In the evening we have
a Katu.ta - tori party a
poem card ' game. The
game is played with a set
of two hundred cards, nam¬
ed in Japanese Hyakunin
Isshu, literally a hundred
poems from a hundred
people. It is an anthology
of a hundred Waka or 31-
syllable odes composed by
historically celebrated poets
and poetesses. Half the
cards, each containing the
whole poem and usually the
author's portrait are used
for reading. The other
half, each containing only
the last two lines of the
poem, are used for playing.
All the participants hunch
forward over the playing
cards arranged on the Ta-
tami or straw mat, exchang¬
ing quick glances so as to
pick up the card correspond¬
ing to the poem which is
being read aloud. There
are only a few sets of cards
of this kind, of which the
most popular is that col¬
lected by Fujiwara Teika,
a 13th century nobleman.
Of the many public festi¬
vities still extant in Japan,
Dezomeshiki or the Fire¬
men's First Parade is per¬
haps the most celebrated.
It is held in Tokyo and
some other of the principal Japanese cities, with the partici¬
pation of firemen dressed in ancient uniforms.
The exhibitions given by the firemen are particularly in¬
teresting, being one of the special features of the capital
since the Edo Period. The acrobatic performances on the
tops of the ladders were initiated in those days to show the
agility of Edo firemen when confronted with danger. Even
after the Restoration of 1868, the feats were performed in
the same traditional spirit as before and thrilling man
vres in the air still continued for the enjoyment of Tokyo
citizens.
Due to the changed conditions of the capital, however, the
old system of fire brigades became obsolete and its reorga¬
nization was imperative to cope with modern requirements.
Thus the new system, installed in 1939, brought an end for
a time to the time-honoured exhibition. Recently to the peo¬
ple's delight, the old custom was revived.
Matsunouchi, or the days of the gate pine, which comprise
the first week of the New Year, ends on January 7. On the
preceding night we gather up all the decorations and burn
them for exorcising purposes. The New Year festivities gra¬
dually die away and everything goes back to normal.
Japanese Tourist Association
their New Year presents. In Japan,
and young alike and a tako one of the
Japanese boys welcome at New Year.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Nr 12. 1955
WINTER 'S DEATH is
symbolized by this figure
of plaited straw with
empty ears of wheat.
BEARDED MASK in birch bark
found in festivities in Siberia.
Such masks are widely used in
peasant games and masquerades.
STAG'S HEAD mask
from Rumania is typical
of many used in Eastern
European countries.
Old Slav legends
NIGHT OF
THE GOATS
AND GILDED
PLOUGHS
by Eveline Falck
All photos copyright Musée de l'Homme, Paris.
Snovym godom's novym scast'em"
(With the New Year new happi¬
ness), say the Russians as they
kiss one another on New Year's Eve
once called the Vasili vecer (Saint-Bas¬
il's night) or the Melanka (Saint Mel-
ania's night). What was the "new
happiness" that they wished one an¬
other "with the New Year ?"
In early times the Slav peoples did
not bother much about astronomy or
the exact computation of time ; as
peasant farmers, their calendar de¬
pended primarily on the cycle of plant
growth. Whether the year began in
winter or in spring, they wanted it to
bring rich harvests. And, on Saint
Basil's night, they would try to divine
whether or not the season would be
"scedraja" (generous) to them.
In White Russia, two young men were
taken round from house to house, one
richly clad and wearing a crown of rye,
and the other in rags with a crown of
straw. Their garb was concealed un¬
der voluminous coverings and the head
of every household had to try and guess
which was which ; if he chose the
former, prosperity awaited him, but if
the latter, poverty and death.
The first of January was not origi¬
nally a true traditional holiday in any
of the Slav countries. The ceremonies
connected with it were of an official
character and principally associated
with the towns. In olden times, the
Russian Tsars used to set out with
great pomp to "meet" the New Year on
the Kremlin Square on the first of
September. This was when the civil
year began, while the ecclesiastical year
commenced on the first of March. In
1505, it was decided that the same date
should be fixed for both and until the
eighteenth century that date was the
first of September.
But in the year 7203 since the crea¬
tion of the world (i.e. 1699), Peter the
Great decided that the first of January
should be the beginning of the year,
and the people were required by order
to hold rejoicings on that day, to
exchange good wishes, and to decorate
houses with pine, fir and juniper.
The peasants, for their part, were in
the habit of greeting the New Year in
March, with the spring. Ovsen, a word
which may be derived either from oves
(oats) or from vesna (spring), personi¬
fied the New Year. An old song tells
us that he came in on a bridge built
by the boyars from planks of pine-wood
cut in the forest. "Ovsen and the New
Year will pass that way." After 1699
Ovsen had to change the time of his
coming, and the people went out to
meet him on Saint Basil's day (Jan. 1).
The winter festival took the place of
the spring festival, but was fitted into
the extremely complex cycle of the
winter solstice and Christian rites.
The birth of Christ, of the sun and of
the year merged together. The
Church, being unable to abolish the
pagan festivals, took them over and
gave them countenance by transferring
the date of the birth of Christ from
January 6 to December 25, so that it
coincided with the winter solstice.
Each pagan rite was given a Christian
significance. The straw scattered on
the ground in fertility rites became the
straw of the manger ; the miraculous
water became the water of the Kresce-
nie or Baptism of Christ (Epiphany) ;
the grains with which the Polish peas¬
ants pelted one another for luck on
St. Stephen's day (December 26) came
to symboKze the stones which had been
cast at the martyr.
God and the Saints took the place
of the pagan divinities. The prophet
Elijah, who was held in great honour
in Russia, ousted Perun, the god of
thunder. His feast-day fell in the
summer but he also came on Saint
Basil's day to fertilize the earth : "He
holds whips of wire and tin. He shakes
them here and there. The grain springs
up". The old pagan cycle of
twelve days fitted in between (Cont'd on
Rozdestvo (Christmas) and next PaBe
Director of the Arctic Department at France's Musée
de l'Homme in Paris, Eveline Falck is an authority on
Siberia and the Slay countries. One of her most signi¬
ficant publications Is "Rites de la Chasse en Sibérie"
(Hunting Rites, in Siberia).
THE GOAT ¡s a tra¬
ditional figure in the
gay processions which
pass from house to
house in Russian vil¬
lages on New Year's
Eve. Drawing here
is from the Ukraine.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Night of
the goats
(Continued)
Krescenie (the Baptism of Christ).
It is a critical period. Will the sun
and the seasons, having run their
course, resume it again ? It is a time
of preparation and decision for the
coming year, and the twelve days are
the twelve months in miniature. The
Poles foretell the weather for the
twelve coming months by the weather
in- the last twelve days of the year.
Supernatural events are possible at
this time: animals may speak, trees
may suddenly bear fruit, and some¬
times golden fruit, the heavens may
open, water may cure infirmities
whence the custom of drawing water
from holes cut in the ice to wash and
to sprinkle over the cattle and even, in
some cases, of bathing in the streams
and immersing the children. The
Church took over this rite as a com¬
memoration of the Baptism of Christ
and made it a solemn ceremony, at
which the Tsar was present on the
banks of the Neva.
This period of twelve days' and, above
all, of twelve "holy" nights is also one
of the times at which the dead return
to earth; places are set for them at
table and they are offered their portion
of the New Year feast. God and His
Saints come down to earth and walk
among men to see how they are living.
Three hairs from a cat
But evil spirits, sorcerers and wolves
may also appear, chiefly on the
last night of the year, "the night
of terror". On that night, as the Sibe¬
rian Russians believe, the "force of
evil" is let loose upon the face of the
earth and men and beasts must stay
within shelter, under the protection of
the sign of the Cross, drawn in soot
upon the door. These perils of the
New Year continue until Epiphany.
At Christmas or on the first of Janu¬
ary, according to the locality, the
evil spirits are driven out by firing
guns, beating out every nook and
cranny with sticks, and with loud
shouting. On Christmas night, the
Slovaks pull out three hairs from a cat,
dip them in holy water and burn them,
so as to put the evil spirits to flight.
The very name of the evil spirit is sig¬
nificant: Karacun, or Korocun, mean¬
ing "the end", symbolizing the death of
the year and the baneful force which
must be driven out.
The name of the koleda or koljada,
found in all the Slav countries and
elsewhere, is derived from the Latin
calendae. The Roman New Year was
celebrated at the calends of January,
and the Slavs have kept the word to
designate the turn of the sun, the turn
of the year, and the festival, the songs,
the girl or the dummy figure personify¬
ing that critical period.
Some students of folklore have mis¬
taken this allegory for the representa¬
tion of an old god. Koleda, however,
is no more a goddess than Ovsen or
Karacun are gods, but stands on the
same footing as the Lady Maslenica
(from maslo, meaning butter), who re¬
presents Carnival, or Marena, the fig¬
ure symbolizing the death of Winter
which is cast into the water in Spring.
Princess 'Buckwheat'
These are merely examples of the
popular tendency to personify
even the simplest things; there
are likewise festivities in honour of the
Grain, and in praise of the Princess
Kasa (buckwheat meal), while Pluga,
the plough, is often invoked at the end
of the year as a being in whom great
hopes are placed, the prime architect
of future harvests. "The gilded plough
is turning the soil and behind it walks
the Lord himself. Saint Peter helps
him to guide it and the Mother of God
bears the grain."
A plough is often taken round the
village with the singers of the koljada,
who go in gay procession by night from
house to house, sometimes wearing
masks and disguised as animals espe¬
cially as goats, which probably repre¬
sent the spirit of the wheat, and these
masquerades foreshadow the Carnival.
The singers extol the virtues of each
family and wish all a prosperous year.
Magic rites are performed during
this holy time. Ploughing and sowing
are mimed to encourage the growth of
the plants. The scattering of grain
and money, symbolizing abundance,
brings luck. The trees in the orchards
are wrapped round with the straw
which has been strewn over the floors
of the houses and are shaken, caressed
and threatened, "Will you bear fruit
or not?" they are asked, and one
member of the family makes promises
on behalf of the tree. Among the Serbs
and the Poles, in particular, the far¬
mers' wives scatter straw through the
house, imitating the
sounds made by the
domestic animals, while
the children, under the
table, repeat "cluck-
cluck, quack - quack,
cackle-cackle, moo-moo
a hundred chickens,
ducks, geese and cows!"
The new fire rite, con¬
nected with the begin¬
ning of the year or the
return of the sun, took
place at the solstice or
on New Year's Day, and
the yule log common
among various Slav peo¬
ples is a survival of it.
The ceremonies connected with the
badniak (the Serbian yule log) show
that it also represents a New Year rite.
The "Christmas visitor" strikes the log,
wishing his hosts "as much cattle, as
many horses, sheep, pigs, and hives full
of honey, with as much good fortune,
prosperity, success and happiness as the
sparks that fly out."
The meals at these festivals must be
ample: the richer and more plentiful
the dishes the more prosperous will be
the year.
Both the menu and the order in
which the dishes are served are impor¬
tant. The number of dishes may vary
but, in Poland, must always be uneven,
and every type of produce, from farm,
field, kitchen-garden, orchard, forest
and river, must be included to ensure
that there shall be no lack in the
coming year.
As the feast proceeds, the guests do
Photos Copyright Musée de l'Homme, Paris.
GINGERBREAD PEACOCKS are made in
earthenware mould (above) for Russian New
Year feast. Top left, one of many tiny human
figures made in mint-bread for hanging on the
Christmas tree. Bottom left, a gingerbread
carp with little fish cleverly worked Into it.
not, in the midst of their gaiety, forget
to take precautions for the future.
When eating peas, the Poles pull out a
hair, saying: "Peas, twine around the
stake!" When cabbage is served, they
strike their heads with their spoons,
repeating "Form a good head, cabbage,
form a good head!" Millet is bidden
to "Form heavy ears and grow well!"
The scraps left over are kept and
planted, in the kitchen-garden, in the
spring.
Thus, everything is important; every
gesture is significant and has an effect
on the future. The fortune of the New
Year is determined during this critical
period that ushers it in and represents,
in some sort, the dress rehearsal for
the performance to come.
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
LANTERNS
GONGS AND
FIREWORKS
A Chinese philosopher
recalls his boyhood
by
Lin Yutang
Copyright Camera Press Ltd.
LIGHTED JOSS STICKS smoulder outside a temple in Penang (Malaya) as the Chinese inhabitants
celebrate their New Year. These sticks are collected and burned as incense before the ritual com¬
mences. Small boy (top, right) plants his own joss sticks under approving gaze of a stone lion.
MY memory goes back to those excit¬
ing, indelible childhood years. I
lived in an inland village near the
south-east coast of China. It was about
the turn of the century, the Manchu Em¬
press Dowager was still on her throne, and
customs had not yet changed.
As far back as I can remember, when
I was four or five, I felt New Year coming
weeks ahead, the way a western child would
feel the portentous arrival of the Christ¬
mas season. Not shopping and packages;
but my mother would grind rice fjour on
a home mill, to make nienkao, or New Year
pudding, made of rice flour, turnip and
dried shrimps. It was no small excitement
since this was done only once a year.
My sisters would assist my mother at the
small mill, consisting of two horizontal mill¬
stones about a foot and half across, the
upper stone turned by a wooden crank sus¬
pended from the ceiling. It was a very
tricky job, and full of fun. There was a
small hole in the upper stone, and while
one person turned the stone around, an¬
other had to drop rice and water with a
porcelain spoon expertly, at the exact mo¬
ment when the hole came around. Natu¬
rally I demanded to aim the rice at the
hole, too. I may or may not have broken
a few spoons.
The next thing I remember was fal¬
ling asleep trying to sit the Old Year out.
For it was the custom that the whole fami¬
ly should sit up after a sumptuous dinner,
in which besides fried clams, a special roll
made by mother, also only once- in a year,
invariably figured. It consisted of finely
chopped ingredients made into a paste and
wrapped around with a layer of peritoneal
fat from a pig. Red candles burned bright¬
ly on the centre table against the wall.
We would sing hymns and we would pray,
for we were Christians. My father, who
was a jolly man, would crack jokes and
everybody would be so happy, for we were
a family of many brothers and sisters.
Then my eyes would feel drowsy, and the
next thing I knew when I woke up was
the expectation of something akin to the
Christmas stocking. It was not
a stocking, but a cheap black (Cont'd
satin gown with a deep rose on ne*t
vest on top, which the younger P°Se/--
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Nr 12. 1955
LANTERNS
GONGS AND
FIREWORKS
(Continued}
Erich Hartmann, copyright Magnum Photos
A DANCING LION BRINGS GOOD LUCK. Amid the noise and smoke
of exploding firecrackers, the traditional Lion Dance is performed in the streets
of San Francisco's Chinatown, where more than 30,000 Chinese live today.
Thousands of firecrackers are set off to drive away evil spirits. The lion, despite
its ferocious mask, is a symbol of good luck in the coming year. Above, the
lion dancer is aided by a boy who has taken the tail on his s.houlders. This
exuberant dance is a leading feature of the Chinese New Year celebrations.
children were allowed to wear only once
a year on the occasion of the New Year.
My father and my mother would be al¬
ready up at dawn, dressed, but sitting in
bed, waiting to receive the respects of their
children. Hurriedly my second sister would
assist me into my new gown, telling me
that all the others were ready, so that we
could all go in together and make our bow
to our parents. Then while the adults
would exchange New Year calls, we chil¬
dren would go out to set off firecrackers.
Once my eyes were hurt by a spark, and
a small white spot remained in one of
them, but disappeared in time.
The Old Chinese New Year, of the lunar
calendar, was the greatest festival of the
year for the Chinese people, compared
with which every other festival seemed to
have something less of the holiday spirit.
For five days, the entire nation dressed in
its best clothes, shut up shop, loafed, gam¬
bled, beat gongs, let off firecrackers, paid
calls and went to the theatre. It was the
great day of good luck, when everybody
looked forward to a better and more pros¬
perous new year, when everybody had the
pleasure of adding one year to his age and
was ready with an auspicious, luck-bring¬
ing word for his neighbours.
Stubborn Old New Year
The humblest maid had the right not
to be scolded on New Year's Day and
strangest of all, the hard-working
women of China loafed and cracked melon
seeds and refused to wash or cook a regu¬
lar meal or even handle a kitchen knife.
The justification for this idleness was that
to sweep the floor on New Year's Day was
to sweep away good luck, and to wash was
to wash away good luck. Red scrolls were
pasted on every door containing words like
Luck, Happiness, Peace, Prosperity, Spring.
For red was the colour of happiness.
And all around, in the home courtyards
and in the streets, there was the sound of
firecrackers, and the air was filled with the
smell of sulphur and narcissus sulphur
outdoors and the incredible subtle fragrance
of narcissus indoors. Fathers lost their dig¬
nity, grandfathers were more amiable
than ever, and children blew cheap bam¬
boo whistles, wore masks and played with
clay dolls. Country women, dressed in
their holiday best, would go three or four
New Year
echoes from
around
the world
r-pHE Koreans call New Year's
A Day the day of discretion
because of the belief that what
will happen in the coming year
is conceived on this first day of
the first month : Chong-wol or
Il-wol, the first month is, thus
always considered as the most
important of the year. Korean
families are supposed to stay
awake throughout the night of
New Year's Eve and to offer
sacrifices to their ancestors at
midnight.
TN Egypt, the opening of the
1 New Year falls according to
religions. The Islamic New Year
may fall at any time of the
year, but usually it is the first
day of the month of Al Monha-
ran, the month in which wars
are forbidden. The Coptic New
Year occurs during the latter
half of September.
VTARiED local customs are follow-
v ed by the peoples of Viet-
Nam in celebrating their New
Year, the festival of Tet. The
festivities have a ritual and
mystic character : offerings are
made before the temple altars:
purification baths are taken
and the people cleanse them¬
selves for the New Year. The
Tonkingese fix branches of
flexible bamboo to the roofs of
their houses in order to drive
away the evil spirits.
rpHE first New Year visitor to
-** a Swedish home must be a
man. Popular belief holds that
if a woman crosses the doorway
first bad luck will follow.
an old Danish saying runs
A "Noise chases away the gob¬
lins". Hence, in the large
towns and the villages at the
twelfth stroke of midnight
young men and women let off
fireworks, light flares and break
earthenware pots in front of
their houses. In the Nether¬
lands the hooting of ships'
sirens welcomes in the New
Year.
present Gregorian calen-
*- dar was set up to reform the
errors of the Julian calendar
established by Julius Caesar in
45 B.C. In 1582, Pope Gregory
XIII directed that the day after
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
miles on foot to watch a theatre, where
the village dandies indulged in what flirta¬
tions they dared. It was the day of eman¬
cipation for women, emancipation from the
daily drudgery of washing and cooking; if
the men felt hungry, they could fry nien-
kao, or make a bowl of noodles with prepar¬
ed sauce, or stuff themselves with cold
cuts of chicken.
Then the Republic came. The Republi¬
can Government of China officially abo¬
lished the lunar New Year, but the lunar
New Year was still with us, very much so
and refused to be abolished. It lodged
too deeply in the people's consciousness.
It was then about 1930, and I was in
Shanghai.
I am ultra-modern. No-one can accuse
me of being conservative. I am not only
for the Gregorian calendar, but am even
for the thirteen-month calendar, in which
all months have exactly four weeks or
twenty-eight days. In other words, I am
very scientific in my viewpoint and very
logical in my reasoning. It was this scien¬
tific pride which was badly wounded when
I found my celebration of the official New
Year a great failure, as anyone who pre¬
tended to celebrate it with any real feeling
must have found out for himself.
...I didn't want Old New Year. But the
Old New Year came. It came on February
the fourth.
My big Scientific Mind told me not to
keep the Old New Year, and I promised
him. -I'm not going to let you down," I
said, with more good will than self-confi¬
dence. For I heard rumblings of the Old
New Year's coming as far back as the be¬
ginning of January, when one morning I
was given for breakfast a bowl of lapacho,
or congee with lotus-seeds and dragon-
eyes, which sharply reminded me it was
the eighth day of the twelfth moon.
February 3 came. Still I said to myself,
"I'm not going to keep the Old New Year."
That morning, my wife told me to change
my underwear. I asked, "What for ?"
"Chouma is going to wash your underwear
today. She is not going to wash tomorrow,
nor the day after tomorrow, nor the day
after the day after tomorrow." Being hu¬
man, I could not refuse.
That was the beginning of my downfall.
After breakfast, my family was going to the
bank, for there was a mild sort of bank
panic, which came in spite of the fact that
by ministerial orders the Old New Year
didn't exist. "Y.T." my wife said, "we are
going to hire a car. You might come along
and have a hair-cut." I didn't care for the
hair-cut, but the car was a great tempta¬
tion. I never liked monkeying about in a
bank, but I liked a car. I thought I could
profitably go to the City Gods'. Temple and
see what I could get for the children.
I should not have gone to the City Gods'
Temple in the first place. Once there at
this time of the year, you know what would
happen. I found on my way home that I
had not only rotating lanterns and rabbit
lanterns and several packages of Chinese
toys with me, but some twigs of plum
blossom, besides.
What ! No turnip pudding
After coming home, I found that some¬
one from my native place had present¬
ed me with a pot of narcissus, the
narcissus which made my native place na¬
tionally famous and which reminded me
of New Year's Day in my childhood. I
could not shut my eyes without the entire
picture of my childhood coming back to me.
At lunch, the smell of the narcissus made
me think of the New Year rice-pudding,
made with turnips.
"This year, no one has sent us any turnip
pudding," I said sadly.
"It's because no one came from Amoy.
Otherwise, they would have sent it," said
my wife.
"I remember once I bought exactly the
same kind of pudding in a Cantonese shop
on Wuchang Road. I think I can still
find it."
"No, you can't", challenged my wife.
"Of course I can," I took up the chal¬
lenge.
By three o'clock in the afternoon I was
already in a bus on my way home from
North Szechuen Road with a big basket of
nienkao weighing two and a half pounds.
At five, we ate the fried nienkao, and with
the room filled with the subtle fragrance
of narcissus, I felt terribly like a sinner.
"I'm not going to celebrate New Year's
Eve," I said resolutely; "I'm going to the
movies tonight."
"How can you?" asked my wife. "We
have invited Mr. Ts... to dinner this even¬
ing." It all looked pretty bad.
At half-past-five, my youngest child
appeared in her new red dress.
"Who put on the new dress for her?" I
rebuked, visibly shaken, but still gallant.
"Huangma did," was the reply. Huangma
and Chouma were our maids.
By six o'clock, I found red candles burn¬
ing brightly on the mantelpiece, their lap¬
ping flames casting a satirical glow of
triumph at my Scientific Consciousness. My
Scientific Consciousness was, by the way,
already very vague and low and unreal.
"Who lighted the candles?" again I chal¬
lenged.
"Chouma did," was the reply.
"Who bought the candles?" I demanded.
"Why, you bought them yourself this
morning."
"Oh, did I?" It cannot have been my
Scientific Consciousness that did it. It must
have been the Other Consciousness.
I thought I must have looked a little ridi¬
culous, the ridiculousness coming less from
the recollection of what I did in the morn¬
ing than from the conflict of my head
and my heart at that moment. I was soon
startled out of this mental conflict by the
"bomb-bah" of fire crackers in my neigh¬
bourhood. One by one, those sounds sank
into my deep consciousness. They have a
way of shaking the Chinese heart that no
European knows. The challenge of my
neighbour on the east was soon taken up
by my neighbour on the west, until it grew
into a regular fusillade.
I was not going to be beaten by them.
Pulling out some money, I said to my boy:
"Ah-ching, take this and buy me some
heaven-and-earth firecrackers and some
rattle firecrackers, as loud as possible and
as big as possible. Remember, the bigger
and the louder the better."
So amidst the "bomb-bah" of firecrack¬
ers, I sat down to the New Year's Eve
dinner. And I felt very happy in spite of
myself.
Lin Yutang, Chinese philosopher and writer, Is
universally known for his books on Chinese life and
customs. Among some of the more famous are :
"The Importance of Living", "My Country and ' My
People" and the "Wisdom of China and India".
October 4 should become Octo¬
ber 15. It was immediately
adopted by all Roman Catholic
countries but was resisted by
both the Protestant and Eas¬
tern nations. For several centu¬
ries there was a difference of ten
days (and later even more) in
numbering the days. Great
Britain and its colonies adopted
the Gregorian calendar only in
1752. There was an enormous
outcry and people marched
through the streets with pla¬
cards marked "Give us back our
eleven days!". The new calen¬
dar was adopted bv Sweden in
1756, by Japan in 1873, by China
in 1912. The Soviet Union
adopted it in 1918 and the
Greek Orthodox Church in 1923.
The Russian Revolution of 1917
is generally spoken of as the
October Revolution but it is
celebrated on November 7 be¬
cause Russia has since adopted
the Gregorian calendar. (For an
article on the calendar past and
present, see Unesco Courier No 1,
1954).
TN cities and villages of Spain
1 families gather together on
New Year's Eve to celebrate
with music and games. At the
first stroke of midnight each
person present starts to eat
twelve grapes, and all must be
finished before the sound of the
twelfth stroke has died away to
make sure the New Year will
be a happy one.
*
'Scotland's New Year festival
" Hogmanay is the most
important of the'year. The deri
vation of the word Hogmanay
is lost in the mists of antiquity.
The first visitor, preferably
dark, to cross the threshold of a
Scottish home in the New Year
was rewarded with a kiss from
whoever opened the door.
dites marking -the beginning
***- of the New Year were prac¬
tised by many tribes of North
American Indians, although the
times of the festivals varied.
For the Iroquois the New Year
began in February, for the Es¬
kimos in the autumn, for the
Hopi in November and for the
Californian tribes late in July.
Customs also varied from tribe
to tribe : for the Seneca (a
branch of the Iroquois) the
celebrations lasted a week. On
the first day of the year all the
fires were extinguished and the
ashes scattered. New fire was
kindled by the Keepers of the
Faith, and a white dog was
strangled and hung up, During
the following three days the In¬
dians in masquerade rushed
from house to house. On the
fifth day all sins were publicly
confessed, and the white dog
was carried on a slab of bark
to an altar and burned.
t-iivining what the future holds
*-* in store has long been a
New Year practice among many
peoples. In England this used
to be done on New Year's Eve
by Oomancy (divination by
eggs). The albumen from the
egg was let fall into water.
From the shapes which it as¬
sumed the future was foretold.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Nr 12. 1955
Tucked away in the towering Himalayas, the little
state of Sikkim boasts a hundred thousand souls.
A protectorate of India, and largely Tibetan in
character, it is situated to the east of Nepal. Its
rice fields terrace the mountainsides, each one guard¬
ed by its fluttering prayer banners (I) to ward
off the demons. In the hinterland of Sikkim the
Himalayan jungle with its population of monkeys,
leopards and bears, stretches up to a height of
9,000 feet. Here, in the shelter of enormous
ferns, grow orchids worth a king's ransom. Remote
on the mountain peaks lie the Buddhist monas¬
teries, where the secret soul of ancient Asia lives
on. On the 28th day of the Tibetan moon, the
last month of the Sikkim year, the Losungthe
Tibetan New Yearis celebrated. The ceremony
which lasts two days is designed to drive away the
demons of the old year and to welcome the good
spirits on the road of the months to come. The
deep tones of the ancient trumpets of the lamas (2)
mingle with the voices raised in prayer and thus add
rhythm to the sacred New Year dance, the Thiam.
The High Priest, the Lentshi-lama
brandishes a ritual bell and a
"thunderbolt" (3) to evoke the
forces which animate the Thiam.
Protected by a guard clothed in
red, a sacred symbol, the Si-Pa-Ro
presides over the dance. The Sl-
Pa-Ro is a plan of the universe
drawn geometrically with cosmic
symbols, in which each line and
each colour holds a divine message
which must be deciphered in order
to determine the augury for the
year to come (4).
(Copyrighc Bourguignon-Taret Expedition)
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Sikkim warriors also take part in the ceremony.
They sing and dance the long epic poem of their
country's history. Their headdresses sway, their
sabres flash in the sun (5). Clothed in their
richest costumes the lamas trace innumerable
circles. They call up the demons and try to
subdue them (6). Once the evil spirits have been
lured into a circle, the warriors pounce upon
them and help the lamas to exterminate them.
On the evening of the second day there is peace
and silence. Assured that the good spirits are
satisfied, the lamas, still in dance formation (7),
withdraw to the Gumpa (temple). In the shadow
of a richly decorated statue of their deity. Guru
Rimpoche (9), they group themselves in fervent
prayer (8-10).
*^-W
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Nr 12. 1955
Rituals & symbols
of Time reborn
pect, and can be traced back to the
farthest antiquity. Its ideology and
ritual structure existed as early as the
Sumerian period, and the system of
the akitu has been identified from Ak¬
kadian times in the Bronze Age. We
are thus dealing -with documents of the
most ancient civilization known to his¬
tory, in which the sovereign played a
considerable role. He was regarded as
the son and representative of the divi¬
nity on earth and as such was responsi¬
ble for the regularity of the rhythms
of nature and for the welfare of the
entire society. Hence it is not surpris¬
ing to find that the King was a promi¬
nent figure in the ceremonial of the
New Year. Upon him fell the duty of
ensuring the "rebirth" of time.
In the course of the akitu ceremony,
which lasted twelve days, the so-called
Epic of the Creation, Enume elish, was
solemnly recited. This ritual was really
a re-enactment of the combat between
the god Marduk and the sea monster
Tiamat a fabulous battle which had
taken place "before the beginning of
years" and which had put an end to
chaos by the final victory of the god.
Marduk had created the universe from
fragments of the torn body of Tiamat,
and created man from the blood of the
demon Kingu (Tiamat's most powerful
ally). That this commemoration was
in effect a re-enactment or re-actuali¬
zation of the Creation is proved both by
the rituals and by the formulas recited
during the ceremony.
The combat between Tiamat and
Marduk was mimed by a struggle bet¬
ween two groups of actors. The cere¬
monial was also a feature of the New
Year dramatic celebrations among the
Hittites, in Egypt, and at Ras Shamra.
(Continuée/ from page 7)
But this struggle was more than a com¬
memoration of the original duel bet¬
ween Marduk and Tiamat; it was, a
contemporary version of the Creation.
Within the frame of the same akitu
ceremonial was sakmuk, "the festival of
the Fates", in which omens for each of
the twelve months in the year were
determined. These were equivalent to
creating the twelve months to come.
Marduk's descent into Hell was marked
by a period of mourning and fasting for
the whole community and of "humilia¬
tion" for the king, a ritual which form¬
ed part of a vast carnival system. It
was at this time, too, that the expulsion
of sins took place by means of a scape¬
goat. The cycle was closed with the
sacred marriage between the god and
the goddess Sparpanîtû.
Slaves become the masters
We thus see that the Babylonian
New Year festival consisted
of a series of rites, purporting
to abolish past time, restore primordial
chaos and re-enact the creation of the
universe: (1) The first act represented
the domination of Tiamat and thus
signified a return to the mythical
period before the Creation. This
included the enthronement of a
"Carnival King", the "humiliation"
of the real sovereign and the complete
reversal of the social order - (the
slaves became the masters and vice
versa). Every feature suggests univer¬
sal confusion, the abolition of order
and hierarchy, "orgy" and chaos. (2)
The creation of the world, which had
taken place in mythical times, was thus
re-enacted every year. (3) Man parti-
Rosh Ha'Shanah to the sound of the rani's horn
The Jewish New Year, Rosh
Ha'Shanah, marks the birth
of the world which, according
to Jewish tradition, took place on
the first of Tishri (September-
October) 5716 years ago. The fes¬
tival is observed for two days and
during the synagogue service the
Shofar (ram's horn) is sounded to
arouse Jews to duty and responsi¬
bility on the first day of the new
year. The Shofar must be a ram's
horn and not the horn of calf or
cow as this would be a reminder of
the Israelites dancing in worship
around the Golden Calf. Accord¬
ing to the Hebrew prophets, the
sound of the Shofar will also usher
in the Messianic era when the im¬
mortal dead will arise from their
long slumber for judgment and
eternal life.
Jewish families gather together
for a meal following the evening
service in the synagogue. The
master of the household recites the
benediction over a sparkling goblet
of wine symbol of joy from
which all members of the family
then sip. The meal is begun with
slices of apple dipped in honey,
accompanied by a New Year
prayer. All other food eaten at
this meal is sweet and no sour or
pickled foods are permitted as
being incongruous and out of har¬
mony with the nature of the festi¬
val.
On New Year's Day pious Jews
wend their way to a stream of
flowing water. Here, they will
recite prayers by the water's edge,
cast in some bread crumbs and
petition divine pardon for their
past sins. The water symbolizes
purity and the bread crumbs "the
leaven in the dough" being the
Rabbinic description of the proud
and sinful heart.
Rosh Ha'Shanah is, with Yom
Kippur, one of the high holy days
of the year. Both are religious in
character, celebrated in a serious
spirit and are known as the "Days
of Awe". The sanctity . of Rosh
Ha'Shanah is felt most at the
morning services in the syna¬
gogues, where the prayers, the
Shofar, the readings from the
Torah and the Rabbi's sermon all
underline the significance of the
day.
cipated directly, though in a limited
way, in this cosmic process (struggle
between the two groups of actors re¬
presenting Marduk and Tiamat). (4)
The "festival of the Fates" was a fur¬
ther symbol of the creation, since it
decided the "Fate" of each month. (5)
The ritual marriage represented the
"rebirth" of the world and of mankind.
The symbolic repetition of the Crea¬
tion as part of the New Year festival
has been preserved to this day among
the Mandaeans of Irak and Iran. The
Persian Tatars still begin the New Year
by planting seeds in a jar full of earth;
this, they say, is done in memory of
the Creation. This custom is in keep¬
ing with the general Persian system,
as Nawrôz (the Persian New Year)
commemorates the day on which the
world and man were created. The
"renewal of the creation" takes place
on the day of Nawrôz, says the Arab
historian, Albîrunî. "This is a new day
of a new month of a new year", the
King would proclaim, "what time has
consumed must be renewed."
It was also the day on which men's
"destiny" was fixed for the whole year.
Innumerable fires and lights were
kindled on the night of Nawrôz, and
libations were made to ensure plenti¬
ful rainfall during the coming year. It
was also the custom for everyone to
sow seven .kinds of seed in a jar and
"from their growth, they drew conclu¬
sions regarding the nature of the year's
harvest". This custom was similar to
the "fixing of Fates" which marked the
Babylonian New Year, and has survi¬
ved to the present day in the New
Year ceremonies of the Mandaeans and
Yezids in Asia Minor.
The twelve days between Christmas
and the Epiphany are likewise still
regarded as a forecast of the next
twelve months. Peasants in Europe
foretell the weather and rainfall for
each month on the basis of the con¬
ditions prevailing during those twelve
days. The Indians of the Vedic period
considered that the twelve middle days
of winter constituted an image and
replica of the whole year.
Twelve days of the Fates
Almost all Indo-European peoples
possessed, from the very ' earliest
times, ritual dramatizations of
New Year myths which bear a certain
resemblance to the ancient systems
found in the Near East. But simi¬
lar dramatizations can be traced
in China, in Japan, among certain
North American tribes, and others.
The dead return among the living; fire
is put out and rekindled; boys are ini¬
tiated; there is a procession of carnival
masks; ritual battles take place bet¬
ween rival groups; there is a burst of
eroticism (the pursuit of virgins, mar¬
riage by rape, orgies) ; the twelve
months to come are forecast from the
"fate" of the twelve days.
Thus, each of these rituals has its
particular significance, and all contri¬
bute to building up a system whose
aspects include the abolition of the past
and a return to "chaos" (darkness, de¬
bauchery, abolition of rank, etc.), fol¬
lowed by a new creation, that is by a
repetition of the cosmogeny. The New
Year expresses man's deep-rooted
longing for regeneration by regene¬
rating Time and the Universe as a
whole to begin a new life in a new
Creation in other words, to be purged
of one's sins and forget one's failures.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the editor
Sir,
While in H.M. Stationery Office re¬
cently I came across a copy of the
Unesco Courier. Thumbing through
its pages I realized I had discovered
"hidden gold" and at once took out a
subscription.
It gives me great delight to con¬
gratulate you on such a well-produced
magazine, on its attractive illustrations,
and on its enlightening and thought-
provoking articles. It also served to
introduce me to the Unesco way of
life.
Frank Atkin
Stockport, Cheshire,
England.
Editor's note: Many letters have
reached us in response to our
appeal for readers to renew their sub¬
scriptions and to take out gift sub¬
scriptions for relatives and friends, be¬
fore the present rates go up at the end
of the year. Lack of space makes it
impossible to publish all these letters.
The two which follow are typical of
those which came from French sub¬
scribers.
Sir,
Enclosed is our subscription renewal
for the Unesco Courier. We find the
majority of the issues of the greatest
documentary, educational and social
interest...
Headmaster
Boys School,
Maisons Alfort,
Seine.
Sir,
I am delighted to renew my sub¬
scription to the Unesco Courier. Well-
written and clearly presented, your
magazine creates new centres of inter¬
est for its readers every month with
the variety of subjects it covers. My
only regret is that it does not appear
more often.
Laurence Allot
Paris.
Sir,
As I have not received the No 7, 1955
issue of the Unesco Courier it may
have been lost in the post would you
please send me another one, as I want
my collection to be complete. .
While writing, I should like to tell
you how much pleasure I get from your
magazine. It is a real "window open
on the world" and has the happy gift
of showing in all their greatness and
truth the magnificent efforts being
made to harness the world's resources
for the use of mankind. I sincerely
hope that your news and views are
taken to heart by people in all lands
and teach them to know and to appre¬
ciate each other's worth better than at
present. It is through such positive
and constructive efforts that goodwill
and peace will fill men's minds.
Reginald Declerq
Father of the Dominican Order,
Rouen, France.
Sir,
Congratulations on the interesting
magazine you produce. I found issue
No 8/9, 1955 (Conquest of the Desert)
particularly satisfying. I should like
to know of other scientific or cultural
reviews published by Unesco with a
view to taking out subscriptions if they
interest me.
H. Kahia
Rodes, Tunisia.
Editor's Note: Following is a list of
periodicals published by Unesco:
Annual
subscription
Bulletin for Libraries
(monthly) 	 16/6 $3.00
Copyright Bulletin (bi¬
annual) 	 12/6 $2.25
Current Sociology (quar¬
terly) 18/6 $3.50
Education Abstracts (mon¬
thly, 10 issues per year) 9/6 $1.75
Fundamental and Adult
Education Bulletin
(quarterly) 	 5/- $1.00
Impact of Science on
Society (quarterly) 	 9/6 $1.75
International Social Scien¬
ce Bulletin (quarterly) . 21/- 53.50
Museum (quarterly) 	 21/- $5.00
Unesco Chronicle * A
monthly report from
Unesco House 	 10/6 $1.75
(See list of National Distributors be¬
low).
U.N. ANNOUNCES
PUBLICATION OF :
PEACEFUL USES
OF
ATOMIC ENERGY
Proceedings of the
International Conference
in Geneva, August 1905.
THE United Nations announces the
forthcoming publication in their
entirety of the Proceedings of the
Geneva Conference on the Peaceful Uses
of Atomic Energy. This 16 volume issue
will be unique in that it will be the
only publication to make available the
more than 1,000 papers submitted at the
Conference by more than 30 countries
and international agencies. It will consti¬
tute the only complete record of the
Conference, at which approximately
1,200 scientists from 72 nations partici¬
pated. Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy
will provide for the first time a complete
reference work on the subject. The
English edition will be available early
in 1956, other editions during the same
year (Separate English, French, Russian
and Spanish editions will be published;
the price of the Russian edition is yet to be
announced, but orders may be submitted
now). The following special pre-publi¬
cation price for the 16 volumes is avail¬
able until January 31, 1956 (orders
received prior to that date will be fully
protected): $1 10.00; £39stg.; 450 Swiss
francs, or the equivalent in other curren¬
cies. Individual volume prices will be
announced as soon as possible. Orders
may be sent to United Nations Sales
Agents, or to the Sales and Circulation
Section, United Nations, New York,
or the Sales Section, United Nations,
Geneva, Switzerland.
Unesco's National Distributors from whom
the English edition of THE COURIER con be
obtained are listed betow. Other Unesco
distributors ore listed in the French and
Spanish editions of THE COURIER.
Australia : Oxford University Press, 346,
Little Collins Street, Melbourne.
Austria : Wilhelm Frlck Verlag, 27, Gra¬
ben, Vienna I.
Burma : Burma Educational Bookshop,
551-3 Merchan 'Street. P.O Box 222,
Rangoon.
Canada : University of Toronto Press,
Toronto.
Ceylon : Lake House Bookshop, The Asso¬
ciated Newspapers of Ceylon, Ltd., P.O.
Box 244, Colombo I. Rs. 5.
Cyprus : M. E. Constantinides, P.O.B. 473,
Nicosia.
Denmark : Ejnar liunksgaard Ltd., 6 Nor-
regade, Copenhagen, K.
Egypt : La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9, Adly
Pasha Street, Cairo. -
Ethiopia : International Press Agency,
P.O.B. 120, Addis-Ababa.
NATIONAL
Finland : Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, 2 Kes-
kuskatu, Helsinki.
Formosa : The World Book Company Ltd.,
99, Chung King South Rd, Section I,
Taipeh.
France : Sales Division, Unesco. 1 9, Avenue
Kléber, Paris- 1 6e.
Germany : Unesco Vertrieb für Deutsch¬
land, R. Oldenbourg, Rosenheimerscrasse
I 45, München.
Greece : Librairie H. Kauffman, 28, Rue
du Stade, Athens.
Hong Kong : Swindon Book Co., 25 Nathan
Road, Kowloon.
India : Orient Longmans Ltd.» Bombay, Cal¬
cutta, Madras : sub-depots : Oxford Book
& Stationery Co., Scindia House, New
Delhi; Rajkamal Publications Ltd., Hima¬
laya House, Bombay 7. Rs. 4.
Indonesia : G.C.T van Dorp & Do. NV.,
Djalan N usan tara, 22, Djakarta.
Iran : Iranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
DISTRIBUTORS
Iraq : McKenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
Israel : Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd., 35,
Allenby Road, P.O. Box 5154. Tel-Aviv.
Jamaica : Sangster's Book Room, 99, Har¬
bour Street, Kingston; Knox Educational
Services, Spaldings.
Japan : Maruzen Co, Inc., 6 Tori-Nichome,
Nihonbashi, Tokyo.
Jordan : J.I. Bahous and Co.. Dar-uI-Kutub,
Salt Road, Amman.
Korea ; Korean National Commission for
, Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
Liberia : ]. Momolu Kamara, 69, Front
and Gurley Streets, Monrovia.
Malayan Federation and Singapore :
Peter Chong and Co., P.O. Box 13 5.
Singapore.
Malta : Sapienza*s Library, 26, Kingsway,
Valletta.
Netherlandi : N V. Martinus Nijhoff,
Lange Voorhouc 9. The Hague.
New Zealand: Unesco Publications Centre
100, Hackthorne Rd., Christchurch.
Nigeria : C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box 174,
Lagos.
Norway : A/S Bokhj'ornet, Stortingsplass, 7,
Oslo.
Pakistan : Ferozsons Ltd., Karachi, Lahore,
Peshawar. Rs. 3.
Philippines : Philippine Education Co.,
Inc., 1 1 04 Castillejos, Quiapo, Manila. 3.00
Puerto-Rico, Pan-American Book C*.,
San Juan Í 2.
Surinam : Radhakishun and Company Ltd.,
(Book Dept.), Watermolenstraat 36, Para¬
maribo.
Sweden ; A.B.C.E. Fritzes Kungl. Hov-
bokhande, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 16.
Thailand : Suksapan Par.it, Arkarn 9,
Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok. 20 ticals.
Union of South Africa : Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Ltd., P.O. Box 724, Pretoria,
United Kingdom : H.M. Stationery Office,
P.O. Box 569, London S.E.I.
U.S.A. : Unesco Publications Center, 4 75
Fifth Ave., New York 17, N.Y.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Nr 12. 1955
From the Unesco Newsroom
Mj IBRARIES 'OPEN SES¬
AME' : Unesco is studying the
possibility of issuing an' inter¬
national library card which
would- give holders access to
university and research libraries
in all countries participating in
the scheme. . Card holders would
be able to consult books, peri¬
odicals, special collections, mi¬
crofilms, etc., without having to
obtain prior permission from the
libraries concerned.
WEATHER MEN AND
POTATOES: Meteorology is
now helping the Chilean
potato farmers to fight plant
disease. By studying and
forecasting the weather
meteorologists can advise
farmers when to spray po¬
tato crops which have been
infected with blight. Only
if the fungus-killing sprays
are applied at exactly the
right time will the disease
be checked. Now at work in
Chile for the World Meteo¬
rological Organization, under
the U. N. Technical Assis¬
tance programme, is an
Irish meteorologist who is
one the greatest experts in
this field of agricultural
meteorology. Until about five
years ago potato blight was
unknown in Chile, but now
it is a serious menace.
IV
B'ANISHING BABEL:
The International Federation of
Translators, set up with Unes¬
co's assistance in 1953, now
groups professional organiza¬
tions of translators in 12 coun¬
tries. The Federation has re¬
cently brought out a monthly
magazine called "Babel" which
keeps translators all over the
world informed of the latest
developments in their profession.
POLISH POET HONOUR¬
ED: To commemorate the
100th anniversary of Adam
Mickiewicz's death Unesco is
publishing a collection of
essays paying homage to the
memory of a great poet "who
brought honour not only to
Poland but to all mankind".
The President of the Polish
Pen Club, Jan Parandowski,
has contributed an introduc¬
tion to the poet's life and
work. French, Czech, Italian,
Russian and Polish writers
examine the influence of
Mickiewicz's work on Euro¬
pean literature. This beauti¬
fully illustrated volume also
contains selections from some
of the poet's major works,
five tributes by contempora¬
ries of Mickiewicz and bio¬
graphical notes. It can be
purchased through Unesco
sales agents for 53.00 ; 15/6
or 750 French Francs.
EW UNESCO H.Q.: The
cornerstone of the new Unesco
Headquarters was laid on a
site in Place Fontenoy, Paris,
on. November 23, just ten
years after the signature of the
Constitution of Unesco in Lon¬
don. Taking part in the official
ceremony were, French Govern¬
ment and Paris Municipal offi¬
cials, the President of the
French National Commission
for Unesco, members of Unes¬
co's Executive Board and Dr.
Luther Evaps, Unesco's Direc¬
tor - General. The cornerstone
ceremony was followed by the
formal exchange of instruments
of ratification of the headquar¬
ters agreement between the
French Government and
Unesco.
* 5,640 BODILY TERMS:
A list of 5,640 international
anatomical terms, the "No¬
mina Anatómica", has just
been published in English,
French and German with
Unesco assistance, and will
be distributed to anatomical
societies in all countries of
the world. The list was
drawn up by the Nomencla¬
ture Committee of the Inter¬
national Congress of Anato¬
mists and comprises 60 years'
work by anatomists the first
list having been prepared in
1895. The new list will be of
special aid to specialists in ex¬
changing information on
latest developments in medi¬
cine and surgery. It will be
used to prepare other lan¬
guage editions.
MU EARNING WHILE
ABROAD: By the end of 1955,
69 Yugoslav educators holding
Unesco fellowships will have vi¬
sited other countries to study
their educational systems, as
part of one of Unesco's biggest
single projects of technical as¬
sistance to a Member State.
Since 1945, the Government of
Yougoslavia has done much to
increase the number of its
schools and universities, but
a good deal of school reform is
urgently needed to meet pre¬
sent-day requirements. As part
of the programme for determin¬
ing the basis of this reform, the
69 Unesco fellowship-holders
are each spending, three months
studying abroad. They work
mostly in teams of three to
eight members, studying the
school systems as a whole in
the countries they are visiting
or concentrating on some spe¬
cialized branch of education.
The fellows, who are all expe¬
rienced in teaching and educa¬
tional administration, ' will re¬
turn to influential positions
where they can advise educa¬
tional authorities in their spe¬
cial fields of interest.
INTEGRATING IMMI¬
GRANTS: The Israeli Broad¬
casting Service, Kol Israel,
has begun to use radio pro¬
grammes to help immigrants
adapt themselves to their
new way of life. To aid the
development of adult edu¬
cation programmes of this
type, Unesco has sent a Brit¬
ish broadcaster out to Israel
under the U.N. Technical
Assistance programme.
. lEACHING OTHER
TEACHERS : The Nicaraguan
Government is setting up a fun
damental education centre to
train leaders and teachers for
work in communities through¬
out the country. Students from
the centre in the valley of the
River Coco will have practical
training among the Indians liv¬
ing in some 42 rural communi¬
ties in the surrounding area, in¬
cluding Cabo Gracias a Dios
and Cabo Viejo, where Colum¬
bus landed on his fourth voyage
of discovery. The teaching staff
will be provided by ten Nicara¬
guan graduates from the Latin
American Fundamental Edu¬
cation Centre in Patzcuaro,
Mexico, which was established
in 1951 with Unesco's assistance.
UNESCO DIRECTOR-GENERAL VISITS THE U.S.S.R.
Dr. Luther H. Evans, Director-General of Unesco, spent a week in the
U.S.S.R., from September 30 to October 6, at the invitation of the Soviet
Ministry of Culture. While in Moscow, Dr. Evans discussed the U.S.S.R.'s
participation in Unesco's programme with Soviet officials and visited the
Kremlin, the Lenin Library and the University. While he was in Leningrad,
Dr. Evans' programme included visits to the Library and the Hermitage
Museum. Above, Dr. Evans on the Moskova Bridge in front of the Kremlin.
Below, he inspects a rare volume at the Lenin Library.
V. Kochevoi, Soviet Información Service.
'_V^
	
.-	
i'St
.... % 1
1É' à! im-M IS ' ^4
» ""' n
Y T*
Jk
W\ Mb^^Ki Lfl\m^JM
. <
AW M tiff^wE**^
% - m
¡p X *** m rLu4
ij /%
Imwmml M
M,
SäWGm^jB
l^^H ^gj
- -T 1 gÇ
# L-
u
z
<
CE
z
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Corning next month :
FLIGHT AND FREEDOM
M The Nobel Peace Prize has just been awarded to the Office
of the U.N. High Commissioner for Refugees
M The refugee situation in the world today
M Unesco examines some of the human, economic and social
problems involved
Don't miss these future issues :
M WHAT'S WRONG WITH OUR TEXT-BOOKS ?
Distortion of history in school books. Text-book publishing a great unknown industry.
M KILLERS OF THE INSECT WORLD
Modern "plagues" spread by insects. The staggering toll in death, ill-health and poverty
from insect-borne diseases.
M 2,500 YEARS OF BUDDHIST ART AND CULTURE
The influence of Buddhathe Enlightened Oneon almost 500,000,000 people of Asia. The
great monasteries of Burma, Thailand, Tibet. The fabulous riches of Buddhist art.
M WELCOME STRANGER
International fellowships and exchanges of people between countries as one of the most powerful
ways of building peace and international understanding. Unesco's exchange programme.
Student and teacher exchange. Workers abroad.
M WONDERLAND OF MUSEUMS
A voyage of discovery into art, science, industry and natural history In the modern museums
of today. Museums that tell the fascinating story of metals, wine, textiles, tobacco. The
dusty "cemeteries" of yesterday transformed.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Copyright Almasy
m THEY FLY THROUGH THE AIR...
Many centuries ago in North India a strange ritual known as the
- , * Dola-yatra (swing-festival) was held to mark the New Year. Four
volunteers were attached to a tower by large iron hooks thrust into
their back muscles and then whirled around in representation of the
sun-course. The ceremony ended with their death. Today the
tower is still built each year and volunteers come forward, but the
iron hooks have been replaced by strong harnesses and the worst
discomfort the young men suffer is a bad attack of dizziness (For
other aspects of New Year festivals in India, see page 17).
feai^i¿
]]>
</page>
</document>
