<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="070070eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
H° 10
1954
(7th year)
Price : 7d (U.
30 francs (France)
PRISONERS
ARE PEOPLE
The right to human treatment
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
f* 11,11111--^
^.aK- "
PRISON LIFE has
become mor
able since
ers have been
en useful work ''
do. Here, inmate
in a British prison
are stitching mail-
bags. But keeping
men occupied is not
enough, say modern
penologists. More
emphasis should be
placed onthe reform¬
ative and educa¬
tive aspects of the
* humane " treat¬
ment to which every
prisoner has a right.
(Photo copyright
Atlantic Press).
<a^W« > » i
ill
£
r^ t x x , * . - ., * * v
"n^v»>t
$L
f
*l
\
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO Courier
Number 10-1954
7th YEAR
CONTENTS
PAGE
3 EDITORIAL
Human Rights and the law breaker
4 JUSTICE
A net freeing the innocent
but trapping the guilty
By Reginald Hemeleers
8 'MAN-CAGES'
From "habeas corpus" to a new "habeas anlmam"
By Carlo Levi
I I STORY OF PRISONS
Their evolution as an agency of punishment
By Ronald Fenton
12 SEVEN APOSTLES OF PRISONER RIGHTS
20 PASSING THOUGHTS
On the right to life and the death penalty
By Georges Fradier
22 A BOY IN TROUBLE
What can we do to help him ?
By J. R. Rees
25 BRECOURT
Where the gate is always open
By D. Behrman
30 THE TRAGEDY OF FRANCES
A case that might have been prevented
By Prof. Sir Cyril Burt
33 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Brief notes on education, science and culture
34 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
Published monthly by
The Department of Mass Communication of the United Nations
Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, 19, Avenue Kleber, Paris 16, France.
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition: Ronald Fenton
French Edition: Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition: Jorge Carrera Andrade
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Individual articles not copyrighted maybe reprinted from THE COURIER but
must be accompanied by the following credit line: "Reprinted from UNESCO
COURIER". Signed articles reprinted must carry the author's name.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied by an inter¬
national reply coupon covering postage.
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of THE COURIER.
Annual subscription rates of THE COURIER : 6/-: S 1.50 or 300 French frs.
MC. 54.1 85. A.
Unesco Courier. Nr 10. 1954
DECEMBER 10, 1954
HUMAN RIGHTS DAY
It may 'seem paradoxical to speak of human
rights in connection with men who have been
legally deprived of one of the most fundamental
of all rightsfreedom. But for centuries writers,
thinkers and humanitarian men and women have
fought so that the prisoner might retain at least
the right of being treated as a human being.
c
1 RIME has been called a many-headed monster with
tentacles that reach out far and wide embracing people in
all walks of life. Of the numerous problems that confront
society in modern times there are probably few that have so
strong an impact on the general public as that concerning the
criminal.
Crime is a world problem of tremendous complexity. It
directly affects not only the police, the lawyer and the judge
along with the average person who reads about it in his daily
newspaper, but the psychologist, the psychiatrist and the social
worker.
Somehow, though, most of us are apt to forget that it
also affects the man who has actually broken the law and who
is "sent away." We may not realize it but the plain fact is that
98 per cent of those who go into prison ultimately return to
their communities and to society.
A person who has broken the law or committed a crime has
the same feelings, the same emotions and ambitions as other
human beings. The act he committed may be the result of
blind passion or of a Ufe of distorted viewpoints, out of keeping
with what the rest of .us consider right and normal. But the
mere fact that a man has broken the law and been sent to
prison does not stamp out his desires and ambitions, or make
him any less a human being even though all of us condemn
his act.
Today, whether we admit it or not, society still punishes
for punishment's sake. The majority of our prisons are still
grim man-cages, surrounded by high forbidding walls, patrolled
by armed guards and bristling with other restrictive devices.
And although much progress has been made in recent years
in prison reform, the public still believes that merely locking a
man up will sober him and make him want to be a better
person. Yet the reverse is usually true. Most men come out
of such places worse than when they went in, filled with
bitterness and even hatred for society which deprived them of
their freedom without giving them a chance to better their
condition.
In the past few years, the idea has been gaining consider¬
able ground of prisons without ' walls, without guns, without
armed guards, where the dignity of the individual is recognized
and where emphasis is placed on self-discipline. Such prisons,
known as "open institutions", now exist in a number of
countries, and in 1945 Sweden became the first country v-;
them the normal basis of its entire prison system.
Since 1948, the United Nations has assumed the leadership
in international activities concerned with the prevention of
crime and the treatment of offenders (both young and old).
Through its Department of Social Affairs it has taken over the
work formerly performed by the International Penal and
Penitentiary Commission, and has arranged periodic meetings
of regional groups to re-assess the practical forms of crime
prevention and treatment of offenders. A world congress on
this entire subject is now scheduled for 1955.
Unesco has not done much in the field of criminology. It
has dealt with certain psychological and social aspects of
juvenile delinquency, primarily in co-operation with the World
Federation for Mental Health and the International Federation
of Senior Police Officials. Since 1950 it has given financial
aid to the International Society of Criminology which groups
five international associations dealing with the scientific study
of criminal behaviour, and last year helped finance the second
International Criminological Course at Unesco headquarters.
For the sixth anniversary of the adoption by the United
Nations of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights on
December 10, the Unesco Courier devotes- this issue to the idea
that prisoners are people, that the person who breaks the law
is a human being who has the right to be treated as such, that
prisoners should be returned to society with a better attitude
than when they entered prison, that they must be taught the
dignity of work and given an opportunity to acquire new skills
by which they may make an honest living and once again
become decent citizens.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Respect for local traditions and (he
rights of minorities is applied to
legal matters in French Morocco,
where several kinds of courts
function side by .side. Koranic
courts for Arabs and Rabbinical
courts for Moroccan Jews deal with
religious and family questions such
as marriage, divorce, inheritance,
etc. Offences carrying sentences of
less than two years' imprisonment,
whether involving Arab or Jewish
Moroccan citizens, are judged by
local "Pacha" courts, while more
serious cases are heard in higher
"Shenfian" courts. In cases where
one of the two parties concerned
is French, judgment is delivered by
a French court. Photos on these
pages show: above, a "Pacha"
court judge, an accused person and
his lawyer; below, a Rabbinical
court and a French court (Photos
copyright Paul Almasy).
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier N' 10. 1954
JUSTICE
A net freeing the innocent
but trapping the guilty
By Reginald Hemeleers
knows that they
NO peace-
loving citi¬
zen with a
clear conscience
ever takes to his
heels at the sight
of a policeman.
On the contrary,
the badge and
the polished but¬
tons usually give
him a sense of
security. He
will protect him
¡ against danger and injustice.
The role of the policeman and of
! the entire judicial structure is to
protect the security of the citizen. The
! policeman is not an enemy of freedom;
I instead, he is its guarantor. It is he
who prevents the anti-social citizen
from disturbing the peace of society.
Few people will quarrel with these
statements. But they probably will
tempt a good many people to wonder
why men have always fought so
desperately against excesses of power
| and why the severest criticism which
can be levelled against a political sys¬
tem is the label "police state".
The answer, of course, is that the
police can quickly become the worst
possible menace to individual freedom
if free institutions are not solidly
established or, even worse, if the
morality of society is decaying.
The police, in themselves, are only
an instrument. In the hands of
arbitrary power, this instrument can
become a blind force of evil. Naturally
not all authoritarian regimes have
been inhuman. Despotism can be
enlightened. Did not Plato proclaim in
his Republic that men shall be happy
when kings become philosophers or
philosophers become kings? Machia-
velli, Rousseau and a good many others
meditated over the eternal problem of
the "good tyrant".
Nevertheless, man prefers not to put
himself in the hands of fate. Instead,
he demands guarantees the t's crossed
and i's dotted on his rights.
Men have fought hard to obtain such
guarantees of individual liberty from
Reginald Hemeleers was formerly a barrister at the
Brussels Court of Appeal. A founder and editor of
La Revue nouvelle and a former director of the Belgian
weekly, La Relève, he is the author of many papers
on legal questions. Since 1953, he has been head of
Unesco's Press Division.
their rulers. In England, centuries of
struggle led to the Habeas Corpus Act
adopted under Charles II in 1679 and
it was this act which spelled out the
main safeguards of individual liberty
to be found in most modern con¬
stitutions. The storming of the Bas¬
tille in Paris, a turning point in
Western history, was no more than a
popular uprising against a reign of ar¬
bitrary arrests and "letters of cachet".
Today, what guarantees do we have
of individual liberty? First, it should
be noted that they vary from country
to country. They have been stated
differently, having been integrated into
different legal structures but their
principles are generally the same.
The first of these principles is that
no man can be punished unless he has
violated a law already on the statute
books. The second is that his punish¬
ment must be decided by an inde¬
pendent magistrature independent,
that is, from the ruling power. At the
base of this system is the legislator
who must define prohibited acts in
advance and lay down penalties to
enforce his prohibitions.
Adopted by the United Nations Gen¬
eral Assembly on December 10, 1948,
the Universal Declaration of Human
Rights states, as a general principle,
that "no one shall be subjected to
arbitrary arrest, detention or exile".
Then it goes on to underscore the need
of a legal basis for any condemnation.
In Article II (section 2), it declares:
"No one shall be held guilty of any
penal offence on account of any act
or omission which ' did not constitute
a penal offence, under national or
international law, at the time when it
was committed. Nor shall a heavier
penalty be imposed than the one that
was applicable at the time the penal
offence was committed".
This is an enormous guarantee. The
definition of a crime and the fixing of
its penalty must be established in
advance and made known. Under this
article, it is not possible for the state
to concoct an infraction at the last
minute to imprison a citizen as has
been done so often in the past.
Still, it is only a guarantee in law.
It is not enough, unless it is reinforced
(Cont'd on next page)
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
JUSTIGE (Cont'd)
CAMEL-MOUNTED police capture a suspected bandit after a
wild chase across Syrian desert (lower photos). Above, suspect
'is interrogated by police authorities to determine whether formal
charges are to be preferred. (Copyright Paul Almasy).
by another concerning the enforcement
of the law. It is the judge, after all,
who must decide whether or not an
infraction has been committed and, if
necessary, pass sentence. He cannot
do so conscientiously unless he has a
clearly-defined status guaranteeing his
independence.
The Anglo-Saxon system of the
separation of powers, which has been
widely imitated, safeguards the inde¬
pendence of the judiciary both from
the legislative and the executive arms
of government. This independence
the law of the land in most nations
demands of any judge an acute aware¬
ness of his responsibilities and the
gravity of his mission. There would
be no point in protecting .the inde¬
pendence of a. judge willing to take
orders or vulnerable to corruption.
In France, Henri François d'Agues-
seau, chancellor of France in the early
18th century, has come to symbolize
the judge of integrity, fiercely jealous
of his independence. D'Aguesseau did
not hesitate to lay down a maxim
which remains true to this day: "The
judge who is not a hero is not even
an upright man."
Strictly speaking, the principles of
the legality of punishment and the
independence of the judiciary are not
guarantees of individual freedom. They
are merely two main prerequisites for
an equitable system of justice. Of
course, they give a defendant a
.maximum of opportunities to stand on
his rights, but they are only part of a
series of principles whose objective is
to avoid, insofar as possible, condemn¬
ing an innocent man.
The entire question of individual
liberty cannot be separated from the
problem of preventive custody. Ob¬
viously, if ,a man is suspected of a
serious crime such as a murder, he
cannot be left completely free until a
verdict is rendered. There is always
the risk that he may go into hiding
or flee the country. Secondly, in a
serious case, investigators nearly
always require that the suspect be
kept in custody if only to prevent him
destroying the evidence of his guilt.
This principle of preventive custody
is widely accepted and it does not
conflict with the Declaration of Human
Rights (Article II, Section 1) where it
is stated that "everyone charged with
a penal offence has the right to ' be
presumed innocent until proved guilty
according to law in a public trial at
which he had all the guarantees
necessary for his defence".
But preventive custody does carry
the seed of a grave danger to indi¬
vidual liberty the possibility that,
once a suspect is arrested, he may be
simply left to rot in prison by authori¬
ties that never go to the trouble of
accusing him formally and never give
him his day in court.
The insidious growth of a form of
administrative detention without any~
admitted causeand without any
fixed limit in time must be avoid¬
ed at any price. A perfect penal code
would be meaningless if authorities had
the power of locking up a citizen
without telling him which of its laws he
had violated. A corps of honest,
independent judges would be useless
if men could be imprisoned without
their cases ever coming before these
judges. And the accused man's care¬
fully-defined right to a defence is
valueless if he never has the possibility
of defending himself. Under such
conditions, society returns immediately
to the "letters of cachet" which the
burners of the Bastille thought they
had destroyed for eternity!
When burghers fled
To avoid these abuses, nearly every
country has laws to limit preven¬
tive custody. In most natrons, no
man can be arrested without a warrant
delivered by a judicial authority. Under,
the justly-famed principle of habeas
corpus, charges must be preferred
against him after an extremely short
period following his arrest. The burden
of proof is on the state to show why
preventive custody is believed neces¬
sary and why the suspect should not
be allowed to go out on bail.
In some countries, the procedure is
somewhat different. There, the state
must obtain a "confirmation" of the
warrant in court and, if the warrant is
not confirmed, the prisoner must be
set at liberty until his trial. In any
case, this confirmation is only for a
short period, usually several weeks,
and the warrant must be confirmed all
over again if the suspect is to be kept
behind bars.
This is a brief and simplified des¬
cription of the system of preventive
custody which varies in its finer points
from one country to another. It is
intended to provide only a general
- - r-
- J^"^'*-
.--*>*.'15*¿L'
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
view of a technique which has been
developed in the - long struggle for
human freedom to protect the citizen
in his dealings with authority.
Earlier, I mentioned that the average
citizen is usually comforted by- the
sight of a policeman. This has not al¬
ways been the case. For centuries,
burghers fled automatically at the
approach of the watch. Only a few
years ago, the Nazi regime filled pri¬
sons and concentration camps with
men who had never been judged, men
who were to die shamefully without
ever knowing the reason why. Even
today, all of the fundamental guar¬
antees of individual liberty proclaimed
in the Universal Declaration of Human
Rights are not fulfilled everywhere.
On this anniversary of Human
Rights Day, it might be wise to medi¬
tate for a few moments on the long,
hard road . which men have had to
travel before their "right to liberty and
security of person" was formally
recognized. This is the most basic of
rights after the right to life itself.
Until he is condemned, a defendant
is presumed innocent. It is up to the
state and its representative to prove
the accusations against him.
More than at any other time, it is
during the phase of investigation that
the state must remember that the
accused is presumed innocent and that,
even if -he is found guilty, he remains
a man and must be treated as one.
The Universal Declaration of Human
Rights states very simply: "No one
shall be subjected to torture or to
cruel, inhuman or degrading treatment
or punishment".
Curse of all eras
THERE is a good deal in this short
sentence. In its soberness, it
opens some frightening glimpses
of the infinite range of human agony.
Torture was not the exclusive property
of the Middle Ages. It has been the
curse of all eras and of all countries.
For there has always been and there
always will be the irritating case of
the defendant accused from all sides
but without any proof against him.
At this point you can find the
obsession of nearly every police force
the extortion of a confession.
Though the rack and the thumb¬
screw may not be used today, there
are still endless sessions of grilling
without food or sleep, to say nothing of
the more or less refined form of the
"third degree".
No doubt, the job of tracking down
criminals is a delicate one and basic
to the survival of society. But a
balance must be struck between the
demands of society and an elementary
respect for the man who is presumed
innocent under accusation.
'Occupational disease'
IT is this preliminary investigation
which is the most delicate phase of
the relationship between the citizen
and the judicial authorities. This is
the phase which is the least controlled
by law; therefore, it demands the
highest degree of education and of
conscience from judicial personnel at
all levels.
Once the investigation is complet¬
ed, the defendant is brought to
trial. In addition' to those two
basic guarantees of a legal basis for
punishment and the independence of
the judiciary, there are two other prin¬
ciples fundamental to equitable justice:
a public trial and the presence of
counsel for the defendant.
Low blows are always struck in the
dark. Throughout history, one-sided
trials have been held behind closed
doors and often before special juris¬
dictions created to hear a single case.
The public trial is a strong guarantee
of justice. Within a locked room, a few
accomplices can perjure away the
weight of evidence. But it is much
more difficult to do so in public,
especially in front of press writers
whose accounts of the testimony may
be printed for millions to read.
This does not mean that justice
should be rendered with an eye to
public opinion, which is often impas¬
sioned and ill-informed. The verdict
is the province only of the judge's
conscience and it is up to him to
divorce himself from any external
influences.
The right of the defendant to a
counsel of his own choice to aid him
Unesco Courier. Nr 10. 1954
and act in his name is so essential
that, without it, all of the other
guarantees become almost illusory. A
defendant .can be illiterate or, at any
rate, unfamiliar with legal procedure,
where only a specialist after all is at
heme. If a competent person cannot
act fcr him, then the advantages of the
prosecution are absurdly one-sided.
Many countries accord another
guarantee to defendants facing serious
charges: the right to trial by jury. The
jury, you might say, offsets the risk
that the judge might suffer from a sort
of "occupational disease" as the result
of his coming into contact every day
with criminals and, therefore, might
tend to see criminals everywhere. The
jury relieves the specialist of his
heaviest responsibility and confides it
to a dozen citizens chosen by. lot.
Experience has proved that jurors,
freed as they are from the grinding
routine of law, usually perform their
duties with the utmost conscientious¬
ness and often lend a more willing
ear to the Counsel for the defence
when he argues the weaknesses of the
evidence presented than might a judge
who had heard such arguments all too
often in the past.
No courts infallible
ONE after another, these guar¬
antees have made justice a net
whose mesh allows the innocent
to pass but traps the guilty. The
guarantees cited here are only the
most often applied. They provide a
picture of humanity's eternal effort to
bring order to society without menac¬
ing the peaceful citizen.
Courts have always made mistakes.
The most perfect technique can only
serve to reduce the number of these
mistakes to a minimum. But anyone
who has studied the problem closely
will agree that judicial error is one of
the most flagrant scandals which can
afflict society, a scandal which must
be combatted as if it were the plague.
. When citizens lose confidence in
justice, they return to the anarchy of
personal revenge. This means nothing
less than the death of liberty, the
oppression of the weak by the strong
and the very negation of rule by law.
^iteî^^^&Ésa Afc.«
' ' ¡-TU >373y%$S*ii**V^
7
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
BIG, OLD PRISONS are still the rule rather than the exception in the penitentiary systems of all countries.
Prison design and construction has not kept pace with progress in penal ideals and methods. The result is
that convicted offenders still serve their sentences in "man-cages", like the prison above, and are often
required to "exercise" in the limited space of a prison yard like the one shown, below. Of these particular
exercise yards, one observer wrote: "They are a maze of concrete, with sad oases of earth, where a few
soot-covered flowers turn their defeated faces to the sky. Here the prisoners walk round and round and
back and forth, clockwise and anticlockwise, as if in a crazy squirrel cage".
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Dlne April afternoon many years ago, I found
I myself on the roof of a large school which
I was being built in a suburb of Paris. With
j me were two friends, the architect (one of the
J most famous in Prance) and an Italian anti-
| fascist political leader who had . recently
I escaped from one of Mussolini's gaols.
The three of us were inspecting the new
building which was almost completed. We
admired its beautiful lines, its highly rational structure and
its bold conception. The new school was obviously the
product of a highly civilized world. It was open to the
sun and fresh air and dedicated to children who were free
and carefully looked after.
From the top of the roof, we stopped to look down on the
old houses of the suburb
and the surrounding coun¬
tryside. The architect and
the political leader began
a .discussion on their im¬
pressions. The politician,
recalling his prison exper¬
ience, said that after the
defeat of Fascism, the
architect would have to
help wipe out the shame
of our old prisons by
building new ones design¬
ed like the new school
modern, humane, open
on the world and offering
every comfort required.
The architect replied that
never, at any price, would
he have any hand in the
building of a prison.
Not having any first¬
hand knowledge of prison
life at the time (though I
later obtained it quite a
number of times) I merely
listened. It seemed to me
that both of my friends
were guilty of the same
sin of Utapianism. But if
I had had to choose be¬
tween the two Utopias, I
must say it would have
been that of the architect
who wanted to abolish
prisons altogether rather
than that of the political
leader who wished to
make them comfortable.
When you dream, I said
to myself, you might as
well let the dream be as
perfect as possible.
I was reminded of this
conversation some years
later in a Florence prison
room where I was being
interrogated by a member
of the Fascist political
police, O.V.R.A. By that time I had become an old hand
at prisons. -To me, a prison had always seemed a
complete absurdity, like a place that is not really a place,
or time that is not time.
On entering the prison room I saw that it was almost
entirely taken up by a large iron cage something like
the ones circus people use to exhibit their wild animals.
The thought that this cage had been built to imprison a
human being seemed so ludicrous to me that I could not
restrain a short burst of laughter.
We were in the spring of 1943. By then, a session of
questioning by the O.V.R.A. police was no longer a terrify¬
ing event. Fascism was already dead from exhaustion.
A leading Italian writer and artist. Carlo Levi suffered imprisonment and was banish¬
ed to South Italy for his opposition to the fascist Regime. He is the author of
Christ Stopped at Eboli and other works.
"After some months or years, the prisoner loses his sense of time to the point
where the reality of his own existence blurs and vanishes."
Unesco Courier. N' 10. 1954
I therefore told my police official how utterly senseless
and insane the whole idea of prisons seemed to me with
the iron cage standing as the symbol of our absurd ritual
of punishment. The police official turned to mc with a
look of pitying stupefaction on his face. Then, he pointed
his finger toward the cage, and his eyes lit up with ecstatic
admiration. "What are you talking about, doctor," he
exclaimed, "it's the very foundation of the State !"
What was this State, founded on cages, on walls and
padlocks, on bars and grills, on blind devotion to authority
and on the coercive separation of its inhabitants, which
my police official worshipped? It was the Fascist Slate.
But the Fascist State did not invent the "man-cages". The
march of history does not mean that the slate of the past
is wiped completely clean. Too often, ugly practices of
the past arc carried along
side by side with new
ideas, new developments
and real progress.
Thus even todav, and in
the most advanced demo¬
cracies of our time, we
still find certain practices
and institutions dating
back to the Middle Ages,
and numerous traces of
antiquated authoritarian¬
ism. That is precisely
how I feel about our pri¬
sons. To me, prisons are
a typical relic of archaic
and cruel cults, one of
those carry-overs of past
history which humanity
has allowed to subsist al¬
most through indifference
and inertia, if not through
ignorance.
Let there be no mis¬
understanding about what
I have just said. It is
obvious that the State, any
State, must be able to
defend itself against com¬
mon, even political, crimi¬
nals. It is equally obvious
that when the need arises,
the State must be able to
isolate those dangerous
elements. And it is fin¬
ally obvious that all mea¬
sures that are truly effica¬
cious are legitimate, pro¬
viding one condition, but
an essential one, is met.
That is that the criminal's
dignity as a human being
be scrupulously respected.
Various measures exist :
surveillance, confinement
to an institution for the
mentally ill, restricted res¬
idence, exile, work colo¬
nies and finally imprison¬
ment. But as soon as any one of these repressive
measures becomes an offence against human dignity,
I believe it is no exaggeration to say that from that
moment on the punishment itself becomes a crime.
The idea of punishing people by segregating them from
the rest of society is based on two somewhat different, if
not heterogeneous, nouons. There is the legitimate
desire to safeguard public order, and also a survival of
archaic beliefs requiring that a crime be expiated by
ritual sacrifice.
In a primitive society considered by its members as an
organic whole, the individual exists only as an integral
part of the clan. Any infraction of the- normal rules of
collective life immediately becomes a stain on the social
body, and must be erased by the expulsion or even the
destruction of the guilty member. (Continued on next page)
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
WHEN THE PUNISHMENT
TOO BECOMES A CRIME
i
(Continued from previous page)
An obvious trace of this mentality remains in our penal
system in the form of the prison, which implies that the'
offender should be hidden from the eyes of others, so
that, having shut out the source of the collective stain,
the public can once again enjoy an easy conscience.
Christian tradition added its ideas of sin, repentance and
redemption to this old-fashioned attitude, endowing
prisons with the strange character they have today, an
anticipation of hell and purgatory." And finally, modern
schools of penal law grafted on to the Christian con¬
ception, the philanthropic idea of re-educating the
criminal.
Obviously, re-education should be attempted by psycho¬
logical and moral means rather than by physical com¬
pulsion. For it would be a patent contradiction of the
idea of re-education to attempt to achieve it by the use of
restraint. But since the notion of physical punishment,
which is the basis of the penalty of imprisonment, has not
yet been submitted to a radical re-examination, it should
be clear that the idea of re-education, although a healthy
one in itself, threatens to add to the physical restraint of
the prisoner a justification of moral constraint which is
extremely dangerous for the inalienable character ot
human liberty.
' Habeas Animam ' as well as ' Habeas Corpus '
t was with this in mind that a young Italian scholar,
to rwhom Fascism had extended the dreadful privilege
of 15 years of prison life, demanded in a series of
articles that the "habeas corpus" should be completed by a
recognition of the "habeas animam". "In a society
founded on respect for the human person," this author
wrote, the soul of even the most abject criminal should
be protected by a habeas animam the sacred right to
inviolability from any judge, or any gaoler... Prison, as
it exists today, is deprived of all redeeming qualities,
because the prisoner gets used to it, and rots there. But.
the prison which has been turned into a laboratory of
redemption, a sanatorium of souls, is a mechanism which
corrupts everyone: those who direct it, those ground down
by it, and those who believe in its utility." . "
It seems to me that so long as the penalty of segregation
retains its character of a sacred vengeance, all attempts to
reconcile imprisonment with the idea of re-education (and
thus with the idea of human dignity which re-education
pre-supposes), will be vain.
The problem posed for modern man
by the persistence of the primitive
conception of punishment as sym¬
bolized by prison, cannot be reduced to
the elimination of physical suffering
such as lack of air and light, dirt, bad
food and the occasional cruelty of
warders. These are conditions 'which
it is certainly worth while trying to
change; but the essential problem is
elsewhere.
Job, seated on his dung heap,
afflicted by a thousand ills and a
thousand woes, loses nothing of his
human dignity, nor of his essential
freedom. But the cleanest and most
scientifically organized prison, the
most humane, in appearance, causes
irreparable harm to the personality of
the prisoner after a certain time, for
the prison strikes at the very depths of
man's being,- at his consciousness of
time. Consciousness of time and exist¬
ence of the individual are two expres-
10
sions of the same reality : the living and moving reality
of the relations between the individual and the World
within eternity. After a certain number of months or years,
the prisoner loses his sense of time to the' point where the
reality of his own existence blurs and vanishes.
He lives in a world without dimensions, without future,
without passions, and thus without humanity.
An unknown force pushes him down
Another Italian intellectual has attempted to draw a
mathematical pattern of what he calls "the wait of
the prisoner". He says : "after a certain number
of years, everything takes place in the consciousness of
the prisoner as if his prison term would never come to an
end. From this moment, all imprisonment is an im¬
prisonment for life. "
"In the 'Metamorphosis' of Kafka, when young Gregory
discovers that each time he tries to get up an -unknown
force pushes him down again, he abandons all hope. He
knows at this moment that he has lost the human dimen¬
sion, despairs and dies. A similar metamorphosis takes
place after a certain time in the personality of the
prisoner : time disintegrates and death, which dominates
his fate, seems infinite and interminable."
The author concludes that nothing can justify a muti¬
lation of the human being which reaches the point of
altering his deepest feelings and his spiritual life. At the
same time, he hastens to add, society is probably not yet
ready for a radical change in the penalties of impri¬
sonment. But the idea that they might be limited to a
maximum of five years, is perhaps not a foolish hope.
I personally believe that in the existing state of society,
any attempt at radical reform of these penalties would be
premature and doomed to failure. But the problem,
nevertheless, remains, and it seems to me that, together
with Unesco's efforts to publicize the Universal Declaration,
an attempt should be made to make present-day society
more aware of these particularly acute problems of human
rights. In my opinion, the problem of the relationship
between the modern penitentiary system and our con¬
ception of human dignity deserves discussion and thought.
I cannot help feeling that the present penitentiary system
as practised in almost every country is marked by the
cruelty, inhumanity and degradation condemned by
Article 5 in the Universal Declaration.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
STORY OF
PRISONS
Their evolution as an
agency of punishment
by Ronald Fenton
Unesco Courier. Nr 10. 1954
PRISON HULKS like this one in the
dockyard at Portsmouth, England, were
used to confine convicts in the last half
of the eighteenth century. Dirty, crowded
and unhealthy, these terrible floating pris¬
ons were constantly infected with disease.
THE PANOPTICON, a circular prison
with cells around the outside walls, was-
designed in 1791 by Jeremy Bentham, the
English philosopher, jurist and social re¬
former. He called it the "Panopticon" or
'"inspection house" because of the ease
with which the whole building could be
observed from a control point in the centre.
Hait-Plan-
^1 - --»-*.
RISONS, said the Romans,
two thousand years ago, are
places for holding, not for
punishing offenders. Today
we are slowly coming back
to' this ancient Roman definition of
prisons, which modern penologists feel
should not be used for punishing an
offender, but for his safe custody and
rehabilitation.
Does this mean that history is
repeating itself? Only up to a point,
for the ideas behind these ancient and
modern definitions of a prison's role
are poles apart. Today we are coming
closer to the idea that the man goes into
prison but his crime halts at the gate.
In ancient times a - man was not
sentenced by law to spend years in pris¬
on. But he had little to hope for as
he laid in some dark, filthy cell. He
might rot there for years awaiting trial
or because he was unable to pay a fine
or a debt. If he had already been
found guilty of a crime, prison was
merely a prelude to brutal corporal
punishment or a horrible death.
Today hope is no longer locked out¬
side as the prison gate closes behind a
convicted offender. Society claims
"the right to punish" and uses prison
as a weapon of self-defence, but it also
recognizes the prisoner's right to be
treated as a human being.
Slowly, humanity has removed the
sting of hatred and cruelty from
punishment. It has begun to look at
the man beneath the criminal, to see
the need for helping him rather than
making him suffer. Thus a prison's
primary role is to give men and women
treatment and guidance that can help
to reform them and to prevent them
relapsing into crime after their release.
When we pass by some, prison or
reformatory and look up at the high
walls and barred windows we wonder
what prison life is like. We may feel'
sorry for those inside because they have
been deprived of freedom or we may
think, unfeelingly, '"it serves them
right". But in either case we look on
prison as the normal way of dealing
with someone found guilty of a crime.
People today are so used to the idea
of an offender being punished by a
prison sentence that they tend to
forget how long it took for their fore¬
bears to accept the same idea. They
forget, too, that it is not so long ago
since men and women in many coun¬
tries were engaged in one of the fier¬
cest struggles in the history of human
rightsthe fight to end the cruel
and- inhuman treatment of prisoners.
Until less than a century and a half
ago most punishments prescribed by
law were brutal and even barbarous.
It is in the code of Hammurabi,
dating back some 4,000 years, that we
first meet the lex talionis, the demand
for revenge of a crime later expressed
in the Biblical words:"an eye for an
eye and a tooth for a tooth". Offenders
were regarded as "brutes", and treated
as such. From earliest times torture
was used, not only to extract, con¬
fessions, but also as a punishment.
Even Aristotle, the great Greek philos¬
opher, condoned torture, and its
elaborate regulation in Roman law
became the basis for all the gruesome
medieval legislation in Italy, Spain,
France and Germany. Though not
authorized by common law, torture
was .practised in England under royal
privilege in the days of the Tudors and
the Stuarts.
Persons condemned to death were
executed in the most horrible ways
imaginable. They were crucified, ston¬
ed to death, buried alive, torn apart by
wild horses, thrown to wild beasts.
Even when forms of capital pun¬
ishment became more humane, more
offences became capital ones. In the
England. of 1789 there were, according
(Continued on page 14)
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
BEHIND the reforms which have gradually diminished the
horror of prison conditions, there are the works of phi¬
losophers and jurists who fought for equality between
men, respect for the individual and the supremacy of reason
over prejudice. There is also the example of charity relieving
suffering and defying unjust laws. The humble devotion of
a St Vincent de Paul was as important to this movement as
the genius of a Spinoza or a Grotius. And it is quite clear
that there is a direct link from Locke, Voltaire, Montesquieu,
Christian Wolff, Helvetius or Rousseau down to the
somewhat specialized reformers a few of whom are presented
here. Here are some of the great men to whom we owe the
major features of our modern penal institutions.
Seven apostles
of the
prisoner's rights
Cesare
Beccaria
(1738-1790)
Few books have had as
much influence on our penal
systems as the great work of
Cesare Beccaria : "Trattato
dei delitti e delle pene"
(Essay on Crimes and
Punishment) which appear¬
ed in 1764. It was an
immediate success in Italy
and in France. Soon, its
fame spread throughout Eu¬
rope and to America. Even
more important, its teachings
were to be embodied several
years later in the constitu¬
tions of certain nations
which, in turn, served ' as
models to the lawmakers of
nearly every country on
earth.
Beccaria was a disciple of
Montesquieu, whose "Persian
Letters" he read enthusiasti¬
cally at the age of 22, and a
friend of d'Alembert, Dide¬
rot, Helvetius and Buffon
- 4 - - S
counting the steps, measur¬
ing the rooms, copying down
the regulations and testing
the supplies. He is said to
have spent over £30,000 of
his own fortune in the work.
Howard then turned his
attention to quarantine sta¬
tions, the lazarettos, where
plague victims or contacts
were isolated, and coura¬
geously visited those of
Constantinople and Smyrna.
Travelling from . Smyrna to
Venice he purposely chose a
ship with a foul bill of
health, knowing that he
would thus be confined in a
lazaretto on arrival in Ven¬
ice. He spent 42 days in
two lazarettos studying
conditions at first hand.
There remained the prob¬
lem of military hospitals,
and knowing those of Russia
to be very defective he set
out on what was to be his
last journey. It took him to
St Petersburg, Moscow and,
eventually, to Kherson, in
the Ukraine, where he nurs¬
ed a young woman suffering
from "camp fever" and died
of it himself on January 20,
1790.
Philippe Pinel
(1745-1826)
About the year 1765, a
French medical student
named Philippe Pinel revolt¬
ed against the prejudices,
case-hardened traditions and
bookish teachings of his day.
He wanted to apply to medi¬
cine "a method similar to
that of the other physical
sciences". ' He followed this
idea all of his life, but he
won his greatest glory as a
liberator. It was not crimi¬
nals who were freed by Pinel
but the insane who had been
treated up until then (at
least in the Western World)
as criminals and worse.
As physician to the Bicetre
Hospital where male lunatics
were kept in Paris in 1793,
he could no longer bear the
sight of these miserable crea¬
tures howling in the cages
where they were chained and
whipped. He wrote to his
superiors: "Far from being
criminals who must be pun¬
ished, the insane are sick
persons whose pitiful state
deserves all of the considera¬
tion we owe to suffering
humanity." The authorities
hesitated; one of the leaders
of the Reign of Terror came
to Bicetre to see for himself.
"Citizen, you must be crazy
yourself to wish to unchain
such beasts" he said.
Pinel's answer perhaps
went beyond merely the
insane: "I am convinced that
the reason why nothing can
be done with them is because
we deprive them of freedom."
He "unchained" his patients
and, two years later, he did
the same for insane women
at the Salpetriere Hospital.
The book he wrote on his
"Research and Observations
on the Treatment of the
Insane" spread his ideas far
and wide. They were daring
ideas: he preached that men
could be cured of insanity
only through the use of
"reason, sensitiveness and
persuasion". "The insane", he
wrote, "should be approached
with a love of humanity
great enough to inspire the
courage to conquer routine
and fear."
Jeremy
Bentham
(1748-1832)
Jeremy Bentham, one of
the English pioneer prison
refcrmers, like Beccaria, bas¬
ed his thinking on the great
principle of utilitarianism :
the just action is the one
which brings the greatest
happiness ( to the greatest
number of' people. This was
the foundation of his work
as a moralist and as a jurist
which brought him recog¬
nition and admiration from
such disciples as Mirabeau,
Thomas Paine and Benjamin
Rush, from distant corres¬
pondents such as Mohamed
Ali and from a large number
of far less respectful imita¬
tors and plagiarists. Talley¬
rand once commented of
Bentham: "Though pillaged
by everyone, he remains
rich". In his writings, Ben¬
tham maintained that pun¬
ishment is an evil in itself
ana can only be accepted "so
far as it promises to exclude
some greater evil".
In his conception of the
treatment of offenders Ben-
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N' 10 1954
- 2 - 3
-who received him trium¬
phantly in Paris.
Applying to criminal law
the main precepts of the
"philosophy of light", Becca¬
ria began with the "Social
Contract", under which the
individual voluntarily gives
up part of his liberty as
small a part as- possible. to
society. The only objective
of criminal law, he reasoned,
was to defend society and,
therefore, the restraint it
places upon the guilty man
can go no further than is
absolutely necessary to pro¬
tect society. As for the
death penalty, it is neither
useful nor necessary, and,
added Beccaria, it has no
basis in law because no indi¬
vidual has ever voluntarily
given society the right to
decide if he is to live or die.
Beccaria probably never
would have written his
book without the help of two
of his fellow countrymen,
the Verri brothers, both ar¬
dent reformers. In Milan,
Alessandro Verri was known
as "the protector of pri¬
soners" and he lashed out
daily against the frequency
of judicial errors, the irregu¬
larity of court procedure, the
cruelty and the dispropor
tionate nature of penalties,
tho use . of torture and the
hellish conditions in prisons.
"Of Crimes and Punish¬
ment", therefore, was the
fruit of common meditation
over first-hand evidence. In
fact, this book became known
not so much for its princi¬
ples but for its criticism of
the arbitrary and ferocious
judicial methods of its time.
Those who read this scathing
analysis (among them was
the Empress of Russia) were
unable to do so without a
feeling of shame. In the
end, their shame proved
salutary.
John Howard
(1726-1790)
When John Howard, a
wealthy English landowner,
was appointed High Sheriff
of Bedfordshire in 1773, one
of his duties was the safe
custody of prisoners in his
county. But unlike others
holding the ' same office in
England he was more
concerned about the dread¬
ful state of the prisons and
the misery of the inmates
than with the problem of
preventing them from escap¬
ing.
He was particularly shock¬
ed to find in prison people
who had been declared not
guilty or against whom a
Grand Jury had failed to
find a true bill of accusa¬
tions, but who remained
there simply because they
could not pay "release fees"
to the prison officers.
It was true that many
such men and women were
not likely to stay in prison
indefinitely for they had
every chance of dying
quickly from hunger or
disease. Howard set out to
change what he had seen in
his county's prisons. Visit¬
ing jails, poorhouses and
houses of correction, he un¬
covered many abuses. When
the evidence he collected
was placed before Parlia¬
ment, two bills were passed
requiring counties to pay
their prison staffs and to
clean prisons, and clothe and
care for the inmates.
But Howard was still not
satisfied. After visiting Scot¬
tisn and Irish prisons he
went to France and visited
the principal Paris jails,
although he failed to get
inside the Bastille. From
here he went to Holland
Flanders and Germany. A
second visit to the continent
and more inspections in
England gave him the mate¬
rial he required for his fa¬
mous work "The Stat» of the
Prisons in England and
Wales", in which he also
included accounts of some
foreign prisons. One of the
results was the passing of a
bill authorizing the construc¬
tion of two penitentiary
houses in which it was
intended to introduce suc¬
cessful mesures Howard had
seen in Ghent and Amster¬
dam such as giving inmates
useful work to do.
A simple, deeply religious
man, Howard worked unaid¬
ed by either state or chari¬
table institutions. Self ap¬
pointed inspector of prisons
at home and abroad he tra¬
velled some 50,000 miles, note¬
book in hand, visiting pri¬
sons, hospitals, lazarettos,
schools and poorhouses,
questioning the authorities,
6 7
tham was far in advance of
his age, but a plan for prison
reform which he proposed
was spoiled by the elaborate
detail which he loved. Under
this scheme, he declared:
"Morals would be reformed,
health preserved, industry
invigorated and instruction
diffused."
Manuel
Montesinos
(19th century)
If a traveller had set out
in 1835 to visit the world's
most modern and most "pro¬
gressive" prison, he would
probably have ended up in
Valencia, Spain. There, Colo¬
nel Manuel Montesinos had
set up a penal system which
'combined liberal ideas with
firm discipline. He operated
it on principles which, even
today, are sometimes regard¬
ed as novel and surprising.
Our traveller certainly would
have been' struck by the
appearance of this prison,
the cleanliness of its cells, its
dining rooms and its work¬
shops, and the charm of its
gardens. He would have
admired the wide variety of
occupations offered its in¬
mates in all, more than
forty trades were taught
there. But Montesinos' ma¬
jor innovation was his me¬
thod of individualized treat¬
ment. When an inmate
arrived at Valencia, he
underwent a detailed exami¬
nation of "his instincts, his
culture, his education and
his moral and religious
situation", and this study
continued until his release.
It was Montesinos who de¬
clared: "Tho crime remains
outside the door of this ins¬
titution; our mission is to
re-educate the man".
Cesare
Lontbroso
(1835-1909)
When Society had recog¬
nised that the insane were
not criminals, a delicate
question began to be posed:
were criminals, in many
cases, mentally abnormal?
The answer of Cesare Lom-
broso of Italy was that "the
criminal is more often a sick
man than a guilty one". A
psychiatrist and an anthro¬
pologist, Lombroso pleaded
that nations, instead of
passing hasty judgments,
should study "the human ac¬
tion called crime". This stu¬
dy, in his opinion, should not
be solely the business of jud¬
ges but should be entrusted
to specialists capable of exa¬
mining a criminal on the
basis of "climate, geography,
race, population density,
birth-rate, diet, alcoholism,
education, economy, religion
and, finally, the prison it¬
self." It was a demanding
programme. To Lombroso, a
crime was usually only the
act of an abnormal or a sick
person. Society's duty in
connection with crime,
therefore, should be only
concerned with "curing the
delinquent." "It is time,"
he declared, "that we change
our concept of the defence
of society to one of rehabili¬
tating the guilty man."
Franz von Liszt
(1815-1919)
One of the most illustrious
figures in criminal law, Franz
von Liszt was as illustrious
in science as was his cousin
in music. Liszt's life work
was the scientific foundation
and reform of criminal law.
He challenged the principle
of regarding punishment as
a reprisal and introduced
the method of investigating
the causes of crime. To¬
gether with G.A. ven Hamel
of Amsterdam and Adolphe
Prins of Brussels, he estab¬
lished in 1889 the Interna¬
tional Association of Crimi¬
nal Law (L'Union Interna¬
tionale de Droit Penal) . The
Association contended that
crime and punishment should
be considered as much from
a sociological as from a judi¬
cial point of view, and the
reforms it initiated became
the basis of modern criminal
law. Liszt's efforts is favour
of conditional sentence and
pardon as well as postpone¬
ment of punishment later
passed into practice.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
The horror of
early prisons
(Continued from page II)
to one authority, no less than 350
capital crimes, compared with only
17 in the early part of the 15th
century. Most of those added after
1500 were offences against property
mostly trivial crimes.
But these brutal laws eventually
provoked a revolt against capital
punishment in 18th century England.
Juries either acquitted the accused or
found them guilty of stealing 39
shillings (the theft of 40 shillings was
a capital offence) regardless of the sum
they confessed to stealing or were
proved to have stolen.
Flogging and branding
Brutal punishments were imposed
for minor offences. Flogging,
branding and mutilation were
the most common. In 16th century
England a beggar was whipped for a
first offence; for the second an ear
was cut off; for the third offence the
penalty was death. Reasoning that
"they might as well be hanged for a
sheep as a lamb," beggars turned to
a more rewarding form of crime
robbery.
.Nagging housewives were strapped
in a ducking stool and plunged repeat¬
edly into a pond. For such offences as
seditious libel, especially in books
published without a licence, giving
short weight and brawling in the
street, favourite instruments of pun¬
ishment in England and the Ameri¬
can Colonies were the pillory and the
stocks. These pinned the victim's
wrists or ankles while he was jeered
at and pelted with rotten vegetables in
the market place.
It was only in the 16th century that
THE PILLORY was once a favourite form of pun
Pinned by wrists and head, offenders were jeered
! L
I*v v i^iiÉyMMMM	Ij
LONGITUDINAL SECTION
tlTniTT
WORi HALL
urn
PAPAL PRISON of Saint Michael, built by Pope Clement XI in Rome, in I 704, was the first important
prison to house inmatesin this case delinquent boysin individual cells. Three tiers of ten cells
lined up on both sides of a building whose centre was used as a workshop for the inmates. Thirty
years later the papal authorities built a second prison designed on similar lines for delinquent women.
prisons began' to be used as places for
punishment in England. This was no
humanitarian move inspired by legal
reforms. There was, in fact, little
humanitarian improvement in penal
practices for another two centuries.
The setting up of prisons was brought
about by the increase in the number of
vagrants towards the end of the medi¬
eval system.
Under the feudal system, the landed
classes regularly provided for their
dependents and helped them in sick¬
ness and old age. Such organized
charity as was needed was provided by
ishment in England and the American Colonies,
at and pelted with rotten eggs and vegetables.
the Church. The end of the medieval
system cut off this "social assistance"
and created a serious poverty problem.
This new situation, together with the
enclosure of peasant farming land in
England, swelled the number of unruly
vagrants to such an extent that the
authorities set up crude prisons in
which to confine the army of vaga-,
bonds, and these early institutions
were the forerunners of our prisons.
The first, opened in 1557 at St. Bride's
Well, in London, gave the name
"Bridewells" _ to others which were
established during the next half cen¬
tury. These Bridewells were the earli¬
est work-houses (or poor-houses as
they were called in Scotland, and later
in America.) The Poor Relief Act of
1601 . directed the overseers of every
parish to raise funds "for providing a
convenient stock of flax, hemp, wool,
thread, iron and other ware and stuff
to set the poor on work." But in this
early period authorities preferred to
maintain "houses of correction" for the
punishment of vagabonds.
Work-houses for the poor then began
to be built on the Continent, especially
in Germany and Holland in the cen¬
tury following 1560. But it was not
until 1773 that the first North Euro¬
pean workhouse which had the main
characteristics of a modern prison'
separate cells and work as a disci¬
plinary and reformative measure
was built at Ghent, Belgium.
Orphans herded with maniacs
IN the 17th and 18th centuries pris¬
ons were filthy, -fever-breeding
places in which men, women and
children - were crowded together
without ventilation and with virtually
no food except what friends provided
or jailers sold. In the workhouses
authorities herded together orphans,
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 10. 1954
old people, criminals, consumptives
and maniacs in large open dormitories.
Already in the 17th century men and .
women were trying to improve con¬
ditions in the prisons and workhouses.
One man who put his ideas into prac¬
tice by personal example was Filippo
Franci. A Catholic humanitarian,
Franci first set up a small workhouse
for unruly and vagrant boys in Floren¬
ce, about 1650, and it was probably his
work and also that of Dom Jean Ma-
billon, the great Benedictine scholar,
which inspired Pope . Clement XI in
1704 to create a prison for delinquent
boys as part of the hospital of St.
Michael in Rome.
What distinguished this prison from
others of the period was its individual
cells. These lined two sides of a large
rectangular cell house, the centre space
being used as a workshop by the in¬
mates. Thirty years later the papal
authorities made another innovation,
building a prison on similar lines for
delinquent women. These two prisons
were the first to bear any close
resemblance to those of today.
Breaking the shackles
New and more powerful forces were
then set in motion by the wave
of ideas which swept in with the
Intellectual Revolution of the 17th and
18th centuries. The rationalism of
The Enlightenment, as it was called,
helped to break the shackles of politi¬
cal tyranny, and the humanitarianism
inspiring this opposition to oppression
carried over into agitation for penal
reform and for the abolition of slavery.
Barbarous criminal laws were attacked
in the middle of the 18th century by
Voltaire and also by ' Montesquieu,
. whose Persian Letters satirized the
European criminal law of this period.
But the most influential reformer in
the field of criminal law was the Ital¬
ian nobleman, Cesare di Beccaria
(1738-1794). His Essay on Crimes and
Punishments, written in 1764, was prob¬
ably the most effective book written
in the whole history of criminal-law
reform. Beccaria argued that the
prevention of ^ crime was more impor¬
tant than punishment; that torture
should be abolished; that punishment
should be used to deter men from
committing crimes rather than to
inflict social revenge on an individual;
that imprisonment should replace cor¬
poral punishment and that capital
punishment should be abandoned.
With . the exception of psychology
and psychiatry which have only recent¬
ly been applied to crime, Beccaria
suggested most of the essentials of
criminological progress that have been
achieved since his work was published
nearly two centuries ago.
Beccaria's book created a veritable
sensation. It was translated into a
score of languages, and Voltaire him¬
self wrote an anonymous preface for
the French edition. Above all, it
stimulated people to improve prison
conditions in many lands, directly
influencing several rulers including
Catherine II, Empress of Russia and
the Grand Duke of Tuscany, who abo¬
lished torture and capital punishment
in his realm.
Beccaria's ideas inspired British re¬
formers like Sir Samuel Romilly and
Jeremy Bentham, and strongly in¬
fluenced the revision of the criminal
codes of the new American states after
1776, the new. criminal code of Revo¬
lutionary France and the reform of
the British criminal code in the first
half of the 19th century.
One of the blackest chapters in the
history of punishment concerns the
penal colonies to which many countries
at one time sent convicted men.
Portugal sent many of its criminals to
Ceuta in North Africa. As early as
1497 those from Spain were sent to the
West Indian island of Hispaniola.
England made the greatest use of
this form of punishment, but not as a
humane substitute for other kinds.
Shipping convicts out of the country
was merely an easy way of solving the
problem of keeping criminals in custody
in England. It was considered con¬
venient and economical and it-provided
a labour force for colonial areas.
Until the American Revolutionary War
put an end to penal colonies in North
America .convicts were sent from
England to Maryland and other
southern colonies more than 50,000 of
them between 1607 and 1776.
Then Australia provided a new
RUNNING THE GAUNTLET was one of the
brutal military punishments of the past in which
a convicted man had to run stripped to the waist
between two rows of soldiers who struck at
him with a stick or a knotted cord. This drawing
shows the punishment being inflicted in 18th
century Austria. The victim was forced forward
at the point of the bayonet, but prevented from
passing too quickly, between the ranks by a
soldier preceding him with a reversed musket.
"dumping ground" when it began to be
opened up as a British colony. Be¬
tween 1787 and 1852 more than 100,000 -
men and women were shipped in filthy
vessels to the prison settlements of
Australia, Tasmania and Norfolk
Island. Many died en route, some
starved to death in the colonies and
others escaped to become "bushran¬
gers" who attacked and robbed the
colonists. Only after a British par¬
liamentary inquiry had denounced the
system as "unequal, without terror to
the criminal class, corrupting to both
convicts and colonists", was convict
transportation abandoned.
The inhuman conditions in which
convicts wer« shipped to Australia
were no worse than those to which
were subjected aboard the
"floating prisons" the old hulks
anchored in British ports. These
ships were filthy, crowded and con¬
stantly infested with disease.
Credit for. rousing the public con¬
science to the barbarism of such
conditions belongs to John Howard, ,
One of the greatest names in the his-
tory of prison reform.
Born in 1726, the son of well-to-do
parents, Howard began his humani¬
tarian work while in his twenties. In
1754, when he sailed to Portugal to aid
earthquake victims in Lisbon he ex¬
perienced the harsh prison conditions
of his day after his ship had been
captured by the French.
But it was in 1773 when, as high
sheriff of Bedfordshire, he visited
Bedford Jail that he fully realized the
terrible conditions existing in his own
country. Horrified by what he saw,
he launched his great crusade at home
and abroad, to expose the horrible
misery which prisoners underwent.
Howard was particularly shocked by
the injustice of the system of exacting
fees for safe conduct and delivery from
jail levied by the unsalaried prison
officials. His efforts to obtain salaries
for them brought Parliamentary action
in 1774, and the disgraceful fee system
was abolished. Thanks to Howard
hundreds of innocent prisoners who
had been unable to pay the delivery
fees, were at last released. At his
own expense Howard had the terms of
the new legislation printed and sent to
every jailer and warder in England.
Howard made four detailed inspec¬
tions of British prisons and went
abroad to study the conditions in those
of Germany, France, the Low Countries
"and Switzerland. On his return he
published The State of the Prisons in
England and Wales. Other reforms
were sparked by his revelations, in¬
cluding the passing of a bill for setting
up penitentiary houses in which pri¬
soners would be confined in cells and
given work to do.
The sudden stirring of England's
conscience by Howard's crusade was
the dawn of prison reform which
slowly developed into the modern
humanitarian movement. Howard's
name is commemorated today in the
Howard League for Penal Reform, an
active British organization.
' Hell above ground '
A. Nother great Englishman who
turned his brilliant mind to the,
problem of legal reform and
prison conditions was Jeremy Ben¬
tham, philosopher, jurist and social
reformer, who lived from 1748 to 1832.
He drew up a scheme for the treatment
of criminals under which he believed
"morals would be reformed, health
preserved, industry invigorated and
instruction diffused", and also worked
out plans for an entirely new prison.
A circular building with cells around
the outside walls, this prison was
known as the "Panopticon", or "in-
pection house" because of the ease
with which the whole institution could
be observed from a central position.
Early in the 19th Century a devoted
band of English men and women, the
"Prison Discipline Society", was reso¬
lutely carrying on the work launched
by John Howard, in jails which were
reported as "relapsing into their former
horrid state of privation, filthiness,
cruelty and neglect."
Among the worst of these jails was
Newgate Prison in London, described
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
The revolt from outside
as a "hell above ground". Here,
among the worst possible conditions, a
young woman named Elizabeth Fry
began a lifetime of work. on behalf of
the "victims" of prison systems.
By her amazing courage and per¬
sonality she completely transformed
conditions at Newgate and then went
on to become the chief promotor of
prison reform in Europe. Spurred on
by her example the reformers in
Britain campaigned successfully for
what are now regarded as the first
principles of a prison systemsepara¬
tion of the sexes, the classification of
criminals, female warders for women,
education and useful employment.
The Great Quaker Law
Elizabeth Fry's investigations of
other kinds of institutions -
brought about many improve¬
ments in the British hospital system
and in the treatment of the insane.
From 1838 to 1841 she travelled the
Continent, urging authorities to im¬
prove their prisons, and before her
death in 1845, she heard from most
parts of Europe that her ideas were
being adopted.
European successes in reforming
criminal laws and making greater use
of imprisonment as a punishment were
actually preceded by a great reform of
Quaker inspiration in one of the
American colonies.
In early colonial times the Quakers
were revolted by brutal corporal pun¬
ishments, especially the shedding of
blood, and in 1682 an important
Quaker reform, "The Great Law", was
submitted to the Pennsylvania Colo¬
nial Assembly by William Penn, the
founder of the colony. For the first
time in the history of criminal juris¬
prudence, it was here provided that
the majority of crimes should be
punished by "hard labour" in a house
of correction.
In 1718 the Pennsylvania authorities
were compelled to abandon this Quaker
criminal code and to adopt those
applied in the other colonies, but after
Pennsylvania gained its independence
in 1776, imprisonnment was again sub¬
stituted for corporal punishment by a
law of 1790 supported by the Philadel¬
phia Prison Society America's first
prison reform society.
The man who gave great impetus to
this movement was Dr. Benjamin Rush,
physician, social reformer and pioneer
penologist, and one of the mqst remark¬
able figures of his* time. "Dr. Rush,
one of the signers of the American
Declaration of Independence, was
16
known to later generations as "The
Father of American Psychiatry" for he
wrote the first general study on this
subject in America and raised the
study of mental diseases to a scientific
level for the first time in his country.
The famous reform group in Penn¬
sylvania, of which Rush was a
member, included Benjamin Franklin,
William Bradford and other pioneers
in American humanitarianism. It laid
the foundations for the famous Penn¬
sylvania prison system based on indi¬
vidual confinement in cells and "work.
The system came to life in a block
of cells built between 1790 and 1792 in
the yard of the Walnut Street Jail,
Philadelphia. This new type of prison,
"the first American penitentiary" as
it has been called, was an improvement
on others of that time, but the cells
were still rather grim places to judge
from a description , written in 1798:
"In every cell, there is one small
window, ' placed high up and out of
reach of the convict; the window well
secured by double iron grating, so that,
provided an effort to get to it was
successful, the person could perceive
neither heaven nor earth, on account
of the thickness of the wall. The
criminal/, while confined here, is per¬
mitted no convenience of bench, table,
or even bed, or anything else but what
is barely necessary to support life,
without risk of endangering health."
The confining of prisoners in indivi¬
dual cells became the guiding factor
in prison construction. Authorities
reasoned that solitude would lead to
reflection and penitence hence the
name "penitentiary" for the earliest
prisons. They also considered that
separate confinement would prevent
convicts from corrupting each other,
with each one adding his own special
knowledge of crime to the general
cesspool of vicîousness.
Soon the Pennsylvania system be¬
came world famous. A competing
type the Aubern system provided
for solitary confinement at night and
for association in prison shops during
the day. These two systems struggled
for supremacy during the 19th centu¬
ry, and while the Aubern system won
most favour in the United States, the
Pennsylvania system was widely
adopted in Europe.
New frontiers of thinking
Prisons today are naturally very
different places from those of
even half a century ago. Treat¬
ment is generally less severe, prisoners
are given more varied and useful work
to do and education, athletics and
entertainment all figure in the pro¬
gramme of a well-run modern prison.
But the "humanizing" of prison
conditions is only one aspect of a
broader and more significant change
in the whole conception of crime and
punishments which the findings of
criminology are slowly bringing about.
No one, say modern criminologists,
inherits "criminal tendencies", al¬
though people may inherit some quality
which makes it easy for them to
become criminals. Crime may show
(Continued on page 18)
PRISON LIFE is largely conditioned by the
surroundings in which the inmates serve their
sentences and the staff works. Gloomy and for¬
bidding buildings make it more difficult for prison
administrators to apply rehabilitation training and
less likely that prisoners will respond to it. Photo,
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N' 10 1954
NEW ARRIVALS
are interviewed,- clas¬
sified, given a uni¬
form and allotted a
cell. Others, sitting
in cubicles, wait their
turn to join Strange-
ways' population of
900 or so prisoners.
THE 'RUB DOWN'
as prisoners call this
search is a regular
feature of prison life
in Strangeways. All
working parties are
searched at the prison
centre for scissors,
knives, razorblades or
anything else that
might serve as a
weapon or could be
used as an escape tool.
TEDIOUS WORK
being done by these
prisoners consists of
untying knots
"Strangeways love
knots", as they call
themin Post Office
string. Prisoners also
shred mattress fibre
and stitch mail
bagstwo mail bags
every seven hours
and forty minutes is
,the standard quota.
taken at Strangeways Prison, Manchester, England,
shows one of the long cell galleries which radiate
spoke-like from the hub of the control centre.
Like many European prisons this one follows the
style of prison construction which was conceived
and first employed in Pennsylvania, U.S.A.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
The man inside the crimina
(Continued from page 16)
the inability of the individual to deal
with the world he lives in or the ina¬
bility of society to provide a decent
environment for all people. Crime is
often caused by poverty, over-crowded
living conditions, bad associations and
accidental factors such as unemploy7
ment. The criminal may not be to
blame for his crimes, therefore the
idea of "punishment" is not an impor¬
tant one in modern criminology. Thus
it disapproves of courts which seek to
avenge society against the criminal and
to "give him what he deserves."
Psychiatrists have joined criminolo¬
gists in throwing light on the subject
of crime and have provided useful
techniques in dealing with criminals
both in the courts and in prison. But
often criminal practice and psychiatric
theory are in complete conflict.
Guilt and punishment
Psychiatrists complain that crimi¬
nal law, as practised today, is
still guided by the idea of punish¬
ment and deterrence, that rehabilita¬
tion and reformation of the individual
offender is secondary. The psychia¬
trist sees the problem of crime as one
of treatment rather than of punish¬
ment. He approaches the offender as
a patient, not as a prisoner; he is
interested in the individual rather
than the crime.
Does this imply the complete abo¬
lition of all unpleasant ways of dealing
with offenders? No, say psychiatrists,
for even under the best of systems
disciplinary measures, such as confi¬
nement in institutions, would still be
necessary. But such measures would
be imposed primarily because they.,
were felt to be necessary for the~
offender's own welfare and for the
welfare of society, and not as punish¬
ment for an offence against the law.
Psychiatrists, psychologists, sociolo¬
gists, criminologists and jurists have
proposed a number of reforms to bring
criminal procedure in line with pres¬
ent-day sociological and psychiatric
knowledge.
They suggest, for instance, that a
psychiatric service should be available
to every criminal and juvenile court
and to every penal and- correctional
institution, and that a psychiatric
report should be made on every pri¬
soner before he is released.
They have also proposed that in cases
punishable by a prison sentence the
question of responsibility should not
be submitted to the jury. The jury's
role would simply be to determine that
the offence was committed by the de¬
fendant. The disposition and treat¬
ment (including punishment) would
be based on a study of the individual,
offender by properly qualified and
impartial experts co-operating with
the courts. This means a complete
separation of the "guilt-finding" and
the "sentence-imposing" phases in
court trials.
They feel that greater use should
also be made of a flexible indeterminate
sentence which allows for better indi¬
vidual treatment and release- from
prison when progress reports show
that the prisoner is not likely to relapse
into crime. v They also call for a wider
18
use among adults of the probation
system so often employed in Anglo-
Saxon countries for dealing with juve¬
nile delinquents. Probation is usually
applied in the case of a first offence or
where there are extenuating cir¬
cumstances. Punishment is suspended
and treatment and guidance are given.
Progress in improving prison régimes
and reforming criminal law during the
past seventy or eighty years owes a
great deal to the pioneer movement
which began in 1872 when the first
International Prison Congress met
in London. This Congress declared
"Moral regeneration - should be the
primary aim of prison discipline; hope
shbuld be more powerful than fear."
The International Prison Commis¬
sion established by the Congress, and
later called the International Penal and
Penitentiary Commission (IPPC), set
out to internationalize standards of
treatment for offenders and its efforts
led many nations to agree on basic
conditions of imprisonment and me¬
thods of crime prevention. In 1951,
the Commission became a Foundation
devoted to scientific research and
training in criminal science and policy.
Today the prevention of crime and
the treatment of offenders is regarded
more than ever as an international
problem and as an integral part of
social defence policies. The United
Nations has therefore taken over the
, work previously done by the IPPC and
through the Social Commission of its
Economic and - Social Council
(ECOSOC) and through the United
Nations Specialized Agencies, is co¬
operating with the non-governmental
organizations working in this field.
It has organized regional seminars
and ' meetings of experts lawyers,
sociologists, judges, police officials,
jurists, criminologists and many others
to study such subjects as probation,
the indeterminate sentence, standard
rules for the treatment of prisoners,
the training of prison staffs, trends of
crime, open institutions, and the pre¬
vention of juvenile delinquency.
The most recent of such meetingswas
held at Geneva in September 1954,
when European experts in criminal
. policy gave . practical guidance to
countries on probation, prison labour
and programmes for released prisoners.
Today's stumbling blocks
Real progress in dealing with crimi¬
nals and preventing crime is not
likely to come, however, until
the idea that crime cannot be pre¬
vented by repressive measures alone
becomes more widely accepted by the
public as a whole. Both national and
international action to deal with the '
problem of crime as an inherent part
of social defence programmes is still
handicapped by out-of-date ideas still
widely held. An ECOSOC report on
social defence programmes published
last year stressed the need for devel¬
oping a new attitude towards crime as
part of crime prevention policies.
"Existing systems of punishment still
have an emotional content... in which
segregation and counter agression play
a dominant role", it said. "As long as
this is -not overcome, no real progress
can be achieved."
WOMEN PRISONERS are given useful occupa¬
tions in Holloway Prison, London. Th'e largest
women's prison in England, it was built in 1852
as a "House of Correction". Ideas on prisons and
prison treatment having advanced since then, the
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N' 10. 1954
MORNING EXERCISE for the 500 inmates lasts half an hour. They
walk singly or in little groups, on a stone path round a grass lawn.
On one side they see the prison building, on the other, the prison walls
BATH-TIME for babies who are passing
the first months of their lives in prison.
Some were born there, others came in
when their mothers were sentenced. The
babies spend the daytime in the hospital
ward, and the night in their mothers' cells.
THE DOOR TO FREEDOM opens for a
woman prisoner. Modern efforts to im¬
prove prison conditions and rehabilitate
offenders are based on the knowledge that
practically all people who spend a term
in prison will one day return to society.
old building is far from adequate for present-day
standards. Prisoners make radio parts, stitch mail-
bags, mend shoes or work in the kitchen, laundry,
hospital or garden." In summer, parties are taken
out of the prison to work on farms near London.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
o* the
N
110 man ever asserts his
right to life except, perhaps, the man
who is threatened by death. And even .he does
so in secret, because he is ashamed and also because
he does not know to whom he could talk about it
aloud.
J. et the Universal Declaration of Human Rights main¬
tains, in Article 3, "Everyone has the right to life..."
The phrase is somewhat disturbing. There's nothing
obscure in it. But the reader can always add... "the
right to life, except when it is refused by justice."
kJociety tells the condemned
man: "Your crime deserves the death penalty. We are
suppressing your right to life." Society has good
reasons: it has every intention of defending itself
against the forces of evil that is, crime which might
endanger it.
So the right to life isn't absolute. In certain cases, it
is wiped off the list of rights. This isn't very simple,
mind you. For if I give my children the right to use my
library and I discover one day that they've torn my
books, I can revoke that right. He who gives can take
away. Is it society, therefore, which grants the right
to life? From whom did the condemned man receive
his life?
T
JL he condemned man is- nearly always a murderer.
His victim too, had the right to life. The condemned
man is an individual who, one day, from the depths of
his passion, his pride or his greed or from the depths
of his terror decreed the annihilation of another. He
made himself a tyrant. Either calmly or in maniacal
fury, he set up a reign of selfishness for his own
benefits.
At the time of his deed or, at least, at the mysterious
moment when he decided to commit it he plunged
into an abyss where no rights and no laws can exist.
He chose savagery of his own will. Can he then dare
to demand the privileges of a free man? Human
Rights didn't worry him very much when he killed.
They belonged to a kingdom from which he exiled
himself. Therefore, it would seem hopeless to try to
save him today by invoking the principles which he
sought to destroy yesterday.
.GW*
ouG
by
Georges Fradier
But, in reality, it is in the name of these very prin¬
ciples that he will be judged, for society considers the
old law of "an eye for an eye" as barbarous. Once he
has been imprisoned, the fiercest bandit alive is no
longer an outlaw. The verdict is pronounced on a
crime... but it is a man who must serve the sentence.
Is it completely certain that this man can be gagged
if he decides to talk about his right to life? Supposing
he discovers the .Universal Declaration of Human
Rights and then pleads guilty. He might say: "I have
violated the most important rights on this list and
there is nothing in it which absolves me of my respon¬
sibility. But it doesn't absolve you of yours. It does not
allow me to drag you down into my world of darkness
This list bears witness to a respected code of values
I have flouted it on one occasion and now you are
making me answer to it. You are on the side of justice
and I appeal to the justice of the Universal Declaration.
-I' read here : "Every man has the right to life." These
words are overwhelmingly against me. But now you
read them yourselves."
s,
'ociety protects itself...
Society condemns... It is too easy to hide behind society.
We are society... you, me and the rest of us. The cri¬
minal is precisely the man who tried tc leave society.
Now he has been brought back. It is I who am protect¬
ing myself, and it is I who condemn.
Happily, I can delegate my powers to a proxy. This
enables me to hold forth calmly over an after-dinner
cup of coffee on the pros and cons of the death penalty.
Of course, there are some very sound arguments on
both sides... the way things stand today and with the
evidence available, we shouldn't jump to conclusions...
our children will find the answer... the tide of human
progress, etc., etc... You and I, we're independent,
We're neither judges nor criminals.
Independent? And what about those judges who
believe that they condemn in our name? And they're
right: in law, they speak for us. In reality, too. The
condemned man stares out from his cell. He sees not
only the judge who sentenced him, but unconscious
judges as well ourselves. Can it be said that we, as
judges, are hypocrites?
c
ourts, gallows and flames from the stake. During
the Middle Ages, so we're told, judges condemned right
and left. In the 18th century, too, witches and thieves
were handed over to the hangman. Our fathers did
not ask themselves the same questions that we do
about the death penalty. It wasn't that they consid¬
ered human life cheap. But the problem of life and
of death was clearer to them than it is to us and, if
I dare put it this way, less serious. Society today
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 10. 1954
cannot tell itself that it kills the body of a criminal
to save his soul. No one talks about the defendant's
soul in the criminal courts. It's true that they don't
say much about his body, either. Instead, they analyse
his psychology... which is neither a concrete thing nor
an immortal one.
VJo the judges in the Middle
Ages never worried about excuses (Middle Ages a
handy expression to designate societies bound by belief
in the sacred, as opposed to our modern civilizations
which claim to be purely human). These judges
believed that .they had a duty to punish and scourge.
In the death penalty, the word "penalty" took on its
full meaning. It meant that the scales of Justice would
swing back into balance. The criminal atoned for his
deed that is, he purged himself of his sin by under¬
going punishment. At one stroke, he washed away the
stain which he had left on society, and the stain which
he had placed on his soul.
"5.
'end a criminal into the next world"... "He has paid
the supreme penalty for his crime"... There was a time
when there was nothing shameful in these phrases.
They had a meaning, and they gave a meaning to the
penalty.
J. et even today after an
execution some journalists still describe the criminal as
having "paid his debt to society." Do their readers
feel they have now been repaid?
I
n several countries, the courts cling to the terrifying
and imposing garb of sacred justice: black robes, red
robes, wigs, etc. And they keep their solemn and
barely intelligible language. The death sentence is
pronounced in the name of the people, or in the name
of the king or in the name of the constitution.
Who are these people who demand a corpse? Where
are they? In the eyes and in the mind of the con¬
demned man, what is this constitution suddenly turned
into an instrument of vengeance, and what is this law
which demands satisfaction?
JUxecutions, however, are no
longer a public spectacle. Proclaimed pompously, vir¬
tuously and publicly, the penalty must now be carried
out stealthily and quickly at dawn. There can be no
crowd to watch the execution. Even the jurymen are
not invited. When they answered the fateful questions,
they knew, of course, what their replies meant, but no
one asked them to imagine the result. And, at the
moment of this result, no one shall disturb their
slumbers. So all of these weeks of questioning and
testimony and eloquence and headlines, these weeks of
drama and stage direction finish in the furtive half-
hour of an official and shameful execution. During the
trial, with the help of modern means of publicity,
thousands of actors participated in the drama. At the
finale, there are only three or four. All that the others
will do is to read a brief paragraph absent-mindedly in
an afternoon newspaper.
B
efore a man can declare himself for or against the
death penalty, let him first climb the barrier of ab¬
stractions surrounding it and tear away the curtain of
verbiage. He is not reaching a decision which, once
taken, can be put out of mind; not discussing a theory,
but death itself the final physical act. Let him try
to understand the reasons (they must be terribly con¬
vincing) which oblige us to kill a man calmly and
deliberately.
L
Ls it impossible for the
honest citizen, the good husband, the kind father, the
pillar ci society, to put himself for a moment into the
shoes of the condemned man? Is it impossible for him
to visualize himself in a death cell and to tell himself:
"I am not a criminal. I was when I committed this
crime (this murder, or this rape, or this crime against
the State, or this theft, depending on where he lives
and the laws of his land) but since then, months (or
years) have passed and I have changed the way every¬
one changes. I am no longer the same man. Which
man are you condemning? Besides, you do not even
seek to know me for what I am..." Is it impossible for
this innocent man to understand why so many
condemned criminals protest their innocence? Yes,
there's no doubt it's impossible.
A
t least, every man should be able to imagine himself
in the jury box or on the judge's bench. But that only
means that he would be called upon to make his
decision on the basis of his knowledge... knowledge of
law, of philosophy, of anthropology, etc. The one thing
that he will not have time to examine is the right to
life, the right of "John Smith" to his life, a life as
humble, as dangerous, as sad, as miserable and as
mediocre as you care to imagine it, but the infinitely
precious life of the man who does not want to die. No
he will not be able to examine this life... there are too
many abstractions in the way.
-I ou're against the death
penalty? That's easily said, you know. Have you ever
seen the victim of a murderer? Are you capable of
imagining the horrors committed by certain killers?
We are always ready to speak without knowing, and
without engaging our responsibilities. How many
opponents of the death penalty changed their minds
the day they suddenly became "interested parties" and
had to offer a personal opinion.
A
re you for the death penalty? Are you ready to
replace the executionerreplace him officially with all
of the dignity of his profession? When a man has
good and honourable reasons to demand the life of
another man of whom he knows almost nothing, he
certainly should find the courage to go and take that
life himself. Why should such a just and salutary task
be left to obscure mercenaries?
L
Lf the right to Ufe is not
an absolute right, if it must be accompanied by
restrictions which vary according to time and place,
then what right can we count on? Is there any one
right which we can assert under any circumstances?
Not one, but all of these rights must be asserted so
that all of them may become absolute. For all of these
rights stem from a single postulate Article 1 of the
Universal Declaration of Human Rights: "All human
beings are born free and equal in dignity and in rights.
They are endowed with reason and conscience and
should act towards one another in a spirit of brother¬
hood".
Deny or neglect this postulate... and the rest is just
a joke.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
A BOY IN TROUBLE
by Dr. J. R. Rees
Director, World Federation for Mental Health
IN many countries of the world
there is at present a wave of
concern about juvenile delin¬
quency. It has been on the increase,
although now the peak seems to have
been passed. There is little doubt,
however, that more cases of anti-social
behaviour and crime are . brought to
public notice now than in past years.
The explanation of this in part is
that more cases are reported now and
that the police of all countries are
more inclined to take notice of viola¬
tions of the law both by children and
young people.
In addition to this there have been
marked disturbances created by two
world wars and there always is a
rise of delinquency rates following a
war. The dislocation of the social Ufe
of many countries during the recent
war has certainly contributed to the
increase of delinquency. Children
have not had the same settled, secure
home life. Mothers have had to go out
to work, fathers have in many cases
been away for long periods in the fight¬
ing services, and this has created a
situation which was likely to result in
anti-social reactions among children.
The moods of anxiety and moral dis¬
approbation of delinquency always
stimulate the consideration of special
factors which are regarded as being
"the cause" of delinquency. Lessening
of the religious sense, lack of moral
teaching, the more permissive techni¬
ques of child upbringing and education,
and the effects of films, television and
comic strips, have all been blamed.
They may of course play some part in
the encouragement of anti-social be¬
haviour, and all should be kept in
mind, because something could be
done about them. Scientifically speak¬
ing, there is no clear evidence to
justify the statement that these are
causative factors to any large extent.
'Hit them hard' school
SAMUEL Butler, when he wrote
Erewhon, displayed extraordinary
vision in his fantasy that the
development of physical sickness was
something which should be punished,
and that anti-social behaviour necessity
ated medical treatment. Few people"
took this very seriously, but there was
in between the two world wars a cer¬
tain swing towards this point of view,
and an excessive tendency to claim
that delinquents could not help being
as they were, and that treatment
should always take the place of punish¬
ment. This swing of the pendulum, as
Dr. J. R. Rees is Director of the World Federation for
Mental Health and was formerly physician and medical
director of the Tavistock Clinic for Child Guidance,
London. He is the author of many books and papers on
psychological medicine, including The Health of the
Mind and Modern Practice in Psychological Medicine.
in all such cases, was not wise, and the
present attitude of criminologists, psy¬
chiatrists and psychologists is more
realistic and better balanced with
regard to both the causation and the
treatment of delinquency."
As always, there are three attitudes
towards those who disobey the rules
of the community. First, we can
dismiss them as being degenerates,
people whose genetic inheritance has
decreed that they shall be criminals,
who must therefore be excluded as
rapidly as possible from society. Sec¬
ondly, there is the very vocal school,
which is not only composed of the
elderly and the pompous, which says :
"Hit them hard. Give them the most
rigorous punishment that can be
devised." The third~~ attitude, least
emotional and best balanced, sees that
there can be no effect without a
cause; there is no child who is just
naughty, no adolescent who is just
delinquent, or adult who is just a
criminal.
No spiritual aspirin tablet
IF we are to protect society and help
the individual, then we must of
necessity understand something of
the causes and background which have
given rise to the particular conduct of
which society properly disapproves.
Diagnosis should precede treatment.
The doctoï who merely treats symp¬
toms without attempting to "un¬
derstand the underlying cause of the
condition is a quack or a charlatan.
The parent, the teacher or the magis¬
trate who treats disorders of social
behaviour without concerning himself
about the reasons for that behaviour
can also quite properly be called a
charlatan. There is no spiritual or
legal aspirin tablet which will cure
every disorder.
Much careful research is being made
into the fundamental causes of anti¬
social behaviour, and the U.N. Economic
and Social Council, Unesco and the
World Health Organization are making
their contribution to this exceedingly
important problem. There can, of
course, be factors of bad inheritance
which we must consider, but the gene¬
ticists have not produced as yet any
very convincing evidence that the ten¬
dency to crime is inherited, though
clearly many defects and limitations of
personality may be passed on. There
is no real conflict between the impor¬
tance of heredity and environment.
We should think always of nature and
nurture, for both play their part.
The problem of deUnquency is part
of the much wider problem of mental
and emotional ill-health, and over the
past thirty or forty years we have
become increasingly aware of many
factors of importance. We know, for
example, that the general management
YOUNG OFFENDER. Parents wait anxiously
at door of Juvenile Court in Italy while young
offender hears verdict. Although many coun¬
tries still apply Stone Age methods to punish
juvenile delinquents, enormous progress has
been made since the enlightened English jurist
of the 18th century, Sir William Blackstone,
could write: "Under seven years of age.. .an
infant cannot be guilty of felony.. .but at eight
years old he may be guilty of felony." (Unesco
Photos by D. Seymour.)
of small children from infancy
upwards is very important, that good
standards and ideals for life and
conduct must be shown to them by the
adults with whom they are in contact,
rather than given to them as mere
dogmatic statements. Children are es¬
sentially imitative. The child whose
parents spend time in reading the
more lurid crime and sex stories in the
press is obviously more likely to be
attracted by the "horror" comics than
he would otherwise be.
We know that every child needs
some rules laid down for it, or it will
feel insecure, and we know, too, that
every child needs to have sensible and
wise discipline, which must be main¬
tained. . Spoiling and indulgence is
exceedingly unfair to the child . We
know that the threat of a penalty to
be incurred by some particular act can
be very harmful if in fact the penalty
is never imposed. In the past, chil¬
dren used to be told that the devil or
the policeman would get them if they
did what was wrong. Nowadays they
are told that they will suffer some
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 10. 1954
.what can we do to help him ?
deprivation, of pocket money, or
sweets, or something else that they
value, if they are not good. But if
nothing happens children often distrust
their parents and feel thrown back on
their own resources to get what they
want for themselves just when they
want it.
These points of view imply better
education for those who have or are
going to have children, and if we are
patient a lot can be done, and it can
be done in the home which is the
right place. Let it never be thought
that the so-called scientific approach
to delinquency implies that every child
who is naughty or anti-social must be
referred to a doctor or to a clinic.
There can be no easy evasion of the
responsibility of parents, teachers or
others.
We are probably getting nearer to
truly causative factors when we recog¬
nize that in disciplining or admini¬
stering the proper form of punish¬
ment, however slight it may be, to a
child, or indeed to an adult who has
offended against the rules of society,
we should always make it clear that
we strongly, disapprove of the anti¬
social conduct, but that we do not
disapprove of the individual who has
made these mistakes; that we respect
and love him or her just as much as
ever. Punishment becomes meaning¬
ful in this way, it does not create
rebellion nor a sense of exclusion and
insecurity, as often occurs in the indi¬
vidual who is made to feel that he is
bad and outcast.
For many years physicians and
others who have tried to deal with
individual cases of delinquency have
said that the commonest cause of
stealing is a sense of being unloved.
Because this sounds- rather an unusual
statement, we must look into it a little
more closely.
The child in a broken home, or who
is immured in an old-fashioned type
of orphanage, may suffer from a
genuine lack of interest and love. He
may lack a sense of nearness and the
feeling that he matters to someone
and is respected. Equally, the child
who has had too much demonstration
of love and affection, who has been
unwisely indulged and become spoilt,
may, if he becomes demanding and
tiresome, which is quite natural, be
dealt with by irritated adults in too
strict and arbitrary a fashion, and he
will then have a great sense of in¬
security and considerable resentment.
This is the type of child who very
often decides that since he is no longer
loved or liked, he must "go it alone",
he must get what he wants for himself,
and certainly can disregard the teach¬
ing and the standards of those who
have let him down.
This is logical, and is the explana¬
tion of a good deal of delinquency in
its beginnings. Many things in the
process of our police system, courts
and reformatory institutions tend to
add to exactly these difficulties, and
consequently they have led to recidi¬
vism and to the development of an
anti-social Ufe.
In the past few years some very
significant research has been done in
a number of countries throughout the
world, of which the most valuable
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
A BOY IN TROUBLE
(cont'd; Forced to ' go it alone '
examples have been collected together
in a book called Mental Health and
Maternal Care. (1) These collected
facts make it clear that in a large
number of cases the child who is in
the first three years of its life deprived
of that love and security that. every
child needs, which comes primarily
from its mother or mother substitute,
is likely to develop a deep sense of
insecurity, and indeed, to suffer a
distortion of personality which can
never be fully corrected in later life.
Children who are deprived, whether
by a true lack of love, by the broken
home, or by enforced absence from
their mothers, have a tendency to grow
up as embittered individualists, unable
to love or to accept love and friend¬
ship from other people. Their feeling
of insecurity provides a persistent
difficulty throughout their lives which
makes them more liable to irrational
anxiety, and they may have an in¬
creased liability to physical ill-health.
Many of these children as they grow
up, looking for something to enhance
their status, and for companionship/
(1) By Dr. John Bowlby. - Published by the
World Health Organization.
drift into gangs or undesirable groups
which lead them to develop their
delinquent traits, and a good deal of
the juvenile crime of today occurs in
young people of this kind. There is a
high incidence of this type of privation
of love and security in the histories
of juvenile delinquents.
Clearly harsh punitive treatment of
children like this will give them an
increased sense of their "badness" and
their abnormaüty and add to - the
inferiority feeUngs, the sense of isola¬
tion and the general grudge against
society and life they already have.
The medicine most needed in the
world to-day, whether for individual
children who are difficult, for adults,
in the family or industry, and for
nations, is love," and then more lóve.
By love, one means interest, respect
for people and their rights which
implies no lack of firmness and no
sentimentality. There is far more
sentimentality and emotionaUsm dis¬
played often by those who punish
delinquents in the Courts or elsewhere
than one can find in the average
children's psychological clinic.
What, therefore, do we need at this
present time to deal with our young
delinquents ? Certainly we need to
give help and better instruction to
those who are going to have children,
to those who have them, and to those
who teach them. We need much
better training in the science of peno¬
logy and the understanding of these
cases for those who are going to be
children's _ magistrates or judges of
adult courts. Far too often people are
put into these positions because they
are skilled in the arguments of defence
or prosecution, but without any true
appreciation of the personalities of the
people with whom they have to deal.
Similarly, better instruction is needed
for the probation services, where these
exist, and for the police. Better pro¬
vision is needed. in most countries for
the observation and investigation of
children before any court action is
taken. We need on the preventive
side to have far greater encouragement
of parent-teacher associations in con¬
nection with schools, of youth organi¬
sations of all kinds, which provide
outlets for healthy occupation and
interest. We need far more continuing
serious research into the nature and
the handling of our problems. Lastly,
and most important, we need more
real respect for children and their
rights and more love of a wise,
continuing kind.
PROBATION is now the preferred method of treatment of juvenile offen¬
ders in the U.S. and Canada, according to a recent U. N. Survey on Juvenile
Delinquency in North America. But despite the many "model" training
schools and detention homes, the U. N. report adds that in many respects
many "even today have not progressed far beyond their early limitations as a
kind of futile 'cold storage' for troublesome youngsters." (USIS.)
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 10. 1954
I here is nothing out-
I side the gate of
I Brécourt to indicate
that it is a "public
institution of su¬
pervised education"
or, to really call a
spade a spade, a
reform school for girls.
There -is only a stone post and
weathered letters . which simply
announce "Chateau de Brécourt".
Twenty-five miles northwest of Paris,
Brécourt lies in the pastoral setting of
a valley on the edge of the Beauce,
Prance's great bread-basket plain. It
might be a rich man's country estate
(it was until the previous owner was
found to be a spy during World
War II) but for one peculiarity: you
can walk into Brécourt and out of it
good deal easier than into
anyone's country estate.
There is nothing inside its gate,
either, to tell you that Brécourt is a
reform school. Brécourt is the living
proof of an experiment that began in
1944 to try a new tack on the old
problem of what to do with juvenile
delinquents.
With the blessings of the French
Ministry of Justice, two women,
Dominique Riehl and Genevieve Bou-
tault, took over a reform school at
Cadillac, near Bordeaux, a 16th cen¬
tury chateau wherei young inmates
had been locked into individual "cells
at night. At Cadillac, they opened
the doors and, despite a grim setting
and wartime austerity, their methods
worked. In 1947, they moved to
Brécourt with Miss Riehl as director
of the "public institution", and Miss
Boutault' as her assistant director.
Where the
gate is
always open
A SPECIAL REPORT
Prepared under the direction
of GUY SINOIR, French
Ministry- of Justice
TEXT BY DANIEL BEHRMAN
PHOTOS DENISE COLOMB
Copyright 'Unesco Courier'
Today, there are Cu girls from 14
to 21 years f age at Brécourt (when
a new bm ling is completed in
November t ?re will be 40 more).
Their story is the same drab tale of
juvenile delinquency the world over
with nothing to appeal to lovers of
detective novels.
Nearly always, it is a story of
delinquent parents (statistics show
that divorce, separation and shattered
homes cause 95 per cent of the 18,000
cases of juvenile delinquency report¬
ed annually in France). The girl
who is picked up for petty theft,
vagrancy or prostitution and sent to
Brécourt by a children's court judge
is not a hardened enemy of society.
She merely chose an easy way out of
a hard lot.
"Girls get into trouble mucli less
often than boys, but when they do,
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
FUTURE DRESSMAKERS ply their needles
in a sunny room of what was once a rich man's
country home near Pans. Brecourt's delinquent
THE WORLD WATCHES Brécourt and the school is seldom without visiting students and observers
from abroad. Here, a young Brazilian psychologist studying its methods samples the cooking.
THAT PARISIAN LOOK in hand-embroidered
blouses takes years of patient practice. Gifted
the cause is much more deeply-rooted
and harder to get at", Miss Boutault
told me inside the ivy-covered man¬
sion that now serves as Brecourt's
main building. She was a sturdy,
handsome woman with iron-grey
streaks in her hair and a frank note
in her voice. I was willing to believe
she had done nothing during her life
except run a country home for five
dozen youngsters until 1 learned that
she also had a doctorate in law.
"The emotional problem is much
more important for girls", she
explained. "Teaching them a trade
and keeping them busy are not
enough you have to prepare them
for marriage which, after all, is the
best solution."
This means creating a normal
environment, which is exactly what
Brécourt sets out to do, concentrating
on two main goals a thorough train
ing in useful trades, and the creation
of a healthy family atmosphere.
There is no marching and there are
no uniforms. There are no rows of
iron beds in a chill barracks and
there is no cheerless mess hall.
The pupils of Brécourt Miss Bou¬
tault will only refer to them, as pupils
live in groups of eight. Each group
has its own apartment, its own dining
room, and its own "educator", the
title of the devoted woman who is
assigned to each group. She lives
with her group, she eats with it and
she shares its problems. The girls
do not call her "mother", but she is
the nearest thing to a mother that an
institution could provide. And the
group, all too often, is the nearest
thing to a normal family that these
girls have ever known.
Miss Boutault took me through the
home of the La Grappe group (grappe
means a bunch of grapes in French).
A raffia painting made by one of the
girls lent a spot of colour to the walls
of the dining room. In the bathroom,
there were four wg,sh basins one to
two girls compartinented off for pri¬
vacy. The bedroom sparkled with
gay cretonne bedspreads. One girl
had placed a souvenir Eiffel Tower at
the head of her bed; another a plush
donkey. Dolls were common. Though
all in their teens, the girls, of Brécourt
cling to a childhood of which they
have had only a fleeting glimpse.
"They're a lively bunch, La
Grappe", Miss Boutault commented.
"You see, each 'educator' seems to
stamp her. personality into her
group... the Gerbes are probably a
little quieter and less impulsive. We
try to fit each girl into the group best
suited to her character.
During this visit, the apartments
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
girls live to learn their trades so much so the
some refuse to leave before completing the
courses they are given.
girls in Brecourt's embroidery classes are taught
to work from their own designs.
THE LAUNDRY ROOM is not a chore but another class where girls are taught the tricks of hand-
ironing. Naturally, they learn by doing their own washing.
were empty but Miss Boutault still
took care to keep me and my note¬
book out of sight. "These are girls,
not guinea pigs," she had said and
politely, but firmly, refused to allow
any staged photographs during my
visit.
The apartments were empty be¬
cause the girls were in their classes.
To most of the outside world, Brécourt
is known simply as the Public In¬
stitution of Professional Training
and, unless Miss Boutault told you
otherwise, you _ could not tell the
difference between Brécourt and a
modern 'trade schcol with boarding
facilities for its students.
Every girl at Brécourt learns a
trade, depending upon her aptitudes.
She can be taught stenography, or
dress-making, or hair-dressing or
even farming but, when she leaves,
she takes the same examination in
Pans or in nearby Pontoise as the
pupils in any trade school. Her "cer¬
tificate of professional aptitude," too,
is the same as that given to any
other successful candidate. It bears
no mention of her stay in an "insti¬
tution", nor does she have a black
mark in a police record ...or, in fact,
any police record at all.
Recently, Miss Riehl and Miss Bou¬
tault made a study of what had
happened to 100 girls who had gra¬
duated from Brécourt ("graduated" is
the right word often a girl asks to
stay to complete her training). It
showed that 70 were doing well
married or holding jobs. Twenty
had dropped out of sight (once a girl
is over 21, she no longer needs to
report to probation officers) and 10
per cent were not leading what Miss
Boutault termed "a regular life".
(Continued on page 29)
170 ACRES OF LAND make Brécourt almost
self-sufficient. Some girls are trained as future
farm workers, but all receive an introduction
to country life in the school's gardens and in
its model barns.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Re-education: plenty of faith and
UNIFORMS ARE TABOO
for the school's sixty pupils
who work and live in the
sort of setting which might
well be the envy of any
girl's trade school anywhere.
THE LOST CHILDHOOD of a Brécourt girl (authorities estimate that 95 per cent of
juvenile delinquency is "rooted in shattered homes) is reflected in the dolls to which she clings
even in her 'teens. Brécourt girls live in small "family" groups. A group bedroom isshown here.
28
A CAREER WITH A CURLING IRON is very much in
demand at Brécourt whose beauty salon is always full. Even
the school's directors have their hair done there.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
few illusions
(Continued from page 27)
Not one, however, had turned to
crime. "Ten per 'cent of failures...
that's quite a good margin of error
in any school", she commented.
One reason for these results prob¬
ably lies in the "open-door" policy
applied to Brecourt's 170 acres of
parks, woods and farmlands (occa¬
sionally, a game poacher' from a
nearby village is flushed). Girls are
often sent unaccompanied on errands
or else visit parents in Paris on Sun¬
days, taking the bus by themselves.
There are about half a dozen "es¬
capes" a year, but they are not plann¬
ed "jail-breaks". A girl might walk
out of the gate on an- impulse but
she nearly always comes back of her
own free will.
None of this should give the im-'
pression that teen-agers are pampered
at Brécourt. Suzanne or Thérèse in
La Grappe or Le Nid begins her day
at 6.45. From 8 a.m. to noon, she is
in her trade class and she goes back
there from 2.30 to 5.15. She has
leisure, but it is organized. Idleness,
the plague of prison 'systems, has
been scoured out of a day at Brécourt.
Sweet-tooth and nest-egg
There is nothing to stop Suzanne
from indulging her sweet-tooth,
either. While the girls are train¬
ed for their future professions, they
earn money, part of which is put
aside to constitute a nest-egg when
they leave Brécourt and part of which
they receive as a weekly allowance.
Here, too, another effort has .been
made to prevent the school from
taking on the heartless character of
an "institution". After all, the old
reform-school with its cells' and its
uniforms could serve only as a pre¬
paratory school for prison later on.
The purpose of Brécourt, on the other
Unesco Courier. N' 10. 1954
hand, is to prepare its girls for life.
The girls are sturdy and well fed.
They prepare their own meals with a
diet based upon Brecourt's farm
production (the day I was there,
pupils were eating veal chops, the
last of a series of veal menus which
followed the killing of a calf). Phy¬
sical culture is an important part of
their programme all the more so
because it demands a mental as well
as a physical effort. As we watched
a group playing volleyball, I noticed
that one girl was wearing a skirt
instead of shorts.
"It's taken us a year and a half to
get her interested in sports",- com¬
mented Miss Boutault. "Now that
we've come this far, the shorts can
wait a little longer."
Teachers want to learn
PEiuiAPs the most amazing feature
of the way Brécourt is run is the
absence of any dogmatic system.
Miss Riehl, Miss Boutault and their
staff of six "educators" and six trade
instructors are always willing to
learn. "In re-education, you never can'
say that you know the answers...
because that means you are suffering
from an intellectual hardening of the
arteries", said the assislant director.
/ In one respect, Brécourt runs con¬
trary to methods used in cerlain other
countries where psychiatric treatment
is stressed. Of course, Brécourt
makes use of educational psychology,
but its directors and French rehabi¬
litation authorities in general feel
that the methods of the psycho¬
analyst, are more valuable in treating
children at home than girls living the
life' of a boarding school type of
institution.
"There's no formula in this work,"
commented Miss Boutault. "In re¬
education, you must have a large
quantity of faith... and a small
quantity of illusions."
THE MENTAL SIDE of sports is just as important as the exercise in Brecourt's programme. French educators
believe it serves an invaluable role by demanding an effort of willpower from girls who had once chosen an easy
way out of difficulties. But to get the girls interested in sport often calls for plenty of patience.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
:>.
, Vf
y.?V; i '^^Si
* - *
: v 'Vi'
i*
a tragedy
that might
have been
prevented
by Sir Cyril Burt
IN dealing with physical disorders it has become increas¬
ingly recognized that prevention, wherever possible, is
far better than cure. The same holds true of delin¬
quency and crime. To illustrate how urgently such mea¬
sures are needed, let me start with a single, case typical
of a vast number in which cure proved impossible, but pre¬
vention would probably have achieved success.
Frances, when I first saw her, was a' tall and attractive
girl of fifteen and a half, who might almost have sat as a
model for Greuze. With her long fair hair, flushed cheeks, .
and well-developed bust, she looked much older than her
age. She was born in a London slum a couple of years
before the outbreak of the war; and, when her father was
called up and her mother found work in a munitions factory,
Fanny (as her family called her) was evacuated with her
older brother and sister to a farm in Somerset.' Here she
ran wild, and by the age oí seven had become the terror
of the village children.
Returning to London at the end of the war, she proved
to be exceedingly backward in her lessons; but, apart from
a tendency to giggle, chatter, and occasionally weep, she
gave no serious trouble in the classroom. At the age of
eleven she was reported to the police for stealing money
from a confectioner's till, and referred by the magistrate
to a child guidance clinic. From the case-file it appears
that she had been regularly pilfering at home for three or
four years. The father was described as a rough and
drunker! dock labourer, constantly quarrelling with his wife,
whom he eventually deserted. The mother was an excitable
woman, who had freely consorted with other men while her
husband was overseas and was constantly in debt. 'Non-co¬
operative', was the social visitor's final remark.
After the change from country to town, Frances' own
'One of the world's foremost authorities on problems of juvenile delinquency. Sir
Cyril Burt, Is tmentus Professor of Psychology at the University of London and was
formerly Psychologist to the London County Council. He was the first psychologist to
be officially appointed by any education authority m the world. His many books
include The Young Delinquent (considered a classic in the field), The Backward Child
and The Subnormal Mind.
30
í>5rV - * S
it* -afS
V. -f.- * Jif'
fit
.v
y¿í'-.
. > -
v.
1 t-v
. V -
Arnim 1
MW
".4#P.; .
B$#i -*?:
k.-'t- '(-? -¿V-'-i
M&£'
health had steadily declined; and, with a few imaginary
touches of her own, she succeeded in presenting a pathetic
picture of weak and pretty innocence, neglected by her
parents and misled by bad companions. At first the attitude
of those who saw her was pity rather than reproof or punish¬
ment. Later more drastic measures were tried docking her
pocket money, corporal chatisement at home and at school,
daily sessions with a psychoanalyst, and ultimately removal
to a convalescent home, from which she absconded.
After leaving school, she was dismissed from one job after
another. At her last, she took a bundle of five-pound notes
from the _ cashier's desk, and vanished from sight. The
police found her three weeks later, living in a Liverpool
lodging-house with a Portuguese sailor; and "'Francesca", as
she now called herself, was brought back to London. She
was discovered to be suffering from venereal disease, and
was put on probation. When I saw her, I felt at once that
she was already a hopeless case. In spite of every effort
to reclaim her, she drifted about from place to place, de¬
teriorating physically and mentally. And a few months ago
she died of tuberculosis at the age of eighteen.
Frances' history, like that of most others who swell the
records of recidivists, shows clearly the converging influence -
of two main factors a difficult temperament and an
unfortunate environment. By "temperament" I mean the
child's inborn mental constitution. What is inborn can
obviously never be removed. < . One of the girl's school¬
mistresses had indeed declared that in her view the child
was morally defective and should be certified as such. But
to make use of wholesale measures of this kind would clearly
be impracticable.
Nevertheless, both teachers and doctors still frequently
cling to the old-fashioned notion that an habitual offender
must have been endowed at birth with an inherent criminal
nature, and that nothing can reform him. Today no psy¬
chologist subscribes to Lombroso's celebrated theory of il reo
nato, the criminal who is born and not made. Nor does
any moralist nowadays believe in the ancient philosophical
doctrine of an inheritable moral sense, common to all law-
abiding individuals, but lacking to a greater or lesser degree
in certain exceptional cases. Moral behaviour is the result,
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier Nr 10. 1954
'-.'li "A *
. Y
IL >:«V\*
iJt
-./
Üi
ít-Jf» *3 ri
ääBv -fîT y 1
.- ? i" *.t « ": *
not of a single or simple innate faculty,
Dut comes from individual experience "
anü social training.
At the same time we are forced to
recognize that there are certain tem¬
peramental conditions which make it
far easier to- succumb to temptation.
Most juvenile delinquents like Frances,
exhibit from the earliest years a
marked emotional instability which
often runs through all the family.
Like the rest of us, they inherit certain
specific emotional impulses anger,
fear, sex, and so on; but, unlike the
calmer law-abiding citizen, they in¬
herit them with an excessive strength.
Sooner or later this highly-strung,
ill-balanced disposition is apt to give
way under continued strain, and the
child breaks down with neurotic
disorder or delinquent reactions fre¬
quently both.
Now, what is inborn is only a ten¬
dency; and it is by no means inevitable
that the tendency should be fulfilled.
Because a child inherits a liability to -
tuberculosis, we cannot assume that he
is fated to die of that disease. If the
potential neurotic or the potential
delinquent is detected at an early age,
and suitably protected and cared for,
the potentiality itself need never come
ro maturity.
Emotional characteristics are not the
only qualities that are partly de¬
termined at birth: our intellectual
abilities, both general and special, are
also conditioned by our inborn limit¬
ations. Differences in general intelli¬
gence can be readily measured by
standardized tests; and, since it is
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
(com'â)
An aceumulation
of many straws
essential to consider how far a child's behaviour is likely to
be guided by intelligent 'or rational motives, his capacities
should, be assessed at the earliest possible age.
Frances was tested at the age of eleven and found to
possess the mental age of an average child of nine. In
addition, owing to truancy and inattention, she was more
than four years behindhand in her reading and arithmetic.
Her bright manner thus concealed an innate incompetence;
and in after-life one of the chief reasons why she lost her
jobs was that she was really too stupid to perform her
work effectively.
Disrupted homes teach bad habits
Her lack of intelligence, however, was not so severe that
she could be formally certified as mentally deficient.
Yet, had she been tested as soon as she returned to
London, and transferred to a school or class for the educa¬
tionally subnormal, her whole history might have taken a
different turn. Unfortunately at that date no facilities existed
in her district. Among my own delinquent cases nearly 70 per
cent have been 'seriously retarded in their intellectual devel¬
opment; and it is from the ranks of these dull and backward
pupils that the majority of our future delinquents and
recidivists are eventually drawn^
Although we cannot alter a child's heredity, we can do
much to improve his environment. During early childhood
the conditions which chiefly affect his moral and emotional
development are those obtaining within his own home.
Thirty years ago poverty with its inevitable concomitants
hunger, overcrowding, and lack of space and facilities for
play generally figured as the most conspicuous charac¬
teristics of households in which juvenile crime was bred.
Today, as every social worker would agree, it is not so
much the material conditions as the moral and emotional
atmosphere that play the decisive part.
It is comparatively rare for a child who has been brought
up from infancy in the midst of a stable, intelligent, and
law-abiding family to embark on a criminal career. But
when, like Frances, the youngster is deprived of a mother's
tender care almost from birth, and when the home itself is
disrupted by divorce, separation, or mutual conflict, the
child has little or no chance to form steady habits of his
own or to acquire a respectful affection for those who
should control and watch over him.
But of all the causal factors that are observable in the
young delinquent's home, by far the commonest is inefficient
discipline. Discipline may be too lax, too severe, or (worst
of all) of the forcible-feeble type where the child is at one
moment scolded and slapped and at another coaxed and
cajoled.
Delay will be disastrous
Much could be done by educating parents particularly
the mothers of the next generation in the principles
of child management. Sometimes this will be out of
the question, and the child must be removed. But in every
case our motto should be, in the words of The Children's
Charter : "For every child a home, and that love and security
that a home should afford, and for those who need foster-
care the nearest substitute for a home of his own".
It is far easier to change the conditions in the school, or
to shift the child from a school where he has become
maladjusted to one more closely suited to his needs.
Moreover, the school offers the readiest link between the
supervising authority and the child's immediate relatives
and friends. With the English public school as our
traditional model, we have gradually come to recognize that
education must embrace the training of character as well
as the instruction of the intellect.
Transferred to a small class where every child can be
studied and taught along individual lines, with a flexible
32
THE PARENT AND CHILD. At a School for Parents opened in San
Francisco, California, to combat juvenile delinquency, parents whose chil¬
dren have committed serious crimes (above) hear court judge lecture
as part of mandatory weekly night course. Below, I S years old delinquent
submits to lie detector test. (USIS)
curriculum adapted to the needs of each, the dullard can
be supplied with wholesome interests and taught simple yet
useful forms of skill, his ill balanced temperament can be
adjusted and stabilized, and the restless and high-spirited
adventurer can be furnished with outlets for his natural
Impulses through the medium of games, sport, hobbies,
idancing, music, and the more elementary arts and crafts.
To fit the daily work to the capacities of each individual,
±he pupils must be systematically tested and observed; and
their school record cards should include, not only comments
on educational progress, but temperamental assessments,
notes on behaviour out of school as well as in, and full
details regarding the home background.
At the very first sign of irresponsible conduct, appropriate
steps must be taken before the actions become ingrained as
habits. When ordinary measures are likely to be of no
avail, the child should be promptly referred to the child
guidance clinic. Delay will be disastrous. In almost every
.instance, as the story of Frances herself so clearly shows,
there is seldom a single cause of crime : a multiplicity of
converging factors is nearly always at work.
It is not the last straw, but the accumulation of straws,
that breaks the camel's back; and every adverse or demo¬
ralizing influence must be detected and if possible removed.
Physical health may need attention; bad companions
separated; parents aided with prompt advice as each .little
emergency arises. Above all, the child himself must be
tactfully handled and helped.
In most cases, what will be required is not so much
treatment as moral training an education or
re-education of the child's own misguided impulses, with a
' view to building up better habits of self-restraint and
providing him with loftier ideals suited to his individual
abilities and needs.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N' 10 1954
From the Unesco Newsroom...
.tm IDING ASIA'S EDUCA¬
TORS : An International In¬
stitute of Child Study has been
set up in Bangkok by the Gov¬
ernment of Thailand and
Unesco. It will carry out basic
research in child development
and will equip Asian educators
with the background they need
to make use of successful educa¬
tional ideas and methods from
other parts of the world in ex¬
tending and improving their
own school systems. The first
six staff members six Thai
educators recently completed a
year of special studies in psy¬
chology at Toronto University,
Canada, under Professor W.
Line, Unesco consultant to the
Bangkok Institute.
HUMAN RIGHTS' FILM-
STRIPS : Wales is produc¬
ing a series of filmstrips for
schools to explain the Uni¬
versal Declaration of Human
Rights. Prepared by the
Welsh Unesco Committee the
eight filmstrips deal with
early Welsh history, the
right to education and free¬
dom of worship, political
rights, humanitarianism,
science and human welfare
and Welsh contributions to
human rights and inter¬
national understanding.
Commentaries for use by
teachers and adult education
groups accompany each
filmstrip.
^ HILDREN'S COMMUN¬
ITY CLUBS : A far-reaching
cultural programme has just
been drawn up by El Salvador's
Literacy and Adult Education
Department. The plan involves
setting up a network of rec¬
reational clubs across the coun¬
try. The clubs will function
with the help of local parents'
associations and will be super¬
vised by trained educators. In
these clubs, children will play
and work together, and also
will learn about the important
social problems of their com¬
munity.
EUROPEAN UNIVER¬
SITY PACT : A new inter¬
national convention now
enables students holding a
diploma giving access to a
university of a member
country of the Council of
Europe to enter universities
in "other member countries.
The convention came into
force after the first three
countries England, Ireland
and Denmark had ratified
it.
1^ HAIN REACTION'
TEACHING : Students from
eighteen Latin American coun¬
tries, who have graduated from
Unesco's Regional Fundamental
Education Training Centre at
Patzcuaro, Mexico, are now do¬
ing valuable work in their own
countries on educational pro¬
jects often the training of new
teachers. Graduates who re¬
turned to Honduras, Cuba and
Venezuela are working in na¬
tional centres along similar lines
to the one at Patzcuaro. In
Costa Rica, five graduates have
formed a team that travels
throughout the country giving
courses for rural teachers. Eight
graduates are working for gov¬
ernment educational and agri¬
cultural projects in Brazil. Sev¬
eral of the Mexican graduates
are working with newly-created
rural welfare brigades. And
graduates from Peru, Guate¬
mala, Honduras and other
w ORLD S LARGEST
TAPESTRY : The largest ta¬
pestry ever woven (43 1/2 by
28 1/2 feet) has been presented
by Belgium to the United Na¬
tions. The tapestry's themes are
'Peace, Prosperity and Equali¬
ty", and views of the chief cities
of UJtf. Member States line the
borders. The work of art was
designed by an Antwerp artist,
Peter Coifs, after a nation-wide
competition. Fourteen artist
craftmen put together 94,000
miles of yarn (equal to four
times the distance round the
equator) to create this huge
work, under the direction of
Gaspard de Wit of the Royal
Belgian Art Factory. Working
on a special loom they added an
average of two and a quarter
miles of yarn to the tapestry
every hour. The U.N. Tapestry
is to hang on the wall of the
U.N. General Assembly Building.
UNESCO GENERAL CONFERENCE
OPENS IN MONTEVIDEO, URUGUAY
Delegates from Unesco's 72 Member States were on hand on
November 12 when the Eighth Session of the Unesco Gener¬
al Conference opened in Montevideo, Uruguay. The confer¬
ence will last four weeks until December 11. Delegates will
shape Unesco's future programme and policies. And they will
vote on a budget for financing Unesco's activities. The propos¬
ed figure is twenty-two million dollars for the two-year period
of 1955-1956, but the final figure must be decided by the dele¬
gates. This is the first time since Unesco was founded in 1946
that so many nations have been represented at a General Confer-'
ence. Unesco recently has been strengthened by the adhesion
of four new member states: the Soviet Union, Ukraine, Byelo¬
russia and Chile. In addition, Poland, Hungary and Czechoslo¬
vakia all have recently resumed active membership and Ruma¬
nia and Bulgaria have applied to join.
Among its work, the conference in Montevideo will be consi¬
dering proposals that Unesco extend greater aid for research
and experimentation in the peaceful utilization of atomic energy,
research in desert and humid tropical zones, oceanography and
marine biology. Proposals also call for the creation of a South
Asian centre to study various social problems arising out of
recent industrialization. The establishment of an educational
film production institute in Latin America and an educational
film library for the Middle East is also to be examined.
countries are also at work in
their home countries.
PARENTS' UNIVER¬
SITY : Members of parents'
school committees and work¬
ers in trade union children's
committees are able to follow
six month's study courses in
educational questions at a
"parents university" in Len¬
ingrad. Since the "univer¬
sity" was opened, some 700
parents have completed the
course and have since taken
an active part in public and
social work.
M. LASTIC ARTISTS : The
International Association of
Plastic Arts has just held its
first General Assembly. The
meeting' took place in Venice
from September 28 to October 4
and scores of artists from all
continents participated. The
Association was founded two
years ago by an international
conference of artists convened
by Unesco. Its purpose is to
assure cultural co-operation be¬
tween countries and defend the
interests of painters, sculptors,
and engravers of all nations.
* MEDICINE'S MAGIC
EYE : Research with new
nuclear aids shows that 98%
of the basic material in the
human body is replaced year¬
ly, according to Dr. Paul
Aebersold, Director of the
Isotopes Division of the
United States Atomic Energy
Commission. Studies with
radioactive isotopes disprove
the old theory that the body
takes in food, air and water
mainly as a fuel to provide
energy. Findings on the
body's rate of turnover were
revealed by scientifically re¬
cording the course of radio¬
active elements in the human
body. {See the special issue
of The Courier, "The World
Within the Atom", December
1953 for an article on radio¬
active isotopes.)
M. HE XMAS SPIRIT : For
the sixth consecutive year, the
United Nations Children's Fund
(UNICEF) is again selling a se¬
ries of gay and colourful Christ¬
mas cards for the benefit of the
world's needy children. The
cards carry as their theme "Joy
for the World's Children", and
show boys and girls at play in
Indonesia, Korea, Iran, Austria
and Mexico. Last year, UNICEF
sold nearly two million cards
and netted one hundred thou¬
sand dollars, enough to provide
powdered milk for seventeen
thousand children once a day
for a whole year.
THE PEACEFUL USE
OF ATOMS : The first in¬
ternational - scientific re¬
search laboratory in the
world came into being on
September 29 when France
and the Federal Republic of
Germany simultaneously rati¬
fied the Convention setting
up an European Organiza¬
tion for Njiclear Rtfecrrrh.
The Convention, drawn ip
under Unesco auspices, had
already been ratified by
seven countries. The Euro¬
pean Organization will con¬
struct an international labo¬
ratory for nuclear research
in Genera and will develop'
co-operation between exist¬
ing laboratories in theoreti¬
cal studies. The research
will be of a non-military na¬
ture, and its results iclii be
published or made generally .
available. Director of the
Organization jciU be Stciss
scientist Felix Bloch-, No¬
bel Prize Winner, tcJso has
directed fhe Institute of
Physics 0/ Stanford Univer¬
sity (tJSA} for weny years.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom... (Continued)
ILJ NESCO PACTS SIGNED:
Denmark has become the for¬
tieth nation to sign an inter¬
national convention sponsored
by Unesco to protect cultural
property in time of war. The
convention now awaits ratific¬
ation by the countries who
signed it. The same number of
countries have now signed an¬
other Unesco-sponsored agree¬
ment Universal Copyright
Conventionand in October,
Spain became the third country
to ratify that agreement. The
Universal Copyright Convention
goes into effect as soon as
twelve nations officially ratify
it.
REFUGEE TRAINEES :
Over a hundred young Arab
refugees have been taken
out of the routine of camp
life and are being trained at
a modern vocational training
centre just outside ancient
Jerusalem. The centre was
established by 'the United
Nations Relief and Works
Agency for Palestine Refu¬
gees, with help from the In¬
ternational Labour Organiza¬
tion and Unesco. The Relief
and Works Agency is caring
for almost a half-million
Palestine refugees in Jordan
alone. It is trying to open
new horizons for these men
and women who to-day have
no way of earning their own
livelihood. The young men
at the vocational training
centre are learning to be¬
come radio mechanics, elec¬
tricians, machinists, plumb
ers, carpenters and weld¬
ers. When they graduate,
they will be helping to over¬
come Jordan's serious short¬
age for skilled workers. The
centre hopes to train at least
six hundred young Arab ref¬
ugees during the next three
years.
w OMEN'S RIGHTS:
Hungary recently became the
fifteenth country to sign the
United Nations Convention on
the Political Rights of Women
since it went into force on July
7, 1954. The Pact grants .wo¬
men the right to vote, to be
elected to public office and to
exercise all public functions on
equal terms with men. It was on
July 7, sixty-one years- ago that
a national ballot "was cast by a
woman for the first time, in
New Zealand.
SCHOOLS ADOPT
FARMS -.Geography and na¬
ture study lessons have taken
on a new meaning m secon¬
dary schools at Birmingham,
England, since the children
began to "adopt" farms in
nearby counties. The time
spent at work on the farms
by the "farm study groups",
the follow-up work m the
classroom and the exchange
of letters between children
and farm families provide a
practical lesson in "citizen¬
ship" the training for com¬
munity living in its widest
sense.
UNITED NATIONS DAY AROUND THE WORLD
On October 24 United Nations
Day the UN flag waved over
national capitals, towns and
even villages all over the world
as men, women and children of
all races celebrated the United
Nations' ninth birthday. In Li¬
beria, post offices put on sale
a new series of Liberian stamps "
honouring the United Nations.
Churches throughout the coun¬
try held services calling for
world peace. Public demonstra¬
tions included a parade of the
flags of UN member states
through the main streets of the
capital. Australia and the Phi¬
lippines decided to make their
celebrations a United Nations
Week. Burma arranged film
shows, public lectures and photo
exhibits, and India sponsored a
wide variety of events, radio
broadcasts, a new postage stamp,
exhibitions, leaflets and cele¬
brations in the schools.
In Pakistan, schools and uni¬
versities arranged special pro¬
grammes, and there were exhi¬
bitions, pageants and flag-rais¬
ing ceremonies. Children in
Thailand, Colombia and the
Scandinavian countries cele¬
brated wilth folk-dancing and
singjng. In the Soviet Union.
UN leaflets and posters were
widely distributed and publica¬
tions of the UN and the Special¬
ized Agencies exhibited.
UN Day. in Medellin, Colom¬
bia, was marked by the opening
of the country's first modern
public library, a ceremony at
which Dr. Luther Evans, Direc¬
tor-General of Unesco officiat¬
ed. The new library is a Unesco
pilot project designed to encour¬
age public library development
in Latin America. It will be
the first in the country to lend
books for home reading. Apart
from its imtial collection of ten
thousand books which soon will
grow to fifty thousand the
new library also has a sizeable
record collection and many pic¬
tures and filmstrips. It will
operate in close conjunction
with local adult education
work.
In Great Britain, the UN Day
activities included displays in
shop windows, a great children's
gala and special radio and tele¬
vision features. A large UN
poster was displayed on ten
thousand outdoor advertising
sites. Mexico held a national
essay and poster contest, and
the prizes will be distributed on
December 10, Human Rights
Day. In the United States
which celebrated UN Day in a
wide variety of ways, a special
committee chose as the theme
for this year's ceremonies: "The
UN depends on you."
The UN flag flew over towns
in all parts of France, and in
Marseilles, a giant illuminated
banner shone out over (he Old
Port, proclaiming "Journée des
Nations Unies." In Paris and
other cities, schoolchildren saw
special film programmes or
visited UN exhibitions. UN
programmes were presented on
radio and television.
These were just a few of the
many UN Day celebrations.
Every land honoured the birth¬
day according to its own nation¬
al characteristics, its history
and its culture. But everywhere
prevailed the same hope that
the United Nations will help win
the battle for a lasting peace.
LETTERS TO
THE EDITOR
EDITORS NOTE. In previous issues, the Unesco
Courrier has devoted considerable space, in this column,
to letters from readers on various aspects of auxiliary
international languages, such as Esperanto, Ido, Interlin-
gua, Volapuk, etc. Letters from readers in every continent
and in almost every country in the world continue to
arrive at our editorial offices in Paris in increasing
numbers. The Editors wish to take this occasion to
express their thanks to all our correspondents for their
interesting remarks and comments, but regret that the
huge volume of letters makes it impossible to reply per¬
sonally to each correspondent. However, all letters have
been carefully studied by the responsible officials at
Unesco prior to the opening of the General Conference
of Unesco in Montevideo, Uruguay. At this conference the
question of Esperanto and international auxiliary langua¬
ges are being examined.
Sir,
As I read the article on "The Flag with the Blue and
White Shield" (issue n° 7 Saving Our Heritage in
Stone) and saw the photos of Samothrace Packed Away,
it all brought back to me one of the most moving stories I
ever heard.
Shortly after the 1945 Armistice I was in the Louvre
staring up at the Winged Victory. I was thrilled to
find this old friend right back where she belonged, at
the top of her majestic stairway, ready to welcome the
world chez elle. . .
I turned to a guard standing nearby and smiled
gratefully. He, in turn, nodded understandingly, walked
slowly up to me and, with deep emotion, confided in me.
"Oh. monsieur ! what would you have felt if you had
been in my place at the outbreak of war, the day they
took 'her' off for safe-keeping ? For days they hammered
away. Boards, machinery, pulleys, and such noise! Ima¬
gine, we got so used to this fuss and bother that we
didn't pay any more attention to it. Not like the 'first
few days when they took out' la Vénus and then la Jo-
conde. Well, before we knew what was happening, it
was all over. She was being carefully lowered down the
stairway, dispossessed, taken away from us. Now what
would become of her? Who would defend her? Where
would they hide her ? And for how long ?... Quite
suddenly, yes instinctively, the workers and we guards
all stopped in our tracks and stared with disbelief at
this new disappearance. We took off our hats and bent
our heads in mourning, the better to hide our tears... Be¬
lieve me, monsieur, we felt that the flag of France was
being withdrawn..."
Laurelton, N. Y., U.S.A. Maurice Kurtz
Sir,
I congratulate you on the American Negro issue of the
Unesco Courier (N° 6 of 1954). It is the sort of thing that
gives one some hope for the future of the world.
You must realize that the question of elimination of
race-prejudice and race-discrimination is one of the
fundamental questions on the basis of which we are
going to judge the sincerity and honesty of the whites.
What is happening in South Africa, Kenya and other
African regions in the possession of whites is so
exasperating and discouraging to the non-whites in this
world that the present issue of The Courier is a ray of
hope...
Fergusson College, Dr. D.D. Karve
Poona, India.
Sir, '
This summer I came across two copies of The Unesco
Courier. What, I think, really distinguishes it from
other reviews and magazines is the spirit which inspires
it. It does not limit its coverage to "superficial" or just
picturesque facts about peoples from many lands, but
presents precise and vivid information on what is being
done to give help, culturally and economically, to people
who need it. Reading this publication I could sense a
great current of effective brotherhood flowing from a
great many hearts filled with goodwill
...In the issue of the Courier I have in front of me
there appeared "A Letter to Jennifer", in which an
American father tells his daughter about Unesco.. I must
admit, though I blush to do so, that this was the first
time that I understood and really "felt" what Unesco is,
and how much we need it to protect the human values
which we still yes, still prize today.
Basel, Switzerland. J.B.
Editor's Note. The aboce letter Was originally published
in the letter column of the co-opcialive weekly "Co-operation",
in Basel, Switzerland.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
A MAGNIFICENT CHRISTMAS GIFI
NEXT MONTH
An exceptional
Xmas number with
6 pages of colour
plates on RARE
MASTERPIECES
OF WORLD ART
THE UNESCO COURIER
Single issue: 1 / -
or 5 0 F r . Francs
Yearly subscription :
6¡- or 300 French Francs
TO SUBSCRIBE
In the United Kinjjdom send your
remittance to U.M. Stationery Offi¬
ce P.O. Box 569, London S.E. 1.
In other countries write to National
Distributors listed below.
IÍ your country is not listed write
directly to Unesco Sales Division
19, avenue Kléber, Paris, France.
Unesco's National Distributors from whom
the English edition of THE COURIER can be
obtained are listed below. Other Unesco
Distributors are listed in the French and
Spanish editions of THE COURIER
Australia : Oxford University Press, 346,
Little Collins Street, Melbourne.
Austria : Wilhelm Frick Verlag, 27, Gra¬
ben, Vienna I.
Burma : Burma Educational Bookshop.
551-3 Merchant Street, P.O. Box 222,
Rangoon.
Canada : University of Toronto Press,
Toronto.
Ceylon : Lake House Bookshop, The Asso¬
ciated Newspapers of Ceylon, Ltd., P.O.
Box 24-4, Colombo I. Rs. 5.
Cyprus : M. E. Constantinides, P.O.B. 473,
Nicosia.
Denmark : Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd., 6 Nor-
regade, Copenhagen, K.
Egypt : La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9, Adly
Pasha Street, Cairo.
NATIONAL DISTRIBUTORS
Ethiopia : International Press Agency,
P O B. 120, Addis-Ababa.
Finland : Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, 2 Kes-
kuskatu, Helsinki.
Formosa : The World Book Company Ltd ,
99, Chung King South Rd, Section I,
Taipeh.
France : Sales Division, Unesco, I 9, Avenue
Kléber, Pans- 1 6e.
Germany : Unesco Vertrieb fur Deutsch¬
land, R. Oldenbourg, München.
Greece : Elefthéroudakis, Librairie Inter¬
nationale, Athens.
Hong Kong : Swindon Book Co., 25 Nathan
Road, Kowloon.
India : Orient Longmans Ltd., Bombay, Cal¬
cutta, Madras : sub-depots : Oxford Book
. & Stationery Co., Scindia House, New
Delhi; Rajkamal Publications Ltd., Hima¬
laya House, Bombay 7. Rs. 4.
Indonesia : G.C.T. van Dorp & Do. NV.,
Djalan Nusantara, 22, Djakarta.
Iraq : McKenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
Israel : Blumstem's Bookstores Ltd., 35,
Allenby Road, P.O. Box 5 154 Tel-Aviv.
Jamaica : Sangster's Book Room, 99, Har¬
bour Street, Kingston; Knox Educational
Services, Spaldings.
Japan : Maruzen Co, Inc., 6 Ton-Nichome,
Nihonbashi, Tokyo.
Jordan : J.I. Bahous and Co , Dar-ul-Kutub,
Salt Road, Amman.
Liberia : Jacob Momolu Kamara, Gurley
and Front Streets, Monrovia
Malayan Federation and Singapore :
Peter Chong and Co., P.O. Box 135,
Singapore.
Malta : Sapienza's Library, 26, Kingsway,
Valletta.
Netherlands : N. V. Martinus Nrjhoff,
Lange Voorhout 9, The Hague.
New Zealand: Unesco Publications Centre
7 De Lacy Street, Dunedm, N. E. 2.
Nigeria : C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box 174,
Lagos.
Norway : A/S Bokhjornet, Stortingsplass, 7,
Oslo.
Pakistan : Ferozsons Ltd., Karachi, Lahore,
Peshawar. Rs. 3.
Philippines : Philippine Education Co.,
Inc., 1 1 04 Castillejos, Quiapo, Manila. 3.00
Surinam : Radhakishun and Company Ltd.,
(Book Dept.), Watermolenstraat 3 6, Para¬
maribo".
Sweden : A B CE. Fritzes Kungl. Hov-
bokf-ande', Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 16.
Thailand : Suksapan Pan it, Ar kam 9,
Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok. 20 ticals.
Union of South Africa : Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Ltd., P.O. Box 724, Pretoria.
United Kingdom : H M. Stationery Office,
PO. Box 569, London S.E.I.
U.S.A. : Unesco Publications Service, 475
5th Ave , New York 17, NY.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
i
. ñ» P
»'I ' ' *" * *'** *« ci
: - :-V *'y
"«^¿4»%*%-*'" Sr*4"?. *£
j4 * a
.y^
*CJ.^rt*ff «
rç.
B* e §&
. -"fc*
:"^*****3r*Ä /
kP«f* *
;
w«;
,t-:^:¥-
** "¿3**lí
~TS^I«?
^¿«vsplr-
C^»«|;
i Suma -. <--*v. íi*W' ^Kß"^
..-
't
"*\^^r
Far from the city streets
DELINQUENT GIRLS GET
THEIR FIRST CHANCE
(See story page 25)
]]>
</page>
</document>
