<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="070196eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Page 2. MARCH I 953
EDITORIAL OFFICES :
UNESCO, 19, Ave. Kteber, PARIS-16
*
Editor-In-Chief : S. M. KOFFLER
(English edition : R. S. FENTONEDITORS French edition : A. LEVENTIS
'Spanish edition : J. DE BENITO
*
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco r
the editors of the COURfER.
*
Imp. GEORGES LANG, II, ru e Curial, Paris
MC. 53 I 69 A.
SUBSCRIPTIONS
Yearly subscription : $2 ; 10s 6d ; SOD French
francs. Sales agents are listed below.
Where none is listed, write to Unesco, Paris.
Argentina : Editorial Sudamericana, S. A., Alsina
500, Buenos Aires.
Associated States of Cambodia, Laos and
'Viet-Nam : K. Chantarith. C. C. R., 38, rue Van
Vollenhoven, Phnom-Penh.
Australia : Oxford University Press, 346, Little
Collins Street, Melbourne.
Austria : Wilhelm Frick Verlag, 27 Graben,
Vienna 1.
Barbados : S. P. C. K. Bookshop (Regional Office
Caribbean Area), Broad Street, Bridgetown.
Belgium : Librairie Encyciopedique, 7, rue du
Luxembourg, Brussels IV.
Bolivia : Libreria Selecciones, Av. 16 de Julio
216, Casilla 972, La Paz.
Brazil : Livraria Agir Editora, Rua Mexico 98-B,
Caixa postal 3291, Rio de Janeiro.
Canada : English speaking : University of Toronto
Press, Toronto. French speaking : Centre de
publications internationales, 4234, rue de la
Roche, Montréal 34.
Ceylon : Lake House Bookshop, The Associated
Newspapers of Ceylon, Ltd., Colombo I.
Chile : Libreria Lope de Vega, Moneda 924,
Santiago de Chile.
Colombia : Emilio Royo Martin, Carrera 9a, 1791,
Bogota.
Costa Rica : Trejos Hermanos, Apartado 1313
San Jos.
Cuba : Unesco, Centro Regional en el Hemisferio
Occidental, Calle 5, No 306, Vedado, Havana
Czechoslovakia : Orbis, Narodni 37, Prague I
Cyprus : Tachydromos, P. O. B. 473, Nicosia.
Denmark : Einar Munksgaard Ltd., 6 Norregade,
Copenhagen, K.
Ecuador : Casa de la Cultura Ecuatoriana, av.
6 de diciembre, Casilla 67, Quito.
Egypt : La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9, Adly Pasha
st., Cairo.
Finland : Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, 2 Keskus-
katu, Helsinki.
Formosa : The World Book Company Ltd., 99,
Chung King South Rd., Section 1, Taipeh.
France : Sales Division, Unesco, 19, Avenue
Kléber, Paris 16".
Germany : Unesco Vertrieb fur Deutschland,
R. Oldenbourg Munchen.
Greece : Elefthéroudakls, Librairie Internationale,
Athens.
Haiti : Librairie"A la Caravelle", 36, rue Roux,
Port-au-Prince.
Hungary : Kuitura. P. O. B. 149, Budapest 62.
India, Orient Longmans Ltd, Bombay, Calcutta,
Madras : uh-depocs : Oxford Book & Stationery
Co., Scindia House, New Delhi. Ralkamal
Publications Ltd, Himalaya House, Bombay 7.
Indonesia : G. C. T. van DOlp & Co. NV., Djalan
Nusantara, 22, Djakarta.
Iraq : McKenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
Israel : Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd., 35, Allenby
Road, Tel Aviv.
Ualy : G. C. Sansoni, via Gino Caponi 26, casella
postale 552, Florence.
Japan : Maruzen Co, Inc., 6 Tori-Nichome,
Nihonbashi, Tokyo.
Jordan : J. 1. Bahous and Co., Dar-ul-Kutub, Salt
Road, Amman.
Lebanon : Librairie Universelle, Avenue des
Francis, Beirut.
Luxembourg : Librairie Paul Bruck, 50, Grand-
Rue.
Malayan Federation and Singapore : Peter
Chong and Co., P. O. Box 135, Singapore.
Malta : Sapienza's Library, 26, Kingsway, Vaietta.
Mexico : Libreria Universitaria, Justo Sierra 16,
Mexico D. F.
Netherlands : N. V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange
Voorhout 9, The Hague.
New Zealand : South's Book Depot, 8 Willis
Street, Wellington.
Nigeria : C. M. S. Bookshop, P. O. Box 174, Lagos.
Norway : A/S Bokhjornet, Stortingsplass 7,
Os ! o.
Pakistan : Ferozsons Ltd., Karachi, Lahore,
Peshawar.
Panama : Agencia International de Publica-
ciones, Apartado 2052, Panama.
Peru : Libreria Internacional del Peru, S. A.,
Giron de la Union, Lima.
Philippines : Philippine Education Co., Inc.,
1104 Castiiiejos, Quiapo, Manila.
Portugal : Publicacôes Europa-America, Ltda,
4 Rua da Barroca, Lisbon.
Puerto Rico : Pan American Book Co., San
Juan, 12.
Spain : Aguilar S. A. de Ediciones, Juan Bravo 38,
Madrid.
Surinam : Radhakishun & Co., Ltd., Watermo-
lenstraat, 36, Paramaribo.
Sweden : AB. C. E. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel,
Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 16.
Switzerland : French-Speaking ; Librairie de
i'Universite, 22-24, rue de Romont, Fribourg.
Germain-Speaking ; Europa Verlag, 5 Rami-
strasse, Zurich.
Syria : Librairie Universelle, Damascus.
Tangier : Centre International, 54, rue du Statut.
Thailand : Suksapan Panit, Arkarn 9, Raj-
Damnern Avenue, Bangkok.
Tunisia : Agence Agh'ebik, 20, Grand-Rue,
Kairouan.
Turkey : Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal caddesi,
Beyoglu, Istanbul.
Union of Burma : Burma Educational Bookshop,
551-3 Merchant Street, P. O. Box 222, Rangoon.
Union of South Africa : Van Schaik's Book-
store, Ltd., P. O. Box 724, Pretoria.
United Kingdom : H. M. Stationery Office, P. O.
Box 569, London, S. E. t.
U. S. A. : Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad-
way, New York.
Uruguay : Centro de Cooperacion Cientifica
para la America Latina, Unesco, Bulevar Artigas
1320, Montevideo.
Yugoslavia : Jugoslovenska Knjiga, Marsala
Tita 23/11 Belgrade.
Excerpt. when otherwise started, articles
appearing in this issue may be reproduced
without prior permission, provided acknow-
ledgement is given to the Unesco COURTIER.
K. BERTAZZINI
A scene in the TV studio of Radio Italiana in Turin. Small images seen on screens are picked up from studio cameras.
Image on far left is reproduced on centre screen, showing that this is being seen by public at the moment.
WHAT HAS TV TO SAY TO US ?
TELEVISION for the public is only
17 years old. In 1950 television
activities, other than of an expe-
rimental nature, had achieved impor-
tance for the general public only in
France, Great Britain, in the United
States and in the U. S. S. R. Today, hardly
three years later, it is a practical re-
ality in 24 countries.
No new medium of communication
has ever been greeted with such enthu-
siasm by SO many. Yet in one respect
the reception of television appears to be
different from that of previous media.
Experience with radio over 25 years
appears to have combined with aware-
ness of the fantastic potentialities of
television to provoke, from the outset,
some questions and even some alarm.
What, people ask, will this new instru-
ment do to us ? Are those who control
and direct it conscious of their respon-
sibilities ?
It is, perhaps, significant that it is
by educators that the voice of warning
and even of alarm has been chiefly rais-
ed."I don't want kids watching
things,"says one educator."I want
them doing things. They should be
solving problems, modelling in clay, mak-
ing things at a work bench, experi-
menting in chemistry, throwing a ball,
playing a trombone, skinning a squir-
rel. They should be learning skills,
skills, skills. Watching is one of the
best ways of learning, but not if you
just stay and watch. You should see the
pattern and then go out and do it."
These words, spoken at a national
education convention in the United Sta-
tes provoked quick and angry response
from the chief announcer of a television
station."Having spent some time in
the TV field, and also having in my
home a four-year-old daughter who is
vitally interested in television, I would
like to enlighten you about the so-call-
ed watching and not doing habits form-
ed by the children I have come in
contact with. They form the habit of
being moral citizens, believing that truth
and right will triumph over evil, false-
hood and wrong. They learn to grow
straight in body and mind, they learn
in many instances the meaning of the
golden rule ! I believe that people like
yourself who berate television, all the
time saying that it is not bad, then
attempting to prove that it is, are doing
a great deal of bad for the country, and
especially for the children. If enough
of the so-called intellectuals of the nation
pan, attack and criticize TV or attempt
to dabble in fields not their own, I be-
lieve that it will do immeasurable harm
to the television industry as a whole and
thereby rob the public and the chil-
dren of one form of educational enter-
tainment."
But the fears and anxieties of educa-
by Prof. Charles SlfPMANN
tors persist despite such angry denuncia-
tion. The former Chancellor of the
University of Chicago thus reads the
future."Under the impact of television
I can contemplate a time in America
when people can neither read nor write
and will be no better than the forms of
plant life."
Another educator thinks that televi-
sion may prove as"dangerous to culture
as the atom bomb is to civilization."
On the other hand, a senator of the U. S.
sees in television the possibilities of a
"great public forum and a real means
of furthering government of and by the
people."
Some parents share the anxieties of
some educators."It's not healthy,"one
says,"the way Johnny plays. All day
it's machine guns, murder, and gangs.
You can't tell me kids don't get those
UNESCO seeks to aid its member statesin developing television in the inte-
rests of education, science and
culture through the encouragement of
research, through clearing house services
gathering and furnishing information.
Last month, Unesco issued its first volume
on the subject, entitled :"Television and
Education in the United States."The
author is Professor Charles Siepmann, of
New-York University, who has devoted
much time to the effects of T. V. and its
use as a medium of education. The
new Unesco publication (priced at $ 1. 00 ;
6/- ; 300 frs) will be of special interest
to teachers, everyone concerned with the
use of audio-visual means for education,
individuals and institutions engaged in
adult education or school broadcasts, and
broadcasters engaged in or planning tele-
vision production. The material in this
issue ot the Courier is taken in major
part from Professor Siepmann's book,
supplemented by additional information
from Unesco's television service which is
shortly to publish a special report entitled.. Television, a Worfd Survey". The artie/e
on this page is reproduced from the intro-
duction 0/Professor Siepmann's book.
ideas from radio, TV and the movies."
For other parents television is a god-
send."TV keeps the children from
getting under foot.""TV keeps Billy
off the streets. It's a built-in baby sit-
ter."And so it goes. Opinion, con-
flicting and sometimes self-contradictory,
but opinion. Much of it, everywhere.
The concern, if not the alarm, of pa-
rents is justified by a fact of which few
of them, probably, are aware. For tele-
vision marks the high point of a curve
in the development of mass communic-
ation, which has proved as steady as it
it remarkable. Each new medium in-
vented has tended to embrace a younger
group of devotees. Newspapers, olde5t
of our four modern giants of mass com-
munication, are read mainly by adults.
Then came the cinema. The cinema, in
the United States at least, is predomi-
nantly an adolescent pastime. Radio,
next, absorbed the pre-adolescent child.
With the advent of television, mass
communication appears destined to ab-
sorb us from the cradle to the grave-
television is viewed with rapt attention
by infants.
Last century John Ruskin was asked
by a group of journalists to comment on
what at the time was a triumph of tech-
nology-the completion of a cable line
from England to India. Ruskin offered
no comment, but posed them the ques-
tion :"What have you to say to India ?"
What, we may likewise ask. will tele-
vision have to say to us ? Those in
charge of television in the U. S. in Bri-
tain and elsewhere, are conscious of the
portentous undertaking on which they
are embarked. Educators in the U. S.,
who were laggard and half-hearted in
availing themselves of radio's resour-
ces, have been quick to grasp the cultu-
ral significance of this newcomer on the
mass communication scene.
In the sense that all experience is edu-
cational all television programmes are
educational. But the educational inten-
tion of television varies, and will vary,
from country to country and in accord-
ance with the nature and purposes of
the organizations and institutions operat-
ing television stations and producing
television programmes.
Programmes range from education in
a very broad sense and with a heavy
sugar coating to'formal instruction un-
der classroom conditions.
There can be no question that, in the
matter of educational telecasting, there
are'those who ! have rushed in where an-
gels fear to tread. Television is not an
unmixed blessing. It is a two-edged
sword. Every technological advance
does not automatically spell progress.
Without the exercise of great intelli-
gence and true conscience, it may, in-
deed, prove a curse. Faith and enthu-
siasm have been the keynote of deve-
lopments in educational television thus
far. The condition of further effective
advances in this field is caution-great
deliberation, more careful and extensive
testing and, above all, concern with
standards.
Television is developing fast every-
where. Its expansion thus far is as no-
thing to its likely development over the
next 10 years. This images it the more
important to take stock of the present
situation and of the short past which is
already rich in evidence, in examples of
intelligent experiment, and in clues to
the future development of this latest of
the media of mass communication.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
'COURSER MARCH 1953. Page 3
THE WORLD TELEVISION PICTURE
A LL over the world people are talkingtelevision. Almost every day one reads of
new transmitters b=ing installed in one
country, new stations going up in another,
plans being completed in a third. In Morocco,
engineers are at present staking out the site for
a new TV centre at Casablanca. In Japan, daily
television broadcasts were inaugurated only a few
weeks ago. The Government of Thailand has
purchased television equipment from abroad, and
technicians from countries as far apart as the
Philippines and Haiti, Australia and Guatemala,
Indonesia and Finland are visiting TV centres in
Europe and the United States to learn more about
this powerful new medium of communication.
Reports received by Unesco show that in
January 1953, fifty-five countries were developing
television activities : thirteen had introduced
regular services, while 11 were conducting
experimental broadcasts. At least 30 additional
countries and territories are preparing to establish
TV stations or are seriously studying the idea.
It is in the United States that television has had
the greatest development. There are now 128 TV
stations on the air and over 20, 000, 000 sets in use ;
2, 053 new stations are envisaged including up
to 242'non-commercial educational stations.
In Great Britain, the war put a temporary halt
to the pioneer work undertaken by British
engineers, but today five powerful stations cover
80 per cent of the country and over 1, 700, 000 sets
are in use.
In France, television resumed slowly after the
war. Lack of capital resources and other
economic hardships, uncertainty about broadcast
standards and line definition retarded the
construction of stations and the production and
sale of receivers. In recent years, however,
France has advanced rapidly in the TV field.
More than 60, 000 receivers are now in use and
sets are being sold faster than the industry can
produce them (about 6, 000 sets a month).
Public television broadcasts in the U. S. S. R.
were first begun in 1938. Here too, the war halted
its development, but transmissions were resumed
immediately after the war on 7 May, 1945. Today,
powerful stations in Moscow, Leningrad and Kiev
are broadcasting regular programmes which reach
over 60, 000 sets. Other stations are. planned by
the government and a highly developed movement
of amateur TV broadcasters.
Perhaps the most surprising and rapid growth
of television is taking place in Latin America.
Cuba, for example, which did not begin tele-
casting until October 1950, is today : one of the.
few countries in the world where programmes can
be seen in every part of the land. Six stations are
now on the air andi at least three more
are scheduled to begin transmission this year.
Broadcasts reach an estimated 100, 000 sets and
several. hundred thousand viewers. Most of the
programme. s are highly commercialized, but the
need for educational and cultural programmes
has been recognized. Last July, a conference of
broadcasters, advertisers and educators at the
University of Havana, unanimously urged that
certain educational broadcasts should be tried out.
The Cuban Ministry of Education is now working
with one station in the production of a Sunday
night, top-listening-time show entitled"One Hour
of Art and Culture". Dramatic productions,
children's films, news reports and current events
discussions are also telecast by other stations"to
contribute to the enlightenment of the public".
Similar programmes are offered in Mexico, where
four stations are now on the air and 50, 000 sets
in use. Over 20 new stations are planned.
In recent years, Brazilian technicians have not
only been working to expand TV reception in the
cities but also considering its enormous possib-
ilities for the nation's vast rural areas. By
January 1953, three stations were broadcasting
daily programmes to 35, 000 homes and 287 new
transmitters in 180 communities were foreseen in
a government plan just published. Of special
importance is the municipal station which the
government is now completing at Rio de Janeiro
to be used exclusively for educational program-
mes. In Sao Paulo, educational programmes
during the past two years have included a regular
half-hour weekly show devoted to Unesco in
which articles and photographs from the COU-
RIER have been extensively used. The first TV
station in Latin America to be used exclusively
for educational purposes was inaugurated at Ca-
racas, Venezuela, at the close of 1952.
Something like a television"fever"is sweeping
across most of the other Latin American
countries. New projects are reported almost
every week."Televisiån en Guatemala... !"
triumphantly proclaims the journal"Antena
Popular"in its issue of June 1952. Even the tiny
Dominican Republic has been transmitting since
August 1952. Argentina began in October 1951 ;
a station its about to open in Puerto Rico ; and
plans are being made for broadcasting in Bolivia,
Chile, EI Salvador, Peru and Uruguay.
In Europe, many countries are still officially in
the"experimental"stage of TV Although
several now have daily or weekly programmes, the
final form of their TV organization has, in many
cases, not yet been settled. In the Netherlands,
two programmes a week reach about 5, 000 sets.
In Italy, two well-equipped stations at Milan and
Turin beam programme. s to a similar number of
receivers. Educational aspects of TV are now
by Dr. Henry R. Cassirer
being studied, although drama and light opera
are already regularly broadcast. Among other
European countries now experimenting with
television or planning its introduction, are Spain,
Hungary, Switzerland, Poland, Denmark, Bulgaria,
Rumania, Yugoslavia, Monaco and Sweden.
Germany became the third country on the
European continent to begin regular broadcasts
in December 1952 (the first two : France in 1937,
the U. S. S. R. in 1938). Five stations now operate
in the German Federal Republic, including one
in Berlin. With the separate transmitter oper-
ated by the German Democratic Republic, Berlin
is so far the only city in Europe where more than
one programme is available to the viewing public.
The arrival of TV in Western Germany was
greeted with considerable reserve and even scep-
ticism by those who feared its effects on children
and the cultural life of the nation. Producers
have sought to overcome such attitudes by trying
to offer high quality programmes and stressing
adult education, on-the-spot coverage of current
events, and good dramatic productions.
Public bodies are taking great interest in the
development of television in Germany. The
Catholic and Protestant churches have formed
TV committees and hope to co-operate in
producing certain programmes. The'.'People's
High Schools" (adult education schools) are
studying the use of this new medium for their
purposes ; and German schoolteachers have
formed an organization in preparation for the
introduction of TV in classrooms.
Outside Europe and the American continent
(Canada has 160, 000 receivers and 2 stations),
public television services exist only in Japan.
But plans are being studied for its development
in the Middle and Far East, in Africa, Australia
and New Zealand. Among countries discussing
the possible introduction of television are India,
Morocco, Algeria, Tunisia and Turkey. At Istan-
bul, the Technical University now has a small
experimental broadcasting unit. Thailand, as
has been mentioned earlier, has purchased equip-
ment for educational broadcasting.
In Japan, television research goes back as far
as 1930, and experimental programmes were
begun in 1940, suspended during the war and
resumed in November 1950. On 1 February, 1953,
the Japan Broadcasting Corporation began a
regular, four-hours-per-day TV service over
stations at Tokyo, Nagoya and Osaka, and will
emphasize educational, cultural and news pro-
grammes with occasional entertainment. Two
commercial companies have received preparatory
licenses for TV and expect to start a competing
network of sponsored programmes later this year.
At the moment, there are about 3, 000 receivers in
Japan, and although the cost of sets is much
beyond the purchasing power of the average Jap-
anese, the television authorities believe that this
cost will soon be reduced, and that the number
of sets will rise to about 10, 000 within a year.
While television is rapidly developing as a
world-wide movement, countries are far from
agreed as to how it should be run. For one thing,
there are great differences in the technical
standards which are being adopted in different
parts of the world. The number of lines which
make up the televised image vary considerably
from one country to another. In Great Britain,
the picture has 405 lines ; in the U. S. and most of
the American continent as well as Japan, 525
lines are used. Most European countries use 625
lines ; France and those countries dependent upon
France have adopted a definition of 819 lines.
There are also basic differences between Western
European standards and those adopted in the
Soviet Union and other countries of Eastern Eur-
ope. It is as if many countries were building
railroad systems but adopting different gauges.
The system under which TV operates as well
as programme services vary greatly from country
to country. Generally speaking, the character of
television corresponds to the traditions and
cultural patterns of the land in which it is being
developed. In the U. S. and most Latin American
countries, the basic system is commercial. The
drawbacks of this system as far as educational
programmes are concerned, have been recognized
by the U. S. Government, and it Ls now planned to
set up non-commercial educational stations. In
Europe, television is generally operated by gov-
ernments or public corporations, but the intro-
duction of commercial stations, or commercial
sponsorship of public-owned stations, has also
been considered.
Certain countries whose past practice and
present inclination run counter to commercial
television may therefore be forced to have
recourse to it. On the other hand, countries
which began television purely on a commercial
basis are now finding it necessary to add non-
commercial educational stations.
Whatever road is taken, however, and despite
its high cost, television will continue to spread
around the globe. As its potentialities are further
explored and discussed, it is to be hoped that
television will grow not only as a new force for
entertainment, but as a powerful new instrument
of education and enlightenment.
Photo M. Zalewski
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Page 4. MARCH 1953 UNESCO CO
THE BRITISH APPROACH TO EDUC
T ELEnsIO has been called a windowopening on a world far beyond that of the
ordinary man's limited experience. In
November 1936, Great Britain became the first
country in the world to open this"window"to
the general public with the inauguration by the
BBC of regular television transmissions. It
was, in fact, Great Britain that led all other
countries in both the quality and extent of its
programmes until the suspension of all tele-
vision operations at the outbreak of World
War II in 1939. At that time, however, the
range of television transmissions was limited
to the London area and receivers numbered
only 20, 000 to 30, 000.
With the resumption of programmes after
the war and their extension to other parts of
the country, public interest developed rapidly.
Today the number of receivers is estimated at
well over 1, 700, 000 and most of the heavily
populated areas of the country are within the
service area of the BBC's five transmitters.
Television in Britain, like radio, is operated
by a non-profit, public service corporation, the
British Broadcasting Corporation. The BBC is
a monopoly but, contrary to widespread belief,
it is not Government controlled.
When one of the 1, 700. 000 or more owners of
television sets in Great Britain switches on his
receiver and relaxes in a comfortable chair in
his living room, he can be pretty sure that he
will see a wide variety of information and
entertainment programmes but there are, as
yet, no regular transmissions of formal educa-
tion programmes. The main categories of
the regular five hour daily output of the BBC
are news, broadcasts of actualities such as
sports events, drama, light entertainment, films,
talks, features and documentaries.
Though the main emphasis is on entertain-
ment, the BBC claims for its programmes
certain educational values of an informal kind.
Thus in drama many plays have been televised
in full, including Hamlet, King Lear, The Rivals
and St.. Joan, also plays by Yeats, Pirandello,
T. S. Eliot, Cocteau and O'Neill. Full length
opera and ballet, performed by leading
companies, are transmitted regularly. One
recent example was Fokine's"Le Carnaval"
given by the Sadlers Wells Theatre Ballet.
Talks, features and studio documentaries
cover a great variety of subjects. In one
programme,"Inventor's Club", inventors are
invited to bring their models for scrutiny by
experts. So far, more than 360 inventions,
chosen from between 5, 000 and 6, 000 submitted,
have been shown to viewers. Among a dozen
which were shown recently was a flagpole
device---off particular interest in Britain's
Coronation Year-and a novel pneumatic
trouser press. Requests from overseas for
details of the inventions are received in
increasing numbers. In this way a new outlet
has been provided for unrecognized, and often
unrewarded talent.
The possibilities of the visual arts as material
for television programmes have also been well
exploited. In a series called"The Eye of the
Artist", paintings and sculptures, as well as
other forms of art, are regularly shown. When
works taken from current exhibitions, such as
that of Dutch painters recently held at the
Royal Academy have been shown on the
screen, it has encouraged viewers to go and
look at the original more closely and with some
equipment of expert comment. Science, of
course, is a frequently recurring topic.
, ballet for beginners'
TilE particular attention paid by the BBC tochildren is obvious from the large place
allocated to programmes for young people in
the daily transmissions as well as from their
quality and content.
While presented in the form of entertain-
ment, much of this material is deliberately
educational as : well as informative. An
example is"Ballet for Beginners", a pro-
gramme in which a ballet is analyzed, and the
way it is composed and put together is shown
before it is performed. In one children's pro-
gramme,"Nature Detectives", young viewers
receive suggestions on how they can discover
for themselves the habits of wild birds and
animals and the wonders of plant life.
In presenting these programmes, however,
the BBC is fully alive to the dangers of
passivity. Dealing with this problem"The
BBC Quarter) y" stated,"participation, which
represents the creative aspect of imitation, has
been actively encouraged. Children have been
shown how to paint scenery and make
puppets ; a nursery opera was performed with
properties and puppets made entirely by young
viewers. Illustrated poems poured in after a
programme on the centenary of Wordsworth's
death in 1930. One series of programmes sent
children into the country, following maps and
instructions on the screen, to find Norman
arches, country craftsmen, bird songs, flints and
barge names and all the various sights and
sounds of the countryside".
The BBC writer added :"Anything which
makes a contribution to creative activity rather
than to passive and continuous viewing is
worth a lot of trouble and a calculated propor-
tion of the financial expenditure."
Another BBC official, discussing the term
"education"in relation to the content of
television programmes in Great Britain, wrote :
"Television broadcasting, like sound broad-
casting, is in this country required to be a
service of information, education and enter-
tainment. It is not easy to draw the dividing
line, but I should regard a programme like
'Ballet for Beginners', which is explanation and
appreciation added to performance, as being
education. If one of the objects of education
is to increase and intensify enjoyment, the
production of plays of artistic worth comes
within the term as does opera."
As already stated, BBC television pro-
grammes at present include no formal educa-
tion, though the Corporation is moving
cautiously in that direction. On possible
classroom uses of television, it says :"We are
at present holding to the doctrine that we in
broadcasting are seeking to complement rather
than displace the teacher, though we think it
possible that, at certain points, as, for example,
in the teaching of science, experience may
suggest more directly didactic broadcasting
than has been acceptable in sound and that this
will be a useful service to the secondary
modern schools."
Last May, the BBC began to explore its
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
COURIER
ATIONAL TV
future contribution to formal education when
it broadcast its first experimental television
programme for schools.'Twenty programmes
were televised'and sent out on a special
wavelength for six schools in the neighbourhood
of the London transmitter. About 1, 000
secondary school children saw the programmes
on receivers which radio manufacturers had
loaned free of charge.
The purpose of the experiment was primarily
to study programme technique, but the subjects
chosen-current affairs, the industrial scene,
geography, aesthetics, science-were held to
be those which would seem obvious for
inclusion in a school television service if it were
started. The production was a team effort in
which the staffs of the Television Service and
of the sound School Broadcasting Department
collaborated.
Pilot test
SINCE the conclusion of this experimentmemb rs of the School Broadcasti g
Council (an advisory body consisting of mem-
bers of the teaching profession) have studied
reports, by some of their members who acted
as observers in the schools concerned. They
have studied teacher and pupil attitudes to the
programmes, but so far no decision has been
taken regarding the continuation of such
experiments or their extension to other parts
of the country.
The first"pilot"test has helped the authorities
to study many educational and technical
questions such as the extent to which
programmes may be a cause of passivity on the
part of children or the size of screens needed
to make viewing easy for a class of 40 children.
Great Britain has also been studying the
economic implications of school television. At
present, well over 20, 000 schools use radio
programmes specially broadcast for schools.
Quite apart from the cost of producing regular
TV programmes, the total expense involved in
providing one or two sets in each school at a
cost of between S70 and E100 apiece would add
tremendously to the budgets of local education
authorities.
This was one of the points raised by some of
the people who protested at the time of the
tentative experiment, against the possible
introduction of television in British schools.
No less a person than the Archbishop of
Canterbury, formerly a distinguished school-
master himself, asked :"Are we justified in
promoting or even considering such a move
involving great expenditure at the present time,
or should it be postponed until there is money,
material and labour to play with"It was a
remarkable thing, he added, that"just at this
moment when, as a nation, we are in extreme
financial peril, it should be thought appropriate
to increase the, in many ways, unnecessary
amenities of ordinary living. Television is by
way of becoming one of such amenities".
'D Disastrous wedge'
THE Archbishop describes television toschools as"nothing less than a perfect
disaster. It drives another wedge between the
teacher and the pupil, and is bad for the
children, who ought to be looking to the
personal contribution of the teacher for their
own personal growth. It is a dangerous thing
when they think they can be educated by
mechanisms from outside."
In a reply to the Archbishop, Mr. J. L.
Longland, Chairman of the Television
Committee of the School Broadcasting Council,
stated the reasons which prompted educators
and the BBC to undertake the experiment :
"You can't argue good cases from bad teachers"
he wrote."Television could help to give a
lazy teacher an even lazier life, but so can
providing a textbook for every child, or devoting
an hour or two to silent reading. Television
will be worth having only if it does two things
simultaneously-if it adds to the armoury of
the good and average teacher, and if it opens
for the children new windows on the
surrounding world."
Whichever way the controversy over
classroom television is settled in Great Britain
it is obvious that the approach so far made to
the problem has been more cautious and
tentative than that adopted in the United States.
As a BBC official recently declared :"It may
seem very deliberate, but I think the
deliberation is wise ; at least it is what the
educational world seems to want. There is a
certain amount of indigestion already over the
visual aids, and both the School Broadcasting
Council and the BBC are determined not to
undertake direct television broadcasting to
schools until there is shown to be a place for
it."
MARCH 1953. Page 5
FRANCE'S UNIQUE
CONTRIBUTION TO
TV FOR THE MANY
by Alexandre Leventis
FRANCE is the only country, apart from theUnited states, which has thus far devel-
oped formal educational TV. While pro-
grammes are as yet modest and the hours of
transmission limited, they include services both
for schools and as a basis for adult education.
When most people think of television, they
tend to think of a highly industrialized country
in which millions buy sets for their homes, and
families are grouped around the little screen in
the living room. This is the way TV has grown
in the U. S. and Great Britain during the past
six or seven years.
An entirely new approach to TV, however, has
sprung up n France. From the limited
resources of tiny villages scattered over the
countryside east of Paris, a small movement has
been born which may eventually be more signif-
icant for many countries than the more general
pattern television has so far assumed elsewhere.
In the French villages (whose experiments
were described in detail in the August-Septem-
ber 1952 issue of the Courier) a receiver is
bought collectively and placed in the local school
for the use of the community. Adults pay a
small admission fee to see broadcasts in the
evening. During the day the set is used exclus-
ively to receive school programmes for children.
This movement has given the French villages
the only way to get TV at all. The vast majority
of people in most countries cannot afford to
buy a TV set. But many might be able to afford
small entrance fees at regular sessions which
would help pay for a set whose initial pur-
chasing price was advanced. It is basically
immaterial whether all, part, or none of the
money for the set is advanced by members of
the community. Naturally though, there is a
more vivid interest in the venture if the villagers
have a personal stake in seeing to it that the
set is paid for, and it is easier to spread the
movement if it is not dependent entirely on
initial government funds. In France, villagers
usually advance 85 per cent and the schools 15
per cent of the cost of the set.
The rapid development of TV in Latin Amer-
ica and the plans for its use in the Middle
and Far East, point to the need for collective
purchase of sets if they are to serve the mass
of the people. In societies where there is a vast
gap between a very rich minority and the
poverty of the majority of the people, television
is today spreading largely as a luxury for the
upper income groups. To turn TV into a power
for the education of the mass of the people,
fundamental changes in its structure and pro-
gramming would no doubt be required. But no
amount of educational broadcasting can be of
value if extensive reception is not equally or-
ganized. It is here that the French movement
points the way.
Monsieur R. Louis, head of the National
Federation for Educational and Cultural Tele-
vision (an organization set up last year to help
collective viewers and now grouping about 75
local"telecluhs") recently described some of the
changes that the movement has brought about
not only in the habits and way of life of the
villagers but in their attitudes and thinking.
Thus the very purchase of a set, he points out,
leads to a new sense of community spirit and its
operation requires group action to arrange
and supervise the shows. In two of the villages,
made up mostly of workers at a nearby engine
factory, a friendly rivalry sprang up to see
(Continued on next page)
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Page 6. MARCH 1953 UNESCO
THE'TELECLUB'CHANGES
FRENCH VILLAGE HABITS
(Continued from previous page.)
which would collect the needed
money first. A thermometer, grad-
uated in thousands of francs, was
hung at the school entrance of each
village. Each day the workers
gathered together and heatedly
discussed the results of the two
collections. Within a week both sets
had been bought.
"The chief form of amusement in
the villages before the introduction
of TV,"M. Louis writes,"'consisted in
playing cards at the local café late
into the night. Now this has lost
considerable ground in favour of the
various shows offered two or three
times a week."
At first, many villagers came on-
ly to watch the horse-racing and
wrestling matches broadcast on the
popular newsreel show,"Television
Journal", but as the sports events
were often preceded by programmes
on political, economic and scientific
questions their interest was slowly
drawn to these subjects as well.
Many television sessions attended
by the villagers are now followed by
lively discussion under the direction
of the local teacher, who usually
organizes the"teleclubs". Villagers
eagerly participate, and the move-
ment is generally considered a
success.
Where community television has
been installed in the schoolhouse
under the guidance of the teacher,
a radical change has come about in
the place of the school and of the
teacher in the community. Through
personal acquaintance, the villagers
take a closer individual interest in
the school ; equally important, the
teacher gains new stature and res-
pect in the community.
No funds needed
COLLECTIVE viewing, moreover,may well be the answer to the
big dilemma facing most schools-
how or where to get the money to
buy a television set ? Collective TV
offers a unique method of installing
a receiver, often without using any
school funds. In fact, instead of
spending money, the school in the
long run finds in it a valuable source
of new income. Once the cost of
the receiver has been amortized from
the entrance fees (in France, where
75 per cent of the receivers are
already paid off, adults pay 20 francs
or about six cents for admission, and
children in the evenings pay 10
francs or three cents), the set
becomes the property of the school
and future receipts can be used to
finance school trips, extra equip-
ment, general improvements or cul-
tural activities within the com-
munity.
In the first village where a receiver
was installed (February 1951) the
cost of the set has been recovered
and the village TV co-operative had
a credit of 60, 000 francs (8170) by
June 1952, which will be used to buy
sports equipment and stage scenery
and organize an excursion for chil-
dren and adults.
The French Television Service has
been in contact with leaders of the
movement from the start and has
been receiving regular audience
reaction reports, suggestions for
improvement and criticisms. Thus,
villagers'objections to the number of
crime films offered eventually con-
tributed to their suppression. Ar-
rangements were recently made for
programmes specially designed to
meet the requirements of the village
audiences.
The wide gap between the
broadcaster and his audience is one
of the fundamental problems of
radio as well as TV. Present me-
thods of surveying, observing and
polling home audiences rarely give
more than quantitative reactions of
like and dislike. Co-operation with
group viewers can help to bridge
this gap and open up new perspec-
tives for improvement.
Efforts to meet the interest and
requirements of teachers and pupils
are also being made by the Televi-
sion Française in its three weekly
half-hour shows broadcast to schools
in 10 departments in the Paris area
and retransmitted in northern
France through the Lille relay sta-
tion. Two of these programmes
consist exclusively of filmed material
. and include a science series, geo-
graphy, history and man's applic-
ation of recent technical discoveries.
The third, is France's first"live"
show for schools, entitled"La Classe
en images" (the class on the TV
screen). Inaugurated in October
1952, the programme is designed for
children 6 to 14 years old in one-
room schoolhouses which, even
to-day, are by far the most common
primary schools of rural France.
Broadcasts are divided into sections
of about five minutes duration each
in an attempt to balance content, as
far as possible, for all pupils in this
wide age group. Shows are still
experimental and may be modified
in the light of comments and sug-
gestions sent in by teachers.
Last year, sections included a
series on a land of the French
Union ; great civilizations of the
past ; monuments of Paris ; our ani-
mal world ; and songs of France.
For the first half of this year,
drawing lessons and a gymnastics
course are being offered, as well as
a film sequence commemorating an
historical event, and the adventures
of a small donkey called Bim. When
"The Class on the TV Screen"is one of three weekly school programmes televised in France. The presence of a"live"
class on the screen heightens pupils'interest and encourages letter writing between the studio and village classes.
possible, subjects specially requested
by the schools are also given.
The"`Classe en images"uses as a
setting a typical rural schoolroom in
France along with a number of
lively youngsters. It is considered a
convenient background for the
action and dialogue of the children
and a way to stimulate young
viewers, to join with this class"just
like their own". Hundreds of letters
and reports on the programme come
from schools whose pupils are also
inspired to make models and do
designs and drawings.
The usefulness of the programme,
however, has been questioned by
some teachers.'''Is it really necess-
ary to have a make-believe class in
the studio ?" asked one..'Why must
we be shown the wall charts, maps,
tables of statistics and other familiar
classroom objects ? Of what interest
can these be to our pupils who see
them every day anyway ? Besides,
we don't teach three or four children
but forty ! The conditions you
show are not those we experience, so
the problems are not the same..."
Many letters are full of praise.
One headmaster recently wrote :
"My pupils, peasant children for the
most part, are not easily roused, but
they were wild with enthusiasm over
your programme from the moment
it started."
Some criticism comes from well-
meaning people who forget that
enthusiasm and ingenuity must
often make up for lack of funds.
Constructive letters like the follow-
ing are far more useful : "Dear
Television, I don't think you should
give lessons on the past participle.
And do you really think we need the
camera to tell our classes-and at
what speed-the meaning of vert-
ical and horizontal ? On Wednes-
day, our class was thrilled to watch
the very interesting documentary on
soil formation ; but on Saturday,
attention wandered while the P. T.
teacher babbled on with his wonder-
ful theories about breathing in class.
And during all this time, the screen,
ironically enough, showed several
children with their arms folded so
tightly across their chests that they
probably couldn't breathe at all.
If such demonstrations are to be of
any use the chidren must show some
life ; the instructor must talk less..."
Sorbonne telecasts
QUITE a different viewpoint wasexpressed by another teacher
who wrote :"I think the greatest
success with my boys was the
drawing class, and I believe that TV
will break down a certain inequality
now existing between city and
village schools by making lessons by
. highly specialized teachers available
to us all."
French TV producers note all
remarks and comments and then
take steps to remedy shortcomings
and faulty methods.
Last month, French television
embarked on a series of six exper-
imental programmes to be shown
each week on screens installed at
the Sorbonne. This is France's first
effort in university-level educational
programmes.
"We wish to discover the possibi-
lities of using television as a new
technique for presenting scientific
subjects to the public, and eventually
as an auxiliary of higher educa-
tion,"the Dean of the Faculté des
Sciences declared.
These programmes have been
prepared by professors at the Faculté
who personally produced the films
and photographs shown during the
half-hour transmissions.
The first, which went on the air
on 17 February, was devoted to Mi-
croscope cinematography, and show-
ed the multiplication of cells by
a tiny organism which throws light
on the process of heredity. In an-
other telecast this month, an anthro-
pologist will present scientific data
on the races of Africa and the Pyg-
mies in particular. Other telecasts
will deal with the Birth of the Stars,
Some Physiological Experiments on
Animals, Early Man and the Growth
of the Human Mind.
The Sorbonne hopes that these
highly scientific programmes will
mark the beginning of a new ven-
ture in educational television for
French university students, scientists
and the thinking public in general.
The schools of many villages in
the Paris region have now become
community meeting places where
people gather to watch telecasts
and to discuss them each evening.
In the afternoon children have been
watching the school programmes.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
MARCH 953. Page 7
CHART SHOW'S TELEVISION COVERAGE IN THE U. S. IN 1952.
U
5
A
HOW FUTURE STATIONS ARE EXPECTED TO COVER THE LAND.
ONE TV VIEWER FOR EVERY TWO AMERICANS
EDUCATORS made the biggest news in Americantelevision during the year 1952. The
persistent efforts of. a small group of
enthusiasts who had faith in the great possibil-
ities of educational television, led the United
States Government to recognize officially for the
first time the need for non-commercial, educa-
tional stations side by side with commercial
broadcasting.
On April 13, 1952, the Federal Communications
Commission announced its plan for the future
development and expansion of American TV, and
authorized the establishment of 2, 053 new stations
throughout the country. The challenging and
perhaps revolutionary feature of this plan is that
242 stations-or over 10 per cent of the total
number authorized-were reserved for educa-
tional institutions and non-commercial broad-
casting.
It is not difficult to imagine the sensation that
this decision has caused in educa-
tional circles in every part of the
United States. One educator, Harold
E. Wigren, director of audio-visual
education in Houston, Texas declared
that"April 13, 1952, may go down in
the annals of American education as
the date on which a new era of
educational opportunity was opened to
the American people."Another stated
that'''nor meeting of the American
Council on Education nor any other
group of educators will ever again be
the same. Something new has been
added. That something new is
exciting, it is challenging, it is
revolutionary."
All American educators do not share
this enthusiasm, and point to the
staggering difficulties, both in financ-
ing, and in programming, that
television raises. The FCC decision,
too, was made over the strong
objections by most segments of the
TV industry, led by the National
Association of Radio and Television
Broadcasting, which held that such
educational institutions never could
make a financial success of television.
and might"waste"their allotted
channels.
Up until now, television in the
United States has been operated as a
system of free commercial enterprise
within a framework of regulations
and controls set by a government
agency, the Federal Communications
Commission. The 128 stations now
on the air all carry commercial broad-
casts, and all, except one (run by
Iowa State College) are owned by
private interests who operate them for
profit. Many of these stations are
linked together in coast-to-coast
chains of four networks which provide
nation-wide programmes. In addition.
local stations., even when affiliated
with the networks, televise their own shows. In
the U. S., TV programmes are either commercially
sponsored or"sustained", that is, they are
produced at the stations'expense to meet their
responsibilities as a public service.
Commercial broadcasters point out that it was
only through their effort and capital outlay that
the enormous development of TV was made
possible in America. About one half of all
families in the United States today own televiion
sets. Some don't have it because they don't like
TV, others just cannot afford it, and others live
in areas which are not yet reached by TV
signals.
With the inauguration of coast-to-coast trans-
mission in 1951, people in San Francisco have
been watching programmes every day coming
from New York, 3, 000 miles away, and they accept
this technical miracle as a matter of course.
Children grow up with the idea that it is quite
natural to see the inauguration of a president
in their own living room, or animals pacing about
their cages in a zoo at the other end of the
country.
All parts of the country can take part instant-
aneously in events of national significance.
Dramatic performances can be seen by many
who may never have attended a theatre in their
lives. Many educational and cultural broadcasts"are produced in co-operation with schools and
universities. But the effects of cheap entertain-
ment, of crime stories and of excessive commer-
. cialization, have aroused the public to demand
an improvement in the quality of broadcasts.
Mindful of this criticism, broadcasters in
December 1951, adopted a TV code which
recognizes that"'television, and all who participate
in it, are jointly accountable to the American
public for respect for the special needs of child-
ren, for community responsibility, for the ad-
vancement of education and culture, for the
acceptability of the programme materials chosen,
for decency and decorum in production and for
propriety in advertising. This responsibility
cannot be discharged by any given group of
programmes ; it can be discharged only through
the highest standards of respect for the American
In this photo, the lines (formed by dots) which make up all television images
have been greatlyexaggerated to show how a picture is reproduced on the screen.
home, applied to every moment of every program-
me presented by television".
But the question has been raised as to how
effectively this code has really been applied.
Surveys in past years have pointed to the high
percentage of crime and low standard entertain-
ment in many TV programmes. Since the be-
ginning of this year, a veritable wave of appre-
hension and criticism seems to be sweeping
across the United States, and is evident from the
many newspaper articles, public statements, city
council hearings, parent-teacher association
declarations, etc.
Commercial broadcasters point out that they
are meeting the demands of the overwhelming
majority of the public when they furnish not
only information and education but primarily
entertainment and"escapist"programmes. The
great response to television in America, they
state, is in itself evidence of this.
They feel that they are already making many
serious efforts to meet their responsibility to the
government in broadcasting a certain percentage
of"public service"programmes in return for the
privilege of being permitted to use one of the
limited numbers of broadcast frequencies.
It should be pointed out, in fairness to com-
mercial broadcasters, that almost all the educa-
tional programmes and experiments referred to
in the articles on the next pages have been
conducted over the facilities of commercial sta-
tions. In addition, these stations are co-operat-
ing with museums, zoological gardens, observa-
tories, and other institutions in creating
educational shows of wide interest.
"Zoo Parade", for instance, comes regularly
from the Zoological Garden in Chicago. Through
commentary and demonstration by the director
, and the keepers, it provides instructive and
. entertaining insight into the life of many animal
species."What in the World ?" comes from the
University of Pennsylvania Museum and stumps
', experts who have to identify rare objects such
as a ritual cup from Africa, an old sword from
Siberia, or statues from Peru.
The San Francisco Museum of Art has been
very succesful with a regular programme entiti-
end art in Your Life."Its audience
has grown to more than 80, 000 view-
ers."This means reaching approxi-
mately half the museum's annual
attendance with one TV programme,"
notes the producer, and another
comment notes that"`interest has
been stimulated among people never
before reached by the museums."
TV viewers have had the exciting
experience of watching the stars
through the telescope of a famous
observatory, and the museum at
Stamford, Conn., co-operated with one
network in describing the phenome-
non of a lunar eclipse.
Such broadcasts, however, can be
no more than isolated examples in
a programme pattern which is design-
ed primarily for commercial reve-
nue and must meet the demand of
maximum popular appeal and not
merely of minority groups partic-
ularly interested in education. Many
educators have felt therefore that the
great opportunities of television for
the school and adult education could
not be exploited fully under a purely
commercial system. To change this
situation, their organizations united in
the Joint Committee for Educational
Television.
During the winter of 1950-51, at
hearings before the FCC, this group
representing teachers, educators, ad-
ministrators, men and women in pub-
lic life and other citizens, pleaded
strongly for the reservation of TV
channels for non-commercial educa-
tional institutions. They presented
75 witnesses and a great amount of
evidence to show the need and the
practical possibility of operating non-
commercial television stations devot-
ed to regularly scheduled courses
for children and adults both in cities
and rural areas. They said that
many programmes of these stations would be
integrated with state educational systems and
prepared by local TV councils drawn from
schools, universities, and cultural institutions.
The organizers of this movement had to con-
vince not only the government but also many of
their colleagues in the world of education who
were opposed to large expenses for this pur-
pose. Obviously, such stations could not be set
up unless the majority of educators actively
backed the movement.
When the FCC met the demands of this group
it stated the principal reasons which had convin-
ced it of the need for educational stations in these
words :"'The justification for an educational
station should not, in our view, turn simply on
account of audience size. The public interest will
clearly be served if these stations are used to
contribute significantly to the educational pro-
cess of the nation."
Replying to the contention by the TV indus-
try that the solution lay in educational pro-
grammes over commercial facilities, the FCC
concluded"that voluntary co-operation cannot
be expected to accomplish all
the important objects of edu-
cational television. In order
COURIER
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
PageS. MARCH) 95 UNESCO :
U. S. CHILDREN : TV'S MOST AVID FANS
All over the
United States
millions of chil-
dren, from in-
fants hardly able
to walk to teen-
agers, are sitting
with their eyes
glued to televi-
sion every day.
The impact this
is having on the
habits of chil-
dren has been
occupying
parents and tea-'T'T'tT"'^.,.. nn......... ^",, +chers ever since the TV set came out
of the barroom and entered the
American home.
Are most of the programmes bene-
ficial or injurious to children, many
ask ? How can you ensure that the
youngsters will not neglect their
homework ? That they will continue
to read books ? Does it help to bring
the family together ? Does watching
programmes discourage more creative
forms of recreation ? These and a
host of other questions have received
many conflicting answers which have
stirred the nation.
One thing, at any rate, is certain.
American children spend a good deal
of their time before the TV screens.
A study at Stamford, Connecticut,
first brought out that schoolchildren
are looking at programmes 27 hours
a week-almost as many hours as
they attend school. According to
another survey conducted in Cam-
bridge, Massachusetts, the average
child watches TV for some two and a
half hours on weekdays and for three
and a half hours on Sundays. These
figures apply, on the whole, to chil-
dren of all age groups and from all
income groups. But it has been found
that five-and six-year olds tend to
watch TV even more than older chil-
dren (perhaps because school work
fills less of their time).
The reason for TV's enormous
appeal to children is not far to seek.
As the American educator, Dr. Paul
Witty, of North-western University,
says,"TV offers exciting stories told
in short episodes or instalments
that keep up interest. The spoken
word is easy to understand... The
accessibility of TV (as of comics, radio
and the cinema) adds to their appeal.
Children can have TV merely by
turning a knob in the living room...
Even if a child is a good reader, many
homes and classrooms just don't have
enough interesting, attractive reading
material that can compete success-
fully. Too few children have good
books in their homes. Children also
have the fun of meeting old friends
over and over again. (They) enjoy
belonging to their hero's clubs,
offering special rings, code books and
badges. It makes them feel they
belong to something big and im-
portant. Through radio, TV, cinema
and comics, youngsters also believe
they are participating in something
grown-up and worth while."
Research indicates however (though
findings vary on this point) that
children do not spend more time with
other children of their own age once
they have television. The tendency,
instead, is for children who have TV
sets in their homes to become isolated.
Initially, at any rate, TV presents
parents with certain disciplinary
problems. Many, for instance, end it
difficult to get their children to leave
the set to come to meals, and the
eating habits of many children have
been affected since they must often
be served in front of the set.
Bedtime, also, is often a serious
problem. Most studies, in America
and Great Britain, indicate that
children in TV homes go to bed later
than those of the same age in non-
TV homes. Many teachers report
that small children are"sleepy heads"
in school, and a survey of elementary
schools in a New Jersey community
revealed that it is not unusual for
second and third grade pupils to talk
about 10. 30 p. m. programmes they had
viewed. The General Superintendent
of Schools of Chicago, Illinois, de-
clared that youngsters turn up in
classes with what he termed"TV
hangovers".
It has been claimed as a virtue for
TV that it tends to bring families
closer together. This is undoubtedly
true-in the sense that they spend
more time in each other's company.
There is, however, very little discus-
simon or other interaction among
family members when they watch
television together.
Adverse reading habits
T he powerful appeal of TV has hadimportant consequences in the
daily living habits of children. At-
tracted by the TV screen, youngsters
are listening to the radio less, going to
the cinema less, and reading less ;
exactly to what extent is not easy to
determine. But most studies in the
United States and Great Britain agree
that reading is seriously affected and
that radio listening is substantially
reduced.
Audience research carried out in
England reveals that the desertion of
radio is particularly marked among
the young, despite the fact that 90 per
cent of TV homes still have radios.
Thus, during the TV Children's Hour
of the B. B. G., viewing outnumbered
listening in the following proportions :
among 5-to 7-year olds by 18 to 1 ;
among 8-to 11-year olds, viewers
outnumbered listeners by 11 to 1 ; and
among 12-to 14-year olds by 4 to 1.
Afternoon cinema attendance, fur-
thermore, was found to be down by
about 40 per cent and evening
attendance by about one-third.
One American child put the matter
succinctly. When asked how often he
went to the cinema or listened to the
radio, he answered :"only when the
television isn't working."
But a report published in December
1952 by WOI-TV in Ames, Iowa (the
only all-educational station in the
U. S.), reveals.'no special evidence
that TV has reduced moving picture
attendance."
In December, 1951, station KING-
TV in Seattle, Washington, decided to
undertake a 13-week experimental
series of telecasts to increase chil-
dren's interest in books and stimulate
them to read more.
Shown on the screen was a group
of children, their backs to the
viewers, seated at the feet of a young
story-teller. In her hands was a
book from which she told the story.
The backdrop was a huge open book
with the inscription"Telaventure
Tales... Once Upon a Time". Across
its pages moved a non-realistic char-
acter, Penjamin Scribbler, who knew
all the books and all the authors.
In the first half of the programme,
an episode from a book was related
by the story-teller. A few live scenes
were enacted to vary the story
technique. The second half of the
programme involved a game in which
the TV audience participated. Scenes
from a number of books were pre-
sented, and the viewers were invited
to write in the name of the character
portrayed, the name of the book, its
author, and"`Why I like this book".
The immediate results were re-
markable. By the second programme,
the Seattle Public Library and all its
branches had reported that every book
by the author featured had been
borrowed. The programme's influen-
ce extended into the rural areas.
The county public library reported
that all the books by all the authors
mentioned on this programme dis-
appeared from the shelves of its
38 branches and two bookmobiles.
At a conference on"Reading in the
Family", held in New York last
December, Robert L. Shayon, TV
critic and author of"`Television and
our Children", ipointed out that
television can provide a bridge to
books if parents made the most of
the opportunities it presents. If a
youngster is fascinated by the
Westerns he sees, parents might get
a good Western story to read with
the child and compare the two, trying !
to build discrimination and taste. He f
also suggested using TV as a.'cross I
reference"to reading. If parents I
watch shows with their children, he it
said, they are very likely to find in
them occasions to refer to books or
characters that would help arose
the child's interest in books. (
TV and school grades
Much has been said to the effectthat poor homework, poor grades
and TV seem to go hand in hand. A ;
survey undertaken by the New York
Times in June 1951 found, however,
that"the overwhelming majority of
school officials from coast to coast
believe that the new medium is
benefitting youngsters in many dif-
ferent ways and is not having sig-
nificantly adverse effects."But the
same survey also reported that *'a
preponderance of educators were
critical of the cultural quality of
today's general run of commercial
television programmers".
The effect of TV on the child's study'
habits and class marks was recently
the subject of a special investigation
undertaken by Xavier University and
the Crosley Broadcasting Corporation
in Cincinnati, Ohio. About 1, 000
sixth and seventh grade pupils
participated in the study. Those not
having TV sets were matched with
pupils, of the same class and mental
age, who had sets. Four major
conclusions were drawn :
1. There was no significant differ-
ence in school results between"TV
children"and"non-TV children".
2. Learning at school was not much'
affected by the way parents controlled
their children's viewing.
3. The lower the child's intelligence,
the more likely he is to watch many
TV mystery-crime programmes. As
the report put it, poor TV habits, 
lower LQs., lower parental control,
and poorer school marks tend to be
found in the same child.
4. TV results in damage to physical
well-being and mental alertness when
used to excess.
Several other studies carried out in
the United States confirm that watch-
ing TV does not, as fa rule, seriously
affect school results. But despite
these findings, a great many teachers,
drawing on their own observations
and experience, persist in claiming
that it does.
Thus, when the teachers of Cleve-
land, Ohio, high schools complained
that the quality of home work was
seriously deteriorating, the principal
of one school made a survey of 274
students. He found that 112 or 41
per cent had TV sets. More than 89
of them watched television for over
an hour a day ; and of these, 86 said
they thought it handicapped them in
their school work."Maybe really
good students could s tan d the
diversion", the principal said. He
doubted, however, whether the poor
students could, pointing out that,
unlike radio, TV was a'''completed
attention"activity, and that while it
was possible for some students to do
their homework and listen to the
radio at the same time, it was
impossible to watch TV and study at
the same time.
Exploring the art world
Educators have suggested that TVappreciation courses be instituted
in the classroom to encourage children
to discuss the programmes they see.
In secondary schools special courses
in literature or cinema appreciation,
are already common, and it has been
proposed that TV might be included.
In addition, the oral language period
at any grade level is felt to be an
important place for discussing tele-
vision and helping children to develop
better viewing standards.
The principal of one New York
elementary school has already decided
to do this, and has suggested to his
teachers that they incorporate at
least one weekly. lesson on television
in their language, art or social studies
classes. A similar effort is planned
by the chairman of the English
Department of a New Jersey sec-
ondary school in order to relate
education more closely with living,
and to reduce as far as possible the
child's sense that"academic"subjects
are just and only that-academic.
It may be of interest, at this point,
to mention the TV effort originated
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
: OURIER MARCH 1953. Page 9
by Victor d'Amico, director of art
education of the Museum of Modern
Art in New York. The museum has
produced a series entitled :"Through
the Enchanted-Gate"which the pro-
gramme notes state,'''guides the
three-to ten-year-old through a
wonderful explanatory course in
esthetic self-expression. Accent is on
the child, but the parent is si-
multaneously coached into playing a
helpful part in the development of the
child's creative impulses. And the
proper attitude for parents and
teachers is suggested by a group of
professionals who work with children
on the programme."
There has been (and still is) much
debate in the U. S. about the psycho-
logical influence of TV on children.
Professor Charles Siepmann, in the
Unesco volume just published on
"Television and Education in the
United States", does not hesitate to
write :"It had better be said cate-
gorically that there is at present no
solid evidence on this point. For it
is virtually impossible to separate out
the influence of TV, whether on
children or adults, from the conco-
mitant influence of other mass media
and the complex of factors in the
general social environment.
"To say this, however, is not to
dismiss the subject as of no im-
portance. It is obviously of supreme
importance. It simply means that if
one is looking for proof on this matter
one will not find it. It is a matter of
judgment and opinion. And the
absence, whether now or in the
future, of scientific corroboration
provides no alibi for serious thought
and discussion of the problem or for
responsible action."
Psychiatrists and child experts are
generally of two opinions regarding
TV's effect on children. One group
feels that with proper control and
parent supervision television is not
harmful. The other sees TV as a real
threat to child development.
Dr. Frederic Wertham, psychiatrist
and author, is fairly representative of
the second point of view. He feels
that many people glibly discount the
influence on children of TV, comic
books and mass media in general.
"What children get out of comic
books", he writes,'''is that kindness,
sympathy and regard for human
suffering are all weaknesses ; that
cunning and shrewdness are the kind
of thing that counts ; and that women
are not to be respected as persons,
but are luxury prizes like automobiles,
distinguished chiefly by sexy attri-
butes rather than by any high ideal
of womanhood."
He sees similar evils in television.
Because of TV, he says, children
"confuse violence with strength, low
necklines with feminine ideal, sadism
with sex and criminals with police."
Crime and violence
C rime arid violence as major themeson TV programmes are in fact
the sharpest criticisms levelled against
the current output of television in
America. Some startling figures have,
indeed, been revealed on the subject.
"By and large", says the TV
correspondent of the New Yorker
magazine,'''television writers are
fascinated by death... Week after week,
programme after programme, death
in one form or another assumes a
major role... Over the past year, I
find that 16, 932 men, women, children
and animals have passed away on TV
programmes since November 1950,
most of them in a sudden and quite
violent manner."
Figures published in January 1953
and based on a comprehensive survey
made by the Parent-Teachers Asso-
ciation of Chicago, reveal even more
startling findings. The study was
based on reports by a group of mon-
itors who watched every children's
programme on every one of Chicago's
TV stations during the period
between last Christmas morning and
New Year's Eve. The monitors tab-
ulated 295 violent crimes portrayed
exclusively on children's shows. These
included 93 murders, 78 shootings, 9
kidnappings, 9 robberies, 44 gunfights,
2 knifings, 33 sluggings, 2 whiplash-
ings, 2 poisonings, and 2 bombings.
The number of shows for children
totalled 134 ; 48 were Western crime
films and 33 were old films of various-
types.
Somewhat similar results have been
found by the National Association for
Better Radio and Television in a
report published last July on the Los
Angeles, California, area. The study
showed that 56 per cent of the
broadcasts were considered"ob-
jectionable"or"most objectionable"
for children. It indicated that crime,
violence and mediocrity dominated
programmes and called for a revision
of children's shows.
However, psychiatrists of the oppos-
ing school of thought, like Dr. Lau-
retta Bender, head of the Child
Psychiatry Department of Bellevue
Hospital, New York, are convinced
that such programmes offer no threat
to the healthy development of
children. They feel that the violence
on TV merely provides a harmless
outlet for the natural and normal
aggressiveness of all children (1).
Another psychiatrist, Dr. Phillip Po-
latin, believes that cowboy films,
despite general parental disapproval,
are an"excellent outlet"for the
child's aggression, and he suggests
that critics.. who object to television's
"passive entertainment"watch a
group of boys popping cap pistols,
yelling at villains and encouraging
heroes as they sit before the TV set.
Thus the answers go, for and against
television. In reality, it is part of the
great debate which has raged for
years over the influence, of all the
mass media on young people and
adults as well. There have been the
dime novels, the cinema, the radii,
and the comics. The latest battle-
ground is now television. Practically
all critics and supporters will admit,
however, that the picture is actually
neither all black nor all white.
As the New York Times aptly put it
in an editorial,"It (is) abundantly
clear that television represents a new
problem for the world of education,
but the implications obviously extend
far beyond the classroom itself. Any
medium which can command such a
high proportion of a child's waking
hours no longer can be regarded
merely as a novel form of en-
tertainment. It is a social force
with enormous potentialities for good
or bad, and the course which television
follows in the future quite properly
should be the concern of the
community as a whole."
(IJ.-POT a report on"aY (JTes ; iveness" in child'Ten se. eartid"You Can't Chanue Human Natu'Tt-False !..
bV Ashlev Montag"in Feb. 1953 CtlIJrier).
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Page 10. MARCH 1953 UNESCO OU
THE CASE FOR AND AGAINST
light entertainment TV shows reach millions of
viewers each week. Above, Jimmy Durante in a
song number that also amuses studio staff.
for an educational
programme to
achieve its aim it is
necessary that
broadcast time be
available for educa-
tors on a regular basis. An audience cannot be
built up if educators are forced to shift their
broadcast period from time to time. Moreover,
the presentation of a comprehensive schedule
of programmes comprising a number of courses
and subjects which are designed for various
age and interest groups may require large
periods of the broadcast day-difficult if not
impossible to obtain on commercial stations."
It is important, however, to point out the
FCC did not relieve commercial stations of
their responsibility to serve the public when
it set aside the 242 non-commercial channels
for educational purposes. As the FCC stated,
"this provision does not relieve commercial
licensees from their duty to carry programmes
which fulfil educational needs and serve the
educational interest in the community in
which they operate. This obligation applies
with equal force to all commercial licensees,
whether or not a non-commercial educational
channel has been reserved in their commun-
ity, and similarly will obtain in communities
where non-commercial educational stations
will be in operation."
Educators had won their first victory. Per-
haps it was also the easiest victory, for the
FCC had given them no more than paper
allocations and in addition had warned that
these allocations might be turned over to
commercial broadcasters after June 1953 unless
educators could give practical assurance that
they would be able to use the frequencies
reserved to them. In short, the FCC plan
simply handed to the educators the urgent
task of finding the necessary resources to set
up TV stations all over the country. TV
costs are staggeringly high. Roughly $ 250. 000
are needed to put up the simplest station and
another $ 250, 000 for operating expenses.
Educational organizations in every State of
the Union are now busy preparing the way.
They must convince legislatures in order to
obtain the needed subsidies, they are consult-
ing engineers on production costs, they are
debating with boards of trustees of universi-
ties on the need for a TV station. They seek
to convince boards of education about the use-
fulness of school TV. And almost every day
the American press carries such headlines as
"TV for Education Urged as a Right" ;
"Chicago may go to public for educational TV
station fund" ;"Teachers in South back TV
network" ;"Milton Eisenhover forms group
pushing for educational TV stations" ;"Non-
commercial Video stations must be spoken for
now or forever lost."
Educators have realized that they must
work together now and in the future. Educa-
tional stations are planning to co-operate
closely on the production of programmes, in
exchanging films and in many other ways.
Statewide TV networks are in preparation and
the U. S. may eventually be covered by a na-
tionwide educational broadcast network. In
New York State, for example, the State Uni-
versity has already been granted licences for
stations in six different cities which will bring
education not only to citizens of large cities
but especially to rural areas and small towns.
By the end of 1952, only 19 applications for
educational TV stations had been filed with
the FCC and 10 construction permits issued.
But none of these stations is yet on the air.
There is a long and. hard road ahead for
educational TV in America. But educators in
the United States are seeking to meet this
challenge which may vitally affect not only the
future of the country's educational system but
the entire character of television broadcasting,
that new force which has struck so deeply into
the heart of the American family.
"I N Utopia", writes Professor Charles Siep-mann,"every classroom in every school
would be equipped with a television receiver.
But Utopia is far off."It is, in fact, so far off that
educators are still eyeing the entire question of the
classroom use of TV with a good deal of mixed
feeling. On the one hand there is the conviction
that it will lead to a more effective means of
mass education ; on the other, there is scepticism
even as to its potentialities. The ultimate deci-
sion as to the place of classroom television in the
overall picture of educational telecasting will
depend to a great extent on the information which
is now being assembled and which will be gather-
ed in the next few years.
Classroom TV today is still in its infancy. It
is only in the past five years that pioneer groups
in the United States have ventured forth into this
unknown and unexplored territory. Only about
40 school systems, concentrated mostly in the
eastern part of the U. S. and in certain large city
areas of the Middle West and California, now use
television. Television sets in schools are still
scarce, except in a few areas, like Philadelphia,
Los Angeles and Minneapolis.
According to many persons, Philadelphia is the
outstanding example in the U. S. of experimenta-
tion in the use of school TV. It has come to be
regarded as'''a Mecca for those interested in the
future development of school television,"and has
attracted visitors from 40 States and at least
10 foreign countries.
Regular telecasts to primary and secondary
school classes first began on 7 March 1949, with
31 schools participating.'''Operation Classroom",
as it was called, followed two years of arduous
pioneering effort on the part of Philadelphia
school authorities and teachers, during which
many school programmes, not intended for class-
room use, were transmitted regularly during after-
school and evening hours. These were intended,
to show parents and the general public what goes
on in the public schools of Philadelphia ; to give
teachers and children an opportunity to view TV
with a more critical eye ; to increase confidence
in television as a classroom medium ; and through
trial and error, to train teachers in the highly
specialized skill of programme production.
Today, 13 programme series for classroom use,
graded for different age levels, are being broad-
cast weekly over three commercial stations which
donate the time and studio facilities. And some
40, 000 pupils now watch these telecasts during
school hours on 900 sets throughout the greater
Philadelphia area.
The purpose of these programmes is primarily
to provide the schools with material and person-
alities normally not available in classroom educa-
tion. They include for instance :"The World at
Your Door"which discusses problems of educa-
tion, government, industry and agriculture with
guests from other lands ;"Exploring the Fine
Arts", where children are shown exhibitions from
the Philadelphia Art Museum or dramatic scenes
from Macbeth presented by an English teacher ;
"Science is Fun", includes discussions and dem-
onstrations of interplanetary travel, observation
of phenomena under a microscope and sugges-
tions of science activities for summer days. Other
programmes include stories for young children
and discussions of children's books with guest au-
thors, music education, talks about teen age man-
ners and social problems, and a weekly quiz on
American events and history.
Students and teachers participate eagerly and
in fact practically constitute the entire show. At
the end of the second year of operation, 2, 500 pu-
pils had taken part in 210 live telecasts.
Philadelphia has explored various educational
implications of classroom TV. It quickly saw the
need for printed guidance so that teachers would
know what to do before the telecasts began and
have material for"follow-up"activities. The Sup-
erintendent of Schools admits that this material
is still inadequate and will need considerable am-
plification to be fully useful. In addition, a sum-
mer workshop has been held every year since the
beginning of the project to give teachers practi-
cal training in the various uses of school TV.
All in all, the Philadelphia schools'television
staff are encouraged by the results achieved so
far.'''Follow-up activities are almost amazing,"
they say."Teachers report that as a result of
'Science is Fun', children built small motors, col-
lected insects, built small radios...'Everyone's Ar.
Artist'led to a tremendous number of art projects
in the classrooms."
Teachers opinion surveys list a number of bene-
fits of classroom TV : it stimulates class activities ;
field trips are requested ; vocabularies are enlarg-
ed ; children seek supplementary reading ; they
are more aware of the importance of good diction ;
they retain the skills and processes they see with
amazing accuracy ; many of the teaching tech-
niques used on the screen are good training for
the class teacher himself.
It should be pointed out, however, that these
findings are expressions of opinion and not scien-
tifically verified conclusions.
Very little research of scientific testing has as
yet been undertaken in the U. S. (or in'other coun-
tries for that matter) to determine how effective
TV really is as a classroom tool. Practically no
tests have been made to find out how much chil-
dren actually understand and remember of what
they see on the screen.
One of the rare studies made thus far is an
experiment in teaching elementary school music
by TV. Eight music lessons were telecast in 1951,
with sixth grade classes in seven Washington, D. C.
schools taking part. Similar classes of children
who did not see the TV programmes were used as
a control group. Telecasts lasted a half-hour,
except for a 45-minute opening lesson.
The"public affairs"programme is one branch of educational television now being widely developed in the U. S.
which contributes to the cultural advance of the community. It ranges from news, discussion and religion
to documentaries and special events programmes. Using maps, photos and charts, the speaker (above) can
make his explanation clearer and more forceful than is possible in broadcasts over the radio.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
ESCO OURIER MARCH 1953. Page II
iCHOOL TV
In these programmes, the
children were told about Beet-
hoven and other composers
whose works were then played ;
they saw unusual instruments.
heard them played and explain-
ed ; they were shown how easy
it is for any child to play simple
instruments like the melody
flute.
Although this study was ad-
mittedly limited, school author-
ities drew the following con-
elusions :
1-Parents and pupils were
enthusiastic about the teaching
of music by TV.
2. The experiment failed to
show any advantage in favour of
teaching music by TV. Test re-
sults showed that pupils did not
learn more about music as a re-
sult of classroom TV than if the
lessons had been taught without
television.
3. Answers given on the tests
revealed"the limitations of
learning by TV and suggest that
a transient TV show seen in a
classroom may prove of little
permanent value unless the tea-
cher does something in follow-
up teaching to sharpen up and
fix the facts, concepts or anti-
tudes." (Lack of preparatory
and follow-up materials is, at
the moment, one of the major
problems and one of the serious
defects in the operation of class-
room television. >
4. There were unexpected ben-
efits. Many parents followed
the programmes with interest,
thus learning how their chil-
dren study music and creating
a more direct link between
school and home. Children con-
fined at home voluntarily partic-
ipated, thus opening up a whole
new field of service.
In this connexion, it is inte-
resting to note that ill and crip-
pled children can now earn 3-
diploma in New York City by
watching the"Living Black-
board", a regular series of telev-7 7i 1... 41... i. : Eised lessons prepared by the city's board of edu-
cation.
In the last chapter of his book on American
television, Professor Siepmann sums up his per-
sonal conclusions on classroom TV, based on
these and many other experiments ; in school
television in the U. S. today. He writes :"Televi-
sion of this kind is, at the present time, probably
over-rated by pioneer enthusiasts, as it is also too
summarily dismissed by others. That it has value
as a tool of education is almost beyond cavil..."
Such value depends, he says, on two things-
the quality of teaching and the cost of TV.. Tele-
vision can't replace the teacher. It is a most
effective supplementary tool in the hands of the
gifted teacher. The poor teacher usually botches
the job, and despite its superficial attractiveness,
the screen is likely to be a distractive influence
rather than a teaching aid. As for the cost of
television,"the wise school administrator will
pause before launching on the vast expenditure,
both of money and of effort, which the installa-
tion of receivers and their use involves."
He points out that"in any school system, in
any country, the first consideration is good teach-
ing. Adequate premises and adequate equipment
come, perhaps, second, together with the desir-
ability of classes small enough to allow of effec-
tive instruction."
Variety and relief
HE cautions against believing that a final formof educational broadcast has yet been found
and cites the following opinion of a radio-TV
consultant in an important American school
system :"I have been very unhappy to learn that
in many school systems educators who have
experimented a little bit with television are
convinced that a certain format should be
followed. One group will say, use children in the
telecast ; another says use only teachers ; another
says teachers and a few children ; and so on. I
am sure we are all in an experimental stage yet,
and I hate to see people begin to set up patterns
on television as they did on radio."
Classroom TV has a number of obvious advant-
ages but it also has some distinct disadvantages.
Television can bring current events as they occur
into the class and can thus stimulate a child's
sense of living and participating in a real world
despite the physical remoteness of the events.
Likewise the living presence on the school screen
of distinguished personalities enhances a child's
sense of belonging. Television gives students the
stimulus of variety and is a welcome relief from
the habitual teacher.
All reports indicate that children enjoy partici-
pating in TV programmes. As Professor Siep-
mann says,"Why would they not ?" Whether this
has the educational value usually claimed for
such experience or whether the same advantages
might not be realized even more effectively by
other methods, remains opens to question in his
view.
The value of TV in science teaching, in arts
To appraise television as an aid to teaching, schools in Washington televised a series of eight elementary school music lessons
in 1951, as a means of bringing into the classroom the teaching skills of specialists. Children learned to play simple instruments.
and crafts classes, and in demonstrating the ins-
truments of the orchestra and their use, is ob-
vious. The occasional but not excessive use of
demonstration lessons is likely to provide an
added resource of great value in most classrooms.
Certain educators, however, contend that films
can do everything that television can, and can do
it better-with one exception : television can pre-
sent important public events on the classroom
screen. Films, they point out, are superior in
quality ; cutting and editfng allows for a more
finished product. Films, moreover, can"go
places"just as the TV camera can. Two supreme
advantages are further advanced for films.
First, they are available at call in the school
library or elsewhere. The major criticism of TV
in schools is its"tyranny of time", that is the
necessity of synchronizing viewing hours with
class schedules. Films can be used whenever the
teacher wants to without adjusting his curricu-
lum.
Secondly, films have the enormous advantage
in that teachers can preview them at leisure and
make adequate preparation for their integrated
use in the lesson. They can also be shown more
than once. Screens are larger and much easier
on the students'eyes and colour film can be
shown-those these two advantages of the film
are probably only temporary. Advocates of the
film also claim it is cheaper.
Because of this controversy, Professor Siepmann
questioned school superintendents and teachers
in order to get their opinion on the comparative
merits of films and TV in the classroom. He
found that"no convincing answer has yet been
given by proponents of the use of TV to those
who claim the superior advantages of film, with
the one exception (current events, noted earlier),
which is unreservedly conceded."
The results showed that when faced with the-,----- _L_'= ;'_' : _--..-'---_.... +.... .. 1.-......
choice, a striking number rated the
film higher than TV as a teaching aid.
But Siepmann points out that'''great-
er and longer familiarity with the
film may well have influenced the
choice of many of the respondents,"
and that where school TV has been
used the longest, distinctive and not
comparable advantages for both are
claimed.'''Given opportunity to use
both media,"he writes,'''current ex-
perience suggests the desirability of
using both."
In actual practice, most schools to-
day must choose between the two be-
cause of limited funds. Professor
Siepmann's conclusion is that"as of
the moment, it would appear that
most schools, if forced to a choice,
would chose films, and regard tele-
vision as something of a luxury."
Where classroom TV exists, it has
been criticized by teachers who have
stated that it is often difficult to cor-
relate programmes with class work,
that it takes time from the regular
curriculum without true compensatory advanta-
ges, that a 15-minute telecast is too short, and
that a week between programmes is too long.
Some schools have asked simply for better qual-
ity programmes. As one sympathetic but critical
observer put it after studying television activities
in the classrooms :"My reaction to what I saw
may seem brutal ; nevertheless it can be express-
ed in a single sentence. The TV set wasn't big
enough ; the programme wasn't good enoughs"
Teachers and school officials alike are unani-
mous on one point. They urge that in all school
systems"competent instruction in the intelligent,
integrated use of TV programmes should consti-
tute a regular part of in-service training, as it
should also be part of overall training in teacher
training schools."
Instruction in audio-visual techniques is still
sadly lagging at most teacher's colleges, and only
three States-Pennsylvania, Ohio and California
- make even a rudimentary acquaintance with
these techniques mandatory for obtaining a tea-
cher's certificate, though many offer"elective'
courses on the subject.
.'zit is clear", writes Professor Siepmann,'''that
television education is useless unless it is support-
ed by adequate preparatory printed information
and skilful follow-up work on the part of the tea-
cher. This requires a familiarity by the teacher
with the possible use of television."
And he adds :"The use, even of films designed
for classroom use which have been with us for a
quarter century, remains far less effective than it
might be because so few teachers have been train-
ed to use them intelligently. All the money spent
on television by school systems will be largely
wasted unless this defect at the training level is
made good. It is, indeed, the master key to the
future value of television as a tool of classroom
instruction."
Thanks to TV, people in San Francisco can now be spectators at
important public events taking place 3000 miles away in New-York
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Page 12. MARCH 1953 UNESCCOUÐ
tivities. Something like forty institutions, most
of which have been offering radio training and
instruction for years, have incorporated the new
art into the existing radio curriculum.
But still more significant for the development
of educational television is the number of students--.,.....
and faculty members already
contributing frequently to tele-
vision programmes over commer-
cial stations, either as individuals
or in co-operative undertakings
between stations and the college
or university for the presentation
of programmes designed and
executed by the college.
In Philadelphia a group of 20
colleges has combined to present,
between them, a regular series of
adults education programmes.
Similar programmes originated
by some 40 or so other institutions
are being transmitted by com-
mercial stations. In only two
cases are such programmes pre-
pared for classroom use-the vast
majority designed and executed
zion the campus"are for adult
consumption.
The range of subjects treated
is about as extensive as the
departments of instruction at the
universities. Of the six com-
monest subjects, science in all its
aspects leads. The others most
frequently offered are psychology,
art and literature, history, forums,
drama.
In general, then, universities
and colleges are at present
making use of television to bring
education"into the living room"
of millions of viewers, not into
their own classrooms. Television
applied to classroom instruction is
most often used in courses for
students majoring in radio or
television, or both.
What are the"target ob-
jectives"of these institutions of
higher education in planning
programmes which they know
will reach millions of people ?
At a number of colleges and
universities, the primary objective
appears to be that of public
relations-to create goodwill for
the institution concerned and to
bring to the general public fuller
knowledge of the opportunity of
"'on the campus"education.
Thus, at the University of Akron,
film tours of the campus have
been televised, and a course on
rubber chemistry. has highlighted
a specialized activity of the
university.
The commonest type of pro-
gramme, however, reflects an
attitude typical of many univer-
sities and colleges in the U. S.,
particularly the so-called"land
grant"colleges. These institutions
owe their existence to an 1862
Act of Congress which granted
public land to each State to found
a college of, agriculture and
technology. Some of these ins-
titutions were incorporated in.....  ;....  ;......,...". C"'+..............- ;........-... ; + ;.............. +\..existing State universities ; others remained
separate.
Founded and developed in a tradition of service
to the community, these institutions exemplify
the great concern throughout American education
that it be related to life and that the resources
of scholarship be harnessed to the needs of the
community. This is why so many courses are
offered which reflect the needs and activities of
the community surrounding the college or
university.
In this particular field, the work of Iowa State
College stands out not only because of the
advanced stage it has reached, but also because
of the college's unique position as the first and, as
yet, the only college or university owning and
operating its own television station.
The State college exists to serve the people of
the State. The aim of its station has been to
extend and facilitate such service among the
600, 000 or so people in its area-the richest and
heaviest populated part of Iowa.
Programmes put out reflect the general
characteristics, in terms of service rendered, of a
State Agricultural College, as the following
examples show :"Down to Earth" (information of
interest to the home gardener) ;"Books on Trial"
(discussions of books, classics and modern) ;
COLLEGE COURSES BY TV
Television has solved a major problem for the instructor in medical schools. It enables
him to show effective close-up views of demonstrations of delicate techniques to as
many as 40 or 50 students at a time, instead of to only small groups as in the past.
The first subject to be chosen was school
district reorganization i. e. how to achieve a more
rational distribution of the State's schools. This
is a problem of local importance but of national
scope. The town selected for the discussion was
Cambridge, Iowa, which had a problem of
declining high school enrolment, and school costs
per pupil well above the average. After some
discussion the townsfolk agreed to participate,
and chose 12 of their number to represent them.
The telecast had two skilfully blended com-
ponents-spontaneous, unrehearsed discussion
and films of the community to dramatize and
underline the problem. Since the first programme
some of the techniques have been modified in the
light of experience.
But the basic principle on which"'The Whole
Town's Talking"was conceived, real people
discussing their own real problems, has remained
unchanged. And what stands out above all is
the sincerity of the programmes. John Dyer, the
rural mailman, alone of all the people in Cam-
bridge spoke up for a type of school reorganization
which might mean better education for the
children at the cost of losing the high school to
another town. John Dyer is a man of over 60.
He does not like to speak in public. But when he
stood up and pointed his finger at the eleven
slightly over 100, 000 individuals
have, during the course of presen-
tation, viewed one or more tele-
casts.
A second series of courses on
"Child Psychology"and.'Physical
Geography"and subsequently on
"General Economics"and"Ap-
preciation of Music"were pre-
sented. The music courses were
given on television in the morning
and the music referred to played
on the radio station the same
afternoon.
Because these were morning
programmes, nearly 90 % of the
viewers were women. Some 64 %
of the registrants completed
the course and took final ex-
aminations. Their work amazed
instructors, one of whom said :
"Even though the age range was
from 19 to over 50, and although
some had not been in school for
over 30 years, the papers were
stimulating, thoughtful and often
refreshing."
A survey also revealed that
56 % of the students came from
outside the county in which the
university is situated. There
were bedridden students to whom
examiners were sent, and also
patients in a war veteran's
hospital. Then there were groups
of women who met to view the
lecture and then discuss it.
When a book was mentioned
during the course, libraries re-
ported a rush to borrow works of
that type. In other words, it
was shown that courses reached
a vast segment of the people
*'thirsting for additional know-
ledge".
Many other types of collegeand university television pro-
grammes can be cited, for most
institutions now active in tele-
vision are producing two or
more programmes a week..'Sem-
inar", presented by Columbia
- University and the American
Broadcasting Company, has made
it possible for viewers throughout
the United States to sit in on an
actual college seminar in Ame-
rican Civilization. One of the
oldest and most popular pro-
grammes bringing science to the
television screen is"The Johns
Hopkins Science Review", which
is just celebrating its fifth anni-
versary. This covers in an easy-
to-understand way the whole
alphabet of science from aero-
nautics to zoology, reviewing
each week, all kinds of devel-
opments.
There remains, of course, the
potentialities of television when
used for classroom teaching and-- _. Z !. L_-_'l-' : -demonstration. In many areas 01 teacnmg,
effective exploitation will depend on imaginative
script writing and direction. But where visual
demonstration is the very essence of the com-
munication, the television camera takes over, as
it were, as instructor in its own right.
It is in medical instruction that use of the
camera is, perhaps, most vividly and dramatically
illustrated. Television is able to provide close-up
views of the demonstration of delicate techniques,
previously available only to small student groups
at a time."Closed circuit"colour television is
already being used for this purpose in several
universities. Similarly, students at Cornell Uni-
versity are getting basic physics training from
television screens. They no longer wait in turn
to use microscopes, for a special midget television
camera is trained into one microscope magnifying
the image on the screen.
In these and many other ways both in and out
of their own classrooms, U. S. colleges and uni-
versities have been answering the challenge of
television, discovering and tabulating its assets,
proving by careful experiment some of the major
opportunities it presents to. education and, above
all, bearing in mind the needs of the many
different audiences that can be reached by
educational television.
"Your Health" (presentation of public health
problems) ;"Farm Facts" (demonstrations of
approved farming procedures) ;"Background
Europe" (Hiscory lectures produced with co-
operation of history and government department).
One of the most striking and successful of the
programmes has been an experiment in mass
education through TV entitled :"The Whole
Town's Talking."
It is, in effect, an effort to facilitate the goal
once bespoken by Thomas Jefferson :"I know no
safe depository of the ultimate powers of society
but the people themselves ; and if we think them
not enlightened enough to exercise their control
with a wholesome direction, the remedy is not to
take it from them, but to inform their discretion
through education."
To this end the State College of Iowa station
has literally gone to the people. For a series of
half-hour weekly discussions the station has sent
its mobile van, its camera and its crew to a series
of communities throughout the State. The basic
idea has been to bring together representatives of
an Iowa community to discuss a serious local.
problem, to look at the alternatives, to weigh the
costs, and to decide what action to take.
other people of Cambridge and said :"What do
you value, your children or your business ?", that
was a moment of courage and conviction not
easily forgotten.
It is difficult to measure scientifically the effects
and action of such a programme, but an adult
education worker had this to say :"It has certain-
ly stimulated thinking in a number of commu-
nities... It has developed a better understanding
of the complex problems involved in the school
district organization of Iowa and in the nation...
in general talks on this problem I have not, in
five years, been able to reach as many people as
you did in two hours..."
The experience of Western Reserve University,
Cleveland,, is indicative of the enthusiastic
response universities have had to their offers
of"college courses by television". In August 1951,
the university announced that it would offer
courses in introductory psychology and com-
parative literature. By the close of registration
109 students had paid full tuition and were
enrolled for credit and 674 had bought the
syllabus in order to follow the course.
Many other people, too, followed these formal
courses. Indeed the university estimates that
ODAY over 65
institutions of
higher learning
in the United
States are
participating in
television acti-
vities of one
kind or another.
Broadly speak-
ing, colleges and
universities have
been relating
their work to
television in two
ways : student
training in tele-
vision and ac-
tual television
programme ac-........ -4-..., +. ;....."'".......-..........
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
ESCCOURIER MARCH 1953. Page 13
SCHOOLS THAT TRAVEL ON CAMELBACK
by André BLANCHET
OUTWARDLY there was nothingabout the brown-coloured
goatskin tent to distinguish it
from the others in the Saharan
nomad encampment I was visiting.
But when I stepped inside I found
myself in a well-equipped classroom.
All the basic materials were there-
a blackboard, the china ink pots, a
teacher's cupboard (a reduced model
about the size of a suitcase) and
even a school timepiece, which in
this case was an alarm clock
showing the official time of the chief
town in the region.
There were other similarities
between this nomad school in Mau-
ritania (French West Africa) and
those in Marseilles or Paris. Subjects
on the list of assignments which was
posted up would have been familiar
to most French children. But the
homework had a distinctly local
character.
I was able, for instance, to hear
one of the boys give an informed
account of camel raising. For the
following day he and. his companions
were asked to write a short essay on
the grinding of millet. Again, as I
leafed through their notebooks I
found that arithmetic had also
absorbed some aspects of the way of
life of these Bidanes (the name
means literally'white-skinned
people'). Exercises and problems
were expressed in terms of camels,
young goats and cups of tea.
In short, everything in the school
had been conscientiously adapted to
the surroundings, even down to the
hours of attendance which had been
arranged so as to fit in with Moslem
customs. The children only start
French classes in the morning after
they have had the traditional Kora-
nic teaching, and lessons begin again
in the afternoon after the second
prayers of the day are over.
The most original and studied
adaptation to local conditions,
however, was made in the setting up
of the school itself. A tent is used
because the school must be able to
travel with the tribe, and the tribe
itself is dependent upon the vagaries
of wells and pasturelands. In other
parts of French West Africa, parti-
cularly around the Niger, boarding
schools have for long been opened
for children of nomads, but these
are permanent buildings, not tra-
velling tent schools.
In Mauritania, a few camels are all
that is needed to carry the desert
school with its classroom and its
specially adapted equipment.
Instead of benches, children use
individual stools. The teacher's
cupboard has two handles to facili-
tate transport. As for the desks,
they take to pieces easily and are
drilled with holes so that they can
be lashed firmly to the swaying
back of a camel.
Pupils are therefore able to work
under normally comfortable condi-
tions as long as the nomad schools'
one merciless enemy, the wind, does
not whip up great clouds of sand.
When this happens school has to
stop for the day.
The wanderings of these Maurita-
nian schools depend upon the habits
of individual tribes. The Adrar
school travels as much as 500 miles
a year, but there are others that
move only every four or five months
and then only for a few miles.
Yet, thanks to an official who
probably is the only one of his kind
in the world, these schools do not
move across the desert like drift-
wood on the ocean, abandoned and
unguided. As the schools have
managed to adapt themselves to the
nomad way of life, so a teacher has
found the way to adapt himself to
the task of inspecting them, and to
do so has traded his traditional
master's cane for a camel-driver's
switch.
If you ask him what his needs are,
he will tell you that he only requires
a camel. Incidentally, he is alloted
one from the herd maintained by
the educational service of Maurita-
nia, which is probably the only
educational body in the world to
include a herd of camels on its
inventory.
'"Director of Camp Schools in Mau-
ritania"-this is the official title
of Marc Lenoble, the inspector who
is always on the move. Very few of
the 800 Europeans living in Mau-
ritania-less than one every 400
square miles-have ever crossed his
path. And they, have little chance
of seeing him in St. Louis, the capital
of the territory. Monsieur Lenoble
spent the entire school year of 1951-
52 without once going there.
He is always on the move because
some of the schools which he
inspects are as much as 220 miles
apart-220 miles of desert. From
Adrar to Trarze, from Krakna to
Tagant, Monsieur Lenoble travels
across Mauritania at the majestic,
rolling pace qf his mount, usually
Marc lenoble, the nomad school inspector of Mauritania, spends two weeks out
of every four on camelback journeying between his desert schools. Some of
these are more than 200 miles apart and travel as much as 500 miles each year
Having a tent classroom, the desert school is able to travel with the tribe whose moves depend
on the vagaries of wells and pastures. At the traditional feast that is offered to him, M. Leno-
ble will try to pursuade a chiefto allow the children of the tribe to attend school. During the
discussions, blue-veiled women dance in his honour before the tent (photons Eric Schwab.)
accompanied by an escort provided
in turn by each encampment he
visits.
So it is easy to understand why,
when he goes on leave after spending
nine months gazing at the Saharan
landscape, the wheat-fields in cen-
tral France look green to him even
at harvest time.
On the job, he mounts his camel,
wearing a huge blue turban, wound
as dexterously as that of any Btdane.
If it weren't for his spec-
tacles, there would be no
way of telling he was a
European. His clothing
consists of two garments
- a black, sleeveless
Mauritanian shirt with
the shirt-front and back
held together by loop
rather than seams, and a
white serouel, the flaring
Saharan trousers whose
generous folds form a
omfortable cushion on a
saddle.
This young teacher
has adopted the nomad
life completely. His only
piece of furniture is his
leather saddle, as deep
and comfortable as an
armchair and lavishly
decorated. The only
luggage he carries is a
long, shapeless bag, also
of leather. A guerbe-
a goatskin waterbag-
the most precious pos-
session of any nomad,
because it means the
difference between life
and death, completes his
equipment which, like
his food supply, includes
nothing European. In
his bag, he carries only
dates, tea and sugar, the
standard menu of the
Sahara.
Desert hospitality,
however, breaks the mo-
notony of this austere
diet. When the inspec-
tor visits the chief of a
tribe or camp, he is
doing so as a sort of
ambassador. In the pres-
'nt stage of education
in Mauritania, his job
calls just as much for
persuasion as it does for
inspection and organization. While
he can check up on the standard of
a school in a single morning, he may
spend many hours or even days in
long discussions before he convinces
a chief that the tribe's children
should be in school.
During the interminable meals
that are offered to the desert tra-
veller he will delicately broach the
subject, while servant girls wearing
blue veils dance in his honour before
the tent. Seated cross-legged on a
pile of cushions next to the chief,
he waits patiently while the long
succession of traditional dishes are
placed before them.
Hours go by. They eat, sleep and
talk. The chief reminds him that
the ambition of a Bidane father is
to prepare his daughters for mar-
riage. They are not required to
work and seldom leave their tents.
But Monsieur Lenoble would like
to see some young Bidane girls in his
camp schools. At present, the only
girls going to school in Mauritania
are some 40 in a class at Boutilimit,
the real educational centre of the
territory, (it has a teacher's training
school and nine teachers). There,
the girls live together, far from the
family tent.'
Insistence on the part of Monsieur
Lenoble finally brings from the chief
the promise that, starting the next
day, he will send his own daughters
to the camp school. After all, you
cannot refuse anything to a guest.
But Monsieur Lenoble cannot be sure
that, the next time he passes by, he
will not have to begin the same
conversation all over again, seated
on the same cushions with more
glasses of boiling hot tea in front of
him.
This change from a quiet, pro-
vincial schoolroom in France to the
life of a nomad in the Sahara is now
taken as a matter of course by Mon-
sieur Lenoble.
Summing up his work, he says :
"One of the guiding principles of
education in this territory is that
the child or the adolescent must not
be separated from his social envir-
onment but must be trained to
serve it."This principle, applied
throughout the'camp schools'will
inevitably become a source of
strength to the Saharan mmad
communities.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Page 14. MARCH 1953 UNESCoCOUR
THE SPLENDOUR OF TURKISH ART
EUROPEAN travellers returning
from Turkey in the 16th and
17t centuries had many tales
to tell of the marvels they had seen
at the court of the Sultan-carpets
of a quality unknown in Europe,
brilliantly executed designs in cera-
mics and tapestry and exquisitely
worked metal objects decorated with
ivory, silver, enamel and precious
stones.
In Paris recently, visitors to an
exhibition entitled :"The Splendour
of Turkish Art"have been able to
see some of the examples of an art
which so impressed the travellers of
bygone days and have also felt some
of the wonder these works inspired
in the past.
The masterpieces assembled in the
Musée des Arts Décoratifs testify to
the artistic greatness of the Otto-
by Georges FRADIER
man Empire when it was an already
remarkable and still developing
power. They also recall an event
which, when it happened just five
centuries ago, revealed to the West-
ern world the full measure of the
mighty force approaching it from
the East.
This year, as it happens, is the
fifth centenary of the capture of
Constantinople by Mohammed the
Conqueror-the event which re-
sounded throughout Europe.
Later the King of France was to
seek an alliance with this new force.
The reply sent to François I by Soli-
man I, whose signature may be seen
at the exhibition, has been pre-
served. It runs : ; sultan of sul-
tans, sovereign of sovereigns, the
shadow of God on earth... You, Fran-
coins, King of the country of France,
have sent a letter to my gate, the
haven of sovereigns... All that you
said was told to me from the foot of
my throne and was taken in by my
imperial wisdom... Be not discou-
raged..."A few months later, in
1532,"the shadow of God"was to
lead his armies to the very gates of
Vienna.
This page of history is also brought
to life at the exhibition through the
many masterpieces amassed by a
people long practised in the working
of metals : armour, silver-inlaid hel-
mets, swords with inscriptions in
gold, coats of mail, chamfrains,
Miniature by Abdulcelil Celebi, better known as Levni, painted in The Book of Rejoicing, an 18th century poem.
The manuscript contains 137 miniatures by Levni whose works are still as fresh as the day they were painted.
daggers and pistols adorned with
ivory, silver, enamel and precious
stones. And there, too, are the
luxurious tents in which the military
commanders held audience... and, of
course, the famous carpets.
These carpets have long been
world-renowned. For four hundred
years, in every city in Europe, they
have symbolized the wealth of Tur-
key. From Smyrna (Izmir) they
were shipped to Venice or Bruges,
and Flemish and Italian and other
European artists vied with each
other in reproducing their colouring
and designs. They succeeded so well
that their paintings often afford a
clue to the date of the carpets them-
selves, some of which-the Uchåk
carpets, for instance-are named
after Hans Holbein.
As early as the 13th century, the
workshops of Anatolia were turning
out masterpieces whose praises
Marco Polo sang after he returned
from his epic journey through Asia..
The imperial factories went on to
introduce one refinement after an-
other in the art of carpet-making.
In West and East alike, they exerted
a very real influence, just as did the
weavers and needlewomen of Brusa,
Konia and Scutari, through their
celebrated fabrics. Some of their
finest works which date from the
16th century have been piously pre-
served-among them the precious
caftans of past sultans, which the
Topkapu Sarayi Museum has loaned
to the Paris Exhibition, along with
many other treasures.
But achievements in the art of
working wool and silk must not blind
us to the brilliance of Turkish cera-
mics which are just as important.
The earthenware tiles, originally
designed for use on outside walls and
later for interior adornment of mos-
ques and palaces, are typical of Tur-
kish decorative art. And while it
was from the Moors that the Span-
iards learned the techniques of
ceramics, it was through the Turks
that faience, which perhaps had its
birthplace in Turkestan. was intro-
duced into Italy, and then spread to
the rest of Europe towards the end
of the 15th century.
In Turkish art, ceramics and tap-
estry share a common inspiration
and use the same colour and designs.
In fact the individuality of the best
Ottoman period lies precisely in or-
namentation. This flower-loving
people chose to make its mark in the
history of art by the unwearying
repetition, in various forms, of a
simple stylized theme-the four
flowers, hyacinth, carnation, tulip
and briar-rose.
The artists of Asia Minor, it is
true, always remained faithful to the
complex heritage they owed to their
Byzantine, Mongol, Tartar, Persian
or Arabic origin. But they made it
unmistakably their own, and the four
symbolic flowers, woven, carved or
painted, became their stamp, their
hallmark.
The miniatures, too, make play
with the carnation, with the well-
loved tulip, and with the hyacinth
and rose. More than 200 species of
the carnation were grown in Istanbul
in the 18th century ; the tulip wa. s
considered as a sacred newer, since
the Arabic letters used to write its
name in Turkish are also those which
spell the word God. Another motif
is the cypress, a privileged tree,
which symbolizes the soul rising to
heaven, in death or contemplation.
In point of fact, Turki. sh painters
were long subject to Chinese, Persian
and Italian influences, which they
had welcomed enthusiastically. Yet
they were hampered by extremely
rigid religious scruples in a society
which forbade the hanging of any
portraits on walls, and they had to
confine their essays in portraiture to
the pages of albums and the illus-
tration of poetic or official works.
These limitations did not prevent
the emergence of a most remarkable
school of miniaturists, which in the
15th century produced such master-
piece. s as the famous portrait of
Mohammed II breathing the perfume
of a rose. In the 18th century, this
school acknowledged as its master
the delightful painter Abdulcelil
Celebi, better known as Levni.
Levni'whom was also a poet, was born
at Edirne (Adrianople) and was sent
at an early age to the art school of
the Topkapu palace where nearly
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
ESCoCOURIER MARCH 1953. Page 15
HORSEMAN WITH BOW AND ARROW. XVTH CENTURY MINIATURE FOUND IN AN ALBUM CONTAINING EXAMPLES OF TURKEY'S REMARKABLE CALLIGRAPHIC ART.
Soliman the Magnificent, who was also known as
'the lawgiver' ; XVlth century miniature by Nigart.
Young Lady with veil. XVlllth century painting
by Levni, the leading miniaturist of that time.
Two examples of ancient Turkish calligraphy-a
distinctive field of the country's decorative art.
all his work was done and most of
his miniatures remained ; they are
still intact, as fresh as the day they
were painted.
Besides reflecting a subtle and res-
trained conception of art, an exqui-
site sense of colour, masterly
draughtsmanship and a deliberate
naivety, these minatures are also
nrst-rate documentary material :
they recall the delights of a legend-
ary, yet true-to-life, Istanbul, with
its officers, its dignitaries, its mus-
icians and dancers, and the splen-
dours of its court. Levni, who died
in 1732 lacked neither rivals nor suc-
cessors ; we can only regret that
their work was not as carefully pre-
served as his.
In Turkish decorative art, there is
one field that stands apart ; this is
calligraphy--a field in which the
masters need no distinctive stamp,
no sign by which they can be iden-
tified.
Every culture Moslem has
dreamed of copying the Koran in a
writing worthy of the divine words,
and the Turkish calligraphers pur-
sued this dream with passion, mind-
ful of the saying that"in the last
judgment the ink of writers will be
valued as highly as the martyrs'
blood."
The most careful study has been
devoted to calligraphy, on which
connoisseurs set fabulous prices, and,
until the 20th century, it was used
not only for the adornment of books
and mosques, but in furniture and
rooms of any household rich enough
to afford a beautiful plate inscribed
with a verse from the scriptures,
poetry, or some philosophical maxim.
Calligraphy is an abstract, non-
representational art, in which the
harmony of clear-cut lines and the
balance of the composition stand
supreme, and it plays somewhat the
same role as the symbolic paintings
of India or China, drawing men's
gaze and thoughts to meditation ; it
had a psychological and religious, as
much as an aesthetic significance.
But this note of austerity is sound-
ed in all the products of Turkish cul-
ture, at least in the best of them.
The finest carpets are those made for
prayer, the loveliest faience is that
intended for mosques ; and, among
similar oriental works, they are dis-
tinguished for their sobriety and
purity of line. We need only think of
the monuments in which they were
and still are housed. The architec-
ture of Anatolia, impressive and
rough-hewn, was that of a people
both religious and warlike, and later,
at Brusa and Istanbul, expanded to
opulence ; but its mosques and hospi-
tals were never gaudy or pretentious.
It is perhaps the strength of this
art and its seriousness that should
be emphasized. For, despite its fame,
Turkish art seems to have been long
misunderstood. Indeed, its fame act-
ed as a handicap by starting a vogue
of inferior European imitations. But
exhibitions such as the one now on
view in the Pavillon de Marsan
should prove once and for all the
authenticity and the quenchless vi-
tality of the art of this.'people
without idols."
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
THE art. of bookmaking reached itshighest degree of development in
Turkey during the 15th and
16th centuries. The refined handwrit-
ing called calligraphy and the illumina-
tion of manuscripts were for many
centuries regarded as essential in the
reproduction of religious and poetical
works. The two miniatures published
on this page were produced when Turk-
ish taste had come to lay as much
stress upon the pictorial appearance of
book pages as upon the texts which
they contained. Many of the books
composed consisted of collections of
illustrated pages with no conbected text
running through the volumes. Besides
their remarkable artistic qualities,
many of the miniatures produced at
that time are also first-rate documen-
tary material. Barbaros Hayrattin,
whose portrait we reproduce above, was
one of Turkey's most famous admirals
when his country became an import-
ant sea power in the 16th century.
"Barbarossa" (Red Beard) as he was
known to the people of Western Eur-
ope commanded the fleet which the
then ruler of Turkey, Soliman the Mag-
nificent sent to support François I,
King of France. In this portrait (the
work of Nigari), the Turkish admiral is
shown holding a carnation, one of the
four flowers (hyacinth, tulip, carnation
and briar-rose) which became hall-
marks of Turkish artistic design. Our
second illustration is the famous por-
trait of mohammed II breathing the
perfume of a rose. Mohammed the
Conqueror, as he was known, extended
Turkey's domains well into South-East
Europe and as far as the Crimea. He
is said to have been of a jocular disposi-
tion, to have afforded a generous pa-
tronage to learning and to have been
master of six languages. (See page 14,
"The Splendour of Turkish Art".)
]]>
</page>
</document>
