<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="071148eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Page 2. OCTOBER 1952
UNESCO :
FROM THE UNESCO NEWS ROOM
ED ITO,", IAL OFF ICES.
UNESCO, 19, Ave. Kléber, PARIS-.'
*.
EdiCOr-ln-Chie' : S. M. KOFFLER
\ Enllilh edition : R. S. FENTONEDITORS Fre. ch edition : A. LEVENTIS
/Spanilh edition : 1. DE BENITO
*
Irnp. GEORGES LANG, H. rue Cu ria', Pari..
MC. H 64 A.
Yearly subscription : $2 ; lOs 6<1 ; 500
French francs. Sales agents are list-
ed below. Where none Is listed,
write ta Unesco, Paris.
Argentins : Editorial Sudamehcana,
S. A., Alsina 500, Buenos Aires.
Aasociated States 01 Cambodia, Laos
and Viet-Nam : K. Chantarith. C. C. R.
38, rue Van VoIIenhoven. Phnom-Penh.
Australia : H. A. Goddard Ltd., 255 a
George Street, Sydney.
Austria : Wilhelm Frick Verlag, 27 Gra-
ben, Vienna 1.
Barbados : S. P. C. K. Bookshop (Régional
Office Caribbean Area). Brvad Street,
Bridgetown.
Belgium : Librairie Encyclopédique, 7,
rue du Luxembourg. Brussels IV.
Bolina : Libreria Selecciones, Av. 16 de
Julio 216, Casilla 972, La Paz.
Brazü : Livraria Agir Editora, Rua
Mexico 98-B, Caixa postal 3291, Rio
de Janeiro.
Canada : English speaking : University
of Toronto Press, Toronto. French
speaking : Centre de publications
internationales, 4234. rue de la Roche.
Montréal 34.
Ceylon : Lake House Bookshop. The
Associated Newspapers of Ceylon,
Ltd, Colombo I.
Chile : Libreria Lope de Vega. Moneda
924, Santiago de Chile.
Colombia : Emilio Royo Martin, Carrera
9a, 1791, Bogota.
Costa Rica : Trejos Hermanos, Apartado
1313, San José.
Cuba : Unesco, Centro Régional en el
Hemisferio Occidental, Calle 5,
No 306, Vedado, Havana.
Czechoslovakia : Orbis, Narodni 37,
Prague 1.
Cyprua : Tachydromos, P. O. B. 473,
Nicosia
Denmark' : Einar Munksgaard Ltd., 6
Norregade, Copenhagen, K.
Ecuador : Casa de la Cul'ura Ecuato-
riana, av. 6 de diciembre, Casilla 67,
Quito.
Egypt : La Renaissance d Egypte. 9.
Adly Pasha st., Cairo.
Finland : Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu. Helsinki.
Formosa : The World Book Company
Ltd., 99, Chung King South Rd., Sec-
tion 1, Taipeh.
France : Librairie Universitaire, 26, rue
Soufflot, Paris (S,).
Germany : Unesco Vertrieb für Deutsch-
land, R. Oldenbourg München.
Greece : Elefthéroudakis. Librairie In-
ternationale, Alhens.
Haiti : Librairie"A la Taravelle"1 36,
rue Roux, Port-au-Prince.
Hungary : Kultura, P. O. B. 149, Buda-
pest 62.
India, Orient Longmans Ltd. Bombay,
Calcutta, Madras : Oxford Book &
Stationery Co., Scindia House, New
Delhi. Rajkamal Publications Ltd,
Himalaya House, Bombay 7.
Indoneaia : G. C. T. van Dorp & Co.
NV., Djalan Nusantara, 22, Djakarta.
Iraq : McKenzie's Bookshop. Baghdad.
Israel : Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd..
35, Allenby Road, Tel Aviv.
Italy : G. C. Sansoni, via Gino Ca-
poni 26, casella postale 552, fla-
rence.
Japcm : Maruzen Co, Inc., 6 Tori-Ni-
chome, Nihonbashi, Tokyo.
Lebanon : Librairie Universelle, Avenue
des Français, Beirut.
Luxembourg : Librairie Paul Bruck,
50. Grand-Rue.
Malaycm Federation cmd Singapore :
Peter Chong and Co., P. O. Box 135,
Singapore.
Mexico : Libreria Universitaria, Justo
Sierra 16, México D. F.
Netherlands : N. V. Martinus Ni) hoft,
Lange Voorhout 9, The Hague.
New Zealcmd : South's Book Depot,
8 Willis Street, Wellington.
Nigeria : C. M. S. Bookshop, P. O. Box
174, Lagos.
Norway : AIS Bokhjornet, Stortingsplass
7, Oslo.
Paki. tan : Ferozsons Ltd., Karachi,
Lahore, Peshawar.
Panama : Agenda International de Pu-
blicaciones, Apartado 2052, Panama.
Peru : Libreria Internacional deI Peru,
S. A., Giron de la Union, Lima.
Philippines : Philippine Education Co.,
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo, Manila.
Portugal : Publicacôes Europa-America,
Ltda. 4 Rua da Barroca, Lisbon.
Puerto Rico : Pan American Book Co.,
San Juan, 12.
Spain : Aguilar S. A. de Ediciones, Juan
Bravo 38, Madrid.
Surinam : Radhakishun & Co, Ltd.,
Watermolenstraat, 36, Paramaribo.
Sweden : AB. C. E. Fitzes Kungl. Hov-
bokhandel. Fredsgatan 2, Stock-
holm 16.
Swilzerland : French-Speaking : Librai-
rie de l'Université, 22-24, rue de Ro-
mont, Fribourg. German-Speatdng :
Europa Verlag, 5 Rdmistrasse, Zürich.
Syria : Librairie Universelle, Damascus.
Tanqier : Centre International, 54, rue
du Statut.
Thailand : Suksapan Panit, Arkam 9,
Raj-Damnern Avenue, Bangkok.
Turkey : Librairie Hachette. 469 IstikJal
caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul.
Union 01 Burma : Burma Educational
Bookshop, 551-3 Merchant Street, P. O.
Box 222, Rangoon.
Union of South Alrica : Van Scheik's
Bookstore. Ltd., P. O. Box 724,
Pretoria.
United Kingclom : H. M. Stationery
Office. P. O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
U. S. A. : Columbia University Press,
2960 Broadway, New York.
Uruguay : Centro de Cooperacion Cien-
tifica para la America Latina, Unesco.
BulevC'"Artigas 1320, Montevideo.
Yugoslavia : Jugoslovenska Knjiga,
Marsa'. a Tita 23/11 Belgrade.
Except when ot erw a8 a e. Ber.-
cles appearlng ln th Il issue may be
reproduced wlthout prior permisalon,
prao. lded acknowleogement la gai. en
: 0 the Unesco COURTIER.
* Switzerland : Scientists from ten
countries met in Geneva last month to
discuss thé. question of Science and Mo-
dern Man. Their talks were part of
the 1952"Rencontres Internationales",
a yearly event at which prominent men
of science and letters from various
countries meet to discuss questions of
international interest. Main speakers
this year were Pierre Auger (The me-
thods and limits of scientific know-
ledge), Erwin Schrodinger. (Our
attitude to matter), Emile Guyénot
(Heredity and Freedom), Gaston Bache-
lard (The scientific vocation and the
human soûl). George de Santillana
(Myths and Science) and R. P. Dubarle
(Science, mirror of the destiny of man).
* International : A group of 20 Italian
building trade workers visited Sweden
this summer to study Swedish building
methods, town planning and production
of building materials. The visit was
arranged under Unesco's programme of
group travel tours for workers in Eu-
rope. About 800 workers have already
benefitted from this scheme by which
trade unions, co-operatives and work-
ers'educational associations arrange
the tours and Unesco protides thé in-
ternational travel cost.
* Turkey : An educational film centrem Turkey has been set up with Unesco
assistance. Two Austrian specialists
are helping with the production of edu-
cational films, and Unesco has granted
short-term fellowships to Turkish film
workers for study in Austria.
* Unesco : The World Braille Council
has just been constituted. This is one
of the results of three years of work by
Unesco to bring about uniformity in the
various Braille scripts used by the blinds
throughout the world. Heading the new
Council will be Sir Clutha Mackenzie,
international authority on Braille. The
nine-man international Council will
advise on the application and the main-
tenance of the united Braille system.
* Belgium : The first International
Biennial of Poetry took place last month
at Knokke-le-Zoute, under the auspices
of Unesco and the International PEN
Club. All member states of Unesco were
invited by the Belgian Minister of Pu-
blic Education to participate in this
world meeting of poets.
* France : An international seminar
on workers'education took place this
Summer at the Château de la Brévière
in the Compiègne Forest of France.
The seminar was organized by Unesco
within the framework of its newly set
up International Centre of Worker's
Education. About forty-five delegates
from twenty-five Member States took
part in the seminar, which lasted until
August 23.
* Jamaica : A seminar on adult educa-
tion opened'last month near Kingston.
Il was organized by the University Col-
lege of the West Indies, with the assist-
ance of Unesco. The central theme of
the Seminar was"The role of Adult
Education in the Caribbean". All Ca-
ribbean countries were invited. The
staff of the seminar included members
of the University of Puerto-Rico and
several Unesco experts.
* Turkey : Teaching about the United
Nations and its Specialized Agencies is
now a regular part of the programmes
of secondary schools in Turkey. This
was revealed by the Turkish govern-
ment in a report received in Paris by
Unesco. The schools also are teaching
students about the Universal Declara-
tion of Human Rights, which has been
translated into Turkish and been cir-
culated widely. The government re-
ported in addition, that it had offered
foreign students and professors mode-
rate priced lodgings at student centres
in Ankara and Istanbul during the sum-
mer vacations.
35 STATES SIEN UNESCO
COPYRIGHT PACT
Thirty-five nations signed the
Unesco Universal Copyright Con-
vention last month in Geneva. This
Convention calls for the elimina-
tion of aU formalities of registra-
tion and legal deposit, and their
replacement by the simple imprint
on each copy of the works of the
letter"C"within a circle, accom-
panied by the name of the author
and the date of the first publica-
tion. Another of its features is
that each country gives to foreign
works the same protection as to
works of its own nationals, this
protection lasting for at'least the
lifetime of the author and 25 years
after his death. Translation rights
are also covered : for a minimum
of seven years, authors will have
the exclusive right to publish and
authorize translations of their
works. The Convention will enter
into force three months after its
ratification by 12 States, four of
whom are not members of the
Berne Convention.
* Netherlands : Ninety students from
abroad now studying in the Netherlands
have just made a special study tour to
learn about the United Nations and its
Agencies. The tour was sponsored by
the Foreign Student Service of the
W. U. S.-the World University Service.
The students-most of them were In-
donesians-started in Paris and paid
several visits to Unesco House to study
Unesco's activities at first hand. They
then visited Geneva where they toured
the Palais des Nations, attended sessions
of UN Commissions and learned of the
work of the International Labour Orga-
nization and the World Health Organi-
zation.
* International : World release is
expected shortly of The Open Window,
a novel documentary film in colours
which has been produced through the
co-operation of five European govern-
ments. The film, which was given its
première at this year's Edinburgh Fes-
tival, shows Western Europe's landscape
as seen through the eyes of such masters'
as Constable, Turner, Rubens, Rem-
brandt, Breughel and Watteau. The
governments of Belgium, France, Luxem-
bourg, the Netherlands, and the United
Kingdom helped finance the project
under their cultural affairs agreement,
and famous treasures were freely made
available 1 ; 0 cameramen in the picture
galleries of Amsterdam, Brussels, Ghent,
London, Paris and The Hague. A top-
fiight international team, headed by
Henri Storck, spent a year producing
the film.
* United nations : More than two thou-
sand, five hundred fellowships and other
opportunities for international training
are being offered this year by the United
Nations and the Specialized Agencies. A
UN survey discloses that possibilities for
advanced study in other countries are
at an all-time high. The awards enable
specialists in the various economic, social
and scientific fields to obtain training
abroad in techniques needed in their own
countries.
* U. S. A. : Books which were burned or
banne in Germany and Austria will
be replaced through the CIO's Unesco
Gift Stamp Programme. The Ameri-
can union has produced a special leaf-
let announcing the programme and
appealing for support from union mem-
bers. Workers are being urged to
launch information programmes on the
United Nations and Unesco in connec-
tion with local cainpaigns for the sale
of stamps.
* Unesco : The Egyptian educator, social
scientist and diplomat, Dr. Abbas Am-
mar, has been named director of the
second of Unesco's international fun-
damental education centres. The new
centre will open later this year at Sirs-
eI-Layan, some forty miles from Cairo.
Its purpose will be similar to Unesco's
first centre at Pâtzcuaro, Mexico, where
a hundred students from fifteen Latin
American countries are now being train-
ed as leaders in fundamental educa-
tion. The Egyptian centre will serve
students from the rest of the Arab world
as weIl as from Egypt itself. These
two centres are the first in what ulti-
mately will be a worid-wide network
being established by Unesco for har-
. nessing education to the task of rais-
ing world living standards.
* International : The economic and
social obstacles to the independence of
the creative artist in modern society,
and his relations with the public, the
State and international bodies, were
discussed by delegates from 40 countries
at the International Conference oÏ
Artists in Venice last month. The con-
ference, which was convened by Unesco
in co-operation with the Biennale, was
divided into five sections-visuel arts,
music, literature, theatre and cinema.
It was under the patronage of some cf
the world's most prominent figures in
arts and letters, including Paul Claudel,
Benedetto Croce, Karl Jaspers, Lin Yu-
Tang, Thomas Mann, Henri Matisst.
Gabriela Mistral, Sarvepalli Radakrish-
nan, Igor Stravinsky, Hector Villa Lobes
and Frank Lloyd Wright.
FOR THE NEW
GENERATION
AND THE OLD
A Unesco fact-finding mission is now in Korea to survey educational needs and to draw up a long-... rem
programme for educational reconstruction. The mission left Paris at the end of August on a six-month
visit at the request of the United Nations Korean Reconstruction Administration. ln a statement issued
on this occasion. Mr. J. Donald Kingsley. Agent General of U. N. K. R. A., pointed out'that"it is difficult
to over-estimate the needs for an effective programme of education at every level. The Korean people
must be provided with adequate education and training in primary and secondary sehoois. colleges and
technical schools and in appropriate fields of vocational training. Nothing that we or anyone else
can do towards the reconstruction of the country is more important th an this." (U. N. photo.)
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
: O : OURIER OCTOBER) 952. Page 3
THE UNITED NATIONS
AND
NAT) ONAL LOYALDES
by Jaime Torres Bodet
HE United Nations has been in existence since 1945, No
longer is it just a vague pacifist hope or a sentimental,
intellectual aspiration ; il is the embodiment of a world
order which must be consolidated and perfected and
which must be defended. But a big question mark
remains. Are aIl the governments in a position to
teach the citizens within their own countries the things
they have prüclaimed to the world outside over their
solemn signatures following the horrible havoc of
the last war ? Are they, in other works, prepared to
teach that aIl States enjoy"'equal soverèignty"but that in thé exorcise
of their sovereignty aIl the nations that joined together to form the
United Nations admitted certain obligations-obligations which every
single one of their citizens has the right to know in full, and the right to
know from school age onwards ?
Unesco's activities on behalf of education for living in a world
community are in no sense subversive : What we are trying to do is to
train citizens who will be faithful in their duty to their own country and
who for that very reason will also be loyal to the international obligea-
tions which their country has assumed. The activities of Unesco are
founded on texts that have been officially approved and are publicly
regarded as the guarantee of peace and essential to the progress of
the whole would.
It has never been the purpose of Unesco to turn citizens from their
national'loyalties. Each one of us belongs to a country, and has
towards that country an essential duty of loyalty which we cannot and
should not evade. But each of our countries, in turn, is engaged in
accomplishing a series of acts, in taking a series of measures, without
which the peace, security and progress of ale would constantly be
threatened. Now, these duties are so closely linked together that it
is difficult to draw a line of demarcation between them that would hold
good for everybody, and in every particular case.
Few sentiments are so spontaneous and lasting as love of the
country where we are born. It is perfectly legitimate that we should
long to see it great. But great by what means ? By violence ? By injus-
tice ? By aggression ? It is very obvious that, in extreme cases, the
patriot who does not care a straw for international obligations delibera-
tely accepted by his country is a queer kind of patriot.
Unesco did not make history, but it cannot ignore history. There
are millions of people who yearn to live in a free and peaceful world
community, but who are discouraged by the difficulties and dangers
which beset them. Let none of us underestimate the magnitude of the
obstacles in the way of adjusting national policy and national interest
to the new system óf international co-operation.
Faced with the discouragement that such difficulties might produce,
we adults need to be reminded, our children need to be informed, III
what circumstances and for what purposes the peoples of the world
established the international organization of the United Nations. Yes,
we adults need to be reminded again and again.
Twice in our lifetime the tidal wave of war has s\vept across the
\vorld.'r'wicp. we set our hands to the task of rebuilding the shattered
community of nations and making it secure. We have seen private
hopes and plans of individuals wrecked in the castastrophe of society.
Economic systems have been wrecked, thé norma ! development of
manufacture and commerce has been violently distorted, currencies
have been debased, savings made worthless, rich landes made desolate,
great cities reduced to rubble and to ash.
Twice in our generation young men throughout the world have
been torn from their homes and families to lose their lives or waste
their years in fields of battle while their wives and children lived
or died under a rain of bombs. Each day brought news of death to
countless homes. Twice this tide of destruction has swept through
the \vorld-through the whole world-and given us in common only
sufTering and tears.
Unesco bears no responsibility for the political evolution of the
past, but must nevertheless insist that this evolution should be kno'wn.
Unesco lives in a would where, whether we like it or not, we are aIl
dependent upon one another. Governments are only too sadly and
precisely aware that they are not free to take décisions in accordance
only with their own immediate and limited interests, unless they wish
to expose themselves to aIl kinds of sanctions, or else to expose other
countries to ail kinds of troubles. Unesco considers tbat thé peop ! e
whose destiny  lies in the hands of these governments should know
this, too.
So long as the obligations which hold the United Nations system
together remain valid, it would be contrary to the spirit of democracý
to keep populations in ignorance. To d'o so would mean in practice
that education was being used, not as a means of access to a better
and fuller life, but as a preparation for aggression, or to confirm the
resignation of weakness in the face of aggression.
To teach young people about the obligations which arise out of
the necessity of living in an international community, does not imply
that we should hoodwink them with the promise of an immutable
world order that can be established as if by magic. International
laws, like national laws, always run the risk of being broken by the
most powerful and the most cynica). But although this danger exists
III every country, education has nevertheless continued to include
courses in civics. The more fragile the protection which the law offers
us, the more necessary it is to train people to help ensure that protec-
tion. To say that comprehensive teaching about the machinery, activities
and problems of the United Nations would incite young people to
forget the respect they owe their own country, amounts to saying that
the country in which that teaching took place either did not belong to
the United Nations system or else be) onged tp it only in appearance.
1 do not believe in virtues which lessen a man. He who, out of
so-called love of his country, despises his native tdwn, loves neither
his town nor his country ; and whoever, out of alleged devotion to
some international order, repudiates his loyalty to his own country,does not really love his own country nor the international order he
daims to admire.
In a system of interdependent nations, internationalism can consist
neither in the predominance of one State nor in the development of
a superficial cosmopolitanism. Education for national democracy
accepts as a corollary, and often as a premise, a clear idea of what the
individuat owes to the nation and'what the nation owes to the world :
whence the expression"international understanding"which was used
. in the programme of Unesco in its early days. But understanding
others is not everything. lt has been said that"to understand every-
thing is to forgive everything". But international solidarity depends
less upon forgiveness than upon justice-not a vindictive justice, but
social justice applied to ail sections of the population alike.
It is therefore right that the notion of collective security, as the
United Nations has proclaimed it, that is to say, peace founded on
respect for law, should be universally known and valued, for once the
moment for decision arrives, everyone'will be called upon to pay Hie
price. What sense is there in having a principle for which millions
of men may lay down their lives and which teachers do not mention
in their classes, or else, at the most, resserve for the higher stages of
university education, that is to say, for a minority, a procedure quite
out of proportion to the unanimity with which the entire population
is called upon when the hour of sacrifice strikes.
Nor is it sufficient to adhere simply to the principle of collective
security, for the light which this throws on l'vents shows only one
aspect of international solidarity and that the most severe, the most
urgent today, perhaps, but not the most exalted. For many, collective
security unless it is accompanied by the hope of economic and social
improvement, is no better than the maintenance of an unsatisfactory
order of society. Now, what helps to give collective security its noblest
human significance is the progress which it enables aIl the peoples of
the world to make. The founders of the United Nations solemnly
recognized this ! when they laid it down in the San Francisco Charter
that :
"With a view to the creation of conditions of stability and well-
being which are necessary fOI'peaceful and friendly 1'elations
among notons oosed on respect for the p1'Ínciple of equal rights
and self-determination of peoples, the United Nations shall p1'omote,
(a) higher standards of living, full employment, and conditions or'
economic and social progress and development ;
(b) solutions of international economic, social, health, and 1'elated
problems : and international cultural and educational co-ope1'-
ation : and ;
(c) universal respect for, and observance of, human rights and
fundamental freedoms fM all without distinction as to race,
ses, language or religion,"
Such is the function which, within the United Nations, devolves
principally upon the Economie and Social Council ; such is the role
assigned to the Specialized Agencies ; such is the goal which the
Technical Assistance Programme, with inadequate resources, is trying
to attain. If we really want these organizations and enterprises to
succeed, it is not reasonable to keep schoolchildren in ignorance of the
reasons which led to these efforts being made and of the objectives
which, in the opinion of Governments, justify them ; for schooichildreil
will'become essential collaborators in this work, the builders of the
community of the future.'If Governments cannot recommend that the children in their
schools should be taught what their representatives publicly declare at
the rostrum of the United Nations, whom are we to believe ? The diplo-
mat who makes speeches, or the teacher who keeps silence ? History
is no doubt full of these tragic discrepancies between the man who
commands and the man who teaches. And that is one reason why
history is bathed in tears and blood.
Unesco invites you to think over these matters. Our activities in'
this field are faced with two dangers : one is propaganda, and the other
verbalism-by which 1 mean paying too much attention to the letter
and not enough to the spirit.
We do not want teaching about the United Nations to be a mère
repetition of political slogans more or less happily conceived. te
want the pupil to use his judgment before he expresses an opinion, to
form his own persona ! views and not just to absorb placidly and
automatically the ideas of other people. Nor
have \VI'l'ver wanted to bore young people with (cont, nued on
a purely \"t'l'bal-education for citizenship. No next poge)
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Page 4, OCTOBER) 952
ACTS, NOT TEXTS, TEACH
HUMAN SOLIDARITY
(Continued from previous page.)
doubt it is important to have a tex-
tuai knowledge of the documents
which govern international rela-
tions in the world today ; but soli-
darity is learnt from acts and not
from texts.
It is neither wise noir désirable to
"play"at Collective Security and
Human Rights. School is more
than an introduction to life : it is
a part of live, even an essential part.
It offers numerous opportunities
for putting into practice the funda-
mental principles of ail'thé docu-
ments 1 have been speaking about.
Unless teachers make an effort to
use thèse opportunities, it wiM not
be of much use to g'ive long textual
explanations of aU the Articles in
question. Schoolchildren will al-
ways be intelligent enough to
understand that education which
cannot be translated into actions
and attitudes cannot be applied to
real lifte. And so most of them,
while paying lip-service to equal-
ity, will take care not to extend
the hand to their obscure feUow-
creatures belonging to another race,
another religion, another latitude,
and wearing quite different clothes.
1 think it is necessary that chil-
dren should know about the Uni-
versal Deciaration of Human
Rights. But it is still more neces-
sary that through the way they are
brought up they should learn to
respect the rights of others. We
want children to have such infor-
mation as they need to be good
citizens in the twentieth century.
We are much more deeply
concerned that their education
should develop those predisposi-
tions, those attitudes to their fellow
human beings, that wiU enable
them to enter fuUy and co-
operatively into the life of our com-
munity of peoples on this planet.
There are many ways in which
this may be donc. When 1 am
asked how 1 view the relationship
befween education and peace, 1 say
that although there is some teach-
ing that may promote peace
directly, the essential contribution
of education to peace is indirect.
Inculcation of a doctrine that we
must live at peace with one an-
other, learning by heart the Decla-
ration of Human Rights, and so
forth, is infinitely less important
than growing up so that we do in
fact co-operate freely and equaUy
with other men of goodwill.
A lively sense of the world
T N some countries where this isappropriate to the educational
tradition, direct courses may be
introduced into the curriculum so
that children are taught formally
about the United Nations, about
the Declaration of Human Rights,
and about their own country's rôle
in the community of nations. I,
of course, welcome that. But it is
not thé onty way. Such instruc-
tion runs the danger of being too
isotated, too compartmentalized,
too divorced from the main stream
of study. And precisely because
it appears to be so direct it may
have to be so hedged about with
précautions-deaMng as it does
with questions that often arouse
bitter controversy-that it be-
cornes almost denatured. The
introduction of direct courses in
international affairs by no means
excludes the promotion of acti-
vities, in school and outside, which
will give a youngster a lively sense
of the world in which he lives and
encourage the right attitudes to be
formed.
To the two dangers 1 have just
mentioned, propaganda and ver-
balism, which it is imperative to
avoid, must be added yet another
undeniable difficulty : education
which aims at teaching people to
live as citizens of a world commun-
ity must be, in every country, a
national education. No one can
impose it on anyone else. lt must
above ail be adapted to the condi-
tions of the environment it aims
at improving, and must proceed
directly from that environment. 1
do not hesitate to say that
nowadays it is national needs
which can best open our eyes to
<. he Ileed for an international order.
Respect for each culture
THE goal is the same for us all,but the means we apply to
reach it are not and should not
be identical. \oVe must respect the
originality of each separate culture,
and appreciate the differences
which distinguish one country
from another ; we must try to win
consent but never to force sub-
mission. This proviso is ail the
more important in that the Uni-
versai Declaration of Human
Rights, for instance, is, as 1 have
often said, a programme of action,
and one extremely difficult to
carry out. What State in the
world can boast that it applies
without distinction, and in ail
circumstances, all the principles
proclaimed on December 10, 1948
by the Assembly of the United
Nations ?
If we don't want to discourage
young people from the outset, we
must explain to them that the
application of each one of these
principles represents the laborious,
slow, patient triumph of good over
evil, humanity over cruetty, co-
operation over setfishness. Unless
teaching about Human Rights is
illustrated, as it should be, from
the data of history, geography,
literature, and the fine arts, then
the traditional training in"civics"
will'achieve nothing.
Perhaps 1 should say a littie
more on that point. 1 will use the
terminology to which 1 have
become accustomed as an old hand
at conferences. One might like to
think of Human Rights in terms
of the agenda of a meeting, and
the minutes of the previous
meeting. Thé Dectaration of
Human Rights states part of the
agenda for the human race. It
declares tasks before us, the work
to be done. The task is to win our
young people to accept as their
own this common human agenda.
But perhaps you will say :"The
trouble with these young people
is that they never read the minutes
of the last meeting". The minutes
of this meeting are nothing less
than thé recorded history of
mankind. In those minutes you
will see what good intentions have
been expressed, what aspirations
avowed, what steps have been
taken, what victories achieved,
and alas, what failures recorded.
It is a long story, this quest for
human freedom. Our children
should know it. It is their story.
Let them read the minutes of the
last meeting. And let them then,
with that knowledge and under-
standing, enter as responsible
citizens into the human assembly.
Let them undertake their part in
the never-ending endeavour to
build a community of free men
and women who one and all enjoy
the rights proper to human dignity
in a world of peace.
This article is a summary of the
address made by the Director-Gene-
ml of Unesco at Woudshouten, Near
Utrecht, in the Netherlands, when he
opened a seminar to study and deve-
lop methods of education for living
in a world cornmunity. The serninar,
which was sponsored by Unesco,
lasted four weeks, and was attended
by more than 80 educators from all
parts of the world.
Fisheries development in Jndonesia.
land reclamation in Israël.
-.
TE C H NI CÀ'L
.. l",...,.". -.
ASSISTANCE
WE are accustomed to read from
time to time in our news-
papers of some wonderful
new drug or treatment which is
alleged to be able to cure one or
other of the diseases to which man
is subject. Whatever the headlines
may shout about such a treatment,
we usually find when we read fur-
ther that the doctor or chemist
responsible for discovering and
developing it is very cautious in the
claims that he makes for it. The
true expert is normally very shy of
speaking of results and achieve-
ments, and prefers rather to speak
of probabilities and experiments.
Our world, our civilization, like
the human body, is also subject to
aU kinds of ills. The symptoms are
plain to see ; poverty, hunger ignor-
ance, ill-health, injustice, inequal-
ity, strife. The diagnoses that have
been made of the cause or causes
are various, and the methods of
treatment and cure remain uncer-
tain ; but aU over the world experi-
ments are going on and studies are
being made which it is hoped may
lead the human race forward to
better times.
One of the general signs of the
world's ill condition is the great
unbalance between the standards of
living in difIerent parts of the earth.
This unbalance is no new thing, but
it is more than ever apparent and
dangerous now that the improve-
men t of communications has.
brought people so much closer
together. The fundamental aim of
some of the biggest experiments is
to try to remove this unbalance, to
raise the levels of living in the less
developed parts of the world to those
which apply in the more developed
parts.
One of the methods which may
lead to the attainment of this pur-
pose is through programmes of what
is called"technical assistance".
Basically, these are programmes
whereby skills and knowledge which
exist in any country may be made
available to any other country in
need of them. This exchange of
skills is carried out by the sending
of experts and the offering of train-
ing and study facilities. Like the
name of some new drug, this phrase
"technical assistance"is becoming
familiar in the world.
It is good that this should be so,
provided that two things are under-
stood : first, that technical assistance
is not new, and second, that it is
not a proved panacea for the world's
troubles. Since the beginnings of
man's history, contacts between
peoples have led to the exchange of
skill and knowledge to mutual
advantage. Explorers and pioneers,
merchants and missionaries, have
all been the means, even if often the
unconscious and indirect means, of
furthering what we now calI tech-
nical assistance. The only new
development is the attempt to pro-
vide this assistance under systema-
tically planned programmes.
There are several of these pro-
grammes in action today. Some of
them operate under arrangements
whereby one advanced country alone
provides the needed assistance, as
under the U. S. Point IV programme,
or the development programmes
through which certain European
nations are trying to help forward
the dependent countries for which
they are responsible. Other pro-
grammes are organized by groups of
nations acting together, as under
the Colombo Plan. But the tech-
nical assistance programme which
has the widest participation is the
newest, that of the United Nations.
The United Nations Expanded
Programme of Technical Assistance,
as it is formally called, is like all
the others in what it is trying to
do. Its original quality and true
importance lie mainly in the fact
that it is an experiment in orga-
UNESCO :'
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
OCTOBER i952. Page 5
Fundamental education at Patzcuaro, Mexico.
Training of skilled labour in Pakistan.
Small industries development in Burma.
Fighting disease in Sarawak.
Building new roads in Greece.
Science teaching in Libreria.
...",-.,.,,-,-,...,
A United Nations experiment in
: :',"-'. ;  ;".'. :".- :, ;'.. .-.''.-.."'...
pooling world skill and knowledge
nizing technical assistance on a
really broad, international basis. If
this experiment shows results, it will
help to prove not just that technical
assistance is a good way of treating
the world's ills, but also that it is
really possible for the nations to
work together constructively for the
common good.
The practice of technical assist-
ance is not unlike that of medicine.
A good physician does not treat
diseases, he treats people. He cannot
expect to cure the body of his
patient if he ignores the mind. But
while concerning himself with the
whole man, he may want more
expert advice on a specifie problem,
and so he calls in a specialist. Simi-
larly, an attempt is made under the
United Nations Technical Assistance
Programme to diagnose the needs
of a country as a whole, and, follow-
proves major projects, and allocates
funds to the member organizations.
But it is the specialized agencies
themselves which study the needs of
Member States in detail and act on
the requests of governments by fur-
nishing foreign specialists and by
arranging for training and study
facilities in other countries.
The Technical Assistance Pro-
gramme is llnanced by the contri-
butions of Member States, furnished
in proportion to their resources and
voted at an annual Technical Assist-
ance Conference. At the first con-
ference in June 1950, slightIy over
$20, 000, 000 was pledged by 50 na-
tions for the programme from
July 1, 1950 to December 31, 1951.
A similar sum was voted for 1952 at
the second conference last Novem-
ber.
According to a recent report of
by Michael HOWSON
ing up this diagnosis, to provide the
appropriate specialized assistance.
Since the Programme came into
operation in July, 1950, an organiza-
tion has grown up to meet its
requirements. Directly responsible to
the U. N. Economie and Social Coun-
cil for the programme is the Tech-
nical Assistance Board. The Board
consists of the heads-or their
representatives-of the U. N. Tech-
nical Assistance Administration and
of a number of the Specialized
Agencies. In addition, the Inter-
national Bank, the International
Monetary Fund, and other Agencies
such as UNICEF, although not
members of the Board, assist in
projects undertaken under the Pro-
gramme.
The Technical Assistance Board
is the central organ which reviews
programmes, arranges for joint
action between organizations, ap-
the Technical Assistance Board,.'by
the end of 1951, some 717 technical
assistance experts in a wide variety
of Seids of knowledge have been
sent out under the expanded pro-
gramme to some 75 under-developed
countries and territories. Some
845 fellows drawn from some 69
countries and territories had been
placed in technical training institu-
tions or had otherwise been provid-
ed with training, study or observa-
tion facilities, in countries other
than their own. By the end of March
1952, an additional 227 experts had
been recruited and 232 additional
fellowships had been awarded."
Since it is in relation to the pro-
blems of the world as a whole that
the programme is conceived, its
scope is naturally very wide. Detall-
ed descriptions of a few of the pro-
jects that are being undertaken are
pul51ished elsewhere in this issue.
The doctor can do hardly any-
thing without the co-operation and
goodwill of the patient. In the same
way, the foreign experts sent out
under the Technical Assistance Pro-
gramme can do hardly anything
without the co-operation and good-
will of the people among whom they
work. No assistance is given unless
a request for it is first received from
the government concerned. By
making a request, a government not
only expresses a wish to have expert
advice and assistance in some neld
which is considered to be important
to the future of its people, but also
implies that it is already engaged in
development in this field or is will-
ing and able to undertake such
development. If, for example, a
government asks for expert assist-
ance in improving its railways, this
implies that resources, financial,
material and human, are available
for railway development. If a go-
vernment asks for a fellowship for
one of its citizens to study welfare
services in a foreign country, this
implies there will be a job for that
person in a field of social welfare
when he or she returns home. In
fact, nearly aIl governments have
their own plans for economic deve-
lopment, and projects of technical
assistance are usually designed to
fit into such plans.
By far the greatest effort for de-
velopment has to be made by the
people of the requesting country
which, in addition to making its
contribution towards the funds of
the Technical Assistance Pro-
gramme, is usually devoting to its
own internai development, resources
for larger than those furnished from
outside.
OfficiaI co-operation is thus assur-
ed for technical assistance projects.
But this alone is not enough. Fun-
damentally, technical assistance im-
plies co-operation between people.
Much must depend on the spirit
in which the advice and instruction
are given and received at the work-
ing level. However expert a foreign
specialist may be in his own subject,
his function is not to present to the
people of the country where he is
working, a ready-made plan which
they have merely to put into affect.
Though, in technical matters, the
foreign adviser may know all the
answers, his ftrst important task in
any country is to ask many ques-
tions. He and his local counterparts
must alike tackle their joint pro-
blems in a spirit of, willingness to
learn.
The Technical Assistance Pro-
gramme has now been in operation
for more than two years ; but except
in the cases of a few projects which
have limited and short-term pur-
poses, it is too soon to attempt to
assess thp over-all results. The
whole Programme is essentially a
long-term experiment, or rather a
series of experiments. Although the
problems which are being faced
urgently need solution, nevertheless
neither those who have some active
part in the Programme, nor others,
(including the general public of the
would), who have the responsibility
for supporting it, must look for
immediate superftcial results. The
experiments have barely started.
The nations who have started
these experiments must see that
they are carried through to conclu-
sions still far ahead. Financially,
the Programme is a small one,
though it is the expressed view of
the ECOSOC that it should expand.
In its special international quality,
however, it is of immense import-
ance. Some of the experiments will
fail ; some will only partially suc-
ceed ; others will bring visible and
sensible benefits. The results will
aIl depend on the extent to which the
efforts of those concerned meet the
needs of the peoples of the world
whom they are designed to help.
) URIER
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Page 6, OCTOBER 1952
AFGHANISTAN
CHOOSES TO
PROSPER
THE modern world encounters aworld of 2, 000 years ago on the
Lataband Pass which leads to
Kabul, the capital city of Afghani-
stan, a country now undergoing
great changes. Thé road climbs up
the sides of the mountains, with
precipitous drops, hazardous bends
and a surface which is little better
than a dirt track. The tribes move
in familles-men, women and
children with aIl their goods and
chattels, their tents, their rugs, their
pots and pans and jars ; tethered
poultry balanced on the backs of
asses ; and children strapped ta the
humps of camels.
Into this ancient world the 20th
century has charged with clamorous
horns. Lorries driven by frontier
tribesmen, who have become the
freight carriers, dispute the right
of way with the camel trains and the
burdened asses.
Beyond this pass and the grey,
barren déserts and mountains lies
Kabul, where at night the two
mountains which divide the city are
picked out in a festoon of electric
lights, proclaiming to the pastoral
peoples around that the Technical
Age has corne to Afghanistan.
But only just. For this is a
country the natural resources of
which are virtually undeveloped.
Here more than 90 per cent of the
population is agricultural and of
that, most are pastoral nomads.
The methods of agriculture are pri-
mitive, and there are few skilled
industrial workers except those in
two recent cotton factories.
The few roads which exist tear to
pieces the modern vehicles which
use them. There are no railways,
and traffic between north and south
Is practically impossible because of
the great barrier of the Hindu Kush.
Coal, which is accessible by simple
mining, is scarcely worked, and the
mountainsldes are continually strip-
ped of any vegetation usable as fuel.
Thus, Afghanistan, which even
superficial surveys have shown to be
potentially wealthy, is unques-
tionably an under-developed coun-
try, and to remedy this state of
affairs the Royal Afghan Govern-
ment requested the United Nations
for help even before the Expanded
Programme was begun.
The original United Nations Mis-
sion sent to the country agreed with
the Government on a programme of
technical assistance, whose main
emphasis was placed on projects by
which changes within the compet-
enCe of the people themselves could
produce benefits, pending the more
ambitious development programmes
requiring large-scale foreign help.
For example, the agriculture of
Afghanistan could be revolutionized
by modern methods. In a country
which has a low rainfall, this would
involve big irrigation schemes and
the discovery and development of
underground water supplies ; that
will corne. But a minor revolution
could be produced immediately by
the introduction, not of advanced
farming technology, but of the
simplest improved devices-like the
hoe or the scythe.
One of the first things which FAO
did under its expanded technical
assistance programme in Afghani-
stan was to introduce a demonstra-
tion team for hand-tools. Afghani-
stan is mainly mountainous, the
land is steep and the holdings
small, so that mechanized farming,
even if it were not too costly for the
farmers, could have only limited
value. The only tool which the
Afghans had for mowing was a pri-
mitive sickle with the blade set at
right angles to the handle, which
has to be used while the farmer is
sitting on the ground and grasping
the corn or grass in his left hand.
A Swiss FAO farm implement
expert, accompanied by two assist-
ants experienced in the scything of
high pastures, gave a series of de-
monstrations in harvest areas of
scythes, hoes, forks and hay rakes,
previously unknown in Afghanistan.
A jeep and the tools were provided
"If you choose to die", an old Afghan saying went,"go to Kundus."Today,
with thé région c ! eared of malaria and agriculture and industries developing,
the saying is justifìably changed to"If you choose to prosper, go to Kundus".
will be trained for a year in Switzer-
land in the use of hand-tools on
mountain farms. By extending this
work during 1952, it is estimated that
the productivity per man can be
increased by as much as five times.
Because of its widespread pos-
sibilities, this programme, which
appeals to the local farmer and
employs the local blacksmith, can
(U. N. photos by Eric Schwob.)
Afghanistan is a remarkable example of how a country is using expert help from
abroad to further its development. ln one season WHO technicians dusted
entire population of Kabul with DDT and prevented annual typhus epidemic.
by the Austrian Government as a
contribution to FAO's work.
The team was able to prove to the
Afghan peasants that a man could
mow many times as fast with the
scythe as with the local sickle.
About 500 scythes have already been
distributed, some of them to the
students of the school of agriculture,
who, after being trained in their
use, have taken them to their own
villages in remote parts of the
country. A fellowship has been
awarded to an Afghan student who
Impressive results have been achleved ln tlght against dreaded rinderpest cattle
disease. Last year, 1, 000, 000 cattle were protected by officia) inoculation and
isolation schemes that were widely supported by the cattlemen themselves.
be of far greater service to Afghan
agriculture than any immédiate
attempt to introduce modern ma-
chinery. Even if lt were though
advisable to introduce tractors and
the like, it would mean not only con-
verting the peasant farmer to un-
familiar machines and training me-
chanics, but also meeting the costly
use of petrol, which has still to be
imported at prohibitive expense.
Another example of how simple
changes can produce immeasurable
benefit is the case of Karakul. Ka-
rakul, the fur of the lamb, is Af-
ghanistan's most important source
of foreign exchange, and gives em-
ployment to over 1, 000, 000 people.
Before 1934 the sheep population
was in a flourishing condition. In
that year, when the karakul mono-
poly was started, only 1, 100, 000 pelts
were exported from the country.
In 1945 this had risen to 3, 200, 000,
but in the following year it had
dropped to 1, 700, 000. This drop was
brought about by bad weather, poor
food and sheep disease.
If, therefore, the technical assist-
ance which FAO is rendering under
its karakul improvement programme
succeeds, it will be providing an
increase in reserve which could be
put to improving the agricultural
conditions of Afghanistan, and also
to helping build up its industrializa-
tion.
The story of karakul, moreover,
provides an interesting example of
how inter-active technical assistance
can be, and how even a malaria
control scheme affects a country's
dollar-earning capacity.
There is an old Afghan saying,
"If you choose to die, go to Kundus."
Kundus is the centre of a large and
fertile area between the Hindu Kush
and the Oxus River. Eight hundred
years ago Genghis Khan destroyed
the canal civilization which had cul-
tivated this area. When the irriga-
tion system collapsed, the malaria
mosquitoes took possession. Since
that time repeated efforts to recover
this area failed because the people
were either killed off by malaria or
Sed.
In 1950, a WHO team set up it
headquarters at Kundus, and within
two years had effectively cleared the
region of malaria. This enabled the
expansion of a large cotton growing
belt and the recruitment of workers
for a cotton mill. While FAO is
helping to improve the yield and
quality of the cotton produced, the
new industry is producing the cotton
seed cake which can supply thp
winter feed of the karakul and help
reduce the death rate. This, with
the other help which the interna-
tional experts are able to give on
sheep diseases and the like, will help
to reduce the death-rate of sheep,
which is as high as 40 per cent in a
season.
With malaria effectively control-
led, the Northern Provinces can now
be opened up, not only for agricul-
tural purposes, but for industrial
development.. In this area lies a
potential oilfield. One of the first
requests agreed between the Govern-
ment and the United Nations was
for an oil geologist. This year, plan"
for the exploitation of the oil re-
sources of this region are going
forward. The old saying has now
been modified :"If you choose to
prosper, go to Kundus."
The malaria control scheme had
other secondary effects. In the off-
season for malaria, the WHO team
moved into the cities of Kabul and
Kandahar, dusted the entire popu-
lation with DDT, stopped the tribes-
men as they came into the town and
dusted them too, and thus prevent-
ed a typhus epidemic which had
recurred annually in Afghanistan.
The success of malaria-control and
typhus-control made a great impres-
sion on the people of Afghanistan,
and led to embarrassing demands
for immediate spraying of the whole
country.
Though agriculture is the central
problem, the services which are
being made available under the
technical assistance programme for
Afghanistan include experts in eco-
nomic planning, public administra-
tion, statistics and industrial en-
gineering ; oil drilling, telephone and
telegraph, underground water, cot-
tage industries, productivity and
labour legislation, and cotton cul-
ture ; civil aviation, oil technology,
health education in aIl its fields,
epidemiology, social medicine, ge-
neral and technical éducation and
teacher training.
This expanding programme is
closely correlated with the U. S.
bilateral programme, which, among
other things, includes help in
opening up the country's mineraI
resources.
Afghanistan is a remarkable
example of how a country is avail-
ing itself of expert help from aIl
corners of the world. The public
health engineer is from Haiti, the
woman expert on children's diseases
from Finland, the doctor in charge
of the malaria control is an Indian,
and the mission has included Bri-
tish, American, Dutch, Scandinavian,
French, Belgian and Austrian parti-
cipants.
UNESCC
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
NEW HIGHWAYS lN
THE SKIES OF IRAN
OCTOBER) 952. Page 7
A,'airman entering Iran for the first time,
across the dangerous"hump"of the
Zagros Mountains, will be surprised by
the strange la dscape around Teheran
the capital. He will see the ground pitted
with curious holes, running in straight hnes
which criss-cross each other.
The pits are the vertical shafts of the
horizontal wells, or banats, a Persian water
system which is supposed to date back 5, 000
years. The horizontal wells are mined along
the underground water courses back to their
sources in the mountains. Some of them
are 30 miles long and the qllallat miners keep
their bearings underground by means of
a primitive lodestone compass which, the
Persians claim, preceded the marine compass
by. centuries and was therefore thé ancestor of
the navigational aids which made ais travel
possible. So, in a way, the services which
ICAO is providing for Iran is a return for the
"technical) assistance"which the Persians
rendered to aviation in remote history.
Iran today stands in need of aIl the assistance
which ICAO can give it because it has a
communications problem which is one of the
biggest obstacles to its development. This
country is a vast territory, as big as France,
Italy, Norway and Spain combined, but with
about a tenth of the population of this
European area. It is mainly a high plateau,
surrounded by battlements of mountain ranges.
About 70 per cent of the country's area consists
of mountains, forests and salt desert. In the
whole country there are only 17, 000 miles of
roads and 2, 000 miles of rai) ways. In thé
north, the mountain passes and railway tracks
may be blocked for weeks by heavy faits of
snow. Isfahan, the former capital of the
country and one of its three biggest industrial
centres, is not sernd by a railway at aH, and
its connection with the capital is by a
road across the desert. GovernmentaIly and
economically the various parts of the country
are isolated by poor communications. LHtimate
development will de pend on ground traffic
arteries, but an urgent problem is how to
establish communications within the country
by air and how to maintain and extend the air
services to neighbouring countries. In this
connection, the country is subject to con-
siderable climatic variation, so that air safety
is a priority problem.
In response to a request from the Govern-
ment of Iran, ICAO agreed to send an expert
to assist Iranian airways in improving their
organization and service. Simultaneously, a
team of experts would be provided to help
the Department of Civil Aviation to train its
personnel in the operation of ground facilities
and services. The team began to operate in
Apri ! 1951. Classes in radio techniques have
been supplemented by regular on-the-job
training and by expert advice on setting up,
operating and maintaining radio equipment.
Air traffic control classes were organized, and
advanced instruction in actual operation of
control towers has been given to the existing
staff.
One of the important functions of the
ICAO mission was to produce meteorological
observers and forecasters and to train and post
observers in various parts of the 628, 000 square
miles of country which has not so far had a
proper weather service. The weather-reporting
stations are beginning to form an effective
network and to provide the forecasters with
the weather data indispensable to safe ftying.
In conjunction with this practical training
the mission has been able to advance its
advisory functions through a General Commis-
sion which the Government has set up, whose
chairman is the head of the mission. This
operates through six sub-commissions con-
cerned with aircraft search and rescue work ;
communications and radio navigational aids ;
meteorology, climatology and statistics ; opera-
tions ; training, licensing and aero clubs ; and
air worthiness.
The mission, which included four experts
from the Netherlands, two from Norway and
one from the United Kingdom, and one stateless
expert, has been able to help in other directions,
and especially in the fields of organization and
operation. Apart from this ICAO has been
able to provide three fellowships by which
Iranians can gain experience abroad in aero-
nautical engineering and electronics.
Since the ICAO mission began its work in
A pril HI ;) ! the economic situation of the
country has deteriorated, thus making it
difficult for the Department of Civil Aviation
and Iranian Airways to take full advantage of
the mission's advice and work. ln spite of
this handicap, the work of the mission has
continued with results which encourage the
hope that when economic conditions improve
the Government will be better able to provid''
the necessary support for civil aviation. At
least it will have trained personnel.
Iran has only 17, 000 miles of roads and 2, 000 miles of railways. Ultimate development will depend on both ground traffic arteries and air communication networks.
With technical assistance, Iran is beginning to form a chain of weather-reporting stations (similar to one shown below) which are indispensable for safe flying.
. OURIER
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Ten countries have joined together at F. A. O. Rice Research Institute in India in a comprehfSive
for i mproving the yields of rice. For millions of Asians, their experiments are a matter of[e an
Women pounding rice is a familiar sight in Sarawak.
Thai airl aathers basic food of half the world's people,
lu thé Terai area of India at thefoothills ofthe Himalayas, U. N. agencies are working to spurfood production. From newfields, Terai now wrests its harvests of rice. Photos show
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
 ! Cf
THE BREAD OF ASIA
FOR hal ! the world's population, the experiments at the Rice-Re-search Institute at Cuttack, in Crissa, India, have a concern which
is more than academic. For many, it is a matter of life and death.
Seventy per cent of the Asian peoples depend on rice as their staple
diet, and while the population has increased by over ten per cent in the
past twelve years, the production of rice is still below pre-1940. The
region, as a whole, instead of being an exporter of food has. become a
net importer of food, depending on bread-grain from North America
and even rice from Egypt and Brazil. Countries like India are poised
on the verge of rice-famine.
Rice-production depends on methods which are difficult to change
and, even though the peasants may recognize the value of new ideas in
cultivation, it takes time for them to learn new skills and modify tra-
dition. On the other hand, better seeds, if they are available, can de-
monstrate their value and carry conviction in a single season. If, there-
fore, the plant-breeders can produce varieties of rice which can give
higher yields from existing acreages, they can bring about an increased
food-production which improvements in the rice-husbandry will further
enhance.
At the Cuttack Rice Re. search station, with the Indian Government
as host and FAO as the sponsor, ten countries-India, Pakistan, Burma,
Ceylon, Indonesia, Indo-China, Thailand, Malaya, the Philippines and
Japan-are combining in a comprehensive scheme for improving the
yields of rice.
Just what that means can only be gathered by comparison between
the yields of differents countries. Japan, for example, gets 2, 352 lbs.
of rice per acre, while the Indian yield averages less than a third of that.
India has the largest acreage in the world under rice, but she has rela-
tively the lowest production. Its 350 million people live continually on
the edge of famine because of rice shortages.
If, then, India could increase her rice yield per acre, if not to the
prize-crops of Japan but only to that of China, which is double, she
could have 25 million tons more rice per year from its present acreage.
The reason for the vast difference between the yields of Japan and
those, not only of India but of the whole of South East Asia, is the fact
that the varieties of rice are different. One is'japonica'and the other
is'indica'.
The following figures show the comparatives average yields in Ibs.
of rice per acre of the two types :
Japonica. indica.
s show harvest being loaded oncartand carriedon peasants'headsfor sacking and weighing at mit).
Apart from the rice-strain, there may be other factors at work, such
as methods of cultivation, but the disparity between the countries with
high yields and those with lower yields is apparent enough to suggest
that japonica has definite advantages.
It is not just a simple matter of substituting one variety for the other.
Japonica is the rice of high latitudes and indica is the rice of tropical
and equatorial Asia. There can be no direct transfer ; the process can
only be by hybridizing the two varieties and that in terms of the local
adaptations of indica in the various countries. Nor is hybridization a
simple process, because japonica in the long daylight of higher latitudes
flowers within 100 days and indica in regions of shorter daylight takes
four to six months.
To achieve cross-fertilization, both have to flower at the same time
and at Cuttack, the process is speeded up by exposing the plants to
artificial light. Experts do the pollinization by hand, and the breeding
rice is protected by paper bags. This, has to be done with individual
plants of each of the different strains from the varied natural conditions
of the participating countries. From the first 60, 000 plants pollinated,
12, 500 seeds were collected-again by hand.
AU kinds of variables complicate the task of finding an effective
hybrid. For example, a cross-breed may produce a magnificent head
but the head will be too heavy for the straw, while straw may be sturdy
at the expense of the head. Others may incline to the japonica parent,
with its preference for a cooler climate and long daylight. Others may
develop quite usefully under Indian conditions and be unsuited for
Javanese cultivation.
There can, therefore, be no standardization but only a systematic
process of adaptation and acclimatization. This takes time, but the
rewards are high. If, for example, a suitable hybrid could be produced
for India it is (theoretically) possible to double the rice yield from the
existing acreages, which, quantitatively, at least, would transfprm the
precarious food situation of India.
The Central Rice Research Station which houses the project is an
All-India centre in the State of Orissa. The International Rice Com-
mission wanted to promote this hybridization work for the benefit of
the whole region. The Government of India has made available the
necessary land and other facilities. The extension of the work is in
the plant-breeding stations of the countries concerned.
FAO's function under Expanded Technical Assistance has been to
provide modest finances for the labour costs of technical personnel, who
are under the direction of the director of the station (who has the status
of consultant without remuneration) and ta arrange for the operation
of a centre there for the training of fellows from member countries of
the International Rice Commission.
The Government of India is providing the director of the centre and
FAO the associate director and certain other instructors, as weIl as any
essential equipment. The Colombo Plan is providing buildings which
will be of permanent value ta the centre as weIl as housing those con-
cerned with the immediate programme and the work of the international
training scheme.
This. is an example of how the enterprise of one government in the
creation of such a centre, the recognition of a common interest through
the International Rice Commission, plus the discreet use of Technical
Assistance funds, can bring together a whole group of countries on a
regional basis. The results, on an optimistic assessment, may transform
the rice situation in South-East Asia and the Pacific and benefit
hundreds of millions. Short of that fulfilment, it still has an Immediate
value in focussing the attention of many nations on a common problem
and demonstrating the value of co-operative investigation.
Java 1, 034
rhailand"'"''''''''''''888
: 816
nia 772
ndo-Chma.............. 716
'philippines 703
Japan 2, 352
Egypt 1, 890
Korea,,..,.,,,..,,,...,,,, 1, 593
Chine1, 549
U. S. A................... 1, 390
This Indian worker is extracting rice with pedal thresher.
Beneath microscope, rice pollen is examined at Institute.
htSive scheme
) ffe and death.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Page 10. OCTOBER 1952
THE three provinces of Libya (Tripolitania, Cyrenaica,
Fezzan), are islands in vast seas of sand. Racially
and geographically, the Libyan population of one
and a quarter million people is divided into several groups
and have never before constituted an independent political
unit ; they have been united on) y as port of the larger
empire of foreign conquerors. Over a fourth of the poputa-
tion consists of wandering desert tribes. Only one in ten
of the people is literate.
It is doubtful whether Libya can be called an underdeve-
loped territory. Historically, it is an over-developed territory,
in the sense that large tracts of the country are a dust-
bowl created by greedy development. These are the areas
which supported a considerable colonial population and were
the granaries of Greece and Rome from 500 B. C. to 500 A. D.
Through the neglect to maintain the wells, cisterns and
trees on which this agricultural prosperity had been based
and after the collapse of an effective administrative orga-
nisation, thé depradations of the nomadic tribes which
replaced the system of cultivation by indiscriminate grazing
and deforestation, this area was largely reduced to desert.
Today Libya is a deficit area to a degree matched by few
other countries. Atthough govemmenta) services are on a very
modest level, the deficit of the ordinary administrative budget
exceeds 30 per cent. There are deficits in the budgets of
ail three provinces and most of the municipalités. There is
a deficit in the balance of trade of ail three provinces, with
a consequent deficit of about 40 per cent in the balance of
payments. This, in the recent past and present, has been
met not by receipts from foreign investments, but by grants-
in-aid and military spending by foreign powers. The wheat-
growing project at Barce operates at a deficit ; so does the
tobocco-growing scheme.
The agriculture of the Fezzan incurs o deficit ; so does the
power plant at Tripoli, and its harbour, and its gas works,
and the raitwoys. The Italian colonization scheme, heavily
subsidized by the Italian taxpayers during the Italian occupa-
tion, still operates at a deficit. Thus the Libyan economy
cannot maintain even the present low standard of living, which
averages in income per capita not much more than $30 o year.
Arresting), 000 years of decay
THE United Nations has eccepted its clear responsibility
for assisting the independent state it created by an
act of the General Assembly to achieve higher standards
of living and social welfare as a member of the family of
nations. This carries with it the recognition that there are
no undisclosed natural resources waiting to be developed, and
that Libya is not only a country with no highly developed
industry-it is a country with no firm basis for industrial
development. It has no water power, no coal, no petroleum
and no commercially-exploitable minerai ores, so far as is
known.
Development must necessarily be inclined toward the
establishment of light industry to process agricultural mote-
rials. The pressing problem, therefore, is one of arresting
the decay which has been going on for over 1, 000 years, of
regenerating its agriculture and reconstituting its forests and
. vegetation. The Libyan potential lies in the recovery of its
desert and developing the skills and resources of its people.
United Nations and specialized agency experts assisted
the U. N. Commissioner in Libya, the Libyan Provisional
Government and the Administering Powers (United Kingdom
and France) to lay the foundation for the new state. Experts
of the United Nations, FAO and the International Monetary
Fund advised the Commissioner and the main interested
Powers on the establishment of a Libyan currency and on two
Libyan economic and social development financing agencies,
one to attract grant-in-aid funds from friendly governments,
the second to attract governmental loan capital. These
agencies have been established by Libyan law. They can
consider on) y proposa) ! from the Government for the financing
of projects approved by the Government.
Experts of the United Nations have also assisted the
Commissioner in preporing the Libyan budget for 1952, the
establishment of a civil service, a provident fund law and
other fundamental public administration acts. The result was
that, on independence day, Libya had in operation, or pro-
jected for the immediate future, a governmental organization
in the administrative, economic and financial spheres, a plan
for the basic operation of the new Government prepared in
full co-operation with representatives of the inhabitants of the
country which would assure the continuing operation of the
governmental machinery.
This plan had already provided for a progressive transfer
of nearly ail powers to the Provisional Libyan Government 50
that the transfer to the government on the day of independ-
ence was only for matters relating to foreign affairs and
defence.
The U. N. Resident Technical Assistance Representative
(who is also personal representative of the Secretary-Generqt)
has an important role in the Libyan picture. ln addition to
the normal functions of such an officiât, he is available to the
Government for consultation regording economic, financial and
social development matters. He is a member of the Libyan
economic planning committee, sits on the board of manage-
ment of the Libyan Development Agency, and serves as
technical assistance adviser of the Libyan Government in the
Libyan Finance Agency. Thus the Resident Representative
has un important role in assisting Libya at 011 stages of its
economic and social development programme.
The problems of the new Government and Administration
which came into existence last December are immense, despite
ail of the above-mentined planning which gave Libya what
was probably the most planned and orderly transition to
independence in modern times through a combination of nor-
mal United Nations and technical assistance effort. The
take-over of the machinery of Government is a major
undertaking in a country which has so seriously lacked edu-
cational facilities for so long.
Great strides in the education of the indigenous population
were made by the administering powers. Now there are
50, 000 pupils in schools, although only about 1, 100 are in
secondary schools. Education in the Fezzan was even more
difficult, because there were no indigenous teachers ; it is dif-
ficult to recruit foreign teachers to serve in this bare and
isolated region.
Every small number of leaders and government officiats
received an adequate training abroad before the last war. A
few who were refugees during the colonial period have return-
ed. There is, however, on overall shortage of people even
with the elements of éducation. Yet somehow the adminis-
tration has to recruit, not only higher civil servants, but cJerks
and typists and postmen capable of reading an address. It has
to find the staffs for new organizations and institutions
without which the first steps in devlopment are impossible. It
has to contemplate somehow, sometime, establishing a univer-
sity.
To futfi) its aspirations as a nation, therefore, Libya needs
ail the assistance it can get in practically every aspect
of civil development. On behalf of the Technicat Assistance
Board, du ring 1951 a general economic appraisal and subse-
quently recommendations for an economic and social deve-
lopment programme for Libya were produced for consideration
by the Government when it took over responsability for the
affairs of the country.
Skill-'the major untapped resource'
E VEN before the transfer of authority, however, the U. N.
agreed with the British and French Governments, then
responsible for administering Libya, on assistance by
experts. On the initiative of the U. N. Commissioner in
Libya, the Economic and Social Council and the General
Assemb) y ogreed that Libya could continue to receive tech-
nical assistance after its independance had been achieved,
and even before it became a member of the United Nations
or the Specialized Agencies.
The economic and social development scheme for Libya
contains no proposais for new industries, new transport
facilities, new public utilities or big investment projects of
any kind. It is o plan recognizing the realities of the exist-
ing situation and the limit of the rate at which the country
could absorb large-scale assistance.
The plan proposes projects and programmes for the im-
provement or expansion of existing activities or restoration of
physical plants destroyed by war. Recognizing that Libya's
.'one major untapped resource"is the latent skill of its
people, it lays heavy emphasis on educational and technical
training. Improvement in agricultural and animal husbandry
techniques and practices was a basic recommendation. Tech-
nical Assistance to Libya during the past year has embroced
education, agriculture, engineering and technical works,
public health and social development, public administration
and finance, statistical services.
Typica) of the urgent measures taken, Unesco began in
Tripoli in 1950 a Clerical and Technical Training Centre,
following requests from the United Kindom and France, as
administering powers. The Centre ils now running under a
technical assistance agreement signed by the new Government
of Libya and Unesco and ILO. The school is under the direc-
tion of an expert from the U. K. with 13 other teachers and
instructors provided by Unesco. This represents the creation
in less than two years of a combined school of trades and
business administration. At present there are 25 students at
the Centre, the equipment of which has been provided by
Libya, Unesco and the U. S.. Point IV programme.
Courses for technical students are designed to train fitters,
turners, blacksmiths, we) ders, carpenters, foundry workers and
motor mechanics. The course of study is two years, but it is
hoped to reduce this to one year although the delay in pro-
vision of equipment will require a third year for present
students in the technical programme. Unesco is also helping
a centre where elementary school teachers will be trained and
where Libyan textbooks will be developed.
UNESCO
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
COURIER OCTOBER.) 951. Page
T echnical \\ briefing"brings Yugoslavia up-to-date
SHORT-TERM AID FOR A LONG-TERM POLICY
EQUESTS for technical assistance can rangefrom those which are so comprehensive that
they involve the entire economy of a coun-
try, to those, which only involve calling in a
specialist in making piston rings. The first
case may require the training of local experts
capable of transforming their country. The second
usually means that the local technicians and
engineers already exist and aIl they need is a
"briefing"to bring them up to date on the latest
developments in production techniques.
On the whole, Yugoslavia is in the second cate-
gory. It is relatively more developed than most
economically under-developed countries, and al-
ready has a substantial core of expert technicians.
During the war, however, most of them lost touch
with their colleagues and with technical develop-
ments in other countries.
Technical assistance to Yugoslavia therefore fol-
lows a somewhat different pattern from that esta-
blished in lesser developed countries. Instead of
sending teams on one-year or even two-year mis-
sions, the Technical Assistance Administration of
the U. N. has begun an experiment whereby highly
qualifted experts are being sent to Yugoslavia on
assignments lasting only a few weeks.
For a country like Yugoslavia, which has been
carrying on a nationwide development plan of
industrialization since 1947, the short-term assign-ment offers a number of distinct advantages. It
means that for a given sum of technical assistance
funds, many experts, in widely different fields can
be provided ; international specialists whose ser-
vices are needed in many countries will often
accept a brief job but not one where they are.'tied
up"for long periods ; and on the short assignment,
: ietailed advice can be given on difficulties which
may be blocking bigger developments that local
technicians can then cope with unaided.
Yugoslavia's Five-Year Plan of development has
touched almost every phase of the country's eco-
nomic life. The aim of the plan is to turn Yugo-
slavia into a modern industrialized nation with
an up-to-date agriculture. Its primary tasks, in
the past years, have been to raise the level of
industry and create new ones, expand electric
power production and speed the exploitation and
development of the con-
try's rich mineraI resour-. :
ces.
In the first three year,
the plan called mainly for
laying the foundations for 
Yugoslavia's industrializa-
tion-that is, erecting the
buildings, developing the
grids raising the dams,
and digging the tunnels
for power plants and frac-
tories. The programme
was delayed because vital
heavy machinery, such as
tturbines, blast furnaces,
generators and similar
equipment, which hua d
already been paid for,
were not delivered to Yu-
goslavia by certain for-
eign countries. .
The Yugoslavs have 
tried to meet this diffi-
culty by husbanding their resources, ingenuity
and improvization ; by making a good portion of
the machinery themselves ; and by buying it
either in exchange for their own exports or with
credits received from certain western countries.
The progress of the plan and the increase of
production in aIl fields, agricultural as weIl as
industrial, has been remarkable.
In the past four years, for example, new smelt-
ing ovens have been built in Croatia, a factory
for the manufacture of water turbines has been
completed in Slovenia, the cement factory in Split
(cement is one of Yugoslavia's most important
export products) has been rebuilt and enlarged,
and new electric power plants have sprung up aIl
over the country.,
For these and many other industries, Yugoslavia
has availed itself, and is continuing to do so, of
the short-term"briefing services"of the U. N.
Thus, the services of two cement experts from
Switzerland and France were provided for periods
of a month and three weeks to advise on various
problems affecting the cement industry. A U. S.
(yu, ofolo.)
. (Yufofoto.)
expert in the construction of locomotive industry
and bridges advised for one month on such highly
technical matters as locomotive dimensions, the
production of curved sheets for boilers, forging in
casting moulds, welding, and the machine finishing
of locomotive frames.
In response to requests for help in mlning and
electrification, short-term assignments have been
provided on the use of new drilling methods in
large mines, the mechanization of ore-loading and
transportation, and the roasting of mercury ore.
Technicians have been provided 00 advise in the
re-organization of the Turbine Industry Research
Institute at Ljubljana which is seeking to improve
research and development of hydrauIic turbines,
pumps, ventilators and screw propellors ; in the
mass production of electric motors and transform-
ers ; and in the construction of large units of
electrical machinery.
AU of these appointments have been for a
month or less. In certain cases, however, the
technicians have been sent in for longer periods.
Thus a Dutch sanitary and heating engineer
stayed in Yugoslavia for three months, and an
expert on weather forecasting for four months.
The longest appointment so far-12 months-
has been for the services of an expert on rural
electrification, one of the major targets of Yugo-
slavia's industrialization programme.
Alongside these'''weeks-and-months''experts
who are being provided by the United Nations,
another new method of technical assistance is
being tried in Yugoslavia for the first time by the
International Labour Office.
It has often been found that experts. come up
against a hast of practical problème in giving the
full benefit of their experience and training ta
the country they are sent to. Perhaps the most
difficult problem-especially if it relates 00 in-
dustrial training-. arises out of the inability of
the expert to reach the actual worker in the fac-
tory or workshop.
For this reason, the ILO has undertaken 00 help
workers from Yugoslav factories ta get practical
on-the-job training in industrial establishments
abroad. In addition 00 sending 44 foremen-
instructors to Yugoslavia, ILO is arranglng 00
place as many as 377 workers in factories abroad
for periods ranging from 6 ta 12 months. Of these,
263 are already skilled workers who will recelve
advance practical training abroad ; 114 are compa-
ratively young workers having completed their
apprenticeship who will acquire further skills. The
trades in which they will receive training range
from electronics. to foundry practice, from paper
manufacture 00 ship construction, from aeronau-
tics 00 railway engineering, and from precision
instrument making to lorry construction. The
first Yugoslav workers 00 be trained under this
scheme began work this summer.
Unesco, too, is providing technical aid 00 Yugo-
slavia. At the request of the government, a Unesco
exploratory mission was sent 00 the country in
November 1951 and agreed with the Government
that the most urgent need was for a national,
scientific and technical documentation centre ta
service scientific and technical research workers
and students with up-to-date information.
A Unesco three-man mission has now arrived
in Belgrade. The Centre, which is now being
set up, will co-ordinate aIl the scientific and tech-
nical documentation produced by Yugoslav insti-
tutions, will put micro-films within the reach of
research workers, and will enable Yugoslavs 00
benefit from technical abstracts and bibliogra-
phies produced in other countries.
This is only part of the whole story of technical
assistance in Yugoslavia. Other U. N. agencies such
as FAO, WHO, UNICEF and the Monetary Fund
are aU participating 00 help Yugoslavia in the tre-
mendous effort which is transforming the life and
countryside of this nation.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Page t2. OCTOBER 1952
THE AWAKENtNG
VALLEY
(Photo Copyright Herbert Kirchhoff.) *
BOLIVIA LAYS FOUNDATIONS
FOR ECONOMIC BETTERMENT
THE type of association being worked out
between Bolivia and the United Nations
programme of technical assistance has a
special significance. Apart from the direct
economic benefits it should bring to Bolivia,
this association also constitutes a test of the
ability of technical àssistance to help reinforce
administrative and planning services which the
governement considers essential for the success
of its economic development scheme.
Realizing the need for a firm administrative
basis on which to develop more rapidly the
considerable natural resources which can help
the Bolivian people to achieve a higher
standard of living, the goverment requested the
United Nations for comprehensive assistance
both in establishing this structure and in
improving the country's internai economy.
Located not far below the equator, the diver-
sity of Bolivia's climate and vegetation
makes it possible to cultivate almost every
variety of plant or animal product. There are
few material human needs which could not be
satisfied from its rich soils, its rich mineraIs
and its rich water sources. Yet the conditions
of life for the majority of the Bolivian people,
heirs of the Inca and the Spanish civilizations
and inhabiting a country rich, in modern terms,
beyond the dreams of the Conquistadores, are
difficult in the extreme.
initeracy, disease and infant mortality rates
give cause for concern. The maintenance of
roads and railways has become a serious pro-
blem. Agriculture needs developing so that
foodstufis and plant materials can be produced.
in Bolivia insteaß of being imported as they
are today. vide surveys of oil and hydro-
electric power resources must be made so that
these can be properly developed.
For centuries silver from the mountain of
Potosi was one of the most important exports
of the Americas, but as the self-evident source
of wealth, the spectacular deposits of tin have
now replaced silver. IL is also known that
Bolivia possesses reserves of zinc, lead, anti-
mony, tungsten, copper, iron, oil and natural
gas. Gas and oil, with the enormous possibi-
lities of hydro-etectric power, could provide ail
the energy needed to promote Bolivian industry
for générations ahead.
But the tremendous task of developing these
natural resources and realizing improvements
in hea) th, éducation and food supplies calls for
more extensive administrative machinery than
that at present disposed of by Bolivia. This
was recognized by the Bolivians themselves
when they invited the United Nations to share
in a experiment which Mr. Trygve Lie has
described"as an innovation which would be
watched throughout the world by governments
in other countries with similar conditions.
A comprehensive 17 member Technical Assis-
tance Mission organized by the United Nations
under its regular programme in co-operation
with ILO, FAO and Unesco visited Bolivia in
1950 and surveyed the country's needs and
resources. The report of this mission contained
a number of spécifie proposais for economic and
social development in Bolivia, but as a founda-
tion for these projects, it made a suggestion
which the Bolivian Government endorsed, that
the United Nations should assist Bolivia in
obtaining the services of a number of experienc-
ed administrative officiais, drawn from a variety
of countries, whom the Government would
appoint to key positions as integral members of
the Bolivian Civil Service.
In agreement with the Government, and with
the help of FAO and ILO, the United Nations is
recruiting ten officiais for a period of three to
five years and is providing Bolivia with an
annual $ 200, 000 toward their empioyment.
These international recruited officiais are not
UN officiais but are being employed by the
Government and are directly responsible to it.
Eight of them are being assigned to the Central
Bank, the Ministries of Agriculture, Public
Works, Finance, Labour and of Mines, Petro)-
eum and Economy. Two are concerned with
public administration and social security. The
UN is also supplying Bolivia with the services
of 13 technical experts for periods of 6 or 12
months.
Here is an example of a country which is pre-
pared to plan its economic development, in a1l
its phases, with the help of international advice.
The success of this experiment will depend on
the ability of the country to train its own na-
tional experts to carry on without outside
help, and to do so as soon as possible.
THE profile of El Salvador is rugged and so is lifefor its people.
Smailest of the Central American republics
(160 miles long and 60 miles wide), it has one of
the highest population densities in the Western
Hemisphere. Both its birth-rate and death-rates are
high. The average expectation of life is only 26 years.
While 40 per cent of its inhabitants are under 15 years
of age, only 4 per cent are over 60.
The average income of the majority of the families
is less than M50 a year-less than 60 cents a day.
TIliteracy in El Salvador is extremely high. By
law, education is universal and compulsory, but every-
where there is poor enrolment and poor attendance.
Children are family wage-earners and there is an
acute shortage of schools and teachers, which the
government is trying to remedy. Last year, the Mi-
nistry of Education's budget was double that of 1950.
This mountainous country, straddled by 11 major
volcanoes, is primarily agricaltural. About 80 per cent
of the arable land is cultivated, but methods are pri-
mitive. For example, El Salvador is third among the
world's coffee exporting countries-about 136 million
pounds a year-but 25 per cent of the coffee trees
produce 75 per cent of the crop. Destruction of forests
has been responsible for a serious water-shortage in
the country, although the average rainfall is 75 inches
a year.
The minera ! weaith of El Salvador is mainly in gold
and silver, which rank second only to agriculture in
value. Industry, which suffers from lack of electric
power, is restricted largely to the processing of agri-
cultural products. Transportation is limited by the
highways (less than 1, 600 miles improved roads) and
by only 375 miles of railway track.
Thus, El Salvador is, with ail thèse problems, an
under-developed country whose government is anxious
rapidly to advance the coantry's standards and pro-
duction. It turned to the U. N. for aid, even before the
officiaI Expanded Programme began. In 1947, ILO
sent a mission for consultations on a proposed social
insurance scheme. In 1948, the International Bank
sent a mission to study the possibilities of the Lempa
River Hydro-Electric Scheme and authorized a loan
of tl2, 545, 000. UNICEF since 1948 has covered sup-
plementary feeding for children, maternai and child
health and a BCG vaccination programme.
In 1950, FAO and the Economic Commission for
Latin America made El Salvador the first of the Cen-
tral American countries to be studied in the survey on
agricultural credit. Extensive bilateral help has been
made available by the USA. Since July 1951, the
United Nations and its specialized agencies have had
a comprehensive mission in El Salvador.
A United Nations experiment of world-wide import-
ance as weil as of local benefit is the Cuscatlan
Valley Demonstration Project. After El Salvador
offered to provide the site and facilities for a health
demonstration project, an agreement was signed in
March 1951 by WHO on behalf of itself, FAO, ILO.
the United Nations, Unesco and ICAO. WHO
contributed $150, 000 to cover the cost of technical
personnel, equipment and supplies, and assigned
25 specialists to the project.
The Demonstration Area is located in the central
part of the country, immediately north of San Sal-
vador. It was selected because it was fairly typical,
not only of the country, but of many other areas in
Latin America.
It embraces mountains, valleys and fertile plains.
waste lands and rivers. It contains a number of
fairly large towns and many villages and hamlets.
large plantations and small individually owned farms.
There are no substantial factories, but there are active
cottage industries and small workshops, particularly
hand-weaving. The schools in the area are in-
adequate both in number and in accommodation.
Only one of the five municipalities in the area had a
resident doctor and there was only one nutrition
centre.
In September 1951 a combined operation by the
Government, WHO and UNICEF tackled malarial
conditions there. In three months the Insect Control
Programme had been applied to the entire area and
to neighbouring localities. Some 17, 500 houses, affect-
ing 105, 000 people, were DDT sprayed. Training
courses were conducted for graduate nurses, sanitary
inspectors and auxiliary nursing personnel.
By the end of 1951, the government had spent
$46, 000 on the preparations for this experiment of
international import, which is to provide a practical
example of what can be done in providing environ-
mental sanitation, maternai and child health nutrition,
control of malaria, tuberculosis, venereal and other
communicable diseases, dental hygiene, laboratory ser-
vices, health education and public health training.
But health problems cannot be separated from
hunger, ignorance and debased conditions of life.
Other participating agencies are also taking their part
in this area-experiment. Many physical problems of
agricultural production require attention, such as
drainage, irrigation, conservation and proper utiliza-
tion of the soil. FAO is making a detailed economic
and scientific analysis of the demonstration area to
determine the approach to certain land use problems
and thus assist in its agricultural development.
Unesco has assigned two experts to thé team, one
in gênera ! fundamental éducation and one in literacy
techniques. They are making plans to conduct.
fundamental education in the valley and to train rural
health workers in fundamental education techniques
for their work in the villages, first in the valley and
later on throughout the country.
It is not the function of technical assistance to
create a Valley of Privilege in an under-privileged
country. The objects of Cuscatlan are to enable the
government to extend the experience gained to the
whole country, and, beyond that, to set an example
for other countries in like circumstances. Cuscatlan
is, therefore, an international laboratory for the study
of social, economic and technical problems. The initial
benefits which will accrue to the 100, 000 people co-
operating in these experiments, may be multiplied a
thousandfold if the experience gained here is made
available and adopted in similar areas throughout the
worid.
UNESCO
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
OCTOBER 1952. Page t3
THE LILLIPUTIAN HARBOURS OF POONA
by Daniel BEHRMAN
This jumble of pipes, planks and water (above) ! S actuaHy a detailed model reproduction of the port of Cochin in
Southern India. Lilliputian models of dams, rivers and port lay-outs (photos below) enable experts to study irrigation
projects and to work out answers to problems affecting India s ports, her main life-lines to the outside would.
AT land-Ioc. ked Poona. 120 miles from Bombayand the sea, engineers are working out answers
to problems confronting India's ports, her main
lifelines to the outside world. There, 2, 000 feet high
and dry in the Western Chats mountains, sandbars
choke up the Hooghly Estuary, nightmare of cap-
tains taking ships into Calcutta, and cyclones blow
into Madras Harbour, tossing ships at their moorings.
But this is aIl happening in miniature. For 30
years, Poona bas been thé site of a vast outdoor labo-
ratory where engineers have been able to scale down
waterpower and irrigation problems to mode size.
In) 1947, the Central Water and Power Research
Station there was given the added asstgnment of inves-
tigating port problems in its 120-acre laboratory, one
of the largest in the world (elsewhere, weather condi-
tions force engineers to conduct their tests under roofs,
but rain is a rarity at Poona).
There are now 40 engineers and 300 construction
workers at the Poona station, in addition to two men
sent in by Unesco, Alfred Frants Mogensen. a
Danish navigation research engineer, and Dr R. V.
Baud, a Swis engineer whose s-pecialty is testing
structures and materials for safety.
The station's activities are a symbol of India's
scientific révolution and a ! so iliustrate how technical
assistance by a United Nations agency can be dove-
tailed into a well-planned national economy.
Model tests of harbour problems are easily the
most spectacular aspect of the station's work. By
reducing these harbours to small scale, huge sums
which otherwise would have been spent on full-sized
experiments can be saved. Poona's engineers are caU-
ed in regularly to seek solutions to the many pro-
blems of India's ports and harbours.
A typical case is that of Mangalore, a city of
125, 000 on the west coast of India, 500 miles south
of Bombay, and a heavy exporter of coffee, cashew
nuits, pepper and roof tiles. We leamed about Man-
galo ; e's dilernma from V. S. Kudva, one its leading
business men, who had been delegated to visit Poona
and inspect a model of his city's port under con-
struction there.
The main stumbling block is the'port's lack of a deep
channel through the shaHow water stretching three miles
off-shore from the city and which forces ocean-going
ships to be unloaded by shaUow-draft dhows. During
the four-month monsoon season, not even the dhows
can get over the shallaws and Mangalore must do its
exportpng and importing by rai !, and this of course is
an expensive substitute.
Dredging a deep channe) into Manga) ore wtH cost
an estimated 4, 000, 000 rupees, an investment which
the city can amortize in four years if the channel can
be economically maintained. It is this"if"which is
now being studied in a 32, 000 square-foot model at
Poona and, working closely with D. V. Joglekar,
director of the station, Mr. Mogensen visited Manga-
lore to help gather data for the LiUiputian port.
Ot. Baud and Dr. Gurdas Ram of the station's
physics section are working on photo-elastic testing, a
process in which structural models made of plastic are
p ! aced under stress and polarized'light is passed through
them. The light projects patterns on a screen which
reveal to the tramed engineer the weaik points of a
design. Ccê.'. :..-
Dr. Gurdas Ram is a physicist who gave up excel-
lent job in an industrial research laboratory because
he is convinced that the station's studies in irrigation and
harbour problems deserve top priority in India. He
also believes technical assistance has a major role to
play in his country.
"What we lack is practica ! expérience", he explain-
ed."We have the theoretical knowtedge, but we
have not hacf enough opportunity to put it to use.
"In testing structures, for example, we are merely
beginning and we're at about the same point as were
Europe or the United States a few decades ago. But
we cannot wait for these decades to go by in India.
Our people have freedom and they expect gréât thjngs
of it now. When you are dealing with water power
and, especially irrigation to produce more food, time
IS precious.
"In India, we cannot afford to wait."-
; OURIER
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Page 14. OCTOBER 1952
UNESCO
A case
of give
and take
NE of the mot interest-ing technical training
projects of the Inter-
national Labour Organiza-
tion is at present being
carried out in Brazil. The
undertaking is an example
of the"give and take"of
technical assistance.
Brazil avails itself of the
technical aid provided by the
United Nations as a receiver-
nation, but at the same time
it has also pledged $460, 000
as a contributor-nation al-
though it has been agreed
thatthis sum could be devot-
ed to international projects
within the country.
Last year, the ILO entered
into discussions with the
Government of Brazil and
with the Brazilian agency in
Sao Paulo, known as the
National Service of Indus-
trial Apprenticeship (SE-
NAI) and from this emerged
an arrangement by which
ILO has undertaken to ad-
minister a training scheme
for ail Latin America, mak-
ing use of the wide training
facilities and scholarships
for industrial instructors
which the SENAI offers.
The Brazilians have made
available 100 fellowships by
which, under the Technical
Assistance prog ramme,
technicians from ail the
Latin American countries
can become the guests of
Brazil. These include five
three-year scholarships in
spinning and weaving at the
Federal Technical School of
Chemical and Technical In-
dustry ; 10 fellowships last-
ing nine months each at the
SENAI schools, including
training periods in indus-
trial concerns, for the bene-
fit of industrial teachers,
foremen and technicians ; 95
fellowships lasting nine
months each in SENAI
schools for the training of
industrial instructors in me-
chanics, electricity and tex-
tiles.
Since the scheme is es-
sentially a partnership, the
ILO, at the request of the
Brazilian Government, has
provided technical assist-
ance to strengthen SENAI
and to enable it to extend its
services. 1 la has provided
15 school instructors and
granted 13 fellowships for
foreign study by technicians
and teachers from SENAI.
It has also provided com-
plete correspondence cour-
ses in such subjects as
carpentry, boitermaking,
welding, motor engineering
and machine-designing.
The response of the
countries of Latin America
to this type of technical aid
has been encouraging. For
instance, ILO has been able
to place, under the SENAI
scheme, 20 of the Ecua-
dorian workers and foremen
from various trades for
whom it has accepted train-
ing responsibility.
This contribution-in-kind,
however, has not been con-
fined to SENAI and ILO.
The Brazilian Government
has offered a long list of
services which concern
practically ail thé agencies
participating in the Expand-
ed Technical Assistance
programme. These include
a laboratory for obtaining
agricultural data, an inter-
national seminar on pro-
blems of public adminis-
tration, scholarships for
special courses in public
administration, vocational
! raining fellowships, and va-
rious medical facilites, Most
of these offers have proved
most valuable and represent
the cost equivalent of the
$460, 000 which Brazil has
pledged as her contribution
to the programme.
These children are happy but not because the schoolday has ended. They are racing as fast as their legs can carry
them to reach the eight acres of land where their class raises its own ivestock, and grows part of its food. At their
rural school in Cha-Choeng-Sao, they are beginning to learn in terms of soil and seeds how.. knowledge"is not just
a matter oftextbooks, but of hygiène, of agriculture and ofother practica) things that play a role in their daily y) ives.
A NATION TRANSFORMS
tTS EDUCAT ! ON
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
; OUR ! ER OCTOBER 9S2. Page) 5
Thailand needs skilled workers, carpenters, mechanics, machinists and technicians for her economic development. At the country's request, United Nations
Technical Assistance is helping to meet these needs. Picture shows students at microscopes and micro-dissectors studying laboratory techniques.
TRADITIONALL y Thai teaching was a function of
j thé priests. Althaugh it has been secularized,
the lay teaching is usually done in classes
around the temples. It is appropriate therefore that
the educatianal pilot project in Thailand should have
been set up in the grounds of a Buddhist monastery.
At Cha-Choeng-Sao international experts, brought in
under the Expanded Programme of echnical Assist-
ance, mingle with the yettow-robed priests and work ta
the ttnkling'Of the temple bells. leaf bells which swing
in the breeze. But what they are daing is something
new to this traditional setting ; they have been invited
by the Government of ThaHand to hetp with the
refarm'Of the en tire educatianal system'Of the cauntry.
Cha-Choeng-Sao is 60 miles from Bangkok, and
in the district there is a population of 240. 000 adults
and 42, 000 children. It is a provincial capital which
was chasen as a resuit of a Unesco consultative mission
sent out, as a part'Of the narmal programme'Of acti-
vities in 1949, to advise the Government an its educa-
tional development programme. Cha-Choeng-Sao
cammended itself to international experts because,
while it was accessible by road, ra) I and river. It was a
community typical of most of thé hfe of Thailand-
rice-growing. fruit farming and small industry.
It is a jungle area and nearby there is coastal fishing
It was considered that a pattem of éducation evolved
under these conditions and taking account of thé cir-
cumstances of thé area would apply almost anywhere
in Siam. In addition, it is'One'Of the paarest pra-
vinces with one of thé lowest ratings of titeracy in the
country. so that what is being done there can have
direct benefit for the people as weil as having experi-
mental value for the other 70 provinces.
A fundamenta ! éducation expert from New Zealand
surveyed the possibihties of Cha-Choeng-Sao in No-
vember 1950 and, in conjunction with Thai educators.
produced the plans on which the centre is now based.
There was na living accommodation available, but
some of thé existing classrooms were converted into
living quarters, and an o) d monastery building became
a kitchen. The rest of the schoo ! was redesigned for
the manifold ; ; urposes'Of the project.
One of the first needs was to convince the people
of the value of what was going an amongst them, and
so, in March and April 1951, fairs were organized.
where mode) farmhouses, kindergarten playgrounds
and classroom apparatus and arts and crafts materials
were on display. Health and child welfare centres
were set up, and the people were informed of the edu-
cational plans, which cover every aspect of the coun-
try's education-adult, vocationat. secondary. pri-
mary health, physical, music, arts and crafts and social
éducation, as we) ! as teacher training.
With the co-operation of the Thaj educationa)
authorities and with a staff provided by the Govern-
ment, the international team consists of a New Zealand
expert in fundamenta ! éducation, a primary school
specialist from Denmark, a specialist in language
teaching and a vocational training expert from the
United Kingdom, and an expert from the United States
who is known as"the man with the five dollar labo-
ratory", because he can improvise scientific equipment
from local scrap. Specialists from FAO, WHO and
ILO are joining the project. 50 that classroom teaching
can be extended into the practical lifte of the people.
As an academic exercise the internationa ! assignment
is a chaHenging, if difficult one, because the whole
nature as weIl as the structure of education has to be
transformed. Learning in the past has been almost
entirely by rote, formai and verbal, a case of memo-
rizing and regurgitating. The idea that the chi'ld, or,
for that matter, the grown-up should learn by doing
was something 50 novel as to be revolutionary. An-
other handicap of Siamese education has been the lack
of proper teachers'training colleges. They exist, but
have been used rather as an extension of the secondary
school education than as institutions for teaching
methods or encouraging teachers to have any originality
or enterprise.
Instead of the children chanting their lessons from
age-old fables and acquiring a literacy which lapsed,
the new methods being tried out at Cha-Choeng-Sao
employ illustrated textbooks designed in the Thai's
own visual idiom by their own artists ; sand tables on
which the chrIdren construct their own villages and
their own countryside ; and paints and brushes, till now
unknown to the children, but with which they are
allowed to find their own expression. Thai instruc-
tors. adapting thé ideas brought in from the outside,
are teaching science with a vividness far removed from
the formalism in which science had nO part. Chiidren
and adults are beginning to learn, in terms of soap and
water, soil and seeds in their own fields, and the
forgotten crafts of their own locality, how"knowledge".
is not just a matter of textbooks, but of hygiene, of
agriculture and of other practical things in their own
daily lives. This emphasis on"wanting to know"
leads to"wanting to communicate"and 50 to a literacy
which will persist.
Apart from the Thai educators who are the active
and creative colleagues of the international team,
teachers corne from ail over Thailand for courses from
which they take back new ideas which wiU enliven
their existing curricula and, in the process, produce
local reforms while the wider reforms are evolving.
They take back classroom techniques, but they also
acquire the principle of"dirty hands", which means
that they are non longer peop ! e atoof from the practical
needs of their community. To teach the people, they
work with them and thus provide what is one of the
objects of Cha-Choeng-Sao social leadership.
This is only a pilot project. It is the beginning of
a 0-year programme ; in thé nrst nve years they will
develop by experiment and by experience the techniques
which will be extended to the other provinces of the
country ; but in that time Thailand itself will be
evolving a system of education which will be able to
absorb and apply the methods of Cha-Choeng-Sao.
That will involve the reform of the teachers'colleges,
the production of more and better teachers, the crea-
tion of new schools and adult education centres.
There will be the reform of the primary schools and
the extension of the secondary schools. Compulsory
education is already the law of Thailand from seven
to) 4, but a student can leave at the fourth grade,
and the law has been difficult to enforce beeause of
the lack of school facilities and trained teachers.
It is an ambitious programme and a heavy commit-
ment for the government. Thé United Nations agen-
cies, through this, project under the technical assistance
programme, are providing the example and the stimu-
latin. ion conjunction with the funds available from
United Nations sources a scheme was worked out by
the Government whereby United States bilateral funds
and personnel were made available.
As a matter of principle, money and materials are
less important at Cha-Choeng-Sao than training of the
Thais for'leadership, 50 that the project can be handed
over and repeáted elsewhere through trained Thai
personnes.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
o. N. phots.)
d-''.'.-"-'....-".....'..."-.,--".-..',,-,-.'-----...'.-.
HELPING MAN TO HELP HIMSELF-
ON A WORLD-WtDE SCALE
U nder a blazing sun, these Ecuadorans are working hard to repair irri-gation canais which an earthquake has put out of action. They are
being shown how best to do this by experts of the Food and Agriculture
Organization, while other foreign specialists give advice on the protection
and storage of grain in the devastated area. This is only one case among
hundreds of that international cooperation which the United Nations Pro-
gramme of Technical Assistance 50 strikingly exemplifie, The programme
puts technical knowledge within the reach of ail nations that have asked for
it, 50 that they can improve the living conditions of their people-especially
in the under-deve) oped areas. Not that Technical Assistance is anything
new : right from the beginnings of history, contacts between peoples have
led to profitable results. But the value and originality of the United Nations
Programme lies in the fact that, for the first time, this assistance is being
organized on a rational, systematic, world-wide basis that takes into account
ail social and economic factors. For more than two years, the Specialized
Agencies of U. N. have devoted themselves to this immense task which has
so many aspects. But in whatever country these U.N. specialists are working,
the successful outcome ultimately depends on the amount of effort which
the government and people put into it. For United Nations Technical Assist-
ance is above ail a plan which helps man to help himself. (See Page 5.)
]]>
</page>
</document>
