<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="071299eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
PRICE r ! Cents (U. S.), 6 Pence (U. K-), or 20 Francs (PRANCE). JANUARY 1951
CHILD WAR VItTIMS TEll THEM OWN STORY
BRITISH, FRENCH,
ITALIAN NETWORKS JOIN
UNESCO'S RADIO CARA-
VAN ; MILLIONS HEAR
"EVERYBODY'S CHILD"
Here is a p1'Oblem in cornmunicati011, :The ordinary range of a child's voice is small
--and in these days it is often too small to reach
the din-filled ears, the crowded minds and the troubled
hearts of grown-ups. This is particularly true of the
orphans. Yet, the needs of the child are limitless-and
their claim is just-for love, warmth, food, education
and training in the tools and techniques of the world
which is to be theirs. As expressed by the Chilean poet,
Gabriela Mistral,"The outstretched hand of the child
is not'begging,. it is collecting."Yet, the voice of those
whose need is greatest is too often he ; weakest voice
of all. He1'e is a p1'oblem in communication.
Here, in fact, was a problem for the Radio Division
of Unesco's Department of Mass Communication. An
answer was found in the Unesco Radio Caravan, made
possible by the combined skill, knowledge, money and
conscience of three of the world's great radio networks :
the British Broadcasting Corporation ; the Radio-
diil'usion franchise and Radio-Italiana.
As the first result of the Radio Caravan, several mil-
lions of British listeners, at home and overseas, and
several millions of French listeners have already heard
the children-those whose voices are normallv the
weakest. This month more millions of Italian listeners
will have the living reality of these children brought
into their homes, and in the months ahead countless
more people in Europe, Canada, the United States, Aus-
tralia, New Zealand, Latin-American and other coun-
tries will be stirred to action by radio's forceful remin-
der that"No body's child is everybody's child."
The Caravan broadcasts are good"public service"
programmes, but they are also what broadcasters call
"good 1'audio", and the best evening listening hours have
been chosen for them. In this issue, the COURIER
prints pictures of these children, members of the gene-
ration that suffered most from World War II, in the
belief that their publication is timely.
The Uuesco Radio Caravan was planned by radio
experts from eighteen nations meeting at Unesco
House. Early in October 1930, two automobiles loaded
with recording equipment and baggage left Paris.
Their passengers included Marjorie Banks of the
(Continued on page 12)
VOLUME 111-No 12
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 2
AT HAøDONG, AR T
AND AGRICUL TURE
GO HANDøINøHAND
JANUARY 1951
IN July 1940, a group of twenty Indo-
Chinese agriculturists and craftsmen
met at Hanoi to discuss how they
might improve living conditions for
themselves and their families.
Having decided that co-operative
methods of work and the sale of their
products through a common pool offer-
ed the best chance of increased pros-
perity, they formed an association
which they named :"The Small
Craftsmen and Agriculturists : Mutual
Aid and Progress."
As their emblem they chose two open
hands, symbolising handicrafts, hold-
ing two shoots of rice, representing
agriculture, and for their motto :"In
our two hands we hold a treasure."
During the troubled times that Indo
China has experienced since then, the
Association has saved hundreds of re-
fugee families from starvation by pro-
viding them with a means of livelihood
and with temporary homes.
In this work, the Association had a
benefactor and counsellor, Hoang
Trong Phu, a leading citizen and offi-
cial in Tonkin, who throughout his
career worked to improve the standard
of living of his fellow countrymen in
the heavily populated delta region.
Hoang Trong Phu, devoted the last
years of his life to helping the Asso-
ciation and his advice and encourage-
ment were invaluable during its early
days and again during the difficult pe-
riod after the war.
HAVEN AT HANOI
IN 1947, two members of the Group-
Le Van Nghiep and Le Van Dinh-
organized a reception centre at Ha-
noi in two large sheds which they had
repaired. They received families by the
hundred, all seeking work and some
form of shelter, after fleeing from vil-
lages ravaged by civil war. The com-
munity soon overflowed into neighbour-
ing houses, also damaged, but which
were repaired by their new inhabi-
tants.
At the beginning of 1948, there were
about ten handicraft workshops and an
agriculturists'group at Ha-Dong, a few
miles from Hanoi, and during the
Spring of 1949, a farm school and a
new handicraft centre were also set up.
More and more families came to seek
refuge at the Centre. Some only
stayed a short time, for they wished to
return to their villages as soon as the
situation there improved.
Others, having become
accustomed to the region,
were content to stay at
the Centre and to fashion
a new life for themselves,
especially as the town of'
Hanoi offered regular
openings for their produce.
With the same care and concentra-
tion he used to carve the gracefully
beautiful lines of the statuettes seen
on his right, the craftsman puts the
finishing touch to a tobacco pipe.
These people today work at the Cen-
tre under a flexible system of control
whose aim is to advise, guide and help
them through advances of money and
materials. The agricultural work and
The UNESCO COURIER is an international periodical devoted to the work
of UNESCO and to activities and developments throughout the world in edu-
cation, science and culture.
A full year's subscription (72 issue) costs only $1. 50 US., or 5/-or 200
French Francs.
SUBSCRIBE NOW ! Tell your friends about the UNESCO COURIER and
get them to suscribe too.
Write to our agent in your country listed below, or directly to UNESCO
House, 19, avenue Kleber, Paris-16', France.
Argentina : Editorial Sudamericana, S. A., Alsina 500, Buenos Aires.
Australia : H. A. Goddard Ltd., Z55a George Street, Sydney.
Austria : Wilhelm Frick Ver) ag, 27 Graben, Vienna.
Barbados : S. P. C. K. Bookshop (Regional Office Caribbean Area), Broad Street, Bridge-
town.
Belgium : Librairie Encyclopédique, 7, rue du Luxembourg, Brussels IV.
Brazil : Livraria Agir Editora, Rua Mexico 98-B, Caixa postal 3291, Rio de Janeiro.
Burma : Burma Educaiional Bookshop, 551-3 Merchant Street, P. O. Box 222, Rangoon.
Canada : The Ryerson Press, 299 Queen Street West, Toronto.
Ceylon. : Lake House Bookshop, The Associated Newspapers 01 Ceylon, Ltd., Co-
lombo. 1
Chile : Libreria Lope de Vega, Moneda 924, Santiago de Chile.
'China ; The Commercial Press, Ltd, 211 Honan Road (c), Shanghai.
Colombia : Emilio Royo Martin, Carrera 9a, 1791, Bogota.
Cuba : La Casa Belga, René de Smedt, O'Reilty, Havana.
Czechoslovalåa : Orbis, Narodni 37, Prague I.
Denmark : Einar Munksgaard, 6 Norregade, Copenhagen.
Egypt : Librairie James Cattan, Fournisseur de la Cour, 118, Rue Emad el Dine, Cairo.
. Ecuador : Casa de Cultura Ecuatoriana, Quito.
France : Maison du Livre Francis, 4, rue Félibien, Paris (6-). (Booksellers only)
UNESCO, Sales Unit, 19, avenue Kléber, Paris (16<). Tes. : Kléber 52-00. (Indi-
vidual sales.)
Greece : Eleitheroudakis, Librairie Internationale, Athens
Hungary :"Ibusz", Akademia-u, 10, Budapest V.
India : Oxford Book and Stationery Co., Scindia House, New Delhi.
Israel : Leo Blumstein, Book and Art Shop, 35 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv.
Italy : Messaggerie Italiane, Via Lomazzo, 52, Milan.
Lebanon and Syria : Librairie Universelle, Avenue des francis, Beirut, Lebanon.
. Liberia : Pahama and Co, 70, Broad Street, Monrovia.
Malaya and Singapore : Peter Chong and C°, P. O. Box 135, Singapore.
Mexico : Libreria Universitaria, Justo Sierra 16, Mexico D. F.
Netherlands : N. V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout 9, The Hague.
New Zealand : Whitcombe and Tombs, Ltd., G. P. O. Box 1526, Wellington, C. l.
Nigeria : C. M. S. Bookshop, P. O. Box 174. Lagos.
Norway : A/S Bokhjornet, Stortingsplass 7, Oslo.
Pakistan : Thomas and Thomas, Fort Mansions, Frere Road, Karachi 3.
Peru : Libreria Internacional dell Peru, S. A., Giron de la Union, Lima.
Philippines : Philippine Education Co., Inc., Corner Tanduay and Vergara Streets,
Quiapo, Manila.
Portugal : Uniao Portuguesa de Imprensa, 198 Rua de Sao Bento, : joe Esq., Lisbon.
Sweden : A. B. C. E. Fritzes King\. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2 ; Stockholm.
Switzerland : French speaking cantons : Librairie de l'Université, 22-24, rue de Ro-
mont, Fribourg. German speaking cantons : Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Turkey : Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul.
Union of South Africa : Van Schaik's Bookstore (Pty.), Ltd., P. O. Box 724, Pretoria.
United Kingdom : H. M. Stationery Olfice : York House, Kingsway, London (Retail
Counter Service), or P. O. Box 569, London, S. E. 1. (Orders by post)
United States of America : Columbia University Press, 2960 Broadway, New York 27,
N. Y.
Uruguay : Centro de Cooperacion Cientifica para la America Latina, Unesco, Bu1evar
Artigas 1320, Montevideo.
. Venezuela : Editoria"Andres Bello", Caracas.
. Under negotiation.
A fine example of lacquer work on a
wooden panel by craftsmen of the
Ha-Dong Centre, whose ingenuity and
talent spring from their innate sense
of artistry.
that of the craftsmen is supervised by
the head of each family, who acts at
his own discretion and in accordance
with local customs.
HELPMG THE PEOPLE
NEARLY two hundred families are at
present living between Ha-Dong
and Hanoi ; eighty of them are
craftsmen-weavers, workers in wood,
ivory, and lacquer, and metal and iron
workers. The peasants also make bri-
quettes of peat.
The lacquerers are perhaps the most
skilled of the craftsmen. With patient
: : are they produce magnificent panels,
whose traditional patterns are enhanc-
ed by the beauty of the colours, the
depth of tones and the highly polished
surface.
M. Le Van Dinh, Director of the City
and President of the Association envi-
sages two separate stages o : develop-
ment for the future. The first will
continue the present policy of giving
individual initiative free Ten in the
production and sale of goods, with the
Association merely providiDg technical
aid and opening channels o ! trade. The
second stage will aim, through the cor-
porative and social education of the
producers, to encourage thlm to form
a fully co-operative Association in
This craftsman and his wife symbo-
lize the"family"spirit and patient
skill of the workers of Ha-Dong.
which individual advantages and res-
ponsibilities are combined.
In the social fields, the primary school
which is already well attended, will be
improved and enlarged, medical assist-
tance extended, and the lesson of thrif-
tiness inculcated as widely as possible.
Perhaps the most encouraging sign
for the future of the Ha-Dong Centre
is the spirit which animates its work-
a spirit springing from professional
pride in the quality of its products.
The Centre's work has already served
as an example elsewhere in Northern
Indo-China, for it is simply helping
the people to help themselves.
MORE INVENTORIES FOR
SCIENCE TEACHERS
A few months ago, Unesco pro-
duced Vol I of a series of public-
ations designed to implement the
teaching of science in schools and
colleges in war-devastated and
under-developed regions of the
world. Vol II has just been issued
and presents, in detail, university
courses of study and equipment
needed for the teaching of Botany,
Chemistry, Geology, Physics and
Zoology.
"INVENTORIES OF APPARA-
TUS AND MATERIALS FOR
TEACHING SCIENCE VOL II-
UNIVERSITIES".
(English) 145 pages $2. 00 12/3
F. 600.
RADIO AND THE 3 R's
In order to facilitate the organiz-
ation and development of school
broadcasting, Unesco undertook a
survey of this fields, covering the
concepts and methods used and
the results achieved in 13 different
countries. Full reports from these
countries, together with sections
devoted to special aspects of this
work, are included in this recent
Unesco publication.
"BROADCASTING TO SCHOOLS"
(English ; French) ; ! 15 pages
$1. 00 6/-F. 300.
PERIODICALS
Subscribers to one or more of
the periodicals regularly issued by
Unesco are assured of a constant
source of information on the spec-
ific fields covered by the different
journals. Limitations of space here
prevent our giving full details, but
a descriptive leaflet is now avail-
able on request which gives full
information on the following :
BULLETIN FOR LIBRARIES,
COPYRIGHT BULLETIN, COU-
RIER, FUNDAMENTAL EDUC-
ACTION, IXTERNATIONAL SOCIAL
SCIENCE BULLETIN, MUSEUM
and OFFICIAL BULLETIN. IM-
PACT, a quarterly bulletin of
science abstracts, was published
after this leaflet was issued, but
full details are available on request
from Unesco's Sales Service.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
JANUARY 195 I
Page 3-UNESCO COURIER
AFTER the sacrifices willingly made during the two giganticstruggles we have already endured, we are faced with yet
another heacy trial : we must surmount the obstacles which
even now threaten the maintenance of Peace in Freedom under Law.
Never has been more urgent to face the facts with clear vision.
Never, perhaps, has mankind had greater need of that steady cou-
raye which respect for truth demands. If we build our hope on the
undestroyable foundations of clarity and generosity, we will recognize
thut force alone is no solution. Justice must indeed be strong, but
for force to win enduring victory it must be governed by equity. by equity.
The peace for which we hope makes greater demands on our
qualities than does avar. It bears no resemblance to a weak sur-
render to the pleasures of life. It must be a creator of values, and,
far from sanctioning privilege, it must aim at increasing every man's
share of freedom, happiness and culture. Governments and indivi-
duals must hare the courage to overcome habits of thought and
action derived from a thousand years of history. And this effort
is unm'oidable if we are to eliminate war from human experience.
Unesco, which was created to develop the love of peace in the
heurts of men, knows well that it cannot succeed in its educational,
scientific and cultural purposes if once more the thunder of guns
is to silence men's consciences, if hatred is again to destroy the
best of mankind-of men longing for the understanding necessary ta
security and the security necessary to progress.
In the name of the principles which arc the foundations of
Cneseo's existence, I express the most fervent hope that the New
Tear may bring to all the leaders and all the peoples of the world
the wisdom and the good will they need to avoid a catastrophe
wich would break the thread of civilization. May law prevail over
all discords. And may we begin at last within the framework of
the United xations a life in 2which individual and national pride
recognizes the limits imposed upon it by the dignity of man and
the solidarity of men,
Commissions Meeting ProposesUnesco C mmissio s Meeting Proposes
Regional Planning of Technical Aid
A I'LAX to put the United Nations
programme of technical assist-
ance to work on the problems of
an entire region rather than those
of individual countries has resulted
from the first regional conference of
Unesco National Commissions in the
Western Hemisphere, which ended its
thirteen-day meeting at Havana on De-
cember 20.
Conference recommendations for the
drawing up of technical assistance re-
quests on the basis of the needs of a
continent were in the general spirit of
solidarity and co-operation in the
Western Hemisphere which marked the
entire conference, attended by delegates
from sixteen countries.
The keynote of the conference was
sounded on the opening day, Decembcl
8. by M. Jaimes Torres Bodet, Unesco'-
Director-General, who told delegates :
.. The most important of the circum-
stances favourable to the holding of t1li. 
conference, in my eyes, is the fact that
the American peoples make up a demo-
cratic community... are all united ill
their belief in individual liberty and the
dignity o {the human person."
Technical Aid Measures
In the field of technical assistance, theconference recommended hat :
1. A scientific bibliographlcal centre now
being organized by Unesco in Mexico
be extended to other Latin-American
countries in the form of branch offices.
2, Unesco and other United Nations special-
Ized agencies begin a study of the
problems of Latin America's indigenous
peoples, with emphasis on their educa-
tion.
3. Unesco should organize a Seminar to
show Latin American countries how to
determine the type of specialized person-
nel they may need for their economic
development.
U. N. OFFICIAL WINS NOBEL PEACE
PRIZE : On December 10, Dr. Ralph
Bunche, Director of the United Nations
Department of Trusteeship and infor-
mation from Non-self-governing Territo-
ries, was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize
at a ceremony in Oslo. This photo,
taken prior to the ceremony, shows
Dr. Bunch meeting Mr. Martin Traumel,
the veteran Norwegian Socialist leader,
at a lunch arranged by the Norwegian
Nobel Institute.
4, A seminar should be organized to study
the results of Unesco's surveys In Latin
America on teohnlcal needs In the field
of information (press, film and radio)
with the aim of drawing up a regional
programme to meet these needs.
The Conference's work covered vir-
tually all phases of Unesco's aim and
the role played by National Commis-
sions in translating them into national
and local action.
Delegates applauded Unesco's pro-
posal to set up a world network of
regional fundamental education centres
as part of a global campaign against
illiteracy and low standards of living
and agreed to facilitate this programme
"through all means necessary",
They pledged full support to the or-
ganization's international fellowship
programme and offered the services of
national commissions in the orientation
and guidance of holders of Unesco fel-
lowships.
The conference also urged that the
work of the Western Hemisphere's Na-
tional Commissions be brought down
to the community level-especially in
large."decentralized"countl'ies. It re-
commended a broader base for national
commissions through co-operation of
- women's groups, representatives of go-
vernments. youth movements and simi-
lar organization. The creation of full-
time staffs to handle administrative ope-
rations of the commissions was also
urged.
Human Rights Ceremony
The conference also discassed theUnesco coupon scheme, problems
of libraries in Latin America. the
translation of Latin-American classics.
and the teaching of the aims and prin-
ciples of the United Nations.
On December 8, M. Torres Bodet and
Senor Albert Llera Camargo of the Or-
ganisation of American States (OAS)
signed an agreement formalizing the
exist. ing co-operation between UNESCO
and OAS. The two organizations have
held joint educational seminars at Cara-
cas, Rio de Janeiro and Montevideo and
have co-operated in the establishment of
a fundamental education centre in
Mexico to train teachers for all of Latin
America.
The third dav of the conference.
December 10, was marked uy impres-
sive ceremonies commemorating the
adoption two years before of the United
Nations Cniversal Declaration of Human
Rights.
During the Havana conference, dele-
gates also had the opportunity to in-
spect Unesco's travelling science mus-
eum which was brought to Havana
following visits to Ecuador and Peru
where it was. visited by nearly 130, 000
persons.
Countries who sent delegates to the
conference were : Bolivia, Brazil, Co-
lombia, Costa Rica. the Dominican Re-
public, Ecuador, EI Salvador, France,
Guatemala. Haiti, Honduras, Mexico,
Panama, the United States, Uruguay
and Venezuela. Three countries. Chile,
Cuba and Nicaragua, and various non-
governmental organizations also sent
observers.
"HUMAN RIGHTS"DAY IN HAVANA : Delegates to the Regional Conference of Unesco
National Commissions in the Western Hemisphere took part in a ceremony marking the second
anniversary of the adoption of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights, in Havana's Parliament
Building, on December 10. They were addressed by M. Jaime Torres Bodet, Unesco's Director-
General, who during his visit to Havana to attend the Conference received the degree of doctor
"honoris causa"at the University of Havana. This photo shows : (front row, from left to right)
Senor Manual Gual Vidal, Mexico's Minister of Education ; M. Torres Bodet ; Senor Ernesto Dihigo,
Cuba's Minister of Foreign Affairs ; Dr. Cosme de la Torriente, Chairman of the Regional Confe-
rence and Dr. Octavio Mendez Pereira, Director of Unesco's Regional Office in Havana.
BREAKING DOWN BARRIERS TO THE FREE FLOW OF KNOWLEDGE : NATIONS
SIGN THE UNESCO-SPONSORED AGREEMENT ON THE IMPORTATION OF
EDUCATIONAL, SCIENTIFIC AND CULTURAL MATERIALS. In a ceremony
at the United Nations Interim Headquarters presided over by Secretary-General Trygve
Lie, representatives of 17 nations signed the Unesco-sponsored international agreement
which will allow materials to move across frontiers free of duty. Since'hen, one more
country has signed and, more signatures are expected shortly. This photo : show Sir Gland-
win Jebb, of the United Kingdom, signing the agreement.
EXPERTS URGE EXPANDED EXCHANGE
OF PERSONS PLAN FOR LATIN AMERICA
AN expanded exchange of personsprogramme designed to make full
use of Latin America's cultural
and linguistic unity was recommended
by delegates from eleven nations,
meeting during a recess of the regional
conference of Unesco National Com-
missions, in Havana last month.
The delegates, members of a com-
mittee of experts on the exchange of
persons, suggested that Latin Ameri-
can countries immediately begin an
exchange programme for history and
geography teachers. Under this plan,
National Commissions would invite
teachers to apply for a one-year
appointment in a neighbouring country
with salaries and part of their sub-
sistence paid.
They called for wider dissemination
in Latin America of"Study Abroad",
Unesco's handbook on international
fellowships and scholarships, and for
more complete information from Latin
American countries on available
fellowship opportunities.
To help workers travel, the experts
urged Unesco and Latin American
governments to enlist the co-
operation of employers'and workers'
organizations, in an exchange pro-
gramme.
The committee recommended that a
full-time exchange of persons special-
ist be assigned to Unesco's Western
Hemisphere regional office m Havana.
Experts on the committee came from
Argentina, Canada, Chile, Colombia,
Cuba, Ecuador, France, Mexico and
the United States.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 4 JANUARY) 95 !
BRIEFING FOR A MISSION : Members of Unesco's Educational Mission to Burma assembled
at Unesco headquarters in Paris for a briefing shortly before they left for Burma. This photo
shows : (from left to right) Mr. M. Jimsai, Head of the Missions Section of Unesco's Department
of Education ; Mr. Francis T. Fairey, of Canada ; Mr. Richard M. Tisinger, of the United States and
Mr. Luciano Hernandez, of Mexico. On the extreme right is M. Edmond Sidet, of France, who
left for Afghanistan last month as technical adviser to the government and to follow up the work
done by the government and the Unesco mission which visited the country in 1949.
THERE are 2, 750, 000 children ofschool-going age in Burma,
but only 54, 000 receive even
the rudiments of school training.
At least 50 % of the schools have
been totally destroyed by war and
30 % have been badly damaged.
The shortage of trained teachers
is desperate, and facilities for
training them are inadequate, in a
country where technical develop-
ment has been retarded so long.
Along with providing children with
adequate instruction, it is equally
important that teaching be provi-
ded for millions of illiterate adults.
Such a vast programme require. s
heroic efforts by the government
of Rangoon and it can be enorm-
ously speeded by experienced assis-
tance. Accordingly, Unesco has
sent three experts to Burma to
study problems relating to funda-
mental and adult education, de-
velopment of primary and secon-
dary instruction, technical training
and vocational guidance, training
of teachers and allied administra-
tive problems. At the conclus. ion
of their investigation and subse-
quent report, these experts will
help the Burmese government to
carry out the measures which they
have recommended and which the
government has approved.
The three specialists chcsen by
Unesco are men experienced in this
work. Mr. Luciano Hernandez was
Director of Education for the state
of Chiuahua in Mexico. Mr. Ric-
hard M. Tisinger and Mr. Francis
T. Fairey have both worked on
educational problems among In-
dian tribes, one in the United
States, the other in British Colum-
bia. Mr. Tisinger, in charge of the
mission, will devote himself to pro-
blems in primary school instruc-
tion and teaching administration,
Mr. Fairey to secondary school
teaching and technique, Mr. Her-
nandez to fundamental education.
This is not the first time that
Unesco has assisted in such work.
Similar missions have been sent to
the Philippines, to Afghanistan
and to Thailand. One has been
working in Bolivia for several
months. Each of them, within
the programme of general educa-
tional improvement, has been given
a special task directed to the local
needs of the country concerned.
Basic Needs-Special Problems
THE Philippine mission, like the
one in Burma, had to take war
losses into account, as well as
problems in primary and secondary
instruction, adult education, train-
ing of teachers and administra-
tive difficulties related to teaching.
In the Philippines, 8, 300 schools
were totally and 3. 887 partially
destroyed, 95 % of school equip-
ment was lost, scarcely 5 % of the
collections in the National Museum
were preserved intact, and 694, 000
out of a total of 730, 000 volumes
are missing from the National
Library.
In Afghanistan, among other
major problems, school attendance
and children's access to primary
schools, were given special study :
less than 10 % of the boys, and
less than 0. 33 % of the girls
receive primary school instruction
in Afghanistan.
In Bolivia, the most urgent need
is adult education and the mission
of experts is giving primary im-
portance to a campaign against
illiteracy. At present, out of a
population of 3, 700, 000 people, it is
estimated that 2, 000. 000 are totally
illiterate.
In addition to such basic needs,
each country presents its educators
with special difficulties. In Afgha-
nistan, for instance, there is the
problem of a nomadic population ;
in Bolivia, one of the principal
obstacles is the inaccessible moun-
tainous terrain which bars normal
communication between the diffe-
rent small mountain settlements
and with the nearest centres.
The experts sent by Unesco do
not work separately. All their
work is done, ot only in co-ope-
ration with the authorities of the
country concerned, but with the
support, and in consultation with,
local educationists. Unesco also
makes available to the members of
each mission, the findings of simi-
lar organisations, received at its
headquarters in Paris from all over
the world.
Unesco is attempting, through
these missions, to provide a
common pool of experiences-
experiences which would otherwise
never be known-and whose va-
lue is immeasurably increased
through this method of collation.
UNIVERSITIES
OUND FIRST WORLD
ASSOCIATION AT
NICE CONFERENCE
THE world's first International
Association. of Universities
was set up in Nice, France
last month at a one-week meeting
(December 4-10) attended by dele-
gates representing universities in
53 countries.
Assembled in the Mediterranean
University Centre, more than 200
delegates unanimously approved
the constitution and programme of
the new association and elected
M. Jean Sarrailh, Rector of the
University of Paris as president and
Dr. S. C. Roberts, Vice-Chancellor
of Cambridge University as vice-
president.
The main purpose of the associa-
tion, whose headquarters will be
in Paris, is to give universities
greater solidarity through mutual
assistance. The International Uni-
versities Bureau will work in Paris
as the Association's Secretariat and
will constitute a centre of statisti-
cal studies in all branches of uni-
versity life.
By spreading among universities
better knowledge of each other's
curricula and methods of orgar`3-
tion, the Bureau will help to solve
such problems as the equivalences
of degrees and diplomas issued by
higher education authorities in all
parts of the world. A programme
of long-term exchanges of profes-
sors among universities will also be
considered as well as the role that
universities can play in the United
Nations Technical Assistance Plan.
Universities'Mission
FOR its main discussion lastmonth, the Conference chose
the theme of the mission of
universities in the modern world,
the opening speakers being Ber-
nardo Houssay, the Argentine phy-
siologist and Nobel prize winner ;
George Zook, the American histo-
rian and president of the Ameri-
can Council on Education ; and
Pierre Auger, the French physicist
and head of Unesco's Natural
Sciences Department.
Addressing the Conference at its
opening session, M. Jaime Torres
Bodet, Unesco's Director-General,
congratulated the delegates on
their choice of this subject for de-
bate.
"There is little likelihood of the
various dogmatisms of today allow-
ing the universities to become
sanctuaries isolated from the
upheavals of the outer worlds,"he
said,..... 1 am not proposing that
the separate domains of politics and
universities should in the smallest
degree be merged or confused... it
is essential that universities should
hold aloof both from party strife
and from the official ideologies,
that they jealously guard their in-
dependence and their serenity. But
independence does not mean indif-
ference, nor serenity mental blind-
ness. There is no reason why im-
partial teaching based on the
strictest scientific objectivity
should give the impression of flying
from reality and thus leave she
young who are taught i11-equipped
to cope with the world.
Is Youth Prepared ?
"THE gap between scientific
and everyday knowledgeis
growing ever wider. What
the scientist describes is less and
less at the level of being at which
we live... the initiate is cut off from
the everyday world at once by the
narrowness and profundity of this
learning.
"For the university to train
scholars and specialists is very well,
but it must not so confine them to
their own subjects as to leave them
helpless before the general pro.
blems presented to all our con-
sciences by a world of which we
have scarcely yet begun the mate-
rial organization.
.. Universities must not be mere
museums of thought, The object of
research laboratories, of enquiries
and studies, of card indexes of li-
braries and private scholars, is of
course to aid the advance of science
- but also to promote the progress
of man and of society,"
NEXT summer, a chartered plane willleave the United States for India.
carrying a group of educators, speak-
ers and writers-members of a Seminar
. organized by the San Francisco State Col-
lege-to study social and economic con-
editions, the political situation and aspect
of religion and philosophy in India. Pakis-
tan and Ceylon.
Combined with the Seminar Is a u. sèfuJ
plan for international excha. : lge.' The
Seminar organizers and the Indian autho-
rities are hoping to arrange for 50 Indian
stude : J. ts to travel to the United States 
tilde. plane which will. fly the Seminar...
members to India. Later, the student'
will go home in the plane that brings
back the group of Americanas.
Making maximum use of the plane's cap-
acity in both directions will enable the
stude : lt3 to travel for very low fares and
thus make possible a visit that would
normally have been beyond the means of
most of them.
IN THE WAKE OF KOREAN WARFARE : This open air class (above, left) was set up amid the ruins of a primary school In the
village of Eum Pyung, north of Seoul. Before it was demolished by artitiery fire during the fighting for the Korean capital, the school
had 1, 300 students and 23 teachers. When this photo was taken, 12 teachers remained and students were slowly coming back as their
parents returned after taking refuge in the nearby hills. U. N. DAY IN KOREA : (above, right) Korean refugees, carrying whatthey have
been able to salvage from their home, read one of the posters commemorating United Nations Day (October 24) which had been prepared
by a U. N. group organized by Koreans in Seoul immediately after its liberation by United Nations forces.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
JANUARY 195 I Page 5-UNESCO COURIER
Bringing New Life To Sick Regions
LAST month, the Courier announced the approval by Unesco's Executive Board ofa $20, 000, 000 plan for the creation over a period of 2 years, of a world network
of Fundamental Education training centres as bases for a world-wide drive against
illiteracy and low living standards. Because the term"fundamental education"has
enormous implications for the future of the world, we present on this page an article on
the needs, purposes and methods of fundamental education, by Conrad J. Opper, former
Director of Education in Mauritius and now Director of Unesco's Fundamental Education
Pilot Project in the Marbial Valley, Haiti.
The story of the Haiti Pilot Project, where such methods have been tested
under the severest conditions, is told in an article and photographs on pages 6
and 7 of this issue.
Fundamental education, w h i c h
H means a mass attack on poverty,
disease and ignorance is one of
the most empirical of activities.
Like the making of tribal lays, there
are nine and ! sixty ways and every
single one of them is right-or can
be. And as the United Nations pro-
gramme of Technical Assistance for
Under-Developed Areas gets into its
stride we shall hear more about plans
for what is variously called mass, basic,
social or fundamental education.
It is a melancholy thought that three-
fourths of the world's people are under-
housed, under-clothed, under-fed and
illiterate. Or, as Lord Boyd Orr has
said, a state of partial famine is affect-
ing nearly half the population of the
world. The problem confronts us in its
massive simplicity. No sociological
survey is necessary to perceive naked
bodies bloated by intestinal worms,
crippled by yaws, or stunted by malnu-
trition.
If we take a plane ticket to almost
any country lying within the tropical
belt (and to a great many others
besides), and then get off the boule-
vards into the countryside, we shall
soon come face to face with the world's
under-privileged areas. Within the
next year or so we are likely to see a
big expansion of efforts first to expose
the problems rio be faced and then to
work out plans for bringing new life
into these sick regions.
Areas are under-developed because
they present problems which have so
far'defied solution with the locally
available resources. While there may
be a great number of different
approaches, there are definitely no
short-cuts. The effects of diseases
which have stricken a region for
generations, habits of sloth springing
from physical debility, superstftion
penetrating to the very roots of society,
cannot be cleared away in a month or
a year, no matter how determined and
vigorous the attack.
Partners With The People
F UXDAME :-1TAL education must aim atchanging lives from within. It us
not impose on a community large
social and economic development
schemes but lead the people patiently
and unobtrusively to work for their
own improvement, using as far as pos-
sible their own social institutions and
their own leadership.
For people fighting a losing battle
against ignorance, disease and poverty,
there is no dramatic action that can
turn defeat into victory at a single
blow. Resource surveys, mobile film
units, bull-dozers and teams of im-
ported technicians-all the para-
phenalia of large-scale development
schemes-have their place, but if the
people themselves are not active part-
ners, everything will wither away as
soon as the alien resources are with-
drawn.
while there is no magic formula and
no stereotyped plan for the establish-
ment of a fundamental education
scheme, a knowledge of the people
themselves is essential 10 success, It
is not enough to have lived amongst
them, to like them, to speak their lan-
guage ; this may ensure sympathy, but
not necessarily understanding.
It is therefore usual to start with a
survey by a trained anthropologist.
This provides the educators with an
intimate knowledge of the indigenous
culture and of any special local pro-
blems. It permits comparisons between
conditions before the educational pro-
gramme and those that might come into
existence several years later.
The anthropologist's special com-
petence is derived from the fact that
he is trained to look at a total culture
from the point of view of the inter-
relations of its various aspects and that
he thinks not in terms of a single cul-
ture but of the different patterns of
social life that exist throughout the
world. He looks for the sources of
social behaviour and ways of thought,
he tracks down forces that make for
cohesion or disintegration. His ex-
perience enables him to indicate the
strength and weaknesses of a given
situation and what elements in the
existing social organization can be made
use of.
Fundamental education must move
forward in the stream of the people's
culture. The anthropologist shows
where this current flows strongest.
The Team Approach
W ORKIXG with existing socialand administrative organizations
means very different things in
different areas. In many parts of
Africa where a tribal organization still
exists, fundamental education may aim
at reinforcing the leadership of pro-
gressive chiefs and at trying to
penetrate the whole structure of local
authority and the culture in which It
is rooted.
In this case, the fundamental educ-
ation campaign may find a coherent if
rigid framework in which to work. but
at the same time pawerful forces of
conservatism and prejudice to over-
come.
Elsewhere there may be no such
tribal authorities but, in their place, a
system of representative government
and a developing sense of social ser-
vice and community organization which
reveals itself in cooperatives. Women's
Institutes, 4h Clubs (Head, Heart, Hand,
Health) and the like. Here the ground
is already prepared for the fundamen-
tal education project.
Other sets of circumstances are found
in the mission fields, the industrial area,
the plantation, each iwith its separate
organization. Other problems exist in
areas where tribal authority has
weakened or broken down and no-
thing with roots in the people's own
culture has grown up in its place.
The usual and most successful
approach to fundamental education is
through the team. Sometimes the
leader chooses his own team, sometimes
its members are appointed by the
various agencies collaborating in the
Project. These may be missionary
societies pooling their resources in a
common effort or Government depart-
ments, each providing a technician as
a member of a Community Develop-
ment team, or as in the case of the
Unesoo Pilot Project In Haiti, Special-
ised Agencies of the United Nations
working with the local government.
The leader would probably hope to
be able to assemble a team consist-
in of an educationist, an agrono-
mist, a doctor, a woman social
worker, and an expert in small indus-
tries. These would be his mainstays,
each responsible for a wide fleld of
human activities, pushing out his enter-
prises in every possible direction, im-
pinging on but not overlapping the work
FIGHTING ILLITERACY
IN N) ND) A.-"Literacy awa-
kens the mind and provides
incentive for further effort".
Above, young volunteers
teach men and women attend-
ing a social education class
at a village in the Central
Provinces.
FUNDAMENTAL EDUC-
ATION BY RADIO.-The
Lusaka Radio Station broad-
casts, $ :-ClYs, talks and feature
.. ; ; r."grammes on hygiene, hus-
bandry, soil conservation and
sanitation to native popul-
ations in Northern and Southern Rhodesia and Nyasaland. Many thous-
ands of people already listen to these programmes thanks to a cheap and
robust battery radio receiver, produced specially to meet their needs.
of fellow-workers. The M'home plan
wound gradually take shape in the field.
Literacy-The Basic Need
A literacy programme must be thefoundation of the team's"oper-
ations. Literacy awakens the
mind, provides incentive for further
effort and ma'kes it possible to impart
knowledge about the team's objectives.
The adult class also becomes the forum
for discussion, an important develop-
ment in ensuring that plans are pre-
pared not for the people but with the
people. The literate has to be kept
fed with reading matter or his new
skills are soon forgotten and the pro-
vision of simple booklets, a monthly
journal and occasional leaflets on spe-
cial subjects, is one of the team's most
important tasks.
Since illiterates must be taught through
the medium of their mother tongue, the
production of reading material mav
well involve orthographieai experiment
and research into local folklore and
legend. The members of the team will
provide much of the raw material for
book production and a competent local
translator will be essential. From the
primary schools will spring youth or-
ganizatIOns, from the adult or literacy
schools will germinate cooperatives and
perhaps some cultural or recreational
cubs.
The agronomist
must take care of the
soil, what grows on
it and the domestic
animals it supports.
lie must make plans
for soil conservation,
reforestation, irrig-
ation, the improve-
ment of farming me-
Iliods and animal
husbandry. He works
bY demonstration ra-
lIìer than by homih'.
Peasants are the
same the world over,
cautious, wedded to
custorn and suspi-
cious of innovation ;
but a healthy crop
"DO YOU WANT
TO HELP ME ?"
says the Brazilian
worker shown learn-
ing to read from a
literacy primer on
this poster issued
by the Ministry of
Education. Such
posters have a dou-
ble aim-to enlist
aid for Brazil's na-
>tion-wide literacy
campaign and to en-
courage illiterates to
take advantage of it.
growing on a terraced hillside or a two
and a half ounce egg speak louder than
words.
The doctor's most important task is
health education, a programme of vil-
lage sanitation with attention to such
public health undertakings as cleaner
markets, improved water supplies and
anti-mosquito campaigns. The'pro-
vision of medical attention at the Pro-
ject's dispensary should not be a first
call on his time.
Yet at the beginning he may find the
treatment of disease too exigent to
leave him much time for preventive
work. This is a phase that passes and
one which has a high propaganda value
for the project as a whole. Modern
treatments of some tropical diseases are
quite dramatic in their effects and this
medical magic provides a favourable
background for the team's other activ-
ities.
Mending Is Tougher
WORK amongst women is highly im-portant as it reaches out to the
whole family although often
much neglected owing to the special
difficulties it presents. A nurse with
training in public health and domestic
science is a godsend. An entry to the
peasant home is made most easily
through the kitchen. Sewing classes
and talks on baby care at the dispen-
sary get at the younger women and
influence the newer families.
Under-employment is a serious pro-
blem in rural areas in the tropics.
Often the cultivator is obliged by cli-
matic reasons to remain idle for more
than one-third of the total wor'king days
of the year. With so much time going
to waste there is much scope for se-
condary occupations. The team must
seek ways of using local materials in
cottage industries to bring some relief
to the universal poverty of these areas.
There is certainly no blue-print for
fundamental education. Everything
will depend on the team resources
available, the human resources of the
people and the hay in which these two
forces are brought together. Patience,
sincerity, a strong sense of missionary
spirit and an occasional lucky break
can work miracles in places where
nothing short of miracles will do.
The world will also have to be a little
patient. Many world problems call for
drastic and urgent solutions and there
is sometimes suspicion of enterprises
that seem to lack this sense of urgency.
woe are often reminded that the im-
perial age of too little and late has pas-
sed. But fundamental education is not
just bull-dozers, penicillin and cinema'
vans ; it is bringing new life to a people.
And in these sombre days, mending a
life is a far tougher job than ending it.
Permission for the reproduction of
this article must be obtained from
the editor of the Courier.
hy ( ;. J. OPPER
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 6
JANUhy) I 
THE MARBIAl VALLEY.-
An.. under-privileged"area ; home of 28, 000
people.
*W N 1947 the government of Haiti
asked Unesco, then a newly
formed organization, to start a
pilot project in Fundamental
Education in the rural region of Mar-
bial-the central area of the Gosse-
line River Valley in the south of the
island.
The population of Marbial was es-
timated at 28, 000 but no one was
quite sure. No census had ever been
taken of its scattered inhabitants
who lived in shacks perched on the
hillside. Conditions in the valley
provided examples of virtually every-
thing bad in the definition"under-
developed region". It was over-
populated, its illiterate peasants could
scarcely live on the scanty crops they
coaxed from the eroding soil and they
were scourged by such diseases as
malaria and yaws.
Conditions in Marbial were a chal-
lenge, and offered a severe testing
ground for fundamental education
methods.
Unesco agreed to attempt the pro-
ject and in April, 1948 it sent a
survey team to Marbial headed by Dr.
Alfred Metraux, an anthropologist.
Conditions when the team arrived
there were at their worst-an eleven
month drought had drained the last
of the peasants'meagre food reser-
ves. The problem of drinking water
- normally acute-was complicated
by the habits of the people who used
the Gosseline River not only as a
source of water for drinking but
with equal impartiality as a laundry
and a, sewer.
Then, when the drought ended, the
road from Marbial to Jacmel, the
nearest town became a torrent
swirling over boulders. Other han-
dicaps were root d in the minds of
the people of Marbial, who, isolated in
their shacks, were deprived of any
community life and subject to the
tyranny of superstition. But as Dr.
Metraux went ahead with his survey,
the people of the valley began to co-
operate, willing to grasp at anything
that promised to lessen their misery.
Valley Of Despair
THE results of this survey weregraphic epough, yet even statis-
tics cannot tell the full story of
life in Marbial. Fifteen per cent of
Nor do the figures show the effects
of an inheritance system which had
sliced the land into tiny plots so sepa-
rated that a man might waste most
of his working day walking from one
holding to another.
With practically no outside income
the valley was forced to become self-
supporting. In lean years, such as
1948, the result was famine and even
in"good times"mal-nutrition was
chronic. Mal-nutrition to a Marbial
peasant meant that he and his family
lived mainly on beans and millet and
ate meat only once a month.
As the valley's soil had disappeared
- washed away by the rains-so had
most of the possessions of its inha-
bitants. People who once lived in
stone houses were huddled into mud
huts with thatched roofs. Their fur-
niture, crockery and even their clothes
had been sold to make up for poor
harvests. Many of them had to
make work clothes from sugar-bags.
Disease ravaged the valley. In 1948,
at the end of the long drought, Dr.
Metraux reported that scarcely a
household was free of malaria. A
large part of the population was
literally crippled by yaws,. many men
and women being unable to walk
because of great sores on their feet.
Less than 500 pupils were regis-
tered in the three schools serving
the valley's 28, 000 inhabitants, and
only about-half of these actually went
to school, because of sickness and the
fact that many pupils had to walk
two hours each way to attend school.
It COME AND
IFARN how to
work si-
sal ; it's a useful
thing and you
can sell it"reads
this poster in
Creole, used in
the campaign to
encourage and
develop cottage
industries.
the valley's land, for example, was
lost to erosion and 70 % was sub-
standard. Such figures, however,
cannot hope to convey the feelings of
hopelessness and despair of the Mar-
bial peasant, vainly trying to squeeze
a few more'measures of grain from
his land and thus inevitably
destroying the soil by failing to fer-
tilize it, to let it lie fallow or to rotate
crops.,
The teachers, Dr. Metraux reported,
had virtually no training, and their
pupils memorized and mechanically
recited passages from fifty year old
French textbooks without any real
understanding of the texts.
Ran let To Education
THERE was a tremendous languagebarrier to education. Although
the official language of Haiti is
French, Marbial's people spoke only
Creole and textbooks in this language
were not available-no one had ever
agreed which of the four methods of
spelling Creole should be adopted.
To attack this aspect of the pro-
blem, Unesco invited Dr. Robert Hall,
an American professor, who had done
research on Creole in the United
States to come to Haiti. Dr. Hall
established an alphabet so that the
preparation of basic textbooks could
go ahead. Although the final ob-
jective was to teach French, the orga-
nisers decided to begin with Creole,
Marbial's mother tongue.
When they heard that something
called"I'Unesco"had come to Marbia !,
the peasants were stimulated into
action. Within a few months their
co-operatives had turned the track to ;
Jacmel into a road, a"Unesco-centre"i
was built in the valley and a commun-
ity-centre, opened nearby, helped the,
people to break out of their isolation. !
ADULT AND PRIMARY EDUCATION..
has opened nine adult schools j"th
teachers to take ove
The co-operatives dug latrines and
sank a well, and soon peasants living
on the surrounding hillsides followed
their example. Thus a start was
made at cleaning up one of the area's
most dangerous sources of disease.
One of Marbial's three schools re-
ceived a supply of desks, blackboards
and pencils, and trained teachers
went into its classrooms to-give de-
monstration lessons. A literacy cam-
paign was started and spread rapidly.
The Man For The Job
ALL this, however, was only a goodbeginning. Dr, Metraux had
completed his survey mission
but the project was slowed down
while Unesco was looking for a Direc-
tor-the man who would put the
results of the survey to use in eo-ope
ration with the people of the valley.
It was an Englishman, Conrad J.
Opper, who had been Director of
Education in Mauritius, who was
finally chosen. When he arrived at
Port-au-Prince, Haiti's capital, at the
beginning of 1950, he began to attack
the project's"Housekeeping Prob-
lems".
Going to work was also a problem
for the road from Jacmel to Marbial
had relapsed into its original state
generations of Marb ! a ! famines have fallen victim (above, right), result in
weakness and apathy among the people and thus bar the way to better living
standards.
Yaws, with its dlsilgunng and crippling
effects (above, left) and malaria, to whichDISEASE AND POVERTY.-
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
JANUþ {Y 19 5 I Page 7-UNESCO COURIER
- a series of vaguely connected
potholes. Transportation difficulties
were partially solved by moving the
project's headquarters from Port-au-
Prince to Marbial.
The new Director and his Haitian
staff soon saw that all progress in
the valley would depend on the
improvement of agriculture. In
February, 1950, Mr. Opper reported :
"There is no possible doubt that a
project in Fundamental Education
in the Marbial area which is not
based on soil regeneration is unreal-
istic and doomed to failure. To cure
the sores of the peasants, to teach
N-The project has kept the Marbial"'c i children's school in operation and
'the surrounding region, training local
over the classes.
them to read and make pottery is
fruitless if we neglect the soil. This
is the one great problem which is a
matter of life and death for the
coming generation of the Valley."
,.
Stn'inH The Soil
THE United Nations Food and
Agriculture Organization (FAO)
was therefore asked. to join in
the Marbial project. In the mean-
time, however, a Haitian agronomist
set to work to protect Marbial's soil
through land terraces and contour
farming. Several miles of terraces
were constructed under his super-
vision. An order for fifty thousand
sisal plants was placed with a
double objective : the planting of sisal
on newly terraced hillsides would
bulwark the valley's eroding soil and
at the same time the weaving of sisal
mats gave promise of becoming a
local industry. By September, Haitian
manufacturers had already placed an
initial order for 1, 000 mats in
Marbial.
This modest agricultural pro-
gramme was aimed only at preventing
Marbial farm conditions from grow-
ing worse. The FAO intends to
enlarge these activities once it begins
its own programme there.
H VWA MABIAL"
(The Voice of Mar-
bial) : The Project's
monthly newspaper
provides the valley with
news, useful informa-
tion and a means of
expression and also fur-
nishes the schools with
additions ! Creole rea-
ding material......'
Another United Nations agency,
the World Health Organization
(WHO), also took an active part in
the project, sending a doctor and a
nurse to the valley. This WHO team
gave 12, 427 treatments, including
3, 493 injections of pencillin procaine
for yaws, during its stay. It also
helped open a new clinic in Mar-
bial, thus giving the valley its first
modern dispensary facilities.
The project's organizers however
pointed out that this first anti-yaws
campaign was only intended to
demonstrate the power of science
over disease. The doctor has now
been replaced by a WHO health
educator and it is up to the people of
Marbial to follow the elementary
rules of health and hygiene they are
being taught.
The project kept the Marbial
children's school in operation and
also opened nine adult schools in the
surrounding region, training local
teachers to take over the classes.
This interest in the schools also
helped to give birth to"Vwa Mab-
ial" (The Voice of Marbial), a two-
page newspaper with a press-run
of 500,
"By The People"
SOURING this perhaps unspecta-cular but steady development,
Mr. Opper and his team kept in
the background as much as possible,
placing the project in the hands of
the people it was intended to help.
This policy proved so successful that
in August the Marbial people formed
THE PEOPLE OF MARBIA.-
Victims of sickness, poverty, malnutrition and'ignorance.
a regional committee of local leaders
with Father Louis Charles, a Haitian
priest, as President, to advise the
Unesco staff.
The formation of such committees
is the key to progress in Fundamental
Education which can only succeed if
it is"by the people, rather than for
the people". Although outside tech-
nical assistance is needed to give
basic skills and knowledge, any
assistance programme which makes
use of bulldozers and blueprints
without attempting to create a
popular understanding and acceptance
of its objectives is bound to die once
the visiting specialists leave.
In Marbial, Unesco is not building
a false prosperity which relies on the
maintenance of an outside mission,
for such prosperity would not last
after the project ended.
What, Unesco has done for Marbial
is more than counter-balanced by
what the Haitians there have done
for the Organization and for other
"under-developed"peoples around the
world, for the project hag"taught
the teachers"many things they need
to know in dealing with similar
problems-and similar problems
affect more than half the earth's
people.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 8 JANUARY 1951
A
LITTLE more than 100 years haue passed since the H..'orld's
first"public libraries"u.,'ere established in Great Britain.
To-day, libraries are becoming more and more dynamic
and vital elements vn the daily lives of people-and more
and more rar ; pd in their activities. A. ccordingly, lve present stories
of two enormously different libraries-one in India and one in
Seu'Zealand. They hare this, in common, that they make posi-
tire contributions to better lires for the people,
IN NEW ZEALAND-
LIBRARIES FIND THE PEOPLE
Literacy must be followed up. The Delhi Library being set up by Unesco and
the Government of India is aimed primarily to meet the needs of persons
just learning to read, who without practice might slide back into illiteracy.
IN INDIA-A NEW LIBRARY
FOR NEW READERS
APUBLIC library of a new kind-especially designed to meet the
needs of readers using books for
the first time in their adult lives
- is to be opened early this year in
the city of Delhi, India. The institu-
tion is the result of an agreement
between the Government of India and
Unesco, providing for a pilot project
to show how public library services can
effectively support literacy and adult-
education campaigns.
The library is to be housed in a
crowded part of the city, in a building
with ample room for book services and
educational meetings, and a spacious
court for outside reading during the
summer. The services will stress the
needs of adults just learning to read,
taking over where the current literacy
campaigns of the Indian Government
leave oft. Adult readers, newly-liter-
ate, will be helped to improve their
efforts in self-education.
HODELFORTHE FUTURE
D URINO the first year, the librarywill assembly a collection of
about 10, 000 books, plus periodi-
cals, pamphlets, maps and pictures.
Most of the material will be in Hindi
and Urdu but some books in English,
particularly reference books, will be
provided. There also will be services
for children and young people.
Books are to be lent free for home
use, and advisers will help the bor-
rowers, particularly those who have
just learned to read, to plan appro-
priate courses of reading. Reading
interest is to be stimulated through
film showings, discussions, publication
of reading lists, gramophone record
concerts, exhibitions and story-hours
for children.
Unesco's interest in the library
extends far beyond Delhi, for the pro-
ject is intended not only as an end in
itself but as a demonstration of what
can be done. When the project proves
its usefulness, mother cities in India and
in other parts M Asia will be encou-
raged to use it as a model.
The Delhi library programme will
be integrated with the work of local
organizations in the fields of funda-
mental and adult education, especially
with that of the Delhi Education
Board and Jamia Millia, a Muslim
voluntary organization. The former
now operates seven adult education
centres and sixteen literacy centres,
and plans to add nineteen more
centres to its present network. Jamia
Millia operates five centres in Delhi.
One of the critical problems in
developing the project will be the
provision of publications. Many books
in Hindi-one estimate is 2, 000-which
are suitable for the general reader
with some formal education, have
been published in the last five years.
But there is a great shortage of easy-
to-read books for adults and appro-
priate publications for children. Jamia
Millia has published 250 sixteen-page
pamphlets for newly-literate adults,
and has prepared 200 additional manu-
scripts in the local languages. But the
stock of all but fifty of the published
manuscripts was destroyed by a fire,
and publishers are unwilling to reprint
the old pamphlets or publish the new
ones at a price the average man can
afford. An effort will be made to solve
this problem, and ways of stimulating
the production of easy-to-read adult
books and publications for young peo-
ple in Hindi and Urdu will be studied
by the librarians of the new instit-
ution.
By the terms of the agreement
between Unesco and the Govern-
ment of India, Unesco is contributing
a fellowship for study abroad to the
Indian librarian who will be per-
manent director of the pilot project.
Unesco will also pay the salary of a
temporary foreign director to carry out
the organizational activity, and will
provide technical advice and funds for
publicity. In addition, Unesco will
purchase an audio-visual library van
for the project and pay the salary of
the permanent director during 1951.
A second fellowship may also be con-
tributed for a children's librarian, and
it is proposed to ask future Unesco
General Conferences to continue the
financial assistance.
PIONEER VENTURE
THE Government of India is contri-JL buting 150, 000 Rupees ($31, 175i
and use of the building provided
by the municipality of the city of
Delhi for the establishment and ope-
ration of the projet. The agreement
also provides for a further annual
grant of 25, 000 Rupees ($5, 196) contri-
buted by the city of Delhi.
Staff members of the library, who
are granted fellowships, will prepare
themselves for their work by studying
public library methods in other coun-
tries, and on their return will work
with the temporary foreign director in
assembling the book collection and
organizing the services of the project.
While these services will emphasize
primarily the needs of persons just
learning to read, who without practice
might slide back into illiteracy, they
will also take care of more advanced
readers. The pilot project, in addition
to being a pioneer venture in a special
field, will be developed to fit local
educational needs of all kinds.
NEW ZEALANDERS are borrowingover three million more books a
year than they were in 1938. Yet
the number of public libraries has
hardly changed since that time, and
the total stock of books has not
increased to any large extent, accord-
ing to a census taken this year.
Public library membership, however
has almost tripled in twelve years,
rising from 93, 863 to 250, 125. This, in
a country with a population of two
million living in widely scattered areas,
shows a striking development in the
use of libraries. It is mainly due to
the work of a branch of the New Zea-
land library system known as the
Country Library Service. It was
founded in 1938 to improve and
broaden library facilities in country
districts by providing a national stock
of books which could be loaned to local
libraries.
In the country districts of New Zea-
land, where the people live on isolated
farms, the highlight of the week is
usually a trip to the nearest small town,
in a car large enough for the whole
family. The trip nearly always inclu-
des a visit to the library. For during
the long winter evenings from July to
November, the New Zealand farmer
and his family like to gather round
the open fire after their evening meal,
and read or listen to the radio before
going to bed.
SMALL TOWN SERVICE
ONE of the first aims of the newService was to create a group of
free lending libraries in these
small towns. It offered to give town
and borough libraries serving popul-
ations of less than 2, 500 fifteen books
for every 100 of population, on con-
dition that free library systems were
started. The service has since been
extended to cover all town and borough
libraries regardless of size of popul-
ation.
As a result of the Country Library
Service supply of books, nearly 90 town
and borough libraries now provide free
services. The books are changed at
least three times a year, and the Ser-
vice's large grey vans, accompanied by
skilled librarians, are a familiar sight
in the smallest towns and villages.
These public libraries in turn send
books to local hospitals and instit-
utions.
Apart from encouraging free libra-
ries, the Country Library Service also
lends about 60, 000 books each year to
small independent subscription libra-
ries which cannot afford to run a free-
lending system. Nearly 700 of these
libraries receive loans of books for
which they pay a small annual charge.
ANTIDOTE
TO ISOLATION
IN isolated places, such as valleys upin the mountain , w ere there are
only a few solitary farms, travelling
hampers of books are sent to groups of
readers for a small yearly subscription.
The books are passed around among
the inhabitants of the farms, and
returned periodically for exchange.
Lonely lighthouse keepers, coast guards
and others who are cut off completely
from any library service are supplied
free with books.
In the last few years, the Country
Library Service has been establishing
free libraries in the new towns and
settlements growing up round national
development projects, such as big hy-
dro-electric installations. In addition
to providing reading material for many
workers leaving the towns to live in
these settlements, a special request
service permits engineers and spe-
cialists on tne job to keep in touch
with latest developments in their
field,
Readers using any of these various
facilities can request special books
which will be supplied to them on
short-term loans either from head-
quarters stock or from other libraries.
The service also arranges for smaller
libraries to borrow whole collections or
books on particular subjects, such as
anthropology, industrial management,
etc., which gives their readers a chance
to see books which normally only
large-well-stocked libraries would keep.
In the country dis-
tricts of New Zea-
land and in ma-
ny other countries
where people live
on isolated farms,
the highlight of the
week is usually a
trip to the nearest
small town-and a
visit to the library.
Sometimes the li-
brary is housed,
like that shown
at right, in the local
grocery store.
Travelling libraries
-"bibliobuses"-
have done much to
solve the problem
of providing a re-
gular supply of
books for people
living in rural dis-
tricts or outlying
city areas. Here,
children choose
their books inside
a library on wheels.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
JANUARY 1951 Page 9-UNESCO COURIER
Scientists Urge International Co-operation
,
PROPOSALS for a world-wide survey of
scientific research and other proposals
dealing with scientific research and the
improvement of living conditions for
mankind are to be presented to the Sixth Ses-
sion of Unesco's General Conference in Paris
next June. Forming part of the Unesco
Natural Sciences Department's programme,
they are a recognition of the fact that
adequate scientific knowledge alone can prov-
ide a sure basis for human welfare.
Background to these projects is the uneven
distribution of the world's scientific resources
and the knowledge that to meet some of
science's requirements, research must be
conducted on an international scale.
M. Torres Bodet, Unesco's Director-General,
stressed this recently at the International
Conference of Universities when he said :
"The high cost of equipment, the nøed for
highly specialized, and hence very scarce,
staff, the very naturc of research and the
necessity for comparing observations recorded
at widely separated points in the world, all
alike make four the desirability of establishing
centres or laboratories operating on a world
basis indispensable for the advencement of
such disciplines as astronomy, meteorotogy,
cartography, oceanography or geophysics".
Certain aspects of the problem have already
been studied, following the decision of the
Economic and Social Council in 1946 to invite
the Secretary-General of the UN to submit a
general report on the problem of establishing
United Nations Research Laboratories. An
extensive investigation was made by the
Secretary-General of United Nations in 1947,
This inquiry dealt with (a) the current feeling
in scientific circles throuhout the world,
regarding international action to achieve the
most effective organization of research ; (b)
those fields where international work would
be most productive and immediately desirable.
RESEARCH CENTRE PRIORITIES
In August, 1949, a committee of experts fromUnesco and United Nations examined the
results of this inquiry and recommended the
following priorities in the Natural Sciences.
First priority : International Computation Cen-
tre ; lnternational Brain Institute.
Sceund priority : International Astronomical
Laboratory ; International Institute of Bio-
chemistry, ; International Meteorological Insti-
tute ; International Research Laboratory on
Arid Zone.
The committee also studied other proposals
concerning problems in the Technical Assis-
tance programme, and drew the attention of
the United Nations and specialised agencies to
further projects worthy of consideration.
In August 1950, an ECOSOC resolution
invited Unesco to prepare a detailed plan
for the setting up of an International Comput-
ation Centre.
The next session of Unesco's General Confe-
rence is to be asked to agree that a world-
wide survey of scientific research be carried
out, concentrating on those fields outlined by
the Expert Committees ; that steps be taken
to organise and establish an International
Computation Centre ; and that consideration
be given to the establishment of a European
Regional Physics Laboratory for High Energy
Particles and an International Brain Institute.
ASPECTS OF MODERN SCIENCE
THE PRINCIPLE OF INDETERMINACY
ALL natural science is based onobservation. Whether our
knowledge of any segment oí
the external world remains at the
level of a mere cataloguing of
facts, or soars to the heights of
Relativity or of Quantum Theory,
observation of Nature as she really
is constitutes the foundation of
science, and all else is secondary.
There is one aspect of the
business of making observations
that is usually taken for granted,
and that is the faith (for this is all
it amounts to) that any observation
made here and now may be expect-
ed again on any other occasion
when the same conditions prevail.
This proposition is sometimes call-
ed"The Uniformity of Nature"or
the"Constancy of the Universe».
But whether mere faith or someth-
ing else, it works. It is science's
answer to the ancient beliefs in
capricious demons and deities.
Despite the bewildering diffe-
rences between one science and
another, all of them advance lar-
gely by the same general tactics :
observations are made, quantities
are measured (where possible),
results are correlated, theories are
set up and general conclusions are
drawn in the form of natural laws.
The great scientific conquests of
Galileo and Newton, of Darwin and
Pasteur, were made according to
this kind of campaign plan.
A Mechanistic Approach
W HAT we call classical physicsattained a high state of per-
fection toward the end of the last
century. Evolving largely from
ordinary mechanics, it went for-
ward on the assumption that all the
events taking place in space and
by Ira M. FREEMAN
time have the objective character
that we associate with common
mechanical phenomena such as the
falling of a stone or the swinging
of a pendulum.
Early in the nineteenth century
the great French mathematician
and physicist Laplace made the
much-quoted statement that an
omniscient mind, knowing the mo-
mentary location and speed of
every atom in the universe, could
deduce the entire course of events
in the cosmos, both past and future.
The universe was thus viewed as a
machine, with all the parts rigor-
ously interlocked. Every event
was held to be strictly determined
by the preceding one ; every effect
was ascribed to a definite cause.
Later, this mechanistic approach
began to be challenged when
scientists learned to break up the
physical world into its basic consti-
tuents. The ubiquitous quantum
aspect of nature (see"What is the
Quantum Theory"in the Courier
for Nov., 1950) began to assert it-
self once more, and in several
places.
In 1927, a brilliant young theore-
tical physicist, Werner Heisenberg,
was able to state a highly signifi-
cant generalization relative to the
observation and measurement of
elementary processes. It is called
the Principle of Indeterminacy. In
one way of phrasing it, the rule
asserts that the more closely we
determine the location of a particle,
the less accurately are we able to
specify its motion, and vice versa.
Heisenberg contends that the un-
derlying cause of this puzzling
situation is the fact that every
NATURE CONSPIRES TO PREVENT DIRECT OBSERVATION
OF BEHAVIOUR OF SUB-ATOMIC PARTICLES
process of measurement or obser-
vation actually interferes with
what is being measured or observ-
ed.
Light of long wavelength does not disturb the
electron we are trying to observe, but neither.
is any of it reflected. The result is that we
do not observe the particle at all !
light of shcrt wavelength can be reflected,
enabling us to observe the electron, but
this kind of radiation is so energetic that it
knocks the particle away. This kind of inter-
ferencg is unavoidable in all atomic measur-
ements.
The Evosfve Electron
F FOR example, if we should wish
to"see"directly a single elec-
tron, it turns out that it would be
necessary to use light of very short
wavelength for the purpose. But
light of this kind is highly energe-
tic, and if thrown at an electron
would knock it completely out of
its original position, thus defeating
what we are trying to accomplish !
In the same way, there is a fun-
damental inexactness, an uncon-
trollable or indefinable element,
inherent in aU measurements relat-
ing to elementary processes. Of
course, in dealing with ordinary
large-scale objects, the interaction
between object and observer be-
comes vanishingly small, and things
seem to behave in their accustomed
way, but on the sub-atomic scale,
the obvious connection between
cause and effect is no longer in
evidence.
After all, nature does seem to be
governed by order and regularity,
and so if strict causality is not va-
lid in the submicroscopic realm,
what takes its place ? The answer
is that what we observe in coarse-
grained experience is a statistical
orderliness-the average beha-
viour of a multitude of individual
entities-and such an average is
accurately predictable. It is pre-
dictable in the same way that the
death rate in a given population
group may be computed in advance
by a life-insurance company, a :-
though there is no way of forecast-
ing when a given individual is
going to die.
Chance rules the activity of the
individual sub-atomic particles of
physics, but their "cultural" or
"crowd"behaviour, as mirrored by
the large-scale world of ordinary
experience, turns out to be comple-
tely in accord with expectation.
The recognition of this fact has
been of vast importance to the
development of modern science,
and has had profound and far-
reaching effects on philosophical
thinking as well.
If you are interested in reading
more about the Principle of Indeter-
minacy, write to the Division for the
Popularization of Science, Unesco,
19 Avenue KIeber, Paris, for a brief
bibliography on this subject, which
will be sent free of charge.
ROYAL SOCIETY PLANTS
MEMORIAL SCHOLARSHIPS
FOR LORD RUTHERFORD
Britain's famed Rogal Society is seekingto establish memorial scholarships in
honour of Lord Rutherford, the pioneer
uf nuclear physics. An appeal has been
issued for subscriptions to a memorial fund
which, it is hoped, will reach a total of
£100,000. .
The money will be used to set up
Rutherford Scholarships tenable for three
years, to be awarded to postgraduate stu-
dents within the British Commonwealth,
and a Rutherford, Memorial Lecture to be
delivered in New Zealand-where the
great scientist was born in 1871 - and
elsew/IPre in the Commonwealth oversees.
It is also proposed to arrange for the publi-
cation of his collected papers ann, for the
collection, arrangement and binding of
copies of his correspondence.
Rutherford's inspired interp/'elation of
his observations, and his genius for
experiment, lerl to practically all we know
about the structure of atoms. Ile developed
the theory of the atom in Montreal; the
final convincing proof he provided at Jean-
chester, where he showed conclusively that
an atom contains a central nucleus wchich
is the seat of intense electdc forces.
Through his investigations of the struc-
tu/'e of the nucleus itself, he founded in
the Cavendish Laboratory, Cambridge, the
modern science of nuclear physics. Ile
allcays worked on problems at the limits
of human knowledge, inventing and deve-
loping the methods used for observation in
these new fields. Ilis uncanny judgement
and his sheer energy made him the greatest
physical scientist of his age. The practical
results of his work-atomic energy and
its by-products-followed a lifetime of
devotion to the pursuit of knowledge.
It is probable that Rutherford will be
remembered equally for his great powers
of inspiring others. By his personality and
forceful leadership his colleague and stu-
dents'were stimulated to reach heights of
achievement which they could not have
reached alone.
From his laboratories came many of the
world's leaders of physical science to-day :
all countries have felt the impact of his
inspiration through the influence of scien-
tific men trained by him. Moreover he did
not confine his interest to purely academic
science. For many years, as Chairman of
the Advisory Council of he Department of
Scientific and Industrial Research, he gave
wise guidance to the Government in the
encouragement and extension of the use of
the scientific method in industry.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 10 JANUARY) 95
It happened in January...
HENRI BERGSON
When Henri Bergson died in
Paris, on 4th January, 1941, at the
age of 81, the general public and
perhaps philosophical circles as
well, believed that he had died
many years before. Yet a rather
disturbing piece of news circulat-
Bd before his death : that Bergson
had returned his decorations and
renounced all his titles, as a
protest against the Vichy anti-
semitic laws ; he refused any kind
of exemption and ordered himself
to be taken, paralytic though he
was, to the police station where
all Jews were compelled to
register. There was a lapse of
more than 25 years between the
publication of his sensational
"Creative Ecolution"in 1907 and
that of his more conservative
"Origin of Momls and Religion",
The world had forgotten the time
when the name of Henri Bergson
was a password and his philoso-
phy a magical force.
ROBERT
S. BADEN-POWELL
Due tribute must be paid to
this General, sixth son of an
Oxford professor for the thous-
ands and millions of boy scouts
and girl guides throughout the
world to-day, the younger groups
of Cubs and Brownies playing
Red Indians in the thickets and
fields, badge-proud youngsters
hiking on the highways, develop-
ing their tracking-sense in the
forest, their social instincts under
a tent-roof, and their sense of
poetry around a camp-fire.
Baden-PoweH was a man with a
distingubhed military career in
India, Afghanistan and South
Africa, but. his main life's work
was to found in 1908 the Boy
Scouts, and two years later, help-
ed by his sister Agnes, the Girl
Guides. When he died 10 years
ago, on 8th January 1941, he had
seen the astounding progress of
this movement begun, as he loved
[0 explain,"for the pU1'pose of
tmining boys in the essen'tials of
good citizenship".'.
BALTASAR GRAOAN
Baltas3r Gracian y Morales was
born on January 8, 1601 at Bel-
monte de Calatayud in Spain. At
an early age he entered the Jesuit
Order. From 1637 he published
his main works :"eel Héroe y el
Discreto" (contrasting the quali-
ties of a typical courtier and the
ideal man) ;"El Oraculo manual"
and"Agudeza y Arte de Ingert'io"
(a system of rules for the conduct
of life) ;"E< Criticon" (an ingeni-
ous philosophical allegory of
human existence agamst a back-
ground which vividly shows the
rich attainments and deep unrest
of that epoch. Schopenhauer
described this major work as"one
of the best books in the world",
and Defoe is said to have found in
El Criticon the germ of"Robinson
Cl'usoe".
Because he published the first
part of" Criticon"without
consulting his religious Order,
Gracian fell out of favour with
his superiors. Two years later,
he committed a similar offence
and was deprived of his profess-
orship and publicly reprimanded.
Banished from Saragossa, he was
sent to the College of Graus, and
later to Tarazona, where he died
in 1658,
FRANCIS BACON
One day, a
man weary of
abstractions
and formal lo-
gic, decided
that only di-
rect experience
could lead to
the attainment
of pure truth.
When he was
born in Lon-
don, on 22nd
January 1561, Francis Bacon
was pre-destined to study Finance
and Law in which he became an
authority."But he was fitted for
nuthing so'well as for the stuäy of
truth... gifted by nature with
desire to seek, patience to doubt,
fondness to meditate, slowness to
assert, readiress to consider,
carefulness to dispose and set yin
order'... a man that neither affects
what is new nor admits'what is
old, and that hates every kind of
impostul'e. So I thought my
nature had a kind of familiarity
and relation with Troth".
This searching examination of
conscience led to works that are
world-famous : the"Novum Orga-
num"is a particularly noteworthy
contribution to human thought.
Its influence on Bacon's contem-
poraries, engaged in similar stud-
ies, was almost negligible, yet a
century later, his influence was
immense. After Locke, the
Encyclopaedists were proud to
call him"the greatest, the most
unit'ersal and the most eloquent
of philosophers".
KUMARAJIVA
1550 years ago, in January 401,
the"Great Translator"Kumara-
jiva arrived in China, where he
devoted ten years to translating
great works from Sanskrit into
Chinese. As a theologian, he had
learned, he said,"the four Vedas,
the five sciences, tie heretic
shastms and the art of astro-
nomy". Languages were his
special study and armed with this
knowledge, he won favour with
the Chinese general -ho had
invaded his birthplace, the Kucha
Oasis in Central Asia. This gene-
ral was to become emperor, and
Kumarajiva lived in China till the
end of his days, engaged in the
monumental task of translating
the holy Scriptures of Buddhism.
"He knew languages so intima-
telly", says tradition,"that he was
able to add greatly to the sum of
philosophic knowledge".
GEORGE FOX
On 13th January 1691, there
died in London the most fiery
preacher of the 1ith Cen-
tury. Beginning life as a shoe-
maker's apprentice, George Fox
believed himself called by God to
leave his village and family and
set out in search of a spiritual
mentor. But he could not
acknowledge any man as his
master and ended by receiving his
lasting inspiration from the Bible
alone, In 1647, he began his
wandering ministry which was to
continue till he was an old man,
visiting churches, interrupting
S81'm, ms to cry out his yer", iLil of
the truth end the precepts of his
mysticism. The police kept an
uneasy surveillance. The refor-
mer spent six years of his life in
all, in different prisons. He
attracted disciples, and a judge
gave them the name by which
they are still known : the Quakers.
George Fox built a church for
this"Society of Friends", one of
whose main purposes was to do
works of charity of the kind for
which they are so well-known in
all continent of the world to-day.
GIUSEPPE VERDI
A series of
lucky events
can be traced
thorough the
life or Giusep-
pe Verdi. His
parents sent
him to work
for a merchant
in Busseto--
who happened
to be a good
enough musi-
eian to recognize his talent and to
introduce him to the Choir-
master of the Cathedral. In 1832
Verdi's application to attend the
Milan conservatorium was refused
- but he became friendly with
one of the professors who assisted
him in his studies. Eight years
later, he produced a comic-opera
which was a miserable failure
but, just in time, another fortuit-
ous friend appeared-the Impres-
sario of La Scala, Milan. Verdi
soon became the most popular
composer in Europe. But the
culminating point in his life came
after Rigoletto, Il Trovatore and
La Traviata, with the astonishing
conversion which caused him to
write Aida, followed by the
Requiem, dedicated to the memory
of Mazzini, which startled the
critics of 1874, but caused Brahms
to call him"inspired", Dating
from this period, his music
became deeper and richer as the
years passed ; Othello and Falstaff
were his two last operas. In the
evening of his life, Giuseppe
Verdi found no subjects worthy
of his art, with the exception of
the"Laudi alla Virgine"from
Dante's Paradiso and the sacred
poems of Stabat Mater and Te
Deum. On 27th January 1901,
Europe mildly mourned the death
of a pleasing composer ; the world
lost a great musician.
Malta Institute Maintains Historic Heritage
Through visits to ancient sites and famous buildings orga-
nized by the Malta Cultural Institute, the people of Malta are
re-discovering their past history. Above, Dr. Edward Sam-
mut, (nearest to doorway) shows the art treasures of St.
John's Cathedral to members of the Institute.
SITUATED at a crossroads ofthe Mediterranean, Malta
has been since the dawn
of history a focal point for the
currents of all the great civil-
izations which have grown
up around its shores and
have spread their influences
throughout Europe and far
beyond.
Held successively by Phoe-
nicians, Greeks, Carthaginians,
Romans and Saracens, and
from 1530 to 1789 by the
Knights of St. John of Jeru-
salem, Malta can look back on
a colourful history. Today,
the cultural influences which
moulded that history are re-
flected in the interests and
activities of one of the island's
organizations-the Malta Cul-
tural Institute.
Since it was inaugurated in
Valetta, nearly two years ago,
the Institute, under the pre-
sidency of Professor Tonna
Barthet, has progressively or-
ganized Malta's cultural activ-
ities and has branched out
into many different intel-
lectual and artistic spheres.
Along with study circles for
Maltese, English, French, Ger-
man, Italian and Spanish
literature and culture, it has
Professor Gaston Tonna Barthet,
Founder, first president and director
of the Malta Cultural Institute.
organized other groups for art,
astronomy and music. Con-
certs and theatrical product-
ions have been held and
lectures given on subjects
ranging from anti-biotics to
tropical fish.
Archaeology has an impor-
tant place among the activ-
ities, for almost every age has
left a heritage to the island,
and the neolithic temples at
Tarxien bear witness to the
existence of a civilization in
Malta many centuries before
the arrival of the Phoenician
and Carthaginian traders.
Already, the Institute has
received books, films and re-
cords from thirty-five govern-
ments and it is working hard
to extend the links that have
been created with similar
organizations in Europe and
America.
With 900 members drawn
from all sections of the
island's population, the Malta
Cultural Institute is making
an important contribution to
the understanding of the
various civilizations to which
the modern world owes much
of its cultural riches.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
JANUARY 195 I Page I I-UNESCO COURIER
done by the Bureau of Reclamation
Venezuela 1s only one of the na-
tions which have used the facilities
of the Denver laboratories. Ship-
ments of soil have come from
Australia for analysis and engi-
neers have travelled from Poland
to put their highway and road pro-
grammes to test in labora-
tories which determine how much
"punishment"concrete can absorb.
In addition to handling mat-
erials, the Denver engineering
centre also trains men. Today,
engineers from Chile, India, China,
France, Palestine, Thailand, Yu-
goslavia, and Egypt are studying
there under a programme which
has brought as many as 800
engineers and officials from fifty-
four countries to the United States
in one year.
KNOWlEDGE FLOWS
TWO WAYS
TECHNKAL ASSISTANCE
- A CASE HISTORY
LAST year, a three tons shipment of assorted soil and rock from the
Latin American Republic of Venezuela arrived in Denver,
Colorado, one mile up in the Rocky Mountains of the United
States, for analysis by the Denver laboratory of the U. S. Bureau
of Reclamation.
The story behind this rather unusual delivery started in a government
office in Venezuela, (where plans for the construction of a cement plant
were being studied.
Venezuelan ofncials wanted to be sure that raw materials on the site
chosen for the plant would ensure its economically sound operation. So
three tons of sample material were taken from the site and sent off to
Denver for examination by engineers and chemists.
This example of how engineers put into practice what is called
"technical assistance for economic development", is typical of the work
up to 300 inquiries a monthconcerning irrigation pro-
jects throughout the world
come into the Bureau and are
answered by the despatch of
experts or technical documents, the
latter going out in thousands of
copies yearly. Michael W. Straus,
Commissioner of the Bureau of
Reclamation, has pointed out that
this is not one-sided aid, since there
is a constant return flow of tech-
nical information from abroad
which is put to immediate use by
American engineers.
Engineers from the Bureau have
gone into the field on such jobs as
the reconstruction of canal systems
in Japan and Venezuela, the build-
ing of earth dams in southern
Rhodesia and the planning of a
hydro-electric power plant in
Greece.
In the Denver laboratories,
studies have been made for irri-
gation projects in New Zealand,
Guam, Portugal and Greece. En-
gineers have even made tests to
determine the design required for
an earthquake-proof dam in the
Himalaya Mountains in Nepal.
The manpower and material
resources of these laboratories are
enormous. The engineering centre
is a principal part of the Denver
Federal Centre, which spreads over
800 acres. The 2, 242 employees,
of whom 858 are engineers, have
at their disposal equipment valued
at $ 2, 505, 000.
BENEFm FOR BIMINITY
THE most spectacular equip-ment in the engineering
centre is a universal testing
machine, capable of exerting either
a squeeze or a pull of 5, 000, 000
pounds on a sample of steel or
concrete. The machine, which
stands fifty feet above the floor of
the laboratory and extends fifteen
feet below, was put into operation
last year to test materials under
compression or tension to an extent
previously impossible to carry out
under laboratory conditions.
Extensive use is made of scale
models in the study of such
structures as dam spillways, canals,
control gates, outlet valves and
pumps. Relief maps also are made
to bring out the physical features
of a project which may cover
hundreds of square miles.
The Bureau of Reclamation was
formed in 1902 with the task of
developing the irrigation, hydro-
electric and related water resources
of seventeen western states in the
United States.
Since then, it has constructed
160 dams and ninety-six reservoirs,
20, 000 miles, of canals, 200, 000
irrigation structures, 107 miles of
tunnels... the statistics seem almost
endless. Translated into human
benefits, these figures equal homes
and livelihoods for 900. 000 persons
through the irrigation of 5, 000, 000
acres of land. It has been estima-
ted that crops worth $ 6, 000, 000, 000
have been grown on the land irri-
gated through the Bureau's work
since 1902, at an investment of
$ 1, 500, 000, 000.
The work done by the Bureau of
Reclamation in a semi-arid area of
the United States stands as an
imposing proof of what can be
repeated elsewhere through tech-
nical assistance on an international
scale.
UNESCO SIGNS TECHNICAL AID AGREEMENTS WITH 13 NATIONS
"THE government will provide or permit
access to adequate information..,
... lDiU give fu l and prompt cons-
leratlon to advice received.., will undertake
'Sllstained efforts to carry forward the work
'initiated or recommended..."
These statements, taken from the texts of
'. greements recently signed by Unesco and
\ ! governments in Asian, Latin American and
Middle East countries, strike a harmonious note
in a world that has become too accustomed to
hearing declarations that this or that nation
has decided to raise still another barrier to
u-operation and the free exchange of informa-
tion.
The agreements, signed by the heads of 13
states or their representatives, enable Unesco
to send technicians to the countries concerned
n give advice and help for their economic
development-the first phase of Unesco's
contribution to the United Nations $20, 000, 000
expanded programme of technical assistance.
The signing of one such agreement-
between the Government of India and Unesco
- is shown in this photograph (left), taken
at New Delhi. It shows, seated, Dr. Malcolm
S. Adiseshiah (left), head of Uneseo's Technical
Assistance Service, and Dr. Tara Chand, Se-
cretary, Indian Ministry of Education. Stand-
ing, left to right, are C. L. Bhardwaj, govern-
ment information officer at Ne) w Delhi ; and
Drs. N. S. Junankar and G. K. Chandiramani,
educational advisers with the Ministry.
Under the agreement, Unesco will send ten
experts to assist India's large scale scientific
research programme in such fields as plastics,
electrical engineering and irrigation.
The twelve other countries which have also
signed agreements that will bring them tech-
nical aid from Unesco are : Ceylon, Columbia,
Ecuador, Iraq, Indonesia, Lebanon, Liberia,
Libya, Mexico, Pakistan, Persia and Thailand.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 12 JANUARY 195 I
CHilD WAR VICTIMS TELL THEIR OWN
STORY ; MILLIONS HEAR
"EVERYBODY'S CHILD"
(Continued from page 1)
British Broadcasting Corporation, Mille Clara Candiani
of Radiodiffusion francaise, and Aldo Salvo of Radio-
Italiana. The party was completed by Edward Ward, who
served as guide, and Jacques Oguse, Unesco sound tech-
nician.
Their first important stop was the Children's Republic
at Mouiin-Vieux, perched high in the French Alps near.....--...... -_......
Grenoble, where 300 child war
victims live, study and work in a
community of their own, directed
by five teachers. Mouiin-Vieux was
a fortunate choice, for its members
presented an hour-long pageant in
song, depicting the history of
France, with skill and beauty
which will be long remembered by
radio listeners of many countries.
Seeking the widest possible var-
iety in methods of caring for
children, the radio reporters went
next to'''Rayon de Soteit" (ray of
sunshine), an institution near Ta-
rascon. There, they found twenty
boys and girls living together in a
big rambling house with foster
parents, all of them working
A BEAUTIFUL HOME-BUT ONLY FOR 35 CHILDREN
together to make the building look
as much like a home and as little
like an institution as possible.
BREATHING SPELL
FROM HARDSHIP
THE last stop in France was at"Narvik", a children's com-
munity near the Riviera
which is supported partly by Nor-
wegian funds."Narvik"is home
for four months to groups of
Spanish refugee children who are
sent there fifty at a time. There,
they take a breathing spell from the
years of hardshi p their fnmilies
ONE OF THEIR JOBS-TO KEEP MUSIC ALIVE...
, ONE OF OUR JOBS-TO REPLACE FEAR WITCH CONFIDENCE
CHILDREN NEED LOVE-ESPE-
CIALLY CHILDREN LIKE THESE
have passed, and try to learn what
it is like to be children-without
the cares of adults.
"Narvik"has nearly everything
to meet the children's needs, except
for a means of transport. This lack
makes it impossible for the children
10 bathe in the Mediterranean.
Another effect is to increase the cost
of running the camp, because of the
cost of haulage.
The caravan rolled into Italy and,
at Milan, its members visited the
"Casa Don Onone dei PiccoU Muti-
latti"-a rehabilitation centre for
war-maimed Italian children. There
they watched disabled youngsters of
all ages, religions and nationalities
living together and learning how to
use the prosthetic appliances they
need to overcome their disabilities.
Milan also offered the caravan a
glimpse of its"Villagio di Madri di
Fanciulli"-"The Village of Mothers
of Children"-where mothers unable
to make ends meet in the outside
world are given a home for them-
selves and their children. The
village's energetic director finds
jobs for mothers and she herself has
become known throughout Milan for
her energetic fund-raising drives.
MESSAGE FROM
"NOBODY'S CHILD"
F
ONE CHILD STEAKS TO THE WORLD-FOR ALL CHILDREN
 OLLOWIXG visits to Italian insti-tutions where the latest
methods in the rehabilitation
of juvenile delinquents were pract-
iced, the caravan moved on to
Switzerland, to record reports of the
work done by the Swiss Red Cross
in child care.
The institutions visited were of
various kinds and the children, too,
were amazingly different, one from
another, as children always are. Yet
in important respects, they were all
tire same. All of the selfless and
devoted grown-ups who have sup-
ported and operated the institutions
need continuing help in their task.
: 111 the children too have continuing
needs for material things, for
training and retraining, guidance,
reassurance and hope for the future.
This message, that"Nobody's
child is everybody's child"is now
being told. Thus, part of the pro-
blem of communication has been
solved, sand it is the grown-ups turn
to speak.
In addition to the programmes
already broadcast or scheduled, the
Badio Division of Unesco's Depart-
ment of Mass Communication has a
wealth of recorded documents ob-
tained by the Radio Caravan. This
material in several languages is
available to broadcasting organiz-
ations throughout the world.
Encouraged by the success of this
new venture in international co-
operation and in the use of radio
for the benefit of mankind, a second
Radio Caravan is now being planned
for 1951.
KEY TO IllUSTRATIONS
The photographs published in this issue
of some of the children's centres visited
by Unesco's Radio Caravan, were taken
by Edward Ward, who served as guide.
Those on page I show : (top) Boys at
the Arese re-education centre in Italy,
where the latest methods of rehabilitation
of juvenile delinquents are practised, and
(bottom, left) Marjorie Banks, of the B. B. C.,
(facing camera) interviewing a boy through
an interpreter at the"Casa Don Orione
dei Piccoli Mutilatti", Milan-a rehabili-
tation centre for war maimed children.
Photographs on this page show : (top)
The valley in the French Alps where the
members of the"Moulin Vieux Children's
Reþublic"recorded a history of France
in song.
(Centre) : A priest and two of the boys
at the"Piccolo Mutilatti"home for war
disabled children, Milan,
(Left, top) : The school at Trubscha-
chen, Switzerland, where unusual methods
are used to encourage the musical and
artistic talents of children.
(Left, centre) : Members of the choir
at the Scuola Citta Pestalozzi, Florence
recording songs for the Radio Caravan.
(Left, bottom) : Children at the"Rayon de
Solei/"home at Pomeyrol, France, take over
the microphone and interview each other.
]]>
</page>
</document>
