<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="071682eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO TheCourier
JANUARY 1987 9 French Irancs
IN SEARCH OF PARTNERSHIP
Cities
without
limits
The world's
homeless
millions
Is the international
community
a myth?
'Progress^ poverty?
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Eloquent hands
50 India
Vijñána kalâ vedi is a cultural centre dedicated to the preservation of the
traditional arts, crafts and sciences of southern India. Situated in a
peaceful village in Kerala State, it was created by Louba Schild in
collaboration with a team of artists and educators from India and
elsewhere, and with assistance from Unesco's International Fund for the
Promotion of Culture and from the Indian Government. The Centre is
open to Indians and non-Indians alike, and throughout the year offers
training courses, lasting from a week up to several months, for people of
all ages. Above, very young children learn how to make mudras, symbo¬
lic gestures of the hands and fingers.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Editorial
"The concept of 'international community' is widely used today. But we
live in an age when international law is increasingly flouted and when the
world, thrown off balance by unequal development, torn apart by
violence and approaching the end of a century whose problems it has
failed to solve, is now preparing to plunge chaotically into the next. In
these circumstances it seems difficult to understand how a notion so
cruelly belied by history can have met with so much success." Such are the
opening words of the article in this issue (see overleaf) in which French
jurist René-Jean Dupuy analyses the concept of the "international
community" in the modern world. An important part of his analysis is
devoted to the supreme political expression of this community, the
United Nations, which he regards as useful and indeed irreplaceable,
despite its flaws and disadvantages, and as "an incomparable means, for
Third World countries, of pressing their case vis-à-vis the wealthy".
On the eve of the 21st century, problems of unusual gravity confront
the global community as it struggles to achieve self-expression. On the
solution of these problems hinges the lasting establishment of a world
order in which peace and justice prevail. Two of these major problems
receive coverage in this month's magazine. The first is the way in which
rampant world demographic growth and the urban explosion in the Third
World are undermining efforts to bring about development and improve
social conditions in the developing countries. Unsurprisingly in this
context, the General Assembly of the United Nations has proclaimed
1987 as "International Year of Shelter for the Homeless" . The second
problem is a consequence of the paradox that poverty not only still exists
in spite of the potential for progress inherent in modern technology but in
some cases is actually becoming more acute or appearing in different
forms, as in the case of those who have been called the "new poor" in
certain technologically advanced societies.
Among the themes examined elsewhere in this issue are: international
cultural co-operation (to which Unesco makes a maj or contribution) , an
important recent archaeological discovery in China, the development of
the reading habit in the Soviet Union, and the survival of traditional
games and sports. These are just some of the many activities through
which the diverse components of the human community are
endeavouring to live "in partnership".
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
January 1987
40th year
Community
Is the international community a myth? 4
by René-Jean Dupuy
Twenty years of cultural co-operation
by Emmanuel Pouchepadass
Cities without limits
by Rafael M. Salas
The world's homeless millions
10
18
Communities
Poverty and progress
Women on the sidelines
by Amadou Moustapha Diop
The 'new poor'
by Giovanni Sarpellon
Domination and deprivation
by Nguyen van Khoa
Class, caste and power
by Ambalal Somabhai Patel
An open book
A Soviet recipe for promoting the reading
habit
by Igor Petryanov-Sokolov
Games, sports and traditions
Treasures from an ancient Chinese
tomb
by Wen Ruitang
UNICEF at forty
A time to live ...
INDIA: Eloquent hands
20
22
24
26
28
30
32
34
2
Cover: Poster by Nicolae Corneliu, Romania.
Photo Michel Claude © International
Association of Art/Unesco
The Courier
A window open on the world
English
French
Spanish
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Macedonian
Serbo-Croat
Slovene
Finnish
Swedish
Basque
	._ ..,._._ ,lJ7rr,
A selection in Braille is
published quarterly in English ,
French, Spanish and Korean
Published monthly in 32 languages Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese Thai
by Unesco
The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
German
Arabic
Japanese
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese
Korean
Swahili
Croato-Serb
Bulgarian
Greek
Sinhala
ISSN 0041-5278
N°l-1987-CPD-87-l-441 A
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Is the international
by René-Jean Dupuy
community a myth}
THE concept of "international com¬
munity" is widely used today. But
we live in an age when interna¬
tional law is increasingly flouted and
when the world, thrown off balance by
unequal development, torn apart by vio¬
lence and approaching the end of a cen¬
tury whose problems it has failed to solve,
is now preparing to plunge chaotically
into the next. In these circumstances it
seems difficult to understand how a no¬
tion so cruelly belied by history can have
met with so much success.
Since the Second World War, in view
of the great disparities between peoples
in a world where States are increasingly
numerous and where force continues to
reign supreme, this concept has been the
subject of critical examination, as a study
of the different doctrines regarding it will
show.
The schools of thought that we call
"harmonist" have a common feature:
they acknowledge, expressed in varying
forms, the existence of an international
community. "Strategist" doctrines, on
the other hand, emphasize the essentially
conflictual character of the international
system and find the concept of interna¬
tional community unacceptable.
An error common to writers who sub¬
scribe to both schools is that they seek to
impose an all-embracing legal frame¬
work, whereas each theory is capable of
explaining only certain features of the
phenomena in question.
Thus, the harmonists are right to stress
the broad areas of co-operation among
nations, but they are wrong to disregard
the permanence of conflict; the strat¬
egists are right to emphasize antagonism
and struggle, but it is unfortunate that
this conflictual aspect occupies their
whole field of vision.
In fact, both sides make the same mis¬
take. They have an equally false concep¬
tion of the international community,
since they can imagine it only as a whole
whose parts are reconciled. The harmon¬
ists anticipate a fraternal community
which, perhaps, will never exist. The
strategists, on the other hand, mistakenly
believe that community presupposes ab¬
sence of conflict; it does not occur to
them that conflict and community are not
incompatible.
And yet the two go together. It may
even be said that unity and conflict are
the two poles of a tragedy which is all the
more overwhelming in that it is part of
our immediate experience. A couple is a
source of conflicts; so is a neigh¬
bourhood, a province or an association;
The First International Poster Salon was
held at the Grand Palais, Paris, in July
1986. It was organized by the International
Association ofArt/Unesco, the Jury of the
French Grand Prix of the Poster and the
NationalAcademy ofStreetArts ofFrance.
The exhibition comprised 600 posters
from 40 countries, from which the
thousands of visitors voted for those they
thought were the best. Firstprize went to a
poster entitled Peace by the U.S. artist
McRay Magleby (left). Reproduced on the
followingpages are otherposters from the
exhibition.
Right, Hiroshima Appeals 1983, by the
Japanese graphic designer Yusaku Kame-
kura, which won second prize in the First
International Poster Salon.
and a nation is an arena for conflicts of
many kinds. How, then, can the interna¬
tional community, if it is to exist, be
conflict-free? Not only can community
and conflict coexist, but it may be argued
that one implies the other. We must
therefore reintroduce the permanence of
interdependence and antagonism into
our analysis. Our method can only be
dialectical.
Let there be no misunderstanding,
however. Our purpose is to study the
opposing and antagonistic forces at work
in the international fabric, without con¬
sidering the possible or desirable out¬
come of those contradictory trends.
There are two ways of using dialectical
reasoning: firstly the finalist dialectic of
Hegel and Marx, which places the thesis
and the antithesis in opposition to pro¬
duce the synthesis. The synthesis carries
with it the promise of progress: this is a
comforting, prophetic form of dialectic,
heralding the dawn of a brighter
tomorrow.
With all due respect to those who pro¬
fess such a dialectic, we do not consider it
a useful exercise to anticipate the future.
It is conceivable that the contradictions of
the modern world are leading humanity
to a higher level of greater reason and
justice, but it is also possible that we are
now teaching the international law of the
days of the apocalypse. For this reason
we shall keep to what I shall term "open-
ended" dialectic.
This dialectic does not yield a syn-
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
HIROSHIMA APPEALS
1983
4
U
\ï
w.
t*
M -*>
w
%
\
s
m
%,
I L
<: m
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
thesis: it remains open-ended because it
leaves each person free to produce a
synthesis if impelled by a moral or scien¬
tific need to do so. Our purpose, mean¬
while, is to study the antagonisms for
their own sake. We accordingly reject
any kind of system, and use dialectic only
as a method, a means of grasping and
understanding present reality and seek¬
ing diversity in all its manifestations. In
short, when we use this method we are
continually challenging systems and re¬
newing our approach to problems.
Dialectic does not necessarily lead
either to salvation or to despair. It does
not claim that humanity will succeed in
achieving inner reconciliation, nor does it
assert that perdition is at the end of the
road; rather, it concurs with the structur¬
alist approach of those who do not be¬
lieve that the line ofprogress runs straight
ahead without any setbacks or U-turns.
We are with those who see the path of
progress as winding through a landscape
of ruins, with fresh obstacles arising all
the time. Factors of progress and factors
of recession cruelly coexist. Whenever
we learn that a new State has ratified a
United Nations' covenant on human
rights, the newspapers tell us that simul¬
taneously, elsewhere, those same rights
have been atrociously violated.
We learn that, in a particular region or
country, a major effort towards develop¬
ment has been accomplished, and that
the people of that country are beginning
to glimpse the possibility of economic and
social liberation. Meanwhile it is revealed
that elsewhere drought, famine and
epidemics are laying waste the region and
destroying the peoples who live there. All
progress is accompanied by a parallel re¬
gress, and when we focus our attention on
the former, we must not close our eyes to
the latter.
If we examine the aspects of law which
constitute evidence for or against the ex-
"While the developing countries are
asserting their sovereignty and their
identity in a great movement of political
individualism, they are at the same time
appealing to the international community,
in the absence of which the rich countries
could shrug off any positive obligations
towards them." This triptych of posters
(right) exhibited at the International Poster
Salon is the work of a Swedish artist.
istence of the international community,
what does our method reveal? Two series
of observations can be made, the first
concerning the structure of the collective
grouping of nations, and the second con¬
cerning the situations created for States
and peoples in the international system
today.
From the structural point of view, we
find the well-known opposition between
infrastructure and superstructure. Nowa¬
days, it is hardly necessary to be a Marxist
to acknowledge the fact that law belongs
to superstructure, and that the antagon¬
isms which develop at the economic and
social levels are concerned with the
foundations on which law is built. Super¬
structures also act on one another,
however; this is true of political ideas and
cultural phenomena whose influence on
law cannot be ignored. Thus internation¬
al organizations, by their sheer number
and by virtue of the role that they assume,
have introduced a new set of factors into
the system which impinge on the system
of relations between States.
Several strategist writers concentrate
their attention on the law of relations
between States. They see the internation¬
al organization as an entity that is both
secondary and dangerous. Secondary be¬
cause it has no sovereignty, yet danger¬
ous, not so much because it aspires to
dominate its Member States, but because
it is manipulated by great powers.
This view is no longer such a straight¬
forward reflection of reality; it cannot be
claimed that United Nations agencies are
a threat to the sovereignty of States which
have acquired or recovered their
sovereignty in recent decades with UN
support. That fear, which springs from
formal theory, may not have been
groundless in the early days of the United
Nations, when the United States auto¬
matically had a majority in the General
Assembly; but for many years now the
developing countries have been finding
strength in numbers in that forum.
For example, the Group of 77 (which
actually has 121 members) has taken on
the role of interpellant in the Assembly;
its members take the wealthy countries to
task and denounce the inadequacy of
their efforts to establish a new economic
order. They are thus able to ensure that
the General Assembly adopts resolutions
proclaiming principles in which they ex¬
press their desires, their aspirations and
their view of the truth. Admittedly, their
authority in the Organization suffers
from some limitations, but they have
given a new sense of direction and ideolo¬
gical vigour to the United Nations.
In consequence, the institutional
sphere impinges strongly on the sphere of
relations, with the developing countries
striving to extend to the latter the influ¬
ence they have gained in the former.
Over and above these structural
strategies a crucial debate is taking place
on the relations between power and
justice.
For the countries of the Third World
^
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
the United Nations is an incomparable
means of pressing their case vis-à-vis the
wealthy. For Nietzsche, the indispens¬
able weapon of the weak lies in exploiting
the guilty conscience of the strong. In the
General Assembly the votes of the de¬
veloping countries ensure the adoption
year in year out of the same resolutions,
whose object is to make an impact on
consciences. And so it would be simplistic
to present the UN as a reactionary entity
today when on the contrary it offers the
poor nations a platform from which to
proclaim their destitution.
Power is the expression of a force aspir¬
ing to domination. In the nineteenth cen¬
tury the word "powers" was used to de¬
signate the strongest States which made
up the European concert and which,
when they reached agreement among
themselves, dictated their common will
to the other States. Power is always the
characteristic of the large, strong States,
but a coalition of weak, developing States
can, in some circumstances, constitute a
power to be reckoned with.
The rule of law always emanates from a
dominant social force. According to posi¬
tivist thinking, a rule emanates from com¬
petent bodies and is adopted through reg¬
ular channels. But this does not make it
necessarily equitable. Admittedly, law is
supposed to coincide with justice, but
that coincidence is often open to dispute
and is, in fact, disputed.
Positivism has thus found itself in
league with imperialism, colonialism and
I I
von Sergei Eisenstein
E
©
©i
	;
^^
iedaV^ore
eVes^see-
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
various forms of domination, in the ab¬
sence of any legal rules that might have
proscribed them. There can be no deny¬
ing the fact that the overwhelming
triumph of positivism is the triumph of
Creon, with Antigone condemned to
silence.
At present, in the international con¬
text, a number of rules are being re¬
viewed at the prompting of certain coun¬
tries. Classical law is still largely con¬
cerned with form and process, but to an
increasing extent it is becoming regula¬
tory, and is called upon to prescribe rules
for the conduct of States. Inherent in this
development, which the new political
forces are striving to impose on the
powerful States, and for which they have
in many cases already succeeded in win¬
ning acceptance or tolerance, are new
conceptions of international relations.
These new conceptions tend to imply
recognition of the existence of an interna¬
tional community which postulates
obligations for the well-endowed. The
nature of such a community is twofold:
internationalists often refer to a historical
community resulting from real, material
bonds which draw peoples closer
together, and especially from advances in
communications.
But we would put forward another ver¬
sion, a mythical and prophetic interpreta¬
tion which enables the poor to denounce
the power of the rich and the injustice of
the law whose rules they have imposed.
The international community then tends
to take on the dynamic force of a political
myth, in the sense intended by the French
social philosopher Georges Sorel in
other words, an idée force capable of
mobilizing the reserves of strength avail¬
able to fight for change.
The major upheaval occurring today
on the international scene is a result of
the fact that technological development is
making nations interdependent. That
objective solidarity which, on the one
hand, brings peoples closer together on
the material plane, also, on the other,
renders the contradictions between them
more acute. Such solidarity did not exist
in the classical international grouping,
when the nations had little need to be
concerned with what was happening in
distant parts and paid attention only to
their immediate neighbours.
We find, then, that the community
emerging today is not the outcome of
harmonist phenomena arising from new¬
ly discovered bonds of brotherhood, still
less from the settlement of differences.
On the contrary, its contradictory path is
mapped out by forces of repulsion, com¬
petition, refusal and demand, and yet
simultaneously by the influence of soli¬
darity, reciprocal needs and mutual re¬
sponsibilities. Moreover, it is because
they are backed by the existence of a
certain community that the least pri¬
vileged peoples feel that they can chal¬
lenge the wealthier nations and demand
their assistance and support not as a
charitable hand-out, but as a duty and an
obligation.
So, while the developing countries are
asserting their sovereignty and their
identity in a great movement of political
individualism, they are at the same time
appealing to the international com
munity, in the absence of which the rich
countries could shrug off any positive
obligations towards them. The driving
force of history in the making is at the
heart of this tension between individual¬
ity and solidarity. This means that the
international community is not a harmon¬
ist concept, based on a universal con¬
sensus, but a reality of conflict, of perma¬
nent tension between power and justice.
The myth of community, encompassing
both, should not be unfamiliar to legal
experts. The French writer Paul Valéry
foresaw this with admirable clarity: "It
may be said that the world of society, the
world of law and the world of politics are
essentially mythical worlds whose laws . . .
owe to us their existence, their strength
and their patterns of impulsion and
constraint."
RENE-JEAN DUPUY, of France, has been pro¬
fessor of international law at the Collège de
France since 1979. Notable among hispublished
works is Communauté internationale et dispa¬
rités de développement (1981; "International
Community and Disparities in Development").
He has edited and contributed to a number of
collective works, including Le règlement des dif¬
férends sur les nouvelles ressources naturelles
(1983; "The Settling ofDifferences on New Natu¬
ral Resources") and'L'avenir du droit internation¬
al dans un monde multiculturel (1984; "The Fu¬
ture of International Law in a Multicultural
World"). The above article has been extracted
from La communauté internationale entre le
mythe et l'histoire (1986; "The International
Community between Myth and History"), co-
publishedby Unesco and Económica publishers,
Paris.
8
"The major upheaval occurring today on
the international scene is a result of the
fact that technological development is
making nations interdependent. That
objective solidarity which, on the one
hand, brings peoples closer together on
the material plane, also, on the other, ren¬
ders the contradictions between them
more acute." Left, a Polish poster.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Twentyyears
ofcultural co-operation
by Emmanuel Pouchepadass
m
x
\
\
1
Photo Michel Claude/Unesco
THE Declaration of the Principles of
International Cultural Co-operation
unanimously adopted by Unesco's
General Conference on 4 November 1966
is twenty years old. The celebration of this
anniversary late last year was one of many
events which marked the International Year
of Peace at Unesco, in Member States and
in the United Nations system.
The Declaration is founded on the belief
that culture is a particularly important factor
in the development of understanding be¬
tween people and societies, and that inter¬
national solidarity can be strengthened in
important respects by a recognition of the
interdependence of the world community.
Cultural co-operation has acquired a
new impetus at all levels in the past twenty
years. Cultural exchanges have grown in
number and variety. Many joint projects
involving several countries have been
accomplished within and between the diffe¬
rent world regions, especially in the fields of
North-South, South-South and European
co-operation.
Recent initiatives at regional and sub-
regional level have focused on the study of
languages and cultures (in Latin America,
the Caribbean, Central Asia and the Arctic
regions); the training of cultural staff (in
West Africa and Latin America); and the
joint organization of festivals and other
artistic and cultural events. One of the most
interesting aspects of sub-regional co-op¬
eration is the growth of contacts between
universities and research institutes (e.g., in
the Caribbean sub-region).
Latin America has decided to create a
common market for books and is consider¬
ing the introduction of an educational televi¬
sion system. Several West African coun¬
tries have launched operations for the res¬
cue and development of archaeological
sites, notably while hydraulic engineering
projects were being carried out.
Joint projects concerning the non-
material cultural heritage, particularly stu¬
dies of languages and oral traditions, have
also been initiated, with the support of the
Organization of African Unity (OAU) and
Unesco, as part of a ten-year Plan for the
systematic study of African languages and
oral traditions. A number of African univer¬
sities have joined forces in the collection
and study of traditional African music and
dance. In the field of cinema and the media,
there is a growing number of co-produc¬
tions, not only between industrialized coun¬
tries but also in the context of North-South
co-operation.
National Theatre of Vietnam performance
at Unesco Headquarters, Paris, in March
1984.
But the best example of international
cultural co-operation is doubtless the
launching, under the joint auspices of the
United Nations and Unesco, of a World
Decade for Cultural Development which
will begin in 1 988 after being proclaimed by
the General Assembly of the United
Nations. The Decade will call for deter¬
mined, sustained joint action by Member
States of the organizations of the United
Nations system, especially those of
Unesco, and by international non¬
governmental organizations, in order to
meet the challenges confronting mankind
in the late twentieth century.
EMMANUEL POUCHEPADASS joined Unesco
in 1971 as director of the Division of Cultural
Development, after a career in the Indian dip¬
lomatic service. From 1977 to 1981 he was
director of Unesco's Division of Cultural Studies
and of the International Fund for the Promotion of
Culture.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Cities
by Rafael M. Salas
THE world has embarked on a
course which will transform it into
a predominantly urban planet. By
the time population stabilizes at the end
of the next century, truly rural popula¬
tions will have become a very small
minority.
More than 40 per cent of the world
population currently live in urban areas.
This figure will increase to more than 50
per cent shortly after the turn of the
century. Developed regions have been
more than 50 per cent urban since the
mid-20th century. Developing countries
are expected to pass the 50 per cent mark
in the first quarter of the next century.
Within the less developed regions
there are important differences. The de¬
veloping countries of Africa and Asia are
less than 30 per cent urban. Latin Amer-
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
without limits
V
M
«
Î
r
o
ica, on the other hand, is nearly 70 per
cent urban, reflecting the region's stage
of development and the special features
of its urban structure and history.
By the year 2000:
5 'super-cities' of 15 million
Most of the world's urban population
today lives in developing countries. In
1970 the total urban population of the
more developed regions was almost 30
million more than in the less developed.
Five years later the position was reversed
and by 1985 the difference had widened
to more than 300 million. By the year
2000 the urban population of developing
countries will be almost double that of the
developed countries. By the year 2025 it
will be almost four times as large.
The city offers a visionperhaps a mir¬
ageof wealth for the rural poor, who
might otherwise face a bleak future.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
The rise of the cities
By the year 2000 half of the world popula¬
tion will live in cities, according to the 1986
State of World Population report from the
United Nations Fund for Population Activi¬
ties (UNFPA). The map above indicates the
projected populations (in millions) for the
year 2000, in the twelve largest metropoli¬
tan regions of the world.
At present the urban population of
Africa is smaller than that of North
America, but by the beginning of the next
century it is expected to be substantially
greater, and three times greater by the
year 2025.
The proportion of the world popula¬
tion living-in the largest cities will almost
double between 1970 and 2025, because
of the growth of such cities in developing
countries. By the year 2025 almost 30 per
cent of the urban population in the de¬
veloping regions will be living in cities of
over 4 million, more than double the
figure for the more developed regions.
Although only a small proportion of the
African population today lives in very
large cities, by the end of the first quarter
of the next century this proportion could
be higher than that of any other con¬
tinent. In developed countries,
moreover, there is a trend towards de-
concentration.
By the year 2000 there will be five
"super-cities" of 15 million or more in¬
habitants, three of them in the develop¬
ing regions. Two of them, in Latin Amer¬
ica, will have populations of around 25
million. In 1970, nine of the twenty
largest cities in the world were in the less
developed regions; in 1985 there were ten
and by the year 2000 there will be sixteen.
This change signals the end of the close
relationship between large cities and eco¬
nomic development. Until recently such
cities were because of their size centres of
international political and economic net
works, a situation which may now begin
to change.
The urban population in developing
countries is currently increasing three
times more quickly than that of de¬
veloped countries, at a rate of about 3.5
per cent a year, a doubling time of only
twenty years.
There are important differences be¬
tween the developing regions. Latin
America has the lowest rates of popula¬
tion growth, followed by Asia. Africa,
especially East Africa, has the highest.
The current growth rate for Africa is 5 per
cent a year, implying a doubling of the
urban population every 14 years. The
current figure for East Africa is above 6.5
per cent, a doubling time of little more
than ten years.
Migrants to the cities
Such extremely rapid urban growth is
without precedent. It confronts the cities,
especially in the developing countries,
with problems new to human experience,
and presents the old problems urban
infrastructure, food, housing, em¬
ployment, health, education in new and
accentuated forms.
Furthermore, despite migration to the
cities, rural population in developing
countries will continue to increase, at a
rate of around one per cent annually.
Five important points emerge from an
analysis of United Nations population
figures:
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The world's rural population is now
more than 2.5 thousand million;
Rural population density is already
very high in many parts of the less de¬
veloped regions. Standards of living,
while improving, remain low. It is doubt¬
ful whether added demographic pressure
will benefit agricultural development
on the contrary it may jeopardize the
development of many rural areas;
Increasing rural population in de¬
veloping countries will make it difficult to
reduce the flow of migrants to the cities;
The natural growth rate (the differ¬
ence between the number of births and
the number of deaths) of the rural
population is higher than the one per cent
rate often more than double. The dif¬
ference is due to the number of migrants
to the cities;
For most of Africa, unlike the rest of
the developing world, rural populations
will continue to increase until well into
the next century.
Although urban fertility in developing
countries tends to be lower than rural
fertility, it is still at least twice as high as
that in developed countries.
When natural increase in urban areas is
high and migrants contribute substan¬
tially to it, the migrants'. future fertility
becomes an important factor. The high
fertility typical of rural areas may be car¬
ried over into the urban environment;
more optimistically, migrants plunging
into new endeavours in a different con¬
text may adapt rather quickly to urban
values, including lower fertility.
Those who consider urbanization to be
a blessing hold that migration to the cities
is part of a dynamic development pro¬
cess. Those who think that it is a burden
believe that rural surplus population be¬
comes an urban surplus, producing
"over-urbanization", in which an ineffi¬
cient and unproductive "informal sector"
consisting of street vendors, shoeshine
boys, sidewalk repair shops and other
so-called marginal occupations becomes
more and more important.
Urban life has its positive aspects, but
they emphasize employment rather than
what workers get for their labour. A city
worker may earn more than a rural coun¬
terpart, but is it enough to cover the basic
needs of food, health, housing and
education?
Two important aspects of urban life are
income distribution and the number of
city-dwellers living below an acceptable
and culturally adjusted "poverty line".
Reliable data are lacking, but it is prob¬
ably true that the distribution of incomes
is more inequitable in urban than in rural
areas, in that there are proportionally
more very rich and very poor people in
the cities.
This may be as much an indication of
economic development in the urban
areas as of the privileges enjoyed by
urban élites. Rapid demographic growth
among the urban masses also contributes
to the inequality of income distribution
and swells the numbers of the poor.
A massive housing deficit
The most visible manifestations of the
problems of rapid urban population
growth are the makeshift settlements on
the outskirts of every city in the develop¬
ing world. They are usually in the worst
parts of town as regards health and acces¬
sibility, lacking basic services and secur
ity of tenure. They are by their nature
overcrowded average occupancy rates
of four to five persons per room are
common.
The names given to these settlements
graphically express their characteristics.
In Latin America the word callampas
(mushrooms) refers to their almost
magical overnight growth. The term
bidonvilles (tin can cities) , is often used in
Francophone Africa to describe their
makeshift nature. There are many other
labels, usually given by outsiders: those
who live in these settlements might de¬
scribe them differently, perhaps even
CONTINUED PAGE 16
The child in the city
For Third World parents the city may seem the best place to bring up a child - education
and health services are usually better than in the countryside. But there are
disadvantages too: the city child will spend much more of the day away from the family
and at greater risk of exploitation.
URBAN ADVANTAGES
Health and education services are easier to provide in
cities. And mortality and literacy statistics do show the
urban areas in a favourable light
URBAN«
RURAL LU
Colombia
Peru
Kenya
Senegal
Bangladesh
Indonesia
Health
Infant deaths per thousand
live births
84
84
¡12
110
71
	J
196
I But there will be great differences between the poorer
I and richer parts of each city. In Lima, Peru, for
S example, 1 9% of the children overall are malnourished
« but this figure rises to 36% in the poorest districts.
STREET CHILDREN
Some 40 million children around the world spend their
days on city streets- often working. The majority maintain
contact with their families, but millions of children also
live on the street.
Why they are there
A survey in Maputo, Mozambique, asked children why
there were on the street. These are the reasons they gave.
Hunger and poverty in the home 27% /
Treated badly at home 27% hyjJjQjNothing else to do 27% l
Sent by the family 9%
Abandoned by the family 9%
Just following other children 1%
What they do
Many city children work (as well as going to school for
part of the day). Research in Asuncion, Paraguay, asked
children what their major jobs were:
Selling newspapers 27%
Shining shoes 24%
Selling food etc. 33%
Cleaning windscreens 6%
Cleaning and looking after cars 9%
Others 1%
City children also have factory jobs - often in harsh
conditions. And in rich and poor countries alike street
children risk falling into prostitution.
137
137
Document UNFPA
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
13*
Unesco and
human settlements
In 1976, Unesco's Division of Human Set¬
tlements and Socio-cultural Environments
began to publish a series of studies on
traditional forms of architecture and town
planning in different cultures. These
documents, 38 of which have so far
appeared, have been well received by
architects, urban planners, ethnologists
and geographers. They draw attention to
forms of architecture which seem likely to
disappear, describe the ways in which
local materials and traditional techniques
are used, and also take into account the
social setting of the villages or districts
concerned. (Left and below, gable decora¬
tions of a traditional kalê house of north¬
ern Thailand, a form of settlement which
was the subject of a study published by
Unesco in February 1985.) Other studies
have focused on contemporary urban
problems, especially those of people liv¬
ing in poor districts on the outskirts of
large towns and cities, andare intended as
a contribution to urban rehabilitation pro¬
jects such as that in Villa Maria del Triunfo
(right, aerial view and detail), a settlement
described in a study on "self-built
housing" in Lima, Peru, published by Un¬
esco in June 1986.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 13 considering them as starting points on the
path to a higher standard of living.
There is a massive housing deficit in
many large cities. The World Bank esti¬
mated in 1975 that the poorest quarter of
the population in most African and Asian
cities cannot afford even minimal
housing. Wood and cardboard packing
crates, sheets of plastic or corrugated
iron, flattened tin cans, leaves, bamboo
and beaten earth are the main sources of
materials.
Space is also a problem. Landlords
may add illegal floors to existing build-
How cities grow
The urban population of developing countries will be almost
double that of developed countries by the year 2000 - according
to the 1986 'State of World Population' report from the UN Fund
for Population Activities.
CONTINENTAL CONURBATIONS
Latin America has some of the largest cities of the developing world but
Africa is now urbanizing at a rapid rate. The chart shows the percentage of
the population living in urban areas.
poooog
SB»*"»Ï»»'
SJÏÏ
$ß>
1950 1960 1970 1980 1990 2000 2010
BUILDING FROM BELOW
The major architects of today's Third World cities are poor families
building their own homes. The diagram below shows the percentage of
squatters and slum dwellers in four major cities.
Document UNFPA
ings, only to watch their dreams of wealth
collapse along with the buildings and the
lives of the unfortunate inhabitants. In
some cities several workers will use the
same "hot bed" in shifts over the twenty-
four hours. In Cairo squatters have occu¬
pied a large cemetery: the tombs of the
wealthy have become homes for the
poor.
Colonies of squatters occupy the last
areas to be settled, and may be perched
on steep hillsides subject to frequent
landslides, or installed by rivers or on
swampy ground which is flooded regu¬
larly. In Mexico City about 1.5 million
people live on the arained bed of a salt
lake, bedevilled by dust storms in the dry
season and floods in rainy months. In
Lagos, Nigeria, the proportion of wet
land to dry land settled has worsened,
while the absolute area of dry land occu¬
pied has doubled.
Where squatter settlements have been
established near workplaces, the inhabi¬
tants may run the risk of pollution and are
exposed to dangers such as the leak of
poisonous gas in Bhopal, India, or the
explosions at oil refineries in Mexico
City.
Squatter settlements typically lack
water, sewage and waste disposal facil¬
ities, electricity and paved streets. In
Mexico City, 80 per cent of the popula¬
tion have access to tapwater, but in some
squatter settlements the figure is less than
50 per cent. Water consumption in the
wealthy quarters of Mexico City is at least
five times as high as in the poorer areas.
In Lagos, water is strictly rationed and in
some parts of the city residents must walk
long distances to obtain water from a few
pumps which are turned on only in the
early morning.
According to a study carried out in
Lima, Peru, lower income groups spent
three times more per month on water
from vendors but consumed less than a
sixth as much as those with running water
at home.
It is estimated that three million in¬
habitants of Mexico City do not have
access to the sewage system. In Säo
Paulo, Brazil, the absence of sewage sys¬
tems have turned the two main rivers into
moving cesspools.
Because they occupy land owned by
the government, private individuals or
communal organizations, squatters are
frequently subject to harassment, which
increases their feeling of insecurity and
the precariousness of their existence.
Illegal or barely legal occupation does
nothing to encourage squatters to im¬
prove or even maintain the shaky struc¬
tures in which they live.
A number of schemes have been de¬
vised to give more security to squatters,
but there are risks. One is that improving
living conditions in the city will encour-
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
age people to move there. Another is that
improvements to property will increase
its value and encourage squatters to sell,
while moving it out of the reach of other
low-income families.
Two urgent problems:
child health and education
The health of the poor may be worse in
urban than in rural areas. Infant mortal¬
ity in the Port-au-Prince slums is three
times higher than it is in the rural areas of
Haiti . In some of thefavelas of Säo Paulo ,
infant mortality is over 100 per thousand
live births! The overall infant mortality
rate for the slums of Delhi is 221 per
thousand, twice that for some castes. In
Manila infant mortality is three times
higher in the slums than it is in the rest of
the city. (Tuberculosis rates are nine
times higher; the incidence of diarrhoea
is twice as common ; twice as many people
are anaemic and three times as many are
undernourished.) In Panama City, of
1,819 infants with diarrhoeal diseases,
45.5 per cent came from the slums and
22.5 per cent from squatter settlements.
Children living in the best housing were
not affected.
In most cities in developed countries,
young people under 19 constitute less
than 30 per cent of the population. In
developing countries, the proportion is
typically over 40 per cent and may reach
50 per cent in cities such as Manila, Jakar¬
ta and Bogotá. If the education system
breaks down under this sort of pressure,
it will add immeasurably to problems of
employment, delinquency and allied
problems caused by the existence of
"street children".
Education is probably the most press¬
ing of urban problems. A lower rate of
population growth would immeasurably
help the situation, but such a decrease
partly depends on the spread of educa¬
tion. Family planning programmes will
certainly be useful, but they must be
accompanied by renewed efforts to bring
education to the urban masses.
How will the cities be fed?
How will agriculture respond to the
tremendous pressure of urbanization and
the growth of urban population? A recent
study by the United Nations Food and
Agriculture Organization (FAO) and the
. United Nations Fund for Population
Activities (UNFPA) draws attention to
some of the likely effects.
First, urban populations demand
cheap food. By weight of numbers they
force governments to keep retail prices
down. Governments may make up the
difference by subsidizing farmers but ex
perience has shown that, once estab¬
lished, such subsidies are difficult to with¬
draw.
Second, as urban populations grow and
indigenous agriculture fails to keep up
with demand (for lack of incentive to
increase supply), more food is imported.
This drains off hard currency intended for
capital imports with a view to long-term
development.
Third, urban population increase
means that rural populations and the
agricultural labour force will grow more
slowly. But to meet urban needs agri¬
cultural productivity should be increasing
by 17 per cent for each agricultural
worker in developing countries between
1980 and the year 2000. This figure seems
high, but recent experience in Asia and
Latin America shows that it is possible.
For Africa, however, the increase per
worker will have to be almost 25 per cent,
an eventuality that seems very doubtful in
view of recent events. Research in Africa
has shown that lower production gains
were made in countries with high rural-
urban migration. This contrasts with ex¬
perience in other regions, where rural-
urban migration has been at least partly
the consequence of higher agricultural
labour productivity.
Fourth, tastes in food change under the
influence of urban life-styles, as tradi¬
tional staples are partly replaced by foods
such as bread, meat and vegetables.
Fifth, the growth of urban population
intensifies competition for land, water
and energy. Cities gobble up agricultural
land, often the best land because its fertil¬
ity Was the original attraction which
stimulated urban growth. Between 1980
and the year 2000, according to one
study, cities will devour four million hec¬
tares of land with the potential to feed 84
million people.
Sixth, while malnutrition may be more
widespread among rural populations, the
urban poor suffer more acutely. People in
the lowest income groups normally have
to spend more than half of their incomes
on food.
Balanced approaches
to an urban planet
The transformation from a rural to an
urban planet offers both great blessings
and heavy burdens. The transition from
agrarian to urban has always been consi¬
dered a positive step, part of the process
of modernization. However, the rapid
growth of urban populations in societies
rapidly changing in other ways is fraught
with enormous tension and tremendously
complex problems.
In its search for solutions to problems
of urban population dynamics, UNFPA
puts continuous emphasis on three fun
damental objectives: economic efficien¬
cy, social equity and population balance.
It recognizes that the solution for many
urban problems will only come through
economic efficiency and vast growth of
the productive forces. Economic growth
is essential to any solution of urban prob¬
lems. At the same time social equity
should be pursued, with emphasis on
equal opportunity for all.
Neither economic efficiency nor social
equity can be attained without demo¬
graphic balance balance within and be¬
tween urban and rural areas, balanced
population distribution and balanced
population growth.
RAFAEL M. SALAS, of the Philippines, is an
Under-Secretary-General of the United Nations
and executive director of the United Nations
Fund for Population Activities, which he has
headed since it became operational in 1969. A
graduate of the universities of the Philippines
and of Harvard (USA), he has sen/ed asa Minis¬
ter and occupied other high-level posts in the
Philippine Government.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
The world's homeless millions
"More than 1,000 million people a quar¬
ter of the world populationare either
literallyhomeless or live in extremelypoor
housing and unhealthy environments.
About 100 million people have no shelter
whatsoever; they sleep in the streets,
under bridges, on waste ground, In alleys
and doorways."
THE General Assembly of the
United Nations has declared 1987
the International Year of Shelter
for the Homeless. More than 1,000 mil¬
lion people a quarter of the world
population are either literally homeless
or live in extremely poor housing and
unhealthy environments. About 100 mil¬
lion people have no shelter whatsoever;
they sleep in the streets, under bridges,
on waste ground, in alleys and doorways.
The problem of inadequate housing is
universal. It is common to industrialized
and developing countries, to urban and
rural areas. Because of an unprecedented
urban explosion, the developing coun¬
tries are faced with the formidable task of
providing shelter, services and work in
cities for an additional 150,000 people
every day.
In the shanty-towns the urban poor live
in helpless insecurity, evicted repeatedly
from homes which are demolished before
-
~**~
their eyes and confronted by hostile offi¬
cials who refuse to recognize their ex¬
istence. Hostility breeds hostility. In
these mushrooming squatter colonies, a
generation of city-dwellers is growing up
with no stake in the present social order,
which they find unrelentingly oppressive.
Many of them hold society responsible
for their degraded lives; many also have
learned to live by preying upon it.
City after city has therefore turned into
a powder keg of crime and violence. Gov¬
ernments have responded by increasing
the numbers and powers of the police, a
policy which has at best treated the symp¬
toms of the crisis and not its causes. As a
result social peace has become more and
more fragile.
Many of the remedies chosen have
aggravated the disease. For example, the
authorities perceive that the quality of
housing in the cities is poor and that living
conditions are unhygienic. The solution
they adopt is to raise housing standards
through stricter enforcement of more
exacting building codes.
However, higher standards increase
the cost of construction and place legal
housing even further beyond the reach of
the urban poor, more and more of whom
are forced into shanty-towns and inner-
city slums. The authorities find that there
are too many squatters, clear their col¬
onies and raze their hovels to the ground.
Most governments have tried to re¬
house squatters in State-built housing.
This has not solved the problem either.
Not only has the pace of public construc¬
tion lagged far behind the growth of the
cities, but even State-built dwellings of
this kind have proved far too expensive
for the poor. The authorities have there¬
fore been forced to subsidize the poor
and have quickly found that the cost is far
too high. This dismal failure has often led
them to avoid the problem of providing
shelter by pretending that it has ceased to
exist.
Hectic urban growth and the rising de¬
mand for housing push up rents to levels
far higher than what the poor, and even
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
large sections of the middle class, can
pay. The authorities respond by imposing
rent control, a solution which makes in¬
vestment in housing uneconomic and
dries up the supply of new dwelling units,
thus increasing the pressure on existing
units and accelerating the growth of
squatter colonies.
Most obstacles to the provision of shel¬
ter are man-made, rooted in laws and
economic conditions. The removal of
these hurdles involves first of all guaran¬
teeing the urban poor a secure title to
plots of land, however small these may
be; secondly, allowing them to build
whatever kind of housing they can afford
and leaving them free to improve it when
their means permit; thirdly, meeting their
need for sanitation and safe drinking wa¬
ter in the cheapest way possible; and
lastly giving them access to financial and
technical assistance in building their
homes.
In the search for low cost options,
architects and shelter planners have
found that the best way to start is by
taking a hard look at a country's tradi¬
tional architecture and construction
methods. This approach, once practised
exclusively by imaginative architects, has
now been widely adopted by shelter plan¬
ners and is yielding rich dividends. Un¬
baked clay bricks are, for example, not
only considerably cheaper than cement
blocks or fired bricks, they are also much
better thermal insulators.
The second important lesson that plan¬
ners have learned is that if shelter can be
brought within the means of the poor,
then instead of being a drag on the eco¬
nomy, investment in housing for low-
income groups can become a powerful
and sustained stimulus for economic
growth in a developing country.
If they are to solve the shelter problem
the developing countries must mobilize
the savings of the poor to finance the
construction of their own homes. Not
only must private builders become in¬
volved as entrepreneurs in building
houses for low-income groups, but the
output of the building materials industry
must be reoriented to meet the need for
cheap building materials.
This does not mean that the industry
should accept low profit returns on the
production and sale of these materials. It
implies that the industry must be given
the technological support needed to pro¬
duce cheap building materials for low-
cost housing. A final but very important
point is that the success and viability of
shelter projects depend heavily on the
involvement of the beneficiaries.
The urban and rural poor have shown a
tremendous capacity to improve their
housing conditions with little or no exter¬
nal assistance thus demonstrating the
need for policies aimed at "helping the
poor to help themselves", a need being
increasingly recognized by governments
in their development policies and pro¬
grammes.
This approach to human settlement
policies is increasingly being adopted by
the governments of developing countries.
Thus there is hope that current trends can
be reversed, that present conditions are
not unchangeable and that this formid¬
able challenge can still be met.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Poverty
and progress
An international meeting of experts on the theme "Poverty and Progress" took place
from 17 to 21 November 1986 at Unesco Headquarters in Paris. The meeting,
organized by Unesco in collaboration with the United Nations University, was the
follow-up to a series of symposiums devoted to the concept and aims of development,
and to Unesco's work in this field. The purpose of the meeting was to examine, in
different social and cultural contexts, the mechanisms of marginalization and
exclusion resulting from certain development processes, especially those linked to
some forms of technological development, and to throw light on the resulting
manifestations of poverty. Speaking at the meeting, the Director-General of Unesco,
Mr. Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, said: "I believe that one of the great problems of our
time is that of abolishing not only material poverty, but also the moral, human
poverty which can be seen in many places and which may underlie many social
difficulties experienced by some countries which on the face of it appear relatively
wealthy. ... The ultimate aim of development, in reality, is culture, to the extent that
it is through cultural values that humanity can fulfil its aspirations and satisfy most
of its needs." Below, extracts from four of the papers presented at the meeting.
Women on the sidelines
by Amadou Moustapha Diop
THE social exclusion of women in
the countries of the. Third World
has its origin in patriarchal institu¬
tions whose standards, values and models
are exclusively controlled by men.
Ideological constructions subject women
to a "constant reversal of values".
According to this institutional
framework, woman is negatively branded
from birth. "Biologically, motherhood
sets her apart; ethically, her impurity iso¬
lates her; metaphysically, her very being
is guilty, and the great religions systema¬
tize her condemnation: original sin in
Christianity, and reincarnation in the
body of a woman as punishment for a
misspent life in Hinduism".1 Nor should
we overlook Islam, which elaborately de¬
marcates the territory of the two sexes:
the interior of the house, the indoor
world, is the woman's realm, and she
herself is the secret domain of man; the
outdoors is men's field of action and a
strictly male preserve. And "any overlap¬
ping of these spaces is restricted and con¬
trolled by a host of rituals".2
Thus the traditional reproductive and
nurturing role is one of the major obsta¬
cles to women's participation in society.
This socio-biological role is a hindrance
in that it forces women imprisoned in
the straitjacket of their responsibilities
towards their children3 to put up with
mere "pin money", starvation wages in
the agro-industries of the Third World
countries: "The international division of
labour classes them as working mothers,
working wives and working sisters. The
profits of national and international cor¬
porations are swollen thanks to the con¬
cept of 'wives' earnings', which provides
ideological justification for both the
With These Hands, a film, produced and
directed by Chris Sheppard and Claude
Sauvageot, presents the stories of three
women from three African countries:
Kenya, Zimbabwe and Burkina Faso. One
of the most surprising facts revealed by
the film is that women, not men, grow 75%
of Africa's foodas well as finding time
for their domestic chores. Zenabou Bam-
bara (left on photo opposite) of Burkina
Faso, declares: "We wish the men would
help. But a man is ashamed to do women 's
work."
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
existence and the injustice of unequal pay
for the two sexes."1 The gravitation to¬
wards sub-proletarian work is caused by
women's inferior position in the rural
world, and by the family's assumption
that domestic work is a woman's natural
lot, which is treated as non-existent at
national level becauses it is not produc¬
tive work, and hence cannot feature in
the statistics of the decision-makers and
planners.4 Furthermore, women are dep¬
rived of the means of production: under
common law they cannot inherit land,
and so their access to agriculture depends
on the fulfilment of duly pre-established
social conditions a woman must be mar¬
ried, or at least have a recognized status
in the community.
In Femmes du tiers monde, x J. Bissillat
and M. Fiéloux describe one case of the
total exclusion of Senegalese women
from the system of land ownership. In
1979, SAED, the body responsible for
development of the middle region of the
Senegal Valley, decided to organize a
"village lottery for farmers, so that they
might all, regardless of their status
whether formerly slaves, craftworkers or
'masters' have a chance to win in the
distribution of plots of land on the out
skirts of the village where irrigation was
planned. But this exercise in fair play ran
into trouble. Whatever her status as a
wife, single woman or de facto head of a
household no woman was entitled to
receive a plot of land in her own name.
The only way around the difficulty was
for the most needy among them, such as a
widow with four children to support, to
give a fictitious name for the head of the
family, with the villagers' consent: that of
a five-year-old son or a deceased relative,
for example."
Even the usufruct of plots of land con¬
ceded to a woman by her husband be¬
comes precarious with the development
of cash crops, which are "increasingly
taking over the best land, encroaching on
areas formerly set aside for food crops".
Cash crops have destroyed the former
balance of duties and obligations; the old
methods of sharing have fallen into dis¬
use. Cash crops enhance the prestige and
power of men. Women, although they
play an active part in agricultural work,
find their status radically changing; they
become an over-exploited sub-proletar¬
iat since they still continue to tend the
food crops and underpaid wage-
earners. A Dioula woman (Senegal), for
example, after working on her husband's
groundnut plantations, is entitled to
"one-twentieth of the money that he
makes from the harvest".
Trapped in the labour of growing food,
rural women are cut off from the econo¬
mic circuits, and accordingly have no ac¬
cess to co-operatives or to loans. If any¬
one condescends to grant a woman a
loan, it will be at a prohibitively high rate
of interest. For example, Burkina-be
women were offered "a loan access
scheme. But then the paradox became
starkly apparent, because they were com¬
pelled to accept a repayment rate fixed by
the men, slightly higher than the official
rate".
Women perform nearly 80 per cent of
agricultural work in Africa, and yet as
economic partners they are non-existent.
For example, Wolof women (Senegal)
"are kept at a safe distance from the
knowledge, contacts and skills that are
held in the highest esteem. No pro¬
gramme caters for them, whether literacy
teaching or agricultural extension
work".5 When trading institutes do admit
women, they train them in altogether
marginal activities whose usefulness to
the community is negligible. "Rather
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Poverty and progress
than being taught the new cultivation and
management techniques which ... they
are perfectly capable of learning, they are
given lessons in embroidery, sewing,
knitting and cookery."
Like the traditional societies of India
and China, African societies obey the
rules of "institutionalized subordina¬
tion", under which women have internal¬
ized three types of submission: "Before
marriage, obey your father. After mar¬
riage, obey your husband. After your
husband dies, obey your son."4
This system of subordination and "an-
drocentrism" has unfortunate implica¬
tions which result in discrimination in the
areas of food and health. On the subject
of Indian women, ill-nourished and re¬
ceiving inferior health care, it has been
noted that "while there is a higher inci¬
dence of diseases caused by malnutrition
among women, the hospital rate of
admission and treatment of young^-and
adult males for these diseases is larger."4
This exclusion and deprivation of rights
on "biological" grounds opens the door
to other forms of marginalization, in
education in particular: the number of
illiterate women is increasing; when girls
are not "drop-outs, push-outs and left-
outs", they are to be found in "tradi¬
tional, ornamental fields of education"
considered to be "feminine".
In the political sphere, despite the fact
that some women hold senior positions,
most play very little part in politics, be¬
cause they have never been properly
taught and because of the social pressures
whereby "unmarried girls [in India] are
socially and culturally prohibited from
free mingling with males . . . owing to their
parents' fear of a reduction of their
'value' in the marriage market".3 Custom
demands that a married woman follow
her dharma, which is "to be subservient
to her husband, take care of his needs,
make him happy, bear and rear his chil¬
dren". After this taxing ordeal, how can a
woman find time to involve herself in
politics? Surely her everyday household
drudgery is already the first barrier to any
kind of participation in the life of the
community.
1 . Jeanne Bissillat and Michèle Fiéloux. Femmes du tiers
monde, Paris, Le Sycomore, 1983.
2. Fatima Mcrnissi. Sexe, idéologie, islam, Paris, Tierce,
1983.
3. D. Radha Devi and M. Ravindran. "Women's Work
in India", International Social Science Journal, Volume
XXXV, No. 4, 1983.
4. Govind Kelkar. Comparative analysis of Indian and
Chinese experiences of institutionalization of popular
participation in development (in particularfor women),
Unesco, 1979.
5. Claudine Vidal. Les femmes wolof dans un milieu
rural en mutation: marginalisation ou intégration?, un¬
published doctoral thesis, Paris, 1981.
AMADOU MOUSTAPHA DIOP, Senegalese
specialist in migration problems, is engaged in
research with the French Centre for the Study of
International Relations. He also lectures at the
National Institute of Oriental Languages and
Civilizations, Paris.
The 'newpoof
by Giovanni Sarpellon
IN the past decade, three phenomena
have been observed in the West
which are gradually bringing major
changes to the structures of production,
society and even culture. These are the
cessation of big-city expansion, the
mushrooming of small and medium-sized
firms, and the return to a personalization
of labour. The combined effects of these
three phenomena undoubtedly mark the
end of the industrial era which, as it gra¬
dually unfolded, saw the birth of the in¬
dustrial giants and, around them, of the
huge conurbations in which the "working
class" acquired its present form.
This transformation has been greatly
facilitated by the establishment, im¬
mediately after the Second World War,
of large industrial firms which sought to
extract maximum benefit from econo¬
mies of scale in the technical and produc¬
tion spheres. However, all the disadvan¬
tages of these vast enterprises became
painfully apparent in the late 1960s and
thereafter: the technical advantages
proved markedly inferior to the dis¬
advantages where labour organization
and management were concerned.
Independently of any value judgement
on the trade union struggles in these
years results have been encouraging in
many respects but discouraging in
others such struggles inevitably
brought big firms into situations of con¬
flict which have had very harmful reper¬
cussions on their management systems.
The swift but silent response has been to
embark on the "deverticalization" of
large firms, which has been matched by
the parallel development of smaller com¬
panies. I am thinking here of small and
medium-sized firms outside urban areas,
whose expansion is facilitated by tech¬
nological innovations.
The present crisis is above all a crisis of
the city, of urban economics and urban
society.
The numbers of workers with which
large-scale urban industry is flooding the
labour market fail to find, on the spot, the
jobs that nevertheless exist in the "out¬
lying" regions where the new production
process is under way. There is thus from
the outset a "territorial" imbalance be¬
tween supply and demand where jobs are
concerned. Consequently there is grow¬
ing unemployment in the big cities. The
great European cities are facing problems
that were formerly inconceivable: fami¬
lies with no means of support claim full
relief, and attempts are made to satisfy
their needs by wholly outdated means
such as soup kitchens and State hostels.
The territorial imbalance between
supply and demand on the labour market
is aggravated by an equally wide gap be¬
tween the occupational skills available
and the skills in demand. Unemployed
workers are primarily to be found in the
heavy industry sector, i.e. they are skilled
in a trade which emerged, more or less
directly, from the industrial revolution of
the nineteenth century. But the jobs cur¬
rently available are increasingly to be
found in the sector of micro-electronics,
indisputably the mainspring of another
"revolution" which is bringing profound
changes to production systems and work¬
ing methods.
The technological revolution poses a
threat to the productive class as a whole,
numerically, economically and political¬
ly. The traditional industrial sectors are
continually losing jobs and are involving
other, related activities in their decline;
new wealth and new social prestige are
developing out of the new occupations,
and, if present trends continue, the num¬
ber of individuals making a living from
their labour is bound to decline.
At the same time, attitudes towards
inequalities are also noticeably shifting.
Many things have changed since the in¬
dustrial revolution, in the ideological as
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
"The numbers of workers with which
large-scale urban Industry Is flooding the
labour market fail to find, on the spot, the
jobs that nevertheless exist in the 'out¬
lying' regions. ... Consequently there is
growing unemployment in the big cities."
well as the material spheres. In the days
of large firms, it was easy to regard pro¬
duction as the fruit of a joint effort in
which it was difficult to single out the
contribution of each individual. Collec¬
tive bargaining determined workers' pay
as the outcome of a conflictual rela¬
tionship with the employer, who con¬
verted part of the workers' labour into
profit. Workers were thus impelled to
join forces in order to defend themselves
against employers, whom they regarded
as growing steadily richer at their
expense.
The situation has since changed, and
by the same token, so have attitudes to
social inequalities. The recent emergence
of the small production unit has set a new
value on the roles of both company direc¬
tor and worker. The specific contribution
of each individual has become more vis¬
ible: that of the employer, who takes the
risks, and that of the worker, who has his
or her personal stake in the success of the
firm. Profit and "personalized" wages
thus become the "fair" remuneration for
the various contributions made to the
running of the firm. Any differences aris¬
ing are thereby justified; and so are the
resulting inequalities.
This new tolerance of positive discri¬
mination (he who makes the greatest con¬
tribution deserves the greatest reward)
nevertheless has its negative side: he who
does not contribute to the joint effort is
entitled to nothing.
The affirmation of this new attitude has
had major repercussions throughout the
Western world, and much criticism has
been levelled at the systems of redistribu¬
tion of resources especially at the aid
granted to population groups outside the
labour market. This process of frag¬
mentation and individualization weakens
the feeling of belonging to a community
and gradually erodes those areas where
social solidarity with the least privileged
categories of the population can flour¬
ish with people who are excluded from
the realm of production and who are thus
in danger of being deprived of the basic
necessities of life.
This is the context in which the prob¬
lem of the new poverty arises. The ex¬
pression is ambiguous, being open to
different interpretations.
The first interpretation assigned to the
new poverty is inappropriate and should
be dropped. It has to do with the emerg¬
ence of "post-materialist" needs (new
needs) peculiar to societies which have
solved their material problems and which
are now increasingly aware of relational,
cultural or even psychological pressures.
Failure to achieve personal fulfilment,
loneliness, frustration, the inability to
make the most of leisure time, and cultu¬
ral dependence, are some of the prob¬
lems which the affluent society not only
fails to solve but which it causes and
positively exacerbates. These are, of
course, extremely important problems to
which we should not remain indifferent.
But it is equally obvious that they have
nothing to do with poverty, even if we
label it "new" poverty. In the context of
the crisis affecting the welfare state and
industrial society, the emphasis placed on
this type of "new poverty" may be seen as
an attempt to reassert the central position
of the traditional productive class and its
right to expect the State to supply it with
the means of satisfying its new needs. It is
no coincidence that this type of demand is
voiced in the same breath as harsh criti¬
cism of systems of aid (to the destitute).
There is another meaning of "new
poverty". A decade of economic difficul¬
ties has necessarily left deep scars on the
world of work. For a start, the steady
improvement in standards of living has
come to a halt, and the middle class has
been abruptly disappointed in its expec¬
tations. Just when the historical pro¬
tagonists of the industrial revolution were
reaping the fruits of their success, a long-
lasting economic crisis has occurred
which now seems to be taking a new turn.
Those who see themselves as the "new
poor" are the passive victims of this
change of direction. These new poor are
people who are excluded from the pro¬
duction process, but, still more, they tend
to be those individuals who stand to lose
their central position in society. The crisis
looming on the horizon is now taking the
form of a crisis in the unions (undermined
by corporatist attitudes), a crisis in the
political parties (weakened by their
dwindling numbers), and a crisis in cul¬
ture (moving towards new themes and
values). The technological revolution has
also thrown up a new race of "tycoons",
whose fingers are on th ; buttons of sci¬
ence, technology and power: they use
computer language and computer print¬
outs, which have reduced the people at
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Poverty and progress
large to a sort of new illiteracy, not to say
a state of utter dependence.
A new process that creates inequalities
is under way, and no effective measures
have been taken to counter it; it does
seem, however, that there has been a
general growth of awareness. The new
poverty stands revealed as the price that
society must pay if, after a period of
transition of uncertain duration, it is once
again to be able to enjoy a definite im¬
provement in its overall well-being. In
the meantime, both forms of poverty,
new and old, will continue to develop.
The new poor are, and will be, victims
of the crisis and victims of the impact of
the technological revolution. Loss of em¬
ployment is much more serious in a
period burgeoning with innovations in
the production sphere than in a period of
flagging technological progress.
The new poverty has thus evolved from
the world of work: the category most at
risk is that of unemployed adults who lack
the occupational skills made necessary by
the new technologies. There are two cate¬
gories of poor people who are still, for the
time being, in a twilight area, but who
cannot be ignored much longer. These
are the temporarily out-of-work, who are
highly unlikely to find another job in
production, and young people looking
for their first job. The former are not
poor, because they receive unemploy¬
ment benefits, whereas the latter do not
appear in the statistics of poverty because
they are still living at home in families
which are not themselves poor. And yet
both categories are in a situation which is
maintained artificially and which, sooner
or later, will turn into real poverty.
Finally, the fact cannot be glossed over
that, while it is undoubtedly necessary to
pay attention to the new categories of the
poor, whose numbers are steadily in¬
creasing, we must nevertheless not forget
those who have never ceased to live in
conditions which are even worse. This
reminder must be all the more emphatic
in view of the fact that "traditional"
poverty seems to be gaining ground as
growing numbers of individuals find
themselves in precarious and marginal
situations, while, at the same time, sys¬
tems of national assistance seem to be
tending towards steady cutbacks in
benefits, owing to the difficulties with
which national insurance schemes have
increasingly to contend.
GIOVANNI SARPELLON, Italian specialist in
problems ofdevelopment andpoverty, is profes¬
sor of sociology at the University of Venice.
The poorest of the poor
The International Movement ATD Fourth World1 was among the
participants at the international meeting on "Poverty and Prog¬
ress", held at Unesco HQ from 17 to 21 November 1986.
In a working document prepared for the meeting, Huguette
Redegeld and Eugen Brand quote a saying from Africa south of the
Sahara to the effect that "The medicine for Man is Man", and point
out that this "medicine", "for populations weakened by persistent,
acute poverty, is not simply a matter of professional expertise. It
lies in the willingness of men and women to offer an important part
of their lives, to risk their careers in order to work for progress for
others ...
"We note that progress is always slow to reach the poorest of the
poor. When the rest of the population is already beginning to taste
the fruits of forms of progress such as new communications
technologies, the poorest of the poor are still fighting illiteracy and
struggling to learn how to read and write ...
"The very poor should be involved in charting the future. History
shows that if they are not involved at the planning stage of new
projects, then they will not be the beneficiaries of change. Progress
which is meant to benefit everyone has not resulted in the elimina¬
tion of extreme poverty ...
"ATD Fourth World, founded on a refusal to let the weakest be
pushed aside, is pledged to serve those to whom it has made
commitments and with whom it works each day ... The search for
solidarity in face of the plight of the most deprived is a task of such
overriding importance that everything possible should be done to
ensure that it is fruitful. To see man as the centre of progress and to
put the weakest at the heart of our concerns is to take one step
towards mobilizing all mankind for justice and for peace."
Domina
and de
by Nguyen van Khoa
1 . ATD is the acronym for Aide à toute détresse ("Aid for all distress").
POST-COLONIAL society has, up
till now, proved unable to gener¬
ate the momentum that would
carry it forward on the path of progress.
The reason is that, although political in¬
dependence has been achieved, the
framework of dependence and domina¬
tion established under the colonial sys¬
tem remains intact and, with the appear¬
ance on the scene of international capi¬
talism, has, in fact, grown even stronger.
Under these circumstances it is ex¬
ceedingly difficult to surmount the obsta¬
cles of all kinds that stand in the way of
autonomous development.
Vis-à-vis the developed countries, the
newly-independent nations are un¬
doubtedly still in a situation of structural
dependence in that, rather than being
definable in terms of submission of the
weaker to the stronger, the relationship
between the two partners reflects a
structural imbalance. There is imbalance
of power (the industrialized countries
have greater opportunities of influencing
international economic relations), im¬
balance in financial resources (Third
World countries need capital inflow from
outside), imbalance in technological
capacity (Third World countries also
need technological input from the rich
countries) and, finally, imbalance in the
structure of production (industrial econo¬
mies on the one hand as against agricul¬
tural economies on the other).
This dependence favours the domina¬
tion of the stronger partner. Since the end
of the Second World War, imperialist
domination has replaced colonial
domination in the newly-independent
countries. This domination is exerted in
two ways: by the pressure of the Western
industrialized countries and through the
activities of transnational companies, the
effect of whose ever-growing penetration
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
tion
privation
and implantation in the poor countries is
the consolidation of the new situation of
an international division of labour.
The imperialist States and the trans¬
national companies are assuming new
roles in their relations with the dependent
States by means of economic assistance,
technical aid and political and military
supervision. In a dependent State, lack¬
ing political will and, above all, economic
resources, a bloated administrative sys¬
tem develops which becomes the instru¬
ment through which the outsiders wield
their influence. Since economic policy is
no longer in the hands of the dependent
country and strategic decisions are not
taken internally but in accordance with
the aims of the transnational companies,
new imbalances appear. Thus disparities
arise between reliance on sophisticated
technology and minimal use of local raw
materials (assembly and packaging indus¬
tries), between foreign capital-intensive
production and minimal use of local man¬
power, between development of industry
and agricultural stagnation (which results
in increased dependence upon imported
food), and between uncontrolled urban
growth and abandonment of rural areas.
Furthermore, this imperialist domina¬
tion is reproduced within the dependent
country. External imperialism is sup-
"The deeply rational character of accom¬
modation [to poverty] lies behind, at least
in part, the central instruction of the prin¬
cipal world religions. All, without excep¬
tion, urge acquiescence, some in remark¬
ably specific form," writes the American
economist John Kenneth Galbraith in his
bookThe Nature of Mass Poverty. Right, a
Vietnamese village boy.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
ported by an internal colonialism and
outside interests are linked to the in¬
terests of certain internal social groups
who see in this dependence a way of
maintaining and improving their own
status.
In the poor countries those factors that
favour the raising of the standard of living
are lacking. This is due to the operation
of the circular mechanism of the "equilib¬
rium of poverty".1 The mechanism works
like this: life at or near the subsistence
level leaves no margin for saving, and
without saving there is no possibility of
capital accumulation and investment;
without capital the rural economy cannot
itself fund the investment to improve
agricultural technology and the produc¬
tivity of the primary sector; stagnation of
the economy, which prohibits rising in¬
come, makes saving impossible.
1. See The Nature ofMass Poverty, Harvard University
Press, 1979, by John Kenneth Galbraith, from which the
quotations in this article are taken.
In the countries of the Third World,
the "equilibrium of poverty" has led to
the emergence of the "culture of pov¬
erty". The rural version of this is basically
the same as that encountered in the urban
areas whose negative characteristics it
shares, although in the rural areas certain
characteristics (such as the rejection of
innovation and "accommodation to pov¬
erty") are stronger or more pronounced.
Rejection of innovation is due to fear
of failure. Any innovation involves a cer¬
tain risk of failure, but in the context of
the poor countries the risk is particularly
serious. For an affluent Western farmer,
to take a risk and to fail, while it may be
regrettable, rarely entails real physical
deprivation and certainly will not put his
life in jeopardy. For a Third World family
living at the bare subsistence level,
however, "failure means hunger, poss¬
ibly death. So regarded, risk is not some¬
thing to be accepted casually".
All that remains is to accommodate to
poverty, to resign oneself to it and accept
it as inevitable. Such acceptance of
poverty by no means implies weakness of
character; on the contrary, it is "a pro¬
foundly rational response". "It is more
civilized, more intelligent, as well as
more plausible, that people, out of the
experience of centuries, should reconcile
themselves to what has for so long been
the inevitable." "It is, more specifically, a
formula for making the best of a usually
hopeless situation." "The deeply rational
character of accommodation lies behind,
at least in part, the central instruction of
the principal world religions. All, without
exception, urge acquiescence [ in the in¬
evitability of poverty], some in remark¬
ably specific form."
NGUYEN VAN KHOA is a Vietnamese-born
educator who is currently an external lecturer in
research and documentation at the University of
Paris. He has a special interest in the sociology
of development.
overty and progress
Class, caste andpower
by Ambalal Somabhai Patel THE basic cause of poverty in de¬
veloping countries is usually con¬
sidered to be the economic back¬
wardness or stagnation of the rural areas
where the vast majority of the population
live. In India the main occupation of
these rural people is agriculture, which
contributes almost 40 per cent to the net
domestic product. Yet the income of agri¬
cultural workers is substantially below
the national average, and is often almost
at subsistence level.
There are a number of reasons for this,
notably:
the unviable size of land holdings
(still decreasing as a result of the system
of dividing property among many);
lack of irrigation facilities, so that
farmers are dependent on rainfall and the
vagaries of nature;
lack of sufficient financial resources
to invest in seeds, manure or equipment,
or to pay seasonal labour costs;
lack of satisfactory administrative
machinery, such as co-operatives, to
organize the purchase and resale of agri¬
cultural produce;
lack of transport facilities and a
good road network to ensure rapid dis¬
tribution of fresh vegetables and fruit;
inadequate knowledge of farming,
farm products and seasonal crops,
through non-utilization of available faci¬
lities such as further education pro¬
grammes.
The productivity of small farms is
generally low, resulting in very poor re¬
turns on labour input and capital invest¬
ment. The plight of small farmers and
unskilled agricultural labourers is made
worse by the fact that they are ill-
equipped for alternative employment in
related sectors which could provide a
source of income during the slack season.
While economic stagnation results
from external factors that can be altered
by determined implementation of
appropriate development policies and
"Another social mechanism, exploitation,
is a natural consequence of the class,
caste and power systems, and plays an
important role In perpetuating economic,
social and political inequalities." Right, a
scene from Sadgati (1981), a film by the
Indian director Satyajit Ray.
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
programmes, there are other social or
sociological factors, which are deeply
rooted in tradition and are woven into the
fabric of Indian society. Big efforts by the
education system and the media are
needed to overcome these obstacles,
which arise from caste distinctions and
religious beliefs. The rigid hierarchy of
the caste system and the specific func¬
tions assigned to each caste since ancient
times, underpinned by religious injunc¬
tions, provide little scope for upward
mobility. Rural people are also more con¬
servative and traditional in their outlook
and believe so strongly in religious practi¬
ces, social customs and superstitions that
they resist attempts to change social be¬
haviour and attitudes. The weight of past
traditions, customs and values acts as a
brake on economic development and the
rapid elimination of poverty.
Another social mechanism, exploita¬
tion , is a natural consequence of the class ,
caste and power systems, and plays an
important role in perpetuating economic,
social and political inequalities. The rich
exploit the poor in subtle ways of which
the latter may be unaware; employers
exploit employees; engineers exploit con¬
tractors or builders; the upper classes or
castes exploit the lower; school adminis
trators exploit teachers; teachers exploit
students (although sometimes the reverse
is the case); doctors and lawyers exploit
patients and clients; intellectuals exploit
non-intellectuals and create problems of
student unrest.
Among other factors which affect the
economic well-being of a society are
family composition and size, which influ¬
ence not only the intellectual and person¬
al characteristics of family members, but
also affect the family's financial status
and the benefits derived from it. Two
families differing in size and age structure
may derive very different benefits from
an equal total income. On the other
hand, two families of equal size may have
unequal earning capacities because of dif¬
ferences in age, sex, intellectual and per¬
sonality traits, social or job status, or the
number of aged, infirm or young family
members.
Since the poor are usually unem¬
ployed, unemployment is often regarded
as a cause of poverty. It should rather be
seen as a contributing factor, or as a
consequence of other variables which
may co-exist with poverty.
Demographic factors have been raised
in discussions of poverty because the
population parameter appears in the
measurement of wealth in terms of per
capita national income. One conclusion
drawn from this is that in order to reduce
poverty, the numerator (national in¬
come) should increase, while the denomi¬
nator (population size) should be re¬
duced. At one time the population factor
was relegated to the background Karl
Marx, for example, saw no link between
demographic growth and poverty and
held the capitalist system entirely
responsible for the latter. In the 1950s
and 1960s many developing countries ex¬
perienced a population explosion as the
result of a rapid decline in mortality rates
unaccompanied by a corresponding fall in
the birthrate. This again brought the
population factor to the forefront.
However, to imply that rapid population
growth is the cause or even one of the
main causes of the problem of poverty is
clearly an oversimplification of the
problem.
AMBALAL SOMABHAI PATEL, Indian special¬
ist in experimental and social psychology, is
director of the Psycho-Clinic and Psycho-
Assessment Services, Baroda, Gujarat, India,
and editor of the Indian Journal of Psychology,
the official organ of the Indian Psychological
Association, of which he is a former president.
-
<
©
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
An open book
by Igor Petryanov-Sokolov
A Soviet recipe for promoting the reading habit
THE chief purpose of the Book-
lovers' Society of the USSR is to
encourage the greatest possible
number of people to become interested in
books, and particularly to develop a taste
for reading among children and
teenagers, whose attention tends to be
monopolized by television, the cinema
and video. For the book and the screen
are not interchangeable. The cinema dis¬
penses readymade impressions, whereas
reading demands an intensive effort of
thought and imagination which has con¬
siderable formative value.
Seventeen million booklovers of every
Soviet nationality, age and occupation
are members of the Society, which is
active in the fifteen federal republics, in
the autonomous republics, the territor¬
ies, the regions, and in over 4,000 cities,
towns and districts. It has 194,000 cells in
enterprises, factories, construction sites,
agricultural co-operatives and schools.
Its role is to become a genuine instru¬
ment of exchange and dialogue between
cultures through helping all kinds of
people to get to know the treasures of
Soviet and other literatures.
The Society engages in a wide range of
activities including the organization of
exhibitions, literary debates, book festi¬
vals, theatrical and musical perform¬
ances, and meetings with writers. By
these means it seeks to develop a taste for
reading and an interest in contemporary
literature.
Collaboration with libraries has always
been an essential part of the Society's
work. The specialists who serve on the
Society's management committees help
libraries to build up their collections and
inform young people in workers' hostels,
factories, schools and other institutions
about the existence of such library
facilities.
As a contribution to the United Na¬
tions International Youth Year (1985), a
children's art competition was held on the
theme of "pages from favourite books",
and book weeks were organized for chil¬
dren and teenagers.
A regular feature of the Society's acti-
EXLIBRIS UNESCO
a
The Booklovers' Society of the USSR
marked the 40th anniversary of Unesco
with this bookplate design representing a
globe within the pages of a book.
vities are the annual festivals for young
readers organized by local branches in
each republic in collaboration with youth
libraries. Examples include a major chil¬
dren's book festival in Lithuania, a festi¬
val organized by the school sections of the
Booklovers' Society of Armenia, a
Young Booklover's Rally in Azerbaijan,
and the Schools Literary Festival in the
Russian SFSR. A Booklovers' Day and
Book Festival held in Moscow in 1985
were a great success.
It is not unusual for booklovers to give
practical expressions of solidarity with
readers in other republics. Ukrainian
readers organized a collection of books
for libraries in Gazli, a town in Uzbeki¬
stan which was destroyed in an earth¬
quake. Libraries in Tajikistan, which also
suffered in the earthquake, similarly re¬
ceived gifts of books.
The Society also acts as a link between
authors, publishers, distributors and
bookbuyers. Travelling libraries on boats
or in buses go all over the country, taking
collections of the latest books to isolated
communities. One specially equipped
"bibliobus" for readers in the town of
Neriungri in Yakutia caters for a nearby
coalmine, a prefabricated material fac¬
tory and building sites. In the Ashkabad
region (Turkmen SSR) booklovers have
set up small libraries on ships and air¬
liners. They also send books to day-
schools and boarding schools, hospitals,
village libraries and the sites of major
public works projects. The delivery of
parcels of books to construction workers
on the second Trans-Siberian railway was
given top priority.
Most booklovers' circles also try to
meet the ever greater demand from
young factory executives for scientific
and technical literature dealing with their
branch of activity. Young readers are also
interested in book preservation and res¬
toration in a single year, 500,000
volumes were restored in more than 400
bookbinding clubs in schools in the Cher¬
kassy region (Ukrainian SSR). Many
clubs draw on the teaching resources of
museums, and are introducing a growing
number of young workers, kolkhoz mem¬
bers, students and schoolchildren to liter¬
ature, art, history and the sciences. One
example of this trend is the literary and
musical circle accommodated in the for¬
mer home, now a museum, of the novelist
7ïvo examples of calligraphy from the
Soviet Union. Above, a seal designed in
1919 by Sergei Chekhonin for the Depart¬
ment of VisualArt of the People's Commis¬
sariat of Education. Right, a 1913 litho¬
graph produced by Kazimir Malevich for
the coverofapoetryanthology, The Three.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
fc < HMjfr"-*- m Tai r~i Ar*« » i />»**** . ">t ^i
,.,.* M« ^'..,,.-.1 * . ..^^..»^-. « /^UAAM<« ^**y
-.*-- yw-t-r >**-*rt#* ^^» -£**t,w- ,*».'.**, /i--.**.* -
.'«( n4-t»>.<J4 AhAK<VH at**-íVt4t**»á ^ '.«J*S>+«~
,.,-.<* ...
*y-« -<*<.. ¿*"*-y
JEST**, *
(__^-f, _f*. i>HMh(u^ "í--^^
. f*i^-¿t<Va ¿iw /lfXp«4CAPk
..i/'in.M/'* ,*.**»* ii*><i~~^i'4 .Vuw, ¿i»ih *y> *i,
i«AU . ...«y >#- y^ywW» fp«ÉP«vy TV***-*^ J~-\4*J> mi
1111*1 I Jl I l&w*« -.:*.**- -^r-w* .-****. /^4*.*»U - /U4**>
fipTt|_ijL|il1 . 4w .< . - . *r- . B "fr.gm p/miA, «r ><
Jtt.. if if- - f , . .i^, if,(.j|I(. > f*f^ittmu* _d»j*
IlíPtAtC * . A L _ I llVirT r***"" >« UBifiuw //<
/ ¿ui.i / t*.***t«-**<«-»i
ll~la.llii _l|__ ..ifi//i. .(!"#>[ .'* *fc»'»* /m«
- "	. .,.-.KM/iii' .,«..*»#..* f.. PitfjMi /i'rtu. iiifili '-yy* pfffd- . T»y
/ *-*>« »*,,<.» , M . a.<i>i«mi*u.#.ii *« y,.4i*». ,v,^ J»«1*/»* n*/*
MMflW.« i' y y- -*X mvmUBmlßf fa» f, .,..*., ffty,.ii,n***if/i *
pa- « i »j «i *».» , 4H.L.1* ~4+*. -t*»_mciàfm*t~i n .ii»/**», í*'-
* '	 TEJLrlf 	 > _ I II *J fc* *t tru-V 4kj>W*P*PNI
-y/*^../r'. ..-.- ...,, i» ._.« «»£* / ftMrlamMy A*-»- m
*-..- »M«P|» *.,,*.#,. * , *i í'í fM*jM J.J»y,,-.J- . IMMP*Ai A" -rff**0 *4» l*4f'
..-. t" .'. y in - y<.**,.-^*~r **4~i* »». :'-ih..*... f.i * IMwl . ''^1/ J
*-ir#ï^,p
rj*mu .* «fSc« * 6u r»
i/iiii» 0 .	
piiH»< . /4% fffTf n'i Y^-T -^
/fiti^H^^rivm« ¿yfc%*T-***y. J^*t ^-P«*pi- í* -ApXyrt.^T^WjÉ |^ -¿p*^^
pjt ii-+JT' t,$~4-fv ******* F*-* A ^i+sfun* 'in'lJii.K.J.v -W.Í /iu«-«^
+t.J+ c,*-.^ ri4N^-4.jiry. -Nr**.4-y <***»- -' íítau^t --* -^-yj»-^ *"*y*'
v^- *' /'ici'..-» y ** i,»"'/»! /i^y^C"/Mi ^ y,_l.*.**#* jC***»* ^
imtwirn i . fif.*,ji/^.'r.i;./
ff I '^"-(. <-j-**. .ii^.* ivr.ii<i«i<" ^ « iy-" *"* 3 i*»»*^*-»»/!-.
/^«fy^i - ,r*n. ~ i * f'-m^y.. ...*«»»»" y- r< .-*.« .
.# , /' ^HMfl r-.-4-^ *~4*t-4'^*4,i ¿' M</vj, t«r/Mf <¡¡P
ií"<W' .*.'44-»*iM4tF J* Itfii-'i./lf-Mj ^*4y,^*~~.t***L**4^4me, ,jy-,.,,,..+ .
W*rJt*st+. r S* . ''.-y>-P-j -/* J" <iy^.>*t * *é*y**¿j*<-4i
-. Ill«, A.\jt-4 tttJt Jf s*tJ.^-+4*y*414* f'+* ****
ff\tH^ » ,Str***\rti4*r\ J-t- *J
*£Hhj ^ - - - * ' ** n/jt*«< y' yy«4., *<^. - * .mr
i .fr--*~*r"i.t.é ', + ,.,ri- /</...,t,.|y, f m*r- *-£***. ««,
-#--y i ,i0.f 'i * * , ' -y*.
Above, Poems by Osip Mandelstam (1979),
a calligraphic study in Indian ink by Alex¬
ander Yulikov (born 1943), which was
shown at an exhibition on the art of cal¬
ligraphy organized at Unesco Headquar¬
ters in October 1986 by the USSR National
Commission for Unesco and the Artists'
Union of the USSR.
Constantine Fedin at Saratov (Russian
SFSR).
The Society publishes bibliographical
works, literary criticism, biographies of
famous bibliophiles and collectors, and
descriptions of great libraries. It pub¬
lishes more than 300 titles a year, mainly
literary works and art books, with a print
run of over a million copies.
The Society has contributed to the
erection of monuments to great writers
and to the creation of book museums and
book centres in localities which have no
public library. It has, for example, helped
to restore the monument to Nikolai
Gogol at Poltava in the Ukrainian SSR,
and to the opening of the Mikhail
Lermontov Museum at Taman, in the
Caucasus.
The Society's central directorate estab¬
lishes and maintains close contacts with
similar associations in the other Socialist
countries and in capitalist countries
which have cultural relations with the
USSR. International meetings and co¬
operation and exchange agreements in
the fields of books and publishing contri¬
bute to the enrichment of knowledge, the
spread of humanitarian ideals and the
strengthening of friendship between
peoples.
IGOR PETRYANOV-SOKOLOV is president of
the Booklovers' Society of the USSR. A noted
chemist, he is a member of the USSR Academy
of Sciences and editor-in-chief of the Soviet
scientific journal "Chemistry and Life". He has
been awarded the Lenin Prize and the State
Prize of the USSR, and in 1984 was co-recipient
of Unesco's Kalinga Prize for the Popularization
of Science.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Games, sports and traditions
ce
©
ce
m
ai
ABUNDANT documentation exists in
the form of paintings, sculpture and
writing ¡n some cases dating back
to very early times of the importance of
sports, rituals, dances and games in the
traditions of peoples all over the world.
The nature of these activities has been
influenced by the cultures of the peoples
which developed them and shaped them
The North American game of "earthball" is
the modern version of an ancient game
used ceremonially in certain cultures to
express an exuberant belief In the regen¬
erative forces of nature. Two teams take
part in an energetic but good-humoured
struggle forpossession ofa large ball rep¬
resenting the earth, above. A similargame
with symbolic andreligious significance is
still played in Japan. It is known as "the
ball-struggle of Hakozaki Shrine", and
takes place on 3 January each year in
Fukuoka City. The participants (left) are all
young men, clad only in loincloths, who
represent their home districts. A sacred
wooden ball is used in the game. In his
book Naked Festivals of Japan, Tamotsu
Yato writes: "The fighting mêlée gradually
moves in the return direction of the shrine,
while spectators and priests throw cold
water over the naked throng ... The side
that has possession of the ball as the
group enters the shrineprecincts wins and
has the honour of returning the ball to its
priest-custodian. "
into original creations through which the
body can "speak" its own language.
Celtic trials of strength; Afghan buzkashi;
Basque pelota; Korean tae kwon do; Afri¬
can wrestling; Japanese martial arts;
Caribbean limbo dancing; lumberjack con¬
tests in Canada; Moroccan fantasia; Rus¬
sian sombo wrestling; canoe racing and
water jousting these are just a few of the
many traditional sports and games still
practised today.
The world's rich diversity of games and
sports consists of forms of expression
which reflect the identity of each people and
form part of the cultural and artistic heritage
of humanity.
Paradoxically, however, the increasing
popularity of sport is itself jeopardizing the
existence of traditional games which are
too often held to be of minor or marginal
importance because they are confined to
certain localities or regions.
Today the attention of millions of tele¬
viewers around the world is monopolized
by some twenty games and sports, whose
hold is strengthened by the fascination ex¬
ercised by the small screen, the power of
the image and the cult of the heroes created
by the media. The threat of disappearance
or marginalization hangs over a whole set
of authentic popular cultures.
In response to the new awareness of the
value of these traditional games and sports
that has developed in the last few years,
Unesco's Intergovernmental Committee for
Physical Education and Sport (ICPES) has
recommended Member States to preserve
and make more widely known these origin¬
al manifestations of their national cultures.
As a result, a programme of World Fes¬
tivals of Games, Sports and Traditions,
organized in collaboration with the Interna¬
tional Fund for the Development of Physic¬
al Education and Sport (FIDEPS), is sche¬
duled to begin in mid-1987 in Asia and
Europe. A large number of organizations,
countries, towns and cities have already
expressed the wish to be associated with
this initiative. Similar festivals will be orga¬
nized periodically in other continents, so
that most of the traditional sports and
games still practised can be presented to
televiewers throughout the world.
The purpose of the Festivals, which will
include entertainments, public demonstra¬
tions, symposiums, exhibitions and film
shows, is to preserve the authentic nature
of each game.
The forthcoming World Decade for Cultu¬
ral Development (1988-1998) is bound to
draw attention to this renewal of interest in
traditional games and sports.
For further information about the World Festival of
Games, Sports and Traditions, please write to: Unesco/
FIDEPS, ED/SCM, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris,
France.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Treasuresfrom an ancient Chinese tomb *>y w Ruuang
FOR years archaeologists working
in China's Shaanxi Province had
tried to deduce the location of a
2,500-year-old royal cemetery from clues
scattered in an ancient historical chron¬
icle, the Shi Ji. They mounted no less
than five expeditions in search of the
cemetery, the burial ground of the lead¬
ers of the Qin family which ruled in north¬
western China during what is known as
the "Spring and Autumn Period" and the
"Warring States Period" of Chinese his¬
tory (770-221 BC). During the last of
these expeditions, in 1976, they dis¬
covered a large tomb, investigation of
which convinced them that they had not
only located the cemetery but the site of
the Qin capital itself, the magnificent and
mysterious city of Yongcheng,
The tomb, which the archaeologists
called the "Duke of Qin Tomb No. 1"
(the head of a state at that time being
known as a "duke") is situated some 160
kilometres west of Xian. It was about 25
kilometres east of this ancient Chinese
capital that a fabulous army of life-size
terra-cotta statues of soldiers and horses
was discovered in 1974 (see the Unesco
Courier, December 1979). These re¬
markable statues accompanied the tomb
of a later member of the family and
founder of the Qin dynasty, Qin Shi
Huang, the first emperor of a united
China, who lived from 259 to 210 BC.
The Duke of Qin's tomb sheds light on an
earlier period of Chinese history it
dates from several centuries earlier than
that of Qin Shi Huang.
Yongcheng was the political, econo¬
mic, military and cultural hub of the Qin
State for almost 300 years, during which it
became known as a magnificent and gran¬
diose State capital.
Excavations have shown that the site is
divided into two major sections the
cemetery, and a cluster of palace build¬
ings which lay within city walls. Remains
of the walls indicate that the palace area
measured 3,300 metres from east to west
and 3,200 metres from north to south, an
area of 11 square kilometres.
Four main groups of buildings dating
from the Spring and Autumn Period have
been located in the south of the city. One
group, a complex of earth and timber
temples used for ancestor-worship, cov¬
ers more than 7,000 square metres and is
the largest and best-preserved example of
Qin temple architecture yet found.
Another group (covering 21,800
square metres) comprises five palace
courtyards which extended from south to
north and are regarded as the most com¬
plete example of early Qin State
architecture. Comparison of this site with
data from contemporary writings has
convinced archaeologists that heads of
state during the Spring and Autumn
Period administered public affairs in the
open air in such palace courtyards, thus
continuing the tradition of an earlier
tribal society.
The buildings of Yongcheng were of a
sophisticated double-pillar construction,
ornamented with delicately engraved
bronzework, some sixty fragments of
Archaeologists and sightseers are
dwarfed by the size of the first major tomb
to be excavated in the cemetery of Yong¬
cheng, the capital from which Dukes of the
Qin family ruled part of China some 2,500
years ago, before the country was united
under its first Emperor, Qin Shi Huang
(259-210 BC).
which have been unearthed. Archaeolog¬
ists have also found specimens of roof
tiles decorated with graceful human and
animal motifs such as a young deer with
its mother, a jumping frog, a hunter and a
tiger. One interesting feature of the
palace is an underground cold store, the
oldest known icebox, which could hold
some 190 cubic metres of ice.
Yongcheng's cemetery, which extends
7 kilometres from east to west and 3
kilometres from north to south, com¬
prises thirteen graveyards of various
shapes and sizes, each ringed by a moat.
The total length of the moats, which were
formerly linked together, is 35
kilometres.
There are eighteen large tombs with
two symmetrical aisles. These are known
as "tp"-shaped tombs since their layout
viewed from above looks like the Chinese
character "*f". There are also three
tombs with one aisle. These are known as
"^"-shaped tombs since their layout is
similar to the Chinese character "^" . The
number of small and medium-sized
tombs has not yet been calculated. Each
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
large tomb is accompanied by pits in
which sacrifices, such as wagons -and
horses, were buried. The largest pit is 116
metres long and 25 metres wide.
The Duke of Qin Tomb No. 1 is "tp-
shaped" and resembles an inverted pyra¬
mid built into the ground. It extends 59.4
metres from east to west, 38.8 metres
from north to south, and is 24 metres
deep from ground level to the bottom of
the tomb. The two aisles, 7 to 19 metres
wide and with a total length of 270
metres, form a deep valley which leads to
the coffin chamber, which has three
levels and measures 40 metres by 20
metres at the base. Some 160 containers
of human sacrifices were found around
and above the lowest level, arranged
according to their social status in life. In
addition, the bodies of twenty slaves,
their limbs bent, were buried in the dirt
close to the surface.
Each human sacrifice container is
labelled with characters and numbers
carved on cinnabar. Objects found in the
containers with the bodies tools, pig¬
ments, bronze mirrors or strings of
pearls suggest that these men and
women were intended to serve the Duke
in the "other world" as labourers, craft-
workers, or entertainers. Little imagina¬
tion is required to picture their sufferings
when they were buried, and to conceive
of the cruelty and barbarity of the Qin
regime.
The main coffin was placed in a struc¬
ture 15 metres long and 6 metres wide,
built with three layers of square timbers
joined without a single metal nail. The
top layer consisted of 56 timbers, prob¬
ably high quality pine, each 20 cms
square, some 6 metres long, and weighing
about 300 kilograms. All knots in the
timber had been replaced with cast metal,
often in blocks as big as a fist, to prevent
the wood from rotting away. We do not
know how metal was cast in wood at this
early period, when even iron tools were
rare. The timbers were painted and fur¬
ther preserved by a layer of charcoal, up
to 3 metres thick in some places, which
covered the whole structure.
Two long wooden logs , which had been
used to lay the main coffin to rest during
the funeral, were found lying at an angle
in the soil on either side of it. These logs
are the earliest "tombstones" ever found
in China. In later times the tomb owner's
name and his funeral elegy were carved
on such wooden "tombstones", and later
still the practice of placing a stone tablet
in front of a tomb was adopted.
Although the Duke of Qin Tomb had
often been robbed in ancient times,
archaeologists have discovered some
2,600 funeral objects made of such mate¬
rials as stone, jade, iron, bronze, pottery,
lacquer, bamboo, wood, silk, and clay.
The most valuable finds are twenty ex¬
quisitely crafted and highly polished
musical stones or chimes, many of which
are complete and can still produce clear
and melodious sounds. Carved on the
chimes are 190 superbly calligraphed
characters executed in a similar style to
the inscriptions found on drum-shaped
stone blocks from the "Warring States"
Period (475-221 BC).
Several iron artefacts such as shovels
have also been excavated, providing the
earliest evidence of metal technology yet
found in northern China.
Unfortunately, not many precious
metal artefacts are left. Those which have
survived include gold animal figures,
rings, beads, bronze swords with gold
handles, gold decorations for carts and
horses, and gold wire springs. Pieces of
jade, often of high quality with still-clear
designs, have also been found.
Not all of these gold and jade objects
belonged to the tomb owner. Many hu¬
man sacrifices also wore jewellery, such
as strings of gold or turquoise beads.
Even the sacrificial wagons and horses
were decorated with gold, most of the
highly-imaginative designs showing hu¬
man or animal figures of varying shapes.
Such finds, manifestations of a highly
diverse culture, are invaluable for
anthropological studies on the arts and
the forms of entertainment in Qin
society.
Small pieces of silk found in the tomb
illustrate the high standard of weaving
techniques at that time, and their designs,
though faded, still give some idea of the
brightness of the original colours.
Archaeologists and natural scientists
are collaborating closely in the conserva¬
tion of objects from the Duke of Qin
Tomb No. 1, which is still being ex¬
cavated. (The other major tombs are also
to be excavated.) For some time my col¬
leagues and I have been studying the
applications of laser technology and
other modern scientific processes to the
conservation of cultural relics. We have
been successful in using our laser equip¬
ment to remove rust, contaminant and
mildew, and have so far completed the
surface cleaning of twenty-six objects
made of such materials as iron, bronze,
stone, pottery and silk, as well as ancient
paintings and calligraphy.
The most remarkable advantage of the
laser-cleaning technique is that it does
not damage the surface of the object,
including any vestiges of designs or in¬
scriptions. Moreover, when a layer of
rust is removed by laser, the artefact does
not readily rust again.
The application of this technique was
costly at first, but now the expense has
come down to a level acceptable to the
departments responsible for the pre¬
servation of cultural relics. We are
however trying to further reduce the cost
of our service, to ensure that the salvage
and conservation of our cultural heritage
from this ancient civilization will
continue.
WEN RUITANG, Chinese engineer, is a special¬
ist in the conservation ofarchaeological relics by
means of laser technology.
m *
w
nC_ rp
-.; 'v
The ruler buried in the newly-excavated
tomb was surroundedbyhuman sacrifices
and various objects for use in the next
world. Crafted In materials such as jade,
iron, bronze, pottery, wood and silk, the
mass of finds so far unearthed àt Yong¬
cheng shed light on tastes and technolo¬
gies in an obscure period of early Chinese
history. From top to bottom: a jade arte¬
fact, a stone fish, two stone statues andan
eaves tile with an animal design.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
UNICEF
at forty
ON 11 December 1986 UNICEF, the
United Nations Children's Fund,
celebrated its 40th anniversary.
Forty years is a short time when set
against the changes needed to protect the
world's children from death, hunger and
sickness, and to eradicate illiteracy and suf¬
fering. Every six seconds somewhere in the
world a child dies or becomes handicapped
as the result of an illness against which he
could have been vaccinated. Most of each
day's 40,000 child deaths could be avoided.
Much thus remains to be done. But in the
last forty years, UNICEF has carried out
action programmes in many fields:
Aid to orphans and malnourished chil¬
dren in Europe in the aftermath of the
Second World War, and today in the de¬
veloping world;
Emergency aid to millions of children in
Palestine, Kampuchea, Bangladesh, Peru,
Ethiopia and elsewhere;
Long-term development projects in
almost all Third World countries (UNICEF
is currently active in 113 developing coun¬
tries);
Co-operation in efforts to eradicate dis¬
eases such as yaws and smallpox;
Launching new methods of child protec-
PhotO UNICEF
tion with the participation of local popula¬
tions;
Training hundreds of thousands of per¬
sons in teaching, agriculture, childbirth
methods, hygiene, etc.;
Provision throughout the world of medic¬
al and school supplies, water pumps, and
hundreds of thousands of tonnes of equip¬
ment;
Application at country and local levels of
new technical measures relating to vaccina¬
tion, child care, breast-feeding and oral re¬
hydration therapy;
Telling the public through UNICEF
national committees and their teams of
volunteers about new techniques for solving
child welfare problems.
UNICEF is wholly financed by voluntary
contributions from governments and pri¬
vate individuals. 75% of its resources are
provided by governments and 25% from
fund-raising campaigns and the sale of
greetings cards and stationery. This year's
all-the-year-round greeting cards are now
available at UNICEF sales points through¬
out the world. In addition to the cards
UNICEF is also offering a variety of other
stationery including correspondence fol¬
ders, postcards, gift labels, and birth
announcement cards, as well as educational
games (jigsaw puzzles and models) and
other gifts. Above, a poster created by the
Belgian artist Jean-Michel Folon to mark
the 40th anniversary of UNICEF.
The Courier jm
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Office:
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Subscription rates
1 year: 90 French francs.
Binder for a year's issues: 62 FF
The Unesco (Courier is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus date of
issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the
editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author's
name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be
returned unless accompanied by an international
reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not
necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco or
those of the editors of the Unesco Courier. Photo
captions and headlines are written by the Unesco
Courier staff. The boundaries on maps published in
the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The
Unesco Courier is produced in microform
(microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco, 7
Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2) University
Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100,
U.S.A. ; (3) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian
Head, Inc., Ill West 40th Street, New York,
U.S.A. ; (4) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mansfield
Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Editorial staff (Paris)
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Roy Malkin
Caroline Lawrence
French: Alain Lévêque
Neda el Khazen
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov
Arabic: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Braille: Frederick Potter
Research: Violette Ringelstein
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Servat, George Ducret
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Sales and subscriptions: Henry Knobil
Special projects: Peggy Julien
All correspondence should be addressed to
the Editor-in-chief in Paris
Non-Headquarters editions
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ram Babu Sharma (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian:
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra Ilgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwah (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Bozidar Perkovic (Beigrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Lina Svenzén (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
34 IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France) - Dépôt légal : C 1 - Décembre 1986
PHOTOCOMPOSITION : Ateliers de I'UNESCO - PHOTOGRAVURE-IMPRESSION : MAURY-IMPRIMEUR S.A.. Z.I. route d'Étampes, 45330 MALESHERBES.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
TheCourier
For people who care about
the rest of the world . . .
A monthly magazine, each
issue usually devoted to a single
theme
Stimulating and informative
coverage from a wide range of
viewpoints
A window open on the world
A meeting-place for different
outlooks and cultures
A valuable source of ideas and
information on current issues
such as development, new
technologies, human rights and
the rights of peoples, and the
cultural heritage
A powerful instrument in the
service of international solidarity
and understanding
Forthcoming issues include:
The Alpine countries
Travellers' tales
The anthropology of food
Medicine around the world
The baroque
Genetics and ethics
Join or ask
your friends to
join our international
family of more
than 3 million readers
around the world.
Annual subscription
12 issues: 90 French francs
The only magazine in the world
published in 32 languages, with 4 (free) language editions in Braille.
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco periodicals
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58a Gipps St., Collmgwood, Victoria 3066;
Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100,
NSW; Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale
2100, NSW. Sub-agent: United Nations Association of Australia, P.O. Box
175, 5th floor, Ana House, 28 Elizabeth St., Melbourne, Victoria 3000.
AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31, A-1011, Vienna.
BAHRAIN. United Schools International, Arab Regional Office, P.O. Box 726,
Bahrain. BARBADOS. University of the West Indies Bookshop, Cave Hill
Campus, P.O. Box 64, Bridgetown. BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch
edition only: Internationale Drukkerij en Uitgevery Keesing, Keesinglaan 2-20,
2100 Deurne-Antwerpen. CCP 000-0012775-68. French edition and general
Unesco publications agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202 Ave. du Roi, 1 060 Brussels,
CCP 000-0070823-13. BRAZIL Publicaçoes Técnicas Internacional Ltda,
Processing Dept., R Peixoto Gomide 209, 01409. Sao Paulo SP. CANADA.
Renouf Publishing Co. Ltd., 1294 Algoma Road, Ottawa, Ontario K1B 3W8.
STORES: 61 Sparks Street. Ottawa, 21 1 Yonge St., Toronto. SALES OFFICE:
7575 Trans Canada Hwy. Ste. 305. St. Laurent, Quebec H4T 1V6. CHINA.
China National Publications Import and Export Corporation, P.O. Box
Beijing. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L.. Spalena 51-113 02, Prague 1; Ve
Smeckach 30, P.O.B. 790-1 1 1 -27 Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni
literatura, 11 Soukenicka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only:. Alfa Verlag.-Pub-
lishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava-CSSR. DENMARK. Munk-
sgaard Export-OG, Tidsskriftservice, 35 Norre Sogade, DK-1 970 Kobenhavn
K. EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco Publications,
No. 1 Talaat Harb St., Cairo. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, P. O. Box
128, SF-00100 Helsinki. Suomalamen Kirjakauppa Oy, P.O. Box 2, 01641
Vantas 64. Rautikirja Oy. Subscription Department, P.O. Box 1 , 01641 Vantas
64. FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Pans. CCP
12598-48. GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Buchhaus Leipzig, Post¬
fach 140, 71 0 Leipzig, or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R.
FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier: Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher
Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57, D5300 Bonn 3. GHANA. Fides
Entreprises. P.O. Box 14129, Accra. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE John Mihalopoulos & Son SA, International Booksellers, P.O. Box
1 0073, 54 1 1 0 Thessaloniki. G C Eleftheroudakis SA, International Bookstore,
4 Nikis Street, Athens T 1 26. Kostarakis Brothers, International Booksellers, 2
Hippocratous Street. Athens. HONG KONG. Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock
Rd., Kowloon. Hong Kong Govt. Information Services. Publication Centre.
Baskerville House, 22 Ice St. HUNGARY. Kultura-Bushimport-ABT, P.O.B.
149-H-1389, Budapest 62. ICELAND. Snaebjörn Jonsson and Co.. H.F.
Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard
Estate. Bombay 400038; 17 Chitaranjan Ave., Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai,
Mount Road, Madras 2; 5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh, Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1
Mahatma Gandhi Rd., Bangalore 560001 ; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-
500001 . Sub-depots: Oxford Book and Stationery Co., 1 7 Park St.. Calcutta
70016; Scindia House, New Delhi. INDONESIA. Indira P.T., Jl Dr. Sam
Ratulangie 37, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Iranian National Commission for Unesco,
1 1 88 Englab Ave., Rostam Give Building, Zip Code 1 31 58, P.O. Box 1 1 365-
4498, Teheran. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd., Bally-
mount Rd., Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL. A.B C. Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box
1 283. 71 Allenby Rd.. Tel Aviv 61 000. ITALY. Licosa (Librería Commissionaria
Sansoni, S.p.A.), Via Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552, 50121 Florence.
JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo 3-chome Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo
1 1 3. KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64,
Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd. POB 2942, Kuwait: for the
Unesco Courier: Farafaüa Press Agency, P.O. Box SAFA 4541. Kuwait.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur
22-1 1. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic St.. Valletta. MAURITIUS. Nalanda
Company Ltd.. 30 Bourbon St., Port-Louis. MEXICO. DILITSA, Distribuidora
Literaria SA, Apartado Postal 24 448, Mexico DF 06700. N & E Omicron SA,
Bookseller & Subscriptions Agency, Col Condesa Deleg. Cuauhtemoc, Apar¬
tado Postal 40 075, 06140 Mexico DF. Librería El Correo de la Unesco,
Actipán 66. Colonia del Valle, Mexico 12, DF. MONACO. British Library, 30
Bd. des Moulins, Monte Carlo. NEPAL Sajha Prakashan Polchowk, Kalh-
mandu. NETHERLANDS. Faxon Europe, P.O. Box 197, 1000 AD Amsterdam.
NEW ZEALAND. Government Publishing, P.O. Box 1 4277-Kilbirnie, Welling¬
ton; 130 Oxford Terrace, P.O, Box 1721. Christchurch; Alma St., P.O. Box
857, Hamilton; Princes St., P.O. Box 1 1 04, Dunedin. NIGERIA. The University
Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286. NORWAY.
Johan Grundt Tanum, P.O B. 1 1 77 Sentrum - Oslo 1 , Narvesen A/S, Litteraturt
Jenesten, P.O.B. 6125 Etterstad, N 0602 Oslo 6; Universitets Bokhandelen,
Universitetssentret, Postboks 307 Blindem, Oslo 3. PAKISTAN. Mirza Book
Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3; Unesco
Publications Centre, Regional Office for Book Development in Asia and the
Pacific, 39 Delhi Housing Society, P.O. Box 8950, Karachi 29. POLAND.
Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie
Przedmiescie No.7. 00-068 Warsaw. PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda.
Livrana Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SAUDI ARABIA. Dar al Watan.
Olaya Main Street, Ibrahim Bin Sulaym Building, Riyadh. SINGAPORE.
Federal Publications (S) Re Ltd. Times Jurong, 2 Jurong Port Rd.. Singapore
2261. SOUTH AFRICA. American & Overseas Publications (Pty) Ltd., Sub¬
scription Service, P.O. Box 42476, Johannesburg. Universitas Books (Pty)
Ltd., P.O. Box 775, Pretoria 0001. Van Schaik's Bookstore (Pty) Ltd.. Libri
Building. 268 Church Street. Pretoria 0001 . Central News Agency Ltd., Group
Overseas Periodical Div. P.O. Box 61 3, Cape Town 8000. SRI LANKA. Lake
House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata, P.OB. 244.
Colombo 2. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118. Khartoum.
SURINAME. Suriname National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box 2943,
Paramaribo. SWEDEN. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN Forbundet,
Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S-104. 65 Stockholm; Wennergren-Williams AB,
Nordenflychtsvagen 70. S-104, 25 Stockholm; Esselte Tidskriftscentralen,
Gamla Brogatan 26. Box 62 -101, 20 Stockholm. SWITZERLAND. Europa
Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse, Zürich; Librairie Payot, Rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva
11, CCP. 12-236; Librairies Payot also in Lausanne, Basle, Berne, Vevey,
Montreux. Neuchâtel and Zurich. SYRIA. Aleppo University Books Establish¬
ment, University of Aleppo, Aleppo. TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop,
P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42
Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok; Suksapan
Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Ave.. Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO.
National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra St., St. Clair, Trinidad W 1.
TURKEY. Haset Kilapevi A.S., Istiklâl Caddesi, No 469, Posta Kutusu 219,
Beyoglu, Istanbul. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, Agency Sec¬
tion Publications CTR, Periodicals Section-Room 008, Nine Elms Lane,
London SW8 5DR, and H.M.S.O. Bookshops in London, Edinburgh, Belfast.
Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol; for scientific maps only: McCarta Ltd., 122
King's Cross Rd., London WC1X 9DS. UNITED STATES. Bernan Associates-
UNIPUB, Periodicals Department, 10033-F King Highway. Lanham MD
20706. USSR. V/O Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga. Ul. Dimitrova 39, Moskva
113095. YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost, Mica 30/11, Zagreb; Cankarjeva Zalozba,
Zopitarjeva 2, Lubljana; Nolit, Terazije 27/11, Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd.. P.O. Box 2664, Lusaka.
ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 1 Norwich Union Centre, Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
*&j<äß$8ß&f#'.
wT4-
A
M:
* %
(1) Resplendent Quetzal. Pharomachrus mocin
Mexico and Central America. (2| Golden Lion
Tamarin. Leontopithecus rosalia. Brazil.
(3) Philippine Tarsier. Tarsius syrichta.
(4) Cheetah. Acinonyx jubatus. Africa and We:
Asia. (5) Kemp's Ridley Turtle. Lepidochelys
kempt. Gulf of Mexico and the Atlantic coastal
shores. (6) California Condor. Gymnogyps
californianus. (7) Hawaiian Monk Seal. Monachus
schauinslandi.
]]>
</page>
</document>
