<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="073033eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
e Courier
w m
1 m
^H .
v
H
v^ "* ^i
culture
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A time to live...
Jumping for joy
Sierra Leone is a country on the west coast of Africa with a population of
some 3,600,000. It takes its name ("Lion mountain") from that given by
the Portuguese explorer Pedro da Sintra around 1460 to the peninsula
which is the site of Freetown, the country's capital. In 1787 a settlement
for freed slaves was established on land where Freetown now stands. In
1961 Sierra Leone achieved independence, and ten years later became a
republic. Some 65 per cent of the work force is occupied in agriculture,
with rice as the main food crop. Sierra Leone is the world's sixth largest
producer of diamonds. Above, body bent back and almost obscuring the
ball, a boy throws himself into a game of soccer in a Freetown street.
52 Sierra Leone
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Editorial
In the 1960s and 1970s, the development of high-yield cereal varieties
combined with the use of pesticides , irrigation and fertilizer brought a
Green Revolution to some but not all parts of the Third World. This
issue of the Unesco Courier, which is largely devoted to the application of
new scientific techniques to agriculture, enquires into the extent to which
the Green Revolution is likely to be followed by a "Biotechnological
Revolution" which may help developing countries to solve some of their
food production problems.
Although the term biotechnology to denote the use of the biochemical
and genetic capacities of living organisms for practical purposes is fairly
new, man has been engaged in "biotechnological" activities since very
early times. Fermentation and the improvement of useful plant and
animal varieties by cross-breeding are but two examples. The new
biotechnology, however, differs from these time-honoured practices in
that it uses genetic engineering and techniques of fusing cells of different
organisms to surmount previously impassable barriers between species.
Genetic engineering (or gene-splicing) , which involves the direct transfer
of genes "those tiny command posts of heredity that tell living cells
whether they will become bacteria, toads or men" into the cells of
different species has been described as the "most powerful and awesome
skill acquired by man since the splitting of the atom . "
In the first part of this issue we look closely at some of these new
biotechnologies: how they work; how they are currently being used in
different parts of the world and to what effect; the latest trends in this
field where changes occur quickly and possibilities are vast. While our
contributors focus mainly on the direct applications of biotechnologies to
agriculture in the developing world, they also note present and potential
uses in energy production, human and animal medicine and the
management of certain environmental problems.
The second part of the issue asks broader questions. How can the new
biotechnologies be best harnessed to development in different social ,
economic and cultural contexts? Will they be a panacea or, contrariwise,
are they likely to aggravate existing disparities between developing
countries and those of the technologically advanced world? The new
biotechnologies and especially those applied to plants, put great
possibilities into the hands of those who control them. How should this
power best be exercised? How should access to the fruits of research
based on plant genetic resources originating in the developing world be
equitably organized?
Unesco, which is engaged in worldwide efforts to strengthen rural
development through training in the biological and agrobiological
sciences, in applied microbiology and in biotechnology (see article page
27) , is closely interested in the above issues as part of its basic
commitment to promote the use of science and technology for the benefit
of all humanity. The complex nature of the problems and some possible
approaches and solutions are traced by Dr. Albert Sasson in the article
which forms the conclusion of this issue.
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
March 1987
40th year
4
The new biotechnologies
Promise and performance
by Jacques C. Senez
The Green Revolution
13
The gene revolution
by Bernard Dixon
17
Tomatomation
Japan's high-tech food factories
by Koichibara Hiroshi
20
Hybrids for the year 2000
by Raissa G. Butenko and Zlata B. Shamina
22
Grains of hope
by Edward C. Wolf
24
The rediscovery of traditional
agriculture
26
Rusitec the cow
Food for rumination
27
Rhizobium, the farmer's Mr. Fixit
A Unesco programme to promote
biotechnology for development
by Edgar J. DaSilva, J. Freiré, A. Hillali
and S.O. Keya
29
A challenge for the developing world
by Albert Sasson
34
Glossary
2
A time to live...
SIERRA LEONE: Jumping for joy
Cover: Photo © Periscoop, Paris
The Courier
A window open on the world
English
French
Spanish
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Macedonian
Serbo-Croat
Slovene
Finnish
Swedish
Basque
A selection in Braille is
published quarterly in English,
French, Spanish and Korean
Published monthly in 32 languages Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese Thai
by Unesco
The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
7, Place dc Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
German
Arabic
Japanese
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese
Korean
Swahili
Croato-Serb
Bulgarian
Greek
Sinhala
ISSN 004 1-5278
N"3-1987-CPD-87-l-443 A
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
by Jacques C. Senez
The new
biotechnologies
Promise and performance
SINCE the beginnings of civilization,
man has been a biotechnologist, tak¬
ing advantage of the activities of
micro-organisms of whose very existence he
was unaware, to produce foodstuffs and fer¬
mented drinks. Over the centuries, the
practices by which he did this gradually
developed, in a makeshift, empirical fash¬
ion, to attain a high degree of perfection.
Yet biotechnology proper, in the sense of
the scientific use of biological principles for
practical purposes, only emerged at the end
of the last century with the birth of micro¬
biology and its early application to indus¬
trial fermentation processes.
Since the Second World War, biology has
made prodigious progress. In just a few
years the basic mechanisms of life and
heredity at the molecular level have been
unveiled, thus opening up limitless hori¬
zons. Some of these prospects, in particular
that of the development of genetic engi¬
neering (see article page 13) with its con¬
notations of man the creator, captured the
imagination and fired the enthusiasm of the
general public.
The transfer of genetic material between
organisms as widely different as bacteria,
plants, animals and man gave rise to great
hopes, some of which, such as the produc¬
tion of human insulin by bacteria recom-
bined in vitro, have already become reality.
Today, these methods are on the verge of
finding new applications of considerable
economic and social importance in the field
of agriculture. It would be wrong, however,
to think that the prospects for biotechnol¬
ogy are limited to the field of genetic engi¬
neering. Recent advances in fundamental
knowledge and techniques in the physiol¬
ogy of cells, biochemistry, enzyme catalysis
and bioengineering are just as promising.
It is generally thought that there is a great
future for biotechnology in the developing
countries, particularly in its applications to
agriculture. These hopes are well founded,
but it should not be forgotten that progress
involves potential dangers against which all
possible preventive measures should be
taken.
The first major achievement of agri¬
cultural biotechnology was the "Green
Revolution", whose ambitious objectives
have been largely achieved (see box page
7). Thanks to the Green Revolution India,
Bangladesh and several other Third World
countries have achieved self-sufficiency in
food. This was a true success, but it brought
in its train a number of unforeseen social
consequences. The farming of high-yield
cereals requires considerable investment in
fertilizers, pesticides and irrigation which
many small farmers were unable to make.
As a result many of them had their fields
taken over by the large landowners and
were forced to move to the cities and swell
the ranks of the sub-proletariat.
The recent collapse in the world price of
Egyptian bakers and brewers of 3,500
years ago are shown at work in this scene
from a Theban tomb. "Biotechnological"
processes such as microbial fermenta¬
tions have been used for thousands of
years to produce beverages and foods
such as beer and cheese.
Drawing taken from A History of Technology
© Oxford University Press
sugar is another example of a social and
economic backlash due to biotechnology.
Due largely to the production of iso-glucose
in the United States, this sugar price col¬
lapse has spelled ruin to a number of tropi¬
cal countries whose economies are based on
sugar-cane.
Fortunately, not all biotechnology
applications entail problems such as these.
However, there is a danger that some of
them will further increase rather than
diminish Third World dependence on the
richest and most scientifically advanced
countries (see article page 29).
Bearing this in mind, the developing
countries must concentrate their efforts on
programmes which are both of direct inter¬
est to them and which can be implemented
immediately within the limitations of their
financial and economic resources. Many
such opportunities are open to them in agri¬
culture in which two avenues in particular
beckon: that of primary production, where
there are possibilities in the field of plant
improvement and nitrogen fixation, and
that of bioconversion of agricultural prod¬
ucts and wastes into energy and food
resources.
New techniques
for better plants
Plant improvement by the traditional
methods of selection and cross-breeding is
as old as agriculture itself. Thanks to recent
advances in knowledge of the genetics and
physiology of plants these methods have
been refined and will long continue to pro¬
duce very important results. During the
past thirty years, for example, the yield of
maize has increased from 12 to 62 quintals
per hectare, while that of wheat has grown
on average by one quintal per hectare per
year. Similar progress has been made with
rice, the second most important of the great
cereals in worldwide use. Today, the Inter¬
national Rice Research Institute (IRRI),
set up in the Philippines in 1962, has a col¬
lection of 60,000 varieties of rice (see the
Unesco Courier, December 1984).
<
©
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
plant culture of colony of
meristem or cells
cells multiplication
in sterile
conditions
regeneration
of plantlets
mini- greenhouse
In addition to improving yield, the main
purpose of selection is to obtain new vari¬
eties which are resistant to parasites and to
bacterial and viral diseases. In recent years
a number of new techniques have made
their appearance, some of which are
already in use while others are still at the
laboratory stage. One of their main aims is
to reduce considerably the time needed for
a new variety to be put on the market and
brought into large-scale cultivation. Using
classic methods the lead time required to
achieve this is of the order of ten years,
whereas, given the capacity for adaptation
of the phytopathogenic agents (the bacte¬
ria, viruses, etc., that cause plant disease),
the useful life of a new variety is estimated
to be a mere five years.
Another advantage of certain recently
evolved techniques is that they make it pos¬
sible to cross-breed species that are too far
apart for normal sexual reproduction, thus
opening the way for the creation of entirely
new plant varieties.
The first major successes were achieved
by means of vegetative hybridization of
cereal seedlings. This method, which con¬
sists of cross-breeding between plants by
the elimination of self-fertilization, is com¬
paratively easy in the case of allogamous
cereals, such as maize, in which the male
organs are separated from the female
organs and can thus be manually eliminated
before fertilization has taken place. It is
more difficult with autogamous plants, such
as wheat, tomatoes, soya and lupin, in
which the male and the female organs are
contained in close proximity within the
flower. Today, this difficulty has been over¬
come by the discovery of chemical com¬
pounds which render the pollen sterile.
Many varieties of hybrid cereals and
other plants are now on the market. Gener¬
ally speaking, fields should be sown with
first generation hybrid seed. Hybrid seed
usually tends to degenerate and must be
renewed annually. At all events, the world
market for hybrid seed is growing rapidly
and, according to a recent estimate, will
attain a value of $20,000 million by the year
2000.
Other techniques now being developed
are more distant in prospect yet just as
promising. One of these is in vitro vegetative
propagation, or micro-propagation, by the
culture of the meristem or other plant
tissues. Meristem is the name given to a
grouping of embryonic cells situated at the
tip of the plant stem (see drawing below).
Cultivated in aseptic conditions on a solid,
nutritive culture medium, these cells
proliferate producing a callus which can be
divided and reproduced many times.
Treated with plant hormones (auxins,
cytokins and gibberelins), the calluses diffe¬
rentiate into plantlets having all the prop¬
erties of the original plant.
By this means, in a period of eight
The apical meristem is a tiny mass of cells
where growth takes place at the tip of a
plant stem. It plays a particularly important
role in plant propagation because it re¬
mains healthy even when the rest of the
plant is infected with a virus. In vitro cul¬
ture of the meristem of a diseased speci¬
men makes it possible to generate a new,
healthy plant, and allows the rapid produc¬
tion of virus-free planting materials. Be¬
low, sectional drawing of a plant bud
shows the apical meristem at centre, pro¬
tected by enfolding leaf shoots. Meristem
culture calls for particular care in the
choice of culture conditions and nutritive
media.
leaf shoots
Drawing shows in highly simplified form
one of the techniques used in modem
biotechnology for experimentation under
controlled conditions with plant cells, tis¬
sues and organs and for vegetative (i.e.
non-sexual) propagation of plants in ster¬
ile laboratory conditions. The sterilized
plant material which is cultured in the nut¬
rient medium may be a meristem (see
drawing at bottom of page), or some other
piece of plant tissue (see photo story
pages 8-9), or a protoplast, a plant cell
whose outer walls have been removed
(see page 10). From this organ, tissue, or
protoplast, a proliferating clump of dis¬
organized tissue called a callus can be
obtained. From this it is possible to re¬
generate whole intact plants, and to pro¬
duce many genetically identical copies,
known as clones, in a relatively short time.
A one-cubic-centimetre culture may con¬
tain one million cells each carrying the
potential of becoming an entire new plant.
By selecting cells with certain properties,
the process of breeding new varieties of
disease-resistant, stress-tolerant crops,
trees or flowers can be greatly
accelerated.
months, 2,000 million identical tubers,
spread over an area of 40 hectares, were
obtained from a single potato tuber derived
from a meristem, that is a rate of propaga¬
tion 100,000 times greater than that of sex¬
ual reproduction. A further advantage is
that plants obtained from meristems are
free of pathogenic contaminants, in particu¬
lar of viruses, which means that it is possible
to regenerate stock threatened with extinc¬
tion due to diseases that cannot be treated
in any other way.
Tropical agriculture has much to gain
from micro-propagation. For example, a
single oil palm regenerated from a fragment
of leaf tissue could, within a year, supply
500,000 identical, filariosis-resistant plants
producing up to 6 tonnes of oil per hectare
per year, that is six to thirty times more than
the principal oil-producing plants (sun¬
flower, soya, peanut). This same technique
is now being applied to the propagation of
new varieties of coconut palms.
Another technique which holds great
promise for the future is the in vitro produc¬
tion of haploid plants (plants whose cells
contain a single set of chromosomes). Tra¬
ditional methods of selection are made
more time-consuming and complicated
because of the diploid nature of vegetative
plants, that is to say, because the cells of
which they consist contain a double set of
chromosomes, one coming from each pa¬
rent. As a result, some so-called "recessive"
characteristics carried by a chromosome
may be masked by a dominant homologous
chromosome and its presence may only
be revealed, through the operation of
Mendelian segregation, after several
generations.
This, of course, slows down the work of
the person undertaking the selection. The
recent emergence of a technique somewhat
similar to micro-propagation has made it
possible to overcome this difficulty. This
technique enables a complete plant to be
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
obtained either from the male gametes, or
reproductive cells (androgenesis), or from
the female gametes (gynogenesis). Like the
gametes from which they are derived, these
plants are haploid. Since they have only one
set of chromosomes, their genetic charac¬
teristics, whether recessive or dominant,
are immediately evident to the person mak¬
ing the selection. Haploid plants are usually
infertile, but by treating them with col¬
chicine, which induces a doubling of the
chromosomes, a fertile plant is obtained
with two sets of identical chromosomes and
with phenotypically stable characteristics.
Another technique used in gynogenesis is to
fertilize the ovule with irradiated pollen.
In China, new varieties of rice obtained
by androgenesis are being cultivated on sev¬
eral millions of hectares of land. Laboratory
experiments in gynogenesis are also now
being undertaken on barley, rice, wheat,
maize, sugar-beet and other species.
High hopes are also being placed in soma¬
tic hybridization, a technique which consists
of fusing two cells whose cell walls have
previously been removed by enzymatic
treatment. Using this technique scientists
have succeeded in fusing plant cells not only
with other plant cells but also with animal
and even human cells. In most cases,
however, the chromosomes of one of the
fused cells are quickly eliminated and it has
only been possible to obtain complete,
stable hybrid cells from the fusion of cells
from very closely related species. Further¬
more, even when stable stock has been
obtained, it has proved difficult to regener¬
ate a complete plant from such fused cells.
The first success achieved was the regenera¬
tion of the pomato, a cross between a potato
and a tomato. However, the plant is sterile
and remains no more than a laboratory
curiosity.
More recently scientists have succeeded
in regenerating somatic hybrid cells of sev¬
eral plants of agricultural interest such as
rapeseed, chicory and potato. On the other
hand, attempts to do the same with sun¬
flower, cereals and legumes have so far
failed. Nevertheless, there is hope that
present difficulties will soon be overcome,
at least in obtaining hybrids of varieties of
the same species.
The great advantage of somatic hybrid¬
ization is that it makes it possible to transfer
not only the genetic characteristics borne by
the chromosomes of the nucleus, but also
those of the specialized parts of the cell
contained in the cytoplasm (the "liquid"
portion of a cell surrounding the nucleus)
such as mitochondria and chloroplasts.
These latter are the key to processes and
properties of great importance such as
photosynthesis, the assimilation of carbon
dioxide, male sterility and resistance to
herbicides, diseases and drought.
Somatic hybridization has paved the way
for the newly emerging discipline of plant
genetic engineering which is concerned with
the implantation of specific genes", whether
of vegetal or other origin, into the genetic
make-up of a plant (see article page 13).
Using these new techniques the nutritional
value of the haricot bean, for example, has
been improved by the transfer of a gene
from the Brazil nut.
In Europe, Japan and the United States
of America, a number of large multina¬
tional companies are showing keen interest
in these new techniques of plant improve¬
ment with a view to competing for the world
market. Nevertheless, this branch of bio¬
technology also offers great opportunities
for the developing countries. These new
techniques, which they have already
acquired or can rapidly master, will enable
them to adapt their agricultural production
to meet local conditions and requirements.
Nitrogen fixation
Through its World Network of Micro¬
biological Resources Centres (MIRCENs),
one of whose priority programmes is
devoted to the question of nitrogen fixa¬
tion, Unesco is contributing actively to
another field of biotechnology that is rich in
promise (see article page 27).
The nif genes, which are coded for the
fixation of nitrogen, have now been identi¬
fied and their structure is on the point of
being fully mapped out. Furthermore, these
genes have been transmitted to non-
nitrogen-fixing organisms such as Proteus
vulgaris, Agrobacterium tumefaciens and
Escherichia coli. In principle there is no
reason why they should not also be trans¬
ferred to higher plants and important
results in this direction can be expected
soon. However, the creation of nitrogen-
fixing cereals is a distant prospect still in the
realm of science fiction.
With regard to plants other than the
legumes, attention is now concentrated on
nitrogen fixation by bacteria and fungi
which invade their roots either on the root
surface or by entering their tissue where
they form nitrogen-fixing nodules. These
studies have not yet reached the molecular
biology or the genetic engineering stage,
but they hold out much promise for tropical
forestry, sand dune stabilization and the
fight against desertification.
Finally, mention should be made of stud¬
ies being made in the Philippines and Sene¬
gal on the use of the water fern Azolla pin-
nata as a biological fertilizer in rice fields
(seethe Unesco Courier, December 1984).
In symbiotic association with the blue-green
algaAnabaena this water fern has the ability
to fix atmospheric nitrogen. Ploughed into
the soil between harvests, this "green fertil¬
izer" can increase the crop by over 50 per
r
The Green Revolution
RESEARCH into the selection of new
high-yield cereal varieties began after
the Second World War. Wheat and
rice varieties were selected In Mexico and the
Philippines respectively, then during the
1960s the new strains were used in other
parts of the world, and it was later established
that they had contributed to a significant
increase in agricultural yields.
In the mid-1960s, following the introduction
of these high-yield varieties Into several coun¬
tries of Asia and Latin America, the expres¬
sion "Green Revolution" was coined to
describe the various efforts made to increase
agricultural production in the developing
countries by means of these new varieties,
especially wheat and rice. The cultivation of
these crops required the use of pesticides and
Irrigation in addition to fertilization and sound
agricultural practices. Cross-breeding be¬
tween these varieties and hardy local breeds
made it possible to obtain cultivars that were
even better adapted and which gave a better
yield. In addition to wheat and rice, this
research also concerned millet and sorghum,
triticale, maize and several leguminous plant
species.
In just over a decade, more than half the
surface of corn-growing land and one-third of
that of rlceland in developing countries had
been sown with high-yield cereal varieties.
When the latter are irrigated, and receive ade¬
quate supplies of fertilizer and weed-killer, the
yield is two or three times higher than that of
traditional varieties.
The new varieties of wheat were introduced
to India in 1966 and Indian wheat production
had doubled by 1970-1971, when it reached
23.4 million tonnes. As a result of local efforts
to improve varieties and a more widespread
use of selected seeds, output reached 33 mil¬
lion tonnes in 1978-1980. From being the
world's second largest cereal importer in
1966, India had become self-sufficient by the
end of the 1970s. In the Punjab, farm re¬
venues doubled in 1972, six years after the
introduction of new cereal varieties.
In some regions of Asia where water
resources permitted, the shortening of the
growing period of new rice varieties allowed
two or three crops to be harvested per year.
The prime beneficiaries of the "Green
Revolution" were the wealthier farmers of
some developing countries. The countries of
Africa south of the Sahara were scarcely
affected; only Kenya and Zimbabwe in¬
creased the area of land on which new vari¬
eties of maize were grown. The wheat and rice
varieties were not introduced at the same
pace as in Asia where the development of
irrigation, adequate fertilizer supplies, and the
marketing system of farm produce played an
important role in the success of the "Green
Revolution."
Source: Oue//es biotechnologies pour les pays en développe¬
ment? by A. Sasson, Biofutur/Unesco, Paris. 1986
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
cent and its effect, which lasts for two years,
is equivalent to the use of 60 kilograms of
nitrogen fertilizer per hectare.
Energy from waste
Biotechnology's contribution in the field of
new energy sources is today arousing great
interest for two reasons: the foreseeable
exhaustion of our supplies of fossil energy
(oil and coal), and the world energy crisis
which, since 1973, has weighed heavily on
the economies of all countries, but par¬
ticularly on those of the countries of the
Third World.
One achievement, which has already
been developed on a large scale in a number
of countries, is the production of biogas
from cellulose and animal and human
wastes. This is based on the anaerobic
digestion of cellulose and nitrogenous
organic matter by mixed populations of
microbes consisting of bacteria that break
down cellulose into organic acids and other
bacteria that convert these organic acids
into methane.
Experience acquired in India indicates
that the manure from ten cows would
provide a daily yield of 1.8 cubic metres of
biogas, which is the equivalent of 1.3 litres
of petrol, enough to cook the food for four
people or operate a hundred candlepower
lamp for fourteen hours. What is more, the
residue constitutes an excellent fertilizer of
a quality far superior to the original
manure.
A million of these cheap and simple bio-
gas digesters are in service in India and
more than seven million are in use in China.
Production of biogas on farms can be
expected to spread soon to other agri¬
cultural areas in which other forms of
energy are not available. From the ecologi¬
cal viewpoint, biogas has the great advan¬
tage that it can replace firewood, thus
contributing to the struggle against
deforestation and desertification.
Biogas production is also increasing in
the industrialized countries as well as in
large towns and heavily populated rural
areas in general. The main economic gain
here is that the treatment of waste water
and the handling of agro-industrial wastes
and the animal waste from intensive stock-
rearing can be turned to advantage by the
production of methane. Already several
urban water treatment plants in Europe
meet all their energy requirements by the
production of biogas.
Green gasoline
The production of liquid fuels, in particular
ethanol, is another major contribution of
biotechnology in the field of new energy
sources. A large number of agricultural raw
materials can be used for the production of
ethanol by fermentation, including the
sucrose in sugar-cane, sugar-beet and
molasses, the starch from cereals, manioc
and potatoes, and the inulin from Jerusalem
artichokes.
Brewer's yeast (Saccharomyces cere-
visiae) and certain anaerobic bacteria, such
as Zymomonas mobilis, convert the sugars
into ethanol with an average yield of 47 per
cent, by weight. Several suitable raw mat¬
erials are available in considerable quan¬
tities at a low price. However, from the
economic point of view there is one impor¬
tant drawback: the ethanol has an inhibiting
effect on the micro-organisms that produce
it and the maximum concentration in the
reactors cannot exceed 8 to 10 per cent. As a
result, the distillation of bio-ethanol and its
complete dehydration, which is essential to
its use as a fuel, are costly operations con¬
stituting about 60 per cent of the cost
price.
In Brazil, ethanol fuel is produced from
sugar-cane on a large scale. At present pro¬
duction is running at 8.4 million tonnes
which in energy terms is equivalent to 5.6
million tonnes of super-grade petrol. In
agricultural terms the yield is 4.7 tonnes per
hectare of sugar-cane per year.
At present, the cost price of bio-ethanol
exceeds that of petrol by $380 per tonne. In
Brazil, however, the economic motivation
for producing bio-ethanol is to improve the
balance of payments by reducing imports of
petrol and to provide an outlet for the sugar
industry which has been badly hit by the fall
in the price of sugar on the world market.
Bio-ethanol is arousing great interest
elsewhere for similar reasons. In the United
States, "Biohol", an automobile fuel con¬
taining 10 per cent ethanol produced from
maize, has been on the market for several
years. In Western Europe it is planned to
produce 3.4 million tonnes of bio-ethanol
annually. The aim of this project is to make
use of European surpluses of wheat and
sugar-beet. There is also an ecological
motivation. Added to automobile petrol in
a proportion of 5 per cent, ethanol can
replace the tetraethyl lead anti-knock addi¬
tive now used in petrol, but shortly to be
banned because of its toxic effects.
Bridging the protein gap
Generally speaking, proteins, or the lack of
them , constitute the major nutritional prob¬
lem facing the developing countries. Statis¬
tics published by the Food and Agriculture
Organization of the United Nations
(FAO), show that average total protein
consumption per head of population in the
developing countries is only half that of the
rich countries. The difference is even more
marked with regard to protein of animal
origin, average consumption of which in the
developing countries is 13 grams per
day a mere 22 per cent of that in rich coun¬
tries and this falls to 4 grams per day in
the poorest regions of Africa and Asia.
In the developing countries a great vari¬
ety of agricultural products and wastes lend
themselves to the production of single-cell
edible protein. These include, in particular,
ligno-cellulosic matter which is available in
large quantities at a low price. According
to the United Nations Environment
Programme (UNEP), the world crop of
cereals produces annually 1,700 million
The cloning
of the oil palm
The oil palm (Elaeis guineensisj is culti¬
vated as a source ofoil in the humid tropic¬
al zones of Africa, the Americas and
South-east Asia, where oil palm planta¬
tions cover several million hectares.
Selection cycles to produce higher-yield¬
ing varieties through sexual reproduction
were very long, and their results were only
perceptible after 15 or 20 years. In the
1970s, attempts were thus made to perfect
in vitro propagation of the oil palm using
Photo © IRHO-CIRAD/ORSTOM, Paris
tissue culture, and since 1981 oil palm
plantlets have been produced on a semi-
industrial scale at the La Mé research sta¬
tion in the Ivory Coast (1) using a cloning
technique developed by British and
French researchers in the 1970s. Photos
show some of the stages in the cloning
process. Fragments of very young leaves
are carefully removed from the tip of a tree
(2) and placed in a nutrient medium where
calluses develop (3). After going through a
second and then a third culture medium
the calluses evolve into "embryoids" (4)
comparable to the embryos obtained by
sexual reproduction. They multiply spon¬
taneously, and this multiplication is fos¬
tered in a fourth culture medium. A fifth
culture makes it possible for the embryos
to develop into young leaved plantlets (5).
The shoots are transferred to a sixth
medium in which roots are induced (6),
while in a seventh medium entire young
plants are obtained for planting in soil (7).
It takes about 3 months to obtain a 12 cm
shoot from an embryoid.
L
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Powerful protoplasts
Techniques for the cloning of plants are
now so refined that a single cell removed
from the body of a plant can be cultured in
the laboratory and then induced to re¬
generate a complete individual plant.
Drawings at left and below are a schematic
representation of the cloning process
used by Prof. James F. Shepard and his
colleagues at Kansas State University to
regenerate a complete potato plant from
protoplasts (living cells stripped of their
outer wall) prepared from leaf cells. Small
terminal leaves are first removed from a
young potato plant (1). The leaves are
placed in a solution containing a combina¬
tion of enzymes capable of dissolving the
cell wall to produce protoplasts (2). The
solution also causes the protoplasts to
withdraw from the cell wall and to become
spherical, thereby protecting the proto¬
plasm during the disintegration of the
walls (3). The protoplasts are next grown
in a culture medium (4) where they divide
and begin to synthesize new cell walls (5).
After 2 weeks of culture in these con¬
ditions, each protoplast gives rise to a
clump of undifferentiated cells or micro-
calluses (6). These microcalluses develop
into full-size calluses in another culture
medium (7) and their cells begin to dif¬
ferentiate, forming a primordial shoot (8).
The shoot develops into a small plant with
roots in a third culture medium and is then
planted in soil (9). Under appropriate con¬
ditions protoplasts from 2 different plants
can be fused to form a cell possessing
genes of plants which cannot be crossed
using classic methods. The fused proto¬
plasts of some species can be grown into
plants in a process known as somatic
hybridization.
tonnes of straw, to which can be added
some 127 million tonnes of bagasse from
sugar-cane and pulp from sugar-beet. At
present, the main obstacle to their use for
the production of proteins is the lack of
sufficiently active microbial strains for this
specific purpose. Recently achieved labora¬
tory results suggest that this problem will
soon be overcome.
Cuba is, at present, the only developing
country producing single-cell edible protein
from agricultural raw material. Eighty
thousand tonnes of forage yeasts for use as
animal feed are produced annually from
sugar-cane molasses. The Cuban example
will probably soon be followed in other
countries, such as India, where molasses is
also available at a low price.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
33^
yj.
For a long time now Western Europe has
been producing single-cell edible protein
from various agro-industrial wastes such as
lacto-serum (80,000 tonnes per year) and
the sulphite liquors used in paper-making
(25,000 tonnes per year). As with biogas,
the main economic incentive for this pro¬
duction is the elimination of the cost of
handling potentially polluting wastes. It is
to be expected that the same will happen
soon in the developing countries where
increasing industrialization is making pro¬
tection of the environment an ever more
urgent necessity.
One of microbiology's most promising
contributions to the problem of edible pro¬
teins is their production on an industrial
scale from oil, methanol and natural gas.
Born in Europe some thirty years ago, this
branch of biotechnology has developed to
the point where there are factories with a
production capacity of 100,000 tonnes per
year.
The oil treatment processes make use of
yeast micro-organisms (Candida lipolytica
and Candida tropicalis) which are derived
from diesel oil or from paraffin, previously
extracted from crude oil, and having a yield
of 100 per cent by weight. In the case of
methanol, chemically derived from natural
gas, the biomass produced is that of bacteria
such as Methylophilus methylotropha whose
yield on this substrate is of the order of 50
per cent, by weight. The methanol treat¬
ment processes make use of specific meth¬
ane-eating bacteria (Pseudomonas meth-
8
©
Protein enrichment by fermentation is a
branch of biotechnology that could help
some developing countries increase their
protein resources. Microbial fermentation
of such crops as manioc, which contain
much starch and relatively little protein,
yields a product with a substantially high¬
er protein content. The banana is a fruit to
which this process could be applied, and
several banana-producing countries are
investigating the possibility of using in
this way the high proportion of fruit re¬
jected for export and usually wasted.
Above, harvesting bananas in Martinique.
After J.F. Shepard in Scientific American, New York, 1982
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
ylotropha or Methyiococcus capsulatus) in
conjunction with other species whose task is
to prevent the inhibition of the bacteria by
intermediate accumulation of methanol.
Very large-scale experiments with the
products thus obtained from oil and meth¬
anol have demonstrated conclusively their
high nutritional value and complete
innocuousness. Up till now, these edible
proteins have been marketed exclusively as
animal feed, but preliminary studies have
shown that there is nothing to prevent their
being used directly as food for humans.
Following the first oil crisis of 1973, pro¬
duction of single-cell edible protein from oil
and from methanol slowed down in West¬
ern Europe due to the increased cost of the
raw material. In Eastern Europe and in the
USSR, however, it has developed consider¬
ably and now amounts to some 3 million
tonnes per year.
This branch of biotechnology is of
obvious interest to those developing coun¬
tries that are producers of oil and natural
gas, since these raw materials are available
to them in large quantities at prices well
below the world market price. The Organi¬
zation of Arab Petroleum Exporting Coun¬
tries, for example, proposes as a first step to
produce 100,000 tonnes of single-cell edible
protein a year, either from oil or from meth¬
anol, and it estimates the potential market
in the Middle East and in the Maghreb at
more than a million tonnes. It should be
pointed out that this amount of protein
could be obtained from 0.1 per cent of their
total oil production.
Protein enrichment of foodstuffs by fer¬
mentation is another promising prospect.
Application of modern biotechnological
methods to this practice, which is tradi¬
tional in Africa and the Far East, seems set
fair to provide the developing countries
with a substantial increase in their protein
resources for human and animal consump¬
tion.
The end product of this fermentation pro¬
cess is a directly consumable mixture of pro
tein-rich microbial biomass and residual
agricultural raw material whose nutritional
value is thus enriched. This relatively sim¬
ple technology has the advantage that it can
be used both on a large industrial scale and
in small, inexpensive production units
located in rural communities. This means
that high-quality edible protein can be pro¬
duced from a wide range of agricultural raw
materials that are too costly or available
locally only in quantities too small for use
with standard single-cell edible protein pro¬
duction methods.
In all the tropical regions, manioc (also
known as cassava) is the chief agricultural
raw material potentially available for pro¬
tein enrichment. Cultivated throughout
Africa, in Asia and Latin America, the
world production of manioc is of the order
of 100 million tonnes. Very rich in starch,
but containing practically no protein, man¬
ioc is used above all as a supplementary
energy food. Furthermore, although under
good conditions it can yield 50 tonnes per
hectare and over, it is normally only culti¬
vated on small patches of land using rudi¬
mentary methods with low productivity.
At present, the only country in which
manioc cultivation has been developed
rationally is Thailand, which exports 7.5
million tonnes of manioc root to the Euro¬
pean Community each year.
Starting with dried manioc with an initial
content of 90 per cent starch and less than 1
per cent protein, fermentation with an
amylolytic mould (Aspergillus hennebergii)
yields a product containing 20 per cent well-
balanced proteins and 20 to 25 per cent
residual sugars. In this way manioc can
provide nearly 2 tonnes of protein per hec¬
tare, that is, three times more than can be
obtained from the cultivation of soya or
other leguminous plants.
The banana too is a raw material with a
bright future. In the collection centres of
exporting countries, 20 to 30 per cent of the
fruit gathered is rejected. This rejected
fruit, whose protein content at 1.1 per cent
is too low for it to be used as animal feed, is
a complete write-off. For a number of Cen¬
tral American countries which export sev¬
eral million tonnes of bananas annually, the
prospect of recuperating wastage on this
scale by use of the fermentation process is
clearly of the greatest interest and this
possibility is being actively investigated in
Mexico, Guatemala and the West Indies.
Finally, the third major contribution that
biotechnology has to offer to the solution of
the world problem of edible protein is the
industrial production of amino acids as a
complement to plant proteins. Many such
proteins, in fact, are only of limited nutri¬
tional value because of their lack of certain
essential amino acids which man and other
mono-gastric animals (including pigs,
young ruminants and poultry) are unable to
synthesize and therefore must find in their
food. This is the case in particular of lysine,
which is the amino acid in which cereals are
most notably deficient and lack of which is
the main cause of malnutrition in the Third
World. Almost all the amino acids used as a
complement to plant proteins are obtained
by fermentation using hyper-productive
bacterial strains selected genetically.
Apart from methionine, which is
basically intended for use in animal feed,
lysine is the only amino acid produced in
large quantities (40,000 tonnes per year). It
has been estimated that the world deficit in
lysine, most marked in Africa and the Far
East, is 136,000 tonnes for human food and
three times that figure for animal
foodstuffs. As things stand at present, the
cost price of lysine is still too high to ensure
satisfaction of Third World needs and to
compete with soya in animal feed. The sit¬
uation is the same for other amino acids, in
particular threonine and tryptophan,
which, after lysine, are the chief elements
lacking in plant proteins. However, it is
reasonable to assume that, thanks to
genetic engineering, substantial progress
will soon be made.
JACQUES C. SENEZ, French biologist and uni¬
versity teacher, is a former Secretary-General of
the Unesco-sponsored International 'Cell Re¬
search Organization (ICRO) and a consultant
member of the Protein Advisory Group of the
United Nations. A past Secretary-General of the
International Union of Microbiological Societies
(IUMS), he is the author of a number of studies
on microbiology and bacterial biochemistry. In
the late 1960s he initiated the production of
Single Cell Protein (SCP) from petroleum.
2 Many developing countries are engaged in
I programmes to harness the techniques of
e biotechnology for national development.
§ Left, fermenters of a Cuban factory pro-
$ ducing single-cell edible protein from
© molasses. The installation produces some
% 40 tonnes of protein a day for use as anim-
£ a/ feed.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
by Bernard Dixon
The gene
revolution
Photo above shows the distinctive knot¬
like growths or nodules which form on the
roots ol legumes (plants of the pea family)
when they are infected by certain bacteria.
These bacteria, known as rhizobia, take
nitrogen from the air and change it into
forms the plants can use. One important
aim of research in biotechnology is to ex¬
tend this process of nitrogen fixation to
other crops by incorporating nitrogen-fix¬
ing genes into their genetic heritage. The
goal is proving difficult to attain.
GIVEN the mixture of benefits and
problems spawned by the first
Green Revolution two decades
ago (see box page 7) , it is not surprising that
both optimism and apprehension surround
the application of genetic engineering now
to agriculture tomorrow. Mixed reactions
are appropriate, because those develop¬
ments focused upon so-called recombi¬
nant DNA are destined to have even
more far-reaching effects than the tech¬
niques deployed in the first revolution.
Today's new wizardry could undoubtedly
transform agriculture throughout the
world. At the same time, its precision in
modifying living cells offers a stern chal¬
lenge to our prudence and wisdom.
At the centre of the stage is deoxy¬
ribonucleic acid (DNA), the material which
carries in coded form the hereditary instruc¬
tions responsible for the behaviour of cells
and the plants, animals or microbes of
which they are part. The astronomically
long DNA molecule can be subdivided into
regions genes which determine particu¬
lar characteristics. Recombinant DNA is
the name given to the product when a piece
of DNA from one organism is combined
artificially with that from another.
Genetic manipulation of this sort is the
basis for the boom that has occurred during
the past decade in biotechnology. Such
activities were, of course, possible pre¬
viously. Some, like the art of fermenting
sugar to make alcoholic drinks, are almost
as ancient as Man himself. Others, includ¬
ing the first mass production of antibiotics,
were developed earlier this century. But all
of these processes were based on organisms
as they occur in nature albeit with other,
equally natural, methods being used to
select high-yielding strains.
The arrival of recombinant DNA, how¬
ever, has altered the rules profoundly. It
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
has already greatly enhanced our specificity
and power in tailoring living organisms for
beneficial purposes. In future, it will extend
our range of options much further.
The breakthroughs which have led to this
historic watershed in the fabrication of
novel plants and microbes happened during
the early 1970s. The key discoveries were
made by molecular biologists who learned
how to splice into bacteria genes which they
had taken from other bacteria, and even
from totally unrelated animal or plant cells.
They first found out how to locate the par¬
ticular gene they wanted among the count¬
less numbers on the DNA of one organism.
Then they used natural catalysts called
enzymes to cut out that gene and "stitch" it
into a vector. This is usually a virus or a
plasmid (a piece of DNA that replicates
independently from the nucleus, the main
repository of DNA). The vector became a
vehicle for ferrying the selected DNA frag¬
ment into the recipient. Once inside its new
host, the foreign gene divided as the cell
divided leading to a clone of cells, each
containing exact copies of that gene.
Because the enzymes used for genetic
engineering are highly specific, genes can
be excised from one organism and placed in
another with extraordinary precision. Such
manipulations contrast sharply with the
much less predictable gene transfers that
occur in nature. They also make it possible
to splice genes that would be unlikely to
come together naturally. By mobilizing
pieces of DNA in this way, genetic engi¬
neers are beginning to create pedigree
microbes for a wide range of new purposes
in agriculture, medicine and industry.
Although genetic manipulation is taking
longer to perfect in plants, several tech¬
niques are now emerging. The most useful
so far is based on Agrobacterium tumefa-
ciens, a bacterium that causes crown galls
on many flowering plants. It contains a
tumour-inducing (Ti) plasmid which is
responsible for triggering the disorderly
growth that appears as ugly galls. Genetic
engineers have learned how to delete the Ti
plasmid's tumour-inducing genes and use it
as a vector with which to carry new genes
into plants.
A serious drawback so far is that while A.
tumefaciens infects potatoes, tomatoes, and
many forest trees, it does not normally
attack the monocotyledons such as cereals,
which are prime targets for genetic im¬
provement. Progress is being made,
however, and recent research indicates that
rice in particular can be manipulated using
the Ti plasmid. Alternative vectors and
other methods of transferring genes are also
being developed. One exciting possibility is
to use an electric current to promote the
incorporation of foreign DNA. This works
with maize cells, though scientists still have
to persuade the cells to develop into whole
plants.
One gene that has been transferred into
tobacco by A. tumefaciens comes from bac
teria and gives the plants the capacity to
produce a toxin that is lethal to insects. The
inbuilt insecticide makes the plants resistant
to insect attack and does not, of course,
have to be applied repeatedly. Some plants
can mobilize defences against virus infec¬
tion through a process analogous to immu¬
nization in animals, and this suggests
another route for genetic alteration. Incor¬
poration of one virus gene into tobacco has
helped to protect this plant against subse¬
quent inoculation with the entire virus.
Another development concerns
weeds a major limitation on crop hus¬
bandry in most countries. Although weeds
can be combatted using selective her¬
bicides, these often impair the growth of the
crop too. It is now possible, however, to
introduce resistance genes into tobacco and
petunia. One such manipulation results in
the synthesis of enzymes in the plant that
are no longer sensitive to the inhibitory
action of the herbicide glyphosate. Com¬
mercial companies now plan to market a
package containing both herbicide and
resistance seed.
Some 70 per cent of the world's intake of
dietary protein consists of cereal grains and
seeds of legumes. On their own, neither
cereals nor legumes can provide a balanced
diet for human consumption, because the
"storage proteins" they each contain are
deficient in one or more amino acids. Now,
added to analyses of the proteins in both
cereals and legumes, we have precise infor-
How to recombine DNA Drawing shows how a micro-organism (in this case a bacterium) is manipulated
to make it synthesize a desired substance. (1) A bacterium contains a plasmid,
which is a circularpiece ofDNA. This plasmid is isolated (2) and, with the help of
a restriction enzyme, opened in a precise spot (3). Meanwhile, with the help of
other restriction enzymes, the gene for synthesis of the desired substance is
isolated from the DNA ofanother organism (4). Still using enzymes, this gene is
grafted onto the previously openedplasmid (5). The plasmid is re-introduced
into a bacterium (6). The manipulated bacteria are put into a culture, where they
synthesize the desired substance. (7)
o
ó
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
mation about the DNA sequences coding
for them. This knowledge may well lead to
methods of altering those sequences or
introducing new genes that code for a more
balanced spectrum of amino acids.
The world's energy and food supplies rest
upon the ability of green plants to convert
atmospheric carbon dioxide into carbo¬
hydrates, fats and proteins, using light from
the sun. Unfortunately, the mechanism by
which they consume carbon dioxide is inef¬
ficient in those plants, such as wheat, barley
and potatoes, that are cultivated in tem¬
perate climes. Oxygen in the atmosphere
interferes with the first enzyme involved in
the assimilation of carbon dioxide. Consid¬
erable efforts are now being made to alter
the DNA sequence of the gene coding for
this enzyme, to prevent the deleterious
action of oxygen. Other researchers are try¬
ing to introduce into temperate zone
plants certain genes taken from maize,
which has a more efficient mechanism of
carbon dioxide uptake. In nature this
mechanism appears to operate only at
higher temperatures, but there are hopes of
"switching it on" in cooler areas.
Another atmospheric gas is the subject of
parallel efforts to make plants more effi¬
cient. Nitrogen constitutes 80 per cent of
the air, yet plants cannot use the gas
directly. Hence the heavy dependence of
modern intensive agriculture on fertil¬
izers nitrate, ammonia or urea syn¬
thesized by the chemical industry. Natural
nitrogen fixation depends in part on
rhizobia, bacteria that live symbiotically
with legumes such as peas, beans and
clover. The bacteria grow on sugars
provided by the plant, and are maintained
in characteristic nodules on the plant. There
they convert nitrogen directly into
ammonia, leading in turn to the synthesis of
plant proteins.
Molecular biologists have now isolated
and characterized several of the genes
required for nitrogen fixation. They have
found, however, that many more bacterial
and plant genes are involved than they first
imagined. This makes the manipulation of
those genes correspondingly more difficult.
So it will be some years before we can enjoy
the cost and energy savings that should
accrue by providing crops such as wheat and
maize with the ability to fix their own
nitrogen.
Drought and high temperatures are
unwelcome to all plants, despite being bet¬
ter tolerated by varieties that have evolved
in such environments. Desiccated soils also
often contain high levels of salts and metal¬
lic elements, which are toxic to plant
growth. Genetic engineers would dearly
like to fabricate plants resistant to such
stresses, but success is unlikely in the near
future. Before being able to identify the
relevant DNA sequences for transfer
between plants, they require a far better
understanding of the many ways in which
plants respond to their environment. An
additional problem may be the involvement
of several different genes, as with nitrogen
fixation. Drought resistance which depends
on a reduced area of leaf surface, for exam¬
ple, may be caused by the interaction of
multiple genes.
Microbes that contribute to healthy plant
growth are also on the drawing board for
genetic engineering. One possibility being
examined is the production and deliberate
release of rhizobia that fix nitrogen more
efficiently than natural strains. Other bacte¬
ria capable of forming nitrogen-fixing part¬
nerships with wheat and maize are also
being considered. A third type of prospect
follows the discovery by researchers at the
University of California, Berkeley, that
frost damage to strawberries is triggered by
bacteria which act as nucleii for the forma¬
tion of ice crystals on leaves. The cause is a
particular bacterial protein, the gene for
which the California biologists have learned
to delete. They believe they can prevent the
extremely costly frost damage by spraying
crops with this "ice minus" strain , which will
outgrow the natural flora.
A key area in biotechnology research is
concerned with the development of tech¬
niques for isolating genes of one plant and
introducing them into another as a means
of endowing the host plant with new char¬
acteristics such as higher protein content
or resistance to pests. One promising
technique for transferring genes uses
Plasmids (small pieces ofgenetic material)
from a bacterium which causes tumour
growths when it infects certain plants,
above. It is possible to delete the plasmid's
tumour-inducing genes and use the plas¬
mid to ferry new "useful" genes into
plants. Genes of a bean protein have been
transferred to the sunflower using this
method.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
©
I
The use of genetic engineering in food
production offers many potential advan¬
tages. At the same time, questions have
been raised about the possible risks in¬
volved in releasing genetically modified
living organisms into the environment.
One case which led to widespread debate
and concern in the United States arose
from the development and use of geneti¬
cally modified microbes known as ice-
minus bacteria to protect strawberries
from frost damage. In photo, the leafat left
has been treated with ice-minus bacteria.
The leaf at right froze when dipped into
supercooled water.
Genetic engineering holds considerable
promise too in the improvement of "biolog¬
ical insecticides", microbes that attack pests
and have enormous ecological advantages
over their chemical counterparts. Bacillus
thuringiensis, for example, has been used
for many years to combat nuisance species,
but it and similar bacteria and viruses may
well be made more powerful by recombi¬
nant DNA. One possibility is illustrated by
the pine moth, which damages lodgepole
pine trees in northern Britain. In other parts
of the country, the moth is controlled natu¬
rally by a baculovirus that infects the cater¬
pillars. There are now plans to make the
virus more efficient at killing caterpillars
and to release it in the pine plantations. The
first experiments are being carried out with
a virus that has been altered only by having
a "marker" introduced into a non-coding
region of its DNA. This will allow
researchers to follow the virus's distribution
and survival after spraying. If all goes well,
the virus may be given a genè allowing it to
synthesize an insect-killing toxin. The
potential for this technique in other coun¬
tries, against other destructive insects, is
clear.
The safety of laboratory and industrial
activities using engineered organisms is
based on the idea of containment. Facilities
are graded according to the degree of risk.
New questions arise, however, when mi¬
crobes and plants are to be introduced into
the environment. There is concern, for
example, that weeds may be created acci¬
dentally and be inordinately difficult to
eradicate. If such a plant were drought-
resistant, herbicide-resistant, and frost-tol¬
erant, it might spread quickly over large
areas of agricultural land and be very diffi¬
cult to eradicate. As illustrated by the
Kudzu plant in Asia and the water hyacinth
in America, even natural weeds can cause
considerable havoc.
The prospect of genetically engineered
crops themselves becoming weeds is
remote, however, because crop varieties
cannot compete well with other plants when
left unattended. The inherent difficulties of
mobilizing plant genes also make it unlikely
that unwelcome varieties will be produced
accidentally. And there is always the pos¬
sibility of destroying by fire or other means
an engineered plant, released initially in a
defined area, that did create problems.
Nonetheless, field trials with novel plants,
particularly crops able to cross-fertilize with
weeds, need to be very carefully monitored.
Greater caution still is required with engi¬
neered microbes, which would be broadcast
in astronomical numbers and be impossible
to trace in their entirety should anything go
awry. But it is reassuring that no health,
environmental or other dangers have been
caused by recombinant organisms since
they were first fabricated over a decade ago.
Moreover, biologists now agree that there is
no significant difference between a microbe
that has received a new piece of DNA
through artificial manipulation and one that
has acquired the same DNA fragment
through natural mechanisms of gene trans¬
fer. Most experts argue that recombinant
DNA manoeuvres are intrinsically safer,
because they can be vastly more precise and
selective. Certain laboratory manipulations
are ruled out anyway by a priori predictions
that they would generate hazardous recom¬
binants.
Many researchers believe that tests with
recombinants should always be restricted to
closed environments such as greenhouses.
But these "microcosms" can never simulate
the richness of the natural biosphere. So
they can never provide conclusive evidence
about an organism's potential safety or per¬
formance in nature. The scientific con¬
sensus is now for a gradual approach, a
priori evidence about a released organism's
likely behaviour being used as the basis for
successively larger trials during which expe¬
rience and confidence are gathered about
how it actually does behave.
There is one other argument against the
much-publicized view in the USA that
organisms carrying recombinant DNA
should never be released for purposes such
as pest control. One third of the world's
crops are now lost through infection and
pestilence. It would be foolhardy not to
make use of an ecologically acceptable tech¬
nique capable of achieving even a modest
reduction in that toll.
BERNARD DIXON, British science writer and
consultant, is European editor of The Scientist
magazine and was formerly (1969-1979) editor
of the British scientific ¡ournalTUe New Scientist.
Notable among his published works are Magnifi¬
cent Microbes (1976), Invisible Allies (1976) and
(with G. Holister) Ideas of Science, Man and
Medicine (1986).
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Tomatomation
Japan's high-tech food factories
by Koichibara Hiroshi
THE harnessing of high technology to
vegetable farming may be about to
trigger a new agricultural revolu¬
tion in Japan, where some large manufac¬
turers are already offering fully automatic
"factories" in which vegetables are grown in
a computer-controlled artificial environ¬
ment. In their use of automation and high
technology these facilities resemble auto¬
mobile or electronics plants, but instead of
automobiles or video tape recorders their
mass production lines produce fresh vegeta¬
bles, regardless of season or climate.
Strictly speaking, today's factory farming
technology is based not on biotechnology
but on applying industrial production man¬
agement techniques to conventional agri¬
cultural engineering. The aim is to use
artificially controlled environments to grow
plants rapidly and efficiently rather than
improve the adaptation of plants to natural
conditions. Such ideas have already been
applied to poultry farming, egg production
systems, and even the production of foie
gras. Factory farms may thus make a big
impact on conventional agriculture since
they provide planned cultivation regardless
of weather, season, climate or soil.
The essential element in this new
Light, temperature and humidity are com¬
puter controlled in this vegetable factory
in a Tokyo suburb. High electricity con¬
sumption is a drawback.
development is hydroponics, the cultivation
of plants in nutritive solutions. Factory
farms are air-conditioned, and high-pres¬
sure sodium lamps provide twenty-four-
hour-a-day illumination. The density of car¬
bon dioxide, oxygen, temperature and
humidity are controlled by a computer to
maintain an optimum growing environ¬
ment.
The hardware used in this process is not
new. It is readily available from manufac¬
turers of electrical consumer goods, and this
may be the reason why Japanese electrical
conglomerates are active in this field. Com¬
panies in Denmark, the United States and
Austria are also experimenting with vegeta¬
ble factories but for the moment the Jap¬
anese seem to be leading the field.
In 1985, a "supertomato" plant was dis¬
played in the Japanese government-
sponsored pavilion at an international
exhibition held in Japan, Tsukuba Expo.
'85 (see the Unesco Courier, March 1985).
This was a major success for a hydroponic
culture system developed after many years
of research by a Japanese agronomist,
Nozawa Shigeo. The growth of the plant
was accelerated in a nutritive solution which
replaced soil and in an artificially controlled
environment. As a result the plant pro¬
duced more than 13,000 tomatoes during
the six months of the Expo.
Daiei, Japan's biggest supermarket
chain , has installed a factory farm next to its
store in the Tokyo suburb of Fanabashi.
This experimental facility, constructed in
co-operation with Hitachi Ltd. to grow let¬
tuce for sale in the adjoining supermarket,
may be the world's first commercial factory
farm using full automatic hydroponic cul¬
ture technology. The system produces some
130 heads of lettuce and other green vegeta¬
bles per day (some 47,000 per year) on a
floor space of no more than 66 square
metres. Grown from seed, the lettuce is big
enough for harvesting in only five weeks,
3.5 times faster than plants cultivated using
conventional methods.
In this futuristic factory, the sun is
replaced by artificial twenty-four-hour
lighting, soil with nutritive solution and
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Trays of growing lettuce were rotated up
and down on chain conveyors in this
vegetable factory installation shown in the
Japanese Government pavilion at Expo
'85, an international exhibition held at Tsu-
kuba (Japan) in 1985. The lettuce were
grown in liquid nutrients, using the tech¬
nique known as hydroponics. The 24-
hour-a-day lighting, carbon-dioxide-rich
atmosphere and constant temperature
helped the lettuce to reach maturity in 20
days, 4 to 5 times faster than normal. The
moving conveyor belts ensured that every
plant was exposed to the same amount of
heat and light.
farmers with a micro-computer. The crop is
tasty and free from pesticides and her¬
bicides, and is in great demand, regardless
of the price tag, which is double that of
conventionally grown lettuce.
In Mitsubishi Electric's Amagasaki labo¬
ratory, a prototype food factory assembly
line succeeded in growing lettuce seedlings
from 2 grams to 130 grams in 15 days 6
times faster than the natural growth rate.
With specially developed fluorescent
lamps, the photosynthetic ratio is said to be
better than that of the sun. Sprouts cloned
from the tissues of mature plants start at one
end of a conveyor and move along at the
rate of 20 centimetres a day.
In March 1986 Japanese National Rail¬
ways (JNR) built two experimental vegeta¬
ble factories, each with a size of 50 square
metres and a construction cost of $60,000.
Since May, each factory has been producing
120 heads of lettuce a day. Experiments are
being carried out on the cultivation of other
vegetables such as tomatoes, cabbage,
asparagus, melon and green peppers. In the
case of JNR, electric power supplied by its
own power plants can be efficiently used at
night when demand is low, and open spaces
beneath the overhead railway or aban¬
doned tunnels can be utilized as sites.
Artificial lighting and computers are not
essential elements in factory farming.
Hydroponic food factories can be installed
in developing countries where food facto¬
ries may be most needed. Matsushita Elec¬
tric has, for example, installed a vegetable
factory with minimal automation in the
Maldives. The system, which has a plastic
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Photos © AFP, Paris
roof that keeps out harmful sunlight rays,
produces 50 tonnes of vegetables a year,
using about one-fifth of the water needed by
field-grown plants.
Vegetable factories can offer various
advantages: planned production, quality
control, low labour costs, clean products.
They use space efficiently and provide sta¬
ble production regardless of climatic and
seasonal variations. However, high elec¬
tricity costs are a severe drawback. Artifi¬
cial lighting is said to account for 90 per cent
of the Mitsubishi system's operating costs.
On the other hand, there can be no doubt
that research will continue in the search for
breakthroughs in the development of
energy-efficient lighting systems, the
achievement of a higher photosynthetic
ratio than in the natural environment, and
in the applications of biotechnologies to fac¬
tory farming.
It is to be hoped that food factory tech¬
nology will not be monopolized by a group
of industrialized countries and that it will be
applied in those countries which need it
most.
One of the star attractions at Expo '85 was
a gigantic tomato plant, above, which pro¬
duced over 13,000 tomatoes during the 6
months of the exhibition. Fed by a special
nutritive solution, the plant grew in a con¬
trolled environment, with optimum light¬
ing and temperature.
Below, inspecting tomato plants at a
Japanese-made hydroponic food factory
in the Maldives. The technology was
adapted to conditions in this tropical de¬
veloping country in the Indian Ocean.
KOICHIBARA HIROSHI, Japanese economist,
is a member of the Unesco secretariat.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Hybrids for the year 2000
by Raissa G. Butenko and Zlata B. Shamina
THE cultivation of plant tissues, cells
and protoplasts has not only helped
us to learn much that is new and
surprising about the metabolism, genetics
and capacity of the plant cell to fulfil dif¬
ferent development programmes. It has
also served as a basis for creating new tech¬
nologies in agriculture and industry that are
essentially different from the traditional
ones. Some of these technologies are now
being commercially applied, others will be
used in the very near future and others in
the more distant future.
Many important medicinal plants grow¬
ing in natural conditions are becoming
scarce, and supplies of them are limited.
Consequently, their collection as medicinal
raw material may lead to the complete dis¬
appearance of certain varieties. Moreover,
the plantation cultivation of suitable wild
Ceff cultures can be a source for the manu¬
facture of medical products derived from
plants. Ginseng (Panax schinseng), be¬
low, is one plant which Soviet and
Japanese scientists have cultured in this
manner. Its generic name, Panax, is de¬
rived from the same Greek word as "pa¬
nacea". In the East ginseng has from time
immemorial been considered a cure for
many ills.
plants takes up valuable space which could
otherwise be sown with agricultural crops.
A solution to this problem has been
found in the industrial cultivation of medici¬
nal plant cell cultures on similar lines to
cultures of micro-organism products. Using
the classical methods of microbial genetics,
productive stems of ginseng, a relict plant
growing in a limited area of the Far East,
were obtained. These stems, possessing
qualities that reduce fatigue and enhance
physical resistance, are being cultivated in
biochemical factories. They give a high
yield of biomass containing physiologically
active substances. The elaboration of indus¬
trial techniques for the intensive cultivation
of medicinal plant cells has proved profit¬
able, and it is now the turn of other cell
cultures such as Dioscorea and
Rauwolfia.
Apart from the traditional methods of
breeding micro-organisms, there are new
approaches to obtaining productive stems,
in particular the hybridization of partners
which are actively self-propagating and pos¬
sess a high degree of biosynthesis. So far, as
a result of induced mutagenesis and the
optimization of culture conditions, stems
with a generally high level of productivity
have been obtained. In some cases the con¬
tent of biologically active substances was
not lower than in the original plant.
Many vegetatively propagated agri¬
cultural plants accumulate pathogens,
especially viruses, which it is impossible to
get rid of by the usual propagation methods.
But the cultivation of meristematic tips not
only frees the future plant from infection
but enables an unlimited quantity of off¬
spring to be obtained from a single mer¬
istem. This technique, known as clonal
micropropagation , is being widely practised
all over the world for potatoes, ornamental
plants and berry bushes.
Although it is much more difficult for
woody species to regenerate plants from
micro-shoots, conditions have been created
in the Soviet Union for the mass production
of poplar and aspen clones as well as those
of tea plants and citrus trees. This is of great
value since it makes it possible to take start¬
ing material from élite specimens and
obtain within a few years entire groves of
high quality trees that are completely iden¬
tical to the original.
Clonal micropropagation is also
extremely important for the preservation of
genetic resources both scarce, disappear¬
ing species and unique genotypes obtained
through hybridization and mutagenesis.
Clonal micropropagation is now becoming
one of the stages of the breeding process for
sugar-beet, cereal hybrids and pasture
grasses.
The use of haploids in breeding is very
important, especially for the selection of
constant hybrids. Using traditional meth¬
ods, stable forms combining useful charac¬
teristics can be obtained within ten or
eleven years. The breeding of first-genera¬
tion hybrid anthers shortens this process by
a third or a quarter. With this method new
varieties of barley, triticale, tobacco, prom¬
ising original varieties of potato and many
other agricultural plants have been
obtained in the USSR. The new technique
considerably simplifies and shortens the
breeding process.
The art of obtaining so-called somaclonal
variations a broad' variety of plant
régénérants is an achievement of cell biol¬
ogy. From amongst the somaclones it is pos¬
sible to breed forms which retain all the
positive characteristics of the variety but
with the sought-for addition of certain nec¬
essary, especially viable traits. It is difficult
to obtain such a combination of agri¬
culturally valuable traits through the tradi¬
tional breeding methods. But plants com¬
bining high productivity with resistance to
fungi and viruses have been bred from
potato somaclones at potato institutes in the
USSR. The combination of precocity with
longer grains, which it was impossible to
achieve by the usual method of breeding
round-grained rice plants, has proved to be
possible in the rice somaclone. Somaclone
variations clearly provide excellent material
for breeding plants that are both productive
and resistant to stress.
The cases cited above show what has
been achieved by modern biotechnology.
They are examples of the practical applica¬
tions which have been adopted in agricul¬
ture in the Soviet Union and which have
also won a place in industry. Amongst those
orientations which hold out hopes of early
success, that is, those which have passed
laboratory tests but have not yet been
widely introduced, cell breeding is the most
promising. The obtaining of guaranteed
harvests in zones where agriculture is
exposed to risks is perhaps the most serious
problem facing agriculture today. This
implies the creation of strains of the princi¬
pal food plants that are resistant to diseases,
pests, herbicides and unfavourable environ¬
mental factors. In the Soviet Union the
most important qualities are immunity to
salty soils, drought and frost. Breeding at
the cell level enables conditions to be cre¬
ated in which all cells except the resistant
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The organisms in the culture dish, top, are
anthers (tiny sacs of pollen). When placed
in a nutrient solution they form a callus,
above left, and can then be regenerated
into whole haploid plants, above right.
(See page 6).
ones perish and the surviving cells represent
potential plants. Thus, by cultivating cells in
media with a high concentration of salt, it is
possible to obtain salt-resistant plants. This
makes it possible, together with somaclonal
variants, to conduct controlled breeding of
modified cell lines and subsequently of
modified plants with particularly valuable
traits.
The present level and rate of develop¬
ment in breeding imposes a search for new
methods and parent strains for creating
varieties which will hold out prospects for
the next century. There is already an acute
need for new approaches which will ensure
success later on. The way is being opened
for recourse to wild varieties containing val¬
uable genes, for the mutation of genetic
material by combining somatic cells from
early ancestors. There are already examples
of the utilization of somatic hybrids of culti
vated and wild potatoes. Thanks to a syn¬
thesis of the parents' characteristics, one of
them was "endowed", through the transfer
of cytoplasmic genes, with resistance to
viral diseases.
The creation of "cybrids", hybrid strains
which have received the cytoplasms of both
parents and the nucleus of one of them, is
considered to be even more promising. The
possibilities for such constructions are the¬
oretically unlimited. It is possible to trans¬
form a cell by transferring to it not only the
nucleus, cytoplasm or individual organelles
of the other partner, but individual genes
previously cloned in bacteria.
Much of this may seem fanciful, but the
fact that a broad scheme for the implemen¬
tation of these processes has already been
elaborated is due to the imagination of
researchers. The next step will be the cre¬
ation of a transformation technique. The
first characteristics obtained through the
transfer of individual genes will apparently
be resistance to herbicides and to certain
stresses and possibly a heightened bio-
synthetic activity if cell ferments of a bio¬
synthesis of physiologically active sub¬
stances are isolated.
The cloning of individual genes seems to
be a real possibility for the near future, but
the transfer of integral characteristics will
be a more long-term task, for the accom¬
plishment of which it will be necessary to
learn how to isolate and clone regulatory
genes. At present, the solution of this prob¬
lem seems to be far-fetched and distant. But
it is not so long since most of the techniques
now in use in agriculture were treated as the
fantasies of biologists and other scientists.
RAISSA GEORGIEVNA BUTENKO is a leading
Soviet cell biologist and plant physiologist who
has carried out extensive research into the use of
plant tissue and cell cultures for scientific and
practical purposes. A corresponding member of
the USSR Academy of Sciences and of the
All-Union Academy of Agricultural Sciences, she
is head of the cell biology and biotechnology
department of the Academy's Institute of Plant
Physiology and the author of some 300 publis¬
hed scientific papers.
2LATA BORISOVNA SHAMINA is a leading
Soviet specialist in cell biology and plant gene¬
tics. She is the author of over 100 published
scientific papers.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
For subsistence farmers in
developing countries,
biotechnology has
much to offer.
But will the potential
be fulfilled?
r*4 3fcM ^ -
Grains
of hope
'*p ----- \ . *3
*-.W^* *fautes** '
» »<
/3y ¿V/wa/tf C. Wo// FROM 1920 to 1950, agriculture in
industrial countries was dominated
by mechanical technologies that
dramatically increased the amount of food
that could be produced per worker and per
hour. Shortly after the Second World War,
the mechanical age gave way to the chemi¬
cal age as farmers worldwide began to adopt
artificial fertilizers and synthetic chemical
pesticides, which vastly expanded their har¬
vests per acre. Biotechnologies shift the
focus of research toward crop plants them¬
selves.
So far, advances have been made in
industrial countries, where public scrutiny
is intense. The environmental risks posed
by releasing gene-spliced microbes or plants
into the environment remain poorly under¬
stood. Developing regulations and
guidelines for the newly emerging tech¬
nologies has led to a contentious public
debate about genetic engineering. In the
United States, debate has centred on pro¬
posals to release bacteria modified to retard
the formation of frost on strawberry and
potato plants (see photo page 16). Because
the bacteria could reproduce in the natural
environment and thus spread beyond the
fields where they were released, predicting
environmental impacts is both more crucial
and more complex a task than with many
other technologies. Developing the "pre¬
dictive ecology" that critics say is necessary
for thorough environmental review, and
drawing up regulations that guard against
the uncertainties, will slow the marketing of
commercial biotechnology products to
farmers in industrial countries.
The genetic engineering of plants is far
more complex than modifying microbes,
but it is also less controversial on environ¬
mental grounds. Crops with modified traits
are under a farmer's direct control, and
their reproduction and spread in the
environment are both slower and more pre¬
dictable. Crop characteristics such as
drought-tolerance, ability to withstand salty
water, and pest resistance the traits that
have always concerned breeders are a
likely focus of the new technologies.
Given the ability to modify virtually any
plant characteristic and to tailor plants in
precisely defined ways, biotechnology
would seem to offer tools well-suited to
agricultural development strategies that
emphasize resource efficiency and farm¬
ing's internal resources. For example, it
should eventually be possible to modify a
plant's physiology to improve its efficiency
in photosynthesis, enabling grains to pro-
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
.#<; «Hkf ^ ** *"***
'
duce more carbohydrate and thus higher
yields. The adaptations that allow some
plants to lose very little water through their
leaves in transpiration, transferred to more
widely grown crops, could reduce irrigation
needs. Developments like these could
indeed reduce pressures on marginal lands
and perhaps eliminate the need for costly
capital investments in water supply
projects.
There is nothing in the nature of bio¬
technologies that renders them inherently
appropriate to a strategy of efficiency and
regeneration, however. Many biotechnol¬
ogy innovations pose trade-offs rather than
clear-cut benefits. Although increasing
photosynthetic efficiency could increase
yields, it would also be likely to lead to
accelerated depletion of soil nutrients and
heavier dependence on artificial fertilizers.
The most significant factor that will affect
the direction of agricultural biotechnology
is the rapid shift of research from the public
to the private sector. This is especially evi¬
dent in the United States. For nearly a cen¬
tury, public agricultural experiment sta¬
tions and land grant universities sponsored
by the US Department of Agriculture
(USDA) performed most agricultural
research. Private seed companies often use
the plant varieties developed by govern¬
ment-supported breeders. Over the last
three decades, however, the private sector
has assumed control of research efforts. Pri¬
vate companies now administer two-thirds
of US agricultural research.
In biotechnology, the deck is stacked
even further in favour of the private sector.
USDA's Agricultural Research Service and
Co-operative State Research Service sup¬
port most work in agricultural biotechnol¬
ogy, and these two federal programmes
spent less than $90 million on biotechnol¬
ogy research in 1984-85. Monsanto, which
has the largest but by no means the only
plant biotechnology research programme
among private US corporations, has
already invested $100 million in agricul¬
tural biotechnology development. Bio¬
technologies that affect agriculture in the
years ahead will have a decidedly private-
sector cast. With the important exceptions
of mechanization and the development of
hybrid corn, that has not generally been
true of important innovations in agricul¬
ture.
Leaving research priorities to the mar¬
ketplace may eclipse promising oppor¬
tunities. Research efforts on crcps will be
proportional to the value of the crop and the
Farmers in developing countries growing
food for their families on marginal land are
vulnerable to crop failure, erratic water
supply and natural catastrophes. The
potential of biotechnology in allowing the
rapid development of new crop varieties
and hybrids that are resistant to stresses
such as soil salinity and drought could be
an important step towards meeting the
needs of these subsistence farmers, who
are largely unable to afford the costly in¬
puts of fuel, artificial fertilizer and machin¬
ery on which past advances in agriculture
have been based and whose crops have
until quite recently been neglected by re¬
search. Above, hoeing millet in Mauritania.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Below, cassava (manioc) plants are protected from pests by ventilated bags as part of a
biological pest-control project being carried out at the International Institute of Tropical
Agriculture (UTA) at Ibadan (Nigeria). Some 200 million Africans rely on cassava for about
50 per cent of their calories. The UTA has developed disease-resistant cassava varieties
for distribution in a number of African countries.
size of the market. Because improving
crops for small farmers in developing coun¬
tries means producing low-cost agronomic
innovations, many of which must be site-
specific and thus not suitable for mass-mar¬
keting, crop improvement for the vast
majority of the world's farmers offers little
profit. Few private companies are likely to
enter such an unpromising market. Con¬
sequently, investigations of minor crops
like sorghum and millet, grown primarily by
Third World subsistence farmers, will be
neglected.
National research programmes and the
international research centres have an
obvious stake in applying biotechnology.
Refinements in plant breeding, tech¬
nologies for germplasm storage and for
plant evaluation and propagation, and new
alternatives in pest control, are exactly the
kinds of innovations scientists need to
extend research on developing-country
food crops. It took decades of work to pro¬
duce high-yielding varieties of wheat and
rice. With biotechnology, comparable
improvements in millet, sorghum, cassava,
or tropical legumes could come more
quickly.
The private sector domination of bio¬
technology raises questions about the role
new technologies will play in international
research programmes. Private companies
may become competitors with the interna¬
tional agricultural research centres spon¬
sored by the Washington-based Con¬
sultative Group on International Agri¬
cultural Research (CGIAR), particularly
when it comes to improvements in major,
widely traded crops like wheat and rice. The
full exchange of scientific information that
is essential to the international centres may
be curtailed if it appears to compromise
proprietary corporate research. Moreover,
international centres may increasingly have
to purchase or license new technologies that
24
were formerly freely available through
public channels. Finally, private firms will
compete with the centres for scientific tal¬
ent, and the centres may be unable to match
the salaries, facilities and security that cor¬
porate laboratories offer.
Uncertainties cloud the national bio¬
technology programmes as well. A few
developing countries, notably Indonesia,
the Philippines, and Thailand, have estab¬
lished national programmes in agricultural
biotechnology. The Philippines views its
programme as the first step towards an
industrialization strategy based on biolog¬
ical materials that can help free the country
from dependence on imported oil. Philip¬
pine scientists hope to use crop residues and
byproducts as raw materials to produce
liquid fuels and industrial chemicals, and to
develop food-processing industries with
biotechnology methods. W.G. Padolina, of
the National Institute of Biotechnology and
Applied Microbiology at the University of
the Philippines, writes, "The national strat¬
egy is to transform biomass biologically into
food, fuel, fertilizers and chemicals."
Achieving these goals is certain to be
costly. Few countries can afford the invest¬
ment in equipment that major biotechnol¬
ogy programmes entail, and some countries
lack sufficient numbers of trained scientists
to staff such programmes. Agricultural bio¬
technology contrasts sharply in this regard
with conventional plant breeding pro¬
grammes, which require relatively modest
capital investment.
EDWARD C. WOLF is a Sen/or Researcher with
WorldWatch Institute, Washington, D.C., a non¬
profit research organization which was created
to focus attention on global problems and is
funded by private foundations and United Na¬
tions organizations. The above article and the
box, right, have been extracted from Beyond the
Green Revolution: New Approaches for Third
World Agriculture, a WorldWatch Paper pub¬
lished in late 1986. m
AGRICULTURAL scientists have re¬
cently begun to recognize that many
farming systems that have persisted
for millennia exemplify careful management
of soil, water, and nutrients, precisely the
methods required to make high-input farming
practices sustainable. This overdue reap¬
praisal stems in part from the need to use
inputs more efficiently, and in part from the
growing interest in biological technologies.
Traditional farming systems face real
agronomic limits, and can rarely compete
tonne for harvested tonne with high-input
modern methods. It is important to recognize
these limitations, for they determine both how
traditional practices can be modified and what
such practices can contribute to the effort to
raise agricultural productivity.
First, most traditional crop varieties have
limited genetic potential for high grain yields.
They are often large-leaved and tall, for exam¬
ple. These traits help farmers meet non-food
needs, supplying thatch, fuel and fodder as
well as food to farm households. Traditional
varieties respond poorly to the two elements
of agronomic management that make high
grain yields possible: dense planting and
artificial fertilizer. Despite these limitations,
traditional varieties also contain genetic diver¬
sity that is invaluable to breeders in search of
genes for disease- and pest-resistance and
for other traits.
Second, peasant farmers often have to
plant in soils with serious nutrient deficiencies,
where crop combinations and rotations are
needed to help offset the limitations. Many
tropical soils, for instance, lack sufficient nitro¬
gen to sustain a robust crop. Soils in vast
areas of semi-arid Africa are deficient in phos¬
phorus. High-yielding varieties, more efficient
in converting available nutrients into edible
grain, can rapidly deplete soil nutrients if they
are planted by peasant farmers who cannot
purchase supplemental fertilizers.
Nonetheless, traditional methods can make
an important contribution to efforts to raise
agricultural productivity. They offer what have
been called "principles of permanence".
"Neither modern Western agriculture nor in¬
digenous traditional agriculture, in their pres¬
ent forms, are exactly what will be needed by
most small-scale farmers," says one'
researcher, Gerald Marten of the East-West
Center in Hawaii. "The challenge for agri¬
cultural research is to improve agriculture in
ways that retain the strengths of traditional
agriculture while meeting the needs of chang¬
ing times."
Harvest home. A Mauritanian woman fills
her bowl from a heap of millet near the
family tent. Research in recent years has
contributed to a reappraisal of the ecolo¬
gical and agronomic strengths of tradi¬
tional farming techniques such as those
practiced by West Africa's millet and sor¬
ghum growers. Joining biotechnologies
with the ecological insights of traditional
farming may lead to innovative solutions
to economic and environmental problems
in agriculture.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The rediscovery of traditional agriculture
Intercropping, agroforestry, shifting cultiva¬
tion, and other traditional farming methods
mimic natural ecological processes, and the
sustainability of many traditional practices lies
in the ecological models they follow. This use
of natural analogies suggests principles for
the design of agricultural systems to make the
most of sunlight, soil nutrients and rainfall.
Shifting cultivation practices, such as bush-
fallow methods in Africa, demonstrate how
farmers can harness the land's natural re¬
generation. Farmers using bush-fallow sys¬
tems clear fields by burning off the shrubs and
woody vegetation. Ashes fertilize the first
crop. After a couple of seasons, as nutrients
are depleted, harvests begin to decline, so
farmers abandon the fields and move on to
clear new land. Natural regeneration takes
over; shrubs and trees gradually reseed the
land, returning nutrients to the topsoil and
restoring the land's inherent fertility. After fif
teen to twenty years, the land can be burned
and cultivated again.
The bush-fallow system has obvious limita¬
tions. But even disintegrating systems offer a
basis for designing productive and sustai¬
nable farming practices. Researchers at the
Nigeria-based International Institute of Tropi¬
cal Agriculture, for instance, have adapted the
principles of natural regeneration in bush-
fallow systems to a continuous-cultivation
agroforestry system called alley cropping.
Field crops are grown between rows of nitro¬
gen-fixing trees; foliage from the trees
enhances the soil organic matter, while nitro¬
gen fixed in root nodules increases soil fertil¬
ity. A high level of crop production is possible
without a fallow interval. Traditional shifting
cultivation provided the model for this
system.
Conventional research tools can also be
used to overcome the agronomic constraints
that have limited traditional systems to low
productivity. For decades, crop breeders have
tailored varieties to respond to high levels of
artificial fertilizers, assured water supplies,
and dense monoculture plantings. Working
with the genetic diversity available in tradi¬
tional crop varieties, they can apply breeding
methods to produce varieties better matched
to the conditions faced by subsistence
farmers.
As the African examples described here
show, researchers can use traditional princi¬
ples to develop new techniques that preserve
the land's stability and productivity even as
populations increase. Though traditional
methods have limitations, they are not archaic
practices to be swept aside. Traditional
farming constitutes a foundation on which
scientific improvements in agriculture can
build.
&* s
-ar?
- r-v
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Rusitec the cow
Food for rumination
The rumen is an important part of the
digestive tract of ruminant animals such
as cattle, buffalo, sheep and goats. It con¬
tains large numbers of micro-organisms
whose function is to break down fibrous
feed materials such as grass and straw
and convert them to products that can be
used by the animal to produce meat, milk,
wool or draught power.
To study the microbial population of the
rumen under controlled laboratory con¬
ditions, Dr. J.W. Czerkawski of the Hannah
Research Institute, Scotland, U.K., de¬
veloped an "artificial cow". The "cow",
named RUSITEC (from the acronym of
"Rumen Simulation Technique") is today
being used as part of a project to analyse
different feedstuffs being carried out by
the Food and Agriculture Organization of
the United Nations (FAO) and the Interna¬
tional Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA) at
their joint Agricultural Biotechnology Unit
at Seibersdorff near Vienna, Austria.
in the artificial rumen micro-organisms
can be indefinitely maintained by feeding a
normal ruminant diet each day and provid¬
ing the correct physiological conditions in
terms of temperature, pH and flow of sali¬
va. As RUSITEC chews its way through
different feeds, scientists use radioactive
tracing techniques to compare their diges¬
tibility. (The higher the digestibility of a
foodstuff, the higher the nutritive value
that can be derived from it.) By analysing
the quality of different feeding materials in
this way, scientists are seeking to propose
improved diets for domestic animals in the
developing world. Photos on this page
show RUSITEC at work. Below left, the
vessels representing the rumen, where
microbial fermentation of diets takes
place; left, the rumen simulation techni¬
que in operation; below, analysis of the
end products of fermentative digestion.
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
the farmer's Mr. Fixit
A Unesco programme
to promote biotechnology
for development
LUCERNE farmers in Kenya, bean-
growers in Latin America, and rice-
growers in Southeast Asia are
today being helped to boost their yields as a
result of a Unesco programme in which
micro-organisms are being used to
strengthen rural development.
The programme has been established at a
time when many developing countries are
facing the problem of how to increase food
production to feed their expanding popula¬
tions. The quality of food produced must be
sufficient to provide a balapced diet with an
adequate protein content. In response to
this challenge, several developing nations
have been expanding their agricultural
lands into areas that are only marginally
capable of sustaining productivity. Such
attempts are invariably limited by the avail¬
ability of nitrogen fertilizer, which plays a
vital role in maintaining the productivity of
the soil.
By the end of the third quarter of this
century, world food production was depen¬
dent on a supply of synthetically produced
nitrogen fertilizer amounting to 40 million
tonnes and costing US $8,000-10,000 mil¬
lion per year. By the year 2000, estimated
annual needs will be 160 million tonnes.
The cost of fertilizer nitrogen, especially to
the agrarian-oriented economies of the
developing countries which are often
beset by shortages of foreign currency, is
enormous.
Nitrogen constitutes four-fifths of the
earth's atmosphere and is freely available in
nature. Since the nineteenth century it has
been known that the roots of leguminous
plants, in association with certain bacteria,
are capable of extracting nitrogen from the
atmosphere in the process known as nitro¬
gen fixation. The plants concerned include
groundnut, pigeon pea, mung bean, soy¬
bean, lentil, French bean, lucerne, channel
clover, white clover and winged bean, to
mention just a few species that are often
grown in developing countries today.
The most important bacteria which are
capable of nitrogen fixation belong to the
genus Rhizobium. When the bacteria infect
the plants, they stimulate the formation of
nodules swellings on the roots. The bac¬
teria within these root nodules improve the
fertility of the soil for the host plant by
adding nitrogen compounds to it. (In 1975,
it was estimated that the total nitrogen fixed
naturally amounted to 175 million tonnes;
35 million tonnes are fixed by cropped
leguminous plants alone.)
In addition to Rhizobium, other micro¬
organisms at the heart of nitrogen-fixing
systems include the Azolla Anabaena sys¬
tem which has been used for centuries by
rice-growers in Asia (see Unesco Courier,
December 1984), and the Azotobacter,
which live independently in the soil, as well
as Spirillum and Clostridium, which are
associated with certain grasses (such as
sugar cane) and cereal crops.
To contribute to rural development by
promoting biological nitrogen fixation tech¬
niques in developing countries, Unesco has
established, with support from the United
Nations Environment Programme (UNEP)
and the Food and Agriculture Organization
of the United Nations (FAO), a number of
Microbiological Resources Centres (MIR-
CENs) in different parts of the world to
catalogue and preserve Rhizobium and
other micro-organisms of economic signifi¬
cance and to train local manpower in their
use. The Centres form part of a global net¬
work of MIRCENs which are concerned
with the application to development of a
whole range of biotechnological applica¬
tions, from the production of biogas to
biopharmaceuticals .
By inoculating seeds with cultures of an
appropriate Rhizobium species, or
cyanobacteria in the case of rice, it is possi¬
ble to increase the supply of nitrogen avail¬
able to the plants concerned. The produc¬
tion and use of such biofertilizers'can thus
greatly help both to increase the prod¬
uctivity levels of the planet's soil resource
and to conserve petroleum and its expen¬
sive technologically-processed products,
such as fertilizer.
In interaction with other international
programmes, schemes focused on the
development of biofertilizers or Rhizobium
inoculant material are already operating
through the MIRCEN network on a level of
regional co-operation in Latin America,
East Africa and Southeast Asia and the
Pacific, with additional support from FAO
and UNEP.
In the field of biological nitrogen fixation
by Edgar J. DaSilva,
J. Freiré,
A. Hillali
and S. O. Keya
Below, bilingual (English-Swahili) instruc¬
tions for farmers on a packet of fertilizer
produced from bacteria by a Unesco-sup-
ported Microbiological Resources Centre
(MIRCEN) in Kenya. The fertilizer, mixed
with the seeds of certain leguminous
plants such as beans or clover at sowing
time, helps the plants to increase their
intake of nitrogen from the atmosphere
which is essential for their growth.
(g LEGUME INOCULANT
Äj|3yS ^tf (lie<[ïi Itígiimen w use (üftnn«)' Ira* -Ik"
%3(X5i ¿¡ "mruw B»
éBSpgSÎËL rwAmMiNr. <» son sntío ». wh/wy
jSQWjfiraa (MM*« PHlMfCT
yijjfSjtfflf lAOttl» W «ÍBBUU»«f KABH* .M*U5
<?(?U?§»iS jKtvHtari en mmm
ni«« «019 MMfXM KM4Í*
CROP
BAfUH
USE BFRWf
DIRECTIONS FOR USE MAELEZO YA KUTUMIA
Us« onty (a ine orev rueufioner? or lWUu 1 Kv* hcM .Jl",-i>p«'i0*
Sit panai Rie oontew r* ¿u www vv» i» Mkui ;-ïiw# ni bt>
poctn' h jjttutenf t« 15 kg ->" % *» m:'/«»« «wr rMWp« \<imc>
we* Mu »i* «»Mal ot X« kh» iSB H k« \> . jrtuuas« ram
poo)«; well wtt* seeds motetHM -ucnauft! m* münyt. <wo «sjtuiaio
Wit) WOtW 'k sue« MMUltOP ufttfl Jl ujflji <¿a» -ilfHrtC' P'fw.iji. uw* ,uu
seeds wi urttamrv coaled ana sow yti KW »w*«' na upando mata
AOJO
ONYO
CAUTION
Mbégu (ft in.«)«-., i wtveyc
Inoculuterl seeds Inoculent sixwb </-\<-> .iw»kw '"in. n if«Apo jotu
O
Ü not be exposed to sunttgnt neu' i HO .ii' «0*' '" jHI/i>Û«iiH/1."V« te
Eß
<0 mixed win chemical fertilizers M own' M lí'iiow» urturB*
c
5 inoculan' supplie* only nittuuen Mcíxin)'- 'un .- wnso na
"35 therefore jpoty oll other iltruoei *i* inuyt »nao«:
T3
3 to the soli rirvH& BO Rinn rM'KJf» w*i
O
tffcHlQ«
.c
o
5
o
o
c
Û.
STORI IHIt PACHT UNI«R COOL PLACÍ UNTIL USE
VKKA PAMTI HII PAHAU PASIPO JOTO AU AJA KAU
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO MIRCEN
international co-operation
Aim: Have young scientists contribute to research and
development in their own countries and promote
international co-operation by working with high-level
scientists in UNESCO training courses.
Mechanisms
1 MIRCENs
MIRCENsr Microbiological Resources Centres
A world-wide network
Aim: Collect, preserve and use microbial strains for
national development and international co-operation
_.T.V»1
GIAM
GIAM r Meetings of Scientists on Global Impacts
of Applied Microbiology
Aim: Strengthen research co-operation between
industrial and developing countries
Stimulate capacity-building for local research and
training
.1
3 Co-operation with U.N. Agencies and
non-governmental organizations
FAO Food and Agriculture Organization
UNDP United Nations Development Programme
UNEP United Nations Environment Programme
UNIDO United Nations Industrial DevelopmentlOrganization
ICRO* International Cell Research Organization
IFS International Foundation for Science
IOBB International Organization of Biotechnology and
Bioengineering
IUMS International Union of Microbiological Societies
WFCC World Federation for Culture Collections
* Panel on Microbiology and Biotechnology
4 Co-operation with regional organizations
ALAR Latin-American Association of Rhizobiology CEC Commission of the European Communities
AABNF African Association for Biological Nitrogen Fixation SANEM Southeast Asian Network on Microbiology
ABEGS Arab Bureau of Education forthe Gulf States
five MIRCENs are already operating, in
Kenya, Brazil, Hawaii, Beltsville, USA,
and Senegal. The broad responsibilities of
the MIRCENs for the East African and
West African regions include the collection,
identification, maintenance, testing and
distribution of rhizobial cultures compati¬
ble with local crops. Deployment of local
rhizobia inoculant technology and promo¬
tion of allied research are other activities.
Advice and guidance are provided
regionally to individuals and institutions
engaged in rhizobiology research.
The MIRCEN in Latin America, in a sim¬
ilar vein, promotes the identification of
leguminous germplasm of high symbiotic
capacity and soil-limiting factors; the opti¬
mal selection of efficient rhizobial strains
for soybean, clover, lucerne, lotus, peas,
beans and the cowpea group; optimization
of inoculant production for use in demon¬
stration plots and by small farmers; and the
quality control of inoculants for use by pri¬
vate and official laboratories.
The goals of the MIRCENs at Hawaii and
Beltsville, U.S.A., are to contribute
towards alleviating the dependence of
developing countries on chemically-derived
nitrogenous fertilizers. This is accom¬
plished through research to provide a
database to assess the benefits of utilization
of legume-based biological nitrogen fixa¬
tion (BNF) technologies; development and
delivery of validated BNF technologies that
are appropriate to the needs of, and circum¬
stances in, developing countries; and the
provision of support services.
In addition, the MIRCENs in Kenya and
Brazil are involved in the production of
inoculants for legume trials and for use by
farmers.
Inoculant production at the East African
MIRCEN has now been initiated using
strains tested by MIRCEN workers. Inocu¬
lants for eleven pasture legumes have been
supplied to FAO pasture agronomists in
Kenya. The MIRCEN in Brazil, on behalf
A technician at a Unesco-supported Mic-
robiological Resources Centre (MIRCEN)
In Brazil prepares materials for a training
course in the identification of bacteria
from which fertilizer can be produced.
of the Federal Government, is responsible
for the quality control of inoculants pro¬
duced in that country. An average of 100
samples are examined per year. On a lim¬
ited basis this service is also available to
institutions in the developing countries.
The BNF MIRCENs play a valuable role in
maintaining and distributing efficient cul¬
tures of Rhizobium. Collectively, over
3,000 strains are maintained in the
MIRCEN collections.
EDGAR J. DASILVA, Indian microbiologist, is a
former Vice-President of the World Federation of
Culture Collections (WFCC). The author of
several papers on the biotechnological applica¬
tions of micro-organisms, he is a member of
Unesco's Division of Scientific Research and
Higher Education, where he has been largely
responsible for the development and imple¬
mentation of Unesco's MIRCEN programme.
J. FREIRÉ, of Brazil, is director of the MIRCEN
and a professor of soil microbiology at the Uni-
versidade Federale do Rio Grande do Sul. A.
HILLALI, of Morocco, is a rh/zob/ologist at the
Institut Agronomique et Vétérinaire Hassan II, at
Rabat. He has been carrying out research and
consultancy work on the applications of rhizobial
biofertilizers at the West African MIRCEN at
Bambey, Senegal. S.O. KEYA, of Kenya, is
director of the MIRCEN atthe University of Nairo¬
bi, where he is head of the department of soil
science and dean of the faculty of agriculture.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Achallenge
for the developing world
by Albert Sasson
BIOTECHNOLOGIES have much to
offer developing countries. Their
application to agriculture, horticul¬
ture and forestry can contribute largely
both to the improvement of cultivated
plants and to the protection of species
threatened with disappearance. But careful
consideration must be given to the choice of
the most appropriate techniques and their
transfer and adaptation to specific condi¬
tions.
Such processes as plant cell and tissue
cultures and genetic engineering are tools,
not solutions to social problems. For exam¬
ple, the replacement of traditional crop
varieties by new ones may cause unemploy¬
ment if such new varieties require less work.
There is also a tendency for research in
biotechnology to respond primarily to the
needs of international markets rather than
the domestic needs of developing countries.
Furthermore, since it is the big landowners
who possess the financial and management
resources enabling them to profit from tech¬
nological innovations, it is likely that they
rather than the small farmers will gain
from the application of biotechnology to
agriculture.
fn a Kuala Lumpur laboratory, above,
Malaysian biotechnicians tend test-tube
cultures as part of a short-term project to
produce elite oil-palms.
There is a strong possibility that the poor
countries in general will not only reap few
direct benefits from the biotechnological
revolution, but that their economies will be
indirectly hit by the development of new
products (such as artificial sweeteners)
which will compete with their traditional
export commodities. There is a danger that
the technology gap between the rich and
poor countries will grow even wider.
Searching questions must therefore be
asked about the nature of the "Bio¬
technological Revolution" and its long-
term economic, social and geopolitical
effects; strategies must be devised to ensure
that its benefits are equitably shared both
between countries and between different
social groups within a given country.
The "Biotechnological Revolution" is
irreversible, if only because of the commer¬
cial successes that have already been
achieved and the size of the investments
which have been made in the different fields
of biotechnology. It has been estimated that
the sales of products derived from the
application of biotechnologies to food and
agriculture alone may reach between
$50,000 million and $100,000 million by the
year 2000.
Whereas the "Green Revolution" was
largely carried out by the public sector,
which made possible the free exchange of
new plant strains developed notably in
international agronomic research centres
sponsored by the FAO, the impetus behind
the "Biotechnological Revolution" in agri¬
culture is coming largely from the private
sector, although much basic research is
being carried out in universities and in
state-supported agricultural and forestry
facilities.
The privatization of the results of
research in biotechnology means that these
results do not form part of the universally
available body of scientific and technical
knowledge that belongs to the common
heritage of mankind. In addition, the public
sector research institutions and the organ¬
isms which subsidize them are tending to
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
J The Green Revolution and the "Biorevolution"
Characteristics Green revolution
L
Biorevolution
Crops affected Wheat, rice, maize Potentially all crops, including vegeta¬
bles, fruits, agro-export crops (e.g., oil
palms, cacao), and speciality crops
(e.g., spices, scents)
Other products affected None Animal products, pharmaceuticals,
processed foods, energy
Areas affected
~1
Crops displaced
Some locations in some less develo¬
ped countries (i.e., if accompanied by
irrigation, high-quality land, transport
availability, etc.)
All areas, including marginal lands
characterized by drought, salinity, alu¬
minium toxicity, etc.
Technology development and
dissemination
Largely public or quasi-public sector Largely private sector (multinational cor¬
porations and start-up firms).
Proprietary consideration Patents and plant variety protection
generally not relevant
Processes and products patentable and
protectable
Capital costs of research Low High
Research skills required Conventional plant breeding and paral¬
lel agricultural sciences
Molecular and cell biology expertise plus
conventional plant-breeding skills
None (except the germplasm resour¬
ces represented in traditional varie¬
ties)
Potentially any
Source: Ceres, FAO / Büttel et alr
take out patents and thus contribute to the
privatization of the results of research.
The growing tendency to grant patents to
plant breeders as a means of protecting the
creation of new strains is causing wide¬
spread concern in developing countries
where these measures are seen as obstacles
to their efforts to increase their agricultural
output.
The adoption of legislation to protect the
rights of plant breeders by patent (that is,
granting to plant geneticists and the bodies
which subsidize their research exclusive
production and marketing rights over these
varieties) has encouraged multinational
corporations and several major national
chemical and pharmaceutical groups to buy
seed marketing companies and to take
majority participations in firms engaged in
varietal selection and plant genetics
research. In Europe and North America,
the leading multinational petrochemical
and pharmaceutical firms have acquired a
dominant position in this field.
One reason for this trend is to be found in
the complementary roles played by seeds,
fertilizer, pesticides and animal medicines
in boosting agricultural output. It is thus
possible for one firm to influence the entire
production chain.
The market for selected seeds is worth
$12,000 million a year, including $2,000
million for hybrid maize and sorghum
seeds, and $1,000 million for hybrid oats,
soya and cotton seeds. The grip of the multi
national corporations and of other major
industrial groups on the seed companies is
likely to encourage monopolies and sharply
reduce the public sector role in plant
selection.
Measures taken by the technologically
advanced countries to protect the results of
increasingly expensive research into plant
genetics and to ensure that such research is
profitable include the payment of royalties,
notably by the developing countries, for
seed varieties selected in the industrialized
countries. The latter countries are also
tending to use their collections of seeds and
plants (germplasm) for commercial pur¬
poses; the private sector is playing an
increasing role in the collection, preserva¬
tion and use of germplasm.
Many developing countries do not pos¬
sess the financial and technical resources to
establish seed collections or to preserve
such collections in satisfactory conditions.
They have no alternative but to buy new
strains selected from varieties which have
been cultivated or which grow wild in their
own regions. Such varieties may have been
domesticated, cultivated and improved by
many generations of farmers in the develop¬
ing countries before being crossed with
other varieties, protected by patent, and
then sold in their countries of origin as "new
and different". This paradoxical situation
calls in question the validity of the patent
system, for to grant ownership rights and
royalties to those who have recently
improved the genetic heritage of a plant
variety is to disregard the efforts of all those
who have previously transformed the vari¬
ety and derived no profit from it.
"The North may be 'grain-rich' but the
South is 'gene-rich':" the genetic resources
of most cultivated plants are found in the
developing countries, notably in the trop¬
ics, but the selection and improvement
operations relating to these plants mainly
take place in the industrialized countries. In
1982, according to the Organization for
Economic Co-operation and Development
(OECD), the developing countries were
contributing an estimated $500 million a
year to the United States wheat harvest.
This contribution resulted from the use of
plant genetic resources which originate in
the developing countries and are indispen¬
sable to the improvement of cultivated
plants and variety selection in the United
States and in the other industrialized
countries.
In view of the economic importance of
their plant genetic resources, the develop¬
ing countries intend to protect these
resources for example by preventing the
export of plant reproducing material. They
also feel that the purchase price of varieties
of seeds selected and improved from their
own phytogenetic stock is excessive and
that it is unjust to be thus obliged to buy
back indirectly a part of their phytogenetic
heritage.
The risk of a diminution of genetic diver-
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
sity, combined with the question of restric¬
tive practices in the distribution of material
needed for the improvement of cultivated
plants, has led to a search for an interna¬
tional agreement on the conservation of
plant genetic resources, considered as part
of the heritage of humanity, and on their
equitable use, instead of allowing such use
to be regulated solely by national jurisdic¬
tions. If the industrialized countries wish to
have access to the plant genetic resources of
the developing countries and wish to use the
hardy local strains which are found there,
the developing countries wish to benefit
from services provided by gene banks in the
industrialized countries and to claim their
national sovereignty over plants grown in
their countries.
The problems of the conservation of and
free access to plant genetic resources have
thus assumed a geopolitical dimension in
the context of the debate on the exploita¬
tion of the Earth's resources for the benefit
of all humanity. In November 1981 a resolu¬
tion presented by Mexico to the 21st Con¬
ference of FAO invited the Director-Gen¬
eral to prepare a draft international
Convention on the conservation of plant
genetic resources necessary to increase agri¬
cultural production, on the removal of
obstacles to the free distribution of plant
material and on the improvement of inter¬
national co-operation in this field.
In November 1983, a draft international
Convention was accordingly submitted for
examination to the FAO Conference at its
22nd Session. Among its provisions was one
which prohibited the imposition of any
restriction on the availability or exchange of
plant genetic resources for agriculture and
food production.
The 156 countries represented at the
22nd Session recognized that "plant
resources were part of the common heritage
of mankind and should thus be accessible
without restriction". Such resources include
wild species or those close to cultivated vari¬
eties, which should be catalogued and pro¬
tected, for they are threatened with disap¬
pearance, as well as the most recent
cultivated varieties and strains which make
it possible to produce seeds of more produc¬
tive hybrid varieties.
In November 1985, at the 23rd Session of
the FAO Conference, the industrialized
countries opposed the creation of an inter¬
national mechanism to ensure the free
exchange of plant genetic resources and to
abolish payment for varieties selected in the
industrialized countries and royalties to
acquire them. It is thus to be expected that
genetic information needed for the
improvement of cultivated plants may
become a commercial commodity subject to
competition between seed companies,
between countries, and between seed com¬
panies and countries.
However, it is to be hoped that a compro¬
mise will be found between the legitimate
desire to reward human ingenuity by grant-
Completing the brick dome of a digestion
tank for biogas production in China. With
over 7 million biogas digesters, China
leads the world in this field of energy pro¬
duction.
ing patents to selectors in the industrialized
countries and the need for developing coun¬
tries to obtain selected varieties at a price
compatible with their limited means and the
imperatives of their agricultural develop¬
ment. It would also be ethically justifiable
to take into account, in the sale to develop¬
ing countries of seed varieties selected from
their own cultivated plants, the work of the
generations of farmers who have contrib¬
uted to the improvement of these plants.
In the meantime, much can be done to
harness biotechnologies to agriculture, hor¬
ticulture and forestry in the developing
world.
First of all, in each developing country
steps should be taken to establish priorities
and economic objectives which derive max¬
imum benefit from the available resources.
Those biotechnological processes which are
most relevant to the country's social and
economic needs should be identified and
inventories of local resources should be
drawn up.
Secondly, developing countries should
avoid entering into competition, at least ini-
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
* *&.̂
N
"i :
tially, with the industrialized countries in
such advanced fields as gene transfer and
genetic engineering. They should profit
from simpler techniques of plant tissue cul¬
ture, meristem culture (see page 6) and
plant organ culture for the rapid vegetative
propagation of the most useful strains and
for the isolation of virus-free strains. They
should adopt and practise at the appropri¬
ate scale low-cost, proven biotechnologies
which are easy to transfer and to adapt to
local conditions.
Thirdly, biotechnologies should not be
considered as the only means of improving
species of cultivated plants. They should be
seen as complementary to hybridization
methods and efficient agricultural prac¬
tices. The success of biotechnologies in the
developing countries will depend to a large
extent on their being closely associated with
classical methods of crossing and improving
plants, with agricultural training pro¬
grammes, the establishment of remunera¬
tive farm prices and the existence of a good
marketing network for agro-food products.
Fourthly, the choice of appropriate bio¬
technologies does not mean that we should
resign ourselves to accepting an interna¬
tional division of biotechnologies: high tech
for the technologically advanced countries,
outworn technologies for the developing
countries. A range of biotechnologies, of
varying degrees of sophistication and com
plexity, should exist in each specific situa¬
tion. Every national scientific and tech¬
nological community should take into
account international developments in bio¬
technology when considering local needs,
and be able to use the most advanced
techniques or adapt them to development
projects.
Whatever options for the development of
biotechnologies are chosen, education and
training are bound to play an essential role.
Standing as they do at the crossroads of
several disciplines of the life sciences
(genetics, biochemistry, physiology and
microbiology), and of engineering (fermen¬
tation technology, automization of produc¬
tion techniques, chemical and industrial
microbiology), biotechnologies call for
interdisciplinary training programmes and
an integrated approach.
There is a chronic lack of specialists and
biotechnology technicians in the developing
countries. According to one survey, in 1983
there were 23,000 researchers in this field in
the USA, 12,000 in the USSR, 8,000 in
Japan, 3,400 in the rest of Asia, 1,900 in
Latin America and 400 in Africa.
International and regional co-operation
undoubtedly has a major role to play in
encouraging the transfer of biotechnologies
and the fulfilment of their promise in the
developing world, as well as helping to solve
the ethical problems involved. It should be
From test-tube to forest
Biotechnology opens new possibilities for
forest management in developing coun¬
tries. In vitro tissue culture methods,
above, make possible the rapid production
of genetically uniform elite specimens
which must then be tested in field condi¬
tions in the outdoor laboratory the
forest. Lines of eucalyptus in the Congo,
right, stretch as far as the eye can see.
They were grown from clones of carefully
selected hybrids.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
possible for countries within a given region
to carry out joint research projects into mat¬
ters of common concern and to obtain
results which can be applied in several coun¬
tries. Efforts must be made to encourage
co-operation between developing and
industrialized countries, including private
sector institutions in these countries. Exam¬
ples of such co-operation already exist.
They include the production of vaccines
against foot and mouth disease in Botswana
with the co-operation of Rhône-Mérieux in
France; biogas production from wastes
through co-operation between India, China
and several developing countries; and the
cloning of the oil palm and the creation of
new oil palm plantations in Ivory Coast,
Malaysia and Indonesia in co-operation
with the French Office of Scientific and
Technical Research Overseas (ORSTOM)
and the French Research Institute for Oils
and Oil-Producing Substances (IRHO).
The role of international intergovern¬
mental organizations is important in help¬
ing to provide governments with con¬
sultative services with a view to the
formulation of national policies and
programmes in biotechnology; to encour¬
age joint research projects and other joint
activities between developing and in¬
dustrialized countries; to encourage
researchers and technicians from all coun¬
tries to take part in these activities, and to
strengthen national research and training
capacities.
Ever since its early days, Unesco has laid
great stress in its scientific programmes on
international co-operation in research and
training in the life sciences, and at an early
stage drew attention to the importance of
research into micro-organisms and em¬
barked on a programme in applied micro¬
biology. In 1962 Unesco sponsored the
creation of the International Cell Research
Organization (ICRO), and in 1972 joined
with ICRO and the United Nations
Environment Programme (UNEP) in
launching a world programme to safeguard
the genetic heritage of microbial resources
and to make this heritage accessible to
developing countries. Then, in 1975,
Unesco began to create the world network
of Microbiological Resources Centres
(MIRCEN) whose activities are described
in the article on page 27.
Following the adoption of Unesco's sec¬
ond Medium-Term Plan (1984-1989),
activities relating to training, research and
international co-operation in applied
microbiology were strengthened and fur¬
ther extended into the field of bio¬
technologies. Today, in close collaboration
with FAO, the United Nations Industrial
Development Organization (UNIDO), the
World Health Organization (WHO) and
other specialized institutions of the United
Nations system and with international non¬
governmental organizations, Unesco con¬
tinues this work as part of the broader effort
to enable the developing countries to con¬
tribute to and benefit from advances in sci¬
entific knowledge.
ALBERT SASSON, Moroccan microbiologist, is
a doctor of natural sciences of the University of
Paris. From 1954 to 1973 he was engaged in
research at the Rabat (Morocco) Faculty of Sci¬
ences into algology, the microflora of arid lands,
and free and symbiotic nitrogen-fixing micro¬
organisms. A member of the Unesco secretariat
since 1974, Dr. Sasson is the author of several
books and studies on biology, microbiology and
biotechnologies and their applications to de¬
velopment, notably Biotechnologies: challenges
and promises (Unesco, 1984), which has so far
been published in English, French, Spanish, Ita¬
lian, Chinese and Russian and will soon be
appearing in Bulgarian, Portuguese and Roma¬
nian. In preparing this issue, the Editors have
made extensive use of Dr. Sasson 's book Quel¬
les biotechnologies pour les pays en dévelop¬
pement ? (Unesco and Biofutur publishers, Par¬
is, 1986), from which the above article has been
adapted. Dr. Sasson's latest book is Nourrir de-
main les hommes, ("Feeding mankind tomor¬
row") published by Unesco, 1986.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Recent issues of the Unesco Courier on scientific themes:
The Story of the Earth (July 1986)
The New World of the Ocean (February 1986)
Water and Man (January 1985)
The Story of the Universe (September 1984)
Forthcoming:
The World of Medicine Genetics and Society
bio
technologies:
\i«on
Biotechnologies: Challenges and Promises is a comprehensive
survey, accessible to the general reader, of new developments in
the different branches of biotechnology. The book outlines the
promises offered by the biotechnologies and emphasizes the role that
international co-operation will play in fulfilling them. It also discusses
the conflicting interests, problems and challenges raised by these
technologies in industrial development, their transfer to developing
countries and their adaptation to various economic, social and
cultural situations.
Contents include:
Nature and variety of biotechnological processes
Genetic recombination and areas of application
Hybridomas
Biotechnologies and the increase of plant productivity
Production of useful substances by micro-organisms
Microbial conversion of wastes and agricultural and industrial by-products
Energy production from biomass by micro-organisms
Development of bio-industry
315 pages, photos, drawings, graphs 85 French francs ISBN 92-3-102091-9
Also published in French and Spanish
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco periodicals
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58a Gipps St., Collingwood, Victoria 3066;
Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100,
NSW; Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33. Brookvale
2100, NSW. Sub-agent: United Nations Association of Australia, P.O. Box
175. 5th (loor. Ana House. 28 Elizabeth St.. Melbourne, Victoria 3000.
AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co.. Graben 31, A-1011, Vienna.
BAHRAIN. United Schools International, Arab Regional Office, P.O. Box 726,
Bahrain. BARBADOS. University ol the West Indies Bookshop, Cave Hill
Campus, P.O. Box 64, Bridgetown. BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch
edition only: Internationale Drukkenj en Uitgeverij Keesing, Keesmglaan 2-20,
2100 Deurne-Antwerpen. CCP 000-0012775-68. French edition and general
Unesco publications agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202 Ave. du Roi, 1 060 Brussels,
CCP 000-0070623-13. BRAZIL Pubhcacoes Técnicas Internacional Ltda,
Processing Dept., R Peixoto Gomide 209, 01409, Sao Paulo SP. CANADA.
Renout Publishing Co. Ltd., 1294 Algoma Road, Ottawa, Ontario K1B 3W8.
STORES: 61 Sparks Street, Ottawa, 21 1 Yonge St.. Toronto. SALES OFFICE:
7575 Trans Canada Hwy. Ste. 305, St. Laurent, Quebec H4T 1V6. CHINA.
China National Publications Import and Export Corporation, P.O. Box 88.
Beijing. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N T.L., Spalena 51-113 02, Prague 1; Ve
Smeckach 30, P.O.B. 790-1 1 1-27 Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni
literatura. 11 Soukenicka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag -Pub¬
lishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava-CSSR. DENMARK. Munk-
sgaard Expon-OG, Tidsskriftservice. 35 Norre Sogade. DK-1970 Kobenhavn
K. EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre (or Unesco Publications,
No. 1 Talaat Harb St.. Cairo. FINLAND. Akateemmen Kirjakauppa, P. O. Box
128, SF-00100 Helsinki. Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy. P.O. Box 2, 01641
Vantas 64. Rautikirja Oy, Subscription Department, P.O Box 1 , 01641 Vantas
64. FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco. 7 Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Pans. CCP
12596-46. GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Buchhaus Leipzig, Post-
lach 140. 710 Leipzig, or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R.
FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier: Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher
Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb. Basaltstrasse 57, D5300 Bonn 3. GHANA. Fides
Entreprises. P.O. Box 1 41 29, Accra. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE John Mihalopoulos & Son SA, International Booksellers, P.O. Box
1 0073, 54 1 1 0 Thessaloniki. G C Eleftheroudakis SA, International Bookstore,
4 Nikis Street, Athens T 126. Koslarakis Brothers, International Booksellers, 2
Hippocratous Street. Athens. HONG KONG. Swindon Book Co , 13-15, Lock
Rd., Kowloon. Hong Kong Govt. Information Services, Publication Centre.
Baskerville House, 22 Ice St. HUNGARY. Kultura-Bushimport-ABT, POB.
149-H-1389, Budapest 62. ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson and Co., H.F.
Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd.. Kamani Marg. Ballard
Estate, Bombay 400038; 1 7 Chilaranjan Ave , Calcutta 13: 36a, Anna Salai,
Mount Road, Madras 2; 5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh, Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1
Mahatma Gandhi Rd., Bangalore 560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda. Hyderabad-
500001. Sub-depots: Oxford Book and Stationery Co.. 17 Park St., Calcutta
70016; Scmdia House, New Delhi. INDONESIA. Indira P.T., Jl Dr. Sam
Ratulangie 37, Jakarta Pusat IRAN. Iranian National Commission for Unesco,
1188 Englab Ave, Rostam Give Building, Zip Code 13158, P.O. Box 11365-
4498, Teheran. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd.. Bally-
mount Rd., Walkmstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL. A B.C. Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box
1 283, 71 Allenby Rd. , Tel Aviv 61 000. ITALY. Licosa (Librería Commissionaria
Sansoni, S.p.A.), Via Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552, 50121 Florence
JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc. 37-3 Hongo 3-chome Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo
1 1 3. KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64,
Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co , Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait; tor the
Unesco Courier: Farafalla Press Agency, P O. Box SAFA 4541, Kuwait.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur
22-1 1 . MALTA. Sapienzas. 26 Republic St., Valletta. MAURITIUS. Nalanda
Company Ltd., 30 Bourbon St., Port-Lours. MEXICO. Librería El Correo de la
Unesco, Actipán 66. Colonia del Valle. Mexico 12, DF. MONACO. British
Library. 30 Bd. des Moulins. Monte Carlo. NEPAL. Sajha Prakashan Pol-
chowk, Kathmandu. NETHERLANDS. Faxon Europe, P.O. Box 197, 1000 AD
Amsterdam. NEW ZEALAND. Government Publishing, P.O. Box 14277-
Ktlbirnie, Wellington; 130 Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1 721, Chnstchurch; Alma
St.. P.O. Box 857. Hamilton; Princes St.. P.O. Box 1 104, Dunedin, NIGERIA.
The University Bookshop ol He; The University Bookshop ol Ibadan, P.O. 286.
NORWAY. Johan Grundt Tanum, P.O.B. 1 177 Sentrum - Oslo 1 ; Narvesen
A/S, Litteraturt Jenesten. P.O.B. 6125 Etterstad, N 0602 Oslo 6; Universitets
Bokhandelen. Universitetssentret, Postboks 307 Blmdern. Oslo 3.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam. P.O. Box No.
729, Lahore 3: Unesco Publications Centre, Regional Office for Book De¬
velopment in Asia and the Pacific. 39 Delhi Housing Society. P.O. Box 8950,
Karachi 29. POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kuftury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No.7. 00-068 Warsaw. PORTUGAL.
Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livrana Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SAUDI
ARABIA. Dar al Walan, Olaya Mam Street, Ibrahim Bin Sulaym Building,
Riyadh. SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (S) Pte Ltd. Times Jurong. 2
Jurong Port Rd., Singapore 2261. SOUTH AFRICA. American & Overseas
Publications (Pty) Ltd.. Subscription Service, P.O. Box 42476, Johannesburg.
Universitas Books (Pty) Ltd., P.O. Box 775, Pretoria 0001. Van Schaik's
Bookstore (Pty) Ltd.. Libri Building, 268 Church Street. Pretoria 0001 . Central
News Agency Lid., Group Overseas Periodical Div. P.O. Box 61 3, Cape Town
8000. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner
Mawata. P.O.B. 244, Colombo 2. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box
1118, Khartoum. SURINAME. Suriname National Commission for Unesco.
P.O. Box 2943. Paramaribo. SWEDEN. Fonhe Unesco Courier: Svenska FN
Forbundet, Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S-104, 65 Stockholm: Wennergren-
Wilhams AB, Nordenllychtsvagen 70, S-104, 25 Stockholm; Esselte Tidsknft-
scentralen. Gamla Brogatan 26, Box 62 -101 , 20 Stockholm. SWITZERLAND.
Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse, Zurich; Librairie Payot, Rue Grenus 6, 1211,
Geneva 1 1 . CCP. 12-236; Librairies Payot also in Lausanne. Baste, Berne.
Vevey, Montreux, Neuchâtel and Zürich. SYRIA. Aleppo University Books
Establishment, University of Aleppo, Aleppo. TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd.,
40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok;
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Ave., Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra St., St. Clair,
Trinidad W 1. TURKEY. Hasel Kitapevi A.S., Istiklâl Caddesi, No 469, Posta
Kutusu 219, Beyoglu. Istanbul. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office,
Agency Section Publications CTR, Periodicals Section-Room 008. Nine Elms
Lane, London SWS 5DR. and H.M.S.O. Bookshops in London. Edinburgh,
Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol; for scientific maps only: McCarta
Ltd., 122 Kings Cross Rd . London WClX 9DS. UNITED STATES. Bernan
Associates-UN I PUB, Periodicals Department. 10033-F King Highway,
Lanham MD 20706. USSR. V/O Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Ul. Dimitrova 39.
Moskva 113095. YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost, llica 30/11, Zagreb; Cankarjeva
Zalozba, Zopitarjeva 2, Lubljana: Noht, Terazije 27/1 1. Belgrade. ZAMBIA.
National Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd.. P O. Box 2664. Lusaka.
ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd.. 1 Norwich Union Centre. Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
</document>
