<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="073379eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
¡t
rw% s
;.::
.-.-. -
V »
SU RVI VA L
ife in extreme
conditions
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A time to live . . .
** V m
s
©
Volunteer roadworkers
In Lesotho, a small land-locked country in southern Africa, the land is
subject to extensive erosion caused by severe drought followed by
intensive rainfall, by heavy over-grazing, and fuel-wood cutting. To
combat erosion, increase agricultural production, improve the road
network and encourage the development of village woodlots, the Gov¬
ernment of Lesotho, assisted by the United Nations World Food Prog¬
ramme, organized a food-for-work project with voluntary labourers.
Women constituted 90 per cent of the work-force. Above, labourers
shovel earth while widening a track into a road.
55 Lesotho
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Editorial June 1987
40th year
Man has always lived dangerously, ever since his most distant
ancestor, a hominid who probably lived on the African continent,
took the first steps along the path of human evolution and
discovered that a stone held in the hand could be used as a tool or a
weapon.
From the dawn of history onwards, human beings continually
courted danger as the struggle for survival schooled them in
resourcefulness and impelled them to the limits of endurance. This
determination to perform seemingly impossible feats is a thread
which runs through the pattern of human destiny and helps to
explain the extraordinary efforts made by human communities in
various parts of the world to adapt to extremely rigorous
environmental conditions. From the primitive hunters who
confronted their prey armed only with a stone axe, to the space
travellers of the late twentieth century who must reach peak
physical and mental condition in order to spend long periods in a
state ofweightlessness, human beings have always shown
capacities for adaptation both to the natural environment and to
their self-imposed challenges. Man is by nature an inventive,
forward-looking being whose relentless drive to master himself
and the world around him is so strong that today some fear that it
may even lead him along the road to destruction.
This issue of the Unesco Courier looks at the processes ofhuman
adaptation and endurance as they are revealed in a number of
extreme and potentially dangerous situations. A medical doctor
describes his gruelling experiences during a solo expedition to the
North Pole on skis, while another scientist presents some of the
findings of his extraordinary experiments in long-term
confinement underground, cut off from the rhythms of the solar
day. Other articles examine the ways in which space voyagers deal
with weightlessness; the mechanisms of adjustment to high
altitudes; adaptation to conditions in deserts and tropical forests,
to life on and under the sea, and to the wear and tear of everyday
existence in the modern world. Finally we evoke the phenomenal
exploits of a Norwegian long-distance runner who a century and a
half ago ran across Europe and parts of Asia and Africa at a rate of
around 150 km a day.
Survival
Human adaptation to extreme conditions
by Felix Z. Meerson
8
It's tough at the top
Life at high altitude
by Gerardo Antesena, Mario Paz-Zamora
and Enrique Vargas
12
Travelling light
Coping with weightlessness in space
by Oleg G. Gazenko
14
The time of our lives
Subterranean experiments on the rhythms
imposed by the solar day
by Michel Siffre
16
The desert as a way of life
by Hamidou A. Sidikou
20
Hunter-gatherers of the tropical forest
by Laurentiu Palade
23
The sea within us
by Dan Behrman
27
Stress in the modern world
by Lennart Levi
30
Solo to the Pole
Interview with Jean-Louis Etienne
33
Marathon Man
by Bredo Berntsen
A time to live...
LESOTHO: Volunteer roadworkers
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
Cover: Caravan in the Sahara (Mauritania).
Photo ©MaximilienBruggmann, Yverdon,
Switzerland
The Courier
A window open on the world
Published monthly in 33 languages
by Unesco
The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
English Italian Turkish Macedonian Finnish A selection in Braille is
French
Spanish
Hindi
Tamil
Urdu
Catalan
Serbo-Croat
Slovene
Swedish
Basque
published quarterly in English.
French, Spanish and Korean
Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese Thai
German Persian Korean Bulgarian Vietnamese
Arabic
Japanese
Dutch
Portuguese
Swahili
Croato-Serb
Greek
Sinhala
ISSN 0041-5278
N°6-1987-CPD-87-l-'i46 A
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
SURVIVAL
Human adaptation
to extreme conditions
by FelixZ. Meerson
ADAPTATION, in human beings
and in animals, is a process
whereby the organism gradually
acquires resistance to certain factors in its
environment and consequently the
capacity to live in conditions previously
incompatible with life, and to solve pre¬
viously unsolved problems.
"To live in conditions previously
incompatible with life" can mean com¬
plete adaptation, allowing a wide range
of physical and intellectual activity as well
as the perpetuation of the species in con¬
ditions of polar cold, desert heat or short¬
age of oxygen at high altitudes, just as it
can mean a far from complete adaptation
which permits only survival for a more or
less extended period.
Likewise, "to solve previously
unsolved problems" includes resolution
of elementary problems, such as how to
avoid attacks by predators by standing
stock still a passive defence reflex or
of more complex ones, such as travelling
in space or controlling the life processes
of the organism.
All these adaptive mechanisms have
one feature in common: although in the
initial phase of adaptation to any new
factor the organism is close to the limits of
its capacities, the manner in which it
solves the problem is far from perfect.
However, if the person or animal con¬
cerned survives, and the causal agent of
adaptation continues to be active, the
possibilities open to the organism
increase and the extreme or urgent stage
is replaced by one of effective, stable
adaptation.
This transformation is the crucial
moment in the whole process, and it often
has' remarkable consequences, as in the
case of the experiments carried out by a
Peruvian scientist who "lifted" in a pres¬
surized chamber a group of people, some
of whom were already adapted to high
altitudes while others were not. When the
pressure was equivalent to that at an alti¬
tude of 7,000 metres the novices lost con¬
sciousness, while the others continued
playing chess.
Similarly, a healthy but untrained per¬
son can run a few hundred metres at the
most without stopping to rest, whereas a
trained runner can cover more than 40
kilometres. The cold weather which hit
Western Europe in the winter of 1986-87
had catastrophic effects in some countries
and caused a number of deaths. During
the same period in Verkhoyansk, a town
in eastern Siberia and one of the coldest
places on Earth, eight- to nine-year-old
children continued going to school in
temperatures of -57 °C and herds of
thoroughbred horses grazed as usual,
watched over by their herdsmen.
In the field of intellectual activity,
where adaptive reactions are qual¬
itatively more complex, the transition
from the stage of extreme tension to that
of stable adaptation is manifested in an
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
In 1984 a group of walkers crossed a part
of the Kara-Kum desert in the Turkmen
S.S.R. during a Soviet experiment on life in
desert regions. The walkers were not
allowed to drink water during this
endurance test, which was closely
monitored by doctors. Right, a doctor
examines two walkers during a rest
period.
In 1979, a seven-man Soviet expedition
reached the North Pole after a 1,500 km
trek on skis across drifting ice. The expedi¬
tion, which took two and a half months,
made a notable contribution to knowledge
about life in Arctic regions (see the Unesco
Courier, January 1980). A ceremony (be¬
low) was organized at the Pole to celebrate
the achievement.
'*tri i
equally striking manner. This transfor¬
mation of an unadapted organism into an
adapted one is well known, and has been
described in detail.
Two interrelated series of phenomena
develop in the organism faced with a new
situation. In the first series there is a rapid
development in the function of the sys¬
tem most directly concerned in the adap¬
tation process, for example the organs of
movement, blood circulation or respira¬
tion when a physical effort is involved, or
specialized parts of the brain during train¬
ing and acquisition of new skills. The cells
react by increasing the synthesis of
nucleic acids and proteins, and a selective
development of the structures limiting
the function occurs. Thus, during adapta¬
tion to altitude or physical effort, the cor¬
onary arteries expand and there is a two
to threefold increase in the number of
"power stations" (mitochondria) in the
skeletal muscles. As a result, a series of
changes takes place in the cells of the
dominant system, that on which adapta¬
tion depends, which increases the phys¬
iological capacity of the system and forms
the material basis for the transition from
an extreme stage to genuine adapta¬
tion.
The second series of phenomena is the
well-known stress reaction discovered by
the Canadian biologist Hans Selye, which
he called "general adaptation syn¬
drome". It is now known that the stress
reaction manifested by the secretion of
adrenal hormones into the blood not only
mobilizes the organism's energy and
structural resources, but also ensures
their transfer from inactive systems to the
dominant system. In other words, the
reaction allows the vitally important
problem created by the environment to
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
be solved. When adaptation has been
achieved and the individual has become
accustomed to the cold, or learned to
solve mathematical problems or to play
the piano, the stress reaction disappears.
Adaptation to other physical or chemical
factors in the environment takes place in
the same way (e.g., gradual habituation
to increasing doses of poison).
Afterwards the organism can no longer
be damaged by the external factor to
which it has become adapted. It is
remarkable that the multiple reactions
set off by the process of adaptation to one
environmental factor frequently contain
components which heighten resistance to
other factors. Thus adaptation to an
insufficiency of oxygen strengthens the
organism's resistance to physical effort,
hallucinogens, epileptogens, factors pro¬
ducing high blood pressure, stress
damage to the heart, ischaemia (interrup¬
tion of the blood supply to an organ or
tissue), and even to ionizing radiation.
This opens up vast possibilities for the
utilization of adaptation in the preven¬
tion and treatment of diseases. Nowa¬
days, when extensive use and in some
cases abuse of medicines creates a real
possibility of dependence on them, it
would be useful to have doctors pre¬
scribe, not only medicines, but adapta¬
tion to a complex of individually selected
factors.
It is now known that external stress can
provoke or speed up the development of
gastric and duodenal ulcers, high blood
pressure, arteriosclerosis, ischaemic
heart ailments, diabetes, mental disor¬
ders, skin troubles and as has been
shown recently tumours.
Below, Soviet divers study the diffusion of
light underwater, during research in the
Indian Ocean conducted by the Marine
Biology Institute of the USSR Academy of
Sciences Centre for the Far East.
"
m
* -^*v-»v*~*>
«-«
w y
v
However, the role of stress in certain
pathological conditions is now so well
known that it may obscure the important
fact that most human beings and animals,
placed in extreme conditions from which
there is no escape, do not die but acquire
some degree of resistance which allows
them to survive until better times. Such
situations prolonged periods of hunger,
cold, natural catastrophes, interspecific
and intraspecific conflicts still occur
widely among animals in their natural
habitat.
More complex stress situations occur
just as frequently in human society. Dur¬
ing a relatively short historical era man
has survived periods of slavery, serfdom
and world war in such a way as to prove
the efficiency of his powers of adaptation .
Of course, the price of this adaptation has
been unjustifiably high, but these indis¬
putable facts inevitably lead to the con¬
clusion that the human organism must be
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
* -fc » "
»_ * * . ~*
endowed with efficient specialized mech¬
anisms that limit the reaction to stress and
prevent stress damage.
Research carried out in the last decade
has confirmed the existence of these
stress-inhibiting mechanisms. It has been
shown that under pressure from extreme
tensions, the stress reaction is accom¬
panied by intensified activity of the cen¬
tral stress-inhibiting systems. One exam¬
ple is the increased production in the
brain of morphine-like opiate peptides
and other substances which limit the
stress reaction. These substances
accumulate in the brain and neutralize
the stress-inducing excitation of the
nerve-centres.
The activity Of the stress inhibitors also
intensifies in the other organs, where sub¬
stances accumulate that limit the action
of stress hormones on the cells and pre¬
vent stress damage. The dual activity of
central and local stress inhibitors protects
the organism from gastric ulcers, heart
damage , impairment of immune systems ,
arrhythmia, and injury caused by chemi¬
cal factors.
These facts generally correspond to
what can be observed in everyday life.
People who have experienced terrible
ordeals acquire a certain resistance to the
wear and tear of life. Moreover, the pos¬
sibility can now be envisaged of employ¬
ing substances produced by stress-
inhibiting centres, equivalent substances
produced by synthesis, and the chemical
activators of such inhibiting systems, as
substitutes for the natural mechanisms of
adaptation, in order to protect the organ¬
ism from stress and other forms of
damage. This theory, now largely con¬
firmed by experiment, opens up highly
promising prospects for the prevention
and treatment of non-infectious diseases.
The little town of Verkhoyansk in eastern
Siberia (Yakut Autonomous S.S.R.) is one
of the coldest places on Earth. Common
winter temperatures of -60°C do not dis¬
turb the tenor of life. A hardy local breed of
horses Is raised on a Verkhoyansk farm,
above.
FELIX ZALMANOVICH MEERSON, Soviet
specialist in pathology, is president of the Spe¬
cialized Commission on the Pathophysiology of
Adaptation Processes attached to the Scientific
Council of the USSR Academy of Medicine. A
World Health Organization (WHO) expert and a
member of the editorial boards of several inter¬
national science journals, he is the author of 14
monographs, some of which have also been
published in the USA, the Fed. Rep. of Germany
and in Japan, and is co-editor-in-chief with Aca¬
demician Oleg G. Gazenko ofThe Physiology of
Adaptation Processes (1986). He was awarded
the USSR State Prize in 1978.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Suspension bridge over the river
Apurimac in the eastern cordillera (Peru)
was made of plaited grass using tech¬
niques known to the Incas. It is rebuilt
every year.
IT'S
by Gerardo Antesena,
Mario Paz-Zamora
and Enrique Vargas
T
|HE overwhelming majority of the
world's population live between
sea level and an altitude of 3,000
metres. Only some 15 million persons live
in permanent settlements between that
level and 4,800 metres, mainly on the
high plateaux of the Andes in South
America, and of Tibet in Central Asia.
Altitude inevitably imposes constraints
on people who live in these regions. In the
first century AD, Pan Kou, a Chinese
historian, described in these terms the
Karakoram mountain range in Central
Asia: "It is necessary to cross two moun¬
tains, one large and one small, which
make the head ache. The earth lies naked
there, on the scorching slopes, and the
human body loses its colour because of
the heat; the torrid sun causes headaches
and nausea, and it has the same effect on
animals ..."
Father José de Acosta, a Jesuit mis¬
sionary to the New World, describes
acute mountain sickness in his treatise
Historia natural y moral de las Indias
(1590; Natural and Moral History of the
Indies, 1604), and relates it to the fact that
at such altitudes "the air is so subtle and
so refined that it is unsuited to human
respiration, which needs air that is
thicker and more temperate ..."
What exactly is meant by the term alti¬
tude? Altitude in the sense of environ¬
ment consists of a number of physical fac¬
tors, principally the lowering of
barometric pressure1 and therefore of the
partial pressures2 of respiratory gases , the
wide range of variation in day and night
temperatures, increased solar radiation
and a greater incidence of high-energy
heavy particles in the atmosphere.
The lowering of barometric pressure is
by far the most important factor as far as
man is concerned, arid it is an unavoida¬
ble constraint to which technology has
found no practical long-term solution.
Consequently, the values of the partial
1. Atmospheric pressure as indicated by a barometer,
usually of mercury, and expressed in several different
systems of units, such as pounds per square inch, or
millimetres of mercury.
2. The pressure that a gas, in a mixture of gases, would
exert if it alone occupied the whole volume occupied by
the mixture.
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
TOUGH AT THE TOP
Life at high altitude
pressure of respiratory gases, especially
that of oxygen in the arterial blood, are
usually taken as the basis for determining
the physiological limits of altitude.
"Physiological" altitude therefore does
not correspond to physical altitude. On
the one hand, the fall in atmospheric
pressure is not directly proportional to
height above sea level; on the other, the
oxygen content of the blood is not a sim¬
ple function of the partial pressure of oxy¬
gen in the air. Three levels can be dis¬
tinguished, according to the value of the
partial pressure of oxygen in arterial
blood:
- above 70 millimetres of mercury,
changes in the partial pressure of oxygen
(i.e. in altitude) have little effect on the
amount of oxygen contained in the blood .
(The normal arterial blood pressure at
sea level is 90 millimetres of mercury.);
- between 70 and 40 millimetres of merc¬
ury, the effect of the fall in the partial
pressure of oxygen becomes more
noticeable;
- below 40 millimetres of mercury, the
oxygen content of the blood falls consid¬
erably and more or less constantly with
small changes in the partial pressure of
oxygen.
Altitudes of less than 3,300 metres cor¬
respond to the first level; there are no
significant effects on the oxygen trans¬
porting function of the blood.
The Ourou Indians live in floating settle¬
ments on Lake Titicaca, one of the world's
biggest mountain lakes (8,340 km', alti¬
tude 3,812 m), on the border of Peru and
Bolivia. Above, a group ofOurou Indians in
their boats made of bundled reeds.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
«UI
S**- ft **
' ".WfV-
»Mi
Harvest scene In the Dolpo Valley (Nepal),
4,000 m up in the Himalayas. Barley is the
only cereal grown in the valley.
It is impossible for man to live perma¬
nently at the third level above 5,500
metres.
Altitude, in the physiological sense of
the term, thus corresponds to a level of
between 3,300 and 5,500 metres (a baro¬
metric pressure of between 500 and 370
millimetres of mercury).
The main problem for the human
organism in such an environment con¬
sequently lies in transferring oxygen from
the atmosphere to the cells.
Like the higher animals, man has two
active transfer mechanisms: the respira¬
tory system, and the circulatory system
which distributes to the various tissues
the oxygen bonded to the haemoglobin in
the blood. At an altitude of over 3,500
metres the partial pressure of oxygen in
the air is insufficient to saturate the
haemoglobin. Respiration and circula¬
tion rates are therefore the most
affected.
People living at high altitudes have
more red corpuscles and more
haemoglobin circulating in their blood,
and this makes up for the fall in the partial
pressure of oxygen. This increase in red
corpuscles at high altitudes allows the
cardiac output to return to, or sustain, its
sea level value. These two responses,
greater cardiac output and an increase- in
the number of red corpuscles, have the
same purpose: to convey to the tissues the
oxygen they need, despite its rarefaction
in the atmosphere. The first is an immedi¬
ate functional response; the second is
more adaptive and takes over from the
first.
Reduced barometric pressure is not the
only constraint due to altitude; cold is
usually an associated factor. Some phys¬
iological responses to cold, such as
decreased circulation to the skin, are
also among the responses to altitude
hypoxia.3
Man is thus not naturally suited to life
at high altitudes; all the regulatory and
control mechanisms of the human organ¬
ism work in accordance with sea level
conditions. However, in temperate and
tropical regions people live at heights
where the barometric pressure is close to
half that of sea level, and most of the
body's functions have adjusted accord¬
ingly.
People have travelled through and
lived in high altitude regions since ancient
times. They have served as places of
refuge or as extensions of land used for
stock-rearing, for example. The inhabi¬
tants have adapted physiologically to
these exceptional living conditions, but
they depend for subsistence on the poor
pasture land which feeds the animals they
3. Deficiency in the amount of oxygen delivered to the
body tissues.
raise, and they are always at the mercy of
a severe winter which could decimate
their beasts. They also rely on the water
supply from glaciers to irrigate their
fields.
The people who live in the high
plateaux of South America or Central
Asia lead an active life as farmers and
herdsmen. Their extensive empirical
knowledge of the soil and climatic condi¬
tions has enabled them to create a highly
efficient system of terraced irrigation and
cultivation. They follow a sowing time¬
table which ensures that crops can be har¬
vested in the minimum of time, and they
know how to cross-breed animals to
increase their resistance and how to store
food as a precaution against irregular har¬
vests. The growing of cereals and the rais¬
ing of animals are closely interdepen¬
dent, for intensive agriculture is only
possible if manure is available.
The Andean peoples grow potatoes,
maize (corn), fava beans and quinoa (a
plant of the Chenopodium family) and
raise llamas and vicunas. They use the
wool and meat of another camelid, the
alpaca, as well as its skin and its fat, which
is thought to have therapeutic powers.
The breeding of these animals and of
oxen and sheep, which were introduced
in the sixteenth century, is their main live¬
lihood: a herd of 200 animals is needed to
maintain a family of six.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Several centuries of exploitation of
mineral resources have led some peoples
to settle at altitudes of around 4,800
metres at the Chorolque mine in
Bolivia, for example. In Central Asia,
the farmers who live in the southernmost
and easternmost valleys of Tibet grow
barley, peas and, more recently, potatoes
on irrigated land. They also raise oxen
and sheep.
Nomadic tent-dwelling herdsmen in
these regions live entirely by stock-rear¬
ing. In the main they breed animals such
as yaks, sheep, goats and horses, which
are well suited to the conditions. The yak
provides them with milk, from which they
make butter and cheese, as well as meat,
skins and hair; it is also used as a beast of
burden. These nomads control the
greater part of the transport and trade in
salt, bartered for grain from the lower-
lying valleys.
In order to obtain food and survive at
high altitudes, the inhabitants of the
Andean and the Central Asian mountain
ranges have developed production sys
tems designed to subjugate nature,
reduce risk, and make the most of avail¬
able resources (in the case of the Andes,
by making the maximum use of the ecolo¬
gical zones at different altitudes). Their
aim is to take from the environment all
that is necessary to meet their needs, at
the same time eliminating or reducing cli¬
matic risks. This is a basic feature of the
relationship between high mountain
societies and their environment, and it is
to be seen not only in agriculture and
stock-rearing, but in all the other
activities of their life the procurement
of food, shelter and a dwelling-place.
The very wide range of individual reac¬
tions suggests that altitude may have had
a selection pressure on peoples living per¬
manently in high-altitude regions, and
that throughout the generations such
selection may have favoured people who
were better suited to develop favourable
responses and, even more, to reduce
those responses likely to prove
unfavourable.
GERARDO ANTESENA, MARIO PAZ-
ZAMORA and ENRIQUE VARGAS, of Bolivia,
are directors of research on the high-altitude
physiologyandpathology ofman in the Andes, at
the Bolivian Institute of High-Altitude Biology
(IBBA) of the Major San Andres University, La
Paz. These studies are also carried out at the
high-altitude stations of Potosí (4,200 m),
Chorolque (4,800 m) and in the lowlands at
Santa Cruz (400 m).
Entrance shaft of the "Siglo XX" tin mine,
part of Bolivia's most important mining
complex. The Bolivian writer Sergio
Almaraz Paz has written of this mining
region, over 4,000 m up In the Bolivian
Highlands or Altiplano, "There is no
colour; nature is clad in grey. Contaminat¬
ing the belly of the earth, the ore has trans¬
formed it into a desert. "
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
TRAVEUmG__LIGHT
Coping with weightlessness in space
by Oleg G. Gazenko
IT is just over a quarter of a century
since man first ventured into space.
An assessment of the achievements
of astronautics so far indicates that man
now,has a firm foothold in the realm of
space travel and that the human factor
will be decisive in the conquest of outer
space.
Today systematic study is being made
of all aspects of the Universe, with pri¬
ority being given to the exploration of the
Earth from space and to the use of space
technology to solve many of the problems
of our planet.
Every space flight makes an important
contribution to this enterprise, furthering
the study of the Earth's natural resources
and of the world ocean, the application of
new technologies and the development of
new products (especially pharmaceutical
compounds and biological substances
which are difficult or impossible to ob¬
tain on Earth because of the effects of
gravity) and the monitoring of the
environment.
Cosmonauts are remaining in space for.
longer and longer periods and are
required to perform increasingly numer¬
ous and complex tasks, including man¬
oeuvres outside their spacecraft, which
call for continual progress in medical
research to ensure that space travellers
remain healthy and capable of working at
full capacity.
Already, the findings of such research
have opened up new perspectives on the
workings of the human organism, leading
notably to a greater understanding of the
general laws governing adaptation to the
environment, and above all adaptation to
such an unusual condition as weightless¬
ness, which man does not experience on
Earth.
Throughout its long evolution the
human body has never had occasion to
make use of mechanisms capable of com¬
pensating for absence of gravity. On the
contrary, the whole evolutionary process
has been to fight against the force of grav¬
ity, in order to survive in the continual
heaviness imposed by the Earth's gravita¬
tional pull. Gravity influenced the
development of the structures and func¬
tions of the cardio-vascular system, the
motor system and the central nervous
system.
The degree of adjustment that we have
attained, which makes us human, is thus a
logical development, and the individual
in the course of his life is capable of refin¬
ing and improving that adaptation, just as
he can lose it, at least in part, usually
through ageing or illness. However it has
been observed that this can also happen
to young, healthy subjects when they
travel in space and experience weight¬
lessness.
Before the first manned space flight,
some scientists claimed that man would
be incapable of working in a state of
weightlessness. They even went so far as
to declare that a normal human being
would be psychologically unable to cope
with the state of weightlessness and the
cosmic void. The space flight of Yury
Gagarin resoundingly disproved these
pessimistic predictions and, by showing
On board the U.S. Space Shuttle Columbia, gjl
The astronaut at left tries out a sleeping @|
bag, while another, right, equipped with g-
suction cups on the soles of his shoes, ^
floats with two cameras in a state of |
weightlessness. è
that human beings can indeed journey
through space, flung open the gateway to
the stars.
How does weightlessness influence the
human organism? What changes does it
produce, and what shocks can it cause
against which preventive measures
should be taken?
Weightlessness first of all produces a
sensation of disequilibrium and of float¬
ing, due to a disruption in the normal
functioning of sense organs such as the
vestibular apparatus of the inner ear,
sight, touch and muscle awareness. The
cosmonaut has the impression of flying
upside down or falling. Sometimes this is
accompanied by disagreeable and very
uncomfortable sensations of giddiness,
weakness or nausea. The form and dura¬
tion of these symptoms vary greatly from
one individual to another. On more than
200 space flights, two-thirds of the sub¬
jects experienced them to some extent,
lasting for periods ranging from a few
hours to several days. Subsequently the
symptoms wear off, only to reappear, as a
rule, for the first few hours or days after
returning to the Earth's gravitational
field.
The absence of gravity subjects the car-
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
dio-vascular system to a redistribution of
the total amount of blood in the body:
instead of accumulating in the lower part
of the body, the blood tends to rise into
the thoracic and cephalic regions. This
modifies the regulation of the heart and
the metabolism of the cardiac muscle,
which gradually weakens, and also causes
a loss of tone and elasticity in the veins of
the legs. If this state is prolonged, the
absence of blood pressure causes a deteri¬
oration in the reactions of the cardio-vas-
cular system to physical effort or to move¬
ment, and it starts to "run down".
As the influence of weightlessness con¬
tinues, other forms of reaction emerge,
owing to the lack of demands made on the
bones and muscles. Indeed, without grav¬
ity, no effort is required to move around
inside the space station or to shift objects
from one place to another. A gradual
functional atrophy of the muscles occurs,
starting with those which are used to com¬
bat gravity, hold certain positions and
compensate for the Earth's gravitational
pull during movement. This leads to a
partial wastage of the muscle mass,
especially the muscles of the legs and
back.
Decalcification of bone tissue occurs
through loss of calcium salts and phos¬
phorus, but this has never reached alarm¬
ing levels, even on the longest space
flights. However, if effective measures
are not taken, decalcification could
become a serious obstacle to longer man¬
ned space flights.
These phenomena and other phys¬
iological reactions to weightlessness are
primarily functional and do not constitute
a threat to cosmonauts' health.
Furthermore, it is abundantly clear
that human adaptation to the state of
weightlessness signifies, to some extent, a
loss of adaptation to the conditions of life
on Earth. A rather singular situation then
arises: the more complete the adaptation
to weightlessness, the more difficult is the
process of .readaptation after re-entry.
All cosmonauts who have spent time in
orbit are familiar with this experience.
How far this process can be a threat to
their health is difficult to determine.
Adequate scientific evidence is lacking to
enable a valid judgement to be made,
since for all space flights lasting more
than three weeks various methods have
been used to protect the cosmonauts
from the negative influence of weight¬
lessness.
In view of the increasing duration of
space flights, doctors have been obliged
to devise ways and means of counteract¬
ing too great an adaptation to weightless¬
ness, in order to ensure that the mecha¬
nisms indispensable to life governed by
the Earth's gravitational field continue to
function effectively. It has been neces¬
sary to prevent the body's systems from
"forgetting" their terrestrial vocation and
to "remind" them of their, role on
Earth.
These measures include, first and fore¬
most, physical training on bicycles and
moving running-tracks to tone up the
muscles. During long space flights, cos¬
monauts walk approximately 5 kilo¬
metres a day, and cycle for some 10 kilo¬
metres. The amount of exercise depends
on the day in the training cycle, the dura¬
tion of the flight and the individual
characteristics of the body. Additional
exercises using extensors and other
apparatus can also be carried out if
necessary.
To prevent circulatory disorders, the
cosmonauts have to exercise while nega¬
tive pressure is applied to the lower part
of the body. They put on a special gar
ment like a pair of baggy trousers made of
stretch fabric, in which a vacuum pump
establishes a permanent degree of nega¬
tive pressure. As a result the blood flows
into the lower parts of the body, where
the blood pressure rises to the same level
as on Earth. This stimulates circulation in
the legs and prevents reduction of the
ability to stand upright which tends to
affect cosmonauts returning to Earth.
During the last few days of the flight
the cosmonauts take in salt-water solu¬
tions, causing fluid retention and an
increase in the volume of blood. This also
makes it easier for them to maintain an
upright stance on their return. Another
very important preventive measure is to
add an extra ration of vitamins and trace
elements to the diet.
In the future, recourse will very proba¬
bly be had to artificial gravity, but this is a
complex problem which calls for very
careful study, through experiments both
on Earth and in space.
Above, two cosmonauts take a shower on
board the orbiting Soviet space station
Salyut 7.
Left, a cosmonaut (foreground) works out
on an ergometric bicycle in the Soviet
space station Salyut 7. This type of exer¬
cise is vital to enable the body to readapt
to Earth's gravity after a time spent in
space.
Much is now known about the body's
reactions to weightlessness, and how
these reactions come about is largely
understood. The general impression is
that man is capable of adapting satisfac¬
torily to a prolonged state of weightless¬
ness, then of re-adapting to gravity and
smoothly returning to a normal and use¬
ful life on Earth.
However, since human health and
safety are at stake, it is important to
assess each new step in space exploration
with meticulous accuracy, and to pay the
closest possible attention to the smallest
details in the growing store of experience.
Nothing must be overlooked, from the
remote consequences of space flights
already undertaken to the difficulties and
complications likely to be faced on future
flights. Science, especially biological and
medical research in space, has a long way
to go in order to perfect knowledge of
Man and the Universe and penetrate the
complexities of the interaction between
the two, thereby helping to achieve a har¬
monious relationship.
OLEG GEORGIEVICH GAZENKO, Soviet sci¬
entist, is director of the Institute of Medical and
Biological Problems and president of the Soviet
I. P. Pavlov Society. He is an active member of
the Academy of Sciences of the USSR and of the
"Man in Space Studies" Committee of the Inter¬
national Academy ofAstronautics. The author of
over 200 scientific studies, he was Soviet editor
of a Soviet/U.S. publication, Foundations of
Space Biology and Medicine (7975, in Russian
and English). He was a recipient of the USSR
State Prize in 1978 and the Guggenheim Inter¬
national Astronautics Award in 1975.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Subterranean experiments on the rhythms imposed by the solar day
PHYSIOLOGISTS since the time of
Hippocrates and probably even ear¬
lier have demonstrated the impor¬
tant ways in which man is conditioned by
environmental rhythms, especially the
twenty-four-hour alternation of night and
day.
In man, as in other animals and plants,
rhythmic variations in a whole range of
physiological functions alternation be¬
tween sleep and waking activity, formation
of glycogen (animal starch) in the liver,
temperature change, metabolism, for
example occur regularly every twenty-
four hours.
Known as "circadian rhythms" (from the
Latin circa: "about", and dies: "day"),
these more or less independent or inter¬
dependent rhythmic variations, operating
throughout the day/night cycle, constitute
the mechanism that is termed man's "bio¬
logical clock".
These circadian rhythms are of consid¬
erable importance. If they are interrupted
or too rapidly or abruptly thrown out of
phase, serious physical and psychological
troubles can result. It is common knowl¬
edge that total deprivation of sleep over a
period of several days is certain to entail
marked deterioration in mental and physi¬
cal performance. After an east/west or west/
east flight of only a few hours it may take a
passenger's rectal temperature rhythm as
long as fifteen days to adapt to the appropri¬
ate rhythm of the new local time.
It is generally held that, under normal
conditions on earth, environmental factors,
and especially the alternation of night and
day, act as phase-setters or synchronizers
which maintain the coincidence between
human circadian rhythms and the local
twenty-four-hour time scale. What,
however, would happen to our biological
rhythms, to the bundle of nerve cells whose
precise location in the brain is now being
established and which register the periodic
signals of the environment, were those sig¬
nals to be suppressed?
Botanists and biologists have known for a
long time that cycles of about twenty-four
hours continue in many plants and animals
even when they are kept either in total
obscurity or in continuous light. However,
concentrated research on the adaptation of
the human organism to an aperiodic
environment, that is to say to an environ¬
ment in which the normal phase setters or
synchronizers are lacking, only began in
earnest in 1962.
The three main situations in which these
conditions apply are those in which people
find themselves living for long periods in
space, underground or under water. Would
the human organism continue to show evi¬
dence of regulation by circadian rhythms
once deprived of the environmental syn¬
chronizers it had known throughout the mil¬
lions of years of human evolution? Are
there, in fact, other rhythms specific to the
human organism?
This was the crux of my long-term experi¬
ments, deep iq an underground cave, which
have added to our knowledge of how man
adapts to a timeless, aperiodic environ¬
ment. These experiments have shown how
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Left, Michel Siffre's subterranean camp in
Midnight Cave (Texas). The ergometric
bicycle enabled him to study heart fatigue
patterns during his confinement.
complex that adaptation is and how much it
varies from individual to individual, and
have afforded a better understanding of the
mechanism of human circadian rhythms.
Without synchronizers, without time
"landmarks", whether natural (alternation
of day and night) or artificial (clocks or
watches), each individual's internal
rhythms appear to be, but in fact are not,
synchronized with the rhythms of local
times on Earth.
The most important findings concern two
distinct fields of interest the evolution of
the sleeping/waking cycle and of other phys¬
iological functions (such as temperature
and cardiac rhythms), and the internal
structure of sleep itself, which lies within
the field of neurophysiology.
With regard to the sleeping/waking cycle,
all the long-term (two to six months) experi¬
ments I carried out between 1962 and 1972
seem to point in the direction of a lengthen¬
ing of the cycle, that is to say, a lengthening
of the interval between two waking periods
and two sleeping periods. This has been
confirmed by the experiments carried out
by all the other research teams (mainly Ger¬
man, British and American) who have
worked on this problem, even though these
were of shorter duration (about one
month).
Although those who have written on this
subject seem to be agreed on a statistical
average for the sleeping/waking cycle of
around twenty-five hours, this has little sig¬
nificance with regard to the individual. My
long-term experiments have brought out
clearly the multi-faceted nature of a particu¬
lar rhythm and its unreproducibility over a
given period of time. This has been demon¬
strated in spectacular fashion by the fact
that whereas for some individuals the sleep¬
ing/waking cycle changes within a few days
from twenty-four to forty-eight hours
(thirty-four to thirty-six hours of continuous
waking activity and fourteen to twelve
hours of sleep), for others this may not hap¬
pen for several months. A comparison
between my 1962 experiment (when I was
isolated on the underground glacier at
Scarasson in France from 16 July to 17 Sep¬
tember) and my second experiment in 1972
(205 days alone in Midnight Cave, Texas)
shows clearly the unreproducibility of the
sleeping/waking cycle.
A significant outcome of this spon¬
taneous change from a twenty-four-hour to
a forty-eight-hour cycle is that for just a
third more sleep than is normal under
ordinary conditions of life it is possible to
Before descending into Midnight Cave,
where he remained alone, cut off from
the solar day, for 205 days in 1972, the
French speleologist Michel Siffre mea¬
sures his respiration rate in the surface
laboratory.
double the period of waking activity, a very
considerable potential increase in creative
activity, entirely naturally and without hav¬
ing recourse to any form of drug, for a
period of several weeks.
Desynchronization of the circadian
rhythm of sleep and waking activity is paral¬
leled in most of the other physiological
rhythms examined, such as the cardiac
rhythm, the rhythm of the rectal tempera¬
ture, of potassium and of the hydroxycor-
ticosteroid hormones.
I believe that this desynchronization is an
adaptive response by the organism to the
aperiodicity of the environment. This
brings me to the second group of important
findings concerning the structure of sleep in
a timeless situation. We were the first to
undertake such studies which were carried
out in 1966. Under a forty-eight-hour sleep¬
ing/waking cycle the human organism the¬
oretically builds up a sleep deficiency or
debt. The question then arises as to which of
the major stages of sleep (see below) is
reduced to compensate for the abnormal
(thirty-six-hour) period of waking activity.
Progress in this field of research was only
made possible by underground, atemporal
experiments. Previous experiments on
sleep had been carried out within the con¬
text of local time and of a circadian (twenty-
four-hour) sleeping/waking cycle. Con¬
sequently, the natural variations in the vari¬
ous stages of which sleep consists could only
be very limited. The relative proportions of
what is known as REM (Rapid Eye Move¬
ment) sleep and the four other stages of
sleep could only vary minimally around the
mean average, which itself varied according
to the individual concerned and the time of
the year.
However, the spontaneous changes in
periodicity of the sleeping/waking cycle
(cycles of 12, 24, 26, 28, 36, 48, 60 and even
72 hours) occurring within the framework
of my "out of time", aperiodic experiments
revealed the natural evolution of the time
devoted to each stage of sleep, especially to
REM sleep and to what is known as Stage 4
sleep (deep sleep), as a function of total
sleep and in relation to the biological cycles
and the waking period.
In short, the neurophysiological adapta¬
tion of the human organism in an "out of
time" setting is marked by profound modi¬
fications in the internal structure of sleep,
which vary from individual to individual,
and which can be summarized as follows:
Whatever the duration of the sleeping/
waking cycle, the proportion of REM sleep
can be accurately forecast since there is a
precise linear correlation between REM
sleep and total sleep, of which it is a func¬
tion. This phenomenon was observed for
the first time in man during my experiments
underground.
When the period of continuous waking
activity doubles (rising from 16 to 34 or 36
hours), total sleeping time does not double.
However, REM sleep increases in a ratio of
about one to ten to the length of waking
activity.
The change from a circadian to a forty-
eight-hour sleeping/waking rhythm does
not affect the period (some 90 minutes) of
REM sleep, which remains stable.
To conclude this brief survey of the time
factor in human adaptation, it should be
recognized that it is an imperative necessity
for ever more penetrating studies to be car¬
ried out on the desynchronization of circa¬
dian rhythms in order to increase man's vig¬
ilance and operational capacities. The study
of the desynchronization of the biological
clock is all the more essential in that
unavoidable desynchronization creates
fatigue in many situations in modern life
night work (total inversion of the cycle),
work in revolving shifts (continuous and
prolonged desynchronization), east/west
and west/east travel (involving almost con¬
tinuous desynchronization for certain per¬
sonnel), life around airports and other sites
with high sound levels, work in exceptional
surroundings (missile silos, tanks, sub¬
marine-spotting aircraft, nuclear submar¬
ines, spacecraft and space laboratories).
Finally, when the organism is syn¬
chronized (that is to say, when it is subject
to the normal circadian rhythm of twenty-
four hours), the effect of many medicines
varies according to the time of day that they
are taken. Consequently, any change in the
periodicity of the sleeping/waking cycle
(resulting, for example, from an east/west
or west/east jet flight) or of the organism's
other rhythms, could have repercussions on
the action of the medicine, altering or even
reversing its therapeutic effect.
MICHEL SIFFRE, French speleologist, devised
and carried out the first major experiments in
voluntary human confinement. These experi¬
ments, effected in caves in France and the
United States, produced new information relat¬
ing to biological rhythms, psychological time,
sleep and dreams. He is the author of some 50
scientific papers, 8 books and 5 films.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
o
©
The desert as a way of life
by Hamidou A. Sidikou
TO survive in a harsh world man has
no option but to adapt to the
physical and climatic conditions
of his environment. In doing so he must
develop strategies which are often
reflected in salient features of his culture
and society.
The peoples of Niger, and especially
the Tuareg, the Tubu, the Kanuri, the
Guézébida and the Arabs who live in the
difficult conditions that prevail in the arid
and semi-arid regions of the country, are
no exception to this universal rule. Indi¬
vidually and collectively, their way of life
is influenced, if not determined, by the
need to adapt to the rigours of a climate in
which the dominant factors are wide tem¬
perature variations, their duration and
intensity.
Over two-thirds of Niger's total area of
1,267,000 square kilometres consists of
desert and semi-desert zones situated
between latitudes 15° and 23° North. Of
this vast expanse, the Ténéré Desert,
bounded to the west and north-west by
the Air massif and to the north and north¬
east by high plateaux whose southern lim¬
its are marked by impressive cliffs, itself
covers more than 350,000 square kilo¬
metres.
In these climatic zones, a combination
of factors related to rainfall, atmospheric
humidity and seasonal temperature vari¬
ations normally gives rise to four distinct
seasons of varying length.
The rainy season, which lasts from
July-August to September, is short and
irregular. When it does rain, the pre¬
cipitation is often slight, but sudden vio¬
lent storms are a threat to those whose
houses are made of low-quality earth con¬
taining a large proportion of salts which
dissolve rapidly in the wet.
From the end of September to the end
of October there is a short intermediate
season characterized by both a high
atmospheric humidity level and very high
temperatures. This is followed by a dry,
cold season lasting from November to
March when an east wind, the Harmat-
Berber peoples living in Mali, Niger and
other Saharan countries, the Tuareg have
created an original civilization adapted to
the desert and its borderlands. In the
southern parts of the region, nomadic
herding over vast areas is a way of life
conditioned by the arid climate and scar¬
city of water and grassland. Above, a
Tuareg of Niger and his camel.
tan, brings dry mists which are liable to be
transformed into violent sandstorms, and
temperatures fall below zero at night.
Finally, there is a hot dry season which
extends from March to June or July. This
is the season of very great heat, with tem¬
peratures reaching 45CC or more.
The maximum daily temperature
range which is generally experienced at
the beginning and end of the dry season
may be as great as 20°C, while the range
between the absolute minimum and max¬
imum temperatures may even reach
40°C, if not more. An extraordinary
capacity for adaptation is required of
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
peoples subject to such rigorous climatic
conditions. This adaptation is reflected in
every aspect of their lives. The strategies
they adopt are in many cases indissocia¬
ble from the organization of society and
from housing, clothing and diet.
In this setting, human activity is strictly
ruled by the existence of watering places.
Because they are so rare, they have great
economic value and are decisive factors
in the determination of social status.
Three branches of human activity
stock-raising, agriculture and manual
labour appear to be directly deter¬
mined by the harsh climatic conditions.
Stock-raising activities not only fulfil
economic requirements but also meet the
need to adapt to the climate with its great
variations of temperature. Camels and
cattle are the main species raised, pri¬
marily for the production of milk which is
the basic element of the diet. Since cam¬
els are more hardy than cattle, they can
be raised in wide open rangelands and are
able to adapt more easily to variations in
soil composition and grazing vegetation.
The available quantity of milk, which
serves as both food and drink, varies from
season to season, and this is why two com¬
plementary species are chosen for its pro¬
duction. Thus camel's milk, which is
available in adequate quantities during
the hot, dry season, is appreciated both
for its very rich vitamin content and for its
low fat content, characteristics which are
thought to increase endurance and resis¬
tance to hunger. It is also said to have
remarkably beneficial effects on eye¬
sight. The absence or very low proportion
of visually handicapped people among
populations whose diet is based on cam¬
el's milk may be partly due to its high
mineral content.
Camel-herders also engage in trans-
Saharan trading. One reason for this is
the need to reconcile the differing
demands of life in complementary ecolo¬
gical zones. Until it declined following
successive droughts which decimated the
herds and destroyed the vegetation on
which they depended for grazing, the car¬
avan trade, in which tens of thousands of
camels were still involved only a few years
ago, was of more than just economic sig¬
nificance. It was one of many responses
to the particular environmental condi¬
tions and perpetuated a whole way of life
through a wide-ranging network of social
relationships.
Knowledge of the location of watering
places is a key factor in this way of life in
areas where the water supply is a matter
of fundamental and permanent concern.
Agricultural activity is thus limited to the
area around oases where a permanent
supply of water is available. Date-grow¬
ing is the mainstay of this irrigation agri¬
culture adapted to the seasons. Dates,
An Inhabitant of Bilma, a large town in ©
Niger, carries loaves of household salt for s
family consumption. £
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
which are an important item of trade with
the regions to the south, are a source of
food, according to their quality, for both
man and beast.
Manual labour is primarily concerned
with the exploitation of salt and natron.
The latter, a hydrous sodium carbonate,
is an essential element in animal feed
since it meets the animals' salt require¬
ments and also rids them of
intestinal parasites, thus boosting their
milk production.
The concern to adapt diet to environ¬
mental conditions, which always under¬
lies human behaviour, is also apparent in
the unusual, some would say immoder¬
ate, consumption of tea. A beverage that
both quenches thirst and staves off hun¬
ger, tea is served ceremonially. It plays a
part in creating physiological mecha-
Saltpans at Tegguidan-n'Tessoum, Niger.
Salt is produced by solar evaporation of
the brine in each pan. Workers' legs are
covered with ulcers caused by walking
knee deep in the brine.
nisms for adapting to the variations in
temperature.
Dress is another important indication
of adaptation to the environment. The
wearing of the veil and the turban are not
only of social significance (attainment of
adult status, for example), they also serve
to protect the head, and in particular the
eyes, nose and ears against the effects of
low temperatures, the stinging blast of
hot or cold winds and sandstorms. The
wearing of voluminous clothing, usually
made of cotton , is a form of adaptation to
high temperatures.
Finally, housing, its conception, the
materials used in its construction, and the
use made of it in relation to the seasons, is
another important element in adaptation
to climatic conditions. In the Kawar
region of Niger, for example, where, in
past centuries, fortified villages were con¬
structed for security reasons, four main
types of dwellings are found.
Stone houses, the last relics of those
troubled times, are used during the dry,
cold season because they offer better
protection against sharp drops in tem¬
perature.
Finding, transporting and storing water is
a major preoccupation for Saharan
nomads. Right, women of Niger carry
water in gourds, an indication that they
belong to a semi-sedentary village (since
caravaners use water containers made of
goatskin).
During the hot, dry season, houses
constructed of date-palm leaves come
into their own. Cool, airy and well ventil¬
ated, they are divided into rooms desig¬
nated for different functions. A room
reserved for the head of the household
adjoins the entrance; there is a room for
the women and children, a store-room for
food or for animal fodder, a kitchen, and
a living-room in which meals are taken .
Tents, which are made of skins or of
rush matting, vary in size according to the
means of the occupants. They are always
put up on a north-south axis with one or
two openings on the east and west sides to
allow air to circulate and the rays of the
sun to enter. Tents are all-the-year-round
dwellings which can easily be dismantled.
©
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
L ÜL 4 ri^f
-*-
They are set up on top of dunes during the
hot season and in spots protected by
vegetation among the dunes in the cold
season. The tent is the perfect example
of a dwelling fully adapted to the climate.
Straw huts, whose dimensions vary
according to economic considerations
and to the availability of straw, itself
dependent upon rainfall, are used both as
temporary shelters and permanent dwell¬
ings. In the latter case they are used
mainly during the rainy season and in the
hot season since they offer the best pro¬
tection against rain and great heat.
These are some of the strategies
developed by the peoples of Niger who
live in very hot desert areas. Their pur¬
pose is to provide a minimum of comfort
by adaptation to temperature conditions
which remain, throughout the year, a
matter of primordial concern.
HAMIDOUAROUNASIDIKOU.oM/ger./scon-
sultant to several international organizations,
including Unesco, and permanent secretary of
the Committee responsible for developing a
Rural Code for Niger. A geographer, he taught at
the Faculty of Letters, Human Sciences and
Pedagogy of the University of Niamey (1974-
1981), before directing (1981-1985) the Univer¬
sity's Institute of Research in the Human Sci¬
ences.
Loading a camel with its cargo ofsalt in the
sandy plain of Ténéré. Salt is a vital com¬
modity for man and animal in the desert,
where it is still transported by camel car¬
avans and serves as a form of currency.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Hunter-gatherers
of the tropical forest
by Laurentiu Palade
Between 100,000 and200,000 Pygmies live
in equatorial Africa, scattered through the
forest which extends from the Atlantic
Ocean to the great lakes of the east.
Remarkably well adapted to conditions in
the tropical forest, they live byhunting and
gathering. Below, a Uganda Pygmy hunter
with animal hides for use as drumskins.
Beating drums is a form ofcommunication
between isolated groups in the forest.
TROPICAL forests form a green
band around the Equator,
extending roughly 10° North and
South. This means that they account for
only a small proportion, about 8 per cent,
of the Earth's land surface. Yet they com¬
prise almost half of all growing wood on
the face of the planet, and harbour at
least two-fifths of Earth's plant and ani¬
mal species, a genetic resource of increas¬
ing importance to humanity through agri¬
culture, medicine and industry. They also
comprise the most complex and diverse
ecosystems on Earth, which fulfil regula
tory and productive functions that are
essential to man and to his natural
environment.
The question of human adaptation to
conditions in tropical rain forests has
been examined in a number of scientific
studies on groups of hunter-gatherers
such as the Pygmies. The existence of
such peoples is recorded in ancient times.
Representations of them dating back
over 4,000 years are found on ancient
Egyptian bas-reliefs from the tombs of
pharaohs of the Vth Dynasty. They are
mentioned by Homer in the Iliad as well
m
w*£
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Source: Nature and Resources, Unesco, 1 983
Moist, dense, broad-leaf evergreen forests with many epiphytes ("air
plants" growing non-parasitically on trees and other plants and deriving
their nutrients from the air)
i/y- ~: Drier, more open, partially deciduous forests with relatively few
«¿xiia epiphytes
World distribution of tropical forests
as by Herodotus and Aristotle. Yet while
other civilizations have completely disap¬
peared, the Pygmies, living in perfect har¬
mony with their environment, have sur¬
vived the ages.
Pygmies are to be found in most of the
world's tropical forests. They are fairly
numerous; the Ituri Pygmies of Africa,
for example, number some tens of thou¬
sands. Operating in small groups of from
five to thirty-four individuals, they live a
semi-nomadic life adapted to conditions
in the rain forest which are as extreme
and pitiless as those of the cold and inhos¬
pitable Polar regions.
Light penetration of the forest canopy
is minimal. Virtually all ultraviolet rays
are screened out. The accumulated heat
and humidity is so intense that the
atmosphere is like that of a greenhouse.
The average temperature is 28°C, with
variations no greater than from 3°C to
9°C. Average relative humidity is 95 per
cent at night and 60 to 70 per cent during
the day, with only slight seasonal varia¬
tions. Winds are also very light, except
when there is a tornado, and the air is
extremely rich in carbon dioxide and is
laden with scent elements, formic vapour
amd microscopic particles of hair, scales
and fibres. Rapid breakdown and trans¬
formation of organic matter is ensured by
micro-organisms, which teem in the heat
and humidity.
The level of évapotranspiration is very
high three times the average for the
planet as a whole. The forest floor is per¬
manently moist and a protective layer of
branches and leaves is essential should
you wish to lie on it. Ants and termites
abound. Like the flora, the fauna of the
forest is rich and varied. Animal life is
"stratified", with different species living
at different levels. Monkeys and birds live
in the higher levels of the canopy where
conditions are easier and food is more
abundant.
The tropical forest is not very generous
to the people and the larger animals who
live at ground level. Food is difficult to
find and they sometimes have to be con¬
tent with fruit that has been dropped by
monkeys. At night, the large predators
venture out to the open savannah at the
edge of the forest and to river banks and
abandoned cultivated plots. Game con¬
sists mainly of small antelope. At the
same time, the inhabitants of the forest
are under constant threat from insects,
parasites and arboviruses, a group of
viruses that develop in anthropods such
as mosquitoes and are then transmitted
by bites to vertebrate hosts.
One indication of adaptation to forest
life is to be seen in the fact that forest-
dwelling elephant and buffalo are, in gen¬
eral, half the size of their counterparts
living in the savannah. The forest people,
too, weigh less and are shorter than those
who live in open country. A comparative
study undertaken in Africa has shown
that forest-dwellers weigh, on average,
39.8 kilograms and are 1.44 metres tall, as
compared with 62.5 kilograms and 1.69
metres for inhabitants of the savannah. In
comparison with other population
groups, their oxygen consumption during
effort, their pulmonary capacity and their
cardiac rhythm are above average. They
show no signs of protein deficiency or
malnutrition.
Their small stature gives the hunter-
gatherers of the tropical forest a definite
advantage in the form of a relatively high
work capacity under difficult climatic
conditions. A well organized routine,
with major activities carried out early in
the morning or late in the evening, helps
them to avoid excessive perspiration. In
fact, despite the dampness of the
atmosphere, they sweat very little. In
general, they maintain a satisfactory state
of health and, among those who live in a
Pygmies in concert: this man from the
Central African Republic is playing a whis¬
tle cut from a branch of the papaya tree.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Below, a Yanomamo Indian. The
Yanomamo, with a population of over
15,000, live in the luxuriant tropical forests
of Venezuela and Brazil.
forest ecosystem which is still intact,
there is a very low incidence of malaria.
In order to adapt to the constraints of a
life of hunting and gathering in the forest,
the Pygmies, like nomads, have had to
reduce their material possessions to a
minimum. Those they do have are easily
replaced. All they need is a stick to dig
with and a leaf to drink from; a hollow
stem provi Jes a pipe for them to smoke.
As a general rule they manage without
anything that is too heavy to carry, such
as pots and pans and looms. The forest
provides them with liana, bark and
branches with which to built their huts,
make their beds and clothe themselves.
They make strings for their bows and
padding for their shields from raffia fibre.
From the hide of the game they kill they
make belts. They carve traps from roots
and make wicker griddles which, placed
over a fire, enable them to smoke the
flesh of big game. Food is cooked in large
leaves.
Hunting, upon which the survival of
the group depends, is traditionally a male
preserve. It has had a profound effect on
both the individual and the collective
mentality and has forged family and
social structures. The forest is a foster-
mother who must be respected. It is tac¬
itly accepted that no animal should be
killed or tree felled unnecessarily. Game
is usually caught with a net made of inter¬
woven liana and its meat is shared out in
accordance with a strict ritual. Gather¬
ing, which is left to the women, is a com¬
plementary source of food. The produce
of the forest fruit, roots, leaves, mush¬
rooms is abundant. Certain insects,
such as caterpillars and termites, are
gathered, as is honey. The forest also
provides products for bodily care and the
treatment of wounds, sickness and infir¬
mities.
These forest people know their
environment to perfection. Far from
being overwhelmed by their natural sur¬
roundings, they are well organized and
lead an active social life festivities, pal¬
avers, dancing and have a culture rich
in tradition, myth and legend.
The uncontrolled clearing of tropical
forests for agriculture presents the forest-
dwellers with problems of adaptation to
their changing environment and may
expose them to health and other risks.
The pathogenic agents found in a forest
environment attack man more readily in
a cleared area than in an intact forest,
where they concentrate on the primate
and rodent population. An increase in
the incidence of malaria, cardio-vascular
troubles, physiological ailments and
nutritional imbalances has in fact been
noted.
The exploitation of forest regions con¬
stitutes an indispensable economic
development resource in many tropical
countries. In order to achieve a judicious
strategy which respects the natural bal¬
ance, Unesco's Man and the Biosphere
Programme (MAB) is currently engaged
on a project to study the ecological effects
of increasing human activity on tropical
and subtropical forest ecosystems. It is
hoped that this project will help to answer
the many scientific questions raised by
land use planning in the tropics.
LAURENTIU PALADE is a staff member of
Unesco's Division of Ecological Sciences. After
following an academic and scientific career in
Romania, he spent several years in the humid
tropics engaged on a Unesco/World Bank pro¬
ject. The author ofover a hundred scientific stud¬
ies, in 1983 he was awarded the European
Environment Prize by the Goethe Foundation,
Basel, Switzerland.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The sea within us
by Dan Behrman
Traditional method of tuna fishing off the
coast of southern Spain. As the shoals of
fish move from the warm Mediterranean
waters towards the Atlantic the fishermen
trap them in large nets stretched between
their small wooden boats. The giant fish
are then hooked and pulled aboard.
THE sea flows inside us literally.
In our blood as in seawater, the
proportion of dissolved salts is the
same: 3.5 per cent. Like all other forms of
life, we emerged from the sea, yet despite
such links, our attitude towards it is
ambivalent. The sea inspires awe and
fear, it is so unlike the landmasses that we
inhabit. The vastness and solitude we
now associate with outer space have
always been present at sea. Even close to
land, the surf waits to take its toll.
With the ending of the Ice Age 10,000
years ago and the subsequent rise in sea
level, peoples everywhere found them¬
selves driven back by the invading waters.
Peninsulas became islands, the land
bridge between Asia and North America
was swamped and early coastal settle¬
ments drowned on what is today's conti¬
nental shelf. The story of the Flood is
found in cultures worldwide; perhaps dim
memories of the encroaching sea gave
birth to the legend of Atlantis sinking
beneath the waters.
But the ocean gave life as well as taking
life away. Fish were plentiful and easy
game; archaeological finds along the
western coast of Europe include Stone
Age bone fish hooks big enough to catch
deep sea fish. The seine nets, the trolling
gear and the traps devised by the Inuit
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
©
*gM
mittens, for if he slipped, he was a gone
man. All the boats were hoisted in on
deck and there was nothing to be lowered
for him. We had need of every finger God
had given us. . . . Frequently we were obli¬
ged to leave off altogether and take to
beating our hands upon the sail, to keep
them from freezing." Such Olympic
exploits were part of the daily business of
moving passengers and cargo.
Until the end of sail, a seaman's life was
a constant flirtation with death. And
now? Kipling's "call of the off-shore wind
and the voice of the deep-sea rain" can
still be heard, but can it be answered?
Hardly, on the automated tankers and
cargo carriers of today. Noel Mostert,
author oiSupership, describes such a ves¬
sel: "One felt the arid metal acreage
spreading invisibly all around, and its
impact was one of menace: a mechanical
desert of indefinable purpose imposed
upon the sea's own emptiness, and with
forms and shapes that had no reassuring
familiarity; it was filled with wind signs,
not those of masts and rigging but of
abandoned structures upon a plain, and
there was no comfort even from the sea."
Mostert perhaps saw his vessel as a pre¬
cursor of unmanned ships of the future,
sailing under remote control.
There are still those who must seek
the sea fishermen, oceanographers,
divers and they are of a different breed.
The attitudes of small-scale fishermen
have not changed over time. They still
live in small egalitarian communities
where growth is not a goal and informa¬
tion is shared in co-operative net¬
works.
Above, the "Triton", an early breathing
apparatus for divers, named after the son
of the sea god Poseidon. In Greek mythol¬
ogy, Triton lived with his parents in a
golden palace in the depths of the sea.
people of the Arctic in a similar culture
are still used by fishermen today, with
little change in their basic principles.
Attitudes to the sea have been divided
since the earliest times. Some sailed for
trading purposes, endeavouring to spend
as little time on the water as possible and,
at first, to stay within sight of land. They
belonged to the civilizations huddled
around the Mediterranean. Then there
were the sea-peoples, the dwellers on the
ocean, who sought the sea, who returned
to its womb.
They did not shrink from the sea but
embarked upon it in frail coracles or out¬
rigger canoes. And the sea repaid them.
Its waves could be read to indicate the
proximity of land, in the wake of an island
breasting the tidal stream. The skies told
their story by day and by night; there
were nearly always clouds over islands
and mariners set their course by the stars.
Even birds could show in which direction
the land lay, and surf breaking on rocks
over the horizon threw up a telltale haze.
Physical conditions on shipboard in the
days of sail were extremely hard. No one
has described a seaman's life better than
Richard Dana in his narrative Two Years
Before the Mast, published in 1840 and
still a classic. Dana signed on as an ordi¬
nary seaman aboard a vessel bound for
California around Cape Horn, an
unheard-of move for a university gradu¬
ate of good family. In a storm off Cape
Horn, the sailors went aloft to take in the
mainsail : "We had tofist the sail with bare
hands. No one could trust himself to use
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Right, two women aquanauts, a botanist
and a zoologist, carry out an experiment,
on fish behaviour as part of a U.S. marine
research programme on the sea bed. The
scientists lived for two weeks in a 4-room
habitat at a depth of 15 m in the Caribbean
near St. John Island (Virgin Islands).
Left, a diver about to take the plunge from
HMS Tedworth, protected by the cumber¬
some type of diving suit used in the
1930s.
Sociologists observe that fishermen
tend to defer their pleasures and ritualize
their risk-taking behaviour. Risks there
are: the death rate of fishermen is seven
times higher than the average. And they
are a vanishing species, as booming
leisure activities encroach on their
beaches and shellfish beds.
Not all fishing fits these descriptions.
Big trawlers are more like factories, as
William W. Warner points out in Distant
Water: "Not since the great age of whal¬
ing have men stayed at sea for such
protracted periods . . . and no whaler ever,
suffered the continuous and exhausting
work schedules of the modern distant
water fisherman." Despite their size,
these ships fell victim to storms,
especially in winter when they were top
heavy with ice. Adoption of200-mile eco¬
nomic zones shut them out of rich shelf
waters and rendered them obsolete.
Warner sees a future with smaller
medium-range ships such as "autoliners"
that can handle 15,000-hook lines
entirely by machine.
Oceanographers are another variant of
the human species found only at sea: not
only must they survive aboard small ships
but they must do scientific work as well,
collecting data with precision. I once
went out on an Icelandic research ship
and took my turn taking Nansen bottles'
off a wire as they were winched in. All
waste motion had been eliminated from
this series of movements that had to be
repeated tens of times a day, hundreds of
times a voyage. The captain, his big
tousled head stuck out of the port window
of the bridge, made a special effort to
keep the wire within my easy reach. With
the help of propellers and rudder, he
could move his 800 tons of ship literally by
the inch in the empty grey water.
I thought of the oceanographer on this
voyage, Svend Malmberg, reading the
thermometers on his Nansen bottles to an
accuracy of a hundredth of a degree,
when I came across an account of the
contrasting life on board an oil rig 200
kilometres out in the Gulf of Mexico with
four 2,000-horsepower generators roar¬
ing night and day. Crew members worked
seven 12-hour shifts on this platform,
then hoped that bad weather would not
hold up their relief. Drilling for oil is
probably the least nautical of all occupa¬
tions pursued at sea, but it is not neces¬
sarily the safest. Oil rigs cannot run from
a Gulf hurricane or a North Sea storm.
Divers, too, are essential to these cities
on the sea when it comes to finishing up a
wellhead or troubleshooting on the bot¬
tom. One of the oldest of the maritime
trades is here put to good use by one of
the newest. Divers were going down for
pearls in the Babylonia of 4,500 years
ago, using the breathhold technique that
now allows them to stay under for 4 min¬
utes at depths of up to 45 metres (the
record for such diving is 90 metres).
In the nineteenth century, diving suits
fed by compressed air from the surface
were invented, allowing divers to spend
more time on the bottom but bringing in
the danger of the bends, that painful and
potentially fatal condition engendered by
nitrogen bubbles forming in the blood.
Now that man was moving in this totally
alien environment he had to adapt to it,
to the lack of oxygen, to the cold, to the
distortion of vision by water pressure on
the eyes.
He did this with the hard-hat diver's
suit invented in 1819 by a German engi¬
neer, Augustus Siebe, that still left the
diver attached to the surface. Then in
1942, the Frenchmen Jacques Cousteau
and Emile Gagnan came up with their
independent breathing device, the Aqua¬
lung, and the scuba2 diver was born. Here
was a new animal, free-swimming into the
depths.
It was soon apparent that many
psychological and physiological adjust¬
ments had to be made. Nitrogen under
pressure in the divers' air led to "rapture
of the deep" or the so-called "martini
effect" (each 15 metres of depth equals
one dry martini). An oxygen-helium
breathing mixture took care of this but
created new problems: a high-pitched
"Donald Duck" voice and extreme
cold.
Diving tables were developed to show
1. Metal water-sampling bottle equipped with closing
valves and a mercury thermometer to record tempera¬
ture at specified depths.
2. Scuba = self-contained underwater breathing
apparatus
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
how much time was needed in
decompression for a stay at a given depth.
Once a diver is "saturated" at his depth,
the decompression time is the same no
matter how long he stays there. Under¬
standing of this principle led to the first
attempts to colonize the sea floor, the
underwater habitats of the 1960s and the
1970s. Unlike man-in-space missions that
demand rocketry within the capability of
only a few nations, man-in-the-sea
experiments could be carried out by a
number of countries. Among them were
France, the United States, the Soviet
Union, the German Democratic
Republic, the Federal Republic of Ger¬
many, Israel, Poland, Czechoslovakia
and Canada (which set some kind of a
record with an "underwater Volks¬
wagen" costing only $15,000).
The, French were first to develop a
manned underwater station, with Cou-
steau's Conshelf, then the U.S. Sealab
was constructed. All sorts of problems
arose in the habitats. Humidity gave rise
to infections, particularly in the ear, and
wounds were slow to heal. Cooking could
be tricky dough just will not rise in a
high pressure environment and if a can of
fizzy drink is opened the bubbles go
inward. (Some habitats solved all this by
having their meals sent down from the
surface in containers.) Cuisine may not
be all that important, since many aqua-
nauts reported a loss of their sense of
smell and taste.
It has been found that during the first
five days of habitat living, people show
signs of stress which then go away only to
reappear after fifteen days. Life under
the sea is shipboard or submarine life car¬
ried to an extreme. Like space travellers,
aquanauts occasionally resented "ground
control" at the surface with its constant
monitoring of their behaviour. The tele¬
phone could be a hated intruder, con¬
stantly interrupting their routine.
And people had to get on well
together. In one habitat, scientists at first
found themselves at odds with seamen
doing simulated salvage work, but they
ironed out their differences. Everyone
would probably agree with the Soviets
aboard Chernomor, who in 1971 reported
in the newspaper Izvestiya: "The
psychological problems caused by the
confinement of several men together for
long periods of time was of great concern
before the start of the programme . Under
these conditions it is well-known that
men may tend to find fault with each
other, that a man's silence may be taken
for sullenness, a very neat man may be
accused of being fussy. ... There were
some problems aboard the Chernomor
during the first few weeks but soon the
crew came to appreciate the abilities of
the other members and no new problems
arose."
There have been no recent experi¬
ments in underwater living. Instead of
remaining on the bottom, divers can now
be brought to the surface in personnel
transfer capsules and live in pressurized
deck chambers until they go down again.
But there will always be underwater
explorers, just as there were navigators
on the surface. Perhaps they will benefit
from that ultimate transformation, the
invention of an artificial gill through
which the diver's blood will flow and take
up oxygen from the water, as fish do.
Then the age of the sea people will have
truly begun.
DAN BEHRMAN is an American author and
journalist who frequently contributed to the
Unesco Courier during his many years as a
Unesco science writer. He is the author of a
number of books on oceanography including
The New World of the Oceans (Little, Brown and
Co., Boston) and Assault on the Largest
Unknown, The' International Indian Ocean Expe¬
dition 1959-65 (Unesco, 1981).
An engineer makes a tour of inspection
inside one of the legs ofa naturalgas drill¬
ing rig in the North Sea.
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Stress in the modern world
by Lennart Levi
ACCORDING to United Nations
statistics, the world's urban pop¬
ulation has doubled since 1950
and may double again by the end of this
century, by which time three-quarters of
the population of developed countries
and one-third to one half of the popula¬
tion in developing countries will be living
in cities. Current estimates suggest that as
a result of both population growth and
migration, the number of poor people
clustered in slums and shanty-towns is
increasing annually by 10 to 15 per cent.
Conditions in these places are appalling.
The result is tension, depression and vio¬
lence superimposed on physical hardship
and a constant threat of disease.
According to the Athenian statesman
Pericles (495-429 BC), "health is that
state of moral, mental and physical well-
being which enables man to face any crisis
in life with the utmost facility and grace".
This ancient, definition, highlights two
critically important points: firstly that
health concerns man's interaction with
his living conditions, and secondly that he
may lose his capacity to adapt if the life
crisis is severe enough.
Much more recently, this insight has
been echoed in the terms of a Swedish
measure, the Public Health Service Bill
(1984-1985), which declares that "Our
health is determined in large measure by
our living conditions and lifestyle. ..."
The Bill goes on to state that "The health
risks in contemporary society take the
form of, for instance, work, traffic and
living environments that are physically
and socially deficient, unemployment
and the threat of unemployment, abuse
of alcbhol and narcotics, consumption of
tobacco and unsuitable dietary habits, as
well as psychological and social strains
associated with our relationships and
lack of relationships with our fellow
beings."
The Bill strongly advocates what is
called a "holistic approach" to such prob¬
lems and attempts to solve them, mean¬
ing that "people's symptoms and ill¬
nesses, their causes and consequences,
are appraised in both a medical and a
psychological and social perspective".
Bearing this in mind, let us look at some
of these possible "causes" in the human
environment, including some of those in
the world's major cities in developing and
developed countries.
According to recent United Nations
and World Bank statistics, half of the
countries of Africa and southeast Asia,
including four of the five largest, with a
combined population of almost 2,000 mil¬
lion, have an annual median per capita
income of less than $300. This mass pov¬
erty leads to hunger, undernourishment
and malnutrition for vast legions of chil¬
dren in the developing world.
In the worst of cases, children die. In
the "best" of cases, they grow up with
physical and mental disabilities. When
they reach sexual maturity, therefore , it is
even more difficult for them to plan their
families and care for their children, who
then become even more malnourished,
even more disabled, and even less com¬
petent to care for the following genera¬
tion of children. Thus a descending spiral
is created causing morbidity, death and
suffering for hundreds of millions more in
the poor countries of the world.
According to recent UNICEF reports,
in the developing countries 15 million
children die annually before the age of
Poster, right, gives a telephone number of
Switzerland's "Helping Hand" service,
which offers those in despair the solace of
"someone to talk to". The Swiss post
office co-operates by providing the tele¬
phone call free.
Participation in group activities within the
community, above, can be a way of over¬
coming the social isolation which causes
widespread distress in modern cities.
five, most of them because of lack of
potable water, adequate nutrition and
basic hygiene. In many African and some
Latin American countries, plagued by
hunger and shortage of water, this means
almost every other child.
The Food and Agriculture Organiza¬
tion of the United Nations (FAO) and the
World Bank report that at least 430 mil¬
lion human beings are malnourished or
undernourished. In the developing coun¬
tries about 60 per cent of the population
has no access to safe potable water; 75 per
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
cent has no access to basic hygiene
simple latrines, ways to dispose of house¬
hold rubbish, and personal and food
hygiene.
Only 19 per cent of the population of
these countries has access to housing of
acceptable quality. Four out of every five
households live in miserable huts in the
countryside or in shacks made of burlap,
cardboard and sheet metal in the slums of
the large cities. Public health services are
available to less than 15 per cent of the
rural and urban poor.
Such conditions cause acute physical
and psychological and social stress by
creating threats to survival, health and
well-being, to self-esteem, to close
attachment to others, to the sense of
belonging to a valued group. These
threats can in turn provoke potentially
pathogenic reactions leading to further
increases in sickness and mortality
rates.
But causes of psychological and social
stress are also extremely common in
developed countries, in all types of social
and economic systems. In the United
States, for example, 13.7 million children
have unemployed or absent fathers. One
out of three white and three out of five
black children will experience marital dis¬
ruption before reaching the age of six¬
teen. Most of them will grow up in
women-headed families, which are six
times as likely to be below the poverty
level. In 1978, 17 per cent of all children
in the United States under eighteen (11
per cent white, 27 per cent Hispanic, 41
per cent black) lived in poverty, i.e. in
conditions of run-down housing, heavy
traffic, overcrowding, risk of contagion,
accidents, injuries, pollution, violence,
abuse and neglect.
When people are exposed to stress-
inducing conditions of this kind
whether it is a question of lack of control
over their lives, combined with excessive
demands, unsatisfied needs, expectations
that cannot be fulfilled, overstimulation,
or role conflicts most of them experi¬
ence "dysphoric" reactions such as feel-
Above left, an oral health clinic in Thailand. In the developing countries the provision ot
medical treatment, vaccination and safe drinking water is an essential part of a global
approach to environmental health risks which also takes into account other aspects of
the "human ecosystem "such as malnutrition resulting from masspoverty. The Rheuma¬
tic Heart Centre, established at the foot of the Great Pyramids at Giza, above right, came
into being thanks to the initiative of a Cairo voluntary association.
In the developing worldsome 15 mil¬
lion children die annually before the
age of 5, mostly because of lack of
safe drinking water, adequate nutri¬
tion and basic hygiene. Left, Niger
has launcheda community-oriented
nursing programme to improve
child health care. Below, monitoring
the growth ofa toddleratan open-air
clinic in Nicaragua.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
©
£
*
ings of anxiety, depression, uneasiness,
apathy, alienation and hypochondria.
In Sweden, statistics produced by the
National Board of Health and Welfare
(1978) show that every third four-year-
old has mental problems (with symptoms
such as bed-wetting, aggressivity, noctur¬
nal fears). Every third adult suffers from
malaise, sleep disorders, fatigue, dejec¬
tion or anxiety. Every seventh working
person is mentally exhausted at the end of
the working day. Every other man and
three women out of four will suffer from
pronounced mental decompensation
some time in his or her life up to the age of
sixty. Every tenth man has an alcohol
problem. Two thousand people commit
suicide every year, and 20,000 attempt to
do so (in a population of 8.3 million).
Taken together, these figures mean
that approximately every third or fourth
Swede lives a life in which malaise, anx¬
iety, fatigue or dejection is a common
component. Moreover, the situation did
not improve from 1968 to 1974, in spite of
a considerable increase over this period in
material wealth and social security. This
rather alarming picture assumes a further
dimension when related to the ambitious
goals and very considerable material
means of the Swedish welfare state.
According to studies recently sum¬
marized by the World Health Organiza¬
tion (WHO), there are at least 48 million
drug abusers in the world. But this is only
one example of stress-related pathogenic
behaviour. Others include tobacco
dependence, quoted as the primary cause
of one-third of all cases of cancer, 75 per
cent of chronic bronchitis and 25 per cent
of myocardial infarction in the United
States.
As well as reacting emotionally to the
stresses and strains of modern life and
behaving in potentially disease-provok¬
ing ways, we also react physiologically
with our internal organs. Coping with
stress influences basic physiological reac¬
tions in our central nervous system as well
as our ductless (endocrine) glands. The
biologically active agents of the glands,
Air pollution (above) Is only one of many
pressures in modern industrial society
that impose strain on the organism,
adding to the tensions that have always
been part of human life.
Below, for millions of people living in the
slums and squatter settlements of the
great cities of the developing world, life is
primarily a struggle for survival as they
seek to protect themselves from cold,
heat, hunger, disease and dirt. What they
want is decent housing in an environment
which will harm neither their lives nor their
dignity.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
the hormones, together with nervous
impulses, influence virtually every cell in
the organism. If prolonged, pronounced,
or recurrent, such reactions can eventu¬
ally lead to physical ill health.
A WHO report (1986) also mentions
the high prevalence of somatic symptoms
resulting from psychological and social
distress, i.e. in cases with no ascertaina¬
ble organ pathology, or with complaints
of discomfort disproportionate to the
physical problem. This accounts for from
30 to 50 per cent of all consultations in
developed countries and for from 15 to 25
per cent of those coming to the attention
of health care personnel in developing
countries the largest single complaint
category in primary care.
Altogether, the resulting conditions
make for extreme and ever greater suffer¬
ing for over one-quarter of mankind. It is
true that people can adapt even to
extreme environmental influences. Yet,
as indicated above, this adaptation takes
its toll in terms of emotional, behavioural
and/or physiological deformation.
Although a cause-effect relationship is
difficult to prove in specific cases, circum¬
stantial evidence supports the existence
of such a relationship.
In developed and developing countries
alike, governmental action against such
problems is often of a troubleshooting
nature; it addresses only one or a few
specific problems. It may include the
provision of medical treatment, vaccina¬
tion, food shipments, or wells of potable
water. Not infrequently, it takes the form
of acute disaster aid in situations where
disasters are usually chronic. In such
cases, intervention is usually admin¬
istered by one of many specialized agen¬
cies, with no or insufficient co-operation
with other specialized agencies. One
health problem say, ill-health caused by
pollution may therefore be attacked,
while another, such as poverty-induced
undernourishment, is neglected, or vice
versa.
This brief, oversimplified account illus¬
trates the existence of many interacting
and pathogenic factors in the human eco¬
system. If one of its components is influ¬
enced, effects will occur in many of the
others. Consequently, it will probably be
impossible to cope successfully with cur¬
rent and future urban and health prob¬
lems by considering in research,
therapy and/or prevention just one or
two of the components of the total eco¬
system. Success will be more likely if as
many as possible of the critical ones can
be taken into account.
LENNART LEVI, of Sweden, is professor of
psychosocial medicine at the Karolinska
Institutet in Stockholm, where he is chairman of
the Department of Stress Research at the World
Health Organization's Psychosocial Centre. He
is also director of the National Swedish Institute
for Psychosocial Factors and Health (IPM) in
Stockholm. His many publications on stress, .
health andpreventive medicine have been trans¬
lated into several languages.'
Solo to the Pole
An interview with Jean-Louis Etienne
On 11 May 1986, forty-year-old
Jean-Louis Etienne, a French
nutritionist and doctor specializing
in the care of athletes, reached the
North Pole after a solitary hike last¬
ing sixty-three days. Wearing cross¬
country skis and pulling an ultra¬
light sledge, he had covered 750
kilometres in temperatures as low
as -52°C and in winds of up to 100
kilometres an hour. The Unesco
Courier talked to him about his
exploit.
What motivated you to undertake your soli¬
tary walk to the North Pole? Was it the
challenge of a great sporting achievement,
or was it the scientific interest of an experi¬
ment designed to measure the limits of
human resistance in an extreme environ¬
ment?
It was neither. The fact is that such motives
are often advanced to give respectability to
a taste for adventure, a love of open spaces
and the pleasures of discovery. There is
really no need to go such a long way just to
carry out a scientific experiment. It would
be perfectly possible to set up a cold cham¬
ber right here in Paris and live in it for three
weeks, or two months, at a temperature of
-47°C. For me, to go to the North Pole was a
dream, just as earlier I had dreamed of
climbing Mount Everest, rounding Cape
Horn, or sailing round the world. It was also
a human and, above all, a technological
challenge.
What exactly do you mean by that? What
equipment did you take with you?
The North Pole is located in the centre of an
ocean of ice, the Arctic, but it is no skating
rink! The terrain is very uneven. The ice is
cracked, sheets are superimposed on sheets
or collide and compress to form ridges. You
can never see the horizon, and your pro¬
gress is constantly hampered by the ice
which can be completely churned up for
kilometres on end. It is rather as if you
decided to cross Paris in a straight line by
walking across the roof-tops. What is more,
this extremely difficult terrain is only
accessible for about two months of the year,
between the beginning of March, when the
Polar day dawns, and mid-May, when the
ice-pack begins to break up as summer
approaches. It is a real race against time,
and to travel fast you have to travel light. To
equip myself for this undertaking I made
use of materials that have the best low-tem¬
perature performance. With the aid of an
30
v¿ií» w
i ,
K
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
©I
engineer friend of mine , I perfected a sledge
made of Kevlar, a light but very tough poly¬
mer which is being increasingly used in
aeronautics. The sledge was 2.20 metres
long by 60 centimetres wide and weighed 3
kilograms. I managed to get the load down
to 50 kilograms. To keep my bearings on the
ice-pack I carried with me a small Kevlar-
encased safety-beacon-cum-radio-emitter,
the signal from which was picked up by
satellite and transmitted to a computer at
the Centre National d'Etudes Spatiales
(National Space Studies Centre) in
Toulouse, France. Michel Franco, who was
acting as my back-up at our base camp at
Resolute Bay on Cornwallis Island in the far
north of Canada, questioned the computer
by telephone every evening and then
informed me of my position. The beacon-
emitter was powered by lithium batteries
which are capable of withstanding
extremely low temperatures.
Did you also use a compass?
No. The magnetic pole, to which compass
needles point, is some 1,500 kilometres
from the geographical pole through which
passes the axis of rotation of the Earth, and
it was to this "true" North Pole that I was
heading. Furthermore, compasses are dis¬
oriented by the magnetic fields in this
region. Here the sun is the only guide. I
therefore had a watch made on which the
hour hand made only one complete revolu¬
tion in twenty-four hours. Knowing that the
sun is in the east at 0600 hours, in the south
at 1200 hours, in the west at 1800 hours and
On his expedition to the North Pole Jean-
Louis Etienne took specially designed
lightweight equipment weighing 50 kg,
left. His sledge weighed only 3 kg.
in the north at 2400 hours, all I had to do to
find my bearings was to point the hour hand
in the direction of the sun.
Why did you travel on skis?
Skis are indispensable. The ice-pack is
fractured and there are crevasses every¬
where, into which it is easy to fall unless you
take great care. Skis enable you to cross
them. In most places the ice-pack is from 2
to 3 metres thick, but where it breaks the
water freezes again forming a very thin skin
of ice. Skis spread your weight over a larger
surface and enable you to walk over very
recently-formed ice. I used nordic cross¬
country skis to the undersides ofwhich I had
stuck synthetic anti-slip skins. In the past,
people used sealskins for this purpose
because of the rigidity of the seal's body-
hair which enables it to climb on ice without
slipping. When, once a fortnight, Michel
Franco brought me fresh supplies by aero¬
plane, he would also fit me out with new
skins.
What did you have to eat?
Drawing on the recorded experience of pre¬
vious polar expeditions, I had concocted
some special food rations. At the beginning
I allowed myself a daily ration of 4,000 calo¬
ries. However, this proved to be insufficient
and I was somewhat hungry, so I stepped up
my daily ration to 5,000 calories. My meals
for a day were vacuum-packed in bags of
about 1 kilogram. As this was dried food I
would melt some ice to go with it (only
newly-formed ice is salty; old surface ice
loses its salt by gravity). I would heat up the
water on a petrol cooker (at those tempera¬
tures gas is unusable) and pour it on the
dried food to produce a kind of porridge. In
the evenings my supper consisted of soup
and a freeze-dried pre-cooked dish.
The surface of the ice-floe is rugged. The
blocks of ice fracture, collide against each
other and impact to form walls extending
over several km.
Did you also draw on the cold weather sur¬
vival techniques of the inhabitants of the far
north? Did you, for example, dress in their
fashion?
Not at all. These people are hunters who
live in encampments, do not travel far and
do not go in for comparable, long-lasting
physical or sporting activities. They are not
interested in the North Pole, where there is
nothing and where life is not possible, and
they have never been there. In this they are
similar to the Nepalese who would not
dream ofclimbing Everest. As far as dress is
concerned, clothes are now made that are
much warmer and much lighter than tradi¬
tional Eskimo clothing. The clothes I wore
were made of Qualofil, a synthetic fibre
with very good insulating qualities.
Your journey lasted sixty-three days. Can
you describe a typical day?
I used to get up at four in the morning and
set off at six. I would walk for eight to ten
hours a day, until about three or four in the
afternoon. Then I would stop, switch on my
beacon-emitter and put up my tent. After
that I would have a snack and rest until
seven, when I would contact Michel Franco
by radio. After that I would write up my log
book, have my evening meal and go to
bed.
Weren't you ever afraid that you might go to
sleep in the cold and never wake up again?
No. When you are in good physical shape,
as I was, you are always first woken up by
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Nutritionist and medical doctor, Jean-
Louis Etienne devised the contents of
compact rations to provide him with 5,000
calories a day. The food was freeze-drled
and vacuum-packed in numbered packets
each weighing 1 kg. Supplies were flown to
him every two weeks.
the cold. You only die of cold if you are ill,
or tired for example, after being stuck for
several days on a mountain ledge. In that
case, after a long struggle, you get
exhausted and there is a danger of falling
asleep for good.
Did you manage to warm yourself up in your
tent?
No. The temperatures in the tent varied
between -52°C and -20°C. I had to take
great care, before going to bed, to brush off
the frozen perspiration which covered me
like a skin under my watertight clothing and
which could, during the night, have brought
on a chill. I used to make myself a hot water
bottle with a 1-litre aluminium bottle which
I would fill with boiling water and hold
against myself inside my sleeping-bag.
Did you suffer from solitude in those vast
frozen expanses?
Solitude is not a handicap, it is a fantastic
force which enables you to bring all your
resources fully into play. Going to the
North Pole is no joyride. You have to be on
the look-out all the time. You have to pick
your route and avoid falling and injuring
yourself. You are living permanently on the
razor's edge. At the same time, however,
you can give free rein to your imagination.
Blocks of ice are transformed into mountain
peaks, into towers or cathedrals. Some¬
times I would say to myself: I shall go on to
that house ... to that mountain ... After
about three weeks to a month, when you
have got into your stride and the landscape
starts to seem monotonous, other thoughts
take over. I have never thought so much
about my childhood and my family. And
then there was God ... the God of the Arc¬
tic, the God of the Pole, of whom I
demanded right of passage. It was, as it
we're, a sort of journey of initiation. Yet I
never felt any anxiety.
But did you feel fear?
Yes, twice. Once when I saw the tracks of a
bear, and then when the ice gave way under
my feet. My reflex was to fall flat on the
sheet ice and to crawl. Only afterwards did
I realize that I might have had a serious
accident.
When you got back, did you undergo a series
of medical examinations?
Yes. I had lost six kilograms. The most
important test was an evaluation of my
adaptation to the cold. As I had done before
I set out, I underwent tests in a cold cham¬
ber. I stayed in the chamber, naked, for two
hours, in a temperature of 1°C and in an
airstream of a speed of 8 metres per second ,
which is the equivalent of a temperature of
-10"C. My internal temperature and my
consumption of oxygen was then measured.
Before setting out, over a period of two
hours, I had maintained a temperature of
37°C at the cost of a certain consumption of
energy. On my return, it was observed that
my temperature went down progressively to
35.5"C before my body began to fight
against the cold, and that my energy con¬
sumption was considerably lower. In other
words, I had become accustomed to living
at a below normal temperature and, from
the point of view of energy expenditure, my
two hours in the cold chamber had been
very economical. Like primitive man, or
like nomads who sleep in the open air, my
body's thermoregulatory mechanism had
adapted to hypothermic (low tempera¬
ture) conditions. Thus, modern man,
accustomed to high temperatures, can
return fairly rapidly to the physical ther¬
moregulatory comportment of his primitive
ancestors.
Has this experiment of yours added to the
sum of scientific knowledge?
From it I have gained a medical observation
on human adaptation to cold, as well as a
nutritional study the rations I developed
are now being used in France by the men of
the Chasseurs Alpins Regiment and by par¬
ticipants in the Paris-Dakar car rally. The
watch I developed has been put on the mar¬
ket and the tests using the beacon-emitter
supplied by the Centre National d'Etudes
Spatiales are considered to be conclusive. I
have also worked with Professor Jouvet, of
Lyon, on the subject of sleep. In fact, con¬
trary to all expectations, I slept very well
throughout my journey. But it must be
repeated that scientific research, and par¬
ticularly medical research, should be based
on a large number of experiments. No valid
observations can be based on a single case.
Most of all, I have the impression that, in
the eyes of young people, I have taken over
the role of those who first aroused in me my
passion for adventure.
After the North Pole, you now plan to cross
the Antarctic.
This time I shall not be alone. I shall have
three travelling companions, two Amer¬
icans and someone from the Soviet Union.
We shall also have two dog teams. We shall
cross the continent, keeping in contact with
a polar sailing vessel which will hug the
coast and transmit the pictures we shall be
sending. This expedition, planned for 1989-
1990, will coincide with the expiry of the
Antarctic Treaty (1961-1991) which regul¬
ates the status of the Antarctic. We want to
focus attention on this immense territory
which, under 2,000 metres of ice, contains
great mineral wealth which in four years
time will belong to no one. It is our hope
that all industrial or strategic exploitation of
the continent will be excluded and that it
will retain its international status and its
vocation as a land of scientific research.
Above all, our hope is that it will remain a
land of silence.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Marathon Man
by Bredo Berntsen
LONG-DISTANCE running has
enjoyed a popular revival in
recent years, and runners such as
Paavo Nurmi, Emil Zatopek, Abebe
Bikila and Grethe Waitz are household
names. But it was 150 years ago that the
greatest runner of all time was at the peak
of his career. He was a Norwegian named
Mensen Ernst.
His real name was Mons Monsen Oyri.
He was the son of a poor tenant farmer
from Leikanger on the Sognefjord where
he was born in 1795. He lived there until
he was about fifteen years old, when he
moved to the town of Bergen. He went to
sea, and won his first competitive run in
Cape Province in 1813.
As a seaman and adventurer he visited
the American, African, Asian and Aus¬
tralian continents, acquiring along the
way survival skills that were later to help
him navigate, wheedle and bluff his way
through his extraordinary journeys. The
only surviving contemporary portrait of
the "Running King", as he was known in
Norwegian, shows him cradling a sex¬
tant.
In 1818 he arrived in London. It is here
that he officially became a "pedestrian",
a runner or walker who covered long dis¬
tances in return for money. Here he also
took his professional name, Mensen
Ernst. His subsequent career was to last
for twenty-five years.
His first important run was in the spring
of 1819, from London to Portsmouth (116
kilometres) in nine hours. His popularity
was assured when he then covered the 240
kilometres from London to Liverpool in
thirty-two hours.
After a time he began to long for the
Continent, however, and in 1820 crossed
the Channel again, travelling on foot to
Annenrode manor in Mühlhausen (in
what is now the German Democratic
Republic), where he made a number of
life-long friends. From then on he lived as
a professional runner, and his fame as the
greatest runner of all time spread quickly
as he ran from city to city Berlin,
Prague, Rome across the Continent. In
1826 he put on a demonstration in
Copenhagen, where the high fees he
earned included 100 "daler" from the
Danish King Frederick VI. Ironically, his
native Norway was one of the few coun¬
tries through which he never ran.
After some years Mensen Ernst came
to see himself as something of an interna¬
tionalist. He became a genuine traveller,
curious about foreign cultures and
customs; he learned to speak French,
English and German well, and knew
some Italian and Turkish.
The only surviving contemporary portrait
of Mensen Ernst
In 1832, aged thirty-seven, Ernst went
to Paris in order to plan an audacious run
to Moscow. Among those who helped
him organize the stakes was a Swedish
diplomat, Count Löwenhielm. Ernst was
to receive 3,800 francs if he covered the
distance in fifteen days. He left Paris on
11 June, arriving in Kaiserlantern two
days later. "I felt I was sailing ... on my
two unique frigates," he was quoted
later, in a German book about him writ¬
ten in 1838. "Those who witnessed my
running considered me eccentric, or else
a fool, or possessed by the devil."
On 18 June he crossed the Polish river
Vistula and next day was in Russia. He
actually reached Moscow a day earlier
than expected. The commander there
had prepared to greet him, but because of
Ernst's early arrival and the ragged state
of his clothing he was taken at first for a
beggar. He had covered about 2,500 kilo¬
metres, or more than 170 kilometres
daily.
How did Ernst adapt to the extreme
conditions encountered on his journeys,
the burning sun, cold winds, pouring
rain? We know that he had a strict set of
rules that he followed all his life. He stuck
to a simple diet, for example: mostly
bread and cheese, a few vegetables, less
frequently cold meat; but he never ate
warm food. He also preferred to sleep
outdoors, believing that lying on hard
ground kept the body supple. If he did
sleep indoors it was always on a hard
bench, never a soft bed. His only weak¬
ness was for wine, which he used to drink
by the bottle even on his runs, but with no
apparent ill effects.
By the time he returned to Paris from
his Moscow run, Mensen Ernst was a
hero. He had become a living legend who
attracted rapturous audiences of thou¬
sands.
In 1833, he set out from Munich for
Old London Bridge in the early 19th cen¬
tury, around the time when Mensen Ernst
began his running career.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Nauplion, then the capital of the newly
founded state of Greece. He suggested to
King Ludwig I and Queen Thérèse that
he carry documents for their son, Otto I
of Greece, and after a delay of some
months his offer was accepted. His depar¬
ture on 6 June was cheered by a crowd of
20,000 outside Nymphenburg Palace.
This was a particularly dramatic jour¬
ney, partly because of the rugged land¬
scape, partly because of some unusually
severe problems Ernst encountered
along the way. In Montenegro he was set
upon by five robbers wielding pistols and
swords; as well as his money, they took
his maps, compass and quadrant, but for¬
tunately not the letters. He managed to
find his way to the town of Cattaro, where
he got food and drink, new maps and
compass, and started out again only to
be arrested as a spy. He spent three days
in jail before he was freed by the Pasha of
Janina, who "looked more like a Western
general than an Oriental Pasha", as Ernst
later said.
ÍT///.'V.,-»rt- i
On 1 July he stood outside the King's
residence in Nauplion to receive his
award of 1,000 guilders. He had covered
2,700 kilometres in just over twenty-four
days. Allowing about four days' delay for
various mishaps, he had done the run in
twenty days, or about 135 kilometres
daily. These statistics are so extraordin¬
ary that we are lucky to have contempo¬
rary sources to verify them.
Ernst's third and most dramatic project
began with an offer by British merchants
of the East India Company in Con¬
stantinople: £150 to carry important doc¬
uments to Calcutta. He left on 28 July
1836. The vigorous Norwegian had
thought the journey would take perhaps
six weeks; in fact he did it in four, on a
route that took him through Anatolia,
and finally across the Indian sub-con¬
tinent.
On his twenty-eight-day return jour¬
ney he took a more northerly route:
Lahore, across Persia to the Caspian Sea,
Teheran, Tabriz, and up to the Black
The desert near Theben, north of Syene
(now Aswan) in southeast Egypt, where
the great runner died from dysentery in
1843.
Sea. He covered about 8,300 kilometres
in fifty-nine days, 150 kilometres daily
allowing for a three-day rest in Cal¬
cutta.
The newspapers of his day praised his
achievement in completing the Asiatic
tour. The Times on 24 March stressed
"the unquestionable certificates" held by
Ernst.
His fourth epic run was to be his last. It
began when the German author, proprie¬
tor and adventurer, Count Hermann von
Pückler-Muskau, thirty years before
Stanley and Livingstone, asked him to
find the source of the White Nile. Count
Hermann had a keen interest in running
stemming from a visit to Greece in 1837,
when he had watched the Marathon and
heard about the Norwegian's exploits
four years previously.
Ernst left the Count's estate in Prussian
Silesia on 11 May, 1842. He passed Con¬
stantinople and reached Jerusalem in
thirty days, and then ran the 500 kilo¬
metres to Cairo. After some months in
Cairo he headed south along the Nile.
But now his luck had run out. He suc¬
cumbed to dysentery on 22 January 1843,
ending his legendary career in the desert
near Syene, now Aswan. Ten years later a
Norwegian newspaper declared: "The
world will never see his like again." Nor
has it!
BREDO BERNTSEN, of Norway, is deputy
librarian at the University of Oslo. He is the
author of a book about the life and times of Men-
sen Ernst, Loperkongen (The Running King",
Oslo, 1986), and of many other articles and
books including Naturvernets historie i Norge
(1977, "The History of Nature Conservation in
Norway").
The Courier
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Office:
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Subscription rates
1 year: 90 French francs.
Binder for a year's issues: 62 FF
The Unesco Courier is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus date of
issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the
editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author's
name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be
returned unless accompanied by an international
reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not
necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco or
those of the editors of the Unesco Courier. Photo
captions and headlines are written by the Unesco
Courier staff. The boundaries on maps published in
the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The
Unesco Courier is produced in microform
(microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco, 7
Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2) University
Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100,
U.S.A. ; (3) NCR. Microcard Edition, Indian
Head, Inc. ,111 West 40th Street, New York,
U.S.A. ; (4) Bell and Howell Co. , Old Mansfield
Road, Wooster, Ohio44691, U.S.A.
Editorial staff (Paris)
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Roy Malkin
Caroline Lawrence
French: Alain Lévêque
Neda el Khazen
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov
Arabic: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Braille:
Research: Violette Ringelstein
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Servat, George Ducret
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Sales and subscriptions: Henry Knobil
Special projects: Peggy Julien
All correspondence should be addressed to
the Editor-in-chiefin Paris
Non-Headquarters editions
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ram Babu Sharma (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: PauIMorren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra Ilgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwah (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Bozidar Perkovic (Beigrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Lina Svenzén (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
34
IMPRIME EN FRANCE (Printed in France) - Dépôt légal : C1 Juin 1 987
PHOTOGRAVURE-IMPRESSION : MAURY-IMPRIMEUR S.A., Z.I. route d'Etampes, 45330 MALESHERBES.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
TheCourier
For people who care about
the rest of the world . . .
A monthly magazine, each
issue usually devoted to a single
theme
Stimulating and informative
coverage from a wide range of
viewpoints
A window open on the world
A meeting-place for different
outlooks and cultures
A valuable source of ideas and
information on current issues
such as development, new
technologies, human rights and
the rights of peoples, and the
cultural heritage
A powerful instrument in the
service of international solidarity
and understanding
Forthcoming issues include:
The world ofmedicine
The baroque
Underwater archaeology
Japan
The only magazine in the world
published in 33 languages, with 4 (free) language editions in Braille.
Join or ask
your friends to
join our international
family of more
than 3 million readers
around the world.
Annual subscription
12 issues: 90 French francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco periodicals
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58a Gipps St., Colhngwood, Victoria 3066;
Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100,
NSW; Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale
2100, NSW. Sub-agent: United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian
Division, 328 Flinders Street, Melbourne 3000. AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung
Gerold and Co., Graben 31. A-1011, Vienna. BAHRAIN. United Schools
International. Arab Regional Office, P.O. Box 726, Bahrain. BARBADOS.
University of the West Indies Bookshop. Cave Hill Campus. P.O. Box 64,
Bridgetown. BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: Internationale
Drukkerij en Uitgeverij Keesing, Keesmglaan 2-20. 2100 Deurne-Antwerpen.
CCP 000-001 2775-68. French edition and general Unesco publications agent:
Jean da Lannoy, 202 Ave. du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP 000-0070823-13.
BRAZIL Publicaçoes Técnicas Internacionais Ltda, Processing Dept.. R
Peixoto Gomide 209, 01409, Sao Paulo SP. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co.
Ltd., 1294 Algoma Road, Ottawa, Ontario K1B 3W8. STORES: 61 Sparks
Street. Ottawa, 21 1 Yonge St., Toronto. SALES OFFICE: 7575 Trans Canada
Hwy. Ste. 305, St. Laurent, Quebec H4T 1 V6. CHINA. China National Publica¬
tions Import and Export Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Beijing.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L., Spalena 51-113 02, Prague 1 ; Ve Smeckach
30, P.O.B. 790-1 1 1-27 Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura, 1 1
Soukenicka, Prague 1 . For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag.-Publishers, Hurbanovo
nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava-CSSR. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export-OG, Tids-
sknftservice, 35 Norre Sogade, DK-1970 Kobenhavn K. EGYPT (ARAB
REPUBLIC OF). National Centre lor Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb
St., Cairo. FINLAND. Akateemmen Kirjakauppa, P. O. Box 128, SF-00100
Helsinki. Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, P.O. Box 2, 01641 Vantas 64. Rauti-
kirja Oy, Subscription Department, P.O. Box 1, 01641 Vantas 64. FRANCE.
Librairie de l'Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Pans. CCP 12598-48.
GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 1 40. 710
Leipzig, or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R. FED. REP. OF
GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier: Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher Unesco-Kurier
Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57, D5300 Bonn 3. GHANA. Fides Entreprises, P.O.
Box 14129, Accra. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. GREECE John
Mihalopoulos & Son SA, International Booksellers, P.O. Box 10073, 541 10
Thessaloniki. G C Eleftheroudakis SA, International Bookstore, 4 Nikis Street,
Athens T 1 26. Koslarakis Brothers. International Booksellers, 2 Hippocratous
Street. Athens. HONG KONG. Swindon Book Co., 1 3-1 5, Lock Rd., Kowloon.
Hong Kong Govt. Information Services. Publication Centre, Baskerville
House, 22 Ice St. HUNGARY. Kultura-Bushimport-ABT, P.O.B. 149-H-1389,
Budapest 62. ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson and Co.. H.F. Hafnarstraeti 9,
Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamam Marg, Ballard Estate, Bom¬
bay 400038; 17 Chitaranjan Ave.. Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road,
Madras 2; 5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh, Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahatma
Gandhi Rd Bangalore 560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001.
Sub-depots: Oxford Book and Stationery Co., 17 Park St., Calcutta 70016;
Scindia House, New Delhi. INDONESIA. Indira P.T., JIDr. Sam Ratulangie37,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Iranian National Commission tor Unesco, 1 188 Englab
Ave., Rostam Give Building, Zip Code 13158. P.O. Box 1 1365-4498, Teheran.
IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd., Ballymount Rd., Walkin-
stown. Dublin 12. ISRAEL. Literary Transactions, Inc., c/o Steimatzky Ltd.,
P.O. Box 628. Tel Aviv 61006A.B.C. Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71
Allenby Rd., Tel Aviv 61 000. ITALY. Licosa (Librería Commissionaria Sanso-
ni, S.pA), Via Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552, 50121 Florence. JAPAN.
Eastern Book Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo 3-chome Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo 113.
KOREA. Korean National Commission tor Unesco. P.O. Box Central 64,
Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait; for the
Unesco Courier: Farafalla Press Agency, P.O. Box SAFA 4541. Kuwait.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur
22-1 1. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic St., Valletta. MAURITIUS. Nalanda
Company Ltd., 30 Bourbon St.. Port-Louis. MEXICO. Librería El Correo de la
Unesco, Actipán 66, Colonia del Valle, Mexico 12, DF. MONACO. British
Library, 30 Bd. des Moulins, Monte Carlo. NEPAL Sajha Prakashan Pol-
chowk. Kathmandu. NETHERLANDS. Faxon Europe, P.O. Box 197, 1000 AD
Amsterdam. NEW ZEALAND. Government Publishing. P.O. Box 14277-
Kilbirnie, Wellington; 130 Oxford Terrace. P.O. Box 1721 , Christchurch; Alma
St., P.O. Box 857, Hamilton; Princes St., P.O. Box 1 104, Dunedin. NIGERIA.
The University Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O.-286.
NORWAY. JohanGrundtTanum, P.O.B. 1177 Sentrum - Oslo 1; Narvesen
A/S, Litteraturt Jenesten. P.O.B. 6125 Etterstad, N 0602 Oslo 6; Universitets
Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, Postboks 307 Blindem, Oslo 3.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency. 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O. Box No.
729. Lahore 3; Unesco Publications Centre, Regional Office for Book De¬
velopment in Asia and the Pacific, 39 Delhi Housing Society, P.O. Box 8950,
Karachi 29. POLAND. Orpan-lmport. Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No.7. 00-068 Warsaw. PORTUGAL
Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SAUDI
ARABIA. Dar al Watan, Olaya Main Street, Ibrahim Bin Sulaym Building,
Riyadh. SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (S) Pte Ltd. Times Jurong. 2
Jurong Port Rd.. Singapore 2261. SOUTH AFRICA. American & Overseas
Publications (Pty) Ltd. . Subscription Service, P.O. Box 42476, Johannesburg.
Universitas Books (Pty) Ltd., P.O. Box 775, Pretoria 0001. Van Schaiks
Bookstore (Pty) Ltd., Libri Building, 268 Church Street, Pretoria 0001 . Central
News Agency Ltd., Group Overseas Periodical Div. P.O. Box613, Cape Town
8000. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner
Mawata, P.O.B. 244, Colombo 2. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box
1118. Khartoum. SURINAME. Suriname National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box 2943. Paramaribo. SWEDEN. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN
Förbundet, Skolgrand 2. Box 150 50 S-104. 65 Stockholm; Wennergren-
Williams AB, Nordenflychtsvagen 70, S-104, 25 Stockholm; Esselte Tidskrift-
scentralen, Gamla Brogatan 26, Box 62 -101 , 20 Stockholm. SWITZERLAND.
Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse, Zürich; Librairie Payot, Rue Grenus 6, 1 21 1 .
Geneva 11, CCP. 12-236; Librairies Payot also in Lausanne, Basle, Berne.
Vevey, Montreux, Neuchâtel and Zurich. SYRIA. Aleppo University Books
Establishment, University of Aleppo. Aleppo. TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd..
40-42 Charoen Krung Road. Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O, Box 402. Bangkok;
Suksapan Pantt. Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Ave.. Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra St., St. Clair,
Trinidad W 1 . TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S., Istiklâl Caddesi, No 469, Posta
Kutusu 219, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office,
Agency Section Publications CTR, Periodicals Section-Room 008, Nine Elms
Lane, London SW8 5DR. and H.M.S.O. Bookshops in London, Edinburgh,
Belfast, Manchester. Birmingham, Bristol; for scientific maps only: McCarta
Ltd.. 1 22 Kings Cross Rd.. London WC1 X 9DS. UNITED STATES. Bernan-
UNIPUB. Penodicals Department, 4611-F Assembly Drive, Lanham, MD
20706 4391 . USSR. V/O Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Ul. Dimitrova 39. Moskva
113095. YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost, llica 30/1 1, Zagreb; Cankan'eva Zalozba,
Zopitarjeva 2, Lubljana; Nolit, Terazije 27/11, Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd., P.O. Box 2664, Lusaka.
ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd.. 1 Norwich Union Centre, Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Different walks of life
Above, at an altitude of some 4,000 metres, a traveller and his pack-animals wend their way above
the valley of Dolpo in the Himalayas (Nepal); below, a woman aquanaut carries out an experiment
near an underwater habitat in the Caribbean (see page 25).
]]>
</page>
</document>
