<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074116eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
VOLUME 11-NO 9 PRtCE :) 0 Cents (U. S.) or 6 Pence (U. K.) I OCTOBER, t949.
8
THE RIGHTS
OF MAN
The ( (Universal Declaration of Human
. Rights)) adopted by the General
Assembly of the United Nations,
meeting in Paris, on 10 December,
1948, was the fourth historic Act of its
kind, proclaimed by a free Assembly or reluc-
Jantly accepted by a reigning sovereign, within
'a period of seven and a quarter centuries.
« Magna Carta » was signed by King Henry III
of England in 1225 A. D. Nearly 600 years
later the « Bill of Rights ? was embodied in the
Constitution of the United States of America,
and the « Declaration of the Rights of Man H
was incorporated in that of the French Republic.
Now, after a second World War in which the
flame of human liberty came perilously near
to extinction, the age-old refusal of enlightened
peoples to submit to tyranny finds expression
in a new Declaration, signed and proclaimed
this time not by a monarch, a group of citizens
or a national assembly, but by the representatives
of 58 nations, united in defence of democracy.
*
In spite of the lapse of centuries, the fundamen-
tal principles underlying these successive
 charters of human freedom have not chang-
d. The very similarity of their languageproves how constant is the need for vigilance
if the rights of the individual are to be preserved.
The complexity of this ancient problem
in modern times may be gathered from the
symposium on Human Rights prepared by Unesco
this year. Let us quote some passages :
Personal liberty can. be made secure only by
þolishing the abuse of power altogether. Unesco
is engaged at present in facilitating the task
of mitigation ; but it is in the fortunate position
of being able to proceed, if it so desires, to the
incomparably more important task of prevention,
of the radical removal of present impediments to
liberty. This is primarily an affair for the scientific
section of the Organisation. »
« it is vital for the future of the world that
intense animosities and hatreds be allayed. This
cannot be done solely by social and psychological
studies... The immediate objective of the scientist
should be to ensure that all branches of society
in all nations are freed from economic anxiety. »
( The common goals inherent in the ideal of the
rights of man can only be attained as programmes
of education and instruction are based on the
realization that there is no national culture which
does not owe for more than is usually admitted
to the influence of the cultural heritage of man
of all races and of all ages. »
Lastly, an opinion from Unesco House itself :
( From the moment that information comes
to be regarded as one of the rights of man, the
structures and practices which make of it an in-
strument for the exploitation, by alienation of the
minds of the masses, for money or for power,
can no longer be tolerated. »
science, Education, Information-each of theexperts has his own point of view, but all
of them, in effect, give the same warning
to mankind. The Rights of Man must be defended
collectively, with every weapon in the armoury
of peace. « Freedom of speech, freedom of
religion, freedom from want, freedom from
fear M-and, ! et us add, freedom from ignorance
- these are the conditions of emancipation.
( When we enumerate man's rights, we are
also enumerating duties to be accomplished. None
touches ups more nearly than the right to education.))
t
[ Only when these separate freedoms are
truly guaranteed can the world hope to see the
dawn of a universal Freedom born of tolerance,
justice and goodwill towards men.
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 2
IN BRAZIL
EDUCATORS STIRRED
BY NEW APPROACH
TO CONTINENTAL
CAMPAIGN"
AGAINST ILLITERACY
Unesco-sponsored Seminar
launches I global'attack for
education of 70 millions
adult illiterates and
79 million children with-
: out schools in the Americas
. 0"
THE mid-winter months of. July and
August, the tourist books say, are
the most delightful periods tu
visit Rio de Janeiro. Fur a small
group of educators, who had come. to
participate in the Inter-American Semi-
nar on Literacy and Adult Education,
the pleasant Br winter, however.
was no holiday.
They began to arrive, mostly by
plane, towards the end of Juhly. At the
Santos Dumont airport in the heart of
Rio, they werc bundled into high-
powered, spacious taxis and whisked
through the Federal Capital past the
Sugar Loaf and Guanabara Bay. Two
hours later, still breathless and dizzy
from the winding, tortuous road trip
through the Organ Mountains behind
Iso, they were deposited at the door of
the sumptuous Hotel Quitandinha, near
Petropolis Here. they remained for tivc
full wseks. from July 27 to September
2, to examine one of the most burning
problems of the entire.American conti-
nent : 7 :. 0. 000. 000 adult illiterates and
19. OOO. OOO. American children deprived
of s.
To the Inter-American Seminar, or-
ganized jointly by Unesco, the Organi-
zation of American States (OAS), and the
Brazilian Government, came some of
the most distinguished educational
leaders from the New and the Old
world : the originator of Mexico's fam-
ed « Cultural Missions >&gt; for literacy
Professor Guillermo Bonilla y Segura
known throughout his country simply
as (< El Maestro >&gt; young, energetic
Ismael Rodriguez Bou, educational re-
searcher from Puerto Rico : witty Er-
nrsto Nelson, statistical giant of Argen-
tina : Swiss psychologist Jean Piaget :
literacy primer specialist Ann Nolan
Clark, of the United States ; and Colo-
nel George Selwyn Simpson, bringing
with him 35 years experience in literacy
teaching in the British Army.
For the occasion, the Brazilion Gov-
ernment called in some of its best. edu-
cational experts : Fernando Tude de
Souza, Antonio AImeida Junior, Mario
Teixeira de Freitas and Mario Paulo de
Brito.
Dr. Lourenço Filho, directur of Bra-
zil's hignly successtui 2 1/2 year cam-
paign against illiteracy, left his desk.
on the fourteenth floor of the ultra-
modern Ministerio de Educacao e Saude
to take over leadership of the interna-
lional seminar. with him were (uiller-
mo Nannetti. 39-year old former Mi-
nister of Education uf Columbia and
special OAS representative, and Dr
Frederick J. Rex, eminent American
educator and Cnesco's field representa-
tive, in Fundamental Education.
Fresh Ideas
And Techniques
In spile of this impressive team of
educationists the Seminar sought
and achieved no miracl s. The
70. 000. 000 adult illiterates still remain to
he integrated into the life-stream of
Latin-American communities and na-
tions. But from the careful, five-week
exchange or ideas and experiences there
emerged a series or new ideas, new
methOds and techniques, which have
set the bases for the first co-ordinated
attack ever planned on a continental
scale against what Torres Bodet has
termed'"one of the most disquieting
problems of our century".
During recent years, a number of
Latin-American countries have made
special efforts to combat illiteracy
among their urban and rural popula-
tions. In spite of successful advances
in some regions, progress in most Latin-
American Republics has been slow.
what was needed, it was felt. was a
linking up of forces, a pooling of ex-
periences, the weading out of out-mod-
The Unesco Courier is an international monthly periodical devoted to
th work of Unesco and to activities and developments throughout the
world in education, scienc and culture.
A full year's subscription (12 issues) costs only $ 1. 00 US., or 5/-.
SUBSCRIBE NOW Tell your friends about the Unesco Courier and
get them to subscribe too.
Write to our agent in your country listed below, or directly to Unesco
House, 19, avenue Kleber, Paris, 16°, France.
Argentina : Editorial Sudamericana S. A. Alsina 500 Buenos-Aires
Australia : H A. Goddard Ltd., 255 a. George St., Sydney.
Belgium : Librairie encyclopedique. 7, rue du Luxembourg, Bruxelles IV.
Canada : The Ryerson Press, 299 Queen Street West, Toronto.
Cuba : La Casa Belga, R. de Smdt, O'Reilly, Habana.
Denmark : Einar Munksgaard, 6, Norregade, Copenhague.
Great Britain : M. M. Stationery Office : London : York House, Kingsway
(Retail Counter Service) : P. O. Box 509. London. S. E. I. (Post orders).-
Manchester 2 : 39-41 King Street.-Edinburgh 2 : 13a Castle Street.-
Cardiff : I St Andrew's Crescent.-Bristol I : Tower Lane.-Belfast :
80 Chichester Street.
France : Editions A. Pedone, 13, rue Soufflot, Paris (5').
Greece : Eleftheroudakis, Librairie internationale, Athens.
India : Oxford Book and Stationery Co., Scindia House, New Delhi
Lebanon and Syria : Librairie universelle, av. des Francis, Beirut.
Low Countries : N. V. Martinus Nijhoff, Afd., Fondsaministratie, 9 Lange
Voorhout, The Hague.
Portugal : Uniáo Portuguesa de Impresa, Caixa Postal 615, Lisboa
Sweden : Ab. O. E. Fritzes, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
Switzerland : Librairie Payot, Lausanne.
Uruguay : Libreria international S. R. L, Calle Uruguay 183, Montevideo.
U. S. A. : International Documents Service, Columbia University Press 2960
Broadway, New York 27, NY.
THE SECOND ABOLITION. 102-year old Senhor Cequeira of the littie town of
Guaratingueta is a symbol of the desire of Brazilians to benefit from the nation-
wide adult education campaign against illiteracy. (Photo « 0. Cruzeiro".
S. Paulo).
ed methods and techniques, and a
fresher approach to the entire problem.
This the Unesco-sponsored Seminar
at Quitandinha definitely provided.
II provided, above all, a fresh
approach to the continental problem of
illiteracy by inspiring all participants,
in all five groups, with the new con-
cept-for Latin-, America-of Adult
Education, which aims at raising the
general living conditiuns of lite peuple
through the improvement of health.
agriculture, and family and community
life, with literacy training as only one
step towards the accomplishment of
that end.
In this respect. the inspired contribu-
tion of Dr. Guillermo Nannetti, as lea-
der of the working group on Literacy
and Adult Education, won the admira-
tion and enthusiastic praise of the en-
tire Seminar. This vast and unexplored
Üeld in Latin America, came alive in the
short space of five weeks and took on
breadth and force. By the end of the
Seminar, 30 educators and experts,
working under the guidance of Dr.
Nannetti, had produced the first Hand-
book on Adult Education ever to appear
in Portuguese and Spanish. This 65-page
volume, which represents the most am-
bilious achievement of the Seminar cov-
ers an extensive range of subjects.
ranging from the role of the media of
mass communication and agricultural
extension in adult education to labour
organizations and co-operatives.
Most Heated
Debate of Seminar
PERHAPS ; the most important and cer-.
tainly the most heated debate of
tle Quitandindha Seminar was
touched off when the working group
studying literaq'teaclling metllods, ld
bv Dr. Frederick Rex, presented its
findings and conclusions to the final
plenary session of the Seminar.
For five weeks, the group of educa-
tors had studied and analYzed the dil1er-
ent methods for eaching people to
read and write. This included the metal-
od most widely used and adapied in
Latin-America and in other parts of the
world-the Laubach method-based
on the use of"picturahle words rela-
ted to groups uf sounds". The educa-
tors also made a detailed and careful
study of the "Global or Sentence Meth-
ed"-based on the principle that the
student first understands the meaning
of a sentence or thought before he
knows and analyzes its parts (i. e.
words, letters and groups of sounds).
In its conclusions the group went on
record unanimously favouring the Glo-
bal Method.
when these conclusions were pre-
sented to the plenary meeting of the
Seminar the "battle of the methods"
raged for over three hours. Tempers
rose, nerves were frayed. But in the
end, the Global Method was upheld by
an overwhelming majority of Seminar
participants, who agreed that :
Concerning the problem of method, the
Seminar wishes to go on record that It
accepts the scientific evidence in favour
of the sentence or global method for
teaching children to read. On the ba-
sis of objective data and corroborative
evidence of the psychology of aduits,
of their interests and ways of teaning,
the Seminar recommends the same me-
thod for the teaching of adult illite-
rates until such time as the results of
research and controlled experiments
prove the contrary. This preference
does not suggest, in any way, the in-
advisability of extensive experiments to
strengthen, modify, or change the me-
thodological position expressed by the
Seminar.
Teacher of the
Americans
IT way fitting that Dr. Lourenco Filho,
whose work as leader of Brazil's
succcsful literacy campaigns has
won him international recognition.
should have taken over responsibility of
one of the most important working
groups of the Seminar on The Organi-
zation of Literacy Campaigns. At the
end of the five weeks, Dr. Lourenco,
with the aid of his small group, had
completed a series of basic papers
which will be invaluable to any govern-
ment or Organization seeking to under.
take or improve a eompaign for literacy
in an y given part of Latin-America.
For his leadership at the Inter-Ameri-
can Seminar, for his unselfish devotion
to the cause of education, not only in
his own country but in all the Ameri-
can Republics, every member of the
Seminar acclaimed Lourenço Filho as
"El Maestro de las Americas".
Already, the influence of the Inter-
American Seminar has left its mark.
During the final days of the plenary
meetings, the State Representatives of
the Brazilian Literacy and Adult Edu-
cation Campaign met at the Hotel Qui-
tandinha for their annual conference.
As a result of their direct contact with
the participants at the Seminar they vot-
ed tu put into application immediately
one of the final resolutions passed call-
ing for the organization of national
seminars whose aim would be to studY
the application in each country of the
conclusions reached at the Rio de Ja-
neiro Seminar. The first national semi-
nar to be held in the Americas will take
place next month in the city of Sao
Paulo.
Finally, the participants unanimoush
voted a recommendation calling for the
creation of a Centre to train writers
and illustrators from different coun-
tries to prepare basic, supplementary
and general reading materials, as well
as a Centre to train teachers uf adull
education.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Page 3-UNESCO COURIER
CONCENTRATED PROGRAMME'
For Unesco Urged
by Delegates To 4 the
General Conference
THIS issue of the « Courier >&gt; covers only the openingand first days of the UNESCO General Conference
now meeting in Paris. Our last month's number,
containing 32 pages, gave a comprehensive preview of the
subjects to be discussed. Full details of the results and
conclusions reached at the conference as well as reports
on the 3-day debate scheduled to open at the Maison de la
Chimie in Paris on September 27 will be found in our next
number.
Some of the 250 delegates and ob-
ervers (above) at the General Con-
ference. Right, Mr U Ba Lwin, head
of the Burmese Delegation.
ISRAEL
and PAKISTAN
Join UNESCO
AFTER travelling to Mexico City
win 1947 and to Beirut in 1948,
Unesco's General Conference
"came home"to Paris, this year,
for its Fourth Session which on Septem-
ber 19 opened in Unesco House-only a
few steps away from the historic Arch
of Triumph.
Into the plenary hall, on Monday
morning, filed over 250 delegates and
observers under the'''fire''. of world
press and film photographers who are
reporting the conference.
Sharply at 10. 30 a. m. the noise and
talking in the crowded assembly stopped
as H. E. Ahmed Bey Daouk, head of the
Lebanese Delegation, advanced to the
speakers platform, which had as its
backcloth the flags of Unesco's 50 Mem-
ber States, and declared the Fourth Ses-
sion open.
Following the Unesco tradition, its
General Conference is opened by the
representative of the country which
provided the chairman of the previous
Conference. This tradition, Ahmed Bey
Daouk remarked,'''brings to my mind
the ceremonies of the Olympics of
ancient Greece in which runners, handing
on a flaming torch, carried it finally to
the altar of Prometheus".
Later in the morning, Dr. E. Ronald
Walker, head of the Australian Delega-
tion, was unanimously elected chairman
of Unesco's fourth annual conference.
Previous chairmen have been : M. Leon
Blum in Paris (1946), H. E. Don Manuel
Gual Vidal in Mexico ICity (1947) and
M. Hamid Bey Frangie in Beirut (1948).
M. Georges Bidault, former Prime
Minister and head of the French Dele-
gation, who had been proposed as
chairman of the Paris Conference had
declined, stating that as Unesco would
now meet in Paris every two years, it
could not be expected that a French
delegate be chairman every other year.
THE first days of the conference,which this i sue of the COUR-
RIER is reporting, were taken up
almost entirely with the presentation
and discussion of the annual report of
the Director-General. Presenting this
report, Sir Sarvepalli Radhakrishnan,
recently appointed Indian Ambassador
to Moscow and Chairman of Unesco's
Executive Board, warned delegates that
Unesco' mission could be fulfilled only
T"WO countries which recentl,'g, lin-ed their independence-Pakis-
tan and Israel-joined UNESCO on
the eve of its Fourth General Confer-
ence and thus brought the total
number of its member countries to so.
Delegations from both these coun-
tries have been present at the Confer-
ence. Israel's being led by the Israeli
Minister in Paris, Mr : \Iaurice Fisher
and Pakistan's by M. S. M. Sharif.
if governments and National Commis-
sions played their full part."Unfortu-
nately", he said."the activity of many
member states does not extend beyond
attendance at sessions of the General
Conference. It is obvious that atthena-
tional level, there is a breakdown in the
means of im1Jlementation of Unesco's
programme."
The second day of the conference was
marked by a British proposal to alter
the agenda so as to a)) ow the conference
immediately to fix a ceiling for Unesco's
1950 budget. This proposal, coming
24 hours after news of important cur-
rency devaluations in Great Britain and
other countries, provoked liyely opposi-
tion from delegates of a dozen nations.
and was fina)) y withdrawn.
In some respects, the Paris conference
differs from previous ones. In principle
it was to have been"a short business
session", but it has come to be definitely
more important than was at first expected
because of vital discussions on Unesco's
participation in the UN plan for techni-
caul assistance to underdeveloped areas
and the interest already aroused in the
''Duties of the State"debate,
Some'of the latest technical facili-ties and equipm nt have been mo-
bilized to bring the conference's
message to the public. Thus, for the
first time in international conference
practice, the speeches of delegates are
not being set down in shorthand but are
being registered on magnetic-wire record-
ing apparatus. Sound recordings of the
Fourth Session are being made at Unesco
House studios for French, Belgian and
other radio networks and are also being
f ! own to Lake Success for broadcast on
special UN radio programmes. Similar
recordings will also be made for the
international debate beginning on Sep-
tember 2ï which will be placed at the
disposal of broadcasting systems through-
out the world.
THERE MUST BE NO QUESTION
OF A DEVALUATION OF UNESCO
Dr G. Zook (United States), on left, explains a point to Dr F.
Bender (Netherlands) and Sir Ronald Madam (Great Britain),
seated.
THE General Conference of Unesco is morethan a crowd of people invading the ( train
qmlity.) of Unesco House, and more than
mere academic Or diplomatic discussions. It is
a meeting of men and women who have come
together for a short time to give to the world
living proof of the work of Unesco. With the
presence of delegates from all over the world,
Unesco's different projects, experiments and
investigations take on a greater human interest
and warmth.
An educational mission to the Philippines or
to Afghanistan for example might appear to be
of limited interest. It seems very different,
however, when the Afghan representative tells of
the hopes his country places in the work of the
Unesco mission there, or when the delegate of
the Philippines in her striking butterfly-wing
dress expresses the thanks of her war-devastated
country for the help sent to schools, laboratories
and libraries.
But above all a Unesco general conference is a
sign of hope, perhaps one of the few real hopes
for peace that still remain for mankind. ThIs
very idea was expressed by India's representative
Sir Sarvepalli Radhakrishnan. when, in mov !', g
words, he said : « Look at the condition of tne
world ten years after the beginning of the last
war. four years after the victory was won. One
after another the illusions which we have
chenshed are disappearing. We thought that the
sense of community would resolve all class dis-
tinctions. as it did during the period of the
war. It has not happened. We thought again that
the United Nations would be the beginning of a
new world. Well. again it has not happened. We
thought that the allies who fought the war and
won the victory would stand united and win the
peace-that has not happened"
Sir Sarvepalli ended with an urgent appeal to
delegates : « these days are big with fate The
issue of war or peace haunts us ; there is an
atmosphere of gloom ; conflict is creeping slowly
and steadily. Is it not possible under such cir-
cumstances for all our leaders, for those who
stand up for the great ideals, to get together ?
For, say half a dozen of them-two from Asia
two from Europe, America and Russia, to get
together, not for achieving any political results,
but for breaking down this blinding mist of
misunderstanding, breaking through this moun-
tain \"31'of prejudice and trying to understand
(C c) N TIN U E DON P AGE 4)
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page
we are real lovers of peace. Is it impos-
sable ? We are meeting in this great
city, a city of artists, scholars, scien-
tists. writers, a city of a gay, copra-
geous and inspired people, a city which
has seen so many revolutions, born of
distress of mind of anxiety itself. Well.
can't we. from this city, in the name of
Unesco. send forth a message, asking
the leaders to listen to the cry of
anguished humanity, asking them to
build peace, not on the bloodshed of
the peoples of the world in the battle-
fields of earth, water and air, but on
truth and justice, built into the minds
and consciences of human poop, e. Can't
we do that ? >&gt;
Building trJth and justice into the
minds and consciences of human peop. e
is what Unesco is seeking to do in its
day to day work. But the work is too
often hampered by all sorts of difficul-
ties. Like all other efforts of man,
Unesco cannot claim perfection.
That is why. for Unesco. the General
Conference serves as a means'of shelf.
examination. It forces Unesco to take
stock of the efforts made as compared
with the results achieved. At the same
time it enables Unesco's friends not
only to support it, but to offer an ever-
watchful and cC'ìstructive criticism.
And, in fact, such suggestions or criti-
cism concerning Unesco's working
methods, were frankly voiced by the
37 speakers who addressed the Assem-
bly during the discussions of the Direc-
tor-Gsnerat's annual report. Space,
however, permits us to quote only a
few of the many important views ex-
pressed during the first four days of
the Conference.
In Our Own Right
M R. George v. Alien, Head of theUnited States delegation, took
the view that Unesco should
work more closely with the United Na-
tions. <&lt;Unesco exists >&gt;, he said « to
strengthen the system of the United
Nations. How can Unesco best serve the
United Nations ? I hope that this
question w, ll be thoughtfully considered
by evety delegate who proposes a pro-
ject to be undertaken by Unesco, or
who votes a budget item during this
conference >&gt;.
M. Georges Bidault, Head of the
French delegation, speaking a few
hours later, took the opposite view and
asked that Unesco should preserve a
As PART of its Paris Conference this year, Unesco
has decided to bring before the general public
I an important international debate touching on
one of the great problems of our times : the
duties of the State in the modern world. In this
debate the very conception of the role of the State
will be examined, and with it the role of man and
his rights as a member of society.
It is this close relation between human. rigllts and
the duties of the State, and the need for defining
States'duties so as to safeguard man'siJni'lersa/
rights, which has led Unesco to undertake the great
debate which will be open to the Pub/icin Paris, and
which will bye heard by radio listeners 
the world through specially prepared r
Each evening from September 27 to 29,
THE DUTIES
OF THE STATE
In regard to
Education
Science
and
Culture
AN INTERNATIONAL DEBATE ON
ONE OF THE FUNDAMENTAL
PROBLEMS OF THE PRESENT AGE
SPEAKERS INCLUDE.
Georges BIDAULT (France)
Reinho. d NIEBUHR (U. S. A.)
Bertrand RUSSELL. (U. K.)
Jean PIAGET (Switzerland)
F. HERCIK Czechoslovakia)
Alf SOMMERFELT (Norway)
Antonio CASTRO LEAL (Mexico)
Tara CHAND (India)
ent world personalities will present their points of
view on the following question : « What are the duties
of the State in regard to education, science and culture
for the purpose of ensuring a better understanding
between peoples, and what practical steps should be
taken in order to discharge those duties ?))
After the three speakers, five or six ( deboters »
from different countries, particularly representative
of their culture, will take part in a prolonged discussion
of the themes.
degree of independence : ( (... Let us
op2rate)). he said « in our own right,
in accordance with the essential prin-
ciples we share with the United Na-
tions, as one of its Agencies, closely
connected to it, but as an organiza-
tion which nevertheless has its own
life, its own goats, its own intentions
and desires and. be it added, its own
duties').
Nazi speakers stressed the need for
Unesco to « concentrate its pro-
gramme K. Above all, stated M. Paulo
Carneiro. head of the Brazilian de : e-
gation. <&lt; so that the Secretariat can
really give full thought to each pro-
blem H. Other reasons were given by
Mr Hardman, representative of the
United Kingdom : « We here at this
Conference'\ he said, <&lt; who are learn-
ed and intelligent individual men and
women have a special responsibility as
representatives of our Commissions and
governments. The responsibility is, I
think, to see that thinking and public.
city become action. to ally thought
with the doing of things. As it would
be expressed colloquially in parts of my
country. <&lt; Cut the cackle to a mini-
mum and get on with the job". Turn-
ing to certain of Unesco's specific acti-
pities. Mr Hardman went on : « When
one thinks that some forty million pa-
ges of cyclostyled memoranda and doc-
uments in a single year have ema-
nated from the Organization, surely it
is reasonable that we should ask our-
selves. is all this really necessary ?
Pursuing the same-one of thought, he
later said* : «... the kind of questions
this business conference must ask it-
self is this' « How many people have
we taught to :-ead for the first time in
their lives, since the Beirut Confe-
rence ? and not'how many cyclostyl-
ed pages of memoranda and luxury
editions have we published ?.))
mHESE detailed discussions of) Unesco's activities have not meant
that no delegates have tried to
find solutions to the fundamental prob-
lems facing mankinct today. Thus, for
example, Mr Mev Yi Chi. the delegate
of China, conc'uded his speech with
these words : <&lt; For mutual understand-
ing and appreciation between the East
and the West, it seems that much of
the best of the two cultures, in lite-
rature, in art and in philosophy, should
be brosght out as complementing fac-
tors for what we hop2 eventually to ar-
rive at-the birth of a world culture.
The West is making great strides in
the advanc of modern civilization, but
for an ultimate solution of the situa-
tion arising from conflicting ideas and
attitudes as we have to-day, we may
need to search seriously into the phi-
losophies of the East and the West,
perhaps more of the East.
The Polish delegate, M. Putrament,
voiced strong opposition to any Unesco
activities in Germany, thereby differ-
ing completely with M. EI Hashimt,
the de. egate of Iraq, who had com-
p. ained that Unesco was not duing
enough there.
At the close of the discussion, the
Director-General ot Unesco replied to
the various speakers. To those who had
comp. ained that Unesco's programme
was too broad, M. Torres Bodet said :
« Instead of asking for resources ap-
propriate to secure the aims of the pro-
gramme. the programme can be
brought down to the level of the re-
sources. But I wou. d point out that the
programme of which you compiain is
not my programme ; I had it irom you
in Beirut, still warm with the enthu-
siasm of your discussions. It is, there-
fore, you own work that you want to
reduce. You are certain. y entitled to do
,, 0, but, gentlemen, I b2g yoa to think
carefully before you do it, and not to
allow yourselves to be guided sole. y by
financial considerations. Do not let the
currency devaluation which, in certain
countries, has coincided with this Ses-
sion of the Conference, be a sign of
the deva : uation of Unesco ! >&gt;
Holding out Hope
M TORRES BODET then quoted aletter which he had receivedfo. Iowing his opening speech at
the General Conference. The letter
had stated that it was not « boastful
propaganda>&gt; to make Twentieth-Cen-
tury man familiar with Unesco's aims,
but « a way of holding out hopex. « Are
we to be prevented from holding out
hope'). asked M. Torres Bodet. « Do
we wish to hold up Unesco's develop-
ment in its fourth year of existence at
the very moment when it is becoming
firmly established, when it is beginning
to give tangible signs of its resolve and
of successful achievement, by deferring
further progress to a later date ? Or do
Wè wish to push ahead with yet more
energy and larger resources ? I do not
hesitate to state my conviction that if
we defer progress to later, it will be
too late. We shall have foundered in
apathies. Life is a constant effort. He
who does not go forward drops back ;
he who drops back is lost. There can
be no hesitation btween a great and
a little Unesco, between a Unesco which
'tands stil. 1 and a dynamic Unesco, es-
specially at this ear. y stage in its his-
tory, this moment in the world'S his-
Mry. Unesco must be a great force or
nothing. Our Constitution commits us
to greatness. Gentlemen, you no doubt
rea. izethisasc. earlyasldo. andl
hope In all earnestness that your dis-
cussions will make this clear beyond a
doubt".
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Page 5-UNESCO COURIER
T live Paris exhibition on Human Rights, which
on opens at the Musée Galliéra on October 1, is
the most important achievement to date in
H Unesco's plan to publicize the story of
mankind's age-old fight for freedom, so as to
encourage modern man to respect and defend the rights
on which it is founded.
The largest public exhibition which Unesco has yet
organized, it has required months of research and pre-
paration, and, above all, close collaboration between the
Unesco Secretariat in Paris and the Governments and
National Commissions of Unesco's Member States.
Undoubtedly the most striking proof of this success-
ful collaboration is that Unesco has been able to
assemble a remarkable collection of authentic histo-
rical documents upon which are founded the laws and
guarantees now enjoyed by citizens of different
countries.
Loaned by the governments of these countries for
display at the exhibition, these origin : J I documents-
charters, declarations and drafts-not only advanced
the progress of human rights in their countries of
origin, but were a source of inspiration to people in
other land also struggling to achieve freedom.
Documents such as the French Constitution of l7tlf
and Lincoln's early draft of the Emancipation Procla-
mation which freed the slaves in the United States, both
of which are among those on display, illustrate the
fight for human rights throughout the centuries and
their acknowledgement across the world.
BU. T, tllf'. p ; qn p[J['puse of the exhibition is not simplyto two historic documentary evidence on the
progressive recognition of human rights in different
countries. Primarily, it aims to show the debt that
mankind to-day owes to the"fighters for freedom"of
the past and that the task they began will only be
complete when the Universal Declaration of Human
Rights has been converted into fact.
Emphasizing the universal nature of the responsibi-
lity for achieving and defending human rights and thus
bringing out a"world task"theme for the exhibition,
the first exhibit at the J\lusée Galliéra is a planetarium.
Through its window, visitors will see the earth turning
in space-an earth whose political divisions have sym-
Man conquering his FreedUm
bolieally lJeen lefl UlHnHr'ked, And ; as they
look into the window, they will heap a
recorded voice repeating the texts of the first
three articles of the Universal Declaration of
Human Rights.
With this spoken prologue in their minds,
they can next take a"pocket tom"of man-
kind's history from prehistoric times down
to the present âay. Illustrated panels and
panoramas show man's slow emancipation
and his gradual mastery of nature and him-
self : the first tools, the first forms of cultiva-
tion, the first affirmations of moral laws and
the later conquest of civic and political rights
illustrate the contributions of all peoples,
nations and civilizations to the sum total of
Human Rights.
nero, having told the story of how manyof the rights. were achieved, the exhibi-
tion shows in a series of illustrations
how these rights were abused and violated hy
totalitarian states, a state of affairs which led
to the Second World War. A fresh series of
photographs shows the struggle of the demo-
cracies to re-assert the rights and, the even-
tual establishment of the United Nations to
found a peace based on the principles laid
down bv President Roosevelt, in his famous
"Four Freedoms"message of January 6,
1941.
This pictorial"history book"of the last
two Jec : ades leads visitors iuto a second ! jail
where 14 pillars illustrate episodes relating
to one or more of the 30 articles of the Uni-
versal Declaration of Human Rights adopted
by the General Assembly of the United Na-
tions on December 10, 1948.
One side of each pillar shows the periods
in history when the rights concerned were
respected and, lower down, when the rights
were violated or ceased to exist. Illustra-
tions on the other side of the pillar show
steps in the fight for human rights and the
results achieved in the struggle.
It is hoped in this way to bring home the
extent of the debt owed by humanity to those
men and women whose efforts and sacrifices
built up the existing heritage while at the
same time making clear the practical impor-
tance of their achievements.
Having told the background story of the
fight for Human Rights, the exhibition then
shows some of the"milestones"on the road
to their universal recognition-origina !
historic documents from France. Belgium
and the United States.
The last part of the exhibition is devoted
to the duties which each person must fulfìl
if Human Rights are to become and remain
a reality for all, special emphasis being
laid on the responsibility for creating a better
world for children.
To show the measure of responsibility for
safeguarding the rights of future genera-
tions, a number of ingenious devices have
been used. One, showing the average number
of children being born in the world during
each minute is set at zero each morning, and,
by the time the exhibition closes in the
evening, something like 20, 000 births will
have been registered.
IT is very fitting that the words of Mahat-ma Gandhi, one of the greatest defenders
of human rights who ever lived, should
have been chosen as an"epilogue"for visi-
tors to read as they leave the exhibition.
In a letter which Gandhi wrote in 1947 to
Dr Julian Huxley, at that time Director-
General of Unesco, he said :"I learnt from
my illiterate but wise mother that all rights
to be deserved and preserved came from
duty well done. Thus, the very right to live
'accrues to us only when we do the duty of
citizenship of the world. From this one fun-
. damental statement, perhaps it is easy
enough to define the duties of Man and
Woman and correlate every right to some
corresponding duty to be first performed.
Every other right can be shown to be an usur
pation hardly worth fighting for".
The Human Rights exhibition will be open
to the general public from October i until
December 31 and arrangements are being
made for thousands of French school chil-
dren to visit it.
Unesco also hopes that it may be possible
to provide Member States with materials for
organizing in European capitals some sim-
plified replica of the Paris Exhibition. It is
also hoped that photographic reproductions
and plans of the exhibition may be sent to
countries far from Paris so thaI they too may
be able to hold exhibition :- ;'lltÌ I'P IheÙ.
people some idea of what has h.... tl i,,'l1ieved.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
In the « Deep South a an old « mammy » waves a handful
01 cotton which for so many years was the material symbol
01 her people's servitude. In abolishing slavery, the world
was to learn how to ensure the triumph of human rights :
by lulliling a duty that was both national and international.
THE RIGI :
Black slavery continued to flourish until almost the close of the 19th century. For years courageous men fought against this
vicious exploitation of man by man which had begun in the lEth century. An enlightened public opinion finally resulted in inter-
national conventions putting a stop to this inhuman tragic (shown above) followed by total emancipation in one country after another.
HOMO HOMINI LUPUS.-Thus Plautus expressed his idea that man is a wolf to his fellow men. Seventeen
centuries later. Hobbes voiced the same idea : in our times, it even became the principle of a criminal state
policy, for which a new word « {genocide)) had to be coined. Does this mean that « the more it changes the
more it's the same thing ?)) And yet we have advanced far along the road since the « code)) of King Ham-
mourabi, of Babylon, who coldly condemned to death the son of the architect when a house collapsed
and killed the landlord's son... since the disillusioned statement of Plautus... since the revolt caused by the
quartering of Robert-Francois Damiens (engraving upper left) for having struck King Louis XV with a pocket
knife. It is this increasing struggle of the human conscience which will one day testify that « no one shall
be subjected to torture, or to cruel, inhuman or degrading treatment or punishment)).
Mars. Eleanor Roosevelt, Chairman of the
United Nations Human Rights Com-
missions, following the adoption of the
Universal Declaration of Human
Rights, declared :
"A great satisfaction should permeate the
thoughts of all men, for the great documents
declaring man's inherent rights and freedo : ns
which in the past have been written nationally,
are now merged in an international universal
declaration."
To the right, some of the national Documents of
Freedom which have marked the fight for human
rights during the past thousand years.
We must never forget recent scenes such
as these if we wish the Declaration of Human
Rights to be anything but an expression of
good intentions which could again pave the
way. to the hells of concentration camps.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
FIGHTERS
for
FREEDOM
Six Leadèrs A. Tnollg the
Countless Thousands
lL'ho have det'oted their
Lives to the Cause of
é. :
, 3
GROAT BRITAIN
MAGNA CART A (1215),
ONE of the outstanding European landmarks inthe constant struggle for individual liberty,
the Great Charter has been a source of inspiration
10 many who, in lale.-years, dedicated themselves
: 0 the cause of freedom. It defined the condi-
<- ; !'OM unr ! f.'/ ! : c/t tax'M ! / : t 6e/f ! ,/or&eï' : ions under which taxes might be levied, forbade
illegal imprisolllnent or seizure of property.
-"".",'J :., ;,'.
MAGNUS
LAGABOTERS LANDSLOV (1275)
F RO. ; W early times, every free man could speakat the lawmaking councils of Norway and
before the law all men were equal. The Landlov
was a re-codification by King Magnus the
Law-Mender of earlier provincial codes and
defines the powers of government and the sanc-
tity of man's person. It expressly forbids trial
m ! !/ ! OMf M procM ! o//a ! U aM MrM/ ! 0rtywithout due process of law and assures liberty
of the [-ress and of trade.
(NEMINEM CAPTIV ABIMUS ACTI
(1430)
THIS charter which may be compared withthe British Habeas Corpus Tact, expressly
forbids the imprisonment of any individual
without fair trial and thell only in accordance with
oro !  !/ !  tmprt ! OMMMf o/an_y : ? !  ! t) : Ma/
<f/ ! OMf/a !'  : r ! o/ aM r/ ! H o /y t'M accordaMM ! f !'t/ !
the laws of the land.
THE DECLARATION
OF INDEPENDENCE (1776) \
LARG EL Y the composition of Thomas Jef-
ferson, the Declaration set forth in powerful
prose the rational 18th century concept of the
"natural rights"of míw. As its author pointed
out, it was not intended to express any boldly novel
thought but rather to crystallize the prevailing
sentiment of the time. Its eloquence and force
produced a profound impression on {eoples of other
nations.
mmD
DECLARATION OF THE RIGHTS
OF MAN (1789)
DURING the first summer of the French Re-
volution, Frenchmen produced this state-
ment of t he liberties to which an Ùldivid
entitled. It maintains that men are born free
t1/id equal, proc ! aÙlls free-don ; G : f speech, se. : urity
and defense àgainst uppression,. it maintains that
laws are the expression of the general will of the
people, that no individual can exercise authority
over his fellow men unless elected by the people
and defines liberty as power to do anything that
does not injure others. This document was one
of the chief sources of inspiration 10 people in
other lands also srruggling to achie'L'e freedom.
EQUALITY OF THE SEXES-After a long
i. struggle, women in many parts of the world
have won equality with men. Today, women are
distinguishing thèmselves in business prafes-
sions, the arts, the sciences, medicine and
public hairs. Research workers, doctors, am-
bassadors or musicians, women are henceforth
on am equal footing with men... : 7. Times
"hote.',. j
INFERIOR BEING....,
Slave or goddess, treated-
either as a simple child or as an animal,
women for centuries have sought to win recognition
of their own human worth and dignity. The law
established the inequality of the sexes-and man
remained the master. <&lt; Thy banjo. nall feel the
measure of my blows 9 says the French text of
the engraving reproduced above.
HTS OF MAN
THROUGH THE AGES
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 8
]M UnioJlAlJ. f :Ú
(/)cAxA
Now therefore the General Assembly proclaims this Universal Declaration of
Human Rights as a common standard of achievement for all peoples and all
nations, to the end that every individual and every organ of society, keeping this
Declaration constantly in mind, shall strive by teaching and education to
promote respect for these rights and freedoms...
ARTICLE I.-Right to equolity.
ARTICLE 2.-Freedom from discrimination.
ARTICLE 3,-Right to life, liberty, personal security.'
ARTICLE 4.-Freedom from slavery.
ARTICLE 5.-Freedom from torture, degrading treatment.
ARTICLE 6.-Right to recognition as a person before the law.
ARTICLE 7.-Right to equality before the law..
ARTICLE 8.-Right to remedy by competent tribuna/.
ARTICLE 9.-Freedom from arbitrary arrest, exule.
ARTICLE 10.-Right to fair public hearing.
ARTICLE «.-Right to be considered innocent until proved guilty.
ARTICLE l2.-Freedom from interference with privacy, ramify, home, correspondence.
"The task is not finished. We should be less generous than prehistoric man it.
in our turn, we did not work to ensure for our children a more secure and
better life than our town."", :
Anatole France.
In. Brief
ARTICLE 13.-Right to free movement in and out of any country.
ARTICLE 14.-Right to asylum in other countries from persecution.
ARTICLE 15.-Right to a nationality and freedom to change ft.
ARTICLE/6.-Right to marriage and family.
ARTtCLE f7.-Right to own properly..
ARTICLE I8.-Freedom of belief and religion.
ARTICLE 19.-Freedom of opinion and information.
ARTICLE 20.-Right to peaceful assembly ond association.
ARTICLE 21.-right to participate in government, and in free
election..
ARTICLE 22.-Right to social security.
ARTICLE 23.-Right to desirable work and to join trade unions.
ARTICLE 24.-Right to rest and leisure.
ARTICLE 25.-right to adequate living standard.
ARTICLE 26.-Right to education.
ARTICLE 27.-Right to participate in the cultural life of community.
ARTICLE 28.-Right to social order assuring human rights.
ARTICLE 29.-Community duties essential.
ARTICLE 30.-Freedom from State or personal interference in the
above rights.
« Everyone has the
right to education."
Yet even to-day,
two-thirds o'the
world's children
still lack the schools
and the teachers to
help them to play
their rightful part
in the community.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Page 9-UNESCO COURIER
TT T is nine months since I took up my duties as Director-General. Ninc
months is a short time in the history of an organization, and often
no mor  than an episode in a man's life. But no period is short for o e
who must use every single moment for the maximum amount of
action.
As I drafted the report you are about to discuss, I thought at every
stage of the seriousness of this occasion ; in which I meet the General
Conference of Unesco face to face. And so this will be on my part an act
of self-examination ; Unesco would be but a mere bureaucratic mechanism
if it did not also provide the opportunity for frank and fruitful exchange
between those who have faith in its future.
unseen dividend
I will not here reiterate my report. You will, in looking through it, havebecome suffìcienllv aware of our endeavours and of our failures.
I might dwell on the former, but feel it my task rnther to stress the
tatter, so as to conceal nothing of the obstacles we have so far failed to
overcome.. This is, of course, scarcely the usual way for a managing
director to give an account of his stewardship to his board ; but Unesco
is no commercial undertaking. Investments in this venture-the contri-
Imlions of your peop) es, the work of our Secretariat-have as their
single purpose to assure to every man access to education, culture and
science, to the end that every man may in this way reach true personal
fultilment ; thus understanding others better, and be enabled in more en-
lightened fashion to serve the cause of human brotherhood.
Such benefits are not reckoned in francs or
dollars or pounds ; and yet, without this unseen
dividend, how precarious is the signilicance of
the others ! These material attributes of peace,
war can destroy at a stroke ; even in peace they
may be endangered should a mechanical inter-
dependence of material forces prevnil over a
faith and a hope based upon the moral solida-
rity of mankind and free cho-operation of men's
minds.
Facing these prospects, which Unesco may
only ignore at the cost of wif-alJdicat ion, you
will understand Why I am less struck by results
achieved than by obstacles not yet overcome.
woe must act quickly if we are not only to
reach our nearest goals, but to strengthen the
moral authority of our Organization.
In the course of my various travels this year
I met many who knew nothing of Unesco. They
were forthright and honest men who would not
wish to judge us with the elegant scepticism
adopted by certain high priests of culture ; they
were modest, vulllPI'aiJle men like ourselves ;
our brothers, for whom Unesco was created-
and yet to whom our very purpose is unknown ;
men to whom we have not stretched out our
hands to draw them to us, though they would
be our most devoted and ardent helpers and
friends, if they could only be made aware of
our existence.
This, gentlemen, is my real report to you. The
document you have in your hands details our
work in these past months (1) ; it is the Direc-
tor-Generat's account. But I am now adding my
report to you as a man ; and this I can do in a
handful of words : Unesco is still for the most
part a blueprint, and to bring it to full and
selective fruition vve must redouble our efforts.
Each year in conference we trace anew on
lhe blueprint the outlines of the building,
we adjust some detail of the fabric or the
plan, we debate the niceties of departmental
functions, we sum up what the Secretariat has
achieved and regret that it has been unable to
do more. But Unesco is not a Secretariat alone ;
il is an institution whose influence must extend
over the whole world, the Secretariat being no
more than as it were the nerve centre. Of
course it has its own part to play ; but first of
all it should help the other participants, above
all the Member States, to play their parts. Its
tasks are to receive and pass on the views of
the National Commissions, to see to it that no
requests and no replies go astray. We cannot
conch : vie a nerve centre, except in terms of the
living organism whose cohesion and action it
ensures. Yet in our case it is often as though,
my some strange physiological paradox, the ner-
vous system were still in search of its physical
organism.
BIueprÍnt and Fabric
r-]'HERE an'already, it is true, a number ofJ. Natio l Commission . But how many
of them meet regularly ? How many have
attempted to start local branches ? How man'
answer our enquiries, or endeavour to carry
out our programme ? Observers may say that
we are asking too much ; that our question-
naires are too numerous and end by becoming
a burden. And there is no doubt that we must
still improve the methods of work of the Se-
cretariat. Our documents would gain by being
more concise, and vve should allow more time
for answers to reach us. I will do my best to
bring about these improvements. Tlie Secre-
lariat should keep in constant touch with those
bodies which are the sources of its strength
and authority. Where National Commissions
are active and powerful, Unesco has begun to
break down the blank wall of general indiffe-
rence. Where Commissions do not exist, or
are out of touch with the realities, Unesco is
no more than a token.
The very nature of this Organization demands
that the peoples of all its Member States make
a similar effort-though graded to their
means-to participate in our work. Hence I
feel it my duty at the outset of this Fourth
Session of the General Conference to make an
appeal to you. Your discussions will give me
guidance and lines of policy. lour decisions
on the most important items on the agenda,
such as programme priorities-which govern
the distribution of the budget-the total of
the budget itself, the plan for technical assis-
lance for the economic development of the less
fortunate countries, will be of exceptional im-
portance for our future.
But the fundamental problem remains un-
touched : how are we to breathe purposeful and
varied life into these various nationat Unescos
in the several countries, whose steady partici-
pation can alone enable the international Unes-
co to develop ? You are about to examine the
duties which fall upon the State in regard to
education, science and culture, for the purpose
of ensuring a better understanding between
peoples. May I here stress once again what I
wrote at the end of the Report which is before
(1) A summary of this report'U'as published in the
special 32-page Conference issue of the Courier last
1/month.
you, and say onceagnin how much benefit
Unesco may draw from your debates on this
theme ?. '"
No Laboratory of Illusions
OF two truths I am convinced, and neitheris.. COllplet yitheut he other :. of thehistoric mission of Unesco, and of the
sincerity of the countries which have under-
taken to carry out that mission. I hope there-
fore that no one will misunderstand the
frankness with which I underline weaknesses
which are temporary and remediable. I trust
rather that you will mark in this outline of
mine, far from any pessimism which I would
deny, my concern for objectiveness.
I have a deep faith in Unesco, and that is
why I will not have it regarded as a collection
of symbols and a laboratory of illusions. The
idealism expressed in our Constitution is not
a smoke-screen, designed to conceal the hard
facts of reality from the simple-minded. We
are not merchants of day-dreams. The cam-
paigns we have launched against the economic
obstacles which impede the free circulation of
printed material is not an abstract struggle
waged with phrases and speeches, but a concrete
undertaking employing concrete means, namely,
international agreements submitted to govern-
ll1ents for signature.
.. Our Book Coupon Scheme, designed to enable
soft-currency countries to obtain books and
periodicals published in hard-currency coun-
tries, is hardly a metaphysical speculation. Our
educational missions to the Philippines and to
Thailand have had-just as the one now in
Afghanistan-to get hold of the human truths
underlying the problems they were sent to solve.
Whether or what action will be taken as a
result of their findings is not for us to deter-
mine. But the eager and trustful welcome ac-
corded to these missions in these countries
which had asked for them encourage us, since
it demonstrates that frontiers are not always
impassable barriers tao'positive international
action.
Mere Symbolist
THERE is nothing illusory, either, in the workof our scientific cooperation oflìcf's. The
requests for information and for advice
which they receive, the facts they have provided,
t the contacts they have established, are all rea-
listic and beneficial achievements. And wliat
could be more practical than our efforts
to increase the number of fellowships,
than our surveys of technical needs of
press, film and radio, than our endeavours
to improve the techniques of fundamental edu-
cation, or to mobilize private organizations on
behalf of the rebuilding of devastated countries ?
Without claiming undue credit for such emer-
gency help as woe have ourselves been able to
afford, I should like to remind you that this
very year, thousands of Arab and Greek chil-
dren have learnt to utter the name of Unesco
with affection.
Thus we do not \york in the abstract. And
yet we must acknowledge that, through inade-
quacy of means, our action is sometimes so
re ; ; : t ricted a ; ; : to appear merely symbolic.
In an undertaking such as ours, worldwide
in scope, quantity is often the pre-condi-
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 10
AN ACT OF SELF-EXAMINATION
-
There is here a living presence which governs all our
tasks : Twentieth Century Man. His presence, though
unseen, is our spur It spurs us because it commits us ; and
committing US, will judge us'
(Continued from page 9)
tin both of quality and of reality. Slated in
another way, tne question we face in our work
is not so much that, of taking initiative, as or
having the means-means in terms of men.
technicians and experts, in terms of finance.
cash and materials. without a concurrent and
combined increase in all these means, what we
call the concentration of our programme could
not but lead to sheer surrender. To concen-
trate is not to contract ; even less is it to para-
lyse..
I should not forgive myself if I allowed the
slightest doubt to exist as to my view of this
matter. I am in favour of concentration of our
programme ; we have been straining for months
towards that end. Even if we should concen-
trate all our projects into a single resolution
- for example, for the provision of fundamen-
tal education, which hundreds of millions of
men and women still lack-Unesco's existence
would still be justilied. But it would no longer
be justified if, having confined ourselves to this
single field, we further limited ourselves, as
we have far too often had to do in other parts
of our work, to the drafting of memoranda, the
despatch of prospectuses and bulletins, the
sending hither and thither of experts unprovi-
ded with the means to carry out the education-
al campaigns draw up on paper. We need only
thus reduce the notion of concentration of
programme to its absurd conclusion (0 see how
vital it is to give Unesco's work firm roots, and
II believe in the future
to go to the heart of situations which we have
hitherto done hardly more than catalogue.
There are still not very many fundamental
education. specialists,. some may object. But it
is not for us to direct the necessary funda-
mental education campaigns on the national
level. This requires a political authority which
we du not possess, and linanclal means to which
we cannot aspire. what is expected of us on
the international plane is that we should help
in planning campaigns, in perfecting techniques
and above all in increasing the number of spe-
cialists. That is indeed our purpose. Before the
Economic and Social Council's resolution of
4 March 1949, we had already devoted much
time and a not inconsiderable part of our re-
sources to technical assistance tasks. Yet if we
are to train qualified experts in sufficient num-
bers to avoid a Iragie failure to meet the world's
needs, we must prepare for immense efforts,
have the necessary time, and hp given increased
linancial resources.
The deeper we go into the problem which
at first we had to be content merely to skim,
the more clearly we realize that if L'nesco is to
serve the cause of peace, it must concentrate
on mankind's concrete needs. It must he
neither an academy preaching the virtues of
theoretical pacifism without considering the
ways of attaining peace, nor an institutiun
which, in the name of the primacy of the in-
tellect, regards culture as end in itself, ar-
lilicially set apart from the economic and social
factors which govern its growth.
Our mission then is both militant and prac-
tical. It rules out all « conformism ». There is
nothing less conformist than the programme
of our Organization. Is our aim to enable all
men to read and write a conformist one ? Or
our effort to make the Rights of Man known
in every teaching establishment ? Or our cam-
paign in favour of the free circulation of ideas' ?
If there is such a thing as a cultural force of
social change, then we are indeed the instru-
ment of that force. If there is a bold courageous
kind of peace-the antithesis of a peace of
resignation-then it is indeed that heroic
peace prescribed for all men in the Final Art
signed in London in 1945 not a truce imposed
hy weariness, but. a real peace, based on justice
and understanding. a peace built on the sense
of responsibility of each and all.
Let me dwrll on this point. The concord
which it is our duty to cement through educa-
tion, science and culture will be as nolhing if
the peoples of the wOrld do not found it on
freedom- freedom for all men, But can we
imagine effective freedom unless all men are
invested with genuine responsibility ? Let
others dangle before the unknowing the illusion
of freedom unearned, of rights without duties,
of
of such deceit. For our duty of all duties is II
understand, and to make it understood. that all
the problems of mankind merge into the one
/,/'II1, lI'lII of man's freedom ; and hat every free-
dom implies. whether for the community or the
individual. inescapable responsibilities. It was
in Paris under siege that the aged Miechele
repeated, with all The conviction of his youth,
his is famous utterance, that admirable profession
of faith in the fertilily of fl'ee will and. eIf-
decision : <&lt; I I believe the future. because
I make it >&gt;.'
But how can we inspire in every man the
consciousness of his responsibilities, if we do
not ourselves begin with a definition of those
which fall to this our own Organization ?
All those assembled here know and feel how
necessary Unesco is. More than ever before, the
clauses of the Constitution acquire the strength
of commandments. Neither politics nor ambition.
nor even the thirst for knowledge nor love of
the arts have brought us together. What binds
us together is the betief that the peoples must
understand and help one another. But it is vital
that this belief should remain continually live
within us and should inspire all our views and
policies.
Unesco, which will one day become the
living Republic of Minds, the organic hond be-
twern all men serving truth consciously, is
as yet in many respects no more than a piece
of administrative machinery. We know the dan-
get that has always beset all administrations.
They all too easily degenerate into soulless
mechanisms, where life is stifled ; where words
swallow up meaning, the letter destroys the
... because
I make it'
Michelet
spirit. other men's faces fade into mere concepts
the most moving experience dissolves into a
speech, into vague and lifeless affirmations.
Our first duty, in this mission which is assi-
gned to us is vigilance. We fighl against the
force of habit. The vigil on the eve of battle
is doubless often an occasion of austere gran-
deur. bul nobler still is the determination of
those who are conscious, as we'must all be
conscious, of taking part in the'night-watch
that precedes true peace.
Not from Olympus
Our eyes must remain wide open. Everyitem in the programme must remain
living, a fraternal inspiration, it is
in that spirit that the United Nation adop-
ted the Universal Declaration of the rights
of Man. The authors of that documents
did not sec themselves as historians. sub-
mitting for the applau"e of peciailists a
survey of our legislative inheritance. They
threw down a challenge ; and in that challenge,
though in thi language of lawyers, lives the
cry of man. Every right is a basic demand of
the individual, or of society ; it is an act of
defiance to the forces of injustice. These rights
do not flow down from Olympus as mysterious
gifts of benevolent lawgivers. They spring from
the peoples'needs. They voice the peoples'
deepest, desires.
when we enumerate man's rights, we are also
enumerating duties to be accomplished. None
touches us more nearly than the right to edu-
cation. Who can remain unmoved on reading
Article 26 of the Declaration :
« Everyone has the right to education.... Edu-
cation shall bc directed to the full development
of the human personality and to the strengthen-
ing of respect for human rights and funda-
ing. tolerance and friendship among all na-
tions...»
To these words, in our conscience others
echo : two-thirds of all men are illiterate, two-
thirds of the children alive today still await
schools and teachers to help them to become
responsible citizens, to make them free. They
still await the time when the right to education,
which now they ar unable to claim in writing,
To Concentrate is not to contract,
even less to paralyze
Human Rights and education go hand in hand. The
Preamble to Unesco's Constitution proclaims that
"wide diffusion of culture and the education of
humanity for justice and liberty and peace are
indispensable to the dignity of man".
ceases to be a phrase and becomes a reality.
Perhaps the) look to Unesco for just this Only,
it must be clearly underslood that this Unesco
to which the eves of mankind are turned is not
a house in the Avenue Kleber, nor a team of
technicians, nor a gathering of learued people,
nor an academy of thinkers :-it is, first and
foremost fifty governments.
What is true for education is similarly true
for culture and science.
« Eecl"yune >&gt;, stateS Artlicle 27 of the Decla-
ration, ( has the right freely to participate in
the cultural life of the community, to enjoy the
arts and to share in scientific advancement and
its benefits.
Culture  and Bread
Mex need culture in fact as much as they
need bread. They want their share ofmankinds spiritual inheritance, they de-
sire themselves to live its change and growth,
to attempt to enrich it. That must cume to
pass it they are tu be, in the full sense, men,
it the culture of their countries is to bp some-
Ihing Jibing. The future historian may admire
our puets, our painters, our musicians ; but it
is to be feared that he will add : thee great
wen were isolated individuals, living apart,
unknown of the people-of the <&lt; masses » as
the saving was. Those ( « masse » were born.
worked and died without sharing in a culture
for the sake of which they were nevertheless
asked from time to time to surrender their
possessions and their lives.
As to science, it is true that research has
blossomed impressively in certain lands and
brought them a plemtude of well-being and
power. But it is far from having developed
equally everywhere. There are other lands in
which all that is knawn of modern science is
the havoc which its wrongful use can cause.
The task is therefore in the first place to spread
the benefits of science everywhere, and still
more to foster the desire for science every-
where, to nurture the scientific spirit, to build
the foundations of science everywhere. To do
this, it is not enough to distribule manufactures
and to familiarize people with mere techniques.
What matters is that all peoples should be
able to equip their own laboratories and li-
braries, train their own specialists, inspire their
own research workers. Until these aims are
achieved, there can be no talk of the equality
of men before science.
What are you going to do, gentlemen, to
meet such great needs and such high duties ?
I can only listen to your debates with tense
expectancy. But, this expectancy will be more
t. han the natural concern felt bv evry inter-
national official for the future of his organiza-
tion : it will be the anxiety born of the faith
which I have placed in the will of the people
and the respect I hold for the indomi-
table hope that fills men's hearts. There are
doubtless hundreds of millions of men who
know nothing of the aims of this Conference
or of the verb purposes of Unesco. But it is
demanded of (his Conference, as it is demanded
of Unesco as a whole, not to answer these
miHions'unknowingness by knowing them not.
There is here a living presence which governs
all our tasks : Twentieth-Century Man, for whom
we must open the path of intellectual and
moral solidarity, which our Constitution pro-
claims as the essential foundation of world
peace. His presence, though unseen, is our spur.
It spurs us because it commits us ; and com-
mitting us, will judge us.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Page IT-UNESCO COURIER
GRLEK REFUGEES MUST HAVE AID
EACH member of a Greek refugee
family receives 1, 000 drachmae
f. (l0 cents) and 115 grammes of
bread per day. Only a miracle
of moral and physical resistance
has so far enabled these masses of
human beings to survive in the condi-
tions to which they have been subject-
ed. Il the refugees are not resettle
by next winter, it is to be feared that
under-uourishment will be followed by
serious epidemics.
The gravity of the refugee situation
in Greece and the urgent need for
relief measures on an international
scale were brought home to Unesco's
Executive Board on September 15, by
facts such as these, contained in a
report on Greece made by Professor
Paulo de Berredo Carneiro, of Brazil,
following a special mission to the war-
wracked country in July.
After hearing the report, the Exec-
utive Board submitted a resolution
for the approval of Unesco's General
Conference, now meeting in Paris,
recommending that a world appeal be
made to raise the S 47, 500, 000 required
for Greek educational and cultural
reconstruction. It also suggested the
creation of a special fund, under
Unesco's administration, and into
which contributions in response to
Unesco's appeal would be paid.
Professor Carneiro emphasized that
any educational reconstruction pro-
gramme would also require the solu-
tion of the larger problem posed by
the re-settlement of 700, 000 refugees
driven from their homes in Northern
Greece. The Executive Board there-
fore suggested that Unesco should call
on the United Nations to study the
possibility of providing international
help for this re-settlement work, for
which a total of S 93, 000, 000 is still
required.
IF the general situation in Greece istragic that of the refugee children
is particularty pitiful ; most have
never known any other way of life
than that of war and semi-starvation.
Professor Carneiro reports that 338, 000
boys and girls, one third of them
under six years of age, have emigrated
from the Northern provinces.
BEFORE THE WINTER
« nearly all these children are,
together with their families, refugees
in camps or communal dwelling)},
he says. ( (I have been able from my
contacts with them and from further
information... to gauge the fuli extent
or their phYJ ! cal misery and moral
dtstress.
( Their only food consists ot a
small ration of milk in the morning
and soup and bread during the day.
Owing to the lack of space, they live
in clæe quarters-width the adults, in
tents or rooms accommodating any-
thing between 6 and 10 persons.
« (Their extreme emaciation, pale
faces and terror-stricken look create
an extraordinary impression. From
dawn till dusk, these phantom chil-
dren wander hungrily around their
camps barefoot, with their clothes in
shreds, and their elders looking yon
compassionately but powerlessly...
« The little orphans and stray
children are looked rafter by the Organ-
ization that Her Majesty the Queen
of Greece has set up to assist them.
It is responsible for 18, 000 children,
wtco are accomodated in 52 colonies
(Paldopolis).
( (It is a moving thing to see the
ìlhys ; cal and mental transformation
which the children admitted to these
colonies undergo)}, adds Professor
Carneiro.
DEALING with the general problem ofrefugees and its repercussions, Pro-
fessor Carneiro stresses the extre-
me difficulty of the economi con-
dltions facing the Greek Government.
(\ The total number of men, women
and children who are refugees...
amounts to somewhat over 700, 000, or
10 % of the population. >&gt;, he says.
« (Thf' immediate result of their exodus
was a deep economic depression...
Impoverishmg about 1, 000, 000 : nhab :-
tants elsewhere.
«In all, 34 % of the population
today live on appropriations from tw
national budget... showing it is
impossible four Greece of itself to meet
the claims on its financial resources.
« The maintenance of these 700, 000
refugees has solar cost the GreeTi ;
Government a sum equivalent to
: : ; 85, 000, 000. If this state of things
were to continue, there would be no
hope of securing such international
assistance as would save Greece From
irreparable catastrophe. >&gt;
« rhe po ! : t ! cc s : tMat : 07t o : ues( (The political. situation gives
grounds for hope that the refugees
well gradually be able to return to
their fields and villages. This process,
however, will be extremely costly. The
refugees will be largely returning to
a scorchEd earth area ; they will have
to be gwen new homes, cattle, farm
buildings, clothing and agricultural
implements. Until the next harvest
the State will have to feed them.'
{ the total sum required to carry
out the resettlement IS $ 138, 000, 000.
Such is the economic and financial
problem that faces the Greek
Government and that it must settle
at an early date if worse is not to
befall. A sum of $ 50, 000, 000 has been
set aside from Marshall Plan funds as
a reserve for this purpose, but it
remains to find $ 93, 000, 000. >&gt;
« It would be useless to try to'
improve present educational and cur.
tural conditions in Greece before the
material recovery of the country as a
whole hand been brought about >&gt;, says
Professor Carneiro, { (If Unesco wants
to accomplish anything useful, sit
must first obtain from the United
Nations and its Specialized Agencies
the necessary help for the technical
re-equipment and resumption ot
Greece's agricultural and industrial
product n, >&gt;
THE Greek crisis, which is due to
the international troubles that
nave tragically affected the
country's political and economic life
since 1940, will only be solved with the
assistance of a world that is conscious
of its duties.
« It is in the name of culture that
Unesco must issue its appeal to the
whole world on behalf of Greek chil-
dren >j, concludes Professor Carneiro.
« Unesco is a cultural organization
and cou ; d therefore find no better
patrons for : ts enterpr : se than the
towering shades of those illustrious
Greeks who gave fresh impulse to art
philos') phy and science.
( (The little Greek who for threr
years has been a refugee in a camp tun
Epirus or Macedonia is the descendant
of this liTle of leaders that ushered tn
a new era for mankind.
« (Unesco will remind the children
of the world, who daily delight in the
songs af Iliad and the Odyssey,
contemplate the beauty of Greek
statuary, take their first lessons in
sreometry or astronomy, or revive the
debates of the Academy or the
Lyceum, that this mount at which
they quench their athirst has its source
: 7t the same Greece that asks of them.
to-day, a gesture of gratitude and
friendship. »
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
-,
SA VING
OUR
RESOURCES
by
Eleen
SA1Jl
PEOPLE uften think uf <&lt; prutectiun
of nature>&gt; as cuncerned onlY
with natiunal parks and reserves.
and the preservation of animal
and plant species threatened with extinc-
tion. But this Is only a limited part of
nature protection which Is concerned
with man's entire natural environment,
Including the earth's renewable natu-
ral resources. That these natural re-
sources are not inexllauslible is nu lung-
er in doubt. The problem is how to
utilize nature's resources for man's
henetlt and at the same time maintain a
balance between human demands and
the earth's productivity.
This is the problem which brought
together at Lake Success for three
weeks in August and September more
than six hundred scientists, engineers
and technologists from nearly sixty dif-
ferent countries and a score of interna-
tional organizations. Tile'were attend-
ing the United Nations Scientific Confer-
ence on the Conservation and Utilization
uf Resuurces (UNSCCUR) and the Inter-
national Technical Conference on the
Protection of Nature. The second confer-
ence was convened juintly by UNESCO
and the International Union for the
Protection of Nature. As Mr. Fairfield
Osborn, President of the Conservation
Foundation, said in one of the meet-
ings, the earth's resources are unim-
portant in themselves : man is depen-
dent on them, and it is his business to
see how they are used and how they
are distributed. But utilization in itself
creates other far-reaching problems.
T lIUS, while the economists and tench-nicians of UNSCCUR were ex-
clranging information on new
techniques fur wresting more wealth
from the earth's resources, the biolo-
gists and other scientists attending the
\a ! ure Protection Conference deliho'-
ated. uver the 1>o., siblr cun, equences lu
IIII' ! Jalance of nature, tllat is to suy
nature's natural state, of the e. L'ploil-
aliun of furmerly undat !/o]Jed region".
Tiley daoted three of their elaen spe-
('iali ; ed meetings to discussing the best
lecllltiques to be used in educating child-
ren and adults alike to a greater a]J) J/>e-
/"iation of nature, and to au ; areness o {
Ilteir responsibility to {uture generatio/l,'
for sa {eguarding nature's resources.
To exploit a natural resource in order
to get tile highest economic)"ip1--/with-
out considering the total biological
effect on the regions concerned and
perhaps eventually on the world, is
irresponsible and shortsighted. That is
why questions as to the effects of « pian-
ned enterprises on the balance of
nature, the possible consequences on
natural associations of the generalized
use of anti-parasitic products (DDT
etc.), and of the uncontrolled introduc-
tion of exotic species, were given spe-
cial attention. Several of the Resolutions
which the conference passed dealt with
the basic problem of keeping the ba-
lance of nature where interference by
man has also brought about destruction,
and protecting rare species from be-
coming extinct. This is one reason why
it is essential to maintain as wide a
variety as possible of representative
natural communities and environments.
They are a means of helping us to un-
derstand how to manage animal and
plant life, and how to apply scientific
knowledge in our social economic and
i I) d ustrla I life.
THE different aspects of nature pro-j tectiun are so varied-eduea-
tiunally, seientit1call\", aesthetical-
ly,-that tI ; ey clearly enìer within the
interests of other United nations Specia-
sized. agencies, such as \\"HO anù F, \O.
besides UNESCO. Thus one resolution
of the Conference calls on \VHO, FAO
and UNESCO to investigate the esta-
blishment of a Permanent Joint Com-
mission on Pesticides to deal with the
effective regulation of the use of insect
and other pest killers.
The significance of these two confer-
ences. front)) ie human point of view,
was illustrated by M Antoine Gilding.
LX. Deputy. \,, istJnl-Secretary-Gene-
ral for Economic Affair,, who stressed
their importance for the United Nations
programme of technical assistance.
<&lt; I Jill afraid >&gt;, he said, <&lt; that we shall
come lip against failures and seriousu  i t f il r   ri
difficulties if the human aspect of this
great programme is not examined with
care... I am sure that the results of
your work'sill he of great use to me. >&gt;
CARTOONS'ANI)'FILMs
IN
CHINA
A TEACHING technique which hasproved its value in education Is
the use of audlo. visual mate-
rials such as films, filmstrips, radio
and charts. Such materials, capable
of conveying basic ideas and know
ledge without the use of written words.
are of special use in fundamental
education.
There is, however, a grpat shortage
of materials suitable for this branch
of education and it was this need that
prompted Unesco, towards the end 01
1948. to launch n project for the pre-
paration of sample audit-visual ma
terials for fundamental education.
In view of the promising work
already carried out in this field by
China. Unesco asked Mr Hugh Hub-
bard, its regional representative there,
to discuss the project with the Chinese
authorities.
The original plan was to make the
experiment a joint enterprise between
Unesco and three Chinese agencies-
the Chinese Mass Education Move-
ment, the Kiangsu Provincial College
at Wusih and the Audio-Visual Centre
of Nanking University.
EARLY this year, however, comma.E nieation  between Eastern and
Western China became extremely dif-
ficult owing to the war in China and
it was decided to carry out the project
in the experimental"field"of the
Mass Education Movement at Pehpei,
about 25 miles north of Chungking.
Here, in West China, virtually cut
off from the coast where most of the
technical facilities are situated, the
project team is forced to work with
very limited equipment and facilities.
The purpose of the project was to
prepare sets of filmstrips and posters,
slides, cards, plays or other dramatic
Mr Norman McLaren. o (Canada's National Film Board, recently arrive) n
China to join Unesco's Audio-Visual Project team. Above, he applies his
original technique of drawing cartoons directly on film. (C : NFB rhot,,).
at Huang Ke Chen where a campaign
for vaccination, without the use of
visual aids, was launched by the Mass
Education Movement a few weeks be-
fore the experiment. As a result of
the use of audio-visual aids, many
more people came in and asked to be
vaccinated.
To test the effectiveness of the new
materials, two local areas, Shih Tze
Hsiang and Kuang Ke Chen have
been chosen, each having a popula-
tion of about 11, 000 people. The
surveys in these areas will be carried
out by the sociology department of the
College of Rural Reconstruction at
Pehpei, which co-operates closely with
the project activities.
Although the material limitations
l1h'an hardship for the staff, the value
of the project gains by the fact that
the experience obtained will be useful
ill the future, for technical facilities
are likely at best to be rudimentary
III most"fundamental education"
arenas.
The audio-visual project will pro-
bably be completed by the end of 1949,
after which a report on the work will
be published and samples of the mate-
rials produced made available to the
governments of Unesco's Member
States.
media with human or puppet actors,
recordings for broadcasts and a short
16 mm. animated cartoon film.
As one of China's greatest needs is
"education for-health", the topic
chosen for the project's productions
was"A Healthy Village"so as to illus-
trate, simply but vividly, to the Chi-
nese peasants the rules of hygiene and
means of protection against disease.
Later, it was decided to prepare
materials on such subjects as smallpox
and vaccination, trachoma, safe drink-
ing water and food, the use of D. T. T.,
health habits and tetanus.
By the end of May, the team hadproduced three hand coloured
filmstrips ; four wall posters, hand-
bills and a connected plctun'on vac-
cination ; five sets of drawings for Him
strips, posters, handbills and a picture
story on trachoma. Work is now
being done on the subjects of safe
drinking water and food.
In August, Mr Norman McLaren,
head of the Animation Department of
the National Film Board of Canada,
flew to China as a special technical
adviser to the project staff, which
includes six Chinese artists. During
his four months'assignment, Mr Mc-
Laren will train the artists in anima-
tion techniques for the eventual pre-
paration of a cartoon film.
The first practical application of the
materials already prepared was made
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
OF HUMAN RIGHTSUNIVERSAL DECLARA
ARTICLE I All hUman, beings, are born. free
all equal In dignity and rights.
They arc endowed with reason and conscience
<lnd should act towards one another in a spirit
of brotherhood.
ARTICLE 2 l. Everyone is entled to all the
rights and freedoms set forth in
Unis Declaration, without distinction of any
kind, such as race, colour, sex, language, reli-
gion, political, or other opinion, national or so-
cial origin properly, birn or other status
. Furthermore, no distinction shall be made
on the basis of the political, jurisdictionnal
or international status of the country or terri-
lury to which a person belongs, whether it be
independent, trust, non-self-governing or under
any other limitation of sovereignty.
ARTICLE 3 Everyone has the right to life,
 liberty and security of person.
ARTICLE 4 No one shall be held in slavcry
 or servitude ; slavery and the
slave trade shall be prohibited in all their
forms.
 No one shall be subjected tor-
ture or to cruel, inhuman or
degrading treatment or punishment : \lllllg
 ARTICLE 6 Everyone has the right to recog-
nition everywhere as a person
before the law
ARTICLE 7 All are equal before the law and
 arc entitled without any discri-
munation to equal protection of the law. All
are entitled to equal protection against any dis-
crimination in violation of this Declaration and
against any incitement to such discrimination.
ARTICLE 8 Everyone has the right to an
effective remedy by the compe-
tent, national tribunals for acts violating the
fundamental rights granted him by the constitu-
tion or by law,
 No one shall he subjected to ar-
 bitrary arrest, detention or exile.
 Evcryunc is entitled in full
equality to a fair and public
hearning by an independent and impartial tribu-
nal, in the determination of his rights and
obligations and of any criminal charge against
him.
 ARTICLE II. Everyone charged with a pe-
nal offence has the righL to be
presumed innocent until proved guilty accor-
ding lu law in a public Lrial at which he has
had all the guarantes necessary for his de-
fence.
2. No one shall he held guilty of any penal
offence on account of any act or omission which
did not constitute a penal offence, under national
or international law at the time when it was
COMPLETE TEXT ADOPTED ON 10 DECEMBER 1948 BY THE GENERAL ASSEMBLY OF UNITED NATIONS,)
AT THE PALAIS DE CHAILLOT PARIS
2. Everyone has the right, of equal access tu
public scrvicc in his country.
3. The will of thc people shall be the basis
of the authority of government ; this will shall
be expressed in periodic and genuine elections
which sllall be by universal and equal suffrage
and shall be held by secret vote or by equivalent
free voting procedures.
 Iveryune, as a member of socio-
ty, has the right (0 social secu-
rity and is enl idcd to realization, through na-
tional elIort and intcmational eo-opcration und
in accordance with the organization and re-
sources of each State, of the economic, social
and cultural rights indispensable for his dignity
and the free development of his personality.
ARTICLE 23 1. Everyone has the right to
 work, to free choice of employ-
ment, to jusl and favourable condilions of work
and to protection against unemployment.
2. Everyone, without any discrimination, has
the right to equal pay for equal work.
3. Everyone who wurks has the right to just
and favourable remuneration ensuring for hun-
self and his family an existence worthy of hu-
man dignity, and supplemented, if necessary, by
other means of social protection.
4. Everyone has the right to form and to
join trade unions for the protection of his
interest.
ARTICLE 24 Everyone has the right to rcst
 and leisure, including reasonable
limitation of working hours and periodic holi-
days with pay.
ARTICLE 25 I. Everyone has the right to a
standard of living adequate for
till) health and well-being of himself and of
group unit of society and is entitled to protec-
lion by society and the State.
ARTICLE 17 t. Everyone has the right to own
property alone as well as in as-
sociation with others.
2. NO one shall be arbitrarily deprived of his
property.
 Everyone has the right to free-
ARTICLE 18 dom of thought, conscience and
religion ; lids right includes freedom Lo change
his religion or belief, and freedom, either alone
or in community with others and in public or
private, to manifest his religion or beiief in
teaching, practice, worship and observance.
 Everyone has the right, to free-
dom of opinion and expression ;
this right includes freedom to hold opinions
without interference and to seek, receive and
impart information and ideas through any me-
dia and regardless of frontiers.
ARTICLE 20 . Everyone has the right to
freedom of peaceful assembly
and association
2. No one may be compelled to belong to an
association.
 I. Everyone has the right to take
part in the government of his
country, direclly or through freely chosen rep-
resentatives
committed. Nor shall a heavier penally be impo-
spd than the one that was applicable at the
time the penal offence was committed.
ARTICLE 12 No one shall be subjected to ar-
bilrary interference with his pri-
vucy, family, nome or correspondence, nor to
attacks UpOn his honour and reputation. Every-
one has the right lo the protection of the
law against such interference or attacks.
 ARTICLE 13 I. Everyone has the right to
 freedom of movement and resi-
dence within the borders of each State.
2. Everyone has the right to leave any coun-
try, including his own, and to return to his
country.
 L Everyone has the right to
seek and to enjoy in other coun-
Lries asylum from persecution.
2. This right may not be invoked in the case
of prosecutions genuinely arising from non-
pobtical crimes 0r from acts contrary to the
purpose and principles of the United Nations.
ARTICLE 15 1. Everyone has lhe right lo a
nationality.
"2. No one shall be arbitrarily deprived of his
nalionalily nor denied the right to change his
natiotiaiity.
 ARTICLE 16 I. Men and women of full age,
without any limitation due to
race, nationalily or religion, have the right to
marry and to found a family. They are entitled
to equal rights as to marriage, during marriage
and at its dissolution.
2. Marriage shall be entered into only with
Lhe free and full consent of the intending
spouses.
3. The family is the natural and fundamental
his family, indudiug food, clothing housing
and medieal eare and necessary social services,
and the rigllL to security iu the event of
unemployment, sickness, disability. widow-
hood, old age or other lack of livelihood in
circumstances beyond his control
:. 2 Motherhood and childhood are entitled to
special care and assistance. All children
wnethers born in or out of wedlock, shall enjoy born in or out of wedlock, shal  enjoy
the same social ; protection
ARTICLE 26 I. Everyone has the righL to
education. Education shall be
free at least in the elementary and funda-
mental stages. Elementary education shall be
compulsory. Teehnical and professional educa-
tion shall be made generally avaible and higher
education shall be equally accessible to all on
one basis of merit.
2. Education shall be directed to the full
development of the human personality and to and to
une strengthening of respect for human rights
and fundamenal freedoms It shall promote
understanding, tolerance and friendship amongl
all nations, racial or religious groups, and shall
further the activities of the United Nations for
the maintenance of peace.
3. Parents have a prior right to choose the
kind of education that shall be given to their
children
ARTICLE 27 1. Everyone has the right freelyto participate in the cultural
life of the community, to enjoy the arts and
lu share in scientific advancement and its
benefits.
2. Everyone has the right to the protection
of the moral and material interests resulting
from any scientific, literary or artistic produc-
tion of which he is the author.
ARTICLE 28 Everyone is entitled to a social
and international order in which
the rights and freedoms set forth in this
Declaration can be fully realized
 ARTICLE 29 I. Everyone dulies to the
community in which atone the the
free and full development of his personality is is
possible.
2. In the exercise of his rights and freedoms,
everyone shall be subject only to such limita-
tions as are determined by law sotety for the
prupose of securing due recognition andrespect
for the rights and freedoms ofothers and of
meeting the just requirements ofmorality
public order and the general welfare in a demo- in a demi-
cratic society.
3. These rights and freedom may in no case
be exereised contrary to the purposes and
principales of the United Nations.
ARTICLE 30 Nothing in this Declaralion may
 be interpreted as implying for
any State, group or person any right to engage
in any activity or to perform any act aimed at
t the destruction of any of the rights and
freedom set, forth herein.
]]>
</page>
</document>
