<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074678eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
s^&4
MARCH 1984 - 6 French francs»
r^C*/.-'r-Ä
;,"-^ ^
¿të*
^É?í'
ist!
C
/IV
ir /¡r^rw*
i
/ r
X
aH . jA . S^j'. ^i
Ha i,:,!1'-,^'» aBaaal
^^^^fe«a^^^^;^:â|^
BHBBBjV
sUllv^^'Ä^^¿^v^feM^> -&*s ¡r v/;^v^H
THE LIVING CULTURE OF THE TAMILS
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Pause for peace
I
T must be considered both absurd and intolerable that people in all countries should
live in dread of global war, a war which, whether by design or accident, would
inevitably involve a nuclear confrontation.
It is not only that future possibility but its present manifestations that we contemplate
with horror. The increasingly dangerous rhetoric and threats that are bandied about, the
violence that already rages in many countries, the insane arguments that are heard in
favour of increasing still further stockpiles of weapons that are already capable of
destroying the world ten times over these things are even now distorting our daily lives
and playing havoc with the world economy and with the hopes of humanity.
How can we and how can our children, make plans for a peaceful, productive life
when we read that a poll of citizens in a certain town showed they would commit mass
suicide rather than face such a war? How can we live normal, useful lives when the
world's leading scientists tell us we are only a few minutes away from doomsday? What
kind of consolation is it to be told without a word of pity for the survivors that fifty
per cent of the world's population might survive the nuclear holocaust?
Motivated by the growing conviction that the peoples of the world must themselves
assume responsibility for peace, as the representative of Greece, I proposed to the
General Conference of Unesco in Paris last October that, at the stroke of noon on the
first day of spring, 22 March, everywhere in the world, North, South, East and West,
all activity should cease for one minute: for that one minute all traffic should come to
a standstill, workers in factories should lay down their tools, teachers and pupils in their
classrooms and judges in their courtrooms should stand, sessions should be suspended
in the parliaments of the world, and in barrack-rooms and on training-grounds soldiers
should join in a worldwide affirmation that the resolute demand of all is for peace.
I was extremely heartened by the adoption of this proposal in the form of a General
Conference Resolution. I now appeal to Unesco and its Member States, using all the
means at their disposal, to undertake at once a world campaign to publicize this resolu¬
tion and to enlist universal participation. I know that the time for doing so is short, but
time is short in a much deeper sense.
Melina Mercouri
Minister of Culture and Sciences
The Hellenic Republic
The General Conference...
Appeals to Member States to set aside on 22 March 1984, on the stroke of noon, one minute during
which all men, women and children, irrespective of their occupations, will stop their activities in order
to demonstrate, unanimously, their desire for peace, international understanding and universal co¬
operation.
(Resolution adopted at the twenty-ninth plenary meeting, on 23 November 1983).
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
MARCH 1984 37th YEAR
Published in 27 languages
English Tamil Korean
French Hebrew Swahili
Spanish Persian Croato-Serb
Russian Dutch Macedonian
German Portuguese Serbo-Croat
Arabic Turkish Slovene
Japanese Urdu Chinese
Italian ' Catalan Bulgarian
Hindi Malaysian Greek
A selection in Braille is published quarterly
in English, French, Spanish and Korean
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 58 French Francs; 2 years (valid only in
France): 100 French Francs
Binder for a year's issues: 46 FF
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
ISSN 0041 - 5278
No. 3 - 1984 - OPI 84-1 - 408 A
page
THE LIVING CULTURE OF THE TAMILS
by S. Ramakrishnan
SCENES FROM EVERYDAY LIFE
by Sundara Ramaswamy
12 RICE AND RITUAL
The Tamil art of cooking
by Thilaka Baskaran
14 GATEWAY TO THE GODS
1. Sermons in stone
2. Images in bronze
by R. Nagaswamy
25 REFLECTIONS ON SIVA NATARAJA
by Auguste Rodin
26 BHARATA NATYAM: AN ANCIENT ART REBORN
28 VILLAGE GODS AND HEROES
Photo story
32 POETRY IN A LANDSCAPE
The world of Sangam
by François Gros
34 NEW WRITING IN TAMIL
by S. Ramakrishnan
36 TAMIL WOMEN AT THE CROSSROADS
by C. S. Lakshmi
38 THREE GREAT SCIENTISTS
JHIS issue of the Unesco Courier
presents through a mosaic of
texts and pictures some aspects
of the life and culture of the Tamil peo¬
ple, the overwhelming majority of
whom live in the State of Tamil Nadu in
the extreme southeast of the Indian
peninsula.
This culture is remarkable on many
counts, not least because Tamil is the
oldest of India's modern languages it
has been cited as "perhaps the only ex¬
ample of an ancient classical tongue
which has survivedfor more than 2,500
years with its basic structure intact". In
addition to Tamil Nadu, where it is the
State language, Tamil is also spoken by
an estimated four million people who
live in Sri Lanka, Burma, Malaysia, In¬
donesia, the Socialist Republic of Viet
Nam, parts of East and South Africa,
Guyana, and islands in the Indian
Ocean, the South Pacific and the
Caribbean.
The present issue, which consists
largely of contributions from Tamil
writers and scholars, looks at the pre¬
sent as well as the past of a developing
society searching for a fruitful relation¬
ship between ancient traditions and
modern life, between city and coun¬
tryside, between indigenous forms of
creativity and outside influences.
In a scene-setting article current
trends in the social and cultural life of
Tamil Nadu are charted by S.
Ramakrishnan. Other aspects of the
contemporary situation are evoked in
articles on modern movements in Tamil
literature and on the changing status of
women, and in a text in which poet and
novelist Sundara Ramaswamy captures
something of the flavour of everyday
life.
Turning to the past glories of Tamil
culture, François Gros examines the
highly sophisticated techniques of
sangam poetry, the very early Tamil
writings supposedly produced in three
sangams, or academies, in the city of
Madurai. Other distinctive historical
contributions. of the Tamils to world
culture are the great Hindu temples
with their towering gopuram
(pyramidal gateways) and decorative
sculptures, and the remarkable bronze
images ofHindu divinities. In addition
to an analysis of these achievements, we
have discoveredfor our readers a little-
known text in which the great French
sculptor Auguste Rodin thinks aloud as
he contemplates with an artist's eye a
masterpiece of Tamil art, a bronze
statue o/Siva Nataraja, the Lord of the
Dance.
Finally three areas in which past and
present are one: the cult of local gods
and heroes whose colourful statues
adorn the villages of Tamil Nadu;
Tamil gastronomic traditions; and the
classical dance known as Bharata
Natyam which was for centuries per¬
formed in the great temples and which
today, brought to the stage, is cap¬
tivating audiences in Tamil Nadu and in
many other countries too.
With this issue the Unesco Courier
remains faithful to its vocation to pro¬
mote intercultural contact and to make
the achievements of the world's great'
cultures more widely known.
COVER : Detail of the Sri Kapaliswarar tem¬
ple, Madras
Photo © Jean-Baptiste Faivre, Pans
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
t
9 * +
&
THE words "Tamil culture" im¬
mediately evoke the image of the
towering gopuram (entrance
gateways) of the Hindu temple, at once a
commanding grandeur and solemnity; of a
beautiful dancing girl, decked out in all her
finery, graceful and lovely; to the literary
minded, of the squatting sage Tiruvalluvar
with his palm-leaf and stylus; to the
gastronomically inclined, of idli (a rice and
lentil batter) and sambar (lentils, vegetable
and tamarind).
When we attempt to understand what
constitutes Tamil culture in terms of an
average man's life, particularly in the con¬
text of the present day, we encounter
elements which cannot be isolated and
defined, yet are deep rooted in a society
which has always been instinctively aware
of its strengths and weaknesses.
Over the centuries Tamils have spread
outside their territory and in this process
have planted signs of their presence many
of which can be found even today. The
Tamil community thus represents a popula¬
tion outside Tamil Nadu also. In their own
land Tamils have been subject to significant
foreign influences and, today, the admix¬
ture of these influences is so complex that it
is difficult to talk about "typical" or
"native" Tamil culture. Today's fashions,
food habits, life-styles, values are all pro¬
ducts of this long history of interaction.
For the first time in the known history of
two thousand years the land of the Tamils
has definite boundaries and this has
brought about a greater cohesion among
Tamils. Particularly since Independence
and the creation of States based on
linguistic regions, Tamils have had a land
with which to identify their language and
culture. With the introduction of Tamil as
a medium of education at all levels, an at¬
tempt has been made to update the
language after it lay submerged and sub¬
jugated for nearly three hundred years
under the impact of the English language.
The recent establishment of a university
at Thanjavur Tamil University crystall¬
izes the aspirations of their society. The ob¬
jective of this university is to strengthen the
various applications of the language in a
modern context and to enquire systema¬
tically into its past so that a relationship can
be established between tradition and
modern life.
m 4
The emotional togetherness that has
come about has been aided by the planned
economic activities in the State. The most
striking result of the economic programmes
is the high degree of mobility seen among
the people. Tamil Nadu is among the very
few States in India in which almost every
village is connected by road or rail. This
^
S. RAMAKRISHNAN is a qualified econo¬
mist and social scientist who began his career
in marketing. A few years ago he founded a
publishing company to promote the dissemi¬
nation of new, high quality Tamil literature. He
is closely associated with the Kafadataba
literary movement.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The living culture
of the Tamils
by S. Ramakrishnan
mobility has affected the personal,
economic and social life of average Tamils.
The facility of communication has began to
narrow down regional differences in life
styles.
A mobile population is an informed
population. Tamil Nadu is one of the States
in the country with a high rate of literacy.
It must be remembered that one of the first
three universities to be established during
the colonial era (1857) was at Madras, the
present capital of Tamil Nadu. Educational
facilities are growing so rapidly that bet¬
ween 1979 and 1981 the number of boys at
higher secondary schools increased by 45. 1
per cent and that of girls by 66.5 per cent.
Education is no longer confined to tradi¬
tional general education. It has diversified
and new branches of training are constantly
evolving. While the number of universities
offering general education has risen,
separate universities for technical subjects
have also been established. Tamil Nadu
now has one Agricultural University, one
engineering and technological University,
as well as a National Institute of
Technology. Significantly too, women are
entering professional colleges in increasing
numbers.
In Tamil Nadu, the reading habit is
widespread. Every week 1.73 million copies
of eight popular magazines are sold and
read by approximately 8.5 million people.
In one segment of the reading public the
urban Tamils42 per cent of those above
fifteen years of age read a daily newspaper
and 46 per cent read a weekly publication.
The second most widely read weekly in In¬
dia is a Tamil weekly.
These magazines shape public opinion on
all vital issues, but their main motive is
entertainment. They cater for popular
tastes; the three most common themes are
cinema, religion and politics almost in
that order of importance. Cinema gossip
and news dominate.
There are no large-circulation magazines
catering for specialist tastes and preferences
and serious writers have to find another
forum in the small-circulation magazines.
A far more influential medium in Tamil
is the cinema (see box page 1 1). More than
a sixth of the total number of permanent
theatres in India are in Tamil Nadu. This
gives some indication both of the extent of
rural electrification (99 per cent of all
towns, villages and hamlets have been elec¬
trified) and of the penetration of the cinema
into rural areas.
The popularity of the cinema is maintain¬
ed and increased by the popular magazines.
Similarly the commercial channel of the
government-controlled radio is dominated
by film music and programmes on films.
In Tamil Nadu the demands of the film
world gave birth to a "poster-culture".
When talkies were introduced, the popula-
MILESTONES
IN TAMIL HISTORY
\
INDIA L^V 1 BAY
ANDHRA /
PRADESH /
\tamil nadu^ l*s
lu J A.Í *4
\jm y^~< > "^
vH Hf
\^Ft\ ¿r . ~~i i H
W{\ ^T ^ r- . i~-'VÍ J »
\S JK Ba^galor
' jy1 fy* "~v- T
A^j \^¿/ Kanchipuram» J@9S
"""- /"* v. 'n.y Mahabalipuràrn~2Hj
\
KARNA>AKA j S^ /
V
x*> ^J y jTSbndicherry
-i-v r / Salem í
V. Í--VJ2.637 ml I s¿z^L^^B
I r Coimbatore S^_auv_ery ^^^ BB
Ä KERALA ^ Ti,uchi,apalli^^^^^JN,ga(jamilm
\ I N N«
\ * )~J^KP
\ ^S*\ 1
A .' /> ^~^< Madurai ^bH _^\
l\ Vi ^-v / ^CO^
\\ in \^ M T^yvJ
1 V *""*? ^s^^H v^
\ f ^Xl
^» Tuticorinl
V. iPalayankottai ^^H I
i^feu Tnujndrum SRI
\C s*' K LANKA
INDIAN OCCAN 1
1	 	 '	 ' t 1H
JHE TAMIL LANGUAGE is the official language of the State of
TAMIL NADU (population over 48 million) in southeast India and
is also spoken by some 4 million people living in Sri Lanka, Burma,
Malaysia, Indonesia, as well as parts of east and south Africa and islands in
the Indian Ocean, the South Pacific and the Caribbean. There is a scholarly
literature in Tamil dating back to the early centuries of the Christian era. The
language is o/DRAVIDIAN origin. The DRAVIDIANS were the founders
ofone of the world's most ancient civilizations, which already existed in India
sometime before 1000 BC when the ARYANS invaded the sub-continent
from the north. The Aryans, who spoke the SANSKRIT language, pushed the
Dravldians down into south India. Today 8 of the languages ofnorthern and
western India (including Hindi) are of Sanskrit origin, but Sanskrit itself is
only spoken by Hindu Brahman priests in temple worship and by scholars.
In southern India, 4 languages of Dravidian origin are spoken today. Tamil
is the oldest of these.
THE HISTORY OF TAMIL NADU begins with the 3 kingdoms, CHERA,
CHOLA and PANDYA, which are referred to in documents of the 3rd cen¬
tury BC. Some of the kings of these dynasties are mentioned in SANGAM
LITERATURE (see article page 32), and the age between the 3rd century BC
and the 2nd century AD is called the SANGAM AGE. At the beginning of
the 4th century AD the PALLAVAS established their rule with Kanchipuram
as their capital. Their dynasty, which ruled continuously for over 500 years,
left a permanent impact on the history of Tamil Nadu, which was during this
period virtually controlled by the PALLAVAS in the north and the PAN-
DYAS in the south.
In the middle of the 9th century a CHOLA ruler established what was to
become one of India's most outstanding empires on account of its ad¬
ministrative achievements (irrigation, village development) and its contribu¬
tions to art and literature. THE AGE OF THE CHOLAS is considered the
golden age of Tamil history.
Towards the end of the 13th century the Cholas were overthrown by the
LATER PANDYAS who ruledfor about a century and were followed by the
VIJAYANAGARA DYNASTY, whose greatest ruler was Krishnadeva Raya
(1509-1529), and the NAYAKS of Madurai and Tanjore. THE COLONIAL
AGE opened in the' 17th century. In 1639 the British East India Company
opened a trading post at the fishing village of Madraspatnam, today
MADRAS, the capital of Tamil Nadu. In 1947, India achieved IN¬
DEPENDENCE. The overwhelming majority of the population of Tamil
Nadu is HINDU, with active CHRISTIAN and MUSLIM minorities.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
<
Cigarettes, betel leaves, fruit and soft drinks are the principal wares of this typical village shop near Madurai.
tion was largely illiterate and magazines
were only just beginning to appear. Posters
were the only major medium to announce
new films. Now poster-oriented publicity
has spread to other areas of public life and
today one finds the walls of Tamil Nadu
plastered with posters, with those for the
cinema still the largest and most colourful.
The high rate of literacy and the degree of
worker mobility have contributed to the
process of industrialization in Tamil Nadu.
As a result of a planned economic pro¬
gramme a wide range of industrial products
6
are manufactured in Tamil Nadu creating
an incredible range of industrial and con¬
sumer products and large-scale cement, fer¬
tilizer, refining and automobile industries.
The latest addition is the construction of an
atomic power plant to meet the energy
needs of a growing society.
Textile and leather industries have tradi¬
tionally been strong in Tamil Nadu. Two
major ports cater for the needs of industry
and a well-organized transport system
keeps people and goods on the move. In
order to create local employment and to
prevent large scale migration to cities,
dispersal of industry is encouraged by a well
thought out system of incentives. A big
chain of industrial estates for medium and
small-scale industries in the non-traditional
areas has been established in an attempt to
minimize regional imbalances. Thus both in
technology and end-products Tamil Nadu
has revealed pronounced adaptability to
change.
Industrialization has brought about
dramatic change in peoples' life styles and
mode of working. Farm equipment, fer-
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Above, street scene in Madras
(Chennai to Tamil-speakers),
capital of Tamil Nadu and the
fourth largest city in India: in the
background, the imposing towers
of Madras University (founded in
1857). With its advanced centres
of research in plant pathology,
physics, biophysics and Indian
philosophy, Madras University is
the hub of a rapidly expanding
educational system. Economic ac¬
tivity is aided by an effective
transport system and high popula¬
tion mobility. Tamil Nadu is one of
the very few States in India in
which almost every village has a
road or rail link. Some 6,000 local
and express buses, operated by
both government and private
transport agencies, cover some
1.27 million kilometres every day.
ranging from pressure cookers to grinders
have replaced traditional modes of cook¬
ing, offering new leisure opportunities to
the housewife in a family structure which
has changed much.
Industrialization brings in its wake ur¬
banization. Tamil Nadu has the second
highest urban population in India. The
migration of rural populations to the town
and the transformation of rural areas into
new industrial, urban areas continue
unabated. This has brought about enor¬
mous pressure on space in the urban areas.
Housing is becoming more and more dif¬
ficult; open spaces are filled with concrete
blocks; slums are growing; sanitary condi¬
tions crumble under the impact; water
facilities are becoming inadequate; children
have less space to play. Traditional house
architecture is disappearing and today,
flats, with their cell-like rooms and limited
moving space are the reality. Although the
Government is making efforts to alleviate
the problem through housing and slum
clearance programmes, the requirements
are fast outstripping the efforts.
These changed conditions have resulted
in a need to adapt traditional modes to the
new constraints. Women are more free and
have better opportunities to get education
and jobs. However, they continue to be
bound by traditional tasks and modes of
behaviour such as looking after the home
and maintaining a distance from men. Even
dividuals' chart (see photo story page 8).
Religion continues to be a dominant
force in the lives of Tamils. In fact, one
observes a more pronounced increase in the
interest in religion and occult beliefs. At a
time when the average man's life is deter¬
mined by economic motives and security,
this may be the new kind of insurance he
seeks against economic and physical
insecurity.
Observance of religious ceremonies is
marked among the newly educated,
employed population both men and
women. The spread of electronics is helping
religious activity; cassettes, discs and
microphones have invaded places of wor¬
ship. Educated middle-class housewives
organize bhajan (worship through song)
groups in towns and it is not an uncommon
sight to see women commuters on their way
to work absorbed in the reading of simple
stotras (poems in praise of deities). No im¬
portant function, domestic or business is
organized without consulting the almanach
and fixing an auspicious hour. Magazines
pour out information on the movements of
astral bodies and their effect on the average
Tamil's life.
Was the traditional culture of the Tamils
merely the culture of a particular class?
Whether in literature, music or philosophy,
was the thinking that of the dominant
group? It is said that Sangam literature does
not mention caste differences, but the ma¬
jority of people can have had little access to
Tamils are avid readers of newspapers and magazines. Some one and
three-quarter million copies of eight popular magazines are sold each
week and among urban Tamil adults 42 per cent regularly read a daily
newspaper and 46 per cent a weekly magazine.
tilizers and micro-nutrients have altered the
agricultural scene. Increasing numbers of
farmers are installing motor-pumps to draw
water, dispensing with traditional methods
and, in the process, sweeping away into
disuse and oblivion their charming and
evocative work songs.
The electronics industry with its tran¬
sistors, stereos and television sets has
changed the rural landscape, offering new
forms of entertainment and providing
employment to increasing numbers of
school-leaving girls. Domestic appliances
in Madras city, there are still State Govern¬
ment buses meant exclusively to carry
women during peak hours.
Marriage as an institution is a good ex¬
ample of how tradition and modernity can
co-exist or be a source of friction. Marriage
is an important event in the life of an in¬
dividual in any society, but in Tamil Nadu
it reveals a great deal about Tamil society's
attitude to the man-woman relationship
and its place in society. Most marriages are
still arranged by the parents and determined
by the astral bodies governing the in-
the cultivated arts and the conceptual levels
of religion.
Independence brought a greater sense of
social equality and an opportunity for the
majority to express itself. With rapid
economic and technological progress and
the acceptance of values dictated by urban
societies, there is a danger that indigenous
culture may be gradually eroded. It is essen¬
tial that popular forms of expression and
ways of life do not disappear and that the
true essence of Tamil culture shall survive.
S. Ramakrishnan
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
I ^2*W
^BÀ Kl«î
* 1
&*k «*
Jf i l»T*
ME i
" "i^
Ji
^Jni
@
Mass weddings are a comparatively recent phenomenon and are part of an attempt to
reduce the heavy cost of getting married. Above, a mass wedding in Madras begins
with music played on the nagasvaram, a metre-long wood-wind instrument with a dou¬
ble reed fitted in the mouthpiece. No festival or other auspicious occasion is complete
without the music of the nagasvaram, whose powerful tone can carry as far as two or
three kilometres. Many nagasvaram players come from families that have specialized
in the instrument for generations.
GETTING MARRIED
In Tamil Nadu most marriages are still
arranged by parents and intercaste mar¬
riages, although no longer rare, are still the
exception rather than the rule. Child mar¬
riage is now a thing of the past.
Economic status and caste are crucial
factors in the process of selecting a mar¬
riage partner. Marriage is an expensive
business and the bride's family usually has
to meet all the expenses as well as providing
a dowry. To parents with several daughters
this financial burden is a source of constant
worry.
Paradoxically, the education of women
has added to the problem. In many castes
an educated girl can only marry a man with
an equal or better education, but the better
educated the bridegroom is the higher the
dowry the bride has to bring. For many
middle-class families education and
employment for women has meant that
woman have to earn their own dowries! In
earlier days the dowry consisted ofcash and
jewellery, but today it may include such
modern items as scooters, refrigerators,
television sets and pressure cookers.
In the past weddings were big social
events spread over five days. Today the
ceremony is completed in a little over one
day. Weddings are no longer celebrated at
home but are performed in rented halls.
Government legislation on civil marriage
has made things easier for those who want
to keep things simple and laws have been
passed to facilitate intercaste marriages.
For those who, either from conviction or
for the sake of convenience, want to
dispense with ceremonies the Government
has introduced a Self-Respect Marriage Act
which validates marriages solemnized in
non-traditional fashion.
8
In the Hindu religion the wedding
ceremony is the most important of the sam-
skaras (sacraments). The date is arranged in
accordance with careful astrological
calculations. At one point in the ceremony
mT '^m
^^t^m&^ä
«>1Bk ^S^Lv '
ï !Uil
HP
the bridegroom takes his bride by the hand
and leads her round a sacrificial fire to
solemnize their new and irrevocable union.
Finally the newly-weds are taken in proces¬
sion to their new home. It is customary for
a married couple to renew their vows at a
second ceremony held when the bridegroom
reaches the age of sixty.
S. Ramakrishnan
It is customary for married couples
to renew their wedding vows at a
ceremony held on the husband's
sixtieth birthday. Offerings are
made round a sacrificial fire and
water from consecrated pitchers
is poured through a sieve and
sprinkled over the couple. The wife
traditionally receives a second tali,
or wedding jewel.
Seated on her father's lap, a young
bride waits for the mangalyam (the
sacred thread on which is
suspended the tali, or wedding
jewel) to be fastened around her
neck. This is a crucial moment in
the wedding ceremony when the
bride passes from the control of
her parents and comes under the
protection of her husband.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Singing a soft lullaby a Madras
grandmother rocks the baby to
sleep in a traditional Tamil
hammock-cradle.
Photo © Faivre, Paris
Scenes from everyday life
by Sundara Ramaswamy
TAMIL people today have a way of life that carries them
back and forth over twenty centuries. When a young
Tamil with a doctorate in atomic science from a famous
American university advertises for a bride in the matrimonial
columns of a Madras English-language daily, he mentions his
caste and sub-caste and asks a suitable girl with the height and
waistline he desires to write to him immediately enclosing a
SUNDARA RAMASWAMY is a leading contemporary Tamil poet and
novelist.
horoscope. And since computers are now used for casting
horoscopes there need be no delay.
On the day of Ayudha Pooja, the annual festival at which
craftsmen honour the tools of their trade, surgeons who per¬
form open-heart surgery will put a kumkumam mark on their
minute, high-precision equipment.
Village, town, city: each has its own pace and style of life.
Morning begins much earlier in the cities and villages than in the
small towns. In the villages this is a natural and in the cities an
enforced inconvenience.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Village scene in western Tamil Nadu.
Photo © Vivant Univers, Namur, Belgium
In the cities a generation may still survive which remembers
the sound that wonderful sound of milk squirting into empty
metal pots from the teats of cows and buffaloes. The milk
sound, the sound of cow bells, the sound of hoofs, the rattle of
horns, the rustle of straw, the clatter of milk cans on the
ground the only sound like these in the cities today is that of
bicycle bells. In the city milk is left on the doorstep in plastic
sachets, and the customer does not even see the face of the girl
who delivers it. Alas, the alarm has been set too late for that.
Beside the milk is the morning newspaper, and soon the odour
of coffee and news will be in the air. While reading his
newspaper and drinking his coffee, the prudent householder
will remember to turn on the tap and fill his pots and pans with
water. The water supply may continue to flow all day... but
then again it may not.
In the city as in the village, the first thing the housewife
should do when she has taken her morning bath is to draw the
traditional kolam sign in front of her door (see photos page 31 ).
I still remember forty years later how my grandmother once ac¬
cusingly pointed out to her daughter-in-law that although it was
already noon she had still not drawn the kolam. (In fact the sun
had only just risen). In those days the kolam was drawn with
rice flour; today it is traced with white lime powder. Over the
years it has become accepted that a housewife can draw the
kolam after merely washing her face, provided that she has ap¬
plied the kumkumam and arranged her hair above her forehead.
Methods of cooking have changed. There has been a real
revolution in the kitchen. Yesterday gas stoves, electric
grinders, pressure-cookers, hot-plates and refrigerators were
possessions of the rich; today middle-class people aspire to
them. Working housewives are discovering time-saving
strategies in the kitchen. The menfolk and the children will have
to learn to do their bit in the morning hustle and bustle.
From eight o'clock in the morning onwards the sparrows
start to fly away from every home. First the little sparrows, then
10
the big sparrows. Then the house subsides into a great calm.
Now, if anyone rings the doorbell, the door will usually be kept
firmly shut. Even if it is opened, it will only be to a width of four
fingers, and an elderly face, frightened by the sound of its own
non-committal reply, will close the door upon itself.
Crowded buses and trains. Even if a seat is vacant, tradition
still requires that a woman should not sit beside a man nor a
man beside a woman. While boarding, however, men and
women inevitably jostle one another in the crush. They are
bound to bump into one another while standing or moving
down the aisle. But for the time being they have decided not to
sit side by side. Some humorous conductors crack jokes and
make the passengers laugh, helping to dispel the nervousness
that has been rising into the mind like poison ever since
daybreak.
The evenings are starting to belong to the television, which
the middle class has welcomed with open arms. For all practical
purposes the television is simply the cinema that has entered
the home; films that have already been seen at the cinema get
a second showing in the drawing room. Groups of children from
neighbouring families are sitting on the floor in front of the set.
They know what is going to happen next on the screen, and
shout out the emotion-packed dialogue being breathlessly
delivered by hero or heroine, delighted to beat the actors to the
end of each sentence. Not that television has depleted the
cinema audiences; even for midday shows long queues can be
seen waiting outside the cinemas in the scorching sun.
Women attend the free meetings held by religious preachers.
When these erudite religious scholars intersperse epic stories
with examples of behaviour drawn from everyday life, from the
cinema, and from politics in order to show how the ancient vir¬
tues have fallen into neglect, the people in the audience can find
tearful consolation in relating the trials and tribulations of their
own lives to the general decline in values.
The men, and more so the women, also flock to the plays put
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
on by the Sabha, local cultural associations. They rock with
laughter at the crackling jokes, secretly weep with the heroine
when she bewails the sorrows besetting her, and share her joy
when her problems disappear like mist driven away by the sun¬
shine. Then they return home, glad to have found an outlet for
their mental tensions.
For those who do not want to go out or who cannot afford
to do so, there are the weekly and monthly magazines to be
read. These magazines contain adventure stories, love stories
with a social or historical background told with bubbling en¬
thusiasm and ending with a strong insistence on the moral vir¬
tues, titbits of information, revelations about politicians and
film stars, as well as light poetry and essays. Tamils who do not
feel some mental bond with these magazines or who do not
glance at them at least once a day are few and far between.
Sunday is a wonderful day. Sunday mornings are for routine
jobs and the afternoons for more spiritual satisfaction. Piles of
clothes must be mended, washed, ironed and put away. The
bank must be visited (banks are open on Sundays in residential
areas). Certain skills must be brought into play to obtain from
ration-shops slightly higher quantities of scarce grains, low-fat
vegetable oils (sought-after not because of their low
cholesterol but because of their low price), sugar and/or
kerosene. Grain must be pounded and ground. Then, after ap¬
plying oil to the head, it is time for a leisurely bath with careful
rinsing of the hair, followed by a siesta to squeeze out the last
drop of body fatigue. In the afternoon, a film or a trip to the
beach or to a friend's house. And so on and so forth... When
Sunday dawns there are so many plans and projects nagging at
the mind. If you listen to the voice of physical fatigue that says
"Not today, not today", and you stay in bed, then the family
is done for. Even if you get up briskly and chase after time's
fleeting chariot and rush through your chores, time's chariot
somehow manages to keep ahead and when it disappears into
darkness not even a quarter of the work is done. Every Sunday
it is like this. You think back and remember the careless
mistakes you have made, the things you have forgotten to do.
Next Sunday you must try even harder.
The gap between cities and villages has narrowed. Efficient
and steadily improving road transport is helping to bring people
together. The expanding city suburbs are reaching out to the
villages.
The village revolves around agriculture. It is very early in the
morning when the men and women of the village set out to
work in the fields or gardens. There is no time to prepare
breakfast, nor any modern time-saving kitchen equipment. If
there are any left-overs from the previous night's food the
villagers swallow a mouthful before they leave. It is becoming
a custom to drink a cup of tea on the way to work. In the
villages few parents devote much time or trouble to getting
their children off to school; the children must fend for
themselves.
Changing fashions are also reaching the villages. Touring
theatre companies have become very common. Electricity has
brought lighting. It has also brought the blare of loudspeakers.
Simple make-up accessories and new kinds of dresses are
finding a place in village life. The villagers are obsessed by films
and politics, even though their lives are not dependent on them.
In the little shops, at the hairdresser's, and under the trees,
people gather and discuss the cinema and politics. The two
fields are not unrelated. Yesterday's film personalities are to¬
day active in politics. Today's cinema people may go into
politics at any moment.
It would be wrong to say that the old life-style in the villages
has completely disappeared. Time once went by at snail's pace;
now it has started to walk; but it does not yet run. Leisurely
conversation can still be heard on the thinnai, the verandahs of
the houses. In rivers and ponds women take their time to bathe.
Women still carry pots of drinking water on their hips. The har¬
mony that once existed everywhere between men and other liv¬
ing creatures continues to exist in the villages. There are cows,
buffaloes, chickens and dogs. The grinding mills still turn in the
homes, the pestle still rotates in the mortar. Healthy women
still pound paddy with heavy pounding rods* Boiled paddy is
spread outside in the street in front of the door.
The sun still rises over the village. Leave the house, walk
across the fields, look to the far horizon and feel the mountain
breeze like the soft touch of children.
Sundara Ramaswamy
A BOOMING
FILM INDUSTRY
Photo © Raghavendra Rao, Madras
Poster for a film entitled "Skanda's Pardon" (Skanda, also
known as Murugan, Is the son of Siva and the Hindu god of
war). In the foreground, a young lottery ticket vendor.
The cinema is perhaps the most powerful, and certainly the most
popular, of the media in Tamil Nadu. Film stars wield great
influence over the public. Fan clubs (strangely enough only for
male actors, notfor actresses) are common, each with a large mem¬
bership. Club members promote their favourite stars and try to
keep them in the spotlight ofpublic attention. They publicize the
release of new films in which their idols appear, celebrate their
birthdays and garland their cut-out portraits and banner advertise¬
ments outside cinemas.
Films have been produced in Tamil Nadu for over seventy years
and thefilm industry is now huge (487films released in 1982 alone)
with a sophisticated production and distribution network and
employing a large workforce. As technology has improved, black
and white films have become rare (only two black and white films
released in 1982) with the public demanding colour films.
The content of films is largely shaped by popular tastes.
Although for a while, with the advent of the talkies, films became
a powerful toolfor thepropagation of the nationalist message and,
later, the ideals of the "self-respect" movement, no such tendency
is now discernible. Today almost every film has love as its main
theme. There has been a shift away from studio-oriented produc¬
tion and towards location filming in rural surroundings, but the
ingredients have remained the same boy meets girl, violence and,
inserted willy-nilly into the fabric of every production, the theme
of "honour". The beauty of the landscape is emphasized, lovers
express their emotions in dance and song and fighting scenes are
scattered throughout and usually provide the climax.
S. Ramakrishnan
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
RICE AND RITUAL
The Tamil art of cooking
by Thilaka Baskaran
Photo © Vivant Univers. Namur, Belgium
To prepare food for
their families village
women use two age-
old devices for milling
and grinding the sad¬
dle quern (a round
stone rolled or rubbed
on a flat stone) and,
visible in the
background, a pestle
and mortar.
SANGAM literature paints a vivid picture of the social life
of the ancient Tamils and provides the historical back¬
ground for their eating habits. In the Sangam poems
(see article page 32) land is classified into five geographical
areas and the food related to each area is described.
Many inscriptions chiselled on the walls of temples reveal
how food habits and religious practices became intertwined.
These epigraphs give an idea of the role of food in rituals, as
THILAKA BASKARAN, is a Tamil nutritionist and college lecturer.
12
sacrificing, cooking, dedicating and feasting all became part of
worship. Not eating... fasting, also emerged as a ritual.
By the 1 1 th-1 2th century AD, caste groups had appeared
with distinct lines of demarcation, and the eating habits of each
caste began to assume different characteristics. (The culinary
profile of the castes can still be noted by the careful observer).
Such issues as "who can serve whom?" and "from whom can
one accept food?" became significant in the context of caste
structure. Depending upon the degree to which a caste was
"Sanskritized", it became vegetarian or non-vegetarian. A
tradition of vegetarianism, which was largely absent from an¬
cient Tamil Nadu began to emerge, mainly as a result of the
popularity of Buddhism and Jainism.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Over the years, certain interesting concepts in food ap¬
peared. Taste was classified into six groups, and all food com¬
modities were divided into two broad categories, hot and cold.
The whole of Tamil cuisine is still largely based on this
classification which also influenced indigenous medicinal prac¬
tices: illnesses were classified as hot and cold and the diet
therapy was based on treating with cold food those caused by
heat and with hot food those caused by cold. This belief still
persists. Chicken pox, for example, is believed to be a
manifestation of body heat and the foods permitted are those
that are supposed to counter this heat fruit, butter milk and
tender coconut.
Some of the recipes. that were in use in the 1st century AD
are still being followed today, pretty much unchanged. Cooking
is elaborate and complex, and is considered to be a fine art.
Treatises on cooking specify the size of the kitchen, the kind of
stove to be used, the direction in which the stove is to face, and
even the desirable characteristics of a cook (he should be "a
native born of good caste, he should observe the cooking and
eating taboos, not harbour any grudge, be absolutely clean in
his habits, and always tie his long hair into a bun").
The everyday diet is fairly austere, consisting of boiled rice,
sambar (dhal [lentils] vegetable and tamarind), fish or meat
In modern Tamil cuisine coffee has become one of the main
drinks. Brewed from freshly roasted and ground beans, and
served with plenty of milk and sugar, it is always drunk at
breakfast. This method of coffee-making is holding its ground
in all Tamil kitchens in the face of instant coffees promoted in
the media.
Change in food habits is slow in coming to Tamil Nadu, but
some signs of it can be seen. Wheat is being increasingly used
in urban areas. Chappathi (wheat flour pancake) may be
substituted for rice, especially for dinner, and poori (a deep-
fried wheat pancake) and potato be served as breakfast.
Though stainless steel cutlery and crockery are used in urban
homes, food is still served on ceremonial occasions in the tradi¬
tional way on a banana leaf. The leaf is spread in front of the
diner, with the tip pointing left. Serving begins with salt and
pickle being placed at the extreme left. The first course is
sweet everything has to begin with a sweet whether it is an
infant's first solid meal or the newly-wed's first drink. The
series of vegetable dishes, pachadi (a vegetable and curd salad)
and the crisp appalam, all of which go with the various rice
courses, are placed on the top half of the leaf. With every
course the leaf is carefully replenished, the diner's protests be¬
ing totally ignored. Even among non-vegetarians, ceremonial
A celebratory meal being serv¬
ed to guests in the traditional
manner on banana leaves (see
article this page) on the occa¬
sion of the upanayana, or initia¬
tion, of the son of the
household. During the initiation
ceremony, which usually takes
place around the age of twelve,
the boy is invested with the
"sacred thread", a loop of cot¬
ton cord placed over the left
shoulder and falling diagonally
across the body to the right hip.
The thread, which the owner
wears throughout his lifetime,
being replaced annually, in¬
dicates that the wearer has
joined the ranks of the dvija, or
"twice-born".
curry (for non-vegetarians), a vegetable pugadh, rasam (spicy
pepper water) and curds. On special occasions payasam, a
milk-based dessert flavoured with cardomom, is served.
Even in affluent families there is not much variety in the daily
menu, but when there are guests or a wedding is held it is a
totally different story, and a truly ambrosial meal will be produc¬
ed. The food served on these occasions is an indication of the
hosts' status.
Eating habits vary geographically and are shaped largely by
what is grown in the different areas. In the riverine and delta
regions, paddy, sugar cane, banana and coconut figure largely
in the diet. In dry areas millets and grams are the major
foodstuffs.
The delicate blending of herbs, condiments and spices is the
touchstone of good cookery. The combination and quantity of
spices used vary from family to family, providing subtle varia¬
tions in taste. The contrast between opposing tastes is a recurr¬
ing theme. Most of the popular dishes like sambar, morekolum-
bu (curds and spices with coconut) pulikolumbu (a spicy sour
curry with vegetable and tamarind) and the red-hot fish and
meat curry are all different combinations of sour and hot tastes.
The staple cereal in most parts of Tamil Nadu is, of course,
rice, which is often eaten at all three meals. Breakfast in most
middle class families consists of idli (a rice and dhal batter,
steamed), dosai (the same batter fried like a pancake), puttu (a
steamed rice-flour preparation served with coconut scrapings,
banana, and sugar), idiappam (a rice-flour dough pressed
through a mould to resemble vermicelli and steamed) or appam
(a rice-flour and coconut delicacy fermented with toddy and
cooked like a pancake).
feasts are always vegetarian.
Every festival and ceremony has a traditional menu. The first
rice meal given to a baby in the seventh month is sarkarai
ponga!, a combination of rice-milk, sugar and ghee. The
teething of a child calls for pal koshukattai (tiny rice flakes
resembling teeth, cooked in milk with sugar). The coming of
age of a daughter is an important family event, as it is in all tradi¬
tional communities. Milk, banana and sugar are given to the girl
and to all well-wishers who visit her. Seemandam, celebrated
in the seventh or ninth month of pregnancy, calls for a variety
of rice preparations.
Since Tamil Nadu is predominantly agricultural it is not sur¬
prising that the most important festival should be pongal, the
harvest festival, which is celebrated at the beginning of the
Tamil month of Thai (see box page 31 ). Pongal, which literally
means "boiling over", symbolizes the farmer's overflowing
prosperity. Newly decorated mud pots are used to cook dishes
to fit the occasion, such as sarkarai pongal and ven pongal.
Modernization is slowly bringing changes to the culinary
scene. Compromises and adaptations are being made. Tradi¬
tional recipes that call for elaborate and leisurely cooking are
disappearing. Processed foods such as ready-made idli-m\x and
pre-packed curry powders have invaded urban kitchens.
Mechanical aids such as motorized ;d//-grinders are also being
used in traditional cooking. The break-up of the joint family and
the increase in the number of career women have inevitably
changed some Tamil eating habits. A movement towards a
simpler cuisine can be sensed. All the same, Tamil food prac¬
tices and their cultural implications still retain their basic
character.
Thilaka Baskaran
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Photo Emmanuel Guillou © Atlas Photo, Paris
The great temple at Tanjore. Built entirely of granite this grandiose temple to Siva was erected during the
reign of the great Chola monarch Raja Raja I (985 to 1014).
GATEWAY TO THE GODS
1. Sermons in stone
by R. Nagaswamy
FOR the past two thousand years the
life of the Tamil people has cen¬
tered on their temples with their
lofty towers, elegant sculptures and
remarkable bronzes.
A number of places in Tamil Nadu are
said to be directly or indirectly connected
with episodes in certain popular myths
and legends relating to one or other of the
divine manifestations of Siva, Vishnu,
Subrahmanya, Durga and other gods.
Places mentioned in epics and puranas
(collections of legendary tales) assumed a
sacred aura and were visited by a large
number of devotees. While some such
legends are pan-Indjan in nature, most of
them are purely Tamil in origin and in
essence.
R. NAGASWAMY is a specialist in Tamil art
and archaeology. He was curator for art and
archaeology at the Madras Museum from
1959 until 1962 when he joined the State
Archaeology Department, becoming its first
director in 1966. He is the author of over a
hundred books, articles and studies; his Tan-
trie Cults of South India was published, in
English, in 1982.
14
The Vishnu temple of Srirangam and
the Siva temple of Ramesvaram are thus
connected with the Ramayana epic.
Rama worshipped Siva at Ramesvaram
to purge his sin of having killed Ravana.
Thiruchendur, a place sacred to Muruga,
This 16th-century mural
was discovered recently in
the gopuram (entrance
tower) of a temple in the
district of Tirunelveli. It
portrays the arrival from
the Gulf of a ship laden
with horses. The princes
of southern India imported
large numbers of horses
from Persia and Arabia,
despite their high cost; the
king of Vijayanagar is
reputed to have imported
13,000 horses annually
for his own personal use
and to provide mounts for
his officers.
Photo © I.F.I., Pondicherry
is believed to be the spot where
Subrahmanya killed the demon Surapad-
ma. The Meenakshi temple of Madurai is
said to be the place where Siva performed
sixty-four miraculous sports.
Temples were also built for the welfare
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
of the people. An inscription at
Mamallapuram records that a temple of
Lord Siva was erected by the king to fulfil
the desires of his subjects. Whenever a
king settled his people in a new place, he
erected a number of temples and arrang¬
ed for worship for the well-being of the
inhabitants. When Karikala, the
celebrated Chola ruler of the Sangam
period, established Uraiyur as his capital,
in accordance with the instructions given
in the ancient treatises he erected temples
before building housing for his subjects.
Temples were also often built in honour
of rulers, parents, relatives or famous
men.
The great majority of temples,
however, were erected by kings, queens
and nobles out of piety and devotion.
Koccengannan, a Chola ruler of the
Sangam period, erected seventy lofty
temples to Siva as an act of devotion. The
celebrated Pallava monarch Mahen-
dravarnam I (590-630 AD) excavated a
number of temples out of rock as an act
of piety. "Having made this abode for
the Lord Siva, whose image he has in¬
stalled there, he bore the supreme Lord
on his head", says an inscription of his at
Tiruchirapalli. Indeed, Mahendra even¬
tually assumed the title of Mahachet-
takari, or "Great Temple Builder". The
great temple of Tanjore, built by the
great Chola monarch Raja Raja I
(985-1014 AD), was erected as an act of
pious dedication.
Temples were also erected to honour
the dead, either at the place of burial or
in the form of memorials. After a period
of mourning, the dead, it was believed,
became celestial beings and were
therefore to be worshipped. The erection
of monumental structures for the dead
can be found in very large numbers.
Dolmens in particular played an impor¬
tant role in the evolution of temples to
the dead and, in later periods, minor
Façade of the Sivaite temple of
Minakshi at Madurai, the an¬
cient capital of the Pandya
dynasty. The city was totally
destroyed in 1310 and the pre¬
sent temple dates from the
17th century. Our photo bears
witness to the open-minded
catholicity of the Hindu
religion, for, although this is a
Sivaite temple, the statue right
portrays Vishnu who is seen
astride his mount, the fabulous
bird Garuda.
Photo © Claude Sauvageot. Paris
The interior of the Minakshi
temple at Madurai. To the left
can be seen Nandi, the bull
mount of Siva, and, to the right,
a statue of Ganesh, the
elephant-headed son of Siva
and Parvati. Crouched before
him is his mount, a rat.
Photo © Claude Sauvageot, Paris
temples closely resembling dolmens are
to be found. Often an image of the dead
person appears on the back wall.
The form of worship in the temple is
prescribed by ritual treatises called
Agamas or Tantra Sastras. All agamic
texts consist of four parts: Caryapada,
Kriyapada, Yogapada and Jnanapada.
The Caryapada deals with such things as
the personal cleanliness, discipline and
initiation of the worshipper. The mode of
worship in the temple is treated under the
Kriyapada. The Yogapada details the
yogic path to be followed by the devotee.
The Jnanapada is essential as it deals
with the ultimate end of worship,
culminating in the realization of
knowledge and final emancipation and*
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
thus embodies the essential philosophic
concepts of each sect.
The earlier Agamas are elaborate
treatises dealing not only with temple
ritual but also, in great detail, with such
matters as the lay-out of villages and
cities, the building of houses and
temples, and the manufacture of utensils.
Temples dedicated to Gods like Siva,
Vishnu, Durga and Jain and Buddhist
deities existed during the Sangam period
(approx. 300 BC to 200 AD), but they
were mostly built of bricks, mortar and
timber. Virtually nothing of that age has
survived, although the remains of a
fourth century AD Buddhist chaitya
(temple proper) and vihara (monastery)
have been unearthed at Kaveripattinam.
Stucco heads and torsos have also been
found which attest to the continuation of.
the artistic tradition mentioned in early
Tamil literature. By 600 AD, in the wake
of the Bhakti (devotion) movement,
several hundred temples dedicated to
Siva and Vishnu had been erected and
these were also brick and mortar con¬
structions. King Mahendra Pallava I was
a great builder as well as being an ac¬
complished artist, composer and
dramatist. He seems to have taken a keen
interest in the art of painting and called
himself Chitrakarapuli, or "Tiger among
artists". To him are due several rock-cut.
cave temples carved out of small hills
from Madras in the north to Thiruchi in
the south.
His successors continued his work.
Mamallapuram, near Madras, was
established as a seaport in the middle of
the seventh century by Mahendra's son
Mamalla. Here Pallava artists lavished
their skill on the carving of monolithic
temples, the excavation of caves and on
sculptural friezes carved on open rock
faces. Around 700 AD, Pallava artists
were encouraged by king Rajasimha
Pallava to embellish with their carving as
many caves and temples as possible.
There are several monolithic temples in¬
cluding a group of five temples, known
because of their shape and appearance as
the Five Rathas (chariots), which are
Dwarfs dance in ecstasy in this
frieze adorning the base of the
Kailasanatha temple at Kan-
chipuram. The temple, sacred to
Siva, was built by the Pallava king
Rajasimha in about 725 AD.
Photos © R. Nagaswamy, Madras
perfect examples of symmetry and
careful planning and execution. They
simulate the structural temples of the
period, reproducing wooden elements,
such as balustrades and beams, in stone.
As well as the monoliths there are over
fifteen rock-cut temples in various stages
of completion. Some are adorned with
remarkable sculptures of Siva and the
goddess Durga. A carving in the
Mahishasuramardini cave temple por¬
trays the goddess Durga seated on a pran¬
cing lion accompanied by dwarfs and
female attendants. The goddess wields a
bow and a sword and, facing her, a
buffalo-headed demon is retreating van¬
quished. All his warriors are hastily
withdrawing, some falling dead and
others fleeing the battlefield. On the side
of the sculpture depicting the goddess
everything has a vigorous forward move¬
ment, while on the side of the Asura
(demon-god) everything is falling. This is
undoubtedly one of the greatest
sculptural creations of India. Opposite
this sculpture is another depicting Vishnu
reclining in cosmic sleep on a serpent
couch, a picture of composure and peace.
Another masterpiece at Mamalla¬
puram is the great panel carved on a rock
face depicting "-The Penance of Ar-
juna". A central fissure in the rock is
visualized as the celestial river Ganga
descending from heaven to earth and fall¬
ing down to the nether world. Surround¬
ed by celestial beings, hunters, musicians
and other figures, as well as animals and
birds, Arjuna, the hero of the
Mahabharata, performs a penance under
the eyes of Lord Siva. The herd of
elephants at the bottom of the panel is
perhaps the most outstanding animal
sculpture in Indian art.
Nearby is another sculpture portraying
Krishna holding the mount Govardhana
beneath which cowherds and their cows
are taking shelter. The cow and the calf in
CONTINUED PAGE 18
This 13th-century sculpture from
the Vishnu temple at Srinangam
echoes the imagery of many
Vishnavite poems in which the
devout soul is visualized as a
young girl longing for union with
the Supreme Being, personified as
her lover.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
THE TEMPLE
SCULPTURES
OF MAMALLAPURAM
The temple complex at Mamallapuram, on the coast
some 80 kilometres south of Madras, is one of the
great architectural and sculptural achievements of the
Pallava dynasty (4th to 9th century). The most im¬
pressive work is the huge panel carved on a rock face
known variously as "The Penance of Arjuna" or "The
Descent of the Ganga". Near the centre of the panel
Arjuna, a hero of the great Hindu epic, the
Mahabharata, performs a penance to Siva. Beside Ar¬
juna, a fissure in the rock represents the celestial river
Ganga descending from heaven to earth. Stretching
out on either side of the central fissure are magnifi¬
cent sculptures of deities, sprites, saints, musicians,
hunters and townsfolk (see detail right) and of animals
(detail below) and birds, all of whom have come to
witness the Ganga's miraculous descent. In a nearby
cavern are sculpted scenes from the lives of Vishnu.
Bottom right, Vishnu is depicted milking a cow, in his
8th avatar as Krishna the Shepherd-King. In the same
cavern another sculpture depicts Krishna holding up
mount Govardhana to protect shepherds and their
flocks from the wrath of his rival Indra. Bottom, also
at Mamallapuram is a group of monolithic temples
known as "The Five Rathas" (chariots) since they
resemble in shape the chariots on which deities are
carried in procession at festivals. Dedicated to the
Pandava heroes of the Mahabharata and their com¬
mon wife Draupadi, they were hewn out of rock dur¬
ing the reign of Mamalla Pallava (630 to 668) who
gave his name to Mamallapuram.
m &><
&*
ST«*
i %+'
j^fel £*Ä?
^
&
1
J/
:ii*fc.
X
Photo © Paul Almasy, Paris
1 V*:
:t«
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 16
the group are another example of the
Pallava artists' ability to portray animals
vibrant with life. Mamallapuram is a
treasure-house of the sculptor's art and
must rank among the great centres of
classic world art.
The rise to dominance of the Chola
dynasty in the ninth century brought a
change in architectural style. Most of the
structural temples were of modest height
and built of granite. Special attention
was paid to the structure of the sanctum
in which fine sculptures of gods and god¬
desses were placed in appropriate niches
as prescribed in the ritual treatises.
Despite their modesty, their simplicity
and elegant proportions are arresting.
Within a century, these unpretentious
beginnings were to culminate in the con¬
struction of perhaps the greatest of all
temples in southern Indian style, built by
king Raja Raja Chola (985 to 1014).
Some 85 metres in height and built entire¬
ly of granite, the temple at Tanjore is a
marvel of symmetry and structural
design. Everything about it is grandiose.
Even the five-metre-high monolithic
sculpture of the dwarapalas (guardians'
of entrances) pales into insignificance in
the grandeur of the architecture whose
upward thrust overwhelms the visitor.
Raja Raja's son, Rajendra Chola, built a
similar temple at his capital Gangai-
konda-cholapuram and the Chola royal
temples at Darasuram and Tiru-
bhuvanam, near Kumbhakonam, are
edifices of great beauty.
Chola art differed from that of the
Pallava period in that the Cholas were
essentially great architects whereas
Pallava artists specialized in delicate, ex¬
pressive sculpture. By the twelfth century
a new trend began to emerge. Enclosure
walls and lofty entrance towers known as
gopuram were built at all the important
temples and mandapas (halls) with from
1 00 to 1 ,000 slender pillars were built for
festive purposes.
From the sixteenth century, the en¬
trance towers were built to greater
heights, up to sixty metres, and became
the most important feature of Hindu
temples. The Vijayanagara Emperor
Krishna Devaraya (1509 to 1529) built
several such towers at places like
Chidambaram, Kanchipuram, Kalahasti
and Thiruvannamalai. So imposing were
they that all -entrance towers came to be
known as Rayagopura (royal towers).
The ground floors of these towers were
built of stone and the entire superstruc¬
ture was of brick and mortar, painted
and studded with hundreds of stucco
figures, a trend that continues to this
day.
R. Nagaswamy
18
Colour pages
Page 19
Top: A village hero-god surrounded by offerings in the form of
statues and terra cotta horses (see article and photo story page
28).
Bottom left: Tridents, swords and spears are often planted In
the ground in front of representations of hero-gods as a tribute
to their courageous spirit.
Photos © S. Baskaran, Madras
Bottom right: Snakes rise up and sway to the music of the
snake-charmer's flute. This terra-cotta statue may possibly be
a representation of Pampatti Cittar, a 1 5th-century poet. Pam-
patti means "Dance, serpent, dance!" a phrase with which he
used to sign off all his writings. The Cittar were poets and
writers of the ancient popular tradition, some of whose works
have survived in anthologies of popular Tamil poetry. They
wrote about alchemy, medicine and yoga as well as magic or
miraculous powers. The great modern Tamil poet
Subrahmanya Bharati (1882 to 1921) used to claim to be the
latest in the long line of Cittar poets.
Photo © R. Nagaswamy, Madras
Centre pages
Page 20
Top: Detail of the great rock sculpture of the Pallava period
known as The Penance ofArjuna (see photos and caption page
1 7). It depicts a man wringing out a garment or a piece of cloth
he has washed In the holy waters of the River Ganga.
Bottom: Head of Siva, detail from a late Pallava (9th century)
bronze sculpture depicting the marriage of Siva and Parvati (see
photo page 24).
Photos © R. Nagaswamy, Madras
Page 21
Top left: Cinema-going is one of the most popular forms of
entertainment in Tamil Nadu and colourful posters, like this one
advertising a matinée performance, are a feature of the Madras
street scene. (See box page 11). '
Photo © Jean-Baptiste Faivre, Paris
Bottom left: Detail of a late Pallava period fresco depicting Par¬
vati, the consort of Siva, at the Talagirisvara temple,
Panamalai.
Photo © B. Mathias
Top right: This early Chola bronze figure of Siva Natesa danc¬
ing on the head of a dwarf comes from Nallur in Tanjore district.
It dates from about 900 AD and is unique in that it is the only
bronze of a dancing Siva with eight arms. The Siva Natesa pic¬
tured here differs In form and pose from that of the better
known Siva Nataraja (see photo page 25). Many forms of danc¬
ing Siva were made to emphasize different aspects of Siva's
essential nature.
Bottom right: Dance formed an essential element in temple
ritual. Dancing girls (Devadasi) attached to the temple perform¬
ed a highly sophisticated ritual of dance and gestures codified
by the sage Bharata Muni who lived in the 1st century BC. To¬
day, temple dancing as an institution has disappeared, although
one form of temple dance, the Bharata Natyam, has survived
and has been taken up by girls of all groups and social levels
(see also page 26).
Photos © R. Nagaswamy, Madras
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
GATEWAY TO THE GODS
2.
Images in bronze
TAMIL bronze sculpture represents a distinctive contri¬
bution to world art. In early Sangam literature (see
article page 32) there are allusions to metal images,
and ancient hymns of Sivaite and Vishnavite devotees refer
to the statues of deities being taken in procession at
festivals; these processional images were traditionally
made of copper.
Metal ¡mages were made by the lost-wax, or cire perdue,
process and were solid cast in copper, silver or gold.
Later, an alloy of five metals copper, brass, zinc, gold and
silver was used. God is said to pervade the five basic
elements of earth, water, fire, air and ether and his cosmic
body is believed to be composed of these five elements.
Each of the five metals used in the making of images is taken
to represent one of the five elements and ¡mages made of
them are known as panca lona murthi, or "five-metalled
¡mages".
From the initial sculpting of the figure in wax to the very
last act of consecration, every stage in the process is ac¬
companied by rituals and the recital of sacred hymns. The
last sacred act performed by the artist is the "opening of the
eyes" as the carving of the eyes is called. The right eye of
the deity represents the sun, the left eye the moon and the
mark on the forehead fire. The ritual fixing of the ¡mage to
its pedestral is considered to be the final consecration.
Metal ¡mages are worshipped regularly, receive daily of¬
ferings and, on days of festival, are decorated, placed on
chariots and taken out in procession, acting, as it were, as
the representative of a temple's main stone statue. Almost
all temples possess a number of metal images and
altogether they must number several thousand.
The earliest metal objects found in Tamil Nadu are grave
goods excavated at Adiccanallur in the Thirunelveli district.
They consist of copper lamps and ornamental plates often
with bases in the form of dogs and cocks. One tiny figure,
thought to represent the "mother goddess", has also been
found.
Of the few eighth-century bronzes that have come to light
most are representations of Vishnu and are modest in size.
One of the finest examples of bronze sculpture of the
Pallava period, however, is a figure of Siva with his consort,
now in the Madras Museum. A statue of Vishnu in his form
as Trivikrama (the conqueror of the Three Worlds that con¬
stitute the Universe) and another Vishnu statue from
Kodumudi are classic examples of eighth to ninth-century
bronze art. The heights reached by Tamil artists of this
Colour page 22
Top left: Women planting out rice in the district of
Tiruccirappalli.
Photo © Marie-Louise Reiniche, Paris
Bottom left: Saris being dyed. The sari, the traditional
outer garment for women of the Indian sub-continent, is
a piece of brightly coloured or embroidered cloth, some
five metres long (ceremonial saris can be up to eight
metres long), which is worn wrapped around the body.
One end of the sari can be draped over the head as a
hood. Hindu women wear the sari over a midriff-length
blouse and a petticoat.
Photo © S. Baskaran, Madras
Top right: Devotees taking a ritual bath in a sacred pool
in the town of Kumbhakonam on the occasion of a great
twelve-yearly festival. ,
Bottom right: In Tamil Nadu, dance dramas based on
stories from the Mahbharata, one of the major epics of In¬
dia, or on local legends are enacted exclusively by men.
Known as Terukkuthu (street dance), they are especially
popular in rural areas. They combine classic and folk
elements and performances sometimes continue for
several consecutive nights. Dialogue is interspersed with
dance and song and the actors colour their faces and
wear colourful costumes and elaborate headgear.
Photos © R. Nagaswamy, Madras
Detail of a Chola bronze image of Lakshmana, the
brother of the epic hero Rama. Dating from the
mid-1 Oth century it is still an object of worship at
Paruthiyur in the Tanjore district.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The marriage of Siva and Parvati. This 9th-century
bronze from Vadakkalathur is a superb example of the
bronze sculpture of the late Pallava period (see article this
page and detail on colour page 20).
period are exemplified by a superb bronze of Siva marrying
Parvati. It portrays the bashful tenderness of a young girl
standing at the side of her lover and the majesty and pride
of the master conscious of the delicate sensitivity of his
consort whose hand he holds. More than simply a represen¬
tation of a divine union, it is also a vivid portrayal of human
emotions.
Bronze art reached its zenith under the Chola emperors
during the tenth and eleventh centuries and its artistic merit
is now recognized the world over. Early Chola bronze art can
be divided into three schools: the Aditya, the Sembiyan
Mahadevi and the Raja Raja schools.
Aditya Chola (875 to 906) and his son Parantaka (906 to
955) built many temples famed for their beautiful sculptures
24
and ornamentation. Among the many types of bronzes
made under their patronage one in particular won the ad¬
miration not only of the artists of the succeeding genera¬
tions but also of modern thinkers and artists. These are the
Siva Nataraja, or figures of Siva as the master dancer. Both
as an art form and as a symbol representing the highest
philosophical thought of India they are unparalleled. Since
that time images of Siva Nataraja have been a feature of
every Siva temple.
Sembiyan Mahadevi was a Chola queen of great devotion
and refined aesthetic taste. Widowed while still young, she
devoted her life to visiting sacred sites, having temples
rebuilt and bronzes made. She made generous donations to
temples of gold and silver vessels and jewels to adorn their
statues. Bronzes made to her command are notable for their
slender grace and charm.
Raja Raja Chola (985 to 1014) had many bronzes made
for the great temple at Tanjore. Raja Raja's personal atten¬
tion to every aspect of temple life is attested to in inscrip¬
tions, many of which refer to the consecration of bronze
statues which are often described in detail.
Many superlative examples of the bronzes of the Raja Raja
school, remarkable for their majesty and dignity, are now
preserved in the Tanjore Art Gallery. A few still remain in
temples, the finest of these being the statue of Siva Nataraja
in the great temple of Tanjore. The trend set by the Raja Raja
school continued until the end of the eleventh century after
which, although a great number of bronzes were made,
there was a steady decline in quality.
R. Nagaswamy
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
REFLECTIONS
ON SIVA
NATARAJA
General impression of the Siva :
Fullness of life, the river of life, air, sun, overflowing sense
of being. This is how the art of the Far East appears to us!...
The divinity of the human body was captured at that time,
not because they were closer to the origins, for our forms
have remained entirely the same; but the servitude of today
thought it had achieved total emancipation; and we are out
of orbit. The taste is lacking...
Bronze statues of Siva Nataraja, the Lord of the Dance,
are an important expression of Hindu thought and
philosophy and are to be found in separate, south-facing
shrines at almost all Siva temples. They portray sym¬
bolically the pancakrityas, or five acts of the Supreme
Beingcreation, sustenance, destruction, the banish¬
ment of ignorance and the bestowal of grace. The four-
armed Siva is depicted within a flaming aureole (see
photo above and detail left). One hand holds a small,
double-headed drum, symbolizing the initial vibration in
space of cosmic creation, while another holds the fire
that consumes all that is created. The palm of the third
hand, facing the devotee in the abhaya pose assures him
of freedom from fear. The hand of the fourth arm, swung
across the body in the gajahasta pose, points to the rais¬
ed left foot, the place of refuge from ignorance and delu¬
sion (which are symbolized by the dwarf demon trampled
by the right foot) and the ultimate goal of the individual
soul where all is bliss and where there is neither birth nor
death. Siva is the greatest exponent of music and dance.
He is said to dance in the vast expanse of the sky as well
as in the pure mind of the devotee.
The great French sculptor Auguste Rodin (1840-1917) was a
highly perceptive admirer of Indian art. In an issue of the
magazine Ars Asiática published in 1921 he made a series of
succinct and penetrating comments on photos of statues of
the god Siva preserved in the Madras Museum. Below,
salient passages in which Rodin evokes the head andface of
a bronze sculpture of Siva dancing at the centre of a circle
offlames (Siva Nataraja).
During long contemplation of the head
of the Siva:
This swollen, out-thrust mouth, abundant in its sensual
expressions...
The tenderness of mouth and eye are in harmony.
These lips like a lake of pleasure bordered by nostrils
palpitating and noble.
The mouth undulates in damp delights, sinuous as a
snake; the eyes closed, swollen, closed with a stitching of
lashes.
The wings of the nose rise tenderly on a full surface.
The lips which form the words, which move when they
escape. Such a delicious snake in movement!
The eyes which have only a corner in which to hide have
the purity of line and the serenity of nestling stars.
The still fair weather of these eyes; the still outline; the
still joy of this calm.
The chin is the stopping point on which the curves
converge.
The expression is continued with an ending which
dissolves into another. The movements of the mouth are
lost in the cheeks.
The curve which comes from the ear echoes a small curve
which pulls the mouth and, slightly, the wings of the nose;
it is a circle which passes beneath the nose and the chin as
far as the cheekbones.
The high cheeks which curve.
Still before the eloquent head of the Siva:
This eye stays in the same place with its companion; it is
in a propitious shelter; it is voluptuous and luminous.
The closed eyes, the sweetness of time gone by.
These eyes purely drawn like a precious enamel.
The eyes in the casket of the eyelids; the arc of the brows;
that of the sinuous lip.
Mouth, a cavern of the sweetest thoughts, but a volcano
for the furies."
The materiality of the soul that one can imprison in this
bronze, captive for several centuries; desires for eternity on
this mouth; the eyes which are going to see and talk.
For ever, life enters and leaves through the mouth, as the
bees continually enter and leave; sweet perfumed
respiration.
This pretty, lost profile has a profile, but the profile where
the expression reaches completion, sinks, leaving the
charm of the declining cheeks to join the attachments of the
n6Ck. Auguste Rodin
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
-J~
BHARATA NATYAM
An ancient art reborn
Bharata Natyam is the modern name for the classical dance-
drama of Tamil Nadu in which a language of conventionalized
hand gestures and body movements is used to help the dancers
convey meaning and expression. Characters from the Hindu
epics, the Mahabharata and the Ramayana, are portrayed in
this intricate and graceful art which combines drama, music,
poetry, colour and rhythm.
Bharata Natyam is performed according to techniques which
are carefully laid down in the Natya Sastra, a remarkable San¬
skrit treatise covering all aspects of dance and drama which
was probably written around the beginning of the Christian era
by the sage Bharata. For many centuries the dances were per¬
formed exclusively in the precincts of the great temples by
female dancers known as devadasis ("servants of god") who
underwent years of training before they were ready to perform
in public. Many sculptures carved on temple walls, some dating
back to the tenth century AD, depict karanas (positions of
hands and feet described in the Natya Sastra) and testify to the
importance dance then held in religious life. It was through the
temple dancers that Bharata Natyam (then known as dasi at-
tam, the dance of the devadasi) survived to modern times. But
then the devadasi system fell into decline and disrepute and it
seemed that the dance tradition it had preserved for so long
would disappear into oblivion.
In the last fifty years, however, as part of a new con¬
sciousness of ancient Indian cultural traditions Bharata Natyam
has not only been saved from extinction but has experienced a
remarkable revival and achieved international renown. Rukmini
Devi is an outstanding figure in this revival. Born in 1 904, in the
1 930s she became the first woman from outside the devadasi
tradition to learn Bharata Natyam. With other major artists such
as the dancer Balasaraswathi she set out "to bring the spirit of
the temple to the stage", in a movement in which scholars and
creators sought to rediscover the pure forms of ancient
classical dance by studying ancient texts and temple friezes
and carvings and by consulting the survivors of the devadasi
tradition.
In 1936 Rukmini Devi founded an academy in Madras,
Kalakshetra ("Centre of Arts") to train promising artists and
teachers and since then students from many parts of the world
have been trained under her guidance in Bharata Natyam and
classical Carnatic music, as well as following courses in prin¬
ting, weaving, stage and costume design. "It is amazing to see
how limitless an art Bharata Natyam is", Rukmini Devi has writ¬
ten. "For, if one can depict the Mahabharata or the Ramayana
through Bharata Natyam, this means that one can express all
human emotion and thought through it, for these epics and the
other ancient stories portray every possible human
experience."
In Bharata Natyam the language of hand gestures (hastas) is so vast that the
dancer can express practically anything from abstract concepts to objects and ac¬
tions. One gesture may mean many different, unrelated things. On this page: (1)
serpent's head; (2) head of a wild animal; (3) recipient or bud of a flower; (4) open
lotus; (5) the figure 4; (6) bee; (7) to hold; a bird; (8) fear; the figure 5; (9) to eat;
the navel; (10) a bird.
Opposite page: Yamin Krishnamurti, a leading exponent of Bharata Natyam who
was trained at Kalakshetra, the international centre for dance and music establish¬
ed at Madras by Rukmini Devi.
Lt
1=
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Photos © Sylvie Carnot, Paris Photo © Claude Sauvageot. Pari:
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Village
gods
and
heroes
This "Mother Goddess", some 3.5 metres in
height and dating from about 500 BC, was
discovered recently near a group of megalithic
dolmens. She is thought to be one of the fore¬
runners of the Srivatsa, or symbols of the god¬
dess of wealth, which began to appear in the
8th century AD. Similar mother goddess fer¬
tility figures have been found in many parts of
the world.
Potters enjoy a special status in Tamil Nadu. Unlike potters
in other parts of India they wear the "sacred thread" of the
"twice-born" (see caption page 13), which elsewhere is
reserved for higher castes, and they frequently act as unofficial
guardians of the smaller village temples. This hereditary task
enhances their standing in the community and gives them the
material advantage of a share in the offerings made to the gods
of meat, fruit and money. Although their main activity is the
making of pots and similar domestic utensils, Tamil potters are
famed for making the largest terra-cotta statues in the world.
Figures of horses, which can be as much as seven metres in
height, are much in demand as offerings, especially to the god
Ayanar. They are believed to serve as chargers for his warriors
when they make their nocturnal patrols to keep demons away
from the villages. Terra-cotta images of popular deities (wise
men or heroes) are also sometimes of monumental size,
although in recent years these have tended to be made of brick
and cement. Traditional methods are still used, however, for
small or medium-sized ex voto objects or statues offered to a
deity a statue of a child in thanks for its birth or recovery from
sickness; models of feet, hands or other limbs or parts of the
body, for recovery from injury or illness; even of animals (usual¬
ly cows and more rarely dogs and cats). The presentation of a
statue to a temple often involves the performance of quite com¬
plicated rites, but, even for the most humble votive offering,
the critical moment is the placing in position by the potter of the
eyes, the final, essential, life-giving gesture before installation
in the temple.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
©
ALTHOUGH it is the monumental architecture of India's
classical temples which usually overwhelms the visitor,
it is the country's folk temples, several times greater
in number, that reflect the living faith of the people.
India's village temples owe their origin to a belief in the
various manifestations malevolent and benevolent of the
spirit of nature, and to a conviction that God dwells in all
animate and inanimate phenomena trees, rivers, mountains,
water-tanks, the sea, lightning and the wind.
They are also connected to the fertility cult so widely
prevalent throughout the ancient world. Faith in the Mother
Goddess led to the personification of every village settlement
in a grama devata, a village Goddess who protects the villagers,
decides their fate and guides them like a fond mother.
Another concept that has made an important contribution to
the development of village Gods is the worship of heroes who
laid down their lives for the sake of their country or community.
These heroes were commemorated and worshipped by the
erection of Hero Stones or Memorial Stones, thousands of
which are found in Tamil Nadu and other parts of India.
The erection of Hero Stones and the adoration of the dead
hero as the saviour spirit of the community may be considered
as an extension of the prehistoric cult of erecting megalithic
tombs. The Hero-Stones are in the form of a dolmen with three
upright slabs erected in the form of a small chamber and topped
by a cap-stone. The figure of the hero is carved on the back
slab, facing the front. The representation of the hero on the slab
takes various forms. The simplest shows him in the act of
fighting with a spear, a sword, or bow and arrow.
In a number of cases the event relating to the death of the
hero, the period and the people who erected the stone are
recorded in the local language. In Tamil Nadu over 600 inscrib¬
ed memorials dating from the fourth century A.D. almost until
the present day have recently been found.
It is necessary to know something about Hero Stones in order
to understand the social background of the village temples.
Often the Stones stand beneath shady trees in simple surroun¬
dings. Long swords, spears, or tridents are placed in front of
them, as well as terra-cotta horses painted in folk style. It was
believed that the spirit of a hero resided forever in each monu¬
ment, bestowing benefactions on the community. The spirit
was dreaded, loved, adored and worshipped and was con¬
sidered the saviour of the community.
Some regional as opposed to village deities found in Tamil
Nadu arose from the cult of a hero's death. One of them,
Maduraiviran, who is worshipped in central Tamil Nadu, was a
seventeenth-century hero who defended the country valiantly
and was later put to death by its ruler after a love affair. The
romantic element and the hero's tragic end at the hands of the
very ruler he had fought for created such an aura around him
that soon his spirit was recognized as a most powerful divinity
and his temple was found in every village. The most important
feature of his temple is the huge figure of a horse placed either
in front of him or carrying him. People believe that his spirit
ascends the horse after dusk, and goes around the village pro¬
tecting the people at night.
Another factor in the development of village temples was the
veneration of women who died in heroic circumstances. One
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
such death that was popular was that of the chaste wife who
committed sati, that is, she died voluntarily on her husband's
funeral pyre. Recorded evidence for such customs is available
from the beginning of the Christian era. The spirits of women
who die in such circumstances are said to be very powerful,
protecting the community and also severely punishing wrong¬
doers. Their figures are carved on stones, enshrined and adored
as Masati.
In all these instances of the worship of the dead as the village
gods, the offering consists of all types of food and other things
that had pleased the dead person while he was alive. Offerings
of animal flesh and liquor are quite common modes of worship.
Animal sacrifice is often misundersood and blown up out of pro¬
portion. It arises out of the eating habits of the people. The sim¬
ple concept behind this offering is that whatever one eats is
first ceremoniously offered to the deity. The cock, chicken and
goat are offered in the presence of the deity, cooked and then
consumed by the worshipper. There are some temples where
even specially prepared cigars are offered.
Festivals are conducted annually for the village gods or are
specially arranged either to ward off natural calamities,
epidemics or threats to the community which are of human
origin. They are celebrated with great pomp and show. The
presence of the deity is felt so powerfully that to utter a lie in
its presence, it is believed, brings calamity to the teller. Many
disputes, such as proof of adultery, repudiation of loans receiv¬
ed and other such matters are settled even to this day in the
village temple. In many villages in the interior there is no need
for civil or criminal courts to decide the nature of punishments.
The temple of the village god, the impersonal spirit that
permeates and rules the society is sufficient to take care of evil¬
doers.
The village deity wards off all diseases. If a person is affected
in any part of his body, or the whole, he prays to the deity for
a cure and offers a replica of the afflicted member made of
terra-cotta, wood or metal. Or a full terra-cotta figurine
representing a human form is made and placed with devotion
in front of the deity. For happy child birth, a terra-cotta figure
of a child in a cradle is offered. To ward off cattle diseases, large
or small clay figures are likewise placed in the temple. Several
hundred such terra-cotta figurines can be seen in front of many
village temples. And on all such occasions the folk artist (mainly
the village potter) is honoured with new cloth, garlands of
flowers, special food and money. In fact the cult of the village
god was mainly responsible for sustaining and fostering folk
arts.
The cult of the village gods has also been a fount of inspira¬
tion for folk music and dance. Several hundred folk ballads and
songs are connected with the adoration of village heroes, and
during festivals they are sung by village minstrels for hours
sometimes throughout the night. So spirited are these folk
songs that even people who are in their houses rush towards
the sound of the music in a trance and sometimes thousands of
people can be seen on these occasions, marching, singing and
dancing.
This expression of devotion often takes the form of walking
barefoot over fire, piercing one's body with decorated needles
or lances, or carrying firepots in one's arms. Both men and
women take part in such devotions.
The conservatism of the village folk is revealed in their forms
of dress, ornamentation and mode of singing, which can be
traced back several centuries. For example, in the Alagar
festival held in Madurai during March and April, several thou¬
sand villagers dress themselves in colourful costumes, and
wear dresses and ornaments similar to those that can be seen
in sixteenth-century paintings and sculptures. Another festival
in Farur attracts several thousand men, who dress as women
and move through the streets singing and dancing. In another
interesting festival, held in a suburb of Madras, several men and
women clad in neem leaves circumambulate the temple of the
village goddess several times. The fact that such customs-
referred to in literature at the beginning of the Christian era
have survived to this day, very near the capital of the State,
shows the powerful hold these faiths have over the people.
Sometimes such folk beliefs and customs are superimposed
on the classical temple. There is a celebrated temple at Alagar
Koil near Madurai where worship is performed by orthodox
Vishnavite Brahmins according to classical rites. In the en¬
trance tower of the temple is the figure of a folk god, "Karup-
pan of the steps". The Karuppan, the spirit of the hero who
guarded the temple and lost his life when defending it from rob¬
bers, is held in greater veneration by the village people than the
main classical deity, Vishnu. When the annual festival for
Vishnu is celebrated, several million people assemble to adore
both Vishnu and the Karappan. Such a superimposition of folk
customs, music and dance on classical temples can be observ¬
ed in many places and seems, at least for the casual spectator,
to abolish the dividing line between the folk temple and the
classical temple.
However, there is one essential difference between the
classical temple and the folk temple. In the former there is a
trained family of worshippers, the priests, who perform the
daily acts of worship and the rites of periodical festivals as
prescribed. In other words, there is an intermediary between
the devotee and the divine. The priest's presence is accepted
as a necessity; he can perform acts of worship while the rest
of the community pursues its daily tasks and goes to the temple
only when in need.
In the village temples communication between the devotee
and the deity is direct and so the feeling of attachment is more
intimate. The divine spirit is always present in the village temple
and anyone can go and worship directly. Whatever the offering,
or whatever the form in which it is made, the village god is
pleased. This is why the village temples remain so popular.
R. Nagaswamy
30
Erected in 625 AD
during the reign of the
Pallava ruler Mahen-
dra I, this hero stone
immortalizes a hero
who fell, his faithful
dog at his side,
defending his cow¬
shed against robbers.
The details of this in¬
cident and the name
of the hero and the
dog are inscribed at
the top of the stone in
ancient Tamil script.
Photo © State Department of
Archaeology, Tamil Nadu
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Hindu harvest festival
Jean- Baptiste Fa'vre. Paris
Photos on this page show how Tamils in city and countryside
celebrate Pongal, one of the most important popular Hindu
festivals of the year. This four-day festival of thanksgiving to
nature takes its name from the Tamil word meaning "to boil"
and is held in the month of Thai (January-February) during the
season when rice and other cereals, sugar-cane, and turmeric
Ian essential ingredient in Tamil cooking) are harvested. On the
first day of Pongal, the puja or act of ceremonial worship is per¬
formed when rice is boiled in milk outdoors ¡n an earthenware
pot and is then symbolically offered to the sun-god along with
other oblations. Above, wearing traditional dress and markings,
husband and wife of a city brahmin family dispose of elegant
ritual utensils specially used for the puja. In the village, right,
where the ceremony is carried out more simply but with the
same devotion, the little girl is wearing a new dress and hair-
ribbon to mark the festive mood. In accordance with the ap¬
pointed ritual a turmeric plant has been tied around the pot in
which the rice will be boiled. The offerings include the two
sticks of sugar-cane in background and coconut and bananas in
the dish, A common feature of the puja, in addition to the offer
ings. is the kolam, the auspicious design which is traditionally
traced in white lime powder before the house in the early morn¬
ing after bathing. Above right, a highly elaborate kolam with
mazy floral and animal motifs being drawn for Pongal in a Pon-
dicherry street. On subsequent days of Pongal cows and bulls
are worshipped. Their horns are painted, they are decorated
with flowers, garlanded with bells, and offered the cooked
Pongal rice.
Photos John K Isaac
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
RY IN A LANDSCAPE
The world of Sangam
An early 10th-century
bronze of the poet-saint
Manikkavasaghar, author of
the great collection of devo¬
tional hymns known as the
Tiruvasagham. His extend¬
ed left hand holds palm
leaves, representing his
hymns, while his right hand
is in the vyakhyana position,
representing the teaching of
the supreme faith.
32
by François Gros
THE magical word Sangam conjures
up the golden age of Tamil litera¬
ture, that lost paradise of Dravidian
culture. It calls to mind the myth of the
three successive literary academies (the
word "sangam" means "academy") of a
fabulous era. The first and second
academies were swallowed up in deluges
comparable to the end of the world; only
the third was rescued from oblivion.
This third Sangam corresponds to
historical reality. Medieval commentators,
followed in turn by nineteenth- and
twentieth-century scholars, have preserved
the essence of this unique series of an¬
thologies, written in the oldest of all the
modern languages of India, which most
likely date back to the first centuries of the
Christian era. The Sangam is unques¬
tionably one of the high points in world
literature.
Little is known of the more than 450
authors, except that they came from all
classes of society, the sole criterion by
which they were judged being the recogni¬
tion of their talent by their peers. These
court poets sang the exploits of princes and
warriors or the sorrows of a nation at war.
Kings honoured them and they felt a keen
sense of their own dignity. On one occa¬
sion, the bard Mucikkiranar fell asleep in
the palace near the place reserved for the
royal drum, a sacrilege punishable by
death. Discovering him in this invidious
situation, the king, rather than taking harsh
measures against him, picked up a fan and
cooled his sleep, thus rendering homage to
his genius.
In this exemplary anecdote the magical
origins and totemic aspects of royalty are
seen in their relation to the sacred function
of the poet and the cathartic role of the
drummers (Pariahs). It should be added
that contemporary Tamil humour declares
Mucikkiranar to have been the first Indian
civil servant to fall asleep on the job! Yet if
today's poets are ironical, those of the
Sangam were the ambassadors of kings on
conciliatory missions (like Auvaiyar) and
tutors to the royal heirs (like Kapilar). Their
praise had to be merited and could not be
bought; their contempt or curse was
degrading, for they were men who exchang¬
ed gifts with kings.
Among themselves, Tamil poets were far
more than a brotherhood of starving bards
who exchanged addresses of generous
patrons. Rather they formed a sort of
academy, as indicated by the word
"Sangam". The legend of the Sangams was
FRANÇOIS GROS is director of studies at
the Ecole Pratique des. Hautes Etudes and
director of the Ecole Française d'Extrême
Orient, Paris. A specialist in Dravidian history
and literature, he was awarded the Prix Sain-
tour in 1969 for his translation into French of
Paripatal, an anthology of ancient Sangam
texts. The editors of the Unesco Courier wish
to acknowledge with gratitude the help and
advice given by Mr. Gros in the preparation of
this issue.
to be written later, but the historical reality
is somewhat elusive, save what can be
gleaned from the texts, from the stylized
mannerism of refined classicism, the
academism of a lost academy. Its code,
however, is well known to us. The Tolkap-
piyam, both a grammar and a richly com¬
mentated treatise on rhetoric, serves as a
linguistic reference book for this entire
period, which spanned several centuries at
the beginning of the Christian era.
At first reading, this poetrybrief and
varied, violent and outspoken, and at times
excessively romanticseems to speak to all
mankind in the language of the senses and
the passions. The wisdom it preaches is a
very humanistic, hedonistic stoicism, with,
quite exceptionally for India, very few
religious references. Yet these poems,
presented in strictly ordered anthologies,
have an inner discipline; words and images
are never arbitrarily employed. A system of
conventions and figures of speech imbues
even the least significant of notions with
underlying meanings and harmonies.
The anthologies lend themselves ad¬
mirably to modern linguistic analysis, for
they constitute a metalanguage within
which the universe is perfectly structured.
Some poems are concerned with the world
of the senses, with all that is tangible and
external (puram), dealing with civic or war¬
time exploits the seizure or recovery of
cattle, preparations for war (a place of safe¬
ty had to be found for the cattle, women,
children, the elderly and the priests), sieges,
battles, triumph and disarray, victory and
defeat. Others speak of the feelings and
more abstract relationships of the heart, the
anonymous and the internal (agam).
Every situation is described using themes
in which the time, the place and the floral
symbols of each episode are codified. The
inner universe is divided into five geo¬
graphical landscapesmountains, forest,
cropland, seashore and wasteland used as
symbols to imply a socio-economic order,
occupations and behaviour patterns which,
in turn, are symbolized by specific flora and
fauna. Details of secondary aspects are just
as rigidly codifiedthe seasons, the hour, a
god, musical instruments and, above all,
the sentimental connotations of each land¬
scape: lovers' meetings, patient waiting,
lovers' quarrels, separation, and the anx¬
iously awaited return.
The mountain is the scene of the lovers'
union at midnight. It is the cold, dewy
season. The forest is rich with lakes, water¬
falls, teak, bamboo and sandalwood. In
this region millet grows and wild bees are a
source of honey.
Love in this setting is exemplified by
Murugan, that most Tamil of gods, and one
of his wives, Valli, the daughter of moun¬
taineers. He wears the sparkling red kantal
flower and rides a peacock, the bird of the
mountains. The name of the region, kurin-
ci, is also the name of a famous flower from
the lofty hills of Tamil country. In this same
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
region grows the strobilanth, a shrub whose
brilliant white flowers blossom for only a
few days once every ten or twelve years,
blanketing the slopes in radiant whiteness
under the sun. This event of jubilation and
purity symbolizes the frenzy of a sudden
love shared, in concert with the unleashed
forces of nature: the amorous dance of
peacocks, their echoing cries, the splash of
waterfalls, the roar of savage beasts.
The lovers hold each other tighter still
and forget the dangers of the mountain
path. This region is dearest to the hearts of
the Tamil people and, according to legend,
the great poet Kapilar wrote the Song of
Below, the central figure of
this sculpture at the great
temple of Tanjore, built by
the Chola emperor Raja Raja
I around 1 000 AD, is the god
Murugan seated on his
mount, the peacock. The
chief deity of the ancient
Tamils, Murugan later
became identified with
Skanda, the northern Indian
god of war and first-born
son of Siva, and still has a
large following in southern
India under the name of
Subrahmanya. Right,
modern street mural depic¬
ting Murugan.
Kurinci as an example for an Aryan king of
a typical Tamil love poem.
The theme of wasteland and separation
occupies half of one of the most famous an¬
thologies, the theme of the mountain being
only secondary. The theme of the forest and
of shepherds at play, the image of confident
waiting for the loved one, produced an
original offshoot; for this is the region of
Vishnu, and the love theme it represents
symbolizes the devotee waiting in the hope
that Vishnu, as Krishna, will eventually
come and fill his soul, thus experiencing the
joys of expectation.
The plains were the scene of triangular
Photo Emmanuel Guillou © Atlas Photo,
Paris
love plots in which the hero's visits to the
courtesan oblige the heroine to counter with
a mixed show of coquetry and moodiness,
tactics whose limits are described in the
Kural ("Sulking is like flavouring with salt;
a little suffices, but it is easy to go too
far."). Sangam poets offer countless ex¬
amples of this:
The man of the village by the ponds
where the carp seize the ripe fruit of the
mango trees that line the fields.
In our land he is high and mighty; but in
theirs. . .
When arms and legs are raised, he raises
his
Like a puppet, a reflection in a mirror,
He does all he is asked, for the mother of
his son.
The courtesan, jealous of the wife, is
speaking here. The landscape is defined by
the designation of the hero (a fellow from
the village), the mention of a creature (the
carp), the tree (the mango), the water-filled
scenery (the pond), the season (that of
ripened mangoes and sultry heat, a secon¬
dary characteristic and sign of separation).
The situation implies that the courtesan
wishes to be heard by the heroine's con¬
fidante. Through the image of the opening
lines she indicates that the hero has fallen
freely for her wiles and that to win him she
did not have to infringe upon his home
ground; he is a hero of little substance, it
would seem, in a situation dominated by
women.
Although interpretation and the
deciphering of the conventions of these
texts can at times seem tiresome, the last
landscape, the seashore, affords many ex¬
amples of the compelling charm of Sangam
poetry and the extraordinary freshness of
its realism. From behind the conventional
symbolization of waiting there emerges a
picture of the life of the fisherfolk; the nets
and boats drawn up on the beach, scuttling
crabs and cart wheels bogged down in the
sand, the odour of drying fish, cut into
thick slices, which attracts the birds,
beautiful village girls peering through the
pandanus hedges, and the wind blowing
through the cracks in the roughly con¬
structed straw huts at night.
We must allow the texts to speak to us.
The more the theoretical account highlights
the unreality of the conventions used, the
more each verse bristles with realistic
imagesa marvellous juxtaposition of
words and subtle manipulation of rhetoric
in which a twofold technique of suggestion
(iraicci) and complex metaphor (ullurai
uvamam) evokes a situation, and thus a
mood, by describing a natural
phenomenon, whilst the description alone
suffices to imply the, most explicit of sen¬
timental relationships.
Careful use of rhetoric and its underlying
themes and conventions make for great
economy in descriptive writing. In contrast
to the weightiness of the theoretical inter¬
pretation, the poems reveal a subtle
freedom of movement in the dense matrix
of allusions and in the art of bending the
conventions by mixing the themes to test the
shrewdness of the cultivated reader.
Sangam poetry has often been considered
the crowning achievement of a long oral
tradition; however, the works that have sur¬
vived to this day are among the most
magnificent and most living examples of
written poetry. François Gros
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
New writing in Tamil
by S. Ramakrishnan
THE late 1960s were marked by an
upsurge in Tamil creative writing.
The preoccupation with ancient
Tamil culture had subsided, Tamil had been
made the language of school and higher
education and world Tamil conferences
were making the Tamil language interna¬
tionally known. The new poetry movement,
which had started in the early 1930s, was
still finding its feet, fostered mainly by
small, short-lived magazines reaching a
reading public of not more than one or two
thousand.
Against this background Tamil writers
turned for encouragement and support to
two small-circulation but influential
magazines, C.S. Chellappa's Ezhuthu
(founded in 1959) and Ka Na
Subramaniyam's Ilakkiya Vattam (found¬
ed in 1964). These two magazines, and the
writers who contributed to them, took as
their model Manikkodi, a magazine found¬
ed in the mid-1930s, in which the first at¬
tempt had been made to base literature on
the realities of life.
The founders of Manikkodi were vi¬
sionaries. They realized the need to provide
an alternative to the new popular magazines
which were beginning to make their in¬
fluence felt. Although they were na¬
tionalists committed to liberating the coun¬
try from foreign rule, they were also alive to
the need to bring Tamil consciousness into
contact with the mainstream of interna¬
tional culture. They themselves had
benefited from English education and
through it from exposure to world culture.
In Manikkodi there arose a major voice,
that of Pudumaipittan, who still remains a
main source of the contemporary literary
tradition. Pudumaipittan held that writers
had purposes other than that of using
literature simply as a vehicle for the pro¬
pagation of certain ideologies. He declared
that his stories were not intended to be a
means of educating the world and that art
could not be confined within a philosophy
of the sustenance of life. At a time when a
group of writers, such as Girija Devi,
Tamamirthammal and Va Ra, were obsess;
ed with the evils of the caste system and the
need to cut across caste barriers, particular¬
ly as far as marriage was concerned,
Pudumaipittan had the courage to point
out in his writings the problems that could
arise in intercaste marriages as a result
of the partners' differing cultural
backgrounds.
Almost all the progressive writers of to¬
day who subscribe to the Marxist ideology
trace their lineage back to Pudumaipittan.
Among the writers of the post-
independence generation T.M.C. Reghu-
nathan was one of the first to attract wide
attention with his Panjum Pasiyum (1953),
a novel depicting the capitalist/worker
34
THE THREAD AND THE BOOK. Venerated as Mother Tamil and Goddess Tamil,
the Tamil language is traditionally regarded as the creation of the god Murugan
and its grammar as a revelation by the Lord Siva. Tamil literature is the oldest
in India apart from that written in classical Sanskrit. In the Tamil language the
same word nul is used to denote both a thread and a finished work, symbolized
by three generations of villagers, above, twisting coconut fibres into cord.
relationship. He was followed by D. Jaya-
kanthan, a more prolific writer whose
earlier stories and novels espoused the
cause of the underdog.
Jayakanthan wrote about a wide range of
issues: the urban middle-class, the under¬
privileged urban slum-dweller, women in
revolt, the notions of art, the confrontation
between the traditional and the modern way
of life and the changes this necessitated, the
notions of brahminhood, justice, aspects of
sexuality, and so on. His vociferousness
was infectious and he became a model for
many writers.
The younger generation of leftist writers
(including Poomani, Pa Jayaprakasam and
Rajendra Cholan) drew their inspiration
from both Pudumaipittan and Jayakan¬
than, but without displaying the same
breadth of vision and limiting themselves to
close examination of village life and the
working class.
What has marked the work of pro¬
gressive writers has been a common concern
to make literature a tool to awaken and
reunite the working classes. Basically they
are propagandists and, in one sense, this
trend has dominated most modern Tamil
literature.
The earlier progressives were motivated
by what they saw as the threat to Indian
culture from English education and grow¬
ing urbanization. Vedanayagam Pillai, a
former district judge and a Christian whose
first novel Prathapa Mudaliyan was
published in 1879, declared that his work
emphasized devotion to God and the
obligatory social responsibilities. His con¬
temporary Rajam Iyer felt compelled to
write by the need to preserve rural tradi¬
tions and the path to Bhakti (devotion),
while Madhaviah, who also shared the anx¬
iety about the survival of traditional
culture, was urged to write by the status of
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
women, ignorant and uninformed (it was
the period of child-marriage and child
widows), and the threat urbanization posed
to the individual.
In the same vein, the succeeding genera¬
tion of writers used literature as a tool for
social purposes. Two good examples are Va
Ra's Sundari and Bharati's unfinished
novel Chandrikaiyin Karai. Both deal with
the problems of widows, their position in
society and their re-marriage. In 1920 Gan¬
dhi entered the arena of national politics
and his philosophy began to assert its in¬
fluence on many writers. In 1926 Panayap-
pa Chettiyar first wrote about the need for
national independence and in 1930 K.S.
Venkataramani wrote his novel
Desabhakthan Kandan which propagated
Gandhian ideals regarding rural develop¬
ment and the place of the village in the life
of the country.
During the 1930s commercial magazines
began to appear, the most popular being
Ananda Vikatan. It owed its success mainly
to Kalki, a prolific writer and the author of
Thyaga Bhumi, a novel which became an
instant success due to its nationalistic
message. Kalki's impact on his readers was
such that more magazines began to appear
thus creating a vast market for popular
writing. Since the 1970s these magazines
have proliferated and today they have a
strong hold on the cultural life of Tamil
Nadu.
The Pudumaipittan "lineage" can be
traced among a certain number of writers
whose works constitute a very significant
contribution to the language. In a sense,
Sundara Ramaswamy's J.J. Sila Kurip-
pukal and Puliya Marathin Kadhai, and G.
Nagarajan's Nalai Matrumoru Nale, and a
number of his short stories, represent the
realization of Pudumaipittan's objective of
placing literature in the context of the harsh
reality of life. These two writers have in
common their lucidity, their incisive points
of view, sincerity with regard to their ex¬
perience and a balance between social pur¬
pose and the needs of art.
From the time of Pudumaipittan on¬
wards, Tamil literature has drawn inspira¬
tion from a handful of writers, almost all of
whom are the product of Indian culture and
Indian ways of thought. Among the most
important of these are Ka Na
Subramaniyam and C.S. Chellappa. These
two writers were the ones who sustained
modern creative and critical prose and
poetry in the most adverse conditions dur¬
ing the period 1945 to 1965, both, with
equal fervour, leading the movement
towards literary criticism and the new
poetry through the medium of various
small-circulation magazines.
Ka Na Subramaniyam's Poithevu (1943),
one of the most important novels in the
Tamil language, draws upon the Tamil
psyche with its innate preoccupation with
the God/man relationship and the
philosophical quest. His short stories are
uneven in quality, yet one or two of them,
like Azhagi, are very important. Chellap-
pa's Vadivasal and Jeevanamsam also find
their source in the traditional world.
Mowni, whose writings were first
published in Manikkodi, must be con¬
sidered a major figure in Tamil literature.
Mowni's world is the world of the introvert.
He brought forth in his stories an intensity
of feeling which is unmatched in Tamil. He
was able to create this intensitymostly
centering on the themes of man/woman
relationships and death thanks to a
powerful yet deceptively simple prose style.
One of the most popular yet accomplish¬
ed writers in the literary sense is T.
Janakiraman. He is a strange combination
of traditional influences and a capacity to
give a dream-like quality to the life he
depicted. Like many of his predecessors he
was fascinated by the man/woman relation¬
ship, but his depiction of it was a clever
balance between the popular writer's over¬
simplification of its intricacies and the com¬
plexity of Mowni. Born in a Tanjore
village, his descriptions of the enchanting
aspects of rural Tanjore, with its
agricultural setting, temple culture and
music, enhanced the appeal of his writing.
It was in his short stories, however, that
he achieved his greatest literary success, and
in this tradition a group of modern creative
writers has emerged. Significant among
them are Asokamithran, Vannanilavan,
Vannadasan, Sa Kandasamy and Ra-
janarayanan. These authors are situated
somewhere between Pudumaipittan and the
leftist writers. With their under-stated style
Asokamithran and Kandaswamy evoke the
charm and elusiveness of the day-to-day life
of the middle-class. They never over-react,
they operate within narrow stylistic ranges,
but their sensibilities are a sincere reflection
of their experience.
Vannadasan and Vannanilavan have
much in common. Both are post-1970
writers, they come from similar
backgrounds and they are very sensitive to
the physical and emotional life around
them. To both, the simple joys and depriva¬
tions of ordinary people are important,
though Vannadasan tends to romanticize
them. He is a little dreamy-eyed in his por¬
trayal of the eternal abiding goodness and
charm of simple folk. Vannanilavan has a
slightly larger canvas and is concerned with
the psychological implications of
situations of human relationships, of
economic situations and those arising from
a sense of awe at the world.
S. Ramakrishnan
CONTEMPORARY TAMIL PAINTING
In both style and content contemporary
artists of Tamil Nadu draw inspiration
from many sources ranging from tradi¬
tional sculptures with their mythological
allusions to folk themes and devel¬
opments in 20th-century European art.
Brahmasutra (1978), above, by K. V.
Haridasan, who has taken Yantras, linear
diagrams used in ancient Tantric texts as
a support for meditation, out of their
mystical context and used them as a
basis for abstract designs. In Toilette,
below, K. Srinivasulu has combined folk
motifs with a cubistic approach. Discuss¬
ing the challenge modern Tamil artists
have faced as they seek to develop their
own individual styles of expression, the
Tamil artist and critic V. Jayaraman has
written: "... it was and still is today dif¬
ficult for Tamil Nadu artists to give ex¬
pression to an identity in line with their
rich cultural heritage which is tightly
woven around metaphysical values.
Painters were particularly at a loss since
there was no real prototype of traditional
' work for them to follow. Sculptures were
the only forms of plastic expression to
which they could refer since so little an¬
cient painting had survived. They were to
find the nucleus of their inspiration in the
architecture of temples, in the roman¬
ticism that exists within a sculpture in
spite of its rigorous classical
measurements, in the rhythm of rasa
[flavour] and bhava [mood], and in the
fascinating contradiction between
abstract ideas being expressed through
form and figurative forms expressed
through abstract designs a rich foun-
tainhead of 'Surrealism' as opposed to
the self-induced hallucinations of the ac¬
cepted Surrealists."
35
Photos © V. Jayaraman, Madras
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Raghavendra Rao, Madras
Tamil
women
at the
crossroads
by C. S. Lakshmi
IN the Tamil epics women are de¬
picted as formidable personalities
with superior moral power, capable
of such extraordinary feats as burning
down an entire city to avenge the death of
a husband. This image persisted until the
dawn of the twentieth century, by which
time Tamil women were becoming aware
that it contrasted starkly with the realities
of their inferior status and were athirst
for knowledge and formal education. A
number of distinguished men supported
the cause of women's education, but con¬
troversy arose about the kind of educa¬
tion that should be provided and about
the medium of instruction. Since women
were considered as "do-gooders" it was
widely felt that education should prepare
them for service in such careers as
teaching and, later, medicine.
C. S. LAKSHMI is a specialist in women's
studies who is currently working on an illustra¬
ted social history of women in Tamil Nadu in
the twentieth century.
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
While the early women teachers who
taught girls in their homes in the second
half of the nineteenth century had mostly
been Christians, in the early twentieth
century it was Hindu widows who met
the need for a body of committed
teachers. Hindu widows were not allow¬
ed to remarry and there were large
numbers of them because of the prevail¬
ing system of child marriage. (Little girls
aged two or three often found themselves
widows, condemned to a life of
drudgery. Brahmin widows were' also
tonsured when they came of age, and
thus became physical outcasts as well.)
The fate of many of these widows
began to change through the pioneering
work of a courageous young woman
named Subbalakshmi, fondly known as
Sister Subbalakshmi, who grew up
among widows and was for many years
haunted by a childhood memory of atten¬
ding a wedding where she had seen a
three-year-old girl being teased because
she was a widow. Sister Subbalakshmi
was herself widowed at the age of eleven
and was only able to pursue her studies
because she was encouraged to do so by
her liberal-minded father. She trained to
be a teacher and then opened a home for
widows and began to train them as
teachers too.
Women's education gave rise to many
jokes about women who neglected their
homes while their husbands struggled
with the children, and about women who
could not cook without referring to a.
book of recipes. New fashions in clothes
were also made fun of in cartoons and
jokes which expressed the anxieties and
fears of a generation of people con¬
fronted by a changing world.
It was but a short step from education
for "service" to activities in favour of
reform. In the early twentieth century
two Englishwomen, Annie Besant.and
Margaret Cousins, were active in the
social and political life of southern India.
In 1917 Annie Besant founded the
Women's Indian Association, and the
All India Women's Conference was in¬
augurated by Margaret Cousins in 1926.
These movements fought for such major
reforms as the raising of the age of con¬
sent for marriage, the franchise, and the
abolition of the Devadasi system. [The
Devadasi belonged to a caste of women
dedicated to the service of the patron
gods of the great temples]. Many upper-
class Indian women were inspired to call
for social reform by the two
Englishwomen, who were demanding
that the Vedic past should be revived.
Women also began to be increasingly
active in writing and the other arts. Not
only did members of the Devadasi com¬
munity, who were traditionally artists,
appear on stage and screen; women such
as Kalanidhi, Rukmini Devi and D.K.
Pattammal, who belonged to com¬
munities which traditionally did not
practise the performing arts, now became
prominent in dance and music. With the
launching of Jegan Mohini, edited by
Vai. Mu. Kodainayaki Ammal, and
Chinthamani, edited by Sister Balam-
mal, women's magazines run by women
came into vogue and began to stimulate
debate and discussions on women's
issues.
As the nation-wide agitation for in¬
dependence gathered momentum,
women were inspired by Gandhi to enter
the political arena. They picketed shops
selling imported cloth, spoke on party
platforms, travelled to spread Gandhi's
ideas, wrote articles on the need for a new
role for women, and became active in
literacy programmes. p.
Dressed in her finest
clothes and garlanded
with flowers, this Tamil
girl is the focus of atten¬
tion as she undergoes
the ceremony of satanku
to mark her arrival at the
age of puberty. A relative
places a red mark,
known as a pottu, on her
forehead both as a bless¬
ing and to ward off the
evil eye.
Photo © Marie-Louise Reiniche, Paris
Photo © All rights reserved
Sister Subbalakshmi, one of the pioneers of
education for Tamil women and leader of the
struggle to rescue widows from their miserable
status as work drudges and social outcasts.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
TAMIL WOMEN AT THE CROSSROADS
In 1947 the Women's Welfare Depart¬
ment was started and set itself "the dif¬
ficult and comprehensive task of
assisting women in rediscovering
themselves". Since the 1950s the world of
Tamil women seems to have expanded to
encompass fields from which they were
previously excluded. The working
woman has become a familiar figure in
the towns and cities. Women's associa¬
tions have proliferated. The literacy rate
among Tamil women is comparatively
high.
In spite of these changes, however, the
roles formerly performed by women have
neither disappeared nor been transform¬
ed. Although it may be camouflaged in
various ways, the traditional image of the
chaste woman and the devoted mother is
still reflected in modern Tamil literature,
in the media, and in customs. Most
female characters in stories have an overt
and a hidden face. The overt face is seem¬
ingly "modern", but at some point in the
story the character proves that modernity
has not destroyed her hidden, more
beautiful, traditional face. Gruesome
punishments are often meted out to those
who stray from this cast-iron mould: fire
and water are considered purifying
elements and have often been used as
devices for the physical destruction of an
"impure" character. When physical
destruction is eschewed, social degrada¬
tion, ostracism and neglect provide alter¬
natives which in some cases may seem
less merciful.
The media image of women, shaped by
commercialization, is very close to that
found in literature. In the media the
traditional and modern images are often
termed "good" and "bad", and more
often than not the "good" prevails over
the "bad". Commercial values have also
affected family relationships, including
the institution of marriage, with women
being considered as saleable or non-
saleable commodities. The dowry has
assumed oppressive importance; instead
of being liberated, the woman who works
in an office has been transformed into a
dowry-earning individual.
The gulf between the urban and rural
woman has widened. In the early part of
the century the rural woman was con¬
sidered a romantic figure, morally
courageous and physically beautiful. She
sang soft lullabies and traditional love-
songs in her unsophisticated rustic voice.
Much has happened to change this idyllic
image, and it is today realized that the
rural woman belongs to an anonymous,
faceless mass enmeshed in the reality of
the struggle for a better existence.
For the Tamil woman today there are
many grounds for apprehension but
there are also grounds for hope. She
stands at a cross-roads, and the very fact
that she is aware of this is one hopeful
sign. There are others. Most of the
women's magazines that project the im¬
age of the homely woman will sometimes
devote space to discussion of a law affec¬
ting women, women's psychological pro¬
blems, or the way in which women's lives
have been ruined by distorted values.
Although coverage of such topics may be
surrounded by masses of recipes and ar¬
ticles on embroidery and dressmaking, it
nevertheless makes a dent, albeit a small
one, in a structure built on hearth and
home. From time to time a woman with
a questioning mind is also portrayed in
the media, but even though such por¬
trayals are diluted because of commercial
considerations they have still not been ac¬
cepted without comment.
The earlier phases of "rediscovery"
were directed into mother and child care
projects. They were geared to traditional
needs and were an extension of earlier
charitable activities. Today organiza¬
tions such as the Women's Democratic
Front and the Penn Urimai Iyakkam
(Women's Rights Movement) are bent on
transforming the image of women and
working towards more meaningful forms
of "rediscovery". Most women,
however, are still looking at the sky but
have not yet decided to fly. Their wings
are not clipped, and the time is not far off
when they will use them.
CS. Lakshmi
Three great
scientists
Sir Chandrasekara Venkata Raman
(1888-1970) was awarded the Nobel
Prize for Physics in 1 930 for his work on
the diffusion of light and for the
discovery of what is known as the
Raman effect. Raman discovered that
when a beam of light passes through a li¬
quid or a gas it is scattered and the fre¬
quency of some of the scattered light is
changed. This change in frequency pro¬
vides a way to study the structure of the
scattering molecules, and the Raman ef¬
fect has had wide applications in study¬
ing the constitution and properties of
various substances solids, liquids and
gases. Born in Trichinopoly, he founded
the Indian Journal of Physics and the In¬
dian Academy of Sciences.
Srinivasa Ramanujan (1881-1920)
was one of the greatest mathematicians
of modern times. He was born into a
South Indian Brahmin family at Erode,
and at the age of 15 his genius was
aroused when he verified the results of
the 6,000 theorems collected in G.S.
Carr's Synopsis of Elementary Results in
Pure and Applied Mathematics and then
developed his own theorems and ideas.
In 1 91 1 he published his first paper in the
Journal of the Indian Mathematical
Society and in 1914 travelled to England
to work with the British mathematician
G.H. Hardy at ,Trinity College, Cam¬
bridge. Ramanujan's knowledge of
mathematics was extraordinary. His
work has been applied to the investiga¬
tion of the temperature of furnaces and
his theories are being studied to explore
their potentiality for understanding and
regulating atomic furnaces.
Subrahmanyan Chandrasekhar (born
1910), the astrophysicist, is the second
Tamil to win a Nobel Prize. The nephew
of Sir C.V. Raman, he was awarded the
1983 Nobel Prize for Physics for his
Theoretical studies of the physical pro¬
cesses of importance to the structure
and evolution of stars. He developed the
accepted theory of the development of
"white dwarfs" small white stars of
highly compacted, extremely dense
matter.
"o
z in
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the
editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author's
name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on re¬
quest. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply
coupon covering postage. Signed articles express
the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the
editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier
staff. The boundaries on maps published in the maga¬
zine do not imply official endorsement or acceptance
by Unesco or the United Nations.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform
(microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) University
Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100,
U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian Head.
Inc., 111 West 40th Street, New York, U.S.A.; (3)
Bell and Howell Co.. Old Mansfield Road, Wooster.
Ohio 44691. U.S.A.
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
French: Alain Lévêque (Paris)
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov (Pa'ris)
Arabic: Sayed Osman (Paris)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: Mohammed Reza Berenji (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Kim U-Yearn (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salam)
Braille: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slo¬
vene: Vitomir Sudarski (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Alchis Angelou
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Special projects: Peggy Julien
All correspondence should be addressed to the
Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
New trends
in school science
equipment
New Trends in School Science Equipment pro¬
vides an overall picture of trends in the use of
science equipment around the world indicating
the approaches and actions necessary to ensure
that the learning of science becomes a practical
reality for all children.
Four sections deal with Laboratory work and
practical activities The development and pro¬
duction of school science and technology equip¬
ment The training of teachers and technicians
Information and communication.
Edited by Norman K. Lowe
161 pages 50 French francs
Now available
The 1983 Catalogue of Unesco Publications lists all
Unesco books andperiodicals currently available on the
following subjects: General reference; Education;
Science; Social science; Culture; Communication;
Documentation; Libraries and archives; Official
publications. The Catalogue is available from national
distributors of Unesco publications (see below).
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscription
rates in local currency, will be supplied on
request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Colling-
wood Victoria 3066; Publications: Educational Supplies Pty.
Ltd. P.O. Box 33, Brookvale, 2 1 00, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie
Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33. Brookvale 2100, NSW.
Sub- agent: United Nations Association of Australia, P.O. Box
175, 5th floor, Ana House, 28 Elizabeth Street, Melbourne
Victoria 3000. - AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co.,
Graben 31, A-1011, Vienna. - BAHAMAS. Nassau Sta¬
tioners Ltd., P.O. Box N-3138, Nassau. - BANGLADESH.
Bangladesh Books International Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1 , R.K.
Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3. - BARBADOS. University
of the West Indies Bookshop, Cave Hill Campus, P.O. Box 64,
Bridgetown. BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition
only: N.V. Handelmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18,
2100 Deurne- Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco
publications agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1 060
Brussels, CCPOOO-0070823-13. - BOTSWANA. Botswana
Book Centre, P.O. Box 91 , Gaborone. BURMA. Trade Cor¬
poration No. 9, 550-552 Merchant Street, Rangoon.
CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine
Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H 1M7. CHAD. Librairie
Abssounout, 24 av. Charles de Gaulle, B.P. 388, N'Djamena.
CHINA. China National Publications Import and Export Cor¬
poration, P.O. Box 88, Beijing CYPRUS. "MAM", Ar¬
chbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena 51 , Prague 1 (Per¬
manent display}; Zahranicni literatura, 1 1 Soukenicka, Prague
1 . For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers, Hurbanovo
nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava - CSSR. - DENMARK.
Munksgaard Export and Subscription Service, 35 Norre
Sogade, DK 1370, Copenhagen K. - EGYPT (ARAB
REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco Publications, No.
1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo. - ETHIOPIA. National Agency
for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa. - FINLAND.
Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100 Helsinki
10; Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, Koivuvaarankuja 2, 01640
Vantaa 64. FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de
Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP. 12598-48. - GABON.
Librairie Hachette, B.P. 3923, Libreville. GERMAN
DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710
Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R.
- FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier (Ger¬
man, English, French and Spanish editions): Mr. H. Baum,
Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57, D5300
Bonn 3. For other Unesco publications: Karger Verlag, Germer-
¡ng/München. For scientific maps only: Geo Center, Postfach
800830, Stuttgart 80. GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop
Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 1 95, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd.,
P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana, Ac¬
cra; The University Bookshop of Cape Coast; The University
Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1 , Legon. - GREAT BRITAIN.
See United Kingdom. HONG KONG. Federal Publications
(HK) Ltd.. 5A Evergreen Industrial Mansion, 1 2 Yip Fat Street,
Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon.
Hong Kong Government Information Services, Publication
Centre, Baskerville House, 22 Ice Street. - HUNGARY.
Akademiai Konyvesbolt. Váci u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V.
Konyvtürosok Boltja, Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest VI.
ICELAND. Snaebjórn Jonsson & Co., H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9,
Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 1 7 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2;
5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh, Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahat-"
ma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001. Sub-Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery
Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House, New
Delhi; Publication Unit, Ministry of Education and Culture, Ex.
AFO Hutments, Dr. Rajendra Prasad Road, New Delhi 1 1 0001 .
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl.
Oto Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Indira P. T., Jl Dr Sam
Ratulangie 37, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing
and Distribution Co., 28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Enghélab
Avenue. P.O. Box 314/1 486, Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for
Unesco. Seyed Jamal Eddin Assad Abadi Avenue 64th Street,
Bonyad Building P.O. Box 1533, Teheran. IRAQ. McKen¬
zies Bookshop, AI Rashid Street, Baghdad. IRELAND. The
Educational Company of Ireland Ltd, Ballymount Road,
Walkinstown, Dublin 12; Tycooly International Publ. Ltd 6
Crofton Terrace, Dun Laoghaire Co., Dublin. ISRAEL.
A. B.C. Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel
Aviv 61000. ITALY. Licosa (Librería Commissionaria San-
soni, S.p.A.I Via Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552, 50121
Florence. - JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O.
Box 366, 1 0 1 Water Lane, Kingston. University of the West In¬
dies Bookshop, Mona, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book
Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo 3-chome Bunkyo-ku Tokyo 113.
KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O. Box 30571,
Nairobi. KOREA. Korean. National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. - KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait; for the Unesco
Courier; Farafalla Press Agency, P.O. Box SAFA 4541,
Kuwait. LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod.
Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA. Code and Yancy
Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia. - LIBYA. Agency
for Development of Publication & Distribution, P.O. Box
34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22,
Grande-Rue, Luxembourg. MALAWI. Malawi Book Ser¬
vice, Head Office, P.O. Box 30044 Chichiri, Blantyre 3. -
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Cooperative Bookshop,
Kuala Lumpur 22-11. MALTA. Sapienzas. 26 Republic
Street, Valletta. - MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30,
Bourbon Street, Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30
bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. NEPAL. Sajha Prakashan
Polchowk, Kathmandu. NETHERLANDS. For periodicals
only: D&N -Faxon B.V., P.O. Box 1 97, 1 000 AD Amsterdam;
for publications only: KEESING BOEKEN B.V., Postbus 1118,
1000 BC Amsterdam. - NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van
Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A.
NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, Govern¬
ment Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland;
130, Oxford Terrace. P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch; Alma
Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1 1 04,
Dunedin, Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington.
NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The University
Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka; The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zaria. NORWAY. All publications:
Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43,
Oslo 1 ; Universitets Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, P.O.B.
307 Blindern, Oslo 3. For Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narvesens
Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6. - PAKISTAN. Mirza
Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O. Box No. 729,
Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern Book Co., 926 Rizal
Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. - POLAND. Orpan-
Import, Palac Kultury I Naukl, Warsaw; Ars Polona-Ruch,
Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068 WARSAW. - POR¬
TUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo
70, Lisbon. - SEYCHELLES. National Bookshop, P.O. Box
48, Mahé; New Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131,
Mahé. SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay. Njala University and
Sierra Leone Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (S) Pte Ltd. Times
Jurong, 2 Jurong Port Road, Singapore 2261. SOMALI
DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and
General, P.O. Box 951 , Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA. For
the Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Central News agency,
P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg. - SRI LANKA. Lake House
Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B.
244 Colombo 2. - SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box
1118. Khartoum. - SWEDEN. All publications A/B.C.E.
FritzesKungl, Hovbokhandel, Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356.
10327 Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN
Forbundet, Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm.
- SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag. 5
Rämistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211,
Geneva 1 1 , CCP. 1 2-236. Librairies Payot also ¡n Lausanne,
Basle, Berne, Vevey, Montreux, Neuchâtel and Zurich.
TANZANIA. Dares Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-
Salaam. - THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42
Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri. P.O. Box 402;
Bangkok: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue,
Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road,
Bangkok. - TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. National Commis¬
sion for Unesco, 1 8 Alexandra Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I.
- TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S., Istiklâl Caddesi, N° 469,
Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu, Istambul. - UGANDA. Uganda
Bookshop, P.O. Box 71 45. Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM.
H.M. Stationery Office, H.M. S.O., P.O. Box 276, London,
SW8 5DT, and Govt. Bookshops in London. Edinburgh,
Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol;. for scientific maps
only: McCarta Ltd., 1 22 King's Cross Road, London WC 1 X 9
DS. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, 205 East 42nd Street,
New York, N.Y. 10017. Orders for books & Periodicals: Box
433, Murray Hill Station, New York, N.Y. 101 57. - U.S.S.R.
Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Moscow, G-200
YOUGOSLAVIA. Mladost. Mica 30/1 1, Zagreb; Cankarjeva
Zalozba, Zopitarjeva 2, Lubljana; Nolit, Terazije 27/11,
Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National Educational Distribution Co.
of Zambia Ltd., P.O. Box 2664 Lusaka. - ZIMBABWE.
Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union Avenue, Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
, I I I
A striking feature of rural life in the State of Tamil Nadu and other parts of southern India is the presence
in almost every settlement of shrines and colourfully painted statues honouring folk heroes and protec¬
tive deities. Above, the mounted effigy of a folk deity dominates a group of villagers threshing rice.
]]>
</page>
</document>
