<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074696eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
S PEe 1 A L'I S SUE : THE He IN E M A
Elena Varzi extending a hand of friendship in
"The Road to Hope", the 1951 Italian"Silver
Laurel Award"for European films contributing
to goodwill among peoples. (See þages 3 and 7.)
ART I C L E S BY : Sir Michael
Balcon, Charles Spaak, Luigi
Chiarini, Bosley Crowther, Dilys
Powell and Stephen Watts.
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-PACK 1
ED ITOR IAL OFFICES :
UNESCO HOUSE
19, Ave. tCtber, PARtS-tt
Editor-) n-Chief : S. M. KOFFLER
EDITORS
Enclish edition : R. S. FENTON
French edition : A. LEVENTIS
Spanish edition : J. DE BENITO
All reproduction. authorized
Imprimerie GEORGES LANG
II, rue Curial. Paris.
MC. 51. I. 52. A.
A full year's subscription (12 issues)
costs only $1. 50 U. S., *or5/-or ZOO
French Francs.
Write to our agent in your country
listed below, or directly to UNESCO
House, 19, avenue Kleber, Paris-16e,
France.
Argentina : Editorial Sudamericana,
S. A., Alsina 500, Buenos Aires.
Australia : H. A. Goddard Ltd., 255 a
George Street, Sydney.
Austria : Wilhelm Frick Verlag, 27 Gra-
ben, Vienna 1.
Barbados : S. P. C. K. Bookshop (Regional
Office Caribbean Area), Broad Street,
Bridgetown.
Belgium : Librairie Encyclopedique, 7,
rue du Luxembourg, Brussels IV.
Bolivia : Libraria Selecciones, Av. 16 de
Juìio 216, Casilla 972, La Paz.
Brazil : Livraria Agir Editora, Rua
Mexico 98-B, Caixa postal 3291, Rio
de Janeiro.
Burma : Burma Educational Bookshop,
551-3 Merchant Street, P. O. Box 222,
Rangoon.
Cambodia and Associated States 01
Indo-China : K. Chantarik, C. C. R.,
38, rue Van Vollenhoven, Phnom-Penh.
Canada : English speaking : University
of Toronto Press, Toronto.
French speaking : Benoit Baril, 4234,
rue de la Roche, Montréal 34.
Ceylan : Lake House Bookshop, The
Associated Newspapers of Ceylon,
Ltd, Colombo I.
Chile : Libreria Lope de Vega, Moneda
924, Santiago de Chile.
Colombia : Emilio Royo Martin, Carrera
9a, 1791, Bogota.
Cuba : LaCasaBelga, RenedeSmedt,
O'Reilly 455, Havana.
Czechoslovakia : Orbis, Narodni 37,
Prague I.
Denmark : Einar Munksgaard, 6 Norre-
gade, Copenhagen.
Ecuador : Casa de la Cultura Ecuato-
riana, av. Mariano Aguilera 322,
Casilla 67, Quito.
Egypt : Librairie James Cattan, Four-
nisseur de la Cour, 118, Rue Emad
el Dine, Cairo.
Finland : Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
France : UNESCO, Sales Service, 19,
avenue Kléber, Paris (16').
Germany : Florian Kupferberg Verlag,
Eleonorenstrasse 6, Mainz-Kastel.
Greece : Eieftheroudakis, Librairie In-
ternaticnale, Athens.
Hungary : P. O. B. 149, Budapest V.
India : Oxford Book and Stationery Co.,
Scindia House, New Delhi.
Vidya Bhavan Granthagar, Bharatiya
Vidya Bhavan Buildings, Chow Patty
Road, Bombay 7.
Indonesia : G. C. T. van Dorp and Co
NV., Djalan Nusantara, 22, Djakarta.
Israel : Leo Blumstein, Book and Art
Shop, 35, AlIenby Road, Tel Aviv.
Italy : Messaggerie Italiane, Via Lo-
mazzo, 52, Milan.
Lebanon and Syria : Librairie Univer-
selle, Avenue des Francis, Beirut,
Lebanon.
Malaya and Singapore : Peter Chong
and Cho, P. O. Box 135, Singapore.
Mexico : Libreria Universitaria, Justo
Sierra 16, Mexico D. F.
Netherlands : N. V. Martinus Nijhoff,
Lange Voorhout 9, The Hague.
New Zealand : Whitcombe and Tombs,
L'd. G. P. O. Box 1526, Wellington,
C. I.
Nigeria : C. M. S. Bookshop, P. O. Box
174, Lagos.
Norway : A/S Bokhjornet, Stortingsplass
7, Oslo.
Pakistan : Thomas and Thomas, Fort
Mansions, Frere Road, Karachi 3.
Peru : Libreria Internacional del Peru,
S. A., Giron de la Union, Lima.
Philippines : Philippine Education Co.,
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo, Manila.
Sweden : AB. C. E. Fritzes Kungt. Hov-
bokhandel, Fredsgatan 2 ; Stock-
holm 16.
Switzerland : French speaking cantons :
Librairie de l'Université, 22-24, rue de
Romont, Fribourg. German speaking
cantons : Europa Verlag, 5 Rdmi-
strasse, Zurich.
Turkey : Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul.
Union of South Africa : Van Schaik's
Bookstore (Pty.). Ltd., P. O. Box 724,
Pretoria.
United Kingdom : H. M. Stationery
Office : York House, Kingsway, Lon-
don (Retail Counter Service), or P. O.
Box 569, London, S. E. I. (Orders by
post).
United States 01 America : Columbia
University Press, 2960 Broadway,
New-York 27, N. Y.
Uruguay : Centro de Cooperacion Cien-
tifica para la America Latina, Unesco,
Bulevar Artigas 1320, Montevideo.* Outside 01 the United States, $ I.
Signed articles express the
Opinions of the authors and do
not necessarily represent the
opinions of Unesco or the
editors of the COURTIER.
THE study of the film as a means to humanunderstanding is not a mere intellectual
exercise. It is part of a continuing study we
have all got to make in our search for harmony
in a tortured world. The power of the film to
entertain and to distract, to move to action, to
hatred and contempt, to compassion and respect,
is eyerywhere agreed. That is probably why
film is more written about than written, and why
the film more than any of the other creative arts
is subjected to a merciless scrutiny.
To say that the film has the power to interpret
life and help to create a harmonious world is not
to suggest that it should in any way depart from
its duty to entertain. But it is to suggest again
that in the search for themes it is possible for a
greater number of writers and producers and
directors and players in a greater number of
countries to lift their eyes above the frontiers
which divide mankind and from whatever vision
they command help to create a design for life
instead of a passion or an excuse for death or
oblivion. Themes may be gay or sombre, flipp-
ant or serious, but it is the spirit which inspires
them as well as the creative spark they bear
witness to, that matters most.
The responsibility of the film is not greater
than the responsibility of press or radio. But it
shares with television a power to dramatize
beyond the others and an opportunity to play a
leading part in creating a possible and credible
world.
The frontiers which divide mankind are not
only, and not even mainly, the national or poli-
tical frontiers. They are frontiers of the mind
and the spirit which spring from limitations of
training and experience, differences of memory
and tradition and belief and taste, and the wilful
or accidental exploitation of these limitations and
differences for sinister ends. That is why so
many are studying now the implications of the
film for children as well as for men and women.
Our generation may be hopeless, but none of us
will agree that our children are, and for them
especially we seek the hope that they may not
suffer again the obscene horrors of the last
decades. Whether the films are made by men
and women in Mexico or the Argentine, in the
United States or the United Kingdom, France or
Italy or Poland or Denmark, in Egypt or India
or Indonesia or Japan, they all have a common
duty to the world's children and an opportunity
greater than ever before to discharge it because
of the vast challenge it presents.
This is not to say that it is or can be an easy
duty to discharge. There are taboos of many
sorts which make it difficult to express the faith
that one has in man. Screenwriters especially are
bitterly aware of this. There are forces which
profit from a shattered world and which at every
opportunity fetter the creative spirit. There are
problems of finance and facilities and markets.
There is still a vast job of research and inter-
pretation before the duty can be done. But it is
in the faith that it can be done and that it is
possible for men and women to grow and develop
together in creative fields of expression and
research that this issue of the COURIER is
founded.
ROSS McLEAN,
Head, Films & Visual Information Division, Unesco.
Graph shows that for 100, 000 cinemas throuqhout the world, there are a little more than 42 million seats available. Raw fitm bands show
the nine leading feature film producers 01 the wortd. the figures indicating the number 01 leature films produced in one year.
I NTERNA TIONAL
m
AND THE
CINEMA
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Page 3-UNESCO COURIER
THE ITALIAN FILM :
A Mirror of Mankind's
Social Responsibility
by Luigi CHIARINI
Editor, Bianco e Nero, Italian review of film studies
THREE fundamental factors, in my opi-
nion, explain the importance of
films as a medium for international
understanding : their immense popular-
ity and wide circulation ; their direct visual
character which makes them a magnificent in-
strument for concrete, first-hand knowledge ;
and their artistic qualities born of a concentra-
tion on significant detail which permit them to
translate the universal through the particular.
This implies a two-fold conception of the
cinema : first, as a means of achieving cul-
tural, educational and scientific ends, and se-
condly as an artistic medium, for entertainment
purposes. But it implies neither vulgar enter-
tainment pandering to man's lowest instincts,
nor some monstrous machine"bombarding"
the brain with ideological or political dogmas,
thus insulting the human dignity of the spec-
tator because it makes no demands on his
critical faculties.
It is in the light of these ideas that an as-
sessment must be made of the Italian cinema's
contribution in this stormy, conflict-ridden
post-war period towards the promotion of in-
ternational understanding and the active de-
fence of fundamental human values, without
which there can be no hope of real progress.
For reasons of space, and also because of
the attention attracted by our neo-realist films
abroad, we shall confine our remarks to"fea-
ture"films. In the field of the cultural,
scientific and educational documentary film,
the Italian cinema has produced little ; com-
mercial obstacles, combined with problems of
distribution-soon, it is hoped, to be over-
come-have unfortunately prevented these
important aids to knowledge from being as
widely circulated, internationally, as Italian
feature films.
Wolf among Wolves
JUST as there is no such thing as"moral or
immoral"art, so there is no such thing as
"educative"art. This does not mean
that art is a mere empty form. On the con-
trary, it contains the essence of all human
values. Art is, in fact, the full and free affir-
mation of human personality in its essentials ;
the true and complete expression, through the
medium of significant detail, of the human
spirit.
Thus art is always, by definition, moral, edu-
cative and optimistic, in that it lifts man above
human passions and, while faithfully reflecting
the national soul, speaks a language which is
universal.
The stir made in the world by recent Italian
films is due to the very fact that they have been
inspired exclusively by artistic considerations
- the need to express the seething passions
roused by the harrowing experiences of the
war ; to reassert, in art, those human values
which had been trampled and crushed under
foot ; and to combat violence, injustice and
poverty by claiming respect for the human
being.
That is why all the films of which we are
speaking, whatever the politics of their authors,
are permeated by a genuine Christian spirit.
It might seem, at first sight, that art is not the
prime consideration in these films, and that
the producers are mainly concerned to discover
a direct and vivid form of expression, free of
all technical refinements and complications-
to concentrate, in fact, rather on what they
want to say than on how to say it. But it is
the essence of art to eschew all formalism in
expressing human truths.
. Thus, Roma, città aperta (Rome, Open
City), though it depicts the Italian capital
under German occupation and though its cha-
racters are highly individualized, even to the
point of speaking dialect, is universally under-
standable ; in the Italians, the citizens of
Rome, the spectator everywhere, whatever his
nationality, sees man, his passions, his feelings
and his sufferings ; he sees men who, though
victims of the blind brutality of war, are
neither conquered nor resigned, but are capa-
ble of fighting to the bitter end for the attain-
ment of a better world where man will no
longer live like a wolf among wolves.
Similarly, Pots, another film by Rossellini,
shows the various types of Italians, from
Sicily to the marshes of Comacchio, with
their weaknesses, their miseries, their hero-
ism and their religious faith, during the war
upheaval caused by the Allied advance north-
wards. It depicts, through the sufferings of
the Italian people, the sufferings of peoples
the world over who have experienced the
horrors of war.
Crude Reality
OTHER films, especially those of Visconti(La Terra Trema-Earthquake), De
Sanctis (Riso Amaro-Bitter Rice) and
Germi (Il Cammino della Speranza-The Road
to Hope), give a picture of the crude and
moving reality of certain aspects of Italian life,
and evoke, naturally and without rhetoric, a
plea for greater social justice. This is a pro-
blem that is particularly topical in present-day
Italy, where social inequalities are particularly
glaring ; yet it is a problem that is not peculiar
to Italy alone.
In the films of De Sica and Zavattini
(ScmcM ; Ladri di Bicicletti-Bicycle Thieves ;
Miracolo a Milano-The Miracle) the
social argument is centred no longer on the
crowd, but on the individual ; the social theme
is spun around the hero and the other cha-
racters of the story, and the call for the
rights of the individual is then once more
generalized so as to apply to the masses.
In the work of these two producers, neo-
realism assumes a less ideological, a more
warmly human, and one might almost say a
more concrete form ; the centre of gravity
shifts from the people and the various social
categories to their individual representative
- man himself, in all his humanity, man as
a worker, a son, a father, a husband, a com-
rade, a citizen and a member of a religious
community ; man who has feelings, who be-
lieves, thinks and works ; in fact, our fellow
man.
These films, devoid of all the artifices, em-
bellishments and studied effects characteristic
of a"spectacle", and sometimes positively
stark in their simplicity, have helped
to give the world a picture of Italy as it is
today. Avoiding political propaganda, they
have raised, on the artistic and therefore
human level, a question of universal concern
- the need for social justice, harmonized with
the rights of the individual. These films are
the expression of a new humanism ; they issue
a call for, and preach, real human under-
standing.
No.. Escapism..
SUCH is the chief contribution made byrecent Italian films to international under-
standing. Using the screen as a mirror in
which men's actions are vividly reflected, they
indicate, in the strongest possible way, the
need for a sense of social responsibility. Films
of this type are clearly the very antithesis of
"escapist"entertainment.
It is possible that the historical and musical
films made during this period have also helped
to spread abroad a knowledge of our art and
our traditions ; but most important today are
those works which emphasize the affinities,
rather than the differences, between peoples.
The Italian cinema can, if it continues on
these lines, make a valuable contribution to
the development of a mutual understanding
that may, in turn, sow the seeds of that com-
mon conscience which is essential to the estab-
lishment, across political and religious bar-
riers, of understanding between the peoples.
The lesson of art is always a lesson in human-
ity.
Side by side with feature films, it is to be
hoped that in future more progress will be
made in the artistic, scientific and cultural
documentary, which is a potentially important
medium for spreading abroad a knowledge of
our traditions, our genius and our national
characteristics-in a word, the soul of our
country.
OPEN CITY, produced by Roberto Rossellini
SCIUSCIA, produced by Vittorio de Sica
PAISA, produced by Ro. berto Rossellini
THE DIFFICULT YEARS, produced. by Luigi Zampa
THE SUN RISES ALLAYS, produced by
Aida Vergano
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page"
THE BRITISH
FILM :
Showing
the people
of England
as they
really are
by Dilys POWELL
Film Critic,'Sunday Times', London
PASSPORT TO PIMLlCO : A sudden and strange problem of " international relations."
WATEVER criticisms mav
be made of the British
wartime cinema, no-
hody can say that it
betrayed any liking for war. In
fact. paradoxically enough, it was
between 1 ! J40 and 1U45 that British
films began to make an apprecia-
ble contribution towards interna-
tional understanding.
At a first glance the independent
observer might say that there
was nothing particularly interna-
tional about the British cinema.
We have rarely tackled interna-
tional subjects in the way in
which the Swiss have tackled
them in The Last Chance or
Four in a Jeep. We have pass-
ed over such current racial pro-
blems as anti-Semitism and the
colour question (though a version
of Alan Paton's Cry, the Belov-
ed Country is is still to come).
When we have chosen some
theme of racial or national rela-
tionships we have not been parti-
cularly successful in exciting
popular interest. Just after the
war we had an ambitious film on
an important subject to show- :
Men of Two Worlds, a story of
the battle against the tsetse fly
and the position of the African
\vho is torn between his European
education and the traditional
superstitions of his own people.
But Men of Two Worlds, was not
a popular film ; and though the
things it said were very well
worth saying I greatly doubt
whether it made much impres-
sion.
And yet I helieve that the Bri-
tish cinema has been a very con-
siderable factor in creating inter-
national goodwill. The obvious
thing, of course, would be to
point to our long list of docu-
mentaries with their impeccable
democratic principles. And It is
quite true that the documentary
film can do a great deal to make
people see one another's point of
view-or, almost as important,
to show the other man that his
point of view is recognized ;
when Paul Botha made The
World is Rich it was evidence
that people in Britain were not
kept in ignorance of conditions in
hungry India and war-stricken
Asia. The trouble is that the
documentary rarely reaches
beyond an audience which is
prepared for special pleading.
Now and then there is an excep-
tion ; for instance Daybreak in
Udi, a delightful account of the
buildiug of a Nigerian maternity
home in the teeth of the witch-
doctor ; here was a piece, fairly
widely shown, which made its
effect not by talking about pro-
gress but by showing us what
chaming and likable people the
inhabitants of Cdi really are.
Subtle Persuasion
But the real strength of the ci-nema lies in its power to per-
suade people who don't know
they are being persuaded. That
is where the American film has
scored all these years ; while en-
tertaining us it has built up a
great popular sympathy for
America. I believe that the Bri-
tish cinema is making, and
should make, its impact in the
same \vay. In other words, I
believe that by producing films
about ourselves we shall make
our best contribution to interna-
tional goodwill. Uur way of
doing it cannot be the same as
Hollywood's. America is a young
and ebullient nation, and pan-
ache comes easily and naturally
from her. The British are an old
and disciplined people, senti-
mental beneath a veneer of re-
serve, and the British cinema.
must speak in their native emo-
tional accent. That this is the
right approach has been proved
since the war by the success of
British films with Continental au-
diences and minority audiences
in America. To capture the at-
tenlion of the American masses
is another matter; ; let us not pre-
tend that we have as yet begun
to do that. But it is worth noting
that among the most successful
of our films in America have
been some of the most un-
ashamedly British : Henry V,
Hamlet, Quartet - films which
make no concessions to American
taste.
The theory that the sharply na-
tional film appeals to an interna-
tional audience is borne out by
the reactions of the French to
British films. I have to confess
that I am one of the less fanatical
admirers of Brief Encounter,
and I have sometimes been puzzl-
ed by the enthusiasm of my
French friends for the piece ; but
to my enquiries they always
reply :"It's so English.'" One
might be tempted to suppose that
their admiration was less for the
film itself than for its evidence of
British chastity, weere one not
confronted by enthusiasm also for
two films of a very different
type Passport to Pimlico, a
thoroughly English joke in a tho-
roughly English setting ; and
Whisky Galore, a thoroughly
Scottish joke in a thoroughly
Scottish setting.
Interpreters..-.'. j.
Often, indeed, it is the improb-able fìlm \vhich wins heads
abroad : who would have.
thought that Red Shoes would
gain a prize in Japan ? But proba-
ble or improbable, the films serve
as interpreters. As I have said, the
process of liaison began during
the war, when for the first time
in the cinema we began to look
without self-flattery and self-de-
migration at ourselves. It goes on
today with such quiet studies of
character and background as
Morning Departure or The Brown-
ing rersion or Whire Corridor: :
films which observe the beha-
viour of human beings and pre-
sent it with sympathy and under-
standing. What I want from the
cinema of other nations is a truth-
ful interpretation of human na-
ture : I can only assume that in
the long run other people have the
same tastes. And we in this coun-
try have passed the stage when
we could be content to be present-
ed abroad as a nation of comic
housemaids and dukes in mono-
cles.
A RUN FOR YOUR MONEY : A comedy about London, two mining brothers from Wales, and some everyday men and women from England.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
THE FEATURE CARRIES
ON THE DOCUMENTARY
TRADITION
by Sir Michael BALCON
One of the leading film producers in Great Britain, Sir Michael Balcon has
given the world cinema public an amazing number of film successes, including
Passport to Pimlico, Whisky Galore, Kind Hearts and Coronets, Dead of Nfght,
The Overfonders, Nicholas Nickleby, The Captive Heart, Next of Kin, They Came
to a City.
Page 5-UNESCO COURIER
IN the British cinema, there is one
t outstanding success story : not the
story of an individual, but of an
approach, a. point of view. With the
reservations that any generalization re-
quires, it can be said to have started
with the documentary movement in the
late 20's and early 30's. Documentary is
a term notoriously
difficult to define, and
although we all know
what it means, no sa-
tisfactory definition
has yet been found.
Nor will I attempt to
give one : for my pres-
ent purpose, it is suf-
ficient to point out
what it aimed to
achieve, which, since
documentarists seem
also to have been pro-
lific theorists, I can do
easily in their own
words. Documentary,
said Paul Rotha,"has
an important purpose
to fulfil in bringing to
life familiar things
and people, so that
their place in the
scheme of t h i n g s
which we call society
may be honestly as-
sessed". And John
Grierson declared that
"it promised us the
power of making
drama from our daily
events and poetry of
our problems".
I need hardly say
that the documentary
film makers succeeded
magnificently. Not
only did they say
things that, as every-
one with the least
spark of social cons-
ciousness realized,
needed saying badly,
but they developed
new film techniques
and trained new per-
sonnel, in spite of fre-
quent lack of support
and difficulties. In
the period between
the wars, when the
British feature-film
industry had too often
to concentrate on mere
survival, it was the
quality of the docu-
mentaries that kept
the reputation of the
industry as a whole
alive abroad. That is
the greatest compli-
ment that I, as a fea-
ture-film producer, can
pay them. The value
of the work they did
was out of all propor-
tion to its footage :
they made propaganda
without resorting to
politics, and they
made works of art
without losing sight of
their social purpose.
Then came the war.
and the industry's
forces combined re-
gardless of whether
they came from docu-
mentary or feature, to
wield what was soon
realized to be a major
weapon of war : the
result was naturally
called feature-documentary, and equally
naturally, its quality profited by this new
liaison : the British war-time output as a
whole was far in advance of what had
gone before. This is not altogether sur-
prising, since a national emergency always
seems to act as a tremendous stimulus.
What is rather surprising is that the gen-
eral feeling after such an emergency-to
return to the conditions that existed
before as quickly as possible-did not
arise in the British film industry. The
feature film had learned a great lesson :
its responsibility as an influence on the
public, its possibilities as an informative
and didactic force. The aims were now
similar to those propounded by the do-
cumentaries of the 30's.
If I say therefore that the feature-film
has largely taken over from the docu-
mentary, I do not in any way mean to
belittle the latter. On the contrary, this
state of affairs means that their propa-
ganda has achieved its purpose : the be-
liefs of the few of the 30's are now wide-
ly held, their aims have become generally
accepted as being worthwhile, their ap-
proach to the screen has been vindicated.
Of course, at the moment, this is only
the beginning of a new trend in the Bri-
tish industry, and is not yet completely
established. But I am convinced that it
is soreadins. and that we are on the right
lines :. already a num-
ber of the better
known documentarists
are working in feature
films : under John
Grierson, the Exe-
cutive Producer of one
of the news groups
organized by the Na-
tional Film Finance
Corporation, are John
Eldridge and Terry
Bishop, on loan from
Ealing Studios, Pat
Jackson and Paul Ro-
tha have both just
directed their first
feature 61m, and I
think it significant
that in the programme
on Future trends in
a documentary series
organized by the Bri-
tish Film Institute,
Seven Days to Noon
should be shown in
extract.
Let us'examine,
then, a little more
closely, how the fea-
ture film today is car-
rying on the documen-
tary tradition. More
and more it is using
for its backgrounds
parts of the contem-
porary scene such as
made the subject mat-
ter of the past docu-
mentary : farm, slum,
factory. More and
more it makes use of
characters and action
arising out of contem-
porary problems, such
as were handled by
the documentarists :
labour problems, class
problems, problems of
psychology. More and
more it is prepared to
break away from the
studio and its hot-
house plots, to use real
places and real people.
Of course, there are
disadvantages : the
problem that makes a
background in a fea-
ture film can often not
be examined as care-
fully as might be de-
sirable, as profound-
ly as could be done in
a documentary con-
centrating only on the
one subject. But on
the other hand, the
potential influence of
the feature film is
much greater : not on-
ly does it reach a wi-
der audience, but since
feature-films by their
nature must treat all
problems in terms of
individual human be-
ings, they avoid the
slightly impersonal
application to"the
people"that often
mars documentaries,
and. therefore, bring
home to the individual human geings that
make up the audience the problems in a
much more personal and impressive way.
That I think, is the road we should
continue to travel, but it still requires a
new approach from many people. Above
all, it means that all concerned with the
creation of script and film must become
careful students of the contemporary
world ; they must know and feel their
people and their country, the difficulties
and joys that are the stuff of ordinary
life, so that they can recreate it on the
screen. If the film industries of all
countries did this honestly and consis-
tently, each bringing their own people
to the screens of the world, then indeed
we should have made documentary un-
necessary, we should be making drama
from our daily events and poetry of our
problems ! In the meantime, the film
we are at present producing at Ealing
deals with the clash between old and new
in colonial administration, and the next
will be about the probation system.
I KNOW WHERE I'M GOING
KIND HEARTS AND CORONETS
THE CHILTERN HUNDREDS
WHISKY GALORE
THE BROWNING VERSION
Wilfred White : Headmaste
Michael Redgrave : Classics master
Brian Smith : Schoolboy
_.. _. v
Nigel Patrick : Science master
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 6
THE AMERICAN FILM
More than iust Sex and Gangsters,
A Trend toward Social Dramas
Exposing Prejudice and Injustice
by Bosley CROWTHER
Film Critic,'New York Times'
ALL THE KING'S MEN : The ugly career of an incipient American dictator.
THE BEST YEARS OF OUR LIVES : Three soldiers return home from war.
THERE was a time when it
was standard-among the
sharper observers, at least-
to take a dim view of the
social and intellectual contributions
of American films, particularly
with respect to the picture of
American life which they presented
to the world. Fair and responsible
critics, both at home and abroad,
could find little more in Hollywood
movies than glorifications of sex
and gold, of Cinderella and gang-
sters, of romance and opulence, as
though these were solely represen-
tative of the culture and interest
of our land.
And, indeed, the objections of
such critics were not entirely
unjustified, for there was a time
when American movies were dub-
ious mirrors of the American way
of life, as well as unflattering
reflectors of the substantial nature
of mankind. Sensations such as
gangsterism were blatantly over-
emphasized and human behaviour
inconsistent with nature and logic
was displayed. Unfortunately, the
strange impression of America thus
transmitted to the world-and,
for that matter, to many of our
own people with limited horizons
here at home-established a lurid
image of American culture that
was dangerously false. It still
persists in some quarters and
remains to be dispelled.
No one can claim that American
movies are free of all faults today
or that they now constitute ideal
ambassadors of enlightenment and
inspiration to the world. Hollywood
still makes lots of cheap films
which follow the hackneyed for-
mulas. It also grinds out some
costly"epics"which gild human
nature with bright romance. And
it is a singular misfortune of film
commerce that virtually all of
America's films, the cheap ones as
well as the fine ones, are sent all
over the world, which means that
the films of lesser virtues inevitably
predominate in quantity.
And yet a close observation of
American films over the past six
years-that is to say, of our
feature pictures released since
World War II-has conveyed the
gratifying realization that Amer-
ican producers have become more
sharply aware of the responsibility
of the motion picture medium as a
cultural force for social good than
ever before.
Frank Exposures
A HASTY review of the best filmsin this p riod demon trates,
first of all, that a greater im-
pulse towards reality and candour
has pervaded American aims. An
outstanding trend in the post-war
years has been towards dramas
which frankly expose the festering
cankers of intolerance and injustice
in modern society. In a sharp
melodrama entitled Crossfire, the
existence of anti-Semitism in
America was recognized for the
first time, this unpleasant subject
having previously been tabooed,
and this was followed by the film,
Gentlemen's Agreement, which
further disrobed the evil of anti-
Semitic bias.
The peculiar and complicated
presence of anti-Negro prejudice in
this country has also been the
subject of a remarkable series of
post-war films. Beginning with
Home ot the Bravt, a vivid drama
of racial discrimination among
soldiers in the Padfic during the
war, this subjects has been pursued
with a genuine : ervour for the
ideals of democracy is such further
films as Pinky, Losl Boundaries, No
Way Out, and Intnder in the Dust,
he latter a supellative achieve-
ment in cinema ar ; as well.
This regard for social justice and
understanding anong men has
recently been combined effectively
with Hollywood's talent for vivid
war films in a picture called Go
For Broke !-a drama of the
heroic action of an American
regimental combat team made up
of American-born Japanese sold-
iers, termed Nisei in World War
II. And even sone candid ac-
knowledgment of injustice to Ame-
rican Indians that occurred in the
period of westward expansion has
been made in such otherwise
conventional outdcor films as Fort
Apache and BrokEn Arrow, thus
violating the formula for the
standard Western film.
No Punches Pulled
PERHAPS the nost widely im-pressive of Arrerica's post-war
films, both at home and abroad.
has been the diama, The Best
Years of Our Lives. And that is
because this picture not only
understood in universal terms the
emotions of servicemen returning
home after the war, but it fairly
expressed the veteran's yearning
for a fuller democracy and oppor-
tunity for all in thE post-war world.
The American ; cene-in its
light and its dark ; ides-has also
been authentically displayed in
such fine and flavoursome pictures
as Sitting Pretty, Father of the
Bride, Father's Litlle Dividend, The
Jackpot, Miracle en Thirty-fourth
Street, Born YerJ ; erday and All
About Eve, which tre only a few of
the many rich American post-war
comedies ; and i : 1 The Asphalt
Jungle, The Snake Pit, The Quiet
One, Sunset Boulevard, Ace in the
Hole and Treasureof Sierra Madre,
which have been dramas of the
darker side. And a special word
might be mentionej for the picture,
All the King's Ken"because it
pulled no punches. n displaying the
vulnerability of tie mob to the
demagogy of an tspiring dictator
and the viciousness of such a man.
Its story was based upon the career
of the American, fIuey Long.
And, then, of course, there have
been any number of smooth and
light-hearted American films-
such things as T, te Jolson Story
and the comedies cf Danny Kaye-
which have had no particular
social content, save a genial over-
flow of good will It is possible
that such pictures also serve to
create understanding among men.
To be sure, thE American film
industry should : lot be credited
with a paramount aim to make
pictures that will be ambassadors
of culture and e1lightenment in
the world. Its desre is to turn out
pictures that w : ll attract and
absorb an audienc. But in cater-
ing to the public's interests in the
really pertinent dramas of our
times, the American producers may
be said to be C01tributing much
more constructively than ever
before to the good of man.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
THE power-or at least the
potential-of a film to com-
municate information, to convey
ideas and impressions at between
peoples, has long been generally recog-
nized. The most obvious example is
that knowledge of and beliefs (right
or wrong) about the American"way
of life"in most parts of the civilized
world are in the main based on con-
tact, over the years, with the ubiqui-
tous Hollywood film.
Yet remarkably little has been done
outside the educational documentary
and the frankly documentary films, to
make constructive use of this effective
agency for better international under-
standing. In the Western world, of
course, there is always the fear that
anything which might conceivably be
branded as propaganda in the realm
of entertainment will be suspect and
that this reaction will militate against
the commercial success at which all
entertainment films are aimed.
It is worth noticing that this does
not apply in the other half of the
world ; the London"Times"recently
reported from Singapore an intensive
campaign in South East Asia to secure
the widest distribution of Russian and
Chinese films, which are always Com-
munist in content, and uncompro-
mising in their determination to put
ideological inspiration before mere
entertainment. But there have been
from time to time in the West exam-
ples of the fact that a well-docu-
mented fiction film can do a great
deal more than tell a time-passing,
boy-meets-girl story which presents
in the last analysis, nothing more
than a belief that total, absolute and
constant bliss is within the reach of
all.
Mostly the examples have been un-
Page 7-UNESCO COURIER
THERE ARE OSCARS, CUPS, AND PLAQUES GALORE, BUT HERE IS
A FILM AWARE
WITH A REAL PURPOSE
by Stephen WATTS
Author of a syndicated film column appearing in Canada, Latin America, Italy,
Portugal, Japan. London film correspondent,'New York Times'.
consciously brought into being ; at
least they have sprung from no more
than a desire to face up to life as it
surrounds the creators of the film. An
"Open City"or"Paisa"conveyed
vividly what life in war-time Italy was
like, but that was mainly because the
producers, short of equipment, studios
and money, but abounding in ideas,
found their subjects in life, treated
them with telling directness and sim-
plicity, and photographed them in
natural, real settings. Whatever
"message"they carried was integral
and unselfconscious.
Recently a Swiss-sponsored, multi-
lingual film about the Four Power
regime in Vienna,"Four in a Jeep",
has been earning the kind of praise
which suggests again what can be
done along those lines. True, at the
Cannes film festival the, Russians pro-
tested, presumably finding the leading
Russian character portrayed as insuf-
ficiently heroic, but the film was
highly praised, as it was again on its
London presentation and at the Berlin
film festival. There, although the
winner of the German language Silver
Laurel award, to go forward for the
Golden Laurel final at Venice in Sep-
tember, was a locally-produced pic-
ture,"Herrl1che Zeiten","Four in a
Jeep"was specially commended and
will in fact be a candidate for the
Golden Laurel in its own multi-lingual
category.
This film serves as an admirable
example of what the Golden Laurel
award is all about ; some of the
reviews of it, using phrases such as"a
plea for greater understanding be-
tween human beings", are in close
parallel to the declared purpose of the
award, defined by its donor, Mr David
O. Seiznick, as"to pay tribute to those
motion pictures, produced by Euro-
peans in Europe which have made the
greatest contribution to mutual under-
standing and goodwill between the
peoples of the free and democratic
world".
Last year at Venice the Golden Lau-
rel award (then being contested for
the first time) went to the Italian
film"Donne Senza Nome".
Awards in the film business are
legion."Oscars", cups, medals, scrolls
and plaques, even (in Britain) Henry
Moore statuettes are presented for the
best this and the most outstanding
that. For the winners, they make
prestige and useful advertising mate-
rial ; too often they also blatantly glo-
rify the donor.
But the Golden Laurel award has
the virtues, firstly of being concerned
with more long-term, humane values
than are usually considered in the
cinema, and also of being free from
the taint that the donor's motives are
disingenuous and commercially rooted.
Selznick is an American film mag-
nate, but he has so defined the quali-
fications for entry that no American
film can compete, far less win ; indeed
the winner, by reason of the kudos
gained, is in a better position to com-
pete for a place on the world's screens
against the product of Hollywood and
even Selznick himself. The final jury
in New York, which passes judgment
on the"heat"winners from the six
language-groups, includes such public
figures as Dr. Ralph Bunche, of UN
and Nobel Peace Prize fame, Mr Her-
bert Bayard Swope, Mr Edward Mur-
row, Mr John Gunther and Dr. D'Har-
noncourt of the New York Museum of
Modern Art.
This year thirty-two films from
seven countries have been entered.
Apart from"Four in a Jeep"and
"Herrliche Zeiten", are the"local"
winners from the United Kingdom
("Trio"), France ("Justice est faite"),
Italy ("in Cammino della Speranza",
or"The Road to Hope"), and Scandi-
navia ("Medan Staden Sever").
"Trio"made from three Somerset
Maugham stories, has some charac-
teristically shrewd and salted observa-
tion of the British character. The
French and Italian pictures are graver
subjects-one deals with the task of a
jury of ordinary, people faced with a
"mercy killing"trial, the other with
poor emigrants from Sicily who trek
towards the French border in the hope
of finding work.
Whoever may win, the contest can
hardly fail to stimulate European film
production and to direct producers'
minds to an aspect of their work, and
its impact on other people which they
often seem dangerously to ignore.
One American commentator on the
Golden Laurel scheme has written"I
wish Europe would clinch matters by
establishing its own award for the
American film which provides the
soundest information on life in the
United States". That is an extension
of Mr Selznick's idea which is worthy
of consideration in the appropriate
quarters this side of the Atlantic.
There cannot be too many film-
makers aiming their work at the
target of greater mutual understand-
ing.
NACHTWACHE. (Germany) Silver Laurel Award, 1950.
DONNE SENZA NOME. (Italy) The plight of stateless women in a D. P. camp. Golden
Laurel Award, 1950.
The British Film Academy awards an annoa) prize for the best feature film illustrating one or more of the basic
principles of tbe United Nations Charter. Called The United Nations Award, the prize was created in 194&
by the British Fifm Academy in response to a request by the Film Oivis. on of the U. N. The Academy Councj !
reserve the right to withhold the United Nations Award jf none of the films, in their opinions, obtains sufficient
Yotes. to justify its presentation. This was the case in 1948 when no award was presented. The first film to
w. n the prize. presented in 1949, was the Swiss-American M.G.M. production The Search which tells the
moving story of a little refugee boy-one of the thousands of O, P. children separa1ed from their parents during
and after the last World War. Last year. the award went to the M. 6. M. American production Intruder in the
Durst. a furl-length feature film based on WiHiam Fauikner's novel attacking discrimination against Negroes
in the United States (above). Henry Moore, the distinguished British sculptor designed a statuette for the
award. A replica of this In bronze is formally presented to the director of she winning film who receives it
on behalf of the production studio. The bronze Is kept by the studio until passed to the next AC2demy winne1
ACK ON RACISM WINS BRITISH FILM ACADEMY
: AWARD FOR 1950
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
CH) LDREN'S F) LMS...
HOWEVER much adults may re-gret the role that the cinema
plays in the lives of their chil-
dren, it is no good harking back to
the days"When I was a child...".
Good or bad, dangerous or healthy,
the cinema is here, and it has taken
a part in our life which cannot be
excluded.
Also we can do nothing about the
fact that children form a large part
of the cinema-going public. The
Honourable Mrs. Henrietta Bower,
member of Britain's Departmental
Committee on Children and the Ci-
nema, has given the following signi-
ficant figures (1).
Out of a total of 7, 000, 000 British
children aged between five and fif-
(1) Mentioned by Henri Storck in"Le Film
Récréati (1/0111' S} lec/a/eurs l1wéniles",} lublish-
cd VII U lIesco
teen, 1, 250, 000 go to the pictures at
least twice a week, and 550, 000 at least
three times. Three shows a week
mean that the fifteen-year-old has
already seen 1, 560 films-and this does
not include educational film shows
given in the schools.
Financial Difficulties
OBVIOUSLY, therefore, the cinemaplays a big role in the formation
of the child. If it helps to give adults
certain ideas about this world, how
much more so when it comes to the
more receptive and emotional young-
ster, who is particularly vulnerable to
psychological shocks, with their im-
measurable after-effects.
But it would be wrong to say that
only in the cinema does he get
these shocks. Apart from what life
itself teaches him, he has other means
of learning about the world-books
and newspapers, for instance. The ci-
nema is of course, different from
these, but its effects can be judged
by a comparison with them.
Children's literature has existed for
centuries. It has its good points, as
well as its bad, but at least it is
written to suit its readers. It has
had its famous authors : Andersen,
Lewis Carroll, Jules Verne. And
generally speaking, children read the
books and magazines written for
them, rather than those meant for
adults.
But it is just the opposite at the
cinema. It is adult films which chil-
dren see most frequently. Westerns,
gangster films, adventure or love,
news, documentaries and cartoons
pass before their eye. s with that
hypnotic force which forbids one's
attention to wander from that screen
in the middle of the darkness.
Producing special films for children
means all sorts of problems-finan-
cial ones, for instance. What producer
will undertake to make a picture
which he knows will not be accepted
by the usual circuits ? It would not
show a profit perhaps in 15 or
20 years.
Mrs. Bower's solution for this pro-
blem is assistance from governments,
who would create an international
pool of children's films. Interesting
in itself, it is only a suggestion, and
we must content ourselves with things
as they are.
The scarcity of special films means
that people who organize children's
film shows have first of all to choose,
among films made for adults, those
which are most suitable for young
spectators. This poses a question
which remains to be answered satis-
factorily : the criteria for making this
selection.
It is the fashion in certain circles to
blame the cinema for everything.
Children's misdeeds. and crimes are its
fault. It always leads them, if not
to delinquency, at least to immorality,
and shows them how to behave like
gangsters. Its eroticism-even if
nothing more than a kiss-seriously
trouble the young cinemagoers.
Must all this be guarded against ?
The answer is : No, it does not matter
very much.
Indifferent
WE have a tendency to judge theinfluence of the cinema on
children by what it does to us. But it
is quite different with youngsters. Dr.
Le Moal, who has made an important
study of this matter, declares that ;
from five years of age to puberty, love
complications are matters of indiffer-
ence, even boredom, to children.
Only girls over 16 prefer love stories ;
the boys continue to opt for adven-
ture or historical films.
Accusing the cinema of fostering
The photos on this page we !"e
Mars. Henrietta Bower, a mem
Office and Ministry of Education
on children for two years."The
the great need for real entert
shown that even children who
suffer afterwards from nightma
produced primarily for adults
ears and feelings of the child.
bildren's films that really amus
brternational pool of Children's
... FC
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
child delinquency is to ignore the
social and psychological conditions
which are at the root of anti-social
attitudes-lack of adaptability, bad
family conditions, misery, promiscuity.
It is quite wrong to imagine that a
gangster film will lead a boy to crime
if, after the cinema, he can return
home to a happy, prosperous and unit-
ed family. As for the lad who lives
in a slum and in the street, and sees
his drunken parents quarrel each
night, does he really need the cinema
to teach him lawlessness ?
Grave Problems
NEVERTHELESS, it would be wrongto say that the cinema does not
pose grave problems with regard to
children. Very often it gives shocks,
with traces that remain. You have
only to look at some of Mrs. Bower's
infra-red photos taken in darkened
cinemas and shown in these pages.
Such emotions can have dangerous
effects on such young human beings.
But the large number of studies of
this problem have produced very dis-
similar opinions on its effects.
Richard Ford, in his book"Children
in the Cinema", gives the results of
an enquiry made by cinema club
directors into the subjects which
frightened children most. They were :
shots of the mysterious, of the
unknown, of terror ; scenes taken in
the dark showing ghosts, skeletons
and witches ; war crimes ; brawls
which included close-ups of criminal
faces.
Can we accept fully the results of
this enquiry ? Apparently not. Ans-
wering a question put by Mrs. Bower,
a child gave what she regards as a
typical answer :"I like ghost films,
because I know it could not happen
to me."Note that this child did not
say that these scenes made him
frightened-in fact, he enjoyed this
type of fear.
Let us take three films meant espe-
cially for children : Pinocchio, Snow-
White and the Thief of Bagdad. M.
Armand Lanous finds in all of them
a result. Some films leave memo-
ries which are not effaced for months.
That children undergo violent emo-
tional disturbances as a result of
seeing films meant for adults-as
well as those made for children-
cannot be denied. Only the extent
of these shocks is disputed. Some
say they can last a long time. Others,
like Dr. Elliott Jach, contradict this.
Dr. Elliott Jach declares that horrible
. scenes are perhaps a good thing in
that they give the child an outlet for
his anxieties and instincts. For the
cinema is an art-or a distraction-
which only calls for its spectator to
respond spontaneously, temporarily,
and with no long-term call on his
emotions.
The cinema is thus a cultural ele-
ment that is new and, one can even
say, strange. Perhaps it is too soon
to weigh up its effects.
But one fact cannot be ignored : the
cinema demands above all high
finance. To be profitable it must
please the greatest possible number of
people. That is to say, it must follow
at the same time as it creates. And
Clearly it is not only in the British
and American film that one can
gather such stupidities.. They are
pretty general.
Evil and Poverty
T* AKE the last"cliché"in this list :the cinema's representation of
the foreigner. This may be the
only viewpoint many children get for
years.. It can well be the basis of
misunderstandings, with serious con-
sequences for the future of their
country.
There are, of course, exceptions.
All-whether children or adults-
who saw"The Last Chance"got an
opportunity of understanding better
the problems which passions had put
in a wrong light. In this film, no
matter whrLt language is spoken,
everybody is just-a human being.
The conventions which, by force of
circumstances, the cinema must res-
pect affects its best work. Thus, the
conclusions reached by the British
report on children's entertainment
films show that, in order to please
children, the actors who play the less-
attractive roles must bear the conven-
tional signs of their badness-dirty
clothes and rags. and ugly faces
(which, however, must not be repul-
sive.)
M. Henri Storck comments on this
peculiar modern tendency to link evil
with poverty. In the days of melo-
drama, he recalls, the bad person was
the cruel and powerful nobleman.
Dangerous Ideas
IT is easy to see the danger whichcan arise from this linking of the
evil and the poor. After having given
children a view of life which they are
most unlikely to find in reality, is the
cinema going to add some dangerous
ideas about the superiority of some,
while others get no less dangerous
notions about their inferiority ? This
happens often, and the cinema, by its
conventions, makes it occur still more
frequently-thus tending to make the
divisions of society even more rigid.
To want to transform the cinema
would be ridiculous. But its possibi-
lities are immense. There is no hu-
man progress that cannot better
humanity and bring it clooer together
- unless it is allowed to worsen man's
lot and teach him to hate.
It is not fruitless to draw the atten-
tion of those responsible for the evo-
lution of the cinema to the most
subtle, the most far-reaching and the
most serious consequences of their
activities.
Whether the makers of films like it
or not, whether they do something
about it or ignore it, the cinema is a
new aspect of culture. The cinema
must not forget as it forges ahead
that culture forms part of it.
we !'e uken with a special infra-rend camera by the Horn.
ember of the DepartmenUI Committee of the HQme
tion in England which studied the effects of the cinema
"there photograph", Mars. Bower states,"are proof of
ntertainment films for Children". Her enquiries have
who do not show fright at an incident in a film often
htrnares, because"most of the films seen by children are
ults and hence do not uke into account the emotions,
Mild. Mars. Bower has issued a call for the productíOfl of
amuse and entertain the child and the creation of an
en's films sponsored by governments.
OR GROWN-UPS ONLY ?
by Jean BLOCH-MICHEL
sequences which give violent shocks.
When Pinocchio was swallowed by
the whale, the children were fright-
ened to see him inside the monster
(the young spectator identifies
himself very much more with the hero
than adults do>. In Snow-White, it
was the fairy being changed into a
witch which affected them most,
while in the Thief of Bagdad they
were scared by the nightmare fight
with Faraignee.
What about adult films which keep
on showing scenes of violence as their
principal theme ? Mr. P. Mayer de-
clares in the"Sociology of the film"
that often children have been so
impressed by a picture that they
have nightmares and insomnia as
that, perhaps, is its greatest danger
to culture.
The cinema nowadays is at the root
of many prejudices--or at least it
does nothing to combat them. On
the other hand it often presents to
children a view of the world and of
life which has little connection with
reality.
Here, for instance, is a list of"cli-
chés"of the British and American
cinema which Mr. Roger Manvell has
gathered together in his book
"Film" :
Luxury, especially associated
with women, is normal.
The full-time pursuit of women
by unoccupied businessmen and
rich young rulers is normal.
Men are a source of money for
women.
Sex is probably the most impor-
tant sensation in life.
Things of the spirit are either
funny, eccentric, charlatan or
ever so wonderful. (Art is
usually debunked as artiness,
religion as mania, mysticism as
a yearn in soft focus.)
To be foreign is to be under
suspicion. To be Eastern is to
be horrific.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page two
THE FIRST elNEMATle
ENeveLOPAEDIA
FRENCH THOUGHT IN PICTURES
by Yves HACQUARD
AFTER the passage of two hundred yearsthe"Encyclopédie Filmée"is carrying on
the tradition of. Diderot and the great
Encyclopaedists.
"Cow is the feminine of bull ; bull is the
masculine of cow", we learn from the French
dictionary Larousse. Unless you are suffering
from mushroom-poisoning, it will not occur to
you to ask the Dictionary for a definition of
Amanites, especially if you think they are
animal fossils or members of the French Union.
Have you ever thought about the word"artery",
which applies to cities as well as to the blood-
stream ? Or of that word"bureau", which
has come to denote a solemn Council after it
once clothed a mediaeval peasant ? What
have you learnt about arithmetic since you
first stammered through the multiplication
table ?
The month of April 1951 marked a mile-
stone in the history of the cinema, when
authoritative representatives of French letters,
arts and sciences joined with scenario-writers
to revive the tradition of the eighteenth-
century Encyclopaedists. Duly defined, com-
mented upon and expressed in the form of
pictures, words will follow one another upon the
screen in a series of films which will make up
a cinematic encyclopaedia available to the
general public.
It is a big task with many difficulties, not
the least of which is the fact that, despite the
cinema's ideals and successes in many new
fields, it still continues to be regarded chiefly
as a means of recreation. The scholar may
give credit to the producer of educational films
and make the necessary intellectual effort to
retain knowledge presented in a more or less
didactic form ; but the average cinema-goer,
who seeks an escape from time and space, a
journey to what-mig, ht-have-been, will not
willingly exchange it for an analysis of the
meanings of words, however humorous or
interesting they may be.
Diderot discovered the educational influence
of faithful reproduction two centuries ago.
His Encyclopaedia owed a great part of its
initial success to an illustration which pleased
the Royal favourite, Madame de Pompadour.
It was a detailed diagram showing how her
stockings could be woven. She was also in-
terested in finding a good description of how
cosmetics were made. The admirably engraved
plates for the different crafts determined their
vocation for generations of Europeans. Dis-
pensing with unnecessary comment, the pic-
ture became an organic link in the story and
made it possible to secure greater objectivity
or a subtle distortion of reality.
In the course of its growth, the cinema has
developed steadily towards an ideal marriage
between language and sensation. The talking
film has produced science or art documentaries
as well as sound and spoken newsreels : the
picture needs, at the same time that it fears,
the'language which confirms or annuls it,
while words find in pictures virgin soil for the
development of their harmonies, that void and
silence which are the essence of poetry.
Above all, the creators of the cinema ency-
clopaedia are striving to avoid vulgarity, the
circulation of cheap knowledge. Like La Fon-
taine, they want to instruct and to amuse at
the same time and have endeavoured to as-
semble at the outset all the material necessary
to success.
The Editorial Committee for the Film Ency-
clopaedia includes such well-known writers
and novelists, essayists, philosophers and dra-
matists as Marcel Achard, Alexandre Arnoux,
Jean Cocteau, Pierre Descaves, Roger Ferdi-
nand, Professeur Monder, Léon Moussinac,
Marcel Pagnol and Raymond Queneau ; jurists,
high officials and political personalities such
as Madame Georges Bidault, Julien Cain,
Maurice Garçon ; humorists like Jean Rigaux
and Jean Effel ; the Director of French radio
and television, Wladimir Porché ; and a galaxy
of scenario-writers-Jean Benoit-Levy, Marcel
Carne, André Cayatte, René Clair and Jean
Gremillon. Jean Marin is Secretary-General.
These modern encyclopaedists will be at li-
berty to deal with each subject just as they
think fit, without any definite style being laid
down. The encyclopaedia will rely on inspira-
tion, on the results that diverse tempera-
ments can produce with the cinema's means of
expression. It plans to give young people a
chance to show what they can do and to incor-
porate as many new ideas as possible.
Filmgoers will be able to see Pierre Kast
explaining the mystery of numbers, the key to
the universe. Madame Georges Bidault will
try to show-in colours-that red-and-white
mushrooms cultivated by her husband are
better than any grown in the ground.
Seated at his worktable, Raymond Queneau
will humorously meditate before us on the most
abstruse questions of arithmetic. He will ask
how he can be sure that he really has five
angers, will recall that no cotton reels are equal
mathematically to no corkscrews and that
there is only one chance in a billion that a
saucepan which is put over a fire will freeze
up.
The idea is to draw the spectator's attention
insensibly towards wider philosophic or moral
perspectives. Blue, Jean Grémillon tells us, is
the colour of the sky, of the policeman's
breeches and of the Virgin's cloak. The Cote
d'Azur ceases to be azure in Italy, where blue
symbolizes force and skill. But it is the aim-
maker Marcel Pagliero who reproduces the
delicacy and purity of blue by a very lovely
bare-shouldered woman wearing a necklace of
blue stones.
Work on a dozen words beginning with the
letter"A"is to be completed by the end of
this year. Pierre Laroche will gather together
all the meanings of Age. Madame Simon will
sing of Actors. Colette Audry will attack
Absence. Alexandre Arnoux will visit the
Amazon and its Amazons, while Jean Marin
climbs Atlas to look at the Atlantic.
The encyclopaedists not only hope for dis-
tribution of their work through the normal
circuits, but also to enter into agreements with
educational organizations and with television
networks. A dubbed commentary in different
languages will bring their lively and imagin-
ative survey of the French language to many
countries.
In this way a cinematic achievement with
rich possibilities will carry to the four corners
of the earth a message of culture, intelligence
and liberty. With regard to the last item, it
is true, André Gillois observes, at the end of his
piece on Automaton, that it will be some time
before the encyclopaedists reach the letter"L",
adding, however, a trifle cynically, that people
are used to this long wait for Liberty.
ENGLAND IS NOW SYNCHRONIZING Enyli<h
lanFnatre sound tracks on rorei ! fll lllIlIs r"r
the first time, following-"n eXt'hang-e ag-re...
ment signed in Rome. Films imported from
Italy are in future to be shown in Eng-lisl1.
The first Italian production to be shown in
English duhhin) r is Bitter Rice. It is hop-
ed that six Italian films will be synchronized
into English every year.
EDUCATORS IN THE BELGIAN CONGO a""
demonstrating the value of literacy by man,
of a narrative (lem entitled Savolr Lire.
It tells a simple story of a young man, Al-
phonse, who gets into all kinds of difßcullies
and losses a chance to get a job because he
cannot read. Savolr Lire is bein ! r elTe,'-
tively used by mobile Illm nnils taking part
in the Congo's literacy campaigns.
ENCYCLOPAEDIA BRITANNICA FILMS-th.,
largest producer of educational tJlms in the
world-provides TO per cent of all films,
used In American classrooms. This American
organization has produced over 500 titles
covering fields from the Adventures of Bun-
ny Rabbit to Eleotrodynamlos and the Mole-
oular Theory of Matter. Versions in 13 3 fo :-
eign languages are also available for use
in classrooms abroad.
A REVOLUTIONARY THREE-MMEMStONAL
F) LM, Around Is Around, has been produced
for the Festival or Britain by Normal
McLaren, the Canadian animated mm
producer who has gained international fame
for his daring technique or painting or
etching on raw mm without the use or the
camera. The novelty of this ten-minute rim,
produced by the National Film Board of
Canada in collaboration with the British Film
Institute, is that it provides three-dimension
quality both In sound and in images.
Members of the audience are provided with
special spectacles which make the images
appear to stand out from the screen, while
the sound"moves away"from the screen
In all directions at the same time. Experi-
ments in three-dimensional mms are under
way in a number of countries.
AT LEAST 42 COUNTRIES IMPOSE CUSTOM
DUTIES and other restrictions on the impor-
tation of flims. according to"Trade Barrier, ;
to Knowledge", a recent Unesco publication.
These will be alleviated for newsreels and
educational, scientific and cultural films as
soon as two Unesco-sponsored international
conventions enter into force. The first.
coverine'nims of educational, scientinc or
cultural character, has been signed by 18
countries and ratined by four. The second
grants duty-free admission to newsreels im-
ported by organizations. It has been signed
by 23 countries and ratined by three. Bolh
Unesco agreements require 10 ratincations to
become operative.
UNESCO FILM COUPONS. Film projectors,
16-millimetre raw mm and other film mate-
rials can be obtained by individuals In"soft
currency"countries from suppliers in"ha rd
currency"countries through Unesco's Film
Coupon Scheme. So far l"i of Unesco's
Member States have joined this scheme, in-
cluding all the main mem-supplying countries.
Out of a total of nearly one and a half
million dollars'worth of Unesco Coupons
put into circulation, approximately 10 per
cent have been Issued for the purchase of
educational (Urns. The Egyptian Ministry of
Public Health, for example, recently ordered
19 documentary nims, provided with Ar. tbtc
sound-tracks, covering such subjects as
home-nursing, Ilrst-ald, the common cold and
dental care. Another scheme, Unesco Gift
Coupons (see COUMER, March 1950 also
can be, used to buy educational Illms and
111m projectors.
THE GERMAN FEDERAL REPUBLIC has creates
an annual ntm prize ca)) ed the"Theodore"
for producers, authors and actors. Prizes
are given not to leading stars hut to out-
standing beginners. Awards are also made
for fi) ms judg-ed tne most thoug-ht-pro-
vowing, the most democratic, for the most
striking treatment of a social theme, and for
the best development of a European idea, as
well as for the best cultural and fictional
productions.
LA MONTAGNE EST VERTE (The Mountain la
Preen), a medium. length documentary deal-
ing'with the emancipation of slaves In the
former French colonies, has received the
patronage of the United Nations Film Board
for its high ideals and first-class technical
quality. This French ills, produced by
J. K. Raymond-Millet and directed by Jean
Lehérissey, Is a tribute to the memory of
Victor Schoelcher whose life-long-fight for
the abolition of slavery In Martinique and
Guadeloupe led to an emancipation law sign-
ed by the provisional government of the
Second French Republic In t848. La Mon-
tagne eat verte, produced without financial
help from the United Nations, Is an example
of how the cinema can make the principles
of the Declaration of Human Rights more
wide known.
*
THE USE OF MOBILE CINEMA and radio vans
in fundamental education is surveyed in a
Unesco book just published. The survey.
shows that wherever the vans have been
used their effects have been excellent, parti-
cularly where they serve areas lacking cine-
mas and electric power supply. The hook-
let is a practical gUide to the best uses for
these vans, complete with blueprints for
their arrangement and detailed information
on the best equipment available.
..
MOROCCAN YOUTH are seeing more and better
tllms these days, thanks to the efforts of a
tllm association set up in Casablanca in 1949.
Performances of tllms chosen for their qua-
lity and educational value are open to mem-
bers who range upwards from ten years old.
THE TASK AHEAD is the title of a new twenty-
minute documentary film produced by the
Film Division of Unesco on some of the Or-
ganization's activities in different countries
and the work of the Secretariat in Paris.
The film is distributed in t6 and 35 milli-
metres with sound tracks in eight Ian !'uages :
Enfrhsh, French. Spanish. Portuguese, Ger-
man, Arabic, Hindustani, and Italians.
"_ : _
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Page I I-UNESCO COURIER
"JUSTICE EST FAITE
MR. FILM CENSOR...
"Must Everything in the Garden Be Lively ?"
by Charles SPAAK
President, Screen Writers Guild of France, 1950-51
"RETOUR A LA VIE"
or can the cinema help in fosteringmutual understanding and, hence,
mutual esteem, between the na-
tions of the world ? This is an inspiring
subject for people who are given to long
speeches, and one which inevitably calls
forth the most optimistic platitudes.
Of course it could serve those ends, but
the organization and censorship of film
production is such that the result is quite
different. It is precisely because the
screen could give us an intimate insight
into the life of people in other lands
that governments take such vigilant care
to ensure that only an official picture
is given of the areas under their control.
It should not be forgotten that, of all
media of expression, the cinema every-
where enjoys the least freedom, being
the victim of two equally detestable
censorship measures : firstly, with regard
to the home production of films, and
secondly, with regard to the showing
of foreign films. In the first case, there
must be no allusion to any controversial
topic ; in the second case, whenever a
problem which the government consi-
ders dangerous is touched upon, the
people in one country are not allowed to
find out what their neighbours think of
it. So, each nation says to the other :
I should like to have the ideas that your
government allows you to impart, but
only if your ideas are exactly in line with
what my government allows me to utter.
So long as this is accepted, nations are
very willing to exchange information, to
get to understand and esteem one an-
other. Yet in all solemnity, responsible
people wonder what part the cinema can
play in the lofty task of fostering friend-
ship between the nations by helping them
to understand each other's social, intel-
lectual or religious characteristics.
Both entertainment and documentary
films are victims of the same system.
The latter which, as their name implies,
should contain only documentary evi-
dence, are subjected to an even more
rigorous control than the others, and
very little confidence can be placed in
their objectivity.
Everywhere censors suppress films
whose purpose is not in accordance
with accepted tradition, and film
producers are paralyzed by fear of
censorship. What can the Anglo-Saxon
countries have learnt, for instance, from
films produced in Paris during the past
ten years ? That you can sit at tables
on the pavement in front of all the big
cafes, that exotic dance steps are per-
formed in cellars, that married couples
insist on sleeping in the same bed, and
that some depraved individuals have a
misguided affection for ladies whom they
have not married. All that amounts to
very little. But what have they revealed
of France's problems and struggles ?
And what film producer would dare to
allude to such matters ? When Autant-
Lara, producer of Le Diable au corps
wanted to tell the story of a conscientious
objector, when André Cayatte, producer
of Justice est faite-I am deliberately
quoting only well-known films-tried
to describe the Seznec affair (the unfor-
tunate Breton who did twenty years'
hard labour for a murder which no
one now believes he was guilty of), they
both met with such difficulties that they
had to abandon their original ideas.
Don't mention war, don't mention jus-
tice ! If they are not religious, but want
to express their views on religion, if they
wish to describe social conditions which
they consider unsatisfactory, if they want
to express opinions on money, freedom,
love, life or death, let them beware, for
the censor's eye is on them !
What information value, then, can
films have abroad if they reflect
nothing but official or conventional
views ?"Everything in the garden is
lovely..."It is always the same story. In
our comfortable seat in the darkened
cinema, we are lulled into thinking that
all is for the best in the best possible of
worlds ; any uneasiness aroused by the
newsreel is dispelled by the documentary
film and the feature film that follow.
Although they have revealed so little
of the nation's inner, secret life,
have French film producers man-
aged, at least, to further international
understanding through films inspired by
a generous desire for reconciliation with
a former foe ? A film which leaps at once
to the mind is La Grande Allusion. In
that aim, Germans and Frenchmen, at
a time in history when they should have
been implacable enemies, faced each
other without hatred. It was banned in
Germany. And when immediately after
the last war, it was shown in France, the
press launched a violent campaign
against it, trying to get it withdrawn. In
all honesty, it must be admitted that the
cinema which is nationalistic in inspira-
tion does little to advance the cause
of free international exchange of infor-
mation which, by its very nature, it could
do so much to help.
I am all the more sorry, when I think
of the splendid purposes which this
remarkable instrument for the spread of
knowledge could serve. It is not my
fault if men today, like animals shrink-
ing from their own reflection in a mirror,
are afraid to see themselves portrayed
with brutal frankness on the screen.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 12
THANKS TO THE CINE-CAMERA
SCIENTISTS ARE UNCOVERING A STRANGE,
WN WORLD
At first glance we are sure this is a painted African mask worn by some Negro warrior brandishing his arms
in a typical ceremonial dance. In reality it is a magnified close-up film of an African cricket from the Cameroons.
by Maurice GOLDSMITH
THE film was born to do scientific work and
not originally to entertain. Before theinvention of the cinema, the French astro-
nomer Pierre Janssen in 1874 photograph-
ed phases of the track of the planet Venus and
about six years later the French physiologit
Etienne Marey studied the fiight of birds with
a specially designed camera.
But the most impressive experiment that
really begins the story of the scientific film was
the demonstration in California by the pioneer
British-born photographer, Edward Muybridge,
that. a trotting horse has all its four legs off the
ground at the same time. It was Muybridge, in
fact, who gave the first demonstration in Europe
of scientific films. That was in 1882 in the
theatre of the Royal Institution in London.
His lecture on"The Science of Animal Loco-
motion in its Relation to Design in Art"
confounded critics who had declared that the
reproduction of a satisfactory photograph of a
rapidly moving object was absolutely outside the
bounds of possibility. Their surprise was
expressed by a writer in the IDustrated London
News, who described how"by the aid of an
astonishing apparatus called a zoopraxiscope...
animals suddenly became mobile and beautiful,
and walked, cantered, ambled, galloped, and
leaped over hurdles in the field of vision in a
perfectly natural and life-like manner..."
Today the aim has an honoured place not
only in research and investigation as a scien-
tific tool, but also as a basic method of popu-
larizing science and presenting its social impli-
cations.
In the research laboratory the cine-camera
is an indispensable tool because it is an unob-
served and undisturbing observer ; it is insensi-
tive to atmosphere and fatigue ; it can function
for hours on end with a non-sleeping eye,
without producing confusion and overlapping
among successive images ; it can delve into and
uncover a strange, unknown microscopic world.
In addition, the camera can act as a time-
expander and as a time-condenser ; and it can
see things in wave-lengths invisible to the ordin-
ary eye.
UNKNO
LINES
AND
IRe L E S
n o
BrLi
The eye of the crab (1) is (almost) enough to make the lover of shellfish lose his appetite ; white the eyes gleaming above the
huge mouth of this gentle little fish from Madagascar (2) are not very reassuring either. We can only see four of the many eye
of the spider (3) but they are definitely unpleasant. The sea anemone (4) boasts a secret weapon : a deadly liquid hidden ire
hundreds of tiny"buttons"covering its wriggling tentactes. The tail of a shrimp (5), seen under the microscope film camera, :
has the warlike appearance of a hedgehog ready to attack. The camera clarifies what the human eye cannot distinguish.,
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Pace 13-UNESCO COURIER
Baby Seahorse : horizontal. When the baby seahorse is born it assumes the horizontal position
normal to all fishes and acquatic creatures.
Adult Seahorse : wertteat. But when it reaches maturity the seahorse suddenly assumes a
vertical position. It is the only vertebrate creature known that lives and moves in this position in
water. Another curious fact : the male seahorse-not the female-gives birth to its young. The
female lays her eggs in a pouch below the male's stomach where they remain for 40 days, and are
fed by the male's blood until birth. Photo shows two male seahorses.
The Lobster and the Flea. The lobster's claw' (left) bears a striking resemblance to a parrot's
beak or a Commed ! a deH'Arte character. The fresh-water flea (right) reproduces by parthenoge-
nesis since no male : <ist in this species.
Scientific photography is nearly
half-a-century old, and as one writer
has said"has brought many reve-
lations of the beauty and harmony
of the physical universe, and some
notable extensions to our knowledge
of it."In astronomy, for example,
the film has added greatly to our
knowledge of what is happening on the
sun, particularly in the behaviour of
solar prominences-so much so that
far more problems have been raised
than it has been possible to answer.
In an American film Explosions on
the Sun"it is possible to see in a few
minutes changes that have taken
hours to occur, and to marvel at an
eruptive arch expanding at the rate
of about 1, 000 miles a second. In a
field at Paracutin, in Mexico, in Fe-
bruary 1943, a volcano suddenly came
to life. Within a short while scientists
came along with a camera and began
a unique record of the birth, life and
decline of this tremendous eruption of
nature.
In the biological sciences, the first
film was made by the Frenchman,
Jean Comandon, some 40 years ago.
"In our days", he wrote,"motion pic-
tures are a necessity to the scholar
who wishes to demonstrate to his col-
leagues transitory. phenomena, delin-
eate experiments or the general
observation of things, beings or facts."
At the Pasteur Institute at Garches,
such films of his as Cb'lmpignons Pre-
dateurs, which deals with a curious
fungus that preys on worms, and
Substitution de Noyaux d'Amibes,
which depicts the technique of the
removal of the nucleus of an amoeba
and its replacement by another
nucleus, have been basic contributions
to knowledge. His note on this last
film begins :"For studying the slow
movements of an amoeba, time-lapse
and cine-micrography have been par-
ticularly useful and have revealed
things which would not have been
apparent by direct observations."The
cine-camera can, in fact, be attached
to microscopes, telescopes, stereoscopes,
and all kinds of optical instruments
which normally produce a picture for
the human eye to see and to measure,
and so a recording instrument of
the finest accuracy can be produced.
In the medical field, living move-
ments of lungs and limbs can be
viewed repeatedly without danger
of an overdose of X-rays harming
the individual. It has been said
that with the introduction of film the
science of medicine has progressed so
far that"the same patient can be
used over and over again."
On the technical side, infra-red can
be used to take photographs in appar-
ent darkness. It was used to make a
film for scientists anxious to study the
contraction and dilation of the pupil
of an eye when a bright source of
light was switched on and off close to
it. Ultra-violet illumination has been
used, for example, to study the surface
of red-hot steel bars. During the
rolling process foreign bodies may
enter the bars, but it is difficult to see
what is happening because of the
glare from the red-hot metal. Using
a filter over the camera lens and illu-
minating the bar by either blue or
ultramarine violet light, it is possible
to photograph the bar as if it were
quite cold.
Science is popularized on the screen
through the documentary, the teaching
film, and the feature film.
The documentary school founded by
John Grierson has from the outset
tried to maintain links between the
specialist and the technician and the
general public. The documentary is
distinguished from the teaching, or
instructional, film in that its job is
"the creative interpretation of reality",
and when it deals with science it is
concerned with the relations between
science and society.
John Maddison, president of the
International Scientific Film As-
sociation, describes in"Experiment
in the Film", edited by Roger Manvell,
published by Grey Walls Press, London,
1949, two good examples of the
documentary's power to interpret
science. The first is Elton and Bell's
Transfer of Power, in which within
the space of twenty minutes the story
of the evolution of a technical device
is not only told with lucidity and
coherence but is related to the social
pattern. In Blood Transf11sion, Rotha
and Neurath drive home the point,
with an ingenious bringing together
of actuality, models, and animated
drawings, that scientific achievement
is a cooperative international business.
MADDISON refers to"the work ofBritish documentary technicians
in using films as a mass edu-
cational technique under Government
and other sponsorships"and to its
offshoots in Canada and elsewhere.
"Its importance it twofold. It has
illumined the social function of
science in countless ways. In Enough
to Eat, Housing Problems and Smoke
Menace, it has afforded a pulpit to
such progressive interpreters of
science as Huxley, Haldane and Boyd
Orr. During the last war, new labo-
ratory findings and techniques for
dealing with such problems as potato
blight and scabies were made widely
known to an extent impossible without
the use of the film. More recently,
Personnel Selection and Children
Learning by Experience have shown
how the camera can expound at-
tempts to apply objectivity and good
sense to the more delicate problems of
human behaviour."
He adds :"Not less important than
the new techniques of production ex-
plored has been the vast non-theatrical
experiment in distributing films to
audiences outside the commercial
movie houses. Fresh images of scien-
tific achievement have been carried
into schoolroom, workshop, byre and
forest clearing and the thousand and
one places where men meet together."
THE teaching film is known to bei a s imulating influence for both
pupils and teacher. A study
made in the USA concluded that
"when properly produced and wisely
used, the motion picture possesses dis-
tinct pedagogical values over and
above traditional teaching methods on
which the same amounts of time and
energy are expended,"It has been
found that children studying by means
of films have learned more than their
colleagues who have not used this aid.
Among the best of the British instruc-
tional aims-and pioneer efforts
when they began in 1921-is the po-
pular science Secrets of Nature se-
ries, begun by the late Percy Smith.
They were often produced in two ver-
sions-one for schools, and one with
a"popular"commentary for the ci-
nemas.
The feature film is essentially
a form of entertainment. There-
fore, little has been done consciously
to depict science as an everyday
vital force, but the effects of
such films as Pasteur and Madame
Curie have been very great. In this
context, the development of the science
action film is a factor of some import-
ance. These films are very popular
and some, such as Destination Moon,
have not been offensive in their
scientific content. The Russians have
in recent years used the feature film as
a serious medium with which to tell
the personal dramatic story of great
scientific personalities, such as Zhn-
kovsky, the pioneer of Russian avia-
tion, and Michurin the botanist.
Special mention must be made of
the great contribution of the Frencr
and the world-wide recognition of the
work of Jean Painlevé. Maddison des-
cribes how he has attempted"to
create a new sort of scientific film
biography for the ordinary cine-
magoer. He and Georges Rouquier
have made an absorbing study out
of the biological work of Louis
Pasteur in a film entitled The
Scientific Achievements of Pasteur.
Using an unknown unprofessional
actor, a Paris workman with a
strong resemblance to the great sa-
vant, Rouquier has made the scenes
in which Pasteur fought against the
prejudices of contemporary scientists.
come to life again on the screen. But
the main excitement of the film lies
In the way which Painlevé, through
innumerable hours spent with camera
and microscope in the cine-laboratory,
has retold the long tale of Pasteur's
triumph over microbes.
In most western European countries
there are scientific film associations
doing important work in developing
the use and understanding of the
scientific aim. and in 1947 there was
formed an International Scientific
Film Association. They are workirg
for an end of great significance to
society : to build up through the film
a living unity between the scientist,
the artist, and the man-in-the-street.
The photographs on these two
pages are published by kind
permission of M. Jean Pain-
levee, director of the Institute
of Scientific CinematlOgraphy
in Paris. These illustrations
are all extracts from M. Pain-
levee's film.
Battle to the death. A dytiscid gets Its victim. This underwater insect has no mouth ; instead
two sharp hooks, leading directly to the stomach, Inject digestive juices into the dytiscid's food and
then suck them into the stomach.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 14
THE NEWS REEL CAMERA :
THOUGH its potentialities have beenonly partly re liz d, the n w
film is a universal and powerful
means of mass communication. Pic-
tures can be understood by anyone,
whether literate or illiterate, and make
him an eye-witness, as it were, of the
events they portray. In most countries,
the weekly newsreel has become a
feature of contemporary life, like the
illustrated news magazine.
A report just published by Unes-
co (1) shows that each person in the
world attends the cinema, on an ave-
rage, five times a year and that most
of the world's 100, 000 cinemas regularly
include news films in programmes.
These films are classified as regular
newsreels, film magazines dealing
with current events or special topics,
and general information or publicity
documentaries.
Despite their world-wide range,
newsreels have changed little in form
during the past 30 years. In company
with other films, however, they are now
challenged by a powerful new medium
- television. In countries where
television has been developed, televised
news has scored outstanding success
and promises to become the major
means of visual communication.
The story of the newsreel's develop-
ment, as told in the Unesco report, is
fascinating. The world's first films,
dating from the early 1890's, were a
(1). vewsreels Across tile World (La
Pre sse Filmée dans Ie J/onde) : by
Peter Raech/in, Swiss film expert, and
3/aMrice. Muller-Strauss, French film
historian. Unesco Publication 8. 8. $2. 00 ;
1016 ; 500 Fr. fcs. 7'/if present edition,
available at all Unesco sales agents, is
in French. An Engl1sh edition is being
prepared.
form of newsreel and their producers
developed the basic techniques of the
modern film industry, such as the use
of artificial light, camera tricks and
techniques and the reconstruction of
dramatic incidents.
From Nickelodeons
to Cinemas
IN those days the cameramanenjoyed less freedom of access
than he does today and newsreel
makers often had recourse to
"reconstructing"topical events. One
of them, an American named Amet,
staged a reproduction-in his bath-
of the destruction of the Spanish fleet
during the Spanish-American war of
1898. The film had an international
success. Amet later created a sensa-
tion by reconstructing realistic battle
scenes from the Boer War on waste
ground in Brooklyn.
The demand for newsfilms greatly
increased when permanent cinemas re-
placed nickelodeons and travelling
shows around 1907. World War I
gave the newsreel its great chance to
assert itself and gain access to scenes
of world events.
New films are today produced by
three groups-private companies,
joint undertakings with State partici-
pation or subsidy, and State-owned
units. Of the 47 countries covered by
the report, 40 together have a total of
160 producing units. Most of these,
however, produce only"national"
news films which circulate mainly in
the country of origin.
In newsreel production and distri-
bution, a comparatively small number
of big film companies in the United
AROUND THE WORLD
IN 15 MINUTES
by Philip SOLJAK
States, United Kingdom, France and
the Soviet Union have built up inter-
national networks. These companies,
whether private or State controlled,
enjoy a predominance in film reporting,
rather like that of the great news
agencies. This primacy is often
attained by the exchange of news to-
pics and camera services, by the control
of cinema circuits and by"block
booking"of feature films with news-
reels. A number of countries make
national newsreels. But since a news-
reel, to pay its way, must usually be
shown in at least 1, 000 cinemas, it is
difficult for small countries to maint-
ain their own newsfilm.
Largely as a result of these economic
factors, most newsreels tend more and
more to follow a uniform standard
pattern. Emphasis is mainly on the
"entertainment value"of items select-
ed, which normally consist of sport,
general news, fashion and miscellan-
eous material. The exchange of items
among a few big producers-a useful
technical expedient-moreover means
that the same topics tend to be repeat-
ed in newsreels shown over most of the
world.
The Great Challenge
of Television
IN order to utilize fully this impor-tant visual medium, wider inter-
national exchanges of news items
would be required, as well as the
extension to more countries and pro-
ducers of opportunities to obtain
film material from any area.
Today, as television spreads around
the world, newsreels are having to
adapt themselves to the challenge of
a new medium which brings scenes
from near and far directly into peo-
ple's homes. Recent developments
in the United States and United King-
dom suggest that fully-rounded
"film digests", of the documentary or
film magazine type, will be increas-
ingly seen both on television and
cinema screens.
Films are Part of our
Daily lives
EXCHANGES OAF televised news itemsbetween the United States,
United Kingdom and France
are already under way. Such
exchanges, while helping peoples in
different countries to know and un-
derstand each other better, raise an
important technical problem. The
countries where television is most rapid-
ly developing are those which pro-
duce new films that are shown through-
out the world. Any rivalry arising
between television and newsreels in
these few countries will, therefore,
largely determine the character, qua-
lity and presentation of visual news in
other, smaller countries which do not
themselves posses either of these two
media.
Films have become part of our daily
lives. Newsreels can perform a va-
luable service by highlighting import-
ant events and trends and by showing
the ordinary man how his counterpart
in other lands is living and meeting
common problems. The parallel deve-
lopment of news films and television
provides communication experts with a
doubly powerful instrument which must
be used with a full sense of social
responsibility toward all men, regard-
less of frontiers.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Page 5-UNESCO COURtER
THE CAMERA RECORDS CATASTROPHE
A helicopter crashes on a Welsh hillside (Pathe News) A ship torpedoed at sea during the last war (USIS)
THE CAMERA PRESENTS PEOPLE IN THE NEWS
PresidentSoekarno announces Indonesia's independence (UN) Arturo Toscanini poised fora concertopening (March of Time)
THE CAMERA RECORDS POST-WAR RECONSTRUCTION
French speed work on Alpine hydro-electric plant (ECA) Refrigerators will condense steam to drive turbines (ECA)
THE CAMERA RECORDS WORK OF U. N.
UNICEF provides milk four a little boy in Europe Another boy discards his old shoes for new ones
THE NEWSREEL CAMERA RECORDS SPORTS : a split-second shot of an exciting mishap at a motor-race
EARLY NEWSREELS
1900 : Visit to the Paris Exhibition
1901 : Queen Victoria's funeral
1
2
I,
1909 : First air crossing of English Channel by Louis
1910 : The Seine floods Paris
Archives Cinémathèque, Française)
4
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURtER-Page) 6
Most of these
Art Films
Are Unknown
: ALBRECHT DURER : Die grosse
Holzschnittpassion (A U S T R I A),
Dürer's wood-carvings of the Pas-
sion.
RUBENS (BELGIUM), his life and
work
LES FAUX WERMEER (BELGIUM).
close-ups or Han van Meegeren's
forgeries or Vermeers.
TIRADENTES (BRAZIL), based on
the fresco by Portinari depicting
the Brazilian national hero Tira-
dentes.
LOON'S NECKLACE (CANADA), an
Indian legend portrayed with the
help or original masks.
ART OF CINA (CHINA), ancient
architecture, paintings, sculpture,
ceramics, embroidered silk.NEJSTARS) UMEN) (CZECHOSLOVA-
KIA), prehistoric art.
CHRISTIAN IV-SOM BYGMESTER
(DENMARK), story of the Danish
King-who was called"the'Vlaster
Constructor"for his influence on
the Renaissance in his country.
L'AFFAIRE MANET (FRANCE), da-
guerrotypes, caricatures and news-
paper cuttings recall the scandal
in 1865 over Manet's paintings.
IMAGES DE LA FOLIE (FRANCE),
paintings and drawings from the
first world Exhibition of Psycho-
pathological Art in Paris in 1950.
LE6 CHARMES DE L'EXISTENCE
(FRANCE), satirical review of art
shows between 1880 and 19i0.
IMAGES MEDIEVALES (FRANCE).
the Middle Ages depicted by 14th
an 15th century miniatures.
DIE GOTTESMUTTER (GERMANY),
the Virgin in Rhineland art of the
Middle Agues.
EIN MARIENLEBEN (GERMANY),
Marian sculptures by HeInrich Dou-
vermann, 16th century.
LOOKING AT SCULPTURE (GREAT
BRITAIN), a tour of the Victoria
and Albert Museum in London.
MONT ATHOS (GREECE).
SAGA IN STONE (INDIA).
II DRAMMA DE CRISTO (ITALY), the
Giotto Prescoes at Padua.
II DEMONIACO NELL'ARTE (ITALY).
the Temptation depicted by old
masters.
LEZIONE DI GEOIETRIA (ITALY),
how abstract art develops from
higher mathematics.
MOSAICI DI RAVENNA (ITALY),
Byzantine mosaics of the Middle
Ages.
MEXICO PRECORTESIANO
(MEXICO), architecture and crafts-
manship or ancient Mexico.
BISKOPINE (POLAND), prehistorie
art.
VAR GAMLA STAD (SWEDEN).
medieval history of Stockholm and
its royal palace.
MICHELANGELO : La Vie d'un Titan
(A Swiss production, made in
Rome and Florence).
FERNAND LEGER IN AMERICA. His
New Realism (U. S. A.). narration in
French by the artist on his life and
work during five years In the
U. S. A.
LASCAUX, CRADLE OF MAN'S ART
(U. S.. A.), a study or the cave
paintings at Lascaux, France.
WORKS OF CALDER (U. SA r. a visit
to the enchanting world or Alexan-
der Calder, famed for his "mobile"
art.
A. S. PUSHKIN (U. S. S. R.), inspirations
and work of the poet.
A close-up from the Belgian film RUBENS by Paul Haesaerts and Henri Storck, showing Rubens'eye from his famous
self-portrait at Windsor Castle.
WHAT HAPPENS TO ART FILMS ?
WHEN a producer makes a short-reel film devoted
to a work of art or several works of art he
may be congratulated for his achievement or
he may receive a shower of brickbats. But whatever
the reaction, it almost always comes from a small
number of specialized film critics who, more often
than not, are his own colleagues. The art film pro-
ducer may even win some kind of award or other
official forms of recognition to encourage him to
continue his work. But what actually happens to the
film ? It is true that the film on art is a relative new-
comer to the cinema. The first successful ventures
of the Belgian Henri Storck date from 1936, while the
Inspirational Themes of Dekeukeleire, the Michel-
angelo of Curt Certel, and the Mystic Lamb of André
Cauvin appeared only before the war. But the fact
is that the number of real masterpieces produced thus
far in this field is quite high. That many failures
have also been turned out cannot, of course, be denied.
The art film producers themselves have recognized
this and are constantly on guard to avoid the pitfalls
of stereotyped presentation or mere imitation. That
is why they keep hunting for new techniques, new
ideas and fresh approaches more keenly than the
"commercial"cinema does. But what do they gain
in the end ? Once again, what happens to their
films ? Unesco has drawn up a list of 476 titles-of
quite unequal worth it must be admitted-produced
in 21 different countries (1). But ask the cinema-
going public about them, those people who go to the
"pictures"with almost clock-like regularity. How
many have seen any of these films ? How many have
even heard of them let alone been able to enjoy them ?
(On this page we give a list of some of the better art
films. But how many of them have our readers heard
of-or seen ?) In first-run and local cinemas the
documentary stands a chance-of being shown both
in the big cities and in provincial towns ; so does the
short scientific film. But films on art are apparently
considered taboo because it has been"decided"that
the general public is not interested in art. The rare
occasions when the art film has been shown to the
general public has proved that this is simply not true.
In spite of this, Storck, Emmer, Haesaerts ans Resnais
remain relegated to the"cinema clubs"and"art-film
houses". Yet their films could, if given a chance, open
a small window into the magic world of the painter,
the sculptor and the architect for those who know
even nothing of the arts. It would be a revolution.
But it is perhaps too much to expect.
Georges FRADIER.
(t) Published In 1950 and 1951 as an appendix to the two
volumes on « Films on Art » (4/$0.65 or 200 fr. frs.).
Maillol at work. A scene from the French film. MAILLOL by Jean Lods.
]]>
</page>
</document>
