<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074675eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
Jftu jf^^t JANUARY JÊAt- 6 Fif-r" frs-os £
r»i he g 1 ^^B^ *^P ^^ ^^^^
L nesco I l
Bfl^HB^ .^Bb BF ^H
b ^ r 1 1 J« 4
^m^BI ^flftSflBaB'^
Br^i* «räi'-&^3i'f
'Ht ^Wt"! M^
B^^ PT^BJjB ' 1 -Jr%S
Bf>
bV jMv P^^ L Val
Bjjjjjí^^^^B« Bw Bjjjj^^
i*"*,*jRjj' : BJf »~ ^Bj
BH^BB^^Bf ÍÉBk
ÉBa 1 : * !'5&
5^Ç Ckî^bI
MB
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A time to live...
o
BANGLADESH
Brooms and baskets
Located in the delta plain of
the Ganga and the Brahma¬
putra, rivers, Bangladesh is a
predominantly agrarian coun¬
try with a population of over
90 million. It is the world's
largest producer of jute and
its main industry is the pro¬
duction of yarns and textile
fabrics. Cottage industries
and the traditional crafts still
flourish. Left, a vendor of
brooms and baskets hawks his
wares in the streets of Jessore,
a town near the country's
western border.
Photo © Ron Giling, Arnhem, Netherlands
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
JANUARY 1984 37th YEAR
Published in 27 lang uages
English Tamil Korean
French Hebrew Swahili
Spanish Persian Croato-Serb
Russian Dutch Macedonian'
German Portuguese Serbo-Croat
Arabic Turkish Slovene
Japanese Urdu Chinese
Italian Catalan Bulgarian
Hindi Malaysian Greek
A selection in Braille is published quarterly
in English, French, Spanish and Korean
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 58 French Francs; 2 years (valid only in
France): 100 French Francs
Binder for a year's issues: 46 FF
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
ISSN 0041 - 5278
No. 1 - 1984 -OPI- 83-1 -406 A
Cover photo © Bargy, Paris ,
pages
4 GEORGE ORWELL, A 'TORY ANARCHIST'
by Jacques Charpier
8 FROM ANALYSIS TO ACTION
New trends in the psychological sciences
by Agnès Oppenheimer
1 1 PSYCHOLOGY IN BLACK AFRICA
by Amewusika Kwadzo Tay
15 ANATOMY OF INEQUALITY
The economic crisis seen from the Third World
by Jean Sayinzoga
19 IN SEARCH OF NEW ECONOMIC STRUCTURES
by François Perroux
v25 IS CRIME A UNIVERSAL CONCEPT?
by Henri Laborit
30 CULTURE SHOCK AND CRIMINALITY
by Miguel Rojas Mix
34 UNESCO NEWSROOM
2 A TIME TO LIVE....
BANGLADESH: Brooms and baskets
THE calendar is to a large de¬
gree a social convention, and
each newyear does not necess¬
arily usher in innovation and novelty.
All the same, the beginning of the
year, like the beginning ofa decade or
a century, provides a regular oppor¬
tunity to take stock, to test the pulse
of humanity.
At the beginning of 1984 we have
chosen to examine three of the many
questions which are preoccupying the
human community: the effects of the
economic crisis; the latest trends in
psychological research; and the thrust
ofa criminality which seems generally
to be rising.
We invited two specialists to con¬
tribute to the debate on each of these
issues, one from an industrialized
country, onefrom a developing coun¬
try. This is not meant as an endorse¬
ment of one of the accepted ways of
delineating the world today, but as an
attempt to present a diversity of
analytical viewpoints and processes
and, perhaps, to reveal points of
agreement which transcend the in¬
evitable divergences.
It goes without saying that we are
not claiming in this number to cover
the most important threats or pro¬
mises confronting humankind
todayproblems of hunger and
health, knowledge for all, peace,
justice, and harmony among peoples.
The studies in this issue do, however,
have roots in such problems and make
it possible to explore their often hid¬
den complexities if not to propose
potential solutions.
Nor is it in accordance with conven¬
tion that we open this issue with an
analysis of the case ofGeorge Orwell,
which is being widely studied and
questioned in this month of January
1984. Over and above the political
controversy or the so-calledprophetic
nature of the work, the question re¬
mains of man's anxiety in face of his
own "modernity". Is it not the
machine-State more than the
totalitarian State that is at issue here?
And does not the reaction to such a
danger of robotization lead man to
fall prey, paradoxically, to attitudes
that are regressive or invalid?
The sharpness of these debates
should not obliterate our common
hope, reaffirmed by the twenty-
second session of Unesco's General
Conference held at the Organiza¬
tion's Paris Headquarters from 25
October to 26 November 1983. The
Unesco Courier presents its best
wishes for 1984 to its readers and to
all men and women of goodwill
throughout the world.
' ,f*~
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
George Orwell,
a Tory anarchist'
by Jacques Charpier
SOMETIMES the anniversary of the birth or death of an
author, or of the date of publication of a book, offers an
opportunity to pay tribute to universal culture by lighting
candles which in many cases shed only a brief flicker of light on a
writer or his work. This year is somewhat different; it is itself the
title of a book George Orwell's Nineteen Eighty-Four which
since it was published over thirty years ago has made its author
world famous.
Orwell, whose real name was Eric Arthur Blair, was born at
Motihari in Bengal on 25 June 1903. His father, Richard Walmesley
Blair, was in the Opium Department of the Government of India.
Eric's family belonged to the outer reaches of the Establishment.
His great grandfather (died 1820) had been a rich planter in
Jamaica who had married into the aristocracy but had died a poor
man. His youngest son, Eric's grandfather, after briefly studying
at Cambridge, was obliged through indigence to make a career in
the Church of England. His son, Eric's father, became a minor col¬
onial civil servant at the age of eighteen. Somewhat late in life he
married Ida Mabel Limouzin, daughter of a French teak merchant
and boatbuilder. Risky speculations in rice brought the Limouzins
down in the world. This relative social decline may shed some light
on the personality of the future author of Nineteen Eighty-Four
and on a certain ambiguity that can be sensed in him. He said that
he belonged to "the lower upper middle class".
His parents' relatively modest situation did not prevent them
from sending him to Eton, where he studied Latin, Greek,
mathematics and divinity, and rowed and played cricket. He seems
to have been an average student, but he was already determined to
become a "famous author".
Like some of his fellow pupils, Eric displayed a certain refusal to
conform. He read Bernard Shaw, H.G. Wells, and Galsworthy,
and "loosely described myself as a Socialist". One question in a
general knowledge paper at school in 1920 was "Whom do you con-,
sider the ten greatest men now living?" Blair, like fifteen out of six¬
teen in the class, included Lenin in his list. Either because of his
mediocrity as a student or, more likely, because of his family's
financial straits, he did not go on from Eton to Oxford. Instead,
he became a trainee at the Burma Provincial Police Training School
at Mandalay, graduating at the age of twenty-one as an Assistant
Superintendent of Police in the British colonial administration.
About the details of Blair's life during his five years in Burma not
much is known, but we do know that he was torn between two feel¬
ings: a certain distance from the colonialized peoples and a growing
rejection of British imperialism and colonialism. His Burmese ex¬
perience was probably much more important than his unconven¬
tional reading at Eton as a source of his "socialism", and from it
he developed his critique of imperialism and of capitalism in
general.
In 1927 Blair resigned. "I gave it up", he wrote later, "mainly
because I could not go on any longer serving an imperialism which
I had come to regard as very largely a racket".
JACQUES CHARPIER, French poet, essayist and radio producer, is
literary director of a French publishing house. A former professor of
French literature at Bryn Mawr College, Pennsylvania, he is the author
of many articles and books, including Paysage du Salut, Le Fer et le
Laurier, Paul Valéry, Villon and Saint-John Perse.
Back in England, Eric Blair's vocation to become a "famous
author" took practical shape: he decided to start to write. An
unusual period of his life now began. Even though he was in poor
health, there was no question of living off his family. However, I
do not think that it was for such simple and immediate moral
reasons that he chose to live as a vagrant in Paris and London. In
his first published book, Down and Out in Paris and London (when
he adopted the pseudonym George Orwell), he stressed the literary
nature of his work, and it is true that he published a number of ar¬
ticles at this period. He also refers to two novels which he claims
to have written then, but all trace of them has disappeared. It is not
impossible that his deliberate decision to live the life of a tramp was
taken for other reasons. He was not, in the narrow sense of the
term, politically minded. His unconventionality at Eton and his
o
@
George Orwell his real name was Eric
Blairwas born at Motihari, in Bengal,
on 25 June 1903. He is seen above,
aged six weeks in the arms of his ayah
(nursemaid).
criticisms of British imperialism did not go far enough to mould his
behaviour. On the other hand it cannot be ruled out that there were
psychological impulses behind his excursions into vagabondage. He
was aware of belonging to the "lower upper middle class" which
was simultaneously linked to and excluded from the Establishment,
conscious of its poverty yet remote from the "people", stripped of
its ancient privileges but still attached to certain traditions. Let us
say that there was a "bourgeois" streak in Eric Blair and also,
possibly, some unconscious failing which had given rise to certain
feelings of guilt. I would not go so far as to say that during the
Down and Out years Orwell was taking part in a play in which he
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
- 1 <il 4 <
#
***
4 t*> A
1^
4 % 4* 4 m
t
<* > 4ii>
Photo © Saul Steinberg Passport Photos, 1955, ink on paper, a composition of fingerprints by the US artist Saul Steinberg.
was both the actor and the only spectator, but it is not impossible
that he had, in every respect, assumed a disguise. In one episode in
Down and Out in Paris and London, he changes into the outfit of
a "poor man" and recognizes that "my new clothes had put me in¬
stantly into a new world", acting as a kind of passport from the
universe of the bourgeoisie to that of the proletariat. And he is
delighted when a hawker astonishingly addresses him as "mate".
Was Eric Blair looking for exotic social experiences which he
could use for a literary purpose, or was he a guilt-ridden young
member of the bourgeoisie searching for redemption through mix¬
ing with the poor and imitating the way they lived? These two
hypotheses are not irrelevant to an attempt to understand the per¬
sonality of Blair-Orwell. Whatever the answer to the puzzle, it is a
fact that between 1928 and 1930 George Orwell was preparing to
enter literature in the garb of a vagrant.
Although not yet the "famous author" he had wished to become
when at Eton, he began to take part in London literary life. He con¬
tributed to the Adelphi magazine. He became interested in the
social and economic conditions of the hop-pickers. He looked for
work, and took a teaching post at a small private school in Mid¬
dlesex. He wrote for the New English Weekly and The New
Statesman and Nation. He completed Burmese Days. Clearly in¬
spired by its author's experiences in Burma, this novel examines the
problem of the relationship between the white man and the in¬
digenous population, and denounces the subtle and not-so-subtle
dialectic between colonizers and colonized. This is not the classic
master-slave dialectic but one which, as V.S. Pritchett wrote later,
makes for a situation in which "oppression creates hypocrisy and
that hypocrisy corrupts" a formula that suggests the nuances of
Orwell's attitude to the colonial problem at that time. Not that his
denunciation of imperialism was the weaker for it.
Orwell had become a writer. In October 1934 he completed a se¬
cond novel, The Clergyman's Daughter, a work with which he was
dissatisfied and which he regarded merely as an exercise. It tells the
story of Dorothy, who escapes from the family and social prison to
which she is condemned and who, as far as some of the incidents
she experiences are concerned, bears a close sisterly resemblance to
her creator; she goes off to live with down-and-outs« and hop-
pickers, becomes a schoolmistress and then returns home. It is hard
to know what significance Orwell attached to this "unhappy end".
He was already at work on a new novel, Keep theAspidistra Flying,
a fierce denunciation of money, of mercantile society, of the havoc
lack of money causes in individual and collective destinies, of the
profit neurosis, and the worship of the golden calf.
The tone of this novel reflects a sense of moral condemnation
rather than an ideological anti-capitalist stand, just as the anti-
colonialism of Burmese Days is indistinguishably bound up with
moral comment. In discussing Keep the Aspidistra Flying,
however, critics of Orwell's works hasten to point out another facet
of the novelits pacifism. Gordon Comstock, its main hero, is
haunted by visions of a future war which, prophetically, he sees as
being waged principally in the sky. The year is 1935, not so long
before Guernica, the Stuka dive-bombers of the blitzkrieg in France
and the bombing raids of the Battle of Britain.
Shortly after he had finished Keep the Aspidistra Flying, in
January 1936, his publisher, Gollancz, commissioned Orwell to
write a book about the condition of the unemployed in the north
of England. Orwell set off immediately for the north where he was
to remain for two months, living with militant trade unionists and
visiting cotton mills and coal-mines. He carried out a journalistic,
on-the-spot enquiry worthy of a specialist in economic and social
problems which he was not which was to form the basis of a
book published the following year entitled The Road to Wigan
Pier, Wigan being an industrial centre particularly hard hit by
unemployment and short-time working.
Wigan Pier was not just a straight reporting assignment. In its
way it is typical of Orwell's literary style in which fiction is mixed
with autobiographical detail and with descriptions from real life.
What is more, the book contains a number of comments which
betray Orwell as being still tributary to a middle-class conception
of society and of revolution.
5
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
At that time, the Left in England consisted of the Labour Party,
with its various tendencies, the (orthodox) Communist Party and
the Independent Labour Party (ILP), a group whose ideological
identity is difficult to define but which brought together socialist
humanists as well as communists opposed to the doctrines of the
Third International.
Orwell, who was closer to the ILP, described himself as a "Tory
anarchist", a contradiction in terms which can be seen as reflecting
the personal ambiguities of someone whom the experiences of life
and certain personal fantasies had pushed towards socialist
theories. Nevertheless there remained within him the man of the
past who placed great trust in the middle-classes whose leader he
aimed to be in the coming revolution. This contrasted with the
Marxist-Leninists who saw in the Proletariat and its "dictatorship"
the only dynamic, historic revolutionary force. Orwell, who saw
himself as an out-and-out revolutionary, was not a populist, and
even less a plebeian. At times his writing hints at a certain distance
from the common people, who "smell".
But by then it was 1936 and Orwell was seriously concerned
about the threat from nazism and fascism which some elements of
the Left tended to under-estimate and shrug off as merely
epiphenomena. Eric Blair decided to take part in the war in Spain.
dozen of the other" and that this kind of war could end, even in
England, only in a fascist solution.
A new novel, Coming up for Air, appeared between Homage to
Catalonia and his two last works which were to make of him an
author of world stature. It is a nostalgic book. Times past are gone
for ever and unrelenting pessimism is the keynote of the present
pessimism which no belief in the future can fully assuage.
Something died forever in the world at the same time that George
Bowling (the hero of Coming up for Air) said goodbye to his
youth the tranquillity of old England threatened with a political
and warlike Apocalypse.
At that period Orwell seems to have turned to out-and-out
pacifism; the "democracies" such as France and England, with
their colonial empires and millions of men held in subjection and
exploited in shameful fashion, appeared to be in no moral position
to take a stand against the nazi and fascist dictatorships. He saw no
other way out of the existing situation than the creation of a party
of the masses whose aims and actions would be fired by a common
determination to oppose both war and imperialism. But all this he
himself seems to have seen as nothing more than a pious hope, and
the signature of the German/Soviet pact convinced him that the
war had already begun. At this point Orwell discovered in himself
"In the early 20th century the vision of a
future society unbelievably rich, leisured,
orderly and efficient a glittering an¬
tiseptic world of glass and steel and
snow-white concrete was part of the
consciousness of nearly every literate
person." (George Orwell in Nineteen
Eighty-Four). Right, 4D Time Lock:
Modified 4D Twin Tower Office Building,
A-1-13, 1927. Mimeo drawing by
Buckminster Fuller.
This work and that reproduced on page 5 were part of the ex¬
hibition Dreams and Nightmares: Utopian Visions in Modem
Art ax the Hirshhorn Museum and Sculpture Garden, Smith¬
sonian Institution, Washington, D.C.
Photo © Buckminster Fuller
He turned once again to his friends.of the ILP and finally ended up
in Barcelona, in the ranks of the POUM (Partido Obrero de
Unificación Marxista, the United Marxist Workers' Party).
Unlike a number of other intellectuals, Eric Blair did not go to
Spain as a humanist, literary tourist. He went to the front line as
an officer of a POUM centuria, or battalion, complete with car¬
tridge belt and an old model 1889 Mauser. On 20 May 1937, a Fran-
coist bullet struck him in the throat.
Nursed back to healthhe nevertheless had some difficulty in
speaking for the rest of his life he returned to England. He had
thrown himself wholeheartedly into this war which for him was a
war of humanist socialism against totalitarianism. This Spanish ex¬
perience seems to have finally convinced George Orwell the writer
of the "singleness of the adversary": totalitarianism whether of
Party or of State. He was to publish an account of his Spanish ex¬
perience in Homage to Catalonia in which the theme of "revolution
above all" seemed to predominate; the impending conflict with
nazi Germany confirmed him in the idea that a war between
capitalism and fascism would be a case of "six of one and half a
6
a sense of patriotism, somewhat resigned, perhaps, but un-
shakeable. Whatever her faults old England had to be defended
against Hitlerism and, without abandoning his revolutionary
theories, he decided to work as effectively as he could for the war
effort.
His ill health he was suffering from tuberculosis prevented
him from serving in the army. He worked for the BBC on broad¬
casts to India, joined the Home Guard and wrote The Lion and the
Unicorn, a book in which he praised patriotism and criticized those
intellectuals (one of whom he had been himself) who declared their
disdain for national values, while insisting that the war must be a
people's war accompanied by a radical change in society based on
a liberal, collectivist socialism which, nevertheless, must not be
dominated by the State. It must be an English socialism which
would suppress neither the monarchy nor traditional culture and
customs and would respect the nation's past.
He contributed to Left wing magazines such as Tribune and
Horizon and, in November 1943, he began work on Animal Farm,
which he was to finish at the end of the following February.
This work brought Orwell the international fame that Nineteen
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Eighty-Four would confirm. The subject matter is well known.
Revolt is brewing amongst the animals at Mr. Jones's ManorFarm.
But once freed from their human masters, the animals find
themselves in the same condition of servitude as before the revolt,
some of their own kind having replaced their former masters. The
slogan that inspired their revolt, "All animals are equal", has
become "All animals are equal, but some are more equal than
others". Written at the height of the war, the book was refused by
several publishers. When it finally appeared in August 1945, it met
with immediate success.
Already, while he was completing Animal Farm Orwell had in
mind another book which he was to finish in 1948 whilst seriously
ill and which was to be published in June of the following year,
some seven months before his death on 21 January 1950.
The year is 1984. (Let it be said in passing that this date has no
particular significance, being merely the date of the year in which
the book was completed with the last two figures transposed). The
world is divided between three superpowers Oceania, Eurasia and
Eastasia. The action takes place in England which has become an
integral part of Oceania. The country, completely State-controlled,
is dominated by the figure of a single man, Big Brother, supported
by the Inner Party which in turn is backed up by the Outer Party
tellectual manipulation of people through Newspeak, a language
specially designed to eliminate all contestation, indeed all nuances
of thought, while imposing the official "truth", however subject to
change this may be, in a manner that defies logical or factual con¬
tradiction. "The earth is the centre of the universe. The sun and the
stars go round it", O'Brien tells Winston; and, holding up the
fingers of his left hand with the thumb concealed, "There are five
fingers there. Do you see five fingers?"
Orwell examines the question of why and how a regime such as
that of Oceania can exist and last. It is because the men who control
it are interested only in power, power for its own sake, devoid of
any other purpose such as comfort, happiness, liberty, rationality
or ideology. This is a form of oligarchic totalitarianism which is
based on a sort of institutionalized schizophrenia, the single State
for which the exterior, objective world does not exist.
Certain of the themes of Animal Farm are echoed in Nineteen
Eighty-Four, but it is not a political novel. It is not a forecast of the
way in which a particular regime may develop; it is, as Orwell wrote
to his publisher, a parody of the "intellectual consequences of
totalitarianism", and, to some extent, this parodying aspect of the
book attenuates its pessimism. In the same way as we speak of
"black humour" we might describe it as "black burlesque". There
After the publication, in 1948, of his
book Nineteen Eighty-Four, George
Orwell wanted to make his position clear:
"I do not believe that the kind of society
I describe necessarily will arrive, but I
believe (allowing of course for the fact
that the book is a satire) that something
resembling it could arrive. I believe also
that totalitarian ideas have taken root in
the minds of intellectuals everywhere,
and I have tried to draw these ideas out
to their logical consequences. The scene
of the book is laid in Britain in order to em¬
phasize that the English-speaking races
are not innately better than anyone else
and that totalitarianism, if not fought
against, could triumph anywhere." Left,
view of London.
Photo Malcolm Pendrill © Parimage, Paris
machine. The hero, Winston Smith, is an employee at the Ministry
of Truth, an organization whose task it is to spread the official
"truth" of the day and to correct or to eradicate from the records
of past events, declarations, decisions and persons in contradiction
with the present policies of the State. Winston gets to know Julia,
a young woman who works for the Anti-Sex League. One day, by
means of various subterfuges, the young couple succeed in starting
an illicit liaison. Meanwhile Winston comes into contact with a
mysterious person in a position of considerable authority, O'Brien,
who reveals himself to Winston as being an opponent of the regime
and a supporter of Goldstein, the enemy number one and scapegoat
of the leaders of Oceania. Winston confides in O'Brien, but the lat¬
ter turns out to be an important member of the Inner Party, and
head of the Thought Police. Arrested and tortured both physically
and mentally, Winston ceases to oppose the Party, becoming en¬
tirely subject to its will, betrays Julia who in turn betrays him, and
is finally despatched to a minor post in an obscure section of the
Ministry of Truth.
The story line of 1984 is relatively weak. From the relationship
between Winston and O'Brien, however, there emerges a profound
study of every aspect of totalitarianism, not least of which is the in-
is nothing to laugh at about the picture of the world presented to
us in Nineteen Eighty-Four, but the prevailing feeling we have when
reading it is not one of terror. One can even see in it glimpses of
optimism.
"If there is hope, wrote Winston, it lies in the proles (proletariat)
(...) The future belonged to the proles. And could he be sure that
when their time came the world they constructed would not be just
as alien to him, Winston Smith, as the world of the Party? Yes,
because at least it would be a world of sanity. Where there is equali¬
ty there can be sanity. Sooner or later it would happen, strength
would change into consciousness. The proles were immortal (...)."
From this moment on, the lower upper middle-class socialist with
such fond respect for the old English ways, looked to the proletariat
as the liberating force, not without reservations, but with a mes¬
sianic intensity and a poetic power difficult to define and with all
the imprecise passion of the humanitarian, progressive outpourings
of the nineteenth century; thus, in evoking a possible future he
becomes a Utopian voice from the past. After all, we are only in
1984.
Jacques Charpier
7
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
From analysis to action
New trends in the psychological sciences
by Agnès Oppenheimer
PSYCHOLOGY, which at one time
was a branch of philosophy, has
always attempted to assert its in¬
dependence by establishing a particular
goal and a specific method of approach. Its
vocation has been to study the psyche of the
individual, along with his cognitive, emo¬
tional and behavioural processes, based on
the concept of man as an individual
represented by a biological, medical,
physical or metaphysical model.
Shortly before the turn of the century,
Freud's discovery of unconscious processes
could have caused irreparable damage to
psychology, the scope of which was limited
to the sphere of consciousness. On the con¬
trary, this revised view of man gave
psychology a foundation and a new point of
departure. Similarly, developments in the
social sciences were to define this discipline
in terms of then recent advances in
sociology, linguistics, economics and other
areas.
To this day, no clear preference has been
expressed either for including
psychoanalysis as a part of general
psychology or for accepting that since
psychoanalysis is centred on unconscious
manifestations, it breaks away from the
point of view of classical psychology and
exists as an independent science. In the
United States psychoanalysis claims to be
the basis as well as an integral part of a
broader field of psychology, which itself is
concerned with pathology and health. In
France, it is most often looked upon as a
distinct field, not derived from any other.
Photo ©1983 ADAGP, Paris
"Psychology, which at one time was a branch of philosophy, has
always attempted to assert its independence by establishing a par¬
ticular goal and a specific method of approach. Its vocation has been
to study the psyche of the individual along with his cognitive, emo¬
tional and behavioural processes." Above, Exchange of Thoughts, oil
on canvas by the French artist Jean Dubuffet.
Psychology has itself split into several
fields of specialization: social psychology,
psychometry, clinical psychology (per¬
sonality tests), developmental psychology
and psychoanalytical psychology.
Psychoanalytical theories remain a major
point of reference in testing, pathology and
laboratory research, whether efforts are
made to apply them to other fields or to
refute them.
It is inappropriate to distinguish
psychological and psychoanalytical ap¬
proaches by referring to health and
pathology, as the borderline separating the
two is difficult to ascertain and should be
drawn with care. Some therapies are based
solely upon psychoanalysis, while others
are purely psychological; all refer to dif¬
ferent theories that must be taken into
account.
Historical perspective is an essential
feature herein, to the extent that it recreates
certain aspects of individual development
and forms an integral part of all
psychological parameters.
The definition of the unconscious is in¬
separable from the manner in which it was
discovered. Freud sought to cure symptoms
of hysteria using hypnosis. During patients'
trance states, he realized that their recalling
certain traumatic memories caused the
symptoms to disappear. He also noticed
that "abreaction", or gaining awareness of
a traumatic event to which emotion is at¬
tached, has a healing effect. Forgetting is
the cause of neurosis, in other words, un¬
conscious activity exists.
Little by little, Freud substituted free
association for hypnosis. He found that the
act of forgetting is motivated and that sub¬
jects tend to resist their memory. A fantasy,
a psychological phenomenon, comes to
replace the traumatic and pathogenic
memory. Unconscious desire is seen in its
different ramifications, hence the Oedipus
and castration complexes orient human
development.
Psychoanalytical treatment is intended to
recognize intrapsychical conflicts stemming
from the subject's unconscious., The
method consists of reserving judgment con¬
cerning the reality of the events mentioned.
The external factor is not denied, but its im¬
pact is measured in terms of the resonance
it finds in the individual. The individual
AGNES OPPENHEIMER, French psycho¬
analyst, is a lecturer at the University of Paris
VII. A member of the Psychoanalytical Society
of Paris, she is the author of Le Choix du Sexe
( 1 980) as well as many articles and studies on
psychology and psychoanalysis.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
recreates his conflicts during treatment and
the interpretation of this reaction through
transference enables the patient to become
conscious of his psychical determinism. The
analyst's attitude, therefore, must be
neutral when comprehending and judging
phenomena. His silence should be broken
only for as "objective" an interpretation as
possible, since the analyst is no more than
a receiver, a mirror reflecting back the un¬
conscious meanings of the patient's con¬
scious speech. As treatment progresses, the
task becomes more complex, and the
analyst must take into account the different
psychical processes he discovers.
Psychoanalysis does not deal with symp¬
toms, but with the unconscious of a given
subject as a whole whose psychical ap¬
paratus is composed of forces in conflict.
Psychoanalytical theory implies a par¬
ticular technique and attitude which stem
from a precise scientific model, that of the
sciences of nature and empiricism. The ex¬
ercise consists of discovering a cause, a
truth, basic desires, and of decoding an
original unconscious message that is ex¬
pressed in a distorted state, censored by the
conscious awareness. Admittedly, how¬
ever, psychological experiments that have
attempted to confirm these theories have
met with failure.
Over the past twenty years, interven-
tionism has returned to psychoanalysis and
is now a directing force in all therapies. This
^< n 1
^^^^^^^?ï/rrbi ^
"The individual is no longer considered as a decomposable structure, and thus the
understanding of the psyche becomes secondary and seemingly inefficacious. The in¬
dividual exists only in terms of the function he performs in communicating with others,
for everything is communication." Above, Deux Têtes (Two Heads), 1973, gouache
by the US artist Alexander Calder.
©
"The expansion of psychoanalysis and increased understanding of neuroses led to the
development of different, complementary models that offer an insight into other
aspects of pathology, including narcissism and identity." Above, Metamorphosis of
Narcissus, 1 937, by the Spanish artist Salvador Dalí during his surrealist period, clearly
draws its inspiration from psychoanalysis. Freudian theory had a profound influence on
surrealism (dream interpretation, free association, automatism).
9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
^ change can be explained by various factors.
First, the activity of psychoanalysis,
which was limited to the comprehension
and treatment of neuroses, branched out to
cover other, more serious types of
pathologies. It then became necessary to
revise theoretical concepts and create new
technical features. For a new goal it became
necessary to have new explanations and
methods, and above all, a new outlook.
It appeared necessary to take into ac¬
count those early events that conditioned
the environment and gave rise to specific
problems. An individual cannot become
neurotic unless the first years of his life were
free from serious traumas, thus allowing
for the development of a stable psychical
organization. In other cases, it is impossible
for the individual to comprehend himself
with respect to internal conflicts which
could not have taken shape. In the latter in¬
stance, the structure is too deficient.
Moreover, social changes influence the
course of mental pathology, both in form
and definition.
The expansion of psychoanalysis and in¬
creased understanding of neuroses led to
the development of different, complement¬
ary models that offer an insight into other
aspects of pathology, including narcissism
and identity. A more complex clinical ap¬
proach and a modified therapeutic view¬
point are associated with increased
theoretical knowledge.
Admitting the importance of reality in
psychical processes leads to taking into ac¬
count interpersonal relationships during
both infancy and treatment. Observation of
babies supports this discovery.
Parallel to this, there is an
epistemological change. It becomes clear
that the observer influences the observation
and neutrality is a myth. Thus silence is a
form of intervention and the analyst ceases
to be a neutral receiver, since his personality
is just as important as his capacity to em¬
pathize with his patient. The moment un¬
conscious reality reaches the surface, it can
no longer be considered as data, but rather
as a simple version of facts or a point of
view.
From a psychological standpoint, dif¬
ferent models either complement or negate
each other. Aside from basic treatment,
analysis has extended its activities to
borderline and narcissistic cases. In addi¬
tion, psychoanalytical-type therapies are
currently used to treat psychotic subjects.
Research into rapid techniques con¬
tinues. Psychoanalytical psychodramas
allow the individual to act out and exter¬
nalize his conflicts. Psychoanalytical relax¬
ation takes the body into consideration and
is appropriate for subjects who experience
difficulty in verbalizing their emotions.
Psychoanalytical perspective aside,
various therapies are appearing, some of
which focus on abreaction. One example is
the primal scream, the cry of the newborn
infant, which induces regression into past
experience, enabling patients to integrate
this experience. Whether used individually
or in groups, the "new therapies" are based
on the concept of living one's emotional ex¬
periences, coming into contact with one's
body.
10
The multiplicity of therapies answers a
need for change, rapidity, and often
economy. They are based on a certain re¬
jection of psychoanalysis as well as on the
idea that the unconscious cannot be directly
taken into account; thus, mere understand¬
ing is no longer adequate, and the import¬
ant factor is to live.
The coexistence of psychoanalytical and
psychological therapies is accompanied by a
reciprocal influence, unless deeper-lying
changes create a certain diversity. Reality,
pathology and clinical medicine are now
plural concepts. Treatment is no longer
considered a theatre of pure re-enactment
but offers the possibility of living a new
experience.
Over twenty years ago, a new theory
came into being, accompanied by a
therapeutic method which alone could well
become a branch of psychology. Founded
on mathematical discoveries and the theory
Developed in 1921 by the
Swiss psychiatrist Hermann
Rorschach, the Rorschach Test
is a projective method of
psychological testing in which
the testée is asked to describe
what he sees in a series of ten
symmetrical ink-blots. From
the replies received the tester
attempts to establish a broad
picture of the testee's per¬
sonality typewhether, for ex¬
ample, he or she is basically in¬
trovert or extrovert. Below, a
test in progress.
Photo Inge Morath © Magnum, Paris
of systems, it focuses on communication,
the relationships and laws governing the
functioning of families as systems.
The individual is no longer considered as
a decomposable structure, and thus the
understanding of the psyche becomes
secondary and seemingly inefficacious. The
individual exists only in terms of the func¬
tion he performs in communicating with
others, for everything is communication.
"Sickness" does not exist per se. It is the
effect of pathological communication
whose most extreme manifestation is what
has been termed the "double constraint", a
contradictory order one subject gives
another, placing the latter in a position
whereby his choice is impeded. Based on
that premise, there is no such thing as a
disturbed individual; only the system is ail¬
ing, seeking balance through the most
pathological means open to it. The answer
is thus to treat a system. This technique may
be applied to an individual, but he must
always be regarded as part of a system.
The notion of intrapsychical conflict is
absent from this approach, which is centred
on interaction and interpersonal relations.
It is useless to understand, because
understanding does not elicit change, and it
is precisely change that is important. This
method is active, entailing suggestion and
order. It highlights the pathological aspect
of communication that must be modified,
and it is based on psychology without
psychism.
Recent developments in psychology have
led to a division into psychologies or
psychological disciplines. This is due as
much to epistemological changes as it is to
economic and social changes and
ideological influences.
Looking from within the different
psychologies, it is the interaction between
theory and clinical practice that induces
methodological changes, the goal of every
therapy being to effect change. There are
differences in the methods employed both
to cause change and to enable change to oc¬
cur. Interventionism still applies, even
when it takes the form of non-intervention.
However, the active techniques that pro¬
mote change (catharsis, systemic therapies,
etc.) differ from psychoanalytical tech¬
nique, which seeks to make change possi¬
ble, to free the subject from his bonds
without conditioning him in any way
whatsoever.
From a psychoanalytical standpoint,
distinctions are drawn in terms of a given
pathology, making it possible to obtain in¬
dications for treatment, but they are also
drawn with respect to the different
theoretical models that give rise to different
types of intervention.
Some models focus on conflict, others on
certain aspects of pathology, others still on
the development of the personality.
It is possible to discern a trend towards an
integration of the various theories, each of
which represents one aspect of the human
being. All of them are distorted representa¬
tions of phenomena they refract, and which
otherwise would never have come into con¬
scious existence.
Agnès Oppenheimer
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Psychology
in Black Africa
by Amewusika Kwadzo Thy
ANY attempt to define the current
situation of psychology in Black
Africa depends on what is meant
by psychology modern (or Western)
psychology, or traditional African
psychology.
While the former enjoys full scientific
and administrative recognition in many
Black African countries, the latter still has
to assert its existence as a body of
knowledge and practice which can be tested
by the scientific method of hypothesis, ex¬
perimental verification and proof. The
mistrust and sometimes mutual rejection
which prevail between these two kinds of
psychology seriously limit the possibilities
of a form of official collaboration between
them which could lead to a veritable
synthesis.
Modern psychology in Black Africa can
be evaluated in two ways. It can be con¬
sidered as a science with universal validity,
in which case its level in Black Africa is the
same as that which is found throughout the
world. On the other hand, if it is held that
modern psychology can only be truly scien¬
tific in a specific historical and cultural con¬
text, its evaluation entails an assessment of
the evolution it has undergone in its new set¬
ting by being either receptive or closed to
methodological changes and to models
previously elaborated and tested elsewhere.
We take it that modern psychology in¬
cludes the major currents of Western
psychology which lay claim to be scientific
by virtue of their biological, physiological
and/or psychic foundations. It thus cor¬
responds to the ancient physic of the mind
as opposed to the philosophy of the soul,
and englobes psychiatry, psychological
testing, experimental' psychology, which is
often associated with educational psycho¬
logy, social psychology, psychotherapy and
psychoanalysis. Of these major branches,
with their many ramifications and theoret¬
ical trends, only educational psychology
and psychiatry have been trying, in the last
four decades, to take root in Africa. Since
1960, the year when many countries achiev¬
ed political independence, modern ^
AMEWUSIKA KWADZO TAY, Togolese
sociologist, is on the editorial staff of the
French language magazine Présence Africaine
and a member of the staff of the Société Afri¬
caine de Culture, Paris. Formerly assistant
director of the Education Planning Service of
Togo, he is the author of many studies and ar¬
ticles on education and culture in Africa.
"Modern psychology in Black
Africa can be evaluated In two
ways. It can be considered as a
science with universal validity,
in which case its level in Black
Africa is that which is found
throughout the world. On the
other hand, if it is held that
modern psychology can only be
truly scientific in a specific
historical and cultural context,
its evaluation entails an assess¬
ment of the evolution it has
undergone in its new setting by
being either receptive or closed
to conceptual and methodolo¬
gical changes and to models
previously elaborated and
tested elsewhere." Right,
Chieftain's chair from the Lun-
da region of Angola.
Photo © Musée de l'Homme, Paris
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
psychology has been taught virtually
everywhere in Africa, generally in faculties
of human sciences.
Psychiatry, however, is usually con¬
sidered as a medical discipline and is often
taught in faculties of medicine. This dif¬
ference in status, due to the fact that it is
taken seriously by the authorities, is cer¬
tainly one of the reasons why its develop¬
ment has been more remarkable than that
of other branches. The Universities of
Dakar (Senegal) and Ibadan (Nigeria) are
among those which have a world-wide in¬
fluence in this field. Journals, books, inter¬
national meetings and a range of document¬
ary information promote the exchange of
ideas and experience between specialists
and institutions in Africa and those in other
continents. According to the University of
Dakar periodical Psychopathologie Afri¬
caine, 448 articles were devoted to
psychiatry in Black Africa between 1965
and 1979, 200 of them appearing in this
same journal. During the same period 274
works, the proceedings of 70 meetings, and
68 miscellaneous documents were also
published. Although few Africans are in¬
volved in these exchanges of information,
their participation is remarkable in view of
the fact that modern psychology is a recent
import to Africa; it did not reach Black
Africa until 1940.
Nevertheless, it must be admitted that in
psychiatry alone, the human and material
capacities available are far from meeting
the needs of the sub-continent: in some
countries there is only one psychiatrist for
over 500,000 head of population. This
situation is aggravated by certain trends
and characteristics which are peculiar to
modern psychology in Africa, and which
are themselves a result of the cultural and
historical context in which psychology
began to take shape in Greek Antiquity.
The term psychology, or discourse on the
psyche, derives from the Greek notion of
the soul. In Homer, the word soul (in Greek
anemos, breath) had a twofold significance,
englobing on the one hand thumos, mind,
will, passion, that which characterizes the
individual personality; and on the other
psyche, life, the animal inspiration which
gives life to all bodies. From the fifth cen¬
tury BC until the Christian era, this dual
conception of man was worked out more
fully and rationalized within philosophical
and religious doctrines which underlay the
idea of immortality and the divinity of the
psyche.
These doctrines included reincarnation
and the imperative of autoperfection of the
psyche. The individual person was respon¬
sible for achieving this perfection and con¬
sequently for his fate in life and after death.
The precept "know thyself", which was in¬
scribed on the temple at Delphi, is a good
expression of the Greek belief that the hap¬
piness of the individual is based on
knowledge of his-psyche and of his duty to
it.
These Greek ideas on the psyche persisted '
until the nineteenth century when they were
exposed to the test of reason supported by
science, which had triumphed in almost all
fields of knowledge. Psychology was
criticized on the grounds that it was based
on scholastic reasoning which did not stand
up to scientific experimentation. Thus it
was classified as a magical practice because
12
of the bad reputation it had acquired during .
history.
In the Western perspective, that of the
Greek and Judaeo-Christian psyche, the
"madman" is someone inhabited by a
defective soul, which is dangerous because
it can corrupt other souls. Deprived of a
healthy spirit, he ceases to be a person and
thus loses the right to speech. Disconnected
from his culture, he has nothing to com¬
municate. He is dead but responsible for his
state. He must be destroyed, often by fire,
an element as subtle as the soul. For cen¬
turies mental alienation and disagreement
with the established order were confused in
the name of religious and political in¬
tolerance, and heretics, outlaws, and
madmen were transported to distant islands
or interned in asylums in the remote
countryside.
In the nineteenth century Western
psychology reacted against this bad image
and the criticisms of science by diversifying .
itself in a search for scientific foundations.
But in spite of the progress it has made in
this direction, psychology is still considered
as a science of secondary importance, ex¬
cept in the Soviet Union and the United
States. When modern psychology took root
in Black Africa there was a strong concern
that its scientific status should be preserved.
Hence the ambiguities of its attitudes to
African psychology: rejection of it at the
theoretical level, coexistence with it in cer¬
tain universities, and in some cases i col¬
laboration with it in the practical sphere.
While anyone practically concerned ¡with
the question cannot fail to realize that an
authentic African psychology really exists,
in the current state of research and publica¬
tions (numerous though they are) it is im¬
possible to define it in simple, general and
universally acceptable terms. In any case
such is not my intention in this article.
The question of the nature of African
psychology is part of the vaster problem of
the rehabilitation of African negro culture.
For example, the existence of African
psychology as a scientific theory is closely
connected to that of African philosophy,
which is the source of continuing debate
among African philosophers. Nor is it
possible, within the limits of this article, to
give a general assessment of the state of
African psychology in all its aspects.
Accordingly, we have restricted our
reflections to African psychiatry which, by
virtue of its presence and role in the con¬
tinent seems sufficiently representative of
African psychology. If it is accepted that
there is a connexion between mental health
or alienation and the individual personality,
and that psychiatry cannot be effective
unless it is part of a specific geographical
setting, a specific human history, and a
specific culture, then African psychiatry
cannot be understood without reference to .
a specifically African culture and
, personality.
The work of anthropologists,
Africanists, and men of culture both from
Africa and from other continents supports
the idea of the cultural unity of Black
Africa. The basic features of the African
personality exist within this fundamental
unity, which is often masked by physical or
linguistic diversity or by differences in
customs. Since the publication of La
This hand-bell (42.5 cm), carved
from an elephant tusk and known
as a lonflin, is one of the in¬
struments used by priests of Fa, a
traditional divinatory technique in
countries of the Gulf of Guinea.
Photo © Musée de l'Homme, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
In traditional African societies,
the soothsayer has a status
similar to that of the
physician both are consulted
at critical moments in the lives
of individuals or of social
groups. In his own way the
soothsayer fulfils a broad
therapeutic function. Fa (a
word in the language of the Fon
people; Ifa in Yoruba) is a tradi¬
tional divinatory technique of
the countries of the Gulf of
Guinea. In Dahomey (present-
day Benin) the Bokonon or Fa
priest (right) was consulted
before any important decision
was taken. In our photo, taken
in 1 930, the Bokonon is holding
ritual palm-nuts in his left hand,
whilst in front of him are spread
other divinatory accessories in¬
cluding a fatè, a tray symboliz¬
ing space, on which a powder is
sprinkled and in which the
soothsayer/priest draws Fa
signs with his finger-tips.
Photo © Musée de l'Homme, Paris
Philosophie Bantoue by Placide Tempels in
1 945 , the concept of the African personality
as developed by African philosophers ap¬
pears (according to Ibrahima Sow) to con¬
sist of four elements: the body (the corporal
envelope); the biological principle (internal
organs, automatic and psychosomatic
systems); the life principle; and the spirit as
such, the substance of immortality.
This conception of the personality is
situated in a dynamic psychological field
which is defined by three main axes of rela¬
tionships; the personality is at the meeting
point of these axes. There is a vertical axis
which brings the individual into relation
with his founding Ancestor, with God and
with the other invisible Existents; a
horizontal axis, or axis of social order,
which brings him into relation with the
cultural community; and the existential
axis, the axis of the person or the axis of
biolineal existence. (Dr. Ibrahima Sow,
Psychiatrie Dynamique Africaine). The
balance of the personality and thus of its
mental health depend on the balance of this
psychological universe. The coherence of
the whole is maintained, at each level, by
origin-myths, creation-myths, or founder-
myths, as well as by reason, which indicate
the conditions of individual and collective
human experience.
This conception of the personality
defines the individual neither as a Leibnitz-
ian monad (unity) nor, as certain an¬
thropologists would have it, as a tribal sub- 1
Psychotherapy was practised m
Africa by the Egyptians and long
predated the Greek, Roman and
Hebrew tradition in which much of
modern Western psychology is
rooted. Imhotep (right), chief
minister, astrologer and physician
to king Djoser (c. 2686-2613 BC),
who has been described as "the
first figure of a physician to stand
out clearly from the mists of anti¬
quity", practised psychotherapy
with such skill that he was ele¬
vated to the rank of a deity to
whom temples were erected at
Memphis and on the island of
Philae.
Photo © Archives Photographiques, Paris
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
without liberty. Each personality is
unique, while also remaining an expression
of the totality of the main cultural deter¬
minants. This means that there is the
possibility for a psychology of individual
differences in the modern sense, just as
there is everywhere else.
Ibrahima Sow has also written that "the
cause and effect of mental disturbance meet
in that which either affects the vertical
dimension of the Being, its relationship
with the Ancestor or with God, and thus
shatters the person's fundamental identity,
or in that which affects the horizontal
dimension of existential experience and
provokes misfortune. (...) The disturbance
can never simply be an isolated and
restricted inner debate, because the African
conception of relationship is a total and
dynamic one". According to specialists, the
ideas of personal sin and guilt are virtually
non-existent in African madness. The
persecution-depression theme, on the other
hand, is more common, conforming as it
does to the .anthropological structure
described above. The pathogenic agent,
which is always outside the sick person, is
either a wicked person, or an invisible
force, or the founding Ancestor.
Among the various methods used to seek
the deep-lying causes of the sickness are in
tuitive or deductive divination such as Fa,
which is extensively practised in the coun¬
tries on the Gulf of Guinea. An investiga¬
tion is carried out into the sick person and
all the suspect networks of relationships.
The treatment prescribed by the
geomancer, who in addition to his other
qualities possesses that of a subtle
psychologist, takes many forms, incor¬
porating the use of plant drugs, trance,
possession, prayer, incantation, sacrifice,
ritual and propitiatory offerings, and a
temporary change of community (although
the patient is never separated from people
he knows). Constantly cared for by his
family and his community, the "madman"
does not need to be exiled unless his condi¬
tion is so serious that it constitutes a real
physical danger for those around him. Only
if it is can he be temporarily deprived of
freedom of movement.
Thus although African psychiatry has
not yet been expressed in a body of theory,
it cannot be identified, as those who believe
in an extreme form of scientism would
maintain, with magic, savagery or ig¬
norance, and consequently condemned to
disappear or become a "folklore"
psychology. In the urban environment
where mental disturbance develops, the
families of the sick seek the concomitant aid
of both modern and traditional psychiatry,
and the latter often turns out to be more ef¬
fective than tranquillizers which do not
always bring about a definitive cure. This is
one reason why in some countries
specialists and authorities are showing an
increasing interest in collaboration between
modern psychology and African
psychology.
This approach seems particularly
necessary today because there can be no
doubt that, unlike the other sciences, even
those branches of psychology which have
won the most scientific recognition, such as
psychiatry or social psychology, cannot be
exported "tailor made". If it is to be effect¬
ive for a given people it must be developed
from within that people's culture. But it
should also be stressed that the develop¬
ment of African psychology cannot take
place in isolation. Collaboration will be
necessary with all the human and social
sciences, above all with philosophy.
It is in this sense that current debate
about the conditions for the achievement of
cultural identity and about African
philosophy have a particular interest for all
those who believe that the overall qualities
and abilities of a people are in a sense a
reflection of those of each of the persons
comprising it.
Amewusika Kwadzo Tay
The Impact of Psychology on Third World Development was the theme of an international con¬
ference organized by Unesco and the International Union of Psychological Sciences and held in
Edinburgh, Scotland, from 24 to 28 July 1982. The conference was attended by specialists from
a wide range of countries, including Venezuela where, in 1979, a Ministry for the Development
of Intelligence was created. The Minister has described the development of intelligence as "ab¬
solutely necessary for the political, economic and social development of peoples". A national pro¬
gramme has been established consisting of 14 projects. One of these. Project Chess, which is
under the direction of a psychologist, aims to develop a "chess-oriented" way of thinking among
schoolchildren aged 7 to 9 and to study its possible transference to other areas. Below, a game
of chess in progress in a street in Caracas.
- *Ï-.!"J~ v -
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
"The need for a fundamental change in the nature of the relations between the industrialized and the non-
industrialized countries is becoming increasingly urgent. These relations are governed at present by an evolu¬
tionist, linear, diffusionist concept. Despite the obvious heterogeneity of our world, a 'massification' ideology
that is as tenacious as it is false would have us believe that every country and culture should behave in the same
way and pursue the same goals." Above, carved handle of a cane or sceptre belonging to the Oni, the spiritual
leader of the Yoruba people of Nigeria.
Anatomy of inequality
The economic crisis seen from the Third World
by Jean Sayinzoga
JEAN SAYINZOGA, of Rwanda, is an
economist, a member of the editorial staff of
the Geneva based magazine Genève-Afrique
and an associate of the Refugee Section of the
Protestant Social Centre of Geneva. A former
consultant to the United Nations Conference
on Trade and Development IUNCTAD), he is
the author of several articles and monographs
on the developing countries.
Adecline in the growth rate of
gross national product (GNP);
high unemployment; high infla¬
tion, chronically adverse foreign trade
balances and, in the case of the countries
of the southern hemisphere, an external
debt which is becoming dangerously
heavy such are the main indicators of
the economic crisis which currently af¬
flicts the market-economy countries.
It is a commonplace that economic
crises and the decline which they bring
iead to explosive social and political
situations. In some countries' today we
see sudden changes of Government,
reflecting a swing between two oppos¬
ing political trends a phenomenon
which some observers have dubbed "the
hen syndrome", thinking of the way a
hen transfixed by the headlights of an on¬
coming car tries to escape by crossing
the road first in one direction, then in the
other.
In order to analyse this economic crisis
which some describe as short-term but
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
1983 1984
(forecast)
3 % 3.5 % o
ri
n oil-producing c
o
1982 1983
en
a
>
2 to ri
1.5% 2.5%
rr
m
which others regard as structural, let us
examine these indicators more closely.
A comparison of GNP growth rates in
the industrialized countries (not including
the socialist countries of eastern Europe)
with those in the non oil-producing non-
industrialized countries reveals the
following situation:
Industrialized countries:
-year 1982
- average
growth rate 1.5 %
Non-industrialized, no
countries:
-year 1981
- average
growth rate 2.5 %
In the latter category of countries, the
rate of growth of GNP declined by 6 per
cent between 1960 and 1970 and by 5
per cent between 1 970 and 1 980. Even
assuming that an attempt to catch up is
desirable, Irrespective of the conditions
in which it takes place, it is clear from the
above figures that such an eventuality is
not feasible at the present time.
While the unemployment rate in the
non-industrialized countries is at a level
which may without any exaggeration be
described as catastrophic, it should not
be forgotten that in the industrialized
countries 5.5 per cent of the working
population were unemployed in 1972, 5
per cent in 1 979; 8 per cent in 1 98 1 , and
9 per cent around the end of 1 982. Since
this unemployment exists in societies
where the individual is fully socialized,
that is, responsibility is taken for him
from birth to death by the capitalist
economy so far as employment is con¬
cerned and by the State so far as services
(education, health, etc.) are concerned,
the gravity of the situation can be fully
gauged.
Although inflation continues to be ram¬
pant in many countries of both North and
South, some industrialized countries
nevertheless seem to be bringing it under
control. The inflation rate in these coun¬
tries has been brought down from 7 per
cent in 1982 to 5 per cent in 1983 and
the same figure is forecast for 1984.
A direct result of this lower inflation
rate could be a drop in interest rates and
therefore an alleviation of the financial
burden for countries which are saddled
with the enormous external debt which
they contracted with public and private
bodies in the industrialized countries of
the North.
While the average rate of inflation in
the oil-producing countries was 13 per
cent in 1 980 and 1 981 and 1 0 per cent
. in 1982, ¡t reached the record figure of
30 per cent in 1982 for the third con¬
secutive year in the non-industrialized,
non oil-producing countries, mainly
because of the rise in the price of fuel.
The cumulative foreign trade deficit of
the non-industrialized non oil-exporting
countries was 87 thousand million US
dollars in 1982. The figure at present
16
©
Work in progress on a weir which forms part of a project for the improvement of the
surface water irrigation system at Wadi Zabid, Yemen Arab Republic. The project,
financed with the help of a 1 0.9 million dollar credit from the International Development
Association (IDA), was completed in 1979 and covers some 17,000 hectares.
forecast for 1983 and 1984 is between
67 and 68 thousand million dollars.
In this respect, the situation of the oil-
producing countries is worse because it
seems to be in constant decline. After a
surplus of 1 1 4 thousand million dollars in
1980, which was completely wiped out
in 1 982, a cumulative deficit of 27 thou¬
sand million is forecast for the end of
1983. One of the reasons for this situa
tion is a drop of 14 per cent in the price
of oil in 1982 and of 6 per cent in the
volume of sales.
The growth rate of the external debt,
.which was 10 per cent ¡n 1982 (still
higher than that of exports) is half as high
as during the 1 975-1 981 period, but this
is only a slight glimmer of hope.
The fact is that the cost alone of ser¬
vicing this debt as a proportion of export
Export earnings of developing countries,
1965 and 1980
Nonfactor
services
(percent)
J Manufactures
J Agriculture
] Fuels
Metals
1965
$44 billionb
1980
$498 billion"
a. Excluding gold
b. Current prices.
Developing countries can
no longer be caricatured
as exporters of primary
products and importers
of manufactures. Some
have even become
significant exporters of
capital goods, account¬
ing in all for about 6 per
cent of the world total.
These changes, how¬
ever, should not obscure
the fact that for many
developing countries,
particularly the poorest,
primary products still
dominate their exports or
that many countries are
dependent on a single
export commodity.
Source: World Bank, Washington, D.C
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
revenues was 1 5 per cent in 1 976-1 977,
20 per cent in 1981 and 24 per cent in
1982. In other words, the situation is
getting worse.
The two camps, namely, the in¬
dustrialized and the non-industrialized
countries, may tax each other indefinite¬
ly with responsibility for the present
situation without either side being entire¬
ly in the right or in the wrong.
The industrialized countries can
criticize the countries of the South for
not having shown sufficient
perseverance and determination in their
political and economic struggles. This
shortcoming has made it easier for the
North to dominate the South and has led
to the present impasse. But since the
days when many Third World countries
achieved independence, the centres of
responsibility have moved from London,
Paris, Lisbon, etc. to Dakar, Kigali,
Caracas, Bangkok, and so on.
For their part, the countries of the
South can always point to the continuing
deterioration in terms of trade, which is
making them progressively poorer and
the industrialized countries ever richer.
Similarly, they can protest against the
corrupt application of aid programmes
which at present impoverish the
receivers both materially and
psychologically by developing an
"assisted person" complex in them and
making them bear the burden of heavy
financial commitments.
From this three major conclusions
emerge: the gap between the in¬
dustrialized and the non-industrialized
countries is growing bigger every year;
all the remedies tried so far have failed;
the need for a fundamental change in the
nature of the relations between the in¬
dustrialized and the non-industrialized
countries is becoming . increasingly
urgent.
These relations are governed at pre¬
sent by an evolutionist, linear, diffu-
sionist concept. Despite the obvious
heterogeneity of our world, a "massif ¡ca¬
tion" ideology that is as tenacious as it is
false would have us believe that every
country and culture should behave in the
same way and pursue the same goals,
wherever on the earth's surface they
may be situated. This is the basic idea of
the theory of development, which
presupposes the existence of a model
society which supposedly possesses all
the saving virtues and to the level of
which the others must climb by the same
ways and means which it employed and
go through the same stages as. those
through which it passed. This model
society is supposed to embody the future
of all other societies. The vocabulary of
this ideology reflects this pattern of
events which is considered to be in¬
dispensable. Yesterday's "civilizing"
mission becomes today's "aid" mission.
Yesterday's "savage" becomes
"undeveloped", and in the minds of
those concerned the "colonized" com¬
plex is replaced by that of someone who
is "aided".
It is well known that in international
trade any product with a high
technological content enjoys a definite
advantage from the start, whereas the
A new super highway rakes
across the desert in Abu Dhabi,
United Arab Emirates. The con¬
struction of adequate networks
of roads and highways is a key
factor in the development pro¬
cess, but the burden of road
maintenance weighs heavily on
the developing countries (see
box below).
Photo Georg Gerster © Rapho, Paris
The costs of poor road maintenance
The worldwide road-building boom of the 1 960s and 1 970s threatens to
become the road-maintenance crisis of the 1980s and 1990s. Over the
past ten years, roads in many developing countries have been allowed to
deteriorate beyond the point where normal maintenance could be effec¬
tive. Traffic loading has been much heavier than intended, and mainte¬
nance has been widely neglected. Funds budgeted for highways have
been mostly absorbed in expanding rather than maintaining the network.
In a recent survey of twelve developing countries, more than 25 percent
of the tarred road network in eight of them required rehabilitation, streng¬
thening, or resealing.
To prevent further deterioration, maintenance budgets need to be
increased by at least 25 percent in three-quarters of the countries for
which recent studies are available; in more than half, the required
increase exceeds 75 percent. But more money is not the only answer.
Maintenance costs could be significantly reduced by improved efficiency.
For example, use of plant and equipment is often extremely low, some¬
times only a quarter or a third of the rates achieved by the best main¬
tenance organizations.
When road authorities are not able to afford maintenance work, the
costs passed on to road users are larger than the "savings" in public
expenditure. Over the life of a road, the total operating costs of vehicles
are typically four to ten times the costs of road construction and mainte¬
nance. Since operating costs may easily double on poorly maintained
roads, the economic loss is considerable. Moreover, in most countries
the extra costs chiefly involve spending foreign exchange on spare parts,
fuel, and replacing vehicles.
Source: World Development Report.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Irrigation design
and management
Public and private investments in irriga¬
tion in developing countries have increa¬
sed dramatically over the past twenty
years, reaching about $15 billion in 1980.
But the returns are much below their
potential: one recent estimate for South
and Southeast Asia suggested that an
additional 20 million tons of rice, enough
to provide the minimum food require¬
ments of 90 million people, could be pro¬
duced every year with inexpensive im¬
provements in water distribution.
A simple measure of the efficiency of an
irrigation system is how much water is lost
in distribution. Although losses of 25 per¬
cent are regarded as acceptable, they are
often much higher due to management
weaknesses in the operation of the
system.
Losses can often be reduced by rela¬
tively cheap improvements in irrigation
design. In Maharashtra, India, the public
distribution system traditionally consisted
of unlined canals serving forty-hectare
blocks. Where these have been replaced
by lined tertiary canals serving eight-
hectare blocks, water available at the field
has increased by 40 percent, and net
returns on the investment by some 160
percent.
Source: World Development Report 1983
im
mm
The World Food Programme IWFP) is supporting "food-for-work" projects in
Bangladesh employing up to two million workers. The aim of these projects is to reac¬
tivate some of the country's great waterways both to conserve water for irrigation and
to drain away flood water during the monsoon season. The projects include construc¬
tion of over 3,000 kilometres of embankments and the re-excavation of about 3,000
kilometres of canals. Workers are paid in wheat provided by the WFP. The work com¬
pleted so far has already resulted in a large increase in rice production.
producer of raw materials loses both in
the short and long term because in the
present state of economic relations his
commodities are undervalued and in
many cases are non-renewable. In any
case, even if raw material prices were
stabilized, not to say increased, the non-
industrialized countries which are rich in
raw materials would continue to be poor
unless the method of exploiting the latter
is changed. It should not be forgotten
that only from 1 5 to 35 per cent of the
capital invested, for instance, by an inter¬
national company remains in the host
country. The remainder goes into im¬
ported plant, capital depreciation, in¬
terest payments, the salaries of ex¬
patriate staff, transport costs, insurance,
etc. Ultimately, the raw material produc¬
ing country does not gain very much.
It is clear that, for better or worse, the
economies of both the non-industrialized
and the industrialized countries are
bound together, and that the growth of
each should benefit the others. Let us
take two examples.
It has been estimated that if, in order to
18
make up for the 1973-1974 oil price in¬
creases, the non-indus'trialized, non oil-
producing countries had reduced their
imports of manufactured goods, there
would have been 3 million more
unemployed in the member countries of
the Organization for Economic Co¬
operation and Development (OECD).
When asked to estimate the number of
job losses in their country between 1 970
and 1976 because of competition from
Third World countries, heads of major
French enterprises and senior officials
advanced figures that varied between
200,000 and 500,000. They were a long
way from the real figure which was in the
region of 25,000. It occurred to nobody
that, side by side with these lost jobs,
130,000 others were created through
exports of capital goods and consumer
goods. In fact, the growth of trade in in¬
dustrial goods between France and the
Third World from 1970 to 1976 led to a
net increase of 105,000 jobs.
The world is going through a crisis to
which every expert is trying to apply his
own diagnosis and his own treatment.
Each of the protagonists, the North and
the South, is praying for a change that is
slow in coming.
However, the critical situations of the
past and of today can still be a source of
profit. Paradoxical though it may seem,
certain financial bodies may be increas¬
ing their assets thanks to the (temporary)
insolvency of certain debtors, since
renegotiation of the repayment
schedules involves an addition of 2 per
cent on the initial interest rate.
It is therefore becoming imperative to
find alternative solutions to the present
development strategy. There has, of
course, been no shortage of catch
phrases, such as "basic needs", "self-
centred development", "collective
autonomy". But it is the entire concep¬
tion and orientation of the ideologies
underlying the idea of development
which must be thoroughly revised, both
by the North and by the South. It is no
longer permissible to rely on day-to-day
realism, which is often no more than a
lack of new ideas.
Jean Sayinzoga
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
In search of
new economic structures
by François Perroux
THE loose combination and ill-
determined succession of events
and situations which we term
general crisis, is, we feel, inexplicable
in terms of traditional concepts.
In the 1960s the major Western
economy and certain others were at
grips with a certain fall in productivity
and perturbed by a growing perception
of the formidable nature of Japanese
competition.
These circumstances, accompanied
by other internal and external dif¬
ficulties, heralded the decision of
August 1971 which ended the gold
convertibility of the dollar and ag¬
gravated the damage caused by
floating exchange rates, amidst condi¬
tions which were highly inimical to this
policy and dangerous for the medium-
sized and small nations. The United
FRANÇOIS PERROUX, French economist,
is emeritus professor of the Collège de France,
a corresponding member of the British
Academy, an honorary member of the
American Economic Association and founder
of the Institut de Sciences Mathématiques et
Economiques Appliquées. The latest of his
many books has recently been published in
English by Unesco and Croom Helm Ltd.,
under the title A New Concept of Develop¬
ment (see inside back cover).
States and the industrialized market-
economy countries experienced per¬
sistent, high, and increasing
unemployment, very high inflation, ex¬
orbitant international liquidity and a
slowdown in the growth of their gross
national product (GNP). Towards the
end of the 1970s inflation began to
slacken off; this had a moderating ef¬
fect on prices but did not reduce
unemployment or provoke an upturn in
the growth of GNP.
After enjoying two decades of pros¬
perity (1945-1968), combined growth
and development, the industrialized
market-economy countries went on to
experience fifteen years (1968-1983)
of slow and in some cases negative
growth punctuated by hard shocks due
to rises in the price of oil (1973 and
1979) and to cessation of debt
repayments at the end of the 1970s.
The observable trends of the crisis
we are experiencing today may be
hypothetically envisaged in terms of,
the content and effects of the two
motors of contemporary change: in¬
dustry and finance, industrialization
and financing.
Industry is a structure and has a
structuring power. It is simply a com
bination of fixed assets and trading
capital coupled with teams of human
agents organized hierarchically. By vir¬
tue of its two facets as an apparatus of
things and as an organization of per¬
sons, it is a continuing phenomenon.
The sciences and technologies that it
incorporates endow it with a relative
superiority over the rest of the
economy, above all over agriculture,
which it can carry along in its wake
and, to" a certain extent, shape. It
wields this influence through its
capacity to bring down prices, to
widen flows, and through the informa¬
tion it disseminates. The industrial ap¬
paratus is a motor of, and currently the
major centre of, innovation. Industry is
concentrated and consists largely of
oligopolies and groups.
Finance is understood here as a
mass of financial capital, of debts fall¬
ing due at different periods, which are
in the power of a small number of
public or private decision-makers:
banks, financial intermediaries, public
centres of credit distribution. The nor¬
mal functioning of the economy
presupposes finance to launch the pro¬
ductive machine and keep it turning.
Credit launches and maintains the vast
industrial machine and its changing
Photo © 1983 ADAGP, Paris. Paul Klee Foundation, Museum of Fine Arts, Bern
"It is clear that true competition ceases to exist once a certain level of inequality between in¬
dividuals or between structured human groups such as nations has been passed." Engraving
by the Swiss artist Paul Klee (1879-1940) entitled Two men meet, each presuming the other
to be of higher rank.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
-<ïf-
*PW¡fa
--¡sp-.
Photo © Ed. van der Elsken, Netherlands
In November 1 982, Scott Walther, aged 48, one of the 1 1 million unemployed in the United States, set out from Bay City, Michigan,
with his handcart, on a five-month "walk for work" which was to take him over 3,000 kilometres to California.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
ORGANIZATION FOR ECONOMIC CO-OPERATION AND DEVELOPMENT
million THE EMPLOYMENT GAP, 1960-1982
360 r
350
*>
cPj
/
A Tr eU nemployed
^
A
K%
*"
A
340
330
320
310
300
290
280
270
260
0
1960
"The observable trends of the
crisis we are experiencing today
may be hypothetically envisaged
in terms of the content and effects
of the two motors of contem¬
porary change: industry and
finance, industrialization and
financing."
Photo Paolo Koch © Rapho, Paris
62 63 64 65 66 67 68 69 70 71 72 73 74 75 76 77 78 79 80 81 82
Source: O.E. CD., Paris
structure, as new industries stimulate
or replace the old. Finance, like produc¬
tion, is dominated by oligopolies.
Industry constitutes the major and
persistent inequality between the
developing countries, diverse though
they are, and those countries which
have long been developed. Here lies
the problem; it is here that reform
would be useful, if only the problem is
properly perceived and the structuring
power of industry is understood and
turned to the benefit of the
community.
The structures in the developing
countries, though they may differ from
one another in type and degree, have
all been imposed or strongly influenced
by those countries, for which
developed industry regularly produced
machines and arms. Emotional though
they often are, acts of rejection today
have a solid economic basis which pro¬
vokes these long-repressed revolts
which help fuel the world crisis.
There can be no justifiable balance of
supply and demand with a partner who
is compelled to squander his human
resources, who is ill equipped to
deploy investment or innovation in a
beneficial way, and who negotiates
from a position of lasting dependence.
The profound inequality of structures
creates forms of domination which are
just as unacceptable as the overt col¬
onialism of yesterday.
Furthermore, the balance of supply
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
and demand at world level is unat¬
tainable when a vast part of the world
cannot formulate a sustained and
growing demand nor obtain counter¬
parts in international trade freely and
normally. Insufficiency of effective de¬
mand, met by a nation's means of pro¬
duction, cannot be replaced over a
long period and overall by aid or tied
loans.
Finally, it is clear that true competi¬
tion ceases to exist once a certain level
of inequality between individuals or
between structured human groups
such as nations has been passed. In
small countries there is good reason to
wonder whether the highly intensive
competition is between countries or
between industries, some of which
choose to be based in countries
without making common cause with
the rest of its economy and its
population.
Flaws in the relationship between in¬
dustry and agriculture, between bran¬
ches of industry and branches of
agriculture, are at the heart of the
structural crisis of our time. By virtue
of their technical, organizational, infor¬
mational and financial superiority, in¬
dustries dominate agriculture and in a
sense take it over. In the industrialized
countries the success of the agro-food
industry suggests that this inequality is
being corrected, although there is still
room for improvement. But a trend
reversal which will restore to the
developing countries their capacity to
produce food to satisfy domestic de¬
mand, by reducing the emphasis on
export-directed agriculture or redirec¬
ting it, is a necessary task which is
bound to take a long time. It calls for a
restructuring which conflicts with the
immediate interests of the established
industries.
Perhaps the best economic basis for
a major readjustment in the relations
between industry and agriculture
would be through regional groupings of
nations rather than through individual
nations. The experience of Latin
America and West Africa has shown
that short-sighted and ill-considered
nationalism stands in the way of the
general welfare.
The countries of Western Europe
mark time as they try to hammer out a
common policy in which the stumbling
block is the relative importance of
agriculture in certain countries, in con¬
trast with the industries of their
neighbours, which have deliberately
sacrificed their agricultural activities.
Major joint undertakings, coproduc¬
tions and concerted exports bring
substantial opportunities for overcom¬
ing inequalities in the relationship bet¬
ween agriculture and industry. These
preliminary experiments ought to lead
to a joint effort to establish agro-
industrial areas where, through con¬
certed action, powerful plurinational
industrial groups would encourage
agriculture (whether backward or mak¬
ing technical progress) to produce
commodities for export to the less
developed countries of the East and to
African and Asian countries wanting
food products that have been process¬
ed to a greater or lesser degree.
An enlightened strategy should
dovetail with this trend. Such a
strategy will be preferable to a gran¬
diose programme of transfers and in¬
dustrial sharing whereby labour-
intensive industries would be allotted
to the developing countries and
capital:intensive industries based on
extensive scientific and technical
knowledge would remain in the in¬
dustrially developed countries. In spite
of the revolutionary trappings of such a
"Flaws in the relationship between industry and agriculture (...) are
at the heart of the structural crisis of our time. By virtue of their
technical, organizational, informational and financial superiority, in¬
dustries dominate agriculture and in a sense take it over. In the in¬
dustrialized countries the success of the agro-food industry suggests
that this inequality is being corrected, although there is still room for
improvement." Right, grain elevators on the Canadian prairies.
Above, a farmer tends his crop in Upper Volta. ,
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
programme, it seems to us to be
dangerously conservative. It tends to
create and maintain a kind of institu¬
tionalized preference which benefits
the industrialized countries. High-
technology and highly-capitalized in¬
dustries are most likely in the long run
to dominate labour-intensive in¬
dustries. This is certainly not the inten¬
tion of those who advocate such a
system, but the inequality of vast
groups, globally and doctrinally
specialized, may aggravate or
perpetuate domination by those who
possess industries based on the latest
technologies. In point of fact, the
developing countries are striving to
create, as far as their means permit,
complex industries. For the develop¬
ment of their national economies, they
are certainly right.
In addition to the advantages of in¬
ternal development, this option, if
followed successfully, provides an op¬
portunity to become competitive with
the industrially developed countries in
selected fields through inventive
specialization and by drawing benefit
from their relatively low wage-levels.
Certain developing countries have
received, as a result of outside invest
ment and the activities of the multi¬
nationals, a structure which does not
meet the fundamental needs and
aspirations of their people. A long-term
strategy would permit or encourage an
autochthonous industrialization which
would correct these deviations
without recourse to protectionism or
blinkered nationalism; it would restruc¬
ture them in accordance with the
wishes of those who are most closely
concerned.
Other developing countries have
been purely and simply colonized: their
policy of independence can only be
asserted by an industrialization
strategy which provides them with a
weight in international negotiations
which neither their new juridical status
nor the numbers of votes in interna¬
tional organizations could give them.
The current crisis springs from struc¬
tural inequalities; efforts to overcome
it call for new structures on a world
scale. Efforts in this direction go
beyond spontaneous market forces
and the intercompatibility of markets,
implying functional and regional
organizations and the search for an
overall organization which can ar¬
ticulate them with a view to economic
efficiency and social quality.
Finance too is structured. Except for
the specialized public institutions,
financial organisms are oligopolies. In
the United Kingdom there are the Big
Five; in France, the Big Three (formerly
the Big Seven). These monopolistic
enterprises engage in sharp competi¬
tion or form relatively stable
agreements with each other and in
relation to economic monopolies.
Within a given nation and at world
level, the money market evokes a
meeting of giants and makes nonsense
of the ¡mage of tiny units obediently
following the "neutral" law of prices
and interest.
With the exception of the oil-
producing countries, financial power is
in the hands of the industrialized coun¬
tries. It is exercised in the case of self-
financing, the incurring of debts to the
banking system and the issue of long-
term loans. Thus we should forget the
idea of a reservoir of money or quasi-
money responding obediently and in¬
evitably to undifferentiated market
demands. In this field too, the real
situation is that of Adam Smith's
"tacit coalition of masters"; it con¬
tinually exercises pressure on the
.<
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
behaviour of the Small, whether they
be businesses or nations.
In the commodity trade, the law of
compared anticipated costs product by
product, supplies a solution which is
correct in abstract terms. The trouble
is that here too the struggle between
monopolies and their groups is the
general rule, and it is practically im¬
possible to forecast future compared
costs. Those who hold financial power
are liable to make mistakes, the effects
of which are aggravated by the extent
of concentrated supply of and demand
for credit and by the spreading out over
a long period of commitments and
dates at which payments are due. As
the defects which occur at one point
are propagated through banking and
financial networks, which are highly
complex, always sensitive and
become nervous as soon as the first
signs of difficulty arise, the germs of
financial crises appear to be inherent in
developed and innovative industrial
systems. The importance of major
enterprises and nations leads to a call
to reason; their collapse would be a
disaster for everyone.
The instability of financial capital
and its last-minute rescue raise serious
questions.
When a developing country is
criticized for its over ambitious plans,
who is really being blamed? The coun¬
try itself as a whole, or the multina
tional companies and financial groups
which have established themselves in
it? The tax for economic recovery will
fall on all the citizens, but did their legal
representatives play an effective role
in taking the decisions which are
criticized?
On the other hand the disasters of
the financial crisis are avoided because
the money, the currency, and quasi
currency were available. Why and by
whose decision are they only brought
into play as a last resort? Would the
general interest not be better served by
prompt action? Is it politically desirable
to give the impression that finance on¬
ly comes out into the open when and
how it chooses?
Constant experience shows that to¬
day's changing financial situation is
largely in the hands of Central Banks
and Governments which decide on a
budget deficit. The economic brakes
which date from the end of the nine¬
teenth century have so far slackened
that they have lost most of their
effectiveness.
The cumulative effects are wide¬
spread. The key currency (by definition
it is always to some extent dominant),
today the dollar, reaches levels which
cannot be explained in terms of com¬
mercial exchanges, while its fluctua¬
tions are connected with speculative
capital movements sheltered by the
principle of non-intervention.
The excessively high interest rates in
the United States and the gloomy pro¬
cession of rates which follow in their
wake can only be explained in terms of
anticipations which are totally alien to
classical norms. When the community
expects an increase in money supply,
high interest rates may increase de¬
mand for bank finance instead of
reducing it.
The burden of indebtedness on
financial costs and the reduction of
gross anticipated profit margins
reduce the growth rate and, in the
worst cases, involve the liquidation of
assets. There is nothing mechanical or
automatic about these linkages, no
more than there is in debt repayment,
the positive effects of which may
herald an economically justified in¬
crease in product. But the resulting
contagious and cumulative difficulties
of payment may call for intervention by
the Central Bank and the Treasury.
The amount of distress caused by
these sequences of events varies
widely between the developing coun¬
tries and the developed countries. The
cyclical movements of the last century
showed that it is always the unprivileg¬
ed classes which bear the brunt of
recessions and contractions. Is it false
to extend such an observation to the
nations of the world?
François Perroux
"A trend reversal which will restore to the developing countries their capacity to produce food to satisfy domestic demand, by reduc¬
ing the emphasis on export-directed agriculture or redirecting it, is a necessary task which is bound to take a long time. It calls for.
a restructuring which conflicts with the immediate interests of the established industries," Peanuts ready for export, Kano, Nigeria.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Is crime
a universal concept?
by Henri Laborit
WHAT is culture? Is a "culti¬
vated" person more, or less like¬
ly, to become a criminal? Al¬
though any definition of a word limits, nar¬
rows and fossilizes its semantic content, I
would be inclined to define culture as the
sum total of the commonplaces, prejudices,
value judgments and conceptual auto¬
matisms to be found in a human group oc¬
cupying a particular place at a certain
period, and accumulated by experience in
the course of its history.
The fact is that a human group in a par¬
ticular geo-climatic area creates a set of
relationships between the individuals who
compose it, although it is unaware of the
many factors that enter into this creative
process. These relationships are achieved
through language and behaviour patterns
belonging to the group in question and
which in turn are conditioned by the geo-
climatic area in which they occur. These
relationships become institutionalized in
written laws, customs and concepts which
reflect automatisms that have been learned,
transmitted and reproduced from one
generation to the next.
A criminal is someone who transgresses
these laws. This amounts to saying that he
who is a criminal in one place will not
necessarily be one elsewhere. The criminal
is defined by the cultural code of behaviour.
In one place, the individual who expresses
opinions at variance with the State's
ideology is regarded as psychotic and
perverse and is locked up and treated with
drugs, whereas elsewhere the individual
whose behaviour does not conform to the
idea of property is regarded as delinquent
and perverse and is subjected to the same
kind of treatment. The only difference is in
the code and the scale of values.
Now, it is interesting to note that legally
the criminal is someone who attacks per¬
sons, but also goods, and that persons are
themselves generally regarded as goods or
private property.
HENRI LABORIT, French biologist and
essayist, is director of the Laboratoire
d'Eutonologie (the study of the overall
equilibrium of the human organism) at the
Boucicaut Hospital, Paris. Awarded the
American Public Health Association's Albert
Lasker prize for his contribution to research in
biology and chemotherapy, he is the editor of
the international magazine Aggressologie and
the author of some 20 books, some for the
specialist on basic research and others for a
wider lay audience, the latter including his
most recent work La Colombe Assassinée
(The Murdered Dove), 1983.
"Amongst animals (...) the dominating being no longer has occasion to be aggressive
and violent as long as his dominant status is not contested, because the dominated par¬
ties will have learned to their cost the rules of behaviour which must not be broken; they
will, as it were, have learned the 'culture' of the group or species. The hierarchies of
domination amongst men have been based on the same laws since the beginning of the
neolithic age." Above, head of an animal, probably a bear, from the lid of a clay vase
dating from the late Bronze Age in Hungary (2200-2100 BC). It was discovered near
Tiszafüred, in eastern Hungary.
The idea of property is never called into
question. It is accepted as forming part of
man's "essence", and this is done without
any attempts to ascertain its historical or
geographical origins or to consider what
mechanism in man's nervous system has
made it possible for the idea of property to
be given expression. And yet, certain
societies and "cultures" have never known
property and even today there are still a few
which are capable of ignoring it. It can be
proved by experiment that the idea of pro-^
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
perty is not innate or instinctive, but is
learnt. Indeed if it were instinctive, must
man not "control his instincts"? Perhaps,
but only if the latter are harmful to the iden¬
tity and cohesion of the group, in other
words if they do not conform to the code of
behaviour institutionalized by the domi¬
nant element.
It would take too long here to examine
the biological laws, complex but capable of
simplification, which regulate the activity
of a human nervous system in a social situa¬
tion. Suffice it to say that the sole function
of a nervous system is to permit action and
that, in man, thought only enables action to
be made more effective. A nervous system
thus permits an individual to control his liv¬
ing conditions in the space surrounding
him. If this space were empty, action would
be unnecessary. But it contains objects and
living beings, and an organism's contact
with these will be favourable or un¬
favourable to what may be called (with
great caution) the maintenance of its
biological "equilibrium". The sole raison
d'être of a being is to be, otherwise there
would be no beings. Therefore he learns
very quickly from experience that contact
with some of these objects and beings is
gratifying and that contact with others is
painful, dangerous and harmful to his well-
being. He will remember this experience
and will try to reproduce the gratifying ex¬
perience, whereas he will avoid disagreeable
experience or, if he cannot, will try to
destroy its cause. But if, within the same
space, another individual of the same
species who has himself had the same ex¬
perience wishes to enjoy the same objects
and the same beings, both of them will say
"they are mine" and a contest will take
place between them for the desired objects
or beings. Amongst animals, the stronger
one, or the one born of a dominant female,
will be more likely to assert his domination
and to seize the gratifying good.
The hierarchical scales of ascendancy will .
be established on this theme, which we have
presented in an extremely simplified form,
for it has many different modalities. The
dominating being will no longer have occa¬
sion to be aggressive and violent as long as
his dominant status is not contested,
because the dominated parties will have
learned to their cost the rules of behaviour
which must not be broken; they will have,
as it were, learned the "culture" of the
group or species.
"The concept of personal or group
ownership of gratifying goods,
which according to many
prehistorians arose about 6000
BC, was accompanied by the
emergence of criminality between
individuals and States, in other
words, war." Right, Cain Kills Abel
(1511), woodcut by Albrecht
Durer (1471-1538).
Photo © All Rights Reserved. National Gallery;
Melbourne
The hierarchies of domination amongst
men have been based on the same laws since
the beginning of the neolithic age, when
they settled on the land and agriculture and
animal husbandry enabled them to avoid
famine and, by laying up reserves of
beneficial goodsgrains and live
animals to have no further fears for their
immediate biological welfare. Then came
vocational specialization, and urban socie¬
ty, a more complex body than the primitive
clan, made its appearance. This transfor¬
mation took place over thousands of years
during which human groups that were
technically less developed but were compos¬
ed of hunters still skilled in the use of arms,
colonized these neolithic groups in order to
benefit from their technical advances.
The population growth resulting from
this "economic" evolution induced these
groups, which had become hierarchically
organized (chief, warriors, craftsmen,
farmers) to sally forth and conquer ter¬
ritories elsewhere which might increase
their resources. The concept of personal or
group ownership of gratifying goods, which
according to many prehistorians arose at
this stage of the history of man, i.e. about
6000 BC, was accompanied by the
emergence of criminality between in¬
dividuals and States, in other words, war.
Whenever the basic motivation is the im¬
mediate survival of the group in a hostile
environment, co-operation is more essential
than crime.
The human brain gave special features to
the creation of hierarchies and to the means
of establishing forms of domination.
Owing to certain associative cortical zones,
only the human species was capable of
associating previous experiences in an
original manner in an "imagined" context
and therefore of producing working
hypotheses and creating new forms by
transforming, first of all matter, then, more
recently, energy. Thus the species was able
to protect itself with ever greater efficacy
through a progressively better under¬
standing of the laws governing the in¬
animate world.
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Roger Viollet, Paris. Royal Library, Windsor
"The essential means of establishing relations of domination amongst peoples was the
discovery of the principal laws governing the inanimate world, which led to the produc¬
tion of greater quantities and varieties of marketable goods and of more efficient arms
to conquer new territories for exploitation." Above, drawing by Leonardo da Vinci
(1452-1519) of a cannon being mounted on a gun carriage in a foundry yard.
"From the very beginning
men were plunged into an in¬
comprehensible, fearful world
for which they had no rules of
action. They have made
remarkable efforts to in¬
troduce some form of
coherent order into it, which
have resulted in the discovery
of fire and of the atom." Left,
Homo nuclearis, cartoon by
Oak.
Drawing Oak © Encre Libre, Paris
Spoken language, followed by writing,
both of which also resulted from the
phylogenic evolution of this "imagining"
brain, enabled the generations to transmit
their experiences in time and to accumulate
them, very slowly at the outset, then in an
ever more rapid and sophisticated manner,
up to the point where our modern means of
communication shrink time and therefore
also space.
"Cultures" were established and evolved
at the same speed as that of technical pro¬
gress. It was the latter that enabled
marketable goods to be created which could
be exchanged with other human groups at
ever greater distances in space. The essen¬
tial means of establishing relations of
domination amongst peoples was the
discovery of the principal laws governing
the inanimate world, which led to the pro¬
duction of greater quantities and varieties
of marketable goods and of more efficient
arms to conquer new territories for
exploitation.
At the group level, the aristocratic power
of the warrior was replaced by that of the
bourgeois who controlled the means of pro¬
duction and trade, which in turn gave way
to that of the technocrat who invents pro¬
ductive machinery and of the bureaucrat
who manages production relations.
Thus the means may have changed, but
the objective remains the same the
establishment of dominant positions in
order to obtain beneficial goods, of which
the ideal image which the individual forms
of himself is not the least. Only in the
physical sciences has progress been achiev¬
ed. As far as the living world, especially the
world that lives within us, is concerned, we
have not evolved since the beginning of the
neolithic period. Biology, especially that of
our nervous system, which expresses itself
in our modes of behaviour, is only in its
infancy.
During all this time, men were speaking.
From the very beginning they were plunged
into an incomprehensible, fearful world,
for they had no rules of action. They have
made remarkable efforts to introduce some
form of coherent order into it. Convinced
that they were subjects apart in this world
because of what they called their "reflective
conscience" and their belief in their liberty,
in order to hide the anxiety caused by lack
of information and which frustrated effec¬
tive action, they had to invent the laws and
rules which dictate their actions. These were
the myths, religions, moralities and State
laws.
Henceforth, since they no longer had to
ask themselves what they should do, their
anxiety was partly hidden. Nevertheless it
continued to be a fundamental anxiety, not
for their liberty which existed only in their
imagination but which validated respon¬
sibility, but rather anxiety due to their ig¬
norance, especially when confronted with
death.
Thus "cultures", infinite in variety and
number, fulfilled only one function in their
attempts to become established in
languages to co-ordinate the actions of in¬
dividuals within a human group, in other
words, to give permanent form to the struc¬
ture of the group. We have already shown
how and why, since neolithic times, in the
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
world's temperate zones, this structure had
always been a hierarchical structure of
domination. Nevertheless language was a
splendid means of communication and
therefore a remarkable means of action. By
and through language we could influence
the action of others in favour of our gratify¬
ing projects. Through language, inhibitions
to action could be dealt with, the anxiety
resulting from such inhibitions could be
eliminated and a biological equilibrium
established. As a result, that aggressiveness
between individuals, which is the only
resort open to those who cannot make
themselves heard, diminished.
If therefore, as world statistics show,
criminality between individuals has declin¬
ed considerably in recent centuries, con¬
trary to whafthe mass media try to make us
believe, it is perhaps because literacy and
the use of language have become so
generalized that, as the French sociologist
Jean-Michel Bessette has been able to
demonstrate on the basis of reliable
statistics, crime is now confined to those
who are incapable of expressing themselves,
or who can only give inadequate expression
to what they have to say.
But, whereas language is a means of ac¬
tion for the individual, for the social group
it is most frequently a pretext for violence.
Logical discourse has always provided
"good" reasons to defend a "good" cause
by war, genocide and torture. Language has
always made it possible to justify raison
d'état. When we pass from the inter-
individual level of organization to that of
the State, the purpose of language changes.
Now this intangible abstract structure
called the State is merely the legalized in¬
stitutionalization of the hierarchical rela¬
tionships of domination between the in¬
dividuals who compose it. The individual
may not infringe certain pre-established
rules in order to commit a murder, whereas
the State has every right to kill, either within
the group in order to preserve the rules
establishing the hierarchies of domination,
or outside it, against another State trying to
establish its domination over it or over
which it seeks to establish its own
domination.
Thus it seems that it is not culture or
criminality and the relationships between
them that should be studied, but the finality
of the social groups and the central nervous
mechanisms which enable individuals to
establish relationships between each other,
the establishment of forms of domination
in terms of this finality.
Probably the readiness with which the
mass media report interindividual crimes is
merely a response to the needs of States to
have their own crimes forgotten and to
create a state of anxiety which thrusts the
"citizen" into their arms. These arms are
the army and the police which protect per¬
sons and property according to a set of rules
that form the distinguishing features of a
"culture". The latter is always the culture
of the dominant elements, that is to say of
those who submit to the finality of the
system because they benefit from it.
The immigrant problem is an example.
Whenever their labour is needed to produce
goods, because machines have not yet com¬
pletely replaced man in his most "ther¬
modynamic" activities, they are welcome.
But when machines are invented which can
perform these mechanical tasks and this
leads to increased unemployment, these im¬
migrants take away from the citizen the re¬
maining mechanical tasks. They deprive
him of the benefit of remunerated work.
They must be got rid of. The cultural shock
which is often invoked thus seems to be
secondary.
Are our immigrants more criminally in¬
clined than we, the "natives", are? They
would seem to have every reason to be so
their inability to make full use of the same
language and therefore to influence others
through it, the fact that it is impossible for
them to have an ideal image of themselves
which could vie with that of the natives even
when the latter are at the bottom of the
social ladder and the resultant subjection,
not to laws or to a "culture", but primarily
to a form of domination that is reflected in
the native's attitude of exclusion and con¬
tempt. In a period of economic crisis, the
immigrant becomes a scapegoatsome¬
body has to be found outside the social
group, "somebody else", who can be made
responsible for its misfortunes.
As far as the number of victims is con¬
cerned, there is no comparison between
casual crimes and road accidents. The latter
are regarded as normal and, as it were,
"healthy", because they are a result of
economic development. It is the former
which receive attention, because they
enable individual members of the group to
see themselves as belonging to a chosen race
or elite. By banishing the criminal into
outer darkness, they ensure the cohesion of
the group through the flattering image
which each member of it has of himself
because he belongs to the group. As the
French author Fernand Gregh wrote,
"There are no wicked, there are only those
who suffer".
The innumerable factors of suffering in
the case of the criminal can all be put down
to a single biological lawthe inhibition of
his gratifying action. We think we have pro¬
duced sufficient experimental proofs in re¬
cent years that this reality embraces the
whole of pathology including that of
behaviour. Violence amongst individuals is
the violence of those who are not heard,
whose voice is lost in the background noise
of the socio-culture, those for whom the
ultimate form of violence may be suicide,
which is tolerated by the social group
because its forces usually arrive too late to
prevent it and it does not compromise the
cohesion of the group. But to prove this
statement our study must begin with the
molecule and end at the level of the species.
In fact, every expert who has studied
violence and described its "causes" has
done so only at the level of organization
covered by his speciality. The politician, the
economist, the sociologist, the an¬
thropologist, the psychologist, the
psychiatrist, the philosopher and in more
recent times the ethologist, the
behaviourist, the neuro-physiologist and
the biochemist have all provided excellent
explanatory reasons in an outmoded system
of linear causality. It is high time for these
studies to be combined into a coherent
"system" according to inclusive and in¬
cluded levels of organization, which must
have regard to the essential instrument of
expression of violence, namely, the human
nervous system, and to what we already
know about its biochemical, anatomical
and functional structure wherever this
structure is placed in a social situation. We
must even take the history of our species in¬
to consideration in our efforts to under¬
stand the problem. We must also avoid any
facile solution based on innateness, on an
"essence" of man, on instincts which are
always available, depending on the ideology
which inspires the speaker (i.e. the express¬
ion of the unconscious automatized in a
"culture") to serve as an alibi for State
violence or as an excuse or condemnation of
individual violence.
But in our opinion it is essential not to
mix the levels of organization. Each level
has its own structure which should not be
superimposed by analogy on to the over¬
lying or underlying level. Above all, the
structural and functional links which con¬
nect them must be identified, care being
taken not to turn words into tangible ob¬
jects. One can touch one's father, one's
brother, one's friends, but one cannot
touch the family, the State, the mother
country, because they are not things but
abstract concepts which personify a
structure.
Now a structure consists of all the rela¬
tionships existing between the elements of a
whole, and a relationship cannot be touch¬
ed. It is neither matter nor energy, it is in¬
formation which is given a form. Thus, a
nation may be understood as a structure or
a set of relationships uniting the individuals
who live in a given geoclimatic space and
who in the course of time have invented a
"culture", that is a language and a form of
behaviour which are effective within this
space. But instead of allowing this
"regional" structure to decide for itself
what type of economic, political and
cultural relationships it wants to have with
the encompassing system (regional self-
sufficiency is no longer conceivable
nowadays) why inflict upon it the rules of
behaviour of the encompassing system, the
State which, as we have already said, is the
expression of a hierarchical structure of
aristocratic, theocratic, bourgeois,
technocratic or bureaucratic domination?
Why teach black children that their
ancestors were the Gauls when the Bretons
are being forbidden to use Breton?
It does seem that one must be profoundly
regionalist in order to be truly interna¬
tionalist and a citizen of the world, just as
one must be profoundly individualist in
order to admit that one's neighbour is
different.
Henri Laborit
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
"One day Van Gogh's art
will come back into its
own (...) blowing the
dust away from a world
in chains that his heart
could no longer bear",
wrote the French poet
Antonin Artaud. All Van
Gogh's works can be
seen as an individual's in¬
tense struggle against
the violence of a society
that rejected him, and his
suicide (1890) as a hor¬
rific escape from
solitude. The torment on
the face of the artist in
the self-portrait above,
painted in 1889, con¬
trasts starkly with the
serene countenance of
the 12th-century Japa¬
nese statue in wood
(below) of a Bodhisattva
(one destined to become
a buddha).
Photos taken from La nuit Appelle
l'Aurore, by René Huyghe and Ikeda
© Flammarion Paris
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Culture shock
and criminality
by Miguel Rojas Mix
HISTORY offers few better ex¬
amples of the link between ac¬
culturation and criminality than
the trial by Francisco Pizarro, the con¬
queror of Peru, of Atahualpa, the last
sovereign of the Incas. Atahualpa was
sentenced to death for the proven crimes of
idolatry, incest, polygamy and subversion.
He died without understanding what it was
all about. For him, his legitimate wife had
to be his sister, he was incapable of conceiv¬
ing that there could be superior gods to his
own and he had never heard of a higher
king against whom he could rebel. A change
in the terms of reference had transformed
what was normal or even pious and sacred
into a capital crime.
Atahualpa's condemnation symbolizes
what an encounter between two cultures
can lead to, and how criminality can emerge
from the conflict between them. At the
dawn of American history (as Westerners
would put it) acculturation was a massive
social process imposed by a colonialist
minority on an indigenous majority, and it
was started by outlawing the latter's
culture.
As a general rule, whenever acculturation
is at issue it is regarded as something that
affects only non-Westerners. The
Westerner brings his own culture along with
him and imposes it. Many people still find
it difficult to regard the excesses of col¬
onialism as crimes. For long, Western
violations of the rights of so-called
primitive societies (once I was corrected and
told that it was anachronistic to speak of the
"rights of primitive societies") were not
treated as crimes. The term used was
"civilizing process".
Since the eighteenth century, when Vico
and Herder put forward the idea of a
universal history led by progress, with
Europe at its head, the West has allowed
itself to break all the laws of the non-
Western peoples in the name of progress.
To consider this a crime would have seemed
as strange as to describe as a thief the ar¬
chaeologist who removed Aztec antiquities
to the great museums of the West. The
Third World has no "property", only
"treasures" and they were not "stolen" but
MIGUEL ROJAS MIX, Chilean art critic and
historian, is professor of the sociology of
literature and art at the University of Vincen-
nes, Paris. The founder and former director of
the Chilean Institute of Latin American Art, he
is the author of many books and studies in¬
cluding América Latina en el Arte Europeo
(Latín America in European Art), La Plaza
Mayor, Instrumento de Dominio Colonial (The
Main Square, an Instrument of Colonial
Domination) and a brief history of Latin
America for children.
"discovered". They were res nullius, they
belonged to no one.
Nowadays there are other massive ac¬
culturation processes which do not involve
the movement of colonists overseas but
take place in the metropolitan countries
themselves, in industrial centres oras is
more frequently the caseon the outskirts
.of the big cities of the West. These are the
acculturation processes of the immigrant.
Even now the term acculturation is still
understood to be a one-way process. Like
the notion of exoticism (1) it is not
reciprocal but denotes only that which is
strange to a Westerner. This disparity is still
maintained. In many Third World coun¬
tries acculturation of the European does
not arise because his status depends upon
his being European. The identities of
"bwana" or "sahib" are not
criminogenous and do not imply a deprecia¬
tion of a person's identity but rather its
enhancement. In Latin America there are
even compact European colonies, regular
enclaves in which not only is the mother
country's culture preserved but the writ of
an extra-territorial law runs.
Depending on the ability of the two
cultures to communicate, the cultural shock
will vary in violence and in the scope for
dialogue. In practice, cultural relations
seem to operate better at a distance, in the
form of occasional exchanges of exhibitions
and theatrical performances rather than in
the form of everyday dialogue in the ghettos
of great industrial cities. In France and the
Federal Republic of Germany, host coun¬
tries to large immigrant populations, the
cultural shock is less violent for a Spaniard
or Portuguese than for a North African and
greater for an immigrant of rural origin
than for one of urban middle-class
background.
In fact, acculturation presupposes the ex¬
istence of a dominant society and con¬
sequently a depreciation of the culture of
origin. This is accelerated by two sets of cir¬
cumstances which are frequently linked to
each other in the country of adoption,
namely, the processes of civic assimilation
and legal marginalization. Essentially the
civic assimilation process occurs in the
second generation through the education
system and life in the urban community.
Marginality results from a chronic feeling
of insecurity and uncertainty about the
future. It is certainly economic in character
but it is also largely legal, being associated
with such events as the renewal of residence
and work permits and especially with the
threat of expulsion.
The result of this depreciation of the
culture of origin, to which must be added in
many cases racial prejudice, incomprehen¬
sion, intolerance and, generally, all the dif-
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Charles Carrie, Paris
"Obstinate attachment to the culture of origin (...) is also
manifested in exile in the form of an exaggerated love of tradi¬
tional customs (...) religious ceremonies and celebrations."
Above, carnival time in Brixton, London, for immigrants from
Jamaica and Trinidad and Tobago.
The notion of the "right to be different" has little meaning
when "The Other" is looked upon merely as a source of labour
for the most unpleasant tasks and his customs and traditions
are rejected. Left, immigrant workers tarring a street in Paris.
Photo Rémi Berli © Rapho, Paris
ficulties of coexistence, is that cultural iden¬
tity becomes a matter of questioning in¬
stead of self-acceptance. The response to
this questioning will be either a search for
identity or flight from it.
The search for identity is often reflected
in an obstinate attachment to the culture of
origin, which is idealized, especially by the
second generation which did not know it in
situ. Material links with the homeland are
tenaciously maintained or renewed, houses
are bought in the native village and holidays
are spent there, the journey home being
made in a big car whose importance is less
as a means of transport than as a success
symbol with which to impress the folks at
home. This ritual is important because it
enables the emigrant to recover the esteem
of his former neighbours, even if it is only
in a remote, forgotten village.
This attachment is also manifested in
exile in the form of an exaggerated love" of
traditional customs. From time to time
religious ceremonies, celebrations, and
traditional dishes enable the immigrant,
like Antaeus, to recover his strength by
symbolically treading his native soil. This
form of behaviour, typical of the first
generation, contributes to deferring the
conflict of identity to their children and
even to their grandchildren. The identity
problem, which is faced by all adolescents,
is particularly acute for the young im¬
migrant, who has to assert himself both in
the host country and in his family group.
In their obstinate attachment to the coun¬
try of their birth, immigrants do not realize
that customs change rapidly and that they
themselves become cultural anachronisms,
isolated colonies perpetuating models that
v. are already obsolete.
By changing his social milieu the im¬
migrant loses the reference group in which
his identity was recognized, and even if he
does his best to behave in accordance with
the norms of the host country, his per¬
sonality is called into question because of
the culture difference. This is felt as an in¬
justice, leads to a sense. of insecurity and
may provoke reactions of various kinds in
the individual concerned. It may lead him
to seek a compromise and to assume a
chameleon-like identity. Typical of this is
the Muslim who observes Qur'anic rules at
home but eats pork and drinks wine with his
workmates in the canteen. On the other
hand it may cause him to become ag¬
gressive. But especially it may lead him into
a situation of fundamental uncertainty as
regards social models because he will
discover the lack of coherence between the
host culture and his own, and this may pro¬
duce in him an attitude of hostility to all
value systems. He then finds himself in a
situation of anomia (lawlessness) which
may transform him into an antisocial or
asocial person, not only in his adopted
country but also in his family's country of
origin.
Where it is conflictual or there is incom¬
patibility between two life styles and two
value systems, the cultural shock is of
relevance to the problem of criminality.
What is more natural in Mediterranean
cultures than to administer a couple of slaps
to a naughty youngster? In Sweden,
however, this is forbidden by law and what
is a purely family affair becomes a criminal
act. This apparently commonplace example
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
poses the question of the criminal inten¬
tions of the individual in a state of cultural
transition who commits an offence of this
kind.
Another, much more dramatic, example
concerns certain communities where the
father makes an attempt on the life of his
daughter because she has broken the rules
of premarital chastity. For the father the
essential matter is to purge the disgrace and
save the family's honour, an action which
courts in his society treat with considerable
leniency, whereas in the West it is an ex¬
tremely serious offence. Is the fact that the
offender was complying with the code of his
culture of origin taken into account? Is the
question asked what kind of behaviour
should be expected of the individual con¬
cerned? The problem is how to determine
precisely the degree of culpability of this
cultural nomad, who has not absorbed the
system of values of the host society.
On the other hand, where the criminality
of the immigrant is concerned it should be
pointed out that the acculturation problem
must be considered in conjunction with
other criminogenous circumstances which
affect society as a whole, such as social and
economic factors and the urban problem.
Many young offenders come from ghetto
communities. The formation of gangs leads
to early delinquency, often only occasional
but always dramatized and socially inaccep¬
table. It has also been established that ghet¬
tos favour recidivism. This group delin¬
quency offers a solution to the problem of
flight from identity. The ghetto enables a
second generation which feels completely
marginal to respond to the questioning
mentioned above by forming itself into a
cohesive minority.
Broadly speaking, criminality through
acculturation occurs only in two kinds of
circumstances where it is a product of two
systems of social images in which one of
them prohibits what the other permits or
even commands, and where it is a product
of cultural transition and the psychological
factors created by the latter. In any case it
must be observed that in spite of these addi¬
tional difficulties the incidence of criminali¬
ty does not seem to be significantly higher
amongst immigrants than amongst the
native population.
But does this exhaust the subject of
criminality through acculturation? Up to
now we have considered only the case of the
foreigner. But how should we classify
racialist crimes committed against im¬
migrant workers? Are they also attributable
to acculturation? At least they reflect a con-
flictual shock between two cultures.
Cultural dialogue between societies living
side by side, dialogue with minorities,
presupposes much more so than the
dialogue at a distance to which we referred
earlier a modification of social images,
not only on the«part of the minorities but on
that of society as a whole; otherwise
minorities will eventually become unaccep¬
table. There seems to be a tendency for
migrants to settle permanently in the host
country. This involves a fundamental
change in ideas about "the Other", about
one's neighbours, and more directly, a cam¬
paign against racialism, whether it be
ethnic, cultural or political.
It is difficult to explain criminality
32
"Whenever acculturation is at issue it is regarded as something
that affects only non-Westerners. The Westerner brings his
own culture along with him and imposes it (...) By culture is
meant a vision of the world which includes a system of values
and which finds expression in a way of life". Above,
automobile cemetery on the banks of the Choluteca River,
Tegucigalpa, Honduras.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
through acculturation otherwise than as the
result of the failure of a society to integrate
an exogenous group while at the same time
protecting the latter's right to its own iden¬
tity. Any integration policy raises a series of
questions which do not so much demand
answers as point to a number of certainties.
It is inconceivable, for instance, that young
people of the second generation of im¬
migrants should feel threatened by expul¬
sion to a country of origin they have never
known. Equally unacceptable is any action
aimed at imposing conformity on another's
culture in the name of ideals or slogans
which are completely alien to it, such as
feminism or ecology, however relevant
these movements may be in the host
country.
The fact is that only a culturally pluralist
society can provide an answer to these ques¬
tions, and only insofar as it eschews
dogmatic models. Cultural pluralism in the
sense of respect for regional and immigrant
cultures is something which the developed
world must preserve. External colonialism,
now a thing of the past, must not be replac¬
ed by colonialist policies towards
minorities. It is inadmissible that the sole
logic and reason of history should be
economic growth, which seeks higher
returns by uniformizing society.
But pluralism implies that ghettos, isola¬
tion and cultural enclaves must be avoided
too. To ensure this, minorities must par¬
ticipate on equal terms in the organization
of society as a whole. How can this be
achieved? Perhaps by recognizing their
political rights.
Apart from this, we should not overlook
the real or potential importance of the
growth of hybrid creative activities,
especially when they succeed in ridding
themselves of the clichés that are castrating
them. They are one kind of response from
those young people who are looking for
new models. In practice, these models
reflect the conflict between the big city and
the Third World, like that of the
Rastafarians (2) or their marginality, even
in the legal sense. The most popular musical
group founded by North Africans in France
is called "Carte de Séjour" (Residence
Permit).
This hybrid creative activity forms part
of the mental decolonization process, and
will become increasingly necessary as the in¬
habitants of the big cities of the West come
into ever closer contact with the Third
World, not by crossing the Ocean but in the
suburbs of their cities. It will be conducted
by the immigrant, not through servile ac¬
ceptance of the values of the host society
but by realizing that he is creating new
values with them. But it also implies aban¬
doning the illusion that the values of the
past can be preserved, and understanding
that the past can only be preserved as a fer¬
ment to develop the roots of a future
identity.
The West, for its part, will be able to ac¬
cept and contribute to this hybrid creativity
only when it abandons its paternalistic
universalism, retaining of it only that ele¬
ment which does not oppress the im¬
migrant; when it takes notice of the
deleterious effects of its culture; when it
ceases to deify itself and to treat as
backward those societies which are ex¬
periencing acculturation; and when it stops
killing Atahualpa merely because he is
Atahualpa.
Miguel Rojas Mix
(1) The Larousse "Lexis" dictionary of the French
language defines exoticism as "all the characteristics
which distinguish what is foreign from what appertains
to Western civilization". ,
(2) Rastafarians: members of a Jamaican religious and
political movement which takes its name from Ras
Tafari, as Emperor Halle Selassie was known before he
was crowned in 1930. (See Unesco Courier, December
1981).
"Mestizo (hybrid) creative activity forms part of the mental decolonization process." It will develop
not from servile acceptance of the values of the host society but from realization that from them new
values are being created. Below, a performance by Carte de Séjour (Residence Permit) a musical group
formed by north Africans resident in France.
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
G3 0 ffl
Unesco Prize for Peace
Education
The 1 983 Unesco Prize for Peace Educa¬
tion has been awarded to Pax Christi In¬
ternational which was founded in 1 945
by a small group of French and German
Catholics united by prayer and wishing to
pave the way for reconciliation between
their 2 peoples. Today, its horizons ex¬
tending to the far-reaching problems of
world peace, it is represented in 35 coun¬
tries on 5 continents. At a recent
ceremony held at Unesco HQ in Paris, the
Director-General, Mr. Amadou-Mahtar
M'Bow presented the prize to Mgr Bet-
tazzi, President of Pax Christi Interna¬
tional and Bishop of Ivrea (Italy), recalling
that the annual $60,000 award recogniz¬
ed outstanding activity to alert public opi¬
nion to the cause of peace.
Special notice
We ask our regular readers and
new subscribers to excuse any
possible delay in reception of the
Unesco Courier. Recent disrup¬
tions in the French postal services
have delayed reception of
subscription and subscription
renewal requests and have con¬
siderably increased routing times
of our last few issues.
International Fair Play Awards
Swedish tennis champion Mats Wilander
was recently awarded the international
Pierre de Coubertin Fair Play Trophy for
an act of sportsmanship at the 1982
French International Championships,
when he persuaded the umpire to order a
replay of the match point he had just
been awarded in the semi-final. At a
ceremony at Unesco HQ in Paris
diplomas of honour were also presented
to 4 other sportsmen: athlete Francisco
Julio Ardisson of Portugal, French foot¬
baller Patrick Battiston, Argentinian
pelote player Ricardo Bizozero, and
Hungarian skater Andrés Georgenyi.
Wilander, who was unable to attend the
Paris ceremony, had previously received
his trophy from the Director-General in
Stockholm.
Mr. Patrick Seddoh, of Ghana, has
been elected chairman of
Unesco's Executive Board for the
next two years. He succeeds Mr.
Victor Massuh, of Argentina.
School and the arts
Unesco's International Fund for the Pro¬
motion of Culture is giving its support to
a project for the integration of performing
arts theatre, fine arts, music and
dance in secondary schools. Proposed
by the Argentine-born/US composer
Julia Stilman, the project has the backing
of the International Society of Music
Educators, which is an affiliate of the In¬
ternational Music Council, the Interna¬
tional Association of Art, the Conseil In¬
ternational de la Danse and the Institut
International du Théâtre. This new form
of instruction would be adopted in
selected "pilot" schools for an initial
period of four years. Preparations are in
hand for a preliminary symposium, to be
attended by twenty-five international ex¬
perts, at which the new teaching formula
and its relationship with the cultural
heritage of each country will be examin¬
ed. The French composer Michel Fano
has said of Julia Stilman's musical works
that "marked by a remarkable manipula¬
tion of timbre, they carry the attentive
listener into a new and impassioned
realm of poetry." The US choreographer
Carolyn Carlson is to give a presentation
of Stilman's Barcarola, a cantata for
soloists, chorus and orchestra on a poem
by Pablo Neruda, at the music and dance
festival La Rochelle 84.
BOOKSHELF
Recent Unesco Publications
World List of Social Science
Periodicals. Details on over 3,500
periodicals published world-wide.
Prepared by the Unesco Social
Science Documentation Centre
with the co-operation of the Inter¬
national Committee for Social
Science Information and Docu¬
mentation. 6th edition revised.
1983,468 pp. (72 F).
Cultural Policy in the People's
Republic of China. Letting a hun¬
dred flowers blossom, by Bai Lu.
The latest publication in a series
showing how cultural policies are
planned and implemented in
various Unesco Member States.
1983, 100 pp. (35 F).
Elements of the Structure of
Agricultural Education in the
United States of America, by
David L. Howell er al. The latest in
a series of studies intended to pro¬
mote the dissemination and ex¬
change of information on struc¬
tures of agricultural education in
Unesco Member States. 1 983, 72
pp. (35 F).
Coal Utilization. The report on
an international Unesco forum held
in 1 982 to discuss the prospects
of technologies of coal utilization
from technical and socio¬
economic points of view. Special
attention was given to the prob¬
lems of coal utilization in develop¬
ing countries. 1 983, 1 34 pp. (40 F).
Recent Archaeological Disco¬
veries in the Republic of Korea, by
Kim Won-Yong. A survey of 1 1 im¬
portant excavations and disco¬
veries. Co-published with the Cen¬
tre for East Asian Cultural Studies,
Tokyo, which has exclusive sales
rights in Japan. 1983, (approx.
70 F).
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the
editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author's
name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on re¬
quest. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply
coupon covering postage. Signed articles express
the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the
editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier
staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform
(microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) University
Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100,
U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Microcard Edition. Indian Head.
Inc., 111 West 40th Street, New York, U.S.A.; (3)
Bell and Howell Co.. Old Mansfield Road, Wooster.
Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
French: Alain Lévêque (Paris)
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov (Paris)
Arabic: Sayed Osman (Paris)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: Mohammed Reza Berenji (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Kim U-Yearn (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salam)
Braille: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slo¬
vene: Vitomir Sudarski (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Alchis Angelou
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Special projects: Peggy Julien
All correspondence should be addressed to the
Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
François Perroux
new
conceptof
development
Basic tenets
Croom Hclm/Unesco
Just published
The concept of development brings out a
major paradox of our era: the desire for pro¬
gress and mistrust of its consequences. François
Perroux, a leading political economist whose
innovative thinking has made a major con¬
tribution to development studies, aims in this
work to analyse the ideas and theories pro¬
pounded by an economic approach to develop¬
ment and to clarify the meaning and direction
of current research.
Co-published with Croom Helm Ltd.,
London, who have exclusive sales,, rights in the
United Kingdom.
224 pages 100 French francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscription
rates in local currency, will be supplied on
request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 5SA Gipps Street, Colling-
wood Victoria 3066; Publications: Educational Supplies Pty.
Ltd. P.O. Box 33, Brookvale, 21 00, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie
Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 21 00, NSW.
Sub- agent: United Nations Association of Australia, P.O. Box
1 75, 5th floor. Ana House, 28 Elizabeth Street, Melbourne
Victoria 3000. AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co.,
Graben 31, A-1011, Vienna. - BAHAMAS. Nassau Sta¬
tioners Ltd., P.O. Box N-3138, Nassau. - BANGLADESH.
Bangladesh Books International Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K.
Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3. BARBADOS. University
of the West Indies Bookshop, Cave Hill Campus, P.O. Box 64,
Bridgetown. BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition
only: N.V. Handelmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18,
2 1 00 Deurne- Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco
publications agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1 060
Brussels, CCP 000-0070823-1 3. - BOTSWANA. Botswana
Book Centre, P.O. Box 91 , Gaborone. BURMA. Trade Cor¬
poration No. 9, 550-552 Merchant Street, Rangoon.
CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine
Street West. Montreal, Que. H3H 1M7. - CHAD. Librairie
Abssounout,.24 av. Charles de Gaulle, B.P. 388, N'Djamena.
CHINA. China National Publications Import and Export Cor¬
poration, P.O. Box 88, Beijing CYPRUS. "MAM", Ar¬
chbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L. Spalena 51 , Prague 1 (Per¬
manent display); Zahranicni literatura, 1 1 Soukenicka, Prague
1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers, Hurbanovo
nam. 6.893 31 Bratislava - CSSR. - DENMARK.
Munksgaard Export and Subscription Service, 35 Norre
Sogade, DK 1370, Copenhagen K. - EGYPT (ARAB
REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco Publications, No.
1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo. ETHIOPIA. National Agency
for Unesco. P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa. - FINLAND.
Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100 Helsinki
10; Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, Koivuvaarankuja 2, 01640
Vantaa 64. FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de
Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP. 12598-48. - GABON.
Librairie Hachette. B.P. 3923, Libreville. - GERMAN
DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710
Leipzig or from internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R.
- FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier (Ger¬
man, English, French and Spanish editions): Mr. H. Baum,
Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basartstrasse 57, D5300
Bonn 3. For other Unesco publications: Karger Verlag, Germer-
ing/München. For scientific maps only: Geo Center, Postfach
800830. Stuttgart 80. GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop
Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 1 95, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd.,
P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana, Ac¬
cra; The University Bookshop of Cape Coast; The University
Bookshop of Legón, P.O. Box 1 , Legón. - GREAT BRITAIN.
See United Kingdom. HONG KONG. Federal Publications
(HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial Mansion, 1 2 Yip Fat Street,
Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon.
Hong Kong Government Information Services, Publication
Centre, Baskerville House, 22 Ice Street. HUNGARY.
Akademiai Könyvesbolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V.
Konyvtürosok Boltja, Népkoztársaság utja 1 6, Budapest VI.
ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co., H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9,
Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2;
5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh, Hyderabad 500001 (API; 80/1 Mahat¬
ma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001. Sub-Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery
Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House, New
Delhi; Publication Unit, Ministry of Education and Culture, Ex.
AFO Hutments, Dr. Rajendra Prasad Road, New Delhi 1 1 000 1 .
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl.
Oto Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl Dr Sam
Ratulangie 37, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing
and Distribution Co., 28, Vessal Sftirazi Street, Enghélab
Avenue. P.O. Box 31 4/1 486, Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for
Unesco. Seyed Jamal Eddin Assad Abadi Avenue 64th Street,
Bonyad Building P.O. Box 1533, Teheran. IRAQ. McKen¬
zies Bookshop, AI Rashid Street, Baghdad. IRELAND. The
Educational Company of Ireland Ltd, Ballymount Road,
Walklnsfown, Dublin 12; Tycooly International Publ. Ltd 6
Crofton- Terrace, Dun Laoghaire Co., Dublin. ISRAEL.
A.B.C Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel
Aviv 61000. ITALY. Licosa (Librería Commissionaria San-
soni, S.p.A.) Via Lamarmora 45. Casella Postale 552, 501 21
Florence. JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O.
Box 366, 1 01 Water Lane, Kingston. University of the West In¬
dies Bookshop, Mona, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book
Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo 3-chome Bunkyo-ku Tokyo 113.
KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O. Box 30571,
Nairobi. KOREA. Korean. National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. - KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait; for the Unesco
Courier; Farafalla Press Agency, P.O. Box SAFA 4541,
Kuwait. LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod.
Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERÍA. Code and Yancy
Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia. - LIBYA. Agency
for Development of Publication & Distribution, P.O. Box
34-35. Tripoli. -~ LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22,
Grande-Rue, Luxembourg. MALAWI. Malawi Book Ser¬
vice, Head Office, P.O. Box 30044 Chichiri, Blantyre 3.
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Cooperative Bookshop,
Kuala Lumpur 22-11. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic
Street, Valletta. - MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd.. 30.
Bourbon Street, Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30
bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. NEPAL. Sajha Prakashan
Polchowk, Kathmandu. NETHERLANDS. For periodicals
only: D&N -Faxon B.V., P.O. Box 1 97, 1000 AD Amsterdam;
for publications only: KEESING BOEKEN B. V., Postbus 1118,
1000 BC Amsterdam. - NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van
Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A.
NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, Govern¬
ment Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland;
130, Oxford Terrace. P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch; Alma
Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1 1 04,
Dunedin, Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington.
NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The University
Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka; The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zaria. NORWAY. All publications:
Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43,
Oslo 1 ; Universitets Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, P.O.B.
307 Blindem, Oslo 3. For Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narvesens
Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6. - PAKISTAN. Mirza
Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O. Box No. 729,
Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern Book Co., 926 Rizal
Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. - POLAND. Orpan-
Import, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars Polona-Ruch,
Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068 WARSAW. - POR¬
TUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo
70, Lisbon. - SEYCHELLES. National Bookshop, P.O. Box
48, Mahé; New Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131,
Mahé. SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and
Sierra Leone Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (SI Pie Ltd. Times
Jurong, 2 Jurong Port Road, Singapore 2261. SOMALI
DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and
General, P>0. Box 951 , Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA. For
the Unesco'Courier (single copies) only: Central News agency,
P.O.Box 1033, Johannesburg. - SRI LANKA. Lake House
Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B.
244 Colombo 2. - SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box
1118, Khartoum. - SWEDEN. All publications A/B.C.E.
Fritzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel, Regeringsgatan 1 2, Box 1 6356.
10327 Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN
Forbundet, Skolgrand 2, Box 1 50 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm.
- SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag. 5
Rämistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211,
Geneva 1 1 , CCP. 1 2-236. Librairies Payot also in Lausanne,
Basle, Berne, Vevey, Montreux, Neuchâtel and Zurich.
TANZANIA. Dares Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-
Salaam. - THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42
Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402;
Bangkok: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue,
Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road,
Bangkok. - TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. National Commis¬
sion for Unesco, 1 8 Alexandra Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I.
- TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S., Istiklâl Caddesi, N° 469,
Posta Kutusu 219. Beyoglu, Istambul. - UGANDA. Uganda
Bookshop, P.O. Box 71 45, Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM.
H.M. Stationery Office, H.M. S.O., P.O. Box 276, London,
SW8 5DT, and Govt. Bookshops in London. Edinburgh,
Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol; for scientific maps
only: McCarta Ltd., 122 King's Cross Road, London WC 1X9
DS. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, 205 East 42nd Street,
New York, N.Y. 10017. Orders for books & Periodicals: Box
433, Murray Hill Station, New York, N.Y. 1 01 57. - U.S.S.R.
Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Moscow, G-200
YOUGOSLAVIA. Mladost. Mica 30/11, Zagreb; Cankarjeva
Zalozba, Zopitarjeva 2, Lubljana; Nolit, Terazije 27/11,
Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National Educational Distribution Co.
of Zambia Ltd.. P.O. Box 2664 Lusaka. - ZIMBABWE.
Textbook Sales IPVT) Ltd.. 67 Union Avenue, Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
A PORTENT
FOR
THE FUTURE
The Unesco
General Conference
jeg
\ f r'- * r *
HIS Conference opened in a climate
which reflects the doubts and tensions of
, the world today. It closes in a victory for
the spirit of tolerance and mutual understanding."
These words from the closing address of Unesco
Director-General Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow. sum
up the flavour of the 22nd Session of the Unesco
General Conference, held in Paris from 25 Oct¬
ober to 26 November 1983.
During the early stages of the Conference, some
Member States expressed reservations about the
proposed budget for the two years 1984-1985.
Agreement was finally reached on an increase in
real terms of 4 per cent. There was general overall
support for the draft programmes for the
Organization for the next two years. The Con¬
ference stressed the interdependence and intersec-
toral character of the programmes adopted, the
most important underlying themes of which were:
The role of culture in development; The impor¬
tance of the drive for literacy; The increasing role
of informatics and modern technologies and the
Organization's scientific programmes: The
organic links between human rights and the rights
of peoples; The importance of education for peace.
Altogether 2, 126 delegates, representatives and
observers attended the Conference. Among them
were 1,751 delegates from 157 Member States {in¬
cluding 114 Government Ministers), represen¬
tatives of an Associate Member of Unesco, of the
Holy See, of 4 liberation movements, of 1 2 United
Nations Organizations, as well as observers from
35 intergovernmental organizations and 131 inter¬
national non-governmental organizations.
The Conference was honoured by the visits of
four Heads of State, the President of the French
Republic François Mitterrand, the President of the
Republic of Cape Verde His Excellency Arístides
María Pereira, the Prime Minister of the Com¬
monwealth of Dominica the Honourable Mary
Eugenia Charles, and His Majesty King Juan
Carlos of Spain, as well as of His Royal Highness
Prince Hassan of Jordan. Photo shows Unesco
Director-General Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow ad¬
dressing the final session of the General Con¬
ference. Seated on the dais listening to him can be
seen the Chairman of the General Conference Mr.
Said M. Tell, of Jordan, and the outgoing
Chairman of the Executive Board, Mr. Victor
Massuh, of Argentina.
]]>
</page>
</document>
