<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074683eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
V
I
I
I
the African past
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
i H
í^m SB
A time to live...
:,^'í- -i**
í
.rr.
Er" -M
TT ve
ir
"Those hands thatM'man Tine washed so fastidiously each evening, and even more meticulously
on Sunday mornings, seemed to have been fired, hammered against a rock, buried in the earth
and then uprooted with the soil sticking to them; dipped in dirty water, dried in the sun, and
cast with sacrilegious carelessness on the whiteness of that sheet, in the gloom of that hovel. "
These lines are taken from La Rue Cases-
Nègres (1950, "Black Shack Alley"), a
novel by the Martinique writer Joseph
Zobel which describes the struggle of the
agricultural workers of Martinique in the
1930s. A screen adaptation of this classic
work of Antillean literature has been made
and directed by Euzhan Palcy under the
title Rue Cases Nègres (1983). This still
from the film shows the two main
characters, José and his grandmother,
M man Tine.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The
Unesco Courier
A window open on the world
May 1984
37th year
Published in 27 languages
English Tamil Korean
French Hebrew Swahili
Spanish Persian Croato-Serb
Russian Dutch Macedonian
German Portuguese Serbo-Croat
Arabic Turkish Slovene
Japanese Urdu Chinese
Italian Catalan Bulgarian
Hindi Malaysian Greek
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French, Spanish
and Korean
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution
Offices:
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 58 French francs
2 years (valid only in France):
100 French francs
Binder for a year's issues: 46 FF
Editor-in-chief:
Edouard Glissant
Cover: A young inhabitant of modern
Jenné, a bustling town in the inland delta
region of present-day Mali, admires the re¬
mains of some miniature toy animals, made
of clay and dating from between 250 BC
and 300 AD, that were recovered from the
neighbouring site of Jenné-jeno (ancient
Jenné), west Africa's oldest city. (See
article page 12).
Photo Michael and Aubine Kirtley © ANA, Paris
ISSN 0041 - 5278
No. 5 - 1984 - OPI - 84-1 - 410 A
Editorial
MAN is an historical animal and
African man is no exception.
Just as everywhere else in the
world, he created his own history and his
own idea of it. Yet myth and prejudice of
every kind have left the world with a grossly
distorted view of African history, if not
with the impression that Africa has no
history at all.
After a long period of painstaking
research and meticulous preparation, the
record is now being put straight with the
publication of successive volumes of
Unesco's eight-volume General History of
Africa.
The General Conference of Unesco has
placed the preparation and drafting of the
History under the sole intellectual and
scientific responsibility of the 39-member
International Scientific Committee for the
Drafting of a General History of Africa,
two-thirds of whose members are Africans
and whose Secretary is Mr. Maurice Glélé.
Following the directives of the General
Conference of Unesco, the Committee, at
its first session, defined the principal
characteristics of the work in terms which
merit quotation at some length:
Although aiming at the highest possible
scientific level, the history will not seek to
be exhaustive and will be a work of syn¬
thesis avoiding dogmatism. In many
respects, it will be a statement ofproblems
showing the present state ofknowledge and
the main trends in research, and it will not
hesitate to show divergencies of doctrine
and opinion where these exist. In this way,
it will prepare the ground for future work.
Africa will be considered as a totality.
The aim will be to show the historical rela¬
tionships between the various parts of the
continent, too frequently subdivided in
works published to date. Africa's historical
connexions with the other continents
should receive due attention, these connex¬
ions being analysed in terms of mutual ex¬
changes and multilateral influences, bring¬
ing out, in its appropriate light, Africa's
contribution to the development of
mankind.
The General History ofAfrica will be, in
particular, a history of ideas and civiliza¬
tions, societies and institutions. It will in¬
troduce the values of oral tradition as well
as the multiple forms ofAfrican art.
The History will be viewed essentially
from the inside. Although a scholarly work,
it will also be, in large measure, a faithful
reflection of the way in which African
authors view their own civilization. While
prepared in an international framework
and drawing to thefull on the present stock
of scientific knowledge, it will also be a
vitally important element in the recognition
of the African cultural heritage. . .
Volume I, Methodology and African
Prehistory, and Volume II, Ancient
Civilizations of Africa, have already been
published (see the Unesco Courier, August-
September 1979). Volume IV, Africa from
the Twelfth to the Sixteenth Century, and
Volume VII, Africa under Colonial
Domination, are to be published this year.
In this issue of the Unesco Courier we
publish extracts from these two volumes.
The extracts from Volume IV throw new
light on the ancient civilizations of west and
southern Africa. Those from Volume VII
reveal the extent of the African resistance to
the colonial invaders, until now concealed
by what might almost be described as a con¬
spiracy of silence. Our readers will find
faithfully reflected in them the true face of
a great and hitherto largely misrepresented
continent Africa.
. Africa from the twelfth to
» the sixteenth century
4 Four centuries of growth and splendour
by Djibril Tamsir Niane
5 Ife-Benin: two kingdoms, one culture
by Alan Ryder
8 The secrets of Zimbabwe
by Brian Fagan
1 1 Trade links from Europe to Cathay
12 West Africa's oldest metropolis
Africa under foreign
domination, 1880-1935
14 The colonial challenge
by Albert Adu Boahen
1 7 The scramble for territory
by Godfrey N. Uzoigwe
23 An unequal combat
by Godfrey N. Uzoigwe
A continent resists
26 North Africa: the long struggle
by Abdallah Laroui
27 West Africa: the fight for survival
by M'Baye Gueye and Albert Adu
Boahen
30 East Africa: diplomacy and defiance
by Henry Mwanzi
32 The colonial heritage
by Albert Adu Boahen
2 A time to live...
Caribbean: Black Shack Alley
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
?rica from the
Terracotta head
(height 17.4 cm)
from Owo, a town
in southwest
Nigeria, is
modelled in
classical tie style.
It has been
suggested that
Owo art formed a
bridge between the
arts of the two
great centres of Ife
and Benin.
Photo taken from Nigeria, its
Archaeology and Early His¬
tory © Th. Shaw 1978.
National Museum of Lagos
Four centuries of growth
THE period from the twelfth to the
sixteenth century was a key period
in the historical evolution of Africa.
These four centuries saw the rise and
development in Africa of brilliant civiliza¬
tions. In the north and on the eastern
coasts of the continent, under the banner
of Islam, merchant cities sprang up which
made of Africa one of the major cross¬
roads of world trade. Huge caravans
crossed the Sahara linking the north with
the Sudan, the "Land of the Black
Peoples", and with the gold mines of
Ghana and Mali.
Commerce was at its most intense and
trade in goods of all kinds linked the
various regions of the continent. Ar¬
chaeology has today revealed that even
the equatorial forests were not an im¬
penetrable barrier to the circulation of
men, ideas, techniques, goods and food¬
stuffs.
Historians and researchers have long
attributed to Islam the birth and develop¬
ment of the continent's cities, kingdoms
and empires. But far from the Islamic zone
of influence, on the Atlantic coast and in
southern Africa, kingdoms and cities
arose that were just as advanced and well
organized as those of the Sudanese
region. Among them were the brilliant
by Djibril Tamsir Mane and splendour
civilizations of Ife and Benin which reach¬
ed their apogee from the twelfth to the
fourteenth century and whose statuary art
constituted a heritage of striking originali¬
ty. Thanks to archaeology, the civilization
of Zimbabwe, the ancient empire of
Monomotapa, is also gradually yielding
up its secrets. Today we know that perma¬
nent contacts between west Africa and
the Maghreb, Zimbabwe and the east
coast were maintained by pilgrims, travell¬
ing traders and commercial interchange.
Our knowledge of this important period in
African history is based on written
documents, oral tradition and, more and
more, the findings of archaeological
research.
On pages 5 to 11 we present extracts from
two chapters of Volume IV, Africa from
the Twelfth to the Sixteenth Century, of
Unesco 's General History of Africa, as well
as a glimpse of a third chapter which ex¬
amines the role of Africa in the intercon¬
tinental exchanges of the period. Professor
D. T. Mane is the general editor of volume
IV, the English edition of which is to be
published later this year in ajoint co-edition
between Unesco and Heinemann, London,
and University of California Press. (See in¬
side back cover).
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
twelfth to the sixteenth century
Ife-Benin:
two kingdoms, one culture
by Alan Ryder
Still considered by the Yoruba people as a holy city, Ife, in the Oyo province ofpresent-day
Nigeria, was from the eleventh century the capital of a flourishing civilization. By the late
twelfth or early thirteenth century, Ife artists were producing their famous terracotta heads
andfine bronzes made by the cire perdue (lost wax) process. This technique was transmitted
to the Kingdom ofBenin which began to prosper in the thirteenth century and where bronze
art of the highest order flourished for five centuries.
CONSIDERING the central place it
occupies in the general history of
the Yoruba, we know surprisingly
little about the history of Ife. After the
comparative wealth of detail attached to the
legendary founder of the State, Oduduwa,
and his immediate successors, we encounter
a very spare and broken narrative in the oral
traditions for subsequent ages. The archae¬
ological record has done something to fill
the gaps, but this research is in its infancy.
A first phase in the history of the State,
opening around the eleventh century, is
characterized by a scattered settlement pat¬
tern, the widespread use of floors made of
potsherds set on edge, a glass-bead industry
and a very fine terracotta art which specia¬
lized in the production of naturalistic
figures, especially human heads. Because of
this latter feature, a link has sometimes
been posited between the cultures of Ife and
Nok, despite the thousand years which
stand between them.
More significant is the very close resem¬
blance which the terracotta art of Ife bears
to that discovered in other centres of
Yoruba culture. Heads in a style related to
that of Ife have been found at Ikinrun and
Ire near Oshogbo, at Idanre near Ikare, and
most recently and interestingly at Owo,
where a large number of terracotta sculp¬
tures have been excavated in a fifteenth-
century context.
This wide distribution of the style may
indicate the extent of Ife influence, but it
may also be that it marks the spread of a
cultural trait among the Yoruba associated
ALAN RYDER, of the UK, is a professor at the
University of Bristol. A specialist in the history
of west Africa, he has published many works
on the pre-colonial and colonial periods of this
region.
with religious rites rather than with Ife
kingship.
The potsherd floors, which in Ife have
often been discovered in association with
terracotta figures, are likewise not a unique
feature of that city; similar floors have been
found at Owo, Ifaki, Ikerin, Ede, Itaji
Ekiti, Ikare and much further afield at Ketu
and Dassa Zoume in the Republic of Benin
and in the Kabrais district of Togo.
The earliest potsherd floors so far dis¬
covered in Ife date to about 1100 AD and
the latest bear maize-cob impressions,
which means that they cannot be earlier
than the sixteenth century. The subsequent
disappearance of the floors, and apparently
also of the terracotta art, probably reflects
some catastrophe which overwhelmed Ife in
the sixteenth century.
The twenty-five Ife "bronze" heads (they
are in fact made of brass and copper),
which bear so striking a stylistic resem¬
blance to the terracottas, may have been .
made in the years immediately before the
disaster, when imports of brass and copper
by the Portuguese had made casting metal
relatively plentiful. We can at present only
surmise the nature of the events which des¬
troyed this culture; conquest by an alien
dynasty seems the most likely explanation.
If the above interpretation of Ife history
is correct, the dynasty which now reigns
there is that which established itself in the
sixteenth century, built the palace on its
present site and threw up the earliest of the
walls around the central area of the town.
Perhaps the new dynasty has preserved
some of the political and social institutions
of its predecessor, but we cannot assume
that the earlier regime resembled the later in
its political arrangements any more than it
did in its art. Because the modern pattern of
installation ceremonies and royal insignia >
Nok art (900 BC-200 AD) is the most an¬
cient of known Nigerian art. It is named
after the small village in the region ofZaria,
central Nigeria, where the first sculpture of
this type was discovered in 1943. Once
thought to have been confined to the
Bauchi plateaux, the Nok civilization is
now believed to have covered a far wider
area. A natural link stretching across a
millenniumjoins these sculptures to the ter¬
racotta art of Ife, to the southwest, which
flourished between the 12th and the 15th
century AD. Left, Nok terracotta head
(height 19.5 cm) is now in the National
Museum, Jos.
5
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Whether executed in terracotta, stone or
bronze, the sculptures of Ife mark a high
point in the art of portraiture (12th-15th
century). Both realistic and idealized, Ife
heads are outstanding for their nobility of
expression and the delicacy of their carving.
The head, top right, was discovered by the
German anthropologist Leo Frobenius,
who revealed Ife sculpture to the world In
1910. As so often in Ife art theface is scored
with lengthwise scarifications. Produced by
the lost wax method, Ife bronzes display a
high degree of technical accomplishment.
Above, representation of the oni ("king",
still considered a "father" by the Yoruba
people) and his queen. Above right, seated
figure (height 53.7 cm) cast in the Ife tradi¬
tion is a masterpiece of bronze sculpture
from black Africa. This highly naturalistic
effigy from Tada on the river Niger may
represent the hero Tsoede, who influences
the fertility of the people and their crops.
The magnificent bronzes discovered at
Igbo-Ukwu, a village near Awka in south¬
east Nigeria, are unlike those of Ife and
Benin in both design and the composition
ofthe alloy with which they were made. The
product of outstanding formal and tech¬
nical skills, these works of art dating from
the 9th century AD indicate that a vast and
powerful kingdom, of which Igbo-Ukwu
may have been the religious capital,
flourished in this region a thousand years
ago. Right, bronze stand depicting a
woman (not shown) and a man (height 27
cm). Above, bronze bracelet. Photos taken from Igbo-Ukwu © Th. Shaw, 1970
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
are so similar throughout most of Yoruba-
land, including Ife, and because these in¬
signia bear little resemblance to those worn
by supposedly royal figures in the earlier
phase of Ife history, it is reasonable to con¬
clude that modern Yoruba kingship derives
from the later phase, even though States
may originally have been formed on the
pattern of early Ife.
It is not impossible that the rise and fall
of States in the western Sudan in the fif¬
teenth and sixteenth centuries had a direct
influence on State formation in the Guinea
forest zone. Their appearance and expan¬
sion may well help to account for the
upheavals which happened about that time
in the adjacent southern States. We know
that the Nupe drove the Yoruba from Old
Oyo early in the sixteenth century, and that,
before they returned to their capital three-
quarters of a century later, the Oyo had
reorganized their military forces so as to
give greater prominence to the cavalry, the
striking force of armies in the savannah
States. From the Nupe the Oyo borrowed
the Egungun cult of ancestors, and certain
features of their revivified State may have
come from the same source.
Benin was the first State that the Por¬
tuguese visited on the coast; they soon
established diplomatic as well as trade rela¬
tions. Situated south-west of Ife, Benin
probably became a kingdom early on,
perhaps in the twelfth century.
In the fifteenth century a major upheaval
transformed this limited monarchy into an
autocracy and the small State into a large
kingdom. Tradition attributes the changes
to a ruler known as Ewuare, who acquired
the throne by ousting and killing a younger
brother; in the course of the struggle much
of the capital is said to have been destroyed.
Ewuare rebuilt his capital to a new plan
and gave it the name of Edo, which it has
borne to this day. In the centre of the city
a huge ditch and rampart were thrown up,
cutting across older structures as did the
city wall of Ife. Within the rampart a broad
avenue separated the palace from the
"town"the quarters which housed
numerous guilds of craftsmen and ritual
specialists who served the ruler. The palace
itself was organized into three
departmentsthe wardrobe, the ruler's
personal attendants and the harem each
with a staff graded into three ranks
analogous to the age grades of the Edo
villages.
Archaeology has confirmed the tradi¬
tions which assign the construction of the
great wall of Ewuare and a major
rebuilding of the palace to the fifteenth cen¬
tury. It has also shed light on the
developments of the renowned Benin art of
cire perdue (lost-wax) casting in brass and
bronze. All brass objects found in a pre-
sixteenth-century context prove to have
been made by a smithing not a casting pro¬
cess. Although the cire perdue technique
may have been known at an earlier date, it
would seem, both from the archaeological
evidence and from a stylistic study of the
very large body of Benin brasswork still in
existence, that only in the sixteenth century,
with the import of large quantities of Euro¬
pean brass, did this art become important.
In general, wood sculpture dominates
black African art. The Ife-Benin civiliza¬
tion is the brilliant exception, in that one
In the court art of
Benin, many bronze
artefacts are dedicated
to the greater glory of
the oba (king). Benin
figures, despite a
certain naturalism, are
usually highly stylized.
This flautist or
trumpet-player
(c. 1600; height
62.5 cm) belonged to
the oba's court.
finds works of art in terracotta and in
bronze which accounts for the particular
importance of this region in the general
evolution of black African art.
We noted earlier that objects in brass
were either forged or made by the cire per¬
due technique, which was known at Ife pro¬
bably earlier than the thirteenth century. In
the light of the most recent research, a
natural link unites the terracotta art il¬
lustrated by naturalistic figurines, par¬
ticularly human heads, with the culture of
Nok, which goes back to the Iron Age (the
fifth century before the Christian era). This
is most important and underlines the
widespread diffusion of the Nok culture;
moreover, we have evidence of exchanges
and continuing contacts between the coun¬
tries of the savannah and those of the forest
to the south. Thus the well-known bronzes
and naturalistic brass of Ife and Benin are
the culmination of an artistic evolution
begun at least as early as the Iron Age in a
vast cultural region.
This seems to be confirmed by the
discovery in 1939, in the east of Nigeria, of
the site of Igbo-Ukwu, which was explored
in 1959 by Professor Thurstan Shaw; some
800 bronze pieces have been brought to
light which are completely different from
the Ife-Benin bronzes. Igbo-Ukwu is an ur¬
ban complex in the middle of which were
the palace and temples. Different buildings
have been uncovered: a great room where
plates and objects of worship and treasures
i were stored; a burial chamber of a great
I priest, richly decorated; and an enormous
hole in which were deposited pottery, bones
and other objects.
Certainly there are some differences bet¬
ween the bronzes discovered at Igbo-Ukwu
and the works of art of Ife. Nevertheless, a
number of shared traits show that the two
centres were part of the same culture. In¬
deed, we are in the presence, as at Ife, of a
ritual monarchy.
It is believed that Igbo-Ukwu was the
religious capital of a very vast kingdom,
and that the treasures were stored there
under the keeping of a priest-king, Ezi Nzi.
Information is lacking on the culture of
Igbo-Ukwu; inquiries among those who
guard oral tradition are continuing, and ar¬
chaeologists see an extension of the area of
bronze manufacture. Nevertheless, Igbo-
Ukwu appears to contradict much of what
has so far been postulated about State for¬
mation; on the evidence of radiocarbon
dates, this highly sophisticated culture had
evolved by the ninth century among Ibo
peoples who otherwise maintained a
"stateless" form of society. In other words,
the Igbo-Ukwu culture antedates those of
Ife and Benin, and all others of comparable
complexity so far discovered in the forest
region, by at least two centuries.
Alan Ryder
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
jr
The secrets of Zimbabwe
Deep in the heart of southern Africa,
awayfrom the zones of influence of the
Islamic and Christian powers, the
basins of the Zambezi and Limpopo
Rivers were for centuries the setting for
a number of brilliant civilizations, the
most famous of these being that of
Great Zimbabwe. Thanks to painstak¬
ing research by archaeologists, linguists
and anthropologists, the ancient city of
Great Zimbabwe, with its cyclopean
buildings, is gradually yielding up the
secrets of its past.
8
WHATEVER the fundamental
causes behind the rise of Great
Zimbabwe, there is no doubt
that it is a most impressive monument. The
site is dominated by the Acropolis, a long,
granite hill covered with enormous boul¬
ders. Successive generations of occupants
linked the boulders together with stone
walls, making small enclosures and narrow
passages. The westernmost enclosure is the
largest, enclosed by a thick, free-standing
stone wall. It contains a long sequence of
later Iron Age occupation that provides the
basis for subdividing Great Zimbabwe's
history into at least three stages.
The most intensive occupation began in
about the eleventh century; but no stone
walls were built until the thirteenth century,
when the small pole-and-mud huts of
earlier times were replaced by more sub
stantial mud houses. The stone retaining
wall for the western enclosure was also built
at that time, as more imports appear in the
deposits. It was during the thirteenth or
fourteenth century, also, that the first
buildings were constructed in the valley
below the Acropolis.
The Great Enclosure with its massive
free-standing walls was built progressively
during the following century. The enclosing
wall of the Great Enclosure has an average
height of 7.3 metres, is 5.5 metres thick at
the base and between 1.3 metres and 3.6
metres at the top. A length of 52 metres is
decorated with a chevron pattern. Inside is
an unfinished enclosure wall which was evi¬
dently replaced by the present one and
which helps to form a narrow defile bet¬
ween the two walls, leading to a skilfully
constructed conical tower that dominated
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
by Brian Fagan
the Great Enclosure. The Great Enclosure
itself was divided into a series of smaller
enclosures, in which the foundations of
substantial pole-and-mud houses are to be
seen. It was presumably the dwelling place
of the rulers of Great Zimbabwe, an
impressive and politically highly significant
structure.
Great Zimbabwe is a unique site only on
account of its scale, for it is the largest of an
estimated 150 ruins in the granite country
that forms the Zambezi-Limpopo water¬
shed. There are other ruins with between
one and five enclosures, at least partially
surrounded with free-standing walls and
with mud-and-pole huts inside them, built
near Zimbabwe and in Mashonaland. The
regularly coursed masonry is in the Great
Zimbabwe style. Those that have been exca¬
vated contain occasional gold objects,
copper-wire bracelets, glass beads, and the
fire pots and spindle whorls characteristic
of the Great Zimbabwe culture. At the
Ruanga and Chipadze ruins, cattle were
important. Five of the excavated ruins have
produced dates that suggest they were all
built and occupied between the beginning
of the fourteenth and the end of the fif¬
teenth centuries. Some have been dated as
late as the sixteenth century.
All these ruins are small, having had but
a minimal population. They were normally
built near hills that were a plentiful source
BRIAN FAGAN, of the UK, is professor of an¬
thropology at the University of California,
Santa Barbara, USA. An anthropologist and
archaeologist, he has published many studies
on the Iron Age and Stone Age cultures in east
and southern Africa.
South of Harare, the capital ofZimbabwe,
rise the massive stone ruins of Great Zim¬
babwe. Settled by Iron Agepeoples as early
as the 10th or 11th century, by 1300 Great
Zimbabwe had become the centre of a
powerful and influential State. Chinese,
Persian and Syrian china, glass and
porcelain have been unearthed in the ruins
and on other sites nearby, indicating that
the Great Zimbabwe complexplayed an im¬
portant role in the East African coastal
trade which by the 14th century reachedfar
into the interior of the continent. Above
left, air view of the most spectacular ruin,
the Great Enclosure, girdled by ramparts
over 7 metres high. Narrow defile, above, is
formed by the outer rampart and an un¬
finished inner wall which runs part way
along it. Great Zimbabwe was built using
abundant local granite. Its architecture is
considered to be an extension of the
enclosures and chief's quarters which in
other African States were constructedfrom
grass, mud and poles.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
stone. Too small to be viable economic
units, they were probably built by external
labour from surrounding villages that were
able to support themselves by shifting agri¬
culture on the savannah.
At Nhunguza ruins there was a single,
very large hut, divided into three rooms.
One of the rooms was large enough to hold
a large number of people, a second con¬
tained a single seat, a third was a "com¬
pletely secluded room that must have con¬
tained objects of special value including...
what must have been a monolith set in a
grooved stone platform". This unusual
structure may well have been the location
where a prominent religious authority held
sway, an authority that was not only the
reason for the building of the isolated
enclosure, but also the human cement that
held together the Great Zimbabwe State.
One has a sense of an extremely strong
and unquestioned political and religious
authority whose hold over the scattered
rural population was based on some form
of unifying faith in the powers of the divine
Mwari or some other religious catalyst that
reached out to every family.
The borders of the Great Zimbabwe State
are still ill-defined, although its heartland
was in central Mashonaland. Some Great
Zimbabwe-style ruins occur in what is now
Matabeleland, where Great Zimbabwe peo¬
ple infiltrated Leopard's Kopje territory.
The influence of Great Zimbabwe and its
tributary settlements were felt far outside
the immediate, relatively limited boun¬
daries of the State itself. The prosperity of
Kilwa on the East African coast was closely
tied to the fluctuations in the gold trade
with Sofala. Already in the tenth century
the Arab geographer al-Mas'udi was
writing of Kilwa and the gold trade. Four
centuries later Ibn Battuta described Kilwa
as one of the most beautiful cities in the
world, a town whose prosperity depended
on the southern gold trade.
Without question the wealth of the rulers
of Great Zimbabwe waxed and waned with
the fortunes of the coastal trade. Kilwa
itself went through commercial vicissitudes,
reaching the height of its prosperity in the
fifteenth century with the reconstruction of
the famous Great Mosque and its elaborate
domed and vaulted roof. But a century later
Kilwa, the east African coast and Great
Zimbabwe itself had all declined. By the
time the Portuguese arrived at Sofala the
coastal trade was but a shadow of its former
self. For all its isolation, Great Zimbabwe's
trading connexions and the gold within its
borders contributed not only to prosperity
and economic growth on the east African
coast, but also in much remoter lands as
well.
In the fourteenth and fifteenth centuries,
however, there was considerable trading ac¬
tivity in northern Mashonaland and the
Zambezi valley, which is reflected in some
remarkable archaeological discoveries.
This region was settled during the Early
Iron Age, which survived until the end of
the first millennium. Between the twelfth
and fourteenth centuries northern
Mashonaland was occupied by the makers
of Musengezi ware, subsistence farmers
with minimal trading contacts, thought to
be Shona speakers. Their culture is a far cry
from the wealth of their southern
neighbours at Great Zimbabwe, although
more trade goods occur in later Musengezi
settlements.
But the same is certainly not true of the
extreme north-western corner of
Mashonaland and the lower part of the
middle Zambezi valley, where large set¬
tlements and the working and trading of
copper assumed great importance. The
Chedzurgwe site in the fertile Urungwe
district covered over 24 hectares of fine
grassland; abundant cattle and game bones
testify to the importance of pastoralism and
hunting. But copper and iron-working was
of considerable significance, both ores be¬
ing abundant nearby. Copper was made in¬
to standardized ingots of two fixed weights;
wire bracelets made from copper and tin
alloy were commonplace. Textiles were also
in use, and extremely fine pottery was
made, with a finish and delicacy of decora¬
tion on shallow bowls and beakers that is
almost unparalleled elsewhere.
Brian Fagan
The ruins of the great enclosure at Great
Zimbabwe (see previous page) are domina¬
ted by a massive A cropolis, a hilltop strong¬
hold integrated into a natural mass ofgiant
rocks. Left, entrance to a narrow covered
passage in the Acropolis.
The bird depicted
in this soapstone
sculpture
unearthed In ruins
In the valley of
Great Zimbabwe is
today the national
symbol of the Statel
of Zimbabwe.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Trade links from Europe to Cathay
Economic relations between places
bordering the western Mediterranean
VENICE
GENOA
MARSEILLES
MOROCCO
TLEMCEN
Dates in italics indicate commercial agreements
signed between the authorities concerned. Other
dates refer to the principal episodes in these
relations (treaties, exchanges of ambassadors,
disputes, etc.)
Source: Jean Dévisse
1391/92
1356
1251
TRIPOLI
It Is known from Chi¬
nese sources that in
628, under the Tang
dynasty, official envoys
from Black Africa arriv¬
ed in China with per¬
fumes and ivory. They
are depicted in frescoes
in the decorated grot¬
toes (5th to 10th cen¬
tury) of Dunhuang, in
Kansu province, one of
the masterpieces of
Buddhist art. Among
the personages por¬
trayed in this mural,
evoking the "Lamenta¬
tion for Buddha in Nir¬
vana", scholars of the
Dunhuang Institute see
in the dark-skinned
figure with curiy hair (to
the right of the third row
from the bottom) the im¬
aginary representation
of an African.
From the twelfth to the sixteenth century, Africa
played a major role in intercontinental rela¬
tions, particularly in the Mediterranean region
and, via the Indian Ocean, with Asia.
The Mediterranean. Although there was some
trade in such products as nuts, pepper and
ivory, it was through the gold and slaves torn
from its bosom that the African presence
became most clearly visible in the Mediterra¬
nean economy. As early as the end of the tenth
century, Spanish Christians had begun to ob¬
tain gold from the south and gold continued to
flow towards north Africa until the end of the fif¬
teenth century. From the thirteenth century on¬
wards the profits accumulated. An active mer¬
chant class came into being in the great Chris¬
tian ports of the Mediterranean and in certain
large cities such as Milan and Florence. The
"thirst for gold" in an expanding Western
economy was to accelerate ihe search for the
gold routes to the interior of the African con¬
tinent and it is reasonable to assume that a by
no means negligible proportion of African gold
found its way into the European commercial
circuit.
Asia. According to ancient historians, intense
commercial activity already existed in the
twelfth century on the east African coast. This
trading activity expanded considerably during
the thirteenth and fourteenth centuries. Ivory,
collected in the interior and much sought after
for the Muslim, Chinese and Indian markets,
hides, iron and gold constituted the most im¬
portant export products. Gold from the south,
exported through Sofala but marketed at Kilwa,
assumed a dominant place in this trade.
Ships brought various products to this coast:
cowrie shells, new plants, clothing and glass
beads. This was mainly a coastal trade carried
in ships which probably used Kilwa as their
home port. Muslim ships sailed from Mombasa
or Malindi to Asia every year and played an im¬
portant part in developing navigation tech¬
niques which improved considerably from the
thirteenth to the fifteenth century. African
sailors were employed on coasters and other
ships plying between Asia and Africa, at least
if certain paintings on manuscripts are to be
believed.
Over fifty towns, from Cape Gardafui to
Sofala, demonstrated the vitality of urban
development in the Swahili zone, even before
the arrival of the Arabs. One of the most
prosperous of these towns was Kilwa whose
four- and five-storey houses are described by
fifteenth-century Chinese sources.
The Chinese visited this coast of Africa in
force during the fifteenth century. There is
evidence too of the arrival of Africans in China,
possibly as early as the sixth or seventh cen¬
tury. Paintings of the T'ang era show Black
Africans in Buddhist grottoes and a thirteenth-
century compilation probably refers to Swahili
country. As early as 1402, a Korean map gave
an approximately correct outline of southern
Africa. In addition to the slave trade, Chinese
sources mention four major articles exported
from east Africa: gold, amber, yellow san¬
dalwood and ivory.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
West Africa's
THE results of archaeological excavations
carried out in 1977 and 1981 on an an¬
cient site near the city of Jenné, in Mali,
have contradicted previous assumptions about
the history of west Africa by pushing back the
date of the emergence of this city which
became one of the region's most prosperous
trading centres, by almost a thousand years.
The archaeological site of Jenné-jeno ("an¬
cient Jenné" in the local Songhay language)
lies three kilometres south of the modern city of
Jenné, on a floodplain of the inland Niger Delta
rich in fish, cereals (especially rice and millet),
and livestock.
Food has for centuries been produced in
abundance in the hinterland, supplying the
population of Timbuktu further north, to which
Jenné is linked by500 kilometres of navigable
riverway. The gold trade route originating in the
forested region of West Africa passed through
the two cities and then crossed the Sahara to
north Africa.
Until the excavations, directed by two
American archaeologists, husband-and-wife
Roderick J. Mcintosh and Susan Keech Mcin¬
tosh, it was generally accepted that Jenné had
developed simultaneously with Timbuktu
(founded around 1100) in the mid-thirteenth
century as an artifact of the trans-Saharan
trade which brought urbanism to west Africa.
However, excavations carried out on the
main site, a thirty-three-hectare artificial
mound formed of ruins of buildings and the
debris of human occupation, and an extensive
reconnaissance of sites in a surrounding area
of 1,100 square kilometres, have revealed that
a settlement already existed at Jenné-jeno as
early as the third century BC and was inhabited
by a population which made iron and practised
trade. By 800 AD Jenné-jeno had become a
prosperous cosmopolitan centre with a popula¬
tion of some 10,000 people.
In the course of the centuries the city's trade
expanded and diversified. Jenné-jeno im¬
ported from far away stone, iron ore, copper
from the Sahara and, around 600-800 AD, gold.
In return for these goods, the rich city had
various products and foodstuffs to barter,
notably rice (African rice, Oryza glaberrima,
was cultivated at Jenné-jeno as early as the
first century AD), fish, and fish oil.
The key to the city's success was a combina¬
tion of food production and craftsmanship. By
the year 50 AD the settlement extended over
twelve hectares. In 300 AD it had expanded to
some twenty-five hectares, and around 750 it
covered thirty-three hectares and was girded
by a wall some two kilometres long, 3.6 metres
wide and four metres or more high.
At the height of its development, between
750 and 1 1 50, it is thought that Jenné-jeno and
its nearby satellite villages may have had
almost 20,000 inhabitants, and that the density
of settlement in its hinterland may have been
ten times higher than today.
i
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
oldest metropolis
The city's decline is thought to have begun
around 1200. The fact that it was abandoned
around 1400 for the site of present-day Jenné
may perhaps be explained by the desire of a
new Muslim trading élite to change their
capital.
The discoveries at Jenné-jeno, along with
others such as the eighth-century "bronzes"
from Igbo-Ukwu in Nigeria open up major new
historical perspectives. It is now known that
long-distance trade and urbanism existed in
west Africa in the first millennium AD. It is also
established that Jenné-jeno played a central
role in the creation of the great trade-routes
between the Sahara and the Niger Bend and
was not, as was previously believed, a later off¬
shoot of the trans-Saharan salt and gold trade.
The early urban settlements of the inland Niger
Delta are thus seen to rank among the world's
great known civilizations.
Terra-cotta Cooking pot -
statuette
Close-packed buildings of modern Jenné
(centre left in air photo) rise from the
floodplain of the Inland Niger Delta in Mali.
Three kilometres away on a long elliptical
mound (upper right) is the site of ancient
Jenné ("Jenné-jeno"). Left, some ofthe ob¬
jects which have been unearthed by ar¬
chaeologists since 1977 and which chart the
rise ofJenné-jeno centuries before cities were
thought to exist in west Africa. Inset below,
as cattle amble by, workers excavate the cir¬
cular foundations of a mud-brick house.
O
Bracelet White-on-red pot
White-on-red-bowl
Fishhook
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Africa under ^ «
The colonial challenge by Albert Adu Boahen
NEVER in the history of Africa have
so many changes occurred, with
such speed, as during the period
1880 to 1935. Indeed, the most fundament¬
al and most tragic of these changes took
place between 1890 and 1910, the twenty*
year period that saw the conquest and occu¬
pation of virtually the whole continent of
Africa by the imperial powers and the
establishment of the colonial system the
following twenty-five years being essen¬
tially a period of consolidation and exploi¬
tation of the system.
The pace at which this drama unfolded
was astonishing. As late as 1880, in the
whole of west Africa, only the island and
coastal areas of Senegal, the town of Free¬
town and its environs, the southern parts of
the Gold Coast (Ghana), the coastal areas
of Abidjan in the Ivory Coast and Porto
Novo in Dahomey (Benin) and the island of
Lagos had come under the direct rule of
Europeans. In northern Africa, only Al¬
geria had by then been colonized by the
French. Not an inch of eastern Africa had
come under European control, while in cen¬
tral Africa only the coastal stretches of
Mozambique and Angola were subject to
Portuguese rule.
It was only in south Africa that foreign
rule had not only been firmly implanted but
also extended a considerable distance
inland. In short, in 1880, some 80 per cent
of the continent of Africa was still being
ruled by her own kings, queens and clan and
lineage chiefs, in empires, kingdoms, com¬
munities and political units of every size
and kind.
Within the next thirty years, however,
this situation underwent a dramatic change.
By 1914, the whole of Africa, with the
exception of Ethiopia and Liberia, was sub¬
ject to the rule of European powers.
What was the attitude of the Africans
themselves to the establishment of colonia¬
lism? The answer is quite clear and unequi¬
vocal; the overwhelming majority of Afri¬
can leaders and authorities were vehemently
opposed to this change and expressed their
The remaining .pages of this issue of the
Unesco Courier are devoted to extracts
from six chapters of Volume VII, Africa
under Colonial Domination, 1880-1935, of
Unesco's General History of Africa. The
English edition of Volume VII, of which
Professor A. Adu Boahen is the general
editor, is to be published later this year in a
joint co-edition between Unesco and
Heinemann, London and University of
California Press.
14
determination to retain their sovereignty
and independence.
In the face of the French invasion of his
territory in 1883 and their demand for per¬
mission to build a railway across his terri¬
tory Lat Dior, the Darnel of Cayor in
modern Senegal, wrote to the French
Government:
"As long as I live, be well assured, I shall
oppose with all my might the construction
of this railway... That is why, every time I
receive a letter from you concerning the
railway, I will always answer No, No, and
I will never make you any other reply. Even
were I to go to my rest, my horse Malaw
would give you the same answer."
In 1890, King Machemba of the Yao in
Tanganyika (United Republic of Tanzania)
told the German commander Hermann von
Wissman:
"I have listened to your words but can
find no reason why I should obey you I
would rather die first... If it should be
friendship that you desire, then I am ready
for it, today and always; but to be your sub¬
ject, that I cannot be... If it should be war
you desire, then I am ready, but never to be
your subject... I do not fall at your feet, for
you are God's creature just as I am. I am
Sultan here in my land. You are Sultan
there in yours. Yet, listen, I do not say to
you that you should obey me, for I know
that you are a free man... As for me, I will
Africa on the eve of partition and conquest by 1880
Tunis
Madeira
IP)
Canary islands Ifni
(S) (S)
IF)
Gambia
Port-Guinea
Sierra Leone
Senegal
Kita (F)
Bamako IF)
Gold Coast
Lagos
(F)
(F)
Grand-Bassam (S)
Gabon
IF)
Independent Boer
Republics
Angola
South African
Republic
Bechuanaland
Madagascar
Orange
Free State
Natal
Cape
Colony
<
©
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
domination, 1 880-1 935
HMM
not come to you and, if you are strong
enough, then come and fetch me."
Hendrik Wittboi, a king in south west
Africa, told the Germans in 1894:
"The Lord has established various king¬
doms in the world, therefore I know and
believe that it is no sin or crime that I should
wish to remain the independent chief of my
land and people."
Makombe Hanga, of Mozambique, also
told a white visitor in 1895:
"I see how you white men advance more
and more in Africa; on all sides of my
country companies are at work. My country
will also have to take up these reforms and
I am quite prepared to open it up... I should
like to have good roads and railways, but I
will always remain the Makombe my
fathers have been."
In 1895, Wobogo, the King of theMossi,
told the French Captain Destenave:
"I know the Whites wish to kill me in
order to take my country, and yet you claim
they will help me organize my country. But
I find my country good just as it is. I have
no need of them. I know what is necessary
for me and what I want. I have my own
merchants. Consider yourself fortunate
that I do not order your head to be cut off.
Go away now and, above all, never come
back."
Most fascinating of all was the moving
appeal addressed by Menelik II of Ethiopia
to Queen Victoria in April 1891. In his ap¬
peal, Menelik first declared his intention of
re-establishing the former boundaries of
Ethiopia and then continued:
"I have no intention at all of being an in¬
different spectator, if the distant Powers
hold the idea of dividing up Africa,
Ethiopia having been for the past fourteen
centuries an island of Christians in a sea of
pagans. Since the Ail-Powerful has pro¬
tected Ethiopia up until now, I am hopeful
that He will keep and enlarge it also in the
future, and I do not think for a moment
that He will divide Ethiopia among the
other Powers. Formerly the boundary of
Ethiopia was the sea. Failing the use of
force and failing the aid of the Christians,
our boundary on the sea fell into the hands
of the Muslims. Today we do not pretend to
be able to recover our sea coast by force,
ALBERT ADU BOAHEN, of Ghana, is a pro¬
fessor and head of the department of history
at the University of Legon, Ghana.' He is a
specialist in west African colonial history, a
subject on which he has written numerous
studies and articles.
but we hope that the Christian Powers, ad¬
vised by our Saviour, Jesus Christ, will
restore our sea coast boundary to us, or that
they will give us at least a few points along
the coast."
When, in spite of this appeal, the Italians
launched their campaign against Ethiopia
with the connivance of Britain and France,
Menelik again issued a mobilization pro¬
clamation in September 1895 in which he
stated:
"Enemies have now come upon us to ruin
our country and to change our religion...
Our enemies have begun the affair by ad¬
vancing and digging into the country like
moles. With the help of God I will not
deliver up my country to them... Today,
you who are strong, give me of your
strength, and you who are weak, help me by
prayer."
It is clear from all these quotations that
these rulers were confident of their
preparedness to face the European in¬
vaders, and well they might have been.
Many of them had been able to build up
huge empires only a decade or two earlier
and some were still in the process of ex¬
panding or reviving their kingdoms. Some
of them had been able to defend their ter¬
ritories with their well-tried old weapons
and traditional tactics, while others, like
Samori of the Mandingo Empire and
Africa in 1914
Spanish
Morocco
Madeira
(Port)
Tunisia
Morocco I Algeria
Canary Is. (Sp)
Rio de Oro
Libya
Gambie
Spanish Guinea
Port Guinea
Sierra
Leone
Egypt
(Br. occupation)
Anglo-
Egyptian
Sudan
(Condominium)
Eritrea Somallland
Fr. Br. It.
Empire
of
Ethiopia
n
Liberia
Gold
Coast Fernando
Po Isp.)
Sao Thome
(Port)
Spanish
Guinea
Uganda
Cabinda
British
East
Africa
î
t
o
ig
German ., ,_ ,
E.M Zanzibar (Br.)
Africa
Comoro Is.
:: (Fr.)
Angola
Northern
Rhodesia
Nyasaland
Southern
Rhodesia Madagascar
Walvis Bay
(Brit).
Mozambique
South¬
west Bechuanaland
A,rlca Swaziland
(British
Protectorate)
Union of Basutoland
South
Africa
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Born in 1844, at Ankober in central
Ethiopia, Menelik II was one ofthe greatest
ofEthiopia 's rulers and the most successful
of the leaders of African resistance to the
colonial invaders. In 1865 he became king
ofShewa and in 1889 assumed the imperial
crown. As king, and later as emperor, he in¬
corporated large areas ofsouthern Ethiopia
into his domains and undertook a vast pro¬
gramme of modernization. He had the
foresight to equip his army with modern
weapons and this enabled him to resist in va-
sion by the Italians whom he defeated
decisively In 1896'at the battle of Adowa,
one of the great battles in the history of
Africa. He died In December 1913, having
succeeded in maintaining his country's in¬
tegrity and Independence In face of the
onslaught of European colonialism.
Menelik of Ethiopia, had even managed to
modernize their armies. Furthermore, some
thought they could hold off invaders by
diplomacy.
It is also clear from some of the quota¬
tions above that many African rulers
welcomed the changes that had been steadi¬
ly introduced since the third decade of the
nineteenth century for hitherto they had
posed no threat to their sovereignty and in¬
dependence. In west Africa, for instance,
thanks to the activities of the missionaries,
Fourah Bay College had been founded as
early as 1826, while elementary schools and
a secondary school had been established by
the 1870s in both the Gold Coast and
Nigeria. As early as 1887 wealthy Africans
had even begun sending their children to
Europe for further education and profes¬
sional training.
As far as the Africans were concerned,
then, they did not see the need for any
radical change in their centuries-old rela¬
tions with Europe, and they were confident
that, if the Europeans wanted to force
change upon them and push their way in-
16
land, they would be able to stop them as
they had been able to do in the past.
What the Africans did not realize,
however, was that, by 1880, thanks to the
industrial revolution in Europe and the
subsequent technological progress
represented by the steamship, the railway,
the telegraph and, above all, the Maxim
gun, the old era of free trade and informal
political control had given way to what
Basil Davidson has described as "the era of
the new imperialism and rival capitalist
monopolies' ' . It was not only trade that the
Europeans now wanted, but also direct
political control.
Secondly, the African leaders failed to
realize that their muzzle-loading muskets
were totally outmoded and no match for the
Europeans' breech-loading rifles.
The consequences were tragic. All the
chiefs quoted above except one were
defeated. Only Menelik succeeded in
defeating the Italian invaders and retaining
his sovereignty and independence.
Albert Adu Boahen
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The scramble for territory
by Godfrey N. Uzoigwe
ALTHOUGH by the end of the third
quarter of the nineteenth century
France, Britain, Portugal and Ger¬
many had acquired commercial interests
and were exercising considerable influence
in different parts of Africa, their direct
political control in the continent was ex¬
tremely limited.
Britain, in particular, and Germany were
wielding all the influence they wanted, and
no statesman in his senses would choose to
incur the costs and court the unforeseen
contingencies of formal annexation when
the same advantages could be obtained
from informal control.
This attitude began to change, however,
as a result of three main factors which emer¬
ged during the period 1876 to 1880.
The first was the convening by King Leo¬
pold of Belgium of the so-called Brussels
Geographical Conference which resulted in
the setting up of the African International
Association and the employment of Henry
Morton Stanley to explore the Congo in the
name of the Association. These moves cul¬
minated in the creation of the Congo Free
State, whose recognition by the European
nations Leopold managed to obtain before
the Berlin West African Conference ended
its deliberations.
The second factor was a sudden flurry of
Portuguese activity. Piqued by the fact that
GODFREY N. UZOIGWE, of Nigeria, is pro¬
fessor ofhistory at the University ofMichigan,
Ann Arbor, USA. A specialist in east African
history, and in particular on the former
Bunyoro kingdom in Uganda, he has written
several studies and articles on African history.
she had been invited to the Brussels Con¬
ference only as an afterthought, from
1876 onwards Portugal despatched a
series of expeditions which by 1880 had
resulted in the annexation to the Portuguese
Crown of the hitherto virtually independent
estates of the Afro-Portuguese rulers of
Mozambique.
The third and final factor was the expan¬
sionist mood which characterized French
colonial policy between 1879 and 1880, as
signified by her participation with Britain in
the dual control of Egypt (1879), the des¬
patch of Savorgan de Brazza into the
Congo and the ratification of his treaties
with Chief Makoko of the Bateke, and the
revival of colonial initiatives both in Tuni¬
sia and Madagascar.
These moves on the part of France and
Portugal between 1876 and 1880 clearly
indicated that they were now committed to
colonial expansion and establishment of
formal control in Africa; it was this that
finally compelled both Britain and Ger¬
many to abandon informal control and
influence in favour of formal control and
led to their annexations in southern, eastern
and western Africa from the end of 1883
onwards.
By the early 1880s, the scramble for terri¬
tory was well under way and it was out of
fear of being pushed out of Africa alto¬
gether that Portugal proposed the calling
of an international conference to sort out
territorial disputes in the area of central
Africa.
The idea of an international conference
to settle the territorial disputes arising from
European activities in the Congo region,
suggested by Portugal, was later taken up
by Bismarck. The conference was held at
Berlin between 15 November 1884 and 26
November 1885. The news that such a con¬
ference was to be held increased the inten¬
sity of the scramble. The conference did not
seriously discuss either the slave trade or the
lofty humanitarian ideals that were sup¬
posed to have inspired it. Delegates conten¬
ted themselves with passing empty resolu¬
tions regarding the abolition of the slave
trade and the welfare of Africans.
It was not, ostensibly, the initial inten¬
tion of the conference to attempt a general
partition of Africa. It nevertheless ended up
disposing of territory, passing resolutions
concerning the free navigation of the Niger,
the Benue and their affluents, and laying
down "the rules to be observed in future
Delegates from 15
nations at the West
African Conference,
convened in Berlin in
November 1884,
which laid down "the
rules to be observed in
future with regard to
the occupation of
territory on the coasts
of Africa".
t "'
>1
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
regard to the occupation of territory
on the coasts of Africa".
According to Article 34 of the Berlin Act,
any European nation which took possession
of an African coast or declared a "protecto¬
rate" there, would have to notify such
action to the signatories of the Act in order
to have its claims ratified. This was the so-
called "sphere of influence" doctrine, to
which was linked the absurd concept of the
"hinterland" which came to be interpreted
to mean that possession of a coast also
implied ownership of its hinterland to an
almost unlimited distance.
Article 35 stipulated that an occupier of
such coastal possessions must also
demonstrate that it possessed sufficient
authority there "to protect existing rights
and, as the case may be, freedom of trade
and of transit under the conditions agreed
upon". This was the so-called doctrine of
"effective occupation" that was to make
the conquest of Africa such a murderous
business.
Indeed, by recognizing the Congo Free
State, by permitting territorial negotiations
and by laying down rules and regulations
for "legal" appropriation of African ter¬
ritory, the Concert of Europe had ar¬
rogated to itself the right of sanctioning the
principle of sharing-out and conquering
another continent.
There was no precedent in world history
to justify one continent boldly talking
about the sharing-out and occupation of
the territory of another continent. This was
the major significance of the conference for
African history. The argument that, con-
Relief from the Palace of the King of
Dahomey (Benin) Illustrating the
superiority of European arms.
trary to popular opinion, the conference
did not partition Africa is correct only in
the most technical sense; in any case it is ir¬
relevant. The appropriation of territory did
take place at the conference and the ques¬
tion of future appropriation is clearly im¬
plied in its decisions. By 1885, in fact, the
broad outlines of the final partition of
Africa had already been drawn.
i
Prior to the Berlin Conference, spheres
of influence had been acquired by settle¬
ment, exploration, the establishment of
commercial posts, the occupation of
strategic areas and treaties with African
rulers. Following the Conference, influence
by treaty became the most important
method of effecting the paper partition of
the continent. These treaties took two
forms those between Africans and Euro¬
peans, and bilateral agreements between the
Europeans themselves. The African-
European treaties were basically of two
kinds. First, there were the slave trade and
commercial treaties, and, secondly, there
were the political treaties by which African
rulers either purportedly surrendered
sovereignty in return for protection or
undertook not to enter into treaty obliga¬
tions with other European nations.
African leaders entered into these ar¬
rangements for a variety of reasons. In
some cases they hoped that the prestige of
such a relationship would give them
political advantages in dealing with their
neighbours. An African sovereign might
desire a treaty in the hope of using it to keep
recalcitrant subject States in line.
Sometimes a weak African State would
desire a treaty with a European power in the
hope of using it to renounce allegiance to an
African overlord or as a means of warding
off a threat to its independence from
another European power.
Godfrey N. Uzoigwe
Colour pages
Page 19
Above: Portrait of Samorí Touré by the
French artist Pierre Castagnez. Samorí
Touré was one of the great African
resistance leaders of the colonial era. As
head of the Mandingo Empire he opposed
the French colonial forces for a period of
some seventeen years before being cap¬
tured and exiled to Gabon, where he died in
1900. (See article page 27).
Photo © Lauros-Giraudon, Paris
Below: An Independence Day parade in
Dakar, Senegal.
Photo M. Renaudeau © Hoa-Qul, Paris
Page 20
(1) Probably fashioned between the 12th
and the 15th century, this terracotta man's
head (height 17.5 cm) is an example of the
out standing statuary art of Ife, in the south¬
west ofpresent- day Nigeria. In marked con¬
trast to this naturalistic treatment of the
human face is a highly stylized, cylindrical,
terracotta figurine (2) on which only the hair
(or head-dress), eyes and mouth are
represented. Some 19 cm in height, It was
once thought to be an example of an earlier
phase in Ife art, but it probably also dates
from between the 12th and the 15th century.
The highly original bronze art of Igbo-Ukwu
(south-east Nigeria) dates back to the 9th
century. In spite of certain common features
it is very different from the later bronzes of
Ife-Benin, as is shown by this pendant (3) in
the form of two eggs with chains, beads and
bells (height 21.6 cm). The bronze plaque
(4), 47 cm high, probably dates from the
16th century, a period of great fertility for
the art of Benin (15th-18th century). The
figure depicted in this stylized composition
of head, hands and legs is thought to repre¬
sent the ' 'messenger of death ' '. (For the art
of Ife, Igbo-Ukwu, Benin, and Nok, see arti¬
cle page 5).
Photos © André Held, Ecublens, Switzerland
Page 21
These 3 statuettes were unearthed, along
with many other objects, in recent excava¬
tions at Jenné-jeno ("ancient Jenné") in
Mali. Kneeling figures (5), may have been
ancestor-spirits, and (6) the magnificent an¬
drogynous figurine (32 cm high) may also
have had religious significance. Serpents
coil around its neck and arm. The head and
torso were found together but it is not fully
certain that they match. The discovery of
Jenné-jeno was one of the most exciting
events in recent African archaeology and in¬
vestigation of the site is shedding important
new light on early African history (see pages
12 and 13).
Photos Michael and Aubine Kirtley © ANA, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
*
Aw, *it.rc ¿OAto« n*.:
.1 .1 J .. . .Ij
$#5ÉIÉ^U'^iUu|j|4 £ « JA1 -3Jr.
v s«ft '
i . .
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
/
->:
".i. V..>Jjv.';:.;|jr!
.
g^^fc^
V
*¿:%y*
M H
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
ms
HB
HB
Ba
teSSä
Hi
BJ :;-** :
II
an
WM
fcïïX:
Hl
,sí«
HHHB1 Hl HH
HhI H ^^^H H H
^1 USÉ sEl§Í¡9lii*l bT
Si bbhhhI
SöS HHi Hl Saisi
RHH ü
H all?
W
H
«
b--1
tf
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
An unequal combat
by Godfrey N. Uzoigwe
Throwing axes and
knives used during the
1896 Asante War.
Photo © The National Army Museum, London
Colour page left
The roots of apartheid, South Africa's of¬
ficial ideology built on white supremacy and
racial segregation, can be traced back
through the historical record of domination
practised by small white minorities over a
large black majority. This collage, Livre sur
l'Afrique du Sud, by the South African
painter Gavin Jantjes, formed part of the Ar¬
tists against Apartheid exhibition held in
Paris last year and organized by the United
Nations and the Committee of Artists of the
World Against Apartheid.
THE story of the military conquest of
Africa is an epic of heroic resistance
against tremendous odds. It was a
struggle in which, in virtually every respect,
the dice were heavily loaded in favour of the
European invaders.
In the first place, thanks to the activities
of European explorers and missionaries, by
1880 Europeans were far more knowledge¬
able about Africa, its topography and
resources and the strengths and weaknesses
of its States and societies, than Africans
were about Europe.
Secondly, owing to the revolutionary
changes in medical technology, and in par¬
ticular the discovery of the prophylactic use
of quinine against malaria, Europeans
became far less fearful of Africa than they
had been before the middle of the nine¬
teenth century.
Thirdly, the material and financial
resources of Europe were overwhelming in
comparison with those of Africa. Thus,
while Europe could afford to spend mil¬
lions of pounds on overseas campaigns,
Africa could not sustain any protracted
military confrontation with Europe.
Fourthly, while the period following the
Russo-Turkish war of 1877-1878 was mar
ked, according to historian J. Holland
Rose, by "a state of political equilibrium
which made for peace and stagnation in
Europe", in Africa it was marked by inter-
State and intra-State conflict and rivalry
the Mandingo against the Tukulor, the
Asante against the Fante, the Baganda
against the Bunyoro, the Batooro against
the Bunyoro, the Mashona against the
Ndebele.
Thus while Europe could focus its atten¬
tion on imperial activities without any
major distractions at home, African States
and countries had their attention divided.
Moreover, divided though the European
States were on imperial and colonial issues,
throughout the era of partition and right up
to 1914, they always resolved these ques¬
tions without resort to war, except in the
single case of the conflict between the
British and the Boers in south Africa.
Despite competition and crisis, therefore,
the European powers involved in the parti¬
tion of Africa displayed a remarkable spirit
of solidarity which not only eliminated wars
among them but also prevented the African
rulers and communities from playing one
European power off against another.
Throughout this period, various European
powers took on the African powers one at^
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The period of the colonial conquest of
Africa coincided with technical advances in
arms manufacture which revolutionized
warfare and gave the European powers an
overwhelming firepower advantage over
African resistance fighters. The introduc¬
tion during the second half of the 19th cen¬
tury of breech-loading rifles and metal-
cartridge ammunition enormously increas¬
ed the range, accuracy and rate offire ofthe
individual rifleman and signalled the end of
cavalry as an effective military force. Even
more striking was the evolution of the
machine-gun with the invention, in par¬
ticular, of the Gatling gun (see previous
page), in 1862, and the Maxim gun (left), in
1883. With their outdated muzzle loaders,
throwing axes and spears, even the largest
and most dedicated African armies were no
match for the small, well-disciplined,
highly-trained European expeditionary
forces equipped with these deadly new
weapons.
a time and never was an African State as¬
sisted by another European country.
The behaviour of the African States,
however, was marked, by and large, by lack
of solidarity, unity or co-operation. Some
did not hesitate to ally themselves against
their neighbours, only to be vanquished
later in their own turn. The Baganda allied
themselves with the British against the
Bunyoro and the Barotse with the British
against the Ndebele while the Bambara
teamed up with the French against the
Tukulor.
The final and easily the most decisive fac¬
tor was, of course, the overwhelming logis¬
tic and military superiority that Europe
enjoyed over Africa. While Europe had at
its disposal well-drilled, professional
armies, very few African States had estab
lished standing armies and fewer still had
professional armies. Furthermore, the
Europeans could always rely on African
mercenaries and levies to give them the
numerical superiority they needed.
Above all, under the Brussels Convention
of 1890, the imperial powers agreed not to
sell arms to Africans. This meant that most
African armies were armed with outmoded
guns, mainly flint-locks or muzzle-loading
muskets and had no heavy artillery or naval
power whatsoever.
The European armies, on the other hand,
had the support of their navies and were
armed with the most up-to-date heavy artil¬
lery, repeater rifles and, above all, Gatling
and Maxim machine-guns. Towards the
end, they were using motor vehicles and
even aeroplanes. It is significant that
Samori and Menelik, the two African
leaders who succeeded in inflicting some
defeats on the Europeans, were the two who
managed to obtain a certain quantity of up-
to-date weapons. The overwhelming mili¬
tary superiority that Europe enjoyed over
Africa was succinctly summed up in this
couplet by the British poet Hilaire Belloc:
Whatever happens, we have got
The Maxim gun, and they have not.
In view of all these economic, political
and, above all, military and technological
advantages enjoyed by Europe over Africa,
the contest was a most uneven one and its
outcome was inevitable. Indeed, for
Europe, the timing of the conquest could
not have been better; for Africa it could not
have been worse.
Godfrey N. Uzoigwe
A 19th-century Yoruba Oba (king) with two
of his generals. They are armed with flint¬
locks known as "Dane" guns.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
A continent resists
North Africa: the long struggle
by Abdallah Laroui
A spotter aircraft
dropping range
adjustment
instructions to an
artillery unit during
the Rif War,
Morocco.
T
HE nineteenth century colonialist
drive in north Africa was unusual in
being a sequel to earlier campaigns.
For four centuries the Moroccan Govern¬
ment had been resisting the Spaniards who
had established themselves at Ceuta and
Melilla. Moroccans were forbidden to have
anything to do with the Spaniards and it
was to break this blockade that Spain
launched the war of 1859-1860 that was to
be so disastrous for Morocco. By the end of
the century, with the Bay of Rio de Oro,
whose occupation was notified on 26
December 1884 to the signatories to the Act
of Berlin on the division of Africa into
zones of influence, Spain had three bridge¬
heads on the north African coast.
In 1880 and 1881, when the Madrid Con¬
ference on the granting of "protection" to
individuals in Morocco met in two sessions,
the Makhzen (the government of Morocco,
and in a more general sense the country's
religious and political élite) made a last
attempt to get its independence and sov¬
ereignty over a clearly defined territory
accepted at the international level. Despite
British support, the attempt failed in face of
a self-seeking alliance of France, Spain and
Italy.
Immediately after the conference,
France, which for a time had thought that
all was lost in Morocco, raised the problem
of the Tuat oases. There was much talk in
ABDALLAH LAROUI, of Morocco, is professor
of modern and contemporary history at the
University of Rabat. A specialist in the history
of the Maghreb, he is the author of several
studies and articles on the history of north
Africa in the 19th century.
Paris at that time about the plan for a trans-
Saharan railway line that would open up
central Africa to French trade. But the plan
ran up against a serious obstacle. The oases
of the central Sahara were politically depen¬
dent on Morocco. France tried to win over
the Sultan but, buttressed by British sup¬
port, he rejected the French demands while
at the same time strengthening his adminis¬
trative and political presence at Tuat.
In the east of the Maghreb, the Tunisians
had for centuries been fighting the Italians,
just as the Moroccans had been fighting the
Spanish. A unified Italy had designs on the
Regency of Tunis, where it. sent immi¬
grants, invested capital and propagated its
culture. But the real danger threatening
Tunisia came from the French who had
already been established in Algeria for over
half a century.
Following the setbacks he had suffered in
Algeria, the Sultan in Constantinople had
decided to bring Tripolitania and Cyrenaica
back under his direct administration and to
regain his political influence in Tunisia.
There was considerable pro-Ottoman feel¬
ing among the élite in the Regency, but the
Bey, who saw in the Sultan's moves a threat
to his prerogatives, turned to Italy and
France for support. This more or less deli¬
berate line of conduct proved fatal to him.
When the French Government took advan¬
tage of a favourable political conjuncture
to attack the country, the Bey found him¬
self isolated both at home and abroad and
with no option but to sign a treaty, on 12
May 1881, placing himself under a French
protectorate.
However, the inhabitants of the Sahel
and of the religious capital of Kairouan at
once revolted, hoping for a rapid Ottoman
intervention. A second French expedition
was then raised which was to meet strong
resistance in the mountainous areas of the
north-west, the centre and the south. Sfax
and Gabes were bombarded by naval units,
Kairouan withstood a long siege during the
autumn of 1881, and the southern territo¬
ries, near Tripolitania, for long remained
an insecure zone.
Italy maintained her claims on the
country, but the Tunisians obviously could
not play that card. However, they remained
faithful to Islamic sovereignty and this was
to be one of the foundations of early Tuni¬
sian nationalism.
Up until the general agreement of April
1904 between France and Britain, the Euro¬
pean powers with an interest in the Magh¬
reb contented themselves with keeping their
claims alive, occasionally grabbing bits of
territory as security. At the end of the reign
of Hassan I, the war of 1893 enabled Spain
to consolidate her gains of 1860 in the
neighbourhood of Melilla.
Seven years later, at the end of the regen¬
cy of the vizier Ba Ahmad, France judged
that the time was ripe finally to settle the
Tuat problem to her advantage. On the
pretext of scientific exploration, a strong
expedition gradually approached the
coveted oases and, in December 1899, ap-
' peared before In Salah and demanded im¬
mediate surrender. The local chief, ap¬
pointed by the Sultan of Morocco, backed
by the soldiers of the Makhzen and assisted
by the sherifs of In Salah, put up a fierce
resistance. After a series of bloody battles,
such as that of In Ghar, on 27 December
1899, where, given the disparity between
the two sides the outcome was never in
doubt, the whole oasis region was con-
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
quered, the final battle taking place at
Talmin in March 1901.
Alerted by the young Sultan Abd al-Aziz,
Britain and Germany advised him to accept
the fait accompli; this he did, signing under
duress the draft treaty of 20 April 1902. In
return for this major concession, he tried to
have the line of demarcation in the south
and east between Morocco and the French
possessions clearly defined; but his efforts
were unsuccessful since the French prefer¬
red a certain imprecision which offered her
the prospect of further conquests.
The loss of Tuat was one of the main
reasons for the break-up of the Sultan's
authority which continued to crumble until
1911. The Makhzen knew that France
planned to encircle Morocco in order to
isolate and subjugate it. It also knew that
Britain no longer opposed the French
designs and that it could no longer count on
Germany for anything but diplomatic help;
Germany did indeed uphold Moroccan in¬
dependence until November 1911, when it
signed an agreement with France giving the
latter a free hand in Morocco in exchange
for compensations in equatorial Africa.
Having always refused to define the fron¬
tier with Morocco beyond the Figuig oasis,
France pursued a policy of nibbling away
slowly at Moroccan territory. Working
their way up the valley of the Sawra, French
forces gradually occupied the territory bet¬
ween Wadi Gir and Wadi Zusfana on the
pretext of ending lawlessness and insecurity
and allowing frontier trade to expand. The
French Government also proposed that the
Makhzen should share with it customs
receipts, and this was agreed in March 1910.
i
Further south France had imposed her
protectorate on the Emirs of the Trarza and
the Brakna. Then, in 1905, Xavier Cop-
polani introduced the policy of "peaceful
penetration", which took the form of mak¬
ing direct contact with the ethnic and
brotherhood chiefs with a view to winning
them over to French influence. He found
himself up against a worthy opponent in
Shaykh Ma'al-Aynayn who, for more than
thirty years, had been the Sultan's unof¬
ficial representative. The Sultan, Mulay
Abd al-Aziz, was informed and sent his
uncle Mulay Idris who galvanized the
resistance forces. Meanwhile, Coppolani's
camp at Tidjikdja was attacked in April
1905 and the apostle of peaceful penetra¬
tion was killed.
Taking advantage of the internal crisis
racking Morocco, France demanded the
recall of Mulay Idris, which it obtained in
January 1907. Nevertheless, resistance con¬
tinued. A strong expedition led by Colonel
Gouraud moved northwards. It suffered a
severe reverse at Al-Muynam on 16 June
1908, but succeeded in entering Atar on 9
January of the following year. Shaikh
Ma'al Aynayn withdrew with his followers
into the Sakiyat al-Hamra, from where his
forces continued to harass the French and
the Spanish until 1933.
During the same period Spain was ad¬
vancing in the wake of the French. When
France occupied Shinkit, the Spanish struck
out from their settlement on the Bay of Rio
de Oro; in 1906, they organized a Sanaran
intervention force which penetrated thirty
kilometres inland. In the north, the Spanish
waited until the French entered Wadjda, in
1907, before mounting a 45 ,000-strong ex¬
pedition which, in September 1909, set out
to conquer the Rif. In response, galvanized
by Shaykh Ameriyan's call for a holy war,
the Moroccan people mounted a fierce
resistance which was to last until 1926.
Abdallah Laroui
The Italian Occupation of Cyrenaica and Tripolitania
The Italian colonial drive was directed
against the Ottoman-controlled regions of
Cyrenaica and Tripolitania. On 28
September 1911, Italy presented an
ultimatum to Constantinople complaining
of Ottoman negligence, and in October
landed armies at Tripoli, Benghazi, Horns
and Tobruk. The Turks were soon obliged
to withdraw from the country, but the
Italians were unable to subdue the local
population, organized under the banner of
Ahmad al-Sharif (below right), the spiritual
leader of the Islamic fraternity known as
the Sanusiyyah. In 1913, the Italians laun¬
ched an attack on Ahmad al-Sharif''s forces
south of Derna, but, on 16 May, they suf¬
fered a stunning defeat at the battle of
Yawm al-Djuma. Sanusiyyah resistance to
the Italians continued for two decades,
notably under the leadership of Umar al-
Mukhtar (below left). Despite such drastic
Italian measures as the mass imprisonment
of the population in concentration camps,
this resistance was only finally broken with
the capture and execution of Umar al-
Mukhtar in 1931.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
A continent resists
West Africa
The fight for survival
by M'Baye Gueye and Albert Adu Boáhen
THE period from 1880 to 1900 was the
high-water mark of European con¬
quest and occupation of west Africa.
There were French campaigns in the west¬
ern Sudan, Ivory Coast and Dahomey bet¬
ween 1880 and 1898, and British campaigns
in Asante, the Delta region and in northern
Nigeria between 1895 and 1903.
During this period, practically all Afri¬
cans had the same objective, that of defend¬
ing their sovereignty and traditional way of
life, but the strategies and methods they
adopted varied. Three options were open to
the Africans, confrontation, alliance or
acquiescence and submission. The strategy
of confrontation involved open warfare,
sieges, guerilla tactics, scorched-earth poli¬
cies, as well as diplomacy.
From 1880, the French adopted a policy
of extending their control over the whole
region from the Senegal to the Niger and
then Chad and linking these areas with their
posts on the Guinea coast in Ivory Coast
and Dahomey.
In their occupation of west Africa, the
French resorted almost exclusively to the
method of military conquest, rather than
the conclusion of treaties as the British did.
In terms of African reaction, all the options
open to them, namely submission, alliance
and confrontation, were resorted to. How¬
ever, far more of the rulers opted for the
strategy of militant confrontation than for
submission and alliance, and opposition
here was far more protracted than any¬
where else in west Africa for two main
reasons. The first was that as already in¬
dicated, the French themselves used the
military option almost exclusively and this
evoked a militant reaction. The second rea¬
son was that the people were far more Isla-
mized than those of other areas of west
Africa and, as one scholar, M. Crowder has
pointed out, since "for Muslim societies of
west Africa the imposition of white rule
meant submission to the infidel which was
intolerable for any good Muslim", they
tended to resist the Europeans with added
fervour and a tenacity often lacking among
non-Muslims.
These general observations are well illus¬
trated in the history and person of Samori
Touré, the valorous leader of the Mandingo
Empire.
M'BAYE GUEYE, of Senegal, is a lecturer in
history at the University of Dakar. He
specializes in the history of west Africa in the
19th and 20th centuries and is the author of
several works on the slave trade and French
colonization.
ALBERT ADU BOAHEN (for biographical
details see page 15).
[One of the great resistance heroes of the
colonial era, Samori Touré was born in
about 1830, near Sarranko in present-day
Guinea. A Dyoula and a Muslim, he
succeeded in gaining the support of the
Mandingo people andpatiently began cons¬
tructing an empire which, at its height in the
early 1880s, stretchedfrom the Upper Volta
region in the west to the Fouta Djallon in
the east.]
Samori Touré chose the strategy of con¬
frontation and not of alliance though he
used the weapons of both diplomacy and
warfare but with the emphasis on the latter.
By 1881, Samori had already converted
"the southern part of the Sudanese savan¬
nah all along the great west African forest"
between the northern parts of modern
Sierra Leone to the Sassandra River in the
Ivory Coast, into a single empire under his
unquestioned authority.
Unlike the Tukulor Empire, the Man¬
dingo Empire was still on the "up-swing"
by 1882 when the first encounter between
Samori and the French occurred. The con¬
quest of the area had also enabled Samori to
build a powerful army relatively well-
equipped with European arms. This army
was divided into two wings, the infantry
wing (the Sofa) which by 1887 numbered
between 30,000 and 35,000 men and the
cavalry wing numbering not more than
3,000 by 1887.
The infantry was divided into permanent
units of 10 to 20 men known as the sé (feet)
or kulu (heaps) commanded by a kuntigit
Samori Touré at the time of his capture by
Captain Gouraud (seen right) at Guelemou
on 29 September 1898. (See also colour
page 19).
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
(chief), and ten se formed a bolo (arm)
under the command of a bolokuntigi. The
cavalry was divided into bands of 50 called
sèrè. The bolo formed the main striking
force while the sèrè rode alongside each
bolo. Since these units were permanent, its
members developed feelings of friendship
first among themselves and of loyalty first
to their local leader and then to Samori.
Thus, the army soon assumed "a quasi-
national character because it achieved a
very remarkable homogeneity".
What was unique about Samori's army
was the standard of its weapons and train¬
ing. Unlike most of the armies of west
Africa, not only was this army virtually
professional, but it was armed by Samori
himself. Up to 1876, he armed them with
old guns which the local blacksmiths could
repair themselves. But from 1876 onwards,
he also began to order more modern Euro¬
pean weapons mainly from Sierra Leone
and carefully studied them to find those
that were most suitable for his area. Thus
from 1885, he replaced the Chassepot rifles
whose big cartridges soon rotted in the
humidity of the area with the more suitable
Gras rifles with lighter cartridges and
Kropatscheks which were Gras repeater
rifles.
He continued to rely on these two till the
1880s since he was able to train a group of
blacksmiths who could effectively copy
those rifles. From 1888, he also added to his
stock some of the new quick-firing rifles
and by 1893 he had about 6,000 of them
which he used till his defeat. However, he
never acquired any artillery which was a
great handicap in his campaigns against the
French.
Samori was virtually at the height of his
power when he first came into contact with
the French in 1882. In February of that
year, he was called upon by Lieutenant
Alakamessa who notified him of the order
from the Upper Senegal-Niger high com¬
mand to withdraw from Kenyeran, an im¬
portant market-centre which controlled
Samori's route to the Mandingo areas.
As might have been expected, Samori
refused. This led to a surprise attack on his
army by the French commander Borgnis-
Desbordes who was forced to beat a hasty
retreat. Samori's brother, Kémé-Brema, at-
Resistance in the Niger Delta
In the Niger Delta, as in many other areas
of Nigeria, the British had by 1884 signed
treaties ofprotection with most of the Delta
chiefs. While some chiefs allowed mis¬
sionaries to operate in their States others
did not, but all of them Insisted on their
sovereign right to regulate trade and to levy
duties on British traders. This the new
British consuls such as Hewett and Johnson
would not tolerate. Jaja of Opobo (left),
one of the wealthiest and most powerful of
the Delta chiefs, insisted on payment of
duties by British traders and ordered a com¬
plete stoppage oftrade on the river until one
British firm agreed to pay duties. The con¬
sul, Johnson, ordered him to stop levying
duties, but instead of complying Jaja
despatched a mission to the Colonial Office
to protest against the order. In 1887, when
Jaja still refused to comply in spite of
Johnson's threats to bombard his town,
Johnson enticed him aboard a ship under a
promise of safe conduct, but then arrested
him and sent him to Accra where he was
tried and deported to the West Indies.
Stunned by this treatment the other chiefs
surrendered and accepted governing coun¬
cils imposed on them by Johnson.
Photo © Longman, London
tacked the French at Wenyako near
Bamako in April. Though he won the battle
on 2 April, he was defeated on 12 April by
a much smaller French army. Samori
thereupon tried to avoid conflict with the
French and directed his action towards
Kenedugu.
In 1885, when Combes occupied Bure,
the gold of which was important to the
economy of his empire, Samori realized
how great was the threat that hung over his
State. He resolved to expel the French from
the area by force. Three armies, his own
and those of Kémé and Masara-Mamadi,
. were charged with this operation. By a vast
pincer movement, Bure was easily recap¬
tured and the French were forced to decamp
for fear of being encircled.
Samori thereupon decided to cultivate his
relations with the British in Sierra Leone.
After having occupied Falaba in 1884, he
dispatched emissaries to Freetown, to pro¬
pose to the governor that he place his entire
country under the protection of the British
Government. The offer was a mere
manoeuvre on the part of Samori, whose in¬
tention was in no way to relinquish his
sovereignty but to make the French respect
it by allying himself with a powerful
government.
When that move failed, Samori turned to
the French and signed a treaty with them on
28 March 1886. He agreed to withdraw his
troops to the right bank of the Niger, but
maintained his rights over Bure and the
Mandingo of Kangaba. In another treaty
with the French on 25 March 1887 which
amended that of the previous year, Samori
ceded the left bank of the river to the
French and even agreed to place his country
under French protection.
Samori had perhaps signed the other
document in the hope that the French
would help him against Tieba, the Faama of
Sikasso whom he attacked in April 1887
with a 12,000 strong army, while the French
had signed it because they needed to prevent
any alliance between Samori and the
Soninké leader Mamadou Lamine whom
they were then fighting. When he saw that
instead of behaving as allies and assisting
him, the French were rather encouraging
dissidence and rebellion in the areas recent¬
ly subdued and were attempting to prevent
him from obtaining supplies of weapons
from Sierra Leone, he raised the siege of
Sikasso in August 1888 and prepared to
take up arms against the invader.
He reorganized the army, concluded a
treaty with the British in Sierra Leone in
May 1890 which enabled him to buy
modern weapons for the next three years in
increasing quantities, and trained his troops
in the European manner. Platoons and
companies were activated. He adopted
defence as his military tactic. Of course,
there could be no question of using the tatas
(earth-walled settlements) for shelter, as
there was no chance that they could hold
out against artillery. His strategy consisted
of endowing his troops with great mobility,
so that they could surprise the enemy, in¬
flict heavy losses upon him, and disappear.
In March 1890, Archinard captured
Segou and in his attempt to defeat Samori
before ceding the Upper Senegal-Niger
command to Humbert, attacked him in
March 1891. Archinard thought that
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Samori's empire would collapse at the first
onslaught. Though that attack resulted in
the capturing of Kankan on 7 April and the
burning of Bisandougou, its effect was
quite the opposite since it not only provided
Samori with a salutary warning but it enabl¬
ed him also to continue the attacks on the
French at Kankan and to defeat them at the
battle of Dabadugu on 3 September 1891.
The major confrontation between the
French and Samori, however, took place in
1892. Bent on defeating Samori, Humbert
launched an attack on the central part of the
Empire in January 1892 with 1,300 careful¬
ly picked riflemen and 3,000 porters.
Samori took personal command of his
carefully chosen army of 2,500 men to meet
Humbert. Though these men, "fighting like
demons, clung fiercely to every defensive
point on the way", to quote historian Yves
Person's words, they were defeated and
Humbert succeeded in capturing Bisan¬
dougou, Sanankoro and Kerwane.
Humbert himself admitted, however, that
the results were meagre in comparison to
the heavy losses that he had sustained. Fur¬
thermore, Samori had ordered the civil
population to withdraw at the approach of
the French troops.
However, Samori had no illusions. After
the violent encounters with the Humbert
column in which he lost over a thousand
men of his élite units as compared with only
about a hundred lost by the French, he
became convinced of the futility of con¬
fronting the French. There were then two
options open to him: either to surrender or
to withdraw. He ruled out the former and
decided to abandon his homeland and move
to the east to create a new empire out of the
reach of the Europeans.
Still continuing his scorched earth policy,
he began his move eastwards towards the
Bandama and the Comoe rivers. Though in
1894 he lost the last route supplying him
with modern weapons, which was the one to
Monrovia, he nevertheless fought on. At
the beginning of 1895, he encountered and
beat back a French column coming from
the Baule country under the command of
Monteil, and between July 1895 and
January 1896 went on to conquer the Abron
(Gyaman) kingdom and the western part of
Gonja. By that time, he had succeeded in
creating a new empire in the hinterland of
the Ivory Coast and Asante.
In March 1897, his son Sarankenyi-Mori
met and defeated a British column under
the command of Henderson near Wa while
Samori himself attacked and destroyed
Kong in May 1897 and pushed on to Bobo
where he encountered a French column
under the command of Caudrelier.
Caught between the French and the
British and having vainly attempted to sow
discord between them by returning to the
latter the territory of Bouna coveted by the
former, Samori decided to return to his
Toma allies in Liberia. On the way, he was
captured in a surprise attack at Guelemou
by Gouraud on 29 September 1898 and
deported to Gabon where he died in 1900.
His capture brought to an end what a recent
scholar has described as "the longest series
of campaigns against a single enemy in the
history of French Sudanese conquest".
M'Baye Gueye and Albert Adu Boahen
The Hut Tax Rebellion
The Hut Tax Rebellion of 1898 was the
response of the Temne and Mende peoples
of Sierra Leone to the consolidation of
British rule by the appointment of District
Commissioners, the expansion of the Fron¬
tier Police, the abolition of the slave trade
and slavery, the Protectorate Ordinance of
1896 andfinally, the imposition of a tax of
five shillings a year on all two-roomed
houses and ten shillings on all larger houses
In the Protectorate. All the Temne chiefs
refused to pay the tax and rose up in
rebellion under one of their number, chief
Bai Bureh. They . were joined by almost
three-quarters of the Protectorate. The
rebelforces attacked and looted trading sta¬
tions and killed British officials and troops
and all those suspected of assisting the col¬
onial government. By May 1898, the rebel
armies were within about 25 miles of
Freetown and two companies of troops had
to be hastily brought In from Lagos to de¬
fend the town. What was the true nature of
this revolt? The British Governor of Sierra
Leone attributed not only this rebellion but
the general resistance to colonial rule that
was raging at the time to "the growing
political consciousness of the African and
his increasing sense of his worth and
autonomy". As he put it, "the native is
beginning tofeel his strength from the value
that is set on him for products ofhis coun¬
try and his labour by the white man and in
future the latter will not be able to trade so
much on his simplicity and ignorance of the
world as in the past". Above, a sketch by a
British army officer of the rebel leader, Bai
Bureh, after his capture.
Photo © BBC, Hulton Picture Library, London
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
A continent resists
East Africa: diplomacy and defiance
by Henry Mwanzi
THE colonialist scramble for east
Africa was three-pronged, involv¬
ing, as it did, three competing
powers: the Sultanate of Zanzibar, Ger¬
many and Britain. The first on the scene
were the Arabs who operated from Zan¬
zibar. Their interests both on the coast and
in the interior were largely commercial,
revolving around the trade in slaves and
ivory. Before the 1880s and 1890s, these
Arabs and Swahili traders were content to
operate from the coast. But during the clos¬
ing decades of the last century, Arab in¬
terests in the interior of east Africa began to
be threatened by German and British in¬
terests that had been steadily penetrating
the area. In the face of this, the Arabs at¬
tempted to take political control of some
areas in order to protect their commercial
concessions.
The Europeans in the interior included
traders and missionaries, all of whom
wanted the occupation of east Africa by
their home governments in order to provide
them with security as well as a free hand to
carry out their enterprises without
hindrance.
The methods of European advance
varied from place to place. But, on the
HENRY MWANZI, of Kenya, is senior lecturer
in history at the University of Nairobi. He
specializes in east African history on which he
has written several articles and studies.
whole, they were characterized by the use of
force combined with, where it was possible,
diplomatic alliances with one group against
another. The African response to all this
was both military and diplomatic" though
at times there was withdrawal or non-co¬
operation or passivity.
The coastal people of Tanganyika
organized their resistance around the per¬
son and leadership of Abushiri. Socially,
the coast of Tanganyika, as of Kenya, was
dominated by Swahili and Islamic culture.
Here existed a mixed population of Arabs
and Africans who intermarried freely and
carried out local trade.
In the nineteenth century, the coastal
Arabs increased their activities in the in¬
terior in response to increased demand
for ivory and slaves. The result of this
flourishing trade was that many towns
sprang up along the coast. The coming of
the Germans threatened this trade which
they sought to supplant with their own. The
local populations, especially the Arabs,
resented this and organized a resistance.
Abushiri, the leader, was born in 1845 of
an Arab father and a Galla mother. He was
a descendant of one of the first Arab settlers
¿t v | ;¿¡L.ÄW-JT í¡rfdi : - ¿sra
on the coast who came to regard themselves
as local people. Like many others, he op¬
posed the influence of the Sultanate of Zan¬
zibar on the coast and even advocated in¬
dependence. As a young man, he had org¬
anized expeditions into the interior to trade
in ivory. From the profits made, he bought
himself a farm and planted sugar cane.
Under his leadership, the coastal people
fired on a German warship at Tanga in
September 1888 and then gave the Germans
two days to leave the coast. They later at¬
tacked Kilwa and killed the two Germans
there and then attacked Bagamoyo with
8,000 men on 22 September. But the Ger¬
mans who termed this "the Arab revolt"
sent out Hermann von Wissmann. He
reached Zanzibar in April 1889, attacked
Abushiri in his fortress near Bagamoyo and
drove him out. Abushiri escaped nor¬
thwards to Uzigua where he was betrayed
and handed over to the Germans who hang¬
ed him at Pangani on 15 December 1889.
The coastal resistance finally collapsed
Railways were an important instrument of
the colonizing process; they facilitated
military conquest, helped establish political
control and enabled the colonies to be
developed as sources of raw materials for
export to Europe rather than as areas of in¬
dustrial development. The British-built
Uganda Railway, which linked the interiors
of Uganda and Kenya with the coast, reach¬
ed the Lake Victoria basin in 1901. In
Tanganyika a German-built railway was
started at Tanga during the early 1890s and
reached the foothills of the Usambara
mountains in 1905. Below, a plate-laying
gang employed on the construction of the
Uganda Railway shifts camp.
H j U TT O" :V*W*ñVié1 ' ^Bt »
- /X
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
when Kilwa was bombarded and taken by
the Germans in May 1890.
The Germans,, like the British in Kenya,
were practiced in the art of divide and rule
by allying with one group against another.
There were many such allies. The Marealle
and the Kibanga near the Tanganyikan
mountains of Kilimanjaro and Usambara
were, to name but two examples, among
those who saw in the Germans an oppor¬
tunity to make friends in order to defeat
their enemies. These people, like others
such as the Wanga in Kenya, believed that
they were using the Germans even though in
the process they were made use of much
more by the Germans than perhaps they
realized. The Arabs on the coast, however,
were firmly in the employ of the Germans as
they were in that of the British in Kenya and
they provided the first local personnel in the
service of imperialism.
A similar pattern of response to British
colonialism took place in Uganda. The
period between 1891 and 1899 saw a clash
between the forces of Kabarega, the King of
Bunyoro and those of Lugard and other
British agents. After some clashes in which
his forces were defeated, Kabarega turned
to diplomacy. Twice he attempted to come
to terms with Lugard, but the latter would
not countenance these gestures. Mwanga,
the Kabaka of Buganda, at times tried to in¬
tercede on behalf of the Bunyoro King but
to no avail. Eventually, Kabarega resorted
to guerilla warfare, probably the first of its
kind in East Africa. He withdrew from
Bunyoro to the Lango country in the north
from where he harassed British forces time
and again.
One of the British officials occupying
Bunyoro at the time, Thurston, com¬
mented: "Kabarega was at his old tricks
giving every possible trouble but never
standing up for a fair fight, preferring to
pursue his favourite methods of assassina¬
tion. Kabarega caused poison to be given to
a friendly chief and he died, but I have had
the poisoner killed".
What Thurston says here is a perfect ex¬
ample of guerilla tactics, of withdrawing to
a neighbouring country in order to harass
occupying forces in one's own country.
Kabarega was later joined in Lango by
Mwanga, but their hide-out was stormed in
1899 and both kings were captured and
taken to Kisimayu where Mwanga died in
Henry Mwanzi
King Mwanga of Buganda (left) and King
Kabarega of Bunyoro on their way under
escort to the coast after their capture by
British forces in 1899. Kabarega was exiled
to the Seychelles and Mwanga to Kisimayu,
where he died in 1903. Both rulers resisted
British colonialism with a mixture of
diplomacy, direct confrontation and
guerilla warfare.
Chief Abushiri, the
leader of the coastal
people of Tanganyika
in their resistance
against the German
colonial occupation.
©
©
¡1 ü^
w &
[ 'te¡_f
'
1 m Bfc
^^^^H ^ i_
- \J ' Vj
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
I '«J
***
::::::
2?-^Ä*«J
II
I
I»
V Ki
lit
I
-
J "J
»Uli* ,
¡S'il1
* 3.3*»;
>. * *
^îW1 2 ST1
t
X"
f
> t
r^ ^ -»«''
,
"
Is
1»)
> -J
1 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
y. by A IbertAdu Boahen
BY 1935, colonialism had been
fastened on Africa like a steel grid,
and it looked as if it was going to
remain there for ever. However, colonia¬
lism proved just as ephemeral as any other
institution created and maintained by force.
Within a matter of only some forty-five
years from 1935, the colonial system had
been uprooted from over ninety per cent of
Africa and confined to that part of the con¬
tinent south of the Limpopo River.
What legacy did colonialism bequeath to
Africa? Did it constitute an important revo¬
lutionary episode in the history of the conti¬
nent? Was it a major break with the past, or
was it, after all, merely a passing event?
To some historians its impact was on
balance either a blessing in disguise or, at
worst, not harmful for Africa:
"It is easy to cavil today" wrote
P.C. Lloyd, "at the slow rate of economic
development during the half-century of
colonial rule... Nevertheless, the difference
between the condition of African society at
the end of the nineteenth century and at the
end of the Second World War is staggering.
The colonial powers provided the infra¬
structure on which progress in the 'inde¬
pendence' period has depended: a fairly
efficient administrative machine, reaching
down to villages in the most remote areas,
a network of roads and railways, and basic
services in health and education."
Others have contended that the beneficial
effect of colonialism in Africa was virtually
nil. The Black Guyanese historian, Walter
Rodney, has taken a particularly extreme
position:
"The argument suggests that, on the one
hand, there was exploitation and oppress¬
ion, but, on the other hand, that colonial
ALBERT ADU BOAHEN (for biographical
details see page 15).
"The phenomenal growth of the popula¬
tion of the urban centres [during the col¬
onial period] was not the result of the
natural increase of the urban population
but rather of the continuous pull of young
men and women to the urban centres by the
need for education and employment and
the push from the rural areas by famine,
epidemics, poverty and taxation. "
Since independence the rapid growth of ur¬
ban centres in Africa has continued. Op¬
posite page, the modern face of Dakar,
capital city of Senegal.
"A huge gap exists even today between ur¬
ban and rural areas in Africa and there is no
doubt that it was the colonial system that
originated and widened this gap. "
Left, a kraal (village) surrounded by tilled
fields in Ovamboland, Namibia.
Photos Georg Gerster © Rapho, Paris
The impact of colonialism on African art
was neitherprofound norpermanent. Even
when commenting on the colonial condi¬
tion, African artists drew on the continent's
age-old artistic traditions, as witness this
tongue-in-cheek portrayal (inset left) by a
wood-carver from the Congo (Zaire) of a
1920s Belgian colonial official in his
chauffeur-driven car.
Photo © Werner Forman Archive, London 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Jr^W
"Because of the concentration on the pro¬
duction of cash crops during the colonial
era, Africans were compelled to Ignore the
production offoodfor their own consump¬
tion. It was this neglect offoodproduction,
coupled with forced labour, which caused
so much malnutrition, severefamine and so
many epidemics in some parts of Africa
during the early colonial days. Thus, under
the colonial system, Africans were In most
cases made to produce what they did not
consume and to consume what they did not
produce." Above, harvesting the cotton
crop in the Sudan.
governments did much for the benefit of
Africans and that they developed Africa. It
is our contention that this is completely
false. Colonialism had only one hand it
was a one-armed bandit."
From the available evidence, however, it
would appear that a much more balanced
assessment is necessary. The impact of
colonialism was positive as well as negative.
However, it should be emphasized that
most of the positive effects were, by and
large, rather accidental by-products of acti¬
vities or measures intended to promote the
interests of the colonizers.
The first positive political impact was the
establishment of a greater degree of con¬
tinuous peace and stability in Africa than
before. The nineteenth century was the cen¬
tury of the Mfecane and the activities of the
Swahili-Arab and Nyamwezi traders such
as Tipu Tip and Msiri in central and sou¬
thern Africa, of the Fulani djihads and the
rise of the Tukulor and Mandingo empires
in western Sudan, and of the disintegration
of the Oyo and Asante empires in west
Africa; and all this caused a great deal of
instability and insecurity.
The first two or three decades of the colo¬
nial era, that is from 1880 to 1910, intensi¬
fied this state of instability, violence and
disorder and caused wholesale and unpar¬
donable destruction and loss of population.
But after the colonial occupation and the
establishment of various administrative
machineries, most parts of Africa, espe¬
cially from the end of the First World War
onwards, enjoyed a great degree of con¬
tinuous peace and security.
The second positive impact is reflected in
the very geo-political appearance of the
modern independent States of Africa. In
34
place of the hundreds of independent clan
and lineage groups, city-States, kingdoms
and empires, without any clearly defined
boundaries, were now established fifty new
States with, in most cases, fixed bounda¬
ries; and it is rather significant that the
boundaries of the States as laid down
during the colonial era have not undergone
any changes since independence.
Thirdly, the colonial system also intro¬
duced into most parts of Africa two new in¬
stitutions which have been maintained since
independence, namely a new judicial system
and a new bureaucracy or civil service.
The final positive impact of colonialism
was not only the birth of a new type of
African nationalism, but also of pan-
Africanism. Important as this legacy was,
however, it is a typical example of the ac¬
cidental by-products rather than the
deliberate creations of the colonial
presence. No colonial ruler ever set out to
create and nurture African nationalism.
But if there were positive effects, the
negative effects were even greater. In the
first place, important as the development of
nationalism was, it was generated by a sense
of anger, frustration and humiliation
caused by some of the oppressive,
discriminatory and exploitative measures
introduced by the colonial rulers. With the
overthrow of colonialism that feeling was
bound to lose some of its momentum and
the problem that has faced the rulers of in¬
dependent African States has been how to
replace it with a positive and enduring feel¬
ing of nationalism.
Secondly, while admitting that the geo¬
political set-up that emerged was an asset,
even though an accidental one, it never¬
theless created far more problems than it
solved. Though the boundaries of the States
that emerged were not as arbitrary as is
generally believed, there is no doubt that
many of the States that emerged were ar¬
tificial creations made up of a medley of
peoples with different cultures, traditions,
origins and languages. The problems of
nation-building posed by such a medley of
peoples have not proved to be easily
soluble.
Another outcome was that the States that
emerged were of widely differing sizes with
unequal natural resources and economic
potentialities.
Another important but negative political
impact of colonialism was the weakening of
the indigenous systems of government. The '
colonial officials on the spot became, in ef- \
feet, dictators instead of advisers to the <
traditional rulers whom they used to en- ^
force some of the measures deemed obnox- i
ious by their subjects, such as forced ;
labour, direct taxes and compulsory recruit¬
ment of men for the colonial armies. <
Moreover, the spread of the Christian
religion further undermined the spiritual ¡
basis of the authority of the kings.
A product of colonialism which is often
ignored by historians but which has turned
out to be of crucial importance was the
creation of full-time, standing armies.
These armies were originally created, most
of them in the 1880s and 1890s, first for the
conquest and occupation of Africa, then
for the maintenance of colonial control,
and, finally, for the prosecution of global
wars and the suppression of independence
movements in Africa. After the overthrow
of the colonial rulers, these armies were not
disbanded but were taken over by the new
independent African rulers and they have
turned out to be the most problematic of the
products of colonialism.
The final and probably the most impor¬
tant negative political impact of colonialism
was the loss of African sovereignty and in¬
dependence and the right to deal directly
with the outside world.
This meant, above all, the loss of their
right to control their own destiny, to plan
their own development, manage their
economy, determine their own strategies
and priorities, borrow freely from the
world at large the latest and most ap¬
propriate technology, and generally
manage, or even mismanage, their own af¬
fairs and derive inspiration and a sense of
fulfilment from their successes and lessons
and experience from their failures. In short,
colonialism deprived Africans of one of the
most fundamental and inalienable rights of
a people the right of liberty.
Moreover, the seventy-year period of col¬
onialism in Africa was the very period
which witnessed tremendous and decisive
developments and changes in both the
capitalist and socialist countries. It was the
period, for instance, that saw the entry of
Europe into the age of the aeroplane and
the motor vehicle and the nuclear age. Had
Africa been in control of her own destiny,
she could have benefited from or even been
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
"Closely associated with the spread of
Christianity was that of Western education.
Certainly, by the end ofthe colonial regime,
there were relatively few areas without at
least elementary schools... The curricula
provided by these institutions were deter¬
mined by the colonial rulers and were close¬
ly modelled on, if not carbon copies of,
those of the metropolitan countries and
therefore irrelevant to the needs of the con¬
tinent." Right, the Church Missionary
Society High School, Mengo, Uganda.
part of these phenomenal changes. But col¬
onialism completely insulated and isolated
her from these changes and kept her in a
position of dependency.
The impact in the economic field was
equally important and equally mixed. The
first and most obvious of the positive im¬
pacts was the provision of a basic in¬
frastructure of roads, railways, telegraph,
telephone and, in some cases, even airports.
Completed by the 1930s, this infrastructure
facilitated the movement not only of goods,
the new cash crops and troops, but also of
peoples, and this latter factor helped to
minimize parochialism, regionalism and
ethnocentricism.
Equally important and significant was
the impact of colonialism on the primary
sector of the economy. It was during the
colonial period that the full mineral poten¬
tial of Africa was realized; the mining in¬
dustry boomed while the cultivation of cash
crops such as cocoa, coffee, tobacco,
groundnuts, sisal and rubber spread. In
west Africa these cash crops were produced
by the Africans themselves, clear evidence
of their willingness and ability to adapt and
respond to the right incentives.
This economic revolution had some far-
reaching consequences. Before the colonial
era huge tracts of land in many parts of
Africa were not only under-populated but
also under-utilized. The introduction and
spread of cash crops and the mining in¬
dustries put an end to all this. Secondly, the
economic revolution led to an increase in
the purchasing power of some Africans and
with it an increase in their demand for con¬
sumer goods. Thirdly, the growing of cash
crops by Africans enabled individuals of
whatever social status, especially in the
rural areas, to acquire wealth.
Another significant revolutionary impact
was the introduction of the money
economy. This led to the emergence of a
new class of wage earners and salaried
groups. The introduction of the money
economy also led to the commencement of
banking activities in Africa, which became
another significant feature of the economy
of independent African States.
By 1935, the economy of Africa had
become inextricably tied to that of the
world in general and of the capitalist
economy of the colonial powers in par¬
ticular. The years after 1935 merely deepen
ed this link and not even independence has
fundamentally altered this relationship.
Was the colonial impact on Africa in the
economic field then a desirable one? Far
from it.
In the first place, the infrastructure that
was provided by colonialism was not as ade¬
quate or as useful as it could have been.
Most of the roads and railways were con¬
structed not to open up the country but
merely to connect the areas having mineral
deposits and the potential for the produc¬
tion of cash crops with the sea, and there
were hardly any feeder or branch roads.
Nor were they meant to facilitate inter-
African travel and communication.
In the second place, such economic
growth as occurred in the colonies was
based on the natural resources of the area
and this .meant, therefore, that areas not
naturally endowed were totally neglected.
Thirdly, a typical feature of the colonial
economy was the total and deliberate
neglect or discouragement of industrializa¬
tion and the processing of locally-produced
raw materials and agricultural products in
most of the colonies . Simple and basic items
such as matches, candles, edible oil, even
lime and orange juice, all of which could
easily have been produced in Africa, were
imported. All African States were therefore
turned into markets for the consumption of
manufactured goods from the metropolitan
countries and producers of raw materials
for export. This total neglect of in¬
dustrialization by the colonial powers
should be chalked up as one of the most un¬
pardonable indictments of colonialism.
Fourthly, not only was industrialization
neglected but such industries and crafts as
had existed in Africa in pre-colonial times
were almost destroyed as a result of the
importation into Africa of cheap, mass-
produced commodities. African techno¬
logical development was thereby halted and
was not resumed until after independence.
Fifthly, even though agricultural crops
came to constitute the main source of in¬
come for most African States, no attempts
were made to diversify the agricultural
economies of the colonies. On the contrary,
by 1935, the production of only single or, at
best, two cash crops had become the rule
cocoa in the Gold Coast, groundnuts in
Senegal and Gambia, cotton in Sudan, cof¬
fee and cotton in Uganda and coffee and
sisal in Tanganyika. Most African States,
on the attainment of independence, found
themselves saddled with monoculture
economies and were therefore highly sen¬
sitive to the prevailing international trade
winds. Colonialism did indeed complete the
integration of African economies into the
world international economic order, but in
a very disadvantageous and exploitative
manner.
Because of the concentration on the pro¬
duction of cash crops during the colonial
era, Africans were compelled to ignore the
production of food for their own consump¬
tion. It was this neglect of food production,
coupled with forced labour, which caused
so much malnutrition, severe famine and so
many epidemics in some parts of Africa
during the early colonial days. Thus, under
the colonial system, Africans were in most
cases made to produce what they did not
consume and to consume what they did not
produce, clear evidence of the lopsided and
exploitative nature of the colonial
economy.
The colonial presence also led to the ap¬
pearance on the African scene of an increas¬
ing number of expatriate banking, shipping
and trading firms, and from the 1910s on¬
wards their amalgamation and consolida¬
tion into fewer and fewer oligopolies. Since
it was these trading companies that con¬
trolled the export as well as the import trade
and fixed the prices not only of imported
commodities but also of the exports pro¬
duced by Africans, the huge profits that ac¬
crued from these activities went to the com¬
panies and not to the Africans.
Colonialism also virtually put a stop to
inter-African trade as the flow of trade
from each colony was reoriented towards
the metropolitan countries.
Finally, whatever economic growth there
was during the colonial period was achieved
at a phenomenal and unjustifiable cost to
the Africanforced labour, migrant
labour, compulsory cultivation of certain
crops, compulsory seizure of land, forced
movements of populations with the con¬
sequent dislocation of family life, the pass
system, high mortality rates in the mines
and on the plantations and brutal repres¬
sion of the protest and resistance
movements these measures generated.
What is the record of colonialism in the
social field? The first important beneficial
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
During the colonial period, "In the rural
areas, and even to some extent In the urban
centres, new beliefs, new gods, new uten¬
sils, new artifacts arid new objects were
added to the old ones. Certainly, In these
areas many Christians did andstill do retain
their beliefin their traditionalgods. Indeed,
in thefield ofreligion, it was ifanything the
European religions that were Africanized,
as is obviousfrom the rituals ofsome of the
syncretic and mlllenarian churches, and not
the other way round".
Above, Baoulé Gu mask representing the
creator of the universe. The curves of the
mask direct the eye to the mouth, source of
the creative "breath spirit".
"Another highly regrettable social Impact
of colonialism was the deterioration that it
caused in the status of women in Africa...
There does not appear to be any doubt that
women were inhibitedfromjoining in most
of the activities introduced or intensified by
colonialism. The colonial world was indeed
a man's world and women were not en¬
couraged toplay any meaningful role in it. ' '
Below, Fang mask from Gabon.
social effect was the overall increase of the
population of Africa during the colonial
period of nearly forty per cent after an in¬
itial decline during the first two or three
decades. This increase was due to the
establishment of an economic base, the
spread of roads and railways which ensured
that food could be rushed to famine areas,
and the campaigns launched against
epidemic diseases such as sleeping sickness,
bubonic plague and yellow fever.
Closely connected with this was . the
second social impact of colonialism
urbanization. The kingdoms and empires of
Africa had such capitals or political centres
as Kumbi Saleh, Benin, Ile-Ife, Kumasi,
Gao and Zimbabwe, commercial centres
such as Kano, Jenné, Sofala and Malindi,
and such educational centres as Timbuktu,
Cairo and Fez. But there is no doubt that,
as a result of colonialism, the pace of ur¬
banization was greatly accelerated and
completely new towns came into existence.
Moreover, the population of both the
already existing towns and the new towns
grew by leaps and bounds during the col¬
onial era. The population of Nairobi,
founded in 1896 as a transit depot for the
construction of the Uganda railway, in¬
creased from a mere handful to 13,145 in
1927 and to over 25,000 in 1940, and that of
Lagos from 74,000 in 1914 to 230,000 in
1950, that of Dakar from 19,800 in 1916 to
92,000 in 1936 and to 132,000 in 1945.
There was also undoubtedly an improve¬
ment in the quality of life, particularly for
those living in the urban centres. This was
the result of the provision of hospitals,
dispensaries, pipe-borne water, sanitary
facilities, better housing and the abolition
of such practices as domestic slavery by the
colonial rulers as well as the increase in
employment opportunities.
The spread of Christianity, Islam and
Western education was another important
impact of colonialism. It was during the
colonial period that Christianity gained a
firm foothold in eastern and central Africa,
at times following and at times being
followed by the flag and trade. Islam also
spread rapidly in western and eastern
Africa as a result of the general improve¬
ment in communications during the col¬
onial period and the patronage of both the
French and the British rulers. It should be
emphasized that these gains were not made
at the expense of traditional religion. What
colonialism did, then, was to strengthen
and perpetuate religious pluralism in
Africa, thereby enriching its religious life.
Closely associated with the spread of
Christianity was that of Western education.
Certainly, by the end of the colonial regime,
there were relatively few areas without at
least elementary schools. The spread of
Western education had far-reaching social
effects, among which was an increase in the
number of the westernized educated
African élite, an élite which now constitutes
the ruling oligarchy and the backbone of
the civil service of African States.
Another important colonial impact, a
mixed blessing as we shall see, was the pro¬
vision of a lingua franca for each colony or
set of colonies. In all the colonies, the
mother tongue of the colonial power, either
in its pure or pidgin form, became the of¬
ficial and business language and, in many
cases, the main means of communication
between the numerous linguistic groups
that constituted the population of each col¬
ony. It is significant that, except in north
Africa, The United Republic of Tanzania,
Kenya and Madagascar, these languages
have remained the official languages to this
very day.
The final beneficial social impact was the
new social structure that colonialism in¬
troduced into some parts of Africa or
whose development it accelerated in others.
Although the traditional social structure
allowed for social mobility, its class struc¬
ture appeared to give undue weight to birth.
The new colonial order, on the other hand,
emphasized individual merit and achieve¬
ment. All these changes radically altered the
traditional social structure.
Thus, by the 1930s, in place of the pre-
colonial social classes of the traditional
ruling aristocracy, the ordinary people,
domestic slaves and a relatively small
educated élite, a new society emerged that
had become more sharply divided than
before into urban and rural dwellers, each
of which was differently stratified. Mobility
within this new structure was based more on
individual effort and attainment than on
ascription.
On the negative side, however, the
phenomenal growth of the population of
the urban centres was not the result of the
natural increase of the urban population
but rather of the continuous pull of young
men and women to the urban centres by the
need for education and employment and
the push from the rural areas by famine,
epidemics, poverty and taxation.
Moreover, since the Europeans tended to
live in the urban centres, all those facilities
that improved the quality of life were
established only in those areas. The rural
areas were therefore virtually neglected and
this in turn accentuated the drift from one
to the other. A huge gap exists even today
between urban and rural areas in Africa and
there is no doubt that it was the colonial
system that originated and widened this
gap.
Nor did the migrants find the urban cen¬
tres the safe and rich haven they had ex¬
pected. In no town were the Africans ac¬
cepted as equals and fully integrated.
Moreover, nowhere did a majority of them
find jobs or decent accomodation. Most of
them found themselves crowded into the
suburbs and the shanty towns in which
unemployment, juvenile delinquency,
drunkenness, prostitution, crime and cor¬
ruption became their lot. Colonialism did
not only impoverish rural life, it also
bastardized urban life.
A second serious social legacy has been
the European and Asian settler problem.
What made their presence so inimical to
Africans was that the Europeans came to
occupy most of the fertile lands while the
Asians monopolized the retail and
wholesale trades. By 1935, this Asian and
European problem had assumed very
serious proportions for Africa and it has
not been entirely resolved to this day.
Furthermore, though colonialism did in¬
troduce some social services as we have
seen, it must be emphasized that not only
were these services grossly inadequate and
unevenly distributed in each colony, they
were all, by and large, meant primarily for
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
* -
*- fc**
the benefit of the few white settlers and ad¬
ministrators, hence their concentration in
the towns. In Nigeria in the 1930s, whereas
there were 12 modern hospitals for 4,000
Europeans in the country, there were only
52 for Africans numbering over 40 million.
In the field of education, what was pro¬
vided during the colonial days was grossly
inadequate, unevenly distributed and badly
orientated and therefore not so beneficial as
it could have been for Africa. Five different
types of educational institutions were
established under colonial rule: primary,
secondary, teacher-training, technical and
university. But while many primary schools
had been established by 1860 in British
West Africa, it was not until 1876 that the
first secondary schools were established in
the Gold Coast and Nigeria. It was not until
after the Second World War that technical
schools and university colleges were
established in most parts of Africa.
The curricula provided by all these in¬
stitutions were determined by the colonial
rulers and were closely modelled on, if not
carbon copies of, those of the metropolitan
countries and therefore irrelevant to the
needs of the continent. They also struck at
the very roots of African religious beliefs,
sanctions and taboos and thereby shook the
foundations of African societies, bringing
in their trail a sense of uncertainty, frustra¬
tion and insecurity.
The impact of this inadequate, lopsided
and wrongly orientated education on
African societies has been profound and
almost permanent. First, it left Africa with
a huge illiteracy problem, a problem whose
solution will take a long time. Secondly, the
educated élite that was produced was, by
and large, an alienated élite that adored
European culture and civilization and look¬
ed down on African culture. However,
since the élite included the wealthiest people
and since they occupied the highest posts
available both during and after the colonial
era, they came to wield power and influence
out of all proportion to their numbers.
Beneficial as the linguae francae pro¬
moted through the educational systems
were, they had the regrettable consequence
of preventing the development of some of
the indigenous languages into national
languages. Twi, Hausa and Swahili could
easily have been developed as the national
languages of the Gold Coast, Nigeria and
the three British East African colonies
respectively. In fact, an attempt was made
by the colonial administrators of British
East Africa to develop Swahili as a lingua
franca during the 1930s and 1940s, but this
attempt was countermanded by the Col¬
onial Office.
Another highly regrettable social impact
of colonialism was the deterioration that it
caused in the status of women in Africa.
This is a new theme which needs further
research, but there does not appear to be
any doubt that women were inhibited from
joining in most of the activities introduced
or intensified by colonialism. The colonial
world was indeed a man's world and
women were not encouraged to play any
meaningful role in it.
Moreover, under colonialism Africans in
general were looked down upon, humiliated
and discriminated against both overtly and
covertly. In his recent Reith lectures, Ali
Mazrui emphasized this legacy of humilia¬
tion imposed on the African by the triple
sins of the slave trade, apartheid and col¬
onialism when he declared:
"Africans are not necessarily the most
brutalized peoples, but they are certainly
the most humiliated in modern history."
Some historians have concluded that
"colonialism produced its own grave-
diggers", while Maugham has maintained
that "On the tombstone of the British Em¬
pire may be written 'Lost by snobbery".
Worse still was the impact of colonialism
in the cultural field. Throughout the col¬
onial period, African art, music, dancing
and even history were all not only ignored
but positively discouraged or denied. As
one speaker declared at the Second Con¬
gress of Negro Writers and Artists, in
Rome, in 1959: "Among the sins of col¬
onialism, one of the most pernicious,
because it was for a long time accepted by
the West, was the concept of people without
culture."
"The educated élite that was produced [by
colonial education] was, by and large, an
alienated élite that adored European culture
and civilization and looked down on
African culture. However, since the élite in¬
cluded the wealthiest people and since they
occupied the highest posts available both
during and after the colonial era, they came
to wieldpower and influence out ofall pro¬
portion to their numbers." Above, toppers
and frock-coats, picture hats and croquet
on the lawn at Government House, all these
were the status symbols of the "new élite"
of the colonial period.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Ornamental detail on the facade of a tradi¬
tional house of Senegal's Sarakolé people.
Traditional architecture using earth as a
building material has qualities ofform and
insulation that are no longer found in
modern dwellings made of rubble and cor¬
rugated iron sheeting.
Nevertheless, in the cultural field, the im¬
pact of colonialism was relatively speaking
neither profound nor permanent. Such
changes as were introduced in the cultural
field, such racial discrimination as was
practised, and such condemnation of
African culture as was preached, even in the
heyday of colonialism, were all confined to
the coastal areas and the urban centres and
never penetrated into the rural areas where
life ran gaily on very much as before.
African dance, art, music and traditional
religious systems held their own and any
borrowings and adaptations were additions
rather than substitutions.
In the rural areas, and even to some ex¬
tent in the urban centres, new beliefs, new
gods, new utensils, new artifacts and new
objects were added to the old ones. Certain¬
ly, in these areas many Christians did and
still do retain their belief in their traditional
gods. Indeed, in the field of religion, it was
if anything the European religions that were
Africanized, as is obvious from the rituals
of some of the syncretic and millenarian
churches, and not the other way round.
What is more important, the ground that
was lost in the field of culture, even in the
urban centres, has virtually been regained.
Today, African art, music and dance are
not only taught in educational institutions
of all kinds but are now booming in Africa
and gaining recognition in Europe. Thus, as
far as the cultural field is concerned, col¬
onialism was certainly only a brief episode
and its impact skin-deep and ephemeral.
From all the above it should be clear that
it is an over-reaction to write off col¬
onialism as an unmitigated disaster for
Africa that caused nothing but under¬
development and backwardness. Equally
guilty of over-statement are those colonial
apologists who see colonialism as an un¬
qualified blessing for Africa.
But whatever colonialism did for
Africans in Africa, given its opportunities,
its resources and the power and influence it
wielded in Africa at the time, it could and
should have done more. As P.C. Lloyd
wrote:
"So much more might perhaps have been
done had the development of backward ter¬
ritories been seen by the industrial nations
as a first priority."
It is precisely because colonial rulers did
not see the development of Africans as their
first priority or even as a priority at all that
they stand condemned. It is for these two
reasons that the colonial era will go down in
history as a period of growth without
development, of the ruthless exploitation of
the resources of Africa, and, on balance, of
the pauperization and humiliation of the
peoples of Africa.
In the long history of Africa, colonialism
was merely an episode or interlude in the
many- faceted and variegated experiences of
its peoples. It was nonetheless an extremely
important episode politically, economically
and even socially. It marks a clear water¬
shed in the history of Africa whose deve¬
lopment has been and will continue to be
very much influenced by the colonial im¬
pact. The most expedient course of action
for African leaders to embark upon today,
then, is not to write off colonialism, but
rather to be conversant with its impact and
to try to redress its shortcomings and its
failures.
Albert Adu Boahen
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the
editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author's
name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on re¬
quest. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply
coupon covering postage. Signed articles express
the opinions of the «uthors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the
editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier
staff. The boundaries on maps published in the maga¬
zine do not imply official endorsement or acceptance
by Unesco or the United Nations.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform
(microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) University
Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor. Michigan 48100,
U.S.A.: (2) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian Head,
Inc., 111 West 40th Street. New York, U.S.A.; (3)
Bell and Howell Co.. Old Mansfield Road, Wooster,
Ohio 44691. U.S.A.
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
French: Alain Lévêque (Paris)
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov (Paris)
Arabic: Sayed Osman (Paris)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojimo (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: Mohammed Reza Berenji (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salam)
Braille: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slo¬
vene: Vitomir Sudarski (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Servat
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Special projects: Peggy Julien
Ail correspondence should be addressed to the
Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
International Scientific Committee for the Drafting of a General History of Africa
General History of Africa
Some 240 distinguished scholars from many
countries are collaborating on the
monumental eight-volume General History of
Africa which is being prepared under the
intellectual responsibility of a 39-member
International Scientific Committee for the
Drafting of a General History of Africa, two-
thirds of whose members are African. Africa
is considered as a totality in this panoramic
history which shows the changing
relationships between the various parts of
the continent as well as connexions with
other continents, thus bringing out the
contribution Africa has made to the
development of mankind.
Co-published with Heinemann Educational Books
Ltd., United Kingdom, and the University of
California Press, Berkeley, United States, who have
exclusive sales rights in the United Kingdom and
British Commonwealth, and North, Central and
South America respectively; they share sales rights
throughout the rest of the world. Published volumes
available in academic bookshops around the world.
Scheduled for publication this
summer:
Volume IV:- Africa from the Twelfth to the
Sixteenth Century
Editor D.T. Niane
This volume covers a crucial phase in African
history during which the continent developed its
own cultures and written records became more
abundant. Chapters deal with major themes such as
the spread of Islam, the extension of trading and
cultural links and the expansion of kingdoms and
empires, as these relate to different parts of the
continent.
736 pages, 106 black and white plates, 50 figures
and maps, Cased £16.50.
Already published:
Vol. I: Methodology and African Prehistory. 1981,
848 pp. Cased £13.50 (Also published in French,
Arabic, Spanish, and Portuguese; currently being
translated into Kiswahili and Hausa)
Vol. II: Ancient Civilizations of Africa. 1981, 832
pp. Cased £13.50 (Also published in French,
Spanish, and Portuguese; Arabic edition in course
of publication; currently being translated into
Kiswahili and Hausa).
Forthcoming:
III. Africa from the Seventh to the Eleventh
Century
V. Africa from the Sixteenth to the Eighteenth
Century
VI. Africa in the Nineteenth Century until 1880
VII. Africa under Colonial Domination 1880-1935.
Publication scheduled for autumn 1984
VIII. Africa since 1935.
General History of Africa: Studies
and Documents series
Working documents and contributions to meetings
of specialists concerned with the preparation of the
General History of Africa have proved so interesting
that Unesco has decided to publish them in tandem
with the History in a series entitled The General
History of Africa: studies and documents.
Already published:
1 . The Peopling of Ancient Egypt and the
Deciphering of the Meroitic Script, 136 pp. 25 F
2. The African Slave Trade from the Fifteenth to
the Nineteenth Century, 330 pp. 45 F
3. Historical Relations across the Indian Ocean,
203 pp. 36 F
4. The Historiography of Southern Africa, 112
PP. 22 F
5. The Decolonization of Africa: Southern Africa
and the Horn of Africa, 163 pp. 35 F.
Forthcoming:
6. African Ethnonyms and Toponyms
7. Historical and Socio-Cultural Contacts between
Africa and the Arab World
8. Methodology of the Contemporary History of
Africa
9. Africa and the Second World War
1 0. The Educational Process and Historiography in
Africa
1 1 . Libya Antiqua.
Other Unesco publications
The Book Today in Africa, by S.I.A. Kotei. A wide-
ranging inquiry into the current situation regarding
books in Africa. 1981, 210 pp. 32 F.
Rural Journalism in Africa. 1981, 35 pp. 10 F.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
Il ¡s in the Ni'» W orUl more ihun in Lurope
that the African impact has been most far-
reaching. In Ihr Americas the great com¬
munities tit" Ihe African diaspora caused b>
the Iransallan Ik slate I rade hau- simngli
influenced Ihe societies in which lhe> I nok
roui. The black influence un the national
culture of modern Brazil has been par¬
ticular^ profound, and in most Caribbean
socielies Ihe cultures of the black com¬
munities base become preponderani. Bui
Ihe children of the diaspora hate also turn¬
ed lu ihe home continent and plaved a
decisive rule in the hislnr> of modern
Africa: man> returned From exile, while
others influenced Ihe development of na-
tinnalism und pun-Africanism. Ahme, u
macumba cerem»n> in Brazil. This
shamanistic religion (known us candomblé
in Brazil's Bahía State) is based on u syn¬
cretism of Bantu fetishes, Roman t atholic
symbols, and Sudanese rituals.
]]>
</page>
</document>
