<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074686eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The
Unesco
nesco s action plan for the next 6 years
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A time to live...
0 MEXICO Seri maiden
The Seri are a small group of Indians who live on the northwest coast of Mexico not far from Tiburón Island, their
spiritual home. Their main occupations are fishing, catching turtles and gathering shellfish. The Seri have successfully
preserved ancestral customs and beliefs. Some of the women, who wear long brightly-coloured calico dresses, still paint
their faces (above) according to a custom often connected to puberty-rites. The main feature of this facial decoration
is a firm line painted in a bright colour across the bridge of the nose from one cheek-bone to the other. Above this
line, tiny coloured dots form oval or triangular motifs of great complexity.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The,
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
JANUARY 1983 36th YEAR
Published in 26 languages
English Tamil Korean
French Hebrew Swahili
Spanish Persian Croato-Serb
Russian Dutch Macedonian
German Portuguese Serbo-Croat
Arabic Turkish Slovene
Japanese Urdu Chinese
Italian Catalan Bulgarian
Hindi Malaysian
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French and Spanish
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 58 French Francs
Binder for a year's issues: 46 FF
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
ISSN 0041 - 5278
No. 1 - 1983- OPI 82-1 - 394 A
page
21
23
25
28
30
32
l-IV
2
WHERE THE FUTURE BEGINS
by Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
UNESCO'S 14 MAJOR PROGRAMMES,
10 I. REFLECTION ON WORLD PROBLEMS
AND FUTURE-ORIENTED STUDIES
EDUCATION FOR ALL
COMMUNICATION IN THE SERVICE OF MAN
THE FORMULATION AND APPLICATION
OF EDUCATION POLICIES
EDUCATION, TRAINING AND SOCIETY
THE SCIENCES AND THEIR APPLICATION
TO DEVELOPMENT
19 VII. INFORMATION SYSTEMS AND ACCESS
TO KNOWLEDGE
VIII. PRINCIPLES. METHODS AND STRATEGIES
OF ACTION FOR DEVELOPMENT
11 II.
13 III.
15 IV.
16 V.
17 VI.
IX. SCIENCE, TECHNOLOGY AND SOCIETY
X. THE HUMAN ENVIRONMENT AND TERRESTRIAL
AND MARINE RESOURCES
XI. CULTURE AND THE FUTURE
XII. THE ELIMINATION OF PREJUDICE, INTOLERANCE,
RACISM AND APARTHEID
XIII. PEACE, INTERNATIONAL UNDERSTANDING,
HUMAN RIGHTS AND THE RIGHTS OF PEOPLES
XIV. THE STATUS OF WOMEN
THE MEDIUM-TERM PLAN AT A GLANCE
A TIME TO LIVE...
MEXICO: Seri maiden
JJHIS issue of the Unesco
Courier presents in highly
condensed form Unesco's
Medium-Term Plan for the years
from 1984 to 1989. The Plan
charts a general coursefor Unesco
in these years and is not a direct
and detailed programme of
action.
Prepared on the basis of an
analysis of current world prob¬
lems, the Plan is structured, along
intersectoral and hence inter¬
disciplinary lines, aroundfive mis¬
sions which Unesco has under¬
taken to accomplish and which are
in turn divided into fourteen
major programmes.
The 'Medium-Term Plan, the
second in Unesco's history, was
drawn up by the Director-
General, Mr. Amadou-Mahtar
M'Bow, after an unprecedented
survey carried out among
Unesco's 158 Member States and
after consultation with all those
members of the secretariat who
wished to put forward sugges¬
tions. It was then discussed and
ratified by Unesco's Executive
Board, before being amended and
unanimously approved by an Ex¬
traordinary General Conference
convened for this purpose and
held at Unesco headquartersfrom
23 November to 3 December
1982.
On the following pages we pre¬
sent the main thrust of the four¬
teen major programmes which
correspond to the missions
Unesco has set out to fulfil.
An introductory article by
Mr. M'Bow highlights different
aspects of the Plan, afar-reaching
document,which is of unquestion¬
ed importance to anyone wishing
to understand the nature of
Unesco's aims and activities. A
table, printed as a pull-out insert,
provides a synthesis of the Plan.
Finally, to illustrate this special
issue which will be of interest to all
readers who are concerned with
the challenges of current and
future world problems, we pre¬
sent, among other documents, an
evocation ofsome of Unesco 's ac¬
tivities in different parts of the
world.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
WHERE
THE FUTURE
BEGINS
by Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
Director-General of Unesco
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
SINCE Unesco was created thirty-seven years ago as a result
of its founders' determination to provide mankind, in the
sphere of activities of the mind, with the means for
influencing its own future development, the world has changed
profoundly. The international community has expanded
considerably with the emergence of new nations, and mankind has
constantly strengthened its control over the planet and increased its
mental and material powers. Scientific and technological advances,
the successive stages of which have conspicuously marked
development in the last quarter of a century, for instance, enabling
man even to explore space, have considerably improved the lives of
a certain number of peoples and have now given the whole human
race, for the first time in its history, the means of ridding itself of
the major concerns that have preoccupied it since the dawn of
time food, health, shelter, protection against natural calamities,
security.
The spread of education has given more and more people access
to the most varied and advanced forms of knowledge, thus greatly
enhancing the capacity for innovation, and hence the well-being of
many societies. The achievement of political sovereignty by almost
all nations has made possible an extraordinary widening of the
scope for human initiative and liberty and has given each of them
the opportunity to play an active role in a history that will
henceforth be worked out by a collective effort. Exchanges of
goods, capital, knowledge and know-how are becoming more and
more numerous; intellectual and cultural intermixing proceeds
apace; and anxieties, hopes and fears are beginning to converge,
transcending the demarcation lines drawn by history or established
by geography. As all communities are more and more gathered
together within one and the same network of vital relationships and
even mutual dependence, the prospect at last gleams ahead of a
world community joined in unity of purpose and finally reconciled
with itself, where all will be sure of the means to live a better life,
unhampered by fear, and where there will be an ever fuller
flowering of freedoms and creative faculties.
But entire populations are still living in absolute poverty.
Profound inequalities continue to divide peoples and individuals
and the pursuit of progress itself frequently gives rise to
contradictions; uncertainties and doubts. Disturbing harm is being
done to the natural environment. There is mounting tension
between countries and within some countries; life in many societies
is troubled by violence. Instruments of destruction are being further
developed and stockpiled. Nuclear weapons, by their quantity and
destructive capacity, are already capable of annihilating all that
mankind has constructed through thousands of years of effort, and
even mankind itself. Overarming is not only an expression of the
mutual distrust which is advanced to justify it; but it accentuates the
trend towards division of the world into spheres of influence and
leads to military, economic and cultural interference in the lives of
others; and it diverts an enormous volume of resources from the
satisfaction of societies' urgent needs.
One world
From whatever angle one approaches the major questions which
mankind has to answer, one realizes that the future of modern
societies will be enacted in a context now expanding to worldwide
scale.
As a result, societies which had been able to live in almost total
ignorance of each other up to a few decades ago are now in
increasingly regular contact. Reciprocal influences are becoming
ever more numerous and interdependence is becoming a
multidimensional reality. While interdependence is doubtless a
source of mutual enrichment, receptivity, initiative and creativity,
it also leads to frustrations when accompanied by a deterioration in
the lot of some people, a reduction in the scope for mansuvre,
increased unpredictability and greater vulnerability.
The image that emerges from any analysis or effort of reflection
is therefore that of an increasingly complex world in which sources
of friction are on the increase just as the reasons for co-operating
and the means for communicating are becoming stronger.
Asymmetries and inequalities
Economic statistics provide blunt evidence of the scale of the
disparities between nations and groups of nations. But inequalities
also persist within most societies and are in some cases even
becoming more pronounced. The prosperity of many industrialized
countries may conceal an uneven distribution of income, and some
sections of the population in those countries lead a difficult,
sometimes even precarious existence. In the Third World, vast
populations frequently enjoy none of the benefits of progress and
towns and cities in many cases and at least as regards certain social
categories are like islands of modernity cut off from the
hinterland.
The picture of destitution, concentrated for the most part in
countries of the Third World is a familiar one. An age-old word
poverty has today become a central concept of economics. It
betokens serious deficiencies in food, housing, health and
education and an extremely low income level. Depending on the
criteria adopted, it may be reckoned that there are some 800 million
people in the world living in a state of absolute poverty (World
Bank) or about 1,100 million poor (International Labour Office).
Other equally impressive figures have to be taken into account to
form a more detailed picture of various categories of unfulfilled
needs: 430 million people severely undernourished, 1,000 million
badly housed, 1,300 million without adequate access to drinking-
water, and, according to statistics established by Unesco,
814 million adult illiterates and 123 million children of school age
not attending school.
The international economic system
The present situation is really only the most recent stage in a
process that began in the distant past. The rise of certain countries,
the creation of vast colonial empires for their benefit and the
dawning and development within those same countries of the
industrial revolution had the effect of placing them in a position of
economic dominance, which has finally reduced many other parts
of the world to the state described by the concept of "dependence"
set forth in certain economic theories.
Whether politically colonized or not, most "dependent"
countries served as reservoirs of raw materials or specially
favourable markets for the manufactured goods of the dominant
countries. The economies of these countries have thus developed
basically under the pressure of demands originating elsewhere
rather than in accordance with their own needs.
Even today, with the exception of petroleum, the Third World
countries have no control over the prices of the products which
constitute the basis of their exports, nor over the prices of products
which they must import. Many of them are faced with a steadily
deteriorating balance of payments, while their borrowing capacity
is shrinking.
Notwithstanding the different constraints to which they are
subjected and the specificity of their situations, the development of
Third World countries has been conceived, given its basis in theory
and directed, in most cases, by reference to the international
economic situation ' which has been imposed on them.
Underdevelopment has been interpreted as essentially a time-lag in
the various branches of socio-economic activity, as compared with
the situation obtaining in the so-called developed countries, while
development has been seen as a universal process occurring in all
places and at all times in the same sequence of successive "phases".
A progression has thus been envisaged, leading necessarily from the
traditional, predominantly agricultural society towards "modern"
society, frequently described as the "age of consumption", and
inevitably involving, sooner or later, an "economic take-off". This
seems to have been the premiss, explicit or otherwise, behind the
efforts made in the last few decades, an approach which at times
failed to perceive the crucial importance of the constraints imposed
on the developing countries by the international economic system.
It appears, however, that genuine development has to be elicited
from within, willed and conducted by all the vital forces of a nation.
Accordingly, it should encompass all aspects of life and involve all
the energies of a community within which each individual, each p-
*'#-*WVUJlWtJ*
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
^ occupational category and each social group has its part to play in
the general effort and its share in the resulting benefits.
Development cannot therefore be considered solely from the
standpoint of economic performance and the growth of material
goods. No doubt economic growth and the production of material
goods will always be vitally important because of the essential
contribution they alone can make to the general welfare; but they
should serve purposes consciously accepted by all, that enrich
everyone's life, increase the creative capacities of the entire
population and have their roots in culture, with all that it implies
of truth to self and receptivity to progress.
A growing awareness of the importance of the cultural dimension
of development thus emerges as one of the salient facts of our time.
Peace and the arms race
The face of war has changed today. The quantity and destructive
potential of modern nuclear weapons and of chemical and
biological weapons, are such that a conflict between the great
powers, in which such weapons would inevitably be used, would
result in the destruction of the human race. The feature that makes
the present era radically different from previous eras is this capacity
of the human race for self-annihilation. It is a state of affairs
unique in the history of mankind, and one that must be constantly
borne in mind at a time when it is sometimes asserted that with
tactical nuclear weapons, a nuclear conflict could remain localized
and its consequences be surmounted. In practice there is no
guarantee that, once set off, a nuclear conflagration could ever be
contained. The after-effects of atomic explosions would be so
extensive that there would be a strong likelihood of the threshold
being quickly reached where the scale of destruction would prove
lethal for the whole of mankind.
It is against this background that the many localized conflicts
that have occurred since the end of the Second World War,
involving developing countries for the most part and causing the
deaths of millions of people, must be set. Several of those conflicts
have stemmed from the will of the colonized or formerly colonized
peoples to win their independence or to withstand external
pressures that imperil their freedom. Others, admittedly, have more
complex origins confrontations within nations or disputes
between nations but all of them are inevitably aggravated, if not
brought on, by the antagonisms within the world community.
The arms race, originating in many cases« from the will to
predominate or from a sense of insecurity which, far from
mitigating, it aggravates, accelerates under its own momentum. It
has undeniably become a phenomenon which, by virtue of its scale
and implications, dominates the international scene. Total military
expenditure in 1980 may be estimated at over $500 thousand
million a sheer waste of these colossal resources, it may be said,
since they do not enhance the security of those who foot the bill,
the balance tending simply to establish itself at an ever higher level.
It should also be pointed out that the arms race at present ties up
valuable human resources and, especially, very large numbers of
top scientists. If this huge research and development potential were
used for purposes of human welfare, considerable progress could
be made towards solving some of man's major problems, such as
those in the fields of health, education or agricultural production.
Quite obviously, such a redeployment has an ethical dimension and
is one of the major issues in the current debate on the ultimate
purposes of science and technology.
On a more general level, ethical concerns cannot be dissociated
from attempts to build peace, which means considerably more than
the absence of war. Peace has a positive content, demanding as it
does justice in relations between societies and recognition of the
equality in dignity of all peoples and all cultures. It is hence more
particularly synonymous with respect for fundamental human
rights and the freedom of the peoples to make their own decisions.
Human rights
Massive violations of human rights continue; foremost among
them, mention must be made of the apartheid regime that still
prevails in South Africa, despite repeated condemnations by the
international community. That regime continues to institutionalize
racism and to deny, by its very existence, the most fundamental
principle on which human rights are based: the oneness of the
human race and the equal worth of all human beings.
The right of peoples to self-determination is also seriously
flouted. Some peoples are still politically subjugated, as a result of
long-standing, or in some cases recent, historical circumstances.
Many communities are still deprived of the right to an identity.
There are some ten million refugees in the world today; their
situation is particularly grave because of the precariousness of their
living conditions, the fact of their having been uprooted and the
difficulty of finding viable solutions in the prevailing political and
economic circumstances.
No less disquieting is the trend with regard to individual
freedoms, which are jeopardized in various ways, either by blind
terrorism that strikes even at the totally innocent in the name of
particular aspirations or principles, or by the established
authorities. Authorities in many countries have curbed political
liberties and freedom of association and put down opposition
movements. In some cases, the law itself is used to redouble the
attacks upon human rights, for instance by retroactive, repressive
legislation, the widening of the interpretation of national security,
or the institutionalization of emergency measures. There is a
disquieting tendency to "criminalize" opposition by bringing mere
political disagreement within the scope of the penal code.
Furthermore, normal legal safeguards are often set aside, with the
resultant development of various forms of detention without trial.
No less serious, and perhaps even more serious, is the tendency
to adopt, parallel to official and legal repression, procedures
beyond the pale of legality and State power, involving undercover
operations of kidnapping or murder whose perpetrators enjoy a
sort of impunity.
Moreover, although prohibited by legislation in most States,
torture and, more generally, humiliating and degrading treatment
are still practised. In some places they are inflicted, seemingly on
a systematic basis, when suspects are arrested and during their
interrogation and detention.
But not even the denunciation of violations of human rights is
unaffected by the political rifts in the world. For instance, the very
people who habitually express indignation at certain actions tend to
minimize others that are equally serious, because the regimes
responsible for them share their view of the world or serve their
interests. The danger with such attitudes to violations of human
rights is that they may lull consciences into acquiescence; they must
be countered by an unconditional insistence on respect for human
rights, irrespective of the political judgements that may be passed
on particular situations. Individual freedoms and the freedom of
peoples are two sides of the same coin. These problems, like (hose
of development and peace, concern each human being and the
entire human race.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
WHERE THE FUTURE BEGINS
The environment and natural resources
There is another area in which complex networks of interactions
now appear to bind the fate of the individual inextricably to the
collective future of mankind: this is the relationship between man
and nature. Attention is now also focused, as the result of a new
awareness which has become especially marked over recent
decades, on the pressure that man's activities, based on
technological advance, exert on the environment, either through the
unchecked eating-up of resources and of space, or through the
production of wastes that the natural environment can no longer
absorb without suffering far-reaching effects. The major risks
emerging in the relationship between man and nature are the
exhaustion or scarcity of certain non-renewable resources essential
for human activities and irreversible damage that might jeopardize
the balance of the biosphere.
These concerns must be seen in the context of problems of society
and development which are of decisive importance as regards the
environment. Underlying all these problems, in fact, are the forms
of production and consumption of the industrial societies. In the
purely technical and economic logic of industrialization as it has
generally been conceived, the environment and natural resources
are treated simply as instruments serving economic growth. The
pursuit of quick and high -returns means that the cost of
environmental damage is overlooked. Society as a whole,
considered either nationally or internationally, then has to bear
costs which are entirely neglected in any economic reckoning. This
type of behaviour, which leads to unrestrained and what might
fairly be termed unscrupulous exploitation of natural resources,
gives rise to serious damage. In many Third World countries, it
entails an overworking of natural resources that is detrimental in
the long term, whether they be living resources, like forests and fish
stocks, or mineral resources occurring in finite quantities.
But situations of underdevelopment, in themselves, also have
unfortunate implications for the environment. Poverty leads to
over-use or irrational use of the productive capacities of
ecosystems, of soil, water and wood. It also leads to uncontrolled
extension of urbanization, which has today become a major
problem in many countries.
Environmental problems can never be considered apart from the
present forms of the international division of labour and the
constraints imposed by the international economic system. Control
by the developing countries over their own natural resources is,
incidentally one of the main lines of emphasis in efforts to bring
about a new international economic order.
But this objective cannot be dissociated from the idea of a global
environmental ethic based on wise use of the resources that the
planet offers to men and that human ingenuity succeeds in
discovering and turning to account.
Such an aim may in the long term imply changes in the manner
in which resources are used in most countries of the world,
eventually involving far-reaching changes in behaviour and
recognition of the primacy of such values as solidarity and equity,
in application not merely to people alive today but to those who will
come after us, as opposed to behaviour guided solely by immediate
self-interest.
Communication between people and
between cultures
Recent developments have made the world more and more one
as regards communication and exchanges between people and bet
ween cultures. Countless communication networks have grown up
as production, management and organization technologies have
spread throughout the world, with the intensive circulation of pro¬
ducts and people, the rapid strides made by telecommunications
and data processing, and the huge increase in the volume of
messages put out all over the world by the mass media.
These technologies are playing a part in transforming societies
and causing them to move towards ever greater complexity. Com¬
munication and information may in fact be regarded as the nervous
system of contemporary societies: they are essential to their ac¬
tivities, particularly in economic matters, and play an essential part
in financial transactions and banking and in the development of
trade, of land, sea and air transport, of health or public administra¬
tion systems, and of military systems. Any political power is of
necessity placed at the centre of a complex communication and in¬
formation system, since decision-making increasingly necessitates
consideration of more and more constantly changing items of infor¬
mation, and since, furthermore, any policy needs to be explained
and commented on if- it is to gain acceptance. Some people con¬
sequently consider that tomorrow's economy will be one based
mainly on information, and that information is in the process of
becoming the key resource marked out for a major role still more
decisive than that of raw materials and energy.
This makes the very great disparities in the different countries'
situations as regards their communication and information capaci¬
ty all the more serious. The least well equipped countries, especially
the developing countries, are deprived of some of the most effective
means of controlling the various aspects of the development pro¬
cess. The development of communication and information in the
developing countries, which is generally recognized to be necessary
by the international community today, is therefore a prime pre¬
requisite for the advent of a world of greater equity and solidarity
and for the free development of democracy within the various
societies. If they were better able to communicate and to acquire
and impart information, the developing countries could not only
make their voices heard more effectively in international affairs but
could also make more progress in education particularly in the
struggle against illiteracy and could develop their scientific and
technological potential, improve their health systems, promote
rural development, and be in a better position to deal with natural
disasters. Communication and information can also help those
countries, and indeed all others, to consolidate national unity,
preserve their cultural identity and make provision for greater par¬
ticipation by the public in the changes currently taking place.
It seems essential, therefore, to do away with the obstacles that
prevent people and nations from gaining access to all sources of in¬
formation and from directly expressing their own points of view, as
also to avoid the distortions which compromise the dignity and in¬
dependence of peoples. In this context, it is clearly important to
foster the development of all forms of communication and infor¬
mation in all countries, and particularly in the developing coun¬
tries, and. to encourage efforts to discover and apply innovations
which will allow of readier adaptation of structures and content for
the purposes of different categories of users, the compiling of infor¬
mation with broader participation by the public, and greater diver¬
sification in cultural expression.
Science, technology and society
Existing modern technologies already confer enormous powers
upon man, and their potential is such that many of the problems
confronting human societies could be solved if they were ^
3
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
systematically employed. The prospects opened up by modern
science are therefore full of new promise.
To obtain a clearer picture of these prospects, it is important to
note that very profound upheavals have reshaped the map of the
scientific world and the relations between the various sciences. This
development and its practical implications are bound to exert a
strong influence on scientific and technological strategies. A new
configuration of fields of knowledge could be said to be forming,
in which the branches of the future appear to be biology, data pro¬
cessing, systems theory and the communication and information
sciences. We are thus witnessing nothing less than a scientific and
technological revolution, which seems capable of transforming not
only methods of production and patterns of consumption but men¬
talities and social practices as well. It is even tending to efface, to
some extent at least, the old-established demarcation lines between
the natural sciences and the social and human sciences. We are
perhaps living in an era in which cross-over points are emerging bet¬
ween the major fields of human creativity: among the various scien¬
tific disciplines and between them and culture.
Although considerable efforts have been made, much more re¬
mains to be done in order to find appropriate solutions to the prob¬
lems of energy supply, food, housing, transport, leisure or the
management of the environment still encountered in all societies in
different forms and degrees. The bulk of scientific and
technological potential is still concentrated in a limited number of
countries which alone possess the means for conducting research in
certain fields, especially the advanced fields, and therefore hold the
keys, so to speak, to the major advances of the future. Moreover,
the lines of emphasis in research and the choice of fields in which
it is applied are determined primarily by the needs and problems of
the countries that are already best provided for which adds to
their accumulated wealth of scientific and technological
knowledge, while the existing stock of knowledge and know-how is
still inaccessible to most developing countries.
Science must be used to increase the well-being of all peoples.
This presupposes a freer and more intensive flow of information
and knowledge concerning both science and technology, a
worldwide concerted effort to make scientific research more rele¬
vant to the needs of the whole of mankind, and to ensure in all
countries, the developing countries in particular, their own develop¬
ment of science and technology. On this last point, it should be
stressed that scientific and technological development must come
about as a result of a set of complex interactions between the need
for scientific and technological solutions to economic and social
problems, on the one hand, and, on the other, efforts to train
researchers and specialists and to organize scientific research and
experimental development programmes.
Cultural identity
The need to rethink development, and to invent new strategies to
take account of what is distinctive in each nation's way of life and
culture and to call into play the enterprise of all the individuals and
groups that go to make it up, is becoming all the more urgent today
because of the tendency towards uniformity that is developing and,
in many countries and among many sections of the population, im¬
pinging upon life-styles and modes of thought and on the organiza¬
tion of the social, individual and family environment. This tenden¬
cy results less from a convergence of the different values of civiliza¬
tion than from the predominance of certain centres propagating the.
knowledge, know-how and social usages specific to the best
endowed societies. The very fact of the growing oneness of the
world in economic, social and cultural matters is bringing certain
needs and aspirations to the fore, in more and more environments
and within various societies, and causing them all to follow the
same model, based on goods and services produced and distributed
throughout the world. In every area of life from food to clothing,
from transport to leisure the same patterns of consumption are
tending to spread. This tendency is enhanced by the media and the
cultural industries which are extending it into cultures, ideas and
ways of seeing or depicting the world.
This logic of growing uniformity favours certain lines in the pur¬
suit of knowledge to the detriment of other forms; it imposes cer¬
tain aesthetic or ethical values; it stimulates the growth of certain
areas of activity, encourages certain talents and modes of feeling
and ignores others. Whole sectors of creativity are thus repressed,
societies mutilated in their individuality and their distinctive struc¬
ture. Carried to the extreme, this logic could lead to mankind's
becoming ossified, since diversity, if accepted on a footing of com¬
plete equality, is indeed an essential and fertile source of vitality
alike for individual societies and for the whole world.
The growing homogeneity that world uniformity based on a
single model would produce could well leave all humankind bereft
of the means to face unknown or new dangers. Who can say
whether a given culture or a given genetic feature, now lost beneath
the ruins of traditional societies, may not have been an integral part
of a heritage and perhaps essential to the further progress of
humanity? Nor can we rule out the possibility that one day the
global technological society might perish from entropy, for lack of
a sufficient differentiation between cultures.
These would appear to be the historical implications in reaction
to the growing globalization of fundamental social processes and
the pressures towards uniformity brought to bear on the individual
or collective mentality of the reawakening of specificities, which
is the manifestation of a now overriding demand, that of identity,
which can be seen everywhere in the world and which in some coun¬
tries links up with the efforts successfully carried out or more
recently undertaken to enhance the status of the national culture.
In this respect, it is significant that the demand for cultural identi¬
ty, first voiced in certain parts of Europe in the nineteenth century
and which crystallized the aspirations of the young nations former¬
ly under colonial rule for whom the conquest or reconquest of
their mutilated past represented the most precious achievement in
the struggle for independence should now be raised again in the
industrialized societies, where the need to preserve or to revitalize
regional or ethnic identities is increasingly felt. In all regions,
cultural identity appears now as one of the chief driving forces of
history, representing neither a fossilized heritage nor a mere collec¬
tion of traditions, but an internal dynamic, a process whereby a
society continually creates itself, nourished by internal diversities
consciously and voluntarily accepted, and welcoming, assimilating
and if necessary transforming contributions received from
elsewhere.
Far from coinciding with withdrawal into an immutable, self-
enclosed past, it promotes a lively, original and constantly renewed
synthesis. Identity thus appears increasingly to be the sine qua non
of progress for individuals, groups and nations, for it is the force
that animates and underpins the collective will, that gathers to itself
the internal resources for action, and that turns necessary change
into creative adaptation. More and more linguistic, religious,
cultural and occupational groups are accordingly asserting their in¬
dividuality and strengthening their internal bonds. The protection
of their specific identities seems to be the first step towards the
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
WHERE THE FUTURE BEGINS
regaining of their creative faculties, their inventiveness and ability
to participate in a world that has tended to efface them. It should
in no way be interpreted as a mere revitalization of former values,
but betokens chiefly a search for new cultural designs whereby to
carry on from rehabilitation of the past by an awareness of increas¬
ed responsibility for the future.
Uncertainties and the renewal of values
While it is now clearly appreciated that economics cannot be the
only criterion in development, that other objectives must be defined
and that new methods, modelled more closely on the requirements
and aspirations of the community must be invented, the striking
feature of many contemporary societies is extreme diversity in the
behaviour, demands and aspirations of individuals and groups, and
the juxtaposition, at times, of different scales of values. This diver¬
sification in systems of standards is no doubt connected with the
development of societies and changes within them but it is also con¬
nected, in part, with the increasing flow of goods, services,
technologies and messages from one part of the world to another.
In most countries of the Third World, a host of needs and new
motivations are appearing, based on the systems of standards and
values specific to certain industrialized societies. The combination
of new aspirations and traditional loyalties produces divided values
in certain regions, within certain families and even in the hearts of
more and more individuals. The sharp division between modernity
and the underlying cultures appears in many countries to be open¬
ing a gulf between those who have integrated into the new world
and those to whom it remains foreign, thus aggravating the
polarization between groups, between town and country and bet¬
ween the industrialized and rural sectors.
In the past few years, however, there have in a number of coun¬
tries been attempts to rebuild society on the basis of a revival of its
most deeply rooted cultural values. It is this aspiration that is im¬
parting fresh impetus to the spiritual, religious or mystic
movements through which part of the population in those countries
is seeking to re-establish links with an ethic of solidarity and mutual
assistance. It is this, too, that is inspiring certain peoples with the
determination to build their own version of modernism, by reinter¬
preting tradition so as to identify its creative features. This ambi¬
tion calls for an endeavour to renovate social standards and prac¬
tices by drawing on those cultural traditions and traditions of work,
and aesthetic or moral values, that will enable the society to make
room for progress without self-betrayal, and by rejecting all those
traditions and values that would shut it into a past offering no way
forward.
Questionings and new approaches are also appearing, for dif¬
ferent reasons and in other forms, in a number of industrialized
societies where more and more groups, particularly among the
young, are tending to adopt new attitudes towards income and
social success, work and leisure, and the man-made and natural en¬
vironments. New aspirations are emerging and giving rise to a
greater demand for decentralization and participation; to an at¬
tempt to find a new, settled place in small communities, whether
geographical, professional, religious or linguistic; to a lesser em¬
phasis on order and even on economic security, and to a desire for
emancipation vis-à-vis anything that may have a centralizing func¬
tion. Are these changes the forerunners of an imminent transforma¬
tion in the axiological systems of certain industrialized societies? It
is difficult to assess either their scope or their precise significance
because of the extreme diversity of the attitudes involved, their
uncertain and often ambiguous or contradictory nature, and the
heterogeneity of the aspirations they reveal.
In some countries social movements of a new kind are emerging,
bringing into the political arena and the sphere of collective action
matters hitherto regarded as strictly private, like birth, old age,
housing, environment and communication. Associations that cut
across the usual social barriers are being set up women's groups
or clubs for "senior citizens", neighbourhood co-operatives, con¬
sumer or user associations, and groups getting together for leisure
activities or work which are experimenting with novel types of
cultural activity and often introducing new relationships between
the economic and political spheres. As a result, new issues now have
their spokesmen in society, while cultural production is linked once
more with social production as in the past.
All these ventures show that people are radically challenging the
established order and exploring new avenues in a great variety of
ways, which may denote a revival of social creativity.
Between breakdown and renewal, therefore, a fundamental
challenge arises and will no doubt face a large number of
societies and the international community itself in the coming
years: how, with the growing complexity of forms of organiza¬
tion and production systems, to reconcile the demand for the
cohesion and effectiveness needed both nationally and interna¬
tionally for action to promote development with the demands
for a share in initiative and creativity that are often voiced? The
movement towards a diversification of systems of references, in
reaction against the trend towards uniformity and conditioning,
is undoubtedly indicative of the intrinsic vitality of contem¬
porary cultures. It may herald a regeneration, on condition
however that more appropriate forms of communication and
exchange are established, within a context of greater justice,
among societies and within those very societies, among social
groups separated by their differing loyalties and aims, and
among nations which must arrive at mutual understanding and
reach agreement on the co-operative actions which are called for
and indeed demanded by the world today.
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
The Fourth Extraordinary Session of the General Conference of Unesco, at which the Organization's Medium-Term Plan for the
period 1984 to 1989 was unanimously approved, was held in Paris from 23 November to 3 December 1982.
In an effort ofjoint reflection, one hundred andfive Member States, nineteen in¬
tergovernmental organizations, and eighty-three non-governmental organizations
have set forth considerations on the problems currently facing humanity, couched
in different terms but also revealing a remarkable convergence. Thus Unesco 's pro¬
grammes are indebted to the overall thrust of these contributions; a diversity of
viewpoints set in a unifyingframework has dictated thefourteen majorprogrammes
that define Unesco 's action.
I. World problems: Reflection
and future-oriented studies
THE purpose of this major programme is to strengthen
Unesco's role as a "think tank" which collects, analyses
and compares reflections and studies carried out in the
different regions and which concern the situation in the world
today, the trends emerging in all fields that affect the lives of
peoples, their progress and their co-operation in a word, the
destiny of mankind. The spirit in which this work will be carried
out will be one of rigorous independence from any partisan
position but also of a will to make room for the diversity of in¬
tellectual currents, for the sensibilities specific to different
cultures and for ideas from the most varied horizons, while
drawing inspiration from a vision centring on Unesco's lofty
ideals.
It consists of two sections: the first involves the analysis of
work already completed outside the Organization on the study
of the general situation at present and of prospects for the
future and methodological works aimed at identifying the place
of educational, scientific, cultural, communication and infor¬
mation factors in the overall analysis of world problems. The
second section is devoted to an international. future-oriented
study which should constitute an original contribution by
Unesco to international future-oriented reflection. Special em-
10
phasis will be placed on the cultural dimension of future
developments, taking account of different cultures' particular
viewpoints.
It seems more than ever necessary that all communities and
their individual members should become fully aware of the im¬
plications for the future of decisions adopted today. This would
make it easier to take preventive action in all fields so as to be
forearmed against any future intensification of existing pro¬
blems and to take steps in good time to avoid any exacerbation
of impending difficulties. Of course, a large number of future-
oriented studies are being conducted throughout the world, but
they are often prompted by specific considerations relating to
only one sector of community life or by a concern to help for¬
mulate the strategies, chiefly in the economic field, of a par¬
ticular State or group of States. There seems to be a paramount
need for an approach that transcends sectoral or regional con¬
siderations and makes full allowance for the social and cultural
dimensions of problems.
In implementing this major programme, much will depend on
the contribution of the social and human sciences and of
philosophical reflection: the latter is very likely to find its main
field of application at Unesco in this area in the next few years.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
IL Education for ail
IN spite of a decrease in the world illiteracy rate, the absolute
number of adult illiterates is still growing, notably because
of the population increase. There were 760 million il¬
literates in 1970, 814 million in 1980 and, if present trends con¬
tinue, there will be 900 million illiterates towards the end of the
century. Illiteracy can thus be regarded as a major challenge to
the international community.
But the democratization of education is not simply a matter
of quantity. The aim must be to ensure "equal opportunity for
all" by giving the "best opportunities to each".
The extension of education
One of Unesco's main priorities in its action over the next ten
years will be to foster the development and renewal of primary
education, coupled with literacy training for adults. This should
be intensified and closely associated with formal education,
which retains all its importance. However, there is often a need
for it to be better adapted to local requirements so as to avoid
any break with the rural world.
The aim will be at one and the same time to develop educa¬
tional facilities in the most deprived areas, to mobilize all
available resources, to stimulate the effective co-operation of
the whole community and to promote innovative approaches.
Special importance will be attached to the training of personnel
able to teach children, to run adult literacy programmes and to
promote innovative activities aimed at facilitating the entry of
young people who haye left school into the world of work.
The democratization of education
The second plank in the strategy will be to place the principles
of equity and justice at the very core of educational action. The
Organization will continue to fight against all forms of
discrimination in education and to assist in promoting measures
to enable the most disadvantaged social groups to exercise their
right to education.
The democratization of education appears to be inseparable
from lifelong education. This implies the broadening of educa¬
tional possibilities to be made available at every stage of life to
those who have not had access to the school and university
system and who wish to complete their education.
In the context of lifelong education, adult education takes on
a new importance as a means of achieving both personal fulfil¬
ment and vocational recycling. Special attention will be paid to
increasing adults' job mobility, in particular through co¬
operation between adult education bodies and workers' and
employers' organizations. Furthermore, one of the most impor¬
tant tasks of adult education is to prepare adults for the exercise
of their civic responsibilities and the management of communi¬
ty affairs, making use of the educative support of the means of
communication.
Not only does lifelong education imply educative activities
for the elderly, it also involves the development of pre-school
education which, among other things, enables compensation to
be made for certain socio-economic and socio-cultural
disadvantages.
The education of women
Girls and women are still in the minority in education in many
countries and the proportion of girls and women tends to
decrease progressively as the level of education rises.
One of the most urgent problems, however, is still that of il¬
literacy among women (in 1980 33.9 per cent of women aged
15 years and over were illiterate, as against 23.3 per cent of
men) which may have particularly harmful effects on the future
of the younger generations.
Here Unesco's activities, carried out on a broad inter¬
disciplinary basis, will draw on the social and human sciences
in order to demonstrate the economic, social or cultural factors
which, in different contexts, impede the access of girls and
women to, and their participation in, education. It will also aim
to highlight the effects, on education itself, of the relatively
large proportion of women in the teaching profession.
Unesco will co-operate with Member States in order to assist
them in framing policies to reduce the number of illiterate
women. Assistance will be provided for the improvement of na¬
tional educational and vocational guidance services as part of
the programme to promote equal access for girls and women to
scientific studies at all levels of technical and vocational
education.
The villagers of Ban Nong Pai in north¬
east Thailand voluntarily gave their
time to build this experimental child
care centre. The basic design was
prepared by Unesco but modified by
the villagers to make the best use of
locally available materials. UNICEF
helped with the purchase of materials
the villagers could not obtain
themselves.
Photo John Beynon, Unesco, ROEAP, Bangkok
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Education in rural areas
In many countries, most people live in the rural areas. Here
the problem is to increase the number of schools and univer¬
sities established in rural areas and to improve the quality of
rural educational services. In rural zones, schools and univer¬
sities are often too distant from the homes of children and
young people, many schools do not offer a complete educa¬
tional cycle, many teachers have only meagre qualifications and
school buildings and materials are often inadequate. The task
is to ensure an improved contribution of education to the
In 1978, after the liberation struggle, 52 per cent of -the adult
population of Nicaragua was illiterate. In 1980, aided by Unesco
and the international community, the Nicaraguan Government
launched a national literacy campaign, mobilizing some 270,000
volunteers to form the People's Literacy Army. Within six months
more than 400,000 people had been taught to read and write and
the illiteracy rate had been reduced to 13 per cent. Above, a team
of literacy teachers in Nicaragua.
Unesco co-operates with UNRWA (the United Nations Relief and
Works Agency for Palestine Refugees in the Near East) in providing
educational services for Palestinian refugees in the Near East.
Right, lessons begin again in a school in Chatila camp, Lebanon,
after the massacres which horrified the world.
A remarkable effort has been made in the developing countries over
the past two decades to increase enrolment in school. At the
primary level, the enrolment ratio increased from 61 per cent in
1960 to 86 per cent in 1980. But soaring populations have com¬
pounded the difficulties. As the drawings, below, illustrate
graphically, to maintain an enrolment ratio of 86 per cent in the year
2000 the numbers actually enrolled would have to increase by
some 50 per cent, and by 75 per cent if a 100 per cent enrolment
ratio was to be achieved.
1980
Enrolment ratio
2000
Enrolment ratio
development of rural areas and to increase its relevance to the
needs of local populations, whilst avoiding any division bet¬
ween "urban education" and "rural education".
The handicapped, refugees, migrants
Unesco's aim will be to help certain groups to overcome the
obstacles which prevent them from exercising their right to
education to the full. Action will stress measures to detect and
prevent handicaps and will pay special attention to educating
the parents of disabled children, informing the public of the
problems raised for individuals and societies by the integration
of disabled persons and of the solutions that have been found
to these problems, and applying special educational methods
adapted to specific needs.
There are ten million refugees in the world, of whom five
million are in Africa. Unesco will continue to co-operate with
UNRWA on the education programme for Palestine Refugees
in the Near East. It will provide technical support for the HCR's
(United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees) educational
activities for refugees and will encourage the governments of
host countries to introduce special curricula for refugees into
their education system. Unesco's educational assistance to na¬
tional liberation movements will be expanded and focused
above all on making the right to education a reality.
A major problem is that of migrant workers and their
families. Action will be concerned with adapting second-
generation migrants to the living conditions of the host
country chiefly by helping them to obtain a command of the
language and preparing them to integrate subsequently in
their home countries. Special attention will be given to the
teaching of the mother tongue, and to the mutual recognition
of degrees and diplomas. Other activities will seek to provide
immigrant children with special instruction to keep them in
touch with the cultural values of their countries of origin.
Photo UNRWA
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
III. Communication
in the service of man
COMMUNICATION is increasingly tending to become a
complex system of signalling and conditioning that
strengthens the power of the major organizations both
public and private, national and international. These organiza¬
tions have far greater opportunities to exert their influence and
to take action than do individuals and groups who possess only
piecemeal information. This is a source of considerable cultural
power, which, it may be anticipated, might even eventually ex¬
ercise control over both the political and the economic forces.
The consequences may be all the more serious for the freedom
of individuals and the life of societies, and for the relationships
between them, in that information and the media by which it is
transmitted through public, private and/or commercial bodies
can be manipulated in a number of ways. Information can be
used to perpetuate preconceived ideas, to reinforce ignorance
and contempt even intolerance for others, just as it can be a
fertile source of mutual understanding and respect.
Obviously, it is not Unesco's business to dictate to the media
what they are to transmit, but it is entitled to stimulate and en¬
courage the use of the media to promote development in educa¬
tion, science and culture.
Studies on communication
In view of the speed of technological change, continuing
research is called for into the socio-cultural, economic and
juridical aspects of communication, as well as its future. This
research will be carried out in accordance with three guidelines.
The first (Development of research) aims to strengthen na¬
tional and regional institutions, facilitate the dissemination of
results, improve the methodology of studies and make them
more comparable, and increase facilities for the training, fur¬
ther training and exchange of researchers. Studies will also be
undertaken on the nature and characteristics of the "informa¬
tion society" which is gradually emerging, and of its political,
economic and social implications.
The second consists of investigating in depth the idea of the
right to communicate, for both the individual and the com¬
munity, and its various components (the right to be informed,
the right to inform, the right to privacy, the right of access to
administrative documents); promoting free access to informa¬
tion sources and participation by the public in decision-making
concerning communication; studying the operation of
mechanisms for the production and dissemination of messages.
The third is designed to contribute towards preparing and im¬
proving planning and programming methods which can be ap¬
plied to the development of communication, taking into ac¬
count the diversity of cultural environments and socio¬
economic systems.
Free and balanced information
Freedom of information includes the freedom of individuals
and groups to organize the collection, flow and dissemination
of news, ideas and programmes, and to participate therein as
well as freedom of access to all means of communication and
all the various official and unofficial sources of news and pro¬
grammes. The exercise of this freedom still encounters
numerous obstacles of all sorts throughout the world
political, legal, economic, financial and technical including all
forms of censorship and self-censorship which hinder the en¬
dogenous and pluralist production of books, newspapers, news
and programmes, curb their free flow and restrict the growth
and diversification of exchanges.
However, freedom implies a heavy responsibility on the part
of communicators, be these individuals or public or private cor¬
porate bodies. All those involved in communication and
information journalists, press agencies, book, newspaper and
magazine publishers, mass media proprietors, manufacturers
of audio-visual materials, radio and television organizations
have a duty of truthfulness, accuracy and fairmindedness
towards the community. The special situation enjoyed by com¬
municators calls for professional integrity and a conscientious
and ethical approach to one's work, which also guarantee the
protection of individuals and the public. The mass media could
make an important contribution in scrutinizing all actions
which might lead to abuses of power.
The communication media are incomparable instruments for
achieving respect for both individual and collective human
rights. The media can defend principles and bring to light viola¬
tions, as impartially as possible, wherever they occur.
Three programmes of action are envisaged for a free flow and
a wider and better balanced dissemination of information.
The first sets out to identify and gain a fuller understanding
of the nature of the obstacles to the international flow and to
suggest the means of reducing or overcoming them, particularly
by studying professional practices in the book industry, the
press, news broadcasting services, radio and television
organizations, and the cinema industry, etc.
The second concerns the public and private mechanisms for
the exchange of books, news and programmes at national,
regional and world levels. It is designed to stimulate the creation
and building-up of public or private press agencies, to improve
the efficiency of systems for the gathering and distribution of
news, as well as that of regional news exchange networks, and
to foster the local production of books, newspapers, radio and
television programmes and films, particularly in developing
countries, in order to reduce the existing disparities in the
capacity to produce, process and disseminate information.
A third thrust is designed to encourage the contribution of the
media to ensuring mutual respect, international understanding
and peace, and to the solution of major world problems on the
part of those in charge of communication by means of action
designed to develop awareness among those who influence
public opinion.
The development of communication
Political determination is indispensable to enable every form
of communication to play its full role at national, regional and
world levels, ranging from traditional interpersonal forms to
the most modern examples, and to strengthen endogenous
capability, particularly in the developing countries, and, at the
same time, promote their self-reliance so that the disparities
that exist between the different countries and regions in this do¬
main will be gradually eliminated.
Seven action programmes:
The first provides for co-operation with States and organiza¬
tions responsible for communication in formulating national
communication development policies in respect of the
infrastructures equipment and personnel to be set up and
training activities for such staff.
The second covers co-operation with States and organizations
responsible for communication in the choice and acquisition of
equipment corresponding to the needs of the population and the
different media in each country or region; and in seeking
technologies in keeping with the conditions obtaining in these
countries, and in the local development and production of the
corresponding equipment.
The third (Training and further training of communication
specialists and technicians) provides for co-operation with
Member States, other organizations in the United Nations
system and international governmental and non-governmental
organizations of world or regional scope, with a view to
strengthening at national, regional and world levels the
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
The world and the media
The huge disparities that exist at international level in the production and circulation
of messages and programmes is today a recognized fact. In 1978, the developing
countries, representing 70 per cent of the world's population, commanded only a
small fraction of the media of communication: 22 per cent of book titles published,
17 per cent of total newspaper circulation, 9 per cent of newsprint consumption,
27 per cent of radio transmitters, 1 8 per cent of radio receivers, 5 per cent of televi¬
sion transmitters and 12 per cent of television receivers. The figures in terms of
number of inhabitants were the following:
DEVELOPING COUNTRIES INDUSTRIALIZED COUNTRIES
Newspapers 36 copies per 1 ,000 inhabitants 321 copies per 1,000 inhabitants
Paper 1.2 kg per inhabitant 18.2 kg per inhabitant
Book titles 37 per million inhabitants 450 per million inhabitants
Cinema seats 1 1 per 1 ,000 inhabitants 63 per 1 .000 inhabitants
Radio sets 89 per 1 ,000 inhabitants 762 per 1 ,000 inhabitants
TV sets 24 per 1 ,000 Inhabitants 322 per 1 ,000 inhabitants
Far from diminishing, these disparities, which also affect certain industrialized coun¬
tries, have on the contrary been constantly increasing as technology has developed.
Disparities between rural and urban areas are also particularly marked throughout
the world.
..
Above, woman worker in a printing plant pro¬
ducing literacy teaching materials in Addis
Ababa (Ethiopia).
Photo D. Roger, Unesco
structures and methods of initial preparation, general training
and further professional training of communication personnel
at all levels (managers, directors and producers of film, radio
and television programmes, editors and journalists working for
the press, press agencies and broadcasting, publishers,
booksellers, graphic artists and personnel connected with book
manufacturing, engineers and technicians working for the
various media, maintenance personnel, archivists, documen-
talists, printers, etc.), bearing in mind the requirements created
by the increasing specialization entailed by technical progress
and the need to increase the proportion of women among com¬
munication personnel.
The fourth seeks to establish or strengthen endogenous
capacity for the production of printed materials, news and pro¬
grammes in all media, in order: to increase the self-reliance of'
the developing countries in this domain by encouraging the im¬
plantation of local cultural and communication industries; to
facilitate the establishment of appropriate structures for
lifelong education and distance education, which are essential in
ensuring the general provision of primary education and the
eradication of illiteracy; to contribute to the dissemination of
culture, the assertion of cultural identity and to cultural
development in general; and to use communication resources
for the popularization or science.
The fifth (Action to promote books and reading) consists in
promoting books and encouraging reading in all societies.
Special attention will be given to works which may be of use for
literacy and post-literacy work. A further aim is to encourage
the international dissemination of books, emphasis being plac¬
ed on their circulation within and between developing regions
and on their flow from such regions to the industrialized
countries.
14
Left, young pupils in a primary school
established by Unesco near Kabul (Afgha¬
nistan). Unesco's Medium-Term Plan provides
for a programme to promote books and en¬
courage reading in all societies. Special atten¬
tion will be given to material which may be us¬
ed in literacy and post-literacy teaching.
Photo H. Fehl, Unesco
The sixth (Action to promote the cinema and the audio-visual
media) seeks- to promote the development of the cinema,
photography and television in each country, in particular for
the purposes of formal and non-formal education, conservation
of the cultural, physical and non-physical heritage, mutual
knowledge of cultures, artistic creation and the popularization
of science. The action involved, which will consist in encourag¬
ing the manufacture of sound and image recording media, the
training of producers, the production of films and programmes,
and the development of the photographic heritage, will further
aim to encourage the preservation and conservation of
photographs, films and other audio-visual media, particularly
those of special cultural and historical significance.
The seventh (Education of Users) seeks to encourage the
drawing up, experimentation and implementation of pro¬
grammes providing education in communication designed to
foster an independent approach in the acquisition of informa¬
tion and knowledge, to develop a critical mind and to
familiarize the various categories of users, especially young peo¬
ple, with the ways in which the means of communication are
organized and used.
Developed along these lines, this major programme seems to
constitute the conceptual framework which should make it
possible to lay the foundations and to seek those principles on
which, in accordance with an evolutive principle, a new world
information and communication order could gradually be
brought into being, an order such as would ensure that all-
individuals, groups and nationsmight engage in free,
reciprocal and balanced communication.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
IV. The formulation and
application of educational policies
THE rapid pace of social change and progress in
knowledge and its applications, together with the
development of the means of communication, have of
necessity led to more dynamic development and an increased
capacity for innovation in education systems. At the same time,
the importance of the role of education and the complexity of
educational problems have prompted more systematic efforts to
devise and clarify education policies.
To enable education to fulfil its role, Unesco will promote the
elaboration of education policies and the conditions necessary
for their implementation with regard to the planning and
management of education, the renewal of content and methods,
the training of education personnel and of the infrastructures of
educational systems.
Decisions entailed in the formulation and application of
education policies are taken more and more often in the light of
experience acquired in the educational sciences and in the
related social and human sciences such as psychology,
sociology, linguistics and socio-linguistics and educational
economics, physiology, biology, dietetics, ergonomics and the
information and communication sciences. Educational person¬
nel can derive valuable assistance from the means of com¬
munication, data processing and the whole range of audio¬
visual media which help them to renew their methods and
evaluate their work.
Special prominence is given for the first time to developing
the education sciences it being considered vital to strengthen
and broaden education research if the renewal of the education
process is to be undertaken on a sound basis.
A wide dissemination of the studies and the findings of
research, of experiments and innovations is therefore of vital
importance to teachers, specialists in the design of curricula and
researchers, as well as those responsible for educational
policies, the planning, management and development of educa¬
tion as an aid to the decision-making process.
The various goals assigned to education, in its twofold func¬
tion of ensuring continuity and of creating receptivity to
change, are reflected, as regards the content of education, in a
large number of sometimes heterogeneous demands and pose
sensitive problems of priority, selection, organization and
balance in content. Indeed, the provision of education which is
adapted to the human and natural environment, the psychology
of the child or adult, to the state of knowledge and the needs of
society, is one of the most difficult of tasks.
A growing disparity is often to be found between the current
state of knowledge and values and the content of curricula,
which need to be updated regularly if education is not to become
marred by irrelevance or to be in danger of causing disaffection
or meeting with indifference among students. The emergence of
new fields of knowledge and activity often leads to the addition
of new subjects to those included in the curricula. Education,
however, cannot be divorced from the environmental context;
it is important, therefore, to see to it that education ensures the
transmission and development of indigenous values while being
a means of creating receptivity to other cultures.
In the near future, the proliferation of computers and the in¬
creased use of cable television, information technology and
communication satellites will make existing problems even
more acute such problems as the value of the contribution
made by these technologies to the educational process, their
harnessing for teaching purposes, the role of the teacher in rela¬
tion to the instruments which science has put at his disposal and
of which he now has to master the use, thus learning to enter a
new world. Preparing teachers for this new responsibility is one
of the features of the in-service training which is now added to
pre-service training in order that they may be equal to their ever
more complex and numerous duties.
To make education a continuous and coherent process which
preserves its specific features while renewing itself in rhythm
with changes in the social environment and the progress of
knowledge, such is the challenge facing all who, in various
capacities, are responsible for education, provide it or help to
promote its development.
A discussion group at a regional workshop held in the Philippines
in August-September 1 980 to review the state of biology educa¬
tion in Asia. The workshop was one of a number held under the
auspices of APEID (Asian Programme of Educational Innovation for
Development), a co-operative programme of Unesco Member
States in Asia and the Pacific region aimed at stimulating innovative
approaches to the problems of education related to development
needs.
Participants in a Unesco-sponsored regional seminar on problems
relating to the introduction of productive work into educational
systems, held at Porto Novo and Come in 1980, visit the craft
workshop of the Centre d'Enseignement Moyen Général (centre for
general secondary education). Come, People's Republic of Benin.
Photo Unesco
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
V. Education, training
and society
EDUCATION has its specific characteristics and its own
requirements. It is not, however, independent of society '
as a whole which in large part determines its nature. But
education itself is by no means passive; to a great extent it con¬
ditions the evolution and hence the future of society. It is
becoming more and more receptive towards the contemporary
world and is increasingly orientated towards the solution of
practical problems. Education alone cannot offer a solution to
all problems, but it can supply the knowledge needed to under¬
stand and solve them and arouse the attitudes and will that lead
to action and results. Education can thus contribute to the solu¬
tion of the major problems facing mankind, such as peace,
human rights, development and the environment. Furthermore,
special importance should be attached to the relationship bet¬
ween education and certain other aspects of social activity.
Education and culture
The function and content of education bear a direct relation
to culture. In many countries, and particularly in those which
have recently gained independence, the assertion of cultural
identity is clearly an essential means of civic training and a
powerful factor in national cohesion. Education can help to
restore a country's cultural heritage to its rightful place in all the
wealth of its forms of expression, to bring out the distinctive
characteristics of each culture. But education must do more: it
must ensure the emergence of a modern humanism which
couples certain traditional values with a number of new values
that carry within them the seeds of progress. Concern to
strengthen cultural identity coupled with concern for efficien¬
cy of teaching has in recent years produced in many countries,
in particular those which have recently gained independence, a
tendency to use the mother tongues or national languages as
languages of instruction. Unesco will encourage this trend.
The mass media a "parallel school"?
During the last few years the mass communication media
have had a growing impact on adults, as they have on children
to the point where people speak of the "parallel school", a
source of possible divergence from the educational institution.
The question that arises is whether education can turn to good
account the increasing flow of information and messages emit¬
ted by society and at the same time help to counter, where
necessary, the negative influences they may have on outlook
and behaviour among teenagers. It might henceforth be one of
the essential functions of educational institutions to help young
people to bring their critical faculty to bear in selecting and sor¬
ting the messages spread abroad by the communication media.
Teaching of science and technology
Unesco will aim to make the teaching of science and
technology the general practice at all levels and in all types of
education and to promote the popularization of science, par¬
ticularly in the developing countries.
A special effort will be made to expand and improve the
teaching of science and technology at the primary and secon¬
dary levels and in out-of-school education by laying greater em¬
phasis on the understanding of scientific concepts, observation,
experiment and guidance towards the solution of practical
problems. The content of this science and technology teaching
should be in keeping with the latest advances in scientific
research and technological innovation and take into account the
characteristics of the local environment.
Education and the world of work
In recent years the concern to bring education closer to life
has led many educators to emphasize the need to strengthen
liaison between education and the world of work. A series of ac¬
tivities is envisaged to encourage the introduction of productive
or socially useful work into the educational process, because of
its pedagogical, ethical and social value; bringing educational
policies and employment policies into line with each other; the
development and improvement of technical and vocational
training. These activities will tend to modify young people's at¬
titudes towards work, to develop vocational guidance, to pro¬
mote better working links between general education, technical
education and the world of work and to eliminate the age-old
rift between manual and intellectual work.
Physical education and sport
The practice of physical education and sport is not
guaranteed everywhere as a fundamental right for all. The con¬
ditions of modern life, however, and increasing urbanization
and mechanization mean that physical activities are essential to
the development of a complete personality and to the preserva¬
tion of health. In many countries, more than half the popula¬
tion currently practise no sport and 80 per cent of children in
developing countries receive no physical education at all. The
Properly used, modern developments
in communication technology hold im¬
mense promise in the field of educa¬
tion. The "parallel school" of educa¬
tional programmes broadcast on radio
and television can reach the remotest
village and hamlet, ending centuries of
educational deprivation. Right, even
the inhabitants of this underground
dwelling at Matmata, Tunisia, can
benefit from the "television
explosion".
Photo © André Stevens, Winksele, Belgium
16
~* *
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
activities envisaged will contribute to the training of personnel,
the provision of the necessary equipment and the development
of sport for all, as well as the strengthening of co-operation bet¬
ween Member States, non-governmental organizations and
youth movements.
Higher education, training and research
The very great disparities in access to education, especially
higher education, and the inequalities in the development of
education that exist between countries and within one and the
same country are reflected in uneven access to knowledge and
inequalities in the possession of potential to create knowledge.
A score of industrialized countries share more than 90 per cent
of the world's scientists; the rest are distributed among some
130 countries. Without sound higher education no modern
State can hope to train its managerial personnel or play its part
in the international research effort. The role played by higher
education in development has been more and more clearly
perceived and this explains the interest Member States attach to
its expansion and improvement, as well as international co¬
operation in this field.
The activities envisaged are aimed at improving the contribu¬
tion of higher education to the advancement of society, par¬
ticularly by the expansion and reorientation of training courses
and by adopting interdisciplinary approaches to research and
training. The research and training tasks of higher education
with a view to improving the education system as a whole will
be emphasized.
Furthermore, higher education is considered to be a key ele¬
ment in the whole national training and research system in the
perspective of a long-term action to encourage, step by step, the
harmonization and then the integration of training and research
activities.
Above, an adult literacy class in Senegal where instruc¬
tion is given in six of the country's national languages.
During the colonial era millions of children and adults
were handicapped by receiving all their instruction in an
alien language. Today, educators throughout the world
are becoming increasingly aware that the use of mother
tongues or national languages as the language of instruc¬
tion results both in more effective teaching and in a
strengthening of cultural identity and national cohesion.
Photo Unesco - BREDA, Dakar
VI. The sciences
and their
applications
to development
SUBSTANTIAL disparities are still a feature of the distri¬
bution throughout the world of material and human
resources in the field of science and technology. Expen¬
diture on research per head of the working population is sixty
times less in the developing nations than in the industrialized
countries. As regards results, the disparities are just as great.
Over 93 per cent of the patents registered throughout the world
come from the industrialized countries.
Science and technology
in the service of development
These disparities lie undoubtedly at the heart of development
problems. A more judicious distribution of research projects
and the creation of new poles of scientific and technological
development would enable societies which up to now have had
a very small part to play, to make a greater contribution to both
scientific and technical progress and the definition of the
ultimate aims of science and technology at the international
level.
The broadening of international co-operation in this way
would appear to be all the more necessary in view of the fact
that certain scientific fields, such as geology, oceanography,
climatology, radio-astronomy or epidemiology, transcend, by
definition, national or regional boundaries.
The International Centre for Theoretical Physics, at
Trieste, established in 1 963 and financed by Italy, the
International Atomic Energy Agency and Unesco, pro¬
vides post-graduate courses and high-level seminars
for young physicists from developing countries to
enable them to keep abreast of modern
developments, update their knowledge and enjoy the
stimulus of contact with other scientists. Below, a
few of the 1,500 physicists the Centre welcomes
each year.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
More
than
enough
\n optimistic assessment of world ener©
Ldiled by Robin Clarke
Photo I Unesco Pr<
Photo Paul Almasy, Unesco
Is the world exhausting its energy supplies? Will there be enough to go round as the planet's population
rises to 6,000 million or more over the next twenty years? These are among the questions tackled by over
a dozen experts in More Than Enough? the first title (above left) in Unesco's new Sextant series, designed
to enable the layman to find his bearings in an ocean of complicated and often confusing information on
a wide variety of problems. New and renewable sources of energy are supplying an increasing proportion
of the world's energy needs; solar energy in particular holds great promise as an energy source for develop¬
ing countries. Above right, solar oven developed at the Solar Energy Laboratory of Dakar University,
Senegal.
The objectives are therefore to strengthen national research
potential in the natural sciences and to improve institutional in¬
frastructures; to develop university and postgraduate training
programmes, adapting them to specific needs and conditions;
and to broaden and strengthen international co-operation.
Like the natural sciences, the main engineering sciences have
developed rapidly, so that the increasing volume of knowledge
makes technical versatility harder to attain. The solution fre¬
quently advocated for this problem is a type of training design¬
ed to inculcate not encyclopaedic knowledge, but essential con¬
cepts, to be supplemented by other ways of learning and acquir¬
ing knowledge (lifelong education, individual research and
documentation, training courses in firms).
The new technologies hazards and hopes
The combined advances in computer technology and
microelectronics, and their applications, which are spreading
from the services sector (telecommunications combined with
data processing, office automation) to the manufacturing pro¬
duction sector (the development of robotics and other
.automated systems), will bring about radical changes in the
nature and structure of industry in the industrialized countries,
with the very probable result that the developing countries will
lose outlets for their products, which are less competitive.
Biotechnologies contribute both to the preservation of.
genetic diversity (collections of microbe cultures, the selection
of new strains, new cultivated plant varieties, and new species
of domestic animals) and to technological innovation, both of
which are of interest to the developing and the industrialized
countries. Biotechnologies draw to a greater extent on inven¬
tiveness and know-how than on sciences necessitating heavy
equipment, and their development is within reach of the less
privileged countries, provided that objectives are clearly
defined.
Unesco's objectives are therefore to contribute to the
dissemination of new technologies after assessing all their con¬
sequences and considering any necessary adaptations or ad¬
justments, to strengthen the training of the specialists and
18
technicians concerned and to create favourable research condi¬
tions; and to develop exchanges of specialized information.
The social sciences a vital role
The need for research in the social and human sciences has
become particularly acute in the developing countries. It would
appear vital to highlight the patterns of unequal terms of trade,
the consequences of the introduction of cash crop farming, the
forces at play in rapid social change and their repercussions on
human values and cultures in general. An effort must also be
made to assemble socio-economic data and devise the necessary
instruments for the formulation of development plans, and, at
the same time to elucidate historical processes, the nature of in¬
ternal social relationships and their impact on development pro¬
cesses, the juxtaposition of or the interference between modern
and traditional forms of power, the influence of certain pro¬
cesses of modernization on economic, cultural and social life
and on the technologies of traditional medicine, customary law
and the parallel structures of power in the rural environment,
etc.
The comprehension of such problems and the quest for solu¬
tions implies recourse to several disciplines operating in sym¬
biosis. An approach such as this is particularly important when
the issue under review is the vast field of development.
Here Unesco's aim is the introduction of training and
research programmes at university and postgraduate levels.
The programme activities planned within these key areas ac¬
cordingly include not only the establishment or strengthening of
research and training infrastructures, but also the formulation
of policies and programmes and, at the same time, a better
perception of the social and cultural consequences of introduc¬
ing and developing new technologies.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
VIL Information systems
and access to knowledge
WITH the explosion of knowledge during this century,
there has been a spectacular increase in the produc¬
tion of printed matter throughout the world. A few
figures will help to gauge the size of this phenomenon. In 1970
more than 6,000 items of printed matter appeared each working
day, i.e. 2,000,000 in a year, and it is estimated that this figure
will be four or five times greater by 1985, when 8,000,000 to
10,000,000 scientific and technical documents will be published
and printed. This significant increase in the volume of informa¬
tion has created a need for information storage and distribution
systems.
It is interesting to note that out of the 900 bibliographical and
numerical data bases now available on-line internationally, less
than one per cent are produced in the developing countries. Ac¬
cess by all nations to the whole range of these data bases would
seem essential to the progress of individual societies and the
In 1973 Unesco launched, in collaboration with the Interna¬
tional Council of Scientific Unions, an intergovernmental
programme known as UNISIST, to meet the need for "co¬
ordinated and sustained international action to facilitate
transfer of scientific and technical information for the
economic and social development of nations". In 1979, the
scope of the programme was expanded to include, in the
perspective of a worldwide information network, all scien¬
tific, technological, economic and social information useful
for development. Above, the logo of UIMISIST.
general advancement of human knowledge.
It is therefore essential that developing countries should be
able to use other countries' data bases, as and when they need,
and at the same time set up data bases and data banks of their
own, at the national or regional level.
Free access to information
Among the obstacles preventing free access to information is
the extremely high cost of the new data processing and telecom¬
munications technologies used for handling information. The
poorest developing countries may therefore find themselves
unable, without recourse to external aid, to set up the in¬
frastructure necessary for the installation of automated systems
and networks. Moreover, the new technologies raise complex
legal problems, especially in matters of copyright.
The industrialized countries at present enjoy a kind of defac¬
to monopoly in the field of information, affecting both the
substance of knowledge and the technical means of circulating
it. As a result, the transfer of information technologies and of
information itself to developing countries may be hindered by
restrictive practices, but it may also put these countries in a posi¬
tion of dependence on privileged suppliers.
Restrictive practices inhibiting the free flow of information
are also found in relations between industrialized countries and
within individual countries.
It is now clear that the setting up of a worldwide information
network is to constitute a major element in the development
strategy to be applied in establishing a new international
economic order.
The General Information Programme, which at present
covers most of Unesco's activities in the fields of information,
libraries and archivesand of which UNISIST forms an in¬
tegral part is clearly particularly well suited to the nature of
the main tasks that are to be carried out under this major pro¬
gramme. The latter will in fact be based on the machinery and
networks for co-operation established under the General Infor¬
mation Programme, UNISIST and the various specialized
systems and services developed under the Organization's other
major programmes. It applies to the natural and to the social
and human sciences, as well as to all the other branches of
knowledge and to all sectors of human activity.
VIII. Principles,
methods
and strategies
of action
for development
THE industrialized nations have enjoyed unprecedented
economic growth during several decades, but have not
always succeeded in finding a satisfactory answer to the
question of the equitable distribution of income, nor to that
arising from the crisis of values that sometimes accompanies
rapid change. In some of them, poverty continues to prevail
among different strata of the population, and the decline in the
sense of civic and moral responsibility seriously affects certain
sectors of the population, particularly the young. New
economic and social difficulties are emerging as a result of the
recession and the combined effects of inflation and
unemployment.
While the revival of economic growth appears essential for
overcoming the crisis some of them are undergoing, differences
emerge with regard to the policies that should be adopted.
Far-reaching questions are being asked as to the aim of
growth, the consequences that it can have on the natural envi-
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
ronment and on human welfare. Furthermore, while the in¬
dustrial and sometimes even the agricultural potential of several
industrialized countries remain virtually underemployed, the
unsatisfied needs of the developing countries are still enormous.
This brings us to an issue that is at once economic, social and
political, but also ethical: that of the coexistence in the same
world of areas of poverty and even destitution with areas where,
conversely, it is over-abundance that poses the problem.
The need for global action
Although it has not been possible to make any decisive pro¬
gress in international economic co-operation, the international
community does seem to have become convinced that the in¬
creasingly worldwide nature of production, of economic and
financial flows and of exchanges of information henceforth
renders unilateral solutions based on a partial analysis of the
problems totally ineffective, and that only global, integrated ac¬
tion that takes into account the interests of all peoples and na¬
tions can bear any fruit. A global situation founded on competi¬
tion perpetuates a line of reasoning whereby everyone thinks he
can solve his own crisis by exporting it to someone else. This
produces situations where there are serious shortages in some
countries, while in others the means of production are either not
used to full capacity or else only used as a source of profit, even
if they run counter to the collective interests of humanity, as is
the case with the armaments industry.
Beyond a mechanistic view of growth
For a long time it was thought that development could be
reduced to its economic aspect only, and consequently all the
other sectors of human activity had to be subordinated to the
needs of economic growth.
In practice one should rise above such reductionist ap¬
proaches. Only by progressively wider integration of policies
relating to each sector of human activity social, economic,
technical and cultural would it be possible to create a motive
force of social creativity capable of harnessing science and
technology to the interests of communities, thus meeting the
aspirations of their populations.
It is therefore important that cultural dimensions be duly
taken into account in any enterprise relating to development. A
feeling for the continuity and vitality of cultural values is essen¬
tial. These values should be viewed in the light of the oppor¬
tunities they offer for development, a development that, in its
style and its rhythm, incorporates the heritages of the past and
the desire for change in such a way that the requisite changes en¬
joy the widest possible measure of popular support. One of the
principal methods of obtaining this general support is participa¬
tion by the people at large in the choices made on behalf of the
community to which they belong, with regard to the objectives
to be attained as well as the action to be undertaken and the con¬
cessions to be made in return.
Special attention will be paid to analysis of the significance
and ultimate aims of development in different cultural contexts
and to the study of the forms of action likely to foster participa-
,' tion by the people at large in defining development objectives.
Autonomy and self-reliance
It is particularly important to clarify the links between
development and international relations in order to bring out,
from the standpoint of the development of countries, the
positive factors inherent in international relations as well as the
constraints they entail. The studies to be undertaken along these
lines could focus, among other things, on: the relations between
peace, disarmament and development; the structural factors
responsible for the phenomena of domination and dependence;
the effects of the activities of transnational companies; the con-
Fashioned some 3,000 years ago, this 23 cm-high bronze
model of a mannikin atop a ladder was recovered from a
burial site in the Amlash district near Lahijan in northern Iran.
Today Unesco is helping Member States to construct a lad¬
der of international solidarity that will enable the under¬
privileged nations of the world to reach a level of develop¬
ment at which they will be able to achieve their deepest
material and spiritual aspirations.
20
ditions for the establishment of a new international economic
order and their impact in Unesco's fields of competence. We
need to study in greater depth the conditions that might enable
the developing countries to strengthen the bases for collective
self-reliance and development while stressing the socio-cultural
aspects of regional and subregional integration. The situation
of the so-called least developed countries should be given special
attention, as also should studies or action relating to strategies
for reducing the isolation of some of these countries.
As for the relations between population factors and develop¬
ment, they should undoubtedly be studied not only from the
historical and geographic standpoint but also in the light of
social, economic and cultural conditions.
It goes without saying that studies on development processes
should be conducted in different geographical settings in order
to bring out the specific nature of various experiences of
development resulting from the diversity of historical and
cultural contexts in which they take place.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
IX. Science, technology
and society
THE growth of human capacities for scientific and
technological creation is not always accompanied by a
commensurate mastery of technological developments,
and does not necessarily lead to uses that would meet men's
aspirations and serve all peoples fairly.
The worldwide scientific and technological effort which is
devoted to increasing the destructive power of armaments, and
which sets off the arms race, is a cause for grave concern. Not
only is arms research immobilizing substantial resources which
could be used to meet the priority needs of societies, but the
technological innovations which it yields call for further in¬
novations even more detrimental to the security they are sup¬
posed to provide.
Furthermore technological development, when poorly con¬
trolled, can have extremely disturbing consequences: degrada¬
tion of the environment, massive migrations and uncontrolled
urbanization, threats to employment and a calling into question
of certain cultural values. In the developing countries the im¬
portation of technologies, often through transnational corpora¬
tions, leads to the setting up of industries which, although re¬
quiring substantial investments, nevertheless do not create
many jobs and lead to profound changes in consumption pat¬
terns and life-styles. Elsewhere the progress of computer and
robot technology is causing concern on the score of the possible
effects of such technology on employment, on working condi¬
tions, on the freedom of individuals and on the preservation of
privacy.
Implanting science and technology
Technology is often treated as a commodity for export,
whereas what is needed is an organized transfer of know-how
and an endogenous capacity to adapt that know-how to the
socio-cultural and natural environment.
The implanting of science and technology in society is not a
mere matter of grafting knowledge, know-how, practices and
techniques on to social tissue that has not been prepared to
receive it. There cannot be a situation with science and
technology on one side and society on the other. On the con¬
trary, science and technology must put down deep roots in
society, and their rise depends at one and the same time on
material, social, economic, cultural, historical and political
realities.
Governments are aware of the importance of what is at stake
and are adopting an increasingly voluntarist attitude in the mat¬
ter. In this they are responding to an increasing demand on the
part of young people, who are no longer prepared to leave it all
to fate or chance. This is also the reason for the existence of
policies on science and technology.
Participation of specialists and the public
It is difficult for the developing countries to master or control
transfers of technology inasmuch as they do not possess enough
specialists capable of selecting and adapting foreign
technologies and seeing to it personally that those technologies
are assimilated. This shortage of specialists is often worsened by
the brain drain.
It is important that not only political leaders but also
academics, scientific researchers, engineers and representatives
of the various sectors of production should be associated with
the search for progress. It is also desirable to ensure the par¬
ticipation of the public in identifying their needs and their col¬
laboration in determining the orientation of research and in the
introduction and dissemination of innovations. In this
connexion it is particularly important to secure the participation
of women and young people.
It has been realized more clearly in the last few years that cer¬
tain fundamental ethical, religious and cultural values need to
be taken into consideration in the formulation of such policies.
The explanation doubtless lies in the need felt throughout the
world to keep up to date with scientific knowledge and advanc¬
ed technologies while at the same time cherishing whatever can
help to preserve or even bring to full flower the traditions and
human values through which each society expresses its specific
character, identity and dignity. As a result, science and
technology policies are less and less influenced by the
"technocratic" approach based on exclusively cognitive and
utilitarian criteria.
Technology is often treated as a commodity for export, whereas its
successful transfer requires a real appreciation of local needs and
an understanding of its long-term economic, social and cultural ef¬
fects. Above, a wind-powered water pump in the Gozirah district
of Sudan.
Photo Eric Schwab, Unesco
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
JbCOlOgy 111 aCtiOn MAB: an international programme
When Unesco's international programme of research and training,
the Man and the Biosphere (MAB) Programme was launched over ten
years ago, its general objective was defined as being "to develop
within the natural and social sciences a basis for the rational use and
conservation of the resources of the biosphere and for the improve- what is MAB?
ment of the relationship between man and the environment; to
predict the consequences of today's actions on tomorrow's world
and thereby to increase man's ability to manage efficiently the
natural resources of the biosphere".
The results of MAB's 1 ,000 and more research projects being carried
out in 79 countries find their way into the normal scientific channels;
but, since decisions on land-use, and environmental planning involve
cultural, social and political considerations, they need to be
presented in a form which can be understood and used by the non-
scientists (decision-makers, educators, environmental groups, local
associations, food producers and the general public) for whom they
are also of vital interest.
To achieve this, the MAB secretariat, in co-operation with a Paris-
based communications group. Etudes et Planification des Com¬
munications, has designed a mobile exhibit consisting of 36 posters
relating to five main themes: integrated approaches to land-use;
tropical forests; marginal lands (arid zones, mountainous regions);
cities and urbanization; conservation of nature. Three of these
posters are reproduced on this page. The poster top right introduces
the MAB programme and demonstrates its worldwide nature, its pur¬
pose and its organization. The second poster, centre, explains the
need to synchronize the work of scientists, planners and the people
who actually put MAB research results into practice, each of whom
may have a different time scale of concern (e.g. the scientist may be
concerned with long-term improvement of the yield of a strain of
wheat, the planner with meeting a forecast food shortage six months
ahead, the farmer with getting his harvest in before the onset of the
rainy season in a week's time). The third poster, below, highlights
the risk of soil degradation and suggests ways of avoiding it.
The exhibit, which is available in three language versions (English,
French and Spanish), is entitled Ecology in Action. It has already been
displayed in schools, government ministries, at trade fairs and scien¬
tific conferences where it has aroused enormous interest.
The risk of sou degradation
I émm*«m kM 4*aMt kj «to ytu MM, tkt xrreMta. of «ck we»
' ilw>|n«iMiihkliM<w«ta)r«HiktkM«kcfants
The MAB Programme at a glance
res
Synchronizing scientists and planners
...A TIME TO STUDY, A TIME TO
ACT, A DATE TO BE KEPT...
In* different
ili tlctrni disciplines, «id of scwtttkis
and planners should be harmonized.
HriimiiuiíK Denote «nd aMe to
changtaf conditions is also necessary
deal with (be moving targets of rapid!:
evorvkg bed use problems.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
X. The human environment
and terrestrial and marine resources
THE development of the industrial societies has come
about on the basis of the large-scale use of natural
resources, verging, in certain cases, on the squandering
of those resources, including energy, mineral and biological
resources.
These various processes, taking place in a world characterized
by a very uneven distribution of industrial activities between
countries and regions, have frequently given rise to the excessive
use of resources of all kinds from Third World countries, which
have played the role of suppliers of raw materials in the context
of the international division of labour. Another effect has been,
in some instances, the transfer to those countries of certain ac¬
tivities which cause pollution and which the societies that are
better provided for tend to refuse to allow to be carried out in
their own territories. In addition, the developing countries have
had only a limited capacity for exploring and exploiting their
own resources in the interests of their own progress.
With a view to the preservation of ecosystems and certain
threatened species, natural parks and biosphere reserves have
been established in most countries and in most biogeographical
regions. The protection of seas and coastal zones from increas¬
ing pollution has often involved concerted action by countries
bordering on those seas.
At the same time, there has developed a stronger awareness
of the importance for all countries but for developing coun¬
tries in particular of making more intensive use of and exer¬
ting better control over their own natural resources. Indeed, this"
constitutes one of the basic aspects of the search for a new inter¬
national economic order.
In this context, Unesco has specific programmes devoted to
the earth's crust and to mineral and energy resources; water
resources; the ocean and its resources; coastal and island
regions; and the resources of terrestrial ecosystems.
The Intergovernmental Programme on Man and the
Biosphere (MAB) thus finds concrete expression in five of the
proposed programmes (Management of coastal and island
regions; Land-use planning and terrestrial resources; Urban
systems and urbanization; The natural heritage; and En¬
vironmental education and information). The fact that MAB is
represented here, far from constituting fragmentation, makes it
possible to reflect its interdisciplinary character and its con¬
tribution to several important fields. The coherence of MAB
and the unitary nature of its work will be strengthened in its
specific activities and in its structure.
The earth 's resources
Research undertaken by Unesco on the earth's crust and its
mineral and energy resources covers the following areas:
Spatiotemporal geological correlation within the
framework of the International Geological Correlation Pro¬
gramme (IGCP), a joint undertaking of Unesco and the Inter¬
national Union of Geological Sciences designed to achieve bet¬
ter knowledge of the geological history of the planet; Geology
for economic development designed to provide the data need¬
ed to survey and develop mineral resources in the developing
countries; Geology for land-use planning including the study
of those geological and geochemical factors that should be
taken into account in land-use planning and civil engineering
projects; Processing and dissemination of data relating to the
earth sciences aims to collect, process and disseminate infor¬
mation on the earth sciences, largely in the form of geological,
metallogenic and tectonic maps, with emphasis on interpreta¬
tion of the data provided by remote sensing techniques.
Natural disasters of geophysical origin such as earthquakes,
volcanic eruptions, tsunamis and landslides year by year take a
heavy toll in human lives and cause destruction on a very large
scale. Other disasters, of climatic origin, such as exceptional
droughts and floods, may have even more far-ranging con¬
sequences, particularly in the developing countries.
Here the emphasis will be on international co-operation in the
fields of scientific and technological research, the social sciences
and the behavioural sciences, and through direct co-operation
with countries threatened or afflicted by natural disasters.
Droughts and floods
Although in global terms water resources are well in excess of
foreseeable demand, they are unevenly distributed and some
regions are already experiencing a severe water shortage which
is in danger of worsening1 in the future. Such instances of an in¬
sufficient supply of water in relation to demand are periodically
and, in some cases, endemically complicated by major fluctua¬
tions in supply.
In many cases, the situation is further aggravated by the poor
quality of water, which makes it unsuitable for various pur¬
poses, and by the pollution of surface water and even ground¬
water caused by factory effluents and the intensive use of
pesticides and fertilizers.
The International Hydrological Programme (IHP) will con¬
tinue to be the main instrument of action. The basic lines of em¬
phasis of the third phase of the IHP (1984-1989) concern the ex¬
tension of research and training activities in the field of water
resources planning and management and the encouragement of
interdisciplinary studies.
The three major regional projects on the rational use and con¬
servation of water resources in rural areas that were started in
1981 in Africa, Latin America and the Caribbean and in the
Arab States are intended to contribute to the growth of en¬
dogenous scientific and technical potential, to the progress of
research and the development of information networks, and to
a rational utilization of water resources that is based on the
choice of the most appropriate technologies and takes account
of biogeographical and socio-economic conditions. These pro¬
jects may be extended to other regions.
Exploration and exploitation of the oceans
Even though the negotiations that have been under way for
the past ten years within the framework of the United Nations
Conference on the Law of the Sea have not yet culminated in
a "new "order" of the sea, a new customary law has come into
effect which sanctions national sovereignty over "exclusive
economic zones" and should vest the international community
with added responsibilities in the matter of exploration, conser¬
vation and management of the resources, including those of the
ocean depths, regarded as "the common heritage of mankind".
Many developing countries now find themselves in possession
of rights over very extensive sea areas which, for many island
States in particular, are considerably greater and possibly richer
in resources than their territory proper. Most of them, however,
have neither the technological and financial means nor the
qualified manpower for the systematic exploration of their new
domains. They thus have to concede deep-sea fishing rights or
the rights to underwater oil-prospecting and to purchase equip¬
ment and seek technical assistance from other nations, par-
ticularly the major maritime powers. ^
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Unesco and its Intergovernmental Océanographie Commis¬
sion (IOC) must therefore take up a double challenge: on the
one hand, many Member States are in greater need of assistance
to attain their objectives in this area and to participate effective¬
ly in international programmes of oceanological research and
ocean services; on the other, océanographie knowledge must be
mobilized to achieve rational exploitation of ocean resources
and to protect the marine environment.
Coastal and island regions
Two persons out of three today live in coastal regions, near
the sea, on the shores of continents or on islands. This situation,
which is the consequence of population growth and population
movements as well as of economic development, concerns
regions with a delicate balance, very often areas of ancient
civilization whose prosperity was largely based on shipping and
maritime trade and also on the relatively high productivity of
the coastal environment.
The coastal environment is highly conducive to the establish¬
ment of human settlements, both permanent and seasonal, ur¬
ban and industrial. Coastal zones, in particular, are affected by
the scale of seasonal tourism. Beaches, estuaries, lagoons,
mangroves and coral reefs are all environments which are
vulnerable, and particularly exposed, to the effects of modern
development.
The countless islands of the world, especially those having an
area of less than 10,000 km2, are subject to the same pressures
as continental coasts and moreover are confronted by dif¬
ficulties of a specific nature. Island ecosystems are exceedingly
vulnerable and the efforts made to increase production to meet
development needs or respond to population pressure come up
against especially acute spatial limitations.
In a large number of islands, terrestrial resources, especially
agricultural resources, are no longer adequate to satisfy the
needs of a growing population; the exploitation of coastal and
marine resources thereupon becomes an economic imperative.
This is a problem of concern to all countries that are responsible
for managing more or less numerous groups of islands and of
particular concern to island States.
In this area Unesco has four main objectives: (1) to promote
better knowledge of the characteristics of certain particular
coastal or island ecosystems, to further interdisciplinary
research and to make a synthesis of available knowledge concer¬
ning interactions between the continental and coastal en¬
vironments; (2) to contribute to an integrated management of
coastal zones that takes account of the various options that
make possible the resolution of conflicts of interests between ur¬
banization, tourism, industrialization, intensive agriculture,
aquaculture and fishing; (3) to develop interdisciplinary
research on the island environment, the relations between
populations, resources, environment and development; (4) to
train specialists responsible for the integrated management of
coastal and island regions.
Unesco's International Hydrological Programme (IHP) is concerned
with the scientific assessment, development and rational manage¬
ment of one of the earth's most precious resources water. The
snow and ice programmes of the IHP are helping to broaden our
understanding of the interrelationships between snow and ice,
climate and water supply. Annual ice layers, like those clearly visi¬
ble in this photo of the Quelccaya ice-cap in Peru, constitute a
valuable record of climate and climatic change over a period of
several hundreds of years.
Photo L.G Thompson, courtesy of Science © The American Association for the Advancement
of Science, Washington, D.C
Man and the biosphere
In all regions, land-use gives rise to competing activities such
as farming and herding, the establishment of industries, ur¬
banization, tourism, etc. This results in conflicts of interest
linked with the specific nature of local conditions but also with
economic interdependence and imbalances on a world scale.
Numerous systems of land-use planning derive from those
adopted in a few industrialized, temperate-zone countries; they
are not readily applicable to the ecological or socio-cultural con¬
ditions of other zones. In the industrialized countries
themselves, land-use planning in certain vulnerable interface
regions (town/country, coastline and mountains) has taken on
new complexity and necessitates the development of new
approaches.
Unesco's action is aimed at developing scientific knowledge
of the physical and biological processes and the social and
cultural conditions that need to be taken into account in any in¬
tegrated land use policy and the rational use of the resources of
terrestrial ecosystems.
The Intergovernmental Programme on Man and the
Biosphere (MAB) provides conceptual unity and unity of
24
management for operational research, training and demonstra¬
tion activities relating to the conservation of protected natural
areas and the management of rural and urban areas.
Over 130 Member States will be participating actively in the
MAB programme by 1989; the projects, which will remain bet¬
ween 1,000 and 2,000 in number, will be more integrated and
more directed towards practical applications; they will include
a greater number of training and popularization activities. The
number of research workers and technicians involved in the
MAB projects will be in the region of 20,000.
As regards the national integrated pilot projects of research,
training and demonstration in land-use planning and the ra¬
tional development of national resources, which constitute the
key elements in the regional networks, there will be fifteen to
twenty such projects per network and, in all, about a hundred
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
towards the end of the period covered by the Plan. Each year,
over 300 specialists from the developing countries will receive
postgraduate training two-thirds of them on the site of the
pilot projects themselves and the rest at centres of excellence in
the industrialized countries.
Urban spread
By the year 2000, over half the six thousand million or so in¬
habitants of the earth will probably live in urban areas. In the
developing countries, two thousand million people will live in
the towns. Another thousand million will live in the urban areas
of the industrialized countries. Of the sixty cities with over five
million inhabitants, forty-seven will be located in the develop¬
ing countries. It is in these countries that twelve of the world's
fifteen largest cities will be found.
To date, planning has in most cases scarcely taken account of
the complexity of the relationship between the town and sur¬
rounding rural areas; this is without doubt one of its main short¬
comings. As they develop, towns come to depend on ever more
distant regions for their supplies of water, energy, food and
building materials. This increase in demand often leads to a
deterioration of neighbouring and more distant land through
overexploitation. A better understanding of the relationship
between towns and surrounding rural areas should make it
possible to manage this complex rationally.
The natural heritage
Immovable cultural property, such as historic monuments
and groups of buildings, and natural property, such as national
parks and outstanding sites, raise a set of common problems
regarding their preservation and enhancement and call in the
same way for international co-operation. They were placed on
an equal footing in the 1972 Convention for the Protection of
the World Cultural and Natural Heritage, which Unesco is
responsible for implementing and to which more than sixty
countries have acceded.
Preserving the natural heritage means, first and foremost,
preserving the living resources on which the survival of the
human race depends: all cultivated plants and all domestic
animals originate from wild species, and it is essential to
preserve as many wild congeners as possible for the purpose of
genetic selection, on which ultimately depend the maintenance
and expansion of agricultural production. In addition, as yet
unknown plants, animals or micro-organisms are capable of
providing mankind with products or of rendering it important
services, as is shown by a large number of recent discoveries.
Efforts will be directed not only at the protection of land¬
scapes or remarkable living beings, but also at the protection of
entire ecosystems, balanced man-made landscapes and certain
ecological and evolutive processes. This work will be conducted
mainly through the development of a worldwide network of
biosphere reserves containing representative samples of the
world's principal ecosystems.
A geologist's hammer has been
adopted as the "trademark" of the
International Geological Correlation
Programme (IGCP), a major scientific
venture, undertaken jointly by
Unesco and the International Union
for Geological Sciences (IUGS),
devoted to the study of the earth's
crust and its mineral and energy
resources. Projects undertaken by
the IGCP range from the study of
geochronology to prospecting for
economic mineral deposits and the
processing of geological data.
XI. Culture
and the future
THE assertion of identity is inseparable from the store set
by a heritage: examples of art and architecture, but also
signs and symbols handed down through oral traditions,
literature and languages, handicrafts and folklore, music and
dances, beliefs and myths, rites and games.
Many kinds of problem arise regarding the conservation and
development of the monuments and the art inherited by
peoples: technical and financial, archaeological and historical,
socio-cultural, museological and legal. Some of them are
pyschological, primarily those caused by the indifference of
populations, even though a conservation movement has un¬
doubtedly developed during the last twenty years, thanks to the
international campaigns for the safeguarding of outstanding
monuments launched by Unesco.
In the case of countries dispossessed under colonial rule of
the works of art and monuments which were the most symbolic
of their identity, and in which the illicit traffic in cultural pro¬
perty is most prevalent, the problem of safeguarding is also the
problem of restitution.
Efforts to introduce on a general basis the conduct and co¬
ordination of surveys and the collecting and recprding of oral,
musical and gestual traditions, are still of a sporadic and
dispersed nature.
Culture as an industry
In this respect attention should be drawn to both the potential
uses and the risks involved in the development of the cultural in¬
dustries, which have profoundly changed living conditions and
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
In co-operation with the United Nations
Development Programme (UNDP),
Unesco created in 1980 at Niamey
(Republic of Niger) a Regional Training
Centre for museum specialists from
French-speaking African countries. Six-
month courses are scheduled to be held
at the Centre until 1 986. They will cover
museum administration and manage¬
ment, the preservation of the cultural
and natural heritage, African archaeo¬
logy and prehistory, ethnomusicology,
photography and display techniques,
taxidermy and conservation. Left, an
anthropomorphic harp from the Central
African Republic.
Photo © Musée de l'Homme, Pans
the climate of cultural expression in many countries. These in¬
dustries provide the possibility of considerably broadening the
fields of knowledge and the scope of man's imagination: they
can substantially increase the opportunities for contact with
outstanding cultural works and play an increasingly significant
part in encounters between cultures and their mutual enrich¬
ment. Nonetheless, they sometimes appear to set their seal on
a pattern of "consumption" of culture which does not always
foster personal, enriching contact with creative works. Thus
there is a visible deterioration in cultural practices, leading to a
kind of "cultural escapism" based on inactivity and a rejection
of reality.
The very nature of these industries makes them promote pro¬
ducts which are the easiest to distribute and which have often
been denounced for their standardization, not to say their
mediocrity. This can lead to the erosion of cultural values,
within a society or throughout the world.
The impact of the cultural industries will be considerably in¬
creased with the advent in the near future of cultural com¬
munication satellites.
The crucial question for each country will therefore probably
be not to limit the influence of foreign products, but to acquire
its own cultural industries which will be based on the cultural
values of the community, encourage the creative participation
of individuals and groups in the life of the community, and
enable national artists to gain access to commercial production
and dissemination facilities.
The cultural heritage
The cultural heritage, and especially its architectural compo¬
nent, is at present exposed to serious risk of damage owing to
the' effects of urbanization and industrialization, air pollution,
some types of climate and certain kinds of tourism. Further¬
more, the illicit traffic in cultural property is constantly im¬
poverishing the heritage of all peoples, thus compounding the
26
losses incurred by many countries in the past under colonial or
foreign occupation.
. The objectives of the proposed programme are first of all to
get to know, i.e. to draw up inventories of, the various com¬
ponents of the heritage, especially non-physical elements such
as oral traditions and languages, beliefs and myths, dance and
music. An equally urgent objective is that of protecting the
components of the cultural heritage: the drafting of appropriate
legislation, the adoption of international protective instruments
in fields not already covered and, above all, their implementa¬
tion at national level, and the continuation of operational ac¬
tivities to safeguard and enhance historic monuments, groups
of buildings and sites. All of these are vitally important tasks.
The principles of action to be applied in carrying out this pro¬
gramme are as follows: improved facilities for taking rapid ac¬
tion to counter threats such as war or natural disasters that may
have irremediable effects on the heritage; the protection of the
cultural heritage of mankind calls for a universal effort to com¬
bat the illicit traffic in works of art and archaeological objects;
each people which so desires must be given the opportunity to
reconstitute the irreplaceable components of its cultural
heritage.
Identity and inter-cultural contacts
Far from having to turn in on themselves, cultures need each
other. At both the national and international levels, a communi¬
ty that is firmly rooted in its own authenticity helps, through ex¬
change, to strengthen and diversify that larger community
created by co-operation. Increased co-operation in turn makes
it possible to preserve the diversity of cultures which is necessary
for human progress. But one condition has to be fulfilled: co¬
operation must take the form of relationships based on recogni¬
tion of the equal worth of cultures.
In this connexion, priority should be given to the following
objectives: the rejection of ethnocentrism, the recognition of
cultural pluralism within and beyond national frontiers, and the
discovery and appreciation of cultures of other groups or other
societies.
A major problem is that of the relationship between culture
and industrial development in general: data processing, infor-
Unesco encourages the return of
works of art removed from their coun¬
tries of origin. Right, the Afo-A-Kom, a
sacred throne figure of the Kom people
of Cameroon which was stolen and
later sold in the United States. It was
subsequently purchased by the
Museum of African Art in Washington
DC, with financial support from US
collectors, specifically for return to the
United Republic of Cameroon. Far
right, mannequin adorned with ritual
objects which were smuggled out of
Ecuador.
Photo © Museum of African Art, Frederick Douglass
Institute, Washington, DC
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Unesco is preparing to launch an inter¬
national campaign for the safeguard of
Göreme in Cappadocia (Turkey) and
for the preservation of the historic
quarters of Istanbul, including the area
known as the Golden Horn, which are
threatened by modern urban develop¬
ment. Göreme (right) which began to
be settled in the 5th-6th centuries, is a
unique site where churches, shrines
and dwellings decorated with Byzan¬
tine frescoes were hollowed out of the
rock.
Photo Else Madelon Hooykaas © Rapho, Paris
mation technology, robotics, office automation, genetic
engineering. The interactions between pre-industrial and in¬
dustrial cultures may be negative, but compatibilities between
them may emerge under certain conditions.
Creation and creativity
Creativity, which represents the ability of groups and in¬
dividuals, or even whole societies, to discover, invent or rein¬
vent all the forms of expression related to their own universe is
a vital aspect of individual and group involvement in the crea¬
tion of their own culture.
Certain forms of creation seem to be on the decline, par¬
ticularly in the developing countries, owing to the weakening of
The world's common
heritage of rock art is
rapidly deteriorating
under, the combined
onslaught of public
works, pollution and
vandalism. Unesco has
therefore launched a
new programme which
aims to create a world
inventory of rock art
sites, to protect such
sites, and to promote
the development of ar¬
chaeological parks and
ecomuseums around
them. Right, rock pain¬
ting at Tassili N'Ajjer
(central Sahara)
depicts a dromedary.
Photo J.-D Lajoux © Rapho, Paris
their ties with certain functions of social life. In the industrializ¬
ed countries, other forms of creation are also in a state of crisis
because of competition from the audio-visual media. In the
field of literature, music, and sometimes the visual arts, con¬
sumer products are distributed on a massive scale at the expense
of more difficult works. '
Certain aspects of aesthetic and intellectual creativity are
likewise undergoing erosion or even being undermined. Leisure
time in the industrialized countries, although increasing, is
usually devoted to passive cultural consumption. In the ]
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
developing countries, alongside some remarkable forms of
creative expression, a certain loss of confidence in local values
as against imported forms can also be observed. A society which
loses its creativity, however, becomes weakened in general.
In order to act in these fields, first of all freedom of creation,
expression and dissemination should be established in the
various social and cultural contexts as a principle preceding any
action in support of creation and creativity. It will then be
necessary to facilitate relations between creative artists and the
society in which they live through all available means.
Cultural development
Development cannot be limited to economics alone but im¬
plies that the goals of growth must also be defined in terms of
cultural improvement.
This view of development, less energy-consuming, more
respectful of the environment and more concerned for com
munity life and conviviality, has begun to be accepted by the
developing as well as by the industrialized countries.
The objectives are to obtain a better understanding of the
concrete significance of considering culture a dimension, and
even the foundation, of economic and social development; to
study the discrepancies between individual and group cultural
practices (often different from their underlying aspirations) and
' the cultural policies applied; to enable all countries to obtain the
instruments necessary for cultural development and to assist
them in adapting the latter to the different political and social
contexts; to train the appropriate personnel, particularly need¬
ed in many countries, making sure they have multi-purpose
qualifications, know the cultural needs of each population and
maintain relations with the other agents of development; and to
contribute to the strengthening of international cultural co¬
operation, thereby helping to bring peoples closer together and
promoting the building of peace.
XII. Prejudices, intolerance,
racism, apartheid
IN spite of the progress that has been made in the last thirty
years, racism continues to flourish, ethnic conflicts are on
the increase, and intolerance and prejudice have even
gained ground, notwithstanding the fact that all States, with the
exception of the Republic of South Africa, have publicly under¬
taken to end all forms of discrimination.
Racism
In those countries where groups, often defined as "races",
have for historical reasons been discriminated against, in¬
equalities persist at nearly all levels. Education systems, even
where they are theoretically open to all, in fact often perpetuate
long-standing inequalities between racial or ethnic groups, as is
shown by the fact that the percentage of children completing
secondary education varies for different groups, and by data on
the ethnic origin of the vast majority of students in certain
disciplines in higher education. Mention must also be made of
the selection process, which often influences the professional
prospects and the social position of candidates having the same
educational background and qualifications, and operates to the
detriment of certain groups. The effects of obstacles resulting
from belonging to a particular "racial" or ethnic group are par¬
ticularly apparent in the crucial areas of science and technology
and in the matter of access to positions of responsibility. Thus,
if the members of certain groups are confined to particular sec¬
tors of the economy or are relegated to performing more menial
jobs, "race" or membership of an ethnic group may come to
coincide to some extent with class.
Situations of this kind are likely to lead to conflicts with the
dominant population on the one hand and subsidiary conflicts
between ethnic groups on the other.
While internal migration continues as a result of the scientific
and technical revolution, an increasing number of countries are
now using migrant workers.
More and more frequently, however, immigrants are not only
recruited to replace local workers in those sectors of the
economy where the latter no longer wish to work, but are also
in some cases employed as agricultural labour, concentrated in
sectors which are subject to specific discriminatory legislation.
Where the immigrants are from former colonies or dependent
territories, stereotypes associated with colonialism may con¬
tinue or be reactivated.
While situations of this kind occur mainly in the highly in¬
dustrialized countries, the use of immigrant labour in certain
28
sectors of the economy in some countries which are now in the
process of industrializationsomething quite separate from the
recruitment of highly skilled or trained employees may also
lead to difficult problems in "racial" and ethnic relations.
Ethnic or economic conflicts
and religious intolerance
Although problems of a "racial" or ethnic nature are more
noticeable in urban settings, they are by no means unknown in
rural areas. An extreme case is that which arises with the con¬
vergence, in certain areas, of extreme poverty, land shortage
and racial divisions. A frequent result of such a situation, which
may be a consequence of past conquest, is that certain groups
are relegated to the poorest agricultural areas or are concen¬
trated in the plantation sectors where there is a considerable
need for seasonal labour.
The existence of so-called "racial" groups and ethnic groups
is nevertheless a cultural fact resulting from language, religion,
common historical experience and shared cultural values and
forms of expression. Culture is also often the vehicle through
which prejudices are transmitted, ideas of dominance take
shape and resistance to injustice and inequality is forged.
In those countries where many languages are used, factors
that are primarily economicespecially in the case of the
poorer countriespreclude the equal use of all of them in
education, administration and the media; furthermore, the re¬
quirements of nationwide communication may make it
necessary to use, at this level, only one or a few languages. A
so-called common language may however be imposed as part of
the apparatus of domination, as a symbol of conquest, or to in¬
stitute a de facto "racial" or ethnic discrimination where none
is officially recognized. Some ethnic conflicts may thus be ex¬
pressed in terms of language.
As far as religions are concerned, although it is true that they
are inseparably linked with the highest spiritual and cultural
values of every society, it is no less true that religion may be the
cause and justification of certain kinds of exclusion. Different
religious affiliations may then be a cause of division between
groups or be a contributing factor in certain social conflicts,
despite the fact that these same religions preach tolerance.
Opposition to colonial systems has often united many groups
in their struggle for independence and freedom. But the way in
which the occupation was carried out, the inequality of access
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
to education, the methods of recruitment to the civil service and
of allocating land or settling disputes occasionally caused con¬
flict between different ethnic groups.
The inhuman policy of apartheid is the foundation of South Africa's
political and economic system. An essential element in the enforce¬
ment of apartheid is the system of passes, or "reference books",
which Africans, women as well as men, have to carry at all times
and show on demand to the police. A black South African who
enters a "white" area without a pass faces prosecution and im¬
prisonment. Above, cover and some of the inside pages of a
"reference book".
The media and textbooks as vehicles ofprejudice
While certain aspects of culture may be vehicles for the
transmission of prejudice, it is increasingly through the media
that the general public gains a knowledge of other countries and
of racial and ethnic groups. Even where it is not racist, the man¬
ner of presentation of news may nevertheless keep prejudice
alive by laying emphasis, for example, on crime associated with
particular ethnic or cultural groups. Articles on social questions
may involve negative stereotyping. Immigration may be
presented in such a way as to make one think that it is illegal or
in need of regulation. Cultural differences may be presented in
a twisted or negative way.
The influence of the media is often accentuated by that of
school textbooks. Although these may be free of explicit racism
and even proclaim the equality of all peoples, they nevertheless
tend frequently to describe historical events, industrial develop¬
ment and cultural achievements without adequate explanation
or simply in an unbalanced way. While some particularly
flagrant errors have been rectified, the stereotypes are still there
and are accepted all the more readily because the bias is not
perceived. "Aggressive nationalism" does not always identify
itself in clear terms. The way in which historical events are
selected may suggest the existence of intrinsic superiority or im¬
mutable differences.
The gravity and scale of these problems make it essential for
Unesco to mobilize its own forces and those of peoples
everywhere in the struggle against apartheid, racism and
discrimination, prejudice and intolerance. The first step should
be to analyse and expose the mechanisms of these phenomena.
Without prejudice to the role of governments and the political
decisions they must take in order to effect structural change,
Unesco's mandate lies essentially in the area of those social in¬
stitutions which are tainted by discrimination. Special emphasis
will be placed on the problems of access to education, science
(including the social sciences), culture and values that sustain
prejudice, intolerance and racism.
Against apartheid
Increased attention will be paid to the question of apartheid,
which will be the subject of a special programme. Studies based
on a structural analysis will be undertaken to expose the
methods used to ensure for the South African economy the
benefit of a virtually unlimited pool of labour that can be ex¬
ploited at low cost; to throw light on the specific mechanisms
whereby the tensions that exist in other societies are exploited
and magnified in the Republic of South Africa in the service of
a racist policy; to demonstrate the way in which spurious
"culturist" ideologies are used to justify the presentation of
apartheid as "separate development"; and to unmask the
deliberate use of language as an instrument of division.
More generally, this major programme will involve both con¬
sideration of the meaning of tolerance in the context of widely
differing social situations, historical experiences and cultural
and philosophical traditions and research activities centred on
the nature of prejudice and its modes of transmission and on the
aetiology and social implications of discrimination, prejudice
and intolerance this reflection and research to be conducted in
such a manner as to provide guidance and information for
action.
In addition to their publication in a form accessible to the
public at large and to their circulation among journalists,
educators, etc., steps will be taken to incorporate the results of
this works in teacher-training courses, and in education at all
levels.
Photos © International Defence and Aid Fund, London
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
XIII. Peace,
international understanding,
human rights
and the rights of peoples
THE arms race is a major threat to peace, and constitutes
an enormous waste of human and material resources: a
million dollars are spent every minute on arms and
some 500,000 scientists are currently engaged in military
research throughout the world.
The arms race gives structure to systems of alliances and
perpetuates relationships of domination. The States which sell
arms also derive substantial economic benefits in that their
defence systems cost them less thanks to their large-scale arms
production. These States refine their technologies through the
intermediary of the "laboratories" provided by battlefields.
Peace is incompatible with malnutrition, extreme poverty
and the refusal of the rights of peoples to self-determination.
Disregard for the rights of individuals and peoples, the per¬
sistence of inequitable international economic structures, in
terference in the internal affairs of other States, foreign occupa¬
tion and apartheid are always real or potential sources of armed
conflict and international crisis. The only lasting peace is a just
peace based on respect for human rights. But it must be
recognized that human rights and the rights of peoples are con¬
tinually being violated. The worst of all the typical forms of
violation of human rights is torture; its very widespread practice
is a flagrant repudiation of human dignity.
Effective respect for human rights is one of the basic concerns
of Unesco, which attaches great importance to the connexion
between the rights of the individual and the rights of peoples.
Respect for the dignity of the human person is inseparable from
respect for the freedom of peoples and respect for the equality
of the rights of nations. While it is essential that the individuals
and groups concerned should be able to become aware of all
their rights and to exercise them effectively, the State must also
In search of peace
Article I of Unesco's Constitution
proclaims that "the purpose of the
Organization is to contribute to
peace and security by promoting col¬
laboration among the nations
through education, science and
culture...".. Accordingly Unesco is
doing all in its power "to bring about
a gradual change in mental attitudes
so that more thought is given to the
pursuit of peace" (Amadou-Mahtar
M'Bow). Recent Unesco activities in
this field include: a World Congress
on Disarmament Education (Paris,
1980); regional training seminars for
university teachers in the field of
disarmament (Caracas 1981,
Djarkarta 1982); studies on the
social, economic and cultural effects
of the arms race; publications in¬
cluding a reader on armaments, arms
control and disarmament (1981),
handbooks, and a series of works on
"New Challenges to International
Law".
Drawing André Pans Photo © André Paris,
Fontenouille, France
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
assume the great responsibilities which fall to it to guarantee the
exercise of individual rights, whether civil and political or
economic, social and cultural.
To express the idea of a "right to peace" for nations, peoples
and individuals, is to evoke not only a basic requirement of sur¬
vival and security, but also the legitimate aspiration of any na¬
tional community to participate fully and freely on equal terms
in the concert of nations and the building of a more satisfactory
world order.
Lastly, the recognition of the right of each people to the
preservation and full development of its personality and to a
determination of its future has contributed to a unanimous
awareness of the vital importance of the cultural dimensions of
the collective identity. The right of the individual to free access
and unhindered participation in the culture of his choice cannot
be called in question. However, the idea has taken root that the
right of peoples to the preservation, assertion and development
of their own culture, considered as a living and developing
culture, occupies an important place in the list of human rights
and the conditions necessary for peace.
From this standpoint, three plans may be distinguished: for
research and study in the field of social sciences and philosophy;
for standard-setting; and for education and information.
Whether the issue is human rights or peace, the emphasis
should be on reflection and research in a global and historical
perspective, bringing out, in particular, the role that education,
science, culture and communication can play or have played in
the past. It is for philosophical reflection to shed light on the
relationship between different systems of values and the exigen¬
cies of peace and of respect for human rights.
Ignorance concerning human rights is still widespread. By
virtue of its vocation, Unesco should pursue its educational mis¬
sion in this area with ever-increasing vigour. In addition, the
media should be encouraged to balance their presentation of the
results of research carried out in this field in different parts of
the world, so as to promote access to knowledge concerning
peace and human rights in a spirit of international
understanding.
The promotion of peace and international understanding, the
attainment of freedom by peoples and the realization of human
rights are the tasks of a strategy which must be devised as a
coherent whole, for the objectives to be pursued are interdepen¬
dent and mutually complementary. The struggle for peace and
human rights must be waged at all levels and in response to the
challenges of all specific situations.
HUMAN RIGHTS
SOME LINES OF UNESCO ACTION
.¿ViO' 4° <*
*° v> &
# / S9
# ' / %
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
XIV. The status of women
WOMEN represent 50 per cent of the world adult
population and one-third of the official labour
force, but they perform nearly two-thirds of all
working hours, receive only one-tenth of the world income and
own less than 1 per cent of world property. Much of the work
women do is not officially recognized, and consequently does
not entitle them to any remuneration, respect or rights usually
associated with work.
A source of cheap labour
Concealment of the real economic value of the daily tasks
that women perform in the home accounts for the belittlement
of this so-called "women's work", regarded not as work but as
a duty inherent in the natural function of women.
Moreover, despite anti-discriminatory legislation, in practice
bias often persists in recruitment or wage policies, owing to the
stereotyped attitudes of employers who, for equal qualifica¬
tions, prefer to reserve the best-paid positions for men,. In a
period of crisis, the image of women as "job-stealers" re-
emerges with all its force. Current economic difficulties have
been instrumental in reviving the ideology of "a woman's place
is in the home", which is hardly likely to speed progress towards
equal opportunity.
The situation of women in the labour force is connected part¬
ly with their education and qualifications, which are generally
inferior to men's. The most serious problem is undoubtedly il¬
literacy among women. From world figures available for 1980
it is projected that the number of illiterate women will reach an
estimated 539 million by 1990.
Out of the jobs that really matter
It should also be noted that in a great many countries women
have not yet succeeded as effectively as men in taking advantage
of the education that they have received in order to gain
equivalent economic, social or political power. Socio-cultural
behaviour, whether family attitudes or tendencies encouraged
by the school system, inclines girls more often towards literary
studies rather than training in science and technology. On the
whole, there are very few women at levels and in branches of
education leading to the upper echelons of the civil service.
Everything seems to suggest that women may have access to
culture and prestige, but not to power.
The difficulties women encounter in attaining positions of
responsibility strongly emphasize the fact that equality is
basically a political problem, and that it is related to the balance
of power. The participation, or rather non-participation, of
women in political life is a fundamental part of the problems
surrounding the status of women.
Education can play a decisive part in making women aware
of their own aspirations, their real potential and their rights. To
that end, it remains necessary to revise textbooks and educa¬
tional materials so as to rid them of all forms of discrimination;
to examine, in the same light, the processes of filtering and
orientation that take place at various levels of education; to take
specific measures to change the traditional attitudes of boys and
men towards women and to encourage a redistribution of roles
between the two sexes, particularly in the home.
As far as the media and cultural industries are concerned,
women are represented far more often as objects than as sub¬
jects, and have little opportunity to convey their own view of the
world, their interpretation of reality, and their image of the
future. It is a remarkable fact that almost all scenarios of the
future that have yet been devised have been the work of men.
Do they, in the long run, accept the man-made universe in which
they live, and confine themselves to seeking equality with men,
or have they a different vision of the world, one which they will
try to get their male partners to accept?
32
' ' Women 's problems ' '
problems of society at large
All too often, again, action undertaken on behalf of women
has been of a piecemeal and fragmentary nature: literacy cam¬
paigns, improvement of household and agricultural know-how,
access to technical and vocational training, etc., geared to par¬
ticular aspects of the status of women but not integrated into a
comprehensive view of society, its organization and its modes
of operation. The crippling restrictions which weigh on women
are hardly likely to disappear so long as they are regarded as
"women's problems" and not as global problems of concern to
society as a whole, so long as any action on behalf of women
is not preceded by the launching of activities designed to inform
the entire community and arouse its awareness.
For the whole of society must be involved. The achievement
of equality between the sexes does not merely mean enabling
women to attain the same status as men in order to fit into a
world fashioned according to the interests and dreams of men
alone. It means starting a decisive process of transformation of
the relationships between men and women in order to arrive at
a genuine redefinition of their respective roles.
Hitherto the international community has all too often
deprived itself of their contribution and their vision in the task
it was pursuing,- by trying to build the unity of the human race
on the basis of a single model and an implicit reference: the
male. Sustained efforts must now be made to eradicate the
masculine bias from the very concepts of universal knowledge.
Unesco is increasingly involved in the search for solutions to the
major problems related to women's status in the modern world,
notably their participation in development, the improvement of
their economic situation, literacy and education. Unesco's action
follows the lines of its participation in the activities of the United
Nations Decade for Women (1975-1985): equality, development
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Giving all women access to
education, reducing female il¬
literacy and encouraging
greater participation of
women in the development
process are among the aims
of Unesco's major programme
on the status of women. With
these aims in mind, Unesco
collaborates in the organiza¬
tion throughout the world of
regional studies on equality of
educational opportunities for
women and training courses
for those responsible for the
education of women in rural
areas. Left, a Mexican woman
sets off to market.
Photo Silvester © Rapho, Paris
It is clearly for women themselves to define their problems
and to identify the solutions that appear most relevant. Hence
any action undertaken by Unesco to help in improving the
status of women must be devised and launched in close co¬
operation with governmental and non-governmental organiza¬
tions of women and with the institutions set up at the national,
regional and international level. Special efforts will be made to
assist women's movements and organizations in strengthening
their activities and in mobilizing greater numbers of women
from all walks of life. Broadly speaking, Unesco wishes to inte¬
grate the female dimension into the whole range of programmes
and activities contemplated under the second Medium-Term
Plan.
Effectively to put into practice in the world of today the need
for the solidarity of mankind, evoked by the founders of the
Organization, is a possibility now within our grasp, for events
in recent years have brought about the existence of a vast
worldwide human community; it is also an overriding necessity,
dictated by the perils with which we are threatened. If the frail
craft of mankind is to be prevented from drifting towards a
future beyond anyone's control, the only course is that which
leads to the emergence of a world community which will be
united and reconciled with itself, in a spirit of mutual tolerance,
justice and peace.
Among its other activities on behalf of women, Unesco seeks to
strengthen the role of women in national liberation movements and
to increase women's participation in national reconstruction in
newly independent countries. Above, a young mother waves Zim¬
babwe's new flag on the first anniversary of the country's in¬
dependence, achieved in 1980.
Photo James Stanfield © National Geographic Society, Washington, DC
and peace. But Unesco is also working towards an overall redefini¬
tion of the roles of men and women in the context of the problems
facing contemporary societies. Left, a young Indian woman
teacher at Bombay's higher technical school. Right, a young Euro¬
pean father does the family ironing.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
STOP PRESS... STOP PRESS... STOP PRESS... STOP 1
A S this issue of the Unesco Courier goes to press, the
/\ Fourth Extraordinary Session of the Unesco General
Jl\. Conference is drawing to a close. We are
therefore unable to publish infull the speech of the Director-
General, Mr. Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, in reply to the gen¬
eral debate on the Organization's Medium-Term Plan for
1984-1989. However, we present below the salient points of
thespeech in whichMr. M'Bow summed up the general tenor
of the Conference and replied to certain observations on the
Plan made by delegates in the course of the debate.
The overall structure of the Plan had won general appro¬
val, Mr. M'Bow declared, and the debate showed that the
inclusion in thefirst part of the Plan ofan analysis ofmajor
world problems had made it possible "better to understand
the interrelationships between the different problems and
thus to put them in perspective in an overall view ofpresent-
day reality".
It was apparent that, despite the diversity ofsituations and
philosophical orientations, there existed hopes and fears,
which the delegates held in common. Thus there was "the
possibility of a consensus going beyond the divisions of
North and South, East and West, which would unite the
international community in a shared understanding ofa cer¬
tain number ofcritical issues". The Director General empha¬
sized that the debate had been dominated by a sense of
urgency to seek solutions "which must be called, in the ful¬
lest and widest sense of the term, cultural responses".
The majorprogramme on Reflections on World Problems
and Future-oriented Studies "constituted one ofthe essential
tasks of Unesco 's intellectual and ethical calling ". The pro¬
gramme, resolutely innovative asfar aspoints of view, inter¬
pretations and ideas were concerned, had to reflect the entire
diversity of approaches which existed in all the world's
regions, allow a better articulation between thought and
action, and be carried out with the greatest objectivity.
Turning to the communication issue, the Director-General
declared that "a wide agreement had emerged on the general
conception" which guides Unesco in thisfield. Emphasizing
that the notion of communication is more "complex" than
"ambiguous", Mr. M'Bowfound that there was wide agree¬
ment on the diagnosis ofthepresent situation, but this agree¬
ment did not mean that there were not many hesitations on
the implementation of the solutions. Thus it was premature
to begin preparing a declaration on the principles of a new
world information and communication order, but necessary
"to continue, to deepen and to enrich the dialogue so as to
allow the progressive emergence of a certain number of
principles let us not call them standards capable of
guiding international action in this field".
The Director-General recalled that the concept of culture
had been defined more and more precisely during recent
years. He stressed the close links between development
action and the understanding of local cultural situations. He
was particularly concerned about the cultures of "small
populations" whose languages were little known.
After referring to the question of The Status of Women,
Unesco 's concern with which is reflected in all its program¬
mes, and to the major programme on Principles, Methods
and Strategies of Action for Development, the Director-
General discussed delegates' observations on the majorpro- ,
gramme on The , Elimination of Prejudice, Intolerance,"
Racism and Apartheid. The text of the Plan, he pointed out,
"covers entirely the different forms of discrimination, in¬
tolerance and prejudice, whether they are ethnic, linguistic,
cultural or religious in nature".
With regard to the major programme on Peace, Interna¬
tional Understanding, the Rights of Peoples and Human
Rights, the Director-General noted that "the vast majority
of speakers expressed the conviction that more than ever
today peace constituted the common aspiration of huma¬
nity". Unesco had always encouraged research at the highest
intellectual level, reflecting the worldpanorama ofconcepts
and theories on peace. Unesco would also continue to encou¬
rage education for disarmament and the dissemination of
information on peace and disarmament to schools, univer-
' sities and scientific circles, as well as to the general public.
Turning, finally, to questions concerning priorities and
programme concentration, the Director-General stressed
that the planning methods adopted had enabled Member
States to determine thepriorityfields and strategies ofaction
for the period of the Plan. He noted that "the delegations
had expressed themselves asfavouring a gro wth of Unesco 's
activities", going towards their enrichment and not towards
a selectivity which would neglect certain of their aspects.
There was, indeed, sometimes a contradiction between the
wish to extend the activities of the Organization and the ten¬
dency expressedfrom time to time not to increase its resour¬
ces accordingly. The balance between action and reflection
ought to be maintained; evaluation should not become an
end in itself but rather a means to assist the Organization to
act under the most appropriate conditions.
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (11
issues a year including one double issue).
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and three vouchee copies are sent to the
editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author's
name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on re¬
quest. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply
coupon covering postage. Signed articles express
the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the
editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier
staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform
(microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) University
Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100,
U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian Head",
Inc., 111 West 40th Street. New York, U.S.A.; (3)
Bell and Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road. Wooster,
Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
French: Alain Lévêque (Paris)
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov (Paris)
Arabic: Sayed Osman (Paris) '
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: Mohammed Reza Berenji (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed' Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Lim Moun-Young (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salaam)
Braille: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Punisa Pavlovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Bulgarian: Pavel Pissarev (Sofia)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Six Unesco international quarterlies
PROSPECTS studies all aspects of education, particularly innovation and reform.
Annual subscription: 68 French francs Single issue: 20 FF
INTERNATIONAL SOCIAL SCIENCE JOURNAL takes an interdisciplinary look at the latest developments in social
science theory and practice.
Annual subscription: 110 FF Single issue : 34 FF
IMPACT OF SCIENCE ON SOCIETY reports on science as a major force for social change, emphasizing the inter¬
relationship of science, technology and human development.
Annual subscription: 68 FF Single issue: 20 FF
NATURE AND RESOURCES reviews the latest research on man and the biosphere, ecology, hydrology and the
earth sciences.
Annual subscription: 38 FF Single issue: 12 FF
CULTURES. Dialogue between peoples of the world examines the cultural achievements of different world civiliza¬
tions, their value systems, customs, ways of communication and popular traditions.
Annual subscription: 110 FF Single issue: 34 FF
MUSEUM presents for layman and specialist alike the latest developments, techniques and exhibits in the world of
museums.
Annual subscription: 110 FF Single issue: 34 FF
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the
National Distributor in your country. (See list
below; names of distributors in countries not
listed, along with subscription rates in local
currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Coll-
ingwood Victoria 3066, Publications: Educational Supplies
Pty. Ltd. P.O. Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals:
Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale
2100, NSW. Sub- agent- United Nations Association of
Australia, P.O. Box 175, 5th floor, Ana House, 28 Elizabeth
Street, Melbourne Victoria 3000 - AUSTRIA.
Buchhandlung Gerold and Co , Graben 31 , A-101 1 , Vienna
BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International Ltd., Ittefaq
Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only. N V.
Handelmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100
Deurne- Antwerpen French edition and general Unesco
publications agent- Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1 060
Brussels, CCP000-0070823-1 3 - BURMA. Trade Corpora¬
tion No 9, 550-552 Merchant Street, Rangoon -CANADA.
Renouf Publishing Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West,
Montreal, Que. H3H 1 M7. - CHINA. China National Publica¬
tions Import and Export Corporation, P O. Box 88, Beijing
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makanos 3rd Avenue, P.O
Box 1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L.,
Spalena 51, Prague 1 (Permanent display): Zahranicni
literatura, 1 1 Soukenicka, Prague 1 . For Slovakia only: Alfa
Verlag. Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava
CSSR. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export and Subscription
Service, 35 Norre Sogade, DK 1370, Copenhagen K.
EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco
Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo. - ETHIOPIA.
National Agency for Unesco, P.O Box 2996, Addis Ababa. -
FINLAND. Akateemmen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1,
SF-00100 Helsinki 10, Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy,
Koivuvaarankuja 2, 01640 Vantaa 64. FRANCE. Librairie
de l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP.
12598-48. - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus
Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internationalen
Buchhandlungen in the G DR.- FED. REP. OF GERMANY.
For the Unesco Courier {German, English, French and Spanish
editions): Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb,
Basaltstrasse 57, D53O0 Bonn 3. For other Unesco publica¬
tions. Karger Verlag, Germering/Munchen. For scientific maps
only: Geo Center, Postfach 800830, Stuttgart 80 -
GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd , P.O. Box 195,
Accra, Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The
University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University
Bookshop of Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legón,
P.O. Box 1, Legón - GREAT BRITAIN. See United
Kingdom - HONG KONG. Federal Publications (HKI Ltd., 5A
Evergreen Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen.
Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon. Hong Kong
Government Information Services, Publication Centre, Basker-
ville House, 22 Ice Street. - HUNGARY. Akadémiai
Konyvesbolt, Váo u. 22, Budapest V; A K V. Konyvturosok
Boltja, Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest VI. - ICELAND.
Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co., H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik
INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate,
Bombay 400038, 1 7 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 1 3; 36a,
Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; 5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh,
Hyderabad 500001 (AP), 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road, Banga-
lore-560001 ; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-
Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co. 1 7 Park Street, Calcutta
70016; Scindia House, New Delhi; Publication Unit, Ministry
of Education and Culture, Ex. AFO Hutments, Dr. Rajendra
Prasad Road, New Delhi 110001. - INDONESIA. Bhratara
Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto Iskandardinata III, Jakar¬
ta; Gramedia Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta, Indira
P.T., Jl. Dr Sam Ratulangie 37, Jakarta J'usai IRAN.
Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co., 28, Vessal Shirazi
Street, Enghélab Avenue, P.O. Box 314/1486, Teheran, Ira¬
nian Nat. Comm. for Unesco, Ave. Iranchahr Chomali No. 300,
B.P. 1533, Teheran. - IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, Al -
Rashid Street, Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Com¬
pany of Ireland Ltd., Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin
12. - ISRAEL. ABC. Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71
Allenby Road, Tel Aviv 6 1 000 J AMAICA. Sangster's Book
Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston. -
JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc , Shuhwa Toranomon
3bldg, 23-6, Toranomon 3-Chome, Minato-ku, Tokyo 105,
KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O Box 30571,
Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. - KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait; for the Unesco
Courier: Farafalla Press Agency, P.O. Box SAFA 4541,
Kuwait. LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod,
Lesotho, Southern Africa LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy
Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency
for Development of Publication & Distribution, P.O Box
34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22,
Grande-Rue, Luxembourg. MALAYSIA. University of
Malaya Co-operative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur 22-11.
MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta.
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street,
Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins,
Monte-Carlo. NETHERLANDS. For periodicals only: Dek-
kerand Nordemann NV.P 0 Box 197, 1000 AD Amsterddam;
for publications only KEESING BOEKEN B.V., Postbus 1118.
1000 BC Amsterdam. - NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van
Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N A.
NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, Govern¬
ment Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P 0 Box 5344, Auckland,
130, Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Chnstchurch; Alma
Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1 1 04,
. Dunedin; Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington
NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife, The University
Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka; The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zana. NORWAY. All publications:
Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43,
Oslo 1 ; Universitets Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, POB.
307 Blindem, Oslo 3. For Unesco Courier only: A S Narvesens
Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6. - PAKISTAN. Mirza
Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O. Box No. 729,
Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern Book Co., 926 Rizal
Avenue, P 0. Box 632, Manila D-404. - POLAND. Orpan-
Import, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars Polona-Ruch,
Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068 WARSAW. - POR¬
TUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livrana Portugal, rua do Carmo
70, Lisbon. - SEYCHELLES. National Bookshop, P.O. Box
48, Mahé; New Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131,
Mahé. SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and
Sierra Leone Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (SI Pte Ltd., No. 1 New In¬
dustrial Road, off Upper Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19.
SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop
and General, P O. Box 951 , Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA.
All publications: Van Schaik's Book-store (Pty. I Ltd., Libri
Building, Church Street, P.O. Box 924, Pretoria For the
Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Central News agency,
P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg. - SRI LANKA. Lake House
Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O B.
244 Colombo 2. - SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box
1118, Khartoum. - SWEDEN. All publications A/B CE.
Fritzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel, Regeringsgatan 1 2, Box 1 6356,
10327 Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-
Forbundet, Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm.
- SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag, 5
Ramistrasse Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211,
Geneva 1 1 , C C P. 12-236. - TANZANIA. Dares Salaam
Bookshop, POB. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam. - THAILAND.
Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg
Phaya Sn, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok: Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company,
1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. - TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I. - TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi
A S , Istiklâl Caddesi, No. 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu,
Istanbul - UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 7145,
Kampala - UNITED KINGDOM. H M. Stationery Office,
P.O Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Govt. Bookshops in London,
Edinburgh, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol; for
scientific maps only: McCarta Ltd., 122 King's Cross Road,
London WC1 X 9 DS. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park
Avenue South, New York, N.Y. 10010. - U.S.S.R.
Mezhdunarodnaya Kmga, Moscow, G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost, Mica 30/11, Zagreb; Cankar-
jeva Zalozba, Zopitarjeva 2, Lubljana; Nolit, Terazije
27/1 1 , Belgrade - ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales IPVT)
Ltd , 67 Union Avenue, Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
THE
MEDIUM-TERM
PLAN
AT A GLANCE
1984-1989
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
THE MEDIUM-TERM
ANALYSIS OF WORLD PROBLEMS
A worldwide context
The first observation concerns what might be called "globalization" of human activities, henceforth placed in a
worldwide context. As predicted by the French poet Paul Valéry more than half a century ago "Nothing will be done
any more without the whole world being involved". Yet despite this clear awareness of the worldwide nature ofproblems
we generally have only incomplete analytic and predictive tools with which to tackle them.
Interdependence
The second observation is that interdependence co-exists, paradoxically, with fault lines criss-crossing the world, and that
the disparities between individuals and populations are widening and hardening and threatening to reduce vast numbers
of human beings to despair.
The arms race
The arms race has reached such proportions that it now dominates the international scene. But peace too has its dynamic,
reflected in the growing movements which exist in all countries. However, disparities and the arms race must be set in
their context: on the one hand, what might be called "ma/development" which affects all societies and an international
economic system whose dysfunctions are having painful effects; on the other, tensions and conflicts which emerge both
on a worldwide scale and in the various regions.
A new international economic order
It is in this perspective that we must place the efforts being made to introduce a more equitable system of international
economic relations and to adopt approaches based on the idea that "genuine development has to be elicitedfrom within,
willed and conducted by all the vital forces of a nation".
Human rights
The analysis of human rights brings out the paradoxical nature of the present situation. The concept of human rights
has increased in scope and substance, it applies to civil and political rights and economic, social and cultural rights. Not
only individuals but also peoples should enjoy their own specific rights. On the other hand there are massive violations,
particularly under the apartheid régime, infringements of the rights ofpeoples to self-determination, millions ofrefugees,
the challenge to individualfreedoms, mainly in the context of the repression ofopposition movements, the use of torture.
The environment
The threats overhanging the environment bear witness to the links that now bind individual and collective destinies: hence
the search for common ground and the forging of bonds of solidarity in the quest for solutions.
Universality and diversification
A further line of reflection concerns the dialectical tensions that are appearing between a trend towards the universaliza-
tion of certain ways of life, thought and action and a claim to uniqueness, to diversification.
New forms of communication
The development of new forms of communication is offundamental importance. It may be a source of enrichment and
progress provided, however, that it does not lead to the pre-eminence of certain poles ofproduction and dissemination
of knowledge, know-how and life styles. However, there are already signs of a trend towards uniformity in patterns of
behaviour and ways of life that may prove to be an impoverishment for mankind.
A new configuration of knowledge
A new configuration of knowledge is being established and the new relations being formed between the natural and the
social sciences should make it possible better to apprehend the complexity of reality. From this may result changes not
only in modes ofproduction and consumption but also in social relations themselves. The fact remains that the uneven
development of the world scientific and technological potential is such that a small number of countries alone hold the
key to the great advances of the future.
Culture the driving force behind development
Science and technology, communication and information, like education, are an integral part of culture, and the main
conclusion to emerge from this reflection on world problems is that culture is the driving force behind development.
Similarly, environmental problems refer back to fundamental value choices, which means, once again, a cultural view¬
point. Threats to peace, flagrant violations of human rights, intolerance and racism also have cultural roots.
i ' ";,: i.,-::;,,.,::.."::::.i,".,.::. 	":r::~'~":r	r::"	 "",,,"" :.';:,".",' 	:, 	 ,:-;:.:,:,:: ;, -zz
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
PLAN AT A GLANCE
THE FIVE MAIN TASKS THE MAJOR PROGRAMMES
In keeping with its fundamental constitutional
mission, the main tasks of Unesco over the years
to come may be defined as follows:
1
To contribute to a continuing study of pre- î'
sent world problems so as to create a greater \\
awareness of the common destiny which now unites :'.
individuals and peoples alike. ¡\
Reflection on world problems and future-
oriented studies.
2 To help to pave the way for the widest parti- \\
cipation by individuals and groups in the \\
life of the societies to which they belong and in that j;
of the world community. \\
II. Education for all.
III. Communication in the service of man.
-r~"3
3 To assist in strengthening problem-solving
capability by fostering the development and
democratization of education and the advancement of
science, by increasing and developing the creative poten¬
tial, both scientific and technological, of all peoples by
reinforcing aptitudes and abilities, by developing
research and training infrastructures and by promoting
the free flow of knowledge and know-how.
IV. The formulation and application of educa¬
tion policies.
V. Education, training and society.
VI. The sciences and their applications to
development.
VII. Information systems and access to
knowledge.
4 To help to facilitate the changes and transi¬
tions that are now recognized as necessary
by the international community as a whole, in fields
where the convergence of aspirations gives rise to a
broad consensus.
VIII. Principles, methods and strategies of action
for development.
IX. Science, technology and society.
X. The human environment and terrestrial and
marine resources.
5 To arouse and encourage a renewal of values
within a context of genuine understanding
among peoples, thereby advancing the cause of peace
and human rights.
XI. Culture and the future.
XII. The elimination of prejudice, intolerance,
racism and apartheid.
XIII. Peace, international understanding, human
rights and the rights of peoples.
Each oftheseJive tasks corresponds to an essential measure
that the Organization must take, given the state of the world
as it emerges from the analysis of world problems.
XIV. The status of women.
j | This major programme seeks to define a new vision oftheioles
j 1 of men and women in all fields of human activity. But thefemi-
s ] nine dimension of the problems with which Unesco is concer-
^ ned appears in all parts of the Plan.
Ill
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Walking Man
IV
Sculpture by Alberto Giacometti. Photo Dominique Roger, Unesco.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
the future begin
. ie servant of peace and of the peoples of the^rOrld, Unesco sees atfits actions as beginning and ending
with man. Man as the fount and the end of ajt^rogrej^s is symbolized in our two cover photos: above, the
Alpine source of a river and, front cover; the estuary:.bf-a river in Colombia. In this issue of the Unesco
Courier we present the broadjHJtlines ofthe^jg^izatlöiVs thinking on world problems and its plan of action
for the periodJ.984 10,198*. ¡¡^''3*À'':-.
iver photo: G^org Gerster © Rap+KrV'pim*., ~ Back cover photo: Claude Thibault ? Fotogram, P-
~*~
]]>
</page>
</document>
