<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074684eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The
Unesco I.
The artistic genius
of Latin America
fl
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A time to live...
25 Cuba
The artist in his studio
For the first time our "A time to live..."
series features a photo of a known and
named artist. This deliberate departure is
intended to emphasize the fact that art is an
integral part of the life of human com¬
munities, not an elitist adventure but a
testimony drawn from the deep soul of the
people. Both artisan and artist, the Cuban
sculptor Agustín Cárdenas works in both
wood and marble. Born in 1927, he is today
recognized both in his own country and
throughout the world as one of the most
significant sculptors of our day. Two
aspects of his work graceful totems carv¬
ed in wood, rounded volumes sculpted
from marble and more resistant materials
can be seen in this photo of the artist at
work in his studio (1971). As in the paint¬
ings of his fellow countryman Wifredo
Lam, in Cárdenas' work the memory of the
African lineage lives again in the masks and
forms, the profusion of vegetation, the
rotation of bulbs, the spikiness of thorns,
which lie at the heart of the African
aesthetic, all this in harmonious marriage
with the most recent achievements of the
plastic arts. Going beyond the facile vision
of what used to be called exoticism, paint¬
ing and sculpture are thus the contem¬
porary history of our planetthe meeting
of cultures and their often fertile symbiosis.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Unes«,courier
A window open on the world
Editorial July 1984
37th year
TO attempt a general presentation of the artistic pro¬
fusion of Latin America in a single issue of our
magazine is a challenge that we have accepted with all
its attendant risks. It was, for example, imperative to select,
in a field in which choosing is bound to be to some extent ar¬
bitrary. In making choices we have been guided by the
subterranean unity which structures creativity in this region
of the world.
At the outset we were helped in our task by the strong
presence of the Amerindian peoples. The sense of the ver¬
tical, so overwhelming as one descends the twisting road
leading to Chavin in Peru and contemplates the landscape
rising upright before one's eyes; the propensity for altitude
characteristic of the Mayas, the Aztecs and the Incas, which
sets aside the fertile stratagems of perspective and gives itself
to flatness and unbridled luxuriance of forms; the winding
curves of geometrical figures and raw colours which are part
of the legacy of pre-Columbian ceramics and carved stone
temples: all these elements can be found in the construc¬
tivism of the countries of the Rio de la Plata, in Mexican
mural art, in the work of such contemporary artists as
Gamarra and Botero, and to an extreme degree in the kinetic
structures of Soto or Cruz-Diez.
Engrafted onto this Amerindian root are certain in¬
fluences which originated in the West and have had a decisive
impact: the widespread representation of and familiarity
with death; the exacerbated conventions of colonial Ba¬
roque, which are so outstandingly displayed in the architec¬
ture of Old Havana and whose masterpieces of plastic art
seem to find a distant echo in the accumulation and density
of the painting of Seguí, in the bold architecture of contem¬
porary cities, especially Brasilia, and in the graphic inven¬
tions of modern art which Matta has taken so far. In all these
fields Latin American artists soon ceased to submit to out¬
side influences and became masters of creation, faithful to
the genius of their peoples.
It is not surprising, then, that folk art, both crafts and
painting, is so important in this part of the world. The art of
the urban barrios and rural art, Amerindian art par ex¬
cellence, it is often closely linked to the African influence.
Nevertheless, the most striking examples of African in¬
fluence are to be found in the "natural" painting of Haiti
and Brazil, but also in the highly wrought works of a Lam
or a Cárdenas.
The basic factor of Latin American art is the mixture of
cultures and their dynamism, which is renewed as a result of
this very intermingling.
Finally, we regret that lack of space has prevented us from
setting our presentation of South American art as fully as we
would have wished within the context of the daily life of the
peoples to whom it belongs. Above all we regret that we have
not been able to cite the many artists, young and still little
known beyond the frontiers of their countries, who are today
maintaining the continuity and almost boundless fecundity
of Latin American art.
Cover: Detail of The Doubts of Three Worlds, a mural executed for
Unesco's Paris Headquarters (1956) by Roberto Matta (born 1911).
Photo Jean-Claude Bernath © Unesco Courier
4 The sacred and the profane
Two faces of Meso-American art
by Jacques Soustelle
9 A labyrinth of forms
The pre-Hispanic culture of Peru
by Jesús F. Garcia Ruiz
1 4 The legacy of colonial art
by Damián Bayón
18 'Enchanted seasheir
A portrait of Old Havana
by Manuel Pereira
21 Brasilia : 'The capital of hope'
by Briane Elisabeth Panitz Bica
22 Four artists in chiaroscuro
by Edouard Glissant
29 The vibrant world of Cándido Portinarl
by Antonio Carlos Calado
30 Armando Reverón: A lust for light
by Juan Calzadilla
31 The bread (and butter) art of Ecuador
by Jorge Enrique Adoum
32 The originality of Peruvian popular art
by Manuel Checa Solan
34 The master-craftsmen of Mexico
by Anharad Lanz de Ftios
35 The dance of death
by Miguel Rojas-Mix
36 Castles in the air
Haiti's painters of high spirits
by René Depestre
37 The artistic ferment of a continent
by Carlos Rodriguez Saavedra
2 A time to live...
Cuba : The artist in his studio
Published monthly in 27 languages
by Unesco,
The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
English Italian Turkish Macedonian A selection in Braille is published
French Hindi Urdu Serbo-Croat quarterly in English, French, Spanish
Spanish Tamil Catalan Slovene and Korean
Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese
German Persian Korean Bulgarian
Arabic Dutch Swahili Greek Editor-in-chief:
Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb Edouard Glissant
ISSN 0041-5278
N° 7 - 1984 - OPI 84- 1 - 412 A
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
The sacred and the profane
by Jacques Soustelle Two faces of Meso-American art
The Valley of Mexico has yielded a rich
harvest of terra-cotta figurines that are pro¬
bably linked with agrarian cults of the pre-
classical period (2000 BC - 300 AD) which
preceded the rise of the high Meso-
American civilizations. This double-headed
terra-cotta figurine, dating back to between
2000 and 1000 BC, symbolizes, perhaps, a
form ofdualism that was deeply rooted In In¬
digenous thought.
OUR Western civilization has broken
away from the sacred. For this
reason we have difficulty in under¬
standing the art of other cultures that have
never ceased to be firmly entrenched in their
religious concepts and their view of the
world, dominated by the traditional myths.
The notion of "art for art's sake" is
foreign to these civilizations. Their plastic
arts fulfil a specific function: conjuring up
the sacred world, providing the
iconography and the material framework
that ritual demands, and making visible and
palpable the symbols that constitute the
esoteric language of religion.
Nevertheless, important though the role
of the sacred may be, the profane is not
altogether lacking; but its purpose is mainly
to glorify the greatness of men, rather than
gods, of particular men: leaders in battle,
kings, high-ranking priests.
A glance at the remains of pre-
Columbian art in Mexico and Central
America, that "Meso-America" which for
three thousand years was one of the most
brilliant centres of world culture, reveals
both the predominance of the sacred and
the vitality of a "profane area" closely link¬
ed to the social and political structures of
the autochthonous States.
It should be" noted at the outset that our
knowledge is limited to only certain of the
pre-Columbian arts, though these are ad¬
mittedly very important and extremely rich:
sculpture, whether bas-reliefs or sculpture
in the round,' the carving of semi-precious
stones, murals, the illumination of
manuscripts, designs for fabrics and
ceramics. The magnificent gold jewels vir¬
tually all disappeared in the crucibles of the
conquerors. With two or three exceptions
the fragile masterpieces of the artists who
worked delicately and with infinite patience
on the mosaics of multi-coloured feathers
were destroyed. Even though we are well ac¬
quainted with Indian instruments such as
the two-toned teponaztli, the flutes and the
horns, we know practically nothing about
JACQUES SOUSTELLE, French ethnologist,
writer and politician, is a former government
minister and is currently director of studies at
the Ecole des Hautes Etudes en Sciences
Sociales, in Paris. A specialist in the pre- Col¬
umbian cultures of Mexico and Central
America, he is a member of the Mexican In¬
stitute of Culture and has been awarded the
international Alfonso Reyes prize. Notable
among his scientific works published in
English are The Daily Life of the Aztecs on the
Eve of the Spanish Conquest ¡Stanford
University Press, 1961) and The Four Suns
(1971). In May 1984 he was received as a
member of the Académie Française.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
©
The most ancient of the Meso-
American civilizations was
that of the Olmecs, a people
who came to prominence
around 1000 BC on the coast
of the Gulf of Mexico. Rising
like an island, some 4.5
kilometres long, from a sea of
marshland, La Venta, in the
present-day State of Tabasco,
Mexico, was the first centre of
the Olmecs, whose language
and history are still shrouded
in mystery and whose in¬
fluence extended from the
Pacific coast to Guatemala,
over a period of some eight
centuries. The Olmecs in¬
vented a calendar and a form
of hieroglyphic writing, but
their civilization Is characteriz¬
ed above all by stone work and
statuarypyramids, temples,
stelae, altars, statues and
statuetteslinked to a half-
human, half-feline god. The
basic themes of Olmec art per¬
sisted for fifteen centuries in
Meso-American pre-Columbian
art in all its variations, from the
Aztecs to the Mayas. Photo
top left: carved in pale green
Jadeite and dating from bet¬
ween 500 and 100 BC, this
sculpture, 55 cm. high,
represents a man, probably a
priest, holding In his arms a
baby with feline features. It
was found at Las Limas in the
southern part of the State of
Veracruz. Top right, this stela,
at La Venta, carved In basalt
and known as "The Am¬
bassador", shows a man ad¬
vancing holding a flag. Above,
detail from another stela from
La Venta on which can be seen
a figure carrying a child, a fre¬
quently recurring theme on
the altars of this great
religious and ceremonial
Olmec centre. Even after the
decline of the Olmecs their In¬
fluence continued to be felt in
the Oaxaca region, as can be
seen, left, in this terra-cotta
masterpiece from Cuilapán,
known as "The Scribe".
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
^ Indian music, and are completely in the
dark regarding its melodies and rhythms:
the music that came over from Europe
engulfed everything.
Can the first tentative experiments of the
so-called "pre-classical" period be called
art? Indeed they can, for this "archaic
horizon" as it is often termed, corresponds
to the beginnings of agriculture and of the
peasant cults of the second millennium BC,
and its characteristics are recognizable
more or less everywhere from Central Mex¬
ico to Costa Rica. Terra-cotta figurines
predominate; they are very frequently
feminine figures that evoke our prehistoric
European "Venuses", with their ample
forms. They are probably minor deities of
the land, who were expected to make the
soil fertile and the harvests good. The
Valley of Mexico is particularly rich in
figurines of this kind.
This whole "pre-classical" period forms
an introduction to what were to be the
essentials: the high Meso-American civiliza¬
tions. The story starts somewhere around
1200 BC with the most ancient of them, the
Olmec civilization which for eight centuries
was to shed its brilliance over a region ex¬
tending from the coast of the Gulf of Mex¬
ico to the Pacific and Guatemala. It was
among the Olmecs, about whom we still
know very little, that took shape the
characteristic traits of Meso-America which
were in evidence right up to the time of the
Aztecs, nearly three thousand years later:
the paramount importance of the
ceremonial centres and consequently of
sacred art, the predominance of sculpture
and carving, stelae with bas-reliefs and
monolithic altars. The first elements of
hieroglyphic script and of the complex
calendar of Meso-America also date back
to the time of the Olmecs.
The most striking aspect of the art of the
Olmecs is their stone statuary. From the
beginning it dealt with the two major
themes mentioned earlier: the world of the
gods and the world of man. The first theme,
to give a few examples, includes the altars
of La Venta and of San Lorenzo whose bas-
reliefs show figures, gods or priests, bearing
in their arms a strange half-human, half-
feline child; the goddess of rain and of good
harvests displayed at Chalcatzingo; the
"baby jaguar" of Las Limas, a masterly
jade statuette, and the "were-jaguars" of
the Bliss Collection in the Dumbarton Oaks
Museum in Washington, D.C.
The theme of statesmen, chiefs and am¬
bassadors, is magnificently interpreted: the
colossal heads that characterize Olmec
culture would appear to be portraits. They
have individual traits and the helmets they
wear are decorated with glyphs no doubt
the names or the titles of these great men.
At La Venta, the famous stela known as
Copan, In present-day Hon¬
duras, was one of the great
religious centres of the Maya
civilization of the classical
period (300-900 AD). Copan is
famous for its sculptures in
the round and its magnificent
stelae. This grotesque-style
head is a detail from a
sculpture which is probably a
representation of the god of
storms. He carries a torch on
which is carved the glyph of
water.
"The Ambassador" tells of a historic fact:
the advancing man waving a flag is accom¬
panied by four hieroglyphic signs. Even
more celebrated is the "Uncle Sam" stela,
whose bas-reliefs show a "confrontation"
between a typical round-faced Olmec, and
an individual with angular traits: could it be
a political meeting between two chiefs of
different ethnic origins?
Thus as early as the first millennium BC,
Meso-American arts had assumed what was
essentially their definitive shape. This ob¬
viously does not mean that they remained
immutable and similar to one another dur¬
ing the whole period up to the Spanish Con¬
quest. Far from it! Each civilization and
each province developed its own styles.
However it cannot be denied that they all
share a "family resemblance". Whereas the
Olmec statuette, the Mayan bas-relief, the
painting of Teotihuacán or the Aztec statue
are all recognizable as such at the first
glance, all these works taken together are
closer to each other than those left behind
by the Andean civilizations from the
Chavin to the Tiahuanaco and the Mochica
to the Incas.
From the viewpoint of the plastic arts,
the history of Meso-America after the
Olmecs may be said to have two major
phases: the classical period, from the end of
the first millennium BC and the beginning
of the Christian era up to the tenth century,
and the post-classical period from the year
1000 to the beginning of the sixteenth cen¬
tury. The first phase encompasses the art of
Teotihuacán, of the "classical" Mayas,
Monte-Albán and Oaxaca, as. well as that of
the Gulf of Mexico (Veracruz). The second
includes the recent Mayas (Yucatán), the
Toltecs, the Mixtee culture of the Oaxaca
mountains, and that known as "Mixteca-
Puebla." which developed between the Oax
aca mountains and the plain of Cholula and
Tlaxcala, and finally the imperial civiliza¬
tion of the Aztecs.
Classical Mayan art, as it is to be found
in the metropolises such as Tikal, Palenque,
Yaxchilán, Copan and which was at its
height between the sixth and eighth cen¬
turies, can no doubt be considered the
apogee of American indigenous aesthetics.
Whether we consider the major bas-reliefs
such as those of Palenque (Panel of Slaves,
sarcophagus of the Temple of Inscriptions),
the stelae of Tikal and Copan, the lintels
and panels of Yaxchilán, or the precious
objects discovered in the tombs, such as
jade jewellery, engraved bones, or inscrip¬
tions in elegant lettering similar to arabes¬
ques, the Mayan style compels .recognition
through its unique combination of power
and grace. Gods, priests and mythological
or ritual scenes usually predominate, but in
Yaxchilán and Piedras Negras admirable
bas-reliefs recount the dynastic history of
the towns and exalt the glory of the kings.
At Bonampak the rare frescoes that escaped
destruction as a result of the corrosive ef¬
fect of the climate depict life in a medium-
sized Mayan principality, the ceremonies
and dances, the orchestras and
noblewomen, as well as violent scenes in
which proud warriors clad in jaguar pelts
and crowns of plumes play the leading
roles.
The' embellishments painted on the
polychrome vases of the high period also
tell us something about the classical Mayas,
their clothes and their ornaments, such as
the famous vase of Nebaj (in the British
Museum).
The Teotihuacán civilization on the high
central plateau was contemporary with the
classical Mayas and kept up steady relations
with them despite the great distances
separating them. Yet Teotihuacán art re¬
mained profoundly original. Its sculpture
was in the main secondary to its austere and
grandiose architecture: thus, for instance,
the magnificent temple of the Plumed Ser¬
pent, in the gigantic complex of the
"Citadel", is decorated with low and high
reliefs of the gods of rain and of vegetation.
Similarly, beautiful sculptures adorn the
columns of the recently discovered "Palace
of the Plumed Butterfly" (Quet-
zalpapalotl). A statue, or rather a
sculptured slab of monumental dimensions,
now in the Museum of Mexico City, por¬
trays a water goddess. Yet Teotihuacán art
is first and foremost the mural. This sacred
art, which is displayed in splendour on the
walls of the edifices of Atetelco and Tepan-
titla, presents the gods, the priests, the rites
and sometimes the faithful and the blessed
in Paradise. The face of the god of life-
giving rain appears as an almost obsessional
motif not only on the painted walls but also
on the ceramics, which are also painted in
fresco, a technique that was very
characteristic of this civilization.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The ancientpeoples of Mexico
and central America wrote on
stone, hide and paper. Their
writing was a combination of
pictographlc, ideographic and
phonetic elements. Right, part
of the Fejervary-Mayer Codex,
showing the four directions of
the universe. The Codex is in¬
scribed on buckskin and Is of
Mixtee origin. The Mixtees
were an ancient people whose
civilization (1200-1521) had
great artistic influence. The
upper part of the Codex
represents the "side of light";
the lowerpart is the "women's
side"; to the right is the "side
of the dead"; and to the left is
the "side of thorns",
associated with the god of
rain. The god of fire is
depicted in the centre.
Finally, the artists of Teotihuacán reviv¬
ed and brought to the highest degree of
perfection an art form that had been out¬
lined by the Olmecs: the portrayal of the
human face. These were no longer colossal
heads but funeral masks made from a hard
gemstone, and often inlaid with turquoise,
jade and mother-of-pearl, which were
carved and polished.
If one were to summarize in a few words
the art of the classical period in Oaxaca and
the Gulf region, it would be possible to
resort to schematic formulations: with
regard to the Zapotee art of Monte-Albán,
Mitla, Yagul, Monte Negro and other sites
in Oaxaca, the predominant form is
assuredly ceramics, modelled terra-cotta
for depicting the gods and sometimes
human beings, as in the case of the extreme¬
ly beautiful statuette of the "scribe"; but
the murals displayed in the funeral rooms
cannot be overlooked. Regarding the
coastal area in the present-day State of
Veracruz, the most distinctive trait is the
sculpture, the religious bas-reliefs at El Ta-
jin and above all the enigmatic objects
relating to the ritual ball game, known as
"yokes" and "palamate stones", with their
sophisticated workmanship and great
plastic beauty. However, the terra-cotta
statuettes and statues (some of which are
nearly two metres in height) which repre¬
sent either divinities or else priests or war¬
riors, are no less original.
Teotihuacán appears to have succumbed
to an assault from outside or to an internal
convulsion in the seventh century, and, at
the beginning of the tenth century,
building, sculpting and painting came to a
halt in the Mayan cities. Indeed, towards
the end of the first millennium AD, the
classical world was showing clear signs of
fatigue. Nevertheless, certain urban centres
escaped, so to speak, from the general
crisis. This was certainly the case with
©
regard to Xochicalco, on the western slopes
of the high plateau, with its beautiful,
typically Mayan bas-reliefs and its
hieroglyphics in the style of Monte-Albán.
Similarly, at the foot of the volcanoes
situated on the Puebla plateau, the ad¬
mirable and recently uncovered Cacaxtla
frescoes reflect the mythological concep¬
tions of a population that probably
originated from the Gúlf area and was
under Mayan influence, while certain
panels recount battle scenes and war
exploits.
Be that as it may, the ninth, tenth and
eleventh centuries witnessed the opening of
Mexico to large-scale migratory population
movements. The nomadic and warlike,
peoples of the northern steppes streamed in
successive waves towards the central
plateau. Some of them pressed forward to
Yucatán and Guatemala. The great city of
Tula, founded in the ninth century, took
over part of the heritage of Teotihuacán,
but the newcomers brought with them
cosmological conceptions and rites, par¬
ticularly human sacrifice and the doctrine
of cosmic war, which were reflected in art.
In Tula, the caryatids supporting the roof
of the great temple are enormous statues of
warriors standing stiffly under the weight
of their weapons, and wearing rigid crowns
made from eagle feathers. The bas-reliefs
have as their themes processions or military
marches, and eagles and jaguars devouring
human hearts. Macabre sculptures adorn
the tzompantli, where the skulls of the
sacrificial victims were piled up. The Plum¬
ed Serpent, formerly interpreted in
Teotihuacán as being the benevolent divini¬
ty of agricultural plenty, became in Tula a
god of the Morning Star, the archer-god
with the fearsome arrows.
Imposing and austere, Toltec art was the
reflection of a society dedicated to the study
of the stars and to war. Transposed to
Yucatán where it was engrafted onto
Mayan tradition, it evolved, became more
flexible and elegant, juxtaposed Mayan
motifs, such as the god of rain Chac, and
Toltec divinities, and blossomed into the
grandiose architecture of the Temple of
Warriors and the tlachtli court (a
ceremonial ball game) at Chichén-Itzá. This
hybrid art form was to enjoy two centuries
of dazzling brilliance. We owe it not only
the beautiful sculptures of the monuments,
but also interesting murals and magnificent
carvings, gold discs engraved with Toltec
motifs (for instance, scenes of human
sacrifice) with truly Mayan mastery.
In Oaxaca, the Mixtee mountain tribes
increased their pressure on the valleys and
by the eleventh century forced the Zapotees
to move eastwards, in the direction of
Tehuantepec. Once they had become the
masters of Monte-Albán and Mitla, the
Mixtees developed their own particular
style in art which reached its peak in the
creations of their goldsmiths and in the il¬
lumination of manuscripts. The gold and
turquoise jewels discovered in the Mixtee
tombs arouse our admiration. Although in¬
tended primarily as ornaments, they are
often of a religious or cosmological nature:
a pectoral has the symbols of the earth, the
sun and the cosmic tlachtli court; another
shows the god Xipe Totee; yet another a
conversion table for the Zapotee and Mix-
tec calendars. Mixtee manuscripts or
codices, with their polychrome illumina¬
tions and their pictographs, constitute a
veritable illustrated encyclopaedia, reflec¬
ting religious beliefs and rites and the
history of the aboriginal dynasties and cer¬
tain national heroes such as the legendary
chief "8-Deer". The style and colour range
of the illuminations, as well as the symbols
linked to the ritual calendar, are also found
in the murals.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
The influence of Mixtee art played a very
important role in the artistic development
of Central Mexico. The culture known as
"Mixteca-Puebla" developed from the
mountains of Oaxaca up to Cholula and
made a substantial contribution to forming
the art of the valley of Mexico. Religious
codices of high aesthetic value and great
ideological interest such as the Borgia
Codex, the frescoes of Tizatlán (Tlaxcala),
and the polychrome ceramics of Cholula
belong to this cultural movement.
The Aztecs, the most recent arrivals in
Central America, did not enter the race for
hegemony until the beginning of the fif¬
teenth century. Having very rapidly gained
ascendancy first over their neighbours on
the central plateau, and then over the
greater part of Mexican territory from coast
to coast, they began assembling the mosaic
of cities and small and large States, into
which the country was divided, into a con¬
federation. At the same time they set
themselves the aim of achieving a religious
and artistic synthesis. The main roots of
Aztec art lie in Toltec tradition tempered by
Mixtee and "Mixteca-Puebla" influences.
The discoveries of recent years in the an¬
cient Great Temple of Mexico City show
that the Aztecs knew and appreciated the
masterpieces of the civilizations that had
preceded them: that of the Olmecs, of
Teotihuacán, or those whose cities they had
occupied such as Monte-Albán. Aztec art is
After a long period of eclipse, the Maya
civilization experienced a veritable
renaissance from the end of the 10th cen¬
tury, when the Toltecs arrived in the
Yucatán peninsula, to the 16th century. The
sacred city of Chicheo Itzá is a fine example
of the marriage of Maya techniques with the
art of the Toltec invaders. Below, the "Tem¬
ple of the Warriors" at Chicheo Itzá. The
forest of pillars to the right of the temple
once supported a corbelled vault roofa
specifically Maya techniquewhich rested
on wooden lintels. The roofing finally col¬
lapsed when the lintels rotted. This vast
hypostyle hall, known as the "Thousand
Columns" was an architectural triumph
covering a surface area ofover 1,300 square
metres.
The powerful, all-conquering
Aztecs founded their capital,
Tenochtitlán (Mexico City) in
the 14th century. Their
civilization attained a high
degree of development before
its brutal destruction by Cor¬
tés and his conquistadores at
the beginning of the 16th cen¬
tury. The themes of their
statuary were mostly religious
or cosmological. Above,
statuette (68 cm. high) of the
benevolent god of rain, Tlaloc,
carved in andésite and found
in the region of Mexico City.
thus an imperial art, that of a State attemp¬
ting to absorb and restructure the heritage
of an immense group of diverse peoples.
Although much of it was destroyed,
Aztec sculpture left behind innumerable
proofs of its technical perfection and the
power of its symbolism. Once again
religious and cosmological themes
predominate: the monumental and over¬
whelmingly symbolic statue of the earth
goddess Coatlicué; the stone disc depicting
the moon divinity Coyolxauhqui; the gigan¬
tic Aztec calendar that sums up a whole
view of the world and of time: the
Cihuateteo, the macabre and grimacing
company of deified women and demons of
the twilight; the benevolent Tlaloc, the god
of rain, and Xochipilli, god of youth and
flowers. Countless examples remain of
these impeccably worked representations of
the gods which caused their contemporaries
to say that the Aztecs were "the most pious
of men". However, profane subjects were
not forgotten. The famous "Stone of
Tizoc", with its bas-reliefs glorifies the ex¬
ploits of the emperor of that name
imaginary exploits, since according to the
chronicles, this sovereign was not in truth
the valorous warrior his propaganda would
have us believe. There are numerous sober
yet touching statues of maceualli (men of
the people) as well as many sculptures
depicting plants and animals, shaggy
coyotes and insects. Less flamboyant than
those of the Mayas, less rigid than those of
the Toltecs, the art forms which flourished
in Tenochtitlán when Cortés and his com¬
panions in adventure arrived there in the'
fateful year. 15 19 were the reflection both of
a long tradition and of profound creative
sensitivity.
The "minor" arts goldwork, jewellery,
stone-carving and featherwork were
greatly appreciated by the Aztecs and the
rare examples preserved today in museums
give us a tantalizing glimpse of the perfec¬
tion they must have attained. Was not
Quetzalcoatl, the benevolent Plumed Ser¬
pent, the civilizing hero and inventor of
writing and of the calendar, the protector of
artists par excellence?
Jacques Soustelle
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
A LABYRINTH OF FORMS
The pre-Hispanic culture of Peru
by Jesús F. García Ruiz
WHEN one enters the world of the
arts and creations of pre-His¬
panic Andean societies, one fact
become immediately evident; although the
creative artists of these different cultures
employed similar techniques and materials,
each society excelled in its mastery and
perfection of form in only one of the
various branches of creative activity.
The craftsmen of Chavin had no equals
when it came to expression in stone; those
of Paracas used the distaff and spindle to
create original forms in textiles; the Nazcas
and Mochicas modelled the most beautiful
ceramics; the craftsmen of Tiahuanaco in¬
troduced the monolithic architecture which
would later be developed by the Incas; no
one equalled the Chimús in the art of
feather-work and in metalwork. The Incas
synthesized the various branches of creative
art by incorporating into their empire the
artists whom they found throughout the
length and breadth of the territories they
conquered or subjected. It is from this
specificity and variety that the art of the
Andes derives its importance.
The world of forms reflects an
astonishing level of artistic maturity in
Chavin de Huantar (1500 BC to 400 BC).
The techniques and materials used vary, but
it is in bas-relief stone carving that excep¬
tional perfection of form is displayed.
Like their contemporaries the Olmecs of
Central America, the artists of Chavin suc¬
ceeded in mastering stone and imprinting
upon it complex meanings through a
labyrinth of forms. The genius of these ar¬
tists can be appreciated at its best in bas-
reliefs such as those at El Lanzón, the
Raimondi and Yauya stelae, the obelisk at
Chavin or the warriors of Cerro Sechin,
where we can admire the genius of these ar¬
tists at its greatest. The theme is a symbolic
group embodying the anthropomorphiza-
tion of the jaguar associated with the ser¬
pent, the condor and the fish. At EI Lan¬
zón, for instance, the figure is depicted in a
standing, forward-facing position. The
head clearly indicates the symbiosis of
feline characteristicsfangs, claws, eyes
and maw. The body, like the extremities, is
reduced in size and the hair is in the form of
JESUS F. GARCIA RUIZ, of Guatemala, is a
doctor of ethnology who is currently a
research officer with the French National Cen¬
tre of Scientific Research. He is the author of
Los Mames: Estructura Sociopolítica y
Sistema de Creencias (E.H.E.S., Paris, 1977),
and Los sesos del Cielo: Etnología del Copal
(Colección Ceiba, Chiapas, Mexico, 1984)
and many articles published in international
reviews.
serpents. The Yauya stela bears an even
more striking composition. The head is
formed of two feline faces meeting in a
common mouth, while the body is that of a
fish with its gills and dorsal, ventral and
caudal fins.
The underlying meaning of this world of
forms is still to be discovered. But one thing
is clear: the artists of Chavin had mastered
the technique of working in stone and were
capable of imprinting upon it an indelible,
permanent testimony of their wisdom and
knowledge.
The civilization of Paracas (1100 BC to
200 BC), for its part, attained a high level of
artistic production in textiles. Thanks to the
ecological conditions prevailing in the
region, specimens have come down to us in
a perfect state of preservation. They include
many burial fardos (bales or bundles), with
the offerings and the cloths in which they
were wrapped. Amongst the many items
discovered ceramics with decorations in¬
cised after baking, fire-engraved vessels,
obsidian knives, cotton netting and
gauzethe painted cloths and cotton and
woollen embroidery are especially striking.
For archaeologists and art historians the
artists of Paracas will always be associated
with the art of textiles because of the com¬
plexity of their motifs and the harmony and
beauty of their colours. The most in¬
teresting items are the so-called mantos.
The base of the textile is formed of a weft
of wool or cotton, upon which a multitude
of motifs are embroideredjaguars similar
to the Chavin stylizations, bicephalous con¬
dors, reptiles, fishes, birds, hands grasping
obsidian knives, severed heads. All these
motifs are worked with great freedom of
form. The attention is especially attracted
by the wealth of ornamentation, the move¬
ment given to the forms, the constant
balance of colours. The colouring has re¬
tained all its freshness and intensity.
While it is true that pottery techniques at¬
tained high levels of artistic maturity
amongst the ceramists of Chavin, the
highest artistic levels were achieved by the
Nazcas (200 BC to 600 AD), and the
Mochicas (200 BC to 700 AD).
The Nazca ceramist was also a master of
forms and of polychrome painting. The ar¬
chetype of his creativity is the semi-globular
pitcher with two cylindrical beaks placed
vertically and joined by a bridge neck. The
potter's wheel was not used in America.
Ceramists used the technique of the rolled
clay "snake", which was first fixed at the
base and then stretched to form the walls of
The oldest culture of Peru takes its name
from the archaeological site of Chavin de
Huantar in the country's northern
highlands. Between 700 and 300 BC the in¬
fluence of the Chavin culture spread
throughout the central Andes. Chavin stone
carving, perhaps the most beautiful in South
America, is inspired by a religion based on
the worship of a feline god. The site itself,
extending over some 12,000 square metres,
consists of a complex of massive construc¬
tions. Nearby, a number of carved stone
blocks, which may originally have been
decorative elements, have been found. One
of the most famous is the diorite Raimondi
Stone, left, which stands 1.95 metres high
and dates from 1200-600 BC. This strange
semi-human figure, holding a long
ceremonial staff in each hand, displays the
combination of interwoven human and
animal forms which Is characteristic of
Chavin art.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
The influence of Chavin art is
reflected in that of the Cupisni-
que culture which flourished
on the northern coast of Peru
from around 850 to 300 BC.
Cupisnique craftsmen produc¬
ed outstandingly beautiful
brown and black pottery with
curves and whorls in
decorative patterns In which
the feline motif predominates.
Left, black ceramic stirrup
vase from the Cupisnique
region (c. 850-600 BC).
The Mochica culture
associated with Moche, the
valley on the northern coast of
Peru where its most important
remains have been found,
flourished from the 2nd to the
8th century AD and is noted
for its remarkable ceramics
evoking aspects of everyday
life. Below, polychrome terra¬
cotta vase-effigy (600 AD,
height 32.5 cm). The forehead
is framed by two birds (only
one of the wings is visible in
photo).
^ the vessel. When this initial stage had been
completed a coating of fine sand was ap¬
plied to protect the object during baking.
Afterwards it was polished to obtain the
smooth, brilliant surface which would serve
as a basis for the pictorial decoration.
It was in this final stage of painting that
the Nazca artists excelled in the creation of
unique forms. Their mastery of abstract art
attained such a level that even today we are
amazed by the imaginative power displayed
in their designs. Some pieces contain as
many as eleven colours, not counting blend¬
ed colours. The motifs used are sometimes
similar to those found in the textiles of
Paracas. They consist of anthropomorphic
figures framed b'y geometrical patterns. The
central figures are overlapped by real beings
from the animal and vegetable worlds,
everyday objects and utensils.
Apart from their paintings, the ceramics
of the Mochicas achieved a level not attain¬
ed by other cultures. They introduced, a
sculptural dimension into the modelling of
clay. Unlike the Nazcas, the Mochicas were
completely true to life. Both in painted
scenes and in the sculptured forms given to
clay the dominant theme is that of daily
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
life banquets, official ceremonies, dwell¬
ings and their surroundings, flute-players,
drummers, dancers, hunting, fishing,
warfare.
But it is in the huacos-retratos that this
lifelike quality is most apparent. This term
is applied to a certain kind of object in pot¬
tery which is an exact reproduction of the
human head, with the various expressions
that can appear on the human face. These
expressions are so true to life that some peo¬
ple believe them to be genuine portraits of
historical personalities. These huacos-
retratos provide us with a mass of informa¬
tion of the greatest value, unique in
American ceramics. They are veritable
historico-ethnographical documents, sup¬
plying information about systems of
decoration, face-painting, possible facial
deformation, varieties of human expres¬
sion, and so on.
This realistic art includes ceramics of
erotic inspiration. The many examples ex¬
tant include all the possible forms, variants
and expressions of sexual life. The Mochica
artist was capable of capturing and
reproducing them with all the unmistakable
veracity of his powers of observation.
The Chimú civilization (1000 AD to 1470
AD) is notable for the quality of its work in
feathers and gold. Like the Aztecs in Cen¬
tral America, the Chimús used feathers to
clothe and adorn themselves. The feathers
were placed overlapped on a textile base of
cotton or fibres, the end of each feather be¬
ing folded and fastened with knots of
various kinds. Cloaks made in this manner
became a part of the ceremonial wardrobe.
They were not only beautiful but
waterproof.
We are also indebted to the Chimús for
specimens of the goldsmith's art which are
amongst the finest and most perfect of the
pre-Hispanic world. They mastered the
techniques of smelting and welding, the lost
wax process, beating out leaf metal,
gilding, plating and the manufacture of
alloys. Tempering was achieved by cold
hammering, repoussé-work by hammering
the metal sheet on wooden moulds. With
moulds they made masks, ceremonial
vessels and knives, and all kinds of jewels.
There are many proofs of the artistic skill
of the Chimús. Here is what the Spanish
historian Juan de Torquemada wrote in
1613: "They were very skilful in the arts of
The Chimú were outstandingly accomplish¬
ed metallurgists, and the funerary masks,
sacrificial knives, ornaments, breastplates,
and decorative architectural elements
which they made In precious metals were
largely Instrumental In Inspiring the myth of
Peruvian gold, the Eldorado which bewitch¬
ed the Conquistadores. Above, ceremonial
knife in copper, gold and turquoise (length
40.5 cm) is from Mima in the valley of Lam-
bayeque and dates from 1100-1400.
Skilled metallurgists, the
Mochica worked in gold, silver
and copper. Above, gold
votive hands (300-600 AD).
From the year 1000 onwards,
the Chimú extended their In¬
fluence to the whole of nor¬
thern Peru, creating an empire
which was conquered by the
Incas around 1465. In the ruins
of their immense capital,
Chan-Chan, on a site
stretching over more than 28
square km at the mouth of the
Moche valley, Is a complex of
rectangular walled precincts
or "palaces" which measure
as much as 530 m by 265 m
and must have been used as
dwellings by the ruling class.
The brick walls are decorated
with relief designs (right).
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
The astonishing wealth of pre-
Columbian civilizations is il¬
lustrated by these objects from
three major cultural areas, Meso-
America, the Caribbean, and the
Andes.
Reclining figure carved in
lignite; length 15 cm
(Venezuela).
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
smelting and casting and made gold and
silver jewels of great beauty, greatly sur¬
passing our Spanish jewellers because they
could make birds whose heads, tongues and
wings could be made to move. They made
monkeys and other animals in whose hands
they placed trinkets which seemed to dance
with them... which caused Spanish jewellers
to marvel".
When the Incas burst upon the Andean
cultural scene, they brought about a pro¬
found change in the different pre-existing
creative currents. Ruling an empire implied
a strict, efficient organization of society.
This was made possible by concentrating
and centralizing power in the hands of the
Inca and his council. Since art formed an in¬
tegral part of social life, it was in turn con¬
centrated and became, as it were, a State
art. The Incas were efficient planners and
brought to their capital, Cuzco, all those
who in one way or another were
depositaries of knowledge and skills. In this
way artists were identified and brought
together.
The specific creative contribution of the
Incas was manifested principally in ar¬
chitecture. Inspired, perhaps, by their
ancestors from Tiahuanaco, the Inca ar¬
chitects seized space and filled it with
massive constructions on a gigantic scale.
Cyclopean blocks of stone were cut, ad¬
justed and arranged with the utmost preci¬
sion. At Sacsahuamán, for example, one of
the stone blocks forming the wall is seven
metres high. Solidity was ensured by
embedding and adjusting the blocks in such
a way that the projecting parts of some fit¬
ted into the depressions of others, and so
perfect were the joints that it was impossi¬
ble to insert even the blade of a knife.
Cuzco was the architectural centre par
excellence of the Incas. The temple of Cor-
icancha was the centre of the empire and its
most important building. The complex was
situated on a terrace surrounded by sanc¬
tuaries and dwellings. A stone aqueduct
brought water from the mountain. All the
façades of the palaces and temples were
painted and decorated with gold plate.
Standing on top of a hill a kilometre away
from Cuzco, the fortress of Sacsahuamán is
another amazing example of Inca architec¬
ture. The defensive walls are made of
megaliths, one of which weighs about two
hundred tons. These walls were constructed
in saw-tooth form by more than 30,000
workers shortly before the Spanish
conquest.
Machu Picchu is the best preserved of the
Inca cities. It was discovered in 191 1 by the
American archaeologist Hiram Bingham.
Built in the midst of a mountain range, on
top of a peak, its construction was very
carefully planned. Defended by inaccessible
slopes more than a thousand metres high,
and by two lines of fortifications, Machu
Picchu is at one and the same time a city, a
fortress and a sacred enclosure. It is an
overwhelming sight. Situated on high,
pointing skywards, built stone upon stone,
it exemplifies a fundamental aspect of the
Inca genius majesty of form and solidity
of construction, in the service of the cen¬
tralizing power of the State.
Jesús F. García Ruiz
Machu Picchu, the most fan¬
tastic fortress of the Incas,
stands on a rocky spur
overlooking the river Urubam-
ba in the heart of the Peruvian
Andes. Inhabited by the Incas
between the 15th and 16th
centuries, it was abandoned
for reasons that have not been
explained, and only redis¬
covered, by the American ar¬
chaeologist Hiram Bingham,
in 1911. At the topmost level
of this impregnable
stronghold is a city with a
multitude of dwellings and a
ceremonial centre dedicated
to the sun. Right, terraces and
staircases of Machu Picchu.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
The legacy of colonial art
by Damián Bayón
UNTIL the last third of the eighteenth
century, Spanish and Portuguese
colonial art in the New World was
dominated exclusively by religious themes. It
was also influenced to a large extent by art
trends in Europe.
Although forms of artistic expression p'ractis-
ed in some of the great pre-Columbian cultures
at the time of the Conquest were of real worth,
their techniques and range differed so widely
from the needs of the missionaries that any
degree of syncretism was scarcely possible.
Some collaboration did, however, begin to
take shape in Mexico, in painting far more than
in sculpture. Those among the indigenous
population who had a gift for drawing and the
use of colour were trained by friars who were
proficient in these subjects. As a result, a large
number of murals were executed in the early
monasteries, inspired by engravings and in
some cases by the illuminations of printed
books in the early Renaissance style.
European artists initially had to be "im¬
ported" for easel painting, and in turn they
trained local artists. The first European
painters to arrive in the Spanish colonies
naturally included Spaniards, but there were
also many Italians, Flemings and Germans,
some of whom were subjects of the Spanish
crown. Their work was marked by the prevail¬
ing styles of the period. At first it displayed a
certain archaic quality, a hint of Italian Man¬
nerism and its Spanish and Flemish
derivatives. By the late seventeenth century
the European schools of painting were taking
fifty to a hundred years to reach America. This
delay was gradually reduced and towards the
end of the eighteenth century and the begin¬
ning of the nineteenth, the rococo and
neo-classical styles appeared almost
simultaneously in the mother countries and in
the colonies.
In the sixteenth century three Italian painters
of a certain stature appeared in South America:
the Jesuit Bernardo Bitti (1548-1610) and the
laymen Matías Pérez de Alesio (1547-1628)
and Angelino Medoro (1565-1632). They were
important not only because of their own works,
which were influenced by the international
Mannerism of the day, but also because they
trained local-born artists such as the
Ecuadorian Fray Pedro Bedón and the
Panamanian Brother Hernando de la Cruz,
both of whom worked in Quito.
About the same time a Fleming named
Simón Pereyns (1558-1589) appeared in Mex¬
ico and soon became famous. He was followed
by a number of Spaniards including Baltasar
de Echave Orio (1548-1619) who was to create
a dynasty with his descendants Echave Ibia
(1583-1660) and Echave Rioja (1632-1682).
On the ceilings of two manor-houses at Tunja
in New Granada (now Colombia) are a number
of curious paintings which, although of no great
This statue of Hercules sup¬
porting a pillar in the church of
Our Lady of Mount Carmel, at
Sabara, Brazil, is the work of
Antonio Francisco Lisboa, O
Aleijadinho (the little cripple),
1730-1814, the most important
Ibero-American sculptorof the
colonial era.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Holy Family, by Diego
Ouispe Tito (1611-1681), a
Peruvian artist of Indian
extraction, who was the
leader of the so-called
"Cuzco school". This
painting is now in the
church of La Merced, Cuz¬
co, Peru.
importance from a strictly artistic point of view,
suggest through their combination of
mythological and Christian themes an unusual
humanistic culture. Also based in Colombia
was the founder of another dynasty, Baltasar
de Figueroa. Born in Seville around 1600, he
was the father of Gaspar and the grandfather of
Baltasar de Vargas Figueroa, who is mainly
remembered through his pupil Gregorio Vás-
quez de Arce y Ceballos (1638-171 1), a highly
accomplished painter and undoubtedly the
most accomplished artist in New Granada dur¬
ing the colonial period.
In Ecuador, Father Bedón and Brother Her¬
nando de la Cruz were succeeded by at least
two other Important artists, Miguel de Santiago
(1626-1706) and Nicolás Javier de Goríbar
(1 665-1 740). The only outstanding figure of the
eighteenth century seems to have been
Manuel de Samaniego (1767-1824).
Seventeenth-century Peruvian art was mark¬
ed by the rivalry between Basilio de Santa Cruz
(died 1699), an academic painter and protégé
of Bishop Mollinado, and the far more original
Diego Quispe Tito (1611-1681). The latter, of
Indian stock, was the pioneer and chief
representative of the so-called "Cuzco
School", a seventeenth- and - eighteenth-
century movement whose anti-realism was
reflected in the free adaptation of the Flemish
engravings then, widely circulating in America.
Other characteristic features of the School
were a rejection of perspective, an insistence
on the frontal presentation of sacred figures,
and the use of arabesques applied to the can¬
vas in gold leaf, what is known professionally
as brocateado.
DAMIÁN BAYON, Argentine historian and art
critic, has worked with Unesco on a number of
occasions and has taught at several univer¬
sities. Among his published works are Artistas
Contemporáneos de América Latina (Unesco,
1981), The Changing Shape of Latin
American Architecture (co-author), and Latin
America in its Art, of which he was editor (see
inside back cover).
In Bolivia, the remarkable figure of Melchor
Pérez de Holguín (1665-1724) bestrides the
seventeenth and eighteenth centuries.
Although he had tried to imitate Zurbarán, he
became one of the most original of the colonial
painters.
Meanwhile, in Mexico, painting continued to
follow European trends. The country's most
notable painters between the seventeenth and
eighteenth centuries were Sebastián de
Arteaga (1610-1 656), a Spanish disciple of Zur¬
barán who emigrated to Mexico, where he had
a powerful influence; José Juárez (161 5-1 660),
who may have studied with Arteaga but seems
more archaic than his master; and above all
Cristóbal de Villalpando (1645-1714), a painter
who recalls the Spanish painter Juan de
Valdés Leal. With another great master of
decoration, Juan Correa (died 1739) he
decorated the sacristy of the cathedral in Mex¬
ico City.
But the most important of all seems to have
been Miguel Cabrera (1 695-1 768), born in Oax¬
aca and therefore a Creole, who painted for the
famous church of Santa Prisca in Taxco and
produced, among other works, a well-known
portrait of the great Mexican poetess Sor
Juana Inés de la Cruz.
Portuguese-Brazilian colonial painting took a
completely different direction, eschewing the
easel in favour of the large-scale decoration of
wooden ceilings. This art form was deliberately
"perspectivist" and followed the example of
the great painter of "glorias", Father Pozzo,
who worked during the brilliant period of the
Italian seventeenth century. ^
Pulpit of the church of San Francisco, at
Quito, a city which is included in the World
Heritage List of Cultural and Natural Proper¬
ties. The façade of the church is considered
to be one of the finest in South America and
its interior decoration is among the best ex¬
amples of colonial religious art. The pulpit
dates from the mid-16th century. The
statues are polychrome and the niches and
columns, like the various altars of the
church, are covered in gold leaf.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
^. Brazilian historians identify two periods in
this type of paintingthe Baroque and the
Rococo. The most outstanding exponent of the
former was José J. da Rocha (1 737-1 807), who
executed the paintings in the church of La Con¬
cepción de la Playa in the lower city of
Salvador, in the State of Bahia. His style is ar¬
chitectonic, favouring sombre colours which
heighten the dramatic character of his
subjects.
The Rococo is represented by a number of
artists of merit, outstanding amongst whom
was Manuel de Costa Athaide (1762-1837),
who was born in Mariana in Minas Gerais
State. He painted the admirable ceiling in the
exquisite little church of St. Francis of Assisi at
Ouro Preto. In this instance the painter's inten¬
tion is in perfect harmony with the dictates of
the Rococo style: the painting is less realistic,
more ethereal and undefined, and the colour
range is deliberately limited to pastel shades.
Ibero-American colonial sculpture obeys dif¬
ferent criteria. In both the Spanish and Por¬
tuguese territories, statuary, altar-pieces, choir
stalls and pulpits reveal unmistakably Penin¬
sular origins. Among those who travelled to
America in search of fortune in the new lands
were better sculptors than painters, and almost
from the outset they trained locally-born pupils.
At the beginning of the colonial period in
Mexico a somewhat crude form of sculpture
known as tequitoui ("tributary" in Náhuatl) was
produced by Indians who worked under the
supervision of Spanish monks and made carv¬
ings, predominantly of- atrial crosses, into
which they introduced materials or elements
characteristic of their ancestral culture. In cen¬
tral America as a whole and in the Caribbean,
the European impact was so complete and final
that it is impossible to distinguish between the
work of Spanish and indigenous sculptors.
The remarkable expressiveness of South
American statuary originated in Quito, where a
sculptural tradition was established which was
undoubtedly due to the creation by the first
Flemish Franciscans of the San Andrés School
of Arts and Crafts. The Quito image-carvers
This picture of Saint Luke and
the Virgin Mary is a Mexican
work dating from about 1850.
In style it is typical of Spanish-
American painting of the col¬
onial period, but the artist has
used fragments of feathers in¬
stead of pigments in the man¬
ner of the Aztecs and other
pre-Columbian peoples.
adopted types and poses derived from the An-
dalusian schools, but their use of colours was
influenced by the Castilian School, in the sense
that they produced a brilliant finish that con¬
trasted with the sombre finish practised in the
south of Spain.
The Quito sculptors form a coherent group.
All, or nearly all, of them were American born.
They included at least one mestizo and one
pure Indian. First of all there was Father Carlos
(approx. 1620-1680), who carved life-size
figures with a certain degree of realism and
was the teacher of José Olmos, known as
"Pampite" (active between 1650 and 1690),
who was also influenced by Martinez Montanes
and specialized in figures of Christ and
Calvaries. The brilliant mestizo Bernardo de
Legarda (died 1773) emerged somewhat later.
He was a highly accomplished artist, a sculptor
of altar-pieces, a gilder and image-maker who
invented an elegant type of figure called the
"Virgen Danzante" (Dancing Virgin),
sometimes carved on a reduced scale. Finally,
the work of the late eighteenth-century Indian
sculptor Manuel Chili, known as "Caspicara",
marks a contrast with the smiling gracefulness
of Legarda and includes the Descent from the
Cross, a sculpture of great pathos, in the
cathedral of Quito.
It is curious that central America, the Carib¬
bean, New Granada and Peru did not produce
the equals of the great Quito sculptors or their
Brazilian contemporaries. In those parts
sculpture was at its best in choir stalls and
altar-pieces rather than in statues. Two notable
examples in Mexico are the Spaniard Lorenzo
Rodriguez (1704-1774), creator of the
Metropolitan Sanctuary with its two exuberant
Baroque facades, and Jerónimo Balbas (who
worked between 1709 and 1761) and executed
the famous Altar-piece of the Kings in the
cathedral of Mexico City.
During the sixteenth and seventeenth cen¬
turies, examples of Portuguese art had a
strong influence in northeastern and central
Brazil. A notable feature of this early period in
Brazilian sculpture was that nearly all the
sculptors were lay brothers who worked for
their respective Orders. The Jesuits tended to
carve in wood whereas the Benedictines
modelled in clay, producing objects which they
painted in various colours and then baked in
ovens at a high temperature. There was one
notable exception, the Benedictine Father
Domingo de la Concepción (died 1717), who
carved directly in wood.
A number of interesting artists emerged in
the eighteenth .century. One of them was
Manuel Brito (active between 1726 and 1739),
who collaborated with his kinsman Francisco
Javier de Brito (died 1751) on the altar-pieces
of the splendid church of San Francisco de la
Penitencia in Rio de Janeiro.
Both of these artists influenced, from a
distance, the most important figure in colonial
sculpture in the whole of the Americas-
Antonio Francisco Lisboa (1730-1814), a
mulatto better known by his nickname O Alei-
jadinho (the cripple) because of a terrible infir¬
mity which deformed his hands. An ac¬
complished artist, O Aleijadhino was an ar¬
chitect, like his Portuguese father, and above
all a great sculptor capable of carving directly
in stone or wood.
Damián Bayón
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Baroque splendours
of Latin America
Immediately after the Conquest, Spanish
missionaries began building churches
and convents In the architectural style of
their homeland, adapted to meet the ex¬
igencies of these new latitudes. Gradual¬
ly a new style evolved which, from the
17th century, was to culminate in the rich
ornamental profusion of Ibero-American
Baroque, In which the originality ofnative
artists found full and free expression. On
this page we present four examples of
this "Colonial" style. Top right, façade of
the church of La Merced, Antigua,
Guatemala. The outside of the church,
which dates from the 17th century, is
completely covered with decorative
relief-work, including garlands, twisted
fluting and geometric and figurative
designs. Right, the cathedral of Potosí,
Bolivia, built at the beginning of the 19th
century following the layout of the
cathedral of Havana. Bottom right, altar-
piece of the high altar of the mid-18th
century church of Santa Prisca, Taxco,
Mexico. Santa Prisca is a masterpiece of
' 'Churrigueresque "baroque art (inspired
by the art of the Spanish architect Chur-
riguera). Below, the Interior of the 18th
century church of Our Lady of Mount
Carmel, an excellent example of the
Brazilian baroque style sometimes also
termed "Rococo".
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
ENCHANTED SEASHELL'
SOMETIMEaroundl515,ahandfulof
Spaniards led by Captain Panfilo de
Nárvaez and Fray Bartolomé de las
Casas established a settlement in Cuba on
the southern coast of what is now the pro¬
vince of Havana. However, this settlement
did not last long and its founders moved to
the northern coast near the Straits of
Florida, whose swift currents were an aid to
navigation. They came to a harbour con¬
sisting of a narrow inlet opening into a large
bay, well protected by hills against hur¬
ricanes. The town of San Cristóbal de la
Habana was finally established on the
western shores of this bay in November
1519. The exact date is no longer known
since the records of the municipal council
covering the period from that year to 1550
were burned by the French pirate Jacques
de Sores.
Oral tradition has it that, in accordance
with the custom of that time, the weary
founders celebrated their first mass and
held their first meeting beneath a ceiba tree,
in the shade of which a settlement of bohíos
(huts) began to grow, for initially the Euro-
MANUEL PEREIRA is a Cuban novelist and
journalist whose novels El Comandante
Veneno and El Ruso have been translated into
several languages. His reports on Nicaragua
have been published under the title Cro-Nica.
He is currently a member of Cuba's Permanent
Delegation to Unesco, and is working on a
novel set in Old Havana.
peans adopted the indigenous style of
dwelling houses made of palm-leaves with
a roof of two sloping sides and a beaten
earth floor.
Gold fever and Faustian restlessness so
captivated the minds of these con¬
quistadores that their only thought was to
set forth in search of riches on the mainland
(Mexico, El Dorado, El Darien) and of the
Spring of Eternal Youth in Florida. The
embryonic town lapsed into oblivion and
only acquired the title of city when the
Spanish crown realized that, thanks to its
geographical situation, it was the principal
port of call on the route to the Indies. It
became the gateway to the New World,
through which all the gold and silver from
America had to pass on its way to
metropolitan Spain.
Pirates and privateers soon became
aware of this traffie and were not slow to at¬
tack it. Havana was fortified and surround¬
ed with a girdle of stone ramparts which
made it impregnable. Remains of this ar¬
chitectural frenzy can still be seen: Morro-
Castle, La Punta, and the Castilla de la Real
Fuerza.
Set on a rock at the mouth
(like the lighthouses of San
Rico and of Arico in Chile),
of El Morro has been aid
since 1630. The Castillo de
was built between 1555 and
oldest castle in America,
of the harbour
Juan de Porto
the lighthouse
ing navigation
la Real Fuerza
1577. It is the
and the first
building of its kind on the continent in
which the Renaissance design which revolu¬
tionized military architecture was used. On
one of its bastions stands the Torre del
Homenaje (Tower of Homage) the cupola
of which is topped by a weathervane known
as the Giraldilla, an obvious allusion to the
Giralda in Seville.
The famous nine o'clock cannon fire,
which alarms foreigners and enables the
locals to check their watches, is another
reminder of those nights of torches and
General view of Havana and its bay, in a
lithograph by Eduardo Laplante (1818-7).
Old Havana, one of the oldest and most
beautiful cities of the New World, was
founded by the Spanish in 1519. Since 1982
it has been included in Unesco's World
Heritage List. However, its restoration and
preservation today pose a serious problem
for the Cuban authorities who addressed an
appeal for help to Unesco. In July 1983, the
Director-General of Unesco, Mr. Amadou-
Mahtar M'Bow, launchedan appeal to the in¬
ternational community in favour of a cam¬
paign to safeguard the Plaza Vieja, the city's
historic centre, and Old Havana in general.
In making his appeal Mr. M'Bow described
Old Havana as "the epitome of all the new
cities that have landmarked the epic of the
Americas and as an example par excellence
of the flamboyant intellectual, artistic and
architectural syntheses that sprang from the
intermingling of so many destinies all over
the continent".
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
A portrait of Old Havana by Manuel Pereira
daggers. It announced the closing of the
gates in the ramparts (built in the seven¬
teenth century and demolished around
1865), for after this hour Havana was in
danger of attack by pirates.
It was thanks to the growing importance
of the port that Havana became a maritime
city. Carpenters, cabinet-makers, caulkers,
mast- and spar-makers and labourers
thronged its streets lined with stores,
workshops and merchants' premises. The
most important ships in the Spanish fleet
were built in Havana's shipyards.
The city was also evangelized. The sword
was an earthly cross, the cross was a
heavenly sword. The green cross embedded
in a corner of the Calle Amargura (the street
of bitterness) still marks a halting-place for
the procession of the Via Crucis to the
church of Cristo del Buen Viaje. But
Havana's oldest surviving church is that of
The Holy Spirit, built between 1638 and
1661. It is the only one whose catacombs
have been preserved intact.
At the same time Havana acquired its
squares: the Plaza de Armas; the so-called
Old (formerly New) Plaza; the Plaza de San
Francisco; the Plaza del Cristo del Buen
Viaje; and most famous of all the Plaza
de la Catedral. Construction of the
cathedral was started by the Jesuits in 1748;
it marks an explosion of Baroque, a splen¬
did unfurling of forms, a book of rock,
music turned to stone. Its highly wrought
volutes in coral-veined rock recall the
spiralling smoke of a Havana cigar.
The cathedral façade is the finest surviv¬
ing expression of Cuban Baroque, unique
for the simplicity of its lines and its sensual
movement.
Inside the cathedral there is a niche
dedicated to Christopher Columbus,
although his sarcophagus, borne by the col¬
ossal statues of four sailors, is in Seville,
and his body is said to be in Santo
Domingo.
The noblemen's palaces lining the
cathedral square form the best-preserved
and most harmonious architectural group
in Old Havana. "This is the finest colonial
square in America," said Walter Gropius,
founder of the Bauhaus.
An endless dialogue between architecture
and nature was the distinctive feature of
these buildings, which were adapted to local
conditions and represent a distinctive
Havana cathedral is a
noteworthy example of the
adaptation of Spanish
religious architecture to the
needs of the West Indies. The
great Cuban poet and writer
José Lezama Lima observed
that one must see the
cathedral in profile "in order
to capture its undulating
rhythms".
Cuban style. Venetian blinds to let in the
land breeze, multi-coloured window-panes
to attenuate the glare of the Cuban light,
narrow streets shaded by awnings these
are the constant features of an urban ar¬
chitecture that is integrated into the land¬
scape and in which stone, sea and vegeta¬
tion form a harmonious whole. Ayagruma
flowers on a balcony; the walls are veined
with white fossils; no house turns its back
on the sea; all seek its breeze.
Havana also has its little mysteries. The
stones in the walls still bear the personal
marks of the masons, cut with their chisels,
sometimes initials, sometimes in¬
decipherable signs. Many of the tiles bear
the thumbprints of the tilers who moulded
them into shape on their thighs, and there is
even one which has a proverb inscribed on
it in Chinese ideograms "What the heart
commands, the hand performs".
In the patios palm trees conduct a
dialogue with pillars, as though trunks and
columns had mingled and the colonnades
been transmuted into petrified palms. Such
correspondences and syntheses are a cons¬
tant feature of this labyrinthine city, which
grew in harmony with its surroundings,
profiting from the changing light, assuming
the varying rhythms of the waves, imposing
itself as a living, dynamic organism. Old
Havana is a habitable animal, an en¬
chanted, convoluted seashell.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Courtyard of the Palace of the
Captains General of Havana,
now the City Museum.
^ Arab influence is evident in the
geometrical ornamentation of the carved
ceilings, the ironwork arabesques, the
foliate motifs on the arches, the stars etched
by fire on the ceilings, the proliferation of
patio fountains, reflecting nostalgia for the
starry skies of the desert and the unquench-
ed thirst of the mudejar. If Havana
resembles any other city, it is Seville, except
that its walls are not whitewashed; its col¬
ours have always been green and blue,
vegetation and the seathe city's secret
passions.
In 1762 the British made a breach in El
Morro and occupied Havana for eleven
months. The fortifications which had so
stubbornly resisted pirates and filibusters
succumbed to British dynamite. This period
became known in folk humour as "the time
of the mammees", from the name of the
Antillean apricot-tree, because of the red
coats of the British soldiers.
Spain recovered Havana, and Charles
III, having learned a lesson, ordered a huge
fortress, La Cabana, to be built on the hill
dominating the western shores of the har¬
bour. Havana thus became the first for¬
tified stronghold in the Americas, but it
cost such a colossal sum that Charles III,
appalled by the cost, went out onto the
balcony of his palace and asked for a
telescope to look at the lofty walls of La
Cabana. "It has cost me so much", he said,
"that it should be visible from here".
At this period Havana, with its 30,000 in¬
habitants, was already one of the major
cities of the New World, more populous
than Boston, New York, or Philadelphia.
The snuffboxes of Louis XVI's courtiers
20
were filled with Havana snuff, and our
sugar was beginning to sweeten Europe.
The sugar boom transformed Havana
from a place of transit into a terminal.
Towards the end of the eighteenth century
about a thousand ships a year entered the
bay to load sugar and deliver goods from
overseas. The independence of the United
States brought an influx of traders eager to
make fortunes. The revolution in Haiti led
to the arrival of large numbers of French.
Cosmopolitan elegance prevailed, but
slavery was a powder keg ready to explode.
Thus appeared the Cuban capital at the
beginning of the nineteenth century. It was
at this time that neo-classical architecture
appeared in Havana. A small-scale imita¬
tion of the Parthenon, El Templete, stands
a stone's throw from the mole, on the spot
where the city is supposed to have been
founded more than four and a half cen¬
turies ago. It was erected, not only to com¬
memorate the foundation, but as an act of
fealty to Spain by the Captaincy General in
the name of "faithful Havana", at a mo¬
ment when America was swept by rebellion.
The entrance pillars are surmounted by
bronze pineapples, an emblem of Havana.
Behind the gates stands the founding ceiba
treeor rather its descendant, since the
original died in the middle of the eighteenth
century from the effects of the salt air from
the sea nearby.
The inventions of the nineteenth century
soon reached Havana. Watt's steam engine
was operating in the city within four years
of its invention. Havana was the fourth
capital in the world to establish a railway
and the third to be lit by gas. Morse had
scarcely launched his campaign to promote
his telegraph system before Havana had its
telegraph lines. The telephone arrived with
its inventor. Moreover, Havana was the
first city in the world to have an automatic
telephone system, because it was chosen as
a showplace for the experiment. The first
radio station was opened by Marconi
himself in Havana. Six months after their
introduction in Paris, the first
cinematographs to appear in America were
set up in Havana.
It was a century of prosperity, or rather
of apparent prosperity, for after 1868 the
flame of the fight for independence from
Spanish colonial rule was alight in the
eastern part of the country.
Meanwhile, splendour took over in
Havana. In the mansions of the nobility,
luxurious but on a human scale, iron
gradually replaced wood: doors patterned
with nails, grilles, door-knockers, locks and
handrails... roofs with terracotta denticula-
tions. What we now call Old Havana and
what was then simply the city within the
walls, is thronged with images. This is the
Havana of Marti and Carpentier, of Hum¬
boldt, Einstein, Sarah Bernhardt,
Garibaldi, Juan Ramón Jiménez, Lorca,
Antonin Artaud, Mayakowski, Isadora
Duncan, André Breton, Caruso, Simón
Bolívar, Benito Juarez, Francisco de
Miranda, Valle-Inclán, Igor Stravinsky...
They all came here and were dazzled.
When the twentieth century began, the
star-spangled banner was flying over El
Morro. After thirty years of war against
Spain, Cubans had failed to achieve full in¬
dependence because of armed intervention
by the United States. A make-believe,
frustrating republic was subsequently pro¬
claimed. The last gas lamps gave way to
electricity, trams replaced the two-wheeled
carriages called voluntas, and asphalt took
the place of cobblestones. Art Nouveau and
Art Déco made a fleeting appearance on
some buildings, but the dominant style was
that of the foreign banks: grandiloquent,
eclectic, theatrical. Meanwhile, first the
aristocracy then the bourgeoisie moved out
to the new suburbs El Cerro, El Vedado,
Miramar that were growing outside the
city walls, and their city mansions were con¬
verted into phalansteries, the community
dwellings known in Havana as solares.
Overcrowding and promiscuity were the
hallmarks of intra-mural Havana during
the first half of the present century. The
port area was full of "joints" with il¬
luminated signs in English in a country
where more than a million people could not
even read Spanish. Many historic buildings .
were demolished to make way for absur¬
dities in imported glass.
The Cuban historian Emilio Roig de
Leuchsenring (1889-1964) protested, but
the demolitions continued, and it was only
the triumph of the revolution.in 1959 that
halted the destructive advance in the name
of "modernity" and "civilization" which
threatened to fill the oldest part of the
capital with skyscrapers. After half a cen¬
tury of officiai indolence, the Revolution
inherited a sad, badly scarred Old Havana.
A land of passage for so many years, peo¬
ple of the most diverse origins from
Africa, Europe, China, Yucutàn have
met here in a kaleidoscopic amalgam that
has produced our unique but varied ethnic,
ethical and aesthetic identity. A crucible of
cultures, styles, iconographies and
mythologies. Is it because our streets are so
narrow and the balconies so close to each
other that the inhabitant of Old Havana is
such an expansive, loquacious, cordial
being? The humble folk who people this
city, living in former palaces, are like new
princes who need no coats of arms because
their nobility is of the heart.
It is impossible to rescue 465 years of
stone overnight, but Old Havana will be
saved. Its splendid face will be restored and
be converted, not into a lifeless museum but
into a museum that is living and can be lived
in. It will be saved, with its gas lamps and
distant ships, its harbour wall for lovers,
and its shadow pantomime, its nine o'clock
cannon and whispering fountains, its damp
pavements and the winking eye of the
cyclops on El Morro.
Manuel Pereira
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Brasilia: 'the capita
of hope'
by Briane Elisabeth Panitz Bica
NEXT year will mark the twenty-fifth
anniversary of the inauguration of
Brasilia and the twenty-eighth of
the beginning of its construction. This is not
a long time in the life of a city, but Brasilia's
presence in the history of Brazil goes back
more than a century. The idea of transfer¬
ring the capital to the central plateau was
first suggested in 1817, when José
Bonifacio de Andrade e Silva, known as the
"father of Brazilian independence", pro¬
posed what are now its permanent site and
name. From then on, the proposal was
periodically repeated, until it was finally
adopted by Juscelino Kubitschek during the
1956 Presidential election campaign.
As the most extensive and complete ap¬
plication of the principles of modern city
planning, Brasilia has made its own con¬
tribution to the history of urban develop¬
ment. It had its origins in an act of reason,
without any roots in Brazil's urban past,
without any link with the land on which it
was created. Each line traced on paper by
Lucio Costa, the pupil of Le Corbusier who
conceived Brasilia, was transformed into an
avenue traced by a tractor across the coun¬
tryside. The meeting of the two axes, "The
first act of someone who takes possession
of a site by tracing a cross on it", gave form
to the city "the capital of hope" towards
which flocked, from every corner of the
country, all those who, by participating in
the epic of its construction, were embarking
on the creation of a "new Brazil" which
would make their dreams of a better life
come true.
BRIANE ELISABETH PANITZ BICA is a
Brazilian architect who is actively involved in
the restoration and conservation of her coun¬
try's urban environment. She is currently co¬
ordinator of a working group for the preserva¬
tion of the Environmental and Cultural
Heritage of Brazil.
Through a dynamic of its own, the con¬
struction process of Brasilia adapted itself
to the future site. On the one hand there is
official Brasilia, seat of the central Govern¬
ment, and on the other its satellite towns
designed to house the mass of the less
privileged citizens. The former now has
300,000 inhabitants, and the seven satellite
towns have a total population of one
million, forming an aggregate which, by
reason of its size and urbanizing influence,
has overflowed towards the municipal cen¬
tres of the neighbouring States and has led
to the complex officially known as the Geo-
economic Region of Brasilia. The principles
of city planning applied in Brasilia have
also influenced the configuration of new
towns in other parts of Brazil and in other
countries.
While the city has been experiencing a
process of consolidation a sharp debate has
been going on between Brasilia's defenders
and its critics. Some point to its advantages
compared with other great cities the com¬
fort of living in its supermanzanas (com¬
plexes consisting of six-storey buildings,
shops, schools, a patio, church and a
spacious green area, situated along the ma¬
jor highway axis), the vast panoramic view
with a diaphanous sky and clouds forming
a backdrop to the plateau, the absence of
atmospheric, sonic and visual pollution, the
spacious green areas, the free flow of traffic
and ease of parking. Others criticize the
logic whiclj the city imposes on its in¬
habitants and point out its defects: an ex¬
cessive division of the city's activities into
different topographical sectors; the gigan¬
tism which predominates even in residential
districts; the long distances between
buildings which make it difficult for
pedestrians to get about the city, lead to an
excessive use of cars, and bring an element
of remoteness to personal relations; the
divisions of the city caused by high-speed
Memorial monument to
Juscelino Kubitschek, the
President of Brazil who took
the decision to build Brasilia
on the central Brazilian
plateau and designated it as
the nation's capital In 1960.
One of the reasons for the
creation of Brasilia may be
found in these words of
Juscelino Kubitschek: "Our
country, the fifth largest in the
world, has immense fertile
lands as empty as the Sahara,
while millions of Brazilians
cling to the crowded
shoreline."
motorways; the famous "lack of corners"
due to the fact that buildings are scattered
in such a way that there are no angles form¬
ed by street intersections; and the excessive
social stratification caused by the high cost
of living in Brasilia.
Apart from the pros and cons there can
be no doubt about the exceptional character
and quality of Brasilia as an achievement of
urban planning and architecture involving a
synthesis between the rationalistic ap¬
proach adopted by Lucio Costa and the ex¬
uberant architecture of Oscar Niemeyer,
who designed the most important buildings.
Brasilia is also notable for the fact that so
far it has succeeded in preserving its integ¬
rity almost completely in spite of dif¬
ficulties and the not always peaceful coex¬
istence between the interests of the federal
administration, for which the city was
created, and those of the local authorities
responsible for its functioning.
Brasilia's size and dynamism, together
with its- unity and physical homogeneity,
are a matter of surprise for visitors,
especially students of the urban process,
who find themselves in a laboratory where
theories which have been discussed all over
CONTINUED PAGE 28
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
22
Four artists
in chiaroscuro
by Edouard Glissant
MATTA
MATTA is an artist who escapes the controversy between
abstract and figurative art, slipping out of the debating
chamber and dissolving like a wraith in the bluish haze
with which so many of his greatest works are suffused. And if what
he paints has not the immediacy of the real, neither is it a sketch-
plan or a diagram of something that exists. I would go so far as to
say that Matta is forever painting the pulsation of life.
Depth in Matta's painting is achieved by a projection forward in
front of the canvas of pictural space, a proscenium which saw his
first attempts to render visible the convulsion of modern thought:
the disintegration of old systems of logic, the vertiginous flights of
Eros, resistance against tyrannies, the unshackling of the "Savage
Mind".
Is it possible to "paint", not states of mind, but the very func¬
tioning of the mind or, going still further, that fabulous gamble the
"complete man" , reconciled with all forms of humanity, finding in
them his own being and fulfilment?
Matta's painting shows us that it can be done. What we find in
them is the movement that fuels our most personal upsoarings and
consolidates the roots we share most widely with others. Planes that
combine or resist each other on the canvas, spirals of discovery, ex¬
plosions of revealed incompatibilities, condensation into new stars
of our most intense convictions here matter joins company with
and follows the dynamism of the spirit. Matta does not paint
"things", he illuminates trajectories.
This is an artist who forever seeks to find out and demonstrate
"how things work". Not merely, like an architect reflecting on his
work, how it is constructed, but how it really functions. Can we,
for example, gauge or even begin to comprehend the vast ferment
of cultures reacting and interacting with each other today? We have
no guide or blueprint to judge by; but does this mean that we should
renounce all attempts to read the Book of Destiny? Matta's paint¬
ings raise questions such as these and show us that there is no
halting the spectacle of life.
This is thoroughly modern painting, aloof from conventional
quarrels, investigative, always in movement; we know that it has its
origins in the ancient wisdom of the Andes, but already it is explor¬
ing unknown regions that humanity is projecting on the forefront
of the proscenium stage of history.
SEGUI
THE art of Antonio Seguí has affinities with the art of prose,
the obstinacy and ruggedness of which Seguí adopts to
probe reality and bring out its raw qualities.
It has often been said that colonial Baroque resulted from a
superabundance of being. The artist took pleasure, a mischievous
pleasure perhaps, in showing that he was capable of rendering to
excess what he was expected to express: catholicity, civilization,
flamboyant rhetoric.
In the case of Seguí, we are without any doubt in the presence of
another kind of Baroque, which does not strive towards the
overelaboration of being but tracks it down behind its masquerades
and gesticulations. The aim is to discover our true nature, or what
is left of it, perhaps, when it is divested of the shabby finery impos¬
ed upon it. Paradoxically, it is the shabby finery that Seguí shows
us, so that we can guess at what is hidden beneath.
In all the different stages of Segui's painting, stages which follow
each other with mounting speed, we find the forms of this Baroque,
constantly renewed. Rickety towns, overrun towns, prostrate
passers-by, leering catastrophes, smashed dolls, clothes for
scarecrows, but also the emotion diffused by the light of a street-
lamp, the warm colour of a single tree, the word of a rainbow, the
sun of a man's step. In other words, the everyday, which pares
away our pretensions or alienations and reassures or consoles us at
the same time.
CONTINUED PAGE 27
Colour pages
Page 23
Above: polychrome terra-cotta mask (1 7 cm
wide) from the Classic Period (Teotihuacán
III) of Meso-American civilization between
100 and 200 AD (see article page 4). The
mask, which incorporates a stylized butter¬
fly in its lower part, is a representation of
Xochipilli, god of spring and flowers. It is
preserved in Mexico 's National Museum of
Anthropology and History.
Photo © Henri Stierlin. Geneva
Below: a head, half man, half jaguar, of the
kind known in Peru as a cabeza-clava, or
"nail-head", is embedded in a wall of the
pyramid of Chavin, the oldest stone sanc¬
tuary ofpre-Columbian Peru. The Chavin de
Huantar culture (1500 BC-400 AD) blossom¬
ed suddenly in a high valley near the
sources of the river Marañón. (See article
page 9).
Photo © Henri Stierlin, Geneva
Page 24
Above: Mount Champaqui in January, oil on
canvas (?) (1984), by Antonio Segui (born
1934). See text this page.
Photo © Fernando Chavez, Paris
Below: Detail of the Virgin of Mount Carmel,
now in the museum of the Convent of San
Francisco, Quito. The Virgin Is one of the
most celebrated sculptures by the 18th-
century Ecuadorian artist Caspicara, of
whose works it has been said that they have
the lustre of porcelain. Caspicara 's real
name, Manuel Chili, was found carved at the
back of a wooden plaque depicting the
sleeping baby Jesus.
Photo © Salvat Editores S.A., Barcelona-Quito
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
^
V
y
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
g *"'
tip
'.,.
^Ä
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Colour pages
Page 25
Above: Seated Woman (1949), oil on canvas
by Wifredo Lam (1902-1982). See text this
page.
Photo Almasy © SPADEM, Paris
Below: Coloured wool tapestry depicting a
Colombian landscape was made and sold in
a Bogotá market.
Photo © LEDA, Paris
Page 26
Above: The Ambush (1980), oil on canvasby
José Gamarra (born 1934). See text this
page.
Photo © All rights reserved
Below: Clay pitcher dating from the period
when the Paracas Cavernas culture, in what
is now Peru, was influenced by the Chavin
culture. It is 18.5 cm high and represents a
feline divinity. The incised decoration was
painted after firing. (See article page 9).
Photo Werner Lang, Lima © Banco de Crédito del Perú.
Taken from Arte y Tesoros del Perú.
Four artists in chiaroscuro (continued)
The unexpected thing is thus that in Segui's work the obstinacy,
and ruggedness are full of an unfailing charm. This prose is also
poetry which navigates in the depths. Seguí paints that which
perverts our nature and makes us strangers to our truth, but also
everything that carries us away, secretly nourished by an inner sun,
in the tango of tenderness.
LAM
THE art of Wifredo Lam involves a double objective: to seek
out and bring into relief the forms secreted by a very
concrete reality, that of his native island, and at the same
time to draw attention to the cultural predicament in which we find
ourselves today and which demands a contribution from each one
of us.
Lam's first concern was to fill the canvas; its poetry lies not in
the tree but in the profusion of vegetation, verticals surging from
the memory, exploding into an island-space-filling jungle. African
forms are revived, not through cliché-clouded eyes, but in all their
vital inner mobility triangles wide-eyed with astonishment form¬
ing lozenge-shaped bucklers, burgeoning ears of moon-horned
grain; and those anatomical anthologies obduracy of feet round
which the soil seems to lap like water, the Sumerian slant of the
torso inclined towards a divinity to impart a secret.
The mocking reply of the oppressed. How heartening it was, at
the turn of the 1940s, on the fringe of the drama of the Second
World War, to discover thus that nothing had been lost of the an¬
cient splendour. Delicate breadth of this assembly, within the same
space-time as Aimé Césaire, Nicolás Guillen and Langston Hughes.
The people of the Antilles had retained not only the memory of the
word, they bore within them the lightning flash of the brush-stroke,
the ochreous eminence of so many landscapes recombined.
Lam's work viewed as a whole brings together everything that the
artist has amassed, all the elements, the forms, the majestic out¬
pourings, of his island and of his remembrance, and spreads their
directing influence to everything from design to the fiesta, to en¬
counter with others. The canvas becomes less saturated. The facts
of the Caribbean reality, the revalued ways of the Black African
universe fan out in all directions to reach fulfilment, achieving con¬
summation in the vast unforeseen of the interacting world.
Lam, heaven's alchemist, preserves in his work our earthy
memories. It is his offering that every breeze that blows, no matter
whence it comes, loves to stir with its caress.
GAMARRA
IN José Gamarra's paintings animal and plant life are never
far from the source of their perpetually renewed beginning:
the fathomless waters of eternal genesis. The Forest here
unfolds from the mysterious liquid (pond, river or seashore) from
which arise, at any moment, primordial creatures and the promise
of the future. Gamarra's Forest is no illusion; it is the land of
dreams, with its astonishingly sharply defined contours, where
tropical flowers carve out their outlines against the dark blue mass
of the sky, where the new man, escaping the relentless eye of the
hunter, prepares his festivals..
This South American space-time capsule is so living, so organic
that we cannot distinguish that which was from that which is or will
be, or the forest from the plantation, the blood of the beast from
the blood of the land, the spurt of water from the cascade of oil,
the primeval bird from the helicopter.
No known artistic artifice could portray such complexity; neither
naive realism nor the sham distortions of the avant-garde whose
time scale has no foothold here. What forms and relationships
could be imagined that could meet this challenge?
Gamarra's art does more than merely offer a reply to this ques¬
tion. It defines a place where natural representation unites with the
symbolism of form, where caricature is inscribed in the living flesh
of the landscape, where the clairvoyance of myth is punctuated with
mocking laughter, and where humanity, that is to say living and
suffering beings, hide and in so doing reveal themselves.
Thus artistic tension is at one with a living experience which is
more than merely passively undergone. We are enticed to recom¬
mence a voyage of exploration more perilous than that of the seeker
of gold. Our task is to reassemble so many obscured and suppressed
stories of this America and to embed them in the tranquil per¬
manence of forms adapted to their rebirth.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 21
the world have been given practical
expression.
Notwithstanding its uniqueness and the
careful attention paid to its conservation,
certain developments in Brasilia are causing
concern. The increase in land values in a
city with strictly defined physical limits is
leading to pressures that are difficult to
control by an administration which lacks
the necessary legal and procedural in¬
struments. There is no regulatory plan or
building code, and no clear-cut decision has
been taken to treat Brasilia as part of
Brazil's cultural heritage. As a result, cer¬
tain criteria laid down in Lucio Costa's pro¬
ject have not been observed, leading, for in¬
stance, to the grant of permits to increase
the height of buildings in certain parts of
the city and to build on land unsuited for
construction, and to the enlargement of
parking sites and changes in the highway
system.
On the other hand the city's inhabitants,
who come from the most varied and distant
parts of Brazil, are now beginning to exer¬
cise their civil rights as they come to form a
large, solidly established population, unlike
those residents who have no permanent
links with the city and move with each
change in the Federal Government.
Moreover, this fusion of cultures has been
followed by the emergence of the first
generation of Brasilia-born citizens, who
are full of enthusiasm for their city.
' Today, thirty years after it was founded,
it is clear that Brasilia must review the ways
in which it functions. Economic and social
conditionsTiave changed, and above all oil
is no longer a cheap source of energy. Ex¬
perience has also shown that excessive "sec-
torization" has not brought any real
benefits for the functioning of the city.
These are important problems and impor¬
tant measures are needed to solve them.
Since 1981 the Federal Government, the
Government of the Federal District and
Brasilia University have been trying jointly
to cope with this situation while at the same
time safeguarding the essential character of
the city. They are engaged in a unique
pioneering undertaking to find new ways of
preserving a city that is still developing and
that was envisaged as a model and synthesis
of Brazilian culture by Aloisio Magalhaes,
the man who inspired it.
The successful integration of Brasilia into
its natural environment required detailed
analysis, since the quality of the views from
the city to the horizon and to Lake Paraná
and, conversely, of the views of the city as
a whole from various observation points
depends on the quality of land use manage¬
ment. The exceptional location of the
Federal District must also be taken into ac¬
count. Affluents of three major
hydrographie basins of South America con¬
verge on this small territory, bringing
geomorphological evidence of their plant
and animal life, whose presence in the
Federal District must be preserved intact as
a source of information about the conti¬
nent's physical evolution.
Dominated by the sixteen
40-metre-high concrete pillars
of the cathedral of Brasilia, a
concrete disc provides
welcome shade from the
noonday sun.
Finally, the purpose of the Pilot Plan for
Brasilia is to determine which features
safeguard the city's character and which
tend to weaken it, in order that the former
may be strengthened and the latter cor¬
rected. A number of different procedures
have been used. Surveys have, for example,
been carried out among the resident
population in order to discover how they
see and use their city, and their criteria have
been compared with analyses made in the
field by specialists; models have been
prepared for visibility tests; a surveyor's
study has been made of the evolution of the
city since the original project was prepared;
documents dating from the time when the
city was built have been analysed. From
these and other undertakings a picture will
emerge to provide a basis for plans to
preserve the city's character.
This major operation will lead to a Plan
for the Protection of the Historical and
Cultural Heritage of Brasilia, which will in¬
clude legal norms and procedural guidelines
which, if adopted, will provide the Federal
Government, the State authorities and the
Federal District Government with the
technical means to protect and improve the
essential spirit of Brasilia.
The challenge made by Aloisio
Magalhaes must be translated into reality
and inspire the authorities, and generate a
continuing conservation process which
must not, however, stifle the evolution of a
city which is still far from having acquired
its final form. Brasilia today is at a
crossroads. It must choose between preserv¬
ing and strengthening its individuality or,
like so many cities which lack a character of
their own, become depersonalized. It would
be a pity if it were to abandon its undeniable
role as a heritage for the future. The deci¬
sion rests with its citizens and with the
authorities.
Briane Elisabeth Panitz Bica
Housing in this residential
district of Brasilia contrasts
sharply with the bold
"futuristic" architecture of
the public buildings in the cen¬
tre of the city, whose popula¬
tion has risen to 300,000 in 24
years. A million more persons
live in seven satellite towns.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The vibrant world ofCándido Portinari
by Antonio Carlos Calado
BORN in 1903 into a family of poor
Italian immigrants who worked on
the coffee plantations in the State of
Sao Paulo, Cándido Portinari won a
travelling scholarship in painting which
took him to Europe. There he absorbed im¬
pressions like a sponge, and recorded what
he saw in the great art galleries and exhibi¬
tions. On his return home he soon made a
name for himself and by 1935 was already
well known not only in Brazil but in the
United States, where his famous painting,
Coffee, received favourable notice at the
International Exhibition held at Pittsburgh
under the sponsorship of the Carnegie In¬
stitute. A study of his work was published
by the University of Chicago Press in 1940
under the title PortinariHis Life and Art.
This book contains many black and white
and full colour reproductions, including
paintings on social and religious themes and
some magnificent portraits which show that
he reached the height of his powers at an
early age. It also reveals that by this time
Portinari had already been acclaimed by no
less a person than Rockwell Kent, the
American painter, illustrator and writer.
Kent (1882-1971) wrote the introduction to
the book, and it is still a pleasure to note the
enthusiasm with which he welcomed his
young colleague from the south. This is
how he describes the vision that is central to
Portinari's art:
"The world of Portinari: as, compelled
by it, in thought, we move about in it, with
wonder fear, perhaps but with the same
acceptance of its macabre elements as our
unconscious selves accord the most fan¬
tastic dreams that trouble us in sleep, we
come gradually to the realization that this is
no world of pure imagination but an inten¬
sified, fantastic re-creation of the world
that Portinari knows, his native land,
Brazil. Of this his other paintings are the
evidence. In them we see the landscape,
tread the soil; we see its workers and their
poverty not agonized about, just told.
And told with love. Not love for poverty
and unremitted toil, but love for woman,
man, and childwho, rich or poor, to him
are lovable. He paints them trustfully.
'Blessed are the meek' would seem to be his
utterance from his heart. And if the condi¬
tions of their life on their Brazilian earth
would seem to us to be no great inheritance,
they by their goodness make life seem
worthwhile. They work; they marry and
rear families'; their children play. And of
their happiness, of the happiness of
carefree children at their play, there are no
paintings in the treasury of art more
eloquent".
Thus wrote Rockwell Kent about the
great Brazilian painter in 1940. I have just
ANTONIO CARLOS CALADO is a Brazilian
novelist and playwright. His best-known novel
is Quarup. A film based on his widely acclaim¬
ed play Pedro Mico is currently being made.
The author of one of the most comprehensive
and reliable biographies of Cándido Portinari,
he was awarded the Goethe prize for literature
in 1983.
Coffee (1935), oil on canvas,
by Cándido Portinari. After
winning an award at the
Pittsburgh International
Festival the painting was ac¬
quired by the National
Museum of Fine Arts of Brazil.
been looking in the Encyclopaedia Britan¬
nica (1972 edition) for the article on Por¬
tinari. There is none,' and the entry on
Brazil contains only two lines about him.
On the other hand Rockwell Kent is the sub¬
ject of an excellent article, running to more
than twenty lines and accompanied by a
reproduction of one of his pictures, The
Trapper. And yet if Kent has a certain posi¬
tion in the art and culture of the United
States, it is in no way comparable to that oc¬
cupied by Portinari in the painting and
culture of Brazil and Latin America. The
tribute which Kent paid him in 1940 was
prophetic. Portinari's art continued to
develop until the end of his life.
Cangaceiro, oil on canvas
(1951). Amelia and Leao Gon-
dim de Oliveira Collection.
No painter of comparable stature has ap¬
peared in Brazil since his death in 1962.
During the first half of the present century
two Brazilian artists, each working in a dif¬
ferent art-form, enriched their country's
culture and enhanced its international
standing. They were Portinari and in
musicVilla-Lobos. To add the name of
Oscar Niemeyer, the architect of Brasilia, is
to define the area in which the Brazilian
cultural sensibility has spread and influenc¬
ed the sensibilities of other peoples. But
there is no doubt that it is Portinari who
best and most directly illustrates the
Brazilian phenomenon, and by "illustrate"
I mean describing a country in figurative
terms.
For reasons of personal taste some peo¬
ple may think that other Brazilian painters
are more important than Portinari, but no
one would deny his absolute primacy as the
painter of Brazil as a whole. The monumen¬
tal heritage of Portinari's work is gradually
being recorded, photographed and
catalogued as part of the Portinari Project
(see "Unesco Newsroom", Unesco
Courier, August 1983). The Project gives
an idea of the artist's impressive output of
more than 4,000 works on social themes
Säo Paulo peasants, migrants from the
poverty-stricken Nordeste, cowhands,
labourers, popular musicians as well as
religious and historical paintings, and
portraits.
Portinari produced flawless masterpieces
in each of these fields, including murals
which alone would have brought fame to
less prolific artists. Two enormous works
by him, War and Peace, can be seen in the
entrance hall of the United Nations
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Armando Reverón: a lustfor light
by Juan Calzadilla
FOR Latin Americans of yesterday,
the only conceivable tradition to
which the work of an artist seeking
recognition could be related was that of
European art and, more specifically, of
modern European art. This was a field in
which everything was alien to us, but we
were quick to assimilate. Techniques, tools,
industrial materials -and concepts were
taken, and sometimes snatched, from Euro¬
pean art by our artists and academies and
applied unchanged, except for the visual
content, i.e. the subjects, as part of the ar¬
tist's search for a place of some kind (even
at the cost of losing a kind of hallmark of
Latin Americanism) within the chronology
of international art. Our modernity was
based on offshoots of Impressionism and
on what Herbert Read aptly called "the
tyranny of the eye" which the Renaissance
imposed upon all modern European (and
by extension Latin American) art.
If the work of the Venezuelan artist Ar¬
mando Reverón (1889-1954) is considered
against this historical background it can be
seen to represent a revolt against the Im¬
pressionist tradition in which a whole
generation of artists were brought up and in
which Reverón himself was trained. It is on¬
ly in his early works, produced between
1908 and 1920, that there is a point of view
familiar to an eye unaccustomed to the light
of the tropics.
In accordance -with tradition, Reverón
accepted the rules of the game by com¬
pleting his youthful studies at Caracas
Academy where he acquired the conven¬
tional knowledge which, talented as he was,
and capable of taking all kinds of risks, he
exploited in the remarkable achievements
of his first period, which lasted until about
1920.
JUAN CALZADILLA, Venezuelan poet, art
critic, and university teacher, is a long-serving
member of his country's museographical ser¬
vice. He is the author of a number of books in¬
cluding a major bibliography on the arts of
Venezuela and a catalogue raisonné of the
work of Armando Reverón.
' if ;>
Self-Portrait with Dolls (1950).
Pencil, charcoal and pastel on
paper, by Armando Reverón
11889-1954).
A journey to Spain and to Paris led him
to reflect on the deterministic influence of
Europe on a dependent culture like ours, in¬
capable of creating its own models (how far
is this still true?). From this time
(1915-1916) onwards, Reverón became
obsessed with the idea of Creating an art
outside the official framework, rejecting
conventional doctrines, traditional ethics,
and standardized habits of interpretation
which had taught people to assess values by
reference to European models ("Ah, he is
not as good as Monet, but you can see that
he has seen Monet!").
Reverón realized that the basis for this
revolt lay, if not in change of social
structures which was a lot to ask for at
least in a change in the pattern for in
dividual behaviour. A deep-rooted need to
isolate himself and to draw close to nature
led him to settle in a spot (half desert at that
time) on the coast near Caracas. Here he liv¬
ed in contact with nature a life that was
simplified to such primitive extremes that
eventually his physical resistance broke
down, leading to madness; here, between
1952 and 1953 he accomplished powerful
works, both concentrated and boundless,
skilful and yet dense, which seem to have
been torn from the light which served as his
central figure rather than an object (the in¬
candescent light of our environment seen
face to face and created on a stage
dramatized by the deep reflection of the
energy hidden in matter, in continuous
movement).
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 29
building in New York. Thanks to these two
paintings, to Kent's book, and to the two-
volume work by Eugenio Luraghi published
in Italy (one of them is devoted to Por¬
tinari's visit to Israel and the attractive
works it inspired) art-lovers everywhere can
appreciate the genius of this Brazilian
painter who was so. important an interpreter
of his country's culture.
Portinari's stature in Brazil has con¬
tinued to grow since his'death. He has been
the subject of a steady flow of newspaper
30
articles, essays, and studies not only in his
own country but also in the international
press. And even if there is a certain indif¬
ference towards the Third World, as il¬
lustrated by the shocking example of the
Encyclopaedia Britannica, Portinari's
prestige continues to grow in Brazil.
Of all artistic manifestations it is paint¬
ing, perhaps, which provides the clearest
evidence that the great works of today will
provide our psychological substance
tomorrow.
Cándido Portinari is the painter who in
his canvases and murals forged the con¬
sciousness of the Brazilian people with the
greatest assurance. The success he enjoyed
during his lifetime and his posthumous
fame stem from the fact that he gave an en¬
tire people the instruments of its vision.
Antonio Calado
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The bread (and butter) art of Ecuador
WHILE the arts of jewellery and pot¬
tery, of leatherwork and woodwork,
of metal and wool, are practised in I
virtually all the countries of Latin America, it I
seems that the figurines made from flour paste, I
popularly known as "bread figures", are found I
only in Ecuador, where they are produced 'in I
the little town of Calderón some fifteen I
kilometres north of Quito.
In decorating the figures, which reproduce I
elements from the environment and daily life, I
the creative artists of Calderón shun the easy I
temptation of realism. In a sense they yield to I
realism when they fashion human figures I
Indian men beside grazing sheep, Indian I
women sitting beside sacks of fruit in an im- 1
aginary market. But the animals they model I
belong to the world of plants as much as to the I
world of animals: llamas, horses, bulls, parrots, I
tortoises and even fish (which do not exist in I
the region) have big flowers, garlands of leaves I
and petals with edges like silk, instead of skin, I
hair, feathers, or scales. The colours, which I
are used indiscriminately, are those found in I
the dress of the local women: orange, green, I
scarlet, and the bluebetween navy blue and I
sky bluewhich the Indians call "colour of I
dawn".
The figures are the product of domestic and I
collective craftsmanship. At any hour of the day I
girls can be found sitting around rough and
ready tables in the inner patios of Calderón
houses, deftly moulding figures which are iden¬
tical except for some tiny detail, which may be
the result of skill, error or chance. The figures
are then lightly baked in an oven or dried in the
equatorial sun before being painted. Maybe
they are coloured by the same children, but in
some cases the mastery of relief or line
displayed in the eyebrows or lips of the tiny
faces or in the single eye of a llama seen in pro¬
file seem like the work of expert adults. Certain¬
ly the paste is prepared by the mother and it is
she, alone or with her husband, who sells the
figures to the public in an increasing number of
bigger and bigger shops.
The figures show that fondness for minute
detail which is a general characteristic of
popular Ecuadorian craftsmanship. Large
specimens measuring as much as twenty or
thirty centimetres in height are few and are
used to decorate walls (their backs being fitted
with a piece of wire or string for this purpose).
More commonly they measure a mere five or
six centimetres, are decorated nonetheless
with an extraordinary profusion of detail, and
are displayed on shelves or tables. Recently, in
response to market demand or in an attempt to
expand the market, production has begun of
tiny figures of Indians ("Cholas") and llamas
fastened to safety pins and sold as women's
brooches. In this instance, like that of mirror
frames decorated with flower motifs, this art is
in a sense utilitarian. However, unlike other
forms of craftsmanship the bread figures are
works of pure art created with no other end in
view than the pleasure to be derived from con¬
templating, admiring and living among them.
Calderón is little more than two rows of
houses, mostly workshops, storehouses and
shops where bread figures are sold, on each
side of a dusty road. The community lives from
Photos © Silvie Fischer, Nyon, Switzerland
"... Flowers, garlands of
leaves and petals like silk... "
.tourism. A major draw for the tourists, from
Ecuador and other countries, is the proximity of
the equator, which is marked at the base of an
obelisk (inside which a museum of popular arts
is being created) where visitors can be
photographed standing with one foot in the nor¬
thern hemisphere and one foot In the southern
A head and two feet peep out
from beneath a plant form
crowned by a rose in this
bread figure evoking a
tortoise.
hemisphere. Tourism has also brought a host
of posters and signs written in an English full of
touching spelling mistakes. It has also brought
the pressure of a different kind of demand
which has led to the recent appearance among
the bread figures of portrayals of Father
Christmas and Christmas trees. The Calderón
artists have long modelled crèches which are
authentic reproductions, touched with in¬
nocence and originality (the Virgin may be In¬
dian, one of the Magi may have no beard) of
those traditionally produced in some European
countries. Until recently it was also possible to
find clowns whose clothing was the finest ex¬
ample of the artists' consummate skill in depic¬
ting tiny details and of richness of colour.
The bread figures also differ from other
forms of traditional craftsmanship whose
origins it is difficult to pinpoint in time, in the
sense that they can be associated with a
specific date and historical period. The date is
1535, when the Flemish priest Fray Jodoco
Ricke brought the first ears of corn to Ecuador
and taught the people to use wooden ploughs.
The period began when the Calderón com¬
munity had sufficient bread to be able to use
some of its flour to fashion these figurines
whose ingenuous beauty is a joy for ever, like
that of any authentic work of art, although In
this case their lives are usually short. The
figurines are extremely fragile and in certain
regions, especially on the tropical coast, they
fall prey to the appetites of ravaging insects.
H Jorge Enrique Adoum
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The originality
THE great Peruvian writer José Maria
Arguedas asserted that "the popular
indigenous art of Peru is the purest
expression of the personality of the indigenous
Peruvian peoples, their creative genius and
their finest artistic traditions. Moreover, this art
in all its forms and varieties proves in a most in¬
teresting manner how the indigenous peoples
absorbed elements of Western culture, and
how those elements have been transformed
and adapted to the nature of our cultures".
The fusion with Spanish culture produced a
form of art that was particularly rich in Mexico
and Peru. This is because the most important
viceroyalties of the continent were established
MANUEL CHECA SOLARI is a Peruvian art
collector. His articles on Peruvian "high" art
and folk art have appeared in a number of pub¬
lications in Peru and Chile.
in those two countriesin the heartlands of the
two great empires of the Aztecs and the
Incaswhich had a centuries-old tradition of
craftsmanship. This tradition was rooted in the
old indigenous cultures and these were enrich¬
ed by the Spanish contribution.
In Peru the conquerors encountered a
number of different ethnic groups who had sur¬
vived within the Inca empire. For peoples who
had no knowledge of the wheel, the introduc¬
tion of the potter's wheel by the Spaniards
meant a revolution. It enabled local artists to
create new techniques and to produce works of
extraordinary beauty.
The rich quality of Peruvian handicrafts was
maintained during the early centuries of the
conquest, and was revealed in all its splendour
at the end of the eighteenth and beginning of
the nineteenth centuries. The Spanish element
was by then very diluted. It is at this'period that
we encounter the principal, or at least the best-
Small Peruvian retablo or
miniature "altar-piece" (each
side of the panel measures 13
cm) depicting a village
celebration beside a giant cac¬
tus.- Musicians are shown in
the background. Figures in
foreground are 3 cm high.
known, product of Peruvian craftsmanship
the "Pucará bull". As a symbol of strength and
courage the bull was, and still is, typically
Spanish, but it was adopted by indigenous
craftsmen and is now one of the most important
forms of popular art in Latin America.
As we know, the principal animals to be
found in the Andes in pre-Columbian times
were the llama, the vicuña, the alpaca and the
guanaco. Although these animals continued to
be modelled in a variety of materials, the figure
of the bull, which initially had a ceremonial
An engraved mate or gourd
(diameter 11 cm). A
popular celebration in a
public square Is depicted
in the detail shown here.
Musicians can be seen in
the midst of the crowd.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
of Peruvian popular art by Manuel Checa Solari
significance, began to be established as
typically Peruvian. The "Pucará bull", which is
both ornamental and utilitarian, is provided
with a handle in the form of a ring on its back,
and is commonly used as a flower vase. Its
strong, vigorous appearance Is more sug¬
gestive of an ox. It is made of earthenware.in a
great variety of sizes and is always painted in
white and ochre, with a lock of hair on the
forehead and a kind of dewlap In the form of a
plait or garland, coloured green. The "Pucará
bull" is also manufactured in Quinua.
Equally well-known in Latin America are
retablos or miniature "altar-pieces". They
originated in the city of Ayacucho and are
made in the altiplano. They are inspired by
Spanish altar-pieces, and the treatment clearly
reveals a cultural and artistic fusion. They
usually depict religious scenes containing a
large number of figuresthe Bethlehem crib,
Christ's entry into Jerusalem, the Way of the
This "three-dimensional
painting ' ' of the square at Cuz¬
co is a variant of the retablos
produced by the folk artists of
Ayacucho, Peru. The sky is
painted on wood. The houses
with their corners and
balconies are of stucco, and
the human figures, like those
in the retablos, are made of a
mixture of plaster and cooked
potato and are painted and
varnished when dry.
Cross and processions with the Virgin. The
figures, which are sometimes no more than 1 or
2 centimetres high, reveal remarkable creative
and imaginative powers. They are made from a
mixture of plaster and the flour from boiled
potatoes, are painted and given a protective
coating of colourless enamel. But the subjects
depicted in these light wooden cases are not
always religious. Bullfights and cockfights are
also frequently represented, as are ingenious
and sometimes humorous models of hat
shops, grocery stores, taverns and other
places of popular fréquentation.
Another typical example of Peruvian crafts¬
manship is the so-called mate burilado. This is
a dried pumpkin decorated with a multitude of
human figures and a profusion of geometrical
patterns. Some mates burilados may possibly
tell a story, true or imaginary, but on account of
their circular form and the decoration without
beginning or end any attempt at interpretation
would be like trying to solve a riddle:
As can be easily imagined, technical ad¬
vances, like the oven in the case of the
"Pucará bulls", and greater commercialization
due to the growth of tourism, have somewhat
impaired the original purity, beauty, Ingenuity
and magic of popular art.
This decorated earthen¬
ware "Pucará bull" from
Peru stands just under 1 1
cm high.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
The master-craftsmen of Mexico
by Anharad Lanz de Ríos
Writing about the arts ofMeso-
America, Jacques Soustelle
noted: "The décor of life was
above all that used, with ex¬
ceptional skill, in the 'minor'
arts for the embellishment of
both rare and commonplace
objects; from the most
unassuming terra-cotta dish to
jewellery made of gold
nothing was vulgar, there was
no impression of work done in
haste or merely for effect or
profit."
OF all the countries of the American
continent, Mexico undoubtedly has
the largest number of active crafts¬
men and the highest level of hand-craft produc¬
tion both in quantity and quality. These popular
plastic art forms still reflect residual echoes of
the pre-Columbian heritage as well as impor¬
tant Spanish, Asian and universal influences
subject to constant adaptation and change.
There are no precise statistics concerning
the proportion of the population engaged in
hand-crafts in Mexico, but it has been
estimated that some one million two hundred
thousand heads of households undertake
some form of craft activity. Training in the
crafts is a part of normal family life and from a
very early age children are taught the basic
skills which will enable them to master these
crafts. Thus, although craft production in Mex¬
ico is organized in a number of different ways,
the greater part of it is the work of family
groups.
There is often a division of labour between
men and women. For example, men are
seldom involved in the manufacture of textiles.
Pottery, too, is women's work with the men
confined to transporting the clay and wood and
firing the vessels.
In the sixteenth century the Spanish con¬
quistadores came across craft centres in Mex¬
ico of varying levels of advancement many of
which, however, had mastered a number of
very advanced techniques, such as the
polishing of ceramics. Highly advanced tech¬
niques were also employed by goldsmiths and
weavers. The Conquest triggered off a vast
process of acculturation, giving rise to crafts,
such as forging, for example, which in time,
despite their strong Spanish roots, came to be
looked upon as traditional.
ANHARAD LANZ DE RÍOS, Mexican an¬
thropologist and sociologist, is a member of
Comunicación Educativa Latinoamericana, an
institution based in Cuemavaca, Mexico.
During the period of the Viceroyalties, the
crafts could be classified in three groups. In the
first group were artistic objects with ancient
Mexican motifs and using special techniques
and raw materials. These included pottery,
jewellery and woven materials. The craftsmen
knew and used gold, silver and copper. Among
vitreous materials they knew only quartz and
obsidian. For weaving they used soft fibres
such as cotton and silk, but they had no
knowledge of wool.
The second group consisted of the work of
indigenous craftsmen whose production was
intended to meet their own needs. In this group
decorative and manufacturing techniques
were not very advanced.
From the interaction of these two groups and
the reciprocal influence they had on each other
was born the third group which is today known
as "traditional mestizo". The main
characteristics of objects of this type are the
low economic value of the raw materials of
which they are made and the artistic expres¬
sion they incorporate. Regardless of their
economic value and the quantities produced,
all the crafts mentioned above still survive in
present-day Mexico.
Today the so-called "Mexican curio", or
"airport art", with its reduced production times
and costs, presents a distorted image of
authentic popular craftsmanship. By the very
nature of their production organization, coupl¬
ed with the lack of raw materials, the authentic
crafts find it difficult to compete on even terms.
Nevertheless, the staunch resistance of the
craft groups and the deeply-rooted craft tradi¬
tion make of Mexico a country outstanding for
the rich variety of craft objects produced.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
The dance of death
by Miguel Rojas-Mix
EVERY year on the second of November
Mexicans eat death. They consume it in
the form of sugar skulls and savour it in
confectionery. Children play with death,
manipulating skeletons with string and making
them dance. They amuse themselves with little
figures called padrecitos ("little fathers"),
which have a chickpea for a head, or make
death jump out of a cardboard coffin like a jack-
in-a-box. In fact, the whole country moves to
the rhythm of an enormous dance of death:
shop windows, cyclists, toys, couples dressed
up in wedding costumes. Everything is
transformed into a calavera, a word which in
Mexican Spanish means not only a skull (as it
does in Castilian Spanish) but a whole
skeleton.
Eros and Thanatos, love and death. On the
second of November death succumbs to the
pleasures of life and calls on craftsmen to
depict death in order to help those who mourn
the dead. In other words death becomes a
source of livelihood for the confectioners who
fashion the traditional sugar calaveras and in¬
scribe on the foreheads the names of relatives
of their customers, and for the potters of Oax¬
aca, Santa Fé de la Laguna and Michoacán
who make incense burners for the altars to the
dead or floral decorations for tombs. It provides
a living for those who make the little black glaz¬
ed bulls surrounded by candles and zem-
pasuchitl flowers which are found at Puebla,
multi-coloured images of souls, earthenware
toys with skeleton drummers from Guanajuato,
and coaches with musical skeletons from
Metepec.
In death two traditions meet to form the basis
of the Mexican identitythe indigenous pre-
Cortesian tradition, and the Spanish. The
former has left us marvellous artefacts such as
skulls carved in rock crystal, the finest example
of which is Coatlicué, the Aztec goddess of the
earth and of life, depicted with a skull-like face.
This tradition is preserved in the Mexican
sense of life, which is quite different from that
of the Old World. For the Mexican, death is not
something frightful but a necessary prelude to
resurrection. In the cosmic cycle it engenders
life.
Death is also embraced in the European
especially the Spanishmystical tradition, in
the danse macabre evoked in the poetry of
François Villon and the engravings of Holbein
and popularized in Latin America through
Baroque art. The calavera called in question
the power and riches of this world. It is shown
carrying away kings, bishops and peasants
and thus restoring human equality. As the
fifteenth-century Spanish poet Jorge Manrique
wrote:
Popes and emperors
Prelates and poor shepherds
There, death treats them all alike.
In the engravings of José Guadelupe Posada
death is transformed into an image of the Mex¬
ican people. The pelona ("bald one") as she is
popularly called, goes off to the Revolution with
Zapata, brandishes a sword, weeps, dances,
eats spicy meat dishes, and gets drunk on pul¬
que. Posada's skeletons are corrosive precise¬
ly because they form part of an ancient tradi¬
tion of social criticism associated with death. In
his La Quijotitaysu Prima (1818) Fernández de
Lizardi tells us that it was the custom on the se¬
cond of November to send leaflets to politicians
and people of standing anticipating the dates
of their deaths and presenting an obituary
notice. These leaflets which described how the
"deceased" had lived were called calaverasM
Calavera of a Zapatist Revolu¬
tionary by José Guadalupe
Posada (1851-1913).
The Venezuelan writer and art
critic Mariano Picón Salas
observed how the Mexican
people "by force of wisdom
and experience play with
death in order to grow ac¬
customed to it without fear".
The famous Aztec skull carved
from rock crystal which is now
preserved in the British
Museum, London. Aztec
lapidaries cut hardstones with
tools made of wood, plant
fibres, and emery.
MIGUEL ROJAS-MIX, Chilean art critic and
historian, is professor of the sociology of
literature and art at the University of Paris. He
is the author of many books and studies in¬
cluding América Latina en el Arte Europeo
(Latín America in European Art), La Plaza
Mayor, Instrumento de Dominio Colonial (The
Main Square, an Instrument of Colonial
Domination) and a brief history of Latin
America for children.
I
Imposing plastic "calaveras"
(death figures) of musicians in
Mexico City.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Castles in the air
Haiti's painters of high spirits by René Depestre
IT all began one April day in 1943. The
English teacher during our final year
at the Lycée Pétion was a North
American of Dutch origin, DeWitt Peters.
He was mild-mannered, genial, competent.
Every now and then a cloud of sadness and
nostalgia would suddenly pass across his
mocking eyes. He would stop teaching and
talk to us about his dreams. The last time he
did so he announced to his young pupils and
friends that he was going to give up teaching
and devote all his energies to painting. Had
he taken leave of his senses? He was tired of
being a Sunday painter, and a full-time
painter was taking possession of his hands
like a loa (a supernatural being a god or
demon, spirit or genie) in the head of an
adept of voodoo. Those of us who liked him
were saddened by his departure, and found
it hard to get down to our English studies
again.
A year later, in May 1944, the Centre
d'Art Haïtien at Port-au-Prince, directed
by the same DeWitt Peters, held its first ex¬
hibition. One of the most exuberant
movements in twentieth-century art was
beginning to grow.
To the unknowns who came to his studio,
Peters offered a working space, canvas or
paper, brushes and tubes of colour. In addi¬
tion to these tools and materials he also
gave technical advice: academic notions of
drawing, and the application of the seven
"souls" of the rainbow.
The men who came to Peters tended to be
cobblers, barbers, taxi-drivers, fishing-boat
builders, house-painters, tailors, voodoo
priests, servants, hawkers. Those who had
already handled a paintbrush (like the
housepainter Hector Hyppolite, one of the
first masters of the movement) had done so
to decorate doors, trunks, windows, trucks,
domestic objects and objects used in
voodoo ritual.
These men who had come straight from
the itinerant mysteries of Haitian reality
would in the next few years hurl a dazzling
system of pictorial forms at the face of the
world. Loa took over painting as such gods
as Baron Samedi, Dambalah Ouédo,
Agoué, Ogou Badagris, Shango and Erzuli
Fréda-Dahomin, a thousand leagues away
from the Italian Renaissance, Cézanne and
RENE DEPESTRE, Haitian author, has publish¬
ed several volumes of poems, essays and fic¬
tion including Un Arc-en-ciel pour l'Occident
Chrétien (published in English as A Rainbow
for the Christian West, University of
Massachusetts Press, 1977) and Poète à
Cuba, (Poet in Cuba). He has collaborated on
two collective works produced by Unesco,
Africa en América Latina ("Africa in Latin
America") and América Latina en sus Ideas
¡"Latin America in its Ideas").
36
Heaven and Earth
(1959) by the Haitian
painter Préfète Duf-
faut. Usually con¬
structed from rising
columns ofmatter in
a state of flux, Duf-
faut's landscapes
are inspired by the
town of Jacmel,
where he was born.
Picasso, gave the popular surrealism of the
Haitians the chance to express itself.
The imaginations of Hector Hyppolite,
Philomé Obin, Rigaud Benoît, Wilson
Bigaud, Castera Bazile, Préfète Duffaut,
Louverture Poisson, Jasmin Joseph,
Micius Stephane and a dozen more began to
transform into painting the dream-world in
which Haiti is rooted. The forms thus set
free experienced frenzy, ecstasy, unbridled
fantasy, universal generosity, and a
fulgurating harmony with new climates of a
literally bedazzled collective imagination.
Then, working with phantasmagoric
patience, a whole people of artists made a
fantastic inventory, of breath-taking lyrical
freshness, of the slightest details of the Hai¬
tian reality and dream. Other masters join¬
ed the ranks of those named above: J.E.
Gourgue, Antonio Joseph, Casimir
Laurent, Senèque Obin, André Pierre,
Dieudonné Cédor, Gérard Valcin, Robert
St. Brice. And other hands, from all over
Haiti, which were enduring the terrible
works and days of a crucified people, join¬
ed in this rebellious exuberance of a lust for
life as rich in thermal energy as the sun
itself.
It is a movement in the full, dynamic
sense of the term; even the tap-tap (buses)
which drive on the country's rough roads
have not escaped the painterly frenzy of
those who use them. The itinerant gods
watch over every crossroads as biblical
scenes mingle with scenes from a desperate
everyday life. In Haiti the imaginary has
tap-tap wheels, it performs feats of
acrobacy in joining the two extremes of a
possessed and a possessing reality, a fren¬
zied reality, a reality best not met on a dark
night. The Haitian painters, however,
courageously set forth to meet it and to cast
in its teeth the strokes of a brush moistened
with tenderness and beauty. In this way a
masked world withstands the daily assaults
of poverty and the difficulty of being Hai¬
tian in one's native Haiti or anywhere else.
The mad gods of painting still drive too'fast
on Haiti's dusty roads. Where are the
"naive painters" in this wild light?
Assuredly there has never been a "naive"
phenomenon in Haiti. It was as a result of
a dubious tourist craze that the label of
"naivety" was tied to the creative
phenomenon which possesses the Haitian
visual imagination. To celebrate this Hai¬
tian renaissance as a poet, I humbly follow
the example of Apollinaire as he con¬
templated the paintings of the Douanier
Rousseau. Masters of the marvellous in
Haiti, great itinerant loas of joy and pain,
I invite the world to watch "your baggage
pass freely through the gate of heaven".
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
The artistic ferment
of a continent
by Carlos Rodriguez Saavedra
FOR more than four centuries Latin American art has
reflected both the impact, the imposition or the
variously assimilated influence of the Western system
over a vast area originally inhabited by indigenous peoples
of a variety of cultures, and the beginning of a slow, complex
process of hybridization. Latin America is a prolonged
historical assertion of a vast plurality, open to all the world's
cultural manifestations but capable of absorbing them
without impairing its identity.
The characteristic feature of Latin American painting in
general from 1920 onwards was the rejection of academic
precepts and their replacement to a greater or lesser extent by
avant-garde trends. Many painters from the Andean and
tropical countries decided at an early stage to express in¬
digenous national or regional themes in the new idiom. In
Mexico, painting was also to be used as a means of political
CARLOS RODRIGUEZ SAAVEDRA is a Peru¬
vian writer, essayist and art critic. He has
published many articles and studies on pre-
Columbian art and modern Latin American
painting.
and nationalistic expression. The mural painting associated
with the revolution in that country began as a form of
glorification and finally became a vehicle of criticism and
controversy.
Because of their volume and importance the works of
Orozco, Rivera and Siqueiros occupy a special place in the
history of Latin American art. They also demonstrate the
capacity of the American world for cultural syncretism.
With deliberate anti-Western emphasis, they use Western
painting techniques and idioms to express Mexican na¬
tionalism and reassert the country's Aztec past. In
monumental style and descriptive virulence, the works of
Rivera displayed in public buildings, especially in the Na¬
tional Palace in Mexico City, attain a grandeur hitherto
unknown in Latin American painting.
By contrast, the works of Clemente Orozco are devoid of
rhetoric and figurative detail, but in their plenitude and
tragic intensity they represent the highest achievement of
painting during this period. Like the painter himself, the
work of David Alfaro Siqueiros was violently concerned
with revolutionary politics and has been the subject of much ^
DIEGO RIVERA (1886-1957).
The Conquest of Mexico: the
true portrait of Hernán Cortés
and the enslavement of the In¬
dians. Fresco, 1929-1935, Na¬
tional Palace, Mexico City.
Along with other mural
painters, such as José
Clemente Orozco and David
Alfaro Siqueiros, Diego Rivera
was a successor of José
Guadalupe Posada. This mural
offers a new vision of the
past the Conquest as seen by
those who were its victims. The
re-interpretation of history from
this standpoint and the recon¬
ciliation of the pre-Columbian
tradition with modern times
were two of the great themes of
the Mexican revolution, and it
was from them that present-
day Mexican art was born.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
<
©
.JOSE CLEMENTE OROZCO (1883-1948).
The Slave. Oil on canvas, 1947.
"Ours is the only way" declared David
Alfaro Siqueiros, the leader, with Diego Rivera
and José Clemente Orozco, of the great Mex¬
ican muralist movement. Orozco, however,
distanced himself somewhat from the others,
rejecting the demagogic, "folklore" aspects
of the movement, preferring to give free rein
to his highly personal conception of painting.
In his polemical Carta a Orozco (Open Letter to
Orozco) Siqueiros acknowledged that he had
created "the finest plastic forms that heralded
the Mexican movement". Guatemalan art
critic Luis Cardona y Aragón declared that
Orozco was the most important artist to come
out of Latin America.
controversy. However, perhaps because of the controversies
it provoked, the revolutionary period and the mural paint¬
ings associated with it have served as a starting-point for con¬
temporary Mexican painting. If these paintings had not ex¬
isted to serve as a basis or a challenge to be rejected or sur¬
passed, the works of such painters as Rufino Tamayo, José
Luis Cuevas or because of the vast scope they have opened
up for Mexican art of more recent artists, would be
inconceivable.
In Brazil the new art burst on the public with the challeng¬
ing "Modern Art Week" in Säo Paulo in February, 1922.
The conjugation of avant-garde initiatives in literature,
music and the plastic arts by Oswaldo de Andrade, Anita
Malfatti, Mario de Andrade, Tarsila de Amaral, Lasar
Segall, Victor Brocheret and Emiliano Di Cavalcanti,
amongst others, was primarily aimed at asserting the right to
aesthetic revolt and freedom of expression. At the same
time, by using the conquests of the European "isms" these
artists came to the rescue of personal, popular and national
values.
The international recognition and official support accord¬
ed a few years later to Cándido Portinari demonstrated the
extent to which this aesthetic revolt, in addition to changing
the orientation of art, had gained solid ground in the coun¬
try. Born and bred amongst the cotton and coffee planta¬
tions, Cándido Portinari remained faithful until the end of
his life to the images of his childhood. His masterly series of
murals for the Ministry of Education in Rio de Janeiro
demonstrate, in an integrated pictorial idiom combined with
a personal style, his capacity to use freely the vocabulary of
Cubism, Expressionism and even Surrealism to represent the
country's regions, ethnic types and products. The main
features of his work were described by Mario de Andrade as
traditionalism, lyricism, realism and nationalism.
Meanwhile in the Caribbean Amelia Peláez, a powerful
Cuban artist who had assimilated and selectively rejected in
Paris the teachings of such masters as André Lhote, was
using the formal achievements of Cubism to express typical¬
ly tropical themes, especially in her still-lifes. Just about this
time another Cuban, Wifredo Lam, was setting out on his
journey through the world of painting, taking with him
ancestral elements which, thanks to his contacts with Picasso
and the Surrealists, he would later release in images that were
strange to Western art.
At the opposite extreme, painting in Argentina and
Uruguay, having no pre-Hispanic roots or nationalist or
political commitments, developed from the beginning within
the main currents of Western art. Emilio Petorutti, who had
lived in Florence since 1913, returned to Buenos Aires in
1924 enriched not only by his study of the 15th century
masters but by his friendship with the leaders of the new
"Futurism". At the time of his return he had achieved a
38 ?
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
DAVID ALFARO SIQUEIROS (1898-1974).
The Kiss.
The eager impetuosity with which Siqueiros
lived his life, a life full of incident, of ups and
downs and adventures, was also the driving
force in his artistic work, in the service of his
revolutionary ideas. His murals, like those of
those two other great Mexican muralists
Diego Rivera and José Clémente Orozco,
adorn the walls of many public buildings in his
own country (for example, his famous
450-square-metre mural La Revolución Mex¬
icana) as well as in Chile and in Cuba. Influenc¬
ed by Expressionism and Surrealism, Si¬
queiros' work is inspired particularly by social
and proletarian problems.
. RENE PORTOCARRERO (1912- ). Carnival,
Gouache, 1970.
Cuba is the focus of René Portocarrero's
preoccupations Havana, its folklore, its
fiestas, the Afro-Cuban tradition. In his urban
landscapes, in which are to be found echoes
of the stained-glass window and the baroque
tradition characteristic of the island, the
houses seem to move to the rhythm of form
and colour. Portocarrero works mainly on
three themes portraits of Flora, the carnival
and the town three images and a style which
are his contribution to the Cuban identity.
k JORGE CAMACHO (1934- ). L'Ornéoscope.
Oil on canvas, 1981.
For Camacho death is a dance to the rhythm
of the rumba. For Cubans the Angel of Death
is a lifelong companion. Camacho's world is a
charnel-house. His ossuaries in metamor¬
phosis are surrealism impregnated with
African rites; they recall both Breton and
Chango (a Voodoo deity), are both playful and
macabre, and in them are echoes of Bosch,
Goya and, above all, of José Guadalupe
Posada.
mastery of the forms established by Braque, and especially
of the synthetic Cubism introduced by Juan Gris. During
this period others, including Horacio Butler, Juan del Prête,
Héctor Basaldúa, Antonio Berni, Raúl Soldi, Raquel Forner
and Lino Eneas Spilimbergo, made a decisive contribution
to the establishment of modern art in Argentina in works
which demonstrated individual creative assimilation of the
main currents represented in the Paris School.
Uruguay's contribution to the Latin American art of this
period is represented by the work of two quite dissimilar ar¬
tists. Pedro Figari crowned a rich career successfully devoted
to a variety of humanistic activities by exploiting the Post-
Impressionist vein opened up by Bonnard. Joaquin Torres
Garcia, whose reputation has continued to grow since his
death in Montevideo in 1949, embodies the highest achieve¬
ment of Latin American art at this period.
His life, marked by sojourns and experiments in many
cities Barcelona, New York, Paris, Montevideo was con¬
tinuously devoted to intellectual and artistic investigation
aimed at solving a fundamental problem: that of the rela¬
tionship between reality, which painting normally
represents, and the absolute which it aspires to reveal, bet¬
ween the fleeting image and the eternal idea. In opposition
to the transient and the descriptive, Torres Garcia elaborated
his theory of "Constructive Universalism". In his books
Metafísica de la Prehistórica Indoamericana and Estructura
he analyses the fundamental principles of ancient American
art and postulates constructive principles for the new art. In¬
spired by this model, he invented a symbolic alphabet or con¬
structive cryptography whose aim was to give universally
valid expression to man and reality.
The work of the so-called indigenista painters in Peru bet¬
ween 1920 and 1940 was a response, not only to a social reali¬
ty but also to an aesthetic demand to create an art form
with its own meaning and importance, rooted in native im¬
ages and values, and through this art to restore to the in¬
digenous inhabitant and his milieu their original rightful role
in Peruvian culture. From 1920 onwards José Sabogal
assembled around his painting and doctrines a group of
pupils that included Julia Codesido, Enrique Camino Brent
and Camilo Blas, who formed the nursery of indigenista art.
For the first time Peruvian painting was devoted exclusively
to recording and representing people, customs, architecture
and landscape, especially amongst the Andean communities
and in the interior.
Armando Reverón is undoubtedly the greatest name in
Venezuelan art of this period. After his studies in the
academies of Madrid and Barcelona the work of Reverón in
his native country is a true reflection of his personality, com¬
pounded of total dedication and demand, which in its last
phase could be defined as absolute illuminism. Derived from
an Impressionism that progressively discarded nearly every
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
©
JOAQUIN FERRER (1 929- ). Restless Space.
Oil on canvas, 1978.
In 1960, the Cuban painter and engraver
Joaquin Ferrer came to Paris on a government
grant to study painting. There he came into
contact with surrealist groups and has since
developed his career there with a number of
collective and one-man exhibitions. Ferrer's
graceful "geometric" designs, usually in two
distinct tones, have the ordered aspect of
vegetation that is both lush and restrained.
A HERVE TELEMAQUE (1937- ).
Tribute to the Equals Sign. Collage,
1983.
The Haitian artist Hervé Téléma-
que studied in the United States of
America from 1 957 to 1 960 before
settling in Paris in 1961. Influenced
at first by the lyrical abstractions of
the American school, he has since
returned to the fundamentals of
surrealism (Chirico, Magritte)
which has led him to discover the
object as an important element in
the urban landscape.
Photo © All rights reserved
ALICIA PENALBA (1918-1982).
Great Vegetation Liturgy. Bronze,
1957.
After winning the prize for paint¬
ing at the National Exhibition at
Buenos Aires, her native city, Alicia
Penalba moved to Paris in 1947. It
was at this time that she turned to
sculpture. From the beginning her
style was founded on basic forms.
Her first series of sculptures, entitl¬
ed "Totems", seems to evoke
great petrified plant forms, such as
the giant cacti to be found on the
flanks of the Andean cordillera. Her
later works retain this plant-like, ar¬
chitectural quality.
kind of objective support, his so-called "white" and
"ochre" periods identify the dazzling light of the Caribbean
with the very reason for painting.
The Second World War brought Latin America closer to
European trends. Even where art was concerned the conflict
lent a new, magnified dimension to Europe in the Latin
American consciousness. Furthermore, because of the war a
number of artists who had been formed in the Paris School
returned to their native countries. The presence and
contribution conceptual freedom and formal
experimentation of some of these painters played a lasting
role in the modernization and Westernization of Latin
American painting. The postwar period, especially from the
1950s onwards, was marked by another development. The
centre of artistic experiment moved to New York and, start¬
ing in the mid-1950s, that city began to exercise a powerful
influence on young Latin American artists both as a centre
for the diffusion of new trends and as a pole of attraction.
The scope and variety of Latin American art was sustained
and even intensified throughout the period of renewal that
started about 1960. During these years a style of painting was
40
defined in most of the Latin American countries which
responded creatively to their specific cultural circumstances
through full assimilation of contemporary aesthetic
postulates. In the leading artists of this period identification
of substance with form, the assumption of meaning by the
vehicle of its expression, produces that revelation of hitherto
unknown contents an opening to forms of life previously
culturally felt but not yet given objective visual
expression which is typical of authentic artistic creations.
This is true of Wifredo Lam, Rufino Tamayo and Roberto
Matta.
Thanks to his own creative urge and to the "tools" sup¬
plied by avant-garde trends, Tamayo, who received his early
training during the last stage of Mexican muralism, escaped
from the political and nationalistic limitations of revolu¬
tionary art. Post-Cubism enabled him to break down form
and liberate its content. This is essentially evocative of
magical, mythical, pre-Columbian or folk symbolism. But it
is his aesthetic ability to transform this material into struc¬
tured forms of refined chromatic lyricism that make it a
work of art. This explains why, while affirming that he per-
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
GONZALO FONSECA
(1922- ). Sculpture.
Marble, 1970.
Architecture? Fantastic
constructions? Rather we
should think in terms of
enigmas, of timelessness,
of metaphysics. Fonseca
has assimilated the example
of Torres Garcia and
transposed it to sculpture.
His works, like those of Gar¬
cia, seem to be imbued with
a cosmic feeling. For
Fonseca, "humanist con¬
structivism" means seeing
the block as living-space.
Reliefs, symbols, epochs
are integrated in the unity of
form and the compactness
of volume, yet they are dif¬
ferentiated as different
worlds because they are
constructed on different
scales.
ANTONIO FRASCONI
(1919- ). Comes the
Storm. Wood-engraving.
For years now the
Uruguayan artist Antonio
Frasconi has been one of
Latin America's most
outstanding xylographers.
Resident for many years in
the United States of
America, where he works
and teaches, Frasconi has
brought to his coloured
wood-engravings a style
which strives to go beyond
the normal limits of this
medium to achieve the
delicacy of an oriental paint¬
ing, yet with no loss of
strength and firmness of
line.
Photo © All rights reserved
JOAQUIN TORRES GARCIA
(1874-1949). White Construc¬
tive. 1931.
In 1891, at the age of seven¬
teen, Torres Garcia set out from
his native city of Montevideo to
which he was not to return until
1934on a crucial Odyssey
which took him to the Barcelona
and the Paris of the first three
decades of the century and to the
discovery of the most vital cur¬
rents of the European avant-
garde. His iconoclastic tenden¬
cies were already apparent in a
note written during his youthful
days in Barcelona: "Nothing is
more wonderful than to forget the
past and to set out in search of
adventure. I am the enemy of all
traditions, whatever they may
be." Drawing inspiration from the
work of Van Doesburg and Mon-
drian, Torres Garcia laid the foun¬
dations of "constructivism", one
of the two or three great
movements of twentieth-century
Latin American art. His El Univer¬
salismo Constructivista, publish¬
ed in Buenos Aires in 1 944, sums
up the purpose of his artistic
quest.
©
sonally has "very deep roots", he can assert that a work of
art is "a product that derives its value solely from its plastic
qualities, acquired through a process of purification until its
essence is obtained".
The paintings of Wifredo Lam demonstrate the catalytic
power and disturbing revolutionary effects that a study of
Picasso could produce in a young Cuban artist. "What he
learned from Picasso and from Oceanic and West African
sculpture", writes Gilbert Chase, "bound him to his own
Afro-Cuban heritage". For this reason people have tried to
see in the work of Lam a direct pictorial expression of the so-
called primitive animist and fetichist religions, and of the
jungle. This is a simplistic analysis which ignores« the in¬
decipherable part of the creative process. In this respect the
work of the Cuban artist, like that of Tamayo, reveals an
authentic dimension of the cultural infrastructure of Latin
America. Compounded of ancient roots given new
significance, it produces a disturbing effect. It has an im¬
pressive, sombre power.
The effect of Surrealism on Roberto Matta was similar to
that of Picasso on Lam. Coming from Chile, a country in the
Western tradition, without any pre-Columbian or African
cultural heritage but possessed of intense visionary power,
Matta has created works that are unusual even in avant-
garde terms. The originality of his work lies, not in technical
or formal innovations, but in the creation of a boundless
universe full of strange dynamic energy and peopled by am¬
biguous, brilliant, erotic, violent, disturbingly fascinating
creatures.
The following generation extended the expressive scope of
Latin American painting even further, in conditions of
growing internationalization. In Ecuador Diogenes Paredes,
Eduardo Klingman and Oswaldo Guayasamin, who evolved
from indigenismo to Expressionism with unparalleled vigour
(especially Guayasamin, with his paintings, murals and
sculptures) were succeeded by artists like Enrique Tábara,
Aníbal Villacís and Oswaldo Viteri, whose work, although
purely pictorial, was more complex in content and quality.
After Reverón there was a void in Venezuela which has
been filled by a large group of artists, most of whom have
acquired and used the language of contemporary painting.
In 1955 Jesús Soto (born in 1923) started to use plexiglass for>
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
k GERARDO CHAVEZ (1937- ). Mother Earth.
Oil on canvas, 1979.
Chavez is a Peruvian artist who has been liv¬
ing in Paris for many years. The all-pervading
theme of his work is the imaginary. He creates
a world of forms in constant physiological
metamorphosis. The cultural roots of this ex¬
travagant, forcefully personal painting can be
deduced from its echoes of Spanish Baroque
as assimilated by Peru, from its echoes, too,
of the great painters who fascinated Chavez
during his adolescence Bosch and Brueghel.
RUFINO TAMAYO (1899- ). Man with
Telephone. Oil on canvas, 1956.
Mexican artist Rufino Tamayo's early paint¬
ings drew their inspiration from the structural
and symbolic geometrical forms of pre-
Columbian sculpture. Soon, however, his
work became less abstract and acquired more
movement, his use of colour became more
subtle and his subject matter more universal.
His unusual studies of the human form came
close to surrealism. The French poet and
writer André Breton said of him that he raised
the humdrum daily round to the realms of
ritual and poetry.
compositions which, through the inter-relation and interplay
of planes, produced a remarkable impression of optical
vibration, with similar but more subtle results than those
previously achieved in experiments in geometrical abstrac¬
tion. After 1958 he began to use metal wires grouped
together and moving freely over plane surfaces, enabling
him to create multi-dimensional spaces in which strange ef¬
fects of dynamism were produced which were previously
unknown in abstract art. The field of abstract art has been
cultivated by many other excellent Venezuelan artists. Carlos
Cruz-Diez has produced some solid work, carefully executed
and of remarkable optical refinement, of which his
Fisiocromias are an example.
The rich variety of Argentine painting in the mid-1960s led
Tomas M. Messer to wonder why so many excellent artists
emigrated to other art centres. Broadly speaking it can be
said that the transition from the early Informalism to
present-day styles of painting represents an assertion and
clarification of positions. This is demonstrated by the
Abstract Expressionism of Sarah Grilo and Antonio Fer¬
nández Muro. In her sensitivity of expression and colour
Sarah Grilo has achieved a degree of maturity that is rare
amongst avant-garde artists, and the constructive precision
of Fernández Muro's work is accompanied by a classical
balance that is also rare nowadays. The first neo-
figuratives Deira, de la Vega, Macció, Luis Felipe Noé,
42
Antonio Seguíhave followed a variety of paths. Seguí
enlivens his themes with a mixture of humour and drama but
avoids pictorial literature. Despite the individuality of its
members the Geometries constitute one of the most coherent
groups. Vidal, Brizzi, McEntyre, Silva and the "generative
painting" concept invented by them represent an advance on
static geometrism. A combination of the mysterious with
precision of language, a translation into lines of the energy
which animates the world and the vitality which actuates
lifegenerative art uses the idiom of the technological age
to which it belongs.
The so-called "Recherche d'Art Visuel" established in
Paris in the 1960s and including Gyula Kosice, Hugo Demar¬
co, and Julio Le Parc represents better than any other group
the need constructively to break through the plane of tradi¬
tional pictorial support and the possibility of creating tri¬
dimensional works that are rich in optical effects and kinetic
values.
The characteristic features of the movement in Peru which
followed indigenismo were a growing receptiveness to con¬
temporary concepts from the liquidation of the Paris
School to the adoption of the Abstract idiom together with
the use of these concepts by a number of leading artists to ex¬
press values of an impersonal, mythical, magic character.
This was true from the 1960s onwards of Fernando de
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
k OSWALDO GUAYASAMIN (1919- ).
Hands of Protest. Oil on canvas, 1968.
At one with the Mexican mural painters in
his passionate involvement with indigenous
culture and sharing their aamiration for Pablo
Picasso, the Ecuadorian painter Oswaldo
Guayasamin is a man firmly rooted in the soil
and in the people. He is concerned more with
space than with history with his dominating
views of rugged scenery as seen from Mount
Pinchincha to the more reverential vistas from
the valley of Quito. Rather than with its past
he is concerned with the soul of Ecuador
which he lays bare to us in his "Hands" series
of paintings.
Szyszlo, who learned to express a Peruvian content, com¬
pounded of formal allusions and chromatic qualities, in
purely abstract language.
Brazilian painting also adopted contemporary language
and outgrew the influence of the Paris School in the 1950s
and especially in the 1960s when the European influence was
replaced by that of North America. Ibere Camargo, Arcanio
Ianellitrue to an intense European-style FormalismIvan
Serpa and Manabu Mabe are among the exponents of the
new painting in this period. The scene became richer and .
more varied towards the end of the 1960s and after. After
1970 the new Brazilian painting embraced all contemporary
forms of expression.
In Mexico the generation of artists who came after Rufino
Tamayowho was responsible for the break with revolu¬
tionary muralismare those who have incorporated the new
trends into their painting. The breakthrough was made in the
1950s by a group of young artists including Manuel
Felguérez, Vicente Rojo, Pedro Coronel, Lilia Carrillo,
Alberto Gironella, Vlady and José Luis Cuevas, who
welcomed the foreign ideas. Gifted and receptive, they
followed a variety of paths, introducing a range of concepts
which now form the basis of Mexican art.
From an early stage José Luis Cuevas displayed an incisive
mastery, free of illusions, in the portrayal of an entire series
JESUS SOTO (1923- ).
Vibration (the swimming-pool).
Wood and plastic, 1962.
The Venezuelan artist Jesús
Soto maintains that true
abstraction can only be achiev¬
ed through movement not
mechanical movement but the
potential movement created by
the observer when he moves,
the vibration created by the
repetition of shapes, the super¬
position of geometrical objects
on a striated background, the
reverberation of two moiré
screens. Soto's aim is to free
himself completely from the
restraints of figurative art.
CARLOS CRUZ-DIEZ (1923- ).
Fisiochromia. Mixed technique,
1967.
With his "Fisiochromia", the
Venezuelan artist Carlos Cruz-
Diez reveals his "additive col¬
our" theory. Using fine
transparent or opaque strips at
regular intervals, he uses red,
green, black and white, causing
an interaction between these
colours which act on the
observer's retina creating the
full range of the chromatic spec¬
trum. A combination of the
movement of light and of the
observer provides an infinite
' variety of effects.
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
i JULIO LE PARC (1928- ). Knocking the
Establishment. Tumbler-dolls, 1968.
Founded in Paris in 1960, the "Visual Arts
"Research" group uses optical and kinetic ef¬
fects to induce observer participation. The
Argentine artist Julio Le Parc gives the added
incentive of a game-playing element,
sometimes using figurative ¡mages. Here the
observer is invited to knock down people from
the establishment, presented in the form of
tumbler-dolls.
DE SZYSZLO (1925- ).
House No.8. Engraving, 1975.
"Indigenism" (the integration of indigenous
culture) is a growing trend in the Andean
region. Initiated in Peru by José Sabogal and
Julia Codesido, it has evolved with Szyszlo in¬
to what might be termed "abstract in¬
digenism". His work, which draws its inspira¬
tion from literature, aims to recover and revive
traditional myths or, if necessary, invent
them.
JUAN CARLOS LANGLOIS ( 1926- ).
Miguel Angel Asturias. Indian ink on paper,
1981, in the Homage series.
Leopold Sédar Senghor described the work
of the Argentine artist Juan Carlos Langlois as
"painting-poetry", and pointed out its resem¬
blance to Chinese and pre-Columbian art.
Langlois' art is an art of metamorphosis, of the
reduction of the ¡mage to its basic elements
which, in the case of Latin America, are essen¬
tially, "bone, root and cloud".
ARMANDO MORALES (1927- ).
Two Figures. Oil on canvas, 1 970.
The Nicaraguan painter, engraver and car¬
toonist Armando Morales has lived in New
York for many years. He has alternated bet¬
ween figurative and abstract work; in his
latest stage which has most enhanced his
name as a painter his work has taken a
"metaphysical" or "visionary" turn with
representations of large figures, generally of
female nudes, against dark backgrounds or
dark blue skies with cotton-wool clouds.
44
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
. ENRIQUE ZANARTU (1920- ).
The Beachcomber. Oil on canvas, c.1962.
The Chilean Enrique Zañartu is a surrealist
rather than an abstract painter since the
figures that fill his canvases are symbols. He
makes play of ambiguity in that shapes are
people and splashes of colour or shading in¬
dicate the landscape. He juggles with the logic
of the "real" and the logic of "form". Like the
"Beachcomber" pacing the shore, all is
illusion.
, FERNANDO BOTERO (1932- ).
The Horseman. Bronze, 1981-1982.
By drawing on the heritage of popular art
and devoting his work to the study of daily life,
the Colombian artist Fernando Botero has
established his own distinctive identity of
style. Botero's world is an impressive, more
than life-size world. Everything is large-scale,
from his view of the history of art to the
tablecloths and watermelons of his still-lifes.
With his "over-sized images he has taken
possession of the world and made it
Colombian".
t- of tragi-comical characters. The penetrating, sarcastic sen¬
sitivity of his pen, pencil and ink rapidly placed him in the
front rank of his generation. Shortly afterwards some evolv¬
ed towards geometricism. Outstanding amongst them is
Manuel Felguérez. His sound theoretical basis, technical
precision and advanced investigations he is at present
working with computersplace this extremely sensitive ar¬
tist amongst the most important of his generation in Latin
America.
Others, such as Francisco Toledo and Alberto Gironella
are, to quote the historian and critic Jorge Alberto Manri¬
que, "establishing a special relationship with objects and the
living world that is both critical and oneiric". Although they
do not possess the instantaneous permeability of the Argen¬
tine artists, the young Mexicans have a capacity for selective
.assimilation and are capable of achieving a high degree of
maturity. They, too, occupy an outstanding place in Latin
American painting.
The generation immediately following that of Roberto
Matta in Chile includes two outstanding artists, Nemesio
Antuñez, who in recent years has been expressing on canvas
his concern for anonymous humanity, and Enrique Zañartu,
whose work is an investigation of the deeper, darker
realities.
The founder and most distinguished representative of con¬
temporary painting in Colombia is Alejandro Obregón. His
work draws its sustenance from the very sap of the Latin
American tropics. It radiates energy and creates its own
myths and images. Fernando Botero, who is internationally
known for his stylistic concept of the circular form carried
to the utmost extremes, is a complex artist. He is both a
realist and a satirist. He takes an ironic delight in reality,
which he magnifies for sarcastic purposes. He is more subtle
and ambiguous than the satisfied collectors of his works are
aware. The elegance, compassion, not to say tenderness, of
his images are only lightly suggested in the fullness of his
forms. The most recent Colombian painting reflects the
wealth of talent and variety of ideas to be found in the new
generation.
One of the most surprising developments in terms of scope
and quality is that recently achieved by painting in Bolivia.
The. pioneers of contemporary painting in that country in-^
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
Argentina
Aizenberg, Roberto
Bonevardi, Marcelo
Chab, Víctor
Kemble, Kenneth
Krasno, Rodolfo
Ocampo, Miguel
Peluffo, Marta
Pucciarelli
Sobrino, Francisco
Testa, Clorindo
Tomasello, Luis
Bolivia
Baptista, Carmen
da Silva, Alfredo
Ugalde, Gastón
Valcárcel, Roberto
Brazil
Amaral, Antonio Henrique
Dacosta, Milton
Djanira
Netto, Gontran
Piza, Arthur Luiz
dos Prazeres, Heitor
For readers' further information we list below the names of some
contemporary Latin American artists whose works, to our great
regret, we have been unable to discuss in this issue; the list, of
course, is not exhaustive.
de Resende Carvalho, Flavio
da Veiga Guinard, Alberto
Volpi, Alfredo
Chile
Balmes, José
Bonati, Eduardo
Bru, Roser
Cienfuegos, Gonzalo
Dávila, Juan D.
Dittborn, Eugenio
Irarrázaval, Pedro
Lira, Benjamín
Núñez, Guillermo
Opazo, Rodolfo
Téllez, Eugenio
Toral, Mario
Colombia
Cárdenas, Juan
Cárdenas, Santiago
Coronel, Cecilia
Grau, Enrique
Hernández, Manuel
Rayo, Ornar
Rojas Herazo, Héctor
del Villar, Hernando
Costa Rica
Carballo, Fernando
Cuba
Bermúdez, Cundo
Carreño, Mario
Herrera Zapata, Julio
Martínez, Raúl
Rodríguez, Mariano
Dominican Republic
Cestero, José
Ecuador
Almeida, Gilberto
Aráuz, Carlos
Bueno, Mauricio
Cifuentes, Hugo
Jácome, Ramiro
Molinarí, Luis
Pavón, Germán
Ricaurte, León
Svistoonoff, Nicolás
El Salvador
Solís, Armando
Guatemala
Aldana, Díaz
Cabrera, Roberto
Reciño
Rojas, Elmer
Honduras
Ruiz Matute, M.A.
Mexico
Coronel, Pedro
Coronel, Rafael
Corzas, Francisco
Martínez, Ricardo
Nissen, Brian
Rubalcava, Cristina
Reyes, Aurora
Van Gunten, Roger
Panama
Alvarado, Antonio
Dutary, Alberto
Paraguay
Careaga, Enrique
Colombino, Carlos
Rolandi, Carlos
Peru
Braun, Herman
Tsuchiya, Tilsa
Uruguay
Broglia, Enrique
Cabrera, Germán
Solari, Luis Antonio
Venezuela
Borges, Jacobo
Carreño, Omar
Colmenares, Asdrúbal
Guinand, Edgard
Hung, Francisco
Hurtado, Angel
Lucena, Victor
Manaure, Mateo
Navarro, Pascual
Otero, Alejandro
Palacios, Alirio
Poleo, Héctor
Quilici, Pancho
Sánchez, Edgar
Valera, Víctor
^ elude artists like Maria Luisa Pacheco, who preserves her in¬
ner Andean soul in abstract form in New York, and Gil Im¬
ana. Amongst the uncompromising cultivators of abstrac¬
tion, mention should be made of Alfredo La Placa, Alfredo
Da Silva and Maria Esther Ballivian. Enrique Arnal is the
most gifted and brilliant. Social protest, the quest for pic¬
torial quality for its own sake, abstract landscape and in-
timism also have their adeptsValcárcel, Herminio Forno,
Inés Córdoba, Gustavo Madeiros, Chela Rodó, among
others. New generations of artists are emerging not only in
La Paz but also in other parts of the country.
The early success of the Guatemalan artist Rodolfo
Abularach has recently been confirmed at the Latin
American and international levels. He is extraordinarily
talented and prolific. His search for a style and his incursion
into pre-Columbian art in the manner of Rufino Tamayo
and Mérida came to an end during his stay in New York at
the beginning of the 1960s.
The Nicaraguan Armando Morales is one of the foremost
Latin American painters. Born in 1927 and therefore formed
amongst the trends and "isms" of contemporary art, he
reflects in his work a resolute independence of expression,
uninfluenced by any avant-garde trends and indifferent to
fashion. Nevertheless his work is fully contemporary and
purely pictorial.
The predominance of trends which originated in the world
centres of Western art has led some critics to deny the ex¬
istence of Latin American painting in the strict sense. I
believe on the contrary that the use of an international
system does not necessarily exclude creative originality
which in the case of Latin America is essentially hybrid. But
what, then, is the position, the contribution, the
distinguishing feature, of Latin American painting?
When trying to answer this question one must above all
avoid making false dogmatic statements of the kind one still
currently hears, and be prepared to accept a pluralistic reply
corresponding to the cultural reality of Latin America. Like
the vast region extending from Mexico to Cape Horn, this
plurality must perforce include elements that are
recognizable as specific or significant. Some of our art
critics, and some prejudiced, naive people abroad, would at¬
tribute those elements exclusively to original or indigenous
values. In fact they should be attributed to all those values
resulting from international exchanges which have taken
root in our soil. Hybridization is Latin America's vocation,
and no living language is foreign to it.
Carlos Rodriguez Saavedra
«to
Sir
z9
cc1-
_Z
O (T
Ol
. U
tO LU
te ce
P
3Z
go
it
0; to
S°
OC Q.
QO
ecu
<o
at¬
oo
CCI
m q.
Editorial. Sales and Distribution Offices:
Unesco, 7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 58 French francs. 2 years (valid only in
France): 100 French francs. Binder for a year's issues:
46 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering pos¬
tage. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions and
headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boun¬
daries on maps published in the magazine do not imply offi¬
cial endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the United
Nations.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm and/or
microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor.
Michigan 48100. U.S.A.: (2) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian
Head. Inc.. 1 1 1 West 40th Street. New York. U.S.A.: (3) Bell
and Howell Co.. Old Mansfield Road. Wooster, Ohio 44691,
U.S.A.
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
French: Alain Lévêque (Paris)
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov (Paris)
Arabic: Sayed Osman (Paris)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Rajmani Tiwari (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Brotdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: Hossein Razmdjou (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salam)
Braille: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Vitomir Sudarski (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Servat
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Special projects: Peggy Julien
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
46
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Where to renew your
	 subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller
or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors
in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Colling-
wood Victoria 3066; Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd.
P.O. Box 33, Brookvale, 2100, NSW, Periodicals: Dominie Pty.
Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-
agent: United Nations Association of Australia, P.O. Box 1 75,
5th floor. Ana House, 28 Elizabeth Street, Melbourne Victoria
3000.
AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31, A- 1011,
Vienna.
BAHAMAS. Nassau Stationers Ltd., P.O. Box N-3138, Nassau.
BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International Ltd., Ittefaq
Building, 1, R K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3. -
BARBADOS. University of the West Indies Bookshop, Cave Hill
Campus, P.O. Box 64, Bridgetown.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V.
Handelmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 218, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13.
BOTSWANA. Botswana Book Centre, P.O. Box 91, Gaborone.
BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552 Merchant Street,
Rangoon.
CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street
West, Montreal, Que. H3H 1M7.
CHAD. Librairie Abssounout, 24 av, Charles de Gaulle, B.P. 388,
N'Djamena.
CHINA. China National Publications Import and Export
Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Beijing.
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makartos 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box
1722, Nicosia.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena 51, Prague 1
(Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura, 11 Soukemcka, Prague
1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers, Hurbanovo nam.
6,893 31 Bratislava - CSSR.
DENMARK. Munksgaard Export and Subscription Service, 35
Norre Sogade, DK 1370, Copenhagen K.
EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF». National Centre for Unesco
Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo.
ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis
Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100
Helsinki 10; Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, Koivuvaarankuja 2,
01640 Vantaa 64.
FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700
Paris, CCP. 12598-48.
GABON. Librairie Hachette, B.P. 3923, Libreville.
GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach
140, 710 Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the
G.D.R.
FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier (German,
English, French and Spanish editions): Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher
Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57, D5300 Bonn 3. For
other Unesco publications: Karger Verlag, Germering/Munchen.
For scientific maps only: Geo Center, Postfach 800830,
Stuttgart 80.
GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195,
Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The
University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop
of Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1,
Legon.
GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
HONG KONG. Federal Publications (HK> Ltd., 5A Evergreen
Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book
Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon. Hong Kong Government
Information Services, Publication Centre, Baskerville House, 22
Ice Street.
HUNGARY. Akademiai Könyvesbolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V;
A.K.V. Konyvtürosok Boltja, Népkóztársaság utja 16, Budapest
VI.
ICELAND. Snaebjörn Jonsson & Co., H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9,
Reykjavik.
INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate,
Bombay 400038; 1 7 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a,
Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; 5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh,
Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road, Banga-
lore-560001 ; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad- 50000 1 . Sub-
Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co. 1 7 Park Street, Calcutta
70016; Scindia House, New Delhi; Publication Unit, Ministry of
Education and Culture, Ex. AFO Hutments. Dr. Rajendra Prasad
Road, New Delhi 110001.
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl. Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Indira P. T., Jl Dr Sam Ratulangie 37,
Jakarta Pusat.
IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co., 28, Vessal
Shirazi Street, Enghélab Avenue. P.O. Box 314/1486, Teheran;
Iranian Nat. Comm, for Unesco. Seyed Jamal Eddin Assad Abadi
Avenue 64th Street, Bonyad Building P.O. Box 1533, Teheran.
IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, AI Rashid Street, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd, Ballymount
Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12; Tycooly International Publ. Ltd 6
Crofton Terrace, Dun Laoghaire Co., Dublin.
ISRAEL. A.B.C. Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby
Road, Tel Aviv 61000.
ITALY. Licosa (Librería Commissionaria Sansoni, S.p.A.) Via
Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552, 50121 Florence.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101
Water Lane, Kingston. University of the West Indies Bookshop,
Mona, Kingston.
JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo 3-chome
Bunkyo-ku Tokyo 1 13.
KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O. Box 30571,
Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box
Central 64, Seoul.
KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait;
for the Unesco Courier; Farafalla Press Agency, P.O. Box SAFA
4541, Kuwait.
LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod. Lesotho,
Southern Africa.
LIBERIA. Code and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286,
Monrovia.
LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication & Distribution,
P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue,
Luxembourg.
MALAWI. Malawi Book Service, Head Office, P.O. Box 30044
Chichiri, Blantyre 3.
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Cooperative Bookshop, Kuala
Lumpur 22-11.
MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta.
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-
Louis.
MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo.
NEPAL. Sajha Prakashan Polchowk, Kathmandu.
NETHERLANDS. KEESING BOEKEN B.V., Joan Muyskenweg,
22, Postbus 1118, 1 000 BC Amsterdam.
NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O. Box
200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A.
NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, Government
Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 130,
Oxford Terrace. P.O. Box 1721 Chnstchurch; Alma Street, P.O.
Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1 104, Dunedin,
Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington.
NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The University
Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka; The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zaria.
NORWAY. All publications: Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers),
Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1; Universitets Bokhandelen, .
Universitetssentret, P.O.B. 307 Blindem, Oslo 3. For Unesco
Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O.
Box No. 729, Lahore 3.
PHILIPPINES. The Modern Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O.
Box 632, Manila D-404.
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068 WARSAW.
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livraria Portugal, rua do
Carmo 70, Lisbon.
SEYCHELLES. National Bookshop, P.O. Box 48, Mahé; New
Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé.
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown.
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (S) Pte Ltd. Times Jurong, 2
Jurong Port Road, Singapore 2261 .
SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and
General, P.O. Box 951, Mogadiscio.
SOUTH AFRICA. For the Unesco Courier (single copies) only;
Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.
SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam
Gardiner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2.
SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum.
SWEDEN. All publications A/B.C.E. Fritzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356. 10327
Stockholm 1 6. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN Förbundet,
Skolgrand 2, Box 1 50 50 S- 1 04 65, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag. 5 Rámistrasse.
Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 1 1, CCP.
12-236. Librairies Payot also in Lausanne, Basle, Berne, Vevey,
Montreux, Neuchàtel and Zurich.
TANZANIA. Dares Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-
Salaam.
THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road,
Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P O. Box 402; Bangkok: Suksapan Panit,
Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam
Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok.
TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco,
18 Alexandra Street, St, Clair, Trinidad, W.I.
TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S., Istiklâl Caddesi, N" 469, Posta
Kutusu 219, Beyoglu, Istambul.
UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 7145, Kampala.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, H.M. S.O., P.O.
Box 276, London, SW8 5DT, and Govt. Bookshops in London.
Edinburgh, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol; for
scientific maps only: McCarta Ltd., 1 22 King's Cross Road,
London WC IX 9 DS.
UNITED STATES. Unipub, 205 East 42nd Street, New York,
N.Y. 1001 7. Orders for books & Periodicals: Box 433, Murray
Hill Station, New York, N.Y. 10157.
U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Moscow, G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost, Mica 30/1 1, Zagreb; Cankarjeva
Zalozba. Zopitarjeva 2, Lubljana; Nolit, Terazige 27/11, Belgrade.
ZAMBIA. National Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd.,
P.O. Box 2664 Lusaka.
ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union Avenue,
Harare.
CÉSAR FERNÁNDEZ MORENO AND
JULIO ORTEGA. EDITORS
IVAN A. SCHULMAN^ EDITOR
ENGLISH-LANGUAGE EDITION
LATIN AMERICA IN ITS CULTURE, VOLUME I
Holmes & Meier Publishers, Inc., of New York
and London, have published an English-
language edition of América Latina en su
Cultura, a survey of the cultures of Latin
America in their literary and artistic expression,
originally published in Spanish by Unesco. Four
volumes deal, respectively, with art, architecture,
literature and music, each surveying the rich con¬
temporary culture of Latin America. The con¬
tributors, including outstanding Latin American
critics, analyse the current state of the arts in
their fields.
Latin America in its Literature, edited by C"csa:
Fernández Moreno.
Latin America in its Architecture, edited by
Roberto Segré.
Latin America in its Art, edited by Damián
Bayón (Forthcoming).
Latin America in its Music, edited by Isabel
Aretz (Forthcoming).
Damián
Bayón
Paolo
Gasparini
The changing
shape of
Latin American
architecture
Brings together a series of ten interviews with im¬
portant architects from ten different Latin
American countries which were recorded by Da¬
mián Bayón, and over 200 photographs taken
specifically for the book by Paolo Gasparini.
Produced under the auspices of Unesco, and
originally published in Spanish in collaboration
with Unesco, the English-language edition is
published by John Wiley & Sons Ltd.
These publications are available through book trade
channels throughout the world. Please note, however,
that they are not stocked or sold by The Unesco Press.
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
«i à »
<» $ * »
«Î. ft*
ZZ * *s » *».».«*. v *
"» /» ^ d a . » ft
¿
è i 4 o ., #0« A3
** ** * . r*e *
»Ä f\ -s s
£ c e ,,/
'd> d)3» N
A 9b A O T .':
9 I
1 #
9 v ' *
s*4##¿
-¿.re
With a conception of painting that is neither academic nor
avant-garde, their choice of themes drawn from daily life,
and because they are generally self-taught and there is a cer¬
tain superficial ingenuousness in the execution of their paint¬
ings, contemporary Latin American artists have often found
their works classified as "naive" art. In spite of their
originality and intrinsic value and their relatively recent ap¬
pearance in private art collections, their paintings are rarely
handled by the major art dealers, but are to be found on sale
in market-places and on the street. Above, Brazilian cotton
plantation scene (1973) by Neuza Leodora.
]]>
</page>
</document>
