<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074687eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
BOROBUDl
Rescued a masterpiece of the world heritage
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A time to live...
© ALGERIA Market day in the Mzab
The Mzab region of Algeria is a rocky Saharan plateau etched with deep ravines. In the history of Islam it is known as the
place where the "Mzabites" or "Mozabites", heterodox Berbers belonging to the Ibadite sect, settled in the 11th century.
The Mozabites became established in the towns of Algeria where they exercised a virtual monopoly over trade in such pro¬
ducts as spices, fabrics, carpets, and meat especially mutton, a favourite dish in Arab countries. The chief town of the
Mzab, Ghardaia, is noted for its picturesque architecture and as a date-producing centre. Above, market scene at Ghardaia.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
FEBRUARY 1983 36th YEAR
Published in 26 languages
English Tamil Korean
French Hebrew Swahili
Spanish Persian Croato-Serb
Russian Dutch Macedonian
German Portuguese Serbo-Croat
Arabic Turkish Slovene
Japanese Urdu Chinese
Italian Catalan Bulgarian
Hindi Malaysian
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French and Spanish
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 58 French Francs
Binder for a year's issues: 46 FF
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
ISSN 0304 - 3118 '
No. 2 - 1983 - OPI - 83-1 - 395 A
page
4 BOLIVAR THE LIBERATOR (1783-1830)
Undimmed by time, a bright vision of a New World
by Arturo Uslar-Pietri
7 FROM JACMEL TO SANTA MARTA
by René Depestre
8 BOROBUDUR
Indonesia's Buddhist sanctuary a sermon in stone
by R. Soekmono
1 6 HOW BOROBUDUR WAS SAVED
by R. Soekmono and Caesar Voûte
1 7 FROM REDISCOVERY TO RESTORATION
24 TASHKENT
The capital of Uzbekistan celebrates
its two thousandth anniversary
by Erkin Yussupov
27 A GOLDEN TREASURY OF MANUSCRIPTS
by Muzaffar Khayrullaev
30 CULTURE IN A COLD CLIMATE
The reindeer herdsmen of Lapland
by Pekka Aikio
34 A STRATEGY FOR DISARMAMENT
by Constantin Ene
38
2
UNESCO NEWSROOM
A TIME TO LIVE	
ALGERIA: Market day in the Mzab
A man who wrote a chapter of
/I world history, a monument
jCjL without parallel in the world,
the cultural treasures of an ancient
city, a community in search of its
cultural identity, the quest for
peace these apparently disparate
subjects, which make up the content
ofthis issue of the Unesco Courier, all
form part of the common heritage of
mankind that Unesco is pledged to
preserve and defend.
The bicentenary of the birth of
Simón Bolivar, the great Latin
American liberator and the visionary
whose noble ambition it was to unify
a continent, is celebrated in prose and
verse by A rturo Uslar-Pietri and René
Depestre. '
Drs. Soekmono and Voûte, respec¬
tively Director and former Unesco
Co-ordinator of the Borobudur resto
ration project, trace the history of the
thousand-year-old Buddhist sanc¬
tuary of Chandi Borobudur and tell
how, after centuries of neglect and
abandon, this monument to human
genius has been savedfor posterity by
a combination of Indonesian pride
and perseverance and an effort of in¬
ternational co-operation and solidari¬
ty inspired by Unesco.
Erkin Yussupov describes how, over
its two thousand years of existence,
the "stone village" of Tashkent has
grown to become the capital of the
Uzbek Soviet Socialist Republic and
the fourth largest city of the USSR.
One of the cultural cross-roads of
central Asia, Tashkent houses a
magnificent collection of ancient
manuscripts which, as Muzaffar
Khayrullaev, Director of the Al-Biruni
Institute of Oriental Studies tells us,
bear witness to the interpénétration of
philosophical and scientific thought
and aesthetic and moral values ofcen¬
tral Asia over the centuries.
Thousands of kilometres away, in
the Arctic Circle, live the Laplanders
ofFinnoscandinavia, a people united
by a common language and a life based
on the herding of reindeer. Pekka
Aikio describes how the Laplanders
are affirming their cultural identity
and their right to maintain their age-
old way of life.
Finally, Constantin Ene explores
the complex problems of disarma¬
ment and proposes a number of ways
in which the cause of peace, vital to
human survival, can be advanced.
Cover: Buddha framed by stupas, Borobudur
Photo Michelangelo Durazzo '< ' ANA, Pans
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
BOLIVAR
THE LIBERATOR (1783-1830)
Undimmed by time, a bright
vision of a New World
by Arturo Uslar-Pietri
TWO hundred years after his
birth, Bolivar undoubtedly re¬
mains one of that tiny but
distinguished group of people who have
had something to teach mankind. He
died in 1830, but the sheer magnitude of
his personality is still being revealed to us
and still has the power to move us. In the
eyes of his contemporaries, he was the
outstanding leader of the struggle for the
political independence of Latin America,
a charismatic figure who, virtually
without resources, managed to overcome
all manner of obstacles and setbacks in
directing and sustaining the long-drawn-
out and difficult fifteen-year offensive
which was to put an end to Spanish domi¬
nion over America. His unyielding
tenacity, his conviction that in¬
dependence could and should come
about in his own lifetime and his far-
reaching vision of the future of the New
World, all set him apart from the many
other exceptional leaders who emerged
during the war for the emancipation of
the continent.
For the Western world, he soon
became the symbol of the struggle against
despotism and the old monarchies. His
name was synonymous with freedom.
The revolutionaries of 1 830 and 1 848 , the
"Carbonari", the liberals, the young
Romantics all looked to him and his ex¬
ample. He was the hero who had pitted
himself against three hundred years of
ARTURO USLAR-PIETRI, noted Venezuelan
writer and his country's former ambassador and
permanent delegate to Unesco, is the author of
many novels, short stories, and essays such as La
Otra América (The Other America). The text
published here is the introduction to a forth¬
coming anthology of the writings ofSimón Bolí¬
var which Unesco is publishing in Spanish and in
six other language versions.
Right, map of South America before Bolivar's time. In
1819 the Liberator constituted the Republic of Great Col¬
ombia (inset) from the independent territories of
Venezuela, New Granada (present-day Colombia) and
the présidence of Quito (today Ecuador). This was the
first step towards the fulfilment of his dream of unifying
all the countries of what is now Latin America. Later, in
1825, when Upper Peru became independent of Spain
and chose to be called Bolivia after the Liberator, it tried
to merge with Peru. However, the federation of States
envisioned by Bolivar broke up definitively in 1830. Op¬
posite page, the Liberator as depicted by artists from the
five countries whose destiny he shaped.
4
the old régime in Spanish America, had
succeeded in bringing it to an end, and
had proclaimed a new order of
democracy and freedom in its stead. His
admirers ranged from the restless young
people in the Paris of the Bourbons, who
sported the "Bolivar hat" as though it
were a battle standard, to students of
world politics and to Byron, who gave
Bolivar's name to the boat on which he
dreamed of bringing freedom to Greece.
Bolivar had become the eternal
"Liberator", the man who had per
sonified a continent's determination to
be free and who had striven to establish a
political order founded on justice and the
rights of the individual.
There can be no doubt that, as a
military leader, he won significant vic¬
tories against all the odds. He sowed the
seeds of destiny, in that nations were
born of the battles he waged, and he
secured freedom for vast numbers of
people and an enormous Iandmass. In
1825, when his triumph at Ayacucho put
an end to the Spanish Empire and made
^.^AMERIOUg
yMÉnWIONALE Y'
I AUWBOLIVAm
3i/pr.t / Alimy it H. Ö.-XK- I8Í5
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
him the arbiter of the destinies of Latin
America, he conceived and attempted to
give substance to the grandiose plan of
uniting America as he saw it, in a bid to
bring about a new age of stability and
justice for mankind. Indeed, his disagree¬
ment with his former followers and the
growing difficulties he had to contend
with stemmed from his vision of the
future.
For him, independence was not so
much an end in itself as a necessary step
along the road to a more difficult but
much more ambitious project. His aim
was not merely to replace one set of men
by another, to put Creole leaders in the
seats vacated by the Spanish viceroys and
governors and thereby perpetuate the
political and social patterns inherited
from the colonial past. He wanted
something totally different: literally to
create a powerful and free New World,
setting an example through its institu¬
tions, intent on dispensing justice in all its
forms, and laying the foundations for a
new global order which Bolivar himself
spoke of as a "new equilibrium for the
universe".
Right from the start, Bolivar was
distinguished for the clarity and boldness
of his thinking. Had he done no more
than commit to paper the ideas and
judgements on the American world
which he bequeathed to us, he would still
be considered one of the most original
thinkers of his time. Moreover, he was an
outstanding stylist and his letters and
speeches are among the best prose
writings of the period. No-one could
equal his gift for expressing himself in
terms that were robust and penetrating
Map United Nations
The boundaries on this map do not im¬
ply official endorsement or accep¬
tance by Unesco or the United
Nations
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
and charged with significance. His
language faithfully reflected his tempera¬
ment and his deep anxieties. He was a
master of concision and of striking
similes. His words were as good as his
deeds.
There have been few other figures in
history who combined as he did the gifts
and qualities of a man of action and those
of a thinker, of those who were leaders of
men and also visionaries, whose political
acumen did not prevent them from form¬
ing grand designs or from rising above
petty day-to-day concerns. His tragedy
was his inability to ensure that his vision
of the future would come true. He could
not rest content with the extraordinary
task he had accomplished, since he con¬
sidered it merely as the necessary prelude
to the new political organization of Latin
America and a new world equilibrium.
Only a person of his quality could have
regarded the second stage as being more
important than the first.
Bolivar is a figure of infinite variety. If
we see him as being no more than the
leader of a highly successful insurrection,
we obliterate one whole side of his per¬
sonality and overlook some of the most
interesting and admirable aspects of his
achievement. He was never just a man of
action, perpetually engaged in a struggle
that must often have seemed hopeless;
nor was he an ideologist unimaginatively
applying doctrines and examples culled
from other countries and other historical
situations.
What is more, he was not just a politi¬
cian bogged down in the immediate pre¬
sent. A study of his life leaves us con¬
stantly amazed at the profusion and
variety of talents he displays. In his eyes,
the past of the Latin American peoples
was as alive as their present. He identified
himself totally with the historical and
cultural predicament of his fellow
Americans, and yet at the same time he
could look forward to the future as he
wished to see it and could work for a far-
reaching transformation of society and
its goals. He was not blinded by the
various brilliant political theories of his
day. He had carefully scrutinized the
ideas of Rousseau and Montesquieu,
comparing them with his own experience
in the struggle and with the lessons of the
American past.
His conclusion was that the future of
the American peoples did not lie in mere¬
ly imitating or adapting the ideas and in¬
stitutions of other nations born of differ¬
ing historical and cultural circumstances;
in his opinion, only the facts, however in¬
tractable, could be the starting point for
the determined and clear-sighted effort
needed, since the colonial past had in no
way prepared those peoples for their dif¬
ficult metamorphosis.
One fundamental theme of Bolivar's
ideas on nation-building was what we, in
present-day international parlance,
would call the cultural constraints on
development and the difficulty of adap¬
ting foreign models. He was forever aler¬
ting legislators dazzled as they were by
the examples of the institutions that
emerged from the revolutions irt the
United States and France to the impor-
6
tance of allowing for specific Hispano-
American practices, traditions and ex¬
periences of the past. He ardently desired
freedom, justice and democracy, but he
did not lose sight of the social and
political realities which three hundred
years of life under colonial rule had
created in the America he knew.
Nor did he lose sight of the interna¬
tional situation hovering on the horizon.
The independence of Latin America
could not be envisaged and achieved as if
it were an isolated local phenomenon: it
was a major upheaval establishing a new
situation and a new pattern of worldwide
relations. The sudden emergence of a free
and sovereign America would inevitably
produce significant changes in political
relationships all over the world. This was
the exceptionally wide-ranging context
within which Bolivar's action and think¬
ing evolved and which afforded him his
status and relevance as the guide of the
American peoples and the embodiment
of their spirit.
and wealth, he climbed the mountain of
silver that had been the symbol of col¬
onial authority, accompanied by the
representatives of Argentina, Peru and
Chile. As he took in the panorama
stretching out before him, as he felt and
expressed the compelling need for in¬
tegration as the only course capable of
securing the future of so vast a slice of
humanity and territory, he caught a
glimpse of the scenario of universal
history. It was at this time that he conven¬
ed the Panama Congress that was to
bring together representatives of the
whole of America in a bid to work out the
practical aspects of the continent's
policies, its self-defence and the joint ac¬
tion it would be required to take in its
dealings with the rest of the world.
We need only leaf through the main
documents in which his ideas are
assembled to realize that his conception
of the common destiny of Latin America
never changed. As early as 1812, in Car¬
tagena, when he had scarcely emerged
To commemorate the bicentenary of the
birth of "The Liberator" (1783-1830)
Unesco is to issue an official Simón
Bolívar medal. Designed by the
Venezuelan artist Hector Poleo and
engraved by Denis Châtelain, the medal
will be struck by the Paris Mint. On its
obverse the medal bears a profile portrait
of Bolivar, while the reverse depicts a
symbolic sun rising over a Latin America
in the process of unification, with the
dove of peace taking wing.
This, moreover, is an attitude that
prevailed throughout his life and in all his
writings. From the outset, his vision of
independence embraced the whole conti¬
nent and, in this respect, he was at one
with his celebrated predecessor Francisco
Miranda. The issue as they both saw it
was not to win independence for a few
portions of the Spanish Empire but to en¬
sure that the whole territory it covered
would become conscious of its identity
and destiny, and would attain full
sovereignty. This accordingly implied a
form of political organization and the
adoption of goals that would encompass
the entire New World. From the very
beginning, he spoke in the name of
America rather than of Venezuela, and
was not afraid to suggest ways in which
political integration could come about.
As he said on several occasions,
"America is our homeland".
The question now is what he meant by
America and what form of integration he
had in mind. His scheme of things did not
rule out any significant part of the
America that had been subjugated by the
European powers. He started with the
peoples of Venezuela, New Granada and
Ecuador which were close at hand and
were subsequently to combine to form
Colombia, but he went on to include all
parts of the Empire in successive designs
for co-operation.
When, in 1825, after the final and
decisive victory at Ayacucho, he arrived
at Potosi, that magical centre of power
from the ruins of the first attempt he
made to set up an independent republic in
Venezuela, he issued a bold manifesto
sounding the alarm against the mistaken
belief that any part of America could
achieve and preserve its independence in
isolation. As long as Venezuela was not
liberated, the independence of New
Granada would be threatened, since an
expeditionary force organized from
Venezuela and setting out from the
"Provinces of Barinas and Maracaibo"
would be able to penetrate into "the fur¬
thest reaches of southern America".
Indeed, the huge efforts which he ex¬
pected on the part of the enemies of
freedom were exactly the same as those
he himself had to make throughout the
long hard years of his political and
military career. From then on, the whole
of Latin America became the theatre of
operations for a single combat, the strug¬
gle for independence, only to be achieved
by the integration of all its peoples in a
single body that would guarantee the uni¬
ty of its presence and action on the world
scene.
In the astonishing letter which he wrote
in Jamaica in 1815 to "a gentleman of
that island", he painted the most detailed
and challenging picture of his vision of
the American destiny. His theme was not
Venezuela but rather "a vast, varied and
unknown country, the New World". He
looked upon it as a fact of history and
geography, asking impatiently whether
the entire New World was not mobilized
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
and armed to defend itself, and adding:
"On this battlefield, some 2,000 leagues
long and 900 leagues wide at its extremes,
sixteen million Americans are either
defending their rights or are being
oppressed".
In his view, an unavoidable historical
phenomenon had occurred, one that was
bound to have far-reaching consequences
for the world. It was here that he express¬
ed the gist of his thinking: the projected
independence of America was a necessary
goal "because world equilibrium
demanded it".
This, then, represented his fundamen¬
tal view of things. The time had come to
strike a new universal balance. The pat¬
tern of imperial domination could not
continue. In the words used by Virgil in
his prophetic Eclogue, a new order was to
come to pass. The Spanish Empire had to
be brought to an end so that an authentic
New World could come into being and
engage in a dialogue on fair and just
terms with the other powers of the earth.
For Bolivar, the term "New World"
did not have the restricted connotations
earlier historians had given it. He did not
conceive of it merely as a recent adjunct
to an old world and an old order but as a
heaven-sent opportunity of creating a
new society that would not repeat the
mistakes of the old world and would
usher in a new era in relations between all
nations.
Bolivar thus became the prophet not
only of the New World but of a new
world order. Henceforward, he sensed
and made it plain that the time was ripe
for the emergence of new and indepen¬
dent nations and also that the very ex¬
istence of such nations would dictate the
setting-up of a new pattern of relation¬
ships. Using words that would be equally
relevant to the struggle currently being
waged by the new nations of Latin
America, Asia and Africa to bring about
a new order of relations, to the dramatic
dialogue going on between North and
South, or to the far-reaching process of
the emergence of the Third World,
Bolivar said: "There is another balanced
order of importance to us, and this is the
equilibrium of the universe. This struggle
cannot be partial for its outcome will af¬
fect vast interests scattered all over the
world".
How topical and alive his words sound
today! Their subject is the key issue now
being feverishly debated in the leading in¬
ternational fora. Two hundred years
after his birth, Simón Bolívar is in the
front line of the fight for the establish¬
ment of a new international order.
Unesco formally acknowledged this
when, in 1978, its governing bodies ap¬
proved the creation of the International
Simón Bolívar Prize "to be awarded
every second year, starting on 24 July
1983, the bicentenary of the birth of
Simón Bolívar, to those who have made
an outstanding contribution to the
freedom, independence and dignity of
peoples and to the strengthening of
solidarity among nations, or who have
fostered their development or facilitated
the quest for a new international
economic, social and cultural order".
Arturo Uslar-Pietri
Bolivar in the rock
of Santa Marta*
/ rose early to sing you
in the path where your good news
precedes all our dreams. From son to son
of the Caribbean I dance your ideas.
Supported by your roots my steps
feel the pulsation of the fate of men:
Help! Simón Bolívar, help!
Captain, times are bad!
The world needs your health,
The planet is losing the life ofyour roots
like a young queen her hair!
I seek you in the rock of Santa Marta
Are you still a beguiler of shores?
Have you said the last word to the waves
of solitude that have withered our lands!
What of the morning star remains in you?
Where is the house you had at Jacmel?
How many times have they heralded in you
the myth of the genius burned alive at the stake
of his own legend? How many times
have they hailed the return in force of your life
in the seeds of nourishing maize?
Where shines your heritage as the father of bread
and the peace of women, father
of the house where we would live in peace
each people enlightening the other in a single universe?
We have lost treasures with your name
We have taken for life the word libertador
turning it into a maker offrontiers.
Where is the roofyou had at Rosario
on your creóle home of the Americas?
Where is the house of a single crystal
where you will enter as one leaves one's mother's womb?
Inventor of new seeds,
man of beginnings, prophet
of the guitar and cacao,
each day of sunshine is in danger,
each starry night brings to our doors
the nuclear shame which will extinguish life.
Bolivar knock at whatever number you please,
the door will open,, whatever the street,
you are welcome, they will not dare
to shatter the right of everyone to be a sun
if they know that the strong tenderness of a man
has come back to the house of human brothers.
Paris, December 1982 RENE DEPESTRE
* On 18 December 1816, Simón Bolivar embarkedfrom the Haitian port of Jacmel
for a campaign which would end with the liberation of Venezuela and several other
countries of Latin America. He died at Santa Maria on 17 December 1830.
RENE DEPESTRE, Haitian poet, essayist and novelist, is a member of the Unesco
secretariat. Among his works are Un Arc-en-ciel pour l'Occident Chrétien (pub¬
lished in English as A Rainbow for the Christian West, University ofMassachusetts
Press, 1977) and, more recently, Alleluia pour une Femme-Jardin and Bonjour et
Adieu à la Négritude. He has collaborated on a collective work produced by Unesco,
América Latina en sus Ideas (Latin America through its Ideas).
7
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
BOROBUDUR
- ' -
^p.
¡
~:
^-^^ i
j-
»
i
Ntf
-V*
.-
* "***
>
3$.
* ,1 . * -
&
^
^
0
*{flB^K * * "v-'s
* N t 1
¡efe
:S5> i ^Elb^P
V,;
- 5
i fr*.k ;
.'
:ê >
1 *
If- . M ¿1
« 4 ^ _^^_
m w
«i
*' ' ^
* *
Photo £) A.J Bernet Kempers, Arnhem, The N etherlands
RICH IMAGERY OF BUDDHIST COSMOLOGY ¡s displayed on Borobudur's
1.460 narrative bas-reliefs which, taken together, cover 1,900 square
metres. Detail above shows an incident from the story of prince Sudhana
and the nymph Manohara. While searching for the nymph near the capital
of her father the king, Sudhana meets girls bringing water to bathe her. To
announce his presence he drops a ring into one of the water vessels.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Indonesia's Buddhist sanctuary -
a sermon in stone
by R. Soekmono
In the centre of the Indonesian island of
Java, on a fertile plain bordered by rugged
mountains and volcanoes, stands the
magnificent Buddhist sanctuary of Chandi
Borobudur. With its stone terraces rising
skywards, wave upon wave, with its profu¬
sion of unique stone reliefs and statues of
the Buddha, capped by a great central
stupa, Borobudur has been called "the
vastest, oldest, and most beautiful monu¬
ment in the southern hemisphere". But for
centuries after it was built over a thousand
years ago, Borobudur was abandoned and
forgotten. When it was rediscovered in the
nineteenth century it was ravaged with
decay, and although a number of repairs
and holding operations were carried out, it
seemed doomed to eventual collapse. In the
years after Indonesia became independent,
the new nation made thepreservation of this
tangible evidence of its glorious past a
priority objective. Today, through a unique
combination of multidisciplinary technical
skills, Indonesian pride, and international
co-operation channelled through Unesco's
international campaign for Borobudur, this
great work ofhuman genius has been saved
for posterity. The finishing touches have
now been put to a vast archaeological rescue
operation which has taken ten years and has
involved the stone-by-stone dismantlement
and reconstitution of the square lower ter¬
races of the colossal edifice. Here,
Dr. Soekmono, of Indonesia, the Director
of the Borobudur Restoration Project,
traces the history of the monument and of¬
fers an interpretation of its significance;
in a second article Dr. Soekmono and Dr.
C. Voûte, Unesco Co-ordinator of the
Borobudur project 1971-75, describe the
threats to Borobudur and show how at¬
tempts to save it have finally been crowned
with success.
R. SOEKMONO, Indonesian archaeologist and
ancient historian, is director of the Borobudur restora¬
tion project. Professor ofarchaeology at the University
ofIndonesia, ofwhich he is also executive secretary, he
has published several studies on Borobudur, notably
Chandi Borobudur, A Monument of Mankind pub¬
lished in 1976 by Unesco and Van Gorcum, Assen/Ams¬
terdam, The Netherlands.
MANY theories have been advanced about the origin of
Borobudur, perhaps the most poetic being one claiming
that it originally represented a lotus flower floating on
the surface of a lake which once covered the surrounding plain, the
mythical lotus from which the future Buddha will be born.
No written documents about the construction of the monument
survive, but inscriptions point to the conclusion that it was pro¬
bably founded around the year 800 AD during the Golden Age of
the powerful Sailendra dynasty of Central Java.
Nor do we know with certainty how long Borobudur was in ac¬
tive use, or when it ceased to function as a monument to glorify the
greatness of the Sailendra kings and, at the same time as.a centre
of Buddhist pilgrimage.
The general assumption is that the Chandis (the name given to
monuments dating back to the ancient period of Indonesian
history) fell into disuse when people were converted to Islam in the
fifteenth century. However, it is quite possible that the monuments
in Central Java were abandoned as early as the tenth century, when
historical importance shifted from there to East Java.
Whatever the truth may have been, it was not until 1814 that
Chandi Borobudur emerged, actually and figuratively, from its
dark past. Java was then under British rule, and the representative
of the British Government, Sir Stamford Raffles, took a keen in¬
terest in the island's history. In 1814, when he was informed of the
existence of a huge monument called Chandi Borobudur, he sent
a Dutch engineer named Cornelius to investigate.
Cornelius hired some 200 villagers to fell trees, burn down
bushes and dig away the earth and rubbish in which the monument
had long been buried. The activities of Raffles and Cornelius
stimulated interest in Borobudur, and a later Dutch administrator
arranged for further removal of the debris so that by 1835 the en¬
tire edifice was freed from its last disfiguring cover.
The monument that stood revealed is a colossal stepped pyramid
consisting of nine superimposed terraces and crowned by a huge
bell-shaped stupa. It was built around and on top of a flattened
hill, of andésite, a porous, bluish-grey volcanic rock which had
been taken from nearby rivers. Laid without mortar, the stones
had been made to grip by means of dovetails in the horizontal con¬
nexions, and indentations in the vertical joints. This system allows
a certain flexibility, so that the monument can withstand slight
movements without an immediate danger of collapse.
The structural design is complicated, but a main vertical division
into three parts base, body, and top is evident. The base forms
a square with sides measuring some 120 metres, the total area thus
being slightly less than one and a half hectares.
The four-metre-high walls of the base are supported by a
foothold resembling a huge plinth, 1.5 metres high and 3 metres
across. In 1885, the Chairman of the Yogyakarta Archaeological
Society made the sensational discovery that these walls encased a
series of 160 carved reliefs, which became known as the monu¬
ment's "hidden foot". (A photographic record of the reliefs was
made in 1890-91, after which the "foot" was again hidden with the
original stones, except for the southeast corner.).
Some scholars have suggested that these reliefs had been
deliberately covered to conceal them from the eyes of pilgrims.
However, the use of 12, 750 cubic metres of stone to make the en¬
casement, and the sacrifice of architectural elements and reliefs,
seem to indicate that the soundness of the monument was at stake.
As a considerable part of the gradually mounting foundations of
the stepped pyramid had to rest on loose filled earth, sliding pro¬
bably took place. In other words, the encasing wall was a retaining
embankment thrown up to prevent further sliding and to avoid
worse disaster.
9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Unesco-Institut Géographique National, Pans
Aerial photos, above and top of page, show the basic architec¬
tural features of Borobudur, a stepped pyramid consisting of
nine superimposed terraces and crowned by a huge bell-shaped
Stupa 35 metres above the ground. Cross-section, right,
shows how the vertical layout of the structure, divided into a
base, a central and an upper part, corresponds to the three
spheres of the Universe in the Buddhist cosmogony:
kamadhatu, the sphere of the Desires; rupadhatu, the sphere of
Forms; and arupadhatu, the sphere of Formlessness.
The body, or middle part of the monument, is composed
of five terraces which diminish in size with height. The first
of these terraces stands back some seven metres from the
sides of the base creating a broad platform right round the
monument. The other terraces retreat only two metres at
each stage, and balustrades at the outer sides convert the nar¬
row galleries into corridors.
The superstructure is in its turn clearly distinguished from
the terraces. It consists of three circular platforms, each of
which supports a row of bell-shaped stupas containing Bud¬
dhas half visible through perforated stonework. Surmoun¬
ting the rows of stupas, which are arranged in concentric
circles, the great central dome on top of the monument soars
into the sky to a height of nearly thirty-five metres above the
ground.
Access to the upper part of the monument is provided by
stairways in the middle of each side of the pyramid. The
stairs lead through a series of gates (most of which have been
lost) directly to the circular platforms, at the same time in¬
tersecting the corridors of the square terraces. The main en¬
trance is at the eastern side, as is clear from the start of the
narrative reliefs.
Chandi Borobudur is one of the most complex and in¬
tegrated religious symbols in the world; each of its levels has
a different kind of sculptural symbolism. It should be con¬
sidered, not as a temple, but as a place of pilgrimage, or a
school or university of a special type. The Buddhist student
is guided gradually along successive terraces and staircases to
the uppermost platform, experiencing physically as well as
spiritually the long and hard journey in search of the
Ultimate Truth.
Buddhism lays particular stress on the stages of mental
preparation to be undergone before attaining liberation from
all earthly bonds and the ultimate exclusion from being
reborn. The universe has three spheres. The lowest sphere is
kamadhatu or the Sphere of the Desires. At this stage man
is bound to his desires. The higher sphere is rupadhatu or the
Sphere of Forms, where man has abandoned his desires but
is still bound to name and form. The highest sphere is
arupadhatu, or the Sphere of Formlessness. In this sphere
there is no longer either name or form. Man is once and
forever freed from all bonds with the phenomenal world.
At Chandi Borobudur the Sphere of Desires is represented
by the base; the Sphere of Forms by the square terraces; and
the Sphere of Formlessness by the three circular platforms
and the great stupa.
The base is concealed from the visitor's sight today, but
the 160 reliefs and the short inscriptions carved over many of
the panels (apparently constituting instructions to the
sculptors indicating the scene to be carved) depict the work¬
ings of morality on earth.
Drawing Unesco
KAMADHATU
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Blameworthy activities, from gossip to murder, with their
corresponding purgatorial punishments, and praiseworthy
activities like charity and pilgrimages to sanctuaries, and
their subsequent rewards, are both shown. The pains of hell
and the pleasures of heaven, and scenes of daily life are
represented in a full panorama of samsara, the endless cycle
of birth and death, the chain of all those forms of delusional
existence from which Buddhism brings release.
In contrast to the openness of the earthly life in the Sphere
of Desires, the path leading to ultimate salvation requires a
narrowing of bodily sight and concentration of the mind.
The narrow galleries of the Sphere of Forms help the faithful
to achieve this. At first sight they are bewildering. The walls
and facing balustrades are packed with reliefs. No less than
1,300 panels of narrative reliefs for a total length of 2,500
metres, and a further 1,212 decorative reliefs, flank the cor
ridors. The biography of the Lord Buddha, from his descent
from heaven until his enlightenment, is depicted on the main
wall of the first gallery. The reliefs which cover the walls of
the second, third and fourth galleries tell the story of the
tireless wanderings of Sudhana in search of the Highest'
Wisdom and the Ultimate Truth.
The narrative reliefs on the walls read from right to left,
those on the balustrades from left to right. This was done for
the purposes of the pradaksina, the ritual circumambulation
which the pilgrim makes, moving in a clockwise direction
and keeping the sanctury to his right. The narrative starts at
the left and ends at the right of the eastern stairway, confirm¬
ing that this stairway is the real entrance to the monument.
The perseverance of the principal figures of the Sphere of
Forms and their tireless efforts to reach the Ultimate Goal
despite their involvement with the extreme richness and
CONTINUED PAGE 15
fe a&îfgp jMS^ ft S f & Ai.
^S^R?i
-<%
-if
*"
- - .
r*"* "J V
**'
"WM*
&t»< **
mí«-
«ff iâr
Borobudur' s
hidden foot
The base of Borobudur, usually call¬
ed "the hidden foot", is concealed
from view by a heavy stone encase¬
ment which was probably built to
prevent the still-uncompleted monu¬
ment from collapsing through sub¬
sidence. Adorning it is a remarkable
series of 1 60 reliefs which were only
discovered in 1885, over ten cen¬
turies after they were created. The
hidden foot was then exposed and
its masterpieces photographed
before being covered up again, ex¬
cept for the southeast corner. The
panels, which are outstanding for
their enthralling panorama of scenes
from everyday life, illustrate the
workings of Karma, the Law of
Cause and Effect. Scenes are shown
which may lead to a future incarna¬
tion characterized by "a short life",
"a long life", "much pain", "little
pain", "ugliness", "gracefulness"
and so on. Since the pious visitor to
Borobudur should walk around the
sanctuary in a clockwise direction in
accordance with the rite of
pradaksina, the initial deed is usually
depicted on the right side of the
panel, the good or bad result on the
left. Left above, a two-part scene
divided by the tree at centre il¬
lustrates wicked deeds that lead to
the torments of hell: people throw¬
ing fish and turtles into a cauldron
are themselves cooked over a fire
(right of central tree), and a mother-
slayer plunges headfirst into hell
(left). Left centre, refusal to give
alms leads to poverty. Left below,
the exposed hidden foot at the
southeast corner of Borobudur.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
^5ï
rtÄ/y^.
«r''
¿Mf
â *-ä
A
SSS5
J
fi$g&£] The life of the
Lord Buddha
Photos on this page show 5
of a set of 120 Borobudur
reliefs which portray
episodes in the life of the
historic Buddha, Siddartha
Gautama, according to a
sacred scripture called the
Lalitavistara. The relief
showing the birth of the
Buddha as prince Siddartha,
son of King Suddhodana and
Queen Maya of Kapilavastu
Swl (in present-day Nepal) is
preceded by panels depic¬
ting various preparations
made to welcome the final
incarnation of the Bodhisatt-
| va (the Buddha-to-be). Top
photo, two goddesses have
flown on clouds to behold
the future mother of the
Bodhisattva in her pavilion
surrounded by attendants
and soldiers.
The Bodhisattva grows up
and marries, and after the
wedding ceremony he is
visited by gods who convey
their congratulations but
also recall the holy task
awaiting him. King Sud¬
dhodana fears to lose the
son who is intended to suc¬
ceed him and builds three
palaces for him. They are
specially guarded to prevent
any attempt by the prince to
escape. Second photo: the
Bodhisattva is sitting in the
middle of the sleeping
women of the court.
One night he leaves the
palace grounds to start a
new life. Third photo: after
passing through many coun¬
tries he says farewell to his
groom and his beloved horse
and cuts off his hair.
After many wanderings, the
Bodhisattva finds five fellow
disciples who agree to join
him in his search for salva-
' tion. In fourth photo, he sits
""\x meditating, left, among
rocks, trees and peacocks
¡ on the Gaya mountain. To
the right are the five
* **V disciples.
Having resisted the
allurements of Mara the Evil
One, the Bodhisattva attains
the Highest Wisdom,
becoming Buddha, "the
, Enlightened One". Bottom
j photo: the gods persuade
! the compassionate Buddha
to reveal his doctrine and
give his special attention to
¡ the suffering world.
Photos Luc Joubert-L/nesco Courier. From
Description de Borobudur 1 920 by
N.J. Krom and Th. van Erp
\
wyt
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
THE GREAT VEHICLE
In the sense that there was no god to be worshipped, Buddhism was not
originally a religion. It was rather a doctrine explaining how to achieve the
ultimate release from all sufferings. Underlying the doctrine is the conviction
that life is misery. Since the phenomenal world is not real, life in all its aspects
is illusion. Life is both a continuation ofearlier lives and a preparation for the
next one, a station in the endless cycle ofbeing born and reborn. Theform and
circumstances of each station are determined by their predecessors.
The determining factor is the karma, the balance of good and bad acts. A
positive balance will secure a better next life and a life that continues to improve
will culminate in a rebirth in heaven. This however does not break the cycle of
birth and rebirth, since a celestial being is also a temporary manifestation. The
ultimate goal is therefore to avoid any form of rebirth.
In the further development of Buddhism, the attainment of nirvana, ab¬
solute non-existence, ceased to be the ultimate goal. To be consistent with the
Buddha's example, it was the salvation of others that should be striven for
rather than one's own. The figure of the Bodhisattva, one whose nature was
enlightenment, replaced the image of nirvana. This school, which became
established in Indonesia, /sca/VeÉ/Mahayana or The Great Vehicle. Its principle
is to pursue salvation for the many, and the ideal of the Mahayana Buddhist
is to become a Bodhisattva. R.s.
SERMONS IN STONE unfold
before the eyes of visitors who
wend their way around the ter¬
races of Borobudur. Photo shows,
above, an episode from the
Lalitavistara, the biography of the
historical Buddha from his descent
from the Tushita heaven to his first
sermon in the' Deer Park near
Varanasi. The Bodhisattva (the
Buddha-to-be) is seen bathing in
the Nairanjana river. Below, a ship
on the open sea, part of a series of
reliefs depicting the earlier lives of
the Buddha before his last incarna¬
tion in the world of human beings.
Photos © A J Bernet Kempers, Arnhem,
The Netherlands
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Tilgrim's
Progress
of Buddhism'
Winding round the second,
third and fourth terraces of
Borobudur are 460 panels,
many of them life-size,
which illustrate the tireless
search for Enlightenment
of the merchant's son
Sudhana. They are mostly
inspired by the Gan-
davyuha, a sacred text
sometimes referred to in
the West as "The Pilgrim's
Progress of Buddhism".
Sudhana's spiritual quest
leads him to an astonishing
variety of spiritual guides
I ranging from monks and
businessmen to a sea cap¬
tain and night-goddesses.
(1) Sudhana pays homage
' to a woman, putting five
parts of his body on the
ground. (2) He visits the
Great Bodhisattva Man-
[ jusri and requests his
teaching. Manjusri is the
figure at centre; Sudhana
is to the viewer's left. The
concluding reliefs in the
series are based on
another sacred text, the
Bhadracari. In one of the
most remarkable scenes
(3) the Bodhisattva
Samantabhadra appears
no less than three times.
First he is seen standing on
the ground (right), then on
a lotus cushion in mid-air
(centre) and finally flying in
the upper sky. The scene is
thought to illustrate the
passage, "Up to the end of
the sky, and until all... kar¬
mas and worldly passions
have ceased, my vows will
know no end."
Photos Luc Joubert-Unesco Courier
taken from Description de Borobudur
1920 by N.J. Krom and Th van Erp
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 1 1
beauty of forms, provide a model for the pilgrim as he
perambulates the successive stages.
In striking contrast to the square terraces of the Sphere of
Forms the circular platforms representing the Sphere of
Formlessness are plain: no carvings, no ornaments, no
embellishments. The only break in the monotonous plain¬
ness is offered by the row of stupas that encircle the great
central dome.
The complete openness of the arupadhatu, and the
magnificent view from it, symbolize the endless widening of
his spiritual horizon that the pilgrim can achieve by con¬
sistently following the devout conduct in life of the Lord
Buddha. Having absorbed the spirit of the arupadhatu, he
knows the delight of becoming wiser, if not enlightened, and
the ordinary visitor finds that his own weary journey is richly
rewarded.
The exceptional design of Chandi Borobudur has led to
much speculation about why it was built; the identification
of the monument with the cosmic mountain is only one of
many interpretations by which scholars have sought to reveal
its mysteries in the over 500 learned studies that have been
devoted to Borobudur.
The most satisfactory explanation of the symbolic mean¬
ing of the monument has been found by Dr. J.G. de
Casparis, who has made a minute analysis of a number of
eighth and ninth-century inscriptions. In one of them dating
from 842 AD he recognized the compound word
Bhumisambha-rabhudara which he recognized as the
original name of Chandi Borobudur.
This complicated word serves both to explain the
significance of the mountain and to name its founders as
well. As a technical term in Mahayana Buddhism (see box
page 13) the compound means: "The mountain of the ac¬
cumulation of virtue on the ten stages of the Bodhisattva".
A Bodhisattva is one who, like the historical Buddha
Gautama, has set out to attain Enlightenment. The term may
also be interpreted in architectural terms as "The mountain
which is terraced in successive stages" or in a more general
sense as the "King(s) of the accumulation of earth", i.e. the
Sailendra dynasty (saila indra = king of the mountains).
Such ambiguity in a technical term is quite common in the
Sailendra charters, as de Casparis has convincingly shown.
In the prehistoric cultures of Indonesia, a stepped pyramid
is the symbol of the abode of the ancestors in the mountains
and hence it can be plausibly argued that ancestor worship
played a significant part in the designing of the monument.
Consequently, the symbolical meaning of Chandi
Borobudur has a twofold origin, in Mahayana Buddhism
and in ancestor worship. In this context de Casparis inter¬
preted the great stupa as the tenth storey of the monument.
The ten mounting terraces of the structure correspond to the
ten successive stages the Bodhisattva must achieve before at¬
taining Buddhahood; they also correspond to the Sailendra
kings who had until then ruled the kingdom.
It is well known that kings identified themselves with their
divine patrons: Hindu kings with Siva or Visnu, and Bud¬
dhist kings with Bodhisattvas. The liberation from the cycle
of birth and death constitutes the final goal in Hinduism (just
as it was in the early evolution of Buddhism) but to the
Mahayana Buddhist it is the start of the Path to be followed
by the Bodhisattva. A Sailendra king had to do his utmost
to pave the way for the attainment of Buddhahood. He had
to accumulate as much virtue as possible during his reign. He
also had to glorify his predecessors, and one of the most
meritorious ways of doing this was to erect monuments
dedicated both to his patron and to his forefathers.
In terms of ancestor worship, a predecessor is assumed to
have reached a higher stage of perfection than a successor.
The most remote forefather, the founder of the dynasty, is
assumed to have attained the ultimate perfection. And the
other ancestors are ranked successively by order of seniority.
This was apparently the underlying idea of the founder of
Chandi Borobudur when he decided to create a monument
that differed radically from the traditional design. His dar¬
ing break with tradition was meant to demonstrate the high
esteem in which he held the forefather whom he identified
with the Buddha; and a stepped pyramid with a stupa on top
was a most appropriate symbol for depicjing the virtue the
dynasty had accumulated along the Path of the Bodhisattva.
Chandi Borobudur can only be understood by fusing Bud¬
dhism and ancestor worship.
R. Soekmono
Borobudur is exceptionally rich in stone statues depicting
Dhyani (transcendental) Buddhas seated cross-legged on
lotus cushions and facing outwards. At first sight they all
seem alike but they differ, especially as to the position of
the hands (mudra). Right, a Dhyani Buddha in the Abhaya
mudra symbolizing the reassurance to refrain from fear.
Photo taken from Description de Borobudur 1920 by N J Krom and Th van Erp
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
How Borobudur was saved
by R. Soekmono and Caesar Voûte
THE present restoration project for Borobudur is the
culmination of a long period of studies and research.
Earlier restoration and conservation measures dealt
only partially with the factors endangering the monument,
even the major work carried out by Theodoor Van Erp bet¬
ween 1908 and 1911. Van Erp rebuilt the crumbling stupas
and cleaned many of the carvings of lichen and moss. Never¬
theless, if all the cleaning operations, repairs and studies car¬
ried out since the rediscovery of Borobudur in 814 are in¬
cluded then research and conservatory action can be said to
have covered more than 150 years.
The threat to Borobudur was due to a combination of
causes. The monument was built on an unpropitious site, not
on level ground but around and over the top of a hill. As they
worked the builders tipped loose earth and rubble before
them so that the foundations of the edifice rest on a layer of
man-made fill. Even during construction this unstable fill
caused sliding which the builders countered by taking
remedial measures notably the retaining wall which conceals
the "hidden foot" (see previous article).
Borobudur is in an earthquake zone and has suffered
seismic shocks ever since it was built. As recently as 1961 two
earthquakes took place within a month. Though only very
slight they dislodged numerous stones in the leaning walls
and produced new cracks and fissures.
For over a thousand years the rigours of the tropical
climate have probed the latent weaknesses of the edifice.
Sudden changes of heat and cold between day and night in
an area where temperatures may vary by 20° Centigrade in
twenty-four hours cause porous stones to crack. But the
worst havoc has been caused by the heavy rains (over 2,000
millimetres a year on average, with torrential downpours of
up to 15mm in five minutes). They overwhelmed the inade-
On-site research was carried out into techniques for cleaning,
treating and conserving damaged stones, statues and wall
reliefs. Above, chemical tests in the laboratory.
quate drainage system, percolating down into the central
core where they washed away the earth and weakened the
foundations. As a result the terrace walls sagged and tilted
at crazy angles and the floors sloped inwards. The lower ter-
, race walls were particularly affected and were on the brink
of collapse. Had they done so the whole colossal structure
would have come tumbling down in a great slithering avalan¬
che of earth and masonry.
Moisture on the stones had also corroded many of the
beautifully carved reliefs and favoured the growth of
disfiguring patches of mosses and lichens.
For Indonesians Chandi Borobudur is a spiritual beacon,
and even during the struggle for independence the monu-
Drawing NEDECO-Dwars,
Heedenk and Verhey,
Amersfoort, The Netherlands
CAESAR VOUTE, of the Netherlands, is professor ofgeology at the Inter¬
national Institute for Aerial Survey and Earth Sciences ITC, at Delft and
Enschede. He was Unesco co-ordinator on the Borobudurprojectfrom 1971
to 1975. He is the author ofsome 60 publications in various scientific disci¬
plines ranging from palaeontology to the conservation of monuments.
R. SOEKMONO (seepage 9)
Drawing Unesco
Overloading and stresses caused by sub¬
sidence (schematic drawing far right)
threatened to bring down the walls and ter¬
races of Borobudur in an appalling avalanche
of masonry and sculptures. Vertical section,
near right, shows design of the system of
reinforced foundations, filter layers,
drainage ducts and impermeable layers
whereby the monument has been saved.
16
ENCASEMENT'Vi- Á
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Damaged Buddha statues await repair. During the rescue operation a computerized stone registration system was used to keep track
of over a million stone blocks which were dismantled, cleaned, dried, restored and treated before being re-erected on new founda¬
tions. Some stones had to be stored carefully for 4 or 5 years before rebuilding.
ment continued to receive special attention; In 1948 two In¬
dian archaeologists were invited to survey it, and in 1955 the
Government asked for Unesco's assistance. Regular measur-
ings carried out in 1959 revealed alarming irregularities; the
actual differences may have seemed insignificant but since
the slightest movement of a leaning wall might have been
fatal no deviation could be neglected.
Since Chandi Borobudur is so integrated and deterioration
was so widespread, it could not be effectively safeguarded by
partial restoration measures. Thus a bold plan was evolved:
to dismantle and rebuild the square terraces and at the same
time install an efficient drainage system behind the walls and
under the floors.
It was also decided that the earth-core of the monument
would have to be hydrologically isolated from the stone
masonry, and for this purpose it was proposed to install a
combination of filter layers and impervious structures when
building the new foundations. In any case, the weakness of
the foundations dictated a reconstruction of walls and floors
on new foundations of reinforced concrete. Adequate
strengthening of these foundations could only be achieved by
the construction of concrete slabs which would spread the
weight of the walls and the balustrades over a wide surface.
Another imperative was to maintain a certain flexibility in
the monument. Thus it was decided to construct independent
ring-like foundations under each of the galleries. I
FROM REDISCOVERY TO RESTORATION
Some time after being founded by a
king of the Sailendra dynasty of central
Java in the 9th century AD, Chandi
Borobudur is abandoned.
1814. // is rediscovered by Sir Stamford
Raffles and the envelope of rubble and
vegetation around it is gradually remov¬
ed. Specialists study all aspects of the
monument, recording its features in
drawings and photographs.
1885. Discovery of the "Hidden Foot",
bas-reliefs concealed by a retaining wall
built to prevent the edifice from
collapsing.
1907-1911. Restoration work carried out
by Theodoor Van Erp. "Thanks to him
the disappearance of the monument was
avoided". He dismantles and rebuilds the
three circular terraces and the stupas.
1929. A new commission appointed to
identify damage sources and propose
means of arresting further decay.
1950. The Republic of Indonesia joins
the United Nations and Unesco.
1955. Indonesia asks Unesco to advise on
problems of counteracting stone
weathering on Indonesian monuments,
especially Borobudur. A comprehensive
restoration plan is proposed.
1967. The Indonesian Government again
asks Unesco for technical assistance.
1968. Experts from several countries
carry out on-site studies in close co¬
operation with the Indonesian Ar¬
chaeological Institute and Government
agencies.
January 1971. International panel
meeting in Yogyakarta unanimously
agrees that the only way to save
Borobudur from disintegration is to
dismantle and rebuild the square
terraces.
April 1971. Indonesia sets up the Badan
Pemugaran Candi Borobudur (Agency
for the Restoration of Chandi
Borobudur) to handle all aspects of the
restoration project.' A Unesco co¬
ordinator appointed.
December 1972. International Con¬
sultative Committee set up. Unesco laun¬
ches international appeal.
29 January 1973. The Government of In
donesia and Unesco sign a formal agree¬
ment for the implementation of the
Borobudur Restoration Project. On the
same day agreements regarding volun¬
tary contributionsfor the preservation of
Borobudur are also signed between
Unesco and several donating Member
States. A special International Trust
Fund established, being managed by the
Director-General of Unesco assisted by
an Executive Committee comprising
representatives of Member States con¬
tributing to the project.
1975. Work begins on north façade.
Restoration will take 7 years after
dismantlement.
Early 1981. Reconstruction of east and
west façades well advanced.
October 1982. Final restoration work
completed.
23 February 1983. Grand celebration in¬
augurated by the President of the
Republic of Indonesia.
Total cost amounts to over S 20 million,
two-thirds of which are provided by the
Government of Indonesia.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
It was originally intended to open up the bas-reliefs of the
"Hidden Foot" for permanent inspection by inserting a
covered trench in the encasement around the foot of the
monument. However, this part of the plan had to be aban¬
doned because of the risk of sliding and collapse, especially
during earthquakes.
A vast amount of preliminary research was carried out
before the final design was adopted. The disciplines involved
in these preparatory activities included: airphoto analysis,
archaeology, architecture, chemistry, conservation tech¬
niques, engineering seismology, foundation engineering, tech¬
nology, landscape planning, meteorology, microbioloby,
petrography, physics, soil mechanics, surveying and ter¬
restrial photogrammetry. It can easily be imagined hat a
project of such complexity and magnitude as this required
special measures for organization and management.
International involvement at first consisted of the provi¬
sion of expert advice and assistance in the training of Indone¬
sian personnel. Then Indonesia asked Unesco to launch a
campaign to mobilize international support for the operation
(see box page 17).
The execution of the project has been in Indonesian hands.
In April 1971 the Indonesian Government established a
special agency, the Badán Pemugaran Candi Borobudur
(Agency for the Restoration of Chandi Borobudur). Staffed
by senior engineers and archaeologists and assisted by scien¬
tific advisors from several universities, the autonomous
Badan has handled all aspects of the project, technical and
administrative, national and international. The setting up of
the Badan and the simultaneous appointment of a Unesco
CONTINUED PAGE 23
Before restoration, many of the superb Borobudur reliefs
were fractured and dislocated as a result of the strains
imposed on the colossal sanctuary by tropical weathering.
COLOUR PAGES
Opposite page. On the three circular upper ter¬
races of the great sanctuary of Borobudur (In¬
donesia) stand three symmetrical rings of 72 bell-
shaped stupas, or shrines, with perforated walls.
Each shrine contains a statue of a Buddha (below
left). Above, one of the statues whose shrine has
crumbled faces a line of smaller stupas which pin¬
nacle the walls of the colossal monument which is
adorned with the world's largest and most com¬
plete ensemble of Buddhist reliefs. Detail of carv¬
ing, below right, shows grace and simplicity with
which the sculptors treated the themes of Buddhist
iconography.
Photo bottom left Michelangelo Durazzo © ANA, Paris
Other photos © Bann Namikawa, Tokyo
Centre pages. As if suspended in mid-air above the
mist-wreathed plain the majestic upper terraces are
plain and unadorned. Close at hand, in the twilight
of the fretted stupas, the pilgrim can just discern
the meditating Buddhas. Surrounded by a sea of
light, his gaze encompasses the chain of volcanic
peaks rising on the horizon.
Photo © Kyodo News Enterprise, Japan
Page 22. Above, Borobudur is set on an un¬
dulating plain bordered on practically all sides
by rugged mountain ranges. Lower photos, in¬
spired by sacred scriptures and working with
consummate skill and precision of detail, the
ancient sculptors embroidered stone master¬
pieces which have now been saved for
posterity.
Photos © Bann Namikawa, Tokyo
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
* ft
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
m A
r
ÉK
'
tu»
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
m mm
1 ¿T
Ai
!
»,
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 18
co-ordinator proved to be of the greatest benefit. Awareness
of a common responsibility soon developed complete mutual
understanding and the closest co-operation.
The Badan has carried out all the photographic and non-
photographic documentation and survey work, stone
restoration, dismantling, stone conservation work and
reconstruction, including the construction of the watertight
layers behind the walls. Over 600 technicians and labourers
have been involved.
Among the new techniques introduced for the project have
available for damaged stones, bas-reliefs and statues. On
average it took about two weeks to treat and repair each
stone. Then the blocks had to be moved back to their million
positions. An additional task was that of identifying some
ten thousand stones that had fallen off the building over (he
years, matching them with the existing architecture and
finally restoring them to their original places.
Despite the vast scale of the undertaking re-erection of the
terraces on their new foundations has proceeded according
to timetable allowing for the reinauguration of the monu¬
ment in March 1983.
The same relief in 1910 (above) and in the late 1960s (below). Chemicals picked up by water seeping from inside the monument
to the surface and secretions from various organisms caused considerable changes in the appearance of the reliefs, as well as physical
and chemical modifications.
Photo from Chandi Borobudur, by R Soekmono © Unesco
been the use of airborne and terrestrial photogrammetry for
precision surveys, the analysis of aerial photography, the ap¬
plication of geophysical surveys as aids to archaeological
prospection, and the use of computer facilities for work
planning and project management.
The task has been colossal. After the completion of the
photogrammetric survey of the monument more than a
million stone blocks were dismantled by a forest of hand-
operated cranes in an order carefully planned beforehand to
prevent the risk of unbalancing the monument.
Each stone was identified and coded then transported to
the nearby treatment area where a battery of restoration
measures ranging from cleaning with water or dry brushing
to the application of a clay and chemical "facepack" were
The Borobudur project thus constitutes an example of
very close multidisciplinary collaboration between a large
number of specialists from many different fields all con¬
tributing to the preservation and better understanding of a
monument which is a highlight in mankind's cultural, artistic
and technical achievements.
It has reflected a nation's desire to preserve its cultural
heritage for the future; the wish of a people to permit the
greatest possible number of persons to enjoy the artistic crea¬
tion of the past; and the solidarity of the international com¬
munity in preserving a masterpiece that belongs to the
universal cultural heritage.
H R. Soekmono
Caesar Voûle
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
TASHKENT
The capital of Uzbekistan celebrates
its two thousandth anniversary
by Erkin Yussupov
TASHKENT, the capital of the
Uzbek Soviet Socialist Republic
and one of the major cities of cen¬
tral Asia, is two thousand years old.
The earliest references to it occur in
certain Chinese chronicles of the second
century BC which speak of the oasis of
Tashkent. A century later this oasis is
called Yuni or Yuini, and is described as
forming part of the powerful State of
Kangyu, with a town of the same
name Yuni at its centre. The distin¬
guished orientalist V.V. Bartold, who
analysed these chronicles, advanced the
theory that the region of Yuni was iden¬
tical with that now occupied by Tashkent.
Professor M.E. Masson, a specialist in
the history of Tashkent, came to the same
conclusion.
Later the region came to be known as
Chzhesi, which apparently renders the
Chinese pronunciation of Tashkent's an¬
cient name, Shash or Chach.
Information about the history of
Tashkent is also found in the writings of
the Greek astronomer and geographer
Ptolemy, who refers in his Guide to
Geography to a city called "Stone
Tower". The great scholar and en¬
cyclopaedist Abu Rayhan al-Biruni
(973-1048), who was familiar with
Ptolemy's work, wrote that the city
which was called "Stone Tower" in
Greek was actually Binkent, the capital
of Ash-Shash, "which in the Turkic
tongue is Tashkand".
The name Chach is found in early
eighth-century documents originating in
Sogdiana, the historical area which now
forms part of Uzbekistan. The famous
ninth-century mathematician and
astronomer al-Khwarizmi mentions the
names of Shash and Tarband (probably
today's Otrar). Valuable information
concerning the history of medieval
Tashkent may be gathered from Arabic,
Persian and Turkish manuscripts of the
ninth-twelfth centuries. The city's ex¬
istence was known in Russia as early as
the fourteenth century, and is mentioned
in the "Book of the Grand Design"
under the name of Tashkur.
ERKIN YUSSUPOV, Soviet educator, is vice-
president of the Academy of Sciences of the
Uzbek SSR. He is the author ofseveral scientific
works.
24
All these references have received a
surprising amount of backing from the
latest archaeological discoveries on the
site of modern Tashkent. Particularly in¬
teresting are the results of excavations
carried out at Shash-Tep (the "hill of
Shash", situated in the southern part of
the city) in an area covering some twenty-
five hectares along the banks of an an¬
cient tributary of the Dzhun river, and on
This year the two million inhabitants of Tashkent, capital of the Uzbek SSR and the
fourth largest city of the USSR, are celebrating their city's two thousandth anniversary.
Above, a view of modern Tashkent showing the boulevard and square of "Peoples'
Friendship".
One of the oldest cities of central Asia, Samarkand is famed for its fine, mausoleums,
mosques and madrasahs (Muslim schools) which span six centuries of central Asian
architecture. Above, the Ulugh Beg madrasah in Rigestan Square.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Cotton plantation at the Moskwa State Farm, near Andizhan, in the fertile Fergana
Valley, a vast area devoted to the growing of sub-tropical crops and known as "the
Pearl of Uzbekistan".
Part of an ancient fort, dating from the 2nd or 1st century BC, excavated at the site of
Shash-Tep (the "hill of Shash") to the south of Tashkent. Arrow-shaped loop-holes
were a feature of central Asian fortifications.
the site of the ancient town of
Manguryuk, where remains of dwellings
and fortifications have been unearthed.
The archaeologists have established that
here, in the earliest years of the modern
era, craftsmanship and trade were
developing alongside agriculture and
livestock-raising.
During the Middle Ages, Tashkent
underwent many changes of fortune. In¬
vasion first by the Arabs, then by the
hordes of Genghis Khan, incursions by
neighbouring nomad tribes and wars bet¬
ween the various feudal States led more
than'once to devastation and ruin, but
the city never totally disappeared. Its
favourable geographical position and the
strong traditions and solid relationships
established over the ages in the fields of
craftsmanship and commerce, invariably
provided the incentives for renewal.
Restoration of the natural tributaries of
the Chirchik river, the construction of
canals, the transformation of the city in¬
to a major commercial, industrial and
cultural centre and the growth of new ur¬
ban settlements in the vicinity all con¬
solidated the reputation of Chach as "the
land of a thousand cities."
The Middle Ages were a period of great
expansion for Tashkent. Its skilled crafts¬
men produced metal tools, weapons,
decorative objects and household articles
of the highest quality. Others excelled at
processing farm products, and others still
produced cotton and wool textiles, pot¬
tery and glassware. In terms of the
. number of its merchants, Tashkent held
third place among the great trading cen¬
tres of central Asia, after Bukhara and
Samarkand. At the same time, the
world's scientific and cultural heritage
was enriched by the achievements of the
many scholars and writers who have lived
and worked in Tashkent. These have in¬
cluded the philosopher, poet and
theologian Abubakir Kaffalon Shoshi
(10th century), the physician Abu Ab-
dullakh Mukhammad ibn Yusup al Iloki
(11th century), the eye specialist
Ubaidulla ibn Yusup Ali Alkakhal (16th
century), the poets Badir Chachi (14th
century), Kulfat (18th century) and
Komy Tashkandi (19th century) and the
linguist Kamaliddin Khafuz Kokhakki
(16th century).
The development of production, com¬
merce, science and culture in ancient and
medieval Tashkent did not take place in a
backwater. Study of the objects unearthed
by archaeologists, of manuscripts, ar¬
chitecture, and the age-old trades and
ceremonial customs of the people of
Tashkent reveals a combination of purely
local traditions with influences from
other lands. This is not surprising;
peoples and cultures cannot develop in
isolation. As a result of immemorial links
with- neighbouring regions and with the
more distant countries of the east, the
cultural traditions, the language and the
literature of Chach underwent external
influences and in turn exercised their own
influence elsewhere.
The seventeenth and eighteenth cen¬
turies saw a strengthening of commercial
and economic ties between Tashkent and
Russia, as the mutual advantage of such
relationships became increasingly ap¬
parent. The merchants of Tashkent
travelled to the Russian frontier towns of
Siberia. In 1739-1740, the first Russian
caravan made its way to Tashkent from
the newly-established city of Orenburg,
in the Urals.
The absorption of Tashkent, together
with the whole of central Asia, into the
Russian empire in the second half of the
nineteenth century opened a new chapter
in the city's history. The seemingly
endless period of internecine wars came
to an end, industry continued to develop,
and by the beginning of the twentieth
century Tashkent had been transformed
into the economic, cultural and ad¬
ministrative centre of the governorate-
general of a multinational province,
Turkestan.
After the October Revolution of 1917,
the city began to expand more rapidly
than ever before, thanks to the
disinterested and fraternal collaboration
of the different peoples of our country.
During the darkest days of the Civil War,
a decree adopted on the initiative of V.l.
Lenin created the first institution of
higher education in the Soviet East the
Turkestan State University, which at¬
tracted noted scholars from Moscow,
Petrograd and other cities. A "science
train" carrying books, personnel and
equipment set out from Moscow and ar¬
rived two months later at Tashkent,
whose people will never forget the names
of the engineers, teachers and doctors
who fostered the rapid development of
education, health services, science and
culture, and who did so much to
eradicate illiteracy, build new schools,
and create institutions of higher educa¬
tion and scientific and cultural centres.
In a relatively short time, Tashkent
became a major centre of social,
economic and intellectual progress for
the whole of central Asia, as the city
where many writers, politicians, scien¬
tists and intellectuals from all the Central
Asian republics and from Kazakhstan
came to complete their education.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Between 1941 and 1945, the city played
an important part in the struggle against
the Hitlerite invaders. Hundreds of
thousands of its people fought valiantly
on the battlefields. As a city far behind
the front, Tashkent gave refuge to hun¬
dreds of thousands of evacuees from the
areas then occupied by the Nazis,
lavishing particular care on the children
who had lost both parents during the
fighting. Among the moving episodes of
this period, the exemplary behaviour of
Shaakhmed Shamakhmudov, a foundry-
worker, and his wife is still remembered.
During the darkest time of the war they
adopted and brought up no fewer than
fifteen orphans of eight different na¬
tionalities. Their gesture was emulated by
tens of thousands of their fellow-citizens,
who became foster-parents to children in
similar circumstances.
No history of Tashkent would be com¬
plete without mention of the disastrous
earthquake of 1966 which destroyed or
damaged some 36,000 buildings, in¬
cluding 100,000 apartments, and left
hundreds of thousands of people
homeless. Damage was also caused to
factories, cultural institutions, hospitals
and community centres, schools, univer¬
sities and many other facilities. Represen¬
tatives of all the republics of the Soviet
Union joined in providing relief, and it
was not long before Tashkent had been
extensively rebuilt, and had become
View of the interior of
the Museum of Applied
Arts, Tashkent.
Photo © Progress Publishers,
Moscow
Carved from a single block of stone, this sculpture of the Bud¬
dha, seated under the Bodhi tree (tree of enlightenment) and
flanked by two disciples, dates from between the 1st and the
3rd centuries AD. Discovered near the city of Termez,
Uzbekistan, it is now preserved in the Museum of the History
of the Peoples of Uzbekistan, Tashkent. The Museum houses
some 50,000 items from prehistoric times to the 1 9th century.
Part of a 2nd-century ivory drinking horn found during the
excavation of Shash-Tep.
again one of the most attractive cities in
the country.
Today Tashkent is a city where two
million people, of some hundred dif¬
ferent nationalities, live together in amity
and harmony. Its highly developed and
diversified industries produce aircraft,
tractors, excavators and machine-tools
which, together with the products of light
industry and food-processing plants, are
exported to seventy-five countries.
Tashkent is also a major scientific and
cultural centre, the home of the Academy
of Sciences of the Uzbek SSR, the Cen¬
tral Asian Department of the Academy
of Agricultural Sciences, and many other
high-level scientific institutions. Young
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
people from . sixty countries study
alongside Soviet students in more than
twenty establishments of higher educa¬
tion. There are a large number of
technical high schools and hundreds of
primary and secondary schools. The
quality of the city's medical services is
high.
It would be difficult to enumerate all
the features of life in this effervescent,
kaleidoscopic modern city. Tashkent
regularly hosts meetings of writers from
Asian, African and Latin American
countries. Its international film festivals,
eight of which have been held since 1968,
have won a high reputation. Every year
international conferences and symposia
are held on themes related to social pro¬
gress, science and technology. All these
activities contribute to the strengthening
of mutual understanding, friendship and
peace among peoples. The international
prestige of Tashkent is also reflected in
the fact that it was there that the leaders
of India and Pakistan met in January
1966 to settle a number of controversial
issues between their two countries; the
result of this meeting was the historic
"Tashkent Declaration".
Visited by increasing numbers of
tourists, Tashkent is a member of the
United Towns Organization and has
special links with Tunis, Skopje, Mar-
rakesh, Potiala, Seattle, Tripoli and a
number of other cities.
The two millennia of Tashkent's
history are spanned by an invisible
bridge, whose outline may nevertheless
be discerned in the city's architecture and
also in the domains of science, literature
and art. The songs, dances, poetry, music
and popular wisdom of ancient Chach,
constantly enriched through contacts
with the cultural achievements of dif¬
ferent countries during different periods
in history, have won their place in the
modern world.
Modern dance, spoken poetry, and the
applied arts are not merely echoes from a
distant past; they are also achievements
of our times. Traditions of popular crafts¬
manship acquired during generations of
meticulous labour find a place in modern
industry. Cloth woven of gold thread,
national costumes and decorative art ob¬
jects are universally admired. The
dancers of the Uzbek State Ensemble
"Bakhor" and the singers and in¬
strumentalists of the "Yalla" and
"Navo" companies combine the tradi¬
tional and the modern in their
repertoires.
Drama has also followed a long path
from past to present in Tashkent, whose
people took pride in the fact that the
Uzbek Academy of Music, the Alisher
Navoi, was selected to represent the
USSR at the 1982 Berlin International
Opera Festival.
This fusion of the traditional and the
contemporary finds an echo in the hearts
of millions of people, whatever their
aspirations. May the invisible bridge
which spans Tashkent's two thousand
years of history serve the cause of peace,
brotherhood and friendship between all
peoples of the West and the East.
Erkin Yussupov
A golden treasury
of manuscripts
Á,
0\ " rr
TpaMOTHbid TBOft ¿lour oóywb HerpanoTHbix!
""- 	
Published in Tashkent, in 1920, at the start of a literacy cam¬
paign, this poster bears the message, in Uzbek and Russian: "It
is the duty of those who are educated to teach the illiterate to
read and write".
by Muzaffar Khayrullaev
IN the history of the East, central
Asia and its citiesBukhara,
Samarkand, Khiva, Tashkent,
Urgench and Termez are renowned as
centres of an ancient civilization.
The region, which in Antiquity lay on
the Silk Road and was in the Middle Ages
MUZAFFAR KHAYRULLAEV is director of
the Abu Rayhan al-Biruni Institute of Oriental
Studies, Tashkent. He is a corresponding member
ofthe Academy ofSciences ofthe Uzbek SSR and
the author of many scientific publications.
one of the most highly developed and"
prosperous parts of the Arab caliphate,
was for centuries involved in exchanges
with other peoples. Among the great
achievements of the culture that was born
of this process are architectural
monuments, works of popular crafts¬
manship, and also a heritage of il¬
luminated manuscripts.
In Uzbekistan many of these
manuscripts have been preserved, either
in city libraries or in private hands. The
State provides for the restoration and
conservation of the documents, which
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
are gradually being concentrated in the
Institute of Manuscripts of the Academy
of Sciences. However, the richest collec¬
tion is that of the Abu Rayhan al-Biruni
Institute of Oriental Studies.
At present the Institute's manuscript
holdings amount to more than 18,000
volumes containing over 40,000 works,
as well as a considerable collection of
deeds and official documents evoking the
grandeur and decline of the feudal States
of central Asia.
The manuscripts cover a period of
almost a thousand years from the mid-
tenth to the early twentieth centuries and
an area ranging from the Near East to
northern India, Iran, the Arab countries
and the Maghreb.
For the most part, the texts are in
languages which were common in the
Muslim East during the Middle Ages:
Arabic, Persian and various Turkic
languages. Urdu and Pushtu are also
represented.
Thematically, the manuscripts encom¬
pass virtually all the domains of medieval
written culture the natural and exact
sciences, the humanities (history, poetics
and philology), literature, music, ar¬
chitecture and philosophy. Some are
devoted to Islamic themes: the Qur'an,
the Qur'anic sciences, the hadith,
jurisprudence, Sufism, and other cur¬
rents of Islamic thought. Others are con¬
cerned with various crafts, with
agriculture, commerce, and with subjects
related to construction. There are many
dictionaries, encyclopaedias, glossaries
and other works of reference.
Some of the manuscripts are unique,
either because copies are to be found
nowhere else in the world's archives,
because they constitute the most com¬
plete example of a given text, because no
earlier version exists, or because as works
of art they have no equal.
One outstanding example in the
Museum of the Peoples of Uzbekistan is
the seventh-century Qur'an of Uthman,
transcribed on parchment. A unique
specimen of the treatise on chemistry by
ar-Rhazes (ninth-tenth centuries)
discovered in the Institute of Oriental
Studies is a valuable source of knowledge
concerning research in the natural
sciences in the medieval East.
The Institute also contains several
works by the great Ibn Sina (Avicenna,
tenth-eleventh centuries), notably several
pages from his Canon of Medicine, the
oldest of which dates from the thirteenth
century. There are many works by Al-
Biruni (tenth-eleventh centuries) the most
precious being a copy of his en¬
cyclopaedic work "The Book of
Understanding of the Elements of
Astrology" which deals with matters
related to astronomy, mathematics,
geodesy and other subjects. The
manuscript dates from the thirteenth cen¬
tury and is considered to be one of the
oldest transcriptions of this text.
A unique seventeenth-century volume
entitled "Collected Writings of Wise
Men" contains 107 treatises by the great
thinkers and scholars of Antiquity and
the Middle Ages: Aristotle, Plato and
Galen among the Greeks; Al-Kindi, Ibn
28
Rushd (Averroes) and Ibn Badzh among
the Arabs; Farabi and Ibn Sina from cen¬
tral Asia; Bakhmaniar from Azerbaijan;
and many others. These documents
create a complex picture of the intellec¬
tual inquiry and philosophical systems of
the great minds of the past. The
manuscript was written in Damascus,
doubtless by an amateur of philosophy
who devoted much of his time to collec¬
ting philosophical works.
In the Middle Ages literature and
especially poetry constituted the most
widespread and popular form of express¬
ing spiritual and emotional experience.
They were also, especially in the hands of
the great masters of verbal expression, a
means of transmitting popular wisdom,
ding musician who introduced many in¬
novations into Indian music and is con¬
sidered to have invented the sitar. He
wrote on many subjects but he was most
famous of all in India for the songs which
he wrote in the Hindi vernacular. The
copy in the Institute's possession is par¬
ticularly valuable because three of the
five poems were transcribed by the great
poet Hafiz (fourteenth century).
Another of the Institute's treasures is
an album containing original letters by
fifteenth-century scholars, poets and
writers compiled for the Uzbek poet and
statesman Ali Shir Navoi. It includes let¬
ters by the famous Abd al Rahman
Djami. These letters deal with the social,
economic and cultural life of Khorassan
Letter written by the
15th-century poet
Abd al-Rahman
Djami to the Uzbek
poet and statesman
Ali Shir Navoi. Djami
authenticated his
letter by signing
each sheet in the top
right hand corner.
r^ítiMe*
'JÓlrjl J.-tu,-
*>. s,
* * >, >-j
J** %
-77-
JE-»*
X, : >a~
~*-jJ>y¡,
"in
u j'j > .-»
ft
^i
¿te -i^í"
'
-~^^-t¿ -y »i
*Vr- . " *"" -
*- -
"
the historical experience, and reflection
on the meaning of existence.
The poetry of the medieval East is
represented in the Institute's archives by
the works of great artists of central Asia,
India, Iran, Afghanistan, Azerbaijan,
and the Arab countries. Examples in¬
clude a fourteenth-century copy of a
peom by Yusuf Balassagun entitled
"Knowledge, bringer of happiness".
The archives also contain a unique ex¬
ample of the Khamsah ("Pentology") by
the great fourteenth-century Indian poet
Amir Khusru. In the words of Jawaharlal
Nehru, Khusru was an outstanding poet
who wrote mainly in Persian but was also
a master of Sanskrit. He was an outstan-
and central Asia in the fifteenth century
and constitute an invaluable document
for the study of the history of the empire
of the Timurids.
Works by medieval historians are well
represented in the Institute's holdings.
They include a twenty-volume universal
history by Ibn al-Assiri and a history of
the ancient and medieval world by Ibn
Muhammad al-Djuwayni (thirteenth cen¬
tury). The pearl of the collection is an
early (fourteenth century) copy of a text
by Rashidaddin ibn Imadovla, who was
famous throughout the East. There are
also Uzbek translations of historical
works in Arabic and Persian, from the
seventeenth to the nineteenth centuries.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Examination time at the Miri-Arab
madrasah (Muslim school) at
Bokhara, Uzbekistan. The curriculum
of a madrasah is traditionally centred
on the Qur'an but, in addition to
Islamic theology and law, grammar,
literature, mathematics and some¬
times medicine are studied.
Below, one page from a manuscript
copy of The Book of Understanding of
the Elements of Astrology, an en¬
cyclopaedic work by the great scholar
and scientist Al-Biruni (973-1048)
which deals with subjects such as
astronomy, mathematics and geodesy.
Dating from the 13th century, this
manuscript is believed to be one of the
oldest existing transcriptions of Al-
Biruni's text.
Photo © V Seleznev, Moscow
Some of these manuscripts are
veritable works of art. Their pages are
embellished with brightly coloured orien¬
tal designs and illuminated with gold
paint, and the texts are executed in ex¬
quisite calligraphy. Works by the great
poets Firdusi, Nizami, Saadi, Navoi,
Amir Khusru, Hafiz and Dzhami are
decorated with miniatures of exceptional
artistic quality.
All these manuscripts, which relate to
different periods in the history of the
peoples of a vast region, constitute an
irreplaceable source of information
concerning the social, economic and
spiritual life of the peoples of the Near
and Middle East, of central Asia, India,
Afghanistan, Pakistan, and eastern
China.
Before the October Revolution of
1917, the department of Eastern
Manuscripts of the Tashkent Public
Library, whose archives formed the basis
of the collection now conserved by the
Al-Biruni Institute, possessed no more
than a few hundred works. Today the In¬
stitute's holdings are growing every year
thanks to subventions from the
Government.
There is also an active programme for
the exchange of microfilms with other
manuscript archives throughout the
world. The Institute already possesses
more than 3,000 microfilms. Each year it
receives hundreds of requests for
photocopies of rare texts from the United
States, the Federal Republic of Germany,
Afghanistan, the Arab countries, India,
Czechoslovakia, the United Kingdom,
and other countries. Research students
from many countries come to work at the
Institute.
In recent decades, the orientalists of
Uzbekistan have done much to place the
study of manuscripts on a more
systematic footing. Ten volumes of
manuscripts have already been published
and three more are in preparation. There
is also an ongoing programme for the
publication of catalogues of works by in¬
dividual thinkers and poets. Manuscripts
belonging to the Al-Biruni Institute also
formed the basis for the publication in
Russian and Uzbek for the first time of
Avicenna's Canon of Medicine, in six
volumes; a six-volume selection of works
by Al-Biruni; a multi-volume edition of
the works of the great Uzbek poet Ali
Shir Navoi; works by Farabi, the
"Aristotle of the East"; as well as works
by Zahir ud-din Babur, and the tenth-
eleventh century historians Narshakhi
and Baikhaki, and other writers.
Preparations are currently being made
to celebrate the 1,200th anniversary of
the birth of the great scholar Mukhamm-
ed ibn Moussa al-Khorezmi, whose name
is linked with the invention of algebra
and the logarithm. Plans have been made
for the first-ever edition, in Russian and
Uzbek, of his major works on
mathematics, astronomy and geography.
The work of the Institute of Oriental
Studies on the rich cultural heritage of
the peoples of the East has been recogniz¬
ed by the award of the first International
Avicenna Prize. The study and publica¬
tion of the works of the great humanists
of the East, the propagation of their
noble ideals, the strengthening of scien¬
tific contacts and the exchange of
manuscript material make an important
contribution to international cultural and
scientific co-operation and hence to
friendship between peoples.
Muzaffar Khayrullaev
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Culture
in a cold climate
The reindeer herdsmen of Lapland
by Pekka Aikio
Members of the "Lapp Parliament" at work during the annual session of the
representative body founded in 1973 as an expression of Lapp identity and as a means
of preserving traditional rights.
BECAUSE of its latitude, Finno-
scandinavia the geographic to¬
tality of Finland, Sweden and
Norway constitutes the most densely
inhabited "desert" in the world. In
fact, the historical development of nor¬
thern Scandinavia owes much to the
temperate influence of the Gulf
Stream. Without this warm current the
land of the Lapps, at the northern ex¬
tremity of Finland, Norway and
Sweden, would be a sparsely populated
arctic tundra, like the vast tundra zone
of North America.
Around a million people live on the
PEKKA AIKIO, president of the Lapp parlia¬
ment of Finland, is a specialist in reindeer far¬
ming. He is currently contributing to research into
reindeer rearing being carried out by the univer¬
sity ofOula and the Finnish Academy.
30
Nordic ice-cap, the region of Sweden,
Finland and Norway north of the Arc¬
tic Circle. It is not easy to say how
many of them are Laplanders since on¬
ly Finland has attempted to define what
might be called the "Lapp ethnic
group" and the criteria on which this
definition is based are not accepted in
either Sweden or Norway. In Finland,
a person who speaks Lapp as his
primary language or whose parents or
one of whose sets of grandparents
spoke Lapp is considered to be a
Laplander. On the basis of this defini¬
tion the Laplanders of Finland elect a
representative body commonly called
the "Lapp Parliament", yet the situa¬
tion remains paradoxical since Lapp
does not have the status of an official
language and in the statistics it is not
recognized as a mother tongue.
-~.n
- ml* "
-ft
fi- **
w
MI..H-.* '***«*"
T^"*"*
^ gt
Definition of a "Lapp cultural iden¬
tity" is an even trickier question in the
neighbouring countries of-Sweden and
Norway, where the Lapp ethos has
always been closely linked with
reindeer herding, to such an extent
that, at times, only Lapp reindeer
farmers have been considered
Laplanders.
In 1973, Lapp territory was defined
in Finland as consisting of the com¬
mons of Enontekiö, Inari and Utsjoki
and the Lapp community's domain of
Sodankylä. It was at this time that
language was designated as the
criterion for belonging to the Lapp peo¬
ple. This definition increased the Lapp
population of Finland to somewhat
more than 4,500 people, ten per cent of
whom live outside their territory, in
southern Finland or abroad. This may
appear at first glance a conservative
estimate.
Sweden and Norway undertook
demographic studies of the Laplanders
in the 1970s. It was found that while the
Swedish Lapp population numbered
from 17,000 to 20,000 individuals, only
2,000 of them were reindeer farmers.
Norway was found to have approx¬
imately 2,500 Lapp reindeer farmers,
for eighty per cent of whom reindeer
farming was their main professional ac¬
tivity, out of a total of between 35,000
and 50,000 Laplanders. These figures
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
ijr* - p¿
i* '
r -">
It.fW
-
-^
j» ^" ar Wf,^.
**" ^^
«. w
w* »*" - *> ~«
k.- -f
***** 5* ^î <^_ T^* , ^- - gt
. «**AÎ*
"A
». r- *
During their seasonal migrations reindeer herds cover very considerable distances, ranging in Norway, for example, from 300 to
400 kilometres. Special agreements allow the reindeer herders, who live a nomadic or semi-nomadic life, to cross the national fron¬
tiers of the Scandinavian States with their herds.
do not take into account the coastal
Lapps, the "Maritime Laplanders",
who pose extremely complicated prob¬
lems of cultural'identity. Thus it ap¬
pears that neither the use of the Lapp
language nor the practice of reindeer
farming are adequate criteria for judg¬
ing who is to be included in the Lapp
population.
The wild reindeer, from which our
modern herds are descended, were at
one time to be found throughout the
northern hemisphere. From very early
times the species branched out into two
distinct types: the arctic mountain
reindeer and the forest reindeer,
adapted to the conifer forest zone. The
nordic reindeer is descended from the
mountain reindeer, while the forest
reindeer, increasingly rare, has almost
A Lapp reindeer-farmer feeds his herd. In the Finnoscandinavian countries, with the
growth of domesticated herds,pasturelands are coming under pressure and at times the
reindeer are faced with local shortages of graze.
disappeared from the Finnoscandina¬
vian environment.
Traditional forms of domestic
reindeer husbandry have survived only
in Eurasia. Broadly speaking, all the
Eurasian zone north of the zero degree
isotherm can be considered reindeer-
raising territory. Of the world's four
and a half million reindeer, about three
million are domesticated, seventy-
seven per cent in the Soviet Union,
twenty-one per cent in North America,
and much smaller numbers in Scotland
and Greenland. Small herds have also
been relocated in remote places such as
the islands adjacent to the Antarctic
continent, where they have adapted
very well.
According to Soviet specialists, there
is enough pastureland in the USSR to
maintain three and a half million
reindeer, while North America is
estimated to have pasturage available
to feed three million. But in the Nordic
countries the number of reindeer can¬
not be appreciably increased; the
Swedish and Finnish pasturelands are
overgrazed and from time to time in
certain areas reindeer herds are faced
with famine.
There are four principal zones of
Eurasian reindeer-raising. To the ex¬
treme east the nomadic Chukchi and
Koryaks raise very large herds. They
use reindeer as draught animals and as
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
a source of milk. In western Eurasia,
however, the Lapps have developed a
totally or semi-nomadic husbandry
with the reindeer serving as both pack
and draught animals as well as for the
production of milk. On the Soviet
coastline of the Arctic Ocean, the total¬
ly nomadic Samoyed* use their reindeer
neither for milk nor as pack animals.
The forest Tungus, the Soyots and their
neighbours, who occupy a small area
between the Samoyeds and Chukchi
and the Koryaks, are semi-nomadic
reindeer farmers, milking their herds
and using them as beasts of burden as
well as for breeding.
Man's first contact with reindeer was
The coastal Laplanders were,
perhaps, the first to domesticate the
reindeer in Scandinavia. At first the
reindeer were used as harness, pack and
decoy animals, and for their milk. Not
yet very numerous, the reindeer accom¬
panied these primitive semi-nomadic
hunters in their search for game. As the
wild reindeer became more and more
scarce, the Laplanders increased the
size of their domesticated herds and in
their search for pasturelands gradually
became totally nomadic.
The first written evidence of reindeer
raising is contained in tax registers of
the 14th and 15th centuries. Since the
reign of Gustavus Vasa, the sovereigns
% "jwMtjjptr mi
Modem Lapp nomads use snowmobiles, motor-driven snow scooters,
to follow and round up their herds.
as prey to be hunted and snared by
means of traps, ditches and stockades.
Many traces of reindeer-herding
civilizations are to be found in Finland,
but little is known of more ancient
times when reindeer were. exclusively
hunters' prey. At Jiebmaluokta, near
Alta, however, a rock carving has been
found which depicts an enclosure for
reindeer. It is in the shape of a four-
leafed clover in which were enclosed
reindeer and elk. Several reindeer are to
be seen entering the enclosure while a
hunter, goad in hand, is herding them
into a corner. Since this carving is
thought to be between 5,500 and 6,000
years old, it would appear that a fairly
sophisticated form of reindeer hunting
was practised by the coastal Lapps as
far back as 3,000 BC.
* The editors of the Unesco Courierw/s/i to point
out that the Russian word "Samoyed" is used in
English and in many other languages as a purely
technical term without reference to its original
sense.
32
of Sweden have recognized the siidas
(traditional Lapp administrative
districts),- by virtue of which Lapland
was separated by a frontier from the
rest of the realm. Recent jurisprudence
seems to be unanimous in accepting
that since that epoch the right of the
Laplander to raise reindeer has not
been only a recognized, but also a
transmissible, hereditary, right.
At the end of the 17th century,
Lapland was still an undivided region
situated on the frontiers of the Nordic
States. The separation of the Kingdoms
of Denmark-Norway and of Sweden-
Finland, which was agreed to at
Strömstad in 1751, had significant
repercussions on the Laplanders' rights
and way of life. An annex to the treaty
of Strömstad specified that the Lapps
could cross the new frontier and make
use of the land and waters for husban¬
dry and fishing, but could own taxable
land in one State only. In addition, they
had to choose between Norwegian and
Swedish nationality. The Lapps lost
these rights when the frontier was clos¬
ed, first in 1852, then in 1854 and 1889.
The annex to the treaty of 175 1 con¬
tinues nevertheless to exert a certain in¬
fluence in Sweden and Norway. Thus, in
1972, the two countries ratified an agree¬
ment about the reindeer pasturelands,
according the Lapps of the siidas in
Sweden the right to use certain frontier
land on the Norwegian side as spring
and summer pasturage, the Lapps of
Norway having, reciprocally, the right
to use certain regions in Sweden for
winter pasture. As it now stands, the
agreement is criticized on both sides; it
seems to put the economic interests
related to reindeer-raising before the
political and national interests of the
Lapp community.
In Sweden and Norway, an essential
aspect of the annual reindeer-raising
cycle is the transhumance between
various seasonal pasturelands. These
migrations in Sweden follow ancient
custom, respecting the boundaries bet¬
ween the siidas. In Norway, these
migratory movements can cover
distances of up to 400 kilometres, going
from high mountain terrain to the
coastal archipelago of the Arctic Ocean
in the summer, and in the opposite
direction in the fall. Often a number of
communities follow the same itinerary,
the herds setting out at intervals of a
few weeks.
By means of what is designated as a
"reindeer-raising concession", the
right to raise reindeer is being granted
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Photos Pal Nils Nilsson © G Bern. Paris
to non-Laplanders in Sweden. The
Lapps of the siidas fear that in the end
the owners of these concession lands
will have a decisive influence on ques¬
tions of reindeer-raising practice. In
northern Lapland, this has been the un¬
questioned prerogative of the Lapps. In
Finland, as we have seen, membership
The art of the lasso.
of this Lapp ethnic group is based on
the spoken language. But recent
juridical and historical research may
throw new light on the question of
ethnic roots. Most of the present-day
reindeer-raising domain of Finland
corresponds to the territories of the an¬
cient siidas, and it is highly possible
that the majority of today's reindeer
farmers are its lawful'owners. Should
these ancient rights be recognized, if
only in part, the protection of the
reindeer pasturelands and the defence of
the traditional Lapp way of life would
undoubtedly be greatly strengthened.
Pekka Aikio
-
."**- - *-*' tí*"*" 	 .	 , ^>
-*r - m
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
A strategy
for disarmament
by Constantin Ene
Since 1970, Sylvia Lind¬
ström of the Swedish Save
the Children Federation
has been gathering draw¬
ings on the theme The Tree
of Life by children from all
over the world. Left, The
Tree of Life as drawn by
Ana Maria, aged 12, of
Spain.
Photo Co Rabén and Sjoren, Stockholm
THE ending of the arms race and
the achievement of disarmament
have become a fundamental
challenge of primary importance and
urgency. Under the present cir¬
cumstances of grave international ten¬
sion the attainment of real disarma¬
ment measures has emerged as the main
path to the revival of the policy of
détente, mutual confidence and co¬
operation.
CONSTANTIN ENE, Romanian specialist in
international affairs, was formerly his country's
permanent representative at the United Nations,
New York.
Since its inception the United Na¬
tions has devoted much time and effort
to international action for disarma¬
ment. Yet, even today the traditional
way pursued by humanity the search
for security through the possession of
arms still has a strong appeal. Effi¬
cient action in favour of disarmament,
commensurate with its intended goal,
should include, along with a strong
political campaign, a reasoned orga¬
nization of efforts.
Disarmament requires deeper insight
and analysis. The first special session of
the United Nations General Assembly
devoted to disarmament had this in
mind when it proclaimed a "strategy"
for disarmament. Unesco has also tried
to achieve the same objective by apply¬
ing international co-operation in the
fields of education, science, culture and
information to the search for ways of
removing obstacles to disarmament
and of stimulating further thought and
action.
The main task of the second United
Nations Special Session on Disarma¬
ment, held in June 1982, was to develop
these efforts further. A prospective
view on disarmament should discover
in the investigation of the arms race
and its dynamic not only the roots of
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
the escalating spiral of competition
but, above all, the source of a dynamic
and a more rational approach towards
disarmament.
The existence of nuclear weapons
and the continuing arms race have
brought the world to a very critical
juncture.
In military terms the accumulated
destructive power, especially of nuclear
weapons, the emergence of a new
military technology and the armament
dynamic pose a most serious threat to
international peace and security and
confront mankind with the prospect of
self-extinction. In economic terms, the
arms race causes a huge wastage of
financial, material and human
resources, produces particularly grave
distorting and destabilizing effects on
economic growth and considerably
diminishes the economic and social ad¬
vancement of all peoples; in political
terms, it perpetuates the use and the-
threat of force in international life,
hinders' the solution of other vital
problems facing mankind and stifles in¬
novating processes.
Historical experience proves that
periods of détente were never accom¬
panied by a relaxation of the arms race.
This is, in fact, one of the reasons
behind the unprecedented tension we
are experiencing in international life to¬
day. And the existing tension is used as
an excuse to step up the arms race even
more feverishly.
Indeed the early part of the current
decade shows clear signs of a new
round of arms escalation, under the
powerful impact of modern military
technology, which is destabilizing by its
nature, and of new military doctrines.
The 1970s produced a series of
technical solutions designed to over¬
come many of the factors of inhibition
and restraint over the use of political
and military pressure, while the under¬
lying strategic doctrines enlarged their
operational area to cover both peace¬
time and war-time periods.
Of special gravity is the deployment
of nuclear missiles of intermediate
range in Europe, on a continent where
the existing vast arsenals, of nuclear
weapons alone, already pose an in¬
calculable threat to the European na¬
tions and where the two military ,
alliances face each other.
The seriousness of the present condi¬
tion is evinced by the fact that the
reassessment of the military and
strategic relationship is being under¬
taken against a background of an un¬
precedented exacerbation of interna¬
tional tension, in a world climate load¬
ed with numerous unsolved complex
problems and dominated by acute
mistrust. Any of these moments of ten¬
sion could become the trigger of partial
or all out use of existing weapons, in¬
cluding nuclear ones.
Disarmament talks are manifestly
stagnant. Mankind is justifiably disap¬
pointed with the sterile results of the
WAR. Doll sculpture by Christiane de Casteras
and Andrée Marquet, Paris
Photo © Christiane de Casteras and Andrée Marquet, Pans
WAR. Oil on canvas by Dado.
Photo © Private Collection
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Unger Franz (Austria)
debates and the negotiations held dur¬
ing the past two decades, which pro¬
duced no more than resolutions on
disarmament, while the arms race, far
from being slowed down, was given a
new and strong impetus.
It is obvious that mankind has reach¬
ed a deadlock which can be overcome
only by a new and courageous ap¬
proach. More than twenty-five years
ago Bertrand Russell and Albert Eins¬
tein said: "We have to learn to think in
a new way. We have to learn to ask
ourselves not what steps can be taken to
give military victory to whatever group
we prefer, for there no longer are such
steps; the question we have to ask
ourselves is: what steps can be taken to
prevent a military contest of which the
issue must be disastrous to all parties".
The new approach, based on the
analysis and the appreciation of past
experiences should necessarily be
multidimensional .
The essential factor is the political
will of governments to overcome the in¬
ertia imposed by the technological arms
race. International effort always pro¬
ceeds from the national effort. To that
end States should give disarmament
priority in their foreign policy, par¬
ticipate in good faith in negotiations,
seek and propose solutions to the ex¬
isting problems and take unilateral in¬
itiatives, when necessary, as a
demonstration of good will and
readiness to increase mutual con¬
fidence. At times of tension, like the
one we are experiencing, unilateral in¬
itiatives are especially important.
History convincingly reveals the
value of such initiatives in the field of
disarmament. A positive experiment
was the decision taken by the USA and
the USSR in 1964-1965 to announce in¬
dividual reduction of their military ex¬
penditure on the basis of "mutual
example".
National example and unilateral in¬
itiative may play an important role as a
36
Hassan Rizig-alla Taha (Sudan)
confidence building measure. However,
only on the basis of negotiated measures,
under strict international control, can
disarmament be achieved.
A new approach to disarmament re¬
quires a fundamental revision of the at¬
titude of States, primarily of the heavi¬
ly armed States, towards the concept of
security.
The accumulation of weapons, par¬
ticularly nuclear weapons, today con¬
stitutes much more of a threat than a
protection. It is high time therefore, to
put an end to this situation and seek
guaranteed security by way of disarma¬
ment. Real security can be obtained on¬
ly through arms reduction and disar¬
mament. Since the arms race contains
in itself the cause of disruption of the
very military balance it seeks, the
military balance must be sought at
steadily lower levels.
Disarmament has become an integral
component of national security. The
history of the last two decades,
characterized by the departure from
disarmament efforts and their replace¬
ment by arms control, i.e. controlled
joint armaments, evinces the fact that
the policy of arms control cannot con¬
stitute the way of achieving genuine
progress towards disarmament.
When agreements of this type were
reached in the past a particularly dif¬
ficult process, with the slow pace of the
negotiations being constantly surpassed
by the fast-moving military technological
innovations, with destabilizing effects
the ceilings established under the
respective agreements were so high that
they served merely to codify a still
greater competition and a massive and
steady growth of nuclear armaments.
The arms control policy did not lead
to disarmament nor did it help build a
real and durable relaxation of tension.
The only viable alternative is a com¬
prehensive long-term programme of
genuine disarmament, within an agreed
step-by-step framework, leading to the
HALT
THE ARMS
RACE
In 1981, the United Nations
launched an international poster
competition on the theme of disar¬
mament. On these pages we pre¬
sent a selection from the 66 of¬
ficial entries from United Nations
Member States. The winning
poster was by Gerhard Voigt of the
German Democratic Republic (see
the Unesco Courier, March 1982,
page 6).
DEUXIEME SESSION EXTRAORDINAIRE
SUR LE DESARMEMENT
W
Riadh Larif (Tunisia)
ASSEMBLEE GENERALE
DES NATIONS -UNIES
DEUXIEME SESSION EXTRAORDINAIRE
SUR LE DESARMEMENT - 1982
-
Renée Weber (Luxemburg)
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
ultimate goal of general and complete
disarmament.
Resolute action in favour of disar¬
mament must be organically integrated
into a long-term policy designed to
bring about the ultimate removal of
force and war from international life.
History proves that as long as the
military balance is considered the cor¬
nerstone of an international system
based on force, in particular on
military force, the search for such a
balance will only serve to conceal the
steadily soaring arms spiral, with all its
consequences for the peace, security
and progress of mankind.
The conclusion of international
treaties, both at world and regional
levels, on non-resort to the use and
threat of force in relations between
States, as well as of international in¬
struments to secure the settlement of all
disputes between them by peaceful
means only, could substantially favour
progress towards disarmament.
By the same token, due considera¬
tion should be given to the natural rela¬
tionship between détente and disarma¬
ment, since progress achieved in the
field of détente is complementary to,
and mutually conditional on progress
in the field of disarmament.
Disarmament should be tackled in
direct relation with the social and
economic needs of States, in particular
of developing countries.
The relationship between disarma¬
ment and development embodies two
facets of one and the same imperative,
namely, reshaping international struc¬
tures and the system of traditional rela¬
tions based on inequality and on
dominance by the more powerful.
Linking disarmament to develop¬
ment efforts may open new vistas and
provide new levers capable of setting
the disarmament process on a new
course, one which would meet the
needs of the broad masses of the people
and eliminate economic underdevelop¬
ment. Such an approach could
materialize in a broad international ac¬
tion aimed at the freezing and reduc¬
tion of military budgets.
Any innovating approach to disar¬
mament efforts should be based on the
active participation and contribution
by all States. Disarmament is a matter
of vital concern to all countries and
peoples, whether big or small, irrespec¬
tive of their military force or the types
of weapons they possess. Therefore
decisions in this field can no longer be
taken by a restricted group of States.
As a corollary of this, the United
Nations should be the focus of inter¬
national activities devoted to
disarmament.
The arms race directly affects the life
and security of the people around the
world. Therefore they should be the
first to have a say in disarmament
negotiations and be able to protect their
own interests.
Public opinion has been lulled into
apathy by arguments that problems of
armaments, because of the high
technology involved, are too complex
to be understood and dealt with by
non-experts. The latest mass participa¬
tion in peace demonstrations all over
the world indicates mark a new mo¬
mentum in the history of disarmament.
It should become the central task of
peace education to raise societal con¬
sciousness and activate public opinion to
try to bring about change. As the presi¬
dent of Romania put it "one should not
expect to solve the vital problems of
mankind at the negotiating table only.
The masses should defend by their own
force, the life, security and future
development of human civilization. It
is the masses who will be able to impose
disarmament...".
A primordial role devolves upon
scientists, who are best situated to
know the dangers overshadowing
mankind as a result of the huge ac¬
cumulation of nuclear weapons and of
other means of destruction. Conse¬
quently, they must be provided with
adequate conditions enabling them to
voice their views at the United Nations,
in the Geneva Committee on disarma¬
ment and in other negotiating fora.
Implementation of dynamic -con¬
cepts in the field of disarmament re¬
quires efficient debating and
negotiating fora. The first United Na¬
tions Special Session on Disarmament
created a more democratic machinery.
It is essential now to use it more effi¬
ciently. Far from being a matter of
form, the institutional and the pro¬
cedural aspects of the negotiating
bodies have a direct impact on the very
content of the work. They may provide
or, on the contrary, deprive the
negotiating machinery of the necessary
instruments to mobilize the political
will of States. In this respect, the con¬
duct of negotiations outside military
alliances, which, by definition,
stimulate mistrust and confrontation,
is of special importance.
The task of the day is to resume the
disarmament negotiations. The decisive
factor for achieving genuine results is
the political will of States, especially of
those possessing nuclear weapons. This
goal can only be reached by the mo¬
bilization of governments, political
organizations and social forces favour¬
ing disarmament, by encouraging the
peoples and public opinion all over the
world to work together and to
recognize the urgent need to halt and
reverse the arms race, in particular the
nuclear arms race. The international
organizationsthe United Nations,
Unesco and other specialized institu¬
tions can make a major contribution
to developing international action in
order to reach this goal.
I Constantin Ene
UNITED NATIONS GENERAL ASSEMBLY
SECOND SPECIAL SESSION
ON DISARMAMENT 1982
/
Lasse Persson (Sweden) Renato Bisquera (Philippines) Hubert Chaillet (Mauritius)
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
G3 ib Gl rn
ü
Unesco issues medal
for Fez campaign
The latest medal issued by Unesco in sup¬
port of its campaigns to safeguard the
cultural heritage is devoted to the city of
Fez (Morocco). The first capital of the Sheri¬
dan empire of the Maghreb, Fez was found¬
ed at the end of the second century of the
Hegira, (8th century AD). For over 30 years
the old Medina of Fez has been the site of
social and economic developments which
have disturbed its traditional balance and
threatened its architectural heritage and
spiritual values. In recent years the Moroc¬
can Government has undertaken a vast ef¬
fort to safeguard Fez, and in 1976 Unesco
decided to support this effort by an interna¬
tional campaign. Launching the campaign
in April 1980, the Director-General of
Unesco, Mr. Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, de¬
clared: "Fez must be saved. For its popula¬
tion whose well-being is linked to its
renovation; for Morocco, whose spiritual
capital it remains; for the Islamic world for
which it is a unique testimony of the many
cultural achievements of Islam; and finally
for the whole international community, for,
as the precious inheritance of all, it now
belongs to the common heritage of
mankind".
Enquiries about the medal, struck at the
Paris Mint in gold, silver and bronze, should
be addressed to: Philatelic and Numismatic
Programme, Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy,
75700 Paris.
1 36 sites on World Heritage List
Twenty-four sites of outstanding cultural
or natural interest have been added to the
World Heritage List by the World Heritage
Committee, which met at Unesco's Paris
headquarters from 13 to 17 December
1982 under the chairmanship of Mr. R.O.
Slatyer, of Australia. The Committee, which
consists of delegates from 24 States, has
the task of implementing the Convention
for the Protection of the World's Cultural
and Natural Heritage which was adopted by
Unesco's General Conference in 1 972. The
Convention came into force in 1975, and
has now been ratified or accepted by 69
States. The 24 sites added to the List,
bringing its total number to 136, are: the
Tassilli n'Ajjer, the M'Zab valley, Djémila,
Tipasa and Timgad (Algeria); the national
parks of western Tasmania and the Lord
Howe Islands (Australia); the historic town
centre of Olinda (Brazil); the Tai National
Park (Ivory Coast); the old city of Havana
and its fortifications (Cuba); the historic
Cahokia mounds of Illinois (USA); the Royal
Salt Works at Arc-et-Senans (France); the
historic national park, the Laferrière citadel,
the Sans-Souci palace and the site of Les
Ramiers (Haiti); the Rio Plátano biosphere
reserve (Honduras); the historic centre of
Florence (Italy); the archaeological sites of
Leptis Magna, Sabratha and Cyrene
(Shahhat) (Libyan Arab Jamahiriya); the
Aldabra Atoll (the Seychelles); the Holy City
of Anuradhadpura, the historic city of
Polonnaruva and the ancient city of Sigiriya
(Sri Lanka); the Selous game reserve (Tan¬
zania); and the ancient town of Shibam and
its wall (Democratic Republic of Yemen).
"Space Flight" sculpture
presented to Unesco
A bronze statuette entitled "Space
Flight" has been presented to Unesco by
the Government of the USSR. The
sculpture, which depicts a young woman
springing into space holding out an open
book, was carried aboard the Soviet space
vessel which returned to earth on 10
December 1982 after establishing a dura¬
tion record in orbit. It was presented to the
Director-General of Unesco, Mr. Amadou-
Mahtar M'Bow, during the "Soviet Days"
held at Unesco's Paris headquarters from
13 to 21 December 1982 to mark the 60th
anniversary of the formation of the Soviet
Union, by the First Deputy Minister of
Culture of the USSR, Mr. Yuri Barabash, the
permanent delegate of the USSR to
Unesco, Mr, Yuri Khiltchevsky, and the
cosmonaut SvetlanaSavitskaia. Concluding
the "Soviet Days", the permanent
delegates of Byelorussia, the Ukraine and
the Soviet Union presented to the Unesco
library works published in Russian, Byelo¬
russian, Ukrainian, English and French.
BOOKSHELF
Recent Unesco publications
Where the Future Begins, by Amadou-
Mahtar M'Bow. A penetrating analysis of
the world problems which form the back¬
ground to Unesco's Medium-Term Plan,
1984-1989. 1982, 118 pp. (20 F).
Higher Education and the New Interna¬
tional Order, edited by Bikas C. Sanyal.
Contributions by eleven distinguished
specialists from both developing and in¬
dustrialized countries. 1982, 242 pp.
(100 F). Co-published with Frances Pin¬
ter (Publishers) Ltd., who have exclusive
rights in the UK.
Literacy and Illiteracy, by André
Lestage An overall view of literacy cam¬
paigns or activities conducted by Unesco
in different world regions. (No. 42 in
Unesco's "Educational Studies and Docu¬
ments" series) 1982, 31 pp. (10 F).
An International Survey of Book Pro¬
duction during the Last Decades, pre¬
pared by the Division of Statistics on
Culture and Communication, Office of
Statistics, Unesco. A statistical profile of
world book production from 1956 to
1977. 1982, 87 pp. (14 F).
Employment-Oriented National Youth
Programmes in Africa: Situations, Prob¬
lems and Prospects. A study which aims
to identify the problems facing the large
number of young people with neither
education nor employment in Africa, and
to analyse a number of employment-
oriented out-of-school training pro¬
grammes. (No. 44 in Unesco's "Reports
and Papers in the Social Sciences"
series) 1982, 61 pp (12 F).
Social Science in Latin America and
the Caribbean, 1 . Social Science needs
and priorities in the English-speaking
Caribbean and Surinam (No. 48 in Unes¬
co's "Reports and Papers in the Social
Sciences" series) 1982, 54 pp. (12 F).
The Economics of Book Publishing in
Developing Countries, by Datus
C. Smith Jr. under the auspices of
Franklin Book Programs, Inc. (No. 79 in
Unesco's "Reports and Papers on Mass
Communication" series. 1982 (first
published 1977) 44 pp. (10 F).
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the
editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author's
name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on re¬
quest. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply
coupon covering postage. Signed articles express
the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the
editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier
staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform
(microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) University
Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100,
U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian Head,
Inc., 111 West 40th Street, New York, U.S.A.; (3)
Bell and Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road, Wooster.
Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
French: Alain Lévêque (Paris)
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov (Paris)
Arabic: Sayed Osman (Paris)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: Mohammed Reza Berenji (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Y¡ Kae-Seok (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salaam)
Braille: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Punisa Pavlovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Bulgarian: Pavel Pissarev (Sofia)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Statistical yearbook
annuaire statistique
anuario estadístico
OO
ON
1,211 pages
Trilingual English/French/Spanish
Hardbound: 295 French francs
Just published
The latest edition of Unesco's indispensable reference
book of statistics from some 200 countries and ter¬
ritories on:
Population
Education
Science and technology
Libraries
Museums and related institutions
Theatre and other dramatic arts
Book production
Newspapers and other periodicals
Paper consumption
Film and cinema
TV and radio
Prepared with the co-operation of National Commis¬
sions for Unesco and national statistical services, and
with the help of the Statistical Office and the Popula¬
tion Division of the United Nations.
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the
National Distributor in your country. (See list
below; names of distributors in countries not
listed, along with subscription rates in local cur¬
rency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Coll-
ingwood Victoria 3066, Publications: Educational Supplies
Pty. Ltd. P.O. Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals'
Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale
2100, NSW. Sub- agent: United Nations Association of
Australia, P O Box 175, 5th floor. Ana House, 28 Elizabeth
Street, Melbourne Victoria 3000 - AUSTRIA.
Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31, A-1011, Vienna.
BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International Ltd., Ittefaq
Building, 1, R K. Mission Rd , Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only N V
Handelmaatschappij Keesing. Keesmglaan 2-18, 2100
Deurne- Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco
publications agent. Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060
Brussels, CCP 000-0070823-1 3 - BURMA. Trade Corpora¬
tion No. 9, 550-552 Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA.
Renouf Publishing Co. Ltd., 21 82 St. Catherine Street West,
Montreal, Que. H3H 1 M7. - CHINA. China National Publica¬
tions Import and Export Corporation, P O. Box 88, Beijing
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makanos 3rd Avenue, P 0
Box 1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - SNTL,
Spalena-51, Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni
literatura, 1 1 Soukenicka, Prague 1 . For Slovakia only: Alfa
Verlag. Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava
CSSR. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export and Subscription
Service, 35 Norre Sogade, DK 1370, Copenhagen K.
EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco
Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo. - ETHIOPIA.
National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateemmen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1,
SF-00100 Helsinki 10, Suomalamen Kirjakauppa Oy,
Koivuvaarankuja 2, 01640 Vantaa 64. - FRANCE. Librairie
de rUnesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Pans, C C.P.
12598-48. - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus
Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internationalen
Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R. - FED. REP. OF GERMANY.
For the Unesco Courier (German, English, French and Spanish
editions): Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb,
Basaltstrasse 57, D5300 Bonn 3 For other Unesco publica¬
tions: Karger Verlag, Germenng/Munchen. For scientific maps
only: Geo Center, Postfach 800830, Stuttgart 80.
GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195,
Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd , P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The
University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University
Bookshop of Cape Coast, The University Bookshop of Legón,
P.O. Box 1. Legón. - GREAT BRITAIN. See United
Kingdom. - HONG KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., 5A
Evergreen Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen
Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon. Hong Kong
Government Information Services, Publication Centre, Basker-
ville House, 22 Ice Street. - HUNGARY. Akadémiai
Konyvesbolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V; A K V. Konyvturosok
Boltja, Népkóztársaság utja 16, Budapest VI - ICELAND.
Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co , H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate,
Bombay 400038; 1 7 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 1 3; 36a,
Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; 5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh,
Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road, Banga-
lore-560001 ; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-
Depots' Oxford Book & Stationery Co. 1 7 Park Street, Calcutta
70016, Scindia House, New Delhi; Publication Unit, Ministry
of Education and Culture, Ex. AFO Hutments, Dr. Rajendra
Prasad Road, New Delhi 1 10001 . - INDONESIA. Bhratara
Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl Oto Iskandardinata 111, Jakar¬
ta, Gramedia Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira
P T., Jl. Dr Sam Ratulangie 37, Jakarta Pusat - IRAN.
Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co., 28, Vessal Shirazi
Street, Enghélab Avenue, P 0 Box 314/1486, Teheran; Ira¬
nian Nat. Comm. for Unesco, Ave. Iranchahr Chomali No. 300,
B.P. 1533, Teheran. - IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, Al -
Rashid Street, Baghdad IRELAND. The Educational Com¬
pany of Ireland Ltd., Ballymount Road, Walkmstown, Dublin
12. - ISRAEL. A.B C. Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71
Allenby Road, Tel Aviv 6 1 000 - JAMAICA. Sangster's Book
Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston. -
JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., Shuhwa Toranomon
3bldg, 23-6, Toranomon 3-Chome, Minato-ku, Tokyo 105,
KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O Box 30571,
Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco,
P O. Box Central 64, Seoul. - KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co , Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait; for the Unesco
Courier: Farafalla Press Agency, P.O. Box SAFA 4541,
Kuwait. LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod,
Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy
Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency
for Development of Publication & Distribution, P.O. Box
34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22,
Grande-Rue, Luxembourg. MALAYSIA. University of
Malaya Co-operative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur 22-11.
MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta.
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street,
Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins,
Monte-Carlo. - NETHERLANDS. For periodicals only: Dek-
ker and Nordemann NV, P 0 Box 1 97, 1 000 AD Amsterddam,
for publications only: KEESING BOEKEN B.V., Postbus 1118,
1000 BC Amsterdam. - NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van
Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O Box 200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N A.
NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, Govern¬
ment Bookshops at. Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland,
130, Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch, Alma
Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1 1 04,
Dunedin; Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington.
NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The University
Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka, The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop-of Zana. NORWAY. All publications:
Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43,
Oslo 1; Universitets Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, P.O B
307 Blindem, Oslo 3 For Unesco Courier only: A S. Narvesens
Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6. PAKISTAN. Mirza
Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O. Box No 729,
Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern Book Co.. 926 Rizal
Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. - POLAND. Orpan-
Import, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars Polona-Ruch,
Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068 WARSAW. - POR¬
TUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livrana Portugal, rua do Carmo
70, Lisbon. - SEYCHELLES. National Bookshop, P.O. Box
48, Mahé, New Service Ltd., Kmgsgate House, P.O. Box 131,
Mahé SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and
Sierra Leone Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (SI Pte Ltd., No. 1 New In¬
dustrial Road, off Upper Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19
SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop
and General, P.O. Box 951 , Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA.
All publications: Van Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd , Llbn
Building. Church Street, P O Box 924, Pretoria. For the
Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Central News agency,
P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg. - SRI LANKA. Lake House
Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B.
244 Colombo 2 SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box
1118, Khartoum. - SWEDEN. All publications A/B CE.
Frltzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel, Regenngsgatan 1 2, Box 1 6356,
10327 Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-
Fdrbundet, Skolgrand 2, Box 1 50 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm
- SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag, 5
Ramistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211,
Geneva 11, C.C P. 12-236. - TANZANIA. Dares Salaam
Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam. - THAILAND.
Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg
Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok* Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company,
1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. - TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W I. - TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi
A S., Istiklâl Caddesi, No. 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu,
Istanbul. - UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 7145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H M. Stationery Office.
P 0. Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Govt. Bookshops in London,
Edinburgh, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol, for
scientific maps only. McCarta Ltd., 122 King's Cross Road,
London WC1 X 9 DS. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park
Avenue South, New York, N.Y. 10010. - U.S.S.R.
Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Moscow, G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost, llica 30/11, Zagreb; Cankaneva
Zalozba, Zopitarjeva 2, Lubljana; Nolit, Terazije 27/11,
Belgrade. - ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd , 67
Union Avenue, Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
SIMON BOLIVAR
Profile of a liberator
Simón Bolívar, the Liberator of Latin America (1783-1830) by the
Venezuelan art ist Héctor Poleo. The design is being used as a poster
to mark the launching of a biennial International Simón Bolívar
Prize established by the Government of Venezuela and awarded
under the auspices of Unesco. The Prize rewards activity of outstan¬
ding merit which has contributed to the freedom, independence and
dignity of peoples and to the strengthening of solidarity amor,
lions, or facilitated the quest for a new international economic, social
and cultural order. The award is being made for the first time this
year, the bicentenary of Bolivar's birth (see page 4).
j
]]>
</page>
</document>
