<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074798eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
FEBRUARY 1982 - 5 French francs
r
JJÊk
y
In this issue
Mother tongue and the brain
Are we getting the science we need ?
The world of Dostoyevsky
Knots as numbers
An African cosmology
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
^%
Sierra Leone
Mende helmet mask
The expression in symbolic form of higher, non-human forces of the
universe, the masks of black Africa are worn during initiation rites to sug¬
gest a supernatural presence. Although wearing them is usually a male
prerogative, among some peoples such as the Mende of Sierra Leone
there are women's cult associations which possess their own masks.
This polychrome helmet mask (42 cm high) sculpted in dark wood, is an
attribute of the Mende women's society called Bundu. More "realistic"
than many of its kind, it has been preserved since 1920 in the Museum of
Anthropology and Ethnology in Leningrad.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
FEBRUARY 1982 35th YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 25 LANGUAGES
English Italian Turkish Macedonian
French Hindi Urdu Serbo-Croat
Spanish Tamil Catalan Slovene
Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese
German Persian Korean
Arabic Dutch Swahili
Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French and Spanish
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 48 French francs
2 years: 84 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 36 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (11 issues a
year including one double issue}.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New York. U.S.A.; (3) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mans¬
field Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Editor-in-chief: Jean Gaudin
Assistant Editor-in-chie4: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
Howard Brabyn (Paris)
Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
English Edition:
French Edition:
Spanish Edition:
Russian Edition:
Arabic Edition: Sayed Osman (Paris)
German Edition: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese Edition: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Italian Edition: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi Edition: Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
Tamil Edition: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras')
Hebrew Edition: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian Edition: Samad Nourinejad (Teheran)
Dutch Edition: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese Edition: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish Edition: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu ... Edition: Hakim Mohammed Saïd (Karachi)
Catalan " Edition: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian Edition: Bahador Shah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean Edition: Lee Kwang-Young (Seoul)
Swahili Edition: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salaam)
Braille Edition: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene Editions: Punisa Pavlovic (Belgrade)
Chinese Edition: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
page
4 ARE WE GETTING THE SCIENCE WE NEED?
A hard look at science as a trigger of change
by André Danzin and Ilya Prigogine
10 MOTHER TONGUE AND THE BRAIN
A Japanese specialist's surprising discovery
by Howard Brabyn
15 THE WORLD OF DOSTOYEVSKY
by Elena Dmitrievna Mikhai/ova
16 PORTRAIT OF A GENIUS
A pictorial biography of Dostoyevsky
22 DOSTOYEVSKY, 'OUR GREAT CONTEMPORARY'
by Octavio Paz
24 KNOTS AS NUMBERS
by Georges Ifrah
26 AN AFRICAN COSMOLOGY
by Sulayman S. Nyang
34 UNESCO NEWSROOM
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
SIERRA LEONE: Mende helmet mask
Cover
Produced at the Bispebjerg Hospital,
Copenhagen, using a multi-detector camera,
the ¡mage on our cover represents patterns
of activity in the left side of a human brain
when the subject Is reading aloud. Changes
in the amount of blood flowing In areas of
the brain, reflecting changes in the activity in
those areas, are graphically revealed with
the aid of a radioactive Isotope, Xenon 133,
injected into a brain artery. The colours in¬
dicate the level of blood flow, with red and
white indicating a high level and blue a low
level of activity. Using this and other tech¬
niques scientists are discovering more and
more about the precise localization of brain
function in humans. See article page 10.
Photo © Lassen, Ingvar and Skinhöj, Lund, Sweden
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Are we getting the
science we need?
A hard look at science
as a trigger of change
by André Danzin and Ilya Prigogine
SCIENTIFIC research reflects a very
special and fundamental need of
mankind: the need .to under¬
stand, to explain, and to know. The
search for knowledge has always been
ANDRE DANZIN, of France, is director of the
Institut National de Recherche d'Informatique et
d'Automatique IINRIA). He is president of the.
European Committee for Development and a
member of the Club of Rome.
ILYA PRIGOGINE, of Belgium, is director of the
International Institutes of Physics and Chemistry,
Brussels, and of the Ilya Prigogine Center for
Statistical Mechanics at the University of Texas,
Austin. He received the Nobel Prize for chemistry
in 1977. This article is an abridged version of a
text that will appear in a forthcoming book Scien¬
tific Research and Social Goals, edited by
Federico Mayor, to be co-published by Unesco
and Pergamon Press.
an inspiration. By its very nature,
research explores what is unknown; the
scientist is always prepared for the
unexpected, and he knows that what
he is going to discover when his work is
complete could be very different from
what he expected, could even turn out
to be the exact opposite of the
hypothesis on which he based his ex¬
periments. He is willing to accept the
most far-reaching changes in the reality
created by his mental models.
Science itself is characterized by
logical rigour, but its effects on human
society often appear irrational. What
one finds is not necessarily what one
expected, and the results are, as often
as not, much more significant than the
"expected" result which originally in¬
spired the work. If one ignores the un¬
predictable and irrational character of
research and if. one limits the freedom
of the research worker by giving him a
specific objective, one strikes a mortal
blow at the whole process of scientific
productivity.
But the popular view is rather dif¬
ferent; it sees the application of science
as a perfectly rational process. Man
lands on the moon, eliminates diseases,
transplants organs, communicates over
huge distances, travels faster than
sound, controls nuclear energy. Man
becomes all powerful, thanks to the
great god science. "If science were to
be properly directed, if it could be freed
from pressures that pervert it the arms
race, and the constant search for pro¬
fit would provide all the answers
man needs to solve his problems." This
is a view one often hears expressed by
people who have no idea how scientific
research works.
Given the obvious and acute need to
find answers to these problems, there is
something rather sad in this dilemma;
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
how, when one knows that the very
essence of science is its uncertainty,
can one be sure of satisfying a hope
based on a mistaken notion of what
science is?
Difficulties increase as one begins to
analyse what human needs really are.
Man's needs are in fact extraordinarily
varied, depending on where he lives
and the stage of development of the
society he lives in. The situation is so
complex that one cannot give a simple
description of what it is that mankind
really needs. Even the perception of
needs changes. Man is a creature more
of desires than of needs; and as soon as
his desires are satisfied, he tends to ask
for more. It is in his nature to do so.
Man is made for evolution, a process
which constantly turns up new ques¬
tions, some of them born from the very
answers to the previous series of
questions.
So it is not only the complexity of the
subject, and its huge regional varia¬
tions, which prevent onjî from putting
forward a few models which would
serve as ¡deal examples of develop¬
ment. The real reason is that what
seems sensible to us today may soon be
useless. How does one create a policy
for science in a climate which is so hard
to define and which is in a constant
state of change?
But this analysis may seem to offend
against common sense. Science has
demonstrated its power, most convinc¬
ingly in the development of new
technologies. During the past hundred
years it has been the most powerful
cause of change in the economy, in
morals, and in ideas. It is difficult to ad¬
mit that we cannot direct this force and
put it to the service of satisfying human
needs, some of which, like malnutri¬
tion, the energy crisis, and the con
quest of illiteracy, are clearly of the
highest priority.
Before going any further and risking
giving a false notion of things, we must
stop to think for a moment about the
nature of change. When a phenomenon
is as complex and as subject to altera¬
tion as human society undoubtedly is,
its evolutionary path consists of long
periods of continuity interrupted by
abrupt changes of direction.
When a moment of change is reach¬
ed, where many different courses are
possible, it needs only the slightest in¬
tervention, or "trigger", to send the
system one way rather than the other.
But once this change of direction has
taken place it is irreversible and the
system develops in its own way until it
reaches a new point of instability.
The last quarter of the twentieth cen¬
tury seems to be heading for a moment
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
of change, even if we are incapable of
guessing how things will evolve after
that change. The developed world lives
in fear of economic crisis, inflation,
unemployment and energy shortage;
the oil-producing countries have
established an illusory wealth which
they do not know how to invest and of
whose future they have no guarantee.
In China attempts are made to improve
the individual standard of living while
each year brings ten million more
mouths to feed and ten million young
workers in search of employment. The
situation in the poorest countries is
even more alarming.
Science cannot produce answers to
problems whose nature is more moral
and political than technical. But it can
have an indirect influence: first by
modifying the social environment, se¬
cond by acting as a "trigger" for
change.
From the very earliest times,
technology has always modified the
social environment. Societies of the
New Stone Age, the Bronze Age, and
the Iron Age, and the other successive
waves of human evolution were not
established simultaneously all over the
world. At different times China, Egypt,
Greece and, more recently, Europe,
have been the leaders, but technology
has spread to isolated communities (or
perhaps been rediscovered by them)
much more slowly.
Remarkably enough, social struc¬
tures have evolved in much the same
way in each region affected by the
change, just as if for every stage of
technological evolution there is for man
a corresponding social structure.
Neolithic society probably had little divi
sion into hierarchies, but the Bronze
Age brought with it a much more rigid
power structure, often based on
slavery. The Iron Age coincided with a
shift towards the feudal system, while
industrialization, with its demands for
trade and its rewards for enterprise;
produced new democratic ideas.
Of course, the social environment is
not changed by technology alone. It is
the interaction between philosophical
ideas and the applications of new
technology which produces the
change. Which comes first? This is real¬
ly no more interesting than asking
whether the chicken or the egg came
first, because what we are considering
is a continuous process of action and
reaction. The more social conditions
and the political climate favour the
emergence of new technology, the
more is produced. At the same time,
technical progress reinforces the ex¬
isting social structure, at least until a
certain threshold is reached, or success
becomes gross and contradictions
emerge.
In fact it is the growth of knowledge
which is principally responsible for
modifying the social fabric. Bit by bit,
man accumulates knowledge and infor¬
mation; from this he derives a growing
power over nature and an increased
ability for self-examination. The ascen¬
dancy over nature appears to be
limitless; it creates what one might call
a "rule by machines". And human in¬
trospection is limited by the problems of
complexity, which increase just as
rapidly as knowledge does. Because of
the growing interdependence of the dif¬
ferent parts of the economic and social
system, no part can be analysed on its
own, detached from the rest.
Our period is characterized by a new
phenomenon, created by the invasion
of science and technology into the up¬
per levels of our society. This does not
differ in kind, but in degree, from what
happened in the past. Certainly
Pythagoras, Pascal, Leibniz and
Newton played a major part in the
discussion of ideas in their own time;
and they had no hesitation in being
philosophers as well as scientists, to the
extent that it is sometimes hard to
decide which was more important in
their work, science or philosophy or the
cross-fertilization between them. But
these were exceptional individuals.
Since the end of the 1950s, those who
work in laboratories in the developed
world can be counted in hundreds of
thousands, or in millions if we include
technicians and administrators as well
as scientists. The consequence has
been an explosion of new knowledge,
with profound implications for the
social and economic system.
Curiously enough, at the very mo¬
ment scientists were acquiring de facto
their position as principal agents of
change, they were attempting to retreat
into the isolation of their specialities,
renouncing their philosophical back¬
ground. Instead of acknowledging the
global nature of knowledge, most
scientists were trying to restrict their ef¬
forts to narrow technical questions
under the pretext that only in this way
could they preserve their objectivity.
There are already signs that in the
years to come we are going to see an
end to this isolation. The transforma¬
tion of science should be marked by a
renewed ability for scientists to move
relatively easily between one speciality
and another, and by a closer involve-
Human needs, societal goals and research priorities
The quest for a new International
economic order marks the beginning of a
new phase of international co-operation,
with the ultimate goals of Improving the
conditions of human life in developing
countries, and a shift in world priorities
which, in turn, should affect scientific
research and its long-term management.
The changes foreseeable will be not only
economic. A new approach to science
and Its potential applications must be
developed so as to make research more
relevant to immediate as well as long-
range needs.
It is against this background that
Unesco, in 1974, launched its 'Research
and Human Needs' programme.
The programme's main objective is the
investigation of the interrelations bet¬
ween scientific research and human
needs, with special emphasis on the pro¬
motion of International co-operation and
the re-orientation of research efforts and
priorities. The purpose is improved
satisfaction of human needs, particularly
in developing countries.
The programme keeps under review
those areas of directed research with the
best chance to contribute substantially
to solving present and future human re¬
quirements. The results are used by
Member States and the scientific com¬
munity in order to focus on priority fields
of research and co-operation. The pro¬
gramme is aimed also at facilitating ac¬
cess by national institutions to the
world's pool of knowledge.
Several outstanding institutions are
associated with the activities of the
Research and Human Needs Project.
These include the International Federa¬
tion of Institutes for Advanced Study
(IFIAS); the National Commission for In¬
formatics, Algeria; the Bariloche Founda¬
tion, Argentina; the Science Faculty of
the University of Yaounde, Cameroon;
the Institut de Recherche d'Informatique
et d'Automatique (IRÍA), France; the
Tata Institute of Fundamental Research,
India; the Italian National Research
Council; the Polish Institute for Basic
Technological Research, Polish
Academy of Sciences; the Science Facul¬
ty of the University of Dakar, Senegal;
the Centro Latino-Americano de
Economía Humana, Uruguay; the In¬
stitute for Systems Studies of the Union
of Soviet Socialist Republics; the In¬
stituto Venezolano de Investigaciones
Científicas; the Institute for Scientific
Research, Zaire; the International Coun¬
cil of Scientific Unions (ICSU); the Com¬
mittee on Science and Technology in
Developing Countries (COSTED); and the
World Federation of Scientific Workers
(WFSW).
These institutions are collaborating
within the framework of regional groups
or are associated with specific working
groups, such as those related to the cre¬
ation of an information system and data
banks on research and human needs, one
on methodologies in the same field, and
another on trends in research in this area.
For further discussion of this subject see
Unesco's Impact of Science on Society
Vol. 29, no. 3, July-September 1979.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
"Science has demonstrated its power, most convincingly
in the development of new technologies... The discovery
of fire, the invention of language, the use of the wheel,
the moulding of shapes... the development of harness for
draft animals, the invention of gunpowder, printing and
the magnetic compass all seemed like accidents to which
very little attention was paid at first but which later turned
out to be powerful agents of change in human society. "
Alberto Giacometti's Chariot, 1950
"We are living through a
revolution in information
technology which is
transforming the way
knowledge is stored and
exchanged, touching the
very core of our culture. "
ment between science and human
values. The message of science will
then cease to be purely technical, and it
will be possible to understand man in all
his complexity, in his need for social
stability just as much as in his desire for
personal freedom.
A science policy directed along these
new avenues could act as a powerful
force for change, and most probably a
wholly beneficial one. Properly applied,
it could help man understand the full
range of problems he faces today and
will face tomorrow. It could help to
distinguish between real human needs,
and the false gods created by ideology.
The alliance between science and socie¬
ty could thus help to prepare the
ground for a new culture, and provide a
new spirit so often sought by today's
social critics. Everything possible must
be done to help reconcile the natural
sciences with what man perceives as
his human rights, and how this might
be done is beginning to emerge: human
mobility, the transfer of technology, the
rapprochement between human and
physical sciences, the growth of infor¬
mation technology and the reform of
education could all have a part to play.
But preparing the ground is not
enough. It is also necessary to envisage
a decisive event in our earlier analogy,
a "trigger"which opens the way
towards one solution among the many
which seem at present to be equally
possible.
The remote past can provide ex¬
amples of such agents of change. The
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
*
discovery of fire, the invention of
language, the use of the wheel, the
moulding of shapes, first with ceramics,
then with metals; closer to our own
time, the development of harness for
draft animals, the invention of gun¬
powder, printing and the magnetic
compass all seemed like accidents to
which very little attention was paid at
first but which later turned out to be
powerful agents of change in human
society.
Pasteur could not have guessed that
his work with micro-organisms and pro¬
tection from disease by vaccination
would lead ultimately to a new attitude
towards life and death because of its
dramatic effect on the growth of
populations. The engineers responsible
for developing the various kinds of heat
engine had no idea that they were help¬
ing bring into being a civilization which
would conquer air and space. We
ourselves are living through a revolution
in information technology which is
transforming the way knowledge is
stored and exchanged, touching the
very core of our culture.
There is not much chance that man
will ever be able to predict the long-
term consequences of such changes,
but at least he should by now be aware
that such processes do effect human
evolution. He can then attempt to con¬
trol them, either by strangling them at
birth if their effects are by general
agreement likely to be disastrous, or by
encouraging them if their results seem
likely to respond to a real need.
This process of planning by looking
out for key triggering events calls for
some thought. In the state of uncertain¬
ty we find ourselves in today, the only
certainty we have is that things cannot
go on the way they are, and we must
accept that an abrupt change lies
ahead. This being so, then everybody
must be allowed to express their point
of view. One can bring "imagination to
power" by allowing inventive ideas to
come forward, and one can also select
those specialist areas where new ideas
are likely to be most productive. For ex¬
ample, it is probable that tropical
agriculture might be transformed if one
could attach nitrogen-fixing bacteria to
the roots of cereal crops; there is thus
every reason for a special effort in this
area.
The process then becomes a ques¬
tion of political priorities, but one must
always keep an eye open for the unex¬
pected. The discovery of penicillin,
partly a lucky chance, turned out to be
much more important than all other
contemporary work on chemotherapy.
Without denying that progress could
be made if our society were better
educated in science and technology, it
would be naive to believe that the huge
questions facing humanity today could
be so simply solved. The technology we
have is relevant only in particular
places, at particular times, and under
particular political conditions.
Western society is not exportable; it
consumes too much energy and too
many primary products. High levels of
mechanization are not suited to the
growing pool of unemployed man¬
power in the developing countries.
Agricultural techniques work only in a
temperate climate where the land is
good, exposed neither to drought nor
to soil erosion. They do not produce a
high return without the use of fertilizer
and pesticides, and they consume
through the use of machines many
more fuel calories than are produced by
the food which is grown. Such a solu¬
tion cannot be applied generally in any
situation, nor is it likely to survive for
ever even in the developed countries.
One can multiply examples: if im¬
proved health standards prolong life
and reduce perinatal mortality (as they
do) and if they are not accompanied by
a reduction in birth-rates, then popula¬
tion problems sooner or later become
insoluble; which brings the matter back
into the realm of morals. To believe that
all that is necessary is to extract the
knowledge one needs from a reservoir,
like water from a well, is an enormous
error, unfortunately widely shared.
What is needed is to establish basic
research facilities and so direct them
that they follow useful paths leading to
the solution of the problems of
underdevelopment. The science of the
North has until now taken little account
of the needs of the South, and the
research workers of the South, often
excellent in quality if limited in number,
have not concentrated on problems
relevant to their own areas, absorbed as
they are in the science of the developed
world. It is time for a change.
I André Danzin and Ilya Prigogina
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Mother tongue
and the brain
A Japanese specialist's surprising discovery
by Howard Brabyn
ENCLOSED in the protective armour
of the skull, enveloped in several
membranes and surrounded by a
shock-absorbing cushion of fluid, the brain,
a lump of wrinkled, pinkish-grey matter the
size of a small cantaloupe melon and
weighing around 1,360 grammes, is at the
origin of every thought, feeling or action of
which man is capable
Packed into this confined space are an
estimated ten thousand million neurons,
microscopic nerve cells that constitute the
working units of the brain, grouped into
millions of individual circuits that each per¬
form a function assigned to it by heredity or
learned by experience.
The brain, of course, is not a purely
human attribute. Even the most primitive
forms of animal life have an organ that
might be crudely approximated to a brain.
Only in man, however, has the brain
elaborated sufficiently to be able to cope
with language, the evolutionary gift that
enables us to communicate what we have
learned and to pass down from generation
to generation our collective experience and
memory.
Over the past hundred years, scientists
have attempted, with considerable success,
to map the brain and to determine which
cells control which activities. They have
discovered that the brain is divided into two
hemispheres, each controlling the physical
functioning of half the body. For some
unknown reason, the nerves from the body
cross over in the spinal cord before they
reach the brain. Thus the left arm, left leg,
etc., are controlled by the right half of the
brain, while the right side of the body takes
its orders from the left hemisphere.
Specialization of the two hemispheres,
however, goes beyond purely physical con¬
trol. In 1861, the French surgeon Paul Broca
discovered the area of the brain involved in
HOWARD BRABYN is editor of the English
edition of the Unesco Courier.
articulate speech and furnished the first
anatomical proof of localization of brain
function; and in 1874, the German
neurologist Carl Wernicke located the area
of the left hemisphere concerned with com¬
prehension of spoken or written language.
In more recent years ever more refined ex¬
periments have shown that in about ninety-
five per cent of people, in addition to
language, the left hemisphere controls such
logical processes as mathematics, while the
right hemisphere is involved in non-verbal
activities of a more artistic or emotional
nature.
In fact, three centres of the left
hemisphere of the brain are involved in
language skills (see diagram). In Wernicke's
area words are selected from the verbal
memory. If writing is involved, the muscles
of the hand are alerted. If speech is to be
used, Broca's area, which controls articula¬
tion, comes into play. When vision is involv¬
ed, another centre known as the angular
gyrus acts as a link between Wernicke's area
and'the visual cortex.
Ever since Broca and Wernicke, this
lateralization of the speech function in the
left hemisphere of the brain has been one of
the major themes of neuropsychology. A
great deal of current research involves
observation of how normal people respond
to auditory stimulation given separately to
the right and left brain hemispheres.
A leading figure in this field of research,
professor Tadanobu Tsunoda of the Medical
Research Institute of the Medical and Dental
University, Tokyo, has been conducting ex¬
periments on right or left brain dominance
for some fifteen years, and in a paper
presented at a Unesco symposium held in
Athens in April 1981, he revealed some of
the astonishing findings of his research.
These findings have important implications
for education and give the lie to certain
deep-rooted racist assumptions.
The story began in 1965, when professor
Tsunoda undertook a series of experiments,
with a group of normal Japanese subjects,
aimed at determining ear-dominance for a
group of vowel sounds and spoken syllables
in the Japanese language. It should be
borne in mind that left ear dominance for a
particular sound indicates right brain
dominance for that sound, and that right ear
dominance indicates left brain dominance,
since the auditory nerves of each ear in large
part connect with the opposite side of the
brain.
Professor Tsunoda had devised
sophisticated techniques of auditory
stimulation using delayed feedback (see box
page 12 for detailed explanation) designed
to test how the brain distinguishes various
types of sounds, such as mechanical noises,
vowel sounds and synthetic tones, and to
establish with remarkable precision which
brain hemisphere is dominant for a particular
sound.
The tests, repeated over a number of
years, each time with native Japanese sub¬
jects, conclusively indicated right ear (left
brain) dominance for both spoken syllables
and what are known as "steady-state"
vowels in Japanese. So far, however, there
was nothing particularly unexpected in
these results.
Tsunoda then continued his experiments
by replacing human vowel sounds with syn¬
thetic noises resembling vowel sounds in
structure. Analysis of human vowel sounds
showed the existence of a series of
characteristic frequency peaks known as
formants. Using a synthesizer, it was possi¬
ble to probe deeper by filtering out certain
formants. He discovered that two condi¬
tions had to be fulfilled for a synthesized
sound to cause right ear (left brain)
dominance: the frequencies of the formants
had to be inharmonic and there had to be a
certain minimum degree of frequency
modulation.
This stage of the experiments showed
that the brain is capable of detecting the
structural features of sounds and that left or
right brain dominance is determined on the
basis of the structure of sounds heard. It
was noted that human vowel sounds, sobb¬
ing, laughter, insect chirping and other
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Motor Cortex
I
E
Primary visual area
Angular gyrus
Wernicke's area
Although the two hemispheres into which the brain is divided
appear to be symmetrical in structure, they are not identical in
function. Language skills are located In specific areas of the left
hemisphere (above). The mechanics of speech are controlled by
Broca's area while Wernicke's area functions as a word retriever
and selector. When language depends upon vision, as in reading
and writing, the angular gyrus acts as a link between the primary
visual area and Wernicke's area.
natural sounds all have frequency modula¬
tion and inharmonic combinations and that,
among the Japanese subjects tested, these
all induced right ear (left brain) dominance.
The true significance of these findings on¬
ly became fully apparent when, in 1972, by
pure chance, professor Tsunoda applied his
tests to his first non-Japanese subject, a
Frenchman. To his surprise he found that
the French subject showed marked dif¬
ferences from his Japanese subjects in the
patterns of cerebral dominance in response
to the same auditory stimuli. After further
experiments with both Japanese and non-
Japanese subjects, professor Tsunoda
became convinced that the difference bet¬
ween them was due to the influence of the
mother tongue.
Professor Tsunoda proceeded to build up
overwhelming experimental evidence for his
theory. Altogether he tested fifty-seven
speakers of West European languages such
as English, French, Spanish, Italian, German
and Swedish; fifteen Chinese speakers (Pek¬
ing, Canton, Shanghai and Taiwan
dialects); seventeen speakers of Korean; as
well as a number of native language
speakers from Vietnam, Cambodia,
Thailand, Indonesia, Israel and Africa.
The results of these tests were con¬
clusive. They indicated that "steady-state"
vowel sounds as well as pure tones induced
left ear (right brain) dominance, while
syllables elicited right ear (left brain)
dominance. Only native speakers of Polyne¬
sian languages (Tonganese, Eastern Sa-
moan and Maori) showed the same
dominance patterns as the Japanese,
displaying right ear (left brain) dominance
for both vowels and syllables and left ear
(right brain) dominance for pure tone
sounds.
To answer the question as to whether the
difference between Japanese and non-
Japanese might be genetic, twenty second
and third generation Japanese emigrants
were tested. Of these twenty, eighteen who
spoke Spanish, Portuguese or English as
their mother tongue until the age of eight
showed Western-type dominance patterns.
The remaining two, who were educated in
Japanese until the age of nine, showed
Japanese-type dominance patterns. In con¬
trast to this, two Americans and four
Koreans who were brought up in Japan
showed the Japanese-type dominance pat¬
tern. The difference in patterns was
therefore clearly caused by the auditory and
linguistic environment and not by genetic
factors.
Despite these differences in brain
dominance patterns it is still correct to con¬
sider the left hemisphere as the "verbal
brain" in both groups of people because
their left hemispheres, in both cases, are
dominant for syllable sounds. But what is it
that makes Japanese and Polynesian people
exhibit left brain dominance for both vowel
and syllable sounds whereas other people
show right brain dominance for vowel
sounds and left brain dominance for syllable
sounds?
The answer seems to lie in a common
feature of the Japanese and Polynesian
languages: the presence in them of a large
number of vowel-only words and words
with two or more vowels combined with
consonants. In these vowel-dominant
languages vowels are as important as con¬
sonants in the cognition of words and
sentences. As a result, vowel sounds are
processed in the left or "verbal" hemisphere
of the brain because for those languages
they have the same importance as any other
speech sounds. What is more, any natural
sound with a vowel-like spectrum is also
processed mainly in the verbal hemisphere.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Test 1 Test 2
Right
Sound to right
ear delayed
0.2 seconds
Left Right Left
Sound to left
ear delayed
0.2 seconds
Synchronous tone
at a constant
intensity of
40 decibels
Delayed auditory
feedback relay
In Test 1. orderly tapping is
disrupted at 55 decibels,
i.e. at an intensity of
15 decibels above the constant
synchronous sound.
Electronic switch,
sound source and
amplifier
Delayed auditory
feedback relay
In Test 2. orderly tapping is
disrupted at 75 decibels,
i.e. at an intensity of
35 decibels above the constant
synchronous sound.
The two tests show a right ear (left brain) advantage
for this type of stimuli of 35 minus 15 = 20 decibels.
The key tap brain-dominance test
When we speak, we hear, simul¬
taneously, the words we utter, and nor¬
mal conversation Is controlled by this
"auditory feedback". If, however, we put
on headphones incorporating a delaying
device so that we hear what we have said
about 0.2 of a second later, then our
speech becomes disturbed.
Professor Tsunoda's brain-dominance
test is based on this phenomenon
(known as "the Lee effect"), but instead
of testing a subject's speech perfor¬
mance he asks him to tap out con¬
tinuously a rhythmic pattern on a key
similar to those used for transmitting
messages in Morse. Each tap on the key
produces a short pure tone and, when
this is fed back synchronously to both
ears through the headphones worn by
the subject, he is able to maintain con¬
tinuous, correct tapping patterns; but,
just as with speech, when the auditory
feedback is delayed, the rhythmic tapp¬
ing pattern is disturbed.
The next step is to feed synchronous
sounds to one ear while sending the
same sounds, delayed by 0.2 of a second,
to the other ear. The subject is told to tap
out a continuous, stable sound pattern
and to concentrate his attention on it as
it is fed back synchronously to one ear.
At the same time low-intensity delayed
sounds are fed to the other ear. As the in¬
tensity of the delayed sounds is gradually
raised above the constant intensity of the
synchronous tones, it becomes extreme¬
ly difficult to maintain the correct tapp¬
ing pattern and the threshold at which
orderly tapping is disrupted (the delayed
auditory feedback or DAF threshold, as it
is called) is measured.
When the process is repeated with the
hearing channels transposed, the
delayed auditory feedback thresholds of
the two ears can be compared and we
can establish which ear (and therefore
which hemisphere of the brain) is domi¬
nant in a particular test subject for a
specific sound. Remember that right ear
dominance means left brain dominance
and left ear dominance means right brain
dominance, since the auditory nerves
from each ear cross over and connect
with opposite sides of the brain.
In the first of the two hypothetical
tests illustrated above the DAF threshold
is reached at 55 decibels, that is, at 15
decibels above the constant intensity of
40 decibels of the synchronous sound be¬
ing fed to the left ear. The hearing chan¬
nels are then switched and the second
test is performed. In this case the DAF
threshold is reached at 75 decibels, or 35
decibels above the constant, syn¬
chronous decibels this time being fed to
the right ear. Comparing the two DAF
thresholds it can be seen that, for this
particular subject, the right ear (left
brain) advantage for this type of stimuli
is 20 decibels (i.e. 35 minus 15). In other
words, the subject has been able to con¬
centrate better on the synchronous tone
in the right ear than on the same tone in
the left ear. The right ear (left brain) is
therefore dominant for this specific tone
for this particular subject.
This key-tapping method can be used
to measure ear (and therefore brain)
dominance for many kinds of sounds, in¬
cluding vowel, mechanical and en¬
vironmental sounds.
Professor Tsunoda sums up his findings in
the following terms:
"The dominance patterns of the Japanese
people for various sounds suggest that their
function of emotion, together with the
language and language-based logical func¬
tion, is based in the verbal brain. In contrast
the brain of the Western person clearly
specializes the language and related logical
functions in the verbal hemisphere and
separates the function of emotion in the
non-verbal hemisphere (see diagram).
"In the Japanese people, sounds related
to emotion are processed in the left brain,
and this left brain dominance becomes firm¬
ly established as speech ability is developed.
Then the left brain also becomes dominant
for emotional functions as a result of the
established link between emotion-related
sounds and emotion-related experiences.
"The same processes apply to non-
Japanese people with respect to their right
brain dominance for emotion-related sounds
and functions. It can therefore be said that
the laterality of emotion is acquired through
the mother tongue.
"I believe that the mother tongue differen¬
tiates the way in which people receive, pro¬
cess, feel and understand sounds from the
external environment. The mother tongue is
closely related to the development of the
emotional mechanism in the brain. I conjec¬
ture that the mother tongue acquired in
childhood is closely linked with the forma¬
tion of the unique culture and mentality of
each ethnic group."
H Howard Brabyn
The song of the cricket
At a critical moment in his research on the
brain Professor Tsunoda was seated in
front of his recording apparatus unable to
work. Through the open window he could
hear the chirping of a cricket. Idly he
switched on his recorder, but when he
played back the recording he was
astonished to find that the sonogram
showed a remarkable similarity in the
sound structure of the cricket's song and
the vowel-sound structure of the Japanese
language. Further experiments showed that
this was true of other natural sounds such
as the rustle of the wind, the sound of
running water and the breaking of waves,
as well as of human non-verbal sounds,
such as sighing, that convey emotion.
Because of their similarity to vowel sound
structures, all these sounds are processed
in the left or verbal hemisphere of the brain
in people of Japanese or Polynesian mother
tongue, whereas they are processed in the
right brain hemisphere in people of non-
Japanese or Polynesian mother tongue (see
diagram opposite page, above). This, says
Professor Tsunoda, is because, unlike most
of the world's languages, in which
consonant-vowel-consonant syllables
predominate, the Japanese and Polynesian
languages are marked by the presence of
many vowel-only and vowel-consonant-
vowel words. This may also in part account
for a marked characteristic of written
Japanese, its poetry, literature and art the
many references to nature and natural
sounds. Opposite, an illustration for the
famous 11th-century Japanese literary
masterpiece. The Tale of Genjl, by the 17th-
century artist Sumiyoshi Gukei.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Comparison of brain-function patterns
Japanese Pattern
Left Hemisphere Right Hemisphere
Language \ i
Vowels «	,1
f=E
_) Consonants
9 Human voices
P Animal sounds
Singing of insects
The sounds of
traditional Japanese
musical instruments
# Calculation j \
i Kokoro (heart/soul)
t
i
0 Logos
# Pathos
# Nature
I Mechanical sounds\
) Music
^The sounds of
Western musical
instruments
Mono (thing)
Material things
Left Hemisphere
Language
Western Pattern
Right Hemisphere
Consonants
I Logos
Vowels
Human voices
Mechanical sounds\
i Music
I Animal sounds
* 3
fEEi ^Singing of insects
fei
The sounds of traditional
Japanese musical'instruments
/
The sounds of Western
musical instruments
) Pathos
Nature
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
a/	 fl%AHA\ /¡^mm/ mf0*mM&m
-**-..
I ft 4* ""^4G.
SrV
Photo © State Literary Museum, Moscow
Holograph manuscript from Dostoyevsky's notebook for Crime and
Punishment. "This is a psychological account of a crime...", he wrote of
the plot. "A young man expelled from the university..., living in the
direst poverty, the victim of certain bizarre 'half-baked' ideas that are in
the wind, decides out of lightheadedness and instability of thinking to
extricate himself from his deplorable situation with one bold stroke. He
decides to kill an old woman... a money-lender... There are no
suspicions of him. Then the psychological process of the crime unfolds.
Insoluble questions arise before the murderer, unsuspected and
unexpected feelings torment his heart... and he finally feels forced to
give himself up..."
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The centenary of the death of Fyodor Mikhailovich Dostoyevsky (1821-1881),
the great Russian writer whose works have been translated into more than
fifty languages, was celebrated at Unesco last December by an exhibition
organized by the USSR Permanent Delegation, on the theme "the world of
Dostoyevsky as reflected in Soviet museum collections". There are seven
Dostoyevsky museums in the Soviet Union, each in a place where the great
novelist spent part of his life. In the article below and the pictorial biography
on pages 16 to 21, Madame Elena Dmitrievna Mikhailova, who organized the
Unesco exhibition, evokes Dostoyevsky's world, life and works through
photos and documents from these museums. On page 23 the Mexican poet
and essayist Octavio Paz gives a Latin American view of the man whom he
describes as "our great contemporary".
The world of Dostoyevsky
by Elena Dmitrievna Mikhailova
FYODOR Mikhailovich Dostoyevsky
was born in 1821, in an apartment at
the Mariinskaya hospital where his
father was a doctor. He spent the first six¬
teen years of his life in these surroundings,
forming his first impressions of the "insulted
and injured" by observing the poor who
came to the hospital for treatment. During
these formative years he entered the world
of books through the works of Pushkin,
Gogol and Walter Scott. The death of his
mother acquainted him with misfortune at
an early age. Then, although he remained a
Muscovite at heart, he left Moscow for St.
Petersburg where he entered the military
engineering school.
The last year of Dostoyevsky's life is also
linked with Moscow. On 6 June 1880 he
delivered his celebrated speech on Pushkin
during the inauguration ceremony of a
monument to his favourite poet. This ad¬
dress, in which he affirmed the noble calling
of the artistic genius, who should preserve a
bond with the people and should aspire to
universality, stirred all Russia and stimulated
widespread debate and reflection.
In 1928, part of the former Mariinskaya
hospital was turned into the F.M. Dostoyev¬
sky Museum, a branch of the State Literary
Museum. Its exhibits consist largely of a
donation from Dostoyevsky's second wife,
Anna Grigorievna, which had been
presented to the city of Moscow in 1916.
Ever since then the Museum's collection has
continued to grow. The building is currently
being restored, and the Dostoyevsky
family's apartment is being entirely rebuilt. It
is planned that a literary exhibition will be
held on the first and second floors.
Dostoyevsky's creative activity will always
be associated with St. Petersburg (now Len-
ELENA DMITRIEVNA MIKHAILOVA, Soviet
philologist, is director of the scientific and metho¬
dological service of the State Literary Museum,
Moscow. She has organized many exhibitions,
both in the Soviet Union and abroad, and is the
author of a number of studies on museology.
ingrad) where he studied at the engineering
school and where the avant-garde writers
Belinsky, Nekrasov and their friends gave an
enthusiastic reception to his first novel, Poor
Folk. There too he joined the circle of young
writers, scientists, philosophers and officers
who had gathered around the 28-year-old
Mikhail Petrashevsky, whose attachment to
Utopian socialism they shared.
During their regular Friday meetings they
analysed the works of the French socialists
François Marie Charles Fourier and the
Comte de Saint-Simon, and those of the
Welsh Utopian socialist Robert Owen. They
recited Pushkin's poems and read articles by
avant-garde Russian journalists which had
been banned by the Tsarist censorship. The
group's activities were cut short in 1849
when its members were arrested and con¬
demned to death, a sentence which was
commuted at the last minute to one of penal
servitude.
Dostoyevsky was condemned for "having
had criminal designs to be deprived... of the
enjoyment of all his possessions and to be
deported to a fortress to serve a sentence of
eight years hard labour". The Tsar decided
to modify the sentence to four years hard
labour to be followed by service in the army,
in the full knowledge that by commuting the
penalty he made it harsher.
On his return to St. Petersburg, after ten
years of prison and military service,
Dostoyevsky again took up writing and jour¬
nalism. The creation of his most compelling
work, from The House of the Dead (1861 -62)
to The Brothers Karamazov (1879-80) is con¬
nected with St. Petersburg. In 1971, to mark
the 150th anniversary of his birth, part of the
building where he spent his final years was
transformed into a museum.
In the 1870s, the Dostoyevsky family
began spending the summer, and
sometimes the winter, at the resort of
Staraya Russa in Novgorod district. In these
surroundings he could work and also devote
more time to his children and to family life. It
was at Staraya Russa that he wrote A Raw
Youth, some chapters of 777e Brothers
Karamazov, his Pushkin speech, and many
page's of The Diary of a Writer. On 4 May
1981 a museum was inaugurated in this
country house whose original setting and
atmosphere have been scrupulously
recreated.
At Omsk, where Dostoyevsky served his
sentence of hard labour, preparations are
under way for the inauguration of a museum
which will be attached to the Historical and
Architectural Museum created in the house
of A.F. de Grave, commandant of the Omsk
fortress whom Dostoyevsky described as
"an extremely decent person", and who
entertained the writer as an equal. The
Dostoyevsky room will become the nucleus
of this museum which aims to present
a panorama of the literature of the entire
Omsk region.
After serving his term of hard labour at
Omsk, Dostoyevsky went to Semipalatinsk,
also in Siberia, to do his military service.
While there he worked on The House of the
Dead, and dreamed of returning to the
literary life of St. Petersburg. It was at
Semipalatinsk that he met his first wife,
Marya Dmitrievna Isaeva. "She was the light
of my life", he wrote. "She appeared at the
gloomiest moment in my existence and
revived my soul." The house he occupied at
Semipalatinsk between 1857 and 1859 has
long been a museum. A new annexe to it
has just been completed.
Another Dostoyevsky museum is current¬
ly being created in the nearby town of
Novokuznetsk, in the house of D.I. Isaeva,
where the writer visited his wife-to-be.
Finally, an exhibition on The Brothers
Karamazov and Dostoyevsky's other work
has been organized in the little house where
the novelist stayed during a two-day visit to
the monastery of Optina Pustyn, not far
from Kaluga, in 1878. The exhibition evokes
the impressions made on Dostoyevsky dur¬
ing his stay by his conversations with the
Elder Amvrosii, the prototype of Father
Zossima, a character in the novel.
The seven museums perform a dual task.
They provide visitors with an opportunity to
acquire a deeper understanding of the
writer's work as a whole, to enter the world
of his imagination, to understand his aspira¬
tions, his periods of discouragement and the
times when work poured from his pen, and
to grasp the full complexity of his creative
and philosophical quest.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
PORTRAIT
OF A GENIUS
A pictorial
biography
of Dostoyevsky
Mikhail Andreevich and Mariya Fyodorovna
Dostoyevsky, the writer's parents (from a
pastel of 1823). A graduate of the Imperial
Medical-Surgical Academy in Moscow,
Dostoyevsky's father was a "sullen, nervous,
suspicious" man, according to the writer's first
biographer. His mother was a gentle, pensive
woman with a talent for literature.
This sketch is the first known portrait of Dostoyevsky. It
was drawn by his classmate at the St. Petersburg
Academy of Engineers, Konstantin Trutovsky, who later
became a well-known artist. It shows Dostoyevsky as he
was In 1847, the year in which he wrote Poor Folk, a novel
which was acclaimed by the celebrated critic Vissarion
G. Belinsky, who wrote: "Honour and glory to the young
poet whose muse inspires love for the garret- and
basement-dwellers and cries out to those living in gilded
palaces: 'Why! They too are human beings, your brothers!'
Entrance arch and wing of the former
Mariinsky Hospital in Moscow, where
Dostoyevsky's father was a doctor. Visible
through the archway are the porch and
entrance to the apartment where
Dr. Dostoyevsky and his family lived. Today
the whole wing where the family apartment
was located is occupied by the F.M.
Dostoyevsky Museum-Apartment.
Phot« ( Sum UMnry MuMum.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
-
Among the exhibits preserved in the Moscow Museum are
Dostoyevsky's desk and some of the tools of his trade including
the favourite pen with which be wrote many pages of The Brothers
Karamazov and The Diary of a. Writer.
A The writer's widow, Anna
Grigor'evna, photographed in
1916 in the Dostoyevsky
Room of the Moscow
Historical Museum with
some of the Dostoyevskyana
she had donated to the
Museum.
Many artists have found
inspiration in the works of
Dostoyevsky. This illustration
to Poor Folk was drawn by
his contemporary Boklevsky
and depicts the novel's hero,
Makar Devushkin. In this
early work the writer
expressed what he called an
"idea central to all
nineteenth century art", the
"rehabilitation of an innocent
victim crushed by the weight
of circumstances, centuries
of stagnation and social
prejudices. The idea is the
vindication of the
downtrodden and of all
outcasts of society."
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
PORTRAIT
OF A GENIUS
(continued)
Drawing by Mikhail Znamensky in 1888
shows the lay-out of the prison at Omsk in
Siberia where Dostoyevsky served his
sentence of hard labour. In The House of
the Dead he described the prison: "Imagine
a large courtyard, 200 paces long and 150
wide, in the form of an irregular hexagon,
all enclosed by a paling, that is, a fence of
high posts stuck deeply into the earth,
touching one another, strengthened by
crosswise planks and pointed at the top;
this was the outer fence of the prison. On
one side of the fence there is a strong gate,
always closed, always, day and night,
guarded by sentries; it is opened on
instructions, to let us out to work... And
how much youth lay uselessly buried
within those walls, what mighty powers
were wasted here in vain! After all, one
must tell the whole truth: those men were
exceptional men... But their mighty
energies were vainly wasted, wasted
abnormally, unjustly, hopelessly. And who
was to blame, whose fault was it? That's
just it, who was to blame?"
In 1849 Dostoyevsky and other members of the Petrashevsky circle of Utopian
socialists to which he belonged, were arrested. Dostoyevsky was sentenced to
death. On the morning of 22 December he and his fellow-prisoners were taken
to their place of execution, the Semenovsky parade-ground. When all the
preliminaries of the execution had been carried out, it was announced that they
had been reprieved. Dostoyevsky's sentence was commuted to forced labour in
Siberia. Engraving below, by an anonymous 19th-century artist, recreates the
execution scene. Recalling the event in his Diary of a Writer (1873), Dostoyevsky
wrote: "We... stood on the scaffold and listened to our verdict without the
slightest repentance... The deed for which we were convicted; those ideas and
conceptions which ruled our spirit, were regarded by us not only as not
requiring repentance but even as something purifying as martyrdom for which
we would be forgiven much!" In the same book he wrote: "We were infected
with the ideas of the then prevailing theoretical socialism... All these new ideas
of those days were tremendously appealing to us in Petersburg; they seemed
sublimely sacred and moral and, most important of all, common to all mankind,
the law for all humanity, without exception, in the future. Even long before the
Paris Revolution of '48, we fell under the fascinating influence of these ideas.
Already in '46, I had been initiated by Belinsky into the whole truth of that
future 'regenerated world' and into the whole sanctity of the future communist
society..."	
Aleksandr I. Ivanov, a doctor at the prison
in Omsk where Dostoyevsky served his
sentence of penal servitude from 1850 to
1854. Ivanov and his superior. Dr. I.I.
Troitsky treated the writer with great
solicitude and tried to keep him in hospital
as long as possible to enable him to write.
Whenever Dostoyevsky left the hospital he
would give his notebook to Ivanov for safe
keeping. He later used this notebook,
which contained some 500 entries popular
expressions, witticisms, scenes of everyday
lifeas material for The House of the Dead
and other novels. "How many native types,
characters, did I take with me from
prison," Dostoyevsky wrote to his brother
in February 1854 after his release. "I lived
side by side with them and therefore, it
seems, I know them pretty well. How
many tales of vagabonds, robbers and, in
general, of the whole black, wretched
existence. There is enough for entire
volumes."
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Dostoyevsky (right) and the Kazakh scholar
and teacher Chokan Valikhanov whom he
met in Omsk. They later met in
Semipalatinsk, where Dostoyevsky served
as a soldier after his release from prison.
In December 1859 Dostoyevsky returned from Siberia to St.
Petersburg (now Leningrad). The Leningrad building where he
lived from 1878 until his death on 9 February 1881 today houses
the F.M. Dostoyevsky Literary and Memorial Museum. It was
here that he wrote his novel The Brothers Karamazov. The
Museum is located in the last apartment occupied by the
Dostoyevskys, and literary exhibitions dealing with his life and
works are held in rooms adjoining the apartment. Dostoyevsky's
study has been arranged to recapture the setting in which he
often workedat night, by candlelight (photo below).
Photo taken in 1881 of Dostoyevsky's house at the resort town of
Staraya Russa. "Fyodor Mikhailovich considered our Staraya
Russa villa his place of physical and emotional peace..."
{Reminiscences of Anna G. Dostoyevskaya). The house is now a
Dostoyevsky museum.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
PORTRAIT
OF A GENIUS
(continued)
In 1878 Dostoyevsky paid a brief
visit to the monastery of Optina
Pustyn. While there he met the
Elder Amvrosii, the prototype of
Father Zossima, a figure who
would play a key part in his last
great novel. The Brothers
Karamazov. Photo left shows
Amvrosii's cell at Optina Pustyn.
An illustration to Book V ("Pro and
Contra") of The Brothers Karamazov
showing the famous conversation
between two of the brothers, Alyosha
and Ivan. Ivan's terrible admission ("I
do not accept this world of God's")
reflects Dostoyevsky's own tortured
doubts: "I want to tell you this about
myself: I am a child of this age, a child
of disbelief and doubt... I have been
and still am tormented by longing for
belief, which grows all the stronger the
more reasons I have not to believe...
More than that, if anyone proved to me
that Christ was outside the truth, and it
really was a fact that the truth was
outside of Christ, I would rather remain
with Christ than with the truth." Thus
wrote Dostoyevsky in a reappraisal of
his views after his release from penal
servitude.
/« V;*¿¿áar>*
- WE\\
F-HÍ
ir " 1f ^ -
wM
A
ffiL,*
L_ fei
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Illustration by the artist
Dobuzhinsky for Dostoyevsky's
White Nights.
A still from the film of
Dostoyevsky's novel The
Idiot, directed by Ivan Pyr'ev.
The role of Prince Myshkin
(right) is played by Yuri
Yakovlev and that of
Rogozhin (centre) by
L. Parkhomenko.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Dostoyevsky
'our great
contemporary'
by Octavio Paz
Text © Copyright.
Reproduction prohibited
OCTAVIO PAZ, Mexican poet and essayist, is
one of the most outstanding writers in the
Spanish language today. He has been Mexico's
ambassador to India and has taught at several
universities, including Cambridge (U.K. ¡where he
was Simon Bolivar Professor of Latin American
studies. He has published several volumes of
poetry, including Libertad bajo Palabra ("Liberty
on Parole"). English translations of his essays in¬
clude Claude Lévi-Strauss: An Introduction
(19721 and Alternating Current (1973). In 1981 he
was awarded the Cervantes Prize, one of the
highest distinctions in Spanish literature. The arti¬
cle published here has been abridged from a
longer study
SINCE his death a century ago,
Dostoyevsky's influence has con¬
stantly grown and spread: first in his
own country, where he had already achiev¬
ed renown during his lifetime, then in
Europe, America and Asia. This influence
has not been exclusively literary; it has af¬
fected the way people feel, think and live.
Several generations have read his novels not
as fiction but as studies on mankind, and
hundreds of thousands of readers all over
the world have taken part in silent conversa¬
tion and debate with his characters, as if
they were old acquaintances.
His work left a mark on minds as different
as Nietzsche and Gide, Faulkner and Camus.
Two modern Mexican writers, José
Vasconcelos and José Revueltas were pas¬
sionate readers of Dostoyevsky, perhaps
because they belonged to the same intellec¬
tual family and saw themselves in many of
his ideas and obsessions. I still remember
the interminable conversations I had with
my classmates when finishing my bac¬
calauréat: Ivan and Dimitri Karamazov war¬
red in every one of us.
Nothing could be more natural than this
passion, for in spite of the century that
divides us, Dostoyevsky is our great con¬
temporary. Very few writers of the past are
so much of our time; to read his novels is to
read a chronicle of the twentieth century.
But his modernity is not that of the latest in¬
tellectual or literary fashion. By virtue of his
tastes and preoccupations he is a writer of
another age; he is given to prolixity, and
were it not for his extremely modern sense
of humour many of his pages would be
tedious. His historical world is not ours. His
vision of history, .though sometimes pro¬
found, is nevertheless confused. It lacks
that quick, penetrating grasp of events
which delights us, for example, in Stendhal.
Nor did he possess the gaze of a Tocqueville
which could pierce the surface of a society
and an age. Nor was he, like Tolstoy, an an¬
nalist on an epic scale.
He does not give us a description of what
is happening, but instead forces us to "go
underground" in order to see what is really
going on; he forces us to see ourselves in
ourselves. Dostoyevsky is our contemporary
because he foretold the dramas and con¬
flicts of our age, and he did this neither
because he had the gift of second sight nor
because he was capable of foreseeing
events, but because he had the ability to
penetrate into the interior of human beings.
He was one of the first, perhaps the first,
to give an account of modern nihilism. His
descriptions of this mental state are un¬
forgettable and still compel the reader by
their penetration and mysterious accuracy.
The nihilism of Antiquity was related to
scepticism and epicureanism: its ideal was a
noble serenity, the attainment of equanimity
in face of the vicissitudes of fortune. The
nihilism of ancient India, which so impress¬
ed Alexander and his entourage, was a
philosophical position in some ways similar
to that of the Greek philosopher Pyrrho of
Elis and one which led to the contemplation
of the void. For Nagarjuna and his followers,
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
nihilism was the antechamber of religion.
But modern nihilism, although it too springs
from an intellectual conviction, leads neither
to philosophical impassibility nor to the blest
state of imperturbability. It is rather an in¬
ability to create or affirm anything, more of a
spiritual flaw than a philosophy.
Nietzsche imagined the coming of a
"complete nihilist", embodied in the Super¬
man who would play, dance and laugh in
the gyrations of the Eternal Return. The
dance of the Superman celebrates universal
insignificance, the evaporation of con¬
sciousness, and the subversion of values.
But the true nihilist, as Dostoyevsky more
realistically envisaged, neither dances nor
laughs: he moves restlessly from place to
place around his room or around the
world, it's all the same to himwithout ever
being capable of doing anything. He is con¬
demned to go round and round in circles,
talking to his fantasms. His sickness, like
that of Sade's libertines or of the medieval
monks who were afflicted with accidie, is a
constant dissatisfaction, an inability to love
anything or anyone, an aimless agitation,
self-disgust and also self-love.
The modern nihilist is a wretched Nar¬
cissus who looks in the water and sees his
¡mage shattered into fragments. The spec¬
tacle of his downfall fascinates him: he feels
sick at the sight of himself yet cannot tear
his eyes away. His situation can be grasped
from these words by the Spanish poet
Quevedo:
The waters of the abyss
in which I fell in love with myself.
Stavrogin, the hero of The Devils writes
as follows, to Darya Pavlovna, who loves
him: "I've tried my strength everywhere.
When I tried it for my own sake and for the
sake of self-display, it seemed infinite, as it
has before in my life. . . But what to apply my
strength to that's what I've never seen and
don't see now in spite of your words of ap¬
proval... I can still wish to do something
good... and that gives me a feeling of
pleasure. But the one and the other feelings
are, as before, too petty, and strong they
never are. My desires are never strong
enough. . . I tried wild debauchery. .. but I do
not like debauchery and I had no desire for
it... Perhaps you dream of giving me so
much love that you hope at least to set up
some aim for me by it? No you'd better be
careful: my love will be as petty as I am
myself... Your brother told me that he who
loses his ties with his native soil, loses his
gods that is, all his aims. One can go on
arguing about anything for ever, but from
me nothing has come but negation, with no
magnanimity and no force. Even negation
has not come from me. Everything has
a/ways been petty and life/ess. Kirilov, in his
magnanimity, could not compromise with
an idea and shot himself. I can never lose
my reason and I can never believe in an idea
to the same extent as he did. . . I can never,
never shoot myself.
What word can be used to describe this
condition? Discouragement, lifelessness.
Stavrogin: the man without a soul.
Nevertheless, after writing this letter,
Stavrogin hangs himself in his garret. As a
final paradox, the rope was made of silk and
the suicide had carefully smeared it with
soap beforehand. The grandeur of the
nihilist lies neither in his position nor in his
ideas, but in his lucidity. His clarity redeems
him from what Stavrogin called his pettiness
or mean-mindedness. Unless, far from being
an answer, suicide is yet another test. If so,
it is anïnadequate test. It is not important:
the nihilist is an intellectual hero because he
dares to penetrate into his divided soul,
knowing that he is involved in a hopeless
quest.
Nietszche would have said that Stavrogin
is an "incomplete nihilist": he is ignorant of
the Eternal Return. But perhaps it would be
nearer the truth to say that Dostoyevsky the
man, like so many of our contemporaries, is
an incomplete Christian. He has ceased to
believe, but he has not managed to replace
the old certainties by new ones, nor to live
an unsheltered life, without ideas to justify
or give meaning to his existence. It is God
that is dead, not evil. The loss of the super¬
natural frame of reference does not abolish
sin. On the contrary, it endows it with a kind
of immortality. The nihilist is closer to the
pessimism of the Gnostics than to Christian
optimism with its hope for salvation. If there
is no God there can be no remission of sins,
but neither can there be aboliton of evil. Sin
ceases to be an accident or a state, and is
transformed into the permanent condition of
men. It is Augustinianism in reverse: being is
evil. The Utopian would like to bring heaven
to earth and make us gods. The nihilist
knows that he is condemned from birth: the
earth is already hell.
Is the portrait of the nihilist a self-portrait?
Yes and no. Dostoyevsky wished to escape
from nihilism not by suicide and negation
but by affirmation and joy. The answer to
nihilism, the sickness of the intellectuals, is
the life-giving simplicity of Dimitri
Karamazov or the supernatural joy of
Alyosha. In either case the answer is to be
found not in philosophy and ideas but in life.
The innocence of simple people is the
refutation of nihilism. Dostoyevsky's world
is peopled with men, women and children
who are both ordinary and extraordinary.
Some are anxious, others are sensual; some
sing in abject poverty and others despair in
prosperity. There are saints and criminals,
idiots and geniuses, pious women and
angelic children tormented by their fathers.
(How different was Dostoyevsky's vision of
childhood from Freud's!) A world of
criminals and upright citizens: the gates of
the kingdom of heaven are open to all of
them. They .can save themselves or go to
perdition.
Although ideas have a great importance in
his work, Dostoyevsky was a novelist, not
an ideologist. As Dimitri Karamazov, one of
his heroes, observes: "We ought to love life
more than thinking about life". Dimitri is one
answer to Ivan but not the answer.
Dostoyevsky does not set one idea against
another, but one human reality against
another. Dostoyevsky is different from
Flaubert, James or Proust in the sense that
ideas are real for him, not intrinsically but as
a religious dimension of existence. The only
ideas that interested him were Ideas em¬
bodied in flesh and blood. Some come from
God, in other words from the depths of the
heart; others, and they are the most
numerous, come from the devil, in other
words the brain. Like the soul of the
medieval clergy, the conscience of the
modern intellectual is a battlefield. Seen in
this light, Dostoyevsky's novels are religious
parables and his art is closer to St. Paul, St.
Augustine and Pascal than to modern
realism. At the same time, by virtue of the
rigour of his powers of psychological
analysis, his work anticipates and in a sense
transcends that of Freud.
We owe to Dostoyevsky .the fullest and
most profound diagnosis of the modern
sickness: psychic division, divided con¬
science. He describes the phenomenon
simultaneously from a psychological and
religious point of view. Stavrogin and Ivan
suffer from visions: They see and talk with
spectres, devils. At the same time, since
they are modern men they explain these ap¬
paritions in terms of psychic disturbances.
They are projections of disturbances of the
soul. But neither of them is very sure about
this explanation. Time and again, as they
talk to their ghostly visitors they are despair¬
ingly compelled to accept that these visitors
are real, and that they are actually talking to
the devil. Awareness of the split within them
is diabolical. To be possessed is to know
that the self has been destroyed and that
someone outside us is usurping our voice.
Is this outsider the devil or is it our¬
selves? However we answer this question,
the identity is split. These passages are
hallucinatory; the conversations of Ivan and
Stavrogin with their devils are related
realistically, as if they were unexceptional
events. There are many absurd situations
and ironical reflections. At one moment fear
makes us laugh, at another it makes our
blood run cold. We experience an am¬
biguous fascination: psychological descrip¬
tion imperceptibly becomes metaphysical
speculation, which in turn becomes a
religious vision, and the vision becomes a
tale in which the supernatural and the banal,
the grotesque and the unfathomable are in¬
extricably intermixed.
Dostoyevsky's devils have an authenticity
which is unique in modern literature. Since
the eighteenth century the supernatural
creatures in our poems and novels have
ceased to be convincing. They are comic
figures, and the affectation of their language
and behaviour is simultaneously pompous
and intolerable. In Goethe and Valéry they
are plausible precisely because of their
highly intellectual and symbolic nature. They
are also acceptable when presented in a
deliberately ironical manner as fantastic
figments of the imagination, as in Gérard de
Nerval's La Main Enchantée and Cazotte's
delightful Diable Amoureux. But the modern
devils do everything in their power to make
us aware that they come from the beyond,
from the subterranean world. They are the
parvenus of the supernatural.
Although Dostoyevsky's devils are
modern too and bear no resemblance to
medieval or baroque devils lustful, astute
and a trifle stupid they are not literary. '
They possess what might be called a clinical
reality. Here lies, perhaps, Dostoyevsky's
great discovery. He saw the hidden relation¬
ship between evil and sickness, between
possession and reflection. They are rational
devils which, as if they were
psychoanalysts, obstinately try to prove that
they do not exist, that they are imaginary.
They triumph as a result of this irrefutable
reasoning. Ivan and Stavrogin, two intellec¬
tuals, have no option but to believe in them:
they are really the devil because only the
devil is capable of reasoning in this way. But
they would also be possessed by the devil if
they obstinately insisted on believing in ,
what are the mere hallucinations of a sick
mind. In either case they are possessed by
negation, the essence of the devil. Hence
the thought that terrifies Ivan: to believe in
the devil it is not necessary to believe in
God.
Octavio Paz
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Knots as
by Georges Ifrah
Fig. 1 - A Peruvian quipu.
Fig. 2 - The unit numbers one to
nine as represented in
the Inca quipu system.
THOUSANDS
HUNDREDS
TENS
UNITS
3000
600
40
3643
Fig. 3 - Representation of the
number 3,643 in the
Peruvian quipu system.
WHAT possible link could there be between a German miller
delivering flour to the village baker at the turn of the cen¬
tury and a Tibetan monk performing his prescribed ritual
today? The answer ¡s... a length of knotted cord or string. Both
monk and miller belong to the groups of people which, in different
parts of the world, from ancient times until the present day, have
used knotted plant fibres to help count objects, to measure the
passage of time, or to record numerical data.
The practice achieved a particularly sophisticated form in the Inca
civilization. The Incas, who were in all likelihood ignorant of writing,
devised a highly ingenious system which allowed them to depict all
the numerical operations they had to carry out in everyday life, gave
them access to accurate and up-to-date information about the
resources of their empire, and enabled them to keep a tangible
record of all the calculations involved. This system, known as quipu
(from the word in the Quechua language meaning "knot"), con¬
sisted of a length of string or cord, held horizontally, to which more
slender, different-coloured strings were attached, brought together
in several groups and joined at regular intervals by various kinds of
knots (fig. 1).
Quipus were nothing if not versatile. They were useful for
representing liturgical or chronological information, they served as
calendars, and they could be used for transmitting messages, since
the colours of the strings corresponded according to convention to
different objects or abstract ideas. But first and foremost they were
used for keeping accounts: the colour of the strings, the number
and relative position of the knots, the thickness and spacing of the
groups each had a precise numerical significance (figs. 2, 3 and 4).
They were carefully preserved when the results of computations
(carried out in this case according to a decimal system) had to be
recorded. In other words they constituted an extremely valuable
statistical tool in every area of the life of the empire, from military
surveys to the evaluation of crop-yields, from recording the number
of animals killed in hunting to census-taking, establishing statistics
of births and deaths, tax receipts, and surveys of human and
material resources.
The Incas had a highly organized administrative system. In every
. town, village and district officials named quipucamayocs ("keepers
of the knots") were responsible for making the quipus, interpreting
them at any given moment and providing the government with such
information as it desired. Each year they made an inventory of the
various products collected in the region or carried out a census of
the population, recording the results on the knotted cords. These
"registers" were then forwarded to the central government which
thus disposed of stocks of statistical information comparable to the
national archives of modern times.
The Inca quipu was so simple and so useful that it long continued
to be used in Bolivia and Ecuador. It seems that in the mid-
nineteenth century, notably on the high Peruvian plateaux, herds¬
men always used knotted cord to keep a record of the size of their
GEORGES IFRAH, of Morocco, is a specialist in the history of writing and
numeration. Formerly a professor of mathematics, he gave up teaching to
devote himself entirely to historical research. His comprehensive Histoire
Universelle des Chiffres (A Universal History of Numbers), Editions Seghers,
Paris, 1981, is the fruit of many years of study of museums and archives
throughout the world.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
numbers
flocks and herds, with white strings being used for sheep and goats,
and green strings for cattle (fig. 5).
Even today the Indians of Bolivia and Peru use a similar system
which is known as the chlmpu and is a direct but more sophisticated
descendant of the quipu. A single string is used for the units (with
the user tying as many knots as he needs, up to nine); the tens are
indicated by knots on two adjacent strings; the hundreds by knots
on a group of three strings, and so on. Six knots, for example, on a
chimpu represent 6, 60, 600 or 6,000, depending on whether they
are tied on one, two, three of four cords at once (see fig. 6).
The knotted cord method of computation is not exclusive to the
Incas and the peoples of South America; it has been used in a varie¬
ty of times and places.
The Greek historian Herodotus (485-425 BC) tells how King Darius
I of Persia (522-486 BC) once entrusted his Greek allies with the task
of guarding a bridge of vital strategic importance. He gave them a
strap tied with sixty knots and ordered them to untie one knot each
day. "If I am not back by the time you have unfastened the last
knot," he told them, "go back to your ships and return home".
In second-century-AD Palestine, then under Roman domination,
the publicans (tax-collectors) kept their records using a long cable,
probably formed from several lengths of string. Each tax-payer was
given a receipt consisting of a length of cord knotted in a specific
way.
Similar systems of doing calculations connected with census-
taking, keeping accounts and archives seem to have been used in
ancient China when writing was in its infancy. Tradition has it that
the semi-legendary Emperor Shen Nong had a part in developing the
knotted cord system for accountancy and helped to promote its use.
This method is also mentioned in the l-Ching ("Book of Transforma¬
tions"), a classic work which may have been written in the first half
of the last millennium before Christ.
In the Far East this use of knotted cord has still not completely
disappeared. J. G. Février notes in his "History of Writing" that it is
still extant notably in the Riu-Kiu islands: "Workmen in certain
mountainous areas of Okinawa island use such a system of knotted
straw to record their days of work, note what money is due to them,
and so on. [...] In the town of Shuri pawnbrokers keep account of
their transactions by using a long rush or bark string divided into two
parts by another string which is tied to it halfway along. Knots on
the upper half denote the month in which the loan was granted;
knots in the lower part indicate the amount of the loan."
The same practice is still to be found in the Caroline Islands (near
Tahiti), in the Hawaii Islands, and in West Africa, notably among a
Nigerian tribe. Similar methods have also been observed among
North American Indians such as the Yakima (Washington State),
the Walapi and Havasupai (Arizona), and the Miwok and Maidu
(California).
Present-day examples of this use of knotted string and cord are
survivals of an ancient system, curiosities in a world in which the
positional decimal system has prevailed. Yet, with other phenomena
from the past, they bear witness to the universality of human in¬
telligence and recreate a step in the history of figures and numerical
systems which, with the history of writing, holds a central place in
the evolution of human thought.
658 89 258 273 38
E D C B A
Fig. 4 - Interpretation of a group of knotted strings in the Inca
quipu system representing the number 658. String E gives the
total of the four strings A, B, C, D. The drawing shows the first
group of strings of a Peruvian quipu preserved in the American
Museum of Natural History, New York.
. t , . <
> » + > >
u» » w m
Fig. 5 - How shepherds of the Peruvian altiplano used the quipu
to keep track of their sheep and cattle.
Group B (green strings)
B, = 203 bulls
B2 = 350 milking cows
B3 = 235 barren cows
B4 = total 788
Group A (white strings)
A, =254 sheep
A2 = 36 lambs
A3 = 300 goats
A4 = 40 kids
Aj = 244 ewes
As = total 874
5 KNOTS ON FOUR STRINGS -
4 KNOTS ON THREE STRINGS -
-* 5000
7 KNOTS ON TWO STRINGS
-»- 400
70
7 KNOTS ON ONE STRING
5477
Fig. 6 - Part of a chimpu, a more
recent version of the quipu,
used by the Indians of Peru and
Bolivia.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
It
m
~ AT«
Ü
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
An African cosmology
by Sulayman S. Nyang
AFRICA was, and still is, rich in cos-
mological ideas. Though the diver¬
sity of Africa's religious and cosmo-
logical heritage has until recently been little
known outside the continent, the intensive
researches of Africanists around the world,
and the growing global interest in Africa,
have now combined to draw attention to the
nature of Africa's spiritual gift to humanity.
Africa's traditional cosmology is diverse,
but beneath this diversity lies a core of
shared beliefs which spread across the con¬
tinent. In this cosmology, certain ideas have
always held sway over men's minds.
SULAYMAN S. NYANG, Gambian educator, is
currently associate professor of government and
public administration at the Center for African
Studies, Howard University, Washington, D.C.
He is author of a number of studies on African
political and philosophical issues, the most recent
being an essay on "Millennium in Traditional
African Thought". His book Christianity, Islam
and African Identity is to be published shortly.
"It is remarkable," writes the Kenyan
scholar Professor John Mbiti, "that in spite
of great distances separating the peoples of
one region from those of another, there are
sufficient elements of belief which make it
possible for us to discuss African concepts
of God as a unity and on a continental
scale."
This Divine Creator is usually pictured as
the Lord and Master of mankind. In the
numerous myths of African peoples, such as
those of the Yoruba, the Ashanti and the
Dogon, in the beginning God was very close
to mankind but later, as a result of man's
provocation, error or folly, withdrew and so.
man forfeited his privileges and the benefits
of being in close proximity to his Creator.
These mythological ideas help us to
understand the traditional African's defini¬
tion of selfhood vis-à-vis the Supreme
Being. From the work of students of African
religion it emerges that there is a close rela¬
tionship between man and the Supreme Be¬
ing. According to this view, man is more
than a spectator on the stage of life. Though
he is a creature who is circumscribed within
the parameters set by the spiritual ancestors
and the evil spirits, man still exercises his
own will on both the material and spiritual
worlds. If he is to function effectively in the
material world, he must learn to pursue his
human needs and personal interests without
antagonizing the spiritual forces above.
In traditional African cosmology man is
caught in a matrix of spiritual relationships.
He is bound by unbreakable ties to the
Supreme Being, who created the earth and
everything therein for man and his progeny.
These ties are unbreakable because man's
existence is ontologically dependent upon
his Creator.
Man also has to maintain a correct rela¬
tionship with the lesser entities within the
spiritual kingdom. His day-to-day activities
are not only designed to harmonize his rela¬
tionship with the divinities and the departed
ancestors, but they are also motivated by
the fear that bad relations with these
spiritual forces could endanger the life and
safety of his community.
This understanding of the triangular
matrix of relationships beween the individual
and his community, on the one hand, and
the spiritual kingdom, on the other, puts a
premium on good behaviour and obedience
to communal customs and practices. This
sense of obedience and harmony hinges on
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
man's realization that the universe is a
religious one, and that everything within it
dances to a cosmic music whose tunes and
rhythm echo the words of the spiritual
forces.
Life is a constant dialogue with the
sacred, and each passing moment demands
the utmost devotion to the spiritual forces
above, and to the words of religious com¬
munications issuing from their invisible lips.
It is because of this constant dialogue with
the spiritual world around him that the tradi¬
tional African man conceives himself as the
centrepiece of creation. John Mbiti captures
this aspect of traditional Africa's ontology
when he writes:
"... African' ontology is basically an-
thropocentric; man is at the very centre of
existence, and African peoples see
everything else in relation to this central
position of man. God is the explanation of
man's origin and sustenance; it is as if God
exists for the sake of man. The spirits are
ontologically in the mode between God and
man; they describe or explain the destiny of
man after physical life."
This African conception of the Man-God
relationship is radically different from beliefs
wherein man is generally looked on as an ab
ject sinner who must submit to God in order
to deserve His mercy in the hereafter.
Another important point is that traditional
African man sees the universe as a hierarchy
of vital forces, with man as the force which
links the inanimate objects to the world of
spiritual forces above him. This makes him
both a manipulator of spiritual power and a
target of such power. His view of man,
especially as characterized in Bantu
philosophy, has been described as vitalistic;
that is, it is based on the belief that life is a
vital unity and that the human being is only a
point on the cosmic circle of life. Another
African scholar, Vincent Mulago, writes:
A citizen
of three
worlds
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
"Traditional African man
sees himself as a citizen of
three different worlds at the
same time... He lives in the
world of concrete reality, the
world of social values and
the world of the ineffable
self-conscious. "
' m
i
x/ rß
f
i i¡y*U
!
i»¿i? W~$ér?^ \Mr.W
laW flS LaT¿ * WT Vtl'aMl
r
fuiil k*¡y rJJ^hr>^
*.
& 1 «W - fi fi ' '
p <* *¿ V'ifla
> f V-XJi
<
HF 1/ J
m
m . *
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
"Traditional African man
sees the universe as a
hierarchy of vital forces,
with man as the force which
links inanimate objects to
the world of spiritual forces
above him. "
In traditional African society
activities that .involved working
with matter and transforming it
often had a sacred or occult
character. As the "Master of
Fire" and possessor of the
secret of transmutations, the
smith was highly respected as
the repository of knowledge
handed down from generation
to generation and originating in
an initial revelation. More than
merely practical implements, the
tools of his craft were handled
with loving care and were often
objects of beauty, like this
finely-carved pair of bellows
from Gabon.
"The common factor which explains the
solidarity of clan or tribe is not all simple. It is
not the life of the senses, nor the life of
thought. Neither is it life in the multi¬
coloured diversity we find in newspapers or
in the modern novel. It is life as it has been
derived and received from the source of
'power', as it turns toward power, is seized
by it and seizes it. This life is not destroyed
by death, although death may subject it to a
change of condition."
This understanding of man, as described
by Mulago, is very much related to Father
Temples' formulations in his Bantu
Philosophy. In this widely quoted but con¬
troversial work, Father Temples claims that
the end of the whole range of African man's
activities is "to acquire life, strength or vital
force, to live strongly [...] to make life
stronger, or to assume that force shall re¬
main perpetually in one's posterity."
Mulago contends that "for the Bantu,
living is existence in community; it is par¬
ticipation in the sacred life (and all life is
sacred) of the ancestors; it is an extension of
the life of one's forefathers, and a prepara¬
tion for one's own life to be carried on in
one's descendants."
Mulago's statement is generally accepted
by specialists as a standard belief among
Africans. It is, however, worth pointing out
30
that he added to the understanding of the
Bantu view of man with this explanation:
"The Bantu view of life may be seen in
two ways: first, as a community of blood
(the main primary factor); and secondly, as a
community of property (the concomitant
factor which makes life possible)."
This view of man is a fairly adequate
assessment of what the majority of tradi¬
tional African religionists would accept. It
does not only show that the African believes
in the sacred perpetuation of the powers of
procreation in his line of descent, it also ar¬
ticulates the universal African belief that all
the non-human elements in nature (trees,
animals and inorganic beings) are the exten¬
sions and means of life of those to whom
they belong.
This conception of life is the basis of the
African fear of impotence among men and
barrenness among women. Such human
mishaps and existential woes are construed
by the traditional African as the severing of
the chain linking the living and the dead. In
the view of traditional African man, the link
between the ancestors and their present
successors on earth comes from the unity of
blood and the common life which flows in
the veins of all members of the community.
Janheinz Jahn has also attempted to
reconstruct Bantu philosophy in his in
teresting book Muntu. His contribution to
the understanding of the traditional African
view of life and of man's role in the process
of vital participation is the claim that one of
the touchstones of traditional African cul¬
ture is the "magic power of the word".
The truth of this is not widely disputed,
for the word is all powerful in Africa. Indeed,
the traditional African religionists not only
took the word seriously, they also saw
language both as the badge of man's
spiritual superiority over the non-human
elements in the universe, and as his shib¬
boleth at the spiritual gates of the Supreme
Being's invisible kingdom.
This view of the magical power of words
is evident in the many references by scholars
to the African's use of incantations in his
everyday life. The belief in the magical
power of words gave rise to specialization in
the execution of functions in many tradi¬
tional African societies. The caste system,
for example, emerged in certain societies in
Africa simply because the African people felt
that such a division of labour could bring
about a good relationship with the spiritual
world, and that human elements so chosen
for such functions could execute their
delicate and sensitive tasks without
endangering the lives of others in the
community.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Photo Claude Lefevre © Editions du Chêne, Paris
"In traditional African cosmology
man is caught in a matrix of
spiritual relationships... His day- to¬
day activities are not only designed
to harmonize his relationships with
the divinities and the departed
ancestors, but they are also
motivated by the fear that bad
relations with these spiritual forces
could endanger the life and safety
of his community. "
Ancestral
homes
The buildings erected by the Dogon
people of West Africa have a symbolic
link with their Creation story. In a
Dogon village, the most important
building is the meeting-place of the
elders, the Togu na (above). This is a
rectangular building the roof of which
is supported by eight main pillars
representing the ancestors: four men
and four women who were the
offspring of the first man and woman
created. Houses are built in the shape
of the human body (see diagram right),
the circular kitchen representing the
head, the two side rooms the arms, and
the vestibule the legs.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Amadou Hampate Ba, in commenting on
the nature of African arts, has argued that
the African conception of art will not be in¬
telligible to a person who is secularistic in his
understanding of reality, for such an art is
inspired by a world-view that is all-
embracing.
He further contends that in the old Africa,
"Every act and every gesture were con¬
sidered to bring into play the invisible forces
of life. According to the tradition of the
Bambara people of Mali, these forces are the
multiple aspects of SE, or Great Creative
Power, which is in itself an aspect of the
Supreme being known as Maa Ngala"
(Unesco Courier, February 1976).
In the traditional African ontological
system, the human being is given a definite
destiny. Man is viewed as a cosmic traveller
who is destined to cross the equator of
death. This boundary line between the living
and the departed is what gives meaning to
life itself, for, just like the equator, it serves
as a demarcation line between two in¬
separable portions of total. reality. Death is
"not the ultimate reality but life itself. At
death, the individual dissolves into collective
immortality of the living-dead, that is, pro¬
claims the great solidarity of life."
For the traditional African religionist,
death is the process and the condition by
which the physical body of man is disin¬
tegrated. It is also the fragmentation of the
unity of life: body and spirit. Thus "Death is
conceived of as a departure and not a com¬
plete annihilation of a person. He moves on
to join the company of the departed, and the
only major change is the decay of the
physical body, but the spirit moves on to
another state of existence."
Father Temples has pointed out that "the
dead live on in a diminished condition of life,
as lessened life forces, while retaining their
higher, strengthening father life force." In
other words the departed, by going through
the individualized agony of death, have
gained a deeper knowledge of the mystery
and the process of vital participation in the
universe.
This paradoxical understanding of death
has led many African peoples to explain
death as the result of four causes. The most
commonly cited is magic, sorcery and witch¬
craft. This cause is viewed by most Africans
as a very dangerous one, for victims of such
evil practices may turn out to be wandering
ghosts whose souls will not be at
rest.
The second is the curse. Many African
societies teach their new members that a
powerful curse brings immediate death to
the accursed. Such a fate is widely feared in
African traditional societies, and every
precaution is usually taken not to violate
taboos, customs and traditions.
The third is the living-dead. These
departed souls may be dissatisfied with the
lives and activities of their survivors on earth
and so decide to tell them to change their
ways by visiting them with calamities.
(There is little evidence that living-dead ac¬
tually cause death.)
The fourth is God. This category is not
rigid, however. The traditional African may
accept God as the ultimate cause of death,
but to satisfy his psychological and emo¬
tional needs, he would still insist on an in¬
termediate cause of death.
32
These four causes of death could affect
the destiny of man, which would remain un¬
fulfilled at the moment of death. It is this
fear of one's fate after death which drives
many an African into the arms of diviners
and magicians. These mediators between
fragile and vulnerable men and the spiritual
powers dispose of great knowledge in the
mystical arts and their ability to allay the
fears of their clients and to subdue real or
imagined targets, has contributed a great
deal to African social stability in the past..
These qualities have also guaranteed the
peaceful passage of man from the realm of
humanness to the world of spirits.
John Mbiti has pointed out that "the key
to our understanding of the basic religious
and philosophical concepts (of African on¬
tology) is the African concept of time." He
went on to argue that "according to tradi¬
tional African concepts, time is a two-
dimensional phenomenon, with a long past,
a present and virtually no future."
These remarks by Mbiti have given cur¬
rency to the view that, to the old Africa,
history consists of 'two parts, the Sasa and
Zamani. The former is composed of all the
events which in the Western or linear con¬
cept of time would be considered as the
future. This concept, in the writings of
Mbiti, is taken as that dimension which em¬
braces all events that are about to occur or
are in the process of occurring or have
recently occurred. It is also understood as
the most meaningful period for the in¬
dividual.
The latter, on the other hand, is described
by Mbiti as the macro-time which embraces
all the past events that link the beginning of
things to the present unfolding of events in
the universe. In his view, Zamani is more
than the past; it is, as he suggests, "the
graveyard of time". Zamani, therefore, is
not only the period of termination, but also
the period of myth.
Mbiti's conceptual scheme is a help in
understanding the particular nature of
African thought.
I should like to put forward an alternative.
In my view the key concept in traditional
African thought is the cosmic schizophrenic
tendencies of man. By this I mean that tradi¬
tional African man sees himself as a citizen
of three different worlds at the same time.
That is to say that he lives in (a) the world of
concrete reality, (b) the world of social
values, and (c) the world of the ineffable
self-conscious.
The first world is that of man, trees, stars
inanimate objects and phenomena. The se¬
cond is that of values governing the mental
and spiritual processes of man and his com¬
munity. The third is that of unreachable and
inexpressible spiritual powers.
When analysed carefully, the beliefs and
thought patterns of the traditional African
man could be fitted into the three major on¬
tological categories. The tendency of the
students of African religions to assert that
Africans do not worship one God is due to
tnis cosmic schizophrenic behaviour in man.
Traditional man places the High God, in
the world of the ineffable self-conscious.
Though he shuttles between this particular
world and the other two, his ontological
make-up seems to incline him more to the
realms of concrete reality and social values
respectively. This is to say that traditional
African man's view of history is different
from that of the ascetic religious traditions
of the East, where man renounces this ear¬
thly life and devotes his entire life and being
to the world of ineffable self-conscious.
The African view is also different from the
Western scientific view, which focuses
almost completely on the world of concrete
reality. The Western view, it should be add¬
ed, is based on the dynamics of matter; its
conception of time and history is bound to
be affected by the changing paradigms in
the scientific community of the West. As
long as Western man hankers after the
mysteries of matter, his concept of time will
be unilinear. In other words, the conception
of time of a human group is determined
more by the ontological focus of its
members (that is, which of the three worlds
they wish to choose) and less by an inherent
racial or geographical factor.
Contrary to Mbiti, I would argue that
African traditional man indeed has a sense
of the indefinite future, but that his on¬
tological focus has been, not on revolu¬
tionizing the physical landscape around him,
but on socializing the new members of
society to anticipate their successful acces¬
sion to fatherhood (which is a few years
hence) and to refresh their memory of past
events. This latter aspect of the African
response to the ontological challenge put a
premium on the retrieval facilities of the
mind and its memory.
I would conclude that the traditional
African man's concept of time is three-
dimensional. This is to say that he believes
in a past, a present and a future. Yet, in con¬
ceding this point, I need to add that the
matter does not end with the three-dimen¬
sionality of time. The nature of such a con¬
ception needs futher exploration.
First, it should be pointed out that the
concept of unilinearity of time, as developed
in Western history, is based on an illusion,
which is detectable so long as man chases
after the mirage of materiality. This illusion
becomes exposed the moment the ontologi¬
cal response of a society shifts its focus
from excessive love for materiality to ex¬
cessive love for the social values between
man and society.
I would argue that, whereas the Western
theory of historical unilinearity is inspired by
the matrix of causes and effects that
governs the worjd of concrete reality, the
African's conception of time is guided by his
excessive concern for communal harmony in
rituals, deeds and thoughts.
The idea of unilinearity of history is in¬
spired by, and based on, the intercourse
between the various elements in the hier¬
archy of ontological units in the universe.
These two visions of history and life are very
different indeed, and it would be a serious
mistake to absolutize the concept of
unilinearity as developed out of one ex¬
perience, and then try to impose it on the
rest of mankind.
Traditional African man sees himself as a
party to an ontological and cosmological
partnership and because of this understan¬
ding of his life on earth, he always sees har¬
mony as the best form of human expression.
To the traditional African man, life is chaotic
so long as man's links with God and others
in existence are shattered. Because of this
fear of breaking the ontological bonds, tradi¬
tional African man always prefers harmony
and social order.
M Sulayman S. Nyang
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
\\
"If you know yesterday and
today, you will know tomorrow,
for the weaver's thread is the
future, the woven cloth is the
present, the woven and folded
cloth is the past. " (Fulani
proverb).
Photo fieorg Gerster Ç Rapho, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
G3 P
ib fia
j\.
nn
lii
Unesco exhibition
shows ecology in action
To focus attention on the need for wise
management of the environment, Unesco
has produced an easily presented exhibition
entitled "Ecology in Action". The exhibition
consists of 36 full colour wallcharts, each
measuring 80x120 cm, and covers:
research for land use planning; tropical
forests; arid, cold or mountainous marginal
lands; towns and urbanization; and conser¬
vation. For further information about obtain¬
ing the exhibition, write to Man and the
Biosphere Programme Secretariat, Unesco,
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
International congress
on child abuse
The 4th International Congress on Child
Abuse and Neglect is being organized by the
Association Française d'Information et de
Recherche sur Les Enfants Maltraités et
Négligés and will be held from 7 to
10 September 1982 at the René Descartes
Faculty of Medicine, Paris. Its theme will be
"abused, neglected and exploited children in
institutions and in society". For further
details please write to: Dr. P. Straus,
AFIREM, Hôpital des Enfants Malades, 149,
Rue de Sèvres, 75730 Paris Cedex 15,
France.
'Modelling'-
latest theme of Impact
The latest issue of Unesco's international
quarterly Impact of Science on Society is
entirely devoted to modelling. All aspects of
the question are discussed, from the use of
simple models for science education to the
basic principles of mathematical modelling
and their use as a means of forecasting the
future. Contents include: an interview with
Dennis Meadows on "modelling, limits and
understanding"; models in science educa¬
tion, by George Marx and Esther Tóth; and
working models promote rural development,
by Jean Gimpel. (See "Bookshelf" this
page).
'Add life to years'
Aging is the theme of this year's World
Health Day (7 April 1982) and of a United
Nations World Assembly later in the year. In
a message for World Health Day, whose
slogan is "Add Life to Years", the Director-
General of the World Health Organization,
Dr. Halfdan Mahler stresses that "the elder¬
ly are a group requiring special protection
but also one with a positive contribution to
make, particularly if they are integrated into
society". The World Assembly on Aging will
take place in Vienna from 26 July to
6 August.
Growing resistance
to antibiotics
Disturbing reports of the increasing ineffec¬
tiveness of a range of antibiotics have led
the World Health Organization to convene a
scientific working group on antimicrobial
resistance. Widespread misuse of an¬
tibiotics, unwise self-treatment and the
prescription of antibiotics for ailments that
do not require them have contributed to the
problem of resistance. Unless something is
done, treatment of a number of common in¬
fectious diseases will be jeopardized;
medical costs will soar higher because of the
high cost of alternatives; and lives will be
lost through ineffective medication.
The artist and society
The material conditions of artists' lives and
their status in society are discussed in the
latest issue (No. 76) of the journal Art
published by the International Association
of Art (IAA). The issue also contains the text
of the International Recommendation on the
Status of the Artist adopted by Unesco's
General Conference at its 21st session. Con¬
tents also include articles on the theme "Ar¬
tists and the relationship of nations: towards
a new international order", which will be the
subject of the next IAA congress scheduled
for 1983.
Heritage of Nepal
Monuments of Northern Nepal, a new study
just published by Unesco, is a further result
of co-operation between Unesco and the
Nepalese Government in the listing and
preservation of Nepal's cultural heritage. In
1977 Unesco published an inventory of the
monuments of the Kathmandu Valley and
then embarked on the exhaustive survey of
monuments in northern Nepal whose
preliminary results are presented in the new
publication. The study highlights the diver¬
sity of building styles which, though
originating in common patterns, evolved in
response to differences in ecological- and
cultural environment. (See "Bookshelf" this
page).
African rangers
win valour award
Over 20 rangers who lost their lives in
defence of Virunga National Park irr Zaire
between 1960 and 1967 have been
posthumously awarded an International
Parks Valour Award by the International
Union for Conservation of Nature and
Natural Resources. By repelling armed
poachers and various military forces, the
dedicated rangers "ensured the survival of a
World Heritage Site for all humanity", says
the citation. A second valour award went to
Mr. Joseph Kioko of the Kenya National
Parks Department for showing exceptional
resourcefulness in helping to create a new
national park.
BOOKSHELF
RECENT UNESCO
PUBLICATIONS
International Yearbook of Educa¬
tion. Vol XXXIII - 1981, prepared for the
International Bureau of Education by
Robert Cowen. Analyses educational
development trends between 1975 and
1978 according to the data provided by
Unesco Member States. Unesco: Inter¬
national Bureau of Education, 1981.
253pp. (35 F).
New Trends in Chemistry
Teaching Volume V. An anthology of
articles grouped in sections dealing with:
Chemical information; What should we
teach and how? Chemistry in space.
Chemistry of the future. Controversies in
teaching chemistry, Simple experiments.
Low-cost equipment. Games and
simulations, Chemistry and industry.
1981.270 pp. (52 F).
The Planning of Nonformal Educa¬
tion, by David R. Evans. Published by
Unesco: International Institute for
Educational Planning, 1981. 102 pp.
(15 F).
Working with Braille. A study of
Braille as a medium of communication,
by Barry Hampshire. 1981. 177 pp.
(60 F).
Apartheid. A Teacher's Guide, by
Godfrey N. Brown. 1981. 104 pp. (25 F).
The Decolonization of Africa:
Southern Africa and the the Horn of
Africa. Fifth in the series "The general
history of Africa: studies and
documents". 1981. 163 pp. (35 F).
Monuments of Northern Nepal, by
Corneille Jest. 1981. 121 pp. (25 F) (See
news item this page).
Impact of Science on Society,
Vol.31, No. 4, 1981. Price per issue
16 F; one year subscription 56 F; 2
years, 90 F (See news item this page).
Research Trends and Priorities in
Relation to Human Needs Problems,
Second Biennial Report; A Directory
and Bibliography on the Theme
'Research and Human Needs' (Se¬
cond edition). 1981. Unesco's Division
of Scientific Research and Higher
Education (See box page 6).
Problems Raised by Mathematical
Modelling of Social Phenomena. Pro¬
ceedings of a symposium organized by
the Institut National de Recherche en In¬
formatique et en Automatique, France,
and the European Institute fftr Advanced
Studies in Management, Brussels, under
the patronage of Unesco, 1979. Institut
National de Recherche en Informatique
et en Automatique, Rocquencourt,
78150 Le Chesnay, France.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Just published
Islam, Philosophy and Science is a collection of
four public lectures organized by Unesco to celebrate
the beginning of the 15th century of the Hegira, the
starting point of Islamic civilization and culture. Con¬
tents, which include a supplementary essay:
Tolerance in the Prophet's deeds at Medina (by
Muhammad Hamidullah)
The development of philosophical thought in its
relationship with Islam up to Avicenna (Jean
J olivet)
Islam and innovation (Jacques Berque)
Modern Muslim thinkers of the Indian subcontinent
(Rahat Nabi Khan)
Islam and the flowering of the exact sciences
(Roshdi Rashed)
Preface by Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
168 pages 50 French francs
Islamic Cities and Conservation aims to stimulate
interest in the Islamic architectural and urban
heritage and offer guidelines for consideration by ar¬
chitects and town planners.
109 pages 45 French francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscrip¬
tion rates in local currency, will be supplied
on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P.O.
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne (Victoria!, 3000.
AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31, A-
1011, Vienna. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7. CHINA. China National Publications Import and Export
Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Beijing CYPRUS. "MAM", Arch¬
bishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia. CZE¬
CHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena 51, Prague 1 (Perma¬
nent display): Zahranicni literatura, 1 1 Soukenicka, Prague 1 . For
Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893
31 Bratislava - CSSR. - DENMARK. Munksgaard Export and
Subscription Service, 35 Norre Sogade, DK 1370, Copenhagen
K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for
Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo.
ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis
Ababa. - FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1,
SF-00100 Helsinki 10; Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, Koivuvaa-
rankuja 2, 01640 Vantaa 64. - FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco,
7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP. 12598-48. - GER¬
MAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140,
710 Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the
G.D.R. - FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier
(German, English, French and Spanish editions): Mr. H. Baum,
Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57, D5300
Bonn 3. For other Unesco publications: Karger Verlag,
Germering/München. For scientific maps only: Geo Center,
Postfach 800830, Stuttgart 80. - GHANA. Presbyterian Books¬
hop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers
Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape Coast; The University
Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1, Legon. - GREAT BRITAIN.
See United Kingdom. HONG KONG. Federal Publications
(HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street,
Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon.
Hong-Kong Government Information Services, Publications
Centre, GPO Building, Connaught Place. - HUNGARY.
Akadémiai Könyvesbolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V.
Konyvtürosok Boltja, Népkoztársasag utja 16, Budapest VI.
ICELAND. Snaebjörn Jonsson Er Co., H. F., Hafnarstraeti 9,
Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcut¬
ta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf Ali
Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road,
Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-
Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta
70016; Scindia House, New Delhi; Publication Unit, Ministry of
Education and Culture, Ex. AFO Hutments, Dr. Rajendra Prasad
Road, New Delhi 110001. - INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers
and Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia
Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr
Sam Ratulangie 47, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie
Publishing and Distribution Co., 28, Vessal Shirazi Street,
Enghelab Avenue, P.O. Box 314/1486, Teheran; Iranian Nat.
Comm. for Unesco, Ave. Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B.P. 1533,
Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, Al -Rashid Street,
Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland
Ltd., Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL.
A. B.C. Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel
Aviv 61000 - JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O.
Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston. - JAPAN. Eastern Book
Service Inc., Shuhwa Toranomon 3btdg, 23-6, Toranomon
3-Chome, Minato-ku, Tokyo 105, KENYA. East African
Publishing House, P.O. Box 30571, Nairobi. - KOREA. Korean
National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul.
KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait -
LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho,
Southern Africa. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd.,
P.O. Box 286, Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency for Development of
Publication & Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEM¬
BOURG. Librairie Paul Bruck, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop,
Kuala Lumpur 22-11. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic
Street, Valletta. - MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30,
Bourbon Street, Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30
bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. - NETHERLANDS. For the
"Unesco Koerier" Dutch edition only: KEESING BOEKEN B.V.,
Postbus 1118, 1000 BC Amsterdam. - NETHERLANDS AN¬
TILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad,
Curaçao. N.A. NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Of¬
fice, Government Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344,
Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch;
Alma Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box
1104, Dunedin; Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington.
NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The University
Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka; The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zaria. NORWAY. All publications:
Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43,
Oslo 1; Universitets Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, P.O.B.
307 Blindem, Oslo 3. For Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narvesens
Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6. PAKISTAN. Mirza Book
Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3.
- PHILIPPINES. The Modern Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue,
P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. - POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac
Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przed-
miescie No. 7.00-068 WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & An¬
drade Ltda. Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon.
SEYCHELLES. New Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box
131, Mahé. - SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University
and Sierra Leone Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New In¬
dustrial Road, off Upper Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19.
SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and
General, P.O. Box 951, Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA. All
publications: Van Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Building,
Church Street, P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier
(single copies) only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033,
Johannesburg. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir
Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2.
SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. -
SWEDEN. All publications A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl, Hov-
bokhandel, Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16.
For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Förbundet, Skolgränd 2,
Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. - SWITZERLAND-. All
publications: Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse. Zurich. Librairie
Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11, CCP. 12-236. -'TAN¬
ZANIA. Dares Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam.
- THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung
Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok: Suksapan
Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam
Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. - TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I. - TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi
A.S., Istiklâl Caddesi, No. 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu,
Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda 8ookshop, P.O. Box 145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Govt. Bookshops in London,
Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmin¬
gham, Bristol. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue
South, New York, N.Y. 10010. - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya
Kniga, Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska
Knjiga, Trg Republike 5/8, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba
Slovenje, Titova C 25, P.O. 8. 50-1, Ljubliana. - ZIMBABWE.
Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union Avenue, Salisbury.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Portrait of Fyodor Mikhailovich Dostoyevsky (1821-1881) painted by V.G. Pierov in 1872.
(See page 14).
]]>
</page>
</document>
