<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074736eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
MARCH 1981 4.50 French francs
SCIENCE IN THE SERVICE OF ART
'I,*' i
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
@
Lebanon
Baal the Storm God
This bronze statuette (18.5 cm high) was un¬
earthed during excavations at the ancient
Mediterranean seaport of Tyre, renowned in
ancient times for its far-flung commerce, its
purple-dyeing industry, and its people's cul¬
tural and intellectual activities. The figure,
dating from around the middle of the second
millennium BC, depicts Baal, God of the Storm
in the Canaanite pantheon. A wide diversity of
religions, technologies and art styles met and
flourished in Tyre, which attracted in turn
Phoenicians, Assyrians, Greeks, Romans,
Byzantines, Arabs, Crusaders and Ottomans.
In December 1979 the United Nations recog¬
nized the archaeological site of Tyre as part
of the "world heritage". Unesco is actively
supporting the International Committee which
is now, in close collaboration with Lebanon,
working to safeguard the remains of this great
city of Antiquity.
Photo © International Committee for the Safeguarding of. Tyre, Pans
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
unes-Courier
A window open on the world
MARCH 1981 34th YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 25 LANGUAGES
English Italian Turkish Macedonian
French Hindi Urdu Serbo-Croat
Spanish Tamil Catalan Slovene
Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese
German Persian Korean
Arabic Dutch Swahili
Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly In English, French and Spanish
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 44 French Francs
2 years: 75 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 32 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (11 issues a
year including one double issue).
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A.: (2) N CR. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New York, U.S.A.: (3) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mans¬
field Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691. U.S.A.
Editor-in-chief: Jean Gaudin
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
page
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Edition
Edition:
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition
Edition
Edition
Portuguese Edition
Turkish Edition
Urdu
Catalan
Malaysian
Korean
Swahili
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Howard Brabyn (Paris)
Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Werner Merkli (Berne)
Abdel Monëim El Sawi (Cairo)
Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Samad Nourinejad (Teheran)
Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Lim Moun-young (Seoul)
Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salaam)
Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene Editions: Punisa Pavlovic (Belgrade)
Chinese Edition: Shen Guofen (Pekín)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Philippe Gentil
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor- in-Chief in Pans.
Braille Edition:
5 SCIENCE IN THE SERVICE OF ART
by Magdeleine Hours
6 LASCAUX
SAVING A SANCTUARY OF PREHISTORIC ART
8 THE HALL OF BULLS
Reconstituted masterpieces of early man
12 THE SCIENTIFIC INVESTIGATION OF PAINTING
I. X-ray of a Rembrandt
II. True or false?
15 HEAT TREATMENT UNMASKS A SHAM ZAPOTEC
16 X-RAY MICROFLUORESCENCE
AND A MEROVINGIAN TREASURE
17 ANCIENT METALLURGY
The computer is turning up a mine of information
20 ANATOMY OF A HARP
21 ART, ARCHAEOLOGY AND THE ATOM
Nuclear dating techniques and how they work
by Bernard Keisch
24 A ROGUES' GALLERY OF FAKES
by Stuart J. Fleming
27 THE PRINCIPLES OF CONSERVATION
by Bernard M. Feilden
30 A MUSEUM IN A SUITCASE
Three-dimensional 'replicas' of works of art,
produced by the astonishing technique of holography
by Ivan G. Yavtushenko and Vladimir B. Markov
34 BIRD'S EYE VIEW OF THE PAST
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
LEBANON: Baal the Storm God
Cover
Science is today proving to be a powerful In¬
strument in the service of art, enabling
specialists to analyse ancient creative
techniques, unmask fakes, date ar¬
chaeological finds, and even chart the cur¬
rents of cultural transmission. Another
notable example of the close association of
art and modern technology Is the conserva¬
tion of cultural property, a new discipline
which is being fostered and encouraged by
Unesco. Photo shows a statue of a seated
Ariadne from Myrina, now in the Louve'
Museum, Paris. In background is equipment
used in thermoluminescence, a technique
which enabled the statue's date (first half
of 2nd century BC) to be scientifically
confirmed.
Photo © Laboratoire de Recherche des Musées de France, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Detail from statue of queen Nefertari is taken
from a photogrammetric survey of the façade of
the small temple of Abu Simbel.
Photo© Kodak-Pathé I.G.N., Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Science
in the service
of art
by Magdeleine Hours
ART and Science are two terms which
have been set apart by a long his¬
tory of opposition. The former was
identified with "creation", the product of
human sensibility; the latter was considered
to lead to the "discovery of the laws of
nature".
Twentieth-century man has seen the
growing impact of scientific and
technological development gradually
change the pattern of his daily life. In the
world of the arts, among both students and
artists alike, this phenomenon produced a
defence mechanism and a feeling of ap¬
prehension the importance of the
sciences as a source of inspiration for
twentieth-century art is undeniable.
However, in the last thirty years, the
world conscience has so often been aroused
by the extent of the destruction of works of
art and by the need to preserve the artistic
and cultural heritage, that a new alliance has
emerged between scientists and those
whose task is to study and conserve the ar¬
tistic heritage.
In Europe the close links between science
and art were formed as early as the eigh¬
teenth century: in Paris through the ac¬
tivities of the Encyclopaedists Fontenelle,
Charles, Diderot and others; then in London
through the work of Humphry Davy. During
the nineteenth century, research was more
sporadic, but both the French chemist and
microbiologist Louis Pasteur and the Ger¬
man physicist Wilhelm Roentgen applied
their own scientific methods of analysis to
the study of works of art. On 6 March 1865
Pasteur wrote: "There are circumstances in
which I clearly see that the alliance between
science and art is both possible and
desirable, with the chemist and the physicist
sitting at your elbow and informing you...."
Thirty years later in 1895, Roentgen
discovered X-rays, and, working in Munich,
attempted to take the first X-ray photograph
of a painting.
Half-way through this century the world's
great museums created their own
laboratories, and universities began to use
their facilities and in some cases to enlist
their research workers to discover the
origins of objects and their date, and to
establish the technology with which they
were made. Initially it was thanks to the pro¬
perties of electro-magnetic waves that
historians and curators found themselves
equipped with techniques for studying
works of art which vastly increased the
power of the naked eye. Through ultra¬
violet rays it was possible to detect and
photograph those places, hitherto invisible,
where an artist had made changes in his
work or returned to it after an interval. Infra¬
red rays and X-rays enable us to penetrate
wood and canvas, go back in time, and
rediscover unsuspected steps in the act of
creation.
These methods have shed some light on
the techniques used in creating a work of
art, but they yield less information in this
field than procedures which have been
developed to analyse the materials used by
artists and craftsmen of former times.
Methods of physical and chemical analysis,
which even a few years ago were seriously
handicapped because they required a sam¬
ple of the object to be removed, are now so
highly developed that only a tiny sample (of
the order of a few microgrammes) need be
taken. In the case of the nondestructive
technique of X-ray microfluorescence, no
sample at all is needed. Analytical tech¬
niques are now so accurate that they not
only reveal the secrets of materials but pin¬
point their origin. In this way the mysterious
invisible power of radiation is enabling us to
chart the trade-routes of ancient metallurgy
(see page 17).
While spectrometry and nuclear methods
cast light on the unfolding story of objects
and sites, dating procedures permit us to
situate objects in time. A number of dating
systems are currently in use, carbon-14 be¬
ing increasingly successful since it now re¬
quires the destruction of less and less
organic material. Thermoluminescence has
made it possible to date ceramics, and den¬
drochronology the age of wood, while for
questions of prehistory, the dating of bones
and the system of racemizing amino-acids
are yielding important information. '
The dialogue which has now been
established between the exact and the
human sciences in art and archaeology is
akin to that which exists between pure
science and medicine. It is to be hoped that
the various international initiatives in this
field will lead to a standardization of scien¬
tific methods which would have beneficial
consequences for the exchange of informa¬
tion, the conservation of the artistic heritage
and the campaign against forgers, as well as
providing historians and archaeologists with
new and more accurate criteria for dating
objects and relating them to their environ¬
ment.
In the exploration of the past there is
room for two methods of analysis, two ap¬
proaches which should lead to the same
goal: the unity and the broadening of the
concept of culture. For there is today a real
danger of a split between scientific culture
and the human sciences. If this hypothesis
of a divided universe became widely ac¬
cepted, it would mean the end of "Culture".
And so we should do all we can to promote
ever closer co-operation between the exact
and the human sciences. Such an effort is
bound to meet obstacles and it will call for
efforts on every side, but it is the only way,
in our opinion, towards a new humanism.
MAGDELEINE HOURS, of France, is head
curator of her country's National Museums, and
has directed the French Museums' Research
Laboratory since 1946. Madame Hours was Com¬
missaire Général of a major exhibition, "The
Secrets of the Great Masterpieces Science in
the Service ofArt", which was held in 1980 at the
Grand Palais in Pans. The exhibition presented a
series of outstanding works of art and also
displayed the spectrum of methods of scientific
examination, analysis and dating which are today
being used in the study and conservation of
works of art. Over 60 laboratories and almost a
hundred research workers were involved in the
work of the exhibition, for which a 330-page
catalogue was prepared comprising a description
of the works shown, scientific notes on the
methods used in connexion with them, andan ex¬
planatory list of scientific techniques in current
use. On the following pages we present specially
chosen extracts from this catalogue. We express
our thanks to the authors, the Réunion des
Musées Nationaux, and Madame Hours herself,
for authorizing us to publish them.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Lascaux
Saving a sanctuary
of prehistoric art
THE prehistoric painted cave of Lascaux is situated near the little
town of Montignac in the Périgord region of south-west France.
The whole area is rich in prehistoric sites, but it is in the lime¬
stone cliffs which run beside the winding course of the Vézère river
that the ancient rock shelters and caves are most abundant.
The Lascaux cave was discovered on 12 September 1940 by four
children from Montignac while they were playing among the pines
and chestnut trees on a steep slope above the river a kilometre or
two outside the town.
The opening of the cave, barely 80 cm square, was half hidden
beneath a layer of dead leaves. It plunged vertically into the hillside,
ending in a pile of debris and rubble.
In the next few weeks, the undergrowth surrounding the entrance
was cleared, and an enormous pit several dozen metres wide was
dug in front of the hole. The excavations provided virtually direct ac¬
cess to the grotto which, because of the animals depicted on its ceil¬
ing and walls, was to become known as the Hall of Bulls.
Access to the cave had probably never been easy. After the last of
the cave artists had left, rocks falling from the roof gradually piled up
and sealed off the grotto for thousands of years. Air currents and
water infiltrating through the debris caused little damage, except
possibly during the period at the end of the Ice Age, when
geologists believe that the calcite hollows known as gours were
formed. The calcification of the surface of the cone of rubble, the
formation of stalactites, and the infiltration of sand and clay washed
down by glacial meltwater must have consolidated the barrier at the
entrance. Studies would later show the importance of this barrier in
preserving the frescoes on the walls of the cave. The roof of the
limestone vault, between six and eight metres thick, was covered by
a layer of impermeable clay. As a result, the paintings, including the
"unicorn" situated less than ten metres from the original
passageway, remained in a perfect state of preservation.
The listing of the site as a historic monument on 27 December
1940 enabled the French authorities to intervene on what was a
piece of private property, and the owner was wisely persuaded to
erect a wooden door at the entrance to the cave. However, this was
mainly to prevent uncontrolled access by the public, not to preserve
the grotto's "microclimate", the significance of which was still
unsuspected.
Major operations at Lascaux did not begin until World War II was
over, and it was not until 14 July 1948 that, with a stone staircase, a
bronze door, an entrance hall and a paved pathway through the
grotto which had been equipped with protective barriers and
lighting, Lascaux was opened to the public.
The scenes portrayed in colour on the brilliant white calcite crust
are a supremely beautiful and impressive display of Palaeolithic art,
with their remarkably skilful use of the relief of the cave walls to
depict animals caught in mid-movement, and their highly individual
mixture of "perspectives and profiles. The conservation of the fres¬
coes called for scrupulous care and constant supervision.
In July 1955, the curator noticed that during peak visiting periods
condensation coloured by pigments from the frescoes was dripping
from the walls and ceiling. Scientific investigation established that
this was caused by the carbon dioxide exhaled by the visitors.
In 1958, an air conditioning system was installed. The air in the
cave was sucked through a filter to remove dust, decarbonated, and
to a constant temperature of 14°, while the humidity was
kept close to dew point (95-98. per cent). This electronically
regulated system was hooked up to a turnstile which recorded the
number of visitors entering the cave.
It proved so successful in eliminating condensation and purifying
the atmosphere that the owner was authorized to keep it running at
full power at the height of the summer tourist season, when on
some days over a thousand visitors filed through the grotto.
In September 1960, the curator noticed a green spot, so tiny as to
be scarcely perceptible, on the ceiling of the cave. Despite the ap¬
plication of a treatment recommended by the Pasteur Institute, tests
the following year showed that more spots had appeared. And so, in
March 1963, the Minister of Cultural Affairs, André Malraux, ap¬
pointed a special committee of scientists from a wide range of
disciplines to investigate the problem and propose solutions. It took
over ten years of dedicated efforts and close collaboration between
scientists from over a score of laboratories before the frescoes were
finally saved.
The closure of the cave, on 20 April 1963, was no solution to the
problem. The colonies of microscopic plant organisms which were
the source of the danger continued to spread, and within a few
months had increased from three to 720. Laboratory tests revealed
the presence of many species of algae, as well as growths of ferns,
mosses and fungi. Shock treatment was clearly required to eliminate
these sources of pollution.
After making sure that the paintings would not be harmed, the
scientists rid the cave of bacteria in the air by spraying the cave with
Photo © Institut de Photographie Scientifique et Médicale, Faculté de Medicine, Marseilles, France
antibiotics. The algae on the walls, which had by now spread out in¬
to 1,350 colonies, were gradually destroyed by spraying with solu¬
tions of formalin, in concentrations of 1:10 on the cave floor, 1:20 on
the bare rock, and 1:200 on the paintings. After two years of treat¬
ment, the micro-organisms had been totally wiped out, but in order
to prevent further contamination, visits were limited in number and
duration, and the intensity of the lighting was considerably reduced.
Regular analysis of the bacteria and the algae in the atmosphere and
on the floor of the cave, and inspections of the walls and ceiling
have made it possible to limit precautionary measures against new
outbreaks to a minimum.
Scarcely had the biological attack been repulsed, however, than a
new threat to the paintings materialized. The right-hand wall of a
smaller cave which leads out of the Hall of Bulls and is decorated
with stags, began to disappear under a fine crust of calcite crystals.
The same thing began to happen, to a lesser extent, to the unicorn
in the main grotto.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Archives Photographiques Paris/SPADEM
Left, the head of a
huge, four-metre-long
bull at Lascaux. The
mysterious, three-
pronged sign In front of
the bull is thought to be
a symbol of the male
sex. The visitors who
thronged Lascaux
during the fifteen or so
years that it was open
to the public disturbed
the delicate
microclimate of the
cave which had for
thousands of years
preserved intact this
amazing gallery of
prehistoric art. The cave
became excessively
humid and crystalline
formations such as the
calcite crystal (opposite
page) began to appear.
The only way to combat
this "white sickness"
was to re-create the
original microclimate
and this unfortunately
involved closing the
cave to the general
public.
After examining the formation of the calcite crystals by means of
microphotography, the scientists undertook a comprehensive ex¬
amination of the entire structure and climate of the cave, using
various other ultra-modern hydrological and geological techniques.
The outline of the cave, and its relation to the surface of the hillside,
were plotted in detail. The soil was analysed and, by means of a ver¬
tical photogrammetric survey carried out every 5 mm, contour lines
were established for all the painted areas. The pigmentation of the
paintings was examined in depth and content, and the temperature
of the soil was studied by infra-red radiometry. At the same time, the
temperature at various points on the cave walls was measured to
within 1 /100th of a degree, and the volume of the enclosed space
was accurately determined (1,778 m3). Aerodynamic studies were
carried out to detect the existence of microclimates through data
provided by electronic equipment which recorded in minute detail
the temperature, humidity, carbon dioxide content and barometric
pressure.
The processing of all the data obtained over several years led the
scientific committee to decide on a course of action designed to
preserve as far as possible the "natural" climate of the cave, and
more particularly to prevent changes in temperature, humidity and
carbon dioxide content.
Air entering the cave is now chilled; excess carbon dioxide of
natural origin is tapped at its source (the so-called "Wizard's Well")
and pumped out of the cave. Partitioning of the cave into several
compartments also helps to stabilize the temperature (at 13°),
humidity (at 98 per cent), and carbon dioxide content (at 1 per cent).
No more than five visitors, who must be bona fide scientists, may
enter the cave on any one day. The cave is completely sealed on two
days each week.
Eighteen years after the cave was closed to the public, the wall
paintings of Lascaux have been saved from what had seemed to be
certain destruction.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
-*<*
Photo© Archives Photographiques Paris/SPADEM.
Above, general view of the Hall of Bulls, and, opposite
page, the reconstruction presented at a recent exhibition
at the Galeries Nationales of the Grand Palais, Paris.
Below, a plan of the Hall of Bulls.
The hall of bulls
THE Hall of Bulls forms the heart of the
Lascaux cave complex. Its form and
prolific painted decoration make it a
masterpiece of prehistoric art. From 1963 to
1975, twenty-five French laboratories work¬
ed together with the historic monuments
authority and prehistorians to save the site.
Their efforts constitute an outstanding ex¬
ample of how science can serve art.
Although the grotto was saved, its condi¬
tion remained fragile. A balance had to be
carefully maintained between the tempe¬
rature, humidity and carbon dioxide con¬
tent. This balance was precarious, and visits
now have to be strictly limited.
To enable a wide public to appreciate the
beauty of Lascaux, a life-size facsimile of the
Hall of Bulls was constructed for the
Science au Service de l'Art exhibition held
last year at the Grand Palais, Paris. The fac¬
simile was produced with the collaboration
of the French National Geographic Institute
which had previously made a photogram¬
metric survey of the cave. This made it
possible to reconstitute the contours of the
Hall of Bulls to an accuracy of a quarter of a
centimetre.
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Photo J. Rochaix © Kodak-Pathé, Paris
Reconstituted masterpieces of early man
Using the data from the Institute's survey,
a firm specializing in the construction of
theatre sets began the difficult task of
building an artificial cave. A team of
specialists made twenty-six unit modules,
each module comprising a frame with five
vertical and seven horizontal sections in
plywood at intervals of twenty-five cen¬
timetres.
The modules were then filled in with ex¬
panded polystyrene blocks to reconstitute
the cave's macrorelief. Each block was then
modelled to obtain the microrelief of the
rocky sides of the cave. The polystyrene sur¬
face of the blocks was protected by a layer
of latex and then a mixture of polyester resin
and fibre glass was sprayed on, forming a
resistant, fireproof layer about five
millimetres thick. This plastic structure
faithfully moulds the underlying cast, but
without adhering to it.
This polyester structure held by the
wooden frame was then removed from the
polystyrene blocks and covered with an
ochre and red coating mixed with sand,
gravel and resin to give the overall impres¬
sion of a limestone and calcite surface. The
areas which were to receive the reproduc¬
tions of the frescoes were painted white.
The twenty-six fireproof modules were then
assembled by screwing them on to a raised
platform which resembled the sloping floor
of the cave.
So far so good! A replica of the Hall of
Bulls now existed. But how could
photographic enlargements of the wall pain¬
tings be placed on the uneven surface of the
walls? To attempt a photographic
reconstitution in relief of the Lascaux pain¬
tings seemed to be to defy the laws of
photography and physics. A team of experts
from the Kodak-Pathé research laboratories
at Vincennes, near Paris, came up with the
following ingenious solution to the problem.
The technique they evolved is new and
consists of transferring by a decalcomania
process a photographic image, previously
stripped of its original paper base, on to any
type of surface (wood, stone, metal, fabric,
plastic, plaster, etc.). Transfer is achieved
after a treatment which makes the stripped
film elastic. The resulting gelatin layer is only
a few microns thick and features the amaz
ing property of not distorting laterally when
stretched.
Strange as it may seem, when this layer of
film containing the photographic informa¬
tion is transferred it faithfully moulds onto
the boldest relief without changing the true
density of the original colours. Added to the
exact reproduction of colours and the details
of the photographic technique is the realism
of the underlying relief.
The photographic enlargements to be
transferred to the walls were printed from
twenty-five colour negatives provided by the
French National Geographic Institute, keep¬
ing to the original dimensions of the Lascaux
paintings. This required fine optical ad¬
justments. Allowances also had to be made
for any variances in density and colour from
one image to another after processing.
One of the problems was to calculate and
assemble the photographic prints as a flat
mosaic. The prints had to fit together
perfectly despite the inevitable distortions
due to picture-taking angles which were ag¬
gravated by the overhanging concave sides
of the cave. I
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
The Hall of Bulls (continued)
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
> Once printing had been completed on col¬
our paper the actual transfer of the images
to the cave face had to be prepared. The
first operation consisted of calculating the
colour photo assembly on a 1:6 model. Us¬
ing this "puzzle" the original mosaic was cut
up into about 200 quadrangular prints. Each
print position was carefully identified on the
final layout and a standard 60x80 cm size
adopted to facilitate subsequent automation
of operations.
The cut-out prints were pasted emulsion
face down onto decalcomania paper or¬
dinary paper comprising a layer of water-
soluble gelatin. The photographic ¡mage
was then peeled off its original base in a
special machine which dissolves the resin
underlayer, isolating the photographic emul¬
sion from its paper base. After drying, the
layer which holds the picture is thus affixed>
to the decalcomania paper which is easily
removed by wetting.
Each print was then pasted with an
adhesive on to the area marked out for it.
The paper was easily removed with wet
sponges and brushes so that only the
photographic image remained pasted to the
artificial rock face and its myriad indenta¬
tions.
Once the enlargements had been trans¬
ferred, retouching had to be carried out to
compensate for any imperfections during
the decalcomania process, particularly at the
junction of the modules. Lastly, the tints of
the paintings had to be harmonized with the
adjacent rocks.
The realism of this three-dimensional
photographic reproduction of the Hall of
Bulls was heightened by low-temperature
air-conditioning and music evoking the
sound of dripping water.
1) Assembling the plywood framework of
the artificial cave.
2) A section of the artificial cave is eased
into position.
3) The photographic prints of the wall
paintings being assembled as a flat mosaic.
4) Assembling the llfesize enlargements.
5) and 6) The delicate process of
transferring the photographs to the
modules of the artificial cave walls.
Photos 1 , 3, 4, 6. Pertuisot © Kodak-Pathé, Paris
Photo 2: J Rochaix © Kodak-Pathé, Paris
Photo 5 Courtoix © Kodak-Pathé, Pans
Pages 9-11: photographic reconstitution of the wall paintings of
the Hall of Bulls, Lascaux, produced by means of a process of
photographic transfer in relief perfected by the Kodak-Pathé
Research Centre for the 'Musées de France for the exhibition Ls
Vie Mystérieuse des Chefs-d'Oeuvre, la Science au Service de l'Art
(Secrets of the Great Masterpieces, Science in the Service of Art),
organized by Madame Magdeleme Hours
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
The scientific
investigation
of painting
Painting is a form of creativity
which has developed in a historical
context. It is both the result of an
act putting brush to canvas and the
fruit of reflexion. No factor in this pro¬
cess should be overlooked, for each
step is a contribution to the making
and hence the understanding of
masterpieces. Science can help us
here in three fundamental ways: by
shedding light on history, by revealing
the technology used by artists and
craftsmen, and by helping to ensure
that their works are preserved for
posterity.
The contribution of scientific in¬
vestigation to art history is essential.
This does not mean, however, that the
new approach should be granted
privileged status, to the detriment of
connoisseurship and the traditional
methods of art criticism (the opposi¬
tion between scientist and humanist is
a thing of the past), but simply that
the properties of various kinds of
radiation and the resources of modern
physics are today enriching our
perceptions of works of very different
styles and periods.
Studies to establish the authenticity
of paintings may call for the use of
powerful apparatus such as the elec¬
tron probe microanalyser and
sophisticated techniques such as
X-ray microfluorescence. These tech¬
niques are used to analyse the tech¬
nology of the artist and his period, the
materials he used and the way they
have aged, as well as providing infor¬
mation about dating and artistic
techniques. The proliferation of fakes
and the skilfulness of forgers has put
us on our guard, and in the search for
truth the results being obtained from a
whole range of methods and the infor¬
mation being subsequently stored in
computers, are helping us even more
than heavyweight equipment.
Methods for dating paintings are
currently being studied all over the
world, but they are still at the ex¬
perimental stage and it is too early as
yet to bank on their efficiency.
Finally, scientific analysis is playing
a crucial role in the conservation of
paintings. We can only conserve what
we thoroughly know, and for the
health of a work of art, like that of a
human being, a laboratory diagnosis
must precede treatment.
12
LABORATORY examination of Rem¬
brandt's Portrait of a Young Man
made it possible to rediscover the
picture's basic structure and to compare its
characteristics with those of other works by
Rembrandt.
Two types of investigation, one global,
the other detailed and highly specific, were
conducted from the surface of the painting
down to the deepest layers, in order to
discover the techniques used by the artist.
X-ray photography revealed the original
sketch for the portrait and the overall con¬
struction of the composition, while detailed
analysis of a small cross-section sample
disclosed what materials the artist used, the
layers in which they were applied and the
technology involved.
The X-ray picture (below right) shows an
earlier composition of a woman leaning over
a cradle, which the artist had overpainted. It
Rembrandt's Portrait of a Young Man, dated 1658, Louvre Museum, Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
I. X-ray
of a Rembrandt
II. True or false?
also shows that the features of the young
man's face have been broadly outlined in
white lead with the large brush and firm
strokes that. were characteristic of Rem¬
brandt's work at the end of his life.
Microscopic study of a small cross-
section removed from the central part of the
picture during restoration work confirmed
the presence of more than one painting:
eight different layers of paint could be
observed, four belonging to the lower com¬
position and four to the more recent one.
The cross-section also showed that the
underlying painting was completed, for
traces of varnish are visible between the
layer of white depicting the woman's veil
and those depicting the young man's
garment.
Analysis of the cross-section by an elec¬
tron probe microanalyser made it possible to
identify all the elements of which the paint is
composed. With the aid of X-ray
An X-ray image of the painting reveals its underlying structure and the bold
wide brush marks typical of Rembrandt's technique. The X-ray also brought to
WIUU UlUStll llianvo lyi^iv i wi i i*-i n«" m. .«.. « ..w«	^	 	 	-.-
liaht the presence of an earlier painting of a woman seated beside a cradle
photographs, specialists can chart "density
distribution maps" of the various elements.
In this way the distribution of lead, iron,
silicium, aluminium, phosphorus and
calcium can be traced. Exploration of each
microcube of paint with the "electronic
brush" gives a representative picture of the
pigments used, singly or together. This can
be compared with the artist's characteristic
techniques.
Both the quality of the sketch disclosed
by the X-ray and the nature of the painting
materials revealed by the cross-section and
the electron probe microanalyser proved
that this work tallied with pictures by Rem¬
brandt that had already been scientifically
analysed.
X-RAYS and analytic studies have also
proved valuable in distinguishing
fakes from authentic works. One
painting which was authenticated in this
way is the Virgin of the Annunciation, an
early 15th-century work by the Italian artist
Taddeo di Bartolo (photo top left, overleaf).
The X-ray photograph (photo top right,
overleaf) shows a clear image of the com¬
position and of the wood panel on which it is
painted. The poplar panel is in a good state
of preservation, despite a knot in the wood
at the level of the Virgin's chest, which has
been filled in with an opaque substance
which does not let X-rays through. The
panel consists of two separate lengths, join¬
ed together with a substance which is also
opaque.
To make the support smoother and to
level out knots in the wood, a canvas was in¬
corporated into the gesso, the substance
with which the surface was prepared for
painting. A large piece of this canvas covers
the whole of the lower part of the panel
below the Virgin's eyes. The entire surface
of the panel was prepared for painting, in¬
cluding those parts not covered with paint.
The X-ray ¡mage of the painting has a very
low density, for the elements in the painting
materials (earths, lapis lazuli and lacquers)
have a low atomic mass. The details of the
face, the hair and the veil covering it, as well
as folds in the dress, have been painted in
with a soft brush and very fluid paint rapidly
applied. A faint tracery of fine parallel
cracks, perpendicular to the grain of the
wood, has had an effect on the material
used.
An infra-red photograph also showed up
the artist's elegant, flowing style. In places,
the lines of the drawing itself can be seen,
especially in the hair, the face, the hands,
the folds of the garments and the strip of veil
on the bosom. Some deterioration can be
observed in the cloak.
Study of the painting materials shows
that both the substances and the
technology involved correspond to the sug¬
gested period and origin of the picture:
The dressing applied to the panel con¬
sists of a gesso made up of calcium sulphate
and size, applied in two layers and in which
a canvas is included.
The blue of the Virgin's cloak consists
of coarse grains of lapis lazuli crystals.
These are covered by a layer of Prussian
blue, evidence of an early restoration of this
part of the picture.
The red of the robe is a mixture of mad¬
der lacquer and white lead.
The coloured layer has been applied
with an egg tempera.
All these features are consistent with the
tradition of Italian painting at the beginning k
of the fifteenth century, as described f
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
minutely by Cennino Cennini in his Libro
delTArte. The rediscovery of this treatise,
published in Italy in 1821 by Cavalière Tram-
boni and translated into French in 1858 by
the painter Victor Mottez, gave rise to a
series of fake Italian primitives.
The Virgin and Child (photo bottom left),
another painting on wood closely related in
its general style to the Sienese school of the
15th century, has been shown to be a fake.
Several formal details in this painting are
hard to reconcile with its presumed period
and origin.
In a case like this, scientific analysis using
optical and microchemical methods can pro¬
vide data which may confirm or refute
results obtained by the historical and
aesthetic criteria used by the art historian.
X-ray photography is undoubtedly one of
the most useful methods of authenticating
pictures. It reveals the structure of the work
in depth, the sketch outlined by the artist
and any anomalies that may exist, thereby
making it possible to compare the painting
with evidence obtained from fully authen¬
ticated works.
Clearly the X-ray photograph (bottom
right) is very different from those of works
of the 15th century. The X-ray image of the
composition is practically invisible; there is a
vague outline of draped folds on the
shoulder and sleeves which can no longer be
seen in the picture in its present state. The
most interesting information provided by the
X-ray is a large network of premature and
artificially-induced cracks. These are of an
entirely different nature from the tracery of
fine cracks indicative of age which covers
the surface of genuine primitives.
An infra-red-ray photograph (not shown
here) restored the original form of the
cloak's drapery, subsequently hidden by a
layer of repainting. It was also possible to
see damage to the face which had later been
repaired. The photo showed that the picture
had been extensively restored, and this was
confirmed by study of the layers of painting
materials.
Microchemical analysis revealed, in fact,
that there were anachronisms in the com¬
position of the paint. Cross-sections showed
that the application of the paint of the
pseùdo-Sienese Virgin followed the tradi¬
tional pattern with the colours being applied
over a thick white gesso. However there
were several anomalies:
Above, Madonna, by the Sienese
painter Taddeo di Bartolo (1362-1422),
now in the Petit Palais Museum,
Avignon. The X-ray image reveals
features characteristic of the Sienese
school of the early 15th century.
Right, forged Virgin and Child, In the
style of the Siena school. The X-ray
¡mage, with its lack of density, is quite
different from those obtained from
genuine paintings of the period.
Chemical analysis revealed the presence
of lithopone, a white pigment not in
use before 1875.
The white imprimatura overlaying the
gesso on the entire surface of the picture is
made up of a layer with a base of lithopone,
a mixture of zinc sulphide and barium
sulphate which only came into use after
1875.
Lithopone is also present in the flesh-
coloured layers. It should be noted,
however, that these were traditionally made
up of a layer of pink on a layer with a green
earth base.
The red paint has a cadmium base only
used since the 19th century, and the yellow
has an antimony base. Antimony was a pig¬
ment known in Antiquity but which did not
come into use again until the 18th century.
This evidence is sufficient to show that
the picture could not have been painted
earlier than the end of the 19th century.
In addition, cross-sections of the yellow
of the Child's robe and of the red of the
Virgin's robe revealed that the paint had
penetrated into the cracks of the im¬
primatura layer. This suggests that the latter
was artificially dried before the layer of col¬
our was applied.
Finally, the binding agent in the paint is a
distemper with or without the addition of
some oilwhich is chemically quite dif¬
ferent from the egg tempera that one would
expect in a painting of this period.
Thus, although the picture has undergone
considerable restoration and although the
painter was skilful enough to use a tech¬
nique resembling that of primitive painters
of the 15th century, the presence of recently
adopted pigments uniformly and, therefore,
mechanically ground, makes it extremely
easy to identify as a fake.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Heat treatment
unmasks a sham Zapotee
IN the past few years stylistic studies of
pre-Columbian objects in some of the
world's major museums have brought
to light some puzzling findings.
Thermoluminescence (see article page 21)
and optical microscopy are two scientific
techniques that have been used to solve the
problems arising from these discoveries.
The former revealed that some of the ob¬
jects in question were of recent manufac¬
ture; the latter pinpointed where the objects
had been made.
Photos above and right show two of forty
terra-cotta statues belonging to the Musée
de l'Homme in Paris and to the Royal
Museums in Brussels which were studied in
this way. They are both examples of the
Zapotee style named for the Zapotee Indians
of what is now southern Mexico. One is an
authentic archaeological specimen; the
other was made in relatively recent times.
Photo above shows the head of an old
man which forms part of a large terra-cotta
object symbolizing the cult of an elderly
god. The god is depicted as an old man
whose tall headdress surmounted by plumes
was a brazier in which copal was burned in
his honour.
Photo right shows an anthropomorphic urn
representing the god of corn. The figure
holds an ear of corn in each hand and the
headdress is also decorated with ears of
corn. These great anthropomorphic urns are
characteristic of Zapotee civilization. They
were often found in tombs and sometimes in
temples.
Thermoluminescence makes it possible to
distinguish between ceramics fired several
centuries ago and those produced recently.
Measurements were made with a forty-
milligramme sample of powder to determine
its natural thermoluminescence, on the one
hand, and, on the other, its artificial ther¬
moluminescence after it had been irradiated
in a laboratory.
The results obtained enabled specialists to
calculate the amount of radiation deposited
in the ceramic material since it had been
fired: the old man's head had absorbed
about 300 rads, a dose commensurate with
an "archaeological object"; whereas the
dose absorbed by the corn god was no more
than 17 rads. It was therefore possible to
conclude that the corn god was made
recently, and even to date its manufacture
to the beginning of the 20th century.
Examination of thin strips from ancient
and modern Zapotee objects through a
polarizing microscope revealed the following
facts: several different clays had been used,
but all contained, in varying proportions, a
type of mineral found in a zone of the Oax-
aca valley where the Zapotee civilization
developed, and in particular at Monte
Alban, the main site of this civilization. It
can thus be assumed that both ancient and
recent objects were produced in the same
area.
Microscopic examination has also reveal¬
ed that a number of modern objects, mainly
large anthropomorphic urns, were probably
produced in the same workshop. The
ceramic pastes used in these objects are
remarkably uniform and contain the same
minerals, of identical size and in equivalent
proportions, set in a base of yellowish,
clayey paste.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
X-ray microfluorescence
and a Merovingian treasure
X-RAY microfluorescence is a spectro-
metric technique which can be used
to analyse the constituent elements
of any material. The spectrometer consists
of a source of X-rays which "excites" the
material to be analysed, a detector which
measures the radiation emitted, and two
analysers which divide the radiation into
rays.
This apparatus is particularly well adapted
to the needs of museological research. Its
results rank between those produced by the
electron probe microanalyser and those
yielded by classic X-ray fluorescence spec¬
trometers.
X-ray microfluorescence makes it possible
to analyse, directly and without causing the
least damage, all types of objects and ar¬
chaeological materials, whether they are
conductors (metals) or nonconductors
(ceramics, glass and organic compounds),
and whatever their shape or size. It can thus
be used both with large-scale works of art
(paintings or archaeological specimens), or
with tiny samples of powder, glaze, solder,
encrustations, corrosion, patina or painting
materials.
Using this technique, direct analysis can
be made of tiny areas of an object, ranging
from a tenth of a millimetre to a dozen
millimetres in diameter. If specially adapted,
it can be used to analyse samples only a few
dozen microns in diameter. In this case, the
sample must be preserved, for since the sen¬
sitivity and precision of X-ray micro-
fluorescence are constantly improving, it is
useful to be able to complete preliminary
analyses later on.
This non-destructive technique, recently
developed by the French Museums'
Research Laboratory, proved its worth in
analysing the treasure of Queen Aregunda,
wife of the Merovingian King Chlotar I
(c. 497-561 AD), whose tomb was
discovered at Saint-Denis in 1959 by Michel
Fleury. This is the only Merovingian royal
tomb which has ever been identified, except
for that of Childeric I, discovered at Tournai
in 1654. Queen Aregunda's tomb contained
a rich store of precious objects.
A painstaking laboratory study was made
of the treasure, which consists of a pair of
pins, ear-rings, a long pin, two round fibula,
a signet ring, ornaments for a belt, garters
and shoes, and gold sleeve bands.
The state of the objects was such that it
was impossible to take samples, and
analysis of the gold or silver alloys of which
they were made was carried out directly on
the surface using X-ray microfluorescence.
The analysis was effected at several points
on each of the jewels in order to obtain
quantitative results, taking into account
possible changes in the surface composition
due to deterioration of the gilding and niello-
work.
The results showed that each pair of ob¬
jects was made of a different alloy, whereas
the objects in each pair were made of the
same alloy. Examination through a binocular
magnifying glass also showed that the
workmanship of one object in each pair was
highly skilful, while the other revealed an in¬
ferior level of craftsmanship. It could be
deduced from this that each pair of objects
was from the same workshop (since the
composition of the alloy was the same) but
that one item in each pair had been made by
the master craftsman and the other by an ar¬
tisan.
Gold and silver pin encrusted with garnets. It
was buried near the Queen's breast.
These two circular gold clasps encrusted
with garnets fastened Queen Aregunda's silk
tunic at the neck and waist.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Ancient
metallurgy
The computer is turning up a mine of information
METALLURGY is a field in which,
more than any other, close co¬
operation has developed between
specialists in the exact and social sciences,
who have built on the multidisciplinar/ foun¬
dations laid by the remarkable work of the
metallurgist Cyril Smith at the Massa¬
chusetts Institute of Technology.
Extractive and chemical metallurgy, which
is linked to the nature and origin of mineral
ores, is one of the new lines of ar¬
chaeological research that have developed
over the last fifteen years thanks to the rapid
evolution of spectrometric, atomic and
nuclear techniques.
Ores of different geographic origins have
a different chemical composition
characterized either by the proportion or by
the nature of the impurities which reflect the
geology of the various rock formations. Ar¬
chaeological research is concerned either
with metallogeny, that is the processes
through which ore is transformed- into
metal, or with the analysis of their trace
elements and the magnitude of the lead
isotopes. The purpose of this research is to
discover indicators which then make it
possible to determine the origin of ar¬
chaeological objects.
Such multi-disciplinary research, in which
analysts, archaeologists and geologists co¬
operate, deals with archaeological prospec¬
tion of ancient copper, silver, gold, tin, lead
and antimony mines. It is being carried out
in many parts of the world, notably by in
stitutes in the United States, Europe, the
Soviet Union and Japan.
The metallurgy of processing and
manufacture, which investigates the actual
making of objects, is a more traditional line
of research. X-ray photography can reveal
assembly and smelting techniques, while in¬
vestigation of thermal, mechanical and
chemical processing, which modify the
crystalline structure, requires elementary
analysis of the metal, or microscopic ex¬
amination of a metallographic section, along
with dilatometric or thermal analysis.
[Dilatometry is the measurement of changes
of volume caused by thermal or chemical
effects.]
Examination through a microscope of the
metallographic structure discloses the
technological past recorded by the metal.
This method, which has been used in
metallurgy for over two centuries, makes it
possible, among other things, to explain the
role of carbon in the crystallization of the
steel in damascene swords, which are
decorated with peculiar markings produced
during manufacture.
Physical metallurgy establishes relations
between the physical properties of a metal
obtained by mechanical, thermal or
chemical effects on the crystalline structure.
Very delicate technology such as the elec¬
tron microscope, electron-, neutron- and
X-ray diffraction, the electron probe
microanalyser or the ionic microprobe is
used to carry out these physical
measurements.
With such ultra-modern equipment
researchers can now understand the
transformation processes of metal; it is
possible to identify an effect of corrosion
and discover its origin. Research on
deterioration in metals, and in particular in
ancient alloys, has increased our under¬
standing of slow corrosion processes and
The "vase à la cachette"
discovered on the citadel of
Susa, Iran, in 1908. Beside it
are the copper and alabaster
objects it contained. The
vase, 51 cm high and 20 cm
in diameter, dates from
approximately 2400 BC.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
. contributed to the conservation of metal ob¬
jects. Thus the practical experience acquired
by artisans in Antiquity and the natural age¬
ing of metals are a source of scientific infor¬
mation which applies both to art works and
to the most up-to-date industrial activities.
The technical research applied to art both
for obtaining data and processing them is
helping the exact sciences to interpret the
history of metallurgy itself, together with its
techniques. Thus, for example, extensive
research carried out on finds such as the
"vase à la cachette" ("the treasure-trove
jar") has enabled specialists to draw up a
map of the ancient trade routes for copper
and tin.
The "vase à la cachette" is in fact the
treasure contained in two large jars, one
undecorated, the other painted, together
with its lid, which were discovered on the
site of the Susa citadel in 1908 by the mis¬
sion led by the French archaeologist
Jacques de Morgan. The treasure includes
crude metal the residue from five
crucibles, weapons, and tools for making
copper vessels similar to those found in the
"royal tombs" of Ur as well as alabaster
jars and cylindrical seals. The latter which
are either of local style or imported from
Mesopotamia, confirm not only the date as
being approximately that of the first Ur
dynasty (between 2500 and 2350 BC), but
the links which united Susa, one of the main
cities of Elam (the plain of present-day
Khuzistan in south-west Iran) and the land
of Sumer (see map).
Susa, a city with a culture related to those
of Mesopotamia and the Iranian plateau,
was in fact the meeting point of the routes
crossing the plateau, along which were
dispatched the raw materials and finished
products necessary to the powerful States
of the alluvial plains.	
Highly advanced copper metallurgy is
known to have existed in Elam as early as
the beginning of the fourth millennium. It
spread to Mesopotamia right at the end of
this period and especially during the third
millennium. Yet both these regions are
without any natural mineral resources. The
raw materials necessary to the artisans of
the Mesopotamian cities could have come
from a number of areas, such as Anatolia,
the Iranian plateau, where metallurgy had
been developed as early as the fifth millen¬
nium, or the mountains of Oman, to men¬
tion only the nearest.
How can we establish what really were
their sources of supply?
The use of physical and chemical
parameters as a means of identifying the
mines and the manufactured objects that
originated from these mines has made it
possible to establish the relationship bet¬
ween mineral resources and metal objects.
And, by assigning to each group of ar¬
chaeological objects its original ore, it has
become possible in turn to determine
precisely where the various cities obtained
their copper.
One of the techniques used to analyse the
composition of microsamples of native cop¬
pers and ores collected during prospection
in Iran, Oman and Afghanistan, as well as
the composition of finished objects from
Susa, such as the "vase à la cachette", is
spark source mass spectrometry. This
technique has made it possible to conduct
simultaneous quantitative analysis of more
than 30 different chemical elements in each
sample.
Computer processing of the data thus ob¬
tained has enabled us to reconstitute the
chemical transformations that take place in
the course of the ore's conversion into metal
and to check that the geochemical features
of the original ore are present in the
manufactured object.
Thus despite the changes that occur
when the ore is reduced and the objects are
cast, the correlation of the different
chemical elements and their respective
distribution are seen to correspond before
and after the pyrotechnical transformation.
This use of computers to chart the evolu¬
tion of concentrations of trace elements and
minor elements has enabled us to refine
research on the "ore-object relationship"
and to establish a connexion between cer¬
tain ores and groups of objects which,
otherwise, would have gone unnoticed.
Throughout the study great attention has
been paid to the consistency of the results
both from the technological and historical
viewpoints. Basic information about ancient
mining sites the dates when they were
worked and the mineral resources they
yielded as well as detailed analysis of
various residues and remains of
metallurgical activity (such as casting ducts
and the walls of furnaces), have all been
taken into account. Moreover, precise
methods of identifying elements added to
copper ore to increase its fluidity during
casting or to serve as alloys have been
developed.
The combined use of elementary analysis
and the techniques of data analysis has pro¬
duced new information on the supply
sources of copper and tin in the Middle East
during the fourth and- third millennia before
the Christian era.
In the fourth millennium, most of the cop¬
per came from the Iranian plateau. But an
important change took place at the beginn¬
ing of the third millennium when new trade
links were established along the Gulf and,
from then on, the copper used in Meso¬
potamia came from the mountains of Oman,
the Magan of ancient Sumerian texts.
Map Unesco Courier. Source La Vie Mystérieuse des Chefs-d'OEuvre, Editions de la Réunion des Musées Nationaux, Paris
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Celestial radiance
Photos © Laboratoire de Recherche des Musées de France, Pans
12th-century replica of an
11th-century Tibetan brass
statue of Vajrapani, a
celestial Bodhisattva
("Buddha-to-be"). The X-ray
¡mage reveals the internal
structure of the statue as
well as the method of
casting used.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Anatomy
of
a harp
X-RAY examination ofmusical instruments is basic to under¬
standing the technology, invisible from the outside, which
has a direct bearing on their acoustic qualities: the shape
and roughness of the holes in a wind instrument, for example, or the
form and structure of the sound board of string instruments.
The structural changes which each instrument has undergone in
the course of its history are also very important since, in addition to
providing historical data, they can make it possible to reconstitute
the sound originally produced by the instrument.
Among Egyptian musical instruments, the harp has always been a
particular favourite; its shape and dimensions have varied con¬
siderably. The instrument shown above dates from sometime during
the first or second millennia BC, and is in a perfect state of conserva¬
tion. The harp, now in the Louvre, consists of a vertical sound box
(1.10 metres high) entirely covered in green leather, and a console
(cross-piece) made from a cylindrical bar of wood set at an angle of
85 degrees to the sound box. Twenty-one strings are wound around
the console, and cords ' with a tassle at the end en¬
abled the player to tune the instrument.
Visual examination does not reveal the various elements of the
sound box the essential part of the instrument but X-ray
photography has enabled specialists better to understand the form
and structure of this type of instrument.
In profile, the sound box is shown to be a massive piece of wood
hollow from the top down to the level of the console. The upper part
is closed by an oval piece of wood set in between the sides of the
sound box. Fixed to the sound box is the suspension rod to which
the strings are attached. It tapers towards its lower end, just above
the console.
The two sides of the sound box are maintained apart by five small,
intricately-worked cross-pieces about 7 cm high. These dovetail-
shaped wedges are set at regular intervals in the sound box, which is
reinforced by two vertical ribs from one to two centimetres thick.
The small piece of wood jutting out from the top of the sound box
on the left may have been a support for a symbolic figure similar to
those found on certain musical instruments.
X-ray photography shows that the base of the sound box hidden
beneaththe leather has an outline slightly different from what is visi¬
ble from the outside. Moreover, a small piece of wood has been add-
20
ed to reinforce the base on which the instrument rests, but this in no
way alters its character.
The different components and their position have enabled
specialists to compare the harp with one formerly preserved in
Berlin. The Berlin harp was in a very bad state of conservation, but
after detailed study a copy of it was made on which it was possible
to play. The copy and the original harp, which have since disap¬
peared, were described in a published study, and it is interesting to
note that there is a close similarity between the harp in the Louvre
and the Berlin instrument. Both reveal a relatively sophisticated
technology, and could even have been produced by the same
instrument-maker.
To understand a musical instrument, all its aspects must be con¬
sidered: how it was made, how it works, its acoustics and its
aesthetic appearance.
The X-ray photographs show that the techniques used in making
this Egyptian harp were advanced. Detailed analysis of its shape
shows that the "aesthetic ideology" of ancient Egyptian harp-
makers was based on proportions similar to those used in architec¬
ture. The harp's outline is that of a specific geometrical figure whose
measurements are absolutely proportionate to the "Royal Cubit"
(52.35 cm), a unit of length used in ancient Egypt.
This type of instrument consists of two parts: an "instigating"
system, represented here by the strings, and a "resonance" system,
represented by the sound box.
The design of the sound box with its dove-tail-shaped cross-
sections and that of the console and their respective positions show
that the mechanical problems had been mastered. The strings could
vibrate once they had been stretched and the sound box was "flex¬
ible" enough to change shape temporarily.
Greater amplitudes of vibration in the lower ranges are required to
make the sound appear homogeneous to the ear. This was done by
making the lowest-pitched string four times longer than the highest
one, for the aim was not to achieve sounds of great intensity but
sounds which were warm and mysterious. This explains why a
leather sound board was used instead of a wooden one. In order to
bring the whole of the board into play, the wooden rod to which the
ends of the strings are attached was placed under the leather.
Acoustically, the system is appropriate and effective.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
M
s
]ß*mmm
i r.
Analysis of the sound range by "acoustic spectrography", that is,
,the "response curve" obtained by tapping at each extremity the
longest, medium and shortest string, shows in each case a dif¬
ference in the degree of "freedom" between the two points.
The end nearest the leather has a lower pitch than the console
end. The timbre has therefore two different frequency areas similar
to those of the "human voice".
The harpist used to tune his instrument by stretching the strings
to the point where the sound corresponded with the ideal of the day;
fine-tuning was done later. He changed the pitch according to the
"scale" of the piece he happened to be playing. It seems likely that
the twenty-one strings covered three octaves of seven notes which
could be adjusted at will.
The workmanship that went into making the harp, its physical
characteristics and results of the acoustic studies all point to a high
degree of technical sophistication. The acoustic study, however, is
not entirely conclusive since the instrument is not in a state to be
played; the strings do not have the proper tension, the leather has
lost its elasticity and the handle has probably been altered. The con¬
ditions in which the instrument was tuned and played have in¬
evitably changed.
However, the X-ray photographs and readings from the
"response curve" would make it possible to construct a model on
which a real study could be made.
Réunion des Musées Nationaux, Paris
These texts original/y appeared in the catalogue of the exhibition "La Vie Mystérieuse
des Chefs-d'OEuvre. La Science au Service de l'Art" (Secrets of the Great Master¬
pieces Science in the Service of Art!, which was published by Les editions de la Réu¬
nion des Musées Nationaux, Paris 1 19801 under the direction of Madame Magdeleine
Hours. They have been extracted from articles, notes and graphics by: Magdeleine
Hours, Max Sarradet, Suzy Delbourgo, Jeanne Gautier, Michel Fleury, Juliette Liszak-
Hours, Christian Lahanier, Pierre Amiet, Thierry Berthoud, Lola Faillant-Dumas,
Florence Abondance, France Drilhon, Emile Leipp.
Art, archaeology
and the atom
Nuclear dating techniques
and how they work
by Bernard Keisch
ONE cannot possibly overemphasize the importance of
carbon-14 dating in the fields of art and archaeology since
its discovery shortly after World War II.
The importance of the method was recognized immediately and,
in 1960, earned for its discoverer, Willard F. Libby, the Nobel Prize.
The reasoning behind the method is this. The earth is being con¬
tinually bathed in cosmic radiation. One product of that radiation, a
quantity of neutrons, reacts with nitrogen in the upper atmosphere
to produce carbon-14.
Since the flux of neutrons has been nearly cohstant for the last
several thousand years, the rate at which carbon-14 has been
produced by this means has been just as constant.
The carbon-14 atoms react chemically with oxygen to form car¬
bon dioxide, which eventually mixes, throughout the atmosphere,
with ordinary carbon dioxide. (Ordinary carbon atoms contain
6 protons and 6 neutrons and are not radioactive.) Carbon dioxide in
our atmosphere is incorporated into living tissue by growing vegeta¬
tion. Animals that eat vegetation, and the animals that eat
vegetarians, etc., also eventually contain carbon-14.
The end result is that all living things must contain carbon-14 in
the same concentration that occurs in the atmosphere during their
lifetime. But carbon-14 has a half-life of about 6,000 years, and
when an organism dies and ceases to participate in the biosphere, its
carbon-14 supply is no longer being replenished by freshly produced
carbon-14 through' the food chain. The concentration of carbon-14
in its tissues thus begins to decrease.
The nature of radioactivity is such that we may express the rate at
which a radioactive substance disappears in terms of its half-life. In
this case, it means that after 6,000 years, one-half of the carbon-14
atoms will have disappeared. After a second 6,000 years, half of that
remaining after the first 6,000 will have disappeared, or three-
quarters of the original number will be gone.
Up to about 1900 the concentration of carbon-14 in our at¬
mosphere and biosphere was such that the radioactivity of each
gramme of carbon was about 15 disintegrations per minute (dpm).
This way of expressing radioactivity, dpm per gramme, is called
"specific activity". Put another way, for our present case, 15 dpm
per gramme means that in among the 50 thousand million million
million atoms of carbon-12 in 1 gramme, there are about 650 thou¬
sand million atoms of carbon-14 of which 15 "disappear" by radioac¬
tive decay each minute.
Thus, 6,000 years after an organism dies, the carbon-14 specific
activity will be 7.5 dpm per gramme; in 12,000 years, it will be 3.75
dpm per gramme, and so on. By using large samples (if they are
available) and efficient instruments for measuring the radioactivity, it
has been possible to date objects made of wood, for example, that
are as much as 50,000 years old. Most carbon-14 dating, however, is
done on objects that are no more than 10,000 to 15,000 years old.
Most of the objects dated by this method are made of wood. It is
also possible to date objects of bone, textiles, ivory, and iron. (It is
possible to date iron because iron contains a few per cent of carbon
which, in old samples, came from wood charcoal.)
Another method for the dating of ceramics, radiation-induced j
thermoluminescence, was first used by George C. Kennedy in 1960. I
BERNARD KEISCH, U.S. radiochemist, has specialized in the applications
of nuclear technology to the identification of works of art. This article has
been adapted from material appearing in his study Secrets of the Past :
Nuclear Energy Applications in Art and Archaeology, published by the Office
of Information Services of the U. S. Atomic Energy Commission.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
y This method was eventually refined by workers at Oxford University
at the University of Pennsylvania and has become an extremely
valuable tool. One reason why it is so valuable is that bits of pottery
(called potsherds), which are quite durable, are almost always found
at "digs", or archaeological sites.
The method itself is based on the principle that radiation distorts
the electronic structure of insulating materials and so stores energy
within the material. This process may be likened to the stretching of
a spring. When the material is heated to a certain temperature the
forces holding the electrons "out of place" begin to "loosen", the
structure relaxes as a stretched spring would, and the stored energy
is released. This released energy is emitted in the form of light.
The radiation that produces this deformation comes mainly from
naturally radioactive materials like uranium, thorium, and potassium,
which are present in the pottery in low concentrations. The soil in
which the pottery was buried also contains naturally radioactive
material that affects the pottery in the same way. Cosmic radiation
also contributes to the radiation "damage".
As time passes, more and more energy is stored in the material
and thus the system acts like a clock. The clock is started at "zero",
which is the last time the material was heated to the temperature at
which the system "relaxes" (a process called annealing). In the case
of pottery, this is the time when the pottery was baked as the final
step in the manufacturing process.
To read the clock for a potsherd years after it was started, one
must know or measure at least three important things.
1. How much radiation "ran the clock" since it was started. This
information is obtained by measuring the radioactive constituents of
a sample of the potsherd and the soil in which it was buried,
estimating the small contribution of cosmic radiation, and
calculating an annual radiation dose.
2. The amount of energy stored in the sample must be measured.
To measure this, a small amount of very fine powder taken from the
sample is spread in a very thin layer and attached to a block of metal.
A light-measuring device (called a photomultiplier) is set up so that it
faces the samples. The metal block is then electrically heated so that
its temperature (and that of the sample) rises slowly and steadily.
The temperature and the light emitted are continuously measured
and recorded to give a thermoluminescence curve. Any material that
is heated begins to emit light, or glow, when it gets hot enough. The
trick here is to measure the extra light emitted by the pottery.
3. The susceptibility of the sample for radiation induced ther¬
moluminescence. This is determined by measuring the artificially in¬
duced thermoluminescence produced by irradiating the sample with
a known quantity of radiation after the original measurement is
complete.
Relating these three factors in an equation gives the age of the
piece.
It takes careful work and attention to detail to obtain an accurate
date by this method. For example, the sample must be powdered
carefully because grinding it too hard and fast may heat it enough to
emit light prematurely. Nevertheless, the techniques have been
worked out, and quite a number of dating problems have been solv¬
ed in this way.
Other ceramic items besides potsherds can and have been dated.
Terra-cotta statuary and ceramic figures have also 6een analysed,
and forgeries have sometimes turned up.
H Bernard Keisch
Cosmic rays
yield
neutrons
which react
with nitrogen
atoms
to make
carbon-14
which shows up
as carbon dioxide
throughout the
atmosphere, the
hydrosphere.
CARBON-14 DATING
but when
an organism dies no
fresh carbon-14 replaces
the carbon-14 decaying ir
its tissues and the
carbon-14 radioactivity
decreases by half every
5,700 years.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
COCK
*
^Á
-#*i i'
Í&' I ! 1
^"^ tI^f- ßEi^^^^^ Lu
BASE
\ IB Mf
Gamma-ray 'fingerprints'
This 18th-century brass cock was made by
the Benin people in the part of Africa that
is now Nigeria. It was constructed of two
parts, the bird itself and the base, and a
question was raised as to whether the two
parts were made by the same people. To
solve this problem recourse was had to a
technique known as neutron activation
analysis. This is an extremely sensitive
analytical technique by which it is possible
to detect and measure the trace elements
that occur in almost every substance. The
concentrations of trace elements in a
substance constitute a "fingerprint" by
which the source of a substance can be
identified. A sample is placed in a nuclear
reactor and.bombarded with neutrons.
Some of the elements in the sample
become radioactive and give off gamma
rays. The graphs superimposed on the
photograph of the cock are the gamma-ray
spectra obtained when samples taken from
the two parts were activated by neutrons in
a reactor. Notice how similar the shapes of
the two spectra are. Each peak represents
a gamma ray of a particular energy and can
be identified as coming from a particular
element in the brass. The height of each
gamma ray is related to the quantity of that
element present. In all, seven elements
were identified and found to be in almost
identical concentrations in the two parts of
this sculpture. This tends to prove that the
two parts, although made separately, were
made at the same time and place.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
A rogues' gallery
of fakes
Text © Copyright.
Reproduction Prohibited
THE history of forgery and imitation goes
back many centuries. The Roman
appreciation of Greek Classical sculpt¬
ure in stone and bronze prompted extensive
imitation that is now extremely difficult to
detect, while blatant forgery of early silver
coins from many cultures in the Empire was
recorded in verse by the Roman poet
Phaedrus during the reign of the Emperor
Augustus.
Coinage has always been a prime target
for debasement because of the immediate
financial rewards that result. We find early
examples of counterfeiting amongst the
subject peoples of the Roman Empire, par¬
ticularly in Britain. Around AD 198, during
the reign of Severus, the silver denarius was
already debased by the addition of about
42 per cent copper, but imitators took the
devaluation much further. We also know
from excavated clay moulds impressed from
original coinage that the folk of Whitchurch
in Somerset (U.K.), during the last quarter
of the third century AD, produced their own
silver antoniniani once official minting in the
area had ceased.
Attitudes to fakes and the reasons for
their existence have changed many times in
the past. Roman materialism seems to have
been very akin to that of our present genera-
by Stuart J. Fleming
tion while in the medieval era there was a
greater interest in an item's subject matter
than its age.
The year 1524 marks the earliest
documentation of forgery amongst Euro¬
pean paintings, in Pietro Summonte's
discussion of the activities of a Neapolitan
artist, Colantonio, some seventy years
earlier. A portrait of the Duke of Burgundy
was so well reproduced that the merchant-
owner from whom the original had been
borrowed accepted the return of Colan-
tonio's version without suspicion.
A little more than a century later there
began a saga that remained untold until
1871. A work commissioned from Hans Hol¬
bein the Younger, in 1525, The Madonna as
Protectress of Jacob Meyer, Mayor of
Basle, and his Family, passed through
several hands before reaching an Amster¬
dam dealer, Le Blond. Then the "Madonna"
developed a split personality.
STUART J. FLEMING, a British physicist who is
currently scientific director of the University
Museum, University of Pennsylvania, is an inter¬
nationally recognized authority on thermolumi¬
nescence dating of ceramics and bronzes. This
article has been extracted from his book Authenti¬
city in Art: The Scientific Detection of Forgery,
published by the Institute of Physics, London and
Bristol, in 1975.
One version (probably the original) even¬
tually entered the Ducal collection at Hesse.
A second version was pawned to a firm of
Venetian bankers and found an honoured
place in the Dresden Collection in 1743. Only
when the two panels were brought together
in the last century did the second version
proclaim its seventeenth-century style by
comparison with the original. The copyist
(possibly Bartholomeaus Sarburgh) felt he
had to introduce some "improvements", the
figures becoming smaller and the architec¬
tural surround more dominating. Current
taste demanded more space of movement
and a colour scheme of deeper, richer tones.
Some later case histories kept their
secrets for a much shorter time. Luca Gior¬
dano, at the end of the seventeenth century,
found himself in court for painting in the
style of Durer. The work, Christ healing the
Cripples, bore the renowned "AD"
monogram prominently enough while Gior¬
dano's own signature was concealed
elsewhere in the picture. Oddly enough he
was not found guilty, as it was judged that
he could not be blamed for being able to
paint as well as the German master. The
more recent court judgement of one year's
imprisonment on Han van Meegeren, in
1947, for his "Vermeer" imitations wask
scarcely more severe. f
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
jipir
Opposite page below, a pastiche (or forgery) of an ancient Etruscan wall-painting on a
terra-cotta slab. Each element in the work is the copy of a detail from an authentic piece
of Etruscan art, and the forgery, which seems to display a remarkable unity of conception,
is actually a kind of jigsaw puzzle of different motifs (below). The painting depicts Troilus,
son of King Priam, and his sister Polyxena, about to fall into an ambush laid by Hercules.
(The forger cunningly showed only part of the chequered fountain, letting it be supposed
that it was completed with another, missing, plaque, with Achilles lurking behind it.)
Photos above show the origins of the different motifs used in the pastiche: 1) Detail from
a clay altar from Corinth; 2) Fresco from the Etruscan "Tomb of Bulls" at Tarqulnia (Italy).
Detail shows Achilles waiting to ambush Troilus; 3) Banquet scene painted on a Greek
wine-jar; 4) Detail of fresco from "Tomb of Augurs" at Tarquinia; 5) Terra-cotta wall-plaque
of "female figures" unearthed at Banditaccia (Italy); 6) Decorative frieze on funeral urn
from Tarquinia (detail).
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
> Forgeries fall into three main categories.
The first of these, fakes without a model,
is rare. The path to acceptance can be
made easier if the subject chosen has some
connexion to a legend or a fragmentary
documentary reference. The fourteenth cen¬
tury provides us with one of the better-
known examples of a fake based on a
legend. Political manruvres against the
Knights Templars in 1306 included a claim
that they worshipped an idol called
Baphomet. The production of these idols
(small mis-shapen stone figures covered in
meaningless inscriptions) probably dates
from the time when this story was popular,
in the literature of the Gothic revival.
Fakes designed to fit in with genuine
documentary evidence include some
remarkable wholesale inventions of a com¬
plete, spurious artistic style, such as that of
the Obotrites (a Slavonic tribe from the
Mecklenberg region later over-run by the
Huns) and of the Moabites who came to
public attention in 1869 with the discovery
of a genuine inscription related to their King,
Mesha.
Archaeological material has been par¬
ticularly susceptible to this kind of forgery.
Gustav Wolf, in 1907, announced the
discovery of cremations among Danubian
peoples who first raised cattle and farmed in
the region of Wetterau in the fourth millen¬
nium BC. The unearthing of about a hun¬
dred of these graves led to the revision of
academic belief that skeleton burial was the
custom of those times. Finely-pierced flint
tools, notched bone implements and
carefully arrayed necklace beads all helped
to compound a funerary assemblage. Wolf,
in his autobiography, gave full credit for the
finds to his co-excavator, Bausch, and died
oblivious of the fact that he had been
deceived by that very man.
The Old Stone Age and Neolithic cultures
offer great potential to the forger because of
the simplicity of workmanship required and
the ready availability of media (flints, shales,
antler bone and cave-wall rock) all ready for
embellishment in hitherto unacknow¬
ledged ancient styles. Hieroglyphs cry out
for interpretation, our fascination increasing
in direct proportion to our ignorance. New
languages emerge; new cross-linkages are
established between cultures and the situa¬
tion becomes more and more confused.
Runic inscriptions have been particularly
prone to forgery. The Ura Linda Chronicle,
with .its notion that the Finns and Magyars
are blood relations and its assertion that the
Frisians are a Chosen People, was readily in¬
corporated into the early racialistic attitudes
of the Nazi Party in 1933. The Rune Stone of
Minnesota served, for a while, as evidence
of a Viking occupation of America by the
end of the tenth century, long before Col¬
umbus set foot there.
Similar unique documents have appeared
intermittently, including the last words of
Moses to the children of Israel written on
leather by an Egyptian scribe, Uanious, and
scripts of a "new" Phoenician historian call¬
ed Sachuniathon. The Frenchman, Vrain
Lucas, was a specialist in this type of pro¬
duction. In the course of a long career he
forged thousands of original manuscripts
purporting to stem from the hands of an il¬
lustrious gathering including Julius Caesar,
the Apostle Paul and Joan of Arc.
We find scarcely any examples of fakes
with no' such literary associations, possibly
because forgers realize that they will not fit
into any art historian's "data-bank" and are
therefore liable to immediate rejection.
Alterations and additions to a work supply
our second category of fakes. We might
mention, as an example, a painting with
figures in the style of the seventeenth-
century Dutch painter Philips Wouwerman
superimposed upon a genuine landscape by
his near contemporary Jan van Goyen. The
presence of both artists' monograms sug¬
gested the work was a joint effort but it now
seems probable that the parts of the paint¬
ing attributed to Wouwerman are the work
of one Robert Griffier.
Simple anthropomorphic sketches on
bone and small sculptural reliefs executed
on stone can endow Neanderthal man with
unexpected skills while similar schoolboy
rock-carvings have been known to rise to
the status of national treasures.
The third and most common form of
forgery is that of pastiche, that is to say, an
object that derives its detailed units from a
variety of similar elements in authentic
material. Our illustrations (pages 24 and 25)
show this process for an "Etruscan" paint¬
ing on a terra-cotta slab, the authentic form
of which would have decorated a niche of a
tomb. The scene is that of Troilus, son of
Priam, leading his horse to water, accom¬
panied by his sister, Polyxena. The fountain
is only shown in part so that we could an¬
ticipate the existence of a further plaque, to
be mounted to the left, displaying a
treacherous Achilles waiting to pounce
upon the unsuspecting prince.
This legend is depicted in a fresco from
the "Tomb of Bulls" at Tarquinia in Italy
which provides the main theme and, in
detail, is the source of the fountain chequer¬
ing. Polyxena enters the scene via a frieze of
this ambush that appears on the Corinthian
"Timonidas" flask, but she now has the
shawled dress-style of the females on a
plaque excavated at Banditaccia, near
Cerveteri.
The reined horse is derived from a
funerary urn from Tarquinia with many of
the outlines and muscle emphases
reproduced with almost mathematical preci¬
sion. The same accuracy of drawing is in
evidence in the lion mouth-piece of the
fountain and the upper border "tongue"
design that occur together on a Corinthian
clay altar. Fresco details are faithfully copied
with the birds taken from the wrestlers'
scene in the "Tomb of the Augurs" and the
small decanting jug taken from the "Tomb
of the Lionesses". Greek vases supply the
water pitcher (from the "Onesimos" bowl in
Brussels) and the crouching dog (from the
"Eurytios" krater in the Louvre). Every com¬
ponent is readily available in photographs of
books of the past two decades, often
helpfully in colour.
An alternative source of information for
the would-be forger is the showcases of
museums. This is most convenient for single
leaves of illuminated manuscripts; three-
dimensional objects, parts of which are not
visible through the front glass partitions, are
often poorly executed. In the past engrav¬
ings and woodcuts proved a valuable in¬
spiration both for transfer into easel paint¬
ings and extension into an extra dimension
as marble or terra-cotta statuary and stone
reliefs. Similarly, medals supply small-scale
versions of portraiture that translate well in¬
to stone reliefs of grander proportions while
offering less risk of anachronism in costume
and hair styling.
Slavish plagiarism is rare. It only appears
at all commonly in the field of drawings,
where it was common practice of the
leading studios of the past to give each ap¬
prentice old prints to copy as part of his
education. The eighteenth-century English
painter Sir Joshua Reynolds produced
"Guercino" sketches with consummate
ease. Michelangelo deliberately set out to
deceive his master, Ghirlandaio, by copying
a head, smoking the surface of the paper to
simulate the effects of ageing, and exchang¬
ing his product for the original. Raphael,
whose popularity was at its zenith in the
nineteenth century, has been copied
repeatedly even to the extent of enlarging
small folio details into full-scale cartoon
elements.
Surfaces often need major treatments to
give them the necessary antique ap¬
pearance. Cracking of a paint surface is an
ageing effect that follows from the pigment
or priming layers being too rigid to cope with
the stretching of the flexible canvas or panel
support. Once the oil medium has dried a
simple rolling-up of a canvas will simulate
this cracking quite well.
Other "recipes" include application of a
heavily-contracting varnish or stiff glue to
break up the picture's surface. Alternatively,
some kind of heat treatment followed by
rapid cooling causes shrinkage of the sup¬
port at too great a rate to be taken up by the
paint layers. For paintings on wooden
panels the paint break-up usually runs
parallel to the fibre structure of the wood
and so the pressure directions require some
deliberation. A final brush with soot
highlights the damage.
A "fly-blown" appearance can be produc¬
ed by stippling some areas with a stiff-bristle
brush in a matching colour to create an illu¬
sion of antiquity. Swiftly applied restoration,
damp-staining and blotching of paper, rim-
chipping of pottery and the use of worm-
eaten wood are all stock-in-trade skills of the
ambitious faker.
Similar ageing effects giving an ap¬
pearance called craquelure, occur in the
glazes of ceramics. The glaze ingredients
fuse during kiln-firing and a glassy coating
seals the pores in the underlying clay. If,
during cooling, the clay cools less than the
glaze the latter is put under stress and
coarse fissures appear on the surface. This
crackling is due to kiln treatment and in no
way indicates antiquity. The passage of time
leads to the development of many more,
much finer crazing lines. This must be quite
a difficult effect to simulate, judging by the
rarity of good craquelure on established
fakes, but examples do exist.
In the case of metals, corrosion of the sur¬
face, termed patination, records the effects
of long-term exposure to the atmosphere or
burial moisture. The copper content of
bronzes oxidizes to form amorphous cuprite
which, in turn, reacts with carbonated water
to form the familiar green encrustations of
malachite. Other impurities in the metal, like
tin, may preferentially oxidize to give a
silvery sheen.
Sulphur and chlorine, present in the at¬
tacking moisture, each give rise to different
characteristic tarnishing effects. Unfor¬
tunately, the softening tone that patination
produces on the raw, shining metal seems
CONTINUED PAGE 34
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The principles
of conservation
by Bernard M. Feiiden
THE conservation of cultural property
demands wise management of re¬
sources and a good sense of propor¬
tion. Perhaps above all, it demands the
desire and dedication to see that cultural
property is preserved. In this sense, two
familiar maxims are pertinent: "Prevention is
better than cure" and "A stitch in time saves
nine".
Modern long-term conservation policy
concentrates on fighting the causes of
decay. Natural disasters such as floods and
earthquakes cannot be prevented, but by
forethought the damage can be greatly
reduced. Industrial development cannot and
should not be halted, but damage can be
minimized by combatting waste, uncontroll¬
ed expansion, economic exploitation and
pollution.
Despite the difference in scale and extent,
the underlying principles and methods of
conservation are the same both for movable
and immovable cultural property.
, There are, however, important logistical
differences. First, architectural work entails
treatment of materials in an open and vir¬
tually uncontrollable environment. Whereas
the museum conservator-restorer can
generally rely on good environmental con¬
trol to minimize further deterioration, the ar¬
chitectural conservator cannot. He must
allow for the effects of time and weather.
Secondly, the scale of architectural opera¬
tions is much larger, and in many cases
methods used by museum conservator-
restorers may be found impracticable due to
the size and complexity of the architectural
fabric.
Thirdly, and again due to the size and
complexity of architectural conservation,
the various measures of conservation must
be carried out by contractors, technicians
and craftsmen, while the museum
conservator-restorer may do most of the
treatment with his own hands. Communica¬
tion and supervision, therefore, are impor¬
tant considerations for the architectural
conservator.
Lastly, architectural conservation must
take place within the context of a historic
structure, and take account of its site, set¬
ting and physical environment.
For both movable and immovable cultural
property, the objects chosen for treatment
and the extent and nature of the treatment
are based on values and priorities which in¬
evitably reflect each different cultural con¬
text. For example, a small wooden domestic
structure from the beginning of the 19th
century in Australia would be considered a
national landmark because it dates from the
founding of the nation and because so little
Australian architecture has survived from
this period. In Italy, on the other hand, with
its thousands of ancient monuments, a
comparable structure would have a relatively
low priority in the overall conservation needs
of the community.
Whatever form of conservation treatment
is adopted, the following standards of ethics
must be rigorously followed. First, the con¬
dition of the object, and all methods and
materials used during treatment, must be
clearly documented. Second, historic
evidence should be fully recorded, and must
not be destroyed, falsified or removed.
Third, any intervention must be the
minimum necessary. Fourth, any interven¬
tion must be governed by unswerving
respect for the aesthetic, historical and
physical integrity of cultural property.
Interventions should be reversible, if
technically possible, or at least not prejudice
a future intervention whenever this may
become necessary. They should not hinder
the possibility of later access to all evidence
incorporated in the object, and should allow
the maximum amount of existing material to
be retained. If additions are necessary, they
should be less noticeable than original
material, while at the same time being iden¬
tifiable. Conservator-restorers who are in¬
sufficiently trained or experienced should
not undertake such interventions without
competent advice. However, it must be
recognized that some problems are unique
and have to be solved from first principles
on a trial-and-error basis.
Seven "degrees" of intervention can be
identified, but in any individual conservation
treatment, several degrees may take place
simultaneously in various parts of the
"whole". The seven degrees are:
prevention of deterioration
preservation
consolidation
restoration
rehabilitation
reproduction
reconstruction
Prevention of deterioration (or indirect
conservation). Prevention entails protecting
cultural property by controlling its environ-
BERNARD M. FEILDEN, British architect, is
director of the Rome-based International Centre
for the Preservation and Restoration of Cultural
Property (ICCROM) which was founded by
Unesco. He was previously surveyor to St. Paul's
Cathedral, London, and responsible for consoli¬
dating the foundations of York Minster and
saving the spire of Norwich Cathedral in England.
He is the author of Conservation of Historic Buil¬
dings, fo be published later this year, andan Out¬
line of Conservation, being published by
Unesco.
ment, thus preventing agents of decay and
damage from becoming active.
Prevention thus includes control of
humidity, temperature and light, as well as
measures to prevent fire, arson, theft and
vandalism. In the industrial and urban en¬
vironment it includes measures to reduce at¬
mospheric pollution, traffic vibrations and
ground subsidence due to many causes,
particularly abstraction of water.
Preservation deals directly with cultural
property. The object is to keep such proper¬
ty in its existing state. Damage and destruc¬
tion caused by humidity, chemical agents,
and all types of pests and micro-organisms
must be stopped in order to preserve the ob¬
ject or structure.
Maintenance, cleaning schedules and
good management aid preservation. Repairs
must be carried out when necessary to pre¬
vent further decay. Regular inspections of
cultural property are the basis of prevention.
When the property is subjected to an uncon¬
trollable environment, such inspections are
the first step in preventive maintenance and
repair.
Consolidation (or direct conservation).
Consolidation is the physical addition or ap¬
plication of adhesive or supportive materials
into the actual fabric of cultural property, in
order to ensure its continued durability or
structural integrity. In the case of immovable
cultural property, consolidation may entail,
for example, the injection of adhesives to
secure a detached mural painting to the
wall. Movable cultural property, such as
weakened canvas paintings and works on
paper, are often backed with new suppor¬
tive materials.
In many cases it is wise to buy time with
temporary measures in the hope that some
better technique will evolve, especially if
consolidation may prejudice future conser¬
vation work.
Restoration. The object of restoration is
to revive the original concept or legibility of
the object. Restoration and reintegration of
details and features are based on respect for
original material, archaeological evidence,
original design and authentic documents.
The replacement of missing or decayed
parts must integrate harmoniously with the
"whole", but must be distinguishable on
close inspection from the original so that the
restoration does not falsify artistic or historic
evidence.
Contributions from all periods must be
respected. All later additions that can be
considered as a "historical document"
rather than merely a previous restoration,
must be preserved. When a building in¬
cludes superimposed work of different I
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
.periods, only exceptional circumstances can
'justify revealing the underlying state: when
the part removed is widely agreed to be of
little interest and when it is certain that the
material brought to light will be of great
historical or archaeological value, and when
it is clear that its state of preservation is
good enough to justify the action. Restora¬
tion also entails superficial cleaning, but
with full respect for the patina of age.
Rehabilitation. The best way of preserving
buildings is to keep them in use, a practice
which may involve what the French call
"mise en valeur", or modernization and
adaptive alteration.
Adaptive re-use of buildings, such as
utilizing a medieval convent in Venice to
house a school and laboratory for stone con¬
servation, or turning an eighteenth-century
barn into a domestic dwelling, is often the
only way that historic and aesthetic values
can be made economically viable.
Reproduction entails copying an existing
artefact, often in order to replace some
missing or decayed, generally decorative,
parts to maintain its aesthetic harmony. If
valuable cultural property is being damaged
irretrievably or is threatened by its environ
ment, it may have to be moved to a more
suitable environment. A reproduction is thus
often substituted to maintain the unity of a
site or building. For example, Michel¬
angelo's famous sculpture of David was
removed from the Piazza della Signoria in
Florence to a museum to protect it from the
weather. A good reproduction took its
place.
Reconstruction of historic buildings and
historic town centres using new materials
may be necessitated by disasters such as
fire, earthquake or war, but reconstructions
cannot have the patina of age. As in restora¬
tion, reconstruction must be based on ac¬
curate documentation and evidence, never
on conjecture.
Moving entire buildings to new sites is
another form of reconstruction which is
justified only by overriding national interest.
However, it entails some loss of essential
cultural values and the generation of new
environmental risks. The classic example is
the temple complex of Abu Simbel, which
was moved to prevent its inundation by the
Aswan High Dam (see Unesco Courier,
February-March 1980).
B Bernard M. Feilden
Photo © Kodak-Pathé-National Geographic Institute, Pans. From the exhibition Le Fil des Pierres, Photogrammetry and Conservation of Documents
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Borély Museum, Marseilles, France
Miniature and monumental
asäBSasoä
IlSMMMIMitti
Left, façade of the temple of
Borobudur, on the island of Java,
Indonesia. The temple dates from the
9th century and is the world's biggest
and most complete ensemble of
Buddhist bas-reliefs. The image was
produced by photogrammetry, the
process of using photographs for
measurements in surveying. A decade
ago, at the request of the Indonesian
Government, Unesco launched an
international campaign to save
Borobudur, whose foundations had
been undermined by 12 centuries of
exposure to torrential monsoon rains
and whose galleries had subsided as a
result of the seismic disturbances
which are common in this region. It
was decided to dismantle the temple
stone by stone, and rebuild it on a
specially designed concrete structure
which would withstand earthquakes
and allow rainwater to drain away.
Before work could begin, a survey was
carried out by France's National
Geographic Institute. Because of the
size, complexity and pyramidal shape of
Borobudur, many parts of the temple
were not visible in photos taken from
ground level. Consequently, 180
additional pairs of stereoscopic photos
were taken, as well as 35 shots from a
helicopter. In this way an exact survey
of the monument's volume was made,
along with an estimate of the
restoration work that would be
necessary to save it. Above, six Bronze-
Age fish-hooks (between three and five
centimetres long) unearthed in the
South of France and preserved in the
Borély Museum, Marseilles. Even the
humblest everyday object can provide
precious evidence of past ways of life.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
A museum
in a suitcase
Three-dimensional 'replicas' of works of art,
produced by the astonishing technique of holography
by Ivan G. Yavtushenko
and Vladimir B. Markov
THE technique of producing holographic images was first ad¬
vanced in 1949 by a Hungarian-born British physicist, Dennis
Gabor. However, his method proved unusable for lack of a
suitable light source. Not until the development of the laser as a
source of coherent light was further progress possible.
The breakthrough came in 1962, thanks to the work of American
scientists Emmett Leith and Juris Upatnieks, and a Soviet scientist,
Y.N. Denisyuk. Leith and Upatnieks took the laser as their source of
light and, working with a modified version of Gabors method, proved
it possible to record and reconstruct a three-dimensional image of any
light-reflecting object. Meanwhile, Denisyuk's fundamental work
established the principle of the complete reconstruction of the light
field created by a real object.
What is holography and how does it differ from conventional
methods of recording ¡mages? Non-holographic techniques use a lens
to produce an image of the subject on light-sensitive material, and of
course, the original three dimensions are then converted into two.
Holography consists of recording the light field emitted by the sub¬
ject same field as is normally perceived by the human eye.
The theory of the technique of holography may be described as
follows. As in photography, one needs a light source, a photographic
plate and, of course, an object. The layer of photosensitive emulsion
is comparatively thickabout 10 microns. The object is illuminated by
the light of a laser; the reflected light falls on the plate. However, in
contrast to ordinary photography, the plate is also illuminated by
reference light rays from the same source. These two beams of light
combine, and are registered by the photographic plate, which is called
the hologram.
The image is reconstructed by placing the hologram as before and
directing onto it a similar source of light. The effect of this upon the
structure recorded on the hologram is to produce light beams which
are an exact replica of those reflected by the original subject, so that
the viewer sees a three-dimensional copy of that subject.
(Denisyuk's holograms can even be viewed with a pocket flashlight.)
This description of the recording and reconstruction of the image is
the key to the origin of the word holography, which Gabor coined
from two Greek words: holos, meaning "complete", and graphein
meaning "to write". In other words, it is a method of recording all the
information about the light field emitted by a real object.
It is the hologram's ability to produce an exact optical copy of the
subject which suggested that it might be widely used in museology.
There are many ancient objects which, for a variety of reasons, can¬
not be displayed: perishable items that need special storage, or those
unique antiquities for which unusual security arrangements are re¬
quired. This problem can largely be overcome by exhibiting
holographic replicas of such objects. Again, it is no secret that par¬
ticularly valuable items found in provincial areas usually find their way
to large central museums. Holograms could well be made of them and
placed in provincial museums, providing exact replicas which could
advantageously replace laborious castings. Equally important is the
potential use of holograms in establishing the origin and identity of ob¬
jects and determining their age and state of preservation. Optical
replicas may now be used in this research, rather than perishable or
particularly valuable originals.
30
Holography holds out exciting prospects for museums in the
organization of exhibitions. There are many exhibits which must be
viewed from several angles, or at least from two opposite sides. This
is especially true of coins or medals, since the designs on the
obverse and the reverse sides are different. Such items as chalices
and goblets also fall within this category. Holograms containing
every detail of the structure of such items can be produced by taking
circular reflective holograms. But this is an extremely difficult pro¬
cedure: a simpler method is to take two-sided reflective holograms.
The latter technique employs a single plate to record separate
holograms of the obverse and the reverse of the subject, which must
be done in such a way that when reconstructed the ¡mages exactly
coincide.
The first phase in this process is to take a hologram of the
"obverse" side. The exposed plate is then turned round, and a se¬
cond exposure is taken of the "reverse" side of the same subject. In
order to avoid an overlap between the ¡mages, it is essential that the
exposure be taken with the light striking both the subject and the
plate at obtuse angles. When processed, this hologram is set up and
illuminated from both sides, so reconstructing an ¡mage of both the
"obverse" and the "reverse" of the object.
A further use of holograms in museology arises from their ability
to reconstruct pseudoscopic ¡mages. This method holds particular
advantages in those frequent cases where the mould of a seal or a
die is too ill-preserved to be used for casting, since an image can be
produced of the article which the mould was used to make. The
technique is as follows. The exposed and processed hologram is
rotated through 180 degrees in relation to the light source, and a
beam is directed onto it. The image thus produced is a pseudoscopic
copy of the mould in other words, an image of the real article.
Enlarged or scaled-down three-dimensional ¡mages of real objects
can also be produced, these methods being particularly appropriate
where small objects are to be displayed, or for showing the minor
details of a large exhibit. Lastly, the applications of holography are
not restricted to historical objects, but may include holographic por¬
traits of contemporary figures, or holographic views of interiors.
One highly successful use of holograms is in travelling or perma¬
nent exhibitions, which can quite easily be set up in any locality. This
is confirmed by the fact that such exhibitions have been organized in
Moscow, Kiev, Yalta, Simferopol, Sebastopol and other Soviet,
towns and cities. The international exchange of these exhibitions is K
arousing strong interest. One sign of this is the popularity of an ex- f
IVAN GRIGORYEVICH YAVTUSHENKO is the head of museum science
and methodology at the Ministry of Culture of the Ukrainian SSR. His explo¬
ration of the possibilities of holography in museum work forms part of his
activities in the field of museum research, the design and technical equip¬
ment of museums, preservation techniques, and the display of exhibits.
VLADIMIR BORISOVICH MARKOV is the head of the laboratory of
applied holography at the Physics Institute of the Ukrainian Academy of
Sciences. He has written widely in Soviet and international publications on
questions related to optics, laser technology and holography.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Artist's impression of the arrangement
of components in a holographic set-up
(above) for the production of a
hologram of a vase, and (below left) for
the reconstitution of a three-
dimensional image of the vase from the
hologram. Below, simplified diagram of
a hologram production lay-out.
Mirror
Object
Beam
spreader
Laser
Beam
spreader
Reference
beam
Beam
splitter
Object
illumination
beam
Prism
E
2
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
> hibition of holograms of historical objects from Ukrainian museums,
which has been shown in Belgrade, Yugoslavia, during the twenty-
first session of Unesco's General Conference; at the "OPIEM" inter¬
national conference on holograms in Strasbourg, France; at the
lntercamera-79 exhibition in Prague, Czechoslovakia; and at exhibi¬
tions in Finland, the German Democratic Republic and elsewhere.
Holography provides enormous potential for the establishment of
special thematic exhibitions combining items from several
museums. It is notoriously difficult to bring together, for example,
the objets d'art of antiquity, or collections of Scythian gold, which
are housed in museums scattered throughout the world. Yet a
specialized exhibition of holograms could be arranged on any such
topic, and would prove extremely popular not only among specialist .
historians or art experts, but also with the general public, since it
would bring together articles from a given historical period.
Another possibility would be to arrange for the centralized pro¬
duction and sale of original souvenirs in the shape of holographic
replicas of rare ancient objects. These would find a ready market,
and would be excellent publicity for museums both at home and
among foreign tourists.
In view of the enormous number of exhibits, this list of possible
museological applications is sufficient evidence that research in¬
stitutes alone could not cope with the volume of work involved. This
is why the Ukraine, for example, has taken steps to associate both
physicists and museologists in attempts to provide global answers to
a number of problems. As a first step, holographical laboratories
have been set up at the museums themselves. The Applied
Holography Laboratory of the Institute of Physics of the Ukrainian
Academy of Sciences provides them with scientific and technical
advice, trains their experts, and also develops new holography
techniques. It is intended that these museum laboratories should
produce holograms of all the rarer objects in their collections, and
firstly of their perishable articles or those which require special
storage or security.
The particular way in which the image is produced in holography
gives rise to extensive applications in the field of science and
technology. One such application is holographic microscopy. The
chief fault of existing microscopes is that a sharp ¡mage can only be
obtained of the part of the subject on which the instrument is focus¬
ed, while the rest of the image is out of focus and so lacks definition.
The study of objects which are unstable in time is even more dif¬
ficult, since the microscope must continually be adjusted. The
holographic microscope enables three-dimensional images to be
frozen at any point in time for subsequent study in detail. Such in¬
struments are particularly efficient in the study of small suspended
particles (aerosols) or of transparent objects. For instance, a
holographic microscope has been used to produce a three-
dimensional image of a neuron with a diameter of less than 0.001
millimetres.
Among the most rapidly developing applications is holographic in-
terferometry, a technique which draws upon a single hologram's
ability to record several successive ¡mages. The first exposure
records the ¡mage of the object at rest: the object is then subjected
to an external stimulus, and a second exposure is taken. If a sup¬
plementary beam is directed onto the hologram, both images are
reconstructed simultaneously, and the light beams thus formed are
mono-directional. Since these beams are coherent, interference oc¬
curs, and the resulting image is covered with light and dark patterns.
This interferential structure, which varies according to the nature of
the external stimulus, may be used for such purposes as determining
the topology of the subject, identifying deep-seated defects, or
comparing two subjects.
I Ivan G. Yavtushenko and Vladimir B. Markov
Right, holographic exhibition in the
Ukrainian Museum of History, Kiev.
Itinerant holographic exhibitions
open up immense possibilities for
bringing the treasures of the
world's great museums to the
attention of a worldwide audience,
at very low cost and with no risk to
the treasures themselves. It has
been estimated, for example, that
the entire contents of a major
exhibition in Moscow, "The
treasures of the State Museum of
History", could be recorded full size
on 110 holographic plates
measuring 60 by 80 centimetres
each, all of which could be packed
into a crate of just one and a half
cubic metres.
Below, Shermazan Kakichashvili, head of the optical
research laboratory of the Cybernetics Institute of the
Academy of Sciences of the Georgian SSR (at left of
photo) looks at a circular hologram of himself.
Illuminated by a laser beam, the hologram is mounted on
a turntable which, when turned, shows his head in
profile, from behind and full face.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
I National Commasion lor Unesco
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
ROGUES' GALLERY OF FAKES
(continued from page 26)
to have been to the taste of other civiliza¬
tions besides our own. Vasari, in his discuss¬
ion of technique in the Renaissance era,
comments on the desirability of artificial
ageing treatments such as oil-blackening,
"pickling" in vinegar and even varnishing.
Silver often carries a slight purplish tinge
owing to chloride corrosion. However, this
is a slow reaction compared with oxidation
or chlorination of any copper present so that
alloyed systems like those encountered in
debased coinage usually suffer these reac¬
tions first. Chemical induction of artificial
surface degradation poses no particular
difficulty.
Despite the simplicity of the notion few
deliberate artificial treatments offer the faker
a better reward than burial of his work for a
year or so to allow nature to begin the "age¬
ing" process. Although this requires pa¬
tience and a steady nerve (someone else
may accidentally dig up the forgery before
the market is ripe) the method remains an ef¬
fective one. Even the slightest traces of sur¬
face concretions or roots marks together
with a degree of "natural" damage and the
inevitable softening in decorative brightness
can only be helpful in generating a good ar¬
chaeological provenance for a fake that has
been subjected to a period of burial.
This does not always work, particularly if
the forger is careless in preparing a burial
spot. In 1905 the Abbé d'Aguel, anxious to
demonstrate that trade between Egypt and
Gaul dated back to Neolithic times, an¬
nounced the discovery of a number of finely-
worked flint implements and weapons.
These, according to the Abbé, had been
dug up from the sealed sedimentary
limestone layers on the Ile de Riou, off the
Marseilles coast. Experts soon became con¬
cerned that the surfaces of the objects had a
bright, almost lacquered appearance the
kind of surface patination found on objects
which have been exposed for long periods
to a dry desert atmosphere, not on articles
buried in limestone for thousands of years.
The material was certainly authentic and
Egyptian but its voyage from Egypt to
France had been rather more recent than the
Abbé claimed.
.Stuart J. Fleming
Bird's eye view of the past
Aerial photo (left) taken on a winter's day
above Warfusee in northern France shows
the plan of a large Roman Villa. It
illustrates how airborne archaeology can
locate historical sites which may be
concealed from the eye of the earthbound
archaeologist by centuries of farming
activity. Such faded Imprints of the human
past can be detected by aerial archaeology
at certain fleeting moments of the day and
at certain seasons, as after winter
ploughing. One advantage of this method is
that it does not disturb the archaeological
site, whereas a badly executed piece of
excavation may cause irremediable
damage. Surveys being carried out by aerial
archaeologists and covering entire regions
are today making a major contribution to
the recording and protection of the
archaeological heritage.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Just published...
statistical yearbook
annuaire statistique
anuario estadístico
Stxn« i«d weh nolo»
Librum
Book produclíon
Ntwipipcri und other
pCTHxJlCfth
Biblmihíatim
Edición de libres
puMicacinnct periodic«
Pipel cul'unl
Pilkulu y ci«
Rtdiodi fanon sonora
O
oo
0\
The latest (1980) edition of Unesco's indispens¬
able reference book of statistics from some 200
countries on :
D Population
D Education
D Science and technology
D Libraries
D Book production
D Newspapers and periodicals
D Paper consumption
D Film and cinema
D Radio broadcasting
D Television
Prepared by Unesco's Office of Statistics with the
co-operation of National Commissions for Unesco
and national statistical services, and with the help
of the Statistical Office and the Population Divi¬
sion of the United Nations.
Trilingual English/French/Spanish 280 French francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscrip¬
tion rates in local currency, will be supplied
on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications- Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P.O
Box 33, Brookvale, 2100, NSW Periodicals Dominie Pty. Subs-
cnptions Dept., P.O Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent,
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne (Victoria), 3000
AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co, Graben 31, A'
1011, Vienna BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd , Ittefaq Building, 1, R K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3
- BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only N.V. Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent- Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13 - BURMA. Trade Corporation No 9,550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co Ltd , 2182 St Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7 CHINA. China National Publications Import Corpora¬
tion, West Europe Department, P.O. Box 88, Peking
CYPRUS "MAM", Archbishop Makanos 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box
1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S N T L , Spalena
51, Prague 1 (Permanent display!, Zahranicm literatura, 11 Sou-
kenicka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only. Alfa Verlag Publishers,
Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava - CSSR. - DENMARK.
Munksgaard Export and Subscription Service, 35 Norre Sogade,
DK 1370, Copenhagen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OFI
National Centre for Unesco Publications, No 1 Talaat Harb
Street, Cairo ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P O
Box 2996, Addis Ababa. FINLAND Akateemmen Kina
kauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100 Helsinki 10 - FRANCE
Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Pans, CCP
12598-48. - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leip¬
zig, Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhand¬
lungen in the G D R. - FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the
Unesco Courier (German, English, French and Spanish editions)
Mr H Baum, Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse
57, D5300 Bonn 3. For other Unesco publications
Karger Verlag, Germenng/Munchen. For scientific maps only
Geo Center, Postfach 800830, Stuttgart 80 - GHANA. Pres¬
byterian Bookshop Depot Ltd , P 0 Box 195, Accra; Ghana
Book Suppliers Ltd , P O. Box 7869, Accra, The University
Bookshop of Ghana, Accra, The University Bookshop of Cape
Coast, The University Bookshop of Legon, P 0 Box 1, Legon
- GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. - HONG
KONG. Federal Publications IHK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial
Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-
15, Lock Road, Kowloon. - HUNGARY. Akadémiai Kbnyves-
bolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V. Konyvturosok Boltja, Nép-
koztársaság utja 16, Budapest VI. ICELAND. Snaebjorn
Jonsson & Co., H F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA.
Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay
400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai,
Mount Road, Madras 2, B-3/7 Asaf All Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1
Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.
17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House, New Delhi; Publi¬
cations Section, Ministry of Education and Social Welfare, 51 1
C-Wmg, Shastri Bhavan, New Delhi 110001. - INDONESIA.
Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29JI.Otolskandardinatalll,
Jakarta; Gramedia Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta,
Indira P.T., Jl. Dr Sam Ratulangie 47, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN.
Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co., 28, Vessal Shirazi
Street, Enghélab Avenue, P.O. Box 314/1486, Teheran; Iranian
Nat. Comm. for Unesco, Ave. Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B.P.
1533, Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, Al -Rashid
Street, Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of
Ireland Ltd., Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12
ISRAEL. ABC. Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby
Road, Tel Aviv 61000 - JAMAICA. SangsteKs Book Stores
Ltd., P O Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston - JAPAN. Eas¬
tern Book Service Inc., Shuhwa Toranomon 3bldg, 23-6, Tora¬
nomon 3-Chome, Mmato-ku, Tokyo 105, KENYA. East Afri¬
can Publishing House, P O. Box 30571, Nairobi KOREA.
Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64,
Seoul. - KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co , Ltd, POB 2942,
Kuwait LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod,
Lesotho, Southern Africa LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Book¬
shops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency for
Development of Publication & Distribution, P.O Box 34-35, Tri¬
poli. LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue,
Luxembourg MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co¬
operative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur 22-11. MALTA. Sapien-
zas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta - MAURITIUS. Nalanda
Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis. - MONACO.
British Library, 30 bd des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. - NETHER¬
LANDS. For the "Unesco Koener" Dutch edition only. Syste¬
men Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75, Amsterdam-1007. Agent for
all Unesco publications- N V. Martmus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout,
9, The Hague. - NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-
Eddine N V , P.O. Box 200, Willemstad, Curaçao NA- NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, Government Books¬
hops at. Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland, 130, Oxford
Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch; Alma Street, P.O. Box 857
Hamilton; Princes Street, PO Box 1104, Dunedin;
Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington. NIGERIA. The
University Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan,
P 0 286; The University Bookshop of Nsukka, The University
Bookshop of Lagos, The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of
Zana NORWAY. All publications Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco
Courier only A S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam,
P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3 - PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co , 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404.
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw, Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda, Livrana
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES New
Service Ltd , Kingsgate House, P 0 Box 131, Mahé
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications IS) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19. - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P O. Box 951,
Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA. All publications- Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty ) Ltd , Libn Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg
-SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam
Gardiner Mawata P 0 B. 244 Colombo 2. - SUDAN. Al Bashir
Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. - SWEDEN. All
publications A/8 C E Fritzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel,
Regenngsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16. For the
Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Forbundet, Skolgrand 2, Box 150
50 S- 104 65, Stockholm - SWITZERLAND. All publications
Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse. Zurich Librairie Payot, rue
Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11, CC P. 12-236. - TANZANIA. Dar¬
es Salaam Bookshop, POB 9030 Dar-es-Salaam
THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road,
Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok: Suksapan Panit,
Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam
Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W I - TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi
A. S , Istiklâl Caddesi, No. 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu,
Istanbul UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145,
Kampala - UNITED KINGDOM. H M Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Govt Bookshops in London,
Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmin¬
gham, Bristol -UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue
South, New York, N Y 10010. - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya
Kniga, Moscow, G-200 - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska
Knjiga, Trg Republike 5/8, Belgrade, Drzavna Zalozba
Slovenje, Titova C 25, P O.B. 50-1, Ljubliana - ZIMBABWE.
Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd , 67 Union Avenue, Salisbury
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
ART MUSEUMS WITH NO EXHIBITS
>
©
Museums full of people admiring works of art
that are not there may one day be common¬
place, thanks to holography, a revolutionary
method of creating three-dimensional represen¬
tations of objects of such perfection that the
viewer has the impression that he is looking at
the objects themselves (see article page 30).
Photo shows a third-century-BC mask of
Silenus, the companion of the god Dionysus,
discovered in the Ukraine in 1935, as presented
at the permanent holographic exhibition at the
Ukrainian Museum of History, Kiev.
]]>
</page>
</document>
