<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074755eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
FEBRUARY/MARCH I960 7.00 FRENCH FRANCS
i*jfjfffl*^"'
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
^
m m
t*
Photo © National Museum, Warsaw
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
The Sudan
Fiery steed from Faras
The spirited movements of a rearing horse are perfectly captured in this detail of a twelfth-
century mural from the Cathedral of Faras in Sudanese Nubia, near the Egyptian border. The
Cathedral, an important religious centre in Christian Nubia, was excavated by the Polish
Archaeological Mission to Nubia, and was one of the first archaeological sites in Sudanese
Nubia to be submerged by the waters of the artificial lake created by the Aswan High Dam.
The two prong-like lines beneath the right foreleg suggest that this is a picture of an ornament
which could be pinned or fastened to a garment. Egypt and the Sudan donated to each State
which took part in the Nubian campaign a share of the treasures discovered by its archaeologi¬
cal mission. The above mural is now displayed in Poland's National Museum, Warsaw.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco COUPICF
A window open on the world
FEBRUARY-MARCH 1980 33rd YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 20 LANGUAGES
English Italian Turkish
French Hindi Urdu
Spanish Tamil Catalan
Russian Hebrew Malaysian
German Persian Korean
Arabic Dutch Swahili
Japanese Portuguese
Published by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 35 French Francs
2 years: 58 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 29 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, (11 issues a
year including one double issue). For list of distributors see
inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A.: (2) N.C.R. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head. Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New York, U.S.A.; (3) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mans¬
field Road, Wooster. Ohio 44691. U.S.A.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in the Readers'
Guide to Periodical Literature, published by H.W. Wilson
Co., New York, and in Current Contents - Education,
Philadelphia, U.S.A.
Editor-in-chief: Jean Gaudin
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
Edition: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
Edition:
Edition: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Edition: Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Edition: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Maria Remiddi (Rome)
H.L. Sharma (Delhi)
M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Edition: Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
Edition: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese Edition: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish Edition: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu Edition: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan Edition: Cristian Rahola (Barcelona)
Malaysian Edition: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean Edition: Lim Moun-young (Seoul)
Swahili Edition: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salaam)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition: Djamel Benstaali
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Philippe Gentil
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
page
4 'A SINGLE, UNIVERSAL HERITAGE'
by Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
VICTORY IN NUBIA
Unesco and the world community
in the greatest archaeological rescue campaign of all time
5 I. EGYPT
by Shehata Adam Mohamed
16 II. THE SUDAN
by Negm-el-Din Mohammed Sherif .
8 MILESTONES IN THE CAMPAIGN
14 TEMPLES RESCUED FROM THE NILE
Map
20 NUBIA UNEARTHED
From prehistory to Pharaonic times
by Torgny Säve-Söderbergh
25 NUBIA'S CORRIDOR OF TIME
From the Kingdom of Kush to the triumph of Islam
by William Y. Adams
30 SITES EXCAVATED
Map
32 A CHRONOLOGY OF ANCIENT NUBIA
32 HIGHLIGHTS OF THE ARCHAEOLOGICAL EXPEDITIONS
35 FOUR PAGES IN FULL COLOUR
46 THE HOLY ISLE OF PHILAE
by lorwerth E.S. Edwards
48 THE MYSTERIES OF ISIS AND OSIRIS
by François Daumas
53 THE MAGIC OF ABU SIMBEL
by Christiane Desroches-Noblecourt
58 SERMONS IN STONES
The musings of a modern Egyptian poet before the temples of Abu Simbel
by Tewfik El Hakim
62 THE FLOODED FORTRESSES OF NUBIA
by Jean Vercoutter
66 THE BLESSED LAND
by Robert A. Fernea
70 FURTHER READING ON NUBIA
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
THE SUDAN: Fiery steed from Faras
This special issue was prepared with the invaluable collaboration ofAbdel Moneim El Sawi,
editor of the Arabic edition of the Unesco Courier who, first as Under-Secretary of State
and later as Minister of Culture of the Egyptian Government, was one of the prime movers
and organizers of the International Campaign. We are also grateful for the collaboration of
the well-known French archaeologist Louis Christophe who, as Unesco's principal
archaeological adviser, played a key role, in the campaign and who gave freely of his vast
knowledge of Nubia and his practical experience during the preparation of this issue.
Cover
On March 10, 1980, Unesco's twenty-year International Campaign to save the
treasures of Nubia from the waters of the Nile as they rose behind the Aswan High
Dam comes officially to an end. To mark this occasion the Unesco Courier is
breaking with custom in publishing, for February and March of this year, a double
issue devoted entirely to this unprecedented example of international co¬
operation. Our usual double issue, for August/September, will be replaced by two
single issues. Cover photo shows a column from the temple of Nectanebo, part of
the Philae complex of temples, as it stands today on its new site on the island of
Agilkia. The head carved on the column is that of the ancient Egyptian goddess
Hathor. During the campaign workmen, engineers, architects and archaeologists
combined their efforts to move to safety twenty-two temples in what must rank as
one of the greatest technical exploits of this century.
Photo Mohammed Fathy Ibrahim Dessouky © Documentation Centre for Ancient Egypt, Cairo
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
'A single, universal heritage'
THEstory ofmankind begins to unfold from the moment
that men's memories, their hopes and doubts, take
shape in stone or find expression in a mask or a musical
rhythm. In defiance of death the message is passed down
from generation to generation, spinning the long thread of
historical continuity that enables nations to perpetuate
their collective identity in the face of change.
The works that constitute the spiritual or material, the
literary or artistic fabric of this continuity have thus, from
earliest times, come to acquire inestimable value in the eyes
of the peoples that created them. But only recently have
they begun to be respected, studied and appreciated by the
rest of the world.
Indeed, our generation is the first in history to perceive
the totality of these works as an indivisible whole, each of
them being considered as an integral part of a single univer¬
sal heritage.
The International Campaign to Save the Monuments of
Nubia is a striking example of this new awareness. It has
been marked throughout by a spirit of the widest possible
co-operation and thus has attained all the objectives origi¬
nally assigned to it. It will be numbered among the few
major attempts made in our lifetime by the nations to
assume their common responsibility towards the past so as
to move forward in a spirit of brotherhood towards the
future.
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
Director-General of Unesco
HHHHHHW
Photo Mohamed Fathy Ibrahim Dessouky, Documentation Centre for Ancient Egypt. Cairo
bmumik» m/j '"*&ymt&r-'"*<*WÊÊ®aaiL- m
'-IM**
^N|
$
0T
t *iÈ&-¿m
**
<^5H&
«
* i -
* r ÉÜk.~
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Unesco and the world community
in the greatest archaeological rescue campaign
of all time (1960-1980)
Victory in Nubia: Egypt
by Shehata Adam Mohamed
IN THE LAP OF THE GODS. Work in progress during the reconstruction of the great
temple of Abu Simbel. Completed in September 1968, the mammoth, five-year task
of dismantling, transporting and re-erecting Ramses the Great's most grandiose
construction was a triumph of technical and engineering skill (see pages 10 and 11
and central colour pages).
THE boat weighed anchor and set off
on a voyage up the Nile through
Nubian territory. As it. glided silently
over the water, the first glimmer of dawn
appeared on the horizon. Hemming in the
valley on either side was a desert landscape
that stretched as far as the eye could see.
Here and there, tiers of Nubian houses
stood on the slopes which rose from the left
and right banks of the Nile, the river that is
the life-blood of Egypt and the Sudan.
These houses, remarkable for the decora¬
tions covering their façades and walls, and
for the domes built over their inner
courtyards, were inhabited by the Nubians,
whose loose-fitting robes were as snow-
white as their eyes were piercingly dark.
Before long, as the boat continued quietly
to ply the blue waters, the sun rose on the
eastern horizon and began to climb slowly
into the heavens, revealing, as it did so, a
succession of temples built on either side of
the river temples where Egyptian and Nu¬
bian deities were once worshipped. There
were tombs, too, cemeteries, and the re¬
mains of churches and mosques, some of
them already visible, others still buried in the
ground. And the rock faces bore inscriptions
left behind by the various civilizations that
had passed through or lived in this region in
the course of history.
The twentieth century, however, ushered
in important changes for the peoples who
had for so long been settled on the banks of
the Nile. The building of the Aswan Dam
(1898-1902) and its heightening on two
occasions (1907-1912 and 1929-1934) meant
that the Nubians had to move their towns
and villages to higher ground. Archae¬
ological excavations were therefore carried
out in areas due to be submerged by the
Nile, which would rise to a height of 121
metres above sea level. Certain temples
were consolidated so they could withstand
the fluctuation of the waters which would
cover them for most of the year.
Under the Aswan High Dam project,
however, which was designed to generate
hydroelectric power and increase cropland,
the waters of the Nile would be raised by a
further sixty-two metres above sea level, to k
SHEHATA ADAM MOHAMED, of Egypt, is
president of the Egyptian Antiquities Organiza¬
tion. He was formerly director of the Monuments
of Nubia Service of the Egyptian Ministry of Cul¬
ture and later of the Documentation Centre for
Ancient Egypt in Cairo. He is the author of many
articles and studies on Egyptian archaeology,
including an important thesis entitled Travellers of
Ancient Egypt.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Photos Georg Gerster © Rapho, Paris
A 1,600-piece
jigsaw puzzle in stone
Re-built by the Emperor Augustus from the
remains of a temple erected in late
Ptolemaic times, the temple of Kalabsha,
120 metres long and 70 metres wide, is as
big as a medieval Gothic cathedral. It was
dedicated to the god Mandulis, the Nubian
equivalent of Horus son of Isis. Photo
above shows temple on its original site on
the west bank of the Nile some 50
kilometres south of Aswan. When the
temple was threatened with total,
permanent submersion following the
construction of the Aswan High Dam, the
Federal Republic of Germany undertook to
dismantle and re-erect it on a new site. The
task of dismantling involved lifting some
one thousand six hundred sandstone
blocks, some weighing as much as twenty
tons, loading them on barges and
transporting them to a storage area (left)
near the new site being prepared on a hill
on the west bank of the Nile about one
kilometre south of the High Dam.
Reconstruction of the temple began in
October 1962 and the last piece in this
gigantic jigsaw puzzle was slotted into
place in October 1963. Meanwhile, in
January and February 1962, the Egyptian
Antiquities Service had re-erected on the
same site the ruins of a small Roman
monument, the Kiosk of Kertassi. Top
right, the temple of Kalabsha, with the
Kiosk to the left, as it stands today on its
imposing new site.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Hochtief, Essen, Federal Republic of Germany
the south of Aswan as far upstream as the
Dal Cataract in the Sudan, creating a vast
lake that would engulf for ever all trace of
life from ancient or modern times.
This dramatic prospect prompted the
Egyptian and Sudanese Governments in
1959 to ask Unesco to launch an interna¬
tional appeal aimed at saving the Nubian
historical heritage as the embodiment of a
civilization which had played a leading role
in the history of that part of the Nile valley.
Nubia was not unknown to the interna¬
tional community at large. It had not only
featured in the works of classical Greek and
Roman authors, but had been described by
European explorers like Louis Norden,
Johann Ludwig Burckhardt and Amelia Ed¬
wards. Nubia had also been studied and ex¬
plored by various scientific and ar¬
chaeological expeditions during the nine¬
teenth century, including those of François
Champollion, who succeeded in deciphering
hieroglyphic writing, and of Karl Richard
Lepsius, who published a twelve-volume
work devoted to Egyptian and Nubian anti¬
quities. In the twentieth century, too, impor¬
tant excavations and surveys carried out by
successive archaeological missions in both
Egyptian and Sudanese Nubia have thrown
light on the various Nubian civilizations that
once flourished between Aswan in the north
and Kerma in the south.
This time, however, the problem was of a
more complex nature. Unesco therefore
organized a conference of experts whose
task it was to draw up an international plan
of action aimed at saving the Nubian
heritage in its entirety. The experts met in
Egypt in October 1959. They visited Nubia
and examined its monuments between
Aswan and Semna. In their recommenda¬
tions, they pointed to the need to carry out
excavations on each and every archae
ological site, to survey all Nubia's ancient
structures, and to move the threatened
temples and rebuild them on ground higher
than the High Dam lake.
To save the two temples of Abu Simbel, it
was proposed either to build protective
dams or to raise the temples on hydraulic
jacks. The conference eventually recom¬
mended that an earth and rock fill dam
should be built round the two temples.
Three projects to preserve the temples of
Philae were also examined. The first of these
was based on the principle of building a pro¬
tective dam round the temples; the second
provided for them to be dismantled and re-
erected on the island of Philae after its level
had been raised; and the third called for the
construction of three dams linking the island
of Bigeh to that of Agilkia and to the right
bank of the Nile. This solution was adopted
and recommended by the conference.
The work of the conference, which was
carried out at the same time as similar work
on ways of salvaging the monuments of
Sudanese Nubia, resulted in an international
plan of action being clearly defined in accor¬
dance with the wishes of Unesco and of its
Executive Board. Launching an international
appeal on 8 March 1960, the Director-
General of Unesco called on the world com¬
munity to supply the financial and technical
assistance which could save the Nubian
monuments in both Egypt and the Sudan.
He stressed the fact that the treasures were
part of the heritage of all mankind.
His appeal was followed up by intensive
international exchanges which were closely
geared to every phase of the International
Campaign. The Egyptian Government
showed, by its perceptive action, that it had
a clear awareness of the extent of the pro¬
blem involved. Ancient objects were
selected from the nation's museums and
sent abroad for exhibition so as to promote
understanding of the value of the Egyptian
heritage and of its cultural role. Moreover,
the Government set up a Special Committee
for the project, as well as other advisory
committees, made up of experts in the fields
of archaeology, technology and finance.
Egypt also founded a Service for the
Safeguard of the Monuments of Nubia,
which played a very effective role. Further¬
more, the General Conference of Unesco in
1962 set up an Executive Committee, which
was entrusted with the task of supervising
work on the project. These combined efforts
brought the work of the Campaign to a suc¬
cessful conclusion.
The international appeal met with a
favourable response. First to rally to the
cause, not surprisingly, were the teams of
archaeologists who came, at a very early
date, to carry out excavations and surveys in
Egyptian and Sudanese Nubia. They
discovered traces of the ancient civilizations
that had succeeded each other in Nubia,
from the dawn of history up to the Christian
and Islamic eras. Their work helped to reveal
the ruins of cities, forts, cemeteries and
dykes, paved the way for anthropological
studies and for the investigations of human
and animal origins, and, lastly, threw light
on relations and contacts between the north
and the south.
Similarly, research carried out in Egyptian
Nubia focussed specifically on the Nubian
people, their way of life, and their more re¬
cent communities. Other work was carried
out at the same time on the documentation
of Egyptian temples and tombs. From 1956
on, no effort was spared to this end by mis¬
sions from the Documentation and Study
Centre for the History of the Art and Civiliza¬
tion of Ancient Egypt, in collaboration with
Unesco, which had helped to set up the
Centre. The missions included experts from w
France, Poland and Belgium. A team from f
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
M
Milestones in a twenty-year campaign
à 10 March 1980
August 1979
April 1977
May 1974
1972
S.
1970
6 November 1968
22 September 1968
September 1964
14 May 1964
Spring 1964
1962-63
Nov. Dec. 1962
Summer 1960
8 March 1960
9 January 1960
24 October 1959
6 April 1959
Completion of Unesco's International
Campaign to Save the Treasures of
Nubia
Work completed on Agilkia
Foundations of the Philae
monuments ready on the island
of Agilkia and reconstruction work begins
Cofferdam around the island
of Philae is completed and water
is pumped out
Work begins on Philae rescue
operation; monuments to be
transferred to nearby island of Agilkia
Construction of High Dam completed
The Director-General of Unesco
launches International Campaign to
save the Temples of Philae
Completion of the Abu Simbel
operation
The water begins to rise behind the High Dam
Diversion of Nile to feed the turbines
of the High Dam
Work begins (construction of a protective coffer¬
dam) on transfer of Abu Simbel temples to a
higher site 5îj»
Temple of Kalabsha dismantled,
transferred and re-erected
Unesco's General Conference creates Executive
Committee for the International Campaign
The Nubian temples of Taffa, Dabod and Kertassi
dismantled by the
Egyptian Antiquities Service
The Director-General of Unesco
appeals to the international
community to save the treasures
of Nubia 9 __
Work on the Aswan High Dam
officially inaugurated
The Government of the Sudan appeals to Unesco
for aid in saving the antiquities of Sudanese
Nubia
The Government of Egypt appeals to Unesco for
aid in saving the Nubian historical heritage in
Egypt, threatened by the artificial lake to be
created behind the new Aswan High Dam
Two of the most spectacular engineering
feats of Unesco's International Campaign to
Save the Monuments of Nubia were the
dismantling, removal and re-erection of the
temples of Abu Simbel (see pages 10 and
11) and of Philae (see pages 46 and 47).
These technical exploits rivalled in scope the
achievements of the ancient Egyptians who
raised Philae and carved Abu Simbel from
the solid mass ofa Nubian hillside over 3,000
years ago.
ABU SIMBEL
Total cost: $ 42,000,000, of which half was
borne by the Arab Republic of Egypt and
half provided by international contributions.
Organizers: The Ministry of Culture of the
Arab Republic of Egypt assisted by Unesco.
Advisers: Executive Committee for the
International Campaign to Save the
Monuments of Nubia, composed of
representatives of 15 Member States elected
by the General Conference of Unesco.
Various groups and committees of
experts architects, archaeologists and
engineers.
Consulting engineers and architects:
Vattenbyggnadsbryan (VBB), Stockholm.
>the Oriental Institute of the University of
Chicago explored the temple of Beit el VVali.
Teams carrying out excavations also
recorded rock inscriptions. All these mis¬
sions used photogrammetric maps prepared
by the French National Geographical In¬
stitute in collaboration with the Egyptian
armed forces. The maps, which were fully
developed in Egypt, were made available to
all those working on the salvage projects.
All excavations, investigations and
archaeological surveys were completed
by 1965, the date at which the waters of
the High Dam lake began to rise.
Work on transferring the temples also
started in 1960. At that date, the Egyptian
Government undertook to move the temples
of Taffa, Dabod and Kertassi at its own ex¬
pense. In 1962, it assumed the technical and
financial responsibility of moving the
temples of Dakka, Maharraqa and Dendur.
The Federal Republic of Germany, mean¬
while, took on the task, between 1961 and
1963, of salvaging the temple of Kalabsha
and rebuilding it to the south of the High
Dam, on the site where the Egyptians re-
erected the kiosk of Kertassi. All these
temples date from the Graeco-Roman
period.
Egypt also moved the temples of Beit el
Wali and of Wadi es Sebua, reconstructing
the first near the temple of Kalabsha, and
the second just five kilometres from its
original site, 150 kilometres from Aswan.
Both these temples were among the six
monuments built in the thirteenth century
BC by King Ramses II. Egypt also undertook
to move the tomb of Pennut, a nobleman
who lived under King Ramses VI in the
twelfth century BC, and relocate it on the
new site of Amada in the lee of the moun-
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Contractor: Joint Venture Abu Simbel,
a consortium consisting of the follow¬
ing firms: Hochtief, Essen; Atlas, Cairo;
Grands Travaux de Marseille, Paris;
Impregilo, Milan; Santab and Skanska,
Stockholm.
PHILAE
Total cost: $30,000,000, approximately, of
which half was borne by the Arab Republic
of Egypt and half provided by international
contributions.
Organizers: The Ministry of Culture of the
Arab Republic of Egypt assisted by Unesco.
Advisers: Executive Committee for the
International Campaign to Save the
Monuments of Nubia, composed of
representatives of 15 Member States elected
by the General Conference of Unesco.
Various groups and committees of
experts architects, archaeologists and
engineers.
Consulting engineers and architects:
Office of Dr. William Selim Hanna, Cairo.
Contractors: Joint Venture for Philae, a
consortium consisting of the following
firms: High Dam Company for Civil Works,
Cairo-Aswan; Condotte-Mazzi Estero, SPA,
Rome.
Etching of Gerf Hussein by FC. Gau © Documention Centre for Ancient Egypt, Cairo
tain. The transfer of these three monuments
was made possible by a financial contribu¬
tion from the United States; the cost of re-
erecting them was borne by the Egyptian
Government.
Egypt also moved the front section of the
temple of Amada, which was built by King
Thutmose III in the fourteenth century BC.
The rear section of the building was salvag¬
ed by the French Government. In order not
to damage the inscriptions engraved on that
part of the temple, covered with plaster and
painted, it was moved on metal rails (see
back cover). Egypt also preserved the chapel
of Ellesiya, which dates from the reign of
King Thutmose III, and those of Qasr Ibrim,
which were hewn out of the rock in the four¬
teenth century BC. In 1964, Egypt moved
the temple of Derr, which had been built to
the glory of King Ramses II, and
reconstructed it between 1971 and 1973 near
the temple of Amada and Pennut's tomb.
The transfer of these last-mentioned
buildings was completed by 1965.
As for the temple of Gerf Hussein, which
was dedicated to King Ramses II, and that
of Abu Oda, which was built in honour of
King Horemheb in the fourteenth century
BC, they were, for technical and financial
reasons, only partly salvaged. Lastly, the
Christian inscriptions from Wadi es Sebua
and from Abu Oda were preserved by a
Yugoslav team of archaeologists. By the
time this work was completed, all the
temples, tombs and chapels of Egyptian
Nubia had been preserved except for the
two temples of Abu Simbel and the temples
of Philae, which were the subject of two
special projects.
For the two temples of Abu Simbel, k
which had been hollowed out of the rock by r
Above, etching dating from 1818 by the French architect
François-Chrétien Gau of the temple of Ptah erected by
Ramses II at Gerf Hussein, some 90 kilometres south of
the First Cataract. Below, a statue of Ramses II from the
courtyard of the temple. The inner sanctuary was carved
into the mountain and, although much smaller and
different in style, was based on that of Abu Simbel. The
temple now lies beneath the waters of the Nile, but some
of the statues and reliefs have been preserved.
Photo Paul Almasy, Unesco
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
, King Ramses II, two solutions were examin¬
ed in detail: one called for the construction
of an earth and rock-fill dam, while the other
recommended that the temples be raised on
hydraulic jacks. The first plan turned out to
be financially onerous ($82 million), not to
speak of the damage to the temples which
would be caused by damp arising from
capillary attraction. The second solution
was estimated to cost $62 million. So both
schemes were ruled out.
The Egyptian Government then decided
that the two temples should be cut up into
blocks and transferred to higher ground on
the Abu Simbel plateau. The cost of the
operation, which was originally estimated at
$36 million, eventually ran to $41.7 million
(18.5 million Egyptian pounds). A total of
forty-eight nations helped to finance the
project, with Egypt alone shouldering half
the cost.
Work on the project began in November
1963, when a cofferdam was built to prevent
operations being hampered by the rising
waters of the lake. A drainage pipeline was
then installed to pump off seepage. Scaf¬
folding was erected to support the ceilings,
sides and colonnades of the monuments.
An aluminium tunnel was connected to the
interior of each temple to provide access to
them, then their façades were covered with
sand and topped with iron screens to pro¬
tect them from falling boulders as the task of
removing the rocks from behind the temples
got under way.
Once these operations had been com¬
pleted, work started on cutting the temples
up into blocks. Every attempt was made to
respect the integrity of the archaeological
features and inscriptions on the 1,036 blocks
of stone, which weighed between seven and
thirty tonnes each. Work on transferring the
two temples was completed in February/
March 1966. They were re-erected at the top
of the mountain with the same orientation
so that they would catch the rays of the sun
just as before. This operation was finished in
September 1967.
Then work on the final stage began: this
entailed the construction, above each tem¬
ple, of gigantic domes capable of supporting
the rock covering that was intended to make
the mountainside above the temples look as
much as possible like their original site.
Work ended in September 1968, and the
completion of the scheme was officially
celebrated by an historic ceremony on the
22nd of that month.
Thus the most imposing monument ever
hewn out of rock, and the jewel of the Nu¬
bian treasures, had been saved. At the same
time, the transfer of the temples fulfilled
King Ramses t I's dream of immortalizing his
"temple in the land of Nubia, hewn into the
rock, like no other ever carved before," ac¬
cording to the inscription on the façade of
the small temple of Abu Simbel, which he
dedicated to his beloved wife Queen
Nefertari.
The two temples of Abu Simbel, which
perhaps more than anything else symbolize
the success of the International Campaign,
now stand in all their grandeur high on the
mountain. Behind them lies the town of Abu
Simbel, which housed all those whose ef¬
forts helped to make a success of that great
undertaking. This new town, with its
houses, lawns and. trees, today welcomes
visitors from all over the world who come to
marvel at man's achievements both past and
present.
10
Saving the Great and Small
Temples of Abu Simbel from
the rising waters of the Nile
must rank as one of the
great engineering feats of all
time. The brute force
required to hew the temples
from the rocky hillside in
which they were carved and
to lift and transport blocks
of stone, weighing up to 30
tons, to the new hilltop site,
60 metres higher, was
matched by the surgeon-like
delicacy and precision
demanded in cutting the
fragile sandstone statuary
into manageable blocks.
Once installed on the new
site the temples were
topped by soaring reinforced
concrete domes (the one
covering the Great Temple
spans 60 metres) to take the
weight of the overlay that
has recreated the original
appearance of the
landscape. Above,
reinforced concrete arches
2.5 metres thick were built
to support the shuttering for
the construction of the
dome. Above left, a view of
the partially erected dome
from behind. Bottom left,
under the glare of
floodlights the face of one
of the colossi of the façade
being sawn prior to removal.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Drawing © National Geographic Society, Washington, D.C.
With the aid of royal astronomers the
engineers of Ramses' day aligned the axis
of the Great Temple of Abu Simbel in such
a way that twice a year the sun's rays
penetrated the innermost sanctuary (see
photos pages 56 and 57). The artist's
reconstruction, left, of the temples on their
new site and the "ghost" of the old site
now under water, shows the precision with
which the alignment of the temples and the
general appearance of the setting has been
respected. The light of the sun still streams
into the inner sanctuary twice yearly.
Below, photo of the Great and Small
Temples of Abu Simbel on their new site
was taken in September 1968 just after the
work was completed.
How Abu Simbel was saved
, Photo Dominique Roger, Unesco
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
, The Sudanese Government also took
steps to save its Nubian monuments before
they were submerged by the waters of the
Nile. It organized the transfer of a number of
temples, blocks and rock inscriptions in con¬
junction with the surveys and excavations
being carried out by archaeological
missions.
The temples of Queen Hatshepsut at
Buhen, the temple of the god Knhum at
Semna East, and the temples of Dedun and
of Sesostris III at Semna West were all mov¬
ed. Some blocks from King Ramses I I's tem¬
ple at Aksha as well as reliefs and sculpted
lintels from the tomb of Djehuti-hotep at
Debeira were salvaged. Also rescued were
four column plinths and part of the floor of
the main entrance of Thutmose Ill's temple
at Buhen, along with three blocks of pillars
from the temple of Isis put up by King
Amenhotep II in the town of Buhen.
Inscriptions by the first dynasty King Djer
on the rocks of the Gebel El Sheikh
Suleiman near Buhen, other rock inscrip¬
tions dedicated to a viceroy of Kush by the
name of Setau, and blocks from Faras were
also moved to. safety. The Sudanese
Government transferred all these antiquities
to the Khartoum Museum.
Unfortunately, however, nothing could be
done to prevent the waters of the lake from
engulfing every aspect of Nubian life, both
in Egypt and in the Sudan, as far south as
the Dal Cataract. Nubian houses, with their
decorated walls and façades, villages, even
whole towns vanished for ever. Lush, green
trees and palms still bearing their clusters of
dates Nubia's most delicious fruitwere
consigned to a watery grave. The Nubians
tearfully gathered together their belongings,
beasts of burden and chickens, and set off
for a new life in another town, Kom Ombo.
But they never really gave up all hope of be¬
ing able, one day, to return to their dear
homeland on the banks of the lake.
The lake created by the High Dam con¬
tinued to rise, covering more and more land
on either side exactly as foreseen by the
planners. Attention was then turned to the
island of Philae, between the Aswan Dam
and the High Dam. The temples on Philae,
island of love and the "Anas el-Wagud" of
legend, were submerged. Only the tops of
the buildings were still visible above water.
Studies on the rescue of Philae showed that
the construction of a dam round the island
had several drawbacks, such as the effect
on the temples of damp arising from
capillary attraction, very high' costs, and
maintenance which would require, among
other things, constant pumping to deal with
seepage.
The Egyptian Government then decided
to transfer the temples to the neighbouring
island of Agilkia, which would first be land¬
scaped to resemble Philae. The Director-
General of Unesco launched an appeal to
save this "pearl of Ancient Egypt", and the
project got under way in 1972. When the
building of a cofferdam round the island of
Philae was completed in May 1974, the
water was pumped out, leaving the island
high and dry. At this point, it became possi¬
ble to explore the temples archaeologically
and make photogrammetric records of its
architecture.
Meanwhile, Agilkia was made ready to
receive the temples; and foundations were
laid. This stage of the work was completed
by April 1977. At the same time, prepara¬
tions were being made to transfer the
temples. The first stage of rebuilding them
began in March 1977. The blocks were mov¬
ed in May of the same year, and the final
stone was slotted into the reconstructed
temples in August 1979. Then the final
phase of the project, aimed at making the
island more attractive, was set in motion:
palm trees, acacias, henna, papyrus and
lotus were planted so that the temples of
Philae could have the same setting on the
island of Agilkia that they had once enjoyed
on their previous site before the building of
the Aswan Dam, in other words before the
turn of the century.
Among the reconstructed monuments
was the temple of Augustus, the blocks of
which had been recovered with the help of
the Egyptian and British navies. In all, 45,000
blocks of stone made up the temples of
Philae. The cost of the salvage operation
came to $30 million. Twenty-two nations
made financial contributions to the project,
as did the World Food Programme. Egypt
alone shouldered more than half the total
cost.
The temples of Philae now stand ma¬
jestically on the island of Agilkia, their
beautiful pylons and superb colonnades
enhanced by the water and granite islets
that encircle them.
So at last the aspirations of both Egypt
and the world at large have been fulfilled.
The Egyptian Government showed great
generosity. As a token of gratitude, it
donated an ancient object, a vase or a statue
to each nation that had helped to save the
treasures of Nubia. It even made a gift of
four of its temples to countries which had
contributed substantially to the project:
Dendur was given to the United States,
Dabod to Spain, Taffa to the Netherlands,
and the chapels of Ellesiya to Italy.
It will soon be time to celebrate the
outstanding success of the International
Campaign to save the Nubian heritage,
which has proved to be a victory for world
co-operation.
March 10, 1980, will be the day set aside
to commemorate this enterprise, which was
carried out in all the Nubian territories of
Egypt and the Sudan. It is not only symbolic
of the friendly and fraternal links which unite
peoples with one another, but a token of
mankind's potentialities and of the
achievements of human genius.
The same day, will see the laying of the
foundation stone of the new museum of
Aswan, which will house the antiquities
discovered during the campaign in Egyptian
Nubia.
The boat gliding along the Nile will not be
dropping anchor all that soon: it is continu¬
ing its voyage to bring new life to Nubia,
where there are still more temples, and
where the fertile soil will never cease to give
of its fruit.
Fortunate, indeed, were those who work¬
ed with us on that International Campaign,
the first of its kind ever to succeed in carry¬
ing through such a remarkable salvage
project.
Let me pay tribute to Unesco, to the
countries and organizations, to the scien¬
tists, experts and workmen who toiled night
and day for years, in the freezing cold of
winter or under the scorching summer sun,
to bring this memorable enterprise to a suc¬
cessful conclusion.
Shehata Adam Mohamed
Philae reborn
The rescue of the Philae temples, which
have been rebuilt on another island,
Agilkia, was the final phase in the Nubian
campaign. Before work began in 1972
Philae was permanently submerged and its
monuments flooded to about a third of
their height (see photo caption page 46).
The island was then girdled with an
immense cofferdam consisting of two rows
of sheet steel piling packed with a million
cubic metres of sand, and the water was
pumped out (below). Before being
dissected into some 40,000 stone blocks
and transported to Agilkia the monuments
were cleaned and measured by a special
technique called photogrammetry which
enabled the engineers to reconstruct them
exactly as before, to the last millimetre.
Right, piles of stone (some weighed up to
25 tons) awaiting re-erection on Agilkia. Far
right, protective scaffolding surrounds the
colonnade of the famous mammisi, or
birth-house of the god Horus, during
rebuilding. The dismantling, transfer and
reconstitution of the monuments (total
weight 27,000 tons) was done in record
time, thirty months.
Photo Alexis Vorontzoff, Unesco
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Monuments rescued
The International
Nubian
Campaign
Philae
,
Dabod
à
Taffa Beit el Wali Kalabsha Dendur
Dakka Maharraqa Wadi Sebua
"Üwirr,
Í H
1
Amada Derr Ellesiya
f
Aniba Qasr Ibrim
1/
Abu Simbel
Kertassi
Gerf Hussein
H \
25 50 km M Ao Aswan
iL Philae
Dabod »\
Kertassi
Taffa
Beit el Wali »V.
Kalabsha
Dendur »V
Gerf Hussein
Aniba L"oi"ra
'/ Qasr Ibrim
Abu Oda Debeira
Egypt
Abu Simbel »
r'Âbu Oda
Buhen
i Debeira Sudan
Buhen Semna West
Semna West i
Semna East
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Photo credits page 14 Phi¬
lae: Vorontzoff, Unesco. Dabod:
© Documentation Centre for
Ancient Egypt, Cairo. Kertassi:
© Egyptian Antiquities Service,
Cairo. Taffa: © The Leyden
Museum, The Netherlands Beit
el Wall, Qasr Ibrim: © Almasy,
Paris. Kalabsha, Buhen, Semna
East Semna West: © Rex Kea¬
ting, Paris. Dendur, Wadi es
Sebua: Van der Haagen,
Unesco. Gerf Hussein, Amada,
Dem Almasy, Unesco. Dakka,
Abu Simbel: Laurenza, Unesco.
Maharraqa, Ellesiya, Aniba, Abu
Oda: Unesco. Debeira: © Sudan
National Museum, Khartoum.
Map by Monika Jost, Unesco.
Photo V. Shustov © APN, Paris
Nearly 5,000 years elapsed between the construction of the world's earliest recorded dam, a 15-metre-
high barrage erected at Kosheish on the Nile to supply water to King Menés' capital at Memphis, and
the commencement of work, in 1960, on the Sadd El-Aali or Aswan High Dam (above). Four kilometres
across and a towering 110 metres high, the dam itself was completed in 1964, but it took another six
years before the hydroelectric installations became fully operational. The water impounded behind the
dam has created a 500-kilometre-long lake, the world's second largest man-made lake (after the Kariba
Dam lake in Rhodesia Zimbabwe) with an average volume of one hundred and sixty thousand million
cubic metres of water. Built with the aid of the USSR, the Aswan High Dam has twelve powerful
turbines with a design capacity of around ten thousand million kilowatt hours a year, an output which is
conveyed by two thousand five hundred kilometres of high energy power lines to the big industrial
plants and population centres of Egypt. Below, a colossus from a temple at Tebo in the Sudan on the
way to its new home in Khartoum (see also photo page 17).
Photo Gunvor Jorgsholm © Pressehuset, Copenhagen
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
The Nubian king Taharqa (690-664 BC) makes an offering to a god and receives in return the ankh or
symbol of life. This relief from a temple at Buhen, near the Second Cataract, is now preserved in the
Sudan National Museum, Khartoum.
Victory in Nubia: The Sudan
by Negm-el-Din Mohammed Sherif
THE decision to build the Aswan High
Dam by the Government of Egypt
had two very grave consequences for
the Nubians. On the one hand, it meant the
loss of their fatherland for good, and on the
other hand it entailed the complete disap¬
pearance of the cultural remains of their
ancestors.
The two aspects of the decision were too
much for them to bear; but being fully aware
of the importance of the High Dam for the
economic welfare and advancement of the
peoples of the Nile Valley in both Egypt and
the Sudan, the Nubians willingly accepted
the idea of building the Dam, thereby
sacrificing their beloved, peaceful and
beautiful homeland. But they were deeply
concerned about the known and the
unknown archaeological remains which
would ultimately be lost under the waters of
the proposed Dam.
Archaeologically speaking, Sudanese
Nubia, unlike Egyptian Nubia, was practical¬
ly unknown, for although it offered ar¬
chaeological remains from the Palaeolithic
period up to the conquest of the Sudan by
Mohammed Ali Pasha of Egypt in 1820, it
16
had never been thoroughly investigated.
Thus it was unthinkable to the Nubians that
a region of such great importance for the
history of mankind in general, and that of
Africa in particular, not to mention their own
history, should disappear beneath the water
without thorough archaeological research
being carried out into it.
Moreover, a number of important known
monuments were directly threatened by the
new reservoir and had to be saved. But it
was quite clear that the whole enterprise
was beyond the technical and financial
abilities of the Sudan Antiquities Service.
Faced with this distressing situation, the
Sudan had no option but to take refuge in
the shade of Unesco and to request aid from
the international community. On 24 October
1959, the Sudan appealed to Unesco for
financial, technical and scientific help to
save the antiquities of Sudanese Nubia. This
was followed by an appeal issued by the
Director-General of Unesco to all Member
States and institutions to extend assistance
to the Governments of both Egypt and the
Sudan so as to save the cultural heritage of
Nubia.
The international response was prompt
and extremely soothing to the hearts of the
Nubians. The campaign to save the
monuments of Sudanese Nubia began.
During the period between 1960 and 1970
the Sudan witnessed intensive ar¬
chaeological work of an unprecedented
kind. Nineteen foreign archaeological mis¬
sions worked in the Sudanese territory en¬
dangered by the waters of the Aswan High
Dam, between Faras in the north and Dal
Cataract in the south.
Outside the concessions granted to these
missions, the Sudanese Antiquities Service
conducted with its own resources a survey
whose aims were to discover and define ar¬
chaeological remains worthy of excavation
by foreign missions, and also to excavate
any site not wanted by the foreign expedi¬
tions. This survey, carried out with the help
NEGM EL DIN MOHAMMED SHERIF, of the
Sudan, is director-general of the Sudan Antiqui¬
ties Service and played an active part in the
Nubian campaign. He is also director of the
Sudan National Museum, in Khartoum, and edi¬
tor of Kush, an archaeologicaljournalpublished in
Khartoum.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
of a number of Unesco experts, covered the
full extent of Sudanese Nubia between
Faras and the head of the proposed reservoir
at Dal.
Moreover, there were other surveys
beside that of the Sudanese Antiquities
Service. A Scandinavian Joint Expedition
exhaustively explored a portion of the en¬
dangered area extending sixty kilometres
south of Faras on the right bank of the Nile,
excavating practically all sites in their con¬
cession area and documenting thousands of
rock drawings. Other surveys in the region
covered rock pictures and inscriptions as
well as the investigation of Stone Age relics.
The results of the campaign in Sudanese
Nubia were extremely gratifying as far as
both scientific information and ar¬
chaeological finds are concerned. The part
of the Sudan flooded by the waters of the
Aswan High Dam is now the only region in
the entire country which has received any
systematic archaeological investigation.
Many beautiful finds have been unearthed
and a great deal of information has been
gathered. Now we can reconstruct in great
detail the history of culture and civilization in
this region of immense importance not only
for the history of the Nile Valley but also for
the history of Africa. In short, the scientific
information these unprecedented ar¬
chaeological activities yielded has enor¬
mously enriched human knowledge.
The great collections of archaeological
finds acquired as a result of this international
campaign have enriched many museums in
different countries and have enabled the
Sudan Antiquities Service to establish the
Sudan National Museum in Khartoum,
depicting the past of the Sudanese nation
from the Old Stone Age to the advent of
Islam. In the garden of this museum,
monuments removed from the endangered
area in Sudanese Nubia have been re-
erected beside an artificial pool symbolizing
the Nile, along which they had originally
been built. This garden in itself has become
an open-air museum.
These collections also helped the Sudan
Antiquities Service to reorganize a provincial
museum at the town of El-Obeir in Kordofan
Province, supplementing its exhibits to il¬
lustrate all the periods in the ancient history
of the Sudan, and to establish a new provin¬
cial museum at the town of El-Fasher in Dar-
fur Province. Moreover, two other provincial
museums have now been built and most of
their exhibits will also be finds discovered
during the international salvage campaign in
Sudanese Nubia.
The archaeological work carried out in
Sudanese Nubia has manifestly proved that
Lower Nubia is very rich in antiquities.
Moreover it has raised many questions the
answers to which are believed to lie still
buried under the sand in the archaeological¬
ly unexplored parts south of the Dal
Cataract. To find the answers to these ques¬
tions, excavations have been undertaken in
that region. Ten missions from those ex¬
peditions which took part in the salvage i
campaign in the endangered part of I
Seven metres in height and weighing thirty
tons, this colossus is one of two found
lying in the sand at the entrance to a
temple at Tebo on the island of Argo near
the Third Cataract. The statues, one of
which was found broken in two, are
probably representations of the Meroitic
king Natakamani (12 BC to 12 AD). The
statues, which now stand in front of the
Sudan National Museum, were taken the
thousand kilometres from Tebo to
Khartoum by special truck, (see photo page
15), by boat and by rail. Right, arrival at
Khartoum.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Left, the motif of this relief from a temple
at Semna East, a stylized representation of
the lotus intertwined with the papyrus
plant and encircling a hieroglyph meaning
"unite", is to be found on many
monuments and temple walls in Nubia. It
signifies the unification of Upper Egypt
(represented by the lotus) with Lower
Egypt (the papyrus).
Carved out of granite and with the figure of
the king standing within the protection of
its forelegs, the huge ram, below left, is
one of two which once stood in front of
the great temple of Amon at Gebel Barkal.
The ram was the symbol of Amon whose
cult was predominant at Thebes. The two
statues, which date from the reign of the
Nubian king Taharqa (690-664 BC), now
flank the steps leading to the entrance of
the Sudan National Museum in Khartoum. .
The object below, found in a house at
Meinarti, on the east bank of the Nile
above the Second Cataract, is the topmost
basin of a wine press consisting of three
basins made of brick and lined with a thick
coat of stucco. The lion spout formed the
outlet for the grape juice which flowed
down to the second and third basins. The.
installation was at first thought to be a
public bath, possibly intended for ritual
bathing, but after comparison with eleven
similar installations found between Faras
and Ikhmindi its true purpose was
established. Dating from the later Meroitic
period, it is now preserved in the Sudan
National Museum.
Photo © Sudan National Museum, Khartoum
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
, Sudanese Nubia have been operating there
since 1964, and more foreign expeditions are
expected to take the field soon.
The international campaign to save the
antiquities of Nubia will go down in history
as one of the most important achievements
of Unesco. It has been a magnificent
manifestation of human co-operation and
world brotherhood. It has constituted con¬
crete evidence that under the umbrella of
Unesco the inhabitants of our planet can
work in complete harmony, achieving
marvels for the good of humanity,
regardless of nationality, political creed or
religious belief.
Thus one of the most important results of
this international campaign, outside the
sphere of archaeology, is that it has ad¬
mirably shown the Sudanese public the im¬
portance of Unesco as a very effective in¬
strument of international co-operation in the
field of culture.
Another pleasing outcome of the interna¬
tional salvage campaign is the wide interest
it has aroused among the Sudanese people
regarding the past of their country. The
keen interest Unesco has taken in the anti¬
quities of Nubia, the intensive informational
efforts it has exerted, the international reac¬
tion to the announcement of the imminent
disappearance of a great number of sites
and monuments in Nubia, the deep concern
the whole world has expressed in connexion
with the salvage question and the rush of so
many archaeologists into Nubia have
brought home to the Sudanese the impor¬
tance of their cultural heritage; and what the
archaeologists have unveiled has clearly
manifested to them that they have a past of
which they should feel proud.
Negm-el-Din Mohammed Sherif
Below, in the cathedral of Faras workmen
remove the last basketfuls of sand and
debris that for centuries had covered this
magnificent Nativity scene. One of the
finest frescoes discovered at Faras, it
measures seven metres by four metres and
dates from the end of the 10th century or
the beginning of the 11th. After being
painstakingly removed from the wall (see
photo page 39) and fixed to a wooden
backing, it was carefully wrapped and
transported (it had to be carried part of the
way by men on foot) to the Sudan National
Museum, Khartoum.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Nubia unearthed
THE, first traces of human life in
Lower Nubia date from hundreds
of thousands of years ago and
consist of extremely primitive tools used by
our earliest ancestors, long before the ap¬
pearance of homo sapiens. But in contrast
to findings in Kenya and Tanzania, skeletons
or human remains found in Nubia or Egypt
proper date only from rather late in
prehistoric times.
The earliest remains are the traces of
what seems to have been a human tragedy.
Just north of Wadi Haifa, fifty-eight
skeletons were found covered by a thin layer
of sand and stones. Arrowheads found
among the bodies and scars on the bones
show that they were probably all killed in a
battle or a massacre.
An analysis of the bodies and their ages in
combination with what is known from food
remains and other finds in settlements
dating from the same period (around 10000
BC) makes it possible to reconstruct their
living conditions in detail: how they hunted
the big game which came down to the valley
to drink before retiring into the savannah
areas which are today desert. Fishing and
the hunting of migratory birds also con¬
tributed to their diet. Recent research has
led to the even more amazing conclusion
that a primitive cereal agriculture probably
already existed at this time.
Similar living conditions are also found at
a later stage of prehistory, during a period
with a wet climate. Thousands of rock draw¬
ings along the valley, which have all been
recorded by archaeological expeditions,
illustrate the fauna and the life of hunters
during the very late Stone Age. The same
types of rock drawings are found all over the
present desert areas of the Sahara and
presumably indicate connexions between
the inhabitants of immense savannahs and
steppes where nomads could roam freely
unhindered by drought.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Great Temple of Abu Simbel in its
original setting, before the construction of
the Aswan High Dam. The temple is now
situated sixty metres higher up on top of
the hill from which it was carved over 3,000
years ago (see central colour pages).
These rock carvings of giraffes were discovered by the University of
Strasbourg archaeological expedition in the Tomas area in the heart of
Egyptian Nubia. The thousands of rock drawings of a rich fauna,
including elephant, hippopotamus, giraffe, gazelle and goat, found in
this region indicate that at one time the desert of today was a
steppeland rich with life.
From prehistory
to Pharaonic times by Torgny Säve-Söderbergh
The most interesting conclusions re¬
garding cultural development and the in¬
terplay between different civilizations and
cultures are usually drawn from simple ob¬
jects such as potsherds. This was borne out
by the oldest potsherds found during the
Nubian campaign; the same general types
occurred over vast areas from Nubia in the
north to the neighbourhood of Khartoum
some 1,500 kilometres further south. The
entirely unexpected discovery in Nubia of
types previously known only from areas
much further south opens up new vistas of
the cultural development of this part of
Africa, where we can now study cultural in
terrelations over immense areas and thereby
connect southern cultures to their better-
known and better-dated counterparts fur¬
ther north.
Such so-called "techno-complexes",
groups of "cultures" with similar
technologies but not necessarily politically
or ethnically closely connected, may have
provided a basis favourable to the rise of the
first States in human history. This was the
case in the Egyptian part of the Nile valley,
where the earliest State was organized by
the Pharaonic rulers around 3000 BC.
Contemporary with this development in
the north a special type of civilization, called
by archaeologists the "A-Group", spread all
over Lower Nubia. The Nubians of the
"A-Group" produced wonderful handicraft, k
especially pottery, and imported luxury f
TORGNY SÄVE-SÖDERBERGH, of Sweden, is
professor of Egyptology at the University of
Uppsala and president of the Royal Swedish
Academy of Letters, History and Antiquities
(1978). He is the author of a number of articles
and books including an outstanding study entitled
Egyptians and Nubians. He has been a member of
the Executive Committee of the International
Campaign to Save the Monuments of Nubia since
1962 and was leader of the Joint Scandinavian
Expedition to Nubia.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
o
«f
E
These clay figurines depicting a mature woman and a girl were
found by the Joint Scandinavian Expedition in the tomb of a
woman at Haifa Degheim in Sudanese Nubia. They date back
some 5,000 years to the "A-Group" culture which developed in
Lower Nubia at about the time of the first Pharaonic dynasties.
They represent, perhaps, a kind of magic "insurance" to
guarantee a life after death, rather like certain Egyptian
funerary statuettes. The terracotta hippopotamus head, is from
Qustul in Egyptian Nubia and also dates from the "A-Group".
The stylized head was probably part of a statue of a complete
animal; it must have been of considerable size since this
fragment alone measures 19.7 cm in height.
t goods from the Pharaonic State in the
north.
Rich tombs excavated by a Chicago ex¬
pedition near Qustul just north of the
Sudanese frontier indicate the presence of a
political centre ruled by a dominant chief or
king. These tombs may even be earlier than
the first royal tombs in Egypt and perhaps a
development towards a centralized State
had started in Nubia as well as in Egypt. But
if so, this Nubian kingdom never achieved
the efficiency and " power of the first
Pharaonic State.
To begin with. Nubia traded peacefully
with Egypt to the benefit of both countries,
but as the power of the Egyptians grew,
they started to take by force merchandise
which they had previously paid for. Before
the end of the Second Egyptian Dynasty
(c. 2650 BC) the "A-Group" population of
Lower Nubia disappeared. They may have
been massacred or driven out by the Egyp¬
tians, or they may have left this part of the
Nile valley because of climatic changes.
It seems to be a common trait in the pat¬
tern of Nubian history that Nubia is poor
when Egypt is rich. The Egyptian apogees
often correspond to a cultural or political
vacuum in Nubia. This was the case during
the Old Kingdom, when Egyptian civilization
reached one of its highest peaks, and Egypt
was the biggest and richest State in the
world of its time.
Recent research has clearly shown that
there is no evidence for the assumption that
the "A-Group" still existed in Lower Nubia
after the first two Egyptian Dynasties, and
there are practically no finds illustrating an
22
indigenous culture in Nubia during the Old
Kingdom before the Sixth Dynasty, that is,
in the several centuries during which the
great pyramids at Saqqara and Giza were
built.
Egyptian activities in Lower Nubia are
only illustrated by two find complexes. The
first complex, known since the 1930s, is a
series of rock inscriptions and Egyptian tools
found in the quarries in the western desert,
where the Egyptians extracted diorite for the
famous royal statues of Chephren and other
rulers.
The other complex is an Old Kingdom for¬
tified town excavated by Professor Emery
just north of the Middle Kingdom fortress of
Buhen in northern Sudan. To judge from the
finds, consisting of Egyptian ceramics and
the remains of kilns for copper smelting, this
was an Egyptian strongpoint for the ex¬
ploitation of Nubian raw materials.
These Egyptian enterprises seem to have
taken place during a vacuum in Nubian
history, and when King Snofru tells us that
he "hacked up the land of Nubia, taking
7,000 prisoners and bringing away 200,000
cattle and sheep", we are at a loss from an
archaeological point of view, for no traces
have been found of this population with its
vast herds.
The fact that King Snofru mentions cattle
as characteristic of the Nubian economy of
his time indicates that his opponents were
pastoralist nomads, probably living in the
areas which are now desert which were
more habitable at that time thanks to a more
humid climate. They may also have lived in
Dongola in the south where recent research
has uncovered a transitional stage between
the "A-Group" and the "C-Group", the lat¬
ter constituting the later population of
Lower Nubia.
So it seems that the farmers of the
"A-Group" became nomads again, leaving
Lower Nubia, either because of political or
climatic factors, or maybe both.
Many questions remain unanswered. This
is often the case for similar periods when
there are no archaeological finds to
enlighten us about what really happened.
Such a vacuum also exists for nearly one
thousand years after 1000 BC and again
from the beginning of the Middle Ages to
the 19th century AD.
Towards the end of the Old Kingdom we
find a series of texts relating to the expedi¬
tions of Egyptian caravan leaders to Nubia,
including the famous text of Unis in his
tomb at Saqqara, and others in the tombs of
Herkhuf, Pepinakht, etc., at Aswan. They
tell of peaceful trade or warfare in Lower
Nubia and also perhaps in Dongola.
These texts, the earliest records of travel
abroad, are already classical and much has
been written in attempts to reconstruct the
journeys and to identify the countries men¬
tioned. Thanks to new finds of inscriptions
in Lower Nubia we are now in a better posi¬
tion to do so. These finds constitute the
earliest remains of what archaeologists have
long called the "C-Group".
We can again see how peaceful trade
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
developed into armed conflicts, with dif¬
ferent Nubian tribes uniting under one
leader to oppose the Egyptian attacks. The
interrelations between Egypt and Nubia
broke off when the centralized political
power in Egypt was weakened and inner
conflicts made trade or warfare abroad
impossible or ineffective. Nubian civilization
now developed into a cultural structure of its
own, quite different from the Egyptian
way of life but to some extent influenced by
it, as attested by imported goods.
When Egypt was still weak after the fall of
the Old Kingdom, its influence on the early
"C-Group" testifies to peaceful relations and
trade which benefited the Nubians. After
the unification of Egypt, with the rise of the
11th Dynasty, the Egyptian rulers tried to re¬
establish their prestige in Nubia by more
violent means and there was a decline in the
quantities of Egyptian goods reaching
Lower Nubia. At the same time Egyptian
texts tell us that the Nubians were made to
pay tribute, thus bringing about a negative
balance in the exchange to the detriment of
the Nubians.
Egypt regained its full power with the 12th
Dynasty and conquered Lower Nubia as far
as Semna in the region of the Second
Cataract. Thanks to the epigraphic expedi¬
tions in the 1960s, especially that of
Czechoslovakia, we now have new historical
documents relating to this conquest, and
the excavations at Buhen, Mirgissa, Semna
and at other sites have given us an insight
both into the sophisticated art of fortifica¬
tion practised by the Egyptians and into the
history of the military occupation (see article
page 62).
The chain of Egyptian fortresses in the
region of the Second Cataract was con-
to defend the Egyptian border at
Semna and to protect the trade route
southwards. To the south of the Egyptian
frontier was the realm of the "Ruler of
Kush", with its capital at Kerma in Dongola
and a subsidiary centre on the island of Sai,
to judge from recent excavations there.
The culture of Kerma was already known
long before the Nubian Campaign through
excavations by the American archaeologist
G.A. Reisner before the First World War.
The main monuments were a huge brick
building, called the Western Deffufa, and a
cemetery with what seems to be the first
large royal tombs in Africa outside Egypt.
The rulers were interred with their wives in a
central chamber, and their courtiers,
sometimes up to 400 individuals, were
buried alive in a corridor on both sides of the
royal burial chamber.
Some of the objects found are in¬
digenous, but so many Egyptian goods were
found that Reisner even came to believe that
the tombs were those of Nubianized Egyp¬
tians. Later analysis has shown that this in¬
terpretation is untenable.
The wealth of the Kerma kingdom is il¬
lustrated by these archaeological finds, and
the Egyptian defence system against the
Kerma rulers shows their political and
military strength.
After the end of the Middle Kingdom and
at the time when foreigners, the so-called
Hyksos, ruled Egypt, the military control of
Lower Nubia ceased and the fortresses were
abandoned. This is when the kingdom of
Kerma flourished, and the richest and
largest tombs date from this period. Lower w
Nubia now belonged to the realm of the*
These curious, well-like
structures are in fact tombs in a
typical "C-Group" cemetery
discovered at Serra West, in
Sudanese Nubia. They date from
about 1900 BC.
This terracotta woman's head,
5.4 cm high, was found in the
cemetery at Aniba in Egyptian
Nubia. It dates from between
1900 and 1550 BC and is a
product of the "C-Group"
culture. The eyes and mouth are
portrayed by simple horizontal
incisions. The holes at the back
of the head represent the hair.
Photo Alexis Vorontzoff, Unesco, © Egyptian
Museum of Karl Marx University, Leipzig
Photo © Joint Scandinavian Expedition
Photo © Oriental Institute Museum, Chicago
Discovered in a "C-
Group" cemetery at
Adindan, this terracotta
bowl measures 13.9 cm
in diameter and is
decorated with three
rows of unhorned cattle.
It dates from between
1900 and 1650 BC.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
i^ "Ruler of Kush", who probably resided in
Kerma; Egyptians in his service have left in¬
scriptions in the former Egyptian fortress of
Buhen, which was now a Kushite political
centre in Lower Nubia.
The Unesco campaign demonstrated that
many problems could not be solved in
Lower Nubia because of lack of evidence:
the disappearance of the "A-Group" and the
ensuing vacuum in Nubian history; the com¬
ing of the "C-Group"; the interrelations with
the south; and the nature of the Kushite
domination at the time when the Hyksos rul¬
ed in Egypt. Solutions to these problems
had to be looked for elsewhere, and as a
result archaeological investigations were in¬
tensified at Kerma, on the island of Sai and
on other sites in the Dongola province.
According to preliminary reports, the
development of the Kerma culture can be
followed from the Old Kingdom down to its
disappearance during the New Kingdom,
when Kerma was conquered by the rulers of
the 18th Egyptian Dynasty. Moreover a tran¬
sition from the "A-Group" to the "C-Group"
during the time of the vacuum in Lower
Nubia seems to have taken place in
Dongola.
Three archaeological groups, probably
corresponding to different ethnic groups,
dominate the picture of Lower Nubia during
the time of the Hyksos and the early New
Kingdom: the "C-Group", the "Kerma
Group" and the "Pan Graves", representing
a desert tribe called the Medja (modern Bed-
ja) and also found in Egypt as mercenaries.
All three seem to have had a common origin
in Dongola and were closely related to one
another at an earlier stage there than when
we find them further north.
Around the Western Deffufa at Kerma
(where all these stages can be studied in dif¬
ferent cemeteries) a fortified town has been
found, the oldest known urban centre in
Africa outside Pharaonic Egypt.
The end of the Hyksos rule in Egypt is
marked by several texts of the Theban
liberator of the country. King Kamose, in
which the political situation is described.
The Asiatic Hyksos ruled the north, Kamose
the central part of Egypt down to Aswan,
and the "Ruler of Kush" (from Kerma) from
Aswan southwards. The Kerma domination
of Lower Nubia did not change its cultural
character.
The Lower Nubian civilization of the
"C-Group" developed along different lines.
Part of the population adhered to the old
traditions in such matters as burial rites and
pottery, and to this indigenous basis they
added Egyptian luxury goods. Others,
however, seem to have become more Egyp-
tianized, and from now on the situation is
such that it is difficult to distinguish bet¬
ween Egyptianized Nubians and Egyptian
immigrants.
The most plausible interpretation, to my
mind, is that once the Nubians were free
from the Egyptian military occupation, their
aversion to Egyptian culture and Egyptian
goods ceased. The free Nubians were rapid¬
ly Egyptianized and did not hesitate also to
call in Egyptians to serve them. As a result
their power of resistance was weakened and
their opposition to Egyptian aggression at
the beginning of the 18th Dynasty was
ineffective.
The texts of King Kamose provide some
details about the interrelations between the
Hyksos and the Nubian ruler of Kush. The
Asiatic Hyksos in northern Egypt had tried in
vain to make the Nubians, the people of Ker¬
ma, attack Kamose from the south at the
same time as he was waging war against the
Hyksos in the north. This plan failed for
unknown reasons, and Kamose and his
brother Ahmose managed to throw the
Asiatic Hyksos out of Egypt and also to con¬
quer Lower Nubia. Their successors, Thut¬
mose I and Thutmose III, pushed further
south, put an end to the kingdom of Kerma
and established the Egyptian frontier at the
Fourth and Fifth Cataracts, thus incor¬
porating the whole of Dongola into the
Egyptian empire.
Nubia under Egyptian rule during the New
Kingdom (1550-1080 BC) provides a
fascinating chapter of human history from
many points of view. For this period, we
have an overwhelming amount of material,
both archaeological and textual, and we also
know much more about the individual actors
in the drama. A recent doctoral thesis deal¬
ing with the Egyptian administration of the
Nubian colony, used some 800 textual or
pictorial documents, to describe the ad¬
ministrative machinery, the persons
employed and their careers, the taxes paid,
and the revenue exported.
Were the Nubians replaced by Egyptian
immigrants, did they leave Nubia on their
own initiative or did they stay on and
become Egyptianized? The Egyptian texts
and pictures describing Nubia in the New
Kingdom tend to indicate the last alter¬
native.
A number of early New Kingdom
cemeteries of traditional Nubian types
belong to population groups which largely
resisted Egyptian influence and adhered to
their old beliefs and culture.
Otherwise the archaeological picture is
dominated by burials of Egyptian types.
How are they to be interpreted? Were their
occupants Egyptians or Nubians? Here -the
specialists do not agree and perhaps both
answers are correct. In the countryside, far
away from the Egyptian administrative cen¬
tres, there are strong indications that the
tombs tended to belong to Nubians, and
even in the cemeteries of the Egyptian
towns misunderstandings of Egyptian burial
customs in some cases indicate the
presence of Egyptianized Nubians rather
than ordinary Egyptians.
That the Egyptians did by no means exter¬
minate or drive out the Nubian population of
Lower Nubia is quite clear from the evidence
from tombs of Nubian princes which came
to light during the Nubian Campaign.
The older ones, from the reigns of Queen
Hatshepsut and Thutmose III (about 1450
BC), were investigated by the Scandinavian
Joint Expedition in the northernmost part of
the Sudan, in the district of Debeira (see
page 41). They belonged to two brothers,
Djehuti-hotep and Amenemhet, born of Nu¬
bian parents to judge by their names. They
bear the titles of Egyptian officials but also
that of "Great One of (the district)
Teh-khet", "Great One" being the
denomination of royal persons or even kings
of foreign countries. The tomb of Djehuti-
hotep, the elder brother, is decorated in the
style of the tombs in the capital, Thebes.
The tomb of the younger brother,
Amenemhet, is also entirely Egyptian and all
the finds in the tomb are of good Egyptian
craftsmanship.
So those tombs which are the most Egyp¬
tian by their form, decoration and burial gifts
belong, according to the texts, to Nubian
CONTINUED PAGE 70
This terracotta pot (left) with its
rounded shape and ram's head
spout is typical of the "Kerma"
culture which was
contemporary with the "C-
Group". It is 22 cm in height and
dates from between 1750 and
1550 BC. It was found in 1914 by
the famous United States
archaeologist George Reisner
who dubbed vessels of this type
"teapots". Rams with horns
curling around the ears were a
frequent decorative motif on
pottery from Kerma where
sheep had religious and
ritualistic significance. The
identification of the ram with
the god Amon, which had
developed in Egypt by the time
of the 18th Dynasty is believed
to have originated in the ram
cult in Nubia.
Photo © Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York
Detail from the famous painted relief in the
tomb of Huy,. at Thebes, the ancient capital of
Egypt, depicting a procession of tribute from
the southlands. Huy was the viceroy of Nubia
under the Pharaoh Tutankhamun. Between the
horns of the cattle can be seen the heads of
Nubians adorned with feathers. The horns of
the cattle terminate in the form of hands, or
gloves, stretched out in an attitude of adoration.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Nubia's corridor
of time
From the Kingdom of Kush
to the triumph of Islam
William Y. Adams
OR more than five centuries, from
1580 until around 1000 BC, the region
between the First and Fourth Cata¬
racts of the Nile was ruled by Egyptian gar¬
risons and governors, and its revenues went
to support the Pharaonic regime in Egypt.
When at last the occupiers went home, it
was an Egyptianized Nubia (or Kush, as it
was then known) that they left behind them.
For millennia thereafter the people of Kush
were able to sustain a high civilization of
their own, and intermittently to play a part
on the world stage as well.
Neither history nor archaeology provides
a very clear picture of events in Nubia during
the centuries immediately following the
Egyptian departure. It seems however that
the worship of Amon and other Egyptian
Egyptian rule of Nubia, then known as "Kush", ended sometime around 1000 BC but Egyptian traditions were maintained there for
centuries by Nubian rulers who when they died were buried under pyramids. These two pyramids in the royal necropolis of the
kingdom of Kush, at Meroë, were built so close together that their bases touch.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Photo © National Archaeological Museum, Athens
Finely worked gold ram's head earring (6th
century BC) is from a necropolis at Meroë.
On the forehead are two crowned uraei,
and a sun disc is on the head. Ram's head
pendants forming part of the regalia of
Kushite kings may be connected with the
age-old veneration for the ram in Nubia.
> deities was maintained at the temple cities of
Napata and Kawa, either by Egyptians or by
a native priesthood that kept up Egyptian
traditions.
By 800 BC we see evidence for the rise of
a local dynasty which may have allied itself
with the priests of Amon at Napata. Only a
short time later one of the Nubian princes, a
certain Kashta, was invited by the priests of
Amon to assume the ancient crown of the
Pharaohs in Egypt itself.
Kashta duly travelled to Thebes, the an¬
cient Egyptian capital, and was there in¬
vested with the titles and authority of the
Pharaoh. Except for this one journey there is
no evidence that he ever made any con¬
certed effort to rule in Egypt. In the follow¬
ing generation however another Nubian
ruler, Piye or Piankhi, was again summoned
to the aid of the beleaguered 'domains of
Amon in Egypt. Unlike his predecessor,
Piankhi was not content merely to relieve
the threat to Thebes; he chased the invaders
back into the north of Egypt, subdued them
one by one, and reunited the country under
his personal rule. For the next 88 years, from
751 to 663 BC, the Nubians ruled over both
Egypt and Kush as the Pharaohs of the
25th or "Ethiopian" Dynasty.
Nubian rule in Egypt was terminated by an
Assyrian invasion in 663 BC. Back in their
own country, however, the erstwhile
WILLIAM Y. ADAMS, of the United States, is
professor of anthropology at the University of
Kentucky. During the late 1950s he was director
of archaeological salvage excavations in Glen
Canyon on the Colorado River. Invited by Unesco
and the Sudanese Government to assist in the
salvage operations in Nubia, he planned and
carried out excavations for the Sudanese
Antiquities Service from 1959 to 1966 and co¬
ordinated the activities of fourteen other
expeditions. He is the author of an important
book entitled Nubia, Corridor to Africa, Allen
Lane, London, 1977.
Bronze head, left, is a likeness of
Shabaqa, one of the Nubian Kings who
from 751 to 663 BC ruled over both
Nubia and Egypt as Pharaohs of the
25th or "Ethiopian" Dynasty. Two uraei,
stylized representations of the sacred
asp, an emblem of Egyptian
sovereignty, are combined with a
typically Nubian royal attribute, the
skullcap, to symbolize the unification
of Nubia and Egypt under one king.
Pharaohs from the south continued to main¬
tain the political, religious, and artistic tradi¬
tions of ancient Egypt for another
1,000 years, until sometime in the fourth
century AD. They built temples in the Egyp¬
tian style to the Egyptian gods (as well as
some of their own), proclaimed their deeds
(at least in the earlier centuries) in
hieroglyphic texts, and when they died were
buried under pyramids.
Their royal capital was at first established
in the old Egyptian temple-city of Napata,
near the Fourth Cataract of the Nile. Later it
was transferred to the city of Meroe, at a
point considerably farther up the Nile.
The conquest of Egypt by Alexander the
Great in 332 BC brought both Egypt and
Kush (or Aethiopia as it was usually termed
by Classical writers) to the immediate atten¬
tion of the Classical world. Diplomatic rela¬
tions were established between the Nubian
kingdom and the newly enthroned
Ptolemaic (that is, Greek) rulers of Egypt,
and over the next centuries many Greek and
Roman diplomats and merchants travelled
to the almost legendary city of Meroe, deep
in the African interior.
Archaeology has revealed that Meroe in
its heyday was indeed an impressive place.
Among its buildings of stone and brick it
numbered more than half a dozen temples,
at least two major palaces, and a Roman-
style bathing establishment. The great Tem¬
ple of Amon was second in size only to the
Temple of Amon at Thebes, in Egypt. Two
miles away to the east, a serried rank of
stone pyramids marked the final resting
place of the rulers of Kush. In the hinterland
to the south and east of the capital, the
steppeland cities of Musawwarat, Naqa and
Wad ben Naqa were almost as impressive as
Meroe itself.
The establishment of Roman rule in Egypt
in 30 BC was marked initially by hostilities
along the Roman-Nubian frontier. However,
The Kushite King of Egypt, Taharqa
(25th Dynasty, 690-664 BC) has been
described by a modern scholar as "a
great personality and a great builder
approaching the scale of Ramses II".
The black diorite portrait of Taharqa,
above, has Kushite characteristics but
his features have been idealized to
conform to the canons of Egyptian
royal portraiture. Right, frontal view of
a 75-cm-long granite sphinx of Taharqa
in which his Sudanese features are far
more strongly expressed.
a treaty signed in 21 BC ushered in a period
of amicable relations between the two
powers which lasted nearly three centuries.
The last centuries of the Roman Empire
were a time of upheaval and migration in
north Africa no less than in Europe and Asia.
The Empire of Kush, now more than a thou¬
sand years old, was menaced by barbarian
nomads Blemmyes and Noba both
in the east and in the west. An equally
serious threat was posed by the newly
emergent power of Axum in the Abyssinian
highlands, which vied with Meroe in the
long-distance trade of gold, ivory, and
slaves to the Mediterranean lands. In
350 AD one of the rulers of Axum, Aezanas,
marched to the Nile with the intention of
subduing the crumbling empire of Kush. He
found however that he had been forestalled
by the barbarian Noba, who had already
overrun the city and hinterland of Meroe and
brought its ancient dynasty to an end.
The traditions of the Pharaohs seem to
have died with the last of the Meroitic rulers
in the more southerly parts of Kush. The
next two centuries comprise a dark age from
which we have neither archaeological nor
historical evidence of any consequence. But
in the northern districts, on the frontiers of
Roman Egypt, Pharaonic traditions per¬
sisted a little longer in the successor
kingdom of Ballana, or Nobatia as it was
later to be called.
Our principal knowledge of this kingdom
comes from the opulent mound-tombs of its
rulers, in the great twin cemeteries of
Ballana and Qustul close to the present
Egyptian-Sudanese border. Here we can
find evidence for the continued worship of
the Egyptian deity Isis, and for the con¬
tinued use of some of the traditional
Pharaonic insignia by the Ballana rulers. A
short distance further north, at the fortified
citadel of Qasr Ibrim, there is also evidence
for the continued use of the Meroitic system
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Photo Alexis Vorontzoff, Unesco'© British Museum, London
of alphabetic writing, which had been
developed in the later centuries of the em¬
pire of Kush (see inside back cover).
A new beginning in Nubian history is
marked by the introduction of Christianity in
the middle of the 6th century. Ecclesiastical
historians suggest that at this time there
were three independent Nubian kingdoms:
Nobatia in the north, Makouria in the region
between the Third and Fourth Cataracts of
the Nile, and Aiwa around the junction of
the Blue and White Niles. The conversion of
all three kingdoms was effected before the
end of the 6th century, a fact which is at¬
tested archaeologically not only by the ap¬
pearance of many churches but by an abrupt
change in burial ritual all over Nubia at the
same time.
About a century later the two northern
Nubian kingdoms of Makouria and Nobatia
were consolidated under one ruler. The
royal residence was at Old Dongola, in the
territory of Makouria, but the old territory of
Nobatia retained a separate name and identi¬
ty. It was governed by a viceroy called the
Eparch of Nobatia.
Less than a century after the Christianiza-
tion of Nubia, Egypt fell to the armies of
Islam. For a long time afterward however
the bulk of the Egyptian population remain¬
ed Christian, and the indigenous Coptic
Church continued to prosper even under
Arab rulers. It was with this native Egyptian
church that the Christians of Nubia were af¬
filiated. Their bishops were appointed by the
Patriarch of Alexandria, and many of them
were of Egyptian nationality.
Almost immediately after their conquest
of Egypt the Arabs tried to add Nubia to
their domains, but two separate invasions in
642 and in 652 were successfully repulsed.
The Nubians and the rulers of Egypt then
concluded a treaty, called the Baqt, which w
guaranteed the territorial integrity and the Y
Rare sandstone head,
right, with its small
mouth, pointed face
and curly hair, is a
funerary object
produced in Nubia
during the so-called
"Meroitic" period
which takes its name
from Meroë, the
capital of the Nubian
Kushite kingdom for
some six centuries
until the 4th century
AD. Almost life size,
it was discovered in a
child's grave at Amir
Abdallah by a
Franco-Sudanese
archaeological
expedition.
The production of highly distinctive
forms of decorated pottery was
among the remarkable
achievements of Nubia during the
Meroitic period. This red brown
earthenware pot with black and
white decoration (2nd to 3rd
century AD) was unearthed at
Karanog (Egyptian Nubia). The
stylized leafy vine branches
encircling its shoulder indicate that
it was produced by a school of
artists whose trade-mark was the
vine motif. Its body is adorned with
antelopes, plants and birds. Other
works by the same artist, dubbed
the "Antelope Painter", have been
identified.
Photo © Egyptian Antiquities Service, Cairo
The sides of this delicate glass
vessel (1st-2nd century AD) are
less than a millimetre thick.
Glass bottles, flasks and beakers
found in the graves of
Meroitic Nubians are thought
to have been largely imported from
Egypt or even further afield.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Bronze oil lamp with horse's
head handle, below, was found
in a grave at the fortress of Qasr
Ibrim during the excavation
campaign of 1961-1962. Probably
dating from the 2nd or 3rd
century AD, it reflects
Hellenistic influences but
is thought to have been
produced in Nubia.
Photo A. Vorontzoff, Unesco © British Museum, London
Photo © Egyptian Antiquities Service, Cairo Photo © Egyptian Museum, Cairo.
Silver crown and bronze oil lamp in the form of a man's head (above) together with
the remarkable wooden chest with ivory inlays (below) are part of a sensationally rich
find made over forty years ago in a Nile-side royal cemetery at Ballana. They date from
the 4th-5th century when Ballana was the centre of a kingdom which flourished in
northern Nubia on the frontier of Roman Egypt. Fastened to the circlet of the crown,
which is richly encrusted with semi-precious stones and glass, are five winged uraei
which show how ancient Pharaonic traditions had survived into a period when
Hellenistic and Byzantine influence was very strong in Nubia. The chest (late 4th
century) has the shape of a multi-storied house. Its ivory panels are incised with Greek
and Egyptian gods including Pan, Zeus, and the Egyptian god Bes.
independent sovereignty of Nubia for cen¬
turies to come.
Protected by the Baqt treaty, and revitaliz¬
ed by zeal for its new Christian faith. Nubia
in the Middle Ages entered a second golden
age of peace and prosperity. Religious art,
architecture, and literature flourished, ex¬
hibiting a combination of Coptic and Byzan¬
tine influences as well as some strictly in¬
digenous elements. The court at Dongola
was organized along Byzantine lines, as
were the legal institutions of the northern
Nubian kingdom.
Both Makouria and Aiwa evidently pro¬
spered from the supply of African goods to
the Islamic empires along the Mediterranean
littoral.
The 200-year episode of the Crusades
gave rise to a new species of military
feudalism whose effects were felt alike in
Europe, in the Near East, and in north
Africa. In Egypt this tendency culminated in
1250 in the establishment of the dynastic
quarrels which weakened and undermined
the Christian kingdoms, and provided a fer¬
tile field for Mameluke intervention.
A final blow was dealt to the medieval
monarchies by the migration into the Sudan
of a great many Arab nomads who had been
displaced from Egypt by the harshly
repressive measures of the Mamelukes. At
first they moved southward through the Red
Sea hills, but gradually they spread
westward to the Nile Valley and beyond,
overrunning and destroying the already
weakened Christian monarchies. In
Makouria and in Aiwa the last vestiges both
of central authority and of the organized
practice of Christianity died out around 1500
AD.
We know little about events in Nubia dur¬
ing the centuries following the destruction
of the medieval kingdoms. It is evident
however that the disappearance of an
organized faith left a fertile ground of activi¬
ty for wandering Islamic teachers and
mystics, for within a matter of two or three
centuries the whole of the northern Sudan
was converted to the faith of Islam.
When the Pasha Mohammed Ali, founder
of the modern Egyptian state, conquered
the Sudan in 1821, he found the whole
country united in the Islamic faith although
politically it was divided into more than a
dozen petty principalities.
William Y. Adams.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
THE NUBIAN CORRIDOR
IN AFRICAN HISTORY
Over the last 3,000 years the Nubians have
been participants in each of the major civiliz¬
ing waves that have swept along the north
African shore: the ancient Egyptian, the
Classical, the medieval Christian, and the
Islamic. They have moreover been stead¬
fastly loyal to each. Both the traditions of
the Pharaohs and those of medieval Chris¬
tianity lasted longer in Nubia than in Egypt
itself, and today the Nubian people are
famous for their Islamic piety.
Nubia was and is poor in agrarian
resources. Its agricultural economy could do
little more than feed its own rather limited
population. The basis of Nubian prosperity,
like that of all later African civilizations and
empires, was the supply of various kinds of
African exotica that were always coveted by
the peoples of the Mediterranean littoral. In
this category were gold, tropical animal
skins, ostrich feathers, ivory, ebony wood,
incense, and dark-skinned slaves.
Nubia was, in short, the first and most en¬
during of the great African trading empires.
Its prosperity waxed and waned partly in
response to the demand for exotic luxuries
by the Mediterranean peoples.
For almost 3,000 years, from the dawn of
history until the last centuries BC, the Nile
corridor represented the only safe avenue of
commerce across the Saharan barrier, link¬
ing the African coast with the Mediterra¬
nean coast. So long as that was true the Nu¬
bians, as occupants of the corridor, enjoyed
a monopoly on the trade of African goods to
the north. The Nile monopoly was however
threatened eventually by the opening of
maritime commerce in the Red Sea.
A short time later the privileged position
of Nubia was further undermined by the in¬
troduction of the camel and the develop¬
ment of trans-Saharan caravan trade. Gold,
ivory, and slaves now flowed in increasing
quantities across the desert to the port cities
of north-west Africa. In the interior, new
African civilizations and empires Ghana,
Mali, Songhai, and Kanem-Bornuarose as
a direct consequence of this trade. But the
final coup de grace to Nubian prosperity and
to the strategic importance of the middle
Nile Valley was dealt by the opening of Euro¬
pean maritime trade with the west African
and Guinea coasts, beginning with the Por¬
tuguese explorations of the 15th century.
The long and sometimes hazardous Nile cor¬
ridor route was no longer an effective com¬
petitor with the European sea routes, and
Nubia at the end of the Middle Ages subsid¬
ed at last into a geopolitical backwater.
W. Y. A.
Sandstone relief from Christian Nubia, below, was carved in the
early 7th century as part of a frieze in the cathedral at Faras
where it was discovered by the Polish Archaeological Expedition
(see page 39). The bird with its head turned was adopted from
Egypt, where it was a frequent motif in early Christian iconography.
Photo © Friedrich Hinket, German Democratic Republic. National Museum, Warsaw
A falcon-headed god was worshipped throughout Egypt in
prehistoric times, and as Horus, the son of Osiris and his sister-
wife Isis, later became part of the Osiris cult. In this Coptic
sandstone carving (41 cm high), executed as late as the 5th-7th
century AD in Egypt, Horus is shown harpooning Seth, the
murderer of Osiris, who has assumed the form of a crocodile.
Photo Chuzeville© Louvre Museum, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The International
Nubian
Campaign
Kertassi-Taffa Czechoslovakia .
Beit el Wali Switzerland and U. S.A. a\
Kalabsha Italy i
0 200 400km
Caircn
> Luxor \ ^.
T Aswan
*?J
Egypt
Sudan
J Khartoum
Sabagura Italy
\ Wadi Allaqi USSR
Egypt
Sudan
Semna South U.S.A. a
Melik en Nasir Fed. Rep. Germany
Sonqi Italy
30
Akasha Switzerland
Kulubnarti U.S.A.
Dal Cataract
Tomas France ,
a Amada //fed1. flep. Germany
Korosko-Qasr Ibrim Italy
Qasr Ibrim United Kingdom
Faras South. Photo © Rex Keating, Paris
Abdallah Nirqi Netherlands and Hungary U Gebe| Adda Egypt and U.S.A.
Ballana Egypt and U.S.A./^Qu^ Egypt
Qasr el Wizz U.S.A. a,
Faras Poland i
Aksha France and Argentina a/
Serra West Scandinavia a,
Debeira West Ghana a
Argin S/ja/h a
Dabarosa U.S.A. a
Buhen-Kor United Kingdom
. Ukma Switzerland
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Kom Ombo plain.
Photo - Philip E.L. Smith, Montreal
¿*m^ ^> f ~ ti»!r " ' .Z?»--
Kertassi. Photo © The Czechoslovak Institute of Egyptology
S/tes excavated
Debeira Wast. Photo © Rex Keating, Paris
In the twenty years that have elapsed since the day in
March 1960 when the Director-General of Unesco
launched an appeal for an international campaign to save
the monuments and sites of Nubia, the area now covered
by the waters of the Nile has been the scene of the
greatest archaeological "dig" in history. So rich were the
findings that it will be many years before the full
historical, cultural and anthropological value of the
campaign is comprehensively assessed. On the following
pages, the Unesco Courier presents a series of excerpts
from reports by the various expeditions. For reasons of
space these excerpts are necessarily brief and selective.
Nevertheless, they afford us a glimpse of the major
achievements of the dedicated groups of men and women
from many countries who, for two decades and often
under difficult conditions, raced against time to save from
oblivion a priceless portion of the cultural heritage of
Nubia and the world.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Highlights of
the archaeological
expeditions
EXPEDITION: UNIVERSITY OF
CAIRO
Chronological summary
NUBIA BC EGYPT
Emergence of
"A-Group" culture
3000 Early Dynastic Period
( 1st and 2nd Dynasties)
Royal burials at Saqqara
2500
Old Kingdom
(3rd to 6th Dynasties)
Great Pyramid at Giza
End of "A-Group"
Emergence of
"C-Group" culture
1st Intermediate
Period
(7th to 10th Dynasties)
The Egyptian fortresses
in Nubia
2000
Middle Kingdom
(11th to 12th Dynasties)
Amenemhet
2nd Intermediate
Period
(13th to 17th Dynasties)
The Hyksos in Egypt
"C-Group" people
culturally absorbed
by Egypt
1500 New Kingdom
(18th to 20th Dynasties)
Amenophis III
Ramses II
1000
Late Period
(21st to 31st Dynasties)
Taharqa (25th
"Ethiopian" Dynasty)
The Meroitic Kingdom 500
AD
Graeco-Roman Period
Alexander the Great
and the Ptolemies
The Romans in Egypt
(3rd to 6th centuries)
Break up of the Meroitic
Kingdom
"X-Group" culture
in Nubia
500
The Arabs in Egypt
The Christian kingdoms
of Nubia
Faras capital of Nobatia 1000
Installation of Timothy,
one of the last
Nubian bishops at
Qasr Ibrim
SITE: ANIBA
REPORTER: ABD-EL-MONEIM ABU
BAKR
The tomb of Pennut
DURING the 1960-61 and 1961-62 seasons the
University of Cairo expedition carried out excava¬
tions in the Aniba region. The expedition record¬
ed all the inscriptions in the tomb of Pennut,
governor of Miarn (the ancient name of the Aniba
district) during the reign of Ramses VI, prior to
the removal of the tomb and its reconstruction
near the new site of the temple of Amada. The ex¬
pedition also attempted, unfortunately without
success, to find the temple of the god Horus
which was known to have existed in Miam in an¬
cient times but of which all trace had been lost.
A thousand burials
The expedition also excavated a thirteen-
kilometre-long stretch of the west bank of the
Nile, on either side of Pennut's tomb, discovering
over a thousand tombs in two distinct groupings.
The necropolis of Nagaa el-Tahouna consisted of
A-Group tombs. The bodies uncovered were sur¬
rounded by Kerma type terra-cotta vases,
necklaces and scarabs. These findings indicate
that the population of Aniba of the period had
close links with the Hyksos kings of the Nile
Delta. One of the scarabs was inscribed with the
name of the Hyksos king Apophis who sought to
form an alliance with the Nubians against the
threat from the princes of Thebes.
The second group of tombs, situated much closer
to Aniba, belongs to the second Meroitic period.
The most important find was a chest whose four
side surfaces are incrusted with ivory representa¬
tions of the goddess Hathor and the god Bes.
Ivory figures of Hathor and Bes, from a Meroitic chest.
Photo © Egyptian Antiquities Service, Cairo
SUDAN ANTIQUITIES SERVICE
AERIAL PHOTOGRAPHIC SURVEY
ARCHAEOLOGICAL SURVEY
SUPPLEMENTARY EXCAVATIONS
AT the outset of the Nubian campaign the situation
in Sudanese Nubia was that there had been no
previous surveys which could provide a data base
comparable in any way to that available in Egypt.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Sudan Antiquities Services therefore organiz¬
ed both an aerial and a ground survey of
Sudanese Nubia from Faras to Dal. Concessions
in the area were offered to foreign expeditions
and these were backed up by supplementary ex¬
cavations by the Sudan Antiquities Service at
sites not taken up. The achievement of the
surveys was staggering. In 1959, only ten sites in
the area had been excavated, but by the time the
surveys were completed, in 1969, more than a
thousand sites had been identified. The aerial
survey offered some unexpected finds, including
the natural rock barrier across the Nile at Semna,
where traces were discovered of a barrage con¬
structed by Egyptian engineers thirty-nine centu¬
ries ago. (See also article page 16).
EXPEDITION:
SITES:
FRENCH INSTITUTE
OF ORIENTAL
ARCHAEOLOGY
WADI ES SEBUA TO
SAYALA
REPORTER: FRANÇOIS DAUMAS
THE temple of Ramses II at Wadi es Sebua was the
first site excavated and the approach road, or
"dromos", to the temple produced an unusual
find. This was a sort of portable bronze stove,
discovered in a complex of buildings at the side of
the dromos, which bore what seemed to be the
emblem of Ramses II.
A strange sacrifice
The expedition also examined a nearby quarry
from which blocks of stone for the construction
of the temple had been extracted. Near the top of
the quarry a cavity was discovered, which must
have been used as a tomb since it had a carefully
carved door. A 19th dynasty plate and a gourd as
well as portions of goat's meat, goose and goose
eggs had been placed inside. This curious find is
thought to be the remains of a sacrifice made to
mark the opening of the quarry.
A prehistoric site
Excavation of the temple of Ramses itself reveal¬
ed that it was built on a site that had been oc¬
cupied in prehistoric times. In a small valley near¬
by a number of unusually fine rock carvings of
animals were found. It was not possible to date
them exactly.
A thirty-nine-century-old barrage.
Photo © Sudan Government Aerial Survey
Drawing Lenthéric © F. Daumas, France
Ramses offers a bouquet to St. Peter
A Coptic church had been constructed inside the
temple of Ramses and one section of this church
presented an astonishing spectacle. The Christian
artists had plastered over the Egyptian reliefs and
at one spot had painted a representation of
St. Peter. Over the years part of the plaster fell
away revealing the ancient Egyptian reliefs and
we were treated to the sight of Ramses II offering
a bouquet to... St. Peter!
Other paintings, such as that of an angel holding
in her arms a mummy, which probably
represented the soul of a deceased person por¬
trayed at one side, give us a better understanding
of Coptic painting.
A C-Group village
On a cliff overlooking the Nile a Nubian C-Group
village was discovered dating back to the 18th
century BC. It was enclosed with a dry stone wall
with a fortified gateway on the more vulnerable
east side. Excavation brought to light some Nu¬
bian pottery and a number of bone tools and wea¬
pons.
EXPEDITION: ARCHAEOLOGICAL
MISSION OF THE
HENRY M.
BLACKMER
FOUNDATION AND
THE CENTRE OF
ORIENTAL STUDIES
ON THE UNIVERSITY
OF GENEVA
SITES: AKASHA REGION
REPORTER: CHARLES MAYSTRE
THE mission had the good fortune to find a
palaeolithic site which yielded a fine selection of
stone tools comparable to those of the Levalloi-
sian stone industry. Over 9,000 neolithic artefacts
were also found. The tools were of the "Early
Khartoum" type and the potsherds showed a
variety of decorative styles.
Over two hundred Kerma tombs
Another exciting discovery was that of a
cemetery containing more than two hundred
tombs dating from the three periods of the so-
called "Kerma" civilization (about 2500 to 1500
BC). Although the tombs had been plundered
once, considerable finds were made including
some fine tulip-shaped, black-bordered, red
vases.
A Meroitic vase with ten left eyes
The area appears to have been virtually abandon¬
ed during the New Kingdom period, but in the
Meroitic era it was occupied again as the many
cemeteries of the period attest. These tombs
were later emptied and re-used for Christian
burials, but a number of Meroitic objects of quali¬
ty survived, including a fine terracotta vase
curiously decorated with a ring of ten left eyes.
Evidence of the Christian era
Four groups of dwellings, three churches, a small
fort, the fortified surround of the church of
Kageiras and a large number of Christian
cemeteries and re-used tombs from earlier eras in¬
dicate that the region was comparatively heavily
populated during the Christian era (up to 1500
AD).
Meroitic vase with ten eyes.
Photo © C Maystre, Switzerland
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
EXPEDITION: USSR ACADEMY OF
SCIENCES
SITES: DAKKA REGION,
WADI ALLAQI
REPORTER: BORIS PIOTROVSKY
WORK in the Dakka area involved the exploration of
ancient settlements and burial grounds and
monuments along the bank of the river. Important
collections of palaeolithic tools were made, a
large number of predynastic rock carvings were
found and Ancient and New Kingdom graves
were investigated.
Wadi Allaqi, the golden road
The most interesting phase, however, was the in¬
vestigation of Wadi Allaqi, one of the largest
wadis in Nubia, through which led the road to the
ancient gold mines of Nubia. Even before pro¬
specting for gold in Nubia began in the time of the
New Kingdom the Pharaohs of the Sixth Dynasty
had sent caravans along the Wadi Allaqi in search
of stone, ebony, ivory and panther skins. These
expeditions are described in detail in a number of
inscriptions along the route. We came by chance
across an inscription by a "chief of caravan", the
Prince Hunes, a noble court official of the Sixth
Dynasty whose tomb at Aswan is well known.
Even more surprising was the discovery of a short
inscription by another famous court official. Uni,
who travelled many times to Nubia. Most of the
two hundred inscriptions that we discovered,
however, date from the Eighteenth and Nine¬
teenth Dynasties, at a period when Nubia became
the main supplier of gold for Egypt. We now
know, for example, that some of the objects
found in the tomb of Tutankhamun were made of
gold from Nubia.
The well of Ramses, the beloved of Amon
One of the major problems facing these caravans
was the lack of water along the Wadi. In 1842, in
the ruins of an ancient fortress at Kubban, at the
mouth of Wadi Allaqi, the French archaeologist
Prisse d'Avennes found a large stela depicting
Ramses II bringing offerings to the god Horus "of
the land of Bak" and to Min "who dwelt in the
rocks". The extensive text tells how the Pharaoh
was concerned about the lack of water along the
road leading to the lands rich in gold.
Although his father had tried in vain to find water,
Ramses ordered the governor of the region to
pursue the search. At last water was found and a
well was dug and named after the Pharaoh. When
found by Prisse d'Avennes, however, the lower
part of the inscription was broken off precisely at
the point at which the name of the well was writ¬
ten: "Ramses, the beloved of Amon, valiant...".
For years Egyptologists puzzled over the problem
of what the end of the phrase could be and the
precise location of the well.
Our expedition, too, was anxious to solve the rid¬
dle of the missing text and to locate the well and
our hopes were pinned on a site at which many in¬
scriptions had been found and which was known
as "Bir-al-Askari", the soldier's well. Indeed,
there were signs of excavations there, but our
guide assured us that these were the work of
British soldiers who had established a military
camp there during the last century and had
themselves dug in search of water.
On the very last day of our stay at Bir-al-Askari,
on the site of the old military camp, we found
fragments of stone, bearing hieroglyphs, which
when pieced together were found to form a stela
depicting Ramses making a sacrifice to the god
Min. At first it seemed of little interest as the
hieroglyphs were so damaged that they were im¬
possible to decipher. Then we noticed that a
single phrase remained undamaged. It read: "The
well of Ramses, the beloved of Amon, valiant in
life". We had found the stela that marked the
position of the well and the part of the inscription
missing from the stela found by Prisse d'Avennes
at the Kubban fortress. Thus was solved a
120-year-old mystery. g
Ramses' well, the completed stela.
Drawing £> B. Piotrovsky, USSR
EXPEDITION: INDIA
SITES: AFYA, TOMAS
REPORTER: B.B. LAL
EXPLORATION of the terraces of the Nile around
Afya and Tomas brought to light Middle and Late
Stone Age tools. These are believed to be the first
Stone Age tools to be discovered in the Afya-
Tomas region.
Carbon-dating of the A-Group
The A-Group Culture of Nubia had generally been
thought to be contemporary with the late pre-
Dynastic and Early Dynastic Cultures of Middle
and Upper Egypt, although this was still a matter
of debate. The Indian work would appear finally
to have settled the issue once and for all since it
provided three 14C dates which, after Masca-
correction, show a clear range from" 3160 BC to
2985 BC. ;
A link between Nubia and India?
Of no less interest was the "C-Group" cemetery,
ascribable broadly to the first half of the second
millennium BC. The dead were buried in round-
ended oblong pits measuring about 1.5 to 2
metres in length, about 1 metre in width and 1 to
1 .5 metres in depth, with the knees drawn up and
usually resting on the right side with the head
towards the south-east. After burial, a stone-
circle often with a tumulus, was raised around the
grave. Amongst the objects recovered from the
graves were: a quartz dish with kohl-marks, a
wooden mirror-handle and a lot of pot¬
tery black-and-red, red, and buff wares in
a variety of shapes and designs. Particularly
pleasing was a bowl with a white-filled incised
design depicting a series of hand-in-hand
dancers. Certain similarities were detected bet¬
ween these C-Group graves and the megaliths of
South India.
Colour page right
Fragile plaster funerary masks
preserve the features of three
persons who were buried some
4,000 years ago in Nubia. They have
been reconstituted from fragments
which the French Archaeological
Mission to Sudanese Nubia found
in a necropolis near the fortress of
Mirgissa on the Second Cataract of
the Nile. The painted masks were
made from a mould taken when the
dead face had been bandaged for
mummification.
Photos © André Vila. Franco-Sudanese Archaelogical Mission
Central colour pages
The colossal seated statues of
Ramses II in front of the main
temple of Abu Simbel overlook the
Nile from the new site to which
they were removed during the 1960s
in a stupendous feat of engineering
lasting four and a half years.
Photo © Fred J. Maroon, New York
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
'-»tor
ät^Jb
»A<
is
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
T*'
I I
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
F
It'
J-
rjL?
/
e-
I
L^l
I .
wt
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Colour page
"A landmark in the history of
Byzantine art" is how Professor
Michalowski, leader of the Polish
expedition, describes the gallery of
Christian frescoes discovered in the
ancient cathedral of Faras, in
Sudanese Nubia (see text this
page). Far left, the martyr
Damienne was the daughter of the
governor of a province of the Nile
delta and a Christian convert. She
was martyred in 284 during
Diocletian's persecutions. The
fresco dates from the end of the
10th century. Left, the Apostle
Peter stands behind the Nubian
Coptic bishop Petros, his hands
placed protectively on his
shoulders. Petros was bishop of
Faras from 974 to 999. The painting
dates from the same period.
Bottom photo, dating from the
early 11th century, this fresco
depicts Marianos, bishop of Faras
from 1000 to 1036, beside the
Madonna and Child. All these
frescoes are now in the National
Museum, Warsaw.
Photo Georg Gerster © Rapho, Paris
Photos © Interpress. National Museum, Warsaw
EXPEDITION: POLISH CENTRE FOR
MEDITERRANEAN
ARCHAEOLOGY
SITE: FARAS
REPORTER: K. MICHALOWSKI
The church under the sand
THE most important contribution of Polish
archaeology to the Nubian campaign was
incontestably the discovery of Faras in Sudanese
Nubia. There, among a whole complex of sacred
and profane buildings buried in the sand, under
the walls of an Arab citadel, the expedition
uncovered an imposing early Christian church the
walls of which were decorated with more than
120 frescoes in excellent condition. Today Faras
lies some forty metres beneath the waters of the
Nile, but in the 7th century it was the capital of
northern Nubia. During three years of excavations
the Polish expedition succeeded in resuscitating a
hitherto unknown chapter of the history of early
Christian Nubia and a large portion of its art.
Saint Anne enjoins silence
Among the most famous works discovered are a
head of Saint Anne with a finger to her lips in the
sign for silence, the Black bishop Petros under the
protection of the Apostle Peter, the olive-skinned
bishop Marianos, the dark-complexioned Queen-
mother Martha, and a vast Nativity scene which
includes the shepherds and the Three Wise Men.
It would be impossible to list all the objects such
as the splendid 11th century glass chalice found
during the excavations which covered not only
the great church but also a whole complex of
buildings including an eparch's palace, two
monasteries and a second church.
A race against time
The excavations at Faras were a race against
time. In the course of four seasons, each lasting
five to six months, the expedition succeeded in
salvaging the most important objects, not only
the frescoes of the church, which were taken
down and packed in cases, but also the bronzes,
the ceramics, the inscriptions and the tombs of
the bishops complete with their skeletons. The list
of their names which was found on the walls of
the church constitutes one of the original
documents of Christianity in Nubia. Hardly had
the expedition finished nailing up the cases for
removal when the water of the Nile reached the
level of the hill on which the excavations had
taken place. Some months later, the tops of a few
palm trees emerging from the waters were all that
remained to mark the spot where Faras had once
stood.
EXPEDITION: THE ARGENTINE
EXPEDITION TO
NUBIA
SITE: AKSHA
REPORTER: A. ROSENWASSER
SINCE 1961, Argentina has sent several teams of
archaeologists to work in collaboration with
French archaeologists in Sudanese Nubia. These
teams cleared the temple of Aksha and removed a
number of important reliefs which are now in
Khartoum.
Royal son of Kush
During the 1962-63 season, the Argentine mission
discovered five chapels built by the Pharaoh Seti
I, father of Ramses II and part of a door to a
chapel dedicated to Heqanakht, who was Nubian
viceroy under Ramses II. On the door the viceroy
is seen in ceremonial dress with the inscription
"Heqanakht, Royal Son of Kush".
M
Saint Anne, Faras
Photo K. Michalowski,
National Museum, Warsaw
Heqanakht, Royal Son of Kush, Aksha.
Photo © A. Rosenwasser, Argentina
Removal of fresco at Faras. Photo © Rex Keating, Pans
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
EXPEDITION:
SITES:
CANADA
THE KOM OMBO
PLAIN
REPORTER: PHILIP E. SMITH
The Kom Ombo Plain
THE Canadian Expedition to Nubia chose to do
research not in the reservoir area itself but about
50 kilometres downstream from the Aswan High
Dam, on the Kom Ombo Plain. This was because
the majority of the Egyptian Nubians were shortly
to be resettled on reclaimed lands around Kom
Ombo, the ground levelling had already begun
and prehistoric sites were liable to be destroyed.
In the 1920s a local French engineer, Edmond
Vignard, had published several reports on
prehistoric sites in the area; as late as 1962 these
reports provided virtually all our knowledge of the
Upper Palaeolithic period in Egypt. Palaeolithic
peoples very likely lived in the area for several
hundred thousand years, but little evidence has
been preserved in situ until roughly 15000 BC.
Five prehistoric cultures
Vignard had identified a culture he named the
Sebilian with a peculiar style of stone tools, and
he suspected the presence of others. There were
in reality at least five "cultures" (as defined by
their stone tools) in existence around Kom Ombo
between ca. 15000 and 9000 BC. We were able to
salvage some of their campsites, both surface and
subsurface and to produce the first radiocarbon
dates for the Palaeolithic of Egypt.
Briefly, our reconstruction of human occupation
of the Plain is as follows. Around 15000 BC there
was a group making flint tools of a type called
"Halfan" in Nubia, and apparently grinding some
plant foods as well as hunting and fishing. This
was followed between 13000 to 12000 by two
newly defined and distinct groups: the Silsilian,
which emphasized small, even microlithic stone
tools, and the Sebekian whose tools were mainly
on long, narrow blades. About 11000 BC we find
a fourth industry which we called the Menchian
which has many heavy flake tools especially
scrapers, and a considerable number of sand¬
stone grinding slabs which probably reflect food-
preparation activities. Finally, from roughly 11000
BC onward there is Vignard's Sebilian, which
seems to have continued into early Holocene
times.
The picture we obtain during these six millennia is
of small bands of people, probably totalling
several hundred at any one time, who frequented
the Kom Ombo Plain and adjacent zones during
all seasons of the year. They were essentially
hunters.
A unique style of rock art
We also recorded a series of rock drawings of wild
animals engraved on the cliffs at the northern end
of the Plain. These may reflect the activities of
local hunters in the millennia before food produc¬
tion reached Egypt after (presumably) 6000 BC.
Although their precise age is uncertain the art
style seems unique in the Nile Valley.
The results of our research on the Kom Ombo
Plain should of course be seen in the context of
the revised view of prehistoric life in the Nile
Valley of both Egypt and the Sudan that has
become accepted in the past twenty years. The
Valley is now known to have been in late
Palaeolithic times not a thinly-inhabited, isolated
and impoverished culture area but one where
many different groups of people lived and in¬
teracted in what at the time was one of the
world's most congenial environments.
The reconstruction we have been able to make
can be seen as a microcosm of how many similar
pre-agricultural peoples must have lived in Nubia
and Upper and Lower Egypt at this time and an il¬
lustration of how they adapted themselves to the
peculiar conditions of the Nilotic environment and
its adjacent hills and desert fringes.
Liturgical text fragment, Sunnarti.
Photo © E. Dinkier, Heidelberg
EXPEDITION: GERMAN
ARCHAEOLOGICAL
INSTITUTE, FEDERAL
REPUBLIC OF
GERMANY
SITES: KULB, ISLANDS OF
SUNNARTI,
TURMUKI AND
TANGUR
REPORTER: ERICH DINKLER
THE Institute carried out excavations on the three
islands of the Batn el Haggar, between the Se¬
cond Cataract and Akasha, as well as at Kulb,
some three kilometres to the west of Akasha on
the west bank of the Nile.
Three village churches
Three churches were excavated, each of which at
one time served a small village and could hold no
more than twenty to twenty-five people. The best
preserved church was that found on the island of
Sunnarti. The altar was still standing with its mar¬
ble top. The central part of the church was
dominated by the pulpit. On the west side were
separate entrances for men and women. This
church dated from the 12th or 13th century.
Three fortified settlements were also excavated
and once again the most impressive fortifications
were those on Sunnarti. Constructed in the form
of a triangle in natural stone, they were adapted
to the topography of the ground and enclosed a
group of some fifteen dwellings and enough open
space for some cattle.
The fortified village of Kulb
The fortified village of Kulb was particularly in¬
teresting and dates probably from the 8th cen¬
tury. The encircling wall, however, is probably of
later construction. In many of the dwellings
fragments of objects marked with the name
Michael or with monograms representing this
name, all in Greek lettering, were found. These
fragments had holes pierced through them,
presumably so that they could be hung on the
walls. In view of the large number of such graffiti
found it would seem that the inhabitants of the
village knew the Greek alphabet.
The oldest liturgical text
Perhaps the most important find of all was that of
a small piece of parchment lying in the sand on
the floor of the church of Sunnarti. It contained
the oldest liturgical text of the Nubian Church so
far known. On one side was carefully written out,
in red and black ink, the text of a Greek
eucharistie prayer.
EXPEDITIONS: UNIVERSITY OF
TURIN
UNIVERSITY OF
MILAN
UNIVERSITY OF
ROME
SITES: DEHMIT,
KALABSHA,
IKHMINDI,
MAHARRAQA,
KUBBAN,
SABAGURA, TAMIT,
SONQI
REPORTER: SERGIO DONADONI
THE Italian contribution to the Nubian campaign
was a three-pronged effort: the University of
Turin investigated sites at Dehmit and Kalabsha,
the University of Milan at Ikhmindi, Maharraqa,
Kubban and Sabagura, and the University of
Rome at Tamit and Sonqi.
An ensemble of local cultures
Research was concerned less with Egyptian anti¬
quities on Nubian soil (although this was an
aspect of the work at Dehmit and Kubban) than
with remains and vestiges that enabled typical
local cultures to be identified. These were often
ensembles of cultures that had no writing and
could speak to us only through their artefacts. In
a cemetery at Tamit, for example, we came
across vestiges of the oldest period, contem¬
porary with the Egyptian predynastic and early
dynastic period; and the rock drawings and pot¬
tery found at Sabagura and Kubban tell us of the
pastoral populations of the Middle Kingdom
period.
An independent Nubia
But the most successful research was perhaps
that relating to a later period. The identification at
Maharraqa of a Meroitic necropolis, right on the
frontier between the Roman world and the ter¬
ritories of the Nubian kings whose capital was in
far distant Meroe, indicates how far to the north
this African culture imposed the stamp of its per¬
sonality.
At Ikhmindi we had the good fortune to discover
an inscription which was virtually contemporary
with the introduction of Christianity into the
region on the basis of which it was possible to
identify a certain form of Christian urbanism at
Ikhmindi, Sabagura and Kalabsha.
We found other important Christian monuments
dating from the zenith of independent Nubia,
when for the first time inscriptions were written in
the language of the country rather than in the
languages of neighbouring countries: a sanctuary
complex at Tamit and a small cemetery church at
Sonqi have provided a series of paintings, inscrip¬
tions and other evidence of a social and cultural
life linked with and just as richly varied as that of
the nearby metropolis of Faras.
Sudanese workers at Argin
Photo © M. Llongueras-Campana
40
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
EXPEDITION: INSTITUTE FOR
EGYPTOLOGY OF
HUMBOLDT
UNIVERSITY, EAST
BERLIN, GERMAN
DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC
SITES: FARAS TO DAL
(WEST BANK), 2nd
CATARACT TO DAL
(EAST BANK)
REPORTER.' FRITZ HINTZE
600 rock inscriptions
and 750 groups of rock drawings
TWO working groups from the expedition under¬
took the huge task of collecting all the rock in¬
scriptions and rock drawings in Sudanese Nubia
from the Second Cataract to Dal, on the east
bank of the Nile, and from Faras to Dal, on the
west bank, excluding, of course, those on the
concessions of other expeditions.
All the drawings and inscriptions discovered were
copied and photographed and latex squeezes
were made of the more important ones. For this
purpose a new technique of coloured latex
squeezes was developed. Work continued over
three seasons and the material collected and
documented included almost 600 rock inscrip¬
tions and over 100 rock picture sites with 750
groups of pictures.
The distribution of the rock inscriptions is signifi¬
cant. North of Semna, which was once the
southern boundary of the Middle Kingdom of an¬
cient Egypt, most of the inscriptions date from
the Middle Kingdom period; but south of Semna
all the inscriptions, with the exception of three
Old Kingdom inscriptions from a site near the Dal
Cataract, are from the New Kingdom period. The
three exceptions are the most southerly Old
Kingdom rock inscriptions discovered in situ up to
now. They were made by scribes and overseers of
prospectors searching for minerals and gold in the
mountains. The expedition also recorded the
' famous Nile level marks at Semna and Kumma.
The rock drawings cover the time span from
prehistory to the Middle Ages of our era. Approx¬
imately ten per cent are pictures of wild animals
such as elephants, giraffes, antelopes, gazelles
and ostriches. Sixty per cent show domestic
animals and the majority of these are cattle, but
horses, camels, sheep, goats and dogs are also
depicted; the remaining thirty per cent portray
varied scenes such as men hunting, riding horses
or camels, women dancing, and boats. There are
many symbolic signs whose meaning is not easy
to determine.
The stela of Prince Amenemhet.
Photo © T. Säve-Söderbergh, Uppsala
EXPEDITION: SCANDINAVIAN
JOINT EXPEDITION
TO SUDANESE NUBIA
SITES: EAST BANK OF THE
NILE FROM FARAS
TO GEMAI
REPORTER: TORGNY
SÄVE-SÖDERBERG
THE expedition, a joint effort of the four Scandina¬
vian countries, Denmark, Finland, Norway and
Sweden, worked in the northernmost part of the
Sudan during the four winters of 1961-1964 and
made a complete archaeological investigation of
the east bank of the Nile from Faras on the Egyp¬
tian border to Gemai in the region of the 2nd
Cataract, a distance of some sixty kilometres. The
number of registered sites totalled about 490 and
they represented the whole development from the
earliest Stone Age to the Middle Ages. Practically
all these sites were previously unknown. Some
4,200 tombs were excavated, five churches and
some fortified areas. Approximately 2,600 rock
drawings were photographed, mapped in detail
and documented. The expedition recovered some
3,000 more or less complete New Kingdom
vessels, 6,000 fragments of textiles and
osteological material from 1,500 individuals.
The stela of prince Amenemhet
A rich cemetery of 692 tombs was found at
Fadrus in the district of Debeira. The assumption
that these tombs belonged to Egyptianized Nu¬
bians is supported by the fact that nearby is the
tomb of Djehuti-hotep, Prince of Teh-khet
(Debeira) who also had the Nubian name of Pait-
sy. From his titles it is clear that Djehuti-hotep had
been educated at the Egyptian court.
The expedition excavated the tomb of his brother
Amenemhet which lay on the west bank of the
Nile. Amenemhet was first an official in the Egyp¬
tian administration and then succeeded his
brother as Prince of Teh-khet. In the cult chamber
of his tomb the expedition found a magnificent
stela with a long hieroglyphic text and pictures of
Amenemhet, his wife and his parents.
Human remains
A large collection of skeletal remains, represen¬
ting 1,546 individuals, ranging in date from the
A-Group to the end of the Christian period (1500
AD), was submitted to computer analysis. The
age distribution shows that the Nubian population
as a rule died at an early age. In the A-Group and
the X-Group mortality frequency is highest in the
20 to 25 age group, while in the other groups it is
highest in the 35 to 50 age group. An analysis of
various anthropometric and non-metric data
seems to indicate that a change of population
took place in the Late Nubian period in the transi¬
tion from the Meroitic culture to the X-Group
culture. The immigrating X-Group was not ex¬
ceedingly different from the Meroitic series but
had distinct differences from the earlier C-Group.
EXPEDITION: THE EGYPT
EXPLORATION
SOCIETY OF LONDON
SITE: QASR IBRIM
REPORTERS: J.M. PLUMLEY AND
R.D. ANDERSON
The fortress site of Qasr Ibrim
THE project that proved rewarding beyond all ex¬
pectations was the excavation of the fortress hill
site of Qasr Ibrim. Excavations have shown that
the site has a long history of human occupation,
reaching back at least to the early New Kingdom,
if not earlier, and continuing in almost unbroken
sequence until 1812 AD, when the place was
finally abandoned. Since the rising of the waters
of the lake the site has become an island, and suf¬
ficient areas remain to warrant further excava¬
tions.
The fortifications that were once so impressive a
feature of the site have been rebuilt many times.
The date of the mud-brick bastion, discovered in
1978, is not yet known, but the earliest con¬
tinuous girdle wall may well have been built in
Meroitic or Ptolemaic times, and was rebuilt and
strengthened probably by the Roman governor
Petronius in about 22 BC.
The temple of Taharqa
The finding of a considerable number of blocks
containing the titles of Taharqa, a Pharaoh of the
"Ethiopian" Dynasty (7th century BC), suggested
that a building from his period had once existed
at Ibrim, and during the 1972 season considerable
remains of a temple erected by Taharqa were un¬
covered. Of special interest was the finding of a
wall painting containing the face of Taharqa, the
only example of a portrait of Taharqa in this form
yet known.
A tavern in the (X-Group) town
Excavations in the fortress area revealed a large
X-Group town built over earlier Meroitic struc¬
tures. It is possible that Ibrim may have been a
royal residence and the artefacts of the period
reveal a hitherto unsuspected degree of cultural
achievement.
The largest secular building in use during the
X-Group period at Ibrim appears to have been a
tavern. It was originally built about the middle of
the 4th century AD, in late Meroitic times. Carv¬
ings on the outside, showing an amphora resting
on a tripod and a bunch of grapes, suggest the
purpose of the building. This was confirmed by
the discovery in adjoining rooms of broken wine
jars and goblets by the thousand.
The cathedral of the Virgin Mary
Qasr Ibrim is dominated by the remains of a splen¬
did, stone-built cathedral, itself a rebuilding of an
earlier structure. The arcades of the cathedral are
decorated with carved stone rosettes and other
motifs. A double-aisled building with monolithic
granite columns, a semicircular apse to the east
and two deep crypts with tomb shafts, it was ap¬
proached by a magnificent flight of ornamental
steps.
The Nubian bishop Timothy
In 1964 the burial of a bishop was found under the
entrance to the north crypt of the cathedral. Com¬
missary letters in the form of two scrolls four and
a half metres long, from the Patriarch of the Cop¬
tic Church, found in the grave, reveal that his
name was Timothy, that he was Nubian and that
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
down for the first time towards the end of the 8th
century AD. To add to the extensive finds of
literary and non-literary documents, the last
season at Ibrim produced five bilingual psalms
written in Greek and Nubian which are now being
carefully studied. H
Wmf SAH V
The body of Bishop Timothy, showing the two
commissary letters found in his grave.
Photo © J.M. Plumley, U.K.
he was consecrated bishop in 1372 AD. It was at
one time thought that Timothy was the last
bishop of Nubia, but that this was not the case
was proved by one of nine leather scrolls found at
Ibrim in 1964. Written in medieval Nubian and
dated 1464, the scroll indicates that a Nubian
king, Joel, was then reigning at Gebel Adda and
that a bishop Merki was resident at Ibrim.
The baqt
The undisturbed nature of the site and its dryness
meant that discarded material was often wonder¬
fully preserved. In 1972 a magnificent Arabic
scroll was found which dealt with the functioning
of the baqt or treaty between Christian Nubia and
Moslem Egypt. In the past some scholars believed
the whole question of the baqt to have been an in¬
vention of later Arabic writers. The scroll puts its
historical reality beyond all doubt. In it the gover¬
nor of Egypt writes in the autumn of 758 AD to
the king of Nubia complaining that the terms of
the treaty were not being adhered to. Runaway
slaves from Egypt were not being returned,
Moslem merchants were not being granted safe
passage in Nubia, messengers were being un¬
necessarily detained.
Cornelius Gallus the governor-poet
The most exciting find of the 1978 season was a
papyrus containing ten lines, some very fragmen¬
tary, of elegiac verse by Cornelius Gallus, the first
governor of Roman Egypt, known to the ancient
world as the captor of Cleopatra, friend of Virgil
and a passionate poet later admired by Ovid.
Before the Ibrim discovery the modern world
knew only one pentameter by Gallus. The text is
written in small formal book hand and is probably
the nearest we yet have to a contemporary copy
of a well known Latin poet.
Clues to two unknown languages
At the core of Ibrim's fascination lie the two large¬
ly unknown languages which may in time be inter¬
preted through discoveries made there in suc¬
cessive seasons. The earlier is Meroitic, the
language of the southern city that dominated
Ibrim for much of its history, and of which the
script is derived from Egyptian demotic signs.
Words can be read but their meaning is largely
elusive. The wooden tablets and potsherds turned
up at Ibrim will assist the task of decipherment.
The other language imperfectly known is
medieval Nubian, apparently already written
Rock drawing from Sayala.
Photo © Kunsthistorisches Museum, Vienna
EXPEDITION: AUSTRIAN
EXPEDITION IN NUBIA
SITES: SAYALA REGION
REPORTER: WILHELM
ENGARTNER
THE task allotted to the Austrian expedition
included the exploration of tombs and the
collection and scientific study of skeletons found,
and the recording of rock engravings and
paintings. The area investigated covered the
whole district of Sayala on both banks of the Nile.
Ships of all ages
Along with a large number of rock drawings of
cattle, giraffes, elephants, ostriches and human
beings, 140 representations of ships were found.
Dating and classification were aided by examina¬
tion of the type of construction depicted. They in¬
cluded representations of Nagada II type ships,
ships of the dynastic periods, with cabins amid¬
ships, Roman ships with high freeboards, multi-
oared vessels of later times as well as more recent
feluccas.
History from bones
Modern physical anthropology goes beyond the
measurement of such indicators as skull size or
body height. It attempts the more ambitious task
of reconstructing the entire biological structure of
a population or a segment of a population. This
includes such factors as the proportion of sexes,
infantile mortality, the process of child growth,
overall life duration.
The expedition examined a total of 107 human
skeletons; 30 were from the late C-Group, 13 from
the Roman-Nubian period and 64 from the early
Byzantine period. Among the C-Group skeletons
not a single woman was found and of the children
most were in the 1 to 6 age group. Where were
the women buried? And why did some of the
children receive the same burial distinctions as
grown men? Several males were found to have
unusually large teeth. Among the Byzantine
period skeletons a surprisingly large number were
found to have lost their teeth at a comparatively
early age (25 to 35). Children and juveniles,
however, appeared to have been unaffected.
What can have brought on this sudden change at
the age of maturity? These are some of the ques¬
tions which remain to be solved.
EXPEDITION: INSTITUTE OF
EGYPTOLOGY OF
PRAGUE UNIVERSITY
SITES: TAFFA, KERTASSI,
WADI QITNA,
SOUTH KALABSHA
REPORTER: MIROSLAV VERNER
The lost temple of Taffa
ONE of the most exciting achievements of the ex¬
pedition was the finding of the lost Southern
Temple, in the Taffa area. Built in the Roman
period and re-used later by Christians, this temple
was still known at the beginning of the last cen¬
tury, but by our times no trace of it was to be
seen. The temple was located somewhere on a
plain one kilometre long and half a kilometre wide
and covered with five metres of mud brought
down by the Nile after the construction of the first
Aswan Dam.
By studying two daguerreotypes made in
1850-1851 by two French travellers, Maxime du
Camp and Félix Teynard, the team succeeded in
calculating the photographer's position from the
perspective of the cliff behind the temple and thus
established its exact location.
The fortress of Kertassi
Simultaneously with the excavations at Taffa
work was going ahead with the mapping out of a
large ancient fortress at Kertassi. Nearby was the
huge Kertassi quarry which at one time provided
stone for the temples of Philae. It is carved in the
form of a vast amphitheatre. A niche, flanked by
two half statues, carved on part of the quarry face
gives the quarry the appearance of an ancient
ruined temple.
550 X-Group graves
Excavations at Wadi Qitna and south Kalabsha
led to the discovery of some 550 X-Group graves
of the 4th and 5th centuries. The rich funeral trap¬
pings included collections of pottery, glass, metal
objects, jewellery, fragments of wooden cots,
remnants of food and abundant anthropological
material.
Epigraphic research
In two fifty-kilometre-long areas stretching from
Naga el Dom el Dakar to Naga el Qurud and from
Naga el Birba to Gerf Hussein the expedition car¬
ried out epigraphic research which yielded some
240 Egyptian, Meroitic, Carian, Aramaic, Greek,
Latin and Coptic inscriptions.
The quarry at Kertassi. Photo Manara, Unesco
42
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
EXPEDITION:
SITES:
Noah's Ark fresco, Debeira West.
Photo © Rex Keating
EXPEDITION: UNIVERSITY OF
GHANA
SITE: DEBEIRA WEST
REPORTER: PETER SHINNIE
Domestic life in medieval Nubia
THE investigation of the medieval town Debeira,
on the west bank of the Nile between the modern
villages of Serra and Argin, was deliberately plan¬
ned to get the maximum amount of information
on domestic aspects of medieval Nubian life. The
objects found and the nature of some of the
buildings, were more elaborate than had been an¬
ticipated and Debeira was shown to be something
more than just a settlement of poor peasants.
It consisted not only of the main town, but also of
two churches, and a monastery!?). The main
town was occupied at two quite separate periods,
the first dating to the seventh century AD and the
second from c. 750 AD to c. 1100 AD. Between
these two periods the site was abandoned and
was covered with wind-blown sand. The chur¬
ches are associated with the main, richer, second
period of occupation, whilst the monastery ap¬
pears to have been occupied at the same time as
the first town, that is in the sixth century or even
somewhat earlier.
The early settlement
The early (seventh century AD) settlement had
been largely built over by the later town but a few
dwellings had not been built over. These
buildings, of light construction, appear to be
storage rooms and kitchens, perhaps part of a
more elaborate structure underlying later
buildings further south.
Nubian houses of the second period
The second period of occupation was more in¬
tense. Most of the buildings appear to have been
dwellings, and though none of them are identical
it is possible to see regularity in the pattern of Nu¬
bian houses of the period. They are small, fre¬
quently of two rooms, roofed with the Nubian
vault and sometimes with a staircase leading to
the roof. All the buildings are of mud brick with
the exception of a unique stone house in the
southern extension of the site. It seems that this
area represents the latest occupation in the town
and the stone house is probably to be dated to
somewhere about AD 1100.
An age-old way of life
Domestic life probably did not differ very much
from the life of the recent past. One of the main
differences is to be seen in the lay-out of the
villages over at least the last 150 years the Nu¬
bian village has consisted of large courtyard
houses, standing free, and arranged in a line fac¬
ing the river. The medieval village was quite dif¬
ferent; the houses were very much smaller, they
were packed tightly together, and there was ap¬
parently no logical arrangement.
Agriculture and diet
Agriculture must have been much the same as to¬
day, with a dependence on the saqia wheel for ir¬
rigation. Debeira produced one structure which
may have been part of a sesame oil press. Crops
can be assumed to have been much the same as
today, wheat and sorghum, and diet cannot have
been very different.
THE ORIENTAL
INSTITUTE,
UNIVERSITY OF
CHICAGO, U.S.A.
BEIT EL WAD TO
KALABSHA
REPORTER: BRUCE WILLIAMS
The tombs of the Blemmye chieftains
FIELD operations began in 1960-61 when a joint ex¬
pedition with the Schweizerisches Institut für
Bauforschung und Altertumskunde conducted an
expedition just south of Aswan to record the part¬
ly rock-cut temple of Beit el Wali constructed by
Ramses II of the Nineteenth Dynasty and ex¬
cavate sites between there and Bab Kalabsha.
Most interesting was the excavation of several
sites with pottery and objects of a previously
unknown and distinctive material culture,
especially large circular stone tombs that contain¬
ed a beautiful red-burnished pottery decorated
with linear designs along with objects and coins
of late Roman times. It is now believed that these
were tombs of kinglets or chieftains of the so-
called Blemmyes, a powerful tribe known to have
occupied this part of Nubia in the dying days of
the Roman Empire. The new objects and pottery
of these tombs appear to give a cultural
substance to the Blemmyes, a people well known
in classical sources but hitherto unknown in ar¬
chaeology.
The largest A-Group tombs ever found
In January of 1964, members of the expedition
working at Qustul, just north of the Sudan fron¬
tier discovered a cemetery of A-Group tombs of
far greater size than ever before found in Nubia.
Although the tombs had been plundered and
burnt, the fragments of pottery and objects are so
numerous, varied and of such high quality, in¬
cluding some that are entirely unique, that had
these tombs been found in a Predynastic
cemetery north of the First Cataract or had they
been of much later date, they would have been
considered royal at once.
The testimony of an incense burner
However, there was additional evidence of
Egyptian-type kingship in the specific symbols
and regalia. Previously, contemporary evidence
of kings in Egypt extended back only two or three
generations before the start of the First Dynasty
about 3100 BC and a number of palace façades in¬
cised on pottery extended our knowledge a
generation or two further. This evidence has been
combined with later lists, annals, and legends to
make a speculative reconstruction of prehistoric
Egypt. Never before, however, had actual clear
remains of kings been found that corresponded to
these disconnected fragments.
In the tombs of Cemetery L at Qustul were found
two groups of evidence that confirm their royal
character and offer new clues to connect many of
these previously disconnected fragments. The
first group is a number of decorated incense
burners, cylindrical objects of sandstone or a
curious mixture of clay minerals that were
sometimes carved with representations. Mostly
these were incised, but one, the Qustul Incense
Burner, a particularly large example, was
elaborately carved in a sunk decoration related to
rock drawing in the Nile Valley and adjacent
deserts.
The piece had been seriously damaged by those
who destroyed the tombs and, though a proces¬
sion of three ships ending at a palace façade
could easily be seen, two of the three main
passengers on the ships had been badly damag¬
ed. However, when the piece was reexamined in
the light of the obviously royal character of the
cemetery, the restoration was immediately clear.
The first ship was taking a bound prisoner and his
guard to the sacrifice before the palace façade. In
the second ship was a king, shown by the White
Crown of Upper Egypt and the Horus falcon,
almost certainly on a serekh or palace façade; the
king seated on a block throne with a falcon perch¬
ed on a palace façade that contains his name in
front of him is a typical representation in Early
Dynastic Egypt.
The earliest recorded historical event
The second group of materials to give a historical
substance to the kings who had been buried in
Cemetery L is a series of painted pottery vessels
that show actual or claimed events. On one piece,
a bird attacks an oval that contains two diagonal
strokes, the symbol for Hierakonpolis, most
venerated of the ancient capitals of Upper Egypt.
This reference to a conflict is in fact the earliest
mention of this city, the earliest reference to a
political entity in Egypt and very probably the
earliest recorded historical event.
The most important of these vessels is a bowl,
originally with four groups of giraffes flanking
palm trees. Only two scenes have survived in one
of which can be seen a plant, which, though
somewhat oddly shaped, is clearly the symbol for
Upper Egypt. Again this is the first mention of Up¬
per Egypt as a political entity.
This new material will help define the date of the
few monumental objects from Egypt that refer to
events in this "prehistoric" age and they will also
help, along with the Qustul Incense Burner, to
identify other objects and a monument already
known in Nubia as belonging to the Pharaohs that
first led Nubia to political unity and cultural
distinction.
The Qustul incense burner
Photo © Oriental Institute
of the University of Chicago
Scenes depicted on the Qustul incense burner
Drawing © Oriental Institute of the University of Chicago
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
A-Group Nubia a unified state
The evidence derived from Cemetery L makes the
period just before the First Dynasty accessible as
a historic age for the first time. One point stands
out, completely unexpected, completely contrary
to previous thought or opinion. For nine genera¬
tions or more, between 3500/3400 and 3200/3100
BC, A-Group Nubia was a unified State, with the
full equipment of civilization, a government, a
Pharaoh, officials, State cult, writing and monu¬
ments, a State which succeeded in uniting people
who were not blood relations for a common pur¬
pose. Thus the inhabitants of Ta-Seti, the "Land
of the Bow" as Nubia was called by the ancient
Egyptians, participated fully and more equally
than anyone has ever supposed in the fateful
achievement of civilization on the Nile.
Tomas during the Christian era
When Nubia was converted to Christianity,
Tomas retained its importance. At Sheikh Daud
the expedition recorded several graffiti from the
Coptic era and excavated a tomb in which were
found the remains of four burials and a fragment
of pink sandstone cut in the shape of a camel.
EXPEDITION: UNIVERSITY OF
STRASBOURG
SITE: TOMAS
REPORTER: JEAN LECLANT
A number of Old Kingdom inscriptions found by
the expedition indicate that Tomas was an impor¬
tant trading centre of ancient Nubia and a depar¬
ture point for routes leading to various oases and
the desert route to Aswan. A careful survey of the
river bank on either side of Tomas revealed a
hitherto unsuspected abundance of north
Saharan rock art.
The stela of Bertoye
During the late Meroitic period Tomas and the
district around it formed part of one of the frontier
provinces of the Meroitic kingdom. At the site of
Karanog just upstream from Tomas, the expedi¬
tion discovered two extremely important texts,
one on a stela and the other on an offertory table.
Both were written in cursive Meroitic script and
both mentioned the name of Bertoye, a high of¬
ficial and priest of several religious cults of the
region and in particular of Amon. Bertoye figures .
in several other inscriptions in Meroitic, demotic
and also Greek, some of which are dated between
253 and 260 AD. He was therefore a contem¬
porary of the Meroitic king Tequerideamani. The
two texts from Karanog will be of great impor¬
tance in the studies of the Meroitic language now
being carried out (see inside back cover).
Previously only 800 Meroitic inscriptions, many of
them short, were available. The discovery of two
exceptionally well-preserved, long texts will be of
great value to the computer-aided study of the
Meroitic language.
Tha Mala of Bertoye.
Photo © J. Leclant, France
EXPEDITION: PENNSYLVANIA-YALE
EXPEDITION, U.S.A.
SITES: TOSHKA, ARMINNA
REPORTER: WILLIAM KELLY
SIMPSON
The prince of Miam
ONE of the more interesting of the expeditions'
achievements during the Nubian campaign was
the identification by the Pennyslvania-Yale Ex¬
pedition of one of three tombs at Toshka East,
just north of Abu Simbel, as the tomb of Heka-
nefer, prince of Miam (Miam being the ancient
name of a district of Nubia).
As early as 1905, Arthur Weigall, then Chief In¬
spector for the Antiquities Service, had found an
inscription near the tomb which he translated as
reading "chieftain of Miam, prince (heka) of
Nefer", not realizing that the last part of the in¬
scription was a proper name and that the transla¬
tion should have been "the chieftain of Miam,
Heka-nefer". Now, far to the north at Thebes, in
Egypt proper, a prince of Miam named Heka-
nefer is represented in the tomb of Huy, the
Viceroy of Nubia under King Tutankhamun
(about 1352-1343 BC). Tutankhamun, Huy and
Heka-nefer are all represented on the same wall of
the tomb, with the latter being shown in a proces¬
sion of tribute from the southlands. Of the figures
represented Heka-nefer alone is singled out by
name.
Although later investigators made the connexion
between the Heka-nefers of the Toshka inscrip¬
tion and of the Theban tomb, realizing that they
were the same individual, they failed to recognize
that the tomb at Toshka was that of the same
Heka-nefer. This is not so surprising as it might at
first seem, since there is a striking contrast bet¬
ween his representation at Thebes, where he is
shown as a typical Nubian with dark skin and
southern costume, and the impression made by
the tomb at Toshka, modelled on the Theban
tombs, from which one would surmise that he
was an Egyptian official.
Child of the nursery
Not only did the expedition locate the inscription
concerning Heka-nefer described by Weigall, it
also discovered four other previously unknown in¬
scriptions some distance to the south of the
tombs. One of these indicates that Heka-nefer
was the chief river transport agent, with control
over all river traffic in his principality. Three other
titles give a good indication of his relation to the
royal court at Thebes. Foremost of these is "child
of the nursery", a designation borne by the sons
of nobles and foreign princes who were sent to
the Egyptian court to be brought up with the
children of the Pharaoh. These classmates of the
Pharaoh proudly bore this title into their old age
as an indication of their childhood association
with the great court at Thebes. Second, he was
"bearer of the folding chair of the lord of the two
lands", a designation relating to his ceremonial
position in the royal service. Third, he is called
"king's sandal" or "king's sandalmaker", a title
which either stresses his subservience to the ruler
or else suggests that Miam was a region in which
a leather industry of note flourished.
Funerary statuette of Heka-nefer.
Photo © W,K. Simpson, Pennsylvania-Yale Egyptian expedition
Servants for the life hereafter
The most exciting discoveries in the tomb were
the five funerary statuettes of the prince which
were found in the pit leading to the burial
chamber. Cast aside by the grave robbers who
had removed all the finery and treasure buried
with the body, these statuettes were the prince's
shawabtis statuettes inscribed with a text ex¬
plaining that they would take the owner's place in
the after-life every time he was called upon to per¬
form manual labour. They are among the finest
shawabtis ever found in Nubia.
A Coptic stela
At Arminna West the expedition turned its atten¬
tion to a site previously thought to be that of a
monastery complex but which is perhaps better
described as a settlement inhabited successively
in the Meroitic, X-Group and Christian periods.
The most unexpected feature was a Coptic
church similar to several of the small churches
found further to the south. In the small apse a
Coptic tomb stela of terracotta showed that the
church was probably in use in the 10th century.
EXPEDITION: DUTCH
ARCHAEOLOGICAL
MISSION TO NUBIA
SITES: SHOKAN,
ABDALLAH NIRQI
REPORTER: H.D. SCHNEIDER
Late Meroitic settlement at Shokan
FROM 1962 to 1964 the Dutch mission excavated a
late Meroitic period (1st to 4th century AD) settle¬
ment, consisting of more than thirty houses, at
Shokan, some two to three kilometres north of
the Abu Simbel temples. The settlement was
notable for a three-room unit house system. The
houses had vaulted roofs, the doors were lined
with stone elements and the walls had niches and
sometimes red painted band decorations. A fine
eggshell ware beaker was found. It was decorated
with black line drawings of two prisoners tied to a
stake in the presence of a panther.
The church of Abdallah Nirqi
The mission discovered and excavated an 8th
century church at Abdallah Nirqi, four kilometres
north of Abu Simbel. The mud brick church
measured 15 by 12 metres and the walls were
preserved to a height of 3.5 metres. In the central
part of the church a staircase of seven steps led to
the pulpit. Walls and ceilings were covered with
painted scenes of the Holy Family and important
historical figures of the Nubian Church. Many of
these paintings were saved by the efforts of an
Egyptian/Yugoslav restoration mission.
44
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
Man in the jar.
Photo © H.D. Schneider, Netherlands
Christ and the Four Holy Beings
On the east wall of the right wing of the church
was a mandorla containing a bust of Christ sur¬
rounded by the Four Holy Beings of the Revela¬
tions, a man, an eagle, a calf and a lion. To this
motif a rich Greek cross, in Christian Nubia a sym¬
bol of new life, has been added. To the left of the
mandorla is the figure of a priest with a palm
branch in his hand.
Prisoner in the jar
A unique mural painting at Abdallah Nirqi depicts
a saint riding a white horse. Between the legs of
his mount is seen a naked, bearded man, im¬
prisoned in a storage jar, who cries out "Kyrie
eleison". Lord have mercy. This is thought to be
the representation of the climax of a lost legend,
when a Christian shut up by heathens in a vessel-
prison prays to a saint for help and deliverance.
The theme of imprisonment in a vessel is known
in Greek mythology and it is believed that in the
ancient East slaves were sometimes punished by
being enclosed in a "pythos", the grain storage
vessel of the granary.
EXPEDITION:
SITE:
REPORTER:
HUNGARIAN
ACADEMY OF
SCIENCES
ABDALLAH NIRQI
L. TÖRÖK
THE mission of the Hungarian Academy of
Sciences started work in Lower Nubia in summer
1964, at a time when only a few weeks remained
available for excavation. The site was on the west
bank of the Nile four kilometres north of the
famous rock temples of Abu Simbel.
Although the significance of the remains of Ab¬
dallah Nirqi (the name derives from the name of a
local farmer who lived near the site in the 1930s)
had already been recognized by the First Ar¬
chaeological Survey, it was still a surprise when,
in a church on the desert side of the site, the
Dutch Mission discovered wall-paintings of the
8th-12th centuries representing an artistic wealth
rivalling that of the Faras cathedral. After clearing
the church and detaching the wall-paintings, the
Dutch Mission had been obliged to leave Abdallah
Nirqi and, when the Hungarian Mission accepted
the proposal of the Antiquities Service of Egypt to
take over the concession, it decided to concen¬
trate its activity on the settlement and the Chris¬
tian cemetery belonging to it.
The bishop, the archangel
and the saint on horseback
The central part of the settlement, including the
church excavated by the Dutch Mission, was sur¬
rounded by a citadel wall. Two other churches
were discovered outside the wall. One of them,
the Western Church, was built shortly after the
citadel church was completed in the 8th century.
The other one, the Eastern Church, at the village
cemetery, was built some decades later. The
Western Church was decorated with wall-
paintings in the 11th century. The decoration of
the Western Church was, however, destroyed
fairly early on by the collapse of the vault.
Scraped-off pieces of the painting were found
scattered around in the filling of the new floor laid
after the vault was rebuilt. From the fragments we
were able to reconstruct three figures: those of a
bishop, of an archangel and of a saint on
horseback.
EXPEDITION: THE SPANISH
MISSION TO NUBIA
SITES: SHEIKH DAUD,
MASMAS, ARGIN,
QASR I KO,
ABKANARTI
REPORTER: E. RIPOLL-PERELLO
AND M.
LLONGUERAS-
CAMPANA
THE Spanish mission began work in Nubia in 1961.
It was divided into two teams, one operating at
Sheikh Daud and Masmas, in Egyptian Nubia,
and the other at Argin, Qasr Iko and the island of
Abkanarti, in Sudanese Nubia.
A fortress with a Roman-style street plan
In the fortress of Sheikh Daud, built in the second
half of the 6th century, thirty-eight dwellings and
a church were excavated. The streets were found
to be laid out on the model of a Roman encamp¬
ment. Abundant finds were made of pottery,
metal objects, seals and sandstone plaques,
weights, fragments of necklaces and some
sculptures, as well as some architectural items.
However, no inscriptions were found.
Excavations at Masmas
A large quantity of. prehistoric and historic rock
carvings and inscriptions were found and several
cemeteries, including C-Group, New Kingdom,
Meroitic and Christian burials were excavated.
The Meroitic cemeteries provided the richest fin¬
dings of any site examined by the Spanish expedi¬
tion in Nubia. They included a number of
sculptures very characteristic of the art style of
the period, inscriptions, interesting decorated of¬
fertory tables and, of particular interest, some fine
decorated vessels and an outstanding vase or¬
namented with floral and anthropomorphic
designs.
In Sudanese Nubia
The extensive Argin region, on the west bank of
the Nile, proved to be rich in tombs from the
C-Group and Pharaonic periods to the Christian
era. These provided a wealth of finds from every
epoch. An outstanding item from the Pharaonic
period was a fragment of a painted sarcophagus
dating from the 19th Dynasty. The Meroitic
period burials yielded some silver and silver-gilt
vases, a great variety of jewellery and a number of
weapons.
Two island sites
Further south, the expedition investigated sites
on the islands of Qasr Iko and Abkanarti. On Qasr
Iko two small Christian churches were excavated
and in one of them the remains of some murals
were discovered. On Abkanarti a village with a
fortified wall and a small fortress perched on a
rocky hill were examined. An interesting find in
this village was a metal foundry furnace and pot¬
tery kiln.
EXPEDITION: YUGOSLAV
INSTITUTE FOR THE
PROTECTION OF
HISTORIC
MONUMENTS
SITES: WADI ES SEBUA,
ABU ODA, SHEIKH
ABD EL GADIR,
ABDALLAH NIRQI
REPORTER: MILORAD MEDIC
THE Institute's contribution to the Nubian cam¬
paign consisted primarily of the difficult and
delicate task of removing, transferring and preser¬
ving mural paintings from temples and churches
at a number of sites.
Artists from every age left their mark on the Valley
of the Lions (Wadi es Sebua). Prehistoric rock
drawings were found not far from the Egyptian
reliefs and Christian paintings that adorned a tem¬
ple built by Ramses II and subsequently converted
into a Coptic church. Artists who accompanied
the first Christian missionaries painted fine por¬
traits of St. Peter and St. George, crosses and
other Christian symbols over the Egyptian reliefs.
Today more than thirty mural paintings from the
temples of Wadi es Sebua can be seen in the
museums of Cairo.
Coptic art
from Abu Oda and Abdallah Nirqi
At Abu Oda the mission removed from the temple
of Horemheb some of the oldest and finest Chris¬
tian mural paintings found in Nubia, including a
representation of Christ and a holy martyr. Mean¬
while, a team of Dutch archaeologists had
discovered a small Christian church at Abdallah
Nirqi which contained a number of well preserved
murals including a fine mandorla. These, too,
were removed by the mission and sent to the
Coptic Museum in Cairo.
Sheikh Abd el Gadir
The final task of the mission was the removal
from the 9th century church of Sheikh Abd el
Gadir of some fine murals including one of a Nu¬
bian eparch holding a model of the church in his
hand, a nativity scene and a portrayal of the Holy
Trinity.
A technical feat
The removal and preservation of these murals by
the Yugoslav mission was a very considerable
technical feat. In many cases the murals were
liable to fall to pieces at a touch. Before undertak¬
ing the work the Yugoslav Institute carried out a
series of preliminary experiments which resulted
in the development of the techniques successfully
employed under the difficult conditions of the Nu¬
bian campaign.
The mandorla mural at Abdallah Nirqi.
Photo © M. Medic, Yugoslavia .
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Condotte-Mazzi Estero, SPA, Rome
The holy isle of Philae
Photos on these pages show three episodes in the chequered story of the
monuments of Philae in modern times. Engraving (opposite page, top) shows the
island as it was in the mid-19th century, high and dry above the Nile, its temples
virtually unchanged since Antiquity. The threat to Philae goes back to the turn of
the century when the first Aswan Dam was built downstream of the island and
later raised on two occasions (1907-1912 and 1929-1934). For thirty years (1934-1964)
the temples were engulfed in the Lake formed behind the Dam except for three
months each year when the Dam's sluices were opened and the monuments
emerged in their entirety. When the waters were at their highest only the tips of
the twin towers of the first pylon of the temple of Isis were visible. Photo opposite
page shows Philae during this period. It was taken shortly after the sluice gates
had been closed and the waters were starting to rise. The monuments survived
their plight because the Egyptian Antiquities Service had consolidated their
foundations before the Dam was built. Then, in 1960 the construction of the new
High Dam upstream brought the threat of eventual destruction to Philae. From now
on the monuments would be at the mercy of the waters between the two Dams
(since the original Aswan Dam continues to function). By 1965 the temple of Isis
was permanently flooded to about half its height. Daily fluctuations in the water
level (up to six metres) gradually eroded the monuments. After several rescue
projects had been considered, it was decided to dismantle the monuments and re-
erect them on the nearby island of Agilkia which is always above the water level
(see photo caption page 13). Photo above shows the temple of Isis on Agilkia,
which was specially landscaped to resemble Philae.
46
WHEN the Pharaoh Nectanebo I
(380-363 BC) built a temple at
Philae, no one could have fore¬
seen how prominently the island and its
priesthood would figure in Egyptian politico-
religious history for the next thousand years.
In 332 BC, thirty-one years after the death of
Nectanebo I, Egypt was conquered by Alex¬
ander the Great and, for the three centuries
following his conquest, the throne was oc¬
cupied by rulers of Macedonian stock, all of
whom bore the name of Ptolemy except the
last, who was the famous queen Cleopatra
(51-30 BC). From the outset, they adopted
the Egyptian religion, and in particular the
cult of Osiris and Isis. Philae's principal
monument, the temple of Isis, was built by
Ptolemy II, Philadelphus (285-246 BC), and
Ptolemy III, Euergetee I (246-221 BC), apart
from the main doorway of the First Pylon
which was a relic of the temple of Nec¬
tanebo.
It was not only in Egypt, however, that
the cult of Isis and Osiris had advanced in
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Photo Georg Gerster © Rapho, Paris
by lorwerth E.S. Edwards
popularity during the Ptolemaic Period.
Greek settlers, many of whom were traders,
had transported it to their native land and its
dependencies, with the result that by the
year 30 BC, when the Mediterranean coun¬
tries, including Egypt, were united under
Roman rule, the cult was firmly established
throughout the Aegean region. It had,
moreover, reached Rome, where Isis ac¬
quired the reputation of being the protec¬
tress of mariners, and thence it spread to the
remotest parts of the Empire.
At first, Philae received no visible proof of
imperial patronage, apparently because
Augustus was disinclined to show partiality
towards Isis, who had been the goddess of
his enemy, Cleopatra, but eventually he
relented and, in the eighteenth year of his
reign (9 BC), he built a temple at the nor¬
thern end of the island. Much of it is now
lost, but those of its architectural elements
which have survived show that it was once a
fine edifice.
Tiberius, Augustus' successor, and seve¬
ral later Emperors also left their mark at Phi¬
lae, mostly by adding reliefs and inscriptions
to existing monuments, but four Emperors
erected new buildings, namely Claudius (AD
41-54) a temple to Harendotes, Trajan (AD
98-117) the most celebrated of all Philae's
monuments, the kiosk on the east side of
the island, Hadrian (AD 117-138) the gate¬
way and vestibule near the temple of Haren¬
dotes, and probably Diocletian (AD
284-305) the ceremonial gateway at the
northern end of the island.
While the cult of Isis was gaining ad¬
herents across the Mediterranean, it was
also making headway in Nubia, even as far
south as the kingdom of Meroe, whose capi¬
tal lay about 75 miles north-east of Khar¬
toum. One of the kings of Meroe, Ergame-
nes, enlarged the temple of Arsenuphis and
travellers from Meroe left graffiti on the roof
of the Birth-House of the temple of Isis.
It was in Lower Nubia, however, that the
cult of Isis made its greatest impact, espe¬
cially in the so-called Dodekaschoenos, the
territory extending southwards for 80 miles
from the First Cataract to Maharraqa. For
the inhabitants of that region Philae became
the religious metropolis.
Philae retained its privileged position even
after the Emperor Theodosius I issued his
decree in AD 391 suppressing pagan wor¬
ship throuthout the empire. Political expe¬
diency was undoubtedly the chief rea-
CONTINUED PAGE 70
IORWERTH E.S. EDWARDS, of the United
Kingdom, was Keeper of Egyptian Antiquities at
the British Museum until his retirement in 1974.
He was a member of the Committee of
Archaeologists and Landscape Architects
appointed by Unesco and the Egyptian Ministry of
Culture to advise on the removal of the
monuments of Philae to Agilkia. He is the author
of several books including The Pyramids of Egypt,
Max Parrish, 1961.
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
The mysteries
!k^ . «^ .
-
1
V ijtVÍ
r ni
'l 1
-
-
} 1
Is IHr * *- '*
1 >4j
Pel
£r *^ -«^E
r j^^MBeS ^Su^Sel
il^K. J^JAé
^tór
F->
^ V s
* **^
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
of Isis and Osiris by François Daumas
Two episodes from the myth of the god
Osiris are shown in these drawings of bas-
reliefs from Pharaonic temples. Scene
below from a Philae chapel depicts a priest
watering an effigy of the god made of river
mud and sprouting with barley shoots. It is
a reminder that Osiris was a god of
agriculture, the personification of Egyptian
soil and its periodic rebirth, before he
became the ruler of the underworld who
guaranteed a life hereafter. After being
murdered and hacked to pieces by his
brother Seth, Osiris was given new life by
his faithful wife Isis and came to symbolize
the triumph of good and innocent creatures
over death. In the 1st century AD the
Osiris-myth was described by the Greek
writer Plutarch who claimed to have heard
it at first hand from the Egyptian priests.
Lower drawing from the temple of Dendara
corresponds to Plutarch's description of the
tomb of Osiris in the abaton, the inviolate
sanctuary on the island of Bigeh in the Nile
(see map next page). The mummified body
of Osiris stretched out an a funeral bed is
shaded by a shrub on which the god's bat
or soul, is perched.
Drawings B. Lenthéric © F. Daumas, France
Sunlight streaming through an aperture in
the roof of the temple of Dendara strikes
the body of Osiris on his funeral bed. This
symbolic scene evokes the death and
resurrection of one of the most important
Egyptian gods, Osiris lord of the
underworld.
Photo © Henri Stieriin, Geneva
IN pre-Christian times in Egypt, the
appearance of the First Cataract of the
Nile was quite different from what it is
today. The shallow river swirled amidst pink
granite rocks darkened and polished by its
waters. On each bank, great drifts of copper
and gold sand were interspersed with rocks
of more sombre hues. Islands of all sizes
emerged from this riot of colours and
sounds.
Upstream from Aswan and Elephantine,
on the eastern side of the river, were three
islands, all close together: the rock-island of
Konosso, where in the days of the Pharaohs
visiting kings and officials engraved inscrip¬
tions; the island of Philae where until a year
or two ago the temple of Isis still stood; and
the island of Bigeh, once the site of the
Abaton, or sanctuary of Osiris (see article
page 46). Although we do not know for cer¬
tain how such an imposing temple came to
be dedicated to Isis at the frontier of Nubia,
legend and mythology furnish their own
distinctive explanation.
Osiris had once reigned over Egypt and
had taught its people agriculture, animal
" husbandry and justice. He had married his
sister Isis, a wise and powerful enchantress,
who was deeply in love with her husband.
Unlike Isis and Osiris, their brother Seth,
God of the barren desert, was incapable of
any creative act and had an evil character.
One day, during a banquet, Seth locked
up Osiris in a coffin and threw it into the sea.
Isis set out in search of her husband's body,
which she recovered at Byblos. She brought
it back to Egypt where it was discovered by
Seth in the marshes of the Delta. He cut up
the body into fourteen pieces and scattered
them in the Nile.
Isis travelled all over the country and
retrieved the dispersed fragments of her
husband's body. In order to thwart Seth's
evil intentions, she pretended to bury each
part of the body where she found it so that it
would be impossible to know exactly where
Osiris was really interred. Consequently, the
various Osirian legends differ on this point.
Some believed that he had been buried at
Abydos, where his head was preserved,
while for others the burial place was at
Memphis, Busiris or Taposiris. Others still
claimed that he was to be found in the
Abaton of Philae. For the local priests, there
could be no doubt that his final resting place
was on Bigeh, the Holy Island as it is called
in the inscriptions on the Temple of Isis.
Here on the island of Bigeh there was a
monument which no one was allowed to ap¬
proach except for the small group of priests
who were in charge of funerary rites. This is
why the Greeks named this site the Abaton,
the inviolate area within which it was forbid¬
den to penetrate. The tomb, probably very
austere, was located inside a sacred grove
where perseas, jujube and acacia trees
grew. This small monument was shaded by
the "Methide" tree about which much has
been written but whose species has never
been identified. It was, at any rate, taller
than an olive tree. In the grove 365 tables of
offerings were set out so that a libation of
milk could be poured out every day of the
year. Up above, in the tree which shaded the
tomb, was perched the bai of Osiris, one of
the elements of the God's personality. In
order that the bai could drink continuously
of the regenerative milk, the tables were
covered with leafy palm stalks which kept
the liquid fresh. Each day this ritual was
celebrated by the highest-ranking priest,
who doubtless also officiated at the temple
of Bigeh, whose ruins are still standing in
the eastern part of the island, facing Philae.
The "pure Island" was supposed to re¬
main in eternal silence, so that the god's
sleep should never be disturbed. Not only
was it forbidden to talk in a loud voice, but
the beating of the tambourine, an action
symbolizing joy, was also prohibited. No
one was allowed to sing to the accompani¬
ment of the harp or the flute. According to
the legend, birds and fish kept away from
the island; in any case it was strictly forbid¬
den to hunt and fish there.
Every ten days, Isis visited her husband's
funeral mound to pour out the libation and
to adorn his tomb. She crossed the river,
which was narrow at this point, on a sacred
barque called The Protectress. The
ceremonies were particularly solemn on the
12th Epiphi which, if our calculations are
correct, corresponds to the 17th of July. On
that day Harendotes, Horus who protects
his father, accompanied Isis on the sacred
pilgrimage. Although the information at our
disposal is incomplete, it seems that the
main purpose of this celebration was to pre¬
sent the funerary offerings. The specific
details remain obscure, but we can be cer¬
tain that Isis offered milk. Sometimes the in¬
scriptions seem to indicate that libations of
water were also offered. However, the same
Egyptian word is used to designate both
water and liquid, and it is hard to be com¬
pletely sure about what exactly took place
during this ritual.
These ceremonies, unique to Philae, were
partly a result of the geographic disposition
of the islands of the cataract. Nonetheless,
it is certain that the major Osirian rites
observed in many other cities which wor¬
shipped Osiris, such as Edfu, Dendara,
Abydos, Memphis, Sais, Busiris, were also
performed at Philae. During one of these
rites, known as the Guard of the Hours, the
gods stood around the body of Osiris and
kept a vigil during the twelve hours of night
and the twelve hours of day. Each of them j
took turns in addressing the body of Osiris I
FRANÇOIS DAUMAS, of France, is professor
of Egyptology at the University of Montpellier. A
former director of the French Institute of Oriental
Archaeology in Cairo, he is the author of
numerous articles and books including a thesis
entitled Les Mammisis des Temples Egyptiens,
(The Mammisis of the Egyptian Temples) and
Civilisation de l'Egypte Pharaonique (The
Civilization of Pharaonic Egypt). During the
Nubian campaign he led a French expedition to
Wadi es Sebua.
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
For the ancient Egyptians, symbolic
suckling marked the transition from one
stage of life to another. When a young
prince became king he passed from the
mortal to the immortal world and drew
sustenance and wisdom from the divine
milk to perform his sovereign mission on
earth. Right, the Nubian goddess Anukis,
who was worshipped on Elephantine Island
with the god Khnum, suckles the young
Ramses II. Far right, the Pharaoh is suckled
by the incarnation of motherhood, the
goddess Isis, who brought up her son
Horus in the marshes of the Delta at
Chemnis, constantly afraid that Seth would
hunt him down and kill him. Photos show
reliefs from the temple of Beit El Wali,
which was saved from the Nile waters
during the Nubian campaign.
Photos © Documentation Centre for Ancient Egypt, Cairo
Map drawn in 1913 of the southern part of
the First Cataract shows the islands in the
lake behind the first Aswan Dam in
summer after the Dam's sluicegates had
been opened and the water level in the lake
had dropped.
( laid out on its bier, and spoke words which
would bring him back to life.
It is difficult to summarize this long
discourse which is known from copies
engraved on the walls of Philae, Edfu and
Dendara. The task is further complicated by
the fact that the inscriber constantly makes
use of allusions, and omits vital information,
for the Osirian religion possessed mysteries,
in the Greek sense of the term, and as with
the Eleusinian mysteries it was forbidden to
reveal them. Plutarch's treatise on Isis and
Osiris, the only work to provide a coherent
account of this myth, is silent about certain
episodes that were absolutely secret. A
famous hymn dedicated to Osiris, engraved
on a stela now in the Louvre Museum, is a
masterpiece of discretion, only alluding to
the death and resurrection of the god in
obscure sentences. Plutarch says nothing
about either of these events.
However, in the Guard of the Hours Isis is
made to say the following words: / clothed
him who was naked on the banks of the
Nedyt. From this we may conclude that
Osiris was stripped of his clothing after be¬
ing murdered in the accursed place cited in
documents dating back to the time of the
pyramids. The same text reduces Isis' search
to the following description: / flew over the
country; I crossed the primordial ocean; I
recognized the thing close by the river.
These sentences obviously refer to the god¬
dess's sustained efforts to re-unite the scat¬
tered parts of the divine body and describe
the success which crowned her search. The
thing is the god's body, whose parts lay on
the banks of the river.
A description of the resurrection rites, the
most sacred and secret of all, is also lacking.
It may be imagined that the air wafted by the
wings of his two sisters, Isis and Nephthys,
breathed life back into Osiris. Their wings
are upon you, the liturgical text states
laconically. Bv comoarinq the half-confi¬
dences of the different versions of the myth
we can make certain conjectures about what
actually happened. A large scene on the
tomb of the great priest Petosiris, with in¬
scriptions that are strangely defaced and
mutilated, informs us that gold, the material
of which the sun-god Khepri was made,
played a role in the rebirth of Osiris. Water
also sustained him with its life-giving power:
[Through] the divine water that his heart
loves,
The august /ot/a-plant grows green with life.
And when it grows green, the country
grows green.
And thus the vindicated Osiris renews his re¬
juvenation.
The generative power of water was used
in a symbolic rite performed during the
festivities of the month of Khoiak, which
corresponded approximately to our month
of December. During this ritual, the priests
commemorated Osiris's return to life. These
festivities were so widespread and important
in the lives of the Egyptians that later the
Coptic Christians of Egypt replaced them
during the same month by a liturgy specific
to Egypt and known as the Holy Psalm for
the Month of Khoiak.
During the Osirian celebrations in this
month, a statuette of Osiris was made of
sand and mud from the Nile, mixed with
spices, in which grains of barley were
planted. It was watered every day and the
grains sprouted. This symbolism reflected
the return to life of Isis's husband, as part of
nature's great cosmic cycle. Each of the
dead who had been initiated into the god's
cult also became an Osiris in his own right,
and hoped to be brought back to life with
him. Thus large wooden frames in the shape
of Osiris and adorned with his distinctive j
crown have been found in several royal!
50
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
The Winged
Enchantress
By wafting the air with her
wings, the Great
Enchantress Isis (left) slowly
brought new life to her dead
brother and husband Osiris.
On the walls of Egyptian
tombs Isis is often portrayed
with outstretched wings,
and in this bas-relief, now in
the Louvre Museum in Paris,
she is shown protecting the
body of Ramses III. Carved
in bas-relief on the Isis
temple of Philae is the
sacred boat (below left) in
which Isis embarked every
ten days for the nearby
island of Bigeh to offer a
libation of milk at the tomb
of Osiris. Detail from a bas-
relief in the Isis temple of
Philae (below) shows
reliquary containing the
crowned head of Osiris.
Nearby stands the
mummified god, protected
by the wings of Isis.
51
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
r tombs. The lower part of the frames, adorn¬
ed with plaited reeds or flax, was covered
with sprouted barley, and the entire object
was wrapped up in bandages like a mummy.
Plutarch makes a passing reference to these
practices in his Treatise on Isis and Osiris.
In the Osirian tomb at Philae which
sheltered the fragment of the god's body,
on the roof of the temple of Isis, an extreme¬
ly curious representation illustrated the crea¬
tion of the vegetating Osiris in the month of
Khoiak. A mummy-shaped statuette lies
upon a kind of platform, borne by the sym¬
bols of stability and life. On top of the mum¬
my grows a cluster of stalks ending in ears
of corn, which a priest is carefully watering.
Above, there is an inscription which reads as
follows: It is the unknown mystery produced .
by the water of the flood. In this case, texts,
royal funerary relics and tableaux all coincide
to enable us to grasp the profound meaning
of these rites which assured eternal life to
the devotees of the ailing god. The Egyptian
priests went so far as to believe that the
grains of barley were the very essence of
Osiris's body.
Let us imagine how the island of Philae
must have appeared to the travellers and
Egyptologists of the nineteenth century.
The tiny village of Aswan, with its Bicharin
nomads grouped to the south was truly the
gateway to tropical Africa. Date-palms,
acacias and doom-palms grew side by side.
Calotropes flourished along the sides of the
canals and on the edge of the desert. It
seemed a very different world from that of
Egypt. The copper-coloured sands and
black rocks emerged from an overflowing
river of brick-red water.
If the traveller proceeded southwards to
the end of the Cataract, he would have seen
to the east, the little island of Philae display¬
ing among blue-green palm-trees and airy
groves its kiosk, colonnades, porticoes and
pylons, whose subdued but lively colours
are now only evoked in a handful of plates in
the works of the German Egyptologist
Richard Lepsius (1810-1884).
In spite of the depredations committed by
Justinian's warriors, Isis still seemed to reign
over the harmonious landscape created by
the architects of Antiquity. The size and pro¬
portions of the island perfectly illustrate the
profoundly human quality of its gods and
their transparent mystery: a divine king, just
and benevolent, treacherously murdered; a
dauntlessly faithful goddess, gifted with in¬
telligence and sovereign power, recovers her
husband, brings him back to life, and brings
up his son to succeed his father, after van¬
quishing his enemy. Osiris and Isis will
reward with blessed immortality those who
worship them and those who, like them, act
justly. Since the story echoes mankind's
deepest needs, it comes as no surprise that
this divine couple which reigned over the
southern confines of Egypt should, through
their inspiring and hopeful legend, conquer
much of Europe from the Greek islands to
the distant borders of Germania.
François Daumas
In this bas-relief sculpture from the Isis
temple of Philae, Osiris lord of the dead is
shown as a mummy swathed in bandages
and covered by a shroud. On his head is a
mitre adorned with tall feathers and
twisted horns. He holds a sceptre and a
whip. At right stands Isis with a symbolic
key of life in her left hand. She is wearing a
sun disc set between two cow's horns, the
headdress of Hathor goddess of love, with
whom Isis is sometimes equated.
Photo © Henri Stierlin, Geneva
53
52
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
The magic of Abu Simbel
by Christiane Desroches-Noblecourt
THE name Abu Simbel, today a byword
for technological expertise and a
landmark in international co-op¬
eration, was unknown to the general public
only thirty years ago. In those days, few
even among Egyptologists could boast that
they had visited this holy site in Egyptian
Nubia where, in two rocky bluffs rising from
the Nile downstream of the Second
Cataract, Ramses the Great had hewn for
himself and his favourite queen, Nefertari,
two speos or cave-temples decorated with
magnificent reliefs and statues carved from
the cliffside.
Abu Simbel was doubtless so little known
because of its inaccessibility (the boat which
linked the Egyptian and Sudanese railway
systems only plied between the First and Se¬
cond Cataracts once a week), but also
because of declining interest in a region
which had been partially flooded for nine
months of the year since the height of the
original Aswan Dam had been raised for the
last time.
When the "Father of Egyptology", the
Frenchman Jean-François Champollion
(1790-1832) discovered the Egyptian past by
seeking the testimony of its monuments,
which revealed their story to him for the first
time in 1827 and 1828, he did not stop half¬
way up the Nile as the famous Commission
des Sciences et des Arts set up by Napoleon
Bonaparte had had to do when its accompa¬
nying army led by Desaix halted across from k
the Island of Philae in 1799. t
CHRISTIANE DESROCHES-NOBLECOURT,
of France, is chief curator of the Egyptian
Antiquities Department of the Louvre Museum,
Paris. She was Unesco consultant to the
Documentation Centre for Ancient Egypt in Cairo
and participated from its inception in the
International Campaign to Save the Monuments
of Nubia. A member of the directorate of the
French Centre National de la Recherche
Scientifique, she is the author of many works on
Egyptology including Life and Death of a
Pharaoh, published by Rainbird Ltd., London,
and the New York Graphic Society, New York.
Photo Dominique Roger - Unesco
Below, façade of the smaller of the two temples of Abu Simbel after being
dismantled and re-erected on its new site (see photo caption page 11). This
rock-hewn sanctuary built by Ramses II on the left bank of the Nile is
dedicated to the goddess Hathor and to Nefertari, the Pharaoh's favourite wife.
On each side of the door two colossal statues of Ramses flank a statue of the
queen. The rebuilt temple faces the rising sun, just as it did on its original site.
53
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
The image of the sun-god Re
(left) dominates the entrance to
the Great Temple of Abu
Simbel. It is flanked by two bas-
relief figures of Ramses II, each
offering to the god in an
outstretched palm the figure of
the goddess Maat. The god's
right hand rests on a sceptre,
called ouser in ancient Egyptian;
beneath his left hand is another
small standing figure of the
goddess Maat. The ensemble
forms a representation in figures
of Ramses' coronation name:
ouser-Maat-re. The Great
Temple was dedicated to the
three principal gods of the age
of Ramses: re-Horakhty the sun-
god, Amon and Ptah.
> It was from Abu Simbel that Champollion
set out in order to survey and study
systematically all the monuments he had
noted as he travelled up the Nile from Cairo.
His disciple, M. de Vaucelles, had already
been able to read without difficulty the
name Ramses on the walls of the great tem¬
ple, using his teacher's method of decipher¬
ment. That was over one hundred and fifty
years ago.
When the monuments of ancient Nubia
stood in the greatest danger (the crucial
years being, of course, those of the first
third of the twentieth century), the Govern¬
ment of Egypt's Antiquities Service called
on Egyptologists from various countries to
make rapid surveys and to publish details of
the most endangered sanctuaries. The latter
were those which had been partially or com¬
pletely erected of layers of sandstone (from
Egyptian Nubia) and which stood very close
to the Nile, such as the Ramesside
hemispeos (temples partially constructed on
and partially carved from the rock) of Derr
and Wadi-es-Sebua (North), and the Greco-
Roman temples and chapels of Dabod, Ker¬
tassi, Taffa, Kalabsha, Dendur, Dakka and
Maharraqa.
The charming temple of Amada, dating
from the glorious age of theThutmoses, was
built higher up and escaped immediate
danger, but it too was rapidly surveyed. On
the other hand, the famous speos of Beit-el-
54 .
Wali, Gerf Hussein, Wadi es-Sebua (South),
Abu Simbel and Abu Oda, were at that time
beyond the reach of the rising waters and
were not covered by the surveys; nor was
the temple of Ellesiya. However, the con¬
struction of the new Aswan High Dam
meant that the sites of these monuments
would almost completely disappear beneath
the risen waters of the river.
One of the tasks assigned to the Centre
for Study and Documentation on Ancient
Egypt, established in 1955, was to carry out
a systematic survey, in the most scientifical¬
ly exhaustive manner possible, of all these
temples except one, and to publish the
results. The exception was the hemispeos of
Beit e)-Wali, where the Oriental Institute of
the University of Chicago was authorized to
conduct archaeological excavations (see
page 43).
On the island of Philae, which liesto tne
south of the original Aswan Dam,
meticulous precautions had been taken early
in the century by the French Egyptologist
Gaston Maspero (1846-1916), the Director-
General of the Antiquities Service. Maspero
organized the reinforcement of the founda¬
tions of the Philae monuments, and handed
over responsibility for them to Captain
Lyons, himself supervising the clearing and
excavating operations, as well as the
restoration of the superstructures of various
sanctuaries. He strove to alert public opinion
in order to save the island from submersion,
but the time was not yet ripe for the magnif i- .
cent display of solidarity which Unesco later
called into being. Nevertheless, Maspero's
appeal did not entirely fall on deaf ears, and
his efforts were echoed in the French writer
Pierre Loti's famous book La Mort de Philae
(The Death of Philae). The survey of the
religious buildings dedicated to the goddess
Isis, assigned to the French Egyptologist
Georges Bénédite (1875-1926) was begun at
this period but could not be completed for
lack of time.
Now that the Campaign to Save the Nu¬
bian Monuments is reaching its conclusion,
and that its most prestigious achievements
have been marked at Abu Simbel and at
Philae by the dismantling and transfer of
cave-temples and a group of stone-built
sanctuaries, it is perhaps appropriate to ask
what inspired the Pharaohs, during certain
periods of history, to construct along the
Nubian Nile far from the capital, so many
sanctuaries which were not intended for use
by the indigenous population; for in these
temples, only the priests performed ritual
acts of worship of the divine forms, in¬
cluding that of the Pharaoh himself.
The Philae monuments, comprising the
great sanctuary of the goddess Isis and the
Mammisi (or "birth house"), the chapels of
Osiris, of Hathor and of the sacred Barque,
reveal above all through the texts inscribed
on their walls, the overall symbolism and
hence the significance of the rites celebrated
in them; rites which marked the passing of
the seasons, the trials of nature and of man,
and the incarnations of divinity, the concept
of which would be bequeathed by Late
Egypt to the Western world.
The redoubtable fortresses at the Second
Cataract were provided, doubtless during i
the first Kingdoms, with magnificent
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
Ramses the God
The temples built by Ramses II in Nubia are an expression of the
divine nature of the Pharaoh and queen Nefertari, his favourite
wife. In the small temple of Abu Simbel, dedicated to Nefertari,
is a scene showing her coronation by the goddesses Isis and
Hathor (left). Woman, queen and goddess, Nefertari is portrayed
wearing a crown with two lyre-shaped horns framing a sun-disc,
and two tall feathers. Another bas-relief in the small temple
depicts the coronation of Ramses himself (below left). The gods
Seth and Horus, each standing on a pedestal, hold in eternal
balance the emblems of royalty they have bestowed on the
Pharaoh. An even more striking illustration of Ramses as a god is
the relief (bottom photo) from the temple of Wadi Es Sebua. It
shows the Pharaoh venerating four divinities, including himself
(the others are Onuris, Tefnut and Nekhbet). In bas-relief from
the small temple of Abu Simbel (below) Ramses, accompanied
by Nefertari who is shaking a Sistrum, offers flowers to Taurt
goddess of births. The plant offerings of papyrus buds and stems
are a symbolic allusion to the birth in the marshes of the Delta of
the child-god Horus, son of Isis and Osiris, and to the world's
first blossoming. The scene is an affirmation of the divinity of the
descendants hoped for by the royal couple, themselves part of
the cosmic forces on which Egypt depended.
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
.chapels intended to ensure that their bas¬
tions would be impregnable, as well as to
pay tribute to the glory of the sovereign.
Similarly, during the Late Period, the temple
of Dakka was reconstructed on the ruins of
the Thutmosid sanctuaries, located on the
parallel which marked the end of the road to
the Wadi Allaqi gold mines (see page 34).
What was the fundamental concern of
Ramses II when he decided, several times in
the course of his long reign, to establish
cave-sanctuaries and hemispeos at Beit el
Wali, Gerf Hussein, Wadi es-Sebua, Derr,
North and South Abu Simbel, and Aksha?
At least seven such temples have been
found: six scattered from north to south
along the left bank of the Nile in Egyptian
Nubia, and one, the temple of Derr, on the
right bank. Seven sanctuaries, hewn or
erected along a 300-kilometre-long strip of
land, where the cultivated area was in some
places no more than TOO metres wide and
where by the time of the New Kingdom
many men were living and working in an
Egypt which had become their metropolis.
It has been suggested, with some
justification, that these temples may have
been a form of political propaganda. But this
hypothesis is not wholly satisfactory. It is
true that in the chief divinity worshipped in
each of these holy places may be found
traces of the gods of the Empire who, under
Ramses the Great, formed in an audacious
syncretism the image of the all-powerful.
This triunity, constituted by Amon, Re and
Ptah, was conceived of as a large body, con¬
trolled by a head, but powerless without all
its members. Amon, Re and Ptah were also
the three divine forms which protected the
armies of Ramses II at the battle of Kadesh
in 1285 BC, when the Egyptian army was
saved from defeat at the hands of the Hit¬
tites. The fourth army was placed under the
guidance of the god Seth, who was con¬
sidered to be beneficent under the Ramessi-
dle rulers since their family and ancestors
had adopted him as their protector. In his
Nubian temples, it is possible that the
audacity of the king, thus playing the role of
Seth, led him so far as to substitute statues
of himself for those of his divine ancestor.
For in each sanctuary the Pharaoh is in¬
cluded in the group of divinities. The royal
statue, sculpted in the recesses of the deep
rock caves and surrounded by divinities,
adopts the features of the godly form that
he represents in each of these holy places:
Ptah in the temple of Gerf Hussein; Amon at
Wadi es-Sebua; and Re at Derr. This prac¬
tice reaches its highest expression at Abu
Simbel, where the two cave-temples, the
most famous in the whole of upper Egyptian
Nubia, may help us to unravel part of the
mystery.
Set into the rock wall in the depths of the
great temple are four statues representing
Ptah, Amon, Ramses and Re-Horakhty
seated side by side. At the equinox, when
the first rays of sunlight appear on the
horizon and penetrate the temple, they
reach the divine figures in the depths of the
sanctuary, and Amon, the King and Re-
Horakhty are suddenly illuminated. Only the
shoulder of the earth-divinity, Ptah, who
decides when the earth's crust will split
open, permitting the growth of all living
things, is touched by the sun's rays. The
King, a god among gods, is linked on one
side to the hidden forces coming from the
south, personified by Amon of Napata, who
flows with and in the life-giving current of
the Nile. On the other side of the royal
statue, with Re-Horakhty, the King is touch¬
ed with the light and heat of the sun, which
is renewed each year on New Year's Day,
and he is assimilated into these forces of
light and heat.
Ramses II thus wished in his Nubian
monuments to express in material form his
total identity with the divine, of which he
was no longer the earthly offspring, but
would soon become the true incarnation.
When he had finished building these
temples throughout Nubia, he had left a
record in stone of a Pharaoh who had
become a god.
Thus the sculptor depicted him in the bas-
reliefs on the walls of the Wadi es-Sebua
sanctuary as the third figure in the triads of
gods. As a god he receives homage, and
pays homage in his turn, as King, to the
gods amongst whom he figures.
Ramses must have been in at least the for¬
tieth year of his reign when he returned to
his great temple at Abu Simbel, built long
before, and ordered the iconography to be
changed. His silhouette was to be inserted
This low-relief on a wall of the Great
Temple of Abu Simbel depicts scenes from
the battle of Kadesh, when Ramses II led
the Egyptian forces to victory over the
Hittite army. The Pharaoh, colossal in
proportion to the other figures, is holding a
council of war with a group of officers.
Upper frieze shows the charge of the
Hittite cavalry. Below, the Egyptian camp
can be seen protected by warriors armed
with shields; in the centre two spies are
forced to yield their secrets. Far right,
chariot-borne archers of Ramses ll's army.
Ramses II is here portrayed as a child.
Falling across his right temple is the tress
of hair, curled at the end, which indicates
his status as a royal child. The right index
finger touching the mouth is a convention
often used by the Egyptians to denote
childhood.
5 58 am 6.03 am
At certain times of the year, the rays of the
rising sun, after illuminating the colossal
figures on the façade of the Great Temple
of Abu Simbel. pierce no less than sixty
metres through the galleries and chambers
hewn into the mountainside until they
reach the very heart of the temple. Here, at
as that of the son-divinity of each divine
couple: on the south wall he takes the place
of Khonsu between Amon and Mut, and
between Ptah and Sekhmet he replaces
Nefertum.
In the light of these phenomena, Egyp¬
tologists have come to grasp the
significance of the figures on the temple
walls. Anyone who subscribes to the theory
that the many Ramesside sanctuaries were
designed as a means of political or even
religious propaganda must also admit that it
was the very presence of these monuments
which had an impact on the Nubians, for
they, like the Egyptians, were denied access
to the sanctuaries. Thus the rich
iconography adorning the walls had been
created solely as part of the internal func-
' V * . fi .1 il H il te - -3fe
¡i *
ssäL'
mx
litt mm
56
]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[
6.08 am 6 12 am
the far end of the inner sanctuary, they
pick out the seated figures of three
immortals: Ramses, the god Amon, and the
sun-god Re-Horakhty. A fourth statue
portraying Ptah the god of creation does
not fully emerge from the shadows. The
moment when the radiant sunlight
6.15 am
penetrated the darkness within the temple
must have coincided with a key stage in
the performance of the rites. To achieve
this astonishing play of light the Egyptian
architects and engineers left nothing to
chance in their choice of site nor in the
construction of the chambers within the
6.20 am
mountain. This series of photos showing
the gods at sunrise was taken on 19
October 1963. Today, rebuilt on its new site
high above the Nile, the temple faces in
exactly the same direction as before.
tioning of these sacred shrines. Its principal
role lay in the "sympathetic magic" it was
expected to perform: whatever was
represented in the temples was conjured in¬
to existence and became "operative" for all
eternity.
And so we can see why Ramses II should
have been determined to make some of the
reliefs in his great temple consonant with
the concept of royalty which he had
developed. Each year an important
ceremony would be held at Abu Simbel to
mark the predominant role of the sovereign
in Egyptian life and the sovereign's assimila¬
tion, once and for all, into the great cosmic
forces upon which Egypt relied.
Indeed, the meticulous study of the two
temples which we carried out when we
organized the Documentation Centre's
scientific survey in Nubia, has revealed how
closely related they were, paralleling, in fact,
the male-female relationship of the royal
couple. The temples were undoubtedly so
designed, by order of the Pharaoh, that the
axes of the two sanctuaries should converge
in the Nile. Similarly the northern temple, in
the direction associated with the female,
was dedicated to the queen while the
southern speos was reserved for the
Sovereign. The façades alone of Abu Simbel
present a striking resume of their imagery:
above the entrance of the great temple,
Ramses appears in all the power and
dynamism of majesty as the Sun-god, his
falcon-head dominated by the Heavenly
Body. This image is also a rebus, spelling
out the king's coronation* name.
îl'ÊS
The façade of the smaller temple is adorn¬
ed with two pink sandstone statues of the
young and radiantly beautiful Nefertari,
flanked by statues of the Pharaoh. She
seems ready to spring from the cliffside, to
stand radiant on the horizon.
The reason why the great Nubian temples
of Ramses (and probably even those built
before and after them) were implanted in
far-off Egyptian Nubia was undoubtedly
connected with the life-giving Nile, with the
Pharaoh's role as guarantor of the life and
wealth of Egypt, and with the responsibility
which in a sense he bore for the flooding of
the Nile.
The temples of Abu Simbel must have
been the site of most of the ceremonies
marking the return of the floodwaters which
each year brought renewed life to Egypt.
This miraculous annual inundation, which
inspired the Greek historian Hecataeus of
Miletus (late 6th century BC), well before
Herodotus, to write that Egypt was a gift of
the Nile, coincided with the 19th of July in
the Julian calendar and was announced in
the Egyptian sky by the reappearance of the
star Sothius, which had disappeared from
view seventy days before.
A few moments after the rising of the
star, and in approximately the same spot,
the sun would suddenly appear on the
horizon. This celebrated heliacal rising of
Sothius (Sirius) heralded the rejuvenation of
the earth and the beginning of the new year.
This New Year's Day also marked the King's
jubilee and the celebration of his revitaliza-
tion.
Late Egyptian texts tell us how on this oc¬
casion the King also made a mystic voyage
on the floodwaters of the Nile which had
come to regenerate the land of his
ancestors. It was at Abu Simbel, north of
the Second Cataract, where these flood-
waters entered Egyptian Nubia, that the
sanctuaries dedicated to the royal couple
provided the stage for a sublime mystery. It
was here that preparations were made for
the heliacal rising of Sothius. On the sand¬
stone façades the event was portrayed in the
forms of Nefertari-Sothius and Ramses-
Sun, the reinvigorated guarantors of the fer¬
tility of an Egypt whose eternal productivity
was heralded by the many offspring which
escorted their sacred images.
Christiane Desroches-Noblecourt
57
]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[
Sermons in stones
The musings of a modern Egyptian poet
before the temples of Abu Simbel
by Tewfik El Hakim
THE first time I went to Nubia was to
visit the temple of Abu Simbel on its
original site, before it was dismantled
and rebuilt on the top of the mountain in
order to protect it from flooding after con¬
struction of the High Dam. This grandiose
project of moving a temple from its resting-
place of three thousand years, without
changing any facet of it, and without mislay¬
ing a single stone, is one of the great
achievements of which Unesco may be just¬
ly proud.
We left Aswan by steamer for the south
where the famous temple stood with its four
statues representing Ramses II, with his wife
Nefertari at his side, Ramses immensely tall,
and the small figure of Nefertari barely
reaching up to her husband's knees.
The steamer ploughed through the Nile,
passing on either bank the houses of the Nu¬
bians, built of dark earth, on the walls of
which they had drawn figures and faces
which were striking in their simplicity and
their vivid colours. This art of drawing was
doubtless inherited from the distant past,
from their ancestors. I do not know whether
they were inspired by instinct or heredity, by
a secret awareness, by meditation or by a
deliberate will to imitation; for the Nubians
are simple folk. They live at one with the
silence of nature and the art of their
ancestors.
At last we reached the temple and the
boat was about to berth. " Ramses, im¬
pressive, with his four statues sculpted into
the mountain, and his wife Nefertari, seem¬
ed to be welcoming us.
After disembarking, we approached them
and I began to contemplate them... I felt
then that these figures of stone were not as
mute as one might think. They talk to each
other and understand each other, even
though no movement crosses their mo¬
tionless lips, and even though no-one hears
them.... But I did hear them; I knew what
TEWFIK EL-HAKIM, of Egypt, is one of the
great contemporary writers of the Arab world, he
drew on his experience as a magistrate for his
book The Magistrate's Diary; other well-known
works include The Confused Sultan, Schehere-
zade, Pygmalion, The Cave-Dweller and Fate of a
Cockroach. He was formerly Egypt's Permanent
Delegate to Unesco.
they were saying. ..perhaps because of the
spiritual bond that united us through time.
I cried out to them: "I am your son ! I hear
what you say !". And I took out a sheet of
paper and a pen to write down their strange
conversation. Looking up at the rising sun,
Ramses uttered these sybilline words:
"Every morning the Nile still flows at my
eight feet and the sun shines on my three
faces, since my fourth countenance has
been effaced by the hand of time."
Nefertari:
"That is so, my dear husband,
This morning is the same long morning;
and the sun lights up my four faces;
time does not obliterate my fourth face;
for I hide under the sky of your shadow".
Ramses:
"Yes, it is the sun on the East bank.
It appears through the hills covered with
golden wheat;
And the first monkey cries from the top of
my temple
And the sailor cries from the top of the sail:
A boat appears on the horizon
With shining white lances:
it has vanquished the black pirates;
sleep flies away from the eyelids
and birds fly away from their nests;
but everything is now asleep."
Nefertari:
"Yes, everything around us sleeps,
except the Nile which flows on:
the rings in its waves
resound like silver
as it washes the ground
next to our feet."
Ramses:
"Yes; it is the same long morning
unchangeable as the mountain;
And you and I are now part of the mountain.
And all the things around us disappear."
Nefertari:
"Only the Nile flows on
even when it dies;
Osiris rent in fragments
and from every fragment sprouts a blade of
grass.
From the countries of the North
where the sun deposits its gold on bare
heads,
From the countries of the South
where the vine and the olive tree grow ripe.
People come.
They come to make their offerings;
Fervour and admiration
shine in their eyes.
And it is a long unchanging morning
as old as thousands of years."
This was their conversation. Who can be
sure that they remained silent throughout
the centuries? Who can be sure that their
eyes of stone see less than our eyes of
glass? I feel that they know all there is to
know about the things around them. But do
they understand exactly what is going on
around them today? They see the boats
bringing admirers from the North and
South. Admiration is a feeling they know
well. They were admired when they were
flesh and bone and now this admiration is
given to their statues and their temple. They
know and understand this. But today, at
Abu Simbel a strange feeling assails them,
as if something unusual is about to happen.
They read it in the eyes blue, green, brown
and black that rest on them. They wonder
at the reason for such a host of visitors.
Why all these workmen, these boats, this
machinery, all this equipment and these
massive quantities of cement and concrete?
They also wonder what misfortune has
befallen these forsaken villages on both
banks of the Nile, which have remained as
silent as embalmed falcons.
Many events have taken place in more
than three thousand years: some powers
have been supplanted by others, and disap¬
peared; cults and religions have changed.
Only one thing has remained unchanged:
their firm conviction that they had been
placed for eternity on this spot which
touches the waters of the Nile: "You and I
are now part of the mountain and all the
things around us disappear." The
foreboding of some serious happening was
now clearly reflected on the face of Ramses.
I looked at each of his faces and on every
one of them I read the same concern.
Should I tell him the truth? When the visitors
had disappeared after the guide who was
telling them the story of the Pharaoh, I
stood alone in front of Ramses; I decided to
speak out, to tell-him the truth:
"Yes," I said, "something is about to hap¬
pen; something you will find hard to believe,
something which even I find astounding !"
The black pirates, the thieves of light, the
baboons, the sons of the sun, fell asleep on
the frieze of the temple awaiting the light of
day; Ramses could not shut his eyes. He
who had slept over the glories of yore began
58
]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[
\
^
^ v
*w
t
\
^
]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[
At the far end of the Inner
sanctuary in the Great Temple of
Abu Simbel are four statues
representing (from left to right) the
god Ptah of Memphis, the god
Amon of Thebes, Ramses II and the
god Re-Horakhty of Heliopolis (see
also photos on pages 56 and 57).
The statues and the bench on
which they are seated were hewn
out of the living rock of the
mountain. The faces have badly
deteriorated, and multicoloured
paintwork which once adorned the
sculptures has completely faded.
The forearms, which have almost
entirely disappeared from three of
the figures, may have originally
consisted of movable segments. A
sacred barque, shown in bas-relief
on the walls (not visible in photo)
may have stood on pedestal
in centre of the sanctuary.
h to be awakened from his dreams of the past
by sounds from the North; the sound of the
pick-axe breaking the rocks reverberated in
his head. And he whispered in his wife's ear:
"Can you hear that?" Nefertari too was
awake, and as anxious as her husband.
Ramses continued speaking: "Where are we
going? Can it be possible that we are being
moved after so many long centuries?"
In times gone by everything stayed in its
place. Man had genius, but nature was all-
powerful. The mountain was the mountain.
Man built temples and altars. He sometimes
copied the mountain: he built the Pyramids.
And there his power ended. But today he is
no longer satisfied with imitation. He is able
to transform nature itself according to his
wishes. The temple was situated at the foot
of the mountain. But the High Dam raised
the level of the waters of the Nile and the
temple is being moved to the top of the
mountain.
And the miracle came to pass. Ramses
and Nefertari could not really understand it.
But every now and again they were assailed
by doubt: Ramses looked at the Nile and
said: "It is strange, but I never realized that
the river was so low and our temple so
high!"
And Nefertari replied:
"What can you mean, my beloved husband?
The Nile is always the Nile".
"That may be so", replied Ramses, "but
the distance between the temple and the
river is no longer the same."
Nefertari laughingly replied: "Are you
suggesting that the temple has flown to the
top of the mountain like a bird?"
And Ramses went on: "This temple is no
longer where it used to be... But I do not
understand how that could have
happened".
And Nefertari answered: "Why do you
say that? Just look around you and you will
see that nothing has changed."
And Ramses looked around him. In the
distance he saw a half-clad peasant turning
a Shaduf to water his field; and he saw
another peasant working a plough drawn by
two cows. He could see the Sakieh. He saw
the same donkeys bearing the same palm-
leaf sacks. Everything was the same.... only
his temple had changed. And he could not
understand how it had come about.
Ramses thought that the God Ptah,
depicted on the wall of his temple, could
]]>
</page>
<page number="61">
<![CDATA[
supply him with the answer. But Ptah did
not know. He never went outside the tem¬
ple. He had seen nothing.
Ramses asked him if he had heard any
rumours of what was going on, from the
visitors who flocked to bring him offerings.
The God Ptah sighed and said:
"All I hear from my visitors are complaints
and petitions. They bring me offerings
which only benefit the priests". And he add¬
ed sadly: "I have always wanted people to
come and see me for the sake of friendship,
just to have a chat and give me news of the
outside world. That would have filled my
lonely hours and broadened my horizon, and
then I could have been able to advise you
sometimes".
"Why did you never ask us?"
"I did once, but my visitor did not under¬
stand."
"Perhaps he was afraid lest he wearied
you with useless chatter?"
A smile spread over the face of the God
Ptah, and he said:
"Useless chatter! That is all I ask for. You
can keep your offerings and your honours,
and give me a little bit of useless chatter!"
"Do you think that that is easy? The
priests only allow people into the temple if
they have petitions to make and offerings to
give".
"I do not want their offerings".
"You do not, but the priests do!"
And so my visit to Abu Simbel came to an
end. I took the boat back and thought of.
Ramses, Nefertari and the God Ptah as I
contemplated the beautiful landscape of
Nubia. For the Pharaoh and his wife I wish¬
ed for peace in their environment. I wished
that the God Ptah would find a friend, and I
prayed to Heaven to give me the chance to
go back to Abu Simbel.
Tewfik El Hakim
Photo of feluccas on the Nile (above) was taken around
1890 by G. Lekejian of Cairo. Below, the kiosk of Trajan at
Philae before the construction of the first Aswan Dam,
photographed by J. -P. Sebah around 1870. These rare
documents belong to the recently rediscovered historic
photographic collections of the Harvard Semitic Museum.
Photos © 1979, The President and Fellows of Harvard College for the Harvard Semitic Museum, Cambridge, USA
]]>
</page>
<page number="62">
<![CDATA[
IN 1895, the English archaeologist J.E.
Quibell, while excavating behind the
Ramesseum (the funerary temple of
Ramses II) at Thebes, discovered the tomb
of a doctor or a magician-medicine man.
Although the tomb had been looted, Quibell
recovered a large quantity of papyrus, with
hieratic writings dating from the end of the
Egyptian Middle Kingdom (approximately
1700 BC).
Amongst these writings were fragments
of famous literary works such as the Story
of Sinuhe, or the Tale of the Eloquent Pea¬
sant, but the discovery was especially
noteworthy because of one rather curious
text: a kind of index in which the words, ar¬
ranged in columns, were classified by
groups according to their meanings. Ap¬
parently, this papyrus had been used by the
Egyptian scribes as something like a dic¬
tionary or an encyclopaedia.
By modern criteria, this index must be
judged as rather haphazard, since after giv¬
ing a group of plant names, it goes on to a
series of names of birds, and then mam¬
mals, which is in turn followed by a list of
names of different kinds of bread and cakes,
cereals, and parts of the body. However, the
text then abruptly switches to a list of
geographical names, which are very well
classified, as they begin in the south and run
north, like the Nile.
One of the results of the excavations
The flooded
fortresses
of Nubia
by Jean Vercoutter
undertaken after Unesco's appeal of 8
March 1960 to save the treasures of Nubia,
was to identify positively, on site, and with
only one exception, the first fourteen
geographical names listed on the papyrus,
which is now well known to Egyptologists as
the "Ramesseum Onomasticon".
These names designate the fourteen for¬
tresses or fortified towns which defended
entry to Egypt in the south. They are: Sem¬
na South, Semna West, Semna East (or
Kumma), Uronarti, Shelfak, Askut,
Mirgissa, Buhen, perhaps Serra West or
Faras (the only doubtful case) and Serra
East, all of which are in Sudanese Nubia
(see map page 30), followed by Aniba, Kub¬
ban, Bigeh, and Elephantine, which are in
Egypt.
More than half of these fortresses are in
the most desolate but also the most
beautiful region of Sudanese Nubia. This
area, known as the "Batn-EI-Haggar" or
"Belly of Stone" is unfortunately now
covered by the backwaters of the Aswan
w #¿
]]>
</page>
<page number="63">
<![CDATA[
Photo Paul Almasy, Unesco, Paris.
The gigantic fortress of Buhen once
protected the strategic area of the Second
Cataract between Upper and Lower Nubia.
Excavations of the Egyptian strongholds on
the Nile, with their double rows of
ramparts, moats, jutting bastions and
massive outer walls (up to eight metres
thick at the base) have revealed the
sophistication of Pharaonic military
architecture. Archaeologists reckon that
over ten million sun-dried bricks were used
to build Buhen.
Aerial view, left, taken before
the beginning of the
International Nubian Campaign,
shows the Second Cataract of
the Nile. Quadrangular outline
on large island marks the
remains of the fortress of
Dabenarti. On the left bank of
the river stood the citadel of
Mirgissa, one of the most
powerful links in a chain of
strongpoints which defended
the southern approaches to
Egypt. The Nubian Campaign
shed new light on the
importance of these fortresses,
most of which are today
submerged beneath the waters
behind the High Dam.
High Dam. Before the dam came into ser¬
vice, this stretch of land extended from a
point slightly south of Buhen, approximately
at the latitude of Wadi Haifa, to the area
above the Dal Cataract, fifty kilometres
south of Semna. Here, in addition to other
rapids, are those of the Second or "Great"
Cataract whose noise, according to the
Greeks, was so loud that it actually deafened
the people who lived on the river banks.
The very fact that the ancient Egyptians
found it necessary to construct fortresses in
such a desolate region, to which access was
so difficult, is a problem in itself. Why did
they build such massive strongholds? Why
did they construct ramparts more than ten
metres high, and fortified doors that could
be defended both from the inside and the
outside, such as those at Mirgissa and
Buhen? Finally, why were two fortresses
often built, one to the west and the other to
the east of the Nile, both at the same level,
when a handful of determined men could
have blocked entry to the mountainous
gorges through which the river rushes in a
raging torrent?
Anyone who knows the wild landscape of
the Batn-EI-Haggar at first hand or has walk¬
ed through the enormous ruins of the now-
submerged fortresses, will realize why these
questions should be asked. What power
could have threatened Egypt to such a
degree that the Pharaohs of the 12th Dynas
ty (2000-1785 BC) felt compelled to build not
just isolated fortresses but veritable fortified
complexes in the passages which were the
most difficult to penetrate?
The rapids at Semna, already a very dif¬
ficult natural obstacle, were defended by
five fortresses. One was located upstream,
at Semna South, and two more, Semna
West and Kumma, were built on either side
of the barrier of rocks which forces the Nile
into a narrow channel which at low water is
only a few metres wide. As if these were not
sufficient, two more fortresses were built in
this veritable "fortified zone", downstream
from the first line of defence: one at Uronar-
ti, right in the middle of the narrow moun¬
tain gorge where the Nile emerges from the
Semna rapids, and the other at the end of
the same gorge, at Shelfak.
At the other end of Batn-EI-Haggar was
the defence complex of Mirgissa-Buhen,
with its advance post at Askut, a central l
nucleus at Mirgissa and an annex atr
JEAN VERCOUTTER, of France, is director of
the French Institute of Oriental Archaeology in
Cairo, and was formerly director 'of the Sudan
Antiquities Service. While professor of
Egyptology at the University of Lille he headed
the Franco-Argentine expedition to Aksha and
the French archaeological mission to Mirgissa. He
is the author of numerous works on ancient
Egypt.
63
]]>
</page>
<page number="64">
<![CDATA[
y Dabenarti, where the rapids of the Great
Cataract virtually prohibit the passage of
shipping, as Mohammed Ali's troops learn¬
ed to their cost in 1820 and Lord Wolseley's
in 1884-1885. Finally, at the northern end of
the complex, there was the fortified area of
Kor (Buhen South) and Buhen itself, along
with the two fortresses of Serra East
(Khesef-Medjayan in Egyptian) and Serra
West or Faras (Ink-taouy), which faced each
other across the river.
Obviously there must have been some
great danger 'for the Pharaohs to build ten
fortresses and two fortified camps in the
Batn-EI-Haggar area alone, to protect Egypt
from an aggressor coming from the south.
Egyptian texts reveal the identity of this ag¬
gressor: it was the land of Kush, whose
name appears on Egyptian monuments at
the very moment when the fortresses were
gradually being built along the river.
The potential danger that the land of Kush
represented for Egypt is clearly
demonstrated in a text written approximate¬
ly two centuries after the construction of the
great Pharaonic fortresses of Nubia. This
document is a dispatch which Apophis, the
Hyksos ruler of the northern, richer half of
Egypt sent to the ruler of Kush sometime
around 1580 BC.
This dispatch, it was learned from a stela
discovered in the temple of Karnak in 1954,
was intercepted by the Theban king
Kamosis, who explains: "I seized his
message south of the oasis, on the road to
Kush. It was a letter actually written in the
hand of the prince of Avaris [the stronghold
of the Hyksos kings in the Egyptian Delta]:
'I, Aouserre-Apophis, greet my son, the
prince of Kush... Are you aware of what
Egypt is inflicting upon me? Its prince
Kamosis is attacking me on my own ter¬
ritory... He has chosen to besiege two coun¬
tries so that he may oppress them: mine and
yours, and he is laying waste to them. Come
to the north, do not be afraid. He is now
fighting against my forces here. No one ex¬
pects to see you come into this part of
Egypt. I will hold him at bay until you arrive.
Then the two of us will divide up the Egyp¬
tian cities and your country will rejoice' ".
In the Karnak text, Kamosis makes no fur¬
ther reference to Kush and so we do not
know whether its ruler actually joined forces
with the Asiatic Hyksos. It may be doubted
that he did so. But this dispatch points clear¬
ly to the danger that threatened Egypt. At
any moment the country faced the risk of
having to fight simultaneously on two
fronts: in the Delta or the Syro-Palestinian
corridor against Asiatics attracted by the
wealth of Egypt, and in Nubia when Nubia
was united and hostile.
This permanent danger explains why, on
the one hand, the Egyptian rulers of the
Middle Kingdom who already had to face
Asiatic incursions in the north, attempted to
consolidate their southern frontier by
building the fortified defence system I have
described, and on the other hand, why the
Pharaohs of the 18th and 19th Dynasties
would not rest, from 1580 until 1300 BC, un¬
til they had occupied the entire territory of
Kush.
Nevertheless,, the fortresses of Batn-EI-
Haggar were not constructed for strategic
reasons alone. They were also intended to
protect and control the river route which led
from Egypt to the resources of Africa, for
the land of Kush, inhabited by the Nehesyu,
supplied Egypt over a long period with many
64
commodities including cattle, wood (espe¬
cially ebony), incense, ivory, semi-precious
stones, and "tropical" products such as
giraffes' tails, ostrich feathers and eggs, and
the leopard skins worn by Egyptian priests
when officiating at funerals. Live giraffes,
cheetahs and monkeys were also imported.
During the Middle Kingdom gold was added
to this list of goods. However, as early as
the third millennium BC, it was as a source
of manpower and primarily military man¬
power that Egypt looked to the south. The
"scouts" of Kamosis's army which fought
against the Hyksos in the Delta were Nu¬
bians.
Thus the Nubian fortresses performed a
military role by protecting Egypt from a
massive invasion by the redoubtable war¬
riors who throughout the ages lived in what
is today the Sudan, and by providing
jumping-off points for expeditions launched
in the south, along the Nile or the desert
routes. The army of Sesostris III set out
from Semna (1880-1850 BC) and crossed the
rapids of the Dal Cataract, thus preparing
the way for the annexations by the Pharaohs
of the 18th Dynasty of the entire region bet¬
ween Batn-EI-Haggar and the Third
Cataract.
Certain rather curious documents dis¬
covered with the "Ramesseum
Onomasticon" reveal another aspect of the
fortresses' military activities, that of wat¬
ching over the desert routes. These
documents, known to Egyptologists as the
Semna Dispatches, were copies of letters in¬
tended for the archives which the com¬
manders of the fortresses exchanged
amongst themselves and sent to the central
authorities. According to these texts,
patrols of Egyptians and Medja, Nubian
mercenaries enlisted in the Egyptian army,
Photo André Vila © French Archaeological Mission to the Sudan
were regularly sent into the desert. There
they often detained groups of nomads
which were brought back to the fortresses
for interrogation. The nomads were then
sent back to their own regions, after "being
given bread and beer", as the Dispatches
put it. In this way the Pharaohs were always
kept informed about what was happening in
the south and could be forewarned and
forearmed in the case of a raid on Egypt by
the Nehesyu.
The second role of the fortresses was to
maintain and promote freedom of move¬
ment on the Egyptian routes leading south.
This is why the Mirgissa slipway (see photo
this page) was constructed to enable the
boats which plied between Egypt and Nubia
to be dragged around the Great Cataract.
The "dam" built at Semna by Amenemhet
III (1850-1800 BC) fulfilled the same role
since, by raising the water level of the Nile
when it was at its lowest point, it improved
the flow of traffic along the river and made it
easier to cross Batn-EI-Haggar.
A hieroglyphic text discovered at Semna
itself sums up the dual purposes of the for¬
tresses. It is engraved on a granite stela
which Sesostris III set up in Semna West
and reads as follows: "Southern boundary
[of Egypt] made in the year 8, under the ma¬
jesty of the King of Upper and Lower Egypt,
Sesostris III, in order to prevent any
Nehesyu from crossing it, by travelling to
the north, by land or ship, or with any
Nehesyu herds; with the exception of
Nehesyu who shall cross it for purposes of
trade in Iken or any authorized, profitable
business with them, but without allowing a
ship of the Nehesyu to pass beyond Heh,
northwards, forever".
This text has been interpreted as evidence
of the first colour bar in history. However,
this is incorrect since the Nehesyu were pro-
Left, the remains of a
two-metre-wide slipway
used for dragging boats
around the rapids of the
Second Cataract of the
Nile, impassable during
the low water season.
Discovered beneath
several centimetres of
sand, it originally
consisted of a layer of
slippery Nile mud
reinforced with wooden
crosspieces, which
perished long ago.
]]>
</page>
<page number="65">
<![CDATA[
hibited from entering Egypt not because
they were "blacks" but because they
belonged to a nation which, in terms of
power, presented a danger to the in¬
habitants of the lower valley of the Nile.
Nonetheless, the text clearly emphasizes
both the military role of the Nubian for¬
tresses in preventing an invasion from the
south, and their economic role in facilitating
and promoting trade with the same area.
We now know that the Iken referred to in
the Semna stela is Mirgissa, and that Heh is
probably the rock of Abousir which marks
the end of Batn-EI-Haggar when travelling
from the south.
Thanks to the campaigns for the
safeguarding of Nubia, we now know more
about the role played by the Nubian fort¬
resses in Egyptian history. The excavations
at Buhen, Mirgissa, Askut and Semna
South have shown how the construction of
the forts was perfectly adapted to the terrain
and have demonstrated the extraordinary
complexity of their architecture, with their
double ramparts, high and low, their
loopholes arranged so as to permit all possi¬
ble angles of fire, and their amazingly strong
outer walls, in some places eight metres
thick at their base.
These excavations have also furthered our
knowledge of garrison life. The military
posts were isolated in a hostile region and
the physical protection afforded by the
strongholds was not felt to be sufficient.
Therefore a kind of supernatural protection
was provided by magical texts engraved on
vessels and statuettes, which were "killed"
and buried in areas which the enemy was
sure to cross, thus acting as veritable magic
"mines". Such texts have been discovered
both at Mirgissa and Uronarti. All the
fortresses were undoubtedly protected by
similar texts.
As the troops were stationed throughout
the year in these fortresses, they had
gardens and presumably orchards to provide
them with vegetables and fresh fruit, which
supplemented the regular rations sent from
Egypt in packages whose official seals have
been found by the thousands. Excavations
north of the fortress at Mirgissa have unear¬
thed the homes of "civilians" who may have
organized trade with the south. We have
discovered the hearths where they baked
their bread, the large jars in which they
brewed their beer and the bowls from which
they drank.
The temples rebuilt in stone during the
reoccupation of the fortresses under the
New Kingdom (1580-1200 BC) at Semna
West, Kumma and Buhen, show that
religion was still powerful and that alongside
the troops, some of which, according to the
Semna Dispatches were recruited locally,
lived priests, scribes, artists and artisans.
They exchanged letters, copies of which
have been found near the Ramesseum at
Thebes, and also moulded and painted the
remarkable funeral masks found at the
necropolis of Mirgissa.
Exploration of the Nubian fortresses has
thus yielded outstanding results. Never¬
theless, we should not forget the destruc¬
tion of the edifices themselves, submerged
beneath the waters of the new lake. Of
course, it has been possible to dismantle the
stone temples and transport them to Khar¬
toum, but the lofty constructions which
commanded the noble and savage beauty of
Batn-EI-Haggar have disappeared forever.
Jean Vercoutter
Six hundred metres from the mighty
fortress of Mirgissa which kept
watch over the rapids of the Second
Cataract, archaeologists discovered
in a pit a cache of magic
"execration" texts and figurines. In
order to '"kill" their enemies, the
defenders of Mirgissa scratched the
texts on to ceramic vessels which
were ritually smashed and buried.
Many figurines covered with texts
(right) were also found in the pit.
Photos André Vila © French Archaeological Mission to the Sudan
The pillars of the temple built by
Amenophis III (1402-1364) at Soleb in
Sudanese Nubia are carved with about a
hundred enigmatic human portraits and
Inscriptions whose significance has long
been debated by specialists. Each portrait
shows the bust of a man whose hands are
tied behind his back; beneath it is a kind of
cartouche or frame bearing the name of the
man, his people or a region of Africa or
Asia from whence he came. This portrait
shows an African, identifiable by his
beardless face, his earring and his
headdress. His accompanying name is
Tirtir. It was once thought that the figure
depicted the Pharaoh's prisoners, but
according to another theory these images
of submission had a magical significance,
representing peoples over which some kind
of spell had been cast.
65
]]>
</page>
<page number="66">
<![CDATA[
-ai. -T - A" __ .
Photo © Georg Gerster © Rapho, Paris
S% >i. V * V.
Left, gateway leading to
the inner courtyard of a
house on the island of
Argo in Upper Nubia
(Sudan). According to
custom, the decoration is
an integral part of the
architecture, except for
the three plates set into
the upper part of the
structure and, a curious
detail, the headlamp in
the centre of the arch.
Facing page, a Nubian
works the shaduf, an
ancient irrigation device
used for watering the
small riverside plots of
cultivated land.
The blessed land
by Robert A. Fernea
WHENEVER Nubians gather togeth¬
er, they speak of the past, of Old
Nubia, the "blessed land", which
stretched from Aswan south across the
Egyptian border into Dongola in the Sudan,
and which now lies under water. In Kom
Ombo, Egypt, where the majority of Egyp¬
tian Nubians were resettled, the people
wonder whether it will ever be possible to
return to this "blessed land" and settle on
the shores of the new lake. What was this
"blessed land" which is discussed with such
nostalgia ? And who are the people who liv¬
ed there ?
During the Nubian ethnographic survey,
which took place from 1961 to 1964,
66
American and Egyptian social scientists
made an effort to describe the society and
culture of Old Nubia before it disappeared
forever.
What we discovered was that culturally
there was no single Nubian people.
Moreover, the people in Nubia had met a
diversity of environmental circumstances
with a wide range of adaptive social
responses. The emergence of "Nubian" as a
social identity in Egypt, now shared by all
peoples from south of Aswan, has been the
product of the traumatic experience these
diverse people share : the flooding of their
villages and the loss of their homeland.
The first Aswan Dam, built in 1902 and
heightened in 1913 and 1933, flooded all the
communities of Egyptian Nubia, stretching
along the Nile on either side of the valley.
The communities in the north were totally
ROBERT A. FERNEA, of the United States, is
professor of anthropology and Middle Eastern
Studies at the University of Texas, Austin. From
1961 to 1964 he directed the Nubian
Ethnographical Survey, a project financed by the
Ford Foundation and administered through the
Social Research Centre, the American University
of Cairo. He is the author of Nubians in Egypt:
Peaceful People, University of Texas Press, 1973,
for which Georg Gerster did the photographs.
]]>
</page>
<page number="67">
<![CDATA[
flooded, and the houses were moved to high
rocky ground. Those in the south lost only a
portion of their agricultural land. This was
the reason why during the time of our study,
some northern villages had no resident adult
males, while in the southern districts and in
the Sudan, more than fifty per cent of the
male population was present. Thus the rates
of migration from Nubia to the cities were
high throughout the region, but varied
greatly, depending on the quantity of arable
land available in particular areas.
Language was not a uniting factor in the
old days. From north to south in Egyptian
Nubia, the people spoke three mutually
unintelligible languages: Kenuzi, Arabic,
and Mahasi. However, Kenuzi, the northern
language, was close enough to the
Dongolawi language spoken in the Sudan
that these two groups could communicate.
Thus there are really only two living Nubian
languages: Kenuzi-Dongolawi and Mahasi.
Arabic was the exclusive language of
villagers in the central area of Egyptian
Nubia, near Wadi el Arab.
After government schools were opened in
Nubia in the 1940s, Arabic was taught to all
the children in Nubia, and by the time our
study was made, the majority of Kenuzi and
Mahasi speaking men (and many women)
spoke Arabic in addition to their native Nu¬
bian language, and this was true of nearly all
the children. In addition, individual men
spoke English, French, German, and Italian
according to their experiences as labour
migrants.
Before the flooding and the trauma of
resettlement, the great majority of Nubian
people were far more likely to travel to Cairo
for work than to another Nubian community
only a few miles away. Indeed, we met Nu¬
bian men who had lived in Europe and the
United States but had never set foot in a Nu¬
bian district other than their own. Working
in Egyptian embassies abroad and in the
homes of foreign diplomats, individual Nu¬
bians came home with knowledge of various
parts of the world, both east and west.
This knowledge of customs, geography,
politics, styles of lifewas widely shared
through conversations and anecdotes which
travelled through the Nile-side villages more
easily than the people. Thus Nubian people
combined inward and outward perspectives,
attitudes both cosmopolitan and provincial;
they knew Egypt and Europe from their own
experiences and those of friends and
relatives, but they were not familiar with all
of Nubia.
Historically, the men of Nubia were
known in Egypt as domestic servants, but
by the time our studies were made the Nu¬
bian urban migrants had begun to make in¬
roads into the professions, as well as into
factory work and other blue collar jobs; in
fact, the profile of their employment in
various sectors of the urban economy was
similar to that of other Egyptians.
In Old Nubia, agriculture was the basis of
subsistence despite an almost total absence
of rain. The Nile was used to water the land
with both modern and ancient mechanisms.
The shaduf, a weighted water bucket which
swung a few gallons of water at a time up
from the river, sufficed to irrigate the small
plots of soil which had been dredged up on¬
to sand and rocks after the first Aswan Dam
was built. The shaduf, common in northern
Nubia, was used in Pharaonic times and is at
least 3,000 years old! But in districts such as
Ballana and Dakka, modern diesel pumps ir¬
rigated larger areas of land, basins. of clay
soils which were admittedly not so fertile as
the river banks, but which helped make up
for some of the land flooded by the First
Aswan Dam.
Further south, distinctive hand-hewn
waterwheels were used, particularly in
Adendan and the Sudan. These chains of
buckets, turned by cattle power and often
co-operatively owned, could irrigate an acre
or more of land. The waterwheels were in¬
troduced in Roman times and permitted a
significant increase in the Nubian population
by opening up higher areas of fertile land
along the river.
Almost all that was grown in Old Nubia
was locally consumed or otherwise utilized,
down to the last strip of palm fibre.
Vegetables and grains were eaten locally, as
were most of the dates of the south. Sur¬
prisingly, the one agricultural cash crop of
the region which was exported was animals.
Though the desert which tightly bordered
the narrow valley offered little grazing or ^
fodder, the fallow lands and fields were, f
Photo Abdel Fattah Eid © Robert Fernea, Austin, USA
]]>
</page>
<page number="68">
<![CDATA[
> after harvest, important sources of fodder
for the sheep, goats and cattle.
Furthermore, fodder could be quickly
grown in the summer when the dam was
open, on land covered by water the rest of
the year. The exportable animals were car¬
ried to market in Aswan or Wadi Haifa on
the Sudanese post boats and the lateen-
sailed feluccas.
Despite the often ingenious uses of the
bits and pieces of land available. Old Nubia
remained a minimal subsistence area
throughout its recent history. Food was
sometimes in short supply in parts of Nubia
and many residents depended on remit¬
tances from sons and husbands working in
the cities. On the other hand, the housing
was far more spacious than most families
would have been able to afford in Cairo or in
other Egyptian villages. The rectangular
walls of the southern homes, for example,
often contained two courtyards, guest
rooms, a summer kitchen and a winter kit¬
chen in addition to family rooms. Enclosures
for animals were built outside, near to the
houses.
However, such homes were rarely oc¬
cupied at the same time by all the people
with ownership rights to the property. Most
residents of the houses we visited could list
several men, often married and with
families, who had a room or a storage space
in their Nubian house, but who lived
elsewhere. Thus Old Nubia was a land of
large partially empty homes, ready to pro¬
vide living space for visiting kinsmen at
times of marriage, childbirth, sickness,
unemployment, or festivals. Twice as many
people were considered residents of Egyp¬
tian Nubia as the 50,000 who actually lived
there. Nubia was a refuge and a shelter for
its absent natives, all of whom were con¬
sidered part owners of the "blessed land".
The architecture of the houses in Old
Nubia was admired by visitors and was a
source of pride for the residents. Rebuilt
since the last heightening of the Old Aswan
Dam in 1933, these homes combined
elements from both Pharaonic and Islamic
styles in a manner which was distinctively
Nubian. Whitewashed and brightly decora¬
ted, plastered with mud and straw, the
homes throughout Nubia were a sign of the
twentieth century prosperity and security.
In the northern Kenuz region, the house
roofs over the guest or bridal rooms were
barrel-vaulted with mud bricks, an older pat¬
tern restored to this region after the flooding
from the first dam killed the palm trees
which once provided roof beams. Here,
where only sand and rock were left above
high water levels, paint and whitewash
restored some of the colour which nature
could no longer provide. Only a small frac¬
tion of the native villagers could live in these
communities; lack of productive means in
northern Nubia had forced the majority of
men and many of the women and children
to live in the cities of Egypt. It was the
moulids, celebrations of saints' days, which
annually reunited many of the migrants with
their relatives in the villages.
The moulids were offered by different
tribally organized villages, each of whom
sponsored the ceremonies for certain
Muslim saints. Processional visits to the
cenotaphs of the holy men, accompanied by
prayers and supplications, were the major
purposes of the moulids. However, dancing
and feasting were also part of the occasion,
along with visits from travelling merchants.
Boatloads of Nubians from neighbouring
villages were added to the city migrants. The
latter were expected to combine their efforts
and financial resources with the resident
villagers to host such occasions.
Southern Nubia was quite different. Here
in districts such as Abu Simbel, Ballana and
Adendan, the effects of the old Aswan Dam
were minimal and vegetation was still lux¬
uriant, with fields of millet and other- crops
green in season along with palm groves fur¬
ther inland, a rich landscape watered by the
Nile. As in the Sudanese Nubian villages
(which continued uninterrupted along the
river to Wadi Haifa and beyond) the tradi¬
tional pattern of life had not been changed
by the Aswan dam and the annually renew¬
ed alluvial soils continued to be farmed as
they had been for thousands of years. In the
southern area, moulids were not as common
as in the north, but the activities of farming
often involved communal labour. Land and
palm trees were owned by co-inheritors and
linked many members of the communities
4 Photo © P.A. Interpress. National Museum, Warsaw
Shown here are four examples, taken from different historical periods, of the crescent
moon and horn designs which the Nubians have used as decorative motifs since very early
times. (1) On the façade of a modern house near Serra; (2) On a bronze statue of Isis;
between the horns is a moon-disc; (3) On a 4th-century-AD king's crown of silver and semi¬
precious stones. The crown was discovered in a tomb at Ballana in Egyptian Nubia. Beneath
the crescent is a ram's head, another typical Nubian motif; (4) In a wall-painting of Christ
protecting an eparch, discovered in the cathedral of Faras (see also page 2). The eparch
was an official who functioned as the metropolitan or bishop of a province. His most
important attribute was his helmet-like crown topped by a crescent mounted on a rod.
]]>
</page>
<page number="69">
<![CDATA[
economically along with the social ties of
kinship and marriage.
Marriages in particular were occasions for
three days and nights of dancing and
feasting in the Mahasi speaking region,
bringing together men and women from
villages and districts up and down the Nile.
The flat-roofed homes of the south did not
need such elaborate decoration as in the
northern region. Even the dresses of the
women were the more sombre gar-gara-s,
long-trained robes of filmy black material.
The rich land covered with productive fields,
grazed by many animals, and farmed by men
and women, provided the colour and beauty
which all of Nubia had once enjoyed. The
dignified dancing of the women, the athletic
line dancing of the men were joyous celebra¬
tions in this setting; even though many men
were absent as migrant workers the Mahasi-
speaking areas of Egyptian and Sudanese
Nubia were still a setting where both
ceremonial and subsistence activities provid¬
ed a busy yearly schedule of activity for all
the residents.
As our research progressed, we found
that though the villagers of Nubia were
clustered along the banks of great rivers,
much of their economic condition and life
styles resembled that of the oases societies
in the Sahara to the west. For example,
migration has long been a way of life for
many of these oases, in Libya, Algeria and
Morocco. As in Nubia, distance and ter¬
ritorial isolation both protect the local com¬
munities from too much outside interference
and force some of the inhabitants to leave
when the absolute limits of the local
resource base are reached.
We found that for the people of Nubia,
the more obligatory it was to leave Nubia,
the more blessed Nubia became: a land of
security for families, a place of marriage, the
true home among one's own people.
Yet the advantages of the city were also
well understood. Better medical care, better
schools for the children, and above all better
job opportunities were primary considera¬
tions. As in other parts of the world, some
preferred country life and others preferred
life in the cities. Nubians who became doc¬
tors and judges, who became part of the
middle class in the cities, were less likely to
return to their villages of origin.
Nubia was also the home of several
minorities, each of whom responded to the
limited economic opportunities in their own
way. The Halabi, for instance, were pedlars,
who traded toys and trinkets for handfuls of
dates from children and women during the
harvest season. Arabs, such as the Ababda,
were also visitors to the villages, occasional¬
ly marrying Nubian women and settling
down in the communities. Sayiidi farmers
from Upper Egypt worked the land exposed
in the north for two months each summer
while the dam was opened, sharecropping
for the Kenuzi women looking after the
family property. The crops of melon they
produced were found in the Aswan market.
Other Sayiidi fished up and down the Nile or
worked in pump irrigated projects.
In terms of integrating outsiders into
the Nubian communities or transforming
Nubian migrants into urban Egyptians, mar¬
riage has been of key importance. The
cultural and social integrity of Nubia, as
witnessed by the preservation of the Nubian
languages, has been maintained. This has
been true because of the relative isolation of
the region and because Nubians could draw
upon the economic opportunities of the
cities for support.
Nubian history reveals an enduring pat¬
tern of biocultural adaptation; infusions of
foreign peoples into Nubia have been slow
and steady rather than radical and over¬
whelming. When social change is mediated
by kinship and marriage the languages and
traditions, the skills and abilities of the com¬
munities are not lost. Neither migration from
Nubia nor into Nubia ever seems to have
totally disrupted the continuity of local
life till the last decade.
The relocated Egyptian Nubians in New
Nubia are now part of the Aswan-Kom Om¬
bo population and must accept the full im¬
pact of Egyptian life on their new com¬
munities. Arabic is the language of business
and politics, the source of personal ad¬
vancement in the competitive milieu of
modern Egyptian life; everyone is learning it.
But if Old Nubia is now only a memory, it is
nonetheless of great importance, for it
unites the Nubians of Egypt in their new
roles as an ethnic group.
The "blessed land" is thus still of great
importancejust as it was to migrants in
past times who were often unable to return
for year after year. The effort to convince
the Egyptian Government to explore the
possibilities of settlement along the shores
of the new lake now unites many Egyptian
Nubians in a common cause. Already some
preliminary studies are underway and
perhaps one day new villages may be built
near the old ones which have now melted
away.
Robert A. Fernea
The circle painted on the wall meant that
this house was doomed to disappear
beneath the waters of the Aswan High
Dam. The inhabitants had to abandon their
homeland for a new life far from the
"blessed land" of Nubia.
Photo Gunvor Jorgsholm Pressehuset, Copenhagen
]]>
</page>
<page number="70">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 24
princes. Thus it seems natural to assume
that tombs which are mainly Egyptian but
deviate in some details from the orthodox
model should also be regarded as belong¬
ing to Nubians.
A third tomb is quite as instructive. The
tomb in Thebes (modern Luxor) of the
Viceroy Huy, who governed Nubia for the
famous king Tutankhamun, contains a
series of paintings showing how he levied
the taxes in Lower Nubia. Among the tax¬
payers is a dark-skinned man, dressed as
an Egyptian but with some exotic additions
to his dress; he has, moreover, a typical
non-Egyptian face. The text calls him
Heka-nefer, "the Great One of Miam",
which is the name of the administrative
centre of Lower Nubia (Aniba in modern
times).
One of the sensations of the Nubian
Campaign was that Professor Simpson
from Boston found the tomb of this Nubian
prince, a figure well known since the early
days of Egyptology, thereby definitely pro¬
ving that Heka-nefer was a historical per¬
son and not simply a conventional figure in
Egyptian iconography (see page 44).
Now, thanks to the titles of these Nubian
princes we know that they were all
educated at the Eygptian court together
with the Egyptian princes, that they then
pursued the usual career of an Egyptian of¬
ficial and were finally sent to rule their
countrymen in their home district of Nubia.
In Nubia there was also an Egyptian
Viceroy with a staff of Egyptian officials,
and the tribute lists show that slaves and
raw materials, such as gold, minerals, cat¬
tle, African wood, and exotic African
goods, were exported from Nubia to
Egypt. Egyptian goods, not mentioned in
the official texts, but occurring in the
tombs of Lower Nubia, demonstrate that
there was at least to some extent a return
traffic from Egypt.
Lower Nubia seems to have been a
flourishing colony, to the benefit both of
the rulers and of their subjects. But this
situation gradually changed during the
New Kingdom, to judge from the decreas¬
ing number of tombs and cemeteries which
can be dated to the later half of this period.
In fact, in the thirteenth century, when
Ramses II built his famous temples in
Lower Nubia Abu Simbel, Wadi es
Sebua, and Derr the population of Nubia
was rapidly becoming smaller.
Very few tombs can be dated to his reign
and practically no traces of settlements,
although enough is preserved to show that
it was not a period of a total vacuum. The
temples needed a certain number of priests
and servants to function, so we must not
exaggerate the implications of the scarcity
of archaeological remains.
On the other hand further south, in
Dongola, outside the area of the Nubian
Campaign, big cities of Ramesside times
have been discovered, which show that the
economic centre of the Nubian colony had
shifted southwards and that Nubia had
become only a country of transit to richer
regions further south. Later, owing to the
disruption of the Egyptian State, this part
of the colony also declined and about 1000
BC there is no longer any trace of Egyptian
rule.
I Torgny Säve-Söderberg
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 47
son for this act of toleration. Closure of the
temples of Philae would have met with
strong resistance from the inhabitants of
Nubia, especially from the Blemmyes, a war¬
like people from the eastern desert who had
long caused trouble to the Roman authori¬
ties by their raids on Upper Egypt. In AD
451-452 Maximinus, the general of the
Emperor Marcian, led an expedition against
them and defeated them.
A treaty ensued, by which the Blemmyes
undertook to keep the peace for a hundred
years and, in return, they were allowed to
offer sacrifices at Philae and even to borrow
the sacred image of Isis periodically for the
purpose of obtaining oracles.
Before the expiry of this pact, however,
Justinian sent his general, Narses, around
AD 536, to put an end to the last outpost of
paganism in the empire. The temple of Isis
was closed, the priests were disbanded and
the statues transported to Constantinople.
Soon afterwards, the hypostyle hall was
converted by bishop Theodorus into a
church, dedicated in the name of St.
Stephen, and a Christian community settled
on the island.
During this new phase in Philae's history,
which lasted until the 11th - 13th centuries,
very considerable damage was done to the
monuments. Blocks were extracted from the
monuments and re-used, some in the buil¬
ding of a Coptic church and others in the
construction of a street.
Fortunately the hieroglyphic inscriptions,
both in the temple of Isis and in the other
surviving buildings, have generally been
spared deliberate mutilation. One text on the
north wall of Hadrian's vestibule, in front of
a figure of Mandulis, is dated by an accom¬
panying note in Demotic to 24 August, AD
394; it is thus the latest datable example of
the hieroglyphic script now known.
The Christian iconoclasts also left unda¬
maged many hundreds of Demotic and
Greek graffiti, some written by priests and
others by pilgrims who regularly came to
Philae, either simply to pay homage to Isis or
to seek her intervention in obtaining relief
from their ailments.
Here again, Philae has preserved the latest
known examples of one of the three scripts
in which the Egyptian language was
written in this instance Demotic, a cursive
script ultimately derived from hieroglyphics.
This graffito, which is dated to 2 December,
AD 452 was written by a priest named Esmet
on a wall of one of the Osiris chambers of
the temple of Isis. It shows that knowledge
of the ancient language was not completely
lost as long as Philae continued to serve the
needs of the worshippers of Isis.
Philae, moreover, preserved one inscrip¬
tion which proved invaluable in the recovery
of that knowledge after it had been forgot¬
ten for more than a thousand years. It was a
Greek inscription on the pedestal of an obe¬
lisk which bore a hieroglyphic inscription.
The texts were not two versions of the same
document, one in Greek and the other in
Egyptian, but both mentioned Cleopatra III,
a wife of Ptolemy VII, Euergetes II, and it
was the recognition of her name in the hie¬
roglyphic inscription of the obelisk, when
combined with the previously uncorrobora¬
ted identification of the name of Ptolemy on
the Rosetta Stone, which provided the star¬
ting point in the decipherment of the hie¬
roglyphic script.
lorwerth E.S. Edwards
Further reading on
the Nubian Campaign
and Nubian History
Nubia, Corridor to Africa, by Wil¬
liam Y. Adams. Allen Lane, London,
1977. 797 pp. (£19.50)
Nubian Rescue, by Rex Keating.
Robert Hale and Co., London, and Haw¬
thorn Books, Inc., New York, 1975. 269
pp. (£3.80)
Africa in Antiquity. The Arts of
Ancient Nubia and the Sudan. The
catalogue of an exhibition with the same
title, organized by the Brooklyn
Museum. 1978. Published in two vo¬
lumes by the Division of Publishing and
Marketing Services, The Brooklyn
Museum, Eastern Parkway, Brooklyn,
New York 11238.
The Salvage of the Abu Simbel
Temples, Concluding Report, Decem¬
ber 1971. Vattenbyggnadsbyran (VBB)
Consulting Engineers and Architects,
Stockholm, Sweden. 1976.
Nubian Twilight, by Rex Keating.
Rupert Hart-Davis, London, 1962.
111 pp.
Kalabsha: The Preserving of the
Temple, by G.R.H. Wright. Gebr. Mann
Verlag GmbH., Berlin, 1972.
Campagne Internationale de
I'Unesco pour la Sauvegarde des
Sites et Monuments de Nubie:
Bibliographie. A bibliography prepared
by Louis Christophe (in French only).
Unesco, 1977. 123 pp.
Nubian Treasure, An Account of the
Discoveries at Ballana and Qustul, by
Walter B. Emery. Methuen Ltd., Lon¬
don, 1948. 72 pp. with 48 plates and 10
maps and plans.
The Scandinavian Joint Expedition
to Sudanese Nubia, by Torgny Säve-
Söderbergh. A lecture prepared for the
Danish Academy of Sciences and Let¬
ters; distributed by Munksgaards Bog¬
handel, Copenhagen. The Scandinavian
Joint Expedition to Sudanese Nubia has
published nine volumes of results under
the General Editorship of Torgny Säve-
Söderbergh: 1. The Rock Drawings;
2. Preceramic Sites; 3. Neolithic and
A-Group Sites; 4. C-Group, Pangrave
and Kerma Sites; 5. Pharaonic New
Kingdom Sites; 6. Late Nubian
Cemeteries; 7. Late Nubian Sites,
Churches and Settlements; 8. Tex¬
tiles; 9. Human Remains. Africana
Publishing Corporation, 101 Fifth Ave¬
nue, New York, N.Y. 10003.
Unesco has produced or co-produced a
number of 16 mm. films on aspects of
the Nubian campaign. They include
Report on Philae, The World Saves
Abu Simbel and Philae in the Saving.
A Unesco television programme on the
campaign, Victory in Nubia (16 mm.
52 mins., colour) will shortly be avai¬
lable.
For information about the distribution of
these films please apply to the Press and
Audio-Visual Information Division,
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700
Paris.
70
]]>
</page>
<page number="71">
<![CDATA[
The peopling
ofancient
Egypt
and the deciphering
of Meroitic
script A new Unesco series...
...on African history
The general
history
oíAfrica
Studies and
documents t
(yresoo
Who were the people of Ancient Egypt? Where did they come
from? These are two of the questions examined in The Peopling of
Ancient Egypt and the Deciphering ofMeroitic Script. This book is
the first in a new Unesco series of publications, the 'General His¬
tory of Africa: Studies and Documents', based on symposia and
seminars held in connexion with the preparation of the General
History ofAfrica. The first part of the work attempts to unravel evi¬
dence about the origins of the ancient Egyptians as it appears to
anthropologists, historians, ethnologists, specialists in linguistics
and human palaeontologists. The second part examines possible
interpretations of a language used in what is now part of the Sudan
between the 8th century BC and the 4th century AD. Also discuss¬
ed: questions of transcription and the relationship of the Meroitic
language to other languages of Africa.
136 pages 25 francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscrip¬
tion rates in local currency, will be supplied
on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P.O.
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne (Victoria), 3000.
AUSTRIA. Dr. Franz Hain, Verlags-und Kommissionsbuch¬
handlung, Industriehof Stadlau, Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasse 5, 1220
Wien. - BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. - CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7. - CHINA. China National Publications Import Corpora¬
tion, West Europe Department, P.O. Box 88, Peking
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box
1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena
51, Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura, 11 Sou-
kenicka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. - Publishers,
Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava - CSSR. - DENMARK.
Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Norregade, DK 1165, Copenha¬
gen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for
Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo. -
ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis
Ababa. - FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1,
SF-00100 Helsinki 10. - FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7,
place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP. 12598-48. - GERMAN
DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710
Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R.
FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier (German
ed. only): 53 Bonn 1, Colmantstrasse 22. For scientific maps
only: GEO CENTER D7 Stuttgart 80, Postfach 800830. Other
publications: S. Karger GmbH, Karger Buchhandlung, Ange¬
rhofstrasse 9, Postfach 2, 8034 Germering/München.
GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195,
Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The
University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop
of Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1,
Legon. - GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. - HONG
KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial
Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-
15, Lock Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY. Akadémiai Könyves-
bolt, Váci u. 22, ßudapest V; A.K.V. Konyvtürosok Boltja,
Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest VI. ICELAND. Snaebjörn
Jonsson & Co., H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA.
Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay
400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai,
Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf Ali Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1
Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001. Sub-Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.
17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House, New Delhi;
Publications Section, Ministry of Education and Social Welfare,
511 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan, New Delhi 110001. -
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah
Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr Sam Ratulangie 47,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution
Co:, 28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Shahreza Avenue, P.O. Box
314/1486, Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco, Ave.
Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B.P. 1533, Teheran. - IRAQ.
McKenzie's Bookshop, Al -Rashid Street, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd.,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. - ISRAEL. A.B.C
Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv 61000
- JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101
Water Lane, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc.,
Shuhwa Toranomon 3bldg, 23-6, Toranomon 3-Chome, Minato-
ku, Tokyo 105, - KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O.
Box 30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. - KUWAIT. The
Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait - LESOTHO.
Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern
Africa. - LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box
286, Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency for Development of
Publication & Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue,
Luxembourg. - MALAYSIA. Federal Publications, Lot 8323,
JI.222, Petaling Jaya, Selangor. MALTA. Sapienzas. 26
Republic Street, Valletta. MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company
Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis. - MONACO. British
Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. - NETHERLANDS.
For the "Unesco Koerier" Dutch edition only: Systemen
Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75, Amsterdam- 1007. Agent for all
Unesco publications: N.V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9,
The Hague. - NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine
N.V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. - NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, Government
Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 130,
Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch; Alma Street, P.O.
Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin;
Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington. NIGERIA. The
University Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan,
P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of Nsukka; The University
Bookshop of Lagos;The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of
Zaria. NORWAY. All publications: Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco
Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-e-azam,
P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. -
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda, Livraria
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. - SEYCHELLES. New
Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé.
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19. - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951,
Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA. All publications: Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.
SOUTHERN RHODESIA. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union
Avenue, Salisbury. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100
Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2.
SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. -
SWEDEN. All publications A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327
Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Förbundet,
Skolgränd 2, 8ox 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. -
SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva
11, CCP. 12-236. - TANZANIA. Dares Salaam Bookshop,
P.O.B. 9030 Dares-Salaam. - THAILAND. Nibondh and Co.
Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box
402, Bangkok: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern
Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road,
Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. National Commission
for Unesco, 18 Alexandra Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal Caddesi, Beyoglu,
Istambul. UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Government Bookshops in
London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham,
Bristol. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue South,
New York, N.Y. 10010. - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga,
Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knj'iga, Trg
Republike 5/8, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba Slovenje, Titova C 25,
P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubljana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="72">
<![CDATA[
>r-":
1 1 * > '
IF
A temple
that made tracks
across the desert
The International Campaign to Save
the Monuments of Nubia from flooding
by the waters of the Aswan High Dam
at Sadd El Aali is now coming to an
end. just twenty years after it was
launched by Unesco. The campaign
has been the biggest archaeological
rescue operation the world has ever
seen and an unprecedented victory for
international cultural co-operation. This
aerial photo shows a section of the
temple of Amada after it had been
hoisted in one piece onto a three-track
railway and slowly edged 2,600 metres
across the desert to a site beyond
reach of the mounting waters. Tracks
stretching into the distance are the
remains of the railbed. Heaps of rocks
nearby are the stones of another
temple awaiting reconstruction.
Altogether more than a score of
ancient shrines and temples were
removed and rebuilt elsewhere during
the Nubian campaign. (See page 6).
Photo J. Marthelot © Universal Photo, Paris
]]>
</page>
</document>
