<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074748eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
AUGUST SEPTEMBER 1981 - 9 French francs
^^^B
m
,:l^,^,i,.-.,LL
J -Tul
Jasa
4.35
ffJffni«»>rSB!
yet-S -vvU\
f/%^»3
VÍ*3E^l^
M f. "
f à** 4Mj^
^(#T
S®
S là»,
' IM
m
l'wl til
Islam: 15th century of the Hegira
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
:
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
Egypt
Religion, way of life, culture and civilization Islam englobes every field of
human activity in a unifying vision. The search for knowledge, set forth as man's
bounden duty by the Qur'an, ¡s a dynamic force in this grand design and educa¬
tion has always been of central importance in Islamic society. Learning was im¬
parted in the Madrasahs, educational institutions associated with the mosques.
Above, the mosque of al-Azhar in Cairo. Inaugurated by the Fatimids on 7
Ramadan 361 (22 June 972 AD) it became the nucleus of one of the Islamic
world's most outstanding universities. Al-Azhar, which each year awards
thousands of degrees in such varied disciplines as theology, Arabic, medicine,
the sciences, and architecture, has for centuries made a brilliant contribution to
the spread of Islamic learning.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
AUGUST-SEPTEMBER 1981 34th YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 25 LANGUAGES
English Italian Turkish Macedonian
French Hindi Urdu Serbo-Croat
Spanish . Tamil Catalan Slovene
Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese
German Persian Korean
Arabic Dutch Swahili
Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French and Spanish
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 44 French Francs
2 years: 75 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 32 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (11 issues a
year including one double issue).
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: ID University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100. U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Micro-
card Edition. Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New York, U.S.A.; (3) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mans¬
field Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Editor-in-chief: Jean Gaudin
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English Edition: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Russian Edition:
German Edition: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Arabic Edition: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Italian Edition: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi Edition: Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
Tamil Edition: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew Edition: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian Edition: Samad Nourinejad (Teheran)
Dutch Edition: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese Edition: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish Edition: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu Edition: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan Edition: Joan Carreras ¡ Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian Edition: Bahador Shah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean Edition: Lee Kwang-Young (Seoul)
Swahili Edition: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salaam)
Braille Edition: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene Editions: Punisa Pavlovic (Belgrade)
Chinese Edition: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Philippe Gentil
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
page
5 At the dawn of the fifteenth century of the Hegira
THE MESSAGE OF ISLAM
by Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
6 THE MESSENGER OF GOD
by Muhammad Hamidullah
~8 ISLAM'S HOLY BOOK
9 THE SUNNA: THE GUIDING VOICE OF TRADITION
13 THE WORLD OF ISLAM
In words and pictures
14 A UNIVERSAL MISSION
by Habib Chatty
23 IBN BATTUTA
Around the world in thirty years
28 MUSLIMS OF THE SOVIET UNION
by Ziyauddin Babakhan
30 RENEWAL AND REFORM IN INDONESIA
by Siti Baroroh Baried
32 THE IMPACT ON BLACK AFRICA
by Sulayman S. Nyang
34 TEACHERS, DISCIPLES AND THE ETHICS OF LEARNING
by Mohammed Allai Sinaceur
43 THE HEGIRA
by Hakim Mohammed Said
44 THE SCIENTIFIC ACHIEVEMENT OF EARLY ISLAM
by Abdul-Razzak Kaddoura
50 UMMAT UL-ILM
Towards a Commonwealth of Science
by Abdus Salam
56 THE DYNAMIC OF ISLAMIC THOUGHT
by Abdel Ma/id Meziane
63 THE EYE OF THE HEART
Mysticism in Islam
by Rahmatullah
67 MYSTIC VOICES
68 A NEW ARCHITECTURE ROOTED IN TRADITION
by Dogan Kuban
78 BOOKSHELF
I ftAiMialB M-1."_!!
s.:
j|-- ,i.^^.n -Is
cover
At the dawn of the fifteenth century of the
Hegira, this double issue of the Unesco
Courier highlights some of the basic facets
of the thought and spiritual ideals of the
Islamic community, which embraces almost
a fifth of humanity. The geographical and
cultural diversity of this vast community
bears witness to the universality of the
Islamic message and civilization. Our cover
shows the Ka'ba sanctuary in the Haram
mosque at Mecca, the religious heart of
Islam.
Photo Abdelaziz Frikha © Sud Editions. Tunis
3
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
'In the Name of Allah...
. the Compassionate, the Merciful
This invocation, the Bismiliah al-Rahman al-Rahim, appears at
the beginning of every Surah (section) of the Qur'an (with the
exception of the ninth) and is pronounced by Muslims before any
important act or undertaking. All believers, whatever their native
language, must recite in their prayers a few verses of the Qur'an
in the original Arabic, and the Bismillah is therefore every day on
the lips of millions of men and women throughout Islam. The
Arabic word Islam means "submission" (to God), and Muslim
means "one who performs the act of submission". In its wider
signification Islam has also come to denote a vast cultural complex
embracing millions of people bound together by a common
faith and a sense of belonging to a single community. Above,
XIV/20th century (il calligraphies of the Bismillah by Jalil Rassouli.
(1) Throughout this issue of the Unesco Courier dates are
given, where appropriate, according to both the Islamic
and the Gregorian calendars. The Islamic date is given first.
(See also box on the Islamic calendar page 43).
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
At the dawn of the fifteenth century of the Hegira
The message of Islam
by Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
Director-General of Unesco
IT is fourteen hundred years since the
Prophet Muhammad, who for ten years
had been calling upon the people of
Mecca to walk in the way of God, found
himself forced into exile.
In Mecca he had gathered about him a
group of faithful followers but had also
made unrelenting enemies who, after vainly
trying temptations and threats, planned to
murder him. He therefore decided the time
had come for his community to leave. Ac¬
companied by the loyal Abu Bakr, he set off
in secret one evening from the town, arriv¬
ing at last, after a long and dangerous
journey across the desert, in Yathrib, where
his companions had gone before and where
the villagers welcomed him with open arms.
Of this humble settlement the Prophet
made Medina, the town of towns which was
to become the second of the holy cities of
Islam, and this small oasis he made the point
of departure for a new civilization.
The epic story of the exodus, or Hegira,
contains several clues as to why the
message brought by Muhammad came to be
identified, after him, with the hopes of so
many peoples, adding a new spiritual,
ethical, political and social dimension to
their lives.
The first significance of that message is its
universality; it was by addressing
themselves to the whole man and to all men
that the Prophet and his companions were
to build a new society, that the first Caliphs
were to carry Islam beyond the boundaries
of the Arabian Peninsula, and that their suc¬
cessors were later to spread its influence
over a vast area linking Asia, Africa and
Europe.
The message proclaimed by the Prophet
indeed radically widened the spiritual
horizons of the peoples that received it, il¬
luminating their lives with a faith transcen¬
ding the contingencies of everyday ex¬
perience, placing political matters on an
ethical basis and ensuring the full rights of
every individual within the community.
For the freedom of the Muslim communi¬
ty is a fabric of which the warp and weft are
individual freedoms, that can only flourish if
the whole community flourishes; when the
latter is threatened or attacked, each in¬
dividual is affected or hurt in his innermost
being; and when its members are prevented
from living their lives fully by participating
freely in the life of society, that life is in¬
evitably impoverished and society ceases to
be itself.
The rights of each individual proceed from
the absolute equality of all before God.
"You are all equal as the teeth of the comb",
said the Prophet. This basic equality, unaf¬
fected by the privileges of birth or the
vagaries of fortune, implies a legal and moral
responsibility equal for all. Hence, each is
answerable to God and to men for his own
conduct and for the conduct of the com¬
munity's affairs.
Islam breathed upon worlds which had
previously been worlds apart in history,
geography, language and culture the unify¬
ing breath of a shared hope which drew
them closer together in many ways, setting
up a constant current of mutually enriching,
cross-fertilizing exchanges.
At the same time, Islam was receptive to
the knowledge to be obtained from all the
cultures it came across in the course of its
expansion. The Prophet advised believers to
seek knowledge ''from the cradle to the
grave" and for that purpose to go "to China
if need be"; Islam, starting out with a unique
vision, consequently developed an aptitude
for taking the accumulated intellectual
wealth of the peoples sharing the same faith
and the main elements of the rest of the
world's stock of knowledge and combining
them into an integral whole.
The teachings of Islam have thus kept an
ever-renewed relevance; and the epic
adventure of the Hegira, during which these
teachings took shape, has continued to in¬
spire minds and hearts. Muslims today recall
the many episodes of that story as if they
were about people but recently departed
from this life whose memory remains very
dear to them, whose words and deeds still
have the power to move them deeply, and
whose example continues to inspire their
thoughts and actions.
They "recall the moving story of how the
companions of the Prophet entered Medina
and of the brotherly welcome which the Par¬
tisans accorded to them, receiving them into
the bosom of their families and sharing their
homes and their belongings with them.
They then find themselves dreaming, in the
here and now, of another such surge of
solidarity between peoples, each feeling
others' needs as his own and all who enjoy
plenty stretching out the hand of friendship
to those stricken by war, by want, by ig¬
norance and disease.
Muslims also tell how once the Prophet
was explaining his plan for an impending
battle. One of his companions having asked
whether this plan partook of Revelation or
stemmed from his own understanding, the
Prophet replied that it was the fruit of his
own deliberation. The companion then gave
his own views on the battle plan and finally
persuaded the Prophet to change it. Then
the Muslims of today all find themselves
dreaming of such another climate of cordial
brotherhood as would allow the lowliest to
express himself fearlessly before the most
highly respected, in that atmosphere of
mutual tolerance which is the essential
prerequisite of democracy for all.
Muslims yet again tell of the Caliph Umar,
the spiritual and temporal head of a by now
immense Islamic State, who, being over¬
come by weariness, lay down in the shade
of a palm tree where one of his subjects,
seeing him, stopped and addressed to him
these infinitely tender words: "Thou hast
accomplished thy public duties, Omar, thou
hast served justice and with a heart set at
rest thou hast fallen to sleep". Who can help
but dream, today, of the renewal of that
same sense of equality whereby the ruler
would be a man among men, so devoted to
the good of his fellows that each of them
would, in turn, feel a little responsible for
him?
These values of freedom, responsibility
and solidarity enlightened and purified by
faith, are as essential to man today as in the
days of the Prophet. Now as in the past and
in the future, they offer man an ideal to live
by, such that his highest spiritual aspirations
irradiate the. humblest acts of his daily life.
I Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
The Messenger
by Muhammad Hamidullah
In the presence of the Prophet
In the following text, taken from the Universal History
by Tabari Id. Baghdad 310 AH/923 AD), the best-known
description of'the Prophet's physical appearance is
sketched by Ali, his cousin and son-in-law. Islamic tradi¬
tion, reacting against the idolatry which prevailed in the
Arabian peninsula before the coming of Islam, originally
forbade the reproduction of images of living creatures,
especially of man. From the time of the Abbasids this
rule became more flexible, thus opening the way to the
flowering of the miniaturist's art, notably in Persia and
Turkey. Nevertheless, where the Prophet and some of
the most revered figures of Islam are concerned, it is
still scrupulously observed in the Muslim world.
Asked for details of the Prophet's ex¬
ternal appearance, AH said: he was of
medium height, neither very tall nor very
short. His complexion was pinkish
white; his eyes were black; his hair was
thick, glossy, and beautiful. A full beard
framed his face. The hairs of his head
were long, fa/ling to his shoulders. They
were black [...]. His gait was so
energetic that you would have said that
he tore himself from the rock with each
step, and yet at the same time he moved
so lightly that with each stride he seem¬
ed not to touch the ground. But he did
not walk proudly, as princes do. There
was so much gentleness in his face that
once in his presence it was impossible to
leave him; if you were hungry, you were
satisfied by looking at him and thought
no more of food. Any man suffering
from an affliction forgot his troubles
when in his presence, charmed by the
gentleness of his features and his
discourse. All who saw him agreed that
they never met, neither before nor after,
a man whose discourse was so delight¬
ful. His nose was straight; there were
gaps between his teeth. Sometimes he
would let the hair of his head fall natural¬
ly, at others he wore it knotted into
two or four bunches. At sixty- three
years, no more than fifteen hairs on his
whole body had yet become white with
age... U
ONE night in the month of Ramadan in
the year 609 AD, Muhammad Ibn
Abdallah Ibn Abd al-Muttalib Ibn
Hashim, the future Prophet Muhammad,
had a vision in the cave of Hira near Mecca.
A voice said: "I am Gabriel, the angel sent
by God to announce to you that you have
been appointed by God to communicate His
messages, His revelation to humanity."
The first revelation he received was this:
"Recite in the name of your Lord, the
Creator,
Who created man from a clot of blood.
Recite! Your Lord is the most bounteous
One
Who by the pen has taught,
Taught man things which he did not
know."
These words form the first five verses of
the 96th chapter of the .Qur'an, the Holy
Book of Islam, which contains this and the
many other revelations Muhammad would
receive in the course of the next twenty-
three years before his death (see page 8).
Mecca, the birthplace of Islam, was at the
beginning of the seventh century AD a pro¬
sperous trading centre with some 10,000 in¬
habitants. It stood at the cross-roads of
several major trade-routes, which traversed
the Arabian peninsula, which itself stood at
the confines of the two most powerful em¬
pires of that time: The Persian Sassanid em¬
pire to the north-east, and the Byzantine
empire to the north and west (Syria and
Egypt).
Through Mecca passed caravans
transporting the most precious commodities
of the age: silk from China, spices from In¬
dia, and perfumes from the Yemen, en route
for Byzantium and the rest of Europe. It was
a well-organized city-state with a council of
ten hereditary oligarchs and with ministries
responsible for justice, defence, worship,
external relations, consultations with the
citizens and other civic affairs. Each of these
ministries was held by one of the major clans
of the tribe of Quraysh, to which Muham¬
mad belonged.
The people of Mecca had a reputation for
generosity and honesty: when famine struck
they fed the poor; and to protect the in¬
terests of foreigners who had been unjustly
treated in Mecca they had founded an
MUHAMMAD HAMIDULLAH, an Islamo/ogist
from Hyderabad (India), is currently an honorary
research officer at the French National Centre of
Scientific Research in Paris. He taught for
25 years at the University of Istanbul and for shor¬
ter periods at the Universities of Ankara, and
Erzurum (Turkey) and Kuala Lumpur (Malaysia).
Among his published works are Le Prophète de
l'Islam (Paris 1950 and 1980), Muslim Conduct of
State (Lahore^ 1977) and a translation of the
Qur'an into French (Beirut 1980, tenth edition).
In the article above quotations from the Qur'an
are in the author's own translation.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
of God
"order of chivalry". They believed in one
God but, like most of the sedentary or
nomadic peoples then living in the Arabian
peninsula, they also worshipped idols
which, they hoped, would intercede with
the deity on their behalf. They did not
believe in the resurrection or in an after-life.
Mecca was noted for a temple known as
the Ka'ba which had become a major centre
of pilgrimage. Reputedly built by Adam and
restored by Abraham, the Ka'ba was a
cubical building, adorned all around with
360 idols. The Virgin Mary and the infant
Jesus were among the figures depicted on
frescoes inside. A black stone in one corner
of the Ka'ba was the object of particular
veneration: it marked the spot where the
ritual procession around the temple began,
and on it pilgrims swore fidelity to God. The
annual pilgrimage to the Ka'ba attracted
crowds of worshippers from all over the
Arabian peninsula.
The overwhelming majority of the people
'of Mecca, including Muhammad, were il¬
literate but they were renowned for their elo¬
quence and appreciation of poetry. Indeed,
poets from all over the peninsula came there
to display their talents and earn the approval
of the Meccans.
Such was the setting to which the
message of Islam was first brought by
Muhammad.
When he received the first revelation
Muhammad was forty years old. An Arab
born in Mecca into a family of merchants, he
had become the leader of caravans, like his
father and grandfather before him. His wife
Khadijah was the widow of a merchant, and
on her behalf he had journeyed to Syria, the
Yemen, East Arabia (Bahrain, Oman), and
possibly even as far as Abyssinia which had
highly developed trading links with pre-
Islamic Mecca. As a young man Muhammad
had already revealed exceptional qualities
which distinguished him from his fellows. In
particular he had won a reputation for probi¬
ty in business which earned him the name of
al-Amin (worthy of confidence).
According to historians, Muhammad
once bought a young slave named Zaid Ibn
Harithah, whom he treated very kindly. Zaid
had been captured during a war. After a
long search his father, chief of a big tribe,
found his son in Mecca and asked Muham¬
mad to return the boy in exchange for a ran¬
som. The future Prophet replied that he
would free the young slave for nothing, pro¬
vided that the boy willingly agreed to go
with his father. Faced with this choice, Zaid
at once and unhesitatingly announced that
he preferred to stay with Muhammad. The
latter was deeply moved and immediately
set the boy free, took him to the Ka'ba and
declared that he had decided to adopt his
former slave as his son.
Another incident, which happened some
five years before the first revelation, also
sheds a revealing light on Muhammad's
character. The Ka'ba had been destroyed by
fire and torrential rain, and then rebuilt by
the Meccans. However, just as the Black
Stone was about to be returned to its place,
a quarrel broke out between the different
clans, each of which coveted the honour of
replacing the sacred object. The issue seem¬
ed likely to be settled at swordpoint when an
old man proposed that the decision be left in
God's hands and that whoever came on the
scene first should arbitrate the issue.
The first-comer turned out to be Muham¬
mad, who placed the stone in a wide piece
of cloth and asked a representative of each
clan to lift the cloth by its edge. In this way
every clan participated in the restoration of
the Black Stone to its niche, where it was
placed by Muhammad to the satisfaction of
everyone.
It was around this time that Muhammad
became dissatisfied with the worldly life
around him and began to retire to spend his
days in meditation, his favourite retreat be¬
ing the cave of Hira. For five successive
years he thus went into seclusion during the
whole month of Ramadan, which then fell in
mid-winter. It was during his fifth annual
retreat that he had his first vision of the Ar¬
changel Gabriel.
When the vision was over, Muhammad
returned home, profoundly shaken, and
described his experience to his wife Khadi¬
jah. He was in a state of great agitation and
feared that the angel might have been the
devil in disguise. Khadijah did all she could
to comfort him and the next day they both
visited her cousin, Waraqa Ibn Nawfal, a
blind old man who had been converted to
Christianity and was versed in religious lore.
As soon as Muhammad had finished tell¬
ing his story, Waraqa exclaimed: "If what
you say is true, this is similar to the Nomos
(Torah) of Moses. If God spares me, I shall
defend you when the hour of your persecu¬
tion comes'."
"What!" replied Muhammad. "Shall I be
persecuted for having talked of God and his
blessings?"
"Yes," said Waraqa, "no prophet has
escaped persecution from a part of his
people."
The story of Muhammad's vision spread
throughout the city. The first to proclaim
their faith in his message were Khadijah, the
devoted Zaid, Muhammad's friend Abu
Bakr, and his young cousin Ali whom he had
brought up as an adopted son. Others were
sceptical, if not openly hostile.
Then three years went by without Gabriel
appearing again to the Prophet. Muhammad
was on the verge of despair when his aunt,
Umm Lahab, taunted him saying: "I am sure
that your devil (Gabriel) has abandoned you
and that he detests you."
This insult touched the' prophet to the
quick. He climbed a nearby mountain, and
when he reached the summit Gabriel ap¬
peared before him, calmed him and recited
to him the words of God: "By the morning
hours and by the night when it is stillest.
Your Lord hath not forsaken you nor doth he
hate you... Therefore the orphan oppress
not, the beggar drive not away, and of the
bounty of your Lord be your discourse."
(The Qur'an, XCIII: 1-3 and 9-11). Muham¬
mad immediately grasped the meaning of
this message ordering man to believe in God
and to be charitable.
The message which Muhammad began to
preach to the people of his birthplace had
two main doctrines, the unicity of God and
the resurrection and life after death. The idea
of a single omniscient and omnipresent God,
to which everyone will one day have to give
an account of himself, conflicted with the
idolatrous beliefs and practices of the Mec¬
cans. At first they were amused by Muham¬
mad's teachings. Then they began to pour
scorn on him. Finally they unleashed a wave
of persecution against the Prophet and the
small group of converts who had embraced
the new religion. When it became in¬
tolerable, Muhammad advised his new com¬
panions to seek refuge in Abyssinia where a
Christian king gave them asylum and protec¬
tion. When the Meccans furiously sent a
delegation to demand the extradition of the
Muslim refugees, the Abyssinian king turned
down their request.
The Meccan delegation thus returned
home frustrated, and as a result the persecu¬
tion of those Muslims who had remained in
Mecca was stepped up.
Eventually the pagan Meccans decided to
proclaim a boycott of the Prophet and his
clan. All commercial transactions, including
the sale of food, were forbidden, and many
Muslims died during the boycott.
After three long years the Meccans lifted
the embargo, but this was not the end of
Muhammad's difficulties. His uncle, Abu
Talib, head of the family and his protector,
died, and the new head of the clan, another
uncle, Abu Lahab, declared Muhammad an
outlaw whom anyone could kill. Faced with
no alternative but to leave Mecca, Muham¬
mad sought asylum in the neighbouring
town of Ta'if. However, the people of Ta'if
turned out to be even more hostile than the
Meccans and the Prophet soon returned to
his native city under the protection of a non-
Muslim friend, since he himself was excom¬
municated by his clan.
He now conceived the idea of making con¬
tact with the foreigners who came to Mecca
each year on the annual pilgrimage to the
Ka'ba. After many vain efforts with con¬
tingents from different tribes, a small group
of people from Yathrib, later to be known as
Madinat al-Nabi, "the city of the Prophet",
or simply Medina, "the city" rallied to his
cause and agreed to preach the message in
their town. The following year twelve people)
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
¿>-l»p.j=»* y/j» y *JmJi.^> jJ'yA,
f.»é m J.9 I 9¿^- L>f~-±.laUJ ¡
-O Lu±. Jjt, L-l «o j» -¿ «*«-/ .» <Ju-^9
-V .»« «=** *» f - -*- JiJP, o«'"r' AÜ x*
¡j*. r IfJlp J »I » "*** f .-»y *
&>»/« /_ j¿ «,* -*=»Mr -Jptit»
j J70U iJjj.J^jZ 71*
^JSJ ¿& 'jp 'si 9/^*i I -y* L/r
J J/. -J*mLJ. S. j/-^9 ylJ fs JkV..
Jf* tJi^ -> eUJ l.péL*. aà±*&^».9 **É
-cJ*» l¿^jL L- -J-U '..g&¿.' j. --*J
1~
¿ArJIrYf *-** y1
JJj »til} Uf*+JJ '*Tr~am?/f^
* rt y »i ^ * ,-» ** '*
/s^tS M Y-=-> 9*,* '-**-**J'
MI
\j
'"
»;,& 9*-
Left, this Qur'an was copied
on vellum during the ll/8th
century, probably in Mecca
or Medina. It is in an early
Arab script called al ma'il
and is believed to be one of
the two oldest extant Qur'an
manuscripts.
Islam's Holy Book
In the name of Allah the Compassionate
the Merciful
Praise be to Allah, Lord of the Creation,
The Compassionate, the Merciful
King of the Last Judgement
You alone we worship, and to You alone
we pray for help
Guide us to the straight path
The path of those whom You have
favoured, not of those who have incur¬
red Your wrath, nor of those who have
gone astray.
The Qur'an (the Koran) is the Holy Book of the
Muslims. In Arabic, qur'an means "reading" or "recita¬
tion". It contains all the revelations made by God
through the archangel Gabriel to Muhammad over
about the last twenty years of his life.
Muhammad, for Muslims the last of the prophets and
the chosen Messenger of God, described how these
revelations were made in the following terms:
"They happen in different ways; sometimes Gabriel
takes the form of a man who speaks to me as a man
speaks, sometimes he ¡s another kind of being with
wings, and I remember all that he says. At other times,
it seems as if a bell were ringing in my ears-and that
is the most terrible ordeal-and when this state of
ecstasy fades I remember everything perfectly as if it
were engraved on my memory."
The Qur'an is written in Arabic and is divided into 114
surahs, or chapters, sub-divided into verses, They are
of unequal length and are arranged not chronologically,
but in order of decreasing length, except in the case of
the first surah which is entitled al-Fatiha (the Exor¬
dium) and which has only seven verses (see above). It
is considered the epitome of the Holy Book and is the
only part of the Qur'an that must be recited at every
prayer.
For Muslims, the Qur'an is a guide through the whole
of human life, temporal as well as spiritual, individual
as well as collective. It is for all men, without distinc¬
tion, in all countries and for all time, since, according to
the Holy Book, there will be no further revelation.
The sacred text does not follow a chronological order
and the messages dictated to the Prophet at Mecca,
before the Hijra, are interspersed with those received
at Medina.
The Meccan surahs, which make up about one third
of the Qur'an, were addressed to a hostile and pagan
community and constitute a kind of ethical code that
teaches charity, perseverance and purity. They also
have a marked eschatological character, reminding the
believers that the Last Judgement awaits them.
The Medina surahs, which constitute about two
thirds of the Qur'an, are interspersed with legal
prescriptions necessary to the communal life of the
new society established in Medina.
The revelations continued to occur, until the Prophet's
death in the eleventh year of the Hijra (632 AD).
The fragments of the Qur'an were put together under
the direction of the Prophet himself. After each revela¬
tion, he dictated the words received from Gabriel to
one of his literate companions, indicating the exact
place this new element was to occupy in the complete
work. Muhammad chose a thematic rather than a
chronological arrangement; apart from some very long
texts in which several problems are discussed, the
chapters are generally made up of revelations from dif¬
ferent periods but dealing with the same subject. This
gives the Book a logical structure.
The work of transcription lasted for the whole of the
Prophet's ministry. After his death, the community was
not allowed to change the long sequence of Qur'anic
revelations either by addition or suppression.
The task of establishing a complete and definitive ver¬
sion of the Qur'an in a single book devolved upon the
Prophet's successors. Since paper was unknown at
that time to the inhabitants of the Arabian peninsula,
the first Muslims in Mecca and later in Medina record¬
ed the revelations on crude and perishable materials
-pieces of leather, wooden tablets, the shoulder-blades
of camels, date fibre, soft stone, etc. The texts thus
recorded were often fragmentary and showed certain
divergencies.
The text of the Qur'an was also preserved by the
hafiz, believers who had learned it by heart from the
mouth of the Prophet. After his death many of them
perished during the wars of apostasy, which broke out
when certain Muslims rejected Islam and refused to
pay the compulsory alms, or zakat. In order to
safeguard the Qur'an and complete the verification of
its text by those hafiz who were still alive, the first
Caliph, Abu Bakr, on the advice of Umar (who was
later to succeed him), commanded that the various
fragments be assembled into a single work. It is said
that Umar himself wrote down the sacred text in one
volume. But it was the third Caliph, Uthman, who reign¬
ed from 23 to 36 AH (644 to 656 AD), who drew up the
complete and official version of the Qur'an.
The Qur'an established not only a religion but also a
language -Arabic.
In Muhammad's time a large number of Semitic
dialects were spoken in the Arabian peninsula. The
divine revelation was made in the idiom of the power¬
ful Quraysh tribe and thus the Arabic language became
a vehicle of civilization for hundreds of millions of
people. The first known book in Arabic, the Qur'an is an
inspired text of great formal perfection. It is written in
prose although some of its verses rhyme.
Although it has been translated into nearly all
languages, Muslims throughout the world must recite
in their prayers a few verses from the Qur'an in the
original Arabic.
(Unless otherwise stated, quotations from
the Qur'an appearing in this issue of the
Unesco Courier are taken from the English
translation by N.J. Dawood).
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
'from Medina came to Mecca at the time of
the pilgrimage and declared their conversion
to Islam. When they returned home they
were accompanied by a missionary from
Mecca who had been instructed by the Pro¬
phet to preach Islam in Medina.
The missionary was so successful that the
next year dozens of converts came to Mecca
from Medina and invited the Prophet and all
persecuted Muslims to emigrate to their
town. Muhammad accepted, but first he
asked the Muslims in Mecca to go to Medina
in small groups because if they migrated en
masse the people of Mecca would probably
molest them. So secretly, in small groups,
they went.
As more and more Muslims left Mecca,
the Meccans became afraid that if Muham¬
mad too found refuge elsewhere he would
eventually return with his hosts and attack
his native city. And so they decided to
assassinate him. When news of the plot
reached Muhammad, he went to his friend
Abu Bakr and they both decided to leave
Mecca under cover of darkness and go to
Medina. Abu Bakr engaged a man to bring
two camels to their hiding place and to guide
them by unfrequented routes. After many
adventures they arrived safely in Medina, to
the joy of the Muslims who were already
there.
This event, the Hegira (in Arabic, Hijra), is
the starting point of the Islamic calendar
which has now ended fourteen centuries.
Before it, life was full of difficulties for Islam;
after it, in Medina, there came a time of
relative security and progress which permit¬
ted the establishment of an Islamic State.
Muhammad was a practical man. He
wanted to establish how Muslims should act
in every aspect of their existence in their
spiritual and personal lives and also in their
political lives as members of the community.
In Medina he embarked on this great task.
The first problem facing him was that of
the refugees. He suggested that each
wealthy Medina family should fraternize
with a family of Meccan refugees; the two
families should work together, earn
together, and live together as a single fami¬
ly. The Medina Muslims agreed and in this
way the problem of the refugees was soon
solved.
The next problem was that of security. On
the Prophet's arrival, there was a political
vacuum in Medina, which consisted merely
of a number of warring clans who recogniz¬
ed no ruler and no form of state authority.
Muhammad called together representatives
of all the population Muslims, idolatrous
Arabs, Jews and Christians and proposed
the establishment of a city-state whose
strength would deter anyone who might
think of attacking it. The proposal was ac¬
cepted, and Muhammad was himself
selected as head of the new state.
As head of state his first measure was to
draw up a constitution. The text, which has
survived to the present day, is the world's
first known example of a written constitu¬
tion. It defines the rights and duties of the
head of state and his subjects, and makes
provisions for defence, justice, social in¬
surance and other needs. The hallmark of
the constitution is tolerance in the widest
sense. Under it everyone, Muslim and non-
Muslim alike, is to enjoy not only liberty of
conscience but also liberty of law and
justice: Muslim law was applied to non-
Muslims neither in civil nor penal cases.
Muhammad next began to organize the
security of the Muslim state by making a
series of defensive alliances with the tribes
which lived around Medina. Strengthened
by these alliances, he forbade the Meccan
caravans travelling to Syria, Egypt or Iraq to
cross Islamic territory. When the Meccans
tried to force their way through they found
their way blocked by bands of Muslims three
and sometimes ten times fewer than their
own forces. The great victory at the battle of
Badr (year 2 of the Hijra) was won, for]
The Sunna: the Guiding Voice of Tradition
The Sunna (the word means custom, use and wont)
comprises the deeds and utterances of the Prophet
Muhammad and acts and sayings to which he gave his
unspoken approval during his ministry.
Second in authority only to the Qur'an, it consists
essentially of the Prophet's commentaries on the
Qur'an and of rules of conduct laid down for the entire
Islamic Community.
Known also as the Hadith (tradition of the Prophet),
the Sunna was the source of a host of practical rules
by which judges were guided during the earlier cen¬
turies of Islam before the codification of the corpus of
Islamic law. Even today it continues to be a source of
law in many countries which apply, whether wholly or
in part, the Shari'a, or Holy Law of Islam.
Muhammad made a clear distinction between the
Qur'an, the word of God dictated to him by the angel
Gabriel which could not be altered even in the slightest
detail, and the inspiration which prompted him in his
daily life to words or acts approved by God. Sometimes
a revelation would correct a decision made by the Pro¬
phet himself. The Prophet personally supervised the
collation of the Qur'an, but not of theiHadith.
At first, the Sunna was handed down from memory
by the companions of the Prophet. Some of them, like
Abd'Allah Ibn Amr and Anas Ibn Malik, noted down the
Prophet's words and actions during his lifetime, others
did so only after his death. Most of them, however,
passed on their knowledge orally to their disciples.
Sometimes, to resolve a legal or moral problem, a
precedent would be sought in the life of the Prophet on
which a decision could be based.
The early generations of Muslims felt the need to col¬
late and authenticate the Hadith of the Prophet. Many
"traditionists", or scholars of the Sunna, set out to col¬
lect the oral traditions, often travelling great distances
to receive them at first hand from those to whom they
had been directly transmitted.
The body of the Tradition soon swelled considerably.
In some cases Hadith were invented to give credence
to a particular view or doctrine, and in others, through
an excess of piety, edifying sayings or moral teachings
were falsely lent the authority of the Prophet's name.
Towards the second century of the Hijra, therefore, it
became essential to authenticate each Hadith by
establishing a chain of transmission beginning with the
last authority and ending with the original authority, a
task which developed into a discipline in its own right.
Biographical studies were made of the people who
figured in these chains of transmission in which their
antecedents, ideas, doctrines and degrees of honesty
were examined so as to allow an assessment to be
made of the reliability of their words.
Thus every Hadith came to consist of two parts the
Isnad, which consisted of the names of the persons
who handed on the substance of the tradition to one
another, and the Matn, or text of the tradition itself, as
in the following example :
(i) Isnad : Al-Homaidi told us that according to Sufian,
on the authority of Yah'ya Ibn Said el-Ansari, that
Muhammad Ibn Ibrahim at-Taimi had informed him that
he had heard Alqama Ibn Waqqas al-Laithi say: "I
heard Umar Ibn Khattab" (may God be pleased with
him) say from the minbar (pulpit) that he had heard the
Messenger of God (peace be upon Him) express himself
in these words:
nil Matn: "An action can be judged only by its
intention."
Six great collections of Hadith are recognized as
authoritative the Sahih (authentic collections) of al-
Bukhari and of Muslim, and the Sunan (traditions) of
Abu Oawud, al-Tirmidhi, al-Nasa'i and Ibn Madja, all of
which were compiled during the 3rd century of the
Hijra (9th century ADV
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
- example, by some 300 Muslims pitted
against some 950 pagans.
As the years went by, Mecca began to
show signs of economic exhaustion.
Muhammad generously offered a truce but
when it was violated by the Meccans he oc¬
cupied their city without a blow being
struck. His first decision was to proclaim a
general amnesty which affected the Mec¬
cans so profoundly that most of them were
converted to Islam overnight.
With the conquest of Mecca, the
Prophefs hands were freed to deal with the
Byzantine empire which was hesitating
neither to assassinate Muslim ambassadors
nor to put to death those of its subjects who
embraced Islam. He could also pay attention
to the rest of the Arabian peninsula, from
where scores of delegations came to Medina
to declare their conversion.
Two years later he again went to Mecca to
perform the pilgrimage of the House of God,
that culminating and final element of the
edifice of Islam. His mission on earth had
been accomplished: three months later he
breathed his last.
By the time of his death in 11 AH/632 AD
the whole of the Arabian peninsula as well
as the southern parts of Palestine and Iraq
had been converted to Islam. The Islamic
state which had been born in a part of the
town of Medina in year 1 of the Hijra had ex¬
panded to cover three million square
kilometres and was endowed with the finan¬
cial, military, educational, administrative,
judicial and other institutions necessary for
its survival and development.
Before he died he had summed up the
basic duties of Islam: acceptance of the con¬
fession of faith ("There is no God if not God
and Muhammad is the Messenger of God");
saying daily prayers to God; paying tax
(Zakat); the pilgrimage to Mecca; and
fasting during the month of Ramadan.
These five pillars of faith, where material and
spiritual mingle in a single balanced whole,
remain today the foundations of Islam.
M Muhammad Hamidullah
Mecca
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Photo Abdelaziz Frmna © Sud Editions, Tunis
Mecca is the birthplace and the heart of Islam and the Ka'ba
sanctuary its most holy shrine. Five times a day, every day,
millions of Muslims throughout the world turn towards Mecca as
they recite the prescribed prayers; and it is to Mecca that, for
fourteen centuries, Muslim pilgrims have come to perform seven
ritual circumnambulations of the Ka'ba, to kiss the Black Stone,
and to walk seven times between two mounds, al-Safa and al-
Marwa, within the precincts of the mosque. The salat, or daily
prayer, and the hajj, the pilgrimage to Mecca that every Muslim
who has the material means to do so is called upon to make once
in his lifetime, are two of the five "Pillars of Islam", which are a
summary of the basic features of Muslim religious beliefs and
duties. The other three pillars are the shahada, the profession of
faith, the zakat, alms-giving, and the siyam or fasting. Above, an
aerial view of the Great Mosque at Mecca, with the Ka'ba
sanctuary in the centre of the courtyard. Tradition has it that the
Ka'ba (the word means "cube" and is an allusion to the shape of
the building) was built by Abraham and his son Ishmael. The Hajar
al-Aswad, or Black Stone is built Into the eastern corner of the
Ka'ba about one and a half metres from the ground. One tradition
holds that the Black Stone was brought to Abraham by the angel
Gabriel and was originally white, acquiring its present colour
through contact with Impurity and sin during the pagan period.
Another account states that the Black Stone fell down from
heaven. The Ka'ba is covered with a kiswah, or vesture, made of
black cloth with gold lettering, which is renewed every year. The
interior of the Ka'ba, to which access is strictly limited, is bare.
Three wooden pillars support the roof and the only furnishings are
a number of gold and silver lamps. Left, an Ottoman style
illuminated design (Xll/18th century) representing Mecca. It ¡s a
companion piece to the representation of Medina reproduced in
colour on page 42.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Sfe^?-
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The world
of
Islam
The emergence of Islam and the excep¬
tionally swift pace at which it came to
spread out into the world marked a
turning-point in the history of
mankind. After being revealed to the
Prophet Muhammad in Arabia, Islam
ranged, in the space of a few genera¬
tions, from Africa's Atlantic seaboard
to the coasts of South-East Asia. At the
present time, Islam embraces more
than 800 million men and women who
have the deep-rooted feeling of belong¬
ing to one and the same community.
Even today, Islam is continuing to
spread. The deep-seated cause of its
growth lies in a universalist outlook
that transcends all distinctions of race,
and enables peoples to join together in
Islam while still preserving their own
culture. On the following pages we
give, in words and pictures, a glimpse
of this diversity in unity which is the
hallmark of the Umma, or Community
of Islam.
1. The Great Mosque (XIV/20th century)
at Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia.
Photo Jacques Thomas © Explorer, Paris
2. Minaret of a mosque in Tripoli,
Libyan Arab Jamahiriya.
Photo David Lomax © Robert Harding Associates, London
3. Minaret of the Great Mosque
(lll/9th century) at Samarra, Iraq.
Photo © André Stevens, Wtnksele, Belgium
4. The Mosque of Sultan Hassan
(Vlll/14th century), Cairo, Egypt.
Photo Georg Gerster © Rapho, Paris
5. The Minaret of Jam (Vl/12th century),
Afghanistan.
Photo © Roben Harding Associates, London
6. The Koutoubia Mosque (Vl/12th century),
Marrakesh, Morocco.
Photo Jean Mazenod © Editions d'Art Lucien Mazenod, Paris
Photos of people, Abdelaziz Fnkha © Sud Editions, Tunis
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
The world of Islam
A universal mis
This huge encampment on the plain of Arafat houses some of the
million or more Muslims from all over the world who each year
come to Mecca to make the hajj, the pilgrimage that every Muslim
who has the means to do so must perform at least once in his
lifetime. As he approaches Mecca the pilgrim dons the seamless
garb of ihram consisting of two pieces of white material. The hajj
takes place in the month of Dhu 'l-Hidjdja and involves the
performance of a number of ritual acts. These include the tawaf,
the sevenfold circumnambulation of the Ka'ba and the sa'y, which
involves going backwards and forwards seven times between the
mounds of al-Safa and al-Marwa, which are within the precincts of
the Haram, or Great Mosque of Mecca. Further rituals are
accomplished in the neighbourhood of Mecca, Including the
throwing of seven stones at three stone columns representing
Satan, at Mina, and the ascension of the sacred Mount of Jabal
al-Rahma, on the plain of Arafat. This is followed by the adha, the
sacrificial slaughter of a sheep, which marks the beginning of the
greatest festival of the Islamic year. Before returning home, most '
pilgrims also visit the Prophet's tomb at Medina.
.*WR'
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
sion
by Habib Chatty
"Men, have fear of your Lord, who created
you from a single soul. . . "
(The Qur'an, IV: 1)
Photo Abdelaziz Fnkha © Sud Edftions, Tunis
^
r £« ^¡v^Si
* ' -'i i í
«P-J^f
ft*
THE basic characteristic of Islam is the
universality of its message. It has no
place for particularism. The Muslim
religion is, by its very essence, open to all
and does not seek to impose itself upon
anyone. The appeal of the Qur'an is address¬
ed to those who hear it. God said to
Muhammad: "We have sent you forth to all
mankind, so that you may give them good
news and warn them" (XXXIV:28).
Islam is essentially peace-loving and
presupposes the fundamental equality of all
mankind, based on their essential oneness,
their common origin and their common
destiny: "Men, have fear of your Lord who
created you from a single soul. From that
soul He created its mate, and through them
He bestrewed the earth with countless men
and women" (IV:I).
No distinction of race or nation, no
privilege of caste or class, no right of birth
can prevail over obedience to God and devo¬
tion to the cause of humanity. "All
mankind", said the Prophet, "is one family
in the care of God; the man best loved by
God is he who makes himself most useful to
his family". Or again, "The Arab is not
above the non-Arab, nor is the white man
above the black unless he is more pious". It
would be difficult to find a better expression
of the solidarity of mankind or of the fun¬
damental equality of all men.
But these are not the only reasons for the
universality of Islam. Not only is it the last of
the revealed religions, it also claims to be the
ultimate synthesis of all previous divine
messages. For this reason a Muslim is
bound to believe in such of these messages
as were previously transmitted to mankind
by messengers other than Muhammad. This
illustrates the extent to which Islam, by its
very essence, is a religion of concord,
friendship and tolerance; it is a synthesis
which reiterates all that had already been
revealed to Abraham, Moses, Jesus and
others, commenting, correcting, elucidating
and elaborating their message: "The Apos¬
tle believes in what has been revealed to him
by his Lord, and so do the faithful. They all
believe in Allah and His angels, His scrip¬
tures, and His apostles: we discriminate
against none of His apostles..." (11:285).
This is why Islam may be seen as a crucible
in which all the divine truths have been
merged, a source where any willing spirit
may encounter its own truth, inspiration and
serenity.
Such, in my view, is the inner, vital princi¬
ple which has contributed so much to the
rapid expansion of Islam to the four corners
of the earth, rejecting all prejudice based on
race, colour or culture and all geographical
compartmentalization.
Man, God's vice-regent on earth, is not
obliged to remain in any one spot. With the
exception of the three great centres: the
Sacred House in Mecca, the Mosque of
Medina and the al-Aqsa Mosque in
Jerusalem, meeting place of the three
revealed religions, Judaism, Christianity and
Islam, all places on earth are equal. Man's
duty is to inhabit them and enjoy their gifts:
"It is He who has subdued the earth to you.
Walk about its regions and eat of that which
He has given you..." (LXVII:15)
In fact, a Muslim is not supposed to grow
too attached to any particular place. The
whole earth is his country. All points of the
compass are good. It is up to him to explore
them, either to bring something to them or
to find refuge there. Wherever he goes the
Muslim is always at home. He is pre¬
eminently a citizen of the world.
It is not surprising therefore that the map
of Islam should have taken no account of
natural and geographical factors, as the
faith reached out beyond deserts and moun¬
tains, beyond the arid and rainy regions
alike.
For nothing can be greater than the
"domain of Islam". Geographical and con¬
ceptual universality go together. Idea is
embodied and developed in reality.
The present geographical area of Islam ex¬
tends from Asia to. Africa and from Europe
to the continents of America and Australia.
In all climes and in all seasons, without
distinction of race or ethnic group, whether
Muslims have been in the majority or the
minority, Islam has illumined the earth; it
has moved all hearts and penetrated into all
cultures. Nothing can hem it in, for it is as
open as the sky and it breaks through all
barriers.
Our non-Muslim friends often find it hard
to understand the phenomenon of Islamisa¬
tion. Admittedly it runs counter to the form
of reasoning that classifies and sets out
causes and effects in one homogeneous
context. It is perhaps for this reason that
Islam is often regarded in the West as a
religion of war, violence and coercion.
Yet, if one examines the question closely,
it is clear that Islam has never and nowhere
imposed itself by force. This would be con¬
trary to the spirit and the letter of the Qur'an :
HABIB CHATTY, Tunisian diplomatist, has been
Secretary-General of the Organization of the Isla¬
mic Conference since October 1979. He had pre¬
viously served for several years as his country's
Minister of Foreign Affairs and had been Tunisian
ambassador to Lebanon, Syria, Turkey, Iran, the
United Kingdom and Morocco.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
The world
of Islam
which says in so many words: "There shall
be no compulsion in religion" (11:256).
To make Islam known is indeed a work of
piety, but only if dialogue and gentleness are
used rather than violence and force: "Call
men to the path of your Lord with wisdom
and kindly exhortation. Reason with them in
the most courteous manner." (XVI:125).
The Qur'an is even more strict when it refers
to the "People of the Book", whether they
be Jews or Christians: "Be courteous when
you argue with the People of the Book..."
(XXIX:46). For how can one compel a
human soul to love what it rejects? Any ac¬
ceptance obtained through coercion would
be superficial and temporary.
But the problem has not been entirely
solved and, at a time when we are seeking to
establish a dialogue between men and bet¬
ween civilizations, we must not tryto gloss
over difficulties or put forward simplified
solutions.
Islam's detractors are always quoting a
few verses from the Qur'an which in fact call
for a "holy war". In support of their argu¬
ment they also cite "historical facts" which
are often unfamiliar to them or wrongly
interpreted.
The true meaning of these verses and
these facts cannot be fully understood
unless they are seen in their historical con¬
text. Like all religions, Islam was not a
disembodied event. It came into being in
time and space, in the midst of men and
ideas. The first Muslims who adopted it
were also subject to the vicissitudes of world
history and the contingencies of human ex¬
istence in all its ideological, political,
economic and intellectual aspects. Faced
with a choice between commitment and
aloofness they chose the more difficult solu¬
tion, even though it meant engaging in bat¬
tles that were not of their seeking.
Recourse to war, even to holy war, is sub¬
ject to all kinds of moral and material restric¬
tions and to a series of strict conditions; war
is only a "last resort" to be adopted in cer¬
tain circumstances. A Muslim can react to
aggression when he is the victim, but in no
circumstance must he be the first to attack:
"If any one attacks you, attack him as he at¬
tacked you. Have fear of Allah, and know
that Allah is with the righteous" (11:194).
Legitimate defence is allowed but not un¬
justified attack. This is why, while prescrib¬
ing war to the Muslims, the Qur'an
recognizes that it can only be the object of
aversion. War is really a "last resource",
something resorted to under compulsion:
"Fighting is obligatory for you, much as you
dislike it. But you may hate a thing although
it is good for you, and love it although it is
bad for you..." (11:216). A Muslim has the
right to fight only those who fight him:
"Fight for the sake of Allah those who fight
against you, but do not attack them first.
Allah does not love the aggressors" (11:190).
Islam in fact is the only religion which has
exactly defined the rights of reprisal and the
practice of revenge in time of war. This is all
the more remarkable because, in war-time, a :
16
Photo Abdelaziz Frikha © Sud Editions, Tunis
Above, one of the four minarets of the Mosque of the Prophet at Medina. Capital
of the first Muslim State, founded by the Prophet after his emigration (Hijra) from
Mecca in September 622 (year 1 of the Hijra). Medina is with Mecca and Jerusalem
one of the three most sacred cities of the Islamic world. Muhammad's house at
Medina, where believers gathered to pray, was a prototype for later mosques. The
Prophet was buried in a chamber which forms part of the mosque of Medina, built
in the ll/8th century by the Umayyad caliph al-Walid. Here too are the tombs of his
two companions who followed him as head of the Islamic community, Abu Bakr
and Umar. Rebuilt several times after being damaged by fire, the mosque was
considerably enlarged by the Ottoman Sultan Abdul Majid in the middle of the last
century and further expansion has been carried out by the kings of Saudi Arabia
since 1953. The tombs of the Prophet, his daughter Fatima and his two successors
are virtually all that remains of the Umayyad construction. Right, a view of the
town of Ghardaia, a fortified town in Algeria which is dominated by its mosque.
The town was founded in the IV/10th century by a Berber Ibadiyah Muslim sect.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Organization of the Islamic Conference
The Organization of the Islamic Con¬
ference (OIC) which has 42 member
states, was created in September 1969
by the first summit meeting of Islamic
heads of state and government, held at
Rabat (Morocco).
The Organization, whose headquarters
are at Jeddah (Saudi Arabia) groups
states from the Arab world, Asia, Africa
and Europe, in which Muslims constitute
the majority of the population.
Its supreme governing body is the Con¬
ference of Heads of State, which has so
far been held three times: at Rabat in
1969, at Lahore (Pakistan) in 1974; and
at Mecca and Taif (Saudi Arabia) in
1981. The Conference of Foreign
Ministers has met annually since 1970 in
different cities of the Islamic world.
Several specialized committees and sub¬
sidiary bodies have been created by the
OIC, notably: the Islamic Development
Bank, the Islamic Solidarity Fund, the In
ternational Islamic News Agency, and
the Islamic States Broadcasting
Organization, all at Jeddah; the Centre
for Statistical, Economic and Social
Research, at Ankara (Turkey); the
Research Centre for Islamic History, Art
and Culture, at Istanbul (Turkey); the
Centre for Technical and Vocational
Training and Research at Dacca
(Bangladesh); and the Centre for the
Promotion of Commerce, at Tangiers
(Morocco).
The OIC, whose activities are financed
by contributions and donations from
member states, has the following aims:
"To promote Islamic solidarity among
member states. To consolidate co¬
operation among member states in the
economic, social, cultural, scientific and
other vital fields and to arrange consulta¬
tions among member states in interna¬
tional organizations. To endeavour to
eliminate racial segregation and
discrimination and to eradicate col¬
onialism in all its forms. To take
necessary measures to support interna¬
tional peace and security founded on
justice. To co-ordinate all efforts for the
safeguard of the Holy Places and sup¬
port for the struggle of the people of
Palestine to regain their "rights and
liberate their land. To strengthen the
struggle of all Muslim people with a view
to safeguarding their dignity, in¬
dependence and national rights. To
create a suitable atmosphere for the pro¬
motion of co-operation and understan¬
ding among member states and other
countries."
In addition to the OIC there are two
other major international Islamic
organizations: the World Muslim League
and the World Muslim Congress whose
headquarters are in Karachi (Pakistan).
They are both non-governmental
organizaíons.
Photo © C. Bastin and J. Evrard, Brussels
. r *- . » r.
f'^te
b%
JBB.
«-
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
The world
of Islam
-believer is either the persecutor or the
. persecuted, the victor or the vanquished: "If
you punish, let your punishment be propor¬
tionate to the wrong, that has been done
you. But it shall be best for you to endure
your wrongs with patience" (XVI:126). So,
if by good fortune the enemy inclines to
peace, a Muslim must do the same.
What could be more conducive to peace
than a heavenly voice saying: "Believers,
submit all of you to Allah and do not walk in
Satan's footsteps..." (Il:208). Those who
raise the bogy of an Islam steeped in blood
and violence are merely indirectly projecting
the image of their own unexorcized past.
Islam owes its expansion in the first in¬
stance to its universal vocation. When we
examine how it spread through the world,
we get the impression that each group won
over to the new religion behaved as though
it emanated from themselves. In all the bat¬
tles waged by the Muslims against those
who attacked them, it was the Syrians, Per¬
sians or Berbers converted to Islam who
provided the major part of the manpower,
not the Arabs. There is no more effective
means of propagating an idea than the ex¬
emplary behaviour of those who believe in
it. It is instructive to note that several far-off
countries where no fighting took place
adopted Islam of their own free will without
any outside pressure. The warmth of human
contact, the integrity of Muslim traders and
the sincerity of peaceful missionaries were
enough in themselves to overcome
paganism and to give birth to civilization.
Wherever it has been, Islam has left
behind unforgettable traces. Its spiritual
demands make it a civilizing faith. And this
must be remembered when we draw up a
world map of religions. How else can we ex¬
plain the number of urban settlements set
up by a faith which came into being not in
an industrial society, not even in an
agricultural one, but in a community which,
as Ibn Khaldun pointed out, was hostile to
city life.
Before it became a staging post for
caravans trading between distant lands, or a
Ribat (stronghold) defending believers
against enemy assaults, the Islamic city was
the setting for a way of life where everything
was done in common and everything was
decided communally. The preaching
mosque was the first distinguishing sign of
an Islamic town, as distinct from a village.
There was also the market with its separate
guilds, caravanserais and public baths. It
was a microcosm organized in a hierarchical
and concentric pattern, designed to embody
the religious and social ideal of Islam in
which men lived together, prayed together
and shared common aspirations. The object
was to gather together and not to scatter, to
unite and never to divide. Is this not an ¡deal
corresponding to every man's aspirations?
Is it not a model for construction and
civilization?
The Islamic city, a place both of work and
of worship, was also a centre of science and
culture. This, again, is one of the re¬
quirements of the Islamic faith. And in this
CONTINUED PAGE 24
18
COLOUR PAGES
4
5
6
1. A doctor takes a patient's pulse in this miniature from a
manuscript (VI I l/14th century) of Kali/a and Dimna, a Persian version
of a famous collection of Indian stories known after their narrator as
the "Fables of Bidpai". In the Islamic world medical ethics and
doctor-patient relations were defined in the IV/10th century by Razi
(known in Europe as Rhazes) who produced a vast encyclopaedia of
the medical sciences, al-Hawi (the "Comprehensive Book" famed in
the Latin world under the title Ccntinens) as well as many treatises
expounding his experiences as a physician. Along with Ibn Sina
(Avicenna, see Unesco Courier, October 1980), Razi was for centuries
considered as one of the great masters of medical science both in
the Islamic world and in the Christian West.
2. Miniature of a sesame plant from a Vll/13th century Arabic
translation of the Materia Medica of the Greek physician and
pharmacologist Dioscorides (1st century AD), a work which was
known in the Islamic world by the lll/9th century. Muslim scientists
such as the great encyclopaedist al-Biruni, Ghafiqi (Vl/12th century)
and especially Ibn al-Baytar (VI l/13th century) developed and refined
the pharmacology. Ibn al-Baytar wrote a treatise on simples which
lists 1,400 drugs of animal, plant and mineral origin. In the
19th century this work was translated into French and German.
3. This IX/15th century miniature is a striking example of Arab
hippology, the scientific study of horses, which generated a prolific
literature. Authors were preoccupied with listing and labelling
horses' physical organs as seen from the outside. For religious
reasons the dissection of animals was prohibited, but according to
some sources monkeys were brought specially from Nubia on the
orders of the Abbasid Caliph al-Mu'tasim (lll/9th century) and
dissected near Baghdad.
Photos Roland and Sabrina Michaud © Rapho, Paris
4. In accordance with a tradition of Arab cartography the south is
shown at top of this world map from a manuscript of the atlas
produced by the Vl/12th century Arab geographer al-ldrisi. Little is
known of al-ldrisi's life but according to some sources he was born
at Ceuta (Morocco) in 494 AH/1101 AD and studied the classics at
Cordoba before travelling widely in the Muslim West and probably in
certain Christian countries. He then became the court geographer of
the Norman King Roger II of Sicily, constructed a silver globe and
planisphere, and completed for his patron a work of descriptive
geography lavishly illustrated with maps and generally known as
"The Book of Roger". A synthesis of existing Greek and Arab
knowledge, "The Book of Roger'' is considered by specialists to be
the high point of Islamic cartography.
Photo © Bodleian Library, Oxford
5. Drawing of the constellations from a IX/15th century manuscript
of Suwar al-kawakib al-thabita (Images of the Stars), a treatise
written by the Persian astronomer Abd al-Rahman Sufi in the
IWIOth century at the request of the Sultan. Often copied and
illuminated, the work had a great influence on European astronomy
through a treatise written by the Spanish King Alfonso the Wise, the
Libros del Saber de Astronomía.
Photo © Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
6. Al-Biruni, born at the end of the IWIOth century, is one of the
greatest thinkers in the history of mankind. Astronomer, historian,
botanist, mineralogist, linguist and philosopher, he made notable
contributions to every branch of learning of his time (see Unesco
Courier, June 1974). Among his works is a general Introduction to
astronomy and astrology, the Kitab al-tafhim, (Elements of
Astrology) in which he discusses the different types of astrolabe and
their uses. Drawing shows part of the system of toothed wheels
whereby an astrolabe can be used to determine the position of the
heavenly bodies.
Photo Roland and Sabrina Michaud © Rapho, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Uc*-
*r
T-li j
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
1 *
-VM
ÎV V.,
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
äöfc
A
-2¿A-^J ^£U
7 - ^llh^N
^m^LW\\ ml
Kl .
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
COLOUR PAGE
Top: during the first centuries of the
Abbasid dynasty (ll-VII/8th-13th
centuries), Baghdad became a melting
pot of all the cultures of the ancient
world. Its school of translators, led by
Hunayn Ibn Ishaq (died 263 AH/877 AD)
made accessible to the Arab-Islamic
world masterworks of Greco-Hellenistic
science and philosophy, notably those
by Aristotle, Galen, Hippocrates and
Dioscorides, and encouraged the
development of a technical vocabulary
in Arabic. Aristotle, considered to be
the supreme master, is seen teaching in
this miniature from "The Best
Sentences and the Most Precious
Sayings" (from a Vll/13th century
manuscript). The accompanying text
provides a pen-portrait of the great
philosopher.
Photo © Ara Güler, Istanbul
Bottom: another strong formative
influence on Arab-Islamic civilization in
the early centuries of the Hijra was the
heritage of India and Persia. Kali/a and
Dimna, a masterpiece of classical
Arabic prose, was translated in the
ll/8th century by Ibn al-Muqaffa from a
Persian version of the Indian fables of
Bidpai. Beneath the guise of animal
stories the fables present shrewd
observations on the nature of power.
The narrator, the sage Bidpai, is here
seen bringing enlightenment to the king.
Photo © Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
IBN BATTUTA
Around the world in thirty years
Perhaps the greatest traveller who has ever lived, Ibn Battuta was born at Tangiers,
Morocco, in 703 AH1 1304 AD. At the age of twenty-one he started his travels by
undertaking the pilgrimage to Mecca. This was the start of thirty years of wandering
during which he would travel almost 120,000 kilometres and visit all the Muslim
countries.
In the course of this great journey, comparable only to that of Marco Polo, he
visited Mecca four times, became a judge in Delhi and in the Maldive Islands, accom¬
panied a Greek princess to Constantinople, sailed to Sumatra and Java, and
journeyed to China as ambassador of the Sultan of India. Then, in 750 AH1 1349 AD
he returned briefly to his own country ("the best land in the world") before setting off
immediately to the kingdom of Granada and after that on a journey through Africa to
the Niger basin.
The diary which Ibn Battuta dictated to a scribe during his travels is a source of the
first importance for the history of the Muslim world of his time, especially for the
history of India, Asia Minor and West Africa.
If there are historical inaccuracies in Ibn Battuta's writings, they are largely at¬
tributable to the pronounced taste for the bizarre which was characteristic of the age,
and to the loss of his notebooks during a pirate attack in the Indian Ocean.
But errors or exaggerations do not detract from the value of Ibn Battuta's narrative
which is written in a direct, straightforward style punctuated by observations which
are not without humour. His entertaining story has been translated, wholly or in part,
into some 15 languages and ranks among the masterpieces of Arabic literature.
The following brief extracts from The Travels of Ibn Battuta have been translated
from the 4-volume Arabic edition established by C. Defremery and B. R. Sanguinetti.
The first and third extracts are from vol. I and vol. II of the translation by
Sir Hamilton Gibb published for the Hakluyt Society by the Cambridge University
Press in 1958 and 1971.
The bountiful city of Cairo
I arrived at length at the city of Misr
(Cairo), mother of cities and seat of
Pharaoh the tyrant, mistress of broad
provinces and fruitful lands, boundless
in multitude of buildings, peerless in
beauty and splendour, the meeting-
place of comer and goer, the stopping-
place of feeble and strong. Therein is
what you will of learned and simple,
grave and gay, prudent and foolish, base
and noble, of high estate and low estate,
unknown and famous; she surges as the
waves of the sea with her throngs of folk
and can scarce contain them for all the
capacity of her situation and sustaining
power. (1, 67-68)
Portraits in Pekin
As far as painting is concerned, no na¬
tion. Christian or otherwise, can vie with
the Chinese; they have an extraordinary
talent for this art. Among the
astonishing things I have seen among
them in this respect I will say that every
time I entered one of their cities and have
returned thither since, I have always
found my portrait and those of my com¬
panions painted on the walls and on
papers in the markets. Once I entered
the city of the Sultan (Pekin); I crossed
the painters' market and arrived in the
sovereign's palace with my companions;
we were all dressed in the style of Iraq.
In the evening when I left the castle I
passed through the same market; I saw
my portrait and that of my companions
painted on pieces of paper stuck to the
walls. Each of us began to examine the
face of his comrade and we found that
the likeness was perfect. ( IV, 262)
Post haste in India
In India the horse-post, which they
call ulaq, consists of horses belonging to
the Sultan (with relays) every four miles.
The service of couriers on foot has
within the space of each mile three
relays, which they call dawa, the dawa
being a third of a mile, and a mile itself is
called by them kuruh. The manner of its
organization is as follows. At every third
of a mile there is an inhabited village,
outside which there are three pavilions.
In these sit men girded up ready to move
off, each of whom has a rod two cubits
long with copper bells at the top. When
a courier leaves the town he takes the
letter in the fingers of one hand and the
rod with the bells in the other, and runs
with all his might. The men in the
pavilions, on hearing the sound of the
bells, get ready to meet him and when
he reaches them one of them takes the
letter in his hand and passes on, running
with all his might and shaking his rod un¬
til he reaches the next dawa, and so they
continue until the letter reaches its
destination. (Ill, 95-96)
This clay statuette of a carpet-seller of Arab or Persian origin is from
the Chinese city of Kashgar, a fertile oasis at the foot of the Pamir
mountains. It dates from the Tang era (l-IV/7th-10th centuries) when
Kashgar was a thriving trading centre at a meeting point of two
branches of the silk road. As the figurine suggests, Arabs and
Persians travelled to China at the beginning of the Tang dynasty to
trade or to make their home. Around the time of the great Arab -
traveller Ibn Battuta, who arrived in Pekin in 673 AH/1275 AD, four
years before Kublai Khan became emperor of China, the Mongol
conquerors of Sung China encouraged Muslims, Jews and Christians
as well as various peoples of central Asia, to settle in China.
Photo © Royal Ontario Museum, Toronto
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The world
of Islam
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 18
age of exact sciences and precision
technology, the objective historian cannot
fail to recall the decisive role played in this
field by Islamic cities such as Kairouan,
Cairo, Fez, Marrakesh, Tlemcem and Alex¬
andria in Africa, Baghdad, Basra, Kufa,
Damascus, Ispahan, Bukhara, Samarkand
and Lahore in Asia, and Istanbul and Cor¬
doba in Europe. Within these medinas, with
their minarets towering above all others in
the sky of human knowledge, the sciences
of the whole world Chinese and Indian,
Greek and Roman, Egyptian and Chaldean,
theoretical, practical, experimental and for¬
mal patiently gathered together, lov¬
ingly preserved, translated, commentated
upon, studied, recreated and rethought by a
succession of inspired scholars. The Islamic
city was an intellectual workshop which
gave rise to an unprecedented development
of knowledge without which the modern
world as we know it would never have been
possible. This is recognized unanimously by
historians of science from Sarton to Crom-
bie in the United States and from Duhème
to Koyré and Taton in France.
The opportunities open to the Islamic
world today seem even richer than those
which produced the glories of its past. The
realm of thought which has given so much
to mankind is still full of promise, eager to
serve and to work for a better international
order.
True, the Crusades, the Mongol inva¬
sions, the Spanish Inquisition and, more
recently, colonialism have left bitter
memories which caused the Islamic world to
adopt for a time a defensive attitude. But to¬
day, despite all obstacles, it is regaining con¬
fidence. The task will not be an easy one.
The Muslim world must first overcome its in¬
ternal contradictions and dissensions. It
must seek cohesion within each country, for
at present this cohesion is threatened by
disputes between movements and sects
which are not really divided by anything ex¬
cept a legitimate desire to be more useful. It
must also strengthen the fraternal and.
neighbourly links between the countries
involved.
There is no denying the fact that the
Islamic world is going through a crisis. But
these are only growing pains. Disputes bet¬
ween religious sects (Sunnites and Shi'ites)
political differences and armed conflicts can
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Right, street scene in Skopje,
Yugoslavia, with mosque in
background. Skopje and Sarajevo are
the main centres of the Yugoslav
Islamic community which is estimated
at about three million. Below, the
domes of Istanbul with in the
background, the Golden Horn and the
minarets of the famous "Blue Mosque",
built In the Xl/17th century by Sultan
Ahmed Djami.
only be seen, from a historical point of view,
as passing difficulties.
Over and above incidental conflicts and
temporary inconsistencies, Muslims see
themselves as members of an Umma or
spiritual community which transcends all
differences and resolves all disagreements.
For this reason, I believe that the divine link
uniting them will always prove stronger than
the interests which today oppose some
members of the Islamic family.
Our history, both modern and ancient,
which shows that Muslims disagree with
one another only to come eventually to a
better accord, strengthens me in this con¬
viction; so does the history of other peoples.
The present lack of unity in the Muslim
world is not a unique case in the history of
mankind. Europe, flourishing today, has liv¬
ed through two devastating wars. Yet it has
succeeded in assuaging its passions. The
Muslim world has all the more reason for
believing it can do the same since it sees
itself as an Umma, a community in which
mutual aid, protection and confidence are
the rules of life and the basis of a common
spirituality.
This need for unity is all the more urgent
because the Muslim world is confronted
with a centuries old problem of
underdevelopment. It has done much
already to solve this problem, but must do
more still if it is to take its rightful place in a
modern world which Islam, though tem¬
porarily left behind, contributed so much to
create.
Such are our hopes and preoccupations,
such is the meaning of the task which the
Muslim world has undertaken to achieve.
These are also the objectives of the policy
which the Organization of the Islamic Con¬
ference (O.I.C.) has followed since its incep¬
tion. Grouping a quarter of the Member
States of the United Nations, the O.I.C. is a
major force in international politics which
keeps an equal distance from the super¬
powers in its desire to maintain its autonomy
in decision-making, its freedom of choice
and direction. By creating the O.I.C, the]
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The world
of Islam
. Muslim countries, conscious of the impor¬
tance of their human and natural resources
and of their economic and political weight,
have set themselves a single goal: to unite,
so as to face the exigencies of modern life
and serve mankind better; to establish a
dialogue between men everywhere without
distinction of race, culture or ideology, so as
to help them know one another better and
recognize both their basic likenesses. and
their legitimate differences.
We believe that this is the way to achieve
the victory of peace over war, brotherhood
over hatred, tolerance over fanaticism, a
better world order and a life of more justice
and dignity. We are convinced that by
holding out our hand to our neighbours in a
spirit of sincerity we shall call forth a
response that will fulfil the aspirations, not
only of the Muslim countries, but of all
mankind. This is the meaning of the
message from Mecca, solemnly proclaimed
in Taif (Saudi Arabia) by thirty-eight heads
of State representing one thousand million
Muslims. May this appeal be heard and a
true dialogue of civilizations be established
between the peoples of the world.
Habib Chatty
Document Courtesy of André Stevens
Below, the Taj Mahal, Agra, India, the summit of Indo-
Islamic architecture, was built in the Xl/17th century by
the Moghul ruler Shah Jahan as a mausoleum for his wife
Mumtaz-i-Mahal. Its ethereal lightness contrasts with the
impressive mass (below right) of the mausoleum of Imam
Reza, at Mashad, one of the holiest cities in Iran. Imam
Reza is revered by the Shi'ite Muslims as the eighth
Imam, or leader, in direct line of descent from the
Prophet. The mausoleum was built during the lll/9th
century and successive Muslim rulers have added to it
over the centuries.
Photo Georg Gerster © Rapho, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Above. Chinese scroll
showing the layout of a
Muslim compound built
during the II 8th century
under the Tang dynasty. The
compound was located in
the centre of the city of
Chian in the province of
Kiangsi, south central
China. The mosque (photo
right), which is clearly
recognizable in the scroll, is
now being restored.
Photo © Roger Wood, London
« \ ELM
*Wf ¿, V ' inn B"V
£ ? ,~ ''"&£m:. R ¿fh *
i 1 ¡Í
i
/ 'i
f§ fil ï^ f 1#¡
/íí^ (£m% H* , . ;
ill
I»1
" 1
A
II*****
it* * * *,
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
The world
of Islam
Muslims
of
the Soviet Union
by Ziyauddin Khan Ibn Ishan Babakhan
Muslim scholars in the library of the Miri-Arab madrasah (see caption page 34)
at Bukhara, in the Uzbek Soviet Socialist Republic.
"You are the noblest nation that has ever
been raised up for mankind. You enjoin
justice and forbid evil. You believe in Allah. "
(The Qur'an, III: 110)
IN the Soviet Union Islam is professed by
people representing dozens of nations
and ethnic groups. The proportion of
Muslims is highest in central Asia, the
Caucasus and the Middle Volga regions.
The majority of these Muslims profess the
Islam of the Hanafite school of the Sunni
trend, but there are also Shafi'ites in the
northern Caucasus, Shi'ites in Trans¬
caucasia and Isma'ilis in the Pamirs.
Striving to build the most just and pros¬
perous society free from social conflict and
class struggle, the Muslims of the Soviet
Union scrupulously carry out all the
prescriptions and rites of their Holy Religion.
The month of Ramadan is a great and
joyful event for every Muslim. In the Islamic
tradition it is the holiest month, that of the
obligatory fast from dawn to sunset.
Muslims in the Soviet Union prepare for it in
good time. Already during the month of
Sha'ban which precedes it special sermons
are preached in the mosques by the Imam-
khatibs in which they explain the
significance of the fast.
The advent of the month of Ramadan is
marked by another important custom. From
the first days of the month groups of
children of the faithful visit the houses of
other believers to wish them health and hap¬
piness, singing traditional songs concerning
the holy month and asking Allah to send the
master of the house a lusty son. In return
the faithful lavish sweets and presents on
the children.
Muslims fast with great zeal and in exact
conformity with the prescriptions of the
Holy Qur'an; they say their prayers five
times a day and in the evening they go to the
mosque to take part in the Salat al-Tarawih
(optional prayers said only during
Ramadan). Many of the older Muslims begin
to fast two months before Ramadan which
for the Muslims of the Soviet Union is tradi¬
tionally a period when friendships and family
ties are strengthened. Grown-up children
who have their own homes or families visit
their parents and receive their blessing.
Friends and acquaintances visit one another
and a particular effort is made to ensure that
no Muslim is left without help.
This is also the time of the ancient na¬
tional rite of Iftar; a Muslim family will invite
several dozen fellow-believers to break the
fast after sundown with them and this is
often accompanied by prayers and readings
from tne Holy Qur'an by a member of the
clergy. As a result of rising standards of liv¬
ing, almost every believer manages to invite
a group of the faithful to his house at
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
least once during the month of Ramadan for
this nightly breaking of the fast.
The Lai/at al-Kadar, one of the most
revered nights in the month of Ramadan,
when Allah started to send down the Qur'an
to the Prophet Muhammad (Peace be on
Him), is celebrated by all the Muslims in the
Soviet Union. In some places it is marked by
solemn services and special sermons in the
mosques, while in others it is more of a fami¬
ly occasion with readings from the Holy
Qur'an and prayers to Allah.
On the first day of the month of Shawwal,
the month after Ramadan, begins the
solemn feast of Id al-Fitr which marks the
ending of the fast. On the eve of this feast
every Muslim contributes a Sadaka al-Fitr, a
voluntary offering originally intended for the
poor but, now that living standards have
considerably improved, are made to the
mosque to be used for benevolent purposes
such as the restoration of cultural
monuments and as contributions to the
Soviet Peace Fund.
On the feast day solemn services are con¬
ducted and famous theologians preach ser¬
mons concerning the principles of the
Islamic Faith, the need to do good and the
desire of Muslims for peace and friendship
among peoples. The celebrations also have
a worldly aspect; in the republics of central
Asia the mosques are surrounded by im¬
provised bazaars which offer various oriental
sweets, soft drinks and toys for children,
while swings and other entertainments are
also available. In the country areas horse-
riding is a popular attraction.
Another memorable feature of the fast of
Ramadan is the Khatm Qur'an, the recital of
the whole of the Holy Qur'an by heart. The
ability to recite the Holy Qur'an by heart ac¬
cording to all the rules is highly appreciated
throughout the Muslim world and Muslims
in our country have long been noted as ex¬
perts in this art. Those who can perform this
feat are given the title of Hafiz, the keepers
of the Holy Qur'an. To this day hundreds of
people keep this noble tradition alive,
displaying their skill not only during the fast
but also at the regular Friday services or on
other festive occasions. At an international
competition on the occasion of the 1,400th
anniversary of the sending down of the Holy
CONTINUED PAGE 78
MUFTI ZIYAUDDIIM KHAN IBN ISHAN
BABAKHAN, is Chairman of the Muslim Reli¬
gious Board for Central Asia and Kazakhstan, one
of four such Boards of Muslims in the USSR. A
well-known figure in the world of Islam, he has
attended many international Muslim conferences
and is a member of the Supreme Islamic Council
for Mosques at Mecca. His book Islam and the
Muslims in the Land of Soviets was published in
English by Progress Publishers in 1980, on the eve
of the 15th century of the Hegira (Hijra).
Í
Once the capital of a powerful Khanate, the ancient city of Khiva, in the Uzbek SSR, is
now preserved as a "city-museum". The old walled inner city contains palaces, mosques,
minarets and madrasahs (colleges) which, like the Kutlug Mourad Inat madrasah, seen
here at the end of a narrow stone-paved street, bear the imprint of the eastern Muslim
architectural style. .
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The world
of Islam
Renewal and
by Siti Baroroh Baried
SURPRISING though it may seem to
non-specialists, Indonesia, on the
other side of the globe from the
birthplace of Islam, is the home of a larger
Muslim population over 120 million than
any other nation. And yet in this archipelago
of over 3,000 islands strung across the
Equator, Islam has been helping to shape
the course of history for hundreds of years.
In the present century, especially, after In¬
donesian thinkers and scholars came for the
first time into contact with the vital centres
of Islamic thought, a powerful Islamic
reform and modernization movement came
to the fore. It exercised, and continues to
exercise, a wide influence in such fields as
education, culture and social welfare. One
of the organizations belonging to this move¬
ment, the Muhammadiyyah, has played a
pioneering role in the Indonesian women's
movement.
The origins of Indonesia's vast Muslim
community can be traced back directly to
the proselytizing efforts of Arab and Indian
missionaries who initially had to carry out
their work without any patronage or
assistance from the rulers of the country,
relying solely on the force of persuasion.
It is impossible to fix a precise date for the
introduction of Islam into the Malay Ar¬
chipelago, of which present-day Indonesia is
a part, but it may have been brought there
by Arab traders in the early centuries of the
Hijra. Trade with China, through Ceylon,
began to expand rapidly at the beginning of
the l/7th century, and by the middle of the
ll/8th there were large numbers of Arab
traders in Canton. Later, from the IV/10th
until the IX/15th century and the arrival of
the Portuguese, Arabs were the undisputed
masters of trade with the east.
We may therefore conjecture with
reasonable certainty that Arabs must at a
very early period have established trading
settlements on some of the islands of the
Malay Archipelago, just as they did
elsewhere. Although no mention is made of
these islands by Arab geographers before
the IV/10th century, the Chinese annals,
under the date 54 AH/674 AD, give an ac¬
count of an Arab chief who, it may be con¬
jectured from later evidence, could have
been the head of an Arab settlement on the
west coast of Sumatra.
Missionaries must also, however, have
come from the south of India, judging from
certain characteristics of the Islamic
theology which was adopted in the islands.
This is important because they brought with
them a form of Islam which had inevitably
been influenced by Hinduism and, since
Islam had already crossed Persia before it
reached India, had also received Persian
cultural influence. The Indian missionaries
SITI BAROROH BARIED, of Indonesia, is pro¬
fessor of Islamic Studies at the State Islamic Stu¬
dies Institute, Yogyakarta, and professor of Indo¬
nesian Language at Gadjah Mada University,
Yogyakarta.
belonged to the Shafi'yyah sect, which still
holds sway in parts of southern India, while
the Shi'ism of which traces are still found in
Java and Sumatra must also have come
from India or from Persia.
Islam probably gained its first real
foothold in Indonesia sometime late in the
Vll/13th century when the Islamic Kingdom
of Samudra Pasai was founded in northern
Sumatra. Its Sultan's tomb, dated
696 AH/1297 AD, has survived and bears an
inscription written entirely in Arabic. Echoes
of the persistent relationship between the
archipelago and India and Persia were evok¬
ed in the following century by the famous
Arab traveller Ibn Battuta (see page 23) who
described how the Sultan of Samudra had
entered into friendly relations with the court
of Delhi and how, among the learned doc¬
tors of the law favoured by this devout
prince there were two of Persian origin.
The spread of Islam throughout the ar¬
chipelago was a long process which lasted
for centuries and was marked by the rise and
fall of a succession of Islamic kingdoms in
Java, Celebes, Borneo, Molucca and Sum-
ba. As it gained ground the new faith came
into contact with local cultures, especially
the mixture of animism and Hinduism that
had hitherto prevailed, and acquired as a
result certain features which went against
strict Islamic principles. Sufis and groups of
mystics were the chief architects of this ex¬
pansion, and an inclination towards
mysticism came to be characteristic of Islam
in Indonesia. It has been said that these
mystic teachings fostered a blind faith rather
than a spirit of enquiry into the laws of
Islam, carried out in harmony with ¡deals of
development and progress, and that Islam's
greatness during these shadowy,
kaleidoscopic centuries was only apparent in
a handful of outstanding figures. But until
the Xlll/19th century the Muslims of the ar¬
chipelago did not affirm their personality
and identity.
It was the invention of the steam ship and
the development of sea travel which gave a
remarkable new impetus to Islam in In¬
donesia. Now for the first time well-to-do In¬
donesians were able to make the pilgrimage
to Mecca. This marked the real beginning of
direct communication between Indonesian
Muslims and the birthplace of Islam, and
brought them into contact with Muslim
leaders from other countries such as Egypt,
Syria, India and Algeria.
Many Indonesian pilgrims stayed on in
Arabia to study the teachings of Islam from
original sources, and closely followed the
rise of the reformation movement launched
by the Wahabi group, Jamaluddin al-
Afghani and the Egyptian Muhammad Ab-
duh. Some of these scholars wrote books
on religious subjects in various Indonesian
languages. When they returned home,
where they became known as the Islamic
Reformists, they set out to lead Indonesian
Muslims back to a form of Islam based ex¬
clusively on the Qur'an and the Sunna, to
simplify the religious service, and to get rid
of everything which was extraneous to the
Islamic faith.
A theologian and trader named Kyai Haji
Ahmad Dahlan was one of the leading
figures in this movement. Dahlan realized
that Muslims in Indonesia were facing a
crisis of faith, and in Yogyakarta in 1330
AH/ 1912 AD he founded an organization
called the Muhammadiyyah, which was
dedicated to the purification of Indonesian
Islam and the elimination from it of animistic
influences. In its early years the Muham¬
madiyyah functioned through the pesan-
tren, the traditional institution of Islamic
learning in Indonesia, but in the course of
time it became a highly organized movement
active in education, social welfare, culture,
health, economic life, the law, publishing,
the youth movement and the women's
movement.
A striking example of Dahlan's pro¬
gressive approach was his decision to create
a women's section of the Muhammadiyyah.
Since many parts of the Qur'an and the
Sunna are addressed to women and con¬
cern their rights and duties, he reasoned,
then women must be instructed in the
teachings of Islam if they are to enjoy these
rights and carry out these duties. He was
also fully aware of the potential of women,
as well as men, in building the Muslim com¬
munity. In this preoccupation with educa¬
tion, Dahlan shared the ideals of Kartini, the
Javanese woman who is considered to be
the first Indonesian champion of equal rights
and education for women. The difference
was that Kartini observed the lives of
women in aristocratic society, whereas
Dahlan, travelling to remote parts of the
country on business, saw at first hand the
wretched conditions of women living in
poverty.
The women's section of the Muham¬
madiyyah, the Aisyiyah, came into being in
1335 AH/1917 AD. It began its existence in
the village of Kauman Yogyakarta where it
built in 1341 AH/1923 AD Indonesia's first
mosque for women, then considered to be
an important step forward to reform. Today,
half a century later, the organization is still
as active as ever in carrying out its mission
through the establishment of schools, or¬
phanages and hostels for girl students, and
through organizing courses on themes rang¬
ing from mental health to handicrafts.
In 1346 AH/1928 AD Aisyiyah was one of
seven women's organizations which took
the initiative of holding the Indonesian
Women's Conference. This led to the crea¬
tion of the federation, now known as the In¬
donesian Women's Congress, which groups
all Indonesian women's organizations and of
which Aisyiyah is still a member.
It continues to work for the progress of In¬
donesian women, and its activities, thanks
to Dahlan's farsightedness as a reformist, il¬
lustrate one of the many contributions
which the Islamic modernization movement
has made to life in Indonesia.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
reform in Indonesia
^tfSá
A gathering of members of the Aisyiyah, the women's
section of the Muhammadiyyah Muslim reformist
movement in Indonesia.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The world
of Islam
The impact
on
black Africa
by Sulayman S. Nyang
Built in 1951, the central mosque at Kano is the largest in Nigeria.
THE expansion of the religion of Islam in
Africa had great significance for the
peoples of the continent. Since Islam
came to Africa as a belief system that prided
itself on its command of the written word
and on the material culture associated with
the Word of Allah Himself, it is certainly not
surprising that its propagators found it
necessary to teach their doctrines and rituals
while trading with the inhabitants of African
Kingdoms on or below the Sahel.
This intercourse between the Arabs and
the Berbers, on the one hand, and Black
Africans to the south on the other, opened
the door to greater cultural penetration.
When we look at the balance sheet of
Arabo-lslamic/African relations, we find
that the major contribution of Islam in the
continent is in the field of intellectual, social,
and cultural development.
Islam introduced a new way of looking at
life, man and community. Whereas
previously the African man lived primarily in
a self-enclosed world which restricted his
cultural and mental encounters to the en¬
vironment of his primary ethnic group, the
impact of Islam on his consciousness gave
rise to a sense of cosmopolitanism. The con¬
version of the tribal African exposed him for
the first time to the brotherhood of Islam,
whose borders were beyond what his eyes
could see and whose message was aimed at
and directed to, all men and women living
on this planet.
On the social plane, the conversion of the
tribal African to the religion of Muhammad
opened, to a certain degree, the door of
inter-ethnic co-operation. The fact that the
Muslim propagators were in most cases
merchants made the converts more recep¬
tive to the new ideas and new wares
brought into their areas by their fellow co¬
religionists.
Islam provided a common moral basis for
commerce and trade and the Shari'a guided
all the Muslim merchants in their dealings
with one another and with their non-Muslim
customers. In addition, in areas of endemic
conflict there was a need for readily iden¬
tifiable neutrals to serve as go-betweens,
and the parties to conflicts granted special
treatment to those who, by virtue of their
trade or profession, were considered
non-combatants.
The close relationship between trade and
Islam made it possible for the new convert
to develop gradually some degree of trust
and confidence in men who did not
necessarily speak his language but embrac¬
ed the teachings of his newly adopted
religion. This new attitude towards non-
members of one's ethnic group was certain¬
ly revolutionary, and its potential for greater
inter-ethnic co-operation could not be
dismissed lightly.
Though Islam was not the factor responsi¬
ble for the immediate founding of the three
great West Sudanese empires, the fact re¬
mains that these empires and their rulers
profited from the Islamic symbols of their
day and their cultural and economic systems
were, in varying degrees, exposed to the
forces and pressures of the faraway Islamic
centres of civilization to the north and
northeast.
In fact, in talking about the Islamic con¬
tribution to the social universe of the
African, one could argue that the arrival of
Islam in the continent widened the horizons
of the traditional African to some extent.
Whereas in the past this man entrusted his
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The oasis cities of Tichitt (above), Ouadane, Chinguetti
and Oualata, in the Mauritanian Sahara, are the last
reminders of the former greatness of a region which
lay at the cross-roads of major caravan routes linking
the Maghreb and the Sahel. Their fame as centres of
intellectual as well as commercial exchange attracted
scholars from throughout Islam. At Chinguetti, the
starting point for caravans setting out for Mecca, a
great library was established, and here too an original
architectural form took shape which blended the
ideals of Islam with the African cultural tradition.
Today the trade routes pass elsewhere and these once
great cities are threatened by drought, decay and
desert advance. In February 1981 the Director-General
of Unesco launched a solemn appeal for international
action to safeguard these historic sites for posterity.
destiny to the spirits who resided in a well, a
tree or a stream and saw man's life as a link
in a chain of beings going back to a mystical
founder of his clan or tribe, and whereas he
wished to placate the gods and the
ancestors, under the Islamic religion he
found that his life was for an appointed term
and that his deeds on earth had a meaning
specific to himself.
He also learned from his Islamic mentors
that whatever he did in his lifetime would be
accounted for in the hereafter, and the only
way he could save his soul and himself at
the Day of Judgement was to accept the
responsibility of living. This is to say that the
conversion of the traditional African meant
his gradual realization of the spiritual
loneliness of man in the world and his
responsibility for living up to the expecta¬
tions of his religion.
Such an understanding of self and life
gave rise to the attempt on the part of many
African converts to put into practice the
rituals and teachings of Islam. It was indeed
in their attempt to live up to the Islamic ideal
that many traditional Africans learned to
pray with fellow Muslims, or to stand alone
before Allah. In their desire to win the
favours of their Maker, they learned to fulfil
the expectations of the Qur'anic teachings
on cleanliness and modesty in clothing.
At the institutional level, one can argue
that the religion of Islam introduced several
changes in African life. The arrival of a
Muslim scholar in an African community
most often led to the establishment of the
Madrasah (Qur'anic school). This new in¬
stitution gradually replaced, or co-existed
with, the traditional centres of education,
and the students who were brought before
the Qur'anic teacher were slowly inducted
into the Islamic culture from the north and
northeast.
Besides the Qur'anic school, there were
other institutional forms of cultural borrow
ing. With the gradual penetration of the
African consciousness, Islam began to in¬
vade the African conceptual world and soon
the process of linguistic absorption started
to take effect. Consciously or unconscious¬
ly, the newly converted African Muslim
began to drop traditional words in his
language in favour of borrowed Islamic
terminology.
A classic example of an African language
that has been very much penetrated by the
Arabo-lslamic influence is Wolof. The arrival
of Islam not only affected the Wolof's con¬
ception of time, it also substituted many
Arabic terms in his vocabulary. As an il¬
lustration, let us take the names given to the
seven days of the week. As a result of the
Arabo-lslamic influence, the Wolof
language, as spoken in the Senegambian
region, carries four Arabic words for Tues¬
day (Arabic Thalatah), Wednesday (Al-
Arba), Thursday (Al-Khamis) and Friday (Al-
Jummah). This is a phenomenon that is
widely known in the African communities
that have established long contact with the
Islamic religion.
Another example of institutional borrow¬
ing was the Tariqa (Sufi brotherhood). The
arrival of the Sufi brotherhoods ushered in a
train of developments which affected the
history of many African societies south of
the Sahara. It is well-known in the growing
literature on the Islamic jihads in Africa
south of the Sahara that the followers of the
Sufi brotherhoods played an important role.
A further contribution of Islam is the suc¬
cessful adoption of the Arabic script for the
reduction of African languages into writing.
This Arabo-lslamic cultural contribution is
by no means insignificant. Indeed such a
development in Africa's cultural history led
to the emergence of a limited form of
literacy among many of the Muslim peoples
of the West Sudan.
The first products of this newly imported
technology of intellectual conservation were
the epistles and explanatory comments writ¬
ten down by the ulema (men versed in
Islamic religion and law) in the West Sudan.
It is quite conceivable that many of the West
Sudanic ulema found it desirable from time
to time to reduce to writing their thoughts
on certain matters affecting the education of
their students.
Another possible reason for the
emergence of the written forms of the ver¬
nacular was the desire of the more ag¬
gressive propagators of the religion to make
their message more accessible to the rank
and file of their Islamic movement. Some
scholars have recently suggested that the
earlier literary products of the African ver¬
nacular languages that adopted Arabic or
even a European language, cannot be
classified as literature. They were merely the
first manifestation of a foreign script at the
service of an African language.
They also believe, and quite correctly,
that "... such texts in the West African
languages were usually merely parallel to the
more important and prestigious originals in
the particular languages of the given
cultures and powers." But regardless of the
limitations of the newly established
technology of intellectual conservation,
there is strong evidence that such a develop¬
ment had a great impact on the traditional
African's social universe.
SULAYMAN S. NYANG, Gambian educator, is
currently associate professor of government and
public administration at the Center for African
Studies, Howard University, Washington, D.C.
He is the author of a number of studies relating to
Islamic, African and Middle Eastern questions. A
longer version of the present article was presen¬
ted at the World of Islam Conference organized
by the Organization of the Islamic Conference and
held at Unesco HQ in Paris in December 1980.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Teachers, disciples and the
by Mohammed Allai Sinaceur
The madrasah ("school") was the university of the Islamic world in
the first centuries of the Hijra. The curriculum was based largely on
the Qur'an, the Hadith (see boxes pages 8 and 9) and Islamic
theology and law, but other disciplines were also taught such as
grammar, literature, mathematics, and sometimes medicine (with a
hospital being attached to the madrasah). Education was free in the
madrasah, which was supported by the system of waqf (pious
endowments), and students were awarded bursaries and provided
with lodgings. The teacher lectured from a pulpit while his pupils sat
in a circle around him. Below, the great mosque of Qarawiyyin at
Fez (Morocco) is the centre of one of the world's oldest universities,
founded in 245 AH/859 AD. It stands in the heart of the Medina (old
city). In 1960 the university's teaching activities were transferred to
buildings outside the old city.
THE Qur'an is one of the most beauti¬
ful hymns to knowledge. It invites
study, harmonizes mystery and rea¬
son, and exalts those who meditate on the
creation and are just towards their fellow
men. All these themes are brought together
at the beginning of the LV Surah, "The Mer¬
ciful", which reads:
"It is the Merciful who has taught you
the Qur'an. He created man and taught
him articulate speech. The sun and the
moon pursue their ordered course... He
raised the heaven on high and set the
balance of all things, that you might not
transgress it. Give just weight and full
measure."
The gift of language in a universe govern¬
ed by order and moderation and the quest
for honesty and justice in dealings between
menall these are different expressions of a
single design. And it is through the Qur'an
whose spirit permeates a whole system of
learning that the Muslim receives his first in¬
itiation and gains his first apprehension of
the world. The knowledge generated by the
Qur'an reassures and liberates because it
shows the way to the comprehension of
things, to self-knowledge and recognition of
others.
It is therefore a special kind of knowledge
which frees man from the debilitating quest
for absolute truth, which recognizes that
progress is a continuing process and that its
meaning and ends are justified only by the
benefits it brings to humanity. The ideal of
the perfect man wholeheartedly and
unhesitatingly defending the rights of God
and persevering in the performance of his
duties lies at the heart of the extraordinary
flowering of culture and the all-
encompássing curiosity that incorporated
and assimilated the wisdom and skills of
past civilizations.
The exigencies of learning and the
demands of humility are linked in the obliga¬
tion to learn and to know, to understand and
to pass on the results of research and
knowledge, as is symbolically expressed in
the parable of Moses related in the Surah of
the cave.
According to tradition, Moses claimed to
be the wisest among men. He came to
realize his temerity when he met al-Khidr,
"one of Our slaves to whom We had given
of Our grace and of Our knowledge". (A
slave, according to the Qur'an, is a man who
fulfils his religious obligation, a pious man,
who is the slave only of God and to whom is
MOHAMMED ALLAL SINACEUR, head of
Unesco's Division of Philosophy, was formerly a
department head at the French National Centre of
Scientific Research and later professor of socio¬
logy at Hassan II University in Casablanca
(Morocco). A member of the Academy of the
Kingdom of Morocco, he has published a number
ofarticles, notably on philosophical questions and
the history of mathematics.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
ethics of learning
granted saving powers of mind, will and
word.) What better reward for the passion
of learning, what better fulfilment for the
duty of knowledge than this pious man's
meeting with Moses, who came upon him
after a difficult quest!
"Moses says to him: Can I follow you on
the true path, so that you may teach me a lit¬
tle of what you have been taught?" The no¬
tion of path is akin to the modern concept of
method. But here the method is a path, not
a ready-made formula for a solution. It is a
way to be followed, a road along which one
is led and to which one asks to be led.
The master, "Our slave", answered: "You
will not be patient enough with me. How
should you be patient when you do not
understand?"
Learning calls for patience. Nothing is
learned in haste. Learning means suspen¬
ding one's judgment for a while. But the
master does not refuse to teach, nor does
the disciple scorn to follow. For both, the
teaching relationship is maintained not by
hierarchy but the difference of function.
Moses said: "If God so wills, I shall be
patient and not disobey thee." Though
Moses was a prophet and knew all that
.divine science could teach, he received this
answer: "If you follow me, ask me no ques¬
tion unless I speak first."
A lesson in listening, but also and above
all an exercise in the virtue of silence.
Silence is a form of wisdom that few people
practise. Without it one cannot reach one's
inner self, and if one does not know one's
self one is deaf to the words of others. This
is the meaning of the parable: for the Qur'an
the master/disciple relationship symbolizes
the quest for knowledge at whatever price;
the patience required to achieve it; the
spiritual discipline needed to assimilate it;
and meditation on its consequences.
The parable also teaches that insight en¬
tails foresight, and that the consequence of
the act of knowing is part of the act itself.
All teaching is seen in an ethical context.
And the ethic holds good for all knowledge,
sacred or profane, legal or medical,
technical or theoretical. It is the basis of
every method of acquiring and imparting
knowledge.
The frequency of the terms to know, to
learn, to teach, and the amount of literature
about them show the importance of
knowledge and its diffusion in Islam, as well
as the realization that knowledge is bound
up with human and social responsibilities
and that the teacher's role, therefore, is
always more ethical than technical. Hence
the universal value for man of knowledge
which affects his destiny, his fulfilment and
the conquest within himself and outside
himself of the dialectics of change.
The teacher/pupil relationship must
therefore be exemplary. It is modelled on the
transcendental God taught Adam and its
meaning is confirmed by revelation; the Pro¬
phet, God's Messenger, is first and foremost
a teacher, the mu'a/im, we are told, of an
almost illiterate and innumerate community.
Prisoners were set free if they taught ten
Muslim children to read. And the Suffah
mosque, built when the Prophet came to
Medina at the beginning of the Hijra, whose
anniversary we are now celebrating, was the
first institution to teach "the Book and the
Wisdom".
The unique quality of Islam is that it
preserved both the transcendent and the
human reference of knowledge by combin¬
ing faith and knowledge without restricting
the latter to revelation or if such a distinc¬
tion can be made making it subservient to
revelation's ends.
The logic inherent in faith teaches that
"truth can be distinguished from
falsehood", that it leads "from darkness to
light" and embodies the rights of God and
the rights of man, religion and scholarship.
Hence the extraordinary versatility of the
root "Urn" in the verb "to know" and its
derivatives which can be applied at all levels
and to all disciplines.
Islam's originality lies not only in the ex¬
ceptional importance it attaches to
knowledge, but also in the ceaseless quest
for learning perceived and defined as a com¬
mon heritage which no man may
monopolize. Nothing is more foreign to'
Islam than a system that limits the use of
knowledge or restricts its circulation submit¬
ting the flow of scientific or technical infor¬
mation to the needs of the market, of effi¬
ciency and profitability.
The belief that knowledge is designed for
the entire community obliges the scholar to
pass on his learning to all those who seek it. ]
- tu* *i4
u
vi
1 1 IT
uli j 111
I I ! Ill
III III
¿ * *%* V«,
[#Là '4Mb
^5jEf-s
ill», ^5 ^J
^»
A
Be'*"1
Photo © Malaysian Embassy, Paris A lecture In progress at the University of Malaya, Kuala Lumpur.
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
-That it represents a legitimate aspiration is
shown in this appeal by one of the prophets:
"Lord, increase my knowledge." That the
scholar is worthy of respect is implied in this
question: "Are they who know equal to
those who know not?", and the Qur'an also
bids us heed the scholar: "If you do not
know, ask of them who do.".
Knowledge, moreover, signifies a never-
ending learning process, an infinite possibili¬
ty of improvement and progress. Islam
tends to concentrate less on speculating
about the nature of knowledge and on
evolving a science of knowledge than on
making it a "productive" reality, more im¬
portant for what it aims at and for the
changes it brings about than for what it is.
The fundamental relationship established
between knowledge and action is based on
Right, pupils in this rural primary
school in Afghanistan learn to read and
write and acquire a grounding in
religion by learning verses from the
Qur'an read out by their teacher. They
are also taught geography, natural
sciences and maths.
Photo © Laurence Brun, Paris
Students at work in a physics
laboratory in Omdurman, Sudan.
Photo Jean Mohr, Unesco
this concept. Any act that contradicts
knowledge calls knowledge itself into ques¬
tion. This idea is expressed in the popular
saying: "Knowledge unapplied is like a
cloud without rain". Though the delights of
learning for its own sake are often proclaim¬
ed, knowledge must also be useful in the
widest sense, serving the spiritual, intellec¬
tual or material needs of mankind. For
reciprocity between diverse elements is part
of the spirit of Islam, which combines
secular education (adab ad-dunia) and
religious education (adab ad-din) without
losing sight of the difference between them.
Science and technology must be guided
by practical principles compatible with
man's destiny and the preservation of the
heritage entrusted to him as God's lieu¬
tenant on earth, as the vessel of revelation
responsible before God for Nature as well as
for himself, since he has accepted the
awesome honour of this mission before
which "the mountains themselves drew
back".
Knowledge was also inseparable from
education, the paideia of the ancient
Greeks. The notions of 'ilm (knowledge/
science) and of 'adab (humanistic or moral
training) are always related, as is shown by
their derivatives ta'lim and ta'dib, signifying
respectively education resulting in
knowledge, and education as a way to
enlightenment and to moral elegance. In
other words: well-founded knowledge and a
high sense of social obligations, an ideal
which unites the defence of God's rights
and the demands of life on earth. Or again:
all that is needed for the complete develop-
Üt&
£jr~
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
ment of man's moral and intellectual
personality.
The 'alim, or man of learning, was a
teacher before being a specialist.
Knowledge cannot be reduced to informa¬
tion acquired from books and other sources.
The teacher played such a vital role in the
educative project of the community that the
Qur'an exempted him from fighting in time
of war. For the Muslim, he embodied an
ideal that raised education and knowledge
to the status of a social ethic and aesthetic.
As a VI /12th century author expressed it:
"Knowledge without education is like a fire
without fuel; 'adab without knowledge is
like a mind without a body."
The master was a living example of what
he taught, committed to the message he
transmitted, a motive force for social change
insofar as he himself was capable of change.
One can see why folk wisdom has preserved
the idea that knowledge proceeds out of the
mouths of men provided, of course, that
such men be wise, accomplished and wor¬
thy to serve as an example. Above all, one
can see that education is not just a diligent
and studious apprenticeship but a socializ¬
ing processa training for living and being
which is not limited to fighting ignorance
but reforms the spirit, teaches it to be serene
and spares it the torments of anxiety and all
vain questings of the soul.
Thus Ibn-Hazm, seeking a goal that
everyone could aim at, discovered only one:
to rid oneself of anxiety or, as the Qur'an
puts it, to find tranquillity, serenity and
peace. Knowledge is the opposite, not only
of ignorance, but also of stupidity, impa¬
tience and unreason (humq); as stated in an
early Vlll/14th century manuscript of a
treatise on the superiority of knowledge over
intellect (Fi tafdil al-'ilm ala-l'aql), it is
serene, enlightened understanding much
more than an "academic and intellectual"
accomplishment.
Moreover, a distinctive feature of Islamic
education is that it considers the way
knowledge is transmitted to be as vital as its
substance, whence the importance of the
master/disciple relationship as an essential
component in the handing down and recor¬
ding of traditions. This explains the original
kind of "diploma", the ijaza, awarded by a
scholar to his disciple as a licence to teach. It
is a certificate granted not by an institution
but by an individual. Such a diploma was
given to the explorer Ibn Battuta at
Damascus in the year 726 of the Hegira by
the learned Zeinab, daughter of Kamal ed-
Din Ahmed, son of 'Abderrahim Al-Maqdisi.
Originally the ijaza was required only for
teaching the Hadith or sayings of the Pro¬
phet. In order to attribute a given saying to
the Prophet, the teacher had to have at his
command a chain of reliable sources. He
had also to be familiar with the traditions
concerning other works existing in several
versions, like Malik's classic work the Kitab
al-Muwatta, and with the ways in which this
information was handed on. The develop¬
ment of a methodology for ascribing books
to their authors made it possible to extend
the chain of evidence to nearly all important
texts. It was not enough to get knowledge
from books. One had to go to the sources,
obtaining suggestions and advice from the
scholar in person. This explains why
scholars travelled so widely, as well as
Islam's passion for knowledge and
understanding.
Unlike similar phenomena at the time of
the Renaissance, this eagerness to learn was
not inspired by a desire for geographical
conquest. Knowledge was not the concern
of Conquistadores. It meant learning from a
master, and the self-taught student had not
yet become respectable. The word tashif
means "falsification"; etymologically, it is
related to sahifa, the page of a book, and,
by extension, means someone who may use
incorrectly a word taken directly from a
sahifa. Learning acquired only from books
was therefore not highly regarded in any of
the sciences. Every journey into knowledge
was a spiritual quest in which the communi¬
ty of scholars was united in time and space;
it explains why Islam's method of appren¬
ticeship was a spiritual voyage much more
than a mere technical or intellectual process.
Implementation of the moral system
described in treatises on the duties of
teacher and taught, like that of al-Ghazali,
who lived at the time when education was
becoming institutionalized, was made easier
by the fact that the teacher was free from
administrative duties. He treated his pupils
as if they were his own children, com¬
municating to them his own delight in learn¬
ing. As intellectual functions were separate
from administrative tasks, teaching could be
independent and flexible, unclouded by the
fear of failure, and due account could be
taken of each pupil's natural learning rhythm
and rate of intellectual development.
For his part, the pupil was expected to
reflect on the questions he was asked, for,
according to the tafdil (see above), if one
understands a well-framed question one is
already half-way to its solution; the pupil
should be freed from material preoccupa¬
tions so as to devote himself entirely to
study and was entitled in this respect to help
from the community; he should avoid sterile
argument and hasty judgments, and be able
to sustain a discussion of conflicting view¬
points, weighing the force of different
arguments and developing a dialectical ap¬
proach; he should also be able to appraise
the value of knowledge in practical terms,
not allow himself to be discouraged by the
difficulties of study and respect his master
who would respect him as his own child.
The teaching ethic of Islam can be summ¬
ed up in one word: dialogue. It is a perfect
conversation between master and disciple,
because what the one says is coloured and
attuned by the attentive presence of the
other. This teaching method fosters critical
acuteness and envelops the subjects under
discussion in that ideal atmosphere which
makes debate one of the highest pleasures.
The ethic posits a world where there is
room for everything, including poetry,
which is more than a mere recreation. The
creation of the madrasah (originally a centre
for studying law) as a means of passing on
knowledge provided an institutional basis
for this teaching without diverting it from its
true purpose.
The madrasahs were not created to satisfy
the demands of a State ideology; they were
conceived first and foremost as an act
of piety. They solved the pupil's practical
problems of board and lodging and provided
teachers with a regular salary, but the
State's intervention did not interfere with
the schools' autonomy or with academic
freedom.
The symbol of this academic freedom was
the mosque, which had fulfilled this
teaching role since the beginning of Islam.
From the time of the Prophet, its classes or
halqa had been centres of learning, and so
they have continued to be until modern
times at the al-Azhar mosque, in Cairo, the
Qarawiyyin, in Fez, and the Zaytuna, in
Tunis, as well as in rural zawiyas and in small
local mosques which have always given
religious instruction.
These study circles where the scholar sat
side by side with the student and the
craftsman, all united in a common quest for
knowledge, existed in a wide variety of in¬
stitutions. Teachers and pupils first met in
the mosques the madrasah proper was
established only in the fifth century of the
Hijra (11th century AD). But in the mean¬
time "houses of wisdom" were created, the
first at the time of Mu'awiya I whose reign
began after the death of AN in 40 AH/ 661
AD, and who we are told "devoted much
time to study".
Houses of learning, libraries and obser¬
vatories multiplied, broadening the scientific
horizon of Islam, diversifying knowledge
and creating specialities without ever sever¬
ing links between the various sciences. A
house of wisdom equipped with a library
and run by a Shi'ite with a Hanafite scholar
as director of studies would provide oppor¬
tunity for interdisciplinary discussion. Such
meetings were also organized by the Majalis
al-Nazar or scientific councils composed of
jurists from various law schools, as well as
theologians and eminent traditionists.
Among specialized establishments, par¬
ticular mention should be made of the
madrasah where law (fiqh) was the chief
subject of study. It was the home of dars,
the law lesson. Originally, this took place in
the masjid or mosque-school. But, unlike
the madrasah, the masjid did not provide its
students with board and lodging.
More generally, any place of prayer, any
holy place, the tomb of a saintly person or a
place of pilgrimage could be a centre of
teaching. So could the zawiyas, centres of
study run by a brotherhood, that linked
together the poorest and the most far-flung
regions of the rural world through a network
of libraries and learning. This may explain
the surprising fact that there was less il¬
literacy before the colonial era than after it.
Foremost among the zawiyas were the
famous centre at Tamagrout in south
Morocco, the Ahmed Baba centre at Tim¬
buktu, in Mali, and the dara (schools) of
Senegal. They taught the Qur'an, law, tradi¬
tion, adab, grammar, logic and arithmetic.
For even specialized institutions could ac¬
cept only pupils already proficient in
humane studies and grammar.
The pupils could be children being in¬
itiated into religious and social life, town
artisans, craftsmen, potential faqihs
(theologians) or even masters' assistants.
The teacher or mudarris, was primarily a
specialist in law. He was assisted by a depu¬
ty or na'ib and by an under-master. Classes
took the form of lectures, or commentaries
on a text read aloud by one of the best
pupils and explained, discussed and analys¬
ed as to subject and form by the teacher ac¬
cording to his speciality law, tradition,
logic, reading and study of the Qur'an,
arithmetic, geometry and astronomy.
All these subjects were using the same
methods up till a few decades ago in the
mosques, masjids, cathedral-mosques or
universities, or institutions like the )
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
-Qarawiyyin, where the Malaki school held
sway, and the Zaytuna, which also taught
Hanafite law, not to speak of astronomy for
which there was a long tradition: one of the
last astronomical treatises dates from the
year 953 AH/1372 AD.
A popular practice in teaching was to use
didactic poems, with a commentary given
by the teacher. Some of these poems were
so highly thought of that they were
translated into Latin, like Ibn Sina's (Avicen-
na's) poem on medicine which begins by
praising God who has given all men access
to knowledge. Other poems dealt with
grammar, logic, arithmetic, etc.
It is because of this continuing educa¬
tional tradition and aim that Islam today is
not a civilization of the past. While recogniz¬
ing the value of other civilizations it has re¬
mained true to its own culture, to the ideal
of educability.
From the earliest initiation into the Qur'an
to the highest levels of study, the Islamic
educational system, which expressed the
scientific sensibility of a whole society, finds
in this dual approach a path toward the
universal and the assertion of its own identi¬
ty. Whatever changes may take place in the
system, and changes are taking place, they
are not dictated by the need to adapt, but by
the wish to strengthen and enrich itself, to
preserve and assimilate the best wherever it
may be found: God Himself revealed the
Qur'an through repeated manifestations in
the course of man's troubled history, a
history which is not a series of disconnected
events but a confrontation with the perils
that man must sometimes face for his own
good.
The Islamic ethic permeates the concept
of education. Underlying it is the idea that
man must change in order to change the
world, for God changes nothing in men until
they have changed what is in themselves.
This calls fora return to the generalization of
teaching, education and culture advocated
by Islam an essential precondition of any
attempt at progress or renewal.
Islam is not an inquisitorial religion; "I
have not been commanded to probe the
hearts of men", says one of the Prophet's
Hadith. It tends rather to exteriorize faith in
cultural and social life, establishing a com¬
munal, but not a mass, culture, that is both
responsible and inventive, ethical and scien¬
tific, and harnesses random progress to
achieve ordered change. For change must
have an object, a goal, that cannot be reach¬
ed by technical means alone, but only if one
enlists in its cause the human will, that spark
which carries man's future through from age
to age. No other light can guide those who
believe man is capable of achieving the
changes required of him. Like Moses in the
parable, we must learn that to man is given
little knowledge and perhaps much joy.
Mohammed Allai Sinaceur
38
COLOUR PAGES
OPPOSITE
Jerusalem, a holy city for the three great monotheistic religions,
is the site of two of Islam's most venerated mosques, al-Aqsa
and (right) Qubat al-Sakhra (the Dome of the Rock). Built by the
Umayyad caliph Abdul Malik (I /7th century) on a rock in the
centre of the esplanade of the Temple, the site recalls the Mi'raj,
the Prophet Muhammad's ascension to heaven, as well as the
sacrifice of Abraham. Byzantine, Syriac and even Sassanid
traditions are richly interwoven in the mosque, the first great
achievement of Islamic architecture. The interior was originally
decorated with a profusion of marble panels and glass mosaics in
the form of plant motifs, necklaces, pendants and crowns which
symbolized the V'umph of Islam over the two great pre-lslamic
empires of Byzantium and Sassanid Persia. Mosaics covering the
exterior of the building were replaced in the 16th century by
polychrome enamelled tiles in the Ottoman style. On
11 September 1981 the World Heritage Committee included the
old city of Jerusalem and its walls on the World Heritage List.
Photo © Henri Stierlin, Geneva
CENTRE PAGES
The calligrapher used several different styles of writing In these
pages of a Qur'an, open at the first verses of Surah XIX, which is
thought to have belonged to the Ottoman Sultan Bayazit (886-
918 AH/1481-1512 AD). The text itself is written in a style known
as muhaqqaq, the rules of which seem to have been established
by the great Turkish calligrapher Hammidullah (X/16th century).
Between the lines is a translation into Persian written in the
cursive nashki style of Arab calligraphy. The heading of the
Surah (right hand page, above and below) is written in kufic, a
very ancient style which has been used for decorative purposes
in every age. The work shown here was one of a number of
magnificent Qur'ans presented at an exhibition, "Splendours of
the Qur'an", at Unesco Headquarters in Paris from 16 June to
3 July 1981. The exhibition was held in collaboration with the
World of Islam Festival Trust as part of celebrations marking the
15th century of the Hijra.
Photo Pieters Davison International Ltd. © Chester Beatty Library, Dublin
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
^
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
;
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
The Hegira
T'HE great nations of the world that
have made a deep and lasting impres¬
sion on history and civilization have
always established their own calendar
systems by which they fix the beginning,
length, sub-divisions and the important
dates of the year.
The Muslim calendar takes as its starting
point the Hegira {Hijra), the Prophet
Muhammad's journey from Mecca to
Medina. The Arabic word hijra means
"migration", but, because of its association
with the Prophet it has become invested in
Islam with a much wider and more deeply
significant meaning. It has sometimes been
wrongly translated, as "flight" or "refuge",
but primarily it connoted the breaking of the
ties of kinship or association. To this pre-
Islamic meaning, Islam added the sense of
"breaking of the ties of kinship for the sake
of God".
The Prophet started his mission in the
year 610 AD, when he received the first
revelation on Mount Hira, in the vicinity of
Mecca. Soon he won over to his faith a
small but devoted band of followers. As
time went on, the Prophet attracted more
and more adherents to his religion which, in
turn, evoked strong opposition from the
Meccans, especially from the oligarchy that
controlled the economic life of the city.
As the opposition grew, it became fiercer
and after thirteen years of ceaseless
preaching and struggle it became obvious to
the Prophet that his movement had reached
deadlock and there seemed little hope of
any early success against the obdurate
opposition.
It was at this juncture that he decided to
leave his native city, Mecca, and migrate
with his followers to Medina, whose people
promised him their help in carrying out his
mission. The Hijra was now the only hope.
But it was not an easy decision, however.
by Hakim Mohammed Said
For the infant Muslim community, it meant a
great sacrifice in that they had to give up
their homes and properties, their social con¬
tacts and blood relationships, their
economic and commercial base, and all the
privileges they enjoyed as citizens of the
most developed and prestigious city in
North Arabia, and settle in a city which had
hardly any material opportunities to offer.
The motives for this migration were,
therefore, a new and revolutionary concept
of the sublimity of purpose, a noble cause,
and sacrifice for the sake of God to protect
His message and to convey it to mankind
from a safer base.
This spirit of sacrifice as the motive for Hi¬
jra is reflected in many traditions of the Pro¬
phet and his companions. Thus, for exam¬
ple, a companion of the Prophet expresses
his sentiments and those of others in these
words: "I have left my kith and kin and my
property making the Hijra towards God".
Another tradition reads: "We have Hijra
with the Messenger of God seeking the
pleasure of God, The MostBlessed and the
Most High."
When a Muslim leaves his house, and his
kith and kin purely for the sake of God's
pleasure he acquires a great spiritual and
psychological force which enables him to
overcome all his spiritual and material dif¬
ficulties. If a man does not leave evil behind
him, his Hijra is useless, as far as its results
are concerned. Someone asked the Pro¬
phet, "0 Messenger of God, which Hijra is
the most excellent?" The Prophet replied,
"The most excellent Hijra is that you de¬
nounce what your God is not pleased with."
In the light of these traditions Muslim
scholars divide the Hijra into two
aspects the inward and the outward. In¬
ward Hijra means the renunciation of all the
evil temptations of the Self; outward Hijra
means saving the religion from destruction
by moving from one place to another.
Historically, however, the Hijra of the Pro¬
phet from Mecca to Medina in 622 AD,
marked a turning point in his prophetic mis¬
sion and a revolution in Islam. Externally,
the Islamic movement assumed a new shape
and formed a definitive community under a
single chief. In Mecca Muhammad was a
private citizen, in Medina the Prophet-Head
of a community. In Mecca he had to limit
himself to more or less passive opposition to
the existing order, in Medina he organized a
religious society. In short, the Hijra of the
Prophet gave explicit form to what had
hitherto been implicit. It ushered in a new
era in the history of Islam.
It was because of this historical impor¬
tance of the Hijra, along with its conceptual
significance, that when the question of
adopting an independent Muslim Calendar
arose under the second Caliph, Umar Ibn al-
Khattab, the companions unanimously
voted to adopt the date of the Hijra as the
beginning of the Muslim Calendar. They
unanimously dismissed the important event
of the Prophet's birth as the beginning of
the Muslim Lta. They also chose not to mark
its beginning from the day when the Prophet
received his first revelation. Muhammad did
not war.t to preach the faith only, he wanted
to put "Faith in Action". And it was the Hi¬
jra which made this possible. In the entire
history of Islam nothing can be compared
with the event of the Hijra in historical im¬
portance, and in its ideological, social,
political and cultural impacts.
HAKIM MOHAMMED SAID, of Pakistan, is
adviser on traditional Islamic medicine to the
Pakistan Ministry of Health, and President of the
Hamdard National Foundation (Karachi) which is
devoted to scientific and medical research. He is
editor-in-chief of the Foundation's periodical
Hamdard Medicine and Managing Editor of the
Urdu edition of the Unesco Courier.
Colour page, left
Ottoman style illuminated design
(Xll/18th century) representing Medina,
known in Arabic as Madinat al-Nabi
"the city of the Prophet" or simply as
al-Madina. "the city". (See also photo
and caption page 16).
Photo © Museum of Islamic Art, West Berlin
THE ISLAMIC CALENDAR
"It was He that gave the sun his brightness and
the moon her light, ordaining her phases that you
may learn to compute the seasons and the
years. "
(The Qur'an, X:5)
The Islamic Era is calculated from the year of the Hegira
which took place in 622 AD by the Gregorian calendar.
Following the guidance of the Qur'an which expressly makes
the moon the measurer of time, the Islamic year is based on
the moon and consists of 354 days divided into 12 lunar
months which are 30 or 29 days long.
In each thirty-year cycle, years 2, 5, 7, 10, 13, 16, 18, 21, 24,
26, and 29 are leap years with an extra day added to the
month Dhu 'l-Hidjdja.
Since the Islamic year is shorter than the solar year, the
Islamic New Year moves backwards regressing through all
the seasons every 32.5 years.
Days of the week
Yawm al-Ahad (Sunday)
Yawm al-lthnain (Monday)
Yawm al-Thalatha (Tuesday)
Yawm al-Arba'a (Wednesday)
Yawm al-Khamis (Thursday)
Yawm al-Djum'a (Friday)
Yawm al-Sabt (Saturday)
Months of the
year
Muharram
Safar
Rabi' I
Rabi' II
Djumada I
Djumada II
Radjab
Sha'ban
Ramadan
Shawwal
Dhu 'l-Ka'da
Dhu 'l-Hidjdja
Working out accurate correspondence between the dates of
the Islamic and the Gregorian calendars involves fairly
plicated calculations.
The date Friday 30th of October 1981 AD (Anno Domini)
corresponds in the Islamic calendar to Yawm al-Djuma 1
Muharram 1402 AH (Anno Hegirae), the next Islamic Ra's
al Sana (New Year's Day).
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
The scientific achievement
by Abdul-Razzak Kaddoura
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
of early Islam
"In the creation of the heavens and the
earth, and in the alternation of night and day
there are signs for men of sense; those that
remember Allah when standing, sitting and
lying down, and reflect on the creation of
the heavens and the earth, saying: Lord,
You have not created these in vain. Glory be
to You! Save us from the torment of Hell-
fire..."
(The Qur'an, 111:190, 191)
The nilometer on the island of Roda in the
Nile at Cairo was built in 246 AH/861 AD by
the mathematician Ahmad Ibn Mohammed
al-Faraghani on the orders of the Caliph al-
Mutawakkil. The building was linked to the
Nile by three tunnels and the central,
graduated column enabled the floods of the
Nile to be measured.
SCIENCE is man's endeavour to under¬
stand, by his own efforts, the world
around him and himself. Muslims have
always maintained that their faith not only
did not hinder such efforts but that it ex¬
pressly enjoined the believers, to undertake
them, and gave the necessary guidance for
their success.
This striving after knowledge has been a
constant commandment of Islam. It goes
back to the very beginning of the Revela¬
tion. From that first memorable day until
they succumbed for a time to external and
internal ills, the Muslims never ceased to be
at the forefront of science and technology.
It is, of course, impossible here to do full
justice to their great achievements and we
shall only mention one or two highlights in
the fields of mathematics, physics, medicine
and chemistry.
Mathematics, according to the English
mathematician Godfrey Hardy, is about
beautiful patterns of logical thought. It is
thus akin to music, poetry, painting and
other arts which attempt to compose
beautiful patterns of sounds, words, col¬
ours, etc. For Muslims, this pursuit of
abstract mathematical harmony was par¬
ticularly appealing and was directly linked
with their practice of art and architecture,
poetry and music.
Among the many advances made by
Muslim mathematicians, the one that could
be singled out is perhaps their elaboration of
the positional notation for the expression of
numbers, and, probably most important of
all, the use of the concept and symbol of
zero. This legacy has since become the
foundation of our number system.
No major scientific advance is of course
ever the product of a single individual or
even of one culture. Science and technology
are the result of continuous accumulation by
successive generations of men and women
from different parts of the world and are
thus the truly common heritage of all
mankind. This was beautifully stated by one
of the greatest scientists of all times,
Newton, when he said that if he was able to
see further than his predecessors, it was
because he stood on the shoulders of
giants. Having said that, and due credit
given to those from whom they borrowed,
including the Babylonians, the Indians, and
the Greeks, the achievement of the Muslims
in handing down to us the present basis of
our reckoning system is indeed of the very
first magnitude. This is popularly recognized
down to the present day by the name of
Arabic numerals, a term in universal use.
There are other obvious traces of Muslim
mathematics in contempor;ry terminology.
One of them is the Word algebra which
comes from the Arabic al-Jabr meaning the
restoration of something incomplete. This
mathematical discipline was perfected by
the Muslims on the basis of earlier work.
The major contribution in this field was
made by one of the greatest, perhaps the
greatest, among Muslim mathematicians:
Muhammad Ibn Musa al-Khwarizmi who
lives on today in the modern concept of the
"algorithm", a term derived from his name.
His book entitled Kitab al-mukhtasar fihisab
al-jabr wa'l-muqabalah (The Concise Book
on the Calculation of Restoration and Equa¬
tion) introduced algebra to Europe through
its Latin translation. The modern symbol for
an unknown, x, is derived from Shay which
is the Arabic word (meaning "thing")
originally used in Muslim texts on algebra.
Trigonometry, another of the major
mathematical disciplines, was essentially
established by the Muslims. The word
"sine", which designates the basic
trigonometric function, is the direct transla¬
tion of the Arabic original jayb. Many basic
trigonometric relations were elaborated by
Muslim mathematicians.
On the basis of Greek results, and in par¬
ticular those of Euclid, the Muslims made
great contributions to geometry. One of the
most eminent Muslim workers in this field,
although his modern fame does not
recognize this essential facet of his genius,
was Omar al-Khayyam. Another great
Muslim geometer was Nasir al-Din al-Tusi,
who wrote a commentary on the Elements
of Euclid.
Like almost every noted Muslim
philosopher, al-Tusi also devoted part of his
writing to natural philosophy, which, in his
day, included physics as well as the life and
the earth sciences. The work of Muslim
physicists was always characterized by a
delicate sensitivity to fundamental
theoretical principles (reflecting their ad¬
miration and reverence for God's creation)
and a practical approach (devoted to cater¬
ing for the needs of God's creatures).
Starting from a deep knowledge and
criticism of Aristotelian natural philosophy
(physics), Muslim scientists undertook a
thorough examination of the foundation of
this subject. The extensive correspondence
exchanged between al-Biruni, the leading
Muslim physicist, and the great Ibn Sina
ABDUL-RAZZAK KADDOURA is Unesco's
Assistant Director-General for Natural Sciences
and their Application to Development. He was
formerly Rector of the University of Damascus.
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
-(Avicenna) is a towering intellectual achieve¬
ment where all physical concepts of the day
are carefully analysed. It reminds one of the
Einstein-Bohr correspondence on the inter¬
pretation of quantum mechanics.
The study of motion in particular, and of
mechanics in general, led Muslim scientists
to advance the solution of several important
problems. Among these are the motion of
projectiles, the concept of momentum (cen¬
tral to contemporary physics and which was
developed by Ibn al-Haytham), the braking
of the motion of a body by the material
medium through which it moves, the fall of
bodies under the action of the force of gravi¬
ty, and the variation of the force of gravita¬
tional attraction between two bodies as a
function of their distance. All these con¬
tributions, and many others too numerous
to be mentioned here, paved the way for the
major scientific revolution initiated by
Galileo and crowned by Newton.
The science of optics was essentially
established by Ibn al-Haytham (Alhazen)
who is rightly called the father of optics. His
Kitab al-manazir (The Book of Optics),
which was translated into Latin, is con¬
sidered to be the most important medieval
work of its kind.
Among his many achievements are the
study of atmospheric phenomena, parabolic
and spherical mirrors and their aberrations
(in connexion with which he gave his name
to the famous Alhazen's problem whose
solution requires that of a fourth degree
equation which Ibn al-Haytham solved by
geometrical methods), and the first enuncia¬
tion of the minimum path principle for light
which was later perfected by Fermât and
became called by his name. Ibn al-Haytham
also did fundamental work in the study of
refraction, and discovered an approximation
to its law which was later established by
Snell and Descartes.
It is important to note that Ibn al-Haytham
was, at the same time, a skilled experimen¬
talist, building pieces of equipment with his
own hands, and a consummate theoretician
thoroughly familiar with the most
sophisticated mathematical techniques of
his day. By this blending of theory and ex¬
periment he anticipated modern science
which was born, according to Bertrand
Russell, from the merging of Greek specula¬
tion with Arab empiricism.
Ibn al-Haytham combined in his investiga¬
tions the skills of a physicist with the art of a
physician, and it was therefore natural that
he should have studied human vision with
particular effectiveness. He describes, with
great precision, the various components of
the eye, their individual functions and inter¬
relationships. Rejecting the false tactile
theory (according to which light is con¬
stituted by feelers emitted by the eye and
used to detect the seen object), which was
prevalent among pre-Muslim workers, he
correctly maintained that the eye is only the
receptor of light emitted by luminous
bodies.
Care of the eye was a major interest of
Muslim medicine. The ophthalmologist was
a familiar character of the society of Islam.
Under the name of Kahhal (from Kuhl which
means Kohl), he simultaneously practised
medicine, supplied (and sometimes even ap¬
plied) make-up, and often acted as a confi¬
dant and counsellor. If modern knowledge
leads us to ask whether "the eye is not an
external extension of the brain", it is
remarkable that this intimate link between 3
46
's';-' -
f.
^tK^i^U^^jJUs^^^, .ki
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
The mathematical table, right, is a
detail from a Vl/12th century
manuscript, Al-Bahir fi "dm as-Hisab
(The Book of Enlightenment on
Arithmetic), written by the
mathematician, doctor and philosopher
As-Samawal Ibn Yahya al-Maghribi who
died at Moragha in about
575 AH/1180 AD. It consists of a system
of numbers, arranged triangularly,
giving the coefficients of the expansion
of the expression (a + b)m, where misa
whole number. Inset right, the same
table which is known in the West as
Pascal's Triangle, after the famous
French mathematician and writer Blaise
Pascal who re-discovered it during the
17th century and was long thought to
be its originator. In his manuscript,
which is now preserved in the Hagia
Sophia Library, Istanbul, al-Maghribi
states that he copied the table from the
works of the Arab mathematician al-
Karaji who was born towards the end
of the IWIOth century. Thus the Arab
version of the table pre-dates Pascal's
version by at least six centuries.
During the golden age of Islamic
science, the theoretical aspect of music
was regarded as a branch of
mathematics and leading Muslim
scientists, including Ibn Sina and Qutb
al-Din al-Shirazi wrote whole treatises
on music. The close links between
music and mathematics is apparent in
this page (above left) from the section
on music of al-Shirazi's Durrat al-taj, an
encyclopaedia of philosophy and
science written in Persian. At that time
science was not strictly
compartmentalized as it is today and
most of the leading figures of Islamic
science were at home in several
disciplines. The great physicist Ibn al-
Haytham also made his mark as an
astronomer and a meteorologist and
was known as "the father of optics". A
qualified physician, he took a special
interest in ophthalmology and was one
of the first to recognize that the eye
was a receptor of light emitted by
luminous bodies. Below left, diagram of
the human eye from a treatise on
ophthalmology now in the Egyptian
National Library, Cairo.
Around the Vll/13th century, many
Muslim scientists were fascinated by
complicated mechanical devices,
gadgets and automata such as those
described in the Kitab fi ma'rifat al-
hiyal al-handasiyyah (The Book of
Knowledge of Ingenious Mechanical
Devices), written in 602 AH/1206 AD by
the engineer al-Jazari. Right,
illustration of one of his hydraulic
devices which he describes laconically
as "for use in the household".
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
The "Elephant CLock", an illustration from a version of al-Jazari's Book of
Knowledge of Ingenious Mechanical Devices dated 715 AH/1315 AD. The clock is
a marvel of ingenuity. Time is indicated on a scale to which the figure in the
howdah points and by openings (not visible) under the canopy that change from
black to white every hour. Every half hour the bird at the top revolves and
whistles, the mahout strikes the elephant and the figure above the falcon causes
the latter to drop a pebble into the dragon's mouth. The dragon's head drops
down carrying the pebble to a vase on the elephant's back and the pebble falls
inside the elephant where it strikes a gong.
the two was at the centre of Muslim
(ophthalmology.
Arabic has supplied Latin, and through it
(other European languages, with a rich ter¬
minology. One of the most authoritative
treatises on the subject is Tadhkirat al-
Kahalin (The Handbook of Ophthalmologists)
(written by the famous Ali Ibn Isa who was
the first to propose the use of anaesthesia in
(surgery.
But the name that comes most naturally
(to mind when one speaks of Islamic
medicine is that of the "prince of
physicians", the great Abu Ali Ibn Sina
((Avicenna). A child prodigy who memorized
(the Qur'an at a very early age, he was self-
taught in many subjects. A scholar of ad¬
mirable self-discipline and vast learning, he
(wrote works which remained for centuries
the standard references for medicine both in
Islamic countries and in Europe. His al
Qanun fiat-tibb (the Canon of Medicine) has
had incomparable influence on medical
practice and theory. It was translated into
many languages and remained, until the late
Middle Ages, the foremost medical treatise.
(it was based on the best knowledge
available in Ibn Sina's time, including, in
particular, his own observations and
discoveries which included the important
(results he obtained in the study of
epidemiology (applied for example to tuber¬
culosis), of meningitis (which he was the
first to describe), and of psychic disorders.
Most, if not all, Muslim men of science
(were highly versed in several scientific
(disciplines, in addition to being often at
| home in other branches of knowledge in¬
cluding philosophy, literature and one or
several of the arts. This general rule is
| nowhere as true as in the case of Muslim
physicians. Many of them, and certainly
their leaders, such as Ibn Sina (Avicenna),
| Ibn Rushd (Averroes), al-Kindi, and al-Razi
| were truly encyclopaedic men partaking of
practically all fields of knowledge of their
| times.
It is no coincidence that the Arabic word
| in common use today to designate a physi¬
cian (tabib), coexisted, during many cen-
| turies, with another word (hakim) whose
precise meaning in Arabic is "sage".
| Although hakim is less often used today
| than tabib, particularly among the educated
people in countries where Arabic is the
native language, its use has by no means
I disappeared and may in fact be re-asserting
itself with the present trend towards a return
I to cultural roots.
This unity of the various sciences, em¬
bodied in the polyvalence of their most emi¬
nent practitioners, was also reflected in the
conjunction of their transmission to the
students. Many of the hospitals, which were
a distinctive character of the Muslim world,
had schools (madrasahs) attached to them
where the future physicians were trained in
the theoretical aspects of their art, while the
clinical side was catered for by practical ser¬
vice in the hospitals.
The hospitals were often, and certainly in
the case of the most important ones,
academic and professional institutions of a
very high standard. They possessed in addi¬
tion to the usual components, libraries, lec-
ture halls, living quarters for the teachers,
the students, and most of the technical sup¬
porting staff, and many other facilities. The
institution of waqf (an endowment or trust
fund), which played such an important role
in Muslim life, ensured that the hospitals
48
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
MMMWt$&M*WM%&^&&:£-
Cape
specially
woven for
King Roger II
of Sicily
on the occasion
of his coronation |
in 525 AH/1130 AD, some
forty years after the end of a period
of 200 years of Muslim rule in the island. It is bordered with a woven Arabic script in which
is recorded the date of its manufacture as well as a prayer for the king couched In traditional Arabic terms.
Islamic textile designs and techniques spread from Sicily throughout the West and Turkish, Persian
and Arab designs are still current in Europe today.
had dependable and continuous means of
support.
Medicine is of course much more than
medical science, and to describe the many
contributions of the Muslims to its various
facets as a science, a healing art and a social
service, would be a formidable task. It
should be stressed, however, that Islam has
a rich tradition enjoining upon the believers
a code of personal and collective behaviour
conducive to a healthy state. The Qur'an
and the traditional Hadiths of the Prophet
give numerous and clear instructions about
personal hygiene (in particular through the
ablutions and in preparation for prayer),
dietary habits ("We, as a people, do not eat
until we feel hungry, and when we do eat,
we stop short of satiety", says one Hadith),
physical exercise ("Teach your children
swimming, archery, and horse-riding",
commands another), and many other
guidelines ensuring a healthy mind and
body.
Two social practices deserve particular
mention. One is the dispensation of
medicinal and other drugs which is the
business of the druggist (al attar) who often
acted also as an auxiliary medical practi¬
tioner (barbers also filled this latter function
in part). The other is the very important in¬
stitution of the public bath (al hammam)
which was a major meeting place acting at
the same time as a club (used alternately by
the two sexes) for social entertaining and
festivities, as a cleansing place and as a
forum for some kind of physical and
psychological relaxation for people going or
having just gone through periods of physical
and/or mental stress. An interesting in¬
stance of this last aspect is the universal
practice, which has waned in recent times,
of taking women to the hammam a certain
period after their giving birth, in a big group
of relatives, for a purificatory and festive
ceremony.
The notion of birth underlay the work of
the Islamic alchemists who, according to
Seyyed Hossein Nasr, in his book Islamic
Science, saw "the ¡deal of alchemy as a
form of obstetrics which delivers gold from
the bosom of nature".
Although alchemy should not be regarded
as a kind of protochemistry, the history of
chemistry is inseparable from it. The study
of chemistry was started by the Muslims in
their earliest days, but it was mainly the
philosopher, physician and alchemist Jabir
bin Hayyan (also known as Geber) who
made the first major Muslim contribution to
chemistry. Jabir bin Hayyan lived in the
second century AH (eighth century AD) and
wrote an impressive number of books
among which Kitab al-Sabin (book of the
seventy), and Kitab al-mizan (book of the
balance) are of particular importance.
The next major Muslim chemist is
Muhammad ibn Zakariyya al-Razi who was
also an outstanding physician. It was he
who proposed the classification of
substances into mineral, vegetable and
animal categories. He is credited with impor¬
tant advances in the study of several
chemical processes including that of distilla¬
tion. It is believed that he was the first to ex¬
tract alcohol from fermented substances
and to use it for medical purposes. The word
alcohol is of Arabic origin. The original word
could be al Kuhl (meaning Kohl) or al gaoul
(mentioned in the Qur'an and prob¬
ably denoting the objectionable ingredient in
wine).
The present state of Islamic science is of
course far from comparing favourably with
its prestigious past. But this sad situation
(for the Muslims and for the world as whole)
should not lead to an excessively un¬
favourable assessment of science and
technology in Dar-il Islam (The Domain of
Islam). One must recall first the impressive
numbers of Muslim scientists and engineers
already practising, or being trained, in all the
countries of the vast Muslim world. It is
beyond all doubt that this generation, and
the next one, will produce, because of their
sheer numbers, many outstanding scien¬
tists, some of whom are already among us
(Professor Abdus Salam was awarded the
Nobel Prize in Physics for 1979 and is thus
the first Muslim scientist to have achieved
this distinction).
Islamic countries are, for their part, in¬
creasingly aware of the fact that the
renaissance of Islam is linked with a new
flowering of science and technology within
the Umma (the Islamic Nation). They recall
the Hadith of the Prophet (May God bless
Him and give Him peace): "The end of this
Nation will only be secured through what
secured its beginning". Muslim countries
are therefore determined to work not only
individually but, more importantly, collec¬
tively, and in co-operation with all other na¬
tions of the world, to contribute to the
development of science and technology.
They have " recently founded the Islamic
Foundation for Science, Technology and
Development, whose Director-General is an
eminent Muslim scientist, Dr. Ali Kettani.
The Foundation has at present a modest
budget of fifty million dollars, but a signifi¬
cant fraction of the Islamic Fund for
Development, which amounts to two thou¬
sand million dollars will, as was stated at the
Islamic Summit Conference in Taif in
January 1981, be used for science and
technology. On this road to scientific and
technological renewal, the Muslims recite
reverently the words of God:
"And say: My Lord,
Lead me in with a just ingoing, and lead
me out with just outgoing; grant me
authority from Thee, to help me".
(XVII: 80)
M Abdul-Razzak Kaddoura
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
Ummat ul-ilm
Towards
a Commonwealth of Science
by Abdus Salam
"Allah is He who made (it possible) for you
(to acquire) mastery over the ocean; thus
(your) craft can ply thereon, with Allah's
command. . . Allah is He, who gives you sub¬
jection over all that is in Heaven and on
Earth: Herein are Allah's signs for peoples
given to reflection. "
(The Qur'an, XLV: 12,13)
Built by the Indian Prince Jai Singh in
the Xll/18th century, the observatory at
Delhi, left, though it incorporated
elements of Hindu astronomy, basically
continued the Islamic tradition of
observatory building as represented by
the great observatories at Maragha
(Vll/13th century), Samarkand (IX/15th
century) and Istanbul (X/16th century).
The Maragha observatory, with a staff
of twenty astronomers drawn from all
over the Islamic world directed by the
great scientist Nasir ad-Din at-Tusi, was
probably the world's first observatory in
the full sense of the word.
ABU AHMAD MOHAMMAD ABDUS
SALAM BIN HUSSAIN, FRS, of Pakistan, was
awarded the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1979 for
work in electromagnetic interaction between ele¬
mentary particles. He has been professor of theo¬
retical physics at the Imperial College of Science
and Technology in the University of London since
1957, and is founder and director of the Unesco-
sponsored International Centre for Theoretical
Physics, Trieste. In the article above, quotations
from the Qur'an are from the translation by A.J.
Arberry.
THROUGHOUT the ages, man has
reflected on nature, attempted to
discover its laws, and sought to
subdue it. The Holy Qur'an, by repeated in¬
junction and illustration from natural
phenomena, enjoins the twin pursuits of
reflection on (taffaqur) and mastery over
nature (taskheer) as bounden obligations of
the Muslim community. Following these in¬
junctions, barely a hundred years after the
Holy Prophet's death, the Muslims made it
their task not only to master the then known
sciences; they also acquired an ascendancy,
in the creation of the sciences, which lasted
over the next six hundred years.
In his monumental Introduction to the
History of Science, George Sarton divides
his story of achievement into ages, each age
lasting half a century. With each half cen¬
tury he associates one central figure. The
period 450-400 BC he calls the Age of Plato;
this is followed by the half centuries of
Aristotle, of Euclid, of Archimedes. From
600 AD to 700 AD is the Chinese century of
Hsiian Tsang and the I Ching and then from
750 AD to 1100 AD -350 years con¬
tinuously is an unbroken succession of
the Ages of men belonging to the culture
and the Commonwealth of Islam: Jabir,
Khwarizmi, Razi, Masudi, Wafa, Biruni and
Omar Khayyam Arabs, Turks, Afghans
and Persians chemists, algebraists, clini¬
cians, geographers, mathematicians,
physicists and astronomers.
Only after 1100 AD in George Sarton's
story of science, appear the first Western
names Gerard of Cremona, Roger Bacon
but the honours are still shared for another
250 years with men like Ibn Rushd, Nasir-ad-
din at-Tusi and Ibn Nafis, the man who an¬
ticipated Harvey's theory of circulation of
the blood.
Of the high level of achievement, the
following, taken from my own subject of
physics, may serve as examples.
Contrary to the views of the Greeks, "Ibn-
Sina (Avicenna, 370-428 AH/980-1037 AD)
regarded light as an emission by the
luminous sources of particles travelling at
finite speed; he understood the kinetic
nature of heat and of force and motion".
His contemporary, Ibn al Haytham
(Alhazen, 354-430 AH/965-1039 AD), one of
the greatest physicists of all time, besides
making experimental contributions in optics,
"enunciated that a ray of light, in passing
through a medium, takes the path which is
the quicker, anticipating Fermat's Principle
of Least Time. He understood the Law of In¬
ertia, later to become Newton's first law of
motion. He described the process of refrac¬
tion in mechanical terms by considering the
movement of a particle of light as it passed
through the surface of separation of two
media, in accordance with the rectangle of
forces a mode of approach independently
discovered later and elaborated by
Newton".
Al-Biruni (362-439 AH/973-1048 AD), a
great experimenter like his contemporary
Alhazen, was as modern and as post-
medieval in outlook as Galileo with whom he
shares the independent (and prior) discovery
of the Galilean invariance of the laws of
Nature. Al-Biruni's comments on scientific
methodology in his famous review of Indian
science and his correspondence with
Avicenna on the subject of elementarily of
fundamental particles, might have been
written today, such is the freshness of Al-
Biruni's mode of reasoning.
Qutb-al-Din al-Shirazi (633-710 AH/
1236-1311 AD) and his pupil Kamal-ud-Din,
gave the first explanation of the rainbow,
stated that the speed of light is in inverse
ratio to the optical (not material) density of
the medium; and that hyperboloidal lenses
avoid spherical aberration.
It should not be forgotten that these men
were not just physicists; they made equal or
greater contributions to medicine,
mathematics, geology, philosophy and
astronomy.
Three reasons can be given to explain
why, during their Golden Age in the ll/8th,
lll/9th, IWIOth and V/11th centuries, the
Muslims searched for and developed the
sciences to such a high level. First and
foremost the Muslims were following the
repeated injunctions of the Holy Book and
the Holy Prophet. According to Dr. Moham¬
mad Aijazul Khatib of Damascus University:
"In contrast to 250 verses which are
legislative, some 750 verses of the Holy
Qur'an exhort the believers to study Nature,
to reflect, to make the best use of reason
and to make the scientific enterprise an in¬
tegral part of the Community's life".
The second reason, connected with the
first, was the status accorded in Islam to
men of knowledge and science (A/ims). The
Qur'an emphasizes the superiority of the 3
51
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
Left, Persian brass astrolabe
dating from the Xl/17th
century. Astrolabes were
used in computing the
position of the stars and the
movement of the planets, as
a means of telling time, and
as navigational instruments.
They date back to before
Islam, but were vastly
improved by Muslim
astronomers. Right, diagram
from an Arabic manuscript,
dated 602 AH/1205 AD and
now in the Topkapi
Museum, Istanbul, which
explains the working of the
astrolabe.
one possessing knowledge and
science by asking how those without such
attributes could ever be the equals of those
who do? The Holy Prophet of Islam gave the
proud title of "Inheritors of Prophets" to
believing men of knowledge and science for
they were the ones who could recognize
Allah's design and its sublimity. Absolutely
explicitly he said: "The quest for knowledge
and science is obligatory upon every Muslim
man and woman". He further enjoined his
followers to seek scientific knowledge even
if it be in far Cathay.
An aspect of this veneration for sciences
was the patronage extended to their crea¬
tion in the Islamic-Arabic Commonwealth.
To paraphrase what the orientalist H.A.R.
Gibb has written about Arabic literature to
the parallel situation for Sciences: "To a
greater extent than elsewhere, the flowering
of Sciences in Islam was conditional... on.
the liberality and patronage of those in high
positions. Where Muslim society was in
decay, science lost vitality and force. But so
long as in one capital or another princes and
ministers found pleasure, profit or reputa¬
tion in patronizing sciences, the torch was
kept burning".
A third reason for the success of the
scientific enterprise in Islam was its interna¬
tional character. Not only did the Islamic
Commonwealth itself cut across nation and
colour, the early Muslim society was also the
most tolerant of those from outside of it and
their ideas. As al-Kindi wrote eleven hundred
years ago: "It is fitting then for us not to be
ashamed to acknowledge truth and to assimi¬
late it from whatever source it comes to us.
For him who scales the truth there is nothing
of higher value than truth itself; it never chea¬
pens nor abases him who seeks".
After the beginning of the VI/ 12th century,
science in Islam started to decline; by 750
AH/1350 AD the decline was complete. Why
did we in Islamic lands lose out? No one
knows for certain. There were indeed exter¬
nal causes, like the devastation caused by
the Mongols, but, grievous though it was, it
was perhaps more in the nature of a tempo¬
rary interruption. Sixty years after Ghengiz,
his grandson Halagu was founding an obser¬
vatory at Maragha. In my view, the demise of
living science within the Islamic Common¬
wealth was more due to internal causes.
To illustrate this let me quote from Ibn
Khaldun (732-808 AH/1332-1406 AD) one of
the greatest social historians and one of the
brightest intellects of all times in his field. Ibn
Khaldun writes in His Muquddimah (Intro¬
duction to History):
"We have heard, of late, that in the land of
the Franks, and on the northern shores of
the Mediterranean, there is a great cultivation
of philosophical sciences. They are said to
be studied there again and to be taught in
numerous classes. Existing systematic expo¬
sitions of them are said to be comprehen¬
sive, the people who know them numerous
and the students of them very many... Allah
knows better, what exists there... But it is
clear that the problems of physics are of no
importance for us in our religious affairs.
Therefore, we must leave them alone" (1).
Ibn Khaldun displays no curiosity, no
wistfulness, just apathy, bordering on hosti¬
lity. This apathy led to isolation. The tradi¬
tion of al-Kindi, of acquiring knowledge
from wherever it could be obtained and
improving on it, was forgotten. The Muslim
world of science sought no contacts with
the West where sciences had now begun to
be created.
Five centuries before, Muslims had avidly
sought knowledge first from the Hellenic
and Nestorian colonies of scholars at Hun-
dishapur and Harran, where translations
were made from Greek and Syriac. They had
then founded in Baghdad, Cairo and elsw-
here international institutes of advanced
study, Bait-ul-Hikmas, and international
observatories, the Shamsiyyas, at which
ft) See translation by F. Rosenthal Vol .III, pages 111-
112, 116-118, 153-155 and246-253. Routledge and Kegan
Paul, 1958.
52
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
¿g¿ » i>^> è^*^^'Hlí>v>¿ '¿«f[¿
Wt
JßW
ÀBï
9~#yr-&*p
congregated scientists from all lands,
creating new knowledge.
Such international concourses had begun
to be assembled from around the beginning
of the Vll/13th century in the West, starting
with Toledo and Palermo where translations
were feverishly made from the then
prestigious language of science, Arabic.
Thus a candle was lighted in the West from
a candle then burning brightly in the lands of
Islam. But there was no converse movement
in Islamic lands, which maintained the most
superficial scientific contacts with science
elsewhere.
To complete the story, from Ibn
Khaldun's day this intellectual isolation con¬
tinued, even during the great Empires of
Islam, the Empires of the Osmanlis, of the
Safvis, and of the Moghuls. The very en¬
cyclopaedic nature of knowledge and
science in Islam was now a hindrance, for
any science that was cultivated was concen¬
trated in religious seminaries, where tradi¬
tion was valued more than innovation.
It was not that the Sultans and the Shah-
in-Shahs did not know of the technological
advances being made by the Europeans.
They could hardly be unaware of the in¬
trusive superiority of the Venetians or the
Genoese in the arts of gun-founding or of
the navigational and ship-building skills of
the Portuguese who controlled the oceans
of the world, including all oceans bordering
on Islamic lands, and even the Hajj sea
routes. But they do not seem to have realiz¬
ed that the navigational skills of the Por¬
tuguese were not accidental but had been
scientifically developed and sedulously
cultivated starting with the research
establishment of Sagres set up in 822
AH/1419 AD by Prince Henry the Navigator.
And even while envying and trying to ac¬
quire the technologies involved, they failed
to understand the basic inter-relation bet¬
ween Science and Technology. As late as
1213 AH/1799 AD, when Selim III did in¬
troduce modern studies of algebra,
trigonometry, mechanics, ballistics and
metallurgy into Turkey, importing French
and Swedish teachers, so as to rival the
European arts of gunfounding, he failed to
place emphasis on basic scientific research
in these subjects, so that Turkey never
caught up with Europe. And even today,
when we have come to recognize that
technology is the sustenance and the
power, we have not appreciated that there
are no short cuts to it; that basic science and
its creation must become part of our civiliza¬
tion, as a pre-condition of the mastery of
science in application.
How can we turn the pages of history
back and excel in science once again? Most
of my remarks apply to the developing world
in general, but I shall speak with special
reference to the situation in Islamic
countries.
In keeping with our own experience of
earlier centuries, in keeping with the ex¬
perience of others and in keeping with the
obligations laid on us by the Holy Book and
the Prophet, our society as a whole, and our
youth in particular, must develop a pas¬
sionate commitment towards bringing about
a renaissance of sciences. We must impart
hard scientific training to more than half of
our manpower; we must pursue pure and
applied sciences with 1-2 per cent of GNP
being spent on research and development
and at least one fifth of this on pure sciences
alone.
This was done in Japan with the Meiji
revolution and is being undertaken today in
a planned manner, for example, by the Peo¬
ple's Republic of China the far Cathay of
the Holy Prophet's Hadith with defined
targets, in space sciences, in genetics and
biotechnology, in microelectronics, in high
energy physics, in agriculture, in the control
of thermo-nuclear energy. There is a clear
recognition that all basic science is relevant
science; that the frontier of today is tomor¬
row's application and that it is crucial to re¬
main at the frontier. In this context one may 3
53
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
-recall that the GNP of the Islamic-Arabic
nations exceeds that of China, while the
human resources are not significantly
smaller.
I have spoken of patronage for sciences.
One vital aspect of this is the sense of
security and continuity which a scientist-
scholar must be accorded for his work. Like
all humans, a scientist or technologist can
only give of his best if he koows he will have
security, respect and equality of opportunity
for his work and advancement, and is shield¬
ed from all forms of discrimination.
I have referred to a Commonwealth of
Science for the Islamic and the Arab coun¬
tries. Such a Commonwealth of Science
was a true reality in the great days of Islamic
Science, when Central Asians like Ibn Sina
and al-Biruni would naturally write in Arabic,
or their contemporary and my brother in
physics, Ibn al Haytham, could migrate from
his native Basra in the dominions of the Ab-
basid Caliph to the court of his rival, the
Fatimid Caliph al-Hakim, sure of receiving
respect and homage, notwithstanding the
political and sectarian differences which
were no less acute then than they are now.
This Commonwealth of Science needs
conscious articulation, and recognition once
again, both spiritually and physically, by us
the scientists, as well as our countries. To¬
day we, the scientists from the Islamic coun¬
tries, constitute a very small com¬
munity hundredth to one tenth in size,
in scientific resources, and in scientific
creativity compared to the international
norms. We need to band together, to pool
our scientific resources. We need the ar
ticulation of a compact conferring immuni¬
ty, for, say, the next twenty-five years, dur¬
ing which those within this Commonwealth
of Sciences, this Ummat-ul-llm would not
be discriminated against on national or other
grounds.
And finally, there is the isolation of our
scientific effort from international science. It
is not just the physical isolation of the in¬
dividual scientist from his scientific peers
elsewhere that we suffer from. There is also
the isolation from the norms of international
science, the gulf between the way we run
the scientific enterprise in our countries and
the self-governing manner in which it is run
in the developed countries.
The renaissance of Sciences within an
Islamic Commonwealth of Sciences is con¬
tingent therefore upon five cardinal precon¬
ditions: passionate commitment, generous
patronage, provision of security, absence of
sectarian or national discrimination, self-
governance and internationalization of our
scientific enterprise.
Why am I so passionately advocating our
engaging in this enterprise of creating
knowledge? This is not just because Allah
has endowed us with the urge to know, this
is not just because in the conditions of today
knowledge is power and science in applica¬
tion the major instrument of material pro¬
gress; it is also that as members of the inter¬
national world community, one feels that
lash of contempt for us unspoken, but still
there of those who create knowledge.
My self-respect suffers a terrible hurt
whenever I enter a hospital and find that
almost every potent life-saving medicament
of today, from penicillin to interferon has
been created without a share of inputs from
any of us from Arab and Islamic lands, or in¬
deed from any in the Third World.
To turn from science to technology, the
Holy Book of Islam places equal emphasis
on Taskheer (Technology) as on Taffaqur
(Science); it emphasizes acquiring mastery
of Nature, through scientific knowledge, as
much as the creation of new knowledge.
Besides lacking a base in Sciences, what
are the present obstacles in our societies to
our acquiring the highest proficiency in
technology? After all, never before in human
history has so much effort and such
magnitude of funds gone into creating
technical facilities in such a short duration of
time as in our lands during the last decade.
Unfortunately, most of these projects have
been executed in the turnkey mode; their ex¬
ecution has had little association with and
little employment of the incipient research
and development community of our men of
technology and engineering. Our societies
have become consumers of technology, not
technology-minded.
At least in part this is due to the fact that
the decision-maker is, as a rule, a non¬
technical person. Our countries are the
paradise of the planner, the administrator;
the technologist has had no part in decision
making. And yet experience shows that the
long term goal of technology acquisition
depends on complete accord, participation
and involvement between the scientist, the
technologist, and those who run the
development machinery of Statewith full
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
-» $¿> *9-
A daring challenge to the usual architectural drabness of utility
buildings, these striking water towers stand out on the skyline of
the city of Kuwait, a symbol of the search for new ways of
assimilating modern technology into existing traditions. Supplied
by two seawater distillation plants, a total of thirty-one of the
mushroom-design towers ensure a constant supply of fresh
water to the growing city. Opposite page, these three towers.
situated prominently on Kuwait Bay, offer a contrasting design.
The main tower is a 185-metre concrete column supporting two
spheres which contain, in addition to a reservoir, a restaurant, a
banquet hall, an indoor garden and an observatory. A second
tower supports a single spherical reservoir. The third structure, a
concrete needle, completes the composition.
trust in each other's sphere of work. And
the same rule applies, besides industrial and
science-based technology, to the whole area
of science in application, in agriculture, in
public health, in energy systems, and in
defence.
I wish to conclude with three appeals.
First, to my brothers in Sciences: We, the
scientists, have rights, as well as obliga¬
tions. We are few in numbers, the sizes of
our communities are individually sub-
critical. This, however, would not be so if
we were to band together in an Ummat-ul-
llm (a Community of Sciences). The
building up of such a Commonwealth of
Science depends, in the last analysis, on us.
I have personally been engaged in a quest
for a unity among the seemingly disparate
fundamental forces of nature. This is part of
our faith as physicists and of mine as a
Muslim, in the ultimate unity and symmetry
of Nature. At the Nobel Banquet in 1979 I
had the privilege to remind the audience of
this:
"The creation of physics is the shared
heritage of all mankind. East and West,
North and South have equally participated
in it. In the Holy Book of Islam, Allah says :
'Thou seest not, in the creation of the All-
Merciful any imperfection, Return thy gaze,
seest thou any flaw. Then return thy gaze,
again and again. Thy gaze comes back to
thee dazzled, aweary'. (LXVII: 3,4).
"This, in effect, is the faith of all
physicists, the faith which fires and sustains
us; the deeper we seek, the more is our
wonder excited, the more is the dazzlement
for our gaze."
Following this sentiment, my second ap¬
peal is to those among us who are shaping
our societies through their teachings; do not
forget these words from the Holy Book, nor
what their implications are for the goals of
our society. Let me humbly suggest that one
implication of this is that seminaries in
Islamic lands must include in their curricula
studies of the concepts of modern sciences
and not just sciences as at the time of Ibn
Sina (Avicenna).
And finally, my third appeal is to those
responsible for our affairs. Science is impor
tant because of the underlying understan¬
ding it provides of the world around us and
of Allah's design; it is important because of
the material benefits its discoveries can give
us. We, in Islam, owe a debt to international
science, which in all self-respect, we must
discharge. However, the scientific enterprise
cannot flourish without the generous
patronage of our rulers, just as in the past
enturies of Islam. The international norms
of one to two per cent of GNP, would mean
expenditures of the order of four to eight
billion dollars annually for the Islamic world
on research and development, one fifth of
this spent on pure science. We desperately
need such funds.
We need science foundations in our coun¬
tries, run by the scientists. We need interna¬
tional centres of higher learning within and
without our universities, providing liberal
support, security and continuity. Let no
future historian record that in the fifteenth
century of the Hijra the scientists were there
but there was a dearth of "princes and
ministers" with their generous patronage.
Abdus Salam
55
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
The sacred language of script
Calligraphy, the art of elegant
writing, was vested with a
sacred character because it was
the vehicle of the divine
message, revealed to mankind
in Arabic. Very early in the
Islamic era it became a branch
of knowledge governed by
precise rules and a widely
practised art which still holds an
honoured place beside that of
modern typography. Examples
of calligraphy, destined for
religious, official or private
purposes, are found in all
Islamic countries not only on
parchment and paper but in
many cases on utensils, in art,
and woven Into the fabric of
architecture. Calligraphy was
blended into ornate designs and
angular geometric lettering
could be used alone as a
decorative motif. Above left
ceramic dish (Iran, IV-V/10th-
11th centuries) adorned with a
proverb in the style of writing
known as knotted kufic. The
inscription reads: "Knowledge,
its taste is bitter at first, but
ultimately it is sweeter than
honey. Good health! (to the
owner)." Below, divine words
encrusted in the enamelled tiles
of a cupola on the great mosque
of Yazd, Iran (built
776 AH/1357 AD). Above right
brass hand-warmer inlaid with
silver (Syria, X/16th century).
The wide band of braided
strapwork on each hemisphere
resembles a highly ornate kufic
inscription.
56
MUSLIM thought, which contributed
so greatly in the past to the deve¬
lopment of universal philosophy,
is undergoing today a profound reappraisal
which carries the promise of new dynamism
and creativity. Unlike its counterpart during
the reformist period at the end of the 19th
century, contemporary Islamic philosophy is
not so much concerned with adapting itself
to the modern world as with examining con¬
temporary civilization critically and playing
its part in the universal attempt at revival.
Islam's recognition of earlier religions, its
almost complete acceptance of all scientific
knowledge and the interest it shows in the
various eastern and western cultures are
proof of the open-mindedness and spirit of
synthesis which characterize Muslim
thought. It was because of this attitude that
one of the great problems faced by Muslim
civilization in the past was how to find the
right balance between adaptation to human
evolution and revolution on the one hand
and, on the other, preserving the essentials
of its own philosophy and its own intellec¬
tual and practical achievements.
The task was made more difficult by the
fact that from the start and at the doctrinal
level Islam adopted a unitarian stance, op¬
posing all separation between theological
and social, spiritual and secular. Given such
an approach, it was impossible for Islamic
thought, whether scientific, philosophical or
of any other kind, to adopt a neutral or
transcendental attitude towards human life
or the life of human societies. Any intellec¬
tual innovation, therefore, had either to be
adapted or rejected.
In the context of a public opinion anxious
to preserve its identity and traditions many
intellectuals have been drawn towards either
rigid conservatism or radical reformism.
Thus the universalism of Ibn Sina (Avicen¬
na), who adapted science and philosophy to
Muslim theology, was counterbalanced by
the essentially Islamic spirituality of al-
Ghazali, while the reformism of Ibn
Taymiyya, who rejected any form of adapta¬
tion, reflected the desire of the people and
the community to maintain a purified form
of Islam freed from the encroachments of
medieval cosmopolitanism.
Of course the main movements of Muslim
philosophy during the Middle Ages never
went beyond a not very dynamic alternation
ABDEL MAJID MEZIANE is Rector of the Uni¬
versity of Algiers, where he has taught since
1965. He is the author of several publications (in
French and Arabic) on the sociology of culture
and of many studies (in Arabic) on philosophical
questions.
]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[
The dynamic of Islamic thought
by Abdel Majid Meziane
between synthesis and adaptation though
for the period this represented a fairly satis¬
fying view of the world! But despite the
vigour and realism of the socio-political at¬
titudes to which it gave rise, the tendency
towards radicalism produced serious in¬
tellectual difficulties. In the absence of a
religious philosophy strong enough to hold
its own against the Hellenistic, and par¬
ticularly the Aristotelian, heritage, Muslim
thought sought authenticity by developing
such disciplines as post-Mu'tazali theology,
spirituality and the legal and linguistic
sciences, each with its own specific field
and methodology.
By the end of the VI /12th century, the
idea of a comprehensive world universality
had given way to that of an exclusively
Muslim universality and this regression in
self-development was in itself indicative of a
slackening of creative energy. Not only did
theology no longer use philosophy as it had
been able to do during its early days of
greatness, but from the Vlll/14th century
onwards it ignored philosophy completely.
Parallel but compartmentalized development
of the different branches of knowledge, with
"sacred" and "profane" rarely brought
together, gave rise to a traumatic situation
in which the "spirit of theology" was
outstripped by the attainments of science
and often had difficulty in adapting itself to
the situation.
This problem of course was not peculiar
to Islamic culture; from the Renaissance on¬
wards the "theological outlook" in the
Christian West was also outstripped and,
ever since then, religious disciplines have
constantly lost ground. But for the Muslim
community the problem has to be seen and
examined in different terms. The political
decline of Islam, accentuated by the inroads
made by external ideologies, revived suscep¬
tibilities dormant since the great confronta¬
tion of the Crusades and aggravated by the
fact that the worldwide intellectual revival
was led by the Western world, with its tradi¬
tional hostility to Islam. In Islam, the cen¬
turies of decadence were above all a period
of Cultural survival in which little attention
was paid to philosophical debate and scien¬
tific achievement. Some of the reform
movements chose the easy path of conser¬
vatism and "fundamentalism", not so much
because they were incapable of accepting
cultural progress as because it was a means
of self-defence and of preserving Islam's
identity.
Neither the philosophy of "adaptation"
nor conservative and "protectionist"
theology enabled religious thought to
develop its true potential. Today, however,
a new Muslim humanism is developing
along two fundamental lines of thought.
This could provide an intellectual dimension
lacking in the cold reasoning of science and
our increasingly reckless "Promethean"
philosophy.
The first approach is concerned with
developing a system of ethics for science.
For Islam, both the end and the founda¬
tion of any science must be a system of
ethics providing rules by which man may
avoid all excess and deviation. The sole vir¬
tue of the "man who knows" is that he
"serves mankind".
Scientific ethics therefore are not a
separate code specially drawn up for the use
of scientists. For the scientist, far more than
the layman, must be conscious of his
responsibilities, which, from time im¬
memorial and for the whole of mankind,
proceed from an existential covenant bet¬
ween him and the Creator, the created
universe and all his human brothers. Seen in
this context, human progress is part of a
general scheme of things in which morals
and spirituality form a bulwark against the
vagaries of science, capable of destroying
nature and of leading to the domination of
man by man.
For dynamic Muslim thought, the task of
a moral philosophy of knowledge is not to
adapt itself to science or to indulge in ran¬
dom criticism of the scientific spirit, but
rather to shed light on scientific thought in
such a way as to humanize and give it back
the spirituality it lost when it was annexed
by political and economic forces.
The second line of thought that I would
like to describe here briefly is a social
philosophy which aims at being "revolu¬
tionary", not only in the form of protest, but
also in a constructive and co-operative
sense, with the object of rebuilding our
civilization and correcting some of its errors.
Religious philosophies and Muslim
philosophy is no exception have often
been accused of abandoning their original
goal of freeing man from all forms of
despotism whether intellectual or political.
In the Qur'anic texts, the monotheistic
religions represent history in terms of broad
periods and outstanding liberators:
Abraham struggling against the tyranny of
Ur, Moses against Pharaoh's pride, Jesus
against the domination of the priests, and
Islam against imperialism oppressing small
nations. Such symbols are easily grasped by
the popular memory and readily motivate
moral and political behaviour, but they must
be updated constantly and given new life by
a social philosophy sensitive to current
events and highly critical of those political
systems that recall ancient tyrannies.
The first responsibility of any community
is "to work for the triumph of good" and
"the prevention of evil". Of course, this fun¬
damental principle of Islamic moral and
social philosophy has often been misap¬
plied. Under the dynastic and oligarchic
systems deriving from man's so-called
primitive political nature, there were those,
particularly among the "tame" intellectuals,
who either participated in the establishment
as men of law or, as philosophers, justified
the government's misdeeds in the same way
that Aristotle justified Alexander's im¬
perialism. It is too often forgotten that in the
early days of Islam there were guardians of
religious doctrine who exercised an active
and vigilant political responsibility and were
prepared to oppose all despotism at the risk
of their own interests and even their life.
But while it is critical of its own history
and of its own political mistakes, Islam's
social philosophy does not hesitate to
criticize new forms of imperialism. A truly
universal democracy, to be created through
the common efforts of all mankind, can
derive much benefit from a philosophy
which, through the ages, has been sensitive
to the aspirations and struggles of the many
and varied peoples living in the Islamic world
and continuing to draw inspiration from its
ideals of justice and equality.
By instituting and advocating a system
based on economics, contemporary
establishments have increased alienation
and thrown up more and more oppressive
governments. Every principle of Islam's
socio-economic ethic condemns in¬
temperate behaviour, whether individual or
collective, just as it condemns those non-
collective interests that generate conflict
between nations.
Countries possessing economic power
and by the same token all other power, be it
military, political or technological, increase
this power at the expense of small, im¬
poverished peoples who are kept in a cons¬
tant state of inferiority. This division of
mankind, of course, is not a new
phenomenon. It is the legacy of ancient im¬
perialisms whose rich capitals were built
with the blood and sweat of the masses.
Such injustice and inequality are con¬
demned by all monotheistic religions in their
economic ethics. But the vigour with which*»
57
]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[
-Islam preaches egalitarianism has never
been equalled.
The historic liberation struggle of small
nations against the great powers is today
reactivated by a new revolutionary Islamic
philosophy that seeks to defeat all forms of
exploitation generating hatred between na¬
tions and to abolish all the discrepancies
which divide mankind in two.
The basic principles of Islam which break
down all racial, national, economic and
cultural barriers, are still sufficiently alive to¬
day to bring hope to the masses in many
countries of the Third World. A world where
there is no discrimination between educated
and illiterate, between the "people of the
Book" and the "Gentiles" and between rich
and poor, remains, according to the basic
texts of Islam, a universal aspiration which is
no mere Utopia.
Islam does not set itself up as the only
model of a universal community, for in prin¬
ciple and in practice it is a "multi-
communal" society. But, despite national
and cultural diversity and differing political
systems, mankind is basically one both in its
anthropological origins and final ends. In a
world where the difficulty of co-existence is
the source of major problems, the social
philosophy of Islam can assert its originality
and creativity by stressing mankind's basic
unity within its diversity.
Recognition of each socio-cultural unit
without hierarchical distinction is the star¬
ting point of a new anthropology in which
separate communities will ultimately merge
into one. For Islam, universality can never be
a weakening factor since the whole of
mankind and each human being taken in¬
dividually have the same existential value
and each recognizes the other. The Qur'an
declares that earthly corruption or the un¬
justified taking of human life is tantamount
to murdering the whole of mankind, while
restoring one man's life is the same as
resuscitating all humanity.
H Abdel Majid Meziane
Colour pages
Opposite
Persian art enjoyed a golden age under the Safavid dynasty which was
founded in 920 AH/1514 AD by Shah Ismail and ruled Persia until the
Xll/18th century. The royal mosque (Masjid-i Shah) at Ispahan, Iran, was
built in the Xl/17th century as part of an immense urban development
programme which saw the construction of religious edifices, palaces,
gardens and hydraulic installations. The mosque is famed for the brilliant
enamelled tiles which adorn its minarets, the walls around the courtyard, its
Inner walls and cupolas. Photo was taken beneath the cupola of prayer.
Photo Jean Mazenod © Editions d'Art Lucien Mazenod, Paris
Page 60
Above. The conquest of Delhi in 932 AH/1526 AD by Babur (a descendant
of Genghis Khan) led to the rise of the Moghuls, perhaps the most brilliant
dynasty of Muslim India. The culture of Moghul India was influenced by
Persia, whose language it borrowed, while preserving its own originality
and producing outstanding achievements in art and literature. The emperor
Akbar (X-XI/16th-17th centuries) encouraged the development of an
original architectural style marked by the affinities between Muslim and
Hindu art. Photo shows the delicate tracery of openwork marble windows
in the mausoleum of Itimur al-Dawla, minister of Shah Jahangir (Xl/17th
century) at Agra, India. All the surfaces of the mausoleum are covered
with marble panels carved with openwork floral and geometric designs.
Photo © Henri Stierlin, Geneva
At the death of the Sultan Suleiman the Magnificent (X/16th century) the
Ottoman Empire encompassed Turkey, the Balkans as far as the Danube,
and the whole of the Arab world with the exception of Morocco. Under the
influence of the Sultans, Islamic culture flourished in every field. The arts of
the book were highly esteemed by the court and calligraphers displayed
extraordinary inventiveness. Below, calligraphy of Hasan Ahmad Qara Hasari
(X/16th century). The text ¡s a variant of the formula "Praise be to God".
Photo Roland and Sabrina Michaud © Rapho, Paris
Page 61
The city of Fez (Morocco) was founded in the ll/8th century by the Idrisid
rulers and became under the Almoravld dynasty one of the foremost
centres of Islam in the West. Later the Marinids (VI-IX/12th-15th centuries)
chose Fez for their capital and built magnificent madrasahs (schools) and
other monuments. Photo shows detail of a wall in the prayer room of the
most remarkable of these madrasahs, the Madrasat al-Attarin, an example
of the Hlspano-Moorish style at its finest. Every Inch of the walls, lined with
enamelled tiles and onyx, is covered with ornamental motifs. The
architecture of the Medina (old city) of Fez, as well as its natural
environment and the traditional activities flourishing there are today
endangered. Unesco has launched an appeal to international solidarity for
the safeguard of the old city, and several projects are now being studied for
the preservation and development of a site which was one of the jewels of
Islamic culture.
Photo Maximilien Bruggmann © La Spirale, Lausanne
Islamic Culture and the Modern World
"Islam's determination to maintain its authenticity is in no
way incompatible with its sincere desire to collaborate with
other religions and doctrines whenever such collaboration is
for the benefit and well-being of humanity. As the Prophet
(Peace be upon Him) said: 'All creatures form part of the
family of God and the most beloved of God is he who best
serves His family.' Indeed, it is this very determination to
maintain its authenticity which enhances Islam's capacity to
enrich humanity in those areas where civilizations meet and
interact.
"Today, we are more aware of the encounter between
cultures than we were in the past, when each great civiliza¬
tion believed itself to be the custodian of the highest values
and to be the only one worthy to expand and dominate the
world. Nowadays men have come to appreciate the diversi¬
ty of cultures, their interactions and the enrichment born of
mutual exchange. [.'..]
"Islam today has a.duty to make its culture known and to
participate in the dialogue and interchange between civiliza
tions. But more than this, the modern world demands of
this culture that it provide solutions to the major world
problems and the means to escape from current ideological
and economic crises."
Extract from a speech made by the Secretary-General of the World
Muslim League, Sheikh Mohammed Ali Al-Harakane, at an inter¬
national conference on Islam held at Unesco in Paris in December
1980.
The World Muslim ' ?ague is an international, non-governmental
organization with headquarters in Mecca and branches in Africa,
Europe, Asia and America. The objectives of the League are to
serve and defend the Islamic religion, to instruct Muslims and to
bring together Islamic communities. At present the League pro¬
vides the secretariat for the annual meeting of Ministers of Islamic
Affairs, for the International Council of Mosques, and for the
Supreme Committee for Islamic Information. Its Constituent Com¬
mittee, on which 54 Islamic countries are represented, meets an¬
nually to review the League's activities and plans for the future.
58
]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[
ä£SS3&
iraszsra*
it:
R i
I
L"
k L
y
!
]]>
</page>
<page number="61">
<![CDATA[
>:*: *:*:«
]]>
</page>
<page number="62">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="63">
<![CDATA[
The Safavid era in Persia was the golden
age of the miniature, largely due to the
encouragement of Shah Tahmasp
(930-984 AH/1524-1576 AD), a gifted
amateur who brought together the most -
talented artists in the land in a studio
attached to his court. Apart from drawing
and painting the artists also learned how to
make their own paints and brushes. This
miniature, attributed to the famous painter
Sheikh Muhammad, is from a manuscript
of Han awrang (The Seven Thrones) by the
poet Jami who died at the end of the
IX/15th century. It illustrates a scene from
the popular love story of Layla and Majnun
in which the poet Qays (known as al-
Majnun, "the madman") falls in love with
Layla, the daughter of a powerful sheikh.
Majnun, above right, is casting an
affectionate eye on his beloved who is
standing at the entrance to the tent.
Photo © Freer Gallery of Art,
Smithsonian Institution, Washington DC
The eye
of
the heart
by Rahmatullah
ISLAM is not only a religion, a social
system and a form of culture. It is also
a deep mystical tradition that has
developed over the last fourteen centuries.
Muslim gnoseology distinguishes four
forms of knowledge accessible to man
which, according to the Vll/13th century
Persian Shi'ite philosopher Nasir ad-Din at-
Tusi, are symbolized by four liquids. The
first is sensory perception of the
phenomenal world acquired through the five
senses of the body and the reasoning faculty
of the mind; this is what we call science. It is
symbolized by water, which is a clear
liquid and easy to assimilate.
The second is intuitive knowledge ac¬
quired through the mind's imaginative facul¬
ty; this is the realm of art, literature and
philosophy in the usual sense of the word,
i.e. speculative thought. It is symbolized by
milk, which is a more nourishing drink.
The third form of knowledge is the objec¬
tive study of the supra-sensory experience
of prophets and mystics and of their
teaching; this is philosophy in the
etymological sense of the word, i.e. love for
divine wisdom (theosophia, hikmat ilahiya).
It is symbolized by honey, which is even
more nourishing, and delicious as well.
The fourth kind of knowledge is direct ex¬
perience of supra-sensory Reality acquired
without the intermediary of the physical or
mental faculties through the development of
man's potential powers of spiritual percep¬
tion; it is revelation, divine inspiration or the
mystic dream. It is symbolized by wine,
which transports the drinker to the depths of
himself. It is this celestial knowledge and not
the terrestrial alcoholic drink that is
celebrated by the famous VI /12th century
Persian poet Omar Khayyam in his
Ruba'iyat.
A century later Umar Ibn-al-Farid, the
greatest Arab mystic poet, wrote in his
poem In Praise of Wine :
We drank to the memory of the Beloved a
wine which enraptured us before the vine
was created...
He who has lived on this earth without rap¬
ture has not really lived, and he who has not
died from his rapture is devoid of reason.
For Muslims the supreme example of a
mystical experience is that of the Prophet
Muhammad on the two great "Nights"
celebrated in the Islamic calendar. The first
is the Night of Power, when Muhammad
received the first Qur'anic revelation through
the intervention of the angel Gabriel. The se¬
cond is the Night of the Ascension, when
the Prophet, transported to the Rock of
Jerusalem, had a brief foretaste of the
Resurrection.
Thus the Qur'an, the word of God enun¬
ciated by the Prophet, and the Hadith, or
"sayings" of Muhammad handed down by
his companions, constitute the main source
of mystical meditation in Islam. Particular at¬
tention is given to those verses of the Qur'an
which are of a symbolic nature; the Book
itself encourages this: "Allah gives parables
to men so that they may take heed". (XIV:
25).
Among the Prophet's Hadith are some in
which God speaks in the first person.
Because of this they are called qodsi (holy).
One of the most frequently quoted says: "I
was a hidden Treasure, and I wished to be
known; so I created the world". These in¬
spired words have been the object of special
study by lovers of wisdom.
Mystical meditation also draws from the
almost inexhaustible corpus of writing and
sayings by Muslim mystics which has grown
up in all parts of the Islamic world. Some of
them were prolific writers and produced
monumental works. This was the case of
Muhy'iddin Ibn al-Arabi (born in Andalusia,
died in Damascus in 637 AH/1240 AD).
Shortly before his death he drew up a list of
his 270 works, the longest of which, Meccan
Revelations, comprises 560 chapters.
The Mathnawi of Jalal al-Din Rumi (born
in Balkh, died in Konya in 672 AH/ 1273 AD)
is a 45,000-line epic poem of profound
wisdom and striking beauty. Rumi was the
founder of the Mawlawi Sufi Order, better
known in the West as the whirling der¬
vishes. Two great Persian mystics, Farid al-
Din 'Attar (Vll/13th century) and Jami
(IX/15th century) compiled biographical!
RAHMATULLAH is an authority on Islamic
mysticism. A British citizen (born in the Indian
sub-continent) he is the author of a number of
specialized articles on aspects of Islamic
philosophy.
63
]]>
</page>
<page number="64">
<![CDATA[
Sufi (Islamic mystic) calligraphers have
often practised a kind of "double"
mirror writing in which the right side of
the composition is a reflection of the
left. Right, giant calligraphy of the
word Huwa "Him" (God) in the
mausoleum of Rumi, the great Sufi
poet in the Persian language, at Konya
¡Turkey). This balanced, harmonious
mirror calligraphy expresses the Sufi
unity with God. Left, portrait of Ja la I al-
Din Rumi (604-672 AH/1207-1273 AD)
also known as Mawlana ("Mevlana",
Our Master, in Turkish). The founder of
the fraternity of the whirling dervishes,
Rumi is considered to be one of the
greatest mystic poets of all time. Apart
from prose works he wrote the Divan-e
Shams e-Tabrizi (The Collected Poems
of Shams of Tabriz) and a vast poem of
some 45,000 verses, the Masnawi, a
veritable mystical epic which has
profoundly Influenced Islamic thought.
-dictionaries and anthologies of the
aphorisms of other Muslim mystics.
But it is mystical poetry that has had the
greatest impact on the Muslim masses. At
first it was written in Arabic, the religious
and cultural language of Islam, but it
gradually spread to other languages.
Whether they wrote in Persian like Hafiz of
Shiraz (Vlll/14th century), in Turkish like
Yunus Emre (Vlll/14th century) or in Urdu
like Khwaja Mir Dard (Xll/18th century), all
described their supra-sensory experience:
Last night, at sunset, I was freed from
anguish; and in the darkness of the night, I
received the Water of eternity.
(Hafiz).
Now, I can offer my doubts to plunder...
For I have renounced myself,
I have discarded the veil which covered my
eyes,
And I have achieved union with the Friend.
(Emre)
Whither, 0 Dard, has my heart cast its
glance?
Wherever I look, I see none but Thee.
(Dard)
The Muslim mystics have always had a
universal outlook. Husain Ibn Mansur al-
Hallaj, the IV/IOth century mystic and mar¬
tyr, sums it up very well when he writes: "I
have pondered on the religious denomina¬
tions, striving hard to understand them, and
I consider them as one principle with many
branches. Do not ask a man therefore to
adopt one denomination rather than
another, for that would divert him from the
essential principle. It is the principle itself
which must seek him out, for through the
principle all greatness and all meanings
become clear. Then will man understand".
In his Book Uniting the Two Wisdoms,
the Ismaili philosopher-poet Nasir-i
Khusraw, who lived in Persia in the V/11th
century, demonstrated the harmony bet¬
ween Greek philosophy and Islamic
gnosticism. Similarly, in the Xl/17th cen¬
tury, prince Dara Shikoh, son of the Indian
emperor Shah Jahan, and himself a mystic,
asserted that, apart from a few superficial
differences of terminology, Sufism and the
Advaita Vedanta (the philosophical system
of Brahmanism) were fundamentally the
same thing. It has been pointed out that one
finds in Sufism tales relating to the Buddha,
such as those on which Ibn Sina (Avicenna),
the great V/11th century philosopher-
physician of Central Asia, based his Tale of
Salman and Absal.
"We created man. We know the promp¬
tings of his soul, and are closer to him than
the vein of his neck", God says in the Qur'an
(L: 16). And one of the Prophet's Hadith
quoted by the mystics says: "He who knows
his soul (nafs) knows his Lord". It is through
the hidden depths of his being that man can
hope to know supra-sensory Reality. But
such knowledge cannot be attained through
the physical or mental faculties. To
recognize this limitation of human nature is
to have a presentiment of the supra-sensory
world, as Abu Bakr, the first caliph of Islam,
puts it: "Praise be to God who gave His
creatures only one path to His knowledge:
their inability to know Him". And the lll/9th
century Egyptian mystic Dhu n-Nun-al-Misri
said: "He knows God best who thinks he
knows Him least".
Knowledge of supra-sensory Reality can
be attained only through the development of
a faculty of spiritual perception called the
Eye of the Heart. But this is a grace from
God and cannot be acquired through the will
of man. "I saw my Lord with the Eye of my
Lord", says the Prophet. And 'Attar ex¬
plains: "You must know God through God
Himself, not through yourself. He, not
human wisdom, shows the path that leads
to Him."
The Heart (qalb) or spiritual Soul is an on-
tological state or level of being between
human nature (nasut) and divine nature
(lahut). It is the rampart (barzakh)
separating the two seas mentioned in the
Qur'an (XXV: 53). It is the ¡nterworld, the
celestial Earth between the terrestrial earth
and Heaven. It is the angelical world Calam
al-malakut) of the angel Gabriel. It is the
spiritual centre, symbolized by the Ka'ba at
Mecca and by the Rock of Jerusalem,
towards which the aspiring mystic travels in
order to accomplish his esoteric pilgrimage,
the Great Pilgrimage. It is the Active Im¬
agination or Intellect contemplating the in¬
telligible world. It is the Throne of God. One
of the Prophet's Hadith qodsi quoted by the
mystics says: "My earth cannot contain Me,
nor can My heavens, but the Heart of My
faithful servant can contain Me".
The Heart or the spiritual Soul only
reflects its own Soul which is the Holy Spirit
(ruh al-qods) or Soul of the Soul. "The Soul
is concealed in the body, and Thou art con¬
cealed in the Soul," says 'Attar. "0 Soul of
the Soul, Thou art greater than everything
and before everything. All is seen through
Thee, and Thou art seen in all things".
The Holy Spirit is the Face of the Lord
mentioned in the Qur'an (LV: 27), the Belov¬
ed of the mystics, and the Active In¬
telligence of the philosophers. It is the divine
Nature (lahut) which conceals the divine
Essence (hahut) or divine Abyss.
64
]]>
</page>
<page number="65">
<![CDATA[
Ibn 'Arabi described his mystical dream in
these words; "Active Imagination achieved
in me such strength that it showed me my
mystical Beloved in a corporeal, objective,
extra-mental form, as the angel Gabriel ap¬
peared corporeally to the Prophet. At first I
did not have the strength to gaze upon this
Form. It spoke to me; I would listen and
understand... I never ceased to gaze upon
this Form whether I was standing or seated,
moving or at rest".
I saw my Lord with the Eye of the Heart,
says Hallaj. "I asked: Who art Thou? and He
answered: Thou." For to the mystic only
God really exists; any existence outside of
Him is as unreal as an image in a mirror.
Amadou Hampaté Bâ, a disciple of Tyerno
Bokar Salif Tal, a Muslim mystic of negro
Africa, has expressed this very well:
"Basically, there is only one existence: that
of God, one letter: alif (the first letter of the
Arabic alphabet); one number: 'one'. ". Bet¬
ween microcosm and Macrocosm there is
therefore a fundamental unity of being
(wahdat al-wojud) like the identity of
substance between a drop of water and' the
ocean, as Omar Khayyam explained:
The drop of water began to weep, because
it had been separated from the Ocean.
The Ocean began to laugh, saying: "It is we
who are all;
Verily, there is no other God outside
ourselves;
And all that separates us is a single, a/most
invisible speck".
But the microcosm cannot claim to be the
Macrocosm, any more than a drop of water
can claim to be the Ocean. Concern for
maintaining the absolute transcendence of
God, together with a fear of descent into
pantheism, gave rise to the hostility of the
exoteric authorities against the Muslim
mystics. Because he had exclaimed while in
ecstasy, "I am the real Truth (haqq)", Hallaj
was beheaded in Baghdad in 309 AH/
922 AD. Five centuries later, in distant Java,
another Muslim mystic, Sjech Siti Djenar,
was to be executed for a similar pronounce¬
ment made in a state of ecstasy.
It was the famous V/11th century
theologian Abu Hamid al-Ghazali who
restored mysticism to the mainstream of
Islam. He relates in his autobiographical
treatise how, after a spiritual crisis during
which he doubted the truth of religion, he
realized that mysticism was the best an¬
tidote against scepticism and constituted
the loftiest aspect of religion. In his most
famous work, Vivification of the Religious
Sciences, he reminds the community of
the mystical tendency which had marked
Islam in the time of the Prophet and his
companions.
In the Vl/12th century, Abd al-Qadir
al-Jilani, a hanbalite jurist who became a
Sufi, established the Qadiriyya religious
brotherhood which developed rapidly and
became the most important Sufi Order.
The development of the faculty of
spiritual perception is an act of God, not of
man, but man nevertheless can hasten this
event, as the Prophet explains in one of his
best known Hadith qodsi: Nothing that
brings my servant close to Me is more ac¬
ceptable to Me than the fulfilment of the
duties I have prescribed for him. In addition.
My worshipper constantly draws nearer to
Me through supplementary acts of devotion
until I love him. And, when I love him, I am
the hearing with which he hears, the sight
with which he sees, the hand with which he
strikes, the foot on which he walks".
Speaking of the Heart, Rumi asks: "Do
you know why your mirror reflects nothing?
It is because it has not been cleansed of
rust. If it had been rid of all rust and all
defilement, it would reflect the light of
God's sun... He who recognizes and con¬
fesses his faults moves swiftly towards
perfection. But he who considers himself
perfect does not move towards the Omni¬
potent. No sickness can ravage your soul
worse than imagining yourself perfect".
The Prophet said: "For each thing there is
a solvent that removes rust; and the solvent
of the Heart is the invocation of God." And
the Qur'an says: "Pray to your Lord with
humility and in secret" (VII: 55). This is the
esoteric prayer, the Great Prayer. Sultan
Muhammad Aga Khan, Imam of the Ismaili
Shi'ites, develops this in the following way:
"It is said in the Qur'an that we live, act and
exist in God. This concept is often express-
ed»in the Holy Book in terms that are both
strong and poetic. When the deep meaning
of these words becomes clear to us, we are
ready to receive the gift of revelation".
"He who knows God, loves Him; and he
who knows the world renounces it," said al-
Hasan al-Basri (ll/8th century), one of the
first Sufis. And the Prophet said: "In this
world be like a stranger or a traveller". And
ad-Din Attar declared: "Destroy yourself;
therein lies perfection. Renounce yourself;
this is the pledge of your union with Him.
That is all". But renouncing the world does
not mean shunning the world, as the
Xlll/19th century African warrior-
philosopher al-Haj 'Omar has explained;
"Asceticism does not consist in withdraw¬
ing from the world, but in banishing it from
one's heart."
For renunciation is the result of a struggle
waged amid the trials and temptations of J
65
]]>
</page>
<page number="66">
<![CDATA[
VunuS fmremiz
*f'^\s^mm\
//| *" & ^m
H
ISw^l« r^vr
IPrA^.ùfrycr ^^9 *kif7t.
| ^rz^uy^s^^^s^sx^^s^s^^ Il
3t** Wmca. JO J»**-
Above, portrait of the poet and Sufi
(Islamic mystic) Yunus Emre, one of the
great figures of Turkish literature. Little
is known about his life. He was born
around the middle of the Vll/13th
century, lived in Anatolia, and died
c. 719 AH/1320 AD. Tradition has it that
he was poor, of peasant origin, and
belonged to a dervish religious
fraternity. His work, written in Turkish,
expresses deep feeling in direct, simple
language. It marked a sharp break with
that of the other writers of his age who
were steeped in Persian culture and
book-learning, and
has had an enduring influence on
Turkish lyrical poetry.
-this world against one's demanding self
(nafs al-amarrah), the "egoity" that men call
Satan. This is the inner battle (jihad), the
Great Battle. And the Pakistani mystic
Muhammad Iqbal (1877-1938) urges us to
struggle ceaselessly:
Do not dally on the shore
where life's melody dies a gentle death.
Leap into the sea, fight with the waves,
for immortality is won through struggle...
Happy the man whose soul knows no
repose.
Jami, author of two great love poems,
Layla wa Majnun and Yusuf wa Zulaykha,
maintains that passionate human love
prepares man for Divine love: "If you would
be free, be a prisoner of love. If you would
be happy, open your heart to the suffering
of love. The wine of love brings warmth and
rapture; without it there is nothing but icy
selfishness... You can pursue many ¡deals,
but only love will deliver you from yourself.
If you long for a draught of the mystic wine,
sip first the wine of appearances".
Sultan Muhammad Aga Khan explains it
admirably in these words: "He who is for¬
tunate enough to arouse and feel the love of
a human being should give himself up to it
66
and respond gratefully, considering it a
blessing and a source of pride... But, just as
the joys of human love surpass all that
wealth and power can bring to a man, so
spiritual love and revelation the fruit of this
sublime perception, of this direct vision of
Truth, which is a gift and a grace of
God surpass all that the deepest and most
sincere human love can bring us."
"All paths lead to God," says Rumi. "I
have chosen that of dance and music... He
who loves, feeds his love by listening to
music, for music reminds him of the joys of
his first union with God".
The fact that the XIV/20th century has
produced such great Muslim mystics as the
Moroccan Ahmad al-'Alawi, the Pakistani
Muhammad Iqbal, the Peul Tyerno Bokar
Salif Tal, the Libyan Ahmad Zarruq and the
Iranian Sultan Muhammad Aga Khan proves
the extent to which mysticism is still alive to¬
day in Islam. And it will remain alive, as is
stated in this Hadith of the Prophet Muham¬
mad: "The world will always have forty men
like the Friend of the Merciful (the prophet
Abraham). Through them you will receive
both food and drink."
M Rahmatullah
The Dream
"On a certain night, after completing the
Prayers and liturgical recitations ordained
for the hours of night, I continued to
meditate. And lo! deep in ecstasy, I had a vi¬
sion. There was a lofty Khanqah I house of
Sufis); it was open; I was myself within the
Khanqah. Then suddenly I saw that I had
gone forth from it. I saw that the totality of
the universe, in the structure it reveals, con¬
sists of Light. Everything had become one
colour, and all the atoms of beings, through
their own mode of being and their specific
character, proclaimed: "I am the Truth". I
could not properly interpret the mode of be¬
ing which made them utter this proclama¬
tion. When I had perceived this state in a vi¬
sion, rapture and exaltation, an extraor¬
dinary longing and delight, welled up inside
me. I wished to take flight in the air. I no¬
ticed that at my foot was something
resembling a piece of wood which
prevented me from taking my flight. Carried
away with emotion, I stamped on the
ground in every possible manner until this
piece of wood came away. Like an arrow
shooting from a bow, or rather with a hun¬
dred times more force, I rose and flew off.
When I reached the first Heaven, I saw that
the Moon had melted, and I passed through
the Moon. Then, returning from this state
and from this absence, I came back to
myself".
Shams al-Din Lahiji
Shams al-Din Lahiji Id. 911AHi 1506AD) is a
Persian mystic known for his commentaries
on a classic of Sufism, The Mystic Rose
Garden (Golshan-e raz) by the great Persian
mystic Mahmud Shabestari.
]]>
</page>
<page number="67">
<![CDATA[
Mystic voices
Zubaida and the Sufi
On this page we present two
extracts from The llahi-nama or
Book of God by the great Persian
mystic poet Fand al-Din Attar
(Circa 537-627 AH1 1 140- 1230 AD)
translated into English by John
Andrew Boyle. (The translation,
with a foreword by Annemarie
Schimmel, was published by the
Manchester University Press in
1976 and forms part of the Unesco
Collection of Representative
Works). Doctor, pharmacist and
perfumer, Attar (whose name
means "He who trades in
perfumes") wrote a prose work
containing much information on
the mystics, Tadhkirat ul-Auliya
(abridged English translation,
Biographies of the Saints 1961) as
well as several major works of
poetry, notably Mantiq-ut-Tair
(Eng. transi. The Conference of the
Birds, 1955) and Mosibat-nameh
(The Book of Affliction).
Zubaida was seated on a camel-lifter, journeying auspiciously
upon the Pilgrimage.
A gust of wind blew the curtain to one side: a Sufi caught sight of
her and fell headlong to the ground.
He set up such a crying and commotion that no one could silence
him.
Perceiving that Sufi Zubaida whispered to a eunuch:
"Free me quickly from his noise even though it cost thee much
gold".
The eunuch offered the man a purse of gold: he would not take it,
but when he was offered ten purses he gave way.
Having accepted the ten purses of gold, he ceased at once to cry
and to utter pitiful moans.
Zubaida, perceiving the true state of affairs, that that Sufi had
turned away from the mystery of love,
Told the eunuch to bind his hands and to break his seven limbs
with blows of the rod.
He cried out: "What then did I do that I should suffer these
endless blows?"
Said Zubaida: "0 lover of thyself, what wilt thou do henceforth,
liar that thou art?
Thou didst pretend to love such a one as I, and yet when thou
wert shown gold thou hadst enough of loving me.
I have found thee nought but pretence from head to feet, and I
find thy pretence to be false.
Thou shouldst have sought after me; since thou didst not I knew
for certain that thou wert feeble in action.
Hadst thou sought after me, all my goods and property, all my
gold and silver, would have been thine absolutely.
But since thou soldest me I resolved to punish thy ardour.
Thou shouldst have sought after me, 0 foolish man, and then all
would have been thine at once."
Fix thy heart on God and thou shalt be saved; if thou fix thy heart
on men thou shalt be afflicted.
Close tightly to thyself all other doors; seek out His door and fix
thy heart upon it entirely,
So that through the dark cloud of separation may shine the light
of the dawn of knowledge.
If thou find that light thou shalt find also the way to knowledge.
The saints that raised their heads to the moon were guided by the
light of knowledge.
Story of Bishr Hafi
Bishr Hafi was walking along early one morning drunk with the
lees of wine and yet pure in his soul.
When he found lying in the road a piece of paper on which was
written the name of God.
All he had in the world was a single grain. He sold it for musk. See
what gain!
At nightfall that God-seeking man perfumed the name of God
with his musk.
That night, just before dawn, he dreamt that there came a Voice
to him saying:
"0 thou who didst raise My name from the dust and with
reverence didst both perfume and purify it,
I have made thee a seeker of the truth; I have both perfumed and
purified thee".
0 Lord this sweet-singing 'Attar has perfumed Thy name with the
perfume of his poetry.
And yet what though he sang sweetly? Thy name has always been
perfumed.
Still by Thy grace make him the dust of Thy doorway; make him
famous with Thy name.
He can expect nothing save from Thy grace, for he can produce
not a single act of devotion.
67
]]>
</page>
<page number="68">
<![CDATA[
A new architecture
by Dogan Kuban
DOGAN KUBAN, noted Turkish architect, edu¬
cator and historian of architecture, has been
director of his country's Institute of the History of
Architecture and Restoration since 1974. He has
been a visiting scholar orprofessor at several U. S.
universities, most recently in 1980- 1981 when he
was Aga Khan Visiting Professor of Islamic Archi¬
tecture and Urban Design at the Massachusetts
Institute of Technology. He is a member of the
Steering Committee of the Aga Khan Award for
Architecture.
WHEN Granada, the last Moorish
stronghold in Spain, fell to the
armies of Ferdinand and Isabella
in 1492, its Spanish conquerors were so im¬
pressed by the beauty of the Alhambra, the
palace of the Moorish monarchs, that they
decided not to destroy it. Later, apparently,
the Emperor Charles V found it unsuitable
for an imperial residence. Alongside it his
architect erected a palace which is accepted
as one of the purest examples of Spanish
Renaissance architecture.
The Alhambra and Charles's palace, stan¬
ding side by side, allow us to make in¬
teresting comparisons. It is evident, for ex¬
ample, that certain architectural qualities
which were so perfectly expressed in the
Alhambra and which still retain their fascina¬
tion today, were far outside the frame of
mind of Renaissance Europe. Today
however it would be impossible to imagine
the land of Spain without the Alhambra or
the Great Mosque at Cordoba, and the
vision embodied in them, which totally
eclipses that of Charles's palace.
The Alhambra holds more than an exotic
appeal. Extremely well adapted to the
climatic and topographical conditions of the
hills of Granada, it appears to the visitor as
an organism of masterfully arranged, inter¬
connected spaces of rare elegance. An
original feeling for the organization of space
and for dimensional relationships, and an
exquisite use of decoration, bear witness to
the refined taste of a cultural milieu which is
formally in open contrast with that of
IX/15th and X/16th century Europe. Long
disdained by European art history and labell¬
ed "decorative", this architecture in which
the most profuse decoration scarcely in¬
terferes with the purity of architectural
design has a strong appeal for modern taste.
68
]]>
</page>
<page number="69">
<![CDATA[
Left, ribbed domes of the great mosque of Qayrawan (Tunisia). The blind arcade in
foreground displays typical Arab features, notably the horseshoe arches which
reappear in the illustration (below) to Beatus' Commentary on the Apocalypse, a
brilliant example of what is known as Mozarablc art. The Mozarabic style was created
by the Christian population which continued to practise their religion under Muslim
rule in Spain and combines elements from the two civilizations.
rooted in tradition
What can be seen at the Alhambra can
also be perceived in the products of many
architectural traditions in Islamic countries.
But so slight and superficial is the
knowledge of Islamic architecture that has
reached modern intellectuals, including
Muslims, that for today's generation of
Muslim architects the exploration of their ar¬
chitectural past is a veritable revelation.
Most of today's architectural thinking,
education and practice, basically formulated
after World War I, takes place under the
spell of the industrial ideology of the
Western world. This ideology has also been
overwhelmingly adopted by the ruling
classes of the non-Western world. As a
result it is often difficult to discuss the
values of traditional architecture and the
traditional environment without being labell¬
ed a historicist, a traditionalist, and a lover
of the picturesque, if not a reactionary.
Although the traditional outlook may sub¬
sist and colour many political attitudes, a
strong dichotomy prevails between the ac¬
ceptance of a general set of spiritual values
and the acceptance of specific values
governing our appreciation of the material
culture of the past. Nevertheless, nothing
can escape the continuous reshaping power
of history as long as different languages,
beliefs, social systems and national sen¬
timents exist. And this process is bound
eventually to generate a sympathetic
approach to the values of the material
environment.
Thus a new interpretation of the nature of
the traditional Islamic environment is bound
to influence, negatively or positively, the
practical attitudes of Muslim architects. The
realization that an appropriate environment
cannot be created simply by the transfer of
industrial ideology and the importation of
techniques and materials is gradually replac¬
ing the romantic belief in the universalism of
early rationalism. On the other hand,
although theoretically the tenets of the inter¬
national style in architecture have fallen into
disfavour, they still constitute the entrench¬
ed ideology in architectural practice. Muslim
architects are thus caught up in a dilemma
between the demands of a practice based on
Western images and the exigencies of a na¬
tional identity and a cultural heritage of
great power.
There are two imperatives: on the one
hand the wider necessity of reinterpreting
Muslim history, and on the other the need to
search for a different ¡mage of the modern
environment in the Islamic world. The
former is a task for the scholars and intellect
tuals of Islam; the latter for the architects,
designers and planners. A new vision of J
69
]]>
</page>
<page number="70">
<![CDATA[
1
W "
\
«
T^Ç5""J
- -*- £
ii
m*
-W.ZK
Ct
I
*
J
]]>
</page>
<page number="71">
<![CDATA[
Light and water play an important role In Islamic architecture.
Caught and reflected on stucco or enamelled tile surfaces, light
dispels heaviness and brings a spiritual, incorporeal quality to
brick and stone. Water is a source of coolness and a symbol of
purity, and a small fountain or pool in a central courtyard is often
the focal point of palaces and other Islamic edifices. The subtle
interplay of light and water is particularly remarkable in the
Court of Lions, left, in the Alhambra Palace (Vlll/14th century) at
Granada in Spain. The court, whose walls are lined with
enamelled tiles and delicate stucco-work, owes its name to the
12 marble lions which support the fountain in its centre. The
garden was also an expressive art form in Islam. In the Moghul
painting, below, Babur (IX-X/15th-16th century) the founder of
India's Moghul dynasty, inspects a garden where water channels
are laid out in a characteristic cruciform pattern.
" history will have major implications in every
field, including that of architecture.
Architects express the material dimen¬
sions of an existing image of the world, but
they do not produce that image themselves.
It is to be hoped that a new consciousness
of the relationship between man and his en¬
vironment, filtered through this new vision
of history, will create the intellectual and
emotional atmosphere to which Muslim ar¬
chitects will eventually respond with ap¬
propriate inventiveness.
It is generally acknowledged by recent
historiography that the modern version of
Islamic history, like that of the history of the
non-Western world in general, has been
written by Westerners as an appendix to
Western history. A radical reinterpretation
of history will not only bring to light the
Islamic world-view in its many regional ex¬
pressions, but also its global relationships,
sometimes in symbiosis, sometimes in con¬
trast, with other, non-Islamic traditions.
This will also change our evaluation of
Muslim artistic traditions. The study and
understanding of the rich variety of tradi¬
tional experience in handling form and
space, be it the monumental styles of Spain,
Egypt, Turkey, Iran, or the Indian sub¬
continent, or the amazing richness of in¬
digenous settlements in an area stretching
from Morocco to the Philippines, might give
modern generations of architects the
possibility of understanding certain formal
relationships which are perhaps still valid,
at least as sources of inspiration for the
creation of a new image of the human
environment.
The development of new concepts and
perspectives with such goals and dimen¬
sions is difficult since it has to take place
against a background of rapidly changing
perceptions of national histories, in the
presence of the strong traditions of Western
scholarship, and under pressure from the
overwhelming output of Western publica¬
tions. If, as has so often been observed,
Muslim intellectuals and architects incor¬
rectly interpret and évalue the material
heritage of their own history, this was and
still is the result of the established attitudes
of Islamic art history, in which Islam is por¬
trayed in its medieval garb, as a museum
piece.
The surviving environment, in accordance
with this view, is seen as a hindrance to a ra¬
tional development, that is development
which adheres to models imported from or
imposed by the West. (This insistence on
the negative influence of the West should
not be interpreted as an overall attack on
everything Western, but as an indication of
a new consciousness of history and a refusal
to imitate blindly everything offered by the
West. The subtle balance between borrow¬
ing and interpretation may only be achieved
through an objective re-evaluation of the
past.)
As far as our environment is concerned,
the Western ¡mage has not necessarily pro¬
duced better living- conditions, and has
disfigured or totally destroyed old cities such
as Cairo, Istanbul, Teheran or Jeddah which
had, as we appreciate more fully today^
sound ecological qualities. ~ Examples of
destruction are alarming and discouraging,
not only because of their extent, but
because- of their brutality and lack of
sensibility. >
71
]]>
</page>
<page number="72">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Yvette Vincent Alleaume, Paris
The capital of the Ottoman empire, Istan¬
bul, was once an example of exquisite urban
architecture. Today it contains the most
banal examples of modern architecture.
Neither modern technology at the level at
which it is used, nor the culture of the socie¬
ty in question are capable of producing an
architecture of decent aesthetic quality,
because the transition from one culture to
another has been too sudden to allow the
crystallization of a clear set of definitions
and goals.
The cases of Istanbul and other great cen¬
tres of the old Near East such as Cairo,
Damascus and Jerusalem are very instruc¬
tive, because Western taste in architecture
was introduced in these cities as early as the
Xll/18th century if not before.
The destruction and loss of character of
the traditional environment is not intrinsical¬
ly the result of modernization, but rather the
outcome of an inability to realize and recon¬
cile the imposed image of a city, its architec¬
ture and the life-style which goes with them.
72
That this image was not universally ap¬
plicable is another matter. Our societies do
not have the potential, whether economic,
technological, cultural or social, effectively
to produce and maintain this image which
was not theirs. The relationship between the
image and its potential realization cannot be
expressed by a mere equation, as it is often
simplistically claimed.
The environment of the past has, never¬
theless, remarkable powers of survival.
Despite the drastic destruction of recent
decades, the traditional environment,
especially in rural and semi-rural areas, still
has a reasonable chance of remaining with
us for some time to come. There is a grow¬
ing tendency for Muslim architects to
evaluate and use the traditional building
stock, monuments and settlements as part
of a modern environment in which the old
and the new are integrated, in which
changes occur at a perceptible but less rapid
pace, and in which Muslim societies do not
lose the thread of history. It is perhaps the
responsibility of the present generation to
express these aspirations. But in the present
circumstances of rapid change, especially in
countries where the natural resources at the
disposal of governments seem limitless, the
fight for a more controlled development and
a slower rate of change, thus respecting
history and harmonizing with the remnants
of traditional culture, is beset with many
difficulties.
Given the impact of industry, the
monopolizing and levelling effects of world
politics and communication systems, and
the needs of large sections of the world
population, the role of architects and plan¬
ners in defining a new ¡mage may only
emerge from an awareness of the cultural
dimensions of the present situation. We
should continue to emphasize the principle
that the possibility of creating a healthy en¬
vironment depends not on the capacity to
buy Western technology, but on a potential
inherent in the cultural and social structure
of the society.
]]>
</page>
<page number="73">
<![CDATA[
In Islamic countries from the Atlantic to the Ganges, a distinctive architectural
"language" came into being and developed over the centuries. It was based on
a common faith and civilization and transcended geographic, cultural and
climatic diversity. Far from jettisoning earlier cultural traditions, Islam
assimilated and transformed them, producing works of monumental
architecture prodigious both in quality and number. The extent of this
achievement can be measured not only in mosques but in many other types of
building such as madrasahs, mausoleums, observatories, palaces, citadels and
caravanserais. Islam also made a notable contribution to town planning. On
these pages, roofscapes from three countries. Left, rooftop of the mosque at
Djenne (Mali) an old trading city and centre of Islamic culture founded in the
Vll/13th century. The mosque dates from 1905. Above, housetops of the village
of El-Mahder (Algeria) as they appear from the roof of the village mosque.
Below, undulating rooftop of the bazaar at Yazd (Iran).
Photo © Ch. Bastin and J. Evrard, Belgium
How can all these questions, anxieties
and aspirations be translated into everyday
forms of architecture? How can a feeling for
the traditional environment and forms
perceived by an architect be expressed in a
modern building? Since the terms traditional
culture and modern environment are
susceptible to interpretation and subject to
continuous change, their relationship can
only be defined by practice. Theoretical dis¬
cussions cannot determine universally ap¬
plicable Islamic forms, but they may perhaps
give shape to certain attitudes which may
help to attain such forms in their specific
cultural context, which will most probably
vary from region to region.
Recent debates on modern architecture
and town planning in Islamic countries, such
as the seminars sponsored by the Aga Khan
Award for Islamic Architecture, conferences
on the Islamic city held in many Arab coun¬
tries, and symposia sponsored by interna¬
tional agencies such as Unesco, have shown
that it is extremely difficult, even hazardous, i
73
]]>
</page>
<page number="74">
<![CDATA[
- to define in physical terms a modern en¬
vironment consonant with the traditional
culture.
Some individual examples may convey
such relationships, but they cannot provide
formulae which may be applied elsewhere.
The works of architects who make con¬
scious efforts to solve these problems
basically refer to formal elements taken from
traditional architecture and the traditional
environment. They emphasize the virtues of
indigenous buildings, the work of
anonymous builders, whose qualities still
capture the imagination. Thismay be called
a search for an architecture in the spirit of
Islam, Islam defined as cultural tradition.
This trend is best represented by the now-
famous Egyptian architect Hassan Fathy and
others sharing the same approach. It is a
belief that a broad but sensitive application
of traditional forms and design principles is
conducive to healthy modern architecture.
Hassan Fathy has put it as follows:
"...people do recognize and wish to
remedy the cultural confusion in our ar¬
chitecture... This confusion is seen as a prob¬
lem of style, and style is looked upon as
some sort of surface finish that can be ap-
Left, the Friday Mosque at
Zarla (northern Nigeria).
Founded in the Xl/17th
century, Zaria Is the ancient
capital of the Hausa
kingdom. Right, inside the
prayer hall of the great
Umayyad Mosque at
Damascus, completed
around 97 AH/714-715 AD.
The horseshoe arches rest
on tall slender columns
revealing the influence of
classical antiquity.
plied to any building and even scraped off
and changed if necessary... In the architec¬
tural schools they make no study of the
history of domestic buildings, and learn ar¬
chitectural periods by the accidents of
style... Thus the graduate architect believes
this to be all there is in 'style', and imagines
a building changes its style as a man
changes clothes."
Here style is used synonymously with
monumental style. Hassan Fathy em¬
phasizes the importance of the vernacular
and the organic relationship between style
and culture. As a matter of fact, a compe- )
Detail of a façade of the
Mustansiriya madrasah in
Baghdad built under the
Abbasids (Vll/13th century).
It displays a strong Persian
influence and the decorative
patterns based on octagons,
six- and eight-pointed stars,
and other geometrical
motifs are characteristic of
Islamic art.
74
]]>
</page>
<page number="75">
<![CDATA[
¡A
Il A >M I
HL v 1
B 5; s
H if
:
]]>
</page>
<page number="76">
<![CDATA[
-tent and conscious use of traditional forms
with the partial integration of modern
techniques may lead to satisfactory
aesthetic solutions and provide modern
comfort. The Halawa house at Agamy,
Egypt, which recently won an Aga Khan
Award for Architecture, is a case in point.
But one must confess that this building
could easily be labelled "elitist". It is only in
the rural context and with a complete use of
traditional techniques that this approach has
any chance of being adopted. Under today's
economic restraints, to rely on old building
techniques for new purposes ¡s a challenge
for architects, since traditional technology
still prevails in many regions of the Islamic
world and seems economically rewarding.
Here too, the Gourna village experiment of
Hassan Fathy, the subject of his book
Architecture for the Poor, was a pioneering
example.
A large group of architects have found
that a rather free use and interpretation of
tradition without resorting to the original
forms themselves is a satisfactory approach
to design. Both modern and traditional
materials may be used for this purpose. A
still unfinished project, the Great National
Mosque at Islamabad, the work of the
Turkish architect Vedat Dalokay, is a large-
scale example of this trend at its freest. An¬
dré Raveréau's Health Centre at Mopti
(Mali), which has also been awarded an Aga
Khan Prize, is a highly qualified illustration
of the same approach on an everyday scale.
Nevertheless, for most architects, an ar¬
chitecture in spiritual continuity with the
past means incorporating formal echoes of
the past.
Traditional forms have not yet been
satisfactorily used in large-scale buildings,
and it is impossible to maintain that they
ever will be, because there is a fundamental
difference between the application of tradi¬
tional forms to small buildings and their use
in large ones. The monumental "accent" of
our environment has changed. Monumental
architecture has a different symbolic
resonance when it is not related to religious
or political requirements.
A project such as the new Jeddah airport
or a project once proposed for the city cen¬
tre in Tehran, like many new university cam¬
puses all over the Islamic world or large-
scale housing schemes, illustrate the power¬
ful symbolism of the new functions but also
reveal the anarchy of taste prevailing in the
minds of designers, Muslims and non-
Muslims alike. The same confusion is to be
observed in urban renewal projects where
planners insert space concepts of Western
origin into the existing urban fabric, with
fatal results. Such projects include the
renewal of the city core of Mashad around
the shrine of Imam Reza, speculative
destruction of the old city of Istanbul,
destruction of old Jeddah and Mecca.
These should not be interpreted as in¬
dividual failures. They might even, in some
ways, represent competent planning. But
what is missing in all these endeavours is the
basic sureness of an architect or planner in
complete harmony with his society, and a
society which has clearly formulated the
demands it wishes to make on them.
In the continuous flux of life, respect for
the past cannot be a static reverence; it re¬
quires a dynamic interpretation. Thus
modern development in Islamic countries
brings architects more responsibility than
7R
has been customary until now. They are not
only supposed to be sensitive to the struc¬
ture and inclinations of social forces but also
to be equipped with a responsible
understanding of culture and history.
In developing a new ¡mage for a future en¬
vironment, through an enriched vision of
history and within a vision of future cultural
plurality, the link between theoretical think¬
ing and everyday practice cannot be main¬
tained by the efforts of architects, planners
or scholars alone, but through the demands
of a public opinion increasingly aware of its
cultural identity within an unbiased historical
perspective.
M Dogan Kuban
Photo ©Aga Khan Award for Architecture, Geneva
The Agricultural Training Centre at Nianing,
Senegal, a regional training school for
80 students, received one of the 1980 Aga
Khan Awards for Architecture. The
application on a larger scale of a prototype
developed by Unesco, it was constructed
by local craftsmen using a labour-intensive
building system.
]]>
</page>
<page number="77">
<![CDATA[
In 1976, the Aga Khan announced
the creation of an award to
encourage an architecture in the
spirit of Islam which would honour
projects that met modern needs
whilst remaining in harmony with
local culture and climate. The first
awards were made in 1980, when
fifteen projects were honoured by
a distinguished jury of architects,
planners, sociologists and art
experts. In addition, the Egyptian
architect, artist and poet Hassan
Fathy was honoured by a special
Chairman's Award in
acknowledgement of his life-long
contribution and commitment to
architecture in the Muslim world.
A champion of indigenous building,
he has shown, particularly in the
village of New Gourna, near Luxor,
Egypt, that mud brick structures
can be graceful and economical to
build and are admirably suited to
the climate, as witness the mosque
of New Gourna (above). Left, street
scene at New Gourna.
77
]]>
</page>
<page number="78">
<![CDATA[
MUSLIMS OF THE SOVIET UNION
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 29
Qur'an, Rakmatulla-kori Kasymov from An¬
dizhan, in the Uzbek Soviet Socialist
Republic, was named as one of the best
reciters in the whole Islamic world.
Following the example of the Prophet
Muhammad (Peace be on Him), who com¬
bined prayer and meditation with active ser¬
vice to his land and to all mankind, the
Muslims of the Soviet Union combine ser¬
vice to Allah and the observance of religious
rites with due and conscientious fulfilment
of the social obligations deriving from their
sacred duty towards the people of their
country and to all men.
The World Muslim Congress has publish¬
ed a number of pamphlets on Islamic
teachings in the modern world. One of
them, dedicated to the Daruriyat Sitta, the
six basic requirements of Islam concerning
food, clothing, housing, education, health
and security, stresses in particular that "It is
the duty of every Muslim State to guarantee
the satisfaction of these basic needs for all
its citizens, both Muslim and non-Muslim."
A Muslim State which does not do so, says
the author of this pamphlet, fails in its
Islamic duty. On the other hand, if the policy
of a non-Muslim State conforms to the six
basic requirements of Islam, points out the
author, it fulfils to a considerable extent the
tasks inherent in Islam.
One cannot but agree with this point of
view. Indeed, a non-Muslim State which,
like the Soviet Union, grants its Muslims
freedom of religion so that they can adhere
to its canons and helps them rise to the level
of modern civilization from a state of
political dependence and economic
backwardness does greatly contribute to the
goals of Islam.
Ziyauddin Khan Ibn Ishan Babakhan
FURTHER READING
ON ISLAM
The World of Islam: Faith, People, Cul¬
ture, edited by Bernard Lewis. Thames and
Hudson, London. 1976. 360 pp. (£12.50);'
Art of Islam: Language and Meaning,
by Titus Burckhardt. 1976. 204 pp. (£12.50);
Islamic Science: an Illustrated Study,
by Seyyed Hossein Nasr. 1976. 273 pp.
(£12.50) ; The Quranic Art of Calli¬
graphy and Illumination, by Martin Lings.
1976. 242 pp. (£20); Geometric Con¬
cepts in Islamic Art, by Issam El-Said and
Ayse Parman. 1976. 154 pp. (£10). All
published by the World of Islam Festival
Publishing Company Ltd.
Early Islam, by Desmond Stewart and
the editors of Time-Life Books, Time Inc.,
New York. 1967 (2nd impression 1970).
192 pp.
The Genius of Arab Civilization:
Source of Renaissance, edited by John R.
Hayes. Phaidon Press, Iver, Bucks, U.K.
1976 (£15).
Introduction to the History of Science,
by George Sarton. 3 vols. Baltimore, Mary¬
land, 1927-1948.
The Legacy of Islam, by Joseph Schacht
with CE. Bosworth. 2nd edition, Oxford
University Press, 1974.
Glimpses of Islamic Civilization. Cata¬
logue of an exhibition held at Unesco head¬
quarters, Paris. 1980.
Hegira, Year 1400, is the theme of
Unesco's quarterly review Cultures (Vol.
VII, No. 4). Contributors are noted specia¬
lists on différent aspects of Islamic civiliza¬
tion from Asia, Africa and Europe.
WORKS FROM THE ISLAMIC WORLD
IN THE UNESCO COLLECTION
OF REPRESENTATIVE WORKS
Translations from Arabic
Al-Ghazali. O Disciple! (Ayyuha l-walad).
(Bilingual edition.) Trans, by Georges
H. Scherer. Beirut, Catholic Press, 1951.
xxvi + 28 p., 30 p. (A mystic's message.)
Averroës (Ibn Rushd). On the Harmony of
Religion and Philosophy (Kitab fas Al-
Maqal). Trans, by George F. Hourani. Lon¬
don, Luzac, 1961. 126 p.
The Incoherence of the Incoherence (Taha-
fut at-Tahafut). Trans., Introduction and
notes by Simon van den Bergh. London,
Luzac, 1954. 2 vols. Vol. I, xxxvi + 373 p.;
Vol. II, 219 p. (Philosophy.)
Three Short Commentaries on Aristotle's
'Topics', 'Rhetoric', and 'Poetics' (Bilingual
edition). Ed. and trans, by Charles E. Butter-
worth. Albany, State University of New
York Press, 1977. 206 p.
Awwad, Tawfiq Yusuf (Lebanon). Death
in Beirut (Tawahin Beirut). Trans, by Leslie
McLoughlin. London, Heinemann, 1976.
190 p. (Novel.)
Hilal, Al-Sabi' The Rules and Regulations
of the 'Abbasid Court (Rusum Dar Al-
Khilafah). Trans., Introduction and notes by
Elie A. Salem. Beirut, Lebanese Commis¬
sion for the Translation of Great Works,'
1977. 134p.
Idris, Yusuf. The Cheapest Nights and
Other Stories (Arkhas Layali). Trans, by
Wadida Wassef. London, Peter Owen,
1978. 196 p.
Translations from Persian
Attar, Farid al-Din. The llahi-nama or Book
of God. Trans, by John Andrew Boyle;
Foreword by Annemarie Schimmel. Man¬
chester University Press, 1976. 392 p.
Muslim Saints and Mystics [Episodes of the
Tadhkirat al-Auliya' ('Memorial of the
Saints')]. Trans, by A. J. Arberry. Chicago,
III., University of Chicago Press, 1966.
xn + 287 p; London, Routledge & Kegan
Paul, 1966. xi'i + 287 p.; Toronto, University
of Toronto Press, 1966. 287 p.; London and
Boston, Routledge & Kegan Paul, 2nd ed.,
1973. 288 p.
Fasa'i's, Hasan-E. History of Persia under
Qajar Rule (Farsnama-ye Naseri). Trans.
Herbert Busse. New York and London,
Columbia University Press, 1972. 494 p.
Ferdowsi. The Epic of the Kings (Shah-
Nama). Trans, by Reuben Levy. London,
Routledge & Kegan Paul. Chicago, III., Uni¬
versity of Chicago Press, 1967.
xxviii + 423 p.; Toronto, University of
Toronto Press.
Folk Tales of Ancient Persia. Trans, by
Forough Hekmat with the collaboration of
Yann Lovelock. III. by Muhammad Bahrami.
Delmar, New York, Caravan Books, 1974.
119 p.
Gurgani, Fakhr ud-Din. Vis and Ramin.
Trans, by George Morrison. New York and
London, Columbia University Press, 1972.
357 p. (Mediaeval novel.).
Juvaini, 'Ala-ad-Din' Ata-Malik. The His¬
tory of the World Conqueror (Ta'rikh-i-
Jahan Gusha). Trans, by John Andrew
Boyle; Introduction by S. Runciman. Man¬
chester, University Press, 1958. 2 vols. Cam
bridge, Mass., Harvard University Press,
1958. 2 vols. Vols. I and II: xiv + vi + 763 p.
Khayyam, 'Umar. The Ruba'iyat. Trans,
by Parichehr Kasra. Delmar, New York,
Scholars' Facsimiles & Reprints, 1975.
183 p. (Love poems.)
Love and War (Adventures from the Firuz
Shah Nama of Skeikh Bighami). Trans, by
William L. Hanaway, Jr, Delmar, New York,
Scholars' Facsimiles & Reprints, 1974.
208 p.
Nizam Al-Mulk. The Book of Government
or Rules for Kings (The Siyar al-Muluk or
Siyasat-nama). Trans, by Hubert Darke.
London, Routledge & Kegan Paul, 1960,
1978. New Haven, Conn., Yale University
Press, 1961. xi + 259 p.
Rumi, Jalal-AI-Din. More Tales from the
Masnavi. Ed. and trans, by A. J. Arberry.
London, Allen & Unwin, 1963. 252 p.
Mystical Poems of Rumi (First selection:
poems 1-200). Trans, by A.J. Arberry. Chi¬
cago and London, University of Chicago
Press, 1968. 203 p.
Mystical Poems of Rumi (Second selection:
poems 201-400). Trans, by A.J. Arberry.
Boulder (Colorado), Westview Press, 1979.
187 p.
Sa'di. Morals Pointed and Tales Adorned
(Bustan). Trans, by G.M. Wickens. Toronto
and Buffalo, University of Toronto Press,
1974. 316 p.
The Ship of Sulaiman (Safina'l Sulaimani).
Trans, by John O'Kane. London, Routledge
& Kegan Paul, 1972. 250 p. (Travel.)
Tabib, Rashid al-Din. The Successors of
Genghis Khan. Trans, by John Andrew
Boyle. New York and London, Columbia
University Press, 1971. 372 p. (History.)
77?e Tarikh-e Sistan. Trans, by Milton Gold.
Rome, Istituto per ¡I Medio ed Estremo
Oriente, 1976. 369 p.
Tusi, Nazir ad-Din. The Nasirean Ethics
(Akhlaq-i Nasiri). Trans, by G. M. Wickens.
London, Allen & Unwin, 1964. 352 p. (Philo¬
sophy.)
Warawini. The Tales of Marzuban
(Marzuban-nama). Trans, by Reuben Levy.
Greenwood Press, 1969; London, Thames &
Hudson, 1959. 254 p.
India i
Basheer, Vaikom Muhammad. Me Gran- %
dad 'ad an Elephant! (Three Stories of Mus- »
lim Life in South India) (Malayam). Trans. §
by R.E. Asher and Achamma Coilparampil <
Chandersekaran. Edinburgh, Edinburgh Uni- -
versity Press, 1980. 204 p. X
Pakistan
Iqbal, Muhammad. Javid-Nama (Persian).
Trans. With introduction and notes by A.J.
Arberry. London, Allen & Unwin, 1966.
151 p. New York, Hillary House, 1966.
151 p. (Philosophical poems).
Works included in this list may be obtained
either through booksellers or directly from
the publishers who can also inform prospec¬
tive purchasers or inquirers as to whether or
not a given title is still available in print.
78
]]>
</page>
<page number="79">
<![CDATA[
Two important contributions to Islamic studies
THE ARTS Ol THE BOOK
in Central Asia
i
^ ^^
":*% ¡
1
Gmcnl Uar HAM)
The Arts of the Book in Central Asia is a scholarly and beau¬
tiful volume in which an international team of leading scholars
surveys the arts and skills of manuscript production during a
classic period of Islamic civilization, from the 14th to the early
16th century AD. The book, compiled over a period of ten
years, is an outcome of a Unesco-sponsored study programme
on the civilizations of the peoples of Central Asia, being carried
out in co-operation with the International Association for the
Study of Central Asia.
General Editor: Basil Gray, Fellow of the British Academy,
formerly Keeper in the British Museum
328pages 250 illustrations 350 French francs
Co-published with Serindia Publications, London, who have exclusive
sales rights in the UK, and share the market with Unesco in the rest of
Europe, in India and the Middle East; and with Shambha/a Publications
of Boulder, Colorado, who have sales rights for North and South
America
The Islamic City, a collection of essays by architects,
archaeologists, art historians and scholars in the field of Islamic
studies, examines the religious, legal, governmental and educa¬
tional institutions of the Islamic city as manifested in its physi¬
cal features. Includes four case-studies: San-'a, Fez, Aleppo,
and the vision of Ali Mubarak for the replanning of Cairo. The
essays were selected from contributions to a Unesco-
sponsored colloquium on the Islamic City, held at the Univer¬
sity of Cambridge, UK, as part of the World of Islam Festival.
210 pages 36 French francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscrip¬
tion rates in local currency, will be supplied
on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P.O.
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne (Victoria), 3000.
AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31, A-
1011, Vienna. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. - CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7. CHINA. China National Publications Import and Export
Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Beijing - CYPRUS. "MAM", Arch¬
bishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia. CZE¬
CHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena 51, Prague 1 (Perma¬
nentdisplay); Zahranicni literatura, 11 Soukenicka, Prague 1. For
Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893
31 Bratislava - CSSR. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export and
Subscription Service, 35 Norre Sogade, DK 1370, Copenhagen
K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for
Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo.
ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis
Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1,
SF-00100 Helsinki 10. - FRANCE. Librairie de I'Unesco, 7,
place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP. 12598-48. - GERMAN
DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710
Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R.
FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier (Ger¬
man, English, French and Spanish editions): Mr. H. Baum,
Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57, D5300
Bonn 3. For other Unesco publications: Karger Verlag,
Germering/München. For scientific maps only: Geo Center,
Postfach 800830, Stuttgart 80. - GHANA. Presbyterian Books¬
hop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers
Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape Coast; The University
Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1, Legon. - GREAT BRITAIN.
See United Kingdom. HONG KONG. Federal Publications
(HK) Ltd., 5A .evergreen Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street,
Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon.
Hong-Kong Government Information Services, Publications
Centre, GPO Building, Connaught Place. HUNGARY.
Akadémiai Könyvesbolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V.
Konyvtürosok Boltja, Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest VI.
ICELAND. Snaebjörn Jonsson & Co., H. F., Hafnarstraeti 9,
Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcut¬
ta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf Ali
Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road,
Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-
Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta
70016; Scindia House, New Delhi; Publications Section, Ministry
of Education and Social Welfare, 511 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan,
New Delhi 110001. - INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and
Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia
Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr
Sam Ratulangie 47, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie
Publishing and Distribution Co., 28, Vessal Shirazi Street,
Enghélab Avenue, P.O. Box 314/1486, Teheran; Iranian Nat.
Comm. for Unesco, Ave. Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B.P. 1533,
Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, Al -Rashid Street,
Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland
Ltd., Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL.
A. B.C. Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby. Road, Tel
Aviv 61000 - JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O.
Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book
Service Inc., Shuhwa Toranomon 3bldg, 23-6, Toranomon
3-Chome, Minato-ku, Tokyo 105, KENYA. East African
Publishing House, P.O. Box 30571, Nairobi. - KOREA. Korean
National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul.
KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait -
LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho,
Southern Africa. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd.,
P.O. Box 286, Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency for Development of
Publication & Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEM¬
BOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop,
Kuala Lumpur 22-11. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic
Street, Valletta. - MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30,
Bourbon Street, Port-Louis. - MONACO. British Library, 30
bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. - NETHERLANDS. For the
"Unesco Koerier" Dutch edition only: KEESING BOEKEN B.V.,
Postbus 1118, 1000 BC Amsterdam. Agent for all Unesco
publications: N.V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The
Hague. - NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine
N.V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. - NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, Government
Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 130.
Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch; Alma Street, P.O.
Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1104. Dunedin;
Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington. NIGERIA. The
University Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan,
P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of Nsukka; The University
Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of
Zaria. NORWAY. All publications: Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco
Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6.
- PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam,
P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. -
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livraria
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. - SEYCHELLES. New Ser¬
vice Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé. - SIERRA
LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19. - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951,
Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA. All publications: Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.
SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gar¬
diner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2. - SUDAN. Al Bashir
Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. - SWEDEN. All
publications A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel,
Regenngsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16. For the
Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Förbundet, Skolgränd 2, Box 150
50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. - SWITZERLAND. All publications:
Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue
Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11, CCP. 12-236. - TANZANIA.
Dares Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam.
THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road,
Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok: Suksapan Panit,
Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam Com¬
pany, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. - TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I. - TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi
A.S., Istiklâl Caddesi, No. 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu,
Istanbul. - UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Govt. Bookshops in London,
Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmin¬
gham, Bristol. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue
South, New York, N.Y. 10010. - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya
Kniga, Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska
Knjiga, Trg Republike 5/8, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba
Slovenje, Titova C 25, P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubljana. - ZIMBABWE.
Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union Avenue, Salisbury.
]]>
</page>
<page number="80">
<![CDATA[
*w
.
mir
.-*.-»
The world of Islam
Today, at the dawn of the fifteenth cen¬
tury of the Islamic calendar, the faith
and civilization of Islam form a bond
uniting hundreds of millions of men and
women on every continent, above all in
a vast swathe of land stretching from
West Africa to Southeast Asia. As the
place of congregational worship, the
mosque is the centre of religious life in
the Islamic world and a symbol of the
unity of Islamic civilization. Photos
show: (left) the mosque at Taluksangay
on the island of Mindanao, the Philippi¬
nes; (below left) tower of the mosque at
Agadès, Niger; (centre) a mausoleum in
the Shah-i Zinda necropolis at Samar¬
kand in the Uzbek Soviet Socialist
Republic; (below right) mosque at
Yafros in the Yemen Arab Republic;
(bottom photo) the Badshahi mosque at
Lahore, Pakistan.
Photo Jacques Brunet Explorer. Pans
"f
Photo Robert Harding Picture Library, London
]]>
</page>
</document>
