<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074734eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
JANUARY 1981 - 4.50 French francs
V
The handicapped tenth of humanity
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
^
Bulgaria
The stricken doe
This miniature carved bone plate (46x35 mm) is an example of tenth-century Bulgarian art. It is
decorated with the image of an animal, thought to be a doe, wounded in the neck by an arrow.
The whole posture of the stricken beast, depicted with upraised head and open mouth against an
abstract background, is a vivid expression of pain. Now preserved in the National Archaeological
Museum at Sofia, the plate was unearthed at Preslav, the capital of Bulgaria in the tenth century
and an important centre of arts and crafts.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
JANUARY 1981 34th YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 25 LANGUAGES
English Italian Turkish Macedonian
French Hindi Urdu Serbo-Croat
Spanish Tamil Catalan Slovene
Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese
German Persian Korean
Arabic Dutch Swahili
Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French and Spanish
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 44 French Francs
2 years: 75 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 32 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (11 issues a
year including one double issue).
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor. Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New York, U.S.A.; (3) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mans¬
field Road. Wooster. Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Editor-in-chief: Jean Gaudin
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English Edition: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Russian Edition: Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
German Edition: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Arabic Edition: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Italian Edition: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Hindi Edition: Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
Tamil Edition: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew Edition: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian Edition: Samad Nourinejad (Teheran)
Dutch Edition: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese Edition: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish Edition: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu Edition: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan Edition: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian Edition: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean Edition: Lim Moun-young (Seoul)
Swahili Edition: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salaam)
Braille Edition: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene Editions: Punisa Pavlovic (Belgrade)
Chinese Edition: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Philippe Gentil
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
page
4 THE INTERNATIONAL YEAR OF DISABLED PERSONS
A message from the Director-General of Unesco
~5 THE HANDICAPPED TENTH OF HUMANITY
by Federico Mayor
1 THE UNITED NATIONS DECLARATION
ON THE RIGHTS OF DISABLED PERSONS
~8 FEELING FREE
Photo story
TO THE COURAGE TO TAKE RISKS
by Edward V. Roberts
12 SEEING WITH MY HANDS
by Olga I. Skorokhodova
14 THE HANDICAP OF PREJUDICE
by Peter O. Mba
Ï7 'I AM SO AFRAID THEY WILL LAUGH AT ME'
by Barbro Lundahl
18 THE UNESCO BRAILLE COURIER
by Frederick H. Potter
19-21 FOUR PAGES IN BRAILLE
26 LOUIS BRAILLE: A TOUCH OF GENIUS
by Serge Guillemet
27 UNESCO AND THE INTERNATIONAL YEAR
OF DISABLED PERSONS
by Nils-lvar Sundberg
29 DISABILITY AND THE DEVELOPING WORLD
by Norman Acton
30 THE DOUBLE PROFILE OF DISABILITY
34 ABC INTERNATIONAL
A FUTURE FOR EVERY BLIND CHILD
by Pierrette Posmowski
36 A WORKING DEFINITION OF HANDICAP
38 UNESCO NEWSROOM
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
BULGARIA: The stricken doe
Cover
According to latest estimates, 450 million
people, one tenth of humanity, are handicap¬
ped. As 1981, designated by the United Na¬
tions as International Year of Disabled Per¬
sons, begins, the Unesco Courier examines
the attitudes of society towards handicap¬
ped people. A desire to be given their full
place in society, to be seen as people first
and only afterwards as handicapped, is the
common theme of the testimonies of a
number of handicapped people published in
this issue. In a further issue to be published
later this year the Unesco Courier will con¬
sider more specific problems such as the
latest developments in special education for
handicapped people, their integration into
professional life, and scientific, techno¬
logical and medical action for the investi¬
gation and alleviation of their condition as
well as the prevention of avoidable han¬
dicaps. Our cover design is by the graphic ar¬
tist Rudi Meyer.
Photo Unesco Courier
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
fe)
The International Year
of Disabled Persons
Racism takes differences in the colour of individuals' skins or in the
cultural patterns of various groups and makes of them the outward and
visible signs of a total otherness and the distinguishing marks of in¬
herent inferiority or superiority. Can modern societies summon up the
necessary courage and show the necessary clear-sightedness to break
away from a pattern of behaviour towards the handicapped which at
times proceeds from a similar extrapolation?
Handicaps, whether of body or mind, sometimes result from acci¬
dents, but they are often the consequence of thefaults orfailings war,
hunger, disease of the societies in which we live. The victims emerge
bearing the stamp of a profound difference from their fellows, a diffe¬
rence which too many people believe to be irremediable. Thus it is that,
in both the industrialized and the developing countries, the handicapped
nearly a tenth of humanity may find themselves under sentence of
exclusion from society.
Our laws and, more generally, the whole organization of our every¬
day life in its simplest acts seem to overlook the very existence of the
handicapped. The fact that they are in many cases shut up in special
institutions, kept dependent on assistance and cut offfrom the rest of
the community perpetuates society's ignorance of their real needs and
deepest aspirations. Yet they ask for nothing more than the means
ofjoining in the various aspects of social life and, as a corollary, for
society fully to accept their participation.
The satisfaction of this legitimate demand requires, however, a two¬
fold line of approach. First, it is necessary to mobilize all the material,
scientific and human resources needed not only to prevent peri-natal
accidents and to cure the disabilities of the handicapped, but also to
enable them to take their share of responsibilities and enjoy their rights
on an equalfooting with all other members ofsociety. Such is the objec¬
tive ofspecial education, whose primary aim it must be to ensure their
social integration.
Secondly, thepublic needs to be educated and to learn to welcome the
handicapped into its midst unreservedly, yet unobtrusively and without
condescension, for they are, as of right, full members ofsociety. In this
context, education first andforemost means presenting objective infor¬
mation about the possibility of their doing so. This is why a large por¬
tion of this issue of the Unesco Courier, thefirst of two to be devoted to
theproblems of the handicapped aspart of Unesco 's contribution to the
International Year of Disabled Persons, has been set aside to allow
them to speak for themselves.
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
Director-General of Unesco
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
m
Photo Igor Zatin, Tass. Unesco exhibition "Full Participation and Equality' A blind sculptor at work.
The handicapped tenth of humanity
by Federico Mayor
IT is reckoned that about 450 million people roughly 1 0 per cent
of the world's population suffer from some form of physical,
sensory or mental handicap. The figure may be even higher
around 13 per cent according to recent estimates by the World
Health Organization (WHO). Still more serious is the fact that the
problem, seen in both quantitative and qualitative terms, shows no
signs of diminishing.
To such underlying causes of deficiencies and impairments as
parasite-borne diseases, infections during pregnancy and acute
malnutrition during gestation and the early months of life, must be
FEDERICO MAYOR, Spanish biochemist, is Deputy Director- General of
Unesco. A former fellow of Trinity College, Oxford, he has been professor of
biochemistry and director of the department of biochemistry and molecular
biology at the Autonomous University of Madrid. He has also been Rector of
the University of Granada and Spain's Vice-Minister of Education and
Science. He has produced an extensive output of scientific works, including
studies on the biochemical analysis of the causes of mental retardation.
added such recent trends as the rising number of road and industrial
accidents, as well as the effects of alcoholism and drug addiction.
The problem of disability is thus one facing industrially developed
and developing countries alike. Though the causes and nature of the
handicaps may differ, the outlook is (albeit for different reasons)
everywhere equally gloomy.
Moreover, these remarks take no account of endemic warfare,
which, given the size and nature of modern weapons, may assume
catastrophic proportions. The prospects are no brighter when we
look in this direction, either.
Everything humanly possible must be done to prevent the occur¬
rence of handicaps and disablement. And where, in spite of all our
efforts, cases of disablement exist, it is the duty of the authorities
and society at large to do their utmost to attend to them as they
deserve, to improve the situation of the handicapped as far as
available knowledge permits and make sure that they lead as normal
a life as possible.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
The International Year of Disabled Persons proclaimed by the
United Nations must mark the start of vigorous, imaginative and
concerted action at the international level, in favour of all those suf¬
fering from congenital or acquired disabilities. The theme of the In¬
ternational Year is "full participation and equality": total equality,
and participation as full as personal circumstances permit in each
case. Fortunately, the world is increasingly moving towards a per¬
sonalized approach to education and health care. Every individual is
unique, and this must be the focal point of all action and every
strategy.
The International Year of Disabled Persons provides us with an ex¬
cellent opportunity to lay the groundwork and this is a genuine
moral duty for the meticulous individual care and attention which
handicapped people deserve and need. With a sense of hope and ex¬
pectation which we must not disappoint, they are waiting to see
how the international community is taking them into consideration
and is preparing to offer them all the aid within its power.
In 1981 , we must, each and every one of us, do all we can to make
those around us aware of the extent of the problem, and above all of
the need to take organized and effective action to ensure preven¬
tion, care^nd rehabilitation by exploiting to the full our resources of
scientific and technical knowledge. Moreover, and let there be no
misunderstanding on this point, we must do this without the
slightest hint of doing "good works" or providing misplaced charity.
A question of human rights is involved.
Whoever finds himself or herself debarred from exercising certain
of those rights should have the opportunity to enjoy fully those
rights that are consistent with his or her condition. In recent times,
these rights, which have been duly recognized by the United
Nations, have been written into the constitutions of a number of
countries. This is an example which should be emulated because it is
a touchstone of the concern with which a country treats all its
citizens, without making any exceptions or displaying any
preferences.
In my view, the first right of any disabled person is not to be
disabled. In other words, the most important thing is to use all the
means within our power to prevent disablement, whether physical,
sensory, or mental, from occurring. Hence, we must pursue our
researches, in order to learn more about the origins of disabilities; at
the same timeand this is where the most flagrant inequality and in¬
justice liewe must apply the knowledge already available.
A great deal can be done in terms of legislation, assistance,
education, employment and prevention. There is much to learn from
the experience of other countries through exchange of information
and findings. If we are to be aware of the problem, we must be in¬
formed about it, and if we are to become involved, we must be
aware.
The year 1981 must usher in an era in which increased concern is
shown for all disabled persons and in which national and interna¬
tional endeavours are co-ordinated. How can this be done? At the
national level, through the work of various associations in the crea¬
tion or mobilization of effectively-run scientific and public informa¬
tion systems; through the introduction of preventive measures (such
as genetic counselling, vaccination, early diagnosis, the laying-down
of standards in order to prevent or reduce accidents on the roads
and in industry; the keeping of a just peace, and so on); through the
development of special education characterized by the maximum
degree of integration and by the most individual approach possible
consistent with the nature and severity of the disability; through full
rehabilitation and incorporation into the workforce; through as full a
participation as possible in cultural, political, social and economic
life; and, lastly, through the dismantling of architectural or other
barriers.
At the international level, it will entail concerted action by the
competent specialized institutions (in particular the World Health
Organization, the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United
Nations, the International Labour Organisation, and Unesco) and
other organizations such as UNICEF and the World Food Pro¬
gramme, together with the indispensable assistance of the relevant
non-governmental organizations, with a view to drawing up
guidelines which, as they come to be accepted and implemented by
the different countries, will enable 1981 to be seen as the beginning
of the end of a situation that urgently calls for unlimited collabora¬
tion in the fields both of human rights and of solidarity between all
men and nations.
As an Organization that is most outspoken in its opposition to any
form of discrimination, Unesco cannot fail to advocate the fullest
possible integration of disabled persons into society, with full ac¬
count being taken of the specific details of each individual case. We
should set our face firmly against compartmentalization, for if the
"right to be different/ ' is wrongly interpreted, it may turn into de
facto segregation, whereas the real aim is to achieve the opposite.
This is why "specialized" help should be given to parents, both in
their present and in their future plans, in a manner consonant with
the gravity and degree of irreversibility of the disablement affecting
their children. This is why priority must be given to helping the fami¬
ly, since, in most cases, no other school or place of training or in¬
stitution can or should replace it. This is why disabled persons must
be helped and educated in every possible way. This is why it is
necessary to assist and train specialist teachers, as well as those
who can make any kind of contribution to the integration process.
Last but not least, this is why society and all its members must be
"specially educated", so that they can facilitate integration and,
with courage and respect for human solidarity, can narrow down the
"differentness" and "dependence".
If the International Year of Disabled Persons is primarily a year for
the completest possible integration of every individual disabled per¬
son, it will also herald a new, clearsighted approach to an issue that
is of the deepest concern to us all.
At its recent General Conference in Belgrade, Unesco unanimous¬
ly adopted a resolution inviting its Member States to devote special
attention to establishing and implementing all measures that could
benefit disabled persons. Countries from every corner of the earth
and at every level of development voiced, through their represen¬
tatives, their profound commitment to the problems of disabled per¬
sons. The action which some of them have already decided to take,
or are planning, gives additional cause for hope.
On the threshold of 1981, deeds not words are called for if that
hope is not to prove a disappointment to those who are so much in
need of encouragement.
Federico Mayor
"A handicap is not simply the corollary of a disa¬
bility, it is also in part imposed by society. Fur¬
thermore, the definition of a handicap varies
according to a country's culture, traditions and
level of development. In a rich country a blind
person can, for example, obtain a complete edu¬
cation giving access to a profession, whereas in
most developing countries he or she may not
have access to education; such a person would
be handicapped not only by a disability, he or
she would have an additional handicap imposed
by the social and economic conditions in his or
her country. One of the major objectives of the
International Year of Disabled Persons is preci¬
sely to encourage governments to eliminate pro¬
gressively all such forms of handicap, of which
disabled persons are the victims."
Zala Lusibu N'Kanza
Executive Secretary
for the International Year of Disabled Persons
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
*
(y)The
United Nations
Declaration
on the Rights of Disabled Persons
THE GENERAL ASSEMBLY
MINDFUL of the pledge made by Member States, under the
Charter of the United Nations, to take joint and separate action in
co-operation with the Organization to promote higher standards of
living, full employment and conditions of economic and social pro¬
gress and development,
REAFFIRMING its faith in human rights and fundamental
freedoms and in the principles ofpeace, of the dignity and worth of
the human person and of social justice proclaimed in the Charter,
RECALLING the principles of the Universal Declaration of Human
Rights, the International Covenants on Human Rights, the Declara¬
tion of the Rights of the Child and the Declaration on the Rights of
Mentally Retarded Persons, as well as the standards already set for
social progress in the constitutions, conventions, recommendations
and resolutions of the International Labour Organisation, the United
Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization, the World
Health Organization, the United Nations Children's Fund and other
organizations concerned.
RECALLING ALSO Economic and Social Council resolution 1921
(LVIII) of 6 May 1975 on the prevention of disability and the
rehabilitation of disabled persons,
EMPHASIZING that the Declaration on Social Progress and
Development has proclaimed the necessity of protecting the rights
and assuring the welfare and rehabilitation of the physically and
mentally disadvantaged,
BEARING IN MIND the necessity ofpreventing physical and men¬
tal disabilities and of assisting disabled persons to develop their
abilities in the most varied fields of activities and of promoting their
integration as far as possible in normal life,
AWARE that certain countries, at their present stage of develop¬
ment, can devote only limited efforts to this end,
PROCLAIMS this Declaration on the Rights of Disabled Persons
and calls for nationaland international action to ensure that it will be
used as a common basis and frame of reference for the protection
of these rights:
1 . The term "disabled person" means any
person unable to ensure by himself or
herself, wholly or partly, the necessities of a
normal individual and/or social life, as a
result of a deficiency, either congenital or
not, in his or her physical or mental
capabilities.
2. Disabled persons shall enjoy all the
rights set forth in this Declaration. These
rights shall be granted to all disabled per¬
sons without any exception whatsoever and
without distinction or discrimination on the
basis of race, colour, sex, language,
religion, political or other opinions, national
or social origin, state of wealth, birth or any
other situation applying either to the dis¬
abled person himself or herself or to his or
her family.
3. Disabled persons have the inherent
right to respect for their human dignity.
Disabled persons, whatever the origin,
nature and seriousness of their handicaps
and disabilities, have the same fundamental
rights as their fellow-citizens of the same
age, which implies first and foremost the
right to enjoy a decent life, as normal and
full as possible.
4. Disabled persons have the same civil
and political rights as other human beings;
paragraph 7 of the Declaration on the Rights
of Mentally Retarded Persons applies to any
possible limitation or suppression of those
rights for mentally disabled persons.
5. Disabled persons are entitled to the
measures designed to enable them to
become as self-reliant as possible.
6. Disabled persons have the right to
medical, psychological and functional treat¬
ment, including prosthetic and orthetic ap¬
pliances, to medical and social rehabilita¬
tion, education, vocational training and
rehabilitation, aid, counselling, placement
services and other services which will enable
hem to develop their capabilities and skills to
the maximum and will hasten the process of
their social integration or reintegration.
7. Disabled persons have the right to
economic and social security and to a de¬
cent level of living. They have the right, ac¬
cording to their capabilities, to secure and
retain employment or to engage in a useful,
productive and remunerative occupation
and to join trade unions.
8. Disabled persons are entitled to have
their special needs taken into consideration
at all stages of economic and social
planning.
9. Disabled persons have the right to live
with their families or with foster parents and
to participate in all social, creative or recrea¬
tional activities. No disabled person shall be
subjected, as far as his or her residence is
concerned, to differential treatment other
than that required by his or her condition or
by the improvement which he or she may
derive therefrom. If the stay of a disabled
person in a specialized establishment is in¬
dispensable, the environment and living
conditions therein shall be as close as pos¬
sible to those of the normal life of a person
of his or her age.
10. Disabled persons shall be protected
against all exploitation, all regulations and all
treatment of a discriminatory, abusive or
degrading nature.
1 1 . Disabled persons shall be able to avail
themselves of qualified legal aid when such
aid proves indispensable for the protection
of their persons and property. If judicial pro¬
ceedings are instituted against them, the
legal procedure applied shall take their
physical and mental condition fully into
account.
12. Organizations of disabled persons
may be usefully consulted in all matters
regarding the rights of disabled persons.
13. Disabled persons, their families and
communities shall be fully informed, by all
appropriate means of the rights contained in
this Declaration.
Resolution 3447
Thirtieth session, 2433rd plenary meeting
9 December 1975
7
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
feeling free
The television series Feeling Free was created by the Workshop on
Children's Awareness, a division of the American Institutes for
Research, Cambridge, Massachusetts. The photographs, by Alan
Bnghtman, and the quotes from Holhs, Laurie and Gmny
reproduced on these pages are © The American Institutes for
Research, Cambridge, Massachusetts, U.S.A.
HOLLIS
My disability is called cerebral palsy,
and I was born with it. There are
different kinds of cerebral palsy. With
the kind I have, the brain messages
come down to the legs a little bit
slower than they usually would in a
physically fit person's body. My legs
are limited in what they're able to do.
For example, when my friends are
walking somewhere, I can usually
keep up, but when they run they leave
me behind. That's OK with me though.
I don't really care how fast the others
go. I just go at my own pace.
Sometimes, when I'm walking down
the street, people stare at me and ask
me questions.
I really do like it better when people
ask me questions instead ofjust sitting
there staring at me or talking about
me behind my back. I figure they
might just as well ask the question
instead of keeping it in their head.
Otherwise, how are they going to get
an answer? And when they do ask, it
gives me a chance to say, "Listen, you
can do things I can't do, and I can do
things you can't do. "
One thing that helps me an awful lot
is getting encouragement from my
family and my friends. It helps to keep
me on my feet.
I do have a lot of handicapped
friends, but I like being friends with
people who aren't handicapped, too.
My friends don't look at my handicap
as much as my personality, and I really
like them to do that. If I can keep
making other people do that, I figure
everything will be better.
I think everybody has problems...
not just people with handicaps. I figure
everybody should work with their
problems andjust think of a way to
solve them. If that doesn't work, they
should just keep trying, and if
everything doesn't work they should
just complain a little bit. Then, after
they complain, they should try it again.
GINNY
When I was a baby, I looked like any
other baby, but when I was about
three or four years old, they found out
I was a dwarf. At first they thought I
was just a short girl, but then the
doctors took some X-rays and they
could tell for sure.
A dwarf is a person whose bones
don't grow as fast as everybody else's.
In fact, they grow much slower. That
means that my arms and legs are
shorter, but all of my insides are the
same as any other twelve year old's
insides... my heart and my liver and all
that junk.
Sometimes it's really hard to be
small; there are certain things that are
just much more difficult for me to do.
It's hard to reach things that are too
high, it's hard to run very fast, and it's
hard to walk in places where you have
to keep going for a long time, like
zoos and parks and shopping centres.
The hardest thing about being a
dwarf is when people tease me and
stare at me.
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Feeling Free is the title of an award-winning American television series that
introduced children to their disabled peers. Its aim was to help schoolchildren
feel free with their handicapped colleagues and make friends with them, to
create a climate in which candid questions could be asked and discussions
could take place, and to help disabled children to feel free to be themselves
within the school environment. The programme enabled children from all
over the United States to put questions about disabilities to those best able to
answer them the handicapped children themselves. It attempted to give
some insight into what it is like to be blind, deaf, retarded or physically han¬
dicapped. On these pages we introduce Hollis, Laurie and Ginny, three of the
children who appeared on the programme and who were willing to answer
questions about what it means to be disabled, to speak about their likes and
dislikes, their fears and joys, and about not only what makes them different
but also what makes them like everybody else.
If people would realize that dwarfs
are people too, it would make It a lot
easier to be small.
People are just people, and all those
things that make us different don't
really matter. It's friends that matter,
just sharing things with them... being
with them.
My friends and I have such a good
time doing things that we forget about
each other's sizes and shapes and
freckles and fatness and skinniness
and all those things that are different
about each other. A difference doesn't
matter so much when you're with
friends.
One thing's for sure: I don't want
special attention. It's really lousy when
people try to baby me or carry me or
something like that. I don't want
anyone to think they have to take care
of me like that, because I'm old
enough to take care of myself. And
I'm pretty good at it, too.
LAURIE
It's funny, you know, but I don't like
to consider myself handicapped. I have
as many friends as anyone else, I go to
public school just like anybody else... I
don't think of myself as being so
different.
I guess I'm just like most 14-year-old
girls. I like to do all the same things,
but it's just that sometimes I have to
learn my own way of doing them.
Before I went totally blind, I used to
think that if you couldn't see, you
wouldn't be able to do anything on
your own. All I could think about was
a little man on a street corner holding
a tin cup. I never thought of a blind
person being able to go to school or
take a bus or do almost anything. I
guess that's the way most people
think about It.
You want to know what makes me
really uncomfortable? Every once in a
while there are these people who
come up to me and don't say
anything. They keep real quiet and just
look at me. It's as if they're going to
find the answers or something all over
my face.
I guess people stare because they
just don't understand what being blind
is all about. I guess they have
questions that they don't know how to
ask.
Another thing that really aggravates
me is when people talk about me as if
I weren't there. I can't even describe
how angry that makes me. Like
sometimes someone will ask my
mother, "And how's Laurie?" ...and, I
mean, I'm standing right there. I'm not
invisible.
Confidence is maybe the most
Important thing to have. It makes me
remember that I'm me, so that I don't
have to keep worrying about what
other people are going to think. If you
have confidence, then it doesn't really
matter much what people think.
Now I'm beginning to realize that
I'm my own person, and that the way I
dress and the friends I have and the
things I like to do are just different.
They're not better or worse... they're
just different.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
The courage
to take risks
by Edward V. Roberts
EDWARD V. ROBERTS, who has been a
quadriplegic (paralyzed in both arms and both
legs) since 1953, directs California's Department
of Rehabilitation from a wheel- chair with an at¬
tached respirator. Under his leadership the
Depanment has become the principal state agen¬
cy providing services for disabled people.
ONLY a few years ago people like my¬
self were considered objects of
charity. In many ways we were
lucky if we obtained the kinds of services we
needed to become part of the mainstream.
I remember the attitudes that I faced at
fourteen years of age, when, in about four
days, I changed from an aspiring athlete to a
helpless cripple. We know how devastating
that can be for individuals and for their
parents who cannot know the future. I look
back to the time when my greatest fear was
what would happen when my parents died.
Their greatest fear was exactly the same
thing. I remember the doctors telling my
Himself confined to a wheelchair, a
Japanese worker welds wheelchair
frames in a productive, semi-sheltered
workshop at Beppu City, Japan.
Disability
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
mother that I would be nothing more than a
vegetable.
We know that disability is not the over¬
riding factor, but instead it is a motivation; it
is believing in yourself and having people
around you believe in you; with teachers
who know that if they have the right kind of
skills and knowledge and a basic belief in
you, nothing is going to stop you. No bar¬
rier, whether it is a ramp to get on to the
podium, a communication barrier for a deaf
person, reading for a blind person, or a
barrier imposed by attitudes about people
who are labelled retarded, can stop that
motivation.
In terms of my own development, one of
the things that helped me the most was that
I was not segregated. My community did
not have a separate school for the disabled.
They had to figure out a way to get me from
my bed as a literal shut-in to begin my
education again. I had to overcome the fear
of going out and having people stare at me
because I was different.
Then in my senior year of high school, I
discovered it is not too bad to have people
stare at you. You can take it in a negative
way, or a positive way. In a negative way,
you can say a person is weird or different; in
a positive way, you can be a celebrity. You
might as well take it in a positive way or you
will remain a shut-in. There were people
around me who encouraged me to begin to
come out. They cajoled me in a way. From
that time, I was beginning to recognize that I
had some choices, and that to get anything,
I had to learn how to take risks.
Risk taking is something that too many
young people with disabilities are sheltered
from, for a variety of reasons. Young people
with disabilities often do not learn how to
take that next risk. I remember when I was
at the University of California in Berkeley
and I fell in love. It became incredibly in¬
convenient to have to take an attendant with
me everywhere. I had been told for years
that I could not drive a power wheelchair,
that I was too severely disabled. But I decid¬
ed to take the risk because I had a lot at
stake. At the beginning, I had some crashes
but then I learned how, with some help, to
make it work for me.
We have moved a long way in the last
twenty to thirty years. We recognize that
people have limits, but that we cannot
define those limits per person. If there is
anything I have learned about in my own
life, it is this whole issue of limits. So many
times I was told that I could not do this or
that. I was even rejected by the very depart¬
ment I now direct. I was told that I was too
disabled to work.
It is important that we work together to
help society understand the vast potential of
people with all kinds of disabilities. I myself
strongly reject the idea of a hierarchy of
disabilities, where a person with a disability
who can "pass as normal" is considered
more socially acceptable than a person who
is visibly "different". We all have potential
and the right to fulfil that potential.
I have devoted much of my life to en¬
couraging the coalition of people with
disabilities and I am convinced that together
we can be an incredibly powerful force for
change. We know that a disability is not so
terrible but we also know that the fears,
ignorance and isolation that often accom¬
pany a disability are terrible. Each of us can
serve as a role model for others. My courage
can help a person with a very different
disability take control of his or her own life.
We can also enrich one another's life. Here
I'm reminded of my friends, Dennis Santine
and Bob Metz, who enjoy rafting down the
wild white waters of the Stanislaus River in
California. Dennis is blind and Bob is a
quadriplegic but that doesn't stop them.
They share their strengths and both benefit
from it.
If there is one message that I leave with
you, I would like it to be how much we all
share in the problem of attitudes. The at-
titudinal barriers that prevent a quadriplegic
from living a life of purpose and value also
isolate and degrade a person with other
special needs. We are in this together. The
stereotype connected with one disability im¬
pacts on the life of a person with a totally
different disability. We can only change all
that by working together.
Concentration and determination at the
1980 Olympic Games for the
Handicapped at Arnhem, Netherlands.
Fu Yuchuu, a high school student at
Qiogdac, China, cannot walk, but her
friends make sure that she never misses
school or the fun of leisure activities.
is not the overriding factor, instead it is a motivation'
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Seeing with my hands
by Olga Skorokhodova
Text copyright © reproduction prohibited
Poet and essayist Olga Skorokhodova is both blind and deaf.
She was born in 1914 at a village in southern Ukraine. Before
the age of five she contracted meningitis and completely lost
first her sight and then her hearing, so that her speech
became impaired. At that time she lost both her parents. In
1925, she entered the clinic for deaf, dumb and blind children
set up in Kharkov two years earlier by Professor Ivan
Sokolyansky. There her speech was restored. With the help of
special methods devised by Professor Sokolyansky and with
Braille, she was taught regular school subjects and completed
her secondary education. In 1961, she took a doctorate in
psychology and pedagogical sciences and is now the senior
research assistant at the Institute for the Handicapped of the
USSR Academy of Pedagogical Sciences in Moscow. Her
book How I Perceive, Imagine and Understand the World
Around Me, from which the extract below is taken, was
published in Moscow in 1972 and has been translated into
many languages.
PEOPLE with normal sight who are not familiar with the blind
frequently ask me questions such as: "Who chooses the style
and colour of your clothes? Who advises you to buy one dress
rather than another? Who sees to the decoration of your room and
decides on the arrangement of the furniture? Why are these objects
placed here rather than there?"
When I reply that I choose almost everything myself, they look
very surprised, so I am told, and often incredulous. Yet it is true.
For example, when I go into a shop to buy a ready-made dress, I
examine it and I am able to tell immediately if I like the style and if the
dress will fall well. I feel all this with my hands and know at once if a
dress suits me. As for the colour, I naturally have to rely on the ad¬
vice of sighted people.
Sometimes the friends who are with me will say that the colour of
a dress or a coat and skirt is attractive and that I look well in it. But if
I feel that it does not suit me as well as they say it does, that it is too
wide or too narrow, too short or too long, I do not buy it.
During my life I have often had to move house and, on each occa¬
sion, I arranged my room according to my taste, relying entirely on
my own judgement. This may sound banal and hardly worth men¬
tioning. And it is true that for people who can see and hear, such
small events are part and parcel of daily life and appear insignificant.
But, for me, moving rooms is a very serious matter.
A sighted person entering a room for the first time will immediate¬
ly be able to gauge its approximate length and width. And even blind
people who can hear are able to fall back on acoustics: they can tell
the approximate size of a room from the sounds and vibrations pro¬
duced by footsteps and voices.
But how does someone like myself who is not only blind but also
deaf, set about it? Since I can neither see nor hear, the only way is to
examine the whole room very carefully with my hands, in order to
discover its length and width and whether it is square or rectangular.
Then I have to find out opposite which wall or window the door is
situated. Only after a thorough examination of this kind do I really
get an idea of the room's shape and size and "see" it in my mind's
eye in relation to my furniture. Then I can decide where to put the
various pieces.
Naturally I do not visualize all the furniture at the same time but,
rather, individual pieces a chair, the table, the cupboard, bed,
sofa, etc. I do not imagine them bigger or smaller than they are in
reality, but in their normal size. And when I think of these objects, I
do not break them up into constituent parts, say, the leg of a chair,
then the seat, the back, I see the whole chair in its real size.
It would be different if I were to examine only one part of an un¬
familiar object. Not knowing what the whole of it is like, I would
have a mental picture of only that part which I had touched with my
hands.
For example, if I were to touch the tip of a stag's antlers and were
then asked: "Can you visualize the animal's general appearance and
the shape of its antlers?", I would certainly reply: "No". On the
other hand, if I touch the edge of my bed-head, I visualize the whole
bed. And once I have studied the peculiarities and distinctive
features of a particular chair, I have an exact image of that chair and
could recognize it anywhere.
So, having examined my new room and discovered its size, width
and length, I can easily arrange my furniture without the help of
sighted friends. I arrange it according to my taste following a plan I
have thought out in advance. Sometimes I do not follow the initial
plan entirely, but that is merely for the sake of convenience: to put a
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
table in the middle of the room, as many housewives do, would be
very impractical for a blind person like myself.
Since I always maintain the same order in my room and keep
things in the same place, I gradually adapt my movements to the
position of the furniture in a completely unconscious way. For in¬
stance, if I am sitting on the sofa and want to pick up a sheet of
paper or a pencil from the table, I stretch out my hand in the right
direction without a moment's hesitation. And when I need
something from the cupboard, I take exactly the number of steps
required.
Often after moving from a small room to a larger one, or the
reverse, I feel uncomfortable for the first few days. The big room
seems immensely long and I stop instinctively in the middle without
going as far as the table or the cupboard I am searching for in the
empty space around me. When the room is smaller than my old one,
I bang into the furniture at the beginning, because I imagine the
chairs and table to be further away than they actually are. But in
both cases the furniture does not seem to be larger or smaller; I see it
in my imagination in its true dimensions.
This shows, I think, that blind people's perception of the world
around them is true to lifedifferent from but not inferior to the
perception of .sighted people.
A well-meaning woman once tried to convince me that the blind
cannot perceive the true shape and volume of objects. She believed,
I can't imagine why, that they see them as larger or smaller, especial¬
ly smaller, than they are in reality. Then she said:
"If one were to put an apple and a cucumber into your hands, and
then take them away, how would you perceive them? Small or big?
Round or long?"
I told her what I felt:
"I would 'see' the apple, as an apple, not as anything else, true to
size and round, of course, with a little stalk. And I would perceive
the cucumber as a cucumber, long and narrow. Naturally, I would
never confuse it with an apple".
"But when you feel an object and then move away from it, do you
perceive an image of the entire object, or only part of it?" she asked.
"At the moment I feel your hand in mine, but I am not familiar
with your face, for I have not yet examined it. I cannot therefore im¬
agine what it is like. I know, however, that you have eyes, a nose
and a mouth, like every human being. If I touch only the tip of your
nose, I vizualize the tip, but I realize that you have a complete nose.
Let us suppose for a moment that you have masked your face or hid¬
den behind a screen, but through an oversight one eye and part of
your chin are still visible. A sighted person coming into the room by
chance would retain the image of one eye and a bit of chin, though
he would acknowledge, or course, that you have a complete face."
I do not know whether this answer satisfied my friend entirely; she
remembered to thank me for a pleasant chat but seemed a little
disturbed...
After this conversation I analysed the various mental pictures I
formed very carefully. I had to be sure I had given a correct answer
when comparing the images perceived by blind and sighted people.
All day long, I kept trying to remember various examples of percep¬
tion and representation of which I had read or been told.
I am well aware of the power of imagination. Fine, expressive
hands have sometimes led me to believe that the person I am com¬
municating with is endowed with every physical and moral quality.
But when I later discoverwith the aid of my hands that I am
mistaken, the image dissolves and all that is left is a beautiful dream.
The illusions of the imagination are as hurtful to sighted people as
they are to the blind. Sometimes emotions erode our will-power, but
reason and common sense must illuminate reality and help us to
struggle against false perceptions of the world.
Olga Skorokhodova's example has been an inspiration to
countless handicapped people in the Soviet Union and
throughout the world. The three deaf-blind scientists seen
in animated conversation below, from left to right
Georgei Gazenco, Sergei Sirotkin and Natasha Korneeva,
have followed in her footsteps. Sirotkin and Korneeva
graduated with honours from Moscow University in 1977
and are now engaged in research at scientific institutes.
Gazenco ¡s a graduate of the State Historical Archive
Institute, Moscow, and is preparing a thesis on the
history of Italy. In the USSR between 500 and 600 blind
people enter institutes of higher education every year.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
The handicap
Wá Mr F
\
i -'# i i * V
1
À
m
I
¡Li
|
«%
^ua
*
A
^
r Fr / i^r
V f v*
f
A group of enthusiastic pupils at a centre for deaf children in Yaounde, Cameroon.
NO amount of straining the imagina¬
tion can adequately convey to the
normal hearing person what it feels
like to be deaf from birth or in early
childhood. Deafness deprives the deaf in¬
dividual of the ability to enjoy, not only
music, but even more important, en¬
vironmental sounds such as those made by
singing birds, rustling wind, croaking frogs
and running streams.
Great as these deprivations are, they are
nothing to compare with language retarda¬
tion which early profound deafness imposes
upon its victim. Edna Levine, a notable
psychologist who had studied extensively
the problems of deafness, once lamented:
"Not to hear the voice is not to hear spoken
language. Not to hear spoken language
means that the proverbial child remains
in complete ignorance of this basic verbal
tool for human communication and
communion".
Lack of hearing subjects the deaf child to
learning language visually and artificially,
without first having heard it spoken. This
explains why many who were born deaf or
who became deaf early in life, are bedevilled
by language difficulties all through life.
PETER O. MBA is head of the department of
special education at the university of Ibadan,
Nigeria. He lost his hearing in an accident at the
age of twenty-five.
14
Communication problems apart, personal
experience, supported by the literature, in¬
dicates that deafness has a pervasive effect
on the total personality of the deaf person,
including his social adjustment, perception
and general motor activity. He is severely
limited in understanding the world around
him, in making himself understood, and in
making the most of his learning experiences.
Be this as it may, quite a few deaf people
have surmounted the difficulties inherent in
deafness, and have gone on to achieve
world recognition. Our world is richer today
because of the lives of deaf persons like
Beethoven, the composer, the Spanish
painter Goya, the French educator Laurent
Clerc, and Thomas Edison the inventor.
Apart from these great stars, many other
lesser lights have contributed in their various
fields of endeavour to the general enlight¬
enment and progress of humanity.
By and large, however, the number of
deaf people who have achieved renown is
infinitesimal in comparison with the millions
of illiterate unemployed and under¬
employed hearing-impaired people all over
the world especially in the developing
countries. I recently carried out a survey
which showed that less than 10 per cent of
school-age deaf children are receiving
education in the so-called "Third World",
due to widespread prejudice by the general
public, not only against the deaf, but against
disabled people in general.
There is much in the literature about the
attitude of society towards those perceived
as handicapped or different from others.
One researcher, for instance, found that a
negative attitude towards handicapped per¬
sons is widespread, even in the United
States a country widely acclaimed as one
of the most advanced in the world, in terms
of services which it provides for its disabled
citizens.
Die-hard myths and superstitious beliefs
about causes of disabilities buttress negative
attitudes and determine the way a handicap¬
ped person is perceived and treated, even in
his own family circle. In a recent study of at¬
titudes towards the deaf, I noted that in
parts of East Africa, a congenitally deaf child
is believed to be obeying an injunction by a
god who had warned him not to divulge
some secrets confided to him. To avoid
possible risks, the child opted to be born
"deaf and dumb". This, in turn, provided a
good cause why other people should have
little to do with him. A similar belief in some
parts of Nigeria explains deafness in terms
of adherence to the adage : "Once bitten,
twice shy". A child's soul coming back to in¬
carnation chooses to be deaf because in the
preceding life he had listened to everyone
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
of prejudice
by Peter O. Mba
Dance can play a role in the education of the deaf and in their
integration into society. As well as providing a means of self-
expression, it may help them to develop physical balance and
communication skills, and contribute to their intellectual and
psychological fulfilment. Photo shows a young deaf dancer
communicating in sign language while warming up. She is a
student at Gallaudet College (USA), an institution for the deaf
whose dance group has a world-wide reputation.
Photo © Gallaudet College, Washington, D.C.
who appealed to him, and thereby met his
untimely death.
Although education and general
enlightenment are fast changing negative at¬
titudes, one still frequently encounters acts
of cruelty to deaf persons. There have been
cases of forcing deaf youngsters to submit
to "treatment" by faith healers who very
often prescribe days of fasting. Some of
these healers even recommend corporal
punishment and self-mutilation as a form of
penance all for being "deaf and dumb".
A few years ago, a deaf girl was left to
waste away in a psychiatric ward where she
remained for four years without any ailment,
except deafness. She was later discovered
by a state rehabilitation counsellor.
In many under-developed communities
people frequently become very emotional
when confronted with deafness. Thus, they
embarrass the deaf individual and compel
him to see himself as a person of no worth,
an object of ridicule.
A couple of years ago, an expectant deaf
girl was among a group of other expectant
mothers who were waiting to see their doc¬
tor in a prenatal clinic. The deaf girl sat
quietly in a corner while the other women
carried on a lively discussion. A few minutes
later a young teacher who had taught in the
last school attended by the deaf girl,
recognized her and walked across the room
to say "Hello" to her. Soon, both were con¬
versing in the language of signs. There was
a hush in the room as the other women
stared at the two people making signs and
laughing. A minute later the women were
sobbing and dabbing their wet eyes with
handkerchiefs. One of them had explained
to the others that the girl making signs was
deaf. They could not believe it. They did not
think that a deaf girl could also be an expec¬
tant mother! Naturally, the poor girl was
greatly embarrassed at this unwarranted
display of sympathy. Incidents like this
occur in various situations in rural com¬
munities.
To conclude, my thirty years experience
as a deaf man who lost his hearing at the
age of twenty-five has taught me so much
about the humiliations, misunderstandings,
denial of human rights and lack of empathy
which deafness frequently brings upon the
deaf, that I have come to believe that the
crucial factors in deciding whether or not a
deaf person will live a successful life are
the prevaliling attitudes at home and in the
society in which the lives.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
When
social stress
proves
too strong
Social factors are related to the occurrence of mental
illness in a number of ways. It often happens that social
events or conditions are largely responsible for precipi¬
tating a mental illness, while social conditions may
combine with psychological or biological factors to
predispose an individual to illness. As the sociologist
would put it, the cultural environment and the changes
in it certainly affect the prevalence of mental illness in
a community and in the social groups composing it.
Social factors can also influence the course and out¬
come of a mental illness, since the effectiveness of
treatment will depend largely on the social context in
which it is provided. Moreover, retraining and rehabili¬
tation programmes are necessarily designed to meet
social objectives. Cultural attitudes and beliefs also
play a part in defining who in a society is to be labelled
mentally ill, in the process by which a person is rec¬
ognized as needing treatment, and in the decision
whether or not he is to be referred to the psychiatric
services; they also influence the scope and the type of
psychiatric services that society provides.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
7 am so afraid
they will laugh at me'
by Barbro Lundahl
ANNA is a mentally retarded woman
in her thirties. She went to school
under the system of special educa¬
tion for the mentally retarded. After leaving
school she tried to work on the open labour
market but was forced to give up when she
found she could not cope with the
demands. At present she is living with her
boyfriend and taking care of the household.
The dialogue below is from a conversation
with psychologist Barbro Lundahl in which
Anna tells how she experiences her han¬
dicap, of how she is ashamed and afraid,
and how she feels herself to be on the
' outside.
Anna: To be retarded is to be not well...
When something is wrory in the head...
When a person can't do as much as other
people... like graduate from high school or
work in a hospital like others do. Things go
slower for the retarded... But maybe that's
why I'm retarded... Because tr&re's
something wrong in my head?
Barbro: Who has told you that you are
retarded?
Anna: My mother said that I'm a little
retarded, and... I'm not like other people.
Barbro: In what way are you not like other
people?
Anna: Everything goes so slowly for me, I
move so slowly, I forget things, and when I
talk, it sounds funny and no one
understands what I say. I think they don't
understand me because I'm not like other
people... That I'm a kind of scapegoat.
Barbro: When was the first time you felt like
that? Can you remember?
Anna: Yes, in school. It feels bad to be
retarded. It's so depressing to be retarded. I
want to be well, like other people. Well and
happy. But I just feel unhappy.
Barbro: Is it something to be ashamed of,
being mentally retarded?
Anna: Inside of me, I think it's ugly to be
retarded... Like when people look different
from other people, or when they look sick. I
think I look different from other people
when I'm retarded.
Barbro: You mean that you must look
strange because retarded people look
strange?
Anna: No, I don't look as strange as them.
But inside me I feel strange that I'm retard¬
ed. I just want to cry, just cry.
Barbro: Have you been able to talk to
anyone other than to your mother about
being retarded?
Anna: At my job, where I worked before...
they used to say "she's cracked."
Barbro: Did they say that? How did you
feel?
Anna: Unhappy.
Barbro: Haven't you ever tried to explain
why some things are hard for you, what the
reason is?
Anna: No, I don't dare. I would feel even
dumber. Maybe I feel like that now, when I
tell you.
Barbro: What do you think I feel about
people who are retarded?
Anna: That they are like other people.
Barbro: If you think that, why would you
feel dumb when you tell me things?
Anna: I just feel like that inside me.
Barbro: What do you feel about other
retarded people? Would you rather be with
them or with other people?
Anna: I want to be with normal people.
Listen. . . can I ask you about something? We
who are taking this course... are we all
retarded?
Barbro: Yes, more or less. It wouldn't be
right to call all of those taking this course
retarded, but every person here has had dif¬
ficulties in school. You think a lot about your
boyfriend... Was that what you wanted to
know... if he's retarded? Is that important
for you?
Anna: That's not so important. But I don't
dare tell him I'm retarded. He might want to
break up.
Barbro: Do you really believe that? Don't
you think he has understood that ifs hard
for you to do certain things and that he likes
you anyway? This being retarded... it's only
one part of a whole person. You have so
much more you can feel things and show
what you feel. And you can do lots of dif¬
ferent things. It's on/y a few things which
are hard for you to do. You're worth just as
much as a person as anyone else.
Anna: Yes, but I don't want to be retarded.
I want to be well. My sisters aren't retarded.
Barbro: No, they have hada little more luck
in life than you have... You say that you
aren't well. Have you ever wondered if there
is a medicine that retarded people can take
and be well?
Anna: Yes, but that wouldn't work, ifs too
late. Can you see I'm retarded?
Barbro: That is a hard question to answer.
But I don't think it shows on you. I think you
look like most other people.
Anna: But here, inside my head?
Comments: Anna is deeply unhappy over
her mental retardation, which she ex¬
periences as shameful and unattractive. She
dare not talk about it and expects no
understanding from those around her. Thus,
it is natural that she, like many other mental¬
ly handicapped persons, tries to conceal her
handicap. She mentions several times that
she believes other people can see that she is
retarded. She says that she wants to be
normal. She separates herself from other
mentally retarded people when she speaks
of them both as "they" and "we".
Anna needs much support and help in
learning to accept and stand up for herself.
It has been my experience that this is com¬
mon among adult mentally retarded people.
They must be given opportunities to talk
about themselves and their situation in an
atmosphere where they dare bring forth all
their ideas and questions. They must
understand that they are not suffering from
some shameful disease which cannot be
talked about.
They need to know which of those dif¬
ficulties they experience are due to mental
retardation, and which are due to
discrimination experienced in social con¬
tacts, both official and informal. We who
work with the mentally handicapped must
seek out their opinions and then respect
those opinions, rather than present patent
solutions to their problems.
We must learn to listen with a sensitive
ear and be open and honest in our contacts.
Only then can we expect the mentally
handicapped to be able to express their own
wishes for their lives, to set goals and to
take the responsibility necessary to realize
those goals.
BARBRO LUNDAHL is a Swedish psychologist
with many years experience of working with the
mentally retarded. She is the author of a book on
psychology specially written for use by the men¬
tally retarded.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Photo Michel Claude - Unesco
The world
at our fingertips
Have you a friend who is blind? If so,
take out this Braille text and give it to
him or her. It contains the following mes¬
sage, printed in English, French and
Spanish Braille:
"Unesco Braille Courier published in
English, French, and Spanish by the Uni¬
ted Nations Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization, 7 Place de Fonte¬
noy, 75700 Paris, France, Telephone 577
16 10. This free, quarterly magazine for
the blind contains articles specially selec¬
ted from the Unesco Courier on all
aspects of education, science, culture
and communication. Requests for copies
should be sent to the Editor-in-chief at
the above address. "
Sighted persons who may wish to read
the text should refer to the Braille alpha¬
bet reproduced on page 23. The English
text of the message covers the whole of
the first of the 4 Braille pages (page 19 of
the magazine). Braille reads from left to
right, but since for production reasons
these pages have been inserted side¬
ways, to read the English text you must
first turn the magazine Topen at page 18-
19) round longwise so that the "top" of
the ink-printed pages is to your left. The
top line of embossed dots, running paral¬
lel to the serrated outside edge of the
page, shows where the text begins.
The Unesco Braille Courier
by Frederick H. Potter
FREDERICK H. POTTER, who is himself blind,
is Managing Editor of the Braille edition of the
Unesco Courier.
AT the time of Unesco's first involve¬
ment with visually handicapped
people in 1949, when the Govern¬
ment of India requested the Organization's
assistance to bring order to replace the
chaos of the multifarious, unrelated adapta¬
tions of the Braille system in many coun¬
tries prospects for most of them of
receiving suitable education and vocational
training were poor.
Unesco's response was to establish a
World Braille Uniformity Programme which,
by the end of 1953, had achieved recognized
success. It was, though few seemed to ap¬
preciate it at the time, a fine example of
what can be accomplished when people of
different languages and cultures work
together for the common good. Not only
was agreement reached on literary codes, so
that blind people throughout the world
might read the same Braille books, learn
foreign languages through Braille, exchange
ideas and experiences in Braille letters, but
important progress was made on the use of
the embossed script in music and science
notations.
There followed the launching of the
World Braille Council, which was to enable
all other Braille matters to be discussed at an
international level. World Braille Usage, an
important reference book for those involved
in Braille printing, improving Braille codes
and creating new ones in developing coun-
18
tries, was published by Unesco in 1953, and
an up-to-date edition will appear this year. A
new publication, Working with Braille, will
also become available in 1981. These in¬
itiatives aroused great interest in Unesco
among people who could not read our
magazines and pamphlets through lack of
sight, and, as the years passed, this interest
intensified in proportion to the growth of
Unesco's activities. Many inquiries were
received from the visually handicapped
about the Organization's aims, history, and
programme, but when told that there was
no documentation in Braille, they felt ex¬
cluded and wondered about the "right to
information".
I remember most vividly that spring day in
1974, when an advance copy of Unesco's
first publication for the blind arrived from
the printer, and how my admiring fingers
caressed those beautiful, neat Braille
characters. It was a general pamphlet on
Unesco in English, French, and Spanish,
containing the answers to all those ques¬
tions which had been addressed to us. This
was a big stride forward, and two years later
appeared issue number one of the six-
monthly magazine, the Unesco Braille
Review, composed of articles from different
Unesco periodicals.
Red Thread Riddles, a fun-book for blind
and sighted children from six to ten years of
CONTINUED PAGE 24
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
-" "" *
*f A * *
#i JSk. ' We-
1
ibih.
juutajjufaju. jglHÖOII'1 J
I
^ "
¿1
'"nMHIflfllIlllù&H&l11 jdulHflSSSSiiS&^,,''V «ÑyVJnnV^'
. i3iF np^ w . ' flp" MBrii'
n
V
I Til
..-.«¡P'''
l* .joJflMWu^Jfl
fiftf' iiy»
'"ï
tflfiSßBft*' **
r S
J
*
j». juuUuiV'- .. ..
/'
lui
W
^teL"..
:I
jihhh, jiuuuiiwníiy "^""
v" jlDKCar^ juyOOr^wtl sor
JuflWgglflj¡5 í
V w
.»jmiiu, "'htau?'1 ..iMiA."'
*''lw"»*'*«!«' m/\.'
V jf
' ^wy^issy 4¡¡¡¡¡]^fl¡¡Kf' .-¿¡¡¡¡¡¡WMf
t *"ï P H í I / í * cl '- '" *"
f'lrittfflffli&p ""
RED THREAD
RfDDLES
Braille is a ende oí small
raised dots un pai.'e( that iifti*
he read by touch. Named
«iftur its invento), the blind
Frenchman Louis Braille
Í 1809- 1852). ti->e system i s
based on s "oeii" or six dots
which can t>« arranged in
various oombinatioiis to
represent different ¡otters
and sounds {see article page
26!. Ahovs risjfit, the Braille
aiphîuiîfît n s ¡jfesentsd in Red
Thread Riddles, a book I ut of
i í't i.ï« n to i.j s wOfd pij ifi \¿"i
wi-iifih Unesco hsiped te
produce. The nouelty oí the
book, fciy Virginia Alian
Jensen and Pally Ed man. ¡s
that i!, is aimed at an
aijrfienr:« of both visually
handicapped and sighted
children. The text is in both
Braille ¡¡nd ink print, witli
embossed illustrations in
colour. Right, an illustration
of a page from Red Threat!
Riddles i s e a " 8 (¡íik s í"í elf"
ps ge 38i.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 18
age, was produced as part of Unesco's In¬
ternational Year of the Child Programme in
1979. The text, consisting of word puzzles,
is in ordinary print and in Braille; the simple
illustrations are embossed and in colour. In a
class of children who can see and others
who can not, it shows the former exactly
what Braille is and how it is used, and the
latter acquire greater self-confidence
through being placed on a par with their
fellows where this book is concerned.
It follows the current trend towards in¬
tegrating the visually handicapped child into
the ordinary education system, rather than
providing him with the traditional, separate
form of instruction in specialized institu¬
tions. In the past, after the completion of
studies in such a sheltered environment, the
emergence into the hurly-burly of the
workaday world caused many young blind
people serious problems of re-adjustment.
Red Thread Riddles has also been a boon to
blind mothers with young, sighted children,
for it is usually the first book they have ever
been able to read together. Only an English
version is available at present, but it is hoped
that adaptations in other languages will be
produced later this year.
In March 1980, the six-monthly Unesco
Braille Review became the quarterly Unesco
Braille Courier (most of the Review's
material had come from the Unesco
Courier). It is published in English, French,
and Spanish, at the moment, but plans are
afoot for the production of other language
versions. English and Spanish editions are
printed in Grade 2 (contracted) and Grade 1
(uncontracted) Braille respectively, while the
French edition is in both uncontracted and
contracted Braille. Care should, therefore,
be taken to state which form is required
when requesting French copies: people who
can read intégral may find abrégé quite
beyond them.
The decision to make no charge for the
Braille magazine remains unaltered. The ma¬
jority of non-sighted people live in develop¬
ing countries: they are usually very poor and
cannot afford to pay for a Braille publica¬
tion. Thus, being available to all who can
read it, the Unesco Braille Courier is an in¬
centive for blind people to become literate,
which helps open up to the road to educa¬
tion and the possibility of a higher standard
of living. That so few of the 70 million
sightless people in the world today are able
to read Braille, is one of the most challeng¬
ing facts for Governments to ponder over
during this International Year of Disabled
Persons. Illiteracy is so much more prevalent
among the blind than among the sighted
because, when budgetary allocations are
made in many countries, little attention is
given to the educational needs of the
former.
Publication of the Unesco Braille Courier,
the only Braille magazine produced by the
United Nations system, makes available to
blind people, for the first time, all the
resources of a major international magazine
published in twenty-five different language
editions, thus placing them on an equal
footing with the estimated million and more
sighted readers of the Unesco Courier.
It contains articles of general appeal
which reflect current trends of thought and
action in Unesco on world problems, articles
describing peoples and their living condi¬
tions in different lands, a wide variety of
cultures, and physical features in various
regions of the world. Of course, the special
interests of our readers are taken into ac¬
count by the selection of material on sub¬
jects such as all forms of music, scientific
and technological advances which may have
some application to the improvement of ap¬
paratus or services for the visually disabled,
innovations in special education, etc. Ar¬
ticles must not be too long, for, when
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
transcribed, one page of ordinary print
becomes three or four pages in Braille.
To judge from letters we have received,
this publication is the most popular Unesco
achievement to date among people who
cannot see. "It is a new light in our
darkness", wrote a young man in an African
country. One of our printers said that he and
his staff always enjoyed working on it,
"because the articles are so different from
those usually published in Braille."
Increased longevity in industrial countries
over the past thirty years has changed the
average age of sightless members of their
populations; more than half of them now
lose their sight after the age of fifty, a time
of life when it is difficult to acquire the sen¬
sitive touch necessary for reading Braille
with one's fingers. To solve this problem,
recording our magazine on cassette is a
possible future development. In whatever
form it is received, it is hoped that the
Unesco Braille Courier will continue to help
satisfy that hunger for information and
knowledge which is just as acute among
blind people as among any other members
of society.
Frederick H. Potter
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Louis Braille
A touch
of genius
by Serge Guillemet
THOUGH blind people in France enjoyed
certain privileges during the Middle
Ages, their situation was generally
very precarious. Their main activity was beg¬
ging and the highways and byways were full
of desperately poor blind men and women,
drifting wretchedly from place to place.
They were a frightening sight with their dull,
expressionless eyes, ill-assured gait and
torn, dirty clothes.
The second half of the eighteenth century
was marked by humanitarian trends. Valen¬
tin Haiiy, a young civil servant, was moved
and deeply disturbed by the plight of the
blind in the community, the state of
dependency and inferiority in which they
were kept and their consequent lack of self-
respect. He was particularly outraged in
1771 at the way they were exploited at
fairs made to wear cardboard spectacles
and perform discordant tunes on broken-
down musical instruments with the scores
turned upside down. It was then that he
decided to devote his life to improving the
lot of the blind and he became their first
teacher.
His school the Royal Institution for the
Blind was established in 1784 and Haüyset
about teaching the sightless to read by
printing in relief ordinary letters of the
alphabet, much enlarged and stylized. These
early books for the blind were few in
number, cumbersome and very expensive.
Yet the letters and words painstakingly
deciphered by sightless students who could
not yet write, awakened in them an im¬
mense thirst for knowledge. Valentin Haiiy
had created the climate necessary for further
research and paved the way for a new leap
forward.
SERGE GUILLEMET, who is himself blind, is
director of studies at the National Institute for
Young Blind Persons, Paris. From 1975 to 1978 he
was inspector of education at the French Ministry
of Health. The co-author of a noted study on the
education of blind, visually handicapped and
deaf-blind children and adolescents, he has taken
part in many radio broadcasts both in France and
abroad.
This was to be the work of a remarkable
man, Louis Braille, who lost his sight as the
result of a stupid accident. The son of a
saddler, he was born on 4 January 1809 at
Coupvray, a small village to the east of Paris.
As soon as he was able to walk, the boy
used to spend his days in his father's
workshop, playing with pieces of leather he
found there. One day, when he was three
years old, the knife he was handling slipped
and entered his eye. The infection which
developed soon spread to the second eye
and, by the time he was five, Louis was
completely blind.
His family, however, refused to give up
the struggle. They wanted the boy to be
given an education and every possible op¬
portunity to develop. So Louis was sent to
the village school where his lively in¬
telligence and excellent memory enabled
him to make good progress. Far from being
a passive pupil and an object of pity he took
an active part in the work of the class along
with his sighted school fellows. His father
taught him to read by hammering nails into a
plank to form the letters of the alphabet.
The village schoolmaster, however, decid¬
ed that Louis deserved to be given special
training and, in 1814, at the age of ten, he
was sent to the Royal Institution for the
Blind, in Paris. The school, at that time, was
housed in damp, cramped and very
unhealthy premises (and many of the blind
students, including Louis Braille himself,
later developed tuberculosis).
The new pupil showed himself to be ex¬
ceptionally gifted.
In 1821, a former captain of artillery,
Charles-Marie Barbier de la Serre
demonstrated to the blind students a system
of "sound" or "night-writing" which he had
developed to enable soldiers in the field to
communicate with one another during the
hours of darkness. It was a phonetic system
of raised dots in which the different sounds
were represented by two columns of six
dots.
Young Braille (he was then only twelve
years old) was not satisfied with Barbier's
system: there were too many dots, no spell¬
ing was required, and there were no accents
or symbols for mathematical and musical
notation. But the idea of using raised dots
had been born. It was to develop in Louis
Braille's mind as a means of freeing his
fellow-students from the drudgery of a very
limited system of education.
He continued to attend school regularly in
the daytime, but spent the evenings working
out and experimenting with a more effective
system of reading and writing for the blind.
During the summer holidays which he spent
with his family in his beloved Coupvray, the
peasants would often meet him sitting by
the roadside, busily "pricking away" at a
thick sheet of paper.
Louis was not yet sixteen when, at the
end of 1824, he came up with an idea of
genius an alphabetic code based on the
various permutations of six raised dots set
out in two parallel columns of three (See
page 23).
We all have two shoulders, two hips and
two knees. Put a raised dot on each of these
points and you get the idea of the basic let¬
ter much enlarged of Louis Braille's
system.
For the first ten letters of the Roman
alphabet: A B C D E F G H I J, the dots are
only on the shoulders and hips. The follow¬
ing ten: KLMNOPQRST, repeat the
"design" of the first ten, with an additional
dot on the left knee. The next five: U V X Y
Z, also repeat the first letters of the alphabet
but with extra dots on both knees. And
finally the last symbols: CH GH SH TH WH
ED ER OU OW and W duplicate the com¬
binations of the first ten with an additional
dot on the right knee.
Altogether sixty-three permutations are
possible with this system. The distance bet¬
ween two Braille dots is 2 or 2.5 millimetres,
and to decipher a text the reader slides his or
her fingertips along the embossed line.
In 1829, Louis Braille published a short
work presenting and explaining his system,
which he had completed by adding symbols
for punctuation and mathematical and
musical notation. The final version of his
script was published in 1837.
Braille's invention was greeted with en¬
thusiasm by his pupils and colleagues at the
Royal Institution where he was now a
teacher, and his script was immediately
adopted, for it proved far superior to the
classical system of reproducing Roman
characters in relief.
But Barbier de la Serre was jealous of the
young inventor and continued to press for
the adoption of his "sound writing", while
sighted teachers at the school still favoured
ordinary letters in relief and were reluctant
to let the blind use a different code for the
alphabet. Later other systems of relief
writing were suggested in place of Braille,
including the New York point and Moon
systems.
Despite constant ill-health and a very
heavy workload by 1818 he was teaching
geography and algebra, to which he later
added music, and had become organist at
the Paris church of Saint-Nicolas des
Champs Louis Braille continued to strug¬
gle to gain recognition and make his system
more widely known.
Gradually his script came to be adopted
throughout the world. This modest and
compassionate man all those who ap¬
proached him spoke of his kindness thus
became the benefactor of blind people
everywhere. He died on 6 January 1852 at
the Institut National des Jeunes Aveugles in
Paris aged only forty-three.
Used today for transmitting knowledge in
every field of human endeavour, the Braille
script can be mastered by scholars and sim¬
ple folk alike. Modern electronic appliances
are now available for transcribing ordinary
writing into Braille, but Louis Braille's
original code still serves its purpose.
In many countries blind children now at¬
tend school along with their sighted fellows,
and are provided with textbooks, dic¬
tionaries and other Braille materials, while
specialized libraries offer books and journals
in Braille.
Yet innumerable blind people are still
denied the opportunity of benefiting from
Louis Braille's invention. It is to be hoped
that these men and women will soon be pro¬
vided with the means of acquiring
knowledge and education so that they can
lead useful, productive lives and play an ac¬
tive role in their communities.
Louis Braille restored the dignity of the
blind as human beings. His alphabet of dots
is a star that lights their darkness.
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Unesco and the International
Year of Disabled Persons
by Nils-lvar Sundberg
FROM its earliest days. Unesco has worked
to improve education for disabled children
and young people, and in 1966 a compre¬
hensive programme was drawn up to develop co¬
operation with the United Nations and other UN
agencies such as the World Health Organization
(WHO), the International Labour Organisation
(ILO) and the United Nations Children's Fund
(UNICEF) as well as some 40 non-governmental
organizations working for handicapped people;
carry out worldwide surveys and studies on
special education for the deaf, the blind, the men¬
tally and motor handicapped; and provide
member countries, at their request, with the ser¬
vices of experts and consultants to help plan ac¬
tivities for the disabled and train their teachers.
Unesco also provides fellowships for the training
of personnel in specialized fields, supplies equip¬
ment to schools and centres for the handicapped
and supports meetings and training seminars.
Through special studies and meetings Unesco is
drawing up guidelines for member States for the
development of education for the handicapped.
Since 1968 when its special education programme
was launched, the Organization has supported
more than 200 projects in some 80 countries
around the world, from Algeria to Zaire.
Unesco has also helped organize theatre
workshops and seminars for deaf players,
published a major work on the standardization of
Braille, and established a scheme enabling
schools and institutions for the disabled, especial¬
ly in the developing countries, to buy special
equipment and material abroad.
Action in the field
Unesco plans to launch a regional project in
1981 to stimulate the creation of educational
facilities for the handicapped in the English-
speaking countries of Africa. This project, to be
financed by a $780,000 grant from the Swedish
government, will include a seminar for high-level
decision-makers and for training administrators of
special education programmes in the region, as
well as four national training seminars for
teachers of the handicapped, fellowships for
study abroad and consultancy services for coun¬
tries in the region.
Teacher training will also be stressed at the
Bahrain rehabilitation centre for handicapped
children and young people which started
operating in April 1980. The centre, set up with
Unesco/UNDP (United Nations Development
Programme) assistance, consists of three units
for educating the mentally retarded, the deaf, and
for vocational education and training. It also
receives assistance from ILO and the UN Office of
Technical Co-operation.
NILS-IVAR SUNDBERG, of Sweden, has direc¬
ted Unesco's programme of Special Education for
Handicapped Children and Young People since it
started in 1968. Formerly Director of Special Edu¬
cation in Stockholm and lecturer at the Stock¬
holm School of Education, he was for nine years
Advisory Officerat the Swedish National Board of
Education on questions of special education for
the handicapped, including teacher training and
curriculum planning.
In Syria, the activities of the Aleppo and
Damascus Institutes for the deaf are to be extend¬
ed, and two new institutes will be established at
Horns and Lattakia with Unesco/UNDP
assistance.
During IYDP, consultants in special educa¬
tion will be attached to the four Unesco Regional
Education Offices in Africa, Asia, the Arab States
and Latin America to advise Unesco member
countries on the development of educational
facilities for the disabled, and mobile teams will
carry out training seminars for teachers of the
handicapped in these regions.
Under Unesco's "Research and Human Needs"
programme, a multidisciplinary project on "re¬
quirements for the physical and mental develop¬
ment of the young child" is to be carried out in
Algeria, Italy, Portugal and Spain. The aim is to
identify and assess the nutritional, biological, en¬
vironmental and other needs of infants, young
children and lactating women and promote effec¬
tive measures to offset disease and physical and
mental deficiencies. Research will be conducted
by national teams, including biologists, nutri¬
tionists, chemists, geneticists, neurophysiologists
and sociologists. This work will be co-ordinated
by Unesco in collaboration with UN specialized
agencies such as FAO (the Food and Agriculture
Organization of the United Nations) and WHO,
and non-governmental bodies like ICRO (Interna¬
tional Cell Research Organization), IBRO (the In¬
ternational Brain Research Organization) and
IUNS (the International Union of Nutritional
Sciences).
Cultural events
A series of activities planned to encourage
participation of disabled people in cultural life and
develop their creative talents, will include theatre,
dance and music workshops, as well as training
seminars for specialist personnel. Among ideas
being discussed with organizations of the han¬
dicapped and international cultural organizations
are a workshop on music therapy for disabled
people, an exhibition on the art and culture of the
deaf, and a literary contest on the theme: the pro¬
blems faced by the handicapped.
An exhibition of posters for IYDP designed
by European artists will open at Unesco head¬
quarters early in 1981, together with a display of
photos illustrating participation of the handicap¬
ped in the life of the community in countries
around the world.
A series of special activities at the local and
regional levels is also planned by the 2,500
Unesco Clubs operating in 77 countries.
Conferences
A major international conference to be held
in Spain in November, 1981, will examine in a
global interdisciplinary context the contribution
education can make to solving the problems of
the handicapped. To be held under the patronage
of Her Majesty the Queen of Spain, who has
always taken a special interest in all problems
relating to disabled persons, this meeting will also
be attended by Mrs. Zala N'Kanza, Executive
Secretary of the International Year of Disabled
persons. It is being organized in consultation with
UN agencies and international organizations of
the disabled.
A seminar arranged in co-operation with the
United States Department of Education on the
role of parents and pre-school training in the
education of small handicapped children.
An expert meeting on the integration of
multiple and severely handicapped people into or¬
dinary and vocational education, under the joint
sponsorship of Unesco and the Federal Republic
of Germany.
A seminar on the way new attitudes to han¬
dicaps reflected in children's literature can help
the integration of disabled children into everyday
life. This meeting, to be organized with the
Bologna Children's Book Fair in March 1981, will
bring together publishers and specialists in the
education and counselling of the handicapped.
A symposium on ways of eliminating pro¬
blems that may arise from the application of
copyright to materials for the visually and hearing
handicapped. Studies on the production and
dissemination of such materials, prepared by the
World Council for the Welfare of the Blind and
the World Federation of the Deaf, will be examin¬
ed by the administrative bodies of the Universal
Copyright Convention (UCC), for which Unesco
provides the Secretariat, and the other major in¬
ternational convention, the Berne Union.
Co-action programme
Through this programme, groups and in¬
dividuals can purchase special Unum
cheques, a kind of international money order
issued by Unesco, and make a contribu¬
tion a small one to help the handicapped
in developing countries.
In 1978-79, over $130,000 were donated in this
way to special education projects in Ethiopia,
Ghana, Haiti, Lebanon, Madagascar, Malaysia
and Peru, while $46,000 went to the World Coun¬
cil for the Welfare of the Blind to help finance
their prevention programmes and buy much
needed equipment for schools for the blind in the
Third World.
Co-Action is issuing an illustrated booklet
outlining the activities and needs of schools and
centres for the handicapped in Africa, the Arab
countries, Asia and Latin America. Among the
most pressing needs are: funds to provide
medical treatment for the prevention of blindness
and finance training programmes for teachers, as
well as Braille typewriters, hearing aids for the
deaf, education toys, and equipment for pottery
and carpentry workshops.
These are some of Unesco's plans for the Inter¬
national Year of Disabled Persons. As new in¬
itiatives and activities in favour of the education
of the handicapped arise the Organization will
continue to give them its support, both during
IYDP and in the years tocóme.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
*
IV
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Disability
and the developing world
by Norman Acton
Asurvey conducted in 1963 by Rehabi¬
litation International, an interna¬
tional agency with 105 member
organizations which serves disabled persons
in sixty-five countries, produced the now
familiar estimates that there were some
450 million people in the world with signifi¬
cant disabilities, and that the number was
increasing by approximately three million per
year. Subsequent calculations by other in¬
stitutions, including the World Health
Organization, substantiate that the total is
probably in the range of the original
estimate. If the increase has been at the rate
estimated, then the total today is nearly
500 million. It can be assumed; therefore,
that at least ten per cent of any population is
likely to have been born with or to have ac¬
quired a physical, sensory or mental disabili¬
ty of sufficient impact to prevent their func¬
tioning as fully as persons of their age and
sex are expected to do in their societies.
Information about the situation in the
developing areas is the least accurate. It is
probable that the incidence is higher. While
progress in the more advanced areas has
reduced the amount of impairment caused
by diseases such as poliomyelitis and
trachoma, by malnutrition and by faulty pre¬
natal care, it has provided equivalent in¬
creases through the automobile, in¬
dustrialization, pollution, increased longevi¬
ty, diets laden with sugars and fats and
other blessings. Nevertheless, it is probable
that the conditions in the less developed
areas malnutrition, poor sanitation,
endemic and epidemic crippling diseases,
faulty practices surrounding birth, inade¬
quate treatment of infection are producing
even larger proportions of disability than in
the industrialized countries.
If the assumption that at least one in ten
of every population is likely to be born with
or acquire a significant disability, is applied
to the developing areas of the world, this
means that we find in those countries at
least 300 million, and probably more, people
with disabilities. These are the places where
we find the world's least advantaged
people those for whom poverty, hunger,
ignorance, disease, misery and
hopelessness are the only conditions of life.
Most of these people live either in one of
some two million rural villages where the
population ekes out a traditional existence
with little or no benefit from the resources
and capabilities of modern society, or they
live in one of the vast and squalid slums
which aregrowing and festering in and
around many major metropolises.
For the most part, the people of these
hungry villages and these suffering slums
are without access to or knowledge of the
most basic health and social services,
without primary education and without op¬
portunities for vocational preparation. Food
is not available to meet minimal nutrition
needs, the most elementary requirements of
sanitation are neither known nor practiced.
Exposure to all of the main causes of im¬
pairment of mothers and
children, birth defects, diseases and ac¬
cidents universal, and none of the
knowledge, skill or resources needed to
assist those who are impaired is effectively
present.
Even when rehabilitation programmes are
in operation, as they are in many cities in the
developing countries, their services do not
reach these people the residents of the
rural areas and the urban slums. Distances
to be travelled and the costs of transporta¬
tion, the costs of rehabilitation and related
care, traditions, social and cultural barriers
are all obstacles. Even if they were not, the
basic fact is that whatever services exist are
incapable of dealing with more than a few of
the people with disabilities.
Thanks to a study of the situation of han¬
dicapped children being carried out by
Rehabilitation International with assistance
from the United Nations Children's Fund
(UNICEF), I am able to offer some
generalizations that I am certain are valid for
the great majority of the people living in
such areas.
The first has to do with the dreadful im¬
plications of the combination of disability
and poverty. Either one may cause the
other, and their presence in combination has
a tremendous capacity to destroy the lives of
people with impairments and to impose on
families burdens that are too crushing to
bear.
We have not come to grips with the in¬
teractions between these two forces the
frequency with which untreated impairment
starts or accelerates the collapse of a
family's already fragile economic base, the
degree to which social and economic
deprivation are fundamental causes of im¬
pairment, and of the escalation of impair¬
ment into permanent disability. We do not
yet think of services to prevent impairment
and to rehabilitate disabled persons as being
basic components of economic and social
development because we have not yet faced
the evidence to be found out there in the
villages and barrios and favelas that they
are.
Second, we are finding that, when pro¬
grammes to assist in the development of the
community reach it, the benefits go last and
least to those families that are burdened
with both poverty and disability, usually
because the family with a disabled member
has been to some degree rejected from the
mainstream of community life and
resources. Within the family, it is too often
the child with the impairment who is denied
the chance for better food, for education,
for medical care, for social and intellectual
stimulation, even when these benefits do
become available to his or her sisters and |
brothers. I
NORMAN ACTON is Secretary-General of
Rehabilitation International, the world's largest
federation of organizations providing services for
the disabled. He is also chairman of the Council of
World Organizations Interested in the Handicap¬
ped, a co-ordinating group of major international
non-governmental organizations. Founding Presi¬
dent of the International Sports Organization for
the Disabled, he has been a consultant on prob¬
lems of the handicapped to the United Nations,
Unesco and UNICEF.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The double profile of disability
IN the world's industrially developed
countries the scale of the disability
situation is just the same as in the
developing world, but the nature of the
problem is different. There is no
trachoma, no onchocerciasis, no severe
quantitative malnutrition, but alcoholism
and drug-addiction are on the increase,
and road accidents and accidents at
work those characteristic features of
industrial society are claiming a rising
toll of victims.
It is estimated that some 40 million
persons are handicapped as a result of
alcohol or drug abuse. In 14 of the 16
countries where WHO has carried out
surveys, over 2 per cent of the popula¬
tion are alcoholics. In France, for exam¬
ple, alcoholics constitute 4 per cent of
the population, while 9 per cent drink ex¬
cessively. It should be noted that
alcoholism is a cause ofmanypsychiatric
disorders, as well as accidents on the
roads and at work.
Cardiovascular and cerebrovascular ill¬
nesses, which have major disabling ef¬
fects, are particularly widespread among
those who live at the hectic pace of the
industrially developed world. Every year,
in Europe alone, 2.2 persons in every
thousand, that is 900,000 persons under
the age of 65, have a heart attack
(myocardial infarct). An estimated third
of these may live on for at least another
ten years, but theirparticipation in active
life will be reduced. This means that
some 3 million persons will be handicap¬
ped to a greater or lesser degree. This
cause of handicap is far less widespread
in the developing countries.
The various afflictions resulting from
peri-natal accidents (some 110 million
births take place each year) are found in
all countries, but they are mostprevalent
in the developing world. This is not only
because of insufficient medical attention
during pregnancy and confinement but
because some 75 per cent of all births
take place in the developing countries
where, moreover, peri-natal risk is
several times higher than in the more
developed countries. Besides, in India
and Sri Lanka, for example, 35 per cent
of new-born babies weigh less than
2,500 grammes, whereas in Europe the
figure is between 6 and 8 per cent.
Nutrition during pregnancy and the
first months of life is vitally important,
yet some 800 million persons today go
hungry and 800 more suffer from dietary
deficiencies. In 1978 at least 20 million
children under five perished because
they were deprived of the minimum con¬
ditions necessary for survival.
Even in the most developed countries,
at least 40 per cent of those considered
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
to be mentally backward and) or to suf¬
fer from motor deficiencies, owe their
disability to peri-natal defect. The most
common cause is anoxia (oxygen lack or
deficiency).
The age of the mother is another key
factor in determining the incidence of
various genetic defects. Over the age of
36, for example, the risk of giving birth
to a mongol child increases exponential¬
ly. The avoidance of premature births
will also help reduce the number of
handicapped persons.
Everyone in the world must feel con¬
cerned by these problems, and current
knowledge must be made widely known,
for in every country the disparity bet¬
ween what can be done and what is
done is glaring and intolerable. All too
often the benefits are being reaped only
by an elite.
Federico Mayor
The understanding and
support of the family are of
vital importance to the
handicapped. For the past
ten years the Family Centre
at Kaele, in north
Cameroon, has been giving
courses which teach the
parents of handicapped
children how best to help
them adapt to their
handicap and to live a
normal life participating
fully in the life of their
community. Opposite page,
a father and mother
teaching their handicapped
child how to stand and
walk. Right, learning to
walk with crutches.
. Third, and directly connected with
everything I am saying, there is an abysmal
lack of accurate information about disability,
its causes and consequences, and about
what we can do about these things; and an
equally appalling wealth of misinformation,
prejudice, superstition and fear. This is a
major factor in the family's inadequate reac¬
tion to the problem when it arises; it is a fun¬
damental reason for the community's
ostracizing individuals and families that are
affected with disability; ¡t exists in the in¬
stitutions that might be helping, but
aren't the health centre, the school, the
religious grouping; it permeates all echelons
of government from the village chief to the
ministers of health, education, welfare,
labour, community development, planning
and whatever else may exist; and it is
endemic in the representatives of interna¬
tional and other organizations who are ad¬
vising on the procedures and priorities of
development, and administering interna¬
tional assistance. This absence of informa¬
tion and understanding, and the manner in
which it reinforces the traditional distorted
concepts of disability which flourish
throughout the world, does much to con¬
ceal the real magnitude of the problem and
to confuse everyone's thinking about the
solutions.
Fourth, these factors combine to produce
attitudes and patterns of individual and
social behaviour that are themselves impor¬
tant causes of disability and of handicapped
lives. Children with even minor impairments
are often stigmatized as crippled or blind or
deaf or retarded and shut off from the very
support and stimulation that would enable
them to develop and function in society.
Adults with certain categories of disability,
varying with traditions and culture, are
denied participation in the basic forms of
social life the productive activities of the
community, its institutions of government,
marriage and parenthood more because of
the stigma attached to disability than
because it practically limits the capacity for
action.
These social forces are not unique to the
developing areas; they are well known in
every part of the world. In general, however,
in the developing world, the individual's role
in the community is much more rigidly defin¬
ed by the circumstances of the family and its
traditional relationships and his or her self-
image and confidence are derived from the
capacity to fulfil that role in the social con¬
text in which it has been evolved. Thus
when, because of the functional limitations
associated with an impairment or because of
the stigmatization of the disabled person, he
or she is not permitted to grow into and fulfil
the traditional role, the individual is very like¬
ly to become a non-person, an outcast
without value to self, to the family or to the
community.
Fifth, at least 90 per cent and probably
more of whatever rehabilitation services ex¬
ist in the developing areas have been design¬
ed and activated on the basis of models
found in the industrialized West, and have
been assisted and staffed by people trained
in those models. This international co¬
operation and assistance has taken place
almost entirely in the past 30 years. It has
produced some islands of excellence cen¬
tres, schools and programmes that are per¬
forming as well as the models from which i
they have been derived and workers of I
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
. great dedication and skill. Two crucial prob¬
lems remain. First, the totality of the existing
services reach at best a few thousand people
in the areas where we estimate there are at
least 300 million with disabilities and an ad¬
ditional two million each year. And
second, we may question whether the con¬
cepts of rehabilitation services which have
evolved in the industrialized West are
necessarily appropriate for areas with quite
different economic and social situations.
The rehabilitation model which has
dominated the scene both in the industrializ¬
ed West and in our international assistance
activity has three working parts: fancy
buildings, elaborate equipment and highly
specialized professional personnel. We have
evolved standards for each of these com¬
ponents in the most sophisticated setting
with unlimited research and development
funds, and have cloaked these standards in
an aura so sacred that our friends in the
developing world are led to believe that
anything different is unacceptable.
Our emphasis has been on services that the
professional will give to the disabled person
and, to a lesser extent, to the family. Initially,
because the fashions of our epoch have led
us to believe that we can solve anything by an
operation, a pill, a pad, an exercise, or a diet,
we have projected rehabilitation as an essen¬
tially medical exercise. Educational and voca¬
tional rehabilitation have been close behind
and, in the cities of the developing areas, the
numbers of centres specializing in the
medical rehabilitation of a few people are
followed closely by other centres dealing in
what is called special education and voca¬
tional training and sheltered employment, but
which too often carry out primarily custodial
functions.
We have said, "Bring your disabled per¬
son to our magic house, with our charmed
equipment and our inspired specialists and
we will change him or her and send him or
her back to you, less disabled and better
able to cope in your community." But we
have also had to say, depending on the cir¬
cumstances, "We can take only those of
you who can pay our charges, or who are
within the neighbourhood of the magic
house, or who can come back three times a
week for six months, or who have transpor¬
tation, or who are willing to accept our
definition of your future".
It has been our practice, and the burden
of the example we export, to lift both the
problem and the person with the problem
out of the social context in which they exist
and to attempt to find a solution in a new
context of our making. We have only slowly
learned that a person with a disability is also
a person with a lot of other things: with a
family, with traditions, with customs, with
tastes and appetites, with fears and ap¬
prehensions, with pride and ambition, and
with a culture through which these elements
are integrated. The foundation of the think¬
ing we have exported has been to remove
the individual from everything in his or her
life except the impairment and to concen¬
trate on that. We have, to all practical pur¬
poses, ignored the rich array of support that
is ready to be activated in the community, in
the family, and in the individual with the
impairment.
Numbers six and seven are ideas that
apply to all international aid for develop¬
ment, and are directly relevant to our con¬
cerns. Number six is the principle of social
magnetism. It says that, by and large, when
we venture into the developing world, we
32
find our greatest empathy with the people
who can speak our language, who share
some of our ideas about how society should
be organized and with whom we feel com¬
fortable. People who meet these criteria are
of course usually people who, for one
reason or another, have had a Western
education and acculturation, who under¬
stand the conceptual basis on which our
human assistance programmes are based,
and who aspire to a similar, albeit inap¬
propriate, set of services in their countries.
Please understand me, some of my dearest
friends in the world are in the category I
have just described, and I fully understand
the roles they have played in motivating
developing activity, but the hard reality is
that they do not always comprehend the real
dimensions of the disability problem as it af¬
fects all the people of their countries, and
their reinforcement of our parochial con¬
cepts does not necessarily mean that they
are relevant. Our most important challenge
is to understand what disability means to the
person and the family in the village, and the
urban slum.
Number seven, also applicable to all
development activity, is the collapse of the
"trickle-down" theory. We have assumed
that, by stimulating and assisting the
establishment of showplace institutions in
capital cities, we would start a trickling-
down process that would eventually diffuse
appropriate levels of service to the smaller
communities. When we have talked about
national programmes, we have referred to
networks of show place centres which
would trickle down. It hasn't happened, and
we should now know that it won't happen
unless there is a very hard-headed plan,
based on the realities of both resources and
culture to activate it.
What can we do to get a better result
from the resources we expect to put into the
improvement of the life of disabled persons
in areas in the earlier stages of development?
Let me suggest some principles that I think
you should consider.
I haven't said much about prevention, but
this should not imply that I do not think it
important. It is completely obvious that we
will never effectively reduce the problem of
disability until we do something intelligent
about reducing the incidence of impairment.
Look at the major causes malnutrition,
birth defects, disease and accidents and at
the multi-faceted action necessary to reduce
their tragic consequences.
We can prevent the impairment by
preventing the malnutrition, the birth
defect, the disease or the accident; if it hap¬
pens, we can prevent the permanent
disability by effective care and treatment;
and we can prevent so many of the real
social consequences, the handicap, by in¬
telligent social action and public education
programmes.
We have made a major mistake in
separating prevention and rehabilitation.
The human experience is a progressive
development which starts before concep¬
tion, when the characteristics of the mating
partners may or may not produce impair¬
ment, and terminates at death which too
often is the culmination of a progressive
reduction of capacities, a process which in
other contexts we call disability. Everyone is
faced, at the moment his potential parents
meet, with the prospect of impairment;
everyone is likely to suffer a diminution of
capacity during his or her lifetime and
whether it will be called a disability depends
on the culture more than on the incapacity.
Our programmes, and the programmes we
have urged upon the developing countries,
are not based on these realities. They are
based on the idea that an impairment is a
special event, and that it requires that the
recipient be immediately removed from the
normal stream of development and perfor¬
mance, and introduced to the blessings of
our buildings, equipment and professional
personnel.
I would like to suggest that the whole pro¬
cess should be a continuum of prevention,
rehabilitation and social action. These are
not separate crusades, they are interlocking
and interacting components of a system
whose only purpose is to support the op¬
timum development of each individual's
capacity and personality. Our planning, and
the planning we discuss with the developing
countries, should be an extension of that
concept.
A high priority must be given to cor£]í>/
ing everyone who deals in policy ai-<Gt
these things that disability is an important
cause and consequence of under¬
development, and that dealing with it must
be a priority item in any >nelligent develop¬
ment plan.
Another concern is with what we gran¬
diosely call the infrastructure. Because of
our involvement with the "magic house, the
charmed equipment, and the inspired
specialists," we have generally overlooked
the potential contribution of the people and
institutions which, having more general ob¬
jectives, nevertheless can and should be
helping us. Rehabilitation International has
talked with a great many village health
workers, teachers, social security agents,
political and religious leaders, community
development motivators and others who
should be ready to assist in this area. The
pervasive lack of information I mentioned
earlier applies, and also there is an absence
of understanding and spirit and motivation
that must be corrected if we are to change
the situation.
The most important asset for any pro¬
gramme for disability prevention and
rehabilitation is the family, and in most
developing areas the ties and functions of
the family are strong components of the
social context of the individual. We should
give a much higher priority to activities that
will overcome the superstitions and fears of
the members of the families of disabled per¬
sons, instruct them in procedures they can
follow to prevent disability or assist the
rehabilitation process, and acquaint them
with the sources of help that may be or
become available. Successful work at this
level, by remaining within the existing social
framework of the individual's life, can do
much to maintain normal human develop¬
ment and performance whether or not the
impairment can be eliminated or reduced.
I am aware that I have both over¬
simplified and over-generalized the situa¬
tion, and that there are examples of pro¬
gress supported by international assistance
that are more positive than I have described.
I will continue, however, to defend the
thesis that the situations I have described
are those in which the great majority of
disabled people ¡n the developing world are
living, and that the characteristics I have
ascribed to most of our efforts to assist
them are accurate the evidence is out
there to prove it.
Norman Acton
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The scars of war
One of the many evils caused by war is the
suffering of the enormous number whose
survival is bought at the cost of terrible
physical, mental or emotional handicaps.
Even worse, if that ispossible, than thepain,
the mutilation, the burns and the psychoses
that are the direct effects of war are the in¬
direct effects which still make themselvesfelt
years later: the chaos into which warplunges
a country's economy, the havoc it wreaks on
thefabric of its society, thepoverty, hunger,
malnutrition and psychological disorders it
leaves behind, the multitudes of refugees it
banishes from hearth and home. And it is
often children who suffer the most enduring
consequences of war. This is the story told
so dramatically in the photo below. It was
taken over thirty years ago in a special
school for war-handicapped children in
Poland, but its message is just as relevant
and universal as ever. The little girl had been
asked to draw her house andfamily. The in¬
extricable maelstrom of lines she drew, and
the baffled expression on her face are the
mirror of disorder and ruin the Second
World War brought to Europe.
Photo © David Seymour
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
ABC International
A future for every blind child
by Pierrette Posmowski
THE place: a town in northern Bangladesh. The time: any week¬
day during term-time. Two boys are sitting side by side in a
classroom, the older one busily writing away with a pen, while
the younger, a look of intense concentration on his face, moves his
hands regularly across a kind of board with a ruler attached to it. The
younger boyyou will have guessed is blind and the contraption
he is using is a Braille set.
The Edward School at Mymensingh, north of Dacca, is one of
47 establishments in Bangladesh practising "integrated education".
It has a dozen blind pupils who work and play alongside sighted
youngsters in a normal school environment. The education they are
receiving will equip them to lead productive, independent lives and
take part in many of the community's activities on an equal footing
with sighted people.
These children, however, are a tiny, privileged minority. To be
born or to become blind is a terrible infirmity by any count. In a
developing country it is all the more tragic in that disablement is
often considered a stroke of fate which nothing can alleviate. So the
blind child is left to vegetate, growing up in isolation without any
kind of stimulus or occupation when he is not actually looked upon
as subnormal and hidden away in shame.
Extreme poverty combines with disablement to produce a vicious
circle of cause and effect. Every year, it is estimated, some
100,000 children in the developing world lose their sight through
vitamin A deficiency associated with chronic malnutrition. 17,000 do
so in Bangladesh, for in this country of 90 million people, 80 per cent
of the population live below the poverty line.
It was against this backbround that Dr. Michael Irwin arrived in
Dacca early in 1977 as UNICEF's representative in Bangladesh. A
British physician who has worked for the U.N. for nearly twenty-five
years, his task was to direct the very big programme, in terms of
both staff and funds, which UNICEF is carrying out in that country.
"One of the things the struck me almost immediately", he recalled
in a recent interview, "was the very large number of blind children.
No one is quite sure of the total, but it must be at least 50,000."
So in April 1978, together with several Bangladeshi friends. Dr. Ir¬
win set up an organization called Assistance for Blind Children or,
simply, ABC. Among the personalities and professions represented
on its executive committee are Mr. Habibullah Khan, Minister for
Jute, (now Acting President); Mr. Monsur A. Choudhouri, of the
Bangladesh National Society for the Blind; Mr. A.M. Mufazzal, Ex¬
ecutive Editor of the Bangladesh Times; Mrs. Munira Khan, of the
Women's Voluntary Association, Mrs. Salma Khan of the Social
Welfare section of the Planning Commission; and Dr. Rabiul Husain,
medical adviser. Central Hospital Management, Bangladesh Na¬
tional Society for the Blind. One of ABC's main activities is to pro¬
vide funds to carry out sight-restoration operations on young
children who are blind because of some congenital defect like con-
PIERRETTE POSMOWSKI was, from 1963 to 1980, editor of Unesco
Features, a press and radio service published monthly by Unesco in
English, French, Spanish and Arabic. This article is based on an interview
with Dr Michael Irwin, president of ABC International and senior adviser
on childhood disabilities at UNICEF headquarters. New York.
genital cataracts. These can be removed by simple surgery in a
hospital environment.
In less than two years, between 1978 and 1980, about 300
children one third of them girls have had such operations under
ABC sponsorship. "To see a child's life changed in this way is one of
the most exciting memories I have of Bangladesh," Dr. Irwin said.
ABC is also supporting the government drive for integrated
education. In the past two years it has opened five hostels attached
to regular schools, where blind pupils can live when their homes are
too far for them to travel to and fro to class every day. And a total of
110 children are receiving stipends to pay for their residential and
educational expenses. Several of them. Dr. Irwin said, are near the
top of their class.
ABC also provides equipment such as Braille kits, watches and
radio sets. But perhaps its most exciting venture is the vocational
training work it recently started with blind village children in the
Mymensingh area.
In the traditional village environment, blind children leadvery pro¬
tected and unproductive lives. They get no formal education and,
even if it were available, they would be unlikely to benefit from it.
ABC has helped to introduce them to agricultural or farm activities
such as vegetable-growing, poultry-raising, fish culture or looking
after cattle.
The latest ABC project, currently being developed with the
Bangladesh Department of Social Welfare, is the establishment of
mobile teams to test the sight of children who normally would not be
reached through the school or the health systems. This should help
reduce blindness in the villages, for early detection and treatment of
a defect or an infection can often prevent a child from losing his
sight.
In the Third World impairments are generally due to chronic
malnutrition, faulty child-bearing practices, accidents or preventable
diseases often linked to extreme poverty. Nutritional blindness, of¬
ficially known as xerophthalmia or keratoma lacia, is actually the
destruction of the tissues of the eye caused by a combination of
severe malnutrition and a great lack of vitamin A.
This condition is widespread in the rice-eating areas of Asia,
where green vegetables are not usually included in the diet because,
culturally, people are not accustomed to them. "In Bangladesh",
Dr. Irwin observed, "you find natural sources of vitamin A growing
wild throughout the country in the green leaves of plants and
vegetables. Normally, these are eaten only by cattle, and yet they
could be given perfectly well to human beings."
UNICEF is helping to combat nutritional blindness in several coun¬
tries in the area by providing massive supplies of vitamin A cap¬
sules the tune of 30 million a year in Bangladesh alone. These
are distributed by community workers to as many children as pos¬
sible under the age of six: in 1979, for example, 70 per cent of the
children in that age group received the required two capsules during
the year.
But more important than such emergency measures are long-term
efforts to teach people where to find natural sources of vitamin A.
Several health and nutrition education programmes of this kind are
being launched in Bangladesh and neighbouring countries.
One example ¡s a project started in the state of Tamil Nadu in
south India where it is estimated that 6,000 children lose their sight
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Edward School at Mymensingh, Bangladesh.
Accompanied by the local mayor, a health worker
from an ophthalmologics! clinic in Latin America
goes through the market looking for people
suffering from eye infections and persuading them
to have treatment. Several Latin American
countries have launched vigorous campaigns
aimed at preventing blindness by rapid detection
and early treatment of eye diseases.
every year. At the Nutrition Rehabilitation Centre attached to Rajaji
Hospital in Madurai young patients are treated for night blind¬
ness white spot which appears on the eye when the diet is lack¬
ing in vitamin A and can lead eventually to complete loss of
sightwhile their mothers are taught how to cook five nutritious
meals a day on only one rupee (15 cents). The meals consist of ragi
(a cereal grass) and groundnut gruel, wheat and bajra flour mixture,
with greens like drumstick leaves, spinach and a slice of papaya.
Last year, 26 children suffering from night blindness were treated
at the Madurai centre. But they are only a fraction of those in need
of care. To reach rural children the centre has started a training pro¬
gramme for balsevikas (child care workers) who take a short course
at Madurai and then return to their village community to spread the
good word.
This experiment is typical of the new approach to prevention and
rehabilitation which draws upon resources already available within
the family and the community. In both the industrialized and
developing worlds there is increasing realization that to put a disabl¬
ed child in an institution is not always the best solution. Such special
schools tend to accentuate the child's isolation; they are expensive
to run and benefit relatively few children. A more realistic approach
advocated by organizations like Unesco and WHO is to preserve the
child's normal development as much as possible by integrating care
and education into existing services. As Dr. Irwin put it:
"By adding a few simple concepts to the training of community-
level, workers para-medics, health and rural social workers, and
primary schoolteachers you can make them aware of the problem
and show them what can be achieved by preventive action and
modest rehabilitation efforts."
The success of ABC in Bangladesh has led to the establishment of
ABC groups in other Asian countries: India and Sri Lanka to begin
with and, more recently, Malaysia and Pakistan. In India, for exam¬
ple, several children are being sponsored at schools in the Bombay
area and the extension of ABC projects to Pune and Bangalore is be¬
ing explored; while in Sri Lanka financial support has been given in
recent months for several sight-restoration operations, and in
Pakistan ABC is providing 300 Braille Kits.
To co-ordinate the activities of these groups and increase
awareness of the plight of blind children ¡n the developing world
ABC International was set up in April 1980 with offices in New
York(*).
Support for ABC's activities has come from organizations around
the world, including the Christoffel Blindenmission, in the Federal
Republic of Germany, the Royal Commonwealth Society for the
Blind, in the U.K., and Helen Keller International in the U.S., as well
as a number of smaller foundations and individuals.
But funds are still needed, and needed urgently, for the number of
blind children being assisted in south Asia is pitifully small less
than 3,000 out of 50,000 sightless youngsters under 15 in
Bangladesh, and about 15,000 out of 250,000 in India.
Twenty dollars (or £10, or 100 French francs) will pay for:
a sight-restoration operation on one eye for a child suffering
from congenital cataract. (In Bangladesh, the National Society
for the Blind pays the surgeon, but the cost of an attendant to
stay with the child in hospital, the general anaesthetic, food and
travelling expenses between the child's home and the hospital
are covered by ABC);
a Braille kit for a child in the integrated school programme, con¬
sisting of the various instruments required in class packed in a
strong wooden box;
full residential and educational expenses for one month at one of
the five hostels maintained by ABC.
Smaller contributions of, say, $2 (£1 or 10 francs) would pay for a
pair of "cataract glasses" manufactured locally; while, at the other
end of the scale, $5,000 (£3,000 or 30,000 francs) would cover the
construction and furnishing costs of a residential hostel, built of
brick, with a concrete floor and metal roofing.
Sir John Wilson, director of the Royal Commonwealth Society for
the Blind, once said that "it is only in the statistics that people go
blind by millions: each person goes blind individually in his own
predicament". Keeping that in mind, ABC is striving to ensure "A
future for every blind child".
* ABC is one of the projects being sponsored by Unesco's Co-Action Pro¬
gramme during 1981 International Year of Disabled Persons. Further infor¬
mation on the project and details of this international scheme which helps to
provide equipment and training facilities for schools and centres for the han¬
dicapped in the developing world, can be obtained from: "Co-Action", OPI,
UNESCO, 7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris. Contributions should be clearly
marked: "ABC International Bangladesh".
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
A working definition of handicap
AFFECTING about 10 per cent of the world's population, dis¬
ability should be considered as a major medical, social,
psychological and economic problem, the magnitude of
which can be expected to increase in the future.
Health authorities and medical practitioners have in the past been
more attentive to the problems of mortality and acute morbidity than
to the less dramatic problems of long-term impairment and perma¬
nent disability. A greater understanding is badly needed of disability,
of its causes and consequences, and of what can be done to reduce
its impact. Disease-oriented medicine needs to be complemented by
disability-oriented medicine, and it should be realized in every coun¬
try that the objectives of medicine are not only the prevention and
cure of disease but also the optimum restoration of the individual to
normal social function.
In current usage the terms "impairment", "handicap",
"disability", "prevention" and "rehabilitation" are often confusing.
For several years now the World Health Organization has been in¬
strumental in developing an international classification of diseases
(the ICD code), which deals mainly with diagnoses but not with the
outcome of diseases or with health status measurements, such as
"disability".
In the International Classification of Diseases, the development of
an illness is considered to follow a pattern the phases of which relate
to the natural history of disease: its aetiology, its pathology and its
manifestation. But a sick person also experiences changes in his ac¬
customed social role. If these are long-lasting or severe enough, the
patient perceives a need for care which is not primarily related to the
pathological manifestation of disease. Thus, there is a need for a
complementary pattern to describe the changes in social role
resulting from the disease, i.e. impairment, disability, handicap.
Many definitions of these terms have been published but have not
been universally accepted. Difficulties arise because several of the
terms used are of legal and administrative importance, e.g. terms of
eligibility of invalids for pensions. The attempts to define "impair¬
ment", "disability", etc. have almost exclusively been concerned
with those resulting from physical manifestations and neglected
those in which the primary impairment is psychological.
It is quite clear that agreement on the definitions of terms in this
area will not be reached for several years. However, in 1980 the
World Health Organization published, for trial purposes, a manual of
classification relating to the consequences of disease, the Interna¬
tional Classification of Impairments, Disabilities and Handicaps. The
manual contains three distinct classifications each relating to a dif¬
ferent plane of experience consequent upon disease:
Impairments
concerned with abnormalities of body structure and appearance
and with organ or system function, resulting from any cause; in prin¬
ciple, impairments represent disturbances at the organ level;
Disabilities
reflecting the consequences of impairment in terms of functional
performance and activity by the individual; disabilities thus represent
disturbances at the level of the person;
36
Handicaps
concerned with the disadvantages experienced by the individual
as a result of impairments and disabilities; handicaps thus reflect
interaction with and adaptation to the individual's surroundings.
Example 1
A 16-year-old boy is involved in a traffic accident and one leg has to
be amputated above the knee.
Impairment: loss of leg
Disability: decreased ability to walk
Handicap: decreased ability to work, to enjoy normal social
activities (sports, dancing), and to make social
relationships.
Example 2
A 50-year-old male, who has had hypertension for several years, suf¬
fers a stroke resulting in a right-side hemiparalysis and dysphasia.
Impairment: hypertension
disturbance of brain function
Disability: decreased ability to talk
decreased ability to walk and use right hand
fatigue through low physical endurance
Handicap: inability to work, partial inability to look after
himself, and reduced ability to interact with sur¬
roundings.
Example 3
A 3-year-old girl is left with severe scars on her face and her entire
left arm after burns.
Impairment: burn scars
abnormal appearance
Disability: decreased mobility of arm
decreased interest in and contact with sur¬
roundings
Handicap: decreased capacity to take part in household work,
disturbed social relationships (rejected by family
and community members), and marriage pros¬
pects much reduced.
Example 4
An adult married female, with two children, with a two-year history
of "schizophrenia".
Impairment: auditory hallucinations
lack of volition (i.e., normal drive and interest)
disturbance of thought processes
Disability: inability to maintain drive and interest in daily tasks
poor attention and grasp of information, lack of
contact with reality
Handicap: failure to care for children, perform housework,
maintain personal hygiene and appearance, and
relate to family members and friends.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
CAUSATIVE FACTORS
THE HANDICAP
PROCESS
Disease
Environment
World incidence of disability
(in millions)
The accepted minimum estimate of the magnitude of the
disability problem is that at least one person in ten is born
with, or acquires, a physical, mental or sensory impair¬
ment. The data are very incomplete: estimates rise to 15 or
20% depending on definitions used and conditions inclu¬
ded. Rehabilitation International's figure is 500 million:
over two-thirds of these live in developing countries,
mostly without any rehabilitative services.
*e.g.: back disorders, heart conditions, epilepsy, arthritis, etc.
Source WHO
Total = 514 m
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
BOOKSHELF
UNESCO PUBLICATIONS
ON THE HANDICAPPED
Constructive Education for Special
Groups, by W.D. Wall. (See opposite
page).
Economic Aspects of Special Edu¬
cation. Three studies (on Czechoslova¬
kia, New Zealand, and the USA) with an
introduction and a summarizing chapter.
152 pp., 1978 (6 F).
Terminology Used in Special Educa¬
tion. Lists of terms used in special educa¬
tion with definitions in English, French,
Russian and Spanish.
A Unesco: International Bureau of Educa¬
tion publication. 368 pp., 1977. - *
Integration of Technical and Voca- .
tional Education into Special Educa-'
tion. Four studies (on Austria, Colombia,
Iran and Tunisia) with an introduction and
a summarizing chapter. 220 pp., 1977
(36 F).
Case Studies in Special Education.
Four studies (on Cuba, Kenya, Japan and
Sweden) with an introduction and a sum¬
marizing chapter. 195 pp., 1974 (24 F).
The Present Situation and Trends of
Research in the Field of Special Edu¬
cation. Four studies (on Sweden and
other Scandinavian countries, USSR,
USA, and Uruguay) with an introduction
and a summarizing chapter. 306 pp., 1973
(28 F).
Red Thread Riddles, by Virginia Allen
Jensen and Polly Edman. An ingenious
booklet of word-puzzles, specially produ¬
ced for enjoyment by both visually handi¬
capped and non-handicapped children
aged from six to ten. The text is repro¬
duced in Braille and in inkprint, and the
illustrations are embossed and coloured.
24 pp., 1980. (Requests for copies of this
booklet may be sent to Mr. F.H. Potter,
Unesco Courier Division, Unesco, 7, place
de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris) See also
page 19.
RECENT UNESCO BOOKS
Consensus and Peace, Amadou-
Mahtar M'Bow, Mario Amadeo, Gerald
Antoine, Rachid Daker, Asbjorn Eide,
Mihajlo Javorski, Joaquín Ruiz-Giménez,
Abdoulaye Wade. Edited by Beseat Kiflé
Selassie. 231 pp., 1980 (55 F).
Drugs Demystified. Third impression
of a work first published in 1975. 92 pp.
(10 F).
The Place of Information in Educa¬
tional Development, by Leo R. Fernig.
A study prepared for the International
Bureau of Education. A condensed ver¬
sion of the discussions and documenta¬
tion of the 1977 International Conference
on Education, the special theme of which
was educational information. 135 pp.,
1980 (24 F).
Information: an Essential Factor in
Educational Planning and Policy, edi¬
ted by George Psacharopoulos. 303 pp.,
1980 (50 F).
G3 rû
b mam rn
hi
Unesco medal
for Picasso centenary
To mark the centenary of the birth of the
great Spanish artist Pablo Picasso (see
Unesco Courier, December 1980) Unesco is
issuing a commemorative medal in silver,
bronze and vermeil. The medal (right) has
been designed by Picasso's compatriot and
friend Joan Miró and struck from a ma¬
quette by Mlro's collaborator Joan Gardy
Artigas. Obverse side of medal bears the in¬
scription "Pablo Picasso Malaga
25. X. 1881" and is described by Miró as
follows: "in the centre, an eye, like the eye
of Picasso, deep-set and alert, surrounded
by magical and musical inscriptions".
Reverse side, inscribed "Miró Unesco
1981", shows "a deserted plain, with only a
growing tree and a star over the horizon".
For further information please write to:
Philatelic and Numismatic Programme,
Unesco, 7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
The World Heritage
on slides
Unesco's Cultural Heritage Division has
prepared a slide series on the World
Heritage Convention (see Unesco Courier,
August 1980). The series of 44 slides il¬
lustrates sites on the World Heritage List
and is accompanied by descriptive texts. For
further information please write to: Jeanne
Brodie, Division of Cultural Heritage,
Unesco, 7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Award-winning song
will aid Unesco's work
for handicapped
All proceeds from the sale of a record whose
lyrics were written by a 13-year-old Filipino
girl, Odina E. Batnag, are being donated to
Unesco's Education for Handicapped
Children Programme. The song, entitled "I
am but a small voice", won first prize in a
world-wide children's song-writing contest,
on the theme "Children Helping Children",
sponsored by Unesco and the Radio Cor¬
poration of America (RCA). Odina's words
were set to music and recorded by the inter¬
nationally known singer Roger Whittaker,
who is also donating his royalties to the
Unesco programme. The record, released as
a single by RCA, can be purchased from
commercial record dealers or direct from
Unesco, Co-Action Programme, 7, Place de
Fontenoy, 75700 Paris. (Price 15 French
francs including postage).
U.N. stamp issue
for year of disabled
The International Year of Disabled Persons
will be the theme of a set of six stamps and a
souvenir card to be issued by the United
Nations Postal Administration on 6 March
1981. For further information about this
stamp issue please write to: U.N. Postal Ad¬
ministration, Palais des Nations, CH-1211
Geneva 10, Switzerland.
/ "I * \
X \
î J / /' J
f y
/
j-
%
ï,- Si
ii . , M"""*m	
'<X
/
./
i
* i
-	 J...
»
7.
\ *
1 *
'" /**'
1 ' -i
..
-~~Cl1 ¡: r> I '"'
Photos Unesco
Unesco launches
Prize for Peace Education
Unesco has established an annual Prize for
Peace Education with the aim of promoting
all forms of action designed to "construct
the defences of peace in the minds of men".
The prize, worth approximately $60,000, will
be financed by the interest from a $1 million
donation from the Japan Shipbuilding In¬
dustry Foundation. The laureates, who may
be "an individual, a group of individuals or
an organization", will be designated by the
Director-General of Unesco on the basis of
proposals by a jury of 9 members drawn
from the different world regions.
'Water taps
before hospital beds'
The United Nations has declared the 1980s
International Drinking Water Supply and
Sanitation Decade. Addressing the U.N.
General Assembly, meeting in special ses¬
sion in New York to launch the Decade, Dr.
Halfdan Mahler, Director-General of the
World Health Organization (WHO), affirmed
that safe drinking water and adequate
sanitation by 1990 is an achievable goal for
2,000 million people in the developing coun¬
tries. Dr. Mahler noted that the Decade will
require on average an estimated annual in¬
vestment totalling some $30,000 million, and
commented: "Because of what it will imply
in planning and results, the number of water
taps per 1 ,000 persons will become a better
indicator of health than the number of
hospital beds". Today it is estimated that
between 1,000 and 2,500 children under five
die every hour for lack of clean drinking
water or enough water to be properly
washed.
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Constructs
education for
special groups
Handicapped and
deviant children
WD Wall. PhD.
Harrap Cjnesco
How can society improve its ways of identifying and rehabi¬
litating the handicapped who are all too often the casualties
of the educational system? In this book, of interest to all
concerned, whether for professional or personal reasons,
with the problems of handicapped children, Prof. W.D.
Wall describes:
the prevalence and educational consequences of
physical disability
the principal groups of the mentally and physically
handicapped
psychological growth: the home and the family
the education of physically handicapped children
Prof. Wall is Emeritus Professor of Educational Psychology at the
University of London. His two previous works in the Unesco: IBE
(International Bureau of Education) series on comparative educa¬
tion were Constructive Education for Children and Construc¬
tive Education for Adolescents.
144 pages 35 French francs
Co-published with George G. Harrap and Co. Ltd., London, who
have exclusive sales rights in the United Kingdom.
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscrip¬
tion rates in local currency, will be supplied
on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd P.O
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW Periodicals Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept., P.O. 8ox33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent.
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St , Melbourne (Victoria), 3000.
- AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31, A-
1011, Vienna. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd , Ittefaq Building, 1, R K. Mission Rd , Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only N V. Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent- Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13 - BURMA. Trade Corporation No 9,550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7. - CHINA. China National Publications Import Corpora¬
tion, West Europe Department, P.O Box 88, Peking
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makanos 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box
1722, Nicosia - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. -SN T.L., Spalena
51, Prague 1 {Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura, 11 Sou-
kenicka, Prague 1 . For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers,
Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava - CSSR. - DENMARK.
Munksgaard Export and Subscription Service, 35 Norre Sogade,
DK 1370, Copenhagen K. - EGYPT IARAB REPUBLIC OF).
National Centre for Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb
Street, Cairo ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O.
Box 2996, Addis Ababa - FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirja¬
kauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100 Helsinki 10. - FRANCE.
Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Pans, CCP.
12598-48. - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leip¬
zig, Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhand¬
lungen in the G D R. - FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the
Unesco Courier (German, English, French and Spanish editions):
Mr. Herbert Blum, Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basakts¬
trasse 57, D-5300 Bonn 3. For other Unesco publications'
S. Karger GmbH, Karger Buchhandlung, Angerhofstrasse 9,
Postach 2, 8034 Germenng/Munchen. - GHANA. Presby¬
terian Bookshop Depot Ltd , P.O. Box 195, Accra, Ghana
Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University
Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape
Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon, P 0 Box 1, Legon
- GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. - HONG
KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial
Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-
15, Lock Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY. Akadémiai Kbnyves-
bolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V; A K.V. Konyvtürosok Boltja, Nép-
koztársaság utja 16, Budapest VI. ICELAND. Snaebjom
Jonsson & Co., H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA.
Orient Longman Ltd , Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay
400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13, 36a, Anna Salai,
Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf Ali Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1
Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001 Sub-Depots. Oxford Book & Stationery Co.
17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016, Scindia House, New Delhi; Publi¬
cations Section, Ministry of Education and Social Welfare, 511
C-Wmg, Shastn Bhavan, New Delhi 110001. - INDONESIA.
Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto Iskandardmata III,
Jakarta; Gramedia Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta;
Indira P.T., Jl. Dr Sam Ratulangle 47, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN.
Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co., 28, Vessal Shirazi
Street, Enghélab Avenue, P.O. Box 314/1486, Teheran; Iranian
Nat. Comm. for Unesco, Ave. Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B P.
1533, Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, Al -Rashid
Street, Baghdad IRELAND. The Educational Company of
Ireland Ltd , Ballymount Road, Walkmstown, Dublin 12.
ISRAEL. A. B.C. Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby
Road, Tel Aviv 61000 JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores
Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston. JAPAN. Eas¬
tern Book Service Inc., Shuhwa Toranomon 3bldg, 23-6, Tora¬
nomon 3-Chome, Mmato-ku, Tokyo 105, KENYA. East Afri¬
can Publishing House, P.O. 8ox 30571, Nairobi. KOREA.
Korean National Commission for Unesco, P O. Box Central 64,
Seoul. - KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942,
Kuwait LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod,
Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Book¬
shops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia LIBYA. Agency for
Development of Publication Et Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35, Tri¬
poli. - LUXEMBOURG. Líbrame Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue,
Luxembourg. MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co¬
operative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur 22-11. MALTA. Sapien-
zas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta. - MAURITIUS. Nalanda
Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis - MONACO.
British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. NETHER¬
LANDS. For the "Unesco Koerier" Dutch edition only: Syste¬
men Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75, Amsterdam-1007. Agent for
all Unesco publications. N.V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout,
9, The Hague. - NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-
Eddme N V., P 0. Box 200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. - NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, Government Books¬
hops at. Rutland Street, P O Box 5344, Auckland; 130, Oxford
Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Chnstchurch; Alma Street, P 0. Box 857
Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin;
Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington. - NIGERIA. The
University Bookshop of Ife, The University Bookshop of Ibadan,
P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of Nsukka, The University
Bookshop of Lagos, The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of
Zana. NORWAY. All publications Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco
Courier only: A. S Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-e-azam,
P.O. Box No 729, Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co , 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404 -
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7 00-068
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda, Livrana
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. - SEYCHELLES. New
Service Ltd , Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé. -
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19. - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P O. Box 951,
Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA. All publications: Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty I Ltd., Libri Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only Central News agency, P O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.
-SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam
Gardiner Mawata P O B. 244 Colombo 2. - SUDAN Al Bashir
Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. - SWEDEN. All
publications A/B CE. Fntzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel,
Regenngsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16 For the
Unesco Courier- Svenska FN-Forbundet, Skolgrand 2, Box 150
50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. - SWITZERLAND. All publications:
Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue
Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11, CC P. 12-236. - TANZANIA Dar¬
es Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam.
THAILAND. Nibondh and Co Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road,
Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok- Suksapan Pamt,
Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam
Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I. - TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi
A S , Istiklâl Caddesi, No 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu,
Istanbul - UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O Box 145,
Kampala - UNITED KINGDOM. H M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S E.I , and Govt Bookshops in London,
Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmin¬
gham, Bristol. -UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue
South, New York, N Y. 10010 - U.S.S.R Mezhdunarodnaya
Kniga, Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska
Knjiga, Trg Republike 5/8, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba
Slovenje, Titova C 25, P 0 B 50-1, Ljubliana. - ZIMBABWE.
Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union Avenue, Salisbury.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Breaking through the sound barrier
The joy of participation and seif-fulf iiment radiates from the face of this
child at a school for the deaf in Trinidad and Tobago. Advance* in elec¬
tronics have made possible the development of devices that can heip
the deaf to break through the sound barrier that cuts them off from so
much of everyday iife. But for every deaf child to whom these modern
techniques are available thousands more throughout the world remain
outside the mainstream of society, immured in a worid of siience.
]]>
</page>
</document>
